How is the world are we living in ?
How to study the Universe ?
Using the only information we receive from
it:
light
The goal of this course it to provide an overview
of the physical concepts
used in astrophysics
to analyze the observations taken
by large ground-based and space telescopes.
With these observations, the goal is to imagine
the physical mechanisms
responsible for the light radiation we receive
from celestial bodies
and for their motion, and to model them.
And of course, as always in science,
one needs to confront theoretical predictions
to observations.
The material in this course spans a broad
range of theoretical concepts
which astrophysical applications
play a role at all temporal and spatial scales.
The course is organized as a voyage
from our Solar System to the whole universe,
from stellar formation to galaxy evolution.
To this end, we will use images,
demonstrations on the slidepad
focusing on the links
between theoretical concepts and observations.
My name is Frédéric Courbin, I am a researcher
at the Laboratory of Astrophysics
of the Swiss Federal Institute of Technology
in Lausanne
where I spilt my time
between research in observational cosmology
and teaching.
The course I propose here is given to the
students in physics
in their second year of Bachelor at EPFL.
It consists in the mandatory basis for the
more advanced astrophysics courses
but also allows students to see physical phenomena
they may already know, but in a completely
different context.
Prerequisites are minimal.
They correspond to the knowledge
of a first year of university in physics ;
they include trigonometry, simple integral
calculus,
Taylor expansions and solving
first order differential equations.
However, as we put much more emphasis on the
physical concepts
than on long numerical developments,
the course remains simple and accessible to
most of you.
I am looking forward to meeting you very soon
for this introduction to astrophysics.