Hello and welcome to this seventh and last
module of the MOOC
on managing protected areas in Africa.
This module is about what we have called
the topical issues of protected areas,
namely the hot topics of today.
These have been covered in previous modules,
in more or less detail.
So this week, the module focuses on the following
subjects.
The first lesson will be on climate change.
What is it?
How does it impact protected areas?
How can they mitigate climate change?
In the second lesson we will look at the connectivity
of protected areas
and associated concepts, of buffer zones,
resilience, etc.
The restoration of protected areas,
which has unfortunately become essential in
numerous sites,
is the subject of the third lesson.
In the fourth lesson we will learn about equity,
particularly, gender equity
because, in protected areas, as well as in
other places,
equity must be a key notion in decisions
and the way they are made.
The fifth lesson will address
the difficult issue of corruption
and the trafficking it generates within protected
areas.
The sixth lesson is this week's convention,
the very last one
and we will talk this time about the Ramsar
Convention,
which deals with wetlands.
And finally, the traditional summary
of the important points, covered this week,
will be offered in the form of an animation,
followed by a conclusion of this MOOC
when we will attempt to review everything
we have looked at together.
So here we go,
have a great seventh week with us.