Hello and welcome everyone.
Today's lesson is dedicated to protected areas
and climate change.
We are going to have a quick look at the definition
of climate change,
the challenges for protected areas, the effects
the role of adaptation and mitigation of protected
areas.
I suggest you take a look at this website
to learn more.
Climate change is a sustained change
related to the expected and usual climate
conditions
for a given region.
It occurs over decades, or maybe even longer
periods.
It concerns significant statistical variations
of the general state of the climate
or of their variability, which persists for
a prolonged period.
Today, climate change is of major interest
to scientists as well as the public,
due to the implications regarding
food security,
health,
the economy on a global and national scale,
as well as our lifestyles,
population growth,
the evolution and degradation of habitats,
as for example deforestation and degradation
of wetlands etc.
The main cause of climate change, according
to experts on the subject,
is the increase in greenhouse gas, especially
carbon dioxide,
due to widespread use of fossil fuels
since the industrial era, and especially the
last 100 years.
The unprecedented increase of global temperatures
that happened in the 20th century
is the greatest of the last millennium, according
to IPCC.
This increase is mostly due to the impact
of human activity
on the climatic balance of the planet, and
has induced changes
in rainfall patterns, in times of drought,
storms,
the acidification and temperature of oceans,
the sea level rise etc.
The challenges for protected areas facing
climate change.
For several decades, protected areas have
been considered
to be an essential tool for biodiversity conservation.
The impacts of climate change now give them
a renewed role as an adaptation tool to climate
change.
They have a threefold function in this respect:
to help species to adapt to the pattern of
climate change
and to sudden climate events
by providing refuges and migration corridors.
Protecting populations against sudden climatic
events
and reducing vulnerability to flooding, to
drought,
and other catastrophes linked to climate.
Directly helping economies to adapt to climate
change
by reducing costs deriving from the harmful
effects
of climatic events.
From the point of view of ecological challenges,
the world has now more than 200,000 protected
areas.
Those consisting of land masses
cover more than 15% of the surface area of
the globe,
and protected areas appear amongst the most
effective tools
in protecting species against extinction
and the impact of man-made threats.
Concerning social issues,
protected areas might be able to supply services
specifically for the ecosystem
and increase the ability of the local population
to adapt to climate change.
On the impact of climate change.
Climate change modifies two factors
that control the distribution of biomes,
namely temperature and precipitation.
That means that the ecosystems that we find
within the biomes,
are directly affected by climate change.
A number of other factors of anthropogenic
sources
complicate the response of the vast majority
of ecosystems
when faced with climate change.
Conversely,
changes in the function of ecosystems
due to the anthropogenic component and climate
change,
could greatly influence the world's climate.
We note the impact on nutrient and carbon
cycles.
As an example, one of the most well known
impacts
of the accumulation of greenhouse gas is global
warming.
The impact on vegetation, for example global
warming,
could cause temperatures that the local vegetation
is not adapted to
and it would not be synchronized with the
photoperiods.
Impact on fauna, for example,
birds, that migrate over great distances,
could see their reproduction area and wintering
ground modified.
The effects of natural and anthropogenic disturbances.
As an example, the appearance and proliferation
of invasive species
could be accentuated by climate change
in forests and in Sudanian Savanna.
Listen to Ibrahim Thiaw,
Deputy Executive Director
of the United Nations Environment Programme,
on the role played by protected areas faced
with climate change.
Today, in the world, there are around 200,000
protected areas .
They cover a little more than 14% of the world's
land
and almost 3% of oceans.
Beyond their initial function of conservation
for fauna and flora,
they are progressively transformed
into providers of natural and cost effective
solutions
thus contributing to taking up certain great
contemporary challenges,
which are the most difficult to explain.
Humanity is still confronted with these issues.
Therefore, protected areas contribute to mitigation
and adaptation
to climate change.
Well conserved, protected areas form important
carbon sinks.
In fact, UNEP estimates that 15% of terrestrial
carbon stocks
are stored in protected areas.
However, mismanaged, degraded forests contribute
up to 17% of global carbon emissions,
which makes it the third emission source above
the transport sector.
Protected areas also form buffer zones against
catastrophes,
whether they are natural or anthropogenic
in origin,
for example flooding, forest fires, hurricanes
etc.
Furthermore, they supply essential ecosystem
services:
food, pure air and freshwater.
As you see, protected areas deliver many benefits
to humanity.
We must therefore invest in conservation or
restoration of natural capital,
the only thing capable of guaranteeing services,
not only in the short term
but also the long term,
working thus as a safety valve for generations
to come.
In conclusion, in module 2 on planning,
you have seen the planning methods for protected
areas.
So that the protected areas network is effective,
the selection of sights must be the best it
can be
and strategies must be adapted for the establishment
of protected areas
in the context of global change, and climate
change is one of them.
To achieve this, it is essential to define
the networks of resilient protected areas
manage them for resilience, climate adaptation
and mitigation
and integrate them into the climate planning
process.
This is the end of this lesson.
In the next class we will examine another
aspect related to today's subject:
connectivity between protected areas.
Until then, have a great day!