- Hello Geoffroy.
- Hello Paul.
Hello everyone.
Today's lesson is dedicated to two important
concepts
concerning the management of protected areas:
connectivity and buffer zones.
While they are different, they partly coincide
and that is why we are dealing with them in
the same lesson.
You will find more information on this topic
in the eBook of the World Commission of Protected
Areas,
in chapter 27.
Let's therefore start with connectivity.
It isn't that easy to define
even though everyone understands the general
meaning of it:
it's not very complicated.
Connectivity refers to the opportunity that
species have to move
between different points in an ecosystem;
or even the amount of connections that will
exist
between the components within that ecosystem.
It can also refer to the nature of these connections,
or even an environment's ability
to preserve the ecological processes that
occur there,
for example, migration.
So to keep it simple, we will talk about the
connectivity of habitats
when beneficial habitats are linked to each
other,
and therefore not isolated.
And we will talk about the connectivity of
ecological processes that may exist,
even if at a distance, when we look into the
migration of birds.
Connectivity
is an important notion in the evolution process
as well,
because it enables genetic mixing to still
be possible.
It therefore also involves longer-term effects,
but that are obviously essential for the survival
of species.
And yes, this connectivity concept is becoming
more and more important
with the fragmentation of environments,
the boom of invasive species,
the development of infrastructures or the
human population,
and of course, climate change,
which forces certain species to move,
if they can,
mainly between protected areas.
Connectivity works based on the principle
of networking,
which, in theory, seems simple for protected
areas
that are more or less close to each other.
In reality, the discontinuities produced
by strongly anthropic territories
that separate two protected areas
sometimes lead to the need to implement
functional migration corridors,
especially those in favor of terrestrial fauna.
It is true that, in fact, a landscape that
maintains more connections
between its different parts will be more able
to preserve biodiversity
because they will be able to move between
these different zones.
While certain species, which are naturally
mobile,
become independent quite easily
from physical links with their usual habitats,
others, on the contrary, will only move when
those links exist.
Sometimes a simple disruption in the environment,
like a road, for example,
can have disastrous consequences for the survival
of a species
by blocking migration, its migration,
while other species may not be disrupted by
this road at all.
It is important to keep this in mind.
Wildlife is not sensitive in the same way
when habitats are not connected.
Fauna corridors, for example, are territories
that link together habitats used by wildlife.
In fact, frequently they link together protected
areas.
They are created based on the assertion that
species in the protected area
will in fact move around, and also use that
passageway.
So, absolutely, it's true that certain species,
will not venture out
in man-made spaces surrounding the park,
and so, if there are corridors, obviously,
they will rather go through the corridor.
But that is not correct for all species,
as some have quite an erratic way of moving
around,
like the elephant frequently does, for example,
not always, but frequently.
Let's have a look at quite a functional case
study of corridors
in Senegal with Moussa Diouf.
In Senegal, we have many interconnections
between protected areas.
There is Djoudj and Diawling between Senegal
and Mauritania,
that's more of an air corridor than a land
one.
There is the corridor between Mali and Senegal,
through the Niokolo-Koba and the Bafing, therefore
through the Senegal River,
but the model that is
used the most anyway, the most complete corridor
there is,
is the corridor between biosphere reserves
of Niokolo-Koba and of Ferlo.
Niokolo-Koba has been a biosphere reserve
for a long time: since 1981.
The status of biosphere reserve has only just
been awarded three years ago
to the Ferlo biosphere reserve.
So, it is something completely new.
We are in the process of putting in place
managing bodies.
The objective of this biosphere reserve,
which is the destination zone of fauna migrating
from Niokolo-Koba,
is to reintroduce ecosystems into the zones
in Ferlo,
which are not liable to flooding.
When Niokolo-Koba is flooded during the rainy
season,
so at the end of the rainy season,
Niokolo-Koba's fauna, namely the large antelopes,
who are more trypanotolerant than resistant,
leave the park
and find themselves in these northern zones.
Now, the corridor that is used still functions
today,
because we have had proof, witness accounts
from the villagers,
who, during each wintering period, recount
to us the fact
that, mainly the roan antelope, the Hippotragus
equinus, pass through,
leave Niokolo-Koba to go towards Ferlo
and then return there around the end of the
rainy season.
Yet, this corridor is greatly threatened by
human occupation now,
but development and management programs for
these spaces,
which are being implemented at the moment,
may be able to allow us to reinvigorate them
and make them more functional.
So, to keep it simple, there are three different
types of corridors.
A landscape corridor is a group of territories
with multiple uses:
agricultural, hunting, harvesting, pastoralism...
They will however allow animals to pass.
A linear corridor
is a territory that we keep in quite a natural
state
to link together two protected areas,
so, globally, that is its only function: being
a thoroughfare.
Finally, ”stepping stones”
are territories that are close enough
to allow species to pass
from one protected area to another.
More specifically, we can try to maintain
large territories,
which directly integrate protected areas and
their connectivity,
or we could target little ecosystems, like
rivers and their galleries,
which will link together different protected
areas.
We can work on developing infrastructures
to avoid environments being disrupted.
We can also, when necessary,
recreate beneficial environments between the
protected areas,
or even expand from the conservation nucleus.
Paul Ndiaye has an interesting example for
us.
Connectivity also comes from a system of territories
more or less adjacent, which have statuses
that are progressively changing
from being completely focused on conservation
to being fully anthropized.
It is therefore about putting in place zoning
measures,
which allow a smooth transition for wildlife
travelling
from spaces protected in a strict way to ordinary
spaces.
This option was frequently applied
within the framework of biosphere reserves
organized as a whole, nested together.
The model known today throughout the world
for zoning protected areas,
is the model advocated by UNESCO for the concept
of biosphere reserves.
It's a model that needs to be encouraged and
that is very functional.
In fact, personally, I don't know of any others.
This model implements a core area, a buffer
zone and a transition area.
The core area is generally composed of a classified
ancient forest,
defined as a national park or a fauna reserve,
which is surrounded by a "to be defined" buffer
zone.
And it's at that point maybe, that we need
to be very inventive
to explain this buffer zone.
In Senegal, we have recently put in place
what we call the concept of a natural community
reserve.
They are indigenous areas surrounding the
park
and each
local community puts in place this land,
which is a natural community reserve,
but which belongs
to the village land.
So this space is deliberated and managed in
a rational way,
with relations forged in symbiosis
between the managers of protected areas and
the people
so that the people can find in the buffer
zones, what they want there
and avoid the risk of meeting the managers,
and rangers, inside the protected areas.
Well, Moussa mentioned the importance of the
buffer zones
in the organization of the community or the
conservation of protected areas.
Note that it is a notion that differs from
one country to another,
and sometimes even from one park to another
in the same system.
Generally, the point of establishing a buffer
zone lies in natural resources
being secured in the best way,
obviously, that's understandable.
It also lies in the relationship
between the protected area's local populations
improving,
and of course, in the ability to respond better
to the needs of certain species in the park,
who are susceptible to occasionally
leaving the strict boundaries of the core
area.
Buffer zones surround the protected area and
are used to reinforce conservation
by creating an interface between this protected
area
and the other territories where access isn't
monitored.
So, it enables, for example, farming activities
and elephants,
who will plunder the harvests, to avoid coexisting
directly together,
or even so a cattle farm and a territory used
by lions and hyenas don't coexist.
The buffer zone is therefore useful for managers
of protected areas
and for those living in their outskirts.
Defining a buffer zone is complicated,
because, essentially, it relates to the issue
of governance.
Its size must make sense in ecological terms.
Therefore it will be large enough from the
perspective of the custodian
to protect the protected area,
but it must also take into account the outskirts
and the people,
and so it will not encroach too much on farming
land.
In Senegal, an approach consisted
in creating a certain number of community
reserves
all around the Niokolo-Koba park to protect
it better.
By extending this zone of natural community
reserves
all the way along Niokolo-Koba,
we have therefore tried to create a strip
of more than 691,000 acres
of community protected areas,
that almost completely surround the central
nucleus of Niokolo-Koba.
And I think that we have, through this natural
community reserve,
explained this notion of the buffer zone.
It is a space, we need to make sure is clear,
it is a space that is on village land,
and so that originally belongs to the villagers.
It is now managed in a rational way
by villagers alongside the managers of the
protected areas
in such a way as to produce in this space
everything
that the villagers went to get in the park
in the form of poaching,
and for which they risked their lives.
So it is really a negotiation, an arbitration
zone
for the various concerns of the managers,
the protected areas and the people.
The construction of connectivity or of buffer
zones requires, in practice,
a sustained participatory approach.
That is where the main difficulty in their
development lies,
but it is also a unique opportunity,
because it forces productive dialogue with
the outskirts.
There, the essential has been said.
I will see you again in the next episode,
which will be about ecological restoration
of protected areas.
In the meantime, have an excellent day!
See you very soon.