Hello and welcome everyone.
Today's lesson is dedicated
to the ecological restoration of protected
areas.
We will have a look at the definition of ecological
restoration,
the principles and guidelines
of ecological restoration of protected areas,
an example of ecological restoration,
and the process of ecological restoration
for protected areas
suggested by the World Commission on Protected
Areas.
To find out more, you could, in fact, refer
to the document
Ecological Restoration for Protected Areas:
Principles, Guidelines, and Best Practices.
A document prepared by the World Commission
on Protected Areas'
Ecological Restoration Taskforce on this topic.
During its Conference of the Parties, the
twelfth session,
the Convention on Biological Diversity has
reaffirmed the necessity
of reinforcing the support and the cooperation
intended to promote ecosystem restoration
efforts
in developing countries.
All with the purpose of implementing
the Strategic Plan for Biodiversity 2011-2020
and meeting the Aichi Biodiversity Targets.
This is why the Convention on Biological Diversity
has decided to expand and reinforce
monitoring of the deterioration and restoration
of ecosystems.
This is with the aim of supporting adaptive
management
and drawing up a report on the progress made
on the Aichi Biodiversity Targets,
and particularly on Targets 5, 14, and 15.
Definitions.
Ecological restoration is
the process of assisting the recovery of an
ecosystem
that has been degraded, damaged, or destroyed.
It is therefore an intentional activity
that initiates or accelerates the recovery
of a previous ecosystem,
that is old or recent regarding its specific
composition,
its community structure, its ecological functioning,
the ability of the physical environment to
support all of its living organisms,
and its connectivity with the landscape.
This assumes and requires good knowledge
of functional and adaptive ecology of targeted
ecosystems,
knowledge of the history of anthropogenic
deterioration,
and finally of choosing a reference ecosystem
to guide planning, implementation, follow-up,
and assessment
of the restoration project.
The reasons and the targets for ecological
restoration:
restoration in, and around, a protected area
contributes to a number of societal aims and
objectives,
which are linked to biodiversity conservation
and human well-being.
The reasons for implementing restoration projects
varies and can include, for example,
the recovery of certain species,
the reinforcement of an ecosystem function,
or connectivity at the level of a terrestrial
or marine landscape,
the improvement of possibilities for tourist
experiences,
or even, the recovery or the improvement of
diverse ecosystem services.
Restoration can contribute to the ability
to adapt to climate changes
by reinforcing resilience when faced with
changes,
and by supplying ecosystem services.
It can contribute to the easing of climate
change
by capturing carbon dioxide in ecosystems.
Climate change and other rapid global changes
form new challenges for restoration
and they highlight the need for adaptive management,
as was highlighted in module four.
The World Commission on Protected Areas
identifies three fundamental principles
for the ecological restoration of protected
areas.
Ecological restoration of a protected area
must be:
effective.
This means, effective ecological restoration
is one that recovers and preserves the values
of a protected area.
Efficient.
Efficient ecological restoration
is one that maximizes positive results
by minimizing time, resource and effort costs.
Commitment.
Ecological restoration of protected areas
that induces commitment is one
where partners and interested parties collaborate
together,
that favors participation,
and that improves the visitors' experience.
Specific good practices which must be applied
to a given project
must be chosen during the planning and conception
stages of the project.
Let's take the examples of ecological restoration
introduced by Abdou Salam Kane
from the Direction of the National Parks of
Senegal.
In 2006, thanks to a partnership with the
Danone Livelihood Fund,
the project developed by Oceanium
with the purpose of restoring an extremely
degraded mangrove forest
came about at the same time as the launch
of the mangrove reforestation program
along the Senegal coastline.
Mangroves, which used to be abundant along
this coastline,
have gradually disappeared after human intervention,
from the rise in sea levels and from the drought.
The local population has seen its subsistence
sources,
especially food sources, disappear.
Over time with people stocking up shrimp farms,
and in a general way, oyster farms, which
used to be prosperous
in mangroves,
and with saltwater penetrating the soil,
paddyfields have stopped producing.
To this day, nearly 150 million mangrove trees
have been planted in nearly 500 villages at
the Saloum Delta and in Casamance.
It is the largest world-wide program for mangrove
reforestation
with nearly 30,000 acres of mangroves having
been planted.
Moreover in the Delta of the Senegal River,
the Tocc Tocc community nature reserve, which
is involved in the Lac de Guiers,
is a continental area
of permanent fresh water.
It is in the process of being restored by
local communities
with technical support from the Direction
of the National Parks
and a number of partners.
The result of the restoration efforts
have enabled it to be recognized as a Ramsar
site.
With global warming, the rising sea level,
the Tocc Tocc community nature reserve's initiative
and the one by Oceanium are all crucial projects,
which guarantee the improvement of livelihoods,
and which demonstrate the need to collaborate
with nature
in order to guarantee that the environment
and populations, who depend on protected areas
and wetlands for their livelihood,
receive support for codevelopment activities.
The World Commission describes a seven stage
process,
recommended as a way of undertaking
the ecological restoration of protected areas.
The stages are not strictly sequential,
and some elements, like adopting adaptive
management
must occur throughout the whole project.
This process is placed in context
through a series of diagrams and more conceptualized
graphic boxes,
which provide extra information.
To conclude, ecological restoration of protected
areas contributes
to reaching the global targets for biodiversity
conservation.
It involves acting with caution and humility,
and recognizing that ecological restoration
is a complex and difficult process,
and that us intervening can have unexpected
consequences.
The World Commission on Protected Areas' approach
for restoring protected areas is a policy
framework
based on a group of clear principles,
which, rather than defining rigid processes,
supports an approach favoring a holistic approach,
large collaboration, careful planning, and
thought-through implementation
so as to obtain the desired results.
You can find out more
by also reading the 69th edition of the NAPA
letters,
which summarizes the guidelines which helped
me to prepare this lesson.
There, we have reached the end of this lesson.
The next episode will talk about the issues
of gender and equity
in managing protected areas.
Meanwhile, have an excellent day.