Hello, in this sequence, we will look into
the notions
of gender and equity in protected areas.
The reference book for this sequence is is
French:
Gender and equity in the Protected Areas of
West Africa
by Julienne N. Anoko for FIBA and IUCN.
This is the reference book that I recommend
you read.
What is equity?
According to a commonly accepted definition,
taking into consideration the equity principle
"aims at an equitable access of men and women
to develop their capacities,
regardless of their sex, gender, social class,
religion or age".
The issue of equity, please take note of this,
tends to be associated or confused
with women's demands,
because it is mainly them who suffered and
who continue to experience inequality.
But you will have realized that there is much
more to this notion.
In the process of managing protected areas,
in most cases, dialogue only takes into account
the men's perspective.
It therefore excludes the other groups, women
whose roles as users,
managers, environmental experts,
but also as destroyers of natural resources
are clearly evident.
It also excludes young and old people,
and other sectors of the population.
And yet, the approach for sustainable development
recommends recognizing and taking into account
all of a nation's strengths in order to attain
their objectives.
It subsequently becomes essential
that all development projects include the
principle of equity
in each of their phases.
Let's have a look together at some extracts
from the video on equity,
a video developed and prepared by the IUCN
PAPACO Programme.
Equity...
I see equity much more as a justice principle,
insofar as... the two genders
have just as much the same ability
to intervene in the development process,
and that the female gender is frequently made
invisible
despite all the efforts they make.
It would simply be establishing justice.
We need to start from the woman's place in
society,
which is good,
and try to move forward so that there is this
equity,
because we know so well
that they participate in the management of
areas.
She is the one who lives it daily,
and it's through the day-to-day that we can
change, I believe.
Throughout the centuries, it is the women,
who have suffered the most from discrimination.
Today, we feel obliged to try and first of
all balance things out,
to at least level things out
for there to be a certain, and a faint balancing
out,
at least before incorporating all of the other
social classes.
These girls come from local villages
in the hunting zone in Ghana,
and as their zone's benefits are reduced,
their zone's natural resources,
we can only pay them back
by supporting them with their children's studies.
It is true that other activities are carried
out in this field,
there is maybe gardening that may have been
mentioned to you,
there is also some drilling that has been
done in some villages.
So that's what we do with the idea
that we can still give back to these local
zones.
Educating these young girls, it's also educating
a family.
We therefore think that if, in these villages,
there are girls who manage to succeed, they
will be more sensitive,
they will come back to support their parents
and these are immediate impacts
and its the whole village, who will benefit
from it.
One day, these women will come back to work
on their village's development
for decision-making,
for the other activities.
We have been thinking
that, for now, it is better to support these
young girls,
who have not only been abandoned,
because the parents prefer to give them away
in marriage,
but we think that, now, as soon as they succeed,
they will come back to support their village.
With equity, we also think
that we must aim to eliminate all of the barriers
that are an obstacle to people possessing
their economic,
social and political rights.
Equity is also justice.
This means eliminating all sorts of barriers
that mean that people cannot benefit from
what is rightly theirs.
Pendjari Park covers nearly 300,000 hectares.
It was created in 1961.
It belongs to the savanna that extends over
several million acres
between Benin, Burkina Faso and Niger.
They are mainly composed of W Park and Arli
Park.
In the south, it is bordered by the Atakora
Mountains.
The Pendjari river is the only significant
waterway
and it runs for around 125 miles within the
park.
Pendjari park was declared Biosphere Reserve
in 1986.
It has been split into several zones with
one for hunting,
where there are dozens of wildlife species,
including elephants, lions, buffaloes and
antilopes.
In the 1980s, Pendjari Park's natural resources
gradually deteriorated.
Local people were therefore kept away from
the park
and poaching was rife throughout the area.
Having observed this, management decided to
involve the local populations
in the management of the reserve.
Equity has added to the management of natural
resources,
particularly in West Africa, firstly by showing
us
that women and vulnerable groups
are knowledgeable,
and equity has enabled the knowledge that
these people have to be valued.
Equity has also enabled these advantages to
be spread out
and equity has enabled many of these people
to come forward,
to have a voice so that they can express themselves,
as we've been able to listen to groups that
we were not listening to,
thanks to equity in conservation in West Africa.
The Urok community area has the essential
characteristic
of cultural inclusion.
Management rules are decided
by updating traditional management rules.
In traditional management, women play a role
in every stage
of exploiting strategic resources,
like, for example, shells for food security.
And we cannot be effective when managing these
resources
if we do not involve women.
And so, more than just a question of finding
equity,
it is also about finding effectiveness.
Along with other women, young and old,
Iana is off to collect shells on the shores
at low tide.
These shells are one of the staple foods in
the Bijagos,
especially just before the harvest, when the
lofts are empty.
It is also a traditional ritual
that is transmitted from one generation to
another
and tradition is always closely linked to
the environment.
We cook the shells with rice, if we have rice,
otherwise we can cook them with mangoes.
We can also use mangrove fruit,
it is very very nourishing.
It is a traditional dish.
Our grandmothers and mothers taught us how
to prepare shells.
It is also very important during rituals and
ceremonies.
Bijago people are organized by age groups
and to transition from one age group into
another,
a ritual and ceremonies are needed.
For these events, we prepare the traditional
dishes.
I am a member of Urok's management commitee.
I have every right to speak in this meeting,
to express myself.
In West Africa, we have started to act,
we put it in place, the people accepted it,
but we still have many obstacles,
which mean that people aren't taking the plunge.
People don't have the courage to say "yes,
we will accept change."
And I think we should not be afraid,
because it's a desire
and until we decide to change things ourselves,
to work on it, I don't think we will manage
it.
But there are still many constraints.
We must also understand that things were built
over many centuries
and what we would like is for people to be
made aware,
to accept that we can change,
and that the changes are not just negative.
There, this sequence is now finished.
You now understand the whole point of integrating
and taking into account
the principle of equity in managing protected
areas.
For the manager, it is about prioritizing
dialogue
between all social classes.
It is about integrating equity
in developing and preparing the management
plan.
It is about having all the groups participate
in the activities,
in the protected area's actions.
Finally, it is about ensuring an equitable
distribution
of access to development, to activities,
and to the benefits that protected areas can
bring.
There, this sequence is finished.
I invite you to refer to the guide and the
video.
Have a good day.