Hello and welcome to this lesson,
dedicated today to a problem,
we regularly encounter in managing protected
areas:
corruption and trafficking, which goes hand
in hand with it.
Of course, this is not the only sector where
this phenomenon exists,
but its influence on numerous failures in
parks and reserves is such
that we wanted to make it a specific topical
issue.
In addition to this lesson,
you can find more information on this phenomenon
on the websites shown on this picture,
which discuss the subject and give you
at least some solutions.
So for this lesson, a specialist from EAGLE
Network will help us.
EAGLE are eco-activists for governance and
law enforcement.
We have Luc Mathot, who is based in Libreville,
in Gabon.
So the first question to ask ourselves
is whether this phenomenon of corruption
is a significant problem in our protected
areas.
I work mostly in Central Africa.
In each protected area, if you have 20 or
30 eco-guards,
there will be at least one who is corrupt,
but actually sometimes, it tends to be the
other way round:
one of twenty who is not corrupt.
I don't have the evidence,
but in every protected area there are always
corrupt eco-guards.
It's inevitable.
I am not only talking about eco-guards,
it is the gendarmes around them, etc.
Salaries are not always very high, the temptation
is very strong.
They give you one or two million.
The question is, "What does corrupt mean?"
Is it someone who let's through a little meat,
or who closes his eyes to game coming through
or is it someone who organizes the trafficking?
So there really are several levels of corruption
and complicity.
I don't know if it starts at the top
or the bottom, but it is at all levels.
We have had water and forestry agents implicated.
In Gabon, there was a captain in the Gendarmerie
that we had arrested with ivory.
He was selling ivory himself, it was in his
official car.
A prefect has been arrested, he did seven
months in jail,
a sub-prefect, so it can be at all levels.
We have had cases... we have had eco-guards,
for example,
or the managers of protected areas are corrupt.
You should know that traffickers, poachers
have money.
It is of course for profit
that they take part in trafficking
and so they have a tendency to get close to
eco-guards,
to get close to managers to corrupt them,
to offer them money.
So either it is a bit organized like that
or maybe a little opportunistic.
Eco-guards who catch a poacher, a trafficker
of ivory or something else,
automatically, the poacher will try to corrupt
the eco-guard
or the manager of the protected area who caught
him,
so we have had a lot of cases in North Congo,
Cameroon,
they are eco-guards who have been arrested
who have gone to prison
and who have been convicted.
So it is important to look at this problem
and that the eco-guards
and managers of protected areas are ready
to react.
You can also find recent information on the
species
that are the most exposed to trafficking
and the consequences that it has on their
conservation
in the leaflets published by EAGLE Network.
Let's now look with Luc
at the main challenges of wildlife trafficking
in Africa.
We are always talking about the problems of
means, of capacity,
we don't have enough cars, we don't have enough
money...
The real problem, is actually
the lack of real political will and corruption,
even collusion.
It is not that traffickers of ivory or other
things,
are really strong, organized.
We are not at the level of drug trafficking
with armed men
who shoot at you at any time...
We could stop the trafficking.
We really could stop it.
If on our side,
we had really honest, effective teams...
and they were competent,
because often we work with eco-guards, water
and forestry agents
who are not used to fighting against trafficking.
So, we must work with specialists, agencies
who fight against drug trafficking, cocaine
trafficking.
The same agencies can fight against ivory
That's what we did,
that's the opportunity we had in Togo,
where now it is the anti-drug agency which
works on ivory.
And for them ivory is like cocaine,
and now we have much more effective results,
real legal procedures, real investigations.
An eco-guard, a water and forestry agent is
not even used to arresting someone,
to taking him to prison, to taking him in
front of a prosecutor,
the code of criminal procedure, he can't master
it.
So there is this problem of competence and
then that of corruption,
I have already talked a lot about it,
but we think it really is the biggest problem.
A subject, we talk a lot about at the moment,
is ivory trafficking.
How is the struggle against this phenomenon
going?
In the case of ivory, if we talk about corruption,
it is a special case but similar,
it is a special case
in that the amounts involved are large.
You sometimes seize three or four tons of
ivory,
that represents three or four million of Euros
in Asia.
And when there is more money, it is easier
to corrupt.
There is a lot of complicity,
a lot of corruption, obviously.
Certain countries like Botswana,
which is the least corrupt in Africa along
with the Seychelles,
there is very little trafficking.
There are 200,000 elephants, something like
that, in Namibia as well.
You realize that a lot of States say, "It's
not our fault,
we are an African State.
It is because there is demand for ivory from
the Chinese."
Yes, that is true, but why in Botswana,
why in Namibia, is there much less trafficking
than in Central Africa, than in West Africa?
It's because they are the countries which
are more watchful,
where there is less corruption,
in which the law is more vigorously applied.
There is also a lack of political will.
You hear all the time
that a certain country has signed agreements,
there are laws, they want to fight,
there are action plans, strategies, workshops...
I almost want to say each month, in any case
each year,
but overall on the ground, nothing changes.
There is not really a political will.
The elephant is also an animal that is a little
anachronistic,
which causes damage,
which is not always welcomed by populations.
This has perhaps some consequences for political
will,
but I think that it is above all
because there are financial issues behind
this pro-ivory lobbying.
And of course, there is always corruption.
So concretely, are there solutions to this
problem?
Again, solutions to improve slightly the fight
against wildlife trafficking,
it would be, as I said just before,
to work with specialists in the fight against
trafficking.
Not biologists, not water and forestry agents
nor eco-guards,
but people who have worked on drug trafficking,
on mass trafficking, human trafficking.
So they are much more effective.
They can work day and night, they are used
to that.
They are used to dealing with legal procedures,
arresting people, interrogating people.
Most of the water and forestry agents in all
countries,
they finish work at 4pm-5pm,
Often also they don't feel strong, they are
not armed,
they are not trained for that.
So again, working with the most competent
structures
and then anticipating corruption,
knowing if we arrest a trafficker,
we know very well that there will be someone,
maybe even a lot of people, who he will call
to get this person released,
maybe because they received money, or he's
a friend,
maybe because they do business together etc.
So you must anticipate the corruption.
To illustrate all this,
let's look in more detail at EAGLE's action
on the ground.
We try above all to work with the national
authorities in Africa
so that they can increase the degree of law
enforcement.
EAGLE's work can be resumed in four points.
We have the investigation:
we identify or localize the traffickers
and we gather a maximum amount of evidence
against them,
traffickers of ivory in particular, wildlife
in general.
Then we put pressure on the authorities to...
facilitate the arrest of these traffickers.
Always caught in the act or almost always
in the act
with the ivory in their hands,
so whilst they are selling the ivory or panther
skins or live animals.
And then, there is the legal side.
We have the legal experts who follow the case
with the authorities,
who check that records haven't gone missing.
Sometimes, a file goes missing, a clerk takes
the file,
it can then no longer be found...
We check all that, we follow the case to court
with our teams of legal experts but also our
lawyers
who are there to defend the water and forests,
to defend governments.
And then there is the media side, we broadcast
all the results.
We inform the public, the authorities at the
same time,
to also dissuade potential traffickers.
So it is on these four points,
that we really put a strong emphasis in the
fight against corruption.
This is the end of this lesson.
The next episode will be an introduction to
the Ramsar Convention,
which deals with wetlands.
Have a great day!