Hello and welcome to everyone,
today's class is about Ramsar Convention
on wetlands.
We're going to review the presentation of
the Convention,
organs, missions, pillars
and international organizations that are partners
with the convention.
For more informations, you can check the website
of the convention for more details.
Wetlands are a public good that we ought to
protect,
they contains 80 per cent of biodiversity.
They have a major role in the regeneration
of water resources
and the preservation of biodiversity.
The convention on wetlands
is the framework of international cooperation
and national action
for conservation and rational use of wetlands.
It's also called Ramsar Convention
from the name of the Iranian city where it
was adopted in 1971.
About 80 percent of UN member states
are contracting parties of the Ramsar Convention.
The convention adopted a large definition
of wetlands
including all lakes and rivers, underground
aquifers,
swamps and marshes, wet grasslands,
peatlands, oases, estuaries, deltas and tidal
flats,
mangroves and other coastal areas, costal
reefs,
and all human-made sites such as fish ponds,
rice paddies fields, reservoirs, salt pans.
Organs of the convention : the application
of Ramsar Convention
is the result of a permanent partnership between
contracting parties,
169 on the date of 10 June 2015.
The permanent committee is the secretariat
of the convention
that benefits from advice of a subsidiary
organ of experts,
a scientific and technical review panel
and the support of the program on communication,
capacity building, education,
participation and awarness.
Every three years, representatives of the
contracting parties
gather in a conference, as the supreme political
organ
of the convention, adopting resolutions in
order to administrate
the work of the Convention and to improve
the means
required by the parties in order to achieves
its goals.
The mission of the Convention is the conservation
and the rational use of wetlands by actions,
on a local,
regional and national scale, plus international
cooperation
in order to contribute to the realisation
of sustainable development in the entire world.
In accordance with the three pillars of the
Convention,
contracting parties commit to :
- Work for the rational use of every wetlands
in the framework of national plans, politics
and laws,
management measures, and education of the
public.
- To register appropriate wetlands on the
list
of wetlands of international importance,
called, again, Ramsar List and to take care
of their governance.
- To cooperate on the international level
for cross-border wetlands,
shared wetlands systems, shared spaces
and development projects that could effect
wetlands.
What do wetlands do, and what could happen
to them.
They stock water, and guarantee its quality,
contributing
to resilience against drought.
They protect against flooding and storm effects.
They provide food and other services
such as transport and leisure.
They offer different types of housing for
biodiversity
and play a key role in biological cycles
for numerous species, and in annual migration
structures.
Under the pressure of a growing demand from
a human population in expansion,
wetlands are deteriorated and disappear.
Excessive exploitation of the latest wetlands
threatens more and more
their ability to provide essential services.
To counter this, we must ensure rational use
of wetlands
and the water they contain, restore degraded
wetlands,
and if necessary, create new ones to regain
the services
that we need.
Listen to Ania Grobicki, general secretary
of Ramsar for the functioning of the convention.
The most important body of the Ramsar Convention
of wetlands
is the conference of the parties, the COP
which meets every three years
to decide on the key strategic directions
of the convention.
In between the COP, the standing committee
meets annually
to guide the convention, it is composed of
the regional representatives
of each region of the six regions of the convention.
There is a scientific and technical review
channel, the STARP
which is a group of scientific and technical
experts
who publish important guidelines on the conservation
and wise use of wetlands.
Finally, at a global level, the Ramsar Convention
secretariat
is based in Gland, Switzerland, and manages
the everyday activities
of the Convention,
which includes publishing the Convention documents
and administrating the Ramsar sites of international
importance.
On a national level, the administrative authority
in each country
implements the strategic directions of the
Convention in that country
and the national wetlands commitee
which are multi-stakeholder platforms include
the private sector,
NGO and civil society to support the government
in implementing the Convention.
Finally, under the sustainable development
goals
the Convention is in charge of with monitoring
the extent of wetlands
worlwide.
Thank you very much.
Ramsar Convention recognises six International
Organizations Partners
that provide specialized technical assistance
and advice, in accordance with the principles
of the Convention.
They are :
Birdlife International, the International
water Management Institute,
the International union for conservation of
nature,
Wetland international, WWF international and
WWT.
The Convention is in collaboration with a
network of partners.
Listen to Anada Tiega, former general secretary
of Ramsar Convention, about relations between
protected areas and wetlands.
Links between wetlands and protected areas
are close.
Actually, it's because wetlands bring water
to biodiversity
and every protected areas which goal is the
conservation
of biodiversity include wetlands as an essential
part.
Because they are used as habitat, and also
as a place for reproduction, for breeding
little ones and bringing survival.
In fact, if we take a look, for instance,
at the world heritage
in those natural sites, every one of them
have wetlands
as a crucial part.
The MAB system for biosphere reserves
also include wetlands, in their central part.
Finally, Ramsar sites are exclusively wetlands.
Those Ramsar sites exist in order to protect
species,
every endemic migrant vulnerable species
in danger of extinction.
To conclude, wetlands are crucial for sustainable
development
because they provide the water we need.
Wetlands are the cradle of biological diversity
and provide water and primary productivity,
that an incalculable
number of plant and animal species rely on
for their survival.
Ramsar Convention is one of the only one to
take in account
a special type of natural environment.
That's it, we're at the end of the lesson,
next episode will be
a conclusion of the course called topicality
and conservation.
Looking forward to it, I wish you a good day.