Hello!
In this episode we're going to see
a new type, which is the type "String".
This type let's us define variables
corresponding
to a sequence of characters.
Declaring such a variable is
done as usual:
I begin by the name of the
type, which is "String",
followed by the name of the variable
that we are declaring, ending with a semi-colon.
For example, if I make this
declaration,
I declare a variable of type "String"
named "unNom" [means "someName"]
and which is not initialized yet.
In this declaration and initialization,
I declare a second variable also of
type String,
named "Message" and which I can
represent like this...
So be careful, the quotation marks here
aren't part of the sequence of
characters,
they just allow to define the beginning
and the end of the sequence.
So my variable Message contains a
reference to the memory
where my sequence of characters
"Bonjour tout le monde" is stored.
The characters that make up the
sequence of characters
have their own type, which is the type
"char", that means that I can declare
variables of type "char" which will
contain one single character each.
For example, I declare a variable
c1 of type "char"
and which will contain the
character "m".
So, please note that to delimit the
character, we use this time
what are called simple quotes,
whereas to delimit a sequence
of characters,
for example the sequence "mémoire",
we use quotation marks,
also called "double quotes".
A good mnemonic to remember the
difference between the two is
that for a unique character we use
simple quotes,
for a sequence of characters which
contains generally several characters,
we use the double quotes.
As for the arrays, a variable of
type String
contains a reference to a
sequence of characters.
The semantic use of the operators =
and == is then the same as with arrays.
For example, here I declare a variable
"chaîne" which contains a reference
to the empty String;
here I declare a variable "chaine2"
which contains a reference
to the String "foo".
When I do this operation, this
instruction, I assign the value
of chaine2 to the variable chaine,
chaine2 contains a reference to "foo",
so I am copying this reference in my
variable chaine,
the reference to the empty String
is lost,
as it is overwritten by this new
reference,
and "chaine" also points to
"foo".
Now, if I do
"if (chaine == chaine2)",
well this condition is true, as "chaine"
and "chaine2" contain
the same reference, both
to "foo".
The String literals occupy the same
unique memory addresses, which is called
the "String pool" or "String literal pool".
For example, when I do this
declaration and initialization,
I declare chaine1 which will contain
a reference to "foo".
In fact, this "foo" String will be put in
the String literal pool
and when I do this second declaration
and initialzazion,
chaine2 will also be initialized to
the "foo" String and it's
this same reference, this same "foo"
String that will be used.
Therefore, chaine1 and chaine2 will contain
the same reference, that means
that when I use this condition
chaine1 == chaine2, this condition
is true.
Now let's move on to the printing
of a String type variable.
I declare and initialize here
a variable named "chaine"
with the sequence of characters "Welcome";
"chaine" contains therefore
a reference to "Welcome".
Now when I call the function "print"
and pass it "chaine",
I am entitled to expect that "print" prints
what is contained in "chaine",
that is the reference to the memory
where is effectively stored
the sequence of characters
"Welcome".
Well that isn't the case and "print"
indeed prints "Welcome".
At this stage of your learning, we can
consider this as
an exception for Strings as opposed to
other non-primitive types.
But it's a useful exception, as
when we
print a sequence of characters, we
want to print
the sequence of characters rather than
the reference to that sequence.
We can concatenate a sequence of
characters,
that is put them end to end, by
using the "+" sign.
In this example chaine1 and chaine2
are variables of type
"sequence of characters", and
chaine1 + chaine2
is a new sequence of characters made
of chaine1
followed by the characters of chaine2.
For example, here I declare a variable
named "nom"
of type "sequence of characters",
and here a variable "prenom".
["prénom" means "firstName"]
Let's suppose that I have put a value
for "nom", for example "Dupont",
and for "prenom", another value,
"Jean" [means "John"].
In this assignment here, I begin
by doing
this first concatenation , that is I
put together
"Dupont", and this sequence of characters,
that is formed of a single space.
So for the moment I get a sequence
of characters that is
"Dupont" followed by the space character,
and with this String, I am going to concatenate
once again, by adding the value of
"prénom", that is "Jean", to it.
All this constitutes a new sequence
of characters.
As I am going to assign the result
to my variable "nom", "nom" will contain
a reference to that new sequence
of characters,
and that reference will be
lost.
So be careful, concatenation
never modifies
the concatenated Strings.
It makes a copy of the Strings
into another memory location.
That's what we can see on this diagram:
"Dupont" hasn't been modified.
The following combinations are possible
for concatenating two Strings.
I can simply concatenate two
variables of String type,
but I can also begin with a variable
of String type
followed by a variable of
a basic type,
that is "int", "double", "char", etc.
Or the inverse: begin
with a variable of one of the basic types
"int", "double". "char", etc.
followed by a String-type variable.
If I take the previous example, I had
used a sequence of characters
to insert a space between "nom" and
"prénom", we could recognize
that it was a sequence of characters
because I used quotation marks
which are also called "double
quotes",
but I can also use a simple
character,
that's what we see with
this combination.
So in this example I'll use
this time a single character
that is recognizable by the fact that
I'm using simple quotes.
This assignment will do
the exact same thing as
the previous one.
A concatenation of the form
"String + char"
is a very useful way to add a
character at the end of a String,
In the same way, the
concatenation "char + String"
let us add a character at the
beginning of a String.
Let's take this example, where we
declare a variable "reponse"
that will contain a reference to
the String "solution"
and let's suppose that I want to
change "solution" to the plural form
if a variable "n" is greater than 1.
I'll do the test and here I'll do
a concatenation.
"reponse" still has the value "solution", and
with the concatenation I'll add "s" to it,
and I'll put the result in my variable
"reponse".
Therefore, "reponse" will now contain
a reference
to the result of the concatenation,
and this link will be lost.
So here we are! That's the end of
this first video about Strings.
In the next episode, we'll focus
essentially on
the comparison of sequence of
characters.