In this episode, we'll focus
on the comparison of sequence of
characters.
Be careful, the operators "==" for
the equality
and "!=" for the non-equality,
when applied on two variables
of String type,
test if the two variables have a reference
(or not) to the same memory addresses,
which contains a sequence of characters.
Additionally, with the use of the
String literal pool,
this causes a number of
subtleties,
that we are going to see
in this example.
Here I have the declaration and the
initialization of a variable "s1"
that will reference the sequence of
characters "abc".
Here, "s2" is also initialized with the
sequence "abc".
This sequence "abc" is part of the
String literal pool.
That's why "s1" and "s2"
have the same reference on the
same sequence of characters.
Here, I declare a varialbe "s3"
in which I copy the content
of "s2".
"s2" contains a reference to
this sequence "abc"
and therefore "s3" will now also
contain
a reference to this same sequence
"abc".
I now do this last assignment.
To "s4", I'll assign
the concatenation of the
variable "s1",
which is "abc",
and the empty sequence, which I'll
represent like this.
I finally simply obtain the
sequence "abc".
And "s4" will get a reference to
this sequence "abc".
But note that this "abc" isn't the
same as this one.
More precisely, they aren't in the
same memory location
and this reference is different from
these references.
So why exactly?
That's because "s1", "s2" and "s3"
were directly initialized from
String literals,
while that isn't the case for "s4".
We can verify that by executing
these instruction lines.
This "println" prints the result
of this condition.
This condition is true when
"s1" is equal to "s2",
that is when the reference in "s1"
is the same as the reference in "s2".
And in the diagram we can see that
it is indeed the case.
Therefore this condition is true.
"s2" is indeed equal to "s3"
as "s2" and "s3" both contain
a reference to this same sequence
of characters "abc".
This condition is true.
And as here there's a "&",
this whole condition is true.
We'll therefore print "true", as we
can verify it in practice.
When I execute this instruction
line,
which prints the sequence of
characters "s4",
we'll get the sequence "abc"
printed,
which is this sequence here.
Let me remind you that when we
execute the function
"print" or "println" on a String
variable,
we don't print the reference, but the sequence
of characters that is referenced,
which is useful.
Now, if I print the value of
this condition,
which is "s1" = "s4",
"s1" contains this reference,
"s4" contains this reference,
which are different references,
so the conditon is false.
And this "println" will print
"false",
even if the two sequences corresponding
to "s1" and "s4"
are the same, are both "abc".
So it is indeed the references that
are compared.
But in practice we want to compare the
sequences of characters themselves
rather than their references.
And to achieve this, there's a
specific process
to compare Strings.
To effectively compare two sequences
of characters,
we have the function "equals".
For example, to compare two variables
"chaine1" and "chaine2",
I'll call my function "equals"
like this.
So, first the name of the first variable.
followed by a point, followed by the
name of the function "equals",
and followed by the second variable that we
want to compare, as an argument to "equals".
This "equals" function will return
either "true", if "chaine1" and "chaine2" correspond
to the same sequence of characters
and don't necessarily have the same
reference;
or "false", if the two sequences
are different.
For example, here I declared
a variable "s1"
that contains a reference to a sequence
of characters "abc",
a variable "s2" that contains a reference to
a sequence "aBc",
but with "b" in capital letter,
and here a variable "s4"
that is initialized to the result of the concatenation
of "s1" and the empty sequence.
"s1" corresponds to the sequence
"abc".
When I concatenate "abc" with the empty
sequence, I simply get the sequence "abc".
And "s4" will contain a reference to
this sequence "abc".
We saw in a previous slide that
the references contained in "s1"
and "s4" were different,
so I can't directly compare "s1" and "s4"
by using the character "==".
However, I can use the function
"equals".
That's what I'm doing here, I compare "s1" and
"s4" by calling the functrion "equals"
and I can verify that this time
I do obtain "true".
Because the sequence of characters are exactly
the same, the characters "abc" are the same.
If I now test if "s1" is equal to "s2",
it turns out that the function "equals"
makes the difference between
lowercase and uppercase letters,
and as 'b' is lowercase here,
and this 'B' is uppercase,
the function will return "false".
That was the comparison of two
sequence of characters.
In the last video, we'll see what else we can
do on sequences of characters.