In this video we'll conclude on
sequences of characters
and see other computations that are
possible on sequences of characters.
We can individually access the
characters
of a sequence of characters.
For example, the instruction line chaine.charAt(index),
with  index in argument,
will return the character of index 'index'
of the sequence 'chaine'.
The instruction line chaine.indexOf
with a character in argument
returns the position of the first occurrence
of the character 'caractère',
that is the character passed as an
argument  in 'chaine'
and will return -1 if 'caractere'
isn't in 'chaine'.
We also have the function
length,
which means that we can write
chaine1.length() with parenthesis
and it will return the length of
the sequence,
the number of characters in the
sequence.
Careful, careful!
There's a pair of parenthesis.
So it's different than arrays,
in this case.
For example, here I declare
a variable s1
that will reference a sequence of
characters 'abcmbx'.
When I execute this declaration and
initialization of the variable 'longueur',
the variable 'longueur' will contain
the number of characters of s1,
that is 6.
This declaration declare a variable c1
that will be initialized
to the character of index 0 of the
sequence s1, which is this 'a'.
So c1 will contain the character 'a'.
In this declaration of c2 I put the
character of s1
that's at the index 'longueur - 1'.
'longueur' contains 6, so 'longueur - 1' is 5.
And the character of index 5 is
0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5.
That's the last character of the
sequence s1.
And finally, the declaration of the
variable i will put in i
the index of the character b starting
from the left in the sequence s1.
So s1 is this sequence.
'b', the first 'b' is at the index 1.
And therefore i will be initialized
with the value 1.
So be careful, the characters are
numbered
like the elements of an array,
they begin at zero.
At this point, we can do a quiz.
In your opinion, what does this code
print when we execute it?
Take your time to execute the code
step by step.
I'll let you think about it.
So the variable 'essai' is initialized
with the sequence "essai".
The variable 'test' is initialized
with the empty sequence.
We enter this for-loop, where i
will vary from 1 to 3.
During the first round of the loop,
we'll execute this assignment.
For the moment test is the empty sequence
and we concatenate with it the character
that is in 'essai' at the index of the
value of this expression.
i has the value 1, so 6 minus 2
times i is 4.
We'll therefore consider the character
of index 4 of 'essai'.
That is 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, all have
the value 'i'.
We'll concatenate this character 'i' with the
empty sequence and obtain i
and put the result in 'test'.
'test' will now point to the sequence "i".
Let's then move on to this instruction line, that
will concatenate the character of index i
of the sequence of characters
'essai'.
i has the value 1, the character is
the character 's'.
We'll concatenate it with the sequence of
characters contained in 'test',
which is simply "i".
The result of the concatenation is the
sequence "si",
we'll put "si" here.
We then come back to the start
of the for-loop.
i now has the value 2.
We execute this assignment.
'test' now has the value "si".
This character is the character
of index 2 in 'essai'.
The character of index 2 is
(zero, one, two).
It's an 's',
that we'll concatenate with the
sequence "si"
and we'll obtain "sis", that we'll
assign to the variable 'test'
to obtain this.
Let's move on to the second
assignment.
essai.charAt(i). As i has the value 2,
it's this 's'
that we'll concatenate with the sequence
that corresponds to 'test'.
That is "sis", and we'll obtain
"ssis"
which we'll put in 'test'.
We'll now return a last time here,
with i that has the value 3.
'test' has the value "ssis" and we'll
concatenate this character,
so the character of index 0, in the
sequence 'essai',
that's this 'e' here.
We'll put the result in the
sequence 'test',
so we'll put "ssise" in 'test'.
We now move on to the
assignment.
essai.charAt(i) : i has the value 3,
it's the character of index 3
of 'essai',
that's 0, 1, 2, 3,
so 'a'.
We'll concatenate that with what
'test' contains, that is "ssise",
and get the sequence of characters
"assise".
'test' will now therefore point
to the sequence "assise".
We exit the loop, as i has
the value 3.
We get to this print instruction that will
simply print assise.
Just a word about inputs/outputs
with characters.
It turns out that there doesn't exist a
function nextChar() in the Scanner class.
To get a character
using this class,
you have to first declare a Scanner,
as usual.
Then you have to read a line
by using the function nextLine()
applied to the instance of
Scanner type
and put the result in a variable of
String type that I named s.
Then take the first character of this
sequence s
with the function charAt(), passing it
the index 0 as an argument.
So here in 'c', we'll obtain the first
character
that the user will have input
at this moment.
A String literal, entered by the user
during a read instruction line
for example with a Scanner, doesn't
belong to the String literal pool.
For it to be part of it, you have to
explicitly put it in,
with the help of the intern function.
Let's consider this example where I
begin by declaring a Scanner s
that will allow me to read what the
user inputs on the keyboard.
Here I declare a variable 'response'
of type sequence of characters
and I have a do-while loop
that will stop when the user enters
oui (= yes) as an answer.
This 'oui' is a sequence of
characters
that's in the String literal pool.
Now let's continue with the code.
Let's suppose that I read what the user
inputs on the keyboard,
and that I put the result in the
variable 'response'.
I'll get something like this.
Let's suppose that he has already
input "oui",
because he wants to exit
the loop.
But if you followed what I've
just said,
this "oui" isn't in the String
literal pool,
which means that this "oui" is
different from this "oui".
This print will indeed display 'oui'
for 'response'.
On the other side, this test won't
do what I want,
as here I'm testing the references.
'response' contains a reference
to this "oui"
and this "oui" isn't stored at the
same reference,
as it's in the String literal pool.
So in this test, the condition will
be false,
even if 'response' contains "oui".
I'll add the call to the 'intern'
function,
that I had hidden here.
What happens in this case?
When we execute this new
instruction line,
the 'oui' contained in 'response'
will be put in the String literal
pool.
It turns out that there already is
a "oui" in the String literal pool.
What will happen is that now
'response'
will contain a reference to this
"oui".
And this link is lost.
This print instruction line will display
a 'oui', like before.
This is the 'oui' that will be printed.
And now, when we do this test.
We are still testing the references.
That is the reference contained in
'response'
with the reference of this "oui",
which is in the String literal
pool.
But as this reference points to the
"oui" of the String literal pool,
it's the same reference and this test
will this time be true.
This is due to the 'intern'
function.
We saw there exists a number of
functions specific to String,
like the 'equals' function, or the
'length' function.
All these functions follow the
same syntax,
we begin with the name of a variable
of String type.
Then the function's name, with the
'point' character between them,
and followed by the arguments that
the function needs.
These functions are called
methods in Java.
They always produce a new
sequence of characters.
The sequences of characters
involved in this use
aren't modified.
For example, we have the function
'replace' that can be applied
to a variable of String type,
for example 'chaine' here.
It awaits two characters to be able
to function.
This 'replace' function will replace
the character 'char1' of 'chaine' with
the character 'char2'.
For example, if I have a sequence 'exemple'
initialized with 'abracadabra',
and that I call the 'replace'
function
by passing it the character 'a'
as first value,
and the character '*' as
second value.
This function will create a new
sequence of characters
where it will have replaced the 'a's
of 'abracadabra' with a star.
And that's exactly what I obtain here.
Note that the sequence 'exemple' still contains
the original sequence 'abracadabra'.
Another function is 'substring'.
It's also applied on a variable of String
type, like the 'chaine' variable,
and awaits two positions to
operate.
The positions of two characters.
This function will extract a
substring
from the variable given here.
So for example,
here I declare a variable 'exemple' initialized
with the sequence "anticonstitutionnel".
In this assignment, I execute the
function 'substring'
on this sequence by passing it the
values 4 and 16.
That means that I'll extract the
sequence of characters
that begins at the characters of
index 4.
'a' is the character of index 0.
1, 2, 3, 4, so it's this 'c' here.
The character of index 16 is
this 'n'.
But the last character is
not included.
So I'll stop here.
And this function will return the sequence
that is here, "constitution",
which will be used to initialize
the variable 'racineMot'.
Voilà, that's all we'll see for the
String type.