In a previous episode we studied
fixed-size arrays in Java.
We saw that for this type
of arrays,
once the size is set when we
initialize the array,
it isn't possible to modify it anymore
when the program executes.
Today we'll study dynamic
arrays,
which will free us from
this constraint.
Dynamic arrays have the particularity
to be able to increase
or decrease their size while
the program executes.
Their use requires a number
of concepts
related to object-oriented
programing.
However, as with character strings,
it isn't necessary to have any
preliminary knowledge
of these concepts to be able
to use
their functionalities.
We decided to present them very early
in the context of this course,
because dynamic arrays can be used
in very natural manners
to resolve many problems
that aren't necessarily related to
object-oriented programming.
As with fixed-size arrays,
dynamic arrays are a collection of
homogeneous data.
To use them,
we use a particular predefined type
in Java
called ArrayList. This type isn't
defined by default.
To use it in a program, you must include,
at the beginning of the file,
an import directive that will make
the ArrayList type accessible.
In Java, we can declare a variable
of ArrayList type
by using the following
syntax:
we put the variable name, and
as type,
we put the reserved name
"ArrayList",
followed by two characters "less than"
and "greater than".
Between these two characters, we
put the type of data
we want to put in the array.
Note that the type must imperatively
be an advanced type.
Here's a concrete example:
here we declare a variable
"tableau" [TN: means "array"],
the type of this variable is a dynamic
array of strings.
Note that the so-declared variable
isn't initialized:
we didn't assign any initial value to it.
How can we initialize an ArrayList?
A usual way of initializing an ArrayList
is to initialize it with an
empty array,
an array without any elements.
This is done like this:
to the variable associated with
the array,
we'll assign an empty array created
in the following manner.
It has to be used exactly like this.
The reserved word new, the
reserved word ArrayList,
here we'll put the exact same type
as the one we used for the
array declaration,
followed by two parenthesis,
not to forget.
Here we resort to a way related
to object-oriented programming,
but it isn't necessary to
fully understand
the ins and outs of it
to use it.
What you must remember here is that
with this instruction line,
you constructed a  dynamic
array
without any elements.
Here you have a concrete example
of declaration-initialization
of an ArrayList of Strings.
The "tableau" variable contains a
reference to a dynamic array
of Strings without any element yet.
As this so-declared array doesn't
contain any elements,
we'll naturally ask ourselves
the following question:
how do we put the values in
this array?
As for the strings, there exists a number
of specific methods related to
the ArrayList type.
To be able to use these functions,
you must use a particular syntax; the
array's name, followed by a dot,
followed by the name of the
function
and then we must indicate, in
parenthesis, the data
that the function needs to be
able to be executed.
Here you have a concrete
example.
I declare an ArrayList of strings,
named "prenoms" [TN: means "first name"]
and I initialize this array
with an empty array.
Then I use a particular
function
defined for ArrayList, called "size".
This function simply returns
the current size
of the ArrayList.
I used the syntax I just
mentioned,
that is the array's name,
followed by a dot,
followed by the function's name.
"size" doesn't need any
external information
to return us the array's size,
so I must put an empty pair
of parenthesis.
Of course, this instruction line's
execution will print 0,
as I've initialized the array with
an empty array.
Now here's a non-exhaustive
list
of a few typical functions associated
with arrays.
We just saw the "size" function
[a.k.a. "size" method]
that allows us to get the array's size
and that returns it as an integer.
There exists other functions/methods
such as "get" and "set"
that I'll use according to the
same principle,
that is the array's name, a dot,
followed by the function's name.
Here I notice that unlike the
"size" method,
I need to give data to the
"get" or "set" methods
in order for them to work.
The "get" and "set" methods are
the equivalent
of the indexation mechanism for
static arrays.
For a simple static array, if I want
to access
the element of index 'i', I
use indexation.
This mechanism doesn't exist
for dynamic arrays.
Instead, you must use methods
such as "get" and "set".
For a dynamic array,
if I want to access the element
of index 'i',
I'll use this notation
rather than this one.
The same applies if I want to modify
a static array.
I'll use this notation,
so if I want to modify the i-th
cell of a static array
I'll use this notation.
This doesn't exist for dynamic
arrays,
instead we'll have to use this
type of notation;
the array's name, a dot, "set",  and in
parenthesis the index of the cell
that I want to modify and the
corresponding value.
So this notation doesn't exist either
for dynamic arrays.
The restrictions on the
index's bounds
stay however the same as for a
fixed-size array,
the index varies between 0 and
the array's size - 1.
array's size - 1 is written
like this for
a dynamic array, for example.
So, as with fixed-size arrays,
any access attempt with an index
out of the bounds
will translate into an error
at the program's execution.
It's possible to test if a dynamic
array is empty
by using the "isEmpty" function.
This is a function that doesn't
need any data
to work. It will return
a value of boolean type,
true or false,
depending if the array contains
values or not.
The returned value will be true if
the array doesn't contain any values
and false otherwise.
The "clear" method empties
an ArrayList,
which means that it deletes all
its elements,
and transforms it into an empty
array.
If we imagine for example that
at a given moment
in a program, I have an ArrayList
that is in this state of filling
-- let's imagine that it's an ArrayList
of integers named "tab" --
if I call the "isEmpty" function,
it's obvious that the result
will be the false boolean,
as the array isn't empty.
I can now apply the "clear" function,
for example,
that will delete all the elements
and transform it into an empty array.
There is no more element in it.
So if I call again the "isEmpty" function,
this time the result will be true,
as the array is now empty.
The "remove" method allows us
to delete
the element of index 'i' in an ArrayList.
So if we imagine for example that
at a given moment,
we have an ArrayList of integers
with three cells,
that has this particular form,
the indexes vary between 0 and
size - 1, which gives us this.
Let's assume that the array is
named "tab".
Now, if I call the "size" function
on this array,
it will return 3 because my array
contains three cells.
Now if I call the "remove"
method
and pass it the index 1,
this element will be removed,
so all the elements
that follow this element will be
shifted to the left
and I'll finally obtain an array
with two cells.
And if I apply my "tab.size()" function again,
it will obviously return 2.
Here we see that for an ArrayList,
the size can indeed vary during
the execution
with the calls to methods of
this nature.
The index of the element that
we want to remove
obivously has to exist
in the array
when we call the "remove" function.
Let's suppose for example that instead
of doing "tab.remove(1)*,
I try doing "tab.remove(4)".
This will result in an error during
the program's execution.
If it's possible to remove elements
from an ArrayList,
it is also possible to add values
in such an array.
To achieve this we'll use the
"add" method,
and we'll have to give the value that
we want to add to the array.
The value will systematically be added
at the end of the array.
Let's take a concrete example of
an array of integers.
Here, "tab.size()" returns 3.
I add the value 8 to my array
by using the "add" method.
The result will be an array with
an additional cell.
This cell is at the end so I'll
have this in "tab",
and of course "tab.size()" will now
return 4;
we can see that the array
increased by one cell.
Now here's an example with a
few basic manipulations
that we can usually do on an ArrayList.
So we saw that to be able to
use the ArrayList type,
it was necessary to begin the
file
with an import directive
that will make the ArrayList type
available in the program.
I can now use the ArrayList
type
to declare a variable
and here I'm declaring a variable
of type ArrayList of Strings.
We also saw
that in order to initialize the array
to an empty array,
we have to use this sort
of notation.
So at the end of the execution
of this instruction line,
I get as a list the reference to
an empty ArrayList.
I then execute the following
instruction line.
I call the "add" method that allows me
to add a particular element,
here the string "un" [TN: means "one"]
at the end of the ArrayList.
As the array is empty, it doesn't make
a big difference;
ultimately I'll have a dynamic
array that will look like this.
I execute the following instruction line
that adds a string,
the string "deux" [TN: means "two"]
at the end of the array.
So here I get the following
content in the array.
If I want to print the content of
my ArrayList at this stage,
I use a for-loop.
We saw that we could use
for example a for-loop iterating
over a set of values.
Here my for-loop will alternately take
each element of the list
and print it by separating
them with a space.
So here, after the execution of this
instruction line, will be printed
the string "un" separated by a
whitespace from the string "two",
that will get printed like this
on the screen.
If I want to access the i-th cell
of an ArrayList,
either to look at its content, or
to modify it,
I'll have to use the "get" and "set"
methods.
So if I execute this instruction line,
knowing that the array filling at this
stage is like this,
I'll use the "get" method
that will access the element of
index 1 in the array.
This element of index 1 is the
string "deux"
and at that moment I'll print
the sequence "deux".
When I execute the following
instruction line,
I'll modify the element at
the index 0
in order that its new value is the string
"premier" [TN: means "first"].
So my array will now look like this,
after the execution of this
instruction line.
The element of index 0 that was "un"
has been changed into "premier".
In every example of ArrayList
showed until now,
the content was of type "String".
Of course, it's a deliberate
choice
that responds to the constraint that the
content of an ArrayList in Java
must systematically be of an
advanced type.
It can however turn out that
we need
to work with dynamic arrays
of integers.
How would we then proceed?
It's enough to know at this stage
that Java offers for each basic type,
a corresponding advanced type.
For example, for the 'int' type,
you have the Integer type, with
an uppercase 'I',
that is equivalent to "int" but is
of advanced type.
The same applies for the
"double" type.
There is an equivalent, "Double
with an uppercase 'D';
and this is valid for each basic type.
These advanced types of a
patricular kind
are particularly useful in
some contexts,
typically for ArrayList.
Why?
Because we saw that in
an ArrayList,
it's only possible to store values
of advanced type.
Thereby, in a Java program,
I can never declare
an ArrayList of "double" with a lowercase
'd', nor an ArrayList of "int".
I can however declare an ArrayList
of "Integer".
Once the array's declaration
is done
and respects the constraint that
the content is of an advanced type,
I can put
values of elementary type in
my array,
for a very simple reason.
That reason is that the conversion
of basic types into advanced types
can be done automatically.
That was't the case in the first
versions of Java,
but that's how it's done now.
And I can therefore work
with dynamic
arrays of "Integers" or of "Doubles"
while being nearly free from
the constraint
of using advanced types.
Now let's see that with a
concrete example.
Here we want to write a
small program
that fills an ArrayList
of integers
with stricly positive numbers.
We suppose that the values will
be requested from the user
and we also want to adhere to
a number of conventions.
If the user enters the value 0, that
will be the convention
that we want to restart filling the
array from the beginning.
If the user enters a negative
number,
that will be the convention that
we want to remove
the last element introduced
in the array.
The program's execution could
look like this.
We ask the user
to enter three strictly
positive values,
and we'll ask him each of these
values alternately.
Here we ask him to enter
the value of index 0
and we suppose that he
entered 5.
This value being strictly positive,
we'll store it in the array.
We then ask him the second
value, the one of index 1.
This value is strictly positive,
we put it in the array, once
again.
We then ask him to enter
the last value,
the value of index 2. But it turns
out that the user enters a 0,
which corresponds to the convention
to restart from the beginning.
Which means that at this point,
we want the array to be empty again.
So as the array is emptied again,
the next value
that we'll ask from the user will
be the value of index 0 again.
Here the user enters a 7, we'll
therefore have this array.
He then enters a 2, we get
this array.
He then enters, for the last
value again,
a negative value, which
corresponds for us
to the second convention, the one
that says to remove the last element.
The last entered element is the 2,
so we want the array to now
look like this,
and that's why, at the next step,
we'll ask the user to enter the
second value again,
as the array now contains only
one value.
At that moment the user enters a 4,
that we'll store in the array,
he then enters a 12 as last
value,
and we'll end up with this array.
As we indeed have the three
desired values,
we constructed our array as we
intended to,
and we'll finally end up with an
array that contains 7, 4 and 12,
which are all strictly positive
values.
Here we see that during the entire
program's execution,
our array's size increases and decreases
following our needs.
So that's typically a case
where the use of an ArrayList
is particularly adapted.
Now let's see how all this
looks like
in the form of a Java program.
The computations showed
in the previous example
can be implemented with
a small Java program that
looks like this.
We begin by declaring an ArrayList of integers.
As we can't create an ArrayList
of "int" type,
of any elementary type, we use the
"Integer" type.
Our ArrayList is named "vect"
and is initialized as an empty
ArrayList.
So ultimately the "vect" variable
will contain
the reference to an empty ArrayList of integers.
We then ask the user
how many values he wants
to enter in the array.
We input the size that the user
wants for the array
with a keyboard interaction.
We then ask the user
to input the different values
to fill the array.
To achieve that, we use a loop,
as he is potentially going to
enter many values.
The loop is such that
while the actual array size hasn't
reached the desired size,
we continue to loop.
During each loop
iteration,
we ask the user to input one of
the values in the array.
But what value precisely?
Here we want to indicate to the user
the index of the value to input.
Let's suppose that the array's
filling state is the following:
so at this moment
vect.size() has the value 2
and the last element
has index 1,
which is vect.size() - 1.
That means that the next value of the
array that we want to input
does indeed have "vect.size()"
as index,
and that's what we can see here.
We'll ask the user to input
the value
that's at the position vect.size(), that
will occupy the position vect.size().
The value to put in the array
is again input
with a keyboard interaction.
And that's when we begin testing
the different cases
to adhere to the different
conventions presented
in the previous example.
One of the conventions that we wanted
to implement
is that if the value introduced by the
user is negative,
that would mean that we want
to remove
the last element introduced in
the array.
So concretely, we'll use the
"remove" method
to do this suppression.
And at that moment we'll remove
the last element of the array,
the element of index vect.size() - 1,
as we saw here.
However, we have to take a
precaution.
We can process with this
suppression
only if the ArrayList
isn't empty.
Therefore, we must combine this
first test
with a second test
that will test if the ArrayList,
is empty or not. So we'll proceed
with the suppression
only if the value is negative and if
the array isn't empty.
Whether it is empty or not is tested
with the isEmpty function.
The fact it isn't empty is expressed
with this negation.
If the condition expressed here
isn't verified,
we must then proceed with
other tests.
We saw that we wanted to have the
convention
that if the user enters the
value '0',
that means that we want to
empty the array.
We therefore proceed with an
alternative test here.
To completely empty an ArrayList,
you use the "clear" function.
So here, simply,
if the value entered by the
user is null,
then we completely empty
the array.
Otherwise, if we reach this
stage of the execution,
that means that either the
entered value
is strictly positive, or the
vector is null.
It therefore isn't strictly
guaranteed
that the entered value
is positive.
You must therefore test it again;
that's what we do here.
If this is the case, if the condition
is verified,
we can then add the value to
our ArrayList
and that is done with the
"add" function.
So, we are going to iterate over
these computations
while the ArrayList
hasn't reached the size
wanted by the user.
Note an important thing.
We constructed our array, we
declared it
by using the advanced type
'Integer'.
This means that in our array,
we don't directly have
integer values
like this,
or like I have shown
very schematically
in the example.
But to be exact, we have
references to integers
in the array.
So here the situation would
be as follows:
at the position '0' we would
have a reference
to a memory address that contains
'12', and not directly the value '12'.
In this case, how did we
enter
a value of 'int' type in the array
like we have done here?
Indeed, as our array has been
declared
as containing 'Integer',
we expect to be able to add
to this array
only values of the same type,
and therefore not directly an integer,
but a reference to an integer,
which we don't know how to construct
or initialize for the moment.
However, we were able to directly
enter an 'int'.
This is allowed thanks to the
automatic conversion
that is done between the
basic types
and the corresponding advanced
types.
So in reality, when we execute
this instruction line,
what we put in the array isn't
directly the value "val"
entered by the user, which is
of 'int' type,
but we put in the array
an "Integer", which is a reference to
the value "val".
All this is done in a completely
automatic and transparent way.
We didn't have to worry about
conversions.
So thanks to this automatic
conversion,
it becomes completely natural to
also work
with ArrayLists of integers, of
doubles, or of a basic type.
The only precaution that we
must take
is to declare the array
with the corresponding advanced
type.
This automatic conversion between
a basic type
and a corresponding advanced
type
is what we call "autoboxing",
in technical terms.
We saw that an ArrayList
can only contain
elements of advanced types.
To conclude, let's examine the incidence
that this has on the comparison
of the elements of such an array.
At the first instruction line,
I'll have the automatic conversion
of a value of basic type
to a value of 'Integer' type.
But I am in reality adding to my
ArrayList isn't
directly the value 2000,
but a reference to this value.
So I end up with a memory
situation
that is the following.
Here the value 2000 was not directly stored
in our ArrayList,
but its address.
So when I execute the second
instruction line,
it's exactly the same
situation
that happens,
except that at that moment
I have 2 references.
It turns out that these references
have a similar content,
but they were created by two
distinct "add".
And at that moment, they are two
different, distinct, memory addresses.
So here, if I want to compare the content
of the first entry of the array
with the second, with something
like this,
the result of this instruction
line's execution
will in reality be false.
Why? Because I indeed have
2 distinct memory addresses,
and it isn't the same memory
location,
and the comparison will return
false.
If we are more interested in
comparing the contents,
then, as we did with the Strings,
we mustn't resort to
an equality test with '==',
but rather to an equality test
with 'equals'.
So we access the first element
of the array, which is an 'Integer',
and we apply the 'equals' method on
this element to compare
it with the second element
of the array.
And here, the result of this instruction
line's execution
will indeed be 'true' because the
values are identical.
The values to which the references
point are identical.