Welcome back to this section
on system templates and design.
In the last section, we mostly discussed
waterless pit-based systems,
whereas in this section, we'll focus
on systems that are mostly water-based
but still contained at the household
or decentralized level.
This system is called
the Pour Flush Pit System
without Sludge Production.
The name is a bit long,
but it also describes very clearly
what happens in the system.
First, it is a system
based on a pour flush toilet.
Unlike previous systems,
there is not a choice
when it comes to the user interface.
This is because the pour flush toilet
is water based,
but it doesn't require too much water.
Too much water would flood the twin pits.
You can see here that there is only one
technology option
for the collection and storage.
To prevent too much water in the pits,
the gray water is diverted,
although small quantities could be added.
Because only one pit is used at a time,
the black water in the pit
degrades over time into a thick,
relatively stable hummus-like material.
Unlike sludge
which accumulates in single pits,
the materials from the twin pits
cannot be pumped
and must therefore be removed by hand,
probably with a shovel.
Again, there is only one option
shown here for the conveyance technology.
The material underwent
treatment in the pit,
so there is no need for further treatment
and therefore no technology choice
for the treatment option.
The material can be used or disposed of
depending on local needs.
The biogas system is designed
with the goal of producing biogas
for use in cooking or lighting.
This, like the previous system,
would be chosen
if there was a specific need
for the use of the end products,
but care must be taken to ensure
that the right technologies
are selected and organized before.
In this template we can see
several choices for the user interface,
either a pour flush toilet can be used
for all of the excreta and flush water,
or if there is a desire for urine
so that it could be used
in a liquid fertilizer,
then a urine diverting toilet
or urinal could be installed.
If urine is separated, it must be stored
and transported separately.
Of course, it could also
be directed towards a soak pit,
although there is really
no reason to do this
and this option
is indicated by the thin line
leading from the urine to the soak pit.
The black and brown water
that is generated
should be mixed with some sort
of organic material in the biogas reactor.
Biogas can be produced
without the addition of organics,
but if they are available,
they should be added.
The reactor will produce
a fairly constant supply of gas
which must not be allowed to build up,
or the pressure could become too high
and the tank could crack or explode.
Important to note also is the fact
that sludge is formed within the reactor.
Depending on the design of the reactor,
the sludge will either be pushed out
as the gas pressure builds,
or it must be emptied periodically
so that the reactor continues to function
and so that there is still enough space
for the gas to accumulate.
Notice again that gray water
is treated separately
in a parallel treatment train at the top.
This is to prevent the mixture
in the biogas reactor
from becoming too diluted.
If a significant quantity of organics
or animal waste is added to the reactor,
some gray water could be useful.
The last system template
from this section of water-based,
mostly decentralized systems
is called the Blackwater
Treatment System with Infiltration.
As the name implies, a key feature here
is the infiltration that happens.
A water-based user interface
generates black water,
which is collected
in an on-site storage technology
like the septic tank shown here,
that produces both effluent and sludge.
Sludge, as we have seen,
requires a number of sequential
and sometimes parallel technologies
to transport, treat, and use it.
The effluent, though, in this case,
will simply be infiltrated into the soil
using a soak pit or a leech field,
both of which require
appropriate ground water
and soil conditions,
not to mention sufficient space.
This system would not be appropriate
for a very dense urban area like this one,
but would be suitable for a rural
or peri-urban application,
where the distance between houses
would not make it possible to connect them
with any kind of sewer,
but where sufficient quantities
of water would be available
to ensure that the septic tank
or ABR would function properly.
In summary then, water-based systems
can be contained at the household level
and do not all require
water-based transport.
Infiltration is the key mechanism
that removes the need
for off-site transport.
For this reason, however,
greywater must be carefully managed
so that it does not
overload the technologies.
And, end use of some products
is still possible
with the use of water-based technologies,
but as before, requires careful planning.
In the next module I will present
the final section on system templates.