This week closes our overview
of sanitation systems,
and the many different
sanitation technologies.
Next week, we go to the field
and explore some of the case studies
of urban sanitation planning
and implementation,
and some of the lessons learned
at both neighborhood and citywide level.
In this week, we've looked at
different sanitation systems
from the very simple to more complex ones,
like the one shown here,
System 8: Blackwater Transport to
(Semi-) Centralized Treatment System.
We've introduced the different
functional groups
like the user interface,
the collection and storage treatment,
and we've also introduced
the input and output products
that come out of these
treatment technologies.
Furthermore, we've taken
a closer look at
some of the centralized and
(semi-) centralized treatment processes,
and dealt with issues like the
anaerobic baffled reactor (ABR),
or technologies like the anerobic filter,
the aerated pond,
or constructed wetland.
We've also looked at how the safely
treated output products
can be used for reuse and disposal.
We've look at applications like
the application of urine,
the application of dehydrated feces
for compost or irrigation.
We've presented some off-site
decentralized treatment systems
like the pre-fab modular decentralized
wastewater treament plant shown here,
developed by BORDA,
or off-site centralized
treatment plants like this one,
the waste stabilization ponds
of Cuenca, in Ecuador.
Up next is our first on-line quiz.
Please take part to see and evaluate
what you have learned so far.
The hard deadline is
November 9th.
And please also send us
your questions to the Forum.
We'll be collecting these
and answering them
during a Q&A studio session
in the last week of this course.
Looking forward to hearing from you.