Hello and welcome to the
second module about treatment
In the last module,
we looked at the different
treatment stages
as well as pretreatment technologies.
We are now moving further along
the treatment process
and having a look at
primary treatment technologies
as well as anaerobic
technologies as a whole.
We saw already what primary treatment is.
Primary treatment is the separation
of the settleable solids
from the liquid part.
You learned about anaerobic processes
in module 2.7, presented by Lucas Ulrich.
Anaerobic means processes that happen
without the presence of oxygen.
Anaerobic means literally, no air.
Anaerobic bacteria live
in the absence of oxygen
and transform the organic matter
into carbon dioxide or C02,
and methane or stage four,
also called biogas.
Anaerobic processes are used both
in primary and secondary
treatment technologies.
They are very efficient,
especially in warm climates.
Sometimes smelly, but exciting isn't it?
Let's start with the
primary treatment technologies.
Don't forget that for each
technology that we present,
you will find more information here,
in the compendium.
For example, the settler.
The settler is the classical,
primary treatment technology.
It is designed to remove suspended solids
by sedimentation.
The low flow velocity in the settler
allows sediment particles
to sink to the bottom,
while the lighter constituents
will float to the surface,
forming the scum.
The outlet is placed between these two layers
in order to collect the settled effluence.
A settler may also be called
a sedimentation or septic tank
or in conventional treatment plants,
a clarifier.
Settlers can achieve an initial reduction
of up to 50% to 70% of suspended solids,
and up to 20% to 40% of organic material.
Settlers can be independent units,
or merged into other technologies.
Like in the septic tank that you saw before,
and others that we will see later.
The performance of settlers can be enhanced
by including inclined plates
called lamella or tubes
or with the use chemical coagulents.
Let's now have a look at the Imhoff tank.
The Imhoff tank is a primary
treatment technology
that combines solid liquid separation
and digestion of the septic sludge.
Because there is sludge digestion,
there is production of biogas.
whose bubbles may disturb
the settling process.
For this reason the flow tank,
or settling compartment,
is designed with a "V" shape.
which prevents gas bubbles to come up
and fold them to the sides,
as well as the scum.
Depending on the design and conditions,
the Imhoff tank may have the advantage
to lead to good sludge stabilization.
which is not the case
with the standard settler.
So to sum up,
the advantage of the Imhoff tank
over a standard settler
is the production of a more
stabilized sludge, easier to treat.
The sludge removal frequency
is also much lower.
On the other hand,
it is a more complicated system to build,
it is quite a high or deep infrastructure,
and consequently, also more expensive.
That's it so far for the purely
primary treatment technologies.
Let's look now at anaerobic technologies
which also fulfill secondary treatment functions.
[inaudible] the ABR or anaerobic baffled reactor
and the anaerobic filter.
You may already have heard about
them in the module 2.7
as they can also function as a collection,
storage and treatment system
at building or neighborhood level.
Now we will consider them
as proper treatment units.
Same thing for the biogas reactor.
It was presented in Module 2.7 by Lucas Ulrich.
Please refer to that module
to learn more about it.
Let's talk about ABRs.
An ABR is a kind of improved septic tank,
with a series of baffles and a ridge
where the wastewater is forced to flow
The baffles can be replaced by tubes
as shown here
which is a hydraulic design improvement.
The settler can be integrated
to the ABR, or separate.
The wastewater is forced
to flow through the sludge
which is a thriving, active biomass.
The anaerobic bacteria
present in the sludge,
degrades part of the suspended matter
present in the wastewaster
passing through it.
Usually the ABR counts between
three and six upflow chambers.
Upflow, because the water
flows in the bottom
to the top of each compartment.
The technical advantage is to
allow for contrary release of the gases.
In an ABR, the hydraulic retention time
is between 48 and 72 hours.
ABRs can be very efficient
to remove organic matter
with a reduction up to 90%.
The ABR presents many positive aspects
for low- and middle-income areas.
It has low operation and maintenance costs,
no electrical energy is required,
and it is resistant to organic
and hydraulic shock loads.
As for the sludge.
the retention time is long,
from six months to several years.
It is then well stabilized
and easier to treat further.
And sludging is not required frequently.
An ABR is quite compact
as shown here in Egypt.
What is more, it can be built underground,
which gives flexibility
for their implementation.
They can even be implemented
under a garden or parking space.
However, if the ABR looks simple,
one should not forget that,
as all the treatment
systems presented here,
it relies on biological processes.
It is like a living organism.
The start up period is crucial
to reach an optimal performance
and requires expert follow up
at least for the first six months.
The ABR is particularly appropriate
for small-scale or sometimes called
decentralized wastewater treatment plants.
It is important to mention here
two opportunities linked
with such systems,
modularity and prefabrication.
Modularity, such as
represented in this figure
from the German organization BORDA,
provides much more flexibility
and a low symmetrical plant,
much closer to the needs,
with the possibility to add
further modules as the population grows.
The prefabrication of treatment units
allows for a much better quality control,
a material which stands better
in anaerobic wastewater.
It also dramatically reduces
the construction time.
Such units can be locally manufactured,
such as here in Indonesia.
Let's close this [inaudible]
and go back to our technologies.
Usually the effluence from an ABR
needs further treatment.
To improve its effluent quality,
a few compartments packed
with [inaudible} can be added.
These are known as an anaerobic filter.
Anaerobic filters can also be built
immediately after the settler,
as shown in this figure.
It works on exactly on
the same principle as the ABR
with the addition of filter media
like gravel, crushed rocks, cinder,
pumice or plastic chips.
Typical filter material sizes range from
12 mm to 55 mm in diameter.
The ideal filter should have a large
surface area for the bacteria to grow,
with pores large enough
to prevent clogging.
As in th ABR,
the water flows from the bottom
to the top of the compartment
and the vent is installed on the top.
The water level should cover at least
0.3 meters to guarantee an even flow.
The filter is supported by a grid
so not as to clog the bottom
of the compartment.
The hydraulic retention time
is the most important design parameter
influencing the filter performance.
The hydraulic retention time of
12 to 36 hours is recommended.
Clogging is a main stress
in an anaerobic filter.
When the efficiency decreases
the filter must be cleaned.
This is done by running the system
in the reverse mode,
or if you prefer, backwashing.
Or by removing and cleaning
the filter material.
This being difficult,
it is better to avoid clogging
as much as possible.
The picture here shows
four parallel ABRs and anaerobic filters
at a construction in India,
for a design capacity of 150 cubic meters,
which is equivalent to
about 1,500 inhabitants.
Let's now have a look at a more
sophisticated anaerobic technology,
the upflow anaerobic sludge blanket reactor
or UASB.
The UASB is a single tank process.
Wastewater enters the reactor
from the bottom,
and flows upwards.
A suspended sludge blanket
filters and treats the wastewater
in its early flow through it.
The sludge blanket is comprised of
small agglomerations of microorganisms
with a diameter of about 1 mm to 3 mm,
which because of their weight,
risk being washed out in the upflow.
Basically, the crucial point here is
to maintain its equilibrium
so that the sludge blanket does not settle
but is not washed out either.
That's what makes it a sensitive system.
An upflow velocity of 0.7 to 1 meter
per hour must be maintained.
During the digestion process
biogas is produced and goes up.
Critical elements for [inaudible] reactor
are the inflow and distribution system,
the gas solid separator,
and the effluent [inaudible] design
The UASB allows a high reduction of BOD,
can withstand high organic loads,
at least to allow low sludge production.
It requests high-strength wastewater,
and so it is often used for
industrial wastewater.
However, for it to run properly,
it needs skilled operators,
and a constant wastewater
supply and electricity.
Developing the granular sludge
may take several months.
So expert follow up during
the start up period is very important.
To sum up, we consider anaerobic systems
are among the most efficient and compact.
They work at best in warmer climates
so are particularly appropriate
for tropical areas.
What is more,
anaerobic baffled reactors and filters
require very little operation
and maintenance.
However, if they are very performant
at removing organic matter,
they remove little pathogen and nutrients.
Thus, the effluence and the sludge
need further treatment.
In the next module we will review the
different aerobic treatment technologies.
See you then.