Hello and welcome to this last module
on treatment technologies.
After reviewing the technologies
treating waste
water and effluent,
we will now tackle
a very important
but often neglected
topic: sludge.
Sludge in all its forms
and all its names.
Faecal sludge, septage,
secondary sludge.
One product: sludge.
Sludge is a very
variable product.
It can be fresh, old,
stabilized, unstabilized,
thick, diluted, yellow, black.
What is sure is that it is
much more concentrated
than wastewater.
Let's consider for example
faecal sludge, meaning
the sludge coming from on-site
sanitation technologies
such as pits or septic tanks.
The factors which influence
the characteristics
of faecal sludge are the
tank emptying technology
and the patterns of emptying,
the performance of septic tanks,
the intrusion of groundwater, temperature,
admixtures to faecal sludge ,
like grease, kitchen, or solid waste,
and of course, the storage duration,
which can last from months to years.
These characteristics have
practical implications for treatment.
For example, sludge
which is still rich
in organic matter
and has not undergone
significant degradation
is difficult to de-water.
Conversely, sludge
that has undergone
significant anaerobic degradation
such as from septic tanks
or ABRs - in other words,
which is stabilized,
is more easily dewatered.
All these factors influence
faecal sludge characteristics.
Faecal sludge is a very
variable material.
Consequently, management
systems need to be designed
on a case-by-case basis.
The four main functions
of sludge treatment are:
the solid-liquid separation,
stabilisation,
dewatering or drying,
and pathogen reduction.
It is important to define
the end use or disposal option
and select the appropriate
treatment level accordingly.
Sludge will not be treated
the same if it is to be used
for agriculture or in
a cement factory.
Potential beneficial end uses
are dry side as a fertilizer,
dry side as a fuel,
or biogas.
For example,
the different treatment technologies,
can be categorized according to the four
functions which I just mentioned:
solid-liquid separation,
stabilization,
dewatering or drying,
and pathogen reduction.
The technologies in dark yellow
are those which are commonly applied
for faecal sludge treatment
in low- and middle-income countries,
and which are presented
throughout this course,
some which already in Module 3.2.
The technologies in pale yellow,
on the other hand,
are mainly applied in Western countries
such as the filtre press,
or under investigation
in low- income countries,
such as the sludge pelletiser.
Please note that some technologies
may fulfill two functions,
such as the Imhoff tank or
the planted drying beds.
Let's start with the
sedimentation thickness ponds
whose function is
solid-liquid separation.
Such ponds allow
the sludge to thicken.
As the sludge settles
and digests,
the supernatant must be decanted
and treated separately.
The thickened sludge can then
be dried or further composted.
Two tanks operated in parallel
are required so that one
can be operated while
the other is emptied.
To achieve maximum efficiency,
loading and resting periods
should not exceed
four to five weeks.
The main drawback
is that the thickened sludge
needs to be removed
by a front-end loader.
This technology is relatively low-cost
but requires a large land area,
if possible, far from habitations,
as it generates odors and flies.
Let's now move to the most common
sludge treatment technology:
the unplanted drying bed.
The bottom of a drying bed
is lined with perforated pipes
to drain the leachate away.
On top of the pipes are layers of gravel
and sand to support the sludge.
The bottom layer should be coarse gravel,
and the top one, fine sand.
Thus, the liquid part of the sludge
can both infiltrate and evaporate.
The sludge, however,
is not effectively stabilized
and its pathogen content is still high.
According to the end use,
for example, as a fertilizer,
it must be further
stored or treated.
Dried sludge can be removed
after ten to fifteen days,
according to the climate conditions.
After the unplanted drying beds,
let's move to the planted drying beds,
which is much better
at pathogen reduction.
The key improvement of the planted
over the unplanted drying beds,
is that they don't need to be desludged
after each filling and drying cycle.
The plants and their root
systems maintain the porosity
of the filter, which means that
sludge can be added
layers after layers, which imply also
a much longer retention time.
Thus, this technology leads
to a much better stabilization
of the sludge, which is partly
converted into humus.
The appearance of the bed is similar
to a vertical floor constructed wetland,
as we saw in the last module.
The filtrate flows down
through the filter
and is collected through
a drainage system.
Ventilation pipes connected
to the drainage system
contribute to aerobic
conditions in the filter.
When constructing the bed,
a free space of about 1 metre
should be left above the top
of the sand layer to account
for about three to five years
sludge accumulation.
Sludge should be applied
in layers between 75
and 100 millimetres thick
and re-applied three to seven days.
Obviously, plants are crucial
in planted drainbeds.
The start out and acclimation
phases are very important,
and requires much care.
Finally, let's have a look
at co-composting.
Co-composting is like compost,
but using mold and [inaudible].
In this case, sludge is added
to organic solid waste.
Composting is the aerobic
degradation of organics.
It can be done in two ways,
either open or in vessel.
In open composting, such as shown
in this figure, the mix material
is piled into long
heaps or windrows
and left to decompose.
The piles are periodically turned
to provide oxygen and
ensure a homogenous treatment.
For de-watered sludge,
a ratio of 1:2 to 1:3 of sludge
to solid waste should be used.
Composts are simple,
but the mixture must
be carefully designed
so that it has the proper
carbon-nitrogen ratio,
moisture, and oxygen content.
Co-composting is quite labor
intensive, so it only makes sense
if there is a demand
for the product
from customers that
are willing to pay.
To sum up, we saw that sludge
is a highly concentrated
and variable material.
Before constructing a faecal sludge
treatment plant, it is necessary
to make a good assessment
of the initial situation in the city
and estimate the characteristics
and quantities of the sludge to treat.
This can strongly influence
the choice of technologies.
For example, first sludge
from public toilets,
needs to be digested
and stabilized
with the possibility
to produce biogas.
On the other hand,
sludge from septic tanks
is already digested
and usually ready
for de-watering or drying.
Faecal sludge management
requires an integrated
planning approach.
It is more complex than
conventional systems
where a sewer network
brings the wastewater
to the treatment plant.
In faecal sludge management,
there are many more stakeholders
to bring on board, starting with
the manual and mechanical
service providers as
discussed in module 2.8.
For faecal sludge
to reach treatment plants,
there are often new management
and financial schemes to be put in place,
agreements to be reached,
and sometimes even new policies to draft.
Think about it.
To learn more about the different
sludge treatment technologies,
and about faecal sludge
management planning,
we recommend you to refer
to Eawag Sandec FSM book,
which you can download
for free at the link below.
Finally, do not forget that
the sanitation system
does not end
at the treatment plant.
A treatment plant also generates
products which need to be
disposed of, or in the
best case, re-used.
How to dispose and how to use:
that's what you will discover
in the next series of modules
with Lukas Ulrich.
Enjoy.