Hello and welcome to this module
on building sanitation systems.
In this module, we are going to combine
everything that was covered
in the previous modules,
the products, the functional groups,
and the technologies,
into complete systems.
The goals of this module are to first,
introduce what a santitation template is,
second, to understand how to
work with the sanitation template
by following the flow paths
of each product
and then selecting each technology
for each functional group,
and finally, to be able to build
a complete, logical sanitation system.
This is an example of what we call
our system template.
We will discuss each of the parts
in detail as we progress,
but for now, let's focus on the products.
The products, as you will remember,
are the materials that flow through
and are generated
within the sanitation system.
We read the system template
from left to right.
On the left, you can see a list of the
products in the first column:
input products.
You can identify the products
by the rounded side and the color,
as well as the name, of course.
You can see that there are lines
connecting the products
to the rest of the elements
in the diagram.
These lines indicate the flow path
of the particular products
so it shows you what technology
the product will pass through.
You can see also that there are
two thicknesses of lines.
The thicker black lines are those which
are most commonly followed
and should be considered as
the most important.
The thinner lines are those that are
somewhat less important or optional.
For example,
the main products are
feces, urine and flushwater.
These are all connected together
with a thick black line that flows
into the first red box.
We'll talk about these boxes later,
but for the moment,
look at the bottom of the products,
and look at the anal cleansing water
and the dry cleansing material.
These two products both have
thin lines attached to them
because realistically,
they're not the most important
thing to consider.
Also, you'll notice that the thin line
goes in two directions.
up and across here.
That means that the products can go
either to this first technology box
over here,
or be mixed in with the products above.
The choice would basically depend
on the local context and conditions.
It's worth stressing here
that although we use system templates
to help us guide
the decision making process,
they cannot solve all of your problems.
There's still a fair amount
of context specific information
and engineering,
that's needed to build a proper system.
What we can also see are the
products that are within the system,
blackwater for example.
Fecal sludge is another example
of a product
that did not go into the system.
Notice it was nowhere here on the left.
Fecal sludge, like all the other products
that you can see within the system,
emerged from different technologies.
Some of the products will emerge
in the same form as they entered
and some of them will be transformed,
like how urine, and feces, and flushwater
were transformed into
fecal sludge and effluents.
Now we are going to focus
on the functional groups.
The titles of each functional group
are listed across the top
and are color coded
in the way they were before.
Within each functional group column
there are technology boxes.
Each technology box,
under each functional group heading,
lists the possible technology choices
for that functional group,
for that product.
In essence, it is like a matrix.
The products are listed on the left
and are flowing from left to right.
The functional groups are the columns,
and where the functional groups
intersect with the product paths,
for example here,
the technology options
are listed in the technology boxes.
You will notice that there is not
a technology box
for every functional group.
Not every product requires a technology
from every functional group.
Gray water, for example,
does not enter the system
through the user interface.
Remember it comes in
from another water source
in the house, but not the toilet.
Therefore, the gray water
bypasses the user interface
and enters the sanitation system
directly at the point
of collection and storage.
In this case it could be a septic tank,
an AVR, or an anaerobic filter.
Your job therefore, as the engineer,
is to follow each product
along its flow path
until it intersects with a
relevant functional group
and then choose the most appropriate
technology from the options listed.
The choice will depend entirely
on the local context and conditions.
Let's actually do that now
and select the technologies
that we will need to form
a complete sanitation system
using this template as an example.
Normally, we would know
much more about the population,
but in this case we are going
to have to make some assumptions.
Let's assume that the population
is made up of wipers,
and that they throw paper in the toilet,
so we don't need
a separate technology for it.
Our gray cleansing material
will follow this light line
and mix it in with our urine,
feces and flushwater.
The urine, feces and flushwater,
along with the toilet paper,
will all flow into the user interface,
and here we have two options.
We can either choose a pour flush toilet
or a cistern flush toilet.
Let's, for the case of this example,
choose a pour flush toilet.
Here it is, we've marked it down
so that we can build our system
and continue from here.
Once all the products
go into our pour flush toilet,
they are mixed together
and referred to as blackwater.
The blackwater
needs to be collected and stored.
So here, it flows into the collection
and storage functional group
and again we see
we have three choices,
a septic tank, an AVR,
or an anaerobic filter.
Let's say that we were designing
for a small group of houses
and there's a little bit of space,
so we want to install something
that 's a little bit robust
that can handle the variation
of the blackwater inflow
and we decide
on an anaerobic baffled reactor.
Here it is, we've selected it
for this technology interface.
The AVR creates two different products,
the effluent and the sludge
which settles to the bottom.
The effluent, which is created constantly,
needs to continually leave the system.
In our example, let's say
we have a bit of space
so we can pipe our effluent
into a soak pit shown here.
The effluent will infiltrate through,
and because we have some space,
will be absorbed by the soil
without any real impact
on the surrounding area.
So we've taken care of the effluent,
we've followed it through.
Now we need to deal with the sludge.
The sludge that accumulates into the AVR
will need to be emptied periodically.
So let's assume
that we are working in an area
that has emptying businesses
that own and operate pump trucks
to suck out and transport
the accumulated sludge.
Here's our truck,
it's come along and it is emptying
this layer of sludge from our AVR.
The truck will now need to transport it.
We're lucky in this case,
because there is a functioning
treatment plant dedicated for the sludge.
It happens to be based
on a planted drying bed.
Here we can see the planted drying bed
with the truck emptying the sludge
into the grit chamber.
The sludge will be layered
on top of the filter.
The effluent will filter
through the porous layers beneath
and will come out on this side.
The sludge, as it accumulates,
will dry and be turned
into a dry sludge product.
This dry sludge that comes off
will need to be taken care of in some way.
So what we're actually going to do
is just give it away
to some of the local farmers
so that they can use it
as a soil ammender
and help to improve the porosity
and water storing properties of the soil.
Remember however,
the planted drying bed
produces two products,
the dried sludge
which we've given away,
but also the effluent
which comes out here,
and which needs further treatment.
What we're going to do
is dump it into one of the small,
local waste stabilization ponds
that happens to be nearby.
Quite lucky for us, but also,
a very useful technology.
So the effluent from the planted
drying bed that we have here
will flow into our waste
stabilization plant.
Now as a final step,
we need to get rid
of all this effluent somehow,
so what we're going to do
is we're going to actually put fish
into a final finishing pond
and dilute that effluent
so that we can grow fish
and hopefully generate
some revenue in the process.
Of course, we could have chosen
different technologies
at each step for every product
so this is just one of many
possible combinations.
But still you can see
how we linked
all of the technologies
for each of the products
all the way through to the very end.
Furthermore, this is just one template.
The choices we have were limited
because of the type of input products
and the logical sequence of technologies
that were specific to this template.
In summary, the system template
is like a matrix of products
and functional groups.
Technologies are selected
by following flow paths
that guide each product
through the necessary functional groups.
There are a variety of technologies
that can be chosen
so the ultimate decision
is based on the context,
the designer,
and the end use objectives.
In the next section we will discuss
the nine different templates
that include nearly every possible
technology combination.