Hello, and welcome to this module
on waterless pit based systems.
In this module we're gonna discuss
three different system templates
that are similar because they're all
based on pit technologies
that are mostly waterless.
The first system is called
the Single Pit System.
Unsurprisingly,
it's based on a single pit.
So moving from left to right
and starting with the products,
we note that the two main products
are urine and feces,
as they have the thick lines
attached to them.
The other products are optional,
or not necessary depending on the system,
but we'll have to consider those
as we move forward.
The first question we're presented with
is whether to choose
a dry waterless toilet
or a pour flush toilet.
The choice will depend on whether or not
there is water available,
but also whether or not there are
the resources and capacities
to build up the necessary infrastructure
that comes later.
It's important to note that although
we build up the system from left to right,
it is often necessary
to revise your choices,
and so, the process
can become quite iterative.
The key element of this system
is the single pit.
Either a basic pit or a VIP,
Ventilated Improved Pit design.
In both cases sludge will be produced,
so the quality of this sludge will vary,
of course, depending
on the user interface chosen,
the amount of water used, the lining
of the pit, and the soil conditions.
You can see on the diagram
that the sludge,
once it arrives for treatment,
will be split into two fractions:
the treated sludge, and the effluent.
Looking at this system template
is both interesting and important
because the first half,
the dryer toilet, plus a single pit,
is very, very common
in most parts of the world;
however, as we have discussed before,
the second half of this system,
the transport, treatment
and uses of the products
becomes quite complicated,
involves a lot of technical components,
and potentially very difficult decisions.
The lesson here is to never assume
that a single pit system
is a simple system.
System two: Waterless Pit System
Without Sludge Production.
seems from the name
that it might be quite simple,
but in fact, it is complicated
by the variety of products.
This system is based
on the idea of alternating pits,
so either a double VIP or a fosa alterna.
You can see that organics,
shown here on the left,
is an optional product,
but it's not optional
if a composting chamber is chosen
for the collection and storage technology.
If the double VIP
or the fosa alterna is chosen,
no additional organics are needed.
The quality of the product that emerges
will, of course, be different
so the type of [inaudible]
you will have will influence
the collection and storage
technology that you choose
and of course,
the availability of the organics
as well as the willingness to add them
and the need to use the final product.
This application goal will essentially
determine your choices.
This is the template for the classic
urine diversion system.
It is interesting to look at this template
because it's not very straightforward.
There are multiple flow paths
to take into account,
and parallel technologies
that need to be designed.
Bear this in mind when you hear
that Ecosan or waterless sanitation
technologies are called simple.
The individual technologies may be,
but this system certainly is not.
In fact, we can see from this template
that although the actual toilet,
the urine-diverting toilet may be simple,
there are numerous parts
and products to consider.
Also, because the system is waterless,
the gray water
must be considered separately.
Whereas in other systems it could be
simply mixed in with the gray water,
here it remains entirely separate
through the duration of the process.
This system is not necessarily
complicated to build,
but it certainly requires
careful planning,
especially in terms of how
to use the final products,
so the stored urine and the dried feces,
and determine how they can be
either applied or disposed of.
Here is a photo from Durban, South Africa,
where you can see a whole community
with urine-diverting dry toilets.
Take a minute and see
if you can identify where they are.
Clearly, we have one in the front,
but there's also one here,
there's one here, there's one here,
there's one here.
In fact, you could basically
spend the whole day identifying
the hundreds of urine-diverting toilets
that dot this community.
In this particular community, the urine
is collected in storage containers
and then collected
by trucks for recycling.
The dried feces that come out
of the storage chambers here
are simply buried on site.
This is one of the technology
combinations that is possible
on the system template
that we just went through.
So in summary, waterless technologies,
or technologies like pour flush toilets
that do not require a lot of water
are not necessarily simple,
and the systems built
around waterless technologies
can in fact become very complicated.
System building is left to right,
but may require iteration,
especially when the needs and uses
of the products that remain
at the end of the system
are taken into account.
In the next module, we'll take a look
at decentralized water based systems.
I hope you'll join me then.