The week begins with Doula,
We wish to welcome the participants
from Doula.
Today the African city grows mainly
by its subdivisions.
Even though the authorities focus on
the resorption of precarious housing,
the large majority of city dwellers,
the future residents of African cities,
are going to arrive in subdivisions
these next few years.
However, the issues of subdivisions,
the quality of living conditions
which we are putting in place
in the outskirts of the city is
absolutely never discussed.
We are going to see these issues
this week,
not the main issues of the debate,
but the question of knowing how to build,
step by step, a quality subdivision.
The challenge of planning a
subdivision is not only technical
but it's about understanding a
social and environmental object
as well as understanding the networks
the geometrical aspects or even
economic profitability.
So we will lay the groundwork this week
of a reflection on how
to produce a quality subdivision,
where people live, work
and have leisure activities.
We will see for example the impact of
the layout, the drawing, the design,
on the costs, but also the correlation
that there is
between the level of service
and cost of the plot.
We will show some standards,
by paying attention to explain
and to say that the standards change with
time and places.
The construction norms in 1950 in Dakar
weren't the same
as in Raahein as in Abidjan, and Abidjan
in 1960 certainly didn't have
the same norms as today,
I'm intentionally mentioning
Abidjan as an element of demonstration
because it' a a textbook case for urban
planning and construction standards.
President Bouani had high-tech building
in his political program.
If standards change,
building techniques as well.
Let's imagine the telephone, for example,
first of all, without telephones
in certain subdivisons,
in the subdivisions
no doubt the richest and oldest,
we have begun to put a telephone network,
installing electricity wires
so as to eventually not at all,
with the advent of mobile phones,
have need of
these wired telephones and
we are little by little
not even imagine that we could
put telephones in the subdivisions.
Finally, whether the subdivision
be public or private, the two exist,
it's necessary to carry out all of
the reflections
that we are going to carry out now.
We will talk about the issue of needs.
For whom, for how many people
are we going to make a subdivision?
We will talk about the issue of potentialities,
what are the potentialities of the site?
We will look at the issue of program,
each subdivision has a program
that must be defined beforehand,
and then we will the issue
of the layout or of
the indicative planning.
So this week we will have, after this video,
this short introductory video,
a first video on the issues of
defining the subdivision,
the block, the plot,
then on the basic principles,
principles that must generate spatiality
of the subdivision, a second video on how
to make the networks profitable,
how to make a subdivision profitable,
then we will see a step by step video,
meaning that step after step,
stage after stage, we are going to see
how to build a subdivision,
and finally we will have some examples
taken from here and there in African cities
to see the differences that we can have
between Khiali, Dakar or Ouanda.
There you have it,
this week's program.
You decide!