Hello.
In this video, we are going to talk
about two things.
First, the basic vocabulary.
What is a plot?
What is an islet?
What is a housing development?
And so on.
The second thing we are going
to talk about, is
the big principles that generate the drawing
of the housing development,
and that allow most of
the time to make profitable
the housing development's networks.
So we are going to talk,
point by point, about what is
a plot, what is an islet, and what is
a housing development.
So the base unit of the housing
development is the plot.
In this context, a plot is a legal
or physical delimitation of a land.
This delimitation includes the notion of
property or appropriation for use.
Or both of them.
The collectivity governs
the delimitation and/or the use.
So the definition of the plot can
change depending on the time and the place.
A set of plots is an islet.
And a set of islets is a piecemeal.
Therefore, the housing development is an
operation in order to create a piecemeal.
The housing development can
therefore be defined as an operation
of housing development and the result
of that same operation.
On the other hand, we have the reparcelling
which is the contrary of a
housing development, as it is about
gathering several plots in one.
So for instance, to resume our
definition of the housing development,
the housing development is an
volunteer operation, as we can see
on the picture, of creation
of a piecemeal fabric.
So we see three types, one here,
a second one
there and a third type of piecemeal
on the bottom of the picture.
It consists of dividing a land into
several plots, doomed to
construction in theory.
By extension, the piecemeal and the housing
development totally confuse themselves.
The picture is interesting here, because
it shows us diverse types of standing.
I resume my three types of
housing development with a pretty high
standing, a medium one here
and the lowest standing,
that only consists in making
a certain amount of plots viable,
in putting electricity poles and then in
clearing the land and that's it.
The first principle, for the housing
development, is the principle of reinforcement.
The idea behing that, is to not think about
the different elements in
an autonomous way, but to articulate them
with each other.
For example, if I have a bus station here,
an other taxi station, we
would rather try to put the elements
together, so that, at the end,
my taxi station and my bus station,
and also my pedestrian movement,
for example, could be together
and react together
and articulate one another.
This is really the principle
of reinforcement.
We use the elements
to reinforce all of them.
The second principle
is the principle of continuity.
Continuity of the movements, continuity of
the built space, continuity of green spaces.
We try to create like this, corridors with
trees for the fauna and the flora,
espacially the small fauna,
or for movements,
to avoid movements to be cut up
and to allow them to floz
in the city in a fluid way.
This is the principle of continuity.
The third principle is the basic principle.
The principle of outsourcing.
What does that mean?
It means that we do not have
to find equipments specifically in the
housing development, we can imagine
a certain amount of big equipments.
Like a big hospital, that can be
outside the housing development.
So, the housing development doesn't need,
for its equipments,
to be totally autonomous, but
we can go look for a certain amount of
services outside the housing development.
Earlier we had the principle
of continuity as a basic principle,
we are now going to recommend
the exact opposite,
as it is about the principle of
discontinuity,
actually, it is about, in the fluidity,
in the continuity,
creating a certain amount
of exceptions, to avoid too much monotony
in the city and in the housing developments.
The fifth and last basic principle for
the housing development,
is the principle of concentration.
We will actually try to concentrate
the equipments, those that
require an important accessibility,
on the crossroads
more than in places hard to access.
So we will use the crossroads that have a lot
of people to specifically concentrate a
certain amount of things.
This is the principle of concentration.
An other example of
the principle of concentration.
It is the concentration of a population
all around an equipment.
The more people we are
in a 300 meter perimeter
of walking all around my equipment,
or a 500 meter,depending on
the equipments, it doesn't matter,
the more people you have in this perimeter,
the more profitable it will be
to have an equipment in the center.
On the other hand, if I enlarge my plots,
I will for sure, in the same perimeter of
300 or 500 meters, I will have less
people who will be able to use my equipment.
It is also a way to show
the principle of concentration.
Here we are, we went through
the five basic principles.
As a reminder: reinforcement,
continuity, outsourcing,
discontinuity and concentration,
In the next videos
we are going to talk about how
we can implement those big principles.