We are going to talk about two things.
First of all the issues of density
and which are the phenomena
that influence this density.
And secondly how to make
our networks profitable
when we draw up the subdivision.
The first element which influences density
is the issue of
the size of the lots or
of the right to build.
We can also increase the rights to build
and this will increase
the density and we can also change
the size of the lot.
The more the plot grows,
the more density will decrease.
The issue of public facilities.
It's necessary, the more people we have,
the more it becomes profitable to have
public facilities.
This seems very logical.
There is the issue of temporality
which clearly influences
the question of density.
We can find ourselves in less densely
populated neighborhoods
that decades later begin to densify,
becoming very densely populated
working class neighborhoods.
The issue also of public transportation
has an influence in two ways.
We need many people for transportation
to be profitable and conversely,
the more transportation I have, the more
people I can have in my neighborhoods.
And finally the question of public space.
In fact, the more dense I am,
the more I densify,
the more I have a significant number
of people, the less large lots I have,
and so the more I need
generous public spaces
which allow people to have a little
breathing room in the city.
The symbol of this public space is
Central Park where New York is
of an incredible density and finally
we have this green lung in the middle.
It's a symptomatic example.
There are many others in the cities.
This doesn't necessarily have
to be parks, these can be plazas,
these can be large boulevards,
but we need, at some point,
to have space so that the people
who live in this density are able to
enjoy themselves in the open air.
How to increase density?
We have begun to see this.
We have two solutions, either we decrease
the size of the lots and the length of the facade.
We will see in a little while
how to do this.
We might increase the building rights.
We might decrease the areas which
are not assigned to housing.
Rather than make parks and plazas,
you are making housing and this
will allow you to increase density.
We quickly see that it is not an option
and then we refer back to the question
of the increase in building rights.
Since there are rarely controls
on these building rights, we need to have
a policing of constructions
which would be vigilant to say if,
yes or no, this was done to code.
And well, we'll also realize that it's
a rare possibility and so
the only way is to decrease the size
and the length on the street
to increase the density.
Profitability of plots
or rather of networks.
The influence of the size plays
an important role on public spending.
I take my plot, let's say my four plots,
versus here six plots, right?
If I have 100 linear meters this means
that there will be a pipe here,
each one with connections.
On 100 meters, I will be able to,
in the first example with my facade
on the street of 25 meters connect
four households while here,
I would have six households
with a plot of 6.67.
And it's clear that the more
the plot decreases,
the more the distance
on the street decreases,
the more I can increase
my density, but the more
I can reduce my public spending per unit.
Profitability of networks
and transferable areas.
What is a transferable area?
So let me show a quick diagram.
Here we have a large plot with two blocks
and then we are going to quickly draw,
we have plots here,
we have some here also with a large plot
in this spot here.
So, once again, to advance quickly,
we can imagine
that this whole area here
is devoted to housing.
That's what we call transferable area.
It's to put housing and then we would have
this plot here which would be facilities
and then eventually the rest of the plots,
here would be what we call
the public domain.
So the idea is to say, here we have
transferable areas.
It has to be at 50%.
You will often find it at
a much larger proportion.
Here, public domain, we have between
20% and 25% and then the facilities,
large infrastructures also
between 20% and 25%.
So of course, if we are at 20% of roads,
we have to give 30% to facilities,
but let's say that we're at 20%-25% also
in this place here with the facilities.
We can reduce the transferable area,
we can increase it.
Many increase it to have more to sell
and of course to make better
economic transactions.
But don't forget that it's very important
to have places where
the people, the denser it is,
the more need there is for places
where people can go and meet
and that's why
the facilities area plus the public domain
should also be at 50%.
Making the networks profitable.
So we have several possibilities.
We have already partially seen how we can
increase the number of constructions
by plot, we can decrease the facade
on the street, we can decrease
the overall size of the plot or consolidate
the plots in a cul-de-sac as we will see
in a little bit with the diagrams
that we will draw in a few moments.
Let's go back to our drawings.
Making the networks profitable at
a constant size means that if we want
the size to remain the same, of the plot,
we have to decrease the street facade.
This means we have a diagram that is
roughly like this because each time
that I decrease the size of my plot,
I have to increase the depth
so if I have here 15 out of 30,
I'll have 12, sorry, 12 out of 37.5,
I will have 10 out of 45 etc., etc.,
But we must be very careful about
what is left in a proportion.
If I have a building here,
often we go to at least 12 meters.
This means 12 x 37 since the plots
that would be like this are just
unconstructible and thus uninhabitable.
If I take the constant proportion
this time.
So it's no longer necessarily
the size of the plot
but that I want to keep the proportion
so that it is a rectangle,
so I still have this type of proportion
and not the one we drew earlier.
Well, we find ourselves in a situation
where, here, we draw the plot,
the proportion is here and
I want to increase,
I'm going to increase each time here
in my plot in the proportions.
So if I go to 7.5, I will have 10,
12.5, 15 etc., etc.,
So there it is, this is
a graphical geometric trick,
to increase, in constant proportion,
the size of the plots.
The proportion of the plots.
Here also it's very important.
We have just seen it.
A plot like this would be
almost unconstructible.
So, roughly, we have plots that would be
rectangles which are, in fact, based on
a double square and we are going to find
plots that are 12 x 14 or even
plots that are 30 x 15, 9 x 18.
Why the double square?
It's that we can then,
when we draw the subdivision,
we can then easily return the plot,
since we have here 9 and 9
so we have the necessary 18.
There it is.
So if I'm dealing with the double square
I can draw my plot geometrically,
very easily and return it
in the end to the block.
Making the networks profitable also means
regrouping the plots.
So, once again, let's quickly draw
four plots, let's draw four other plots.
Here, I'm drawing my houses, which are
little individual houses in the center,
and I'm drawing a version
where the houses are regrouped.
In the first version of my drawing,
I have a conduit and each time
individual conduits.
In the second, we can imagine, like this,
to save the number,
the linear meter of conduit, which makes
it so that it's profitable,
as we go along the networks since
I'm regrouping the plots.
Yet another possibility,
which is very seldom used
but which exists is that here,
I have my main road,
here I have my plots, I'm going to draw,
each time, my four plots,
and then I can draw my buildings here,
there it is.
The idea here is to have a sort of
technical gain, like in a building,
except that it's in the subdivision, where
we have a gain that happens here.
So we maybe have here a meter available
and then we have,
each time, the networks which,
are then distributed in this manner.
So it's of course very, it's of course possible,
this diagram here is still possible
but is very seldom used and then,
unfortunately, it's finally these diagrams
that we find
most often since they're done
one after the other and
since there is no need,
like this to have to coordinate
with the neighbor,
to create, to make
the networks profitable.
So then, once we have made
the networks profitable, we must still
find the balance between
land and real estate.
As such, there are several elements that
will be taken into account,
the first element is land cost,
the second, the real estate investment.
Then we have a balance mechanism
which has to happen between the two.
There are geometry questions and
right of use which is taken into account.
And land cost determines
economic interest,
it's what we are going to see
as we continue.
So land cost is at the same time
the price of land acquisition plus
the state of this land, plus the provision,
the networks, plus, in certain cases,
not always, the facilities.
There it is.
All of this represents my land cost.
Managing the future:
how to manage the future?
In the first example here, we have
a plot which seems to us much too slack,
the public domain areas
are much too big and then
finally the plot will not be,
without a doubt, profitable.
On the other hand, if I have
an extremely dense situation,
it will no longer be possible, mid stream,
to add other new facilities.
So we will try to find a balance
between these two situations.
The other thing also, is if I have only
small plots available for the facilities,
this will not work either,
since at some point there
will be facilities,
of much larger scale, in place.
So the idea is to have both
large facilities plots as well as
small plots, both enough space here,
there it's too little and not
too much either, there.
So it's a mix of these two and
it's really important to take into account
the plot in the long term, to understand
how it's going to evolve and the needs
that it will have in the future.
So, do not go on something
too large because
finally if the plot is much too big,
there is a risk of it not filling up,
but it's important to be pragmatic,
and to give enough
available space so as to then be able
to continue to densify
the plot as it should.
Then, once we have tried to make
the networks profitable,
once we have discussed the land cost,
once we have imagined
how to draw our plot,
we still have to discuss the level of
facilities that will be put in place.
The level of equipment is the quality of
the service infrastructure we want.
I this can be very high level, high-end,
where I want water, electricity,
fiber optics,
or, on the contrary, I can have situations
where I want a provision,
the simplest possible, meaning
some standposts,
a relatively flat and directly
constructible area,
and highways which are in fact
only right-of-way openings
and that's all.
So between the high-end
and a very low-end development,
we see that the costs are very different
since the quantity of networks,
the quantity of services to put in place
is very different.
When we talk of network issues,
of levels of facilities, we are of course
talking about sanitation first.
Am I going to put in place
a collective sanitation system
or an individual sanitation system?
The drinking water supply:
what kind of supply?
By standpost or directly on the plot?
The other networks: telephone networks,
electricity networks.
Are all the parcels connected
to the electrical grid,
or do I produce only public lighting?
Finally, the facilities: markets, schools.
Am I going to put all of
the necessary facilities
on my plot or, as in the main principles
that we mentioned in another video,
is that I'm going to outsource
these facilities and consolidate them
elsewhere than in my plot?
Finally public spaces: ensuring that they
are sufficient,
ensuring they are in the right place
so that people can use them fully.
There you have it,
the profitability of networks.
Facilities issues hold no more secrets.
We have gone very quickly over
the issues of facilities
and infrastructures.
We don't have the time to look at this
in more detail and depth but this
gives us a sort of general view of
what we need to do when
we are planning a plot.
Don't forget that it is really
by the geometric tool,
the reduction of the facade
or increased building rights,
but we have seen that
there are very few cases where this works,
so it's really the geometric tool
which allows,
when you create a plot, to render
your plots more or less profitable.
Don't forget that a plot must register
in the duration and that moment zero
is not the same as at 10 years,
15 years, 20 years or 50 years.
And this duration, it's what is
most difficult
to take into account but it's what makes
the issue of the plot.
And good plots, it's when we are able to
take into account the notion of time
and the notion of duration in planning
which we are putting in place.