In this video we'll follow the creation,
step-by-step, of a development.
Many stages, the first of which
is choosing a site.
As a matter of fact, for
the same program within a city
several possible sites will,
in general, be possible
It is thus a question of evaluating them,
to choose the best site for our program.
To this end we'll have a grid of questions
which will help us, as we'll see,
to decide which site is best
for the program we are implementing.
Here is our questionnaire
and the space for its responses.
It will be easy to quickly
eliminate certain sites.
And in addition to these responses
is the question of building costs,
which we'll address at the end.
But it is possible to do
a very quick evaluation
of the different costs involved
to know what is, finally,
the most cost-effective and viable site.
Another thing is we are speaking here
of technical choices, rational choices,
from the point of view
of the city's manager.
We are not talking about
political or economic questions,
which also have their importance,
and which are often even
more important in site choice,
whether to build or not.
The first question: building
according to the SDAU.
Does the master development plan
say that the land is viable for building?
We'll imagine that the answer is yes,
otherwise we'd stop here.
A development zone:
is it zoned for residential
or zoned for industrial use?
Now, let's also imagine that
it's zoned for development,
for residential development.
Now we are in a case study.
There are cities which
do not have a SDAU.
There are cities which have an SDAU,
but don't respect it.
There are cities which do not have POS.
There are cities which have POS,
of land-use plans,
but which don't respect them.
So really what we have here for
the first two responses, are case studies.
Availability of the land?
Again, we'll assume it is, otherwise
the questionnaire would end there.
If the site is not available for building,
there is no point in asking
further questions.
A slope of less than 8%? Why?
Because when it exceeds 8%, or 9 or 10%,
building on the slope becomes difficult,
and the additional costs for construction
on a slope are such that
it no longer makes sense, except for
a very high-end development.
Otherwise level land is preferable
from a cost standpoint,
it is also because technically
it's easier to manage.
Solid ground?
Yes, we need solid ground which
will allow for construction.
Is the distance to the water table
greater than three meters?
Yes, because if it is close
to the water table,
there is a risk of a rising water table,
and thus of flooding.
Now we'll go to the column of the "no's"
with its major nuisances.
Let's assume there are
no major nuisances in this zone.
Let's also assume that there is
no pollution risk in the zone, no risk,
that the zone is not polluted,
and so we can build on it.
And then the question we'll also
ask ourselves is that of presence,
once the development is complete,
will it pose a pollution risk
to the immediate environment?
It is there where we'll need a "no,"
otherwise we'd have to
start making choices.
Does it make sense to build there?
Is the land serviced by access roads?
Yes, or no.
There are two possible responses.
Sufficiently serviced by roads?
Yes or no.
We can have both answers at the same time,
because we pass from linear meter
to linear kilometer
to determine the length of the roadway.
Ultimately, to create roadways
is not too difficult.
The question is one of the cost involved
in servicing sufficiently this need.
Near public transportation?
Yes, but this, once again, is a case study
because in most cities
there is no public transport
with predetermined routes,
but instead it is the transport
which goes to areas where there are
many people who need it.
Now, if your development is very dense,
and has a large population,
it is extremely likely that there will be
public transport available,
whether by minibus, taxi,
or motorcycle-taxi.
Water service?
Same thing.
The question? Yes or no.
Can the water be serviced by gravity?
Yes or no.
Now there are different methods,
but by gravity is the best,
because it is, financially speaking,
the most reasonable.
And if there is not, we are once again
looking at linear meter.
Electric service?
Same thing, yes or no.
Is the power sufficient?
Yes or no.
If not it will have to be built,
and what is the length of the line
that must be installed?
Is there a low-tension transformer?
Yes or no, same thing.
So these are questions
of public equipment.
For the development will we need
construction equipment?
Yes or no.
Perhaps we're building a health-care
center, an elementary school,
a market, a sports center,
and then an administration.
And if not, what is the distance
in linear meters
to the nearest hospital?
How far is the nearest high-school,
or middle school?
These are very important elements,
because often undeveloped land is used,
so undeveloped that there is no school,
no market, it has nothing available,
and so we put people in a situation
which becomes extreme,
because they need access
to education or to health-care.
Second step in the creation
of our development,
is the question of site allocation.
We have, for example ... let's imagine
a river here.
We put a bit of water,
color it in blue, here.
The question now becomes,
which land is conducive to development?
We have here a very steep slope.
We have here a flood zone.
Here we have a forest, and we realize
that all of this zone here is not
a good place for development.
and finally we are left without a doubt,
here, this zone,
to create our development.
Now to back up a bit,
a quick review of the different things
we've already discussed.
Sloping terrains, if the land
is too steeply sloped,
it becomes difficult to build on it.
If the land is uneven,
if the land is completely wavy,
and it looks like this, for example,
there is no point building on it,
It's too difficult, too costly.
Mountains, hillsides,
by their very nature are sloping,
and these are the lands sought out,
generally, by the wealthy.
And in most cities,
the shantytowns pop up here,
because it is in forests,
or on steep slopes,
where no one wants to settle.
Quarries, sandy areas, humid zones,
areas that are environmentally fragile.
These may be conservation zones
which are environmentally protected,
or where there are species
of flora and fauna found only there,
And no building should be done there,
to safeguard them.
Flood zones and archeological sites,
or cultural heritage sites,
zones like these, natural or built.
There are lands which simply
should not be built on.
Now, from the plan we've developed,
we'll subtract all those zones
where building is not advised.
There too we are with a case study,
for in most cities
you'll find construction in sandy zones,
humid zones, flood zones,
but in planning a development we must
take these things into account,
and in principal remove
all zones such as these,
subtract them from any plan.
And, finally, all those lands
not in the zones described above,
become then, buildable lands.
Next we'll perform
a diagnosis of the zone.
A sort of state of the land,
once the land is chosen.
Once we've seen
its different characteristics,
have chosen the first perimeter
of our land development,
we can then begin to prepare
a diagnosis of the zone.
Now the diagnosis is made up
of questions which might be...
questions of climate,
the sun, here we have rain falling.
This is the data to take into account,
the climate, the microclimate.
Another important piece of data
is the nature of the land.
We have geological strata marked here,
what type of land we have,
what type of drainage one might have
here on the surface.
Naturally the water will flow
in the direction of the slope,
and then we have nature,
the flora and fauna.
So this is important to know,
are there species to be protected?
Now, the second part.
Here we are not in cutaway,
but on the plan.
It is what exists. Is there already
an infrastructure of roadways
which leads here, if I consider as
my development zone this one?
OK, and then are there water and
electrical networks that can reach here?
We also ask ourselves the question,
to know what are these lands,
the nature of the land adjacent to it.
Next phase, the topographical
survey of the zone.
We'll use a scale of 1/1000 to 2/1000,
and will imagine a scale of 1/500,
which is far more precise,
with far more details,
but far more time-consuming to survey,
and we'll ask ourselves if it's
reasonable or not
to spend so much time in preparing a plan
at a scale of 1/500 when often
1/1000 or 1/2000 would be sufficient.
Now, let's assume we've chosen
this zone here,
and let's review its different points.
perhaps the group of buildings
doesn't serve us at all,
in this case, while blocks would allow us
to use, as a start, the roads
which already exist.
We'll also highlight the forested limits,
We'll look at water.
We'll highlight everything
that's on the site,
and then we'll make level curves
at 1 meter, 1.5 meters, 2 meters,
in relation to the nature of the land.
We'll also of course highlight
any large trees we find.
The large baobabs, for example,
which must be preserved,
and any element worthy of protection,
which is cultural or non-cultural,
which is part of the cultural heritage,
we'll highlight very carefully.
After this, we'll determine the size
and shape of the parcels.
The size and form are influenced
by social conditions, societal,
by the nature of the land,
by the building conditions,
we'll review all of these
different aspects
one after another,
beginning with...
Lifestyle.
Why lifestyle?
Because we can clearly see that we have
very, very dense parcels, like this,
and we won't have the same
relationships between neighbors
as those where the parcels
are very loose,
with large streets dividing them.
So here we won't see the same
lifestyles as we would here.
Why lifestyle too?
Because if I want to design
a shared parcel,
shared equipment and facilities,
surely I will need to put
all my islets, and we're speaking,
of course, of islets,
around, because it is very, very clear
that they are directly connected to here.
It's not the same thing under another
plan where I have my parcel here,
and the islets I'll develop only there.
So we have a social structure which
influences the size of the parcel,
for we are not building
for the same family,
if it's made up of seven or eight
people per household,
or of four, as in South Africa.
We were in Senegal, before.
So this can determine
the size chosen for the parcel
in regard to the social structure
of the family.
The building techniques
are not at all the same.
We can easily see that in the case of
this neighborhood here
or this type of habitat,
the construction techniques,
the status or the building norms
also define the middle-sized parcel
if we want this type of building
or this type of habitat,
we'll of course have, here,
parcels which are bigger than
these small, individual parcels over here.
The nature of the parcels.
We're speaking of the residential,
which is the case we'll find here.
These are the blocks, as you see,
different residential blocks,
and then we see that their sizes
are not at all the same
when it is on an industrial scale
or even if all this is,
at some point or another, subdivided.
We don't have the limits we might want
for land development,
but we see these small blocks here,
and the large blocks,
which are parcels for industry.
Then we have geometric rules.
We can imagine that we have one size,
here, which is the minimal.
Beyond that, it becomes really
too dense, really too closed in,
the people are on top of one another,
at the maximum size,
which we'll mark here,
beyond which the cost
of development is such that
it's no longer possible to make
a cost-effective development.
So the form of the parcel,
as we saw earlier,
the closer to the street,
the less linear infrastructure,
the larger, the more needed,
but the size of a parcel like this,
which is very slim, we can easily see
how difficult it would be
to build a house or a shack
on a parcel such as this,
and, finally, the best size
is the double square here,
a rectangle based on a double square,
which allows us, we recall, as we've seen,
to return to the plan
at the end of the islet.
Next, is of course not to use the square,
which is the least rational form
we've seen thus far,
and then the last shape of parcel,
which is the potatoid, or potato-shaped,
which in principle is not liked,
because it has too many restrictions,
but we can imagine,
no reason not to imagine,
that in the case of the restructurization
of precarious zones,
we end up with land titles assigned to
potato-shaped parcels.
Then, as to size, we can issue
rules which give
alignments or zones
which prohibit construction,
which help to avoid building
over-dense areas,
and we can do this,
with public spaces,
and we can do exactly the same thing
between two parcels,
saying that it is not permitted
to build at less than 3 meters,
less than 2, less than 1 meter,
or 50 centimeters.
It's a choice, but one of
the methods of urban planning
that opens up a number of views,
opens up proximity or overcrowding,
and these are the instruments,
the alignment plans which
will be used relatively often.
The same with sectioning,
we can imagine
that the relation between public space,
here, and construction
is a maximum height, or a minimum height,
and that if we section here,
between neighbors,
which will have a maximum height
of x meters or of x floors,
which keeps us from building a 50-story
building next to a very small house.
Finally, and certainly of great importance,
the economic conditions of the population
who will inhabit the development.
Whether low-income or high-income,
we must take into account the revenues
and the possibilities that families
or households have to purchase a parcel.
So the size of the parcel will depend on
the revenue of the household.
Same with the nature of the site.
It is also very important
with sloping land,
in regards to the morphology of the site,
that parcels are designed so that
they are not exactly the same,
whether rectangular or potato-shaped,
as a function of what one has.
Finally, we must determine
the types of zones of the development,
the most classic being that of habitat,
but also zones for small business,
retail zones, socio-educational zones,
and public domain, green zones,
as we'll see in detail next.
Here is an example of a development
where we can clearly see a market,
so we have a first zone,
which is a market area.
Here we have green spaces, perhaps
either flood zones or unbuildable,
which is our second zone.
Then we have all the unallocated zones,
which will clearly be habitat zones,
a transformer, electric, perhaps,
and then between these habitat zones,
what remains is public domain.
So we see only by chance, here also
most likely a small business unit.
In a simple development we already see
this group of zones, as described.
Now, perhaps we lack a school,
a clinic, or athletic fields,
but we see that any development
will incorporate these zones.
To finish with these different zones,
we have the question of percentage.
In principal, residential zones
should be at least 50%.
You'll find in certain developments
a much higher percentage,
because we count the surrounding roadways
as 20% of the orders of magnitude.
Here we have 70% roadways plus habitat,
with 30% spanning these different zones,
which might be commercial, social,
recreational, or green spaces.
It is very important to maintain this 30%,
but often what we see is that
this 30% drops to 10%,
because of equipment,
and what makes our 50% becomes 70%.
Inevitably, the more residential zones,
the more assignable zones,
and the more land to sell.
And if I'm no longer in business,
this lowers the parcel price
of my development.
But let's try today to say that it's 50%,
neither more nor less,
which is residential,
the rest in roadways, green spaces,
shared spaces.
So we must establish
a development program.
To do this we ask the question of
how many people will live in it?
It's A.
B.
The number of people per household.
And then, the number of parcels needed.
It's simple. A divided by B.
And once I get the number of parcels,
which I then multiply
by the average surface area
of my parcel.
We end up with a total of x,
and, finally, since I have 50%
of residential parcels,
Two times x is equal to the total
surface area of my development.
To this we'll add next the question
of the equipment program,
and we must define what importance
we want to give each type of equipment,
and which situation we want
to give to our development.
So again, for the equipment
we have a population,
and we have a norm,
the number of inhabitants per equipment.
And this will give us
the number to create.
So we have a surface for equipment,
and we know the surface necessary.
Next we'll try to adapt our development
to the topography.
If I position myself like this,
with my roadways,
we'll very quickly have problems,
because the speed of the flow
perpendicular to the slope will be huge,
and we'll have problems
of soil cutaway here,
and of flooding of the housing.
To remediate this,
there are many techniques.
We can erase and begin again.
First, instead of making wide streets
like those we've just made,
we'll make them staggered,
which allows us in this way to achieve
flow speed which is notably less.
So the water cannot flow directly
as we had before, but is,
at each point, broken,
and as a result, this slows down
the water speed,
as well as the risk of land cutaway.
Another way might be instead of
perpendicular, like this,
which is to say at a slight slant
in relation to the slope.
There too we can imagine that the water
will flow at a much slower speed,
gently descending, while before
it went directly, straight.
And if we couple these
last things we've done,
which is to say that in
breaking up of the slope,
we find ourselves in situations where
the development becomes
something which might be like this,
and the question we must then ask
is if it is pertinent or not
to have these angles here,
instead of right angles.
So we must at the same time choose between
a perpendicularity in
the creation of the road,
and, ultimately, the design
of the roadways
which allow the water to flow gently.
The choice must be made,
and is, without doubt,
an intermediate situation
where we'll end up.
Next, nuisances.
Nuisances might be noise,
are often related to noise, right?
We'll avoid spending too much
time on nuisances.
Another one might be the wind.
If my residential areas are here,
the dominant wind like this,
I'll avoid putting
my industrial zone here
because the pollution will land there,
so instead I'll put it here, so the wind
blows across the residential area
and then over my industrial zone,
without bothering anyone.
The same for the sun.
If we have a slope, and residential areas.
The question is, depending
on the latitude,
to protect it from the sun or,
on the contrary,
to seek exposure to it.
The eleventh stage of our step-by-step
is the question of service.
Now of course, when speaking
of African cities, in most cities,
the rate of car ownership is very low.
We have, for example, 17, 20, 25
or 30 vehicles per 1000 inhabitants,
while in those countries,
let's call them industrialized,
we might have up to 500 cars
per 1000 inhabitants.
So the question of purpose
is certainly important.
But we must keep these
numbers in our heads,
there is a very small elite who are able
to get around by car.
But even in a situation such as this,
we have the same thing
in the poorest neighborhoods.
So we cannot economize
in service by cars.
We must imagine that cars are
exclusively in public spaces.
That there are no parking spaces,
or very few, on private space,
on one's own parcel.
So the public space must
at the same time manage
the circulation as well as
the parking of vehicles.
And then, as we can see in this image,
we can easily see that we must also
plan ahead, in our templates,
for these types of situations where
the street ends up so torn up,
in such a sorry state, that it
cannot support this narrow a roadway.
A much wider one is necessary,
so that cars can easily circulate.
So the template of service is not only
tied to the number of
vehicles which will circulate,
but equally to the conditions of the road
and the climatic conditions of the city.
Let's consider, finally,
other infrastructures.
Which plan to adopt?
A linear plan, a mesh plan?
A mesh plan will be more expensive,
will demand more pipelines,
but when there is an outage
here or there,
the system continues to supply
water to everyone,
while with the other plan,
if we cut it here or there,
an entire sector of the population
will no longer have access to water.
The next step is to estimate
the costs of development.
Quickly, of course the point, the land,
its purchase.
Second point, the work in situ,
which is, of course,
the preparation of the land, the roadways,
drinking-water supply, electricity.
Third, the off-site, so each time
we are here, B, here, C.
The fourth point, equipment.
Fifth, the studies and supervision.
And sixth the diverse and unexpected.
Finally, the price of the development,
the cost of its development.
Now we're on points A through F.
Once we have this cost, we have
the cost of development,
as we've just seen.
Next we have a surface,
of the development.
To keep in mind.
Then the assignable surface,
or that which can be sold, the habitat,
and this, as we've seen, is around 50%
of the surface of the development,
and which gives us
a cost per square meter of land,
which, if we want parcels
of 150 square meters,
will give us the unit-price
of the parcel.
Let's not forget to say that
the cost of development varies
as a function of the standards
or the norms applied to it.
If it is affordable or luxury,
if we want the road paved throughout
or just stabilized earth,
if we want strong equipment
coverage or not,
if we want electrification,
if we want individual
water distribution or not,
so all these things enter in and form
the costs of development,
directly linked to the choice of building
class, low or high-end.
The surface of the development,
as we saw earlier,
and then the assignable surface,
which should be 50%,
and then you can without hesitation
give a per-parcel cost for 150, 200,
300, 400, 600 square meters.
There are parcels much larger
still, as we've seen.
Remember, in terms of cost,
we must also take into account,
when there is an international investor,
the exchange rates.
We must also take into account
inflation, cost increases,
because from Day A, when you submit
your development sketches,
to Day Z, when you've finished your work,
you'll realize that
many years have passed.
And given the inflation in certain
countries, it's important
to be cognizant of this inflation
in the costs of your development.