In this very short video,
we will see an important aspect
of housing development.
It's the balance between
real estate and land
in free-market economies.
As we said, there is a balance
between the cost of land
and real estate investment.
What is the cost of land?
It's first and foremost
the price of the plot.
Plus the land development,
land clearing,
making a plan,
network costs,
and finally equipment costs
if they are assigned to the cost of land,
which is not always the case,
sometimes, the equipment is not included.
Next come real estate investments.
What are they?
They are any buildings on the land.
If we take the geometry of the plot,
or of the right to use,
it gives the building volume,
which determines the possible
real estate investments.
If I start from the cost of land,
I get an economical interest in building.
We can play with the different factors,
for example, a high cost of land
will spur to create density
in order to report the high cost
on as many houses as possible.
On the other hand, if we want
to decrease the cost of land
we can, for example,
lower the network cost,
therefore the service provided
with the networks,
or modify the geometry of the plots.
If the building volumes are too small,
we will try to increase them,
it's a well-know speculation:
plots are being bought
with low building rights,
then we put pressure on the government
to try and increase the rights
in order to have the best profitability.
These examples happen obviously
in a free market economy
where land and real estate
balance each other out.
In a non-market economy system,
the role of the government
is utterly important
as it may fluctuate the land prices.
Although, it cannot change
the cost of the infrastructures,
it may still be able
to vary the cost of land.
So the government in some countries
that have a lot of plots
may flood the market
in order to lower land prices
in the free market economy
or put pressure on this market
to increase land prices.
So the government leeway
on the cost of land
is utterly important.
This is roughly the balance issues
between land and real estate.