Here in this last video of this week,
we will talk about some examples that
are going to take us to Luanda, Dakar
Dakar or Kigali and we will see that in
these cities, depending on the standard or
the standing of the chosen subdivision,
there are large, indeed, very,
very large disparities
between the surface areas
of the subdivisions.
First example, the city of Luanda.
A neighborhood chosen at random,
we see that the subdivision
is very regular, we see, the double block,
let's show it differently, so each time,
we come to determine a plot,
and we realize that the plots are
more or less 13 meters by 14,
so we have seen it,
it's not the best, we are almost dealing
with a square,
it's not the best of the solutions,
but we have plots
which are relatively small, we will see those
ones later, that are 182 square meters.
Road allowances, primaries at 18 meters,
11 meters for the secondary
and the tertiary at eight meters.
Another example in Luanda, we see that
we change the standing, here we have
696 meters once again between 24 and 29,
we almost have a square.
What is interesting to see here is that
the roads are however much smaller
than in the other subdivision.
It's normal with plots of 696 square meters,
we really have far less residents
so a very different road need.
Another example, Kigali, we recognize
the city easily
by its hills, let's take a
first neighborhood.
We see the blocks here, which are subdivided
in plots, it's easier to see,
here we have three plots,
so the first neighborhood we have
very small plots, 9 by 12, 108
and then primary roads at 12 meters
and secondaries at 10 meters.
We have a very very high density.
We change aspect, we change
neighborhood, we have a neighborhood
which starts on the hillside, we see it
by its curves which follow more or less
the natural curves and there we find
ourselves with surface areas
of 425 square meters,
so they are enormous plots, even though
we are dealing with
equivalent routes for primary
and secondary
and a tertiary which is practically
for the pedestrian.
Another example, still in Kigali,
we see here that
the size of the plots, it's very easily
detectable and here we are looking at
surface areas of 600 square meters which
are surface areas that one must admit,
are huge compared to
the needs of a family.
Now to Dakar.
We travel very quickly, we were in Luanda,
we go on to Kigali, we arrive in Dakar,
with a first neighborhood, here also
easy to see the different blocks,
we can then subdivide them and
we have 12 by 16, 192 square meters
of plot once again 12, 7 and 5 meters.
All this to give you a palette of
what is possible and what exists,
we see now North Pikine,
so we see density but it's because
we're not using the same scale, the primary
is very big and the secondary
and tertiary are very small and the plots
on the other hand,
which are plots of 300 square meters.
Finally Keur Massar,
on the outskirts of Dakar,
really, previously outskirts
since the city
is catching up rapidly,
we also have
a certain number of plots
of 300 square meters.
There you have, some examples,
very quickly examined, we have seen
we are at 700 square meters in a subdivision,
while in others we are at 108 or sometimes
a plot of 100 square meters.
A summary neighborhood, we added
Bangui et Bamako, we see that
we are at 108, without a doubt, at
the smallest, searching, to the biggest,
which is 748 square meters, so we have
differences which are huge
depending on, not only the standing that
we want to create in the neighborhood,
but also the construction practices.
The 192, which is a module
of 12 by 16 in Dakar,
is without a doubt the one which
we find the most in the whole city,
we find it in a second neighborhood,
while the 300 square meter plots
in Dakar are relatively rare.
On the other hand, we see that
we are much more large,
much bigger in Luanda,
and we are not talking about
Bamako where the three neighborhoods
chosen at random
show the huge plots relative to
the needs of a family.
There it is, there is no value judgment
behind these different subdivisions,
but simply to show that the contrasts are
enormous and that if we are dealing with
a subdivision of 108 or 192 square meters
and a subdivision of 748,
inevitably the profitability of the pot
will not be the same.
There you have it,
that's how our video ends.