This week's lectures are dealing
with the basic contrast mechanisms of MRI
and so I want to first, however, start out
with a very important message
that is dear to me and this is:
we are dealing here
with one physical phenomenon
and that is magnetic resonance.
We're dealing with one instrument
that is one magnet
but what we are getting
out of this modality,
out of this biophysical mechanism
is many different contrasts.
So we have many different
contrast mechanisms.
So I want to first start out
with some examples.
This is a so called proton density
weighted image.
So we have a cut through the head here.
This is from the brain
and if it's proton density
then essentially what has been imaged here
is the equilibrium magnetizations,
so that reflects the density
of the protons in the MRI.
Then here's an example
of a T1 weighted image.
Again a similar cut from the subject.
It's a transversal cut, T1 weighted,
so, and here is a T2 weighted image.
So these are some
very basic contrasts,
proton density
T1 weighted and T2 weighted
and you can see that just by changing
some experimental parameters,
one can substantially change
the appearance of the image.
So here, what is interesting to note here
is the cerebrospinal fluid,
the ventricles, they are filled with
cerebrospinal fluid.
Here they are more intense
than the others
because they have a bit more water
In the T1 weighted image they're dark
because they have a long T1
and in T2 weighted image they are bright
because they have a long T2.
Here's an example which
is more pathological
so this is clearly not
a normal part of the brain.
This is T1 weighted
and here it's T2 weighted.
Now what is this space here?
It's dark on T1 weighted
like the cerebrospinal fluid.
It's bright on a T2 weighted
like cerebrospinal fluid.
So this is a cavity where
tissue has been eliminated.
in fact it is a large cyst.
It's just cerebrospinal fluid.
Probably a resected tumor
or some complication early in life.
Now here's another example,
it's a bit more elaborate
that I want to illustrate here
and this is imaging multiple sclerosis,
so we're looking at the plaques.
So we're looking here
at the T2 weighted image on the left
and we see that cerebrospinal fluid
is bright, it's here in the ventricles,
and it's also in the cell site.
And if one looks very carefully among
all these bright signals,
one sees some signals here
that are somewhere
where they shouldn't be.
But this is, with this--
all this bright signal
is difficult to detect.
So then the approach that is often
used in multiple sclerosis
is to use the so-called
fluid attenuated
inversion recovery approach.
So or FLAIR.
That's the acronym for that
and this is a combination
of T1 and T2 weighted.
First what is done with an inversion pulse
and an inversion time TI
that is such that the signal from the CSF,
the magnetization,
the longitudinal magnetization
from the CSF is zero.
At that point when the
longitudinal magnetization
in the cerebrospinal fluid is zero,
the signal is read out
and then detected with a long echo time
so it is T2 weighted.
What then happens is
that these lesions here
in the brain tissue
the signal changes appreciably
compared to the brain tissue
and there's substantially
more contrast to noise ratio.
Here the signal to noise ratio
is substantially better
but here the contrast ratio
that's distinguishes
these demyelinating legions
from the normal appearing tissues
around them is much easier detectable.
And finally, we have the T1 weighted image.
On the T1 weighted image
because demyelinating legions
are destruction of tissue,
so there's less tissue, less membranes,
less proteins around, T1 and T2
are getting longer,
T1 is longer, they appear as dark
and then again not as visible
as they are here on the middle image.
So we have here just the examples
T1, T2, and proton density
that give us already
three basic contrasts in MRI.
Another contrast I want to discuss
this week is T2* weighted.
We're actually going to discuss
this contrast first.
With T2* weighting,
what is often done is venography.
And the goal here is to use
experimental conditions
that at which point the magnetization
that's in the venous blood has decayed
so venous blood, the signal
from venous blood is darker
than normal tissue.
So it's a reduction in magnetization
in blood.
What is a venogram?
What does it look like?
Here is from the brain.
So this is a T2* weighted image
and all these black stripes here,
that are in here,
they're in fact normal manifestation
of venous blood that has a short T2*.
That is deoxygenated
and we'll see shortly.
We'll discuss this shortly.
In research there has been functional MRI
has been coming along.
It's based on blood oxygen level
dependent functional MRI
or BOLD fMRI
and what I want to highlight here
is an example of the very first images,
or some of the very first images
that Seiji Ogawa at Bell Labs
obtained at the time
in the late 1980's from the rat's brain.
So this is a rat brain
under normal conditions.
This is what such a T2*
weighted image looks like.
And one day he noticed
that in one of the animals
which was having trouble breathing,
he obtained an image
that looked like this.
There were the venous structures
that were dark appearing
and general the sensitivity of the signal
had decreased.
And he had the enormous insight
to realize that from neuroscience
we knew that there is an increase
in cerebral blood flow
much more than oxygen extraction.
So this would lead to a change
in deoxygenation in the blood vessels
and he proposed at the time
that this is possible to exploit
in normal brain activation studies
to see the activity of the brain
and hence in the early 90's
the functional MRI was born.
Nowadays the datasets used for fMRI
for brain activation studies
depict datasets like this,
so we have the anatomical image.
Here are the eyeballs, retrobulbar fat.
this is axial cut, this is a coronal cut,
these are sagittal cuts and overlaid
on the anatomical images
are the area of the brain
that have been activated
in response to an external stimulus.
That stimulus can be finger tapping,
it can be looking at an image,
it can be listening to a sound,
it can be a mental task, and so forth.
Now I want to give here another view
on spatial coding with MRI.
Last week we have introduced
a two dimensional
spatial encoding with MRI
and I'm sure you have found it
not the easiest topic to understand.
So I want to give it here another try
and give you another argument
to rationalize how we reconstruct
images with MRI.
So let's start with the basic experiment.
We need to have an RF pulse to flip
the magnetization into transfer plane
so we have something that precesses
that we can detect.
This is done typically
with a slice select gradient
so we're selecting a slice
like this in the brain
and then we have the frequency
and encode gradient that is switched.
The first part
of the experiment is excitation
and then we have frequency and coding,
so two phases of the experiment.
We observe here the echo time
at this time point.
The echo, we observe the echo
at this time point
and this is defined by the echo time.
We have seen that we need
this negative gradient refocusing gradient
to have maximal sensitivity
to minimize the effects of dephasing
under slice select gradient.
Here is the frequency encoding
dephase and rephase
and when these two areas
are the same we have echo.
So now I'll introduce a time
and I'll call it T2.
You'll see shortly why I call it T2
and not just simply, T2.
So as we record the signal
with this scanner,
we'll call the time
during which this happens, T2.
And now we're going to look at the signal
as a function of T2
starting at this time point.
So this is time zero here.
This is equal to
the transverse magnetization
as a function of position x.
We have the gradient here,
we'll assume along x.
So gradient will assume
the frequency codes along x.
So magnetization starting here,
they're all aligned, they're collinear.
And then we have the different
precessional frequency
based on the deposition along x.
So it's gamma G x times x times T2
is the face as it evolves.
And of course the entire [scene]
we see is the summation
of all the signals along x.
So now the link between the signal
as a function of T2
the time domain signal
and the magnetization
as a function of position,
the link between the two is given
by the Fourier transformation.
And we take a standard Fourier pair,
time and frequency.
So the Fourier transform
of a signal and time
gives you a function as a function
of frequency.
That's a standard Fourier pair,
time frequency.
So if we have T2 as our time variable,
then omega 2 is our --
we'll call omega 2
the corresponding Fourier pair variable.
Now omega 2 is the
gamma Gx times x,
that is linked to the position
because the gradient is fixed.
The gamma is fixed so this is
omega 2 is linearly related
to the position.
So the magnetization is a function
of this frequency
is equal to the magnetization
as a function of position.
Okay so actually if we look
at a two-dimensional object
at a given position in x,
all the magnetizations that have
the same coordinate along x,
for this gradient along y,
they'll have the same
precessional frequency
so we cannot distinguish them.
They'll just appear as a stronger signal
and this is reflected that
we have to sum along y,
all the magnetizations along y,
for a given position x.
That's our magnetization along x.
And so it turns out that
after Fourier transform
of our echo here of this signal
we're getting M of x
and M of x is the Radon transform
of the magnetization along
the direction x.
Now what we can do is here,
this is for a particular direction x
but I have not defined what x is
so I can choose any coordinate system
and have x different.
And so we can actually change
the orientation of this projection,
the magnetization of x,
by now changing the orientation
of the gradient,
because the direction
of this Radon transform
is entirely defined
by the gradient orientation.
So if I now choose a gradient,
and remember we have introduced
gradient as vector
as a linear combination of--
as with two components
basically with a constant amplitude
but I will rotate it by an angle phi.
What this amounts to is,
that we are recording the projection,
the echo, along an orientation
that is rotated with respect to x
by the angle phi.
You can verify that,
if phi is zero,
then we have a gradient along x.
If phi is 90 degrees,
then we have a gradient along y.
And of course we can be changed
between the two gradually
by changing phi gradually.
And so this we can repeat,
we can repeat different projections.
We'll collect
after Fourier transformation
the Radon transforms
of our magnetization.
We'll do this in many steps
just like with CT.
We'll have to take into account
that we have to every time
to measure new Radon transform.
We'll have to do a new excitation.
So this will be done every TR seconds
based on the repetition time.
This leads to a sinogram.
In principle we can reconstruct any image
with projection reconstruction
or we can make a link to
Fourier transformation
with a central slice theorem.
So if this helps you to understand
why MRI scans take some time
we are going to have to collect
the different projections,
the different angles,
we can do that just as well.
It has been done in the X-ray techniques
and then reconstruct the image
using those techniques is definitely
a possibility.
So this could convince you
that it indeed,
A, it is possible to reconstruct
an image,
and B, why collecting the data of an image
does take considerable time
because if we want to have
a 256 by 256 matrix
that means we have to collect
256 angles phi
and for this we have to wait
256 TR periods.
TR is linked to T1 so it is typically
on the order of the T1 relaxation time
and therefore that explains
why it takes typically a couple of minutes
to obtain an MRI image.
Okay so if this helps you,
but now I'm going to try to look
at the phase encode gradient
because the MRI reconstruction
and data requisition is rarely done
using the Radon transform approach.
There are some applications
but they are the vast majority.
The major application, the major way
of obtaining the image is done
by two-dimensional encoding
using the phase encode gradient.
Now what I want to make here the argument
is phase encoding is essentially
just frequency encoding
in a second time dimension.
So we'll just put in here
a phase encode gradient.
We're looking here at this time period.
It's the third-dimension
and now we'll look at here
at the y gradient we've had last week
we have talked about phase encode gradient
having a certain amplitude,
and a certain duration tau.
And if we have now an Nth step
then the amplitude of the gradient
is N times delta gamma y,
that's the gradient strength
times y times gamma times the duration
that gives us the phase twist induced
by this gradient.
So for the Nth phase encode state
the transverse magnetization
after this phase encode gradient
so right here is given by the
magnetization before
so that's the transverse magnetization here
times this phase term here.
And what we have done is we've argued
that if we now step through
these amplitudes with a decrement
or an increment of delta Gy,
we do this several times.
That this essentially allows us
to encode the second spatial dimension.
The argument there was that I made
it was graphical to say,
well in the end the computer
cannot distinguish whether
we have collected
one-dimension immediately
and the other one step by step
or if we do it in reverse
and therefore these two things
are equivalent.
Now what I want to argue here is
that we can actually look--
if you look here at the gradient times
time term,
the n delta Gy tau,
I can rewrite this and I'll say,
well n times delta Gy tau,
I'll express this as a constant gradient
times n times delta tau.
So now I have a constant gradient
along y and I have this term n delta tau.
What does this mean?
So for the Nth gradient step
we'll start out with
the first gradient step
we'll have an amplitude,
Gy, this is the gradient along y,
and we'll have a duration of delta tau.
If we do now the second step,
then we have a duration of two delta tau,
and three delta tau,
four delta tau, and so on.
Five delta tau here.
So it's up to n delta tau.
And now we'll rewrite the magnetization
the effect of this gradient again,
gradient times time
gives you the phase effect.
So gradient times time n delta tau
times y times gamma is the phase term.
We're just using this identity here
so we're getting the magnetization now
expressed in this form, the evolution
of magnetization on to the gradient.
And now I can say well n delta tau
that's just nothing but a time dimension
which I call T1 that has been
discretely sampled at intervals delta tau.
So in the end effect
what we are now getting
is a signal that depends
on two time dimensions.
T2 is the time as we recorded,
T1 has been defined as the time
step by step
as we increase the gradient duration
for this example
but we have seen
that this is equivalent
to increasing the gradient amplitude
step by step.
So if we consider the signal
is now a two dimensional time signal,
there are of course not
two dimensional times as such
but it's a second virtual
time dimension,
we can do the frequency,
the Fourier transformation,
two dimensional Fourier transformation,
we got two time variables,
and this gives us a--
from the signal of T1 and T2,
gives us a magnetization as a function
of omega 1 and omega 2,
and therefore a magnetization
as a function of y and x,
because omega 1 is linked
to the position in y here
and omega 2 is linked
to the position in x that's here.
So we have a two dimensional time signal
we can view it as that way,
it's not standard way done in the MRI
but if it helps you
this is another way to look at it.
Two dimensional Fourier transform
gives us two frequencies.
A two dimensional object
and these frequencies through
the Larmor equation are linked
to position with the gradient condition.
Okay so much to rehash
the spatial encoding with MRI,
the phase encoding and I hope this helps
you with this relatively difficult topic
and understanding
how we generate 2D images.
Okay so last week we introduced
a gradient echo sequence,
this is the basic experiment
with which one generates images.
We've introduced how
the spatial information is encoded.
So now the question that
I want to go after is:
What is the contrast
in gradient echo imaging?
And here we will introduce
T2* weighting.
So we have the RF pulse
which is at an alpha degree.
We need this pulse to generate
transverse magnetization.
It is done with slice selection.
So we're selecting a slice here
and the areas of these two gradients
are equal but opposite.
This is refocusing
so we have maximum signal.
Then we have the frequency encode gradient
with dephasing and rephasing.
And this area here then defines
the rephasing.
And we have the phase encode gradient.
This gives us the signal that is
ultimately recorded.
We'll set this time here to zero
and here the time is defined
by the frequency encode gradient.
This is the echo time TE.
So this is our basic imaging sequence,
this is repeated n times
to generate the image.
Now what we want to look at is
one effect that produces T2* weighting
and that is to look at the effect
of static field imperfection,
which we haven't dealt with yet.
So far I have introduced you
to the relaxation times
and so far we have dealt with the B0,
aside from the gradient
that we introduce in the scanner,
the B0 is perfectly homogeneous
in space
and this is unfortunately not true.
In very general terms we can write this
static magnetic field to be
around which the magnetization precesses
has to be zero.
We have the gradient term,
now this can be time variant
as we can see here,
times the position plus a term
delta B of r.
This delta B of r is nothing
but the first order approximation
of the Taylor series expansion
of the magnetic field, if you will.
So it is the derivative of the z component
of the magnetic field,
with respect to position
times the position scalar product.
This is a vector,
this is a scalar product.
So this produces a changing magnetic field
and that is spatially dependent.
It is static, it's not time variant
and we can assume
that we have an image voxel
and in that image voxel
we don't have a perfect B0.
So we have a distribution
of magnetic fields in that voxel
of our image.
So what happens now,
this basically means
that if we have a dBz along that,
then basically what we've drawn here
the gradient as zero,
it's actually not truly at zero.
There is a little offset here
that is caused by this term dBz times z.
Same for x so this is dBz
derived by x times x
and the same for y, the y direction.
We're here just thinking about
a particular voxel.
So now our magnetization at time TE,
the signal here our echo at this time,
is given by the magnetization
just after the pulse,
we'll assume we have perfect refocusing
of the slice selection,
then we have e to the minus i gamma
from zero to TE.
The effect of the gradient actually
can include the slice here as well.
This will be nullified
but we have the effect of the gradient
and we have seen that
the phase term
is proportional to the time integral
of the gradient of T times r.
And then we have the term here from
the static field,
e to the minus i gamma,
again integrated from zero
to TE delta B of r dT.
That's our deviation
that's producing also a phase.
So we have-- we are not perfectly
at the Larmor frequency now
for at a given position r
and then we have the T2 effect here.
So what this means now is that
if you look at this term
this is an area,
this is the area under the gradient,
the effect of the phase,
this is also an area on the gradient
because we can write
this as a gradient just like here
but now it's a static gradient
that doesn't vary in time, it's constant.
And so essentially,
we have now the phase effect
of the static imperfection
and in addition to
the effect of the gradient.
And now we're going to be concerned
with the effect of this gradient.
We can write this now.
Empirically what one typically writes
that this is equals given to,
actually this is the integral
directly evaluated
so delta B does not change with time
so delta B times TE,
that's the phase effect.
And so now what we are going to do
to understand
what is the effect of this area here,
the blue area in the three directions.
We're going to use the feature
that I introduced last week
and that is that a gradient applied
simultaneously or sequentially
before the echo has the same effect
on the echo phase.
So what we're going to use now here
is that the gamma delta B times TE,
I can write this as:
gamma times n times delta B
times TE over n.
You see I multiplied by n
and divided by n.
What does this mean here is
now I can pretend to like
I'm implying an n times bigger
static field homogeneity
for an n times smaller time period.
The effect on the phase will be the same.
You can verify this term is in here.
The n cancels out so mathematically
it has no influence on the image phase
but we can easily visualize this.
So let's look at the phase encode gradient
which now here appears in green.
I will do this now,
I will shorten the duration of this
inhomogeneity.
I'll pretend that this is only applied
for a short period of time
and I'll increase the amplitude
by the same amount
so it is now n times bigger.
The area stays the same.
And then I will just say,
well I can again with the properties
I introduced last week,
we can say that this gradient
is applied for a short time just before
the phase encode gradient.
So what does this mean?
So if we have a voxel where there
is a gradient along y in that voxel,
it has an effect
on the magnetization phase
as if we had for a short time
turned on an additional gradient
that corresponds
to the dB0 derived by dy,
the gradient y static gradient times--
as if we have turned on
a little gradient here beforehand.
We can do the same
and they'll change
the color here for the readout.
So we have the area in orange here
will short net increase the amplitude
and now we'll move it somewhere else.
So what do we see here now
for a perfectly balanced imaging sequence
we see that the area here is the same
so the area the echo will be here.
Now the effect of this inhomogeneity
is to have a changing the area here.
This is of course a huge exaggeration here
these effects.
But the effect here of the inhomogeneity
is to introduce additional dephasing
and this will change a little bit
the position of the echo.
So not much to worry about.
However we have the z gradient,
we'll do the same thing here,
so we'll shorten the duration,
we'll just mimic again
the effect of the long time period.
We'll pretend that the effect
of the static gradient here
is being described by something
that is much shorter
but has n times larger amplitudes.
So I'll do this, I'll shorten it,
increase the amplitude
and I'll put it somewhere else.
What is happening here is
now we've had said
we need to have the area of this gradient
equal to the area of this gradient.
Now the static inhomogeneity
is changing the area of this gradient
because it's in this direction
and so now we no longer have
perfect refocusing
of magnetization along z.
So we no longer have maximum signal.
This gradient reduces our amplitude,
this gradient and the redirection
shifts the echo time,
usually it's not perceptible.
And the gray in phase encode direction,
this additional gradient here
will introduce a phase encode
an additional dephasing
can be substantial.
So we have as a result,
we have a reduction in signal amplitude.
And this we can verify,
we'll take this expression here
that we've had
and we'll now sum the magnetization
over one voxel.
So the e to the minus TE
over T2 is constant,
We'll take it out.
It's a three dimensional integral
over the voxel times this phase term
over the echo time.
That's the effect of the phase
of this term here.
We'll assume that
all this gradients have cancelled
because we're exactly measuring here.
So now this term here produces
a dephasing integrated over the voxel
so we have all sorts of different
precessional frequencies in our voxel.
This will create a dephasing
that increases with TE
and therefore a reduction in signal.
Now what one does here is very
empirical.
We'll just say, well the signal actually
is still decaying exponentially
but now with
a time constant T2*,
we'll call this
time constant T2*.
So empirically there's a relationship
between T2 star and T2,
so one over T2 star is equal to
one over T2 plus gamma delta B.
Delta B is always considered to be
a positive term,
gamma is positive so this is--
the right side is bigger.
If the right side is bigger than T2,
then T2* is smaller than T2.
Or T2 is longer than T2*.
So delta B is here really
an empirical parameter, a flux parameter
that just describes the degree
of inhomogeneities
but it is a way to quantify
the inhomogeneities
that are present in the voxel.
So to summarize the effect of
static inhomogeneities,
imperfections in the static magnetic field
creates a faster decay of the signal
is faster than pure T2
and also an opportunity
for additional contrast,
which we'll see in the next section.