So, I've introduced T_2 star changes,
I've introduced T_2 star,
now the question is,
how do these changes in T_2 star
relate to something useful,
to some biophysical mechanism?
Now we'll start here
with magnetic susceptibility.
And we know from magnetism
that the magnetic in an object
depends on the object's properties.
So we have the magnetic field
and the magnetic field inside the object
is linked to the externally applied
magnetic field B_0
through the susceptibility.
You can see this is
multiplied by 10^-6
so the susceptibility here is given in ppm
so it is a relatively small effect.
And the major effects
that we're looking at
is diamagnetism, that's a repelling force,
and paramagnetism,
which is an attracting force--
it has to do with interactions between
the atoms and the external magnetic field.
So here I want to illustrate an example.
This is a levitating strawberry,
it's placed on a strong magnet--
permanent magnet--
that is very inhomogeneous,
and the strawberry is primarily water
so it's diamagnetic
and so it levitates in air here
as you can see on this video from YouTube.
Here's another example.
And that is a Canadian frog
that is also placed
on top of a strong magnet field,
the frog is very light
so it has the same repelling force
as the strawberry,
and about a comparable weight,
so this animal is floating
on top of the magnet.
We could of course ask the question,
at what point
are we able to levitate humans,
but this is more of an academic interest
than of reality, what we want to do.
So these are the effects on
two living examples
from life sciences.
In the following experiments
that I will be showing,
I will be showing you the effect,
the levitation effect,
then we'll look at --
the effect on fluids
in a magnet as it's turned on,
and finally, what we're going to be seeing
is the difference between
molecular oxygen and nitrogen--
that molecular oxygen is paragmagnetic
and nitrogen is diamagnetic
just like water
and we'll see these
three experiments just now.
So in this experiment
what we have here is a strong magnet,
on top of it, a diamagnetic substance
which is held down by another magnet.
So I relieve it now
and now you can see
the repelling force of diamagnetism
of the magnet on the object--
it is hovering in mid-air.
So if I take here a piece of paper
I can easily slide it underneath,
and you can clearly see
how it is hovering on top of the magnet--
there's no physical connection,
there's a distance.
That's the repelling force
of diamagnetism.
Okay, so in this experiment we have again
an electromagnet with the poles.
Between the two poles,
where the magnetic field is established,
we have two cuvettes;
in those two cuvettes,
on your right side, we have water,
and on the left side, we have
iron perchloride which is paramagnetic.
Currently the magnet is off--
so you can see the level of the water
which is on the same level--
and when I turn it on,
the magnetic field,
the paramagnetic substance
is pulled upwards,
much more so than the water
is pushed downwards
because it's being repelled
by the magnetic field.
Okay, so what we have here
is a magnet which is on--
so it's a magnetic field
created between these two poles--
and we'll first pour liquid nitrogen,
in this experiment,
on top of here.
And what you'll see is
that the liquid nitrogen
will just fall through.
So I'll take it now--
and you can see the liquid nitrogen
just falls through.
As we have seen in the course,
liquid nitrogen is diamagnetic
so there's no force on it.
Now if on the other hand
I take liquid oxygen--
I'll repeat the same experiment--
and now we can see how
it is being retained between the two poles
by the magnetic field--
that's the force of the magnetic field
on the paramagnetic molecular oxygen.
Okay.
And a similar situation arises in tissue,
that we have seen now
with the demonstration
with paramagnetic oxygen
and diamagnetic nitrogen.
We have in our tissue,
in our blood actually,
we have two types of hemoglobin:
deoxy-hemoglobin, which is paramagnetic,
and oxy-hemoglobin, which is diamagnetic.
This has to do with the fact whether
there's oxygen bound to the heme, iron,
or not.
This changes the configuration
of the electrons
and therefore changes
whether they are para- or diamagnetic.
So now what happens
if we are looking at a blood vessel
that's put into
an external field B_0 like this.
And here we have
the situation with a lot
of deoxygenated red blood cells.
So we have a number of red blood cells
here that are deoxygenated--
they're in blue; in red are
the oxygenated red blood cells.
The paramagnetism, the effect,
the paramagnetic deoxy--
the susceptibility
of deoxyhemoglobin is 1.6.
So now what happens is
there is a distortion in magnetic field
that is generated.
We do know that this actually happens
based on the orientation:
if you take an infinitely long cylinder--
for those of you who are
familiar with electromagnetics
or remember the calculations--
if you put an infinitely long cylinder
in a magnetic field,
parallel to the magnetic field,
we would not see a distortion
of the magnetic field
like this is seen here.
This one here is our perpendicular,
and here the effects
are quite substantial--
there's a distortion around the vessel
of the magnetic field.
If we take now an oxygenated vessel--
let's take an artery,
here we have a vein--
we have much more
oxygenated red blood cells
and very few
deoxygenated red blood cells,
so the average susceptibility
in the blood vessel is around -0.3.
And here we have very little distortions
of the magnetic field
outside of the vessel.
So, inside the vessel,
we have a big susceptibility effect--
and here I'll take first
the deoxygenated capillary,
the magnetic field is along z,
so it's to the right--
and I'll plot here the susceptibility
as a function of position.
It's a rough approximation; it's a sketch.
We know that we have a deoxygenated
capillary, deoxygenated blood,
so the susceptibility,
the magnetic field, inside is higher.
We have the tissue,
which is essentially just water,
the susceptibility is lower.
So we have a difference of susceptibility
between inside the vessel and outside.
What this means in terms of magnetic field
is that we have a different magnetic field
inside the vessel, and outside the vessel.
And somewhere there is a transition
between the two magnetic fields.
The transition is not immediate--
we don't have a discontinuous nature--
so it falls off gradually
with an appreciable gradient.
So, what this means is that actually,
outside of the capillary,
we have a change in magnetic field,
a change in delta B-0,
that's happening inside the tissue.
If we look at the oxygenated capillary,
I'll draw it in red here,
the difference in magnetic field,
the change that happens in the tissue,
is much smaller because we have almost
a nearly perfect diamagnetic situation
in the blood here.
Now, the consequence, if we have
such a gradient of magnetic field
surrounding the capillary,
the image voxel is much bigger,
so this means that we are going
to have a delta B
that is induced by physiology
and that is non-zero.
So there is a consequence here
that the T_2 star increases
with decreased deoxy-hemoglobin
concentration in the tissue.
So, that is in the blood,
but that's the average
deoxy-hemoglobin concentration changes--
if it decreases, then T-2 star
will increase
because we are reducing
the delt B_0 term here
which we have seen previously
influences the T_2 star.
Of course, a little caveat,
this depends on
the venous architecture in the voxel
depends on blood volume,
it depends on the orientation
of the blood vessels,
but we'll assume here for the rest
that this is fairly randomly ordered.
So now, how do we
get from a change in delta B_0
that's induced by
susceptibility changes in the vessel,
to a contrast that is dependent
on the blood oxygen level?
We know from brain physiology--
we discussed this
in the first part of this course--
that the oxygen consumption increases
much less than blood flow
during a mental task.
The mental task can be finger tapping,
it can be really a mental task,
it can be looking at an image,
it can be listening to a sound, etc.
So what is the consequence
if oxygen consumption
increases less, or doesn't increase,
above blood flow increases?
And this is also something
that we've discussed in Course 7,
is from mass balance,
from fixed principle,
the concentration of oxygen flowing in--
the arterial oxygen concentration--
minus the venous oxygen concentration,
is equal to the rate
of oxygen consumption divided by flow.
So if we take the simplified assumption
that a situation--
just for mentally thinking it--
that the oxygen consumption
does not change, but blood flow increases,
then this difference has to decrease
and the only thing that we can change
is the oxygen consumption in the veins
and this one will increase.
The oxygen consumption in the veins
is linked to the partial pressure
of oxygen in the blood
and this, in turn, is linked
to the percent saturation
of the hemoglobin molecules.
This is the saturation curve
of hemoglobin here--
it's a monotonous curve--
and so the oxygen concentration
in the blood
will change the saturation
of the deoxy-hemoglobin in the blood.
Here we have typically around 90-95%--
most of the hemoglobin is saturated
but this will change in the blood.
We're now looking at
the hemodynamic response,
what one sees in physiology is that
there's an increase in blood flow,
so there's a decrease
in deoxy-hemoglobin in the tissue,
there's an increase in BOLD.
There is, however,
a counteracting effect
that is also a typical
increase in blood volume.
This increases the number
of red blood cells in the tissue,
so the deoxy-hemoglobin increases
and that decreases the BOLD effect.
And I won't go into much of the details--
it's not the purpose of the course
to be a course on fMRI--
but in general, the BOLD response,
the BOLD signal,
is positively correlated
with changes in blood flow,
inversely correlated
with changes in blood volume
and inversely correlated
with changes in oxygen consumption rate.
This is the cerebral rate
of metabolic oxygen,
cerebral blood volume,
and cerebral blood flow.
So if we look at
the vessel architecture of the brain--
this is what we see in an MRI--
in red are the blood vessels typically.
And now, if we zoom in
to an imaging voxel--
that's our MRI voxel here--
then we see inside the voxel
the fine architecture.
So we'll see here the arterial input,
and we see the venules
and the capillary bed.
So this is essentially what contributes
the changes in delta B_0,
we're looking at a voxel here,
inside the voxel
we have this architecture.
And this changes now, depending
on oxygenation here, of this vessel--
this will change the gradient
in magnetic field surrounding the vessel.
So if we look at
the situation now cartoon-wise,
we have the artery supplying
oxygenated blood into the arterioles,
then we come to the capillary bed,
and in the capillary bed
we have all our brain cells here--
we'll focus on the neurons--
then we have the venules,
and finally the vein--
that's the venous effluent.
The whole thing that I've drawn here
corresponds to a length scale
of roughly 1-2cm.
So we have the feeding artery,
the draining vein,
and in between, at some point,
we'll have the capillary bed.
Now what happens
if we apply an external stimulus,
the neurons fire.
As they fire, afterwards we get
the blood flow response,
and the blood flow response
is much stronger
than the oxygen consumption.
That response results
in an increased blood flow in general.
The increased blood flow
decreases the deoxy-hemoglobin content
and the venous blood becomes pink.
You can actually verify that--
if you cut yourself in the foot,
you're standing,
then the blood that comes out
is fairly dark.
If you cut yourself in the foot,
and the foot is high up,
and you put some warm pads
around your leg,
so you arterialize the blood flow--
you increase the blood flow--
then the blood that comes out
of the wound is more pink.
So what is this in time?
So this sequence of events--
we have neurons firing,
we have a change in blood flow,
we have an increase
in oxy-hemoglobin in the veins,
a decrease in deoxy-hemoglobin--
how does this look over time?
We're going to look here
at the fMRI signal--
T_2 star-weighted signal--
we have the stimulus,
which was applied here, in the green bar,
and a few seconds later, we have a change
in the T_2 star-weighted signal.
Notice here the scale:
it's percent change,
so it's only in the order
of a few percent, the signal change.
It's a big enough change
to capture it with statistical means.
It's not a big enough change
to be able to look at an MRI
and say what you're thinking.
So MRI as a lie detector, may work--
people are trying it--
but in general you don't need to worry
if you go into an MRI,
one does not need to worry,
if one goes into an MRI,
that one is able to read from the MRI
right away what you're thinking.
Okay, so we have now the BOLD response,
we see a signal
in T_2 star-weighted image,
and the question is now,
how is this used to image brain function?
So here's a T_2 star-weighted image
of the human brain
and if one now takes a task condition,
like looking at a light
versus not looking at a light,
takes the T_2 star-weighted images,
and takes the difference
between these two time periods,
then one gets an image like this.
Fairly noisy--
outside here is no noise
because it's been zeroed--
and here we see an area
that is fairly bright.
This was in the early days how people
looked at brain activation,
to convince the critics that indeed
one could see brain activation,
but this is no longer
the way this is being done.
But I'm showing it here
for curiosity reasons.
What is actually done nowadays
is that one collects an entire series,
time series, of images over time,
over and over again,
with special techniques that allow us
to acquire this much faster,
and so this is a series
of T_2 star-weighted images;
a time series.
This is recorded--
here's, for example,
the time series of a single pixel
in a brain activation task--
and you can see that the signal changes
relatively periodically.
These activations are linked to the task--
in this particular case,
there were 7 tasks, always the same task--
and the change in T_2 star-weighted image
here, the BOLD change,
corresponds to
the application of this task,
of the repetitive measure of this task.
So now, since what we are looking for
is a change in pixel intensity,
to say this is corresponding
to a change in T_2 star--
in outlying
deoxy-hemoglobin changes--
what one does is,
one takes this time series,
compares it to
the measured time series, the task,
and then does a statistical analysis.
So here, this means "on",
and this means "off"--
actually, it's state A and state B
is the more correct term--
so now comes the hard part
and that's a lot of statistical analysis.
We're not going to go into
the details here--
one has to be very careful,
very stringent how it's being done--
but what happens next.
So what one gets then
is a statistical significance image.
That basically just says, "I'm looking
at the statistical probability
that a particular pixel here
is indeed following
the activation pattern given by the task."
And here we can see
a higher statistical significance.
This actually is not looked at directly--
what is looked at typically
is the thresholded statistical image--
so after a certain z-score,
statistical relevance score,
one decides,
yes, this pixel is indeed activated,
it is responding to this particular task.
And so one thresholds out
the low statistical probability pixels
and leaves only the high probability
of statistical images.
And of course, it's much more interesting
to overlay this on anatomical imaging,
too see exactly where the activation is,
otherwise it appears just as a blob here--
we won't exactly know where that is.
So this is far more intuitive
to see where one exactly is.
So this is --
in neuroscience, a very important
imaging technique has become--
to study brain activation
in systems neuroscience.
It has, since the 90s,
essentially replaced
positron emission tomography
as a means to look at brain activation.
Now we've talked about susceptibility:
the difference between
diamagnetic oxy-hemoglobin
and paradiamagnetic deoxy-hemoglobin.
But we have also other
susceptibility effects to contend with.
And this is particularly
at the air-tissue interface,
because tissue is diamagnetic,
just like oxy-hemoglobin,
and the air--
molecular oxygen is paramagnetic.
We have seen this:
20% oxygen in the air produces
sufficient paramagnetism in the air,
compared to our bodies
which are essentially water
and therefore diamagnetic.
So we'll have the same kind of transition
between the paramagnetic species,
which is the air around us,
and the diamagnetic surrounding--
well, that's our body--
that creates changes in B_0 at delta B_0.
And so here is a gradient echo image
taken from the brain
at a TE that's roughly T_2 star.
And now we can see here
different black areas.
This is an image of the brain--
it's a cut like this, about here--
and can you guess
what these black areas correspond to?
Well, this area up here is the sinus--
we have here, behind the nose,
we have the sinuses air-filled cavity,
so it's filled with
paramagnetic molecular oxygen.
And here we have the ear canal
that is also filled with
paramagnetic oxygen.
And this creates, on this type of image,
it creates a fallout of the signal because
there's dephasing of the magnetization
due to the delta B_0.
Here's another example of an implant.
Implants, if their susceptibility
doesn't match that of the tissue,
they can produce the same effect.
One example is, for example, the TWOS.
So, how can we minimize these effects?
Here we notice that the signal
of the gradient echo
is proportional to e to the minus TE
over T_2 star.
So we can minimize these effects
by minimizing TE.
And if we do this,
then such a T_2 star-weighted image
will look like this--
this is a gradient echo with a short TE.
However, we actually want to have
T_2 weighting to obtain contrast--
one still wants to be able
to see tissue contrast.
So this solution is not applicable.
And here comes the second solution
that we will discuss now,
and that is to use SPIN ECHO,
which eliminates the effects
of static field homogeneity.
This is now coming up.