Okay, so spin echo,
and this is actually a consequence
of using two RF pulses.
Irving Hahn observed this
in the early '50s,
that when using two RF pulses,
then there is an echo observed
at twice the time difference,
and this happens in the presence
of a constant gradient.
You might ask, "In the 1950s,
they did not have gradients;
how come this was observed?"
Well, actually, at the time,
the quality of the magnets,
as they were used, was so poor
that they actually were like a...
The B0 really was not constant,
was not homogeneous,
so there was a big gradient
inside the magnet.
So we'll look here at time.
We'll now pretend that we've turned on
the gradient along Y, and it is always on.
So we'll just consider it is always on.
We'll have a 90° pulse.
This 90° pulse, the B1,
is applied along the X axis,
so it rotates the magnetization
onto the Y axis.
After a certain time,
we will apply a gradient,
an RF pulse of twice the duration,
so it's a 180° pulse,
but this time, around the Y axis.
This time here, we will call this TE/2,
and we're going to look
at what's happening
after another time TE/2.
And at this point, actually,
we will observe a spin echo.
So I'll take here the graphic
What happens with the magnetization
where, after the 90° pulse,
we have the magnetization flipped
into the transverse plane; it's along Y.
So it's a 90° pulse along X.
The magnetization is all in phase along Y.
And now we're going to look
at what's happening over time.
And we're going to look
at the magnetization vector
in complex space,
so the X magnetization component
is, for example, imaginary,
and the Y is real.
It doesn't really matter
what we're using here.
So we have magnetization here,
and I'll just draw four
random magnetizations.
They have different Larmor frequencies,
and/or different signs
of the Larmor frequency.
All in, of course,
the rotating reference frame.
So after the 90° pulse,
all the magnetization is collinear,
and now, what happens
during the time period is dephasing.
We'll have two vectors going to the left,
and two vectors going to the right,
and this is what's happening
during the first TE/2.
So it's dephasing, depending
on their position along Y,
depending on...
they will precess positive or negative,
and with different Larmor frequencies.
So after TE/2, we have
these four magnetization vectors,
that are spread out.
So this is a situation b
that we have here,
just before the 180° pulse.
They have spread out
between fast and slow.
And now, what we are going to do,
is we are going to apply
the 180° pulse along Y.
So we're going to apply
the RF pulse along the Y axis.
What does this do?
Did you see?
Let's do it again.
It flips the X component
of the magnetization.
An RF pulse that rotates around the Y axis
will leave the Y component intact.
We'll go back.
This is before the pulse.
And now, after the pulse,
the X components
have changed the sign for the vectors.
So orange and blue on the right,
red and green on the left,
And now, red and green are on the right,
and orange and blue on the left.
The Y components are the same,
but the X components
have changed the sign.
So this is the situation here,
just after the RF pulse now.
So if we look at what happens
with the RF pulse,
we only changed
the X component, the sign,
so that we have transverse magnetization,
at a certain position,
for any of the four magnetizations.
We only changed the X components,
so the X component changes sign.
So now, the phase.
And the phase can be the effect
of the gradient here,
so it's 𝛾 Gᵧ y TE/2.
So this is the duration,
times the gradient, times 𝛾,
times the position,
that gives us the total phase.
And now, what we are going to do,
we're going to look
what happens from now on.
And we remember blue and orange
move faster in this direction.
Red and green move in this direction.
So if I go back, red and green
moved in this direction.
Blue and orange moved in this direction.
So we're going to redo this,
because they are going to keep
their precession, orientation and speed,
and as we do that, going from c to d,
they continue to go
with the same precessional frequency,
but in the end,
all the magnetization vectors
will align themselves
and be collinear again,
and hence form an echo,
and this is called a spin echo.
So if we look at this in complex terms,
so we have the transverse magnetization,
we have this phase before the 180°,
so the influence
of the inhomogeneities here,
before the 180°.
The 180°, from this expression,
we can also write
the transverse mutation complex
as a transverse, times e ‾ⁱ ᵠ.
So it basically pretends
as if the RF pulse
does as if the inhomogeneity
that has been applied
is switching its sign here.
This is, if you want to make the link
to the gradient echo
that we've discussed last week.
And this week, then, your 180° pulse,
in this scheme here, acts
as if all the inhomogeneities
that are static here
are changing their sign in here.
Of course, they're not doing it,
but we can, to understand
how this echo is done
from this expression here,
we can pretend as if this was happening.
So it's a gedanken experiment.
So this, in terms of phase evolution,
it's as if the static gradient
was with the 180°, was flipping its sign.
Okay, so I want to revisit
the spin echo formation.
We had a graphical argument
why we have echo formation
with a 90°, 180° pulse,
and I want to take here
a more mathematical approach.
So we'll have the RF field.
We'll do a flip angle α.
We have a gradient along X.
And we'll look at the time point 1.
At the time point 1,
we just have Z magnetization,
so this is our magnetization vector.
Then we rotate it by α degrees.
So at this time point 2,
we have the magnetization
is M⒵ sin α, and M⒵ cos α.
And now we'll just consider the terms
of our components, so 0 and Mᵧ.
We just have Mᵧ magnetization,
because we're not concerned
with the effect of the flip angle here.
And now we'll look at just
the magnetization in a transverse plane,
which presents us now
with a magnetic field
that's given by 𝛾 Gₓ x.
So here's our gradient, Gₓ.
We have the echo time TE.
We'll look at time number 3.
So at time number 3, we have now
a precession of the magnetization,
so the X component increases with cosine,
the Y component with sine, or vice versa.
And so, we have expressed it here
that the Mᵧ component's given
by (cos ϕₓ) and (sin ϕₓ).
Now the 180° pulse inverts
the Y component of the magnetization,
so Mᵧ becomes -Mᵧ at this point.
And so, we can now write this
as Mᵧ [cos (ϕₓ) -sin (ϕₓ)],
or Mᵧ [(cos -ϕₓ) and sin (-ϕₓ)].
So this is essentially identical
to the effect of a negative gradient,
like we have argued last week,
and therefore, it produces an echo.
So the signal decays,
and in general, one considers
that the signal decays exponentially,
due to T₂ or T₂* relaxation.
And what is the link between the two?
So, if we have
the transverse magnetization here,
then we have T₂ --
that's the decay with T₂, --
and the decay with T₂*,
with a gradient echo, is faster.
T₂* is always shorter than T₂.
So if we use gradient echo for refocusing,
we have T₂* effects.
If we use spin echo--90°, 180°--
then we have the T₂ effect.
The two are always linked,
due to the imperfect [magnetic] field
in a given boxel--
this term is never exactly 0.
And this is unavoidable in practice,
since a magnetic field,
in an object of finite dimensions,
and complex anatomy, like we are,
The B0 that is in the body
is never perfectly homogeneous,
however, this unavoidable effect
is also exploited in BOLD fMRI
like we have just discussed.
So now we come
to the next imaging sequence,
at the last one that I want
to introduce here,
in terms of spin physics.
That's the spin echo sequence.
So we have RF excitation of the slice,
so this is just like we have had
for the gradient echo.
We have had the dephasing of the gradient,
the rephasing of the gradient,
and now we have the 180° pulse,
and here the gradient is just placed
symmetrically around the 180° pulse,
as we have seen
in the previous two slides,
symmetric placement of a static gradient
will produce no dephasing
of the magnetization
around a 180° pulse.
For the frequency encode gradient,
which here in this example,
we'll presume it's along x,
we have the dephaser.
It's now before the 180° pulse,
so now the dephaser has
the same amplitude, or the same sign,
as the frequency encode gradient,
unlike the gradient echo
when it was negative, beforehand,
this is now positive,
in the same direction
as the frequency encode gradient.
That has again to do
with the fact that we have
the 180° pulse in between.
So this area, and the placement
of the 180° pulses together,
that defines the echo time TE
for this sequence.
We have then the signal,
the echo that is being recorded,
and finally, we have
the phase encode gradient,
along Y in this particular example,
applied for example here,
which induces the phase encoding
for the second dimension.
This is, of course,
applied every TR seconds,
and so, this is what
the spin echo sequence looks like.
So very similar to the gradient echo,
the fact that the 180° pulse is here
changes the sign of the readout gradient,
and the signal is now influenced
by T₂, and not T₂*.
So, if we look now at the signal,
and the signal's proportional
to the transverse magnetization,
for proton density ρ,
this is proportional
to the equilibrium magnetization.
Now we'll just consider 90° pulses here,
so the transverse magnetization,
at this point,
is equal to Z magnetization
just before the RF pulse, times sin 90°.
At the time TE,
the transverse magnetization
is given by the transverse magnetization
here, times e‾ᵀᴱ/ᵀ₂ ,
and the Z magnetization
just before the pulse,
which is the last parameter
that we need to understand here,
is 1- e‾ᵀᴿ/ᵀ₁ * M₀.
Those are the longitudinal coherence
parameters for 90° pulse excitation
and you can look that up
in lectures 9 and 10,
when we dealt with this situation.
So this is, for this 90°/180° sequence,
the signal behavior.
So as we repeat this every TR seconds,
we have to acquire an image,
we have to repeat it every TR seconds
to produce a 2-D image.
So our signal now becomes a function
of the experimental parameter TE, TR.
It is proportional
to the proton density M₀ times e ‾...
this term here,
that's longitudinal coherence,
and this is the decay
of the signal, due to T₂,
for the spin echo sequence.
And we'll work now
through the basic contrasts.
How do we take from this equation here,
which has a number of terms,
how do we produce
the three basic contrasts,
proton density, T₁-weighted imaging,
and T₂-weighted imaging,
that I introduced at the beginning?