So how are the basic
MRI contrasts generated?
So we'll start out here
with proton density weighted MRI.
So for proton density,
just to have proton density,
one wants to minimize
the effects of the relaxation.
So take again the basic equation
here that we have.
The signal is a function of
TR, TE, and TR.
We want to minimize the effect of T1,
so the T1 here is for different tissues.
We don't want to have
the effect of T1 on the signal,
so essentially what this means is
one wants to measure at a TR
that is relatively long compared to T1.
So it's a long TR, in this example here,
it's three and a half seconds.
That will minimize
the effect of T1 differences
and let's pretend we've been good at that,
so we can, by measuring here,
neglect the effect of T1.
So we'll just say this term
here becomes one
and we'll neglect its effect.
So now we're left
with the exponential decay here.
This term here--
and I will look at the signal decaying
as a function of T2.
Again, we want to have
no influence of T2,
so to have no influence of T2
we want this term
to be essentially zero,
T over T2 is--
we can basically say TE zero
then T2 can be whatever it is,
E to the minus zero
is always one.
So the goal here is to minimize the TE,
so we'll use the TE as short as possible,
that minimizes the effect of T2
and so this term is gone
and in this case one has an image
that is essentially reflecting
the equilibrium magnetization,
which reflects--
as we have introduced in lecture eight--
which reflects a number
of spins in a voxel.
So we're imaging the number
of protons per voxel,
in this particular case,
this is the Parameter Rho.
So images with higher density,
spin density
like fat and CSF have
a higher image intensity,
however, if we consider
the contrast that this can bare,
we have to bare in mind that living tissue
typically has water content
that varies between 70 and 100%,
so that is not a gigantic
difference in contrast
between the different tissues,
so it's not a very good--
way to distinguish the tissues.
Nonetheless it's the physical approach,
we want to measure
the density of protons,
we're measuring a quantity,
number of protons per voxel.
This is for proton density MRI.
So second question:
how is T2 contrast produced now?
We'll take again
the same operational equation,
that's our signal
of our spinecall sequence
and now we are looking at the T1 effect.
We are now interested in producing
a contrast solely on the basis of T2
and so in this case for T2 weighting,
we don't want to have the effect of T1.
So we're going to use long TR
to have a reduced effect
of differences in T1.
We are interested in exploiting
just the effect of T2
and so, again here,
a three and a half seconds
we have a fairly long T1
to minimize the effect of T2
and let's say this is sufficiently long
that we are not measuring
the influence of different T1s
and so we can neglect this term
for the following.
Now to measure the effect of T2,
one does not want to measure at a short TE
because there they don't differentiate.
One wants to use a longer TE
to accentuate the differences in T2,
so that's this term here,
we want to accentuate
the differences here,
we pretended that this term is one--
and we don't need to consider it.
So we'll just use a particular T2
and now here the issue is:
what is the optimal TE
that we'll be using here
to accentuate the T2 differences?
Clearly if we use a TE = 0
we have no differentiation
of the T2 differences.
If TE is very long compared to T2
then we have no signal
and we cannot differentiate,
so there's somewhere
in between this an optimum
and this is done by--
the goal here is to find the echo time
at which the transverse magnetization
is most strongly effected
by the T2 differences.
To do this we use the same kind
of variational calculus
or air propagation calculus
that I introduced in lecture one
to obtain this solution.
So we'll do first--
and essentially what it is,
we'll calculate
the derivative of
the transverse magnetization
with respect to T2 that tells us
how much is the transverse magnetization
sensitive to changes in T2
and then we want to know
at what TE is this derivative maximum.
That's the approach.
I'm not going to go
through the details here.
I'm just going to give you the result.
The optimum TE here is --
at the value of T2.
If we have tissues with different T2,
so T2a and T2b then most likely
the optimum TE to use
for differentiating those two tissues
is the TE that's between the two T2 values
so somewhere in between.
So it's automatic --
A crucial requirement, if your T2s
are on the order of 100 milliseconds,
there's no point in measuring it
at 200 milliseconds,
so you set it to 100 milliseconds.
However, if you're in a situation
where the T2s are 50 milliseconds,
the 100 milliseconds are perhaps
not the optimum choice T2 weighting.
Okay, so in this case TE here
is 100 milliseconds.
Okay and finally,
let's discuss T1 weighting.
So we are looking, again,
at the operational equation here
for the spinecall sequence, 91/80 degree
but now we're not interested
in having the effect of T2.
So we want to minimize the effect of T2
and to do this, like with proton density
weighted imaging,
we want to have a TE that is
as short as possible.
So while using a short TE
to minimize the effects of T2,
so we'll use something here
like 20 milliseconds
in this particular example.
And then let's pretend
that we've been successful
and that our TE is sufficiently shorter,
we can largely neglect the effects of T2,
so we'll pretend that
this factor here is one
and we'll just grey it out here
and it's no longer observable.
So now we're interested in optimizing
or looking at this term here
and so the effect
to accentuate T1 effects,
one uses a relatively short TR.
If we use a TR that's
very long compared to T1,
we won't have an effect of T1.
If TR is very short compared to T1,
we're using 90/80 pulses here
then we have no signal.
So there's most likely
also here an optimum for the TR.
So the idea is to use a short TR
to maximize the differences
in longitudinal magnetization
as they are returning
to thermodynamic equilibrium,
so we have CSF here going slow
and we have white matter
going much faster.
So we'll have some differences here
and in this particular example
the TR chosen here is 600 milliseconds.
As a consequence, tissues with short T1
have a higher image intensity
because they are the ones
who are much further along
in their return
to thermodynamic equilibrium
than the tissues with long T1 such as CSF.
So CSF appears dark.
Now again we can ask
what is the good choice of TR.
That's the question.
And I'll give you the answer
because we have actually dealt
with this already in course nine,
and it's a similar calculation
that I introduced in lecture one,
and we just used on the preceding slide,
and the answer here is not surprising,
we're dealing with an exponential return,
that the optimal TR
to see T1 changes is at the TR = T1
We're not going to go
into much of the details here.
Let's illustrate in the following--
we'll illustrate
these different contrasts.
So here's a T1 weighted image of the head.
We can see the tongue here, the nose,
this is a sectional cross,
so here is the back of the head
where we have the little bump back here.
To give you an idea
what the TRs and Ts are,
I've put them in here,
so this is a TR of 510 milliseconds
and a TE of 40 milliseconds.
Here's now a density weighted,
proton density weighted image.
So it is a TR of four and a half seconds
and a TE of 50 milliseconds.
This is a cut through the head coronally,
so we can see the ventricles very bright,
the CSF bright
because this is 100% water.
It's not very bright but it's bright.
It's a greyish image.
And T2 weighted here now,
the TR is four and a half seconds
and the TE is 100 milliseconds.
We can see the liquid filled spaces,
the CSF, cerebral spinal fluid
has long T2.
There's no proteins,
no membranes in there or very little,
so T2 is long, they show up as bright.
And so notice here that we have the fluid,
cerebral spinal fluid here,
here, and here.
We have long T2 for cerebral spinal fluid
and long T1 but
the cerebral spinal fluid is darker T1
because the weighting there
favors the shorter T1 components
whereas a T2 weighted the imaging,
the weighting favors
of the long T2 components.
So this is, again,
a comparison of T1 and T2 images
in the brain of the same subject
we have tissue filled ventricles,
dark on T1 weighted,
and bright on the T2 weighted image.
Here's an example
of a T1 weighted image of the knee
and this is of the muscle,
also T1 weighted fat
typically has a shorter T1
compared to muscle,
so we get good contrast.
This is fat.
This is the bone.
And here we have the lymphoma
in this unfortunate patient,
so this is showing the fat signal.
So we have to remember for water
that a short T1
typically implies a short T2
and a long T1 implies a long T2.
So even though this is long T2
and this is long T1 the contrast,
the way it appears is different
and this is important
because the way
the contrast generate the MRI
changes the appearance
of the same signal or the same mechanism.
The second example on this is
T2 weighted imaging of MRI of cancer
and one of the features is
that cancer tissue has a long T2.
This is a metastases of colon carcinoma
here on this T2 weighted image
of the abdomen.
They are hyper intense,
very brightly visible.
Here's a T2 weighted image
of the brain tumor.
One can see the bright area here
but it shouldn't be
and there's even
some different within that,
that it looks peculiar.
Here's an example of --
a mouse with xenograft tumor,
so the tumor is implanted here
on the surface.
This is the T1 weighted image,
just to give you an idea
what the perimeters are
500 milliseconds TR, 14 milliseconds TE.
This is T2 weighted here and again,
TE is not 40 milliseconds,
TR is two seconds.
And on the T2 weighted image
one can see the xenograft tumor
is much harder to see
on the T1 weighted image,
so T2 weighted images are very often
used to detect tumor tissue.
Here's again, for a mouse implanted
with tumor baring cells,
non-tumor baring cells
in the T2 weighted image
clearly the tumor
that has grown is very visible.
And now on the T2 weighted image,
one has very often a contrast
that is not homogeneous for a tumor
and what is often done
is the application of contrast agents.
Contrast agents which depict the breakdown
of blood-brain barrier or vasculature
and this is now the same patient here,
T1 weighted image after
the application of a contrast agent.
And that bares now the question
on what are MRI contrast agents,
which we'll discuss next.