So how do contrast agents work for MRI?
Remember, we had discussed contrast agents
for computed tomography
that they change
the effectiveness of tissue
and therefore the linear continuation
coefficient.
And so how does a contrast agent MRI work?
And essentially we distinguish
two classes of contrast agents.
The one are those that act on T_1,
it's paramagnetic agents.
These paramagnetic agents--
the interaction as it is done
is very complex.
It's difficult to understand,
but essentially the picture
that we have is,
it is an interaction of the contrast agent
with surrounding water,
it's own molecular tumbling
and how fast the water diffuses
and how close the [lot] diffuses
close to that paramagnetic agent.
So, that's the molecular picture.
Phenomenologically,
the way they are scribed is that
one over T_1 in the presence
of the contrast agent
is given by one over T1 in the absence
plus a term that is
the contrast agent concentration
times this factor r_1,
and this factor r_1 is the relaxivity
of the this contrast agent on T_1.
It, in a way, describes what concentration
of contrast agent one needs
to generate a change in T_1.
So it is a phenomenological equation,
and we'll stick with this.
So, to give you an idea
for a typical parameter here,
if you take a contrast agent concentration
of a millimolar,
relaxivity of 3 per millimolar per second
and T_1 of the tissue
in the absence of the contrast agent
one second
then we can plug these numbers in,
and we'll actually calculate that
the T_1 in the presence of one millimolar
of this particular contrast agent
changes from one second
to 250 milliseconds
followed by a factor of four.
This is huge change in T_1.
Imagine you're doing your image
at a TR of 250 milliseconds,
the T_1 of one second,
this will create a very dark image
but then you're close here
to the optimal repetition time
at this point
and the image, the signal intensity,
will increase drastically.
So if we look at the signal
and now in this case we need to take
some T_1 weighted images
proportional to x magnetization,
so it's T_1 weighted.
We're looking at this expression here
and we have assumed here
for the experiment
that the TE is much shorter than T_2.
This is in the absence
of the contrast agent
and in the presence of the contrast agent,
the recovery to thermodynamic equilibrium
is much faster,
so if we measure at a relatively short TR
the signal becomes bright
in the presence of the contrast agent.
So this paramagnetic agents,
they lead to a brighter signal
of T_1 weighted images.
The other class of contrast agents
are paramagnetic
and susceptibility agents,
they act on T_2 and T_2*,
and the T`-2* agents are called
susceptibility agents.
So if we look here--
actually the expression that describes
the effect on T_2*
has the same expression
that we have for T_1,
it's the effect
of the contrast agent concentration
but now we have the proportionality here
is the relativity of r_2*
So what happens with the signal
as a function of TE,
the signal is proportional
to the transverse magnetization,
this is in the absence
of a contrast agent,
that's T_2* with a gradient angle
and in the presence of the contrast agent
we have T_2 for CA,
that's this T2** here,
a faster decay.
So, to give you an idea,
we take, again, a contrast agent
concentration of a millimolar
typical relaxivity of 50 per second
per millimolar
and a T_2* of 50 milliseconds.
We calculate now,
and with this concentration
we calculate that now the T_2*
is 14 milliseconds.
So we go from 50 milliseconds
to 14 milliseconds.
Now imagine what happens,
you're measuring at
a TE of 50 milliseconds,
now, the contrast agent comes in
at a concentration of a millimolar,
the T_2* is reduced to 14 milliseconds,
at the TE of 50 milliseconds
we no longer have a signal.
So while you were optimal
for the absence of a contrast agent,
now the signal has decayed.
And this basically leads
to a reduced signal
in the presence of the contrast agent
for the paramagnetic
and susceptibility agents
on T_2 or T_2* weighted images,
and that is because
we are measuring somewhere here,
at a more prolonged TE.
So, paramagnetic agents
produce a brighter signal
because they act on T_1,
paramagnetic and susceptibility agents
which act on T_2 and T_2*,
they produce reduced signal.
So let's look at some examples
of contrast agents.
First, some properties,
they are typically restricted to blood,
they are ideal to image vessels,
or leaky vessel walls, such as
what we see in tumors and inflammation.
So here we have an example
of the mouse vasculature.
We have an MRI of the mouse trunk,
so this is before
contrast agent application
and this is after,
we can see a change here,
clearly in the trunk
where the contrast agent has gone.
This is an example of brain;
there's a malignancy in the brain,
before the contrast
and after the contrast.
We can see difference we can see here
the ring that lights up,
this tells us that there is
a breakdown of blood/brain barrier,
which is typical for the tumoral edge,
still very well vascularized breakdown
of blood/brain barrier.
You can also see here
a lots of the vessels,
the bright stuff that lights up,
these are vessels that carry
the contrast agent.
So this is a predominant way
of enhancing leaky tissue.
Here is now an example
of contrast agent application--
before contrast and after the contrast,
and we see here the liver,
and the liver is now suddenly
becoming dark.
This is a susceptibility agent,
it's a T_2* agent,
that's iron oxide in this particular case,
and it has produced negative contrast.
So here we have positive contrast,
positive contrast, positive contrast,
and here this example
of a T-2-based paramagnetic
and susceptibility contrast agent
like iron oxide is producing
negative contrast,
so signal is reduced.
The second example
that I want to talk about
are intracellular contrast agents.
They are much harder.
One is manganese.
Manganese is paramagnetic,
it shortens the T_1.
It has the interesting feature
that is transported by calcium channels
and therefore shortens the T_1.
So this has been used
in, among others, in brain imaging.
This is an image of a rodent brain,
and we can see here very nicely
the structure of the hippocampus,
the different areas, CA3,
the dendrite areas, etc.
corresponding to the structure
seen in histology.
Prior to manganese,
this T_1-weighted image
look fairly uninteresting
after the application of manganese,
one can see a very substantial contrast
which reflects the activity,
the differential activity
of calcium channels
in the brain by region.
Now manganese as a contrast agent
is not used in humans,
it has issues of toxicity,
but in neuroscience it has become
a very interesting and promising tool
to look at fundamental
neuroscience questions
and also other questions.
Now, another thing
for intracellular contrast
is a bit particular
that I want to mention.
That is the imaging
of transplanted cells, or stem cells.
So, what is done here is,
for example, that the cells
that are injected
are preloaded with contrast agent.
So within them, they contain
the contrast agent
and then one looks
at the change in MRI signal
as the cells are being injected
and then migrate within the body.
And this is an example of
transplanted Langerhan cells in the liver,
so lung transplantation of islets
is a recent form of treatment
for Type I diabetes.
These islets are injected into the patient,
and one of the questions here was
that where do these transplanted islets
go in the body?
There has been a suspicion
that they would end up in the liver
and, indeed, what these images show here,
here are the islets, they show up as dark
because they are, in this case,
they were used
with a susceptibility contrast agent,
so a T_2 contrast agent or T_2*
and they are, indeed, showing up here
dislodged in the liver
where they are making their action
on the body
by helping to secrete insulin
and therefore reduce the effects
of Type I diabetes in these patients.