In this video we are going to talk about
facilities and infrastructure.
Let's start with facilities.
So when we talk about public facilities,
we are talking primarily of users.
The users, are the very reason,
for the existence of public facilities.
Without users, inevitably no facilities.
Then, to the user, who is the individual
who is going to use the facilities,
we must also add the service users.
Service users, take for example
a school, the user
is the student and and the service user
is the professor or the teacher.
Another example, at the hospital,
the doctor is the service user
and the patient is the user.
There, we differentiate between
these two types of people.
In countries where
the state is in deficit,
or where the state is struggling to pay,
all the facilities, we can use the users
to create a certain number of facilities.
So the users are going to help
financially, whether by
manual labor in the construction of
a certain number of facilities.
So, if we try to group
or classify facilities
we have several parameters
that may be considered.
We can classify facilities that are
either structuring facilities,
or accompanying facilities.
The structuring facilities are the
main facilities and the
accompanying facilities
are the small facilities that are not
necessarily essential to the whole
of the urban system.
Then we can also
group once again the facilities
depending on their size,
status or their function.
In regards to the planning,
we can plan.
We have, once again, three, four, five
levels, depending on the countries, but
we are going from state to neighborhood
as a general rule.
So we are moving from state
planning to regional,
of urban area, of municipality,
of neighborhood.
And its management is
exactly the same.
We can move from state to
neighborhood with, initially,
something very centralized
at the state level
and something totally decentralized,
that goes back to the local collective
and which is managed
by the neighborhood people themselves.
So when speaking of creating
facilities, we have, I would say
a current position.
Now is the time, of course, and then
it's the variable which is the number
of people or the percentage,
we can do both, of the population which
has access to the base facilities.
So the reality is almost that and then
we always have the same number
who has access to these facilities.
On the other hand, the population
increases like this.
So that's what makes it
so that the gap is so large and that
there are less and less
people as we go along, who have
access to the facilities.
The objective, of course, is one
where we would have here almost
a contact point between on one hand
people that have access to facilities
in this low area and the increase
in population.
So the objective would be that
everyone has access to the facilities
in a sustainable manner.
The reality is unfortunately
quite the opposite,
it's that we have facilities where
people arrive casually,
increased thanks to a certain
number of programs but the population,
like in the first diagram,
is always expanding.
So the final gap here,
x is a little bit smaller
than in the current situation but
the level of service, the number of people
who have access to the facilities remains
extremely low compared
to what it should be.
So there, basically, between
the current situation,
and the objectives, we have a
real situation and we realize
that the population increase is such that
we would need a huge adjustment
in terms of facilities, equip the
neighborhoods, equip the areas
and since these facilities
are extremely expensive,
it is very unlikely for us
to be able to adjust
and that we would, in the next
few years, find ourselves
in the second situation which is
the situation of the objective.
Hence the problem, both of facilities and
of the demand of facilities.
So the demand increases.
Why?
Because, we saw it earlier, there is
a population increase.
So this absolute number, the increase, if
I take water for example,
the number of liters per person, we are
no longer talking about facilities.
We are already in the realm of
infrastructure, we'll talk it about later
but for my demonstration,
water is the perfect example.
We see that with the number of people
increasing, the quantity of water that
I have to put at their disposition will
be larger- but we also know that with time,
the consumption, the number of liters
of clean water per person, is increasing.
So I have this double increase
and it's exactly
the same thing with the facilities.
We are dealing at once
with a population that increases
so a need for health centers,
a need for hospitals that increases,
and at the same time, the number
of consultations increases also.
So we have greater tendency
to go more and more,
of course according to its means, but
more and more at the doctor's office.
So we have this double increase
making it so that the facility
has to respond to this.
And taking into account the scarce
resources, at the city level,
at the state level, at the local
collective level, we finally have the gap
that is growing between people
who have access to these facilities and
the people who have no access
at all to these facilities.
Let's move on now to infrastructures.
So we define infrastructures as
being the necessary factors in the
functioning of the urban area.
So the urban infrastructure is
for the urban system, for
the functioning of it.
So we can have at both buildings,
warehouses, pipelines, these
kinds of things.
All this helps with the functioning of it.
Let's take the example of aviation.
The infrastructure is the airport.
It helps in the functioning
of the aerial system.
We don't need to have
in the open sky
other types of infrastructures
for the planes.
But in order for the plan to take off
and land we need infrastructure.
This helps the system.
It is the same with water,
with electricity, with all these
types of networks.
Also we have to take a look at, in the
broad sense, the term infrastructure.
This infrastructure is finally
also a question
of services, of the quality of services.
For the infrastructure, in order for
the water infrastructure to work,
we have both pipelines
but also standpipe managers
people who will read the meters
in your home and ultimately
it requires in any case
a user like for the facilities.
Here also the user becomes,
I would say the reference point
of the infrastructure as he was
that of the facility.
So we are going to see exactly what
are the facilities,
what is the minimum facility that would
allow the urban system to function.
Above all, it's not really a facility
but we have to provide it
for the memory because
it's important, it needs
available land.
At the same time to create facilities
but also to place users.
So without available land, there is
no possible urbanization.
Then, there need to be means
of transportation, water systems,
water drainage, household waste
drainage, of electricity,
of telephone and internet, of course,
more and more.
So, available land.
We have already indicated it a little bit.
It is necessary to create
these infrastructures.
Of course available land
is also needed
so that the users can settle, can live.
But without land, there
are great difficulties.
Sometimes, they are not available and
people are going to be displaced to put up
infrastructure but it's the essential
condition, the basic condition
that there be lands available on which
infrastructure can be created.
We are talking about means of
transportation but
we are more on the topic
of road infrastructure,
we are talking about roads and we see
that, in theory, in the city centers and
the major roadways, the roads are
asphalted and then the farther we get
from the major roadways, closer to the
neighborhoods, the less asphalted the roads.
So the road between cities is extremely
important as it allows
easier connections or not but also
in the very interior
of the urban perimeter.
It's extremely important for
the large roadways
to have a certain number
of asphalted roads.
So these asphalted roads, are
in theory the national roads
which means that each area from
the main city,
goes in every direction in a particular
area, in another city.
Meaning that since the only
asphalted roads are
the national roads, we have a development
like this, we have to with each
national road that starts along the road.
It is difficult to have a compact
urbanization, when we have roadways
that develop and urbanization in general
that develops around or along
the asphalted roads.
Then, we have water systems for clean
water, the main urban infrastructure.
It's more important to have systems
for water than for roads.
Often it's the opposite
of what is financed.
But it is extremely important and
we can see that
there is an entire system
that is organized
since there are water mains that reach
the neighborhoods, then,
often we have
standpipes with operators, with people
that will bring it, house by house,
in large metallic barrels of water.
So there is a whole system
and an entire economy that is developing
around clean water.
Drainage of waste water.
It's often the poor relative
of the infrastructure.
We have both clear water
and waste water.
It's very rare to have waste water
drainage systems that work.
They can perhaps be found in city centers
but the farther we get
from the suburbs, the more these
are individual systems
on the plot which are septic tanks
that are emptied
from time to time, or rather, no
system at all for the drainage
of waste water and waste, in particular
fecal waste, remains on the plot.
Drainage of household waste.
The same phenomenon as for the
waste water drainage.
Certain systems are in place but
don't necessarily reach
all of the neighborhoods and
we see here and there
entire garbage dumps, since people
have to store it not on their own plot
in the public space, but store the
garbage in front of their house.
We then have the power grid network.
So there is a paradox when it comes to
the power grid network,
some consider it a luxury.
Indeed we can live without electricity
it's more difficult to live without water.
However electricity allows,
for the development
of crafts or of business,
some refrigerators, some electrical
appliances that can operate and can
allow for the development of an activity.
The paradox is that it is a luxury
but it is the network
that without a doubt costs
the least to put in place.
Since it is just some wires and
some posts
comparing it to a road network, comparing
it to a water systems network,
which are the networks in the latter,
that are buried
therefore are extremely
expensive to put in place.
The power grid system is
something that is relatively superficial.
However, the costs of electricity,
the costs of production are such
that it's not necessarily what will be
put in place first in a neighborhood.
Generally, we go from the road, then
the waterways, then electricity.
Good.
We should without a doubt go
from waterways first,
to the road next and then why not,
to electricity.
Then it's about asking questions
about the telephone network really,
there is a cabled network that
some countries still have,
almost everywhere.
Today's question: with the
development of the cellphone,
is it still useful to foresee telephone
networks in neighborhoods?
So this shows quite well that the
standards that will be
put in place, the level of facilities,
can change with time.
There are things that
are more immutable
than others but in the case of
the telephone in particular
some have never had access to cabling,
to telephone networks
and today have access to
communication via the cellphone.
The question will be with the Internet.
In most of the African cities, they
have gone directly to a WiFi network
to a wireless network, rather
than imagine
that one day there was going to be cabling
and the existing telephone networks
were going to be used perhaps,
in particular for the Internet.
So a certain number could be cabled
but in the majority of cases
we realized that maybe
it's a WiFi network
that is the most adapted to the
situation of African cities today.
So there are some synthesis factors.
First about the costs.
Electric networks cost little, the road
network is extremely expensive.
Arbitration must be conducted when
there is an available sum to supply,
in a general sense,
to service a neighborhood
or a new subdivision, there must be
questions asked about the costs
of the various networks.
There are two types of networks,
there are those from which it is possible
to obtain cost-recovery.
It is the power grid network since
electricity will have fees charged,
it's the water network since it will be
be charged by the liter or by cubic meter.
On the other hand, when it comes
to waste water drainage,
household waste, it's extremely difficult
since the mechanisms possible for
cost-recovery have not yet been found,
in particular for waste water drainage.
Finally, there is sometimes a distinction
to be made between what seems to us,
I spoke of water
earlier, which seems to me
totally legitimate and what the
perception of the people.
The rural populations that
arrive to the city
don't have the idea that
the water network,
the waterways of clean water
are a priority.
They are used to doing otherwise,
in particular, going to the well, finding
a variety of ways
but definitely not having a faucet by
which clean water can be obtained.
It's not their priority, for the
rural people that arrive.
However, we have to have an arbitration,
because we know there is a balance
between the level of facility, between
a certain number of facilities
and infrastructure and public
health in particular.
So then it is possible to organize
these various factors
in the form of a grid, that we call
a needs grid.
Very quickly, we have here the
infrastructure, for example
water supply, roads, etc.
And on the other hand we have
the basic needs, the first level,
second, third, fourth,
we can continue like this depending
on the level of service desired
So I'm going to take the example
here of water.
It's a number, liters per person, per day.
Some lenders give us 30, others 25,
in reality we often have less than
25 liters of water per day and per person.
So we could imagine that the first level
is 50 liters, the second 100 liters
and the third 400.
Or rather, we can imagine that the first
is 30 since we started below 25,
then we are at 40 and the maximum
at the third level is 50.
So all of this, this question,
it must be treated according
to the context.
All cities do not have the
exact access to water
and finally, this sum at the third level
here, the quantity of maximum water
has to depend on the geographical
context, morphological of course ,
on the possibility of having or not
having water for the residents.
In the Sahel or Sahara, we will not have
the same number here as
in the heart of
tropical areas, this seems
extremely obvious.
So we can define a certain
number of levels.
Let's take five levels and then it is
possible to say to what they
correspond, what type of work, what type
of services correspond to what level.
So for the first level,
we are talking about basic things.
This just means clearing the brush
and limiting the plots.
Second level.
Roadways profile, perhaps of the laterite,
perhaps lightly of a large paved highway
the edges of waterways that are coming,
very little at the beginning and the
possibility of an electricity supply
for the community needs.
Third level, the highway network,
maybe a little bit more paved.
We can imagine having roadsides,
sanitation facilities, in any case,
ditches that allow rainwater to drain.
In terms of water,
either we develop the standpipes,
or we can imagine
a clean water network and maybe electrical
that before used to serve only to the
supply of public facilities,
may now also be used for public lighting.
Fourth level.
The highway network, we increase
the amount of asphalted highways
and the sanitation is not much more
than ditches that are dug
in the ground, but have a particular
profile and are hard-surfaced.
Finally, the fifth level.
It is of course, the previous level plus
electricity issues where we can
imagine the possibilities
of individual connections to the plot
as well as water systems
or we can imagine
for all the plots this time a possibility
of individual connection.
So there we have quickly examined
the facilities and infrastructures.
What is important to remember is that
we have various
levels of facilities that are various
levels of services
that are given to the population,
that these facilities,
that these infrastructure have a cost,
have a construction cost.
To build a network has a cost.
But they also have management costs as
well, managing the network on a
daily basis has a cost when it needs to be
renovated years later, there is also a cost
behind this which is the cost of
updating the infrastructures.
So three types of costs
must be considered.
In general, only the construction cost
is taken into account
and then what happens doesn't
matter very much.
If we want to create long-term
sustainable planning,
it's not only the construction cost that
has to be taken into account but
the operating cost also,
finally the cost of updating
these infrastructures.