Welcome to our video dedicated
to public spaces.
We are going to take a
look at space issues.
We are going to see
how to define them.
We are going to see the difference between
a public space and public spaces.
And then we will show examples.
The first is the construction
of a public space
in the N'Djamena city center.
The second,
is a method of capturing
public space.
A photographic method that allows
to see modifications, changes
throughout the day, that occur before
our eyes, in the public space.
How to define public space?
Several solutions.
We can define it by its issues, we will
see what the issues are later.
We can define it by its atmosphere.
We can define it by its players.
But we can also define it
by its context, its form or
rather by its connection between what
is public and what is private.
The big themes of public space,
the issues, the themes that then
become issues.
The first, without a doubt,
the most important maybe,
is the question of infrastructures.
Then, there is the question of public
or private transportation plus mobility.
The environmental question
is fundamental.
Occupation versus management
of the space.
The question of built space.
There are a certain number of
public spaces that are
built spaces, I'm thinking
specifically of markets.
The street, is also a resource.
People live off the street
and by the street.
But public space can be
a space of protest, a space
where a certain number
of civil or civic activities occur.
Then, public space is
a violent space, be it real or assumed.
And finally, it's a daily life space
where we pass by, where we stop,
where we discuss.
These are the big themes of
public space as we define them.
With all these big themes,
we combine about all the
questions linked to public spaces.
So, should we say public space
or public spaces?
The distinction is made by Thierry Paquot,
which is very useful here.
Public spaces is when we are
talking about something physical,
it's the network support,
the question of
the organization of architecture,
the question of urban design.
But we understand that
the public spaces
it's the network of roadways,
of spaces.
And we have on the other hand,
public space
which is the political space,
as it is defined by Habermas.
It is connected with political sciences,
the social sciences here,
and more with architecture,
as we saw earlier.
And it's the space of politics,
therefore the space of protest.
There it is.
Between the public space which is
an immaterial space,
space of the politic of protest and
public spaces which are the material
and spatial network of
streets and places.
We have a cursor, like this, which
shifts more to one side, or more
so to the other with a possible
superposition in the middle,
at once of a space of protest which
would be a real and physical space.
And the example we most
often have in mind
for this type of things is La Sorbonne
in Abidjan which was
in any case before the crisis,
the perfect place of protest
or at least of a part of the protest.
Of course, there was only part
of the population that came out.
But where, freely, more or less
freely, we are going to
discuss about political questions,
about societal questions.
And then at the same time,
this space is quite real,
since it's a public space
where people can go.
So we have at the same time
the question of the immaterial
of protests and the question of
the public material space.
So it's for this as well
as to facilitate,
we go from public space
to public spaces.
So when we speak of public space
or of public spaces, we have
seen the difference.
We must talk about public domain.
It's often the network, of roadways
and places that belong to
their local collectives.
Okay.
And then there are the spaces
open to the public.
Spaces that can be private but
are considered
public spaces since everyone
can have access.
It's the case, in particular
of big private markets.
So, we must make the clear distinction
between the virtual space of protest,
the public space.
Public spaces which are the network
of streets, of spaces, that are
physically there.
The public domain which is really,
which corresponds to the land title
and the spaces which
are open to the public,
but which are not.
These are the private spaces.
During our research we have
been able to put forth
a certain number of structuring
factors of space.
I am referring to the bibliography and
the book "The West-African City".
But like its thesis, we have been able to
put forth that there are
three structuring factors.
The first, is the question of climate.
The fact that we are in
a warm and humid climate
where the hot and dry considerably
influence what we are
going to find and the way in which people
are going to move in the public space.
The second idea in our synthesis,
is that public spaces
are first and foremost
the place of the populace.
It is here that the majority
of the poor live.
There is a clear division
between rich and poor
in the public space, and the public space
is first and foremost the place
for the poorest population.
The rich only pass through,
most of the time by car.
Finally, the third structuring element,
is the question of informality.
The informality which structures
a part of the public space, since
a part of social practices that take place
here are of an exclusive domain
of formality or informality.
Here we had the example, earlier, between
public space and public spaces
of La Sorbonne in Abidjan.
Another image, is it really a public space?
A kind of no man's land
which is in fact a road.
I leave it an open question.
In central Dakar, we see
that if we focus on our themes,
we have at the same time
questions about resources, people live,
conduct business in these streets and
at the same time questions about
transportation in this image.
The environment, the public space
is also a space of waste storage
but also a place of storage of any kind.
Another example where finally
there is a sort of
privatization of public space
since the merchant
and the carpet manufacturer are
drying them out in full sun,
in the street and appropriates
the available space.
Which makes it so that the cars
can no longer pass by.
So it's a very clear way here
to appropriate a public space.
Finally, public space is also
to do sports: soccer or
its reduced version.
We are going to see now the
development of a public space
a big square in the center of N'Djamena.
Thanks to Google and the map history,
we can go back like this,
from 2004 to 2011, and we are
going to gradually see
the changes that happened in
the creation of public spaces.
So there is no value judgement
about what has been done.
Is it good, not good?
I just want to show the process
that is in motion when
public spaces are created in places
which are already urbanized.
It takes places gently.
Here we are in 2008, 2009, 2010
also in 2010, some destruction, and
here we have a space that takes
the whole of the homes
that we had before.
We finish with this image.
Maybe if we go on Google today,
there will be the following.
I leave you with the care
to go and see it.
We are in N'Djamena, Tchad.
And we now going to see an example
from the same work which I was
talking about earlier,
"The West-African City"
where a method of capturing
public space was developed.
A method which allows us to see
the daily changes that happen
in the public space.
For this we have placed our camera
and we have taken a photo throughout
the day of a public space.
We are in Nouakchott, an
ordinary downtown street
and every 30 minutes, we took a photo.
So we can see the movements
which take place throughout the day.
All these movements allowed us to evaluate
the number of men and women.
For example, if I take this x axis here,
we have the time or the hours
from early in the morning
until late in the evening.
And here we have the number
of men and women.
So what interests us, is not
the exact number
since it largely depends on the
framing that we do.
What interests us, is the balance
of men and women.
And we see that there are very,
very few women
and that we don't see them
the whole day.
They are there at precise hours.
We can do the same thing
with the children.
We can do the same thing with vehicles.
Another example, another framing
in another village.
We see here that the presence of
women is much more important,
and that the women are
present the whole day.
This allows to see the rhythm of
the city, at which time the city awakens,
at which time we have the most people
walking in the public space.
This allows us to quantify a
certain number of things.
Another example, without any comments.
Another street in Nouakchott,
early in the morning, a seller.
Look carefully at the right hand side of
your screen, what is going to happen.
There. At a certain time, one seeks
protection from the sun.
At certain hours, there is no one
in the street.
At other hours, we see many cars.
And we see, throughout the day,
the sale of fruits, of bananas.
We see the bananas disappear gradually
as the buyers arrive in this tore.
There, very quickly described, some
themes of public spaces,
some structuring elements, the creation
of a public space, a solid example
N'Djamena, and a method of research
which allows the capturing like this,
of the public space
throughout the day.