Settlements - African Cities:
Intro. to Urban Planning (Jérome Chenal)
Hello, our video today-settlement.
Now settlement is not housing.
It's not just a dwelling,
a house, a shack.
Settlement has a broader sense.
Settlement is a way of organizing
human population.
There is housing, the place
where one lives,
and also all of its annexes,
the small alleys which service it,
the spaces in front of the house,
or even its gardens.
All of these things make up
the settlement.
So, in certain urban neighborhoods,
we have situations where
housing is poorly represented,
is largely minoritized, in relation to
the overall system of the settlement.
But one thing is certain,
which is that, globally,
when we speak of settlement
in African cities, we are generally
speaking of housing.
The idea is confused, I would argue,
by the classic definition of settlement,
which we must consider in
a much broader sense.
It is thus possible
to classify settlement
an individual settlement,
a residential settlement.
There are many ways to classify it.
But, generally, what is most important
is how we formulate the basis
for a typology of settlement, which is
on its mode of production.
Now, by mode of production we do not
mean solely the type of construction,
or solely its economics, but rather
the whole of these interventions.
We can find ourselves at the same time
on economic, social, or technical levels.
And we define this as the mode
of production of settlement.
This mode of production encompasses
all of the interventions
which, in one way or another,
modify or create a settlement.
In some ways this is
a very restrictive definition,
but it is at the same time
a vast one,
for we find ourselves on
extremely different levels
when it comes to levels of intervention.
In addition, all of these interventions
can evolve with time.
So, the one who begins
a settlement project
may not necessarily be the one
who will ultimately use it.
So in these modes of production
there are two major types:
the planned settlement,
that of long ago,
the managed settlement,
and the working-class settlement.
The planned settlement is one
of large complexes, extensive rules,
where the state builds a certain number
of housing units, of housing projects,
developments on vast tracts of land.
The managed settlement is one where
it is the private sector who is given
the responsibility for its construction
but within the relatively strict
guidelines provided by the State.
And then we have working-class
settlements,
where there are no rules, where
the informal is given the upper hand,
and the people do more or less
as they choose.
I say more or less, because with
working-class settlements there are,
if the code is not strictly
administered by the state,
within working-class settlements
there are commonly accepted rules,
which are those of the community,
whether in terms of construction,
those of implantation,
or lifestyle rules between neighbors.
So it is not that there are no rules,
but simply that these are
community-based rather than
managed either by the state
or by local authorities.
Thus there are different
parties involved in
the production modes of the settlement,
and these are numerous.
The list is not necessarily exhaustive,
but we can include the community,
of course the state and local authorities,
or even private organizations.
There may also be a developer,
whether public or private.
Likewise, there may be investors,
technicians, the architect
or design office, builders and
of course the construction company,
laborers, inhabitants, managers.
These are some of those who form part
of these modes of production.
Naturally there is one of greater
importance than the rest,
and that is the inhabitant, because
this is the final recipient,
the one for whom
the settlement was created.
So before moving on to
the production chains
of these various participants,
two things.
The fewer there are, the greater
the ease of the process.
This seems evident.
And when speaking of settlements,
the question of financing
becomes, in principal, central.
There must be, on the one hand,
a source of funding.
The beneficiary must be financially able
to purchase their home,
Whether via a loan, or in cash,
all possibilities exist.
But he must have sufficient financial
autonomy to secure housing.
Now, when we speak of
modes of production,
we must include the production chain
of the settlement.
This is a chain made up
of four main links.
The first is public policy as it
pertains to the settlement.
So national policy is
the first link of our chain.
Next is local planning,
the second link.
The third link is property development.
The fourth link, real estate.
We see that we pass
from a national level
to one strictly local down to
the parcel, to real estate.
Now let's return to these four links.
The first link, the national level,
state level, public policy.
What are the problems here? Primarily
it is the question of property.
The question of property is dual;
it is two-fold problem.
On the one hand, land allocation
in no way corresponds to demand.
We distribute far more plots of land
than are needed
This is the first problem.
The second problem is that
it is extremely difficult,
and this in most countries,
to secure a land title.
One can secure titles of occupancy,
but the definitive land title,
which is deposited with the notary,
filed and paid for,
is extremely difficult to obtain.
These then are two problems
inherent in land ownership.
But there is also another problem,
which is a weak banking system.
Indeed, if you do not have
a banking system
which allows one to borrow money,
it will be extremely difficult
for a section of the population
to obtain housing.
And because of this, many prefer
land speculation to property ownership,
and loans within the banking market
in African cities are very expensive.
Mortgage rates are very high,
which in no way encourages
mortgage lending.
Behind this is, without a doubt,
a cultural element as well as
a lack of confidence in and use of
the banking system.
Because of this many prefer to use
other systems, traditional systems,
to finance their housing,
rather than turn to a bank.
We've seen the two principal problems
of land-ownership, the banking system.
This means that certain
solutions can be found
in an overhaul of
the land-ownership system,
an end, surely, to
the level of speculation.
Perhaps this is wishful thinking.
To put in place such a system
is extremely difficult, agreed.
But at any given moment
we may be obligated to rethink
the entire land-ownership system,
because it won't be possible to sustain,
decade after decade,
to put on the market land parcels,
and more land parcels,
and more land parcels, etc.
It's impossible.
So it must be redefined, made reasonable,
with a review of all the processes
which allow one to secure a land title.
At the same time, the state clearly
must invest in the financing of housing,
particularly that designated
for its poorest inhabitants.
Finally, the banking system
must be developed,
mortgage rates lowered, with the state
as guarantor of this system.
To continue, we were on the state level,
so let's go to the city level.
Three principal problems.
The first is the total lack of control
in urban development.
We cannot get a handle
on this development,
despite existing documents.
This is the main goal of our course,
to explore how we can formulate
documents which would,
in fact, create a framework
for urban development.
The second problem is
the chronic underestimation
of the number of housing units
which should be on the market.
When the number is always
underestimated, so is the need.
Third, we have public authorities,
who have little to do with settlements.
There was a long period in which
international sources of funding,
bilateral or multilateral,
financed settlement programs.
This has been abandoned,
and now financing is only available,
with few exceptions, for
large settlement programs.
Communities do not have the means
to finance themselves,
and suddenly there is no more
financing available for settlements.
This is without doubt one of the main
objectives for urban development.
Once again, the solution is
to counteract these problems
or to put in place systems which enable
the documentation of urban planning,
and to utilize these documents.
These documents should be made
with, by and for the community.
The final beneficiary must be able to
contribute his or her advice about
the urban planning document.
And this document of urban planning
must be reinforced,
clearly on a legal level, and must
be enforceable against third parties.
For now, as we've seen,
there are zoning, land allocation
and land-use plans,
which are enforceable
against third parties.
The private should be
subject to the same.
The blueprints, master plans, the SDAU,
do not have the force of the law
when it comes to private,
only public administration.
This, then, is our second level.
This is the level of the city.
Now we'll go down to
the level of land-use.
The level of land-use is
that of development.
There still, we have created a system
which develops the parcel or plot,
with the sole purpose is speculation.
There is no concern for
urban quality behind this.
It is no production calendar
behind the development
of these land parcels.
They are created one by one
without a vision of the whole,
without consideration of the needs
or the parcel demands of
the final beneficiaries, but instead
according to administrations
who create parcels here and there,
with very good or bad reasoning.
We won't go there.
But one thing is clear, and that is that
we have the obligation
to counteract this problem,
to provide quality housing developments.
To ensure that quality housing
is developed in places
earmarked for future urban expansion.
We have a global plan which
would be a master plan,
which defines zones prioritized
for urban development,
and these housing developments
must be built, exactly and strictly
in zones defined by
the general document.
This seems relatively simple,
when put like this
But the examples we have
where this has been working
can be counted on one hand,
of this I'm very positive.
Finally, there remains one level,
the last link, that of the parcel,
which is that of real-estate development.
One can be one's own promoter,
or have a company hired to do
real-estate promotion.
But we are very much
at the level of the parcel,
and on this level there are
two principal problems.
The problem is the relationship
with businesses.
It is no longer, for the
most part, in most cities,
about businesses, but rather
about workers who do masonry.
Or of businesses already formed,
teams, totally informal,
who do not have the minimum of
knowledge or competency
required for the technical
aspects of building,
They are without doubt
full of good intention,
but do not have the skills and
techniques needed for building,
which makes the quality
of construction often unreliable.
Another critical problem
with real-estate promotion
is the price fluctuation
of material costs.
A ton of cement can very quickly
double the cost of concrete blocks.
If you begin with one price, and
a few months later it has doubled,
this poses problems; it poses
financing problems, surely.
These price fluctuations of materials
which has never been
stabilized on a state level,
presents problems even on
a neighborhood level.
As the price increases, as the price
of a ton of cement increases
we see a halt, in some neighborhoods,
of nearly all construction.
In fact, when we speak of housing,
we are often speaking of social housing.
Why? Because housing for those
who are relatively well off,
or middle class, poses few problems
when compared to the number
of poor who need housing.
And to provide housing for the poorest,
one needs an intervention by
the state, or by other funders.
But without intervention
from the outside,
the only real-estate promotion
by the poorest population,
for the poorest of the population,
is extremely difficult, and leads to
the development of slums.
If we want to have an increase
in construction quality,
we must return to these programs,
and to obligatory state aid.
This plan is an extremely easy one.
We finally have standards.
These are the norms, the standards
of construction.
The standards in housing
are going down, for example.
And then here, whether in
dollars or euros,
it is the cost of the standard norm.
And then, this is the income
of the population.
We see that between
this standard, this norm,
and income, there is
a gap, a differential,
and this differential should
be taken into account,
by public authorities.
This differential, is aid to
the most modest households.
There are two possibilities
to fill this gap.
There is the possibility
of offering assistance,
or assisting those who ask for it.
To offer assistance means
to price land modestly.
We can develop the land
without being paid for it.
We can build at moderate prices.
This is what will go on the market.
One can offer aid as materials or land.
Aid on demand is based on a system
of borrowing and spending.
On assists with borrowing, for example,
with a 0% financing, or lowered rates,
with special duration,
or we put in place a system of savings.
We can imagine that
the baseline here is lower
than normal, but we have
these two possibilities.
There is supply, and there is demand.
So with housing programs,
we must find out
where we stand, whether on
the side of supply or demand,
or if we try, in an integral manner,
to blend these two forms of assistance,
to balance at the same time
supply and demand.
Surely, by linking together the two,
we can achieve results
which are no doubt better,
and much quicker,
than aid offered based only
on supply or on demand.
We've touched briefly on
the question of settlements,
the four links in the production
of settlements,
from the state level,
to that of the land parcel.
And then, some considerations
on aid to the poorest
because this is the crux
when it comes to settlements.
It is surely settlements, for those
populations with the lowest incomes
where we must succeed
for urban integration.