In our video, the issue of property.
First, we are going to mention tradition.
Customary land law.
In the customary norm of land law,
the land belongs to the collective.
There is a land chief who distributes
land, but under no circumstances
can the land be privatized,
so it belongs to everyone.
In this state of things, man
is but an usufructuary.
There is no financial transaction,
He cannot buy or sell but he
can benefit from the land.
It was the customary norm, and
when the colonial administration
imposed its rules
land administration was centralized,
it was no longer the land chief but
the colonial administration who was
the owner of all of these lands.
It's the administration that is then
going to distribute, give titles.
So we went from a collective ownership to
a private ownership, and we obviously
go from community management to
centralized management.
Where once there was a
customary occupation
of land and then colonial
property provisions,
we have today a property use system
that is extremely diverse.
We have both private property but also
registered lease, lease in the form
of a cooperative,
there are still customary occupations
and then there is a whole intermediate
that goes from property and
the most strict title
to land to the totally
informal occupation with
between the two, all of these
intermediate phases that exist.
We are not going to detail the board,
it's in the attached documents, it's
up to you to take the time,
for those who wish, to look
carefully at what it contains.
So when we discuss land legislation
We must ask only one question,
to whom does land belong to?
It can be to the state,
the collective or to a private entity.
It's to whom does it belong, so we
are discussing the right,
who holds the right poses three problems:
the question of tenure,
the question of identification and
the question of recognition.
It's not simply a matter of
being an owner, it's also
about the others knowing
that you are the owner.
It must also be registered.
I must also be able to keep
my property rights
throughout the years and not have
someone else appropriate them.
This seems in a certain context
extremely strange to speak of
this type of thing, but in
the African cities
this is an everyday problem.
Land tenure.
I have a property, how will I be
able to keep my property
as long as possible?
Now, some findings on real estate,
so in Sub-Saharan Africa we have a
strong horizontal growth.
Why?
Because real estate, is less
expensive than multi-floor buildings.
At the same time, there is a process
of decentralization that means
that the territory has to be cut up
and we realize that we have new
perimeters of intervention, that each
collective has a new perimeter
with a complete redefinition
of property rights.
There is a significant retreat of
the state, which is slowly disengaging,
in regards to rights, not necessarily
in regards to finance, we have owners,
who have their piece to say,
not only about the role of the
state and public collectives,
but the final owner, the final user,
whether owner or not,
of the remainder, is an important
element of the equation.
There is an extremely difficult
ground management,
we notice that even though
the customary law
has been abandoned in the
urban perimeters for
decades now, it still endures today,
if we begin the story of property in
Douala we realize that even today
one of the biggest problems is
the issue of customary law.
We have territory development that
is problematic, why problematic?
Because, really, no one is interested,
we take themes, we take the issues
in a completely different way
however we don't identify them
as being territory development issues.
So there it is, when we are
discussing property.
We have looked at some issues,
that we are unable to manage.
So this means that urban sprawl
continues, this means
that the city develops without there
being a strict management on
behalf of the public collectives
or of the state on the ground
and as a result, we must ask ourselves
the question: What to do about it?
Should we anticipate, or
should we adjust?
Here we are looking at a case study, on
a hypothesis, where you can choose.
Anticipation is extremely difficult,
there are few examples where this works.
We are almost always adjusting.
Why?
Because the social practices,
because the demand, because
the demographic pressure
are in every case much more rapid
and much stronger than the reaction
of the administration, be it
centralized or decentralized.
So we are unable to anticipate things,
and we are constantly taking
adjustment measures, in any case,
at the property level.
The urban slum, the poor
neighborhoods are an
extremely striking example of these
thematics, that is to say
that we let it happen, why?
Because there was
no other possiblity
than to let it happen and once
the slum is in place, once, often, that
it becomes solidified, we try
somehow, to build roads and
to plan the land development,
to give titles to people, to create
parcels in the poor neighborhoods.
Anticipation would be in the
form of sub-divisions but
we saw earlier
the sub-division is often planned
for good reasons but also for
very bad reasons.
Finally, there are some other big
property issues,
when we project in the future,
forecasting issues,
it is knowing how these resources
are going to be managed,
as we imagine that these resources
have an end, that we are going to
try to understand and imagine, how are
we going to be able to continue
to parcel out while knowing that
one day we will need, to reduce in any case,
maybe not stop, but reduce the rapid
progress of sub-divisions.
There is also the question
of finances also,
since it's one of the big urban economies,
that of property, knowing what
the mechanisms are that
would allow to recuperate one part
of this surplus land value
that is created by property.
There it is, quickly described,
some property issues.
All these things, we will not have the
time to go in depth about the issue
of property, we could do a whole MOOC
about property in Africa,
the connection between modern law
and customary law, without a doubt
is not the goal, the goal is only to
put forth some questioning,
some problems that we've identified,
and to say well here,
we have issues with property, which is
first and foremost a speculative issue.
So there are huge financial issues
when discussing property.
It is for this reason that property is
one of the biggest, even the biggest
problem of the African city.