Cellphones have become so pervasive
now that being able to use your cell phone
to make a call is maybe something
you take for granted.
But when you wanna call a friend,
what needs
to happen for phone calls
to go through?
Two people both need to have
working phones with charged batteries
You need to have paid credit
with a network service provider.
And you need to be within a range
of a working cell tower.
An entire service chain
needs to be in place
and functioning for it to work.
This is similar to faecal
sludge management which also relies
on a complex service chain
to function properly.
This module provides an introduction
to faecal sludge management
and the current global situation.
Following this module
you will be able to describe
what faecal sludge and faecal
sludge management are.
Discuss weak links of the faecal
sludge management service chain.
List the components of a complete
faecal sludge management service chain.
So, first of all, what is
faecal sludge?
Faecal sludge is any combination
of waste water and excreta
that comes from
onsite sanitation technologies.
Specifically meaning it has not been
transported through a sewer.
Examples include pit latrines,
unsewered public ablution blocks,
septic tanks and dry toilets.
So, faecal sludge is highly variable
in consistency, quantity,
and concentration.
Here are some examples of what
faecal sludge looks like.
This is sludge from septic tanks.
You see where samples were taken
and what they look like in the lab.
How a septic tank is emptied that
is located on an internal courtyard.
Bringing the hose pipe for
the vacuum truck inside.
And faecal sludge from
different types of pit latrines.
Emptying of pit latrines with
the vacuum truck.
And also, manually with
shovels and forks.
And barrels transported with
the motorized tricycle.
Faecal sludge from public toilets
does not mean a specific
type of technology,
but tends to have different
usage and storage times.
The faecal sludge management or FSM
service chains there's with
the onsite storage
or containment of faecal sludge
shown here in septic tanks
and pit latrines,
which then needs to be collected
and transported
to treatment facilities.
Where it's adequately treated
for the intended end use
and then ends with resource recovery
or safe disposal.
Faecal sludge management represents
a very significant global need.
This figure made by
the Boston Consulting Group
illustrates the global population
served by onsite sanitation.
All of which are in need of faecal
sludge management.
So, globally, 2.7 billion people or
40% of the entire world's population
are served by
onsite sanitation technologies.
In urban areas of Africa,
Asia and Latin America
this accounts for around
1 billion people.
That number is expected to grow
to 5 billion by 2030.
In most of these cities
the majority of sanitation is provided
through onsite technologies.
Nut sewers providing even
up to 100% of sanitation coverage
in urban areas.
However, the reality is
that in low and middle income
countries there's typically
no management system in place
for the resulting faecal sludge.
The result is that it frequently
ends up dumped directly
into the urban environment.
Problems in the service chain
are households
that cannot afford to pay someone
to empty their system
they're forced to find alternative solutions,
like just digging it out themselves.
Manual emptiers who,
once they empty the systems,
it's physically impossible for them
to transport at long distances.
Mechanical emptiers that have trucks
that once they empty the sludge
the distance is too far for them
to transport it to treatment facilities
or traffic is simply too bad for them
to get to the treatment facility.
The general lack of treatment facilities
in most cities.
And faecal sludge that is used
or disposed of in unhygienic ways.
Examples of how this looks
are poorly constructed
and maintained facilities.
Digging a hole in the street
right outside of a house
so that the contents of a septic tank
that is illegally emptied
manually with buckets
can be illegally dumped into it
right in the street.
Breaking a whole in the base
of the containment,
so the faecal sludge will just drain
directly out.
Emptiers who have to get inside
the septic tanks
or other containment technologies
to remove the sludge with shovels.
A discharged channel
for sludge trucks
that drains directly onto
the beach and into the ocean.
Illegal emptying of sludge trucks
directly into the environment
and scavenging faecal sludge
for unsafe use in urban agriculture.
So, clearly, providing adequate
access to sanitation facilities
does not end when
onsite technologies are built.
That is just the start.
What happens after
they become full?
It's imperative to also take
a longer term focus
which moves beyond
the household level.
The sustainable development goals
or STGs
will hopefully
have a positive impact
as they now include
faecal sludge management.
The target to achieve access
to adequate and equitable sanitation
has been upgraded
to include the safe disposal
or offsite treatment of excreta.
It is important to keep in mind
that onsite
or decentralized technologies
can provide sustainable solutions
in all areas of the world.
Sewer based solutions are effective.
But are also very resource intensive
and expensive.
In a side by side comparison
in Dakar, Senegal
the sewer service chain was found to be
5 times more expensive
than the existing faecal
sludge management service chain.
So, faecal sludge management can
be considered a long term viable option.
And, possibly, more sustainable
compared to sewer based systems
if the entire service chain
is adequately managed.
We need to simultaneously address
how to immediately start getting excreta
safely out of the urban environment.
While simultaneously developing
sustainable
and globally relevant solutions
for managing faecal sludge
into the future.
In the following modules,
we will present examples of solutions
that are being implemented.
One of the most important
things to realize
is that faecal sludge management
is not only about technology.
It's about a complex service chain
that depends on the interactions
among people at every step.
The way forward to finding
sustainable future solutions
for faecal sludge management
includes overcoming bottlenecks
at the crossroads of planning,
management, and technology.
All of which you will hear about
in future modules.
This is the same integrate approach
presented in the book
Faecal Sludge Management,
Systems Based Approach
to Implementation and Operation.
In this module, you had
an introduction
to what faecal sludge
and faecal sludge management are.
The current status of weak links
in the service chain
in low income countries.
And components of a fully
functioning service chain
from the household level
to the final end use or safe disposal.
Thanks for joining!
See you next time.