My name is Dr. Charles Niwagaba
and I'm a senior lecturer of sewer
engineering at Makerere University,
Kampala, Uganda.
I have 16 years experience
in sanitation.
Now, faecal sludge management
is a new and quickly evolving field.
In this module we present you
a video, so that you can visualize
some of the realities
of urban sanitation.
Lean back, enjoy and please keep
in mind the learning objectives
while viewing.
Following this module you will be
able to understand weak links
of urban sanitation.
Name potential solutions that the
U-Act and FaME projects identified
in order to improve
urban sanitation.
Discuss the benefits that resource
recovery can have in terms of faecal
sludge management.
Adequate sanitation can only be
fulfilled with management
of the entire service chain.
Including safe access
to clean toilets
collection an transport
of accumulated faecal sludge
followed by treatment and some form
of safe end use or disposal.
U-Act is taking place
in Kampala, Uganda.
Where in poor areas 84% of
the households rely on shared toilets.
Such as the one shown here.
These toilets are used on average
by 25 people each.
But sometimes by up to 500 people
each.
When toilets are overused it is less
likely that they are kept clean.
This resulting in people stopping
to use them.
And resorting to open defecation.
Considering cleanliness U-Act
research has identified that
up to 4 households can actually
share a toilet while maintaining it
in an acceptably clean and
functional manner.
And thereby provide
affordable and adequate sanitation.
Inadequate toilet facilities
are affecting life in informal
or illegal settlements.
The faecal management enterprises
or FaME project lead by Sandag
is taking place in Dakar, Senegal
Akrogala and Kampala, Uganda.
And starts where U-Act leaves off
with accumulated faecal sludge
onsite sanitation technologies.
The goal of the FaME project is
to increase sustainable access
to sanitation thorough resource
recovery from faecal sludge.
Which could provide revenue
to improve collection, transport
and treatment services.
Many households cannot afford
to have faecal sludge
collected and removed.
Once onsite technologies become full.
For example, in poor areas
of Kampala this costs between
23-46 US dollars.
Which is 15-35% of an entire
household's monthly income.
Even if households can afford
the collection service,
the toilets are often located
down narrow pathways
and are not accessible
to vacuum trucks.
As a result manual laborers are hired
to remove faecal sludge
with shovels and buckets.
Sometimes even getting inside
the onsite technology to dig out
the sludge.
Commonly, manual laborers
do not have access
to motorized transport.
They need to carry or push
the faecal sludge away.
As shown here, this results in
faecal sludge being illegally dumped
either right next to the house,
or into drainage canals
or water bodies, contaminating
the environment with excreta.
If vacuum trucks can access
the toilets, they use hoses
to vacuum the faecal sludge
into trucks.
The U-Act toilets are designed
to increase access to collection
through their design.
U-Act has designed and constructed
156 shared improved latrines.
These latrines are spread
all over the city
in about 35 slums.
These toilets consist of a holding tank
of 6 cubic meters.
Which is fully aligned
from the bottom.
It is lined so as to prevent
ground water pollution
because most of the low income
areas in Kampala are situated
in areas with high water [INAUDIBLE]
And therefore toilets
which are not lined
contaminate ground water directly.
We have given these toilets
additional features
(INAUDIBLE).
For example, on the site we have got
an access point
which is covered by a brick
that can be easily removed
whenever the toilet fills
and needs to be emptied.
The toilet structure
standing over here
has been there for about two years
and in a period of two years
it has been emptied
about three times.
And this emptying has not affected
the integrity of the structure.
And we are very sure that
it can be used several times
for a long time as long as
it is emptied
as and when it feels.
Another way to increase access
to the collection
is to reduce fees at the household
level.
Households rely on collection
and transport companies.
Which charge high fees
because they also incur
many expenses.
If the profitability of companies
could be increased
the fees of the households
could be reduced.
The collection and treatment
of faecal sludge is complicated
by the high variability
of its characteristics.
For example, faecal sludge
from septic tanks that consists
of washing, cleaning
and cooking water
in addition to excreta
is very dilute.
Faecal sludge from pit latrines
tends to be much thicker.
Well, faecal sludge from public toilets
with a high number of uses
is collected frequently.
And so is less stabilized.
The sludge often contains
hygienic products,
batteries, bottles, household waste
and garbage
which can clog the hoses
and damage pipes.
And because faecal sludge
is mostly water
and water is heavy
it's expensive to transport.
Vacuum truck drivers frequently
get stuck in congested traffic.
As shown here in Dakar.
And long lines can form
at discharge locations.
There are also not enough
legal dischage locations
or treatment facilities.
And drivers
must pay a fee to discharge.
Because of these reasons
and the costs
trucks often resort to dump
untreated faecal sludge
directly into urban environments.
If these fees were reduced
or eliminated
could the savings
be passed on to the households
resulting in lower fee?
And with this increase the amount
of faecal sludge that is delivered
to treatment plants reducing
the dumping of untreated faecal sludge
to the urban environment.
Faecal sludge is higher in organic
matter and nutrients.
One way discharged fees
could be reduced
is if the treatment plant operators
could offset treatment costs.
Generating revenue
from resource recovery of the energy
nutrients and water
from faecal sludge.
The FaME project identified that
there is currently
only very limited use
of faecal sludge as a soil amendment
in agriculture and horticulture.
And that the market for the resource
recovery is largely untapped.
Even if treated most faecal sludge
is presently just landfilled
or dumped.
FaME also found that in addition
to use as a soil amendment
faecal sludge has other
potential end uses.
These are as a solid industrial fuel,
biogas from anaerobic digestion,
protein for animal feed from larvae
used in treatment,
The market demand for different
end products varies greatly
among locations
based on such factors
as the availability
of competing products,
local industries and their needs,
and user perceptions.
Faecal sludge treatment
should be designed
to meet the demands of local markets,
so that the end product
produced
the highest possible revenue.
This also ensures that
treatment plans are not overdesigned
wasting financial resources.
Or underdesigned risking public
or environmental health.
For example, if the end use
of faecal sludge is combustion
as a fuel.
Pathogen reduction
is much less important
than it is when the end use
is soil amendment and food production.
But reducing moisture content
is a much more important
treatment goal
The FaME project focused
on large scale markets
such as industrial field to ensure
reliable and consistent demand
and revenue.
In Europe and the US
sludge from wastewater treatment
is already coincinerated
in cement industries.
FaME research found that
if this technology
could be transferred
to faecal sludge
to meet the energy demand
of industries in Sub Saharan Africa
it could generate much revenue
as an alternative fuel.
FaME also demonstrated
that the colorific value
of faecal sludge, which is a measure
of its fell potential
is comparable to other biofuels
that are currently being used.
And it found that the revenues
from this end use
could be significantly greater
than its use as a soil conditioner.
Dried faecal sludge
has not yet been used
as an industrial fuel.
Prior to uptake by industries
pilot scale implementations
were needed to demonstrate
the feasibility of faecal sludge
as a feel to industries.
To address this the FaME project
is designed and constructed
pilot scale kilns
for brick production in Kampala
and waste oil regeneration
in Dakar.
In both kilns
the temperatures achieved
by using dried faecal sludge
met industry's requirements.
In the brick kiln a temperature
of 800 degrees Celsius
could be maintained.
And the strength of bricks
fired with dried faecal sludge
was similar to those produced
by brick factories.
Industries have expressed
great interest
in this alternative fuel.
If there's adequate availability.
[INAUDIBLE] treated faecal sludge
as a solid fuel to industries
requires drying the sludge
to around 90% dryness.
given if low solid content.
Cost effective drying methods
have to be developed
to meet the needs of industries.
FaME researched how to improve
the effectiveness of drying beds
and in Dakar we've experimented
with turning the sludge
and with greenhouses to decrease
the drying time.
And both have reduced it.
Turning the sludge reduces
the drying time by around 20%.
This increases treatment capacities
at existing treatment plant.
But also new plants need
less drying space.
The research findings
of U-Act and FaME
together have identified
innovative solutions
to increase access to sanitation
at the household and community level.
Shared sanitation facilities
can provide adequate sanitation
if the maximum number
of households is set
to ensure clean and usable toilets.
Faecal sludge
can be readily collected
from onsite technologies
if they are appropriately designed.
Affordability
of household level services
could be increased through revenues
from resource recovery.
And designing faecal sludge
treatment to meet the specific
local market demand
could maximize these revenues.
To insure uptake
of these research results
sustainable business models
and fee structures
need to be developed.
And governments need
to acknowledge the importance
of faecal sludge management.