Have you ever found yourself
in a situation where you realize
you should've planned better?
One of the most important things
to realize
about faecal sludge management
is that planning
is an essential component
of sustainable solutions.
To ensure the system works
requires a complex service chain
that depends on interactions
among people at every step.
Including the public, private,
and civil society,
the household level user,
the collection and transport companies,
operators of treatment plans,
and the final end user
of treated sludge.
In this module I will introduce you
to concepts of an integrated approach
that this course is based on.
Following this module
you will be able to explain
why an integrated approach
to city-wide faecal sludge management
requires planning, management,
and technology.
Understand how the book
Faecal Sludge Management
Systems Based Approach
for Implementation and Operation
fits into that framework.
And explain why a sound engineering
design approach is required
for the design and selection
of treatment technologies.
In the provision of city wide access
to sanitation
and sustainable provision of faecal
sludge management
there are, unfortunately,
many examples of failures.
To help understand the scope
of the problem
and think about what not
to replicate
here are a few anonymous examples
of failures
that are based on real life examples.
First, a city where a treatment plan
was designed based on faecal sludge
characteristics that were in published
references from other countries.
The result was that because local
faecal sludge characteristics
were not considered,
the treatment plant was built
twice as large as required.
This represents a waste
of financial resources
and potential operations problems
as the plant will not operate
as designed.
In another city, the treatment plant
was built so far outside of town
that truck drivers could not afford
to transport sludge that far.
This is because land for treatment
is difficult to find
in dense urban areas.
But the result was that it was
never used
and trucks continued to dump sludge
directly in the urban environment.
Both of these examples
illustrate the importance
of always designing and planning
the faecal sludge management solutions
based on the local context.
In another city there was one
designated location
for dumping the faecal sludge.
Which was directly onto the beach
and in the ocean.
So a high core injunction
bended.
However, the injunction had
to be lifted and trucks were allowed
back to dump on the beach
because with no other alternative
trucks just had to find other places
to empty their tanks all over the city.
In another city there're over 40
legal collection and transport
companies operating,
but there's no legal discharge
or treatment location.
So, obviously, the legal businesses
have no other alternative
than to illegally dump sludge
wherever they can.
Both of these examples
illustrate the importance
of institutional frameworks
and the importance of clear roles
and responsibilities
for faecal sludge management.
Another example
from countless cities
is a pump breaking
at a treatment plant.
Resulting in sludge not being pumped
out of (INAUDIBLE) and tanks
greatly reducing hydraulic
retention times
and in general leading to failure
and treatment not being achieved.
This illustrates the importance
of planning
and having a sound operations
and maintenance plan in place.
As design engineers
and practitioners
when working on solutions
at any step in the service chain
we need to be making intelligent
design decisions
based on an integrated approach.
Engineering design
is the formulation of a plan
to allow you to build a product
or infrastructure with the specified
performance goal.
For waste water treatment plans
that usually means
designing treatment
to to meet affluent
and solid requirements.
Instead, frequently
for faecal sludge management
decisions have been made
on available funding
by trying to spend all of it
or to be as cheap as possible,
or, in contrast, just copying
and pasting what worked in entirely
different contexts.
Which has resulted in projects
designed for overly stringent
performance goals.
That also do not perform as intended
and frequently fail.
In an example of an engineering
problem solving methodology
you have a client who could,
for example, be a municipality
and you have your specified
performance goal
that you need to salve for.
Then you determine the relevant
design variables
which include technical aspects,
but also social considerations
like cultural preferences.
Then you further define the problem,
develop alternative solutions,
and then can take decisions
to finally come
to your project realization.
We cannot effectively solve problems
until we have clearly defined
the problem we're trying to solve.
In an engineering design approach
for selection and design
of treatment technologies
this means first defining performance
goals or treatment objectives
Frequently, regulations
for the treatment of faecal sludge
do not exist or are not enforced.
Which also greatly complicates
defining performance goals.
One way to do this is to design
for resource recovery,
which can define performance goals
that need to be met
while increasing financial flows
to offset cost in the service chain.
And providing incentive
for efficient operation
of treatment plans as they're
operating to produce products
that meet a market demand.
Depending on the form
of resource recovery
defined performance goals
are quote different.
For example, pathogen reduction
is not as important
for use of faecal sludge
in combustion.
Whereas pathogen reduction
is of outmost importance
for use as a soil amendment
for edible crops.
In week 2 we will present you
with tools that help select
optimal treatment products
for your city.
The need for institutional
and regulatory frameworks
to stimulate resource recovery
and other aspects
of the enabling environment
are part of the sustainable
implementation
and city wide sanitation planning.
However, an engineering
design approach
is not only about resource recovery.
It is first and foremost
the protection of public health.
And making intelligent
design decisions
starting by defining treatment
objectives is always essential.
For example, if designing
for disposal
it still needs to be safe disposal.
Once you have defined
treatment objectives,
then you can work backwards
considering all design variables
to arrive at a treatment
technology solution
to meet the defined goals.
Overdesigning treatment technologies
waste money and resources
while underdesigning does not provide
adequate protection
of human and environmental health.
This is why a design approach
is so important.
Another obvious design variable
is what will be going into
the treatment facility.
So, you can make it the right size.
However, no reliable methods
exist yet for the quantification
and characterization of faecal
sludge on a city wide scale.
Or relevant scale for the design
of a treatment plan.
So, on week 2, we will discuss
ways to approach
making reasonable estimates.
But what about all these other
design variables?
They include factors
such as existing infrastructure
and services,
skills and capacities,
legal requirements,
regulations,
norms, social acceptance,
operational maintenance,
financial liability.
As engineers and practitioners
working in faecal sludge management
we need to fill many different roles
and realize the importance
of why solutions will fail
if not part of this larger approach.
As we will introduce in week 4
this is where a planning framework
helps you to determine relevant
design variables.
And when in a project cycle
to consider them.
A framework will guide practitioners
from the initial project planning phase
to implementation and ongoing
operations and maintenance.
In week 4 we will introduce
planning and management aspects
of an integrated approach
that helped form the foundation
that longterm successful systems
are built on.
Planning represents the first phase
of designing a system,
but is necessary to ensure
a continuum of success
throughout a life of a project.
Management factors
such as institutionalization,
technical capacity,
legal frameworks, enforcement,
fast recovery mechanisms
and operations and maintenance
will also help to ensure long term
project success.
A systems level approach
is necessary to understand
how all the steps are the complete
system integrate and influence other.
To avoid the types of failures
presented at the beginning
of this module.
In integrated approach
at the city level
is especially important
with the faecal sludge management.
As globally experiencing
time and time again
that onsite and decentralized
technologies
are prone to failure
if not considered
as a component within
a larger system.
In this module we learned why
an integrated approach
to city wide faecal sludge management
requires planning, management
and technology.
How the faecal sludge management
book fits into that framework.
And why a sound engineering design
approach is required
for the intelligent design
and selection
of treatment technologies.
We will continue to revisit
these concepts in the coming weeks.
Thanks for joining!
See you next time.