After your first week
of an introduction to
faecal sludge management,
hopefully you feel confident
to explain what faecal sludge
and faecal sludge management are.
The goal of the first week
was to get you immersed in the topic,
because once you can understand and
define the problem you are working on,
then you can start thinking
of effective and relevant solutions.
You should now have an understanding
of the global significance
of faecal sludge management,
as 40% of the world's population
are using onsite sanitation systems,
and that number
will continue to grow
with increasing urbanization.
You know what faecal sludge is,
how it differs from
other types of sludge,
factors influencing
the wide range of variability
and characteristics
that will be important
for us to consider
with treatment objectives.
Did you have a chance
to look at the examples
provided in this report?
You also learned about how
a complete sanitation surface chain
for faecal sludge management
is different than for
sewer based systems.
In contrast to flush and forget,
it is about interactions
between people
at every step in the chain.
Along with this,
you also learned about
weak links in the service chain.
You saw multiple examples
with pictures
and a video of our FaME and U-ACT
research projects.
Can you already identify
some of the problems
that need to be addressed?
Lack of financial resources?
Lack of existing infrastructure?
Lack of legal and
regulatory frameworks?
Building pit latrines
without thinking
what happens when they become full?
Hopefully,
you are also starting to think about
the different magnitudes
of problems that need
to be addressed.
The immediate problem
of getting excreta out of
communities and cities,
and longer term, the most sustainable
globally relevant solutions.
Onsite sanitation could provide
a less expensive
and more sustainable solution
that is less resource
and energy intensive,
but only if every step
in the service chain
is managed adequately.
Concepts you are learning about
for applying sustainable city wide
faecal sludge management
include
the engineering design approach,
to think logically about
first defining treatment objectives,
then quantifying and
characterizing waste streams
that will need to be treated,
and then considering all of
the design variables
when selecting and designing
treatment technologies
to meet these goals and demands.
In week 2, we will present
fundamentals you need
before you can start
applying this approach,
which will include
treatment objectives,
resource recovery,
a method to select
treatment products
with the greatest market potential
and how to quantify and characterize
faecal sludge on a city wide basis
or a scale that's relevant
to the design
of management solutions.
In week 4,
you will learn more
about all of the different types
of design variables
that you must consider,
and how a planning framework
can help you to think about them
and at which step
you need to consider them.
However, you are also now aware
that solutions are
not only about technology.
Finding solutions
are at the bottleneck
of planning, management
and technology.
This is why the concept
of an integrated systems approach,
as laid out in
the faecal sludge management book
and this course,
is so important to follow.
Hopefully, by now,
you've had a chance
to download and review the book
and see that
there are 3 distinct sections
on technology, planning
and management,
and also how they're all integrated.
Applying an integrated
planning approach
at the city level is imperative.
The entire enabling environment
must be considered.
In particular, management
and financial schemes
must be defined and validated
prior to making final decisions
on technical options.
To demonstrate the importance
of planning and management
for success,
you saw examples
of mistakes people have made.
For example, when not
considering the local context,
a lack of institutional frameworks,
clear roles and responsibilities,
operations and maintenance,
and planning.
In week 4,
we will present more details,
including an integrated
planning approach,
legal frameworks and enforcement.
You also learned about what is working
and what is not working
in the faecal sludge management
service chain
in 3 different cities:
Hanoi, Kampala, and Toyokawa.
In Hanoi, more people
have access to toilets,
most households have a septic tank,
and there are over 40
collection and transport companies.
However, there is nowhere
legal to discharge.
How will that change
with the new decree 80?
In contrast, in Kampala,
there is faecal sludge treatment
but access to toilets is
frequently crowded and unhygienic,
treatment plants are at
or over capacity,
and faecal sludge
in informal settlements
is frequently directly discharged
to the environment.
How will their sanitation
master plan change that?
In Toyokawa,
where 30% of sanitation
is met with onsite solutions,
when 100% of excreta
is safely managed.
Have you started thinking about why
different aspects work
in each of these cities?
Hopefully, you understand now
the scale of the problem.
Did we overwhelm you?
Don't worry.
Solutions happen step by step,
and now we can start moving ahead
learning about deriving solutions.
What are steps you think
you could already take in your city?
Do you have any ideas?
Please add them
to the forum for discussion,
and please also be sure
to review the additional resources
we have provided on the platform.
Now, we'll move on to week 2,
where we present more
of the fundamental knowledge
that you need to start designing
and selecting treatment technologies,
including treatment objectives,
quantification and characterization,
resource recovery,
and we will introduce you
to technologies
that are used to get sludge
from onsite containment
to treatment plants.
Thanks for joining.
See you in week 2.