What type, and how much of solids,
organics, nutrients and pathogens
are included in faecal sludge
in your city?
This is a very important question
to ask
for a selection
of collection technologies
and the design and operation
of treatment plants.
In this module, we introduce such
relevant characterization parameters.
Following this module,
you'll be able to explain
the importance of characterization,
select relevant
characterization parameters,
and choose existing resources
for characterization.
Characterization of sludge
can be qualitative,
for example,
by monitoring the sludge color
that is discharged
at a treatment plant.
The color is different
from brown or black,
as shown in this video,
which could indicate
an industrial contamination.
Such qualitative characterization
is important for treatment operation
but does not replace
quantitative characterization.
It is always required
for the design,
operation, and monitoring
of treatment plants.
Missing or unreliable information
on characteristics
commonly leads to poor performance
or complete failure
of collection
and treatment services.
Let's consider, for example,
this settling-thickening tank:
one technology
for solid-liquid separation
that is discussed
in a separate module.
Among others,
a settling-thickening tank
is designed based on
an amount of solid
that requires treatment.
On the one hand, underestimating
a solid's concentration
in the design process
will likely overload the technology
during operation
and result in
poor effluent characteristics
that can affect subsequent
treatment technologies,
and ultimately,
the discharge concentrations.
On the other hand,
overestimating solid concentrations
will lead to the construction
of tanks that are too big
which wastes financial resources,
and also influences its operation.
Quantitative sludge characterization
requires laboratories
with equipment and technicians,
as shown at a treatment plant here,
in Dakar in Senegal.
As these laboratories
and their operation incur costs,
characterization parameters
should be carefully selected
to answer one, or several,
specific questions.
These questions could be,
for example:
What is an appropriate
collection technology?
What are design parameters
for treatment technologies?
Or does the effluent
from a treatment plant
meet legal discharge limits?
To answer these questions,
it is helpful to group
characterization parameters
that are relevant for
collection and treatment.
Parameters that are relevant
for resource recovery,
for example, compost,
are discussed in another module.
For the selection
of sludge collection technologies
it is important to know
whether the sludge can be pumped.
Therefore, solid parameters
such as total solids,
total suspended solids,
and viscosity are important.
In addition, it is important to know
the amount of solid waste
as it can clog and damage
collection equipment.
Characterization parameters
that are relevant for different
treatment technologies
can be grouped according to
their treatment objectives.
For technologies designed
for solid-liquid separation,
solid parameters such as total solids,
also called TS,
and total suspended solids
are important.
Total solids are, for example,
important for the dimensioning
of drying beds
and other solid-liquid
separation technology,
shown here at
a faecal sludge treatment plant,
close to Bangalore, in India.
Other important parameters
for solid-liquid
separation technologies
include the sludge volume index,
a metric to estimate solid and
liquid separation of faecal sludge,
the amount of solid waste,
oil and grease
and grit and sand.
Removal of grit and sand
and solid waste
is often the first treatment step
following discharge,
as shown here at a treatment plant
in Kampala in Uganda.
For technologies designed
for sludge stabilization
total volatile solids,
also called TVS,
the chemical oxygen demand,
also called COD,
and the biochemical oxygen demand,
also called BOD,
are important parameters.
The BOD and COD are, for example,
important for the design
of waste stabilization ponds
that can be used for treatment
of effluence
from solid-liquid
separation technologies,
such as settling-thickening tanks,
or drying beds.
The ratio of BOD and COD,
and TVS and TS,
can also be used as an indicator
for the relative biodegradability
of organics and faecal sludge
that affects
biological treatment processes.
For technologies designed
for nutrient management,
ammonium, nitrate,
nitrite, and phosphate
are important parameters.
Pathogen inactivation is ultimately
the most important objective
in faecal sludge treatment.
Instead of measuring
individual pathogens,
indicator organisms are used
to provide a measure
of pathogen concentrations
and inactivation during treatment.
Examples of indicator organisms
are viable helminth eggs, and E-coli.
Helminth eggs are commonly used
as an indicator
for pathogens in the solids.
For example, in dried sludge,
or a compost,
as shown here in these pictures,
at a faecal sludge treatment plant
in San Jose in Costa Rica.
In contrast, E-coli are important
for the liquid fraction,
for example, from
settling-thickening technologies,
drying beds, or the effluent from
a faecal sludge treatment plant.
Other important general
characterization parameters
include the pH, the temperature,
and the electric conductivity.
In reality, a combination
of these parameters
is selected for design, operation,
and monitoring of different
treatment technologies,
and an entire treatment plant.
This could be during research,
or to collect characteristics
for treatment design.
In this picture, one of my colleagues
is collecting faecal sludge samples
for a characterization study
in Kampala.
All during operation
of a treatment plant,
as for this treatment plant
in Kampala,
samples may be collected
at in flow,
before and after
treatment technologies,
such as the settling-thickening tanks
and drying beds,
to assess their performance.
Only effluent from treatment
to assess the effluent characteristics
meet discharge limits.
You might be overwhelmed
by the number
of characterization parameters
presented here.
For implementation
of characterization in your city,
you can find more information
on sample collection,
preparation, protocols,
and considerations
for quality assurance and control
In these Sandec reports
that can be downloaded
for free from our website.
Standard operating procedures
are also available from the website
of the Pollution Research Group
at the University of KwaZulu-Natal
in Durban, South Africa.
In this module, we introduced you
to characterization parameters
that are important for collection,
design, operation and
monitoring of treatment plants.
These parameters are measures
of solids, organics,
nutrients and pathogens
in faecal sludge.
We hope that you explore the
additional material provided
and find it helpful for
faecal sludge characterization
in your city.