If you have ever taken care of plants
you know that they need to be
watered so that they don't welt.
That's because plants take water up
into their cells and this water
pressure helps keep them upright.
But have you ever seen on a really
hot day, plants welting
even though they appear
to have enough water?
That's because a plant's respiration
includes transpiration
of moisture out of their leaves.
On a hot day this transpiration
can occur faster than plants can
take up more water
causing them to welt even when
they do have access to water.
Following this module you
will be able to explain
treatments processes and operation
of planted drying beds,
discuss operation and
maintenance requirements
and name
important design parameters.
Over the last 20 years Sandec has
collaborated with researchers
in Thailand, Cameroon and Senegal
to transfer the knowledge of
operating planed drying beds
in Europe with waste water and
bio-solid sludge to the treatment
of faecal sludge.
The technology has now been
successfully proven
but there is still not enough full
scale operating experience
to provide precise design and
operational parameters
for different contexts and so
implementation of this technology
still requires special
care and attention.
Planted drying beds are similar
to unplanted drying beds.
They consist of a gravel
and sand filter bed.
Sludge is loaded onto the top
and the leachate percolates
through the bed and is drained
away in a perforated pipe.
The differences are
in planted drying beds
the filter bed is used
for growing plants.
This means that in
addition to evaporation
de-watering is occurring
through plant transpiration.
Both of these together are called
evapotranspiration.
The plant roots also function
to help keep the bed from clogging
and provide a more complex
environment for the growth of bacteria
within the bed.
Planted drying beds are also
operated in continuous mode;
not as a batch
so sludge is continually
loaded onto the beds
but only removed
after a period of years.
One of the most important
considerations for the
design and operation of planted
drying beds are the plants.
They need to be able to grow in
relatively hostile faecal sludge
conditions and be tolerant to
fluctuating water levels and salinity.
They need be fast growing,
have high transpiration rates,
deep-growing rhizomes and roots
and be non-invasive.
In Europe, reeds or Phragmites and
cattails or Typha
are the most
commonly used plants.
In Africa, Asia and Latin America,
indigenous plants are being explored
for adaption such as
Antelope Grass or Echinochloa
and papyrus
or Cyperus.
An example is this paper identifying
3 new indigenous species in Senegal
that are good candidates for use
in planted drying beds.
Echinochloa crus-galli,
Paspalidium geminatum
and Pasplaum
veginatum.
This is a drying bed following
harvesting of plants
also showing the plants
starting to grow back.
Plants are harvested by cutting
them at the surface of the bed
not by pulling them out
which could damage the bed
and prevent regrowth. Plants
are harvested when sludge is removed
but can also be harvested more
frequently for maintenance or
to sell as fodder.
For example,
this paper found that in Cameroon,
sale of the plants as fodder
could offset 7% of the annual
operating costs.
Another important design and
operating parameter
is the aclimazation phase
required by plants
prior to growing in
full-strength faecal sludge.
The start-up phase takes
on average around 6 months
and in arid climates it should
start during the rainy season
for best growth. Examples of
how to do this
are going gradually from a loading
rate of 50 to 200kg total solids
per meter square per year with
a feeding frequency of
of at least twice a week.
Another way would be
starting out with dilute waste
water or for example
effluent from a settling
thickening tank
and gradually moving to
full-strength faecal sludge.
During this period, visual
indicators of plant stress
such as yellowish color
or slow growth rates
should be carefully
looked out for.
Ponding to retain liquid
in the bed can also be used
to prevent welting
in tropical climates
and potentially increase
treatment performance
but the bed should then be left
to fully drain before reloading.
This is sludge on a bed
without loading for 1 week.
Sludge loading rates can be based
on hydraulic loadings
or the amount of total solids.
Loading frequencies
are also going to depend on the
types of plants,
climate and
treatment goals.
For example, this paper found
that increased loading frequency
can increase plant growth, liquid
lost to evapotranspiration,
and the nitrification
of leachate.
If you base loading
rates on total solids,
to determine the required
surface area
you need to know
the total volume of sludge
that will be treated
on an annual basis.
The average total solids
concentration of the sludge;
then we just convert the
units here
divided by the loading rate
that you're going to use
and this tells you
the required surface area.
Desludging frequencies are
going to depend on factors
such as loading rate
and climate.
Experimental data
from Cameroon
suggests that a loading rate of
200kg total solid
per square meter per year had
50 to 70cm per year
sludge accumulation.
That means
if you had a free board of 2m,
this could result in
3 to 4 years
for desludging.
However other studies have had
lower accumulation rates
and desludging intervals can
even be up to 10 years long.
This is a hole looking down
into the sludge layer.
After the last loading, sludge
should be then left for a few months
for increased moisture
and pathogen reduction.
These long sludge
retention times
also mean that following removal,
the sludge is much more
stabilized than with the short
retention times of
unplanted
drying beds.
This table from the Fecal Sludge
Management book
summarizes observed
treatment performances
with loading rates.
Percent removals
meaning what percent stays with
the sludge layer versus the leachate
are quite high but what is
important to remember with
percent removals is that starting
with very high concentrations
that are in faecal sludge,
you still end up with
concentrations in the leachate
that are higher than
discharged standards.
Ways to treat dewatering liquid
from sludge are discussed in
Co-treatment
and Leachate Treatment
modules.
In summary, important design
and operating parameters
are loading, feeding frequency,
resting periods,
plant density, plant acclimatization,
and plant harvesting.
Conclusions from Sandec's
collaborative research
on adapting planted drying beds
for the treatment of
faecal sludge include, planted
drying beds are viable
for faecal sludge treatment;
they're resistant to highly variable
hydraulic loadings;
higher loading rates
can be used in tropical climates;
plants need to be selected
for the local context;
fodder production can offset
some of the operation costs;
sludge can be stabilized on the beds
however it needs further treatment
for safe use in agriculture.
Desludging periods can be
up to 5-10 years long.
Pre-treatment with settling tanks
results in better de-watering
on planted drying beds.
The leachate requires further
treatment and research as it remains
one of the biggest challenges.
In this module we learned about
treatment processes and
operation of
planted drying beds,
operation and
maintenance requirements
and design
parameters.
Thanks for joining
and see you next time.