Why do you think this waste
water treatment plant failed?
Examples of failed waste
water treatment plants
are abundant throughout
low income countries.
One common reason why is
people try to use them
for the treatment of fecal sludge
even thought they were designed to
only treat waste water.
In this module, we will learn
about ways the fecal sludge
and waste water could
be co-treated together.
Following this module,
you will be able to understand
key considerations and
potential impacts
of co-treatment of sewer-based
waste water treatment systems
explain the importance of
influent characteristic
on modeling of waste water
treatment plant performance
and understand that waste
water treatment plants
are complex systems with
processes that could be upset.
As you are well aware by now,
fecal sludge is different from
waste water and cannot
just be treated the same.
It is much more concentrated,
variable, and is partially degraded.
There are possibilities for
co-treating fecal sludge
and waste water, but the possibility
of failure is high and
the consequences to failure
are very significant as then
neither waste would be
receiving treatment.
Waste water treatment
plants are not black boxes
they are basically very complex
factories that are receiving
polluted water and turning it into
clean water and sludge.
The basis for stabilization
treatment are very diverse
from Lagoons, to activated
sludge, to trickling filters
as for de-watering from drying beds
to, centrifuges, to screw presses.
What is possible for co-treatment if
anything will depend on the type
and design of technologies,
the quantities and characteristics
of waste water and fecal sludge
including most importantly
is the treatment plant
currently at capacity or not
and existing infrastructure.
It will also require a competent
waste water engineer who also
understands the complexities
of fecal sludge to model any
proposed modifications, and
also verify with in field testing.
If you have a waste water
treatment plant that is currently
under capacity there are three ways
you can investigate co-treatment
with fecal sludge.
One, de-water the fecal sludge
and send the resulting solid and
liquid streams for treatment with
the solid and liquid
waste water streams.
Two, treat the fecal sludge together
with the bio-solids starting from
the de-watering stage.
And three, directly treat the fecal
sludge with the influent waste water.
In general, three is
not recommended
and it needs to be stressed that
fecal sludge should never be added
directly into secondary
waste water treatment.
The preferred option for
co-treatment is starting
with de-watering of fecal sludge.
This could include settling
thickening tanks
drying beds,
or mechanical de-watering.
If you're looking for
fecal sludge de-watering
solutions prior to the development
of additional infrastructure
temporary options like geo-textile
bags could be considered.
The afluent could then either go
into primary or the secondary
treatment for co-treatment
with the waste water depending
on the characteristics and
the solids could be co-treated
together with the waste
sludge or bio solids.
With this option, waste increased
de-watering and frying of
both solid streams could be
investigated thereby increasing
the treatment
capacity of the plant
for example, with conditioning
the bio-burn pelletizer
mixing of sludge on drying beds,
or thermal options.
The second option is very similar,
but the fecal sludge going directly
to the waste water solids
de-watering step of
the treatment plant, for example,
de-watering on drying beds.
This figure is from the 1984.
US EPA publication on
how to co-treat septic sludge
in waste water treatment plants.
The allowed loading depends whether
the treatment plant is a capacity
and what type of treatment
technologies are employed.
Now think about this,
if only 10% of operational
capacity within the aerated
lagoon you can still only add
3% of the total volume
as septic tank sludge.
For treatment plants that
are operating at 90%
of their capacity, the allowed
loading volume metrically
is less than one half of 1%
of the total influent volume.
But what is even more
important to consider
is that these calculations
were based on selected values
for septic tank sludge
in the united states
in the 1980's.
If we put the design value for
that figure onto our figure
It's obvious that the diverse range
of fecal sludge that we're working
with in general a lot
more concentrated.
This means the possible loadings
would have to be adjusted to be
even much lower.
This stresses the importance of
when implementing anything
the tests need to be
made on local sludge
that will be treated to understand
the settling, de-watering behavior
and the characteristics and
the quantities that will be
treated.
Chapter 9 in the fecal sludge
management book
covers detailed modeling
and more depth, it cover
the impacts that fecal sludge with
different strengths, concentrations
degradable organic matter
and also inert solids have
on the loading on the waste
water treatment plants.
Impacts on operations
that can lead to failures
include reduced afluent quality,
maxed out aeration resulting
in an aerobic process
turning anaerobic
incomplete oxidation,
filament bacteria
and overloading of settling
tanks and clarifiers.
Overloading of anaerobic systems
can also lead to inhibition of
biological processes and
increased sludge production
maxing out solids handling.
In addition the US EPA
recommendations are
for waste water treatment plants
serving areas that
are mostly sewered.
In areas where there is any
significant coverage by
on-site systems, which is the case
in most cities we are working in
in Asia, Latin America and Africa,
there needs to be separate
designated treatment of
waste water and fecal sludge.
For management purposes
it can effectively take place
at the same location but it
needs to be carefully planned out.
As covered in other modules,
there are plenty of options for
the treatment of fecal sludge
and even many more possibilities
like this process flow for treatment
of septage, or septic tank fecal
sludge with an ABR filter and
wetland from the United States.
Finally, one of the most important
considerations when co-treating is
when and how to
add the fecal sludge.
Fecal sludge should never
be discharged to the sewer
unless it has been
de-watered first.
And the afluent is
going to the sewer.
Sewers are designed for the gravity
flow of waste water and thicker
fecal sludge does not have
the same flow properties
resulting in blockages
and overflows.
To avoid shock loadings
the proffered method
would be a continuous flow at
a rate that is proportional to
the waste water influent.
To illustrate these points, I will
show you two different examples.
The first in the city of Manila,
the capital of the Philippines
is a treatment plant operated
by Manila water which is
a successful case study of
example one, de-watering
of fecal sludge and then co-treating
the liquid and solids with
the separate solid and liquid
streams from waste water.
This plant receives 2 million
liters per day of conventional
waster water and 0.8 million liters
per day of septic tank sludge
or septige.
This is the process flow
for the treatment plant.
The waste water treatment chain
is conventional activated sludge.
The waste water is treated
by primary sedimentation
activated sludge,
secondary sedimentation
and then disinfected
prior to discharge.
For the fecal sludge management,
vacuum trucks empty septic tanks
deliver the sludge to the treatment
plant, there is separate
pre-treatment for the fecal sludge
and then it is de-watered together
with the solids from the waste
water stream with the addition of
polymers and a screw press.
The co-processed waste water
and fecal sludge solids are then
transported off site by an approved
contractor for treatment with drying
beds and co-composting with
rice hole and then used as
the soil amendment.
The second example is a project
developed by the federal university
of Minas Gerais, Brazil, as a part
of the international program
financed by the Bill and Melinda
Gates foundation for the project
coordinated by the UNESCO-IHE.
This is also an example of
the number one de-watering fecal
sludge and then co-treating
the liquid and solids together
With the separate solid and liquid
streams from the waste water.
This project took place in
Belo Horizonte in the state
of Minas Gerais, Brazil, which has
a well developed sewer network
together with poor areas
served by septic tanks.
Domestic waste water treatment
occurs in three parallel French
system system treatment wet-lands
that have been
operational since 2009.
They operate in a weekly
cycle of feeding and resting.
Waste water is directly loaded in
batches onto one of the beds
following screening
and grit removal
and they achieve (INAUDIBLE) treatment
efficiency of 80% of COD and 84%
of TSS.
in 2013. the researchers evaluated
using the wet-lands system
for co-treatment with fecal sludge
form septic tanks, they did this
by loading unit one with fecal
sludge and then alternating
different loadings onto units two
and three with the fecal sludge
leachate from unit one together
with the raw waste water.
The research was
focused on whether
the wet-lands system
could effectively
co-treat waste water
and fecal sludge
and whether ponding or retaining
the leachate within the fecal
sludge bed for one week could
increase treatment performance.
Even with the reduced area
for waste water loading
with only two units being used
instead of three, almost the same
treatment efficiency was observed
for waste water of 72% for COD
and 84% for TSS.
Ponding in the fecal sludge unit
also had the greatest impact
on improving treatment performance
with  removals for the fecal sludge
of COD of 90% and TSS as 72%.
Based on their experience this
type of system is effective for
co-treatment of fecal sludge
and waste water with one unit
designated for fecal sludge with
the leachage going to co-treatment
with waste water.
This full scale pilot could provide
fecal sludge treatment for around
2500 population equivalence
with the 30 square meter surface
area for receiving the sludge.
And with available land this could
readily be scaled up as necessary.
In this module we've learned about
the complexities and dangers of
co-treating fecal sludge in
waste water treatment plants
and the importance of understanding
influent characteristics on
the complex functioning
of treatment plants.
Do you know of an example
in your city?
One that is a failure and why,
or another that's an example
of success?
You should add it to the forum so
we can include it for discussion.
Thanks for joining
and see you next time.