Hello and welcome to this module
on the assessment
of the initial situation.
We will look at the data that
you need to collect in order
to get a comprehensive overview
of the sanitation situation
in your city and to be able to
take informed decisions.
The aim of this module is also
to link the different aspects
requiring data collection
presented in this course.
The main goals of the assessment
of the initial situation are to set
the scene, understand the context,
get to know the stakeholders
and provide enough
information to start elaborating
the fecal sludge
management scenarios.
This includes, among others,
the definition of context specific
design parameters.
It would allow you to make
logical plans to move forward.
This phase of the planning process
is therefor characterized by data
collection via different means.
The question is which data
and by which means?
The idea is to get a snapshot
of the situation.
Start with a helicopter
view of your city.
You can take a map or look
at Google Earth and start by
identifying different
situation context
as discussed in the previous module.
What are the existing
infrastructure services?
Are there sewer networks?
Which type of toilets
do people have?
Who are the service providers
and how are they organized?
Whether they bring the sludge?
You can start by looking
at the general context
like demographic, water and hygiene,
storm water management
and climatic conditions.
Then collect data about
the sanitation sector
considering the whole
sanitation supply chain
as mentioned in the last module.
Especially, carry out a stakeholder
analysis and establish the profile
and practices of manual and
mechanical service providers.
Further on, it is important to
understand the practices
a household level and
at the other end of
the sanitation chain
the end use practices and
the potential market for
the treatment product.
Talking about stakeholders
we should know what are
the financial transfers between them.
For example, how much do households
currently pay for emptying services?
At that stage, you should check
the enabling conditions.
How is the government support?
What is the legal and
regulatory framework?
What are the rules but
also where are the gaps?
Which are the relevant institutions
and how are they organized?
What are the skills and capacities,
especially in terms of
human resources and management?
The financial arrangements,
as I mentioned before.
And, lastly, the socio-cultural
acceptance of different options.
The environment is rarely fully
enabling in the beginning of
the process and identifying the gaps
is the basis to plan for action.
A lot of  this information with
a type of (INAUDIBLE), standards
or the stakeholders
needs and interests
will also help you to quantify
and characterize the sludge
to be treated and estimate context
specific design parameters for your
future fecal sludge treatment plant.
Talking about treatment plants
you will see if you look at
the FSM from A to Z planning
synthesis presented in the previous
module that it is also the time to
identify the potential
treatment sites.
As this is also a very
difficult question
it is good to start
as soon as possible.
Often, there's not available land,
land is expensive or people do not
want a treatment plant
in their back yards.
If you're lucky, you will have
several options to choose from
by then comes the question
of the level of decentralization.
So we will have one
or several plants.
In large urban areas it
makes a lot of sense to have
several plants at
different locations.
The mechanical service providers
should be at the core
of the decision.
First, they know all about
the current disposal sites.
Then it is crucial to identify what
are the constraints of their business
for example, problems with traffic,
the average distance and duration
of the trips and the money they
gain from each of them.
They are the ones who can
tell what is practically
and financially feasible.
We have to see that larger treatment
plants require on average longer
haulage distances from the pits,
implying higher costs for
the collection companies.
Companies then have two choices
either increase the tariff
for the households
which may threaten the affordability
of the service
or use closer,
illegal disposal sites.
There are examples of fecal sludge
treatment plants which were never
used because they were too
far away or not accessible.
We talked a lot about data,
but not yet about how to
collect it.
It is not that easy to collect
good quality useful data.
There is a lot of bad quality data
around and it is important to
get your own primary data
as much as possible.
The best way to get accurate
information is to get it from
different sources
and then cross-check.
Data can be gathered through
literature review, semi-structured
interviews, household surveys,
qualitative field observation.
We will see a few more tools
in the next module and you
will find a few interview guides
in the fecal sludge management book.
Finally, what do we
do with our data?
Well, we have to analyze it,
and also it is important
communicate the results in a form
that is understandable
and adjustable by
the different stakeholders.
You will get more insight in
the analysis of the different data
in the respective module
of this course, so we'll
not go any deeper here.
I would like to mention that in
addition to Sundeck's work
there are a number of
tools and tool boxes
under development to
help you in the collection
analysis, and visualization
of your data.
You may have heard
about the FSM toolbox
the world bank's diagnostic
and decision making support tools
about the tool kit
of Sept in India
or WHO sanitation safety plans.
You will find the links to these
and more in the course materials
as well as dedicated modules in
our MOOC on sanitation planning.
Now, let me just show you two ways
to share some of your results.
First, SWOT analysis.
With the SWOT analysis you
systematically analyze the strengths
weaknesses, opportunities,
and threats, for the implementation
of a proper fecal sludge
management scheme
in your city.
Strengths and weaknesses describe
existing situations whereas
opportunities and threats
represent the potential
that you've identified.
You can make this assessment more
systematic by doing it for each
of the enabling
environment components.
Secondly, you were already
introduced to the Shit Flow Diagrams
or SFDs.
This is an effective way
to represent in one figure
the main results of the assessment
of the initial situation and provide
a good advocacy tool
to talk to authorities.
The SFD website is there to
help you make your own SFD
and you can learn more about it
by watching the dedicated module
in our MOOC on sanitation planning.
A large part of your success with
the future of fecal sludge
management scheme
actually depends on the quality
of the assessment of
the initial situation
and how it is communicated.
Don't forget the importance of
the human dimension of
this assessment.
It is the time for first contact
but also the trust building
which is the best way to access
information and get people on board.
It is also paramount for
the selection of the potential
sites for treatment.
Now you got a better picture
of how to collect data
and what to do with it.
I hope that this module helped
you to link some of your learnings
in the course, that you can better
visualize what an integrated
approach practically is and how to
assess the enabling or disabling
conditions.
Creating enabling conditions
has a lot to do with
stakeholder involvement.
That's what we will see
in the next module.
See you then!