Hello and welcome to this module on
stakeholder analysis and engagement.
As you have seen throughout
this course
and as you can see behind me,
there are quite a number
of stakeholders that are linked
to faecal sludge management.
That's one of the main differences
between faecal sludge management
and waste water management.
Faecal sludge management
is much more about people.
Especially, sewers are replaced by
manual and mechanical service providers.
In faecal sludge management, it is
not possible to impose blueprints.
But this is not the only difference.
Often, the role and responsibilities
for faecal sludge management
are much less clear than
for waste waster management.
That's why we need stakeholder analysis,
understand them and engage them.
People in organizations are at
the heart of faecal sludge management.
In this module we will see how to
characterize the key stakeholders,
and their main interests
and constraints.
Then we will see how to determine
the degree
to which they should be engaged
with the participation levels.
Finally, we will see how to engage
them with an introduction
to different
involvement tools.
The stakeholders in a group,
organization, or individual
that can influence
or be influenced
by the faecal sludge
management scheme.
The stakeholder analysis
has identified early
who will be affected by the project
and who could
influence the project,
positively or negatively.
It helps to understand the social
and institutional context.
This part of the stakeholder analysis
is sometimes referred to
as political economy analysis.
The stakeholder analysis also helps
to assess the needs
and to plan for the participation
of the stakeholders.
In a field where the informal
sector often plays an important role
this is also about how to empower
them and bring them on board.
Finally, it is also about meeting
people and building trust.
Let's start with the identification
of the stakeholders.
First, of course, you have
the mechanical and manual emptiers.
Then you have the households,
in a way the customers,
which we could divide in
landlords and tenants.
Moving to the other end of
the sanitation chain,
you have the potential end users,
like farmers
or industries that may use that
as a fuel.
You have then the stakeholders
directly linked to the government
which I may call institutions.
Among them you have the utility,
sometimes named sewage company
and they still don't have
faecal sludge on their agenda.
We have the municipal authorities,
which include
the technical services
and the police.
On the higher level, you have
the regional and national authorities
which may play a role,
especially for
the legal and regulatory
framework.
Next, the four major state actors
who we often find
traditional authorities
and influential leaders
to whom people may be more willing
to listen to.
Then you will also find
non-governmental organizations
active in sanitation,
like NGOs or CBOs.
and also academic institutions,
who often have important advisory role.
And finally, last but not least
you have the international donors
which have an important
decision-making power and in some
countries are literally leading
the faecal sludge management agenda.
Once we identify the stakeholders,
we need to characterize them.
In particular, we want to make sure
to identify
all potential supporters
and opponents of the project
and any vulnerable group
that may not be given a voice.
Typical problems faced by faecal
sludge management stakeholders
are a lack of influence
and recognition.
Think, for example, of manual
emptiers, who typically
operate illegally and even in dark
to avoid being seen.
For the mechanical emptiers,
you have issues such as
the cost of transport, traffic,
or the lack of dumping sites.
Lack of resources and capacities is
often a problem at institutional level.
You may observe tension
between stakeholders
like power games between
institutions, or competition
between private service providers.
Lack of awareness, typically at
household level.
I will let you have a look in the
stakeholder analysis chapter
of the FSM book to see how
you can extract this information.
Something important to look at is
who has an interest
and who has influence,
or lack of influence.
These figures show the
attributes that are relevant
to either interest, influence,
or both.
For example, stakeholder having
an activity linked
to faecal sludge management
have an interest.
Authority that are not directly
related but still have the power
to block the project,
have influence.
Municipal authorities would be
in the middle
having both strong interest
and also influence.
Recognizing this, you can then draw
an influence interest matrix.
So, for example, if a small company
providing an emptying service
has an interest (INAUDIBLE)
faecal sludge management scheme,
but not much influence,
we put it here.
A national entity may have
a strong influence, for example
for delivering permit or fans
although it does not have
the direct interest in the project.
So we would put it here.
Or the municipal authorities,
as we saw,
have both an interest
and influence, so we put it there.
Now the question is how to engage
the stakeholders?
First, we need to define the level
of participation.
There are four main ones,
information which goes one way.
So you give information
to some one.
Consultation, which goes two ways.
So you ask people for their opinion.
Collaboration, where you develop
your project together.
And finally, empowerment or
delegation
where you give power to the others.
In a simplified approach, we can
try to identify appropriate
participation levels, based on
the influence interest matrix.
For example, the stakeholders
located here
with low interest and low influence
just need to be kept informed.
Those with low influence
and high interest
need to be consulted
and sometimes empowered.
Those with a low interest
but high influence,
need to be informed or consulted.
And finally with these, you would
rather (INAUDIBLE) consultation,
collaboration or even delegation
at the end of the process.
Know that the stakeholder analysis
is an iterative process.
So a stakeholder that is here at
the beginning, may gain influence
if it is empowered, and may
end up there.
Typically, this could be the case
with an organized group
of mechanical service providers.
There are different tools
to engage stakeholders.
For example, personal meetings,
household surveys,
focus group discussion, workshops,
site visits,
participatory mapping,
media campaigns,
advocacy or lobbying,
or mediation.
Please refer the faecal study
management book
to learn more about these
involvement tools
and to which level of participation
they correspond.
You may also have a look at
the module
Tools for Institutional and Political
Economy Analysis
for Sanitation Solutions in our MOOC
on Sanitation Planning.
Remember that the goal in the end
is to be able to define
and allocate clear roles
and responsibilities
which the respective stakeholders
will endorse in the long run.
We must be aware and must agree
on what they will have to do
and especially, what they
will have to pay.
You don't want your FSM system
to collapse
because vacuum truck owners
don't agree to pay the tariff,
because emptying fees are
unaffordable for households,
or because the utilities
or authorities did not
secure enough funds to run
your treatment plant.
It sounds logic, but unfortunately
that issues are often the case.
You will learn more about financial
and institutional arrangements
in the two next modules.
What I presented in this module
is a simplified approach
to stakeholder analysis
and involvement
for you to get
introduced the topic.
Of course, there is much more.
You now got a first glimpse into
how to characterize stakeholders,
and into the different
participation levels,
and how this can help you decide
how to involve stakeholders.
Remember that this is iterative
and should be done
throughout the planning process.
Start thinking about who would be
the key stakeholders in your city.
Start mapping the relationships
between them.
Try to think on how you could bring
them in the same table.
The social aspect of faecal
sludge management,
is very important and make sure
that at whatever level you are
you take people's needs
and constraints into account.
As a key final message, I want
to say that it is worth to invest
the time and resources,
to understand and involve the people
because involvement leads
to commitment and project ownership.
Good-bye.