Hi.
I'm Doctor Linda Strande.
I work at Sandec
the Department of Sanitation,
Water and Solid Waste
for Development,
at the Swiss Federal Institute
of Aquatic Science and Technology.
Have you ever wondered
what happens to excreta
after you use the toilet?
- Why sorry!
- Hey, Linda!
I didn't realize
someone was in there.
Hi, I'm Moritz Gold.
I work together
with Linda at Sandec.
We would like to introduce you
to our new MOOC
on faecal sludge management.
40% of the world's population
relies on unsafe
sanitation technologies,
such as  pit latrines
or septic tanks.
Hence, the management
of faecal sludge is imperative
for the protection
of human and environmental health.
Our course provides
a solid introduction
to the essentials
of faecal sludge management.
Following this MOOC,
you'll be equipped to start working
on faecal sludge management
in your city.
with practical tools
that can be applied
and a basis to continue building on.
The course covers aspects
of the service chain;
including collection,
transport, treatment,
and end-users resource recovery
of safe disposal.
This course is part
of the MOOC series
Sanitation, Water
and Solid Waste for Development.
This course is based on information
presented in the book,
"Faecal Sludge Management
Systems Approach
for Implementation and Operation".
Faecal sludge management
is a new and quickly evolving field.
Therefore, this MOOC will include
recent research
and promising examples of successful
faecal sludge management.
All of this information is available
for free on our website.
The course covers
an integrated approach
to faecal sludge management
that it includes
planning and management
along with technology
to ensure that systems
are integrated
into complex and dynamic
urban environments.
Sign up for free to take our course
on faecal sludge management.
To register,
just go to the Coursera website.
We are looking forward
to seeing you soon!