Seismic Hazard
A Resilient Future: Science and Technology
for Disaster Risk Reduction
Hello, my name is João Almeida.
I am a researcher at
the Earthquake Engineering and
Structural Dynamics Laboratories of EPFL.
I am your lecturer for this video
in which I will talk about seismic hazard.
I will first start by recalling
how earthquakes usually occur
and their waves propagate.
I'll then define
seismic hazard and discuss
how we can measure
the size of an earthquake,
namely in terms
of magnitude and intensity.
There are different types of earthquakes.
They can be due to volcanic activity,
collapse of underground cavities,
or even produced by blasts or explosions.
However, the major source
of large earthquakes
is definitely the rupture
of the Earth's crust,
namely in the so-called
interplate earthquakes.
The next few slides
will bring back to memory
what you most probably learned
in primary school.
The Earth is divided in four major layers:
the inner and outer core,
the mantle and the crust.
The 'skin' or the hard outer layer
of our planet is called the lithosphere
and it's made up of the crust
and the cool, dense
and rigid upper part of the mantle.
However, our planet's skin
is not all in one piece.
It is composed of many pieces
covering the surface of the Earth,
called tectonic plates.
These tectonic plates are not immobile.
In fact, the difference in temperature
between the core and the crust,
creates convection currents
that force these plates
to keep slowly moving around
in different directions
at different speeds,
sliding past one another
and bumping into each other.
The edges of these plates
are called plate boundaries.
The boundaries are made up of many faults
and most of the largest earthquakes
around the world,
occur on these faults.
Since the edges of the plate are rough,
they get stuck while
the rest of the plate keeps moving.
When the plate has moved far enough,
a rupture stress is reached at the point
the two mass blocks
on either side of the fault unstick
and slide along the surface of the fault,
with an instantaneous release
of the elastic strain energy.
The point within the Earth
where an earthquake rupture starts
is called hypocenter or focus.
If its depth is up to 60 kilometers,
we say that it is
a superficial earthquake,
while deep ones have hypocenters
between 300 to 700 kilometers.
The epicenter is the point
directly above the hypocenter
at the surface of the Earth.
The energy released in an earthquake
is transmitted
in the form of seismic waves.
Such as, the faster compressional waves P
and the slower transverse waves S,
which propagate inside the Earth,
in a radial direction
undergoing phenomena
of reflection and refraction.
Until now, I've recalled
how earthquakes originate
and their waves propagate.
Seismic hazard refers
to all the physical phenomenon
caused by earthquakes
that may be potentially damaging.
Either directly for human life,
for physical assets,
or in any other social, economic
or even environmental dimension.
They include:
ground shaking,
which can make difficult for us
to stay on our feet--
or more importantly,
make structures collapse.
But also, surface rupture for those cases
where the fault does not remain
buried or hidden
under the uppermost layers
of rock in the crust;
tsunamis, and you may recall
that in the Indian Ocean,
in 2004, as shown in this picture,
or after the recent
Japanese earthquake of 2011;
liquefaction, when a water-saturated soil
temporarily loses its strength
and behaves as a fluid;
or even landslides and rock falls.
Instruments that characterize
the ground motion
have been developed since ancient times.
As Zhang's seismoscope--
where a bronze bowl
drops from one of the eight dragon heads
to the toad's mouth
to indicate the earthquake direction.
In more classical seismographs,
as represented in this sketch,
when an earthquake causes
the ground to shake,
the base of the device shakes too,
but the hanging weight does not.
The relative displacement between
the shaking part of the seismograph
and the motionless part
is what is recorded.
Modern seismometers based on analog
and digital technologies
allow not only to register
the displacements
associated to ground shaking,
but also, ground motion records
of acceleration and velocity.
Besides, these records can be measured
along any two perpendicular
horizontal directions
or even along the vertical axis.
Using the existing
networks of seismometers,
scientists can then determine exactly
where the earthquake was,
based on the speed difference
between the P and S waves,
and by using the method
called triangulation.
When it comes to measuring
the size of an earthquake,
there are basically two measures
that can be employed:
magnitude and intensity.
Magnitude quantifies
the global energy released
by an earthquake,
while intensity expresses
the local earthquake effects,
this is, at a specific site.
It is therefore easy to understand
that for each earthquake,
there is only one magnitude value.
Instead, many parameters can be used
to measure the intensity.
With respect to magnitude
there are several scales.
Although the Richter scale
developed in the 1930s
is perhaps the most famous,
the one which is commonly used
for official purposes
is the moment magnitude,
developed in the 1970s.
It is based on the seismic moment
of the earthquake,
which is proportional
to the average displacement
along the fault
and the size of the area that slipped.
Just to give you a rough estimate
of the amount of released energy,
consider that a magnitude for earthquake
is approximately similar
to the explosion of a small atomic bomb,
within the radius of 100 kilometers.
An increase of one step
on this logarithmic scale,
corresponds to approximately
32 times increase
in terms of the amount of energy.
Which means that, for instance,
a magnitude 7 earthquake
is around 100 times bigger
than a magnitude 5 earthquake.
This should put things
in perspective if I tell you
that a few earthquakes
with a magnitude larger than 9
have been measured over the past 70 years.
The maximum magnitude
registered until today
was approximately of 9.5 in Chile in 1960.
Seismic hazard is, however,
typically expressed
through the intensity
of ground shaking from an earthquake
at a given site,
which can be measured
using a number of parameters,
as stated before.
These can be categorized into two types:
Intensity that is assigned
based on observations,
also known as macroseismic intensity,
and intensity that is measured
from instruments
such as accelerographs, commonly known
as ground motion parameters.
The conversion between observational
and instrumental intensity,
involves much uncertainty.
Let's see why,
by looking in more detail
into each of these categories.
Following the definition of Bolt,
observational intensity
"is a measure of ground shaking
obtained from damage done
to the structures built by humans,
changes in the Earth's surface,
and felt reports."
It is an indirect measure
for ground shaking,
being particularly useful
for historical earthquakes--
this is, where no records
of the ground motions are available,
or for recent earthquakes
in regions where no accelerometers
were installed.
The most famous scale is probably
the Modified Mercalli Intensity (MMI).
However, there are others.
For example, this table
presents the short form
of the European Microseismic Scale, EMS-98
which is a twelve-point scale.
Roman numerals are used
to emphasize the fact
that these scales
are neither continuous, nor linear.
The Level III corresponds
to the level of human perceivability,
while damaging structures
initiate in Level VII.
The top two degrees
are rarely attained, if ever.
This figure on the right
shows the application
of a macroseismic intensity scale
to the Chile earthquake of 2010.
Note that due to local side effects,
the maximum intensity does not
necessarily occur at the epicenter.
Further, one can also observe
the iso-intensity lines
which bound in an approximate manner
a region with one predominant intensity.
For what concerns ground shaking
as recorded by seismic instruments,
a large number of parameters
can be considered.
One can, for instance, take
the maximum absolute value
of the ground acceleration
during an entire earthquake record,
the so-called
peak ground acceleration or PGA,
or any other ground motion parameter,
such as the Peak Ground Velocity
or the Arias Intensity which measures
the energy within the record.
Seismic hazard, however,
is not only characterized
by location and intensity.
Its frequency or probability of occurrence
is also required.
This can be expressed
by the return period T of an earthquake,
which is the mean time
between the occurrence of two earthquakes
with a magnitude equal or larger
than the specified value.
Finally, seismic hazard can be expressed
in the form of hazard maps,
which show the levels of ground motion
with a given probability of exceedance
over a period of time.
This example, for instance,
displays the peak ground acceleration
for a 10 percent exceedance
probability in 50 years,
as obtained for Europe
by the program SHARE.
In a nutshell,
in this video, we have seen
how earthquakes generate
and their waves propagate,
how we can record them,
and how we can measure their size,
namely in terms of
magnitude and intensity.
Many different intensity measures
can be used to express seismic hazard
due to ground shaking
at a given site or region.
Besides, seismic hazard
due to natural earthquakes
can be characterized probabilistically
and it is approximately constant in time.
In other words, the seismic hazard
here in Lausanne, where I live,
is expected to be approximately
the same today
or in one hundred years time.
Does this mean
that the seismic risk of this region,
or any other region,
will also be the same in 100 years?
The answer is no,
and the reason is that seismic hazard
is only one of the components
that influence seismic risk.
I'll explain this in more details
in the video of week 2.
See you there!
Dr. João Almeida and the Cooperation and
Development Center (CODEV) would like to thank
Dr. Helen Crowley and Prof. Rui Pinho,
for providing the technical and
educational input for this video.