Hello, my name is Michael Lehning.
I'm a professor here at EPFL
of Cryospheric Sciences,
and I'm also leading the research units
now on Permafrost
at the WSL Davos,
in fact the SLF in Davos,
and this video will be on floods
and other hydrometeorological
natural hazards.
So in this video we will give you
an introduction to flooding,
then give you a definition
of what flooding is about.
We will quickly talk about
the historic context of flooding,
and then go on to explain
the mechanisms of flood formation.
Consequences of flood
will be touched upon,
and then we will talk about floods
in comparison to other natural hazards,
give you two comparative
examples of flooding,
and then end up
with other hydrological hazards,
cascading hazard events,
and sum up with the main points.
So floods are the most common
of all natural hazards,
and they have affected humans
throughout history.
A formal definition of flood is
the "overflowing by water
of the normal confines of a stream
or other body of water,
or the accumulation of water by drainage
over areas which are not
normally submerged."
In simple words
that means you have water,
and you have abundant water
where you should not have water.
The previous slide gave you the definition
of flood in a narrow context,
but floods are a sort
of hydrometeorological hazard,
and therefore I would also like
to give you a more ample definition
of hydrometeorological hazards.
What you can see here is
why the flood definition
was more in terms of
a physical quantity: abundant water.
The hydrometeorological hazard also includes
the aspect of consequences,
so damage or a disruption to culture,
human lives, or similar.
Let's take a quick look back
at the historical dimension of flooding.
Flood has always kept
the minds of people busy,
and it has always been an event
that was discussed in culture.
The most common reason for flooding
is a high rain intensity,
or the duration of precipitation
exceeding absorption capacity
of soils and surface waters.
But it can also be caused
by storm surges at the coast.
Blocking of rivers is another mechanism
that can cause flooding.
So you don't necessarily have to have
an abundant input of water;
it is also a common cause of flooding
that something blocks
the drainage of water in rivers.
One interesting example
for a cause of flooding is a tsunami,
because the origin is the earthquake
that generates the wave.
But when the wave hits the land,
it causes large flooding.
So sometimes tsunamis are seen
as a hydrological event,
and sometimes they are also seen
as a geophysical event.
Another man-made disaster
related to flooding
are dam overflows and dam failures.
As introduced, an important mechanism
of flood formation is heavy precipitation.
Here we look at an example
from the 2005 flood in Switzerland.
You see here the rain intensity,
or the total accumulated rain
over four days.
We get the values
up to 300 mm in these areas,
maximum precipitation over four days.
When you compare this to typical values
of yearly precipitation in Switzerland,
that range between 500 and 2000 mm,
you can see how extreme
this event was with respect
to generating a lot of water
in a very short amount of time.
The disposition of the soils
in the catchment is very important,
something that is not often looked at.
We see here an example
of a small catchment in Switzerland
that was analyzed in detail
to show how much water
the soils could store away
before producing runoff.
This was before the 2005 event.
What we see here
are areas that can only hold
as much as 40 mm of rain input,
while next to it,
there's also soils that can hold
much more water, up to 200 mm.
So depending on the distribution,
and the relative distribution
of soils with a lot
of water-holding capacity,
and those
with a low water-holding capacity,
the same precipitation event may cause
a completely different response
of the catchment,
and this is important
to take into consideration.
What also sometimes happens is
that this is a function not only
of the previous precipitation,
but also of previous dryness.
Very often it is observed
that very dry soils will not be able
to absorb a lot
of heavy precipitation initially
because they need to be wet first
for the rain to infiltrate.
So it can happen that very dry soils
produce runoff from precipitation
immediately.
We distinguish between damages
and actually beneficial
consequences of flooding.
Within the damages,
we can talk about direct damages,
such as drowning
or infrastructure failures.
Just imagine a flood hitting a house,
and the house collapses.
Then you can easily imagine
that the collapsing house
will cause fatalities.
Other direct consequences
include infrastructure failure
on a larger scale, such as bridges
which then inhibit also
the teams to come in and to help people.
Indirect consequences or damages are often
even more important
than the direct damages,
in particular, because
heavy flooding often damages
the drinking water and sewage systems.
As a consequence of that,
waterborne diseases,
such as cholera and typhus,
may spread more easily,
and as a long-term consequence,
flooding may lead to famines.
On the other hand, you also have
significant benefits from flooding,
in particular, during ancient times.
The fertilization that was caused
through regular flooding
in the Nile, Euphrates, Ganges,
or Yellow River catchments
has been very important
for their respective cultures to develop.
Talking about consequences of flooding,
it's worth mentioning the worst
flooding event in known history.
That happened in China, in 1931,
and killed approximately 3 million people.
This shows you how devastating
an individual flood can be.
But it's also worth mentioning
that floods occur very regularly
and affect large numbers of people.
In the next few slides,
we will see concrete numbers
of how flooding, in comparison
to other natural hazards, affects people.
The numbers, they are not always
consistent between each other,
because there are differences
in how individual organizations
count consequences of flooding.
Sometimes an event
is attributed to flooding,
or to a hydrometeorological event
such as a storm,
and therefore sometimes
different statistics result from that.
But the main message is quite clear,
that a lot of people are regularly
affected by flooding.
So in this slide we see a statistics
of flooding comparison
to other natural hazards.
it is important to realize
that the purple color
is the average between 2001 and 2010,
while the pink color is
an individual year 2010,
which happens to be, in fact,
quite close to the average,
which is not always the case.
What this graph shows you is
that we have flood here, in the middle,
that the total number of affected people
is always very large for flooding,
when compared to other natural hazards.
The only two that generate
comparable numbers
are drought and storms, and, again,
sometimes storms are also counted
as floods and vice versa,
because very often the consequence
of the storm is a flood.
On the other hand, if we see
on the right-hand side of this graph,
the total number of fatalities
is typically not as large
for flooding events
than for geophysical events
such as earthquakes and tsunamis.
For Switzerland, we have
very good statistics with the years
that allow you to distinguish
within hydrological natural hazards
between floods, debris flows, landslides,
and then rock fall, apart from that.
You can see in this graph that flooding
is occurring quite regularly
in Switzerland,
and that it dominates
economic loss in that country.
Now I would like to talk
about two examples,
two particular events, that occured--
one in Switzerland, and one in Pakistan,
and compare those two events
to each other.
For the Switzerland case,
we have already looked
at the rain input,
it was the flooding of 2005,
which was a 100-year event,
approximately.
What does that mean?
A 100-year event means that it has
an approximate return period
of 100 years.
So that means that, on average,
you expect a flood of similar magnitude
to occur every 100 years.
Of course you can have
two or three centuries in a row
where you don't have such a flood,
and then you can get
two or three of these floods
within one decade.
So this 100-year flooding in 2005
in Switzerland caused six fatalities
and a total damage of three billion
Swiss francs in economic loss.
This is significant.
But now let's look
at the Pakistan example.
As you can see from the map,
the flood in Pakistan was larger
in terms of the area
that was affected by the flooding.
But it wasn't that much larger,
so you can see a scale of 500 km.
in the bottom of the slide,
and you can compare to Switzerland,
which has an extension of
about 200 km across the Alps.
Now, if you compare these two floods,
in terms of their return period,
then they are comparable.
Both of them had a precipitation input
that you expect to occur
once in about 100 years.
And that translates also
to runoff magnitudes
that you expect to occur
with a same return period,
so about once in a 100 years.
When we now look
at the 2010 flooding event
in the Indus Basin, in Pakistan,
which extended to neighboring areas
such as China,
then we have a total number
of fatalities of 6,000 people,
and we have 50 billion
US dollar damage.
This is almost three
orders of magnitude more.
So far we have been
concentrating on flooding,
because on a global scale this is
the most important
hydrological natural hazard,
but on a local scale,
there are other natural hazards
that are quite important.
What is important
to consider with all types
of hydrometeorological natural hazards
is that they may experience an increase
in the context of climate change,
and therefore they need
to be looked at in quite some detail.
Towards the end of this video,
I would like to talk
about cascading hazard events.
What is a cascading hazard event?
It is when one natural hazard
triggers another one
with potentially even larger damage.
So you could talk about it
as if that was a more extreme event.
A very famous example is Fukushima, 2011,
when a subsea earthquake caused a tsunami,
and that led, at the end,
to the breakdown
of nuclear infrastructure in Japan,
with well-known catastrophic consequences.
An important feature
of these cascading hazard events
is that they are
very difficult to forecast,
simply because the exact
mechanistic understanding
of how they are connected to each other
is very often not available.
At the end of this video
I would like to summarize
four important points.
Point one: Floods have always been, are,
and will in the future be
major disruptive events,
that can kill people,
that can disrupt
the functioning of a culture,
but they can also have
potential positive consequences.
Floods, avalanches, and debris flows
are all hydrometeorological hazards
that occur because
of an excess in water input.
We learned about different mechanisms,
how they can be formed,
and said that it's not always
only an excess input of water.
But remember, too much water
at a place where it should not be
is the cause for flooding.
Floods typically occur
on quite short time scales,
but the consequences,
they can last for a long time.
They can last a whole season,
or even a whole year.
As you all know, our climate is changing,
and those changes are rapid
in some areas of the world.
Therefore, with the potential
of hydrological natural hazards
being heavily impacted
by those climatic changes,
we need to study them carefully.