We are at the United Nations in Geneva,
to interview Dr. Robert Glasser,
Special Representative
of the UN Secretary-General
for Disaster Risk Reduction.
Dr. Glasser is heading
the United Nations Office
for Disaster Risk Reduction, UNISDR.
UNISDR is the focal point in the UN system
coordinating disaster
reduction activities,
and ensuring synergies
with regional organizations
in the field of socio-economic development
and humanitarian action.
So UNISDR is a UN organization
that focuses on supporting
the reduction of disaster risk.
And it uses, as its foundation,
an international agreement
called the Sendai Framework
for Disaster Risk [Reduction],
which countries signed in 2015,
So with that as the basis,
the scope of work involved
in implementing the Sendai Framework
to reduce disaster risk is enormous.
It ranges from early warning
and preparedness,
and even work within disasters,
to incorporating risk reduction measures
as part of core economic
planning and investment.
It focuses on large-scale
sudden-onset disasters,
protracted disasters,
slow-onset disasters.
It focuses on large-scale, national scale,
sub-national scale,
and it focuses on multiple hazards,
like pandemics,
or radiological nuclear reactor meltdowns,
or climate change, earthquakes, and so on.
So it is such a broad agenda
and in every single one of those areas
there are significant needs
for science and technology.
To give you a few examples:
climate change.
Climate change is projected as actually
already having an impact
on extreme weather events,
a major hazard,
particularly in developing countries
but in wealthy countries as well.
We need to understand better
how climate is going to change,
what patterns it will take,
what impacts the release of CO2,
of greenhouse gas emissions, will have
on tipping points in the climate system.
We need to understand
what impact global warming will have
on the frequency and severity,
or patterns of El Niño, La Niña events,
which are the key source
of weather variability around the world.
So if you just focus on climate change,
understanding those dynamics
are an enormous challenge for science
as we've seen.
If you look at other levels of detail,
if you focus on, say,
the impacts of extreme weather,
like drought,
then there are a whole range
of other issues about
"Okay, well how is drought changing?"
We understand modeling at a global level,
what about a regional level?
What about a sub-regional level?
We can talk about science in terms of
"Okay, these places are now going to
experience more droughts more often."
How do people adapt to that?
Are there different varieties of crops?
Are there water harvesting techniques?
What sorts of technologies and approaches
can be brought to bear?
And science to be underpinning them,
to be brought to bear,
to help people cope with those things.
If we look at sea level ri--
I mean you can go through
every single hazard that you can imagine,
many of which are exacerbated
by climate change--
including the emergence of new disease,
or re-emergence of old disease,
or pandemics--
and there are a range
of scientific and technological challenges
that need to be addressed.
The Paris Agreement on Climate Change,
the SDG, Agenda 2030 agreement
and the Sendai Framework--
all of them have explicit roles
for science and technology.
If you look at the SDGs,
there's a section on technology
and science and technology,
a unique section.
Also within many of the development goals,
the Sustainable Development Goals--
whether it's energy, ecosystems,
anywhere, climate change-- you see that.
Similarly the COP,
of course the whole IPCC process
is fundamentally integrated with science
in terms of some of the isssues
we discussed a moment ago:
modeling climate at sub-regional scale,
the impacts on ecosystems
and human settlements,
these sorts of issues.
And with Sendai as well
there's actually a specific objective
on technological cooperation
and the role of science is really key.
There's a reference to the need
as part of this agreement
to bring together
the science and technology community
to develop innovative solutions
to address these issues.
So number one, science and technology
underpins all three.
A practical-- this is maybe more
at a level of detail--
but a practical integration
between the three
is that the SDGs,
there's a process under way now
to develop indicators
for each of those goals.
And for the Sendai agreement,
there's a similar
inter-governmental process
to development indicators.
And ISDR is ensuring
that we don't duplicate,
that the indicators we're developing
for disaster risk can plug in
to those that are linked to climate change
or the SDGs, particular SDGs.
So there's a lot of effort under way--
at least within the UN system--
to make the process,
to integrate that as much as possible.
If I look at Sendai, I would have to say
that if there is one
fundamental risk treatment
to reduce disaster risk
it is to reduce greenhouse gases
as quickly as possible.
Just because climate change
will have such an existential impact
on everything else, even conflict.
We've seen in the case of the Middle East,
an unprecedented period of drought,
which of course you can't necessarily link
any one event to climate change,
but it's what you'd expect
from climate change.
It triggered a mass migration of hundreds
of thousands of people into cities.
It wasn't the cause of the Syrian crisis,
but it was certainly
a contributing cause of even conflict.
So for me, that absolutely
has to be integrated
and so when we talk
about disaster risk reduction,
we're very much talking about
climate change mitigation
as a risk treatment,
and mitigation,
addressing loss and damage,
adaptation to climate change.
And all of those have fundamental science
and technology issues associated with them.
What are your key messages to researchers
on science and technology for DRR?
The first message
is that what they're doing,
the development of science and technology
on this issue is really important
and urgent because when we talk
about disaster risk,
it's a nice, cold-sounding term,
but it means hundreds
of thousands of deaths.
It means increases in poverty.
It means huge economic losses.
Over 350 billion a year,
which is money that could be spent
on teaching and medicines,
and economic development.
The second message is that
this is not an issue
that you solve in a silo.
Disaster risk, it's multi-hazard risk
and it's social science,
it's physical sci--
it's physicists, it's geologists,
it's psychologists,
it's political scientists.
The only solutions that are going to work
are going to be multidisciplinary,
interdisciplinary.
I was in California-- I'm Australian
but was in California recently--
northern California
having lunch in a restaurant,
and suddenly all the cell phones
went off at once.
And when we looked,
everyone stopped and read their phone.
My phone said, "Tornado heading your way.
Take cover immediately."
And there was a lot of talking
and then everyone
just went back to eating.
I got up and went outside and looked,
and I could see the cloud was moving
in the other direction,
the storm cloud.
But the reason everyone ignored that
was because there had never been a tornado
in that place before,
at least in people's memories,
so they just assumed it must be a mistake.
In this case, it was okay,
but the lesson they learned was
number one, you can ignore warning
even of the highest technology,
the most efficient sort of warning
you could imagine;
and number two, probably next time
they'll do the same thing,
and next time they mightn't be lucky.
So it just highlighted for me
that that element of the psychology,
and the training and the awareness raising
has to go hand in hand with technologies
and other solutions
involving technology and science,
in order for it to be effective.
And if one is missing
then you might as well
not even have the other
because it won't work.
Acknowledgments: The Cooperation and
Development Center (CODEV) would like to thank
the Special Representative of the Secretary-
General (SRSG) for Disaster Risk Reduction,
Dr. Glasser, for his highly valuable
participation in this MOOC.