Professor David Bresch has
a background in Physics.
More than a decade ago,
he joined Swiss Re in Reinsurance,
especially to work
in Natural Catastrophe Modeling.
More recently,
he became professor at ETH-Z,
in the context
of Weather and Climate Risk.
In this video, Professor Bresch will focus
on Catastrophe Modeling related to storms.
Natural catastrophe modeling has
many sources where it started from.
One was just the willingness
to understand things better.
That's more the scientific part
of the story, where people say,
"We would like to understand
how these things come about,
and what might be a consequence
of something happening."
So it's almost the scientific element
of natural catastrophe modeling.
And then you have, on the other side,
you could say those impacted,
be it on the ground or being
those who help them,
who are impacted,
for example, those who provide
financial relief, namely insurers,
and they wanted to better understand
what could all happen,
basically, to our clients,
and how can we better help them
to cope with the situation.
And what we normally do
in the natural catastrophe modeling
community, you might say,
is really to quantify hazard--
how often, and how strong
things can hit you?
Second, where are you?
What are your interests,
your livelihoods,
what matters to you,
be it your life, be it your belongings?
and then also to quantify vulnerability.
And then we play it all
through in a model
by basically simulating artificial storms,
so storms that haven't yet happened,
but could happen,
and hit such a place, and then figure,
"Aha, that would be the wind speed
a scientist tells me
could happen in this place.
That could be the damageability
of a building,
or that could be the necessity
for people to move out temporarily,
and come back after the storm,"
and you can quantify risk
using all these tools.
So what you see
on this short animation is,
first, a layout of exposed assets
in Bangladesh, in a map,
colored from blue to green,
basically where people are,
and then basically you see
a tropical cyclone coming across,
hitting from the coast all these assets,
and where the dots turn
from yellowish to red,
that's where the things are hit
by the tropical cyclone.
And that's what's in the center
of such a natural catastrophe model.
It now simulates
not only one single cyclone--
this was Sidr, in fact, in Bangladesh--
it simulates all kinds
of possible cyclones hitting exposure,
for example, such as on this picture,
and then with that type of an approach,
you can quantify risk much more precisely
and spatially explicit.
Then you can basically use that model
to think about what would happen
if people would build differently.
So you change
the vulnerability of buildings.
Or what would happen
if people were better warned,
warned earlier,
and could basically evacuate?
You can use these models
to quantify these consequences.
On the building side, probably more
on the damage in dollar terms,
but when it comes to people,
in the evacuation and emergency planning,
also how many people,
how many lives could be saved
in such cases, such a kind of event.
And so you can use
this engine to help you
identify the kinds of risk mitigation options
that you might have,
and then figure what would be
a reasonable basket,
or a reasonable group of things
you should implement,
in order to strengthen
your local resiliency
against, for example, tropical cyclones.
Then, interestingly,
you can also use that model
not only for risk today,
you can also put in the model
your development plan,
and say, over time there will be
more people in that place.
Now, if you don't change anything else,
so caeteris paribus:
more people, same hazard,
it will still be more risk,
and so you can also put
in a model climate change.
You can also say the storms
are going to change
in intensity and frequency, and also
that if that's going to increase,
then obviously there is more risk,
so the model can show you
how much more risk there is.
But, interestingly, it will also
tell you that you shape,
and people, local communities
shape their future.
So if they develop in another direction,
take another pathway,
it could be, there will be more people,
but they will not be more vulnerable.
They might build in a different style.
They may be better informed,
better managed on a governance level,
and therefore risk can be maintained
or even reduced in these places.
And so you can also then use these models
to look at the impact side,
"What's the benefit
of a specific intervention?"
and you can also use the same model
to cost that intervention,
and say, "How much
would it cost me to do so?"
So we use this kind of facts, also,
to help local decisionmakers
to build an adaptation strategy,
and underpin this strategy
with an adaptation roadmap:
ultimately, a funding plan.
The contribution of science to that
was to really very well understand
the hazard part of the story.
We're still learning a lot
about the other components of the model.
Especially the vulnerability part
is not so well understood.
It's also much more difficult because
it has a lot to do with social science.
It's culturally extremely different,
so there are societies
which react differently.
The same speed of wind
at the same level of flood,
there are different reactions
by different communities
and constituencies,
and that's absolutely fine,
it just needs to be understood.
And so there is this element of,
on the social science side,
to understand how do communities react
to these kind of exogenous shocks
to their economies and livelihoods.
And then, obviously, the contribution
from the financial services sector,
you could say,
or from the reinsurance
and insurance in particular
is that they added
a certain rigor to these models
to really be able to use these models
as decision tools.
Not all cultures value the present,
the future, and the past
with the same relevance, or weight.
So some cultures
are more rooted in the past,
some more in the present,
and for some,
the future matters more.
And these models bring that
very much on the table.
So for some constituencies,
the emphasis we put
on the future situation, say 2030--
What would climate change
look like by then?
What would your livelihoods
Some people they're not
so much interested in that.
Ten, twenty years down the road
was too long a time scale.
It mattered more
what's currently happening.
And let's be honest,
most OECD-country companies
also operate on, when they say 'strategy,'
they mean five years.
So it's pretty human
to rather look at the present,
and then build it from there.
And let's be honest, many are
at least as much guided
by the past,
rather than by their foresight.
And I think that what we should try,
what the modeling community
tries to bring to the table,
is make better use
of all the things we know already.
So in that sense, often we do not need
even deeper science,
in one of these specific areas,
you could also say silos.
What we really need
is to connect these things.
The model needs to have a purpose,
and a model is not, per se, good or bad.
The question is only is my model
fit for the specific purpose?
Now, you could say a model
that can accommodate
more than one purpose, or a wider purpose,
is probably a bit more powerful model.
But still, good or bad
is too much a normative
kind of a question in that context.
It's more is it fit for purpose?
For example, a global circulation model
in a climate space is fit for purpose
to determine the climate sensitivity
of that weather and climate system.
You ask questions or answer questions,
"Is there human influence,
and how could that play out?"
Now, a natural catastrophe impact model
is much more on the ground,
it's much more specific to say
if a quake is happening,
if a hurricane is happening,
what's the physical consequence?
What's the environmental,
social consequence?
What's ultimately the economic
consequence of things?
And you can always ask
what kind of complexity you really need
in order to tackle your question.
And then there is probably at this point
the simplest model
that is fit for purpose
has definitely an advantage,
just because it's simple
to operate, to use,
and not least, simple to communicate.
And so that's also an element.
I've often seen too many
bells and whistles in these models.
You might get a bit better,
a notch better still,
but if you engage in community dialogue,
and you want models
to be embraced by a community,
you better err on the simpler side,
because that's where there's
a higher buy-in,
and then over time you can still increase,
in specificity or in precision of models.
And, let's be honest, it's quite often
also mock precision,
because it's not so easy
for some of these models
to measure their performance,
because luckily in many places
you haven't seen so many catastrophes,
and so these models are used
to play possible outcomes through,
and they should not so much
be used as predictive tools
to say that's exactly
how it's going to be,
it's more to say it helps us understand
what we can do
about natural catastrophes.
What's really made, I would say,
a tremendous change to that endeavor
in the past decade or so
is that more and more of that data
is openly accessible,
so a lot of the hazard information
you can get for free.
The only thing you need is have
the skills to digest that information.
And then also the cat modeling,
so the engine which puts hazard,
exposure, and vulnerability together,
exists now more and more
in the open space.
One thing to mention
is what I've developed,
since five, six years now, is Climada,
a natural catastrophe
risk assessment model
which builds on a wealth
of openly accessible data,
for example worldwide, all hurricanes,
tropical cyclone events,
as called in other places,
then also, on the earthquake side,
the volcano side.
And basically it provides--
to model natural catastrophes
in quite high resolution,
normally higher resolution
than a kilometer,
almost all over the planet.
What then users have to put in
is their own exposure,
so they have to figure where they are
and what matters to them.
That's something
you cannot impose on people.
So these models need to be open
also in the sense
to digest additional information
that comes from different sources
and constituencies.
And again, important is not only
that the engine is an open piece,
also the interfaces to it are open,
and can easily be changed.
That's why this thing
is developed in MATLAB,
which is an engineering software,
which luckily also has
an open-source version to it.
So those who are not in a position
to pay a MATLAB license,
they can use Octave,
and Octave is
an open-source clone of MATLAB.
So basically anybody who has a laptop
can download all of it for free
from the internet,
and get started, so to say.
But I mentioned, it does need skills,
so it's definitely something
where people with training
in engineering, natural science,
and also social science,
for the impact side,
have an edge, and an advantage.
And I think for those people,
what such a model provides
is in essence a platform,
a platform to bring
all these different components together
to really quantify risk.
How will natural catastrophe models
further develop?
One avenue is clear:
still more comprehensive coverage,
so more perils,
combined perils, for example.
Our models, they do combine
tropical cyclone wind, and surge,
and the heavy downpour,
the excess, the torrential rain,
and you can basically look
at the combined impact of these things.
One thing you also see
is people like to look
at consequential events,
so series of events.
These models do capture them.
You can make them capture them.
But the question is
if a community has been hit once,
it will not be the same afterwards.
And if it's hit three times,
it starts to adapt.
So an interesting avenue would be
agent-based approaches to cat modeling,
to say, hey, these people
being hit by a storm,
they will not sit and wait
for the next one.
They act.
Nowadays, the models
do not incorporate that.
You basically would play it once,
and it would say,
"Aha! That's why people
do something differently,"
but then you would basically
not bring that back to the model.
But that would be an interesting avenue.
So one is definitely the resolution game.
Still, it's not over,
because still it can get better,
going for city, even street resolution;
you do learn something from doing that.
It depends, again,
what you want to do with the model.
So if the model is built,
or should be built,
for the purpose to advise city planners,
then there is ample ground
to improve the quality
with that goal in mind.
But if it's more to say
how can these models help us
better understand
how our development pathways,
in a pretty turbulent world,
could shape out,
then probably this other avenue
of bringing more, you could say,
the socio-economic piece
more actively into the modeling,
is something I see a lot of potential.
Also, linking it up
with economic growth trajectories,
development trajectories,
and how people shape
their own risk landscape,
because currently the models
are pretty static in that sense.
That's a place where I do think
we will see a lot of change
in the next decades or so.