Seismic Risk: Overview and Calculation Models
Hello. This is João Almeida again.
In one past video,
I told you about seismic hazard
and how it could be expressed
by using different intensity parameters.
Additionally, I mentioned
that seismic hazard
was one of the components
required to compute seismic risk.
In this video, I will tell you about
the other components,
namely, exposure and vulnerability,
and briefly explain
how they all come together
to obtain a measure of seismic risk.
I will also give you some examples
of databases and tools
that are currently available to compute
components and risk in general.
Seismic risk can be defined as
"the probability of losses
of different types, due to earthquakes
in a particular region
over a future time period."
Ultimately we are interested
in developing models
that help us estimate
the probability of loss
due to a seismic event
that has not yet occurred.
To do so, we need to identify and assess,
individually, each of the components
that together make up seismic risk.
These components are:
the hazard, exposure, and vulnerability.
The seismic hazard
was discussed in detail in week one.
For what concerns exposure,
these two photos illustrate the concept.
They were taken from the same area.
On the left, back in 1930,
and on the right, more recently in 2005.
It is apparent that unlike seismic hazard,
exposure can be highly variable in time.
Measures of exposure can include
the number of people, GDP,
buildings or others.
And they are described by groups
according to their geographical location,
taxonomy, and value.
Exposure models are based on
global population distribution databases
that consider both urban and rural areas.
The data sources are censuses and surveys
gathered at political
or administrative units level.
Various georeferenced
global databases exist.
They are generated with different methods.
The project, Gridded Population
of the World (GPW),
was the first main effort to create
a global georeferenced
population data set.
Available population data at the lowest
sub-national administrative unit,
is assigned uniformly
across all the grid cells of the unit,
without consideration of the type of area,
urban or rural.
By contrast, the LandScan
Global Population Database
distributes national populations
following a model that takes into account
different coefficients of population
depending on the type of land cover.
The use of aerial photography
and high resolution satellite imagery
helps to improve the collected data.
This database also considers
the average movement of individuals
over 24 hours,
the so-called ambient population.
Finally, the Global Rural-Urban
Mapping Project (GRUMP)
combines the GPW
with census and satellite data
in order to build higher resolution
gridded population data
of urban and rural areas.
Exposure can also be expressed
in terms of the gross domestic product.
The World Bank created
a global gridded distribution of GDP
using GRUMP high resolution
population data.
It includes the sub-national
gross regional product, where available.
Finally, building exposure models
should take into account
not only the different
characteristic building typologies
that can be found around the world,
but also at the local scale,
as these photos taken from
the same city illustrate.
The United States Geological Survey
PAGER system,
to which I will come back
later in this video,
provides a building inventory
with residential buildings'
top distributions
available for different countries.
It uses a variety of sources
such as UN-HABITAT,
housing census, published literature,
expert opinion, and so on.
Finally, reference should also be made
to the Global Exposure Database
of the Global Earthquake Model,
which I will also introduce in this video.
The database structure is made
for accommodating buildings
and people data from the country level,
to the individual building level.
In the first version, the information
on people and the number,
built area and reconstruction cost
of residential
and non-residential buildings,
is aggregated
at the one kilometer resolution.
Data on single buildings
are accessible for some areas.
This availability
will become greater with time.
In a nutshell, exposure expresses
the locations, characteristics,
and the value, count, or area of the assets.
We can now address
the last component required
to compute seismic risk:
vulnerability.
Vulnerability can be quantified
by a vulnerability function,
which describes the distribution of loss,
such as fatalities or repair costs,
with increasing intensity measure levels.
I recall that such intensity
measure levels
express the seismic hazard,
as discussed in week one.
When sufficient data is available,
vulnerability can be further
desegregated into fragility,
and consequence functions.
Fragility expresses the distribution
of physical damage,
given an intensity measure level.
This graph illustrates this point.
For any value of observational intensity
in the Modified Mercalli Intensity Scale,
one can obtain the fraction of buildings
that are expected to show
one of the five physical damage states
indicated in the horizontal axis,
which range from negligible to collapse.
Given one such damage state,
a consequence function,
as exemplified in this figure,
can then be used to obtain
the distribution of loss,
herein expressed, for instance,
in terms of repair to replacement cost.
On the right we can see another example
of a consequence function,
where the number of buildings
heavily damaged
are related to the number of fatalities.
In other words, vulnerability
can be assessed directly
as an independent component,
or then as the aggregation
of these two sub-components.
The approach to be followed will depend on
the availability of data
for the particular region under study.
There are roughly three categories
of methods to develop
the corresponding models:
empirical, analytical,
or those based on expert opinion.
When assessed independently,
vulnerability is typically based
on expert opinion
or on an empirical method.
One can think of an example
of expert opinion as the best estimates
given by a group of similar
earthquake engineering specialists,
on the ratio of repair cost
to replacement cost,
for different building typologies.
Their weighted mean,
based on the experience
and confidence levels
for each building class,
is an expedite way
to obtain vulnerability functions,
that can be used in situations
when damage data is not available.
However, its reliability
in terms of producing
realistic estimates of loss,
is necessarily debatable.
On the other hand, this figure illustrates
a very simple empirical method
to determine vulnerability.
It estimates losses,
shown in terms of number of deaths,
with magnitude from past observations.
The drawbacks of this approach are evident
as it doesn't take into account
the different levels of shaking
across the affected region,
or the associated
distribution of population.
Let us now consider the case
where each sub-component
of the vulnerability is evaluated.
Expert opinion fragility,
which, again, relates an intensity
measure level with a damage state,
has a questionable reliability,
but provides damage probability matrices
with minimal effort.
Empirical fragility is based
on the observed damage data,
which is then related
to observed ground shaking.
Ideal sources of data should include
all of the buildings in a given area,
including the non-damaged ones.
Finally, analytical fragility resorts
to the application of numerical models
to estimate the response
and performance of buildings
under increasing levels
of seismic action.
Consequence functions are generally
expert opinion-based or empirical.
And they are used
to convert damage to loss,
either in terms of repair
or replacement cost, or fatalities.
In summary, vulnerability expresses
the damage and losses
conditional on a given level
of ground motion intensity,
for certain assets.
Finally, the three components,
which we addressed separately,
can then be combined to calculate
the seismic risk.
This is the probability of losses
due to earthquakes.
This probability can be obtained
by calculating the probability
of levels of ground motion
(that is, the seismic hazard)
to which populations
or buildings are subjected
(defined and classified
within the exposure model),
and multiplying this
by the probability of loss,
given a level of ground motion
(that is, the physical vulnerability).
Social, economic, or political factors
that influence vulnerability
should also be taken into account.
One of the most relevant
global collaborative efforts
of the recent years,
in terms of providing tools and resources
for the assessment of earthquake risk
anywhere in the world,
is the Global Earthquake Model, or GEM.
OpenQuake is the GEM suite
of open-source software
for seismic hazard and risk modeling.
It comprises the platform
which allows users to visualize,
explore and share GEM's data sets;
tools and models;
the engine (which is GEM's
state-of-the-art software
for seismic hazard and risk assessment);
and a great variety of modeling tools.
OpenQuake allows to assess losses
not only for single deterministic events
(that is, for specific
earthquake scenarios)
but also considering all probable events,
including classical probabilistic
seismic hazard-based,
and probabilistic event-based,
risk assessment.
The USGS PAGER, which I mentioned earlier
in the context of building inventories,
is an automated system that takes in
seismic data from remote sensors
following significant earthquakes
worldwide,
and provides fatality
and economic loss impact estimates
within 20 to 30 minutes
of the earthquake's occurrence.
That is well in advance
of in situ observations or news accounts,
and that can hence play
a primary alerting role.
Users can also sign up
for earthquake alerts,
for custom geographic regions,
and magnitude ranges
through the USGS
earthquake notification service.
Other seismic risk tools include
the Earthquake Loss Assessment
for Response and Mitigation (QLARM)
which provides loss estimates
for scenario earthquakes
(that is, which are likely
to occur in the future)
and loss estimates for earthquakes
just hours after they happen
anywhere on the planet.
Another tool is
the Earthquake Loss Estimation Routine,
developed as part of a European project,
which provides rapid estimation
of earthquake shaking and losses
in the Euro-Mediterranean region.
In short, what are the main points
that we can take from this video?
Firstly, that the seismic risk
is the aggregation of three components,
namely, the seismic hazard,
the exposure and the vulnerability.
The seismic hazard,
as we discussed in a past video,
is constant in time.
The seismic vulnerability,
which is the only factor that as humans
we can actually try to control,
tends to reduce as, fortunately,
new structures
are usually safer than old ones.
However, since the exposure
or the amount of assets
present in hazard regions can increase
very significantly over time,
the resulting seismic risk can also grow,
overshadowing desirable reductions
on the vulnerability.
Finally, we briefly overviewed
some of the existing software and tools
to model and compute seismic risk
or each of its components
which greatly vary
in complexity and accuracy.
The earthquake engineering community
worldwide, has been
and will continue
to resolutely work on these models,
and on making them
available to the public.
The reduction of seismic vulnerability
must be one common goal of our society.
Thank you for watching this video.
Acknowledgements: I would like to thank
Dr. Helen Crowley and Prof. Rui Pinho
for providing me with technical
and educational input for this video.