Geographic Information Systems
A Resilient Future:
Science and Technology
for Disaster Risk Reduction
This lecture covers
the most fundamental aspects
of geographic information systems
and actually provides a
sort of very short summary
of another of our online courses
called an Introduction
to Geographic Information Systems,
which is for the time being
only available in French.
We would like to recommend you
to refer to this online course,
if at some point you would like
to dig further into these matters.
I will present the two first parts
of the lecture
on the digitazation
of the geographical space
and the storage of the obtained
geographical information,
whereas my colleague,
Stephane, will then continue
with the use of geographical information
in spatial analysis and visualization.
The digitization
of the geographical space
can be seen as a contolled reduction
and simplification process
that turns a complex
three-dimensional reality
into a flat, north-oriented
representation.
This is basically a map only showing
a limited set of selected features,
such as the ski lifts in this example.
This means that this process
depends very much on the thematic content
of the expected result
since the features and processes
to be accounted for
need to be chosen adequately.
The words "features" and "processes"
drive us very naturally
to the two main elements
of geographical information:
on one side,
the crisp, homogeneous features
with a well-defined geometry,
such as points, lines or polygons,
which define actually
the vector or object world,
and, on the other side,
processes or phenomena
with values that are continuously
changing over space
and are therefore
best described by grids and values
which define the raster or image world.
In both cases--vector and raster data--
we need to link
the descriptive information
to a position in space
either in the form of the coordinates
of the vertices of a geometry
or the coordinates of the cells
forming the grid.
These coordinates are defined
within a projection system
that describes
the mathematical transformation
of the three spherical coordinates
(latitude, longitude and distance
to the center of Earth)
to the two coordinates,
easting and northing,
of the two-dimensional space.
Unfortunately the rules of geometry
show that this transformation
cannot be achieved
without loss of information.
Any given projection system
will only preserve
simultaneously directions, areas
and distances in a narrow,
6 degree-wide band.
This is why each country has its own
or several own projection systems.
And in turn this explains
why GIS software need to be able
to handle all kinds of projection systems
and convert coordinates
from one system to another.
The aquisition of position data
is fundamentally based
on traditional land surveying techniques
nowadays complemented by the use
of global positioning systems.
The aquisition of thematic data
can be achieved by direct measurements
or by all kinds of airborne techniques
ranging from remote sensing
to drone surveys.
The provided images
may need geo-referencing
to fit them at the right place
and are often used as a support
to digitize the vectorial
objects of interest.
Numerical information on objects
or phenomena linked to spatial position
need to be stored in computer files
from which the information
will then be retrieved later on.
Geographical information may be stored
in simple, sometimes semistructured, files
with a broad range of file formats
both in the vector
and in the raster world.
The most commonly used
vector file format
is probably the set of files
of the shapefile system
with the .shp files storing
the spatial information,
the .dbf storing the thematic information
and the shape index .shx file.
In the raster world
the most widespread format
is probably the .tiff image format,
either with its spatial
positioning information
embedded in the header of the file
(the so-called GeoTIFF format) or stored
in a separate file, the world file.
As compared to simple files,
a database has the advantage
of providing a data management system
that includes powerful tools
to facilitate manipulation
and querying of the data set.
Databases are also supported
by software engineering tools
used to design and implement
the sometimes complex data structures.
Finally, their major interest is perhaps
to be well suited to deliver data services
in a client-server architecture
when simultaneous and concurrent
addition processes need to be handled.
This is it, and I will now give the floor
to my colleague Stephane.
The first part of this lecture
allows to describe the properties
of phenomena occurring
on the surface of the Earth,
The spatial distribution
of these phenomena
can be either discrete or continuous
and this distinction structures
spatial analysis into fields.
The first one is about object models
used to represent and analyze
discrete spatial distributions.
And the second one is about the modeling
of continuous surfaces
used to represent phenomena
defined at any position in space,
such as altitude or temperature.
Discrete geographic variables
are used to represent
discrete spatial phenomena.
This is the case when the distribution
of the thematic properties
of a given phenomenon
are discontinuous in the geographic space.
The three types of spacial entities
that can represent
discontinuous phenomena
are points, lines, or polylines,
and polygons.
It should be noted
that the same object may be represented
with different primitives,
according to the scale.
The main type of spatial analysis
carried out on discrete
geographic variables
is the measure of spatial dependence.
In 1970 Waldo Tobler
proposed the first law of geography
stating that everything
is related to everything else,
but near things are more related
than distant things.
This law is the foundation
of the fundamental concepts
of spatial dependence
and spatial autocorrelation.
Typical measures
of spatial autocorrelation
include Moran's I,
Geary's C or Ripley's K.
On the territory these indices
characterize the spatial arrangement
of geographic units
according to the value
of a given attribute.
Here with the LISA index, for instance,
red dots representing
soil sampling stations
with high values
of potassium concentration
significantly resemble each other
within a spatial lag of 10 km.
A phenomenon is continuous
when it is defined at every point
of the geographical space
and its properties vary locally
in a gradual and structured way.
Examples include altitude
or soil moisture,
as illustrated on this map.
This type of data
must be acquired by sampling.
Sampling can be random, regular,
carried out according to a regular grid,
along the transact,
or along the pre-existing network.
Once samples are collected,
it is necessary to use inference
and interpolation
to extend the values of point data
to the entire area studied.
Among interpolation methods
are the nearest neighbors,
the triangle network, B-spline function,
or kriging, for example.
The most common
continuous variable is altitude.
The term altitude is commonly used
to mean the height
above sea level of a location,
but in geography the term elevation
is often preferred.
The elevation of the geographic location
is its height
above or below a fixed reference point,
most commonly a reference geoid.
A digital file
containing elevation measures
characterizing
the geo-reference nodes,
or cells, of a regular grid
constitutes a digital elevation model.
There are different ways
to acquire elevation data.
The most common are leveling,
photogrammetry and laser scanning.
More information about these methods
can be found in the MOOC
"Éléments de Géomatique".
Digital elevation models are useful
to provide quantitative measures
of topography.
Global indices can be computed
to characterize a relief in given areas,
like mean elevation, mean slope, distance
between summits of different classes.
And specific algorithms
based on different window sizes
are able to locally measure
the horizontal
and the vertical curvature,
the slope, or the orientation.
All of these indicators
can be represented on maps.
Digital elevation models
also make it possible
to calculate visible areas
from a given location in the landscape,
to carry out shade analysis,
to calculate solar radiation,
to identify drain systems,
to delimit catchment areas
and many other
terrain analytical functions.
After the analytical phase
geographic data and derived indices
must be represented on maps.
This representation
is controlled by rules
most of which have been defined
by Jacques Bertin
in the context of the semiology
of graphics in the seventies.
The main goal of the rules
defined by this semiology
is to build graphical signals
as effective as possible
to communicate information.
The main tools of the semiology of
of graphics are a system of signs,
on one hand, and visual variables,
on the other hand.
This system of signs is composed
of four visual structures,
which are points, lines,
surfaces and volumes,
and whose properties can vary.
Then, there are eight visual variables
that can be used
to differentiate objects in a map.
The use of these variables is limited
by the ability of the human eye
to see differences.
Size differences must be
sufficiently large for map users
to identify high and low values.
Not all the variables
are appropriate for every kind of data.
In particular, only size and location
are truly appropriate
for depicting quantities.
Visual structures and visual variables
are then supported
by different components on the map--
like a title, a cartographic scale,
a commentary and so on--
to improve the transmission of information
and participate in the production
of new knowledge.
We have here a few examples to show
how information on natural hazards
is stored and made available in national
or local regional infrastructures.
This example shows the portal
to the Swiss geographical
information infrastructure
hosting all kinds of detailed layers
on various sorts of natural hazards.
If we look a bit closer to the area
of Martigny in the Rhône river valley,
we can have a closer look
at the flood-prone areas
with a return period of 50 years--
the same thing with a return period
of 100 years,
over bank sedimentation-prone areas,
debris flow areas,
areas that are prone to snow avalanches,
rock-fall-prone areas,
landslide-prone areas, etc., etc.
Another example here
with the canton-wide portal
with specific thematic entrances
showing the danger maps again--
danger maps for flooding,
debris flow, landslides, etc.
Here in the area of Lausanne,
there are basically along the rivers
the most threatened areas.
The same thing in the canton of Neuchâtel
with thematic entrances to danger maps.
The interest of all those danger maps
being to share the same symbology
with a given set of colors
to describe the different danger levels.