Mapping of flood prone areas in Niamey
A Resilient future: Science and Technology
for Disaster Risk Reduction.
Hello, this lesson which is a case study
shows how to use GIS
to map flood prone areas,
in order to make decisions
for land-use planning.
This lesson is based on the analysis
of hydro-meteorological processes
and human settlements.
But this study does not allow
to address in all its facets
the problem of flooding in Niamey.
However, it helps to provide
the competent authorities
with mapping tools
to guide them towards better
flood risk management.
To begin, we must first remember
that Niamey is the capital of Niger.
Niamey, located in the far west
of the country,
with about 1.3 million inhabitants in 2011,
spreads over an area of ​​240 km²,
with an elevation ranging from 180 to 250 meters.
It is bisected by the River Niger,
what has shaped moreover
the development of urban
and suburban areas.
We distinguish that the left bank is
more developed than the right bank.
The left bank, which shelters
four municipal districts,
is a plateau above the river
at an average altitude of 220 meters
and notched with many talwegs,
of which the most important
is that of Gountou Yena,
with north-south direction.
As for the right bank, where
the fifth municipal district is located,
it is an alluvial plain with an average
altitude of 200 meters.
Physiographic features of the city of Niamey
and various associated human and economic
issues
show that floods are, for the most part,
clearly linked to the strong
urban growth over the last thirty years.
Indeed, population growth
and the development of
socio-economic activities
led the city to extend in flood prone areas.
Thus, since the beginning of the seventies,
Niamey has grown on the right bank
of the river,
and the urbanization of
this particularly exposed area
is ongoing.
On the left bank, the very vulnerable
old quarters of Goudel and Saga,
densify and extend through
the allotment of new plots.
The spatial assessment of flood risk
by intersecting hazard and
vulnerability issues
allows mapping of flood risk areas
in the city of Niamey.
Floodings in the Sahel
have become more and more recurrent,
and Niger is not on the sidelines.
During these last few years,
Niger experienced excess rainfall,
with heavy rains causing
unprecedented flooding,
practically in all regions of the country,
including the capital Niamey.
The protective dikes in Niamey
with a height of 5 meters,
on the right bank,
were completely submerged during
the last flood.
These floods caused many deaths,
population displacements and relocations,
destruction of homes and farms.
The hydrology of the Niger River
in Niamey is well known,
thanks to the measuring station in Niamey,
installed since 1928 and regularly
used since 1944.
The hydrological regime has two floods.
The "Malian" floods, which take place
from December to January,
from the top of the basin,
and local flooding that occurs
during the rainy season.
Over the last years,
the local flood has become
increasingly important,
as we see in the image
and is the cause of frequent flooding
during the rainy season.
Local floods are usually caused
by the exceptional peaks of rainfall.
In August 2012, the daily peak of
121 mm caused 28 deaths,
more than 51 000 victims,
more than 4 500 damaged homes,
and more than 250 hectares
of destroyed farms.
The analysis of daily rainfall peaks
in Niamey
reveals a high amplitude
in the variability of the maximum
daily peaks in July and August
from 7 to 121 mm, with peaks
of 50 mm per day
met or exceeded almost every year
since 2000.
What are the factors aggravating
these floods?
We will focus on the factors caused by humans.
These include soil sealing and soil degradation,
particularly in connection with
deforestation and urbanization,
which results in less infiltration
and more runoff.
More important is the spread of Niamey city,
in the main river bed,
which increases the vulnerability
of the city.
You should also add the
maintenance of watercourses,
which induces sedimentation.
We must remember that the concept of risk
is perceived as the possible occurrence
of a hazard on potentially
vulnerable elements.
The study of flood risk is based on
two main points.
First, analysis of hazards,
based on knowledge of natural phenomena
causing damage,
their processes and operations.
In this case, it is important
to analyze the morphological,
topographical, geological, soil and water
features concerning the phenomenon.
Second, the mapping
and assessment of vulnerabilities
of the major elements.
This is to integrate data
on human and socio-economic activities
in the assessment of flood risk,
knowing that flood risk
is at first a social issue.
These two maps,
that is to say, the hazard map
and the elements at risk map,
are combined to determine
the flood prone and flooded areas map,
that is a decision support tool for land-use planning.
Mapping of flood hazard
is based on the analysis
of natural factors,
including morphology, topography,
geology, soil science,
that influence the development
and extent of the flood,
as we said earlier.
Based on the available data,
in the case of this study,
the most relevant hazards
include defining exposure to overflow of
the Niger River
and exposure to the accumulation of runoff waters,
following a downpour.
Thus the hazard of direct overflow
of the river is determined
from the analysis of a series
of historical data
of the Niger flow in Niamey
allowing to define the 100-year flood.
That is to say, a flood that comes
on average every hundred years.
The 100-year flood is often
used as the reference event
for the implementation of
flood risk prevention plans.
The radius of influence of such floods
helps determine the exposure
to overflow of the Niger.
In this study, it is defined within 400 meters.
The linear distance of each
unit relative to the riverbed
determines its level of exposure
and is presented by a buffer zone
on both sides of the river.
The closer the entity is
to the river route,
the stronger its exposure
to overflow.
Regarding the accumulation of water,
the most representative variable here
is the topographic index or Beven index.
It is calculated from the DTM obtained
from the ASTER DEM data.
This is the natural logarithm
of the ratio of the area
at a given point on the slope.
This index provides information
on the spatial distribution of
the accumulation level
of runoff water of each entity.
Other factors are considered constant
and have no notable effects
on the flood phenomena.
They will not be taken into account
in this study.
Once the two maps,
that is to say the overflow hazard
and the accumulation hazard,
are determined, we will build
the map of flood prone areas.
For this, according to the floodability:
low, medium or high,
we will conduct a reclassification
of images,
using the three criteria,
including the factors aggravating the flood,
taking into account
the topographic,
hydrological and hydrogeological elements.
The combination of these two maps,
therefore, determines the Niamey flood prone areas.
One of the most important elements
is the map of elements at risk.
This map was produced
by mapping the dynamics of land use
between 1998 and 2013,
using Landsat TM images of 1998
and Landsat OLI images of 2013.
The goal here is to show that
the settlements have evolved over the years,
thus showing a particular
interesting aspect of this study,
where populations have become vulnerable
because of urban growth.
The supervised classification of images,
followed by a validation by field missions,
made it possible to establish
the land use dynamics.
Then we digitalised buildings
to produce the map of elements at risk.
This map, superimposed
to the digital elevation model,
clearly shows that one part of the city
is on the bed of the River Niger.
The challenges therefore concern
economic and socio-economic activities.
How do we characterize these activities
to determine the map of elements at risk?
Here we have not included
a specific criteria
for government buildings
public and private companies, and homes.
We have considered
the same level of vulnerability.
Even if the vulnerability of the buildings
is considered to be the same,
we can still map the elements at risk,
that will be coupled to the hazards thereafter
to help us make decisions about land-use planning.
One of the most important
findings of this study,
is the flood risk map.
Given the topography, hydrography,
the climate and the Niger River system,
Niamey city is obviously at risk of flooding,
in light of the analysis of this map.
This map is an example of a decision map.
It was established in a very simple way,
but it has the advantage of locating
the flood prone areas of Niamey.
It may serve as a basis
in future land use/plot allocations
in areas along the river,
while avoiding the dangerous areas.
What can we learn from this case study?
We used GIS
for mapping flood prone areas
in Niamey, Niger.
We also observed that
there is strong urban growth along the river,
over recent years.
This has accentuated land
and population vulnerability.
This document can be made
available to policymakers,
and this simple map shows
the areas vulnerable to flooding,
in order to take preventive measures against floods,
which is a natural hazard
that affects all countries of the world.
Even Niger, a Sahelian country,
is affected by floods
near the main bed of River Niger,
and because of uncontrolled
urbanization in these areas.