DETERMINISTIC VS. PROBABILISTIC MODELING
A Resilient Future: Science and Technology
for Disaster Risk Reduction
Hi, in this additional material video,
Professor David Bresch will explain
the difference between deterministic
and probabilistic modeling.
Yeah-- when we talk about
natural catastrophe modeling
That's an extremely fuzzy thing.
I often say, as soon as you take the back of
an envelope and put a number down,
that's a model.
It starts even earlier, when I talk about
risk, I try to build
a shared mental model
with the audience to say,
think about hurricanes,
think about people on the ground.
Think about how they might react to it.
That's your idea model of how a hurricane
hits an exposed coastal population.
And now what you do in modeling
is basically,
just making that more rigorous.
Instead of saying,
think about the hurricane,
you put down a footprint
on a hurricane, on a map.
And instead of thinking about people
being somewhere,
you say, 'That's exactly the coordinate,
where these houses are.
That's exactly the coordinate
of the school building.
of the road connecting them.'
So you build the model by basically
putting things more precisely in context.
And so you can use these models
in a deterministic sense,
that you could use them as they're often
used, for example,
in warning application,
that you would take a protected path
of a hurricane,
put it in such a model
and say, 'Ah-ha! If the storm
comes along that way,
these are the people that will be affected
and that's how strongly
they will be affected.'
So that's a deterministic way of using
such a model is by putting
one single event in.
It can also be a historic event,
you can also replay say
Cyclone Sidr in Bangladesh
and see what would happen
if that historic storm
happened again today.
That would still be a deterministic
application of a model.
Now, since luckily we haven't seen
all the bad things happening,
but we should be better prepared,
very likely.
We can use these models also
in a probabilistic sense.
Probabilistic in the sense to say,
What else could happen to a place?
Do we really exactly understand
where people are?
Do we exactly understand how they fare
in case of an event?
And you can start to play
with the parameters in your model.
And you can also ask the question,
What would happen if the storm
comes from another direction?
And so you can build a probabilistic
set of storms;
you can build a lot of artificial storms--
these are physically consistent events,
so they're not impossible to happen
but luckily we haven't seen them--
and you can play it all through,
but now not for a historic event
or for single event, for many thousandths
of possible manifestations of nature
you could say.
And therefore, you can test all your risk
management options,
not only against the past or against
a specific single prediction,
you can also test your specific options,
for example,
is it worth to, for example,
evacuate earlier, five days early,
is that better or worse?
Hard to say if you only compare
with one event.
But in such a model, you can play through
all the thousands of possible storms
that could hit that coastal stretch.
You probably would learn, 'Ah-ha,
if you're able to warn a day earlier,
you can save so many more lives.'
And so you can use these probabilistic
models to, in essence,
play through many kind of possible
future outcomes
and therefore you have an ability
to play through your options
and therefore you have the option
to get better at understanding
your options, and ultimately,
it can help you in decision-making:
in a sense, Should I now really
implement that option or not?
Because I would know cost and benefit
much better that way.
In order to illustrate the difference between
a deterministic and a probabilistic model,
the easiest way is to look at the
situation in the North Indian Ocean,
where you have only a few storms
recorded in consistent way
in the past-- these few red lines
there and that's good enough
to get the first impression.
It's good enough to figure
where there might be people at risk.
But it's not good enough to do
a proper modeling of risk
in a higher spatial
and temporal resolution.
And that's why when you then build
a probabilistic model,
you try to generate artificial storms
that are physically consistent,
and these are all the black spaghettis
or dark blue spaghettis,
which fill all the gaps.
And they basically happen over a timescale
of over five thousand years.
Not in the future, but more to say,
would we repeat next year,
five thousand times, then if we would put
it all on the same map,
it would look that dark blue.
So it's not to say the probabilistic storm
has more frequency than an historic storm.
It's more one way to render the--
you could say the coverage
of a probabilistic model
on a single slide.