Hi. In this video
Professor David Bresch from ETH-Z
will talk about insurance and reinsurance
in the context of disaster risk reduction.
So insurance, in essence,
puts a price tag on risk.
It means it does bring risk transparencies
so with that it helps people
better understand the risk
and it also helps them, obviously,
to share some of that risk.
That's what the insurance market
is all about.
Insurance therefore builds very strongly
on the concept of trust,
of mutual trust, of those
who pay a premium now
in order to be indemnified
in case of a large catastrophe
some time in the future.
Or if luck prevails,
they never have to get compensated
and that's why the premium
is normally quite low
compared to other means of dealing with
natural catastrophes,
especially compared to
waiting until things happen
and then try to sort it all out.
But honestly, insurance
doesn't operate in a vacuum.
So if risks are too high,
if they're too frequently happening
people are not prepared at all
and if the consequence of a catastrophe
hitting a place is tremendous,
insurance comes to its limits, obviously.
This price tag mechanism,
in the sense that if prevention
to a right level is in place
then it lowers the price for insurance
and at the same time
then insurance is a very effective means
to cope with the financial consequences
of natural catastrophes, for example.
It does not help in other dimensions.
So it doesn't protect people
from being affected.
It also doesn't protect directly
their livelihoods.
It only helps them
getting back on their feet
after an event
on the financial dimension of things.
And that's very important
to keep that in mind
and only see
that insurance has a role to play
but it doesn't play this role in isolation.
So insurance as a mechanism
builds on the concept of insurability.
One I mentioned already--
there need to be many
similarly exposed risks
such that the law
of large numbers is playing
and the statistics are kind of performing
in a sense that if you want to insure
one single individual and nobody else
it's much harder to figure how that
exactly should all play out,
than if thousands of people
similarly exposed--
say, all of them exposed
to some extent to hurricanes,
tropical cyclone or cyclones
depending on what part of the planet-- typhoons--
what part of the planet you are--
then you basically have
that law of large numbers,
which means it's easier
to also assess risk.
So number two in reinsurance and insurance
is the ability to quantify risk
because otherwise it's very hard
to figure what the premium might be
and what the financial arrangement
should look like
in order to deal with
that type of a catastrophe.
So number two
is the assessibility of risk.
Can it be quantified?
Can there be ultimately
put a price tag to things?
We use-- and we might come to that
in a second-- a lot of models
to determine this kind of the equation.
And then absolutely important,
absolutely key for insurance
is that the risk
needs to happen by chance.
If the insured can influence the outcome,
there's no alignment of interest,
then you could basically insure
with-- trigger, say, a fire,
the building burns down,
and he gets a cheap way to rebuild.
So you have to put measures in place
such that neither the insured
nor the insurer can influence the outcome
or trigger the insured event.
And the last one is commercial liability,
again, for both sides.
You can, in essence, insure things
that happen more than once a year.
It's just very costly to do so.
And then the ability and the willingness
to pay for the insured,
those who are seeking insurance
might be a bit limited, so frankly
it's just commercially
not attractive to do so.
And on the other hand,
if people are not willing to pay
anything for insurance
then it's very hard to operate
for the insurance company
because they do need
the commensurate means
in order to pay claims.
There are different forms of insurance.
You can either insure things
once they have happened,
in a sense that you indemnify people
for their damages.
Or you can also not directly
compensate them for their loss or damage,
you can also pre-arrange
just an amount of money
you're going to pay after an event.
You often have that in life insurance
where there is,
if there are calamities in life
it's a lump sum you get if, say,
somebody in your family dies.
And also in the natural
catastrophe insurance
there's what we call parametric insurance
where you would say
"We measure the intensity of a storm
and if that storm is a heavy storm
you're entitled to so many dollars
of compensation."
It's an easier arrangement, in a sense,
you do not need to wait
to adjust the damage, the claim,
to the exact location
and how it played out
and people have to reconstruct.
In that sense, it pays more immediately.
Fast payment, easy in execution.
The problem is, it could also be
you have bigger damage at your home
than what you are entitled to receive.
So what we call basis risk--
the difference then between
your amount you're entitled to get
and your incurred damage.
And so that's an element
in parametric insurance
people should be aware of.
But often the speed to execution
and the easy arrangements around that
do play in favor of parametric insurance.
Not so much-- and then we come to
to who gets insured--
not so much for the single individual
because you, if you own only one home
you very likely
would like to get compensated
to be able to rebuild.
And if then by chance,
the hurricane wasn't that strong
at your doorstep, and you get only
half the compensation,
in the parametric sense,
that's not very much helping you.
But the more you, again, aggregate risk,
say, for a city, for a region,
for a country, a parametric cover
is an extremely powerful tool.
That's what we've done
especially in the Caribbean,
since, I think, 2009, with the Caribbean
Catastrophe Risk Insurance Facility,
there's a mechanism
which compensates 16 states
against hurricanes,
all on a parametric basis.
So the hurricane hits the place,
scientists and
the meteorological organizations
measure the intensity of the event
and a couple of weeks after
the payment is made
to the government's balance sheet.
And in that sense,
it is a very fast track mechanism
to get post-disaster finance
which are on pre-arranged terms
or pre-agreed terms.
A single individual on the ground
normally seeks insurance
from a local insurance company.
And the local insurance company
therefore insures thousands of people,
say, in a region, in a country, in a city.
Now if that particular city or region
is hit by a large catastrophe
be it an earthquake, be it a hurricane,
a large scale flood,
many of these risks will be hit
at the same time by the same event.
So that insurance company has to pay
a lot of claims at the same time
and that will very likely stress
the balance sheet
of the insurance company
or even exceed its capacity
to deal with such kind of an event.
And that's why insurance companies
do reinsure themselves
with even larger reinsurance companies
who operate on a global scale.
So while one city might be affected by,
say, a strong hurricane,
all the other thousands of cities
in a portfolio
of that reinsurance company,
are not affected.
And therefore a reinsurance company
does diversify risk
of an insurance company
and provides an insurance company
with capital at much lowered cost
than what they have to borrow locally
as even the borrowers will be in stress
if something is happening.
So in that sense, insurance
and reinsurance play together
to absorb larger quantities
of natural catastrophe risk.
In many places on the planet,
also the boundary conditions,
special legal certainty
is not so much there.
So people are not so sure,
this game of trust
where they would pay premium over years
they would ever get something back.
Insurance is not the first option.
It's really awareness,
early warning systems,
that's where you make the huge difference
and that's where you'll save
the lives firsthand.
But once you've done that
it's absolutely reasonable to think about
city planning, regional planning
and how you play with
all these different constituencies
to better help them perform better,
so to say, in the next catastrophe.
And only once these elements are in place
then mechanisms--
be it micro or macro insurance--
can make a difference.
And that's what we're then also working on
to figure what kind of arrangements
would now help people,
first, getting better
at managing risk themselves,
and then second, allowing them to share
the remaining part of risk
with other communities,
first within the country
but then also across the border.