Hello!
In this video, we will be discussing
the topic of early warning systems.
After some definitions, we will address
the need for people-centered
early warning systems.
Doctor Holger Frey
from the University of Zurich
will share his views
on early warning systems
in terms of what [their] role, complexity
and crucial elements [are].
Finally, some of the remaining challenges
regarding improvement
of early warning systems
will be addressed.
An early warning system
can be defined
as the set of capacities
needed to generate
and disseminate timely and meaningful
warning information to enable individuals,
communities and organizations
threatened by a hazard to prepare
and to act appropriately
and in sufficient time
to reduce the possibility of harm or loss.
Following the 2004 Indian Ocean tsunami
and after the third International
Conference on Early Warning
that took place in 2006,
early warning systems are considered
effective if they are people-centered.
This means that people should be able
to easily understand and access them
in a timely manner.
Very importantly, early warning systems
also need to be tied
to specific response actions.
Early warning systems
should be end to end,
that is to say,
encompassing a complete process
starting at the hazard assessment
and finishing at the community response.
People-centered early warning systems
are composed of four elements:
risk knowledge, monitoring
and warning service,
dissemination and communication,
and response capability.
Risk knowledge can be built, for example,
by conducting applied research,
compiling historical databases,
and performing risk assessments.
Timely early warning systems
are based on forecasts.
Those require observational data
and monitoring, modeling,
and situational awareness.
Additionally, effective
early warning systems
are those that are embedded
in the risk management plan,
specifying the institutional
and operational arrangements.
The dissemination
and communication elements
of a people-centered early warning system
refer to the way the warnings are issued,
presented and communicated.
The effectiveness also depends
on the content of the message
and the consideration
of the target audience
characteristics and needs.
Finally, the response capability
of a community
depends on the risk perception
and education of the people
as well as existence of response plans.
Many technologies can be used
in early warning systems.
These can be based, for example,
on sensors, satellite data
and GIS, crowd-sourcing and models.
Mobile technology allows us
to warn people through text messages
and alarm appliances can allow people
and systems to take actions
to protect life and property
from destruction.
Even a few minutes of warning
can enable protective actions,
such as moving to safe locations,
automated systems that ensure
elevator doors to remain open,
and power infrastructures to be protected.
With advanced warning,
emergency personnel
can start to prepare and prioritize
the response decisions.
Moreover, communication sciences,
social sciences, or management sciences
can help us to enhance the effectiveness
of early warning systems.
And now you will hear Dr. Holger Frey
presenting his view
on early warning systems.
Dr. Frey is a research associate
at the department of Geography
at University of Zürich in Switzerland.
One of his research focuses
is on early warning systems
for different mass movement processes
in mountain regions
in the Andes, Himalayas, and central Asia.
I see early warning system
as a very good opportunity, actually,
to complement existing
hazard risk reduction
or disaster risk reduction measures.
In the past, at least in the field
of high mountain hazards,
we had a lot of efforts going towards
the physical mitigations,
structural measures,
bridges or walls that were built,
and early warning system
is really a different kind of system
that tries to lower the exposure
and the vulnerability
of the exposed population.
Early warning system consists of such
a wide variety of different systems.
The most simple system is a person
standing somewhere
and observing something with
a communication device in his hands,
and on the other end of the spectrum
we have really global early warning system
for instance, considering tsunamis,
really involving different countries,
different continents,
these are really complex systems.
Early warning systems
are highly complex systems
because they involve
not only technical components
but also institutional,
legal and social aspects.
So if we talk about early warning systems,
very often, we only think
about the technical devices,
but actually, it's very important
for successful implementation
to also consider
the institutional context,
the legal framework of the place
where it is implemented
and also the social aspects,
the social components are very critical
to finally achieve a positive
and effective response in the end.
And because it's so interdisciplinary,
that makes early warning systems
very complex systems.
A fundamental aspect
of every early warning system,
basically a prerequirement for having
a successful implementation
is a detailed understanding
of the process,
a detailed understanding
of the hazard situation,
of the risk, of the vulnerability,
so really a good process understanding.
And this is where we need science
and models to understand the system
and also to be able to design, in the end,
successful early warning systems.
On the technological side,
every early warning system
includes measurement sensor
that measure any particular value,
parameter of the environment.
This depends of the type of the system
and typically this involves
not only one sensor
but a bunch of sensor
also to have a redundancy
that are placed somewhere,
distributed wherever it is appropriate
to measure environmental parameters.
Then we have communication technology.
This means we need communication networks.
This can be independent,
autonomous radio communication,
can be satellite communication,
can be public communicaiton networks,
as our cell phones, internet, whatever
this depends as well on the system.
Then every early warning system
has a center, a data center,
where all the information is collected,
stored, maybe processed,
made available to the stakeholders,
to the authorities, to the actors
and finally this also the place where
normally alerts or alarms are emitted
or decisions are taken.
And in the end, most of the systems
also involve an alert
or an alarm network system.
This could be sirens, this could be mass
communication devices, mobile phones,
radio, TV, whatever,
this depends on the system,
but a certain network to communicate,
or disseminate the alerts or alarms.
And what is crucial and applies
to all these components,
these hardware technical components,
is the energy supply because very critical
for early warning system
is that we have at any moment,
under any circumstances
sufficient energy to run
the system, actually.
And this is also must be true
on the conditions of a blackout,
on the conditions of long-term
bad weather situations
where we don't have much energy available
for solar radiation.
These are crucial
for a successful implementation.
Considering the variety of early warning
systems that are available,
it's probably not possible
to give an average number of years
that an early warning system can operate.
Actually, it is also not even
the need for each early warning system
to have a long-term perspective,
consider situations like a landslide
or rockfall situation,
where it's probably important
that for an imminent case
to have an early warning system
but few weeks, few months later
the event happens,
and afterwards, the early warning system
is not needed anymore,
So, there are situations where
it's not really an aim or a requirement
of the system to be long-term.
On the other hand, there are of course
systems which really need to have
a long-term perspective
and to achieve a long-term perspective,
it's important to first
have sustainable financing,
also regarding
the maintenance of the system,
second to also really work
with the system, so the authorities
need to constantly use the system,
to train and also to know what to do
in case of an event.
And third one is very important
is also to regularly check
whether the system is still adequate,
whether the hazard situation has changed,
whether the vulnerability,
exposure situation has changed,
and if all these reconditions
are considered,
early warning systems
can consist for many years.
In my view, very critical and probably
most critical component is to achieve
an effective response by the population.
And to achieve such an effective,
positive and good response
really involves strong involvement,
strong collaboration
with the potentially affected population.
So it's not sufficient to only collaborate
with the authorities,
this is required as well,
the institutional side,
but really, we need to get
in touch with the local population,
the local communities.
Especially in many contexts,
we are working in contexts
where local population
has low confidence to the authorities,
low confidence to the government
and this is where we really need
to inform them, work with them,
train them to achieve a positive repsonse,
also that they see the benefit
of the early warning system
for themself and this is really critical
and very demanding
and critical aspect of early warning.
Indeed, improving this last mile
of early warning systems
was identified by the DRR community
as one of the major gaps to focus on.
You will see in the next video
an initiative aiming to close that gap.
In addition to improving the four elements
of people-centered early warning systems,
the use of science and technology
should help to take into account
the interrelated effects of disasters
that occur simultaneously
or accumulate over time
through multi-hazards early warning systems.
In ths video, we have seen
that early warning systems
should be people-centered
and that they are complex
and interdisciplinary.
Improving the response of communities
through their early involvement is key.
Science and technology
has an important role to play
to improve early warning systems
and, in particular, to develop
multi-hazards early warning systems.