I am Max Wyss, I started my career
in Switzerland
In Zürich, I got a diploma from
the Federal Institute of Technology
and later became a seismologist.
Now I'm retired and I would like
to give back a little bit of my expert
knowledge to society.
The way I do this is by estimating losses
immediately after earthquakes.
What does immediately mean?
It means in 30 minutes I make an estimate
of how many people are dead,
how many people are injured.
And that is transmitted
to first responders
who then can get fast onto the scene.
Very first thing that happens is,
the earthquake itself.
Houses collapse,
people are hurt, endangered,
but in the world,
nobody knows anything about this.
Now I get a message by SMS,
I have telephones here, two,
so in case one is failing
then the other is still reporting,
and I calculate how many dead,
how many injured,
approximately, that's my estimate.
And I transmit this to anyone
who wants to receive this message.
The important thing of course is
that first responders look at my message,
what is my message?
Look at this slide now.
On the left top is the input,
epicenter, depth, magnitude,
I need to know that to calculate
what's on the top right.
The number of fatalities,
the number of injured
as I think it is and in the middle
we have a map of mean damage
for every settlement in my dataset.
The damage to houses is important,
because it's buildings that collapse
that kill people,
the earthquake itself does not.
In order to make this calculation,
we have to have information
for the whole world.
This slide simply shows a black dot
for every settlement that
we have in the dataset,
and these are nearly
two million settlements.
What do we know for settlement?
Coordinates, name, number of people
and a model for the buildings
present in the settlement.
Now I want to tell you quickly
what actually happens.
First you see an earthquake happens,
waves are travelling through the earth,
and they have to arrive at stations.
That takes a few minutes,
once they arrive,
international locations like,
the US geological survey
or the center in Germany in Potsdam,
calculates the episode,
and this is X and Y
is latitude, longitude,
Z is depth, M is magnitude.
Now we have a first model
of the earthquake itself,
a simple model,
just a point source X and Y.
Next now I get that information,
next I have to consider
the transmission of seismic waves
through the earth.
Sometimes in some places
the transmission is good,
in other places less good
and if I know that
I can build that in my program,
it's programmed and I can choose
different attenuation, one calls this,
transmission properties.
From this I calculate the impact
on the buildings
and that is the most important thing
because the impact on the buildings
is what make damage to the buildings
if the building collapses it kills people,
its not the earthquake itself.
So I have to know how many people
so the next thing is,
the impact on the people
and I calculate the probablity
how many are dead,
how many injured
and so then, our result are,
building damage
and fatalities and injured.
That's the QLARM job and I framed it here
so that you see clearly what the QLARM job
is. At the very top is the input I get,
now I framed the part that I do,
and at the bottom you see
the response. It is out of my hands,
I then hope that the first responders
and the government, the authorities
in the countries affected make the right
decision to the ultimate aim
at the bottom right,
you see, helping the people
who have been impacted by this earthquake.
So here we have a model of a big city,
big cities are always the top concern
for some people because of course,
big cities are where most people live,
big cities are where the greatest
casualties occur.
And it's also a point where one
can go to and say,
"that is the worst case
in this earthquake,"
and this is just an example to show you.
This case Lima, Peru,
it is close to an earthquake belt
so we make a model for a magnitude
8.5 and what do we calculate?
We calculate the mortality,
in each district of the city.
What is a district?
It's a predefined area of administration.
So actually it's not geology,
you would like to have predefined volume
of bad soil or good soil or different
building properties,
the villa district is different
from the industrial district,
which is different from downtown
a mixture of buildings,
but we don't have that information,
that's what we would like,
so here I just showed you,
how is the mortality to be expected
in different administrative districts.
In Mexico, we know,
everybody knows
that there is a trench offshore
the western coast of Mexico,
that produces large earthquakes.
Historically there has been
a really large earthquake
about 500 kilometers in rupture length.
So I model an earthquake
that you see here in,
as a rupture of 500 kilometers
and give it a magnitude
of approximately nine,
magnitude nine is a pretty much
at the upper level, the maximum
that we can expect.
And here is a map of mean damage,
red of course terrible situation,
blue is minor.
Now I think the value
of a map like this is,
that we have an idea
of what should first responders,
what should medical people,
hospitals expect to happen,
what should they be ready for?
It is also clear that we don't have enough
information to do the best job we could do
we could do a much better job
if we had more information.
And especially we would like
to calculate losses in hospitals
so that the first responders
are not transporting all the injured
to the wrong hospital,
we would like to calculate
the damage in schools,
because the children
are the most precious part of society.
And so we think that,
we need better data,
and we need support
from the population in getting that,
and if we do then we have
very good estimates of future losses
of earthquakes that are likely to happen.
And we would like the population
and the governments to pay attention,
and improve their building structures,
in those places where we expect
great damaging earthquakes in the future.