Hi, Jacobo Quintanilla is
the Community Engagement Advisor
at the International Committee
of the Red Cross.
In this video, he will talk
about ICT innovations
for emergency response.
Talking about technologies
for disaster response management,
I think we need to start looking
into, first and foremost, how communities
use technology and what technology
is in the hands of communities today.
Obviously, this question
cannot be answered
without talking about
the role of mobile technology
and how mobile technology
has revolutionized
the way we understand the world
and the way we communicate,
the way people are able
to coordinate around response,
share information and start
organizing their own response.
There are more mobile phones
than people today.
And I think mobile phones
have helped people tremendously
to share information that is critical
before a disaster happens,
and also start organizing
and coordinating their own response.
Mobile technology is also enabling people
to demand greater accountability
and participation,
not just from their own governments
but also from the media
and from humanitarian responders
like the International Committee
of the Red Cross.
One of the most interesting features
when talking about technology,
including mobile technology,
is who has and who has not access
to technology.
We said there are more mobile phones
than people around the world.
That does not mean that every single human
has access to a mobile phone.
What happens to those
who do not have access to technology,
particularly mobile phones?
And we can think of the most
underprivileged and probably
most need of assistance
who are those who don't have
access to technology.
Think of women, think of younger groups.
Think of the elderly,
think of the disabled.
We cannot assume because mobile phone
is pretty much ubiquitous,
that that actually affects
and people have access equally.
When we talk about technologies
for disaster response
and disaster management,
I think one of the first things
that we need to take into consideration
from my community's perspective is
how people are able to access energy
and how to reconnect
within their own communities.
Something that has emerged
as a big issue, finally,
within the humanitarian sector is the role
of energy and connectivity
as form of aid in their own right.
So we can talk as much as we want
about access to mobile technology,
about smartphones,
the internet of things,
but if people, at the time
when they need it the most,
cannot trust the mobile phones--
they cannot connect to the outside world--
I think we are certainly
missing a big important point.
We need to increasingly,
more and more,
look into the role of energy connectivity
and how we can provide energy
and connectivity as an enabling factor
for people to be able to coordinate,
to start organizing their response,
to communicate with the outside world.
When we look at technologies
for disaster response
and disaster management,
we are looking into
the latest emerging technology,
we are looking about
the Internet of things,
we are looking at interconnected devices
that are able to transfer data.
I think we still need to really
make a strong point
for so-called traditional technology
such as radio.
Being FM radio or shortwave radio,
in many countries around the world
is still the technology
that has proved to work the best
for disaster response and to a
certain degree disaster management
in terms of sharing life saving,
useful and actionable information
for disaster affected communities.
This also helps create spaces
for dialogue between local communities
and responders.
Being a government and also international
and local humanitarian organizations.
And the beauty of radio
is that you don't need to be literate,
you don't need to be able
to necessarily own an expensive device.
And this provides the space
for dialogue and conversation.
It's not just about we telling them
what they need to know.
It's also about creating
a two-way communication
between local communities
and disaster responders.
I think we need to
put at the center of anything we do,
local communities themselves.
One of the interesting turns
of events in recent years
is to reinvigorate the discussion
about the role of local communities
as disaster responders,
as communities who always respond first.
It is interesting that we are calling
attention to this particular issue
because it has always been like that.
As an interesting part
that technology brings
into this equation is that
finally it seems that we are
paying more attention to all the different
questions and capacities
that people always had.
The difference is that 40 or 50 years ago
in Biafra, people didn't have
the opportunities to make
their voices heard that they have today--
in places like Burundi,
in places like the Philippines,
in places like Yemen.
There's been a-- particularly since Haiti,
even though people getting online
and collaborating is not something
that happened just from Haiti--
but since the earthquake in Haiti
in 2010, we saw an emerging group
of volunteer and technical communities
that crafted this new way of working,
what is known as crowd sourcing.
So communities online
that put themselves to tasks
to try to really help communities
in need of assistance.
Social media is transforming--
has transformed-- the world.
Network collaboration,
which is the backbone of the internet,
is really transforming the way
we communicate across the globe,
the way we are able to access knowledge,
the way we are able to share our opinions,
the way we are able to prepare,
respond and recover
from natural disasters
and conflict situations.
I think the question is still,
when it gets to social media,
is the amount of data
which is circulating every single day
all around the world,
in terms of Tweets,
in terms of Instagram posts,
in terms of Facebook messages,
in terms of everything.
From disaster preparedness
and disaster management perspective,
I think the challenge for communities
is to actually go through
what is good from what is accurate.
One of the most important factors
to take into consideration is that, yes,
the world is a much more
interconnected place,
but do we know better,
do we know more?
So it is important to look into
connectivity and access to social media,
not just as a good in it's own right,
the question is the content.
What is the water
that goes through the pipes?
We have an incredible network
around the world,
but what is the content
that people need to know
at a time when knowing
the right answer to some questions
can be the difference
between life and death.
Is there an alternative to social media?
That's a very interesting question.
We always try to answer in one way.
Whatever works in the field.
First and foremost,
I think we should not assume
that we understand how people communicate
and what questions
they are looking answers for.
The most important thing is to go
to the source, to the experts
and figure out what works for them
and what doesn't work for them.
And there's not going
to be a silver bullet.
There's not going to be a "killer app",
there's not going to be
one solution that fits all.
There's always going to be
a multi-platform, multi-tiered approach
that enables communities
to communicate and reconnect from within,
to communicate
with humanitarian responders
and try to figure out what are
the best solutions.
Alternatives to social media--
I think we've seen there's nothing
that can replace face-to-face
human interaction.
The question is in many emergencies
around the world--
and this is less of an issue
in natural disasters--
when we are talking about
armed conflicts, face-to-face
it can become a luxury
because of security,
because of a many number
of issues with regard to access
doesn't enable us to spend
as much time as we would like
to be in close proximity
with disaster efforts
in communities.
So the question is how we can also
build proximity 2.0
using whatever technology may work.
But knowing that technology
is not going to accommodate everybody.
It is important that we
understand how people use
technologies and what technologies
they use and what technologies
they trust.
We just cannot assume
that in this country,
this is going to be the most
used technology.
I think we can assume,
but it is important that we understand
as well some of those nuances.
Particularly the social cultural
implications of using modern technologies
and who falls and who doesn't fall
through the digital cracks
through the gender divide
and so on and so forth.
I think there's an interesting role
for academia.
We're looking at social scientists as well,
looking into helping us understand as well
some of these anthropological issues
with regard to how people use technology
and how people understand information
and how they communicate.
The future of social media?
I think we are entering an era
of profound connectivity.
I think-- again, the numbers are
only going in one direction.
Everything at some point
is going to be integrated.
You have the Internet of things,
you have wearable devices,
you have anything that you can imagine
is going to be producing data
and leaving data trails,
which means that everything
is going to be available to people
to analyze, to visualize it, to share it.
The future is a much more
integrated place.
The numbers are only going
into one direction.
I think there may be as well,
according to different analysts,
a cry for greater privacy
and greater opportunity to actually
take and extract your data
and be private.
The question is when you look
at developing countries,
do people have the opportunity
to actually raise the concerns
with regard to data protection
on data browsing?
Do actually people have
the opportunity to accept
or not consent on how
we extract information from them?
And I think that's going to be
one of the most important debates
going forward.
I think the issue of digital literacy
is also critical.
I would stress once again
that it is not about connectivity
and connectivity only.
It's the question: What sort of content
do you create today,
and what sort of content people need
to make decisions that affect their lives
and to be able to raise
their voice and concern.
In case if someone switches the button
and energy and connectivity
goes down--
I think we've seen that
in many different places.
I think it's a phenomenon
to see how creative and generous
communities around the world are.
And I think we've seen examples
of different ways where people have
really turned situations upside down
by looking into communicating
in different ways.
People will resort to pen and paper.
I remember in the aftermath
of the triple disaster in Japan in 2011,
if you look at the demographics
of those who were caught up
in the coastal areas,
they were people like our parents
and our grandparents,
people who do not necessarily
have access to mobile phones.
People who don't necessarily
know how to function
a mobile phone or connect to Twitter
or Facebook and so on and so forth.
People resorted in some of those shelters
to basically printing wall papers
and pasting them on the walls.
That's the way that people
access information.
That's the way announcements were made.
So let's not just think that technology
is just the silver bullet.
It is-- don't get me wrong--
it is certainly transforming
and has transformed the world
in unpredictable ways,
but when the electricity
and connectivity goes down
or a party decides to switch it off,
people will resort to communicating
in the most locally relevant ways,
from face-to-face to different messages
to motor bikes with messengers,
you name it.
When we talk about technology
for disaster response
and disaster management,
I think it's important as well
that we do not forget language.
Most of the technologies
are written in language,
first and foremost.
Those are languages
that are not for everybody
at the same time everywhere.
There's also an issue of how we relate
with local committees and services
and how language in many
different locations--
of course it becomes a barrier
because we don't understand each other.
There is an interesting development
that has been explored over the last
few years but is gaining momentum
now with regard to machine translation.
And companies which are developing
ear piece translators that enable us--
you know, you're speaking Russian
and I'm speaking Swahili--
to actually be able to communicate
with each other in real time.
That can be a fascinating development
in the humanitarian world
because it can somehow help us
to bridge the gap between people
who don't speak and understand
the same language.
My take on this whole conversation,
very simple, put communities first.
Technology is just a fraction
of what the solution can be.
The most important thing
is to understand how communities
themselves are looking
at trying to erase the problems
that we have been facing
before we arrive and after we leave.
For most of the problems that we have,
the technology already exists.
The question is the human component
and what the organizations
and communities themselves
do with that technology.
It is also important to emphasize
the fact that technology
is not accessible to everybody
at the same time everywhere,
that technology is also increasing
gaps and inequalities...
and creating new ones,
and as we mentioned,
I think the most important thing
is to try to understand
and have a more humble
and empathetic take
on how we look at technology,
how we look at communities,
first and foremost,
because they are first responders
and they are experts themselves.