Hi.
Cristiano Giovando
is a Technical Project Manager
at the Humanitarian OpenStreetMap Team.
In this video, he will talk about
the OpenStreetMap initiative.
So, Volunteered
Geographic Information, or VGI,
is what we like to call community mapping
or crowdsource mapping.
It's basically the community participation
to create the geographic information
and create a map.
We use VGI and crowdsource mapping
in different moments
of the disaster response cycle.
Community mapping, or VGI, was used
by Humanitarian OpenStreetMap
in Nepal during the 2015 earthquake,
to create an open map that then was used
by responders on the ground.
Before that, and during
the years before 2015,
the community in Nepal
started learning about OpenStreetMap,
and produced tools and capacity
to build around OpenStreetMap.
And so when the disaster happened in 2015
they actually had already the knowledge
of how to apply OpenStreetMap
for rapid disaster mapping.
Recently, in April of 2016,
we had the strong earthquake in Ecuador,
and 2,000 volunteers
from the OpenStreetMap community
came together in just less than a week,
and they mapped 95%
of all the affected areas
with OpenStreetMap.
Humanitarian OpenStreetMap Team
applies the concept of open source
and OpenStreetMap
to humanitarian response.
We develop tools that are open source,
like the Export tools,
or the Tasking Manager,
or open area map,
which all support different sets
in the cycle of disaster response.
The Tasking Manager
is another open source tool
developed by Humanitarian OpenStreetMap,
and it allows to coordinate
thousands of volunteers that come online,
and they try to map areas of the world
in a coordinated way.
It's open source.
We believe that open source
is the most sustainable way
for communities to participate and to make
disaster response more effective.
OpenStreetMap, as someone called it,
the "Wikipedia of maps,"
is an open geographic
database of the world.
Anyone can contribute to OpenStreetMap,
and contributors might be volunteers,
or at the same time
might be paid surveyors,
might be employees
of navigation companies
that want to improve
the database that they all use.
So, OpenStreetMap is different from VGI
in the fact that it doesn't just employ
or it doesn't use volunteer data,
volunteer contributor data,
but it also works with governments
that want to use
OpenStreetMap as a platform,
and so they use it as a way to contribute
through their different departments,
different surveyors,
that see OpenStreetMap as a way
to maintain their maps updated.
We have seen several instances
of OpenStreetMap being used
as a platform for doing research,
and also to support
some citizen science projects.
A good example of this is Wheelmap.
Wheelmap is a project that allows
to explore any area in the world
and understand what are
the barriers to accessibility,
and what are, for example,
areas that are, in fact,
more accessible than others.
OpenStreetMap is an open database,
it fosters the concept of open data,
and we believe that open data
is more sustainable
for several of the projects
that Humanitarian
OpenStreetMap carries out.
We believe that open data
brings many benefits
to the communities that use it.
For example, it makes
the process of collecting data,
and using the data, more transparent.
So, when communities
are engaged in collecting data
through an OpenStreetMap project,
for example, they also feel
more empowered.
So, having open data
gives them the opportunity
to own the data set, to own the map,
that then they see being made
for their community.
Another thing the open data provides
is an easy way for innovators,
for companies,
to use data sets that might
otherwise be inaccessible,
and create innovation
based on these open data sources.
The other great aspect of open data,
and, in particular, of OpenStreetMap,
is the fact that the data can be updated
and kept fresh by the volunteers
and by the community.
Things that, if you're looking
at a closed data set,
it might take years
before that department goes through
and updates that same data set.
And with OpenStreetMap,
anyone today can go and update the map,
anywhere in the world.
Not necessarily open data is free
and open for anyone to use.
There are some different types of licenses
that govern the way
of how open data can be used,
and this is really important.
There are some open data licenses
that are completely free and open,
which means anyone can use
the data for any reason,
and the most common one,
the most famous one
is the Public Domain,
or CC0, Creative Commons Zero License.
Other open data licenses,
for example, like the CC BY,
the Creative Common Attribution,
requires that, whoever uses
the data for any application
provides an attribution
of the source of the data.
Licensing is definitely an aspect
that, in some ways,
constrains the use of open data,
or at least it provides a framework
for how to use open data correctly.
The other way that we can
use open data more efficiently
is through international standards
for interpretability.
And so when data is made open,
it's also more effective if it's actually
used and shared through these standards,
otherwise it might be
put somewhere on a web server
through a closed zip file,
and then it might be hard to access
or get fresh updates of that data set.
Some data in open data set
might carry some sensitivity
and security implications.
OpenStreetMap, for example, maps sites
that are considered sensitive,
for military aspects,
or, for example, during disaster response,
it's important that high level of details
of certain areas may be protected
and not exposed through a public data set.
The good thing of OpenStreetMap
in this regards is that it's a community.
So, when we work with a community,
for example, during disaster response,
we also try to understand
what are the needs,
and, at the same time,
what are the levels of details
that we can, and we should map
through a community response effort.
So, we always work with the community,
with the local community,
and try to understand that, in order
to protect the privacy and security
of the people on the ground.
With Humanitarian OpenStreetMap,
we actually want to make sure
that the data that we produce
is used on the ground
or by disaster responders
using GIS and mapping tools.
So, we created facilitating tools
for making this process easier.
One of these projects
is called Export Tools,
and it allows anyone to define
an area on the map,
select the features
that they want to download
and convert into a shapefile, or a KML,
or any familiar GIS format,
and easily download it,
and that data set is updated hourly,
so that data is fresh as it gets updated
by the volunteers in OpenStreetMap.
OpenStreetMap is a critical tool
to disaster response
and disaster preparedness.
It actually allows to create maps
that otherwise would take
a long time, maybe years to create.
By harnessing the power
of the online community
and the local community,
we're able to combine
a massive amount of data
that is created through
satellite image interpretation
with the local knowledge.
For example, to add
the conditions of the buildings,
or street names,
or anything that cannot be extracted
by analyzing satellite information.
One of the challenges
that OpenStreetMap is facing right now
is also a consequence of its size,
in that there's a lot of data
inside OpenStreetMap;
there are over 50 gigabytes of data
currently in the OpenStreetMap database,
almost 200 million buildings
being created everywhere in the world.
So, one challenge is to really
visualize and understand
what is the impact of the OpenStreetMap
community around the world.
We recently created a tool
that is able to quickly scale
and bring to a web browser
these visuals of the impact
of the OpenStreetMap community.
It's called OpenStreetMap Analytics,
and it's available online now
as a beta platform,
but it really allows you, and anyone,
even without the OpenStreetMap knowledge,
to understand the impact
of the OpenStreetMap community
anywhere in the world, over time.
Another challenge and innovation
that we see possible
for the OpenStreetMap community
is to enrich the availability of imagery
through which the map is being created.
We rely a lot on satellite imagery,
and now on our own imagery,
to trace that information
and add it to OpenStreetMap.
Unfortunately, not much
of the satellite data is being made public
and openly available for anyone to trace.
That normally happens
during disaster response operations.
But we believe that also
with the new revolution
in earth observation
provided by drone mapping,
we believe that there's going to be
a need for coordinating the collection
and in sharing of imagery
that is becoming more and more available.
So, we built an open aerial map,
which is an online repository
of open source
and openly licensed imagery,
where everyone
in the OpenStreetMap community
can go and understand what images
are available for a certain area,
and be able to use it
for tracing and mapping.
Humanitarian OpenStreetMap Team
is a US-based organization
which started after the response
to the Haiti earthquake in 2010.
After the earthquake, we realized
that the OpenStreetMap community
needed a way to coordinate
the mapping response that we provided,
and that resulted really useful
on the ground for responders
to understand the impact of that disaster,
and also to have a reference base map
for navigating and moving around.
After 2010, the Humanitarian
OpenStreetMap Team was born,
and right now we have several
staff members all over the world,
and we are a distributed organization.
And most importantly, Humanitarian
OpenStreetMap is a community,
a community of thousands of volunteers
from anywhere in the world,
and they participate
in different local projects,
community mapping projects,
and when needed they come together
online and build maps quickly.