Sandec & EPFL are partnering to bring
you a series of online courses or MOOCs.
This MOOC is dedicated to household
water treatment and safe storage or HTWS.
So who might be interested
in this course?
Maybe you work with communities in a region
that doesn't yet have reliable and safe water supply?
Maybe you're involved with emergency response
and need short-term solutions for
treating water when public supplies are
out of commission.
Maybe you work with people who are particularly
vulnerable to diarrheal disease,
such as people living with HIV/aids.
Or perhaps you are a researcher interested in developing
and improving solutions for situations
like these.
In this course we will learn about the different pathogens found in
drinking water that cause disease.
We will discuss different pathways of
exposure to these pathogens and how
these pathways can be blocked.
We will also examine the burden of disease
caused by unsafe water
as well as the related problems of poor sanitation and hygiene.
Household water treatment is practiced by millions,
even billions of people around the world.
In this course, you will learn about the
different ways
that water can be treated at the household level.
We will examine the roles that can be played by
non-governmental organizations, businesses
and government agencies.
We'll hear from people with expertise on reaching those
affected by natural disasters.
And you'll also meet guest speakers
from the World Health Organization,
the London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine
and other places specializing in HWTS.
You'll learn more about measuring
water quality using portable equipment.
And you'll get to find out what
this device is and how it works.
So I hope you'll join us for
this short course on household water treatment
and how it can be applied
around the world.
We look forward to working with you!