In this module, we'll talk about
diseases caused by unsafe water,
sanitation and hygiene,
and how they can be classified,
as well as the burden of disease due to
unsafe water, sanitation, hygiene,
both in terms of deaths or mortality
and disease or morbidity.
They say that three things in life
are certain: birth, taxes and death,
and somehow some people manage
to avoid taxes.
But deaths are inevitable.
There are about 55 million people
who die every year
but there are even more people
who have babies every year.
About 135 million new babies
are born each year.
So that means overall there
is about a 1.1% increase
in the global population each year,
and the population will double
every sixty years at current rates.
One useful way to classify diseases
was was proposed by the authors
of the 1972 classic book
“Drawers of Water”.
According to environmental
transmission pathways
this so called “Bradley Classification”
includes four types: water-borne,
water-washed, water-based
and water-related diseases.
Now some of those 55 million deaths
per year are caused, at least in part
by unsafe water, sanitation and hygiene.
And we can think about different ways
to classify those diseases.
First, we can talk about
the water-borne diseases
which are diseases caused
by actually drinking, ingesting water
that has some pathogens in it.
These include the diarrheal diseases
caused by different pathogens:
Rotavirus, Cholera,
Shigella or Cyptosporidium
but also Hepatitis A and E
and even Polio can be transmitted
through drinking water.
For any of these water-borne diseases
an intervention to reduce the disease then
could involve improving the water quality.
Next we have the water-washed diseases
which are caused by poor hygiene
due to lack of water
rather than by direct ingestion.
Most water-borne diseases
are also water-washed
because they can be transmitted
through hands
and contact with other surfaces.
Trachoma is the leading cause
of preventable blindness globally
and is transmitted by flies
which land on people's faces.
And acute respiratory infections
are also transmitted through contact
with pathogens on hands
and other surfaces.
Water-washed diseases can be reduced
by increasing the amount of water
that is available to improve hygiene.
Water-based diseases
are those caused by parasites
which live part of their
life cycle in water.
The most serious of this
is the Schistosomiasis or Billharzia
which affects 160 million people
globally, mostly in Sub-Saharan Africa.
Another serious water-based disease
is Guinea Worm, or Dracunculiasis,
which is a horrible disease
which used to affect many people,
3.5 million people in 1986,
but cases are now down
to only 542 in 2012
and those are confined to about
four countries mainly in South Sudan.
For water-based diseases
control-mechanisms
involve targeting
the aquatic organism host
and protecting surface water bodies
from contamination.
Finally, there are water-related diseases,
which are caused by insects
which breed in water,
especially mosquitoes.
The most important of these is malaria,
which affects about 250 million people
each year, causing about 589,000 deaths.
The great majority of those
are in Sub-Saharan Africa
and affect children
under the age of five.
Another important mosquito disease
is Dengue fever,
which is growing in numbers
and can cause explosive outbreaks
especially in urban areas.
In both cases, the mosquitoes breed
in certain types of water,
and a control mechanism
is to remove their habitat.
So in summary, there are many diseases
which are caused at least partially,
by unsafe water, sanitation and hygiene.
Water-borne diseases are those
that are caused by directly drinking
or ingesting contaminated water.
And those diseases could be controlled
at least partially, by treating the water
at the household.
Household water treatment though
shouldn't be expected to have an impact
on other diseases that are water-washed,
water-based, or water-related.
Now let's take a little break.
You see on your screen
five different infectious diseases,
and I'd like you to think for a minute
about which of them cause
more or less deaths each year.
Arrange them in the order
of number of deaths per year.
The most recent global mortality figures
were released by the WHO in 2014
and estimate deaths
over the years 2000 to 2012.
You can see that Lower
Respiratory Infections such as pneumonia
were by far the largest cause of death
among these diseases.
Diarrheal disease cause about
1.5 million deaths,
followed by Tuberculosis,
Malaria and Measles.
Diarrheal disease is the most important
of the water, sanitation
and hygiene-related diseases,
and a major contributor
to the global burden of disease.
Diarrhea is among the main causes
of child mortality globally,
second only to acute
respiratory infections.
It's responsible for about one
out of every ten deaths
among children under the age of five.
That's about 1000 child deaths per day.
The WHO estimates that 56%
of deaths due to Diarrhea worldwide
are attributable to inadequate water,
sanitation and hygiene.
So it's clear that poor access
to the basic services
have a major impact on global health,
especially through preventing
the transmission
of water-related infectious diseases.
So far we've been talking about
burden of disease
in terms of deaths or mortality,
but it's also important
to consider sicknesses
which can greatly reduce
the quality of life or morbidity.
We can do this through a metric
that's called Disability Adjusted
Life Years, or DALYs.
What DALYs do is combine two aspects.
First, the Years of Life Lost
in comparison to
a Standard Life Expectancy
and second, the Years of Lost to Disability
which are the number of years
you live with the disability
times a weight for how serious
that disability is.
Well, let's consider this
with some examples.
First, consider a person who has
a normal life expectancy of 80 years
and has no particular disabilities.
Then this person lives
a fully healthy life for 80 years
and has zero years of life lost
or years lost to disability.
So they have no DALYs.
Second, let's consider the example
where someone also
has a life expectancy of 80
and lives a very normal life,
to begin with,
but then has some kind of sudden accident
at age 70 and dies prematurely.
Then they have years of life lost.
How many?
Ten years of life lost.
There's no disability here
so the number of DALYs is ten.
Okay, this time let's consider a person
who lives a normal healthy life
until age 50, when they have
some kind of accident
which leads to a loss of a foot,
amputation of the foot.
Now the disability weight
for the foot amputation is 0.3.
So it goes up to there.
But then that person lives
to the expected life expectancy of 80.
So here we have years of life lost
to disability. How many?
Thirty years from age 50 times
the weight of 0.3 for foot amputation
is a total of nine, so that's 9 DALYs.
Finally, a more complicated example
is a person who lives a normal life
until age 36,
when they contract HIV AIDS.
Full-blown AIDS without any medicine,
without antiretroviral therapy
has a weight of 0.5.
But after four years, that person then
is able to get medication
and have a much better quality of life
with the weight of 0.167.
Then that person lives until age 70,
dying prematurely.
Thirty-six and forty.
So here we have years lost
to disability,
and here we have years of life lost.
How many? Ten years of life lost.
How many years lived with disability?
We have four at that high rate,
that's a total of two,
plus thirty at a lower rate,
that's five, for a total of seven.
So then the DALYs equals to ten
plus seven for seventeen.
So you can imagine
the diarrheal disease then,
which impacts a very young children
in many cases,
will also have a high contribution
to DALYs
because of the large number
of years of life lost.
Now that we have a metric for morbidity,
the DALYs, we can examine
the overall burden of disease
posed by diarrhea
and compare it to other diseases globally.
Now that 2013 WHO report
about deaths globally
hasn't yet been analyzed
to develop DALY estimates.
So we have to look at
an older WHO report from 2008
shown up here, where they reported
that diarrhea disease caused
over 52 million DALYs per year,
which again the distribution
was very similar
to the mortality numbers we've seen
with a little bit more than 3%
of the global total and about 9%
of the burden of disease for children.
This report also listed country-wise DALYs
and you could see that India was by far
the largest country in terms of DALYs,
in terms of disease burden
followed by other large countries:
China, Nigeria, Pakistan,
and the Democratic Republic of Congo,
which all had more than 3 million DALYs.
In fact, in DRC, the contribution of DALYs
to the overall disease burden
was more than 10% of all DALYs.
So far we've been talking about numbers
generated by the WHO,
either their 2000 report on mortality
or earlier reports for morbidity
or risk factors.
But there is another large important
and recent data set out there,
it's called the Global Burden
of Disease 2010 Study
and it was done by the Institute
for Health Metrics and Evaluation
or IHME based in Seattle, Washington.
The GBD 2010 Study
was a massive undertaking
involving hundreds of scientists
from all around the world
including many WHO researchers.
However, even though it uses
similar approach to the WHO models,
WHO hasn't endorsed the findings
in part because of some
methodological differences
and in part because
they weren't given access
to the data and the findings
to validate them for publication.
Some of the main differences
between the two studies are that, first,
IHME calculated new disability weights
for various health conditions.
This was done through
a participatory online process,
as well as through field surveys
in a number of countries.
Second, while WHO considered hygiene,
water and sanitation risks,
IHME found that the data available
for hygiene practices,
nationally representative data sets
were too weak,
so they decided not to include
this risk factor.
And then finally, in the IHME model,
people accessing a basic level of
water and sanitation,
such as improved sources of water
like a borehole or a protected spring,
or improved sanitation, a basic pit latrine,
they were considered to suffer
no burden of disease
due to their water and sanitation.
This was not the approach followed in the WHO models.
Nonetheless, this was a massive
and important undertaking
and we can learn a lot
through its findings.
Let's take a look at them.
Let's take a look at the GBD 2010 data
from the IHME website.
You can find it just by searching IHME.
Then let's go straight
to their data visualization.
They have many different
visualizations tools.
We'll look at GBD Compare.
Now in GBD compare,
this is what's called a tree map
and if you hover over different diseases
you can see the percent
of their contribution
to the burden of disease.
Here let's put a focus
on diarrheal disease,
now that box will always have
a square on it,
and we can change
between DALYs and deaths,
we can look at global
or specific countries or regions,
we can change years,
we can see that if we look at
"Under five children"
the contribution of diarrheal disease
is much larger.
So you can find out a lot of things
from this kind of map.
Down below, we have different options
for secondary visualizations.
We could look at Time Plot for instance,
and see the number of deaths
decreasing over time
here shown as Rates or as Numbers.
Decreasing from 1.7 million
under five deaths in 1990
to about 666,000 in 2010.
We can also look at the Map and see
which countries have greater
or lesser burdens of disease.
Here we can see that India,
who has a 150,000 child deaths
is by far the largest contributor
to burden of disease,
but if we look at Rates,
then we would see more high rates
in Sub-Saharan Africa
and the same
if we look at proportion of DALYs.
What both of these data sets tells us
is that the burden of disease
from unsafe water,
sanitation and hygiene is high
and that diarrheal disease
is the leading contributor
to that disease burden
both in terms of morbidity
and mortality.
You can now access these reports
or websites
to get more detailed information
if you need.
In our next module,
we will be looking at
some of the specific pathogens
that cause diarrheal disease
in drinking water.