HWTS of course stands for Household
Water Treatment and Safe Storage.
Household water treatment uses
some
treatment processes which are very similar
to those used
at larger scales in community schemes or
municipal treatment plants.
These can include pre-treatment steps,
filtration, disinfection,
Often applied in series to allow multiple
barriers against pathogens passing through
the system.
So in this module we'll briefly introduce
these processes.
We'll discuss their effectiveness against
different classes of pathogens.
The bacteria,
the protozoa or the viruses.
Where effectiveness is how well the
process works in
removing or inactivating or killing the
pathogen under ideal conditions.
Efficiency is something different.
It's how well the process works when it is
actually applied at the field level in
real households.
We'll discuss that more in later modules.
Today we'll give some brief advantages and
disadvantages of each of the main
processes.
Sometimes pre-treatment is required in
household
water treatment or treatment at larger
scales.
If water has a lot of suspended solids in
it
or turbidity, those particles can
interfere with other treatment processes.
At the household level, very simple forms
of pre-treatment can be
done, including rough filtration, through
cloth, or sand filters, or sedimentation.
Either passive sedimentation, letting a
bucket of water sit overnight, so
solids settle to the bottom, or
assisting sedimentation with a coagulant,
like alum.
Filters are usually efficient at removing
large pathogens,
like guinea worm or protozoa.
They also usually work well against
bacteria, depending on the design.
Some filters are even able to remove
viruses.
But recall that viruses are very small and
they can pass through the pores of some
filters.
Generally speaking, people tend to like
They're often easy to operate and require
little technical capacity at the household
level.
Filters normally don't give any strange
taste to water,
and ceramic filters can even cool the
water through evaporation.
If raw water is turbid from high iron or
other particles, this
is generally removed, and the treated
water looks much cleaner, which people
appreciate.
Disadvantages of filters include the need
for supply chains, including to replace
broken components and the possibility of
recontamination after filtration.
Especially if treated water is transferred
to another container.
The most widely practiced household water
treatment process is boiling.
Boiling is highly effective against all
classes of pathogens and people
all around the world understand that
boiling makes water safer to drink.
And they tend to trust the treatment.
However, boiling can cause health risks,
especially where biomass fuel
is used, and more fire means more indoor
air pollution.
More fire also needs more fuel, which
costs more money.
Boiled water can also have a flat
taste, and sometimes chalky precipitates,
formed during boiling,
which doesn't look nice.
And finally, boiled water is very
vulnerable to re-contamination.
Treated water has to be cooled before
drinking, and if this
is done in an open container, there are
good chances for re-contamination.
Ultraviolet radiation is another form of
energy used in disinfection.
Ultraviolet lamps are highly effective
where there's electricity.
But even without electricity, ultraviolet
radiation from the sun can be used.
The solar disinfection system, or SODIS,
involves filing clear plastic bottles
with water and placing them in the direct
sunlight for several hours.
Different pathogens have very different
abilities to tolerate ultraviolet
radiation.
Bacteria such as E. coli are relatively
quickly killed, but Crytoptosporidium
is somewhat more tolerant and some viruses
can withstand high ultraviolet doses.
SODIS is technically easy to implement.
It doesn't require any complicated
supplies
or chemicals and it's very inexpensive.
Other advantages are, that SODIS doesn't
change
the taste of the water, and that water
is generally treated in the same container
which
is later used for storage and even
drinking.
So the risk or recontamination is low.
However, SODIS treatment is time
consuming.
Most commonly, water is cooled overnight
before drinking, and
it can only treat relatively small volumes
of water.
And finally, if the raw water is highly
turbid, suspended
particles can shield pathogens and reduce
the effectiveness of treatment.
The most commonly used disinfectant in
household water treatment,
just like in large scale treatment plants,
is chlorine.
Chlorine can be applied in liquid or
tablet
form, and is more effective with longer
contact times.
Usually chlorine should be given at least
30 minutes to disinfect water.
Chlorine is very effective against
bacteria, but
higher doses are required to kill some
viruses.
And some protozoan cysts are highly
resistant to chlorine.
Cryptosporidium cysts can even survive for
short periods in full strength, undiluted
bleach.
One advantage of chlorine disinfection,
which is missing for heat and radiation
disinfection, is that residual chlorine in
the water can protect against
re-contamination.
Chlorination is also easy to apply at the
household level and is very inexpensive.
Large volumes of water can be treated
within relatively short periods of time.
Like ultraviolet radiation this treatment
is less effective on turbid water.
Consistent chlorination requires supply
chains and ongoing commitment from users.
And finally chlorine does have a
distinctive taste and an
odor which can be unpleasant if people
aren't used to it.
Now that's a brief introduction to the
main processes involved in household water
treatment.
We'll go into them in more detail in
coming modules.
You have seen though that different
processes have
different levels effectiveness against
different classes of pathogens.
So that means that different household
water treatment processes will
be better suited for different
applications, depending on the local
conditions.