I am happy to introduce
our guest lecturer Dr Batsi Majuru,
a technical officer
at the World Health Organization.
Hi, I am Batsi Majuru
from the World Health Organization.
I work on the household water treatment
and regulation of drinking water quality.
I am here today to talk
about the International Network
and household
water treatment and safe storage.
In this module we'll take a brief look
at the background of the Network
and why it was established.
We will discuss the mission
and objectives of the Network
and look at a few examples
of the Network's activities.
The Network was established
by the World Health Organization
with the objective
of accelerating health gains
to those without reliable access
to safe drinking water.
At the time of the establishment
of the Network in 2003
the field of household water treatment
and safe storage
was rapidly evolving.
And it was difficult to keep up
with the various developments.
Research was fragmented
and not always accessible.
Practitioners were diverse,
and working initiatives
were often disconnected.
And there was no coherent voice
on all those various developments
to enable adoption of policy.
The Network was formed
as a global platform
to bring together these various
entities and coordinate efforts.
The Network aims to contribute
to a significant reduction
in waterborne, in water related
vector-borne diseases,
especially among vulnerable populations
by promoting household water
treatment and safe storage
as a key component of community targeted
environmental health programs.
Vulnerable populations include children,
people whose immune systems
are compromised
and of course those
who do not have access
to safe and reliable water supplies.
The mission's statement
of the Network also emphasizes
that household water treatment
and safe storage
is not an alternative
to improve water supplies,
but it is a complement
to infrastructural improvements.
It also emphasizes
that household water treatment
should be integrated within wider public
and environmental health programs
to maximize health impact.
To fulfill this mission the Network
has forced strategic objectives
that are centered around advocacy,
communication, research,
implementation and scaling up.
The network is coordinated
by the World Health Organization
and the United Nations'
Children's Fund (UNICEF).
Communication support within the Network
is provided by the University
of North Carolina.
Today the Network has
over 150 participating organizations,
including academic institutions,
the private sector,
non-governmental organizations,
policy makers and donors
and brings together all these entities
to share experiences,
know-how and find new and effective ways
of getting safe water
to those who need it most.
Some examples of the network's activities
include regional workshops
to support development
of national policies and frameworks.
These workshops bring together
government officials,
donors and implementers
working in various countries
and have led the development
of over twenty national action plans
and household water treatment
and safe storage.
Here is a picture
of one of these workshops in Lao.
The Network has also developed
resources and best practices,
including the toolkit
for monitoring and evaluation
of household water treatment
and safe storage.
In addition the Network
has been advocating
for integration of household
water treatment and safe storage
within key public health efforts,
including maternal and child health,
nutrition and HIV.
The latest research and activities
related to household water treatment
and safe storage
is regularly shared
through the Network newsletter.
If you are interested
in finding out more about the Network
please visit the website.
You can sign up for the listserve
and be able to receive
the regular newsletters
and announcements,
participate in webinars and hear
what's going on in this field
and share your feedback
on the Network's tools and resources.
So, in summary,
ensuring that health gains
from household water treatment
and safe storage
are realized by those who need it most
requires coordinated effort
across various disciplines and sectors.
The WHO/UNICEF HWTS Network
is the global forum
that brings together
these various entities.
Thank you.