So, we've made it through the first week
of the course.
We started by discussing the global burden
of disease following different disease
classification systems.
We learned about the importance of
diarrheal disease, both in
terms of morbidity, expressed in DALYs,
and mortality or deaths.
And we saw some different resources where
you can get information about
burden of dis, of disease from the World
Health Organization and from IHME.
We also had an introduction to the
different water-borne pathogens, the
helminths, protozoa, bacteria, and
viruses, that
can cause disease in drinking water.
We then looked at contamination pathways
which can
lead to people being exposed to fecal
pathogens.
Using the tool of the F-diagram, we
focused in on the water related pathways.
The safe water chain.
Moving from the water resource to the
point of consumption.
We also discussed fecal indicator bacteria
as a way of monitoring
a proxy of fecal contamination rather than
trying to directly measure pathogens.
Next, we had a first glance at the
treatment processes, sedimentation,
filtration
and different types of disinfection.
Followed by safe storage.
These will be explored more in the coming
weeks.