Hello.
In this module we're going to discuss
sedimentation,
which is one of the water treatment
processes that
can be done in household treatment, or
also at
the community scale, as discussed in our
previous modules.
Sedimentation by itself is not a complete
water treatment.
But it can be a necessary, preliminary
step to be followed by
filtration and disinfection before safe
storage
in the case of household water treatment.
To discuss sedimentation, we'll introduce
the concept of turbidity.
We'll define turbidity and we'll show how
turbidity can
be reduced either through simple settling
using gravity,
by enhanced settling through the addition
of chemicals called coagulants.
Turbidity is simply the presence of
suspended particles in water.
If the particles are large, they can
eventually settle out of water through
gravity.
But if they are small they will remain
suspended.
They won't settle.
particles can be made of
organic materials, such as microorganisms
or algae.
Or they can be inorganic, made of silt,
clay or other minerals.
There are a variety of units used to
measure turbidity.
Nephelometric turbidity units are based on
scattering of light thru turbid water.
While formazin turbidity units are made
with reference to a
standard series of chemical dilutions
using the reference material formazin.
Jackson turbidity units are historically
based on
sighting a flame through a volume of
water.
But all of these units are roughly
comparable to each other, so you
don't need to worry too much about which
type of unit is being used.
Turbidity in and of itself isn't a health
risk.
It depends on which particles are causing
the turbidity.
So there are no health based targets
around turbidity.
However, turbidity can have significant
impacts
on treatment processes, including
filtration and disinfection.
So there are often operational guidelines
before such treatment is applied,
typically in the range of five to ten
turbidity units.
This is also the range at which turbidity
becomes notably visible, and
people may have aesthetic concerns when
they see that the drinking water is cloudy.
Of course, when people are habituated to
drinking
turbid water, this may not pose any
aesthetic problems.
Perhaps the simplest form of HWTS is
gravity settling or simple sedimentation.
Here you simply take a volume of water,
set it aside, and let gravity do its work.
Depending on the size of the particles,
particles
will then be removed by settling to the
bottom.
This process can remove some turbidity and
can improve the
visual appearance, but has a very limited
effect on pathogen removal.
Some of the very larger pathogens,
protozoa, helminth eggs, can be removed.
Also, when the water is being stored for
sedimentation to occur, there's
the possibility of introducing secondary
contamination,
if the storage container is not hygienic.
An example of simple gravity settling is
the three pot sedimentation method.
In this method, three different storage
vessels are used so
that drinking water has always been stored
for at least two days.
Which gives time for some pathogens such
as
schistosomes, the cause of Schistosomiasis
to die off.
So in this example one always takes
drinking water from pot number three.
And when it's empty, you can slowly pour
water from
pot two into pot three, leaving the bottom
sediments untouched.
And then wash out pot two.
Then, pot two can be refilled, by slowly
pouring water
from pot one into pot two, and washing out
pot one.
Finally, you can pour water collected from
the source, from a bucket, number four,
into pot one and if it's very turbid you
could strain this through a clean cloth.
It's also possible to use a flexible pipe
to siphon water from one
pot to another, without disturbing the
sediments at the bottom of the container.
Gravity settling has only limited
reduction of turbidity,
especially when the particles forming
turbidity are small.
But, settling can be enhanced through the
use of chemicals called coagulants.
And what coagulants do, is they make the
particles in water stick to each other
better.
They also add new particles, so that there
are more particles around that can bump
into
each other, collide, stick, and form
larger particles
that are easier to settle out of solution.
Many small particles suspended in water,
like
colloids, have a negative charge on them,
and
two negatively charged objects will repel
each
other, so they can't stick to each other.
Coagulants add positive charges to this
mixture.
So the positive charge of a coagulant
can neutralize the negative charge of a
particle.
Or in some cases a larger coagulant
molecule can bridge between two negatively
charged particles, helping them to come
together and settle out of solution.
Coagulants can also remove some dissolved
compounds
and improve the color of the raw water.
It's possible to make coagulants from
locally grown plants.
One of the most commonly used plants for
this
purpose is Moringa oleifera, shown here on
the left,
which is grown widely in Africa and Asia.
It's called the drumstick tree in Asia,
because of those long seed pods.
To use moringa, you collect and dry the
seeds and grind them into a powder, and
then
add them to water to be treated, often at
a dose of about 200 milligrams per liter.
There are many other plants that are used
as coagulants.
The prickly pear cactus is commonly used
in Latin America, and Nirmali seeds in
India,
which aren't very effective as a primary
coagulant,
but can help if another coagulant is
present.
And there are other plants available in
different settings, that are also used as
coagulants.
The way that these plant based coagulants
work, is that the plant material contains
a compound, a chemical, it's often a
water soluble protein, that has a positive
charge.
In fact it might have many positive
charges and be polycationic.
And that can interact with particles that
have a negative charge
to make them stickier, and make
them settle some solution.
Plant-based coagulants tend to be most
effective at higher turbidity when there
are more particles around to bump into and
stick to each other.
So if the turbidity is at least 30 or 50
these coagulants will work better.
Some of the plant-based coagulants, such
as moringa,
may also have some antibacterial
properties as well.
But in general, they're not considered a
complete treatment,
but a precursor to be followed by a
disinfection step.
One disadvantage of the plant-based
coagulants, is that they
add a lot of dissolved organic carbon to
the water,
which can foster regrowth of bacteria and
eventually could cause taste and odor
problems.
Chemical coagulants are much more widely
used than plant-based coagulants.
And the most common of these are metal
salts using aluminum or ferric iron.
Aluminum sulfate in particular is widely
available
locally, because it has many household
uses.
One of them is that you can use alum when
shaving. If you cut
yourself shaving, and rub a little bit of
alum on it, it stops the bleeding.
So alum may be locally available.
Alum consists of aluminum and sulfate
and a number of water molecules.
And the way that it works is, it
creates this aluminum ion with three
positive charges,
which are very able to interact with those
negatively charged particles and help them
to precipitate.
Alum potash using potassium as well as
aluminum is another locally available
chemical coagulant.
Ferric salts works well, as well.
They tend to be a little bit less widely
available.
They work well over a broader pH range
than aluminum.
Chemical coagulants tend to
produce coarser
flocs, compared to plant based coagulants,
which means
that they settle faster, but it also means
that they create a larger volume of
sludge.
Let's take a look a short video that
demonstrates coagulation and flocculation.
This video uses a product called the PNG
purifier of water, produced by Proctor &
Gamble.
It's the HWTS product formerly known as
PuR, and it uses
a combination of coagulation with ferric
salts, and disinfection with chlorine.
Let's take a look.
And stirring it rapidly to dissolve the
salt, and allow it to
hydrolyze and create flux, and bump into
the particles in the water.
Then there's a period of slower settling
and bumping when the particles
get larger and larger, and finally form
flux that settle to the bottom.
The solution is then filtered through some
cloth and stored for a while
for the chlorine to be effective before
the water is safe to drink.
Coagulation is a complex physical and
chemical process, and
can be effected by very many different
operational parameters.
The temperature is important.
It doesn't work as well at low
temperatures.
And especially the characteristics of the
water,
the pH and the alkalinity are important
variables.
If the alkalinity is low, well,
coagulation consumes alkalinity,
so the pH can drop to very acidic
levels if there's insufficient alkalinity.
In that case it might be necessary to
add some lime or sodium carbonate to
increase alkalinity.
But if the alkalinity is too high, the pH
is
often high as well and chlorination would
be less effective.
Another important factor is the physical
mixing, it's important to
mix rapidly at the beginning so that the
coagulant dissolves,
and is spread evenly throughout the
mixture, and has a
chance to bump into and interact with a
lot of particles.
Then finally the dose should be optimized.
If there's too much coagulant, as well
as too little coagulant, it doesn't work
optimally.
So the best practice would be to do a
series of tests, called
jar tests with the actual water to be
treated to determine the optimal dose.
One issue that may arise in connection
with coagulation, where aluminum
salts are used, is that of residual
aluminum in drinking water.
Some studies have found a link between
aluminum exposure, and neurological
problems, including Alzheimer's disease.
However other studies have not found these
things.
The World Health Organization has reviewed
the
literature, especially focusing on
exposure through drinking water.
And so far has decided not to set a health
based guideline for drinking water.
In part, because drinking water
constitutes only a small portion of
the total intake of aluminum, with food
being a much larger factor.
However WHO does recommend for aesthetic
reasons, that residual
aluminum be kept to certain levels in
finished water,
because it impacts the visual appearance
of the water.
And in a large, well-managed system,
it's easy enough
to keep residual aluminum below 0.1
milligrams per liter,
and in smaller systems below 0.2
milligrams per liter, through a
combination of dose optimization, and
following coagulation with a filtration
step.
If you'd like to see the WHO's rationale
for not setting a health-based guideline
in more detail, take a look at the text
from the WHO guideline values.
So in summary, sedimentation is a
pre-treatment step,
which is often necessary before moving on to filtration,
disinfection, and safe storage.
The purpose of sedimentation is to remove
suspended solids, and this
can be done either through gravity
settling, or through use of coagulants.
Either plant based coagulants, or salts
such as aluminum, or ferric salts.
Sedimentation does result in some pathogen
removal, but
should not be considered as a complete
treatment.
However, it does allow subsequent
treatment steps to be more effective.