In this module we're going to look at
ceramic filtration, which falls in between
sand filtration and synthetic membranes in
terms of pore size and physical exclusion.
Ceramic filtration is hot.
There is tremendous growth in sales of
ceramic filters in many low income
countries.
Although there are also some drawbacks
which we'll look into, ceramic pot
filters with pots that look little bit
like flower pots are popular
and can be locally made and there are also
smaller ceramic candle
filters which can be installed in
different kinds of water storage
containers.
Here's an animation of a ceramic pot
filter.
Operation is very simple.
The pot is filled with water which then
passes
through the ceramic and into a storage
container below.
This design includes built-in safe
storage.
And filtered water is collected from a
tap.
Ceramic pot filters don't require any
electricity or consumables.
But they do require periodic cleaning,
especially if raw water is turbid.
Normally this is done by scrubbing with a
small brush.
Ceramic pots can be produced using local
materials.
Though it's not easy to set up a high
quality production facility.
The main ingredient in ceramic filters is
clay, which can be
sourced directly from local mines or
indirectly by crushing unfired bricks.
Clay shouldn't have too much sand or
organic material in it, and
usually local potters will know where good
quality clay can be found.
Clay is mixed with burn-out material to
increase porosity of the finished product.
Usually, organic waste material like
sawdust or ground rice husks can be
used with three or four times as much clay
as burn-out material by weight.
The proportion and size of burn-out
material
can dramatically effect filter flow rates
and efficacy.
Most ceramic filters are coated with this
thin layer of silver just after firing.
This helps improve the biological
performance of the filter.
We'll talk more about silver in a bit.
A few filter factories also add metal
oxides, like goethite or iron-rich
soils like laterite to the mix in order to
improve removal of viruses.
Once the materials are mixed together,
they're pressed into shape.
The flower pot press seen here, is a
common
shape, but oblong and semi-spherical
filters are also widely produced.
Once pressed into pots, the pots must dry
for a
week or two and then be fired in a kiln.
It takes a bit less than a day to fire
the pots, typically at a temperature of
around 800 degrees Celsius.
And then around a day for cooling before
the pots can be handled and checked.
Once pots are fired, it's very important
to test every single
pot to make sure there are no cracks or
other defects.
Quality control begins with visual
inspection and checking to see if the
pot makes a clear bell like sound when it
is tapped or pinged.
Immersing the pot in water without letting
the water come over the rim, is a
simple kind of pressure test that can
quickly identify cracks that might not be
visible.
A more thorough flow rate test can also
identify cracks
by using a calibrated t-device like the
one in shown here,
which rests on the rim of the pot.
When the pots are then filled with water,
it's possible to
check how long it takes for the water
level to drop.
A typical target is around two liters per
hour,
though that depends on the size of the
pot.
Finally, challenge tests can be conducted
to see
if filters are able to remove bacteria
like E. coli.
Typically, around ten to 20% of filters
will
fail these quality control checks and must
be destroyed.
Factories have to build in this loss into
their business models.
Unfortunately, defective filters can't all
just be ground
up and used in a next production run,
because the clay properties have
irreversibly changed.
However, some factories do include small
amounts of ground
up fired clay, which is called grog, in
production.
But viruses then, are too small to be
removed through physical straining.
They can however be removed through
electrostatic attraction.
Most viruses have a negative surface
charge, and they
are attracted to positively charged
surfaces such as metal oxides.
Laterite soil contains high levels of
goethite and iron oxide with a positive
charge and some manufacturers add laterite
soil
to the clay used in filter production,
in order to improve removal of viruses.
However, the effectiveness of this
practice hasn't been rigorously tested.
Also, if electrostatic absorption is the
key mechanism in virus removal,
there's possibility that absorption sites
could eventually be completely filled up.
Or even that absorbed viruses could be
remobilized due to changes in influent
water.
In general, virus removal in ceramic
filters is poor and more research
is needed to identify mechanisms that
could lead to better virus removal.
There is a third mechanism for removing
pathogens in ceramic filters through
chemical reactions.
It has been known for thousands of years
that metallic silver
has anti-microbial properties, and it has
become very common to coat
ceramic filters with silver after the
firing process, either by dipping
filters in a silver solution or by
brushing it onto the sides.
The amount and type of silver applied
seems to be more important than
whether silver is put on the inside or the
outside of the pot.
There's no need to be concerned about
silver leaching
from the pots and causing human
health problems.
There is no WHO drinking water guideline
value for silver.
And the amounts that have been measured
leaching from pots are very low.
There have been reports however, that
arsenic can
leach into filtered water at levels of
health concern.
This has nothing to do with the silver.
It's thought that the arsenic is
naturally present in the
clay and that with time, arsenic leaching
will drop to safe levels.
However, it is important to check
the concentration of arsenic in filtered
water.
The silver seems to have two effects.
First, to increase the
removal of bacteria, and second, to
prevent biofilm formation on the ceramic
surface which can reduce the flow rates.
It's thought that silver doesn't have much
impact on viruses.
Two types of silver are used in
ceramic pots: colloidal silver, also
called nanosilver, which
consists of very small particles as the
name
suggests of 100 nanometers or less in
size.
Quick quiz.
How many microns is that?
Go back to science if you don't know.
The interactions on nanosilver and
bacteria are
complex and the subject of active
research.
It does seem that size is important and
that nano
particles may even enter into bacteria
cells and cause internal damage.
It also seems that contact with the silver
surface is important and that
release of dissolved silver can't alone
explain all the effects seen on bacteria.
The other kind of silver is ionic silver
created from salts such as silver nitrate.
Actually, silver nitrate is used in
commercial production of colloidal silver.
For example, by the large company,
Argenol,
which produces a nanosilver powder branded
as Collargol.
Some ceramic filter factories produce
their own colloidal
silver from silver nitrate in order to
save costs.
However, it's not clear that the locally
produced nanosilver is as effective as
commercial varieties.
RDI, a leading producer of ceramic pots in
Cambodia that uses silver nitrate,
reports that they create colloidal silver
particles around five microns in size.
Such large particles certainly couldn't
penetrate inside a bacterial
cell, and might have very different
effectiveness from smaller nanoparticles.
Until the efficacy of silver nitrate
is more conclusively demonstrated, it's
recommended to
use commercial nanosilver products, though
this will
slightly increase the cost of filter
production.
Protozoa are fairly well removed by
ceramic filters
with two to five log reduction values
typically seen.
This is mainly through physical size
exclusion processes.
Bacteria, which are a bit smaller, have
somewhat lower reduction
in the range of one to two or more log
reduction values and the calculation of
these can be complicated
by regrowth and recontamination on the
clean side of the ceramics.
However, viruses show much poorer removal,
with some studies showing no
removal at all, and others showing one or
maybe two log reductions.
It's thought that the main removal
processes
here are electrostatic rather than size
exclusion.
Ceramic pot filters have been produced for
many years in
Latin America and there are mature
products in markets there.
In the last ten years or so, ceramic pots
have
seen tremendous growth in Cambodia led by
two non-governmental organizations.
Resource Development International
Cambodia or RDIC,
and International Enterprise Development
or IDE.
IDE began producing ceramic filters in
2001 and RDI a few years later.
Both NGOs produce their own pots, and sell
them without subsidy through a
variety of distribution channels including
direct sales,
sales to vendors, and sales to NGOs.
The price is typically around eight to 15
U.S. Dollars.
And in recent years, IDE has partnered
with the U.S.
NGO PATH to produce a more
aesthetically pleasing model, shown here.
Their main model is called the Tunsai,
which is Khmer for rabbit.
And their new model is the Super Tunsai.
Although the Super Tunsai costs almost
twice as much as
the regular Tunsai, the new model has
considerably stronger sales.
Both RDI and IDE can produce several
thousand filters per month and
each has sold hundreds of thousands of
filters over the last ten years.
In 2007, the World Bank's water and
sanitation program, together with
UNICEF, supported an evaluation of the RDI
and IDE filters in Cambodia.
The study contains a lot of really
valuable information, and
I encourage you to read the full report
available here.
A summary of some of the key findings
are that, in total, only 30%
of households, which were randomly
selected, were using
the filters at the time of the visit.
However, this was heavily influenced by
the time since implementation.
Nearly 90% of those who had gotten filters
within the past six months were still
using them.
There was a clear and steady decline of
about two percent per month
so that after two years, only about half
of the filters were in use.
The most commonly reported reason for
disuse was breakage,
either of the ceramic element itself or
the tap.
Only about five percent of respondents
reported
slow filtration rates as the reason for
disuse.
Also, use among those who had paid for a
filter was somewhat higher, at 50 percent.
Those who were actively using a filter,
reported filling the filter
almost twice in a day and cleaning two to
three times per week.
The evaluation found that filters removed
about 70% of
turbidity and had an LRV of 1.7 for
E. coli.
Older filters were not less effective at
E. coli removal in
spite of the manufacture recommendation to
replace filters after two years.
However, given the studied breakage rates,
two years
seems like a good estimate of filter life
time.
Ceramic candle filters like this one, have
long been used in middle
and upper class families often after
boiling to remove calcium and magnesium
precipitation.
These candles can be screwed into metal or
plastic household containers and must be
regularly scrubbed clean.
Conventional candle filters tend to be out
of the price range for low income
households.
But new products like the tulip water
filter are bridging that gap.
A tulip filter consists of just the
ceramic candle element in a
plastic protective housing, connected by a
long tube to a safe storage container.
By using a long tube, the pressure
difference is increased and the
flow rates are higher at around four to
five liters per hour.
Tulip candle filters, unlike ceramic pot
filters, can be backwashed with
a plastic bulb and of course can also be
scrubbed clean.
A big advantage is the small size.
A tulip filter can easily be packaged and
transported without fear of breakage.
Tulip has recently produced table top
model, which includes a safe storage
container.
The market isn't as big yet as for ceramic
pot filters.
But several tens of thousands of these
filters have
been sold in a number of low income
countries.
One of the big advantages of ceramic
filtration is
the high social acceptability and fairly
high use rates.
However, those are balanced by moderate
effectiveness especially for viruses.
Most ceramic pot filters include a
in-built safe storage element.
But have a fairly low flow
rate of a few liters per hour.
Ceramic filters involve a one-time capital
cost,
but also need supply chains for
distribution and replacement.
It's possible to produce ceramic pot
filters locally, but the quality can
be variable and it's important to have a
strong quality assurance program.
Finally, ceramic filters do visually
improve the water quality by
removing turbidity, but they do
not provide and residual protection.
And there is still the possibility of
recontamination or
regrowth, especially if filtered water is
transferred to another container.
Much of the content from this module has
been taken
from some really excellent resources
which are freely available online.
The first, is produced by the ceramics
manufacturing working group.
And is a best practice recommendation
for local manufacturing of ceramic pot
filters.
The second, is a ceramic water filter
handbook produced by RDI
in Cambodia, and both of them are freely
available on the internet.
So in summary, ceramic filtration is a
fast
growing and exciting sector within
household water treatment.
Ceramic pot filters can be locally
produced, though
it's important to have a strong quality
assurance program.
And there are examples and resources to
help production facilities do that.
Ceramic filtration involves a variety of
removal mechanisms, including primarily
physical, but also electrostatic and
chemical with the use of colloidal silver.
However, removal of pathogens is mixed.
Protozoa tend to be well removed.
Bacteria fairly well removed.
And viruses, not terribly well removed at
all.
Still, ceramic filters are very user
friendly,
and tend to have high user satisfaction
rates.