Welcome to the end of the second week of
the course.
In this week we started off by looking at
the water safety framework of the
World Health Organization, and then got
into
exploring some of the first processes in
HWTS.
Starting with sedimentation, and then
looking at three different
kinds of filtration: membrane filtration,
ceramics, and biological filtration.
The water safety framework of the World
Health Organization
consists of five different steps, starting
with health based targets.
And then moving into a system
assessment, operational monitoring, and
management and communication.
These three together are called water
safety plans.
Finally, water safety plans are confirmed
with verification monitoring.
We saw how this concept of water safety
plans, while normally applied
to community scale systems, can also
be useful in considering household water
treatment.
We also introduced a key metric which is
the Log Reduction Values, LRV, which is
just the base ten log of concentrations
of something before and after treatment,
usually pathogens.
Finally, we looked at four different
stages in household water treatment, and
spent
significant amounts of time looking at
the first two stages, sedimentation and
filtration.
Sedimentation is frequently required as a
pre-treatment step when the
raw water contains high levels of
turbidity, or suspended solids.
In some cases, gravity settling alone is
enough to remove
particles but in other cases, enhanced
settling is required through the
additional of chemicals called coagulants
which can either be naturally
occurring, derived from plant materials or
metallic salts, such as alum.
Membrane filtration includes a wide range
of
different kinds of processes, from simple
cloth filtration,
to filtration through synthetic membranes,
micro-filtration, ultra-filtration,
nano-filtration, and reverse osmosis,
having increasingly small pore sizes.
Those pores are seen in comparison to the
sizes of inorganic particles but
also to microbes: bacteria, protozoa, and
copepods, and those smallest of microbes,
viruses.
The smallest the tightest of the membranes
like reverse osmosis can
even remove dissolved compounds, even
salts and some other small ions.
However, these synthetic membranes that
remove that, have very small
pore sizes need increasingly high pressure
to push water through the membranes.
Ceramic filtration is similar to membrane
filtration,
except that instead of passing through a
synthetic membrane, water is passed
through ceramics
made from clay and burn off material.
We looked at physical electrostatic, and
chemical mechanisms for removing microbes.
And saw that ceramic filters have good
removal of protozoa, pretty
good removal of bacteria, but variable to
low removal of viruses.
However, they are very user friendly, and
are
a rapidly growing segment of the HWTS
market.
Biological filtration, such as in the
biosand filter
shown here, also realize on physical and
electrostatic removal,
but the principal mechanism is biological
removal through
the formation of an active biofilm called
the Schmutzdecke.
Biosand filters also, like ceramic
filters, have good removal of
protozoa, modest bacteria removal, and
variable to low virus removal.
However, again they are user friendly and
easy to operate.
A key message from this week then, is that
household
water treatment is very similar to
conventional water treatment, in
that it uses some of the same processes,
each of
which can involve multiple mechanisms in
removing or destroying pathogens.
We've looked at sedimentation, methods to
reduce
the particles and turbidity in raw water.
Often as a pre-treatment step.
And also filtration mechanisms involving
physical and electrostatic mechanisms.
As well as biological and chemical ones.
However, filtration alone doesn't fully
remove pathogens from water.
And next week we'll look into more detail
at actual disinfection processes.