[BLANK_AUDIO]
Hello and welcome to the third week of the
course.
Last week we looked at sedimentation and
filtration,
which are ways to remove suspended
particles from water.
This week we focus in on disinfection
processes that result in
high levels of removal or inactivation of
the different classes of pathogens.
We'll start by looking at heat.
Heat, in fact, kills.
Through different mechanisms heat impacts
enzymes and
causes them to denature and become
nonfunctional.
It can affect the proteins that make up
cells
and cause them to unfold and change their
shape.
And also within a cell it can increase the
pressure which damages cells.
We'll look at two broad classes of heat
treatment, boiling and pasteurization.
To understand how heat disinfection works
we have to
first think a little bit about temperature
and pressure,
and recognize that pressure affects the
boiling point.
If the pressure is higher, then the
boiling point can be higher.
And in fact, this is how an
autoclave works with steam sterilization
and high pressure
about one bar above atmospheric pressure
and
that allows water to reach 121 degrees
Celsius.
And if it's kept there for 15 minutes
under steam it's a very effective
sterilization technique.
Conversely, if the air pressure is lower
the boiling temperature is also
lower and we'll discuss the implications
that that can have on boiling.
With disinfection processes both
the amount of disinfectant present and the
time that the pathogens are exposed have
an impact on removal efficiency.
For heat disinfection then, we can think of
both
the temperature and the time of
exposure, and recognize
that at higher temperatures a shorter time
of treatment
is required to achieve an equivalent
amount of pathogen reduction.
The thermal death kinetics of heat
disinfection
are assumed to follow first order or
exponential decay.
Which means that a fixed amount of
time is required to achieve one log
reduction value.
This is called a D value typically set at
121 Celsius.
And if a D value for one pathogen was ten
minutes,
then after ten minutes, 90% of that
pathogen would have been inactivated.
After 20 minutes, it would be 99%, and so
on, and so on.
The food canning industry is very
concerned about
thermal death kinetics because foods are
pasteurized before canning.
And canned food can be on shelves for a
long time, months, even years.
Before being consumed.
So the guidelines are very strict for
ensuring high levels of disinfection, with
a 12 D reduction of Clostridium botulinum
spores being a typical industry standard.
Drinking water treatment is normally less
strict.
Drinking water doesn't sit on shelves for
years before being consumed.
And typically seven log reduction is
considered as complete disinfection for
practical purposes.
Boiling is the oldest method of household
water treatment, and today
it's practiced by an estimated 600 million
people around the world.
It's particularly common in East Asia and
in Uzbekistan, Mongolia, Viet Nam, and
Indonesia.
More than 90% of the population report
boiling their water regularly before
drinking it.
Boiling is effective against all classes
of pathogens, viruses, bacteria, and
protozoa.
And it's not effected by turbidity
in water, unlike some other disinfection
processes.
However after water is boiled, it must be
cooled
before drinking, and it's often
transferred to a secondary container.
Where it is quite prone to
recontamination.
Finally boiling removes all dissolved
gases from water.
which changes the taste of
the water.
It can give it a flat taste, and if the
water is hard,
calcium and magnesium can precipitate out
forming
small white particles which can cause
esthetic problems.
In recent years, a number of studies have
examined
the effectiveness of boiling as applied in
different countries.
These studies have found significant
reductions in indicator
bacteria, usually thermo-tolerant
coliforms, but have also documented
substantial recontamination of water with
roughly half to 60,
maybe 70%, of samples having no detectable
indicator bacteria.
However, the level of contamination tends
to be
small with roughly 75% of samples falling
in
to the low risk class of having less than
ten colony forming units per 100 mLs.
Also, the log reduction values of one
to two
may also reflect relatively good quality
of the pretreated water.
If the pretreated water has low to medium
levels of contamination, it's very
difficult to demonstrate higher levels
of removal.
In many low and middle income countries,
when boiling is practiced, biomass, either
wood, or some crop residues or other
materials are used as the fuel.
And this can have substantial negative
impacts.
First there can be health impacts.
If biomass is burnt inside the house, a
lot of soot and smoke is generated.
Which has serious negative impacts on
health.
It's a risk factor for lower respiratory
infections.
Infections which are a major cause of
child mortality.
Biomass burning also has negative
environmental impacts,
where deforestation can be exacerbated by
widespread use of biomass
as well as the
release of CO2 and smoke into the
immediate environment.
Finally, burning of biomass can be very
costly in terms
of both the fuel itself and the time
that's needed.
Two of those studies from the previous
page,
done in India and Vietnam, also examine
the costs
of boiling and found that the fuel cost
alone was around .5 to 1.5% of monthly
income.
But that substantial amounts of time were
needed, either for collecting fuel, if
it's not bought, or for treating, taking
extra time to treat the water in the home.
And that these have significant economic
impacts equivalent
to possibly two to 5% of monthly income.
While boiling is highly effective
against all classes of pathogens, it's
not actually necessary to reach 100
degrees to get good log reduction values.
The mechanisms by which heat operates,
enzymes denaturing, protein damage,
an increasing pressure within cells are
having impacts at much lower temperatures.
In fact, it's possible to cook an egg at
72 degrees.
This is high enough to damage the
proteins,
causing the whites and the yolk to become
opaque.
Similarly milk pasteurization is done at
72 degrees for only fifteen seconds.
At a lower temperature of 63 degrees
Celsius, thirty minutes are required for
pasteurization and both of these achieve
roughly seven log reduction of common
pathogens.
Recall also, that the heat up time and
the cool down time, contribute to the
pathogen reduction.
So, it's really not necessary to bring the
water to a full boil to get effective
treatment.
The problem, of course, is that it's
difficult to know
when you've reached an effective treatment
temperature, like 70 degrees
for pasteurization.
One tool that can help is called a, a WAPI
or a water pasteurization indicator.
It's a small tube that has a little glob
of wax which melts at 70 or some specified
temperature.
Perhaps because of the difficulties in
determining
when an appropriate pasteurization
temperature has been
reached, there's been relatively little
experience with
pasteurization as a household water
treatment system.
One example comes from Bangladesh which
was
developed by professor Fakhrul Islam at
Rajshahi University.
And this is called the Chulli system.
And it takes advantage of readily
available
waste heat that comes from inefficient
cook stoves,
homemade clay stoves which reach a
temperature of about 600 degrees.
But more than 80% of that heat is wasted.
So Professor Islam developed a coil,
a metal coil made out of aluminum
which acts as a heat exchanger.
And when this coil is built into a cook
stove, water can be passed through the
coil during cooking,
and, water heated up to the pasteurization
temperature before it comes out the other
side.
Here's what it looks like in practice.
That coil is built into a clay cook stove
and
then attached to a reservoir for raw
water that then feeds
the water through a tube into the coil
during cooking
and it comes out through a tap into a
storage container.
Now, the nice thing about this system is it
doesn't take additional
fuel, because it takes advantage of heat
that's already being used for cooking.
However, an evaluation made in 2007 found
that while it
was microbiologically effective with a
medium of five LRV E. coli.
Only about 20% of people who received
the Chulli systems were actually
using them.
So compliance was a definite problem.
Heat disinfection is widely effective
against all classes of pathogens
with six to even more than nine log
reduction values possible.
Some of the pathogens which are
particularly resistant to other treatment
processes, filtration or chlorine for
example, are very vulnerable to heat.
So we see that cryptosporidium cysts can
be
inactivated after just one minute at 72
degrees.
And viruses are easily killed.
Some of them even at 60 degrees.
Many studies have been done on bacteria.
Many from the food industry and again,
these are vulnerable. There are some
special
examples of things like anthrax spores
which
can actually survive boiling for several
minutes.
But the pathogens of concern in drinking
water tend to be vulnerable to heat
treatment.
For a more detailed review of heat
sensitivity of different pathogens.
here are two articles, which are freely
available on the internet.
The top one also describes the Chulli Water
treatment system in more detail.
Now recall that pressure affects the
boiling temperature and
at lower pressure water boils at a lower
temperature.
Well, on this earth we have elevations
ranging from negative
427 meters to 8,848 meters on top of Mount
Everest.
And what impact does that have on boiling
temperatures.
Well, of course at mean sea level,
the boiling temperature is one hundred
degrees.
It's the same in Dhaka at four meters
above sea level.
It's pretty much the same in Dübendorf,
home of Eawag in Switzerland.
And if we look at some of the high cities
in the world,
Addis Ababa, La Paz, Aspen we see boiling
temperatures of around 90 degrees.
If we would go all the way to the top of
Mount Everest and boil some
water, it would be at 72 degrees, which
we have seen is an effective
pasteurization temperature.
At La Rinconada in Peru, the highest
continuously
inhabited place on earth Water boils at 83
degrees.
So, while it's true that water boils at
lower temperatures you're still getting
effective pathogen removal at any of these
temperatures if the water boils at all.
By the way, just for information altitude
also affects the amount
of oxygen available, the relative oxygen
compared to mean sea level.
So in a place like Addis Ababa, there's a
lot less oxygen around.
And, of course, if you're on top of Mt
Everest, you're only
having about a third as much oxygen as you
would at sea level.
So then, how long is it necessary to boil
water for?
Some organizations recommend 10 minutes,
20 minutes, or even longer.
And while this may be necessary to
really inactivate the most recalcitrant
of microbes, like
anthrax spores, it is not necessary for
the pathogens of most concern in drinking
water
leading causes of diarrheal disease.
Giardia,
Cryptosporidium,
enteric bacteria and viruses,
are all relatively vulnerable to heat.
Pasteurization, alone, should give
adequate protection for drinking water.
And anywhere in the world, where you can
boil water, the
water will reach at least 70 degrees, and
be effectively pasteurized.
Remember too, that pathogens die off
during the
warming up and boiling off phases as
well.
So by the time water boils, even a tiny
bit
at any altitude, most of the pathogens
have already been killed.
Now I don't recommend boiling water on top
of Everest.
Not least because there's hardly any
oxygen up there.
But for a water treatment practice it
would still count as pasteurization.
W.H.O. recommends that water should be
brought to a full rolling boil.
And while this is actually more heat
treatment than is needed, it
does give a clear objective signal,
that the disinfection temperature has been
reached.
Some considerations then for heat
treatment both, boiling and pasteurization
then
are that it is highly effective against
all classes of pathogens, and
that it's not affected by turbidity as
some other treatment processes are.
However, it does take a long time,
especially
when cooling time is added or collecting
of firewood.
And it does change the taste of the water,
which some people might not like.
It's very simple to operate.
No special equipment is needed for
boiling, though
there is a possibility, a significant one,
of recontamination.
Finally, boiling is widely accepted,
understood,
and even promoted all around the world.
And maybe one of the most significant
challenges is the high
energy and time costs required to boil
water in the home.
So, in summary, we've seen that
heat kills.
It is an effective household water
treatment process, effective against
all classes of pathogens whether boiling
or pasteurization is used.
Boiling is very widespread.
It is the most commonly practiced of the
HWTS options.
But recontamination of boiled water is
also very widespread.
Pasteurization works well technically, but
is much less widely applied.