Today we look at Chemical Disinfection.
And in particular chlorine, which is the
most widely used disinfectant globally.
We'll explore a bit the chemistry of
chlorine and chlorine dosing.
We'll look at different forms of chlorine,
gas, liquid, and solid.
And review the effectiveness of chlorine
in reducing pathogens.
Finally we will give an example of
chlorine use in Haiti.
Chlorine has been used for over a century
for the treatment of drinking water.
Beginning in the UK and USA in the early
20th century.
Today, chlorine is used in 98% of U.S.
water
utilities and in similarly high
numbers across the world.
Chlorine is also widely used at the
household level.
Of course, many households use bleach for
cleaning and laundry.
But in surveys conducted in low and medium
income countries
5.6% of respondents reported adding
chlorine to their
drinking water to make it safer to drink.
This was the second most common
household water treatment practice
mentioned, after boiling,
and was particularly high in Latin
American and Caribbean countries.
Chlorine is a strong oxidant.
And it reacts rapidly with different kinds
of
organic material, including cell wall,
DNA, and enzymes.
That's also why it's good at
cleaning things, it really destroys
organic compounds.
But actually, in part because it's so
reactive, the
key mechanisms in pathogen inactivation
are not well understood.
Especially for viruses and protozoa.
When we talk about chlorine, we can refer
to many different things.
Large drinking water utilities typically
use
elemental chlorine, present as chlorine
gas.
Which is cost effective, and includes, by
definition, 100% chlorine.
The next most concentrated form, also used
in
many utilities, is high test hypochlorite,
or HTH.
Which contains about 60 to 70% chlorine
and comes in powders or tablets.
Bleaching powder or chlorinated lime or
calcium hypochlorite is another powdered
form.
And is often marketed as around 35%
chlorine.
But the chlorine isn't stable and actual
concentrations vary widely.
Sometimes as low as 15%.
It makes calculating doses difficult.
Household bleach is a solution of sodium
hypochlorite, usually around 5% chlorine.
And Javel water is a similar product,
typically a little bit less strong.
Finally, it's possible to make chlorine
locally by
passing in an electrical current through
simple salt solution.
This usually results in something less
than 1% chlorine.
Whatever the chlorine source, when it is
added
to water, it becomes hypochlorous acid, or
HOCl.
And hypochlorous acid loses a proton at
higher pH
and becomes hypochlorite or OCl, with a
negative charge.
These two species together are called Free
Chlorine.
At pH 7.54, the two species are present in
equal amount.
At higher pH, hypochlorite dominates.
While at lower pH, hypochlorous acid is the
main species.
This is important because hypochlorous
acid, the one with
the proton attached, is a much stronger
disinfectant than hypochlorite.
For this reason it's recommended that
water should always have
a pH of less than eight when chlorination
is being applied.
So that there's a reasonable amount of
hypochlorous acid present.
Chlorine is highly reactive, and when
added to water, a lot
of the chlorine will react with natural
chemicals in the water.
So, the dose has to big enough to meet
both the chlorine demand of the water.
And to produce a residual that is strong
enough to kill the target pathogens.
Chlorine demand can be caused by organic
carbon, which is naturally present in
surface waters.
But also by iron and manganese, or
ammonia,
which tends to be more present in ground
water.
It's normally recommended that to have a
residual
concentration of at least 0.5 milligrams
per liter.
And this can require a dose of any where
from one to
five milligrams per liter with two
milligrams per liter being fairly typical.
Turbidity reduces the effectiveness of
chlorine both
by shielding pathogens directly and by
consuming chlorine.
So standard doses are normally doubled
when the water is turbid.
Ideally, the right dose will be determined
through trial and error.
By adding different amounts of chlorine to
the water
to be treated to see what yields the
desired residual.
Chlorine doesn't pose any
health risks itself
though the concentrated forms can be
dangerous to handle.
WHO does list a guideline value of five mg
per liter.
But this is conservative and would
probably result in
unacceptable tastes or odors at this level
in any case.
The use of chlorine in household water
treatment was first developed by
the US Centers for Disease Control, and
the Pan American Health Organization.
They proposed an intervention, including
three elements.
Chlorine disinfection, and this was later
expanded to include other HWTS processes,
Safe storage, and behavior change
communication.
This model has been widely taken up,
especially through Latin America and parts
of Africa.
And typically involves production of a
dilute
sodium hypochlorite solution around 0.75%
free chlorine.
Now, because hypochlorous acid is much
more reactive and also more volatile
than hypochlorite, the shelf life is much
longer at high pH.
So these solutions are typically
stabilized at pH 11 or greater.
For similar reasons household bleach has a
pH around 12.
And it's slightly irritating to the skin.
In different countries, different brands of
liquid chlorine are promoted.
Some of the common brand names are Water
Guard, Clorin, Claro and in francophone
countries, Sur Eau.
The bottles are normally designed so that
one capful
is a good dose for the locally used
storage containers.
For example, a five milliliter capful of
0.75% free chlorine
added to a 20 liter jerry can gives a dose
of 1.9 milligrams per liter.
And, again, this dose should be doubled if
the raw water is turbid.
There is another form of chlorine
which isn't used in conventional water
treatment,
but is popular in swimming pools and
increasingly in household water treatment.
This is a chemical with a long name.
It's called sodium dichloroisocyanurate.
So you can see why people call it NaDCC
instead.
And it's about 60% free chlorine by
weight.
The other 40% is a chemical, cyanuric
acid,
which bonds with free chlorine and
provides a reservoir.
Thus, as free chlorine is consumed
through chlorine demand or inactivation of
pathogens,
the reservoir can release more free
chlorine into the water.
Cyanuric acid itself doesn't pose a health
risk.
The guideline value of 40 milligrams per
liter is well
above levels that would be reached in
drinking water treatment.
Because of this reservoir effect, any DCC
allows
a more steady and consistent free chlorine
level.
Which may lead to fewer reports of taste
and odor problems.
NADCC is produced in the form of
effervescent tablets or fizzy
tablets, which are individually wrapped
and have a long shelf life.
They come in a wide range of
concentrations.
The most popular are 33 and 67 milligram
versions.
Which are good for 10 or 20 liters of
water, respectively.
Aquatabs, shown here, is one of the
leading
brands globally, but there are others as
well.
NaDCC tablets are easy to use and have
proven particularly popular in emergency
settings, but now are increasingly used
routinely at the household level.
Chlorine efficacy, like other
disinfectants is a combination
of the concentration and the time of
exposure.
For chlorine the dose can be expressed as
a
CT value in units of minute, milligrams
per liter.
For conventional drinking water treatment,
a common goal is to
have a residual of 0.5 milligrams per
liter free chlorine.
In contact with water for at least 30
minutes to ensure a good pathogen kill.
Multiplying these together gives a Ct
value of 15 minute milligrams per liter.
Which is also equivalent to 15 minutes at
one milligram per liter.
In HWTS, a typical dose is around 1.9
milligrams per liter,
which gives a larger Ct of 56 minute
milligrams per liter.
How effective is this dose?
Well this chart shows the Ct99.
That's the Ct dose necessary to achieve
99% kill.
And you all know instantly by now that
that means a two log reduction value,
right?
Well bacteria are very sensitive to
chlorine.
And a Ct of less than 0.08 is necessary to
achieve 2 LRV.
But viruses are significantly tougher.
It takes a Ct of from 2 to 30 to get our
two log reductions.
And protozoa are tougher still, with Ct99s
from 25 to 245.
And that doesn't include cryptosporidium
cysts,
which are basically unaffected by
chlorine.
One study even reported a Ct value of over
15,000, just to achieve 3 log reductions
of cryptosporidium.
Now recall, our typical dose was in the
range
of 15 to maybe 60 milligrams per
liter.
So you can see that chlorine is not very
effective against some protozoa.
Now to be fair, not all protozoa are as
resistant as cryptosporidium.
Giardia, for example, has a Ct 99 of about
15.
So on balance, chlorine can achieve from
two
to five LRV for protozoa though not for
cryptosporidium.
Bacteria are more sensitive to chlorine
and removal can easily exceed six LRV.
Viruses have intermediate resistance
Disinfection might take a
bit longer, but still good removal can be
achieved.
Up to now we have been talking about free
chlorine which is that combination of
hypochlorous acid and hypochlorite.
But when free chlorine reacts with
ammonia,
it creates a different form called
chloramines.
And there is a whole family
of chloramines with monochloramine,
dichloramine, and trichloramine.
These are called combined chlorine, and
they're a less efficient disinfectant.
But they're still used in some countries
because they're long
lasting and can be useful, say, in a
distribution network.
However, the chloramines have a stronger
odor, especially Trichloramine.
In fact, trichloramine and a bit of
dichloramine
is what's responsible for that swimming
pool odor.
If you ever smell a strong indoor swimming
pool,
it's not the bleach itself for the
hypochlorine.
It's the combined chlorine.
Combined chlorine isn't typically used in
household water treatment.
Though it can be formed unintentionally if
the water has high ammonia levels.
There's another important potential,
unintended reaction
that can happen with free chlorine.
If there are high levels of dissolved
organic carbon in the water being treated,
then the free chlorine will react with the
carbon and produce what are called
disinfection byproducts.
Such as trihalomethanes or haloacetic
acids.
And some of these compounds have been
shown in laboratory studies
to cause cancer in laboratory animals when
applied at high doses.
So accordingly, WHO and many governments
have derived health based
drinking water guideline values for these
compounds in drinking water.
And these are typically set at a level
which would be expected to cause one
additional case of bladder or kidney
cancer for every 100,000 people,
who drink two liters of water per day at
that guideline value for a 70 year
lifetime period.
And while that is a real health risk, it's
still very small
compared to the mortality rates caused by
diarrhea and other waterborne diseases.
Here's what the World Health Organization
has to say about disinfection
by-products.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
>> The Jolivert Safe Water for Families
Program has
sold sodium hypochlorite to households in
rural Haiti since 2002.
The program began at the Missions of Love
health clinic, in Jolivert northern Haiti.
And since 2008, it has been managed by the
NGO, Deep Springs International.
The program makes its own chlorine through
electrolysis of salt water.
Which is branded as Gadyen Dlo, meaning
water guardian in Haitian Creole.
Project team members enroll families by
selling safe
storage containers or Bokit Espesyal with
lids and taps.
The team also sells bottles of Gadyen Dlo
keeping sales records for each family.
And conducts regular household visits to
monitor use and provide ongoing education.
One bottles costs about $1.25 and contains
enough chlorine to treat
an average family's drinking water for
about a month and a half.
By May 2010, the program had reached over
4,000 participants and had
sold enough Gadyen Dlo to treat 12 million
liters of drinking water.
In 2010, an impact evaluation was done in
northern Haiti
and reported a few years later in a
scientific journal.
The team found that 3/4ths of the randomly
selected households
in the program area reported that they
were currently using Gadyen Dlo.
And 56% of these households compared to
just 10% in controlled
areas had free chlorine residuals between
0.2 and 2 milligrams per liter.
Indicating that they were applying
chlorine correctly.
This evaluation was made after the
earthquake in January
2010, but focused on areas not affected by
the quake.
The Gadyen Dlo program was extended to the
earthquake zone.
And accelerated greatly after the onset of
cholera in the region in October 2010.
Half a million bottles of Gadyen Dlo
were distributed in the affected areas for
free.
Use of Gadyen Dlo in the earthquake
effected zone has
continued but this may be due to continued
distribution of free product.
It's an open question whether people will
be willing to
pay for Gadyen Dlo once the free
distribution period ends.
While chlorine is by far the most
commonly applied chemical disinfectant.
There are other ones,
especially in commercial treatment,
chloramines or
chlorine dioxide in some cases.
And ozone is gaining in popularity.
But these are not typically applied, at
a household level, in lower and middle income
countries.
There are some emerging products that use
bromine as an alternative to chlorine.
Some filters have this.
And silver has at least a bacteriostatic
and maybe a bactericidal effect.
And is often combined with another
treatment, such as in ceramic filtration.
So certainly one of the main advantages
of chlorination is it's highly effective
against bacteria,
including cholera and has been
demonstrated to really stop cholera
outbreaks.
However, it's ineffective against at least
some
protozoa and requires longer contact times
for viruses.
Chlorine does give a residual protection
which can help minimize recontamination or
regrowth.
But it has a characteristic taste and odor
which people
may find unpleasant if they are not
accustomed to it.
It's fairly simple to apply chlorine but
it
does require that the water has low
turbidity.
Chlorine application is low cost, but
does require supply chains to replace
consumables.
And then finally, there's
often misunderstanding about disinfection
by-products.
And the relative importance of these.
Which can cause resistance to chlorination
programs.
So, in summary, chlorine is a widely used
disinfectant in both conventional
treatment and household water treatment.
Chlorine can be obtained from a wide
variety of sources, but all
of these produce free chlorine in water,
which is the active disinfectant.
Chlorine is highly effective against
bacteria including vibrio cholera
and also is effective against viruses and
some protozoa,
but is not effective against
cryptosporidium
which is a major cause of disease.
Cryptosporidium cysts are larger and
should be removed
through filtration processes especially
following coagulation and flocculation.