[BLANK_AUDIO]
Recall from the first week that we
discussed different ways in
which drinking water can become
contaminated along a safe water chain.
Safe storage of drinking water can help
to minimize such contamination risks
during collection
and transport, when the source is outside
the home as well as during household
storage.
Especially when water is treated at the
household level, it's very important
to store it properly so that the gains in
quality are not lost.
There are a number of characteristics we
would
like to see in an ideal household storage
container.
Perhaps the most important one is that the
container
should be covered and that there should be
an
opening, which is small enough to
discourage people from
putting their hands into the container
during water collection,
or from using a scoop or a ladle to
retrieve stored water.
The opening however, should be large
enough to
allow easy filling at the point of
collection.
And usually openings are between five and
eight centimeters in diameter,
and ideally, they have a screw cap of
some kind.
Although you don't want it to be too easy
to
insert hands into the container, it is
good if the
container can be cleaned periodically, and
in some designs a
lid can be removed and the insides can be
cleaned manually.
Where this isn't possible, users are
recommended to periodically add
sand or pebbles and shake them about to
clean the insides.
You can also add soap or chlorine after
removing the
pebbles to wash the insides of the
container.
Water can be safely retrieved by pouring.
But this requires some physical effort to
lift the bucket and a risk of spilling.
So it's preferred to have a tap which can
be used to withdraw water.
Taps should have a fairly large bore so
that the flow rates are high.
However, taps do break or leak so they
should also
be simple enough to be repaired or
replaced with local hardware.
Often storage containers are also used for
transporting
water from the point of collection to the
household, so the container shouldn't be
too large. Even a 20 or 25 liter jerry can
is very heavy when it's full. And of
course, it should be strong and stable so
it
isn't easily tipped over or broken. And
it's better
to be opaque to prevent the growth of
algae.
If chemical disinfection is being used,
it's good to use a container
size, that corresponds to an easy chemical
dose typically ten or twenty liters.
And finally, the container should be
affordable and ideally available through
local markets.
Here are some examples of containers
that were designed specifically for safe
storage.
This is the container developed by the
U.S. Centers
for Disease Control and the Pan American
Health Organization,
as part of the safe water system.
It's a modified jerry can that holds 20
liters of water and costs about $5.
The Oxfam bucket has a lid with an
opening and cap
built in, and the cap is attached so you
can't lose it.
You can also completely remove the lid
which allows very
efficient transport since the buckets can
be stacked inside each other.
These also cost around $4 or $5 and while
they were designed
at Oxfam in the UK, they're now produced
all around the world.
In many countries in Africa, 20 liter
jerry cans are
now widely used for collecting,
transporting and storing water.
They're fairly easy to carry on the head
though they are
heavy and have a small opening which
prevents putting hands inside.
Water is normally poured out of the
opening.
They're not easy to clean, and they can be
quite
dirty like this example here from the
Central African Republic.
On the right, you see a modified jerry can
being distributed in the Philippines after
Typhoon Haiyan by the NGO Plan
International with support from DFID.
These jerry cans have a large screw top for
filling that also allows cleaning.
And they come with a built-in tap, that
small, red, knob at the bottom.
It's very easy to convert a standard
plastic
storage bucket into a safe storage
container by
drilling a hole through the plastic wall
to
install a tap, like this guy is doing
here.
The buckets are usually then labeled
with a sticker including instructions,
especially
about using the tap to withdraw water
rather than dipping into the bucket.
In Haiti, where this picture was taken,
this is an easy message since the tap
is seen as a sign of higher socio-economic
status and families take pride in using
it.
In many cultures people like to use clay
pots, because they cool the water due to
evaporation.
In some cases water is transported in clay
pots, but in most areas water
is transported in plastic containers and
then
transferred to clay pots at the household.
By working with local potters it is
possible to modify
clay pots to have a tap, as shown in this
example.
One way to demonstrate the importance of
safe water storage containers is to look
at the impact that providing a storage
container alone can have on water quality.
There aren't many studies available on
this topic since normally safe storage
containers are distributed, along side
some
kind of treatment for example chlorine
disinfection.
There are a couple of studies however,
that suggest that
safe storage alone can have a significant
impact on water quality.
The first is a somewhat old study, it's
from 2001, made in a Malawi refugee
camp, where there were repeated outbreaks
of diarrhea and cholera.
Although the microbial quality at the
wells,
where people collected their drinking
water was good.
The camp organizers provided randomly
selected 100 households with an
improved storage container, and this is
what it looked like.
And households had to exchange their
existing storage containers for the new
ones.
The households, along with the households
that didn't get the new containers
were monitored for four months and the
researchers found that fecal coliform
levels were reduced by over 50%, by
the improved storage containers, or
nearly 70% if, the geometric mean rather
than the arithmetic mean is used.
The biggest impact is seen on water
quality directly after collecting water
at the source, with much better water
quality in the improved bucket.
The researchers also found that the hands
of
people collecting water had high levels of
fecal bacteria
on them, further strengthening the idea
that contact
between hands and water is the cause of
contamination.
In addition to finding a good reduction in
water quality, there
was a 30% reduction in diarrheal disease
among children under age five.
And at the end of the study, households
were
offered the chance to get their old
storage containers back.
But the great majority of them
chose to keep
the new containers indicating that
they liked them and appreciated them.
More recently, 72 villages were studied in
rural Benin setting.
These villages had to have at least 40% of
the household using public pumps or
standpipes, but instead
in spite of having relatively good sources
of water,
household water quality was quite poor at
the baseline.
In half of these 72 villages, every single
household was provided with a free
improved storage container.
Either a 30 liter plastic jerry can or a
30 liter clay pot, and both of these were
fitted with taps and had stickers on them
encouraging
people not to put their hand inside the
container.
In all, 364 households were included in
the intervention,
and a similar number were monitored in the
non-intervention villages.
The evaluation found that after six
to eight months after receiving the
containers,
88% were still in use and actually, it was
95% of the plastic containers,
and just under 80% of the clay pots that
were still being used.
And people reported significant breakage
of the clay pots
and also that they were more difficult to
clean.
Stored water in the improved containers
had 70%
less E. coli than in the control
households.
But the researchers did not find a
significant impact on diarrheal disease.
So, in summary, we've seen that safe
storage containers can be designed to
minimize
recontamination and we have looked at some
of the desired characteristics of a good
container.
We have seen some examples of containers
that are
widely used, and also I had two examples
of
intervention studies that seem to show
quite a significant
impact on water quality from improved
storage containers alone.