Now, we discussed in the first week,
how the processes involved with household
water
treatment, are the same processes used in
conventional water treatment at community
or municipal scales.
But professional treatment at these
scales, typically involves multiple
barriers to contamination, especially when
surface water is being treated.
We've seen that some pathogens are more
resistant to
certain kinds of disinfection than others
are, and that for
this reason you might have water with no
E. Coli
bacteria, but still contaminated with
heartier microbes, such as
cryptosporidium cysts.
Well cryptosporidium cysts are large, so
filtration is normally more effective
than disinfection in insuring that
drinking water doesn't contain crypto.
It's more difficult, naturally to apply
multiple
treatment steps at the household scale.
It's hard enough to correctly and
consistently apply one treatment step.
How much harder is it, if two or three
steps must be followed?
Perhaps for this reason, there are
relatively few
examples of informal combinations of
multiple barriers in HWTS.
There are, however, a good number of
commercial products which incorporate two
or more processes in a way that is more or
less invisible to the consumer.
Informally, there are many different
combinations
that could be made involving some
kind of pretreatment or filtration along
with a disinfection step and safe storage.
This image from CAWST shows, how a biosand
filter can be combined with safe storage,
that's an
Oxfam bucket and CAWST recommends that
people then use
chlorine or another disinfectant step
before drinking the water.
It's not clear how seriously this
recommendation is taken in the field.
But, this kind of combination, say of
filtration followed by chlorination
and safe storage, is probably the most
manageable kind of informal combination.
If we look at commercial combinations, one
very potent one
is the combination of a coagulant
flocculant, with chlorine disinfection.
The coagulant removes suspended particles,
allowing the chlorine to act effectively.
We saw a video of the coagulation progress
from this product, the Procter and Gamble
purifier of water, in an earlier episode
this product was formerly marketed as PUR.
But there are other similar commercial
products such
as Watermaker, developed by Control
Chemicals in South Africa.
This combination is particularly good in
emergencies, where water might be highly
turbid.
In fact, the more turbidity in the water,
the better the coagulation process works.
A drawback is that a large-mouth container
is needed to
add the chemicals to the water and stir it
well.
You can't do that in a jerry can.
Then, a second container is also needed,
which might
be a safe storage container, like this one
with the
tap, since the treated water should be
filtered through
a simple cloth before use to remove any
remaining flax.
There are many more commercial systems
based on the combination of filtration
and disinfection typically with chlorine,
particularly
targeting middle income or upper income
households.
These systems work best with water that
has only low levels of turbidity, since
their filtering elements could easily get
clogged
if there were high levels of suspended solids.
These filters are particularly popular in
Eastern or South
Eastern Asia, but are growing in
popularity throughout the world.
Here, you see the Aquasure filter produced
by Eureka Forbes, and Hindustan Unilever's
Pureit.
Both of these include a chlorine
cartridge, which is called something else,
something innocuous like the germkill
battery
in Pureit which must be regularly
replaced.
The Pureit uses a secondary activated
carbon block,
following the chlorine step to remove
residual chlorine.
So there's no taste for the consumer.
The Tata Swach filter uses colloidal
silver as the disinfectant.
And mineral pot filters
are produced by a variety of companies,
and sometimes branded as Korean filters.
They they typically don't have
a chlorine disinfectant, but do have small
amounts of various porous material such as
activated carbon,
zeolites or ion exchange resins that may
or may not help remove pathogens.
All of these filters do have built-in safe
storage
and most require regular replacement of
filtration or disinfection cartridges.
Most of these companies produce a range of
products, targeting different types of
consumers including high end
models not discussed here, that require
electricity and
do things like fill automatically or
produce chilled water.
So in summary the multiple barrier
approach, which is critically important in
conventional water treatment, it can also
be applied at the household scale.
Multiple barriers provide greater chances
of removing or inactivating all of the
different kinds of pathogens, which might
be present in the raw water.
Combinations can be done in informal
systems, but
are probably more effective in
commercially designed systems.
And the most commonly used combinations
are either coagulation
or filtration followed by chlorine
disinfection and safe storage.