In this week, the second week of looking
at technologies, we covered the
disinfection processes including heat,
ultraviolet radiation
and chemical disinfection in particular
with chlorine.
We also looked at safe storage and
combined systems.
For heat disinfection we started with
boiling, the
most commonly used household water
treatment practice in
the world, which is simply bringing the
water
to 100 degrees if you're at sea level.
And we also looked at pasteurization which
inactivates pathogens at lower
temperatures around 70 degrees.
And we showed that both boiling and
pasteurization.
Are effective against all classes of
pathogens and also are unaffected by
turbidity.
We learned, what ultra violet
radiation is and what effects
it has on microbes and looked at the
differences between UV-C.
Which is used in UV applications with
lamps and UV-A and a bit of
UV-B which are involved in solar
disinfection
using natural solar radiation and plastic
bottles.
We also looked at examples of both of
UV-C application and show SODIS in
developing countries.
Next, we looked at chemical disinfection
focusing on chlorination.
We reviewed briefly chlorine chemistry,
the different ways that chlorine can be
generated or obtained, and applied in
liquids or tablet forms for household
treatment.
We discussed how chlorine has variable
effectiveness for different classes of
pathogens.
It's especially effective against bacteria
such as, E. coli.
And we looked at the safe water system
developed by CDC and PAHO which includes
a disinfection step along with safe
storage and behavior change communication.
And here you see some examples of the safe
water system being applied.
We considered the need for safe storage,
regardless of what kind of treatment step
is applied.
And looked at the desired characteristics
of a good safe storage container.
We showed you several different examples
of such containers.
And referred to two intervention studies that
looked at the impacts of providing
safe storage containers on household water
quality in two different settings.
Finally, after reviewing all of these
different
processes from sedimentation and
filtration to disinfection,
individually,
we reminded ourselves that it's important
to have
multiple barriers to prevent contamination
of water quality.
This is done at a municipal or community
scale,
but can also be done at household scale.
Through informal combinations, such as
this one here,
or commercial formulations, especially the
combination of
coagulation and chlorination or filtration
and chlorination.
Well we've come to the end of the
section of the course that focuses on
technologies.
We've reviewed the various household water
treatment technologies from sedimentation
and filtration through different kinds of
disinfection and on to safe storage.
We've discussed the effectiveness of these
different steps against different kinds of
pathogens and given advantages and
challenges
of each of these treatment processes.
Illustrated with real examples from the
field.
Well, the technologies are
actually the easy part.
It's not all that difficult, actually to
come up with something that will kill
pathogens.
What's much more difficult is to get that
system rolled out, adopted, taken up in
the field, and used effectively and
sustainability to
provide safe drinking water at the
household level.
So that's the subject of the remainder of
the course.
And we'll start next week by looking at
different implementation strategies.