In the last module, we
talked
about different strategies for promotion
of HWTS.
If the objective is purely to maximize
profit, any
reductions in disease that result are
nice, but are secondary.
If on the other hand the goal is
to maximize a social good like reducing
diarrheal disease,
then interventions will often aim to
target the
most vulnerable populations those who are
consuming unsafe water.
And of course the HWTS technology needs to
be effective and applied consistently
We've already looked at the base of the
pyramid but a good strategy can
be to promote HWTS in special settings
where either people face particular health
risks or where they're more likely to take
up and consistently apply a new behavior.
And today we'll look at some examples of
this approach in schools, and integrated
with health interventions.
There's been a lot of interest in improving
water, sanitation and hygiene in schools.
One reason is that many children suffer
from
diarrhea and other disease related to poor
wash.
Another argument is that inadequate wash
facilities prevents
students, especially girls, from attending
and completing school.
If there are no latrines, and girls can't
urinate privately
during the day, they may simply not go at
all.
School boys, on the other hand, often have
no problems urinating in the open.
It is somehow more acceptable.
In many cultures, for boys than girls.
Finally, a third argument for WASH in
schools, is that by reaching children when
they are young and impressionable, good
habits
can be established which will last a
lifetime.
So, there are many reasons to work with
WASH in schools and there
are more and more examples of combining
and integrating HWTS with school settings.
Demand is generally created through school
level demonstrations which may
involve water quality testing to
demonstrate the effectiveness of
treatment.
And in some cases children are asked to
bring some messages back to their homes, or for
example, to demonstrate SODIS to their
parents, in
an effort to stimulate demand within the
broader community.
School interventions tend to be supported
technically by an
NGO or other development partners in
at least
the initial phases, but there's always
close collaboration with,
the relevant government partner, such as
the Ministry of Education.
Costs are generally not recovered from the
students, and schools
themselves usually require financial
support,
especially during the startup phase.
But even during routine implementation
when financial
resources are needed, for operation and
maintenance.
The SODIS reference center at Sandec has
developed the Safe Water School Project,
along with antenna technologies, Helvetas
Swiss
Intercorporation, and supported by the
Swiss government.
The project launched in 2011, and reached,
143 schools in Bolivia, Kenya, and Haiti.
In Bolivia, the project is headed by the
Fundación SODIS and covers all 40 primary
schools in Tiquipaya, a city of 50,000
near Cochabamba.
The project has recently expanded into six
secondary schools
and surrounding communities as well as a
second municipality.
But intervention takes an integrated
approach covering water, sanitation, and
hygiene,
including different types of HWTS,
mainly SODIS and chlorination.
Each school develops a safe water station
for every
classroom, like the one shown here. And
demonstrates both SODIS,
we can see some of the plastic bottles
down here, and chlorination using
electrolytically generated chlorine with
the mini-WATA
generator developed by Antenna to produce
a chlorine solution from salt and water.
The project also trains people to make
their own soap,
which is apparently fun, as well as good
for handwashing.
The safe water school project is planned
and implemented with local
authorities, in this case the
municipality,
and the district education ministry of
Tiquipaya.
The project is monitored at the school
level by
safe water committees with two to three
teachers
and ten students per school, and at the
municipal
level the Fundación SODIS the support NGO
monitors the project.
And after the project is complete, this
is taken over by the District Education
Authorities.
A key part of the intervention is water
quality testing.
This serves to help monitor use of HWTS at
the
schools, as well as to create demand for
safe water.
The schools mostly use piped water, but
the supply is intermittent
and there is almost always some detectable
E. coli in the water.
Here, you see a student from one of
those safe water committees testing for
residual chlorine.
With a safe storage container there and
below these are
some of the E. coli testing plates that are
used.
Students and teachers alike enjoy the
water quality testing, and it has
proven very effective at convincing people
that the treatment is important and works.
The Safe Water project provides initial
training and
support for monitoring. But once the
program is
well established the municipality will
take over with
the NGO Fundación SODIS available for technical
support on request.
It's hard to measure the impact of such
interventions.
Conceptually at kind of the top level,
having safer water
could lead to improved enrollment,
attendance and completion of school,
and perhaps better academic performance.
One might also expect less diarrheal
disease though
there are many exposures outside the
school environment.
It's perhaps more realistic to look for
improved water and sanitation
conditions in the schools and possibly in
the homes of students.
And at a minimum to have increased
awareness about drinking water quality and
WASH.
One of the most rigorous evaluations of
WASH in schools
to date was done by Matt Freeman at Emory
University.
He and his co-authors did a randomized
trial in 185 primary schools in Western
Kenya.
This picture is from a different WASH in
Schools project, also in Kenya.
All of the schools except for controls,
were
provided with hygiene promotion and an
HWTS system,
consisting of safe water storage
containers and a
year's supply of Water Guard liquid
chlorine solution.
Half of the schools were also provided
with additional latrines.
And if schools did not have a year-round
water
source within one kilometer, and no
improved water source
within two kilometers, they were
considered water-scarce, and the
project provided them with a new water
supply facility,
either a bore hole, or a rain water
harvesting tank.
At a follow-up visit six months after the
intervention, all
of the schools, including the control
schools, had better access to
improved sources of drinking water, and
about two thirds of
water samples included residual chlorine,
indicating that water treatment was
ongoing.
Students reported much greater
availability
of drinking water, hand washing water,
and soap, which was also confirmed by the
evaluation teams.
There was also a significant reduction in
diarrheal disease by more than 50%.
But this was found only in the water-scarce
schools, which received a new water
source.
So at least in this one case,
we have evidence of improved knowledge and
behavior,
at least after six months, which may not
alone be sufficient to reduce diarrheal
disease burden.
It's a natural idea to link HWTS with
health interventions.
HWTS is, after all, a health intervention
itself, to reduce diarrheal disease.
And some of the people most vulnerable to
diarrheal disease
might already be in contact with the
health care system.
So reaching them could be easier and
more cost effective through an integrated
approach.
HWTS promotion maybe more credible when it
comes from a
health worker, rather than a water
engineer or an NGO.
And finally there can be mutual
reinforcements,
so that not only is HWTS is more effective
when paired
with another health intervention, but that
other intervention can also benefit.
Otherwise there would be little reason for
them
to take on the additional messages of
HWTS.
We'll look at two kinds of integration
with health care systems.
First, around child and maternal health
taking the specific example of antenatal
care.
And second with a context of HIV/AIDS
management.
There are other potential linkages, for
instance
diarrheal disease compounds and is
compounded by malnutrition.
So there's interests in integrated
interventions there.
And there are even potential links with
water related diseases like Dengue fever.
Since the mosquitoes that carry the Dengue
virus
like to lay their eggs in water containers
a key intervention for vector control is
promotion
of household water storage containers with
tightly sealed covers.
But, in the interest of time, today we'll
just look at antenatal care and HIV AIDS.
First, antenatal care, or ANC.
This example is from Malawi.
Where Population Services International
had been marketing WaterGuard since 2002.
But several years on, awareness was high,
but uptake was still low.
In 2007, the Ministry of Health launched a
project to promote HWTS alongside
antenatal care visits, 15,000 pregnant
women attending their first
antenatal care visits were given hygiene
promotion and free hygiene kits
which included a plastic bucket with a tap
and samples of WaterGuard.
The women were then visited in their homes
afterwards by health workers and if they
return to
the health clinic for their second, third,
or
fourth ANC visits, they were given free
water-guard refills.
They also got refills if they delivered
their babies
in a healthcare facility, or made post
natal care visits.
Now the maternal and child healthcare
sector in Malawi
was very concerned since most women attend
one antenatal visit.
But only about 20% complete the
recommended round of four ANC visits.
And less than three-quarters of them deliver in
a healthcare facility.
And less than half make a timely
post-natal visit.
The U.S. Centers for Disease Control
evaluated the intervention
with follow-ups one year and
three years after the intervention, which
included surprise visits,
testing for residual chlorine, and visual
confirmation of WaterGuard bottles.
After one year, there was a tremendous
increase in confirmed use
of WaterGuard, from 1% to 62% among the
women in the program.
Use of the safe storage containers was
almost 100%.
And the evaluation also looked at the
practices
of close friends and relatives with young
children.
And so a large increase there as well, up
to 27% confirmed use.
It seems like pregnancy and childbirth
represent teachable moments.
When mothers are very concerned about the
health of their new child.
There are a lot of changes and they're
changing many behaviors.
If you are a parent, you know very well
that once you have children, especially
your first one, you change a lot of
your routine behaviors, and that is an
understatement.
Anyway those same households were
revisited two
years later and while there was a
substantial decline in confirmed use among
both
direct participants and the close friends
and neighbors.
These numbers still represent a
fairly high sustained use.
Qualitative research confirmed that the
health care
workers that were involved in promotion
were considered
to be highly credible by the women and
that this influenced them to continue
using HWTS.
What is very interesting about this study
is that the women who were enrolled
were much more likely to return to the
health clinics for repeat ANC visits.
More than half of the women completed the
full four ANC visit cycle.
90% of them delivered their babies in a
health clinic.
And, 90% also made a post-natal checkup,
within six weeks.
And these numbers are much higher
than average for that region.
So this HWTS intervention turned out to
be extraordinarily effective, for the
maternal and
child health people, not only for those
more concerned about water and diarrheal
disease.
And where both parties benefit,
integration is much more likely to
succeed and this pilot has since been
scaled up in Malawi.
If one strategy in optimizing health gains
from HWTS is to target the
vulnerable, it makes a lot of sense to
work on interventions on HIV/AIDS.
People living with HIV have weakened
immune systems
and are particularly vulnerable
to infections, including water-borne
diseases.
They may become sick, with lower pathogen
loads, and an infection
that could be minor in a healthy person
can be life-threatening.
Cryptosporidium is a particular risk.
And a recent review of people living with
HIV/AIDS, in low resource
settings, found Crypto to be the
most common waterborne pathogen causing
diarrhea,
and was a significant cause of mortality.
So HWTS has been recognized to be an
important
element of preventative care for people
living with HIV AIDS.
And while there are not many studies out
there yet.
There is increasing evidence that HWTS
uptake
is higher in interventions with people
with
HIV AIDS than in conventional
interventions, and
that there is significant reduction in
diarrheal disease.
There are even a few studies showing that
HWTS may slow the progression of AIDS.
One study, for example, found that people
with
HIV who received an insecticide treated
bed net
a light straw water filter,
experienced less severe drops in their
CD4 counts, which is an indication of the
severity of the disease.
Participants were 27% less likely, to have
their CD4
counts drop to a critical level, within
the study period.
Here is an example of an integrated
intervention.
And I'd like to thank Rachel Peletz for
this example and the use of her photos.
Rachel conducted a randomized control
trial in Peri-urban Zambia
which enrolled 120 households with
children under the age two.
Including a hundred HIV positive mothers
and 20 HIV negative mothers.
Half of the households were provided with
a water filter and a safe storage
container.
And the other half were used as controls.
Though after one year, the control
households also received the intervention.
Here you see the water filter, and by now
can
you all tell me what kind of filter this
is?
Post it on the discussion forum.
Participants, who are trained by the
project fieldworkers, who
made monthly follow-up visits for a year
after which the
control households received their filters
and then a final follow
up visit was made two years after the
initial distribution.
Follow up visits were unannounced and
involved water quality testing as
well as, recording of diarrhea and
reported use of the filter.
In addition, an objective nutritional
measure was
used called the weight for age Z-score.
Throughout the evaluation period, filter
use was extremely high.
People reported using the filter in 96% of
visits.
This was confirmed by the field workers in
around 85% of visits.
And on the very last visit, after two
years of use.
92% of households were confirmed users.
Of the people who reported using the
filters, 95% reported not using any other
source
of drinking water in the last two days,
either for the mother or for the child.
These are very high numbers compared to
other studies.
That could have been even higher, except
that two of
the filters were eaten by rats, the
plastic tubing part.
So, the evaluation found that the filters
showed more than two log removal
and here it's likely that there were
detection limit problems
preventing measurement of
higher LRVs.
You see if the raw water contains 100 CFU
per 100 mLs
and you measure less than one CFU per 100
mLs, all
you can say is that there was at least two
log
removal you don't know if it's three or
five or nine log.
And if you compare the geometric means of
water in intervention and
control households you can see something
like two orders of magnitude difference.
The evaluation also found more than a 50%
reduction in diarrheal disease.
Which again is high compared to other
studies.
And also found that people consuming more
contaminated water,
more highly contaminated water, experienced
a higher risk of diarrhea.
However, they didn't find any significant
difference in the weight for age z-score.
This module has drawn heavily on a few
scientific studies.
And you can find the full articles here.
Many of them are freely available online.
And the pdf version of this lecture has
the hyperlinks for you.
And these are more general resources which
were very useful in putting together this
module.
Again, the pdfs include the hyperlinks for
all of these reports.
So to summarize, there's a lot of
interest in integrating HWTS promotion
with other interventions.
There may well be a better chance at
realizing health gains because it is
easier reaching people
at higher risks of infection, and because
those
people might trust the people delivering
the message more,
if they're respected figures like teachers
or health care workers.
It's also more cost efficient to reach
these
people by bundling interventions into an
integrated package.
There's suggested evidence, and a lot of
enthusiasm so far,
for integration into school programs, but
there's stronger evidence that
shows that when HWTS is integrated into
other health initiatives
both the objectives can have a better
chance of success.
In the next module we'll look at another
kind
of targeted application of HWTS, which is
emergency response.
This module will be given by a guest
lecturer, Dr. Danielle Lantagne of Tufts
University in the USA.
Don't miss it.