Hello and welcome to week four, module
three
of the Household Water Treatment and Safe
Storage MOOC.
I'll be speaking today about household
water treatment in the emergency context.
My name is Daniele Lantagne and I'm a
professor at Tufts University in the
United States.
First, I'll describe the three types of
emergencies we'll discuss.
The first type of emergency is natural
disasters.
These are earthquakes, eruptions,
landslides, tsunamis, floods or droughts.
They're unplanned for.
The general health effects after
emergencies come after flooding, or
when populations are displaced and move
away from their homes.
These types of emergencies are increasing
as
population increases, as more people live
in
unplanned settlements, and as climate
change exacerbates
the type and severity of the natural
disasters.
The next type of emergency we'll discuss
is outbreaks.
Outbreaks of particular diseases, and in
our case, where we're
concerned about diarrheal diseases, we
particularly are concerned with cholera.
Cholera is on the rise, especially in Sub
Saharan Africa.
The last type of emergency is donor or
United Nations defined
and these are political emergencies, they
are complex emergencies or fragile states.
They're unlinked to particular health
needs, but they are context
in which the State cannot provide services
to its population.
After an emergency, we generally hear very
bold statements
about the health impact that we'll see at
that emergency.
An example statement is this, which was
after the tsunami in Christmas of
2005.
Which states, unless the necessary funds
are
urgently mobilized and coordinated in the
field, we
could see as many fatalities from
diseases, as
we have seen from the actual disaster,
itself.
Another quote,
and this is from a paper that addresses
some
of the myths of responding in disasters,
another
common myth about disasters, is the
affected local population
is helplessly waiting for the western
world to save it.
In reality, there are health needs in
emergencies and after disasters and
outbreaks and
in complex situations, and those health
needs
are linked to where the people are
located.
So, for example, we know that refugees,
and these are displaced populations that
move across an international border,
they're protected by international law.
And they often move into camp situations.
And there is quite an extensive literature
that establishes mechanisms to reduce the
mortality rate within refugee camps.
And the five intervention recommended to
reduce the mortality
rate are the provision of food, the
provision of
water, the provision of measles
vaccination, adequate access to
clinical care and providing health
information to improve people's health.
The second population of concern, that we
work with in emergencies, is internally
displaced persons.
These are people that have moved away from
their home, but not crossed an
international border.
These persons are not formally protected
by international law.
And their mortality tends to come from
increased rate of background diseases.
These people may move in to family
members,
they may be dispersed within the local
population,
they may move into camps. But the
mortality we see in IDP situations
is increased background diseases, whatever
those initial diseases were.
The last type of population in emergencies
is entrapped populations, populations that
are trapped and
do not have access to services by the
emergency around them, such as a war.
Very little is known about the health
needs of this particular population.
So, when we talk about bringing household
water treatment and safe storage to these
types of populations, effected by
emergencies, we
generally talk about providing one of five
options.
These options have been discussed in
previous sessions of this MOOC.
The first option is providing a filter,
such as a ceramic
filter, where water flows through the
porous media and is treated.
Chlorination is often provided in
emergencies.
It's sometimes recommended that
emergency-affected populations use SODIS
and put bottles of water in the sun.
Sand filters have also been provided in
emergencies.
And lastly, PuR, which is the Procter and
Gamble product. It's
a flocculant disinfectant product has
been
widely distributed in the emergency
context.
The two options most distributed in
emergencies are PuR, which is
often distributed when there's turbid
water and various types of chlorine.
Chlorine tablets, liquid chlorine, bucket
chlorination, there's a number of
ways to put chlorine in the water, in the
emergency context.
So, when we started working in household
water treatment in emergencies, the first
thing that
we did was we reviewed the existing
information
on household water treatment in the
emergency context.
And what we found is actually there's not
that much information out there.
There's a total of 30 papers and
that includes both peer-reviewed and gray
literature documents.
We also conducted a survey of implementers
in our review.
And the results of our review and survey
really highlighted that there's a large
data gap
in knowing how and what products and if
to implement household water treatment in
the emergency context.
What we did learn from our literature
review is
that household water treatment can be
effective in some emergencies.
That current products are targeted to high
risk emergencies, emergencies with risk of
diarrheal
disease, such as cholera outbreaks, or
emergencies
where the population is displaced or
flooded.
It generally, it's the product that
dominates the option selection.
So, for example, a responding
organization,
will have a product in its warehouse and
they'll just simply distribute that
household water
treatment product in the context of the
emergency.
So, the users don't really have much say
in what options they receive.
We learn that training is crucial to
uptake.
And the more trainings that are provided,
the more likely people are
to use the product correctly, and
that logistics are important.
That products needed to be stocked before
the emergency.
The products needed to be registered in
the country,
so that they were able to be legally
distributed
before the emergency, and that products
needed to be
distributed with all the materials
necessary to use them.
For example, in the particular case of
PuR, the PuR needs to be distributed with
two buckets, a stirring rod, and a cloth,
and a pair of scissors to open the sachet.
Because it cannot be assumed that
emergency
affected populations have access to all
those materials.
And lastly, in our review, we saw that
the, the dosage of
chlorine is very varied across the
context, and that establishing correct
chlorine dosage
is necessary to balance the issues of
taste and odor if there's too high a
dose with not having effective treatment
if there's too low a dose.
We definitely learned, in our review of
the literature and survey
of implementers, that more research is
necessary in the emergency context.
However, based on what we did learn, we
were
able to develop a document in collaboration
with the
International Federation of Red Cross and
Red Crescent Societies
entitled Household water treatment and
safe storage in emergencies.
This is a document, a booklet, that is
downloadable from the web.
The address for the English version of the
document is included here on the
PowerPoint presentation.
And this document is in plain language,
it's meant for the
emergency responder who may not have much
experience with wash,
with water sanitation hygiene products, to
learn how to respond with household
water treatment and safe storage products
in an emergency context.
After we completed our literature review
and survey of implementers
we also worked with UNICEF and Oxfam to
complete additional research.
And the research questions that we asked
in this research were, what role, if
any, should household water treatment and
safe
storage play in the emergency response
process?
And what are the factors associated
with feasible and potentially, sustained
implementation
of point of use water treatment,
household water treatment, in response to
emergencies?
We conducted evaluations of four
emergencies that
happened within the time frame of our
project.
When we setup our project, we did not know
what emergencies would occur.
We had an open protocol to go to these
four emergencies and evaluate all
the different household water treatment
products that
were distributed by any NGO in the
emergency.
In these evaluations, we conducted
household surveys, water quality testing.
We conducted focus group discussions, key
informant interviews.
We collected GPS points and we also looked
at cost analysis.
The four emergencies that occurred during
the time of our time to
complete this evaluation, were first in
Jajarkot Nepal, there's an image
here of the hilly region of Nepal where
this cholera outbreak occurred.
We completed this evaluation in August of
2009.
The second emergency that we evaluated was
an earthquake in Pariaman, Indonesia.
Then we completed our evaluation in
October of 2009.
The third emergency that we evaluated was
a context where
there was both flooding, as can be seen
here in an
area of Kenya in the northwest section of
Kenya on the
Sudan border, Turkana, where there was
also an on-going cholera outbreak.
We completed our evaluation of this
response in January of 2010.
To give you context, this is a home of a
family that lives in Turkana, Kenya.
And the last evaluation we completed, was
actually in response to the Haiti
earthquake.
And we completed an evaluation of all
household water treatment and storage safe
storage
products that were distributed in response
to
the Haiti earthquake from February to
March 2010.
And so, we were really looking at what
happened
in the acute emergency situations the first
eight weeks after onset.
Were household water treatment and safe
storage products able to
effectively reduce the risk to households
of contracting diarrheal disease?
Now, in these four emergencies, three of
four actually have high diarrheal disease
risk.
And those are the places with cholera,
in Jajarkot and Turkana, with flooding in
Turkana.
And in Haiti, because the earthquake led
to very high internal displacement of a
population.
The one emergency we evaluated that would
not have high diarrheal disease risk
is in Indonesia, because the earthquake
did not lead to displacement or flooding.
So, we would not expect a high
diarrheal disease burden post emergency in
that context.
This is our summary data table which I'll
walk you through.
And it tells the information about
everything we learned
in response, in our evaluations in these
four contexts.
So, in the first column, we have the
country in which we responded.
And in the second column, we have the
household water treatment and safe storage
products that were distributed by any NGO
that we were able to find and evaluate.
So, I want to highlight that none of these
products that we
select or pre-select, we just evaluated
what other people had already,
independently, distributed.
So in Nepal, a local NGO was living in the
community and they
rented houses in the community and they
received
chlorination products, tablets and two
types of liquid.
They received these chlorination products
from UNICEF and they distributed them
on a continuous basis, so for example, if
you ran out
of Aquatabs, you can go back and two weeks
later then,
you might get WaterGuard because that's
what UNICEF had sent that week.
They distributed this on a continuous
basis,
with training and ongoing training for the
users.
And this was in the context of cholera.
Now, in Indonesia, the distribution
was different.
These products, which were AirRahmat, a
liquid chlorine product and
a tablet chlorine product were both
distributed in NFI kits.
These are non food item kits.
They're a box that may have a stove, and a
blanket, and
a tent, and some pots and pans, and some
crayons for your kids.
And these NFI kits come with no training.
They're just distributed as a box.
Now, boiling was not promoted in Indonesia
by any NGO,
but was widely used by the population
because of previous training.
And so, we included it in our evaluation.
In Turkana, it was the same type of
situation.
Aquatabs and PuR were included in an NFI
kit distribution.
And people received a 30 minute training
the day the NFI kits were distributed, on
how to use the products and that was all
the training or follow-up they received.
In Haiti, there were quite different,
modes of distribution.
Aquatabs were distributed in NFI kits
within spontaneous
settlements, places where, where
internally displaced people settled.
But they were also distributed in a
separate
program that had existed in Haiti before
the emergency,
through community health workers in a
distributed network
of 200 community health workers in a rural
area.
And those community health workers visited
people's homes,
and provided ongoing education and access
to the Aquatabs.
In both cases for the filters, and this is
the first
time we see filters, we saw ceramic
filters distributed in Haiti.
Those were flown in from the Dominican
Republic, and
they were distributed with one training to
the household.
And then Biosand filters were distributed
over a
wide area through a network of priests,
and
a few households in each
of the priests' network areas
received Biosand filters.
What I'd like to point out here, of the
products that were
distributed in these emergencies, they're
primarily
chlorination products, and that has to
do with the fact that chlorination
products were warehoused in the country
beforehand, and are quite small and easy
to distribute in the emergency context.
Additionally, the only products of any
distributed in the emergencies, we
saw, and this is within the first eight
weeks of onset,
that were not available in country
warehouse before the emergency, were
ceramic filters in Haiti and some of the
Aquatabs in Haiti.
Every other product was stored in a
warehouse prior to the emergency
when it was used, then, to respond to an
acute emergency situation.
So now, I'd like to walk you through the
next three columns, to show you our data.
So, in Nepal, essentially, what we see is
30% of people reported
using the chlorination products in their
stored household drinking water.
And that's because we can't divide this up
by product really
because you might have received Aquatabs
two weeks ago and WaterGuard yesterday.
So, we're going to lump the stage together
and show that
about 30% of the households reported they
were using the chlorine.
Now, about 65% of those households
actually had free chlorine residual in
their drinking water, when we did
an unannounced household survey.
Which means, really, in total, about 65%
of 30%, which is about
eighteenish percent of the population,
roughly a fifth, had free chlorine
residual in their drinking water, from the
products that were distributed.
We weren't able to test microbiological
indicators in this context
because we didn't have access to any
electricity at all.
And so, we simply left free chlorine
residual as the outcome of interest.
And that's the confirmed use, as the
presence of free chlorine residual,
and effective use is improvement of water
quality as measured by E. coli.
So, to sum up the Nepal data, about one
fifth of the
population had free chlorine residual in
their drinking water from the
intervention.
Now, in Indonesia, we have a very
different story from chlorination.
There was only 3% and 1% reported use
of the products that were distributed that
has to do
with lack of training, as well as a lack
of desire to use chlorine in that context.
Additionally, the tablets were only
provided with English written directions,
so
there were no appropriate directions on
how to use the product.
Because use was so low of these
distributed products
there was no ability to measure confirmed
or effective use.
However, 88% of the population reported
boiling.
Boiling was something they had done before
the emergency and they continued to do
afterward.
We tested untreated water from households,
from untreated storage household water.
And we also tested reported boiled stored
household water.
And we found that 27%, about a quarter
of the population, had safe drinking water
from boiling.
Their treated water was safe and their
untreated water was dirty.
Which meant they'd used boiling to move
from
dirty water to clean water and safe to
drink.
So, about a quarter of the population
effectively used boiling to treat their
drinking water.
In Turkana, which was a NFI kit
distribution, we also saw fairly low use.
And 13% of households reported using
Aquatabs, 6%
reported using PuR, because of the small
amount of
training and the complexity of using PuR,
less than
1% of respondents knew how to use PuR
correctly.
We confirmed these with free chlorine
residual in less than half of the
households that reported use actually had
free chlorine residual in the drinking
water.
And when we take it out to improving the
quality of their stored household water
from dirty to clean, only 5%
of the surveyed households used
Aquatabs
to improve the quality of their water and
2% used PuR, which means 7% of
the households, targeted households, used
one of the
products to improve the quality of their
water.
In Haiti, we have a more complex story.
The tablets, the Aquatabs that were
distributed in the NFI context
in the spontaneous settlements 24%
reported use of that 62%,
about little over half had free chlorine
residual, but only
15% improved the quality of their water
from dirty to clean.
And so, we see a similar number, it's a
low use
when there is NFI distribution and no
training and follow up.
Now, we see much different numbers when we
move to the community health worker
program, where we see 75% in urban
areas and 92% of people in rural areas
reported using the
the household water, the Aquatabs that
were distributed.
And of those families, 75% had free
chlorine residual in their
drinking water and 54% improved the
quality of their water with those
Aquatabs in urban areas and 66%, 2/3rd's
of households use
those Aquatabs to improve the quality of
their water in rural areas.
And the reason for this increased
effective use, in rural areas,
is that the water, the untreated water in
rural areas, was dirtier.
So, more households had dirty water in the
rural areas
unless we're able to use the Aquatabs to
make it clean.
Now the ceramic and Biosand filter storage
are slightly different.
People really liked those filters and they
reported,
even with very little training or one
training,
72% of households
reported using
the ceramic filter, 53% reported using the
biosand filter.
However, the ceramic filters were
distributed
in an area next to an airstrip.
They were flown in, and
then they were distributed right around
that airstrip.
And those households actually already had
clean water.
So, the households were not able to take
dirty, untreated water and
make it clean, so the effective use was
quite low at 20%.
And the Biosand filters were installed by
local technicians who made
errors in installation, so that the
Biosand filters were not installed
correctly.
And so, they were not able to treat the
water effectively.
And so, the effective use was also quite
low at 8%.
So, as you can see here, the use is much
lower
than one might expect, and the effective
use was much lower.
The programs with the highest effective
use, Aquatabs with
community health workers in Haiti, and
boiling in Indonesia.
Both of those had existed before the
emergency, and people
were familiar and comfortable using those
products before the emergency.
And thus, were able to translate that
knowledge into using the products after
the emergency.
And then we have some issues with
knowledge
and training and also correct installation
and use.
So, to summarize up all this data in
a graphic.
We found that effective use happened when
people used an option that treated the
water.
And was effective at treating the
When people actually had unsafe water,
that's an assumption in
emergencies, that everyone has dirty water
and that's not always true.
And when there was user demand,
familiarity and use.
People who knew the program before the
emergency were more likely to use it
after.
And when those three things came together,
we saw effective
use in household water treatment products
in the emergency context.
In summarizing up this presentation, I'd
like
to offer a few thought questions about
conducting
research in emergencies, such as, thinking
about,
what research is ethical to conduct in
emergencies?
What products or projects would you donate
to in an emergency?
What is success in the emergency context?
Should it be distribution?
Should it be reported use?
Should it be effective use?
And how do we find out what the
differences are between those metrics?
How should money be tracked in an
emergency?
How should we spend our money?
How do you balance the ethic of
humanitarianism, which is reaching out to
those most
affected, with the desire to scale project
up,
and meet the, and reach the most people?
How do we better apply lessons learned in
the development
context into our emergency response
projects with household water treatment?
And how do we link emergencies with
development projects, so that we really
offer a holistic household water treatment
strategy to the population of the country?
I'd like to thank you for listening to
this presentation
and end with a quote from a journal
article by Slim.
And say: "The notion that being
humanitarian and doing good are
somehow inevitably the same is a hard one
to shake off.
And I think that research can assist us
in aligning being humanitarian with always
doing good."
I'm happy to take questions, thank you for
listening today.