In our discussion of implementation
models,
we talked about the differences between
profit maximizing approaches and those
that
prioritize social goods, like disease
reduction.
We looked at how different strategies
might be applied
by conventional, profit oriented
businesses,
or not for profit organizations,
or social businesses, kind of combining
some aspects of
both. But success of HWTS is not only
about
the private sector and NGOs, governments
have very important
roles to play, but which governments and
what roles?
Well, one important role of governments is
around national policies and regulations.
And in fact, the international network for
HWTS,
has set targets around national policies
and regulations.
First is that, by 2015, at least 30
countries should have established national
policies or regulations about HWTS.
And this one is on track.
There was a survey done a few years ago,
in 2012, which
found eight countries already with targets
and more than 22 with policies.
And the second target is to reach 50
countries by
2020, which have achieved countrywide
scale up of project based HWTS.
And this second target, at least in 2012,
wasn't yet on track.
The international network for HWTS, which
was
introduced by Michael Forson a few weeks
ago,
made a global review of the policy and
regulatory environment around HWTS a few
years ago.
And they received responses from 46
countries, nearly half from Africa,
but with at least some responses from all
around the world.
In over half of these countries, the
ministry of health
was identified as the lead in issues
relating to HWTS.
And in several other countries, the
ministries
of water or environments were the leads.
But there were a number of other
government agencies
listed including the ministry of rural
development in Cambodia.
The Ministry of Social Affairs in Estonia
and
the Ministry of Housing and Construction
in Syria.
Regardless of which ministry is the lead,
HWTS is
a cross cutting issue and requires
coordination between different ministries.
Like the ones above.
But also, frequently, information on HWTS
is integrated into school curricula.
So, ministries of education must be
involved.
And if technologies are to be certified,
or endorsed,
National Bureaus of standards or other
regulatory authorities may be involved.
In fact, this survey found that more than
90%
of countries reported having a
collaboration between two ministries.
And in more than half of countries, three
or more ministries were involved.
Now, all that sounds great.
In practice, it can mean that progress is
slow, since everybody has to get on board.
So, nearly 2/3rds of the countries in that
survey
had established an inter-ministerial
committee to coordinate HWTS activities.
And that's mostly at the national level.
Many of these ministries have presences at
the regional district
and local levels or municipalities in the
case of large cities.
Or there may be big gaps in knowledge and
capacity about HWTS.
But these government workers are the ones
who would need
to be involved with any field level
implementation of HWTS.
So, there are certainly multiple different
government
entities that could play roles in HWTS.
How can we classify or organize all the
different
roles that governments could play with
respect to HWTS?
Well, there are, of course, many different
ways, but one that I
like is to approach the role of government
from a human rights perspective.
There's been a lot written about the
responsibilities
of governments regarding human rights and
the UN
has recently recognized access to safe
drinking water
as a human right, so it seems appropriate.
And in the human rights framework, the
responsibilities
of government, states, can be divided into
three sets.
The obligations to respect, to protect,
and to fulfill rights.
Respecting rights means that governments
should not interfere,
either directly or indirectly, with a
human right.
And protecting rights means that
governments should
prevent other parties from interfering
with human rights.
For instance, the government could pass
laws or
regulations that prevent pollution of
drinking water resources.
In this last category, the duty to fulfill
human rights, that can be further broken
down.
States can facilitate a right by taking
positive measures that
help people to enjoy the right to safe
drinking water.
States can promote a right by, for
example, making sure that there's
adequate education around the importance
of safe water, and sanitation and hygiene.
And states are obliged to provide a right
when people are unable, for reasons beyond
their control, to realize that right on
their
own, and with the means at their disposal.
Let's take some concrete examples.
One important role that government can
play is about access to information.
Making sure that complete and correct
information
is available to those who need it.
Governments can make themselves aware, at
different levels and
in different sectors, about the links
between HWTS and health.
They can take stock of the existing
drinking water situation, especially
considering household water quality.
And see if people could benefit from using
HWTS.
National health and water coverage
statistics are available
in nearly all countries, managed by the
government.
But might not be widely known to all.
So a first step that governments could
support could be to do a situation
assessment,
a review of the situation, and compile
the relevant information in one
place.
Another important role, that is another
kind
of facilitation, is the role of
coordination.
There are many different stakeholders
involved in HWTS, and governments can make
a really important contribution by
ensuring
that these stakeholders know about each
other.
This can be achieved through a survey of
ongoing HWTS activities and stakeholders.
And local universities or research
institutions could
be brought in to fill knowledge gaps,
and the government can host sector forums,
to share experiences in a very productive
way.
Another part of coordination is the
need for monitoring and evaluation.
This is a key responsibility of government
which might require establishing new
indicators and monitoring
systems, building up capacity, especially
at local levels,
and perhaps investments in new facilities
and equipment.
If we next consider promotion, HWTS will
definitely be
more credible if its promotion is endorsed
or led by governments.
A common action here is to support
development
and funding of a national communication
strategy and campaign.
Usually these are non-branded since
governments often don't want to
be seen as giving preference to one
commercial entity over another.
Governments, typically, are willing to
endorse or
promote only technologies that have been
verified.
And there's currently a real lack of
systems and capacity
for doing piloting and assessing of
technologies before scale up.
And ideally, there should be a range of
options available that
could be promoted for different audiences
and use some different circumstances.
WHO has recently launched a scheme for
evaluation
of household water treatment technologies
described in this report.
And we'll have a guest lecturer from
the
WHO go over the scheme in more detail next
week.
Finally, promotion of HWTS can be
linked with other health or development
priorities
as we saw the example of integration of
HWTS with education or health initiatives.
And these kinds of integrations often
require a supporting policy environment.
Finally, governments do have a
responsibility to provide services if
other
actors do not provide them in a way that's
accessible to all.
This doesn't mean that services have to be
provided for free,
but they do have to be available at an
affordable price.
So, there is a possible role for subsidy
of HWTS which could take different forms.
There could be direct subsidies in the
form of reduced
prices for products which might be
targeted only towards the poor.
Or there could be indirect subsidies.
For example, by supporting the costs of
promotion
through media or distribution through
human resources and institutions.
And a third kind of subsidy, an indirect
subsidy, could be to
relax the import duties on HWTS products
that have to be imported.
If government workers, from whatever
sector,
become involved with provision of HWTS
products
and services, they will typically need
substantial
support and capacity development at
different levels.
This is another aspect of government's
role
in creating an environment where HWTS can
succeed.
Well, there are a lot of different types,
obviously, of roles
that governments can play and of actions
that could be taken.
And a convenient way to package them
together in
a coherent framework is that of national
action planning.
And the HWTS Network has some guidance and
some
templates on elements that should go into
national action planning.
First of all, there should normally be
a background and rationale to have an HWTS
action plan that involves things like the
literature
review and assessment and diagnosis of the
situation.
Next, establishing an overall purpose,
which might be to reduce disease, since
there is a health focus.
And guiding principles, such as targeting
vulnerable groups to achieve the greatest
gains.
Another important principle to establish
is that HWTS is
not in competition with or replacing
conventional water supply.
But is seen as a complementary, short-term
measure until the long-term
goals of safe, sustainable water at home
can be achieved for all.
Certainly a concrete, element in a
national action plan should be a goal.
Which should be time based by some
certain year, and might have some specific
proportion
of the population, who don't yet have
sustainable
access to piped water supply in the house.
Who are practicing an effective HWTS
method,
in a way that makes the water safe
to drink or in compliance with national
standards.
Once that goal is established then, a
number of strategies and
action items can be determined, which will
be very context specific.
And another activity that's very context
specific is a
clear delineation of the responsibilities
of the different stakeholders involved.
Both the government stakeholders and the
non-government ones, including, private
sector, NGOs, universities, research
institutes, development partners, etc.
By now there are many countries, more than 22,
that have established action
plans and policies for HWTS, but one nice
example I like to share is that of
Tanzania.
And in preparation for establishing an
HWTS strategy and plan.
The first thing that was done was a sector
review.
A situation assessment.
Where there's very high mortality from
diarrhea.
This shows Tanzania ranking quite high in
the distribution
of countries, in terms of diarrheal deaths
per 100,000 population.
Also, there was a high use of unsafe
water.
These are national coverage estimates from
the
joint monitoring program of WHO and
UNICEF.
Showing really high and persistent use of
surface water
and other kinds of unimproved water in
rural areas.
And HWTS was being promoted in the
country.
It was aligned with government policies
but there was no
coordination mechanism, so there was
actually a lot of inefficiency.
So, the government hosted and convened an
international conference in February 2009,
led by
the relevant Ministries and supported by
the
International Network and some key
development partners there.
And they prepared a nice background
document to go into the meeting.
Laying out the reasons, the
justification to develop an HWTS sector
plan.
So, having done their homework, the
government of
Tanzania then hosted this workshop in
February 2009.
Brought in 108 people from many different
countries.
And set out four key objectives.
First, to learn from international
experiences, both
within the region and the broader global
community.
To review and strengthen national
initiatives on expanding HWTS.
To develop and strengthen partnerships,
both nationally and internationally.
And finally, to share experiences and
document the
different programs taking place within and
outside the country.
So a lot of the objectives here are around
information management and facilitation.
The conference had a number of actionable
outcomes, there were 15
specific action points that were
identified, I won't go into them here.
But there were five broad recommendations
that,
that were also endorsed through the
conference.
The first being that the ministry, the
lead ministry in this case
of health and social welfare, should
develop a national action plan, and
strategy.
That the ministry should strengthen those
international partnerships.
And also that the government, along with
partners and other
stakeholders, should allocate funds,
financial
resources, towards the strategic plan.
That the government should play
this information management and
coordination role
through strengthening the evidence base,
through
monitoring and evaluation, through
developing standards.
And then finally, that the government
should play the
overarching role of coordination and
networking in the HWTS sector.
These findings were shared in other
regional workshops.
And other countries in the region have
gone through similar processes.
So, that international conference really
set the ball rolling in Tanzania.
And within a relatively short period of
time, of just a few years, the country had
developed, finalized, and endorsed a
strategy and plan
for scaling up HWTS over this five year
period.
It included a national vision, and goal,
and target.
So, the vision being, to have communities
accessing safe drinking water at the
household level.
And a specific target to increase by 20%,
the usage of acceptable HWTS by 2016.
So that's a concrete, measurable, thing.
HWTS has been taken up in a number of
national policies,
including the National Heath Policy, the
Health Sector Strategic
Plan, but also the Environmental health,
hygiene and sanitation strategies.
And there are lists of specific actions
that
the government must take to achieve these
goals.
And I give here just a few examples of
the types of activities that government is
doing here.
Around facilitation, around coordination,
around monitoring and evaluation.
So, while it takes some time and some good
ground work to establish the
foundations, and develop a national
strategy and
action plan, that's really just the
beginning.
The implementation of the plan is where
HWTS
can really be scaled up and realize health
gains.
And here government play such critical
roles.
First, in securing the political supports
and the resources necessary for
implementation.
Government has to play this role of
coordination and
leading, and can also, provide adequate
financing and human resources.
On the implementation of the specific
measures identified in an
action plan, government has many
key roles, especially around building
awareness
in capacity at the lower levels.
And finally, all of these activities that
are implemented through an action plan
and strategy have to be continuously
modified, monitored, modified if necessary
and evaluated.
And here, governments, again, play
the central role and
one can think back to that human rights
framework and consider
that these actions should all be
implemented in a way that
is not discriminatory to any
particular group, including the poor.
And that though participation and
transparency more
long-lasting, sustainable results can
be achieved.
Going back to that survey that the
International Network
conducted of 46 countries about HWTS
policies and practices.
The survey identified key challenges
towards policy implementation, and the
the top one was around monitoring of use
and impact.
Other important ones were the lack of
regulation and
evaluation, limited awareness within
government of the role of HWTS
and limited coordination among ministries,
and today we've talked
about how government can contribute to all
of those challenges.
WHO also has a number of resources
available
through its Internet site that
specifically target these challenges.
For instance, there's a toolkit for
monitoring and evaluation to address this
challenge.
There's a scheme for evaluation of
household water treatment
options that gets at the regulation and
evaluation steps.
And there are specific guidances on other
topics such as integration with HIV
programs, national planning and
coordination in general.
So, there are a lot of rich resources that
can support governments in
developing and implementing these national
strategies and action plans.
And again, on the PDF version of these
slides, you'll be able to
hyperlink you'll be able to click on these
icons and get those reports directly.
So, to summarize then, we've looked at the
many responsibilities
and roles that can be played by government
agencies with HWTS.
We've looked at them through a lens of
human rights approach, thinking
about the responsibilities of government
to respect, to protect and fulfill rights.
And we've shown that fulfilling rights can
be broken down into facilitation, such
as collecting and managing information,
and in coordinating stakeholders,
promotion, establishing policies, and
strategies, action plans,
endorsing certain technologies, and
conducting public health campaigns.
And finally, provision of services,
especially targeting particular vulnerable
groups.
And we've seen how national strategies,
and action plans can bring together these
different responsibilities and roles of
government into a coherent package.