This week we looked at a range
of different ways that HWTS interventions
can be implemented.
We started by considering approaches that
seek to
either maximize profits, or social goods,
like reducing disease,
and how social businesses combine some of
the
aspects of those two approaches.
But whichever
approach is taken, basic questions of
demand, supply,
and financing need to be taken into
consideration.
Next, we looked at targeted approaches
where by integrating with other kinds
of interventions, it's more possible to
reach the vulnerable people efficiently.
So, the examples we looked at here were in
schools, through education programs.
And with the health sector, through either
maternal and
child health initiatives, like this
antenatal care project in Malawi,
or HIV AIDS management programs.
And in both cases there are,
synergies that can be had.
Both interventions can gain if for
example,
in the health care example, it was shown
that people sought more health care when
the program was tied with an HWTS
intervention.
And at the same time, uptake rates were
very high.
And there are a variety of reason for
this.
It could be that the people are
particularly
vulnerable and willing to adopt a new
behavior.
Could be that the communication channels
are
well-trusted whether its teachers or
healthcare workers.
But, for whatever reason, there's evidence
that this kind of
integrated approach can yield benefits
for both interventions.
We next considered a very specific type of
targeting vulnerable populations, that of
HWTS in emergencies.
We had a guest lecture from Dr. Daniele
Lantagne at Tufts University in the USA
and she talked about some of the
experiences evaluating HWTS in a range of
countries.
And one of the key things from her
findings
were that preparation is key in advance of
the emergency.
And also that you have to have that
combination
of unsafe water and effective treatment
and consistent and
effective use in order to realize health
gains and
we'll come back to that message in next
week's modules.
Finally, we looked at some of the
different
roles that government bodes can play in
HWTS interventions.
Different kinds of government bodies at
different levels.
And took as a frame work, the
human rights consideration of,
responsibilities of governments
to respect, to protect and to fulfill
rights, and in particular, with relation
to HWTS.
We saw how that fulfilling responsibility
could
involve facilitation through information
collecting and coordination.
Could also involve promotion and
evaluation of technologies.
And finally, provision of services,
especially targeting the vulnerable
people who have no other ways to access
safe water.
We then gave an example of how national
plans and strategies can
bring together these different roles of
government into a coherent package.