Welcome.
I'm Maggie Montgomery, from the World
Health Organization.
And, here today to talk about the
evaluation
and the validation of household water
treatment technology.
So, I want to thank, Dr. Johnston for
inviting me.
And let's get started.
So there's going to be three main things
I'd like to talk to you about today.
The first is why is it important
to assess the performance of household
water treatment.
And I'll talk just briefly about the fact
that household water treatment, the main
benefit is health.
And so it's important that we know how
well.
Household water treatment technologies
remove pathogens so we
have some indication of the protection of
health.
And second, I'll talk about the WHO
global standards on the performance of
household water treatment.
And give a bit of background about how
they were developed.
And lastly, I'll talk about what WHO is
doing to implement these standards.
Specifically,
discuss the WHO International Scheme
to evaluate household water treatment
technologies.
There's two main reasons why it's
important to
assess the performance of household water
treatments technology.
The first is to understand if these
technologies are achieving
the objectives of improving health, which
requires, first of all that they
remove the pathogens that are causing
the diarrhoeal disease in a specific
population.
And in some cases, we know specially which
pathogens are causing that disease.
For example, in a cholera outbreak, it's
very well known that
is the bacterium vibrio cholerae that is
causing the diarrhoeal disease.
But in other cases, for example, people
living with HIV AIDS, who are more
susceptible to diarrhoeal disease, it
could be
a suite of pathogens that are causing this
disease.
And in all cases, it's important that the
devices that are being used with these
specific populations
are removing the pathogens we are most
concerned about.
And if we don't know exactly which
pathogens those are, it is
prudent to make sure that these devices
remove a suite of pathogens.
The second reason why assessing household
water treatment performance is
important is that government especially, as
well as implementers and funders
need to know that the devices that
they are investing
in are achieving the aims that they set
out to achieve.
And this requires a rigorous evaluation of
household water treatment.
Now, in many countries where household
water treatment is most needed,
Where the water quality is poor and the
diarrhoeal disease burden is
high, governments don't have the
resources,
nor the capacity to do such evaluations.
And lastly, I just wanted to emphasize
that while today's talk
is going to be focused on the performance,
realizing the health
benefits from household water treatment
also requires that users correctly and
consistently use household water treatment
when their water quality is compromised.
So in order to facilitate the evaluation
of household water treatment
WHO came out with global recommendations
on how to assess performance.
Now, these global recommendations, the
goal is to protect
the health of the users and also to ensure
that
more household water treatments products
that achieve minimum performance standards
are
being distributed and used to those that
most need safe water.
Now specifically the recommendations look
at three main classes of pathogens.
And these three classes of pathogens, I
know you've already talked
about with Dr. Johnston and hopefully you
understand well at this point.
But these are the three main classes that
cause diarrhoeal
disease in humans and they are viruses
bacteria and protozoa.
From these three classes of pathogens we
derived
targets and what I mean by targets we
derived, what are the minimum amounts of
removal
that need to be achieved in order to
achieve a certain minimum amount of risk
in a population.
Now these targets were derived based on
what has already been done in the WHO
guidelines for drinking water quality. And
these guidelines
use what is called quantitative microbial
risk assessment.
So quantitative microbial risk assessment
are basically models that allow
us to predict what will be the health
consequences in a population if they
ingest a certain concentration of
pathogens with a certain frequency.
So for these models we obviously had to
pick specific pathogens within each of
these, classes of viruses, bacteria and
protozoa to come up with an estimate.
Now from that estimate we also decided.
What was the minimum amount of risk we're
willing to accept and I'll talk
about that in the next slide, that allowed
us to then develop our removal target.
We also used a tiered approach.
So rather than setting one very high bar
for household water treatment, we
recognized that even
devices that maybe are not the best but
do provide some protection and even
limited protection,
can have a very significant impact in
populations where the concentrations
of pathogens are very high and the disease
burden is very high.
So this tiered approach was done to
acknowledge the fact
that even lesser performing devices can
still have an health impact.
It was also created because we recognized
in some situations it's just simply not
economically feasible to have the very top
device, and cheaper
and perhaps less protective devices can
still have an important impact.
Lastly, the recommendations provide some
information on the laboratory
protocols, or how you would actually go
about doing experiments
to test the performance of these household
water treatment devices.
Before I present the performance
standards,
I want just to briefly highlight what
log-removal is and what it actually means
when we're talking about concentrations of
pathogens.
So let's say, for example, we start with
cryptosporidium before we put the water
through a filter.
We put the water trough the filter and
filtering we have 10 cryptosporidium.
So that means we've removed 90
cyrptosporidium pretty
simple math, we can equate that to a
percentage and we say we have 90% removal
and that is equivalent to 1 log removal.
Now let's say with that same source water
we still have a 100 cryptosporidium.
But after filtering we use a better
filter, a more highly performing filter.
We only have one cryptosporidium remaining
in the water after it's been filtered.
This means we, we've removed 99
cryptosporidium.
Or achieved a two-log removal.
Assessing performance.
So based on the quantitative microbial
risk models I spoke of earlier, we were
able to develop specific reduction targets
for
each of the three classes of pathogens,
based on allowable risk.
Now the most stringent requirements were
the category where
we're allowing the least amount of risk in
a
population, specifically ten to the
negative six DALYs per
person per year, it is a highly protective
category.
Now in this category
devices must achieve at least four log
removal of bacteria, at least
five log removal of viruses and at least
four log removal protozoa.
Now you'll notice, that for the viruses,
the
log reduction is even greater, because we
know viruses
are more likely to cause infection and
disease with
just a single virus, compared to the other
pathogens.
Now for the protective category, we're
allowing
a slightly less conservative risk in the
population.
It's 10 to the negative fourth DALYs.
And consequently, the log removal doesn't
have to be quite as high.
Two, at least two for bacteria, at least
three for viruses and at least two for
protozoa.
The final category "Limited protection"
are actually technologies
that achieve at least two of the targets
for
the classes of pathogens in protective.
Now, these may be technologies that do
really well for
two of the classes, but not on the third.
In populations where we are very sure of
the main
pathogen that's causing disease, they
could be a very effective option.
Now, for each of these classes of
bacteria, viruses, and protozoa,
we had to chose one specific organism to
represent the class as a
whole, in order to develop the models and
come up with the specific log-reductions.
So we choose pathogens that we know in
human
populations do account for a significant
proportion of diarrhoeal disease.
And bacteria specifically it's
campylobacter, virus
is rotavirus, and protozoa was
cryptosporidium.
Now what are some
examples of technologies that are already
being used in the
field and have been tested quite
rigorously in the lab.
That meet these performance standards.
Well for highly protective, the number one
technology or actually it's a method, is
boiling.
This is by far the oldest method we have
and it's very efficacious in the removal,
but the problem with boiling is
recontamination, so that's an important
issue to consider.
Ultra filters, I know you've just
learned about filtration, are
also very efficacious as well as a
combination of approaches.
So you may do filtering followed by
chlorination
in order to achieve a higher level of
protection.
In the middle category we have
membrane filters as well as many
flocculant-disinfectant.
And lastly in limited production category
some examples include chlorine which we
know is very effective against bacteria
especially cholera, but fairly ineffective
against protozoa,
especially cryptosporidium.
Ceramic filters and some bio-sand filters
also fall into this limited protection
category.
Now you may wonder why did we have three
levels of performance.
Well there's two main reasons.
First of all, we know in populations where
there is a high burden of diarrhoeal
disease and
a high load of fecal contamination in
the environment and therefore in the
drinking water.
Even devices that achieved the protective
or limited
protection level could have a significant
impact on health.
We also know that in many of these areas,
economics and costs are huge barriers.
And, sometimes the highly protective
devices may also be cost-prohibitive.
So we don't want to prevent other, maybe
lesser-performing but still having
some protection devices, such as
protective
and limited protection from reaching those
populations.
Nuts and bolts of testing.
So how do we actually
test these devices and what kind of water
do we use
to see that we're actually achieving a
certain level of performance.
Well we want to really mimic the types of
waters that
we find in the environments and
communities that would use these devices.
So, in order to do this,
we've developed two types of waters.
The first is a general test water.
Now this is water that represents high
quality groundwater or rainwater.
It will have a very low turbidity, so
there's not
a lot of particulates in the water, and a
temperature that is fairly consistent with
the ambient temperature. It
is the non-stressed phase of testing, so
it's not technology specific.
We also though, want to see how these
devices will perform when we have
really turbid or contaminated water like
this river that you see here in Lao.
Many people are still using surface water
and this challenge water is supposed to
represent
such surface waters like rivers or ponds,
so the
turbidity is very high as well as the TOC.
Now this is the stressed phase challenge
phase of testing and depending on
the different product, we may vary
the conditions, as different products will
fail
under different conditions,
depending on whether or not it's a filter
or a chemical additive or some combination
of approaches.
We've talked about why it's important to
assess the performance of household water
treatment.
And we've also talked about the global
recommendations on performance of
household water treatment.
The third thing I want to talk about
is the WHO Scheme to evaluate household
water treatment technologies, which
is specifically how WHO and governments
are working to implement these
recommendations.
There's two main objectives to this
scheme.
The first is to promote and coordinate the
independent testing and
evaluation of household water treatment
products based on the WHO criteria.
I would like to stress the word
independent because often we find that
laboratories,
especially in particular countries, do not
have
the ability to provide independent and
objective
evaluations.
The second, is to support national
governments
in building the technical capacity of
research institutions.
So, improve the ability for governments to
assess local products, to
do complimentary testing in the field of
household water treatment products.
Especially after they've been in use for
some time.
And this is all linked to WHO's greater
work in water quality,
on applying the WHO guidelines on drinking
water quality.
In summary, I'd like to stress two main
points.
First hopefully by now you've understood
that the assessment
of household water treatment performance
is important for protecting health.
Now, I spoke only about the
microbiological performance of household water
treatment.
The chemical performance of household water
treatment also
is important and is something that WHO
recognizes,
needs to be addresses, but hasn't been
developed
yet in terms of a set of global
guidelines.
I also want to make sure you leave
by remembering that is equally important
that these
products are used correctly and
consistently by the
groups that are most at risk for
diarrhoeal disease.
So young children, people with HIV/AIDS,
those in emergencies
or in cholera outbreaks are just a few
examples.
Secondly, the WHO International Scheme to
Evaluate
household water treatment aims first of
all to
inform and to provide objective
information about
performance but it also hopes to spark
innovation.
And already we're seeing that
manufacturers are trying to develop
technologies
that not only are highly protective but
also are low cost,
easy to use and can be easily distributed
in places where water quality is
poorest.
And lastly, the scheme aims to build
capacity
so someday in the future, we can work
ourselves out of the job, and
governments
themselves can evaluate and regulate
household water treatment technologies.
So I would like to thank you for your
attention.
I'd like to point you to some additional
resources and information.
First of all, if you want to read the
performance recommendations
I spoke about, you can find them online at
this web address.
These are the recommendations.
Also if you want to learn more about the
scheme, you can go to
the website that presents all the
information
about the scheme, their related protocols,
the laboratories.
And lastly, if you're just interested in
household water treatment more generally,
I refer you
to the WHO/UNICEF International Network on
Household Water Treatment and Safe
Storage,
which is working on a variety of issues,
to try to make sure household
water treatment, gets to where it's
needed, and used by those most in need.
So thank you.