I'm happy to introduce
our guest lecturer, Dr. Batsi Majuru,
a technical officer
at the World Health Organization.
Today she'll introduce
the International Scheme to Evaluate
Household Water Treatment Technologies
which aims to promote and coordinate
independent testing
of household water treatment products
based on WHO performance criteria,
and also to support governments
in building technical capacity.
Hi, I'm Batsi Majuru.
I work with Dr. Maggie Montgomery
on the international scheme
to evaluate household water
treatment technologies.
I'm going to be sharing
more about this scheme in this session.
We're going to take a brief look
at how the scheme works
and who is involved,
and we're also going to be talking
about what the scheme is doing
beyond lab testing of products —
the capacity-building activities
that are being conducted
in various countries.
The scheme is made up
of several components.
WHO acts as the scheme secretariat
and coordinates all activities
under the scheme.
The scheme works together
with an independent advisory committee
of experts in water microbiology,
environmental science,
and epidemiology who provide
advice on test protocols
and processes and recommendations
on the level of performance.
There are currently
two designated testing labs
that are in the United States
and in the Netherlands.
Work is ongoing to expand testing
to other national labs
to conduct complimentary testing.
We will discuss this briefly later.
The manufacturers are
a key component of the scheme,
as they are the ones who submit
the products that are to be tested.
Their interaction is
only through the scheme secretariat
at WHO to ensure independence
throughout the evaluation process.
Ultimately, the results from the testing
are meant to guide governments
and procuring entities in the selection
of household water treatment products.
Last, but certainly not least,
are the users of the products.
In terms of how the scheme evaluation process works,
manufacturers submit
an expression of interest
for the evaluation of a specific product,
or in some instances, several products.
This information is then reviewed
by WHO and the advisory committee
and recommendations are made
on the testing to be conducted.
The product is then tested at one
of the two designated testing laboratories.
The results from the testing
are shared with the manufacturer
and also made publicly available
at the scheme webpage.
Ultimately, these results
are meant to guide procuring entities
and governments in the selection
of household water treatment products.
So this hopefully gives you a flavor
of how testing under the scheme works.
In the following slides,
we're going to talk
about what the scheme is doing
beyond lab testing.
WHO is also working
to strengthen the capacity
of resource-constrained countries
to regulate and evaluate
household water treatment products
to ensure that users
are provided with products
that actually protect health.
Many countries do not have
health-based standards
to assess and regulate
household water treatment products,
and those that do often do not have
the structures in place
to allow for an independent review
and assessment process.
Therefore, WHO is working to strengthen
regulation of these products
and as an example,
countries such as Ethiopia,
are working to provide training
on risk-based assessments,
establish certification processes,
and develop protocols for evaluation
of household water treatment technologies.
This would enable national labs
to conduct their own complimentary testing.
The second area of capacity-building
under the scheme is
assessing locally produced products,
such as ceramic filters,
chlorine solutions,
and bio sand filters.
The quality of these products
is highly variable,
and harmonized manufacturing processes
can have a positive impact
on improving the quality.
The scheme is working with partners
in the international network
on household water treatment
and safe storage
to strengthen quality assurance
and quality control procedures
in these local manufacturing factories.
An example of such quality
management processes
is the Best Practices Recommendations
for the Manufacturing
of Ceramic Pot Filters that was developed
by the Ceramics
Manufacturing Working Group.
This is a certification process
that is currently being finalized
and has been piloted in several countries.
The certification process
focuses on the efficacy of the filter
in removing E. coli and an assessment
of the manufacturing processes
at factories, including
raw materials that are used,
mixing and molding processes,
and quality assurance tests
such as flow rate.
The scheme is working with
the Ceramics Manufacturing Working Group
to expand the application
of this certification process
to other countries.
Here is an example
of some of the findings from assessments
that have been conducted
under this ceramics certification process
from four factories.
You can see from these pictures
that the filters
from factories two and three
are of poor quality
compared to those
from factories one and four.
The third and final area
of capacity-building
is field-monitoring the evaluation
of household water treatment products.
Testing under the scheme
is limited to lab performance or efficacy.
However, to protect health,
products not only need to be effective
in removing pathogens or be efficacious
but also be used correctly
and consistently over time.
The scheme is working with countries
to assess ongoing performance
in the field and use of products
as well as establish platforms
for national consumer feedback
on these products.
I hope that has given you a flavor
of what the scheme is doing,
both in terms of evaluating products
and building capacity in countries.
If you would like to find out more
about the scheme,
you can visit our website
where you will be able
to see the list of products
that are currently under evaluation,
the harmonized test protocols
that we use in testing the products,
and the work that we are doing
to build capacity in countries.
In summary, we have talked
about testing under this scheme,
how it works and who is involved.
The main point to remember
is that this testing is aimed
at ensuring that in the first instance,
products are selected
that are actually capable
of removing or inactivating
pathogens in drinking water,
but we also recognize
that health impact can only be achieved
through correct and consistent use
of effective products.
Linked to this effort is capacity-building
that WHO is doing to ensure
that in the places where the products
will be used most, there are
regulations in place and mechanisms
to assess and monitor
the performance of products
over time. Thank you.