We've seen several times now that there
are
three elements necessary to realize health
gains through HWTS.
People have to be drinking unsafe water.
They have to have access to an effective
option for treatment.
And they have to apply that treatment
effectively and consistently.
This last bit is tricky.
HWTS is not like vaccination where you do
something
once and then you have a long term
protection.
It's also not like many chemicals where
roughly speaking if you
reduce the dose by half, you reduce the
disease burden by half.
Household water treatment is different, in
that it has to be done
consistently and correctly, over and over
again, to realize the health gains.
And this poses particular challenges.
First, unsafe water.
There's actually plenty of it out there.
The Joint Monitoring Program of WHO and
UNICEF
reported that in 2011, 768 million people
were
using unimproved sources of drinking
water, such as
unprotected wells or springs or open
surface water.
But even among those using an improved
source, like tap water, a bore
hole, rainwater collection, improved
springs and
wells, drinking water is not always safe.
Either the resource itself may be
contaminated, or
water can become contaminated thru
collection, transport,
and storage, as we saw in one of those
animations from the first week.
It's been estimated that around 1.8
billion people are actually
drinking water which contains measurable E
coli, or thermotolerant coliforms.
So, there is plenty of unsafe water out
there.
And, in the discussion on targeting
vulnerable groups, we talked
about strategies for reaching those with
particularly poor water quality.
Obviously, you have to apply an effective
treatment option.
And, Maggie Montgomery described to us,
the
WHO scheme for evaluating household water
treatment options.
And remember, the WHO in that document has
defined
three classes of effectiveness based on
log reduction values.
Where to be
highly protective, a technology must be
able
to reduce bacteria by at least four logs,
five for viruses, and four for protozoa.
The protective level is a little bit less
stripped by two orders of magnitude, and
the
interim level applies when a technology
meets the
protective criterion for two of the three
pathogen classes.
But an option which works well in a
laboratory
evaluation may perform completely
differently in the real world.
There are differences of course in the
person applying the treatment but
also in the environment, the water
quality, the containers used, et cetera.
So it's useful to distinguish between
efficacy
which is how well something works under
ideal controlled conditions, and
effectiveness which is
how well it works in the real world.
The WHO scheme will measure efficacy, not
effectiveness.
And there's a good example of the
difference between the two in Ecuador,
where a
long term research project has
examined
household water treatment with chlorine,
among other things.
Now, chlorine is highly effective against
bacteria and particular against E. coli.
And the evaluation team, led by Laura
McLaughlin confirmed this with their own
tests in 2009, finding LRVs of three to
six, depending on the indicator organism.
So the efficacy was good.
But the evaluation team also found that
LRVs
were much lower, around one, in actual
households.
And that there was no significant
difference in
LRV between households applying
chlorination and households that didn't.
Even the measured chlorine residual was
not significantly
higher in households which reported
chlorinating their water.
A similar study by the same group, and
this paper is by Karen Levy, found
that E. coli could be detected in around
half of the households reportedly
protecting, practicing chlorination.
And some of the factors they found that
correlated with poor LRVs were
high turbidity in water, higher
concentrations of E. coli in the raw water.
And there was also evidence of household
level contamination from poor water
handling and storage.
Even if a treatment is effectively applied
at the household level,
it has to be done consistently, day in and
day out.
And this is a major challenge both for
households to
actually do this and for researchers to
monitor and evaluate practices.
If you ask people if they have treated
their
water they may respond with what they
think you
would like to hear, especially if you've
been involved
in the team promoting HWTS in the first
place.
So self-reported HWTS practice is
subjective and probably more useful as an
indicator of knowledge, or perhaps
societal
expectations and norms than of actual
practice.
In some cases, there could be more
objective indicators.
And chlorine is the best example because
residual chlorine
can be measured easily and quickly in the
field.
Others have attempted to observe other
kinds of HWTS practice.
Like seeing if a household filter is wet,
or appears to be in regular use.
Or if SODIS bottles are in the household,
or present up on the rooftop.
Another objective indicator, though, is to
just measure
the E. coli levels in the raw water and
the stored water to see if there has
been some kind of improvement in microbial
water quality.
So objective indicators can help to
measure, effective
use, but consistent use is, is harder
still.
Consistent use, or sometimes people say
compliance
or adherence means only using treated
water for
drinking purposes, throughout the day, the
week,
the month, the different seasons of the
year.
And it's hard to measure this.
What you would really like to have would
be many repeat visits what's called a
longitudinal study.
And this is important but very
difficult and expensive to do.
And where it has been done, researchers
tend to find that people have
very different water treatment practices,
even different
self-reported practices from one visit to
another.
A related issue is the long-term use
sustainability of HWTS use.
And if an evaluation is done just a few
months after an intervention is complete,
it probably doesn't give a very accurate
picture of the long-term consistent use.
HWTS is special because you have to have
both effective use and
high compliance, or consistent use, or
adherence to get large health impacts.
This is the subject of an analysis by Joe
Brown and Tom Clasen, who used modeling to
look at
the relationship between water quality,
raw water quality, consistent
use of HWTS, and they use the term
adherence.
And health outcomes, expressed here as
DALYs
averted for hundred thousand persons per
year.
This graph shows that if the raw water is
of poor quality, high risk.
Let's look at classes A, B, and C.
Then there are large health gains to be
had.
Here's A, B and C, if HWTS is
always applied.
But if you take even 10% of your water
without treatment or have 90% adherence,
then in classes A and B, you have very
little health impact.
That's because even a little bit of highly
contaminated water,
consumed once in a while, can give you
diarrheal disease.
For class C water at moderate risk health
gains are less sensitive to compliance.
But there is still a big drop off and so
that if you drink water with about,
treated water about 75% of the time,
you're
getting about half of the possible
reduction in disease.
Now moderate and low risk waters are
relatively clean to begin with,
so there are not large reductions in
disease to be had at all.
Even if compliance is, is 100%.
Now this analysis assumed two log
reduction for all pathogens.
A similar study by Kyle Enger looked at
how compliance and
efficacy of treatment interact, again but,
to yield reductions in diarrheal disease.
This graph on the left shows that in order
to reduce diarrheal disease by 90%.
You could use a treatment that achieves
two log reductions either 100% or 99% of
the time or a treatment with three log
reductions that you use 95% of the time.
If you use the treatment much less than
that, you might achieve around
50% reduction in disease and the efficacy
of the treatment becomes less important.
Why use a treatment that reduces nine LRV
if you drink untreated water half the
time.
And the second graph shows the same point,
but
taking a more contaminated raw water as
the starting point.
Here, you need a three log reductions to
get even 90% reduction in disease.
Over the past few weeks we've seen some
really stunning examples
of how HWTS has been taken up consistently
in certain cases.
There were the biosand filters in
Cambodia, where nearly 90% of people were
using filters which had been distributed
from six months to eight years previously.
And here, use was defined by self-report
but confirmed
with inspection of the biosand filter to
see if
it looked like, if it was in use, if it
was functional, if it was wet, et cetera.
Then there was the LifeStraw Family,
filter in Zambia, part of the HIV/AIDS
intervention, where 96% of the women in
the study were still using the filter.
95% of them reported having drunk no
unfiltered water
or given any to their children on the
previous day.
And here compliance could have been even
higher
if rats hadn't eaten two of the filters.
There is another LifeStraw evaluation in
Congo which showed more modest compliance
with about 2 3rds of people classified as
consistent users after eight months.
But nearly all of them reported having
drunk some untreated water on the previous
day.
So this is maybe a medium compliance
example.
A study of SODIS in Zimbabwe looked at
three different indicators of SODIS.
Self-reported practice are calculated
through a detailed interview and drink
diary, and then observation by looking for
bottles on the rooftop.
Now, these three measures agreed fairly
well with
each other and for any of the indicators.
More than 2 3rds of the households which
had received household
visits were confirmed users more than two
years after the interventions.
Finally, chlorine treatment offers the
most objective
indicator of actual use by measuring
residual chlorination.
And the evaluation by Harshfield in Haiti
found 56% of
people practicing adequate chlorination up
to eight years after the intervention.
Of course, it's not always such good news.
And there are plenty of examples of low
uptake as well.
It's actually just as important to report
and
study these to learn about what didn't
work.
One example is the ceramic pot filters in
Cambodia where only 31% of people
were still using filters as reported in
an interview and confirmed by visual
inspection.
But here the usage was highly dependent on
the amount of time that had
passed since receiving the filter, and
usage was very high in the initial months.
It was breakage that was a problem.
Before the LifeStraw Family filter, there
was the LifeStraw personal.
We didn't look at that one in the membrane
module, but its another membrane treatment
in which you suck water directly through a
filter into your mouth like a straw.
And in this evaluation in Ethiopia, only
about a third
of people reported using the filter in the
previous week.
And about one in eight people describe
themselves as consistent users.
This study is actually a classic
example of respondent bias for diarrheal
disease.
Because, these same households reported a
25% reduction in diarrhea,
which just isn't plausible with such low
levels of compliance.
Finally, a large evaluation of SODIS in
Bolivia found
that about a third of people were actually
practicing treatment.
Here defined by self-report and confirmed
by observation.
And in one of the earlier evaluations of
HWTS a study of
Pure in Guatemala, while Proctor and
Gamble was still considering a commercial
strategy.
This involved a long pilot and heavy
promotion of Pure.
But, six months after that
intervention, only
5% of the target households had actually
purchased sachets.
Then these last two examples are of
technical
innovations that were being piloted in the
field.
So, it's perhaps not fair to judge them as
mature products.
Both for the Mesita Azul in Mexico, the
ultraviolet system, and the chulli
pasteurization system in Bangladesh.
These both worked well technically, but
had fairly low uptake.
In fact, in Bangladesh only 21 out of 101
households reported using their chullis.
But on a repeat visit it was found that
17 of these households were either not
actually using
them at all or were using them incorrectly
by
passing the water through them without a
fire burning.
So here, only four households were
actually applying the technology
consistently and correctly.
Now, how can we explain this huge range in
compliance,
sometimes for the very same product in
different settings?
Well, household water treatment is a very
personal behavior.
So behavior change and theories of
behavior change are certainly important.
But there are also external factors
outside the
personal domain, such as availability of
supply chains,
the presence of a supporting policy
environment, et
cetera, that are also important in
determining use.
And these factors will be highly
contextual in
different settings and different
sub-populations within a given setting.
Let's take a look now at some of the
theoretical frameworks
that have been used to explain adoption
and uptake of HWTS.
A classic text in behavioral change is
Rogers' Diffusion of Innovations
Theory, first published in 1962 and now on
its fifth edition.
Rogers analyzed how innovations spread
through various
communication channels and came up with a
list
of five stages that people progress
through
as they decide to adopt a new behavior.
These are awareness or knowledge, here
that they
could treat their drinking water with some
technology.
People should then be persuaded that this
would be a good thing
to do before they will take a decision to
try it out.
But even then it has to implemented
regularly and people have to, in the end,
confirm that this is that they want to
do for the behavior to be adopted
sustainability.
Rogers also identifies five attributes of
innovations which help them to be adopted.
I think he liked the number five because
he also talked about five different types
of adopters.
But the five attributes then are that the
innovation should have an advantage over
the current practice.
It should be compatible with existing
values and needs.
It shouldn't be too complex either.
It's useful if an innovation can be
experimented with, trialed on a limited
basis.
People like to try things out.
And ideally they, and other people as
well, should
be able to observe the results of an
innovation.
And these factors together contribute to a
greater likelihood of uptake.
So that's one framework.
Here at Eawag, Professor Hans-Joachim
Mosler has developed a theory
of behavior change based on psychological
theory that's called RANAS.
And that stands for risks, attitudes,
norms, abilities, and self-regulation.
Professor Mosler defines factors which fit
into these five blocks, which together
can determine how likely people are to
adopt and sustain a new behavior.
In his studies, in his research, his team
first measures
which of these factors are most important
in a given context.
And then designs custom interventions to
influence the critical
factors, and so achieve better uptake and
sustained use.
Let's look at one more conceptual
framework
that was developed recently by Robert
Dreibelbis
and his colleagues, who published a
systematic
review of theories of behavior change in
wash.
And also developed a conceptual framework
taking elements from the different
contributions reviewed.
It's called IBM-WASH and it's not
sponsored by a major computer company.
It stands for the Integrated Behavioral
Model for Water, Sanitation and Hygiene.
The authors consider three classes of
factors, or dimensions.
Where the contextual factor, represents
background
factors like access to markets, the
policy environment, characteristics of the
household, and the environment, and so on.
And these factors are largely outside of
the control of
interventions, but have important
influences on HWTS, uptake, and use.
The psychosocial dimension considers
factors like
those described in the RANAS model.
Which, in principle, could be targeted and
influenced by interventions.
Finally the technical dimension includes
the
specific characteristics of the HWTS
technology to
be applied, and how these are preferred or
not preferred by potential users.
Each of these three classes of factors,
these
three dimensions is considered to apply at
different
scales, five different levels, ranging
from the individual
up to larger groups and, eventually, the
entire society.
Here are a few reviews of behavior change
that are all available on the Internet.
The first comes from the Johns Hopkins
Center for Communication programs.
Here's the systematic review that led to
the IBM-WASH framework.
And here is a tool kit from Eawag, from
Professor Mosler and his group.
WHO and UNICEF have published a really
useful
tool kit on monitoring and evaluation of
HWTS programs.
You can download it by clicking on the
icon
or it's in the supplementary reading list
as well.
This tool kit is meant to provide an
overall framework for
planning, conducting, and utilizing
monitoring and
evaluation data to improve HWTS
programming.
And the tool kit provides a set of 20 core
indicators
that are recommended for monitoring
correct and consistent use of HWTS.
These core indicators are grouped into
five classes.
Reported and observed use, correct,
consistent use and storage, knowledge
and behavior, other environmental health
interventions, and water quality.
I encourage you to look at the full list
in the report.
But for today's module about effective and
consistent use, the most relevant
groups are the ones for correct
consistent use and water quality.
In the correct and consistent use group,
there are six different indicators.
A mixture of self-reports and
observations, demonstrations.
And again these indicators are somewhat
prone to bias.
But they can provide an upper limit for
actual practice.
The water quality indicators are more
objective.
These involve actual measurements of water
quality either for E. coli or
other indicator bacteria, or for residual
chlorine in the case of chlorination.
The raw water may also be tested.
So that for E. coli or thermotolerant
coliforms, an LRV could be calculated.
And some people include a certain level of
removal
as part of a definition for confirmed use
of HWTS.
This module has drawn heavily on a number
of publications, some of which you
have seen in previous lectures, and many
of these are freely available on the
internet.
On the PDF version, you can just click on
the hyperlink and get to the actual report
or paper.
These references are mostly about
compliance, either studies that have
measured actual use or models linking
compliance with health outcomes.
And these references, are more about
behavior change.
That could be a nice subject for an entire
MOOC or maybe several MOOCs.
So in conclusion, we saw two models that
predict that for HWTS to
lead to health gains, the technology
has to be applied effectively and
consistently.
Of course, the drinking water should be
unsafe as well.
And in order to get behavior change, it
may also be necessary
that people perceive the water as unsafe,
which is a very different thing.
Well, effective use can be measured and
should be measured when monitoring HWTS.
Consistent use is harder to monitor.
It typically requires multiple visits, and
it's
probably most appropriate at a research
level.
There are a range of different frameworks
for thinking about
and achieving and monitoring effective and
consistent use of HWTS.
Including the behavioral change elements,
but also other dimensions such
as the contextual or technical dimensions
in the IBM-WASH framework.
The important question though isn't which
framework is more accurate or
comprehensive.
But to recognize that consistent and
effective use is critical to realizing
health
gains through HWTS, and to take steps to
both promote and monitor actual use.