Hi everyone.
My name is Sophie Boisson, I work at
the London School of Hygiene and Tropical
Medicine.
And today I'm going to talk about health
impact, of household water treatments, and
safe storage intervention.
You have seen from previous lectures,
the three,
let's say the three elements to achieving
health impact.
First of all, while of course water has to
be contaminated by microbes and it has to
be a predominant route of transmission
for diarrheal diseases and pathogens.
Second, we need to have a technology that
is effective at treating those pathogens.
And third, we need to make sure that
people are using those technology
consistently and correctly.
So this slide is to remind
you that transmission of a fecal-oral
pathogens is complex.
As you can see from this diagram
household water
treatment and safe storage addresses only
one pathway of many.
So, the key question is how much diarrhea
can be prevented by improving water
quality alone?
Over the past 30 years, there's been a lot
of
studies measuring the impact of water
quality intervention on diarrheal disease.
And this figure show show the results from
different
systematic reviews that were published in
the last ten years.
And key findings from those reviews were
that overall
water quality interventions were
associated with about
a reduction in diarrheal disease of 30,
40%.
They also found that there were some
differences
in terms of impact between
water quality intervention at the source
and those at the household level.
The impact on diarrhea was generally found
to
be higher when intervention focused at the
household level.
They also found that there were
some differences between different
treatment methods.
Now we're going to talk a little bit more
about the studies
that measure the impact on diarrheal
disease looking
specifically at the type of design the
outcome being measured, and
highlighting some of the key challenges in
conducting health impact studies.
So in terms of evaluation designs the gold
standard for measuring
health impact of intervention is the
randomized control trial.
So we have a group of participants,
households or
villages that are randomly allocated to
two different groups.
One group will receive the intervention
and the other group will act as a control.
The unit of randomization can vary.
And the participants may or may not be
blinded to the intervention.
And we will cover that in later slides.
We can have other type of study design
such as observational studies which
includes comparing diarrheal
disease rates
among all participants before and after
the introduction of an intervention.
We have case controlled studies which
identify cases and non-cases
of diarrhea and compare the exposure,
adjusting for potential confounding.
And we have ecological studies.
We also have modelling studies and I think
you've already covered
that in the last session using examples of
studying the impact of different levels of
compliance on diarrheal disease.
So, all the studies have been looking at
the impact on diarrhea, but what is
diarrhea?
Diarrhea, is a function of stool
consistency, and frequency.
So WHO definition is the passage of three
or more loose stools, within a 24-hour
period.
And as you can imagine, it's pretty hard
sometimes for people to
remember how many loose stools they've
passed in the last day.
And also stool consistency, okay, it may
vary, may vary by diet
and so that's why it's very hard to
measure it reliably.
So potential issues is associated with
measuring
diarrhea, so we have reporting bias.
So reporting bias may happened for
example in the randomized control
trial when participants in the
intervention
group receive a brand new filter.
They may be more likely
to report that, to the reporter, the
enumerator
who comes to visit them, that they feel
healthier, that they, that their health
has improved.
It can be because they want to please
the enumerator and that's often called a
courtesy bias.
On the other hand,
participants in
the control group who have who have not
received anything
may be more likely to complain and say
that their
health has not improved because they
haven't got any filter.
The placebo effect, it's possible that
participants
who've received a filter
or chlorine tablets for example, may
consciously
or subconsciously think that their health
is improving.
The Hawthorne effect which is
interesting because a lot of studies
have looked at most of those
studies measure diarrhea over time, and
what they often find is
that diarrhea decreases in both
intervention and control group over time.
And one possible explanation for that is
the Hawthorne effect, which is
participants may adopt, safer water
handling
or hygiene practices if some
researchers come to their house regularly.
It's also possible that over time
participants are tired of seeing
the enumerators regularly and and they
don't want to bother answering
questions or they just want to answer very
short, or give
very short answers so that the interview
doesn't last very long.
So these are potential issues to be
considered when, when measuring diarrhea.
So here is to illustrate this
reporting bias that I mentioned before.
So the systematic review conducted by
Clasen and colleagues in 2006
shows that report report the impact on
diarrhea
according to whether the intervention
was blinded or not.
So blinded means that the
participants and assessors, double blinded
means that participants and assessors
do not know which treatment
they have received.
Whereas open means that everyone knows
what treatment they've received.
So what they found was that
there was an important
difference in effect size.
While open trials reported diarrhea
reduction in the
range of 30, 40%, blinded trial reported
no effect.
And although there were
certain issues with those blinded
studies, other researchers have
documented
that the lack of blinding of subjective
outcomes such as diarrhea tend
to exaggerate the magnitude of the
effect by 25%.
Now researchers, a group of researchers,
Hunter
and colleagues, they used this estimate to
adjust
the 30, 40% estimate that was
obtained from open trial, and found that
after
adjustment for this bias, due to lack of
blinding, the effect on diarrhea dropped
to 15%.
So of the many studies that have been
conducted looking at the impact of
water quality intervention on diarrhea the
effect estimates often vary.
And so why do we get very different
reduction
in diarrheal disease from those different
studies?
Well first of all, they may be conducted
in
different settings where the transmission
dynamics may be different.
So the transmission routes or the
importance
of different transmission routes may be
different.
For example, in a setting where
sanitation and hygiene
condition are poor, are very poor and
where water quality
is not a major
concern, then of course
lack of sanitation and lack of hygiene are
more likely to be predominant
routes of transmission for diarrheagenic
pathogens.
Also the etiology for diarrhea may be very
different
depending on the regions as the GEMS-studies
have shown.
Second, the treatment methods may not be,
as you've seen
before treatment methods are not effective
against all class of pathogens.
So you've seen the example of chlorine,
which is less effective against
protozoan cysts, so in a certain area
where the study is conducted
Cryptosporidium is a major etiology for
diarrhea, then a chlorine intervention
maybe less effective at reducing diarrhea.
Then third: compliance.
Of course if the technology or if the
treatment methods
is not being used correctly and
consistently, then
we don't expect to see any, any
improvement or any impact on diarrhea.
And in fact,Arnold and colleagues and
Hunter, later Hunter
and colleagues in 2009, they have illustrated
that
the impact of diarrhea tends to diminish
over time.
And one potential explanation for it
is that compliance
when, the longer the studies are
conducted the
less compliant participant become and
the less likely they are to use
intervention, which may explain why
diarrhea decreased over time.
And then there may be also some difference
between efficacy versus effectiveness
trials where efficacy studies
may lead to a higher reduction in diarrhea
because conditions
are more controlled and more, let's
say, perfect compared to effectiveness
trial which measures
impact on real life situations where
the intervention
may not be so delivered perfectly.
So, so we've seen that measuring health
impact is not easy.
So measuring diarrhea in
particular is very challenging in the
field.
It's very easy to do because
you could just collect this information
through surveys.
However, there's lots of challenges.
And so there's several ways through
which we could improve the way we measure
the health impact of the intervention.
First, we talked about blinding.
Okay.
There's been lots
of studies now
trying to blind intervention, so blinding
chlorination tablets,
blinding filters and there are a number of
challenges associated to that.
So one of the challenge for example with
filters, it will be really hard to
create the placebo filter that
that is not effective,
or doesn't to some degree reduce
contamination of the water.
And also it may be really hard to blind
it effectively
so that participants are not able to find
out which filter they received.
And also there's some, it's potentially
unethical for example if participants
who were boiling suddenly receive an
intervention, they may reduce
this practice and use the recommended
tablet, which may be a placebo or inactive
tablet.
And by switching intervention
among the placebo group, a participant may
be at increased risk of diarrhea.
Another option, if blinding has some
challenges, is to use alternative health
outcomes, so not only rely on diarrhea,
but use a more objective health outcome.
So one of them is nutritional
indicators.
So for example, weight for age.
which can be used as a proxy marker
for diarrhea.
And in fact there has been a study
conducted by Schmidt and colleagues in
2010 showing that the more they
looked at the 14 days windows
and they found that the more days you had
diarrhea
during that period the lower was your
weight.
So this is still being
explored and
see whether this indicator could be a
useful proxy for diarrhea.
But obviously because weight is
influenced by another, by a lot of other
factors such as diet, et cetera, it may be
not sensitive enough to
to reflect changes in diarrhea.
And then we have height-for-age, which is
an indicator of
stunting or impaired growth among
children.
And there's been a few
studies that have
looked at the impact of solar
disinfection on
stunting but there's very few
studies,
and I think the evidence so far remains weak.
It's, at the moment,
there's a lot of interest in looking at
environmental enteropathy, which is the
clinical condition characterized by a
damage
of the gut resulting in
leakage of nutrients and
malabsorption.
And there's an increased interest in
measuring impact of water culture
or other environmental health intervention
on this on this condition.
A third possibility is to look at
certain specific pathogens either in
stools or look at
serological markers for exposure to those
pathogens.
But again these methods also have some
drawbacks.
For example you
need to use laboratory
methods and you need to identify which
pathogen you're going to test for.
And sometimes being infected
with a pathogen doesn't necessarily
translate into being sick with
diarrhea.
But these are the outcomes that should be
considered and there's definitely
an increasing interest in
looking at those in future studies.
Thanks, Sophie, for a clear explanation
of measuring health impacts, illustrated
with nice examples.
If I can briefly summarize, there have
been a
lot of health impact studies which have
shown large reductions
in diarrheal disease, of around 30% to
40%, but, that
these studies may be overestimates due to
the methodologies used.
Especially, there's this issue of blinding
of the interventions.
These studies do show that it is
definitely possible to measure
health impacts, but also that it's not
simple, and that a
really high quality evaluation is complex,
also expensive, and definitely something
that should be designed by public health
specialists, such as epidemiologists.
Health impact studies could still be done
for large programs.
But even for large programs, and certainly
for smaller ones, it's probably better to
focus first on monitoring actual use and
effective use before attempting to
measuring health outcomes.
Here you see some of the papers that
Doctor Boisson
drew upon for this module, the systematic
reviews and the other
papers discussing the evidence base, and
finally, a few of the
individual studies that provide examples
of monitoring health impacts of HWTS.