Well, we've seen the consistent and
effective use
of HWTS can lead to sizable health gains,
at least where drinking water is
contaminated and
represents a significant exposure
pathway,but there are lots of
things that could be done that also reduce
disease burden things like promoting
nutrition or vaccines, for
example and when policy makers have to
make
decisions about which types of
interventions to invest in,
they invariably want to know, how much
does it cost. And
there are many different types of
financial and economic analyses that
can be made in connection with water and
sanitation interventions. And
today we'll take a look briefly at a few
of these.
One type of analysis is called a cost
benefit analysis, and here the costs of
the intervention are added up. And are
weighed against the benefits resulting
from the intervention.
How many dollars of investment does it
take to get how many dollars of benefits?
This is a money for money kind of
analysis.
A problem with cost benefit analysis is
that the benefits can be difficult to
quantify.
A simpler analysis is to only look at the
costs and consider which among several
different approaches is the cheapest to
achieve a certain desired outcome. This
is called cost effectiveness analysis and
in HWTS, a common measure of the desired
outcome is the amount of diarrheal disease
prevented measured in deaths or DALYs.
Either cost benefit or cost effectiveness
analysis can
help policy makers decide how to allocate
scarce resources.
I'll give a brief example of a third kind
of economic
analysis, which is called willingness to
pay or contingent valuation studies.
Like the name suggests, this kind of
analysis seeks to find out how
much people would be likely to pay for a
particular HWTS product or service.
Which can be very useful for social
businesses or profit
maximizing businesses who seek to generate
some revenue from HWTS.
An important cost benefit analysis was
done by Guy Hutton
and colleagues, and they looked at five
possible WASH interventions.
Meeting the water MDG target, meeting both
the water and
sanitation MDG targets, universal access
to basic water and sanitation,
universal basic access along with
disinfection using HWTS
and finally, a higher level of service
regulated piped drinking water and sewage.
The authors calculated the costs of each
of these interventions
in different geographic regions, and also
the benefits and the
benefits here included the reduction in
diarrheal disease both in
terms of incidence and mortality, but also
several economic benefits.
Money saved by not having to manage
diarrheal disease and this could
be money saved by the individual household
or by the healthcare sector
also increased productivity resulting from
improved health and finally, time savings
from not having to travel long distances
to access water and sanitation facilities.
The authors found that WASH interventions
were
highly cost beneficial, that the
benefit-cost ratio
was above one in all cases and in some
cases, was very much larger.
Benefit-cost ratios tended to be higher in
wealthy countries here the letter B means
a region with low mortality, and C, D, and
E are increasingly higher mortality.
Benefit-cost ratios are higher in
wealthier countries in part because
they are a big time savings and these are
valued more highly in wealthier countries.
The figure shows that this one in the
middle here, the purple one achieving
universal basic access with HWTS has a
benefit cost ratio of at least five in all
settings even the highest mortality ones,
and greater than ten in most settings.
In the higher mortality settings, the
benefit-cost ratio is just about the same
of the other two interventions that had
the highest ratios
that's meeting both MDG targets and
achieving universal basic access.
Meeting the water MDG alone doesn't yield
as large
health benefits and achieving universal
access to regulated services
does have big health benefits, but is very
expensive,
so it has a lower benefit to cost ratio.
Well, how about cost effectiveness
analysis?
This is a little bit easier and lends
itself more
to disaggregated analysis like comparing
one HWTS option against another.
Well, the WHO's 2002 World Health Report
included a similar analysis to the
Hutton Cost Benefit Analysis and concluded
that
the intervention which is consistently the
most
cost-effective across regions and would be
classified
as very cost effective in all areas
where it was evaluated, was the provision
of disinfection capacity at point of use.
On purely cost-effectiveness grounds, it
would be the first choice where resources
are scarce and as you can imagine, this
report gave a major boost to HWTS efforts.
Several years later, Tom Clasen at the
London School of Hygiene and Tropical
Medicine
did another cost effectiveness
analysis, this
time looking at differences between
different HWTS options.
He used information from various program
implementers
to calculate the annual cost of different
HWTS
options per person served, and then
compare
this against the cost of conventional
water interventions.
Which in this case was considered as
installing and
maintaining wells, boreholes and communal
tap stands in Asia.
He found that the annual cost of
implementing chlorination or SODIS
was under $0.70 per year, $0.66 and $0.63.
And that that was cost less than source
improvements which
were around under $2.00 or $2.6 per year
in Asia.
Filtration and flocculation disinfection
were more expensive than
the interventions at the sources,but you
have to recall
that improved sources like these don't
necessarily translate
into safe drinking water at the source of
consumption.
The study also calculated the total cost
of implementing these interventions for
50% of the
population in the WHO Western Pacific
Region
and found that for chlorination and SODIS,
the
benefits to the health care sector were
greater than the costs of implementation
and this
is actually a limited cost benefit
analysis considering
only the benefits to the health sector,
and
not other benefits like increased
productivity
from improved health or time savings.
The study also reported the annual cost to
prevent
one DALY and in all cases, this cost was
low.
One rule of thumb is that the cost to
avert one DALY, if that
is less than the per capita gross domestic
product, it's a very cost effective
investment. So, costs as low as $50, or
$100, or under $200 per DALY averted
are very good investments, and even the
more expensive options fall within a
cost-effective range.
Thinking back on the different
implementation strategies, nearly all HWTS
interventions aim to recover at least some
costs from the users.
Public health oriented interventions may
struggle here,
because they may target populations that
have
very little ability to pay and face
multiple competing demands for their
limited resources.
There's a whole field of study called
contingent valuation that aims to find out
how much people are likely to be willing
to pay for a product or service
especially one that is hypothetical or
doesn't
yet exist,like health impact studies. It's
easy to
do a primitive willingness to pay study,
but the results aren't of worth very much.
A properly designed study is complex and
sophisticated, and so
far there are not many good examples for
household water treatment.
However, one significant and sophisticated
study was
done by Jill Luoto and colleagues in
Bangladesh.
In this study, 600 households were given
free two month trials
of each of four HWTS options in rotation,
following a random sequence.
After the trial, people participated in a
bidding auction where they could express
the
maximum amount that they would pay for
a bottle of Aqua WaterGuard liquid
chlorine good
for about two weeks of use strips of
Aquatabs chlorine tablets good for ten
days,five sachet of PuR enough for five
days, or one Crystal PuR ceramic candle
filter,
which is similar to the Tulip filter that
we saw in
week two, with an expected lifetime of a
year or more.
The willingness to pay in this study was
found to be extremely low.
A large number of households said that
they
wouldn't willing to pay anything at all
for these
products nearly half of households were
willing to
pay something like a market rate for the
Aquatabs
and about a third would pay a market
rate for WaterGuard,but only 1% of
households were willing
to pay the estimated market price of about
$7.25 for the filter and no one was
willing
to pay the market price for PuR.
Now, this low unwillingness to pay isn't
simply
due to lack of demand or concern for
safe water less than a third of people
in the study, did consider their drinking
water safe.
One reason could be the, the poverty in
the study area of urban Dhaka slums
per capita household incomes were well
below
$2 per capita per day purchasing power
parenting.
Another reason could be general lack of
experience with paying for water
or with familiarity with the taste and
odor of chlorine in Bangladesh.
So, this is a good study to look at for
methods and to serve as a reminder that
people may
not be willing to invest their own money
in HWTS
options, even when they consider that
their drinking water is unsafe.
So, that's a very brief run through of
some of
the economic tools that can be used to
evaluate HWTS interventions.
We saw that HWTS does fairly well in
a cost benefit analysis with benefit cost
ratios well
above five, and comparable to the other
water and
sanitation interventions having the
highest benefit to cost ratios.
In two cost effectiveness analyses, we saw
that HWTS
can be extremely cost effective in terms
of the
cost to avert DALYs, and that SODIS and
chlorination
are particularly cost-effective options
due to their low cost.
Finally, we saw that in at least one
setting, willingness to pay for different
HWTS options can be quite low even when
the water quality is perceived as being
unsafe.