In weeks two and three of this course, we
looked in
some detail at the processes and
mechanisms involved in different HWTS
technologies.
Each technology has its own strengths and
challenges.
And when HWTS technologies are being
considered or selected,
those should somehow feed into a decision
making process.
Selection of HWTS options can happen at
different levels.
At the household level an individual can
decide
to use or not to use a given technology.
But frequently decisions on technologies
are taken at
a program level or even by central
governments.
And how can these decisions then be made
in a rational way at these different
levels?
Well, the first thing to do is to be able
to say what is wanted.
What are the characteristics of an HWTS
option that are important for selection?
For application of HWTS in a particular
context.
And that involves clearly defining, and
establishing the context both in terms
of the water to be treated but also
all those other factors,
which are outside the control of an
intervention
like the policy environment, existence of
supply chains, etcetera.
Once the context is clear, a selection
among potential
HWTS options can be made by defining
objectives or criteria.
And then there's usual more than one
criteria.
So combining those in some way
and assessing different options against
those
different criteria, and taking a decision.
This can be done in a formal way through a
multiple criteria decision analysis
approach
or informally and even subconsciously.
Selection of an HWTS option is highly
context specific.
Of course, the context includes the
characteristics of the water to be
treated.
An important factor here is whether or not
the water is likely to be turbid.
But also the level of contamination is
important.
Some processes can achieve higher LRV's
than others.
Apart from the water quality,
the way that the water is assessed and
the quantities available and needed can
also influence selection.
Then there are other contextual factors
not related to the
water, such as those described in the IBM
WASH model,
like the wealth and education of the
target population, the
access to markets, supply chains and
information, the policy environment.
And, to these, I would add nature of the
supporting organization.
Because a social business and a profit
oriented business
might choose very different options based
on their differing objectives.
Here are some examples of sets of criteria
that
have been put forward by various groups
working on HWTS.
There are many such examples and I just
selected five here,
that were fairly well documented from
these organizations or research groups.
Let's take a brief look at each of them.
You've seen this WHO training manual by
now, a few times hopefully.
It really contains a lot of useful
material.
And in the section on selecting an HWTS
options,
the authors identify five sets of criteria
shown here.
First, effectiveness.
How effective are the different HWTS
options for
the water to be treated in the given
context?
Next, appropriateness.
These are also
contextual factors,
related to the conditions and desires of
the target populations.
Things like local availability and supply
chains, the amount
of time required for treatment,
requirements for operation and
maintenance.
And the lifetime of the option.
Appropriateness is closely related to
acceptability.
Which the authors takes to include
aesthetic aspects of
the treated water, it's taste, it's smell,
it's color.
But also perceptions of convenience,
health gains,
social status, time and money savings,
etcetera.
Of course, the cost is important,
there are different types of
costs.
Upfront and recurring costs to the
household.
But also costs to the supporting agency,
which
may include subsidies, and an appropriate
business plan.
Finally, implementation is a bit of a
catch-all class of criteria.
It includes things like how the technology
is manufactured and
distributed to the households, how fast
the technology can be implemented.
What kind of monitoring is required for
the technology.
How well it can be integrated with current
government programs, etcetera.
I encourage you to go to the
manual itself for a fuller discussion of
these criteria.
Here's another set of criteria.
This one from Professor Mark Sobsey at the
University of
North Carolina, Chapel Hill, and
colleagues, from a few years back.
They came up with a set of five, sets of
criteria that should be satisfied for HWTS
to be sustainable.
I let you just read them on the screen
and refer to the paper for a more detailed
discussion.
The Netherlands Water Partnership has a
nice brochure on HWTS.
We can download it here.
And, they propose a set of 13 indicators
grouped into
the categories of performance, people, and
planets.
Now, this is a bit different from the
first two in
that this category of planet considers
brings in environmental considerations, as
well.
At EAWAG, I was part of a large project
on mitigation of arsenic and fluoride,
called Water Resource Quality.
Some of you have asked for information
about HWTS for improving chemical water
quality.
And it's a really interesting topic.
But, unfortunately, beyond the scope of
this course.
You can get some good information from the
Water Resource Quality website here.
And one of the journal publications that
came out of this project, that
you can see here, describes a process for
selecting a water treatment option.
Even though the technology in question was
for fluoride removal,
the process could still be useful for
selecting HWTS options.
The author has identified 12 criteria.
Grouped into three broad classes
of Affordability, Acceptability and
Reliability.
One last example now.
This is from the US NGO PATH,
which implemented the safe water project,
that did a lot
of great work about commercialization, of
HWTS in developing countries.
Spend some time at their website, there's
a wealth of information.
In particular, they've established generic
design guidelines for HWTS.
If you ever find yourself building or
designing an
HWTS system, this is a really useful set
of information.
Some of the, highlights of this projects
were
summarized in a special report of PATH's
Perspective magazine.
You can download that here from their
website, definitely worth the read.
As part of the Safe Water Project, one of
the PATH staff, Stephen Himley,
completed his Master's degree in Public
Health in the University of Washington.
And his topic was a very detailed and
rigorous examination
of how to select an HWTS option for a
given context.
He described three main
criteria, acceptability, availability, and
affordability.
And then he broke down acceptability into
six sub-components,
so that there are a total of eight
criteria.
Okay, so there are lots and lots of lists
of criteria out there.
So what?
Again the important thing isn't to decide
which set of criteria is the
best or the most efficient, but to
identify for a particular application of
HWTS.
Which criteria are the most important for
selecting an HWTS
option, and it might not be the same set
everywhere.
I hope that these examples can help you
develop a
set of criteria if you ever find
yourselves in that position.
And if you do, and you come up with a
set of criteria, well, then what do you do
with them?
Well, there are different ways to assess
each
possible HWTS option against the selected criteria.
This can be done in a fairly easy,
non-quantitative way
with landscaping, or through a more
complex and formal optimization process.
A slightly different approach is to use a
decision tree.
Posing a series of sequential questions
that allow
you to narrow down the list of potential
technologies.
Now, here's an example of landscaping.
Again, from the PATH safe water project.
It's their Technology Assessment and
Ranking Tool or TART.
Now please, don't try and read the
text of it.
It's just an example of landscaping.
But it's a table which contains 18
criteria,
or dimensions plotted against 15 different
HWTS systems.
And each of those systems is rated
qualitatively,
good, neutral or bad, for each of the
dimensions.
And then they are colored green, yellow,
or red like the traffic light system.
And in the landscape the different
criteria are not combined or weighted
into an overall score, but everything is
displayed on this one dashboard.
So you can see that a technology like this
one, which is mostly green, or,
maybe, this one with just one red is
probably a better option.
Than this one here, where you see lots of
red or, or maybe this one.
Now, landscaping doesn't select a
particular optimal choice.
And it could be that some of the
criteria up here are more important than
other ones.
And you would need to consider that when
interpreting a landscape matrix.
One way to overcome that problem is to
make more
formal optimization with quantitative
scoring, and weighting of different criteria.
There are different frameworks for this
with different names.
This one here is Multi-Criteria Decision
Analysis.
But, the basic idea is usually something
like this one.
We've talked already about establishing a
decision context.
And of course you have to come up
with a list of potential options for
consideration.
And then we've also talked about
objectives or criteria.
Once you have criteria, you can score each
option each
technology for each of the criteria using
some objective system.
And then weight the criteria so that the
ones that are more important count more.
Then by summing up the weighted stores,
you arrive
at a total score and then look at the
results.
It's also a really good idea to do a
sensitivity analysis.
To see if one particular criterion is
dominating the selection process.
Here is an example of scoring, again,
from, Steven Himley's MPH thesis.
And again, don't try to read the text,
it's just an example that
for each of these eight criteria here
There are rules to assign a score.
For example the top row here is the time
to treat and if the
technology takes more than 20 minutes to
treat water you get a poor score.
Whereas if it takes less than five minutes
it gets an excellent mark.
From that same thesis, here is an example
of weighting.
The three main criteria were assigned
different weights, always summing up to
100%.
For different contexts, urban and rural
lower and low income settings.
So, you can see that affordability is
given the
highest most important weight in a low
income, rural context.
Whereas acceptability is given the
highest
weight in a low income urban context.
And this acceptability criteria, had six
sub criteria, which were
also given different weights for each of
those four contexts.
These weights then could then be combined
with
the scores and presented as a total score.
Here you see total scores for two
scenarios.
On the right you have turbid water, and on
the left, non-turbid water.
You could have a different optimal choice,
depending on the turbidity.
So it looks like in this case chlorine is
a liquid or
tablet ends up being the best option in
all of the scenarios.
Now that might sound funny because
chlorine has problems with turbid water.
And what probably happened is that
technical
effectiveness here is only one of the
criteria.
And apparently didn't have a high enough
weight to overcome
the greater affordability in particular of
chlorine compared to other options.
If you can see, if you look just at the
acceptability scores.
That some of the non-chlorine options do
a little better than chlorine in the
turbid scenarios.
But this example does highlight that a
formal optimization process is tricky.
And can sometimes come up with
recommendations
that might not seem intuitive or correct.
A simpler approach to selection is the
familiar decision tree.
By asking a series of questions, you can
narrow down
the group of potential options appropriate
for a particular context.
Here's a decision tree adapted from that
IFRC report
on HWTS in emergencies, which you saw in
module 4.3.
Here, if the water is muddy, the tree says
that straining, the
3-pot method, coagulation, and
sedimentation or
filtering with frequent cleaning should be
promoted.
And these technologies are all appropriate
for turbid waters.
If the water is not turbid the next
question is,
whether or not HWTS products are available
from outside the community.
If they're not, then you get directed
towards boiling, if fuel is available.
Or three pot methods, sedimentation,
SODIS, and filtration, if fuel isn't.
If HWTS products are available.
Then the tree directs you towards
chlorine.
Either with a normal, or a double dose,
depending on the turbidity.
In all cases, safe water storage and
handling is to be promoted.
So that's one example of a decision tree
for
a particular context, that of HWTS in
emergency response.
It shouldn't be applied universally but it
could be
a good model for developing a context
specific decision tree.
That could be used by decision makers
perhaps
more easily than a full quantitative
optimization process.
So in conclusion, it's not so easy to say
which HWTS option is best
and there is certainly no silver bullet,
no answer to apply in every situation.
The the best solution will
depend on the local context
but also on the criteria that are
considered to be the most important.
And these criteria might be given
different weightings,
particularly if a formal optimization
approach is applied.
But there are also less formal approaches
like landscaping and decision
trees, that can be used to narrow down the
list of options.
In many cases, the goal should not be to
arrive at one single option.
But to narrow down a long list to a short
list.
So that people still have some freedom to
select the
option that works best for them in their
particular household situation.