The biggest threat
to drinking water safety
is microbial contamination
from fecal matter.
Poorly constructed or protected
water sources can become contaminated,
or inadequate sanitation and hygiene
can introduce contamination
after water is collected.
And because pathogens are so small,
contaminated water might smell,
taste, and look perfectly clean.
So the only way to really confirm
if water is contaminated is to do a test,
and traditionally this has involved
using laboratories
with specialized equipment
and trained personnel.
Now, laboratory testing is great,
but it poses some drawbacks.
First of all, distance.
Laboratories might not be located
near to the site
where testing is being done.
And since microbial samples
should be tested within six,
or a maximum of 24 hours after collection,
this has posed a real challenge.
Laboratory testing can also be expensive,
and it can be difficult to get
the results from the laboratory
back to the local authorities.
However, advances, technical advances,
have made field testing
more practical, easy, and cheap.
So some of these new options include
Most Probable Number methods,
where a number
of small compartments are tested,
and a statistical test tells you
the most probable number
of bacteria contaminants.
Also membrane filtration
is increasingly done in the field.
Also, new enzyme growth media
react specifically with certain bacteria,
like E. coli, the preferred indicator
for fecal contamination,
which makes results more robust.
And then, finally, there's a new
generation of low-cost incubators,
that can be done without electricity,
or at least away from
a well-equipped laboratory.
So taking advantage of all these advances,
WHO and UNICEF have developed
a water quality testing module
which can be applied in national surveys,
and this has been done, and piloted,
in a number of multiple-indicator
cluster surveys, or MICS surveys.
The package consists of three elements.
One, a membrane filtration system
made by Millipore, the Microfill system.
Two, growth media,
Nissui Compact Dry EC plates,
and three, portable incubation,
and this is body-belt incubation.
These materials are used
by the MICS field teams
after they go through a basic training.
During the survey,
the teams will ask the respondents
for a glass of water
that they would give a child to drink,
and then they test that water.
In some cases, they also visit the source
where the water was collected,
and test that water
directly at the source.
The way they do the test
is they use a membrane-filtration system
to pass the water
through a special piece of paper
which has small holes in it,
and the holes are large enough
to let water pass through,
but small enough
to trap all of the bacteria
on the paper surface.
That filter paper is then placed
on some growth media
with all the food and water
that the bacteria need to grow,
and left for 24 hours so that
bacteria can grow
and form colonies of billions of cells,
which become visible to the naked eye.
Once the colonies have grown,
they can be counted
and the results can be recorded
and shared with the communities.
In these field tests, the MICS teams
actually test two samples:
a 100 mL test for low contamination,
and a 1 mL test for high contamination,
and this is because if there's
a large number of bacteria in the water
then they can form so many colonies
that it's difficult to read.
So for highly contaminated samples,
a 1 mL sample is the best option.
Now let's look at what
the testing equipment looks like.
The first part of the kit
is a filter instrument, or manifold,
and this one is produced by Millipore,
as part of their Microfill
line of products.
The filter instrument is used
with a filter paper,
and a plastic funnel,
also made by Millipore.
These are sterile and disposable;
you need to use one per sample tested.
We also use a simple plastic syringe
to create a vacuum and filter the sample.
The test requires a number
of small accessories:
forceps to handle the filter paper,
an alcohol wipe to sterilize
the instrument and forceps,
a small plastic syringe
to rehydrate the growth plates,
and a permanent pen
for marking the growth plates.
Finally, you have the growth media.
There are many options available,
but we use an enzyme growth media
produced by Nissui,
called Compact Dry EC Plates.
These come prepackaged
and foil wrapped, in sets of four,
and the nice thing about this packaging
is that the plates can be stored
at room temperature
for up to 18 months.
So, let's see how this test works.
The first step is to get
all of our materials together
and label the two
Compact Dry plates with that pen.
This is a sample of "lake water".
Okay.
I've got a glass of water
I collected earlier from Lake Geneva.
Let's see what's in it.
Next, we have to make sure that
our hands and our equipment are all clean,
and we will use
a simple alcohol wipe to do this,
to sterilize the forceps and the manifold,
and some alcohol sanitizer for the hands.
You could also use soap and water,
if that's more convenient.
So with the alcohol wipe,
first we sterilize the forceps,
and then the part of the manifold
that will touch the filter paper.
Here it's good to use the forceps
to stabilize the manifold.
Okay, then we're going to put down
the forceps on a clean surface
to keep them sterile,
and the next step we're going to do
is take the sterile filter paper.
Now, the Millipore filter paper
comes with a protective blue sheet,
which is not the filter paper,
you don't want to use that,
so what I like to do is first take out
and remove the blue paper,
and then take the white paper,
with the gridded side up,
and place it right on the manifold.
Still need to keep the forceps clean,
but now we're ready
to put the plastic funnel on.
And the plastic funnels are also sterile.
They're kept in these plastic sheaths.
So you just reach in, and take one out,
and put it directly on top
of the filter paper.
There we go.
Now we pour the water
into the plastic funnel,
up to the line on the funnel
that's marked at 100 mL.
A little bit more or less
of the water doesn't matter.
We just want to know
the general level of contamination.
Now we need to rehydrate
these Compact Dry plates.
We'll take the lid off of them,
of the two of them,
and open this 1 mL sterile syringe.
Draw 1 mL of water from the funnel
and place it on each
of the Compact Dry plates.
Now the plates,
they have food for the bacteria,
but the bacteria can't access the food
unless they're rehydrated,
so it's important to add some water.
That's done.
Now for one of these,
the 1 mL test is complete,
and we can put the lid on it.
For the other one, we'll filter
the water through the paper
and put the paper on it.
To do that, we'll use
this 100 mL syringe.
We'll just attach the syringe
to the side of the instrument
and pull it gently
to suck water through the membrane.
Remember, the holes on the membrane
are small enough to trap
all of the bacteria on the paper,
so whatever bacteria were present
in this sample of lake water
are going to be on that filter paper
when we're done filtering it.
It just takes a few minutes.
Okay.
Sometimes you need to remove the syringe
and do two batches,
like we've just done here.
Okay, there we go.
We've got all the water out.
So we remove the plastic funnel.
We're done with this now.
Use the forceps to remove that paper
and put it directly on the growth media.
Now we put the lid back on it
and we're done.
We just have to clean up now,
make sure that we take
all the waste materials,
and throw them away.
In fact, it's a good idea
to have a rubbish bin
when doing the test in the field,
because there's not always
a good, safe place to dispose of wastes.
So now we have bacteria on the plates,
they have food, they have water.
All they need to grow is some warmth,
and a little bit of time.
Now, E. coli will be happiest when
the temperature is around 35-37 degrees,
though they will grow at temperatures
down to 20 degrees,
though it takes a bit longer.
If the temperature gets above 40 degrees,
they don't grow well
on this particular media.
In a laboratory,
you have electrical incubators
that can regulate the temperature
very nicely at the desired temperature,
but for this field testing,
we don't have those,
but there are some newly developed
alternatives that we can use.
The first is to use
an electrical incubator,
but a small, portable one,
like this one
that can run on electricity,
if you have it,
but could also run on batteries
or plug into the cigarette adapter
in an automobile.
So there are different versions of this.
It's a nice option.
(snapping sound)
A second option that's under
development, in the research stage,
is called a Phase Change Incubator,
and this is an example that was developed
at the University of Bristol.
What it does is it's like a thermos,
and you fill this thermos up
with boiling water
and let the water sit for about
half an hour, throw out the water,
and then the thermos retains
the heat from the boiling water,
and if you place plates inside,
and close it,
the incubator will keep the temperature
at about 35 degrees for over 24 hours.
So this is a very nice technique,
that doesn't require
any electricity at all.
But there's another source of heat
available in these surveys,
which we've used in the MICS pilots,
and that's the body heat
of the survey team.
Human bodies are about 37 degrees,
which is a perfect temperature
for incubating,
so the NGO called ENPHO, in Nepal,
has developed a Body-Belt Incubator
to take advantage of that body heat.
This is just a fabric belt,
with some pockets sewn into it.
You can insert the plates
into the pockets,
and then wrap it around the waist,
and voilà!
You become a human incubator.
This has proved very successful
in field trials so far.
There is a fourth option available,
depending on the climate,
which is just to incubate the plates
at ambient temperature,
normal room temperature,
and if you're in a country
where the temperature is above, say,
20, 25, ideally 30 degrees,
that can also be a good option.
Once the samples have been
incubated for 24-48 hours,
we can count the colonies.
Now E. coli bacteria will form
blue colonies on the Compact Dry plates,
and other coliforms, like total coliforms
or thermotolerant coliforms
will produce red or violet colonies.
Here are some examples.
Now, other bacteria
can also grow on the plates,
but they will form colonies
that are white,
or pale yellow, or some other color,
but those are not coliforms or E. coli,
so we're not concerned with those.
Once the colonies have formed,
we can simply count the number of blue
and the number of red or violet colonies,
and record the results.
If the plates have very high levels
of bacteria on them
it's difficult to see individual colonies,
and you can have plates
that are overloaded,
which look completely pink
or completely blue.
Once the results are recorded
they should be shared with
the local authorities, or communities,
and then the plates
should be disposed of safely,
which means that
they should be disinfected
using either chlorine or heat,
and then disposed of.
Well, let's look at some of those results.
The first sample I showed you
was lake water from Lake Geneva.
You can see that this water actually
has quite a lot of bacteria in it,
a lot of those red and violet colonies,
more than 100,
and when it's above 100,
we don't even bother counting anymore.
But it's only got about one of those
blue colonies, which means E. coli.
Now, a second sample that I tested
was taken from a toilet,
and in this water we see
that there are lots and lots
of those blue colonies, E. coli,
more than 100 of them
in the 100 mL sample,
but none at all of those other coliforms,
and that makes sense,
because the toilet water
is full of fecal bacteria.
Once the data are recorded,
they can be analyzed and presented
but it's important to know
that the data are of good quality,
so we have some consistency
and quality control checks
that should be applied.
A consistency check
is comparing the results
from the 100 mL test
against the 1 mL test.
Now, of course,
the 100 mL test should have
about 100 times as many bacteria
as the 1 mL test,
so if that ratio is very different,
there might be a problem.
It's also good practice
to have some blank samples
to make sure that people
are getting zero counts
when the water is known to be
free from contamination,
and it's quite valuable to have
expert teams visit the field teams
as they're doing the field work,
to make sure that
they're doing the test correctly.
Once the quality of the data
is assured, though,
then we can classify the results
into risk classes,
and normally we look at E. coli
as meeting regulatory guidelines,
1-10, 11-100,
and 100+ colonies
representing increasingly dangerous
or high-risk samples.
The MICS team has developed
standard tables and scripts
for the statistical software
that analyzes the data,
to make it easier for countries
to standardize their analysis,
and then the results can be presented
either in a standard summary report
with the rest of the information
collected in the MICS survey,
or in a special focused thematic report
that can go into more detail
about the water quality testing results.
So, we've seen a demonstration
of a testing package for E. coli
that's easy to implement in the field
without need for electricity,
laboratory facilities,
or highly-trained technicians.
By relying on pre-packaged materials,
the system reduces the opportunities
for contamination to be introduced,
though it's still important to include
quality control and assurance measures
like regular testing of blanks.
The system is not very expensive,
and especially when it can
be linked to an ongoing,
and already financed, field program,
the data collection
can be very cost-effective.
This system has been applied in MICS
and other national household surveys,
but could also be useful
for general programmatic use.
As an example, in Bangladesh,
after this system was used
in a MICS survey,
the UNICEF office used the materials
to do water quality testing
of water supplies that had been installed
in their program areas.
Of course, we need to remember
that a single measure of E. coli
is not a robust measure of water safety.
For that you would want
water safety plans,
or at least sanitary inspections,
but for getting a rapid assessment
of drinking water quality
or for monitoring an intervention,
like a household
water treatment intervention,
even a limited amount of microbial testing
can be very helpful
and can help identify problems
and direct resources
towards improvements.