Congratulations!
You've made it to the end of the course.
Hopefully Sara and I have encouraged you
to think critically
about drinking water treatment issues
in developing countries.
And if you've enjoyed these lectures
please consider signing up
for Sandec's MOOCs series
dedicated to WASH in Developing Countries.
The second course in the series
is dedicated to strategic
environmental sanitation planning,
taught by Dr. Christoph Lüthi.
The third Sandec MOOC is focused
on Solid Waste Management
in Developing Countries,
taught by Dr. Christian Zurbrügg.
The final course led by Dr. Linda Strande
is on Faecal Sludge Management.
You can find each of these Sandec MOOCs
on the course web page periodically.
Lectures will also be hosted on Youtube
through Sandec e-Learning web page.
You can find e-Learning link at sandec.ch
In this MOOC on HWTS
we started off with the "why",
or why treat water
at the household level,
covering how drinking water
can be contaminated,
what some of the main pathogens are,
and what the resulting impacts
can be on human health,
especially relating to diarrheal disease.
You should now have some familiarity
with the global burden of disease
and know where to get estimates
about deaths and DALYs
from a number of sources.
We then moved to the "what",
to see what processes and mechanisms
are involved in HWTS
and how effective these are at removing
different types of pathogens.
After these two modules you should have
a good appreciation of the strengths,
as well as the limitations
of different HWTS options.
The last few weeks
have been more about "how".
How can HWTS be effectively
implemented in the field?
Either through a profit-oriented approach
or more of a public health approach
aiming to reduce disease.
We gave examples of focused interventions
targeting particularly
vulnerable populations
and considered the different roles
that governments can play in HWTS.
We ended with the discussion
of Monitoring and Evaluation,
including both validation of technologies
and monitoring of HWTS interventions
and health impacts.
Throughout we've only scratched the
surface of the subjects covered
and we've tried to provide links
to more detailed documents and resources,
wherever possible,
especially those that are
freely available on the Internet.
If there has been
one theme through the course,
it is that no single HWTS option
can solve the problems
of unsafe drinking water.
In fact, HWTS should be seen
as a short term measure
to reduce health risks
until safe, sustainable
drinking water is available
at the household level for everyone.
Until that time different HWTS options
can play important roles
depending on the local conditions.
I'd like to thank
my guest lecturers,
Maggie Montgomery from the WHO,
Danielle Lantange at Tufts University,
Heiko Gebauer and Caroline Saul from Eawag
and Sophie Boisson from the London
School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine.
If you are following the forums,
you got to virtually meet Fabian Suter
and the rest of the supporting team.
They really did an excellent job
fielding questions,
arranging lectures,
and providing translations,
and, of course, we had great
technical assistance
from the teams at EPFL and Coursera.
Finally we would like
to thank you all, the participants,
and especially the hundreds of people
who contributed to the conversations
on the online forum.
So best of luck with that final exam,
and we hope to see you again
in the next MOOC series.
- Good bye.
- Bye.
Oh, that was good.
Can I get you a drink, Sara?
- Maybe a...
- Water would be great.
- A glass of water.
- Thank you.
- Cheers!