In this first part
I will introduce the various notions
of interest rates and related contracts.
Starting from the basic definition
of interest paid on a loan
we derive simple and continuously
compounded rates,
also called LIBOR, and yield.
They depend on the length of the
lending period
and at the short hand coincide
and are equal to the so called
short rate.
Investing and continuously
reinvesting at the short rate
gives us the money market account
and we will see that
this is a risk free asset.
In turn, the zero coupon bond
is the securitized form of a loan.
And they can be used to discount
future cash flows
which is why they are also
called discount bonds.
Interest refers to the rent paid
by a borrower of money
to a lender of money
over a period of time.
Here we have a period of time.
It starts at calendar date t,
and it ends at the maturity date T.
The lender will pay a loan of 1
unit of currency to the borrower.
And the borrower in turn will pay
back this principal amount
plus interest at the maturity T.
Interest is expressed in annualized
interest rates.
With simple compounding, we arrive
at a simple rate
that we call L.
Which is defined
by this equation here
which simply states that L is
the interest R
divided by the length of the lending
period.
There's also a continuously
compounded version
which is also called the yield
and we label it by the letter y.
And is defined
by this equation here.
Here is a market example,
the LIBOR.
LIBOR stands for London InterBank
Offered Rate.
This is the rate at which high credit
financial institutions can borrow
on the London InterBank
money market.
This rate however
has become an important reference
rate for many interest rate contracts
beyond the London InterBank money
market.
It is quoted daily as a simple rate
and this is why
I choose the letter L
to denote the simple rate.
And it is quoted for various
maturities
ranging from 1 day to 1 year,
and it is quoted
for various currencies.
Interest rates depend on the lending
period
this is why we also use the argument
t and T
when we notate for simple and
continuously compounded rates.
If we freeze the current calendar
date t
and we vary the maturity T.
We obtain what is called the term
structure of interest rates
prevailing at t.
We see the curve here in black
the simple interest rate.
And in red, we see the term
structure of yields
which we also call the yield curve.
It is a mathematical fact that
for the same interest,
the simple rate is larger
than the yield.
While at the short end
both curves coincide
and we will see later this is what
we call the short rate.
If we vary the calendar
date t
we obtain a time series
of terms structures
that is plotted in this graph
overhear.
So what we saw on the previous
slide
was a snapshot for a given
calendar date t,
we saw the term structure
of interest rates.
It is clear as calendar time
proceeds, economic conditions
change
and this term structure
will fluctuate.
As you can see from this plot,
which is taken from empirical data.
These fluctuations of
the term structures are manifold.
Modeling this time series,
is the aim of this course
on interest rate models.
Such models are useful then
for financial risk management and
pricing interest rate derivatives
in a consistent and arbitrage free
way.
Here I come back to what we saw
on the previous slide
with term structure of interest rate
and the yield curve.
They both coincide
at the short end.
This common short end is called
the short rate.
The short rate is the rate earned
on a loan over the short period
[ t, t + dt ].
Investing 1 unit of currency
at the short rate, and continuously
reinvesting it
at the short rate
gives the money market account.
The return on the money market
account
over the period B(t + dt)
is given by 1 + r(t) dt.
with the initial normalization, this
equation is equivalent
to this expression here.
So what we see on the plot
on the right hand side
is, for a given trajectory
of the short rate
evolving over time.
We have it on that scale here.
The red line shows us how the money
market evolves.
At each time
the rate of return on this money
market account
is given by the respective
short rate.
The money market account
is a risk free asset.
Risk free in the sense that,
it's return
over a time interval
is known at the beginning
of the time interval.
This is very much in difference
to risky assets
where the return is only known
at the end of the time period.
And where mathematically we would
have to add
a noise term here.
A zero coupon bond with
maturity T
is a contract that pays its
holder 1 unit of currency
at the maturity.
This zero coupon bond with
maturity T
for short is also called
a T-bond.
Its price at time t
is denoted by
P(T, t).
A zero coupon bond is the
securitized
that is, tradable form of a loan.
It is related to a loan
in the following sense.
At t,
the lender buys a zero coupon bond
from the borrower.
and pays the price P.
At the maturity T,
the lender receives 1 from
the borrower.
Buying a T-bond at time t
and holding it until maturity
generates a simple rate
of return
which is given by the simple rate L.
Formally speaking,
the zero coupon bond price is
related to the simple rate
by this equation.
Buying a T-bond and
holding it until maturity
generates a logarithmic rate
of return
which is given by the yield.
Again this is expressed by
this relation down here.
A zero coupon bond. is also
called a discount bond.
P is the price
at calendar time t.
over cash flow of 1 at maturity T.
Now for varying maturities T
we obtain the term structure
of zero coupon bond prices
prevailing at t.
This is also called
the discount curve.
This discount curve is typically
decreasing and smooth.
It reflects a positive time value
of money.
At the short end.
The discount curve equals 1
because the cash flow of 1
at calendar date t
has value 1 at T.
In reality, interest rates depend
on various factors.
They can depend on the credit
worthiness of the borrower.
The less credit worthy the borrower,
the more the lender will charge
for a loan.
They also depend on the
liquidity needs of the lender.
The more liquidity the lender needs,
the more the lender will charge
for a loan.
Interest rates also depend on
regulatory requirements
and the monetary policy
by the central banks.
And interest rates also depend on
the market micro structure.
Various interest rate contracts
are traded on various markets.
And these markets are not always
perfectly integrated.
In theory however,
for this course
we will assume that
there is no credit risk;
which means buying a bond
will give the holder of the bond
the face value at the end
of the maturity.
And we also assume that there exists
a frictionless market.
where all T-bonds for all maturities
are traded.