In this part
we will now introduce forward
rate agreements
and interest rate futures.
Both contracts allow you to lock in
rates today, for loans
on future time intervals.
The rate that you lock in today
is what is called forward rate.
In case of
the forward rate agreement
and in case of
the interest rate futures
it is called the futures rate.
We will relate futures rates
and forward rates.
Forward rate agreement FRA
at calendar date t is specified
by a future period (T-0, T-1),
with lengths that we denote by δ,
a fixed rate K,
and a notional N.
At T-1
the holder of the forward rate
agreement
pays a fixed rate K
on the notional,
and in turn receives
the floating rate on the notional.
This is called floating because
this rate
is only known at the future
time point T-0.
This forward rate agreement allows
you to lock in a fixed rate
today
over the future period (T-0, T-1).
Suppose you know you are
going to take a loan
with notional N
at time T-0)
According to the then prevailing
market conditions
you would have to pay back
the loan
along with the simple rate
L(T-0, T-1).
Suppose you dislike
the uncertainty of this interest
cash flow today
and instead you want to lock in
a rate K
that is fixed today which
you are going to pay on this loan.
Holding this forward rate agreement
does exactly that.
Remember that you will have to pay
the fixed rate K
and you will receive the floating.
As you now can see,
the floating payments
simply cancel off.
And what you are in fact paying
is the fixed rate K.
Of course the question arises,
as to what is a fair fixed rate K
that you will fix today
given the market information
that is
all the zero coupon
bond prices at t.
To answer this question
we now compute the value
of this forward rate agreement
and set it equal to 0.
We start by the pay off of the
forward rate agreement at T-1.
Remember it is given by the difference
of the floating rate payments
minus the fixed rate payment
on the notional N.
We now re-express this simple rate
in terms of
the T-1 bond price at T-0.
We will then call this
I-1
minus I-2
and we will value these components
I-1 and I-2
separately using discount bonds.
I-1
is a cash flow
that we do not know today at time t
but we know it at time T-0.
Hence the value of this cash flow
I-1 at time T-1
at time T-0 is given by simply
multiplying it with the T-1 bond price.
But since I-1 is the reciprocal
of the T-1 bond price
we get as value at time T-0, 1.
So that the time t value
is the T-0 bond price.
At the time t value of I-2,
we get even simpler because this is
a cash flow that we know at time t.
Hence it's time t value
is simply given by
multiplying it with the T-1 bond.
This is what we get.
So the total time t value of the
forward rate agreement therefore is
given by the difference of these
2 expressions
that we have here on the right
hand side, and be called
the value V-FRA.
So we see
that the value
of the forward rate agreement
depends on the choice
of the fixed rate K.
The larger K is,
the smaller the value.
It can even be negative
from the point of view of the holder
of the forward rate agreement.
But of course there is a counter
party to the forward rate agreement.
And for the counter party, the value
will just have the opposite sign.
So it's a reasonable choice
to choose K the fixed rate
such that the value is 0.
Simple algebra shows that the rate K
which renders this value equal to 0
is given by this expression here.
We call it the simple forward rate
prevailing at time t.
When the time t coincides with the
initial date T-0 of the loan period
we get back the simple rate L.
Which we now sometimes also call
simple spot rate
just to highlight the difference
to the forward rate.
It's further an easy exercise to see
that we can re-express
The time t value of the forward rate
agreement in terms of the forward rate
as follows.
Now this expression nicely
shows again
that there is a fair choice
of the fixed rate K
namely the forward rate
which renders this value of
the forward rate agreement 0.
If K is chosen too large
the value will become negative.
If K is chosen too small
the value becomes positive.
Now think of the following situation
that K is yesterday's forward rate.
Now yesterday's forward rate
in general
will be different from
today's forward rate.
That means if you entered a forward
rate agreement yesterday,
yesterday's prevailing forward rate
seen from today's point of view
the value may have become non zero.
It may have become positive
incase
the interest rate went up.
But it may also have become
negative
in case the interest rate
had gone down.
If we let the length of the
lending period
converge at 0,
that is, if we let T-1 converge
at T-0
in the limit, we obtain what we call
the instantaneous forward rate
with maturity T-0.
Elementary calculus shows you
that this limit is given by
minus the logarithmic
derivative of the T bond price
with respect to maturity.
Because the terminal value
of the T bod is 1,
this relation is equivalent
to this formula.
The nice thing about instantaneous
forward rates is that
knowing all the instantaneous
forward rates is equivalent
to knowing all the
T-bond prices.
As before, for varying maturities
we obtain a term structure of rates.
In this case, it's the term structure
of forward rates prevailing
at calendar date t.
This is also called the
forward curve.
It's easy to see that forward
rates are related to yields.
In this way
that means that
the yield is the time average
of forward rates.
It also follows from this relation
that the short ends of
the forward curve
and of the yield curve coincide
and are equal to the short rate.
Similar to a forward rate agreement,
an interest rate futures contract
allows the management
of exposure
to the futures spot interest rate
prevailing over a future period
(T-0, T-1).
In contrast to forward rate
agreements however
interest rate futures are daily
marked to market
or resettled.
To understand what this means
recall that the value of a forward
rate agreement
may change in time.
At time t when you enter the forward
rate agreement,
you will do it typically at conditions
which render its value equal to 0.
But already the next day,
economic conditions may have changed.
And the value of the forward rate
agreement
turns out to your favor
to become positive.
This value may of course
also become negative.
Eventually, it will converge
to the pay off of the
forward rate agreement.
Now instead of sitting, and waiting,
and seeing the exposure
to your counter party
getting a positive value
or negative value;
market participants prefer
to settle any change in value
immediately.
This is done by
marking to market.
In this example it would mean
on the day after today
you would settle
this increase of value
by receiving a cash flow from
your counter party.
Making the exposure to your counter
party again 0.
While the next day
you may have to return
a part of that
to your counter party and so on
and so forth.
Formally, the marking to market of
interest rate futures contracts
works as follows.
At any calendar date t
a so called futures price
is quoted.
This futures price is related
to the futures rate in this way.
This expression looks different than
the value of a forward rate agreement
but in fact, it reacts the same way
to change
in interest rate environment.
The day after today
one determines the futures price
And the difference of the futures
price
on ( t + Δt)
minus the futures price from
yesterday
is the cash flow to the holder
of the futures contract.
Recall this cash flow can be
positive or negative.
Futures rate here is chosen
such that the following
2 conditions hold.
At the settlement date,
or delivery date
of the futures contract T-0.
The futures rate equals the
underlined spot rate.
At any earlier date
the present value of the cash flow
in the future, from holding
the futures contract
has to be equal to 0.
These rules fix the futures rate.
But there is no direct functional
relationship
between futures rates and
zero coupon bonds
as is the case for forward rates.
As a consequence, futures rates
are generally different from
forward rates.
The difference between futures rates
and minus forward rates
is called convexity adjustment.
This difference is typically
positive.
As a market example, I mentioned
here the Eurodollar futures contract
which is tied to the LIBOR.
It was introduced by the Chicago
Mercantile Exchange in 1981
and has been traded since then
on that exchange.
It is designed to protect the owner
from fluctuations
in future 3-month LIBOR rates.
These futures contracts are highly
standardized.
Their settlement or delivery months
are in March, June, September
and December.
This is in contrast to
forward rate agreements
which are traded over the counter.