Bonds with maturity beyond a year
typically pay coupons.
In case these coupons are fixed
we speak of fixed coupon bonds.
In case these coupons are floating
we speak of floating rate notes.
An interest rate swap
exchanges the cash flows,
of fixed coupon bonds
and a floating rate note.
A fixed coupon bond
or simply coupon bond
is specified by coupon dates
T1, T2 up to Tn
where Tn is also called the maturity
of the bond.
It is also specified
by fixed coupon payments,
C1, C2, and so on...
and so on...
Being paid at the coupon dates,
Ti and the bonds also comes
with a principal value N
that is paid at the maturity.
Given what we know about
discount bonds,
we can now determine
the price
of these coupon bonds
at a calendar date "t".
It is given by multiplying
these cash flows
by the respective discount bond
and summing up.
We follow here the convention, that
if the calendar date T
coincides with one
of the coupon dates,
then the coupon itself is not
full part of the price anymore.
In other words the price
is ex-dividend.
A floating rate note is specified
by a sequence
reset and settlement dates
Tnot, T1 up to Tn.
Where again, Tn is the maturity
of the note.
While Tnot is the first
reset date.
Again, the principal is paid
at the maturity.
The coupon payments
now are floating.
That means (INAUDIBLE) T1,
there is a coupon paid
which is fixed at Tnot
The same at T2, there is a coupon
paid which is fixed at T1.
So on and so forth.
Until the last coupon
has been paid.
So, notice that at Tnot
there is not cash flow,
Tnot is simply a reset date.
The price of the floating
rate note,
at any calendar date small "t"
prior to Tnot,
is surprisingly simple.
It is given by the Tnot bond price
times the principal N.
We proof this price formula
by constructing
a self-financing strategy,
Which has the initial cost
equal to the price,
and which yields the same
cash flow as the floating rate note.
Absence of arbitrage, that implies
that this initial cost<
must indeed be equal to the price.
The initial cost is
N x Tnot bond price.
With this amount of money
we can buy N Tnot bonds.
We hold them until Tnot,
and each of the bonds wil pay us
one unit of currency.
So, in total we get N
We then use this amount
and invest it in T1 bonds
How many can we buy?
Well, the amount is given by
the money we have
divided by the price
of a T1 bond.
So we pay N
At the time, T1
this T1 bonds
mature and for each
of the bonds we receive one.
We hold that many bonds
so we receive this amount of money.
Which we can write as
sum of the floating coupon,
plus the notional.
So we get the notional,
and we get the floating coupon.
Now we repeat
and use the money.
N units of currency
and buy T2 bonds
Called into the scheme,
this leads us
Two sequence of cash flows,
where notional income
cancels notional payment,
until the maturity.
Where we receive the notional
plus the last floating coupon.
Now you see that the netcare
flows of these strategies,
is exactly matching the cash
flows of the floating rate note,
and that proves that
the initial cost of this strategy
is indeed equal to the price
that we saw on the previous slide.
When T is equal to the first
reset date,
the price of the floating rate note
is simply equal to the notional.
So we can state inverts
that paying the floating coupon
Ci at the coupon dates Ti
and the principal N
at the maturity Tn is
equivalent to paying
the principal N at
the first reset date Tnot.
Now suppose you have issued
a floating rate note
so that you have to pay
floating rates.
But you would like to pay
fixed rates instead.
Then you can enter an interest
rate swap.
An interest rate swap exchanges
fixed and floating coupon payments.
Formally a payer interest rate swap
settles in the rears,
is specified by a sequence of
reset and settlment dates
Tnot up to Tn as we have seen
for the floating rate note,
Tnot is the first reset date
Tn is the maturity,
and Tn minus Tnot is called
the length of the swap.
Further ingredient is a fixed rate K,
a notional N,
and for simplicity here, we assume
that these time points
are equally distant
with constant difference Delta
The holder of this payer
interest rates swap,
will pay a fixed rate K
at the payment dates T1,
T2 up to TN,
and in turn receives the floating
rates on there dates.
The net cash flows are exactly
the same as you would get
from holding a floating rate note,
and being short a fixed
coupon bond, so the value
of the payer interest rates swap
at date small "t"
is given by the difference
of the value of the floating rate note,
minus the value
of the coupon bond.
Is an easy exercise using
the definition of forward rates
expressed in terms
of cero coupn bonds
to show that this can be
rewritten in this form.
Notice that when N is one
that is when there is only
one cash flow date,
this is exactly the same
as a forward rate agreement.
Now, the value of a receiver
interest rate swap,
it is just the counter part disposition
to a payer interest rate swap.
Is as given by negative of the value
of the payer interest rates swap.
Now again there is a unique
fixed rate K,
which makes the value of the payer
and receiver interest rate swaps
equal to cero.
This fixed rate is called
The Swap Rate.
Prevailing at co-lender date T.
Now if T is strictly smaller
than Tnot,
we speak of forward swap rate.
If T is equal to Tnot, we speak
of the spot swap rate.
In either case, the expression
is given by this formula.
I leave it as an exercise to you.
To derive these equivalent
alternative expression,
with weight W high.
Another simple exercise for you
is to proof this Lemma
Which states that a coupon bond
has par value at Tnot.
If and only these coupon rates
are equal
to the corresponding swap rate.
Formally speaking, this identity.
Interest rate swaps trade
from different starting dates Tnot.
And for various lengths,
this tamble gives an example
of market quotes for swap rates.
These are Euro swap rates,
expressed in percentage points,
from end of August 2013.
The Euros zone swap
pay annual coupons
that is Delta is 1.
We see here in the first column,
the spot swap rates as function
of the length of the swap.
We get the term structure
of swap rates.
Similarly, we get the term
structure of swap rates,
for swaps starting
in one year from now.
And so on and so forth.
Now, interest rates swap markets
are over the counter.
They are not exchanged traded.
But the swap contracts exist
in stand that is form.
For example, by the International
Swaps and Deivatives Association.
Swap markets, therefore
are extremely liquid,
and the outstading notional
is very large.
Tha maturiries or the length
of the swap,
range from 1 to 30 years,
which is standard,
and quotes of sweap rates
are even available up to 60 years.
Member swaps give
market participants
such as institutional investors,
as life insurers.
The opportunity to creat synthetically
long dated investments.