When it comes to the risk management
of bond portfolio
duration and convexity
are the basic measures.
Duration and convexity are the first
and second order
sensitivity measures of bond prices
with respect
to parallel shifts
of the yield curve.
So let's consider
a fixed coupon bond
with cash flow dates T1,
T2 up to Tn.
So with maturity Tn,
and let's assume that the cash flows
at Ti are also containing
the principle at maturity
just for the sake of notation.
To further simplify the notation,
we assume that small t
now is zero,
so that we don't have
to write Ti minus small t
all the time,
and we also abbreviate
the Ti yield just by the letter yi.
So then we have seen
and we have learned that the price,
at time zero of this bond
is given by the sum
of the discounted cash flow Ci.
The question we're going
to study now,
how does this price change?
The duration of the bond is defined
as the relative
first-order sensitivity
with respect a parallel shift
of the yield curve.
Formally speaking, let s denote
the parallel shift
then, we differentiate the price
of the bond as a function of s
with respect to S
at S equal to zero
We divide it by the current prize
and we take a minus sign in font
by convention in order
to get a positive expression.
From that expression,
we can also see that the duration
is a weighted average
of the coupon payment dates
Ti up to Tn.
In other words,
the duration of zero coupon bond
with maturity T,
is simply given by T.
We thus obtain
the first-order approximation
for relative bond prize changes
with respect to a parallel shift
delta y of the yield curve.
As an example, assume that
the yield curve is flat 3%
and consider a bond
with maturity in 10 years
and annual coupon payments of 6%
on the principle of 100.
It's price is 125.14
to duration plugging in the formula,
you can compute
is given by 8.06.
As a second example, we're again
assume the U-curve is flat 3%
and we consider
a five year maturing bond
with annual coupons of 3%
on the principle of 100.
Again, it is an easy exercise
to compute the price
and the duration.
Now let's apply the duration
to immunize the value
of the bond portfolio with respect
to small parallel shifts
of the yield curve.
So let us by pie of s,
the value of a portfolio
to be hedged as a function
of the yield shift s.
Let H(s) denote the value
of the hedging instrument
as function of s.
Now immunization,
with respect to small parallel shift
of the yield curve then means
we want to find q, the number
of hedging instrument
we want to hold, such that
the hedge portfolio
is first-order immune
against parallel shifts
of the yield curve.
Now the solution is given by
this expression
which again is given in terms
with the duration
of the portfolio to be hedged
and the duration
of the hedging instrument.
Let's look at an example and let's
revisit the examples 1 and 2
from the bond duration.
Let's immunize a long position
in one 10 year bond
with 6% coupons
by holding q units
of the 5 year bong with 3% coupon.
Given what we have seen
on the previous slide,
the solution is given by - 2.14.
This means that one should short
2.14 units of the 5 year bonds
in order to hedge one long unit
of the 10 year bond.
This figure shows us the performance
of this hedge.
The red line is the value change
of the immunized portfolio
as a function of the yield shift s.
In other words,
when there is no yield shift
the value change is zero,
and as we can see from this figure,
no matter whether the yield  curve
shifts up or down
the value change is positive.
In this case, that's a good hedge.
The convexity of the bond
is defined  as a relative
second-order sensitivity
with respect
to a parallel shift
of the yield curve.
Formally speaking,
here is the bond price
as function of
the yield curve shift s.
We take the second-order derivative
at s equal zero
and we divide
by the current price p.
This is what we get.
With the convexity and the duration,
we obtain a second-order
approximation for relative
bond price changes
with respect to a parallel shift
of the yield curve.
Now combining duration and convexity
we can immunize
the value of a bond portfolio
with respect to small
and not so small parallel shifts
of the yield curve.
Let's again consider a portfolio
with value pie s
as function of the yield shift s.
Now let's consider
two hedging instruments.
The fist one having value H1 of s
and the second one, H2 of s.
We want to find q1 and q2
such that the portfolio
consisting of the original portfolio
plus q1 units
of the first hedging instruments
plus q2 units
of the second hedging instrument
is having a zero
first-order sensitivity
with respect to parallel shifts
and a zero second-order sensitivity
with respect to parallel shifts.
The above system
can be equivalently expressed
as a linear system in terms
of the duration and the convexity
of the original portfolio
and the hedging instruments,
along with their initial prices.
This is  a simple linear
2 by 2 system to solution
as given by inverting
the 2 by 2 matrix
as shown on that line.
D pie denotes the duration of pie,
C pie denotes convexity of pie,
and similarly DHi and CHi
denote the duration and convexity
of the hedging instrument Hi.
As a numerical example,
we consider a portfolio
with price 32, 863.5,
duration 6.76 and convexity 85.329.
Along with this portfolio
we consider 2 hedging instruments
with price duration
and complexity data given here.
This data is enough
to find the positions
in the hedging instruments q1 and q2
such that the hedged portfolio
is immunized
to parallel shifts
of the yield curve.
The solution is you should buy
140.3 units
of the second hedging instruments
and sell short 304.8 units
of the 1st hedging instruments.