Whenever you work with market data
you have to take into account the conventions
that come along with them.
There are quite many of them and
they have to be checked case by case.
In this course, I will focus on
2 particular ones.
First is the day-count convention.
How do we measure time
between 2 calendar dates?
And the second one is about
clean and dirty prices,
and accrued interest.
And that addresses the issue that
at the coupon payments, you have
systematic price jumps of coupon bonds.
By convention, we measure the time
in units of years.
But what is the time Δ
in units of years between say,
the calendar dates
4th of January, 2000 and the
4th of July, 2002.
The market in fact evaluates the year
fraction between the calendar dates
t and T in different ways.
These are the day count conventions.
Here are some of the most popular
day count conventions.
Actual over 365.
Here the year has 365 days and
the year fraction is given by the
actual number of days
between the calendar dates t and T
divided by 365.
Another convention is actual
over 360.
It's as above but the year
counts 360 days.
Then there is the
30 over 360 convention.
Here every month counts 30 days
and years count 360 days.
That is, formally speaking,
for calendar dates t
which is day 1, month 1, year 1
and T which is day 2, month 2,
year 2.
We have to cap the 31st
of the months
otherwise we divide the difference
of months by 12
and the difference of the years
they counted 14.
It is best to look at an example and
resume the calendar dates
the 4th of January, 2000
and the 4th of July 2002.
The time between these 2 dates
amounts to 2.5
in the 30 over 360 convention
And then the actual over 365
convention
the time amounts to 2.4986.
Note that while this may look
like a tiny difference,
remember that the outstanding
notional
in this interest rate contract
is huge.
So even a 2nd digit difference
in the day count convention
can translate
into thousands of units
of currency.
Recall that the coupon bond
price is given
as X dividend cost.
That means
there are systematic discontinuities
of the bond price trajectory
at the coupon payment dates.
For illustration, look at
this stylized example
of a bond with maturity of 5 years,
annual coupons of 5 percent
on the principle of 100.
The price of the bond typically
increases towards the first
coupon payment
and then is suddenly reduced
by the payment of 5.
And then again increases
to the next coupon payment,
jumps down by 5 and so on
and so forth
until you arrive at
the principle 100.
In order to remedy these price
trajectory jumps
you compute what is called the
accrued interest on the coupon C-i.
It is given by this following
pro rata formula.
If we subtract the accrued interest
from the X dividend bond price
we arrive at what we call
the clean price.
The clean price in our
stylized example
will have a smooth trajectory
bringing us down to the principle
of 100.
Dirty price in turn is what we call
X dividend bond price
which in terms of the clean price is
given by adding the accrued interest.
The clean price is sometimes
what is quoted.
In any case, the dirty price is
definitely what you will have to pay.