Welcome to the M.O.O.C on
interest rate models.
I'm Damir Filipovic, and I will
be your professor for this course.
A component that is common
to various financial products
and transactions,
is the interest rate.
Interest is the rent paid
for a loan of money
over a period of time.
Interest exists because an amount
of money has a different value
at different times.
Interest accounts
for these value changes.
Interest is the time value of money.
Interest rates themselves
change over time
because the economy changes.
Future interest rates
are as uncertain
as the future state
of the economy is.
Stochastic models for the evolution
of interest rates
are an important ingredient
for financial risk management
and the pricing
of interest rate products.
The volume of such products indeed
is huge.
The outstanding notional amount
is in the order of
hundreds of trillions
of U.S dollars currently.
This course gives you an introduction
to stochastic interest rate models.
It consists of the 4 parts
as shown here.
And I will now briefly comment
on each part separately.
In the first part, I introduce
the notion of interest rates
and some related basic contracts.
A bond is the securitized, that is,
tradable form of a loan.
There exist coupon paying bonds
and zero coupon bonds.
The latter, are also called
discount bonds.
The price of a discount bond
is simply
the present value of a cash flow,
of one unit of currency
at some future maturity date.
Interest rates and bond prices
depend on their maturity.
The term structure, is the function
that maps the maturity
to the corresponding interest rate,
or bond price.
An important reference rate for many
interest rate contracts is The L.I.B.O.R.
The London Inter-Bank Offered Rate.
It is daily fixed for various
currencies and maturities.
Loans can also be borrowed
over future time intervals
at rates that are agreed upon today.
These rates are called Forward
or Futures rates
depending on the type
of the agreement.
In an interest rate swap,
counter parties exchange
a stream of fixed rate payments
for a stream of floating rate
payments.
Typically indexed to L.I.B.O.R
of a particular maturity.
When it comes to managing
the interest rate risk
of a bond portfolio, Duration and
Convexity are the basic tools.
We will also review some of the most
common market conventions
that come along with interest rate
market data.
In the second part, we will learn
how to estimate
the term structure for market data.
There are 2 types of methods.
Exact methods produce term structures
that exactly match the market data.
This comes at a cost of somewhat
irregular shapes of the term structure.
Smooth methods penalize
irregualar shapes
and trade off exactness of fit versus
regularity of the term structure.
We will also see what Principal
Component Analysis tells us
about the basic shapes
of the term structure.
Models for the evolution of the term
structure of interest rates
build on stochastic calculus.
In the third part, I will give a
crash course in stochastic calculus.
I will introduce Brownian motion,
stochastic integration and processes,
but without going into
mathematical details.
The good news is that this
will give you the necessary tools
to engineer a large variety
of stochastic interest rate models.
We will then study some
of the most prevalent
so called, Short rate models,
and Heath-Jarrow-Morton models.
I will also review the arbitrage
pricing theorem from finance.
That provides the foundation for
pricing financial derivatives.
Eventually, we will see
how we can use these models
to price options on bonds.
In the fourth part, we will then
apply what we learned
to price interest rate derivatives.
Specifically, we will focus on the
standard derivatives,
interest rate futures, caps
and floors, and swaptions.
We will see and understand
the industry standard
Black and Bachelier formulas
for cap, floor, and swaption prices.
And eventually in a case study
we will see how to calibrate
a stochastic interest rate model
to market data.