Hello. Welcome to this chapter
entitled what is poverty?
Of course, this is a bit
of a provocative question,
and we have to humbly admit
that there is no chance
we could give a “good” answer
in the sense of inclusiveness
and generality.
There is an incredible wealth
of literature on this subject,
so it is a great challenge
to give any kind of answer
in one or two short videos.
Nevertheless, we will try to
give you some basic knowledge
on poverty and how it is measured.
First let’s emphasize one
of the very few facts
on which there is a general
agreement:
Poverty is a very complex and
multi-dimensional problem.
It goes well beyond just material
or monetary aspects.
Let us look at a few so called
determinants of poverty,
meaning conditions that
cause poverty,
or at least are related to poverty.
Let’s look at these determinants
from three angles:
1) at the macro or regional level,
2) at the community level
and 3) at the level of
the households.
At the Macro level,
determinants of poverty
are of course very country specific.
Commonly cited determinants
are Geographic isolation,
which refers for example to
island states or countries
which are landlocked with no access
to sea trading routes.
Having no access to natural
resources can be a factor of poverty,
but the opposite can be
true as well.
Think of the so called
‘resources curse’,
which burdens certain countries
where there is a lot of oil,
but where citizens
are desperately poor.
An inhospitable climate can put
an extra burden on countries:
for example in the Sahel region
where droughts are frequent.
Bad governance is an obvious
contributor to poverty,
for example when corruption
or administrative overloads
are impacting on the ease of creating
companies or doing business.
Conditions of Economic, Political
and Market instability,
will, for example, act as a deterrent
to foreign investment,
which is important for development.
Regional insecurity and wars,
of course, have a direct impact
on countries’ ability to prosper.
Freedom of intellectual expression
is crucial for a sound society
in which problems get
openly discussed and solved.
An ineffective and unfair judiciary
system will create inequality
and promote instability
and corruption.
Finally, Gender, racial, ethnic
or social discriminations
will tend to impoverish
some sections of the population
and the country altogether,
by denying the potentially
fruitful contribution
that all humans can and should
bring to society as a whole.
They are sources
of civil conflicts and wars.
Now let’s look at the determinants of
poverty at the community level.
At that level, lack of access
to adequate infrastructure
is a definite contributor
to poverty:
Think for example how a community
could possibly prosper
without access to paved roads,
stable electricity,
access to schools, access to
markets where to sell goods,
or access to clinics
where to get healthcare.
Unequal access to employment will also
burden some of the poor communities,
who will remain in a vicious cycle
where they are stigmatized,
and are thus not getting access
to decent jobs.
In the same vein, social mobility
is of course also very important:
being able to climb up
the ladders of society,
without hitting glass ceilings
is essential.
At community level,
equitable distribution of land
is a vitally important factor
as it allows local production
and reduces vulnerability
in the community.
Finally, what happens to
the poorest in the community?
Do they have access to
social networks
and institutions to help them?
The community as a whole
will fare better
if its poorer communities
are taken care of.
At the household level,
there are numerous determinants
of poverty as well,
which we can group
into 3 main categories:
Demographic,  Economic
and Social.
In the demographic category we find
determinants such as:
Large household sizes with members
having a younger average age.
Obviously, such households generally
also have a higher dependency ratio,
which means that a higher number
of family members
depend on a few breadwinners
earning an income.
The second category
is related to Economics:
It is very obvious that the scarcity of sources of
income is a problem,
for example, in the case of
widespread unemployment,
but also when the household
has no possibility
to produce its own food.
Lack of property such as
a house, land,
agricultural equipment,
or livestock,
is another obvious determinant,
which also includes
access to financial assets
and credit.
In the last category we find
Social aspects:
Ill health is associated
with poverty
and there are many
manifestations of this link.
Since in many poor countries
there are no health insurances,
individuals are very vulnerable
to falling into poverty,
as a direct consequence
of a health problem.
Having access to education
is absolutely crucial
to be able to take advantage of
income-earning opportunities,
but is not sufficient.
There can be access to education,
but the service is not used
for a variety of reasons.
Having shelter is
a basic human need.
So its absence is an obvious
determinant of poverty.
But shelter alone is not enough:
key services such as
safe water and sanitation,
stable electricity or other safe
energy sources for cooking,
lighting or operating communication
technology are needed too.
For a household
living in isolation,
without access to roads
and public transportation,
is a determinant of poverty.
It will prevent individuals
from accessing markets
where to sell their goods,
or to find jobs.
Last but not least,
lack of personal safety
is a terrible burden for
many people who are thus
prevented from living
productive and joyful lives.
As said before, this list
is by no means complete,
but it gives you a sense of the
multiple dimensions of poverty.
Later in this course,
we will discuss an initiative
that strives to define a framework
for a sustainable development
in many of these areas:
The United Nations
Sustainable Development Goals.
Remember also that correlation
does not necessarily mean causation
and that the real causes
are often hidden:
Things are almost always much
more complex than they appear.
Now let us try to find a workable
general definition of poverty.
For this, let us refer to
an organization
whose very mission it is
to reduce poverty:
The World Bank.
This institution defines
poverty as, quote,
“pronounced deprivation in
wellbeing” unquote.
This does not sound
very useful does it?
Luckily for us, the world bank
has given some precise insights
in their documentation, which
goes on to define wellbeing as:
A state which,
“can be measured by an individual’s
possession of income, health,
nutrition, education,
assets, housing,
and certain rights in a society,
such as freedom of speech.
Poverty is also
a lack of opportunities,
powerlessness, and vulnerability.
And the world bank concludes that:
Poverty is truly a multi-dimensional
phenomenon.”
Now having said that poverty
is multidimensional,
are there ways to assess
poverty quantitatively?
How many people are poor,
how poor are they?
Where are they located?
This, of course, is useful
in order to understand
where to focus our attention
if we want to reduce poverty.
Although there is no single figure
or index or number
which can accurately describe
the state of wellbeing
of a given population or country,
there are indicators which
can be helpful.
There are, broadly speaking, 3
classes of such indicators:
These that are monetary,
that is  they are expressed
in terms of income
or consumption as we will see,
as well as those that are non-monetary,
for example
life expectancy at birth,
as we will see,
or Infant mortality rate
and those which are composite,
meaning that they combine both
monetary and non-monetary metrics.
Let us start with some
monetary indicators,
which are widely used
as a catch-all figures
to assess state of wellbeing
or poverty.
The world bank’s definition
of poverty starts with
“Poverty is pronounced deprivation
in wellbeing, where wellbeing
can be measured by an individual’s
possession of income etc.”
Can we measure a
household’s income?
If we can do that, we may then
be able to define
a threshold under which a
household is considered poor:
that is the so called
poverty line.
We will come back to this.
It is possible to measure
household incomes using surveys
based on interviews conducted
with a sample
of households in the countries.
Unfortunately however
in many cases,
estimating income is
not very convenient
because households tend to
under-report their income.
Also, some aspects of household-income
are difficult to quantify
such as an increase in
farm livestock.
In general, thus economists prefer
to use household consumption
as a criterion except
in certain countries.
Generally, either consumption
or income can be used
and this doesn’t really
matter much
if we look at things
in a general way.
Consumption surveys cover
all monetary expenditures
for goods and services,
plus the monetary value
of all in-kind consumption,
such as food
produced on the family farm.
Countries routinely conduct
such surveys,
which are then aggregated
by the world bank.
Generally economists transform
the Household consumption
into a consumption
per person or per capita.
That means the total
household consumption,
is divided by the number of
individuals living in that household.
This gives a figure of how many
units of local currency
are expensed per person
and per day for living.
Let's imagine a hypothetical country
which we will call country C.
We conduct a survey of
household consumption,
and we get a distribution
of income.
We divide this income by the
number of people in the household
and we get the income
distribution per capita,
in the local country’s currency.
We now draft income as a function
of the share of the population
that lives on a specific
income base.
This is a probability
density function.
Here for example, we have
10% of the population
who lives on say 5 items
of local currency per day.
Are they poor or not?
To answer this question,
the local country authorities
will determine
a minimum level of income
under which an individual is
to be considered poor
by local standards.
This is the National poverty
line and remember,
it is in local currency.
This poverty line is very different
from one country to another.
If we want to know what
is the total share of people
in the country living below
the poverty line,
we have to sum up
or integrate
all the contributions below
the curve, up to that point.
Now let us assume we would
like to compare the situation
of wealth of that particular country
with other countries:
we now have the problem of the
difference in currencies
or exchange rates, but that
is not the only problem.
In fact we all know that prices vary
enormously across countries
even when converted to a reference
currency such as the US Dollar:
The purchasing power is different.
Think for example of the cost
of buying a lunch in a restaurant
or paying an apartment rent.
There are big differences
between countries.
To solve this issue, it is necessary
to convert all local currencies
into a reference currency which
is called the international dollar,
and to factor-out the difference
in buying power.
This can be done by referring to
a standardized basket
of goods and services.
We then determine how much
this basket used to cost
in the United States in a
specific reference year,
for example in 2011.
After that we can determine the cost
of the same basket
of goods and services, in
our country C’s local currency.
The ratio of the cost
in the United States
to the cost in the country’s
local currency
is called the Purchasing Power
Parity or PPP Conversion factor.
It represents how many items in
local currency would be needed,
to have the same buying power
as the Dollar had
in the United States at
a certain point in time.
One PPP dollar should thus buy
the same basket of goods
in Kenya, India or the US.
We can now express consumption
in any country
in terms of international
dollars at PPP.
Doing this with other countries
will allow us to compare them.
Now we can re-calculate the income
or consumption distribution
per capita per day
in international dollars at PPP.
We now have a curve that still
represents precisely the country C
that we are considering, but can be
compared to other countries,
where of course the same
calculations were done.
Having done this, we
would now need to know
what happens to the poverty line.
In fact, what we are interested in,
is to know how this particular country
compares in terms of poverty
with other countries.
For this, the world bank has defined
an international poverty line
that tells us what it means to be
in extreme poverty
in terms of international
dollars at PPP.
This line is calculated by
taking the average value
of the national poverty lines of
some of the poorest countries.
It is currently at 1.9 international
dollar per capita, per day at PPP.
This is a very crude threshold
which being based on the poverty
lines of the poorest countries,
is an absolute minimum.
We can now calculate the number
of people living on less than
$1.9/capita/day in country C.
This gives us the so called
poverty headcount ratio.
It is simply the area under
the curve in our graph,
on the left of the poverty line.
This allows us to determine
where on the planet
most of today’s extreme poor
people live, let us have a look.
This map shows you the countries
with their respective poverty
headcount ratio.
Globally this represents
about 900 million people
living in the most extreme
form of poverty,
struggling to meet
their most basic needs.
Of course there is no such
a thing as a clean limit
between poor and non-poor.
If we were to consider a limit
of $3/capita/day,
which is still very low,
the amount of people concerned goes up
to a staggering 2 billion worldwide.
In general, around 50% of all Africans
live below the poverty line.
In many African countries
it is even more than that.
This is a terrible situation
in this marvelous continent,
and this is why our MOOC is
focused mainly on
the context of sub-Saharan Africa.
For those of you who have read
about the subject of poverty,
there is a concept that is sometimes
used called the Bottom of the Pyramid.
The bottom of the pyramid
is generally defined as
those people living on less
than 2 dollars a day
which is pretty much equal to
our international poverty line.
In our next video,
we will continue the discussion
on monetary metrics such as
Gross Domestic Product.
We will then talk about
non-monetary metrics
and finally we will discuss
Composite metrics,
which combine both monetary
and non-monetary indices.
Good bye.