Hello, welcome to the second part
of the chapter entitled
What is poverty?
In the first video,
we have seen that poverty
is a multi-dimensional problem.
We have also seen
the definition of poverty
by the world-bank,
which we have used
as a base to try and understand
how we can measure poverty.
To do this, we have defined
three types of metrics:
those based on monetary values,
those based on non-monetary metrics
and those which are composite,
combining the two.
We have started looking at
monetary metrics and have seen
the concept of the poverty line,
defined as 1.9 international dollar,
per capita, per day,
at Purchasing Power Parity or PPP.
There is another monetary metric
which we need to mention
because it is very widely used:
the Gross Domestic Product
per capita.
The idea is to measure
the market value
of the total production or output
within a country in a given year.
Without going into details,
GDP is defined roughly as the sum of
private household consumption (C),
such as durable
and non-durable goods and services,.
Plus Investments (I)
made by public or private sectors
on capital equipment,
inventories and structures,
Plus Government  spending (G),
such as compensation
of government employees,
public health spending, etc.
Plus the net exports of the country,
which is the value
of all exports (X)
minus the value
of imported goods (M).
In other words,
it represents the value
of domestic goods
purchased by foreigners,
minus the value of foreign goods
purchased by nationals.
Finally, of course, this figure
is in units of national currency
and must be converted
into international dollars at PPP
as we have seen.
Furthermore,
it is divided by the amount of people
living in the country
to end-up with GDP,
per capita, at PPP.
This concept is based on the work
of John Maynard Keynes
in the 1940’s.
At that time,
there was a need to measure
Great Britain’s ability to wage war,
which in economic words meant:
its ability to produce
tanks and airplanes.
It is really intended to be a measure
of production or output, and
not welfare.
However,
it is still widely used and abused
as a metric for welfare.
To illustrate this discrepancy,
take for example Equatorial Guinea:
it has a GDP which is rather high
at $33’000/capita per year,
which would make it
a high-income country.
And yet close
80% of the population lives
below the poverty line.
How is that possible?
In fact, Equatorial Guinea has oil,
which it exports,
and this increases the X
in our equation.
However,
the share of that GDP available
for household consumption
is only 17% of the whole,
which is the C in our equation.
This tells us that a majority
of all households do not benefit
from the oil-revenues
which are kept by a minority.
We will come back to this question
of income distribution.
Based on the calculation
of GDP per capita,
or more precisely
on Gross National Income
which is a variant of GDP,
the world bank has a defined
a classification of countries.
It defines Low-income
as those countries that have an income
of 1'045 dollars per capita,
per year, or less.
Middle-Income countries
are split into lower-middle
and Upper-middle income,
and finally we have
high income countries.
Those are the ones
with a Gross National Income
above 12’736 dollars per capita
at PPP per year.
In our MOOC
we will often refer
to Low and Middle-Income countries
as the region of interest.
As you can see on this map,
many of the poorest countries
are landlocked,
such as the string of countries
running through the center
of the African continent,
or Nepal for example.
Other countries,
such as Afghanistan or Somalia
remain poor,
because they are afflicted by war.
You might ask yourself
if it is enough to know
how countries compare.
Remember the case of Equatorial Guinea:
wouldn’t it be interesting
to know also how wealth is distributed
inside a specific country?
To determine the level of inequality
inside of a country,
economists use another measure
developed in 1912
by the Italian statistician
Corrado Gini,
thus called the GINI index.
He had the idea
to use the so called Lorenz curve
to calculate inequality index.
The Lorenz curve is obtained
by drafting cumulative income
as a function of cumulative population.
In other words,
you list the poorest on the left
of the horizontal axis
and then sum up the population
in ascending order by degree of wealth,
up to the richest.
You then divide everything
by the total number of people
and you get an axis
with the cumulative share of the population
ranked from the lowest to the highest income.
On the vertical axis you represent
the cumulative share of income earned.
If we consider
a perfectly equal society
you would have to have
the poorest 30% of the people
owning 30% of the income,
the poorest 50%
having 50% of the income
and so forth.
The Lorenz curve
of such a hypothetical country
would be the straight line, in blue.
Unfortunately, in the real world,
income is not evenly distributed:
some parts of the population
have much more income than others.
So the Lorenz curve really looks like
the yellow one, where you can see
that the poorest 30% of the population
own only roughly 10% of the income,
while the richest 10%
get about 30% of the income.
The Gini index measures
the area between the Lorenz curve
and the hypothetical line
of absolute equality.
This is expressed as a percentage
of the maximum area under the line
or A over A plus B.
Thus a Gini index of 0
represents perfect equality:
the yellow curve would be identical
with the straight blue line.
An index of 1
implies perfect inequality
which would mean that
one person gets all the income,
and all the others get none.
This index can now be applied
to look at how
unequal different countries are.
Here is a list of some countries'
GINI indices.
As you can see,
it is not because a country is poor
that it has a high level of inequality:
Tanzania which is a low-income country
is less unequal than the United States,
which is a High-income country.
South Africa on the contrary
is an upper-middle income country
with has a very high Gini index.
This indicates that there are
wide differences
in income across the population.
Together with GDP,
the Gini index
provide convenient ways
to explore and measure progress
with regards to poverty
and its distribution.
However these metrics are based on
monetary dimensions.
As we have seen,
poverty is multi-dimensional.
So let us now turn
to some non-monetary metrics
and indicators
for the state of well-being.
There are numerous such metrics
which measure
any of the different dimensions
of poverty.
We will pick just two,
one in the area of health
and the other in the area
of Education.
Life expectancy at birth
is a health indicator
that is calculated
based on a number of assumptions.
It represents the number of years
a newborn infant would live
if prevailing patterns of mortality
at the time of its birth
were to stay the same
throughout its life.
It incorporates
the mortality patterns
that prevail across all age groups
in a given year – children,
adolescents, adults and the elderly.
In this table we have listed
the average Life Expectancy
at birth per income group
according to the world-bank classification.
Obviously, at first sight,
countries with higher incomes
have a longer life expectancy:
there are more funds available
to pay for healthcare,
clean drinking water
and good quality food.
Things are of course
a bit more complicated than that.
For example if we consider
an African country like Cameroon.
Its Life expectancy at birth
is as low as 55 years.
However, this very low value
is largely influenced
by the shockingly high level
of child mortality in this country:
Cameroon has an infant mortality rate
of 88 children for every 1000 live births
as compared to
7 for every 1000 live births
in the United States.
In other words,
a child is over 10 times
more likely to die
before reaching its 5th birthday
in Cameroon,
than it would in the United States.
This, of course, significantly reduces
the overall Life expectancy at birth.
As with any single numerical indicator,
one has to remain cautious
about how the indicator is constructed:
what it accounts for
and, what it doesn’t.
The second non-monetary metric
characterizes education.
It is called
the primary school completion rate.
This factor measures
the proportion of people
entering the last grade
of primary education
compared to all the people
who would have the age to be enrolled.
In this table you can see that in Chad,
which is one of the poorest countries,
not even 40% of the population
finishes primary education.
The difference between male and female
is also very important.
It is thus very sad
that less than one in 3 girls
can achieve only primary education,
let alone secondary.
This is obviously sad
for the people themselves,
but sad as well from the perspectives
of that country.
We will now turn
to the last type of metrics,
which we called composite,
because they involve both monetary
and non-monetary parameters.
Let us look at one such metric
called the Human Development Index.
It was first proposed in the 1990s
by the United Nations
Development Program.
The Human Development Index
is a geometric mean
of the Life Expectancy index,
times the Education Index,
times the Income Index.
The Life Expectancy Index, or LEI,
is based on life expectancy at birth,
which we have just have seen.
The Education Index, or EI,
is a combination of mean years
of schooling
and expected years of schooling,
and is yet another non-monetary index.
Finally, the Income Index, or II,
is based on the logarithmic value
of the Gross National Income
expressed in PPP dollars per capita.
All these indices
are normalized in order to have
a value between 0 (worst) and 1,
which represents an aspirational
but realistic goal to be reached
in that particular dimension:
for example a life expectancy
of 85 years in a particular country,
which corresponds to the highest
level reached worldwide,
would give this country
a Life Expectancy Index of 1.
The Human Development Index
is used by the United Nations
Development Program
to rank countries:
Let’s look at a few of them.
The table represents
the Human Development Index
in the second column,
and in the third column,
the country’s ranking
when compared to others.
There aren’t any big surprises
at first glance:
high-income countries
have a higher Human Development Index
and of course tend to rank better
than low income countries.
Differences do appear however
if you compare
the ranking of South Africa,
based on the  Human Development Index,
with the ranking based on GDP:
If we refer to GDP,
South Africa ranks 84th,
while it is only 116th
if you look at Human Development Index.
This, of course reflects
the influence of non-monetary metrics
such as Life expectancy
that is accounted for
in the Human Development Index
but not in GDP.
In effect,
the life expectancy at birth
in South Africa is only 57 years
which explains the difference.
We have now been able
to scratch the surface
of this very complex question
of what is poverty.
We have learned to characterize it
using Monetary, non-monetary
and composite metrics.
This will give us
the necessary background
for the remainder of this course
on how to reduce poverty
through innovation
and technology development.
Good Bye.