This lecture will focus on a major
global initiative
to reduce poverty and promote
sustainable development
around the world.
The United Nations defines
Sustainable Development
as development that meets the needs
of the present
without compromising the ability
of future generations
to meet their own needs.
The current initiative
of Sustainable Development Goals
was preceded by a another somewhat
similar but smaller scale initiative
that dates back to the beginning
of the current Millennium.
In the year 2000, the leaders
of the world came together
and made a historic commitment:
To eradicate extreme poverty
and improve the health and welfare
of the world's poorest people
within 15 years.
The commitment was adopted at
the Millennium Summit
in September 2000, and it set forth
the United Nations
Millenium Declaration, whose vision
was expressed
in eight time-bound goals,
known as
the Millennium Development
Goals or MDGs.
What exactly were these goals?
I will summarize them quickly.
Goal 1 intended to eradicate
extreme poverty and hunger.
Goal 2: Achieve universal
primary education.
Goal 3: Promote gender equality
and empower women.
And Goal 4: Reduce child mortality.
And Goal 5 to improve
maternal health.
Goal 6: To combat HIV/AIDS,
malaria and other diseases.
Goal 7: Ensure environmental
sustainability.
Goal 8: Develop a global
partnership for development.
After 15 years, in 2015,
what did we achieve?
For Goal 1, extreme poverty
has declined
significantly over the last
2 decades.
In 1990, nearly half of
the population
in the developing world
live in extreme poverty.
That proportion has now dropped
to 14 percent in 2015.
And globally, the number of people
living in extreme poverty
has declined by more than half,
falling from
1.9 billion in 1990
to 836 million in 2015.
And most progress had actually
occurred since 2000.
And for Goal 2, the number
of out-of-school children
of primary school age worldwide,
has fallen by almost half
to an estimated 57 million in 2015,
down from 100 million in 2000.
And Sub-Saharan Africa has had
the best record
of improvement in primary
education of any region
since the MDGs were established.
And with respect to Goal 3,
today many more girls
are in school as compared
to 15 years ago.
In Southern Asia, only 74 girls
were enrolled
in primary school for every
100 boys in 1990.
But today we have 103 girls
that are enrolled
for every 100 boys
in primary school.
Not only that, but apparently
women have also gained ground
in parliamentary representation
in nearly 90 per cent
of the 174 countries monitored
over the past 20 years.
For Goal 4, despite
population growth
in the developing regions,
the global mortality rates
of children under 5 years old
has declined by more than half
dropping from 90 to 43 deaths
per 1000 live births
between 1990 and 2015.
In sub-Saharan Africa, the annual
rate of reduction
of mortality for children
under 5 years old
was over 5 times faster
during 2005 to 2013
than it was during the period
of 1990 to 1995.
And for Goal 5, since 1990
the maternal mortality rate
has declined
by 45 per cent worldwide
and most of the reduction
has occurred since 2000.
In southern Asia, the maternal
mortality rate
actually declined by 64 percent.
And in Sub-Saharan Africa,
it fell by 49 percent.
Goal 6: By June, 2014, almost
14 million people
living with HIV, were receiving
antiretroviral therapy (ART) globally,
which is an immense increase
from just 800,000 in 2003.
And over 6 million malaria deaths
have been averted
between 2000 and 2015,
and more importantly
this was primarily of children
under 5 years of age
in sub-Saharan Africa.
And the global malaria incident
rate has fallen
by an estimated 37 percent,
while the mortality rate
has declined by 50 per cent overall.
Between the year 2000 and 2013,
anti-tuberculosis interventions
saved an estimated
37 million lives.
Goal 7: Ozone-depleting substances
have been virtually eliminated,
and the ozone layer
is expected to recover
by the middle of this century.
Globally, 147 countries have met
their drinking water targets
while 95 countries have met
their sanitation targets.
And finally, for Goal 8, in 2014
79 percent of imports
from developing countries
to developed countries
were admitted duty free,
which is up from 65 percent in 2000.
And the proportion of external
debt service to export revenue
in developing countries had fallen
by 400 percent in 2013.
So overall, the MDG initiative
was considered a success story!
These successes are a great
source of encouragement,
and have served as
an engine or motor
to galvanize further
and continued action
because despite these successes,
much still remains to be done,
as those at the Bottom
of the Pyramid, i.e. the poorest
and most vulnerable,
continue to be left behind.
So, next time we will speak about
an even more ambitious initiative
that intends to pick up where
the Millennium Development Goals
left off, and instead go much
further than before.
Thank you.