Hello.
This lecture is a follow-up from
the Millennium Development Goals
that we discussed before.
Which subsequently gave rise to
the Sustainable Development Goals,
or SDGs.
The SDGs build on the success
of the Millennium Development Goals
and aim to go further towards
ending all forms of poverty.
The new goals are unique
in that they call for action
by all countries,
including poor, rich
and middle income,
to unite and promote prosperity
while protecting the planet.
They recognize that ending poverty
must go hand in hand
with strategies that
build economic growth
and address a range of social needs
while tackling climate change
and environmental protection.
On the 1st of January, 2016
the 17 Sustainable Development Goals
of the 2030 Agenda
for Sustainable Development
officially came into force.
And what are these SDGs?
Goal 1 is to end poverty,
in all its forms,
everywhere, by 2030.
There are still almost 900 million people
living in extreme poverty.
And the overwhelming majority
of those people
are in sub-Saharan Africa
and southern Asia.
Goal 2 aims to end hunger,
achieve food security
and improved nutrition,
and promote sustainable agriculture.
By 2030, we should end hunger
and ensure access by all
to enough food all year round,
especially to those
at the bottom of the pyramid.
This goal is intended to encourage us
to rethink how we grow, share
and consume our food.
The food and agriculture sector
offer key solutions for development,
especially rural development,
and is central for
hunger and poverty eradication.
Goal 3 aims to ensure healthy lives
and promote well-being for all,
and at all ages.
Significant strides have been made
in increasing life expectancy
and reducing some of
the common killers
associated with child
and maternal mortality.
However, many more efforts
are still needed to fully eradicate
a wide range of diseases
and address many persistent
and emerging health issues.
Goal 4: to ensure inclusive
and quality education for all
and promote lifelong learning.
Major progress has been made
towards increasing access
to education at all levels
and increasing enrollment rates in schools,
particularly for women and girls.
But bolder efforts are still needed
to make even greater strides
for achieving these
universal education goals.
Goal 5 aims to achieve gender equality
and empower all women and girls.
While the world has achieved progress
towards gender equality
and women empowerment
under the Millennium Development Goals,
women and girls continue to suffer
discrimination and violence world over.
The SDGs view gender equality
as not only a
fundamental human right,
but a necessary foundation
for a peaceful, prosperous
and sustainable world.
Goal 6 seeks to ensure access
to water and sanitation for all.
Because water scarcity,
poor water quality
and inadequate sanitation
have a significant negative impact
on quality of life overall.
Drought afflicts some of
the world’s poorest countries,
worsening hunger and malnutrition.
Meanwhile, there is sufficient
fresh water on the planet
to achieve this goal,
but it requires better economic systems
and suitable infrastructure.
Goal 7 is to ensure access
to affordable, reliable, sustainable
and modern energy for all.
Because as we know,
energy is central
to nearly every major challenge
and opportunity the world faces today.
But at the same time,
we have to make sure that
the energy solutions we adopt
do not negatively impact the environment.
And goal 8 seeks to promote
inclusive and sustainable
economic growth,
employment and decent work for all.
Today, about half
of the world’s population
still lives on the equivalent
of about US$2 a day.
Thus, solutions are urgently required
that will allow people
to have quality jobs
that stimulate the economy,
while not necessarily
harming the environment.
Goal 9 aims to build
resilient infrastructure,
promote sustainable industrialization
and foster innovation.
Investments in infrastructure,
such as transport, irrigation, energy,
and information and communication technology
are crucial to achieving
sustainable development
and empowering communities
in many countries.
It has long been recognized
that growth in productivity and income
and improvements in
health and education outcomes
require investment in infrastructure.
Inclusive and sustainable
industrial development
is the primary source
of income generation.
It allows for rapid
and sustained increases
in living standards for all people,
and provides
the technological solutions
to environmentally sound industrialization.
And technological progress
is the foundation
of sustainable industrialization.
Goal 10 aims to reduce inequality
within and among countries.
The international community
has made significant strides
towards lifting people out of poverty.
However, inequality still persists
and large disparities remain
with respect to
access to health, education
and other assets.
Additionally, while income inequality
between countries
may have been reduced,
inequality though,
within countries, has risen.
There is growing consensus that
economic growth is not sufficient
to reduce poverty
if it is not inclusive
and if it does not involve
the 3 dimensions
of sustainable development:
economic, social
and environmental factors.
Goal 11 aims to make cities
inclusive, safe
resilient and sustainable.
Cities are considered to be
hubs for ideas,
commerce, culture,
science, productivity,
social development and much more.
Common urban challenges
include congestion,
lack of funds
to provide basic services,
a shortage of adequate housing,
and declining infrastructure.
While Goal 12 aims to ensure
sustainable consumption
and production patterns.
Because sustainable
production and consumption
is about promoting
resource and energy efficiency,
sustainable infrastructure,
and providing access to basic services
and green and decent jobs,
Its implementation will help to achieve
overall development plans,
reduce future economic,
environmental and social costs,
while strengthening
economic competitiveness.
Sustainable consumption and production
aims at doing more
(and better) with less,
increasing net welfare gains
from economic activities,
by reducing resource use, degradation
and pollution along
the whole lifecycle,
while increasing the quality of life overall.
It thus requires the involvement
of different stakeholders,
including businesses, consumers,
policy makers, researchers,
scientists, media
and development cooperation agencies,
amongst others.
Goal 13 aims to take urgent action
to combat climate change
and its impact.
While goal 14 aims to conserve
and sustainably use the oceans,
seas and marine resources.
Because now climate change is affecting
every country on every continent,
it is disrupting national economies
and affecting life,
costing people, communities
and countries dearly.
But climate change is a global challenge
that does not respect national borders.
Emissions anywhere
affect people everywhere.
It is an issue that requires solutions
that need to be coordinated
at the international level
and it requires
international cooperation
to help developing countries move toward
a low-carbon economy.
Goal 15 aims to
sustainably manage forests,
combat desertification,
halt and reverse land degradation
and also halt biodiversity loss.
The world’s oceans, as we said,
drive global systems
that make the Earth
habitable for humankind.
Our rainwater, drinking water,
weather, climate, coastlines,
much of our food
and even the oxygen
in the air we breathe
are ultimately provided
and regulated by the sea.
Throughout history, oceans and seas
have been vital conduits
for trade and transportation.
So careful management
of this essential global resource
is a key feature
for a sustainable future.
Goal 16 aims to promote just,
peaceful and inclusive societies.
It is dedicated to the promotion
of peaceful and inclusive society
for sustainable development,
the provision of
access to justice for all,
and building effective and accountable
institutions at all levels.
While goal 17 aims to revitalize
the global partnership
for sustainable development.
A successful sustainable development agenda
requires partnerships between governments,
the private sector and civil society.
Efforts are needed
to mobilize, redirect,
and unlock the transformative power
of trillions of dollars
of private resources
to deliver on
sustainable development objectives.
Now before we conclude this lesson,
I’m sure some of you
might be asking yourselves
why should one really care about SDGs.
If you’re an engineer
or scientist for example,
and you wish to develop
an essential technology
that may make a positive contribution
to global sustainable development,
where would you begin?
I would say an excellent starting point
is by understanding the SDGs,
because even many of
the global expert organizations
such as the World Health Organization,
for example (the WHO),
who are entrusted with the mission
of making recommendations or guidelines
for safe technologies
and health measures,
will always look to align
their policies and strategies
with the SDGs.
Major funding organizations, such as
The Gates Foundation,
Welcome Trust, etc.,
typically align their strategies and priorities
with such an initiative.
And same goes for a company
that wishes to expand internationally
or establish a
Corporate Social Responsibility Strategy.
They would surely benefit by looking
at SDGs to inspire their strategy.
And the list goes on.