We will now come to the role
of technology in development
in the fight against poverty.
This course is entitled
Technology Innovation
for Sustainable Development.
Without venturing too much
into semantics,
which is beyond the scope of
the topic today,
my colleague Klaus here will  explain
to us what is meant
by the words
technology and innovation.
There is a lot of literature
and arguing
about the definition of the concept
of technology.
For example, let me cite
an American sociologist, Read Bain
who wrote the following
definition in 1937 :
Broadly conceived, technology is
the most important single factor
in producing, integrating
and destroying cultural phenomena.
Technology includes all tools,
machines, utensils, weapons,
instruments, housing, clothing,
communicating and transporting devices
and the skills by which
we produce and use them.
Note that the citation includes
a list of different technology types.
Of course, what counts here is
the fact that technology
is about objects,
tools and the skills
by which we produce and use them.
We should obviously
also include “information”
as we are now in
the information age.
For the sake of simplicity,
we would like to use another
more concise definition
for the purpose of this course.
The Oxford Dictionary defines
technology as "Machinery and devices
developed from
scientific knowledge.”
This definition is simpler
and captures the essence
of the concept of technology
as we need it in this course.
This is the definition
we would like you
to bear in mind as we move forward.
Humankind has used technologies
since prehistoric times
and has always sought
to improve them.
Quite obviously, new
and improved technology
can provide competitive
and evolutionary advantages.
To look for new techniques or tools
to do things better,
cheaper, quicker is therefore
in the very nature of humans.
The title of our MOOC says
Technology Innovation.
My colleague, Soli,
will now give you
a simplified definition
of innovation.
In equally simple terms,
Innovation can be defined as:
the action of making changes
in something established,
especially by introducing
new methods, ideas, or products.
Note that it is not just about
coming up with new ideas,
but a lot more about
effectively applying them
so as to really meet the needs
or expectations of the beneficiary.
So, for the purposes
of this course
Technology Innovation
is thus defined as:
"Making changes by creating
new machinery and devices,
developed from scientific knowledge
and deploying them
in a way that fulfills
needs and aspirations
of the beneficiaries and
their respective communities.
As we will see later, this will
generally involve a product
and creative implementation planning,
such as a business plan
and an impact plan.
Poverty is a terrible trap
but technology innovation
can be a key enabler
towards solving difficult social,
economic
and environmental challenges.
However, new technologies
are not an end per se,
they are more of a catalyst
for development.
Of course, technologies may also have
have unwanted by-products
such as generating pollution,
depleting natural resources
in an unsustainable way,
or enabling humans to wage war.
We will not venture into
such a philosophical debate,
but simply recognize that
certain technologies are essential
for lifting poor communities
out of poverty
and improving their quality of life.
They help fulfill basic
human needs and rights
such as health,
shelter or education.
Unfortunately, while many
of these technologies are available
in industrialized countries,
they have somehow failed
to be successfully deployed in
Low & Middle-Income Countries
and thus have been
unable to deliver
the desired catalytic effect
for development.
The question we would
like to answer now is:
Which technologies, exactly,
could have a high potential
in reducing poverty and catalysing
sustainable development?
Most of us will agree that weapons
would not belong in this category.
But other technologies, such as
those defined by Read Bain, earlier
like “housing,” seem closer
to what we are looking for,
since having a shelter
is a basic human need.
Klaus, will now tell you about
which technologies we could define
or consider to have a high potential
to help reduce poverty.
Let us first try to define a concept
which we will call
Essential Technologies.
Essential Technologies are
simply those technologies
which can help expedite
the achievements
of the Sustainable
Development Goals.
Now, this sounds vague,
how can we be more specific?
Soli has nicely explained
the Sustainable Development Goals
in a previous video.
He will now try and help us identify
what those technologies are exactly.
For the purposes of this course,
what is considered
Essential Technologies comprises:
Food & Agriculture,
Pharmaceuticals, Medical Equipment,
Energy
Information and
Communication Technologies,
Transportation, Construction
and finally Water & Sanitation.
The selection of this list
was inspired by
the Millennium Development Goals
and the Sustainable
Development Goals.
When we analyzed the goals
set by the UN
from an engineering perspective,
we observed that
these technology domains
stood-out as the most pertinent.
In the same way as the UN
have defined their specific goals
for a sustainable future, we believe
that it is very important
to be able to identify
technologies that can underpin
the achievements of these goals.
This will allow us to focus
our efforts on the areas
which have the highest potential.
However, it must be stated
that this grouping
is not intended to be rigid,
as in practice you may find
various overlaps across
or in between domains.
For example, energy and ICT
may typically be required
in many other
technology applications
in the other domains.
But before we get into the question
of how to develop
impactful essential technologies,
in the following sessions
we will discuss
each of these technologies
along with
their potential role
in development.
Good-bye.