Hello! In the last video,
we have seen three
of the five main challenges
we have to face
when developing technology innovation
for low and middle income countries:
a lack of quality infrastructure,
a lack of trained personnel,
and a lack of financial resources.
Let us now discuss the challenge
of harsh environment.
This picture was taken
in a hospital in Cameroon.
It shows the control panel
of a diagnostic ultrasound machine
which has been severely damaged
by warm and humid conditions
found there.
This illustrates
the fundamental mismatch
between the context
this device was designed for,
and the actual context of use.
High temperatures and humidity
have a severe impact
on technologies which were developed
to work
in temperate
and controlled environments
found in industrialized countries.
In the tropics, temperatures can reach
27 degrees Celsius
with humidity above 95%.
The effect of such environments
are numerous,
such as accelerated aging,
changing in parameters
of electronic components,
changing of material dimensions,
overheating of transformers
and electromechanical components
and enclosures becoming distorted
and failing.
High humidity will cause
corrosion and oxidation of metals,
swelling of materials
due to water sorption,
electrical short-circuits
and fogging of optical components.
Heat and humidity combined
is an ideal environment
for fungus and microbial growth.
Non-resistant materials
are susceptible
to direct attack as the fungus
breaks the materials down
and uses them as nutrients.
Metabolic waste products excreted
by fungus cause corrosion of metals,
etching of glass,
or staining or degrading
of plastics and other materials.
In arid areas, dust and sand
are pervasive enemies of technology.
Dust may obstruct openings,
penetrate into cracks, crevices,
bearings and joints.
It will clog filters
which leads to ventilation malfunction
and overheating.
Sand and dust are
powerful agents of abrasion
and will cause degradation
of electrical circuits
and interference and wear
of moving parts.
Solar light is a boon
in tropical countries
as it represents
a wonderful source of clean energy.
However, intense solar irradiation
takes a severe toll
on equipment exposed to it.
Effects can be thermal,
with the sunlight heating up surfaces
in a directional way,
which is different
from just ambient heat.
This may create destructive tensions
in materials.
In addition to the heating effects,
certain degradations
from solar energy
may be attributable
to other portions of the spectrum,
particularly the ultraviolet.
Deterioration of natural and synthetic
elastomers and polymers will result.
There are many other
environmental problems
such as the presence
of rodents or insects
which damage cables
and enclosures.
We should also mention
the issue of theft.
Sometimes, even low value
and seemingly insignificant components
will be stolen,
which can make equipment useless
with little possibility of repair.
Finally, it is not only important
to consider the environment
where the technology is being used
but also the storage
and transport conditions.
If you are interested
in learning more
about these environmental conditions
and how the resilience of equipment
is tested in these regards,
we recommend having a look
at military norms,
known as MIL standards,
which can be downloaded
from the Internet.
One of the most difficult
and frustrating challenges
is the one posed by the way
we humans make decisions,
and by the way these decisions
are implemented.
Broadly speaking, this is
the definition of governance.
The next challenge
posed by the context
that I would like to discuss
is bad governance.
The concept of governance can apply
to public or private stakeholders.
In the case of public institutions,
we can mention international governance,
national governance
or local governance.
For private institutions
like companies,
it is referred to
as corporate governance.
Bad governance a
ffects many actors
across the society,
such as landlords, NGOs, cooperatives,
unions, political parties,
research institutes, corporations,
media, etcetera.
It involves a wide variety
of inappropriate
decision making processes,
and/or inappropriate implementation
of these decisions.
Specifically, bad governance
may encourage
or facilitate corruption
which is defined as
"abuse of entrusted power
for private gain".
Other effects
of poor governance are:
excessive administrative hassle,
also called "Red Tape",
extortion, embezzlement, clientelism
to cite just a few.
It is only if we have
a solid collaboration
with local stakeholders
in countries
that we will be able to understand
the subtle mechanisms at play
in how decisions are made
and implemented.
They are heavily influenced
by history,
culture, religion
and many other factors.
We should, of course, remember
that bad governance
can be found everywhere
on the planet,
not only in low
and middle income countries.
Let's have a look
at the specific case of corruption.
This map shows
the corruption perception index,
which is defined
as the level of corruption
perceived by people
living in the respective countries.
The higher the score,
the lower the perception
of corruption.
The index is based
on opinion surveys
and expert assessments
from a dozen institutions
such as the world bank, think tanks,
foundations and research organizations.
This is actually representative
of how citizens of the countries
perceive the situation
and it is corroborated
by independent assessments.
As you can see, the problem
is very widespread.
In practice, this undermines society
and prevents businesses
and individuals
from being successful.
In some countries,
it is so deeply rooted and pervasive
that every contact
with government or civil society
will involve requests for bribes.
Simply sending a product
through customs
without paying bribes
is often a major effort
which can take months.
Here again, it is essential
that we work together
with local actors
so that we can understand
the problems.
We strongly believe
that with perseverance
and a good understanding,
it is possible to find
ethically correct solutions
but this remains a big challenge.
There is one more metric
which I would like to tell you about
which is also closely related
to governance.
It is called
the Ease of Doing Business index
and it is very important
for entrepreneurs.
The index is composed of sub-indices,
each measuring a specific dimension.
It focuses in particular
on measuring
the effect of a country's laws,
regulations and processes
on the ease of creating
and running a business.
For example, it determines
how many days it takes
to go through the legal
and administrative procedures
to start a business.
It measures how difficult it is
to get the construction permits
to build a warehouse,
to get connected
to the electrical grid,
or how burdensome it is
to register a real estate property right.
It evaluates how easy it is
to get credit,
how well minority investors
are protected against lawsuits,
how companies will be required
to pay taxes
and how easy it is to trade
across borders.
Finally, it also includes an indicator
of how well contracts are enforced
and how insolvency gets resolved
in case of bankruptcy.
This complex set of parameters
is then aggregated
and countries are ranked
according to how well
they perform.
Rather than showing you
yet another map,
or some country rankings,
we recommend that you go
to the World Bank's website
to have a more detailed look
at how your country of interest is doing.
I would like now to take
a little side step
and talk about donations.
This video was filmed
in a small church
adjacent to a rural district hospital
in Cameroon.
What you can see
is that the hospital
had no more space to store
dysfunctional and obsolete
donated medical equipment.
Donations epitomize
many of the challenges
which we have just seen.
At first sight, it seems
that since low-income countries
can't afford to buy new equipment,
why would we not
recycle used equipment
from industrialized countries
instead?
Unfortunately, a very large majority
of donated equipment
either never becomes functional
at all
or breaks down shortly
after having been delivered.
According to the
World Health Organization,
less than 30%
of donated medical equipment
is ever commissioned.
There are multiple reasons
for these failures
which can, in general,
be attributed
to a combination
of the main contextual challenges
which are the topic
of this video.
Of course,
donations are critically important
in humanitarian disasters
and many other situations.
Donating complex equipment
such as medical devices
can even be successful
and sustainable
if a serious process is followed
which involves
assessing the local situation
and preparing the donation
in close collaboration
with the recipient organization.
Let us listen
to Mr. Andre Mama Fouda,
Minister of Public Health
of the Republic of Cameroon,
as he discusses the case
of medical equipment donations
in his country.
Indeed we receive
donations
coming from
partners from different countries
and the difficulty is often
the age of the given product.
It's often devices
that have a certain age
and which may not be
in the market anymore.
This poses the problem
of spare parts
regardless of the productivity
of the device itself.
Besides that,
with those donated devices
we also have the problem of consumables,
which are not always available
and could be lacking,
causing the users
to put aside the device.
Of course some devices need
calibration and on-site adjustments.
Often we don't have a technician
that already knows that kind of device.
That's why I pay a lot of attention
to donations,
especially when the donation is an
electronic device.
As long as it's something mechanical
we can find local solutions.
But when there is a big
electrical aspect,
we need to be careful with
those donations.
Our discussion
about contextual challenges
would not be complete
if we did not mention
cultural aspects.
On this picture, you can see
a lady in Cameroon
who was sent to the hospital
by her traditional healer
for a medical exam.
The interaction
between traditional practices
and modern western medicine
is sometimes uneasy.
Such cultural and traditional aspects
are very important
and should be seriously considered
from the start.
Technology innovation will,
by definition,
cause some disruptions
in the usual way
things are being done.
We need to be cognizant
of the cultural influences
and here again, there is no better way
than a close collaboration
Of course, this does not mean
that we should design solutions
which are so specifically adapted
to a community
that they lose any interest
for a wider public.
We have to be able to step back
and think about how to broaden
the impact of our technology.
Cultural differences offer
wonderful and fun learning experiences,
but have the potential
to derail the best projects
if they are not deeply understood.
The description of the context
of low and middle income countries
we have just given may sound
negative and difficult.
The challenges are real
but so are the upsides.
We are convinced
that success is possible
and there are many examples
where entrepreneurs
have been able to succeed.
Getting there is exciting, fun
and instructive,
and we strongly encourage you
to not be afraid
by the challenges.
Good bye.