Ever since we got this machine it
hasn't been in good condition.
We had several technicians come
to fix it,
but they didn't understand.
Until now, we are still looking
for ways to repair it
we can't find the
parts on the market.
That's why it doesn't work.
Since we got it, in 2012,
that's when it got here!
The other machine I work with
is an old machine
and there is a switch
that doesn't work.
So I tried to work with
it to get he right image.
There is a cooperation
between China and Cameroon.
They give us equipment
the donations arrive
sometimes with the instructions
fully in Chinese.
When you can't see a translator
if you have a translator
he'll translate the language
but he doesn't have the necessary
technical knowledge,
so we very often
face this situation,
where our engineers do what they can
to make the equipment work
so sometimes they make
mistakes with the plugs and wires
we are often face with
this is the big issue we have
with this type of equipment
These donations of equipment
are often second hand devices,
not adapted
so they'll work for maximum 6 months
and obviously with no transparency
from the customer service
and maintenance team.
Well sometimes it's
very interesting stuff
very interesting
very interesting imagery equipment
echograph scanners
and unfortunately
when it's second hand
it won't last very long.
The problem of the obsolescence
of the equipment
So the problem is that
with these obsolete, outdated
machines
we sometimes have to repeat the
exam 3, 4 or 5 times
to get what we want
and the final image is approximate,
sometimes we accept one because
we have already tried many times
and there is a double,
even a triple risk.
For the patient,
who is radiated several times
because there is a certain
dose the patient shouldn't exceed
and for yourself,
because at the same time,
the personnel is often unprotected,
they don't have leaded screens
they barely have a leaded apron but
that doesn't protect like a screen
Thirdly,
they never have control
of the quantity of radiation they recieve.
The machines come as they are.
we don't know if there are
spare parts
and we don't know if we can
find them locally.
So you are given a machine.
You don't have it from the start,
only for the end
You just receive it and you use it.
When it stops,
if you can't find the parts,
you put it aside and look for
another one.
And as long as it doesn't come you
stay like that,
so this is the real problem
with these machines we receive.
When the machine gets to us
the spare parts are no longer made
because the machine
isn't fabricated anymore.
So this is a huge problem.
We face constraints that
we cannot solve
and sometimes we are giving
up on the machine
and not knowing what to do.
They become what you'd call
the "white elephant in the room".
There is this big
white elephant there
everyone looks at it
but it does not work.
Sometimes there is equipment
we have to pay to get rid of,
so the term "donation"
could be more like
a transfer of responsibility
from one to another.
So that is a subject we
need to analyse with care
and depth.
The donators have good intentions.
But, they give what they have
and that can mean
what they want to get rid of,
which doesn't necessarily correspond
which often doesn't correspond
to the real need from the field.
Either in terms of what we want,
or in terms of reliability,
So they give what they can
because that's what they have, and
maybe they don't use it any more
And we receive it
because they give it to us,
bu maybe we didn't ask for it
and if we asked for
what we really wanted,
they would say "we don't
have that, take this instead."
There is an inadequacy
between what's available
when they donate
and what we really need.