Hello. The success or failure
of launching and scaling up
a new technology
depends heavily on how well
it is adapted
to the context
where it will be used.
In particular, it depends on
the people who will use it
and on the environment,
which can be very harsh.
Low and middle income countries
are different
from industrialized countries
in many ways.
Any innovative technology solution
we will develop
will need to take this into account.
The best way to do this
is to collaborate closely
with local stakeholders.
We will now look at
a simplified framework,
which captures the main challenges
posed by these contexts.
There are 4 main challenges
in this context
and one overarching issue
connected to all of them,
which is poor governance.
As said before,
the context is characterized
by scarcity.
There is a lack
of functioning infrastructure,
a lack of trained personnel
and a lack of financial resources.
Of course, these elements
are all interconnected
and interdependent in complex ways.
The harsh environment
is yet another characteristic
of this context
and we will see
how destructive it can be
for essential technologies.
Let us now look at
these different challenges
and explain how they influence
technology innovation.
Scarcity in quality infrastructure
is certainly
a very widespread issue.
Infrastructure provides
the basic physical systems
and structures
essential to the operation
of a society or enterprise.
It involves many aspects,
but let me mention some of
the most important ones
in our technology innovation
perspective:
energy, transport, communication
and water infrastructures.
This picture was taken in
a district hospital in Cameroon
which has had 6 fires
in only one year,
caused by inadequate
electrical infrastructure.
In both Sub-Saharan Africa
and South Asia,
about 45% of firms identified
reliability of the power supply
and connecting to the grid
as among the key constraints
to doing business.
Africa's informal firms,
who cannot afford a backup
electrical generator,
report that up to 20% of their sales
are lost because of the
frequent power outages.
When power is available,
instabilities such as power spikes
or voltage sags
tend to damage electrical equipment.
According to one study,
up to one third of electrical
medical equipment failures
are due to power instabilities.
Designing solutions for that context
will require
that either there is no need
for electrical power at all,
or the technology has
a robust circuitry
allowing it to resist this
destructive electrical environment.
Another challenge is
the lack of availability
of quality transport infrastructure
such as paved roads and railways,
which means that it is
difficult and expensive
to ship a product
to the people who need it.
This is especially problematic
in low-income countries
in Sub-Saharan Africa
where the paved road density
is less than a quarter
than that of other
low-income countries
in Asia, for example.
When paved roads are available,
they very quickly degrade
due to a destructive combination
of heavy usage, harsh climate
and lack of maintenance.
Supply chains are heavily affected
by this lack of
efficient transport infrastructure
which increases costs
and causes delays.
Access to
communication infrastructure,
such as mobile telephone network,
has very much improved lately,
while fixed lines
have not grown much.
In 2015,
the mobile phone subscription rate
in low and middle income countries
was almost 100%.
However, broadband internet is still
largely unavailable
to people
living in those countries,
where less than 1 in 10 people
have access.
Broadband internet backbone networks
need much greater capacity
than voice traffic,
typically using fibre-optic cables
which have generally
not been deployed yet.
As a consequence,
broadband internet is expensive
when it is available at all.
It remains typically limited
to major urban areas
and to internet cafés,
businesses, and high-income
residential customers.
Finally,
there is the problem of water
and sanitation infrastructure.
Piped water is not accessible
to a large fraction
of the population.
In urban settings in Africa,
in 2005,
about 39% of the population
had piped supply,
as compared to only 4%
in rural areas.
When piped water is available,
supply is often intermittent,
and the quality of the water
can be quite poor.
For sanitation as well, there is
a lack of basic infrastructure
such as sewerage systems,
or water treatment solutions.
There are more challenges
related to infrastructure,
but these should be remembered
as they will influence
the design
of innovative technologies.
The second challenge is
the lack of trained personnel,
which, of course,
is related to access
to adequate education at all levels.
We have seen that
"ensuring inclusive and equitable
quality education for all"
is sustainable development
goal number 4.
Technology is generally developed
thinking that a certain level
of competence to use,
maintain, or repair it
will be available.
When it turns out
not to be the case,
the result is failure.
According to the world bank,
in some of the poorest countries,
the share
of primary school graduates
who cannot read a single sentence
ranges between 25-50%.
Today,
50% of the world's working population
are farmers, or self-employed.
Two thirds of them are poor.
They work mainly in activities
such as farming a small plot of land,
selling vegetables on the streets,
sewing clothes or offering
a range of services
in urban areas.
Firms in developing countries
rank acquiring
appropriately skilled workers
as one of their top concerns.
However,
providing appropriate
training capacity and opportunity
is not enough to assure that
the skills will be available.
When a person receives
adequate training,
he or she will be looking
for a well paid job.
Since such jobs are scarce,
there are chances
that the person won't be able
to work in the domain
he or she trained for.
This may result in skilled people
leaving the country
or taking up other jobs
such as driving a taxi.
For example,
in this picture, you can see
a technician responsible
for maintaining and operating
an emergency generator in a hospital.
People like him do the best they can
with the basic,
often self-acquired knowledge
that they've got.
However, if he gets
additional training,
there are chances that he will look
for a better paid job elsewhere.
and the hospital will need to
find another technician.
As a consequence, as we think of
technology innovation,
it is important to have in mind
that the rotation of skilled labor
can be quite important.
In general,
there is a need for solutions
that are simple enough
to require little or no training
to start with
for safe and effective operation
of the technology.
If that is not possible,
one should think of smart
and affordable solutions
to offer training
and refresher courses
to the people who need them.
Our third challenge
is quite obviously
the lack of financial resources.
As illustrated here
in this slum in Haiti
people in countries
we are interested in are poor
and we have seen that this poverty
has many dimensions.
We need to understand
how these dimensions of poverty
influence the purchase, the use,
the maintenance, the repair and
the decommissioning of the technology
that we are planning to develop.
For example,
in industrialized countries,
many solutions involve consumables
such as razor blades,
or ink cartridges for printers.
This may be convenient in some cases,
and not at all in other situations
where logistic supply chains
are not efficient
or when public budgets do not plan
for recurring costs.
The investment behavior
of households and individuals
are, of course, conditioned
by a need to very closely manage
the little resources they have
and maximize the impact
of these resources.
As a consequence,
when budget is tight,
solutions which allow re-use
instead of disposal
are often much better.
It is striking how much poor people
invest in communication technologies.
Mobile services can indeed represent
up to 20% of a household's spending.
However, there are many good reasons
to do that,
such as improved access
to market knowledge,
or keeping crucial social links.
Also, the poor generally
don't own credit cards,
nor have they access to
traditional banking services.
Cell phones are increasingly
being used
to transfer money
from one user to another.
The poor are also very vulnerable
to various financial shocks,
such as sudden illness of
the household's breadwinner,
or bad harvests due to climate.
Hedging against those risks
is a crucial component
of how these societies work.
Lack of financial resources
at a household,
community, or state level
have numerous
and complex implications
which may influence the adoption
of a new technology.
It is necessary to spend time
and effort
together with local stakeholders
to understand these implications.
We have seen the 3 first challenges
of the context of low
and middle income countries:
a lack of quality infrastructure,
a lack of trained personnel,
and a lack of financial resources.
In the next video, we will discuss
the remaining ones:
harsh environment
and poor governance.
Goodbye.