If we take the ratios
we train at the Yaoundé school
of medicine, in radiology,
roughly 6 to 7
radiologists a year.
And in Cameroon there are
roughly 100
radiologists that work
for 20 million inhabitants,
but the problem
is that if we take these numbers,
we think it's not bad!
They are not
equally dispatched,
They are concentrated
in the urban areas,
in the big cities
and there are whole regions
without radiologists.
So there is a problem
with the amount,
and a problem
with the spatial dispatching.
And what do they say?
They say if you send
me to the outskirts,
I get there
and there is no equipment!
So what I have learnt,
I am not going to apply it,
I am going to forget everything,
why would I go there?
So this is why
they will do anything to stay
in the urban areas and cities.
I started doing
MRI scans.
But I don't know if I can
turn on a MRI machine on,
because when I started
the machine broke down.
What I learnt, I am
forgetting little by little
because the machine doesn't work
and the special exams,
we never do any.
So I don't know what to
do if I have to do one one day.
I don't know if i could do
it without help
maybe from a book or
I don't know
Those are the difficulties
we encounter in our field.
We forget for example
the doses
For a child,
a thorax child,
we forget the doses
and the working parameters
and we can over-radiate
an organ
whilst the practice of
the training would permit
us to keep up
an acceptable level.
Obviously when we don't
work for a while
like a muscle that we
don't use, it gets weaker
the brain could lose everything
at least its working speed
or memory of parameters
or certain positions
to acquire the adequate images.
I think the principal problem
is really the personnel,
because generally we can
manage to buy an echograph machine
when we don't yet know
how to use it
And once the machine is there
either we will try to train someone
or we ask the minister
and sometimes we are given
a young person
that just finished his or her
training
and is still
looking to learn.
So for me the main problem,
is the human ressources
for using the machines.
Compared to the rural zones,
as you have seen
the equipment in these zones
is used
by personnel who is getting old
on one hand
and on the other hand who is
not well trained.
So it would be best if we
did some training courses
to do so we would
need to bring them to the city,
to do short training programs
to use the equipment better
and be able to do exams
they don't know how to do
because they don't know
how to use the technology.
We can't allow in our countries,
high quality equipment
equal to those in Europe
if we don't have locally based
personnel properly trained.
When we have a project
for example to equip
a hospital or a
medical imagery center,
we only think about the equipment,
and not those who will use it,
and who will maintain it,
and who will look after it
for the maintenance
and daily running.