When we buy new devices
it's hard at first,
because the expensive
public market procedures
are laborious,
but when we eventually do it,
the device that is delivered
is often not adapted to our needs.
It cannot cope with two things
that are important here.
The instability of the power supply
is a major cause.
Power shuts off abruptly
while the device is functioning.
And when it comes back there is voltage surge,
which burns
the devices because
they are not
protected from that and we do not have
AC electric supply
that is stable.
So these new devices
are not really adapted for here.
They are maybe too delicate for us.
And when the breakdown occurs
We often do not have the means
to repair it, because we have
difficulties getting spare parts.
There could be one technician
in Yaoundé, but
he doesn't have time,
so repairing
is difficult.
So the devices could be new
or old,
but all are fragiles,
and not really adapted
to these problems or
even humidity problems.
And they are difficult to repair
because there are no spare parts and no staff.
So, we've estimated the availability
of devices to somewhere
from 5 to 15%
in the whole country
depending on the districts.
Hello, and welcome
to this first video of our course
entitled Technology Innovation
for Sustainable Development.
As you have heard
from the brief video,
there is a fundamental problem
with existing technologies.
They are poorly adapted
to the context and the needs
of countries such as Cameroon.
Of course
this is not restricted
to medical technologies
as many others
are crucial for development.
But which are they?
How can we maximize the chances
that new innovative technologies
really deliver their full potential
and in a sustainable way
to the people who need them?
We look forward to developing
these topics and many more
together with you,
but first let us introduce ourselves
as we will be your guides
through this journey.
Hello.
My name is Solomzi
or Soli Makohliso.
I am Biomedical Engineer
by training,
but I have been involved
with entrepreneurship
and start-up companies
for almost 2 decades now,
in Africa, the US, and Europe.
My area of personal interest now
is technology-based innovation
and entrepreneurship
for purposes of having a profound
and sustainable impact,
especially in sub-Saharan Africa.
It’s a great challenge,
but yet an exciting prospect
for us to put together this course.
Because I am a true believer
in the power
of technological innovation
being able to leap-frog
developing countries
out of poverty in certain areas.
Therefore by making this course,
it is our wish that
it can help make a contribution
towards harnessing this power
of technological innovation,
even for those languishing
at the bottom of the pyramid
in society today.
I am Klaus Schönenberger and I have
an engineering background.
I have spent over 10 years
in the private sector,
in research and development,
operations and business development.
I spent most of that time
in the field of medical devices.
After a certain while in my career,
I noticed something
that really shocked me:
Less than 10%
of the world’s population
consumes over ⅔ of all
medical devices produced.
I was appalled.
How could it be that such
an overwhelming majority
of the world’s population
had so little access
to essential medical devices?
This got me to engage
on a fascinating exploration
which took me back to academia
as I am convinced that
we have to deeply change
the way we develop
technological solutions
to meet the needs
and aspirations of the poorest.
I discovered also
that there were many other
essential technologies
which were sorely needed
in developing countries,
but which remained
desperately inaccessible
to those who need them most.
I am glad that you have
decided to join this course.
If you have registered
for this course today
we assume that you are interested
in how technology innovation
can foster sustainable development.
You are curious about
how technology can be an enabler
for the poor to improve their lives.
We assume that you want
to learn how to proceed
towards developing
and deploying sustainable
and impactful solutions
based on technology innovation.
Perhaps you have a project
idea of your own?
An idea of a new technology that
could have an impact on poverty?
Or perhaps,
you are simply intrigued
by the role that
technology innovation
could or should play in development.
Whether you are from
an industrialized country
or from a developing country,
whether you are an engineer,
or a scientist.
Whether you are employed
in an existing company
an NGO,
an international organization
or a state department.
Whether you are
an independent entrepreneur,
or simply a passionate individual,
this course is for you.
In this course
you will learn how
to develop innovative technologies
that contribute
to sustainable development
in countries in the Global South.
For that you will need
to understand,
and be able to integrate
the influence of the context
that prevails in these countries.
We will give you a set
of powerful strategic tools,
that will make you a leader
capable of steering
your project towards success.
This involves understanding
what are the crucial steps
in the process,
the risks and opportunities.
We will teach you
how to minimize these risks
and capitalize on the opportunities.
What we are aiming for
is not the development
of a one-off solution
for, say a village
in Africa or South-East Asia.
This is not just about making
one prototype
and considering the job done.
We want to teach you
how to come-up with solutions
that can be widely and sustainably
deployed and scaled-up,
so that impact is maximized.
As we will see in detail,
our strategy relies
on entrepreneurship.
We believe that
the most efficient
and sustainable way
to deploy a technology innovation
is to find a robust business model,
which will make sure the technology
is made widely available
and also supported in the long run.
Now let us have a look
at the structure of this course.
The course entails 6 chapters.
In the first chapter,
we will provide you with the basics
on poverty and its alleviation.
You will learn
how poverty is defined,
how it is globally distributed,
and about its determinants.
You will also hear
about the major initiatives
launched by the United Nations
to fight poverty,
such as the Millennium
Development Goals before
and the Sustainable
Development Goals currently.
In this chapter we will also discuss
which technologies could be deemed
essential for development.
And we will tell you
about the challenge
and the particularity of the context
found in many or most
developing countries,
and how this context
influences technology innovation.
In the second chapter you will hear
about the 8 Essential Technologies,
where we will give you an overview
of why they are essential
and also discuss
their global access.
In chapter 3 we will
give you an overview
of the process to develop
and deploy technology innovation
adapted to the context
of those countries.
We will present the first
of 3 strategic tools to you,
which is the Impact Canvas.
Which is essentially
a tool that helps you define
your desired
social impact or objective,
and strategies
to construct and monitor steps
towards that social
objective or impact.
We will also introduce a case study
that will help us better
illustrate the use of the tool.
And in chapter 4 you will learn
about what we call
the Product Value chain tool.
This is really
an important methodology or tool,
as it allows you to understand
all the stages
of the product's lifecycle,
including the influence
of the different stakeholders
and the context itself, of course.
In Chapter 5 we will introduce
what is termed the
Business Model Canvas tool,
which is a great and relatively
simple-to-use methodology
to generate solid and sustainable
business models.
However, we have adapted
this tool in this course
to also suit the specific objective
of technology innovation
for sustainable development.
And finally in chapter 6
we will discuss all the 3 steps
of the technology innovation
process in more detail,
as well as how and when
the 3 strategic tools
discussed before are used
to maximize impact
and minimize risk of failure.
We look forward
to your participation
in the course.
We think that
we all have a role to play
in trying to improve the lives
of the poorest people
on this planet.
This MOOC is a unique
opportunity also for us,
as we have a chance
to learn from the experience
of hopefully thousands of people
who are working in this field.
We really hope to get your feedback
so that we can share
the best practices
and have a wide-scale impact
on this unacceptable divide
between the rich and poor,
between industrialized
and developing countries.
We wish to repeatedly emphasize
that developing
technology innovation
for sustainable development
is not something
that can be done alone.
Such projects require
a major effort
to reach out and collaborate
with people from various disciplines
and in various countries.
What is needed, to start with,
is a good dose
of entrepreneurial spirit,
grit and determination,
but also a spirit of openness
and flexibility.
For the rest,
it is the purpose of this course
to give you the necessary
knowledge and tools.
Now let’s get started!