Welcome back.
I am sure you are aware that, currently,
no Smarty City is fully functioning.
We are moving toward Smart City,
and Smart City is actually, rather, a process
than a final state.
Therefore, it may be a little bit premature
to talk about all the challenges
that we see in Smart City services.
What we currently see is that
Smart City services
will raise, we think, 3 main big challenges:
the challenge of services integration,
the challenge of universal
service obligation,
and the challenge of quality.
Let's briefly come back to the conceptualization
of this entire MOOC.
Namely, the idea that you have
infrastructure services
that has already been infrastructures
and, traditionally, the services are delivered
on the basis of the infrastructures.
Now, on top of that we have a digital layer
in between
that, as we have said, changes
the  nature of the services,
and changes, actually, the relationship
with the customers.
From there, we can picture the 3 types
of challenges that are raised.
The challenge of services integration
across the layers
or between the infrastructure and the layer.
The challenge of universal service obligation,
and the challenge of quality.
So let's first talk about services integration.
Traditionally, you have traditional infrastructure
services providers in any city.
The water company.
The electricity company.
The different transport companies.
The waste management company.
They generally own the infrastructure
and are now, thanks to digitalization,
capable of developing their services,
new services, on the bases of their
traditional services.
These are the kind of actors that
are taking advantage of digitalization
to improve, to further advance,
their infrastructure services,
but there are also new providers,
like, let's say, a mobility service provider
who does not own any infrastructure,
who can enter into the market
thanks to this new digitalization
and the data that are generated here.
We have already seen, before, that,
in this case,
the new kind of services, the customers
become much more active.
They can become prosumers.
They can interact.
They can even, themselves,
organize the services:
bike sharing services,
sharing economy.
Things like that.
From here follow the 3 main challenges
of services integration.
The 1st challenge,
actually a traditional one,
but exacerbated because of digitalization,
is the challenge of services coordination
across the different services.
So, the traditional operators,
urban infrastructure operators,
have their different services.
Vis-a-vis the customers, now,
these services are being integrated
or connected.
You can offer, let's say,
to citizens,
customers who own electric vehicles,
you can offer combined mobility
and energy services.
Of course, these kind of services
have to be integrated
physically, and electronically
as well.
So this is the 1st challenge.
The 2nd challenge is the one
of data integration.
This, of course, affects, in particular,
the new services providers
because they can only provide the services
on the basis
of this digital layer, on the basis
of the data
that are generated inside the city,
typically by the traditional
infrastructure services providers,
but sometimes, also, by other actors.
The challenge here is to make sure
these data are integrated
so that the new services are possible.
The 3rd challenge, of course, is, then,
to somehow integrate,
coordinate, old and new services.
Coordinate purely digital services
with traditional infrastructure services
These kind of things need
to all be addressed
at the services coordination level
if we want to have good quality
smart urban services.
Let's go to the 2nd big challenge.
The 2nd big challenge is this challenge
of universal services obligation.
This is a traditional concept that comes
from the traditional infrastructures.
It basically means
that the citizens
should be entitled to some basic services
in terms of quality, accessibility,
and affordability.
This is mainly geared at the weakest
customers,
at the weakest citizens,
who may not be able to afford
or may not have access to these services.
So there are 2 issues here.
The 1st issue is the issue of accessibility.
Think, for example, of information
about public transport.
The new generation gets this information
all on their app on their smart phone,
but there are older generations who are not
equally versed in these kind of technologies
and may not actually have access to certain
of the new services
on the digital layer, in the digital era.
This will be an issue of what
is typically called the digital divide
in the sense that something
needs to be done
to either continue to make access possible
without digitalization for some
types of population,
or to train, to educate, people
in order to also be able to access
these digital services.
The 2nd issue is an issue
of affordability.
This is a traditional issue.
Some of the urban infrastructure services
are essential, like water, like energy,
like some sort of public transportation.
These services may not be affordable
for some of the citizens,
and digitalization does not change anything.
It is not because of digitalization
they will be more affordable,
even though we have seen there may
be some efficiency gains.
The issue here is triple, actually.
There is an issue of equity.
Do all the people have equal access
to these services?
There is an issue of social tariffs.
In case some groups of citizens cannot
afford the services,
should we have different tariffs?
It may be lower water tariffs
for some people for whom water
is not affordable.
Or also questions of subsidies.
Should some households be subsidized
for some of the services?
Also, in the digital era, this question
of affordability will continue to exist.
The 3rd big challenge is the challenge
of quality of services.
We have already said that
in the digital era,
the customers are somehow empowered.
They may create, commence, communities,
shared economy.
They may offer services themselves.
They interact much more
with the services providers.
The remains issues of competition.
Remember when I talked about this tendency
on the digital layer towards concentration,
towards winner-takes-all.
That has a tendency to lead
to monopolies.
That may actually hamper the quality
of the service.
Typically, traditionally, we think that
the quality of a service is guaranteed
thanks to competition, but competition
may not always work
or may not work perfectly.
It will not necessarily work better
in the digital era
than in the traditional, before.
There remain regulatory issues
to make sure that also in the digital era
competition works.
The 2nd big issue is a legal issue.
It is an issue of liability.
There has always been questions
of liability if the bus does not come.
If the train is late, we now have rules
about liability to the customers.
If you get bumped from an airplane,
for example,
but the problem of liability is,
of course,
exacerbated because of the digital nature
of services.
Some of the providers may not be,
themselves,
actually, will not be, themselves,
the providers of the services.
They just have the app by which you
buy the services.
So the question will be,
who is ultimately liable?
Is it the infrastructure provider?
Is it the app owner?
Is it the other citizens in the case
of some sort of shared services?
So there will be big liability issues
that we will have to clarify
at the services layer.
I have now presented to you the main
3 challenges that arise
at the services layer.
Many of them are still a little bit theoretical,
but cities are already starting to face
these challenges.
So let's hear from a practitioner
what kind of challenges and how they
are facing these challenges.
Stay tuned.