Hello and welcome back
to the course.
Today I have the pleasure of having
Norbert Ender
and Ulrich Schimpel
with me from IBM.
Let's get to the first question.
Can you explain to us
and our participants what are the key
strategies to use big data analytics
for managing urban infrastructures
and how different are they
from traditional approaches
in using data?
Yes, thanks for having us.
Very good question.
If we look back we usually think
in system of records which are
data bases or ERP systems that
capture a certain process;
something that we engineer
and use that data for analysis.
Now we are moving more and more into
an area with IoT, mobile devices,
everyone has a smartphone and with
this system of engagement
becoming much more predominant,
we face a huge opportunity
to really bring these 2 systems
together and really put the
user into the center. To have a
user-centric system and
derive insights from this.
We call this System of Insights
that accesses many different data
sources, bridges the silos;
combines it with unstructured data
from the people and then come to
new insights and analytics
that are really to the benefit
of the citizens and of course
of the people running the city.
Yeah Mohammed and a very good
example how this can
be beneficial for the city
and the citizen is the
Smart City project of Madrid.
Madrid turned their process;
how they managed the city services
from an effort-based
to an SLR-based mode. They are
measuring the quality
based on SLA. In order to do that
they established a city-wide
data platform. That platform combines
the ERP data, the contract data
with the IOT data from the cars,
from citizen feedback;
so the citizen can
give feedback through an app.
They combined this and the
evaluate the SLR
and give directions to the service
people; how to improve
and how to operate the service.
The benefit is really huge.
They are saving approximately
1 million euro
with that approach a month so
really beneficial for the city
and also beneficial for the citizen.
They see now a better quality
of the service
for even less money.
Great. Thank you
very much for the answer.
Now let's get to
the second question.
What are the key strategies to
get insight from the city data?
It's going back to the structured
and unstructured data.
Actually we also call the data
'dark data' because 80% of the
data that we are producing with
sensors, videos and audio
and chats are actually not
available for analysis.
Now the idea is really
with this new capabilities of
cognitive computing, machine
learning, artificial intelligence
we have advanced analytics; we have
NLP Natural Language Processing
we have the possibility
to analyze this data and to
derive insights. That actually
brings completely new dimension
of what we can do.
A very nice example of this
is really where you
think of parked cars.
They are parked at least
80% of the time in the city
and they actually do have a lot of
battery. They have very good sensors
and if we can leverage
these new platforms as a service
then you might be looking for a new
parking lot just because you have
some kind of radar in your car.
You might do some gas leak detection
or maybe even observe the traffic
flow with these new systems
and the analysis
of them.
As IBM we see as our aim to make
this easy for city's leaders
and for that we've developed a
platform, a software platform.
It's called Intelligent
Operations Center.
That platform helps really
to bring this data together,
to analyze those data and
we have different use cases
so for traffic management, for water
management, for energy efficiency.
What is also important is
that platform runs on a cloud.
I think it's very important
also as a technology
to put on cloud; to put data on
cloud; to make them available
for different applications and
bring them forth to the clients.
Of course there's also a
downside to the whole thing
which is really the data
privacy and security.
It's not only about the technology
which partially exists but
it's also about the usability
and making people aware
about this sensitive topic.
Countries have different perceptions
and legislation but I think one
very powerful approach is
this approach of opting-in so it is
actually the responsibility of the
people that are offering these
services to convince the users,
the citizens that the services
are of such high value
that they are willing
to give data
for your benefit but of course
also for their own benefit.
Very interesting. Thank you.
Then as a third question, Norbert,
can you explain to us a little bit
what would be a roadmap towards
utilizing big data
analytics in cities?
Okay Mohammed.
We see here 3 steps:
First step is really defined
as more the city strategy
from a business point of view.
Where do you want to have
the priorities? Where
do you want to achieve benefits?
Second one is then develop
the according ecosystem
because there is many parties
has to participate in such a strategy.
Then as the third, develop
the IT roadmap.
Break down the silos.
Define an open data strategy
and approach with a step-by-step
implementation plan.
From the approach point of view,
we see here clear that you must
start and make successes visible
so that you can show the benefits
of Smarter City projects.
Then, accept also failure.
Go step-by-step and learn
and maybe correct
and in all phases really
keep contact to all stakeholders.
Involve them from the beginning.
I think that is also a very
important element of a
Smarter City transformation.
A very good example is actually
the collaboration that IBM has
with Singapore; the Land
Transport Authority there
and again Singapore is well known
for having a very strong strategy
about the city.
Our journey also was a longer process
but also a very agile one.
We started with small POC's,
Proof of Concepts, We started
with simulations and then slowly
put into practice what our
analytics are suggesting.
The topic is basically
incident management.
Whenever a metro line is
blocked by any means
the people still have to
get from A to B
and it's of course a very dense area
so we want to then determine
which buses and other modes of
transportation need to be
put in place to bring the people
to their final destination
with very little time. Of course
now we are in the phase
of then rolling this out and I'm
sure the roadmap will continue.