In the previous session
we talked about the services,
the smart city services,
and the challenges
posed by these services.
In this session, we'll talk about
the challenges posed
to the urban infrastructures
by the smart cities.
And we identify
three such challenges.
First, it's the challenge of standards,
setting the standards.
Then it's the challenge of setting
the right political priority.
And thirdly, it's the challenge
of financing,
financing the infrastructures.
So let's first talk
about the standards.
Now, the standards here
we have already seen.
In the first week we have seen
the question of telecom infrastructures.
The first challenge here is which
kind of network to use.
Are we using
an existing telecom network?
Usually, it's a historical provider,
or is the city developing
a dedicated smart city
telecommunications network?
And the question of course is
if we are using a new network,
who is going to pay for it?
Then, the second challenge is
the interconnection.
We have also seen in the first week
that all the devices,
all these smart devices
need to be connected
to each other via the networks,
via the telecommunication networks.
And so, the big challenge here
is really the challenge
of which standards
are we going to use?
Are we going to have
one single standard,
or if we cannot have
then how good is it
for the smart city?
So who is defining these standards,
is it the telecom operator?
The existing one or the new one?
In case the city develops a
dedicated network,
is it the infrastructure provider,
that is the utilities?
Let's say the energy companies
or the water companies that may have
already their own telecommunications
fiber network in there,
and they are basically
setting the standards for everybody else?
Is it the industry, the different
industries that are involved?
Let's say
the transportation industry itself
is setting the standards
among themselves.
But which industry, is actually
energy industry, transportation industry
that would be the two biggest ones.
Or is the city
setting the standards?
But, here also, the question is
you know, which city
as we have already said several times,
we are generally talking about
metropolitan areas that involve
several cities.
So setting standards by cities
also requires
coordination among cities
to set the standards.
I think currently these kinds
of questions are not yet answered
but need to be addressed.
The second challenge that smart cities
pose to urban infrastructures
is the challenge of setting
the right political priorities.
And we see three such challenges.
First, I think the city needs
to get clear whether it wants
to be about infrastructure
development
and putting in the infrastructures,
or whether
it basically wants
to promote itself as a smart city,
more on the marketing kind of side.
Each of them has risks.
You can develop the infrastructure,
and the smart city doesn't really follow.
Or you can just promote the smart city,
but then you don't really have
the infrastructure in order to follow
upon the marketing that you made.
The second big question
or challenge
in terms of political priorities is
whether you focus
rather on infrastructures,
infrastructure development
including telecommunications
infrastructures?
Or whether, as a city, you focus on
smart city services?
So, setting up the infrastructures
and hoping first,
and hoping that
the services will arise,
setting the right infrastructures,
the right standards
and then automatically the smart
city services will arise.
Or as a city, you want to be
into smart services
smart health services, smart
transportation services,
smart kind of city services.
That's I think the second big question,
political question
that a city has to ask itself.
And the third big question is
on which of the dimensions
of a smart city to actually focus?
At least in terms of priority,
should we start with transports?
Smart transport with smart energy
with smart public services?
Something else, smart buildings?
But, you usually cannot do
everything at the same time.
So which are the most urgent
problems where you reap
the most rapid benefits,
and this I think
is the second big challenge
for a city.
The challenge of setting
the right priorities.
The third big challenge that
smart cities pose
to urban infrastructures, is in
terms of financing.
In the first week of this MOOC,
I have already talked about
the tendency that the value-added
for the city,
thanks to this digital layer,
is moving to the services layer.
Potentially, the profits are rather
made at the services layer
than at the infrastructure layer.
This, I think, is a general tendency
of digitalization.
Now, what does that mean for smart cities
and smart city infrastructures?
As a city you need to make sure
that the services,
the smart city services providers
are not just simply
taking an advantage, cream-skimming
the urban infrastructure
without putting any money
back into this infrastructure.
They are profiting, let's say
a pier-to-pier taxi service
will take advantage of
the infrastructure, but does not
really put anything back into
that infrastructure.
And so the challenge that arises here,
basically a regulatory challenge
for a city is to make sure that some
of the profits that are made
at a services layer get reinvested
back into the infrastructure.
And this is not just for transport,
this is for energy,
for water, and all the value-added
services
that are made at the digital
services layer.
So reinvesting and regulating
reinvestment into the infrastructure,
I think, is the second big issue.
And the third big issue here is
of course,
the investment in
the smart city itself.
So we have seen that
the smart city needs networks.
We have previously talked about
telecommunication networks.
It needs devices, smart devices,
in order to be operational.
And typically, these kind of things
have to be paid for,
either by the city itself,
or by the private investors.
But if you want to have
private investors, the city needs to set
the conditions for this to be
attractive to private investors.
That's another big challenge
for financing urban infrastructures.
To conclude, in the previous session
we have talked about
the challenges that smart cities
pose to the services layer.
In this session, we have talked
about the three challenges
to the infrastructure layers
of a smart city.
Namely, standards, political priorities,
and financing.
Now in the next session we will
summarize all these challenges
across the three layers and see
what these challenges
mean for smart city managers.
Stay tuned.