Welcome back.
In this session, I will summarize
the main strategic issues
that City Managers
have to address.
And these strategic issues
we distinguish them
along the three main layers:
Infrastructure, Services,
and Data or Digital Layer.
Now, let us start with
the Digital Layer,
with the Data Layer, because
his is the real novelty in Smart City
and probably the most important
layer to pay attention to.
We distinguish 5 areas,
in which you have
to make strategic decisions.
We just put here the main
things to consider.
So, on the Data Layer,
let's look at the technological
strategic decisions
and here the main question is
really about standards.
Which standards for the
Telecom Infrastructure?
which standards for the devices?
So that everything is optimal
interconnected.
On the financial side,
this is the question of
the pricing of the data.
How much are you prepared to pay
for the data?
Are they open data?
Are they free?
Who pays for the data,
ultimately?
On the political side,
it's a question of regulation.
Of course, managers do not
regulate
but, managers will behave
differently depending on
whether the data layer is
regulated as an infrastructure
with basic questions of access?
Or whether it is regulated as services
that are competing against each other.
On the social dimension,
the typical questions, the typical
strategic decision
that have to be made
are about data ownership.
Are these data owned by the
citizens themselves?
Are they owned by the city?
Are they owned by the operators?
Are they owned by the carriers?
The Telecom operators?
So, here these kinds of strategic
decisions need to be made
and of course, also decisions
about levels of privacy
that need to be granted.
And on the environmental side,
there are all kinds of
considerations, strategic decisions
about the life cycle
of digitalization.
We all know that many
of these digital devices
also have environmental impact
and we have to consider and
strategically decide about
these digital devices.
Now, let's look at
the Services Layer, okay?
Now, we have already mentioned
before that the main challenge here
on the technological side is
really services integration.
It's about making it possible that
services can be linked to each other,
that they can be bundled, and
they can be offered as a bundle.
On the financial side,
it's the whole strategic decision
about competition and cooperation.
Competition and cooperation
amongst the services providers
but also competition cooperation
amongst services themselves.
On the political side,
It's the whole question of
the type of services
that you want to develop.
Services rather for the citizens,
rather commercial services,
rather transport,
rather in other areas.
So those are
strategic decision to make
On the social side,
It's the whole question of
Digital Divide.
How inclusive do you want to be?
What kind of solutions
do you offer to citizens
who are not capable to fully
participate in the digital world.
As we have already seen, also,
was the question of liability.
If something goes wrong,
if some of these services
are not satisfactorily provided.
Who is ultimately liable?
The service provider?
The infrastructure provider?
The Telecom operator?
Who ever.
And on the environmental side,
I think the fundamental
strategic decision is
whether you want these services
to really respond
to the changing citizen behaviour,
consumer behaviour
or, whether you want these
services
to ultimately optimize the existing
urban infrastructure systems.
Now, on the infrastructure
themselves
I think technologically
the first question to...
the first strategic decision
to make is,
how to integrate new
infrastructures?
New buses, new smart meters
into the legacy infrastructures?
How do you integrate
these kinds of things?
On the financial side,
it's of course the question of who
pays for the digital infrastructure?
Who pays for the smart meters?
Who pays for all kinds of devices
and even the Telecom infrastructure
that is necessary?
On the political side,
one has to be aware of the
longterm impact of  these decisions.
We are talking about infrastructure,
so, whatever technology
is being bought or
implemented will be there
for quite a long time.
so it is important to make the right
strategic decision.
On the social side,
there are of course, all kinds of
externalities
with urban infrastructures.
Some parts of the city,
some citizens
may bare the cost
of these externalities
while other ones may take profits.
And these are considerations
managers have to make,
and finally,
on the environmental side,
there are of course, also
life cycle considerations
of the infrastructures themselves.
So, in this session we have now
talked about
the strategic decisions that
managers may need to make.
In the next session, we will
talk about the decisions
that policy makers need to make.
So stay tuned.