Welcome back.
In this session,
we will now talk
about the strategic decisions
that policy-makers will have to make
in order to move
towards a smart city.
And we will use
the same distinction
along the three different layers.
Namely, the infrastructure,
the services,
and the digital or data layer.
At the end,
we will briefly conclude
the entire MOOC.
Now, in this matrix,
you see the three different layers.
You will also see
the five different dimensions.
So first, let's move along
the digital layer.
The first considerations,
the technological considerations
that policy-makers need to make,
is to decide whether
they want to rely
on their own companies,
on local startups,
or whether they want to use
the knowledge and the expertise
of global players.
Then on the financial side,
they have to make a basic decision
whether they want
the digital and the data layer
to be market driven
or public policy driven.
Are the data a market
by which they attract companies?
Or are they an object
of public policy
that they try to implement?
On the political side,
the big decisions,
the strategic decisions,
are about privacy
as a matter of regulation.
How much privacy?
And of course,
it's always a question
about ownership.
Who owns the data, ultimately,
is a political decision.
On the social dimension,
I think there is
a big policy decision
about digital literacy.
Do the city politicians
want to promote digital literacy
and sort of have their citizens
be the leaders in digital literacy?
Or do they simply want
to have the citizens adapt
to this kind of digital challenges.
On the environmental side,
of course there are a lot of broader
environmental considerations
about digitalization.
How much environmental impact
does digitalization ultimately have?
And how much environmental good
does digitalization
ultimately bring?
On the services layer,
I think the politicians
and policy-makers
have to make a decision
as to whether the city
is simply a user of a platform
that they have bought
from somewhere.
Or whether the city
is on its own a platform owner
and a platform provider
for other users.
On the financial side,
the question is whether
they want to enable
the development of services,
encourage the development
of services by others,
or whether they want to develop
the services themselves.
On the political side,
this is the question
of the governance of the services.
We have already seen
through sharing economy,
there are new companies
where the citizens get involved
in the services themselves.
And this raises
totally new questions
for policy makers
as to how to govern
the new smart services
that are provided in a city.
And on the social side,
we have already seen previously,
that the big strategic decisions
are about the universal
services' obligations.
That is,
what kind of services,
what minimal services,
that the citizens are ultimately
entitled to in the digital age.
And the on the environmental side,
it's more a strategic decision
as to whether to let
the services evolve
by themselves, Laissez-fair,
or whether the cities
want to incentivize
the behavior of the citizens,
so as they use
rather green services.
On the infrastructure side,
and as we have seen previously,
the big strategic
decision for policy-makers
is of course,
whether to use
the existing network,
or whether to develop or to buy
a dedicated network
for the smart city.
On the financial side,
we have previously discussed,
and we summarize here again.
It's the whole question
of sustainable financing
in a context where the value added
is actually moving
to the digital layer.
So the question of how
to generate the money
that is ultimately flowing back
into the urban infrastructures.
On the political side,
it's a little bit the  question
of the development
of infrastructures
for smart city.
Or wether it's more about
the promotion and marketing side
to promote the city as a smart city.
On the social side,
the whole question is:
"The smart city for whom?"
Who is really
the goal of the smart city?
The citizens?
The inhabitants of the city?
Or is it ultimately about
the competitiveness
of a city,
in an increasingly competitive
global economic environment.
And on the environmental side,
the question that policy-makers
have to ask themselves,
How central is the environmental
issues ultimately for them?
And that will decide
what type of infrastructure
they will put in.
Now there are two more things
I want to say before
we conclude this MOOC.
We have always insisted
that we talk about
urban systems,
about socio-technical systems.
Now for pedagogical reasons
we have treated transportations,
smart urban transportation systems,
and smart urban
energy systems separately.
But we should not forget
that ultimately
we are talking about
a system of systems.
With subsystems being:
the water system, the sewage system,
the housing system,
the green infrastructure systems,
all of them
being connected to each other.
And thanks to the digitalization,
becoming even more integrated.
And services also becoming even more
integrated as a result of that.
So first we mark
the systemic nature of
urban infrastructure systems.
The second thing
I want to talk about
when looking into the future,
is technological developments.
Now we have very much
insisted in this MOOC
on the digital technologies.
And the progress made
in the digital technologies
as a game changer
for urban infrastructure systems.
But,
there isn't just digitalization,
there are a lot of other
technological developments
that affect the various
urban infrastructures.
So let's look at some of them.
In the transportation sector,
we see substantial
technological progress
towards self-driving vehicles
and that will be another step
in the changing
urban mobility systems.
We also see a lot of substantial
technological changes,
in terms of storage, batteries,
which will ultimately make a link
between vehicles
and urban energy systems.
We see a lot
of technological developments
in electricity generation,
more and more decentralized,
more and more efficient generation.
Other technological developments,
In terms of drinking water
and waste water treatment,
which become much more efficient.
In terms of recycling,
we see technologies
for waste treatment,
for waste handling,
making the urban resources
much more circular.
In terms of housing,
we see a lot of progress
in terms of materials,
making buildings more efficient,
smarter,
and resilient.
And also in green infrastructures.
There is a lot
of technological development
in terms of genetic engineering,
actually bringing
the green infrastructure
more and more into the entire
urban system and metabolism.
To conclude,
in this MOOC, you have learned about
what it takes to transit
toward a smart city.
We have particularly focused
on the three layers.
All along,
we have made this distinction,
between the infrastructure layer,
the services layer,
and the new digital layer
in between.
Which is the novelty
of the smart city.
We have also shown you
how these layers
are related to each other.
And we have shown you two examples.
Namely, smart urban transportation,
and smart urban energy systems.
And we truly hope,
that you have enjoyed this course.
Finally,
do not forget
to finish the mandatory assignments,
and if you are interested,
to write the optional case.
And then, please stay connected.
Through our website, iglus.org
or through the social media.
Thank you so much.