In the first session, we have expressed
several statements on fundamental points:
what space is, why it matters,
and how to address it.
In the next two sessions, we'll begin
to apply this first block of notions
to two seemingly heterogeneous realities:
the world, the most encompassing
human environment,
and the individual,
the most basic operator in a society.
As for the world, we will see
the apparent complication of this subject
can be turned into complexity,
that is, something sophisticated
but made simpler thanks to reasoning,
concepts and models.
And here, let me tell you,
a spatial perspective
can really be useful.
The world,
an evident geographical reality,
but so big, so complicated.
Can we identify some simple ideas
to think it out?
The world has, of course, something to do
with "global" and with "globalization".
But how?
In this session, we'll begin
with a general discussion
about the emergence
of a relevant world-scale space.
Then, we will propose a multi-stage
historical view of this process.
Finally, we'll try to present
as simple as possible modelling
to address today's globality.
Let's begin with three defnitions.
The world is the most encompassing
human-inhabited space.
In this meaning, World has a capital W.
Its extent is currently the planet Earth,
a natural environment
with which co-spatiality is
less and less optional.
The process of invention
of this emerging reality
is called globalization.
Globalization is the process
through which the world becomes
not only the frame
including other spaces,
but a relevant space in itself.
Globality means, for any social reality,
its global dimension.
The global dimension is present
in any spatial configuration.
Globality can be addressed at any scale.
Looking at the past,
if we try to give dates
and place the origin of globalization
in the scope of human history,
we immediately realize it's not easy.
If, now, we look into the future,
a forecast of how the world will look like
tomorrow or the day after tomorrow,
is by far more trivial.
Many decisive bifurcations are emerging
or will emerge later.
These bifurcations can alter
the horizon of globalization,
Is it irreversible, its content,
what will a globalized world look like?
And the modalities of globality,
how will globalization happen?
Globalization is an event
with geographical content.
To study it,
geographers should take into account
its contrasting temporalities,
which overlap and interact.
As we have seen in session one,
taking into consideration
what the actors want can be useful,
as it allows us not to be content
with [inaudible] tendencies,
what positivism-inspired forecasts
classically do,
but to seize the weak signals
that develop rapidly,
and can become somtimes suddenly
the major components of a given situation.
Thus, what can be called
ecological awareness,
a notion we will examine
more in-depth in session seven,
which clearly fuels political debates
around the open notion
of sustainable development,
has profoundly influenced the images
of globalization and globality.
Globalization not only includes material
objects and actions on these objects,
but also a moving set
of active spatial representations.
When we first had the opportunity
to see the Earth from the outer space
in the late '60s,
it was not only a new image
but a new reality which was offered to us.
Contemporary globalization,
more precisely the contemporary
phase of globalization,
is a process whose one major novelty comes
from the fact that it is
conceived, discussed,
desired or feared, dreamt, transformed
into myth, narrative or ideology,
in brief, represented,
at the same moment as it is made
as an objective phenomenon.
You can be in favor, or in opposition
to what you call "globalization,"
which is not neccesarily the definition
your colleague or neighbor has in mind.
Anyway, there is no time lapse
between thought and agency.
It is even the opposite.
Acting follows imaging.
A significant difference
from other worldwide events,
such as the discovery of the Americas,
World War 1,
or the totalitarian movements
of the 20th century, can be observed.
In all these global events,
representations of what was happening
were generally constructed
according to a model conceived
for other objects,
and originally deployed at other scales
than that of the world.
It could be argued, however,
that some representations
of the world as such
were present very early
in the colonial conquests
carried out by European states.
But, these images were confined
to a specific sphere, mainly geopolitical.
Current visions of globalization,
that reduce the event
to its economic dimension,
or which are derived from issues
of a different nature, are comparable.
So, globalization is not always
comprehended with its full significance.
However, essentially, the actors
of globalization think about globalization
and speak about it at the same time
that they are inventing it.
This singlularity has encompassed
a double characteristic.
The emergence of a worldwide scene,
where great issues are at stake,
largely diffuse tools
of knowledge and communication,
which make possible
an informed exchange between citizens.
Globalization can then be approached
from a cognitive point of view,
as a moment and an act of knowledge.
Stated otherwise, globalization
is not only a context,
which it is, of course,
but also a text,
a paradigm, an epistemy, a referential,
constructed at the same time
as it is used,
in different registers
and by different types of operators.
From this perspective,
the analysis of the discourses produced
should include the exploration
of the cognitive competencies
of the ordinary players,
and set aside the idea
that these representations
would only be illusions that science
would have the mission to overcome.
From indivudual actors,
to scholars and other kinds of experts,
there exists a continuum
that demands caution
in the establishment
of epistemological boundaries.
This doesn't mean
that science-oriented research
does not have questions, methods
or goals of its own,
but it is necessary to go farther,
and to place all these
cognitive approaches, including our own,
with a comprehensive,
in both meanings of the word,
set, that specifically helps us
to better understand
the dynamic of this complex machinery
that globalization is.
The Earth is approximately
4.5 billion years old.
The world is a much more recent reality.
We can easily imagine a situation
where societies would be scattered
all over the planet,
and wouldn't have any relations
with each other.
That is to say, they would be separated
by infinte distances.
and a large number of small worlds
would then exist,
but not one world.
In this situation, the word "World,"
as a proper noun,
would have no significant meaning.
The idea of a World with a capital W
can make sense
when and only when
the distance relationships
between societies
of their parts, to change.
If I can represent myself
or my environment
as near or far from another individual,
or another society,
this means I could at least in imagination
be nearer or farther from them.
Thus, every single person or object,
that is located on the Earth's surface,
is somehow tied in a systemic device,
which is not reducible
to the sum of its components.
If we see the world in this way,
then we can immediately admit
that globalization,
the invention of the world,
is a geographical event
that began a long time ago.
Many confusing things have been said
about the beginning of mankind.
The natural history
of mammals and primates
is often uncontrollably mixed
with the social history of humankind.
But as a species, that is to say,
with approximately the same
transferrable genetic material,
Homo sapiens is only 200,000 years old.
It is true that there have been,
on Earth, other intelligent species,
some contemporary with Homo sapiens,
such as the Neanderthals,
some having disappeared much earlier.
But the genetic material
of each of these supposed
biological cousins or remote ancestors
actually shows significant discontinuities
with Homo sapiens.
Each of these species had
their own history, which is not ours.
The idea of a trans-species
human history is dangerous,
because it confuses
biological temporality, evolution,
with social temporality, history.
This confusion can easily lead
to finalist narratives,
and to the myth of a biological
predestination of the social world.
Therefore, let's remain careful
when we have a look
at the geography of the humanoids
til the emergence of Homo sapiens
in Africa, two thousand centuries ago.
This moment marked the beginning
of prehistory: that is, history.
This map shows a synthesis
of human migrations
during all the Paleolithic era.
The present-day [Cumenae],
including the Pacific islands,
has been totally occupied only recently,
no more than a thousand years ago.
As archaeological findings show,
there is a correspondence
between the first movements out of Africa
between 100,000 and 80,000 years ago
and the advent of high-significance
technological innovations
such as sophisticated tools,
Mousterian and Aterian industries.
Long-distance mobility appears, therefore,
as a constitutive characteristic
of advanced human societies.
This observation contrasts
with Martin Heidegger's view,
which associates inhabiting,
wohnen in German,
to nearness and immobility.
Heidegger rejects
modern technologies of speed
as part of a forgetfulness of being,
and of the dimension of care
that is present in the situated practices
humans experience
in their existence, Dasein.
This approach can be interpreted
as a glorification
of the riveted-to-the-ground
rural societies.
But this reality represents a small part
of all history over time and space.
Moreover, the maps we have just seen
show that mobility
is not a post-rural phenomenon,
but clearly started before
the beginning of farming,
which appeared approximately
10,000 years before today.
The sedentary nature of rural societies
is more of an exception
than a rule in human history.
Contemporary mobility is closing
the incidental period
of an immobile society,
and creates a certain similarity
of our practices
with our Paleolithic ascendants.
We can also identify continuity
between the first migrations
and our times in another way.
One outcome
of our ancestors' migrations
is that they have progressively created
many of the places we now live in.
Some of them have disappeared,
of course, but not all,
and the newly-invented ones,
in the course of history,
have generally linked up
to pre-existing ones.
Let's imagine a counterfactual history.
We know that Paleolithic migrations
have to be related
to the predatory system
of this period.
Groups of people depleted
their local resources,
and were therefore forced to move.
But if the Neolithic
revolution had bloomed
before global migration,
the increase of soil yield,
namely through irrigated farming,
would have allowed
the whole of mankind
to stay in the same region,
and the population might have grown
to a dramatic extent,
but in the same area.
Then, the stock of places
existing all over the world
would have been reduced
to a restrictive number.
Now, these numerous
and diverse places
are the fundamental resource
of what has become
one of the most
productive sectors: tourism.
In 2012, for the first time,
the activity created by the crossing
of an international border
to visit a place
generated more than
1,000 billion US dollars of receipts.
This industry of elsewhere
has been made possible
because the elsewhere makes sense.
The production of these many elsewheres
began with Homo sapiens'
first long-distance migrations.