If we try to address
contemporary globality,
we face a complicated assemblage
of heterogeneous realities.
Clearly, the society model--
that is, considering the world
as an ordinary society,
such as local or national societies--
does not easily suit
this apparent ontological mess.
Nevertheless, if we bring together
inter-societal approaches--
using, for instance, geopolitical logics,
as if the world was a mere aggregate
of independent societies,
and intra-society approaches--
identifying possible political issues
as if the world were working
as a full-fledged society--
we can transform complication
into complexity.
In this perspective,
we get to the provisional conclusion
that the four principles shown
in the following diagram,
in their combination,
offer a good approximation
to summarize the rationales
of the contemporary world.
We'll have an overall view
on these four rationales,
and we will briefly examine each of them.
The world as a set of worlds
is the part of reality
which most takes us back
to our Paleolithic past.
A world made of human groups who are,
for the most part,
unaware of each other,
meeting by chance
and not imagining any communication
between each other.
In this case, it is not even necessary
to recognize the human quality
to non-members of the group.
The distance
between societies is infinite.
Despite appearances,
this situation has not disappeared.
What is often called "cultural areas"
pertains to this dimension.
These areas can be defined
on a global scale
according to religious
or linguistic criteria,
but also on a more restricted scale,
according to all those
specific characteristics
defining communal identities
which make genuine exchanges
with the outside world difficult.
This is the case
for religious, biological, race,
blood, ethnicity, and physical--
soil, land-- allegiances.
Communal identities do not necessarily
take an aggressive form.
Aggressiveness can be a response
to perceived threats
which may be external--
the invasion of foreign concepts--
or internal--
the secularization of identity.
More is now known
about the way this works,
thanks to the body of contributions
made by anthropology
over the last century.
An awareness of difference,
not as incompleteness
as 19th Century evolutionists
naively believed,
but as profound exteriority,
also constitutes a tool
with which we can gain
a better understanding
of our relation to the world,
and avoid destroying the universes
which exist alongside us--
or being destroyed by them.
The following maps show
the existence of ethnic divides
at different scales of sub-Saharan Africa.
Some of them are very old.
Some have been created or revived
in the colonial period.
The third map shows an extreme
but common ethnic fragmentation,
in Ivory Coast.
This configuration
has been used as a resource
by the different political actors
in the unrests
that stained the country with blood
between 2002 and 2011.
The worlds as a field of forces
is the geopolitical model
that is widely used in the analysis
of international relations.
Even if this model uses the resources
of the previous one,
it is substantially different from it.
The tendency for larger and larger
human groups to coalesce
has been strengthened but also obstructed
by the formation of states,
which, in various conditions,
have managed to capture a significant
share of society's resources.
The state, then, appears to be a structure
that is territorially rigid, and either
incorporates non-state groupings,
or adapts to the other states
by brute force,
as in the partition of the world
carried out by European states
and their epigones.
and fully completed
at the end of the 19th Century,
except for the seas and the Antarctic.
The term "geopolitical logic" can thus
be applied to all the processes
whose focus is on the existence
and territorial integrity of states.
This logic creates configurations
that lead to violence,
because each state, real or virtual,
tends to increase its power
by keeping or extending its territory--
reservoirs of resources, people--
which involves confronting its neighbors
and neutralizing any paths
towards border changes
which might result
in the loss of territory.
This widespread non-communication
is manifested
in the existence of as many different ways
of measuring distances
as each state is an actor,
independent from any other.
As geopolitical atlases show,
every single vision of the world
has its own approach to space,
with no common way
of measuring the planet.
Hence, there is a great fluidity
in geopolitical situations,
with their always-fluctuating
alliances and blocs.
The importance of a place--
which might be a town, or a strait--
can change, depending on the use
that is expected of it
Thus, the three Kuril Islands
that are at issue
in delicate, endless negotiations
between Russia and Japan,
are perceived by the former
as a technical element
in a defense scheme,
and by the latter -- as a marker
of national identity.
Geopolitics, therefore, appears
to be the very antithesis to politics.
Because, unless rapidly toppled,
the most savage of despots
has to deal with at least some sectors
of the society they are leading.
For a conqueror, on the other hand,
the hypothesis of the massive
destruction of the population
is always conceivable,
if it at least guarantees
the appropriation of territory,
which also has the prospect
of potential wealth.
The map that summarizes
the field of forces model is very common.
It is the state-based map of the world.
In 1996, Samuel Huntington tried to apply
the same rationale
to what he called "civilizations".
These grouping areas,
based on a combination
of ethnic and religious allegiances,
were supposed to show the threats
that the West had to cope with,
including, Huntington thought,
preemptive wars.
This conservative, aggressive framework
sees the exchanges between societies
as a mere zero-sum
or even as a negative game.
This approach can be criticized
both as simplistic and static,
as ignoring the complexity
and the dynamic of societies,
and seriously underestimating the
communication flows
of the contemporary world.
It shows the limits
of the geopolitical model.
The world as a hierarchical network
is quite different from the previous case.
This model clearly applies to the world
economies described by Fernand Braudel
and adapted by Immanuel Wallerstein
to take account of their evolution.
What already existed over
a part of the world five centuries ago,
is today experiencing
a remarkable expansion
following the unification of the world
by the West,
and the integration of the major part
of human production
into a unified system of world trade.
This model defines cores,
currently made up of the USA,
Europe, Japan, and emerging countries,
and peripheries linked to the cores
by dissymmetric flows
which maintain the existing
gap with the cores
in the exploited peripheries,
increase it in the neglected
or abandoned peripheries,
or reduce it in the integrated
or annexed peripheries.
What is at stake here is not only
a matter of trade,
or even of monetary exchanges,
it applies more generally
to what has been called
"development"--
that is, a dynamic
in the concerned society
which is both multidimensional
and directed towards
what the dominant representations
of this society consider to be progress.
The examples of Japan,
then the Asian Tigers, and now China,
show that the movements
of the periphery toward the core
do not necessarily suppose a common
definition of what progress is,
or a global unification of values.
In other words,
the unversality of the system
adapts to the existence of cultural areas
(model one) and states (model two).
It takes advantage of it,
and the hierarchical differentiation,
as unstable as it is,
operates on the scale of a system
as a complementarity
that reinforces its stability.
In this regard, it is important
to remember
the theoretical misadventure of Max Weber,
who believed possible to contend
that the Chinese religions--
namely, Confucianism and Taoism--
represented unsurmountable obstacles
to the emergence
of an entrepreneurial class in China.
Today, perhaps with comparable inadequacy,
we have no qualms
about demonstrating the opposite.
We are then a long way from a rationale
of territorialized power,
and in the case of states,
it is rather a question of networks
made of places,
that are equally accessible
by modern transport and communications,
where the issue is not to occupy areas,
but to activate nodes and links
or to create new ones.
The world-space formed in this way
does not have the rigidity
of state partitions.
Even, it is partly driven
by states and other actors
some of whom, the transnational firms,
very powerful.
De-territorialization, like the freeing
of the classic constraints of distance,
is a notion that is essential
to understanding this system.
Nevertheless, this space
is not as abstract and arbitrary
as the speed and size of financial flows
crossing it might suggest.
Looked at closely, these flows
do not spread by chance,
and even if they are speculative,
they are subject to determining factors--
sometimes constraints,
sometimes resources--
which impose them their locations.
These networks cannot be understood
without taking into account
their geographical backgrounds,
including territories,
and the system of places
that organizes these territories.
The internet is simultaneously
global and local,
if we look at its accessibility
and its usages.
It is good expression
of this world network,
and a resource for it.
The world as a society is basically
a successful combination
of the three other models--
collective identity,
economic and social integration,
political legitimacy,
structure-- at a global level.
This concept appears both so grandiose
and so remote from more sordid realities
that one might be tempted
to rank it alongside
the more optimistic myth
of humanist eschatology.
A dispassionate approach
to contemporary globality,
in any case, leads to the affirmation
of at least the partial relevance
of this model.
There are in fact global issues.
We know that neither nuclear radiations
nor CO2 emissions respect borders.
We also know that AIDS or other epidemics
represent a new kind of phenomenon,
in that they are the result of a global
configuration of ways of life,
and might interfere with global
demographic dynamics.
The question is, to know
whether there is a global way
of dealing with global problems.
And yet, it can be said,
at least in certain spheres,
that the answer seems to be positive.
Let's take the case of global justice.
Since the Second World War,
firstly in a confused way,
then more clearly
during the wars in Indochina (1946-1954),
Algeria (1954-1962),
and particularly Vietnam (1963-1975),
we have seen the emergence
of international public opinion.
The origin of this movement
goes back to 1859,
on the battlefield of Solferino,
where Henry Dunant,
the founder of the Red Cross,
invented humanitarian consciousness.
Another seminal event has been
the unexpected creation
by the Nuremberg Court, in 1945,
of a first catch
of a global criminal law,
with the notions of genocide
and crimes against humanity,
that definitely trespass states' borders.
The responsibility to protect
was experimented to prevent a genocide
against the Kurdish population, 1991,
and validated
by the United Nations in 2005.
Finally, after ex-Yugoslavia
and Rwanda's first implementations,
the idea of an international criminal
court, was officially created in 2002.
It is now accepted
by large numbers of states.
There exists no democratic
global government and global parliament,
and the most powerful states
can still impose their rule
on many places and on many topics.
However, we have observed
the complete failure
of the unilateral US war
in Iraq in 2003-2008.
The construction of a world-scale
political legitimacy is not easy,
but no plausible alternative is in sight.
Although relatively autonomous
from each other,
these models interact,
and the following diagram shows
how each rationale
can emerge from the others.
Thus, the formation of an ethnic,
territorial or religious identity
can create a base for the construction
of an independent state,
as it happened in 19th Century Europe.
Conversely, the withdrawal
of societal solidarities,
and the overwhelming re-emergence
of communal allegiances
can lead to the crumbling of the state,
like in Lebanese Civil War, 1975-1990.
Finally, we can read these models in
a diachronic-- that is, historical-- way.
We can consider each explaining model
and each layer of the encompassing cake,
whose layout is differentiated
depending on the period analyzed.
Some thousands of years ago,
the communal model was clearly dominant,
while the 1789-1945 period was marked
by the predominance of a geopolitical,
state-centered model.
Where are we now?
The hypothesis proposed by this graph
is that a world-society model
is slowly emerging,
challenging the domination
of an economic-geopolitical couple.
In conclusion of this session,
we can say that in the current stage
of globalization,
an evolution towards
a full-fledged world society
is not guaranteed,
but it's clearly at stake.