Globalization is not
an elementary, linear process
but has a long, complicated story.
We can consider Paleolithic migrations
as the first step towards globalization.
In the continuation,
six other stages can be identified.
After the Age One,
defined by the diffusion
of Homo Sapiens on the planet,
we can identify six great globalizations
or rather six phases
of the same globalization process.
These phases often overlap.
They can be subdivided
and follow the logic
that is sometimes contradictory.
Connection, the beginning of relations
between the different societies
located on the planet.
The completion
of the exploration of the earth
during the Age of Discovery by Europeans
at the end of the 15th century,
must be put into perspective.
The technical capacity of coastal shipping
to face strong headwinds completed
a process of generalized connections
between societies
that had taken place for centuries
in their old world, the Eurasiafrica
stretching up to the Pacific Northwest,
peopling the Americas,
and with the South Pacific Islands
more or less linked to South America.
The Muslim space constituted
one of the principal links of this world.
It was structured on exchanges,
such as along the Silk Road
that was decisive for the empires
that controlled a piece of it only,
and was more durable than these empires.
We can approach this era
by following the journeys of Marco Polo
along the Silk Road, a major trade link
between the eastern
and western part of Eurasia
as we can see on the following map.
This stage of globalization appears modern
in the sense that it was based
more on the research of information
and the rationale
of commercial transactions
than on conquest and power,
leading to territorial control.
Inclusion: the forced incorporation
into worldwide empires.
Overlapping with the preceding phase,
that of the colonization of the planet
by a limited number
of interacting empires,
characterizes this moment.
Western Europe, joined
at the end of this period
by the United States,
detaches itself and becomes
a unique actor in this globalization.
Europe acts, others must submit.
As [Christian Waterloo] has shown,
two types of positions
should be distinguished,
those which aim to provide
goods not available in Europe--
search for otherness--
and those that project a given society
beyond its borders--
search for mimetic reproduction.
Beyond the destruction of civilizations,
which was not a new phenomenon
but took here a radical turn,
the most salient fact was
the contradiction between exploitation--
which manifests itself
by a predatory inclusion of men,
institutions, cultures, raw materials--
and diffusion, which integrates,
for better or worse,
the colonies into a sphere
of the colonizer's culture,
involuntarily providing
the dominated people
with their values of liberty,
equality and progress
which help them in their emancipation.
Internationalization: the creation
of a worldwide space of exchange.
The sequence is situated between 1849,
British overall control over India,
and 1939 at the apogee
of imperial systems.
To a certain extent,
the openness of developed economies is
comparable to the contemporary sequence.
Two key elements set them apart,
however-- on one hand the exchanges
of commodities are based
on the complementarities
of natural origin.
They result from the contrasts
in productivity
based on climate differences.
This is a continuation
of the first type of colonization.
In the next stages,
the relative weakening of agricultural
and mineral raw materials
in trade balances will give
the impression of a step backwards,
even if this is due to the emergence
of more sophisticated
productive technologies.
On the other hand, the world wars
and the impact of countries closing down
in the aftermath
of the 1929 economic crisis show
that a reversibility of globalization,
which does not seem absurd
to the majority of people of this era,
is always possible
at the price of massive diseconomies
and considerable destruction.
Globalisation refused:
the victorious resistance of states.
The 1914 - 1945 period marks
a complete halt
in the process of opening.
The two world wars
and the treatment of the economic crisis
put the states back in the center
in their refusal
to weaken their prerogatives.
While they were at the pinnacle
of their power,
the active states easily succeeded
in mobilizing their respective societies
through their hatred of the other
and in a exacerbated nationalism.
Logically, this paroxysm of the state is
a low point for globalization.
We must wait for the 1980s
to find an economic openness
equivalent to that of 1914.
It is true that in between times,
the content of these exchanges had
profoundly changed
from the trade of tropical products
shipped to colonial metropolises.
The world of commerce moved
to a map of trade,
based on the exchange of the same type
of manufactured production
in both directions,
in particular between rich countries.
With the collapse
of the Berlin Wall, 1989,
marked the end of the communist hypothesis
of an imperial couner-globalization,
wrapped up
in a universalist-like ideology.
Interdependence: acceleration.
multidimensionality and irreversibilty.
After 1945, changes in the geopolitical
and political context
played a considerable role in the return
to the processes
of globalization of exchanges.
The new element is
the growing role of exchanges
between comparable spaces,
as seen in western Europe,
where, during the post war decades,
the swing from 25 percent to 60 percent
of the international exchanges
made on the continent,
accompanies the political construction,
more than just being
a result of this construction.
It is also the moment
when giant national firms are bulit,
conceived at first
in a mercantilist spirit,
that is to say, as part
of the geopolitical logic
that states developed,
then changing with the development
of transnational firms.
These created an industrial,
then financial,
more and more international network
and this network space made
their citizenship elusive.
In the end, the technical aspects,
reduction of the cost of transportation,
the emergence of digital telecommunication
gave an extra push to the process.
It is not simply a question
of monetary exchanges.
It is the moment where everything
that can be exchanged
between different types of operators
is actually exchanged.
Businesses,
but also nonprofit organizations,
can communicate much more quickly
and at a volume
that has never before been seen.
The current period is characterized
by a generalization
that emphasizes speed
and the changes induced.
An important part
of the circulatory dynamic--
fluidity of information,
cultural exchanges,
increased opportunities for interactions
between the inhabitants of the planet--
is very old.
Globalization of science and the arts goes
back to the 19th century.
This time, however,
all of the exchanges experienced
a rapid growth
and this multidimensionality includes
political debates and issues.
We can follow this political emergence
by examining the phenomenon
of public opinion--
the protests against the Vietnam War,
for example, from 1963 to 1975--
of an increasingly common agenda,
in particular about natural environments
after the nuclear accident
at Chernobyl, 1986,
and the Rio Conference in 1992--
of growth in the role
of thematic international institutions,
IMF, World Bank, WTO--
and the birth of a legal framework
with the International Criminal Tribunal
for ex-Yugoslavia and Rwanda in the 1990s.
Cosmopoliticisation:
the World-society at stake.
Recently, from a date
that is conventionally established
as the fall of state communism, 1989,
appearing as an alternative
to globalization,
interdependencies between different places
on the planet have become generalized
and have reached areas
that did not yet belong
to the usual sphere of exchanges
and public debates.
It would not be absurd
to make this phase start in 1945,
the trials of Nuremberg marking
the introduction
of the "crime against humanity" notion
and of a worldwide
domestic justice conceived
to punish this type of crime.
The International Criminal Court,
ICC, created in 1998
and effective since 2002,
embodies this idea.
Ever since the last decade
of the 20th century
the questions of developments
such as economic growth,
income distribution, education,
public health, natural environment,
but also of migrations and tourism,
have become more visible
as explicit world-scale political issues.
The emergence of versatile digital systems
connecting almost everyone
around the world,
including across small,
formerly landlocked routes,
has made possible a somehow
common perception of these topics.
The general issue
of globalization can then be defined
as the emergence of a complete society
at a worldwide level--
of a world society,
which will add a new level
to geographical situations,
of a societal substance already present--
local, regional, national,
or in construction, continental--
without substituting them,
but by influencing them
and being influenced by them.
All of this contributes
to make politics the crucial point
from which the term,
proposed by Immanuel Kant
at the end of the 18th century,
and recently revisited
by Ulrich Beck, 2006,
of cosmopolitics.
Only politics deployed
on a planetary scale can create,
through governmental institutions,
public policies, parties,
non-state actors, public opinion,
minimal cohesion of a societal type,
between all of the paths
of an already active civil society.
Behind these political debates lie
ethical problems.
What are the fundamentals
of coexistence on a planetary scale,
beyond the incontestable differences
between societies?
It is because this type
of question cannot be eluded
that we can characterize
the current process
as universalization.
This can give way
to paradoxical expressions
like the different forms
in which globalization is contested
and to alternative propositions,
more or less coherent.
From the ultra-globalism
to Islamist terrorism
it is also within anti-system postures,
that reinforce
the supposedly challenged system.
Those who oppose to all globalization,
could be distinguished
from those who support
a different globalization,
that would differ
from the one that they blame
as dominated by transnational firms
and the neoliberal agenda.
In fact, these distinctions are
not so simple,
because there is an intermix
between both attitudes.
The anti-globalization movements combine,
in a manner that is more or less coherent,
several orientations--
the criticism of capitalism in general,
that more specific
of its transnational players,
the condemnation of the United States,
the defence of the nation-state
as the ideal and single-level place
for economic production,
political regulation and social cohesion.
The question of knowing
whether globalization will prevail
is an issue in itself.
Can we imagine a future
for a non-globalized world?
It is not a mere academic query.
Since the last time
globalization was rejected,
after the crisis of 1929,
World War Two started.
In few words,
world-as-society is a major issue
of the seventh stage of globalization.
The world is not a full fledged society,
but it probably is becoming one.
It is not a society
1) because intercommunal
or interstate separations continue
to organize a significant part
of global-scale social life
and profoundly divide the world,
and 2) because the interactions
that tend to unify the world
remain largely based on transactions
and therefore lack
an assumed political dimension.
♪ (gentle music) ♪