So, we've come to the end
of this book
and it is time to acknowledge
the contributions
that many have made to the making
of the book.
Some of them wittingly,
some of them unwittingly.
The key contributions-- of course--
come from Peter Hore,
who wrote this little book
that we have been using in these lectures.
So Peter Hore is
lecturer at Oxford University,
and he has written a book
that I have bought in vast quantities
to redistribute among my students
over the last 15 years or so.
He has made a new addition,
which you see the cover page,
which actually
has come out this week
this is now in June 2015,
in which I am speaking,
and therefore,
you should be able to get it
from your favorite local librarian.
I should say that Peter Hore deserves
a great deal of credit for this book.
He came from the world of EPR--
Electron paramagnetic resonance--
and learned enough about
magnetic resonance of nuclei
to pick out the best
examples, that I am aware of,
of applications of relaxation,
of chemical exchange of bio molecules,
and all of these different branches
of magnetic resonance
that are discussed in the book.
So, the next person
I would like to acknowledge
is Sami Jannin,
he is here in Lausanne,
and he has also recorded some videos
that are part of the book,
in fact the idea that
these videos would give you some feeling
of more recent developments
and modern applications
that go beyond the boundaries
of Peter Hore's elementary text.
I should also acknowledge
the contributions of
Basille Vuichoud,
he is a senior graduate student here,
almost coming towards his PhD,
at the École polytechnique
fédérale de Lausanne,
and he has not been seen on the videos,
but he is responsible for the
preparation of the Power Point material
that you have seen
and also for uploading questions
and multiple answers
on the website of the book system.
Finally, I should say,
that there is an entire team at the
Laboratoire de Résonance
Magnétique Nucléaire Biomoléculaire
who have, one way or another,
contributed to making this book possible,
and you have seen some of the
laboratory in the teaser.
Here in the learning center
of the EPFL
there are at least two people
who have made this possible,
Mathew Goodman has done
all of the editing,
and I have seen some of it
and I know that
it is a very difficult task
and he is very proficient.
Gwenael Bacquet has over seen
the entire effort
and coordinated
whatever needs to be coordinated.
So the team
that makes up the
Laboratoire de Résonance
Magnétique Nucléaire Biomoléculaire
here at the
École polytechnique fédérale de Lausanne
of course, changes from
year to year
but I have taken this picture
from a few years ago
because it shows a nice collection
of activities and specialties.
First of all,
in the first row you see
Diego Carnevale,
who is an expert of solid state NMR
and recently moved to
the University of Neuchâtel,
then behind him Sami Jannin,
in the white shirt.
You know him because he
contributed to the book.
In front of him-- Pascal Miéville
who is now at the staff of EPFL,
and did his PhD in our group,
then myself.
Next to me, Simone Ulzega
in a red shirt, he is now at the Eawag.
Kneeling in front of him is
Roberto Buratto,
who is about to obtain his PhD
here in Lausanne,
It is not necessary to kneel to get
a PhD, but he took some precautions.
Then standing behind him,
is Jonas Milani,
who you will see,
or you may have seen in the teaser
where he is showing how the
samples are put into the spectrometer.
And in a dark red shirt, there is
Nicola Salvi,
who did his PhD in our group
some years ago.
Partly involved in new techniques
for screening of drugs,
and after his PhD went off to
Harvard Medical School for a year,
and he is now in Grenoble
at the Institut de Biologie Structurale.
On the second row you see,
somewhat in the dark,
Takuya Segawa who finished his PhD
at Lausanne,
and is now in Zurich,
working on electron spin resonance.
Then the tallest figure of all is the one
of Veronika Vitzthum
who seems like she descended from heaven
through this circular window
that looks a bit like
a halo above her head,
and she is now doing MRI in Bern
at the Inselspital
and also in Solothurn or Soleure--
Northern Switzerland.
Next to her is Marc Caporini
who is an American post-doc
who after few years in Lausanne
returned to Boston
and became involved in
the American Branch of the Brooker Company
and then recently moved into a company
that makes bio-molecules.
And finally, Aurelien Bornet
who got his PhD a few weeks ago
and will stay in our lab a bit longer
to do dissolution DNP.
Now there is a smaller sub-team,
partly composed of the same people,
that is specifically active
in the field of
dissolution dynamic nuclear polarization.
You see them here in front of a machine
that can cool samples
to 1.2 Kelvin, now that's very cold,
as you may realize
and that can irradiate these samples
by microwave with about 50 milliwatts.
And you see on the right side,
sitting, Sami Jannin,
who is rightly proud of this machine
because he worked on it for many years
and developed it virtually from scratch,
with all the whistles and bells,
and the pumps and microwave sources
and the wave guides, and everything else.
Standing in the middle is
Basile Vuichoud
who is also rightly proud
of his achievements,
and you can see
he is not ashamed of what he did.
And behind him is Jonas Milani
who made many interesting contributions
to this machine. In particular,
a magnetic tunnel
that runs just above his head
through which we can transfer samples
from the polarizer,
which you see in this laboratory
to another magnet which is in
the laboratory behind the wall.
Now to the left of Basile
you see Lyndon Emsley
who is going to be my successor
here at EPFL.
In fact he has just been installed here
on June 1st-- about 11 days ago--
as of today, together with two people
that joined him on a trip from
the École normale supérieure in Lyon.
So I should also acknowledge the fact
that I spend most of my time in Paris,
and I only come to Lausanne
every other week
to give lectures and record books.
And in Paris I am in charge of a team
which is partly at the
École normale supérieure and partly at
the Université Pierre et Marie Curie,
and as you can see,
we meet in regular intervals,
about once a week we have group seminar,
and you see some of the members here
freezing in the February cold at the foot
of the Administration building
of the UPMC.
Actually, many of the important people
in the group are missing,
they are mentioned on the list
on the right hand side.
And the whole thing
is a very lively environment
which stimulates and generates
much interest in research,
both in methodology,
as well as bio-molecular applications
and solid state methods.
Now finally I would like to acknowledge--
so to speak-- the rest of the world,
and I suggest starting with a statement
with a quotation from the Talmud,
and I should say that Hebrew
is not one of the many languages
that I tried to learn at school,
and after that,
but I had a friend who tried to teach me
how to pronounce this
and what I remember of this lesson is
roughly like this:
(speaks in Hebrew)
Whether my Hebrew friends--
or Hebrew speaking friends--
understand that or not,
I can give you an English translation,
or some attempt to translate
this into English:
"From my teachers
have I been enlightened,
more from my colleagues,
the most I have learned from my Pupils".
Now this statement comes from the Talmud
and was brought to my attention
by Dr. Ditsa Pines, who is at
The University of California at Berkeley
where I spent a few months
as a visiting professor.
Now teachers, there are of course,
many I could think of;
my PhD adviser Ray Freeman,
I could think of Peter Hore,
I could think of Richard Ernst,
and of Kurt Wuthrich in Zurich,
with whom I did many interesting things,
or at least things I found interesting.
I can think of Bob Griffin at MIT,
who taught me much about DNP
and about solid state NMR.
I can think of Rigitsa Vold
and Bob Vold at UCSD,
with whom I did a post-doc and I learned
a great deal about relaxation from them.
There are many teachers,
in the narrow sense of the word,
but in fact there are many more,
of course,
there's a vast community of people
whom we come across
when reading papers
and studying brilliant ideas
that have been developed
over the last 50 years or so.
The colleagues-- living colleagues--
are quite numerous.
I am not only thinking of
my immediate environment
who are doing chemistry
or physics, or biology--
and of course--
we learn a lot from them.
But there are also people
who come to meetings
and in my field
there are so many meetings
that you can almost move
from meeting to meeting
without ever going home.
Some of these meetings
are held in Europe.
There is a series that is called Euromar
for European Magnetic Resonance
which I have been the founding chair
of the board of trustees
for first six years
that this organization was running,
and it's now going to be held--
this year-- in July,
it will be held in Prague
in the Czech Republic,
and these meetings, which
group about 5-6-700 colleagues,
are always an opportunity
to learn from them
and to be stimulated
and to discover new fields.
But most of all,
I learn from my students;
when lecturing, when trying to explain
things in a classroom,
when trying to advise
my PhD students,
when revising the drafts
of papers they may have produced,
when arguing about
the best graphical material
and how to present their results
in the most seductive way.
All of these things are interactive
between my students and myself,
and I believe that
one learns most from students,
much more so than from the teachers.
Something that was already realized
at the time the Talmud was written.