Hello and welcome to our
Smart City MOOC.
My name is Matthias Finger, I'm a
professor of Management of
Network Industries at EPFL in
Switzerland.
As you all know, cities are the new
relevant entities in the world.
Economically relevant, socially
relevant, ecologically relevant,
increasingly politically
relevant and, of course,
since long, culturally relevant.
The urban infrastructures are the
very backbone of these cities
and in the previous MOOC, which you
may have seen, we have talked about
a series of key topics.
Namely, first, the distinction
between the infrastructures and the
services that are being provided on
the basis of infrastructures,
then we have talked about
the performance of urban
infrastructure systems.
And then we have explained the
processes of planning, maintaining
and operating urban infrastructures.
We have also briefly mentioned the
emerging role of the information
and communication technologies.
Something which has become known
as Smart City.
Now in this MOOC, we will talk about
the impact of the information and
communication technologies on the
urban infrastructures.
And the important managerial and
governments considerations which are
necessary to unleash the potential
of these ICT's for Smart Cities
and we will do that in 5 separate weeks.
In the first week, we will offer an
understanding of Smart Cities.
then in week 2 and week 3, we will
talk about smart urban energy systems
and smart urban
transportation systems.
Week 4 and 5 are dedicated
to the question of transiting
towards Smart Cities.
In order to complete the course,
please watch the videos.
There are also complementary
readings that explain the various
aspects of the course.
There are quizzes that have to be
taken and at the end of the course
there is a final exam.
You also have the opportunity to
write an optional case
which gives you the possibility to
win a prize.
I hope you will enjoy the
course and stay tuned.