Welcome to the 1st week of our
Smart Cities MOOC.
I'm sure you have asked yourself
whether Smart Cities is a hype
or a reality, or both.
and that is what this first week
is all about, that is understanding
what Smart Cities really are.
Now you can expect the following
outcomes from this 1st week.
First we will talk about thinking Smart
Cities, how to think Smart Cities.
then we will offer a
conceptualization of Smart Cities
and thirdly, we will detail exactly
the impact that digitization has
on cities, making them Smart Cities.
and finally, we will look at the
implications of all of this for
management and governance of
cities or Smart Cities.
Now from our previous MOOC, we take
this basic distinction between
infrastructures or an infrastructure
layer and services or a services layer.
It is on the basis of
infrastructures like water pipes
that water services, infrastructure
services are being provided
to customers and citizens.
What is new is really this digital
layer that comes in between
infrastructures and services
and this changes everything.
Now the 1st week is structured
into 6 different sessions.
In the 1st session, we will present
our conceptualization of cities as
socio-technical systems.
This is necessary because only on
the basis of this conceptualization,
can we really understand the
concept of Smart Cities.
In the 2nd session, we will
look at digitization.
What is it exactly?
In the 3rd session, we will look at
the general implications that
such digitization has on
society, on industries.
In the 4th session, we will look,
in particular, at the implications
of digitization on the cities.
and then we will show that there are
actually 2 different perspectives
one can have on Smart Cities.
Finally we will hear from one of the
leading cities in the world
that has pioneered the transition to
Smart Cities.
So, let us move to the 1st
session now talking about
socio-technical systems