Welcome to this first session.
In this session, we will talk about
cities as socio-technical systems.
This is the way we are looking at
cities in this MOOC.
And infrastructures are a particular
type of socio technical-system.
Finally we will look at the
implications of this view on the
management and the governance of
cities and their infrastructures.
So, cities are a place where people
live and work together.
And different people look at this
living and working together from
different perspectives. So there are
people who look at cities as an
economic system.
The generation of wealth,
the generation of jobs,
the economic interactions, the
economic conditions for the workings
of a city as an economic system.
Typically economists look at cities
as an economic system.
Sociologists rather look at cities as
a social system, it's a way of life
of cultural life, of social life, of
activities, of inequities
and all these kind of things.
Then there are people who look at
cities as a political system,
how the different actors
interact with each other,
who decides about what, who has power
over what. So it is also possible to
look at cities as such
political systems.
Our approach is to look in
particular at cities as a
technological system.
Typically the infrastructures
constitute the
technological system of a city.
And of course all these things are
interrelated which exactly makes the
city a socio-technical system.
The way the technology works effects
the economy, the way the economy
works effects whether you have money
to invest in technology the same for
the social and political dimensions.
So this is the very systemic
view of a city.
Now more precisely, as we said,
the city is a place where people
live and work together.
The infrastructures, the urban
infrastructures enable such
collective living and working.
And this is typically done
in a systemic fashion.
The infrastructures enable the way
that people work, the way that people
live, the way that people decide.
You can easily imagine how the
infrastructures are built that
effects social life. Is it easy to
reach the city center or not?
Is the traffic flowing, is it not
flowing? Is water available?
All this effects the quality of
life, of social life and of
economic life of a city.
But also the other way around
the economic and social
and political life
determines how the infrastructures
are maintained, built, invested in,
developed. So it is easily
understandable that depending on
the political decision making
processes, investments are done in
certain parts of the cities and not
done in other parts of the cities.
Business parks are created here, not
there. So typically the city is such
a complex socio-technical system
that decides upon the infrastructure
which in turn decide upon the
social life of a city.
Now, at the same time, one can
look a little bit more in detail.
To look at the infrastructures
themselves as a socio-technical system.
And so we have infrastructures, such
typical infrastructures, such as
transport, housing, buildings,
energy, water and other things
you can add. Waste water, waste.
And the way these infrastructures
are laid out effect the way that the
social and political and economic
life of a city is happening.
Inversely, the decisions made at
these levels will effect where
housing is going to be, whether
transport is developed here or there
whether energy is renewable
or not renewable
whether water is cleaned
or not cleaned.
So one can really look at urban
infrastructure systems
as a socio-technical system in itself
as part of a larger urban system.
Now this systemic view of cities
clearly has implications on the
management and the
governance of cities.
The most important concept here is
the concept of feedback loops.
So all these elements of the system,
of course, interact with each other
and create feedback.
The social dimensions interact with
the technical dimensions.
The technical dimensions interact
with the economic dimensions and
all this creates feedback loops.
This makes cities very, very complex
and the outcomes of what happens in
the city is never attributable to
one single cause.
All these elements are related to
each other.
And of course, all these things are
also path dependent.
So decisions that have been made at
some point in the past deploy their
effects later in the future. What
happens today, may be caused by
an array of complex interactions
and feedback loops that
come from the past.
Let us illustrate that in the context
of cities. So the city is in its
environment. And as we said,
the city and especially its
infrastructure are a complex
socio-technical system interacting
with each other.
So there are feedback loops
on both sides.
There are technical feedback loops.
The way housing works effects
transport. Transport effects energy.
All these technical feedback loops
are going on inside a city.
Similarly there are social
feedback loops.
The different actors interact
with each other.
What is done economically has an
impact on the social life.
What happens socially has an impact
on finances, on the economic life.
And then, of course, even more
so there are interactions,
as I said before, between the social
dimensions and the
technical dimensions themselves.
So how the technology is laid
out effects the social life,
effects the way people work, whether
they get to work or not, whether
they have water or not and the
other way around, of course, also.
Now all this, and this is our
particular approach to the city,
all this leads to certain types of
performance of a city.
We have classified performance in
terms of efficiency, resilience and
sustainability of cities but it is
easily understandable that all these
feedback loops, the complexity, the
path dependency makes the management
and the governance of these cities
extremely complex, unpredictable
and we need to take that fact
into account when we manage
and govern cities.
This is basically what our previous
MOOC was all about.
What is new is this digitalization,
the data layer which comes of top of
all these cities as a socio
technological system.
And what we are going to do in this
MOOC, is to try to understand what
digitalization as a new layer coming
on top of the systemic view
does to the management and
the governance of urban
infrastructure systems.