Welcome back to the course.
In this session we will talk
about digitization.
What is it exactly?
We have structured this
session into 4 segments.
First we will talk about data
generation and storage, then
about communications and Networks,
then we will talk briefly about
Internet of Things
and finally we will talk about
analytics, data analytics.
So let us start with data generation,
as I am sure you have observed,
data is generated from a growing
amount of sources.
Cameras, sensors, RFIDs, GPS,
including what we call self-generation,
that is the smart phones that you
are using are constantly generating
and transmitting data
and all this data is generated
at an ever lower cost
and by ever smaller devices.
and also the storage capacity where
this data can be stored
is increasing exponentially.
Basically all this leads to the fact
that there is an unprecedented
ever growing amount of data
that is being generated.
So that's the first element of
digitization.
The second element is what we call
communication and networks
and that has 3 different dimensions
that all relate to each other.
On the most basic level we have the
telecommunications infrastructures.
Traditionally these are the wired
infrastructures, the cables, the fibre
but increasingly we have
wireless infrastructures also
where the capacity is increasing
1G, 2G, 3G, 4G, WiMax,
WiFi, satellites.
All this makes up for the
telecommunications infrastructures
through which data is transmitted.
The 2nd dimension is the networks,
that is the different devices that
are being used need to be
connected  to each other
through the telecommunications
infrastructure and this is done
by so called protocols, physically
connecting the different
data storing devices to each other
and the 3rd dimension of this
is the identification and
exchange of this data.
What is typically being called the
World Wide Web, that is the location
of this data by way of unique record
locators inside the different
devices, inside the
different computers.
So adding to the data generation,
this second dimension,
the communication dimension,
connects all the data to each other.
So we have basically 4 things, we have
a telecommunications infrastructure,
we have the network, that is
the devices connected to each other
through the internet,
and then we have the identification
and exchange of the different data
of the devices connected
to each other
thanks to the World Wide Web
and, as we have seen in the very
beginning, we have the data
generation and storage.
Now all this has a growing capacity,
there are more and more things that
can be stored, generated, transmitted,
it has increasing speed, data is
transmitted ever more rapidly,
there are reduced power needs, even
to the point that some of the
devices do not need power
anymore such as RFID's,
all this at an every lower cost
and in an ever smaller format,
miniaturized.
Today you can have, for example,
RFID's directly in each letter
in a cost effective manner.
Now all this together leads to what
is currently being called
the Internet of Things.
That is the different devices
connected to each other,
thanks to the Internet and the
World Wide Web
and this has 3 main dimensions.
So we have exponentially
connected devices,
people say that in about 5 years,
the amount of devices that will be
connected to each other through
the internet will double
then we have exponentially generated
and transmitted data.
Again, for example, people say that
in a house in 5 years,
the bandwidth that will be used by
these devices connected to each other
through the internet will take up
50% of all the bandwidth
and then we have increasingly
real time exchange of data.
Already today, you can supervise
your house remotely though your
smart phone in real time, all this
together is leading to this
phenomenon we call the Internet
of Things today.
Now there is an additional element
that we need to talk about
and this is analytics.
All this data needs to be analysed
and also here, there is a rapid
development in the ability and
the capacity to analyse
and also to visualise these.
The visualisation is
necessary because
analytics often cannot really show
what the outcome is so the things here
that are important are what we all
artificial intelligence,
machine learning, deep learning
tools that basically allow for the
intelligent analysis of all these
huge amounts of data.
This has also been called today
Big Data.
Now.
In our MOOC here, the combination
of all these things,
the storage, the transmission, the
networks and the analytics is
what we call digitization.
It is important to stress that it
is the combination of these things
that makes up for the digitization,
and this digitalisation, as we will
see, in the next session has the
disruptive effect on
absolutely everything
and it also has in the session
after, as we will see, disruptive
effects on cities.
So stay tuned to the next sessions.