Welcome back.
In the previous session
we talked about digitalization;
what it is.
Now in this session, we will talk
about the implications
of digitalization. First in general
on industries
and then on
urban infrastructures.
So let's first start
with the industries.
Traditionally, in any industry
you have a production chain;
a physical value chain.
Take a car whereby it is
assembled at different stages and
ultimately sold to a customer.
The customer is connected to the
final element of the value chain
which is the retailer
in this case.
What changes with digitalization is
the fact that you are able to
mirror this physical value chain
in a data layer.
All the information that is contained
in the physical value chain
is now so to speak, duplicated,
replicated at the digital layer.
The physical layer, the
physical value chain still exists;
continues to produce cars until
the end-consumer/customer
but the information about the whole
process is now, so to speak
in a digital value chain and the
customer can now connect directly.
He can order the car on the internet.
He can assemble the car himself.
He can follow how the things have
been produced along the stages;
what materials have been used,
all this so the customer,
the interface with the customer
now becomes a digital interface.
Think for example on Dell computers
which you buy on the internet
and you assemble yourself
on the internet.
That is the first stage.
The second stage is the fact that
the information that are contained
in that data layer can be used
to produce new services, new business
models and have new customers or
the same customers. Think about the
Amazon example: the first layer
would be that you order your book
digitally. It's still produced.
It still arrives physically and the
second layer would be that you,
as a customer are being offered
advice as to other people who bought
similar books. What other offers can
be made to you and how you could
actually profit from the data that
are contained in that digital layer.
There are new services and there are
new business models. This is a
value added on top of the
traditional, physical value chain.
There are many industries that
are affected by the actual -
Potentially all the industries can
be affected by this evolution.
I have put a list here of potential
industries that can be affected
by this mirroring and
by this digitalization.
What are these? Those are the ones
that are particularly information
intensive. For example, education
or health care where a lot
of information is contained; is
known by the doctors or the teachers
and mirroring these information
on a digital layer and
repackaging them to sell to the
customers has a huge, a huge
disruptive effect on
these industries.
Other examples are non-scalable
industries. A typical example here is
the taxi industry which has been
disrupted by Uber, to take
just an example. The industry is
really not scalable. It's at the
urban level or it's even at the taxi
level but aggregating
this information and creating new
services out of it really disrupts
the traditional industry.
Other industries that are
particularly vulnerable to
digitalization are highly
fragmented industries; typically
the logistics industries
with a lot of players in it will
be particularly affected
by this digitalization whereby
the information can be
aggregated and sort of condensed
and repackaged to the customer.
Finally there are also the
information assymetric industries.
Again, health care where the doctor
knows a lot more than you do
or government services and the
duplication, the mirroring of this
information empowers the customer
who now also can become some sort of
a prosumer, delivering information
himself into that digital layer
which again can be used
for new services.
This is the overall effect of
digitalization on, let's say
the traditional industry. Potentially
any, any activity that has a
value chain can be disrupted by
digitalization but some are
more vulnerable than others.
Now lets look at what that does to
cities and urban infrastructures.
The distinction we made in our
previous MOOC which is
the classical distinction between
the infrastructures and the services
that are provided on the
infrastructure. A road
and a transportation service
on the basis of the road.
The customer, the citizen is
connected to the service,
not directly to the infrastructure.
What happens with digitalization
is the fact that
we introduce a data,
a digital layer in between
the infrastructure and the service
in exactly the same way
as I have shown
in the previous slide.
This does 2 things similar to what
I said before:
First, it sort of helps to manage
the infrastructures more efficiently.
It leads to an optimized physical
value chain by the very fact
that you know that you
have information about this
value chain. You have smarter energy
management thanks to this
digital layers, smarter transport
management, smarter waste
management and this is typically
what is happening
in smart cities. The second element
is the new types of
services that can be provided
thanks to that digital layer,
thanks to that data layer.
Smart new services,
new business models that can emerge.
The city can advise you or
the energy company can advise you
about your behaviour,
about saving energy, offering you
new types of services;
combining even infrastructures.
Your behaviour; let's say you have
an electric car and your mobility
behaviour combined with
your energy behaviour.
Let's look at that again in terms of
what that means for smart city:
The first dimension, the
smart infrastructure management
leads to what we call
City 1 plus something.
It is basically a process
of optimization, of incremental
innovation, of improving
the existing systems thanks to the
digital layer.
The second dimension which we then
call City 2.0 is really
the disruptive changes, the
qualitative changes.
No longer the incremental changes by
offering new types of services
thanks to the digital layer;
energy service, transport service
let's say waste services, green
services, all these kind of things.
The smart city has to be looked at
really in terms of these 2 things:
1) the incremental innovation on
optimizing the infrastructure
thanks to the digital layer and
2) the qualitative change in the
services, in even the business
models for the services.
We will go into more details
later on but I think
this is a good description
of the 2 types of things
the smart city
actually brings.
Stay tuned.