Welcome back.
In the previous session,
we talked
about the general implications
of digitalization.
In this session, we will talk
about the implications
of digitalization on cities,
their performance,
their infrastructures,
and especially
about the management
and governance challenges
that this raises.
Now, let's come back
to our original framework
which we had already presented
in the previous MOOC,
So, we have the urban infrastructures
that have particular performances
which we divided into questions
of efficiency, sustainability,
and resilience.
These infrastructures are governed
and managed
and we saw in the beginning
of this block
how this has to be seen
as a sociotechnical system
mutually influencing each other.
The performance
of these infrastructures
has an implication
on the quality of life
that citizens experience
and of the competitiveness of a city
that is particularly relevant
for the businesses.
And both together,
citizens and businesses,
again determine the type
of governance and management
of urban infrastructures.
Now, there are a series of challenges
that cities have to face.
Typically, those are
economic challenges,
financial challenges,
social challenges,
metropolitan challenges
resulting from the fact
that the metropolitan area
is much bigger, generally,
than the political entity
and there are a lot
of political challenges.
And finally, there are
technological challenges
as all the technologies
in the infrastructures
are currently evolving.
What we are concerned with
in this MOOC
is the particular effect
of digitalization,
and as we said,
the effect is pervasive.
That is, it effects the infrastructure,
as well as the management
and their governance.
Now, different people use the word
"Smart City" for different things.
And this slide is here to clarify
what we actually mean
by "Smart City".
So, there are people who focus
mainly on the economic dimension
of "smart cities",
and they are talking
about a digital economy.
That is, they are basically concerned
about how a city can create jobs,
revitalize its economy,
stimulate its economy,
thanks to the information
and communication technologies.
Typically, these people talk
about innovation parks,
about partnerships
between universities and industry
and see the city, the "smart city",
as they say, as a place
where the digital economy
can be stimulated.
Then, there are people who look
in particular at the social dimensions
of digitalization,
and they see in digitalization
the potential to stimulate
community life by way
of online communities,
by way of social interactions,
by sort of stimulating, revitalizing
the social and the cultural life
in a city.
For them, that's what
the "smart city" is about.
There are also people who talk
about this sharing economy
and this sharing economy, I think,
has to be linked,
between the digital economy
and the online community.
So it's a combination of both.
And again, it is clear
that digitalization stimulates
such sharing economy.
Finally, there are people who talk
about the whole political dimension.
They see in digitalization
the potential
to stimulate citizen participation,
civil society or
stakeholder involvement
thanks to concepts like e-government,
e-governance, e-participation,
and for them, this is what
the "smart city" is.
For us, the "smart city"
pertains mainly
to the technological dimension,
that is to the infrastructures,
and this is also, I think, one
of the more generally accepted definitions
of "smart city".
So, to summarize, for us,
"smart city" is mainly focused
on the technological dimension,
on the infrastructures,
and we are not really concerned
with, in this MOOC,
about the digital economy,
the online communities,
and the e-participation.
So we have a more narrow definition
of what the "smart city" is.
Let us illustrate that
by a few showcases.
Again, those are things
that people typically invoke
when they talk about "smart city"
from an infrastructure,
from a technological dimension.
So things that we will see later on,
for example, on transport,
smart cards, online
information mobility as a service,
on the energy level, we talk
about smart metering,
smart lighting, things like this.
On the water level, we talk
about digital metering
and all kinds of things like this.
Then there is a typical group
of people who talk
about smart housing,
intelligent buildings,
energy savings, thanks to that,
and the list is more or less endless.
One can look at other things,
smart waste,
smart green infrastructures,
There are many other things
that can be added.
Those are all examples on the digital city
infrastructure dimension.
So all these showcases, or examples
of "smart city", have to be put
in to the broader picture.
And the broader picture is
the implications that digitalization
has on urban systems.
There are four main implications.
The first implication is
on the management
and governance
of the infrastructures themselves.
The combination, for example,
between the legacy infrastructures
and the opportunities
that the digitalization offers
and this is a clear management
and governance challenge.
The infrastructures lead to services
on the basis of these infrastructures.
You have services, and thanks
to digitalization,
there are plenty of new types of services,
new opportunities of services,
and that leads to other implications
on managing and governing
this services layer.
What is really new for the city
will be the implications
on the management and the governance
of this digital or data layer?
This traditionally has not
been the case,
and the cities will have
to think hard
about the implications
of managing this data layer.
And, of course, all together,
we have an urban sociotechnical system
as we have seen and the fact
that digitalization somehow disrupts
the way this urban system works leads
to big implications in terms
of governing this system,
especially the institutions
the rules about how
this system works.
In the next two blocks, we will talk
about smart urban energy systems
and smart urban
transportation systems.
And after that, we will come
back to all the elements
that we have discussed here so far.
So stay tuned.