Welcome back.
So far we have talked
about our conceptualization
of smart cities,
the different elements that need
to be taken into account
for thinking properly
about Smart Cities.
Now, the concept of Smart Cities
is not originally
an academic concept.
It is a concept
that is mainly pushed
by vendors and pushed
by certain cities.
And so, what we are going to do
in this session is to present
the different vendors' perspectives,
then we'll present
the city's perspective
and then we will briefly talk
about what is at stake
in between these two perspectives.
As we have said,
and I think that's
the academic contribution to it,
this distinction
between the infrastructure,
the digital data layer
and the services,
leaving to the fact that you can
manage the infrastructures
more smartly if you want
and that there are
new, smart services possible
on the basis of this digital layer.
So, this is, let's say, the academic
sort of framing of Smart City.
From here, we can look
at the different perspectives
that are put forward
by different companies
promoting Smart Cities.
So there is first a perspective
of the hardware vendors,
these kind of companies
that produce the various devices.
Generally, those are the
data generating devices,
the smart meters, the sensors,
the cameras, all these things
that basically contribute
to creating that digital layer.
Then, there is the perspective
of the infrastructure companies
themselves.
Unlike the previous type
of companies,
these companies
have traditionally been active
in the urban arena,
be they urban water companies,
electricity companies,
transport companies
even postal services,
telecom operators.
These companies also
have embraced the concept
of smart cities and put
that concept forward
because they can create
on the basis
of their infrastructures,
a digital layer and services
that go with it.
And then there is a
third type of company or vendors.
They are new to the urban area.
Those are the IBMs,
the Ciscos of the world.
They offer services to manage,
to integrate this data,
to manage this data,
to analyze this data,
and they also are maybe
the most vocal ones
in promoting the concept
of "Smart City".
So, from here, we want to go
to the city's perspective.
It's not exactly identical
even though the city will rely
on all the technologies
and the services that
the different vendors provide.
So the city's perspective,
or let's say,
the metropolitan area's perspective,
is the one of managing
these infrastructures, of creating
the smart services
that ultimately will serve
their citizens,
and their businesses.
Now, what is at stake
when you look
at these two things combined?
These two perspectives
are not necessarily identical.
They're overlapping,
but they're not necessarily identical.
And so, we identify sort of
three things that are at stake.
The first thing is really
the citizens versus the consumers.
Typically, the vendors, they look
at consumers.
They want to monetize the services
that they are providing,
and, ultimately,
they will look at the consumers
of the smart services
that they are proposing.
The second stake is the whole issue
of demand pull
versus technology push.
I mean, we have already said
that Smart City is very much a techpush
It's built on digitalization
and digitalization is
a technological development.
And so, digitalization offers
plenty of opportunities
for cities, but there is a
little bit of technology push
especially by the vendors,
to adopt these new technologies.
Whereas, on the city's perspective,
this would rather be
a demand view.
Is this actually needed?
Does it help the city to make better,
more efficiently managed
new services that are
actually demanded?
And so, ultimately, I think
the main stake here
is the leadership
of this transformation.
Is this transformation.
the transition towards a Smart City
sort of led by the vendors,
the companies
that can provide
these kind of services?
Or is it led by the city
or the metropolitan area itself
or at least appropriated by the city
or the metropolitan area?
In this first week, you have
learned about cities
as sociotechnical systems.
We have shown you
how cities are best conceptualized
as complex, dynamic
sociotechnical systems.
Then, I talked about digitalization,
what digitalization is,
and the different elements
that compose digitalization.
After that, we have looked
at what digitalization does to cities
and what Smart Cities actually are.
And just before, I have talked
about different perspectives
on Smart Cities -
the vendors' perspective,
the city's perspective,
and our own academic perspective.
Now, in the coming week,
we will talk
about smart energy systems
and apply these concepts
to the energy part of urban systems.
But just before that, we will hear
about Barcelona.
So stay tuned.