Hello, and welcome
back to the course.
Today I have the pleasure
of receiving Irene Compte,
who is senior consultant
in the consulting firm Anteverti
which is a consulting firm
based in Barcelona,
and they are specialized
in the domain
of the "Smart Cities"
and eco innovation.
Thank you very much for
being with us here, Irene.
Thank you for the invitation.
It's a pleasure.
Thank you very much.
So the first question that
I would like to discuss
with you is about Barcelona.
You have been involved with Barcelona
for quite some time.
and can you give us a little
bit of background
about the evolution of thinking
about the "Smart Cities"
in Barcelona?
Of course.
I have been knowing
the politics, the policies
of "Smart Cities"
in Barcelona for the last,
I would say,
ten to twelve years.
Although, there was some
innovation happening
even before the
"Smart City" concept
was implemented as such.
Barcelona has always been,
we think,
a quite innovative city,
mainly in the urbanism domain
and now, also in the
"Smart Cities" domain.
So there has been, like,
a natural link,
a progression from
the innovation in urbanism,
in the way the city was designed
and planned and managed,
into this new concept
of "Smart Cities" or urban innovation.
This progression has taken Barcelona
from a first stage when
the "Smart City" concept arrived,
where technology was really leading
any action that the city was taking.
And this was not exclusive
from Barcelona.
I would say that in any city,
the first stage is
or the first stages
of their approach to smartness
were going through
technology and new sensors,
new gadgets and how it can help
the transition into smartness.
And it's interesting to see
how Barcelona
and other cities have,
in these last ten years,
evolved into a richer concept
of smartness
which I think it's the way it
had to be.
You start with technology,
thinking the technology
is what's going to change
and, of course,
the evolution takes you
to introducing governance factors
and this is when,
the moment when the local government
takes lead on technology, okay?
And starts to decide
on how technology
can really be useful
for the citizens
and, I would say Barcelona is now
in this kind of third stage
of Smart Cities
where we have the technology,
we have the governance,
and the surveillance,
let's say,
from the local government,
and we have a third,
very important factor
which is the citizen-centered
approach, okay?
So, clearly Barcelona
is now,
in their approach to Smart City,
in this stage.
The new policies, from
a quite new local government
which changed
some months ago
are clearly focused on putting
the citizen at the center
of any sustainability,
smartness, digital policy.
And acting from there
and looking for the benefit
of the life for the citizen.
Great
this leads me to the
second question,
basically, which is about
what would be the vision
of Barcelona for next
ten, fifteen years, let's say?
How you said they started
from technology
then to the governance
and then to the citizens, and then
what would be the next step
that you think would evolve,
eventually?
Well, if one looks at
the new digital agenda,
the digital plan for the city
which will go until 2020,
at least, and then for sure more,
the digital plan for the city
which will go until 2020,
at least, and then for sure more,
one will find some key words,
Technology is regarded as a mean
for key words such as "openness".
They speak a lot about Barcelona
being an open city
in the wider sense of the word,
which means inclusive,
which is another key word.
Democratic city - how technology
will help us
to have a more democratic city
where people,
the citizens, will participate -
that's another keyword.
So participation and
technology helping participation.
Innovation is another keyword
that you will find
in this digital agenda.
Innovation has also,
very wide uses and wide senses.
We will see a lot of social -
the so-called social innovation,
which also links to another key word
that they are using,
which is "circular".
A circular city.
Which leads to a new trend,
very interesting, in my opinion,
which is a circular economy
in cities.
I would say these are some of
the most important key words
in the future of the approach.
Great. Very interesting.
Let me become
a little bit more
practical and concrete.
So this is a vision of Barcelona
and how things evolved.
Can you elaborate a little bit
for our audience
What are the practical challenges
in managing the transition process
from, you know, legacy Barcelona
to a smart Barcelona to 2015, 2016
and a smart Barcelona, 2030, maybe?
A little bit of elaboration
on the practical challenges
There are a lot,
as any ambitious vision
When you start implementing it,
then you face the reality.
I would say the main,
or one of the main challenges,
is integration of existing innovation,
because, as I said,
Barcelona has always been
on the move for innovation.
So you have
some existing infrastructure,
some existing policies,
existing technical teams
in the municipality.
And when you bring new elements,
such as new information infrastructures,
or new policies,
or new ways of doing,
the first and really big challenge
is integrating this into something
which is efficient and
which really makes a difference.
This transition is never, never easy
and is never fast.
And this is for Barcelona,
but really for any city.
And this happened, as well,
in the last ten years,
when Barcelona started to try
new technologies.
We have something interesting
in Barcelona
which is called the Urban Lab,
which is an area of the city
dedicated for startup companies
or innovative companies
to try new technologies
in the streets of the city
and work closely
with the municipality
to really find the best users
of this solutions.
So this happened, we had
some learning from there
but it was not without difficulties.
Also, because, another challenge,
I would say,
is when you bring in new technologies,
new approaches to digital citizenship,
new business models need to arise.
And not only for private companies,
also the local government has to introduce
some changes in their procurement.
So we will hear a lot in the coming years
on innovative public procurement,
which is another challenging area
I would say, because as we all
know by now,
this Smart City projects,
the implementation of these solutions
are long term projects and
financing is another big challenge.
So who finances innovation?
Sometimes the local administration,
makes the push and the first move.
But then these lead to maintenance,
so innovative procurement, financing,
integration of the existing
with the new approaches
these are three,
and I would add four.
There's probably more.
But a fourth would be
how to really make
the citizens participate
not only be informed that their city
is working towards innovation,
efficiency, sustainability,
but really how to make them
participate in the equation
because it's a long-term project
where all the stakeholders
need to be involved.
Great.
I also know that
you have been involved
in all these European projects,
not only in Barcelona.
And the lessons
from Barcelona
are pretty interesting.
But can you also elaborate
a little bit one what's happening
in Europe
in the broader perspective?
How Europe is approaching
the smart cities,
other cities across Europe...
Do you know of any initiative
happening right now?
There's many. There's many.
I know some of them,
but particularly a project,
a European project
which is under a program
called "The Lighthouse" project.
We are working actively
with the municipality of Barcelona
on a project called "Grow Smarter".
Let's see, the framework
of this project
is the goal of Europe
and the European commission
to make Europe sustainable
in the short, mid- and long-term.
They started many years ago.
The Lighthouse program is
a specific one
which is tackling
environmental sustainability.
but also economic sustainability,
and it deals a lot
with how we manage and plant cities
today and in the coming years
to fulfil these goals
of sustainability.
So the Lighthouse program promotes
consortiums of European cities
in this case, the "Grow Smarter" project
has three leading cities.
One is Barcelona
the other one is Stockholm,
in Sweden,
and the third is Koln,
in Germany.
Different areas of Europe
with different environmental needs
and environmental realities.
Of course, the Mediterranean has
certain specificities
in terms of climate and so on -
different than in Stockholm and Koln.
So that's the first thing
which is interesting of this project.
The objectives are, I would say,
threefold in this case.
It's to try measures
or smart solutions
towards sustainability
in three areas.
The first one is try solutions
or develop solutions
in what we call
"low energy districts".
So, how can we intervene
on buildings, on the streets,
on the energy systems
that the buildings share and use
to make them more efficient
and reduce emissions
and reduce energy consumption?
The second area would be solutions
on integrating
information infrastructures.
So, how can we build,
for example,
city platforms which integrate data
and information resources
in order, again,
to be more efficient?
And the third area
is sustainable mobility,
because, of course,
it's not new to anyone
that mobility is one
of the key issues
in, not only European cities,
but worldwide.
So when we intervene in mobility
and implement efficiency in it,
we will be tackling one
of the most pressing problems
in cities.
So the project is trying solutions
at district level
in these three areas.
Great. And, you know,
that was an interesting point
because you mentioned about the smart,
but the smart seems not to be
a goal in itself.
This is a smart for improving
sustainability or efficiency,
as you mentioned.
And I think, you know,
that's an important point -
that sometimes is missing
in the Smart Cities discourse.
Yes, it's clear.
Actually, you cannot speak
about sustainable
without speaking of smart
and the other way around.
Exactly. Good.
Thank you very much, Irene.
It was very insightful
and thanks for joining us
here in the course.
Thank you for the invitation.