We all know that cities
are not efficient,
think for example of congestion.
We also know that cities
are not sustainable,
think of all the energy wasted
and we know that cities
are not resilient.
Think for example of all the
different natural hazards.
Now addressing these challenges
becomes even more important
because of rapid population growth
and global warming, for example.
Infrastructures are the
backbone of cities
and they do play a crucial role
in addressing these challenges.
Over the past few years, technology
is capable in addressing at least
some of these challenges
that are rapidly spreading.
This is especially the case of the
information and communication
technologies currently being
developed by universities,
technology providers, technology
start ups and many more.
Cameras, sensors and other data
collecting devices are producing
unprecedented amounts of data.
For example, data about movements
of vehicles and mobility behavior
or data about energy
and water consumption
by individuals and buildings.
From this data smart mobility,
smart energy, smart buildings
and many other smart
infrastructures can emerge
and ultimately,  this could lead to
what is now called a Smart City
but we know that technology alone
is not going to solve the complex
problems of cities
and our Smart City MOOC is
precisely about that
that is how to make use of
digitalization for addressing
the big challenges to create
Smart Cities.
More precisely our course is about
the management and the governance
of Smart Cities as well as of the
transition towards Smart Cities.
Our course will be structured
into 5 blocks or 5 weeks
along the following structure.
First there will be an introduction
to the concept of Smart Cities
then we will talk about example of
Smart Urban Energy Systems.
The 3rd week will be about the example
of Smart Urban Mobility Systems
and the last 2 weeks are about managing
the transition towards Smart Cities.
In this MOOC, you will hear lectures
from myself and colleagues.
In addition, we will have interviews
with experts from industry.
My name is Matthias Finger and
I'm a professor of Management
of Network Industries at Ecole
Polytechnique Fédérale
de Lausanne, Switzerland.
It will be my pleasure to lead you
through this course on Smart Cities.
This MOOC is one of
the outcomes of IGLUS
which is an action research
project involving selected cities,
international organizations
and firms.
You may already have followed
our previous course entitled
Management of Urban Infrastructure.
In this course, we still talk about
Managing Urban Infrastructures
but now we have a special
focus on the information
and communication technologies
and these technologies totally change
the way these infrastructures are
managed and governed.
This is what we call Smart Cities.
Come and explore this new reality
and join us in this course.