Hi, this is a series of MOOCs
on simulation neuroscience.
I'm Henry Markram
from the EPFL,
the Swiss Federal Institute
for Technology
and I run a laboratory on
neuro-microcircuitry
and the blue brain project.
And these MOOCs
will essentially
help you to understand first
what simulation neuroscience is,
second how to reconstruct
and simulate neurons
and synapses,
and then how to build a circuit
and finally to be able
to simulate circuits,
and see what we understand from that.
In the first MOOC, we are going
to have an overview
and introduction to what
simulation neuroscience is.
We will also look at the experimental
data that goes behind
simulation neuroscience.
We are also going to look
at the neuroinformatics,
how you organize the data, Sean Hill
is going to give you lectures on that.
Then the father of modeling neurons,
Idan Segev, is going to show you
how we model these neurons
and Felix Schürmann and Werner van Geit are
going to show you how we constrain
models with data. And then
there will be an exam in the final week.