Let's look at the informatics
strategies
that we use or the principles
of informatics.
And as I said earlier
neuroinformatics is probably
one of the most challenging
informatics
sciences there are because of the data
heterogeneity, the complexity,
the lack of standardization,
the uncertainty,
different formats, there are many
many problems
in trying to database the brain.
What is very important when
you look at neuroscience data
from a simulation neuroscience
perspective
is that, and you will learn this
more and more as we go further,
is that all data is good.
There is actually no such thing
as bad data.
There is wrong data, there is a lot
of wrong data,
In fact, most of the data is wrong.
But all data is good
for reconstruction.
Even bad data, even wrong data
that says: "Look, you know,
this is just a wrong experiment".
When you have wrong data,
it actually helps you understand
better what is a right data.
So, what we try to do
is to build an infrastructure
and Sean here is going to give
you a series of lectures on this,
we build an infrastructure
that allows us to compare
experimental data with
simulation data.
Because that is how we test
and validate the reconstructions.
So, you have experiments
and your simulations
and we try to make them
as equivalent as possible.
And then we want to informatically
map them in a way
that we can also compare
them as well, as much as possible.
So you want to easily be able
to compare experimental data
with simulation data.
You need access to all the data,
all the papers that is out there.
There are around 10 million papers
that are relevant
to understanding the brain, not all
directly on the brain
but are relevant to understanding the brain.
In some form you want to get
all those papers,
you want to mine them for little
nuggets of knowledge
that may be used, that you could use
on the experiment side
so that at some point you can use
them to validate your reconstruction.
So, you want to find all the papers
and associated data.
The open access and open data
policies are extremely important
if we want to be able to move
towards simulating the brain,
simulating the heart, liver,
or any part of the body
or simulating diseases.
It is essential that data
and papers are open.
You want to organize them,
so you have got to create knowledge graphs
knowledge spaces, so that you can
mine and analyze this data easily
and ultimately, you actually want to
map them onto an atlas.
So that you can navigate
in the kind of coordinate space
that the brain is.
You want to navigate through
to different part of the brain
and you want to say: "What do
I know about it?
What are all the papers, what
is all the data?"
And then I can see experimental
data and I can see simulation data.
And I can compare.
And I can see how close
is the simulation data
getting to the real data.
So, this is the general approach
to informatics or neuroinformatics
that we use.
And again, the principle
is: get all the data.
Wrong data actually helps
in some ways
to be able to find out
and understand what is right data.
And I will give you many examples
of this as we go on
in the next lectures.