Okay, so let's look now at some
of the principles.
What are the principles on which
simulation neuroscience rests?
So, the first important principle
is that we have to do dense
reconstructions
dense, very detailed reconstructions
and we have to do it
from sparse data.
Ok, so, I just gave you an idea,
a glimpse
at how much data there really
is to measure.
And if anybody has
to do a calculation you will realize
that it would take the entire
human race,
thousands of years if you wanted
to map out all of those things
in all of those
different connotations.
So, we will forever
have sparse data.
No matter how much data
we collect, it will forever
be sparse in terms of experimental.
So, the problem we have to solve
is how do we get a complete picture
from sparse data.
So, the first principle of simulation
neuroscience
is we have to establish the strategy
from going to a little bit of data
to using whatever knowledge we have
of how the pieces fit together
to build algorithms
and algorithmically build the circuit.
Now, this first principle is not
a new principle.
It is extremely old, it is the basis,
actually, of our entire society today
of information
and communication technologies.
Let me try and explain
this in another way.
Imagine that you have a TV screen
Okay?
And the channel is unplugged.
So, it is a white noise.
So, basically every pixel
is independent
of every pixel.
Okay?
And now I want to transmit
this image to you.
I want to tell you what
is this image.
I need to give you a complete
picture of what this image is.
Based on Claude Shannon's work
from the 40s
we know the theory here
It is very clear.
I have to measure
if this is a random system.
If this is a random image
or a random system
I have to measure every single pixel.
That is I have no way out,
but to measure every pixel
if I wanna tell you about
this complete story here
Okay?
But it is only if I have
a random system.
If I now have an organized system
where there is a very clear structure
the theory shows you absolutely
clearly
that I don't need
to transmit every pixel
to here, I don't need to transmit
every single pixel,
I don't have to tell you
what every pixel is here
because there are relationships
between all these pixels
and it is the basis
of image compression.
So, this is order.
So, in this case if I have
a random system
I don't need any intelligence,
I just have to copy
these pixels across.
So, I don't need an algorithm here.
Okay?
I don't need an algorithm, I just
need to transfer the data.
But if I have the order
in the system
I need a rule how to rebuild it
if I am going to send a few
of these pixels across
and I want to rebuild this picture.
I need an algorithm.
Okay?
I need some rule that will rebuild
the relationships
that are in this picture.
Okay, so in a way with a random
system I need to measure everything
and I do it blindly, I don't
understand anything,
I just have to copy it
from here to here.
In an ordered system I have
to understand order.
And I have to package it into
an algorithm.
Then I can send it to you
and I can reconstruct it.
Basically, the important message
is that dense reconstructing
from sparse data
is not just because we have to,
because we forever have sparse data
it is because it is science.
It is actually not scientific to say
that we need to go and measure
everything in the brain.
Okay? Only if it is a random system
do we need to measure every pixel.
You don't need any principles,
you don't have to understand
very much and you can close
your eyes and blindly map one thing
to the next.
So, when there is an objection
that says:
"Oh, you can't reconstruct
or simulate a cell
because we don't know everything
about the cell",
that is not a scientific statement.
The challenge is to find the minimum
data you need.
The smallest data set,
not the largest data set.
The real science is to say what is
the least amount of data I need
to be able to reconstruct it.
That is a compression algorithm.
It is a simile, it is the inverse,
what is the least amount of data
that I need to transmit to you
so, you can rebuild the image.
Okay.
In that case you do not need
to measure everything,
you need principles and that is
what drives simulation neuroscience.
And then you algorithmically
reconstruct it.
So a simulation neuroscience
is fundamentally about finding
those principles, packaging them
into algorithms,
and then reconstructing.
That is the first principle
of simulation neuroscience.
The second principle is, actually
also quite similar to computer
and software engineering.
It is a bottom-up reconstruction
process.
And it actually
has very strict rules.
And the rules are, first of all,
you have got to follow
the biological principles.
You don't try and invent how
you think the brain should look.
or the neuron should look.
You measure and you use
as much of the data
that is available and where
it is not available
you have a hypothesis
of what is available.
And you can then
test that hypothesis.
You build the smallest
components first
you really start atomic, if you wish,
you start at the eye channel
to build a neuron, you don't start
at the neuron and then try make
a neuron behave and then say:
"Oh, let me go back and build
eye channels".
You start at the very bottom
and you build upwards
Okay?
And a key thing which is the same
as what you do in computer
and software engineering,
you build modules and cells,
and functions and there you freeze
your variables and you freeze them.
And then you combine them.
We go to pi cell, it is so beautiful,
it is combinatorial
because I just built these
and I can consume them later.
But in order to do that I freeze
the components
and then I can combine
the components.
And the other important thing
and very different from
computation neuroscience,
for example
is you validate upwards.
In other words, you validate
what emerges
when you combine things.
You don't try to fit and your data,
you never fit the data
looking up at an emerging property.
So, for example, you wouldn't try
to say: "look, my brain is not speaking
how can I adjust my eye channels
until I speak?"
You will be adjusting eye channels
forever.
Okay, that is a massively,
it is an intractable problem.
So, you have got to come down
to the emerging property
as close to that parameter
as possible.
For example, an eye channel,
you want to build an eye channel
you look at the behavior of an eye
channel.
You don't look at the behavior of the neuron
to build an eye channel.
So, you always do it, at the bottom
you freeze it,
and then when you say: "ok, I have
got my eye channels,
I want to know what they do,
I put them in a neuron
and then I look at the neuronal
behavior and that way I can see
how they play out when they
are being used.
If you find that you can
never replicate the neurons behavior
then you can say: "maybe
I got my eye channels wrong.
Maybe I don't have the right
eye channels."
And so on.
So that is the way we begin the cycle,
which we are going to learn a lot about
in the course of this
and other lectures.
The guiding principle here is
that if you build it right
it will automatically behave right.
OK, so you build bottom up.
You build the components
you freeze them.
If this is valid in terms
of the behavior
even if you don't know
all the pieces,
but if a neuron behaves right,
and you put in a circuit
you can talk about what
neurons do.
If the circuit behaves right
and you put it into a brain
you can talk about what the circuit
does and not the brain.
OK, so you don't try and tweak
the model to behave right.
If the neuron, if you built it right
it automatically behaves right.
The last, the third,
and there are of course many
but the third principle is that
it is iterative reconstruction
and testing.
So you get your experimental data,
you get your literature, you go
and find all the papers you can
you mind all the facts
you possibly can.
and you try and build
the unifying model of a neuron.
You find the eye channels, you find
the morphologies, the structures
the physiology, any data that
you have about that neuron
you collect.
And then the challenge is how
do you package that into
the simplest algorithm that
will then reconstruct it
that is consistent with all the data
that you gathered?
You obtain your model
and then you interrogate it
anatomically, you look at it
and you see: "OK, I got it right,
it looks like a real neuron,
I do the statistics between
my reconstructed neuron
and the real neuron and I see
that they match".
I look at where the eye channels
are, they match and so on.
And then you simulate it to see
if it behaves the way
that it does in the real tissue.
And then you do an analysis,
you do the systematic comparison
and you get your errors.
Well, it is not going to work
the first time.
In fact, the goal is to do it
very fast, fail very fast, identify
where you may have got the wrong
data or the wrong assumptions
and then you build it again,
and you keep going through the cycle
as many times as you possibly can.
In fact, it is an endless loop,
you keep going and integrating
and perfecting it, but with each
cycle, this model
replicates the tissue more
and more accurately.
You follow this process,
you can't go left, you can't go right
you can't go backwards,
you can only go forward.
So, the model can only improve
each and every time
that you integrate it.
So, to illustrate this
let's just imagine
that you step inside
a forest of neurons
and you look up at the neurons,
there are thousands of neurons
millions of synapses,
and you look around.
And you say:
"I wonder how these neurons connect?
I mean, how are they connecting
with each other?
Who is connected with each
other?
Where are all these...?"
So, how do you approach
this problem?
Of course you can try and let's take
an electro microscope
and measure everything
that is, of course, one approach,
but it you actually look at it
you will be measuring for a very
very long time
But there is another approach
and the way that we do it in simulation
neuroscience, we say:
"OK, let's just look at what we know.
Let's start off and let's imagine
that we have a whole series
of cells, neurons".
OK.
And, of course, there are different
kinds of neurons.
You have many different kinds
of neurons.
Each one looks different,
behaves different
and it can, of course, connect
differently to the others.
So, how do you
approach this problem ?
Well, you can say: "What do we know?"
And maybe there's only
one experiment
that tells you how this one cell,
this one type of cell
connects with others.
There are potentially thousands
of different types of connections
here, but you only have one
experimental data point.
And this experimental data point
you go and you see
that the axon that goes to connect
all these neurons does this.
And you look at this and you analyze
the data here and you say:
"Oh, I can see the principle".
First principle:
The axon somehow touches
every neuron.
Okay?
So, before I look at who is connected
I just see that the way this axon
goes, it is like what we call
a tabular riser.
It goes and it touches
everything on you.
And then I look at this one neuron
and I say: Oh, I see that when it
touches, when it touches onto
another cell, it actually puts lots
of little synapses on it
It never puts just one synapse".
OK?
It never puts just one synapse
it puts lots of them.
So, I see principle number 2:
it is a multi synapse rule.
Okay?
And I think: "oh that's interesting,
but what else can I learn
by looking at this one experiment?"
I see principle number 3:
I see, wow, if I look at
the axon of the cell,
and I look at it very carefully
I see that it has got places
called blue tones
which is where it can form synapses.
So, I think: "how many are there?
And what is the space between them?"
And then I say: "okay, that will limit
how many neurons
this one can contact", right,
because if I have an axon only as two
then it is, of course, going to have
a very different kind of activity
than I have axon
that has many boutons.
Then now I have a bouton principle.
It is a physical limitation.
If I have lots of boutons,
if I have a neuron with an axon
with lots of boutons, then
I can contact lots of cells.
If I have one, I can
contact one cell.
So, these are 3 principles.
Now there are more principles,
but let's just assume, just say: "OK
I like these 3 principles,
I am going to see if I can rebuild
the tissue
just with these three principles".
So, we package them
into an algorithm.
Okay?
And digitally we reconstruct
this tissue.
Now we have 2 possible
scenarios:
it succeeds or it fails.
Succeeds means that
you have a look at it
and then somebody tells you:
"Hey, you know what?
There are 10 other experiments
out there that looked at
how this cell connects,
and this cell connects
and you have other data
that you can check it with".
And then when you look at that
you see that your reconstructed tissue
now reproduces all of that
experiment.
So, you think: "wow, I mean I looked
at 1 cell, applied 3 principles
of how they should connect with
each other
and they reproduce what other people
have done in other laboratories
all over the world".
That is a success.
But what is important to understand
with this success
is that you haven't really gained any
new knowledge, but you have gained
a new understanding.
You understand how
your principles interact.
You understand that this principle
for this neuron applies to all of them.
Two very concrete
new understandings.
It is not new knowledge because
this knowledge existed,
people had measured this, we saw
this, it was just fragmented knowledge
but you didn't even had that sort
of integrated, unified view.
So, when it succeeds,
you understand better.
I am an experimental neuroscientist
and I have looked under microscopes
for 20 years.
And when I put this together,
in a single reconstruction
I understand what I was doing
for all those 20 years.
Because you can see this
as an integrated,
an integrated answer or perspective
on what the pieces are
that you have been collecting
for so long.
Now the other scenario is it fails.
I do this, I check it again,
somebody comes into the door
and they say: "Look, I have
an experiment and it shows me
that this cell, it really doesn't follow
those principles and it connects
in a completely different way".
And then I have new knowledge.
I know that these principles
are not enough.
There have to be new principles.
There have to be some other rules
that will apply
whether they are exceptions,
or whether they are
that these principles have to be modified.
But there has to be something
else that has to be understood.
And then one can start investigating
and that triggers, when you fail
it triggers new experiments
which you have to test now.
How would an algorithm reconcile
these differences?
Another way to describe this
is imagine that this algorithm
works in one part of the brain.
And it explains
all the way the neurons connect.
Now I go to another part of the brain
and it doesn't work there.
You think: "that is terrible"!
No, that is great, because it tells
you that in that other part of the brain
there is something else going on.
And that something else nobody
knew about before.
Because you had too much
fragmented knowledge.
That is when failing really leads
to an advancement of knowledge.
New knowledge.
Because it triggers a completely
new perspective.
It actually shows you the boundaries
of a current knowledge.
You get to the end and you say :
"I've taken all the data,
all the principles
and I can't explain
how this happens".
Then you are at the frontier.
And at that frontier you can either
do theory, you can do experiment
you can iteratively test,
but there are many
ways to advance it.
And this is a very exciting approach
to advancing knowledge.
Okay, so we looked at these
3 principles
on which simulation neuroscience
is based.