Okay.
So, in the last lecture we...
..explored a little bit what
simulation neuroscience is,
what the rationale for it is
and what the principles
on which it is based are.
Now we are going to look
a little bit about how we…,
still part of this introduction,
how do we...
..look, approach data,
what are the data strategies
and informatics and so on.
So in the case of, you know...
..going just up to building
circuits of the brain,
the first approach is,
establish a data hierarchy
and there is a reason
that we actually approach
simulation neuroscience
at the micro circuit level.
It is because it kind of is
in the middle between...
..brain regions
and the whole brain
and cells and molecules
and so you actually capture
how do you integrate
the components below.
Later you can integrate these components
into higher level components.
So, it is relatively simple rules
for how do you approach data.
You establish a data hierarchy.
And in this case,
it is also relatively simple.
You start with your ion channels
which are membrane proteins that
allow specific ions to flow through
and in either directions
or whichever directions,
and as they flow through,
they change the voltage of the...
..membrane of the neuron
and collectively they will shape
the way that the neuron behaves
and we are going to learn
a lot more about that as we go further.
The way we do that
and we are going to also
go further into that in the next series
of lectures
as we do ion channel screening,
biophysical screening,
one has to actually explore
the biophysics of these channels
and then one has to look at neurons
and how we study neurons,
how do we record from neurons
and stay in neurons
and how do we determine
how they behave
and then their synapses,
how do we get to record
how a synapse behaves.
So these are paired recordings
and staining the two neurons,
so you can see how neurons
connect with each other
and then there are also circuits
and how do you study circuits.
You can stain them globally,
you can do antibody staining,
you can do stain for the expression
of the genes,
it is called in situ hybridization,
or you can actually suck out some
of the cytoplasm from inside a cell
and you can find out which genes
are expressed.
You can also
look at the emergent activities
that emerge
in the circuit electrically
and voltage sensitive.
So there are many techniques
and approaches to record
from the sort of levels,
ion channels,
neurons, synapses, circuits
and then...
..in order to do the reconstruction,
you have to...
...and build algorithms,
you have to pay attention
to the way you analyze the data.
So you have to analyze
in the case of ion channels,
you have to analyze the kinetics
of the channels, open and closed.
Distribution - where are they
located? In the cell body
or up in the branches?
What are the combinations
of ion channels?
That is you can't just have one
type of ion channel,
you need lots of different types
of ion channels if you want to get
interesting behavior.
So, what are the combinations
that are possible?
And then how many
of each type do you have?
What is the conductance, how much
current does ion channel pass through?
So, this allows you to build
a model of the ion channel
and we are going to learn
how we do that in other lectures later.
And then you study neurons
and we use patch-clamp
and I will show you in subsequent
lectures how we do that
and that allows you
to get the morphology,
so you can get the branching,
3-D branching structure of a neuron
to the morphology.
You can also record from these,
so you can actually
find out how they behave electrically.
You can stain them, so you can find out
what proteins are located on to them
And you can also suck out
some of this juice
from the cytoplasm,
from inside a cell
and then you can find out
what genes are switched on in the cell,
so you can find out genes.
So it gives you a very
in-depth view of a single neuron
in terms of its structure,
its function, its genes,
its proteins and so on.
And synapses
are of course more tricky.
They are small,
they are half a micron.
Basically, a little bit
bigger than a bacteria,
about the size of a bacteria
for many of them.
They are the most
complex little devices,
biological devices in the universe,
but how do we record from them,
so you have to record from two cells
and then you have to stain both cells,
so you can find
a way for the axon to go out
to touch the other cell
and how did they form synapses.
So you want to measure
and the numbers you need
are like synapses per connection,
you need to stimulate and see how much
voltage is produced on the other side
by the receiving neurons,
you get the synaptic strength
and then you have to play with
the synaptic transmission
to try to understand
what kind of dynamics,
what is the communication
code between two neurons.
Synaptic dynamics
and then you can ask,
"how does the synapse,
how can it be controlled
if you throw a drug on it
or if you throw a chemical on it
like a neuromodulator,
(INAUDIBLE) or adrenaline,
dopamine, histamine".
How does that actually change
the behavior of the synapse.
So these are all numbers
that you can get
and they are being obtained
in many different ways,
in many different labs
around the world
and then you have circuits
and from the circuits you want to know
essentially,
how many neurons they are,
how many types of neurons they are,
how are they arranged together,
how are they positioned,
are they clustered together and so on.
All kinds of geometrical rules
of how do you organize your neurons
in a piece of tissue.
Then there is, of course also,
electrophysiological data
which tells you
how that circuit behaves
and many experiments around
how little pieces of brain tissue
or circuits behave.
So this is, you know,
to summarize the issue,
identify a hierarchy.
In this case it is ion channels.
They go into the neurons,
the synapses connect
the neurons
and you put the neurons
together in a circuit.
So these are the components.
When you build your ion channels
you freeze,
you build your neurons, you freeze,
you build your synapses, you freeze,
you put them
into the circuit and test.