Okay so let's summarize
by looking at caveats.
So the main caveat of course is
that there may be critical data
that is missing.
Now I did mention that the challenge
or the goal, the mission of
simulation beuroscience is not
to get everything.
It doesn't mean that we shouldn't
get as much data as possible
but the algorithmic goal is to find
what is the minimum data I need
to do a complete reconstruction.
And in that search for the minimal
data, it may be that there is
critical data missing.
If you don't have neuronal morphologies,
it is going to be very
difficult to build a circuit.
So you have to find a way to
get neuronal morphologies.
So we can call them
critical data or strategic data.
And that means that one has to go
back to lab and one has to do
experiments and one has to obtain
that critical data.
The other caveat is that biological
data has a lot of mistakes.
In fact there are much more mistakes
than accurate data.
It is by far more that there are
errors than there are correct data.
So we shouldn't be so quick to
believe biological experiments,
I am a biological experiment,
I measure lots of things
and when you actually look at it
and try to use it, you quickly see
if it really fits with other data or not.
In fact the best way to find out if
your data is right or wrong
is to try to use it in the
combination of others.
And we will show you examples
where this actually does show you
precisely where experiments
have gone wrong.
But it does make reconstructing
difficult when you have this huge
discrepancy in the
biological data set.
But on the other hand, it turns
into a positive because you can curate
the data, you can actually
identify what is reasonable.
This data is just not reasonable,
it cannot fit with
all this other data.
And then the other caveat
and it is not really a caveat,
it just means that we are evolving
in the way that we do Neuroscience.
Instead of disciplines
being fragmented
across many labs
and different people,
if you do simulation neuroscience,
you have to become multidisciplinary.
You have to learn about experiments,
analysis of data, informatics
computer science, mathematics,
algorithmics, computational sciences
and so on.
In summary, we looked at approaches.
And it is really experimentation,
theory and the third branch of
knowledge generation is
simulation science.
Not only in neuroscience, in
many of the other sciences.
There are 3 branches of how
you advance a knowledge.
The rationale for simulation
neuroscience is that it is a
big data problem.
It is not going to be solved
only with experiments.
only with theory.
The principles of
simulation neuroscience
are fundamentally that you need
to build a dense reconstruction
from sparse data.
Your challenge is to find the
smallest data set that will
give you a detailed reconstruction.
You build bottom up.
In other approaches,
you start top down.
Iterative reconstruction,
you reconstruct, reconstruct
and it refines.
It is almost like a fitting algorithm
or a gradient descent where
gradually the digital reconstruction
becomes more and more precise
becoming the digital copy
of the neuro tissue.
The data strategy is
really to establish a
hierarchy of data components.
You have to do a lot of very
careful data analysis
so you get all the parameters.
Informatics strategy.
Find it all.
Bring it all on the table and ask:
"how does it fit together?"
There is some value in every study.
And this is actually very powerful
because if you go into the
literature and you say
I am only going to find the
best work out there,
you are going to have a hard time
deciding what is the best work
and there is going to be
contradictions and not
but more importantly, you could
miss very important little
statements, findings in bad papers.
So, our approach is, let's find
the gems in any paper.
Some papers may have lots of gems
and other papers may only have one
and some may have zero but
that is fine, you don't know that
and you actually have to
approach it as if there is a gem
and I want to look for it.
That is the informatics strategy that
we adopt in simulation neuroscience.
Reconstruction strategy,
you build the components,
you freeze down and validate up.
You validate the emerging properties.
You never fit to the emerging or you
try not to fit to the emerging properties.
You build workflows so you can run
this machinery over and over.
You validate against independent
data and emerging properties.
And, of course, you need a
supercomputer because you
need a lot of fast communication
and you need a lot of memory
and it does simulations and is
about allowing you to mimic
experimental neuroscience.