So, in this section,
what we are going to cover
is an introduction
to simulation neuroscience.
First we are going to look
at the approaches to study the brain
and then we are going to go through
the rationale, the principles,
data strategy, informatics strategies,
reconstruction strategies,
and simulation strategies.
So, after this course,
this lecture, the first lecture,
you should have an understanding
of what simulation neuroscience is,
you should have a general idea
on how we treat data
and our approach to informatics,
what we mean by reconstruction
and what kind of strategies
we use to do reconstruction,
tissue reconstruction,
and what strategies
we use for simulation.
These are very general concepts.
We are going to go in the next
lectures much deeper
and you should also have an
understanding of what the caveats are
for simulation neuroscience.
So, we are going to look
at the approaches to study the brain,
because I think we should
take a step back and say:
how do we advance
scientific knowledge?
With our three branches
of exploratory science if you wish
to discover new knowledge.
One of them is,
of course experimental.
That is the ground truth approach,
you observe,
you hypothesize, you test,
and you make more measurements.
For the brain of course,
we can look at normal brains.
Everything from genes,
protein, cell, circuits,
cognition, psychophysics,
all the way up to behavior,
and then of course you have nature's
experiments which are the disease brain.
You can look at the effect
of toxins, effect of drugs,
lesions on the brain,
mutations that are occurring
and degeneration with aging,
and all of these
provides you sort of
a repertoire of conditions
where you can actually
try to understand
what the brain is doing.
The second is
theoretical neuroscience or theory
where you essentially hypothesize
about the data
or about the observations
and one can look at them
in at least four different categories.
They are sort of informatics
which really tries
to look at the trends
or correlations
and patterns in the data.
Theoretical neuroscience
is trying to explain the data.
You see the data, you want to predict
outcomes of an experiment,
and you have a theory
about the data
and your observation.
Computational neuroscience
is more about building
a model to replicate
the experimental data
and generally,
it is to build a minimal model
and the idea is that if you can
explain a phenomenon
in the simplest possible way,
then you have
the deepest understanding.
It is debatable, but that is the
idea of computational neuroscience.
Then you have
applied neuroscience,
where basically you can say
that if I really do understand
how neurons work, then I can build
a device that will listen to them
and I can develop
a treatment that will cure them
and that is applied neuroscience.
Then there
is simulation neuroscience
and in neuroscience,
this is relatively new.
We're sort of driving this
or trying to pioneer this.
And the way to think of simulation
neuroscience is that
it unifies both experimental
and theoretical approaches.
The difference in simulation
neuroscience is that you consider
every detail of the brain.
Nothing is left out.
So for example, if you
had a theory of how language works
and you had a couple of equations
that could build a machine
that would be able to speak.
That would be wonderful.
It would indicate that you
have a deep understanding of language,
but it won't help you understand
how a genetic mutation
impacts language
and how that affects the next
neuron and the next circuit
and the brain activity
and how you should treat it.
So simulation neuroscience is about
taking all the data into account.
All the knowledge into account
and integrating it.
It is also about filling
the gaps of knowledge
with hypotheses, because we may
not be able to measure everything.
Okay. So, another way to look at,
to get a perspective
on the way we approach the brain
is that there are individual researchers
and in the world there are probably
about 200,000 individual neuroscientists
that are exploring the brain.
So they are looking at a genetic level,
at the protein level,
at the behavioral level
and there is a huge repertoire
of different techniques
that can be used
to be able to probe the brain
and to assess what is going on.
And this is producing
a massive range of data
and today there are about
a 100,000 scientific papers
produced by these individual
research from all around the world.
So there is an enormous
amount of data being produced
to understand the brain
and we actually do know
lots and lots of little pieces.
In individual research,
every lab has its own method,
its own conditions,
its own instruments, its own biases
and of course,
that means that
it is not always easy to compare data
and findings across laboratories.
And it is quite a significant
problem that in neuroscience,
a significant amount of the research
that has been done in individual
and individual laboratories...
...are difficult to reproduce
or impossible to reproduce,
but nevertheless,
they provide a massive source
of data and knowledge.
The second approach
to the brain is to go large-scale,
to go industrial scale.
For example,
the way that the Allen Institute
approaches brain mapping
or the Human Connectome Project
or some parts
of the Human Brain Project,
the European Human Brain Project
and the idea there is to standardize.
In the case of the Allen Institute,
for example, they would
standardize all the methods
and they will produce 20,000 atlases
where each atlas
is telling you where one
gene is in the whole brain
and so you have 20,000 genes,
20,000 atlases
and they do that
very systematically.
So, you have very solid,
large block of data.
So this is large-scale brain mapping
and it is really sort of
industrial scale neuroscience.
It is extremely valuable data
for simulation neuroscience,
because it is highly standardized
and it is much easier to use.
But the individual
research is very valuable
to actually validate the model,
the reconstructed tissues
that are built afterwards.
So all data is valuable,
all approaches are valuable.
Then of course,
you have to database the brain
and this has a very long history.
There is a lot of efforts that have gone
into databasing the brain.
It was started in 1990
by Bill Clinton actually.
He started
the US Human Brain Project,
which was an effort
to database the brain.
It has been a very difficult,
very long journey,
because there are so many
different types of data
and different conditions
and different questions.
It is very difficult to decide
how to database the brain,
but there are now
international efforts
and it is also an effort
in the European Human Brain Project
to database the brain
in a systematic way.
It is not a solved problem.
There are a lot of challenges
and you are going to have a lecture
about it in this MOOC series later on.
And how do we approach the data.
And then we have of course:
why do we do all of this?
In the end, we want to put
all the pieces together
and that is reconstruction simulation
or simulation neuroscience.
Another aspect is,
which simulation neuroscience
and large-scale industry mapping
of the brain introduce
is really what is called "team science".
It is very different, it is where you have
a lot of people with different expertise
sitting around the table
and solving one problem.
Very different from the individual...
..that is sitting in the lab
and addressing a specific question.
It is not whether one is better
or worse than another,
they are all part
of the whole approach
that the world today is using
to study the brain
and they are all playing a specific
role and they have their benefits
in their own particular way.
In many cases team neuroscience
is indispensable.
It has to be done that way
and in many cases,
you have to have individual research.
Let's look now at the rationale.
Why do we need
to do simulation neuroscience?
What is the goal
of doing simulation neuroscience?
We have experiments,
we have theory.
Many people say
you only need theory,
you only need experiments,
you don't need to simulate the brain.
There is a lot of debate and discussions
and all kinds of ideas out there
about simulation neuroscience.
Why do you need it?
Well, first of all,
what we have to bear in mind
is that actually simulation science
is at the pinnacle of almost
all the hard sciences.
So you have got a material science
in the beginning,
you were tinkering around
with chemistry and materials
and you were building things,
you were experimenting how materials work
and how strong they are
and how flexible they are
and so on and so forth.
Today, you simulate them.
You simulate materials almost
and you can actually simulate
a huge repertoire of materials
before you actually produce them.
In engineering, there is almost nothing
that is not simulated today.
Toilet paper.
Do you realize that you cannot actually
produce toilet paper without simulation?
These are very fine,
very soft tissue that you have to cut
in very specific ways
and you have to roll them out
at lightning speed in perfect...
this cannot be done
by experimentation.
It cannot even be done by theory.
You actually have to simulate
the physics of the tissue
in order to be able to wrap it.
Diapers, the space shuttles.
They have to be simulated in detail,
all the electronics.
Aircrafts,
they are being built through simulations
and then they are sent out to fly
without even a test run.
They just design them, simulate
and they are ready to go.
So simulation science is
the pinnacle of most of the sciences.
It hasn't arrived yet
at neuroscience, but...
..well, it has arrived now
at neuroscience.
So, I want to give you the rationale,
why do we need
simulation neuroscience
to understand the brain?
The first and actually,
the main reason
is that understanding
the brain is a big data problem.
If you look at the numbers,
you realize that
there is no way that you
are going to be able to understand
all these pieces
and how they interact together.
You have 20,000 genes.
About half of them are expressed
in every cell in the brain.
There is about 1,500
that are very sort of over expressed
in the brain, but most cells express
about 30% to 50% of their genes.
Then they produce
around 200,000 proteins,
different types of proteins,
but each protein has a variant.
So you have about a million
protein variants per cell.
Then you have,
probably, we predict
about a billion molecules in a cell.
There are thousands
of molecular pathways.
There are millions of molecular
interactions per second in a cell.
There at least 2,000 cell types.
So we have about 900 brain regions.
In each brain region,
there can be...
..at a minimum of two types
of cells, but in many cases
10, 20, 50 types of cells.
So there is well over
2,000 different cell types.
In the mouse brain, you have about
a thousand kilometers of fibers.
In the human brain about
a million kilometers of fibers.
In the mouse brain,
about a trillion synapses,
in the human brain about
a thousand trillion synapses.
Mouse brain about
a hundred million neurons,
in the human brain,
about a hundred billion neurons.
So just for one instance,
one age, one species, one strain,
individual variations
and one disease,
this is everything
you have to map
and understand
how they all interact together
to give rise
to the emergent behavior,
to psychophysical properties,
to give rise to cognition,
to give rise to a behavioral repertoire
and so on and so forth.
Imagine if you have to
do it for all the ages,
all the species,
all individual variations,
and for the more or less
600 different brain diseases.
This is not a problem that we can solve
only with experimental neuroscience.
Experiments of neuroscience
is key to ground truth.
You have to go back and test.
Always go back and test and experiment,
but there is no way
that you can understand the brain
if you do not have a strategy
where you can look at
how all of these elements
are interacting with each other.
And be able to predict
and look, explore
how they
could be changing the interactions
in different states of age species
and diseases.
So it is a big data problem
and there is no theory that is going
to solve this whole problem for you
in terms of understanding all the details
of what is going on in the brain
and there is not one experiment
that is going to solve all of this.
So for simulation neuroscience,
the claim is:
it is essential
for an ultimate understanding
of all the components of the brain
and how they give rise to us,
our personalities and behavior.