So, let's now go
to reconstruction strategies.
In reconstruction,
I already mentioned
that you build
your components bottom up.
So you start with your ion channels,
you build your neurons,
you build your synapses,
you connect your neurons with synapses
and you get circuits.
You package them into workflows
and to workflows and you automate
these workflows as much as possible,
because as I said, the most important
thing in simulation neuroscience
is actually to reconstruct,
test, validate, find mistakes,
reconstruct again and again
and again and again
until it becomes a digital copy
of the tissue.
So here is an example
and we will be going over that
in over many lectures.
You have your neurons,
you find out all your types of neurons
and then you work out
how to position them together
and then you find out
how to connect them together
and then you add the physiology,
how do they behave,
every neuron behaves.
And then how every synapse behaves
and then you have a circuit.
The last part that we will look at
is simulation strategies
and of course this involves billions
and billions of calculations
in order to compute
every ion channel opening
and there may be tens of thousands
of ion channels in a single neuron
and then there are currents
flowing inside a neuron.
So there are a lot of calculations
and Felix is going to give
you some ideas of the numbers
of calculations and types
of calculations that have to be done,
but clearly you need a supercomputer.
But sometimes people say
"oh, why didn't you do it on the grid?"
or "why didn't you do it
on some cluster or whatever?"
The important thing
about simulating neural tissue,
not building a model,
(INAUDIBLE) simulating your tissue,
a digital reconstruction is that...
...the whole simulation will run
as slow as
or fast as the slowest interaction.
The neurons have too much memory
to be on one processor,
so each processor
has to transmit information
to another processor
and so when
the neurons communicate,
they are actually
communicating between processes
and if you had a grid for example,
and just one connection was slow,
you would have to wait.
The whole brain, the whole tissue
that you have reconstructed has to wait
for that transmission
to occur before the rest can happen.
So you need a supercomputer,
where there is fast interconnect.
So that is why
you need a supercomputer,
you need
to have simulation code, of course
that can distribute
this problem of all these neurons
across many, many processes
and so you need the parallel code
and in the Blue Brain Project we have...
..worked with the father of
one of the most important
simulators called NEURON,
it is Michael Hines from Yale,
and we worked with him
to advance this code,
so that it can really run very large
scale simulations on supercomputers.
So you need parallel code
and then there are lots of other
challenges.
Supercomputers
were designed and built largely
for nuclear simulations
and for other kinds
of applications in physics
and in particle physics,
where you have a big problem,
you ask a question
and you get the simple answer back.
It is not as simple. It is a very
interesting answer, but you get an answer back
and in simulation neuroscience,
you want to...
you are dealing with a lot of memory
and you want to know everything
that is happening inside
the reconstructed tissue.
So you need
data intensive supercomputing
and you need efficient algorithms
to handle data.
You need to balance the load.
One neuron may be very big
another one may be very small,
so you need to know how to distribute
your neurons across processes
and you need to know how to manage all
your resources, your computing resources.
One may be going very slowly,
one may be going very fast.
So it is a resource
management challenge,
it is a data management challenge,
but principally, you can summarize
that as you need
data intensive supercomputing
and supercomputers are slowly
moving in that direction
where they can hold a lot of memory.
Now the value of simulations,
why do you need a simulation?
Is it just that you get
a nice pretty picture?
Well, it is because if you build it,
you want to see how it behaves
and you want to be able to compare
it to a real piece of tissue.
So the way we see the reconstructed
tissue is like a virtual brain
or virtual piece of tissue
and we want
that we can visualize it
and experiment on it
as if it is a real piece of tissue.
Now we look at real pieces
of tissues under the microscope.
We stain their cells,
we measure them electrically
and so we actually do very similar...
we build in silico microscopes,
in silico recording devices and so on,
so that we can directly compare
experiments with a virtual tissue.
Here is just an example,
where the difference
when you have a reconstruction,
a detailed reconstruction,
compared to the biological tissue
is that in the reconstruction,
you know everything.
You know every neuron,
the name of every neuron,
you know every single
spike that is occurring,
where the neuron is located,
you know every synapse
and so it gives you an x-ray
view into the digital tissue.
This is impossible in experiments.
You can get a tiny small view
into what is going on,
but you can't get a global view
and you can't get a deep view.
So by reconstructing the tissue,
if your algorithms are good enough
to replicate the tissue,
then you
have a virtual exploratory environment
where you have an x-ray view
into all the mechanisms.
And in subsequent lectures, we will see
the power of that.
That it can actually give you,
take you way beyond
what experiments can do.
You can explore mechanisms,
you can test hypotheses
about how the circuit behaves
in ways that
are impossible experimentally.