Let's look now at the
electrophysiological profiling,
how do we profile the electrical
behavior of neurons.
So, as I said, you obtain
these wholesale recordings
from cells.
So you find out, you stimulate a
positive current into this,
so you get a step pulse here.
And then you see how the cell reacts,
in this case, it's producing a burst,
it stops, and then
fires more spikes.
Here you do a high resolution,
it is a short time frame,
so you can actually look at when
does the action potential start,
you can get the amplitude,
you can see how fast it is rising,
you can see how fast it is falling,
you can see how deep it goes after,
because some can go...
afterhyperpolarization,
can be very big, some shallow.
You can give it a ramp pulse
to find out what is the threshold,
what is the threshold of the action
potential,
when does the cell start generating
action potentials,
and then you can give a range of
different current pulses
to see how the cell will react to
different current pulses.
You can try to give a series of
strong pulses to see
whether the action
potential will change,
in some cells, the action potential
drops and gets very small,
in other cases they don't.
So the amplitude can change,
and those old properties...
You can give short pulses and look
what happens afterwards.
And you can see here,
that the cell hyperpolarizes
and it recovers slowly after that.
So this is an afterhyperpolarization
potential.
You can give it a
negative pulse inward,
and then hyperpolarize the membrane
very fast and then it relaxes back.
And you will see in
Idan Segev's course
that this can be used to calculate a
lot of properties about the membrane.
Then you can also give different pulses
below thresholds, sub-thresholds.
And you can calculate the input,
the IV curve,
the current-voltage relationship
of a cell.
So the idea is you do a whole
battery of stimuli,
to actually probe a neuron and see
how it reacts.
It is a bit like a psychologist
for neurons.
And then you classify the
electrical behavior.
So, when you do that,
what we have found is that
there are essentially eleven types
of behaviors.
You have cells that are slow-firing
cells, for example, here or here.
You have very fast-firing cells,
they can go at high speed,
these are fast-spikers or
non-accommodating,
classical non-accommodating cells.
You have cells that,
when you excite them,
they say: "wait a minute",
and there is a delay,
and then they start spiking.
And you have the opposite,
where the cell starts
with a burst
so it starts actually with
a very high frequency burst,
and then it slows down.
So you have all these different ways
that a cell can behave,
some stutter, we call them
"stuttering cells", like here,
that is almost like a morse code.
Stuttering cells.
Others are even called
"irregular spiking",
it means you can't actually predict
when the cell is going to fire.
You stimulate it and then in some
other process they just
fire whenever they
seem to want to fire,
it is not as predictable as any of
these other approaches.
One thing that we found is that
for every morphology,
you can have multiple different ways
that they can behave.
So you can get a certain
morphological type of cell,
and you can discover
that same type of cell
can behave in different ways.
So either a fast-spiking cell,
this is a burst irregular-spiking cell...
So we call these
morpho-electrical types.
And so, in combination,
you can try and map the morphology
with,
"for this given morphology,
which electrical types do you find?"
And you can create a map between
different morphologies,
these are morphologies
and the different
electrical behaviors.
And what that gives you is,
in the case here,
where you have
fifty-five morphologies,
and you have
eleven electrical types.
In combination, it gives you
207 morpho-electrical types.
So these are the individual
characters, if you wish,
of the circuit.