Okay.
In the last lectures,
we learned a little bit about
what is simulation neuroscience,
the rationale behind it, some
of the principles on which it is based
and some of the caveats
to keep in mind.
And in this lecture,
we are going to look at how
we study single neurons,
how we profile the morphologies
and how we profile
the electrophysiological properties
of the neurons.
So, this is an example
of an experimental lab
that tries to reverse-engineer
or experimentally study
the micro-circuitry,
individual neurons,
synaptic connections
and how the micro circuit
is put together.
So there are a number
of components here.
You have what is called...
..an infrared differential
interference contrast microscope.
It is basically a clever trick
you can look it up on the internet.
It is a clever trick to get
very high depth view
into the tissue.
So, it just cleans up some
of the optical noise,
but it is a beautiful technique
that was developed
by Hans-Ulrich Dodt
and really pioneered
in Bert Sakmann's lab in Heidelberg.
We were all postdocs there at the time
and we started doing
a lot of experiments using this
kind of microscope, because
it gave us an unprecedented access
and view into the neural tissue.
There are these manipulators
that will bring electrodes
down into the tissue
that is under the microscope.
It is all controlled by pads
and in fact, we even have a setup
which we call fly patching,
because it is all done
as a sort of remote cockpit
that controls
all of these electrodes.
You have amplifiers
that amplify the electrical signal
and you have a number of...
you can put imaging
techniques as well.
These are controlling
the manipulators,
but you can also
have imaging techniques,
so you can look at fluorescence
or any other kinds of images.
It is just another example of lots
of pipettes,
the sort of record is 12,
you can only record
12 neurons at a time.
It is very few when you think
about the whole brain,
but you get very
high resolution recordings.
This is a movie that basically just
gives you a little bit more
of a perspective of...
..what the setup looks like
and here is a movie that shows you
what patch-clamping is.
This is a glass pipette.
The tip is about a micron in diameter
or a little bit bigger
and it approaches this neuron
and you can see,
it is patching the cell.
Now what that means
is that if you have a cell,
you come in with a pipette
and you come closer,
you actually blow...
you put pressure at the back,
so it blows solution out from the tip
and it cleans the membrane,
so you can actually get
the glass patching onto the cell
and the secret of patch-clamp
which was discovered by...
..Hamill and Bert Sakmann
and Erwin Neher,
and they won the Nobel prize for this,
is that it forms a gigaseal here,
so very high resistance.
It is very high resistance
between here,
so the current will not leak
out of here and it means
that you can break this membrane
and what you end up with is...
..your electrical recording here that
you can then measure
the voltage inside
and as you should know, these
are basic things you should know,
inside is negative
compared to the outside,
so this is typically about
minus 60 millivolts
and then you can see fluctuations
in this voltage.
So this is called
whole-cell patch-clamp.
Whole-cell patch-clamp,
and there are of course
other configurations
that you can also do to get
a piece of the membrane and so on,
but I won't go into that.
So this is whole-cell patch-clamp
and it gives us
access to a single neuron
and with this access
you can inject a dye into it
and here is a movie just showing you
what that cell looks like after
we have injected a dye into that cell
and stained it like developing
a photograph
and then you get a full picture of...
..what that morphology
of that neuron looks like.
You can also inject
fluorescent dyes into it.
You can inject calcium sensitive dyes,
you can do lots of different things,
injecting all kinds of chemicals
and experimental agents into cells
and then you can see them.
You can of course also record
from the dendrites,
you can record from the cell body,
you can record from the axon
and there are many studies
that you can look up about this,
because a lot of these studies are used
in the reconstruction.
And that allows you to really
get a very high resolution view
of nudges, the morphology,
but also the electrical behavior
of a neuron at the cell body
in the dendrites
or in the axon.
These are axons going down.
The sort of repertoire
that you can play out here
as you obtain a whole-cell,
this is a whole-cell patch clamp here,
the pipette is coming in here too.
It has broken the membrane.
You have a gigaseal,
so you can record from the cell
and this is what
an electrical behavior
will give a pulse, if you give it
a step current pulse into the cell
and the cell will react by
producing action potentials.
It is producing one
and then a burst of action potentials.
It stops and then there is
another burst of action potentials
and this, I will show you
how we profile this,
so that you can...
you do a lot of testing
to find out how does the neuron react
to electrical current that comes in.
You can also suck out some of the...
we call it cytoplasm harvesting
where you take out
some of the juice,
the cytoplasm
from inside the cell
and you do...
you isolate the RNA,
the messenger RNA.
You can convert that to cDNA
in a process
called reverse transcription
and then you get cDNA
and then you can fish.
You put in little probes
with sequences of specific genes
and you can fish out different genes.
You can ask yourself
"I want to find out,
if gene X, this purple one,
is inside the cell".
You make a specific gene sequence
and you send in this probe
and it tells you whether
this purple gene is inside this cell
using a process
we call multiplex PCR
and today there
are many more approaches
to find out which genes
are expressed inside a cell.
You can load the cell with a dye
as I said before
and then under a microscope,
you can reconstruct it
and here in red you see the...
in red you see the dendrites
going in different places.
You draw this in three dimensions
under a 3-D microscope
with an XYZ stage.
So, you are actually tracing it in 3D
and then you can also trace the axon
and that gives you
the axonal hover of the neuron.
You have to do this for many cells.
They take a long time.
It takes a week or so
or a few days at least
to draw, trace one cell in 3D,
so you have got
a digital model of the cell
and in our case, you know,
we have about a thousand
of these cells reconstructed
which is not,
as I said in the first stage,
it is still sparse data,
but that took 20 years to obtain,
so you have to find other ways
to build up your data set.
This is just an example
where you can see
the genes, the bands.
There are techniques that you
can use to see which genes...
These are ion channel genes.
Names of different
ion channel genes
and it tells you whether
these ion channels
are the gene that they must
switched on inside the cell.
So this gives you a genetic profile
or a molecular profile.
This is an ion channel profile.
You can also look at
calcium binding proteins
or neuro peptides
so that you can actually identify
the molecular profile of the cell.
So, this is what you can
do all in a single cell.
You basically get its electrical
profile, morphological profile
and a molecular profile.