Okay, so how do we profile
the morphologies?
Well, when you do
this many times
you of course see a vast
number of cell types and here
every cell type is colored
a different color
and there are many
different morphologies
different ways that
the dendrites are branching
different ways
the axons are branching
and so, you need a lot of
examples of each of these cells
and here is sort of a catalog,
a sort of a periodic table
of the main morphological cell
types that are in the neo-cortex.
These are interneurons,
the inhibitory interneurons
and these are excitatory,
typically pyramidal cells
but there are also
other types of cells
that are not strictly pyramidal
cells, but excitatory cells.
You can see they have many
different branching features
they have names,
Martinotti cells
Bi-tufted cells,
Double-bouquet cell
Bipolar cell, and so on,
and these names
actually come from about a hundred
years of anatomical study
starting with Ramon y Cajal,
a very famous Spanish anatomist
who actually drew lots of cells.
Under a normal microscope
he would actually look
under the microscope
and then he would
just draw them.
Today we can
trace them in 3D
but he named many
of these cells
and many of the famous
anatomists that followed
named many
of these cells.
Once you have the morphology,
you can analyze this morphology
and we have released an open
source tool called Neuro-M
which you can
actually just run and analyse these
and you can get lots of
parameters about the cell
how big the cell body is,
how big the arbor is
how frequently they branch,
what the angle of branching is
and so on, and then these features you
can use either to try to classify cells
to see which class a cell fits into
but you can also use
them in other ways
to build new cells, and I will
show you that in the moment.
So, the important thing here
is that the classification
is based on local morphology
so it is just on the way that
this cell looks.
This of course is not
everything about a cell.
Cells may project to further places
but it is typically
the excitatory cells,
they project to different
brain regions
they project... whether it is
across the hemisphere
or to deeper brain regions or even
just laterally to different parts
of the neo cortex, but we just
look at the local morphology
and the name is based on
the local morphology.
Now one of the caveats in
getting morphologies
in slices, brain slices,
you saw the slice before,
is that you actually
shave off in the slice
because this is the slice,
that is the thickness of the slice,
so, you shave off a part of the neuron,
the branches of a neuron.
So after you have done that,
you have to kind of repair
the missing part and there is
software called Neurorepair
which identifies where
these cut points are
and then it grows these extended
parts to be consistent
with the statistics
of the other side.
and then it grows these extended
parts to be consistent
with the statistics
of the other side.
This is how we repair the morphologies.
Sometimes we also use data from
in vivo recordings to learn
how to do this repairing process
better, so in vivo validation.
One needs a certain number of
cells to be able to clone them
and make a bigger data set
and here what you are seeing
is the averages.
The average is many
cells overlayered
on top of each other
and you see a sort of an average
hexagonal structure.
This helps us obtain the statistics
that you need to, A
repair the cells. Also,
you can now computationally
clone these cells
you can make many
copies of them
within the statistical variations.
They are not exact copies,
they are statistical copies
so even in this case of
the neo-cortical micro circuit
we have about a thousand cells,
but we have enough initial statistics,
past data statistics, to actually
build hundreds of thousands
or millions of copies of each
of these different cell types
so we can produce many,
many copies.
That is one approach
and a more recent
approach that we are using,
and we won't go into that
in this MOOC, is where we
actually computationally
synthesized
them using the rules
of how they branch.
The idea here is that you
want to learn how
to synthesize
any cell type in the brain,
and that is a long term goal.