We briefly looked at how
you study single neurons,
we looked at how you
obtain the morphology,
how you could analyze
the morphology,
there is a lot more that you can
read up on morphometrics,
there is open source software
that we have released
that you can use to analyze
the morphologies.
And we looked at
how you record from cells,
obtain electrophysiological
properties,
and how you characterize them,
and how you can use that
to identify different behaviors.
There is a lot in the literature
and a lot of publications
on how you classify based
on these properties.
It is not all clear sometimes,
that it is a clear class,
but there are approaches to be able
to objectively classify,
semi-objectively classify,
and sometimes very
subjectively classify cells.
It is a big area of research to
decide what really are classes,
but in many cases, you have to
look at multiple lines of evidence
in order to decide what a class is,
or whether there is a class.
Lastly, let's look at
just some caveats,
and here that main
caveat, of course,
is that you have to get such
high resolution data,
you need to record
from brain tissue,
and brain tissue means you have
got to cut the tissue,
and that means that you have
cut neurons
and you have to find a way
to repair these cut parts.
With patch clamp, of course, which
gives you the highest resolution
view of the morphology and the
electrical properties
and molecular properties
of a single neuron
but you can only record
from a few neurons.
That is one limitation of it.
So this really gives you
high-quality spa state.
And then, you have to classify.
There is a whole field of science
based on the classification
of different morphologies and
electrical types,
to decide what they are.
In summary, we learned about
brain slices,
that that is where the source of
a lot of very detailed,
high-resolution data comes from.
We learned a little bit about
patch-clamp,
but, again, I encourage you to
go and read up
about the electronics, and the
biophysics,
and the electrophysiological
principles behind it.
We learned how to obtain
morphologies.
And we learned how to
obtain electrical properties.