We looked at studying single neurons.
Two different ways
that we can explore neurons
in terms of the morphology
and electro-physiological properties
And today we are going to
look at ion channels,
profiling, molecular profiling,
what do we mean by neuron types
and how do we actually
obtain neuron densities
and then some caveats in a summary.
So ion channels,
they are the heart of neurons
if you wish
or heart of the electrical activity
of neurons
and it is quite a challenge
when you first go in and look
at all the ion channels,
but the organization
is actually quite elegant.
There are a lot of ion channel
related genes,
but many of these
associated proteins
that will regulate ion channels
or that make ion channels work.
There are about 280
well characterized ion channels
and of them, 145 are voltage-gated
which means that when the voltage
changes, they either open or close.
Now, the way to sort of
make it easy
to digest is first of all,
everybody should
know that ion channels,
they are special
transmembrane proteins that allow,
selectively allow ions
to flow through.
You can have an ion channel
that selectively allows
sodium to flow through for example
or specifically calcium
or you could
have typically potassium
and what you should all remember
and you should look this up is that
the potassium of course,
is very high on the inside of cells,
sodium is very high
on the outside of cells.
Okay.
Calcium is very low.
60 nanomolar or so
on the inside of cells
and calcium
is actually relatively very high
outside of cells in the order
of 1 to 2 millimolar.
Calcium is in the range
of 60 nanomolar.
There are pumps in that
and we are not going to be considering
these at this point in time.
It is not...
something you can get into later.
So when you look
at the potassium channels
or just the channels in general,
you have the sodium channels,
that is over here.
They are the ones that
essentially, help you to get
action potential, spikes.
You have the calcium channels
which also get activated.
For example in the heart,
most of the action potential
starts off as a sodium channel
and you have a long
calcium action potential
and in neurons, the sodium
spikes help activate calcium channels
which brings calcium into the cell
and that drives a number
of other biochemical processes.
So this is how you get
your excitation.
It is with your sodium
and calcium channels
and then you have your
resting membrane potential.
Most cells as you should know
inside is between
6 to minus 60 to minus 80 millivolts
inside the cell
and the way you maintain
that is by keeping a lot of...
..potassium inside,
but essentially,
it is about the permeability.
If a membrane that is only permeable
to potassium channels,
then you will go to what is called
the potassium Nernst potential
which you are going to learn
about later on.
And that keeps
the cell at this potential.
So you have to have
sort of leak channels
or channels that are just permeable,
they are not...
...necessarily very sensitive
to voltage,
they just stay open all the time
and they actually help keep
the resting potential.
So that is these.
These K2...
and the inward rectifiers.
By convention
when current flows out,
positive current flows out,
it is called an outward current
and when positive current flows in,
it is called an inward current.
Okay.
So the resting membrane potential
as I said here is controlled
by these channels.
The depolarization is controlled
by these channels
and then you have hyperpolarization.
What stops the excitation
and brings it back down again,
it is this class of channels,
the voltage activated...
...potassium channels
and you also have the calcium-activated
potassium channels.
So these are very important to
bring the membrane potential
back down again,
to stop the firing
and to allow another spike to occur.
So if we focus a little bit on
the voltage activated potassium channels,
because they are really the extremely
important in controlling excitation.
You block them, you get seizures,
everything goes wrong.
There are 40 genes, only 40 genes
in mammalian tissue
and many of them are also similar
in plants and others.
In 12 classes,
they are called Kv 1-12
and each gene produces
a specific subunit here
and you have to combine
four of them together
to form a channel.
If you combine, if it is one gene
that produces all four subunits,
the same subunit,
then you have what is called
a homomeric channel.
But you can have two genes,
each producing two subunits
and when they combine,
you have what is called...
..a heteromeric channel.
Homomeric for the same,
heteromeric for different subunits,
when different subunits combine.
If it was only homomeric channels
that could be produced,
you would have 40 channels,
of types of potassium channels,
but because there are different combinations
they can combine, different
subunits can combine differently,
the result is that there is well
over 40 different
voltage activated potassium channels.
This is very important, because
depending on which one you use,
you are going to have a different electrical
property in neurons as I will show you later.
So these are the family of...
the Kv family, what we call the Kv family.
How do we characterize
how these ion channels behave?
One way is to isolate
the messenger RNA.
To isolate messenger RNA
from the brain,
so you basically squash up,
homogenize the tissue,
you isolate the messenger RNA,
you do PCR amplification,
you get your cDNA,
you clone the gene
and put it into a vector
and you inject that into cell lines.
So you produce cell lines.
Cell lines like a Chinese hamster.
Ovary cell lines or hex cell lines
or different cell lines
that you can use
and then you can inject
the ion channel gene into these cells
and then they express,
they express the channel
on the membrane
and you can induce
the expression with tetracycline
or other kinds of chemicals
when you're ready
to study the channel.
And in the past it was that you
needed to use patch-clamp.
Patch-clamp, so you come
in with a patch pipette.
A very high resistance patch pipette
here as I mentioned yesterday.
A high gigaseal. Then you can actually
see this channel opening and closing.
Opening and closing.
But today we do this
in an industrial way.
There are robots and basically,
the robot just
puts the pipettes in
and patches automatically
and so you can do this at
a very high throughput way.
Now what you do when you
have your channel and you can study
how it is opening and closing,
you stimulate the channel.
Here you can see that
you give different pulses
of different amplitudes
and you study activation.
How does the channel open
when the voltage changes
and you study in activation
which is how does the channel close
once it has been activated.
So the voltage is active,
but the channel
just starts closing.
Even if the voltage is high,
the channel starts closing.
So you can see here the channel
starts closing.
And then you have deactivation.
Deactivation is,
after it has been activated,
how long does it recover
from this activation.
And then there are
other dynamic variables
and different ways
that you can study the channel,
but the most important is activation,
inactivation, deactivation.
So when you do that
on the 40 ion channel genes,
there are many that are silent,
because
homomeric subunits,
when they combine,
they are not going
to produce any current.
For example here,
you are getting silent channels.
These are silent channels.
But there are many that activate
and the first thing you can see
is that they have different
kinds of activation.
Many different kinds of activation.
This is Kv 10.2.
It has a slow activation.
This is Kv 1.4,
very fast activation
and inactivation.
This one has almost no inactivation.
It just keeps being activated.
So opening,
you can think of it like this
that opening during a voltage change,
you can either be fast activating
or slow activating.
Closing while the voltage is on,
you can have fast inactivating
or slow inactivating
and then how does it recover
after or close after activation.
Fast deactivating,
slow deactivating.
So you can see now
if you combine,
the combinatorics of combining
this can give you a rich,
a very rich diversity
of ion channel kinetics.
Now, this rich diversity of kinetics
is very powerful, because if you
combine them in different ways,
you can produce neurons with many different
electrical behaviors and properties.
Now unfortunately, at this stage,
there isn't a comprehensive
data set of every channel kinetic
which we can introduce into a cell
and we are building this and it will
be completed in the next few years.
In the meantime,
what we do is we look at classes
with build models of classes of channels
and we just call them
transient channels
or persistent channels
of calcium-activated
and these are basically engineered.
So they are engineered channels.
They are not genetically
determined channels.
They are theoretical channels in a way,
but we are replacing these channels
and then you have a neuron
that is very accurate.
What is important in relationship
with what I told you about yesterday
or in the previous lectures
is that, you can do this
and then still fit
the electrical behavior of the neuron,
but what you won't be
able to do is tell
what is the significance
of the ion channels.
The only purpose,
the ion channel serves is to give you
neurons that behave the way
that they behave in the brain
and then you can use those neurons
in circuits
and you can tell what neurons
are doing in circuits,
but not what
the ion channels are doing.
So that is what limits
your interpretation of your...
...simulation results.
Here is Channelpedia.
You can go there.
There is a big database
of all the channels,
giving you literature,
telling you about the channels
as well as the models
and there are Hodgkin-Huxley models
and Markov models that you can download.
You are going to learn how
to do this in later courses.
How to build
the Hodgkin-Huxley model.
So the beauty of having many
different types of ion channels
is that it depends
on how you mix them.
You can create voltage shapes.
All kinds of voltage shapes.
You can create bursting behavior
and you can shape the way
the neuron is going to behave
and here is just
an idea showing you that, you know,
depending on what kind
of sodium channel you have,
it will determine
how fast the voltage rises.
It will determine whether
the action potential gets smaller
with each successive one
or stays the same
and depending on the voltage activated
potassium channels,
it will decide on many things.
How fast you return,
how deep the return is,
what is called
the afterhyperpolarization potential
and whether a new spike can occur
or not occur.
So all these channels,
they really serve to control
many features of the way
the voltage is going to change.