Let's briefly look now at how
we get to neuron densities.
We are going to come back to this much
later in the next MOOC actually
about how do we reconstruct
the circuit,
but I just want to show
you how that is used,
how we use the molecular profiling
to actually get to neuronal densities.
So here is a movie that you can see
that is showing stained cells.
These are cell bodies.
Actually, it is staining everything,
glia and neurons,
but then you can stain,
you can apply different stains
many different stains.
So you can stain for the glia,
you can stain for GABAergic cells
and you can stain for neurons,
just neurons in general
and you can do many other stains
and using these different stains,
you can then start identifying
how many neurons there are
in each of the layers of the neocortex
and these are some numbers
and this is in the cell paper
that you can you should be following
during this course.
The important point to make
here also is that counting
how many cells there are in
a particular brain region is very unreliable.
It is the most unreliable, probably
one of the most unreliable data-sets
you can get to.
If you read a paper,
tells you how many
cells there are in the brain
or in a particular part of the brain,
just bear in mind
that there are 20 other papers
that will be contradicting that data.
The most reliable way to do this
is to do block staining.
A big block and then you use clarity,
so that you make sure that all your
neurons are in that piece of tissue
and there is a lot of certain care
that has to be taken
to make sure that you have controlled
for shrinkage and many other things,
to make sure that you really do know
how many neurons there
are in a particular part of the brain.
Okay. So, here is just a movie,
just showing you
that you put them all together,
we are going to come back
to this much more in the future.
And here again is...
you have the in silico staining
of each of these different peptides.
It is not important what they are.
It is just that you have many different
peptides and each of the neuron
is stained according to those maps
that I showed you before
and then you can do...
so you stain your virtual tissue
or the reconstruction
and then you can have a look at
what real tissue looks like when
it is stained with the same peptides.
And then you count and you
look at the distributions that you see
with in silico and the distributions
you see in the real system.
So then what you find if you actually...
after you have reconstructed
the circuit
with different cells
and different layers
and then you find
that it actually correlates
in terms of the recipe
which was obtained
from getting those densities.
It is one different data set
and the actual measurements
obtained from the real tissue.
So the reconstruction then basically,
looks like the real tissue.
So if you were an anatomist
and you were staining tissue
and you stained
the virtual piece of tissue,
you would see the
same patterns of staining
as you do see
in the brain tissue.