The first important caveat is that
when you have heteromeric channels,
the combinations are vast
which means it is very unlikely
we can measure them all,
so we do need to
find indirect ways
to determine the kinetics of
all the heteromeric channels.
The second caveat is that to obtain
very good ion channel data,
kinetic data, it needs a lot
of standardization.
So you will find a big discrepancy
of ion channel data
in the literature,
and it is largely due to different
standards being applied
in different laboratories.
The third caveat is that
classifications is still
a murky ground,
to classify different neurons
electrically, morphologically,
molecularly...
And ultimately we would need
single cell gene expression
patterns, what we call single
cell transcriptomes
which is close, but it is
not yet a solved problem.
So, to summarize,
in this lecture,
you learned a little bit that
there are many different ion
channel genes,
that each produce
different kinetics,
the electrical properties of a
neuron is determined
by the kinetics of each ion channel,
by the combination of ion channels
that you put into a neuron,
by the location where you put them,
and the densities of each ion
channel type.
If you know how the ion channel
genes are expressed in a neuron,
you can actually calculate
electrical properties.
And you also learned how to obtain
the density of neurons,
or at least got an idea how we
obtain density of neurons.
Okay, that is it for today.