Next, let's look
at the molecular profile.
We will come back to the ion channel
profiling and see
how that relates to the way that
the neurons are constructed.
Let's briefly look first deeper
into the molecular profile.
So here for example,
we started off,
you remember we said
how do we study neurons.
We can do whole-cell patch-clamp,
we get the electrical properties,
we get the cytoplasm and we can
determine which genes are expressed
and we stay in the cell
and we can get the morphology.
Now what you can do is,
and we can characterize
the electrical properties.
So you can say electrical property
one, two, three, four, five
and you can make a huge list
of seventy or hundred
electrical features such as,
the speed of the action potential,
upswing and downswing
and amplitude and so on
and then you can also take these
molecular profiles which genes
are switched on inside the cell
and you can create
Gene 1, Gene 2, Gene 3.
And when you have that,
you can start trying to compare
and ask yourself:
"If I look just at the genes,
how does it relate to what kind
of electrical behavior it is?"
So here you see an example
in this blue cell.
These are the genes that are
sort of negatively correlated,
which means that it is highly
unlikely to find these genes,
it is highly unlikely to find these
genes in the blue cell,
but it is highly likely that you will
find these genes in the blue cell
and here it is the opposite.
So these two neurons,
the one has a delay,
the other one has a fast start,
they are both fast spiking cells,
but they essentially have almost
an inverted gene expression profile.
So they are using
almost exactly the opposite
set of ion channels to produce
their electrical behavior.
And this is one of the information sets
we use when we try
and classify neurons.
So we don't only look
at their electrical properties,
we also have looked deeply into
what genes are expressed in them
and that gives us confidence that
we have two different classes.
As you can see in this case,
it is a very clear
separation of two
electrical types of cells.
So what you can do is you can take this
and this is a very simple linear operator
where you take your electrical
properties going from E1 to E61
and your genetic
or ion channels,
Kv 1-1 all the way down
to even calcium binding proteins
and other kinds of proteins
that are in the cell.
And you can ask how does
each value correlates with each gene.
And there are a lot of statistic
you can do
to see if it is statistically significant
and establish an operator
like this which gives you
the measure of the correlation
between these different parameters
and as I said this
is a very simple linear operator.
You can build much more
sophisticated nonlinear operators
and multi dependency
operators and so on,
but just this linear operator
is already very powerful,
because here you can see
that you can actually predict,
you can look at the genes
that are switched on
and you can apply
the linear operator
and you can calculate
with a very small error,
the size of an action potential,
the width of an action potential,
the fast down swing
of the voltage and so on.
And the reason why this is extremely
exciting and important is it means
that ultimately, we won't have to record
from every neuron in the brain
in order to work out
how it will behave.
We can get the gene expression.
So this is why one of the big goals
of working the Blue Brain Project
is to work with many
labs around the world
to try to obtain the single cell
gene expression profiles.
So if you go for example
to the human brain
or to a nonhuman primate brain
or to any other species,
you don't necessarily
have to restart everything.
You have to do some experiments
to see that this holds for example,
also in another species,
but then you can actually
try and get as much genetic
information as possible
and then you can predict
the electrical properties.
So that is an example again
of how you constantly look for ways
to rely on less and less data.
If we had to rely on recording from
every single type of cell in the brain
in order to find out what
electrical properties they had,
it is going to take us a very, very
long time to understand the brain.
This is a way around it.
It is not yet perfect,
but it is the beginning of...
...a step in that direction.
So in general,
you can see that what determines,
what determines
the electrical properties of a neuron
is essentially
the kinetics of each channel.
It depends on which combination--
if you combine this one,
this one, this one and this one,
you are going to get a certain behavior
and if you combine this one
and this one and this one and this one,
you get a different behavior.
So it depends on this combination
and it depends
on the specific kinetics
and then it also depends
on the location.
Where is this channel located?
Some channels are located
only close to the cell body,
other channels are located much
more out in the dendrites.
Other channels are located
more in the axon
and so if you know
what the kinetics are,
the combination of kinetics
and you know where they are,
you are very close to doing very little
to simulate a single neuron.
You are missing the densities.
You are missing how many
of these channels
do you need to put in
in each compartment.
And that is something
that you are going to learn about
and actually run an exercise
using BluePyOpt to
adjust the densities
in order to reproduce
electrical behavior in a neuron.
So here is just an example again.
The goal here is to get to densities
and in this movie
you can...
it is just trying to illustrate
how distributing channels
differentially on dendrites
can also give you many of these
different electrical properties.
The molecular diversity
can be mapped,
so you have your morphologies over here
and you can also map them
to the electrical properties,
so you can produce
this kind of map,
which tells you how many
combinations you can have
which we also spoke
about previously,
but what is exciting about this
is that you can continue this map.
You can say:
"I have this kind of morphology,
it expresses this these proteins"
and in this case,
it is expressing two different
kinds of proteins
and it will have
one, two, three, four, five
different electrical behaviors.
So you have this cell
expressing these two proteins
and it has five different
electrical behaviors
and you can build a map like that
for each of these cells,
in terms of what is the probability
that they are going to express
these different proteins.
These are calcium binding proteins.
They bind calcium and buffer calcium
and these are neuro peptides
and they exert other
modulatory effects
on how the neuron functions.
It is not critically important
to remember them.
It is just that you have many, many
proteins and peptides.
And we choose these,
because they tend to be
characteristic
of some types of cells.
So with this map,
it is possible now
to actually go and stain
your model neuron,
because you can
calculate the probabilities
that they are going
to have these proteins,
so you can stain them.
You add these proteins
probabilistically into these kinds
of neurons for example.
And that way you can
stain all your neurons,
in silico neurons,
and then you can of course compare them
to what is seen in vitro,
in the real tissue.
So with that,
we can now have a look at...
you have a basic idea
of the morphology profiling,
electrophysiology profile,
ion channel profiling,
how we do that,
molecular profiling
in terms of other types of proteins
such as calcium binding proteins
and neuro peptides.
And now let's briefly
look at neuron types
and there is...
It is quite a huge field.
Debatable.
There is no clear consensus
about how to name a neuron,
how to classify a neuron,
but there are some important guidelines
and the guidelines that we use
when naming a neuron
is a bit like in chemistry.
You start off by...
...identifying the location
of the neuron in the brain.
It may be in the visual cortex,
in the layer two,
so you would call it
the visual cortex layer two cell.
And then you identify
the local morphology.
So it may be in
the visual cortex layer two,
Martinotti cell.
And then you identify what subclass
of electrical behavior it has,
so it would be visual cortex,
layer two, Martinotti cell,
delayed accommodation.
And then you would identify
what molecular profile it has,
such as expressing somatostatin
and then you would go further
and indicate as many genes
as you can find within that cell
that may characterize
that type of cell
and then ultimately it may be
that two neurons
that are almost identical,
they will not be genetically
perfectly identical,
but they may be very similar,
they could actually project
to different brain regions
and you could classify these
according to the projection type.
So the way that we look at neuron
classification and naming
is that we should think
about the dimensions
in very separate ways
and combine them in a systematic way
starting with location to morphology
to electrical properties,
molecular, genetic
and then projection,
projection subclasses.