In this lecture, we are going to
look at synaptic connections
how do we characterize
a synaptic connection and briefly
look at what stochastic synaptic
transmission is and some caveats.
So first of all before we go into
looking at synaptic connections
it is important to understand
the location of synapses.
Where they are is extremely
important for what the cell body
will sense and hence react when
it sends the input further.
So, the location is
a very important feature
and it is not just
enough to say neuron
A is connected
to neuron B.
In the case of
detailed morphology
the location is
extremely important.
And here what you see
is experiments very
elegant experiments
done by Stewart and Sakmann,
where they put an electrode
into the cell body, and then
an electrode into the dendrites
and they evoke this
action potential in the cell body
and it traveled backwards,
because we can see the delay
and then you see it
in the dendrite after
so it basically travels back and
it is called the back-propagating
action potential.
This is very important because
this is a signal that mediates
plasticity and many,
many other things
and it is a very important part...
a lot of learning theory today.
So, this is a key experiment
that is related
to the current understanding
of how neurons learn
but it also illustrates that
if this propagates
back with a delay
it is going to hit different
synapses at different times
so synapses that are sitting
at different places could be
effected in very
different ways when
action potentials
propagate back.
This is another example
if you had an input
here in the dendrite
and you inject a sharp
current in the dendrite
then this is what you
see in the cell body.
Iran Segev is going
to give you all the theory
and the mathematics behind what
happens from here to here
but for now what is
important to understand is
that if you had synapes
here it is quite different
from having a synapse here,
so location is important
and this rationale is
important for how
your characterize
a connection.
In the neocortex, there is
actually only one connection
out of thousands that
could exist, that has been
fully and extensively
characterized
and even in our lab
we only did it once
and then we did it with less
and less data subsequently
so this is this paper which is
a comprehensive characterization
and I will use it to illustrate what
would be a sort of a comprehensive
characterization of
a synaptic connection.
So you record from two neurons,
this is your one pipette
your second pipette,
and then this is the action axon
going from one cell,
and they have collaterals
which you can't see here, and these
collaterals move up and they touch,
they form synapses on this other neuron,
and when you excite this cell
you produce an action potential
then in this cell you see
this response occurring
and every time there is
an action potential
you can see sometimes
it is a small response
sometimes it is a bigger response,
and a bigger response
and so this cell is sending
a message to this cell
but it is receiving it with
a different delay and latency
which is here, it takes about
one and a half millisecond
for the information to get across
to the cell, but there is a distribution
and it also has different amplitudes
so stochastic in its sense is it has different
amplitudes and different latencies
and we are going
to explore why.
You can do a much more higher
resolution view where you have
what we call
a pre-synaptic spike
and then you can look at
the response and
you can characterize
exactly this delay across
many different connections.
Previously it was just in one
connection you can see these delays
but now you can see
across many connections
and you can see
there is a lot of range.
So, some cells will
take one millisecond
to communicate
with another cell
other cells may take six milliseconds
to communicate, the same types of cells,
we got this big range of
time delays between neurons.
Some responses
will be very short
and some responses will
also rise very slowly
so they could go very
fast up and down
where they could go
slowly up and slowly down.
The amplitude also
varies a lot, up to six
actually we have even recorded
even up to about 12mV
for this kind
of connection
but most of them
around 1mV range.
So, typically, when one neuron
connects to another neuron
it excites it, it is producing a
1mV depolarization,
what we call an excitatory
post-synaptic potential.
We can go a little bit further,
and when you study these carefully,
so you are triggering the spike here
and you look at the response
and then sometime it fails,
nothing happens.
If you look at
the amplitudes that you get
you either get nothing
or you get a distribution
so you get a range
of amplitudes that
can be generated
inside a single cell
but then you have
many connections
where most of them don't fail.
So, this is rare for this
type of connection
where most of them don't fail.
So, this is rare for this
type of connection
but there are many
others that fail
and some of them can
have very high failure rate
so they try to communicate
but nothing is getting through.
Here you can see an example,
also, of a very strong connection,
it is about 6.4 - 6.45 millivolts,
but even on each trial there is
a change in the amplitude
and this is
the range of the amplitude,
as you can see.
a change in the amplitude
and this is
the range of the amplitude,
as you can see.
So, when neurons communicate
they communicate with a jitter
a range from 1ms to 6ms,
and the amplitude can range
anything from 1mV to 12mV,
and we need to understand
those mechanisms and how
to recreate those mechanisms.
Okay so when you stain these neurons
as we explained before
how you stain them,
you load a dye
into these cells,
this is a photograph under
a microscope when
you have developed
this dye like a photograph, so
you can see these cells.
You can follow the axon
and their collaterals here
you can follow them,
and you can identify where the axon
is touching the dendrite
of the other cell.
And these areas are what
we call putative synapses
because at the light microscope
level you can't identify
whether it is real synapses or not,
you can just say that because the axon
is passing by
and touching a dendrite
and the axon is forming what
is called a bouton,
it is very likely that that is
going to be a synapse.
But this can be verified
by looking and doing
an electron-microscopic analysis
and here you see
the pre-synaptic side with vesicles,
these are synaptic vesicles
you see here, and this is the cleft.
It is very difficult in
experiments like
this to get very high quality
electro markers,
EM pictures,
and this is the synapse
this is the post-synaptic side.
So you can verify that,
what we call physical touches
are actual synapses at
the electro-microscopic level.
Now, what is important
in this is that
when we did this analysis where
it immediately became clear
is that one neuron
connects with
another neuron by
putting many synapses.
So, this is not a point contact,
it is a hand contact.
Lots of synapses onto
a single neuron.
And this is extremely important
because it is a very strong rule
in the neocortex and you will
see that this rule later
is one of the most important rules
that allows you to actually predict
connectivity in the whole circuit.
This is what is called
the multi-synapse rule
connectivity in the whole circuit.
This is what is called
the multi-synapse rule
and we are going
to discuss it
a lot more about that in the future.
The number of
connections varies
between the different
pairs of cells
some of them can have
an average of 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8
sometimes 10 connections
so this is the distribution
that you see.
The probability that one
neuron will connect
with another neuron is also
quite low, it is around Pc=0.1
or 10% and we will discuss
in future lectures
what combining this knowledge
with this knowledge
means for connectivity.
It has actually a lot
of relevance
for understanding how
neurons connect with each other.
So, this is just a view.
You can see that when
multiple neurons connect
there is a cloud of
synapses that are formed
so you can imagine when
one neuron communicates
there is a cloud of
synapses that are formed
so you can imagine when
one neuron communicates
with all these others, it is
actually triggering lots
and lots of little voltages
in all the other neurons.
So this is not going to
reveal how synapses work
this you should
read up in textbooks
but just to remind you,
you have the axon coming in
it forms a bouton, actually
pretty much it doesn't look like this,
it has a bouton and the bouton
has got mitochondria
which you also see here,
they are the powerhouses
they produce ATP
so that this thing can run
it is below a micron, it is like
half a micron typically
and when the action potential
propagates down the axon,
it gets here, the voltage
shocks the release of these vesicles
and the chemical,
the neuro-transmitter,
diffuses to the other side
in this case Glutamate in
the excitatory connection
and it activates receptors,
different kinds of receptors
here, AMPA, NMDA, Kainite
and when these receptors are
activated they
open and ions flow in.
Sodium, potassium may flow out,
calcium may flow in and so on.
But, let's look a little bit
at the synaptic dynamics
so as we said,
we have one neuron
it has in this case six synapses,
and if you isolate
and this you can do in the model,
you isolate each of these
that are located at different
places, on the (INAUDIBLE) right
and you look at this one individually
and this one individually
you can see that they have
very different behaviors.
Different amplitudes,
different rise times
delay times, and what
you see in the cell body
is also quite different.
So, the location is very important
and one has to bare in mind
that when the single neuron
communicates with a cell
So, the location is very important
and one has to bare in mind
that when the single neuron
communicates with a cell
each of the "fingers" that
are communicating is actually
exerting a different effect
on the target cell.
Okay, let's briefly look at stochastic
synaptic transmission.
This is a very big field as well,
and there is a lot of
very interesting ways to analyze
how synapses work
and you use methods
called quantal analysis, where
for example if only one vesicle
or one synapse fired
you would see this sort of
response and that would
be called the quantal size.
If two fired synapses are released,
you would see a double amplitude
if three, you would see a triple,
and so on.
And in systems where these are
very nice and clearly separated
you see these bumps.
But in the central nervous system,
in the neocortex
because the synapses are in
different places in the dendrites
this becomes blurred
and you basically see
a very blurry distribution.
So it is very difficult to do what is
called quantal analysis
in central nervous
system neurons
and it is important if you can
do it because you can
actually identify how many vesicles,
what is the amplitude
what we call the quantal size
how much impact does
a single vesicle have
or a single synapse have
on the post-synaptic side.
As an exercise,
try to answer for yourself
the following question.
What is the probability of
successful transmission
if you have five synapses
in a connection,
and each with a probability of
0.5 of releasing when
an action potential
comes along?
So, you got five synapses,
each one has the probability
of 50% chance of releasing.
What is the chance that you
will have a complete failure?
Or what is the chance that
it will always be a success?
Also calculate what is
the mean amplitude
if each quantal size was just one.
So what would be
the average five,
each one with
the 0.5 probability,
they each produce
one if they worked
what would be the average?
And calculate what is
the coefficient of variation
of the transmission.
If you need help,
look at this paper.
Okay, let's look
at some caveats.
So, the first caveats is
that it is very difficult
to obtain detailed
characterizations
of synaptic connections.
What I showed you
is one connection
that is being extensively
characterized
and since then we have only
partially characterized up to
about twenty-two
other connections.
And there are
hundreds that remain
and that is one of the reason why
I have to do reconstruction
because you can actually predict
most of those others now
and that is what we are going
to do during the course
of this MOOC and illustrate
how that is done.
You also cannot verify easily
that when an axon
touches a dendrite
that it is a real synapse
and you can't always do
electron microscopy.
So, you do have to
have data that
tells you what is your confidence
that this is a synapse.
And then the last caveat is
that the classical quantal analysis
where you can kind of peel
out what is the effective
and individual synaptic vesicle
or an individua synapse
and the probability
that it is releasing
the size that it is releasing
and how the whole connection
works is quite difficult
because of the uncertainty
about the locations,
the locations are distributed
the number of vesicles
that are released
maybe one or two or three
and then you may
have many synapses.
So, these things make
the quantal analysis
more difficult in central
nervous system
but it is not impossible
there are statistical
approaches around it.
And to summarize what we
learned in this lecture,
the most important thing to
remember is all
synaptic connections
in the neocortex are
multi-synapse connections
they are hand connections,
they are not finger connections.
Synaptic responses vary
because every release
site is probabilistic,
the vesicle can release
probabilistically,
different synapses can
behave probabilistically,
the size of the vesicle
can also vary slightly
not hugely, but slightly
and then the locations
of the synapses
on the dendrites
can vary a lot.
The third piece of information
that you learned here
was that the number of
the synapses per connections
depends on the type of
connection, so if I have...
I showed you an example,
where it is just parametal cells
and they may form between
3 and 8 connections
if you go to a different
type of cell
it may be between
5 and 20 synapses
and so every pair
actually has its own
range of numbers
of connections.
And then lastly, because of
stochasticity in both
the latency and amplitude vary,
with the action potential
one has to bear in mind that it is
a really very noisy signal
that is being transmitted from
one neuron to another.
Okay, that is it for this lecture.