In this lecture
we are going to focus
on synaptic dynamics.
In the previous one,
we touched briefly on
the quantal size of the kinetics,
of the strengths of the synapse
the amplitude of the synapse,
and now we are going to focus
on the dynamics of
transmission in particular.
So, when you record from
four neurons, 1, 2, 3, 4
it is not that they are all
connected to each other.
You will find that
10% are connected
so there is a 10% chance that
they are going to be connected to each other
in this case it maybe that this
one is connected to this one
but remember with
multiple synapses.
Now, what I showed you
previously was that it was
what was the response to
a single action potential
that you produce this EPSP.
EPSP as your action potential.
But if you give a train
of action potentials
so it is a high frequency train
you see that the amplitude
starts dropping
and if you then wait,
you wait for 500ms
and you give another
action potential
you see that it is recovered
to some extent,
it hasn't completely recovered,
you would have to wait longer
before it recovers to this level.
This is called synaptic depression.
Now, it is extremely important
because every synapse has
some synaptic depression.
So they are not
linear synapses,
there isn't any case
in the neocortex
at least where every spike
has the same effect
if it is given in a high
frequency.
So this is synaptic depression,
so you have the conductance
which is the amplitude,
how big is this response
and that is only for
the first action potential
which you see here as well,
and then if you give a train
you see this drop,
so we call this the weights
and what most people know in neuroscience
and most people use in neuroscience
and when they build
models of the brain
and neural network models
they have two
neurons that
are connected and they
adjust the weights.
This is what they are
talking about
as what is the magnitude
of the response when
one neuron communicates
with another neuron
but it is not that simple and it is
actually much more exciting
that there is also an interesting
dynamic in the transmission
so it is almost as if the synapse
gets tired of communicating
you start communicating,
it is a loud sound in the beginning
and then it gets softer.
Now, it has
interesting behavior
interesting properties
of synaptic depression
is that if you start off with 10Hz,
you see this kind of depression
and then you go to
20Hz, 30Hz, 40Hz
and it depresses faster.
If you plotted on a curve,
you see that the synaptic
amplitude drops significantly
and these two
curves are actually
in high calcium
and low calcium.
This is the low calcium case.
The reason why
we drop calcium
is because it lowers
the probability of release
so that the EPSP
starts off smaller.
If the calcium is high it starts off
bigger and depresses faster.
But what is interesting is that,
at a certain frequency
the amplitude drops inversely
proportional to the frequency.
It is what we call one of F behavior
and that is important because
it means that beyond
this frequency
you can fire
the presynaptic cell
as fast as you want
but the product of
the amplitude and
the frequency stays constant.
Which means you are screaming
as loud as you want
and the louder you
scream the more
the amplitude is adjusted
so that you hear exactly the same thing,
and you can see that here
the steady state amplitude plateaus.
So that means that
neurons have a limit
in how they are communicating
with this you can't
just jack up the volume
you can't just communicate
faster and harder
there is a dynamic, it is reacting
to how you communicate
and this is going to turn out
to be extremely important
shaping the dynamics of
neural circuits and we believe
they are fundamental
to the emergence
of higher level
cognitive functions.
Now, an interesting principal,
there are a few principals
we have learned from this
and the first is that, when you...
these are three cells here
there are three cells here,
one, two, three
and one cell is communicating
to both these cells
so here is the action
potential train from cell one
that is communicating
to the other three
and in one cell you can
see a strong response
and in other cell you
see a small response
and that is probably just
because it has less synapses
so it is just connecting
with maybe
two or three or
four synapses
and here it is maybe connecting
with five or six synapses
but also because the probability
of release here may be low
and the probability of
release here may be high.
The principal here is that
even though they have
different amplitudes
they all show depression,
and so the principal is,
when these types
of cells communicate
with each other
these are layer five
parametal cells, they depress.
And this is going to be
important as you are will
see in the next few slides.
Now, what you also
find is that if you have
two of the same
type of cell
and they communicate
with each other
you see the depression,
which is what you see here.
But, if it is also
the same axon and
it touches
another type of cell
suddenly you see an opposite
type of behavior
the synapse gets stronger
and actually it even
gets so stronger
it starts firing this other cell.
So, this singe cell can
start communicating
and then it kind of warms up
and it gets stronger
until this cell reacts.
This is called synaptic
facilitation. Okay.
Synaptic facilitation has
another interesting dynamic
in response to frequency.
So, when you increase
the frequency here
the amplitude first grows,
and then it reaches a peak
and then it starts depressing,
and it starts depressing because
this synapse also has depression
it is just that it
has a slower time
constant for the depression.
So, first you see the facilitation,
that you see here
that makes the amplitude
grow and then it drops
and what is interesting is that
depending on how much
facilitation there is
you can actually
calculate when it is
going to reach its
peak frequency.
This is very important because
that means that these synapses
behave like bandpass filters.
At a certain frequency
they are going to be the strongest.
If the frequency is lower
they are going to be very weak
and if it is much higher, they are
going to be very weak as well.
So, there is a certain frequency
that that they have got to fire
in order to have a maximum
effect on the other cell.
What this translates into
is that if you have
poisson type of firing
which is what
you have when you
record from
neurons in the brain
actually it doesn't look like this,
it needs structure
it looks like there is noise,
they are just firing
and if you apply that kind of
firing to a pre-synaptic cell
and you look at the response
you see wildly
fluctuating amplitudes
so you do not get
a constant amplitude
which is what most
people today still
even ten years
after this discovery,
most people still use
in neural networks
constant amplitude synapses
with just the weight
and not with the dynamics.
But this is how all synapses
in the neocortex behave.
Now there are three classes
there are the synapses
that facilitate,
they grow, and we classify
them and you can actually distinguish
them statistically
you can cluster them
and you can show that
these are different classes
these will occur between
certain types of cells
and not between other
types of cells
and then you have
the depressing synapses
and then you have what we
call pseudo linear synapses,
synapses that with
a facilitation and depression
are almost balanced
so the synapse can fire
at very high frequencies
and they only show a
mild depression.
Now what is
interesting is that if
you look at a single neuron
now you have to consider that
there are many
different types of cells that
are communicating with this cell
and each of them can use
a different type of synapse.
That means that this
neuron is interpreting
even exactly the same
action potential train
that may be coming
even if they could inject the same
action potential train
from each of these cells
this neuron would interpret
this message differently
from each neuron, for each neuron.
But it doesn't just stop there,
it is because these
synapses are also distributed
in many different places.
So, now you can see that what
a single neuron listens to,
when it is listening to this crowd
of other neurons around it
depending on which
cell it is listening to,
those synapses are sitting on
different parts of the dendrite
and it is interpreting
the input from those
different parts of the dendrite
in a unique way
specific to that cell.
So it is almost as if every
neuron has its own way of
selectively listening to
specific types of cells.
And this complicated
map actually is just a map
of what kind of synapse
you are going to place
or exist between
different types of cells.
There are actually
thousands,
as close to three thousand
different types of connections
in this micro circuitry
of the neocortex
and we haven't recorded
from all of them
but what we have discovered
was a set of principles
that allow us to extrapolate that
if you have a parametal cell
and it is connecting with
the Martinotti cell
or any that have these
electrical properties
then it is going to use
this type of synapse
and if it is connecting
onto a basket cell that
has these electrical
properties
then it is going to use
this type of synapse.
This way we actually
have a way today
to almost completely
specify what kind
of synapse exist between
different pairs of cells
even though we haven't
recorded from all of them.
So, the caveats in what
I have showed you today
is that synaptic dynamics
may change during recording
which I haven't told you
but it is because the dynamics
in a synapse may require
an energy supply
and if you patch a cell
you may dilute
the energy supply
ATP, and creating phosphate and
other support systems.
So one has to be careful
when studying dynamics
to ensure that you are doing it in
a way that you are not depleting
to see a sort of rundown
of the dynamics.
The second caveat is that there
is a combinatorial principal,
it depends on
the identity of
the pre and
the post synaptic cell
as to what kind of synapse
they are going to put in there.
That means that you really
need to solve a very big puzzle
where you have all your cell types,
versus all your cell types
and you have to find out
what type of synapse to put
between all of them
and that is not possible to do,
even for a small piece of the brain
let alone the whole brain
but what is possible is to get
some principal so you can
infer that between this type
of cell and that type of cell
they are going to place this
type of synapse.
The third caveat is that you need
to understand dynamics
you have to stimulate
the pre-synaptic cell
with a train of action potentials.
Many people stimulate
with one spike
then you are blind
to the dynamics
and if you stimulate
with two spikes
you can look
into the theory
it is impossible to work out
what the dynamics are.
So, what is called the pen pulse
protocol is insufficient
to characterize
synaptic dynamics
and it is an important
caveat to remember
if one wants to characterize
or interpret
synaptic data that one
finds in the literature.
Okay, so what you learned
in this lecture was
that there are strong frequency
dependence synaptic dynamics
in all connections
in the neocortex
there is no exceptions.
Most excitatory to excitatory
synaptic transmission
shows synaptic depression
although there is depression
between all kinds of cells
and in some you have
synaptic facilitation,
typically onto certain
types of inter-neurons
or inhibitory cells, so they
get activated with a delay.
And then the same axon can travel
and have a depressing synapse
and then the next bouton can
have a facilitating synapse
so when a single neuron communicates
with a thousand other neurons
it actually has different synapses
to interpret the same message.
So it is like I am sending a broadcast signal,
and everybody that is listening
hears something different.
So, the last thing you have learned
is that the synaptic dynamics
depends on both the pre and
post synaptic neurons
so it is a partnering, so you
take any two people,
it depends on the identities
of the two people
as to how they are going
to interpret what
each other are saying.
Same person talks
to another person
there is a different
interpretation
because there is
a different synapse.
Okay, that is it for this
time, thank you.