I am Sean Hill,
co-director
of the Blue Brain Project
and the head
of the division of
the neuroinformatics.
I'll be talking today
about some of
the neuro informatics'
issues and challenges
in organizing all of
the data needed
for the data driven
modeling process.
So, I'll start off taking you
through the importance
of meta data and
provenance and how we use
that to build up
the knowledge graph
I'll introduce ontologies
I’ll give some examples
of text mining
and data integration
from the literature
and I’ll also just give
a quick overview
of the brain Atlases
and search and interface
into our knowledge base.
So, first of all, the challenge
in neuroscience
is really that neuroscience
data is really heterogenous.
Nearly every piece
of data is gathered
in a different lab with
different protocols
and different
experimental techniques
and the challenge is of how
do we take all this data
which is really ranging from
the sub-cellular level
from gene expression
and proteomics
to the cellular level
with individual cell
electro physiology
and morphology
up to the tissue level
and whole brain scale
with the new techniques
coming in
to measure the whole
brain activity
EEG behavioral measurements.
How do we actually
integrate that data?
How do we organize it
so that we can find
the relationships between
those different levels
and ultimately build
models that helps us
go from gene to behavior
and this is the challenge
in neuroscience.
And the way that we
approach it in Blue Brain
and this is the challenge
in neuroscience.
And the way that we
approach it in Blue Brain
is really to establish
an iterative
cycle of data integration
by building models
but building digital
preconstructions
that help us understand
how do the pieces of data
actually fit together
and then if we take this step
by step by starting from data
available data from the literature,
existing models
existing data repositories,
we have to organize
that data into Brain Atlases
so we can start using
to build models
run simulations, and then
perform a validation step
and that validation is really
essential to the process
because it’s only by
validating the model
by showing where
does it work
and where does it not work
where is it consistent
with biological data
and where does it
fail to recreate
the biological phenomenon
that we know occur.
And it’s through
that process
and iteratively
performing that process
that we improve
the models
that we identify
new experiments
that should
be performed
missing data that
would be critical
that would be
filling in key gaps
between the levels,
and overall starting
to identify the principals
by which this whole
brain operates across
different scales.
And the neuroinformatics
platform is really the key
to supporting that process,
that center of the process
by enabling the data
to be organized
data that maybe distributed
around the world
And here, there we got
different components
of the neuroinformatics
platform.
One is the data space,
which is really where
is the data situated,
distributed around the world.
We’ve got data
registration a process
by which we annotate
the data
with the meta data
necessary to discover it
and to anchor it in Atlases.
We’ve god the knowledge
graph and search
which I’ll talk about, which
allows us to actually find
and discover data
and the related data
so any type of data
and its properties
as well as Atlases,
which help
us to navigate the data
discover data related to
particular brain structures
and also anchor data
into a standard space.
And finally, we have
the knowledge space
which the online
community encyclopedia
which really provides
a place where
the current state
of knowledge
can be maintained
in terms of
encyclopedic article
but also links to data
and data that
is either in
the knowledge graph
that we’re talking about
or in other
curated data
bases from
around the world.
So where is the data?
This is actually a massive
challenge for neuroscience
because most of,
what’s the so called
the Long tell data is actually
in printed documents
or it’s unpublished.
There are about a Hundred
thousand publications
or it’s unpublished.
There are about a Hundred
thousand publications
each year in neuroscience,
but unfortunately
a print publication
or a .PDF is not
a machine accessible way
to get data or even
to get knowledge.
It really requires
reading the paper
understanding what is
talked about and seeing
if you can extract data
from that paper manually.
And that’s
a massive challenge
it’s not an efficient way for
the future of sharing data.
What we see on this
graph is that there
is organized big data
in the Allen Institute
for Brain Science
is probably the best
example of generating
high quality large scale data,
but as I was saying
most of the data
is actually unpublished
or dark data or it’s
referred to in papers.
And there’s a big challenge
of how do we discover it
how do we find it,
how do we organize it
how do we make
it accessible?
And the way that
you do that
you’ve got to be able
to make it possible
to combine data, so in order
to find the small data
and to make it
possible to combine it
to make big data,
is that you’ve got to make
that small data discoverable
you’ve got to make it
machine accessible
you’ve got to use
the standardized meta data
data types, data structures,
and identify
which data has actually
been produced using
a compatible
experimental method
or from a compatible
experimental context
from which data
can be compared
and that’s
a massive challenge.
Now, there are different
ways of organizing data.
One of those is to put them
into folders on a hard drive
and this is quite common
when you ask somebody
to share their data,
very often it comes in folders
in sets of different files,
and you navigate the folders
to find the pieces of data
that you’re looking for.
Now, a somewhat more
sophisticated approach
is to actually have searchable
meta data that tags
this data with properties
that are then searchable
and this gives you
a lot of flexibility
and how you can discover
and access the data.
So, we really thing that
having meta data annotations
for the data files
and making that searchable
is really key to having
a much more flexible way
to discovering
and accessing the data.
So, there are three main
classes of meta data.
There’s descriptive
meta data
and that’s really the data
that describes the key
properties of the data for
discovery and identification.
That includes things like
the title, the abstract
the author,
maybe keywords that
help identify the data set.
Structural meta data
is information about
the structure of
the different pieces of data
how are they put together,
for example in a document
how are the pages ordered
to make chapters.
Administrative meta data
is actually that meta
data that provides information
on how that resource can
be accessed, by who
what file type is it, it really
helps provide information
about who can, who
should and what ways
in which that data set
can be accessed.
And that’s
important for things
like protecting privacy
or knowing when
the data set actually
hasn’t been accessed
for a long time
and can be
archived to tape.
But coming out of
the laboratory
that’s really the point where
you want to have
the richest meta data
annotations, in fact
one of the greatest
challenges
in current
neuroscience is that
when you get a data set
it usually it doesn’t have
the meta data
that you would
when you get a data set
it usually it doesn’t have
the meta data
that you would
need to actually understand
the contents
and it would be a lot of work
for the experimenter
to go back and add
that meta data.
So, we’re really
advocating that
at the point of data capture
in the laboratory
that you capture
all the meta data needed
and some of the best practices
that we would advocate
is using the electronic
note books
use of the laboratory
information
management systems
electronically capture
the details of the specimen.
What species is it?
What experimental
protocol are you using?
What is the data captured
from specific experiments?
Document the experimental
design that includes
having the hypothesis clearly
documented the objectives
the protocols are really critical
and the provenance in terms
of which data samples
came from which specimens,
and so on.
Use standardized
vocabularies’
when recoding
meta data values.
This is really essential because
in the end when you
want to analyze what
you discovered
you want to be as consistent
and as rigorous as possible
in the way that you annotate the data.
And also, finally,
curate the data
when you’re selecting
the key set of data
that is used for
the publication
or is used to be shared
with the community
select the high-quality data,
make sure that you flag
and remove the data with
questionable quality.
You as the experimenter really
are the best person to judge
and the best time to make
that decision is when
you’re very familiar
with the data that
has been captured
from the experiment.
One of the additional
challenges is what
meta data is really needed.
How do you find
neuroscience
data set if you’re talking
about any possible type
of neuroscience data set?
And this is a big challenge,
and it still remains
to be addressed by
the community in terms
of setting the common
standards od what is
the minimal meta data
needed to describe
a neuroscience data set.
Here we’ve developed
an initial proposal
we want to see this
developed further
in collaboration with
the community
but also adopted widely.
So, what our proposal
is what we call
“The Minimal Information
for Neuroscience Datasets”
M.I.N.D.S. And that means
what that includes is
actually capturing details
of the subject of the experiment,
the species, the strain, the sex
the methods used,
the protocols
the equipment,
and the parameters
used to perform
the experiment
the classification,
what is the data category
the data format,
the cell type
the brain location
where in the brain
in a standard Atlas
either in terms
of coordinates
or in terms of
just standardized
names for that
brain region
was this data captured,
who other contributors
and what are
their affiliations
and ideally identify those
contributors by something
like an Orchid, a standard
dentifier for authors
so they can get credit for
making their data available?
And then, importantly,
and URL
or a persistent identifier,
and this is something
like a DOY that allows
you to actually go online
and directly access
the raw data.
So that URL is the key part of
the Minimal Information for
Neuroscience Datasets.
So, in this session we
talked about how
neuroscience data
is very heterogenous
and some of the challenges
in organizing it
described to you
what meta data
is and how we can use meta
data to organize data sets
and I’ve also described
to you M.I.N.D.S.
it’s a proposed initial
standard for a minimal
meta data set for
neuroscience data
and we thing that’s really
essential to starting
to get the broader
community to consistently
annotate and organize their data.