Hello, my name is Samuel Kerrien
I'm the manager of
the Blue Brain Nexus Project
which is currently being
developed by the Blue Brain Project.
Today we're going to look
at the challenges faced
by neuroscience in data integration,
we're going to look at
various approaches to do
data integration.
Then we're going to have a look
at the Blue Brain Nexus :
a data platform,
and in that topic
we're going to look
at it's architecture
at how to do the main design,
at the management of ontologies
and how to re-use existing
and well defined domains.
Finally, we're going
to look at MINDS
and what it enables in
the context of data integration.
So first of all, I'll come back
to the issue with data integration
which is that in neuroscience there's
a really broad variety of data.
Not only have we got multiple
scales we want to capture
from sub cellular resolution,
to cellular, to tissue resolution,
and the whole brain, but also
within each of these scales
we have multiple
data modalities.
And so this leads to serious
challenges in integrating data
as you have to cope with
them all in a seamless manner.
So here we're going to discuss
various challenges
of integrating data
in neuroscience.
So like we said,
data is extremely varied.
Then we have data ranging
from very small data to data set
around Petabytes, which is
just by the shear size of it
difficult to handle.
The data, by it's nature
can be distributed in silos
whether it is within
the same organizations,
people having their own
packets of data,
all the way to data being
distributed through
different organizations,
and connecting them
together can be difficult.
There's an obvious
need for data provenance
and I'm not going to
elaborate too much
on these aspects right now,
we're going to look at it
in more detail later;
but essentially you
want to know where
data came from if
the data set was generated
from another specific one
that gives you a lot of useful
information to know why
this data set is and
that gives you a lot of useful
information to know why
this data set is and
assess it's quality.
Then you have the need to
discover similar related data
so obviously you bring your
own data into a platform
you are running your own science
and it is very useful to be able
to tap into what the rest of
the community has actually
brought into the platform in order
to enrich whatever data sets
you had at your disposal
and improve the science
you are currently running.
Finally, neuroscience has
very ambitious goals
and that does require a state of
the art data platform to support it.
So, just to give you a few examples,
the automatic reconstructions
or the reconstruction of neurons,
so here, on the right-hand side
we can see a slice of a mouse brain
that has been generated by
Wuhan University in China, and they
have reconstructed by hand
the morphology of neurons
which you see highlighted:
you have one here,
you have another yellow one,
you have the red one here,
and the green one, so four neurons
spanning the whole width
of the brain, and this task
is extremely time consuming,
thus very expensive.
And wielding tools that will allow
to automate this reconstruction
is extremely valuable.
Now that's a very
difficult task as well
and thus it is
a significant challenge.
And we have a few other examples,
such as electro-physiology
analysis, whole brain imaging,
and finally large scale simulations
validation, which is the heat of
what Blue Brain does.
So next we're going to have a brief
look at the various components
of what makes
a neuro-informatics platform,
and here I'm not going to
give you all the details that
Sean has already explained
in previous videos,
but I want ask to really focus
on the Knowledge Graph
and the search facilities that
the knowledge graph does enable.
So in the next few slides
we're really going to focus on
that part.
So what is the purpose
of the Knowledge Graph?
It is to represent and validate
and store scientific knowledge
and when I say validate,
it means when you bring
the information into
this knowledge graph
It is able to tell you if you have
indeed connected your elements
in the right order,
if you have provided
the right amount of meta data,
if mandatory information
has been indeed provided.
So I'm listing two things here:
This encompasses the entities of
knowledge you're trying to capture
with it's meta data,
but also with
raw data that is attached
to these entities.
You can think of raw data
as your data sets.
Also there's the concern of
provenance that links these
entities together as they are
derived from one and other.
Next, it allows you to search data
based on user defined criteria
and that can be either on
the entity's meta data
whether they are literal values
or ontology terms
and I'll be giving
an example of that later
but at the same time,
it can also be based on
provenance information,
so a user should be able to build
and formulate scientific questions,
submit a query to
the Knowledge Graph,
that both encompasses
meta data
and provenance information,
that gets an answer
to its question.
Finally you want to be able
to discover new data through
the main specific commonalities,
so by leveraging:
meta data is shared by
a number of these data sets
you want to be able to actually find
new things that you weren't
aware of originally
and again, we'll cover
more on that later
and give very concrete examples.
So I have been mentioning
provenance in the past few slides
and I think I would like to take
the time now to actually
tell you again what is provenance.
At a very simple level,
it is a way to tell where your
entities are coming from,
and one way to do that
for instance, is to use
the concept of activity.
So activity may consume or use
a number of entities,
an activity would generate a number,
one or many other entities.
And this activity is associated with
agents and these agents can be
people, you can imagine them like
people doing an experiment in
the lab and generating
a specific data set
it could be software, it has been
used in the process of running this
activity to generate
these entities
so on a very simple level
this is what provenance is
and it really enables you to
track where things came from
and how they have been
deriving into other things.
Now, why provenance?
It really does enable
you to do a lot of things.
Like I said earlier, it enables you
to track the original data
track how the data is being used
and we call that derivation.
Having this information at hand
allows you to asses the quality
of the data and
the trust in the data
you might be re-using for
your own use cases.
Reproducability of workflows
can be ensured as
if you capture all the necessary
information that allows
the generation of
the given data sets
you could just re-run the same
workflow with the same parameters
and reproduce these
exact same data sets,
quite easily.
Another use for provenance
is attribution, whether it is about
the data you're generating,
or algorithms you're creating
you can really find out who
has done the work
and which affiliations they
are associated with.