In the last parts of this presentation
I would like to talk more about
the minimum information,
about neuroscience dataset.
And to start with I'm just going
to repeat what MINDS,
a MIND compliant dataset
should include.
It should define the specimen
it has been generated from
and it should include the age
of the specimen,
it's sex, the species, the strain.
And again, you should already
be recognizing some of these elements:
I mean these 3, for instance.
We've already seen that
a vocabulary exists
to define these things.
The concept of an entity of classification
such as cell types or neuron.
The concept of brain location
whether you want to use
an ontological term to define
a logical area,
or even spatial coordinates
if you happen to have
this precise information.
You want to have the contributors
that enable the generation
of these datasets and their affiliation
so use can give credit to them.
You want to define the method
and parameters used,
generate a data, and the dates
they already were created on.
You want to describe
the data category
and the specific data format
you have used to save these data.
You want to describe
how to access data
so where is it stored,
and the format,
and finally, you want
the license information
so someone can inform itself
as to whether they can actually re-use
this information.
So, what are the benefits
of the MINDS compliant datasets?
So, first you have to see MINDS
as a very useful tool to create
a community consensus
as to how to describe
in the context of neuroscience
the properties of a dataset.
And some of these properties
are extremely useful
and we'll see why actually
in the next slides.
Next, that provides us consistency
in the process of integrating the data
into a platform, so if we really
enforce these MINDS compliants
we know that all datasets
will have specimen
and point us a brain region,
and people typically are very
focused on specimen
and very specific parts of the brain
that really enables them to find
other datasets that can really help
them moving forward in their research.
It gives power to the search facilities
by just having this consistency
in the type of information stored
and the vocabularies being used
to define them,
it gives another power
to search facilities.
And finally, it is with a medium
to find similar and related datasets,
this is in the next part
we're going to look at.
So, here, I have listed quite a few
examples of similarity and relatedness
examples that can be leveraged
from simply annotating your datasets
that are in the MINDS
recommendations.
So I'm just going to list them
and illustrate where appropriate.
You could find dataset
that come from the same species
but different strains, different
kinds of ruts, for instance.
You could also search for datasets
located in nearby brain regions.
You can look for the same brain
regions,
but in different species
or strain.
You can use a neuron
with a broader cell classification.
So, for instance, your neuron
may have been categorized
as the Martinotti cell, but now
you want to look at neurons
that are not only Martinotti cell,
but more generally inhibitory cells.
So, again, playing with a hierarchy
of your ontology,
this is something you can do.
You can look at all the data
category in the same brain region
because bringing different angles
to the data you're currently using
you might strengthen actually your
position in discovering something.
You could use the same data category
but in a different brain region.
For instance, you have
electrophysiology in the thalamus
and you want to get electrophysiology
datasets in a different brain region
and make a comparison between them:
What is different between
these two brain regions?
You could use the dataset
by the same lab or contributor,
or finally, another dataset generated
with the exact same protocol
or derived protocol.