I would like to talk about some
of the activities with text mining
and actually extracting values
for data integration
from the literature
One of the big challenges as we know
that knowledge and data there's been
a tremendous amount of it published
in neuroscience
over the last hundred years
But, we don't easily access that data
So, how do we make the knowledge
and data
from this huge archival past
of literature ?
how do we make it accessible,
to search it, to analyze it
or to integrate it, or to use it
for computational models?
So, most valuable knowledge lies
in an unstructured form
within scientific papers
you've got to read it
you've got to follow it
through the text
and actually find out
where does it say something useful?
Where is a useful parameter
to build my model?
And there is one new paper
each minute on PubMed
So there is a tremendous challenge
here
because there is no standardization
there is no centralization.
There is a tremendous flood of data
and knowledge that is coming out
but is also in the archival history
of neuroscience
and we have got to have some tools
to address that
to start accessing that
So, our goal with text mining
was to take an example
where we wanted to extract
metascale brain connectivity
we wanted to see
can we usefully find connectivity
statements from the literature ?
In order to accelerate
the literature review
rapidly summarize
the existing knowledge
and  provide a centralized repository
of connectivity statements
for neuroscientists or modelers
if they need to quickly find out
is this area connected to this area
they will have a large body
of literature
summarized from this text mining.
Because we don't really think
that we can reliably
get actual connectivity data
for the whole brain here
this is not
where we would just blindly take
the results of the text mining
and use it to build a model
But we use it as a way
of accelerating the process
of going through thousands
upon thousands of papers.
And so the first step in this process
is a process called
“named entity recognition”
and this is where you use
existing databases of words
and the type of word that they are
to parse through and identify specific
types of entities within a sentence
So, in the sentence
“the interstitial nucleus
of the posterior limb"
"of of the anterior commisure”
you can see that these words
are being recognized
as, well, different brain regions
for example,
nucleus of the posterior limb
of the anterior commisure
so it is recognizing overall
that is the name of a brain region
and then there are sub-regions
named within that.
And then, in the next phrase
it recognizes the IPAC
is an abbreviation for that,
and lies at the junction
of the striatopalladial system
so it recognizes
another brain region.
So, through this way, this process
of named entity recognition
you can start to parse out
the different types of entities
described in the sentence
So, to apply this,
we actually want to mine
for example, connectivity statements
where we are using the named entity
recognizers to find brain regions
to find statements of connectivity
and then to find the combination
of those two.
And here are a number of example
connectivity statements
that we parsed out
and specific formal description
of that statement.
And you can see, we have got
the nucleus accumbens
receives projections
from both substantia nigra
and ventral tegmental area
and the formal expression of that.
We do that for many different texts
and that provides a way of ultimately
identifying
specific statements of connectivity
brain region connection type
to another brain region.
And to do this, we use a BLUIMA
it is an open source text mining
system built of UIMA
which is coming
from IBM Watson's technologies
it is an open source project
We use three named entity recognizers
to identify and normalize
brain region names
We use three different extractors
to predict the connectivity
probability
of brain region co-occurrences
And then,
we use the connectivity results
we provide it through a user interface
to allow feedback from a user
to validate. Is this actually a useful
connectivity statement, or not?
And we are using as data sources
PubMed abstracts
full text articles
from open source journals.
And so, we have got named entity
recognizers for the Allen Brain Atlas
from the Brain Architecture
Management System
and from our own brain
named entity recognizer.
So, we ran this system
this set of named entity recognizers
and connectivity statement extractors
on 13.2 million PubMed abstracts
and 630,000 full text publications
related to neuroscience
In that, we found over 4 million
brain region mentions
from the Allen Brain Atlas
and 7 million from the Brain
Architecture Management System
Over 100,000 of those statements
and 160,000 from BAMS
were potential brain region
connections
And when we checked that
we found that there was precision
of about 78%
against actual experimentally
measured NVIVO connectivity data
from the Allen Brain Atlas
And so we actually characterize
the connectivity matrix
and along the sides here
you see the different brain regions
connected to, along the top,
the brain regions again
So, you see which regions
are connected
and the grey shows
the connectivity statement
and we compare on the left
one from the Allen Brain
Connectivity Atlas
to the right, to the connectivities
discovered by our text mining system
So, we see that there is actually
a decent structural similarity
between these two
but importantly, it shows
that this is viable way
of getting connectivity statements
as a rapid way of reviewing
the literature
and we can compare that
to existing data
and data captured from real animals.
As well as use it as a way
to quickly identify for a modeler
the details of specific literature
that makes a statement
about connectivity
from one brain region to another.
Another approach is to actually
annotate the literature
for specific parameters needed
in building models
And so when a modeler is building
a model neuron or a model synapse,
you need things like resting
numbering potentials
or synaptic conductances, or protein
concentrations from the literature.
And we want to enable the scientist
to go into the paper
and make a specific annotation
kind of as though you're taking notes
on a paper, highlight it
and link that highlighted element
within the paper
to a specific machine
readable description of the parameter
and how that needs to be transformed
to be integrated into a model
And so, this is Neuro Curator
this is a tool developed
by Christian O'Reilly
to annotate these model parameters
from the literature
and also track when we use
the parameters in a model:
where did those parameters come
from in the literature?
So, that we can always track
the source document
the specific statement
any transformation that happened
to that parameter
in order to be incorporated
So, this has a graphical
user interface
for keeping track of the corpus
of literature
and all of the annotations
and the transformations performed
And we've extracted large numbers
of parameters here
mostly of 30 parameter types
but this is an ongoing process
we're continuing to do this
to support the thalamal
and cortical modeling
and this gives some examples
of the types of values extracted
Now, another part of the process
a meta-modeler actually lets you tag
in your source code for your model
which parameters you want to insert
from the curator annotation database
And this takes care of passing
into the source code.
So you make a reference
and then it basically replaces
that reference
with the actual parameter
from the literature
keeping track of which paper
was it actually coming from
But this is an important way
of keeping the link
between the literature, the citation
and the model
And then, since we are annotating
as we annotate each
of those parameters
using controlled vocabulary
and using ontologies
in particular, using ontologies
of brain regions
that allows us to link
in specific statements
for example, on cell density
into a brain atlas
So, because we're using
the same names as in the brain atlas
we can annotate
that there are 150.3 relay cells
or 150,000 relay cells
per cubic millimeter
within the dorsal thalamus
for example
and use that information to actually
then parameterize the model
which we provide
through a VoxelBrain API
which allows you
to then query these properties.
Again, linked back to literature
but as actual data
from the atlas to build the models
This is an important way
of extracting data from the literature
linking it into atlases
and then using that
to actually parameterize models
both in terms of building
individual cell models
but also building models
of brain regions
So, in this session you've learned
about some approaches to text mining
for neuroscience data
extracting data from the literature
and a tool Neuro Curator
for annotating literature
for modeling parameters
As well as integrating data
with an atlas via ontologies