I’ll now be talking to you
about a core piece
of the neuroinformatics
platform
which is the knowledge
graph.
And the knowledge
graph is really built
at it’s core on
a provenance data model
And what is provenance?
Why is that important?
So, provenance is really
meta data about the origin
and the transformation
of the data.
Where did the data
come from
and what has happened
to it all along
the way as you
cleaned it up,
You removed artifacts,
you normalized it
you maybe transformed
it to a specific
set of units and you
did an analysis.
That’s provenance.
Keeping track of all those
things you did to the data.
It also can be used to keep
track of who produced
the data and who performed
those transformations.
So, is the data
actually derived?
is it a derivation,
is it some transformation
of a previous data set?
Well, which data set
is it coming from?
Where is the raw
data that led to it?
And what of those
specific processes
or analyses,
or transformations
that were used to
produce the data?
And specifically
keeping track of that.
Which software
and version
for example,
were used?
And all of this
is important
because it enables
reproducibility.
It supports it,
it doesn’t guarantee it
but it certainly
is an important
part of the process of making
science reproducible.
Documenting the steps
involved in the data production.
Being transparent,
providing a clear trail
of the data sources
involved in an analysis.
Helping to improve trust
in an analysis and
in the data it self
by giving a clear audit
of the origins of the data.
Also, to help discover things,
like methods and software
that would be useful to
applying to similar data sets.
Also, finding related
data sets.
And finally,
in providing attribution
And this is really important
in ultimately building up
a global culture of data
sharing in neuro science
Making sure that credit is
given to all of those involved.
Not just in producing data,
but to all of those who
produced the analysis and
who produced the software
to perform the analysis.
All of the participants in
producing a final data set
or figure can be captured
in the data provenance.
So, W3C, the World Wide
Web Consortium
has actually developed
a provenance standard
and this is what we built
the knowledge graph off of.
And this really has
a number of key properties.
But first of all,
there is the entity
which would be for
example, a data set.
But, where was
it coming from?
Is it derived
from something?
How was it produced?
Which activity actually
produced it and who
or what software
actually generated it?
So, the agent is
the who or the what
the activity is the how
and the entity
So, the agent is
the who or the what
the activity is the how
and the entity
is the data itself what
was actually produced.
And this is the pattern
that then you extend
these to be specific
to different
experimental conditions
and different types of context
to fully provide
characterization
of the data
and its provenance.
One example of a W3C Prov.
Data Model
was developed in
the INCF task force
for neuroimaging
data sharing
and they developed
the neuroimaging data model.
And this was the data
model that really could
keep track of all of the details,
from acquisition details
describing the raw data,
the analysis
the workflows applied
to derived data
and ultimately to
the publications.
And the idea is to support
access and search
of imaging data that’s
been annotated with
the neuroimaging
data model through
common API and databases.
This is something
that’s been developed
it’s being integrated
into many
neuroimaging tools
and we’d like to see
that become
commonly used.
The knowledge graph
is really something
also build on the W3C
provenance standard.
So, it can integrate,
for example
the neuroimaging
data model
because it is based
on the same
underlying
metadata model.
But it is provenance based,
semantic metadata catalog.
It gives really a way to keep
track of neuroscience data,
models and literature.
It’s at the heart
of the human
brain project
neuroinformatics
platform, as well
as Blue Brain's
processes for
keeping track
of data for data
driven modeling.
It’s W3C provenance
standard compliant
and it really provides a way
to track, for example
the specimen,
the samples of specimen
in terms of potential
brain slices,
the specific
experimental protocols
and the extracted data
as well as the models
built from that data.
So, by building up
a graph that captures
all of those relationships
as well as the semantic
annotations
and we’ll get to
the ontologies in
another session
But, talking
about consistently
labeling the specimen
with controlled vocabulary
and making it possible
to search through
what was the software,
who were the people
and what were
the techniques
used to produce
this data.
It provides a very rich
annotation for data
and finding, for example,
related data sets
such as an individual
cell morphology
Was it from a slice,
from which there is
also electrophysiological
data?
And you can find those
links between them.
And that’s very
important for supporting
the modeling process.
So, in this session,
you’ve learned about
the use of provenance
information and its importance.
I’ve talked about the W3C
provenance standard
and described to you
the knowledge graph
which is really this
provenance based semantic
metadata catalog necessary
for searching data
but also finding key
relationships between
the data and
the data producers.