So, in the next couple of slides,
we are going to have a look
at the various approaches
we can use to do data integration
into a KnowledgeGraph.
Here, I am going to present
a first approach
which I called
"Fixed Data Model".
In this approach,
we have designed a model
with entities and provenance
that is aimed at encompassing
any used cases we meet
in the field of neuroscience.
I'm going to illustrate a little bit
its structure now
First, we have a specimen,
and the specimen is really
the subject of which we study the brain,
and so that specimen can be derived
into a number of samples,
which can derive from each other.
So, for instance, a sample can be
a specific slice of that brain
into which we are going to study
a number of neurons.
So, if I were to do this use-case,
I would have a specimen,
then I would have
a slice,
and I would have
right next to it
a neuron.
Both of which, slice and neuron
would be of type sample,
I would just have to have a property
in the sample that describes
that this is actually a slice,
and this other one
is a neuron.
Now, let's say I'm in a lab,
and I want to do
and electrophysiology recording
of this specific neuron,
I can then
design an activity
with some protocol
that is going to describe
how this experiment is being run.
And that experiment is going to generate
a dataset.
Itself, it will have a specific category
that can be for instance
"electrophysiology recording".
And this is really the entity
and the metadata describing the dataset,
and we have also
the raw data for this dataset,
as in the files that have been generated
on your local hard drive
when you did your recording.
And that is really
what came out of it.
Another example here could have been
a morphology reconstruction.
So, the scientist can,
for instance,
study the data
that came out
of this experiment,
and do further annotation,
or classification
of this neuron here.
And for instance, define that
this is a fast spiking cell,
by studying the directory response
of this specific neuron
so the scientist can make claims,
and something I haven't mentioned
here,
the activity obviously has a number
of agents,
whether it is a scientist
who run the experiment
or the software that was used to acquire
the directory physiology recording.
So, while this approach can work,
if you are fine dealing
with a very generic data model,
and do not want to do very deep
data integration,
that method can work.
But, you have to bear in mind
that you have to fit a very specific domain
into a very generic formalism,
and that has limitation.
On top of that,
you have very strong operational constraint,
with HBP-PROV, which is the format
I have shown earlier.
Like I said, you can have
loss of details,
so just to give you an example:
if you wanted to record both
electric activity of neurons
but also morphological reconstruction
of that same neuron,
these two kinds
of dataset have very
specific attributes
that differentiates them.
For instance,
an electrophysiology recording
uses what we call
a stimuli
which is the kind of stimulation
we apply to the neuron
in order to observe its response.
Which is something
a morphology reconstruction does not have.
And so, you can not have these attributes
on the dataset per sur,
because it only fits
some of these subclasses of dataset.
So you will not store
this information there.
Again, you have to compromise
on some of these details,
and so this approach in that sense
is not always the best.
As the format is defined, you have to submit
the complete data model in one go,
and so this can be also
a constraint
for the person actually submitting
data to the data platform
in a sense that
today,
you're taking care of the specimen
you're going to work on,
and you could already potentially
enter this information in the platform.
And when you start preparing
the slice
of the brain of your subject,
you could then, at this stage,
enter the information into a platform.
With this model,
you cannot do that
you have to capture
the full provenance of everything you have done,
and submit it in one go,
which has again limitations.
Lastly, the domain as it is represented
in this data model
is a set in stone and
the platform that handles it
has a very good understanding
of this model.
And so if you wanted to evolve this model,
you would have to change a lot of code
in the platform.
And here I'm talking more about
the "behind the scene" of the data platform.
You have people developing it,
maintaining it,
and any evolution of this format
is very time-consuming,
and so the scientist
is becoming very dependent
of the technical people
working on the platform.
And that can slow down
progress of science.