I will be talking in this session
about ontologies.
So, what are ontologies
and why are they useful
for neuroscience?
Well, ontology actually comes
from two Greek words
“onto” for existence
or being real
and “logia” for science
or study.
So, ontology is really
the science of what
exists or is real.
So, an ontology is actually
a formal representation
of knowledge
about a specific set
of entities or concepts.
That is how we use it
in Computer science
it is much more of a schema,
it is a controlled vocabulary.
In fact, ontologies can provide
several different useful tools
for organizing data
and expressing knowledge.
For one, it is providing
a controlled vocabulary
for referring to
a set of specific
entities or concepts
it also contains the relationships
between these entities
and it defines
specific properties
of these entities
as well, it can.
And those are
important things
in how do we structure
and express concepts
their properties,
and their relationships.
That is really what
an ontology is for.
So, and ontology for
a brain region
it is actually quite important
that it provides
a 3D boundary but
linked to a specific name
and the relationship to
any sub-structures
or any parent structure,
so the ontology used
for the Allen Brain
Institute Atlas started
from the Swanson
ontology
and they really used this
to capture, for example
the structures
within the cortex
the sub-structures,
and the relationship of,
for example,
the cortex to the diencephalon.
So, it is using both data
structures for describing
the 3D boundary but also
within the standard space
linking these regions to
a standard name
and then abbreviation.
For the data set used in
the Blue Brain project
used for the initial
Somatosensory cortex model.
There is a large
variety of data
from many
different aspects
including
electrophysiological data
per-synaptic responses,
gene expression
morphological data,
and you have got to organize
that by actually annotating
the structure with
structured ontologies
in order to understand
how do you want to
build a model of these
what are the key entities,
what are their relationships
and what are their properties
that you’re modeling.
So, we had to develop
ontologies
for neuron morphologies
and we identified fifty-five
morphological types.
Here, this picture shows
the different types
of neurons on the left,
you see the interneurons
the inhibitory interneurons,
and on the right
are the excitatory
parameter cells
and stellate cells,
and each one has a name.
Currently you see,
at the top of the column
the abbreviations,
but for example
you have got a layer one
neurogliaform cell
so in layer one
the NGC cell is listed
the layer five
Martinotti cell.
Layer five thick tough
parameter cell type one
and these names are
used to characterize
the specific properties of
neuron morphologies
and that is useful
for organizing
and being consistent
with how you refer
to different types of neurons
within this particular brain region.
The Blue Brain Ontologies
for Electrical Types
actually is based on
the Berthier classification
and that means defining
how does the cell fire initially
so the initial firing type,
there is a burst
a continuous,
or a delay
and you can see this
in the example traces
where maybe initially there is
a short high frequency burst
and other cells start
off immediately
firing without a burst
or there is maybe
a delay in starting
the firing response from
the current injection.
Similarly, for the sustained
firing tether a different type
some cells adapt whether their
inter-spike interval decreases
some are non-adapting
where their
inter-spike interval
remains constant
some are fast spiking,
so they have deeper
after hyper-polarization and
they fire in higher frequencies
and some are
irregular spiking
where their
inter-spike interval
may be quite variable.
And so out of those
for the cells in
the somatosensory cortex
haindling region
we have identified
eleven electrical types
and those are the combinations
of initial firing type
and sustained firing type.
That forms the ontology for
electrical types in Blue Brain.
And here is a table
from the 2015.
cell paper authored
by Markam et. al.
which relates this
inter-neuron classes
to other cell properties
and cell types
described in the literature,
and for example
there are many
different ways
to talk about a cell type
many different
dimensions along
which you can
characterize
Those include,
for example
proteins that are
expressed in the cell
so molecular markers,
electrical types
as we have seen from
the electrical properties
the morphological properties,
the morphological shapes
but there are many others,
including the projections target
where do these cells
target within the brain
or which types of cells
do they receive from.
There are many possible ways,
but we choose specifically
to characterize cells based
on their morphology
and electro-physiology.
Now that does
have a relationship
to specific
molecular markers
and that is very useful
for interfacing
with very
described properties
and also, we use gene
expression information
to identify which types
of ion channels
are present within
a particular cell type.
And so the morpho-electric
cell type ontology
actually combines which
of the morphology types
the M types, combine
with the electrical type
so this is really combining
those two ontologies
that we talked about earlier,
to create a new one
where there are 207
morpho-electric
types of cells.
And we have data on
how many of those occur
how many of each of those
possibilities happen.
Now all combinations
of all morphologies
and all electrical
types do not occur.
So it is just the common
subset, which is 207.
The connections between
these cells are actually
defined by different
types of synapses
and there are specific
properties that govern
these synapses
and we have got
inhibitory synapses
and excitatory and
these are ignite
by different
neuro transmitters.
They also occur
with specific kinetics
which are facilitating,
depressing, or pseudo-linear
between specific types
of pre-synaptic cells
and post-synaptic cell,
and those pre-synaptic types
are morpho-electric types.
So, we have got a map of
synapse types
defined according
So, we have got a map of
synapse types
defined according
to pre-synaptic
morpho-electric class
of cell and the post-synaptic
and then identified by
the specific kinetics
of that synapse,
either facilitating
depressing,
pseudo-linear
inhibitory,
or excitatory
and those are
very key to
the definition of this
synapse ontology.
Finally, in defining
the micro circuits
there is a number of
specific properties
that we have defined
to describe
a somatosensory
cortex micro-circuit
and we see that in general
these same properties can
be used to describe
micro-circuits
throughout the brain.
First of all, you have got to have
a volume boundary
You need to know the minimal
boundary sufficient
to create a complete micro-circuit,
and in this case
we used the saturation of
the dendritic density
to define that.
You have got to
know the cell types
that I have described earlier
in terms of
morphological types
and the electro-physiological
types
and their combinations
to make
morpho-electric types,
the total cell count
and then the distribution,
where of the ME types
where of these
Morpho-electric cells
Morpho-electric types of cells.
Where are they distributed,
in which density
in which distribution
throughout that volume?
And then the synapse
type maps
so you’re combining a number
of ontologies into
the definition of
the micro-circuit.
And then, finally,
a type specific bouton density
is actually critical to making
a functional conversion
to the number
of synapse
to the actually
number of synapses.
So, in this session
you have learned
about what is an ontology
how are ontologies used in
the data driven modeling
and some examples
of ontologies
in the Blue Brain project.