So, in this slide we're going
to look deeper into ontologies.
So, Sean has already given you
basic information
about what ontologies are
and we will not expand on this.
What I'm really interested
in doing here is to show you
for the domain of neuroscience
which ontologies we have decided
to integrate in our Blue Brain Nexus
platform.
So, a lot of the ontologies we have
integrated have been either taken
from the Neuroscience Information
Framework co-developed with them.
The goal of NIF is to define
these concepts
for them in neuroscience and share
them so the community can re-use them
and have a commun agreement to define
neuroscientific concepts.
They have defined
the NIF Standard Ontologies
which integrate a number
of existing ontologies
such as Uberon, for instance
to define brain regions
in manner that is agnostic
of which specimen
or species they come from.
Gabi for instance for description
of small molecules,
the gene ontology or Obi
and quite a few others.
Now in this part, here under,
what I would like to illustrate
is a number of ontologies
we have decided to use
in the Brain Nexus platform
for the domain of neuroscience.
So, for instance, around
the specimens
we have the definition of species
and strain,
so this is really helping in defining
what kind of animal subject
that was, so these two we haven't
created ourselves:
this is part of the NSBI taxonomy.
And so it is, when dealing
with ontologies, really important
to do enough research to find
out : are there any vocabularies
already existing in the community
so that we can just leverage them.
It really would be a waste of time
first to reinvent what is already
working and well accepted
by the community,
but is also a strong advantage
in using and re-using these
these already defined vocabularies.
And very simply if someone
describes rats
with a very specific concept
and you have also defined
rats with again that same concept
so then even though you're storing
your data in different places
they become compatible:
You know that what you call a rat
is also what they call a rat.
And so, if, for instance,
in your lab you deal with
electrophysiology only,
and that other person deals only
with morphology, the data,
at least, is compatible
at the level of the species
and it is very clear to deduce
from the use of the vocabulary
you have chosen.
And then next one will just be...
Yeah, a vocabulary to define the sex
of the specimen-male, female.
Then we have a number of ontologies
for the description of datasets,
so we have the category, so what
kind of dataset is it,
is it an electrophysiology, morphology,
image, imagery data?
This specific data format
that is used to serialize
this data, the raw data
when you save it on your disc
there's a concrete format
that you have chosen
and so there's a way to metadata
to describe this.
This becomes very important
if you look for electrophysiology
in a very specific format because
you have a work that requires it
you can then filter that though
in a platform and only get those
that match and will be compatible
with what you're trying to achieve.
Next, we have a license ontology
which allows us to define
who can re-use the data
you're publishing into the platform.
So, do not underestimate this one.
If you decide that your data cannot
be re-used for commercial purpose
you can actually define it there.
Finally, we have the storage
of the dataset
and this is really a way to describe
where have you stored your data.
So it can be through the platform
in which case you don't really need
to know where it's configured,
you just have to know that the people
managing the platform have
configured it in a way that the data
is going to be backed up and is safe.
But if you were to store the data
on a next storage
to the platform, here we have
an ontology to actually allow you
to describe this, so you can easily
define the data.
For instance, it is store in a cloud
in Amazon and you can define that.
Then we have the concept
of sample classification
which is really important to us,
because from a lot of the datasets
we are integrating
scientists take the time to make
statements on the entities
that we integrate, neurons
for instance,
and it will give them electric types,
morphology types.
And so we have the design ontology
that allows that description.
Finally, another way to classify
them is to define what kind
of neurotransmitters, some entities
are also as another kind of ontology,
but we won't be getting
to the details of it here.
A lot of the data we integrate
really makes sense when
we anchor it in specific
brain spaces.
So, we have a number of existing
brain atlases that are references
for specific species whether
it is Allen mouse CCFv3
or Waxholm for the rats.
We have an ontology that defines
the logical reference
for these spaces and this can
be annotated on the level
of a dataset, for instance.
More detailed in that concept
is the parcellation schemes,
so here we enter still within
the concept of anchoring data
into an atlas,
now we want to actually talk about
in which specific region
of an atlas your dataset
is to be anchored.
And so, different atlas spaces
come with parcellation schemes
where anatomists have just looked
at these spaced and defined
the subvolumes of this space
that corresponds to specific
brain regions or brain parcels.
And so we have three here,
which are put as examples,
we have actually quite a few others
and these define again
vocabulary to describe
these brain regions,
but they are really specific
to that very specific atlas space.
Finally, we have some ontologies
that are really linked
more to the provenance concepts
that really allows to then reach it.
So, for instance, we have the type
of the activity run,
whether these experimental type
run in a lab
or a computational task,
you know, simply run
in a computer or a classification
activity, so you have these
very short vocabularies that really
enable you to describe
the activity you want to define
and later on filter
through the semantic searches.
Then we have measurement methods
so another ontology to describe
the kind of message you've applied
to generate new entities.
And finally, the role of the agents
involved in a given activity:
whether it was the principal
investigator of a project
or researcher doing the actual
experiments in the lab.
So, this is not fully exorstive
but it is a set of ontologies we use
to annotate our data in the context
of neuroscience.
So here, just to tie
it altogether and show you
that we have a central place
where you can actually introspect
all these ontologies, we have
what we call the Ontology Viewer.
So, if you open this web application
you can list all the ontologies
currently available and integrated
into the platform.
And so here we have regrouped
them by logical topics,
so we have a number of parcellation
schemes
and you can see, if I take
the Waxholm space
you can look into white matter
and...
so here you can see there is video
hierarchy of this brain region
and relation is that that region is further
defined by these three other subregions.
And you can through here really
introspect every ontologies
we have done, so if you want
to have a look at electrophysiology
it has a parent term that
is physiologycal data.
And here you have the specific
dataset category
that allows you to define all, this
dataset is electrophysiology recording
The nice thing you can do
with that is that if you have used
this vocabulary
to describe your data
and you're interested in not only
electrophysiology, but also, say,
functional imaging, you could
leverage to hierarchy
of this ontology by, for instance,
using the term Physiologycal Data
and the system is intelligent
enough to know that's
because you have annotated
with electrophysiology
it knows that electrophysiology
is a subtype of Physiologycal Data
and so it will pull back
from the system
all electrophysiology as well as
function imaging,
effective connectivity
and functional connectivity.
So you can really leverage the power
of ontologies and more abstract
concepts to make interesting
scientific questions.