So, at this stage I would like
to introduce Blue Brain Nexus
which is a platform
we are developing now
within the Blue Brain project.
And in a few statements I would like
to tell you what the Brain Nexus is.
It is a data repository, you can
store in it all your data
and manage it from within
the platform.
It is a metadata catalogue
in a sense that you can create
your entities with the very specific
metadata attributes.
And you can manage all these
entities in the platform,
and revise them, update them
without loosing any
of the information
and have full traceability
of who did what on these entities
so you can manage all the metadata.
It does treat provenance
as a first class citizen.
That means, when you install
the platform in your institution,
like we're doing in the brain,
problems is already ready.
So it is a set of entities
like you're going to define your own
entities for your own domain.
But there're already preinstalls
and well understood by the platform
so you can leverage them
from the beginning.
And important thing even so
this presentation
is about neuroscience,
Blue Brain Nexus itself
is agnostic of any domain,
it is not written to be specific
to neuroscience, you could design
any other scientific domain
or industrial domain on it.
So, the point is you have to create
your own domain.
Reuse existing domain and bring
them into your platform
to start collecting your own
metadata and data.
It has a deep understanding
of ontologies and it does support
them inherently,
so you can bring your own
ontologies and vocabularies
into the platform.
It is also semantic search engine
that allows you to
once you have its metadata
progress information,
leverage this information
to ask relevant scientific questions.
It is secure for any
whether scientific or industrial
purposes you want to be sure
that both your data and your metadata
is not being leaked to the wells
and when you enter information
and you require
that this is only visible by me
the platform enforces these rules
and keeps it private.
Now, when you're ready to share
your data with your group
or the rest of the world,
you can say so and the platform
will just reflect these requests
and share the data appropriately.
Finally, it is built to handle
very large amount of data
and metadata and have a highly
concurrent usage.
So, it is built to be a production
system that you can depend on
to build your science.
So, in these slides I will give you
more concrete information
about how you would use the Brain
Nexus to deal with your own domain.
So, like I've said it comes
with provenance,
already present in a platform
and we haven't really reinvented
provenance, this is a well-defined,
well understood concept.
And W3C has already defined
a standard for this called W3C-Prov.
So, very naturally, we have
imported these concepts
into the platform and they
are supported natively.
So, this is what I'm showing here.
So, on the right hand side I have
the diagram that illustrate for you
what you can do with a platform.
So, the lower part here is what
I call the generic part
of the platform.
So, provenance comes already
with it preinstalled
so we don't have to worry about it.
And as parts of the provenance
there's a concept
of a provenance entity
which is completely domain agnostic.
It is just something that can be used
as an item you can derive from.
And so at this stage what is left
for the user to do is to define
your own domain and extend
the concept of provenance entity.
So, this is what I'm showing here,
you have
I'm not going to take yet
very concrete domain,
but let's say your domain is made
of four types of entities,
A, B, C and D.
These entities can extend through
these links.
The concept of a provenance entity
and by doing so
you start being able to use them
in any provenance chain.
So, the first step is to define
your own provenance entities
and there's a formal way to do that
through schemas
and this is many more
of the technical details
I will not really dive too deep
into.
But these formats you have to use
to describe simply
how your entities called
and the properties
you wish to set on it
and the constrains
you want to define on this entity.
Once you have defined it,
so you have your file of this project
you will have to register it
into the platform.
And there's just a way to tell
the platform:
here's my entity, it extends
the provenance entity concepts
and here's its name
and its definition, please ingest it.
And give me an API
to interface with it.
And the important thing here
is by doing so
the platform dynamically
makes available this new entity
to anyone who's allowed to use it.
And you haven't had to write
a single line of code.
So, you're able to define parts
of your domain
push them into the platform
and start operating on it right away.
So, the platform does support
schema and metadata versioning
so obviously you define
your domain today
but you may have forgotten something,
or new use case arrives
and you need to add another couple
of properties into your entity
no problem with that, you can just
take your schema as it were
add the necessary information
you want to put in it.
Save it again and you will get
a new version of this schema
that can then be used
into the platform.
Same goes for the metadata.
So, once you have defined your schema,
you can start creating instances
of this entity, so the schema
is really the definition, the shape
of this entity.
But the instances of this entity
are really the real data.
And with real value for
the attributes
and so you can save them
into the platform.
But again there you may have
say, made a mistake,
or you didn't have the full
info at the time you created it
so you may want to get back to it
and make an edit and save it again.
So, again, the platform fully
supports this and you can trace
who has done exactly what
and look at the full history
of both schemas
and provenance entity instances.
It does support file upload
and downloads with security in mind.
And finally, once you have into it
define your schema
fed the platform with the instances
of these entities
for the metadata,
you can start brand new
semantic queries
that integrate both the metadata
and the provenance stored in a graph.
So, the goal really for us
is to give the power back
to our users.
So the platform does allow
the scientist to really take care
of defining their domain.
It's not a fact that they will do it
all by themselves
we are going to guide them
and help them defining it
and get though some of the technical
hurdles of doing so.
And so we feel that by allowing
the scientist to take control back
of the domain they care about
and they also the most knowledgeable
about this domain, we can each do
what we're best at.
The scientist about the domain
and the software engineers
at building systems that will serve
the purpose of science.
So, that's really the ultimate goal
of the Brain Nexus.