Next, I will take you
through the steps of creating
your own domain.
Here, I'm still going to stay
in the realm of neuroscience
but, typically, the way this happens
is that scientists come to us
and just describes their
needs with the platform
and that, altogether, allows us
to define a specific entity.
Here, I've taken
the example of a neuron
and through the discussion with
the scientists we have identified
that it needs to have a name,
it needs to have a morphology type
and an electrical type,
each of which are going
to be based on specific ontologies
that already predefine
these morphology types
and electrical types.
And so, once this has been written,
typically by a knowledge engineer
in the Blue Brain Nexus project,
then this can be pushed into
the platform registers so
people can start using it.
The next step is now I have
two scientists that both are
working on their
own favorite neurons
and they have done experiments,
and they have identified
that in the top part here,
that neuron is a pyramidal cell
it is also a stuttering cell.
You can then, either through
a private interface
or through a ware application,
enter this information
push it into the platform,
other scientists can
do the same thing,
and should they set the ACL,
the Access Control Lists correctly
on their own respective
entities and share it, say
with people from their group,
and let's assume that these
three people are
working in the same group
then that person can then
request from the platform:
"Show me all neurons"
and you're getting
the two entities back
that these two
scientists have defined.
So, it is a simplistic example,
but all of that, we have been able
to do without having
to modify the platform
without writing code,
and just designing new things
declaring things into the platform,
and automatically people can
start using it and getting value
out of it, and we feel amazing.
So, we've just seen
an example on how to
define your own domain.
Now, many domains have already
been defined by other communities.
I just want to take a few minutes
to describe a few existing domains
that you might want
to consider re-using.
Here, this is probably
the most used vocabulary
on the internet today
in the age of Facebook and LinkedIn.
It is called FOAF,
or Friend of a Friend
and it simply describes a person
and their social network.
It's a very simple concept,
but FOAF has defined
a very specific vocabulary
that allows you to define
someone or a piece of software.
So for instance here,
we can define the name of a person
their title, you can have
images that depict that person
and you can have a family name,
a given name
here, quite an important piece of
vocabulary is the other people
that that person knows
so this is how you start
describing your social network
and connecting that
person to other people.
And I will not read all
these attributes
but there's a number of others
you can potentially be using
whether that person has
a chatline from Jabber
so you can connect with them,
or that person works for
a very specific organization
so potentially in
the Blue Brain Nexus
you can take this vocabulary,
select the properties
that are interesting to you
and register the concept
of an agent or a person,
leveraging this vocabulary
making very clear that it
comes from the FOAF
and just start using it.
So the previous example
was really outside of
the neuroscience field
and here for the sake of
illustrating neuroscience
I want to take another domain
that really is in
the realm of neuroscience
and so NIDM is one of such
domains that deal with
the neuroimaging data model.
And I'm really not planning to
get into the deep details
of how this is described,
but we can see here that
the whole community
has come together to define
a very specific kind of workflow.
So it covers the acquisition
of imagery data
it caters for the representation
of the raw data that
has been acquired
the description of specific
analysis and workflows,
it allows you to represent derived
data from what you have acquired
and to do so it leverages
the W3C Prov
just like we do in
the Blue Brain Nexus.
You can also capture
the publications that have been
created from whatever workflow's
derived data you have created
and as well as the distribution
and sharing of the queries
via a common API.
This is more of a platform,
I guess, of their own
but as the specific data model,
here all of these could be leveraged
in the Blue Brain Nexus by just
importing this very specific domain
and declaring it as within the name
space of NIDM and just re-use it.
A community, like I said,
has already spent time
defining these carefully,
and by leveraging it
you render also the data
you push into the platform
and make it compatible with data
sitting on potentially
other data repositories
which is a very powerful
way to combine data.
Here we have a very brief overview
of the NIDM domain representation,
and here they are leveraging
the visual representation
of the W3FC Prov.
And so you can see
just the main elements
which are the project on which
you're working the specific study
and the acquisition of the data.
And here again, they have emphasized
that they are using
the following provenance elements
and you find again that you
should be familiar with it
they consist of agents of activity,
of entity, and attributes.
So, again, a really powerful way
to leverage existing domains
and vocabularies and bring them
into your Blue Brain Nexus instance.