Here we're going to have a look
at the overall architecture
of this platform,
and we are going to get into
a great amount of details,
but just so that you know
what is part of this platform
what part is generic and can be applied
to any domain, and what part
is maybe more specific
to neuro science.
The top part is really
the generic part, here.
And we have a number of
application here on the left.
We have our Search Clients
which will allow you to
once you've entered
the data into the platform
browse and navigate
the provenance of
the entities that you have entered,
and look at all the details
view the data set,
download data and
really explore everything
you have put into the platform.
We have the Provenance Viewer,
a graphical application that allows
you to really navigate this
provenance graph
and discover new things,
introspect parts of it.
We have an Ontology Viewer,
like I said ontologies are really
a core concept of
our semantic engine
and we have this application
that lists all the ontologies that
have been integrated
into our platforms
we have a central place to go,
review them, and check,
find specific information
that you want to use
maybe in one
of your processes.
We have a Provenance Editor,
which is an application
which allows you to edit specific
entities, make revisions...
While the platform have an API
to interface with where data is stored,
not everybody is a programmer
and we feel that there's a need
for a user-friendly simple way
to bring more information
into the platform, and so this is
the place where you want to do it.
And finally, this is still
to come in the platform:
a Domain Editor that would
allow here again a user-friendly
way to design your domain,
create your entities
define the properties, and put this
information into the platform
make it available so
people can start collecting
this kind of data.
At the very bottom here,
we have the Atlas viewer
and this is really a neuro science
specific application
leveraging the platform so
domain specific applications
can be developed
on top of this platform.
This one in particular allows you
to introspect a 3D brain volume
and look at specific annotations
of this brain volume
and so, maybe I will
demonstrate that.
Here for instance,
I will load
Allan mouse data sets.
Now we're going to look at
the corronal orientation of this
specific data set and we can zoom
into the brain, we could look
at different slices of it
on the left hand side of it
you can see that this one's
generated by the Allan
institute for Brain Science
you can have the information
about the specific specimen
it was a mouse,
it was 56 days post-natal,
you can see the distribution
of the data set,
the specific protocol
that allows generating this
this data sets, and finally
you can draw more information
on top of this image to highlight
the specific brain region we are
currently here highlighting.
That's an example of
the application that is really
domain specific.
Now we're going to focus
on the right hand side
of this architecture,
and the first thing that I want to
to describe is this, so called,
Rest API, and this is really
what people who are able to write
programs whether it's in python,
in java, in go, these people are
able to interface with the platform
through computer programs
and can very easily automate tasks
whether it is to push
data into the platform
or to run searches
to execute workflows
all of this can be
done using the Rest API
which again I want to stress it
is programming language agnostic
and today is a very common way
to access computer systems.
Behind this Rest API, which is
something you cannot interface with
directly,
everything has to be done
through the front of the rest API,
we have other services
that will allow you to do your
domain definition,
so in which you find
the concept of Provenance,
like I said, it is already provided
with the platform and
you will bring in your
your own Entity schemas,
so that's how you register
new entities into the platform.
The Knowledge Graph, of course
has the concept of ontologies
the entities you have entered
that themselves are defined
on the Entity schemas and
the raw data you want to attach
to some of the entities.
Like I said earlier,
security is (INAUDIBLE)
and so we have these
two services here
and ACL service, which stands
for Access Control Lists
and this is really the mechanism
to tell the platform that
the specific entities
is only visible to me
or only visible to my research group
or can be viewed by anyone on
the internet, so that can be at
the level of the meta data
but also at the level
of the raw data.
And these ACLs are intricately
linked to the identity service
which is really, well,
imagine you go to a website
and you log in:
you have your own identity
and the system recognizes
and acknowledges this identity
before they let you into the system.
So first you have to identify
yourself and once you're identified
we can use the ACL service
to find out if you have access
to this part, can we actually show
it to you and all these decisions
are made behind the scene prior to
dispatching the information to you.
Now on the lower part we have some
specific APIs that are also
domain specific, so we have
an Image Service which really is
the back-end of this application
we have looked at.
So obviously this application
is interfacing with the Rest API
but behind the scene this
Rest API dispatches requests
to get tides of your specific
brain slice and the Rest API
relays this information
to your (INAUDIBLE) application.
Similarly we have this other
application called the Voxel Brain
this API is really another
way to organize data in
a brain Atlas.
So, imagine the 3D volume,
that is the Brain you are studying
you only have
additional information
for instance, the density of
the specific kind of neuron
and so that 3D volume can
be sliced into very little cubes
so 3D shapes.
Voxel is really the 3D
counterpart of a Pixel
and so people decided to call
that a voxel.
So it is just a little 3D shape
in which you store, for instance
a numerical value, so if I know
that I have X value
in that specific Voxel,
I can store it there
and so we have this API
that allows you to say:
"Well that very specific region
of the Brain give me all the Voxels"
"annotated with density of
a specific kind of neuron"
"and let me work with that."
And so this API will return this
information to the user
then let them execute their
usecase with information.