In this session, I will be
talking about another
aspect of neuroinformatics,
which is Brain Atlases
and the link, also, to
the Knowledge Space.
Brain Atlases are actually
important in neuroinformatics
for organizing data,
because they establish
a link between
the semantics and space.
A Brain Atlas actually
consists of three things.
One is a coordinate space,
defined by a 3D template volume
a parcellation, which is  the parcel,
the Brain regions typically
within that volume defined
by a 3D boundary,
and an ontology, or defined
names and relationships between
those brain regions defined
by the parcellations.
So these atlases can be
used to integrate data
using either the coordinates
of the space
or the semantic tags
from the ontologies
and both can be
used to integrate.
or the semantic tags
from the ontologies
and both can be
used to integrate.
So, on this slide
I’ll show how you can
search for data,
data that’s been registered
and annotated with
the ontologies,
and once you’ve annotated
the data you can
actually search for
a property, for example
a type of the cell,
a Martinotti cell
when you search for it,
you immediately find all those
cells that have been
tagged by Martinotti
or parametal cell type,
you can find it, discover it
and actually filter out
for a specific cell type
and go and find
out further
details and download
the data.
So, this is
important because
all of those aspects the data
that have been registered
with the meta data that
make it discoverable.
But then, with Atlases if
you tag the brain region
that the neuron morphology
is coming from
you can find data
also according
to the specific
brain region.
And here we’re looking at
a particular data set
from a collaborator in China
from Wu Han
the Britain Chance
Center for
Biomedical Photonics
where they’ve done
a whole brain
Center for
Biomedical Photonics
where they’ve done
a whole brain
Golgi scan
of the rat brain
and by viewing that, you can
see individual morphologies
throughout any
part of the brain
and by overlaying
the brain regions
you can find out which brain
regions are those from.
Now, we’ve also integrated
the Allen Reference Atlas
the latest common
coordinate framework,
and from each brain
region you can find out
the name of the regions,
but also we’ve searched
to something called
Knowledge Space
which is really a way
of searching for data
from around
the world, including
our own Knowledge Graph.
So, goes back and finds you
data from the hippocampus
that has been registered within
the Knowledge Graph,
but in addition it will allow you
to go off and search data
from databases from
around the world.
So for thalamus you can see
many different types of data
physiology,
gene expression,
models, and so on,
from other databases.
Now if we go back to
the more occipital
area, say the primary visual
cortex in the mouse,
the primary visual area layer five
this is where the Allen
institute has been working
to capture a lot
of different neuron types
and actually this
provides a way searching
linking out of the atlas,
to go directly to
the Allen Institute’s data,
it’s all indexed
all linked in to
those atlases
as well as their
electrophysiological data,
which is provided as well.
So, the KnowledgeSpace
is that place, you just saw
that the Atlas links to
the knowledge space,
So, the KnowledgeSpace
is that place, you just saw
that the Atlas links to
the knowledge space,
but the Knowledge
Space is actually
the online encyclopedia
that you can use
to search for any particular
neuroscience concept,
in this case, say,
we can go to the neocortex
you get
a definition of that,
you can find the related literature,
you can find
for example, how much
literature has been
published per year,
the place of neocortex
within a particular ontology,
and then link out to
the other data sets,
in this case neuromorpho.org
which has large number of
morphologies from neocortex
and you can find
other types of data
as we’ve seen before,
from the Allen Institute,
specific layer five
parametal cells,
and actually go in and directly
go get that data.
So in this session,
you’ve learned about
organizing data using Brain Atlases,
searching for data,
finding data via a Brain Atlas,
and through that integration
the common ontologies and
also knowledge-space.org
which is an online
encyclopedia
the common ontologies and
also knowledge-space.org
which is an online
encyclopedia
that is integrated
with this ecosystem using
the common ontologies
to discover data
that’s federated
from around the world.