In the last part
of this presentation
I would like to talk more about
the minimal information
about the Neuro-science data set
and to start with, I'm just going
to repeat what MINDS,
a MINDS-compliant data set
should include.
It should define
the specimen it has been
generated from
and this should include
the age of the specimen
its sex, the species, the strain.
And again, you should already be
recognizing some of these elements,
these three, for instance
we've already seen that
they have vocabulary existing
to define these things.
The concept of
an entity classification
such as cell types for NEURON
the concept of a brain location,
whether you want to use
and ontologycal term
to define a logical area
or even spacial coordinates if you
happen to have this
precise information.
You want to have the contributors
that enable the generation
of these data sets
and their affiliations
so you can leave credits to them.
You want to define
the method and parameters
used to generate the data,
and the dates they were created on.
You want to describe
the data category
and the specific data format
you have used to save this data.
You want to describe
how to access the data
so where is it stored,
and the format.
And finally you want
the licence information
so someone can inform himself
about whether they can
re-use this information.
So what are the benefits of
a MINDS-compliant data set?
First, you have to see MINDS
as a very useful tool
that creates a community consensus,
as to how to describe
in the context of neuro-science,
the properties of a data set
and some of these properties
are extremely useful
and we'll actually see
why in the next slide.
Next, that provides us consistency
in the process of integrating the data
into a platform,
so if we really enforce
this MINDS compliance,
you know that all your data sets
will have a specimen,
and for instance, the brain region,
and people typically
are very focused on
the specimen and
the very specific parts of the brain
and that really enables them
to find other data sets
that can really help them
move forward in their research.
It gives power to
the search facilities
by just having this consistency
in the type of information stored,
and the vocabularies being used
to define them,
it gives a lot of power
to the search facilities.
And finally it is really a medium
to find similar and related data sets
and this is really the next part
we're going to look at.
So here, I have listed
quite a few examples
of similarity
and relatedness examples
that can be leveraged from simply
annotating your data sets
following the MINDS recommendations,
so I'm just going to list them
and illustrate
where appropriate.
So, you could find data sets
that came from the same species
but different strains,
different kinds of rats for instance.
You could also search for data sets
located in nearby brain regions.
You can look for
the same brain regions
but in different species or strain.
You can use a neuron with
a broder cell classification
so for instance,
your neuron may have been
categorized as the Martinotti cell,
but now you want to look at neurons
that are not only Martinotti cells,
but more generally inhibitory cells.
So again, playing with
the hierarchy of your ontology.
This is something you can do.
You can look at other data
categories in the same brain region
because bringing different angles
to the data you're currently using
you might strengthen your
position in discovering something.
You could use the same data category
but in a different brain region
for instance you have
electro-physiology in the thalamus
and you want to get
the electro-physiology data sets
in a different brain region and make
a comparison between them.
What is different between
these two brain regions?
You could use another data set
by the same lab
or contributor,
or finally
another data set generated
with the exact same protocol
or derived protocol.