In this part, we're going to
focus on designing a provenance
entity.
So we've seen that
the platform does allow you
to do these kinds of things.
Now, how do you do it in practice?
And again, I will not get into
technical detail of actually writing
an entity in this lecture, but
just how does an entity look like.
The most important thing
is to give it a name
and it sounds like a very
simple thing to say but
naming things appropriately,
meaningfully,
so that the community can
refer to it and understand very
easily what your entity is
is extremely important.
So naming your entity something that
is understood by everyone around
is going to help a lot.
So, like I said, you're going
to define it through a schema
and you have the ability to extend
entities from one and other.
So I gave already an example,
which is extending the generic
provenance entity defined by
the W3C Prov to define your own
but for instance,
I'll take an example
you have defined a data set entity
and say that the data set
has a category which is
an ontology term, it has a name.
This is fine.
Now I took earlier an example
of an electro physiology
data set and we have briefly
discussed that this type of data set
has also another piece
of information that is
the Stimuli that was used to
stimulate the specific neuron
in order to observe
it's electrical response.
So, this is also a data set.
It is an electro-physiology
data set.
And so at this stage what
you could do is to extend
the data set
and we'll write it if is,
for the sake of writing it showed
and at this stage I could define
a stimuli property,
and what this means is
we have the data set
defined with it's own fields
and the electro-physiology data set
extends the data set, that means
it inherits the category fields,
the name fields, and in addition
it brings a stimuli field.
So that allows you to
build a hierarchy of entities
that borrow information from
one and other and organize
your domain in a very logical way.
So, that's my second point,
entities can extend each other.
All entities can be used
in provenance, however
it is not mandatory if all you
wanted was to create a few
electro-physiology data sets
and save them into the system
without referring to any
provenance information
you could do it, we do not force
you to save provenance.
Now we do believe that
adding provenance information
does increase
the value of the data sets,
does give a lot of context to
potential users of your data sets,
and allows them to
build trust in what
you're generating
by being transparent
about the protocoles you have used,
what specific mouse or rat you have
been using, how you
have extracted your slices
and so on, and so forth.
So, you can push your
entities into the platform
and at the later stage you can
also involve them in provenance
there's no constrain there,
you can do it at the later stage.
So the second thing
you have to do, and I guess
I want to be ahead of myself
by designing this example
is to define the properties
of your entity.
And really you have to think of it
as what questions do you want to ask
the system, the platform,
about your entities
and thinking of it in this way
the listing of all the properties
necessary in your entities
is going to become a lot more
intuitive, because, okay,
in order to as a question
about:"Give me all
electro-physiology recording"
"that have a stimuli
called ID Rest"
which is a type of stimuli
or a square simulation...
and obviously you need to capture
this information in the meta data
of your entities.
It becomes obvious that
you need to create
a property that is stimuli,
and if the community
has already defined
an ontology that's described
this stimuli,
let's import it
because let's speak
the same language
it makes everybody's
job a lot simpler.
And maybe if the specific
property you want to use
doesn't have a well know
vocabulary defined,
then let's define it
and import it into the platform !
So, that's the way we like
to approach property definition
of entities,
and it works really well.
So what can you put into a property?
What can this be,
what types can we give them?
We can have literal types,
and by literal we mean
simply integers,
floating point values
strings, we can have structured
objects which themselves
can be defined with
their own schemas
and registered into the platform
we're going to look at some
specific examples of that later
and finally, and this
is an important one
we can use ontology terms.
And we're going to expand
a little bit in a later slide
on ontologies and why
they are so useful there.
Finally you can define
semantic constrains
so this is really what
you want to enforce.
When someone submits
an entity, one of such entity
into the system,
so an instance of that entity.
What do you want
the platform to check for you?
Maybe complain if one
of these is broken
so that the user knows,
where we were expecting you
to define it in this way
and not in that way.
Please, fix it, it is
your gate-keeper really
when registering
data into the platform.
So, what is at your
disposal here: you can use
enumerations, so sets of
strict values that you must use
to fill one of these property
you can have numerical ranges like
it has to be a value between
zero and ten, and nothing else.
If someone submits
an instance with the value 11
the system will say:
"I'm sorry, you broke that rule."
"Fix it and then you
will be able to save it."
And finally you can
give specific entity types
so when I said you can use
structured object
this semantic constraint can
show the value you have provided
to this kind of structured object
properties does match
the expected types.
Also if you use ontology terms it
can make sure that you use a term
that is really belonging
to the defined ontology.
And finally... Because some
entities will have raw data attached
like an electro physiology recording
but some of the entities
will not have any raw data
directly attached,
for instance, a neuron.
A neuron by itself is a logical
entity, it doesn't have raw data,
now, it can be derived
into a data set itself
as raw data, so you also have
to make this decision
as to whether your
entity has or has not
raw data attached.
But it is just a simple check box,
you have to click or not.