So to conclude, you have learned
a number of things in this session.
First we've looked at the challenges
of data integration in neuro science
and a number of approaches
to address them.
We've looked at different
ways to run data integration.
There are different
models you can use.
It's the fixed data model,
which has some limitations
that have been
issues in the past.
We have the user control,
the main design that really gives
the full flexibility
to the scientist
to really design their model
and really capture precisely
the domain they are working on
but also we have seen the power
in reusing existing domains
and vocabularies
to support your efforts
and make your data integration
compatible with
the rest of the communities.
Finally, we've looked at
the Blue Brain Nexus capabilities
and how it enables
data integration.
There were several aspects to this.
The ability to have an expert
designing their own model
to reuse existing domains,
to publish and search data
and finally to discover
new data sets
that are similar or related
to those you know.