So next I will take you to the steps
of creating your own domain,
so here I'm still going to stay
in the realm of neuroscience
but typically the way this happens
is that scientists come to us
and they just describe their
needs with the platform
and that allows us together
to define a specific entity.
So here, we've taken the example
of a neuron and through discussion
with the scientist,
we have identified
that it needs to have a name,
it needs to have a morphology type
and an electrical type each of which
are going to be based on specific
ontologies that already predefined
these morphological types
and electrical types.
And so, once this has been written,
typically by a knowledge engineer
in the Blue Brain Nexus project.
These can be then pushed
into the platform register
where people can start using it.
So the next step is
now I have two scientists
that are both working
on their own favorite neurons,
and they have done experiments
and they have identified that,
in the top part here
that neuron is a pyramidal cell,
and is also a stuttering cell.
You can then, through
either parametric interface
or through a ware application,
enter this information
push it into the platform,
but other scientists can do
the same thing.
And should they set the ACL, so
the Access Control Lists correctly
on their own respective entities,
and share it with people from
their group, and let's assume these
three people are working
in the same group.
And that person can then
request from the platform:
"Show me all neurons."
and you're getting back
the two entities
that these two scientists
have defined.
So it is a simplistic example,
but all of that we have been
able to do without having
to modify the platform
without writing code,
and just designing new things
declaring things into
the platform and automatically
people can start using it
and get values out of it.
And we find that amazing.
So, we've just seen an example
on how to define your own domain.
Now many domains have already
been defined by other communities.
And so I just want to take
a few minutes to describe
a few existing domains
that you might want
to consider reusing
so here, this is probably
the most used vocabulary
on the internet today in the age
of Facebook, LinkedIn
it's called the FOEF,
or Friend of a Friend.
It simply describes a person
and their social network.
And it's a very simple concept,
but FOEF has defined a very specific
vocabulary that allows you to define
someone or a piece of software.
So, for instance here,
we can define the name of a person
its title, you can have images
that depict that person
and you can have
the Family name, the Given name.
Here, quite an important
piece of vocabulary
is the other people
that that person knows
so this is how you start
describing your social network
and connecting that
person to other people.
And I will not read all these
attributes, but there's a number
of others you could potentially be
using whether that person has
a chat line from Jabber,
so you can connect with it
or that person works for a very
specific organization so potentially
in the Blue Brain Nexus
you could take this vocabulary
select the properties that
are interesting to you
and register the concept
of an agent or a person
leveraging this vocabulary,
making very clear that
it comes for FOAF,
and just start using it.
So the previous example was really
outside of the neuroscience field.
And here for the sake
of illustrating neuroscience
I want to take another domain
that really is in
the realm of neuroscience
and so an IDM is one of such domains
that deal with
the neuro-imaging data model
and so, we're not planning to
get into deep details of how this is
described but we can see here that
the whole community
has come together
to define a very specific
kind of workflow.
So, it covers the acquisition
of imagery data
it caters for the representation of
the raw data that has been acquired
the description of specific
analysis and workflows .
It allows you to represent derived
data from what you have acquired
and to do so, it leverages
the W3C-Prove
just like we do in
Blue Brain Nexus.
You can also capture
the publications that have been
created from whatever workflows
derived data you have created
and as well as the distribution
and sharing of the queries via
a common API.
So this is more of
the platform, I guess of their own,
but as the specific
data model here,
all of these could be leveraged
in Blue Brain Nexus
by just importing
a very specific domain
and declaring it as within
the name space of NIDM
and just reuse it.
The community, like I said,
has already spent time defining
these carefully.
By leveraging it you also
render the data you push
into the platform and make it
compatible with data sitting
on other data repositories
potentially, which is
a very powerful way to combine data.
Here we have a very brief
overview of the NIDM
domain representation
and here they are leveraging
the visual representation
of the W3C-Prove
and so you can see just
the main elements which
are the project on
which you're working
the specific study
and the acquisition of data.
And here again they emphasize
that they are using
the following provenance elements
and you find again and you
should be familiar with it,
it consists of agents of activity,
of entity, and attributes.
So, again a really powerful way
to leverage existing domain
and vocabularies and bring them
into your Blue Brain Nexus instance.