So, in this slide we're going to
look a little deeper
into ontologies.
So, Sean has already given you
basic information about what
ontologies are,
and I will not expand on this.
What I'm really interested
in doing here is to show you
for the domain of neuroscience
which ontologies we have decided
to integrate in our
Blue Brain Nexus platform.
So, a lot of the ontologies we
have integrated have been either
taken from the Neuroscience
Information Framework
or co-developed with them.
The goal of NIF is to define
these concepts
for the domain of neuroscience
and share them so the community
can re-use them and have
a common agreement on how to define
neuroscientific concepts.
They have defined
the NIF standard ontologies
which integrate a number
of existing ontologies
such as, (INAUDIBLE), for instance
to define Brain regions
in a manner that is agnostic
of which specimen
or species they come from,
(Gaby?) for instance for
the description of small molecules
the gene ontology or OBE,
and quite a few others.
Now in this part here,
what I would like to illustrate
is a number of ontologies
we have decided to use
in the Blue Brain Nexus platform for
the domain of neuroscience.
So, for instance,
around the specimens
we have the definition
of species and strain
so this is really helping
in defining what kind of
animal or subject that was,
so these two
we have created them ourselves.
This is the part of the NCBI,
taxonomy.
And so, whenever dealing with
ontologies it is really important to
do enough research
to find out if there is any
vocabulary already
existing in the community
so that we can just leverage them.
It really would be a waste of time
for us to reinvent what
is already working
and well accepted by the community,
but there's also a strong advantage
in using and reusing these
already defined vocabularies,
and very simply if someone describes
a rat with a very specific concept
and you have also defined a rat
with the same concept
so even if you're storing your
data in different places
they become compatible,
you know that what you call a rat
is also what they call a rat,
and so if, for instance,
in your lab you deal with
electrophysiology only
and that other person deals
only with morphology
at least, the data is compatible
at the level of the species
and it is very clear to deduce
from the use of the vocabulary
you have chosen.
The next one will be just
a vocabulary to define a sex
of the specimen, male or female.
Then we have a number of ontologies
for the description of data sets.
So we have the category,
so what kind of data set is it?
Is it electrophysiology,
or morphology image
imagery data.
That's the specific data format
that is used to serialize this data,
the raw data, when you save it
on your disk it is a concrete format
that you have chosen
and so there's a way
in the meta data
to describe this and this
becomes very important
if you look for electrophysiology
in a very specific format
because you have a workflow
that requires it
you can then filter the data
on the platform
and only get those that match
and will become compatible
with what you're trying to achieve.
Next, we have a licence ontology,
which allows us to define
who can re-use the data you
are publishing into the platform.
So I will not
underestimate this one.
If you decide that your data cannot
be re-used for commercial purposes
you can actually define that there.
Finally we have the storage of
the data set and this is a way
to describe where you have
stored your data.
So it can be, through the platform,
in which case you don't really
need to know where it's configured,
you just have to know that
the people managing the platform
have configured it in a way
that the data is going to be
backed up and is safe.
But if you were to store the data on
an external storage to the platform
here we have an ontology to
actually allow you to describe this.
So you can easily find the data.
For instance, it is stored
in a cloud on Amazon
and you can define it there.
Then we have the concept
of sample classification
which is really important to us,
because from a lot of the data sets
we are integrating,
scientists take the time to make
statements on the entities:
we integrate, neurons, for instance
and it will give them
electric types
morphology types, and so,
we have the designed ontology
that allows that
description with NIF.
Finally, another way to classify
them is to define what kind
of neurotransmitters
some entities are
so that's another kind of ontology
but I won't get into
the details of that here.
A lot of the data we integrate
really makes sense when we
anchor it in specific brain spaces.
So we have a number of existing
brain atlases that are references
for specific species,
whether it is the Allen mouse CCFv3
or the Waxholm for the rat
we have an ontology that defines
the logical reference
for these spaces
and these can be annotated
at the level of a data set.
More detailed in that concept
is the parcellation schemes.
So here we enter, still within
the concept of anchoring data
into an atlas, now we want to,
what we talked about
in which specific region of an atlas
so your data set is to be anchored.
And so different atlas spaces
come with parcellation schemes
where anatomists have just looked
at this space and defined
sub-volumes of this space that
correspond to specific brain regions
or brain parcels.
So we have three here,
which I've put as examples
actually we have
quite a few others,
and these define,
again, a vocabulary
to describe these brain regions.
But they are really specific
to that atlas space.
Finally, we have some
ontologies to describe...
that are really linked more
to the provenance concepts
that really allows to enrich it.
So, for instance, we have
the type of the activity run
whether it is an experimental
type ran in the lab
or a computational task,
you know, simply run in a computer
or classification activity,
so you have these very short
vocabularies that really
enable you to describe
via the activity you want to define,
and later on filter through
the semantic searches.
Then we have measurement methods,
so an ontology to describe
what kind of methods
you have applied to generate
new entities.
And finally, the role of
the agents involved
in a given activity
whether it was like the principle
investigator of a project
or a researcher doing
accurate experiments in the lab.
So this is not fully exhaustive,
but it is a set of ontologies we use
to annotate our data
in the context of neuro science.
So here just to tie it all together
and show you that we have
a central place where
you can actually
introspect all these ontologies.
We have what we call
the ontology viewer.
So if you open this
with an application
you can list all the ontologies
currently available and integrated
into the platform.
And so here we have regrouped them
by logical topics
so we have a number
of parcellation schemes
and you can see,
if I take the Waxholm Space
you can look into white matter.
So here, you can see
in the video the hierarchy
of this brain region
and the relations that
that region is further defined
by these three other sub-regions.
And through here you can
really introspect every ontology
we have done.
So if you want to have a look
at electrophysiology
it has a parent term that
is physiological data
and here you have
the specific data set
category that allows
you to define:
"This data set is
an electrophysiology recording."
The nice thing you
can do with that is that
if you have used this vocabulary
to describe your data
and you're interested in,
not only electrophysiology
but also, say,
functional imaging
you could leverage
the hierarchy of this ontology
for instance, by using the term
"physiological data"
and the system is intelligent
enough to know that
because you have annotated with
"electrophysiology" it knows
that electrophysiology is a sub-type
of physiological data
and so it will retrieve
from the system
all electrophysiology,
as well as functional imaging
effective connectivity,
and functional connectivity.
So you can really leverage the power
of ontologies
and more abstract concepts
to make interesting
scientific questions.