So, to conclude,
you have learned
a number of things
in this session.
First, we've looked at
the challenges of data integration
in neuroscience
and a number of approaches to
address them.
We've looked at different ways
to run data integration
there are different
models that you can use.
There's the fixed data model
which has some limitations that
have been issues in the past.
We have the user control,
the main design that will give
the full flexibility
to the scientist
to really design their model
and really capture precisely
the domain they are working on,
but also we have seen the power
in re-using existing domains
and vocabularies
to support your efforts
and make your data integration
compatible with
the rest of the community's.
Finally we've looked at
the Blue Brain Nexus'
capabilities and how it
enables data integration.
There were several aspects to this.
The ability to have an expert
designing their own model
to re-use existing domains,
to publish and search data
and finally, to discover new
data sets that are similar
or related to those you know.