In this part we are going to focus
on designing a provenance entity.
So we've seen that the platform does
allow you to do these kind of things
now, how do you do it in practice?
Again, I will not get into
the technical details
of actually writing
an entity in this lecture
but just: how does
an entity look like.
The most important
thing is to give it a name.
It sounds like a very
simple thing to say
but naming things appropriately
and meaningfully so that
the community can refer to it
and understand very easily
what your entity is
is extremely important.
So naming your entity something that
is understood by everyone around
is going to help a lot.
So, like I said, you're going
to define it through a schema
and you have the ability to
extend entities from one and other.
So, I already gave an example
which is extending
the generic provenance entity
defined by the W3C prov
to define your own
but for instance,
I'll think of an example
you have defined a data set entity
and say, the data set has a category
which is an ontology term
and it has a name.
This is fine, now, earlier I took
an example of an electrophysiology
data set and we have briefly
discussed that this type of data set
also has another piece of
information that is the stimuli
that was used to stimulate
the specific neuron
in order to observe
its electrical response.
So, this is also
a data set.
It is an electrophysiology data set.
And so on this stage what you
can do is to extend the data set.
And we'll write it if it is,
for the sake of writing it short
and at this stage I could define
a stimuli property.
And what this means is,
we have the data set defined
with its own fields,
and the electrophysiology data set
extends the data set,
that means it inherits
the category fields,
the name fields
and in addition
it brings a stimuli field.
So that allows you to build
a hierarchy of entities
that borrow information
from one and other
and organize your domain
in a very logical way.
So, that's my second point,
entities can extend each other.
All entities can be used
in provenance, however
it is not mandatory if all you
wanted was to create a few
electrophysiology data sets
and save them into the system
without referring to any
provenance information
you could do it, we do not force
you to save the provenance.
Now, we do believe that
adding provenance information
does increase the value
of your data sets
does give a lot of context
to potential users of your data sets
and allows them to build trust
in what you're generating
by being transparent
about the protocols you have used
what specific mouse
or rat you have been using
how have you extracted your slices,
and so on and so forth.
So you can push your
entities into the platform
and at a later stage you can also
involve them in provenance.
There's no constrain there,
you can do it at a later stage.
So, the second thing
you have to do
and I guess I want to
be ahead of myself by
designing this example
is to define the properties
of your entity.
And you really have to think of it
as what questions do you want to ask
the system, the platform,
about your entities.
And thinking of it in this way
the listing of all the properties
necessary in your entities are going
to become a lot more intuitive
because, in order to ask
a question about:
"Give me all electrophysiology
recording that has a stimuli
called IDrest", which is a type
of stimuli or a square ,
and obviously you need
to capture this information
in the meta data of your entities,
it becomes obvious that you need
to create a property that is stimuli
and if the community has already
defined an ontology that described
this stimuli,
let's import it
because let's speak
the same language
it makes everybody's job
a lot simpler
and maybe if the specific property
you want to use doesn't have
a well-known vocabulary defined
then let's define it
and import it into the platform.
So, that's the way we like
to approach the property definition
of entities, and we find that
it works really well.
So, what can you put
into a property?
What can this be,
what types can we give them?
We can have literal types,
and by literal we mean
simply integers,
floating point values, strings.
We can have structured objects,
which themselves can be defined
with their own schemas
and registered into the platform
we're going to look at
specific examples of that later
and finally,
this is an important one
we can use ontology terms.
And we're going to expand
a little bit in a later slide
on ontologies and why
are they so useful there.
Finally, you can define
Semantic constrains.
So this is really what
you want to enforce
when someone submits an entity,
one of such entities
into the system,
so an instance of that entity,
what do you want
the platform to check for you?
and maybe complain if
one of these rules is broken
so that the user knows:
"We were expecting you to define it
in this way and not in that way."
"Please, fix it."
So it is really your gatekeeper when
registering data into the platform.
What is at your disposal here?
You can use enumerations,
so sets of strict values
that you must use to fill
one of these properties.
You can have numerical ranges, like
it has to be a value between
zero and ten and nothing else.
If someone submits
an instance with a value eleven
the system will say:
"Sorry, you broke that rule, fix it,
then you will be able to save it."
And finally you can
give specific entity types.
So when I said you can use
structured objects
this semantic constrain can then
show that the value you've provided
to this kind of structured
object properties
does match the expected types.
Also, if you use ontology terms,
it can make sure that you use
the term that really belongs
to the defined ontology.
And finally, it may, and I say may,
because some entities will have
raw data attached,
like an electrophysiology recording
but some other entities
will not have any raw data
directly attached,
for instance, a neuron.
A neuron by itself
is a logical entity
it doesn't have raw data.
It can be derived into a data set
that itself has raw data.
So you have to make this decision,
as to whether your entity has
or has no raw data attached.
But it is just a simple tick box,
you have to tick or not.