In the next part, I have
already done this
design, and I'm going to
present it to you now.
So here are the entities
and the specific fields we're
going to put on them.
So, if you remember,
we had drawn a first entity
I called rat.
And just for the sake of having
something sufficiently generic,
I've called it here,
Specimen
so we could also later on apply it
to mouse, human, and potentially
other species.
So the species itself is captured
through an ontology term
as one field, one property.
And then we have the strain,
which is another ontology.
Turns out that these two, we've
already discussed these,
are coming from the NCBI taxonomy,
but still thse two fiels are separated.
And we need to capture the sex
of the specimen
and finally its age.
And as you see here, it is not
yet a literal value.
For instance, I could have put 14
and define that it is always
expressed in days.
Here, I want to give a little more
flexibility to the users of this domain.
And so I have decided to define
another entity called
Specimen Age
and so the fields age here,
is of type Specimen Age which
itself is defined
just beside it.
And so the Specimen Age is
made of three properties.
1) is the value, the specific age.
The unit, and here I want to
constrain
this value, the unit,
to three potential units
can be in days, can be
expressed in months or in years,
and it's a floating value,
so you could put 1.5 years
if you wanted, or 3 days
just the same.
And finally we have the period
which can be
pre natal or post natal.
Again we have constrained the model
and only these two values can be
defined in the submitted entity,
and if you fail to reuse
one of these,
the system will just fail validation
and let you know
so you can correct your
data submission.
Next, we're going to talk
about the neuron.
So here, we have defined
simply three properties.
The name, because to a scientist
it might be important to give it
the name that was used in
the lab or something intelligible
that will speak to the
intended audience
that will consume this data.
So we have the name of the neuron
and then we have two more properties:
The morphological type, which here
are written shorter as "mtype",
which is of type ontology, and we
have an existing cell type
ontology that you can review
at your leisure
in the ontology viewer application
I showed in earlier videos.
And we have another property
called "etype",
which is based on the very same
ontology but a different branch
of it.
And as you can see just here,
there is no data attached
to the neuron
just like there was no data attached
to the specimen.
Next, we have the data set.
And here, at this stage,
I didn't see
a need to actually differentiate
the electrophysiology recording from
the morphology reconstruction
but we could have done.
So here I'm going to use
the data sets entity
for both these different types
of data sets.
We can give a name
to our data set:
It's just a plain chain of
characters, string.
We have a category which is based on
the ontology data category.
So far, so good. We have
a mime type
which is really the file format
you have used
to save your file on disk
after running the experiment
that generated the data.
And finally a license,
where you can see well
whether it is like usable
commercially or not commercially.
And the last thing we need
to say here is that
we want to allow a user
to attach
raw data to a data set.
This is crucial.