That was part one of this
scientists interview.
Now we want to interview
another person.
Actually it could be the same,
but here
I'm depicting it as
a different person.
The first one was with the
person generating the data.
The second one is more of
the user of the integrated data,
and we are very curious
to find out
what it is they want to do
with integrated data
because this is going to help us
to design the entities further
and add all the relevant
properties on entities
that will enable interesting
scientific queries to be run.
So I'm going to read through
these statements
and this is going to drive later on
the design of the entities.
So the scientist wants to get data
related to a specimen's species,
strain, or age.
So that means that species,
the strain and the age are things
you want to be able to add
into your queries. For instance,
give me all data sets
that derives from a rat,
or mouse, or a human.
Same thing for the strain, and
same thing for the age.
The scientist wants to be able to
get all data sets from a given neuron.
So again, that strengthens
the assumption
that we need to have
a neuron entity.
This is good, and derivation has
to be made from this neuron entity.
The scientist wants to get
data sets
by title, with have called that
category previously.
So we'll have to think of putting
this data set category property
on our data set.
And here, the scientist wants to
get the data set by file format.
So again we'll have to think about
integrating an ontology that
that represents specific
file formats
so distinctions could be made
of the electrophysiology, we called
it in Igor format
which is one known format
or NWB for instance
which is another format.
The scientist wants to get neurons
by classification.
So in that case, we can figure
out this by either
electric type, or
morphological type.
Then the scientist wants to get
data by the protocol used.
So we will have to think at the
level of the activity to capture
the protocol and some forms
and we will describe later
a proposal for that.
And the scientist wants to get data
that specific people generated,
so there again the W3C provenance
is already offering that through
the means of the concept of agent.
So as long as we tie people
who generated the data
to the agent concept of
the W3C Prov
which will be able to do that. So
I think we are in quite a good shape
to carry on.