In this lecture, we're going
to have a look at how
to design practically, a domain.
And more particularly,  we're going
to have a look at the acquisition
of electrophysiology data,
and morphology reconstruction
for a given neuron.
So, as part of this lecture
we're going to have a more detailed
look into the use case
we're going to model.
We're going to go through
the steps of...
an interview with a scientist
that explains
what they've been doing
in the lab.
And then with another scientist that
expresses the type of question
we would like to be able to answer
through the use of the platform
once the data has been integrated.
Then, we're going to go through
the steps of designing a model,
both in defining the provenance
patterns
that essentially defines the domain
we're going to design.
And then into the specifics of
the entities we're going to create.
Finally, we're going to have
a look at the provenance editor
which is a tool you're going
to be using in a graded exercise
this week.
So here, at the top of the page,
you can see information
of the specimen that has been used
to capture the information.
In this case, it is a mouse line.
And you can see the type of neuron
that has been recorded,
and the part that really interests
us here is this data captured.
Here, you can see that there's
a number of stimuli
that have been applied
to this neuron in order to record
its electric response.
And here we will stick with
the long square one.
On the top part of the screen,
you can see the specific stimuli,
and at the bottom you can see
how the cell responded.
So here on the screen
as it is now, we have
all the sequential
sweeps that have been applied
with the specific stimuli
to this one neuron.
What you can then do is to pick
the sweeps one by one
and really look at what the specific
stimulation was like,
and how the neuron really reacted.
And as you flick through them
one by one,
you can see that the intensity
of the stimulation does increase
all the way to the neuron
actually responding
to the stimulation.
And, the higher we get, the stronger
the stimulation gets.
So this is typically used
also in the lab
to identify what is called the real
base of a neuron
which is really the thresh hold above
which the neuron starts responding
with spikes.
So next, we'll have a brief look at
what these morphology reconstructions
look like. So I'm going to
now open again this
webpage. I have left here
the url
for the Allen Institute website,
where you can actually
look at this data.
And this is not really data
integrated now in our platform
but we're going to work
through the steps of doing it.
So let's have a look
at this page.
So here, essentially, is
the morphological reconstruction
of the very same neuron.
And so, on the left hand side,
we can see that
we have the actual
digital captures
of the slice, of the neuron
in the slice
as it was done in the lab.
And so using these
images,
someone has actually retraced
the neuron by hand
and recreated a
3D representation of it.
So if I put it back
in it's original shape
you can really see here...
You can really easily
match the shape.
It is the same representation.
This one is really the original image,
and this one is a reconstructed
one done by
a scientist in the lab.
So these are the two data sets
we're going to
try to integrate into our platform.
And to do so,
we're going to design
a domain
to capture enough information.
So in this part, we're going to
pretend to have an interview
with a scientist to discuss
the origin of the data.
So we have our scientist
depicted here on the left,
and right next to it, I'm going
to show you the summary sentences
of a discussion we've had
with this scientist.
And on the bottom part,
I'm going to show the provenance
pattern we are inferring
from the statements the scientist
is giving us.
So the first statement is that
the experiment was done on a rat
of the strain Wistar Han.
And it was aged p14,
post natal 14 days.
And so quite logically,
it leads us to creating an entity
which for now I will
call a rat,
that allows us to store the
information such as the species,
the strain and the age
of the subject.
So, next.
The scientist is telling us that,
they have recorded several
characteristics
of single neurons.
Just going to do this one.
So next, the scientist
tell us that
they have recorded several
characteristics of single neurons.
So, quite naturally,  we are
going to create
a neuron entity which
self derives
from the rat,
on which we're going to be able
later on to
store these characteristics.
The next fact is that
recorded electrophysiology
of a single neuron has been done
and raw data has been captured.
So, again, we can derive an electrophysiology
recording from that neuron,
and we can indicate here
that raw data has to be attached
to this data set.
Next,
they have reconstructed that
morphology of that very same neuron.
And same neuron here is quite
important because
from the provenance pattern, it means
that from the very same neuron,
the same entity derives
both electrophysiology
and a morphology reconstruction
which also has raw data attached.
So far, so good.
Last thing, is that classification
of the neurons
has been made based
on recorded data.
And these classifications are
of two types:
electric type,
and we have been informed that an
ontology already exists for it,
and we'll also give it
a morphology type.
And there again we have an
ontology pre existing.
So we take note of it, and we know
we're going to try to integrate with it
at a later stage.