So, to conclude,
in this session,
we've been learning
a number of things.
First, we've been learning how to
design a specific domain
to capture a very concrete use case.
This is the one really you're
going to be executing
as part of a grade
exercise this week.
We've been defining the program's
pattern, but we have also been defining
all the entities necessary, and the
specific properties that will enable you to
ask all the questions that the scientists
want to be able to answer.
We've integrated relevant
ontologies as part of this domain.
And finally, we've really
ensured that
the domain we have built together
can answer all the questions
that our scientists wanted
to answer.
Thank you very much.