Here, we have defined already
our provenance pattern,
but we have also been told
by the scientists that
they want to capture the protocol
that will allow to generate
the various entities in
this provenance pattern,
and also to capture the agents
that  contributed
or were part of these activities.
So I have now introduced
these three levels.
The concept of an activity from
which we can also add protocols
and agents and so on...
So originally, we only
had these links,
and so now we have the ability
to ensure the additional information
the scientist does need.
At this stage,
now we can define all
the fields that are
defining an activity.
So, not so many. We have a type,
like I said, we're going to differentiate
experimental activity
from potentially others
like classifications.
We have the method
that has been used,
so in ontology terms describing
the specific methods, and we have
measurement methods, ontology
for that.
We want to define the protocol
and this protocol will be
further defined down here.
And finally, we have the
list of agents
that is defined here.
So an agent is also accompanied
by its role
in the activity, and we have
an ontology for that as well.
If you get a little further on
the definition of the protocol
it's not again very much there but
we want to give it a title.
We want to give it a description,
and you could see that as the
materials and methods of
a typical scientific publication.
So, a thorough description
of all the steps
that led to the execution
of this activity.
And finally, if there are any
known publications
that describe this protocol,
you can capture them
using the concept of cross
references here shortened to Xref
which is defined here.
And so, a cross reference
is simply
built with two fields:
A database which can be
for instance
a DOI or (INAUDIBLE)
and then an identifier.
If you have selected a database
DOI, then you would put the DOI
identifier.
And if you've selected (INAUDIBLE)
you will make sure you
have a (INAUDIBLE) IDENTIFIER.
Just a very simple way to
describe a cross reference.
On the lower part now we can
have a look at the agents
and here we have the given
name, which is a string.
The family name a string, the email
which is very important so we can
facilitate contacts to the people.
And the affiliation that agent,
that person was related to.
And the affiliation is this
right here,
we can have the laboratory
the person works in,
and finally the organisation
that person works in.
And so we have here,
a definition of the activity
that does capture
enough details
so the scientists can ask
the question they wanted to ask.