So in order to analyse
our morphologies,
we will use NeuroM, a software
that is available in GitHub.
With NeuroM, you can visualise
a neuronal morphology,
assess its quality, and extract
basic morphometrics
that can be used for the comparison
and classification of neurons.
First of all, we provide
two applications
to check the quality of the cell,
and extract some basic morphometrics
without even using Python coding.
The first one is morph_check.
You select the morphology
and you give the path to the file
that you want to analyse.
So once you run that,
you go through a list
of checks:
if the whole morphology
is connected,
if it has a soma,
if the IDs are sequential,
if it has valid neurites,
if it contains a dendrite,
if it contains an axon,
and then some more detailed tests
that concern the length
of the segment,
the length of the sections,
and the radius.
So, you don't necessarily need
to pass all those tests
for your morphology to be valid.
For example,
some morphologies do not have
an apical dendrite,
so it's up to you to decide how to
interpret the results of this test.
But then you might want to go
into more details
and do some morphological
statistics extraction.
So we will use the application
morph_stats for that.
Calling this application
you see that returns a list of
different morphological features.
The most common one is
total length.
And then some more
detailed statistics
on the lengths of the sections,
or the volumes.
So this is just
an example
of some feature analysis
that you can run
on your selected morphology.
You see that this is separated
into different sections
that refer to different tree types.
For example, in the beginning
we have the axonal features,
then we sum up the features
for the whole morphology.
Then the soma features,
the apical and
the basal dendrites.
So with this application,
you can extract
the global statistics
and save them into a file and
then do some further analysis.
But if you want to do
that directly in Python,
we can use NeuroM interactively.
So here, we will import
a model
and load the neuron.
To import NeuroM, you just
import NeuroM
and once you have
your module loaded,
you can get your morphology.
So once again you have to select
tot he morphology file.
And then you
do neurom.load_neuron.
In this case, you will just load
one neuron in the program.
You can also do the same thing
for multiple neurons
but then you just have to do
load_neurons
and give the full path to
a set of morphologies,
not the single morphology file.
So once you've loaded
your morphology
we can go into
the visualisation.
Those are just some commands to
setup the size of the figures
but the module we're
going to use
is inside neurom.viewer,
and from that
the draw function.
So from neurom.viewer,
we import the draw function.
And if you want to see more
details about this draw function,
you just call the help.
So you can do that by draw?
And what appears here is
a small example
about how you can use
this viewer.
So here is the help
function of the draw.
You can see the details of how
you can use the
draw function.
And what is currently
available in the viewer
is a 2D plot, a 3D plot
or a dendogram.
So let's go and run those
three functions
and see our morphology.
So if you just do
draw(my_neuron),
you get the figure
of the morphology,
the 2D plot.
And what you can see is the apical
dendrite in purple,
the basal dendrite in red,
and the axon in blue.
And this is a convention we use
throughout NeuroM in general,
this colour code.
Now you can select a different
mode for the draw.
So what you can do is to draw
your morphology in 3D.
And once you do that, you get
the 3D plot of the morphology.
If you're doing electrical
modeling,
you might be interested in
the dendogram of the morphology.
So let's now try
the mode dendogram
of the same function.
If you're interested in
the electrical activity
of the neuron, you might
want to see the dendogram.
To do so,  we select
the mode dendogram.
So we draw our neuron and,
as you can see we use
the same colour code
where the apical is purple,
the basals are red,
and the axons are blue.
And here you can already
see the difference
in the sizes of those
three types of trees
because the apicals and
the axons extend much more
than the basal dendrites.
So now that we've seen
our morphologies,
we want to start
analysing them.
So we want to extract some
basic morphological features.
And the most common features
that are used is
the total length or
the total surface area
or a global statistic such
as the soma size.
To get the complete
list of features
that are currently available
in NeuroM,
you can use the help function
of the get.
So you do neurom.get?
and this help box appears here.
So you have different
levels of features.
The first one is neurite features
which refers to individual trees.
Those are lengths,
volumes,
number of sections,
or number of bifurcations,
or number of terminations,
and then at the end,
you have the neuron features.
So those are global features for
the whole neuron morphology.
Some of them refer to the soma
such as the soma radi,
or the surface areas
and others refer
to the trunks.
So those are soma statistics
about the beginning
of each tree.
So once you've seen
those features,
you can select one
and let's try the total length.
So we run total length,
neurom.get()
and then we add the string of
the feature we want to extract.
And after that, our neuron.
So then we can print
the total length
and see already
the first statistical measurement.
So how long in total
is our neuron?
So this gives us the sum
of the lengths.
What if we want to study the
individual lengths of each section?
Then we can select
another feature:
section lengths with my neuron.
And this is exactly
the same process
for any feature that
you might want to analyse.
So let's see.
You get a very lengthy
list of numbers.
And this is probably
not telling you much.
So what we want to do next,
is start to perform some
statistical analysis
on the morphometrics that
we have extracted.
And we're going to do that
in the next part
of the tutorial.