So in the previous part,
we extracted some basic morphometrics
from the neuron.
What we’re gonna do
in this part is perform
some statistics on the morphometrics
that we extracted before,
and those can be basic statistics
such as the average
or the variance within a feature
but that is not always sufficient.
So what we want to do
is also to draw the distribution
to get an idea about the whole say.
In order to do that,
we will use some basic Python modules.
After that, we will be able
to compute features
between different neurons
or either different types of trees.
So now that we have
extracted our features,
we can perform
some statistics on them.
What we’re gonna need for that
is "numpy" which is a
mathematical module of Python.
So numpy has available
a lot of the basic statistical functions
that you might want to perform
on your features,
so that would be the sum
and then you can compute
the total length
that we've seen before,
or the mean volume,
or the standard deviation,
minimum or maximum.
So just by using numpy dot
and then minimum, maximum
standard deviation,
you can get all the values
that might be interesting.
So now that you’ve extracted
your feature, we can perform
some statistical analysis.
To do so, we will use numpy,
a module that is available in Python.
So we import numpy and then,
we can start performing
some statistics on our section lengths.
So the first one is the sum,
this will sum up all the section lengths
so we can get the total length
of the neuron.
Same way, we can get the mean volume
or the standard deviation,
or the minimum, and maximum
of the section lengths,
and if we run this command,
we can print all those
interesting statistics
on the section lengths
that we’ve computed before.
So now you might wanna go
into more details
and perform statistics
on the individual parts of the neuron.
So before we have been working
with a whole neuron,
now we’re concentrating
on the individual parts
which is basal dendrites,
apical dendrites, and axons.
To do so, we have to select
the neurite type.
So it’s exactly what we did before
but we add an option neurite type
equals neuron dot basal dendrite.
So that will give you
the section length
of the basal dendrites.
And then you can do exactly
the same for the apical dendrites
and the axons.
So you just have to choose
the correct neuron type
and you can play with the morphometrics
of individual parts of the neuron.
So now we can compare
the morphometrics
that we have extracted
for the three different types of trees.
So exactly as we did before,
we can use numpy dot sum
to get the values of the total length
of the three different tree types.
And as you can see,
the axons are much longer
than both the apical
and the basal dendrites.
Even though the basal dendrites
are many more,
you only have one apical dendrite
and one axon,
but still the total length
of the basal dendrites is much lower
because they just stay locally.
The axons are reaching
much further regions
and so are the apical dendrites.
So now we can compute
the average length of each tree type.
We do that using numpy once again
but now we’re gonna use
numpy dot average.
So if we do this, we get three values
for the different tree types.
As you can see, the differences
are not as large
as the total length differences.
So now we are going to compute
the averages of the section lengths
for those three tree types.
We do so using numpy once again,
but now we’re gonna do
numpy dot average. So if we do so,
we get the average value
of the section length
for those three different tree types.
As you can see,
the differences are not as large
as the total length differences
which indicates that even though
the extend, the total extend
of the trees is so different,
the individual sections are comparable.
So now that we have extracted
our morphological feature,
we might wanna go
and plot the distribution.
This will give us a much better picture
of the overall profile of the feature.
It is also very useful
if we want to compare features:
so if you want to compare
a neuron to a different neuron,
or a tree type to a different tree type.
So the first function we’re gonna use
is a histogram. To do that,
we will use the hist from Pylab
that we have imported before.
So we do "pylab dot hist"
of our section lengths
that we have extracted,
and this gives us this distribution.
However, as you can see,
the tail of the distribution
is not very well defined
and that is because
of the small number of bins.
So we might wanna go
and add more bins,
so here we have only 10,
let’s do 25.
Here you get a much better picture
of the distribution.
Another way of presenting
the same distribution
is to do the cumulative plot.
So we do "pylab dot hist" once again,
but now we activate
the cumulative option,
and by doing that,
we get a distribution that extends
from the minimum
to the maximum number.
So now, we might want
to normalize the distribution.
As you can see here,
you just have numbers.
So, if you want to compare
two different distributions
for two different neurons,
that’s not gonna be very helpful.
What we want instead
is to have percentages,
so which percentage
of the section lengths
falls into each of those bins?
And in order to do that,
we need to activate
the normed function,
the normed option
of the histogram of pylab.
And in order to do that,
we wanna activate the normed option
of the histogram function of pylab.
So we just select normed equals true,
and we get the percentage
as opposed to the absolute values
that we got before.
We can use that
to compare different distributions.
So another way of representing
the same distribution is the boxplot,
so we can use the boxplot function
of pylab to generate
an equivalent figure
to the previous one.
The difference here
is that you get the medium value,
the 50% of the data,
then 75%, and 25%,
and then you can see the outliers
of the distribution.
So this is an important feature
to see how many outliers you have.
Now, that we have analyzed
our feature with a histogram,
we wanna go and check
another representation
which is a boxplot.
So we’re gonna use "pylab dot boxplot"
to generate the overall distribution
of the same feature section lengths.
The advantage of this representation
is you don’t have to choose the bin size
and you can get the outliers.
So what does the boxplot means?
This line is the medium value
of the distribution.
This box annotates 50% of the data.
So 50% of the sections
have a length that lies
within those values.
Then 75% of the data
allocated in here,
and then with the small circles
you see the outliers of the distributions
so this is anything that is outside
the 75% of the distribution.
So using the previous plots,
the histogram and the boxplot,
we can start comparing morphometrics
between different tree types
or between different neurons.
Here, we will try to see
what are the differences between
the distribution of section lengths
of basal, apicals, and axons.
So we create a list
with those three tree type features
and we call once again,
"pylab dot hist" with the same bin size
and a normalized distribution.
We also select the labels
so that we can annotate
the color of the distributions.
In order to do that,
we call "pylab dot legend".
So this legend is generated
with the labels we’ve selected,
and then you can see
the three different colors
for the three different tree types.
This is not consistent
with the colors we chose
because those are the colors
of Pylab, not of NeuroM.
So once you’ve plotted
your distribution for the three tree types,
you can understand more
about the behavior of those tree types.
For example,
you see that you have a high peak
for the apicals here,
indicating that there is a high percentage
of sections with this length.
Similarly, you can see that sections
of large length are merely axonal sections,
so you were not able to get that
just by the statistical comparison
that we did before
because we just computed
the average section length.
Now, with the distributions,
you can get the full picture,
and you can see at which section length
you have the highest concentration
for each tree type.
Another way to compare
the same distributions
is to use the boxplot.
So we do these by creating
the same list that we did before
for basal, apical,
and axonal section lengths,
but here, you have to notice yet
that the option is labels.
So we label once again the basal,
the apical, and the axon trees.
And if we do that,
we get three different boxplots.
What is interesting here is that
you can see the axons
have way many more outliers
than the basal or the apical dendrites
which means that the distribution
of the dendrites is much more constrained.
So the section lengths of the dendrites
are much more uniform than the axonal ones.