Hello, and welcome to my part.
I’m Lida Kanari.
I’m doing a PhD in Blue Brain Project
and I’m gonna talk about
neuronal morphologies.
In the first part,
I’m gonna talk about
the different parts
of neuronal morphologies.
How you can visualize them
using an open source tool called
NeuroEM that is available in GitHub.
How you can extract
basic morphometrics,
and then in the second part,
I’m gonna talk about
some statistical tests
that you can run on those morphometrics
in order to compare
different morphologies.
This is a neuronal tree
which consists of a soma and a neurite.
As you can see,
we have different points on the tree.
So the blue points annotate the tips
or the terminations as we call them.
The black points
are the bifurcation points
where two different branches emerge,
and the red points
are just continuations.
So a pair of points defines a segment.
If we put all the segments
between two bifurcations together,
we generate a section.
A section is a fundamental compartment
of a neuron, so we’re gonna use
those fundamental compartments
in order to understand
the morphology.
First, we’re gonna study the global
features of the morphology.
So those features are length,
the area, or the volume.
In order to compute the total length,
we take the distance between two points
and we sum up this distance
for all of the points of the tree.
If we wanna compute the area
or the volume, we need to use
the diameters of the points.
So we generate a truncated cone,
something like that,
and so we sum up the area
or the volume throughout the whole tree.
Some other global features
is the count the number
of bifurcations or terminations.
And then we can go into details
and study the section structure.
So for the sections,
we can do exactly the same.
Sum up the lengths, or the areas,
or the volume of the sections,
but now, we also have
some other types of features:
those are the angles.
The angles can be computed locally
and those are called
local bifurcation angles,
or remotely at the end
of the two sections
and those are called remote.
Then we can compute the branch order
and the branch order is defined
from the start of the tree
and onwards.
So for each bifurcation,
you add one more branch order.
So the first one would be one,
and then the second one would be two,
three, and so on.
About the tortuosity,
we are interested
on what happens within the section.
So this section
is one that wiggles a lot,
and that has a very high tortuosity.
But a section that is completely straight
has a tortuosity equal to one
because the end-to-end distance
and the path distance are the same.
So the tortuosity
is defined as the radial distance
between its two points
by the path distance.
And now another measurement
that is very important
is the asymmetry of the tree.
So we can compute that
at each bifurcation point again,
and the asymmetry defines
how many branches go on the right,
and how many branches go on the left.
So a tree that is completely symmetric
would be something like that,
and a tree that would be
completely asymmetric
would be something like that.
So all those types of measurements
are fundamentally important
for the anatomy of the neuron.
And we’re gonna use NeuroEM
in the first tutorial
in order to get all those features.