Welcome everybody to
my part of this course.
I will be speaking today,
I have a big challenge today
to introduce to you the nerve cells,
in particular the electrical activity
of these nerve cells.
My name is professor Idan Segev
from the Hebrew University
and what I will do today is
actually start with a motivation
just to introduce
the electrical activity
of the brain,
I'm sure you all know
that the brain is
an electrical device
not only, but certainly it is
we can record electrical
activity from the brain
for example,
by EEG from the skull
but today we’re interested to
understand much more about
the elementary units,
the nerve cells
that generate this electrical activity.
So, I will start with
the introduction of the neuron
as this is the elementary unit building
block of the nervous system
any nervous system.
I will introduce the structure
of the neuron first
and then I will go to show
you that this neuron
has a special electrical activity,
very unique. Actually there is
two type of electrical activity.
One type is called
the spike, generated in
one part of the nerve cell,
and the other type of
the electrical activity is
called the synaptic potential.
one part of the nerve cell,
and the other type of
the electrical activity is
called the synaptic potential.
So, basically the same neuron,
the same nerve cell carries
two types of electrical activity,
the spike in the axon
and the synaptic potential
in the dendrite,
we shall try along the course
here to see how does one
mathematically model these
two electrical phenomenon
the spike and the synapses.
And so, I will show you later
in the next part that what
underlies this electrical activity
is charged ion channels
that cross the membrane
of the nerve cell
and this crossing of
the nerve cell’s
membrane generates
electrical activity.
Then I will go to a model,
a mathematical model generated
by Hodgkin and Huxley,
published in 1952
a wonderful work where
by a set of equations
that we shall introduce here
summarize in a compact way
the mathematics of the spike.
So, we can today use
Hodgkin-Huxley mathematically
in the computer to replicate,
and you will see it,
to replicate the activity of
the spike following this
monumental work of
Hodgkin-Huxley
before the World War
published later in 1952.
And then I’ll go to the other signal:
the synaptic potentials.
These are the signals that
run in another region
of the neuron in dendrites,
and I will show you how
to model
synaptic potentials.
And then there will be
the challenge to connect the two.
I have to show you how
the synaptic potential
is generated locally in the dendrites,
propagate from
I have to show you how
the synaptic potential
is generated locally in the dendrites,
propagate from
the side of origin to the other
side of the neuron to the axon.
And so, I will try to combine
these two signals
as the neuron does
and show you eventually
how the input
the synaptic input,
the synaptic potentials
eventually together,
many of them generate a spike
in the other part of the neuron,
in the axon.
So, this will be a summary
kind of lesson or session
whereby I will take the modeling
of synaptic potentials
I will show you how these
synaptic potentials bombard
one part of the neuron,
the dendrite
and generate in
the other part
of the neuron
an electrical signal
another electrical
signal called the spike.
So, this is the plan for today.