I want to start with the motivation.
So here is the motivation, I could
give you many, many examples
because as you all know,
all that we do basically
like myself speaking to you now
feeling a certain feeling,
moving my hand
recognizing a face,
but also becoming sick,
neurological sickness, is reflected
by an electrical activity
in a particular region in the brain.
And I want to show you
a very dramatic example
of a Parkinsons patient.
So what you see here on the screen,
is the scheme of a patient that is normal.
And the red electrode here is just
showing you a recording from this site.
So this is a site, it's called
Basal Ganglia, it's deep into the brain.
And in this region, in a normal
Non-Parkinsonian patient,
a monkey or a human patient,
you will see this electrical
activity on the right top part
which we call normal activity.
So you see now electrical activity
of three nerve cells,
individual nerve cells, we call that
in vivo, in the living behaving brain.
And you can see a phenomena
that is very, very special
actually to nerve cells.
So if I just highlight
what you see
there is this voltage on the Y-axis,
and in the X-axis you will see time.
So what I'm now doing, I'm now
syncing, so to speak
the electrical activities,
so each blip here is a spike.
We shall study more later
how to model the spikes.
So each one is a spike, it's about
100 millivolts, a tenth of a volt.
And in this particular top cell,
if I would put a loudspeaker
I would hear something like
the tuk-tuk-tuk-tuk-tuk-tuk.
Stop-tuk-tuk-tuk-tuk-tuk-tuk.
So this cell fires spikes
in this particular rhythm,
as I just sang for you.
The other cell, the middle one
is much more rigorous
so it fires more strongly.
Again spikes:
tu-tu-tu-tu-tu-tu.
And the third cell, the lower one
is firing spikes less frequently
for tuk(pause)-tuk-tuk-tuk-
(pause)tuk-tuk.
So this is a normal activity of
a normal Non-Parkinsonian brain.
But see what happens when this
particular region of the brain
the Basal Ganglia
become Parkinsonian.
Now you see the activity
of three cells in the bottom trays.
But these three cells, as you can
immediately see
have a different
pattern of activity.
So for example, let's look
at the top one.
You can see that the first activity
is a burst of a set of spikes
So tu-tu-tu stop tu-tu-tu
stop tu-tu-tu stop.
So this cell is now not anymore
like the previous one in a normal case
it fires rather sporadically
and randomly, so to speak
here there is a very clear
pattern of activity.
A burst, stop.
Something or the other of 5
or 10 bursts of spikes per second.
The second cell, the middle cell,
and the top cell
are actually doing similar things,
surprisingly.
There are other replica,
they are similar
in terms of their activity
to the first cell.
So all the three cells
are doing tu-tu-tu-tu-tu stop.
Tu-tu-tu-tu-tu stop.
The whole network is now
synchronized, firing together
in a bursty fashion, firing, stop,
firing, stop.
The output of this activity
is the Parkinsonian tremor.
So the tremor of the Parkinsonian
is the reflection
of this particular state
of the brain
in this particular region of the brain.
This is one example of many
that I could show you
that any behavior
in health and disease
is reflected by a particular
music of activity
if you want to call it this way,
an orchestra of activity
of many, many, many millions
of cells.
You only saw three here that fire
in a particular pattern
And this particular pattern stands
or reflects or codes
for a particular state of the brain,
sleep or awake, happy or sad,
involved with the face recognition
or not, and so forth...
Or sick with Parkinson's
or with Alzheimer's
or with other
devastating diseases.
So the importance of understanding
the electrical activity in the brain
comes from the fact that we know
that any state
in the brain is reflected by
a particular activity
like in the case of Parkinson's.
I'll show you even more,
dramatic, how
electrical is the brain by
the following example.
So in the last 20 years or so,
investigators, scientists,
and physicians, decided to do
something to the Parkinsonian brain.
What they tried to do
is to intervene electrically
with the erroneous activity
that I showed you before
just now in the Parkinsonian case.
where you have the synchronus rhythm
of activity
which is reflected by this
Parkinsonian disease.
And they tried to intervene
into this region
by taking a battery,
Like the battery that people use
for pacemaking the heart,
but in this cas instead of connecting
the wire of the battery to the heart,
pacemaking the heart,
the wire now goes, as you can see
here, up top and then into the brain.
Into this particular region
of the brain.
It's a simple operation, relatively.
It is called Deep Brain Stimulation
because then you can activate
the battery, you can see here
a set of stimuli
a set of pulses generated
by the battery.
The physician can manipulate
the frequency and the amplitude
and so forth, of this stimulation.
And now you stimulate the brain
of the Parkinsonian patient.
So you stimulate deep brain
by electrical activity
coming from the battery.
And I want to show you
a huge success, a great success
of repairing the Parkinsonian
disease
or the symptoms of
the Parkinsonian disease
by intervening directly
with the electrical activity
of the brain
of the Parkinsonian patient.
So first, I want to show you an
example of this devastating disease.
This is a very serious disease
of a Parkinsonian patient
at Hadassah Medical School,
before the deep brain stimulation,
the operation.
So here it is.
you can see the difficulties
in generating a movement,
in balancing the body.
And very soon you will see the
difficulty in generating
a particular rhythm
like I am doing now
fast, or slow,
or even slower.
This is something that a typical
Parkinsonian patient
cannot do, because he has
this rhythm generated
in the Basal Ganglia, and this
particular rhythm
deterministically dictates
the activity, the tremor
and the patient cannot really
generate his or her own
rhythm of, let's say,
hand movement
because the brain region
really dictates the movement.
So you can see now, for example
how difficult it is for the patient
to do something as simple
as we typically do
if we are not sick with Parkinson's.
So this is a Parkinsonian patient.
I'm sure you saw cases like these,
that's one case.
Now I want to show you the same
person, the same patient
after being operated, and after
being injected with electrical current
Deep Brain Stimulation
into this region
And see really a miraculous success.
So here it is.
So this is the same patient,
now getting the stimuli.
This electrical stimulus from
the battery into his head.
You can see that he is walking
almost normally, wonderful.
And he is really balanced, and you
can see very shortly
that he can do this hand rhyth
that I just mentioned before.
So in many ways he doesn't have
Parkinson's anymore.
It's not totally true, but he can
drive now,
He can go to the grocery now,
he can live.
And of course, when you stop
the stimulation
it's gone, he's back to becoming
Parkinsonian.
So, it's a symptomatic treatment,
very successful.
You can see he's now balanced
and so on.
So this is just another
very clear example
of how our brain
is an electrical device
generating
it's own electrical activity
When everything is fine,
then everything is fine,
we shall call it normal.
But when something goes wrong
there is a disease.
When something changes,
then I go to sleep in that activity.
When I am creative,
when I am in love
when I am sad
there is electrical activity
that changes in a particular
region and reflects
these states of the brain:
love, suffering,
Parkinson's, hand movement,
creativity
the feeling of free will
and so forth.
So this is why it is so absolutely
essential to understand
what makes the brain active
electrically.
That's exactly what I'm trying
to explain to you today.