So now we are trying to
acquainted ourselves
very briefly with the nerve
cell, with a neuron.
So, of course one cannot
speak about neurons
without speaking about
these two great geniuses:
Ramon y Cajal, Spaniard,
and Camillo Golgi, the Italian
both got a Nobel prize in 1906
as you can see here
for recognizing
the structure of neurons.
They really developed methods
and used the microscope
in order to recognize
to decipher who are
these building blocks
of the nervous system?
Who are these neurons?
By the way, the term
neuron came later
and they did not invent
these nerve cells.
So, you can see here
a particular type of nerve cell
we call it pukinji cell
from one region
of the brain,
from the cerebellum
and you can see Ramon y Cajal
was a really good drawer
a painter, an artist,
you can see here a retina
where it also has nerve cells
and you can see
another region here
which is a cortex, which is
another type of nerve cells.
All really look like trees,
sophisticated trees
we shall talk about the particular
structure in a second
but you can see
that every region
in the nervous system,
it doesn’t matter if
you look at the retina
or at the cortex,
or dip inside the brain
a simple animal, a slug,
a mouse, a monkey
an elephant,
a human... is built from
these elementary
building blocks.
So morphologically
they are very beautiful
they look like trees,
we shall later, of course,
try to understand
the electrical properties
of these cells,
but now I am only talking about
the structure of these cells.
And Ramon y Cajal was in
some sense a visionary,
in many senses visionary, and,
just by looking at the anatomy
as you can see here a drawing,
he was speculating that
there is a signal or signals
that run through this anatomy,
as you can see here a drawing,
he was speculating that
there is a signal or signals
that run through this anatomy,
here is one signal denoted
by an arrow
so this is a Ramon y Cajal
arrow here,
and he wants to say that
his part of the neuron
which is call an axon, yes,
this part of the neuron,
which is called axon, there
are signals running
in a sort of speak in this direction,
and then somehow
and Ramon y Cajal
had no idea how
the signal from the axon jumps,
sort of speak
transferred here
in the dendritic tree
of the next neuron.
So, I just mentioned two
parts of the neuron.
The axon, which is the output
device of neurons,
and we know today that’s
the case indeed,
and the dendritic tree
you see the more
darker part here
that receives input from
the axon somehow
and then the signal
continues to flow
this red arrow
until it reaches this region
in the axon of this cell number
B and from this axon there
is somehow another jump or
connection through this arrow
into the dendrites of cell C.
So Ramon y Cajal envisioned
some signal flow
that flow from the axon
into the dendrites
and from the dendrites
back into the axon of the cell
where the dendrites
belong to it.
So we already said
that neuron
is built from
the dendritic tree
I will mention it
a lot of times
a cell body
and an axon.
So these are the three
parts of the neuron
that we shall discuss later on,
but already Ramon Y Cajal
just by seeing
the morphology thought
that there must be some
kind of signals running
on top of this
particular anatomy.
And we know today,
and I will convince you later
that indeed axons
are the sending
the output device
of neurons
and the dendrites
are the input
receiving devices
of the neuron
and I will show you
that actually
the input is actually
the one signal:
the synaptic potential, and
the output is another signal:
the action potential,
or the spike.
Ramon y Cajal
noticed something
with his primitive
microscope:
he was already
able to see
that if you zoom into
the dendritic tree here
of a cell, by the way he used
to call this particular cell
which is the majority
of the cell type
in our cortex in
the mammalian cortex
it’s called the pyramidal cell.
In this particular cell, when you
zoom in into the dendrites
you see here a little
branch taken from this
region of the tree
and if you look very carefully
you will see that this branch
is built from these
little protrusions,
these little branchlets,
very small branchlets
something of the order of
the thousandth of a millimeter
a micrometer long
and these are called
the dendritic spines.
I will show you later that
these dendritic spines
are the site for synaptic
connection between
the axon and the dendrite.
So, Ramon y Cajal
already saw
more than a hundred years ago,
that actually
which is a nice
and sad story that
in his death bed Ramon y Cajal
just before he died
he drew spines in
a little notebook
and he wrote down that
we must pay attention
future scientists
should pay
attention to
these little spines
because they
are very important,
they must have a very
important function
and we shall show you later
that he was absolutely right.
So, remember, the neuron
is built from dendrites
cell body, axons, and dendrites
of some cell types
have these little protrusions
that we call dendritic spines.
And indeed, if you look
at many cell types
you can see
the dendritic spines
on this piece
of the dendrite
or on this piece
on this piece of
the dendrite
and here you see,
by the way
a very nice example of an axon,
so this is an axon here
sorry, this is an axon,
coming very close
but of course, we don’t know
if it makes or doesn’t make
a connection with
this dendrite.
I will show later that
the connection is
on the spines
in this particular case.
So dendritic spines
are very important.
Not all the cells
have spines
so there are
spiny nerve cells
and smooth nerve cells,
so the dendritic tree
does not have these spines,
but we’re not going to
talk about this detail
this is just to show you that
the dendritic spines
are very important for
some types of cells
especially these
pyramidal cells
which Ramon y Cajal liked
to call psychic cells
because he believed
we are psychic, psychological
behaving people
and that this cell is a part
of this capability of us
to be psychological behavioral,
emotional, and so forth.
Just to give you
some numbers
just dimensions,
average dimensions,
of course there are
big nerve cells
small nerve cells, long axons,
short axons, and so forth
but just a “ball park”,
just a region
so if you ask what is
the total length of dendrites
so this is
a branched tree
and let’s say if I take this
tree and make one
long wire out of it
it will be on the order
of something like
10 to 15mm long totally.
But of course, from the body
to the dendrite tip
is one millimeter,
but because there
are all these branches,
it becomes long.
The total area of dendrite
is something of this order
20000 micrometers squared,
in terms of the of
the area of the dendrites,
you have on a spiny neuron
like the pyramidal cell,
I showed you here on the left
something of the order of
8000, 10000
in humans we have sometimes
30000 spines per single neuron.
The dimension of
the spine is on
the order of one
square micrometer
there about 10000
synaptic inputs
connections into
a single neuron.
So, if I’m a single neuron,
I am receiving on my dendrites
something of the order of 10000
synapses, connections,
and we shall see how to model
these synapses soon
and the axon could be
a very long process
connected this region
to the brain to this region
with a single cell
and it can be also
something very local.
So, it could go from
a few millimeters
or less locally to a very
long few centimeter long.
So, this is just ballpark dimensions,
just for the introduction
so that you will
know intimately
more intimately
the structure of the neuron.
This is one beautiful example,
it’s coming from Spain
from a group there headed
by Xavier de Felipe in Madrid
reconstructing
human neurons.
So, you can see that the neurons
I showed you before from
Ramon y Cajal and Golgi
came from many animals
it was a mouse, and a fly,
and other types of animals
that they reconstructed
neurons from.
Here’s is an example of
a neuron from a human.
So, this is a pyramidal cell,
all this is a pyramidal cell
from a human cortex
post mortem,
and here on the left you can
see a piece of a dendrite
taking somewhere
from here, or from here
some locally and you can
see that this dendrite
like I showed you before for
mouse, rat, and so forth
also have these
dendritic spines.
So, look at this
one for example.
It’s a dendritic spine,
it’s dendritic spine.
Many, many dendritic spies,
as I said before
in human it could range up
until 30000, 25000 spines
and each of these spines
receive an input
a synaptic input from
a nearby axon of another cell.
Just to show you
that a neuron
is a neuron in general
it has soma, it has
dendrites, a cell body
and then what’s an axon
and in many cases for
their spiny neurons
the dendrites are absolutely
covered by these
little protrusions
these dendritic spines
they are very, very important
for the generation
and the connection
between...
the generation of
the synaptic potential
and the connection between
one nerve to the other.
Just before summarizing
the neuron introduction
the structure aspect
of the neuron
you can see now
a reconstructed
neuron whereby
you see the dendritic
tree in green
so this is the dendritic
tree here,
the green part,
you can see
the axonal branching
so the axons is really
branch, and branch,
here’s a local
branching of this axon
coming from the same cell,
so the axon comes up
and then branch,
branch, branch
and occupies all this region,
it’s an axonal tree
and in this axonal tree
you see many, many
many white dots,
white spots.
These are called
axonal boutons
I will show you
later that this is
the pre-synaptic
side in the axon
where the transmitter is
located in these boutons
and this transmitter,
which is a chemical,
is the element that
enables the communication,
which is in this case
chemical, between
the axon of one cell
to the dendrite
of another cell.
Just to summarize, a neuron
is a really sophisticated,
also structurally,
but later we shall see also
that physiologically,
electrically,
very sophisticated electrical
and morphological element
it is in a branching structure,
both the dendrites
which are more local,
and the axons
which could be very global,
and go elsewhere
between one
region to another
or from my brain,
the motor region into my foot
a long axon, but you
can see that this
is a very complicated structure
and on the top of this
complicated structure
this structure knows how to
generate electrical signals
and propagate these signals
from one region to another
and connect through these
signals one cell to the other.
So here it is.
The structural aspect
of the neuron.