Okay now,
let’s continue
looking at the neuron
as an electrical device.
So, here is a neuron again.
You can see in dark
the dendritic tree
you can see in light red
the axonal tree of
this pyramidal neuron
and you can see
actually if you
look carefully on
the dendritic tree
you can see these boutons,
that I’ve just mentioned
these little spots.
Another one, another one,
another one.
Sometimes ten thousand
of these spots...
as I mentioned these are
the pre-synaptic sites in axon
that will connect
to some dendrites
that are not shown here.
So this is a neuron.
Now I want to highlight
for you by drawing them
the two types
of elementary signals,
the basic signals that the
neurons carry.
So, let’s assume that I record
from inside of a dendrite
so this electrode now
is supposed to impale
deep into the dendrite,
we shall discuss this
inter-cellular recording,
so this is a cell in my brain now,
or in your brain
and now I’m drawing for you
what are the electrical signals
that we call the synaptic
potentials here
that you would see.
In vivo,
in the living behaving brain.
So, this will be a potential and
you would see things like that.
Something goes up,
something goes down
up, down, up, down.
You see these
voltage fluctuations
so this is voltage
and this is on the range
between 1mV to 10mV.
These are the synaptic potentials,
so this you’ll see in dendrites
these little bumps of voltage
of potential, small ones,
some are going up,
some are going down,
and in time you will see some
kind of noisy voltage trace.
These are synaptic potentials,
they are built of many elements
we shall talk about this
particular one element:
the synaptic potential,
a single synaptic potential.
Here you see many of them.
And later we shall also see
that these many of them
are built of these two types.
One is an excitatory
synaptic potential
and the other is the inhibitory
synaptic potential,
now superimposed
one on top of the other.
So that’s what
happens in dendrites.
This is one type of signal,
the synaptic potential.
The other type of signal you
will see typically in the axon
so now if I record from the axon,
from inside the axon
I will see something like that,
I will see this noise
that I showed you before,
the synaptic noise, or voltage,
and from time to time
you see this
kind of very big
phenomenon, the spike.
Noise, spike, spike, spike.
So these are the spikes
and they, sort of speak
ride on top of
synaptic potentials
that are recorded
in the axon
actually in the axon you
mostly see only the spike
but if you recorded
the beginning of the axon here
you will see also
the synaptic potentials.
So you can see that,
somehow the synaptic potentials
are underlying the spike,
this little voltage fluctuations
are underlying the spike here
and from time to time,
you get this big thing.
The spike, which is
about 100mV
so a tenth of
a volt in amplitude.
So to summarize, you saw
two types of electrical activity
in the same neuron.
In the dendrites you saw
what we call synaptic potentials,
small ones
maybe 1mV, 10mV, small ones,
and in the axon
near the cell body,
you will see both of them
and occasionally these
big signals called spikes.
So, these are two
different signals
running in two
different regions.
Dendrites carry synaptic potentials,
axons carry spikes
or action potentials,
as they are used to be called,
so synaptic potentials
and action potentials.
It’s an action,
suddenly big
but we shall call it spike,
now the action potential
will be called the spike,
and the synaptic potential
and what my
mission is in this
part of the course
is to develop
the mathematical models
to describe these
two signals mathematically
and then simulate them
in the computer
so that we should be able to
mathematically simulate
a neuron
and mathematically simulate
the connection
between neuron, the synapses and
the synaptic potential
generated by this connection,
so that eventually after knowing
how to simulate a single
neuron electrical activity
we will be able to simulate
network activity
and that’s what we want to
achieve in this course.
You will be able to simulate,
not only a neuron
not only a synapse,
not only a spike
not only a synaptic potentials
but the activity in large
connected network of neurons.
So now let me show you
just as an illustration
how does the spike
in the living brain,
how does the spike really
not only look like,
but sound like
so, the experimental connected
each spike into the loudspeaker
so whenever there would be
a spike of 100mV
you would hear
“tak, tak, tak, tak”
like I did for the Parkinson
case where I did
on my own voice
“tak, tak, tak, tak”
experimentally like to hear
the spikes
by connecting in vivo
in the behaving brain,
while recording from
the axon and listen to the spikes,
so they know now that
the cell now fires spikes.
So let’s hear the firing
of spikes in vivo
in the axon of a real
in this case,
pyramidal celll.
Let's hear it.
Okay so, this “tak, tak, tak”,
these are the spikes
these white little vertical
lines are the spikes
And you can see that this cell
fires a particular set of spikes
and this is the footprint,
the electrical footprint
of this prototypical neuron.
As I said before, every neuron
goes “ra, tak, tak, tak”
this is the typical activity of
the spiking activity in the axon
and actually in the cell body
of the neurons in general.
One interesting thing,
and I want to finalize this part
of general introduction of
the electrical activity of neurons
by showing you that
different cell types that
are morphologically different
are sometimes
morphologically different.
So here you see a diversity of
the type of morphological cells
you see this cell which
is a bigger one
and now I don’t want to give
names to the different cells
but the different cells
are nomenclature
for different cell types in terms of
the morphology, and so forth
but this is one cell type here,
and this is another cell type there
and in this case,
it’s a morphological type
when I say type,
I say morphological type
so this is another
morphological type.
So, these are like different
trees in the jungle.
One is bigger,
one is more branched
one is less branched,
and so forth
but notice something
interesting here
that these different
morphologies
when you record from
these particular cells
you also see that they fire
different patterns of spikes.
So this cell tends to
fire this pattern
of spikes when stimulated
and this cell fires this
pattern of spikes
so you see you can
think of each cell
as an electrical instrument
firing spikes at the axon
but the structure
of these spikes
is sometimes
“ta, ta, ta, ta”
like in this case
sometimes “ta   , ta   , ta”
sometimes the cell is a burster
“ta, ta, ta, ta, stop,
ta, ta, ta, ta, stop"
a third burst “ta, ta, ta”,
and so forth
so they also have not only
a structural phase
but also the electrical phase
they are different in their
electrical capabilities.
We don’t know exactly how
many types of electrical cells
we have in the brain today,
but it is hundreds of types
probably of morphological types
and maybe some tens
or so electrical types
at least in the cortex,
we know more today.
But I wanted to tell
you the main thing
that the spike is a spike.
It doesn’t matter
if it’s this cell
on the left or this
cell on the right
they generate very
similar spikes
so the elementary beat,
the elementary unit
of a spike is something
universal for many cell types
all cell types are very similar,
this 100mV amplitude phenomenon
but in terms of structure
in the spikes
like in the bar code, sometimes
it’s structured like this
sometimes it’s structured like
that for different cell types
that are physiologically different
but all use the spike which is
a universal signal
for nerve cells
but in a different
pattern of firing.
And this is of course
very important
to generate the music
the philharmonic huge
orchestra of many cells
firing together now
when I’m talking to you.
So they are diverse
morphologically
they use the same
spike as a unit
but they build these
patterns of spikes
from individual spikes like
a bar code in the grocery store
but notice that in
the grocery store
you have different widths of lines
some of them are thicker,
some of them are thinner
and in this case the bar code
is built of same width of spikes
so the amplitude is 100mV,
and the duration
of these “tak”
and disappearing
“tak” and disappearing
is about a millisecond
a thousandth of a second.
So this is the electrical activity,
so I’ve introduced
a thousandth of a second.
So this is the electrical activity,
so I’ve introduced
to you now the electrical
activity of neurons
and I want to proceed into
trying to model these
signals mathematically.
So, let’s summarize.
I told you,
you should think
of a neuron as build
of three main regions
the cell body,
which is the chemical, molecular
genetic machinery,
a dendritic tree
that is about one millimeter long,
sometimes shorter
but extending to
one millimeter
but it can be long if you spread
it up until a few millimeters
ten or twenty millimeters,
and an axonal tree
that also comes
from the cell body
at least in mammals,
and then branch
branch, branch,
it could be very long
at least in mammals,
and then branch
branch, branch,
it could be very long
centimeter sometimes meters,
or very short locally
I told you that the dendrites
carry synaptic potentials
whereas the axons carry spikes
so these two
separate signals
appear in separate regions.
In the axon
you won’t find
synaptic potential
but rather spikes
and in the dendrites typically,
although recently we’ve also found out
that dendrites could
also carry spikes
but typically,
dendrites carry synaptic potential
that dendrites could
also carry spikes
but typically,
dendrites carry synaptic potential
and I will show you
that they are
different in
their propery
and they are modeled
different mathematically.
Also, I just ended
by showing you that
the brain is built from
many different cell types
or neuron types
both morphological types
and also electrical types
so they have different morphology
and different
physiological properties
but basically
all of them carry
both synaptic potentials,
in the dendrites
no matter if it’s a big dendrite
or a small dendrite
there you will find
synaptic potential
and if in the axon,
no matter if it’s a long axon
or a short axon,
you will find the spikes.