So here we come to great explorers,
to great investigators
the Hodgkin and Huxley.
So now, I'm going to explain
to you, slowly,
the mathematical model
of Hodgkin and Huxley,
you see both of them here,
that really got there for their
success in understanding the spike
what they used to
call the "action potential"
we even use this term today
so for understanding
the mathematics of the spike
what is the underlying
mechanism first
and how do I describe this mechanism
in order to understand
mathematically
mathematically describe
the spike.
What Hodgkin and Huxley did,
and for that they got a Nobel prize
in 1962, is the following.
First of all they found
very, very convenient preparation
the squid that you
see in the middle.
This is a very useful preparation
because this particular animal
has a very unique axon.
This is now an axon,
here is an axon...
here is an axon
of the squid,
it's called the squid giant axon
it is giant, it is from here to here,
it's a very thick axon,
in our brain, our axon are very thin
something of the order of a 1μm
a thousandth of a millimeter,
in diameter very thin
but in the squid you have
thick big axons
the squid giant axon,
that's what it's called.
Giant to the level that
it's a half of a millimeter
and this enabled Hodgkin and Huxley
actually for the first time
to directly record the electrical
activity from the inside
of this axon, because they succeeded
to penetrate with a wire
into the axon and really record
the electrical activity
or the voltage difference
between the inside and the outside
directly in this giant
axon of the squid.
As I said, what Hodgkin
and Huxley did
they succeeded to take
the squid axon here and put
a wire inside an axon here, so this
is this wire I spoke about there,
this is an electrode recording
the voltage from within
comparing it to the voltage outside.
So they really measured
the voltage drop
the voltage difference between
the inside and outside.
Before I defined
the membrane voltage
as the difference between
the inside and outside
across the membrane
I said that at rest
the voltage is -70mV
or something like that,
inside versus outside.
But what happens in
the squid giant axon?
They used a stimulation,
they stimulated the axon
because without stimulation
it would sit at rest
something like -70mV at rest,
W=without any perturbation,
but now they stimulate here
the axon by making
the inside more positive
than it was before.
So instead of -70mV,
the move the voltage to -50mV
or -40mV, so the injected current
inside of the cell.
And here's what they found.
When you do this
you depolarize
we call it depolarize,
you make the inside more positive
than the rest, so instead
of being -70mV
you depolarize the cell
to a given level
and suddenly you get this "boom",
this white signal,
the spike
it behaves on its own.
We just brought
the membrane to this region
to a given threshold,
voltage threshold
and suddenly there's
a huge phenomenon
something as I mentioned
of the order of 100mV
so it's an all-or-none
phenomenon.
It happens
or does not happen,
and when it happens it has
this very prototypical shape.
A 100mV or so in amplitude
about 1ms in duration
and then it's gone.
This was the first inter-cellular
direct recording by Hodgkin and Huxley
actually in 1939.
They saw the signal.
But of course seeing
the signal on its own
does not mean that you understand
the origin, the mechanism
the underlying the signal.
And that's where the genius
of Hodgkin and Huxley came
because they systematically
analyzed in four papers
actually more, but in 1952,
there are four papers, A, B, C
and then the D paper,
1952 D, is the theoretical
the mathematical paper
explaining the signal in full.
Very beautifully, very compactly,
a very beautiful mathematical model
for understanding the spike.
So, first they showed experimentally
that this is indeed
and all-or-none,
zero and one
phenomenon.
So look, if they stimulated,
if they shift the voltage
from -70mV, which is here,
by let's say a few millivolts
let's say, to here
they got some voltage response,
which decays.
So this is another attempt,
sub-threshold, it decays.
But if you reach enough voltage
if you depolarize
if you shift the membrane potential
from -70mV enough,
something of the order of 20mV
more positive than -70mV,
let's say between -70mV
you shift the voltage
by injecting the current
into the cell, positive current
inside the cell
then you suddenly see
this phenomenon rising.
So this is an action potential.
And if you inject it even stronger,
inside the cell
you get another action potential.
But all of this action potential
have the same shape
and when they appear,
they appear in full.
there is no half-action potential,
or a third-action potential.
It's an all or none
phenomenon.
So it's either sub-threshold,
where you don't get a spike
or it's super-threshold,
when you get a full spike.
And again, the threshold is more
positive than the resting potential.
So the spike starts from
-70mV or -50mV
and then it goes
100mV high and then
it disappears after
1ms, 2ms, or 3ms.
So that's the all-or-none
property of the spike.
It's a very interesting signal
as I said, it appears in axons
and this was very lucky
for Hodgkin and Huxley to
have this squid giant axon
where they could record from
the inside and from the outside
and can manipulate
ion concentrations
which I'll show
you in a second
but they could study
the spike directly
in this squid's giant axons
and amazingly the same mechanism
of spike generation in axon
of the squid giant axon
is also true from most of
the axons we know today.
So this basic mechanism that
Hodgkin and Huxley found
is really universal
for axons of many types
including the axons of the different
cell types in our brain
that also generate what
we call today a sodium spike.
I will tell you in a second
why it's a sodium spike.
Okay, so we came to the point
where we now want to go into
the Hodgkin and Huxley model.
So before I just show you
the description of the spike
how does it look like,
it appears, it disappears
it has a threshold,
it is an all-or-none phenomenon.
But now how do you measure
the underlying membrane mechanism
that enabled
the spikes to be generated?
So that's the beautiful trick
that Hodgkin and Huxley were using.
They did actually use two tricks,
one is called the Voltage clamp
here
and the other one
is called the space clamp.
So their idea was to
take this wire, a long wire
into the axon and so
the axon becomes
iso-potential, because of this
wire which is highly conductive
there is no voltage drop
between this location
and this location
so the whole elongated axon
becomes electrically very compact
because of this axial wire
but also they use a voltage clamp
and that's the ingenious trick
that was not actually
only devised by them
but also by others,
and the idea was to
try to clamp, to determine
the voltage between the two
sides of the membrane,
to force the two sides
of the membrane
to have a fixed voltage:
a voltage clamp.
Why did they want to do it?
Because they want to measure
what currents flow through
the membrane when I clamp
the membrane to a given voltage
let's say, now I depolarize
the membrane by 20mV
from -70mV to -50mV,
and fix it like this.
And then measure which
are the currents that flow
through the membrane when
I depolarize the membrane by 20mV
30mV, 40mV, and so forth.
So I don't allow the spike
to occur anymore
because I've fixed via
voltage clamp
the membrane voltage
between the two sides
of the membrane,
I don't allow it to change
and in order to do it,
I need to develop a whole
feedback system, so whenever
the spike,
wants to start to be initiated,
I block it, I do no allow it
because I want to fix the voltage
by injecting a negative current
into the membrane to really
balance the voltage into my
voltage clamp pre-determined value.
So I control the spike,
so to speak
by fixing the voltage between
the two sides of the membrane
by injecting negative currents
through my feedback system.
And then I can really measure
what current I should inject
in order to fix the voltage between
the two sides of the membrane
to be fixed.
And that's the voltage clamp idea.
It enables to uncover the ion
currents that flow behind
below the spike,
so to speak.
So I've explained to you
what is the space clamp
and I've explained to you
what is the voltage clamp
and I've told you that this
electric feedback system
enables to control the voltage
very rapidly
so the voltage between the two
sides of the membrane will be fixed.
What did they find
using this technique?
So here's what they found:
They found that, when you
voltage clamp the membrane
above a certain level,
so here they started at -60mV
and they jump to 0mV
so this is a 60mV depolarization
and using their feedback system
record which are the underlying
currents during this voltage step,
voltage clamp,
they see something interesting.
There is a very
fast early inward current
and a late outward current.
So they fixed the voltage,
they don't change it anymore
so it's a fixed voltage clamp
and they measure the current
that needs to be injected
in order to keep
the voltage clamp fixed
and they see that in the membrane,
while doing this voltage clamp
there is first an inward current,
and when I say inward I mean
flowing form the outside
into the inside of the cell,
later they found out
that this is carried by
sodium channels and
if you wait enough time
the current, instead of
flowing into the membrane
into the cell, it flows outside
and this is the outward current
which is carried
by potassium channels
or potassium current.
So this was a very interesting
finding that during voltage clamp
and later of course I will show that
it's also during the spike itself
when you reach the threshold
very early on, after you
reach the threshold
there is an opening of
sodium ion channels
that are open because you
reach a voltage threshold
so these ion channels are
voltage dependent ion channels
we'll talk about this in a second
because you reach
this voltage threshold
very early on,
there is an inward current
of sodium flowing from the outside
to the inside, making the inside
even more positive
during the spike
and a little bit later on,
a few milliseconds later on
you see an outward current,
meaning that the potassium channels
are open carrying current from
inside to outside.
Ok?
So there are these
two separate currents
that underlay voltage change
in the giant squid axon.
The early current which
starts and then then ends
so it activates and inactivates
it activates and then inactivates
very fast and early,
and then later on there is
a current that is activated,
the potassium current is activated
and it lasts as long
as there is a voltage clamp.
So we call the early current
we know now that
the early current is
sodium-transient activated
and inactivated
during the voltage clamp,
and the later current
that activates later
and remains open
remains flowing this
potassium current
remains flowing from inside
to the outside of the membrane
during the voltage clamp.
So these are the two basic currents
that Hodgkin and Huxley found
that underlie
the generation of the spike
in the membrane of
the squid giant axon.
What did they do next?
Next they did voltage clamp
to different levels.
Here is an example of
voltage clamps to different levels.
So from -60 to -40
from -60 to -20, and so forth
so they clamped the membrane
to different levels
and they measured these two
currents that I've mentioned before.
The early sodium current
now reversed just for
the purpose of showing it
but it should have been inward,
it should've been in this direction
in this direction
so this is the early inward current
that is carried by sodium
and this is the late current,
the potassium current
that is late relative to the early
one, during voltage clamp.
So this is what
Hodgkin and Huxley did
they tried to decipher,
to analyze separately
mathematically how
to describe the early current
and how to describe the late current
the potassium current
mathematically.
Because they had
all these measurements
they could fit
mathematical equations
for each one of these currents.
The important thing to know here,
and you already can see it here
is that the currents themselves,
both potassium and sodium
are both voltage dependent,
because you can see
if I change the voltage
I get different currents,
but it's also time dependent
as we said before.
The first one is this sodium,
and it's very important
that the first early current in
voltage clamp is the sodium current
going inward, and this also changes
in time as you get more
depolarization.
So it's for small depolarization,
you get a slower inward current
of sodium
for a larger depolarization,
you'll get a faster sodium current
and also a bigger
sodium current.
So these are currents that
are both voltage and time dependent.
So in principle, I should be able
and that's what Hodgkin and Huxley
tried to do.
To describe the conductance of,
let's say, the potassium
as a function of time
and of membrane voltage.
Similar to the sodium channels.
So this is the sodium conductance
but this conductance depends
both on time and on voltage.
So I should tell you now,
without going into the details
that we know today that in the axons
there are these marvelous, unique
absolutely unique ion channels
that carry potassium and sodium
as we discussed before,
but in this case
these ion channels
that are in the axons
are sensitive to voltage
They are voltage dependent.
So what makes these
channels open and close
is voltage.
They are sensitive to voltage.
These are voltage
dependent ion channels.
That's why I wrote that
the conductance here
of the sodium
is voltage dependent.
It also takes time
for this conductance to open
so it's also time dependent.
So these are very unique channels
they are mostly embedded in
the membrane of the axon
so the axon is absolutely
decorated very densely
with voltage dependance ion channels
both for potassium and sodium
and these channels
are the channels
that enable the generation
of the spike
as I will show you in a second.
So, let's continue with
the Hodgkin and Huxley discovery.
So first of all,
Hodgkin and Huxley
drew this circuit.
Here's the Hodgkin and Huxley
circuit of the squid
giant axon membrane
and as you can see here,
there are these
sodium channels that
are voltage and time dependent,
there are potassium conductances
that are voltage and time dependent,
and there is this thing that
we call Leak conductance
which is the conductance
that is not voltage dependent
these are what we sometimes
call "the passive conductance"
these are all other ion channels,
sodium, potassium, and chloride
that do not depend on voltage.
So these are the two channels,
the potassium and the sodium
that are voltage dependent that
underlie the generation of the spike.
And here you see
the membrane capacitance
which are, as I said,
all the other things
that are not channels,
which can accumulate ions
inside and outside of the membrane.
By the way, in this case
they drew the case upside down
so this is the inside,
so this is the negative part
of the neuron
and this is the outside
which they connected to ground.
And this is the total of the
Hodgkin and Huxley
equation here,
so the current that flows
through the membrane
through this piece
of model membrane here
is a sum of
the capacitative current
so we didn't go into it,
but the capacitative current
is always the capacitant C
multiplied by derivative with time
dV/dt of the voltage
across the membrane
so this is the voltage
across the membrane V
as we discussed before.
So this is a voltage equation here
and it's actually currents,
so the total membrane current here
is the sum of
the capacitance current
the capacitance plus
the sodium current I_Na
you already saw
equation, but in this case
you have this sodium conductance
which is voltage and time dependent.
It's an excitable channel,
it's a voltage dependent channel
similarly to
the potassium current
and also the leak one,
but here it's a mistake, you see
the leak voltage is independent,
so this is I_Leak.
So this is the total current
that flows through the membrane
during the spike.
The question is,
can we use the clamp
and the measurements
they did of the dependence
of membrane currents on voltage,
to now describe
the generation of the spike,
because remember
the spike itself is a voltage change
it's not a voltage clamp,
because it changes
from time to time, changes,
changes, and then goes down
but for each voltage,
we know from the voltage clamp
what are the supposingly
currents
both potassium and sodium,
they go through the membrane
in this voltage,
and then in this voltage
so the voltage clam was a tool
to study the dependence
of this current on voltage
and then use it
to try to mathematically describe
the transient behavior of the spike
using what we learned
from the voltage clamp.
Of course, as they succeeded,
otherwise they wouldn't get
the Nobel prize, because they did
a wonderful work in transforming
from what they learned
form the voltage clamp
into describing the spike.
So here it is.
This is one example of
a voltage clamp experiment
and a mathematical attempt
to capture the current that
they measure,
so the continuous line here
this line
is the theoretical line
and these dots
are the experimental dots
measured by Hodgkin and Huxley
for this particular step
and then they used this equation
to try to describe,
in this case
the conductance of the potassium.
So this is the conductance
of the potassium.
They say that they can fit
very well this particular
experimental result
by describing
the conductance,
so this is again
a function of T and V
yes
by maximal conductance,
so this is a total
conductance of potassium
in a piece of membrane
if everything would've openned,
you would get this
total conductance
of the potassium
multiplied by some
parameter which they call "n"
the activation variable.
And this "n" is a parameter.
that in some sense
it tells you which proportions,
what is the proportion
of the ions available,
potassium ions available
in the membrane that are open.
So "n" goes from 0 to 1.
So if it's zero
there is no conductance
for potassium,
everything is closed
and it's one,
it's the maximal
all the channels are open.
So that's how
Hodgkin and Huxley thought
about the potassium channels,
and they realized that this "n"
this "n" parameter
as I said, it also depends
on voltage
and on time.
So this probability,
or this parameter
between zero and one,
that can be thought of as
probability,
this probability to be open,
the channel probability to be open
depends on voltage,
so the more voltage
depolarization you have
the more probability that
the channel will be open,
but it will also take some time
for this channel to open
and this time dependence
is also voltage dependence.
Ok, so that's the channel.
Here is the complete equation
of Hodgkin and Huxley
you just saw this one.
And now they describe
this parameter "n" here
by two extra additional parameters
αn and βn
these are the rate constances
by which the channel opens
or closes.
So this is the closed
state of the channel
and this is the rate by which
the closed state of the channel
tends to open,
and βn is the rate by which
the open state of the channel
tends to close.
So that's how they describe
this activation function "n"
for the potassium
to depend on these rate functions
of the channel,
like a chemical reaction
either to go towards
the closed state of the channel
or to go towards
the open state of the channel
and this is
the description of this channel
and beta and alpha
are both voltage dependent.
So this is voltage dependent,
and this is voltage independent
and eventually "n", of course,
is both time and voltage dependent.
So that's the Hodgkin and Huxley
equation for the potassium channel.
It has a conductance,
the conductance depends
on this activation variable "n",
and this activation variable n""
depends on the activation rate
of making the closed channel open
Alpha "n", and the activation rate,
activation function
in units of 1 over time,
of making the open channel close.
And as I said,
the α and the β
are both only voltage dependent.
"n" is both time
and voltage dependent.
And now they try to fit
this whole equation,
this hole experimental behavior,
so this is the continuous line here
they are trying to do a good
mathematical approximation
and they found these two
equations both for α
as a function of V,
and for β as a function of V.
These two particular equation
without getting into the details
of why they choose
this particularity equation
they had the intuition of how
this equation should look like
and they fit the numbers
here and here, and so on
and they get a wonderful fit
as you see here
between the experimental results
and the theoretical curve.
So this is sketchuring...
these equations
now capture the behavior
of the potassium current
or the potassium conductance.
They did the same
thing for the sodium
the sodium is more complicated,
here is a voltage clamp experiment
so they clamp it to this voltage,
and to a bigger voltage
and to a larger voltage,
and so forth
and they got this set of curves
and now they are trying to
do the exact same procedure,
like they do for the potassium
separately for sodium.
This is more complicated,
because as discussed before
the sodium first activates
and then inactivates
The sodium first activates
and then, although you continue
to hold the voltage clamp,
it goes down.
So there are two stages,
separate stages
to the sodium channel.
It activates during the polarization
but at the same time
it also starts to inactivate.
So that's what makes
the equation more difficult.
So there is this "m" variable,
which behaves like the "n" variable
but the activation of
the sodium channels
and this "h" variable is
for the inactivation
of the sodium channels,
but in principal
they are absolutely
same equations
with alpha "m" and beta "m",
and alpha "h" and beta "h"
very similar, each one has it's own
prototypical equation
for the description
and here they are for
the α "m" and for the β "m"
so this is the activation
of the sodium channel.
and this is for the inactivation .
So again this is an attempt
by Hodgkin and Huxley
to fit these continuous lines here
continuous line here
are the fit to the experimental
dots using these equations.
Ok, so they use the voltage clamp
in order to get these equations
and now they are trying
to simulate mathematically
all three equations,
actually more than three equations
because you have for
alpha and beta, and so forth
the set of equations together
in order to try to see whether they
can replicate mathematically, capture
the full action potential.
And here is the result.
This is now the circuit
that I mentioned before
of all the channels involved.
These are actually the four
basic Hodgkin and Huxley equations
this is the current equation
depending on the capacitance current
the sodium current, the potassium
current and the Leak current,
and these are three more equations
for the activation of the "m"
of the sodium activation, the
activation of the potassium "n"
and the inactivation
of the sodium "h".
So these are the four basic
Hodgkin and Huxley equations
and now you know
we also have
equations for
the alphas and the betas
for each one of them
separately
using all of these
four equations
plus the equations
for alpha and beta
in a rather old primitive computer,
compared to what we have today,
they succeeded to get
the full action potential.
Here's the first time
you see a simulated
action potential.
So this is the voltage,
the solution for this equation
that I showed you before
is the solution for the voltage.
So here is the voltage solved
by the Hodgkin and Huxley equation
and you see that the voltage
behaves very similarly
to an action potential.
It grows and then it goes down
even bellow the resting potential,
and then it terminates.
But of course they could also
see the underlying mechanism
because they had a model,
for example
you can see that
the conductance of the sodium
is the early conductance
is the one that initiates
the action potential.
Why?
Because very early on when
the action potential starts growing
if you depolarize
the membrane enough
this depolarization very early on
opens sodium channels
sodium starts flowing into the cell
and then charges
the inside of the cell with
positive charge, so the inside
of the cell becomes more positive
and then more sodium
channels are open
more sodium channels are
now carrying sodium charge
into the cell
and the cell becomes more
and more positive inside
and this is
the blowing of the spike.
But later on, the potassium channels
start to open and
potassium channels are later,
but they start to open
this now means that the potassium
escapes from inside to the outside
due to this gradience potassium
leaves the inside of the cell
the potassium ion channels,
and this makes the inside
more negative, more negative meaning
that you end the action potential
and here even more negative
because here there is a lot of
conductance for potassium here
and the sodium almost ended
so now the potassium carries
membrane potential bellow rest
towards the Nernst battery
of the potassium
and then potassium
closes a little bit slowly
and then ends
the complete phenomenon.
So you'll now realize
that the action potential
which actually looks very similar
to the biological action potential
by Hodgkin and Huxley equations,
is a really good description
of the biological
phenomenon that we call spike
or action potential.
So, let me summarize this part.
So as I sad,
the Hodgkin and Huxley
is really a marvelous success
of taking biological measurements,
many years of biological
measurements
of what ions are involved involved
changing the concentration
in sodium and potassium,
but eventually
coming to an equation,
a set of four equations,
with some extra equation to describe
the rate constance, Alpha and Beta,
and then you get
a wonderful description
of this phenomenon
that is called the spike.
We know that the spike
is carried by two ions,
two main ions potassium
and sodium
and that's the main thing
depend on voltage, so these two ions,
the capability of two ions
to flow through the membrane,
depends on particular channels
in the membrane.
Hodgkin and Huxley
used to call them gates
these are gates that are opening
and closing the membrane
and these gates are themselves
voltage dependent.
So you have a phenomenon
that is a voltage phenomenon
the spike, but the voltage
of the spike itself
open the channels,
first early channels
the sodium channels,
which make the spike itself
grow because
the spike in the beginning
insert more and more sodium
channels into the axon
and more and more
of these sodium channels
make the inside more
and more positive
until it blows regeneratively,
we call it
but then later on
the potassium comes in
and the voltage opens
the potassium channels
in the membrane.
These potassium channels
enable potassium to flow
from the inside to the outside,
leaving negative traces inside
and these negative
traces inside make
the spike go off,
shut off, turn off.
So this interplay
between the fast inward
inactivating  sodium,
and the late outward
activated potassium is really
the underlying mechanism
of this fantastic phenomenon,
the spike.
So the capability of spike
to occur in the axon
critically and totally depend
on the existence of
specific ion channels
in the axons
that are themselves
sensitive to voltage.
They are voltage dependent,
or what we call "excitable channels"
and this excitability
of the channels
enables the spikes
to regenerate itself
and blow itself up and then
close itself due to the potassium.
So that's what I wanted
to say about
the Hodgkin and Huxley
equations.
Now, of course, we have fast
computers which I hope you will use
your own computer can simulate
the Hodgkin and Huxley equation
very fast, Hodgkin and Huxley
worked very hard to solve
the equation numerically,
but they eventually succeeded
and they got something very nice
comparable to what they measured
experimentally.
Before ending this part,
I want to say two things.
First of all,
as I said
when solving the four equations
Hodgkin and Huxley succeeded
to replicate the experimental spike
but not only replicate,
and that's a very important
point that I want to make
here about a good model.
A good model is not only a replica,
of what you already put inside.
A good model, which is very
useful for biologists, for example
is a model that gives prediction.
And one of the main predictions
of Hodgkin and Huxley is that
after the spike,
following the spike
there is a period where
you cannot get a second spike.
It's called a refractory period.
This was not a part of the initial
model but it was explained
by the Hodgkin and Huxley
model, so it's a prediction
by a Hodgkin and Huxley model,
we know experimentally
that when you stimulate the axon
and very early on
you stimulate again another axon,
it won't generate a second spike.
So there is a period,
whereby we cannot get a second spike.
It's a very important period,
the refractory period
because it sets
the frequency of spikes
that the axon can generate.
One spike, and then stop,
no spike,
no matter what you do
and then a second spike.
It's called the refractory period,
let's say every 10ms
you can get a spike,
this means
hundred spikes per second,
hundred hertz.
So the Hodgkin and Huxley model
prejudiced and explained
the phenomenon
of the refractory period.
In the same 1952-D paper
also predicted the velocity of
the spike, which is not
a part of this local model.
The velocity of the spike
depends on the length of the axon
the width of the axon
they predicted
the velocity of the spike
in the squid giant axon,
in their mathematical equation
and it was really, indeed
the same velocity
measured experimentally.
So this is a very powerful model
because it doesn't only replicate
the experimental result,
but it explained other results
that were not part of the original model.
And finally, I want to say
something very important
which I already highlighted
or mentioned before
is that the Hodgkin and Huxley
model is a universal model
in the sense that,
no matter what cell you take
let's say, now I take for you
this cell, which is
a pyramidal cell reconstructed
from the cortex, actually
human cell, human pyramidal cell,
you saw before, and this is the axon
of this human pyramidal cell,
or this is a piece of an axon
And you can see that,
if you measure
in this particular cell
the spiking activity,
you get the spikes.
These are the experimental spikes,
these are the brown spikes.
One spike, another spike,
another spike.
These are the experimental spikes.
But now if you model
the spikes using
the extension of Hodgkin and Huxley
and when I say
extension of Hodgkin and Huxley,
I mean that the same formalism
exactly the same formalism
but adding additional currents
still carried by sodium,
potassium, or calcium
but with different kinetics,
so different Alphas
and different Betas for different
channels, we know that there are
slow potassium channels,
even slower then in
in the Hodgkin and Huxley case
there are ion channels
in the membrane
that are sensitive to calcium,
so the channels not only depend on
voltage but also on calcium,
and so forth,
but it's the same formalism,
and when you extend
the Hodgkin and Huxley formalism,
you can get the firing patterns
essentially
of every cell in the brain.
This is just one example,
the green model
succeeds to replicate the firing
of this particular cell
which is a cortical cell,
nothing to do with
the squid giant axon,
but still fires spikes
and spikes and spikes,
but the pattern of activity
depends on these extra channels,
not only the generation
of the single spike
but when will the next spike arrive,
and the next spike arrive
depends on these other
channels with the same
Hodgkin and Huxley formalism.
So it's a wonderful model
because it not only captures
the spike in the squid giant axon,
it captured the whole universal
phenomenon of
a spike in any cell
and that's why we,
in many ways
really adore Hodgkin and Huxley,
because they gave us the tool
to simulate one of the two
most important signals in the brain,
electrical signals : the spike.
The next thing we shall do,
we'll go to the synaptic potential.