Until now, we had the passive model.
Passive model means that
we only had the capacitance
in a leakage
conductance in our model.
To make our model active,
we're going to introduce two new
components to our model.
Namely sodium conductance,
and the potassium conductance.
As you can see,
the conductance of these channels
is slightly different compared
to the leakage conductance.
Leakage conductance had
a fixed conductance value
but the sodium and potassium
conductances are voltage dependent.
This means that we can have
like feedback mechanisms that
create action potential.
So now, we have a voltage
dependent sodium channel
and the voltage dependent
potassium channel.
These conductances can be
composed into smaller components
namely, the maximum
conductance of the sodium channel
which is not voltage dependent, and
voltage dependent state variable M
and for potassium it's H,
which are ruled by their own
differential equations.
This maximum conductance of sodium
also called the GNABAR
and for potassium GKABAR
are expressed in Siemens
per square centimeter.
They basically represent
the density of the ion channels
on the membrane.
So now, let's try to set these
two values that are not zero.
So for example, 0.01 for potassium,
and 0.1 for sodium.
And then we run our model.
You see now, that we created
action potentials.
So here, we basically have
a sodium current that
creates a feedback mechanism
which causes the voltage to go up
very quickly.
To explain what
happens here a bit better
we can look at the reversal
potentials of the sodium
and the potassium
and the leak current.
So basically, we have a 50mV
sodium reversal potential
-77mV for potassium,
and -65mV for the leak.
So basically,
in the beginning of the spike
we have the sodium
channels that open
which pulls 50mV in the cell.
These sodium channels get
inactivated and at the same time
you also have the potassium
channels that open
and they pull back
the voltage to -77mV.
When none of these
channels are active
the leakage current predominates
and it pulls the cell to -65mV.
Now let's see what happens when
we change some of the parameters.
When we change
the value of the GNABAR
we can actually influence
the height of the action potential.
We can do the same experiment
for many values of GNABAR.
Then we can plot the AP height,
or just the maximum voltage
in the trace
compared to the GNABAR,
and you get this kind of plot.
The two vertical lines show
two values that we used
in the previous plot.
Around 0.08 Siemens per square
centimeters for GNABAR
We also see that
there's a discontinuity.
This is basically
the conductance at which
the cell starts firing,
I mean, in this case
we didn't have any
action potentials generated.
So now we have
a little exercise for you.
Do the same as in the previous plot,
but for the potassium
for this range, and use step size
in this range of 0.001.
So try to plot the results
as in the previous graph
as you will see, all the points
are on a linear curve.
So try to fit a linear function
to these data points
you can actually use the following
function in NUMPY
to do the fitting
and send us the two
coefficients of this linear curve.