Until now, we had a single
compartmental model
consisting of just the soma.
So now, let's start
adding the dendrite.
To do this, you create
a new section: dendrite.
And we can also
connect it to the soma.
In this case,
we're also going to use
the nine compartments
for the dendrite
instead of just one compartment.
Again, we will add the HH
mechanism to the dendrite
but we'll add a passive dendrite,
meaning that we'll disable
the sodium and
potassium conductances.
So now let's look
at what the effect is
of adding this dendrite
to our simulation.
We will run the simulation twice
once with and once
without the dendrite.
As you can see, adding the dendrite
has disabled our action potential.
This current passes through
two resistances.
One is the resistance
of the leak channel
and the other is the resistance
of the internal medium
inside the dendrite and the soma.
The resistance of
the internal medium
of the soma and the dendrites
can be set by the RA variable
in the neuron.
So now, I have a question for you.
What happened here?
Why are there no action potentials
anymore after adding the dendrite?
What could be do to save
the action potentials?
I also have a little
exercise for you.
Try to save the action potentials in
the soma after you've
disconnected the dendrite
by changing the values of "dend_ra"
and "dend_gl" in the code below.
While the action potential
is traveling along
this passive dendrite
it's height will be attenuated.
To show this, we can plot a voltage
at different locations
along the dendrite.
And we can also make a summary plot
a plot of the percentage
of dendritic length
we are calling from against
the maximum voltage
and you will see that you have
an attenuation graph.