When we want to start
connecting cells
we also need
chemical synapses.
In NEURON a synapse is represented
as a point process.
Such processes are
located at specific locations
along the morphology
and they will, in general,
inject some current into the cell
when activated.
NEURON have several
build-in synapse types.
In this tutorial we will
use the "ExpSyn" Synapse.
This is a synapse with
a single exponential decay
of its conductance.
The equations to calculate
the current generated
by this synapse
are basically the total current is
governed by this equation
and the conductance
that is used in this equation
has its own differential equation,
which basically shows
the exponential decay
of the synapse.
Every time an event
arrives at the synapse
the conductance
is increased by its weight.
Now, let's add such
a synapse to the dendrite.
To stimulate this synapse,
we have to create a "netstim" object.
It basically plays the role
of a pre-synaptic cell.
The attributes of this object
specify how many times
we want to stimulate the synapse
with each interval
and when we want to start.
The noise attribute determines
the stochasticity of the process.
Zero means a completely regular
firing of the "netstim" object.
This "netstim" needs to
be connected to the cell.
A "netcon" object acts
as a connector between
the pre-synaptic
and the post-synaptic cell.
So we basically
connect the "netstim"
with "expsyn" on
the post-synaptic cell.
And now we can
run the simulation.
As you can see there are five events
arriving in the post-synaptic cell.
Each event injects
a certain current in the cell
and slowly decays afterwards.
In our last example we will
connect two cells together.
We make a pre-synaptic cell,
and inject a current clamp into it
so that it spikes.
By connecting this cell
to a post-synaptic cell
that doesn't receive a current clamp
we can make
the second cell fire also.
So we basically use the cell that
we have created in
this entire tutorial
as a post-synaptic cell and we
create a new pre-synaptic cell
with the suffix P that
has a current injected
also record a current from it,
and we also create a "netcon"
that connects our pre-synaptic cell
to our synapse in
the post-synaptic cell.
As we can see, we have
the pre-synaptic cell firing
and the post-synaptic cell
fires with a small delay.