Hi.
In this tutorial
I will explain
to you how to build
single cell
electrical models
We will first give you an
introduction to the simulator we use.
This simulator is also
called NEURON.
We will first build a single
compartmental model.
We will add some
current injections
and record the voltage
from this model
and we will add some ion channels
to the membrane.
Let me first show
how to load
the neuron simulator
into Python.
This is simply done
by importing NEURON.
As you can see, there's a link here
to the documentation
of the NEURON simulator
so that you can have a look at
all the different functions that we
are going to use later in this notebook.
Historically, the NEURON Simulator
was controlled using the HOC language.
More and more scientists are switching
to the Python interface of NEURON.
In Python there's something
called the HOCObject.
which can be accessed by the
'h' property of the neuron module
which contains the HOC
functionality of NEURON.
For example, to load the
'stdrun.hoc' file
which contains some
handy functionality
one calls the HOC function
load_file using this function call.
We also want to make sure that we
always start from a clean simulator.
So with this comment here,
the 'stdinit'
we can reset the
state of the stimulator.
Also for this tutorial
it's important to know
that all the values used
in NEURON have a certain unit.
Here is a link to the different
units which will be used
and I have specified the most
important ones below.
What we will do in this tutorial
is construct a neuron
consisting of
multiple compartments.
Let's start
with one compartment.
I first want to introduce to you how
NEURON looks at a neuron.
We basically have a
detailed morphology
that was reconstructed
by experimenters
and NEURON will load this
kind of morphology.
It will then discretize
this morphology
in different segments
or compartments
which you can
for example see here.
So this is a zoomed-in version
of a part of a dendrite.
The different segments
are these parts here
and you see the diameter and length
of every segment on this graph.
We also have something
called a section.
A section is something
between two branch points.
So here you have one branch point.
Here you have one branch point.
A section is a piece
of dendrite
or any part of
of the neuron
between two
branch points.
After discretizing the space
NEURON will run
an electrical simulation
of this morphology.
We will see
the details later
but here you
can already see
an example of
such an electrical circuit
that's been
simulated.
Basically every segment
is replaced by
a tiny
electrical circuit
and all the segments
are connected
by wires
with some resistance.
In this tutorial we will build
a ball and stick model.
The ball is the soma of the cell
and the stick is a dendrite.
In light gray you see the
morphology of the model
that we are
going to build.
In dark black is the
equivalent electrical circuit.
We will go into the detail
of all the components later
but basically again we have
one segment or compartment
that represents the soma
and we have different
segments in
the dendrite.
So let's start with
the soma of the cell.
So let's start
with the soma.
Initially we'll create
a section in NEURON
that represents the soma
and we wont add
any channels to
the membrane of the soma.
It means that we will
only have a capacitance
that represents the
membrane of our soma.
Creating the soma
is done by
creating a section object
in NEURON.
This section object
has a name
and also has a variable that
specifies a number of segments
so basically a soma
is one compartment.
Every section
in NEURON
is basically represented
as a cylinder
which is the same
with the soma here.
Then you can see the length
and the diameter of these sections.
For example you can do this
by setting the 'L' attribute
to the soma to 40
which will be 40 microns
and you can also set the diameter
of the soma to 40 microns too
which basically will represent
a sphere instead of a cylinder.
The area function
can be used
to calculate the surface area
of the soma.
And we can actually
use the equation of
the surface area of
a cylinder to see
if what NEURON says to us
is correct.
As you can see
if you execute this block here
you get exactly the
same value for the
area of the membrane
of the soma.
Maybe you find it a bit strange that
everything in NEURON is a cylinder
because basically the soma in most
cells looks like a sphere
but you can also see here
that it actually doesn't matter
too much because if we calculate
the surface area of a sphere
with the diameter and length
of the cylinder to be specified
we get exactly
the same value.
Now we have specified the shape
of the single compartmental cell.
Electrically, the only component
that is present for now
is the capacitance
of the cell membrane.
We can retrieve or set a
specific membrane capacitance
by accessing the 'cm' field
as we can see here.
The units
of this field are
microfarad per square centimeter
(μF/cm2).
This specific capacitance
that is stored in that variable
is only a value per cm²
so per surface area of the soma.
If you want to know
the total capacitance of the soma,
you have to multiply this by
the total surface area of the soma
and as you can see here
we get this kind of value.
You only have to be careful
with the units
because the surface area
is in micrometer squared (μm²)
while the capacitance
is per cm²
so you need to have a
correction factor for the units.
Now we have
this electrical circuit.
What does this mean?
We have the internals of the cell
which is marked by this
connector here
and we have the outside of
the cell which is grounded.
What we will
do in NEURON is
calculate the voltage difference
between the inside of the cell
and the
outside of the cell
NEURON stores the
voltage difference between inside
and outside of the cell
in a variable called 'v'.
So for example even if you
didn't do any simulation yet
you can already ask an initial value
of this value at the soma.
I also want to point out
this 0.5 value here
so basically
every section you can ask
certain variables
at different locations.
The 0.5 here means
that it's the middle of the soma.
If you want to have one side
of the soma, you take zero
and the other side it's 1
so it's basically
there is a range variable
between zero and 1
that you
can specify.
As you can see, the voltage
of the soma is -65 mV (millivolts).
This is roughly the
typical value of a neuron at rest.
Then we also have
the time variable
of the simulator which
will advance during our simulation
but at the moment
this is set to zero.
Then we also have to set
the variable called 'tstop'
which will define how long
our simulation will run.
To record the time and voltage
we create two neuron vector objects.
These objects have a record method
that when passed
a reference to a variable
will record the value of that variable
in the vector
during the simulation.
For example, here we
record the time and the voltage.
Now, running the simulation
is as easy as
just calling
the run method.
The run method will basically
advance the time from zero
to the variable tstop
we have defined.
In this case
100 ms.
I've also created
a little plot function to show
the time
and the voltage.
As you can see, the voltage during
our simulation has stayed the same.
You can also see this
from the equations,
so basically NEURON is
integrating an equation
like the one
you can see here,
and if we put
a zero current
so we didn't inject any current
in the model at the moment,
we actually get
a variable of dV
which is
a voltage difference of zero,
which perfectly explains
our plot here.
To make this simulation
a bit more interesting
we'll inject
a current.
You basically do this
by sticking a pipette
into the soma
and injecting a certain current.
This is done by creating
an 'iclamp' object in Neuron.
The 'iclamp' object let's us
specify the amount of current
we are going to inject
in nanoamps (nA)
and also the delay and
the duration of the stimulus.
When we run our simulation
we now get this kind of curve.
Basically now we are integrating
this equation here
but unlike in
the previous simulation,
the I_m is not
zero anymore
but is equal to the value of
the amplitude of the 'iclamp'.
When we fill out
all the variables is this equation
we actually can calculate
how much voltage difference
we are going
to see in the plot.
So here we are actually
comparing the voltage difference
reported by the simulation
and by our little calculation
and it shows that
these values are exactly the same.
In a real neuron
you don't just have a capacitance
that forms
the membrane
but this membrane
also contains ion channels.
Let's start adding
these to our model.
The first one we'll add
is the lead conductors.
To insert such channels
we have to insert
certain mechanisms
in NEURON.
The mechanism represents which
equations NEURON has to use
to calculate the
ion channel currents.
One example is
the 'hh' mechanism
which represents the
Hodgkin-Huxley model.
When adding this 'hh' mechanism
NEURON will integrate
the following equation to
get the membrane voltage over time.
Like I said, at the moment we are
mostly interested in the leak current
so we are going to set the
sodium and potassium currents
to zero
for the moment;
so the final equation
is this.
Now we have introduced
two new variables.
We have the 'E_leak'
and we have the 'G_leak'.
The 'G_leak' is set by the
'gl_hh' variable
and we can set it
to a certain value.
Now we can also
set the 'E_leak'
and the 'E_leak' is basically
the potential that the
leakage channel
will pull the cell to.
Basically at the moment
we are going to set it
to exactly the
reversal potential so that
the cell will always naturally
fall back to the reversal potential.
When we now simulate this
you see that our graph has changed.
I have now
a little question for you.
Compare this graph
to the previous one
and if you look at the equations,
do you understand
why the voltage flattens out
at the end of the stimulus here?
Also as an exercise,
when you assume
that the time derivative
between 40 and 60 milliseconds (ms)
is zero, calculate the average
voltage in that interval.