Ok, so I promised you that
we'll go to the synaptic potential
and here it is
so let me give you
a little description
of what is a synaptic potential.
I already drew
synaptic potentials for you
but now I want to
go into more detail.
So if you zoom in using
an electron microscope
on the left part of the slide
you will see a piece of a
dendrite here...
And zoom in and you see
all these dendritic spines
one dendritic spine,
another dendritic spine
and you can see here,
schematically, an axon.
So you have to think
of this dendritic tree
with many little spines
and an axon
like an electrical fire,
where a wire goes through the tree
continues elsewhere
but sometimes while
going through the tree
it, sort of speak, touches
but not physically
as I will show in a second
but it comes very, very close
to a dendritic spine.
And there in these dendritic spines
there is this thing that we call
synapse, between the axon
and the dendritic spine.
So let's look here,
this is a high resolution
electron microscope of an axon,
this is an axon here
and this is a dendritic spine
of cell B
for this was an axon of cell A,
and this is a dendrite of cell B
or a spine of cell B
and between them, not touching,
there is a little space
it's called the synaptic cleft.
In the axon you see these vesicles,
you see one vesicle here
and another vesicle here,
a third vesicle here
and in the dendrite,
here in the dendritic spine
in the head of the dendritic spine
yes, here in this location,
the head of the dendritic spine
we know that there
are these receptors
for particular chemicals,
so here there will be a receptor
a receptor, a receptor,
a receptor,
and this receptor is sitting on
the membrane of the dendritic spine
waiting, sort of speak,
for the release of the transmitters
from the vesicles here,
in the axon.
So in the axon
there are these vesicles
full of neurotransmittors
could be gaba,
one name of a transmitter,
could be glutamate,
another name of a transmitter,
inside here many thousands
of molecules of transmitters
are within these vesicles.
In the axon you know
that there are spikes always
and in the dendrite you know
there is a synaptic potential, here.
Ok?
And the question is,
how does the spike in the axon
eventually generate
a synaptic potential
in the dendrite?
As I said,
they don't touch each other
so the spike cannot
go through electrically:
it's a chemical synapse,
so we are now talking about
the chemical synapse,
and this chemical synapse means
that there is a chemical substance
between the pre-synaptic side
which is the axon,
to the post-synaptic side
which is the dendrite,
and this chemical is really the one
which does the communication.
But in order for
the chemical to be released
we will need a spike in the axon
and this spike here that you see
when it arrives to this button,
to this pre-synaptic region
where you have all these vesicles,
these spikes in a miraculous process
fuse the vesicle into the membrane
here and releases into the space
the transmitter.
So the spite is responsible
through a complicated process
to release, to fuse the vesicle into
the pre-synaptic membrane
of the button and enable
the flow of this chemical
transmitter glutamate
into the space of the cleft between
the axon and the dendrite
and some of these chemicals,
some of these molecules
are captured, bound to the receptor
in the post-synaptic side
and these receptors are really
behaving like ion channels
meaning that when they are
bound by the transmitter
these ion channels in
the post-synaptic membrane
start to open,
and here again
you have current flow.
So to summarize what I said,
you have an axon of cell A
an action potential arrives here
and it causes the release,
the fusion of this vesicle,
and the release
of this neurotransmitter.
In the post-synaptic side,
in the dendritic spine
you have these receptors,
here is a receptor,
that is very particularly sensitive
to the presence of this chemical.
Let's say, glutamite, acetylcholine,
dopamine, serotonin,
depending which transmitter
is being released from the axon
but after it is being released
it bind to the receptor
and when the receptor is bound,
there is a channel being open
and through this ion channel,
there is a current flow.
So what I just told you is that,
now we are speaking about
different types of channels
in the dendrites.
I am talking about
the post-synaptic side
this side here,
the sides with the receptors
and I'm saying that when there is
a transmitter binding
to the receptors
these receptors behave as a channel,
or attached to a channel
and this ion channel,
which we already know, opens
but in this case, these ion channels are
not voltage dependent (like in the case
of the spike in the axon but they are
transmitter dependent, chemical dependent,
so these are chemical synapses
and these are chemical receptors
and these channels
are chemically sensitive.
So now I'm talking about
the different types of channels
in the dendrites, but again,
these ion channels, when open
will change the voltage here.
If a positive current flows
because they're open
we will get a positive current.
If a positive current flows outside
you will get a negative voltage.
Ok? So that's the origin
of synaptic potential,
and now I'm going to talk about
the model, the mathematical model,
the electrical circuit
and the mathematical model
of the post-synaptic potential,
the potential in the dendrite.
So first, let's look at
the equivalent cylinder
so as I drew before,
as Hodgkins Huxley did
they drew the electrical circuit
of the post-synaptic region.
Now I'm drawing for you
the electrical circuit
of the postsynaptic membrane here.
What do we have here,
in the post-synaptic membrane?
Again we have the same
thing that we saw before.
We have some channels,
we call it G-synapse:
the conductance
of the ion channels
that are sensitive
to the transmitter.
In this case, they will
be dependent on time.
Why on time ?
Because when, for a given time,
there is a transmitter in the cleft
they will open, and then this
transmitter will be taken away
which happens due
to certain mechanism
we don't want the transmitter
to stay there too long
so it is released from the vesicles,
it is bound to the receptors
and after some times it goes out.
So I'm writing here,
I'll write it again.
I'll have more space,
it will be the synaptic conductance
which depends on the opening
of the post-synaptic ion channels
which will give you a conductance
that will depend on the transmitter.
It's time dependent,
and transmitter dependent
T is for time, but you can
think about this
as the Transmitter also,
and this will be attached
to particular battery because it
will depend on which ion will flow.
Will it be chloride ion,
sodium ion, potassium ion?
So this battery is
the synaptic battery.
It will depend on the ion type
or ions that might flow
through this channel.
So this Nernst's equation
of the conductance equation
which is the extension of
the Nernst equation
will describe this battery
as we did for the resting potential
but in this case,
it will be a battery
that will describe
the battery of the synapse
due to the opening
of the new synaptic channels.
Ok, this is the inside of the cell
as before,
this is the outside of the cell
You have also other channels here,
so these are the resting channels
so the membrane of the spine
also has these other channels
that are neither voltage
nor chemically sensitive and
you have the resting potential here
which is negative inside, let's call it
E-rest, about -70, let's say,
and here you have the capacitor C.
Okay, so this has to be closed.
So this particular branch
the synaptic branch
is typically closed.
Why? Because there are
no transmitters.
And if there are no transmitters,
this branch doesn't function
because the conductance doesn't open
there is no current flow
due to no transmitter.
But as soon as there is
a transmitter this one is closed
meaning that you have a new
channel or channels being open
due to the transmitter.
So this is the circuit which is
actually much simpler than
the Hodgkin-Huxley excitable
membrane circuit,
this is for the synaptic,
post-synaptic membrane circuit.
A very simple circuit
and you can solve it mathematically,
for example
if the synaptic conductance
is a step current like this,
G-synapse, let's say that
it opens for a brief time
when there is a transmitter,
and then it closes, then I can
easily solve this circuit.
Ok, so let's see,
we are now writing
the equation for the post-synaptic
potential.
So the post synaptic potential will
be the voltage that will develop
between the two sides
of the membrane, V.
So I want to say that first of all
the current, the membrane current,
total membrane current,
through the membrane
which is the sum of all currents,
is the sum of the synaptic current
plus the passive or resting
leak current, plus C(dv/dt), ok,
and now I'm writing down
particularly the different currents
so the synaptic current itself
will be G-synapse multiplied
by V minus E-synapse.
And again V is
the membrane potential
that I actually want to compute,
because this will be the potential
generated by the opening
of this conductance,
plus G =-rest multiplied
by V minus E-rest plus C(dv/dt).
Ok?
And now, in order to solve it,
to get the real synaptic voltage,
we'll call it, let's say,
V-synapse,
I can say that this V-synapse
is actually the following equation
which we already know
because it is
the conductance equation that
I showed you before,
but in this case it is
G-synapse multiplied
by E-synapse
plus G-rest multiplied by-E rest
divided by G-synapse plus G-rest
So this will be the study state case.
If there would not have
been any capacitant here
this will be the steady state
synaptic voltage after changing
this conductance.
So this will be again a competition,
between the battery of the synapse
the resting battery here and
the ratio between the conductances
so let's say if
the synaptic conductance
is very, very strong relative
to the resting conductance
then the voltage will be close
to the battery of the synapse
If let's say, if the conductance
of the synapse is purely sodium
then each synapse will be E and A,
the Nerst potential for sodium
and the voltage of the synapse will
reach +60mV which doesn't happen
but it could've happened if
it was a channel only for sodium.
But here, we also have here,
because of the conductance here
capacitance here you also have
something that is time dependent
and it looks something like that,
minus G-synapse plus G-rest
T divided by C.
So actually, this is the solution
for this equation which is
a simple electrical equation
using Kirchhoff law
and this tells you that if you
activate the synaptic conductance
you will get a voltage change, which
we called V-synapse that starts at
the resting potential, let's say
-70mV and here you activate
this location
let's say G synapse
and then you get
some synaptic potential
that will grow as long
as you have synaptic conductance
but when you close the
synaptic conductance,
it will go back to the resting potential.
This will be your
synaptic potential.
In this case, the synaptic battery
is positive relative
to the resting potential.
If you would activate,
let's say from here this location
another synapse,
which opens potassium channels
then you will get this signal.
This signal we called
"excitatory synaptic potential"
it tends to depolarize the membrane,
make the -70 less negative
and this potential they call it
"inhibitory post-synaptic potential"
which makes the -70 more negative
let's say to -75
This is the inhibitory
post-synaptic potential.
So you have two types of synapses
the excitatory
post-synaptic potentials
the excitatory synapses which
are particular sets of synapses
actually all the synapses,
or most of the synapses, not all,
most of the synapses that
contact the dendritic spines
tend to be of the excitatory type.
This means that
the battery associated with
these particular synapses
in the post-synaptic membrane
is a positive battery relative
to rest, this positive battery
when the battery is expressed
because a channel is open
then you will have
a positive voltage
and EPSP, "excitatory
post-synaptic potential",
this will be this fellow here,
and in other locations,
other synapses may contact
with the dendrite, not the spine,
but directly with the dendrite
when they open they
open ion channels typically
either for chloride
or for potassium
and this will carry the resting potential
to a more negative region
this will be the inhibitory synapses.
They will cause inhibitory
post-synaptic potential.
I just told you that there is
this mechanism of
this synaptic potentials which
heavily relies
on the presence of ion channels
in the dendrites that are sensitive
to chemical, to transmitter
that is released from the
pre-synaptic side
bound into the post-synaptic receptor
open ion channels, and then
it depends of which ion channels are open.
If these ion channels carry
inward positive current
this will generate positive potential,
excitatory post-synaptic potential
and if it will carry let's say,
potassium channel from
the inside to outside it will
make the inside more negative,
this will cause an IPSP
an inhibitory
post-synaptic potential.
So you have the synapse,
but you have two types
of potentials using
the same principal mechanism
depending on which
ion channels are open.
So again the whole trick.
like in the spike or channels were sensitive
to voltage,
and they open due to voltage,
so these are the excitable channels
in the axon
in the dendrite you have
chemical dependent channels
but basically you have
two types of ion channels
one that tends to bring
positive current into the cell
and this will be called
the excitatory
post-synaptic potential
and those that will carry
positive current from insidep
to outside and will make the inside
more negative
this will be the inhibitor
post synaptic potential.
The mechanism is the same, but now
it depends on chemical transmittors.
And that's the beauty of the neuron.
In one region the dendritic tree
has the channels that are sensitive
to chemicals and these chemical are
being released by the nearby axons
through this
marvelous special device
that we call synapse,
and in the axon you have
the other type of channels
that are sensitive to voltage
and they generate the spike.
So let us summarize
through the equations.
You have a synaptic current
that depends on
the synaptic conductance
and on the battery of
the respective conductance.
It could be a battery that
is more negative than
rest or more positive
than rest.
It will be inhibitory
or excitatory synapses.
So I want to go now
to describe our way
of describing
the conductance of a synapse.
So I mentioned that this time
dependent conductance
of the synapse depends
of the transmitter in the cleft
that bound to receptors.
And we think about this binding
of receptors are when you bind
the channel opens
and then when the channel gets rid,
sort of speak, of the transmitter
then there is less
and less conductance
and you can describe it as follows.
They say that the synaptic
conductance has some peak value
and some normalization parameter N
and then we describe it
mathematically
with a good description,
as I will show you in a second.
So these parts are supposed
to be describing the rise
of the synaptic conductance,
and this part is supposed to
describe the decay of
the synaptic conductance with time,
and if you look at this equation,
it looks like something like this.
So the conductance
of the synapse looks
something like this, so this is
the synaptic conductance G-synapse
this is the peak synaptic
conductance G-peak
which, by the way, can be,
just to give you numbers
it could be something of
the order of 1nS,
it's a very small
conductance locally.
And this is one way to
think about the conductance.
And in the case of EPSP or IPSP,
this particular conductance
depending on which battery,
will generate different directions
of voltage change.
So in the case of G of EPSP,
this synaptic conductance
that I just described,
is associated with the battery
that is positive relative to rest,
let's say that this is now
-10mV, this is the inside,
this is the outside
of the cell,
and of course there is the other
resting potential
and it's related battery
but this when current flows,
in this case it will flow from
outside to inside
then it will give
a voltage that will look like this
V-synapse.
This is what we
usually call the EPSP.
This is more positive than rest,
and in this case
it's the same conductance idea
exactly as before
but there is the synaptic
conductance G-synapse
but in this case, the battery
associated with the synapse
let's say potassium battery,
for example
yes, and this is the in,
and this is the out,
this will generate a negative
voltage, this will be an IPSP
inhibitory post-synaptic potential.
So that's all that you need to know,
you have the equation here
that describes well the opening
and the closing of
the synaptic channels,
and now you know that the opening
and the closing of synaptic channels
will generate current flow
from inside to outside
or from outside to inside and
this is expressed by the battery
whether it's negative inside IPSP,
or a negative inside IPSP.
Excitetory synapses,
inhibitory synapses.
These are the two types
of synapses that you see.
So it's very interesting
to think about the dendrites
receiving two types of synapses
converge on
the dendritic tree.
Some of the synapse locally
generate a positive voltage signal
the IPSP, some of the signals
converge locally also generate IPSP
a negative signal relative to rest
and this signals intermix between
themselves to generate the
overall little things
that I drew before,
because if you record as I said
if you record from the dendrite here
you see EPSP, IPSP, EPSP, IPSP...
so this is the voltage trace
that I drew before
but now you know that
it is composed of two synaptic types
the IPSPs, excitatory synapses,
the IPSP, and they inter-mingle
integrate together and eventually
flow through the dendrite into
the other region, or the rest
of the dendrite.
And this is what I need
to explain to you next.
Explain to you how the synaptic
potential are generated locally
the spine head or locally that
dendritic side whether there
is a synaptic conduct
between axon and dendrite
now I need to explain to you
how this synaptic current
and voltages merge together,
and flow everywhere in the dendrite
also including axon and the soma.
So to summarize this part.
Synapses are the connecting
sides between the axons of
pre-synaptic cell, cell A,
to the dendrite of
the post-synaptic cell, cell B.
When the spike reaches, arrives,
to the pre-synaptic side, the button
where you have these vesicles,
it releases, through a process,
the transmitter that is
embedded between the vesicle
into the synaptic cleft
a very narrow gap
and then it is being captured by
the receptors that are just sitting
opposite to the button.
So the button is here, the cleft of
the dendrite
the cleft is here and here there are
these receptors,
so here I open a vesicle
and the vesicle is now bound
to the receptor.
When it binds to the receptor,
there are these specific ion channels
either of potassiums, or of sodium,
or of chloride,
you already know these ions,
but this time
so chemical dependent receptors.
chemical gated receptors.
So they are not excitable channels,
they are not voltage dependent
but they are chemical dependent.
They can generate
the post synaptic potential.
The post synaptic potential
in the dendrite
has two dimensions,
two sides.
It could be excitatory
post-synaptic potential
which means the potential
moves more positively
due to the corresponding battery
of this particular ion or ions
that are open due to the receptor,
or it could be an IPSP
inhibitory post-synaptic potential
again due to the corresponding battery.
So there is no miraculous difference
between inhibitory
and excitatory synapses
the difference is which channels
are being open post-synapticly.
We know today,
and that's very interesting
that in our cortex,
for example
the excitatory transmitter
typically is the glutamate
not always, but glutamate
when it releases the pre-synaptic
side it tends to open ion channels
that let current flow through
them positively into the membrane
of the dendrite,
giving rise to the positive voltage:
Excitatory post-synaptic potential.
And gaba,
gamma-aminobutyric acid
is released from other axons
which we call inhibitory axons
these other axons release gaba,
gaba is bound to the receptor
of the post-synaptic cell,
dendrite of the same dendrite
but in another location
and this other location has receptors for
and these receptors for gaba are open
they may open ion channels,
potassium ion channels
or chloride ion channels,
we call it gaba A and gaba B
anyway so these receptors carry
the voltage
to more negative relative to rest,
and this increased negativity
is expressed as inhibitory
post-synaptic potentials:
Inhibitory synapses.
Finally and very interestingly,
unlike the spike in the axon
which is an all or non phenomenon
so it's a digital phenomenon,
a zero-one phenomenon.
The synaptic potentials are graded,
analog phenomenon
so a particular synapse could
become stronger if you want
or weaker if you want,
so the EPSP can became larger
or smaller EPSP,
or smaller larger IPSP
depending for example,
on the density of receptors
in the post-synaptic membrane,
you have many receptors
than the same
amount of transmitters
binding to many receptors
will generate more current
and thus more voltage.
Or if there will be less
or maybe even no receptors
then the release of the transmitter
will cause no voltage
in the post-synaptic membrane,
so it's a graded phenomenon
the EPSP and the IPSP are graded
they can attain
different voltage values
1mV, 1.5mV, 2mV, and so forth
so it's graded, an analog signal
and this means that the dendrites
tend to carry analog
signals the synaptic potentials
the axon carries digital signals
which is the spiking activity
and so you have the same
micro chip in the brain
the same cell, in one region
is an analogue region
in another region
is a digital region
and of course they should
interact with each other
because eventually
the input to the dendrite
the synaptic input to
the dendrite
should generate
: yes or no
depending if you reach or not,
especially in the axon
a spike, so how do they interact ?
The synaptic input,
the analogue signal,
and this spike output,
digital signal?
How do they interact ?
This is the next topic.