So, thank you very much
for being with me in this part.
I hope that you really understood
sort of speak,
the essence of what is the level that
we're trying to understand the brain,
e.g. is very important
because it records
electrical activity, globally;
and other means
to record globally activity
FMRI, EG, and other methods
are essential to understand
the global activity of the brain,
but we need to understand
the local activity of the brain
in terms of electrical activity
and we know now,
through this course
that it is generated
by the intrinsic properties of neurons.
These ion channels
that are distributed in the axons
and are sensitive to voltage
could generate this wonderful all
or none propagating phenomena:
the spike.
These synaptic receptors
that catch up this transmitter
can generate locally the EPSPs,
this other signal
and these two signals interact together
to generate this richness
of the electrical activity
in the brain
and this richness,
especially in the human brain
gives rise to the richness
of what we do,
also, our capability due
to its richness
to understand ourselves to develop
mathematical models of the signals
and maybe repair the brain,
after such an understanding.
That's the role of the scientist,
and I very much hope that now
you would think about the brain
sometimes as generating
two types of signals:
synaptic potential, action potential
and that these signals
stand really in the basis,
in the core, of who we are
Thank you very much for listening.