Okay, so we are now into trying
to understand
the flow of electrical current
of synaptic current in dendrites.
This understanding came
from a very, very beautiful work
by Wilfred Rall
So, Rall in the late 50s
developed what he called
"The one dimensional passive
cable equation”
to describe the flow of synaptic
current generated locally
let's say on the dendritic spine,
into the dendrite
into the rest of the tree,
including the soma and axon
So, what is the idea
between cable equation,
Rall's cable equation?
The idea here, that here
you have a cable
which is supposed to describe
a piece of dendrite.
It's one dimensional cable
because we only look at axial current
So, you only look at this direction
of flow
or this direction of flow
in the X direction
but not in the Y or the Z direction
of this cube,
of this dendritic cube.
So this is a cable
that describes the axon
this is the dendrite,
this is the membrane here
and this is the axial resistivity
inside the dendrite.
And the idea is very simple
but the equation that becomes
is a description of this simple idea
is that if you have an axial current
flowing inside the dendrite
some of it will leak out
from the membrane
and some, after leaking out,
will continue axially
longitudinally,
to other region of the cable
So, you're going to have
an axial current
and then a loss through the membrane
and the rest is continuing
to flow axially. Ok?
This is in the case
of passive membrane, so you only lose...
You inject a current in some location
let's say you inject a current
in some location
any location you may inject
a current. Ok?
You injected the current here
The synapse injected the current here
as if there is an inward current
flowing here.
This inward current starts
to flow axially
some of it is being lost
to the membrane
through the membrane ion channels
the passive ion channels,
they are open
Some of the current goes outside,
the rest go here
some of it being lost here
So, less current is flowing here
and so they will get a decay
of the current
less and less current will reach
less and less distance.
So, if you write exactly what I spoke
now, in words, in equation
you will see this cable equation here
Which is actually showing you
in some sense
that the axial current splits
into either a membrane current,
and we know the description
of the membrane current
because there is capacitance
and there is resistance
and we can describe the membrane
potential due to this loss of current
through the membrane, and the rest
of the current flow axially;
and this is really
this differential equation
It has space here, X,
which is the axial current
And it has time here
which reflects the capacitance
of the membrane
and together you get
this cable equation
which really describes the loss
of current
or the flow of current
through an axial cable
but with the loss
through the membrane
That's the idea behind
the cable equation,
without going into the details
Rall wrote some very nice papers
analytically
to solve this cable equation,
I will just give you some intuitions.
Actually intuitions
are the main thing that I'm doing now
without going
into too many practical details
because this you will do
in your exercises.
Let me give you some intuition.
Here is a cable,
here is a dendritic cable
so it's a branch dendrite.
You see the main trunk
and then it branches to one branch
and then it branches
to another branch.
Suppose you inject some voltage
at this location.
So, you inject current
and there is some voltage here
and you can see that
through this cable
because of what I just spoke about
current loss
you will get attenuation
of the voltage to this branch point
and then more attenuation
to the dotted branches and so forth
So, that's how a synaptic potential
will look in dendrite.
This is another example
suppose you inject the current
in this location
you will get in the injection site
the largest voltage
but then it will attenuate
very strongly to this direction, here,
or to the right direction, there,
and so you will get a big loss,
a very steep attenuation in dendrite.
Rall showed that indeed in dendrites
you may get locally large voltage,
synaptic potential locally,
maybe 20 millivolts locally,
but this synaptic potential
will attenuate very steeply
because of the cable properties
of the dendrite.
And we just saw that
but we can also look at the time,
what happens in time
not only in space, but in time.
So, let's say that you inject
your current here
a transient current,
very brief current
like a synaptic current you inject
and then the current decays locally.
Then, if you wait enough time
you see that after some time
the voltage reaches here
at this location
because the voltage spreads in time
and then here,
after some time it goes down
it goes down, it goes down
And after some time it goes here
and after enough time
the current dissipates
through the membrane
and nothing is left
and you are back to resting potential.
So of course in cable,
because the cable equation
as I said before,
has both space and time,
the solution for the cable equation
now it's not ordinary
differential equation
but partial differential equation
with X and T
it will take both space for decay
of voltage
and also voltage will decay in time
and that's the solution
for the cable equation:
The time and space solution.
This is another example,
so let's say that I inject here
at some location X=0
inject a very strong current
and I get a strong voltage
and I'm looking at some distance
I will get this, let's say EPSP
if I look later at a more distant,
so this is distance
this is close to the injection site
further from the injection site,
even further,
you can see the attenuation
both in time and in space.
One interesting thing
is that you can see
that the shape of the voltage in time
let's call it the EPSP
the shape of the EPSP changes
as a function of distance
from the injection site.
This will mean
that the synaptic...
the shape of the synaptic potential
locally at the synaptic site
will be different
than the shape of the voltage...
of the synaptic voltage away
from the synapse
let's say the cell body
It will actually attenuate,
but also will become broader
It will be smeared out,
like you see here
from something that is sharper,
to something that is more smeared out,
that is what is expected
from cable theory
Rall's cable theory, for synapses.
You can speak about the velocity
how fast the EPSP
or the IPSP propagates
from the site of origin
in the dendrite to another location
So, this shows you here, the velocity.
We didn't discuss this much
but the velocity first is very fast
and then it comes to kind of a steady
state velocity of the EPSP
so this is just to give you a ball park
this could be something
on the order
of say 0.1 meter per second
Something like that, or even less,
so the synaptic potential
from its origin in the synapse itself
in the spine, let's say
until the soma it will take some time,
there will be a delay,
as you can see here.
It happens here, let's say
it takes some time to reach here
it takes even more time to reach here
so there is a propagation delay,
there is a dendritic delay
between the origin of the synapse
until the voltage is seen in the soma.
This is an important aspect,
because neurons delay the signals,
it's not instantaneous
it's actually quite a slow process
of a few milliseconds
or tenth of milliseconds
from the synapse to the soma
depending on where the synapse is,
relative to the soma.
So, this is a demonstration
that Rall already early on, in '67,
already showed something important.
This is his model of a neuron,
this is the cell body
and this is the distal dendrite,
this is firing the dendrite.
So he split the dendritic tree here
into let's say a chain of compartment
number two, number three, number four,
and this is very far in the dendrite,
and this is very close to the soma.
And he was injecting
simulated synapses to the soma
to the proximal compartment
to the more distal, to the more distal,
and looking at the shape
of the synaptic potential
at the soma as a function
of location.
When you normalize this
somatic EPSPs
you see that if you inject
your synapse
into compartment number one
you get a very fast, local EPSP
If you inject it at compartment
number eight, in here
it's this case
and you normalize for the amplitude
because of course
it should have been decayed
but if you normalize there
you see that it takes time
for the synapse
synaptic potential to reach the soma
so it's slower
but it also broader
and now the EPSP is very broad.
So, Rall was actually the first one
to understand
that the shape of the synaptic potential
as measured at the soma
reflects in many way the origin
of the synapse
if it's a very brief EPSP
it probably comes from dendritic
region near to the soma
If it's a very sluggish EPSP,
and broad
it comes probably
from a distal region
so this is a distal synapse.
And because we know that
the dendritic tree is full of synapses
some are distal,
some are in the middle
some proximal to the soma and axon
we know that the shape of this EPSP
is changed, as a function
of the origin,
at the soma
and also the amplitude changes;
and in may ways, the nearby synapses
excitatory synapses
are more effective
in de-polarizing the cell,
if it's an EPSP
than the distal synapses,
which attenuate it.
So, Rall cable equations enable
us to understand
what is the degree of attenuation,
how much a distal synapse
will de-polarize the cell body,
how much the same synapse,
if it would have been proximal
affect the cell body and so on.
So, the cable equation
is really an essential part
of understanding how the neuron
collects its inputs
and then attenuates these inputs
from the synapses
to the cell body and axon,
where the second signal, the spike,
is generated.
Now, in order to solve
the cable equations,
in some cases you can do it
analytically as Rall did
and really get a mathematical,
clean solution for current injection
in this location or another location
and the voltage that emerges
in any other location of the tree,
but typically,
especially for conductant changes
which is perturbing the membrane
properties by opening ion channels
it's hard to solve analytically
and for this you use
what we always now use
in all our simulation
which is called
the compartmental modeling.
So, compartmental modeling
is a numerical implication
or application of the cable equation
so the cable equation
is an analytical equation
the compartment modeling
of the cable equation
is a numerical approximation
of the continuous analytical case.
So, the compartmental modeling
is a numerical simulation
of the Rall cable equation.
And the idea is very simple.
So, let's say that you have
a reconstructed dendritic tree
and that you know all the electrical
parameter of this dendritic tree:
you know the resistance of the soma
you know the capacitance of the soma
you know the resistance of the axial
intracellular resistivity and all that...
Let's say that you have
all these properties,
so you have ,the cable equation
for this one
but let's say that now you want
to inject the synapse conductance
change here
and another,
let's say inhibitory synapse
so this is inhibitory here,
and excitatory there
and another synapse here, and so on...
So, you really want now
to perturb your model neuron
in order to understand
how all these inputs integrate
and generate eventually local
voltages but also axonal voltages.
So, you take the continuous case
which is, as I said, determined
by the cable equation
and you cut it into segments,
or compartments,
here is one compartment,
so, you disquieterize,
you take the continuous case
and you take a delta X and you decide
this I call a compartment
this I call another compartment
So this is one
Delta X disquietization
another Delta X disquietization
another Delta X
And for this disquieterized
compartments
with this Delta X
supposed to be small enough
so that the numerical solution
after this disquietization
will approximate the continuous case,
then, you get the compartmental
representation of the cable case
so this is now one compartment
this is now another compartment
and so on
and you can see that the idea here
is that to describe each compartment
by the membrane
so there is a capacitance
and there is a resistance here
so, this is the membrane
representation here
the resistance, and a capacitance
of the membrane
and there is this axial resistivity
which connects one compartment
to the other compartment:
that's what you see here.
So compartmental modeling,
and you will be using that a lot
for example, simulated by neuron
which is a simulator that is using
compartmental modeling approach
to model neurons and network
of neurons
bombarded by synapses,
and then, of course, because we know
how to model a synapse
let's say this synapse, I know how
to edit to compartmental modeling
another segment that will describe
this particular synapse
with its battery as we just discussed.
So, that's the compartmental
representation of the cable equation,
but the underlying theory
mathematical theory for current flow
in passive dendrites
including synapses,
today we can extend it even
to dendrites that have some voltage
dependence membrane properties
but we are not going
to talk about this,
but the principle is that you take
the equation, which is continuous
and you take a discrete set
of equations
one for each compartment
you connect it together
in a big matrix of connectivity
and you solve this matrix numerically;
each matrix represents a piece
of a membrane
a little segment,
a little compartment
plus the ions that runs there,
it could be synaptic
or in the case of axon,
it could be excitable channels,
we can do all this by simulation,
like Hodgkin actually simulated
the axon
using compartmental modeling
already there,
this is a much sophisticated way
to do it today
using the cable equations
and including synapses
non-linear excitable channels
or anything you want for the membrane.
We have this capability,
and we have this online free software
to implement this compartmental
numerical modeling of neurons
So, for example, you can study
what is the local effect of a synapse
using this simulation approach.
For example, if your synapse
so if your G-synapse
was located distally
and this would be an excitatory
synapse
so excitatory post synaptic
potential (EPSP) locally
you will see that this is a very,
very localized spread
because of this big attenuation
of the synapse
the synapse will affect only very
locally the dendritic tree
and a very, very small
amount of the charge
of the current injected
by the synapse
will reach the cell body.
So, as I mentioned before
this region can have
a big de-polarization
of let's say 10 millivolts
and the cell body will get something
extremely small
maybe 0.5 millivolts
So, the EPSP will attenuate severely
And this means that you cannot use
one EPSP, typically,
to reach threshold for spike varying
at the axon.
You need many EPSPs
if you put your synapse here
it will be very locally affecting
other local synapses
integrating together,
generating local de-polarization
if these are EPSPs
but the big effect will be local
and then it will spread and attenuate
distally.
These are the only synapses
that work.
If the synapse is directed
to the soma, like here
then of course, at the soma
you will get a bigger EPSP
Then, if this same synapse would
have been distally
so this is the type of thing
you can do today, easily,
using neuron simulation
or other simulations
in a compartmental modeling
of this reconstructed dendritic tree.
Ok, so I think we came to a summary
of how to model synaptic potentials
and how to look at it,
in some sense, integratively.
Ok, so I mentioned that locally
you have rather large
sometimes synaptic potentials
both excitatory
as well as inhibitory
But not in the same synapse,
or some synapse generate EPSPs
some other synapses IPSP,
the same dendrite.
And the fact that you have cable
cause these dendrites or synapses
to attenuate from the site of origin
to other regions,
not only to the soma,
so, this synapse may affect
other regions
but it attenuates very steeply,
each synapse attenuate very steeply
because of the cable properties
of the dendrites.
This means, as I said,
that locally
let's say an EPSP could be
on the spine head
where it's initiated 20, 30 millivolts,
but you will see
very small perturbation
small EPSP very attenuated
but also smeared out
broad at the soma,
maybe half a millivolt, maybe less
That means that you need on the order
of maybe 100 or more
excitatory synapses
to converge into the dendritic tree
within a given time window
in order for them to summate some
on top of each other
together, to reach threshold
for spike firing.
Maybe 100 synapses,
each one contributes half a millivolt
a third of a millivolt at the soma,
this should ride on top of the other
they should sum up with each other
in order to reach threshold
for spike firing.
If they don't,
then there will be no spike.
If there is enough excitatory
synapses
but at the same time you will get
a lot of inhibitory synapses
then the inhibitory synapses will tend
to dampen the excitatory synapses
because they have negative signal
and also because they shunt
the membrane
their open conductances
So the excitatory current
cannot reach the soma
because it is shunted
by the inhibition
so this inhibitory effect
is very critical.
So actually, the brain in general
and in particular neurons are very
much dependent on this balance
between excitation and inhibition.
You should imagine
a lot of excitatory coming
let's say in the pyramidal cell
you have 8,000 excitatory synapses
bombarding the tree
8,000
but there are also 2,000 inhibitory
synapses  or 1,500
that tend to dampen
the excitation,
and to shunt, to avoid
this excitation,
and whether there will be spike
or not
really depends on this balance
between how much excitatory charge
reaches the soma
and how much inhibitory charge
dampens the current
from not reaching the soma.
The end result,
the sum of all this charge
of many, many synapses
out of 10,000 will determine whether
you will get one spike, two spikes
a train of spikes, a music of spikes
tatata, stop, tatata and so forth,
this will be determined critically.
But how much charge arrives
to the soma
positive and negative,
whether it reaches threshold
or much above threshold,
or almost threshold,
whether one spike, two or three
and also of course
the pattern of activity
as I showed you early will depend
on the property
of the excitable channels
in the axonal membrane.
Some axon will like by themselves
to fire with burst
some will like to fire repetitively,
so it's the charge that arrives,
plus the properties of the axon
that will eventually determine
the particular music
that this neuron is now playing.
Whether it's tatata stop,
stop, stop, tatata
Whether tatatatata and so forth...
And this is underlying
the neuronal code
so it's extremely important
to understand how synapses converge,
interact, integrate in the dendrite
reaching the soma,
axon, and what type of axon property,
axonal property, excitable properties,
how do the axon
interpret these charge
whether by a burst or not.
When something goes wrong
when you have imbalance
between excitation, inhibition
let's say in the case
of epileptic seizure
then the whole brain goes wild:
too much excitation.
If there is too much inhibition
then the brain is too quiet:
no activity.
And so, the balance is critical
but also the type of activity
within this network
is probably standing as an
essence of the type of behavior
the state of the brain
whether you are going to be a deep
sleep, REM sleep, no sleep,
whether you will have difficulties
in sleep,
whether you will be happy
or sad.
All these activities that emerge
from the synapse
and output axons is really something
that we must understand
both in health and disease.
Lastly, but I'm not going to talk
about this today
these synapses that I mentioned
are a wonderful source of changes
in the brain, underlying memory,
learning and memory
because I told you that these
synapses may change their efficacy:
because they are analogue signals
they may become stronger or weaker
as a function of some activity
we understand only little
about this plasticity rules,
but the plasticity
is within the synapses
so, they preserve the memory
and when they become stronger
or weaker
when they form new synapses between
neurons
you form new capability for a circuit
to be active in a particular way,
generates its own particular
new music
which will stand
for your new learning:
the letter A, a new face,
a new feeling, a new idea.
We must understand synapses,
spikes and network activity
in order to understand a state
but we also must understand
plasticity in the synapses
in order to understand
the emergence of new states,
new creative states, hopefully,
and that's exactly what we are trying
to understand in neuroscience:
both the activity, the computation,
or the coding
that this activity stands for,
and also the plasticity and learning
all embedded in this electrical,
chemical activity
of this miraculous brain.