Hello everyone!
My name is Shrikanth Ramaswamy,
I'm a senior neuroscientist in
the Blue Brain project.
Today I will talk to
you about modeling
synaptic transmission
between neurons.
In the first part of the lecture
I'll talk about the synaptic brain
a brief history about the synapse,
what are the excitatory
and inhibitory synapses,
the process
of synaptic transmission,
the diversity
of neurotransmitters,
and synaptic receptors in the brain,
what's quantal release
and driving force,
mechanisms of
synaptic channel gating,
and how to model these mechanisms,
synaptic transmission mediated
AMPA and NMDA receptors,
and we'll conclude by providing
the summary of all that
I spoke about in this lecture.
The human brain consist
of about 86 billion neurons
which are connected to each other
by 100 trillion synapses.
In the nervous system,
a synapse is the structure
that permits a neuron
or a nerve cell
to pass an electrical
or a chemical signal
to another neuron.
the goal of any synapse is to
either excite or inhibit
the neuronal membrane
that generates or suppress
an action potential in the neuron.
Understanding synaptic function
is crucial for brain function
because synapses are implicated
in virtually all brain diseases
and psychotic illnesses.
Synapses can be chemical
or electrical.
However, this lecture will focus
only on chemical synapses.
The history of the synapse began
in the early 19th century
by the Italian anatomist
Camillo Golgi who proposed
the Reticular theory which
postulated that
the nervous system consists
of a continuous network
or "Reticulum".
According to Golgi's Reticular
theory there are fibers, dendrites
and neuron cells that would be
directly connected to each other
by cytoplasmic bridges
with neuron cell bodies
that were meant to provide
only nourishment support.
However, and equally
illustrious anatomist in Spain
by the name of Santiago Ramón y Cajal,
around the same time
challenge Golgi's Reticular theory
and postulated that
the nervous system
is not a continuous network,
but rather consists of separate
discontinuous units,
or nerve cells called neurons.
Cajal proposed the Neuron doctorine
by adding the law
of dynamic polarization
which states that neuronal signals
only travel in one direction
in the neuron,
from the dendrites and cell bodies
to axons.
Golgi's Reticular
theory was rejected
by the Neuroscience community as
false and Cajal's Neuron Doctorine
failed to explain how a signal
could be transferred from
one neuron to the next.
All those specialized
contact regions
in neurons were
soon suspected
to be responsible for this process
of exchanging information.
No mechanistic explanation
would actually be forthcoming
for a considerable amount of time.
It was only in the 1930's
that Charles Scott Sherrington
at the university of Oxford
adapted the term "synapse"
from the greek "syn",
meaning together
and "aptein", meaning to clasp,
and coined the term "synapse"
that's widely used in
neuroscience today.
So what is the process of
synaptic transmission in detail?
Let's first look at
the structure of the synapse.
Virtually every synapse in
the mammalian brain consists of
a presynaptic locus, which is
a part of the presynaptic cell
and the axon terminal of
the presynaptic cell.
And the presynaptic locus consists
of a neurotransmitter that's packed
into synaptic vesicles.
A synapse also consists of
the postsynaptic locus
with the post synaptic
receptors on
the dendrite of
the postsynaptic cell
and the pre and postsynaptic
loci are actually separated
by a small synaptic cleft
in the order of nano meters.
Then an action potential invites
the presynaptic terminal,
it causes the release of the calcium
by opening calcium channels
in the presynaptic terminal,
and calcium channels in
the presynaptic terminal
then cause
neurotransmitter release.
Neurotransmitters that's released,
flows across the synaptic cleft
and it binds
to postsynaptic receptors
which are nothing
by ion channels
and these ion channels
open and close
depending of the kind
of neurotransmitter
and 'cause the conductance
change that creates a current flow,
and the current flow actually
causes post synaptic
potential changes,
and the postsynaptic
cell could either get excited
or inhibited depending on
the kind of neurotransmitter.
And it's the summation of
the postsynaptic potentials
that actually decide whether
an action potential occurs or not.
So in summary:
when neurotransmitter is
released it flows across the cleft
binds to receptors,
postsynaptic receptors
which are nothing but ion channels
which open or close depending
on the kind of neurotransmitter.
This causes the conductance change
and therefore a current flow
in the postsynaptic membrane
and creates a postsynaptic
membrane potential change.
And depending on the kind
of neurotransmitter
the postsynaptic cell is
either excited or inhibited
and it's the summation
of postsynaptic potentials
that actually determines whether
an action potential occurs or not.
Let's go back to
the structure of the synapse.
As I mentioned before,
a synapse consists of
a presynaptic locus and
the postsynaptic locus
that's separated
by a synaptic cleft.
Now the presynaptic part
consist of vesicles that
are tiny sacs
containing neurotransmitters.
The postsynaptic locus actually
consists of many postsynaptic
receptors on the dendrites
of the post synaptic neuron.
When the neurotransmitter is
released it flows across the cleft
and bind to post synaptic receptors.
So the presynaptic part is basically
responsible for the release
of vesicles which contain
the neurotransmitter
and also to oversee
the dynamics of the vesicle pool,
whereas the postsynaptic locus
is responsible to ensure that
the neurotransmitter
binds to receptors
and the receptors that
are opening and closing
cause a synaptic current.
The synaptic current that's
generated at
the postsynaptic receptor
due to the neurotransmitter release
can be mathematically formulated
as the synaptic current,
I(syn) is equal to
the synaptic conductance g(syn),
multiplied by the driving force
of the synapse which is represented
by the difference between
the membrane potential
of the post-synaptic part
and the universal potential or
the equilibrium potential of
the postsynaptic receptor.
You're already familiar with
what's the driving force
based on Idan Seget's lecture,
but I'll just refresh your memory
again.
So the driving force is represented
by the difference between
the membrane potential
and the universal potential
of an ion channel, or the synaptic
receptor in this case.
And the universal potential
is the membrane potential
at which a given neurotransmitter
causes no net current flow of ions
so the neurotransmitter
receptor's ion channel.
In the brain there are
broadly two kinds of synapses
Excitatory synapses
and Inhibitory synapses.
Excitatory synapses cause
the release of glutamate
as the primary neurotransmitter.
Glutamate released then causes
the opening of sodium channels
in an excitatory synapse,
whereas in an inhibitory synapse
the primary neurotransmitter
released is GABA
and GABA released causes
the opening of chloride channels
in the postsynaptic locus.
Excitatory or glutamatergic synapses
are also called asymmetric
or Type 1 synapses,
because if you looked at
the structure of an excitatory
synapse under an electron microscope
you would see an asymmetry
between the presynaptic locus
and the postsynaptic locus.
Excitatory synapses consist
of AMPA synapses
that mediate fast
synaptic transmission
or NMDA synapses, that mediate
slow synaptic transmission.
The typical universal potential of
an excitatory synapse is around 0mV
whereas inhibitory,
or GABAergic synapses
are also know as symmetric,
or type B synapses.
Why?
Because again, if you looked
at the structure of
an inhibitory synapse under
an electron microscope
you would see that the presynaptic
and the postsynaptic loci
are actually symmetric.
Our inhibitory synapses
consist of GABA A synapses
that mediate fast
GABAergic transmission
GABA A synapses have a typical
universal potential of about -80mV
and GABA B synapses, that mediate
slow GABAergic transmission,
GABA B synapses have a universal
potential of around -100mV.
The universal potential of
the GABA A synapse is close
to the universal potential
of chloride ions
whereas the universal potential
of GABA B synapse is close to
the universal potential
of potassium channels or ions.
There's a huge diversity of
neuro transmitters in the brain
as you've just learned before,
excitatory synapses cause
the release of glutamate that
could be picked up by AMPA
or MNDA, or metabotropic
glutamatergic receptors.
These receptors could further
be ionotropic or metabotropic
I'll talk to you
about ionotropic
and metabotropic
receptors soon after
and AMPA receptors mediate
very fast synaptic transmission
and NMDA receptors
are voltage dependent
mediate slow synaptic transmission.
Metabotropic glutamatergic
receptors as well mediate
slow synaptic transmission
and are coupled to intercellular
proteins and second messengers,
I'll talk to you again
about this a little later.
Inhibitory synapses,
as you've just learned
release GABA as
the chief neurotransmitter
and GABA could be sensed by either
GABA A receptors or GABA B receptors
GABA A receptors
mediate fast inhibition
GABA B receptors
mediate slow inhibition.
In addition to glutamate and GABA
there's also a zoo of
neuromodulators in the brain
such as acetylcholine, which is
responsible for wakefulness
and the tension,
noradrenaline
which is
responsible for arousal
serotonin and dopamine,
which are responsible for
motivation, reward,
and happiness
and histamine that's responsible
for hunger, thirst,
as well as wakefulness.
So these neuromodulators
are also sensed by a diversity
of receptors which are either
ionotropic or motabotropic.
Just like there's a diversity of
neurotransmitters in the brain
there's also a diversity of
synaptic receptors in the brain
but synaptic receptors
could be considered
under two broad classes:
ionotropic receptors
and metabotropic receptors.
So, how are these receptors
different from each other
and how do they function?
Let's look at
the ionotropic receptors.
When the neurotransmitter
flows across the cleft
it binds to receptors on
the postsynaptic membrane.
and these synaptic receptors
are nothing but ion channels
which actually open
to let certain ions in,
depending on the kind of
neurotransmitter that's released.
If the neurotransmitter released
was glutamate, that causes
the flow of sodium ions
across the membrane
from outside of the cell
to the inside of the cell.
If the neurotransmitter
released released is GABA
that causes the flow
of chloride ions
from outside the cell
to inside the cell.
And when these ions flow
from outside to inside
they cause a membrane potential
change in the postsynaptic receptor,
and depending on what kind
of neuron transmitter released
if it's glutamate,
it causes the depolarization
of the postsynaptic membrane,
if it's GABA it causes
the hyper polarization
of the postsynaptic membrane.
The second class
of synaptic receptors
are metabotropic receptors.
Metabotropic receptors
have a more complicated
function than ionotropic receptors.
So how do metabotropic
receptors work?
When the neurotransmitter
flows across the cleft
it binds to postsynaptic
metabotropic receptors.
and the binding of neurotransmitter
activates G proteins, which are
intercellular proteins inside
the postsynaptic neuron.
These intercellular proteins
G proteins,
consist of many sub-units
alpha, beta, or gama,
for example.
When G protein is activated
upon a neurotransmitter binding
it causes further activation
of intercellular messengers
which are like transport
mechanisms inside the cell
and these intercellular messengers
then modulate ion channels
and when ion channels
are modulated they open
and let ions that are outside
of the cell flow through them
to inside of the cell.
If the neurotransmitter released
is glutamate then that causes
a net depolarization of
the postsynaptic membrane.
Whereas if the neurotransmitter
released is GABA
that causes a net hyper polarization
of the postsynaptic membrane.
Let's do a quick recap about
all that I've just spoke about.
Now you know that a synapse
consists of a presynaptic locus
and a postsynaptic locus
that are separated by a synaptic cleft
the presynaptic part consists of
vesicles that are packed with
neurotransmitters,
and the post synaptic part
consists of receptors that send
the flow of neurotransmitter across
the cleft and the neurotransmitters
that are released binds to
postsynaptic receptors to either
hyper polarize or depolarize
the post synaptic membrane.
The presynaptic part
consists of vesicle release
maintaining the dynamics
of the vesicle pool
and the postsynaptic part ensures
that the transmitter binds to
the receptors and that the opening
and closing of receptors result in
the synaptic current.
So the universal potential,
or the equilibrium potential
of a synapse, that Idan Segev
already spoke to you about earlier,
determines that
the driving force of a synapse
and the driving force along with
the synaptic conductance
determines the net current
that's generated in the synapse.
Let's focus a bit more
on the mechanism
of neurotransmitter released and
the driving force at the synapse
When neurotransmitters
are released into the synapse
they are released in
packaged vesicles called Quanta.
So these vesicles
called Quanta are sacs
that are packed with
neurotransmitter
a single quantum of vesicle release
generates what is known
as a miniature end plate potential.
The miniature end
plate potential
is the smallest amount
of stimulation that
one neuron can send
to another neuron.
Each synapse further has a number
of independent release sites
denoted by N
and each release site N
releases a single vesicle
with a certain probability
of a release, P(rel).
So this release probability P(rel)
or U(t) as it will be the explained
to you in the subsequent
part of the lecture
when I will talk about implementing
a widely used synapse model.
So the number of released vesicles
obeys a binomial distribution
and the release probability
the overall release probability
at a synapse is actually a function
of the number of released vesicles
and the number of released
vesicles further depend on
the number of release sites
and the probability of
release of a single vesicle.
So the mean of
the number of release sites
is actually a function of the number
of independent release sites
and the probability of release
of a single vesicle.
So when neurotransmitter
is released it causes a change
in the synaptic conductance
and that then causes
a synaptic current.
The synaptic current could either
hyperpolarize or depolarize
the postsynaptic membrane,
depending on the synaptic
conductance and the driving force,
which is nothing but the difference
of the membrane potential
of the postsynaptic membrane
and the reversal potential
of the synapse.
Furthermore,
the synaptic conductance
is the function of the peak synaptic
conductance a the synapse
which is also governed by
the number of release sites
and the release probability.
Another way to modify
the synaptic channel gating is
by means of double
exponential synapse
which is to model slow
synaptic transmission
such as synaptic transmission
mediated by MNDA receptors.
So in the case where
double exponential synapse
the synaptic response is
characterized by an opening
or a rising phase that indicates
the opening of the receptor
and a closing, or a decay phase,
that indicates
And another way to model
the synaptic channel gating is by
means of a double
exponential synapse.
This is particularly useful to
model slow synaptic transmission
such as synaptic transmission
mediated by an MNDA receptor.
The kinetics of a double exponential
synapse is characterized by
a rising phase that indicates
the opening of a receptor
and a decay phase,
that indicates the closing
of a receptor.
So the double exponential synapse
is a sum of two exponential
the rising phase exponential
and the decay phase exponential
the rising phase is overseen
by a rise time constant, τ(d)
and the decay phase is governed
by the decay time constant, or τ(d)
and k is the normalization
coefficient that is used
to determine the kinetics of
the double exponential synapse.
There are two main types of
excitatory synaptic receptors
in the brain, AMPA
and NMDA receptors.
AMPA receptors,
as I've mentioned before
mediate fast synaptic transmission
and the associated ion channels
with AMPA receptors are more
permeable to sodium
and potassium ions,
rather than calcium ions.
On the other hand, NMDA receptors
mediate slower synaptic transmission
and are structurally more complex
than AMPA receptors
because NMDA receptors contain
separate binding sites
for a glutamate, or magnesium,
or zinc, for example
and NMDA gated ion channels
are more permeable
to calcium than sodium ions.
Let's try and understand a bit
more on how NMDA receptors work.
So when an action potential invites
the presynaptic terminal
it causes the release of glutamate.
The release of glutamate
then diffuses across
the synaptic cleft and is sensed
by the NMDA receptors.
NMDA receptors at
resting membrane potential
which is typically around -70mV
when the neuron is at rest
are blocked by magnesium ions
that prevent the flow of sodium
or calcium ions from
outside cell to inside cell.
These magnesium ions are released
when the membrane potential
of the neuron is about -30mV
and when the magnesium
block is released
at more depolarizing potentials,
then that causes the entry
of sodium and calcium from
outside of the cell
to inside of the cell
through the NMDA receptor.
So the NMDA receptor only conducts
when the membrane potential
is greater than -30mV, and in
the presence of glutamate.
NMDA receptors have important
physiological functions, for example
they act as molecular coincidence
detectors that sense the entry
of sodium and calcium influx from
outside of the cell
to inside of the cell
and this has many
intercellular effects
which for example, could cause
mechanisms of long term potentiation
or long term depression,
which are fundamental
for learning N memory.
So, the NMDA receptor
is basically blocked by
magnesium at membrane potentials
close to the resting potential
that's about -70mV
and the magnesium block prevents
the influx of sodium or calcium ions
to the NMDA receptor.
However, at membrane potentials
of around -30mV
which is more depolarized
than the resting brain potential
the magnesium block is released,
and therefore the NMDA receptor
is able to conduct sodium
or calcium ions through it.
The total synaptic conductance at
an NMDA receptor is a function
of the concentration of magnesium
and the resting membrane
potential of the neuron.
Some experiments were
done by Craig Jahr
and Chuck Stevens in 1990
where Jahr and Stevens recorded
from cultured hippocampal neurons
actually showed that the synaptic
conductance at the NMDA receptor
is a function of
the magnesium concentration
and the resting membrane potential.
So what Jahr and Stevens did was,
they held their postsynaptic neuron
at different membrane potentials
from -80mV to +60mV
and at each of these potentials
they recorded the NMDA conductance
and found that at more
hyperpolarized potentials
closer to rest, for example,
are -80mV, -70mV
the NMDA conductance
was quite negligible
and the NMDA conductance marginally
began to increase in magnitude
when the magnesium block
was relieved around -13mV.
So Jahr and Stevens then came up
with a mathematical formulation
for the NMDA conductance,
which is a function of
magnesium concentration
and the resting membrane potential
which can actually be shown
through a series of sigmoid profiles
depending on
the magnesium concentration
and the holding voltage.
So the steep of the sigmoid is
a function of a magnesium
concentration
and the holding
potential of the neuron.
Therefore the total NMDA conductance
which is a function of the voltage
and magnesium concentration
times the release probability,
the number of release sites
and the release probability
times the driving force,
determines the total NMDA current
at a synapse.
So excitatory postsynaptic currents
in the brain are a combination
of AMPA and NMDA
receptor functions.
The AMPA response of
an excitatory postsynaptic current
is fast and short, whereas
the NMDA response of
an excitatory postsynaptic
current is slow and long.
The AMPA part could respond
to the early phase of
the postsynaptic current
and the NMDA could
respond to the late phase
of the postsynaptic current.
The contribution of the AMPA
and the NMDA receptor functions
to the postsynaptic current,
can actually be studied
pharmacologically by blocking
the NMDA component
or even the AMPA component,
for example
this is an experiment where,
at a more depolarized
membrane potential of about -40mV
where the NMDA receptors
are supposed to be active,
when NMDA receptors were blocked
the late component of
the synaptic current was also almost
blocked;
whereas at -80mV for example, which
is around resting membrane potential,
it was seen that the NMDA component,
which wasn't functional,
had no contribution what so ever to
the excitatory postsynaptic current.
So this can be even better
understood by means
of this current voltage
relationship after
synaptic current
where the black line actually shows
the AMPA component
and as you see here,
is already active around
resting membrane potential,
whereas the NMDA component
is not as active around
the resting membrane potential,
and for the NMDA component
to be active, the membrane
potential should actually be around
-30mV.
So in this part of the lecture
you've learned about
the structure of the synapse,
what are expiatory
and inhibitory synapses,
the diversity of synaptic
transmitters and receptors
in the brain,
what are ionotropic and
metabotropic receptors,
how does one model synaptic
channel gating either as
a single exponential,
or a double exponential,
what are AMPA and NMDA receptors,
how do they function,
and that NMDA receptors
are more complex in their
function compared to AMPA receptors,
because they are blocked by
magnesium ions at resting
membrane potential
and this block is only relieved
at more depolarized potentials
for -30mV, which then causes
the NMDA receptors
to conduct sodium
calcium ions through them.