Hi, I'm Elif Muller,
section manager for cells
and circuits at
the Blue Brain Project.
Today I'm going to show you how
to model your own synapses
in the neuron simulator.
In this tutorial,
you've used the NEURON simulator
to model neurons.
We will use the NMODL language
which is an extension of
the NEURON simulator
to allow you to define your
own synapse models.
We will walk you through this
process and the NMODL syntax
on the example of the model of
the AMPA and NMDA
glutamate receptors.
You will learn how to make
your own NMOD mod file
model AMPA and NMDA
glutamate receptors using
the NMODL language,
compile your MOD file
insert it into a simple
neuron and simulate it.
First, let's look into
how to edit MOD files
get an overview of their syntax.
The NMODL language is
a domain specific language
of the NEURON simulator
to define extension such as
ion channels, or synapse models.
To use the NMODL, the user
writes MOD files adhering to
the NMODL language syntax.
These are programs
external to Python
so it must be edited using
an external editor.
We will use the embedded editing
capabilities of the Jupyter system.
Going to the view of the files
available to the Jupyter notebook
on the home screen, we define
a directory called "mechanisms"
it can also be a directory
of a different name
where we will place our respected
MOD files we would like to include
in the NEURON
simulation environment.
I've prepared a simple
AMPA and NMDA MOD file
for the purposes of this tutorial.
By selecting this
file and clicking edit
you can edit this file interactively
in the Jupyter framework.
Now let's look at the various
sections of the NMODL MOD file.
It begins with comments
describing the contents
of the MOD file
a title, indicating
the purpose of the MOD file
and so on.
The first block to define
is the NEURON block.
This is a definition of
variables which maybe
accessed by the user in
the NEURON simulator environment.
These in include the parameters
you want to expose
to the user and various variables
that you would like to record.
Also this point process statement
defines the name of the mechanism
as treated in the NEURON simulator.
The next block is
the parameter block
which allows the user to define
constance which maybe set
in the NEURON simulator environment.
For this example, we're using
the dual exponential
conductance profiles,
for both the AMPA receptor
and the NMDA receptor.
Here we provide the rise and decay
time constants for
the AMPA conductance
and also the NMDA conductance.
Next, we define the reversal
potential for AMPA and NMDA
and the magnesium concentration
which is required to  implement
the voltage gate of
the NMDA conductance.
Gmax AMPA and the Gmax NMDA
are the conductances of the AMPA
and the NMDA receptors, respectively
in units of micro Siemens.
In the next block, the state block,
we declare the state variables
which make up this mechanism.
Since we're implementing
dual exponential rise kinetics
and decay kinetics of
the respective conductances
we need to implement
two state variables
for both the AMPA and the NMDA
conductances.
The rise kinetics
and decay kinetics.
Next we have the assigned block
this is
the declaration of variables
that are to be computed,
for example in the break point block
which we'll see in a second.
The next block is the initial block,
this is the definition of initial
conditions of state variables,
and is also where we should compute
any calibrating factors.
So first of all,
here we declare some
local variables that allows us
to compute some specific
calibrating factors.
Next we zero the receptor rise
and fall kinetics variables.
Here we compute the constance needed
to normalize the dual exponential
receptor dynamics.
First we have to compute
the expression for the time
to peak of the AMPA dual
exponential conductance
and the NMDA dual
exponential conductance.
Then we compute the normalizing
factor such that the peak
of the rise and decay mechanism
is exactly equal to one.
These factors implement
this normalization.
The next block is
the break point block
this is where we declare the method
to propagate the state
variables in time.
This is the essential simulation
block that defines how your model
will be simulated.
First you specify how to solve
the system of equations
which will be declared
below the derivative block.
The Cnx specifies integration method
it is an implicit integration method
that's stable even
for stiff systems.
Next we compute
and assign quantities
which depend on the state variables.
First we compute the time
varying AMPA receptor conductance
as the difference of the rise
and decay kinetic variables
B AMPA and A AMPA.
This gives us the exponential
rise and decay.
Similarly for NMDA we can compute
the rise and decay kinetics
of the NMDA conductance.
Now we have an additional term
to implement the magnesium
block kinetics,
due to Jarl and Stevens, 1990.
Then the total
conductance is the sum
of the AMPA
and the NMDA conductances.
Next we can compute the specific
currents of AMPA and NMDA.
These are simply the conductance
multiplied by the driving force
which is the instantaneous
membrane voltage
minus the reversal potential.
Finally we can compute
the total current due to
these combined receptors.
The next block is
the derivative block.
This block declares the ODEs to
be solved in the break point block.
Here we see that the rise and decay
kinetics of the AMPA and NMDA
follows decaying exponentials
with their respective
time constants.
The final block in the MOD
file is the net receive block.
This is the block
to be executed
when a presynaptic
spike even arrives.
In this case,
when a spike even arrives
each of the rise and decay
kinetic variables is increased
by a specific jump factor.
This triggers the postsynaptic
response kinetics.