Finally, let's configure the synapse
to realistic biological ranges
for the AMPA and
the NMDA conductances
and the magnesium concentration.
We'll record both the NMDA and
AMPA conductances separately
to visualize their contribution to
the total conductance trajectory.
First we set the AMPA conductance to
1nS, a reasonable biological value
next we set the NMGA conductance
to approximately 70% of
the AMPA conductance
as it is a biologically typical
ratio of NMDA to AMPA
and we set the magnesium
concentration to 1mM.
Next we set up recording vectors
for the NMDA and AMPA
specific conductances,
and then we run the simulation.
Now we can plot the time courses
of the total conductance
and the NMDA and the AMPA
conductances separately.
In this case we've used
the "axis" command
to zoom in to the pulse
occurring at 100ms.
As you can see the total conductance
and the AMPA conductance
are in a pretty close agreement
but there's an additional long tail
component of the total conductance
which is due to the NMDA
component in our synapse model.
Finally, let's plot the dependence
of the NMDA conductance
on the magnesium concentration.
Here we record the NMDA
conductance trajectory
due to 1mM, magnesium
and now we're going to
compute the trajectories,
simulate the trajectories for
a range of magnesium concentrations
going from 0.5mM down to 0mM.
And we're going to assess each of
the time courses of
the NMDA conductance.
Let's execute that step,
and now the last step.
As you can see, the conductance
trajectory for the NMDA component
is rather small for realistic values
of the magnesium concentration
as magnesium goes towards
zero concentration
the overall magnitude of
the NMDA conductance
is increasing dramatically.
This indicates that the NMDA
receptor requires the presence
of magnesium for the voltage block
to be effective.