Now to test our synapse model,
we need to create a neuron
to host our synapse.
Following previous exercises
we will create a single compartment
soma neuron
to host the synapse.
We start by creating a section
object defining its length,
diameter, and inserting
passive membrane properties
and we configure the biophysics,
that is the axonal resistance
and capacitance for each section.
Next we can create the synapse at
the center of the soma compartment.
Because the mechanisms
have been loaded
this simple AMPA and NMDA name
is now a part of the "h" name space.
We can create our synapse model
onto the soma at the center
using this command.
This results in the synapse object.
Now, let's define a stimulus
for our synapse.
Here we're going to define 8 spikes
at 20Hz starting at 100ms
plus one last spike
500ms later.
To this end, we will create
the simulator variable.
It is an instance of
a "vectstim" object
which is a mechanism which was
defined in the vecevent.mod file
along side synapse.mod file
we've just defined.
This mechanism is a standard
mechanism for NEURON
that allows you to define
the lists of spike times to
be played back to synapses.
To use this mechanism,
we define a list of spike times
here at 100ms, 150ms, 200ms,
and so on
as described above.
We create a "hoc" vector
of these spike times
and we invoke the play
command of the "vecstim" object
on this vector.
Next, we create a "netcon" object,
as you've seen in previous tutorials
connecting the simulator
to the synapse
and we define a weight of 1.
Now let's create a recorder for
the synaptic conductance
the current, the soma voltage,
and the time intervals
for this simulation.
To do this, as in previous tutorials,
we define vectors and we record
from specific references within
the synapse object
and the soma object.
Time is recorded from
the "h" object, as seen here.
Now we're ready to
run our first simulation.
First, let's zero
the NMDA conductance
and validate that
the AMPA conductance
is behaving as we expect.
First we simulate,
then we plot
the voltage and
the conductance trajectories.
To begin we define the total length
of time the simulation will run.
In this case it's 1000ms, or 1s.
We zero the conductance of the NMDA
component of the synapse model
and set the AMPA component
of the synapse model conductance
to a realistic value of 1nS.
Next we execute
the "neuron.h.runsim" step
to execute the stimulation.
Now let's run all the cells
up until this point
to start to plot the output,
so we can run "run all above".
Now we can plot the results.
This command gives us fancy
interactive inline plots.
Next, we define
a convenience function
to plot time courses
of depended variables
and lets plot the voltages as
a function of time
for this simulation.
As you can see we have
a series of synaptic events,
neuron is at rest at -70mV,
the postsynaptic potential
is just under 1mV for
each of the 20Hz pulses
and then 500ms later we have
one pulse as defined in our incoming
spike train.
The dual exponential model for
the conductance time course
has a closed form for the response,
due to a single pulse.
Below, we validate our MOD file
implementation running in NEURON
against this closed form solution.
So first we plot the time course
simulated in NEURON for
the synaptic conductance.
Here we compute the dual
exponential time course using
closed form expression
and we plot that on the same axis
for comparison for the pulse
occurring at the 100ms.
We take into account the connection
delay in the "netcon" object.
Let's see what this produces.
As you can see in red,
the mathematical expression
appears to be lying close to
the solution due to NEURON.
Let's zoom in
and take a closer look
by clocking on these hairs,
these cross hairs
and dragging, we can zoom
in on that specific response.
As you can see, the closed
mathematical expression
is in good agreement with what's
coming out of the NEURON simulator.
This model appears to
be doing what we expected.
Now let's also validate
the trajectory
for the NMDA receptor alone.
Here we have to remove
the magnesium block by zeroing
the magnesium concentration.
So first we set the NMDA
conductance now to 1nS
we've zeroed the magnesium
concentration and we set the AMPA
conductance to zero.
And again, we run the simulation.
Now  we can plot
the time course again
and we can see a few features
of the NMDA conductance
that are remarkably different.
Again, there's good agreement
between the mathematical expression
and the NEURON expression,
but we can see that the decay time
course of the NMDA
receptor is much slower
and therefore over
the course of these spike trains
these conductances
will accumulate.