Now we can go back to our notebook
and see if the MOD
file compiles correctly.
As before, we use NRNIV model
to compile our new mechanism.
Let's evaluate that cell.
And indeed, the compilation seems
to have completed successfully.
As seen by this statement,
should an error have occurred
error messages would
have occurred on this line.
Now let's try our synapse model,
as before we configure
the NEURON interpreter
we configure a neuron
to host out synapse in.
Now, let's create the synapse at
the center of the soma compartment.
Here, we've replaced simple AMPA
and NMDA with our new
Tsodyks Markram
AMPA NMDA model name.
Keep in mind that this name has
to exactly agree with the name
we provided in
the process declaration
in the NEURON block
of the NMODL file.
Now let's go to full screen.
Next we define the stimulus
again we will use 8 spikes at 20Hz
and a subsequent
single spike 500ms later
as our standard protocol.
Again, we define
a "VecStim" mechanism
we provide the spike times
as a list in units of milliseconds
and we execute the play statement
on a vector of those spike times.
A "NetCon" object is created
to connect the stimulator
with the synapse object.
We define the weight of
the connection to be one.
And it's in units of nano Siemens.
Next we create a recorder for
the synaptic conductance
current, sum of voltage,
and time intervals as before
and also for U(se) and R state
variables of the synapse model.
Now let's configure biologically
plausible values for the AMPA
and NMDA model parameters.
First, the AMPA conductance
will take on the value of 2nS
and the AMPA conductance
and the conductance of
the NMDA channel
will take on 70% of the value
of the AMPA conductance.
And magnesium is set to 1mM.
First, to try out our model,
let's configure parameters for
the pseudo linear synapse
dynamics E3 and simulate.
To this end we configure a baseline
release probability of 0.2,
a recovery time constant of 200ms,
and facilitation time constant
that is approximately equal to
the recovery type constant
here 200ms.
Let's run for a total time
of one second
and plot the results.
Here we use similar plotting
functionality to
the previous tutorial.
We use this magic command
to invoke fancy interactive
inline plots.
This is a convenience function to
plot time courses of state variables
through the simulation.
Now, let's plot the time course of R
and U(se) throughout the simulation.
In this graph, each
of these saw-tooth jumps
are the times of occurrence
of the pre-synaptic spike
when a post-synaptic release
event has been triggered
as it can be seen in the time course
of the synaptic conductance
of this synapse.
The blue trace indicates
the fraction of readily
releasable vesicles
and at each pre-synaptic event it is
jumping down by a certain amount
and after which it is recovering
with a time constant of 200ms.
As you can see here,
after about 450ms
there's an exponential relaxation
with a time constant of 200ms
towards the fully
recovered value of 1.
Conversely, for each synaptic spike
the running value of the release
probability initially jumps up
by a value of U1
and decays with a time constant
of tau_facilitation, in this case
200ms.
Since the time between spikes
is much shorter than
the time constant of
relaxation and facilitation
each incoming spike causes
an increase in the running value
of the release probability.
As such, we can see
a general trend of the facilitation
that is an increase in
the release probability
of the synapse.
Likewise, as the synapse facilitates
the fraction of readily releasable
vesicles that is emitted
for a given pre-synaptic spike,
is increasing.
However, this is balanced
with the fact that the total
fraction of available
vesicles is depleting.
According to this general trend.
As a result for
the pseudo-linear synapse
the overall total conductance,
although it fluctuates
maintains a fairly even value.
In this case, somewhere
between 0.4nS and 0.5nS.
Now let's configure
a depressing synapse E2.
Such synapses have a much
higher baseline release probability
a longer recovery time from
depression and a very short
relaxation time of facilitation.
Now, here we can see
the analogous plot
for the depressing synapse.
As you could see,
the initial release probability
of this synapse is 0.5,
and exactly half or
the readily releasable pool
is released on the first
pre-synaptic spike.
And subsequently half is released
again and half is released again
and half is released again,
and so on.
There is a very slow time
constant of recovery such that
in between spikes there's
very little recovery
of the readily releasable pool.
Now looking at the facilitation
dynamics, as you can see
the release probability
takes on a value of 0.5
and rapidly decays
back to baseline.
Such that,
for each pre-synaptic spike
the attained value of
the release probability
is only U1, or 0.5.
As a result the dynamics of this
synapse is determined primarily
by the dynamics of
the readily releasable pool.
And as such, the product of R
times U(se) equal to A
is a generally decreasing value,
as it can be seen
in the dynamics of the conductance.
an initially large value,
but generally rapidly decreasing
synaptic responses.
500ms later the synapse
has recovered somewhat
from this train of eight pulses,
but it hasn't recovered entirely
to it's baseline value.
That concludes our tutorial
on modeling synapse dynamics
with NEURON and
the NMODL language.