Now that we've
defined our "MOD" file
it needs to be compiled such
that it can be used in NEURON.
NEURON provides a tool
called "nrnivmodl"
which has the following syntax.
"Nrnivmodl" and then a directory.
Invocation will compile all
MOD files found in the directory
if specified,
otherwise it will compile
MOD files in the current directory.
Our MOD file is located
in the "mechanisms"
so we will compile it as follows.
Note, the exclamation mark
is used to invoke system call
outside Python,
as this application
is external to
the Jupyter framework.
Let's execute this statement.
Here's the output of the statement,
as you can see it is executing
a series of compilation steps,
note the successful completion
of the compilation.
It's important to verify that
the compilation is
successfully completed
if any error messages are generated,
then something may be wrong
in your MOD file program,
double-check your MOD file
and try again,
in such a case.
Now, let's try our new
synapse model out.
If your mod files are compiled
before you import NEURON
NEURON will load your
compiled models
automatically if they are
in your local directory.
In our case, because we
invoked "Nrnivmodl"
in the current directory,
they will be found automatically.
Let's proceed with
the initialization steps
as seen here.
More explicitly, we're importing
NEURON which will trigger
the loading of the MOD files
as compiled above
we're importing "numpy"
and "matplotlib"
for a numerical analysis
and plotting
and we're initializing
the neuron environment
as you have seen in
the previous tutorials.
It's important to know that,
if you forget to compile your
MOD files before importing NEURON,
you can trigger NEURON to load
them as follows.
Note, this command can only
be executed once for a given
directory of MOD files.
Executing it a second time will
will crash your Jupyter kernel.
As seen here.
As we execute the statement
the kernel will crash.
To recover from this we
don't have to recompile this step.
But we do have to
re-execute this line.
Let's comment that
line out to ensure
we don't crash our kernel again.