Hi and welcome to
our second tutorial
on modeling synapse dynamics.
We'll continue where we left off
modeling the glutamate receptor
in the previous tutorial,
and interactively augmented
with the model of short term
depression and facilitation.
In the previous lecture,
my colleague (INAUDIBLE)
described for you a model of
short term synaptic dynamics.
Facilitation and depression.
The commonly used model for
facilitation and depression
is the Tsodyks and Markram model.
As it was described previously,
the model accounts for
the dynamics of
a reserve vesicle pool.
In particular, the "Docked" vesicles
form the readily releasable pool.
In the Tsodyks Markram model
R refers to
the fraction of available
vesicles in the readily
releasable pool.
And U(se) refers to
the running probability of release.
These two variables, R and U(se),
make up the state variables
of the Tsodyks Markram model.
The R variable accounts
for synaptic depression
whereas the facilitation aspect
of the model is accounted for
in the second differential equation
in the dynamic of
the release probability.
Now, let's implement the various
components of this mathematical
formulation of
the Tsodyks Markram model
into a NEURON and model file.
The model we will implement
today is based on
the Tsodyks Markram model
for short term facilitation
and depression, as it is described
in the Fuhrmann 2001 publication
here.
In this tutorial, we're going
to learn how to implement
the mathematical formulations of
the model into NMODL syntax
and therefore gain a deeper
appreciation of
the different components
of the NMODL language,
and also a deeper understanding
of this widely used formulation
of synapse dynamics.
To begin, let's start where we left
off with the MOD file
for the simple AMPA
and NMDA receptor.
If we go to our Jupyter home space,
and go into the mechanisms directory
let's create a copy of the previous
MOD file which we will then
subsequently modify.
So, we duplicate, then we rename,
let's call it the Tsodyks Markram
AMPA and NMDA synapse.
Now, we can edit the file.
First let's update the comments.
Now that we've updated
the comments in the preambule
let's start adding the required
components to implement
this addition to the model.
First, we should
rename the point process.
This is the unique name given
to the model which we'll then
employ in the Jupyter
Python Interpreter to
create an instance of the model.
Here we will give it the name
"TsodyksMarkram_AMPA_NMDA".
Now let's add the additional
required parameters.
The Tsodyks Markram
model has three parameters.
A time constant for
recovery from depression
a time constant for relaxation
from facilitation
and a baseline release probability
in the absence of facilitation.
Now, let's add these parameters
into our NMODL file.
We can add these parameters of
the Tsodyks Markram model
as follows.
First, the time constant of
recovery from depression:
we'll give it an intermediate
value of 200 and the unit
of that value is milliseconds.
Here a comment, time constant
of recovery from depression.
Next, the second parameter
is the time constant
of relaxation from facilitation.
We'll also give that a time constant
for 200ms, these are default values
and they can be overridden
then in the Python Interpreter.
And the final
parameter is "U1".
We will give it an intermediate
value of 0.5
it's a dimensional's quantity
and it is the baseline
release probability.
Next we should add
the additional state variables
for the Tsodyks Markram model.
Let's add them here.
The state variables of
the Tsodyks Markram model
are the variables of the first order
time derivative on
the left hand side
that is R, the fraction of available
vesicles in the readily
releasable pool
and U(se), the running value
of the release probability.
We can add the state variables
U(se) and R as follows.
Simply declare them.
Give them a comment as to
their purpose and you're done.
In the assigned block of the synapse
no additional modification
are required.
Since we've added
two new state variables
we need to also declare
their initial conditions.
Here we give R the value of
a completely recovered
readily releasable pool,
that is that
the fraction of available
vesicles is equal to one
and the release probability we give
it its fully relaxed value of zero.
For the break point block
no additional modifications
are required except to model
the sub-block, defining the ODEs.
The ODEs are defined in this block.
Let's recap
the mathematical expression
for the Tsodyks Markram model.
This system of two ODEs has both
a time continuous component
as shown here,
and as shown here,
and event triggered components.
As shown here,
and here.
These two components will
be treated separately
in the NMODL file.
First let's consider the time
continuous components.
An ODE, a first order linear ODE for
the fraction of
the available vesicles
and likewise for the running
value of the release probability.
In the ODE's block we define only
the dynamics of the time
continuous component.
That is, R prime,
the time derivative of R
is equal to 1-R,
divided by tau_recovery
this results in an exponential
relaxation of R towards 1
that is an exponential recovery with
time constant of tau_recovery.
And secondly,
the continuous dynamics
of the running
release probability
U(se).
That is the time
derivative of the U(se)
is equal to -U(se) over
tau_facilitation.
This shows that U(se) exponentially
relaxes to a value of zero.
With a time constant of "tau_facil".
Finally we must augment
the "NET_RECEIVE" block
this is the piece of code that is
executed for each
pre-synaptic spike event.
First we must define a local
variable for the derived quantity A
which is the scalar
of the synaptic response as
a function of the least probability
and fraction of available vesicles.
Now, let's define the pre-synaptic
spike triggered updates
of the release probability and
fraction of available vesicles.
Now, let's consider the event
triggered portions of this system
of ODEs.
This term in the differential
equation for the fraction
of readily releasable vesicles
is an event triggered component
as it can be seen by the delta
function with respect to time
of the pre-synaptic spike.
The meaning of this is that
at the arrival time of
the pre-synaptic spike
the fraction of available
vesicles is decreased
by an amount proportional to
the current fraction of
available vesicles and their
probability that they release.
The decrease is indicated
by the minus sign.
Likewise, the differential equation
for the release probability
also contains a spike
triggered term.
The meaning of this term
is that following a spike
the value of the release
probability takes on U1
if the running value of
the release probability is zero.
However, this model
accounts for facilitation in that
should the current running
value of the release probability
be greater than zero, then
the value of the release probability
will be incremented beyond
the baseline value of U1.
This term ensures that the value
of the release probability
never exceeds one.
The first update to compute is
the update of the running value
of the release probability,
U(se).
That is updated according
to the expression given
U goes to U(se) plus
the additional delta term
in the ODE, U1 times one,
minus U(se).
The next update to compute
is the update of the fraction of
available vesicles.
Here, R goes to R minus U(se)
times R.
The fraction of available vesicles R
is reduced by an amount
proportional to the currently
available vesicles
and the fraction of those
vesicles that are released.
The final step is
to compute the factor A
which modulates the synaptic weight.
We insert this term here,
here, here, and here
because it modulates, as we said,
the synaptic weight
so it should modulate each
of these cases where
weight appears.
And now, what value does A take on?
This system of differential
equations describes the evolution of
the fraction of available vesicles
and the running release probability
as a function of time.
For a series of pre-synaptic spikes
arriving at times as indicated here.
These traces give you the evolution
of the respected state variables.
To compute the modulation of
the synaptic conductance
as a function of these
running R and U values
we multiply the overall synaptic
conductance by a factor A,
which is the fraction of vesicles
available in the readily
releasable pool
times the running value
of the release probability.
Interestingly, this product
is also the amount
by which R is deprecated for
each incoming pre-synaptic spike.
Also note, that as T
is time dependent and U(se)
is time dependent
the value of A is
also time dependent
and takes on specific values
at each point in time when
a pre-synaptic spike occurs
according to the running value of R
and U(se) at the time of the spike.
Now we add this A term
into the "NET_RECEIVE" block.
U(se) times R.
Now take note, one tricky aspect
of the Tsodyks Markram is where
"A" should be computed.
Depending on if you were
to compute "A" here, or here, or here
the value, or magnitude of
the synaptic transmission event
can be different.
It turns out that the correct
interpretation is to compute
"A" here
after the U(se) has been updated
with facilitatory mechanisms
but before the fraction of
readily releasable vesicles
has been depleted by
the release event.
Intuitively this makes sense
in so far as the fraction
of readily releasable vesicles that
is depleted is actually equal to A.
That is the readily releasable pool
is depleted by exactly those
vesicles which mediate
the synaptic response.
Now, we're almost done,
the only remaining thing to do
is to go back up to the top
to the NEURON block
and declare the additional
parameters such that they can
be configured by the user,
that is tau_recovery
tau_facilitation, and U1.
With that we've completed
our new MOD file of the AMPA
and NMDA glutamate receptor,
incorporating
Tsodyks Markram
short term dynamics.
Let's save the file.