Hi!
Today I will present two tools
we developed at the Blue Brain
to constrain biophysically
detailed neuron models
to experimental data.
Namely the "E feature extraction
library", in short eFEL
and BluePyOpt, which stands for
the "Blue Brain Python
Optimization Library".
This lecture will give
a broad overview
of the functionalities
of these tools.
In the tutorial, later on,
you will learn in more detail
how to use them.
The structure of this lecture
is as follows.
For the eFEL I will describe
the goal of the software
and show an example.
Regarding BluePyOpt
I have some slides
explaining
the optimization algorithm
some examples of how
BluePyOpt is used
and how it can benefit from
parallelization
on cluster computers.
This is a slide you have already
seen in a previous lecture.
It summarizes the different
components we use to model
electrical behavior of neurons.
In this lecture we will focus on how
to extract features from voltage traces
using eFEL to constrain our models.
Once we have these constrains we can
fit the densities of ion channels
or morphologies of the cells,
so that the models could use
voltage traces that match
the experimental data.
So let's start with the eFEL.
Here on the right,
you see an example
of an experimentally recorded
membrane voltage trace.
As you can see, the trace has
five action potentials in it.
The "E Feature Extraction Library"
consists of C++ code
with a Python wrapper
that allows you to extract
important features
from such traces.
These could've been recorded
from real neurons
but can as well be the output
of the electrical neuron model.
Examples of such features are
the width of the action potentials
the amplitude of
the action potentials
or, for example, the firing rate
of the neuron.
The eFEL library is Open Source,
and it's available on GitHub.
Here you see a practical example
of values determined by the eFEL.
When asked for the mean frequency
which is just a number of spikes
per second in a trace
the eFEL response with a value
of around 2.5Hz.
I also requested the amplitude
and the width of the spikes
and you see that we get
five different values
for these specific amplitudes
and for the widths of the spikes.
Typically the experimental data
will consist of many neurons
of the similar type.
Many traces have been
recorded from these neurons
from different protocols,
but also repetition
of the same protocol.
The eFEL enables us to automatically
analyze all these traces,
group the relevant features together,
and calculate an experimental mean
and standard deviation
for each feature.
We will require that the electrical
model for a certain type of neuron
stays within a certain range
of the experimental mean.
This is where BluePyOpt
comes into play.
We have the morphology of our neuron
and we have the description
of the ion channels
the only values that
are very difficult to measure
are the densities of
the different ion channels
along the dendrites.
BluePyOpt allows us to run
an evolutionary
optimization algorithm
to find parameter values for our
model so that the voltage traces
it generates following
the experimental constraints
set by the eFEL.
BluePyOpt is a Python library.
It tires to hide the complexity
of optimization algorithms
and tries to be extensible,
so that it can be applicable
to a wide variety of
neuro scientific problems.
In this lecture I will focus on
how to use BluePyOpt
to fit electrical models
of single cells.
Running such optimization
algorithms can be
very computationally expensive.
So we also provide instructions
together with BluePyOpt
on how to run this software
on large computing resources
like cluster computers.
So we basically have two inputs
to the evolutionary optimization
algorithm in BluePyOpt.
We have an electrical model,
which has some three parameters.p
Namely the densities of ion
channels along the morphology.
And we also have some
experimental constraints
that were extracted from
the experimental data using eFEL.
Then we run an evolutionary
algorithm applying these
constraints to the model
and we get some model parameters
that satisfy the constraints,
which is on the output
of our BluePyOpt software.
The evolutionary
algorithm works as follows.
We have a set of individuals
in a population.
Every individual represents
one set of parameter values
of the model.
We have an evaluation function
that maps the parameters to
objective scores
of the individual.
This is the part where
the experimental constraints
are used.
The closer the model output
matches the experimental data
the better the objective score.
We start the algorithm by
creating an initial population
of random individuals.
The parameters of these
individuals are randomly selected
with bounds specified
for every parameter.
Now the algorithm evaluates
every individual in the population
so that all the individuals
get objective scores.
Based on these scores, a ranking
is created in the population
and the best individuals
are selected as parents.
The Crosser operator then
is used to create children
from these parents.
This is done in a way so that
the parameters of the children
are the combination of the parents.
And the mutation operator
is applied to the children
to create some extra jitter,
and this new offspring
it forms is put together
with the parents
and it creates
a new population.
The individuals in the population
are evaluated again
and a new iteration starts.
So basically, we have a model
that creates better and better
parameter sets over time.
The algorithm keeps on
repeating and repeating itself
in cycles until
a certain stop criteria is met.
We can then use the best individuals
as parameters for our model.
To implement the evolutionary
algorithm BluePyOpt uses
under the hood DEAP library.
DEAP stands for the Distributed
Evolutionary Algorithms in Python.
More specifically,
we use an algorithm called
Indicator Based Evolutionary
Algorithm, or IBEA
which we implemented
in the DEAP framework.
An advantage of
this specific algorithm
is that it is multi objective,
which means that
it sees different objective scores
as different orthogonal dimensions.
It tires to spread the solutions
it finds as much as possible
on fronts of this multi
dimensional space
so that we get a high
diversity of solutions.
Like the eFEL,
BluePyOpt is available
as an Open Source
library on GitHub.
Now, let me give you two examples
to illustrate the workings
of BluePyOpt.
The first example is something
that will probably not be used
in the real world, but it helps
to explain the different concepts
used in BluePyOpt.
So we have a single
compartmental model
which has two parameters.
One for the maximum
conductance of the Sodium
and one for the maximum
conductance of the Potassium.
What we want to achieve is
to find parameter values
for this model, so that they are
constrained by two objectives.
We inject two different
current injections
in our cell and we check for every
step how many spikes are generated.
For the lower step
we want the model to
fire one action potential
and for the higher step, we want
to have five action potentials.
When feeding this problem
into BluePyOpt
it finds good solutions very quickly
within a couple of generations.
On this slide you see a plot
of the solutions base generated
by this example.
on the X and Y axis are the values
of the two parameters.
The maximum conductances
of sodium and potassium.
The core map shows how will
each pair of parameter values
match with our objectives.
The lower the value,
the better.
So blue colors represent
very good solutions.
For convenience,
I've plotted a blue circle
for all the solutions
that have a perfect score
which means that they have
one spike in the first current step
and five spikes in the other.
So basically, all the solutions
here are very good
and the rest of the solutions base
is visualized by all the scores.
In the second example,
I'll show an optimization
of a much more detailed model.
This is the kind of
optimization that was used
to fit the Layer 5
pyramidal cell model
for the Markram Et. Al. 2015
publication that contains
the description of a reconstruction
of a neo-cortical microcircuit.
What you see here is a detailed
morphological reconstruction
of a pyramidal cell.
BluePyOpt will need to search
for densities of ion channels
along the morphology in
four different zones.
We have the Apical and Basal
dendrites, and we also have
the Soma and the Axon.
Only the first initial
segment of the axon is used.
This is where the spike
initiation takes place.
Now we have twenty
parameters to optimize.
Sixteen of these are
maximum conductances
of different ion channels.
Every zone in the morphology
has a different mix of ion channels.
Channels can also be non uniformly
distributed within one zone.
There are another four parameters
controlling the dynamics of
the internal calcium of the neuron.
The constraints are taken
from three somatic recordings
each with a different
current amplitude.
We have recorded these
experimental traces from
five different individual
pyramidal cells.
The constraints we use are
an average of some features
over these traces.
We also have dendritic constraints
in a form of back-propagating
action potential.
We stimulate the soma
and we record at two different
locations this back-propagating
action potential.
The values we took from literature
constrain this shape of
the back-propagating action
potential in width and in height.
Both for our model and experiment
we extract from these somatic
and dendritic recordings using
the eFEL, a total of 35 e-features.
By comparing these to
the experimental mean
and standard deviation,
we can calculate the score
for every objective.
By dividing the value by
the experimental standard deviation
we make sure that all the objectives
have the same scale.
In this plot, the 35 objectives
are shown along the Y axis.
The X axis shows
the score of each objective.
The goal of the optimization
algorithm is to find a parameter set
which minimizes
all these objectives.
The X axis basically translates to,
when I record an e-feature
from the model output,
how many experimental
standard deviations is my model
away from the experimental mean
which is basically shown
here by this equation.
Here you see the results
of the optimization.
On the left we have the evolution
of the total objective value
so that's the sum of all
the objective scores
over the consecutive generations:
both of the best
individual of the population
and of the average
in the populations.
On the right, you see the traces
generated by the solution with
the lower score in dark blue.
The light blue traces
that are shown behind the dark blue
are the best ten individuals
or, this is what we call in
our software, the hall of fame.
Evaluation a detailed biophysical
neuron model can be
computationally very expensive.
You really have to do it many times,
during your evolutionary algorithm.
Luckily all these evaluations
are computationally independent
So we can easily panelize them.
BluePyOpt has a built-in
functionality to allow
the users to use,
for an example
the Python library (INAUDIBLE)
to run the algorithm on cluster
or cloud computers.
So in summary, I've shown
you the eFEL library
which provides functionality
to extract e-features from
experimental data
and model output;
and these e-features are used
as constraints for bio-physically
detailed neuron models.
BluePyOpt uses there constraints
in an evolutionary
optimization algorithm
to find suitable parameter sets
for such models.