Hello. In this part of the MOOC
we'll talk about the case
when it's difficult to find
experimental values
for your model parameters,
so, you have the problem of
under constrained parameters
and we would like to
use parameter optimization
in particular, meta heuristics
such as evolutionary algorithms
to help us in building
the good neuron models.
When you want the computer
to help you with it
you have to be able
to guide the computer
what is a good model
and what is a bad model
and for that, you'll need some way
of assessing the goodness
of fit of your model.
Furthermore
We will try to make a case
that using multi-objective
optimization is a good ingredient
to sort of expose certain trade offs
in the parameter space
and we'll give you an example
that hopefully convinces you
that these are useful techniques
to help us build
detailed neuron models
and of course, as always
there's some caveats
you'll have to consider.
Let's get started.
In previous parts of the MOOC
we were talking about in-framing
the problem by saying
you have a detailed
neuron morphology
and you have certain
electro physiological recordings
that you want to express in
mathematical terms
so that you have a computational
model of a neuron
that then can recreate this behavior.
We showed you
there are different data sets
that you should consider
when building up these models,
you start with morphology,
ideally you have a list
and identification of ion channels
that are creating
the electrical behavior,
possibly you have kinetic information
about how these channels behave,
and ideally you have also information
where these channels are
and how much of a certain channel
is in a certain part of the dendrite.
As we were saying earlier
sort of some of these data sets
might be easier to get
for the neuron of interest
and particular other data sets
like for example the localization
and the maximum conductance
might be less available.
So, when we're talking about using
resorting to computer based
search techniques
of course in principle you could
you could apply them to any
parameter in this space
but in particular we'll talk about
applying them to finding
the right location of a channel
and the maximum conductance.
So, what to do with under
constrained parameters?
Of course, the natural
course of science
is that you would hope that there
will be more experiments,
maybe even novel types of experiments
that can measure aspects
that were previously unmeasurable
and then, of course
you simply wait until this data
becomes available
and then you use that data.
Now, if you can't wait that long,
or essentially it is unlikely
that this will be done, you can
of course resort to guessing
these parameters and hand tune them.
You can be systematic about it
and simply sample
the different parameters in
a regular fashion
but that might become very easily
a large problem,
especially if you have many
parameters to search for.
Another strategy altogether
could be to say
"Well, maybe these are not all
independent parameters
but maybe you can express some
relation between two parameters"
For example the conductance
at 2 different locations
of the dendrite
and instead of searching for them
as individual parameters
maybe you can, again, express
this relation in a function
and sort of that has less parameters
in the first place.
A yet other way of thinking
about it is that maybe
you can infer parameters from other
and more easily measurable properties.
So, take the example
of the ion channel conductance:
ultimately what it means is sort
of how many channels are
in a certain unit area
of the dendrite.
Now, typically you could sort of say
"I could count them under a microscope"
but if you can't do that
why not infer at least
the maximum bound of that value
by saying looking at the size
of the ion channel complex
that it occupies in the surface
and then calculate how much
surface you have in this part
of the dendrite altogether
so at least you could infer
how many channels maximally
could fit into a certain
patch of dendrite.
So, while this is not giving you
the answer of the direct parameter
it at least gives you an upper value
which can be very useful.
So, in this spirit, of course
you could imagine other ways
of inferring properties.
But if all that doesn't help you,
then one possibility is to resort
to parameter optimization.
Parameter optimization
is a mathematical field
which you can express
in mathematical terms
for example for function F of X
which this might be the function
you're looking for certain X zero
that fulfills a certain criteria
for example that the evaluation
of a function at X zero
is the minimum for all of X,
so, you're looking for,
for example,
a global minimum of a function.
This is a longstanding problem
in mathematics
and different large variety
of methods have been developed
for solving these problems,
and first and foremost of course
you have calculus based methods
where you can simply say
"Ok"
"If I'm somewhere in this function
I possibly can calculate"
"the derivative and then
sort of, for example,"
"descend to local minimum, or I can
find maybe do the second derivative"
"and find all my extreme
oppositions" and so on.
So, if your function continues
and has certain properties
you can use these
calculus based methods.
Another group of methods
is when you can express your problem
in different terms.
For example, if you can express your
problem as a set of linear equations,
and then sort of express
the constraints in the same way,
and then you can use a technique
called linear programming
to address the optimization
in those cases.
And then, more generally
there's another class of methods
which fall under
the term of "iterative methods"
that do less assumptions about
the properties of the function;
and this is useful because in our
case, as a matter of fact,
we don't want to make particular
assumptions about our function.
What is our function?
We'll come to that,
but ultimately this is the neuron
model you want to evaluate
and it might be not fulfilling
properties that are required
for calculus based methods
or linear programming.
And, of course, in all of that
is you want to do this
with the minimum number
of function evaluations
because ultimately this
will cost you the time
if you have to sort of calculate
the function at every X
this might take a long time
A variant of parameter
optimization is instead of
trying to set out to find
the global minimum, global maximum
you might be able to get
away with finding a sufficiently
good solution
to an optimization problem
and that maybe because you have
incomplete information about
the problem in the first place
and limited computer capacity,
limited time, at your disposal
So, a metaheuristic says
"Instead of looking for this
global optimum, maybe you can
sort of have an approximation
or a set of reasonably
good solutions",
and in that sense, the metaheuristics
is not the categorization
of calculus based method
or an intuitive method,
but in fact it can be
a combination of the two,
and people have done and combined
for example, local gradient descent
methods with global heuristics
such as simulated annealing.
And another variant
of these metaheuristics
are population-based metaheuristics
like for example swarm optimization
or evolutionary algorithms, where
instead of having one search point
you have a multitude of search points
and treating them at the same time.
The good thing about metaheuristics
is that they make very few
assumptions on the
optimization problem,
and essentially therefore
can also give you approximate
solutions to otherwise possibly
intractable problems.
But that comes with the
down side of it, that essentially
they don't give you a guarantee on
whether is a globally optimal solution
and they tightly and closely
depend on the random number quality
you use for your
sampling of the space.
So, here you just need to be wary
that running your search algorithm
with different random seeds
and good random numbers
is a good quality and might
essentially be the make or break
when sampling a certain search space.
So, how would it look to use
a metaheuristic in neuronal modeling?
The schema is in a way that
you start with the model skeleton,
so in our case you choose
the formalism, like
multi-compartment Hodgkin-Huxley,
and then you have for example
the dendrite
you have the diameters
you have the bifurcations...
So let M be the equations
that describe the cable,
as well as the ion channel
of Hodgkin and Huxley,
and sort of ideally when you come
to this point
ywere able to fix certain
parameters with experimental data,
while another set of parameters
like this factor Pvar are now
the parameters you didn't constrain
with experimental data for which
you would find like to find
a good set by using
a parameter optimization.
So, then the search space
is essentially
the space that's spanned by all
these variables, and of course
they might not be the full
range of real numbers,
but it could be for example
in a certain interval.
What you then have to do
is you create essentially
an initial set of samples of this
search space, and then
you will evaluate
your model on these parameters,
so that for each of these
parameter sets X I
you're going to evaluate
the model equation
between a certain
start time and end time.
You're essentially calculating,
solving, the differential equation
in time for the cable equation
and the ion channels.
Once you've done that, you ideally
have some way of expressing
whether you like the solution or not.
So, you calculate a function
of the response of the neuron,
and that should then allow
you to sort that one
parameter point is better
than another one.
So you can create a ranking
between the different
points you originally started
out with sampling.
And then, in order to continue
you will retain the better ones
and from there generate,
decide, where your search continues
with a new evaluation,
and you keep going until
you hit a certain stop criteria
and the stop criterion
can simply be you ran out of time,
or your absolute value of a metric
reached something that is good enough,
or you have some other constraints
that make you stop the search.
So a particular variant
of metaheuristics are so called
"evolutionary algorithms", which
are population-based metaheuristics
and they are called
evolutionary algorithms
because they are inspired
by biological evolution:
so they use terms like reproduction,
mutation, recombination, selection,
and they call these points
in the search space
"individuals in a population".
So, if you look to the right,
this is an illustration
of how you can think of it
so you have the first generation N
which is a pool of individuals:
A, B, C, and D
and each individual has a genum
which encodes in genes
different search parameters.
For example, these could
be the conductances
of a certain type of channel
in a certain part of the neuron.
With this population
you then generate
and evaluate the phenotypes
so these channel conductances
translate into neuron model
which you can evaluate over time,
and then, you can create
the responses to certain stimuli
and with a mentioned fitness
function, distance function
you might be able to rank and select
that sort of you like solution B
better than A, better than C
and better than D.
And with that information
evolutionary algorithm can then say
"Ok, survival of the fittest:
solutions B and A were good",
so you allow them to, for example,
survive into the next generation
and also say "they are so good that"
"we allow them to mate
and create offsprings".
So you essentially take
the 2 genomes of two solutions
and then combine off-springs,
combining parts of one channel
conductances and other
channel conductance from
the other neuron model.
And another element could be for
example to introduce some randomness
by mutating individual
channel conductances
with a certain probability.
The whole idea of this is that
this new generation
has some knowledge from
the previous generation, in a sense
that sort of solutions
that you ranked
good sort of are those that
you explore further.
So, the idea is that you run this
mini evolution and hope that this
the information about
the individuals is guiding you
smartly through your search space.
By doing all that, of course,
the key element is
"When is a model a good model?".
So, here you have two traces,
a red trace and a black trace,
and how can you express the
difference between these two traces?
So, one way is simply calculating
a simple least square distance norm
where you sort of point
by point calculate
the difference between the two traces
and that will give you an arbitrary
unit distance of 0.3, for example.
When you do that, you
have to be aware
that sort of that
is possibly misleading
because you can find other solutions
like the green trace
which has very little to do in terms
of having spiking behavior,
but in terms of the metric
it will end up having
the same arbitrary unit's
unit's distance between the red
trace and the black from the red.
And this is something which
for the problem of using parameter
optimization for neuronal modeling,
has been sort of a key challenge
and I think there were several
innovations in the last years
that sort of addressed that.
But before we get there, you
need to keep another thing in mind.
Sort of these two traces
we showed you here
in fact are the repetitions
of the same biological cell.
So, by applying the same
stimulus to the same cell twice
the cell might not react
the exact same way.
The reason why that is important
when you are sort of wanting
to guide a computer by helping
you find good models
is you need to sort of be careful
what it is you're asking for :
are you really asking for that
you want to have an
exact match of the red trace
if the cell is behaving differently
the second time you ask it?
And therefore, sort of
it might be a useful thing
to account for this variability
in your search as well
So, a method that proved useful
and which was described by
Druckmann in 2007
is that instead of treating
every point of the trace equally
you essentially say that
"Maybe what is important
for me is that a cell spikes"
that these spikes have
a certain height
if the action potential that there
is a certain time delay
to the first spike and that there
are certain intervals between spikes.
So, instead of saying
"I need to insist on that
this point is correct"
you insist that you want these
basic features of a neuronal trace,
and of course, you can
choose which features
you want and think are important.
What these features allow you
to do is you can measure them
of course, not only in the model
but you can measure them
in the experimental traces
and not only once
but on iterations of
the same stimulus protocol
so you can calculate a mean
and a variance.
So, what is the mean
action potential high
and what's the variance
in the experimental trace?
And by then subtracting
the experimental mean
from the model feature
and dividing it by the standard
deviation allows you to do two things.
On the one hand,
you penalize the model
according to experimental
variabilities.
If the experimental traces
are very well
constrained within
a certain distance
you want the model
to have the same property.
If the experimental traces is
variable in a certain feature
you may not sort of care so much
whether you hit it exactly or not.
And the second aspect
of it that comes with it
is that suddenly the distance
function is longer in arbitrary units,
but it's in the multiples
of the standard deviation.
So, you can say that my model
for this feature
is within one standard deviation
of the experimental variability.
So, suddenly the distance
between your model
and the experimental trace
is something you can interpret.
Another concept that proved to be
very useful while trying to advance
parameter optimization
with neuron modeling
is multi-objective optimization.
So, we just previously described that
sort of these different features:
action potential height
and time to for spike
sort of are different features
but you could now sort of say
"I sum it all up in one scalar
to sort of guide my search".
But instead, multi-objective
optimization says
"you will treat these different
features separately
"you do not try to sort of trade
them in for the other".
So, obviously you might have
many features in your problem,
here we simply depic
two, for simplicity,
and what a multi-objective
optimization algorithm does
you're trying to seek for
better solutions
that might exhibit trade offs.
So if you have different solutions
in your search space
you could imagine again put here
the action potential height
and here the time to first spike.
So, some solutions are very good:
they have a low distance value
for the model to experiment
comparison in time to first spike,
but they are not very good
in action potential height;
while other solutions have
a good action potential height
But sort of don't fulfill your
criterion in time to first spike.
and so, if you'll have
different solutions
that sort of are landing
in different parts of this space
and some of them you
can clearly sort out
because essentially there simply
you have solutions that
are better in all metrics
and therefore you will
be able to remove those
those that are dominated by these solutions
that are better in all features.
And you keep going until you end up
with a set of solutions that are all
not dominating each other.
So what that means is that these
solutions are...
Dominance means that a solution is equal
or better in all of its features
than the other solution.
In this case
the solutions are actually
better in some feature,
but worse in another feature
so, in that sense
there is no clear decision
that one is better than the other
it simply means they're
showing different trade offs
and in the terminology of multi
objective optimization
this is called the Pareto front.
This is very
interesting scientifically
because what it means is that
while you would like to be here
where you have a perfect
match of your model
to the experimental expectations,
this one shows you that you
can have one or the other
and it might prompt you
to ask the question
whether the search space
you've been sampling
is the good search space
or maybe you should add
another ion channel conductance
or maybe you need of another
or maybe you need another type
of time constant in your model.
So, in this one, this type of using
multi objective optimization
for parameter optimization
helps you to expose that
the search space might not be the
right search space in the first place
which you have to always keep in mind:
then if you model something
it is not a given that
the components you put
in your model are sufficient
to create the behavior
you're actually looking for.
So, putting it all together using
an evolutionary algorithm
with feature based metrics
and multi-objective optimization
proved to be a useful
set of mechanisms to advance
the automated modeling of neurons.
We showed that by reverting
back to the paper of
Matthew Larkum and colleagues
where sort of there
is a parametal cell
which was recorded at different
locations with simultaneous patchclamps
and sort of to the right you see
different simulation scenarios.
The upper one is where
you only stimulate
the distal dendritic electrode and you
see some membrane voltage deflection
which is high at the location
of the stimulus
lower at the blue and almost
impossible to see in the black one.
If, on the other hand
you stimulate the somatic firing
with a step current you will see
the spike generation in the soma
and then the back
propagation of the spike
to the other electrodes.
But then, the interesting thing
is when you combine the two,
so you have the somatic firing
in step current injection, and
a little bit later,
within a certain time window,
you do the dendritic stimulation
which mimics dendritic input,
you actually see a non-linear
somation effect that sort of the soma
suddenly sends a little burst
of spiking activity
and you see calcium spike
in the dendrite.
So, this has been experimentally
observed
and we set out to
sort of model this
in a model using automated
parameter optimization.
So, this was published by
Itad Hay and colleagues
and here you now have
a reconstructed morphology,
you sort of have
the different electrode set up
in an insilical experiment,
and you can do replay
the kind of same stimulus protocols and you see
that the model is capable of recreating
this non-trivial interaction between
two spikings of a neuron.
So, this is a nice demonstration
That these parameter search methods
and the combination of techniques
we showed are useful
and create real neuron models.
When you do that, you have
to consider important pieces:
so, recreating your experimental
expectation, of course is the first
goal of all of that,
but at the same time
you have to think further:
I mean, it is very easy to get into
a scenario where you have over-fitting,
where essentially your model exactly
reproduces the behavior you asked it
for, and then fails when you go from
a step current to a REM current.
And we looked into that and found
that actually step currents are quite
a good training-set which then have
a reasonable generalization of when
you then, in a second step, test your
model on a different stimulus.
It's not the same if you trained
your model on the REM current and
then went back, so the time constant
or very fast time constant and slow
and relaxation in the step current
seems to be useful information for
the algorithm to find parameter
locations in the search space
that then have
a more general applicability.
So, this is an important aspect you
always need to consider when doing
parameter optimization that you
don't want to over-fit
and you have to test
for generalization.
Another aspect is that by design,
a metaheuristic doesn't guarantee
that it finds the globally
best solution.
So, it might be finding
similar solutions
that are in your feature space,
look similar, but sort of the way
the value comes about is by very
different mechanisms.
So, especially in these population
based algorithms
you have some solutions
which always seem to be very
constrained in one parameter
but they show quite
a range of expression
in other channel conductances
for example.
So, on the one hand this could
be a problem of the search method
that you're looking in a big
search space and essentially you're
finding parameters that lead to
the same phenotype,
but what is interesting about it
is that this also should prompt you
about thinking whether maybe this
non-uniqueness is the property of
the biological system
in the first place;
because it seems there are some
indication that at least certain
types of firing can
be, are recreated in real
cells by different
channel conductances.
So, what is therefore interesting
when you look at your solutions
you might not only want
to pick the best solution
but you want to understand what
is the range of solutions
and actually ask yourself whether
what you're seeing might be even
a representation of the biological
diversity, but it also
could be an artifac
of the algorithm.
In any case
this values your attention
and for example, Eve Mart
and her colleagues,
they've been studying this
for a long time and it's useful,
further reading.
Lastly, as with every model it is
important that you understand what
the model was built for and what's
the range of applicability
of your model.
So, there's an interesting recent
review of Almak and Corngreen
that took different models
in particular, also the model which
we showed before and sort of tested
them in foreign questions
for which the neuron models
weren't explicitly built for.
So, if you do that, of course
you may have good surprises
that the model actually
is generalizing
even into these new contexts;
or, you have bad surprises that
your model actually cannot react
and predict properly
simply, because the information
you've been giving it
when you built the model
might not be sufficient.
So, this you always have to keep
in mind, that models have a certain
realm of applicability.
And that you constantly need to ask
yourself the question whether you're
still within that realm.
Let me summarize today's MOOC.
So, we're in the context
of constraining
neuronal models with
experimental data.
Sometimes, it's easier than other
times to find these experimental data
and for those cases where it's
difficult to find
the experimental data, what other
alternatives do you have?
Here, we've presented how parameter
optimization in particular
metaheuristic, such as evolutionary
algorithms can be used to help
you find some of these parameters
with the help of a computer.
When you do that you have
to help the computer to determine
what is a good solution
so you'll have to find smart metrics
such as the presented
feature based metrics
and it is useful to use
multi-objective optimization to help
you expose certain trade-offs
in your parameter space
because it's not a given that
the model parameters,
you're actually starting
out with are guaranteed to have
a valid solution for the parameter
for the behavior you're looking for
we presented that
the different techniques
we've shown here can be used
to create valid realistic models.
But at the same time you have to
always be aware of the caveats
you have to make sure to test that
your model generalizes.
You have to think about
the uniqueness
or non-uniqueness of solutions
but overall, and after all
one important thing is parameter
optimization doesn't do magic:
you have a sample space and you have
a certain amount of samples
you're doing, so the more
free parameters you have
the more difficult
it will be for
a parameter optimization
technique to help you.
So, it's always good to look out
for more parameters constrained
from experimental data and resort
to the optimization part
as a last resort.
Thank you very much
for your attention.