Hello, welcome to this week's MOOC
on constraining neuronal models
with experimental data
My name is Felix Schumann,
I'm a Professor at EPFL
working at the Blue Brain Project
where for the last couple of years
we've been working
on the reconstruction and simulation
of realistic neuronal tissue.
In today's part of the MOOC
we will recap the different
mathematical levels
of abstraction that are useful
to describe neuronal behavior.
And I'll make the point
that the multi-compartment
Hodgkin-Huxley formalism
that were described in other parts
of the MOOC
are a good starting point
for realistic neuron models.
We'll be talking about experimental
data sets
that can help us
to parameterize these models
and the challenges that occur
in that process
That should keep us busy
for this part of the MOOC
So, if you have a neuron in mind
which you want to model
and in this case it's a layer
five parametal cell of a young rat
and what we want to model
is for example,
how would the somatic recording
from the step current ejection
look like
how an axe potential is generated
or something similar,
rather electrical behavior.
You have different possibilities
to try to cast that
into a mathematical model,
and it starts with simply modeling
the cell body,
the passive electrical properties
of that,
and use the template mechanism
activated
after crossing a certain threshold
to initiate an action potential.
Or, you can go to the Hodgkin-Huxley
formalism
that extends these types of modeling
with active conductancies
for sodium and potassium currents
and allows to describe
the action potential
as an emergent property
of the electrical system.
Or, you can extend
that further and say
“I'm not only modeling
a single compartment"
"but I would like to have the formalism
to describe the dendritic tree"
"and the cable equation of that.”
And this was described
for example by Idan
with the Rall equations for using
combining the Rall equations
with the Hodgkin-Huxley equations
to have a full bio-physical model
of spatially extended neuron
with an action potential generated
by the bio-physically
correct conductancies.
But it doesn't stop there necessarily.
You can imagine that you can go
into even more detail
and sort of include bio-chemical
reactions, electric fusion
and the Lygen Gedinsen cascades
or other things,
and then you would have to change
the mathematical formalism again
and would have to characterize yet
other properties that lead to
for example, something like
an action potential.
For the purpose of this MOOC,
we will stick
with the multi-compartment
Hodgkin-Huxley formalism,
essentially for two reasons:
on the one hand
computationally speaking,
it is still the simplest mechanism
that can capture spatially
extended features of a neuron
and treat the electrical behavior
as an emergent property.
At the same time, it has enough hooks
in terms of the individual
compartments it's modeling
and the different conductances
you can add
that it is very amenable
to include new bio-physical detail.
And it's exactly these two properties
that it's computationally
still tractable
and yet on the other hand allows
to include a lot of bio-physical detail
that make this formalism
very interesting
for realistic neuron modeling.
When spanning the timeline
from the original experiments
and modeling of Hodgkin and Huxley
then the theory of Rall
to today, there are an important
number of milestones
for this type of modeling
which I think I briefly
would like to capture.
On the one hand,
in the end of the 70s
Roger Traub and Llinas started
to extend the level of detail
of the cable equations
that resolved up until that date.
But note the type of geometries
you see here
are still very much motivated
by making the geometries
more realistic
but still as simple as possible.
So here, you see still see
the two thirds Power Law,
for example, that simplifies certain
mathematical equations.
This is a hippocampal motor neuron
and at the time this was computed
on a mid-frame computer.
In the same year,
for different morphology here,
we're talking now
about a Purkinje cell frog,
these simplifications no longer held:
so here the dendritic tree
it doesn't show these symmetries
and therefore,
this model has about 60 compartments
and does treat these compartments
in their detail,
having to solve the full compartmental
equations in Hodgkin and Huxley.
It took another couple of years
before the morphologies
went really detailed
and so this is now work
by Eric De Schutter and Jim Bower
on the Purkinje cell
and here we now
have a full dendritic reconstruction
of the Purkinje cell tree
And the neuron model they did here
had 1,600 compartments,
ten different channel types,
with differential channel densities,
recreating multiple different parts
of observed behavior of that neuron.
And lastly,
yet a couple of years later,
Mainen and Sejnowski
had modeled a parametal cell
where essentially they could show
that the change
in somatic firing you see,
which is of course
for example mediated
through different channels
for different channel densities,
that alone
a dendritic tree can influence
the somatic firing pattern.
So, what we see here in these last
decades of detailed modeling
that on the one hand
the computational available power
from mid-frame to personal computers
to more powerful computers,
thanks to Moore's Law,
actually allowed to integrate
much more detail,
and at the same time of course
that this more computation detail
necessitates having more experimental
data available
but at the same time allowing
to integrate more experimental data.
So, when we're talking
about realistic neuron modeling today
and constrained neuron models
with experimental data,
we have essentially the computational
power available
and we can think about primarily
which data sets we can use
to constrain the models.
But the starting point
is still very much the same
you want to have a certain morphology
for the neuron of interest
you have possibly certain
electrical behavior
that you've recorded super-threshold,
sub-threshold
from the soma, from the dendrite,
and in the end, you'll have to find
how do I constrain all the parameters
that are exposed in the multi
compartmental Hodgkin-Huxley model?
So, we're talking about the typology,
the passive properties of the cable,
the active conductancies
in the different parts of the tree
their behavior and how many of those
conductancies you have where.
We will now go through looking
for these different data sets
and what are the things you might
want to keep in mind, when using them.
We start with the morphologies
and first of all a very good source
to get the morphology reconstructed
is to go to neuromorpho.org
Now we pick here our favorite neuron
which is labeled by parametal cell
and the neuron looks beautiful if you
look at it in this XY coordinate frame.
But what you should always do that
from seeing a beautiful neuron
on a screen or on a paper
that is not the same as saying that
the morphology has all the parameters
needed to constrain your model,
and this is one example
what could go wrong.
So, if you turn this neuron around
by 90 degrees
you find suddenly that there's almost
half of the neuron
of the dendritic tree
and the axon missing... why is that?
Well, this particular neuron
was recorded and stained in slides
and was at a certain depth
at some point the slides ended
and that meant that certain parts
of the neuron are shaved off.
You don't see that
in this perspective,
but you see it when you turn
the neuron around.
So, keep in mind that depending
on what was the recording
staining and reconstruction technique,
you have to check whether actually
you have all the data
in your experimental data
to constrain your computation model,
because it matters whether
that part of the tree is there or not.
Now, the other systematic artifacts
to look out for
is some staining and fixation
methods lead to shrinkage
or sort of crumbling and that leads
to wiggly branches
which again or other artifacts
which could have computational
implications in your model.
And you always want to make sure
that sort of some other things
like, for example, axons,
are they stained in the first place?
Were they reconstructed?
Are they complete?
All these things suddenly matter
because essentially an axon
which is not there
will not parameterize the cable
in your model.
Unfortunately, the story
of morphologies does not end there
and there are a number
of other little things
that can keep you off track
when using experimental data
to constrain your model.
It can start with that
at the reconstruction process
the diameter wasn't explicitly given,
it's still the software
might connect two points
even though they have zero diameter
with the line,
but electrically
that is not a good parameter
to have in your cable equation model,
to have a diameter of zero
in a certain compartment.
You might see that due to the way
that these reconstructions happen
typically from XY and then the Z
is something that's done
through scrolling through the stack
of the slides
and when reconstructions get started
and resumed and restarted
that sort of not always
the reconstructions are fully aligned
again in the XY plane you won't see
these types of artifacts.
There, sometimes things
like reverse order reconstructions
that sort of things
were traced inside out
and not starting from the cell body
think again when you look
at the topology
of course it matters tremendously
where these different compartments
are connected with each other.
At the same time, sometimes some
things are not connected at all;
or spines get reconstructed
as single segment sections;
or you might find that certain parts
of the morphology
get reconstructed several times
again on a visualization
of such a morphology,
that is not an issue
for electrical modeling
all these parameters lead to different
properties of your cell model.
So, the take home message here is
simply that using experimental data
for realistic neuron modeling
is crucial,
but you have to make sure that
the experimental data set
sort of has the accuracy and the quality
so that it gives you a good electrical
passive frame for your model.
Moving to ion channels !
So, as per the work
of Hodgkin and Huxley
we know that sodium
and potassium currents
are the key to generate
an action potential.
So, you could say,
“Well, I want my cell to fire"
"I put sodium and potassium currents,
that's it.”.
But of course
the story's not as simple
and sort of there are many more
details to be possibly considered
when you're looking
at your particular neuron in question.
And first off, these currents
are mediated
by different ion channels,
so there is not just one sodium
and one potassium channel type
but they are as a matter of fact,
different ones.
And these sodium and potassium
channels shape
a lot sort of
how the neuron de-polarize
how the action potential
gets initiated,
how the after hyper-polarization
happens.
And of course
there are additional ions
there are calcium chlorate
and other ions
that shape additional parts
of the neuron
can be the onset or the spike
or the persistent firing behavior
of your neuron.
So, again, if you have a neuron
that for example is a delayed spiker
or burst spiker, or something else
you will have to add
additional detail
that is not in the original sodium
and potassium parameters
of Hodgkin and Huxley.
Now, as a matter of fact,
there are about 350 ion channel types
known in mammals
and most of them seem to be expressed
in the nervous system.
They roughly categorize
into three different groups.
There are about 150 voltage
gated channels,
there are about 90 ligand
gated channels
and there's the third group, others
aquaporous or chloride channels.
So, in principle,
when you're looking at neuron
and you're looking for data
you're looking at having to identify
which of these 350 channels
might be in your neuron.
But before we go there, first of all
what do we know about these channels?
And here you see an overview
of the voltage gated ion
channel family
And in this case you can of course
classify them in different ways,
you can classify them by ion,
for example
but here, they're classified by
on the one hand they're porous
and then their similarity
in the amino acids.
And you see that sometimes
some channels have four domains,
and then sort of that makes them
more similar
even though they're letting
through different ions,
then, for example calcium channels
to other calcium channels
or on the other hand,
sort of different potassium channels.
to other potassium channels.
So, the take home message of that
is that here there is a wealth
of ion channel experimental data
that might be useful for your
parameterizing of your neuron model,
but of course, you have to know
whether sort of which exact channels
you might have in your neuron
and then the second point
what is known about that channel,
and then, you can use the data
to characterize
the particular activation
in activation parameters
in your ion channels
that you have put
into your Hodgkin-Huxley model.
Now, of course that's exactly
the question:
which of these channels
are in my neuron?
and there are different ways
of finding
of going back to experimental data
to help you with that decision.
There are pharmacological methods,
you can do antibody staining
you can do single cell multiplex
reverse transcription PCR,
or nowadays you can also try
to do single cell transcriptum.
It is all about asking
what in the given cell
which genetically identified
ion channels you might have.
This is a diagram of a data set
which was done through multiplex
reverse transcription PCR.
So essentially there is some
cytoplasm extracted from a cell
and you have different genetic probes
to sort of see
whether you can fish MR&A sequences
for particular ion channel genes
out of this micro-plasma.
Now, of course, having MR&A
is not the same
to say that you have
the protein expressed
so these last two methods,
in a way, give you an indication
that there is the genetic machinery
has been activated
to produce a certain ion channel
but it doesn't mean exactly
that you know for sure
that the ion channel is there,
but there is a high correlation.
But that being said
sort of from these data sets
you can see that even though
and these cell types seem
to have somewhat
similar, sustained firing behavior,
they differ in the onset:
so this delayed,
this is burst spiking,
but you can see
is for the ion channels visible here
you might see a completely
differential expression
of these channels leading
to these type of firing behaviors.
So, these are invaluable data sets
to, out of the jungle of ion channels,
choose which ones of those
might be present in your neuron
and helping you to select
which channels you have to model
in the first place and where you can
look for parameters for your model.
Next, when you now know
which channels you have to consider,
you will have to ask yourself
the question:
do you know the different parameters
like activation,
inactivation parameters
for the channels you want
to put into your model?
And a good source for channel models
is ModelDB which is hosted
it's at Yale University,
this is the URL,
and that's a very important resource
because there, they track published
models of channels, cells and networks
and it sort of allows you to go back
and sort of find out
which parameters were used
in the different model.
So, in principle, once you know
your neuron model
and the channels you might be able
to go to that resource
and ask the question:
"Can I take the parameters
from that channel model?".
Now, in practice, the problem
is a little bit more complicated
which prompted an activity,
which you see here
this part of the screen,
which is the IC Genealogy project
which is hosted at Oxford,
and what they did
is they went to the ModelDB
and extracted every single ion
channel model,
and you now have different ways
of displaying those ion
channel models:
you can display them
by channel family or current family
but you can also ask
the question sort of
"which model was derived
from which other model?
And how similar are these models?"
So, as a matter of fact,
this is a different way
of looking at the jungle
of ion channels,
but namely from the model perspective
What this really means
is that different modelers
for different models might have taken
another modeler's ion channel
and then changed it,
to simply say
“Look here the equations
were modified from [INAUDIABLE]"
"and we for example change"
"the conductions
of the potassium channel”
and the reason why they were changing
the channel properties in the model
was likely that they wanted
to have their cell
or their network behave
in a certain way.
So, as matter of fact,
the channel parameters
were treated as a modifiable
or free parameter
so that in order to get in later
or higher order behavior
you could adjust channel models.
But what that really means
is that you depart
from the bio-physicallycharacterized
channel
as for example done by an experiment.
So, of course there is no criticism
in this
because in the end,
you have to ask yourself the question
"how good is the experimental data
in the first place?"
"Does it have enough quantitative value
to create specific ion channel models?"
Or sort of "were they approximations
in the first place?"
but what it really means
is that it is not necessarily a given
that models of channels
and models of cells
use the experimental quantitative
data for modeling the channels
but that there was, due
to also the absence of data,
a large period of time
when models sort of had
to guess channel parameters.
Now, the good news
is that this may change with time,
and here I would like
to briefly present an endeavor
which is called ChannelNome
and ChannelPedia.
And here you can go to ChannelPedia
where you will find good resource
of ion channels expressed
in the brain
and as well as data sets
and increasingly more models.
And this project has been set out
to create cell lines
that are genetically identified
individual channel types expressed
and then systematically characterized
these channels
under different temperatures
So, it is actually trying
to systematically obtain the kinetics
of all these genetically
identified ion channels.
So, once this is complete
you will no longer have to go
to a colleague's channel model
and sort of modify it for your means,
but you will be able
to sort of create channel models
which are backed by data
effectively reducing the parameters
that are at your disposal
when sort of creating cell models,
making the problem simpler
because you have less parameters
to find.
So, this is a typical example
for how increasing experimental work
helps you to sort of extract
more and more parameters
for your realistic neuron models.
Now you can ask yourself the question
sort of "why wasn't that done before?"
"Why are we still, today,
talking about that effort?"
and the secret lies in a way
of how interesting ion channels
are in the first place.
Some of these channels were found
to be implicated in certain diseases
and then a lot of studies
have been made about that channel,
but some of these channels
are not interesting for disease
they're exotic
and we know very little for the end;
also the genetic characterization
wasn't known
or have since the beginning
of ion channel work
so especially Hodgkin and Huxley
so we know about currents
but we didn't know
about specific ion channels.
So, as a matter of fact,
it is a particular effort
to systematically find
and characterize those channels
and we think that has very good value
for realistic neuron modeling.
Lastly, once we have morphology,
channels, the channel kinetics
we still have to answer the question
as to "where to put them
and how many of those channels?"
and that is a complicated story.
Some neurons, of course
are simple
so they have a small soma
and just small dendritic trees
like the granule cell
where you can actually
through electrical recordings infer
the maximum conductance of channels.
But other neurons
with an extended dendritic tree
it's very difficult to infer
from the somatic recording
what could be the channel
distribution in the dendrites
or the channel conductances.
So, as a matter of fact
through staining, pharmacology,
recordings,
we can piece together
some information
about that sort of some channels
are only in the soma
or some channels are more
in the apical dendrite,
but the matter of the fact,
the picture remains dirty.
So, as it stands today
the question of "will we able
to quantitatively
extract channel distributions
and maximum conductances?"
I think remains an open question,
and we will take and talk
in other parts of the MOOC
what we can do
to mitigate that challenge.
Let me summarize today's course
on constraining neuron models
with experimental data.
So, when you are setting out to build
realistic models for specific neuron
you're faced with having
to identify multiple parameters
neuron's topology, diameters,
which type of ion channels
ion channel kinetics,
maximum conductances and so on...
We think that in order
to make these models meaningful
and the problem achievable
is very important to use
as much biological data, experimental
data to constrain these parameters
so essentially make
the problem simpler
by reducing the number
of free parameters.
We think in particular that multi-
compartment Hodgkin-Huxley formalism
is a good formalism to allow you
to integrate experimental data,
it has the right hooks to
sort of include specific parameters
for an ion channel or specific
densities in a certain compartment.
So in that sense the multi
compartment Hodgkin-Huxley formalism
is not only data driven formalism,
it is data ready,
it makes it easy to absorb data.
That being said,
there are particular parameters
that remain more experimentally
inaccessible than others
and that might make it necessary
to employ other methods
to sort of help find
and constrain parameters
which we'll be talking in other parts
of the MOOC.
Thank you very much
for your attention
and hope to see you
in the next part of the MOOC.