Hi. In the next two tutorials,
we're going to learn
how to optimize the parameters
of the electrical model
so that they fit
electrical constraints.
In the first part I will
discuss how to set up
all the different components
necessary for this optimization.
So we will learn how to set up
the model and how to build
to the evaluator.
So to start using BluePyOpt,
we imported it in the same way
as we did with NEURON,
and in this case we also
import a supply
called "ephys"
of BluePyOpt which contains
some extra functionality that's
very specific to electrical models.
To optimize the model parameters,
we first have to define the model
in BluePyOpt.
We do this by creating a template.
This template consists of
a shape of the cell
which is a morphology,
a description of the ion channels
which are the mechanisms,
and we also have to define
which parameters
are free in the model.
First we're going to add
a morphology of the cell.
NEURON can load different
standardized descriptions
of neuron morphologies.
An example is SWC format.
And I've added a link to exact
description of this format here.
Here you see a description
of such a morphology.
I'm not going to go into detail
but basically it describes
a morphology with a soma
with a radius of 10μm
and also a dendrite which
has a length of 100μm.
Here you can see an example
of such SWC description.
I'm not going to go
into the details
but it basically describes
a morphology with a soma
with a radius of 10μm, and
a single dendritic section
with a length of 100μm.
And that dendrite also
has a radius of 2μm.
We can plot this morphology
using the neuronal
morphology analysis tool
or Neuro M.
It's as simple as just specifying
the location of the SWC file
and calling the Draw function
of the Neuron M.
As you can see we have
a soma and a dendrite.
Now we want to use this
morphology in BluePyOpt.
For this we create an Nrnfile morphology object
which points to the SWC file.
By default the neuron morphology
has the following section lists.
Somatic, axonal, apical, and basal,
which point to the different
locations along the morphology.
Later on, we will have to specify
where certain channels are added
or where certain injections
are occurring.
For this we'll define
the location objects.
For example, we can define
a somatic location object
which points to all the sections,
which in this case it's just one
of the soma.
If you want to point to
all the basal sections
we create also an object, we call
it the Dendritic Location Object.
Now we need to specify which
ion channels are present on
the membrane of this morphology.
The NEURON simulator has
the built-in implementation
of the Hodgkin Huxley Sodium,
Potassium and Leak channels.
Let's add this mechanism,
which is called HH to the soma.
The name field can be
chosen by the user.
This name should be unique.
The suffix points to the same field
in the NMODL file of the channel
and locations specify which
sections the mechanism
will be added to.
So, now we have specified
the shape of the neuron
and we have the set where we
want to add all the ion channels.
The next step is to define which
parameters we want to optimize.
A parameter can be in two states,
it can be frozen, or not frozen.
When a parameter is frozen,
it has an exact value,
otherwise it only has some bounds
but the exact value
is not known yet.
Let's first define a parameter
that's going to set
the capacitance of the cell.
In this tutorial we'll focus on
optimizing the parameters
of the soma.
So we'll also fix the leakage
conductance of the dendrite
and we'll make it
passive by disabling
the sodium and
potassium conductances.
Now we set the bounds for
the maximum conductances of
the sodium and potassium
channels in the soma.
These two parameters
will be optimized later
and here you can see the bounds
in which the algorithm is allowed
to change the parameter.
We put all the components,
so our morphology mechanism
and parameters, together
into a cell model object.
This cell model object
can also be printed out
and it shows you a summary of all
the object we have defined before.
So now we have a cell model
but we have to define which
constraints you want to apply
to the cell model.
To optimize the parameters
of the model
we need to create an object
that will translate parameter values
into fitness scores.
This object will need to know
which protocols to inject
which parameters to optimize, etc.
So we first start by defining
the protocols.
A protocol consists of a set
of stimuli and a set of responses.
These responses will later be used
calculate a score
of parameter values.
Let's create two protocols.
Two square current pulses
at the location
of the middle of the soma,
with different amplitude.
We first need to create
a location object.
So again, this object will point
to all the compartments inside
the somatic section list.
Then we define the stimuli
recordings and protocols.
For each protocol we add...
(so the recording protocols
are defined here)
we add a stimulus
and the recording.
This inner square pulse stimulus
is basically a current clamp
that injects a square
current injection.
And we also add recording and we say
that the location to record from
is the middle of the soma
and this location object
is something we've defined before.
Then we put these two protocols
that we've defined here,
so we have a protocol that's going
to inject 0.1nA and another protocol
is going to inject 0.5nA, into
an object that puts them
together: a sequence protocol,
so that, basically,
it's first going to run
step one, and then step two,
and it's going to put everything
into one protocol definition.
With a cell model in hand,
and the protocols defined
we can now apply the protocol
to a cell.
First we define an object
that represents the simulator
so in this case it's
the NEURON simulator.
We also have to define
a certain set of parameter values
we want to evaluate,
so for example
in this case we're going to evaluate
a GK bar of 0.1 and
the GNA bar of 0.25.
So we basically say
"run our protocol
on the certain cell
model with these parameters".
Running our model returned
a response object.
And now we can plot
the responses.
So basically this response object
can be accessed by
our recording name
and if you want to plot
the time or the voltage
so we basically create the function
that, given a set of responses,
automatically puts them,
and you see that here
we have the first current injection
we have one action potential that's
being generated,
and in the second one we
have five action potentials.
We can also change
the parameter values
so if we change them to 0.1, 0.1
we see that we actually get
a different response which was
of course to be expected.
So now we have a little
exercise for you.
Try to find the values of GNABAR
that produce three spikes
in the first trace, and five spikes
in the second trace.
When you're searching for this
don't change the value of the GKBAR.