Of course, visually inspecting
these choices can be useful
but if we want to automate this,
we can make use of the eFEL
the e-feature
extraction library
to analyze the traces that
were returned to us.
For example, this library
can return to us the number
of spikes in a trace,
the height of these spikes, etc.
So first we take the parameters
we've defined before,
default parents, and again,
we run our protocol.
Then we put our traces into
the two different variables
so we have the time of step two,
and the voltage of step two
and we create a specific dictionary.
This is something that is
predefined by the eFEL
so we basically put the voltage in
the variable V, T,
stim_start, stim_end
show the times of
the beginning of the stimulus
and the end of the stimulus.
Then we import the eFEL and
we give this trace to the function
get featured values.
And we specify which
features we want to evaluate.
So in this case "Spikecount"
"AP_width" and "AP_amplitude".
So now we can print the values
that eFEL returned
so the spike count AP_width
the AP_amplitude, and you see that
it says that there's five spikes
in the trace, which is correct
so there are five spikes in step two
and it also shows us
the width and the amplitude of these
five spikes in millivolts
and milliseconds,
Now we will pass this
on to the BluePyOpt.
BluePyOpt has a class e-features
which basically wraps
around the eFEL
and will calculate
the requested features for us.
In this case,
let's use the "Spikecount"
feature as a target, and let's ask
for four spikes in the first trace
and six spikes in the second.
Different features can be
combined to get them into objectives
that will be used by
the optimization algorithm.
In this case we allocate
one objective per feature.
So this code here will
create these eFEL features
and will ask for four
spikes in the first step
six spikes in the second step.
So with all the information
that we have now we can
create a cell evaluator.
So basically, the cell evaluator
uses a score calculator
which is based on
the objectives
we have defined in
the previous section.
We can combine
all of this together
in the constructor of
the cell evaluator.
So we have our model,
we have our parameter names
we have our protocols,
and we have our score calculator
an also an object that
points to our simulator.
So now, let's use our
cell evaluator we created.
We just call this function on
the cell evaluator with
a set of parameters.
The function will return
a dictionary that
shows for which feature
we have reached score.
So for an example,  the spike count
in the first step has a score of 15
the spike count in the second
step has a score of 3.3.
This score is calculated based on
the target mean
and standard deviation
you have specified in
the e-features before.
The lower the score,
the better the model.
As you might've seen in exercise one
it's not always trivial to find
the parameter value set
that matches the objectives.
Let's now use the BluePyOpt
parameter optimization algorithm
to find a set of parameter values
that generates perfect score of zero
on both traces.
Let us specify that we want to have
an offspring size of ten individuals
this means that every population
will have twenty individuals
ten parents, and ten offspring.
So we basically define
an IBED optimization object.
Now the optimization algorithm can
be run for a certain
number of generations
and you can do this by
calling the run function
and you say how many
generations you want to run maximum.
I just want to warn you that
this cell here if you executed it
it will take some time to run.
An order of a couple of minutes.
In the meantime this number here,
the twenty seven will be replaced
by an asterix (*).
The optimization will
return as four objects.
The final population after
the ten generations,
a hall of fame which shows
the best individuals
found during the optimization,
a log with some statistics
and a history that
shows the different
populations that
were evaluated.
The final population object
contains a list of tuples
with each tuple representing
the two parameters of the model.
Here you see a print-out
of this optimization.
So we basically have
the best model here
has a parameter of 0.11 for GNABAR
and around 0.028 for GKBAR.
So we retrieve the best model
from the hall of fame
an now we can evaluate this model.
So basically, these are just
two numbers that we can
transform using this "param_dict"
function to a dictionary
this is clear and it
shows us the value
of the GKBAR and
the value for GNABAR.
As you can see,
the evaluation returns
the same values as
the fitness values provided
buy the optimization output.
We can have a look at
the responses now.
So we basically run the model,
and it provides us with parameter
values the best individual.
And we print the score.
So you see that you actually get
a model that fires six times in
the second step, and four times
in the first step
and because of this,
it has a score of zero and zero
on both objectives.
Let's have a look at
the optimization
algorithm statistics.
WE can plot the minimal score.
In this case, the score will be
the sum of all
the separate objectives
so the two objectives we have
in every generation.
So you see that in the beginning
the algorithm started with
with some individual that was
pretty bad but when the generations
progressed after seven generations,
we got an individual with a score
of zero.
So to close this tutorial we have
a little second exercise for you.
So bellow here you see a copy
of all of the above statements.
For every variable added
an underscore X for "exercise"
as a suffix so that we don't clash
with any of the definitions
of the code above.
You should change the code in a way
so that instead of
the Spikecount feature
the AP_width feature
is used as a target
and it should have
a value of 1.3 in step one
and 1.6 in step two.
Please, send us back the scores
of the best individual found
by your algorithm.