So the model code also provides
information about the synapses
as they were added in the circuit.
So basically what we are now having
simulated is one single cell
but we can add all the synapses
to the morphology of this cell
and we can also connect
Poisson generators
to every on of these synapses.
So that basically means that
we're having virtual cells
that act as pre-synaptic cells
so that we can see a little bit
of network-like activity.
The information about the synapses
is located in the attribute of
the cell object, namely
the synapses object
and so for example, the synapses
object hast an attribute
synapse lists, which basically is
a list of all the synapse objects.
So if we get the length
of this object we know
how many synapses
there are in a cell.
So for example this particular
cell has 5267 synapses.
So like I said, every
pre-synaptic cell
in this case will be represented
by a Poisson generator
and all these Poisson generators
which are actually implemented
as a "netstim" object
in NEURON
are located in a "netstim" list.
So again, if we look at
the length of this list we get
a number of pre-synaptic
cells, which is 920.
So you might find
this slightly strange
because there
are actually less
pre-synaptic cells than
there are synapses
but this is not strange at all, some
or most of the pre-synaptic cells
are actually connecting to our
cell with more than one synapse.
So it's basically called
a multi-synaptic connection
and as you can see,
there is definitely
a whole set of
multi-synaptic connections
in the pre-synaptic cells
to the synapses of our cell.
So as it was mentioned before
the cells in our circuit
are classified according
to the morphological type.
So actually you can already see here
that there are 55 M types
in the circuit.
You can actually go to
the MNC portal website
and there is a glossary
there that shows
what all these abbreviations mean
so for example MC is
a Martinotti cell
LBC is a large basket cell
and all these morphological
types have been assigned
to certain integer value
in this model package.
So you can actually access
the M type map
type separated file
in the model package
and you can see all these integers
that map to the string
of the M type.
So these integers are important
because some structures
in a model here are sorted according
to this number, so we can easily
get all the pre-synaptic cells
of the certain M type
if you know this exact number.
So we're actually storing this
map into a Python dictionary
so that we can easily get integer
numbers for a certain M type.
So for example, L23PC is 6.
So for example, now we can activate,
all the pre-synaptic cells
which are of certain M types,
so for example
let's activate all the L23PC
pre-synaptic cells so the layer 2
and layer 3 pyramidal cells.
So I've written a little convenience
function that allows you to
initialize the synapses,
so you basically call it like this
you just say "initialize synapses",
and then you say "enable M types"
and you give a list
of names of M types.
So basically what's happening
inside this function is
that we are saying to
the code that we want to go
from inactive synapse to active
synapse for a certain M type
or vice versa to
disable the synapses.
So now that we have activated
all the L23PC pre-synaptic cells
we can run a little simulation.
Again, we're going to run for 600ms
and we're going
to save the recording
input and output.
Again this will take a little
bit of time to execute.
So as you can see,
our L23PCs have activated
our post-synaptic cell here,
and it actually fired one spike
or let it fire one spike;
and we can also see that
now that trace is a bit noisy
because we have all these
post-synaptic potentials
arriving from
the pre-synaptic cells.
As you can see from the trace above,
the cell is not very active
during this bombardment
from the L23PCs.
We can actually show
much bigger activation
by activating the pre-synaptic
L5 thick-tufted pyramidal cells.
It's basically other cells from
the same M  type as this cell
because this cell is also
an L5 thick-tufted pyramidal cell
that are projecting to our
current post-synaptic cell.
So let's also run this code.
So you see that this is
a completely different story.
So in this case, the pre-synaptic
cells managed to get our cell to
fire 8 spikes, and you see
there's a lot more activity
in the baseline level.
Now, let's try to do the opposite,
let's try to actually prevent
the cell from spiking.
This we can, for example,
do by adding some inhibition
so the L23PC is a pyramidal cell,
so it's an excitatory cell
but we can also activate
a whole set of inhibitory
interneurons that will fire
at the same time
that will actually inhibit
the cell from firing.
We can also execute this
line of code.
This is an example of
an output trace that you can get.
You see that now the Y axis
is actually much narrower
so it's going from -67mV to -59mV,
while before we actually had
a much wider range.
It means that reaction
not firing any action potentials
during our simulation.
I also want to warn that these
simulations are stochastic
so the synapses are stochastic.
It's not sure that for every
time you run this code
that it will actually inhibit
the spike and you just have to be
slightly lucky that the inhibition
happens at the right time.
So in case you get spikes,
just run it again and you might
get a different result.
Now let's see how
we can also influence
the activity of this pre-synaptic
Poisson generators .
So every Poisson generator
is represented by a NEURON
"netstim" object, you can actually
look on the documentation page
of the NEURON simulator
to find some information
about these attributes.
In this case we have,
we can access all
the pre-synaptic "netstims"
in a list
and we can, for example,
set the interval variable
in this case, to 10000,
so it means
that actually the average
interval between two spikes
per Poisson process
will be 10 seconds.
But since we have lots of
pre-synaptic cells
we will still have a decent
amount of pre-synaptic
events in the 600ms
we are simulating.
So let's run this code.
So as you can see,
there's now a big difference
in the trace compared
to our previous activation
of the pre-synaptic layer 5
thick-tufted pyramidal cells.
We have much less activity
and you can actually also
nicely now see
the post-synaptic events.
So basically this is one
pre-synaptic cell firing
and creating one
post-synaptic event
on the cell, on our cell,
and again here
two more events.