So later I will show you
how to use the model packages
from the Jupyter notebooks
we provide
but just quickly I will
also show what happens
if you actually run this
on your local computer.
So basically it assumes that you
have NEURON installed
on your computer
I mean, the NMC portal actually
has some instructions on how to
set up all the software,
and basically you can...
if you go to the directory that
contains the model package
you see that there's all
kinds of cells provided
in this model package,
so there are some HOC files
that contains the procedural code,
there are some shell scripts
there is some code
to run the synapses
to generate the plots
and things like that.
So there are are two
different things you can do.
You can use the Python
part of the package
it will just generate the traces
that were shown on the website
or you can run the whole code
which actually will generate
a graphical user interface on your
computer with which you can
access the model and activate
the synapses and things like that.
So running the Python code,
I'm not gonna do that here
because it's basically
similar to what we
show in the Jupyter notebooks.
But I will show you the Graphical
User Interface so this one
you can access by running
the "run_hoc" command
so this is basically the GUI you get
by executing the "run_hoc" command
so as you can see,
it shows you the morphology
of the cell we're going to simulate.
So just to be clear,
we're just simulating the voltage
of one single post-synaptic cell
so in this case Layer five thick-tufted
pyramidal cell.
We can also activate
all the synapses
of this post-synaptic cell
so, for example, we can look at all
the layer 2 or 3 pyramidal cells
that project to this cell.
We can activate all the synapses.
So here, you can actually see
all the synapses projected from
this type of cells.
And every one of these pre-synaptic
cells all the Elter 3PCs
have a poisson
generator connected to them.
So, they are basically going to
inject some poisson spike trains
into the synapses
with a certain rate
so in this case the poisson
generators of all these cells
are set to 10Hz.
So now we can run the simulation,
and you see that
this is the voltage of our
post-synaptic cell
so we basically have
a generation of a spike
because of all the synaptic input
and you also see that
trace is pretty noisy,
because you have
a lot of cells injecting
their events to our cell.
So in this case,
all these L23PCs are
not strong enough to
generate a one on one spike.
So we can actually create
some more activity
by also activating all the layer 5
thick-tufted pyramidal cells
that are projecting to this cell,
so for example
by activating all of them,
you see that now we get a massive
input from pre-synaptic
cells onto our cell
and you get a lot of spikes.
In this plot you can also see
the voltage changing
while the simulation is running.
So another thing you can do
in this interface is to
replicate the traces
that are available
on the NMC portal website,
there's a figure with three traces
each of them you can replicate
with this interface, so for example
you can inject the lower step
current from these three traces
and you can run the simulation
and it will show you
the exact traces available
on the NMC portal website.
So i just want to mention
that the part that I'm showing now
about running this on your local
computer is just an optional
part of this tutorial
just something to show
the capabilities
of the single cell models,
but if you have trouble installing
some of this software on your
computer there's no issue, you can
just look at the Jupyter notebook
tutorial part and that's
more than sufficient.
So it's purely optional.