So now that we have a cell
object in the soma
we can, just as in other tutorials
inject a step current
into the soma object.
For this, we create an I_Clamp,
and we set certain variables
for example, we say we're
going to inject for 400ms
after a delay of 100ms,
and we'll inject a certain amount
of nano amps into the cell.
So you might be wondering where
is this specific nano amp value
coming from?
Basically, the traces you see
on the website have a certain amount
of current injected into them.
This current values can actually
be extracted from a file
that's located in
the model directory
the file is called
"current_amps.dat"
and here you see the code that
actually reads all these values.
So the file contains
four different values
and you see that we use the later
one for our current injection here
so the first one is
the holding current
I'll explain this in a second,
and the last three values are
three different step currents
and every step current
corresponds to one trace that can
be seen on the NMC portal website.
The holding current is actually
athe current that's injected during
the entire length of the experiment
and it's used by
the experimentalists to hold
the cell at a certain
pre-defined voltage.
So for example in our case
it's arround -84mV to -85mV.
So now let's run a little
simulation with this
step current.
So in this case, again
the "init.hoc" file
provided us with the convenience
function, create recording
to automatically initialize
some recording variables
and we can easily run the simulation
by setting the "tstop" value
so the length of the simulation,
so we're going to simulate
for 600ms and with
a time step of 0.05ms.
So let's execute this box of code.
As you can see it will take a little
bit of time to simulate the cell.
Just as in previous tutorials
I have written a little
convenience function
to plot the voltage
so now we can actually get
the time and voltage from
some variables in NEURON
and plot a graph.
As you can see, the model
has fired six spikes
in accommodating
fashion.
So now we have a little
exercise for you.
As you can see,
this trace will not correspond
to the traces that are located
on the MNC portal website.
So this is, because for example here
we are only simulating for 600ms
while on the website
we're simulating for 3 seconds.
So basically rewrite
the code above a bit
so that you stimulate for
a longer time and you also
have to inject another current
using another I_Clamp
that represents the holding current.
So you basically have to inject
that current for the entire
length of the simulation.