So now, let's switch
back to the Jupyter notebook
provided for this tutorial.
Like I said we will
actually download
the model from the MNC portal
and we can actually do
this from inside this notebook
but first we will import
some useful Python modules
like "matplotlib", "urllib",
"zipfile", so we can download
the model file from the MNC portal
and also do some
plotting and things like that.
So we can you
the "urllib" to download
the model from
the MNC portal website.
This is the URL provided by
the MNC portal and we tell "urllib"
to save it in a zip file
on our local disk.
So when we execute this line
the zip file will be saved
and then we can use the "zipfile"
module of Python to actually
extract this zip file
also to the disk.
So we say here, open the zip file
and extract everything
to the current directory.
Now that we have
downloaded the electrical model
we change the directory
of our simulator to
the particular directory provided
by the model packages.
Which is this one here,
and so be careful
once you execute this line here
don't execute
the lines above anymore
because it will create a new
sub-sub-directory of the filed
we have created, so that's not
a good idea because it will
use lots of disk space.
So the model
contains some MOD files
we describe the extensions
to the NEURON simulator
mechanisms that
are used in this model.
As you have seen in
the previous tutorial
you can run the NRNIV model command
to compile all these MOD files.
And you can see if there was
a success if you go to the bottom
of this page, and it successfully
created the special file.
So now, let's also visualize
the morphology.
Just as in other tutorials
we will use the Neuron M package
to show an image of
the morphology.
So we just pick the file where
this morphology is stored
with these specific package,
so that's this one here
and we load it in the Neuron M.
Now we're going to
initialize the model.
This package contains some
custom code that is
very specific for this model,
and it can be loaded
by the loading
the "init.hoc" file in NEURON
So NEURON has this command
"Load File" which basically
allows you to load a custom
HOC file.
So now we're going
to initialize the model.
There is a specific custom code
made for this model that contains
all kind of useful functions,
they all start in the HOC file
The "init.hoc".
So NEURON provides a mechanism
to load one of these files with
a "load_file" command.
So let's do that first.
So one of the functions this
"init.hoc" file has created is
the "create_cell" function.
It takes as argument of one or zero,
give one as arguments you will
load all the synapses.
So we also execute this command.
So once this function
has been called
there is a new global object
generated inside of NEURON
which is called "cell",
so you can access this
by calling "nrn.h.cell"
and we'll assign this to
a Python variables, again "cell"
and we also create a Python
variable for the soma.
So the soma in this case
is a little array
there is only one element
inside this array
so we take the first element
and assign it to the soma variable.