Hi! In this tutorial I will
introduce to you the neo-cortical
micro-circuit collaboration portal
which is a companion website
to the (INAUDIBLE) 2015
cell paper publication
which describes a neo-cortical
micro-circuit model.
I will show you how to download
single cell electrical models
from this website, how to run them
on a local computer
and also we have a Jupyter notebook
that describes how to interact using
Python with these electrical models.
To access this website you can click
on the link provided in the notebook
that comes with this tutorial.
The NMC portal consists
of different sub-sections.
There is one sub-section that
describes the actual
microcircuit model
including all the statistics
that are taken from the model
and also you can download
electrical single cell models
from this sub-section.
Then there is a literature
consistency section
which describes which
papers are consistent
or inconsistent with this model,
then there's experimental data
provided that was used to build
some parts of this network model
and there's also a section with
the videos and the images
related to the building
of this circuit.
For this tutorial,
we are mostly
interested in
the micro circuit section.
This page shows the six layers
of the somatosensory cortex.
On one side you have
the pre-synaptic cells
on the other side you have
the post-synaptic cells
and the bars in between show
the different connections
between all the different layers
and you can click on each of these
bars to get more information about
their connection.
In this tutorial we are
mostly interested
in the single cell electrical models
available on this website.
So we go for example
to the layer five
and in this page of layer five
you can see all the difficult
different morphological types
that are present in this layer.
For this tutorial
we're going to look
at a layer 5 thick-tufted
pyramidal cell
which is also cell-divided
in two different sub-types
so here you actually have the two
layer five thick-tufted
pyramidal cells
and as you can see
on the right side there is
a tab that gives some information
about the anatomy of all these
layer five thick-tufted pyramidal
cells in our circuit simulation.
This link will bring us to a page
that describes this particular
morpho-electical type.
So morpho-electical
because the morphology
is a layer five thick-tufted
pyramidal cell
and the electrical type
is a continuously
adapting pyramidal cell
electrical type.
This page shows a lot of detail
about this morpho-electrical type.
For example, we have the typical
resting potential of this type
a typical input resistance,
and for example
the membrane time constant.
You can also see some
statistic about the anatomy
the apical lengths,
the apical volume, for example
the length of the axon,
the volume of the axon,
and you can also see which ion channels
have been used on the morphology
of this morpho-electrical type.
There are also some images,
it shows particular morphology
of this type and also
some traces that were
recorded from
this single cell model.
As you can see this
page has five tabs.
Each of these tabs presents
one example of morphology
that we picked from the circuits
that represents this
morpho-electrical type.
So what we will do in this tutorial
is take the first example
of this morpho-electrical type
and simulate it in our notebook
and for example one of
the exercises will be
to replicate the traces that are
available here on the website.
To get access to the model
one can just push the download
model button here
which will download a zip file
containing all the procedural
code that's necessary to run
this particular model
as described here
on this page.