Simulation neuroscience
is an emerging approach
to integrate the knowledge dispersed
throughout the field of neuroscience
The aim is to build a unified
empirical picture of the brain
to study the biological mechanisms
of brain function, behavior and disease.
This is achieved by integrating
diverse datasources
across the various scales of
experimental neuroscience
from binocular to clinical
into computer simulations.
In a series of three courses
you will learn to use
the state of the art modeling tools
of the HBP brain simulation platform
to simulate neurons,
build neural networks
and perform your own
simulation experiments.
This is a unique
massive open online course
taught by multidisciplinary team
of world-renowned scientists.
In this first course you will
gain the knowledge and skills
needed to create simulations of
biological neurons and synapses.
Professor Henry Markram
will open the course
and present the basic principles
of simulation neuroscience
and the neuroscience knowledge
it aims to integrate.
Then with professor Sean Hill,
Samuel Kerrienp and Lida Kanari,
you'll learn about the structure
of neuroscience data,
its' analysis and classification,
and how to integrate it
into the neuroinformatic's platform.
Professor Idan Segev will introduce
you to the fascinating world
of biological neurons
and the mathematical methods
to describe their biophysics.
Werner van Geit will show you
how to apply these methods
to create your own neuron models
using the neurone simulator.
From Dr. Srikanth Ramaswamy
and Dr. Eilif Muller,
you will learn the biology
of synaptic transmission
in the near cortex,
and at the simulator using
the neuron simulator.
In the fifth course, professor Schurmann
and Werner Van Geit
will teach you to constrain
neuron models
with experimental data using
genetic optimization techniques.
We invite you to join us
and share our passion
to reconstruct, simulate and
understand the brain.