Welcome back everybody to our course
on smart specialisation strategies.
Now in week three we'll have
a more detailed look at how
really develop such a strategy.
With a bit of theoretical
foundation and the properties
of that concept in the first
two weeks, we now really get
to the work, to
build such a strategy.
To do so let's first look at
a few properties which need
to be reflected in this process.
As the name of three S
already says, such strategy is
smart and special. It's
smart in the sense that it
provides intelligent
combinations and individual
solutions for the region.
And it is special in that
sense that from this process
there should resolve new
specialities for the regional economy.
While it builds on
existing assets, new specialities
should be generated.
Given these properties, it
is probably not surprising
that there is no one size fits all.
There's no blueprint for a
smart specialisation strategy
which fits each and every region.
Instead, the strategy
itself, the contents of the
strategy, of course, have
to be individually adapted to
the region, but not only
the contents, but also the
process leading to this
strategy, the analytical
foundations of that
strategy must be adapted already to
the region itself and
its properties and assets.
But, of course, this is
not the end of that session.
There are a number of
tools, of materials and also a
stylised process
available that you can follow when
developing such a strategy.
Always keep in mind that's
not fixed, but needs to be
individually adapted but you
can take out the elements
out of these tool boxes to
build your
individual analytical process.
It's a little bit like if you imagine
you want to build some new furniture.
I can give you a blueprint
for a wooden table one by two
and a half metres but
probably it won't help any because
the space you have is much
smaller and actually, you want
to have a glass and not wood.
So what we do here is we
provide you with a process which
you can follow, do the
measurement, get a shopping list,
cut the materials, and so on.
We also provide the
materials, you can use glass, wood or
maybe you want to use steel.
And we can provide you with
some tools, a toolbox which
can be used in
building that furniture.
You have to build it
yourself, but you will get a lot of
things you can use in that process.
Now what will we do
throughout that week?
The first session is
really devoted to a suggested
process with elements which
are absolutely necessary for
building a strategy, but
also elements which can be
individually adapted.
In the second session, we
will look at a tool box which
is available for
particularly analytical part of the
strategy building. In the
third session we look at the
data which can be used in
such a process and then the
properties the data must have
which is being used in such a process.
Session four is devoted to
entrepreneurial resources, as
this is especially
important for smart specialisation,
and actually the unique
property of that concept.
And finally we'll give an
example how such a dialogue and
interactions section in the
process building could function.
We will have a lot of
examples throughout the week, the
further we go into
sessions the more we have to work
examples, because there
is less given structures
available, and we will very
often look at the canton of Ticino.
For one reason it helps
to do the examples with one
canton, it gives you a
better overview how the different
steps interact with each other.
But, of course, there's also
the reason that we know the
canton of Ticino very well,
coming from Switzerland, and
it is necessary in the detailed
process that you know the region.
And last not least, we
already did such processes as with
Ticino therefore a lot of
material to build on was available.
Now before going into the
process, what do these other
institutions say about that process?
The EU for example says:
sound analyses of regional
assets and technologies
is part of building a smart
specialisation
strategy, or the OECD puts it at
identifying and selecting a
limited number of priority
areas, identify and select
a limited number, focusing
on their strengths and their
comparative advantages, the
strength and a
comparative advantage of the region.
What do we get out
of these definitions?
First of all, we need a
structured process to really
achieve the goals
given by these definitions.
Without such a process we
will not have a sound base of
analyse and probably not
identify the strengths and all
comparative advantages.
And it must be based on
facts, that is very clear from
that definition,
therefore data is needed for the
process, it's absolutely
essential to build on data.
Now let's go back to
what you already know.
This picture was
already provided in week one.
We will again follow this
picture, but this time with
more focus on: what are
the steps to be done in a
strategy building process?
Of course, we again have to
start with the economic and
industrial structures of a region.
But before going further,
there is one step which might
be a little bit surprising
in the first sight, but to our
experience is very
important. And this is the definition
of the region we are
talking about, of the region the
strategy should be valid for.
Why is this so important?
If different people
involved, and there are many people
involved in the strategy
and in the implementation of
that strategy, if these
people have different ideas about
what region we're talking about,
the strategy in the end won't work.
Therefore, doing this step
explicitly helps a lot in
building the strategy successfully.
But it's also important
that you create some kind of
commitment, which all
of the steps can help by.
If everybody talks about
the same kind of region, then
they commit themselves
stronger towards this region.
When you do so, you
have to keep in mind that
administrative and
functional orders are not already the
same, or functional region is not the
same as in an administrative region.
The functional region is where
there are heavy economic interactions.
And actually a strategy
should be built for a region, for
a geographic area which has
heavy economic interactions
with each other. Of course,
the complete world interacts
today with each other, but
interactions are very strong
that should be a region,
a strategy is valid for.
Of course you also have to
follow administrative borders
and the final
definition will be a compromise.
But it is very important,
in the end, that you agree on
one definition and that
everybody involved in the
strategy is clear
about that definition.
And this is why we put that
at the start of the process
of developing a 3S.
A note on the name region.
Here, and in the following,
we often use "region" as a
synonym for the geographical area
the strategy should be valid for.
Of course that can be a
city, can be a city region, a
city area, a metropolitan
area, there are many different
names a smart
specialisation strategy should work for,
and we just use region
for all of them as a name.
It is important that they
work together as a functional
area and their economic
interactions, it doesn't really
matter what it is named.
Clearly, the next step
is the base of evidence.
Here actually the most
analytical work is necessary.
To be done, there might be a
lot available already, there
might be more work to be
done, but you need to produce a
lot of inputs in that part.
Actually, different kinds
of views are necessary here,
you have to look at the
world and the competitive
position of the region and
the regional industries, the
regional economy, but you
also have to look inside the
region, get a detailed view
on the region itself and on
its assets and properties.
As there is a lot of
elements in there, we will look
at that later on again in
some more detail, let's first
go on with the process.
The next input is
something the region can't change,
which is given from
the regional perspective.
It's the global mega
trends, the trends are
worldwide and driving the
economic conditions of the
region as well. That
could be things like aging of
society, the globalisation
itself is such a mega-trend,
or to digitalisation of
production is also such a mega-trend.
And the second part here is
the general purpose technologies.
Again something which is
not driven by the region, but
kind of given from the
outside of the region, but must be
part of the analysis. Again,
digitalisation is somewhere in between.
Digitalisation could be
named all the communication
technologies, but also
things like nanotechnology for
example, or new materials
are such general purpose
technology that can be applied
in different parts of the economy.
Of course, you're not just needing a
list of these trends and technologies.
You also need to analyse how
they influence the specific
characteristics, the
specific assets, the specific
economy within the region,
how important they are for the
region and how exposed is
the region to these changes.
That is actually part of the
analyse in the base of evidence.
Until now these steps,
global mega trends, the
base of evidence with an
outside and inside view is
pretty well known from
other economic strategies as
well, but now we come to
that part which is really
particularly for smart
specialisation strategy.
That's the analysis of
entrepreneurial resources
available in the region.
In any region there are
entrepreneurial activities, there
might be more or there might
be less, but certainly there
are some activities in this field.
Particularly if you define
that entrepreneurialism in the
broad sense is not just
building start up companies, but
it can be
entrepreneurial activities in existing
companies, it can also
be an earlier stage in the
innovation and invention process.
But there are certainly
activities around, and you should
analyse these activities
so that you get a base of
information, what entrepreneurial
activity you can build the strategy on.
All this information in the
end has to be combined and
brought together,
particularly as, usually, many
different people are
involved in these different steps of
the process, they all and
their information needs to be
brought together, therefore
the dialogue and interaction
part of the strategy
building is quite an important
element.
And then we go to
what we already know.
Of course we have to define
the strategy itself, we have
to define our priority
areas, the promising areas, then
we have to define
activities in these areas, projects,
networks, all these
kind of things, so that the
strategy really is implemented.
Then what you also already
know is we should create that
circle by that
transformative activities building
critical mass by our
activities so that we begin to
influence economic
structure and the whole process
actually can be started
from the beginning again.
Because it's not a one
time off shot, a smart
specialisation strategy, but
it's a continuously adapted
process and a continuously
repeated process actually.
Once you've had success
with one priority area that
probably drops out, but then
another area might be a new
priority area to be
developed and to generate the change
in the economy which
we want to achieve.
Part of this continuous
process is, of course, monitoring
of the process, of the
success of the strategy, of the
impact of the
strategy at different stages.
On the priority areas, we
have to look if this is really
the right priorities. Do
they provide strategic value
for the region? Is the
priority on the activities area,
of course, we have a usual
project monitoring, project
evaluation on going.
Then we have to analyse if
you see the critical mass,
does our priority areas really
create critical mass in the economy?
And then finally is that
really resulting in a structural
change in the economy, or not?
And if any of these fail the
test, we have to, of course,
go back to that step in
the process and review it.
If it's all successful,
then probably the priority at
some point it's kind like
the change is achieved and we
can look for a new priority areas.
Now, summing up, quickly
what we have seen here.
We need a structural
process for a smart specialisation
strategy development.
It's a complex process, it
has many steps and elements
which have to be brought
together in a clever way and
which have to successfully
interact with each other, not
just standing side by side.
It's a multistage process,
we have a couple of areas, we
have an analytical
part, we have a dialogue and
interaction part and then we
have a strategy formulation
part and finally a
monitoring part, there's a consecutive
order to that part.
It is individual for any region.
There is no one size fits
all, you have to adapt, the
strategy itself has to
be adapted to the region's
specific, but also the
process needs to be adapted to the
region specifics to be
successful, but still we
have some structure provided
which helps us building it.
It is interactive, as I have
already pointed out, and it's
continuous, it never ends really.
A successful strategy just
leads to new priority areas
and new activities, but
also in any step of the process
implementation it can be
necessary to go one step back
and do the analyse again
and change the process.
Data is essentially
required for that process.
Without a sound base of
evidence, which is data driven,
the process will only be
successful accidentally, but not
structurally. And there
are two important parts of
analytic input. One is
the base of evidence, we
discussed a little bit which
it would be, we will have a
look at that in the next
session in more detail, and the
entrepreneurial resources
available in the region.
Again we will look at
that in an example in a later
session again, but we have a
little bit of an idea what is in there.
Thank you for your
attention for that session.
In the next part of that
session we will have a look at a
few more details of that process.