After the base of evidence
let's look in another part in
more detail and from the
graphical representation of the
process we have already seen
here that base of evidence,
on the one hand, and the
analysis of the entrepreneurial
resources, on the other
hand, are going together into the
dialogue and interactions.
But let's look in a bit
more detail in the interplay
between these three parts.
In this process there are actually
two ways how it could be organised.
Any of all drawing of the
process we've drawn it like it
is represented here with the
two arrows going towards the
dialogue and interactions.
It could actually be called a
kind of a bottom-up
tactic of the process.
On the one hand we
have the base of evidence.
The base of evidence
provides us with a lot of
information of the economy
and provides us with areas
which have potential for
change, it might be that they
are in need for change,
it might be under pressure,
economic pressure, but it
could also be it's already a
successful area in the
economy but still has potential
for an even further step
change in the future, even
increasing that success more.
On the other hand we have
the analysis of entrepreneurial
resources and that
provides us, completely
independent from the areas
of need, with a list of all
entrepreneurial activities,
projects, people, available
resources for entrepreneurship,
which is available within the region.
And then independently from
these two information in the
dialogue and interactions
part, it is that we combine
these two information to
identify our priority areas.
Then we have to ask
questions like: are there enough
innovation activities in
a possible area in need
or in the potential to
change to achieve finally the
scale necessary really
to have structural change.
Are there sufficient
starting points in the economy for
entrepreneurial activities
which we observed to build one
of the priority areas and
to really be able to get in a
leadership position in
these priority areas, and then
from that discussion you
define the priority areas.
Organising the process in
this bottom-up fashion is
actually the
theoretically optimal way to do it.
It is that what the theory
of smart specialisation would
really say how to do it.
The advantage is that it's
most flexible because you do
the two analytical steps
independently from each other,
they don't influence each
other, and there's not a danger
of missing important
opportunities, particularly out of
the entrepreneurial side
which you might miss if you
don't do that analysis
independently of the economic structure.
But they are of course also
some disadvantages of this process.
There might be an
information overflow actually because
there might be many
entrepreneurial activities and very
difficult then to sort them
and to find all of them actually.
There is a high level of
coordination necessary.
This high governance
difficulties probably.
And it might be dangerous
that pressure groups push the
process (to us to stay)
interested as there is no
pre-defined direction and
might end up capturing the
process.
The alternative
organisation of the process could be
called a more top down
approach and you see that the flow
of information is quite
different in this case.
You do the base of evidence
analysis in a first step, and
that provides us again
this area, this potential for
change, and also provides
as in this case these areas,
these chances for
innovation or competitiveness games.
These areas are now
pre-defined and then given to the
analysis of
entrepreneurial resources, and
entrepreneurial resources
analyses focus on the areas
which had been
identified in the base of evidence
analysis already as
potential areas, and just looks for
entrepreneurial
activities, entrepreneurial projects
fitting within these areas.
That makes it much easier
of course to identify the
appropriate activities,
but you might miss good
chances by that because if
you have a large number of
entrepreneurial activities,
but they don't fit in one of
the priority areas,
you will miss that.
And then after the
analysis of the entrepreneurial
activities, then we go
back to the dialogue and
interaction section and
actually the step then is not as
important as it is in the
other case because here we then
particularly ask the
question does the areas we
identified with
potential for change and the
entrepreneurial activities
that fit to these areas, do
they have this size and
the right potential to really
generate externalities and
the scales necessary to lead
to structural change?
The danger of organising a
process in this way is of
course that you miss
important information as you limit
already the analysis of the
entrepreneurial activities.
And again it might be
dangerous that interest groups push
already for priority
areas and then limit the
entrepreneurial resource
analysis just to the areas of
interest, so here again
there are some governance issues.
In reality usually we will
have a mix of both, and you
should keep in mind the
properties of that so that you
can find the optimal mix
which is for your own region,
which also depends on
structures and governance
capacities available which
process, or if your processes
more going towards the top down or
more towards the bottom-up approach.
Let us a last point for
that video, have a look
on a kind of wording issue,
because we talk about smart
specialisation strategy
or the process of smart
specialisation, and we also
talk about entrepreneurial
discovery and these two are
actually not much different.
An entrepreneurial
discovery process is as it is for
smart specialisation, an
analytical process, it needs
analytical foundation,
it needs a definition of a
priority area and then
includes a number of projects in
these priority areas
interacting with each other, working
together to generate at
the scale and externalities
necessary to really do the
step change for the structural
change in the economy.
But an entrepreneurial
discovery process is the
definition of one
priority area, while a smart
specialisation strategy has
a number of priority areas
and it also has the
monitoring enablation phase which is
not really entrepreneurial discovery.
So, smart
specialisation strategy is actually a
collection of results of
entrepreneurial discovery
processes which each
leads to one priority area.
You could also say smart
specialisation is a kind of
portfolio management of
entrepreneurial discoveries for
one region.
Let's recapture quickly what
the process would look like.
We looked in the first
video of that session, we
discussed the complete
process, in the second video now
we looked at a
couple of more details.
Let's go through the most
important elements again just
to recap them.
The first step we pointed
out as an important element
is the definition of the region.
It is about
identifying your identity.
Be sure of who you are, be
sure what you talk about, and
although it's not really
part of the theoretical concept,
it is really essential that
the strategy is successful,
that you agree on one
definition, there might be already
one, then it's fine, but it
might also be necessary to do
that as a first step.
The second important element is the
base of evidence: identify your needs.
Where is the potential
for structural change?
And where is the need
The next step, or the
next element, the analysis of
entrepreneurial resources.
Identify your opportunities.
What are the chances you face?
What can you do with the
entrepreneurial assets in the region?
What are the opportunities?
Then dialogue and interaction
are the next essential element.
Identify the promising combinations.
Bring the information from
different areas you created
before, you analysed before,
together to really identify
your combinations which
might be most promising for you.
Then define your priority areas.
It's like identify your focus.
Where do you want to focus on?
You can't focus on
everything, you should not focus only
on one thing but identify
the areas you want to focus on.
Then of course in the focus
area, in the priority areas,
you have to define
projects which interact with each
other, create
networks, platforms, invest in
R&D collaborations, all of
these kinds of things, it's
like identify your activities,
identify what you want to do.
Last not least, don't forget
to monitor and if necessary
adapt your strategy.
At each different step,
where this is possible, it could
be said identify what works.
And if it doesn't work,
change something, and if it still
doesn't work probably you
have to drop a priority area.
That can happen. Smart
specialisation is about
entrepreneurship,
entrepreneurial discovery.
Entrepreneurial
discovery is a discovery
process, you can be
successful with it but you might also
fail, this is why you
should not only have one priority
area but look at several,
and you should monitor that you
recognise in time if it works or
not, not to waste more investment.
The seven elements presented
in the last slide, these are
essential for a smart
specialisation strategy, you need
them really, but even one
step further, we also provided
more individual steps
for such a strategy.
They are maybe not all of
them essential, but if you
follow them, you
cover all important areas.
You might have to focus
more on one, than another, but
still you will cover all
areas which might help in
building such a strategy.
Thank you for the moment.
Thank you for this session,
and in the next session we
will look into more detail
into the tools available for
these steps, and
particularly available for analysing
the base of evidence.
Thank you.