Hello everybody let's have a
look on a couple of details
of the process in a
little deeper closer way.
It starts with this
overall picture again, the first
thing I will look at more
detail as promised already is
the base of evidence.
And I have already pointed
out in the last video, the
base of evidence actually
is a big box of different
analytical tools and steps
to be done and let's have a
closer look what belongs to
it, I already pointed out in
the last video a few
differences or different aspects of
the analysis there and actually
we can follow up that further.
The first part, what should
be done in a base of evidence
is a kind of an
outward-looking view, a view looking from
the region to the outside
to the rest of the world and
particularly how the
region is positioned within this
global and competitive world.
It is a very statistic
analysis, there's a lot of data
available, we come back to
the data in a later session
and so we can base a lot of
analytics and a lot of data in that part.
From the topics to be
covered in that analysis, we can
sort it in five topics here,
it could be some more, some
less if you want but we
have to experience that these
files are pretty much what is needed.
It is first a performance,
you need to know what the
region already achieves,
we'll use it as a starting
position (the values) of
the region, the productivity,
how strongly it grew
lately and things like that.
Secondly, the industrial
focus of course is very
important for this smart
specialisation strategy in
knowing which areas, you have to
know which areas the region is good.
Then in a world with more
and more competition, it's
getting more globalised all
the time, competitiveness of
the region as a whole but
also with the key industries in
that region is an
important element in that
analysis. But it's not only
about the industries, which
you need to look at, you
also have to look at location
factors, the conditions the
economy faces within the regions.
They have topics like
taxation, regulation, or
accessibility of the
regions but they also (start) the
topics like quality
of life or cultural
(availabilities) which need
to be considered here and, of
course, also natural
resources, might it be in real
resources, coal and
steel, might it be in
infrastructure or in
connectivity assets like the
possibility for a harbour
city or might it be in natural
resources in the sense
that it's very good for
recreational issues,
mountains, a lake or things like that.
And, of course, smart
specialisation is about innovation,
new things,
entrepreneurial activities.
So the innovation
capacities, in the region, all those
parts of the analysis, we
will come back to that in more
detail, remember this is for
international comparison of
the region, where the region
stands but it's also part of
that analysis. Now we
call that often international
benchmarking, this part
of the analysis because
benchmarking is the method
you should apply here or one
of the methods, the most
important method to be applied
here, benchmark the region with
other regions, compare it with them.
And it certainly should
be international today.
Competition is actually
global and the competition
between regions is not
between two or three neighbouring
regions, although there are
some competition as well but
to really know your
competitive position in the world,
you have to look internationally.
If you want to characterise
that part of the analysis, we
often put it as it is a kind
of a helicopter view of the
region, it gives you the
broad overall picture in the
region, it also shows you
the surrounding, the setting
the region is in and it is
a bit of a neutral overall
look on the region.
In the next step, that will
be a little bit different.
The next step still draws on
data and on statistics a lot
but it focuses much
more on the region itself.
It goes much more into
detail of the region and one reads
that is a separate step
is that often data which is
available for international
comparison is not as detailed
as the data which is
available if you only look
particularly at your own
region and we (inaudible) of
course make use of
these available information.
The topics you are keeping
yourself busy with is that
part of analysis are
actually not that much different
from the part of the
international analysis but instead
of getting a broad over
view, here you really go into the
details and try to understand in
detail what is behind these figures.
Again industrial structures
is an important issue here,
look at the details of
the industries, you might
internationally
recognise you have a very strong
pharmaceutical industry
but when you look into the
details you probably can
find out, is it headquarter or
is it research or maybe it's
the production side of this
industry which is important
for you, which of course the
end of (discretion) has
very different implications for
the strategy building.
Clusters are an important
part of regional economic
development by now, it is
very well established that
clusters can add quite a
bit to regional values.
Therefore they are also
the starting point for new
specialisations not the
clusters themselves but they
might provide input so part
of the individual analysis of
the region is also an
analysis of available clusters.
And clusters is not only
concentration, concentration is
something you already look
at industrial details but a
cluster is defined as a
concentration combined with
activities of working
together with an organisation and
network or another kind of a
structure and these can, of
course, build a starting point.
And again the regional
innovation system is important and
particularly not the system
only by itself, the number of
universities and so on
but also if it fits well,
(inaudible) structures do
the focus of the innovation
system, the good faculties
of the university, for example
or the independent
research companies, do they fit
together with the
industrial structure or not and
actually if tree answer is
not, it might be part of this
smart specialisation
strategy to achieve a better fit
here, to find new
connections between the innovation
system and the economic structure.
As we've said, we know already a lot
about the region but not everything.
There are things which are
not visible in statistics and
that is why also a
contextual analysis should be part of
the base of evidence analysis.
Here we look beyond
statistics to test the knowledge of
the region and particularly
one area which we often have
to look on is the
political environment the region is
living in, the governance
of the region itself, of
course, what are the region
strategies, has it policies
which might influence their
economic strategy but also
the broader economic
environment like national framework
conditions what it
can be used for that.
That is something you don't
find in statistics but, of
course, it's very
important to understand the region.
The next step is something
we already discussed but it is
at that moment in the analysis,
it has to move into the picture.
It is the global
mega-trends in the general purpose
technology and the
questions how do they influence the
regional assets which we already
analysed in the first three steps here.
What is really the
impact of these trends and the
possibilities of these
technologies for the regional
economies or the
assets and structures.
So it's kind of, after doing
the analysis once, you look
at the global mega
trends and the general purpose
technology and find out where in
the region do they influence that.
From all these
analytical steps, we get a lot of
information altogether
and they have to bring that
together now to find out
the… to condense that to an
overall picture and that is
actually what a swot analysis
does, the strengths and
weaknesses, the chances and the
threats for the region
that is the real output of all
this kind of analysis
and brings it all together.
All this builds the base of
evidence and you've probably
noticed that it is very
similar to other strategies, it
is not really particular to
smart specialisation strategy
but if you do a detailed
economic strategy for a region,
you will do exactly
these steps to build it.
What is really new about
smart specialisation is what
comes after building a base
of evidence but without that
base probably you won't be
successful in smart specialisation strategy.