Welcome back everybody.
In this session we will
have a look at the tool box.
You will see a few
examples of tools which we can use
when do the analyse
the base of evidence.
The first step is to remember
why we are doing this at all.
The base of evidence is the
foundation of the complete
strategy, we need to know
exactly what we are building
on, on what we can rely on.
And that's what the SWOT
analysis provides us with the
strengths and weaknesses of
the region we can build on,
but furthermore the
available resources and existing
specialities in the
regions, these are our departing
points for further smart
specialisation, so this is also
something which should come
out of the base of evidence,
but even one step further
the analysis should also
provide us with first ideas
of possible priority areas,
of areas of interest for a change.
Might it be that they need
to change, or might it be that
the change generates
more dynamics in this area.
That's also part of what the
base of evidence should tell
us, or the analysis
underlying it should tell us,
potential priority areas.
But there is even one step
more, it's not only about
identifying priority areas.
The goal is that these
priority areas and the activities
resound in the step change
for the whole economy, that
they have a critical mass,
or generate a critical mass,
they provide externalities
and transformative activities
so that they get a
structural change in the complete
economy, and again the
analysis we do when we build the
base of evidence should
provide us with some information
if this is possible in
the potential priority area.
Before going into the
tools available, let's quickly
recap what questions
we would like to answer.
Which industries which
sectors or activities are
important for the region?
What are the drivers
of the regional economy?
Are these industries
competitive in the international
competitive environment?
Or are they only locally focused so
they are not exposed to competition?
What's the future
potential of these industries?
Are they in a growing area
or in a decreasing market?
Do we already identify
key sectors, or unique
combinations or clusters in
the region which we can build on?
And how is the location
quality in the region?
And does it relate well to
what we found (inaudible)?
Are classes supported by the
right quality factors in the
region, or do they not fit together?
As much specialisation is
a lot about innovation and
change, of course the
innovation capacities are very
important, what are
available in the region?
and how does the
regional innovation system work?
should be answered.
And last not least how do
megatrends and general purpose
technology influence the
results we found (inaudible)
what do they mean for the
future perspective of the focus
areas of the region industries?
Now did I bore you with
these questions a little bit?
I hope so because that should
be already clear that that's
what needs to be answered.
Now let's have a look at
how we can answer that.
Instead of now going
directly to the tools I would like
to try to structure the
further process a little bit.
We at (inaudible) developed
a regional profile toolbox
which should help to have
more structure in the analysis.
It's actually based on
three pillars, what we call
performance attractiveness
and structural potential.
The performance is the
part looking backwards.
It looks at what has been achieved
until now, where is the region today?
and of course as trends
often go on longer, it is often
an indicator what the
region might be developing to.
The second pillar, the
attractiveness, looks at the
location conditions of the
region, how is the region
positioned in a competitive
world: is it attractive for companies?
is it attractive for
certain industries?
is it attractive for people,
particularly for highly qualified people?
And finally the third
pillar, the structural potential,
we want to have a look into
the future, but not in the
sense of a forecast, but in a
sense of potential of development.
Therefore we analyse the
economic structure and look what
potential is inherent
in these structures.
But this is not only a
structure for the analysis, it's
also that we build
indicators for each of these three
pillars, they allow a quick
overview of the results of that pillar.
But of course there's a lot
of underlying analysis and
data and that drill down
possibilities into all these
indicators until
very detailed levels.
But let's see how
really works in reality.
The first example is the
performance index, reflecting
the economic
performance of the region.
An example taken is actually
for the canton of Ticino as
I announced before we have many
examples for Ticino so is this one.
And Ticino is doing
quite well in the economic
performance, you can
see that in this index.
The index is constructed in
a way that one hundred equals
the western European
average, and with a value of above
110 Ticino is doing better
than the western European
average, and actually doing
quite substantially better as
a difference of ten points
means one standard variation,
and so the medium
variations on the average of all
European regions, so
Ticino is even better than the
western European average
than one standard variation, and
you can also see that
if you compare it to the
benchmarking regions, also
given in the chart, Ticino is
in quite a leading position,
all the other Swiss regions
are actually doing better.
Of course a performance
index is only a very brief
overview but gives a first
insight into the development
of the region, to understand
that in more detail you have
to drill down much for more
in the data, and that's what
we will do in the next
few slides and examples.
Of course it won't be
possible to do the complete
analysis here, that would
overstretch the videos quite a bit.
But in the reading materials
you have the example of the
analysis we did for Ticino,
there are many more examples
of graphics and analytics in there.
And actually even there in
the report not everything was
done in the analytical
phase, before to report we did
much more and selected to
analysis which are interesting.
But here I really have to
focus on a very few examples
illustrating that, and the
next example will really show
how much deeper into
the details we can go.
In this example we look at
the details of the industry
structure and actually it
looks at the whole of the
industry of the canton of Ticino.
It compares these industries with
the same industries in other regions.
And the first thing we
see is that the whole of the
sector is fairly important
in Ticino as the horizontal
axis which provides the
share of this sector within the
complete economy, only
central Switzerland has a higher
share, all other regions
have the same or a lower share.
We also see that the
wholesale trade is a quite
successful sector in
Ticino it had not the top growth
but it is among the stronger
growing regions in the last ten years.
So it's a sector which
has some potential and some
importance for Ticino and
could be analysed so for smart
specialisation strategy.
The third example moves away
from the economic structure
now and looks at the
location quality, and this time the
example is not for
Ticino but for Brussels.
We have a number of
locations sectors reflected in that
chart, and again we compare
that to do western European
average of all regions
which equals again one hundred.
We also observe here how the
structure changed, what did
Brussels achieve over this
period of six years from 2006 to 2012?
And if you look at the
details, there is particular
manpower taxation where
Brussels performs first in the
western European average and
actually only improved very
slightly since 2006.
By the way the indicators
defined are defined in a way
that lower values reflect
what is less attractive for
economic activities, so
higher taxes have lower values in
that chart and vice versa.
But Brussels also has
a couple of strengths.
Particularly in the
accessibility, which is one of the
strength of Brussels which
actually improved, at least at
a continental level, over time.
And also in the area of
innovation, the Shanghai index
which measures the
university quality and the (inaudible)
density and the patent
density are rather good in Brussels.
So Brussels is positioned
quite well with its location
factors and also not only
for administrative work like
the EU, but also for
innovative industries, as you can
see on the innovation indicators.
The fourth example now
goes further down into the
analysis, it drills
down further into details.
It's what we call the
capacity to compete.
The idea here is that the
industries have to compete
on interregional and
international markets, and we want
to know how competitive they
are as an indicator for the
possible future success.
You see from that
description that is part of the
structural potential
pillar of the analysis.
Now first of all we have
to know which industries do
compete
interregionally and internationally.
It's not only the industries
which exports their product.
It can also be industries
with produce for the regional
market that could
potentially be replaced by imports to
these market so that they
also face the international
interregional competition.
That's true for most of the
producing industries of the
secondary sector, but it
also is true for quite some
services for example
tourism, in the financial sector, or
in the wholesale trade.
Now let's look at the result
of this example again, which
is again for the canton of Ticino.
We first had a look on the
share of the export-oriented
industries, and is given
again on the horizontal axis,
and we see that wholesale
trade is very important, the
sector we already analysed
before in the example, but
also medical profession
and optimal instruments for
example, or chemicals
and pharmaceuticals.
But now we also need a
measure of the competitiveness of
these industries on the inter
regional and international markets.
And we do that by the
productivity as an indicator for
competitiveness, which is
readily available, it's not the
optimal indicator of
course, but it is the one which is
internationally comparable.
And here we see that the
picture changes somewhat, these
particular textile and
fashion industries which is very
productive in Ticino
compared to other regions in Europe,
it has actually three times
the productivity of the other
regions, that's what
two hundred percent mean.
So although this industry
is rather small in the Ticino
economy, it contributes a
lot to the competitiveness of
the industry overall, that is
given by the size of this figure.
The other very important
industry and it's also the
reason we looked at it in more
detail before, is the wholesale industry.
It is more competitive, it
has a higher productivity than
the average European region,
but is not as far up as the
textile industry, but he
has a very big share in the
economy, so therefore it's
important, it is very important as well.
There is also one
industry which had a negative
contribution to competitiveness,
and its hotels and restaurants.
If you know the Ticino
economy a little bit you know this
is an area where Ticino
really faces difficulties.
And it's now a question
for a smart specialisation
strategy if a step change
in a transformation in that
sector could be possible or
if the potential is higher to
increase the
wholesale sector's success.
These few examples gave an
impression but it's possible
for the outside part of
the evidence base analysis.
Of course there is much
more to be done and much more
tools and analysis to be
used to really get there, much
more than I can
introduce in such a short time.
I did give you an
impression, first of all that there
might be a structure, we
propose a structure of potential
attractiveness and
performance, but other structures can
be chosen as well, and
that there are drill down
possibilities, you start
with an overview analysis, and
then drill down further
into areas of interest, where
they show up that there might
be potential then you go further.
Now what does the outward
looking analysis provide us with?
It is the foundation, of
course, of the complete
strategy, without it it's
not possible to formulate a
successful strategy, or
just accidentally but not
systematically. It focuses
on the relative position of
the region, compares the
region inter regionally and
internationally and reflects
global competition thereby.
And it's that part of the
analysis where the most tools
are available and the most
standardised structures can be
used to analyse it
has been done often.
In the next part of this
session we will see how that can
be more drilled down to the
region, more an inward view
which goes into more
details of the region, and I'm
looking forward to see you
back for that second part of
this session, thank you.