Welcome back to the
second part of the session.
When in last part we
focused on the outward view of the
evidence-based, this time
we will look more into the
inward side of the analyse.
Let's look first what are
the main characteristics again
of this inward view.
We will focus on the
individual region and really going
to the specific and details
of those regions and not look
that much on the
competitive position.
There are a number of
consequences of this feature.
There are analytical tools
of course available for this
kind of analyse but it is much less
standardised than in the outward view.
We need to look more at a
specific need, into specific
characteristics of the regions
and adapt our analyse to this.
Still the focused area of
the analyse are not that much
different from the outward analyse.
We again look at the industry
structure, that's in a much more detailed way.
We will keep us busy with
clusters and we will look at
the regional innovation
system in more detail.
But let's go into some examples.
The examples provided in
the following for analyses on
the inside view are much
more of an illustrative
character than they have
been for the outside view.
But for the outside view there's
a relatively structured process.
For the inside view we
have to look much more on the
characteristics and
individual properties of a region and
adapt the analyse according to it.
Still, the examples,
which I again take in from the
Canton of Ticino, do
provide a couple of interesting
insight and how such an
analyse can be conducted.
Actually the first example already
points to a very important issue.
In a discussion, I pointed
out that the different steps
of the analyse, for example
the industry structure and
the innovation system,
can't be seen all completely
separately but have to
interact with each other.
And that is well something,
precisely, this example does.
It analyses if the
industry structure and innovation
system are harmonised, if
they work together well or if
they do not.
We measure here, with
an RTA index, a Relative
Technological Advantage
index, the importance of
different fields of the
industry, by gross value added
actually, and the
importance of the innovation system
in that field by the
patents intensity actually.
And we can see that, for
Ticino, there are in a number of
industry's areas,
this fit is quite well.
For example the
chemical raw materials or the
pharmaceuticals, in both
cases the concentration index
is higher than in Western
European average, and pretty
close to each other
actually, (inaudible).
So the Ticino innovation
system is focused in the same
areas as the industry in Ticino is.
But that is not true
for all industries.
For example in the
electrical engineering Ticino is quite
focused in this area,
in the industry side.
But the innovation system,
measured by the patents here,
does not reflect that.
So here probably we don't
have that much innovation
capacities to support that industry.
And all this is relative.
Of course some
industries, like, for example
pharmaceutics, produce much
more patents than for example
electrical engineering.
But all of these
measures are relative to Western
European averages, so the
relative patent intensity in
Ticino is lower
than in other regions.
But their relative industry
share is higher and therefore
that does not fit together perfectly.
Which might of course be a
possible approach for a smart
innovation strategy.
If you find innovative
activities which can push the
research side of the
electrical engineering industry,
that could create the transformative
action for these industry possibly.
But we're still in the
statistic analyses, not in the
project of priority area definition.
But it might be a
possible point to follow up.
The next example shows
how the analyse from the
outward side can be driven
down in much more detail by
the inward analyse,
inward looking analyse.
From the outward analyse we
know that the life science
industries, one of the focus
areas of the Ticino industry.
But let's get in,
somewhat, deeper into it.
Although Ticino is one
region, it has several sub-regions
which can be analysed
separately and that's the first
thing which was done in this example.
We see the life, the
location quotient of the life
science industry in this 5
sub-regions of Ticino, and we
clearly see although it is
rather high in nearly all of
these regions, it is very much
concentrated in one region particularly.
Even going into more
details we can look at the
municipalities the life
science industry is located in.
And we see that by the
dots on the graph, that it is
really focused very much in a
fairly small area of the region.
So here really some
cluster features appear.
Furthermore it's a callous
demonstrate, it is not only
one part of that industry,
but if you look at production,
trade with this goods and
research separately, you see
that particular production
and trade are closely related,
and their many
activities in this area also quite
substantial by the size,
reflected by the size of the bullets.
Which is less prominent is
divide spots which reflect
the research side.
And there are also not
really located in the middle of
the cluster but a little
bit further out, although the
distances are not far,
there might be some potential
again here for more
research driven parts.
But again we're not at the
point of that finding priority
areas yet.
That is still the
statistically analyse and we have to
check if we find project
which have the potential to
increase the research side
of the life science industry
which might then help
to complete cluster.
This last example's focus on the
research network of the region of Ticino.
Actually we used again
patent data, joint patent
applications, to see where
are research cooperation with
other regions and Ticino.
What we observe is that
Ticino has quite a number of
corporations but most
of them are focused on a
geographically fairly
near base to Ticino itself.
Most of the corporations
have a Swiss origins or this is
northern Italian origins.
There are less further away
corporations like with London
or the States,
although there are some.
For the smart
specialisation strategy development, that
is a hint that probably we
can use research potential,
some closer by regions quite
well, as these corporations work well.
But on the other hand
also project improving their
further away connections,
if they are useful for the
local industry, might be an option.
Again we are not in
the area of defining
priorities now. But
still in the analytical area.
The defining of
priorities needs more inputs.
And that's what I
want to look at next.
Up to now, the examples that I
provided work the statistics.
But as we recall from
the process, there's also a
contextual part of the
base of the evidence analyses
which is not based in
statistics, where we go beyond statistics.
In that part we have to
access the knowledge of people.
People in the region, but
they also, maybe be outside the
region, access their
knowledge and access their ideas and
their information to
include them in the analyse.
This of course is the most
complex part, probably, of the analyses.
But at the same time it's
the less standardised part.
Therefore we can't provide
many tools here, but we will
see in a later session an
example how that might look
like in a region and how
may that might be organised.
But there are few principles
which we can follow in that
part of the analyses.
It should be interactive.
We should talk to the people,
we have to talk to the people.
But we also might need to go
back to them again, with new
ideas and re-ask them
certain questions to really get all
information which is available.
And it does an explanatory process.
We don't up ahead exactly
know where it will lead.
There might be some misleading parts.
But in the end you have to
follow the map to find out if
they are misleading or not
and you'll find very useful
parts by doing so.
Secondly it is very regional focused.
It is not about international
competition and comparison and benchmarking.
It's really going into
the details of the region,
actually also into details
of certain areas which might
be priority areas later, or even
already to individual projects.
Also at that part of the
analyse, we're not really
looking at projects, these
information, these bits and
bytes of information, which
in the beginning might not be
really connected, might be
important in the end for the
structural analyse, for the base of
evidence to have that really complete.
And thirdly this part of
the analyse can't be done by
administrative people only
alone or by researchers alone.
It is actually
about talking to people.
That administrative part is only
coordinating all the information.
But you need to talk to
people in innovative firms, you
need to talk to researchers, in
universities or other institutions.
You need to talk to
inventors and investors into regions,
and innovators, to all
these kinds of people.
But you also need to
talk to policy makers.
What are they up plans,
what are their views on this.
You probably also need to
talk to senior administrative
people to really get a
complete contextual picture of
the region.
With that, we have seen
examples of the most parts of the
base of evidence analyse.
So we should be
able to follow that up.
In the next few sessions we
will also have a few examples
how that really works but we
now know a little bit about
a toolbox and how to use it.
So looking forward to see
you again in the next session.
Thank you.