Welcome again. Today, we're going
to have a closer look at the data.
We already saw, in the last session
how the data can be used,
what are the analytical tools we can
use with the data.
But today we'll look a little bit
more in what sources of data are
available.
And what are the properties
the data needs to have to be
valuable for analysis.
As we know from earlier discussion
smart specialisation is based
on facts
and therefore all the data
is required.
But the analysis we want to conduct
is very demanding on the data.
It has to have certain properties
so that the analysis is valid
and valuable at the end.
The most important properties are
these that cover the relevant topics
reflecting the economic and the
industry structure of course
But also looking at the quality of
the location and of innovation
resources available in the region.
Because all that is an important
part of smart specialisation.
The data also has to be very
differentiated and detailed.
Smart specialisation is a strategy
not looking at the industry level
but at the sub-industry stage
where things really happen
in a smart specialisation.
And to really have the right inputs
from the data analysis the data
of course needs all  that to reflect
the sub-industry stage of the
economic structure as well.
Furthermore, the data has to cover
the region we want to analyse.
We pointed out before in the
discussion how important it is
to define the region consistently
and to create a commitment
towards the region.
But if the data doesn't cover that
region then of course the analysis
is only of a limited value
to the strategy building
and it might also be bad for
the identification of the region.
Finally, the data should be
internationally comparable
and of course have an
international coverage.
Global competition today is what is
really facing regions and just a
national data analysis would not
really reflect that global
competition for the region
and therefore be again only
of limited value in a smart
specialisation strategy
building process.
Now all these demanding properties
for the data makes it clear that
it is not so straightforward
and there are not so many data
sources available for this
Actually you need to combine
various data sources to get at
those goals anyway.
But there's one data source which we
developed at BAK Basel
as we do that kind of analysis for
many years for regions
it is just that properties which
follows this database
which might be quite useful.
And I will introduce that database
and its properties and its coverage
in the next few slides to you.
Of course you can also use it as a
database, but it might be easier
and more efficient  to use the
existing one than to combine others
but I will come back to that
at the end.
This database, the BAK Regional
Economic Database is explicitly
built to support regions as a key
player in economic development.
Most other databases focusing on
national level and only have
a derivative regional coverage
are not really focused on the needs
of the regions.
In this database it is really the
regions we look at
and the information is supposed to
be useful for regions.
We also take of course a global
perspective and the perspective
of international competition.
It is always the international few
and the comparison of the region
which is of interest to us.
Actually, benchmarking is the
essential tool we use there
and until recently actually the
database was called International
Benchmarking Database.
We just renamed it to Regional
Economic Database because we think
region is the important property
of the database and not
the benchmarking which is nestled
behind it.
But still benchmarking is also
learning from the best that is also
what you can do with that database.
What do other regions do and how
successful are they with what they
do can be analyzed there.
It covers the relevant topics,
economic performance
location quality and innovation
capacities, and all that together
then builds the Regional Economic
Database, powered by BAK Basel.
Now what are the properties of this
database?
As we are interested in regions,
of course the first important part
is the geographical coverage of the
database.
At the core of the database we focus
on OECD countries, the most
developed industrialized countries
as the benchmarking sample for the
regions we are interested in here
but the structures of the database
are easily expandable
so other countries can be covered
there as well.
But of course countries are only
geographic coverage, the core
interest is on regions
And within the 24 countries which
are included in the database
at the moment, there are more than
1100 regions covered in the database.
And this is only the lowest level,
of course we can aggregate further
regions out of these 1100
individual regions.
And this is what we call flexible
geographies within the database and
also provided by the example here.
This actually is the metropolitan
region of Hamburg
and if you know Hamburg
the administrative region of the
city of Hamburg is rather small
and that's actually a Bundesländ
in Germany
so from an administrative level it's
a very divided functional region
the metropolitan area of Hamburg
In most German data you will only
find the Bundesländer
while our database allows you to
flexibly define
what is the metropolitan area
Hamburg.
In that graph you see 3 different
examples but of course
there are more possible and that you
can work with this definition.
And the structure of the database
the consistency and all the data
is complete allows you really to be
very flexible within the geographic
definitions.
Any combination can be used and can
be analyzed into all details.
In this graph you see a quick
overview of the countries which
are covered  and the number of
regions in the individual countries
I leave that to you for further
or detailed analysis
and like to move on to the
sector coverage.
Regions are very important in the
database, but actually for smart
specialisation it is important to
have a detailed industry data
available because you want to go
beyond the usual industry level
like car manufacturing or trade
and go into more details
Within our regional economic
database we cover at the lowest
level, 115 individual industries.
The definitions are based on the
international ISIC classification
which is quite common  and also the
European definitions are based on
the ISIC with very small variations
which helps to compare it with
external data if necessary.
Within  these 115 industries we
usually use the 2 digit ISIC
classification is so-called
but in the production sector we
consider that very important for the
economic development and also very
important for smart specialisation
we also cover the so-called 3 digit
level of the ISIC classification.
So in the production sector we are
even more detailed
while in the service sector the
level of detail is a little bit less.
It is very interesting with that
database that we can also go beyond
the ISIC classification of course.
You see that in the example here
for the Life Science Industry.
The Life Science Industry as it is
defined here,
consists of the pharmaceutical
industry, that's fairly
straightforward
but then there is the manufacture
of medical instruments
or of electro medical instruments.
These are different industrial areas
in the ISIC classification they are
not just next to pharmaceuticals
and usually it is difficult to
analyse them together
but we can do that.
But even more, there is also
a service part related to the
Life Science Industry, and it is the
research in biotechnology that's
also part of the Life Science
Industry but in the usual
structure of economic analysis part
of the services
within our database, it is possible
to create such a Life Science
aggregate and analyse
the Life Science Industry, and that
is only one example of many
Which are possible.
Now of course it is very important
what indicators are covered
within the database.
and it is a kind of two split
database,
the core part is what we call
economic performance which really
looks at economic indicators
and then we also have location
factors, I'll come back
to that in a minute but let's stay
for the moment with the economic
performance.
The structure of the database and
the definition is based on the
system of national accounts.
so that guarantees and helps to have
all the data internationally
comparable
if at some point we need to do
adaptions to that
we did that so really all data
in the database is internationally
comparable.
The two key indicators in the
database are GDP,
or if you look at an industry level
value added, which is the same
concept
and employment, of course.
But there are a number of further
indicators a number of
calculated indicators from these
key figures like working hours
labour costs, unit labour costs
productivity very important in the
competitive analysis
GDP per capita and so on
and so forth.
The database also has various prices
and currencies within the database
though for example of course
we look at real anomaly developments
but you can also use purchasing
power, parities or current exchange
rate, you can have the data in
different kinds of currencies
with Francs, US Dollars or Euros
or any other you are interested in.
So it is very flexible and complete
from that perspective.
In the example here you see
a drawing for another region
for Villa Manin, it's a Euroregion
and actually a cross border region
so you can see how flexibly we can
build these kind of analysis
and you can see the GDP
the productivity and the employment
growth for this cross border region.
I already mentioned that the database
also includes location factors.
Of course while the economic
performance based on the system of
national accounts is very much
harmonizing, the national lean
only needs small adaptions to be
comparable, that's not true for
location factors.
There are many differences in
international measurement
and the way the location factors
are defined.
But what we do in the databases,
the location factors we include,
we guarantee that they are
internationally comparable
and we also usually have
quantitatively comparable
location factors with a quantitative
measure behind them.
Or we use qualitative measures
but then put them through
in depth processes that are similar
to a quantitative measure.
So the location factors which are in
the database can be internationally
compared and can be quantitatively
compared with each other to define
the position of the region
It includes the most important
location factors, particularly
so-called hard factors like taxation
regulation, labour markets, diggers
availability of qualified labour
force and so on.
But we also look at softer factors
if possible of course quantification
is more difficult yes
but for example the quality of life
is one factor which we are
looking at.
Finally there's a special focus on
all innovation related location
factors so that this important
part of smart specialisation is
all covered in the database to the
best possible extent.
Again it is very important that
all this is  broken down to the
regional level if appropriate
but there are also some national
figures in if they drive
the regional economy like national
regulation is of course relevant
for the regional economy as well but
usually like in tax levels
or inaccessibility we look at the
regional level for the location
factors as well.
Furthermore on the indicator side we
not only have what we might call the
the raw information which I
presented up till now
but there are also quite a number of
summarizing information which makes
the database more easily accessible
but then always has the drill down
possibility into the details.
One of them is summarized indexes
which I already introduced last week
in one of the examples, the
performance index attractiveness
or structural potential indexes.
And there are various ready to use
new industry definitions, I showed
one in the example before the Life
Science Industry but there are
quite some more which can be used
in the analysis and they can also
be easily built and then
incorporated on a regular basis
into the database.
And we also have predefined sets of
benchmarking regions.
Who do we compare with?
We can compare with an average of
all regions for example
but we can also look for a region
with strong financial sectors
we can pick all the other financial
sector regions.
Or for a harbor and trade city
we could pick all the other regions
with harbors and trade activities.
And there are a number of sets
already defined of regions with
common properties which built the
right benchmarking samples.
Now summing up what are the key
advantages of our database and what
properties of other data sources
should we follow as well
if they are valid for the analysis
of the smart specialisation strategy.
The extended regional and the
extended industry coverage
is a very important habit
particularly because it goes across
this many numbers of indicators.
You can of course find other
databases which go
into the same regional detail maybe
even more and you can find databases
which have even more detailed
industry coverage,
but usually you don't find that
combined.
And particularly then you can't
compare that internationally.
One thing that I didn't mention yet
is the coverage over time of the
database.
This is actually a database of
annual data, starting in '95 of the
last century and going currently
until 2015 so it covers 20 years.
And usually the database is expanded
around the middle of the year to
cover the last year
so the information is quite up to
date compared with other sources.
The complete database is consistent
and balanced.
That means that many combinations
are possible and you don't get
missing data or not working
because of missing data or some
small parts of it.
So you really have the consistency
and the balanced properties of the
database which allows you a
flexible analysis.
And then the already mentioned
summary indexes are quite valuable
for the analysis and as well as the
new industry structures and the
facts of benchmarking regions.
If you are interested in more
details we are happy to provide them
there is also a web page of course
where you can find all that kind of
information.
Now I introduce our own database and
the properties of it
which shows what is possible
but also there are some limits to it
Of course you can use other
databases as a data source
and actually we did that in building
that database.
We didn't do any primary research
but we used various different
databases to get our internationally
consistent and complete database
together as well as a couple of
statistical and economical tools
to fill the gaps.
But you could go directly to the
original databases and particularly
with the regional accounts
is one of the most important sources
for us and that could be a first
source of access for you as well.
And if you are only interested in
Europe and not look at the global
competition but focus on Europe
you will start of course as an
important source for data.
And both of these sources are more
on the economic performance side
and for the innovation side of the
smart specialisation analysis
always the patent databases ones of
or again if you look more at Europe
it's the European Regional
Innovation Scoreboard
which might be a very useful source.
All this data, our own database
which I introduced but also these
sources I named until now, they are
more suited for the part of the
evidence base which is international
benchmarking setting
the position of the region in the
international setting.
For going into more details you have
to go into more detailed national
statistics which cover the regions.
There's of course national accounts
and regional accounts
production accounts as possible
sources.
Most of what is available at that
level is included actually in our
international database so that we
would give too much additional
information, but particularly labour
force survey
or business righteousness
These are the sources providing very
detailed information on the industry
structure within a country and
within your region then as well
so they should be accessed for that.
And then there are many other
sources, there might be regional
cluster maps or cluster atlases
cluster lists which you can use
and so on and so forth
That then really depends on your
individual region.
Summing up
data is an essential input for
developing a smart specialisation
strategy, without data it will be
very difficult if not impossible
to realign such a strategy
There are numerous data sources
which can be explored but most of
them are not detailed enough for the
kind of analysis which we like to do
as a basis for smart specialisation
therefore you need to combine these
data sources and that's part of
the work we already did at BAK Basel
resulting in the RED, the Regional
economic database which offers an
efficient and effective starting
point for such an analysis.
Thank you for today, looking forward
to see you again soon.