Welcome everybody.
In the last module,
we had a detailed look
at the so called Base of Evidence,
the first pillar
of the information foundation
for a smart specialization strategy.
But there is a second pillar
and that
are entrepreneurial resources
available in the region.
The idea of smart specialization
is not
that entrepreneurial activities
or innovation
has to be generated from scratch
started from a new, from nothing
but to build on what
if already existing.
It is a smart strategy.
It builds on what we have.
But to do that, we of course need
to know what kind
of entrepreneurial resources
are available
and to gather this information,
is everything else,
than straight forward.
Nearly by definition the information
on entrepreneurial resources
is scattered and only unstructured.
So, that makes it so difficult
to gather it.
But let's have a look
how we can proceed.
The process will be interactive
and exploratory.
It is an unstructured set
of information
and therefore we need
to adopt our process
to the kind of information
which we find.
Also it will be usually
qualitative information,
not quantitative ones,
which we need in that part
of the process.
Therefore, it will be also
region specific.
But it's also because regions
differ a lot between each other.
There might be
different institution settings
and different institutions involved
in entrepreneurial activities
in the region.
There might be also
cultural differences in how
the attitudes towards
entrepreneurship
and who is behaving
entrepreneurial.
So, we need to adopt
to be regional conditions,
that part of the analysis.
But in any case, it will involve
many different kind of people.
There will be
entrepreneurs themselves
there can be innovative firms,
there are researchers
at universities
and other institutions
or other inventors or innovators.
To name just a few,
there might be more,
there might be government agencies,
there might be investors involved
in that process, or as a people.
So if need to gather as much
qualitative information as possible,
all these stakeholders should be
involved in the process
and the task of the,
of you,
in designing a smart specific
and strategy,
is more that of coordination
and gathering the information,
than of really doing the analysis
yourself.
Most of the information will be
of that more qualitative nature
and come from people,
but of coarse,
data analysis can support you
in that process,
particularly to identify
the institutions,
the areas to look at,
the people to talk to,
the statistical analyzers might be
the helpful part of that process.
Let's have a bit a look
what kind of data
might be available
to give us such hints.
During our analyze
of the base of evidence,
we already touched some
of this data and here is one example
which you already know here
from our discussion
of the Base of Evidence,
the patent network a region has.
Of course any connection
we see here
in the patent network of the region
might also be a hint
to resources available
to the region
and we can follow up that
in more detail.
And of course, resources available
to the region
are primarily within the region
but such a network connection
to other regions,
to other institutions,
can also be a resource available
to the regions
in a smart specialization process
So, while doing the base of evidence
analysis, you already gather
a lot of information
which you then can use also
for the entrepreneurial resources.
But we can go into more detail.
One example or one good source
for information
are publication statistics
of course.
Particular in the research field,
not the applied innovations
but more of the research part,
publications are an important output
of activities and therefore,
they reflect
the activities available
in the region.
What we see here in this example,
is the fields where publications
are done, and we see
for in this case,
it's Ticino again, that nearly
a quarter of all publi...
no, actually more than a quarter
of all publications
is in Medicine,
and the second quarter
is in two more fields,
Computer Science and Biochemistry.
So these are fields where there
are a lot of publications available
in the region, and probably
a lot of access points
for innovation
and entrepreneurial activities.
Of course, the culture
of publication in different fields
might be different, the high number
of medicine publications
might be, over estimate
the importance of the field
because in medicine you usually
publish a lot, but still,
it is a resource available
and by comparison
this general publications numbers,
you can even filter for such things.
But it gives a hint, for Ticino,
where to look at
for specialization possibilities.
Of course you can also look at
publications in another dimension.
You can look at the institutions
the publications come from,
which university,
which research institutions,
or maybe other bodies
do publish a lot
and are therefore worth
to do have a closer look at
the entrepreneurial resources
which they might provide
to the region and to
the smart specialization strategy.
Here we have another example
of possible information to be used.
It fits and entails a actually
Federal Program
supporting the cooperation
between universities
and other research institutions,
and small and medium sized
enterprises called CTI funds.
These projects nearly by definition
are entrepreneurial
in their spirit and therefore
might be good starting point
to be included
in a smart specialization strategy.
And we see from the statistics
in here
that there are 8 to 12 projects
in every year
in that program
within the Canton of Ticino
and this is 8 to 12 chances to start
smart specialization
and to have entrepreneurial resource
for a smart specialization strategy.
So it might be worth following
that up in more detail
and look and deliver the projects
and insist unions
involved in these projects.
Coming back to the patents again
because this
is a very rich data source
for our innovation
and entrepreneurial activities,
we want to have a look,
a bit more detailed
what could be done here.
Of course, instead of just looking
at the number of patents,
we can also look at who is involved
in patent activities
within the regions,
and again we have here an example
for Ticino and see that there are
a number of companies
very active in patenting
their innovations
and all these might be possible
starting points
for smart specialization again.
But we can have a more detailed look
at patents actually.
Patent databases provide
a lot of information
on the contents of the patents
and which fields
the patent belong to,
and this information can be used.
In an exercise we have done,
we defined 40 future technologies
or cutting edge technologies
which will shape the future world
from what we can
from our today's perspective.
Of course, there might be
different developments in the future
but, these are technologies
with the potential
to shape the future.
It is like internet of things,
drones, biomedical research,
and similar technologies.
We now can draw pattern profiles
relating to these
forty future cutting edge
technologies,
and in this example
we see it, for one region,
what is their technological profile
for number of selected
of these new
cutting edge technologies.
And we see that the region
is particularly well positioned
in the area of medical technology
and pharmaceuticals.
This has the highest number
of patents.
Of course, this is also on areas
which are already
for quite some time active
though it's not surprising
that the number of patents
is higher here,
patent which is very well positioned
in them.
Apart from looking
at the technologies
so that patent fields are in,
we can also look
at the quality of the patents,
there are...
there is a high tendency
to a lot of patents
in the world right now
to secure the elected property,
but there are possibilities
to assess the values
of a certain patent,
and it is done
in the right part of this graphic.
It shows the share of patterns
in the technological field
which is among top 10 %
of worldwide patents.
The top 10% quality.
And we see that
for the medical technology,
it is 36 % or 37 % nearly
in the top quality of the patent.
So that's quite a good number
if you recall
that only 10 % and of all patents
in that field in the world
are defined as top quality.
But the regions even doing better
in pharmaceuticals,
it's nearly half of their patents
which is of this kind
of a top quality.
And we can also see if we look
at another thing,
the Internet of Things,
here, shortcut-ed we see IoT
The Internet of Things
is a very new development
so it's not surprising
that the number of patents
is not so high, but regions again,
nearly 50 % of all patents
are in the top area of the top 10 %
patents in the world.
The region has a very high quality
of their research in that field
and though, therefore again probably
that's a good starting point
for any smart specialization
strategy.
We can even go a step further
after identifying the technologies
and where regions are strong in,
we can look at the institution
and companies behind that, patents,
and analyze them in more detail.
That can be done
in a regional perspective
but in the next example,
that will be done
in a company perspective
The example is for the company
of Siemens,
huge, world wide player
and we analyze
their technological portfolio here.
The size of the bubble
in the graphic
shows the number of patents
in a certain areas.
So it's not surprising
if you know Siemens a little bit,
that energy generation
is the most important patent field
they're active in.
But again, they're also
in a number of other
of these cutting edge technologies,
very active,
particularly then there's
digital processes
and internet of things
are quite important.
So, if a new region Siemens is
and company of a certain importance,
you might have access
to all these technologies
for your smart specializations
strategies via this company.
We can also again
have a more detailed look
how important these patents are
and that is actually
what is provided by the two axis
in that graph.
Under horizontal axis we see,
how often is this field used again
in other companies activities
in activities of Siemens
and we see a huge difference
for example,
the internet of things is not
that much used
in other parts of the company
while robotics for example,
or material designs is used a lot
in other fields as well.
But internet of things
is one of the more important areas
Siemens is active in,
where other companies,
Siemens might cooperate this
or licensing out
it's patents them here these use
these kinds of technologies a lot.
So we see that there's already
kind of a network
for the internet of things
activities of Siemens there
when other companies
used it heavily.
That is what's given under
vertical axis
and might be a useful information
to define
your smart specialization strategy
if internet of things
might be part of it.
All these are of course
only examples.
As I said before, there must be
a region specific analysis
and there might be quite different
depending on your demands,
but this kind of statistics
can help you to get
into the right directions.
Now, summing up briefly
what we have seen.
We know entrepreneurial resources
as in, essential informational input
into the smart specialization
strategy.
We don't want to generate
all entrepreneurial activities
from the scratch or...
get new innovation projects
from the scratch
but we rely on
what is already there.
But it is very difficult
to analyze it.
There is no clear statistics
we can look at.
We have to do it contextual,
we have rely on qualitative
information.
Therefore, of course we have to use
various sources,
access various sources
of entrepreneurial resources
where data and statistics analyzers
might be one, part of,
but certainly not the most
important one.
The most one is people active
in your region
in both in entrepreneurial activities,
in both in innovation
and get them into the process,
gather the information found
and at the same time probably
involve them
into this strategy building.
Last not least,
there might be one way
to gather this information
which we haven't mentioned yet.
But if you recall our discussion
of a top-down or bottom-up approach,
you find priority area first,
and then ask in a call
for proposals
for entrepreneurial activities
in that field or to do it bottom-up,
we find the information
of entrepreneurial activities
and possible priorities
and then combine them.
The first one might actually
be the one
how to gather the information,
or call for the proposals
is also a tool
for information gathering.
Though, it is a difficult task
but there are many opportunities
to get to it, and it is essential
that we are smart and build
our smart specialization strategy
on existing resources
and not starting everything
from scratch.
Thank you very much.