Chapter 1: Systems of equations
linear and dies
Welcome, in linear algebra,
we start with the first chapter
where we talk about systems of equations
linear and dies.
And I have to start by giving you
a definition of
a system of linear equations, and
why I will first give a definition
that it is a linear equation.
Definition: a linear equation
to unknown  x  1 to  x   n
with real coefficients,
is an equation of the form:
a  1  x  1 plus 2  x  2
more  an   x   n  equal to  b
where  I  and  b  are real numbers.
So that's the first part
of the definition, part two:
a family of such equations
is called a system of equations
linear to unknown  x  1 to  n x .
And finally, if we have a system
of equations, we speak of a solution
a system of linear equations
to unknown  x  1 to  n x
is an ordered sequence of  n  real numbers
α 1 to α  n , such that,