So this week it's really about the market opportunity set. And I have
three main learning that I want to get across during this week. It's first
about the description of your core abilities. You need to understand what your
abilities are in their own right. Independent of any product
that you may have already envisioned. Second I want to show you how to
identify possible options that you can derive from these abilities.
The core technology that you may have, you know what type of market opportunities are out there
that you could cater to. And thirdly I want to show you how to assemble a compelling market
opportunity set based on the options that you identify.
If you look at this type of set of questions that I've just outlined.
This all relates to this very first step of the Navigator. The market opportunity set that is depicted
here on the left side in the form of this briefcase because it's really
a place where you say OK I have my market opportunities and I have my set that
I'm going to evaluate in a second step and then I strictures about the set in a third step.
What is this market opportunity set. It's the set of the potential market opportunities
which you can address with your core resources and capabilities. These can be
varied options related to different types of needs for different types of customers.
But the word varied is quite important to you because I said to you that the
choice you have really depends on how heterogeneous how varied these options
are that you identify you we could say have one market domain which is the
refrigerator's the other one is aerospace as we already have. And the third one might be
motorcycle's. This is a very varied set of options. You know you can have a much
narrower set where you say only the automotive industries and some subdomains
within it. Why is this so important. We have talked about this briefly as well for two main
reasons. Just to recap number one because not all opportunities are like some
are presenting more fertile ground than others. And number two it provides you with the agility
It provides it with foresight of seeing this might be a Plan B if the first option should not
work out and it provides me with a growth option. Should the first option work
out. So this provides you with important vision and
agility as well. How is it done? Know you start with assessing your generic
functionality of your core abilities your technology, then you try to understand what other
applications are feasible for you and for different types of customers
in order to guide you through this process. We have created this worksheet that you see here
it's intuitively understandable you have the abilities that you're going to note on the
top and you have the applications and customers set that you noting
on the bottom part of this worksheet and I will walk you in this week through this worksheet
try to explain how it's filled in with some very into a terrific
sample. So this is actually a very straightforward easy process and one that is actually
lots of fun to fill in because you get to know your venture or your potential venture
in a much more, in a much deeper way. So the main
takeaways from this week, from this stage are the following.
First we want you to really enhance your cognitive flexibility and alongside the
flexibility of your venture because once you have seen multiple opportunities you are more
alert to these other opportunities as well and not only focused only
on one. Second, having options at 10 gives you the power of
choosing among different options. And we talked about how important this is
for performance effect and for agility. Third you are able to leave
behind some long held assumptions as this is already the best market
for us here that actually often entrepreneurs say oh this is the best
market but they in fact they have not looked at others so how can you know. And if you
think about the profoundness the importance of this decision it's
a bit of a pity that you haven't looked at other sets of markets because there might be better
options out there and you're just foregoing these better options because you have never.
Spent any effort on identifying them or evaluating them. And finally there's an
interesting intellectual challenge associated with this which makes it fun as well. It's
it's this activity of exploring the options that are in store for you. So it's about the
design of your venture, no one there's no rule that tells you that a venture has
to be designed in a certain way, something you can decide you know. So if you want to pick
up or see a better opportunity that's actually some, some very nice
reward that goes along with it also intellectually because you have been able to design your
venture in a smarter way. So in this week it's really about this first
step the assembling the opportunity set. And I'm going to explain to you next
how you do this with the help of Worksheet 1.