Hello welcome back. This is week two of the market opportunity navigator
during this week we're going to learn how to generate your market opportunity set.
This is actually quite an important week. Why? Because the market opportunity set that you will
generate is actually providing you with the strategic choice that you will have
in Venture creation or a new innovation project. That also means that
opportunity that you don't see at this stage are not in your
set. And you can pursue them. Or put differently. You know, if you have
a valuable set of tents identify a valuable set during this process. Then
there's this can be a true asset to your commercialization effort. So
there are a couple of conceptual issues that I want to point out to you and one key issue
that I want to discuss with you first is the issue of technological
fungibility. This means that technologies are flexible
and we'll see some examples later on. But it essentially means you, you have your
technology and it can be cross applied to different customer sets and
that's what we call technological fungibility. Why is this the case. You can break down your
technologies into different elements. Some might be more generic. Some might be more
specific. We will talk about this later on in in some depth as well.
But in essence it means you have technological components and you can say okay these three
technological components by themselves create a certain functionality
and then you have other technological components that you could actually make think about
adding smartness to your existing technology, computing power
software whatnot. So you can ultimately and this is
depicted here with these legal stones you can
add a new type of technological competence to your existing set of technologies and that
provides additional opportunities for creating the functionality for
existing customers and new customer sets. Okay. So over all this
is a process where I want you to think about your technology something that is up
for design. Break it down into components you can
reconfigure your technologies. You can also add new types of
technological elements to the mix. So when you think about your technology as
being fungible this means also that it can address different
customer sets out there. And when you think about this more
generally these customers sets represent market opportunities so we define a
market opportunity as an application of your technology for a specific set of
customers. So in some ways we draw on all of this
together. You can say OK your technology or the set of abilities that are
behind your technologies can generate multiple market opportunities. And what's interesting
is that this does not only hold for general purpose technology but also for conceptualist technology
as I will show you in a minute. It also holds for high technology as well as low technology.
So let's think about a concrete example of a general purpose technology tactile sensing
technology. This is actually a technology that can be applied in a number
of different domains from surgical tools gaming and virtual reality
rehabilitation monitoring, smart sports, gear robotic, tactile feedback, health
monitoring, variables et cetera et cetera. More
contextualized life type of technology was developed by
Fujifilm. They have great competences in photographic
imaging et cetera. And as you all know there was a move to
digital cameras digital photography in the 1990s
that actually made many of the companies in that space
obsolete because these companies could not reinvent themselves. Fujifilm was one of the
very few that could reinvent themselves because they realize that there are technologies that they have developed
For, the film industry that their technologies could actually be
cross applied in other domains. You know these technologies are fungible. What
does this mean for Fujifilm that could move into cosmetics and this is shown here.
They could address the environment or technologies factor as markets as well.
But based on the fundamental understanding that technologies are not there only
to serve one purpose but they can be repurposed in that sense. Or here's an
example of low technology. This is filters and filters.
Evidentially can be used in many, many different applications here just a few from water
Purification, oil refineries, food industries, heating and
Ventilation, the automotive industry and the marine industry. Of course the filters
will look a bit different here and there. Some might even have smartness added to them, know because of when
it comes to monitoring. For instance water quality. So if
you think about these examples that really gives you the idea that OK technologies are
fungible they can be cross applied. Now it's important to understand what are these components that
comprise the technology. So ultimately it doesn't really matter
what your core abilities are you can always try to think of them as being
more general to generate multiple market opportunities. So in the following video
we actually explain to you why this is so important.