So you may wonder why is it important to create an opportunity set. You know why not
only identify one opportunity and exploit that one.
We call the segment look before you leap because we want to exactly point out to you why this is
so important. So if you think about opportunities markets that you want to
enter. If you identify only one market opportunity you're basically
stuck with the kind of features this market offers to you if you
identify a set of opportunities you actually have a strategic choice set of market
opportunities. What does this mean? This means very concretely that markets come in
different sizes and different growth trajectory et
cetera et cetera, some are very contested some are less contested.
So some of these markets out there just provide more fertile ground for your venture to
growing. You know it's like planting a little seed into the soil, you don't do
this. You don't plant the seed in any type of soil. Know you want to plant it in a type of soil
that allows to nourish the plant and exactly that mindset should be present with an
entrepreneur as well. You know why should you go into the harshly contested are, while
there's more forthcoming types of areas
that you could create your benches in them. And the second important reason might be less
obvious. You know the second important reason is that this early decision in which
area you create your own, your venture in actually imprints your venture in a very
fundamental way. Why is this the case? This is because the type of market you're going to
choose has a lot of implications for other set of
decisions within your bench. Just think about the type of brand name that you're going to see.
Just think about the type of resources you're going to develop the types of
relationship with outside players and also the employees you're going to hire. These
employees have are interested in your firm because you are
working in a particular area. So if you have a firm that is actually active in
the household good industry think about refrigerators. This type of
forum is a very different nature than a firm that would cater for instance to
the aerospace industry. So ultimately this choice of market
opportunity has this fundamental effect on imprinting the type of organization you're
going to create when you put both reasons together. The first reason
that the market actually provides less than more or less fertile ground to you.
And the second reason that you know you have the strong imprinting effect of this
is that this is one decision when you combine those Linnets, I think it's
clear that this early states decision in entrepreneurship and in innovation
management is actually a decision that is quite far reaching. But if you look at the
textbooks out there typically these textbooks assume that you have already identified a
good opportunity until you very well how are you going to exploit that opportunity without
really questioning whether there might be more important better import or better
opportunities out there. This activity of identifying market opportunity is actually not a
trivial one. And the history of technological progress is
full of examples where innovators had a hard time identifying
the best opportunities out there and it took sometimes decades to see the best application now.
So why not try to, to shorten the time and be really good. And seeing these
applications from the outside so that you can pick the best market opportunity for
yourself. Based on what I just said I think it's
almost becomes obvious now why the generation of a market
opportunity set is so important. Let me just point this out to you. First it's of
course about choosing the most attractive option, not all market opportunities are
Alike, that's a lot of heterogeneity and you want to be smart entrepreneur and enter
an area where you have the best chances for growing your ventures over time. But the
second option might again be less obvious. And
to think about it when you see multiple opportunities what does this do to your venture. What does this
do to you in your head. It says OK I have seen multiple opportunities
some of these opportunities might be for better options. You know so I
might enter this market but opportunity two and three they are Plan B and Plan C
for me. So I have this fallback option these fallback options
plans. Or you could say if the first market should work out, I have these
other markets that I can enter as future growth options but
about having this broader perspective on firm growth this is allowing you
to create a venture that is more agile that it's more flexible
over time actually to get into these other domains. Again think about the brand name which is
like the one of the most obvious or
interesting sumps on this front. The brand that you're going to choose can be focused
very much on this one market. Do you see where it can be chosen so that it
could fit the other market domains so that once you create your venture
you can more nimbly more in a more edgy way move into these other domains
and don't have to rebrand your company because these other domains actually fit the overall print.
A similar example can be made with the technology that you are developing. You can develop that technology
more in a more Modula fashion, meaning that you are able to reconfigure it
for quicker and more efficient entry into these other elements. The
bottom line is that you are creating a company that is much more agile. If
you have that type of foresight. These insights are partly based on research I've
been doing together with two colleagues from the Wharton School of the University of
Pennsylvania. You see pictured here to the left in McMillon and in the center
it's my colleague Tommy Thompson and we, we did a study on 80
Technology Ventures and we called the study look before you leap market opportunity
edification in technology ventures. We found two interesting
insights that led to some of the findings
that are based. The book is based on this move is based on, number one what we
have seen this that serial entrepreneurs those who have done it. Done
entrepreneurship repeatedly created firms not only once but multiple times
they actually assemble an opportunity set while the novice once the people who are doing
the first venture typically jump at the first opportunity. We have seen
another interesting insight in this study. Let those who
create an opportunity set those who look at multiple opportunities. Those entrepreneurs can derive
significant performance benefits from this activity. Why is this the case.
This relates back to what I just explained. This is because these people can choose
a better option. More fertile ground. And these people, these entrepreneurs can
actually create companies that are more agile that can maneuver between different
opportunities in a more nimble and flexible way. So some big
picture don't fall too quickly in love with your idea.
Look what's out there. That might be better opportunities that allow you to grow your venture in a
much more ambitious compelling way. So look
before you leap and I'm going to show you the next few segments how you can actually do
this.