So how do you actually generate this all important market opportunities step. There are two
key steps that are necessary to accomplish this first important goal.
The first step is called de-linking. The second step is called re-linking the de-linking
step is one where you look at your technologies your abilities in their own right.
That means independent of any product that you may or have
already envisioned in depend of any market that you may already have seen so really try to
understand your technologies in their own right as if there is no
application to a certain market domain intended for them.
Second you would then say OK we have this technological, these
technological elements and we try to relate them to different markets domains. So
it's de-linking and rethinking. We have
decided a website that actually walks you through this important process. And let me first
explain to you in some detail how this worksheet is set up before we then go deeper into the
de-linking step. So this is the worksheet that was already shown to you.
This is the worksheet 1 for the generation of market opportunities which should ultimately then
lead to your market opportunity set it is structured in a fairly straightforward manner. You see
on the upper part the abilities your technological elements
that you possess or where you want to develop in the future and below you
have the identification of market opportunity step where you actually try to
understand which applications you can offer with your core abilities who may need them et cetera.
So looking just at the upper part, there
is a step where you say okay I try to understand technology your
abilities in the own right. This is a step that is actually
quite an interesting one when we work with inventors.
It's a step where they, they realize actually the power of what they have
developed in a more broader encompassing sense. So what we want
you to do is to list the venturous core abilities or technological elements on the
top of this worksheet. And when we talk about abilities and
technologies we mean a set of resources and capabilities that you currently have. And what's
important also those that you're currently developing or planning to
develop. So concretely and we will by the way see an example of how this is
applied. But concretely you would put technological elements the building blocks
of what you have assembled up here in this upper part
of your work sheet. We have listed four different technological
elements here on this upper part of the work sheet. But
essentially you say okay maybe I only have two core elements and I might add
a third one smartness, computing power software to it which would
occupy the third space on the worksheet. Or you might even have four or five.
In that sense you know you know if you have a fifth one that you identify you would at
this fifth element to the worksheet as well. So this upper
part of the worksheet is really about your abilities about your competencies about your
technology and you're trying to understand those elements in the
right meaning decoupled from any application that you already had in mind.
So to get a good understanding of what you can potentially do with your abilities
competencies etc. you will need to think about them in their own right meaning
You imagine them in a more general way that is decoupled from the specific product
idea or a customer need that you may have originally had in mind.
For instance your unique ability can be an important. Know how that you are processing
about a specific process. A rare resource that you have developed or a special capability
in manufacturing that you have developed over time as well.
These technologies that you have at hand want to develop. They can be
broken down into core elements based on their unique functionality such
as pattern recognition for instance, or based on their structure design
such as nano sized, such as in an Access camera. So think about
your technology in all practical terms as it's being comprised of building blocks
with certain functionalities. Not these building blocks up here. Here are these examples that I
just mentioned. Try to understand and this is now in the blue box, try to
understand the main properties as well as functions that these technological elements
can perform. So you would write the name of the technological element
give it a name and then below it you write the function of all the
properties that describe this technological element. So this
exercise is extremely important not just because it helps you
understand what you have a tense but also helps you in developing what we
call cognitive flexibility. You see your technology you
abilities with new eyes. So let me give you an example that illustrates
more concretely how you feel in that first part of the worksheet.
These friendly folks here are Saar and Gaul. These are two good friends who always wanted to found
Estrada, you know like many people out there. One day back in 2011 Gaul was a
software engineer back then was sent to India by his employer to diagnose a machine
that didn't work properly. He had to fly thousands of miles for that. But as he
entered the room he simply heard with a clear sound that the problem was not the
software but rather a mechanical malfunction. It wasn't at this moment
that an idea came into his mind. Why can't we simply develop
something that listens to machines to diagnose the problems.
A quick technological investigation revealed that developing this technology would be difficult
yet doable. But as they started working on this project Saar and Gaul
quickly realized that machines are literally all around us all the way from
complicated manufacturing lines to simple home appliance so
how can they know what type of machines they should listen to and which
market opportunities should they focus on.
So as we progress along the three steps of the market opportunity and navigator we
will revisit the example of Saar in Gaul and the firm agree to make it
more intuitive for you to apply the market opportunity navigator and to
understand what actually Mark Saar and Gaul chose as their initial opportunity and
what else was in store for them. So a glories technology is really about
this idea of we listened to machines.
Their slogan says machines talk we listen as you see on the slide
and their tagline is we are bringing predictive maintenance to new markets by
listening to a machine we can tell if it is working properly has a malfunction
and even predict future failures.
So if you think about this type of value proposition that they are putting out there
it already tells you a lot about they have vast opportunity space that is in front of them
because they have lots and lots of different machines in working out there. And
they could basically listen to all types of machines and different very different types of settings.
So let's fill in all Worksheet 1 for Saar and Gaul. You know,
by the way I explained it already you can already take guesses of what type of
technological elements they have. Now let's look at this a bit more detail.
In order to listen to a machine what do you need to do you have to have some hard to get device that
has some, some listening power. Well you have to have some device some
smartness built into some algorithm that is actually able to detect what's
going on. And you have to have a user interface that allows you
to communicate with the technology with the hardware to understand
what is actually going on there to understand ultimately what type of machine
failure could be out there and try to understand what type of maintenance programs
etc. can be launched based on that technology.
But think about it in a more systematic manner. We can say this
technology that they have developed has three main components it's listening hardware
it has a number of features and abilities, it can record vibrations and
Ultrasound, it can it's fairly small, it is portable, it is a high
sampling rate. The second part the second technological element is actually
the algorithm, it detects changes and it allows real
time analysis. It's designed for big data. A lot of data points that are collected.
It's based on machine learning. And actually it's a kind of a cool feature built a
malfunction dictionary over time. The third key element that Saar and
Gaul developed is the user interface. It should be
easy intuitive. It should fit the iPhone as well as Android phones.
It generates tailored reports and statistics and it has an online management platform.
So if you think about Saar and Gaul glorious court technological
elements there are three and they have different features. And this is all
you need to do to fill in this upper part. It sounds
kind of simple how I portrayed it and it's actually a
straightforward process but only if you are able to do delink yourself from
a certain market to me.
Another interesting sample is biotia, and this sample is actually quite different to the
first example from Saar and Gaul that we looked at which was mostly based on technological elements
but also is based on the country or know how that is embedded within one person
Neefe O’Howrah and she's the resent Ph.D. graduate it in the whole field of genomics. So let
me show you what her know how it is about and how that can be partitioned into certain
components. So the first component needs sampling abilities so
Neefe is really, really good in understanding complex natural systems that are
widely spread not evenly distributed. She's also quite good at experimental design to
understand the full experimental process and finally she has a certain strong
ability in pathogen monitoring that involves all types of pathogens. She can
do a real time analysis of large data sets. And she's also really good with pathogen
monitoring and understanding the next generation sequencing models. And based on
these three types of unique abilities and know how she decided to create a startup that can offer
environmental surveillance solutions using the power of genomics.
A third and very interesting examples actually flicker. You all know this company it's today a photo
sharing community site that is very popular.
But they didn't start off like this. They started off, in fact in 2002 by developing a multiplayer
online game with real time interaction through instant messaging and one feature of this
game was a chat environment with photo sharing which quickly became valuable in
its own right and surpassed. The game itself in popularity leading the firm to put
Actually the game on hold and to focus on developing a new photo sharing community site. So if you think
about flick a flicker and this upper part of the worksheet the photo
sharing ability which has been one of the technological elements that they
could have put in there. And based on that we then can develop multiple
applications as we explain in the next segment to you.
So in some of these examples and what I explained before. Tell one
clear message try to think about your technologies
in their own right now in the most gentle manner possible. Because only
then you will understand the flexibility inherent in your technology
and that there are many other opportunities out there that you can potentially cater to.