That we just discussed the deal linking step in market opportunity and defecation. This is a
critical first step. We are trying to understand the technological components in their own
right. You know your abilities, your unique abilities in the right decoupled from any
product application in the re-linking step. You will then re-link
these technological components to these market applications that you will identify
and that's the second step that are going to going to explain to you right now.
So let's go back to work She learn that helps you to generate your market opportunities set
we know focus on the lower part the upper part as I remember was to
describe your core abilities or technological elements, the lower part is
dedicated to identifying your market opportunities. And this is a straightforward for what
process you see here, applications on the one hand and customers
on the other hand, and the market opportunity is basically any combination of
application and customer. In order to understand what's in store for you in terms of
market opportunities both are actually vital elements to be considered
and we encourage you to think broadly about applications and the customers that
could use them.
The link between the application and the customer is actually the need and also a
certain application has a functionality and this functionality should serve a certain
purpose create value with your customer assets. So this
discovery process is actually a very fun activity. It's one of the few instances
in the design of your venture of your innovation project. We can think out of
the box, truly out of the box and we want you to think truly out of the box and also
think broadly think unconstrained think with all your creativity
and enjoy that moment you know because this is, this is a fundamental moment as we discussed
in the life of your venture in your innovation project. Make sure that
that you unconstrained and really reach out and try to understand what's in store for you in
terms of market opportunity. I will come back to that and give you some hints and tips of how you can enrich your
creativity and think broadly. And I also will share with you what we learned from research on
which type of opportunities people can typically see.
But this is in essence an activity where say hey I have a
design element in my hands. This is the market opportunity that I discovered the
market opportunities that I will discover. And let's
enjoy this moment. So the lower part of the worksheet is divided into
an application part and a customer part. The application part
designates a specific usage a function which you can create with your core
technologies and abilities. So it's really linking the upper part of
abilities with some functionality that is embedded in these
technological elements or your abilities. It can be it
based on one of these technological abilities that you identified above or
more than one, you know so this can be a combination or can be a single
technological function. Think about this flicker example that we discussed in the private sector. You know there
was only one functional element in the whole set of technological elements that
flicker has detents.
So from one of the previous segments you also remember that you could add technological
elements to the mix that will increase the scope of functionality that
arises from a technology. Think about the example of adding smartness based on hardware and
software components to the turned current technological elements. In
turn this gives rise to lots of new functionalities and notes of new applications.
The final element in your work sheet one is the identification of possible
customers. We designate this with these icons showing
individuals. It could also be companies B2C B2B markets. But
this box down there that links to the application box
is focused on your customers. So as you uncover potential
applications you should also consider who may have the need for those applications.
And this will create your possible sets of customers. Remember at that point the
market opportunity is any combination of application of customers and I will come back
to this in a minute. So as an illustration of the re-linking step. Let's now
turn back to Saar in Gaul. The founders of Augury you remember that they had the
slogan machines talk. We listen so they can have all kinds of interesting
applications in the predictive maintenance market domains.
Let's look again at their worksheet1 so they had identified
three main technological components. First listening hardware with a couple of features
that are listed below the algorithm that is behind their whole technology
with a couple of features and then the user interface. And when they think about
applications they identify a whole range and very different
application domain. So it was for commercial machines for consumer appliances and for
medical purposes. So all three domains are
have some need for predictive maintenance and associated with all three
domains. Are certain sets of customers which are in effect as we will see fairly
different and create a wonderful opportunity set for Augury. The
associated customer segments actually show you another level of breath
in terms of market opportunities that will arise from this bottom part of the
worksheet 1 here they identified on a top level commercial
buildings factories and freight firms all in the predictive maintenance for commercial
machines area. And if you just start looking at the left side the
commercial buildings market can actually be subdivided into HVAC
heating ventilation, air conditioning domain and the elevator
domain. Just think about predictive maintenance for these types of spending.
You know everyone who has been stuck in an elevator knows exactly what I'm talking about right now. That
second element here are the fecker factories. This is quite an
interesting domain as well. The flourless sub-segment this
fecker domain engine, manufacturing machines and infrastructure equipment. Again, if you
can have predictive maintenance for this machine this means less downtime.
You can send in you keep send a team there before the machine actually
is out of service. So there's a lot of cost savings associated with this as well. And then freight
firms similar story cooling containers, refrigerated trucks at some
Sub-segments. The second big domain that they focus on is predictive
maintenance for consumer appliances and the divide between the climate effect trust
and the sub-segments cars and motorcycles and household tools with the sub-segments white
appliances heating and cooling. And again predictive maintenance in all of these domains
could help a lot in terms of saving costs.
increase reliability et cetera. You know so lots of value created
potentially created as well. And finally they also saw
applications in the medical domain artery diagnostic, Lunda Nasik
which is in fact, very different to the two other domains for predictive maintenance of
commercial machines and consumer appliances. But overall if you look at this opportunity
set that is beginning to emerge at the lower part of this worksheet, and this is truly amazing.
This is giving you a rich, rich set of growth options for Plan
B et cetera. So having this at your disposal is already a
fascinating element. The next step will be of course to understand which markets will
be more important than others. We will come back to that in week 3
But before we go down that path I want to show you another
example and what we have just seen with a Augury in the lower part of work sheet One is
that the customer segments the factories can be further
Sub-divided into sub-segments. And there's one
tip that we can give you and how to identify even more segments is that you mentally say OK
we have a swimming in and swimming out process that is associated with opportunity and
deification and let's look at this again with another example. This is the example of Nova. This
is a company that actually develops visual scanning software that mimics human
behavior and reads content like pricing images descriptions and ratings.
So one of the technological applications is deep web search
and in that domain they can say OK we have B2B customers business to business customers
and B2C customers business to consumers relationships. So
you can further segment this and say we're B2B business to business
linkage means e-commerce or classified sites. Then you can further segment the
classified sites into retail. On the one hand or travel. And then you can
go further down the tree and say travel can be further subdivided
into hotels and flights. So beyond this zooming
in and assuming all process that can jumpstart your imagination.
There are a few other tips that we want to give you to identify an appealing and exciting
customer of set market opportunities that ultimately just as appealing as the one from a
Augury that we have just seen. So in terms of boosting your discovery skills, one
first tip that we have for you is mining your own knowledge. Why is this so important.
What we know from our own research is that people tend to identify those opportunities that are
related to the prior knowledge of customer needs of certain market segments
et cetera. So this means you are
predisposed to identify opportunities that are related to your prior knowledge. What
is important to remember in line in association with your prior
knowledge corridor is that not all the knowledge that you have is of course on the top of your mind. And
also you need to mind your knowledge in a way trying to understand what type of
customer needs I came across in the past that are related to the functionalities
embedded in my technological elements. So really mind your knowledge, take your time
lean back try to understand the types of customer sets types of industries et
cetera that you came across during your life so far that might provide
a hunch or an idea of where your technology can provide. So is
this concept that I just explained the prior knowledge corridor concept also means that
we are blind to many things out there now. And by implication, this also means by
turning to other people we can actually enrich
our market opportunity set significantly because they will know about market
opportunities customer needs that you may not even have heard about. And also
in that sense we encourage you to really go out there talk to people try to solicit
information about customer needs that they might know about
based on new technological functionality that you would have never thought of. So
accessing external sources is a key element in order to help your creativity.
It is also useful to go through a systematic list of industries or markets, you know there are
tons of those on the Internet, just Google them and try to see you know
systematically in these lists where your
technology can be applied. You know these are industry lists. You go through them and say hey maybe we can
apply our technology in this domain we just never thought of it or about it. Let's get in touch with
some folks in those domains and try to understand that customer need that we
assume exists there actually exists. And finally what is
also interesting is that you can look at patents that are related to your technological
element and see what type of application areas are named in there. These are just
for tips but there are many other ways of enhancing your creativity. I
think the bottom line and what we urge you to do is take your time for this
step. So this discovery process is highly important as it shapes
what you can do and what the type of value is that you're going to extract from your
venture from your innovation project. So be open and be imaginative, be
creative and identify as many and as varied opportunities as you possibly
can. When I say as varied think really about for instance what Augury has
done to look at very different industries because this creates strategic
choice this creates variety for your venture. And these markets might have
very different levels of attractiveness and we will come back to that later on. And so typically
having three to five market opportunities is there's a good rule of thumb that I've seen actually
teams that were able to push that much, much beyond that number up to 60 different market
opportunities and that's it. So if you're on a creative
roller coaster try identify lots of opportunities lots of varied once
enjoyed that moment because this really is the opportunity set that is at your
fingertips for venture creation. So please take your time. This is a very
important step forward for your project next week. I cannot share with you some
ways to create an opportunity set based on what we have discovered
and how to place this actually in the market opportunity navigator.