So how do you summarize the learnings that you got from worksheet1 on the market opportunity
navigator dashboard. So the idea is to fill in the market
opportunity set on your left with post-its, you know designating the different market opportunities that you
have identified. In this example a firm has identified four different market
opportunities for you for their technological abilities. So the question is
What do you actually put in there. You know you have seen the Augury’s example that there was a lot and
a lot of different opportunities and some might be more valuable than others. Some might be
just nonsense. You know we ask you to be very creative but over time you might say maybe we were a bit
too creative but that's completely fine. You know so. So don't be worried about this. This is now
the step of weeding out those obvious candidates where I say
we do not have a possibility to ever pursue this purpose, perhaps we don't have the abilities
perhaps we the market potential is not there. The goal. Let me remind you this
is to have Post-It notes in the first box that designate your market
opportunities. So again the varied set is an
important asset to your firm. It provides you with the growth options that you have. It provides
you with plan B. And also make sure to fill your market opportunities that with
with truly interesting options. What does this mean in terms of key questions that you can
ask for an initial screening. Weeding out those opportunities that may or may not
be lucrative interesting to pursue. First you
can say does the customer need exist?
A few phone calls might do the trick. Try to understand.
Well does this particular market segment to the customers in this particular market segment
actually have. Second can we really satisfies the customer need using
our unique abilities and in particular an existing solution. This can
be done mostly with desktop research trying to understand what other
options are out there. And are there several areas severe restrictions that would hinder us from
executing on this market opportunity essentially saying well you know maybe there are
legal issues. Maybe there are other issues in terms of costs that we can never
shoulder in order to get to that market. And finally and this is also
important for you to remember. You know you want to do something that aligns
with your moral values with your passion with what you're in for and also
check those opportunities out of the mix that would be in conflict with any of
the core values. And once you've gone through this exercise you have already a good idea
of what type of opportunities you will be able to place in the market opportunity
set. And again as I mentioned before
having like three or five market opportunities in the set should be the rule of thumb
should be the goal that you strive for. We depicted here for on these blue
posted notes. So in order to depict each market opportunity your market opportunity
set it's important to label each market opportunity with a name.
These are very important options for you. So they deserve to have their own name
and this will by the way also help you in the team to refer to this market
opportunity in a clear and concise manner. You write these names on a sticky note and then you post it
in the first part of the market opportunity navigator, your opportunity set.
So as an illustration look again at Saar and Gaul from Augury. They have
identified a fantastic number of opportunities. So
how do they move from worksheet1 to the market opportunity set. You know
this is what their worksheet1 looks like. You remember that slide.
They picked a couple of opportunities for their market opportunities set
down here and they picked HVAC, manufacturing machines, cooling
Containers, white appliances and cars. What is important to remember is
that they actually pick these opportunities that were on the same level of abstraction. You remember
this continents and countries question these are different countries that they pick so that they can actually
compare these different market opportunities where are well known
in their back in their briefcase. They now have these five different market opportunities.
HVAC for commercial buildings, manufacturing machines, cooling containers,
white appliances car manufacturers. OK. So this is an exciting set of
market opportunities that are forming this set right now.
So in some this discovery process is a highly, highly important step in your market
opportunity navigate process. Why? Because these opportunities that you see ultimately
shape what you can do with your over time of course you might add
new opportunities, you might discard opportunities that you deem not to be useful
or interesting. So this is also a dynamic process over time. But what the starting point
of what you see is actually a critical starting point. So take your time and
engage in this process with pleasure.