So the question is now how to move from the bottom part of worksheet1 with all the market opportunities that we have
identified. Remember the Augury sample which presents actually a very broad range of market
opportunities and different sub-segments and how you move from the bottom part
to the market opportunity navigator. And that's only one issue to keep in mind and we call this issue the
continents and countries question. So you remember that every
application of your abilities for a specific set of customers is one
market opportunity of your firm. So when you think about the example from
Saar And Gaul Augury. And the work they have filled in they have a lot of
potential market opportunities that they can move into this first part of them navigate a
process into this briefcase. The market opportunity set as it's picked it up here
on the site. And as you remember also from the Augury example these can
be varied options. Some are very broad. Some are sub-segments
and you might already have a hunch of what my continents and countries issue
will be like that I'm going to address in a minute. But we create
that give you the tip to say can we zoom in and zoom out to identify even more opportunities
zooming in, meaning you are identified based on a broad opportunity sub-segments
or zooming out meaning you actually use sub-segments and then try to
understand what broader market could be above them.
This creates these tree structures. But these tree structures also
bed within themselves. Different levels of analysis. And I think that's
where the trick comes in you know in order to ultimately be able to evaluate different market
opportunities with each other and compare these market opportunities. You will have to have
market opportunities on the same level of analysis. This is the continents and countries
question a continent in that sense is a broad market domain or a vertical in the continent
you know content several countries you know all market segments. So in order to
arrive at a consistent market opportunity set you will have to have market opportunities
at your fingertips that are at the same level of stretch. Otherwise this would be almost
impossible to compare. Two broad is not good because think about it a broad
market segment means that there are some segments below there no country continent
has different cuts of countries. They might have very different types of
feature characteristics some might be very attractive some might be less attractive.
So it's really difficult to understand which is if you look at the continent level
which type of segments are attractive and which type of segments are not attractive.
Some provide just more fertile ground than others. Too narrow is also often not
good as you want to address a market segment that has a certain size to make your effort
worthwhile. An interesting illustration of this continent versus country
that can provide both agree you remember the day I identified a truly exciting opportunity
set on very different continents. They had
the machine applications and they had the human body application. This is very, very
different. These are truly different continents. And when you think about this Augury example Saar and Gaul
really have to make a decision before they commit to a certain market domain.
Which area they want to go. Should they go into the human body
applications or should they go into the area of machine
predictive maintenance. So to make this major decision Gaul and Saar
had to understand first the different possible market segment which is within
each continent then had to evaluate the overall potential and challenges in each continent.
Over all they discovered that their offering could be disruptive in machine maintenance.
While many big payoffs already attempt to offer predictive health care products in the medical
domain hence they considered the potential in the machine
domain to be much higher and the overall challenge is to be lower cost
medical devices require a heavy regulation. For instance, the South Augury is founders
chose to focus on predictive maintenance for machine and put aside the
medical market. So while we urge you to generate
as many varied options market opportunities as possible. Make
sure when you create your market opportunity set, that you pick options at the same level
of analysis. Otherwise you do not end up with a
consistent market opportunity set, pick the same level of analysis.