So when Sharon and me worked with startups established firms inventors etc.
and apply to market opportunity navigate a process with them a couple of questions
have repeatedly come up in this first step of generating the market opportunity set.
And we want to share all these questions and some answers with you. You know the first main question
that. Frequently is why do some technologies pose a bigger
challenge than others when searching for different market opportunities. And this is a question that not only
came up during our work with different types of start ups
etc. but it's also a question that we look more deeply into in one of my research
projects that I've done with a former Ph.D. student of Marianna till we looked
at more than two dozens of different technologies coming out of the EPFL and
what we tried to understand is why is it more difficult for some technologies
to identify multiple applications than for others. And one core feature of one core element
that we repeatedly saw is that technologies that address the human senses
that you can see, that you can feel and that are loosely coupled with the
application context are much easier to cross apply. While there were challenges if
you have an abstract technology think about an algorithm think about a formula
that isn't particularly tightly coupled to the application context. There were some
more challenges than you typically have to involve a person that has strong, a strong technological
competence to help you with these types of technologies and help you
understand what they can do in their own right. So there are in fact
differences in terms of technologies but overall we saw that that all teams
that worked on these technologies could actually identify multiple applications. It's just a bit harder for
some technologies than for others. The second question that
typically comes up is when should I stop searching. The search
process is an exciting one an interesting one but you cannot search forever.
Oh it's a process that has to end at some point. And as I mentioned
before in another segment we had teams that identified up to 60 different
applications. They also said we don't want to stop you prematurely if you are on the roll
and see more opportunities and can find different particularly different
applications in very different continents and different broader market segments.
But as a rule of thumb, three to five is a good number to strive for
three to five after this initial screening process where you weed out those obvious
opportunities that maybe do not make sense that arise due to brainstorming
and going a bit too wide with the opportunities. OK. The third
question that often arises is what happens if I identify opportunities down
the road as I move along. What shall I do with them? The
simple and straightforward answers. Add them to the mix. You know if they pass
this initial screening of course you know if you think that this is an opportunity that is worthwhile to be
considered you can cater to this market based on your
abilities etc.. Add them to the mix and
just see how that further that idea that opportunity progresses further
through the market opportunity navigator. So it's now your turn.
Apply worksheet 1 and generate your market opportunity set. And don't forget to
enjoy. This is a truly exciting and fun activity.