Hi there! As we wrap up this week we would like to go
back to Flyability and show you how they generated their market
opportunity set. As presented in the previous
week Flyability build safe drones for operating in
doors, in complex and confined spaces and in contact with people.
This drone which they call Elliotts can be applied to perform
different jobs for different types of customers. Let's go back to my
Qandil Flyability marketing manager to see how they are
de-link and re-link their technology to identify a set
of market opportunities.
So Flyability has one product which is a drone which
is unique on the market because it has a surrounding protective
frame which actually protect the drone from the surrounding environment.
So basically the drone can hit an obstacle and
keep a city in the air and not crash but it also is
a very unique feature because human can interact with the drone
without risk of injuries. The drone can be piloted remotely from
from a safe place. In this way the operator doesn't need to
enter a dangerous space which is actually the place where
we want to send a drone for gathering images and
content about the environment. So with this live stream that the
drone is sending to the operator you can literally
do a remote inspection of a place.
To begin with, let's describe Flyability's core technology on the
upper part of Worksheet1. First and foremost the
drone that they planned to develop has unique accessibility.
It is taller on two collisions due to the cathode and light protection
cage that surrounds, it can fly or roll on any
surface and it will actually be able to operate in a range of
temperatures and pressures. Second the drone has
unique aviation abilities. It will be piloted manually with an on
site video screen even in very dark smoke or dusty
environments but only for a limited duration due to
battery limitations. Lastly it carries an
automated fully adjustable imagery system with HD and
thermal recordings that are life stream to the control screen and
recorded for a later analysis. Breaking the technology
into its core elements decoupled from any specific usage
helps us to think broadly about the possible applications of these drones.
So that when we're looking at the market the opportunities
we saw initially we thought about natural
Disaster, emergency response and disaster
recovery. And we started there. We quickly went
to other opportunities because we see there is a huge demand
for inspection and providing better means
of performing inspection when it comes to
assessing the integrity of industry or other assets. So each
industry has specific assets it can be a building, it can be a
production tool, and these assets need to
be checked in regular faces and
and it's part of the maintenance operation and part of it is visual
inspection to simply assess the integrity to make sure that everything is fine. And
depending on the results take different actions. So this is really one of the
initial market that we're that we foresee there is other
applications that that were also on the map. If you think of
everything that is outside like a bridge, a dam. So these are
let's say a very different environment because they are open there.
But it seems that the specificities
of educe makes it very comfortable when it comes to flying indoors. So
this will be we kind of move further into
assets that are covered that are closed because it's easier with radios.
There is another market or so that is, that is very interesting
with radios. Is all the operation that
that have to do with security. So if you think of police forces or
special operation that need to access a building where there is for example hostages
it's very practical to be able to send a drone in the place
get visual information to assess the situation and stay in a very safe
place while doing that.
Now let's apply this information to the bottom part of Worksheet 1
as Mark mentioned the team identified several promising applications
at its early stage that could bring real value from the start
inspection of complex industry machineries, inspection
Of difficult to maintain infrastructures and also security
or rescue applications. Each of these applications can address
the need of different types of customers. For example
industrial inspection can be applied in the oil and gas industries to
inspect storage tanks or pressure vessels. It can be applied to
different types of power plants and even to the maritime industry
infrastructure inspection can be relevant for indoor facilities
such as sewers and also for outdoor facilities that as
bridges security and rescue applications can be
used for intelligence gathering by militaries or police
forces or by rescue forces such as firefighters
after an initial rough screening flyer booty's team
decided to further examine those market opportunities. It seems to be
reachable and especially those that mainly require indoor
navigation to suit the expected initial imitations of the drone.
Their market opportunity set included five options.
Among them the market that we had selected there was five market
opportunity that were really, really interesting. The
first one was boiler's the inspection of boilers in thermal electric
plants. The second one was the inspection of
meriting vessels. The third one was oil and gas
storage tanks so big things where you store liquid in bulk.
There was also the nuclear power plant. So inspecting all of the surrounding
environment around the nuclear reactor. And the last one
was the support of special operation with the police forces.
So.
This learning process can now be concluded and depicted in the
market opportunity set of the navigator using sticky notes to
represent each market opportunity. At the end of next week
we will see how flight ability evaluated the attractiveness of each of these
opportunities to understand which one is most valuable for them.