Such changes in modes of contact,
are not without implications,
for the world.
The economy, laws, politics and culture,
– no aspect of social life is spared by such changes.
Distance and the strategies we employ for eliminating it,
have a structuring effect on our existence.
As such, our values and
individual and collective capacity for “living together”,
are inevitably affected.
That is why the Internet is such an important issue,
now and for the future.
Understanding the spatial dimension of the Internet,
is also a way of understanding the extent to which,
our relationship to space is undergoing a profound change.
Access to information has changed,
its distribution being more massive, individualized,
disintermediated and dematerialized.
Production conditions are changing
as new relationships,
- more scattered but also more numerous -,
are being forged a little more each day.
The rules of the economy are also being altered,
as contact between supply and demand
has greatly changed.
Furthermore,
our means of evaluating our environment
are changing as intermediaries seemingly become
less and less essential.
This means that we must not only reevaluate
the nature of our social environment,
but also those who are in charge of it,
discussing expertise and, by extension,
the legitimacy of experts.
More fundamentally, individuals are recreating
their relationship with the world and with themselves,,
their identity, otherness and ability to act in a world that is increasingly vast.
Politics are also affected by such changes.
Changing space means changing coexistence,
our relationship to others and politics.
Politics is thus faced with a double burden :
On one hand, as political action,
it must respond to social change :
changes in ownership, privacy,
freedom of expression, education, sovereignty, etc.
On the other hand, as politics in action,
it must adapt its very framework
to people’s changing modes of expression,
commitment, collaboration and responsibility.
Understanding what is occurring,
does indeed require perceiving the many modes of existence,
and most notably spatiality.
Thus it becomes obvious that changing space means changing
the arrangement of things, changing interpersonal relationships,
changing the World and changing society.
The relationships between the Internet, space and society
are so complex that it is essential to distinguish clearly
between the societal causes that led to its emergence
and the consequences of its spread in society.
The causes are generally the result of the widespread desire
to optimize social interaction, whereas the consequences
are the result of the realization of this desire.
The car perfectly illustrates this distinction:
it meets an identifiable urge for individual mobility,
but the consequences of its use on society
is far more complex.
The cognitive dissonance resulting from the common confusion
between the causes and consequences,
results in expectations, an imaginary and a vocabulary,
marked by a strong dichotomy
between dystopias and utopias.
But such confusion is detrimental
to understanding the actual relationship
between the Internet and its social environment.
The Internet’s emergence brought about not only
the abolition of space and distance, but also
the supposed discrepancy between real space and virtual space,
and, even more, between real life and virtual life.
This discrepancy has raised numerous questions
relative to the Internet’s unique spatiality.
When we go on the Internet,
where are we really going?
What does an address or site mean in such a context?
Of what is the Internet the virtual version?
Understanding the Internet requires a better understanding of space.
Let us speculate that our inability to understand the Internet’s influence
on the World stems from an erroneous conception of space.
Space is generally understood as a material reality
and is often equated to territory,
in which other realities (individuals, homes, vehicles, resources, etc.) coexist:
individuals, homes, vehicles, resources, etc.
The problem with this perception of space, though widespread,
can be summed up in a relatively simple question:
if space is a thing, then where is it?
This question highlights the aporia of considering space
as a material support for action
and underscores the common confusion
between what is situated and what situates.
Yet, space is neither material,
nor a support.
Spaces may be situated,
but always in relation to other spaces.
That is why we must completely rethink space,
as discussed in the previous sessions.
Leibniz’s and Kant’s philosophies in the 17th and 18th centuries,
and physics in the late 19th and early 20th centuries,
clearly showed that space is essentially an a priori requirement
for the understanding that allows us to situate things in a relative way.
It is not a specific thing,
but a specific ordering of things.
an arrangement of things relative to one another.
This conceptual shift,
which significantly changed philosophy and physics,
has not yet fully taken place.
While material realities are an essential part,
of our existence,
contemporary societies are nonetheless increasingly
organized around immaterial resources.
Information in particular has become a major resource,
whose processing, storage and circulation
are the focus of many industries.
Today we consecrate more than a quarter of our lives
to education, which is nothing other than the transmission of information
that has been deemed useful for our development.
Our leisure activities are also affected by the dematerialization
of music, films and many games.
Money is also increasingly simple information
that no longer needs to be in material form to be exchanged.
That is why the consequences of spatial materialism
are relatively numerous.
Such a conception of space, for instance,
lends to an incomplete comprehension of the reality of the Internet.
The contradistinction between real life and virtual life is undoubtedly
one of the most caricatural consequences of this confusion.
But this aporia is particularly unfortunate
in that it de-realizes our increasingly numerous relationships and acts.
Finally, it seems that this confusion between real and virtual
conceals the other, more insidious one between reality and materiality.
More precisely, it is the immateriality of the relationships,
created via the Internet,
that is at the heart of a larger misunderstanding,
of which the materialist conception of space
is the most structural element.
It is not enough to recall that the Internet is made of cables
and data centers to describe its reality.
The reality of the Internet is far bigger.
It includes all the information
and practices that take place in this space.
And yet, these immaterial relationships are nevertheless
real interactions and, each day,
contribute in their own small way to the development
of contemporary individual and collective lives.
Nowadays, the challenge is understanding the tradeoffs
between the material and immaterial, network and territory,
and between the Internet and the spaces existed prior to it.
The Internet does not abolish space,
no more so than it eliminates distance.
Rather, it makes distance less relevant
in certain configurations and with regard to certain issues,
to respond to specific interactions.
For this reason, the Internet creates space,
new relationships between an ever-growing number of realities
and new places that are very much real,
which become interfaces,
that are essential
to increasingly numerous practices.
Wikipedia, Facebook and YouTube, among others,
are spaces that respond to specific problems
with amazing efficiency.
They are not degraded forms of space
or virtual spaces,
but real, contemporary spaces.
The immateriality of the interactions that characterize them
does not detract from their reality.
On the contrary, it increases their capacity
to fully respond to specific needs.
These spaces emerge in response to problems
that territorial spaces
cannot resolve as effectively.
It is unnecessary to emphasize the virtual nature of the relationships
on Facebook or to compare Wikipedia to Britannica.
Instead we should ask of what
Facebook and Wikipedia are the spaces,
and take a more symmetrical approach
that would require the same thing of territorial spaces.
What territorial space could possibly allow for the constant,
instantaneous coproduction of an encyclopedia developed by individuals
who are scattered all over the world, and disseminate this knowledge for free?
What territorial space allows us to interact with people,
regardless of their whereabouts, at any moment?
What territorial space allows you to view or listen to
virtually any contemporary audiovisual resource ever made?
Wake-Up Questions
Could you list the top-ten languages used on the Internet in 2014?
R: English, Chinese, Spanish, Arabic, Portuguese,
Japanese, Russian, German, French and Malay.