Space is indeed
what brings us together and what separates us.
There is space between us, the space we share.
The duality of space is also a major social issue,
that reflects the tension between
the distance necessary for the expression of individuality
and the contact necessary for the expression of society.
Because action takes place,
space is inevitably a problem of desires,
appropriation, inequalities, identities and conflicts.
Living together with space means
finding a way to share that works..
Clearly, the Internet is a space wherein sharing
will become increasingly complicated
as the number of players increases.
Internet also has the particularity
of being simultaneously
global, national and regional.
Yet, tradeoffs must be made together,
in order to organize this space
and guide its future.
Tradeoffs like privacy vs. transparency,
security vs. freedom of expression,
and intellectual property vs. the dissemination of knowledge
can be left neither to the market
nor to the power of individual disappointments.
These adjustments raise many difficulties
because it can legitimately be argued that the space for their regulation
is unquestionably the World.
On the other hand, these tradeoffs have an inevitable cost: policy.
Losing individual sovereignty
to gain power to make
the plurality of the World exist together seems
like the only condition of this coexistence,
in a unified world of interconnections.
Thus, “the Eldorado” has probably lasted too long.
Google prioritizes spaces using opaque algorithms
of which it alone is the master,
giving it unrivalled centrality.
Facebook handles the social practices
of more than a billion people
whose relationships and exchanges become its property.
The network effect of such players
is so great that it is becoming increasingly difficult to escape it,
or risk losing the gains of that which was nonetheless produced collectively
(hypertext links, publications, relationships, etc.).
That’s why it is worth asking
why such key features were not developed
using principles comparable to
packet transmission, IP addressing, messaging or the Web
at the Internet’s founding.
How is it that a private company
can monopolize our social networks
and stockpile our digital traces,
and sell them unbeknownst to us?
Why is it so unthinkable
that social networks are becoming a protocol like any other,
whose market activity will eventually come down to simplifying use,
like messaging or the Web?
Why do private companies give themselves permission
to activate cameras remotely on stolen computers?
Why does Google think it can divert the privacy settings
of a competing browser?
Why did Megaupload prosper
for so long with total impunity?
The answer: simply because politics were largely absent
from this space for many years, and often restricted
its involvement to limited
authoritative prerogatives.
Above all, this authority was largely inapplicable
in a space where the State had so little control.
Yet, defining what is fair and the means for complying
with this is a highly political issue that is little satisfied
with injunctions at inappropriate scales.
Justice is invariably a compromise
between private interests that incorporate
provisional values
and is therefore contextual.
Which is why the World and the Internet share a common problem:
justice can be thought about at this scale
but is only marginally effective.
The Internet as such is facing a formidable problem:
making local conceptions of what is fair commensurable
while changing the practical arrangements
of living together by its very existence.
It is not Wikipedia, P2P (Peer-to-Peer), blogs
or collective evaluation platforms
that should be questioned,
but rather what they will become in a highly commercial world
driven by numerous private interests,
from which the Internet will not escape unscathed
without full consideration of what sharing includes.
Now more than ever we must explore this question
and together devise the means for maintaining this shared space,
and of sharing it.
Paradoxically, the Internet is an ideal place
for implementing such a project,
by dint of the conversations
that take place in a broader public sphere.
But sharing cannot be done without considering
the plurality of individuals,
spaces and institutions concerned by it.
Certainly we must safeguard against idiocy,
which the ancient Greeks defined
as the propensity to restrict one’s horizons
and isolate oneself from a broader world.
The Internet thus appears to be the ideal space for the emergence of a World society,
a society whose ultimate horizon is political.
This dynamic underscores the weakness of nation states,
which were once legitimate before being overwhelmed
by increasingly intense practices
at scales that largely exceed them.
In this respect, individuals’ disengagement from and mistrust of politics
is not so much a failure of politics
as of the nation state,
which clearly no longer has the means to fulfill its ambitions.
Currently, numerous are the events
that take the World
as their pertinent space
for expression and political action.
But the Internet is facing an obstacle
that threatens all of its underpinnings.
Paradoxically, the time seems to have come
where politics must preserve the utopia
it had aspired to do without.
The Internet was in fact conceived and designed with the libertarian ideal
of self-organization,
which left plenty of room for the individual.
Also, this system has demonstrated the effective power of this ideology,
which has already profoundly changed the World.
However, by becoming a reality,
this utopia has taken place.
Now that it’s a place, the Internet is faced
with humanity at its most political:
the reconciliation of individual interests
in a shared space.
Politics could certainly jeopardize
the Internet’s potential,
but it also seems like
the most obvious way to preserve it.
Nation-States were slow
to perceive what was emerging,
but now that their sovereignty has been further weakened and compromised
- overwhelmed on all sides -
they are attempting to regain control of their space.
This jolt takes unequal forms,
ranging from the widespread surveillance techniques
used by the United States
to nationalization in China (and Iran even more so)
to the Domain Name System blockades
imposed on Internet Service Providers in France and the U.K.
The premises of the Internet’s future governance
are a far cry from those initiated at its emergence,
of which TCP-IP (Transmission Control Protocol and Internet Protocol),
messaging and the Web are the heirs.
Though co-authors of this announced catastrophe,
individuals are now witnessing the commercial hyper-concentration
of this space in the hands of a few companies
and its uncoordinated, misinformed, authoritarian regulation
by States legitimately seeking their place
in this space that exceeds their means.
Make no mistake about it.
The legacy of the Internet’s founders is not steadfast.
Changes in protocols, including IPv6 (Internet Protocol version 6),
will simplify national regulations
and the undermining of the network’s “neutrality”,
allowing for unprecedented control of digital practices.
A Stateless space, the Internet was created with the illusion
that politics were incapable of taking control of it.
Pushed to the limits of their intimacy – space –
States are now calling to restore their respective orders.
But because these orders are highly diverse
and in large part contradictory,
the Internet will undergo profound changes in the decades to come.
More than ever
people need to be aware of this fragile balance.
States will intervene as best they can
in response to the increasing excesses
of a space whose unequal control
calls for inevitable regulations
to protect fundamental freedoms,
while unable to coordinate
their actions at the Internet scale (i.e. the World).
Now more than ever, it is not a question of morals but of ethics,
because what we do to the Internet
we do to the World at large.
That is why the future must choose
between the globalization of politics
and the nationalization of the Internet.
The first option would merely be the continuation of a long process
begun in the early coalescences of humanity.
The second would be a terrible decline
that would mean not only the end of the Internet
as we know it,
but also that of a global, emerging society
that is only asking to express itself.
A powerful vehicle of the globalization
that actively mobilizes individuals,
the Internet does suggest
that the time has come for humanity
to think about this upscaling
towards its ultimate horizon: the World.
Because the Internet is the ideal public sphere
for meeting this challenge,
an ideal but fragile place
that we must never cease to consider,
build, share, feed and preserve, together.