There are three ways
of managing distances:
copresence, mobility,
and telecommunication,
[which] have roughly merged
at the same time
at the beginning of the Neolithic era.
But each of them has recently experienced
a dramatic change,
namely the global urbanization,
mass tourism and the Internet.
Digital worlds convey
a profound transformation of society
especially through
their relations to space.
Let's see how, thanks to Dr. Boris Beaude,
an acknowledged specialist
of the digital society
who is also a prominent geographer.
Good morning.
During this session,
we will discuss the spatial dimension of the Internet.
I suggest that we consider the Internet as a real space,
a space in which an increasing portion of our practices,
exchanges and lives take place.
While the Internet can be described
based on its technical, economic and social features,
it is nonetheless an essentially spatial innovation.
The contemporary world is actually more easily understood
once we realize the extent to which the Internet is essentially spatial.
By accepting this premise,
the virtual reality we are faced with
are also easier to understand.
It becomes possible to take hold of it
and act more efficiently
in an admittedly uncertain, complex,
but extremely rich world.
The Internet does indeed present an interesting paradox
and thus is the cause of much confusion.
The Internet eliminates space and yet is itself a space.
The vocabulary is clear regarding the semantic proximity
d'Internet avec between the Internet and space.
We “go” online to sites,
where we browse and surf,
encountering firewalls
and “virtual spaces.”
From its emergence, the Internet has fueled
the already fertile fantasy of ubiquity.
After the telegraph and telephone,
the Internet effectively responds to high expectations of contact
over the largest distances possible.
The rapid adoption of the Internet
in this way attests to the many issues
it carries with it.
It meets the fundamental need of individuals,
to create contact
where there is distance.
In just forty short years,
the Internet has become a global phenomenon.
No communication technology has ever met
such varied demands.
The Internet stands out for its ability to be at once local and global,
synchronous and asynchronous,
symmetric and asymmetric,
permanent and ephemeral,
in other words qualities that typically correspond
to specific means of communication.
The Internet, though young still,
indeed calls into question the organizational strategies
we have developed over the millennia.
Like writing, printing, the train, telegraph,
radio or television,
the Internet increases our ability to act together
over increasingly vast areas.
With each new mean of communication
it is society as a whole that is transformed
by the renewing of the modalities of social interaction.
Such changes have implications for the organization of space,
as well as for economic transactions,
politics and individual and collective identity.
Too often we forget how much our lives are dependent
on how we deal with space
and master the distance
that separates us from realities,
whose presence and qualities we desire.
That is why the virtuality of the Internet is not as we imagine it.
it does not preclude reality but rather the actuality.
It exists in our every act.
If the Internet warrants special attention,
it is probably because the virtuality it provides
is in part new,
and in large part remains to be discovered.
The Internet has indeed become the center of a contemporary world
whose nature and challenges are important to understand.
It is not only intermediary,
but a space where a considerable number of events
are taking place at every moment.
The Internet’s specific qualities have indeed destabilized
even the most established of global players.
Their control of territories,
and transport networks,
guaranteed a secure situation
that does not content itself with an emerging space
over which they have only approximate control.
In just a decade,
Google has effectively upset
many aspects of our activities.
In barely less time Wikipedia has undermined
important values of social order,
governance, and expertise most notably.
Facebook has become one of the main intermediaries between individuals,
while Wikileaks has impinged on firmly rooted governmental practices.
This means we must take the Internet’s ability
to create hitherto unknown centralities seriously,
allowing for an unprecedented concentration of power
in ways that are nonetheless uncertain.
The Internet reminds us, if necessary, that society is made of social ties,
and of contact and interaction in general.
Changing space, from this perspective,
is changing society.
The economy and law are among the dimensions of society
the most torn by this revival,
as the convergence of digital and communications technology
renews the meaning of property, value,
expression, responsibility and identity.
Free access, for instance, has become a model.
The marginal cost of copying, storing and distribution
of digital works
has deeply changed the value of what can be digitized,
at the risk of neglecting sometimes considerable production costs.
The audiovisual industry is a perfect example
of the changes of an entire sector.
The key players in this sector, like Sony,
were overwhelmed by the emergence of widespread practices
they did not anticipate
and of which they are incapable of containing the spread.
The Internet’s ability
to create reticular contact where there is territorial distance
is also a great opportunity for organization, production
and coordination.
Collective intelligence, the wisdom of crowds and crowdsourcing,
are notions that are emerging from this potential.
While the majority of the population is not really involved
in this process,
it is nonetheless decisive.
Humanity is able
to share knowledge
accumulated over centuries,
which can then be discussed and renewed
in a more decentralized manner.
It is not really a question
of equal skills or the legitimacy of players,
but of their non-determination a priori.
It is a question of rethinking governance,
conforming it to the complexity
that arises from such a multitude of individual expressions and acts
whose work is certainly unequally productive
yet potentially useful.
The Internet’s ability to create a shared space
is also an opportunity for territories.
The city in particular has thus been greatly augmented.
An ideal place for interaction,
the city is even more attractive
now that it offers all the possibilities
of material and immaterial contact,
and optimizes more than ever
the potential for interaction between inhabitants
and itself,
but also the World at large.
Moreover,
the spread of geolocation technology
has accelerated the hybridization of space.
Geolocation combines territories and networks,
the material and immaterial,
analog and digital,
giving rise to new practices.
This complex hybridization of spaces with different qualities
also demands consideration of the body
(when senses are missing),
of disembodied identity (when the avatar and anonymity are required),
and co-spatiality
(when we’re on the Internet,
but also in our bedrooms,
classrooms
or around the table with friends).
It also questions our ability
to accompany this change,
both individually and collectively.
One may effectively ask
how we can reconcile the relatively long time scales
of cities’ materiality
with the relatively short ones of the Internet.
Even street furniture does not fit into such time scales
whereas the time of its adoption
more or less corresponds to that of its obsolescence.
All this requires fully considering the Internet as a shared space,
which raises specific issues,
that are often unclear,
sometimes sudden and increasingly intense.
Undoubtedly, we were slow to adapt to writing,
books and television.
But the Internet is more even challenging,
given that it changes faster than our ability
to collectively understand its dynamics.
And yet, it is essential to organize it,
make it habitable and useful.
Dealing with this eminently political challenge is not obvious.
The Internet, inherited from cybernetics,
in its very fundaments supposes that,
what is good for information – i.e. unhindered movement –
is good for society,
a legacy that underscores the strengths and weaknesses,
of a space that is structurally decentralized.
For the first time in the history of humanity,
this dream has become a reality
and has found a place for its expression.
But the presumptions of such a conception of society
are both debatable and debated.
With the Internet, space has effectively changed so much
that society is now driven by a movement
whose dynamics are difficult to comprehend because they are unfamiliar.
Denying the reality and spatiality of the Internet
exposes many actions that nevertheless actively contribute
to derealization and the risk of
no longer understanding it,
entangled with a materialism
that confuses reality and the materiality,
but also space and territory.