The Internet’s strengths and weaknesses
lay precisely in
in its ability to transmit information
with unparalleled efficiency.
As matter is energy
in mass form,
it resists movement.
The larger the mass, the greater the energy
requires to move it.
The light or electricity we use
to communicate information via the Internet,
however, are forms of electromagnetic energy,
i.e. waves whose speed
is ideally close to nearly
a billion kilometers an hour.
It is by channeling this energy
in the form of continuums
that we are able to reach
transmission of this rapidity at a global scale.
Thus are we witnessing the emergence of new spaces
that reorganize the relative arrangement of things.
These spaces are not mere transpositions
of existing spaces:
libraries, shops, newsstands, schools,
bars, public place, etc.
They are original spaces with specific qualities
that use immateriality
in an exceptional way,
which is why they have such impressive transmission speeds
and cover unprecedented expanses.
The Internet’s limitations are nonetheless numerous.
For instance, it is powerless
in meeting the many material needs
of our existence.
Our bodies have a complex spatiality
requiring matter.
Digital technology can undoubtedly help us better understand
our practices and how they evolve,
as feedback to help us make decisions
and change our behavior.
But digital technology is limited to organizing information,
which is not the extent of our bodies’ demands.
Our bodies need protection from the elements, to be fed
with food and to be
healed with compounds.
Multisensory interaction is also widely sought after,
whereas the Internet is limited to two immaterial senses
(vision and hearing)
and cannot truly convey textures, flavors and smells.
Our bodies themselves are made of matter
and have mass, thus limiting their mobility.
Therefore, far from abolishing space,
the Internet reorganizes it, increasing its potential
and differentiating it even more,
constantly activating the value of situated resources
whose materiality is a constraint or a gift.
The Internet thus reminds us of the plural nature of the territories
that are home to our bodies and the places that are home to our lives.
Thus, in just a few decades,
space has radically changed,
offering new interpersonal opportunities.
In a hyperconnected environment,
even disconnection is a change, at least relatively speaking.
The World is more cohesive but is also more diverse.
It is not so much the homogenization of the world we are witnessing
as that of these processes of differentiation.
The latter are based
on generic systems and norms:
airports, hotels, restaurants, cell phones and the Internet,
whose similarities mask their spatial potency
and the diversity of their uses,
like so many points of reference
from which to take action.
Currently, the gap between
our understanding of this dynamic and its effectiveness
is particularly important,
as the Internet has created a space whose potential and practices
stem from logics that fit poorly into the frames
of reference we have developed thus far.
In particular, it gives rise to unprecedented interactions,
from the local to the global scale,
like so much potential contact between individuals
regardless of the distance that separates them.
This dynamic - which began with the first roads and cities,
with shipping lanes, railroads, writing,
printing, the radio,
telephone and television -
is experiencing an important revival.
By changing space,
we affect one of society’s fundamental dimensions,
one of its most powerful driving forces.
How can we imagine that by simplifying the exchange of goods
between China and Europe that we are only
affecting the distribution of material goods?
How can we believe that in inventing the car
we are only affecting mobility?
How can we assume that in creating the Internet,
we are only affecting the circulation of information?
Perhaps the Internet was an Eldorado
inhabited by pioneers who sought the coming of a better world.
But the Internet is above all a space
whose every basic component we build.
It is not so much an existing space to be discovered
but a space to be invented, again and again.
Understanding the tensions that affect
contemporary societies
implies taking space seriously,
not as a mere projection of the social realm
that situates what occurs
but as one of its conditions.
Without space there is no society.
Without contact the social realm disappears without enchantment.
Without communication life is reduced to nothing,
emptied from the outside, without otherness..
Society is therefore not given.
It is born of distance, of the space between people,
for which it is both a solution and a problem.
Because it is fragile, it is constantly recomposed
based on the many acts and individual expressions
that together provide the delicate balance
between today’s society and the one to come.
Society is a solution when it liaises between individuals
with multiple and/or conflicting intentions.
Society is a problem
when it no longer is part of the space that gives it life,
and when it falls short of or goes beyond
the actual relationships between individuals.
Yet, the Internet does not abolish space.
On the contrary, it creates space between people,
a space of considerable power
that reorganizes our environment
in specific ways.
Because the Internet offers a unique space,
it is imperative to think about its architecture,
design, organization and players,
and to identify the practices that develop therein,
their logics and the favorite haunts
emerging from this renewal.
This space – both an economic and a political issue -
has become subject to intense conflicts
in which companies, that have become multinational
in less than two decades,
are pitted against States whose sovereignty is impacted
by a network that is too big for them,
and individuals whose interests
and privacy are challenged
by this space of often opaque intricacy.