In this part,
we learn how to estimate
the term structure
from a given set of market quotes
on instruments including
coupon bonds, LIBOR, forward rates,
and swap rates.
We will distinguish between exact
methods
and smoothing methods.
Exact methods will give us discount
curves
that exactly reproduce
the market data.
But this comes at the cost of
somewhat irregular forward curves.
If we insist on the regular
forward curves
we use a smoothing method
which gives us
smooth yield curves.
But at the cost of not exactly
matching the market data.
We will eventually see what PCA,
Principal Component Analysis
tells us about the basic shapes
of the yield curve.
We now start with
the bootstrapping method,
which is an exact method.
It is a very simple method
and it is most used
among trading desks.
The idea is to build up
the term structure
from shorter maturities
to longer maturities.
And it is most instructive
to learn about the Bootstraping
method from an example.
We look at this following data
from the U.S market
on October 1st, 2012.
We are given LIBOR rates, futures
rates, and swap rates.
The day count convention is actual
by 360.
The aim is to find the discount
curve
for all the reset cash flow dates
that exactly matches these quotes.
Let's look at the first block of
market data, the LIBOR rates.
They're given for overnight, 1 month,
and 3 months maturities.
We denote these maturity dates
by S-1, S-2, and S-3.
In terms of the day count convention,
the year fractions are given here.
The corresponding zero coupon bond
prices are given in this 1 to 1 relation.
The next block contains
quotes on futures prices.
Recall that the futures price for
a maturity date Ti+1
is quoted as:
100 x (1 - the futures rate)
which is the futures rate
for the period with reset date
Ti and maturity date Ti+1.
We have 5 futures prices.
The reset date for
the first futures is
T-1 is equal to the
19th of December, 2012.
We use futures rates as proxies
for forward rates
as shown here.
When looking at the maturity
spectrum,
notice that we have a
maturity overlap
as shown here.
The first reset date of the
first futures contract
lies between S-2 and S-3
the maturities of the LIBOR rates.
From this, we get
The LIBOR rate for T-1
by linearly interpolating
The S-2 LIBOR, and
the S-3 LIBOR rates.
From the T-1 LIBOR rate,
we then get the T-1 bond
and then we derive the T-2 bond
using this formula
which relates forward rates
to ratios of zero coupon bonds.
By iterative usage of this formula,
We eventually get the T-3, T-4, T-5
and T-6 zero coupon bond prices.
The third block contains swap
rates
for 9 different lengths.
These swaps pay annual coupons at
the following 30 dates.
The dates marked in red,
are the dates on which
the 9 swaps mature.
For these 9 dates, we are
given swap rates.
What we will do next is
we will use linear interpolation
to get swap rates for
the black dates
U-6, U-8, U-9, and so on
and so forth.
We will get the swap rate for U-1
as shown on the following page.
Again we note that there is
a maturity overlap
and U-1 falls between T-4 and T-5
which are maturity dates
of the futures.
From the futures quotes, we derived
the corresponding
zero coupon bond prices.
So we are given the T-4 bond
and the T-5 bond prices.
From these, we infer the T-4 and the
T-5 simple spot rates
and then we use linear interpolation
of these 2 simple spot rates
to get the simple spot rate
with maturity U-1.
The simple spot rate with
maturity U-1
gives us the U-1 bond price,
and then we can use the swap rate
formula
which relates the swap rate
for maturity U-2
to the U-1 and U-2 bond prices.
We can solve this equation
for the U-2 bond price
as shown here.
For the remaining cash flow dates
we use linear interpolation
to obtain the corresponding
swap rates.
We can then invert the swap rate
formula
to derive iteratively the U-n
bond price
in terms of the previous bond prices
and the corresponding swap rates
as shown here.
We eventually obtain the U-n bond
prices
for all the remaining maturities
n from 3 to 30.
Setting the initial value of the
discount curve equal to 1
we thus have constructed
the discount curve
for 40 maturity time points
as shown here.
Recall that the blue maturities
S-1, S-2, S-3
correspond to the LIBOR rates.
The red maturities T-1 up to T-6
correspond to the futures rate,
and the green maturities U-1
up to U-30
correspond to the swap rates.
We also see again the overlap
of these maturity spectra.
The T maturities overlap
with the S maturities
and the green swap maturities
overlap
with the red T maturities.
The figure on the left hand side
shows us the discount curve
as a function of time to maturity.
We see that the bulk of
the maturity dates
correspond to the swap contracts.
If we zoom in to the first 3 years
this is what we see on
the right hand side.
We see the short end
of the discount curve.
So here we can nicely distinguish
between
the LIBOR maturity dates, the futures
reset and maturity dates,
and then the first cash flow dates
of the swap contracts.
The figure on the left hand side
shows 3 curves.
The first curve is the yield curve,
that corresponds to the discount
curve.
The second curve is
the curve of simple spot rates
both of which look decently smooth.
But if we look at the forward curve,
this is the middle curve here,
we see some saw tooth.
If we again zoom in to the first
3 years,
this is what is shown on
the right hand side,
we see irregularities also showing
up here.
So in sum
the bootstrapping gives us
an entire term structure
from relatively few instruments.
We had 3 LIBOR,
5 futures contracts,
and 9 swap contracts.
The method exactly reconstructs
these market prices
and this is desirable for interest
rate risk management
and trading desks
because they have to marked
to market their books.
But the implied forward curve
is irregular
and sensitive to bond price
variations.
Bootstrapping is an example
of an exact estimation method.