We saw bootstrapping as an
example of an exact method.
In this part, we will now
formalize the exact method
and see how it can be written
as a linear equation.
We will highlight some issues, and
propose some solutions to these issues.
One solution as we will see
is the bootstrapping method.
I will also show you another
alternative solution to it which
which builds on the pseudo-inverse
of the cash flow matrix.
Formally speaking, the market data
that is given to us
at the spot date t-0
is stacked into a vector P of
n market prices.
Each of these instruments yields
a cashflow
c-ij
so that the value of instrument i
is given as the sum of the
discounted cash flows c-ij.
Now the special thing about this sum
is that we will
sum up all possible cash flow dates,
and there are N of them,
even though instrument i may not
have a cash flow at that date.
We will then simply put c-ij = 0.
So the market gives us the 'P-i's
and it gives us the 'c-ij's
the cash flows on the date t-j.
What is not known is
the discount curve.
We stack the discount curve
into the vector D
and we rewrite this equation
here
as this matrix equation.
The next step is now
to bring the data
into this form.
While this is pretty
straightforward
if the market data describes prices
of coupon bearing bonds,
this is less so in cases where
market data
represents LIBOR, forward rates,
and swap rates.
Let's start with coupon bond
market data.
As an example, we look at these
quotes
of UK government bonds
on the 4th of September, 1996.
We have 9 bonds, and they come
with coupons
ranging from 7% to 12.25%
on a principal of 100.
We see in the middle columns,
the next coupon dates.
And we see in this column here
the maturity dates
of the corresponding bonds.
We also see the dirty prices.
So if we start to count
and order the cash flow dates,
we see that it's bond 3
that pays the next coupon.
The next bond is bond 9.
And the third cash flow
comes from bond 5.
We also see from that table
that bond 1
is the soonest to mature bond.
The next coupon date coincides
with it's maturity date.
So there is only one cash flow
left for this bond.
UK government bonds have
semi-annual cash flows.
So bond 2 has 3 cash flows left
and so on and so forth.
If we summarize this UK government
bonds data
on the 4th of September, 1996,
our prices of coupon bearing bonds
that pay semi-annual coupons.
The day count convention is
actual over 365.
The number of market prices given R
is 9
and the number of cash flow dates
if we sum them up, bond 1 had
1 cash flow left
bond 2 had 3 cash flows left
and so on and so forth;
summing up gives us
104 cash flow dates.
The first one is
the one from bond 3.
The second one is
the one from bond 9
and the third one is the one
from bond 5
as seen on the previous slide.
We can summarize these cash flows
into the matrix C.
In the first row, we see the
cash flow of bond 1
which matures and pays
the principal plus
the 10% coupon rate.
Remember that coupons are paid
semi-annually,
rates are annualized so the interest
paid on the maturity date is 5.
Similarly the 2nd bond will pay
a coupon of 4.875
The third bond, which is the bond
with
the earliest next coupon payment
pays 6.125
and so on and so forth.
Recall that in total we have
104 cash flow dates.
So what we see on this slide are
the first 10 columns
of a 9 x 104 cash flow matrix.
We also see that it is sparse,
that is, most of the entries are 0.
Now let us bring into the price
cash flow form
the LIBOR and forward rates.
The LIBOR rate prevailing
at t-0
with maturity date T
can be cast in the form, by giving
it a price
P of 1 at t-0.
And giving it a cash flow
of 1 + ( δ x the rate(L) )
at maturity T.
A forward rate, remember, was derived
from a forward rate agreement
which corresponds to
a cash flow of -1
at time T-1and cash flow
of 1 + ( δ x the forward rate(F) )
at T-2.
The present value of these
cash flows
at time t-0 is 0.
This carries over to swap contracts
as follows.
Let the fixed rate be K
and let t-0 up to T-n denote
the reset and settlement dates.
Where for the sake of notation,
we assume
that the delta(δ) here is constant.
If K is the swap rate
then
this relation here holds.
So if the swap is spot starting
if T-0 = t-0
this is just value 1, we take
it to the left hand side
and we see that we get a price
cash flow
scheme of price (p) = 1,
cash flows = δ.K
and 1 + ( δ.K ) at maturity.
If the swap is forward starting,
we take this equation literally
as is
the price is 0, of a cash flow of -1
at time T-0 plus
cash flows of (δ.K)
at times T-j and 1 + (δ.K)
at times T-n.
Summarizing these formalizations
at the spot date t-0,
LIBOR and spot starting swaps
have a notional price of 1.
Forward rate agreements and forward
starting swaps have a notional price of 0.
Let us now come back to the example
with the US money and swap
market data
from 1st of October, 2012
that is the example we saw on
the bootstrapping example.
Remember the day count
convention is actual over 360.
We are given 3 LIBOR rates,
5 futures quotes,
and 9 swap rates.
We thus have 17 market prices.
The corresponding cash flows are
3 for the LIBOR, 6 for the futures
and 30 for the swaps
adding up to 39.
The ordered cash flow dates are,
t-1 is the 2nd of October
which is the overnight LIBOR
maturity.
t-2 is the 5th of November which
is the 1 month LIBOR.
t-3 is the 19th of December which
is the first reset date
of the first futures contract here,
and so on and so forth.
If we stack these cash flows into
the 17 x 39 cash flow matrix C
it will look like this.
In the first row, we have the cash
flow of the overnight LIBOR.
Second row, we see the cash flow
of the one month LIBOR.
In the third row, we have the cash
flow of the 3 month LIBOR.
In the fourth row here, we see the
cash flow -1
which is from the first
futures contract
and the cash flow of the corresponding
cash flow at the maturity.
Similarly for the remaining futures
contract in this middle of the matrix
and then in this first row
corresponding to the swap contracts
we have the 2 year swap which pays
2 annual coupons
as shown here.
The next swap has a length of
3 years
and it pays 3 coupons
and so on and so forth.
Again what we see here
is not the full matrix, we just see
the first 12 columns, in fact,
of 39 in total.
Again we see that the matrix
is full of zeros
and is sparse.
On the other hand, it is also
obvious that this matrix has
full rank; the 17 rows
linearly independent.
The linear system for the discount
curve
hence has at least a solution,
it has in fact infinitely many.
Summarizing these exact methods
typically leads to linear systems
for the discount curve D.
Which are under determined because
the number of equations
n is much smaller than
the number of unknowns(N) in general.
As a consequence, there exist
many discount curve solutions.
from which one is to choose.
Now let's recall the bootstrapping
example
from the previous section.
A moment's reflection shows that
we in fact synthetically created new
market instruments
by the linear interpolation of swap
rates and LIBOR rates.
We actually created just as many new
market instuments
as there are equations missing.
N-n
The extended market data then
gave us N X N cash flow matrix
that was invertible.
And so we could solve for the unique
discount curve in that case.
Bootstrapping is one possibility
to deal
with the issue of an under
determined linear system.
As an alternative solution,
we will now see
what the pseudo-inverse of the
cash flow matrix
can tell us.
Here is the idea.
Instead of estimating the discount
function D directly,
we estimate instead, a vector
of weighted increments
of the discount curve
as shown here.
The first entry is the t-1 bond
price minus 1
which is the t-0 bond price
divided by the square root of the
time to maturity.
The second entry is the difference
between the t-2 bond, and the t-1 bond
divided by the square root of the
difference of their maturities
and so on and so forth
to the t-n bond price minus the
t-(n-1) bond price
again weighted.
We can write this in matrix form
as product of a weighting matrix W
multiplying M applied to d
minus the first basis vector.
The weighting matrix W is the
diagonal matrix
with these entries on
the diagonal
and M is this matrix as shown here.
There is in fact a 1-1 relation
between
this vector of weighted increments δ
and the original discount curve d
as shown here.
Where the inverse of M can be
explicitly computed as shown here.
We can thus reformulate
and restate
the linear matching problem
as this linear system here
which is now an equation
for the vector δ.
Remember that market data gives
us the cash flow matrix C,
M is an auxiliary explicitly
given matrix,
W is the diagonal matrix consisting
of the weights
derived from the maturity dates.
P is the vector of market prices.
Again, these are more unknowns than
there are equations.
But typically, the small
n x N-matrix A
has full rank because
C has full rank.
So we can form the pseudo inverse
which gives us a particular
solution
to the linear system
that we saw on the previous slide.
By the definition of the pseudo
inverse, this is in fact
the unique solution of
the linear system
with minimal Euclidean norm.
If we write down what this
Euclidean norm looks like
we now understand in hind sight
why we have weighted these
bond price increments
by the square root of the difference
of the maturity dates.
Indeed the square here implies
that we can omit the square root
and multiply instead these
expressions with delta(δ).
So this gives us a first order proxy
of the integral
of the derivative of the discount
curve squared
with respect to maturity.
We thus obtain the smoothest
possible discount curve
according to this criterion.
Let us revisit the example that we
saw in the bootstrapping example.
US market data from the 1st of
October, 2012
we had 39 cash flow dates,
including the spot date we had
40 points on the discount curve.
The discount curve is shown here
on the left hand side
and zoomed in on the
right hand side
as a function of time to maturity.
The implied yield curve and
the forward curve
is still irregular
but the comparison shows
it is smoother
than the one that we got
from the bootstrapping.
Summarizing
the pseudo inverse provides a
valuable alternative
to the bootstrapping method.
It is an exact method that is very
simple to implement
and that yields the smoothest
possible yield curves.