We saw that exact estimation methods
can lead to ragged forward curves.
This is because discount factors
of similar maturity
can be very different.
Moreover, the discount curve
is sensitive
to small changes in the cash
flow matrix.
This may be critical because
market rate data
can contain outliers.
If our object of interest is a
smooth forward curve
we should apply a smoothing
estimation method.
That is, we should directly
estimate
a smooth forward curve
for market rates
at the cost of possibly not matching
the data exactly.
Let us directly formalize what the
smoothing estimation method does.
For simplicity of notation,
we set the spot date T-0 equal to 0.
That helps us to avoid
writing 2 time arguments
all the time.
We consider market data
consisting of N yields
which we denote by Y-i
with maturities T-i.
The aim is then to find a smooth
forward curve
f(T) that matches the yields
optimally
For pricing errors epsilon which
are subject to be minimized.
There are several good reasons
for considering pricing errors.
Market micro structure effects
could lead to outliers in the data
and in general, there are
bid-ask spreads
which can be wide in
times of illiquidity
so that prices are
not uniquely given.
smoothing methods are mainly used
buy central banks
and any institution that is
primarily interested
in the qualitative shape of the
forward curve.
Is it upward sloping?
Is it downward sloping?
Is it steep in the beginning?
or flat?
The following 3 are key criteria
for smoothing methods.
First is smoothness.
The estimation method should supply
a market expectation
for monetary policy purposes
rather than precisely pricing
all the bonds in the market.
Flexibility.
The method should be sufficiently
flexible to capture movements
to capture movements in the
underlying term structure.
And stability.
Small changes in the data at one
maturity
must not have disproportionate
effects
on forward rates at other maturities.
This is an overview
from the Bank of International
Settlements in 2005.
We see that 9 out of 13 central
banks
use methods called Nelson-Siegel
and Svensson.
While the remaining banks use
smoothing splines.
We will in the following see
what Nelson-Siegel and Svensson
and smoothing splines are.
Let's also look at the third coloumn
which indicates
what type of error
is being minimized.
We see that
we can minimize
the matching error
to yields as we saw on our
former slide.
Alternatively
One can also match prices directly
and weight
the pricing errors
and minimize those.
The simple smoothing methods consist
of
given parametric families of
forward curves.
The 2 major examples are
the Nelson-Siegel
and the Svensson curves.
We see that the Nelson-Siegel curves
are forward curves
of polynomial exponential type
with 4 parameters
β-0, β-1, β-2 and A
where A is the shape parameter
for these exponential functions,
and the Betas are linear loadings
on these basis functions.
The Svensson family extends the
Nelson-Siegel family
by adding 2 additional parameters
expressed in this term.
And adding thus small flexiblity
to these curve families.
We obtain the yield curves in the
Nelson-Siegel family
by elementary integration
as shown here.
So that the Nelson-Siegel yield
curves linear combinations
with parameters β-0, β-1, β-2
of the basis functions
i-0, i-1, i-2.
The figure on the right hand side
shows us these 3 basis functions
for the choice
of the shape parameter
A = 0.3
and we see that
these basis functions
from MVC.
MVC, that is, 3 basis functions
are the level
of the yield curve,
the slope
and the curvature of the yield
curve.
We will come back to these 3
basis shapes
but from a different angle
in the section on Principal
Component Analysis.
The Nelson-Siegel yield curves
are clearly smooth.
The issue with this
family of curves is
their lack of flexibility.
There are only 3 or 4 parameters.
But also the stability
meaning that
changing
a yield data point
especially at a longer maturity
will lead to a dramatic change
of the Nelson-Siegel yield curve
at the short end.
Smoothing splines
can overcome
the issues of flexibility
and stability
of the Nleson-Siegel
and Svensson curves.
The idea is to find the forward
curve matching the data
in the space of all possible forward
curves.
We formalize this
by fixing a finite time horizon
T*
and look at the Hilbert space H
consisting of absolutely continuous
functions
on this time horizon.
And we endow this Hilbert space
with a scalar product as shown
here.
Recall that absolutely continuous
real functions
have a first order derivative
which is integrable
so that this integral
is well defined.
We then look
at all forward curves
in this Hilbert space
that optimally match
the data, the yields Y-i;
and at the same time
are smooth in the sense that
the square of the first derivative
integrated
over the time horizon is being
minimal.
The parameter α
shown here
tunes the trade off between
the smoothness
and the correctness of the fit.
It turns out that this is
a convex optimization problem
in the Hilbert space H
which is infinite dimensional.
The more remarkable it is
that there is a unique solution
which is given in closed form
as shown here.
As a linear combination
of quadratic basis splines H-i
which are defined as piece wise
2nd order polynomials
with these characteristics.
The right hand side shows
quadratic basis splines H-1 and H-2,
for the maturities T-1 = 1 and
T-2 = 2.
We see that H-1 is
2nd order polynomial
with slope
starting at 1
and then linearly decreasing to 0.
And then
as of T-1 being constant.
In red we see
the basis spline
for T-2 = 2.
The parameters β-0, β-1, up to β-n
solve a linear system which
is shown on the next slide.
Here is the linear system that
is solved by the N+1 parameters
β-0 up to β-n.
It can be shown that this linear
system has a unique solution.
This theorem is proved using
elementary functional analysis.
Proof is provided to you
in a separate document.
This result is a fork theorem in the
theory of smoothing splines.
I call it Lorimier's theorem
for this course
because in her thesis
she used this result
to estimate the forward curve.
It can be verified that smoothing
splines satisfy the 3 criteria of
smoothness, flexibility,
and stability.
In fact the parameter α tunes
the trade off between
the smoothness and the correctness
of the fit.
When alpha (α) turns to 0,
in the limit we get the maximally
smooth forward curve
namely, a constant curve
taking value β-0.
On the other hand, when tends
to infinity
we obtain a perfect fit
to the yields
subject to having a minimal
matrix
for the smoothness of the
forward curve.
As an example, we see here
on the right hand side
the curves we get from applying
this smoothing spline theorem
to yield data that we get from
the Swiss Government bond market
in August 2011.
In red we see the 8 data points
and then we have 3 curves
for various values of α
ranging from 0.01 to 10.
We see when α is close to 0,
we get a curve
which is closer to a constant
than the other 2 curves
but it obviously has a bad fit
to the market data.
On the other hand
when alpha(α) is large, that is,
when it is 10
we get the dotted curve
which basically, perfectly fits
the yields.
We conclude that the choice
of α is critical
For a value of α which
is too small
we can get a very smooth curve
which however does a very bad job
in fitting the market data.
The right choice of alpha(α)
has to be done case by case.