A major problem in estimating
the term structure
is the high dimensionality
of the discount curve.
In this part we aim at finding
the basis shapes of the yield curve
by looking at time series
of yield curves.
The technique we'll use is
Principal Component Analysis(PCA).
This is one of the most important
dimension reduction techniques
in multivariate data analysis.
The key mathematical principle
underlying PCA
is the spectral theorem
from linear algebra.
It states that any real symmetric
end by end matrix Q
can be decomposed as shown here
into the product of A
which is an orthogonal matrix
whose columns
are the normalized Eigen vectors
of Q.
They from an orthonormal basis
of R-n.
And L which is the diagonal matrix
containing the Eigen values of Q
we'll always assume without
loss of generality
that these eigen values are ordered
in this decreasing sense
and times A-transpose.
Now let X be an n-dimensional
random vector
with mean denoted by μ
and co variance matrix denoted by Q.
Note that the co variance is a symmetric
and positive semi definite matrix.
We can think of X as being
high dimensional
and is large, it could be a model
for the shape of the yield curve.
In this figure I illustrate
the case where the dimension is 2.
We see the mean vector μ
and this ellipse indicates
that the support of the vector X
is somewhat scattered
with the shape.
Formally speaking, this ellipse
is a level set of the co variance
matrix acting as a quadratic form
on R-2.
The spectral theorem applied
to the co variance matrix Q
gives us
the matrices A and L.
L is diagonal with the eigen values
which are non negative on
the diagonal,
and A stacks the eigen vectors
of Q
as normalized column vectors
a-1 up to a-n.
a-1 corresponding to the
largest eigen value
is giving us the largest
variability of X.
The principal component transform
of X
is given by projecting X
onto these eigen vectors.
In other words, we get
the component Y-i by projecting
the de-centred μ
onto the eigen vector a-i.
We call Y-i the ith principal
component of X
and we call a-i the ith vector
of loadings of X.
In matrix notation, these rates
are shown here.
We can re express X in terms
of its principle components
and that reads like this here.
As we see in this figure here
Y-1 is now capturing
the major variability of X and Y-2
is what remains.
Indeed this is confirmed
on the following page
one can formally show,
and that is an elementary exercise,
that the principal components have
mean 0
and they have a co variance matrix
which is diagonal.
It is actually equal to L.
That means
The principal components
are uncorrelated
and have variances given by
'λ-i's.
Because the 'λ-i's are ordered
it follows that Y-1 has
maximal variance
among all standardized linear
combinations of X
as shown here.
Going on
Y-2 has maximal variance among
all such linear combinations
which are orthogonal to A-1,
the first eigen vector.
And generally speaking
Y-i has maximal variance
among all such linear combinations
which are orthogonal to the first
i-1 linear combinations.
Observe that the sum of all
variances
of all the components X-i
is preserved under the principal
component transformed.
If we thus choose a number K which
is smaller than N,
and sum up the first 'λ-i's
from 1 to K,
and hold this against the sum of
all the eigen values,
we thus obtain
the amount of variability
in X
explained by the first K principle
components.
As such, we could think of X being
an N-dimensional model
for the yield curve, or the daily
changes of the yield curve.
If then the first K principle
components
explain a significant amount of
variability in X,
it is appropriate to approximate X
by the first K principle components
as shown here.
This is now a lower dimensional
model
which however captures
the variability of the original
model quite well.
The loadings a-1to a-k
are in turn, the main components of
the stochastic yield curve movements.
Before we look into an example,
Let us recall the sample analog
of what we just did
for the random variable X.
Assume we have a time series
of observations
that we stack into the matrix X
whose T-th column
is a sample realization
of a random vector X(t).
We assume that this random vector
X(t)
is distributed as X
with mean μ and co variance
matrix Q.
We then estimate the mean vector
of X
by the empirical mean
of the data
and the co variance matrix Q by the
empirical n x n co variance matrix
as shown here.
Applying the spectral theorem
to the empirical co variance matrix
gives us the empirical counter parts
eigen values λ and
eigen vectors â.
indicated now with hats.
The sample principal component
decomposition of X
is then given as shown here
with the empirical principal
components y
and the loadings â-i.
These empirical principal components
are uncorrelated again by construction.
The empirical mean and
co variance matrix
μ̂ and Q̂ are standard estimates
for the true parameters μ and Q
if the observations of X(t) are
serially uncorrelated
as shown here.
If this kind of stationarity of
the time series X(t) is in doubt
the standard practice is to differentiate
and to consider the increments.
We are now ready for the example
and consider monthly changes
of the yield curve
of the Swiss government bonds
over the ten years from August 2005
until July 2015.
For 8 times to maturities τ-i
ranging from 2 years up to 30 years,
running the PCA on this time series
gives us the following first
3 yield curve loadings.
Remember each loading is a
vector with 8 components
and we'll represent the vector
as a function
with values given by its components..
So the first loading
is this black line.
The second loading is the
blue line,
and the third loading
is the red line.
If we look at their shapes,
we see that the first loading
is roughly flat.
It affects the parallel shifts
and can thus be dubbed the level.
The second loading is upward
sloping
It affects the tilting of the
yield curve
and the third is hump-shaped, it
affects the flexing of the yield curve.
It has become common to speak
of these shapes
as level, slope, and curvature
of the yield curve.
The explained variance of these
first 3 principle components
is as shown here.
The first principle component
explains
roughly 77% of the variance,
the second explains 18%,
the third explains 3%.
In sum, the first three principle
components
explain more than 98% of the
variance of the yield curve.
As a consequence
the yield curve (movements)
can be approximated
by a linear combination of the
first three loadings
level, slope, curvature,
with small relative error.
In other words,
a 2 or 3 factor model
will do a very good job in fitting
the time series of the yield curve.