Once made more intelligible,
the global rationales appear
to be combining and interacting
as a vortex of partially
contradictory projects.
It is easy to detect
the role of big actors,
such as transnational companies,
or the states.
What we will see now is that small actors,
as small as ordinary individuals,
do bring a major contribution
to the shaping of today's inhabited space,
including, and perhaps all the more,
at the global scale.
Individuals matter.
Let's see how.
In the World are the individuals.
The apparently smallest operators
are powerful spatial actors.
Let's see how they can be.
We will first retrace the slow emergence
of the individual in society.
Then, we’ll more specifically focus
on the spatial dimensions
of the individual actor.
And finally, we'll connect individuals
with contemporary global issues.
The individual has emerged
as a major spacial actor
with his or her spatial capital
and spatial strategies.
How?
This is a long story.
The capability of a simple and single
individual to become an actor–
that is, an operator endowed
of strategic intelligence –
begins faraway, back in the past.
However, for millennia,
most individuals had
practically no leeway,
and were totally dependent
from the group they belonged to,
and from the role society
assigned to this group.
The process of emancipation
of the individual
clearly began in Europe at the end
of the Medieval period,
and became visible
within the 18th century bourgeoisie.
We must wait for the early 20th century
in Europe and North America
to see the rise of a middle class,
whose characteristics
are precisely not to be a class,
in the meaning that
Karl Marx gave to this word.
The capacity of arbitration
in strategic choices
is provided by a growing
material and cultural affluence
that this group progressively experienced.
Beyond its economic dimension,
this evolution gives the individuals
the opportunity to decide
on their own in fields
that were traditionally
predetermined by communal -
family, territory, religion,
social status, gender, or age - rationales.
A contemporary individual is a worker,
soldier, voter, consumer,
state-protected person,
citizen, self-biographer,
versatile actor,
inhabitant.
The end of the 19th century
and the beginning of the 20th
meant in the West
the advent of the individual worker
because of industrialization,
and the individual voter
thanks to democracy.
With Fordism and the welfare state,
the last two thirds of the 20th century
made the individual a consumer,
whilst marketing embedded
this major change
in the daily life of companies.
It was also a moment when,
in all types of biologically
defined groups –
e.g. women, men, young people,
children, elderly people -
the right to be an individual
was established,
and where discriminations
based on intentional practice -
sexual practices and lifestyles -
or on imposed attributes -
ethnic origins, age,
gender, or handicaps -
were questioned.
All these events are entirely social
and involve other roles
society processes in the economic,
as well as in the political sphere.
But in spite of a huge
pressure to turn persons -
for example, conditioning of
consumption practices,
the continuation of unequal
industrial relations inside companies,
and on the job market -
the ordinary individuals have more
leeway than they used to have before.
This can be measured
through economic rationales -
purchasing power -
and non-economic rationales -
knowledge, mobility, citizenship -
that have substantial
geographical components.
The result is the emergence
of the individual as a significant actor.
And this is all the more pronounced
in societies where, in spite
of an uneven development,
people are benefiting from
a relatively equal distribution of health,
mobility, education,
and other public goods.
In emerging countries, mostly in Asia -
and in a more contradictory way,
in Latin America -
the rapid eruption
of a substantial middle class
of hundreds of millions of people,
whose members are capable of making
strategic arbitrations of their lifetimes,
is a major event in World history.
The Internet opened up an even
more encompassing universe
where individuals’ expectations
are no longer evaluated by surveys,
or market studies -
or not only.
They turned themselves into
producers, inventors, and actors
of the discourses that
talk about themselves.
The massive eruption of blogs
is probably the best expression
of this emergence
with its contradictions,
instability, and no doubt, illusions,
but also its potential capacity
to impose itself on the
market of communication.
Being an actor doesn't mean
being a big actor,
but being able to define and implement
strategic objectives
in a given environment.
What's striking is that the kind of goals
targeted by the different
individuals throughout the World
is converging.
And in spite of huge differences in power,
little folks hold up their heads
next to the big ones
in the domains which really
matter the most for an individual--
that is, long-term security,
self-affirmation,
the capability of developing
a personal development,
and of attaining an actual
social recognition.