As we've said in the first session,
human bodies have three
major spatial characteristics.
First, they are multisensorial sensors.
Secondly, they are mobile
in contrast with some objects
and environments they interact with.
And finally, they're vulnerable.
They can be destroyed
either by natural causes
or social operators, at the risk
of the annihilation of their ‘inhabitant’
that is, the human being.
We can then consider the human body
as the primary environment of the self.
It is an environment in the dual sense
that it conditions the actors agency
and is simultaneously
modifiable by this actor.
Our psyche is made possible
by the existence
of our body and especially by our brain.
However, we know how important
ourselves’ feedback is on our body,
the psychosomatic dimension
of illness is now identified as crucial
and placebos seem to figure
among the most efficient medicines.
My body preconditions me
but I can change my body too.
Given this body is a multisensorial,
mobile and fragile device,
it constitutes a major component
of our spatial style.
Although it is not technically
unthinkable, it is difficult for us
to imagine a body-free way of life.
Our spatiality is, at least so far,
profoundly impacted
by the fact that our body operates
as a pervasive, invasive mediator
in our relationship to the outer world.
One of the most significant aspects
of what is often called
the digital revolution,
is that we can more easily keep our body
off an increasing part of our activities,
including those that require interactions
with objects or other humans.
The huge importance of large spectrum
sex-oriented individual performances
that take place on the web is
particularly intriguing.
This tendency towards
the de-embodying of interactions
helps us understand,
through its opposite,
how critical the presence of bodies is
to define the uniqueness of public space.
We'll examine this point in session five.
Let's keep in memory, anyway,
the simple fact
that human bodies are not alone,
but often in interaction
with other human bodies.
In his work, namely his famous book,
‘The Hidden Dimension’, published in 1971,
Edward T. Hall proposed as early as 1963,
the following definition of ‘proxemy’:
In this perspective,
inter-body distances are to be considered
at least according
to two different scales:
First, at their level,
either contact, remoteness,
convergence, or divergence,
border or a continuum between bodies.
Second, at the societal scale.
Hall, and other scholars,
have tried to identify
contact and non-contact societies,
and this empirical field has still
to be seriously documented.
As Erving Goffman has eloquently shown,
the arrangement of bodies
is strongly related to the general
organization of society,
and space turns out to be
an excellent intellectual vehicle
to explore individual
society relationships.
With and beyond the bodies,
there is a spatial dimension
to this emergence
of the individual actor.
Let's introduce the notion
of spatial capital.
Spatial capital is a species
of social capital,
non reducible to other species.
When using spatial practice
it provides social value
by offering competence in their relations
to spaces and spatialities.
This competence is obtained
through both heritages of
the experience of places
or geographical practices,
and capability: the aptitude
to manage new spatial situations.
Spatial capital is a significant component
of an actor’s social capital
and can be exchanged with other capitals.
A space may have spatial capital too,
in terms of stock and flows.
For example, a city
can take advantage of its location
and develop its relations
with other spaces.
It can also foster its attractiveness
towards various spatial actors.
By putting forward the idea
that there is not one,
but at least three types of capitals
to define the social position
of an individual,
Pierre Bourdieu opened up a discussion
that can serve to explore the complexity
of sociological contexts.
The notion of spatial capital is located
within this perspective.
It allows the taking account
of an integration
of both stocks of experience
and acting capacities.