We've seen in Session 2
that the construction
of a World society is at stake
in the current globalization process.
We've equally seen in this session
that the emergence of individual actors
paves the way to a novel,
post-communal era:
a society of individuals.
If we combine these two
statements, we'll obtain:
emergence of actors as individuals,
society of individuals
plus globalization, World-society,
equal World-society of individuals.
The individual and the World
entertain a strong emerging relationship
to the detriment of communal allegiances.
In such ways, the individuals
make their mark
on the stage of the World’s globalization.
Conversely, the individual
as a relevant social reality
is also at stake in this event.
The globalized individual,
is not the same individual
who developed in Europe
and in North America
during the 19th and the 20th centuries.
The individual is an active operator
in the globalization process,
especially through their mobility,
and their practice of telecommunication.
However, this process is
simultaneously changing their nature.
The notion of identity may help
an understanding of what's happening.
Norbert Elias was the first author
to associate,
for fundamental theoretical reasons,
the emergence of the individual
and globalization.
In a society of individuals,
the individual became
the primary actor of globalization.
Following Elias, the society
of individuals
and the World-society are in fact
one and the same thing.
It's true that there can be
a society of individuals,
as distinct from communal societies,
at other levels than the world.
However, on the one hand,
globalization contributes to relativizing
the national, infra-national, or even
trans-national levels
at which communal ties have operated.
On the other hand,
and in a symmetrical fashion,
the World presents itself
as a space of freedom
open to new modes of organization
in which individual logics
can assert themselves.
However, let's say that these types
of statements do not validate
methodological individualism, or radical
interpretations of the liberal legacy.
Saying that the role
and weight of individuals
is increasing doesn't imply
that society is losing its relevance.
On the contrary,
in ‘Gemeinschaft’-type societies,
communal groups not only take in hand
the destinies of individuals,
but also every single aspect
of social solidarity.
By contrast, in systems
with strong individuals,
social relations are expressed
through a multitude
of institutions - state or non-state -,
such as
social security, education,
political life, and so on.
This appears everywhere,
in the developed world,
including the United States,
where it is only
the classical, European-style
polarity towards the state
that is relatively diminished.
It is thus logical that the
globalized individual
can no longer be
the same individual as the one
that slowly emerged from the heart
of social configurations
that structurally limited its role.
The geopolitical state,
the most accomplished communal structure,
consumed and destroyed
the life of its subjects,
while imposing brutal limits
to personal fulfillment.
At the same time,
however,
the emergence of the
welfare state,
and the establishment
of a democracy
that was explicitly designed
as a response
to the ‘blood tax’ provided
by ordinary inhabitants
offered dramatically new opportunities
for the emergence
of individual autonomy.
The new times of individual identities
are prospering
with this relativization of allegiances
and of the scales of these allegiances.
We then can call alter-identities
the global individual's mode
of identification.
The encounter between
a theoretical hypothesis
about the empowerment
of individuals
and the observation of
a historically-situated, empirical reality
leads to suggest that the notion
of alter-identity -
in Latin, ‘alter’ means ‘other’ -
signifies both the hybridization of
otherness and identity,
as well as an alternative way to deal
with the usual ways
of managing their relations of the self
with the others.
Said differently, what this
term is about is simultaneously
the us-them, and the me-you couples.
Beyond the abundance and richness
of theoretical debates
about idenitites in geography,
it may be argued
that the alter-identity framework
can be a useful boost
and can allow us to go beyond
notions of intersectionalism
or situatedness,
which appear to be
just a refinement of the
classical structuralist perspective.
In ‘Oneself as Another’,
in 1992, Paul Ricoeur
analyzed two different types of identity:
‘mêmeté’(sameness) and ‘ipséité’ (selfness).
In the first case,
a being whose essential features
remain identical forever,
the fixedness and differentiation
towards another is fundamental.
In the second case,
the identification process
constructs itself through
an iterative dynamic
between an individual
and the outer world.
Even though this reflection
was formulated by Ricoeur
without reference to history
and to recent evolution
of contemporary societies,
it's arguable that ‘ipséité’
individual psyches
is more developed today.
The decline of automatic
allegiances creates hybrids
combining ‘Gemeinschaft’ (communal)
and ‘Gesellschaft’(individual)-type elements.
In fact, even if this occurs
in a certain state of confusion,
and even if
spectacular communal movements
such as: Fundamental Christianity,
Radical Islamism,
European, North
or South American Nationalisms,
and African ethnic conflicts
occupy the front stage,
the progressive emancipation
from non-chosen
and irreversible group allegiances
is clearly the major event.
This great crossing from a world
to another represents a major issue
for the anthropology of hybridization.
Increases in the individuals’ leeway,
in the face of their environments’
constraints and resources,
affect the very construction of identity.
This evolves into
two converging directions.
A more marked lifetime
self-transformability
and an increase of intentionality
in the dynamic of the psyche.
Contemporary notions of identity appear
less opposed to a reflexive consciousness
and to the kind of ambitious projects
thereby made possible.
As far as their social capital allows
them to make strategic choices,
individuals can define their
expectations in different ways.
Those that make them move,
for example,
towards various projects
of personal development,
as well as those that pertain
to the field of conservation,
of resistance to what they see as
vital social benefits.
They can be self- or family-centered,
with various family size and values
or conversely a matter of
professional or voluntary involvement.
And all those orientations
can be hosted by the same individual,
simultaneously or successively.
Identity is no longer
an a-priori condition,
but tends to become
a permanent form of self-construction.
Identities are provisional stabilizations,
which evolve in relation
to the pace of the
dis-equilibrating dynamics
acceptable by a given personality.
These imbalances and the risks
they generate are increasingly understood
as an inevitable counterpart
of the supplementary degrees of freedom
that the individuals have acquired
in the fabrication of themselves.
In this context,
the spatial components of identity
are also logically touched upon.
‘Here’ and ‘there’ cannot be defined
once and for all anymore.
Classically, geographers conceived
of the identity tie between the individual
and a place as univocal.
‘To everybody, their place’ is a postulate,
often translated into the metaphor
of rootedness.
It is an obvious identification
between the tree and the soil,
it's natural and easy
to be taken for granted.
The near and the local would then
govern identity.
However, the appropriation
of multiple geographical places,
through mobility or by other means,
throws this model into question.
All anchoring places
can possibly be good clients
for an identification carried out
by an individual,
due as much to its spatial extension,
as to the complexity of its determinants.
the ordinary actors’ spatial system
has a comparable, or more often,
a superior size to the society
in which they principally evolves.
Individual identities may thus,
not merely be seen as little things
placed inside a big box.
They may also be considered
as organized and orientated layers
of space, possessing a specific dynamic,
as indeed, geography and sociology
have convincingly demonstrated since
the first works of the Chicago School
in urban research
in the early 20th century.
This leads to the proposition,
according to which,
‘here’ does not correspond
to a single stable substance.
On the contrary, there are many
‘heres’ in motion, which,
when taken together, contribute
to an individual's relation to space.
Any type of place can become
a referent for identity.
‘Here’ can thus be defined
as a spatial component of identity.
In a symmetrical way, ‘there’
could be said to constitute
the spatial component of otherness.
Alter-identity then seems to be
a phenomenon for which globalization
is the most favorable environment
for its emergence and development.
The dynamic of the relation between
identity and otherness,
is, at the same time, a consequence
and a component of globalization.
Thinking beyond this, however,
certain characteristics of globalization
make possible the appropriation
by individuals of a bigger,
but, paradoxically,
more easily penetrable World.
By reducing the magnitude
of differences,
by creating new singularities
at every scale,
and by confirming big cities
as concentrates of the World,
globalization offers an
enlarged palette for experiencing
this setting in motion of
individual identities.
In this context, anthropologists
have signaled
the appearance of diverse combinations
of identification processes,
fabricated with bricks of various nature.
This is the end of exoticism,
with a triumph of complex patchworks,
hybrids, and cross-breeds.
The notion of environment,
in the sense of an encompassing
reality in interaction with realities
it encompasses, as we've seen in
Session 1, is useful here.
The description of the World
as a differentiated space
is then passed on to the study
of diverse environments,
articulated in various ways
amongst each other,
and not necessarily
in a nesting mode,
but also through co-spatiality
within a unique place.
The possible agency in these different
environments constitutes
the dashboard of individuals,
who are yet also
components of these environments.
Intensity and speed of dynamics,
then, depend less
on the reciprocal influence
of the environment, taken as a whole,
than on the capacity of actors
to activate
the elements of one environment
that could serve their projects,
potentially achieved
in another environment.
The world of individuals is,
thus, per excellence,
any kind of place,
including the World itself.
From the body to the planet
the individual is actively present;
he or she is a privileged courier
of spatialities,
namely by, his or her ability
to cross borders,
beyond the terrible dangers
that this may imply, and the fact that
these crossings are not always desired,
but often forced.
Similarly, the capability to jump
from one scale to another,
or from one spatial layer
to another, is remarkable in itself
and because of the powerful impact
it has on social interactions,
and cultural hybridization.
This is not a completely new reality,
but what's new is that this issue
is present, more or less, and in
a highly uneven fashion
for every individual,
and not only to a tiny minority
of great travelers
or great intellectuals.
The world of individuals
was practiced even during the Holocaust,
in spite of its planned and obscene
extermination of entire populations
and its negation of the existence
of individuals as human beings.
Imre Kertész knew how to describe
a life where the loss of control
over one's own body in no way meant
a lack of activity,
but involved a life dominated by an
interminable slowness,
punctuated by little choice.
For Kertész, ‘fatelessness’ means
having the power to act
and to have the influence
on the future of one's existence
without everything being decided
beforehand.
The paradox lies in the fact that
this horizon was constructed
in a world where freedom,
was, nevertheless, radically banned.
This is a power to move forward
‘step by step’, as he says,
if only to decide about whether
it's best to take the bus or the tram
to go to Auschwitz.
Kertész blames those who give up,
pretending that ‘things happen’,
that is to say, fall upon us
without having been there for nothing.
‘Thinking after Auschwitz’ is saying that
in a society of individuals,
even when crushed by a brutal
and violently imposed weight,
the individual can resist,
and, as incredible as it can appear,
can live intensely, as such,
and not only in their own mind.
If we follow Kertész's leading thread,
we finally understand that,
in these camps, the effort
to make the self exist
doesn't consist of plunging
into the horror,
to pull from it a certain grandeur,
but, paradoxically,
in seeking against all odds
to create an unlikely banality,
which permits an access,
if only for brief moments,
to rhythms, landmarks,
temporary identifications
and pleasant or unpleasant
micro-events which contribute
to build a marvelous daily grayness.
We have noticed that globalization
clearly has an economic dimension,
but not only.
All aspects of social life
are present
in this invention of
a World-scale space.
It's a dangerous mistake
to reduce globalization to flows of money
or to the expansion of companies.
The arrangement of social groups,
politics, science, art or technology,
are also at stake,
in all stages of globalization.
And the role of individuals
helps us not to forget
this multi-dimensional aspect
of global dynamics.
Since late 2010, the Arab Spring,
especially in Tunisia and Egypt,
has shown a new kind
of political movement,
based on individual-driven,
reversible groups.
The 2009 pacific protests in Iran have
sometimes been called ‘Tweeter Revolution’.
In democratic countries, de-aligned
political movements:
‘Los Indignados’ in Spain, ‘Occupy’ in the
United States, in 2011 and 2012,
have shown comparable features.
In Turkey, the 2013 ‘Taksim-Gezi Park’
protest movement
made visible a new side
of political agency
and transcended
the common partisan splits.
In Ukraine, the ‘Maidan Movement’,
which succeeded in overthrowing
the President and his regime,
was mostly composed
of self-organized, self-assigned people,
coming from different
socioeconomic and geographic layers
of the Ukrainian society.
In the case of the Arab Spring,
whose impact is ambivalent,
we can identify different types
of processes and outcomes.
In different cases, the importance of this
new kind of movement is indisputable.
In this perspective, we can
construct a theoretical framework
to elaborate a sociology of globalization,
and of the global society
which takes into account
both the global and other scales.
No individual, of course, has a
100% grip on their own life,
and the weight of economic, political,
or cultural limitations
to their freedom of self-invention
should definitely not be forgotten.
What can be said, however,
is firstly that between zero and 100,
there are many interesting intermediate
situations that deserve to be explored.
Secondly, we can say that this mix
between freedom and constraint
cannot be described by a single aspect,
such as, for instance, income.
The relation between the individual
and the World, actually
as it can be observed,
suggests that the interpretation
of social ties should be reformulated
to integrate their spatial dimension.
This is true in any
geographic configuration.
In fact, globalization gives a new
significance to spatial competences.
This table shows the relative dependence
between economic capital
and spatial capital in a
globalizing World.
It illustrates how people with little
economic capital,
but much spatial capital -
the ‘plugged-In’, for example;
international migrants
who already have experience
of otherness and often benefit
from consistent support from,
for example, relatives and from
fellow countryman and women
at their port of entry, may often
develop a winning strategy
of social ascent, while those who
are here called the ‘entrenched’,
for example, workers with a protected
status in a developed country
are, when faced with globalization,
poor geographical actors
despite their relatively privileged
economic position.
Let's go back to a table we had
introduced in the first session.
As we saw, countries, that is, territories
surrounded by clear border lines,
are by far not the only
observable situation.
Networks are very common,
as well as fuzzy limits.
Moreover, since they include
an infinity of parts,
territories have been mere utopias
for a long period
and states are forced to spend
huge amounts of money
to turn borders into efficient
lock-out fences.
By the way, the practical way
to create territories
is generally the construction of dense,
thick networks.
Networks are precisely effective
in each dimension
of social life and for each actor.
Spacial agency, what we've called
spatiality
is essentially made of networks,
and in networks.
Networks are typically individual spaces.
In this perspective, we should give
particular attention to ‘rhizomes’.
This term is derived from Gilles Deleuze
and Félix Guattari's notion developed
in their book, ‘A Thousand Plateaus’,
first published in 1980.
A rhizome is a borderless network.
This concept expresses the individual's
capability to both develop
weak ties with unknown people -
‘friends’ in digital social networks -
and largely accept the
transitivity of these ties.
My acquaintances' acquaintances
are my acquaintances too.
That's why in small worlds
where interaction systems are random,
unlikely encounters often happen, like
in the book by David Lodge, ‘Small Worlds’.
Transforming a network into
a territory (that is,
adding continuity, contiguity,
and exhaustivity),
or even a place (a space freed
from relevant distances),
is not a trivial or an easy task.
It requires resources and determination.
Is the World becoming a territory
and a place too?
Its inhabitants only
will eventually decide.