Following Week 3, are you ready
to start considering
what type of treatment technologies
are appropriate in your city?
Important concepts that you
learned this week
for evaluating appropriate
treatment technologies
include the level of technology
development established
transferring or innovative.
We have grouped technologies
as established
if there is enough operating
experience, the design considerations
and operations and maintenance
requirements are established
and can be recommended.
We have grouped technologies
as transferring,
if knowledge is currently
being transferred
from other sectors like waste
water treatments.
And we have grouped technologies
as innovative
if they show promise but are in
the research and development phase.
These distinctions are very
important because they will have
a direct impact on implementation
and the required
level of management and partnerships
for scaling up,
such as private partner partnerships
or with research institutes.
Another important concept
that you learned is about linking
treatment technologies
by their treatment objectives.
Frequently a treatment chain
will include a combination
of treatment technologies, depending
on the overall treatment objectives.
This was also illustrated in
the design example
of the Lubigi Faecal Sludge
Treatment Plant in Kampala, Uganda.
This is why in the engineering
design approach
the first steps include defining
treatment objectives
so that you know what you
are designing
treatment technologies for.
Once you have defined treatment end
goals or resource recovery options
then you can simultaneously consider
the treatment objectives necessary
to achieve them together with
the level of technology development
which is important for the associated
level of required management.
This week you learned about
treatment processes
for six different established
technologies,
operations and maintenance
requirements and design parameters.
These were settling
and thickening tanks,
unplanted drying beds,
planted drying beds,
co-composting,
cotreatment with waste water
and effluent treatment technologies.
In Week 5,  we will continue
to learn more about
treatment technologies, specifically
technologies that are in
the transferring and innovative
categories.
It is always equally as important
to consider the fate
of effluent from treatment processes
and how to safely manage it.
Starting at the level of on-site
containment technologies
from the supernatant
and septic tanks,
up to centralized treatment
facilities.
What treatment technologies do you
think are appropriate in your city?
Can you think of any that
you would consider established
that we did not include here?
Please add your thoughts on
the discussion forum and please
also do not forget to visit
the additional resources
on the platform website.
So now that you have
an understanding
of faecal sludge management,
treatment objectives,
and fundamentals
and treatment technologies
in Week 4 we're going
to switch gears
and focus on an integrated
approach.
How to incorporate all of
the design variables
and planning and management aspects
that are necessary
to create an enabling environment.
A groundwork that includes legal,
organizational, financial,
political and cultural aspects.
You will learn about a planning
frameworks,
why it's important to fit
participatory stakeholder
processes within traditional
project cycles
and to engage and work together
with stakeholders.
Other concepts will include
understanding the initial context,
setting up legal and regulatory
frameworks
to define clear roles
and responsibilities
How to consider different models
of financial transfers
that are necessary at each step
of the service chain.
And incorporating management
and operations
and maintenance concerns
from the beginning
of the project planning,
and finally,
how to compare the equivalent cost
of different technology options.
Thanks for joining,
see you next week.