So, following week four,
are you ready to engage
your city more in creating
an enabling environment?
Engineers and practitioners
must wear many hats
as designers, planners, managers,
advocates, lobbyists
community liaisons.
If we want to ensure
that the necessary
and inter related legal,
organizational
financial, political
and cultural aspects
that all need to be in place for
effective fecal sludge management
have been accounted for.
and these factors are all included
as design variables in our approach.
it is also important to remember
that fecal sludge management
on it's own is not
a stand-alone solution
it needs to be incorporated into
a city-wide approach to sanitation
This week you've learned
the importance of assessing
and understanding
the initial situation
in specific context
as sanitation solutions can be
very heterogeneous.
Not only between
countries and cities
but also within cities themselves.
A thorough assessment ensures
that solutions are tailored
to meet the actual needs,
build on what is existing
and takes into account the context
specific strengths and constraints.
These preliminary steps are required
to understand
the existing situation
before you can start defining
the problem that needs to be solved.
One example is site selection.
Due to the difficulty
of obtaining land
in urban areas, that is expensive,
and not readily available
it will already affect
technology selection
as treatment options
that are land intensive
tend to be much less expensive,
whereas treatment options
that don't require a lot of land
tend to be much more expensive.
So it's important also to ensure
that this site is accessible
so it will really be used.
An integrated planning approach
can help you link all
your design variables
into standard project phases
and helps you to manage when
and where to consider each of them.
Also, incorporating participatory
processes within traditional
project cycles, helps to ensure
commitment and ownership during
during implementation and operation.
And success is enhanced by
more effective management schemes
better institutional setups and
integration of the private sector.
Integrating stakeholders
and understanding their interest
and influences should be carried
out through the entire project
as it is a continuous
and iterative process.
For more information
on an integrated approach
to city wide sanitation,
please refer to the (INAUDIBLE) MOOC.
Planning and design of sanitation
systems and technologies.
you learned the importance
of setting up legal
and regulatory frame works
for fecal sludge management
and introducing enforcement mechanisms.
This is necessary to ensure that
regulation and enforcement
of public health and environmental
standards occurs.
As fecal sludge management
is an essential component
of urban sanitation
it needs to be included
in national policies
and also have clear institutional
roles at the local level
to ensure people
take responsibility.
Also, considering different models
of financial transfers
will help to formalize this sector
and make it financially sustainable
and could include incentives
as a method of transition
to new management
models in the short term.
Financial transfers include capital
and operations and maintenance costs
from the household level
to collection and transport
service providers
to treatment plants
and resource recovery.
These are a combination of
public and/or private parties
payments for service,
or discharge fees
taxes, tariffs
and licences.
you also learn the importance
of incorporating management
concerns from the beginning
of the project planning.
Management aspects need to be linked
to decision on technology options.
This is especially important
when evaluating levels
of established, transferring
and innovative technologies.
It is also important to ensure
operations and maintenances
built into the ongoing
project budget
and to ensure demands are
appropriate to the local context.
All too many treatment plants
have failed due to lack
of operations and maintenance.
And lastly financial considerations
are obviously
a very important variable
at the decision making process
selecting different
management options.
This is complicated with
many technologies because
they are not yet
examples of cost data
and it requires many assumptions.
Equivalent cost comparisons
can be used to compare the capital
and operating costs
of different technologies
with revenue generated from
resource recovery incorporated
as a positive under operating costs.
What design variables did you learn
about this week that
you did not know
about before?
Do you think there are any
important ones for your city
that we did not cover?
Please contribute your thoughts to
the discussion on the forum website
and also visit
the additional resources
to learn more about the topic.
Now we are entering
the final week of the MOOC
where you will learn about
the current status
of transferring and
innovative technologies
for collection,
transport, treatment
and resource recovery
of fecal sludge.
This is a very exciting week
as it will provide you
with more of an idea
the ways in which this field
is rapidly changing.
Then we will provide you with
an example of the case study
of Durban, South Africa
a city that was awarded
the Stockholm water prize
for their innovative adapted
and integrated approach
to fecal sludge management
and city-wide sanitation.
Thanks for joining,
see you next week.