How can we contribute
to establishing an affordable
faecal sludge collection service
for neighborhoods like this?
Where sanitation needs
are mostly met by pit latrines.
They produce sludge
with a high viscosity.
That is difficult to be pumped,
and accessed by vacuum trucks.
In this module,
we will look at the few advances
that  work toward making sludge
collection in this context possible.
Following this module,
you will be able to list
innovative collection technologies,
name examples of how the design
and operation of on-site sanitation
technologies can ease collection,
and explain
what container-based sanitation is.
Faecal sludge can have a very high
solid content,
a high viscosity.
As shown here in Lusaka, in Zambia.
Which makes
collection vacuum trucks,
or vacutug,
not possible.
In addition,
sludge with these characteristics
is often located in areas
where they're difficult to access
because of the topography,
settlement density,
or poor road conditions.
In the following,
we will look at three technologies
that were developed for such sludge
that has a high solid content
and viscosity.
Searching the internet,
you'll find other technologies
such as the MAPET
or the manually operated
diaphragm pump
that could be suitable
for your situation.
The Rammer is one example
of such a technology.
and was developed based on operation
experience with the Gulper
in several countries.
The Rammers therefore
also referred to as the Gulper II.
This slide shows the Gulper
and Rammer next to each other.
In contrast to the Gulper,
where the sludge is sucked
through a cylinder
the Rammer lifts sludge
with a raising cylinder.
The Rammer is an improvement
of the Gulper in several ways.
Firstly, the connecting rods
are located outside of the Rammer.
And it has a lever on,
which makes operations easier.
Secondly,
the cylinder of the Rammer
can be extended up to 3 meters.
Whereas it's only 1.5 meter
were possible with the Gulper.
This means that sludge
can be collected
from deeper onsite
sanitation technologies.
This video shows the Rammer
in operation in Kampala.
A third benefit of the Rammer
is that a hosepipe can be connected
to the Rammer,
which makes direct lifting
for transport possible,
and increase the protection
of workers.
Another technology that
has been developed
for removal of sludge
with a high viscosity,
is the screw auger,
also called excrevator,
that has been piled among others
in South Africa, Malawi and India.
As shown in this picture,
a screw auger lifts
the sludge with a screw,
that is located in a pipe.
The screw is rotated by a motor
that is located at the top.
As also shown in this picture here,
the excrevator is placed
on a dolly frame
to increase mobility
and accessibility
of onsite sanitation technologies.
This picture shows the excrevator
in operation in Durban.
As you can see,
the outlet of the excrevator
is connected to a hose
which transport it
to a collection container.
The third technology that we would
like to introduce in this module
is the evac.
Shown in this picture.
It is a small vacuum pump located
on a two-wheel trolley frame.
The sludge is collected in the wide
vacuum cylinder.
Once these (INAUDIBLE)
is full,
the sludge has to be removed
from the cylinders
before sludge collection
can be continued.
This picture shows the evac
in operation in Kigali, in Rwanda.
As you can see,
with a similar power compared
to a small vacuum truck
the evac is much smaller
and still mobile for use in areas
with a difficult topography,
poor road conditions
or narrow lanes.
A problem for the operation
of all these technologies,
is solid waste
that is frequently disposed of
in onsite sanitation technologies.
Screens at the inlet
of these technologies,
such as shown here for the Rammer,
can prevent damaging
of the collection technology.
But do lead to clogging
and stop the collection process.
As shown in this video from Kampala,
A metal rod is frequently used
to remove solid waste
before using sludge
collection technologies.
Or as shown here,
from Durban, it needs to be removed
by shovels.
Removal of solid waste can be
a very time-consuming activity.
Also, the solid waste requires
management following removal,
which is likely contains pathogens
and puts workers,
health and safety at risk.
The disposal of solid waste
into onsite sanitation technologies
is one example of how
the design and operation
of onsite sanitation technologies
can influence sludge collection.
Sludge collection could
for example be improved,
by the implementation of different
drop holes for pit latrines,
that do not allow large pieces
of solid waste to enter the pit.
This shown here in a picture
from Kampala.
In addition,
solid waste should be kept outside
of onsite sanitation technologies,
by implementation
of solid waste management,
or the education of users.
Ultimately, removal of solid waste
before sludge collection
will increase the service fee
the household has to pay
through collection service provider.
This could be a financial incentive
for change.
Next to solid waste,
an access point
to the onsite sanitation technology
can be a constraint for collection.
For pit latrines,
where sludge might get collected
through the drop hole,
the drop hole potential
needs to be increased
which may affect
its future functionality.
This picture shows an example
of how an access point
was integrated
into the design
of a pit latrine in Kampala.
The access point is located here.
And allows easy sludge collection,
without affecting the integrity
and functionality of the structure.
This pit is also
fully lined.
This ensure ground water
protection
and that sludge can be collected
without risking the collapse
of the pit.
Fecal sludge is mostly water,
which is heavy to transport.
Keeping the water outside
of onsite sanitation technologies,
for example in (INAUDIBLE)
dry toilets,
could be another way to facilitate
sludge collection.
If (INAUDIBLE) separating dry toilet
are connected to a collection service
they become referred to
as "container based sanitation".
This is currently being piloted
in several countries,
for example Haiti, Kenya and Ghana.
This picture shows an example
of such an onsite sanitation
technology in Kenya.
The faeces are collected
in the container in the back,
and the urine
in the container at the front.
Every few days,
these containers are then replaced
by empty containers
and transported for treatment.
This picture shows such containers
for replacement and collection
of the full containers in Ghana.
In this module we introduce to three
innovative technologies
that could contribute
to sludge collection
in urban poor areas
with difficult accessibility,
topography,
and with sludge that has
a high solid content and viscosity.
These were the rammer,
the excrevator and the evac.
In addition to these
collection technologies,
keeping solid waste out
of onsite sanitation technologies,
lining, and providing access points
for sludge collection,
examples of how the design
and operation
of onsite sanitation technologies,
can facilitate sludge collection.
Container based sanitation
are an alternative to pit latrines
that are currently being piloted
and could also ease
sludge collection.