We already introduced you
to co-composting
for faecal sludge treatment.
This is a relatively slow process,
and to produce compost, may not
always have a high market value.
In this module
we are going to introduce you
to two new processes,
called vermi and fly composting,
that have the potential
to be quicker
and produce treatment products
with a higher market value.
Such as the black soldier fly
shown behind me.
Following this module,
you will be able to explain
the treatment process and operation
of vermi- and fly larvae composting.
Name advantages and disadvantages
these processes can have
over co-composting.
And discuss important considerations
for the implementation.
Vermi and fly larvae composting
are processes that use
worms and flies
for sludge stabilization
(INAUDIBLE) management
in addition to microorganisms
used in co-composting
Vermi and fly larvae composting
are two processes
that are currently being researched
and piloted for faecal sludge.
Currently, the knowledge
for faecal sludge
is limited to laboratory,
bench scale and pilot scale studies
and most research
has been conducted with faeces.
Faeces can have
very different characteristics
to faecal sludge collected
from pit latrines and septic tanks.
Vermi and fly larvae
composting processes
are being transferred
to faecal sludge
from the treatment
of organic solid waste
which is market waste,
restaurant waste or manures.
For these wastes,
more knowledge and a few examples
of full-scale implementation exists.
Vermi composting, which is also
called worm composting
uses worms for sludge stabilization.
Worms can have (INAUDIBLE)
with faecal sludge
include Eisenia Fetida
which is also called tiger worms
or red wiggler.
And Eudrius Eugenia,
which is also called
the African nightcrawler.
With organic solid wastes,
Lubricus Rubellus is also common.
These worms are selected
for vermi-composting
because they can survive, grow,
feed and reproduce
on a variety
of different feed-stocks
and they grow very quickly.
This is a picture of Eisenia Fetida.
If you would like
to do vermi-composting
and you need worms.
You're likely to find them
in manures or compost.
Once placed in a feed-stock,
such as faecal sludge,
worms start to feed on it
to meet their energy needs,
grow and reproduce.
Anything that the worms
do not take up
during this digestion
process in their gut
they will poop out
as a solid residual
that we call vermi-compost.
Operation of vermi-composting
is commonly in batch or semi-batch.
This means that worms are fed once
with faecal sludge
or a smaller batches every day.
Under favorable
environment or conditions,
worm will directly reproduce
within the waste,
and need to be separated
from the residue
after faecal sludge has been
processed into vermi-compost.
This picture shows
such a batch process
at a research facility
in the Philippines.
In these rectangular boxes,
a mixture of manure,
shredded cornstarch and faeces
are being vermi-composted
with Eisenia Fetida.
Three studies in Mexico,
the Philippines and India,
assess vermi-composting of faecal
sludge collected from septic tanks
and faeces.
These studies highlighted worms
required bedding material
for proper development.
In India,
worms do not lie in faeces without
a bedding material below the faeces,
such as solid compost.
In vermi-composting of solid waste
paper and cardboard
are also commonly used.
Worms also did not feed and survive
on untreated sludge
but required faecal sludge
that was pre-digested.
The research also identified
that high ammonia concentration
faecal sludge can be toxic to worms
and hamper their development.
Let's move to another
fascinating animal use
in faecal sludge treatment.
The black soldier fly.
The black soldier fly
can be found in most temperate
and tropical climates.
In comparison to other flies,
it has the benefit
that it doesn't feed
during its adult life.
This means it will likely not move
between different waste
and sit on waste
that could contain pathogens
and transmit it through environment
which could transmit diseases.
In waste treatment,
black soldier flies
are usually reared in cages
as shown here at a pilot-scale for (INAUDIBLE)
in Nairobi.
In these cages,
flies are kept in conditions
that foster mating
between male and female flies.
Following mating,
female flies like to lay
their eggs in protected place.
To provide such an environment,
treatment operators commonly provide
perforated cardboard
to lay their eggs, as shown here.
This picture shows the egg following
a removal from the cardboard.
On this picture
you can see a few million eggs.
Under favorable
environmental conditions,
within the next three days,
a few million small larvae
with the size around one millimeter
will hatch from these eggs,
and hungry for food.
Once placed
on an organic waste feed-stock,
such as faecal sludge,
the larvae will start processing
this waste for the next weeks,
to meet their energy needs and grow.
As they do not feed
during their adult lives as a fly,
they have a really big appetite
during their life stage as a larvae.
This video shows
the black soldier fly larvae
feeding on faeces during research
in Upsala, Sweden.
Based on bench
and pilot scale testing
in Sweden, Thailand and Kenya,
with faeces and faecal sludge
from septic tanks,
fly larvae can reduce the mass
of sludge during this period
by between 40-50%
based on dry weight.
The feeding of fly larvae
with waste such as faecal sludge,
is commonly done in boxes.
And larvae is either fed once
or every few days.
The boxes and the feeding
are shown here,
at a treatment facility, in China,
where restaurant waste is treated
with black soldier fly larvae.
Based on research
in Sweden and Kenya,
black soldier fly larvae commonly
convert between 10-20% of the sludge
based on dry weight into body mass.
This factor is called
the bio-conversion rate.
In other words,
it means that following
the processing of 1000 kilo
of total solids,
around 100-200 kilo of dried larvae
can be expected.
Are you excited about fly larvae
and vermi-composting?
Here are some
important considerations
that are relevant
for its implementation.
As with other biological processes,
such as co-composting,
that rely on living organisms,
worms and fly larvae only feed,
grow and reproduce
if the suitable environmental
conditions are being provided.
In short, keep your worms
and fly larvae happy.
For example,
both fly larvae and worms
do not like light,
and should be kept
in a shaded place.
They also like environments
with sufficient supplies of oxygen,
and pH, temperature, and humidity
are important environmental factors.
The available literature on the (INAUDIBLE)
organic solid waste
and faecal sludge
suggested a performance
really depending
on feed-stock characteristics
microorganisms,
environmental conditions,
and treatment operations,
and can be really variable.
It therefore best
to determine these parameters
through local bench
and pilot-scale tests
before upscaling.
In this module we introduce you
to vermi and fly larvae composting.
Two new processes that
are currently in research
and being implemented
with faecal sludge
at a bench and pilot-scale.
In these processes,
worms and fly larvae
feed on faecal sludge
and produce animal protein
that has a high market value
in compost.
Based on the current level
of knowledge,
the two processes that achieve
low level pathogen inactivation
in comparison to co-composting
and the compost
and the worm and larvae products
require further treatment.