The number one treatment objective
in faecal sludge management
is always protection
of public health.
Through protecting people
from pathogens that make them sick.
In this module we'll introduce you
to two treatment technologies
that can achieve high levels
of pathogen inactivation:
Ammonia and lime treatment.
Following this module
you will be able to explain
how pathogen inactivation
occurs in ammonia
and lime treatment.
Discuss operational maintenance
requirements of these technologies.
And considerations
for their implementation.
Ammonia treatment
for pathogen inactivation
faecal sludge
is currently in the research
and development phase.
Ammonia treatment relies
on the toxicity of ammonia
to pathogens.
Ammonia can be added
to the faeces in the form of urea.
But this treatment technology
is interesting
because ammonia
can also be provided through urea
that is included in urine.
Nitrogen urine
is in the form of urea,
but which is converted
to ammonia by the urea's enzyme,
that is available
throughout the environment.
Ammonium nitrogen
and ammonia nitrogen
are in equilibrium with each other.
This graph shows
the fraction of nitrogen
that is available as ammonia
as a function of pH and temperature.
As shown in this graph,
by increasing the pH
for example
by the addition of lime or ash,
the ammonia nitrogen
concentration can be increased.
At a pH below 8.5
a mixture of urine and faeces
will still have a lower
ammonia concentration
for pathogen inactivation.
At this pH,
most of the nitrogen
is in the form of ammonia
that is not harmful for pathogens.
An increase in temperature also
increase ammonia concentrations.
Next to the toxicity of ammonia
the high pH
is also additional mechanism
for pathogen inactivation
in an ammonia treatment.
Faecal sludge collected
from septic tanks and pit latrines
is mostly water,
which dilutes the ammonia
and results in low concentrations
to be available
for pathogen inactivation.
Even at an elevated pH.
Loss of ammonia and ammonium
that are volatile
to open manholes and septic tanks,
or drop holes and pit latrines,
also reduce the concentration
of ammonia available
for pathogen inactivation.
In contrast to this type of sludge,
high levels of pathogen inactivation
could be feasible
with faeces and urine
when we lower
the amount of flushing water
and we are in sealed tanks.
In laboratory experiments in Sweden
at 20° C and a pH of 9,
ammonia treatment could
inactivate 99% of Ascaris eggs,
which is the common
Helminths egg in only 24 days.
A decrease in a temperature
and an increase in flush water,
increase desaturation
for the same level
of pathogen inactivation
from several weeks
to several months.
So moving from the laboratory,
how could these results
be used in practice?
One attempt
at the safe sludge project
that is based on the collection
of faeces and urine
without any flush water.
In the first step,
faeces and urine are mixed together
with the contact time of 4 hours,
to convert urea
with the enzyme urease
into ammonium.
Following a (INAUDIBLE) increasing the pH,
which is lime and ash is added
which converts ammonium
into ammonia.
Then this is kept for hours or days
for inactivation of pathogens.
It is important to convert
urea into ammonium
before increasing the pH;
as an increase in pH
inhibits the enzyme urease.
In the laboratory experiments
in the United States,
99% of ascaris eggs were inactivated
through this process.
Such a treatment and process
could be implemented
for pathogen inactivation
in innovative on-site
sanitation technologies
offer treatment following separate
collection of faeces and urine,
As shown here with these jericans
for urine collection,
and a tank for storage,
in Bolivia.
Lime treatment, which is also called
alkaline treatment,
is a common treatment technology
for waste water sludge.
But also has been implemented
full-scale for faecal sludge
for example for the treatment
of septic tank sludge
in the United States
or in the Philippines.
Lime is a fine white powder.
Based on available litterature
on waste water sludge,
the most common form of lime
that is used in lime treatment
is hydrated lime,
or calcium hydroxide.
In lime treatment,
sufficient amount of lime are added
to the faecal sludge
to increase the pH to 12
for several hours to a month.
Such a high pH slows down or stops
biological processes
that are responsive for odors
and it inactivate pathogens.
As discussed before for ammonia treatment,
the increase in pH
also results in the increase
of ammonia concentrations
that can contribute to further
pathogen inactivation.
Lime can be addible to liquid,
sludge, and also sludge following
the watering.
Addition of lime
to more liquid faecal sludge
has the added benefit
it could improve
solid-liquid separation processes.
During laboratory research
that we conducted
together with our research partners
in Dakar,
lime improved dewatering by 90-95%
compared to an untreated control
without lime.
This can reduce the time and space
required for dewatering,
for example
on unplanted drying beds.
The dosage of lime
to adequately raise the pH
is an important design
and operational parameter
for lime treatment.
The average dosage of several
lime treatment applications
in the United States
with septic tank sludge,
and also application in Philippines
was 20% lime per dry mass of sludge.
In one study in Blantyre, Malawi,
addition to 20-35% lime
per dry mass of sludge
was successful
in increasing the pH to 12.
As lime is dosed
as a function of total solids
and they can be variable
and also the chemical
characteristics of sludge
can be variable
that influence lime treatment
it is always important to determine
the required dosage based
on a local sludge characteristic.
This can be done by a simple
bench and pilot scale experiment
where different amounts of lime
are added to faecal sludge
as shown here
in the Philippines.
Following mixing of the lime
and the faecal sludge,
the pH can be monitored over time
with a handheld pH meter.
This picture shows an example
of lime treatment
of a septic tank faecal sludge
in the Philippines.
The workers are adding lime
in a mixing tank
to the faecal sludge in powder form,
or a slurry prepared with water.
Lime is highly corrosive
for infrastructure and equipment
and personal protective equipment
such as safety goggles, boots,
long-sleeve clothes and face masks
should always be worn.
This is because the same process
that increase the pH
in faecal sludge,
also increase the pH
most surface in humans,
such as the skin, eyes and lungs.
Following addition of lime,
thorough mixing is required
to ensure contact
of faecal sludge with lime.
As shown in this picture,
this can be done manually,
but mechanical mixing
can be more effective
and has the potential
to produce higher pH values
at the same lime dosage.
So how effective is lime treatment
in the inactivation of pathogens?
In one study in Blantyre,
and in another study
in Phnom Penh, Cambodia,
additional lime reduced
equal concentrations
below the limits recommended
by the World Health Organization
for use in agriculture.
However, knowledge from lime
treatment of waste water sludge
is (INAUDIBLE) because Helminth eggs
and more persistent bacteria,
treatment may require longer
storage durations at a high pH.
Also the effectiveness
of a pathogen inactivation
will depend on the type
of the pathogen
and the initial concentration
of pathogens in a local context.
It is always important to assess
the inactivation of pathogens
as a function of pH and time
for the local context.
Wrong assumptions can have
a severe public health impact.
Lime treatment has the benefit
that is relatively quick, robust
and effective
for pathogen inactivation.
It also has a small
treatment footprint.
All of these characteristics
also make it suitable
for emergency situations.
However it is important
to consider these benefits
and balance them
with the operating cost,
which are mainly
purchase of the lime.
Price for lime can vary
considerably between countries.
For example, in the Philippines
of price 150-100 dollars per tonne,
in Senegal of 250 dollars per tonne,
and in Malawi of 800 US dollars
per tonne has been reported
in the literature.
Lime treatment inhibits
biological process
in half of the pathogens
by increasing the pH.
It is important to consider that
this process can only be temporary
and pathogen regrowth might occur
if the pH drop below 11.
For example during storage,
transport, or use
of the treatment product.
Pathogen in incubation
only remain safe at a pH of 12.
Another important consideration,
is that lime treatment
does not reduce the sludge volume,
as for example (INAUDIBLE) digestion.
In contrast,
the addition of lime increase
the mass of sludge
that needs to be managed
and disposed.
It is also important to consider
the characteristics of the sludge
following lime treatment
as it can influence
subsequent treatment steps
and resource recovery.
Co-composting, for example,
is based on microorganisms
that inhibited the lime treatment
and the high pH
following lime treatment
may not be beneficial
for all soils.
Lime is also inorganic
and therefore doesn't contribute
to the fuel value,
which means that lime treatment
uses the energy value
for it to recover (INAUDIBLE) solid fuels.
In this module,
we introduced lime
and ammonia treatment,
that are two technologies
for pathogen inactivation.
In both treatment technologies,
the toxicity of ammonia nitrogen
and a high pH
are the main mechanisms
for pathogen inactivation.
The effect of these technologies
for pathogen inactivation
will depend on the type
of concentration of pathogens
the dosage of lime and ammonia
required to produce environments
that are toxic to pathogens,
and the contact time.
For long-term operations
of these treatments
it is important to consider
that both technologies
rely on reliable supply of ammonia
in the form of urine urea and lime.