I hope you have enjoyed this
introduction to fecal sludge
management
and learning about how
to apply some key concepts
a sustainable fecal sludge
management as part of
an integrated approach
to city-wide sanitation.
Certainly by now you already have
a number of thoughts
ideas and opinions
on what important considerations
for sustainable implementation
of fecal sludge management are
and understand how
to address challenges.
In this module, I will highlight
some of the key learnings
from the last five weeks
that achieve this.
The system's level approach
to fecal sludge management
developed in this course
and the associated book
should be seen as a building block
for the future design and operation
of functional and sustainable
fecal sludge management systems.
Developing solutions for
fecal sludge management
and solutions for
city-wide sanitation
that include both sewered
and non-sewered solutions
requires tackling large
complicated issues
that are all inter related.
It is necessary to understand
how these fields fit together
and to understand
the connections
and influences of each field
upon the other.
There have been
rapid improvements
in gains in knowledge,
and although there is still
a long way to go,
these advances will continue
to build upon each other
and improve solutions
and approaches.
Some important aspects
for the way forward
that you learned
about in this course
include designing
for the final end use
or disposal option
of treatment products
to ensure treatment objectives
are met and public health
is protected.
Designing for the actual quantity
and characteristic of fecal sludge
to ensure designs
meet the local context
improving on-site containment
technologies, transfer stations
and emptying methodologies,
safe, efficient and affordable
collection and transport will
help to ensure that fecal sludge
is delivered to treatment.
Developing and understanding
of treatment mechanisms
this will be the basis for
developing new technologies
and for adapting existing ones.
Incorporating management
concerns from the beginning
of the project planing,
link operations and maintenance
to technologies decisions
and long term budgets.
Setting up legal and regulatory
frameworks
and enforcement mechanisms
having one entity of
a city government
solely responsible increases
a sense of responsibility
that can be lost in more
fragmented management models.
Streamlining eliminates any
responsibility overlap
between stakeholders
and also avoid gaps in responsibilities.
Considering different models
of financial transfers
different business models
for sanitation services
need to be considered
to reduce the financial burden
at the household level.
Assessing and understanding
the initial situation
in specific context, especially
important due to the heterogeneity
of urban areas in low
and middle income countries
characterized by rapid growth rates
in varied diverse landscapes
in terms of income level,
sanitation technologies
and formal and informal
settlements in addition
to weak enabling environments.
Integrating stakeholders
and understanding their
interests and influence
which is key for commitment
to responsibilities.
Applying an integrated planning
approach at the city level.
This is especially important in
the field of fecal sludge management
has globally, experience has showed
time and time again
that on-site and decentralized
technologies are prone to failure
if not considered as
a component within a larger system.
For the development
of a sustainable fecal sludge
management systems
a significant step requires first
the acknowledge of it's
importance by stakeholders.
This includes governments taking
responsibility for providing
fecal sludge management
development agencies providing
funding structures for feasible
and appropriate solutions
and large inter-governmental
organizations
promoting safe fecal
sludge management.
As this is a relatively new field
much of the existing knowledge
remains with practitioners in
the field without a written record
and there remains a lack of
affordable and accessible references
materials and curriculum.
Hopefully initiatives like this
course will start to fill this gap
and after completing this course
part of the responsibility
also goes to you.
There is a great need
for the development
of appropriate technologies
even though solutions will
not rely on technology alone.
New technologies are based on
pioneering developments in research
which points to a need
for solution oriented research
to be conducted in countries
where it is directly relevant.
With local researchers working
together with their
urban governments
that are responsible
for fecal sludge management
so new knowledge is taken up,
and has an influence on policy.
Due to the urgent need
for technical solutions
research and implementation
need to continue to be conducted
in parallel, getting to scale
as rapidly as possible.
An example of this was provided
in Durban case study.
Creativity is essential
in every aspect
of fecal sludge management.
To continue to advance solutions
that are globally transferable
and applicable for the forty percent
of the people world wide
served by on-site
sanitation technologies
and the billions more
that will need to be served
in the decades to come.
Keeping an open mind
will be the key to developing
innovative and optimal solutions.
Learning from the past
but also not limiting
future possibilities
through biases of what has
or has not worked in the past
in other situations.
Undoubtedly, this is a very
exciting and promising time
for the advancement
of fecal sludge management
and the field will continue
to advance with
increasing acknowledgement
of the importance
of fecal sludge management.
Along with it, we also need
a new generation of practitioners
scientists and engineers
who are up for the challenge.
Who will be the next drivers
of change in realizing
integrated city-wide sanitation.
Hopefully that includes you.
What would your next steps be
following this course
to make the best use
of your new knowledge and skills
to apply concepts if sustainable
fecal sludge management
in your city?
Will you use this in your job
professional development or career?
Please share your goals and ideas
to the forum discussion.
Thank you for joining
and hope to see you again soon.