During the previous episodes, we have discussed
arrays and character strings.
Today, we will discuss data
structures, which are another
way to represent data.
A program may need to store
so-called "structured data".
For example, we way wish to
to store the age of several people,
as is represented here.
As we have discussed in a previous video,
in such a case, we will need
a kind of array, which would in this case
be declared as follows.
We we will use the "vector" type if we do not
know how many people
the program will consider.
On the other hand,
we will use the "array" type
if, for example, we know that we will
always consider 5 people.
Arrays and vectors are homgenous
data structures. This means
that all the values contained
in them share
the same type -- int in this example.
However, we may also want
to consider heterogenous data,
data with different types.
For example, we could want to consider
data regarding people,
like here, where the
data would be the person's name
-- a character string --
the person's height
-- a double-type value --
their age -- an int-type value --
and their gender -- a character,
either 'M' or 'F', for instance.
Here, we cannot resort to an array
to store all these data,
for they do not share
the same type. However, we can
regroup them in a new
type called "structure".
These "structures" allow us
to represent the data of a row.
We will then create an array/vector of "structures"
to store all the data
regarding a group of
people.
In general, we use structures,
when we wish
to regroup data of different
types or natures.
Structures have various usage.
First of all, we will be able
to represented entities.
These entities will be defined
by several data. For example,
such an entity could be a person
defined, according to the program's needs,
by a first name, a last
name and a birth date.
Another entity could be a date,
defined by
a day number, a month and a year.
Regrouping these data makes it
easier to manipulate such entities.
Another useful application of
structures is when we need to have
a function to return several values.
This will be discussed this later.
Finally, a third use,
generalizing the first one,
is to simplify
the conception and writing
of our programs.
Before we burry ourselves in the details,
let's provide a few examples of structures.
This "Date" structure gathers a day,
a month and a year.
Such a declaration thus defines
a new type,
usable in the program.
Thanks to this type, we can now declare
variables. Here, for example,
we are declaring a date-type variable
called "aujourdhui" [TN: "aujourd'hui" means "today"]
This variable can now
have concrete values
for the day, the month and the year.
This structure "Etudiant" regroups the
student's name, and their faculty
-- both character strings -- as well as his
course inscriptions,
an array containing "Cours"-type values.
[TN: "cours" means "course"],
where "Cours" is another structure,
previously declared in the program.
The last data in this structure
would be
the average of the student's grades.
This structure "Particule" would be
useful for a physics simulation program.
It regroups the values related to an
elementary particle :
first of all, the position of the particle
-- a three-dimensional vector --
the velocity of the particle
-- another three-dimensional vector --
as well as the mass
and charge of the particle
-- both of the type double.
A structure is thus a new type defined
and declared by a programmer
respecting the following syntax.
We begin with
the reserved keyword "struct" followed by
the desired name of the structure.
Then, between braces, is what we call
the list
of the structure members regrouped
in the structure.
As you can see, the declaration
of these members
looks similar to the declaration
of variables. Indeed, the declaration
starts with the member's type,
followed by its identifier or name,
followed by a semicolon.
Also, please note that a semicolon
is required after the closing brace.
Structures are the only circumstance
where a semiclon appears
after a closing brace.
For example here, we define
a new structure,
a new type called "personne". This structure
would be useful in order to define the type
of the elements of the array presented in
the beginning of this episode. It regroups
a person's name, height, age
and gender.
This other structure called "Complexe"
regroups two members.
A member x and a member y. This structure could
be useful to represent complex numbers
-versus real numbers- written
"x + iy" in mathematics.
SImilarly to arrays, the members of a
structure are not limited
to scalar types such as int or double.
The members of a structure can be
arrays or even other structures!
For example, we declare here a type
"Compliquee" (TN:"compliquée" means "complicated")
whose second member is of the type int.
Its first member, however, is an
array of doubles.
And its third member is of the type
"Simple", which has been declared here
and contains two members
of type int and double.
A structure is thus a new type which
we can use to declare
variables. This declaration is no different
from
any other declaration. Namely, we begin
by the type,
followed by the variable's name.
For example, we rewrote here the code
defining the structure "Personne".
and here, I declare a variable "untel"
(TN: "untel" means "someone")
of the type "Personne".
Be careful though, the definition
of a structure must be written outside
any function before we can use it
to declare variables.
On the other hand, the declaration
of variables of this new type
has to occur inside a function.
For example, the definition will be written
outside any function. Then, we will define
the variable "untel" inside
a function,
such as the "main" function, like this.
We can represent this variable
"untel" like this:
it has a member called "nom" (TN:"name")
a member called "taille" (TN:"height"), etc.
In this other example, we first declare
a structure called
"Complexe" with a member "x" and a member "y".
Then, we declare here a new variable
called z of the type "Complexe".
z will thus contain
two members : a member 'x' and a member 'y'.
Similarly to other types,
we can initialize
a structure-type variable.
During the declaration, we will
proceed with the following syntax.
After the type of the structure and
the variable name, we will add
the sign equals and, between braces,
the values
we wish to give to the different
members of the variable.
And, after the closing brace
comes our semicolon.
For example, here is our
structure "Personne" once again.
Here, we declare a personne-type
variable "untel".
"untel" can be represented like this.
This declaration also initializes the
members of the variable untel:
"Dupond" will go into the first
member, the member "nom".
Namely, the member "nom" will contain
the value "Dupond".
The member "taille" will contain
the value 1.75 .
The member "age" will
contain the value 41 .
And the member "sexe" (TN: "gender")
will contain the character 'M'.
Moreover, in C++11,
we can also use this syntax
outside the initialization, for
an assignment and we will obtain
the exact same values in the same members.
Please note that in C++, before 2011,
we could not use this syntax
for the assignment; there was no easy
way to assign literal values to
all the members of a structure.
We now know how to initialize the
members of a structure-type variable,
namely giving a value to its
members during the declaration
of the variable. Now we would like to
access these values. To that end, we
have to respect the following syntax.
We begin by writing
the name of the structure-type variable,
followed by a period, followed the member's name.
For example, let us go back to
our  variable "untel"
of the previous slide, which was a
"Personne"-type variable.
We can represent it like this.
This instruction is an assignment,
which will store the value 1.75
inside the member "taille"
of the variable "untel". Namely,
we will put the value 1.75 at this place
of our representation of
the variable "untel".
This instruction will add 1 to the
member "age" of "untel" (happy birthday!).
In other words, it will go from 41 to 42.
By the way, please note that the
parentheses here are mandatory;
we cannot simply write
" ++untel.age " since the operator "++"
has priority over the operator '.' (dot).
This last instruction here will print
the value contained in the member "sexe"
of the variable "untel"; it will thus print
the character 'M'.
Now, let us detail a complete
example, regarding, inter alia,
functions with structure-type
parameters.
We will start by reusing here the code of our
structure "Personne",
which data are: a name, a height,
an age and a gender.
The function "main" will start
by declaring a personne-type
variable "untel". We can represent
"untel" like this.
"untel" will be initialized through
the return value of
the function "naissance" (TN:"birth"),
called here.
Here is the code of the birth function.
Its goal is to ask the user to give us
the values of the members of a
personne-type variable,
namely, a name, a height, an age and
a gender. The function will then return,
as a structure, the members'
values entered by the user.
This function does not need
any
value in order to work:
it has no parameters.
On the other hand, it returns
a structure-type value;
more precisely, a "Personne"-type value.
The return type of
the "naissance" function is thus "Personne".
How does the "naissance" function proceed, exactly?
It starts by declaring
a local personne-type variable
called "p".
"p" can be represented just like
the variable "untel".
For now, the members of "p"
are not initialized;
we do not know what they contain.
Then, the function "naissance"
will ask the user to enter a name,
which will be stored
directly inside the field "nom"
of the variable "p", right here.
Let us suppose, for our example,
that the user enters the name "Dupond".
Then, the function will ask
the user to enter a height
and an age; let us use
the values
of the previous example.
The function will then
ask the user to enter a character --either
'M' or 'F'-- for the member "sexe"
of the variable "p", making sure
that the user enters
either 'M' or 'F' thanks to a "do-while loop".
Let'assume that our person here
is a man.
Finally, the function will finish
by returning the value
contained inside the variable "p",
that is all the values
stored in its members.
Let's go back to the call
of the function "naissance".
What will happen here, exactly?
The values of the members of the variable "p"
will be copied inside the fields
of the variable "untel". Precisely,
the member "name" will take
the value "Dupond",
the member "height", 1.75,
"age", 41
and the member "sexe" the character 'M'.
The next instruction
in the "main" function is this one;
a call to the "anniversaire" function
(TN: "anniversaire" means "birthday"),
passing the variable "untel" as argument.
Here is the code of the "anniversaire" function.
The goal of this function "anniversaire"
is to add 1 to the "age" member
of the variable passed as argument.
This function has thus
only one parameter of the
type "Personne",
since "untel" is a "Personne"-type
variable.
We will use a passage by reference since
the function aims to modify
the value of the variable passed
as argument.
This function does not return
anything; its return type
is thus "void". If we execute the function's
body in our example,
we will change this 41 -- the value
contained by the member "age"
of the variable "untel" -- to 42.
Then, we will  keep going
in the body of the "main" function,
thus reaching this instruction
calling the function "affiche" [TN: "print"/"display"]
passing the variable "untel"
as argument.
Here is the code of this "affiche" function.
The goal of this "affiche" function
is to print the values of the members
of a variable passed as argument.
This function thus has
only one personne-type parameter.
It will not need to modify
the value of the variable
passed as argument.
We used here keyword "const"
followed by an ampersand
similarly to the passage by reference,
between the paramter's type
and the parameter's name.
This is an optimization you do not
need to worry about for now.
This optimization avoids to
make a copy. Indeed, be reminded
that during passage by value, a copy
is created; a costly copy of a
structure containing many members.
The function will simply print
the values of the different members
of the parameter.
By the way, we are here using a "switch"
instruction to print if the person is man
or a woman. This "switch" instruction
is explained in the complements.
We could also have used
an "if" instruction.
You can verify yourself that, in the
case of our example,
the function will print this.
Once the "affiche" function has been
executed, we will come back in the
"main" function, here. We will then
execute the "return" instruction,
thus ending the program.
We can assign a structure-type
variable
to another variable of the same type.
For example, we declare here a
personne-type variable p1, initializing
its members with these values.
Then, we declare another personne-type
variable p2
without initializing the value
of its members.
In this last instruction -- an assignment --
we will copy the value of the
members of p1 inside the members
of the variable p2. Namely, this assignment
is strictly equivalent
to these 4 assignments, copying
member by member,
the variable p1 into p2. In other words,
we copy here, for example, the value
of the member "nom" of p1
into the member "nom" of p2.
Be careful though, the assignment
is the only global operator
usable for structure-type
variables.
We cannot compare nor
print them in a global way.
Reusing the previous example,
we were allowed to write "p2 = p1",
which is an assignment.
However, we are not allowed
to write "p1 == p2" to compare p1 and p2
or two write "cout << p1" in order to print
the values of the members of p1.
In such a case, we have to proceed
member by member. For example,
we may use this instruction
to print the four members of p1.
Obviously though, it is much better
to write a function tasked with
this comparison or printing.
This is exactly what we did with the former
"affiche" function,
in a previous example.
By the way, please note that even
if the operators == and << are not defined
a priori for structures, in C++, a programmer
has the possibility to define them himself.
This is called operator
overloading,
But this goes beyond this course's frame.
For now, simply remember
that you have to compare structures
member by member.
Now, let us go back to the
example of the beginning of this episode
Remember, we wanted to store
all these values in the memory.
Now, we will be able to use
an array, the elements of which
will be of structure type.
First of all, we will declare
the structure "Personne", regrouping
the four members interesting us,
namely the name, the height,
the age and the gender of the person.
Then, we will declare an array called
"Personnes", here. [TN : notice the plural.]
Its elements will be
of the type "Personne".
Now, each row of this table
will correspond to an element
of our array. Each column of
the table will correspond
to a member of the
array's elements.
We can represent the beginning
of our "Personnes" array like this :
Each element of the "Personnes" array
will contain a member "nom",
a member "taille" and so on.
All this forms the first
element of the "Personnes" array.
And this assignment will store,
among others, these values
inside the first element of the
"Personnes" array. Therefore,
"Dupond" will be stored in this member,
1.75 in this member,
41 here and 'M' here.
As we have said, structures can
used to let
functions returns several values.
For example, we may want to write a function
"division_euclidienne" (TN:"euclidean division")
returning, at the same time,
the quotient and the remainder
of two values passed as argument.
In such a case, we have
several possible solutions.
We could have the function
return a structure
containing the different values we
wish to have returned.
Another possibility is to pass the
variables by reference
and to have them assigned,
inside the function, to the
values we wish to calculate.
We will see an example
on the next slide.
A third possibility, if all the values
have the same type,
is to have the function return
a dynamic array
containing these values.
In more complex cases, we could
even combine the solutions
1 and 3, thus returning either a structure,
with vector members containing
homogenous
data or returning vectors of structure
containing heterogenous values.
For example, in the case of
the function "division_euclidienne", which
has two parameters:
the dividend and the divisor.
the first solution would be to start
by declaring a structure called
here "Resultat" (TN:"result") containing
a member for the quotient
and a member for the remainder.
Then, we will define, as the return
type of the function "division_euclidienne",
the type "Resultat".
In such a case, we will call our
function "division_euclidienne"
like this:
"Resultat" in order to define the type
of a variable containing the result,
and passing two variables by value,
one for the dividend and one for the divisor.
The second solution is to add
two parameters,
passed by reference
and to use the function
like this.
We will start by declaring
two supplementary variables;
they will store the values
calculated by the function.
Then, we will call our function
like this.
The third solution is to define,
as the return type of the function,
an integer array containing two elements.
We will then call the function like this.
We have used here the type "array"
but we could also have used
the type "vector" since "vector" is a more
general form of arrays.
To sum up, structures let us
regroup several data
under a same type. They serve to represent
entities such as people
or dates or to have functions return
several values.
More generally, they let us simplify
the conception and writing of our programs.
Now, we invite you to try and take
the quizzes,
testing the new knowledge acquired
during this new lesson.