At this juncture of our course,
we have already encountered many a type.
We have seen the basic types int and double.
Then we have seen more advanced types
such as dynamic arrays which
we can even compose :
dynamic arrays of
dynamic arrays and so on.
Complex types sometimes make
the writing a little tedious.
For this reason, among others we will
develop soon,
it can be interesting to define
type aliases.
Namely giving an other name to
a previously defined type.
This is done as follows :
You start your line with the
reserved keyword "typedef",
then you write the name of the type you wish to name
anew.
And finally, the new name you
wish to give to this type,
finishing with a semicolon.
For example, let us suppose
you wish to call "Vecteur" (TN: "Vecteur" means "Vector"),
something that is
a dynamic array of double.
How should we proceed?
We will start our line
with "typedef". Then comes the type we wish to
give a new name to : vector.
And finally, the new name we have chosen
for this vector type.
Starting with this line,
you will be able to use
either the old name vector
or, if you want, your new name:
"Vecteur" with a capital V here
is now strictly equivalent to vector,
it is an alias for vector.
For example, you can now declare
a variable v of type  "Vecteur",
which is a dynamic array
of doubles.
Of course, you can keep the old
syntax,
you had previously. For exemple,
you can initialize a vector v2,
with a size of 3 and a certain value,
for example.
Now, the type "Vecteur", as has
been specified here,
is strictly equivalent to
vector .
You can even reuse this type itself
in another type.
For example, you can now define
the type "Matrice" (TN:"matrix") as a
dynamic array of "Vecteur",
which has been previously defined.
This is done with this line :
"typedef vector Matrice"
Vecteur being the type which has already been redefined.
Now, the type "Matrice",
is a dynamic array of
dynamic array of doubles.
Instead of writing, for example :
"vector  > m;" ,
thanks to this line, you can now
simply write "Matrice m;"
which is quite a lot
simpler.
You can also use the initialization.
Matrice here is the newly defined
type.
"rotation" is the variable name,
and the initialization  is here,
between parentheses.
We are initializing a dynamic
array of dynamic array,
specifying that the variable "rotation"
is initialized to 3.
3 what ? 3 dynamic
arrays of double.
But since we have already defined
"Vecteur" why not use it?
We can use three "Vecteur".
Each Vecteur is here of size 3 and has all its values initialized
with the value 1.
Therefore, we will create a "Matrice"
named  "rotation"
which will be a dynamic array of 3
dynamic arrays of 3 doubles,
each one with the value 1.
These type aliases, these "typedef",
are useful for three reasons :
First of all, the declaration of arrays,
which we have just seen.
This will improve the reading,
writing, and manipulating of
vectors and matrices.
It will also make it easier to identify
concepts : the concept of vectors
and the concept of matrices.
The "typedef"s let us clearly define
and identify the concepts;
this is probably the most important
use of these "typedef"s.
So, we can easily identify the
objects we are working with.
Let us take an example.
Let us suppose that we have a program
in which we need to manipulate distances.
We have decided these distances
will be integers.
So, we have a distance d,
declared as an integer.
For example, we have here a distance d2,
Let us suppose that we also
have numbers.
So, we have a number "nb"
of the type integer.
We may also have temperatures and so on.
In our programs, we thus have
a lot of integers,
sharing the same type but representing
completely different concepts :
distances, temperatures, numbers.
Now, let us suppose that we decide
to modify our program
so that the distances will
now be of the type double.
The question is : among all
these ints,
scattered all around our
program,
which ones will have to be changed to double,
which ones will stay ints ?
If you had defined a "typedef",
the solution would have
been much easier.
If you have a "typedef" like here,
"typedef int Distance",
this means that the "Distance"
has now become
a new type, representing an integer.
We can now freely
use this new type,
this type alias
in order to represent lenghts.
The variable "maLongueur" (TN:"myLenght).
At this point of the previous example,
the variables d and d2 would have been distances.
Therefore, if we need to
modify distances so that
they are no longer integers but
doubles,
we only need to modify one single
line -the "typedef" line.
We simply replace the "int" by "double"
like this.
Through this one change
of the "typedef" line,
all our distances will instantly
become doubles;
we needed to change neither the numbers
nor the temperatures.
The use of "typedef" as we have just seen
permits a better identification
of the concepts; this is essential
in order to make your
programs all the clearer
and more readable.
In the same time, it will also
facilitate subsequent
changes such as the modification
of int to double,
here for the distances.
Therefore, modifications will
become much easier.
The usefulness of concepts identification
through "typedef"s
is also illustrated by  the writing
of function parameters.
The writing of the functions
will indeed become
much clearer and more compact.
Let us take an example of a
function which would be the dot product.
The dot product of two vectors.
If we write it like this,
we can clearly see that these
are two vectors returning a vector.
This is made possible by this line here,
placed at the beginning
of the program :
"typedef vector Vecteur;" .
Thanks to this line, it is much clearer to read
that the dot product returns
a vector and takes two vectors
as arguments.
Without it, we would have to write
"vector produit_vectoriel
(vector, vector);
Obviously this is much less
readable and understandable.
For all these reasons,
and fundamentally the first one
-identifying the concepts-
we warmly advise you to use them
whenever possible.
Every time you have the chance to
give a clear type to a variable, please
do so : this will enhance de quality of your programs.