Hello. In this episode, we will see
a new type : "string".
This type will let us declare variables
containing character strings.
A character string is simply
a list of characters,
such as a word, a sentence. For
example, "Hello everybody!".
In order to use this new type, we
must include its definition.
This means we will will have to add
this this line at the beginning of the program :
#include
Then, we can declare
string-type variables.
We will do it like this :
As usual, we will start with the type
of the variable, here "string"
followed by the name we wish
to give to the variable.
We will finish by a semicolon.
In this example of code, we start
by indicating the line
" #include  " so that we
can use this new "string" type.
In this line, we are declaring
a variable called "un_nom"
(TN: means "a_name").
For now, it is initialized
to the empty character string.
This is a specificity of the "string" type
in comparison with the already encountered types.
If we do not put any explicit
initial value,
the value is initialized to
the empty string.
However, this second declaration
declares a variable "message"
initialized to "Bonjour à tous !"
(TN: means "Hello everyone!")
Be careful though, these
characters called "quotation marks"
or "double quotes" are not part
of the string.
They are merely used to indicate the
beginning and the end of the string.
Character strings are thus constituted
of characters.
These characters have their own
type called "char".
Thus, we can declare variables
containing only one character.
For example, here, we are declaring
a variable called c
containing the character " x ".
We can represent it like this.
Please note that the character x
is between apostrophes
also called "simple quotes".
On the other hand, character
strings are delimited by quotation marks
or double quotes.
In this second declaration,
we are declaring a variable  u
also of the type char.
It is not initialized; this means we
do not know what it contains.
Once we execute this instruction,
which is an assignment,
we will assign the character 's'
to the variable  u.
Please endeavor not to mix
the types "char" and "string".
For example, if we write
" char s('c'); " ,
it is the declaration of a variable
which will perforce contain
a single character since
"char" is its type.
If we write : " string s("c"); "
it is the declaration of a
character string
which will contain
one character.
Thus, be careful as you cannot write,
for example, " char s("c"); "
since this is of the type "string".
We cannot assign a string-type value
to our char-type variable s.
A good mnemonic way to
remember this is that
a char-type variable can
only contain one character,
we thus use simple quotes.
A character string will generally contain
more than one character,
and we will thus double quotes to
delimit a character string.
As for any other type,
we can modify, through an assignment,
variables declared of the type "string".
For example, let us start by
declaring
a string-type variable
called "chaine".
(TN: means "string")
We are not giving any value to
initialize it.
Remember that, in this case, "chaine"
will be initialized to the empty string.
Then, here, we declare
a second variable,
still of the type "string" and
call it "chaine2".
"chaine2" is initialized to the
"test" string.
Then, here, we do an assignment
changing the value of "chaine".
we will put "test3" into "chaine".
In the following assignment,
we are copying the value of "chaine2"
into "chaine".
Therefore, "chaine 2" will
contain "test".
This "test3" here will be replaced
by the character string "test".
In this last assignment,
we are assigning the character 'a'
to the variable "chaine",
that is, this one.
Here, it is indeed a character
since we are using simple quotes,
apostrophes to delimit
the characters.
However, C++ will automatically
convert
this char-type value
into a string-type value,
that is, a character string
we can represent like this.
Now, after this last assignment,
"chaine" contains the string "a".
Also, we can concatenate two strings.
This means we can put two strings
one after other
thanks to the " + " operator.
For example, if we have "chaine1"
and "chaine2",
two string-type variables,
we can write this.
This will result in a new character string
beginning with the characters
of "chaine1"
and ending with the characters of "chaine2".
For example, in this code,
we are declaring three string-type
variables.
For now, they are all initialized
to the empty character string.
Let us suppose we have given a value
to the variable "prenom" (TN: means "first name"),
for example, "Jean"
and a surname in the variable "famille".
(TN: means "family").
Once we execute this assignment,
we will first concatenate
the value of the variable "famille"
with this character string
which simply contains a blank space.
This will give us
"Dupont" followed by a blank space.
Let us represent it like this.
Then, we will add the
content of the variable "prenom",
that is, "Jean".
All this forms a new character string
which we will store in the variable "nom"
upon the assignment.
The following combinations are
possible
for the concatenation of two strings.
We can concatenate two
string-type variables.
We can also concatenate
a string-type variable
with a literate value of the
type "string".
Or, we can start with the
literal value
followed by the string-type variable.
We can also start with
a string-type variable
and add a character.
We can also begin with the character
and concatenate it with
a string-type variable.
Let us go back to the example
of the previous slide.
We had used
a string-type literal value
to represent the blank space
we wished to inserate between
the first name and the surname.
Actually, we may also use
a character.
We are doing just that here,
using simple quotes.
This thing here is a char-type
literal value.
We may very well
concatenate a "char" with a
string-type variable.
You can see this here.
Concatenations of the form string + char
are very practical to add
characters
at the end of a character string.
For example, here, we declare
a variable "reponse".
(TN: means "answer")
It contains the character
string "solution".
When a variable " n " is
greater than 1,
we would like to put "solution"
in the plural.
To that end, we will use this assignment.
For now, the variable "reponse"
contains "solution".
And we will simply concatenate it
with the character 's'.
We will thus obtain the string
"solutions" with an " s " at the end.
We will then store the result
in our variable "reponse".
Now, "reponse" will therefore contain
"solutions", in the plural.
We can use the same trick to
add characters at the beginning
of a string.
As for other types, we will
use the " == " symbol
to test if two strings are equal.
Also, we will use the " != " symbol
to test if two strings are different.
For example, in this code, we
are using a "do while loop".
Inside, we are calling a function
which asks a question.
The result of this function
is a character string
which we will assign to our
variable "reponse".
We wish to keep asking the
question
as long as the answer is
not "oui" (TN: means "yes" )
To that end, we will write,
between the parentheses,
this condition here.
It will test if "reponse" is different from
the character string "oui".
This should be enough for
this introduction
on the character strings.
In the following episode, we will
discuss manipulations on strings.