In this episode we will discuss
the processing we can apply
on character strings.
We can access the different
characters of a string individually.
For example, let "chaine"
be a string-type variable.
So, " chaine[i] "
is the (i+1)th character of a "chaine".
It will be a char-type character.
Be careful though! as for arrays
the first character has 0 for index.
The last one has
" taille - 1 " for index,
if "taille" (TN: means "size")
is the number of characters in the string.
For example,
we declare here a variable "demo"
of the type "string".
It contains the character
string "ABCD".
We declare here to characters :
"premier" and "dernier".
(TN: "premier" means "first", "dernier" means "last").
For now, they are not
initialized.
We assign "premier" with the
following assignment.
" demo[0] ". What is this?
Why, "demo" is the string here.
[0] corresponds to this first
character.
Therefore, "premier" will
receive the character 'A'.
Here, in "dernier" we will
store the character
with the index 3 of the string
"demo".
The character with the index 3 is :
0 , 1, 2, 3 this 'D' here.
We will thus store 'D' in
our variable "dernier".
Here is another example : a quiz.
In your opinion, what will this code print
upon execution?
We start here by declaring a variable
called "essai" (TN: means "attempt", "trial").
It contains the character
string "essai".
Here, we declare another
character string
initialized to the empty character string.
Now, we keep going with a "for loop".
There, the variable " i " will
take the values 1, 2 and 3.
For now, " i " is 1.
Now, we enter the "for loop".
" essai[6 - 2 * i]
what does it mean?
First, it will be a character.
Since "i" is 1, the index is 4.
The character with the index 4 in "essai"
is : 0, 1, 2, 3, 3
the character 'i'.
All this is actually the character 'i'.
We will add it to what is contained
in the "test" string.
Since "test" is empty, we will
simply obtain
the string "i" which we will store
in the variable "test".
Now to this assignment :
" essai[i] ". Since "i" is 1,
it is the character 's' here.
For now, "test" contains the
string "i".
All this is now the
string "si"
which we will assign to "test".
Now, "i" is 2.
We can keep going inside
the "for loop".
We will execute this assignment here.
This expression is 2.
Therefore, this is the character with
the index 2 in the string "essai".
It is this 's' here.
Remember that "test" contains "si".
Thus, the result of this
assignment
is that we will store "sis"
into our variable "test".
Let us keep going here.
"essai[i] "
is the element with the index 2
of our variable "essai";
it is this 's' here.
"test" contains "sis".
Through this assignment,
we will obtain "ssis" in the variable "test".
Let us keep going.
This time, "i" is 3.
The expression in this
assignment
is now 0.
This all here is therefore the character
of the index 0 in the string "essai".
This is this 'e' here.
Let us add it to "test".
Now, we get 6 and move on
to this assignment.
"essai[3]" is :
0, 1, 2, 3
this character here.
That means an 'a'.
We will add it to "ssise".
We thus obtain the string "assise"
(TN: "assise" means "seated")
which we will put in the variable "test".
Ultimately, we will thus print "assise".
There are several functions specific
to the type "string" defined in C++
just like for the vectors.
They are used with the
following syntax.
First of all the name of the
string-type variable
followed by a period, followed
by the name of the function we wish to use,
followed by the eventual arguments
required by the function.
For example, we may use
the "size" function.
We will call it like this.
Let "chaine" be
a string-type variable.
This function will return
the size of the string,
that is, the number of characters
of the variable "chaine".
We also have a function called "insert".
It has two arguments.
First of all,
the position of a character,
defining where we wish
to insert a second string.
It is defined with this argument here.
The call to this function will
insert "chaine2"
into the variable "chaine",
starting with this position here.
For example, let us declare
a string-type variable
containing the string "abcd".
Now, we are calling the function
"insert"
with the position "1" (this one)
and the string "xx".
Why, this function "insert" will
insert the string "xx"
between the character index 0
and the character index 1,
that is, here.
Then, we will store the result
into the string "exemple".
After the call to this "insert"
function,
our variable "exemple" will
contain the string
"axxbcd".
We may also use the
"replace" function.
It needs 3 arguments.
First of all, the position (just
like the "insert" function
we have just seen).
A number of characters.
The third argument
is a character string.
This "replace" functions works
a little like the "insert" function.
In stead, it will replace n character
of the variable "string".
To make things clear,
let us take an example.
After this declaration-initialization,
the variable "exemple"
contains the string
"abcd".
We are now calling the "replace" function
with, for position, the value 1.
It corresponds to this 'b' here.
The "replace" function will
replace two characters
starting with this character 'b'.
That means we will replace
this 'b' and this 'c'.
We will replace them with this string here
which is "1234".
In the variable "exemple", we thus
obtain
the string "a1234d".
By the way, we may use
this "replace" function
to suppress the characters
of a string.
To that end, we simply need
to use the empty string
as the third argument.
In this new example,
our variable "exemple"
contains the string "abcd".
As before, we will replace the
characters "b" and "c".
But we will replace them with
the empty string.
Ultimately, we will obtain
the string "ad"
in our variable "exemple".
The "find" function expects only
one argument
of the type "string".
It will return the index in "chaine"
of the first character
of the leftmost appearance
of the string
passed as argument.
So, what does it mean?
Let us take an example.
Let "exemple" be a variable initialized
to this character string here.
We are  calling the "find" function,
passing "ab" as parameter.
Starting from the left, "ab" appears
for the first time
here, in "exemple".
The index of the first character is 2
since we start from 0.
Our "find" function will thus
return the value 2.
There is also the reverse function,
starting from the right.
It is the function "rfind".
So, if we call our "rfind" function
on this same "exemple" string.
As we said, we are starting
from the right.
The first time "ab" appears
in this string
is here.
The index of this character here
is 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6
Thus, our "rfind" function
will return the value 6 in
this case.
By the way, please note that
we cannot be sure
the string passed as argument to
the functions "find" and "rfind"
will be found in the string to which
we apply these functions.
In this case, the functions "find"
and "rfind"
will return a predefined value
written " string::npos "
meaning that we have not found
the string passed as argument.
For example, with this
instruction here.
Let "exemple" be, like in the previous
examples,
contain "baabbaab".
Here, we are seeking the
string "xy".
Since the string "xy" does not appear
in the string "exemple",
the function "find"
will return the predefined value
" string::npos ".
Finally, a last function
called "substr".
It has two parameters : "depart" and "longueur" (TN: "depart" means "start" and "longueur" means "length").
On this example, it is applied on
the character string "chaine".
This call to the function "substr"
will return the sub-string of "chaine"
which has, as length, "longueur"
passed as argument
and starting with the starting position "depart".
For example, we are considering
this character string
"exemple" which contains this value.
The call to this function :
" exemple.substr(8, 4) "
will return a sub-string
beginning with the
character of the index 8.
So, 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8
we will thus jump here.
We will take 4 characters starting
with this 't'.
Thus, the call to this
function will return
the string "tous".
Voilà! this is all we will see
regarding the string-type
functionalities.
Be aware that there are many
others, all operating
based on the same principles.