Hello and welcome to this lesson
dedicated to three-phase
electric power.
We will define what the
instantaneous three-phase power is
in a symmetric system and will
study using two examples
the power with a balanced
charge, or rather, the powers
in
a balanced charge.
To define the instantaneous power within a symmetric
three-phase system,
I would like to start with a short reminder
of the different types of power that exist.
We can count
four types of powers,
starting with
the first
type, if one may say, of power.
The instantaneous power, which is the
power depending on time.
We have then defined the active power
by the letter P.
This active power, we have seen that,
by definition, it is the average
of the instantaneous power
and it is also equal to
U*I*cos(φ)
and all this is measures in watts.
Then, we defined another type of power
that defines the round trip of the
target non-convertible
power called reactive power, and
is by definition equal to
U*I*sin(φ), written in reactive volt-amperes.
Last but not least,
the power called apparent power
is equal to U*I and is
written
in volt-amperes.
Now, how do we solve the
power problems in a three-phase
system ? We have seen that
by symmetry,
all these values are equal in each branch.
We also know that the total power
in a system
is simply the sum
of these powers.
We can then say
that by symmetry
we can write the total power
as equal to the sum
of all three
powers in each phase.
We will be able to write for
each of these types, or each
of these powers
Firstly, for the instantaneous power,
we can write
that it is U_ux which multiplies I_ux,
which are here
instantaneous values depending on time.
We then have the second phase U_vy
which multiplies I_vy, and the
third phase
U_wz which multiplies I_wz.
We will see later
how this instantaneous power is
finally defined and what
conclusion we can draw
in the end.
For the active power,
as mentioned earlier, it is three times the
active power in each branch.
Therefore, we will write U_ux
and I_ux which multiply cos(φ),
and we have the same
for the other two branches U_vy
times cos(φ)  and
U_wz
times cos(φ).
Three times this
which will give us, since these three values
by being symmetrical, are equal
to three times
the phase voltage times the phase current times cos(φ).
You will probably remark
"yes, but if
one of these assemblies is a wye or delta,
will that change the result?"
Well no, since each time either the
line voltage is equal to
the phase voltage, or the line current
is equal to the phase current.
This is always true
and can even be replaced by
the line voltage and current voltage
by writing with the relation √3
U_I
I_l, cos(φ).
Therefore, for the active power in a
three-phase system, we have
a simple relation
letting us focus on one phase only
and not on the more complicated system
since it is simply three
times each phase.
We can now write, in the exact
same way, the reactive
power that we have
three times
the phase voltage:
phase current times the sine of the angle
and in the same way
write this depending on the line voltage
and line current.
We will then have, for the
apparent power,
three times
the voltage phase times the
current phase
or √3 times
the line voltage times
the line current.
All this
we can say
is valid
whatever the setup, so
wye or
delta.
We wil now find interest
in the instantaneous power, as described
previously, that I will rewrite here.
Each of these values U, I
and in each phase
corresponds to an equation that describes,
depending on time,
the voltage and the current.
We will concentrate on the first
term U_ux and I_ux
and describe in a faster way the
two other terms that are
simply out of phase
by 2π/3
and 4π/3 respectively.
For the first voltage U_ux,
by definition, we know that
it is a sine or cosine.
I will describe here
√2 times the phase voltage, which
gives the peak voltage, and for example
lets take
the sine of ωt
with an additional random phase shift
which will define
the zero
of the voltage.
We have for the current
in the same way, √2 times
the phase current
times a sine
that will by shifted by another angle
which will be either β, either (α - φ).
We can describe the other two
values U_vy
and U_vz and the other two values
of current
I_vy, I_vz
in the following way.
The instantaneous power is the sum
of the product of these two
functions
of these two functions
and these two functions. All this seems
very complicated here and we will apply
a relatively simple
general trigonometry formula that
I will show you here.
We know that the sine
of a
the multiplies the sine
of b
is really equal to a sum
of cosines. It is the cosine of the
difference of arguments
minus the cosine of the sum
of arguments.
This can seem more complicated than
before, but you will see that
it will make everthing easier.
By adding up all the terms of
previous U,I
that we have seen, we get:
First of all, we do
the difference of the arguments.
By doing this,
we have the term ωt + α that
disappears each time.
In each
element,
we always do (a-b) and the ωt + α
is found in each of them,
so it disappears.
Thus,
this instantaneous power that is finally
equal to three times
the phase voltage
times the current phase
and,
since the ωt
plus α disappears each time,
there is
only
the cosine of φ left.
We then have a minus sign
that appears here
and this minus will
also be interesting
since we have here
a phase voltage, a phase current
that multiply this time
the sum
of arguments (a+b), and we have this three times.
I will write them down for you.
We have the cosine of
2ωt plus
2α
minus φ
then
another cosine of 2ωt
plus 2α
minus φ, minus 4π/3
and then
one more cosine of 2ωt
plus 2α, minus φ
that is out of phase of -2π/3.
All this,
this sum of 3 cosine perfectly out of
phase of 2π/3 each,
simply gives zero.
In conclusion,
we see that this instantaneous
power, so the power
as function of time
comes down to
because we have here in the first term,
three times the phase voltage
phase current, cos(φ), and this is
none other than the active power
that is also, and that is only
an observation
of
this lesson
that it is a constant.
In other words, the power depending
on time
is always a constant
and equal
to the active power.
This being so,
if we imagine
a future use of a three-phase network
of a charge for an
electromecanical conversion, this
means that
by converting this electromechanical
energy,
we can make a system that
transfers and transforms a
perfectly
constant
power, so without torque undulation
or without a pulsing torque on
the machine.
I would now like to give you two
examples that will show you how
we can calculate
in a
practical exercise
the different powers that we have
just described.
We will then
start with
a first example
described in the following way:
we will connect
on
the lines R, S and T
three
completely identical and
symmetrical charges.
First of all,
this charge will be
made of three resistors
having a value of 10 Ohm
followed by
a capacitance
having a value of 185 μF.
We will connect this at
a symmetrical
three-phase electrical system.
We will now give different elements.
First of all, we know that the line
voltage is equal to 380 V.
If the line voltage is equal to 380 V,
I remind you that the phase voltage
is then equal, in a wye circuit
as here,
to √3 times less
so U_I divided by √3, namely 220 V.
We imagine having a frequency of 50 Hz
and we ask you to calculate
the different powers that we have
in this system.
First of all, we can define the
phase current
that circulates in
each branche with a different
phasor or a different angle,
this phase current will be equal to
the phase voltage divided by
the impedance Z.
We can then write
220*e^j(α).
We will define α as zero and
the reference
on Z
as the phase impedance.
We see here that
we first need to define this
phase impedance.
Lets define
Z_ph
as known, since we know that it is
a resistor and a capacitor.
namely 10 - j
(1/ω) multiplied by 185*10^(-6).
This is also equal to 10 - 17.2j
or
with Euler's formula
19,9*e^j(-60°).
It is a negative value
and is then a good control
since the system being capacitive,
we must get a negative
phase.
The phase current is then equal to
220 V divided by 19.9
and this, e^j times 60° or π/3.
What is the power then equal to ?
We can define the
three types
of power : active, reactive and apparent.
Thus, the
active power in one of the phases
is equal to R*I^2
namely
10*121
which gives 1.21 kW.
We have the reactive in a phase that
is equal to
x,
the reactance, times I^2.
This reactance, defined by the
capacitance, so  (-1/ωc)
that multiplies I^2
and that is equal to, with
the values
in this example, 17.2*121
is negative, and that is normal
since we have
a capacitance, the reactive is
negative.
We now need to
determine the total power in the whole
system and not only in one of the
phases.
The total power
is equal to three times the phase power
namely 3.63 kW.
The total reactive
is simply three time the reactive
of a single phase
namely
-6,24 kVAR.
Finally,
the total apparent power
which, as we know it, is equal to
the active power squared plus
the reactive power squared, gives us
7,21 VA.
We can then see
that we just need
to calculate
the powers on a single phase and to
multiply by 3
to get the values of the whole circuit.
A second example,
this time on a delta system,
will be suggested.
We have here
our
three-phase electrical circuit
on which we will connect
a symmetrical charge,
composed this time of
an inductance
and a resistor
that are evidently perfectly symmetrical.
R will be equal to
15 Ohm and L
will be equal to 32 mH.
Here too, we ask you to calculate the
power given by this system on
this charge. Lets write here R, S and T,
and lets note that the
line voltage is equal to 380 V.
We can then define the impedance Z
as a starting point, which is equal to
R+jx, namely R+jωL
and with the numbers of this problem,
it gives us
the value of 15
plus
10j.
The norm of Z
is equal to√(15^2 + 10^2), namely
about
18 Ohm.
The cosine of the impedance, cos(φ)
being the real part divided by
the total impedance
is equal to 15/18
namely
0,83.
We know that the active power,
which is what is asked in this
exercise, is √3
times the line voltage, the line current
and cos(φ).
We now have the cosine of the angle, the √3
and the line voltage, only
the line current is missing.
I remind you that the line current
is the current circulating for example
here
in this line, and we are searching for
the effective value, that is identical in
R, in S or in T.
We know that
it is the ratio between the line voltage
and the phase voltage
here
in the phase, it is √3.
We can then write that
the line current
is equal to, in effective value,
the phase current
times √3.
What is the phase current equal to ?
It is the phase voltage
divided by Z
(the norm)
and like always, multiplied by √3. This phase voltage, since we are in
a delta system,
is equal to the line √3
divided by Z
times √3.
We have here all the elements
and this is equal to
36,6 A.
Finally,
we can say
that our power is equal to exactely
20 kW and this
finishes
the exercise, where you can see,
once again, that by looking at
only one impedance of the balanced charge
we resolve the
whole system.
To conclude,
we can describe two important elements.
The first one is
that in every symmetrical three-phase system
connected to a balanced charge,
the instantaneous charge is always constant.
The second point is that, to resolve
a power exercise on a
three-phase system,
we concentrate on one of the branches and we simply
multiply by three
the result that we found to get
the power of the whole system.
See you soon.