Hello, welcome to the 7th lesson,
dedicated to non-symmetrical
three-phase systems.
In this lesson, we will define what
a non-symmetrical three-phase
charge is
and we will see how, by connecting
it in a wye or delta setup on a
grid
we will be able to calculate
the current
or the voltage in each of the charge's branches,
letting us define the different values
of a three-phase grid, such as
the active power, the reactive power
or the apparent
power.
The non-balanced charge, or
non-symmetrical,
is easy to define:
it is actually a
three-phase charge whose three impedances
are not strictly
identical.
We will then have
Z_1
different than
maybe Z_2 which is different
than Z_3
in a setup
for example, in which,
in delta,
we have the
three impedances,
here with R,
S and T,
Z_1,
Z_2
and Z_3.
When can this happen ?
This can firstly happen
with a defect in a machine,
a machine or a charge
on which one of the impedances
has been voluntarily changed
or either a default,
for example,
when one of the charges has a
defective connection
and one of the impedances is suddenly
disconnected.
This implies that Z_2 and Z_3
should be identical, Z_1
is then disconnected and switches to 0.
We then face
the case of a non-symmetrical charge
or non-balanced charge.
The first study case will be that of this
non-symmetrical charge
that will be connected using a delta setup.
We will see that it is the easiest study
that we can make, which can seem
paradoxical,
but we will see that
this way
of connecting in delta
is actually quite easy to resolve,
even for a non-symmetrical case.
We remind
the elementary values that we have
seen previously,
that is to say
we have here
the line
voltage,
the U_rs
which will be equal to this phase voltage
so I will write it U_ph1.
However,
as we have seen when studying the delta mode,
the line current
I_R
will be equal,
by Kirchhoff,
to the subtraction between I_1 and I_3
since we have this knot
here.
So the Kirchhof equations will greatly help
us to resolve such
a problem
of a non-symmetrical charge
since, finally,
knowing that
Z_1, Z_2 and Z_3 are different,
we just need to apply,
in a relatively simple way, Kirchhoff.
Then,
we remind you
what the three line voltage
U_rs, U_st and U_tr are equal to
in a symmetrical grid.
Thus,
U_rs
is equal to √3*U*e^j(π/6).
We then have a shift of 120 degrees
for U_st
with √3*U*e^j(-π/2)
and the third
U_tr
√3*U*e^j(5π/6).
This being said, and knowing that the
phase voltage on the terminals of each
impedance Z
is equal to the line voltage,
we can calculate, each time, for the
three values,
this time in an individual
manner, since we have a
non-symmetrical system,
we can calculate I_1
which is equal to the phase voltage U_ph1
divided by
Z_1
but this phase voltage U_ph1, as shown
on the drawing, is also
U_rs
divided by Z_1.
This gives me the phase current I_1
and in the same way, will be
able to calculate I_2:
U_st divided by
Z_2, and I_3:
U_tr
divided by Z_3.
Now that we have I_1, I_2, I_3,
we can, on each knot,
calculate the line currents I_r,
I_s
and I_t.
The three line current are calculated
by applying once again Kirchhoff
on the knot, as shown
previously
and then I_r is equal to
I_1
minus
I_3.
I remind you
that it is a vectorial
subtraction.
I_s
is equal to
I_2 minus
I_1 and
I_t
is equal to I_3
minus I_2.
The calculations are then quite long,
but
relatively simple
and need the calculation for each
branch
considered
separately, since it is non-symmetrical.
It is evident that,
in a symmetrical case,
we only look at one branche and all
the other branches
are simply shifted by 120 degrees.
It is not the case here
and each branch must be calculated
individually.
Now in the case of a charge which is,
this time, connected with
a wye setup.
In a wye setup, you have here
the presented diagram, with shows
a non-symmetrical impedance
connected in a wye manner,
with classically,
a neutral point that appears
and that be connected or not
to the network's neutral.
Thus, we will have two cases,
two solutions, if you want to
starting off with this diagram here
and we need to define now which
of these cases we are handling.
So two possibilities.
The first
is that we have this wye charge
whose neutral is not connected.
Often, the neural is not
connected
to the network, so it is possible
to have a case like ours
if the neutral is not connected. This will
be our case a)
non-connected neutral, so
the easiest way to resolve such a problem
is to
take
the circuit
that is in a wye setup, and
convert the charge as for a
delta setup.
When it is for a delta setup, we
can apply
the previous technique,
namely
the application of Kirchhoff's rules
on the circuit,
this time, a delta system.
Then, the conversion from wye to delta
is done as seen
in the previous lessons
using the rules
for the calculations of the impedances
Z_1, Z_2 and Z_3 which pass
in a wye setup, or a delta setup.
That is the easiest. Once we have
a non-connected neutral, it is enough
to convert this circuit or this
charge for a wye setup, and to pass it
in a delta
setup, before applying Kirchhoff's technique.
In the second case b), where the neutral is connected.
Here things obviously change as we have an
impedance Z_n, which is the impedance
through which the neutral
current will pass, to go back
to the source,
that needs to be taken into account.
We then need to calculate a certain number
of values
that will depend on the neutral voltage.
In particular,
we have a line current that can be
calculated,
still using Kirchhoff,
by taking the U_rn
minus U_n
and this divided by the impedance Z_1.
We can say, in the same way,
for I_s
U_sn
minus
U_n
divided by Z_2, and finally the third
current in the branche t, or in
the line t,
is U_tn
so the phase voltage, minus U_n
divided by
Z_3.
We can also say that
the neutral current, in the neutral
which is normally zero in a symmetrical
charge, but which
will be non zero in the non-symmetrical case it
is then equal to this voltage U_n divided by
the impedance
coming back from the neutral Z_n.
We can also say
that, and we know it,
this neutral current, by Kirchhoff,
is the sum
of the three line current, that
meet up.
From there, we can then replace a certain
number of elements
that come from what we indicated previously,
namely
I_n = I_r + I_s + I_t
and so, we replace with the three
elements that we have calculated
here I_r, I_s and I_t.
What does this give us?
This gives us
the following equation.
I_n
I put on one side the phase voltages
and on the other the neutral
voltages, so we have
U_rn divided by Z_1
plus
U_sn divided by Z_2
U_tn
divided by Z_3
minus
and we have the neutral voltage that
come here, evidently, and that
multiplies 1 divided by Z_1
plus 1 divided by Z_2
plus 1 divided by
Z_3.
This is equal to,
I repeat it, the neutral voltage
divided by Z_n.
We will then eliminate the current
I_n in this equation
and make the top
equation, here
and the bottom equation equal.
In this way, we eliminate
the neutral current
and we can set down
the equation by writing
U_n equal
and then, by extracting the neutral voltage.
We find
U_n equal
firstly
to 1 divided by Z_1, plus
1 divided by Z_2
plus 1 divided by Z_3
plus 1 divided by Z_n
and all this at the power -1
that multiplies
U_rn divided by Z_1
plus
U_sn
divided by Z_2, plus
U_tn
divided by Z_3.
To be clearer, I eliminate what I
put here to get the whole equation
and
then
what do we still need to do?
The whole work is now to calculate
U_rn by taking, each time,
the voltage U_rs
that we have here
and by subtracting this voltage
U_n of the neutral that we have just calculated,
of course in a vectorial
way.
But this lets us
calculate the voltage U_n,
so
on the neutral impedance, to determine
completely the
different values of a non-symmetrical
charge that was connected
in wye, and whose neutral
is connected.
In conclusion, we saw the
non-symmetrical charge, we saw
how, in a delta setup,
we can in a relatively simple way
determine these different values
and by
applying the Kirchhoff equations
for the wye setup
two cases presented themselves, either the
neutral is connected
and then we need to calculate everything,
in particulat the neutral
voltage
and to a relatively complex vectorial
calculation on each of these
values.
Or else, the neutral is not connected
and it is enough to switch
from a wye to a delta setup
and to repeat what we have seen
for the delta setup.