Hello, to this point, we have only dealt with
steady state power supply in this electrotechnology class,
which means
that the excitations of the circuit , whether
currents or voltage, are supposed
to be established since an infinite time
whether it is continuous rating which generates continuous currents
and voltages, or sinusoidal steady state, which generates
sinusoidal currents and voltages.
Is defined as transient state every
state change in a system
which the corresponding disturbance
is a length similar or inferior to the
biggest
time constant of the system.
The most frequent case matches
with the interlock or the triggering
of the RLC circuit
on its power supply.
But it could also be a breakdown, a dysfunction or
a particular functionning as those used in
many common electronic devices.
Calculation methods developed
until today are not valid anymore
because it is not a continuous rating
nor an alternatif rating with only one frequency.
New calculation methods will be established.
Mathematically speaking, the interlock
is transcribed by a function called
"Out-of-Step".
that we will name ε(t) which can take for value 1 or 0.
We will see how does a resistor, a capacitor
or an inductance behaves, if we send in a jump.
We will now calculate their step response.
We will set 2 rules to govern those
phenomenons.
Finally, we will present you
a method to solve a given problem.
The out of step is defined as a time function.
This function is called ε(t).
Its value is zero for a time between
minus infinity and 0.
It goes instantly
to the value 1 at the time t=0,
and is equal to 1
for a time
between 0 and infinity.
The state 0
corresponds to
a circuit triggered, and
the 1 state corresponds to
an interlocked cicuit.
We can write the mathmatical
relation of ε(t).
It is equal to 0
for a time between minus infinite to 0.
and it is equal to 1 for a time
between 0 and infinite.
A voltage jump.
will be defined by the following relation
the voltage as function of time is equal to
the  continuous
voltage that we
switch to the circuit
multiplied by this function ε(t).
We call step response , the response
of a voltage jump
or a current
of the circuit
Practically
this jump will be made by
a two position switch
that we will represented this way.
A switch is open,
before the switching moment
where t is equal
to zero
just before the switching.
Lets look at the step response of linear elements
known as R,L and C.
Now, let's calculate the step response
of a resistor
that is switched on a voltage supply.
Let the following sketch
be a voltage supply
whith a value U
A resistor R
that is initially
short-circuited on itself
at a time t=0, we will
switch it
to the voltage supply U.
Those are the following values
inside the circuit
the current
that goes through the resistor
i(t), and
the voltage measured on the terminals
of the resistor called u(t).
In the time domain
this representation of u(t)
is given by the following graph.
u(t)
as function of time
before the switching,
the voltage is 0
it goes immediately to the value
U, at t=0
and keeps this value
U
infinitely.
The characteristic equation
that describes the behavior
of the resistor is given
by i = u/R.
We have determinated with the out-of-step
the expression of u, that is equal to
ε(t)
mutliplied by U/R
and this
is simply equal to,
ε(t)*I.
This is
the expression
of the step response, i
caused by the voltage jump of the resistor
that we can also represent in the time domain
the following way.
i(t)
as a function of t
is equal to 0
before the interlock
goes instantely
to the value
I
and stays to this value after the interlock.
So we can see that the step
response of a resistor to a current jump
is also
a current jump.
We can use the following reasoning
for a current jump
we can represent
the following sketch, a current source
for value
I
that we switch to a resistor R.
Initially
the resistor is short-circuited on itself,
so there is no current
at t=0
we switch the resistor to the current source.
The values
inside the circuit, are again
the current
as function of time that goes through
the resistor
and the voltage drop doesn't appear
on the resistor, u(t)
Again, if we express
the current
as function of time, so in a time domain
we get the following sketch
as function of time
i(t).
We have no current
before the interlock
and a current that goes instantly
to the value i
when t=0 and
stays at the value i.
The characteristic equation
is given by u
what we are looking for
is equal to R * i
i is expressed with this concept of out-of-step
ε(t)
multiplied by i
multiplied by R, and this is also
ε(t)
multiplied by U
that we can picture again
in the
time domain
the time axis of t
is equal to 0
before the interlock and
instantly
takes the value u
at the time t=0
and keeps this value.
What we see now, is that the current
is the image of the voltage, and vice-versa.
Now let's calculate the step response of an
inductance to a voltage jump.
We consider
the following sketch: a voltage source
for value U
an inductance L
that is short-circuited on itself
initially
a switch allowing the switching of the
inductance on the voltage source at the time t=0.
The characteristic equation
of the voltage
u(l)
as function of the current i
that goes through it
is given by u = L *(di/dt).
By integrating this equation
we get that
the current is equal to
1/L
multiplied by the integral, from -infinity to t,
of u(t)dt.
In this case a voltage jump
the voltage
of the inductance as function of time,
is equal to
ε(t) * u.
We consider the initial condition, which means,
that the current
that goes through
the inductance at the time t=0
i(t=0) = I_0
This is a general case.
So the characteristic equation becomes
i and is equal to
1/L, multiplied by the integral
taken
from 0 to t.
Which means that starting
to the interlock of U
multiplied by
ε(t)
multiplied by dt
plus the initial
current in the inductance, I_0.
The resolution
of this equation for
t bigger than 0
gives us that
i(t)
is equal to I_0
plus
(U*t) / L.
We can see a linear growth
of the current
as function of time.
Represented in the time domain
we get
for the voltage
as function of time
a zero voltage
before the interlock
an instant voltage jump
at the time t=0, and
a value
that is equal to
the value u(t)
which is constant after the interlock.
For the current
the temporal representation
starts
at a value
I_0, which is the initial condition, then
a linear growth of the current
according to the time
whose slope is equal to U / L.
Now lets perform
a current jump through an inductance.
We consider
the following electric circuit
a current supply
for value I
an inductance
for value L
and a switch allowing the switching
at a time t=0
of the current supply on the inductance
The characteristic equation
is given by u(t) = L*(di/dt).
Warning
u(t) is
the current that goes through the inductance
i(t).
We can represent in this time domain
the variation of t as function of time
zero
before the switching
and instantly
the current
will get to the value i
at the time t=0.
We can see that the expression of u
is equal to 0
when there is no current fluctuation.
Which means that
before the interlock, there is no current
fluctuation, and
after the interlock, there is no current fluctuation
Which means that
this expression is equal to
zero
for t  0
that we can represent
as function of time
like this
of t.
Zero voltage
before the interlock
and a zero voltage after the interlock,
because there is no current fluctuations.
On the otherside
this equation
this voltage is infinite a the time t = 0
Why? Well, because the current fluctuation
is infinite
and so
the voltage
given by the current supply should be infinite.
This function that we call "Dirac function"
is not physically reachable
in physics, the notion of infinity doesn't make sense,
because infinity can never be
reached.
In math, there is no way to describe it
easily.
we come to
a first rule
which tells us that a current jump
in an inductance is impossible
Now, lets do a voltage jump
u(t) = ε(t)*U
on the terminals
of a capacitor.
We considerate the following circuit,
made of a voltage supply for value U
a capacitor
that is initially
short-circuited on itself, and
that we will switch
thanks to a switch
on the voltage supply  U at a time
t = 0.
The values inside the circuit are the current
that goes through the capacitor
i(t)
and the voltage at the terminals of the capacitor
u(t).
The characteristic equation
of the capacitor is given by
u = 1/C
times the integral of i*dt.
If we integrate this equation
we get that i = C*(du/dt).
This current
takes the value 0
for t < 0
and also 0 for t > 0
because the voltage fluctuation
is zero.
The voltage
is zero before the interlock and goes instantly
to the value u
at the time t = 0.
If we draw a step response
i, as function of time
we have values
that are zero
before the interlock because there are
no voltage fluctuation
and also
a zero value
after the interlock because there is no voltage fluctuation.
So the current
is equal to 0
before the interlock
and equal to 0
after the interlock.
On the otherside
during the transition, when we do a
voltage jump
on the capacitor
this expression tends towards infinity
and so
the current tends towards
infinity
during the switching
This means again that the
voltage supply should
give us an infinite current
to do an instant
voltage jump on the terminals of a capacitor.
We get to a second rule which tells us that
a voltage jump on the terminals of a
capacitor is impossible.
Now lets considerate a forth case
which consists of calculating
the step response of a capacitor
subjected to a current jump.
We consider again
the following electronic sketch, made of
a current supply
equal to I
a capacitor C
and a switch that allows the switching of the capacitor
on the current supply at a time
t = 0.
The characteristic equation
of the voltage
on the terminals of the capacitor
as function of the current
given by the expression
U =
1/C
times the integral to -infinity to t
of i*dt.
Knowing that
i = ε(t) * I
that we picture here, in a
timing diagramm.
A zero value
before the switching,
and a value i
after the switching.
Again, the initial condition
is the volatge
which
exist on the terminals of the capacitor before the switching of the switch
at the time t=0, and is equal to
U_0.
So we can now rewrite the equation
with the integral by splitting this integral from
-infinity to 0
and from 0 to infinity.
So it comes that
u is equal to
U_0
which is the part of
the integral before the switching
plus
1/C times the integral from 0 to t
of i*ε(t)dt.
By solving this equation
we get that the voltage is equal to U_0 plus (I/C)*t
and this for
t>0.
If we picture
this equation in the timing diagramm
we get
the following curve, as function of time
at an initial value
before the switching, and
after the switching
we see that we have a straight line
a linear growth of the voltage
with the current
which the slope is equal to
I/C.
After studying
all theses cases of step response
we can draw the following conclusions
which tell us that, a current jump
in an inductance is impossible, and that a voltage jump at the terminals of
a capacitor is also
impossible.
These propreties allows us to establish the
integration constants
in the case of a real circuit.