Hello, during the first lesson, we have laid
the theoretical bases of
the behavior of three linear elements
R,L and C with
abrupt state fluctuations, that is to say
transient states.
During this lesson, we will see a few examples
of applications  that will
give you an idea of the importance of
transient states.
We will see a few examples of applications
while keeping in mind that those are
basic fundamentals that are relatively
simplified for the clearness of the
explanations.
I hope that these examples will help you and
will arouse your curiosity.
Lets see a first application example.
It is an engine spark plug.
We consider the following circuit that is
made of a matrix, the
12V battery
of the vehicle
an inductance
that we call ignition coil, and
a switch, that allows a current to go through
the inductance, or to shut it off.
We connect on the terminals
of the inductance a spark plug.
This spark plug, with
its electrode, here.
This spark plug can be represented, here,
by this electronic symbol.
During the current
cut in the inductance, we saw during the
previous lessons, that an abrupt current cut
in an inductance could cause
an infinite voltage.
Here, the voltage will not be infinite, but
it will reach the breakdown voltage of
the medium in which
the spark plug is.
and cause a spark.
All the energy stored
in the inductance will be found, here
on the terminals
of the electrodes
of the spark plug.
This spark will occur on the terminals of the spark plug.
Lets considerate an second application case,
it is the spot
welding.
This process is used a lot in the
industry and consists
in assambling metal sheets together.
The principle is relatively simple, we start with
a charged
capacitor
that will be in this cabinet, and
through
two electrodes
we will short-cut
the capacitor
through the plates.
We saw that short-circuiting a capacitor
is forbidden, and
causes high or almost infinite currents
here the electric resistance is not
perfectly at zero, we will
get a current that is extremely
high
of the order of a few kilo-amps, and
by Joule effect
so by the heating of the material, we will
merge
the material, and therefore realise
this welding.
We see, here, an example of achievement
with weldings of
automotive sheet
on those spots.
Another application example is SMPS
(witching-mode power supply).
Here, the goal is to avoid using
a transformer like the one we use for
electrical networks
by replacing it by a chopper circuit.
This means that the execution
will only be in transient state
and we will see that we will have a high weight
gain
and an increase of the efficiency.
We see on this circuit
that as function of the voltage , which is
constant, given by the
voltage supply, here
is a sequence
of power cuts and interlocks
of the circuit
so we get, at the output
of our circuit, a voltage than can be
lowered down
to a certain level
or, eventually, lowered to a different
level
as function of the time ratio
of the interlocks
and the triggering of the circuit.
This kind of SMPS, also called
a switcher
is very well known
in demotic, for example
we all know
lightbulb
dimmers
that allows to reduce the brightness of
a lightbulb.
Another example, the switched-mode
power supply, but this time
used as a voltage step-up.
As previously
we see
that starting at certain continuous voltage
which is the voltage supply of the circuit
and a sequence of interlocks and triggering
of the circuit on its power supply
we can have an output voltage
higher than the power supply.
An example of the use of an step-up SMPS
is the voltage regulator
for example the xenon headlamps
of a car that we can picture here
by this lightbulb
with gas
in this enclosure
This gas is not
an electric conductor when it is stable
we must create an overvoltage to initiate an electrical arc
and therefore
causes the flow of the current into the lightbulb, and
by this same event
the lightning of the lightbulb.
This is now one last application example. It is
the energy distribution
on very long distances.
Here we talk about
inter-continent distances.
Increasingly,
the diversity of the energy supply
means that
electrical power plants are scattered
all throughout
Europe, Asia
an even Africa
and those distances are extremely long,
we are talking here of several thousands of
kilometers.
If we look at
the electrical
distribution line
we can see that
between
the source
which is the place where the
electricity is produced, and
the consumer, here
there is an electrical line that is characterized by
the following circuit.
A first model
of a line in alternative state,
we can see that this example has
an inductance, here
that will be as high as the distance is long
and therefore the voltage drops of the
inductance terminals  will also
be high.
Capacitors
connected in parrallel, that
represent
the current leaks
in the electrical line.
Those capacitors
are as big as the line is long too,
and therefore
the impedance
the impedance, seen by the line of this
constructor, will be
as small
as the current leaks are big (in this example).
hence the interest
to moove to
a DC
state.
We have, here, the sketch
where the example of the DC line
where the inductances and capacitors
have disappeared because the frequency is zero.
So, there is only this resistor left.
Just like the energy distribution on long
distances using the alternative state
we need to rise the voltage
to
lower the current
for a given power
and therefore, we will, here
create
a step-up voltage, that allows
the energy transport
at a high voltage and then a voltage reducer
that allows
to reuse this
voltage, in a lower form
directly
by the consummer.
Finaly
we will compare the size of different power supplies.
We see here that the classic power supply
made with an alternative
50 Hz  transformer
and here a switched-mode power supply,
we see that this one is much more compact.
This seconde example
shows very well the difference
of two power-supplies
one, with
a transformer, and the other one with
a switch-mode
for a same given power, we can see that
the SMPS (switched-mode power supply) is much
more compact.
Those few examples show the diversity
and the importance of
these transient states in many devices.
During the following lessons, we will study
the details and learn
how to solve such transient states.