Hello, during the last lecture
we have treated  the most complete
case of an RLC circuit in series.
We have defined the equations that
would allow us to find the solutions
for current expression.
According to the discriminant sign, the solutions
of the characteristic equation,
of the 2nd degree
are three different solutions
During this lecture, we will
develop these three solutions
We will start with a recall of
the essentiel results that we got
at the previous lecture
and then, we will develop the
three solutions for the current
expression
that are solutions, called, ''Over-damped''
"damped oscillatory" and "critical damping".
The current expressions that we
have
obtained
were under the form
i(t) is equal to a constant
times a sum of exponentials.
Where λ_1 and λ_2 are
the solutions
of the characteristic of
2nd degree
that we can write, for
simplifications
-R/2L ± ω.
The expression of λ_1 and λ_2
being a sum of two terms that
will be here, in the exponential.
And knowing that the exponential of a
sum is the product of the exponential,
we can rewrite the equation
of the current, in the following way
i(t) equal to
the constant times the exponential
of (-R/2L) * t
times
the sum of the two exponentials.
We recall again that the initial
conditions at time t = 0 were
the current at time t = 0
is equal to 0
and the voltage
at the capacitor's terminals, at time t = 0,
is equal to 0, and the capacitor is
initially empty.
For t=0, we had
U = L * (di/dt).
If we consider the first case where the
discriminant
is bigger than 0
we get two real solutions
And in that case, the current
equation
can be written, slightly modified,
as
i(t)
which is equal
to a constant
times
a first exponential
times the sum of the
exponentials
e^ωt - e^(-ωt)
divided by two,
and we recognize
this expression being the expression
of a hyperbolic
sine.
We can therefore write
this equation in a light
way
and we have that A'
multiplied by e^((-R/2L) * t)
multiplied by hyperbolic sine of ωt.
The initial condition that we have described
before
and that gave us the following equation:
U = L*(di/dt)
allows us to rewrite
with the derivative of the current,
the following expression
knowing
that the current expression is composed
of a product
of two functions,
a first function f
and a second fonction g
and knowing that
the derivative
of a product function
is equal to the sum
f ' * g + f * g'
we get
an expression
a little bit
heavier, but that
is written as: L*A_1'
times
the derivative of the function f, it is
the function itself
times the intern derivative
minus R
divided by 2L
times the exponential
-R/2L * t
times the function g
meaning, the hyperbolic sine
of ωt
plus the function f
exponential of -R/2L * t
times the
derivative of the function
hyperbolic sine that
is a hyperbolic cosine
of ωt
times the intern derivative
if we apply this condition at
time t = 0
this term
turns 1
this term becomes 1 as well
this one
and this one 1
We therefore get a relatively
simple expression
that allows us to say that
A_1' = U/ωL.
We can finally write that
the current expression
as function of time
being
the product
of a constant, the constant that we
just computed
U/ωL, times an exponential
of exponent -R/2L * t
times the hyperbolic
sine of ωt.
It is then, the product
of two functions.
If i represent them separately
in a graphic,
we first have
a decreasing
exponential
two time constant
2L/R
therefore, something as a
decreasing exponential
times a hyperbolic sine of ωt
with that appearance.
The hyperbolic sine as function of time
can be complex in terms of
mathematics, we can verify that
the solution is still bounded when
t tends to infinity.
And the product of the two
gives the function of the current.
Thus, if we have
an RLC circuit with R, L and C
such as the discriminant under
square root
of the solution of
the equation of second degree
is bigger than 0
we then obtain a temporal
evolution of the current, which is the product
of these two functions
that we will see in the video that will follow.
We see first
an increase of the current, and then
a decrease.
In the case where the discriminate
is smaller than 0
we get two imaginary
solutions.
If we write
the following expression
ω = j*ω'
we can write the equation
of the current which is transformed as follows.
i(t) is equal
to a second constant A_1''
multiplied by the exponential of -R/2L
times t
multiplied by the sum of
the two exponentials
divided by 2j
where we recognize
here, the expression
of a sine
of ω't.
Thus, we can write this equation
in a lighter manner,
such as A_1''
multiplied by the exponential of -R/2L* t
multiplied by a sinus
ω't.
Once again, at time t=0
the same initial conditions
as the previous case
allow us
to obtain the integration contant
such as A_1'' is equal to U
divided by ω'L.
Therefore, once again, we can write
the temporal expression of
the current as
the product of the constant that
we have just determined
ω'L
multiplied by an exponential
function where the exponent is equal to
-R/2L * t
and, this time, multiplied
by a sinusoidal function
sin(ω't).
If we represent these two functions
separately
in a temporal graphic
we have
first of all
a sinusoid
of a certain amplitude
multiplied by
an exponential decreasing function,
where this is of type
sinusoidal
this
of type exponential
decreasing exponent
with its time constant equal to
2L/R
and, again, if we deal
with this RLC circuit where R,L and C
are defined such as
the discriminant under the square root of the solution of
the 2nd degree equation is smaller than 0
then, the current
in the circuit
evolves in the following way, as
shown in the video.
We have a sinus
that the amplitude decreases
exponentially.
The last case, is
the case where
the discriminant under the square root is
equal to 0.
In that case, we have only one
real solution for ω.
In this critical case, the solution is obtained from
either solution.
We will consider the 1st one that we found.
i(t) is equal to U over
ωL, multiplied by the exponential
multiplied by the hyperbolic
sine
of ωt.
And when moving
to the limit, meaning
ω tends to 0, we can substitute
the hyperbolic
sine
function
with the first term of the
taylor series
that we won't demonstrate here, but
for
ωt
that tends to zero
we have that the hyperbolic sine of ωt
tends to
ωt.
The solution of critical dumping
could be written under the form
i(t) which is equal to
the constant
U/ωL
multiplied by the exponential of -R/2L * t
multiplied by
ωt.
And this, we can simplify it
into U/L multiplied by the exponential
of -R/2L * t
times t.
They are
two temporal functions
where one is a decreasing exponential
again
with a time constant equal to 2L/R
multiplied by
(this is the exponential
with a negative exponent)
multiplied by a function t
which is a simple straight.
Once again, if we deal with an RLC circuit in series
where
R,L and C are defined such as
the discriminant
under the square root of the solution of
the 2nd degree equation is equal to 0, then
we get the following current evolution.
It looks similar
to the first solution, but of
different nature.
Here we are, we have treated the cases RC and RL, where the
differential equation of 1st order,
leads to exponential solutions.
We have treated the RLC case, the most complete,
that gives de differential
equations
of 2nd order, and therefore
three different solutions.
For the most complex circuit, you should know that it is the combinations
of these cases, and are therefore
treated in the same way.