An archive is like a living organism:
if you want to understand fully
its current structure
you need to understand its history
because an archive changes over time.
It moves, it gets restructured,
it gets old.
Another way of seeing an archive
is seeing it as a volume of volumes
because what does the archive really
is organizing spaces.
You have a big space
cut into smaller spaces
which then lead to the conservation,
the indexation of smaller special units :
Box, registers, statue, painting.
Let's go and have a concrete example.
You see here the corridors
of the state archives in Venice.
80 kilometers of documents,
documenting a thousand years of history.
Venice is a special case because of
its political origin,
it maintained an archival system
over very very long periods.
And this is that archival system
composed of very long document series
that we can now use to think about
the possibility of recreating the density
of the past.
You have documents, registers
but you have also maps for instance.
Not one map, but thousands of maps.
And these maps give a very detailed account
about the structure and spatial organization
of Venice.
But also of many other places.
Let's go a bit deeper in the different typologies
of documents we may encounter.
Administrative documents, testaments,
contracts.
All the documents that permit to have
the organization of a city.
It there are some work to be done,
if there are some transformation in the city
there are new laws that are voted.
All this is documented in the archives.
They used to be at different places in Venice
and it's only at the beginning
of the 19th century
that they got in a single,
very big space.
An ancient covent which is
the state archive of Venice today.
Very huge building, 300 rooms,
80 kilometers of shelves
and the question : how can we transform
that physical space
in an information system.
Are we capable of searching
in so many documents.
What type of technology can we use
to make it accessible.
3 steps are key to this transformation.
The first step is the digitization :
we need first to transform
theses physical documents into images,
millions of images.
Second step : transcription, indexation,
segmentation and analysing the documents
so that they are searchable very easily.
And last step : connecting the information
which are in the document in a big graph
linking people and places.
Typical use case for us would be
a search engine
I would like to be capable
of typing the name of a Venitian
for instance Battista Nani
and find all the documents
that are related with that person.
It seems an easy thing to do
and we do it every day
for the data about the present,
it's quite difficult to do
for the data about the past.
And this is the core subject
of this course.