Hello, and welcome to the sixth module in
the MOOC
on the management of protected areas in Africa.
This module focuses on a crucial question
for the conservation of protected areas:
how do we fund them.
Sylvie Goyet will be fully running this module.
So this week, the module will be structured
like this:
the first lesson will be on financial planning.
That answers the question
about the financial needs of protected areas.
As for the second lesson,
it will look into the economic values of protected
areas,
How do we assess them,
is there an under-valuation of natural capital,
etc.?
The different possible sources of obtaining
funds
will be the topic of the third lesson.
The fourth lesson will then talk about the
financial mechanisms
that can be considered for protected areas.
Projects, trusts funds, for example, etc.
The fifth lesson will focus quickly
on compensation mechanisms and biodiversity
income mechanisms.
The last lesson will examine this week's convention,
once again,
and this time, we will talk about CMS,
which looks after migratory species.
And finally, we will do a quick summary
of the important points mentioned in this
module,
and we will give you assessment related to
this module.
There we go.
Let's get going,
and we hope you have an excellent sixth week
with us!