In this first episode, we are going to look
together
at the basic concept of financial planning.
This is about assessing several things.
On the one hand, the needs of a protected
area,
identifying possible revenue, funding deficiencies.
Then studying preconditions for the set up
of any financial mechanism.
Is this possible?
Feasible?
Do institutional, legislative conditions,
the capacity of a protected area
lead it to the establishment of a certain
mechanism?
And finally to consolidate everything,
it is recommended to develop a business plan;
we will look at that together in part three.
First and foremost, let's look at financial
requirements.
When identifying financial requirements, note
that it is important
on the one hand, to make the link between
the management plan's objectives,
in terms of activity, required investment,
and this, based on needs and priorities over
time,
and I will come back to this soon.
Secondly, to study opportunities to reduce
costs, optimization.
Also to take into account the effectiveness
of the financial management system of a protected
area,
that is the accounting system, the classification
of expenditure,
cash flow management, transparency of financial
data
and the requirements of audits.
I cannot emphasize enough, the need for good
skills
when it comes to the financial management
for a protected area.
Also to analyse carefully
the actual financial situation of previous
years.
But keep in mind
that budgets for protected areas are generally
determined,
depending on available funds
and not on the actual needs of a protected
area.
This management by default is of course a
pragmatic one,
but it does not always allow us to see good
results on the field,
hence the need to set up a business plan.
And finally, extrapolating future needs.
As I have mentioned,
the financial needs of a protected area are
to be evaluated
depending on the management plan's goals and
activities.
But you will have noted that a protected area's
financial needs
are also dependent on its life cycle.
Financial needs and priorities are not the
same
throughout the life of a protected area.
Let's look at a fictional example
of a protected area's budget over 20 years.
At the very beginning of the life cycle of
the protected area
in the identification phase,
we note the great financial needs
for monitoring,
for scientific expertise, to determine baseline
situations.
Fairly important needs
also in consultation with the communities,
with all interested parties.
Then, in the creation phase,
often supported by donors, by projects.
It is at this time that the infrastructure
of the protected area is built,
that personnel is recruited,
which are important needs.
Then throughout the operations,
of the protected area in an operational phase,
budgets are more or less balanced.
However, you will note the differences.
For example, here,
with a tourism project,
a donor project most likely.
A little further on, we have a community development
project.
Still a little further on,
a conservation project or a restoration project.
You can see that these different projects
involve jumps
in the budget of a protected area.
You will have understood that on the basis
of identifying
the protected area's needs,
the identification of plausible sources of
finance,
we can identify the shortfall, the funding
gap.
Before searching for potential funding,
it is important to look at preconditions,
on the one hand, in society, in that country,
and also the protected area's own capacities.
Firstly we will look at the preconditions
on a macro level.
Are the roles and the values of the sites
and ecosystems assessed and shared by all?
Do general policies fully recognise the roles
and values of the MPA?
And have laws been adopted
that implement these PUBLIC policies?
Are there technical capacities, abilities,
able to develop certain financing options?
And finally, is there a system of governance
that provides
and emphasizes the values of transparency,
responsibility and confidence?
The key questions to ask.
Firstly a practical question.
Which mechanism can be set up the most efficiently?
Then, we look at the current legal
and administrative provisions of the country
which can allow for the SET UPof the new mechanism.
Are difficulties anticipated in administrating,
implementing, in raising or distributing funds?
Look to see if this new mechanism
will be seen as fair and legitimate.
And I emphasize this point:
the financial collection mechanism must be
seen
to be fair and legitimate
by all the parties involved.
We look at the support by the interested stakeholders
and government
for setting up this new mechanism.
And finally, we remain vigilant to the environmental
impact
of this mechanism on the protected area's
goods and services.
To consolidate all this information,
we will prepare what we call a business plan.
The business plan is used in all sectors of
the economy.
It serves to compare different options
and to study the financial viability of a
certain initiative.
Adapted to protected areas,
the business plan allows us to maximize environmental
results
with an often limited financial contribution.
It allows the comparison between different
options in the long term
and future planning, to better plan incomes
and financial needs of a protected area.
The business plan must allow to put into perspective
over five to ten years, on the one hand, expected
expenditure,
investments, personnel, operations, activities,
and on the other hand, expected revenue,
self-financing, national budget, donors
and projects and other mechanisms.
Note that is a tool of internal management
which gives us a technical and financial long
term vision.
You will have noted that protected area budgets
are generally determined based on available
funds.
A business plan allows us to implement
and identify the actual needs of a protected
area.
It allows us to determine priority investments.
Also, don't forget, the business plan,
allows us to communicate and present a clear
and concise view
of the activity of a protected area in the
long term
and to show financial needs.
Here you can see a fictional example, once
again, of a business plan.
Don't be concerned with all the numbers,
it's just to give you an idea.
This table has been adapted from the business
plan
of the Iwokrama protected area in Guyana.
You will note that expenditure is organized
based on activity programs.
conservation expenses,
administration, Etc. it's a good thing.
This allows us to make the connection with
the management plan.
You will note that revenue is defined as best
as possible
according to information, and outlook,
and total revenue,
whether from sales, tourism revenue,
merchandise, and handicrafts,
is recorded and extrapolated over the coming
years.
Finally, you'll note that we can identify...
the gap, the shortcomings,
throughout the five years of the business
plan.
THEN It's about, for THE protected area, to
identify fundraising actions
marketing
and external relations to bridge this gap.
The procedure to elaborate the business plan
is well defined in this guide
which I suggest you take a look at.
It is a guide on how to formulate a simplified
business plan
for protected areas
written by Benjamin Landreau for FIBA.
Note particularly the different stages.
Firstly, define the process of the business
plan.
Who is in charge?
What consultations are necessary?
Then, analyze past financial execution.
Then, determine the medium and long term needs,
investments, operating expenses,
salaries, staffing requirements.
Then, indicate the existing sources of finance
and extrapolate potential revenue.
Finally, analyze the funding gap and different
possible scenarios
and evaluate other sources of funding.
This episode has given you the basics on financial
planning.
Note that striving for financial sustainability
is essential for a protected area.
It is about identifying financial requirements
in the long term,
studying and evaluating the preconditions
of the country, the site
and the protected area itself
and to define financing options.
And all this generally within the framework
of a business plan.
Several reference manuals are available.
I have suggested one of them.
I also invite you to have a look at the UNDP's
BIOFIN website,
the work of the TEEB initiative,
mine is blue, this is green, but...
The Economy of Ecosystems and Biodiversity,
a guide which will be available very soon,
Financial Planning for National Systems of
Protected Areas,
and finally, the reference guide, Sustainable
Financing of Protected Areas,
A Global Review of Challenges and Options.
We have reached the end of this episode.
I suggest you have a look at the reference
materials
and I wish you a good day.