Hello.
In this episode, we are going to study
the concept of the value of a protected area.
As in, which goods and services have a value?
What is this value?
How do we measure it, how do we quantify it?
Finally, which methods should we use?
Protected areas have ecological goods and
services that have an ecological value.
That is why they are protected.
But they also have social, cultural and economic
values.
And they can be for different groups, for
different levels of populations,
for communities, for the state,
for the whole of humanity.
Each of these levels place a value on these
goods and services.
But be careful, you can't put a price on the
environment, of course.
Several guidelines and documents are available
for you to refer to.
On the one hand, I recommend
the FFEM's valuation report on its Marine
Protected Areas projects,
and especially Section 8:
Economic Valuation and Calculation
of the rate of return of AMP Projects.
There's also IUCN's guidelines:
Economic Values of Protected Areas: Guidelines
for Protected Area Managers
These guidelines were written in 1998,
and so the methods probably need a little
update,
but the basics are in there.
Economic valuation of a protected area's goods
and services
involves identifying its goods and services
and quantifying and measuring their value.
First of all, we need to identify these goods
and services.
What are they?
And who are they for?
We will look at placing a value on these goods
and services
for the groups involved.
And finally, we will consider
whether or not the benefits of these goods
and services
are being received and by whom, by which groups?
Are some groups receiving the benefits more
than others,
and that's why the protected areas are threatened?
Let's look at it together.
Why do we need to assess the value of
the goods and services of a protected area?
It is to justify important investments that
are needed to protect a site.
The decision makers, i.e., the state most
often, will need to make decisions between
different investments ; a protected area and
an education system for example.
It's about demonstrating
that protecting a site produces important
values.
Applying economic methods
to assess the value of services linked to
the environment
therefore allows us to compare the costs and
the benefits of a protected area
or the extent to which an ecosystem has improved.
It enables us to compare different uses and
different scenarios.
Notice that the studies are not yet widly
spread in this field,
but they are informative.
It is also noticeable that nearly everywhere
managing long term resources and ecosystems
is more cost-effective and profitable
than exploiting these goods and services in
the short term.
For example, in Canada, overfishing of cod
drove the collapse of stocks.
In the short term, the fishing industry gained
an enormous amount of money,
but the stock has run out,
and that cost the state in social expenditure
more than two billion dollars, mainly to compensate
fishermen.
These two billion would have been quite useful
and would have easily been enough
to develop a strict and sustainable management
system for this fishing industry.
Notice that the valuation of these goods and
services
does not necessarily result in a financial
flow
that guarantees sustainability and protection
of the site.
Measures must be taken to capture these values
and to generate revenue that will enable the
site to be protected
and the sustainable development for communities.
I've already highlighted that economic valuation
involves
identifying and assessing the quantitative
value
of the goods and services.
We're talking about exchange value,
the price of a good or service on the market,
of the use value of the good or service.
This could be different from the market price.
For example, water has an important value
in use,
but its exchange value per cubic meter of
water is low.
There is also the emotional value
that we attach to certain goods and services.
So we talk about a total economic value,
that breaks down, as you can see here,
into the use value and the non-use value.
Frequently, only the use value is taken into
account and monetized.
The use value is what you identify
through fishing, tourism, leisure revenues
etc.
Indirect use value is coastal protection,
sewage treatment, waste treatment,
or erosion control.
There are also option values,
which could be the interests of pharmaceutical
industries,
who look to preserve ecosystems that are not
yet well known.
They would do this to exploit genes and plants
for medicine.
Note also that in the non-use values,
there is the existence value,
which is the habitat itself,
the beauty of the site, which we should not
forget.
We also identify the bequest value,
which is the preservation of resources for
future generations.
If the concept of total economic value technique
is relevant
for helping decision-making,
it is important to remember the limitations
of these methods
and of the technique itself.
On one hand, notice that the technique is
considered from a human point of view.
The intrinsic value of biodiversity
or the value that an animal species would
place on another species or habitat
is not taken into account.
Notice also that different groups can place
different values
to the same good or service.
The obvious example is the antelope.
Some might place the value as just looking
at the antelope
and others might prefer to eat it.
Calculating a total economic value therefore
generally brings with it
problems with conflict of values,
and sometimes, with double-counting, or with
values not taken into account.
Finally, note that it is a long, difficult
and expensive exercise.
Frequently, it is not necessary to conduct
a full study.
It could therefore be useful to conduct relevant
analysis
that depend on the manager's needs.
For example, it could be only on the use values.
Putting a price on the environment is not
simple.
Despite the difficulties, economists have
suggested multiple methods
to assess the value of an environmental asset.
Before anything else, it is important
to define the good's user and client for that
situation.
Is it the protected area's inhabitants, those
who live on its outskirts,
the government, the country's businesses,
the NGOs, the international community etc?
After that, we need to frame,
confirm the study's limits,
the timeframe, the data and the available
budget.
Finally, the valuation method needs to be
chosen.
Regarding the method,
the easiest is to refer to the economic values
of the market
to measure the direct use values,
for example, the value of the protected area,
in terms of the tourism service, is measured
by hotel nights,
rights of entry and the location of vehicles.
When no market exists,
we will try to estimate the value
that the clients and users can place on that
good.
We could directly ask those involved.
This method is called a contingent valuation
and it generally relies on their willingness
to pay.
We would ask them,
"How much would you be prepared to give to
save pandas?
To have clean beaches?"
We often use this method for existence or
option values.
They are however subject to a lot of criticism.
The other option is to observe the behavior
of those involved.
Some of the methods used are the following.
The hedonic valuation: we compare the price
that the consumers are prepared to pay
for goods that are similar, but in different
environments.
For example, to determine the value of the
sea,
we assess the difference in price between
two similar apartments,
but where only one has a sea view.
The method for the cost of transport:
we estimate the value that people place on
a good
by measuring how much they spend in terms
for transport.
We can also look at and value their spending
on protection and restoration.
We measure the cost of the deterioration of
the environment,
by calculating how much we would have to pay
to replace or restore that good.
Notice that none of these methods really meet
our full satisfaction from a theory perspective,
and in practice, it isn't much better,
since several methods employed simultaneously
can amount to different results.
We must therefore be cautious.
But considerable progress has been made in
this area,
and the valuation tool is essential
to help the decision-makers to make the choices
that need to be made.
In terms of case studies,
there are relatively many economic studies
on coral reef ecosystems.
Here is one that you will also find in your
course documents.
Here, an example of a study
on the total economic value of coral reefs,
mangroves,
and seagrass in Martinique.
This document is also in your course documents.
Please note that the use values linked to
fishing and tourism
have been well documented,
such as for example, this study on iQoliqoli
in Fiji.
I said it in the introduction,
identifying goods and giving them a value
is not enough
to ensure that large revenues are generated
for the protected area.
It is a question of capturing the value
of the goods and services of a protected area.
For example, by using taxes
on the use of the protected area's resources,
i.e., access fees.
For tourism, it is clearer: entrance fees,
concessions on infrastructures, taxes, fees
for tours.
For a service, such as carbon sequestration
from mangroves, it's more complicated:
there is the REDD+ project.
They are difficult projects to design, to
develop.
Finally, for example, for scientific benefits,
we can impose scientific access fees to the
site.
You see, these different tools, taxes mean
that we can gain a certain revenue
for the protected area, for it to function
and operate.
To conclude, I want an expert to speak to
you.
Nicolas Pascal has worked a lot
on the study of the values of goods and services
of protected areas.
Nicolas works at CRIOBE,
the Center for Research on Islands and on
the Environment
at the University of Perpignan, France.
We can conduct economic assessments of the
benefits of protected areas,
or of marine protected areas with a variety
of aims.
I think to make it simple,
it all depends on who wants the study to be
done.
When it comes to governments,
it may be to value the costs and benefits
of a public investment in nature,
and therefore to assess exactly the role of
this investment
in developing the economy of the local community
or of the territory or land in general.
For development banks,
it's quite a similar aim.
It's a loan or an investment in nature,
in a protected area, for example,
and it's trying to demonstrate a link between
this investment
and the economic development of the local
communities.
For conservation NGOs, it's a little different.
It's more about identifying who benefits from
these protected areas,
trying to demonstrate what these stakeholders
receive.
And so after maintaining certain values
or certain biodiversity ecosystem services,
they also impact the economy,
so, here we identify who the beneficiaries
are.
So there we go, there are always multiple
roles and uses.
Let's say that through different stakeholders,
these are possible roles and uses.
The tools and methods
that are best adapted for the African context...
I think we can distinguish two big cases,
or two major situations.
A first situation where we deal with a study,
is, we'll say, on a national or regional level.
In this situation, we use an approach that
is obviously quite global,
where we will try to assess
who are the main beneficiaries of the areas.
So here, we're still looking at a preliminary
economic analysis.
Another situation, much more precise, is on
the level of a protected area.
So here, we have interviews, investigations
in the area itself
to be more precise about the benefits,
and, especially, about their geographical
division -
about their geographic distribution.
So, are we in the protected area's area of
influence?
Do the...
I'll give an example.
Do the tourism service providers,
based 60 miles from there,
but who use the protected area for their activities,
benefit from it?
We have another geographic distribution of
these benefits.
So here, there are two levels of methods,
which can be put in place.
And that's the first step to determine: the
degree of precision that we want,
and especially the geographic distribution
of the benefits and impacts on the areas.
There we go, it is the end of this video.
You will find more details and more information
in the course documents, feel free to have
a look at them.
You will now understand
that determining the value of goods and services
of an area
can be a bit complicated, but it is an essential
tool
to help with decision-making, with managing
a site.
Have a good day.