Hello.
In this sequence we will talk about the options
in terms of financing sources for protected
areas.
A number of documents and reference guides
are available.
I would recommend this one : Guide to Conservation
Finance
published by WWF in 2009.
An excellent guide that contains almost
all of the options and financing sources that
exist.
It only exists in English.
I also invite you to read two texts, again
from WWF,
Raising revenues for Protected Areas - a menu
of options, published in May 2001
and another guide, more specific on marine
conservation:
Financing Marine Conservation, a manual of
options
from 2004, by Melissa Moye and Boris Spergel.
I also invite you to look up these two websites.
First, the Toolbox developed for the RAMPAO
the West African Marine Protected Areas Network,
to guide and assist them in setting up
sustainable financing mechanisms.
Finally, on the website of the Conservation
Finance Alliance or CFA, you will find
a significant amount of information, guidelines,
references, and experts' advice.
Feel free to have a look at it.
Before we look at possible sources of funding
for Protected Areas,
let's first take a look at the deficits.
It is commonly accepted that Protected Areas
and their management
are suffering from great budgetary deficits,
especially in developing countries.
Recent studies have underlined a deficit in
funding
in developing countries ranging from $1 to
1.7 billion per year
regarding management of existing Protected
Areas.
The study showed here: Financial Cost of Meeting
Global
biodiversity conservation targets current
spending and unmet needs
published in Science magazine, underlines
that current expenditures
are no higher than $0.5 billion per year.
And that the additional needs,
only for the management of current Protected
Areas,
would be of $1.09 billion per year.
Finally, that additional needs, would there
be an extension
of the Protected Areas network, as advised
by the Aichi targets
would amount to an extra $1.69 billion.
Stuart Butchard from Birdlife International
pointed out, at the World Parks Congress,
that current spendings have to be at least
doubled
to guarantee the efficient management of existing
Protected Areas
in developing countries, and increase by a
factor of 6
to ensure efficient management on a bigger
network.
The goal is thus to find additional funding
sources for Protected Areas.
Together let's look at the different options.
First, budgetary contributions
from the State and governments.
Then, we will look at
individual donors' contribution, often in
the form of projects.
Finally, private resources, which we can call
auto-financing of Protected Areas.
Public Funding allocated to Protected areas
is an essential part of their budget.
On average, this public funding amounts to
around 60%
of the funds made available for Protected
Areas.
It's an average, it is certainly less than
that
in developing countries.
But that means it's important to reach out
to government bodies,
especially the department of Finance,
to explain, present, and negociate budgets.
For further information on this topic, I invite
you to refer to this guide
which should come out soon, and is based on
the experience
of 3 Latin American countries : Chile, Guatemala
and Peru.
A popular option is calling to individual
donors
in the form of projects.
You all know the project management cycle.
Who are these individual donors?
The main ones are bilateral donors:
foreign cooperations, German, French,
through the KFW, the AFD, multilateral cooperations
like the GEF (Global Environment Facility).
GEF 6 is on its way
and should propose significant grants to Protected
Areas.
There are also international NGOs.
In Africa WWF, IUCN, Conservation International,
Nature Conservancy
MacArthur, Wildlife Conservation Society,
all these international organizations
are present in Africa and can offer contributions.
There are also private foundations, sometimes
significant in some countries.
Other than substantial projects, you should
know that you can
call on small subsidies.
Again, there are many types of organizations
that make available
those small grants for Protected Areas
In terms of private and direct resources available
for Protected Areas,
you can see here a list of often used options.
These profits can either go directly to the
Protected Area,
or transit through authorities at the Ministry
of Finances.
Note that it is sometimes difficult to gain
back a significant percentage.
Among the options, you can also see fishing
or hunting permits,
permits or commercial fees regarding resource
consumption,
for example tourism, fishing, diving.
Commercial permits for touristic installations
and camps.
You could also earn royalties
on networks or underground or submarines cables.
Used more often, entrance fees to Protected
Areas.
In the Galapagos, the entrance fee is $125
per person,
90% of which goes directly to the Protected
Area.
In terms of entrance fees, look at the numbers
of the Quirimbas Park in Mozambique and that
of Cocos island in Costa Rica.
You will notice that Quirimbas applies fees
to
research programs and science programs.
On the other hand, the Park of the Cocos islands
applies fees to video or movie shootings.
There again, innovative initiatives.
There is also the sales of local products,
guides, goods, etc.
The Protected Area will also be able to impose
a tax on film shooting
or events, here, a wedding ceremony.
The jackpot being, potentially, the shooting
of a TV show,
which could bring in a lot of money.
Allow me to underline as well the potential
income
that would come from illegal activities involving
degradations in the Protected Area.
Of course, they are to be outlawed
and every measure must be taken to cut down
these activities.
Nevertheless, when they are happening, it
is important to ensure that the income
of these deteriorations and fines go to the
Protected Area.
For example, illegal hunting or fishing fines
or measures of compensation for degradation:
an extractive industry, farm pollution, etc.
We will look at this soon enough in sequence
6.5.
You might have noticed that there is more
and more talk
around income that could be taken
from products and services relative to the
Protected Area.
The expression "Payment for ecosystemic services"
is then used.
Services like water, carbon, nursery grounds
of commercial species
or coastal protection.
Take the example of water that the Protected
Area can provide.
Protecting a watershed that provides water
to a population downstream can mean income,
as the Protected Area receives a financial
allocation
to protect its water resources.
Using the example of carbon: the Protected
Area, with its forest cover
but also its mangroves, sea grass beds or
mudflats,
contributes to capturing and sequestration
of carbon.
There again, the Protected Area could be compensated
for its efforts invested in the protection
of those ecosystems.
We can also consider the service provided
by a Protected Area
in the growth of the commercial stock of fish
as a kind of assistance on the Protected Area's
behalf
to the fishing industry of the country.
Therefore, the protected area could also have
a share of the fishing income
or be included in the fishing agreement signed
between powerful industries
and the country in question.
Note that, in order to perceive this fee,
it is generally considered
that a very precise ecosystemic service one
that would permanently supply
a set amount of quality and quantity, would
be connected to
at least one seller, one buyer, within a well-framed
transaction.
For example, in the context of the carbon
market.
It can either be intentional, or legal, but
it must always be verified,
to insure that the service is well provided,
as agreed.
This sequence is over, it is strongly connected
the sequence 6.4 that follows
and I invite you to study these two sequences
together.
Thank you and have a nice day !