In this sequence, we will address the different
mechanisms
that can be put in place to collect the funds
for protected areas.
note that I include here a special focus
on conservation trust funds, which
are mechanism and funding sources
that can enable innovative and additional
funding to be collected
to contribute to the financial sustainability
of protected areas
in the medium and long term.
Funding of protected areas can be obtained
through different channels.
Here are three in particular: projects by
various donors;
budgetary support from the government;
and finally, trust funds for conservation.
Note as well the first point which is: setting
up a bank account.
Setting up a bank account
could be very beneficial to a park,
for example it helps to collect donations
from visitors, friends of the park.
However, it is clear that setting up a bank
account is not always easy.
Let's first of all have a look at the project
mechanisms.
Projects by donor agencies are frequently
a main source of fundings
for protected areas in Africa.
Here's the example of Masoala National Park
in Madagascar
over the 2009 to 2012 period.
Notice the successive projects from different
funding partners:
Zurich Zoo, here; WCS;
a project by KFW; a project by CI;
a project by the region Nord-Pas de Calais,
etc.
Note that the project funding are not always
transferred
into the protected area bank accounts.
We can then have various separate accounting
systems
and it is sometimes hard to consolidate everything,
as it was done here.
Notice as well that each funding partner may
have its own conditions and prerequisites.
Submitting a project, to, for example, the
GEF—
and the GEF-6 is on its way—
requires a certain level of skill,
writing skills and project implementation
skills.
In terms of fundraising from donor agencies,
I invite you to have a look at this little
guide:
Institutional Fundraising for Conservation
Projects
by Maaike Manten and Caroline Pridham for
BirdLife International.
This little guide offers a variety of options,
filled with experience, case studies that
can guide you as you prepare projects
intended for institutional sponsors.
Please don't hesitate to refer to it.
Budgetary support: we have mentioned it,
governmental and state support can be significant.
Support from governments represents more than
60% of funding for protected areas.
Also note that a protected area is a public
good.
It is therefore the state's responsibility
to ensure it continues to function.
Government funding
can come from several places:
of course, from annual public expenditure,
decreed by the government;
also from revenue from fines and taxes;
from mechanisms of converting debts with foreign
powers;
from payments for ecosystem services;
but also from exploitation agreements,
for example compensation from the fishing
agreements;
from income from the extractive industries;
and also from budgetary and institutional
support from external funding agencies.
It is important that protected areas managers
are fully involved in negotiations to find
agreements
for these different options.
It is, of course, the manager's role to convince
and to emphasize
the importance of the values of these goods
and services
of the protected area,
just as we saw in sequence 6.2.
Also, notice that once the compensation and
the funds
have been allocated to the government,
it will then be necessary to ensure the revenue
is received by the protected area.
Sometimes, that isn't easy.
Let's now have a look at conservation trust
funds.
Before going any further,
I would just like to highlight two reference
books.
On one hand, Rapid Review of Conservation
Trust Funds,
in English here, and in French here, published
in 2008.
On the other hand, there is
Practice Standards for Conservation Trust
Funds.
All of a group of colleague's experience,
expertise
has been put in this book, in this guide to
introduce the best practices
in terms of running, operating
and creating conservation trust funds.
These are very precious guides.
What is a conservation trust fund?
The accepted definition, the one suggested
in the 2008 Rapid Review
and reused in publications by CFA, is the
following:
Conservation Trust Funds are private,
legally independent institutions,
that provide sustainable financing for biodiversity
conservation
and often finance part of the long-term management
costs
of a country‘s protected area (PA) system,
as well as conservation
and sustainable development initiatives separate
from protected areas.
The core focus of conservation trust funds
is to raise funds from various sources
and to transfer the revenue or the funds in
the form of donations
to multiple programs and field projects.
Therefore, conservation trust funds are above
all a financial institution
that raises additional, innovative funds
to benefit conservation actions through grants
to protected areas, to conservation partners.
It is a legally independant organization,
we have mentioned that,
which is governed by a joint board of directors,
generally with representatives of donor agencies,
government,
civil society, but also with qualified individuals,
mainly in terms of finance, investment,
regarding conservation and fund raising.
Finally, it's a mechanism that can manage
several accounts
for different objectives.
They are generally endowment funds, where
income funds the subsidies.
But there can also be a sinking find or revolving
funds.
We will have a look at that in a moment.
Let's have a look at the map of conservation
trust funds.
Today, there are about 80 conservation trust
funds
in the world,
but this number is increasing, since there
is greater interest
in trust funds from donor agencies and protected
areas themselves.
The collected capital is estimated to be around
800 million, possibly more.
Notice that the distribution is mainly in
the Latin and Central American region,
but trust funds in Africa are developing and
more and more of those institutions
are being established in African countries.
Let's have a look at the situation in Africa.
In Africa, there are around 20 of these institutions
today.
Most of them were established at the end of
the 1990s,
mainly in east Africa, and set up to serve
to one or several protected areas.
There was a second wave of funds created after
2002.
So one can consider that they are still at
the initial stage of functioning and capitalizing,
essentially in the centre and in the west.
The average capitalization is still low,
around 10 million.
But it is increasing,
and more and more sponsors and partners are
interested in this tool
and they are feeling ready to invest in trust
funds.
Therefore, financial support mainly comes
from GEF
or bilateral donors,
like KFW, AFD,
who have clear support policies regarding
trust funds.
International NGOs and private foundations
also contribute.
Trust funds are financial institutions,
just as their name indicates.
They therefore should have attractive financial
returns.
And yet, financial returns these last years
have been similar to the benchmark indexes:
more than 9%
in 2013,
which is interesting.
Over a period of 3 to 5 years, there is a
return close to 7%,
which is similar to what many funds aim for.
More and more, donor agencies consider conservation
trust funds
to be promising tools.
They have developed general policies in favour
of trust funds.
It has been recognized that these institutions
are able
to generate a significant income over the
long term.
So, they can contribute
to the financial sustainability of protected
areas.
Nevertheless, take note that there are still
issues
regarding the effectiveness of these institutions.
First of all, in terms of the impact on biodiversity,
but also in terms of the quality of the governance
and the level of financial return
when financial markets are volatile.
So there are still many issues, but there
is a lot of good interest
for this mechanism that aims to complement
other mechanisms that we have studied,
namely projects and budgetary funding by
the government.
To finish off, I have asked my colleague,
Doctor Fanny N'golo, Executive Director
for the Foundation for the Parks and Reserves
of Ivory Coast,
to give us his opinion, his opinion as trust
funds practioner,
and to tell us about the Ivory Coast foundation's
experience.
Let's listen to him.
To what extent do the Ivory Coast trust funds
financially contribute
to the functioning of protected areas in the
country?
The Foundation for the Parks and Reserves
of Ivory Coast is a trust fund
created in 2004,
and at this point,
the foundation finances four national parks
in Ivory Coast,
which represents more than 80%
of the total area of the network of protected
areas in Ivory Coast.
For 2015 fiscal year, the foundation has brought
in nearly three million euros
for the Ivorian Office for Parks to manage
these four parks.
Our aim in the medium term, is therefore to,
of course, manage
to maintain this level of funding, i.e. three
million euros per year.
Mr. N'golo, in your opinion, what are the
biggest challenges
that conservation trust funds face in Africa?
With regards to conservation trust funds in
Africa,
there are two major challenges.
The first challenge is being able to sustain
this financial mechanism
that is this trust fund.
And the second challenge is raising funds.
Indeed, most of the financial resources
in trust funds come from donations,
and unfortunately, the tradition of giving
has not caught on that much in Africa.
For this reason, there needs to be a good
strategy for fund raising.
That is still a major challenge.
In your opinion, what are the foundation's
biggest successes?
Regarding the Cote d’Ivoire foundation,
there are three big successes.
The first is the members that make up the
board of directors.
Indeed, the board of directors
is composed of competent and committed people.
The second big challenge was being able to
gather,
during a slightly turbulent period in Ivory
Coast,
nearly 31 million euros, and that is therefore
a key element.
And finally, we think that the Ivory Coast
foundation
is an institution well positioned at the national
level,
because it is a respected institution, that
people listen to,
and that also has an opinion about all of
the conservation problems
in the national parks in Ivory Coast.
Can you give us the three factors
that lead to the success of conservation trust
funds?
In Africa, for trust funds to succeed,
I think there are three factors that play
a role.
The first factor involves the management team.
There needs to be a good team, at the level
of the board of directors,
as well as at the level of the executive management.
The second important element is to apply a
good governance
when managing the foundation.
Daily managing must, of course, be based on
good governance.
And finally, the third important factor
is to have a good return on investments, of
course.
All in all,
the aim is ultimately to be able to gather
enough funds
for the conservation of the park,
or more generally, for conservation.
There, this sequence is now finished.
You should now understand
that financial sustainability of a protected
area
relies on interactions between several mechanisms.
The sources of finance must be varied,
the financial mechanisms must be varied,
and there must be a whole range, short term,
small grants,
medium term, long term,
to be able to really target
financial sustainability for the protected
area.
I suggest you visit whenever you want the
CFA website,
the Conservation Finance Alliance website;
the link is here.
It is bursting with information, case studies
and facts,
in particular on conservation trust funds.
Thank you and have a good day.