Hello.
For the end of this module on funding conservation,
I would like to shed some light,
on one hand,
on the mechanisms of compensation & offset,
and on the other, on the most innovative and
modern approaches:
initiatives from a private investor perspective.
First of all, let's see the mechanisms of
compensation.
Several guides and documents are available
and I invite you to have a look at them in
your course file.
Most of them are in English,
in particular the handbook from the BBOP organization,
which is a benchmark organization in this
field.
There is, for example, this document that
is in front of you,
that lays out the steps on how to set up a
compensation project.
There is also the guide for South Africa.
And there are two studies that are in French:
one on the economy and biodiversity mission,
and the other by the Commissioner-General
for Sustainable Development.
To address this topic, I have asked Ray Victurine
to talk to you;
he is the director of Conservation Financedivision
in an NGO called WCS:
the Wildlife Conservation Society.
Let's hear from him now.
What is compensation?
Compensation is the last step in a mitigation
hierarchy
avoid, minimise and then compensate the impacts
on biodiversity.
It is essential that this sequence be respected,
first of all, by avoiding, then reducing,
and then if necessary, compensating.
It is necessary to compensate for the residual
impacts.
Usually, it is not possible to have large
development projects without residual impacts.
Usually, it is necessary to actually compensate.
Businesses must finance the compensation
and ensure that the results have a lasting
effect.
The elaboration of policies and mechanisms
to sustainably manage funds from compensation
mechanisms
need to be and are a priority.
The terms must be established to ensure existing
or new protected areas
are financed in the long term.
The conservation trust funds offer,
for example, a financial medium
for efficient and transparent management
of these compensatory funds in the long term.
What can compensation do?
First of all, it can improve the management
of protected areas.
There are many examples such as restoring,
rehabilitating a zone,
reintroducing species that used to be there,
to put a halt to the current deterioration,
and recreate or build a lost habitat.
Secondly, by reducing or stopping the current
loss.
We could offer protection,
or link together or strengthen the priority
zones,
reduce or eliminate the current threats to
conservation.
For example, we could introduce appropriate
substitutes
for the targeted biodiversity,
look for ways for alternative resources,
or compensate users for not using or harvesting
biodiversity.
Thirdly, we can pay
the private land owners or communities
for managing the grounds, for preserving biodiversity.
How do they benefit to protected areas?
Compensation mechanisms have been used
as a
conservation tool since the 1970s.
In the United States, from the year 1977,
the adoption of laws at a national level
have been the main motivation for using this
mechanism in wetlands.
Several countries are looking into "no-net-loss"
policies.
If we consider the regulated market and the
voluntary market,
the annual total has gone from
between $1.8 billion
and $2.9 billion
to between $2.4 and $4 billion
between 2009 and 2010.
It is estimated that the funds made available
by these compensation mechanisms
could generate annually $5 to 10 billion from
now until 2020.
To summarize, an increasing use of compensation
mechanisms
is explained by four main reasons.
One: more and more financial institutions
- banks, investors, funding agencies, etc.
-
demand compensation for residual impacts
as a prerequisite to access funds - loans
or contributions.
More and more governments are enacting compensation
policies and laws,
because the governments demand that all of
the businesses
compensate for residual impacts.
Businesses are becoming more and more involved
in compensation projects
on a voluntary
basis,
to have a good image,
to be well-positioned in the market, for the
risk, etc.
Finally NGOs and civil society organizations
are increasingly placing pressure on the companies
to encourage them and to support them into
compensating.
As a result, there is significant potential
for the funds from the private sector
to increase and fund conservation and the
protected areas.
Another potential source of finance for protected
areas is the private investment sector.
I suggest that you refer to this essay named:
Conservation Finance
Moving Beyond Donor Funding Toward an Investor-Driven
Approach.
This essay is surely a turning point in conservation
finance.
Indeed, it is written from the financial investor's
perspective,
for whom investing in the protected area
can be good for business,
as well as an ethical and responsible move.
Let's have a quick look at the main characteristics.
This document highlights the perspective of
an investment
of $200 or $300 billion per year
for the conservation of important ecosystems
around the world.
It also highlights that the main constraint
would be the lack of investable projects.
These are projects with a clear outline of
the risk versus return tradeoff
and of the benefits to conservation,
which can be specified, measured and quantified.
Notice a significant appetite from investors
for this type of investment product and their
interest
for impact investing in conservation and protected
areas.
This will require effort, new roles,
maybe new tools to collect the investments,
and finding common ground
between the investors and the protected area
managers.
This is a field that will grow further, that's
for sure.
To finish off, here is a short video,
that documents an interesting initiative
in Madagascar: the Tahiry Honko project,
a community mangrove carbon project.
It is by the NGO Blue Ventures and filmed,
documented and produced by Chris Scarffe.
It is also an interesting and innovative project.
Let's watch it together.
You will have noticed there is room
for innovation
in terms of financing conservation
and protected areas.
I am sure you know of initiatives
in this field near you
Let us know about them.
It is important to document and share
our experiences and these new initiatives.
The objective is to increase the level
of finance for protected areas
for these sites to be managed
in the long term.
Thank you, and have a good day.