Hello and welcome everyone.
Today's lesson will be
about the Convention on the Conservation of
Migratory Species of Wild Animals,
also known as the Bonn Convention or CMS.
We are going to do an overview of CMS,
look at why migratory species are important,
discuss the threats that weigh on migratory
species,
see why CMS is necessary,
how CMS works,
consider the organizational structure of CMS,
and understand how CMS's strategic plan 2015-2023
was developed.
To find out more, you could visit CMS's website,
shown here.
What is CMS?
The Convention on the Conservation of Migratory
Species of Wild Animals
is a global treaty whose aim is to ensure
the conservation
of land, sea, and air migratory species
within the entirety of their distribution
area.
International collaboration between the distribution
area's countries
is essential in preserving migratory species
that they share.
This is especially when, each year,
they cross one or several national jurisdiction
borders
in a cyclic and predictable manner.
121 countries attended the convention
on the conservation of migratory species.
Why are migratory species important?
Wild animals in their innumerable forms
are an irreplaceable part of the earth's natural
system,
which must be conserved for the good of mankind.
Wild animals are constantly taking on a greater
importance
from mesological, ecological, genetic,
scientific, esthetic, recreational,
cultural, educational, social, and economic
perspectives.
Migratory species form the basis of economic
activities
that generate billions of dollars,
such as hunting and commercial fishing on
a larger scale,
hunting and fishing for pleasure, as well
as tourism.
Many rural communities depend on the seasonal
and predictable
comings and goings of wild animals for their
survival.
Migratory species also contribute to the functioning
of local ecosystems
through their moving from one site to another,
and so participating in the pollination and
dispersal of grains.
They also regulate non migratory species'
populations
by being predators and sources of essential
food.
What threats are there to migratory species?
Due to their nomadic nature, migratory species
are particularly vulnerable to factors of
an entropic origin.
They depend on many habitats and on many different
migration corridors.
Significant threats include bycatches when
fishing,
the destruction and changes to habitats,
the introduction of exotic and invasive species,
non sustainable fishing and hunting,
industrial and agricultural pollutants, and
migration obstacles,
like dams, fences, and electric lines.
Furthermore, climate change negatively affects
reproduction,
increases the transmission of diseases, diminishes
the ecosystem's resilience
and modifies migration patterns,
thus have a negative and cumulative impact
on long distance migratory species.
Why is CMS necessary?
CMS is the only environmental multilateral
agreement
that deals with all migratory species.
It's a unique and necessary approach
to take up the conservation challenge for
species that do not live in one place.
It is also necessary to preserve their migratory
routes.
How does CMS work?
CMS have a variety of instruments
that are legally constraining on an international
level
and other agreements between states regarding
the distribution area
of species and of groups of migratory species.
These agreements can be adapted to the needs
of specific regions.
19 memorandum of understanding and 7 agreements
are actually set up.
Another legal instrument used is the classification
of species
on the lists of one or several annexes, updated
every three years.
Annex one records the migratory species categorized
as endangered
in all of or in a significant part of the
distribution area.
No takings are allowed unless they are for
scientific use
for reproduction, for traditional use,
for survival or even in exceptional circumstances.
Annex two contains migratory species with
an unfavourable conservation status
or that would benefit in a significant way
from international cooperation.
The organizational structure of CMS is as
follows.
The Conference of the Parties is the convention's
decision-making body.
It meets every three years.
The Standing Committee provides political
and administrative guidelines
between the meetings.
The Scientific Council meets
between the Conference of the Parties sessions
to provide opinions and scientific advice
and to identify priorities for research and
conservation.
The Secretariat is the body that develops
and promotes these agreements,
supplies the necessary services at the meetings,
supports and supervises research and conservation
projects,
and cooperates with governments and partner
organizations.
The Secretariat is administered
by the United Nations Environment Programme.
How was CMS's Strategic Plan 2015-2023 developed?
The Strategic Plan for Migratory Species was
developed
based on the Strategic Plan for Biodiversity
2011–2020
and the Aichi Biodiversity Targets.
An approach like this enables the strategic
plan to benefit
from the exposure and political support that
already exists for biodiversity
in general, at national and global levels.
The CMS strategic plan was developed
by using already existing support mechanisms,
for example, through capacity building
or by revising national strategies and biodiversity
action plans:
that is number 20 of the Aichi Targets.
The CMS's strategic plan was drawn up
by developing objectives specific to migratory
species,
by using the Aichi Targets as a framework,
but without constraining it to those targets
in order to preserve the identity of and the
added value of migratory species.
To conclude, as an environmental treaty
of the United Nations Environment Programme,
the CMS offers a global platform for conservation
and the sustainable use of migratory animals
and of their habitats.
CMS brings together states that migratory
animals cross
or states in a distribution area, and it establishes
legal bases
that conservation measures, coordinated internationally
can base themselves on, by migratory species.
CMS acts as a convention framework.
These treaties can vary from being legally
constraining,
known as less formal instrument agreements,
such as Memorandums of Understanding,
and they can be adapted to the requirements
of specific regions.
Moreover, CMS has the ability to develop models
built
based on conservation needs for the whole
of the migratory routes.
Here we are at the end of the lesson.
The next episode will be the conclusion for
this module
in the form of a short animation
and of course, there will be this week's assignment.
Meanwhile, have an excellent day.