Throughout this module,
we have tackled topics linked to funding protected
areas
and conservation in general.
We have seen that it is essential to have
a good financial plan.
It involves identifying and appreciating the
financial needs of the protected area
in the medium term, and predictable incomes,
the prerequisites of the country and of the
protected area
to implement certain mechanisms,
and the conditions that could determine whether
one tool or another is used.
So, it involves consolidating everything into
one business plan.
The functionalities that the protected area
generates
are important for the interested parties:
for communities, for the State,
and even for the whole of humanity.
An economic assessment involves bringing to
light
and reestimating quantitatively
the goods and services the protected area
provides or could provide.
These studies enable investment into protected
areas to be justified
and compared with the costs and benefits of
conservation.
We have tackled the breakdown of the total
economic value,
the process and the methods to carry out these
evaluations,
and we have highlighted the precautions and
the limits of these studies,
all while insisting on their usefulness for
managing them.
To make up for protected areas' substantial
financial deficits,
we found different funding sources and options
for protected areas,
mainly in the form of state subsidies,
contributions from donors, and various internal
revenues,
or self-financing from protected areas.
Amongst the finance mecanisms that we have
discussed,
we have mainly highlighted
the project mecanisms by donors,
budgetary support from the state,
and trust funds for conservation.
All of this while still insisting on the necessity
of diversifying
where the finance is sourced from,
and while still insisting on associating several
different mecanisms
to contribute to the financial sustainability
of the protected area.
Finally, we discussed a new option,
which, on one side, involves compensation
mecanisms,
and on the other hand, involves potential
promising contributions
by financial investors.
We highlighted the potential of these approaches
in the future
to finance the protected areas and for conservation.
That's it; let's now tackle the test for this
module.