Insurance as a Risk Transfer Instrument
A Resilient Future: Science and Technology
for Disaster Risk Reduction
Welcome to this video about insurance
and disaster risk management.
This particular video is produced
for this MOOC by the SDC,
the Swiss Agency for Development
and Cooperation.
I'm Roland Steinmann,
a senior consultant on microinsurance
with the MicroInsurance Centre.
In this video you will get
an introduction to the basic principles
of insurance as a risk transfer mechanism
and I explain how insurance fits into
the broader
disaster risk management approach.
We we look at the definition and
basic principles of insurance,
solidarity and mutuality and its limits,
what is an insurable event,
how to calculate an insurance premium,
the causes for headache from
an insurer's perspective,
and you will get a primer on
index insurance.
(speaker) We all face a variety of risks
and often have several options
at hand to deal with them.
For the purpose of illustration,
let's look at flood risk.
First, we can try to avoid certain risks,
for example, we could move out of
a flood risk zone to avoid being flooded.
Second, we can reinforce dams so that
in the case of a flood,
the impact is lower
than we had not improved it.
Third, we can prepare for the flood event
and plan what to do
in case the flood occurs.
Finally, we can take out insurance
and by doing so, transfer
at least part of the remaining risk
to a third party.
With this final step,
we have introduced insurance
into the disaster risk
management area.
But what is insurance?
Insurance is a risk transfer mechanism
that ensures full or partial
financial compensation for the loss
or damage caused by events
that are beyond the control of
the insured party
within a specified period, provided a fee,
called premium, is paid.
Insurance products can be designed
to cover individuals, households,
groups or enterprises, and even countries.
People buy insurance because they seek
protection from financial losses
that come with experiencing shocks.
(speaker) Good! So let's have
a closer look
at how insurance really works.
At it's very heart lies
the principle of solidarity.
It is about pooling of risks
within a group,
spreading costs within the community
in order to absorb shocks.
We can imagine inhabitants of a village
coming together all contributing
their share to a village health fund
which covers health expenditures
of the unlucky ones who get sick.
The individual contribution is then lower
than they payout of those that fall sick.
You can imagine the same principle
to cover other risks,
like fire in your home
or the death of a cow.
However, there are limits to what can
be handled through solidarity
within a community.
If health issues become an epidemic,
if a fire ravages a whole slum
or a city gets destroyed by an earthquake,
the risk pool is too small
and more importantly, all members
are hit by the same event
with mutuality basically
breaking down.
This is where pooling across
different risks and geographies
through re-insurance comes in.
So what is an insurable event?
An insurable event has to be random.
Random and still you need to have
a good sense of how often it can occur.
The frequency should be rather low
and the event definitely has to be
beyond the control of the insured party.
The event should also then cause
a financial loss
and you need to be able to have proof
of the event of the loss,
that it really has happened.
The calculation of insurance premium
it is the price to pay
for transferring a certain risk can be
highly complex in practice
but the basic components are simple.
(speaker) For example, let's look at
a certain flood level that occurs
every twenty year.
So then the risk premium would be
1/20 years times the severity.
Let's assume it is fifty million dollar
that this flood really costs
so then risk premium would give us
52.5 million dollar per year
that you need to cover the average
expected loss over one year.
In addition to this pure risk premium,
you may have to add something
to make up for the uncertainty.
Does the flood really have a return period
of twenty years
or is it rather eighteen years?
What if the losses were rather
53 million and not 50?
Then, insurers need to cover
their administration cost, capital cost,
commissions paid to the agent,
that sells the insurance policy
and on top, you may add something
for profit and taxes.
What you see immediately from
these calculations is the importance
of good historical data
and loss statistics.
The better you know the past
and the current exposure
the better you can estimate
the likelihood for a certain loss,
calculate the premium and reduce
the uncertainty loading.
In the case of natural disasters,
climate change has an impact
on the value of event data as the past
is not necessarily
a good indication anymore
of what could happen today.
Taking on the risk of others is
the core business of insurance companies.
However, they constantly worry about
at least three key aspects
related to this transfer of risk.
Adverse selection, moral hazard and fraud.
What does this mean?
Adverse selection occurs if
an insurance company designs and prices
and insurance product for
the average member of a given community
but then ends up with clients that are
more exposed to risk than the average.
Examples here include health insurance,
where you don't want to insure
only the elderly or the smokers,
when doing the research
on product design phase,
you have considered a large community
of mostly fit, young, middle-aged people.
Or, in the case of floods, you don't want
to end up insuring
only those living on the riverbank,
like you can see here
in the picture for Paris.
Adverse selection has therefore also
to do with information asymmetry
between the insurer and the insured party.
(speaker) Moral hazard is describing
the fact that people may change
their behavior once they're insured.
This can be positive and be an
intended change, for example when people
visit the doctor more often or quicker
once they benefit from health insurance.
However, even though this is positive
from a public health perspective,
it can cause problems for
the insurance company if that effect
was not foreseen or underestimated.
Moral hazard is also viewed in
the context of crop
and livestock insurance
where some farmers may pay
less attention to their animals or crops
once they know that they are protected
through insurance.
Fraud, or the willful distortion of truth,
is a constant worry
for insurance companies.
For example, livestock is often tagged
in order to identify individual animals.
A few years ago, an Indian insurance
company providing livestock insurance,
required the farmer to send in the ear
with the eartag of the dead cow
in order to make a claim.
This has led some farmers to simply
cut ears off animals still alive,
sending them in and getting
an insurance payout.
The cows with one ear left were known as
Van Gogh cows in the local communities.
Now what happens really if a loss occurs?
Traditionally, the insured party has
to inform the insurance company
about the event.
You may have to prove that you really had
bought insurance and that you have paid
your premium in time
and that you really had lost something
in the event.
Both can be tricky, in the case of
natural disasters.
Let's imagine a flood where your papers
are likely simply gone, washed away.
Potentially the insurance company
has also lost their records too.
And so, you may find it very difficult
to prove that you really have insurance
and what you have lost.
For sure, the sheer number of claims
it has to process would overwhelm
the insurance company, causing long delays
in settling legitimate claims.
Verifying and settling claims
after natural disaster
is typically a lengthy and costly process.
These challenges have motivated
a new approach to insurance,
especially in the field
of natural disaster and agriculture.
It is parametric or index based insurance.
With index insurance, as these products
are often called, the decision
of whether to pay or not to pay
depends on an objective measure
such as quake intensity in the case
of earthquake,
windspeed in the case of hurricanes,
amount of rainfall in the case
of crop insurance,
or water depth in the case of flood.
In other words, the insurance company
creates a correlation
between an objective, independently
verifiable measure on the client's loss.
(speaker) So let's have a look at
this graph.
It shows yearly rainfall data
in millimeters of rainfall over a period
of about thirty years.
The red line indicates
the level below which
the index product would start to pay out.
So in this case here it is about 55mm
of rainfall, if you have less than 55mm,
then you'll get an insurance payout.
What you see here is how this payout
is then really correlated to
the amount of rainfall.
You start by 56mm and then you have
a linear payout up to
about 7mm of rainfall
and in the example here, 1983, you had
a payout of 61% because your rainfall
was about 27mm.
This index approach comes with
huge advantages
as adverse selection and moral hazard
are effectively eliminated
and the insurer doesn't have to send
loss adjusters out to the field
after the event.
Thus, speeding up claims administration
dramatically.
The disadvantages and limitations,
however, are also quite important.
First, you have to find a really, really
good correlation between the index
you want to use, rainfall,
quake intensity etc.
and the losses observed.
Otherwise, clients can't rely on
this type of insurance
and will have to consider it rather
a lottery than effective risk transfer.
Second, you are in trouble if not all
clients experience
the same level of destruction or loss.
This imperfect correlation between
the index and the individual's loss
is known as basis risk.
The policy may trigger in cases where
no or less payouts would be required
and may not trigger, even though
the client has experienced a loss.
Insurance is a useful component
in the context of disaster risk reduction.
What is can achieve is limit the financial
consequences of events
and motivate people to invest
into preventive measures.
However, there is no proper disaster risk
management with insurance alone.
Therefore, we definitely need
a combination of several approaches
and remember the options at hand.
(speaker) Prevention and avoidance
on the one hand
and mitigation of risks, prepare
for events and transfer parts of the risk
to insurance markets on the other hand.
In the context of disaster risk management
and especially in emerging economies,
prevention is almost always
the cheaper option than insurance,
at least in the long run.