Never thought that Marco Polo
would be such a nice guy.
Yeah really.
Oh look who's there,
I think it's MOOC time again.
Due to the popularity of the course,
we thought it would be
a good idea to do a re-run.
That's right this five weeks course
is gonna cover topics ranging from
identifying and evaluating
business opportunities
to entrepreneurial marketing.
And we will also talk about raising
and managing money,
value creation, value capture,
profiting from your innovation
and we also made a few changes.
That's right! This year we're going
to move to a new on-demand model
so you can watch the video lectures,
take the quizzes and exams
all at your own pace,
whenever you like.
And we will be including a new set
of videos from entrepreneurs
That give you additional insights
on the topics covered in this course
Plus, as an additional benefit,
we are again proud to offer
2,500 dollars in seed funding for
the top 3 performers of this course.
Join us from 16th of September 2016
for the new and improved MOOC
"Launching New Ventures"
Hey, speaking of new and improved,
I made some slight modifications
to the time machine that we wrote
at the end of last course
-Oh really you did ?
-Yes, sir.
-That's exciting!
-Right over there...
So 16th of Septembre 2016,
we'll wait for you there!
See you in the future!