In the previous episodes, we have
learnt how to declare classes
and class instances (i.e., objects).
For example, if you wish to declare
a "rect" instance of the "Rectangle" class,
you will simply write it like this :
"Rectangle rect;"
Now, we could wonder
how to give values
to its data members.
Here, we would like, for example,
to initialize
the data members "hauteur" and "largeur"
(TN: means "height" and "width")
of this "rect" instance of the
"Rectangle" class.
In order to give values, we could
resort to the previously discussed
setters such as "setHauteur" and "setLargeur".
Thus we would individually
give a value to each member.
We are doing just that here,
declaring a "rect" instance of the
"Rectangle" class.
Then, we are using a double-type auxiliary
variable "lu". Through this variable, we will read,
for example, the height, printing here
a message for the user
and retrieving the value inside "lu"
through "cin".
Then, with this setter "setHauteur",
we will assign the height.
Then, similarly, we will ask the width,
read it in "lu",
call the setter "setLargeur"
and assign the width of our
"rect" instance.
However, this is a poor solution.
Indeed, since we are
to initialize
all the data members, this solution
presupposes that all data members
are either part of the interface,
thus being public
-- which is not acceptable in regard
to the encapsulation
of the object-oriented conception --
or assiocated with a setter.
This also shatters the encapsulation
because it results
in the interface being dependant
on the internal representation
of the data members since we would  need
one setter for each data member,
However, the goal of encapsulation is
to clearly separate
interface and implementation.
If we had, in the interface, a
setter for each data member,
the implementation choices
would overflow on the
interface,
thus breaking the encapsulation.
Also, regarding conception,
this means that
the task of initializing all data members
will befall on the
programmer-user of the class.
Since they will have to initialize
all the data members,
we are taking the risk of an
ommision -- a major conception flaw.
Normally, the developer-programmer
of the class
should be the one initializing
the data members or at least giving
an initialization possibility
regarding a few data members carefully
chosen by the class developer.
The programmer-user of the
class should not
have to think of all the possible
data members having to be initialized.
Another solution is, as  usual, to
create a specific method
tasked with this initializing the data members.
Here, we would thus create a specific
method initializing the data members.
For example, we could create such
a method called "init"
which would initialize both members
"hauteur" and " largeur" of our "Rectangle".
In order to function, this method
will receive here, a value "h"
which will be assigned to the height and
a value "L" which will be assigned in the width.
This method would be like
a setter for both "hauteur"
and "largeur" at the same time:
a setter
initializing all the data members
needing to
be intialized in one go.
We would use it as follows.
We would declare a rectangle "rect".
Then, we would call the "init"
method, passing two values.
For example 3.0 for the height
and 4.0 for the width.
This way is certainly not a bad
way to proceed.
Actually, it is such a good way
that is is already available
as such in C++.
Such methods are called the « constructors ».
Constructors are particular methods
tasked with initializing the class.
A constructor is thus a method which
is automatically called
upon the declaration of an object;
right when a new instance is created.
Its purpose is indeed to realize
what must be done
at the start of an object's life.
For example, initializing
its members.
In order to declare a constructor,
we simply need to declare, like this,
a method which name is none
other than the name of the class.
This method will receive,
if necessary, parameters.
Then, we will write its definition like
of any other method.
For example, in the case
of our "Rectangle" class,
we could declare the constructor here.
"Rectangle" - the exact same name
as the name of the class.
Our constructor will receive two parameters
in order to initialize
the height and width.
Constructors function almost like
other methods.
There are a few differences, though. Firstly,
there is no return type; we did not write anything,
not even "void", before the
constructor's prototype.
This means that there is no
return type.
Also, the constructor name is absolutely
identical to the
name of the class.
Finally, constructors are called
automatically whenever
an instance of the class
is declared.
For example, if we write, simply,
the declaration of a "rect" instance
of our "Rectangle" class here,
the so-called default constructor
will be automatically
called - we will go back
to this later.
A constructor is thus called
whenever an instance is created:
this call being explicit or not.
These are the constructor
specificities.
However, just like other methods,
constructors may be overloaded
and even have default values
for their parameters.
We will expand on this later. For now,
just be aware
that there can be more than
one constructor
since they may be overloaded.
We can have several constructors
with the same name -the name of the class-
but with different parameters.
We are talking about the class constructorS.
Now, let us go back to
our initial example.
For now, we only wish to declare
one single constructor.
How should we concretely proceed?
We still have the declaration of the
"Rectangle" class.
The data members are still private.
Obviously, the constructor
will be public since it will be used
by the user-programmers of the class;
constructors need to be accessible.
Therefore, the constructor is part of
the interface. We would have here
a constructor with the same name
as the name of the class.
Its purpose is to initialize the
data members height and width
through received parameters "h"
(assigned to the height)
and "L" (assigned to the width).
In the public part here,
we would have the prototype
and the definition of the constructor.
Then would follow all
other methods we decided
to implement in the interface.
By the way, since we now
have a constructor,
we can freely pass the initial values
during the construction of every
instance of the "Rectangle" class.
Therefore, it may not be necessary
to keep these setters which let us modify
each data member.
This choice befalls on the programmer
of the "Rectangle" class.
Should we, yes or no, be able
to modify the data members
"hauteur" and "largeur" after the construction
or is the initial value enoguh?
Let us now see how the
constructors are called.
We said that they are automatically called
upon the declaration of every instance.
But how are the parameters passed?
In order to pass the parameters,
we simply need, during the
declaration
of a certain class instance,
to put, between brackets,
the different values we will pass
as arguments
to the parameters
of the corresponding constructor.
For example, in the "Rectangle" class,
we have a constructor
with two parameters.
We will thus pass, during the declaration
of the "r1" instance of the Rectangle class,
between brackets, the two values
for the parameters
of the height and the width
we have previously declared.
The constructor's purpose
is thus to initialize the data members.
But what about the data members
which are objects themselves?
Let us take an example
which will be improved later
once we have discussed the inheritance
notion.
Here, we suppose that we have a "RectangleColore"
class (TN: means "ColoredRectangle").
In its private part, this class contains
a "Rectangle" data member
which is itself an instance,
an object of the "Rectangle" class.
Another data member would be,
for example, a color (TN: "couleur" in French).
In order to make things easier, we could
suppose that "Couleur" is an enumerated type
or an integer.
How do we initialize
this "Rectangle" data member
of the "RectangleColore" class?
Since it is itself an object
of a class
we will have to call its constructor.
To that end, we could imagine
-- though it is a poor solution --
to write the constructor of "RectangleColore".
-- we thus have the same name here
as the class "RectangleColore" --
this constructor taking the parameters
"hauteur" and "largeur" in
order to initialize the rectangle
and a color parameter in order to
initialize the color data member.
In the constructor's definition, we would
copy an anonymously-created
rectangle which will receive the
parameter "h"
and the parameter "l" in its own constructor.
This rectangle will then be copied
in the "rectangle" data member of the
"RectangleColore" class.
Then, we could initialize
the "couleur" data member
by copying the value of the color
received here.
This syntax, like here, "Rectangle"
without any variable name
in the middle of the constructor call
is absolutely valid.
This will create a so-called
"anonymous instance"
-- it is not named --
of the "Rectangle" class.
This indeed creates an
existing "Rectangle"
with its height and width.
This "Rectangle" will then be
copied in the "rectangle" data member
of the current instance of the "RectangleColore" class.
Like this.
This instance being created and
initialized by the constructor.
As we can see, we will have two "Rectangles".
A first anonymous "Rectangle" here
which is initialized
through a call to its constructor.
And a second "Rectangle", here,
the "rectangle" data member
of the instance we are
currently initializing
in the constructor of "RectangleColore".
This is therefore a very poor solution.
We thus need to find an
alternative.
It would be ideal for the classes
possesing objects as data members
to be able to directly call
the constructor of their data members.
Here, for exemple, we would like
"RectangleColore"
to directly call the constructor
of the "Rectangle" class
during the initialization
of its "rectangle" data member
without needing to resort
to an intermediate copy.
It is much better to put things at the
right place than to pass by a copy
-- especially if the object is voluminous.
To that end, C++ offers us a so-called
"initialization list"
in the constructors.
The purpose of this initialization
list is indeed to call
the constructors of the object data members,
but also to initialize the data members
which are not objects. These
non-object data members are called
"basic types" (TN: or "native types"),
such as "int" or "double".
It is very good practice to use
an initialization list
in order to initialize the data members
instead of doing so
in the constructor's body.
The general writing of an
initialization list is done
as follows :
Between the constructor header
- which includes the same name as the
name of the class
and an eventual list of
parameters here -
and the constructor's definition,
we will write the initialization
list.
This list starts with a colon.
Then, for each data member,
we will have here the name of
the data member
followed by a syntax similar to the
one used
for an instance declaration.
Namely, the call of the constructor
corresponding to each data member
here between brackets, followed
by a comma if there are several data members.
We will keep going like this
for every data member for which
we need to call its constructor,
using this parentheses syntax.
Let us go back to our "RectangleColore"
example.
Be reminded that "RectangleColore"
has for member
a "rectangle" data member which is an
object of the "Rectangle" class.
Also, remember that the "Rectangle"
class had a two-parameters
constructor tasked with initializing
the height and the width.
Also, our "RectangleColore" class,
in addition to the rectangle data member
has a "couleur" data member.
The "RectangleColore" constructor
-- which we are interested in --
will receive parameters
in order to initialize its
"rectangle" data member
and other parameters in order to
initialize its color data member.
This initialization will occur
in the so-called
initialization list here,
starting with a colon.
To that end, we will call the constructor of the
"Rectangle" class, taking two parameters here
for the "rectangle" data member.
Here will we put
the name of the data member, "rectangle",
the same name
since we are precisely initializing
this very data member.
We will write here the name of the "rectangle"
data member using the same syntax
as if we had declared an instance,
initialized a variable here.
Here is thus the call to the corresponding
constructor of the "Rectangle" class.
Then, the comma separating the
different parts
of the initialization list.
Now, similarly, we can
initialize the data members even
if they are of the type double or int.
Here, the non-object data members
will follow a similar syntax. Here,
between parentheses
the value we wish to pass
to the data member, still conserving
the name of the data members.
For example, if we wish to declare
an "r" instance of "RectangleColore",
calling here its only constructor
taking three parameters.
For example, with a height of 3.5,
a width of 4.5
and color which would, for example,
be defined as "rouge" (TN: means "red").
Here, we indeed have the declaration of
an instance with a call to its constructor.
What will concretely happen?
Why, this will effecively create,
in the memory,
an "r" instance of "RectangleColore".
This instance contains a "Rectangle"-type
data member which has itself a height
and a width.
It also contains a "Couleur"-type
data member.
Upon the call to the constructor,
we will plug in here
and execute the colon
section, thus calling
the constructor of the rectangle data member
-an instance of the "Rectangle" class.
To the constructor, we will pass the the parameter
"h", containing 3.5 to the "Rectangle" constructor
in order to initialize
the height value
of the rectangle data member of the "r" instance
of the "RectangleColore" class.
Similarly, here, this 4.5, that is,
the "L" parameter of this constructor
will be passed to the constructor during
the execution of the initialization list.
It is the second parameter of the constructor
of the rectangle data member instance
of the "Rectangle" class.
Here, we will initialize it to the value 4.5
Here, the "Couleur"-type last
parameter "rouge"
will go here, in this section of the
initialization list,
thus initializing the color data member directly.
Using this section beginning
with a colon
-- called the "initialization list" --
is very recommanded.
First of all, it prevents, as we have seen
before, to resort to copies
of all object data members
(class instances).
Also, it lets us regroup in a very
compact and readable way
the initialization of all the
data members.
Finally, it grants the initial values
to all data members
from the start, before the object has
even been created.
Of course, these initializations
can then be reused
or even modified within
the constructor's body;
this is extremly rare, though.
We are illustrating it on this slide
only because it is something possible,
although you will very rarely
have to use it.
For example, here is the constructor
of the "Rectangle" class
where we receive both parameters
to initialize the height and the width.
In the initialization list, we have
initialized the height.
Though, it would be better to initialize
the width aswell, after a comma.
We have not done so in this example
in order to show you
that the width is precisely not
initialized in this portion
of the constructor.
Starting from there,
the value is undefined.
Then, as soon we assign
a value to the width,
of course, the width will have
the assigned value.
What you need to understand is
that we have a section of the constructor
where the width is not initialized.
This is one of the reasons
why we recommand to use the
initializer list (TN: here called in French "colon section").
This section is executed from
the get-go
before we even enter the constructor's
body.
It is executed from the very beginning
Thus, before we even enter the
constructor's body,
we have initialized the height
to the value "h".
If we follow these advice, our
program will look like this.
In the declaration of the "Rectangle" class,
in its interface, we offer here
a constructor taking two parameters
"h" and "L" initializing the height and width
directly in the initialization
list starting with a colon
with the values of "h" for the height
and "L" for the width.
The constructor's body is thus
empty.
This is very frequent in C++ constructors
because we already have
this initialization list
which it is recommanded to use.
By the way, please note
that
we have here a data member name
and here a parameter name.
Indeed we are passing a parameter
to a data member. Similarly, we have here the
"largeur" data member and the parameter "L"
Therefore, there is no masking problem
nor name ambiguity.
Thus, we could naturally name
our parameters "hauteur" and "largeur"
and write something like this
"hauteur(hauteur), largeur(largeur)".
There  is no ambiguity here.
This "hauteur" word refers
to the height data member while this
"hauteur" word here
is a parameter, a value received
from outisde.
Similarly, this "largeur" word here
refers to
the width data member and this "largeur" word here
obviously refers to
the width parameter.
We can encounter
this syntax in several
constructors
in programs written like
this,
giving the same name to parameters
and the data members
they will initialize in the
initialization list.
There is no ambiguity,
no masking.
This concludes our
introductory episode
regarding constructors in general.
We still have a few point to
discuss, such as the "default constructor"
-- there can only be one default constuctor;
thus the singular form.
We will also discuss the "copy constructor".
And, in a last episode, we will
discuss what happens
when we are done using an object,
what happens at the end
of an object's life.