In this new episode, we will
focus on
the so-called default constructor.
This includes two aspects.
Firstly, what does happen
when we declare an object
without associating any
initialization value?
Secondly, what happens in classes
where we have not
declared any explicit constructor?
Let us by begin with the first point.
A default constructor is
either a constructor
without any parameter
-as you can see in this example here-
or a constructor for which
all parameters have default values.
We will see an example of it
a litte later.
Concretely, if a constructor does
not have any parameter
or has default values for all his
parameters, this will mean that this
constructor can be called
without initialization values.
For example, as we proceed to the
declaration of a "Rectangle" object,
like this, we are not associating
any initialization value
to this rectangle-type variable "r".
Concretely, this means that the initialization
task will be supported
by constructor which does not
need any parameter in order to function.
THIS is the default constructor.
We could imagine we wish to allow
three possible ways to
initialize a rectangle of the
"Rectangle" class.
That means that we are anticipating
the presence of three constructors.
A constructor which does not
require any parameter and will initialize
by default the height to 1
and the width to 2.
A second constructor
-not by default since
it expects one parameter-
which will initialize, for example,
the height to the provided value
and the width to two times
the provided value.
And the third constructor,
as we have seen up until now,
taking to parameter and is not
a default constructor either
since its parameter list is not empty.
This constructor will initialize the
height to the first provided value
and the width to the second one.
If we are using this "Rectangle" class
with these three constructors together,
we now have three possible
ways to declare and initialize
a rectangle, a "Rectangle"-type
object.
The first we have showed you
corresponds
to the call to the default constructor.
The second corresponds to
a declaration such as this one,
expecting an initialization value.
In this case we would thus
initialize the height to 2
and the width to 2 times 2, that is 4.
And, finally, the last possible way
is to declare a rectangle while
providing two values
which obviously correspond to the
call to this constructor here,
expecting two values.
Please be careful, though!
Seeing the syntax
employed to call
the two-parameter constructor
or the one-parameter constructor,
it could be tempting to call
the default constructor
resorting to this syntax.
Declaring the "r" rectangle signifying,
with a pair of empty parentheses,
that we are calling this
constructor.
This is NOT the case.
In C++, this syntax does not correspond
to a call to the default constructor.
If you wish to call the
default constructor, you must resort to
this syntax here, without the parentheses.
By the way, if you write this,
the compiler will not produce an error.
In your opinion, how does the compiler
interpret this line of code?
We have just seen that a default
constructor in a constructor
we can call without providing
any initialization values.
This is the case of constructors
with an empty parameter list.
This is also the case of constructors
for which all parameters
have a default values.
Here is an example thereof.
Similarly to ordinary functions
or methods,
a constructor may very well
have default values
for some of its parameters -or all of
them, for that matter.
This constructor is a default constructor
since all its parameters have
a default value.
By the way, please remember
that a default values is a value
we may associate with a parameter
according to this syntax
in the prototype of the
function or the method.
When a function or method has
a default value,
this means that we may
call this function or method
without providing the value.
In this case, the default value
is taken.
Concretely here, if we
declare a rectangle
like this, since we have not provided
any initialization value,
we will seek the default
constructor of the class.
It is this one because it is
possible to call this constructor
without giving it any value.
In this case, it will take 1.
Concretely, this means that
we will build,
thanks to this call, a rectangle
which value for the height member
will be the value provided by default here,
that is 1.
Also, the value for the width member
will be two times the default value,
that is 2.
By the way, please note that using
default values
for the parameters has allowed
us to write both previous constructors
in one single constructor.
We write a single constructor, callable with an empty list of arguments,
and this one, which is callable with an argument.
This constructor can very well be
called like this.
We are declaring a variable, but,
this time, precising
another value than the default value.
This means that we cannot keep
the default value.
We are using the one-parameter constructor.
Instead of using
the default value for "C", we wish
to use the value 5.
We may call this constructor
either with this syntax or this one.
You now know what a default
constructor is.
Let us now focus on the second
point of this sequence:
What does happen if a class
does not contain any
explicitly programmed constructor?
Indeed, the initialization of such
an object is so important
that we cannot do without it.
Therefoew, in C++, even if you do not
declare any constructor in a class,
a basic constructor will be
automatically generated.
This default constructor does
not require any initialization value
and is automatically generated.
We could call it the default default
constructor.
It is furnished by default if we do not
declare any constructor for the class.
It is obviously a default construcor
since it does not expect
any initialization value.
What will this default default constructor
concretely do?
It will initialize the member attributes.
If these attributes are objects,
they will be initialized
through their associated
default constructors.
On the other hand, if the attributes are
basic-type objects, they will remain uninitialized.
Let us take a concrete example.
Let us imagine that we
are writing a "Rectangle" class
with, as attributes, a height
and a width of basic types.
We could imagine that we also
wish to associate another attribute
to this rectangle. This would be
an object permitting
to modelize, for example, the position
of the rectangle on a screen.
If we proceed to the declaration
of a rectangle coded this way,
we can do so, even without any
explicit constructor in the class.
That means that we will call
the default default constructor.
What does this constructor do?
It uses a minimal version of
of the initialization.
The object built like this will have
its fields height and width
remain uninitialized
since they are of a basic type.
On the other hand, the position
member
will have a value provided
by the default constructor of the
"position" class -if the class has one.
For example, we could imagine
that the position is a two-dimensional
coordinates
and that the default constructor
initializes to the position (0, 0).
In this case, we would have these values here
in the position attribute.
As a reminder, the basic types are
the types int, double, char and bool.
However, be careful regarding default
default constructors.
They have the following specificity.
As soon as we specify a specific
constructor in a class,
be it a default constructor or not,
the default constructor is
not provided anymore.
This concretely means that if, in
a class, we specify
an explicit constructor which is not
a default constructor,
then we cannot build objects
of this class
without providing an explicit
initialization value
for the attributes.
This typically corresponds
to something we want.
When we go through the trouble
of programming an explicit constructor
we do not wish C++ to sneakily
add a default constructor
without our permission.
We will see later that C++ 2011
lets us, if we so desire,
reactivate the default default constructor.
We will also see with which syntax
this can
signified to the compiler.
Now we will, through concrete
examples, examine different variants
of constructor declaration in
a same class.
We will see what these variants
let us do or not
regarding the declaration-
initialization of an instance.
In the A variant, the "Rectangle" class
provides attributes, as before,
for the height and the width.
It could also provide other things
but no
explicit constructor for this class.
In the B variant, the "Rectangle" class
provides an explicitly programmed
default constructor.
This constructor will
initialize
the different attributes to 0.
In the third variant, the C variant,
the "Rectangle" class
provides a constructor where all the
parameters have a default value.
This constructor can be
explicitly called
without associating
any initialization value.
In this case, 0 will be put
in each attribute.
This is thus an explicitly programmed
default constructor.
Finally, in the last variant,
the D variant,
the "Rectangle" class provides
an explicit constructor expecting
two initialization values. There is thus
no explicitly programmed
default constructor in this
"Rectangle" class.
Now, we will ask ourselves :
For each variant of the class,
what is the default constructor?
Is this declaration syntax valid?
Is this alternative syntax for the
declaration initialization of a
"Rectangle"-type object valid?
As a remainder, in the A variant, this
was class schema
regarding the constructor declaration.
Here, we are not precising the
attribute declaration
since it is the same for all variants.
Here, in the A variant of the
"Rectangle" class, there was
not explicitly declared constructor.
This means that, regarding the
default constructor in the A variant,
since there is no explicitly specified
constructor,
we will have the default default
constructor
which is automatically generated.
When we proceed to such a declaration
of a rectangle,
we are not specifying
any initialization value.
Since there is no explicit constructor
in our "Rectangle" class,
the default default constructor
will be called.
Also, we know that this constructor
initializes things in a minimalistic way.
Here, for our height and
width attributes,
since they are basic-type
attributes
(they are doubles),
the default default constructor
will not put any initialization
values into these attributes.
Finally, our "r1" rectangle will
have its members
height and width remain
uninitialized.
The object exists but its attributes
are not initialized.
In a class where no explicit
constructor exists,
the only usable constructor
is the default default constructor.
It can only be called with
this syntax,
without any initialization value.
Therefore, any attempt to
initialize an object
using initialization values
is absolutely invalid.
Concretely, this would result
in an error upon the compiling.
Let us now move on to the B variant.
In the case of B,
our "Rectangle" class has its
default constructor
explicitly declared.
Its task is to initialize the
height and width to 0 both.
In this case, the default constructor
is this the default constructor
which has been explicitly declared.
It is therefore possible to resort to
this syntax which does not require
any initialization value. Unlike
the previous case though,
this time, the default constructor, called here,
will properly initialize the height
and width assigning them both 0.
Since there is no constructor
expecting values as parameters
in the "Rectangle" class, this way to
declare/initialize a rectangle object
is invalid in this case.
The C variant is a litttle bit more complex
than the previous ones.
Here we have an explicitly programmed
constructor
for which all parameters
have a default value.
Concretely, this means that
we can call this constructor
in three possible ways.
This way here signifies that we
are calling the constructor
while accepting the default values.
Thus, our rectangle will have 0 and 0
as the values of its attributes.
According to this second variant,
we signify that we are taking the value 2.5
as the value of the first parameter
and that we accept the default value 0
for the second parameter.
Finally, in this last variant, it is also
possible to declare a rectangle,
providing two values.
This means that we are not
using the value 2.5 for this parameter
and the value 3.4 for this parameter.
In the C variant, there is thus
a default constructor
which is one of the three constructors.
The one we can call with this
syntax will give
the value 0 to both attributes.
Therefore, this line is clearly
valid will correspond
to the initialization of both
attributes to 0.
This line, corresponding to this
kind of calls is obviously
valid aswell. In this case,
it will let us initialize the width to 1
and the height to 2.
For the D variant, we have, in the
class, an explicit constructor
which is not a default constructor.
Its parameter list is not empty
and its parameters do not accept
any default value.
As we have seen previously, as
soon as an explicit constructor is programmed,
the default default constructor
vanishes.
Concretely, this means that
there is no default constructor
at all in this D variant.
Consequently, a declaration of this
nature becomes invalid.
Of course, in this variant,
it is possible to declare/initialize
a rectangle like this.
Indeed, the sole existing constructor
expects two initialization values.
Ultimately, we will build here a
rectangle similar to the previous one;
its height is 1, its
width is 2.
As we have illustrated in the D
variant, the default default
constructor ceases to exist as
soon as we define
an explicit constructor in the class -be this
constructor a default constructor or not.
If we wish to reactivate the default
default constructor
(this is possible in C++ 2011), we need
to resort to the following syntax.
We declare in the class the fact
that the default constructor
will be the default variant
provided by the compiler.
If, in the case of our previously seen
D variant, we wish to reactivate
the default default constructor
since it had disappeared upon
the declaration
of an explicit constructor,
we must clearly specify our wish.
By the way, please note that it
is not particularly interesting here.
Whyso? Because we have learnt that
the default default constructor
did not initialize the basic
type attributes.
It is never truly recommandable to
have the possibility to build an object
where certain attributes
are non-initialized.
That said, in all situations where
it is relevant to reactivate
the default default constructor
-typically when all the members
are object-
we will have to resort to this syntax.
Reactivating a default variant is actually
generalizable to other methods;
we will see other examples in
upcoming episodes.
This is also generalizable
for the suppression of a method;
in this case, we will use the
syntax " = delete ".
For example, let us suppose that,
for a given class, there is
a particular method expecting, as
parameter, a double-type value.
We know that C++ let us §§store
an int in a double
Normally it is thus possible to
call "pas_d_int" (TN: means "no_int)
providing, as argument,
an integer value.
We wish to deactivate this possibility,
thus forcing "pas_d_int"
to systematically be called
with a double.
In this case, we may use this
clause,
thus triggering a "delete" of the method
called with an int.
This will render it impossible to call the
"pas_d_int" method with an integer value
as argument.
Also, please note that C++2011
lets us arrange for
a constructor to call
another constructor of the same class.
This is done in the colon section.
Here, the default constructor
of the "Rectangle" class calls.
in the colon section, the two-parameter
constructor
of the same class.
This will let the default constructor
initialize the height
and the width to 0.
Please note that this way to proceed
is much better
than the previous where we
reactivated
the default default constructor.
Indeed, we have seen that reactivating
the default default construtor
had the disadventage of letting
basic type
attributes uninitialized.
This will not be the case here.
Concluding on the initializtion,
please note that, in C++11,
it is possible to assign default
values to attributes
directly where they
are declared.
Namely, outside any constructor.
If it so happens that a called
constructor will not modify the value
of an attribute which has
a default value so specified,
then this default value will be
used.
Let us imagine, for example,
that, in the "Rectangle" class,
we have declared a constructor
initializing the width member without
doing anything for the height.
This constructor is called
through such a twist.
The "r" object built this way will
thus have a width member
initialized to this value through
the default constructor, that is, 5.
However, nothing has been specified for
the height member in the constructor.
We will thus search this value
specified here. The height will
thus be 0.
Actually, it is preferable to let the
constructors deal with the initialization
rather than using these tricks.
Why? Because this lets us have
a clear grasp on the initialization
process only by reading the
constructors.
We do not need to search for
possible default values
in a section of attribute declaration.
Voilà! This concludes our sequence
on the default constructors.
We will have the chance to come
back to them during the inheritance episodes.
In the meantime, you will discover
new ways to build objects;
for example through
the copy constructors.