In this episode, we will focus
on another particular
constructor : the copy constructor.
Namely, we will wonder
what happens when an object
is initialized with a copy
of another object of the same class.
C++ gives us a way to do
instance copies. For example,
we have here a first r1 instance
of the "Rectangle" class
which has been initialized through
a usual constructor, here with
two parameters. This results
in the following situation in the memory.
This instance has thus been initialized to
the values 12.3 and 24.5. We have here
another "r2" instance of the very same
"Rectangle" class. r2 is initialized
with a copy of r1.
This results in the following
situation.
r2 is initialized with a copy of the
values, that is, 12.3 for the height
and 24.5 for the width.
An initial copy occurs
upon the creation of r2.
Naturally, "2 and r1 are distinct
instances, living their life indepently
in the memory. Simply, r2 is initialized,
upon its building,
with a copy of the values of r1. This
is called the copy constructor.
Here is another example where we
call the copy constructor.
Is this correct?
Yes! We indeed have a copy here
since we are passing parameters
by value. Remember, that when we pass parameters by value,
the arguments
are evaluated and copied into
the function parameters.
We thus inded have a copy of r1 which
will be copied into "r", a parameter
of the "f" function. During the call
to f of r1,
the copy constructor of the
"Rectangle" class  is called.
The copy constructor is called because
of passing parameters by value here;
thus resulting in a copy. Obviously,
if we pass the parameters by reference, there is
no copy at all; the copy constructor
is thus not called.
The goal of the copy constructor is
to initialize an instance with a copy
of another instance of the same class
Its prototype is thus fixed. Since it
is a constructor,
its name is none other than
the class name. And since it initializes
with a copy of another instance
of the same, it will only
receive one single parameter here. This parameter
is another instance of the same class.
We will pass this other instance by
constant reference in other to avoid
passing parameters by value which
would create another copy.
In this case, we would enter an infinite loop!
making a copy of a copy of a copy...
Therefore, we use the passage by reference.
Also, the copy constructor
does not modify the received instance
but only modifies the instance
it is currently initializing. Thus, it
does not modified the received
instance : this is a constant
reference.
For example, in our rectangle
case, we would have here
a constructor called "Rectangle"
for the "Rectangle" class.
It would receive another instance
of the same "Rectangle" class, passed by
constant reference. Of course,
it would use the initialization section
starting with a colon.
Here initializing the height of
the instance it is creating
with the value of the height of
the other instance received
as parameter. And similarly,
initializing the width of the
instance it is creating with the
copy of the width of the other instance
received as parameter.
let us go back to the previous
example. We have an r2 instance
created with a copy of the r1 instance.
We indeed have a call to the copy
constructor. In this case, r1 is the
received parameter
and r2 the initialized instance.
Here, we thus have "r2.hauteur"
receiving "r1.hauteur" and "r2.largeur"
receiving "r1.largeur".
By the way, often it is not necessary
to write explicitly the
copy constructor. Indeed, the C++
compiler provied us with
a default one.
There is always a copy constructor
furnished by default. We call it
the default copy constructor.
This copy constructor carries out
a so-called shallow copy.
This means that it will copy the
parameter attributes of the other
received instance one after the other
in order to process the current initialization.
For example, in the case of our rectangle,
we did not have to write the previous
constructor. In this simple case, it is
automatically generated by
the compiler. It is thus not necessary
to write this constructor which
copies the "hauteur" attribute of the
instance received as parameter
into the "hauteur" of the instance
we are currently initializing
and copies the "largeur" of the received
instance into the current instance and so on
for every other possible attributes.
This is how the default
copy constructor is build
Very often, this shallow copy suffices.
Most of the time, you thus will not
need to write the copy constructor
explicitly.
In certain cases though (we are anticipating
on upcoming examples which we will
face much later in this course) it will
be necessary to express
our very own copy constructor.
We will have to resort to a so-called
deep copy.
We are showing it already, anticipating
on upcoming concepts.
Here is a golden rule. If you have to
touch one member of this triumvirate :
the copy constructor, the destructor
and the assignment operator
(that is, the equal operator), then
you must at least
ask yourselves wether you should
also redefine
the other two.
This golden rule anticipates on the
concepts of the destructor
and the assignment operator
which will be presented later.
We have seen that a default copy constructor
is automatically provided.
In certain cases, we could not wish
to authorize the copy.
Since C++ 2011, we can explicitly ask
to remove the copy constructor.
This can be useful when we are dealing,
for example, with classes containing
many on object. For example we could have
the simulator of a physical word
which we do not wish to copy
with all its objects.
We wish to prevent copies of this
huge object to be made since it contains
many, many things.
This can be done with a particular
syntax written : " = delete ".
We simply need to write
" = delete " just after the prototype
of the copy constructor.
For example,  we have here a class
we do not wish to copy.
We will call it "PasCopiable" (TN: means
"NotCopiable). Here are, as usual,
all the class defenition. In order to
avoid the copy we will start
by adding a copy constructor. This
is indeed a constructor, for it has the same
method name as the name of the class.
Here we received a parameter by constant
reference. Its type is the same as the
class, thus "PasCopiable".
Now, we only need to add, here,
at the end of the prototype " = delete ".
Therefore, we cannot call
the copy constructor
anymore since it has been destroyed,
deleted; it exists no longer.
Now, this square is not copiable;
we can simply initialize it
with the other available
constructors.
Instance copies are not longer
possible.
Voilà! This concludes this episode
on the copy constructors in C++.