In the previous episodes, we
have focused
on how to manage the early life of an object.
How to initialize the data members of
an object when we are beginning
to work with it.
Now it is time to invest ourselves in
managing what happens
at the end of an object's life.
This is the topic of this episode.
Dealing with the end of
an object's life
is especially important when this object
is mobilizing resources.
Let us first examine a concrete example.
Let us take a variant of our
famous "Rectangle" class.
Assume now that these data members, instead of having
been declared as doubles,
have been declared as pointers
on doubles.
Like this.
Let us imagine that one
of the constructors of "Rectangle"
is alloccating memory
for these two data member upon
the object's declaration.
For example, we can imagine
there is a default constructor
initializing the "hauteur" data member
(TN: "hauteur" means "height")
while dynamically allocating
memory for a double.
The same thing will be done
for the width.
This definition with pointers
is certainly not
the best possible definition
for the "Rectangle" class.
We are using it here simply as
an illustrative example.
Let us now imagine a program
using the "Rectangle" class.
For example, we could imagine
to simply proceed
in a main program. We would have
instructions and,
at a certain point,
open a block
-- for example through an "if" instruction.
In this block, we are declaring a
local "Rectangle"-type variable,
typically initialize through
the default constructor.
Eventually, the block will
be closed.
Upon the execution of this program,
when we reach this point of the execution,
we will reserve a memory area
for a "Rectangle"-type variable r.
As data member, this variable
will have the members "hauteur" and
"largeur" containing pointers to
two memory areas dynamically
allocated by the constructor.
When we reach this point at
the program's execution,
the variable "r", which was locally
declared in this block, will not exist
anymore. It thus will not be
usable in the rest of the program.
The question is therefore:
What will happen to the ressources
in the memory depending on this object r,
which is no longer used in the program?
It is important to release these
resources after usage
since these ressources have been
dynamically allocated.
We know that, regarding dynamically
allocated memory (for example,
a memory area dynamically allocated
with a "new")
must be explicitly desallocated
by the progrmmer
through a "delete" instruction.
So, we are wondering :
who/what will be tasked with this
"delete", here?
The solution letting the programmer-
user
free this memory (for example, here)
once we know we do not need
to use the variable "r" anymore
and explicitly call
the "delete" on each
of the variable's
data members is not
a good solution.
Do you know why?
This is not good because it is
weakening
the encapsulation.
(TN: a.k.a. "encapsulation leak")
If we wish to be able to do this,
we cannot let our data members
remain "private".
They must essentially be
accessible from outside the class.
The alternative
is to program public
methods
such as a getter providing us
with the pointer to delete.
However, as we have seen in our
case study on the tic-tac-toe,
delivering a pointer
through a getter
is almost as severe as a
weakening of the encapsulation
directly delivering the data member
through the "public" keyword.
Moreover, this explicit release
of the resources
from outside the class can lead
to errors.
For example, we could forget
to release certain resources.
It is also tedious since we have to
do it systematically.
Doing it this way is therefore
clearly not a good solution.
In order not to be forced to
explicitly release resources
required by the object from
outside the class like this,
C++ offers particular methods
called the "destructors".
These have the particularity to be
automatically called at the end
of instance's life.
This means that, once we
finish the block,
the destructor method will
automatically be called,
thus letting us to release these resources
without breaking the encapsulation
nor having to deal with the previously
mentioned inconveniences.
We need to know that the
resources we need to release
at the end of an object's life
are not always memory slots
as we have in this example.
There can be other things such
as files or external devices.
How is a destructor concretely
written in C++?
This method has the same name
as the class
but is preceded with the tilda symbol ( ~ ),
as we can see here.
The parameter list is always empty.
In the destructor's body,
we will put all the releasing operations
that are necessary
at the end of an object's life.
Also, be aware that there can only
be one possible destructor in the class
-- overloading is not possible for destructors.
If the destructor is not
explicitly defined,
the compiler will automatically
generate a default
minimal version.
Let us go back to our little
introductory example.
Concretely, how will we program
the destructor?
Let us make room and write
our destructor.
Here, we declare our destructor method.
tilda, same same as the class,
and an empty parameter list.
In the body, we will write
the necessary operations in order
to release resources.
Like this.
We can now conclude the
writing of our class.
This destructor will thus be automatically
called upon the end
of any instance's life.
Typically, here, at this point
of
the program's execution,
since this "r" variable does no longer
exist outside the block,
the destructor is called.
We will thus release
the resources bound to the object.
And this without breaking
the encapsulation
which was the case in the
previously proposed solution.
If the "Rectangle" class had no
pointer-type data member
and if, more importantly, it had not
itself resorted to the dynamic allocation
of the memory areas tied with its
data members,
it would not have been necessary
to explicitly program
a destructor like here.
In this case, the compiler will automatically
generate a default version of the destructor
with an empty body
(without any instruction
inside).
Now, we could wondering:
Should we always be
content with this minimal version
of the default destructor when
we do not
allocate any resource in the class.
The answer follows here.
Let us move to another concrete example
and suppose that we wish to count
the number of a class's instances, active
at a certain time
in a program.
For example, let us suppose
we wish to count the number
of rectangle instances present
in a program.
We could imagine we use a "compteur" (= counter)
variable in order to count them.
We will focus on its definition
later.
This variable will work like this.
At the beginning, "compteur" is 0;
we do not have any Rectangle instance yet.
Then, we will create a first
"Rectangle" instance
with the default constructor.
We now wish for the counter
to be automatically updated
and account for one active "Rectangle".
We here open a block in which
we declare
a second Rectangle "r2".
We now wish for "compteur"
to contain 2
since we now have two Rectangle instances:
r2 and r1.
When we finish executing
this block,
the variable r2, ceases to exist.
There is therefore only one
Rectangle instance left:
the instance r1.
We therefore wish for "compteur" to
be properly updated,
comptabilizing only one instance present.
At the end of the program,
we wish for our "compteur"
to contain 0 since neither
r1 nor r2
are present anymore.
How should we proceed?
For now, at this point,
in your learning,
regarding the "compteur" variable,
we have no better option declaring
a global variable
outside the "main". This is no
good solution
and we will come back to this
in the next episode.
For the rest, the idea is simple:
the constructor will be tasked
incrementing our counter every time
we build a new rectangle.
If we settle with this only,
the counting will not be
satisfactoy
since we are merely incrementing
the counter every time
an instance is brought to life
but never decrementing the
counter.
Here, typically, after the creation
of the first instance,
"compteur" will be 1.
After the creation of the second instance,
"compteur" will be 2.
And nothing will have the counter
decrement.
This means that, at the end of the block,
we will totalize (incorrectly) two instances
instead of one.
Also, at the end of the program, we will be
incorrectly counting two instances
instead of zero.
We are thus forced to explicitly
define the destructor
so that the counting is done
appropriately
and the "compteur" variable
be decremented every time an object ceases to be.
Concretely, here, in addition to the
constructor incrementing the counter
every time a rectangle is built,
we will need to have the destructor
decrement the counter
every time an instance ceases
to exist.
This typically ranks among the situations
where the default version of the destructor
with an empty body is not
satisfactory
-even if our class is never
explicitly allocating resources.
With this version of the "Rectangle"
class,
incrementing the counter in
the constructor
and decrementing in the destructor,
our counting is now done
appropriately.
For example, at this stage of the
execution,
the r2 variable is no longer defined;
the r2 object does not exist anymore.
The destructor will automatically
be called
and the counter will be decremented,
thus accounting for one instance only.
Similarly, here, the variable r1
ceases to be, is not defined anymore.
The destructor is thus automatically
called, bringing the counter back to zero.
However, what happens to this example
if we invite the
copy constructor to the party?
For example, let us say that, in this block, in addition
to the declaration
of an r2 instance built thanks to
the default constructor,
we have the declaration of another
instance r3, built
thanks to the copy constructor.
We can see that the argument
passed to the constructor
is here another rectangle.
What about our counting?
Obviously, we would like to
account for 3 instances:
r3, r2 and r1.
What is, concretely, the value of
the counter at these 3 places?
Could you tell what is the
value of "compteur"
at each of these places indicated
with a question mark?
Here, the problem is that,
in the "Rectangle" class,
we have not provided any explicit
definition to the copy constructor.
Here, we thus necessarily use the default
version of the copy constructor
which, obviously, will not do anything
regarding the instance counting.
Therefore, the copy of a rectangle
eludes the instance counter.
Here, typically, our counter which
contained 2,
since it is impacted by the
copy constructor,
will remain to 2.
When we reach this block,
there are no longer usable
instances.
The destructor will thus be called
once for r2 and another for r3,
each time decrementing the counter.
We will thus decrement the counter
twice
and its value will be zero,
which is wrong
since we are still supposed to account
for this r1 instance.
Here, for the same reasons, we will end
up with our counter containing -1 :
our "compteur" variable will be -1
instead of 0.
In order to correct this,
we need to add, to the previous code,
the explicit definition of
the copy constructor.
This explicit definition
will be tasked with the incrementation
of the counter whenever we create
a new rectangle through copy.
At this point, when we call
the copy constructor here,
we indeed have our counter
incremented;
the counting is thus correct,
with 3 here.
The counter is then decremented twice,
and will contain 1, which is correct
since we are now accounting this
r1 instance correctly.
Similarly, the final counting will
be correct.
From this discussion arises
a general rule
followed by every good C++ programmer.
Here it is:
If we are to explicitly modify
the destructor,
the copy constructor or
the assignment operator
(which we will discuss in
a later episode)
then we will probably have to
modify the other two aswell.
These three make a whole.
In any way, we at least have to
wonder
on the impact of the definition
of one of these elements on the others.
By the way, please note that, in C++,
-- though it is an advanced notion,
going beyond the scope of this course --
we can add to this list
(including the destructor, the copy constructor
and the assignment operator forming a
whole together),
we can add the the "move constructor"
and the "move operator".
We are mentioning this here
only for the sake of completion.
This concludes our chapter on
the construction/destruction of an object.
We will go back to this when we will
talk about inheritance.
In the meantime, you will discover
the notion of operator overloading
in the next episodes.