Welcome to the course on plasma physics
and applications.
In these next two modules,
we will consider sheath physics
and plasma etching.
We will show the plasma etching
is the only way to make
the complicated structures
that you find in integrated circuits.
In this module we will see
how a plasma forms.
We will see how a sheath forms
when a plasma is in contact with a wall.
We will see some properties of the sheath
and how we can apply these
for plasma etching applications.
In modules 5.2 and 5.3, we saw how
breakdown could lead
to very high densities in the plasma
and as the density increases
the voltage drops down to a glow discharge
and can eventually form an arc.
This is the development from
a Townsend discharge
to a plasma glow and arc.
In the Townsend region, this is a
non self-sustaining discharge
where only an external source
can maintain the plasma.
The plasma density is weak.
The space charge therefore is weak
and we can use the Laplace equation
to calculate the electric field.
But after breakdown the density increases
by a factor of 10 to the 12 or more
and then we arrive at
self-sustaining plasmas.
Where we have strong space charge
and we have to include Poisson's equation
for calculations of electric fields.
This is the same voltage current graph
presented in a different orientation.
This time with current along the X axis,
the voltage on the vertical axis.
This again, is the Townsend region.
This is the glow discharge and arc region.
Again, the vacuum field applies here
and Poisson's equation applies here.
Just note that this curve applies
to parallel plates.
It's not a universal curve because
in other types of configuration,
other types of electrodes, other shapes,
other types of plasmas can form,
such as sparks, coronas, and streamers
depending on electrode geometry.
Now let's consider in a simple way
how a sheath can form in a plasma.
First, let's consider a virtual
or an imaginary surface in the plasma.
There is an ion flux
crossing this surface,
whose value is given by
the ion thermal flux
given by the kinetic theory.
This is simply the ion density times
the ion thermal speed divided by four.
The ion thermal speed is given by
the root of eight, eTi.
Remember the ion temperature
is given in electron volts
over π times the ion mass.
This ion flux can cross this surface
in a uniform plasma
because simply there's the same ion flux
coming back the other way.
There is also an electron flux crossing
this virtual surface.
The electron thermal flux given by
a similar expression
to the ion thermal flux is
in fact much larger than the ion flux,
simply because the electron mass
is much smaller than the ion mass.
We also know that the electron temperature
is generally higher
than the ion temperature
but the principle reason
for the strong electron flux is that
it has a higher mobility
due to its low electron mass.
To resume, the electron thermal flux
is much bigger than the ion thermal flux.
Of course, there's an equal and opposite
electron flux crossing this same surface.
Now in all the courses up until now,
the plasma has always been considered
in isolation from its environment.
That is, the plasma has never been
in contact with any walls or electrodes
in this course so far.
However, if you want to make any devices,
that is, any plasma applications.
Then plasma wall interaction will
of course be necessary
because it's the only way you can
make deposition, etching,
or surface modification.
So now we have to consider what happens
if the virtual surface
is replaced by a metal wall.
In a very short time the electron flux
will flow quickly to the wall
and form a negative charge on the surface.
This will leave behind
a layer of positive ions.
This is called the sheath.
The sheath forms in contact of a plasma
with the metal wall.
Now what happens when the electrons
rush to the wall and the ions
are left behind is that
the plasma potential
rises until the fluxes become equal.
Now as you can see on
this voltage distance graph,
the plasma potential now rises
this potential drop across the sheath
brakes the electrons
to reduce the electron flux
and electric fields now
accelerate the positive ions
across the sheath potential drop
to the voltage of the wall.
So to resume, the ion flux is increased
by the voltage drop,
the electron flux is decreased
due to the voltage drop,
and the fluxes are equalized
in equilibrium
if there's no net current to the wall.
Of course, this positive space charge
in the sheath causes electric field
towards the wall and there's a directional
ion flux to the wall
due to the sheath electric field.
We can learn a bit more about the sheath
by drawing a Gaussian surface,
which straddles the sheath.
On the righthand side,
the electric field metals zero.
The electric field in plasmas is
very small because it's quasi-neutral.
Therefore, we see that the total
free charge in the sheath is zero.
That is, that the positive charge
in the sheath layer is equal and opposite
to this surface charge of the electrons
of the metal surface.
Therefore, with these very simple
qualitative arguments
we can already make a list
of sheath properties.
The sheath provides the transition
between the plasma and the wall.
Positive space charge
is equal and opposite
to the negative surface charge.
The sheath guarantees
a dynamic equilibrium of ion
and electron fluxes to the wall.
Plasma potential is always positive
with respect to the most positive surface.
The sheath layer is thin,
it's only several Debye lengths thick
due to Debye screening of
the sheath potential.
The sheath is a dark layer because
there is a strongly reduced
electron density in the sheath.
Not because the electrons are colder
but because there are very few
electrons in the sheath
and as we've already seen
there is a strong electric field
and therefore positive ion flux,
which is perpendicular and directed
towards the wall.
Let's see how our understanding of
the sheath properties can help
explain the applications of
plasma etching.
This is a plasma etch reactor.
The vacuum chamber is blue.
There are two electrodes
and a plasma forms between the electrodes.
Therefore there's a sheath in contact
with each electrode.
Let's look in more detail
at the sheath region.
We zoom in on the sheath and we see
that we have a plasma in contact
with a Photoresist on a silicon substrate.
The electric field in
the plasma accelerates ions
normally to the surface.
The ions arrive perpendicular
and go straight through the gaps
in the Photoresist down
to the silicon substrate.
To resume, we have a uniform
electric field above a substrate,
vertical flux of ions.
The Photoresist feature here is
at the order of fractions of a micron,
which is much less than a sheath width,
therefore, the ions always
arrive perpendicularly.
If we want to make these type of
structures using plasma etching
with a high aspect ratio then we have
to transfer the mask features
in a faithful way, high fidelity
onto the substrate.
If we use a wet process,
like in the early days of micro circuits,
then the liquid will cause isotropic etch
of the silicon wafer
and not give a high fidelity reproduction
of the photolithographic mask.
And therefore these type of structures
cannot be made using a wet process.
However, with the plasma,
since the ions come down directly
through the Photoresist then
we get a vertical etch.
This is called "dry process"
or "plasma etching".
So we see that in a plasma
the anisotropic etching is given by
the directionality of ions
crossing the sheath.
A very important result is that plasma
processing is the only
commercial technology capable
of such control.
Plasma is indispensable for modern
integrated circuit manufacturing.
On this graph we see how micro electronics
has improved during the years.
This is the date.
This is the number of transistors on
a square millimeter of silicon.
This is the minimum feature size on
the integrated circuit in nanometers.
So we see that during the years,
the number of transistors
on a square millimeter has increased
strongly now coming up to 10 million
transistors per square millimeter
and the Photoresist size has come down
to a few tens of nanometers
as the control of plasma etching
has improved.
Historically the first p-n junction
transistor was made in the 50's.
The basis for integrated circuits
was invented by Kilby, Noyce, and others.
The very first integrated circuits,
for example, in 1961 Fairchild camera.
The feature sizes were of order of
tens of microns.
This graph shows how the number of
transistors per circuit
has almost doubled every few years
and this is the famous Moore's law,
which he formulated back in 1965.
To summarize this module, we have seen
that sheath formation is due to the fact
that the electron mobility is much greater
than the ion mobility.
From this we were able to deduce
the basic properties of a sheath.
And we've seen that the directional ions
crossing a sheath is indispensable
for integrated circuit manufacturing.