Welcome to the course on plasma physics
and applications.
This is the fifth and last module
on basic industrial plasmas.
In the previous module we made
a qualitative description of plasmas
in contact with a wall and now we will
introduce a mathematical description
of sheath physics.
We will show how to calculate the profiles
of potential and density across a sheath.
We will find the ion flux across
a collisionless sheath.
We will calculate the Bohm criterion.
And also the ion energy across
a sheath to a floating wall.
This is a revision of the sheath
from the previous module.
We saw that the plasma potential rises
until the fluxes become equal.
So we have equal ion
and electron flux to the wall.
The positive ions are accelerated
in the drop of sheath potential
from the plasma potential down
to the wall potential.
This same sheath potential drop
has the effect of braking electrons
to equalize the charge particle fluxes.
Now let's introduce some parameters
onto our qualitative profile
for plasma potential.
We say that the potential
on the wall is V wall,
the potential profile is V(x),
where x is the distance from the wall
and V plasma is the
potential of the plasma,
which is equipotential at a large distance
from the wall.
We will introduce an arbitrary 0
of potential at the edge of the sheath,
which will be defined later on
and there is a drop from
the plasma potential
down to the sheath edge,
which we will call ΔV presheath.
Let's consider the ion velocity
in this plasma potential profile.
At a far distance from the wall,
these cold ions have zero drift velocity
in the equipotential profile.
As ions approach the sheath edge,
they are accelerated across the presheath
potential drop ΔV presheath
and they reach a velocity Us
at the sheath edge.
They are further accelerated,
their ion speed increases
with a value u(x)
between the sheath and the wall.
Let's consider the conservation
of ion energy as they cross the sheath.
The energy of the ions as they approach
the sheath is a ½ Mus²
and as they cross the sheath
their energy is ½ Mu ² + eV
as they cross the sheath.
This voltage here is in fact negative.
If we consider that the sheath
is collisionless
and therefore there are no collisions,
no ionizations in the sheath,
then conservation of ion flux simply
gives the ion density times
the velocity in the sheath is equal
to the ion density at the sheath edge
times the ion velocity at the sheath edge.
Now let's simply eliminate the unknown
ion speed in the sheath, u
and we find an expression for
the ion density in the sheath.
Ion density in the sheath equals
the ion density at the sheath edge
times this expression.
Let's also introduce a profile for
the charge particle densities
in this situation.
In the equipotential plasma,
that is in the bulk plasma
the densities of the electrons equal
to the density of ions
for a quasi-neutral plasma.
n₀ = nₑ= nᵢ is the density in the plasma.
In the presheath we consider
that the plasma is still relatively
equipotential and therefore we have
electron density still equal,
closely, to the ion density.
At the sheath edge, therefore,
the density of electrons and ions
are both equal to ns.
This is the quasi-neutral plasma.
However, in the sheath
the electron density
is strongly reduced as we saw
due to the sheath potential drop.
Therefore, we have the nₑ(x)
electron density profile
is lower then the nᵢ (x) the ion density
profile in the sheath,
whose width is s.
To summarize, we have the ion density
in the sheath from our previous slides
and using the Boltzmann relation,
the electron density in the sheath
is the electron density at the sheath edge
ns times the Boltzmann factor exp(V/Tₑ),
V over electron temperature, in the sheath.
Now these two expressions are different
because the ion flux is determined
by the drift speed of the ions
whereas the electron thermal velocity
is much greater than the drift speed
and therefore still determined
by the Boltzmann relation.
Now we introduce Poisson's equation
in the sheath.
That is the second differential of voltage
with respect to the distance
is minus the charge density
divided by the vacuum [permitivity].
The charge density is the ion density
minus the electron density,
multiplied by the magnitude
of the electronic charge.
We substitute for the charge densities
from the previous slide.
This is the electron contribution.
This is the ion contribution.
At the plasma-sheath interface,
where x is small,
we will do a Taylor expansion of
these expressions.
The exponential appears as 1+ V/Tₑ
and the binomial expansion
introduces this expression here
and we find finally this expression
for Poisson's equation.
Now for a physical solution
because we expect the voltage profile
to be non-oscillatory with distance,
we require the expression in the brackets
must be greater than zero.
From this inequality,
we find an important conclusion
that is that the ion speed
entering the sheath, Us
has to be bigger than
the square root of eTₑ/M
where Tₑ is the electron temperature
in electron volts,
therefore, eTₑ is the
electron thermal energy in Joules
and M is the mass of the ions.
Therefore, we see the ion speed
entering the sheath
is determined by the ion mass
and the electron temperature,
not the ion temperature.
This inequality, the lower limit is called
the "Bohm velocity" for ions.
This is the Bohm criterion
for the ion velocity leaving the plasma
and entering the sheath.
The Bohm criterion is an important factor
in sheath physics.
Therefore, we will repeat it here
and discuss the conclusions.
That is that the ion velocity depends
on the electron temperature.
The ions are accelerated to an energy of
½Muᴮ² as they enter the sheath.
If you work it out, this corresponds
to an energy eTₑ/2
which the ions gain in
crossing the presheath.
Now this corresponds to a presheath
potential drop, Δpresheath = Tₑ/2.
Now this is consistent
with Debye screening,
which allows potentials of up to Tₑ/2
to penetrate an quasi-neutral plasma.
Now the plasma density at the sheath edge,
is ns times the electron density
in the equipotential plasma bulk
times the Boltzmann factor
crossing the presheath,
electrons are negative,
the presheath value is Tₑ/2
divided by the electron temperature.
This gives n₀ the base of natural logarithms,
one over the square root
and this works out to be 0.61n₀
that is the plasma density
at the sheath edge is 61 percent
of the plasma density and the plasma bulk
far from the wall.
Using this knowledge, we can now go
back to our plasma profile
and our density profile and start to put
some expressions in
for the unknown values.
The presheath potential drop we found is
Tₑ/2 from the plasma to the sheath edge.
The ion velocity approaching
the sheath edge
is the Bohm criterion velocity.
The electron ion and plasma density
approaching the sheath edge is 61 percent
of the charge particle density
in the bulk plasma.
Now Debye screening means that
the sheath width can only be
a few Debye lengths long.
Now that we have derived Bohm's criterion,
we can use it as a tool to calculate
other effects in the plasma.
For our first example, we will use it
to calculate the ion flux,
which influences the etch rate
in plasma etching.
Now first we need to know that
Bohm's criterion has some
rather general applicability.
It seems to apply in many cases,
for example, radio frequency plasmas,
probably because the maximum
potential drop which can penetrate
a presheath is generally Tₑ/2
and therefore Bohm's criterion
tends to have some general validity
in many cases.
This is part of the great interest
in Bohm's criterion.
Now the ion flux into a sheath equals
the ion flux through the sheath
equals the ion flux to the wall
because of conservation of ion flux
crossing the sheath.
That is, no ionization in the sheath.
Therefore, the ion flux to the wall is
the same as the ion flux into the sheath,
which is ns times the Bohm velocity,
ns times the Bohm velocity again
ns is the plasma density in the bulk
divided by the square root
of natural logs, which is 61 percent
of the plasma density in the plasma.
Now we know that the ion flux to the wall
is equal to the electron flux to the wall
because the sheath potential appeared
in order to guarantee equality of flux.
And therefore, the electrons and ions,
that is the plasma particle loss flux,
is given by this expression.
In making the statement
that the electron flux and ion flux
to the wall are both the same,
this is the same as stating that
there is no current to the wall,
we have assumed no current to the wall.
That is we have assumed the wall
is electrically floating in this example.
Now the ion flux controls the etch rate
as we said at the beginning
and we are now able to calculate also
the ion current to a probe.
A probe of area A will find a current e
nsu ᴮ times the probe area
times this expression.
This is a factor very often seen in
plasma physics is called
the ion saturation current
to a wall or probe.
If the wall is negatively biased,
then the Bohm velocity still
determines the ion flux into the wall
because the ions cannot arrive any faster.
In this case, electron flux is zero.
A second consequence of Bohm's criterion
is that we can calculate
the ion bombardment energy.
For equal fluxes to the wall,
the ion flux can be equated
to the electron flux
and the electron flux is given
by the kinetic expression,
which is ¼ times the electron density
times the electron thermal speed.
The electron density is given by ns
times the Boltzmann factor
in crossing the sheath
and the electron thermal velocity
is 8eTₑ/π mₑ where Tₑ
is the electron volts.
We use the kinetic expression
for electrons and not for ions
because the thermal velocity of electrons
is much much greater than
the drift velocity in these cases.
We can now solve this equation
for the sheath voltage drop.
We find the sheath voltage drop
depends on the electron temperature
and the natural logarithm of the ratio
of ion mass to electron mass,
with a factor 2 π,
substituting the values
for an argon plasma
we find that this is about 4.7 times
the electron temperature.
Therefore, the sheath
voltage drop is 4.7 Tₑ
and this is equal to the ion energy drop
across the sheath.
To get the total ion energy,
we add the presheath voltage drop
to the sheath voltage drop
because the ions are accelerated
across the presheath plus acceleration
across the sheath voltage Vs.
Therefore, the total ion energy
approaching the wall
is equal to the energy they gained
in the presheath
plus the energy they gained
crossing the sheath,
which is eTₑ/2 times one
plus this expression here.
We can put the one inside the natural log
and combine it this way
and we find an expression
which is often given in the books
Tₑ/2 log mass over 2.3 electron mass.
If you put the numbers in, this is 5.2Tₑ
which of course is 0.5 plus 4.7.
Tₑ/2 plus 4.7 Tₑ is 5.2 Tₑ.
In books and papers, if you see
this expression of the ion energy
then that's because we're talking
about the ion energy
crossing the sheath.
If you see this expression
for the ion energy,
it's because we're talking about
the ions from the plasma
through the presheath,
crossing the sheath, to the wall.
That is the total ion energy.
To summarize this module,
we have calculated the Bohm velocity
for ions into a sheath.
We've seen that the ion flux to a wall
is 61 percent of the ion density
in the plasma times the Bohm velocity.
And we have calculated the ion energy
of an ion from the plasma to the wall,
which is about 5.2 times
the electron temperature in volts.