Plasmas are widely used in industry
for many applications and products
that we have in our daily lives,
As shown in the five modules
of this lecture
on basic industrial plasmas.
The plasma parameters in plasma physics
are very different
from fusion and astrophysical plasmas.
These differences are explained
in the first module,
in which we provide the general
introduction to basic industrial plasmas
and plasma chemistry.
We will show the one key
to industrial plasma processing
is that high temperature plasma chemistry,
at thousands of degrees Centigrade,
can be applied to
low temperature substrates,
such as glass, plastics, and even people.
In the next two modules, we describe
how a plasma actually starts,
that is how a plasma forms,
from the moment when the voltage
is first applied across
electrodes in a gas.
As an example of application, we consider
how to apply our knowledge
to a practical case
in the design of satellites.
In the last two modules, we discuss
the basic physics of the plasma sheath
and the applications to plasma etching
and macro-electronic manufacturing.
We show what happens when a plasma
that has formed comes into contact
with a material surface.
Clearly this is important
for any plasma application
where devices are manufactured.
One extremely important
and lucrative example is
the field of micro-electronics,
which has revolutionized our lives
over the last 50 years.
This part of the course is taught
by Dr. Alan Howling,
a senior scientist
with long-standing experience
in industrial and associated
application of plasmas.