In this episode, we will discuss
a second contol structure, namely
the iteration statements
So, what is the use of this new
control structure ?
Let's imagine, for example, that we wish
to print
the square of the five first integers,
just like here.
Obviously, we could reach
this goal
by using five print
instructions. However
in such a case, we can, or even must
use an iteration statement:
the "for loop".
Indeed, this code will do
that printing
by iterating, looping through the
print instruction.
We will thoroughly examine this code
and explain the whos and whys.
A "for loop" simply begins
with the keyword "for".
Then follows
the declaration/initialization of a
type int variable.
This initialisation will be executed only once
before entering the loop.
Then appears something which
you're already familiar with,
for it is a condition,
already discussed
throughout the condition
statement episode.
This condition will be tested before
each iteration.
If it is false, we exit
the loop.
Then comes what we call
an "increment" statement.
Remember that the ++ operator,
applied to
the variable i, is strictly
equivalent to the statement
i = i + 1, and will thus add 1
to the variable i.
This increment statement is executed
at the end of every iteration.
This allows to change the value of
the variable related to the "for loop".
Please note that the declaration and
initialization, the condition and
the increment statement are all separated
by semicolons and
are placed between parenthesis.
Then comes the
block of instructions which is
the loop's body.
It contains the instructions which will be
repeated, executed at every iteration
of the loop.
As with the "if", the curly braces
are mandatory for the
instruction block only if several
instructions must be repeated.
In case there is only one instruction,
here for example,
the curly braces can
be omitted.
Namely, we are not compelled
to place the curly braces here,
at the beginning of the loop,
at the start and end of the block.
But, as was the case with "if", it is advised
to keep the curly braces, which
I did in the previous example.
Now let's detail, step by step,
the execution of our first example
of a "for loop".
The "for loop" starts, here, with the
declaration and initialization
of a variable i, here initialized
to the value 0.
This variable will control the
number of iterations.
Then, the condition "i less than 5"
will be tested. i is equal to 0,
0 is less than 5 : the condiction is
thus true and we will keep going,
entering the loop body.
Namely, we will execute this instruction :
a good old printing which will
print "le carré de" (= "the square of")
followed by the value of i, namely 0,
followed by "vaut" (= "has value") and followed
by the value of i times i :
simply 0.
It is the only instruction in the
loop body.
The loop will now...loop and resume
here.
The increment statement
will be executed.
Namely, we will execute "++i"
and i will go from
the value 0, to the value 1. Then, we
will once again test
the condition "i less than 5".
i is equal to 1, 1 is less than 5.
The condition remains true and we will,
again, enter
the loop body, but this time with i
containing the value 1.
Again, we will execute
this instruction which
will simply
print "the square of" followed by i's value,
which is
now 1, followed by "vaut" (="has value"), followed by
the value
of the expression i times i which
is, obviously 1.
Again we will loop, namely
resume here and execute
the increment statement.
Thus, i will go from the value 1 to 2
and so on.
At a certain point, i will contain the value 4.
We will, again, execute the
increment statement and
i will go from the value 4, to the value 5.
Then the condition
"i less than 5" will be be tested.
5 is not strictly less than 5.
Thus, the condition is now false.
Since the condition is now false,
we will exit the loop.
Exiting the loop means
jumping to the
the instructions after the loop.
Note, by the way, that the variable i,
declared at the beginning of the loop,
will not be usable after the loop.
Indeed, the variable i exists
only within the loop body,
that is, this part here.
The "for loop" follows the
following syntax.
First of all, the keyword "for" then,
in parentheses, the declaration and
initialization
of a variable, not necessarily of the
type int, then a condition,
a priori regarding the aforementioned
variable, though it is not
mandatory then, an increment statement
which should impact
this variable aswell.
And, finally, a block of instructions,
the instructions of which
will be repeated throughout the loop.
Also, we remind you that the three
elements in parentheses
of the
"for loop" are separated
by semicolons
and that there is no semicolon here.
The "for loop" will repeat the instructions
within the block as long as
the condition is true.
If the condition is never to become false,
these instructions will be repeated indefinitely.
By the way, in C++ 2011, there is another
form of "for loop" which will be discussed
in the lessons dedicated to arrays and vectors.
Let us resume with another example
regarding the "for loop".
Let us suppose we wish to print
the multiplication table 5.
Without a "for loop", we will almost
have to repeat 10 times the
same instruction.
Namely, this instruction here which
prints 5 times 1 is 5*1.
Followed by the instruction 5 times 2
is 5*2,
and so on until 5 times 10
is 5*10.
In such a case, it is required
to use a "for loop" in order to
avoid all these repetitions.
This "for loop" will be written like this :
We initialize the variable
in charge of controlling the number
of loops, this time to 1.
As condition we will use
"i smaller or equal to 10". Be reminded
that the symbol "smaller or equal to"
is represented
by the less-than sign (<) followed
by the equal-to sign (=).
Thus, with our initialization to 1, the
condition "smaller or equal to 10"
and the increment statement
at every iteration,
i will take, consecutively, the values
from 1 to 10.
The loop body will be presented
this way:
at every iteration, we will print
the value of i and the expression
5 times i.
As expected, this "for loop"
will print the complete
multiplication table of 5.
The block of instructions, repeated by
a loop, may contain
any instruction.
For example, a conditional statement.
Here's a quiz relating to a
conditional statement in a "for loop".
In your opinion, what will this code print
upon execution?
The correct answer is the answer A.
Let us explain why.
First of all, you can see
that i will
take the values 0, 1, 2, 3 and 4.
At the first iteration, i will
contain the value 0,
This instruction will thus print
i's value, namely 0.
Be careful, there is
no line break here.
Thus the next thing
printed here, will be printed
right after the 0.
Next, we pass to the conditional
statement which tests if
i modulo 2 is equal to 0, that is,
if the remainder of
i divided by 2 is 0.
Since i contains 0, this condition is true
and, thus, the instruction within the
conditional statement, will be executed,
namely printing p.
We then exit the conditional statement
and end up here
printing a blank space,
which we will represent this way.
We are now at the end of the loop.
The loop will now start anew with, this time,
i containing the value 1.
This instruction will be executed again.
Since i contains 1,
we will print 1.
Then, we encounter the condition statement
again, testing if
the remainder of 1 divided by 2
is equal to 0.
it appears that this condition
is now false since
1 modulo 2 is equal to 1 and thus
not equal to 0;
we will skip this instruction and jump
to this instruction here
printing 1 blank space and so on.
You can plainly see that the
code will print what
stands under the answer A, namely
this. Let us ask a subsidiary question :
Can you explain,
in plain English, what this
conditional statement does ? Mathematically, it
tests if the remainder of
i divided by 2 is equal to 0.
In plain words, it means :
is i an even number ?
Self-evidently.
Thus, this condition tests if i
is even.