Let us start by discussing a few
more examples of
"for loops". In this loop,
we declared a variable
p, initialized to 0,
the condition is
"p strictly less than 10" and
the increment statement is p += 2.
Be reminded that
p += 2 is strictly equivalent to
p = p + 2. p is thus
initialized to 0. At the end of the
first iteration, we add
2 to p;  p will thus have the value 2,
then 4 and so on until 10.
In this case, the condition will become
false and we will exit the loop.
Thus, in the
loop, p will take the values 0, 2, 4
6 and 8.
Let us now consider this
instruction "for", which declares
a variable k
initialized to 10, the condition is
now "k strictly greater than 0"
Please note that the sense of inequality
has changed. Also, the
increment statement is --k,
meaning k = k  - 1 .
In other words, we will substract 1
from k at every iteration.
Thus, k is initialized to 10, at the
end of the first
iteration, we substract 1 from k;
k will therefore have
the value 9, then 8
and so on until k will be 0.
In this case, the
condition will become false and we
will exit the loop.
Thus within the loop, k will successively
have the values 10, 9
et cetera until 1.
Let us now consider
a third example, in which we
declare a variable i, initialized to
0, the condition is
"i greater or equal to 0"
and the increment statement
is ++i, meaning we add
1 to i at every iteration.
i will initially be 0, at
the end of the first
iteration, we add 1
to i;
i will thus have the value 1, the condition
will be true and we keep going.
At the end of the second cycle, we
add 1 to i, which will be 2.
The condition is once again
true and we repeat.
As you can see, theoretically
at least,
i will take every possible positive
value without the
condition ever becoming false : the loop
will repeat indefinitely.
So why "at least theoretically"?
For technical reasons,
which we won't explain,
it isn't
completely true. But the loop
will still be repeated many a time.
A "for loop" may thus keep going forever.
This happens when the
condition
is always true.
Several causes thereof are possible,
as in the previous example.
Mayhaps we erred in the condition.
Once again,
in such a case, the loop will
still stop eventually but only
after a lot of iterations.
Another possible cause is
the misspelling of the
increment statement : like
here where we incremented
the variable j, while the condition
relates to the variable i.
If the value of i is not modified
within the block of instructions,
since i is initialized to 0, this
condition will always be true.
Practically, if you ever find yourself
in a situation where
a "for loop" is not stopping, you can always
use the shortcut ctrl-c in
order to shut down
your program.
Let us consider a few mistakes,
frequent among beginners.
First of all, note that there is
no semicolon at the
end of the line starting with the keyword "for".
Namely there is no semicolon here.
However, if you were to type a
semicolon here,
the compiler would still accept
your program,
though your program will behave
strangely. Indeed, this code
with a semicolon,
will only print "bonjour" once.
Why ?
Because the semicolon here,
is considered as
an instruction; an instruction
doing nothing at all.
Thus, your code will
be interpreted
as, first of all, a "for loop",
the body of which
is nothing but a semicolon.
Thus, this loop will repeat
ten times the blank instruction,
doing strictly nothing,
while the "cout" instruction will be
considered as outside
the loop and will be executed
only once.
Let us consider these three lines
of code. These lines will
result in the following print:
namely the first instruction "cout"
will be repeated five
times, and the second instruction "cout"
will be executed but once.
Then why ?
Because, in fact, this code is
interpreted like this :
the first instruction
"cout" is within the
"for loop", while the second "cout" instruction
is placed after the "for loop"
and will thus not be repeated.
And be careful !
It is not enough to shift these lines right,
to make
them both be placed inside
the "for loop".
If you want both these
lines effectively repeated,
one has to place the two
instructions between
braces
In this new version, the code will
indeed produce the printing
"i=0 Bonjour", "i=1 Bonsoir"
et cetera.
Also, refrain from modifying the
variable controlling the number
of iterations within the loop's
body; namely do not attempt
to proceed as in this example, declaring
a variable i at the start
of the "for loop" and then modifying the
variable i, here in the loop body.
But why ?
First of all because it probably
will not result in what you expect;
do not forget that the "for loop"
will modify
the variable i aswell, through
the increment statement. And secondly,
a  human rereader may not notice that
you were modifying the variable i
within the loop's body.
Let us now treat a new example,
clearly demonstrating some problems
we may encounter with "for loops"
This example consists of a program,
asking four
grades from the user and
printing the average of
these four grades.
We will start with a very simple
version, not taking advantage
of the "for loop", simply declaring
four different variables.
These variables are called note 1,
note 2, note 3
and note 4, storing the four values inputted
by the user. (TN: note means grade )
At this time, the variables note
1, 2, 3, and 4 are storing the four
values inputted by the user.
We can thus calculate
the sum of these four variables,
store the result
in a variable we decided to call "somme"
(TN: somme means sum)
and divide this variable by 4
in order to obtain the average.
However, the fact we have declared and
used four different variables
in order to store the four grades
inputted by the user, prevents us,
from directly introducing a
"for loop" and rewriting the program accordingly.
Thus, we will start by modifying this code,
in an equivalent version
using one single variable to store the
four grades inputted by the user.
Here is our new version where we,
indeed, only have one
variable called "note" used
to store the four
grades inputted by the user
and a second variable,
called "somme", initialized to 0.
We will ask the user to
enter a value
and store it inside "note". Then we have
an assignment : "somme =
somme + note".
This code will be
repeated four times.
At this point,
the variable "somme" will, indeed,
contain the sum of the four variables
inputted by the user, which we
will demonstrate by an example.
With this goal in mind, let us
suppose that the user
types the values 5, 4, 6 and 4.
The variable "note" is not initialized,
thus we
have no clue what it contains
now.
The variable "somme" has been
intialized to 0.
As said, the first value entered by
the user, was 5. Therefore,
this instruction will assign 5 to
the variable "note".
We move forward to this assignment,
which will compute the value
of this expression, namely compute : sum,
that is, 0
plus note, which is 5, obtain the result
of this expression, 5 again
and store it inside the variable
"somme".
The second value entered by
the user is, here, 4. For
this assignment we compute
"somme", which is 5,
plus "note",
which is 4, obtain 9 and store this 9
inside
the variable "somme".
Obviously, at this
point, the variable "somme" will be
0, plus 5, plus 4, plus 6
plus 4, which is indeed the sum
of the 4 values entered by the user.
The edge of this new version
is that we can now
move this portion of code, repeated four times,
into a "for loop".
This is precisely what we did here:
We reused the code from the last
slide and simply modified the
the "note" index while
using a "for loop" with
a variable declared inside the
"for loop",
called i, intialized to 1 and going
up to 4.
Do not forget to initialize
the variable "somme" to 0.
Now, our program is only
relevant in case
the user wishes to compute
the average of FOUR grades.
Let us suppose we are to leave the
user choose the number of grades.
How should we modify
the program ?
First of all, we set aside some
space to add the modifications.
Now, we declare an int-type variable
called
"nombre de notes".
(TN: "nombre de notes" means "number of grades")
We ask the user to input a value for
this variable "nombre de notes".
Now, all we need to do is to
replace this 4 here by the variable "nombre
de notes".
Also, we should not forget to replace
this 4 aswell so that we indeed
compute the average.
This was not very difficult.
However, we have
just spawned an error in
our program.
Can you spot it ?
This error will manifest itself when
the user enters
the value 0 for the variable "nombre
de notes".
In this case, a division by 0
will occur, causing a severe error.
There are several solutions to this
problem. For example, we
could test if the number of grades
is, as expected, greater than 0.
To this end, we simply add
a conditional statement,
move the portion of code
asking for the number of grades
inside this
conditional branch aswell as
the instruction printing the
average.
Let us conclude with the
so-called nested loops.
To this end, let us go back to the example
regarding the multiplication table of 5
which used a "for loop" to print the table.
Now let us suppose that we
wish to print all multiplication
tables from 2 to 10.
We only need to move this
"for loop" into
another "for loop" and modify it
ever so slightly.
If we proceed this way,
which we did here, keeping
the "for loop" exactly as it was
and moving it inside another
"for loop" using a variable j,
initialized to 2 with the condition
"j less or equal to 10".
Thus, j will successively take the values
from 2 to 10.
As such, this code will print 9 times the
multiplication table of 5.
However, since we wish to print
all the tables from 2 to 10,
we only need to modify
this 5 here to j and, most importantly,
to modify this 5 to j aswell.
We obtain this code, which we
will detail in order to verify its
accuracy.
The first "for loop" starts with
the declaration of a variable j initialized
to 2 followed by
testing the condition "j less or equal
to 10". The condition is true and we thus
enter the body of the
"for loop" j and exececute this
instruction here
printing "table de multiplication par",
then the value of j, that is 2,
then a " : ". Now we execute the
"for loop" i here,
declaring a variable i,
intialized to 1.
Then we test the condition
"i smaller or equal to 10", which is true.
and thus enter the "for loop" i,
executing this instruction
here, with j's value being
2. We will print "multiplié par " then
the value of i being 1, then
"vaut" and finally the value of
j times i, which is simply 2.
We then keep going,
executing the "for loop" i,
namely coming back here.
The increment statement
will add 1 to the value of i.
i will thus take the value 2.
The condition remains true
and therefore we execute
the body of the "for loop" i,
with j still being 2.
Now, i is 2, we thus
print 2 here and the expression
j times i is now 2 times 2,
that is 4.
And so on until
i has the value 10. Through the
increment statement, i will pass to 11,
the condition will become false
and we'll exit the i-loop.
Exiting the loop means
resuming here.
We reach the end of the
"for loop"'s body.
Thus we will keep iterating
within the "for loop" j,
thus jumping back here,
incrementing j, through
the increment statement ++j.
j therefore has the value 3.
The condition "j smaller or equal to 10"
is still true and we
enter the body of the loop,
first executing this
instruction, printing "Table de
multiplication par", with j's value,
which is now 3.
Again, we enter the
"for loop" i. The variable i
is initalized anew
to 1. The condition is true, thus we enter
the body
of the "for loop" i and execute
this instruction here.
This time, j is 3. We print
"multiplié par",
the value of i, which is 1, then
then "vaut" and the value of this
expression, which is 3 times
1, that is 3 and so on.