In previous episodes we have
discussed the notion of
control structures.
They are special instructions,
making it possible to repeat
processing or to execute
processing
according to a number
of conditions.
Today, we will expand on this idea
with another way
to repeat processing :
the conditional loops.
If, in a program, we wish
to repeat a number of processing
and that the number
of repetitions is known à priori,
that is,
before entering the loop,
it is possible
to use a "for loop".
However, there are situations
where we wish to repeat processing
as long as a given
condition
is true but we do not know how
many times
it will be necessary to repeat
the processing until
the condition becomes false.
In such
a case we have to use
other types of
repetition instructions :
The conditional loops.
Their execution
depends on the fulfillment of a condition.
In C++ they appear as loops
"do while" or "while".
For illustrations purposes, let us reuse our example
tasked with the computation of some grades' average.
A priori, we do not know
how many grades will be entered
to calculate their average. We begin by
by asking it from the user.
The number of
grades will thus be entered
via keyboard interaction.
Then, if this number is
positive, we will
use an iteration "for"
and input all the grades.
At every iteration, a grade will be
typed on the keyboard
and added to the sum of all grades.
Once all the grades have been entered,
we will obviously
exit the iteration and
continue
with the execution of the rest of the program
At this point, we will calculate
the average and print it.
We can surmise that is not
very natural to let the user
input a number of grades
equal to 0. Thus, we wonder
how to compel the user into
typing a number of grades
strictly greater than 0.
Concretely, we wish to repeat
these instructions until
the user inputs
a number of
grades strictly positive.
We do not know how many times
we will have to repeat these instructions,
for we cannot
forsee a priori when
the user will indeed
input a number strictly
positive.
Thus, we will have tu use
a special control structure.
What we are looking for, here,
is the so-called
"do while" loop. The "do while" loop
is written this way :
the keyword "do" followed by a pair
of braces and
the keyword
"while" which means
to repeat as long as
this condition is true.
Concretely, we will repeat
these instruction inside
the body, that is
the instructions in the
braces
as long as the condition
is true.
Let us now examine step by step
the execution flow of
our little example with the
"do while" loop.
We presuppose that a variable "nombre_de_notes"
has been previously declared
and is ready to contain the number of grades
entered by the user.
Once we reach this instruction,
nothing prevents us from
entering the loop's body.
At this point, we wil ask the user
to input
the number of grades.
The number of grades is entered via
keyboard interation.
Now this line will be executed,
evaluating the
loop continuation condition.
Let us suppose that the user
types,
as the number of grades, the value 0.
In this case, the evaluation of the
condition will return
"true" which means that the number
of grades doesn't
fulfill our criteria.
Since the condition is true, we
will enter a new cycle.
Once again, we will thus execute
the loop's body.
This time, let us suppose that
the user inputs, as number of
grades,
the value -1.
During the evaluation of the continuation
condition, this condition
will once again return true, for, of course,
-1 is less or equal to 0.
At this point, we will
once again, enter a new cycle.
We begin our third iteration
and, again,
we will ask the user to
input the number of grades
and read it via keyboard interaction.
Let us suppose, that this time,
the crestfallen user ends up
understanding what we're expecting
and inputs number of grades strictly
positive, for example, 6.
At this time, during the evaluation
of the loop continuation
condition, the evaluation will return false
since 6 is
strictly greater than 0. Thus, we exit
the "do while" loop
and resume the execution right
after the semicolon concluding
the "do while" instruction.
Now let us formally examine
the syntax of a
"do while" instruction in C++.
The keywords "do while" frame
the so-called
"do while body", which rests in
braces.
Following the "while" is the
loop continuation condition.
The semantic is as follows:
the processing within the body are
repeated as long as the condition is "true".
Once again : we repeat the processing
as long as the condition is "true".
Not unlike the instruction of a
conditional branching,
the "do while" loop continuation
condition can be relatively complex,
resorting
to logical operators.
For example, we can formulate such
a condition :
let's repeat the processing as long as
x is equal to y plus z and that
z is greater than 10 or t is
less than 25.
Thus we can imagine pretty
sophisticated continuation conditions,
especially resorting to
logical operators.
It is also worth noting that the
parentheses around
the condition are absolutely
mandatory in C++.
Just as it is with the"if", the condition
will be written in a pair of parentheses.
An important observation regarding
the "do while" loop is
that its body will systematically be executed
at least once.
Indeed, if we recall our
step by step example of a
"do while" loop,
we see that at this point,
nothing prevents us from entering
the body,
thus we will execute the block at
least once.
However, this block will only be
executed once if, after the
first iteration, the evaluation
of the condition
returns "false".
In this case, we will simply resume
the execution after
the loop.
But in the meantime, the block of instructions
will have been executed once.
This is very important and stands among the
"do while" loop's specificities.
Another observation : if the
condition doesn't ever
become false, then the processing
will be repeated indefinitely.
Consequently, one must be careful in
the condition's formulation in order
to prevent an infinite loop.
Indeed, infinite loops are generally
not the expected result,
at least not for beginners.
Those were the
core ideas regarding the "do while" loop.
Before we can put behind us
the topic of the "do while" syntax,
please heed this last warning :
this semicolon here, at the end
of the "do while" instruction,
which is rather easy to forget.
Now, there are situations where we wish
to test the loop's condition
prior to the execution of the body.
In such as case, we will resort
to another variant of
conditional loops :
the "while" instruction.
Its syntax is as follows :
the keyword "while" immediately followed
by the condition, in parentheses.
Then comes the loop's body
in braces.
The "while" loop is rather similar
to the
"do while" loop : we will repeat
the processing as long as
the condition returns true.
The main difference is that, in the "while" loop,
the condition is tested before
we enter the loop.
Thus, if the condition is
false from the get-go,
we will immediately jump
to the next instruction after the "while",
meaning that the block
will not be executed a single time.
As we've seen before, it is not
the case with the "do while" loop
where the block will always be executed
at least once.
Here are two basic examples,
illustrating the
fundamental difference between
"while" and "do while".
We have here two very
similar loops,
with identical continuation conditions.
In both cases, the continuation condition
relies on
a variable i, intialized to 100.
Let us start by examining
what happens during the execution
of the "do while" loop.
When we reach the execution of the
"do while",
nothing prevents us from entering the
loop's body.
At this point, we will print
the message "bonjour".
Now we reach the point of the
"do while" loop
where the continuation condition
is evaluated.
Since i contains 100, the condition
will of course return "false".
Thus we exit the loop and continue
the execution with the possible
instructions after the "do while".
In the meantime, the message "bonjour"
has been displayed on the terminal.
Now on to the "while" loop. Upon this
line's execution, we will right away
test the condition which will,
as before,
since both conditions are identical,
be evaluated as false.
This means that we won't
ever enter the loop's body
and instead continue the execution
right after the "while".
Thus, the loop has not printed anything.
Here, we found ourselves in a situation
where two
very similar loops : one "do while"
and one "while"
do not lead to the same result.
This is due to the time where the
continuation condition is evaluated.
Among the classic mistakes among
beginners using
the "while" and "do while" loops is one
possibly leading to very
puzzling results. This mistake relates
to our famous semicolon.
This semicolon marks the end
of the "do while"
instruction and is placed right
after the condition.
Now, if we were to add
a semicolon after the
"while" condition, our program would behave strangely
and, most importantly, incorrectly.
Let us see what would happen
if we added this semicolon.
This instruction would be interpreted
as if it were a "while" loop
with, as body, an empty instruction.
Therefore, there is nothing
within the loop impacting i.
So, if i contained something
less than 10, for example 1,
this loop would cycle indefinitely
since there is no way to
make i reach a value
greater than 10, which would render
the condition false.
As a matter of fact,
this ++i, which we probably wished
to be inside the body,
will never be reached if
i started containing less than 10.
Indeed, this plus plus i instruction
will be considered as being
outside the "while" loop.
Now you know three ways to
repeat instructions
in a program : the "for loop"
which we have discussed
in a previous episode and what we
have just seen,
namely the conditional loops
which can take two forms,
either "while" or "do while".
Now, we will discuss
how to choose which form to use.
The choice depends on rather
simple criteria.
If the number of repetitions is known
a priori,
we will want to choose the "for" type
iteration.
Imagine for example that you wish
to calculate
the average of all students
attending
this course. We know a priori how many
students follow
this course. Thus, in order to calculate the
sum of the grades
and the average, we will gladly
use a "for loop" since the number
of iterations is known a priori.
However, if the number of iterations is not
known
a priori, we will pick a conditional
loop,
either "while" or "do while".
Now how do we choose
between "while" and "do while" ?
Simply, we will ask
ourselves if we need to execute
at least once the loop's body.
If we want the body to be executed
at least once,
which is the case, if we're
interracting with the user,
for example, if we ask a value from the user
and demand this value to be
between two values, we need
the user to input the value
at least once before we can test
if it fulfills the condition.
In this situation, we will rather
resort to a
"do while" loop.
Otheriwse, we will naturally
use a
"while" loop, that is,
a loop where the condition evaluation
will
occur before entering the
loop's body.
Now, let us enrich our little example
from before.
It is a typical situation where
a "do while" loop
is required since we need the user
to input
the number of grades at least once
before we can
test if this number is within
the desired interval.
Thus we resorted to a "do while"
loop. Now we
wish to upgrade this program a
little so that
the user will be informed upon
entering, for example,
a negative number, of the program's
expectations.
So we wish to complete
the here program so that a
relevant message will be displayed
when the user
enters a negative or null
grade.
How should we proceed ?
Obviously, this message will appear
every time the number
does not fulfill the desired condition.
Thus, it will probably be placed
within the loop's body : we will
repeat this instruction
every time the user
inputs something incorrect.
We could imagine such a solution :
enriching the loop's body
with one more test. After having read
the
entered value, we will test if
the typed number
is less or equal to 0.
In this case, we will display a message
to warn the user.
Please note, that this is indeed part
of the loop's body
since we wish to repeat this process
every time
an unsatisfactory number is entered.
As you can see in this example,
the condition testing if the number
of grades
is less or equal to 0 appears now twice :
Once in the "if" and another
as the loop continuation condition.
It would have been smart to store
the result of this evaluation
in a variable so that we do not need
to evaluate it again.
For example, we can introduce a
boolean variable "saisie_invalide"
initialized to "false". (TN: saisie_invalide means invalid_entry )
We will update this variable here,
in the loop's body at every iteration,
storing the result of the condition
evaluation, that is
"number of grades less or equal to 0". Thus,
"saisie_invalide" will contain either "true" or "false"
This will allow us to write the condition
in a unified way, replacing
this by
"if (saisie_invalide)" and we'll
resume the processing as before.
We will repeat the processing "while" the
the variable "saisie_invalide" contains true.
This here is good practice.
In a program, we always wish
to avoid
situations where we express the same thing
multiple times in independant ways,
in several places.
It is like the copy-paste.
So, let us return to our little example
regarding the input of grades
by a user.
Let us examine different ways to
formulate the condition
in order to tend to different
needs.
Until now, we compelled the user
to type
a number of grades greater than 0.
Let us imagine,
that we wish to restrict the
number of grades to 10.
The question we are asking is:
how do we formulate the condition
with this new goal in mind ?
In order to formulate the
continuation condition,
let us start by expressing it in
plain words.
Now, the number of entered
grades will be incorrect in two cases :
either this number will be
less or equal to 0, which contradicts
this expectation, or the user will
input a number
greater than 10, which contradicts
this.
That means we will loop
as long as
we find ourselves in either one of these
situations.
In both cases, the number of grades,
is incorrect.
It now becomes obvious
that we will have to resort to
the logical connective "OR". Namely,
we repeat the processing as long as
either situation
is encountered.
In C++, this will be translated
by such a code.
We repeat the processing as long
as the entered number of grades is
less or equal to 0
OR that the number of grades is greater
than 10.
Let us move on to another example.
We wish to write a short
program which purpose is
to make the user guess a number.
To simplify, let us imagine
that the number to guess is always 5.
The idea is to code a "do while" loop
asking a number from the user
and comparing it
with the secret number. We will exit
the loop only once the number
has been guessed.
We're wondering how to
formulate the condition so that
we exit the loop once the user has
guessed the correct number.
As before, we will start by formulating
the condition in plain words.
We know that
the loop is to be repeated as long as
the user has not guessed the secret number.
What does it concretely mean ?
They have not guessed correctly as
long as the typed
number is different from the secret
number, which is 5.
How do we formulate this condition in C++ ?
Simply through this line :
we repeat the process
as long as the entered number is
different from the secret number.
We notice that
the formulation in C++ is not
too far from
the formulation in plain words.
Let us now enrich this example where
the user is tasked with guessing
a number. We wish to give the user
only a limited number of trials.
The poor fellow will not be allowed to guess
indefinitely. Thus we will
resort to a
trial counter, that is, a variable we
introduce here. This trial counter
will be
incremented at every loop
iteration.
Now, we wish that,
after three trials, the game will
be over
unless the user has guessed correctly.
Now we're wondering
how to formulate this condition.
Once again, let us start by formulating
this condition in plain words.
We will repeat the loop as long as
the user has not guessed
the correct number and as long
as the user still has trials left.
It is clear that both conditions
must be fulfilled together.
We will keep iterating only if both conditions
are fulfilled.
Now, let us try to formulate
this somehow closer to C++.
The first condition is that the entered
number
is different from the secret number.
The second
condition is that the number of trials
is less
than 3. Both these conditions must be
verified together.
In C++,
this translates into this line of code.
The first condition is that entered number
is different from the secret number,
which translates into what is written here.
The second condition is that
the number of trials must be less than 3,
which translates into
what is written.
We have here the logical connective "AND"
which guarantees.
that both conditions must be fulfilled
simultaneously.
Again, we see, that the C++
formulation
is not too different from the formulation
in plain words.
The user can now exit the loop in
two different ways.
He can exit the loop because he has
guessed correctly, in which case,
this part of the condition
becomes false
or because he has run out
of trials.
Now,
let us suppose that we wish to let
the user know
why, concretely, he exits the loop.
Since we wish to inform the user of
the reason why he
exits the loop, we need to enrich
the program.
Once we have exited the loop,
we will test for which condition
we have exited.
Did we exit the loop because of
the failure
of this condition, namely, because
the user has guessed
correctly. Or did we exit the loop
due to the failure of this second
condition,
namely, because we ran out of
trials.
Thus, we will run the test here.
If the entered number is equal to
the secret number, it means we
exited the loop
because of this condition's failure
and we can
inform the user that he has guessed
correctly.
Otherwise, it means that the user
has burnt all his trials
and we can inform his that he has
lost the game.
We can also print the secret numer
to let him know
what we were expecting from him.
However, we must avoid logical
fallacies in the test formulation.
Let us imagine that, trying to the
see if the
correct number has been guessed, we
test if
the limited number of trials has been reached.
In this case, the situation
where the user has guessed
the correct number exactly on
his third trial
will be interpeted as a failure
while it was actually a success.
Thus, one must remain careful
regarding the logic
in test formulations when we
aim to realize such processing.
The correct way here was
the one presented in the first solution,
namely
formulating the condition not in
relation to
the number of trials but in relation
to wether or not
the correct number has been guessed.
This way,
we avoid the aforementioned
trap.