The objective of this episode is to present
various small complements
related to polymorphism
and inheritance.
The first subject we will cover
concerns polymorphism
and how it applies to the
construction of objects.
Constructors are somewhat special
methods
in the sense that they are
specifically dedicated
to constructing the current instance
of a class.
They are not expected to have
a polymorphic behavior.
Imagining a polymorphic constructor
would mean that it
would be dedicated to initializing
objects other than the current instance;
objects of subclass type,
for example, which doesn't
really make sense.
However, nothing stops us from invoking
a polymorphic method
in the body of a constructor.
But we advise against this.
Indeed, as we will see in the
next example,
the method then acts on an object
which may be only partially
initialized.
In this example, we have a
superclass A
which contains a default constructor
as well as an abstract method,
that it, a method without a body, m.
It so happens that the constructor
invokes this method m.
Remember that an abstract class can
never be instantiated
meaning that we can never
call the constructor
of the class A like this,
since the class is abstract.
Invoking an abstract method
in A's constructor,
that is, invoking a method with no body,
poses no problem
since we will never call this constructor
to instantiate an object of type A,
that is, an object for which m has
no concrete definition.
Thus, this is completely legal.
Essentially, the method m will be invoked
only if the constructor of a subclass
invokes the constructor of the superclass
and if this subclass has a concrete
definition of the method m.
We have an example of this here,
in the class B.
Class B inherits from A and
overrides the method m.
The overriding simply consists in
displaying a message
containing the value of the attribute b of
class B. Class B can be instantiated,
since it overrides all the abstract methods
inherited,
in this case, the method m only.
Now, let's see what happens when we
create an instance of B.
The instance is created here using
the default constructor for the class B.
We know that any constructor from a
subclass must invoke
a constructor from the superclass
when there is no explicit call
to the constructor via the super syntax,
so we know that there is an implicit
call to the default constructor.
This call is made to initialize a
current instance
which is a B.
At the moment m is called in
A's constructor,
since there is necessarily
dynamic binding in Java, the method
will be chosen
based on the real nature
of the instance
and so it is this method m which
will be called.
Remember that at this stage,
we have not yet evaluated the
instruction
which initializes the attribute b of B
with a specific value.
As such, the attribute b has the value
which is given to it by default
before any explicit initialization,
which is the value zero.
This means that when the method m is
executed, the attribute b has a value of zero
and the construction of a B will result
in displaying the message
"b vaut: 0".
If for us, the object B is properly initialized
only if its b attribute is worth 1,
then we can clearly see that this method m
is working on an object
which is partially initialized.
Hence the original piece of advice:
do not invoke polymorphic methods
in the body of constructors.
Let's move on to the second subject,
completely independent from the first.
You no doubt remember the toString and
equals methods that you learned
to write for classes.
But where exactly do these methods
come from?
This is what we will see.
Remember, for example,
the toString method.
It was imposed to you with a
specific header.
It allowed, when it was present in a class,
to define
a display format for the object in the
form of a String.
This toString method allows us to
produce more explicit displays
for objects.
Yet, toString is simply the overriding
of a method
existing higher up in the class
hierarchy.
But what does higher up mean
since here, for example,
the Rectangle class inherits
from nobody.
True, it inherits from nobody
explicitly,
but in Java, every class that
you write
inherits from a universal superclass
which is the Object superclass.
And this happens without you
needing to explicitly write an inheritance link.
Writing this is unnecessary,
but the inheritance link does indeed exist.
So in Java, every class that
you define,
if it inherits from no class explicitly,
inherits from Object.
Thus, we can affect an instance
of any class
to a variable of type Object.
The Object superclass contains, among
other things, the default definitions
for a certain number of methods
useful to all possible objects,
such as toString, equals or clone.
For example, the default definition of
toString allows one
to display objects in the form of a
representation of their references,
that is, something a little strange that
we have already
encountered previously.
The default definition of equals, located
in the Object superclass,
simply compares references by comparing
2 objects using ==.
In most cases, these default
definitions
do not satisfy the needs for
your own classes
and you are thus led to redefine them,
to allow a more explicit display,
for example,
or a comparison which compares the contents,
or a correct copy of your objects.
When we wrote the toString
method
in the Rectangle class of our
previous example,
we were actually overriding
the toString method inherited
from Object.
Many predefined classes override
these methods
and typically, the String class
overrides the toString method,
as well as the equals method.
Let's go back to the case of the equals
method as we wrote it up until now,
in the previous episodes.
In your opinion, does this header for
the equals method
correspond to a redefinition of the
one inherited from Object?
The answer is, of course, no. The
Object class cannot
know of all the subclasses
which will be derived from it.
The header for the equals method
as it exists
in the Object superclass is as follows:
this means, essentially, that the
argument expected
by equals is of type Object,
and not of type UneClasse (TN: means "A Class")
as we have seen up until now.
Thus, in the method equals of the
Rectangle class, we had
a parameter of type Rectangle.
The equals methods that
we have written
up until now are thus not
overrides
of the equals method inherited from
Object; rather, they are overloaded methods.
We speak of redefining,
or overriding,
when a subclass's method
defines a method already present
in the superclass,
a method with exactly the same name,
list of parameters
and identical types, and with compatible
return types.
What we mean by compatible is:
for basic types,
they must be identical; for types defined
using classes,
these types will be compatible
if there is an inheritance link.
For example, if I have a superclass A
defining a method m,
returning an object of type A
If there exists a class B
inheriting from A,
which defines a method m, but
which returns a B,
since B inherits from A, we consider
that the types are compatible in this case,
and so this is also considered as
an override.
If these conditions are not met
and we only have
the name of the method which is the same,
we speak of overloading.
Defining the method equals by overloading,
as we did
in the previous episodes,
can work flawlessly,
however in Java, it is usually recommended
to use overriding
because some methods of the
Java API,
typically methods which work
on so-called collections,
for example methods that will retrieve
a value from a collection,
will implicitly use
the equals method,
which has this exact header.
If it is not present in one
of your classes
and you use this method,
then it is the default method, inherited
from Object, that will be used,
which is not satisfactory
in most cases.
So, how do we proceed if we really
want to override the equals method
inherited from Object rather
than overload it?
We present to you a possible way
of overriding the equals method,
a fairly common solution that you can
find in the litterature.
Note that there are other ways of
writing this equals method,
this is just one solution among others.
The main difficulty we face
when we want to override the
equals method
is that now, it can take as
parameter
any type of object.
When we used overloading,
the parameter had the same type
as the class in which we defined the
overload, so this here,
and invoking the equals method
on something other than a rectangle
for example a string, caused the
compiler to react.
If there was just an overload:
the compiler would tell you:
"I am expecting a String, and you
are giving me a Rectangle"
However, with an override, this form
becomes legal,
the compiler won't say anything,
it will accept this without a hitch.
Why? Because an object of type String
is an Object by inheritance
and so this is totally legal, I can have
a String in an Object.
Note that if we do not redefine the equals
method in the Rectangle class,
at the moment we made such a call,
we would use the equals method
as it is defined in the Object class,
which only compares references
and doesn't necessarily apply
the procedures
we would like to use
when we compare a rectangle with
another object.
So it is up to the programmer
of the equals method
to correctly define the body
of their method
in order for the comparison with
objects of types other than
rectangles to be donne correctly,
for example by returning false.
We want a rectangle to be comparable
to another rectangle,
but not to an object of another type.
To guarantee that a rectangle can
be equal only
to another rectangle,
we have to test if the object passed
as parameter is of the same class
as the Rectangle class.
This can be done using the
getClass method
inherited once again from Object.
With this method, we can test
if the class of the other object
is the same as the class of
the current instance.
And if not, we return false.
To summarize, when we want to override
the equals method,
we start, as we did for overloading,
by testing if the parameter has a
null value:
if it is null, we return false.
If not, and this is the new part,
we test if the other object is of the
same class as the current instance.
If not, we return false here too.
And if so, if we know that autreObjet
(TN: means "otherObject") is not null,
that the rectangle passed as parameter
is indeed of class Rectangle,
then we can proceed to an
attribute-by-attribute comparison,
as we did in the case of overloading.
But here, we have another little
difficulty to overcome:
indeed, if I want to compare
attribute-by-attribute,
I must test if the width
of the current object
is the same as the width as the
other object, autreObjet,
and if the height of the current object
is the same as the height
of the other object.
Yet autreObjet is of type Object,
which does not guarantee the presence
of the height and width attributes,
largeur and hauteur.
We know that autreObjet does
indeed contain a Rectangle,
we made sure of that with the
precautions we took.
However, if we write something
like this,
so if I try to compare the width of
the current object
with the width of the other object,
by using this statement here,
the compiler will throw an
error message
telling us that autreObjet is
of type Object
which does not contain a largeur
field.
Here, we convert autreObjet to
a Rectangle. This is known as casting.
This guarantees to the compileer that
it is possible to access the largeur field.
This will work perfectly here,
since we have guaranteed
that at execution time, autreObjet will
contain an object of type Rectangle.
If we try to do a cast
when autreObjet does
not contain a Rectangle,
we will get an error message
at execution time.
But this is not the case here.
So, basically, this is how
we can proceed
to override the equals method
with the new dangers that arise
when we use overriding
rather than overloading.
This ends our short episode on complements.