In the past lessons, we have seen the basics
of micro Nano fabrication in a clean room.
In the following lessons, I will show you
how you can inspect and measure the fabricated
structures with various methods.
I will start by introducing how you can use
the optical microscope in different imaging modes
to visually inspect the device surface.
I will also show you how you can use the optical
microscope to quantitatively measure
its "y" actual dimensions and to some extents fill sicknesses and vertical features
in the "z" direction.
I will briefly mention the important concerns
of calibration.
So let’s inspect the bi-morph actuator that
we use as a case study in this book.
Let us see how we can inspect it in order
to validate that the fabrication process was
successful.
On the left, you see a photograph taken with
a camera mounted on optical microscope.
The scale bar, in red, is very important and
serves as a reference to perform dimensional
metrology.
You certainly remember from the earlier lessons
that the cantilever are bent of plane and
consequently are not in focus.
I will show later how focusing on the optical
microscope can be used to determine the vertical
extension of the micro fabricated lens device
along the "z" axis.
The optical microscope is projecting the magnified
image of the object
via several lenses onto the imaging plane which is either an eye piece or a camera.
Modern microscopes have both modes available.
Using eye allows somewhat to get a quick overview
and identify contrast mechanisms in the image
quiet fast.
The camera is then better suited to record
images and videos to perform metrology and
to do image processing.
Magnification of samples can go up to 1000
times, which allows seeing features as small
as half a micrometer for high contrast samples.
Light is either transmitted through transparent
samples or is reflected from opaque surfaces.
This photo shows a typical optical mic which
is installed in a clean room.
The number from 1 to 11 indicates the key
components of the instrument that allow adjusting
the microscope settings for various imaging
modes and for the x, y, z positioning of the
sample.
The right side shows the light path coming
from the right source going through the lenses
into the sample and back to the eyepiece or
camera.
In this situation, the specimen is viewed
in the so called bright field imaging mode.
This means that, basically, all the lights
is used to image the surface.
Here, you will see 3 possibly and often used
variations of optical inspections.
Left, the already mentioned bright field imaging,
in the center, the so called dark field imaging,
and in the right hand side, it is the differential
interference contrast mode.
Let’s first look at the difference between
bright field and dark field.
In dark field, there is a path stop introduced
in the light path that blocks the central
part of the illumination.
Using only the peripheral part of the illumination
greatly reduces the image brightness but enhances
the detection of scattered light.
This dark field imaging mode is therefore
much darker, but it shows much better
any irregularities on the surface such as edges,
defects and dust.
In the DIC mode, a Nomarski prism is used
to split the incoming light into two beams
that are shifted by about 2 nanometers.
Any light path difference between these two
beams caused by surface topography will result
in interferences.
Using linearly polarized light ensures that
the two polarizations of the two split incident
light beams are orthogonal to each other after
passing through the prism.
This way, no interferences will occur until
the reflected light from the sample is passing
through the prism again,
But the polarization of the split light beam
is rotated back to the same direction.
Interference between the lights from the 2
adjacent points allow quantifying the height
difference on the sample surface which provides
a 3d appearance of the image in the DIC mode.
When we inspect the bi-morph device in these
3 modes, we can then see clearly how the images
are different.
The bright field image shows the true colors
and gives a general overview of the sample
surface and dimensions.
The dark field is darker in general and highlights
parts of the sample that scatters the light
beside the bands cantilever and the carriage
edge slopes in silicon,
you can see in particular the sharp edges
of the metal pattern, you can also small bright
spots on the metal contact part which shows
some surface roughness due to processing.
They could also be dust or contamination particles
in case the sample was taken out of the clean room.
The DIC image here on the right side reveals
a sort of a 3D surface image as it highlights
small surface topographic variations by the
interference effects.
All three imaging modes show complementary
information if relevant, one should use them
all to complete the inspection of a micro
or a Nano structure surface.
This table provides an overview of optical
inspection variables along with the particular
features and main areas of use.
Besides the 3 modes already mentioned,
the bright field, the dark field and the DIC modes,
the table also lists either imaging modes
that are not shown in detail in this course,
but that are used depending on the sample nature.
For instance, an image living biological cells
that are transparent,
one often uses a phase contrast mode to create
contrast by interference of the light caused
by phase shift inside the sample.
Polarizing the light is another way to create
contrast due to birefringence effects
often used when imaging minerals crystal.
And finally, an often used mode is to work
with fluorescent material that allows labelling
selectively part of the sample to create additional
contrast.
Besides quality control by optical inspection,
it is often necessary to measure dimensions.
This is called metrology and is meant to quantify
the device length width and thickness.
Modern optical microscopes have a scale bar
on the screen as a reference for the lateral
dimensions.
To ensure accurate dimensions, one performs
measurements on a well-known calibration sample.
This allows converting the number of micrometer
per image pixel into physical dimensions.
Using the one handed x objective on a chrome
mask calibration sample, one can see that
1 pixel corresponds to about 0.1243 micrometer.
We now inspect the bi-morph device with a
10x object to determine the lateral dimensions
of the silicon dioxide beams and chrome wires
by using the calibrated value of the pixel size.
In this case, you measure the width of the
chrome wires to be 99.4 micrometers,
which is slightly less than the 100 micrometers
in the design.
This deviation is most likely a result of
telefography processes and chrome etching.
Please also remember that the resolution here,
is limited by the fraction to about 500 nanometers.
To some extent, the optical microscope also
allows measuring vertical dimensions.
This practice is simple to implement and allows
for a first order of magnitude estimations.
As we know, the depth of the focus in an optical
microscope is shallow, particularly when using
high numerical aperture objectives.
If there are 3D at surface features on the
surface that touches 10 cantilever or edge holes,
we can manually displace a sample up
or down by along the z axis by the knob,
and thereby going in or out of the optical
focus.
This knob here, is scaled with 1 micrometer
of resolution.
If we focus on the top surface of the bi-morph,
record the scale number and then shift focus
to the bottom of the silicon cavity,
we can read on this scale the travel of the sample
and hence its radical extension.
Here, we measure the focus which is placed
in z axis by about 70 micrometer,
which is roughly the depth of the edge group.
For more precise measurement,
one should use another metrology tool
such as an optical or mechanical profilometer,
for instance, as shown later in this mooc class.
In this lesson, I have shown you how the optical
microscopy can be used,
as convenient method for inspection,
quality control and dimension measurements
of micro fabricated systems.
After every step in a micro Nano fabricated
process,
it is recommended to perform
a visual analysis of the sample
to detect any potential defect or mistake,
before continuing the processing.
The optical microscope is a workhorse instrument
that provides much information on the device quality and dimensions.
There is no need to contact its sample and
it works for both opaque and transparent specimen.
It is regarded as a fundamental and very important
method which is used very frequently in R&D
as well as in industrial production.