In wafer inspection, metrology and quality
control,
it is very important to determine
the exact thickness of deposited thin films.
Here in this lesson, I will show
how we can precisely quantify
the thickness of transparent films
such as silicon dioxide or silicon nitrate
using optical methods.
We will use again the bi-morph device as an
example and determine the SIO2 thickness.
Remember, we have already seen the silicon
dioxide coated to silicon wafers
in an earlier lesson.
Pay again attention to the different colors
appearance
which is a function
of the sio2 layer thickness.
This effect is due to the interference between the light reflected by the upper
and lower boundaries
of the transparent thin films.
It allows already getting a first estimation
of the SIO2 thickness.
For more precise value, we need specific tools.
I will now show you how we can determine
the SIO2 layer thickness of the bi-morph device
shown here again.
The SIO2 layer not only defines the mechanical
properties of the free standing bi-morph cantilever,
over here,
but it also delineates the mask
layer for the KOH action like here, here , here
and here.
Finally the SIO2 layer also serves as an electrical
isolation between the conducting chrome wires
and the underlying silicon substrate.
There are 2 ways to perform optical measurements shown here
and that use polychromatic light
that is incident to the surface
either normal or on the angle.
The light is then reflected back to the instrument
and by measuring intensity wavelength,
or polarization of the reflected light,
one can compute the thin film properties.
For instance by knowing the film parameters
of "n" and "k",
where "n" is the refractive index,
and "k" is the extension coefficient respectively,
one can precisely determine the SIO2 layer thickness.
It is also possible to measure
multiple thin films.
These techniques are entirely
non-destructive to the sample.
An equipment to measure the layer thickness
of thin films using the normal incidence mode
is called reflectometer or transmitometer
as shown here on the right side.
It is based on illumining the surface with
polychromatic light of wavelength
between 200 and 1100nm.
The reflectometer detects the change
in intensity of the reflected light
over the light source spectrum.
Intensity variations are due to thin film
interferences.
The illumination spot is in the order of 1.5 mm
as a consequence,
only large film samples
can be measured.
The range of thickness measurement is between
1 nm and 40 um.
This is quite a wide range.
This method is often used on photoresist,
SIO2, silicon nitrate class, and polymer samples.
It also allows "n" and "k" values,
in case the thickness is already known.
Please consult a company document for more
physics backgrounds of this measurement.
Let us take again the wafer in process for
the bi-morph device,
shown here.
you apply this method at the border of the
wafer, here,
where there is a large enough surface area
to place the measurement spot.
In this particular case, we measure
the SIO2 layer thickness
after the KOH etching.
Remember that the target value
for the SIO2 layer is 1.5 um.
We also know that the SIO2 serves
as a mask for the KOH etching.
But that the SIO2 is also ached slowly in
the KOH etch part.
Hence, we expect to see
a reduced thickness of the SIO2.
Let’s now verify this here.
The curve here, shows the reflectance on the "y" axis
as a function of the wavelength
on the "x" axis.
This spectrum shows a wafer curve
as shown here,
which is then fitted mathematically
to determine the SIO2 thickness.
In our case, we get 1.278 um which is with
the goodness of fit of nearly 1.
As expected, the thickness of SIO2
has been reduced
from our initial value of 1.5 um to 1.278 um.
The 200 nm difference obtained is expected
and is due to the loss of SIO2
during the KOH silicon etch.
Another often used tool is
the spectroscopic ellipsometer.
Here, the angle of light incident
is inclined
which induces a polarization
change after the reflection.
The linear polarization of the incoming light
is changed to elliptical polarization
for the reflected light.
The spot size of the light is in the order
of 400 um.
And can be aligned to a microstructure
if needed.
The wavelengths can be varied
between 190 nm and 2000 nm,
which allows measuring film thickness
from a few Amstrong
up to 50 um thickness.
The tool also allows determining to some extent
the composition roughness and "n" and "k" values,
where "n" is a real, and "k" is the imaginary
part of the refractive index.
It can be applied to a variety of dielectric
optically transparent thin films,
and even some metal thin films.
Please consult the study material for further
data on the basics behind this method.
As before, I show you now how to use the ellipsometer
to measure SIO2 layer thickness
in the bi-morph shaped area.
The spot size is small enough to measure
the SIO2 thickness at the border of the device
as shown here.
The two curves here, showing the "y" axis, the
"Alpha" and the "Beta" parameter,
for an angle of 45 degree and as a function of wavelengthhere shown in eV unit.
The parameters alpha and beta in y axis of
the spectrum are called ellipse parameters.
They are composed of the incident angle and
some geometric factors that describe the shape
of electrically polarized light
after the reflection.
The measurement here results in 1282 nm,
which increases very well the data obtained
from the reflectometer.
In this module, I have introduced 2 optical
techniques to determine the thin film thickness.
The reflectomer allows us a quick
and simple measurement.
For more precise measurement, it is advised
to use the ellipsometer.
Both of them do not touch and damage the sample,
and no sample preparation is required.