Two additional examples of
optical inspection and metrology
are a white light interferometer
and the laser beam surface profiler.
They are particularly useful to determine
the 3D aspect of MEMS surfaces
as well as film stresses.
We will use again our bi-morph example
and will use both methods
to determine the bending of substrate
and the bending
of cantilever devices.
Here you see again our well known bi-morph activated
devices,
let us now quantify precisely
how much actually
a cantilever is bend upwards.
Remember we could estimate this value
by the focus control of an optical microscope
like shown here.
But, let’s have a much more
precise approach now.
The principle of the white light interferometer
is shown here on the right side
with a general overview of the setup,
a zoom into the detail
of interference part,
and the photography
of the system in our clean room.
The white light interferometer system works as
follows.
The light coming into the mirau interferometer,
is focused by the lens,
and further split into 2 beams
using a semi-transparent mirror.
The reference beam is shown in orange,
whilst the object beam is shown in blue.
On a flat sample surface,
the light path of the reference
and the object beams are totally identical,
which means the light path
difference is 0
and hence constructive interference occurs.
On the other hand,
if the sample surface is not flat,
the light path difference
between the reference
and the object beam
is no longer 0.
Instead, interference intensity as shown in
purple here,
will change accordingly and is detected
by a light intensity detector.
This way, the topographic information
of the sample surfaces obtained,
typical values for field of view resolution
and "z" scan range are listed here.
On the left side, you see the bi-morph
cantilever device image
with the normal optical microscope.
Inspecting the bi-morph under the white light
interference gives us additional information.
White light interference image
delivers interference fringes
that allow quantifying very precisely
the out of claim bending of the cantilever.
We can see these fringes here on the bent
part of the cantilever.
By creating a profile along the cantilever,
you obtain the bending curve with
quantitative values as shown here.
Please notice that for high bending angles
above 45 degrees,
the system cannot detect
any more interference fringes.
This can be seen in the curve,
by the noisy curve and bumps.
The white light interference allows to create
a 3D colored map on the high profile.
Here, red means high,
and blue means low.
From a certain point the value and height
cannot be extracted,
because the bending curve
that can be delivered is too high.
In this case, tilting the sample
could be a solution.
The white light interferometer also allows
measuring the width of surface patterns
and depth of edge grooves as shown here.
In this example, let us assess
the silicon slope
that results from the anisotropic
silicon etch in KOH.
We know it should be about 54.7 degree,
which is the angle between the 100
and 111 crystal planes of the silicon.
But let us measure it now.
The data from the white light interferometer
tells us that the silicon cavity is 66 um deep.
And the silicon slope is 45 um long.
With these two values, we calculate
the angle to be 55.7 degree,
which agrees very well
with the theoretical value.
We can also measure the width
and the thickness of the chrome line here.
But doing so, I also would like to draw
your attention that each measurement
should be accompanied with
a thorough consideration of the sample condition,
to be able to correctly interprets
the measurement results.
Here, the measured line width
of the chrome pattern is 7.05 um.
This is quiet in contrast to
the design width of 10 um.
This difference in values is most likely a
result from a non-optimized lithography
and chrome white etch process,
and should be improved
for more critical devices.
The thickness measurement
indicates 2.25um as thickness.
Remember that chrome thickness
was designed to be 500 nm.
So, how come that we measure 2.25 um now ?
Let us have a look here at this drawing
which shows the cross section
at the point of interest.
The white light interferometer actually
detects the surface of silicon
and beneath, the transparent silicon dioxide film.
Here.
Therefore, the optical path difference is
the sum of both:
the thickness of the chrome
and the thickness of the silicon dioxide.
In addition, we need to take into account
that the SIO2
has a reflective index of about 1.5.
Which also changes the light
propagation inside this medium.
Therefore, since the height difference
is detected by the light path difference
between the reference and object beams,
we have to consider the silicon dioxide thickness as effective thickness,
which equals the refraction
index of silicon dioxide
multiplied by the thickness
of silicon dioxide.
Therefore, the measured total height
difference is obviously larger
than the true summation of 500 nm
for the chrome thickness,
and the true silicon dioxide
thickness of about 1.3 um.
If we take into account the thickness
loss due to the KOH etching
and which was already confirmed
by the measurement result
in the previous lesson.
The situation here reminds us always
not to trust a measurement result
without reasonable evaluation.
Remember in the mooc lesson
on physical wafer deposition,
we mentioned that the stress
from the deposited thin film
could leads to wafer and device bending.
The origin for this upward
or downward pending
can be either compressive
or tensile stress.
Here, I would like to introduce a methodology
to determine a thin film stress level by measuring
the wafer bending before
and after thin filmcoating.
To this end, we use a laser beam surface profiler.
It creates a line scan over
the entire wafer surface
and thereby determines the surface profile
and radius of curvature.
The drawing here on the right side
shows the principle.
A laser beam is aligned to the wafer surface
and then the reflected beam is detected.
The scanning had incorporated both the laser
source and the detector.
The head is scanning across
the entire wafer at a fixed time,
and any bending of the wafer will induce
changes in the angle of reflection.
Therefore, the curvature profile of the entire
wafer surface can be obtained.
To determine any stress piled up during fabrication,
we measure the wafer curvature before
and after the indoor position.
Then we calculate the thin film stress values
according to the Stoney equation shown here.
You already know it from a previous lesson.
Taking the wafer with bi-morph
cantilever device as an example,
let us now see how by adding the chrome film,
the shape of the wafer changes.
The left curve shows the profile of the silicon
wafer recorded on both side with SIO2.
shown here...
before chrome,
the bow is 2.17 um which comes
slightly from the wafer cutting and polishing.
The right curve shows the same wafer after
500 nm thick chrome layer on one side.
Now the bow is about -17.55 um.
From these values, we calculate the chrome
film stress to be 440 Mpa(Mega Pascal)
in the tensile direction,
based on this formulae.
Such values are typical in
inducing the resulting bending
as a common artifact during
thin film processing.
The bow here in the measurement result,
indicates the height difference between the peak
and the valley of the surface profiler.
This concludes this lesson on optical surface
analytical method
for MEMS inspection and metrology.
I have shown the white light interferometer
and the laser beam surface profilometer.
Both are non-contact and dusts do not
contaminate or damage the sample.
They are simple to use, and they all offer
important and in process characterization
of thin film and stress parameters.