After the optical non-contact method for wafer
inspection, this lesson presents tools that
rely on mechanically probing the surface of
a wafer of a MEMS device.
One example is the mechanical surface profiler
for film thickness measurement.
We will apply it to the wafer with the bi-morph
cantilever to measure the thickness of the
chrome thin films used to build the device.
Then, I will show you how the atomic force
microscope is used to characterize the surface
properties in high resolution. We apply it
here to quantify the roughness of the chrome
and sio2 surfaces in the bi-morph device.
The position where we intend to measure the
chrome layer on top of the sio2 layer is here.
To determine the device property, we need
to know precisely the thickness of the chrome
film as well as the surface quality, because
they influence the device performance.
For the first measurement, we used the mechanical
surface profiler, which is basically a diamond
needle that scans along a linear path in contact
with the device surface.
Here, we apply it to determine the thickness
of the chrome, film thickness, and here, we
apply it to measure the depth of the etched
silicon part.
Typically, a linear variable differential
transformer or LVDT is used to measure the
z displacement of the tip.
Here, you can see an illustration of an LVDT
device.
This particular case is based on electro magnetical
inducers.
It is composed of a moving part in green,
and the fero magnetic material in blue,
and the fix part with fixed coils embedded.
Please see in the study documents how such
LVDT is working in detail.
You perform so well measurement down to 1
nm of resolution along the z axis.
Typical maximum scan lens are in the order
55 mm. which is a bit more than half a 4 inch
wafer.
Since a contact force is not well controlled,
it may damage the surface of soft films and
cannot be applied to elastic structures.
The photo on the right side shows a screen
shot from the camera on the tool in our clean
room.
It shows here the tip above and its shadow
below.
We can also see the bi-morph device here.
Here, we see a schematic of the measurement
that will be formed. On the surface, we have
the pattern chrome, on the sio2 layer on silicon.
The drawing is not to scale. We do this measurement
after the KOH etching. As we know, KOH also
etches to sio2 slowly.
So we expect to see this in the profile. The
tip is scanned over a chrome thin film pattern
from left to right.
The scan line is highlighted here in blue
on the photo of the device.
The diagram here shows the height profile
on the z axis as a function of the scan location
on the x axis.
The measured step height is 781.4 nm which
is as expected more than the targeted 500
nm chrome thickness.
The additional step comes from the loss of
sio2 during the KOH aching.
The second curve here shows the scan across
the KOH etch shown here on the photo.
Here, the depth is about 67 um which agrees
well with the design value and also with the
optical measurement shown in the previous
lesson.
Please note while the surface profilometer
is very accurate for vertical displacement,
it has a poor lateral resolution due to the
convolution of a relatively blank tip.
To overcome this resolution limit, we now
consider the atomic force microscope or an
AFM.
AFM is a highly sensitive and high resolution
mechanical surface scanner just like the surface
profiler introduced before. The key distinction
of the AFM is that, it operates in force feedback.
By doing so, it reduces the contact force
between tip and surface.
Due to the high force sensitivity, it does
not harm or scratch the surface and can be
applied to very fragile surfaces.
Very sharp tip is a STEM of a flexible cantilever
that bends when a force is applied to its
end.
The bending is measured by the laser beam
deflection system as shown here.
Here, the tip is a raster scan with an area
of interest and the vertical deflection is
recorded for each x-y position.
Thus providing a 3 d surface image. The said
axis resolution is in the order of 1 Amstrong
or below.
Lateral resolutions are below 10 nm. Besides
making 3 d images of its surface at high resolution,
it allows us to quantify the surface roughness
which often plays a role for device performance.
The image on the right side here shows a TEM
image of a commercial AFM tip, showing a very
sharp epics that provides a higher lateral
resolution.
Let us now apply AFM to measure the surface
roughness of the chrome, and sio2 layer in
the bi-morph device.
On the left side, you see an AFM image of
1 of the bi-morph cantilever. The circle here
indicates the area of interest that we want
to inspect in detail with the AFM.
To this end, we mount the sample to an AFM
system, and we align the AFM to scan the area
here on the chrome, and here on the sio2.
A photo of the AFM setup in our clean room
is shown here.
This video shows a sequence of screenshots
recorded during a real AFM imaging of the
chrome sample as discussed before.
The video is partially accelerated and edited
to make it shorter. In reality, you should
count for about 3 to 5 min to setup and prepare
the measurement.
And then, about 3 min to record an entire
image of about 500 by 500 nm in good resolution.
First we locate the measurement side of interest
with the aid of the integrated optical microscope.
In this case, we aim to inspect a chrome surface
on the bi-morph wafer which is the bright
area on the image.
The AFM cantilever tip is not in contact with
the surface during the navigation.
Once we are at the right spot to measure,
we set up and check the measurement parameters
such as the scan size, scan rate, and sampling
rate, then we approach the tip to the surface
and start scanning.
The approach between the tip and the surface
is done automatically while monitoring the
cantilever response.
After approaching the surface, the scanning
begins. Here in this sequence, you see the
image built up in real time with a real time
topographical profile here at the bottom.
Now we accelerate the video, in reality the
entire image takes 3 min to build up.
Please notice that the x and z axis are not
in scale and the blue and red lines are the
result of forward and backward scanning respectively.
The scanning range here, again, is 500 by
500 nm.
Here, are shown the AFM scan data of the chrome
film here, and sio2 here.
The left shows the top few in color code with
x y scan area and the z scale here in this
color bar.
The surface topography profile along the blue
line is shown in the center where we see the
chrome has a roughness of about 5.72 nm in
average.
We also see that the sio2 is much smoother
and has a roughness of about 0.211 nm in average.
To make this difference clear, we show these
2 scanned data with the same z-x value. Here
and here.
Images on the right are a tilted 3d view of
the same scan as shown on the left.
They allow for our eyes to see easier the
surface Nano scale landscape.
This lesson presented 2 mechanical surface
profiler instruments.
Remember that in some cases the physical contact
between the tip and the surface can induce
some damage.
On the other hand, unlike the optical method
seen before, we can also measure the thickness
of opaque film which is not available with
optical methods.
Hence, we can also use AFM to obtain Nano
scale images on both conducting and insulating
materials. This is an advantage compared to
methods using charged beams as you will see
in the next lesson.