Now, I will show you how charged electrons
in a scanning microscope can be used to perform
inspection, quality control, and metrology.
First, I will remind you briefly how an electron
microscope works and how electrons interact
with matter.
Then, I will list the various electron signals
that I used to examine the sample.
I will briefly mention the issue of electrons
charging, and show how the same can be used
to perform dimensional metrology at a nanometer
scale.
As a quick reminder to what we have already
seen earlier in this mock chapter of electron
beam lithography.
We use a focused electron beam primarily to
overcome the diffraction limit of optical
systems that are typically in the order of
lambda over 2,
or around 300 nm for visible light.
Remember that electrons can be associated
to wavelength depending on the electron energy,
the associated wavelength can be as small
as a few um.
Please notice however that the resolution
of a scanning electron tool is not limited
by the electron wavelength,
but by the focusing ability of the system
and the electrons scattering, as we have already
seen in the previous lesson.
As a thumb rule, remember that a SEM can resolve
images of conducting samples down to a few
nm, as you can clearly see on this electron
microscope here, showing the bi-morph cantilever
in very high resolution.
In a scanning electron microscope, electrons
are emitted from an electron gun here, and
accelerated under high voltage to obtain momentum
and travel through the chamber.
Several electromagnetic lenses shape and steer
the electron beam.
In order to avoid unwanted scattering between
electrons and atmospheric molecules,
the entire system is working in a vacuum chamber.
The electron beam is focused on the specimen
structures down here and interacts with its
atoms.
Detectors and filters, here, number 7 and
8 collect the back scattered electrons.
The brightness of each pixel is determined
according to the number of collected electrons.
The electron beam is deflected to scan the
scanned surface pixel by pixel and line by
line to record an image.
During the electron scanning process, negative
charges accumulate on the surface of the electric
material which reduces the image quality.
Therefore, for high quality images, a conductive
sample is required, or a non-conducting material
has to be coated with a thin conducting film.
Typically, in good conditions, a modern SEM
system can reach resolutions down to about
1 nm and below.
Different electron signals can be detected
in a scanning electron microscope system.
On the right side, you see possible electron
atoms interaction.
We call the incident electron as primary electron
(PE).
Mostly, when a PE hits an atom, it generates
a secondary electron (SE).
Which we can collect to have a secondary electron
image or so called SE image.
This is the most commonly used signaling in
SEM which gives us a good contrast cost by
a sample surface topographic structures.
The SE detector is situated in the electron
beam path as shown here in blue.
And is called in lens SE detector which collects
most of SE efficiently.
Best scattered electrons (BSE) are primary
electrons that are reflected or back scattered
by elastic collisions with atoms.
Atoms with higher atomic number generates
higher BSE signals, which allows detecting
material contrast.
Another special detector is called Everheart
Tonly detector (ET detector).
It is designed to collect both SE’s and
BSE’s.
Unlike the In-lens SE detector, the E-T detector
is placed on the side in the SEM chamber as
shown here in orange.
To be able to collect SE and BSE with large
angles with respect to the PE.
This enhances the image contrast for topographic
and etch features.
The signal generated from these detectors
called high efficiency SE imaging (HE-SE2)
for the specific same model that we used during
the demonstrations in this chapter.
PE with high enough energy can also knock
out inner shell electrons from the sample
atoms.
This causes an electron from a higher energy
state to fill the empty state whereby a photon
is released.
This is the so called characteristic X-ray.
By detecting the energy dispersive x ray,
we can therefore, perform spectroscopic compositional
analysis of the sample
in other words, we can determine what material
we are looking at, and this at a very high
spatial resolution.
Here, we can see 2 SEM image taken with different
detectors.
Both images are taken under same conditions
such as electron energy and working distance.
On the left side, we see the image taken by
in-lens secondary electron detector.
It is very bright because it collects most
of SE.
On the down side, the charging effect of the
sio2 layer on the bi-morph is also obvious.
On the other hand HE-SE2 detector shown here
on the right hand side provides better contrast
and clearer etched definition in the case
of the bi-morph device.
For our purpose, the choice of this detector
is thus preferred.
In order to better demonstrate the material
contrast of BSE image, here, we use a carbon
Nano tube sample as an example.
Such a sample is used to adjust and calibrate
the SEM tool.
Here, are bundles of carbon Nano tubes.
The scale bar is 10um.
The In Lens SE image on the left side, here
we cannot distinguish the metal and cobalt
catalytic Nano particles that are used during
the synthesis of carbon nano molecules.
While in the BSE image on the right side,
each catalytic particle are highlighted and
can be easily detected.
If there is a downside of charged particle
imaging to mention, it is the problem of charging.
If the electrons used to image the sample
cannot be removed to ground, then, they will
accumulate in the sample,
which will deviate the trajectory of the next
electron.
The direct consequence is a blurred image.
The 3 SEM images here show photoresist which
is insulating on sio2 which is also insulating.
One can see the charging effect in the left
image that increases over time in the middle.
One remedy is to coat the sample with a very
thin conducting layer, either gold or chrome
layer.
The result can be seen here on the right.
Notice that, of course, we are now imaging
the gold layer on top of the sample.
But for many investigations in MEMS, this
is not an issue, and allow seeing the surface
quality of the device.
To conduct the electron charger to ground,
it is important to ensure a proper conduction
path.
Example by means of a conducting cape as shown
here.
In order to perform a calibrated dimensional
measurement in an SEM,
one needs to first ensure that the instrument
is calibrated.
This is done typically using a calibration
with known dimension.
This will translate then, the conversion ratio
between each pixel in the data acquisition
and assembled dimensions in nm or um.
This allows defining a scale bar which then
can be used to measure the size of unknown
samples with high accuracy.
The calibration sample are typically made
by electrons beam lithography.
It is however then known that, due to over
exposure or under exposure,
or over or under development, the exact pattern
which is not perfectly predictable.
That is why instead of using the pattern line
with its calibration reference, one favors
a periodic pattern where the pitch is highly
accurate even if the individual pattern widths
are not very precisely defined.
The SEM image on the right shows the surface
of the bi-morph device where the SEM is now
used to measure the width of the chrome pattern.
The white lines are positioned on the same
tool to accurately measure the chrome pattern.
It really confirms now that the value obtained
before, the chrome pattern is about 7.2 um
wide, which is much less than the design 10
um, and which is due to some lithography effect.
If you see how they inspect a MEM sample in
a scanning electron microscope,
we mount the sample hole of the silicon MEM
sample on the transfer stage.
A load lock maintains the high vacuum inside
the SEM chamber during the sample transfer.
After the sample transfer, we setup the right
configuration of the system.
The first step is to position the sample to
a proper working distance with respect to
the electron column and detector.
Then, we use the controller to tune the electron
beam and the image.
Here on the screen, you see the electron beam
image made on a silicon sample with the proactive
IMH goose.
You see how one can navigate around and zoom
in and out.
Here, we have seen how electrons, as charged
particles in a SEM can be used to inspect
a MEM device surface.
They allow for very high resolution in imaging,
and they allow for dimensional metrology.
Remember that some materials might be damaged
by the electron charged or heat generated.