MEMs processes like the ones shown in this
mock, involve layer by layer deposition processes
similar to the fabrication of integrated micro
electronic circuits.
Once the fabrication is finished, it is sometimes
necessary to check and characterize the sub
surface structure,
to perform a quality check, and eventually
analyze when there is a device failure.
One very useful tool in enabling sub surface
inspection is the focused ion beam or FIB.
It allows removing local material, and is
therefore invasive.
I will show you how a FIB system can be used
to determine the z-axis dimension of the layers
in the micro fabricated MEMs device.
Here, we show again the bi-morph cantilever
device our case study where we fabricated
the bi-morph with a layer by layer micro fabrication
process shown again here on the right side
in cross section.
In the previous lessons, the sio2 loss in
the KOH path during the silicon etching in
step 7 here, was already mentioned.
We have already measured this by the mechanical
and optical profilometer.
Here, we will show you how to use the FIB
to inspect and measure the amount of sio2
loss in more detail
without breaking the entire wafer.
An FIB system is like an electron beam system,
and can also be used for both ion beam imaging
and ion beam milling.
Instead of using electrons with very small
mass, you will now use positively charged
ions.
A liquid metal ion source is made of Gallium
which is heavy, has low melting temperature
and thus allows for convenient ion generation.
Imaging with gallium plus ions also dimensions
the surface during scanning.
One can now utilize this fact to sputter material
of the sample surface.
The digging or sputtering mode removes material
from the sample surface in a larger area and
in a faster speed using high ion current.
The milling mode removes material from the
surface with slower rate and better spatial
precision.
It results in smoother cross section, and
performs some polishing, which is essential
to perform cross sectional inspection and
dimension measurement.
In order to have a well-defined cross section
of the sample, there is a need to locally
protect the surface from unwanted erosion
by the milling.
This function is integrated in DEFIT system
by local platinum deposition.
Since ions are damaging the surface when imaging
and modern systems is conflicted into a so
called dual beam system.
That incorporates both an ion beam and an
electron beam column.
As for the SEM, it is better to perform FIB
on a conducting sample.
In the dual beam system, the in-situ SEM and
FIB columns are arranged at an angle of about
52 degree with respect to each other.
In the FIB chamber, we use a tilted sample
so that it senses the ion beam in the normal
direction, in order to obtain vertical cross
section with respect to the sample surface.
Therefore, the in-situ SEM image is taken
at the tilting angle of 52 degree with respect
to the surface.
In order to have a better image quality for
us to compare the ion imaging and SEM imaging,
and the volt charging, we coat the bi-morph
device with a 20 nm thick chrome layer.
The sample here is at the process stage before
the KOH wet etch ach in the silicon.
You can see the image quality is quiet comparative
between ion imaging here, and the SEM electron
imaging.
So keep in mind that however, that the surface
is damaged by the ions in the left image.
We will now use the FIB for what it is actually
designed for, namely to inspect in detail
the cross section in the area where the chrome
pattern forms and etch on the sio2 layer.
Shown Here, This time, we use the bio-morph
wafer after the KOH.
Remember we know that KOH has been used to
etch the silicon, also etches the sio2, and
now, we want to verify this etching in detail.
We used the focused ion driller hole at the
edge of the chrome pad.
First we add a local layer of platinum protection
shown here by the focused ion beam induced
deposition.
This platinum layer.
Not only reduces the charges during FIB milling,
but it also provides a smoother top surface
to reduce ion scattering during digging and
milling, and thus provides a smoother side
wall.
The photo on the right side shows the structure
after the FIB has been used to mill the hole
at the cross section between the chrome pad
and the sio2.
The platinum protection here, and the hole
created here that goes in deeper into the
silicon.
We now zoom into the area of interest.
With the same after the ion milling, so now
we don’t damage the sample anymore.
And for better measurement, we tilt the sample
to see clearly into the cross section.
We see the silicon substrate here.
We see the sio2 which is 1.6um thick here.
And we see the chrome layer 545 nm thick.
We also see the Pt platinum protection layer
here.
We see in particular, the under etched sio2
layer that is about 230 nm under etch.
Which is exactly the value that we expect
from the KOH etching, from the values already
obtained by the optical and mechanical surface
metrology done during the previous lessons.
In the additional study material, you can
find more details on FIB techniques for post
process sample inspection and Feeler analysis,
and to what one should pay particular attention.
In this lesson, you have seen how to use FI
to inspect the MEMS device with very high
resolution.
Remember that this technique is invasive and
damages at least locally the devices.
But it can be applied to a full wafer in mid
process.