In this module, I will present methods to
characterize the electrical properties of
micro and nano fabricated devices and systems.
I will first introduce how to measure the
resistivity of thin films, and particular
provide measured details of the thin chrome
film that we used for the bi-morph actuator.
Then, I will show the functionalities of the
prober station and show how to use it for
electric characterization of the bi-morph
actuator.
Remember our case study of the bi-morph actuator
that we used to run through the typical MEMS
fabricated processes.
If we now have a closer look in how we can
determine the resistivity of the probe thin
film
and show how we can calculate and measure
the electrical resistance of the chrome heaters,
that are used to induced their bending.
A well-known and widely used method to determine
the resistivity of a thin film is based on
the so called Van de Pauw 4 point probe measurement.
It is schematically shown here in this drawing.
4 needles with about 1 mm spacing in between
are in contact with the thin film in yellow.
A source applying a well-controlled current
through the 2 outer probes induced a current
flowing through the sample in same frame.
The 2 inner probes are measuring the voltage
difference.
The strength of this method is that since
we measure the voltage, and not a current,
the contact resistance is not critical, and
allows for more measurement of the resistivity.
This method applies to conducting and semi-conducting
thin films as well as to bulk samples not
shown here in this lectures.
With the measured value of voltage and current,
we can use the Van der Pauw formulae as shown
here, to calculate sheet resistance.
The pi over log of 2 here, is the geometric
factor aid for using 4-point measurement for
thin film with a thickness that is neglect
able with regard to the spacing between the
probes.
We then can calculate resistivity by multiplying
the sheet resistance with the thickness of
the thin film.
The photograph on the right shows the automatic
4-point probe tool in our clean room, which
can measure the sheet resistance on multiple
sites on a wafer automatically.
Here is a video showing the operation of the
resistivity meter in our clean room.
The wafer to measure is a sio2 coated silicon
wafer, after the 500 nm thick chrome deposition.
Once the wafer is placed on the sample holder,
and the measurement is set up,
the probing head carrying 4 needles will start
to measure the sheet resistance from 5 sides
on the wafer automatically.
If you ever reach 5 sites sheet resistance,
and calculate the resistivity of the chrome
film on the bi-morph to be 1.076 * 10power-6
ohm meter.
This is a reasonable value for chrome film
deposited on the silicon dioxide by means
of thermo evaporation.
The resistivity of the deposited metal film
may have different values depending on how
the film is deposited.
It also depends on the underlying material.
Please notice that the resistivity meter can
only measure the un patterned thin film.
In the bi-morph device, the chrome resistance
is pattern by lithography to form a conducting
path with a certain length L, and the width
W, and a U shape as shown here in this drawing.
Let us now calculate the resistance of the
chrome heater.
Resistance equals resistivity times the resistance
length over the thickness and the width.
The definition of sheet resistance = resistivity
/resistor thickness and the squared number
defined as resistance length / resistor width.
The resistance = sheet resistance * sq.
In this case, the sheet resistance of chrome
film is obtained from resistivity meter as
2.152 ohm square.
The effective length of the u shaped chrome
resistance defined as shown here, and the
value is 640 um.
The width of the chrome resistance obtained
by averaging the same measurement resulting
in the previous chapter of 7.13 um.
All together we calculate the chrome resistance
to be 193.
2 ohm.
The tool to access to the inner part of the
MEMS and to apply electrical signals is often
based on a prober,
which is nothing else than fine needles that
can be positioned with micrometer precision
on a specific location of a MEMS device.
Tungsten needles can be controlled on an optical
microscope, with micrometer precision and
controlled electrical signal, that is voltage
and current can be applied.
A minimum contact area of 50 by 50 m is needed
to position the needles properly.
Typical curves that one can extract are IV,
CV, C-f and C-t measurements.
To some extent, high frequency measurements
can be done.
In our case, they apply a DC voltage to determine
the resistive value of our bi-morph MEMS device.
If you see now on the left side SEM image,
one of our chrome bi-morph actuator beams,
the blue arrows show where we apply the prober
needles.
Here again, we use a 4 probe principle to
inject the current here, and to measure the
voltage here.
The current then flows through the cantilever
in and out of this new shaped wire.
By doing so, we are not influenced by the
contact positions between the needles and
the contact pads.
Which is not often well defined and could
induce some errors.
The right plot here shows the resulting IV
curve of the measurement.
The applied current on the x axis and the
resulting voltage on the y-axis.
By calculating the slope, we can find that
resistance of the bi-morph actuator is 215
ohms.
It is about 10 % deviated from what we just
calculated in the slides before.
We have seen a few sample, but essential methods
to determine the electrical properties of
fabricated micro devices, which allows ultimately
determining whether the process has been successful,
and allows further to study new material,
and their electrical properties.
This is very important to improve the device
performance of new MEMS and MEMS.
This last metrology ends inspection lessons,
closes the MEMS mock lectures.
On behalf of the entire mock MEMS team, I
would like to thank you for your interest
and active participation.
As always, we are eager to read your comments
and feedback to further improve these lessons
in upcoming sessions.
Bye for now and enjoy the quizzes.