[Music]
Welcome to our mooc in micro and nano fabrication.
My name is Juergen Brugger and I am one of the
co-authors and teachers of this mooc.
My name is the Martin Gijs and I am the second
co-author and teacher of this mooc.
Together we will show you in the following lectures
the basics of micro and nano fabrication techniques.
We will show you in particular how they are carried out
in a typical clean room environment.
Today we are constantly using micro devices so called MEMS
that help us communicating and navigating
measure our health parameters such as blood pressure and glucose level,
monitor and control automotive safety parameters,
such as airbags and tyre pressure, enable us to enjoy realistic
augmented reality and video gaming etc
These devices are ubiquitously available today
becasue they can be fabricated in large volumes and cost efficiently
The goal of this course is to introduce you to the fundamentals
of the fabrication techniques that are behind these success stories
which actually have enabled them.
After this introduction, we would give you chapter by chapter
the theoretical basis to understand the principal mechanisms of
thin film deposition, lithography, arching and other techniques.
Each chapter is completed by illustrations and examples
so that you can clearly see the link between
a particular fabrication step
and the resulting functionality in the micro device.
[Music]
During this mooc lectures, I will first show some well known
MEMs devices that we are using in our everyday life
I will be showing particular how micro and nano fabrication has
enabled their manufacturing in high volumes and at low cost.
I will then take over to show you how a clean room is designed and operated
to ensure that the fabricated MEMs devices are as clean as possible.
We both we then follow up by describing the
basics of the various fabrication steps
such as thin film formation, lithography as well as arching.
We hope that you enjoyed our mooc lecture. So let's get started.
[Music]
Bye-bye.