Welcome to week two
of cellular mechanisms of brain function.
Last week, we learned about
the phospholipid bilayer
that forms the cell membrane
and electrically acts as a capacitor.
We also learned about ion channeled
proteins that span the plasma membrane
and form conductors with specific
reversal potentials given by
the ionic species
for which that ion channel
is permeable to.
These reversal potentials were given
by the Nernst equation
calculated from the concentration
gradients distributed
across the plasma membrane.
We also learned that membrane potential
was signaled in a complicated way
across the extended neuronal
arborisations of real neurons.
Changes in membrane potential in one part
of a neuron were signaled
to other parts of a neuron, but only after
spatial and temporal filtering.
Temporal filtering occurred approximately
on the ten millisecond timescale
given by the membrane time constant.
The length constant of the cell
on the order of several hundredths
of microns defines the length scale
over which steady state voltage
differences are propagated across
neuronal arborisations.
Now, in real neurons, and in the real
mammalian brain
signals need to traverse
much longer distances.
One part of the brain needs to be able
to communicate with another
part of the brain spanning
some 20 centimeters.
And some parts of the brain need to be
able to communicate down the spinal cord
extending meters.
Given that we know that membrane potential
is filtered significantly by the cable
properties of neurons, how then
do reliable signals
arise in the nervous system?
The answer comes in the form
of the action potential,
a digital all or none signal that's
actively propagated
across the neuronal arborisations
through voltage gated ion channels.
Today we'll study the biophysics of these
Voltage-gated ion channels.
Last week we discussed linear channels.
These are ion channels where
the conductance is independent
of the membrane potential.
And this then allows us to plot linear
current voltage relations-
so-called ohmic conductances.
Today we'll think about
non-linear conductances
where the permeation of cations
through the ion channel
depends upon the membrane potential.
This gives rise to non-linear IV plots
where the conductance
at one potential might be very far
from its linear counterpart.
Such non-linear conductances give
the nervous system
enormous computational power.
How can an ion channel
be voltage dependent?
Let's return to look at the protein
structure of voltage-gated ion channels.
The ion channel is made out of a chain
of amino acids that span
from the inside to the outside
of the plasma membrane
meeting the lipid bilayer in parts
and in other parts
meeting an internal
aqueous channel that allows
the ions to permeate across
the plasma membrane.
If we look down upon the face
of the plasma membrane
and see the phospholipid head groups
and the ion channel from the outside
we would see a view something like this.
Here are the phospholipid head groups
Here are the red sub-units
of the ion channel.
Voltage-gated ion channels are composed
of four similar sub-units.
Sometimes they're part of the same protein
sometimes they're part of different
proteins that come together.
In any case, they form a tight
association, these four sub-units
and down the middle, of course is the
ion conducting pore.
Each of these sub-units is composed
of multiple trans-membrane segments.
Here you see an example ion channel
with the typical six
trans-membrane alpha helices.
We have alpha helix one, two,
three, four, five, and six.
There's a color-coding of these
trans-membrane alpha helices
and you'll see that there's a yellow part
here composed of S5 to S6
and that turns out to form the pore-lining
region of the ion channel.
So, next to these alpha-helices,
we have the aqueous pore.
And, in fact, this turns out to be where
the selectivity filter is located.
The red alpha helices S1 to S3 are here
on the outside of the protein.
They need to interact with the
phospholipid bilayers
the lipophilic part of the ion channel.
And here, colored in blue,
is a special part of the ion channel
for voltage-gating, the so-called S4
voltage-sensing region.
The S4 voltage-sensing domain
that you see again here in blue
is interesting and forms a sort of unit
that can move and is relatively
mobile within the structure of
the ion channel.
The S4 voltage-sensing region is
interestingly, positively charged.
It's full of arginine amino acids
that have positive charge on them.
The ability of the S4 region to be
relatively mobile and that it's charged
allows it to interact with the electric
field across the plasma membrane.
At hyper-polarized potentials,
there's a strong electric field
that is from the outside to the inside.
That electric field acts upon
the charges of the S4
voltage-sensing domain
and pushes it downward
towards the inside of the cell.
The S4 voltage-sensing domain is attached
to a gating mechanism, the voltage-gate.
When these positive ions are pushed in
towards the inside of a cell
the gate swings up, and it's closed.
the ion channel cannot open,
and cannot permeate ions.
If, on the other hand, we switch
to a positive membrane potential
the positive charges on the S4
voltage-sensing region
are moved out in the electric field,
they act upon the voltage-gate
of the ion channel, open it, and allow
the ions to flux when the ion channel
opens and closes in its
random stochastic manner.
So the movement of the S4
Voltage-sensing domain
gates the open probability
of a voltage-gated channel
in a membrane potential-dependent fashion.
We know that there's a physical reality
to the movement of these charges
on the S4 voltage-sensing domain,
because, even in the absence
of any ion flux through the ion channel,
you can measure the gating charge
if you change the membrane potential
rapidly to a positive value
you can see that there's
a capacitative current
very brief, very fast,
on the microsecond time-scale
that indicates the capacitative movement
of these positive charges
on the S4 voltage-sensing domain
as it moves out.
So, at the level of
an individual ion channel,
where we'll now consider the difference
between a linear and a voltage-gated
ion channel, on the right.
For a linear ion channel,
the open probability
of that ion channel doesn't depend
upon the electric field that we have.
The open probability will be the same
if there's a membrane potential
of +60 mV or -60 mV.
And here, we imagine
for example an ionic conductance
that has a reversal potential at 0 mV.
This would be the current,
the voltage
and we have a linear conductance.
And so, at a membrane potential of +60 mV
we have a certain amount of time that
the ion channel spends in the open state,
compared to the closed state, in this case
maybe it's in the open state
about half of the time.
If you go to negative
hyper-polarized potentials
the open probability of a standard linear
ohmic ion channel doesn't change.
The open probability is still about 50%.
But now, of course,
when the ion channel opens
then the currents flow in, because we're
in this symmetric situation here
where we have +60 and -60 mV
the amount of current here is the same
at both ends in an ohmic ion channel
with reversal at 0 mV.
For the voltage-gated ion channel,
the situation is very different.
At negative potentials, the ion channel
has a low open probability.
Remember, the S4 gating area here is
positive, and the gate is closed
at negative potentials.
So, this channel spends relatively
little time in the open state.
When it does open,
however, we get the full normal
single channel currents, just as we would
in the linear situation.
What changes through
the voltage-dependance
of voltage-gated ion channels
is the open probability.
The probability is a function of the
membrane potential.
At positive potentials,
the gating of the S4
voltage-gating region is then changed.
The S4 region moves out, the gate is
then opened, and ions can flux.
The open probability then increases
at positive membrane potentials
for a voltage-gated ion channel.
These changes in open probability can then
be either summated over time
where we take a mean current flux across
a stochastic opening and closings
of the ion channel, or we can think of
many ion channels on the cell membrane
that are opening and closing
independently of each other
and we then have a mean conductance,
that's of course composed
of the single channel conductance
times the number of ion channels
and of course, together with the open
probability of that ion channel.
And so, for a linear conductance,
the conductance is independent
of membrane potential,
so it's a flat line.
The conductance is the same at positive
and negative potentials
because the open probability is the same
at open and negative potentials.
And we've agreed that the single channel
conductance is not a function of voltage.
For the voltage-gated scenario,
we have a change in
open probability in voltage.
At negative potentials,
the open probability is low,
and the conductance,
is therefore, also low.
As we depolarize, we move
the S4 voltage-gating region out,
the voltage-gate opens, and the open
probabilty of the ion channel increases
and we move up here on the conductance
until we reach some sort of steady state
region here, where the ion channel is
saturated with respect
to its voltage-dependence.
If we now think specifically about
sodium and potassium channels,
and voltage-dependent sodium
and potassium channels
are amongst the most important
voltage-gated channels
in the nervous system,
we now need to think
for the sodium and potassium channels,
about their reversal potentials.
And we know that sodium has a positive
reversal potential,
somewhere around +60 mV
and potassium
has a negative reversal potential
somewhere around -90 mV.
And so, the single channel currents all
would be flowing through a single
sodium channel at different
membrane potentials
as the ion channel opens and closes
so this single channel sodium current
will then be linear, and reversing
of course, at the sodium
reversal potential.
Similarly, the single channel
potassium currents
as the ion channel opens and closes
will also be linear
with respect to voltage,
and will of course reverse
at the reversal potential for potassium.
For voltage-gated sodium
and potassium channels
in general, they become activated
at relatively similar membrane potentials.
And so, somewhere around -40 mV
and more positive to that
the ion channels begin to open,
the voltage-gated sodium channels
increase their conductance
above -40 mV and the same is true
for the voltage-gated potassium currents.
And so, there's a regime here
hyper-polarized to -40 mV
in which there's very little conduction
through the voltage-gated
sodium and potassium channels.
They're closed at most
resting membrane potentials.
And at more positive potentials to -40
they begin to become activated
in a strong and steep manner
becoming almost fully
activated around 0 mV.
If we then convolve this voltage-gating
the change in the open probability
of the voltage-gated sodium channel
with respect to voltage
we convolve that open probability
with the single channel currents
and the reversal potential
at the sodium reversal potential
we see that we get a current
voltage relationship
that looks something like this.
At negative potentials
the ion channel is closed
and therefore, there's no
current that flows
as we move through the -40 mV
and the open probability
begins to become significant
we then get single channel conductances
that are substantial then give rise
to an inward current.
As we keep depolarizing,
the voltage gating saturates
we hit the reversal potential for sodium
and we enter the linear conduction regime.
And so we have this interesting
biphasic situation
where between the physiological range
of membrane potentials
from -90 to around +60 mV
we have an inward current
that's generated by the
voltage-gated sodium channel.
For the voltage-gated
potassium channels
the situation is very similar.
At negative potentials
the conductance is basically closed.
And so, there's nothing carried by
the voltage-gated potassium conductance.
As we depolarize beyond -40 mV
it activates, and we see now
that there's an outward current that we
can then compute by multiplying
the overall open probability of
the potassium with respect
to voltage and the single channel
currents that go through it.
As we keep depolarizing the
more and more conductance is activated
until we hit this linear regime,
and that's what we see here,
we end up in this linear regime here
and interestingly, again
in this range of the physiologically
relevant membrane potentials
from -90 to +60 mV here, we always
have an outward current
in terms of what can be carried
by the potassium channels.
So, we've seen some interesting features
of voltage-gated ion channels.
They're largely closed at
resting membrane potentials.
Membrane potential is normally somewhere
in the range from -70 to -50 mV.
In this range, the open probability
of voltage-gated sodium
and potassium channels is very low,
and they'll make
very little contribution
to the overall conductance
of the membrane.
At more positive potentials
to -40 mV the open probability increases
sharply, and the voltage gated
ion channels then begin to conduct
and can contribute
to the overall conductance
of the cell membrane.
The change in conductance
of the voltage-gated ion channels
is not because of a change in the
single channel conductance
but it is a change in the overall
open probability.
Let's see how voltage-gated ion channels
can contribute to changing
membrane potential in neurons.
Let's consider a cell that has
Voltage-gated sodium
and potassium channels,
each of which has a single channel
conductance of roughly 20 pS.
The input resistance of a cell,
it's total input resistance
is somewhere around 50 M╬⌐,
typically, and that corresponds
to an input conductance of
something like 20 nS.
So, this is the leak conductance
of a typical neuron.
And it's dominated by a leak potassium
conductance that keeps membrane potential
somewhere around -70 mV on average.
In order for the voltage-gated
sodium or potassium channels
to have a major impact
upon membrane potential,
we need for these conductances
to get close,
at least in the same ballpark,
as these leak conductances.
Remember that the membrane potential
goes something like the sodium conductance
divided by the total conductance
and the reversal potential for sodium.
So, if the total conductance is dominated
by sodium conductance
the membrane potential will tend towards
the reversal potential for sodium.
So, if we want the voltage-gated
sodium channels to make
a considerable impact upon the
overall membrane potential,
the overall sodium conductance
must somehow at least get close
to the total conductance of the cell.
And we said that the lead conductance
is somewhere around 20 nS.
And so, if we want the voltage-gated
sodium conductance
to make a considerable impact upon
membrane potential
the total voltage-gated sodium conductance
also needs to be somewhere around 20 nS.
The single channel conductance
is around 20 pS.
This is 10 to the minus 9,
this is 10 to the minus 12,
there's a factor of 1,000.
So, something like 1,000 sodium channels
are needed in order to make
a substantial impact upon the
membrane potential of a cell.
And, indeed, most neurons have
high concentrations of voltage-gated
sodium and potassium channels,
so that exactly this,
they can change the membrane potential
rapidly in a voltage-dependent manner
in order to perform
non-linear computations.
Let's see what happens if we open
a voltage-gated sodium
conductance on a cell.
Let's imagine we have a neuron that has
some leak conductance
and it's largely governed by potassium.
In addition, we can then add a voltage-
gated sodium conductance.
We also have the current/voltage
relationships for the voltage-gated
sodium conductance and
it looks something like this,
with the reversal potential for sodium
somewhere at around +60 mV
and the typical cell is sitting somewhere
around here at -70 mV,
a time where the current flux through the
voltage-gated sodium
channel is basically is basically zero.
What if we were now to depolarize the cell
a little bit, and we'll take it
a little bit in this direction, we'll take
the membrane potential to -50 mV.
At this stage, there's still very little
current that flows through
the voltage-gated sodium channels,
and they probably wouldn't
contribute very much.
But as we depolarize
just a little bit more
the current flux begins to flow in.
There's a considerable influx
of sodium into the cell
as we open the voltage-
gated sodium channel.
So, we depolarize the membrane
potential a little bit.
That opens a voltage-gated
sodium conductance.
That voltage-gated sodium conductance
leads to an inward current.
That inward current will bring more
positive charge inside the cell
and will cause the membrane potential
to further depolarize.
Depolarizing the membrane potential
further will lead to an even larger
inward current, which in turn,
will depolarize some membrane
potential even more, and so on, we get
into a positive spiral,
where depolarization increases the
voltage-gated sodium conductance
that further increases the charge influx
further depolarizing the cell.
And if we think about membrane potential
with respect to time
we depolarize it a little bit,
and suddenly the voltage-gated
sodium channels begin to participate
and we're in this explosive situation
where membrane potential has this positive
feedback loop that takes us toward
the reversal potential for sodium,
somewhere around +60 mV
depending upon the strength
of the leak conductances.
So, voltage-gated sodium channels give
rise to an explosive sodium conductance
where a small bit of depolarization
will give rise to a positive feedback loop
taking the membrane potential toward a
sodium reversal potential.
Let's now consider voltage-
gated potassium conductance.
The current/voltage relation
has similar features.
We have reversal potential at -90 mV
for the potassium reversal potential.
We have the activation of the
potassium conductance
at around -40 mV.
So it has zero conductance
here, this is the current.
This is the voltage, and then
somewhere around
-40 it begins to conduct,
and we end up with
the linear IV relationship here
with potassium always forming
an outward current, potassium will then
always want to leave a cell,
and will then always make things more
negative inside the cell.
So, in contrast to what we saw with the
potassium conductance,
the sodium conductance, rather,
where we had the positive explosive
feedback here, as we depolarize the cell,
we increase the potassium conductance
but that makes it more negative
on the inside,
and will then be a stabilizing influence.
So if we depolarize the membrane potential
that will certainly lead to an increase
in the potassium conductance
but an increase in the potassium
conductance will, on the other hand
lead to a reduction in the membrane
potential, and so we have a
stabilizing influence of voltage-gated
potassium conductances.
For a given membrane potential, if we
perturb it by depolarizing it a little bit
the activation of voltage-gated potassium
channels will tend to hyper-polarize
the membrane potential and take it
towards the reversal potential
for potassium, around -90 mV.
So, in today's lesson, we've learned
a number of interesting features
about voltage-gated ion channels.
Voltage-gated ion channels have a specific
Voltage-sensing domain, the S4 region
that's highly charged,
and is very sensitive
to the electric field across
the plasma membrane.
At positive potentials, the gate opens
allowing ion channel permeation
and high open probability.
At negative potentials the S4 voltage
sensing domain swings in, the gate
shuts, and open probability is low.
Open probability is therefore
the key feature that's regulated
by the voltage-dependent gating
of ion channels, whereas the single
channel conductance remains unchanged.
The voltage-gating of the sodium channel,
because of its positive reversal potential
leads to an explosive depolarization
once you get into that voltage-gating
activation regime of the sodium channel.
On the other hand, voltage activation
of the potassium channel
acts to stabilize membrane potential,
hyper-polarizing the membrane potential
towards the potassium reversal potential.
It turns out that a dynamic interplay
in terms of the kinetics of the
opening and closing of sodium and
potassium channels
underlies the generation of the
action potential.
And in the next lesson, we're going
to look at the voltage-gating kinetics
of the sodium and potassium channels.