In this video, we're going to make
a lab excursion and we're going to visit
Semihcan Sermet, who is
a Ph.D. student in my laboratory.
He's going to show you how
to make whole-cell recordings
from brain slices.
Hi, my name is Semihcan Sermet.
In this video I will explain
how to make whole-cell recordings
from brain slices.
I will explain the process
in four parts.
First we will prepare the brain slices,
then we image the neurons,
we prepare our recording electrodes,
and finally we perform
whole-cell patch-clamp recordings.
Our first step is preparing
the brain slices.
We first anesthetize the mouse,
carefully extract the brain,
and then place it
in ice-cold slicing solution
containing, in millimolars,
87 sodium chloride,
25 sodium bicarbonate,
25 D-glucose,
2.5 potassium chloride,
1.25 sodium phosphate,
0.5 calcium chloride,
7 magnesium chloride,
and 75 sucrose which is aerated
with 95% oxygen
and 5% carbon dioxide.
This solution is not a normal
artificial cerebrospinal fluid.
It is modified to keep the cells healthy
during the cutting process.
First, we extract the brain
from the mouse and place it
in the ice-cold sucrose-based
slicing solution.
This solutions helps
to keep neurons in a good condition
during the slicing process.
Then we chop off the cerebellum.
Since we will be recording in neocortex,
we do not need that brain region.
Take the brain and carefully
transfer it onto the platform
which will be going
into the slicing chamber.
The brain is fixed
onto the platform with glue.
Then we take the platform
with the brain and place it
into the chamber filled
with cold slicing solution.
The solution is bubbling with 95% oxygen
and 5% carbon dioxide
to keep a balanced pH, which is 7.3.
We slice the brain with the vibrotome.
It has a sharp blade which vibrates
at 85 Hertz and advances with a speed
of 0.09 millimeters per second.
Slices are 300 micrometers thick.
When the blade reaches
the end of the brain tissue,
we gently push the slice towards the blade
and separate it from the rest of the brain.
Then we take the brain slice
with the Pasteur pipette
and transfer it to a chamber
filled with 35┬░ Celsius
warm sucrose slicing solution.
We keep the slices here about 30 minutes.
During the slicing, the vibrating blade
damages cells in the superficial parts
of the slices, the parts
next to the blade.
In the warm sucrose slicing solution,
the damaged cells tend to float
away from the slice, leaving
healthy tissue behind.
We keep the slices incubated
at 35┬░ Celsius
for 30 minutes in slicing solution,
and then we transfer them
to the room-temperature artificial
cerebrospinal fluid,
containing, in millimolars,
125 sodium chloride,
25 sodium bicarbonate,
25 D-glucose,
2.5 potassium chloride,
1.25 sodium phosphate,
2 calcium chloride
and one magnesium chloride,
which is aerated with 95% oxygen
and 5% carbon dioxide.
Then we select the slice
and place it in the microscope,
superfused with artificial
cerebrospinal fluid at 35 Celsius.
We take our brain slice
from the chamber filled with ACSF,
bubbling with carbogen,
and place it into the recording chamber.
The chamber is superfused with ACSF.
Then we fix the brain slice with the grid
and then start visualizing
with the microscope.
First we look at the lower magnification,
4X, to see the brain region
we would like to record from.
Then we switch to the
higher magnification,
60X, to visualize the cells.
In this case, we use a high-contrast
infrared video microscopy.
It is important to find a region
with healthy cells.
In order to do that, we look
at the slice while
focusing up and down,
until we find a good cell to record.
Now we prepare our patch-clamp
recording electrodes.
We take a borosilicate glass capillary
and place it into a pipette puller.
The electric element covers
the middle of the pipette
and delivers heat to melt the glass.
The pipette is fixed at both ends
and force is applied to pull the electrode.
With enough heat,
the middle of the pipette
begins to melt and the pulling force
causes lengthening and thinning
of the glass capillary.
After several rounds of heating
and pulling, we obtain pipettes
with a tip size of approximately
one micrometer.
Before we start the whole-cell recording,
we fill our glass pipette
with the intracellular solution,
which contains, in millimolars,
135 potassium gluconate,
four potassium chloride,
four magnesium ATP,
ten sodium phosphocreatine,
0.3 sodium GTP and ten HEPES,
which has a pH of 7.3
and osmolarity
of 280 milliosmol per liter.
We also add Alexa-594, a red fluorophore
for further imaging.
In order to have a better understanding
of the whole-cell recording process,
we can first look
at these schematic examples.
First, before putting
our pipette into the bath
and the tissue, we apply
positive pressure in our pipette
so the intracellular solution,
shown as blue, can flow out
and then the tip stays clean.
We apply a test voltage
and observe the current flow
through the pipette.
Then when we touch the cell,
we remove the pressure
and suck gently.
Then a membrane attaches
to the pipette tip
and then forms a tight electrical seal.
At this time, only a very small amount
of current passes through the pipette tip.
This is now a so-called cell-attached
patch-clamp configuration.
Then, we do further
brief suction pulses
to break the membrane
in order to establish
the whole-cell patch-clamp configuration.
Then we break the membrane
and we see a current flow like this
charging the membrane
because of the cell capacitance.
We fill our glass pipette
with internal solution
and place it on the head stage,
which has the silver chloride
recording electrode on it.
The reason for the internal solution
looking purple is that
it contains a red fluorophore called
Alexa-594 to allow fluorescence imaging.
Before we move the pipette
into the ACSF bath solution
we apply positive pressure on it
to keep the tip clean
by always having
an outward flow of solution.
First we find our pipette
under low magnification
and then we switch
to the higher magnification
which we were using
to visualize the cells.
It is important to move the pipette
around with great care,
making sure not to damage
the brain slice.
We bring the pipette down
towards the brain slice,
near to the location of the neuron
we would like to record.
When the pipette touches
the brain slice surface,
we can see the tissue
getting pushed away from the tip.
That is because of the positive pressure
around 15 millibars
we apply to the inside of the pipette,
causing an outward flow
from the pipette tip.
Then we reach our cell step by step.
First we focus deeper
and then we go down with our pipette.
When we reach the cell,
we touch the cell carefully
and move the pipette slightly
towards the cell body.
Now we see a small dimple
where the tip of the pipette
touches the cell body.
Then we remove
the pressure and suck gently
to establish a gigaseal.
When we have a gigaseal, we do
further brief suction pulses
to break the membrane
in order to establish
the whole-cell patch-clamp configuration.
Sometimes we have to continue
the suction pulses
to improve the opening,
reducing the access resistance
between the electrode
and the inside of the cell.
Then we switch to the current clamp mode
to measure the membrane potential.
We can then start injecting
current into the cell.
Here we apply currents
for 500 milliseconds.
First we apply hyperpolarizing current,
then we increase the current
and depolarize the cell
and see action potentials.
The more we increase the current,
the more action potentials we see.
In this case, we are recording
from a neocortical layer V pyramidal cell.
We can zoom in and look
at the action potential waveform.
We can see that action potential
half-width in this cell
is around two milliseconds.
Here on the left we see
the two-photon microscope image
of the cell we were recording from.
On the right, we see
the membrane potential traces
of the same cell responding
to the injected currents.
In the bottom trace, which is here,
we see that the cell hyperpolarizes
and in the top trace,
we can see here,
the cell depolarizes
and fires action potentials.
So we've seen that the mammalian brain
can be cut into thin slices
and the neurons remain viable.
We can visualize the neurons
through high-contrast
infrared video microscopy,
allowing in vitro whole-cell patch-clamp
recordings of membrane potential.