In this episode, we will discuss
a second contol structure, namely
the iteration statements
So, what is the use of this new
control structure?
Let's imagine, for example, that we wish
to print the square
of the five first integers. Namely,
we wish to print
"0 squared is 0", "1 squared is 1",
"2 squared is 4" and so on,
until "4 squared is 16".
Naturally, we could use five printing
instructions.
However, in such a case, we can
- we must! -
use an iteration, also known as
a "for loop".
Such a code will result in the desired
printing by
looping, iterating, on a single printing
instruction.
Now, let us probe this code for the
hows and whys.
An iteration, also known as
a "for loop",
simpy begins with the keyword
"for".
Then comes the declaration and
intialization
of a variable. This variable will control
how many
times we loop.
This declaration and intialization is only
executed once before entering the loop.
Then comes something you're already
familiar with, for it is
a condition. You encountered conditions
during the lesson about
conditional branches.
This condition will be tested before entering
the loop.
If it is true, we will keep on
executing the loop. If it is false,
we will exit the loop.
Then comes an increment statement.
In our example it is "++i".
Please be reminded the increment operator
"++",
used on a variable i, is strictly equivalent
to the instruction " i = i +1".
That means we add 1 to the variable i.
This increment statement will have
the variable i
evolve, thus controlling the number
of iterations.
It is executed once at the end
of every iteration.
The declaration and initialization of the
controlling variable,
the condition and the increment statement
are written in parentheses and are
separated
by semicolons. Then comes
the block of instructions;
it is the loop's body and contains
the instructions repeated at
every iteration.
Similarly to the conditional statement "if",
the braces are mandatory only
when several instructions are to be repeated,
namely, when the loop's body contains
several instructions.
Therefore, if we only wish to have
instruction repeated -as we do here-
we can discared the braces
here and here.
However,
even in such a case, we strongly advice
to use braces. Namely,
adding an oepning brace here, before
the instruction,
and a closing brace here, after the
instruction.
Now, let us detail step by step
the execution
of our first "for loop" example.
First of all, the loop
declares a variable i and
initializes it
to the value 0.
Then, we test the condition. Here, the
condition is "i strictly less than 5".
The condition is true. Indeed,
i is 0 and
0 is strictly less than 5. Therefore,
we can enter the loop's body.
Entering the loop's body means executing
this instruction here. In our example,
it is the only instruction within the loop's body.
This instruction will print "the square of"
following by i's value, which is 0,
followed by "vaut" (= "is"/"has value"), followed by the
value of the expresion
i*i, which is simply 0.
Then, we reach the end of the loop's
body.
So we jump back to this line,
more precisely to the increment
statement ++i.
We will add 1 to i's value :
i is now 1.
Now, we test the condition
"i strictly less than 5", which is
still true and we can thus enter the loop.
Entering the loop means
repeating this
printing instruction : "the square of",
then i, which is now 1,
then "vaut" and, finally, the value
of the expression i*i, which
is obviously 1.
Now we reach
the increment statement again:
i will go
from 1 to 2 and so on until
i has the value 4 and we execute
the increment statement, rising
i's value to 5.
We will test the condition
"i strictly less than 5".
This time,
the condition is false, for
5 is not strictly less than 5.
Since the condition is false,
we will exit the loop.
That means we will resume
right after the loop
and execute these instructions.
By the way, the variable i, declared
here does not exist anymore.
Therefore, we cannot use it anymore.
i does only exist within the loop.
Let us review, the "for loop"'s
syntax.
First of all, the keyword "for".
then, in parentheses, the declaration
and initialization of
a variable -its type is not necessarly int,
by the way.
Then the condition which should,
a priori, relate
to this variable, though it is not
mandatory.
Then an increment statement, which
should relate to the variable aswell.
Finally comes the block of instructions,
constituting the instructions repeated
by the loop.
Please remember that the three
elements inside the parentheses of
the
"for loop" are separated by semicolons but
that there is no semicolon here.
The loop repeats the instructions inside
the block as long as the
condition is true.
If the conditions does not even
become false,  these instructions
will be repeated indefinitely.
Let us move on to another example
a "for loop."
Let us suppose that I wish to print
the multiplication table of 5.
Without using a "for loop", I would have
to repeat almost the same
instruction ten times.
Namely this instruction, printing
"5 times 1 is 5*1",
followed by "5 times 2 is 5*2",
and so on until "5 times 10
is 5*10".
Again, in such a case, one has
to use a
"for loop". The loop will be coded as follows.
We will declare the variable
controlling
the number of iterations and initialize
it to 1.
Our condition will be "i less or
equal to 10".
By the way, remember that the
operator "less than or equal to" is formulated
by the less-than sign (<) followed
by the equal-to sign (=).
Finally, we will use the increment
statement ++i.
The variable i, will thus take the
values from 1 to 10.
This "for loop" is thus equivalent
to all
the ten printing instructions
and will print the multiplication
table of 5.
The block of instructions of a
"for loop" can contain
any instruction whatsoever, a conditional
statement, for example.
Let us have a quiz regarding
a conditional statement inside
a "for loop".
In your opinion, what will this code print
upon execution?
The correct answer is
the answer A.
Let us explain why.
The loop begins by declaring a variable i
and intializes it to 0.
The condition is "i strictly
less than 5". The increment statement
is ++i. Therefore, i will take
the values from 0 to 4.
The first instruction within the loop's
body
prints i's value: right now,
the value 0.
By the way, we used the instruction
"print" and not "println" which means
that the next printed information
will be printed right after the 0,
right here.
Now we move to the conditional
statement, testing if i modulo 2
is equal to 0.
To calculate i modulo 2, we start
by dividing i by 2.
i is 0.
0 is 0 times 2 plus 0 .
Therefore, i modulo 2 is 0. All this is 0
and the condition is true. We can thus
enter the conditional
statement and execute this here instruction
printing the character "p".
Finally, we move on to the last instruction
in the loop's body,
printing a blank space which we will
represent this way.
Now we reach the end of the loop's body
and jump back here.
i goes from 0 to 1.
We execute the loop's body again,
in other words we resume
with this instruction printing's value,
which is now 1.
We move on to the conditional statement,
testing if i modulo 2 is equal to 0.
To calculate i modulo 2, we divide
i,
that is 1, by 2. i can be written
0 times 2 plus 1.
Therefore i modulo 2 is 1.
We conclude that the condition is
false.
We will thus skip this instruction
and
move on to this instruction,
printing a blank space.
Now we reach the end of the loop's
body and jump back here again.
i goes from 1 to 2.
And we resume inside the
loop's body.
We print the value of i, that is 2.
We move on to the conditional
statement and calculate i modulo 2.
i is 2 and
it so happens that
2 can be written 1 times 2 plus 0.
Therefore, i modulo 2, is equal to 0,
this 0 here.
The condition is thus true.
Thus we enter the conditional
branch,
executing this instruction, printing
the character "p".
We move on to
this instruction, printing a blank
space and so on.
We now see that the end result is
none other than answer A.
This condition with the "modulo" here
can be a bit complicated
to understand for beginners but it
can be interpreted easily.
Actually, it only tests the remainder
of a number's division by 2
In plain words, it means we are testing
if this value - i's value - is even.
This condition is thus equivalent to
"is i even"?