In a previous episode,
we have discussed control structures;
they are
Java instructions making it possible
for data to influence,
choose or repeat, different parts
of the program.
We have seen that these control
structures are closely related
to the block notion.
This block notion will impact
the use of variables. We call this
the "scope of variables",
and this will be the subject
of this episode.
In Java, instructions can be regrouped
in blocks, and this intependently
of any control structure.
To this end, one simply needs to
regroup
the instructions in braces.
For example, here, we have a
block, starting with
an opening brace and ending with a closing
brace. Inside, we have declared a Scanner-type
variable keyb, an int-type variable i
and a double-type variable x. We can use
them, for example, to read the value of i,
the value of x
or to print the value of x, the value of i.
These variables belong to the block where they
have been declared.
You can see that, in Java,
blocks have great
autonomy, meaning that they can
contain their own variables.
Now to a simpler example: we have a
block controlled by an "if" instruction.
The block thus begins here and ends
with the closing brace here. In this
block, we
declare an int-type variable j, which we
can then use inside this block.
Once we have exited the block,
starting from this point,
we cannot use the variable j
anymore, since it belonged to the block.
Variables declared in a block, like this,
are only accessible
within this block, we say that they
are variables local to this block.
We can also declare variables outside
any block, inside the class
we are currently working with.
We call those, variables
global to the class.
In the object-oriented programming course
we will differentiate "instance variables"
from
"class variables". However, this would now
take us a little too far.
One advice we can give you is
to declare
your variables the closest possible
to their utilization.
What does it mean?
Let us take an example.
Let us reuse the previous example with
the block here controlled
by an "if" instruction. Inside it, we use
the variable j and we
suppose that we have no use for the
variable j after this block.
In this case, we will write
the declaration the closest from
its utilization,
namely just when we need it,
just before the first line where we
will use the variable j.
In this same situation where
we need here
a variable j, which is not used
anymore after the block
controlled by the "if" instruction,
if we declared this variable here, before
the block,
it would be valid. However, it would not have
been
in accordance with the principle of declaring
variables the closest to their utilization.
Since this variable j, would have been
declared outside the block, it could
still be used later. The idea is to declare it
as close as possible to the place where we use it.
This notion of a place where we use
a variable
or rather of a place where we can use
the variable,
is what we called the "scope".
The scope of a variable is all the
lines of code
where this variable accessible,
where it can be used.
Let us take an example. We have here a
first "if" instruction,
controlling its own block of instructions.
Then, we have a second "if" instruction
controlling its block of instructions
aswell.
In the higher level block, we will
declare a variable j.
In the deeper block, we will declare a variable
k, which we will use.
The scope of k, that is, all the lines
where k
is defined will be the block of the
second
"if" instruction.
In the meantime, the scope of j, that is
all the lines of code
where j is defined, usable, is this block
here, where j has been defined.
Here, you can see that j and k
have different scopes, indicated by these
two blocks.
A question we could ask is,
what would happen if we had declared
a variable
j inside this block?
In Java, such a thing is not
allowed; it is not valid
to have two variables with the same
name in the same scope.
For example, if we had declared,
in the second
block, a variable j. we would
encounter
a compiler error informing us
that
it is forbidden, that there is name
ambuiguity.
Therefore,
in Java, it is forbidden.
You cannot have, in the same scope.
two different objects with the
same name.
However, it is possible in other
programming languages.
A particular scope case, which you should
definitely be familiar with,
is the scope of variables in iterative loops,
"for" loops.
Let us take an example. We have here
a "for" loop,
declaring an int-type variable i. This variable
can of course be
used inside the block. the scope
of i will indeed
be the block controlled by the "for"
instruction, including the
condition and the increment statement.
However, this variable i
will be local to the "for" loop, to the
iterative loop.
After the end of the block controlled by
the "for" instruction, we won't be
allowed to use
this variablle; it is local to the "for"
iteration.