Today we will consider together
un important block
of this programming course:
Object-oriented programming or OOP.
OOP is a programming paradigm
or a certain style of programming
that is used in several programming
languages besides C++
and will give a certain number
of useful proprieties to
your programs
in terms of maintenance and modularity.
At this stage of the course,
you should know
the basic fundamental aspects
of programming.
For example, you know how to
express treatments
using control structures,
such as conditional loops.
You also know how to structure data
using arrays for example,
and, most importantly, you know
how to modularize your programs
using the central notion
of functions.
These basic tools
allow you to code in a
a certain style of programming
called procedural or imperative
programming.
This paradigm has the singularity that
data and functions
appear separately
in a program
Of course, the two interact,
the functions work
on the data,
which influence in turn the execution of functions.
But the two entities appear
separately.
For example, as we will see
in a few minutes,
in a concrete example,
processes can be
represented by functions.
Data and functions can be linked
by the passing of arguments.
Data are manipulated via distinct entities,
such as variables.
One of the fundamental particularities
of OOP
is the possibility to bundle
together functions and data
into one same unit.
Let's consider a concrete example.
Imagine that we would
like to write
a simple C++ program that
calculates the area of a rectangle.
The rectangle is defined by
its width and height.
And so I want to calculate
the surface.
In procedural programming, I would likely
proceed in this manner:
I start by declaring a variable "largeur"
(TN: "largeur" means "width")
that represents the width of the rectangle,
and that I would initialize
at a certain value.
I would do the same for the height.
Next, the area would be
calculated by
passing the width and height
as parameters to a function "surface"
(TN: "surface" means "area") that
would do the appropriate calculation.
So we can see clearly in this example,
that in such a program,
the data and the functions
appear separated.
The variables allow me to
modelize and stock
the data that will be needed.
And the data is processed
with functions.
The data and the functions
are not directly linked.
In this case they are only linked by
the passing of arguments.
So one important objection
that we could make,
concerning this kind of program,
is the lack of a semantic link
between the two entities.
For example, the semantic link
between the width and height.
The fact that we are manipulating the with and height
of a rectangle
is hard to determine.
For example, imagine
that I am not francophone.
So for me, the names "largeur" and "hauteur"
do not tell me anything.
And so it is hard for me to see
that the two names
are linked to the same concept :
a rectangle.
The semantic link that connects the
data in this case,
is not clear.
It's the same for linking the data
and the functions
that go together.
Imagine that you are a bit careless
when you choose the identifiers.
And that, for example, you call this function
"produit" (TN: "produit" means "product").
And that for the arguments,
you give them even less
explicit names.
As a result, it is difficult for
for anyone else who reads the code
to see that, in fact, we are calculating
the area of a rectangle.
However, the link does exist conceptually.
In this case you are indeed
manipulating
the width and height
of a rectangle.
And it is indeed the
area of a rectangle
that you are calculating.
So the fact of consolidating into
one unit, a rectangle,
the characteristics of the rectangle,
such as its width and height ,
as well as the functions
associated with it,
will allow me to establish
an explicit link between these
different entities,
and result in a much more structured
comprehensible program
This one of the fundamental
aspects of OOP.
What you should know
is that OOP enables a set of
new functionalities,
globally giving more
robustness,
modularity,
and readability to your programs.
All this allows for a better
maintainability
and robustness with regard to modifying
the program.
If one day your program needs to be
reused, we would not want to have
to rewrite the whole code
for example because of errors in the
manipulation of data.
Indeed, today most applications
are never developed from zero,
but consist of adding onto or
maintaining existing code.
And it is important to be able
to do this at the lowest cost.
We will see that the fundamental
proprieties of OOP,
that is, more robustness,
modularity, and readability
go exactly in this direction.
OOP offers,
in fact, four principal concepts:
encapsulation, abstraction,
inheritance, and polymorphism
that allow for better
organisation of programs
in regards to robustness,
readability,
modularity, and maintainability,
as I mentioned before.
These central concepts are not exclusive
to one programming language,
but are central concepts of object-
oriented languages in general.
In this episode,
we will
consider defining
encapsulation and abstraction.
We will examine in
the next episodes,
the fundamental notions of
inheritance and polymorphism.
Let's start with the concept of
encapsulation.
Encapsulation is consolidating
into one unit
the data and the functions that
that work on the data.
Typically, as in the example
of the rectangle,
we will regroup into one
unique entity,
the width and height that characterize
the virtual rectangle
and the function that
calculates its area.
In jargon, we will speak of
the data as member variables,
or data members
and the functions as
methods (a.k.a. "member functions").
So in OOP,
we will be able to define new
data types,
with,
as we will see later on,
the concept of classes,
These data types can be
used to work with data
whose types are more
abstract,
such as the type rectangle.
These data will be objects that will
cohabit and interact in
the program.
An object-oriented program
will typically work with
objects that are characterized by
their members:
their member variables and methods.
Let's examine now
the concept of abstraction.
Let's say I want to write
a program that manipulates
several rectangles instead
of just one.
In a procedural approach,
I would typically have to declare
as many widths and heights
as I have rectangles.
Which I do here for the first rectangle.
And I would have to do
exactly the same thing
for the second rectangle.
This is rather tedious!
If I would like to now calculate the
area of these two rectangles,
I would have to call
the function "surface"
and provide, as parameters,
the width and the height
of each of the rectangles
I call the function "surface"
("surface" means "area")
passing each time the correct arguments.
So you have to be careful,
as this can be a source of error.
Imagine for example,
that I enter the arguments wrongly.
If instead of passing as argument
for the first call of "surface"
"hauteur1", I enter "hauteur2",
("hauteur" means "height")
My data aren't coherent,
I am not working with the
same rectangle anymore.
The encapsulation process
results in that
I manipulate higher-level
data,
the notion of rectangle,
to which I associate a
generic description.
In our case, any rectangle can be
described by its width and height
which can be linked to
a same calculation of the area.
As a result, I can work with the
more abstract notion of a rectangle,
instead of working at an
intimate scale
on the representation of rectangles,
which allows us to concentrate
the essential aspects
and hide the details.
Encapsulation allows you to consolidate
into one same entity,
the data,
such as the width and height,
and the functions,
such as the calculation of the area.
It is  the tool that allows me having a more abstract vision
of the data that I manipulate.
As a result,  I will be able to
work with
more abstract entities,
a first rectangle,
and a second rectangle,
both of them are of type Rectangle.
And I will invoke calculations of area on
these rectangles.
We will see that in object-oriented,
I anticipate a little,
I calculate here the area of the
first rectangle.
Later on we will see all this
in more detail.
As a result, my program will focus on
the important elements.
Therefore I am no longer
preoccupied with the fact
that a rectangle has
a width and a height,
but I can concentrate on
the essential aspects:
the fact of working with a rectangle,
and calculating the area of this rectangle.
So when I use a rectangle,
I can only see
what we call in object-oriented
jargon,
its user interface.
That is to say, the functions
that can be used to
manipulate the rectangle, like in
our case, the calculation of the area.
Let us compare this
with an everyday situation.
When you drive your car,
you normally only need to know
the user interface.
You need to know the
steering wheel, the throttle,
the brake pedal,
but you never need to know
how the motor was built.
To drive your car,
you only need to know the
user interface.
This applies to OOP as well.
To use a new type of object,
a new class,
you only need to know
the user interface,
that is provided by
the programmer of the class.
The rest is internal
implementation details
that you do not need to know.
So you can look at the object
from 2 perspectives:
from an external level,
which is useful for the programmer-user,
which uses the notion of rectangle.
From now in a program the type Rectangle exists.
I can declare variables of type Rectangle,
initialize them appropriately.
Next, the elements which interests me
as a programmer-user,
are the useful functions that come
with the class: the calculation of area.
So this external view is the perspective
that interests the programmer-user,
the programmer who uses the
type Rectangle.
The second level is the internal level.
The programmer of the new type,
the Rectangle type,
had to deal with all
the details of implementation.
That is, that a rectangle
has a length and width.
He had to define explicitly
how the area is calculated.
This constitutes the
implementation
at an internal level,
which not necessarily useful
to the user who manipulates
the rectangle.
So in object-oriented programming,
we do not only have the possibility
to regroup
into one same entity the
data and functions,
but we can also define
levels of visibility.
The person who programs
the new type Rectangle,
specifically a class Rectangle,
will be able to say :
" This implementation
will not be accessible to
external users."
and "This is a function that we want to
provide for the external user
and therefore will be accessible
to this user."
Everything accessible to the user and,
therefore, visible
constitutes what is called
the user interface
of the class of the type in question.
Here, in our class Rectangle,
for the new type Rectangle
we have defined
as user interface
the calculation of the surface.
The rest constitutes the
implementation details
that are not accessible to the programmer
who uses the type rectangle.
And we have here an important key
to achieving a more robust program
when faced with the difficulties
of changes made to the program.
Usually, when you change car
even if the motor technology is different,
the interface is more or less the same.
You will still be able to drive,
even if the internal details of
implementation of your car
have changed.
So you only see your car as an abstract object.
You only see that
which you use to drive,
namely, the steering wheel,
the throttle, the brake peddle.
In summary, encapsulation, is consolidating
into one same entity
the data and functions that
characterize it.
And it is also concealing the
implementation details.
The user interface
that we define using
the encapsulation tool,
is what allows me to
end up with
an abstraction, or a abstract
vision of the objects.
As an external user,
only see them as objects that
I can manipulate
through the user interface.
So concretely the class programmer
will decide on the existence of a new type,
and will have to address
the implementation details.
He will have to decide what is visible
to the outside world,
what can and cannot
be used.
The class user,
on his side, uses
the new data type.
But he will have to use it
through the interface.
That is to say, the visible methods
in most cases.
He will not have access to the
internal details.
The user interface is typically,
that which will enable
a link to be established between
the program developer and the user.
And in a very specific way
this interface will be able to
be completely described by the signatures
of the methods available to the
user.
So one of the principal advantages
of OOP
is the better visibility and coherence
of the program.
You have here
two programs that do roughly
the same task,
calculating the area of a rectangle
with a width of 3 and a height of 4.
We are anticipating on
the next episodes.
Namely that we can initialize the
width and height of a rectangle
with this syntax.
But it is more to give you
an idea of
what the program will be
in terms of readability.
If we compare the two approaches,
we realize that here
we are working
with very low-level data.
Here we are working with a rectangle,
which is much more informative,
regarding the purpose of the program.
By reading this program, we know
right away
that we are working with a rectangle.
Here the link between the
data and the functions
is only through the passing
of arguments.
Which is indirect.
Whereas here, the link is
more explicit.
We invoke the calculation of area
on a given rectangle.
Moreover, because in
OOP,
we can only manipulate an object
through methods of the
user interface.
Which gives a framework for
utilization
that is much more rigorous.
For example here, as we saw
earlier,
nothing obligates me in this approach,
to have coherent values,
for the width and height,
the width and height
of the same rectangle.
Here, this error is not possible,
because we are manipulating
a precise rectangle
and thus the associated values
are necessarily coherent.
In addition, because the user is
constrained to use the interface
to manipulate the object,
he is not concerned by modifications
made to the internal implementations.
As mentioned earlier,
if we decide
to modelize a rectangle
not as an object with 2 member variables
of type double, "hauteur" and "largeur",
but  rather as an object  were the relevant
data is stored in an array
with two elements,
the dimensions of the rectangle.
So, if the program developer
of the class Rectangle,
did his job well,
and adapted consequently
the method calculating
the area.
The person who uses the area
calculation will not be effected.
We see in this small example
the advantage of separating
the internal level from the external level.
This results in a more rigorous
framework for using the program.
And any modification to the internal structure
cannot be noticed externally.
So one of the fundamental rules,
that we saw already in the introduction,
the member variables, because
decisions need to be taken
as to their modelling, as well
as  technical decisions,
and implementation decisions,
are considered implementation details
systematically in all
good object-oriented programs.
To summarize, when we define
a new object type
with a class,
we will need to define the member
variables characteristic to the class
as well as its
own specific methods,
and we will
have to define concretely,
what is visible : the user interface,
and what is not : the implementation details.
Therefore once we have decided
what we have to hide,
we end up with the representation
of the object for the external user
that is essentially the user interface.
So the external user's view
will only be
an abstract vision
that is materialized in
the user interface.
The only thing I see of the rectangle
is its calculation of area.
And if I want to follow the rules of
object-oriented programming,
I will consider that the member variables
are also implementation details.
So the interface will be limited
to a number of selected methods.
The external user's vision
of the object will be
restricted to this user interface.
What to remember from today's episode:
abstraction results in
what is called a class,
which allows me to
define a category of objects.
A class will define a new type in a program.
I now have the type Rectangle
that I can manipulate
in a program.
I can declare
variables of this type,
which are actual realizations of this
type. So the declaration of a variable
of this type,
is what is called in object-oriented
jargon, an object.
It is generally manipulated
with a variable.
Note that the term instance is
also used to designate an object.
To summarize and illustrate these remarks
the person who writes the
class Rectangle
conceptually creates a new type.
He will do this of course
by writing a program
that contains the code
of the class Rectangle.
The user of this class
will use the new type,
by declaring variables
of type Rectangle
that will only come into real existence
at the execution of the program.
So the moment the new objects
of this type are created,
we will be able to start working
with these objects in the program.
And the user will work with
specific realizations
of objects of class Rectangle.
We've come to the
end of this presentation
of two fundamental aspects
of object-oriented programming :
encapsulation and abstraction.
You will, in the next episodes,
start to put in practice
these concepts in C++.