In the last episode,
we considered the fundamental
aspects of object-oriented programming (OOP).
In this episode,
we will start to code
all this in C++.
We saw that  OOP defines the concept of class
which is the result of the process
of abstraction and encapsulation
as we saw in the example of
the definition of the Rectangle class,
which had the data members
"largeur" and "hauteur" (TN: means "width" and "height")
and had a "surface" method  to calculate
its area (TN: "surface" means "area").
A class, in the programming jargon,
defines a new type that allows for the
creation of variables of this type,
for example three variables
rect1, rect2, rect3,
that are called in object-oriented jargon,
"instances" or "objects".
So how do you code this in C++ ?
A class in C++ is declared with
the keyword "class".
For instance, to declare
the class "Rectangle",
we will write "class Rectangle"
which defines the name of a new type
then, we will include the data members
and methods (also called "member functions")
as we will specify later on.
All this is closed with a semicolon.
Do not forget this semicolon!
This is a frequent error
when writing the first few classes.
This declaration defines a new type, called
"Rectangle", that we can now make use of
to declare variables,
as we would do
with any other type,
with first the name of the type, followed by
the name of the variable,
As an illustration, to declare an instance,
a variable "rect1" of the Rectangle class,
we use the type Rectangle
followed by the variable name rect1.
For now, our program looks like this.
We start by declaring the new type:
class Rectangle
for the time being, we don't have a
class body;
and we don't forget to end with
a semicolon.
Next in our main,
we declare the variable
"rect1" of type Rectangle.
So how do we complete
the class body?
What data members and member functions
do we need for this class ?
Let's start with the data members,.
The properties of a Rectangle
are its width and its height.
To declare these as data members,
as for the fields of an usual data structure,
simply declare the different data members
with the type and the name of the variable
For each variable we declare the
variable's type and name
followed by a semicolon.
In the Rectangle class example,  this leads to
"double hauteur; double largeur"
(TN: "hauteur" means "height" and "largeur", "width")
it's as simple as that,
as simple as for standard data structures!
And it's the same for using
the data members of an instance,
with the same syntax as for a data structure.
So we have the name of the instance
followed by a period and the
name of the data member that
we want to use.
For example, to use the
height of the "rect1 Rectangle",
we write "rect1.hauteur",
which leads us to the following whole program.
Here I have included the library "iostream"
because I use input and output streams
specifically displaying with
cout and endl.
Next, the usual
"using namespace std;"
Then comes the declaration of
the Rectangle class
that ends with -- don't forget-- a
semicolon.
Next, the two data members:
height and width.
Then here in the main, we
declare an instance "rect1"
of the Rectangle class
and now we can initialize
the height of rect1 at 3.0,
and the width, also of rect1, at 4.0,
and finally print
the height of rect1 on the screen.
All this is very much alike to
the standard data structures presented
in our previous course:
Introduction to Programming.
Note that the code given here does
not compiled as is.
You still require a litlle detail
that will be explained
in the next video.
But apart from that detail, the rest is by large correct.
Let's examine now the
declaration of methods.
Methods are simple functions
that are embedded in a class.
In the case of the Rectangle class,
we will
add the method "surface".
(TN: "surface" means "area")
A method is declared just
like a function
with the return type,
the name of the method,
then in parentheses,
possibly a list of parameters;
all this is the method header,
followed by the actual definition
of the method: the method body
within braces.
The only difference
is that the methods are declared
inside the class itself.
In our example of the Rectangle class,
the method "surface" is
included here in the class
with, its return type -- double because
this method shall return a double --, its name,
no need for parameters here,
and returns the product of the
height and the width.
We could ask ourselves
"Don't we need parameters?"
Indeed, if we had written it
as an ordinary function,
--not a method but a function in the usual sense --
would we have had to pass
the height and width
as arguments to the function
so that their values can
be used in the computation.
So why for this method in
the Rectangle class
don't we need to pass any parameter?
The answer is that
the height and width
are data members
of this class.
Since "surface" is
part of the Rectangle class,
the method has access to
the height and width of the class.
Technically, this is called "class scope",
that is, that all the data
members of a class
are accessible from anywhere in the class
and in particular
from each of its methods.
For example, all the methods of
the Rectangle class
can access the height and length.
Therefore it is unnecessary to pass these
variables as arguments to the methods.
In summary, a method is
simply a function
that is particular to a class,
so is put in the class,
thus has access to the
data members of the class.
This is very important:
do not pass data members ar arguments to
class methods.
This is typically a beginner's mistake.
In our example
we have exactly this,
we have a method "surface"
that does not take any parameters
but can access the rectangle's
height and width
that have been declared in the class.
That being said, it's not because
we don't pass
the data members as arguments to
these methods
that the methods shall not have
any parameter at all.
Of course, if the method
needs certain parameters
from outside the class to
operate,
then parameters would
need to be declared.
For example, suppose that we
have a class "FigureColoree" (TN: means "ColoredShape")
and in this class,
we would have several data members
as well as a method "colorie" that colors
the shape (TN: "colorie" means "to color").
This method should receive a color
[from the outside]
and would modify the color of the instance
of the class FigureColoree.
"Color" is another type
that we would have defined
as another class or with a "typedef".
We could for example declare
a shape, an instance
of the class FigureColoree,
and some red, an instance of
the class Color,
and, jumping ahead a little
on the syntax,
color the shape red.
What I want to illustrate here
is that the color "red" comes
from outside the class FigureColoree
and is not part of the class
FigureColoree.
That's why here we have
to pass it as an argument.
It is not a data member,
so we have to pass it
as parameter to the "colorie" method.
We saw that methods are
a particular form of functions
that are declared in classes
But doing so, frequently
makes the code less easy to read.
For example, we don't have a comprehensive
synthetical view
of all the prototypes of all the methods
offered by a class.
For this reason
-- a better readability --
but also a better modularization,
that is to say a better separation
of the interface
and the implementation,
into two different units,
for all these reasons, it might be
necessary to define
some methods outside of the class.
This does not change
anything of what I said earlier,
but we are simply
organizing the code
a bit differently
by defining the method
outside the class
while keeping its
prototype inside the class.
It changes only one single thing:
if we define the method outside the class
we have to tell the compiler that
it is indeed a method of a certain class,
and not a (usual) function.
Thus the class to which
the method belongs
is indicated in the method definition
in front of the method name:
the class name followed
by what is known as
the "scope resolution operator"
symbolized by a double colon ": :"
For example, in our Rectangle class,
we declared and defined
the method "surface".
If we want to define this method
outside the class, what
we keep in the class Rectangle
is the prototype of the method surface.
The method's definition, outside the class,
will now have the name "surface" preceded by
the class name and ": :".
The definition is exactly the same as before,
but with the method name preceded
by the class name.
Let's consider now another
aspect of methods.
There are actually two kinds of methods:
methods that can modify
valid instances
as we saw earlier
the "colorie" method of the "FigureColoree" class
could modify and change the "color" of an instance.
Such methods are called "non-const methods"
or "non-const member functions".
We distinguish these from methods
that cannot modify their
corresponding instances;
for instance, the method "surface" of the
Rectangle class:
computing the area of a rectangle
does not modify
the rectangle itself.
These methods are called "const methods" or
"const member functions".
For const methods, it is a good
habit to signal these to the compiler
and to other programmers
that will read your code
by adding the keyword "const"
after the parameters list,
at the end of the header,
to say that they cannot modify
instances.
To illustrate, in the Rectangle class,
we would define here
the prototype of the "surface" method
by adding, here at the end,
the keyword "const" which will also be
added on the definition of
the "surface" method,
here, at the end of its header.
We can check, here,
that the "surface" method does not
at all modify
neither the height nor the width.
By using the height and
width,
the method does not modify
the instance.
If you label
a method "const",
that is to say, you mark the method
as a const method, but contrarily,
the method modifies the instance,
which means that in fact it is a non-const method,
then you will get an error message
from the compiler saying
"assignment of data-member"
then the member that you modified
then "in read-only structure".
Here the "read-only" means
it is considered that
through this method
you cannot modify the member cited,
we can only "read", but not modify, "write", it.
So in such a case, there are
two solutions :
either you effectively
made an error
and you have to remove the word const,
or you really wanted the method
to be a const method.
In this case, you made an
error
in the definition of your method.
So, now you know how declare and
define methods of a class
but how do you use there
functionalities?
To do this we will use a syntax
already seen with vectors
and  strings
and almost identical to the
syntax for using data members:
the name of the instance,
followed by the name of the method
and in parentheses potential
arguments
that would be passed to the method.
In the case of vectors,
you wrote "tableau.size()".
Actually, it's because "vector"
is a class and "tableau" is an instance
of this class (TN: "tableau" means "array")
and in this class, we have a method "size".
For instance, to call the "surface" method
of the Rectangle class
on an previously declared instance rect1
of the Rectangle class,
we could write "rect1.surface()".
The usual format is
"name of the instance"."name of the method"
and possibly some arguments.
Here "surface" doesn't have any parameters,
and so we only put
the empty parentheses,
just like when calling a function
that does not have any arguments.
So now,
our program looks like this.
We declare a class "Rectangle",
-- don't forget the
semicolon at the end --
In its body we declare two data members,
representing height and width,
both of type double,
and finally a method
that does not modify
the object that it applies to,
that is called "surface",
that does not have any parameters
that computes the area,
and returns it as a double
defined as the product of
the data members: height*width
Here in main
we declare an instance rect1
of the Rectangle class
We assign the height of this instance the
value 3.0 : "rect1.height = 3.0;"
and the width of the instance
rect1 the value 4.0
and call the area method "surface".
Here the "surface" method does not
take any argument
and applies to rect1, so
it is the area of rect1.
This will print "surface :" and
the value 12 which is 3 times 4.
Note again, as in the
first example,
strictly speaking, this code cannot compile as is,
you still need
a little detail that
will be presented in the next episode.
It's important to understand that
when "rect1.surface()" is called,
"surface" is applied to "rect1"
and takes the height and width of "rect1".
Each instance has its own
set of values for its data member.
If I had declared in the same way
three rectangles, that I
I would assign, for
"rect1" a width 4.0 and a height 3.0,
for "rect2" a width 11.5 and a height 3.8,
and for "rect3" some large values.
Each of these three instances is
a different variable in the memory
and has its own data members,
so when we call "rect1.surface",
it is the general method "surface" of
the Rectangle class
that will be applied to the object "rect1"
and the definition of which, in its body,
will have access to the individual height
and width of "rect1"
And if we call "rect2.surface()",
we will get the area of "rect2"
calculated with its own height and width.
So in brief we can say
that calling "rect1.surface()"
is like calling the "surface" method of the
Rectangle class with, as parameters,
the address of "rect1" which contains
the needed values to do the computation.
So this concludes our
first episode on how to
write real OOP code in C++.
We saw how to declare members :
data members and methods (a.k.a "member functions"),
essentially this axe here,
and we will consider
this other axe
in our next episode.