In the last episode,
we learned how to
code declarations of classes
and instances (a.k.a. "objects") in C++,
as well as
data members and methods.
But we are still not done yet with
this chapter about
"encapsulation and abstraction";
because we have only examined
data members and methods,
this axis of the diagram,
but we still haven't examined how
to separate the visible components,
what is called the "interface",
from the hidden components,
the implementation details.
So we still haven't seen this
axis of the diagram.
This will be the topic of this episode.
As we learned in the video
on the general aspects
of object-oriented programming,
it is not good that all the members of a class
-- its data members and its methods --
are accessible to everyone;
it is much better to limit external access
to only a few well chosen methods.
Concretely, for the class Rectangle
we have decided to limit the interface
to the method "surface" (TN: means "area")
while the "largeur" and "hauteur" data members
(TN: means "width" and "height")
constitute the hidden elements,
its implementation details.
How do we translate
this into C++ code?
To this end, we will use
two keywords called "access specifiers":
"public" and "private".
Let's start with the "private" keyword.
It declares the components that are
"implementation details", and
must be hidden, i.e. "private".
So here, we will declare the
"hauteur" and "largeur" data members
as private variables.
With the keyword "private" followed
by a colon,
all the data members and methods
that follow
are inaccessible
from outside of the class.
This means they are accessible only
from within the corresponding class.
Please note that we can also have
methods in the private section.
Such methods can only be invoked
by instances of the same class,
but not from any other class,
nor from the main().
"Inaccessible from outside the class"
means
that, for example, if in main()
or another class,
we declare an instance "rect"
of the Rectangle class
and we try to access its
height directly with "rect.hauteur"
then we will get an error
message that we are trying to
access "hauteur" which is
a private data member.
The compiler will send a message:
you can't do this:
that component "is private".
By default, if you don't
specify the accessibility of the class members,
so for example, if we haven't
added this keyword,
as we did up to this episode,
by default, every member declared
in this class is private.
Strictly speaking, in this example
because we did not specify
anything for the method "surface"
this method is also private.
That being said, I really encourage you
to systematically
specify the access rights
and explicitly define the private components
with the "private" keyword
and define the components that have to be
accessible from the outside of the class
with the access specifier keyword "public".
So, here, if we want the "surface" method
to be accessible by anyone,
visible from anywhere,
and be part of the interface,
we will add here the keyword "public"
followed by a colon.
Like for "private", everything between
the keywords "public"
and "private" will be in the interface,
and accessible to the public
outside the class.
Concretely, if we take up the last example
where we declared in the main() an
instance rect of the Rectangle class,
we could, in the main(), with a variable
z of type double, declared beforehand,
call the "surface" method
of the Rectangle class,
because this method is public,
and accessible from anywhere,
especially in the main().
If, in contrast, we had omitted
the word "public" here,
by default, the access
would have been private
and could not have been called the
method from in the main().
Its exactly for this reason
why in the last episode,
we said about this example, that its syntax
was not completely correct
because we didn't specify
the access rights,
--everything was private--
so we couldn't have accessed
the data members and methods
from the main function.
Let's now recall some good practice
presented in the earlier episode
about the general principles of OOP.
It's good practice to have as private
all data members
all of the methods that will serve
as internal components
and to have as public
only a few  selected methods,
that constitute the interface.
It is very important to not
have any data member
in the public part.
That being said, you could tell me that,
if all the data members are private,
how will we be able to use them?
For example, if we wanted
to modify the height of my rectangle,
-- this in itself being debatable;
do we really want to change
the height of a rectangle?
but let it be so. --
Or assume that we want to access
the height of the rectangle,
just to know its value.
How can we obtain the values
of the dimensions of the rectangle
if they are private data members,
if we can't access them
outside the class?
I can't do something
like this:
declare a new rectangle and
try to print its height.
This is something that
I cannot do
because the data members were
declared private.
To solve this problem,
we will include in the interface
a few methods necessary to this end
[called setters and getters]
to manipulate the data members
by modifying or consulting them.
So for example a method to
access the "hauteur" data member;
or a method to
modify the width.
For instance, here we
would like a method
that provides the value
of the height
and we would write
something like this:
using a "getHauteur" method.
(TN: means "getHeight").
I would like to insist on
this part of writing a program:
you DON'T have to systematically
include methods
to modify or even to access
the data members of a class,
but you have to decide which
data member can
be modified or accessed
from outside through methods.
The methods that only provide
the value of a data member
are called "accessor methods",
"get methods" or "getters",
while methods that can modify
the value of a data member are
called "mutator methods", "set methods"
or "setters".
Getters are const functions
because they do not modify members,
and so we put the keyword "const"
after the header.
Getters return the value of
the data member,
so if we want to return
the value of "hauteur",
"hauteur" being of type double,
we will return a value of the same type
with "double getHauteur()".
This method being a const function,
we write const here,
and the method body consists
simply of "return hauteur;".
I remind you that methods have access
to the data members of their class,
so here it is indeed the
height of the current instance.
In the same way, we can declare
an accessor method for the width.
Setters or mutator methods
have to modify some data member(s),
by changing their value(s),
and are thus "non-const functions".
For the method to set a
value of an instance's data member,
it has to first receive a value,
passed as argument.
So the method receives
the value to set
but does not return anything,
because its purpose is
to set a value and
not to return anything.
So in the present example, in this method
"setHauteur" (TN: means "setHeight"),
value of the parameter "h" is
copied to the "hauteur" data member,
and likewise in "setLargeur", the value of the parameter
"l" is copied to the "largeur" data member.
Let's examine an entire
example
again with the Rectangle class.
In the public interface, we declare
the method "surface",
we declare an accessor method for the
height, which is a const function,
we declare an accessor for the width, too,
and we declare 2 mutators as
on the last slide,
that take as parameters
respectively the value for the height
and the value for the width.
In the private section of the Rectangle class,
that ends here with a semicolon,
we have two data members:
"hauteur" and "largeur".
So how do we
make use of these elements?
In the main(), we declare
an instance "rect1" of the Rectangle class,
and use the method
"setHauteur"
to set the height of
rect1 to 3.0.
So what happens?
With the instance "rect1",
we invoke "setHauteur"
which will set
the height of rect1
to the value 3.0.
Then we invoke the method "setLargeur"
with the value 4.0
which results in the value 4.0
being placed in the width
of rect1.
I insist that it is indeed rect1
whose width is modified.
Then to print the height of rect1,
we would call "getHauteur"
which will return the height,
the height of rect1 of course,
so it will return 3.0.
My students frequently ask:
"Why do we have to take
all these complicated mesures?
Why don't we simply
declare everything as public so that
all these variables can be accessed
without having
all these getters and setters, and
especially
without having to think about which
methods to put in the interface?"
But if we do this, like for example here
with
a label -- be it a name for the rectangle
or some tool needed internally --
in this case we could
declare an instance rect
of the Rectangle class
and promptly write for example
"rec.hauteur = -36",
therefore setting heights that have
not been checked, that are not valid.
There is absolutely no control over
what another programmer
using this class
can or cannot do
on the representations, instances,
of this class.
On the other hand, if we had
obliged the users of this class
to use set and get methods,
such as setHauteur,
we would have had the possibility
to verify the values received
so as to guaranty the validity
of the values.
So in this case, we could test
the value received,
to see if it is less than or equal
to zero, and if it is,
we would send an error message
(or do whatever appropriate).
While if the value was valid,
we can copy it to the height "hauteur".
This guaranties that
our rectangle always has a height that make sense.
Another reason
setters/getters are important:
here we have access to all the data members,
like this variable "label",
and thus can access to all this
variable's methods,
for example, here the method
"size".
So imagine if you have writen 300 lines
of code like this,
that use this "label" (and its methods),
and that one day, the programmer
of the Rectangle class decides
to change this label; then you
have to throw  your 300 lines of code away,
and write some new.
On the other hand, if you had
limited yourself to using the interface,
which was specified beforehand,
and which shouldn't be changed,
if you use this interface externally,
and the class programmer decides
to change this label data member,
he is the one who will have to recode his class,
while you don't need to change anything because
you only used the interface,
and continue using the
code you had written.
These notions in OOP of [interface] constraints,
of encapsulation,
of abstraction,
of interface restrictions,
make really sense when
writing large programs,
where several people are sharing
the code.
It is actually in this context that
OOP was invented,
developed, and put in place.
OOP is the basis of
good programs that can
evolve, develop, and mature
thanks to their modularity.
So even if you think now that
it is fastidious to do this
for the small programs
seen in the exercises,
think of this practice as the foundation
for more complicated programming
and good programming.
Let's end this episode on
a technical detail
that raises questions from
students,
and that comes from what is
called "name masking"
Masking occurs when an identifier, a name,
"is hidden by" another name.
We saw this in the first course
"Introduction to programming",
with the masking of a variable "i"
by a local variable "i".
Remember that the scope
of the local variable is
the "for" loop,
and so the the scope of this "i",
is the "for" loop,
and so the "i" here is indeed
the "i" of the "for"
that masks the blue "i" that still exists,
but is hidden or masked in the red section,
Here it is certainly the blue "i"
that is masked
in the "for" loop, masked by
this "i".
The same thing happens
when declaring methods,
for example, suppose that we
declared a method "setHauteur"
that receives a value for the height
and so we choose a
name that indicates
that it is the value for the height.
And so we declare
"hauteur" as
the name of the parameter.
How do we then write
the method's body?
We would write "hauteur", the height of the
rectangle is indeed the data member "hauteur",
equals, and here "hauteur" the parameter,
so this height here is what
is received as parameter.
The problem with writing it
this way,
is that the name "hauteur" ambiguously
refers to two different things:
the data member,
as well as the parameter.
Not so great for the compiler that
will scold you with
an error message saying
it doesn't understand what you wrote.
In this case, we can
simply change
the name of the variable,
so as to not have two
identical names anymore,
as we did on a previous slide.
Or we can clarify by specifiying
which "hauteur" we want
with a special feature called
"the pointer this".
The keyword "this" stands for a pointeur that
points to the current instance.
So "this" means we are referring to
the current instance
which roughly means "my address".
For example, for a Rectangle r1,
in a method f of r1,
in such a method, "this" represents
the address of r1.
If we invoked on another
instance r2,
"this", this time, would mean
the address of r2.
So  in a method, "this" points to
the address of the current instance.
For example, we could write this:
"this->hauteur" ("this", arrow, "hauteur")
Let me say, because it is our first
encounter with this symbol
that the syntax "arrow"
like this: "A->B"
simply means  "(*A).B"
(asterisk A, dot B)
If A is a pointer, then *A is
the object pointed to
and we take the field B of the
object pointed to by A.
This is a bit technical, and is
not very important.
Just remember this syntax and that if
we have a pointer "this",
"this->" allows us to access
the methods and data members
of the object pointed to by "this".
Since "this" is "my address",
that means "my data members".
Here this->hauteur, refers indeed
to the height of the current instance,
which allows me to keep the name
"hauteur"
for the parameter.
It is absolutely neccessary
to use the keyword "this"
in the case of masking.
That being said, I reccommend that you
avoid masking
by having different names
for the data members and the
parameters
that would be needed.
To conclude this lesson, let's
summarize what we have learned
about access rights and the scope
of members of a class.
For access rights, there are
2 keywords:
"private" and "public"
that apply to the
lines that follow them,
"private" for what is in
the hidden part of the program,
that is, all the members
accessible only from within the
class itself,
and "public" for the members
that we want to have accessible
from anywhere in the code, in the main()
or in another class.
And, if we declare the data
members x and y here private, they
are accessible anywhere
in the class, particularly in the methods,
so for example, supposing that
we haven't declared any other "y"s,
"y" refers to the current instance.
In contrast, masking
can occur
typically if we declare a variable
like this,
a parameter of a method, which,
because of
the rules of scope resolution
seen before,
will result in
this name resolving to the
nearest scope:
the parameter,
and if we want to access
the data member x here, then
we would have to "unmask"
this name
by adding the pointer "this"
to access x.
That said, I reccommend NOT to use
this way of writing code,
to not use "this" pointer
but to rather make use of different names
to differentiate between the data
members and the parameters of your methods.