In the last episode, you learned
how to write a class in C++.
Now you know how define member
variables (data members) and methods,
and you know how to
implement different
aspects of encapsulation,
such as define what
is publicly accessible
for an outside user of the class,
and what is inaccessible.
In this lesson, we will
examine several examples
to firmly establish these notions.
We will also see that good encapsulation
requires implementing a certain number of measures.
As a reminder, at this stage,
a class is a more "elaborate" structure,
in which you can not only
define certain properties or fields,
called member variables,
but also functions,
that are called methods.
We saw that a class also distinguishes
itself from a structure
by the fact that it can delimit
what is private and inaccessible
to the outside world,
and what is on the contrary
accessible, that is to say public.
Here is the definition of our
favorite class Rectangle,
that served as an introductive illustration
to the fundamental concepts
of OOP.
To define a class, we use
the special keyword "class",
followed by the name
that we chose for our class.
Because this name will be a type
in this program,
it has to be capitalized.
A class is usually caracterised
by a certain number
of data fields that are
also called "data members".
Here we logically chose to
characterize the class Rectangle
by the variables height and width,
(TN: "hauteur" means "height", and "largeur", "width"),
that we chose to define
as two doubles.
A class is also characterized
by a certain number
of specific functionalities
called methods.
So once we have defined
these basic elements,
the data members and methods,
we can now examine which
elements are part of
the internal implementation
and does not need to be
known outside the class,
and those that constitute the user interface,
which the outside world
needs to know and to use
in the class in question.
Here we have made available
to the outside world as functionalities
5 methods that allow
the values of the data members width
and height to be returned
and to be modified, and the
surface area to be calculated with
the values of the width and height.
The components of the
interface are specified
as being "public".
And conversely, the members named
"private" are considered
as implementation details,
and this is usually the
case for data members.
Note that it is
normally not necessary
to systematically define
get/set methods,
for each of the class data fields.
Here we defined them because
at this stage of the course,
we only know how to interact
with the contents of a class,
on a very basic level.
That is why we need setters
to set the appropriate values
of the data members width and height.
Respecting guidelines for
encapsulation
by declaring private that which
pertains to implementation,
typically the
data members of a class,
will give the program designers
of the class Rectangle
the freedom to modify its
implementation
without effecting those
who use the class.
For example, if the
programmer
decides to modify
the class's implementation
by using an array of 2 elements
instead of 2 doubles here, like this,
he only needs to internally adapt
the implementation of these methods,
for instance here, instead of returning
"hauteur" the height,
he returns "dims[0]".
So he only needs to adapt
the implementation of these methods,
for the code to still function
for the user without
any modifications being seen.
Note also that the
external user of the class Rectangle,
can only access the data
fields of the class
through a predetermined interface,
which allows how the data is accessed
to be closely regulated.
Do you know how to improve
this code
for the class Rectangle
with regard to this point?
The code here
corresponds to the class
written by the program designer
of the class Rectangle,
let's see what happens on
the user's side.
The user can be the same person who
coded the class Rectangle,
but not necessarily.
Here is a main program,
that is client
of the class Rectangle, that
was defined on the previous slides.
So the class Rectangle henceforth
defines a new type that can be used
just like any other type
that we've used up to now.
We can declare a variable
of type Rectangle,
that we usually call
an object, or instance,
and start to work with it.
When this line has been
executed,
we now have at disposal
in the memory,
of an object, of type Rectangle,
that has two data fields or data members,
one for the width and one for the height.
So the first rational thing to do,
is to initialize these two
members,
so as to be able to work
with a rectangle with real dimensions.
The initialization of an object,
strictly speaking, is actually an entire topic
that we will soon examine in detail.
For the time being,
let us be content with
assigning values to
the selected data members.
So the assignment of the
width and height,
can be done simply with
input from the keyboard.
We will ask the user to introduce
a value for the height,
a value for the width,
that will be read into a variable "lu"
(TN: = "read")
declared beforehand, and
that will be be set as value for
the data member width of the rectangle
with the set method
that was written for this purpose.
So imagine here that the user
introduces the value 5.0
into the variable "lu", and,
using the method "setHauteur",
along with the dot notation,
which means set the height of
rect at the value of "lu".
So we end up in this situation concretely.
The same applies for the width
like this.
Once the rectangle
is properly initialized,
we can invoke other functionalities
on this rectangle,
in this case,
calculating its area,
and again we use
dot notation
which means here that
I calculate the area of the rectangle.
In conclusion here is
a refined version of the class Rectangle,
based on the externalization
of method definitions.
So here only the method prototypes
are kept in the class rectangle,
while they are effectively defined
outside the class Rectangle.
The link between the method and its class
is made by the scope resolution operator.
The scope resolution operator ( : : )
enables a local name,
for example the name of a method,
to be linked with a more global
name: the name of the class
to which the method belongs.
The advantage of externalizing
is namely that the class declaration is
not cluttered with details
of method definitions.
What is constituted only of
method prototypes and
data members,
is what is called a "class prototype".
And what is constituted of the method
definitions
is called the "class definition".
So exactly like we saw
for functions,
the prototype allows for
agreement between
the program user and the program designer
of the class Rectangle.
The definitions are only
known by the program designer.
The person who uses
the class Rectangle
only needs know the
public section of his prototype.
Note that in a judicious design, we will
be careful to specify as const
the methods that are not mutators,
and do not modify the value
of data members.
Several small details can
be noticed here,
notably that certain programmers
find it useful to use particular
naming conventions especially
for data members,
such as ending the name with
an underscore.
This is to avoid
any possible shadowing
with the names of parameters
in methods.
You will also notice how
the programmer
names the accessors and mutators here.
In the last version of this program,
the method that returned
the height of the rectangle,
was called "getHauteur",
but that here it is simply
called "hauteur".
The same for the width.
Likewise, the method that
can modify the height of the rectangle
by setting a certain value,
was called "setHauteur", but now
is called "hauteur".
Some programmers find
this way of naming
accessors and mutators
more clear, more readable
to use.
For example, here, if in a
program that uses the class Rectangle,
I want to print the height of
a rectangle,
that was declared beforehand,
I only need to write
"rect.hauteur()".
And not "rect.getHauteur()",
which is a bit more bulky.
Likewise, if in a program
I want to modify
the height of a rectangle,
I can simply write: "rect.hauteur(30)"
which is considered
less cumbersome
by some programmers.
Here we are employing the
overloading principle:
giving two different methods
the same name.
The same conditions apply
for
the methods of a class,
as for normal functions.
So there can be no amibguity
concerning which method is called.
The method "hauteur" here
is a mutator that is distinguished
from the method "hauteur"
that is an accessor
by its list of arguments,
which differ from each other,
but also by the presence or absence
of the keyword const.
So  no confusion is possible
here.