A well thought-out user interface of
a class is key to a good design
of an object-oriented program.
Indeed, a poorly-designed interface that
gives the user too much access
to implementation details
can be just as risky as
leaving data members public.
In this episode we will
compare two possible interfaces
for a class.
In the first interface, the
functionalities are too low-level
and reveal to the outside user
the implementation details of the class.
While in the second interface,
only indispensable functionalities
are provided.
We will see, of course, that
the second option
is much better than
the first one.
So we want to program a class
that allows us to play
a game of tic-tac-toe.
As a reminder, it is a game for two
players played on a 3 by 3 grid
with 3 lines and 3 columns.
The first player places Os while
the other player plays Xs.
The two players take turns and
try to
get three of their pieces in a row
either across, diagonally,
or vertically.
In this first version of the class "JeuMorpion",
the programmer has a
minimalist vision of what
functionalities he offers
to the user.
When he designed the class,
he looked at how to model the problem,
and what characterizes a typical
game of tic-tac-toe.
He said to himself that
logically you need a grid.
So he defined a new type Grille (TN: means "Grid")
as an array with a fixed size
to represent the member variable
"grille" (TN: = grid) of the class JeuMorpion.
In the interface, he provides
a method to initialize the grid,
and a method giving the
external user
access to the grid.
So a player who can access this grid
from the outside
could be free to place
his pieces on the grid as he pleases
to implement the game's rules
strictly speaking.
Let's examine more closely the
implementation details
of this first version.
First of all, how does the type "Grille"
model a tic-tac-toe grid?
If we examine this type,
we see that
the programmer made a
particular choice
in order to have an one-dimensional
array.
This means that he probably
sees the grid like this.
So the grid is modeled
by a 1D array of fixed size
where the first 3 places
represent the first line
of the tic-tac-toe grid;
the 3 following positions
represent the 2nd line and
the 3 last represent the last line.
This is one possible choice
even if it is not very natural a priori.
The programmer of the class JeuMorpion
wants to give the user
of this class, access to this grid
so that he can fill out
the grid himself.
So he makes the choice
to model the grid
with a pointer to a grid.
And it is this pointer that is returned
through the method "get_grille".
Concretely, our data member "grille"
is nothing other than a pointer
to an array with a fixed size of 9.
We saw that the primary functionality
of the class JeuMorpion
is the method get_grille
that returned the value of this
pointer to the external user.
And by the bias of this pointer,
it is possible for the user
to access and fill the grid to
implement the game's rules.
So we see that in this design
of the class JeuMorpion, the programmer
entrusts the user with following
the rules of the game
instead of defining them
inside the class JeuMorpion.
This is a very bad decision
and we will discuss it later on.
The second method offered
by the programmer of this class
is the method "initialise"
which simply allocates
memory for a 9-item array.
So someone who wants to use
the class JeuMorpion
could use it in this manner:
To start, he declares
a variable, for example "jeu" (="game"),
of type JeuMorpion.
Then he could
call the method "initialise"
to initialize the grid.
At this point, we would have in the
variable "jeu",
an object with a member variable
that is a pointer, or address
of an array with 9 elements.
To program the game's rules,
it will be for example the user
who will program how the
game is played: with
a player placing one of his
pieces each turn.
So the user
will have to access with this
pointer the grid and place
Os and Xs as needed.
To learn the value of this pointer
giving him access
to the grid, the user
will have to use the
public method "get_grille".
So here, to access the value
of this pointer,
he uses "get_grille" like this.
And we will see how to concretely
use this functionality
to fill the grid using the
functions in this first
version of "JeuMorpion".
Let's now imagine a situation where
a programmer has written
the class "JeuMorpion" with
the functionalities
that we just examined and
that now a user
wants to use it to program
the rules of tic-tac-toe.
Now the user asks himself
"How do I
place a piece, for example
an O, on the grid
in the first box?"
The first thing he would
have to do is adopt
a few conventions on
how to represent the
pieces.
Knowing that the array representing
the grid is an array of integers,
he could choose for instance
that "1" represents an O,
that "2" represents an X,
and that "0" represents
an empty box.
This puts into question
the initialization of the grid.
If we examine the code, the
programmer of the class simply
allocated memory space for the array
representing the grid, but he
never initializes the contents
of each box,
which is still undetermined.
If the user of JeuMorpion decides
to start with an empty grid,
he will have to go through
the grid and fill it with 0s
that represent that the grid's
boxes are all empty.
Here, the initialization of the grid
should have been undertaken
by the programmer,
and not the user.
To place an O in the
first box of the grid,
the user doesn't have any choice
but to go look
at how the class JeuMorpion
is implemented.
He has to know that his variable
"jeu" henceforth contains an
object with a member variable that points
to a 9-element one-dimensional array
and he has to know that placing an
O on the grid
is represented by putting a
"1" in the corresponding position.
He will have
to get the value of this pointer
with "jeu.get_grille".
And so he can access the value referenced by the pointer:
the grid, and more particularly the
box 0 of this grid
where he will put
the value "1".
If he is attentive enough,
the user of "JeuMorpion"
will come up with
a perfectly functional version
of tic-tac-toe.
But he would have had
to deal with several pitfalls and problems
along the way that in principle
he shouldn't have encountered.
One of the fundamental
problems with this first version
of tic-tac-toe is that the user
cannot implement the game
properly without
knowing the class's internal
implementation details.
He has to know under
what form and with what conventions
the representation of the grid is stored,
for example in this case a 1D integer array with
each 3 positions representing
a line.
He will also have to adopt some
arbitrary conventions of his own
such as a "0" representing an empty slot,
a "1" an "O", and
a "2" an "X".
Since these conventions
will probably not be used
by other programmers of this class,
the resulting code
will be hard to understand for others.
In conclusion, to use the class
"JeuMorpion" properly,
the user has to know the
intimate details of how the data is coded
in this class and also
adopt several arbitrary
conventions himself.
Furthermore, the resulting code
of the class "JeuMorpion" will
be completely opaque.
This line is incomprehensible
to anyone who reads it.
What does an "0" mean?
What does a "1" mean?
This line can only be
understood by looking
inside the class "JeuMorpion".
Another thing is that
the user's code
is not robust in the case of
changes made
by the programmer of
the class "JeuMorpion"
to the implementation details.
Suppose that he decides
to switch from a grid represented
by a 1D array to a 2D array.
Well, the user would have to
rewrite this line of code that is now useless.
So the user of "JeuMorpion"
is effected by
any modification made
internally to the class.
He would have to
rewrite this line like this,
if a 2D array is used.
And if he had
written many lines of code
respecting the implementation choices
of the programmer,
he would have to revise everything
he had written.
And finally, an extremely
important point:
with this functionality,
the programmer-user
can access the value of the pointer
which gives him direct access
to the game grid.
This enables, as we will
later see,
numerous manipulations
to be made to this grid
that are undesirable.
So even if the class
programmer of "JeuMorpion"
made the right decision to declare
the data field "grille" private;
which prevents direct
manipulation of the grid
through the data member like this.
However, he allows the value
of the pointer to be accessed freely
with "get_grille" which enables
the exact same manipulation
to be done
but only in a more indirect manner.
This destroys any advantage of
declaring "grille" private,
making the declaration "private"
completely useless
in this case.
More generally, when in a class, a data member
is a pointer to an object,
like this array, offering external
access to the value
of this pointer is adverse
to the goal of encapsulation
because it allows the implementation
details to be accessed.
And this access of the
grid implementation though the pointer
results in many lamentable
consequences.
For example nothing prevents
me to do this:
access a box of the grid
with an invalid index.
The person who uses "get_grille"
can make a mistake in the index,
perhaps not as obvious
as in this case,
but nothing prevents him
to do this kind of manipulation.
At this point, the program
will behave improperly
which can, in some cases,
result in errors like
"segmentation faults" and the
abrupt interruption of the program.
Nor does anything prevent me
to enter unaccounted values
different than 1s and 2s
representing Os and Xs.
We could imagine that
someone using the grid
maliciously or inadvertently
enters unexpected values.
Such as 42, 11 or 3.
This results in a situation
where the game's logic
and rules aren't
respected.
Imagine that
the programmer of the game's rules,
programmed a method
"get_joueur_gagnant" (= "get_winner()")
whose job it is to
go through the grid
and determine if
any Xs or Os are in a row.
If the method is
expecting to find values like
0,1 and 2, and finds 42 instead,
it  will behave incorrectly.
Lastly, imagine that the grid's user
want to cheat,
for example replace
an O with an X
that is already on the grid.
Nothing stops him.
So here we could,
after putting a 1 here,
replace it with a 2
using this kind of command.
There is no control to make
sure not to erase
an existing piece
on the grid.
All these problems proceed from
the fact that the functionalities
offered publicly are
too low of level,
relating too much to the implementation
details which then need to be known.
They offer  too much access
to the data
which can be used
without restriction.
This is obviously a
bad design.
To program a class JeuMorpion
that is correctly encapsulated,
it is crucial that the
implementation choices
are not accessible or visible
through the user interface
that the external programmer
is given.
Furthermore,
the internal implementation decisions
for example, how to
represent the grid and
how to represent the pieces
on the grid;
is the concern of the
programmer of "JeuMorpion",
and not its user.
Now we will study
a superior version of this class.
In this 2nd version
of the class JeuMorpion,
the programmer-designer
has duly chosen
to model all the elements
need to play
a virtual game of tic-tac-toe.
Namely, not only
the grid,
but also the pieces
that will be played.
And to this end, he chose
an enumerated type
to manipulate the pieces
with understandable names.
To model the grid itself,
the programmer made
more logical choices
than in the last version.
He uses an array
with 3 lines and 3 columns,
which is closer
to a real
tic-tac-toe grid.
In the class JeuMorpion,
he doesn't need to access
the grid with a pointer.
So rationally, the data
member is defined
of type "Grille" like this.
And the initialization of
the grid, which was badly and partially
done in the last version,
is thoroughly carried out here.
The class programmer initializes
each element of the grid.
And to do this, he goes
through each line of the grid
and fills each slot of this line
by explicitly putting
"VIDE" (TN: = "empty").
The idea is now to offer
the user
several well-chosen
methods
that allow him to manipulate
the grid without having to
know how it is implemented.
We could imagine that a
method "placer_rond" (TN: = "place O")
whose role it is to place an O
on the game grid
at the intersection of a
line and column given by the user.
Likewise, "placer_croix" places an X
on the line and column that are given.
These methods return a boolean
that indicates
if the O or X was
successfully placed
in the desired location.
We can of course, imagine
other methods
for example, a method
"get_joueur_gagnant" (= "get_winner()")
that evaluates the grid to
see if 3 Os or Xs
are aligned.
Placing a token on the grid
is done with the same
procedure
whether it is an O or an X.
It is therefore logical
to modularize the process
and write a method "placer_coup"
that places
the different pieces
on the game grid.
The two methods "placer_rond"
and "placer_croix" are
sufficient for the user
to place the tokens on the grid.
Consequently, the user doesn't need
to access "placer_coup"
which is an auxiliary method
that helps "placer_croix"
and "placer_rond" in their work but is
not part of the class user interface.
Again, these two methods
"placer_rond" and "placer_croix"
suffice completely for the user
of "JeuMorpion"
to place virtual tokens
on the grid.
On the other hand, "placer_coup" does
not need to be accessed
and can be consider as an
utilitarian method aiding the
aforesaid methods to their work
and does not belong
to the user interface.
Therefore, we will
declare this method
"placer_coup" as private.
So this method
places each move
either an O or an X
on a given line and a given column.
Because this information for the
line and column are given
by the user through
the method "placer_rond"
and "placer_croix",
the line and column have
to be verified
to ensure that the
requested move
corresponds to a valid
line and column.
So the first thing placer_coup does is
to carry out this verification.
If the move is not valid,
the error is signaled
with "return false",
which means that the piece
wasn't placed.
The method placer_coup has to
also verify that the token isn't placed
on a box that is already occupied.
This verification is done
by explicitly testing
the slot to make sure that
it is empty.
If this is not the case,
a error is indicated
by returning "false".
If this is the case,
the token will be placed,
and "true" is returned
to signal that
placer_coup was successfully
called.
You will notice that here it
is not necessary to verify
which symbol is being placed:
an O or an X,
because placer_coup is private
and is only invoked by
placer_rond and placer_croix
that will pass the
right values to be placed.
Let's see how all these
modifications in this new
version of JeuMorpion
effect the user.
So the user of this class
will probably start by
declaring a variable
of type JeuMorpion.
Next, he will use
the public method "initialise"
to initialize the grid's
contents.
Then he will start to
place the different tokens,
on the game grid.
If he wants
to place an O
on line 1, column 1
of the grid,
he would have to use
an expression like this
which is much more
clear and explicit
compared to before.
He simply indicates that he is
placing an O on line 1, column 1.
Especially because this
formula does not neccessitate
prior knowledge of
how the class is implemented.
The user also benefits
from the validation of the move
by the methods
placer_rond and
placer_croix.
And he will be informed with
a boolean returned by these methods
whether or not the move
was made.
Placing an X on the grid
involves the same procedure.
The new version
of the class JeuMorpion
boosts a much more robust and
clear usage.
It frees the user from having
to chose certain conventions
for using the interface methods.
For instance, the user has to
be informed of the convention that
the enumeration of the lines and columns
start with 0 and not 1.
The documentation
of these conventions has to be
given in order to
use the class.
The 2nd version of the class "JeuMorpion"
offers several advantages
compared to the 1st.
The first advantage is
the validation of the user input.
It is henceforth impossible
for the user
to place a
value in the array,
other than one that is expected.
In fact, he doesn't even know how
the values are coded internally.
He doesn't even know
that an enumerated type is used
to represent each of the values.
He has absolutely no idea how things
are implemented.
Another aspect
is that the user
can no longer
fill a box that is already filled.
Which was not the case before.
Here the methods of the interface
are in charge of verifying the move
and will prohibit this from
happening.
Another important advantage:
an implementation like this
allows what is called
"the separation of concerns".
Each programmer is
responsible for his part
and does not have to be
preoccupied with problems
concerning the implementation
of another part.
For example, the person
who uses the class "JeuMorpion"
does not need to know how the
game grid is stored,
nor that it uses integers,
nor which values represent what.
The programmer of the class
JeuMorpion takes care of these details.
And the user only has to
take care of the game's logic.
Another important point:
the readability of this
new code.
The code written by
the user of this class is
even comprehensible anyone.
So here, understanding the expression
"jeu.placer_rond(...)" is
not a problem.
No need for much
explanation
to know how it works.
Again this was not the
case in the previous implementation
where you had to write
a cryptic expression
for a similar command.
The last advantage is that
with the validation of moves,
the user is now informed
of abnormalities in the input
with an understandable message.
So if we place a token
on an invalid slot on the grid,
placer_coup will process the error
and inform the user of the anomaly
and that the piece was not placed.
In the first version,
the program ended with an
unintelligible error "segmentation fault".
We've come to the end of this first case
study on the game of tic-tac-toe.
Which demonstrated the necessity
to encapsulate and hide correctly
the implementation details,
to offer only the functionalities that
are essential to the outside user
and that do not give him
to much control
to alter and modify the implementation
details.