During this third module dedicated
to Bernoulli's principle we will begin
by seeing applications of hydraulics
with free surfaces. We will now see a few
definitions, among other things the notion of head,
of head loss, of specific head,
of steady state. And during the final
module we will see applications to
be able to calculate and make hydraulic calculations
with free surface. To better understand this
notion of head loss, i.e.
the dissipation of energy during the motion,
we can make an analogy with a ball
rolling without slipping  along a
topography in some way of a rollercoaster.
If we assume that there are no losses
of energy by friction, if I release a
particle A with no initial velocity along
a random profile, it will reach
here the point C. So here we have the translation
relatively simple of the principle of conservation
of mechanical energy. This mechanical energy
or total energy is constant, and is equal
to the potential energy + kinetic energy.
When the ball will go down, it will reach
its maximum velocity at point B, which will also
correspond to the point where the potential energy
is minimum in this motion. So of course
it is an idealization of what is happening.
In reality, the ball, due to friction,
will dissipate a part of its energy. So
in practice if you release a particle
on a profile with no initial velocity, it
will roll, slide, and will go a little
less high than the initial position, and so
it will stop here at point C. We will then
have a regular decrease of the total
energy. The height difference here between
the initial point A, which should have been the
final point, and the point C provides information on the
quantity of energy that has been dissipated.
We will see that in hydraulics we will translate
all the energy dissipations in terms
of water height, we will thus see that this
measure of height difference will directly
provide information of the energy dissipation,
that we will call head loss. So to
sum up, the height difference translates
the energy loss, so we always have the
variation of total energy that is equal
to the variation of kinetic energy + the
variation of potential energy. In this
case here the total energy is not conserved
and will be here slightly negative. We
will have a relation that will be identical for
the hydraulics except that the total head
that we will consider will be at the time the gravity
potential, ѱ, the pressure and the kinetic
energy. Hydraulicians are used
to always reason in equivalent energy
of water height, so if I divide this
energy by Ï±g I have something that is
homogeneous to a height. Î”H here that will be
negative will be the head loss. Now,
if I write this head loss translated
in equivalent of water height, I will
have the gravity potential that will correspond
to the height or the position of the riverbed
, the pressure term will correspond
here to the height of my water column, or
the depth of water. We have here a water
motion animated by an average velocity u, I have
here the kinetic energy translated in equivalent
height. As so often we will be interested
in rivers, so in water
flows on distances relatively long,
we will have in general variations of
the bottom elevation that will be relatively
modest compared to the variations of height
or of velocity, so in many applications
this term here will be nearly constant,
what will be varying are h and u. For
this reason we introduce another head
called the specific head, which is
equal to the water height, to the pressure term
and the kinetic energy term converted
into equivalent water height. The sum
of both is called the specific head.
The first application of the notion of specific
head concerns the calculation of the relation
that exists between flow rate and height for a
specific energy or specific head
constant. For that we will use the hypothesis
of steady state : the flow rate per unit
width is constant, and is equal to u/h, so
I will be able to substitute in the definition
of the specific head the velocity by the
ratio q/h. When I do this, I have the following
relation that, for the specific head,
will be equal to h + the term qÂ²/(2ghÂ²). If
I assume that the specific head is constant,
I can easily deduce what q is equal to
as a function of Hð—Œ, and I obtain the following
relation that I can write in dimensionless form
by introducing a dimensionless flow rate,
that will be equal to my flow rate divided by g
the flow rate, by the specific head raised
to the power 3, and I introduce the parameter
xi that will be equal to the water height divided
by the specific head. What we see
is that the dimensionless flow rate is written
as the square root of the following equation. Let's look
at the shape of this function : we have a curve
bell-shaped, but an asymmetric bell,
with here an increasing part that will correspond
if we calculate Froude numbers. to the
Froude numbers greater than
1. We will call this regime the supercritical
regime. The point here Î¾ = 2/3 corresponds
to the maximum flow rate, and also to the Froude
number = 1, and here the decreasing part
will correspond to Froude number that
are smaller than 1. We will speak of subcritical
regime. What is important to note
here is that for a specific energy or
head constant, there exists a flow rate
maximum, so here we cannot exceed
this zone and this maximum flow rate is in fact
linked to the specific head. The second
interesting element to note is that if
we look at what is happening at a given flow rate,
for example here the flow rate = 0.3, I will have
two possible heights, one in the supercritical
regime that will correspond to a small
water height, and another here, in the subcritical
regime, that will correspond to a water
height that will be bigger. The height that
will correspond to the Froude number = 1 will be
called the critical height. What must be
noted is that for any flow rate with a specific
head constant, there exists two possible
heights, one in the supercritical regime
also called torrential regime), and
that this height will end up here, it
will thus be smaller than the critical height. There
exists a second height in the subcritical
regime, also called fluvial
regime, and this height will be greater
than the critical height. The second application
consists in now looking how varies
the specific energy as a function of the height
when we assume that the flow rate is constant.
We fix a flow rate, Q, per unit width,
and we look at how the specific head varies.
For that, as previously, we will introduce
the ratio Î¾ which is the ratio between
the water height and the critical height, and
we also introduce a specific head
dimensionless by dividing the specific head
by the critical height. When we do this
we obtain the relation here which is extremely
simple. We see that when Î¾ is very big
compared to 1, this term that is here becomes very
small. so becomes negligible, so the
specific head behaves as the water
height. Conversely, when Î¾ is very small
compared to 1, this term here is close to zero
and this term here very very big.
Here it means that the specific head
will behave like a function that will be
inversely proportional to the water
height. If I translate this in graphical form,
I find here that a very large number of
Î¾, the specific head, must tend
to the first asymptote, so that corresponds
to H equal to Î¾, and that conversely when
I am at a very small number Î¾, I
must have something that looks like
a parabolic branch, so that must tend
very quickly to infinity. Like previously
what we will be able to do is to distinguish
two regimes. A regime here that corresponds
to the subcritical regime, and here a regime
that will be the supercritical regime, the minimum
here will correspond the transition of the critical
regime, so to the Froude number equal to
1.  This diagram solves problems
extremely simple, for example how
does a water line varies, we will call this a
backwater curve, so how varies the position
of the free surface when we have, at the bottom
of the river, an obstacle.  For example here
a step or a stair tread.
To simplify I will assume that we
are at the upstream at a certain velocity, a certain
height, and that we are in a subcritical regime,
this the Froude number is smaller than
1. I will also suppose that we have a
frame of reference situated here, we thus have a certain
elevation zð–º, than the step's height, of
the step, is equal to p. We also call this
in hydraulics the shovel, it is a term of
old french that designates this height
difference.  As we are in a subcritical regime,
or sub-fluvial, we are situated in this part
here of the curve that links the specific
head as a function of the height. I
will now apply Bernoulli's
principle between point A and the point B. According
to Bernoulli's principle the water height
+ the gravity potential, i.e.
the elevation + the kinetic energy, i.e.
the term here  uÂ²/2g must be constant between
the point A and the point B. We have seen that these
two terms here, the specific charge and
z will vary between the point A and the point B
of a value that will be the value p. If now
I reason in a qualitative way on the diagram
h as a function of Î¾, I am at point A, I am increasing
the height of a value p, so in dimensionless
form this will (p/Hc), so it means
that I must have a decrease of the
specific head here that will be equal to
p/Hc, or in dimensionless form, we will
see that the specific head at point B
it will be the specific head at point A minus
this height difference, i.e.
p. Hence we see qualitatively that in the
subcritical regime, the transition here of a
step by a displacement of point A to point
B will results in a decrease of the
height as we have going from a height
that is here to a height that is here. If
now I reasoned in a torrential regime,
the displacement will be done in this direction here
and it will result in a slight
increase of the height. So typically
if I had a torrential regime I would have
something that takes the shape of the bottom
and that must slightly increase passing
step. We will now address
an important point concerning the equilibrium
conditions of water flows in a
river. To do so we will consider
a volume of water. As we are still reasoning
by unit width, this volume is simply
a rectangle represented here with a certain
length L and a certain height h. This control
volume is subjected to many forces,
so pressure forces, on each side
here, these pressure forces as the height
is constant will counterbalance themselves, we
will thus not take them into account. The volume
is also subjected to is own weight
with a driving component that will simply be
the projection of the weight on the x axis. As we
will have friction during the motion we
assume that we have here a friction force
that is exerted, and this force per units of
area, so the stress at the bottom that we
call wall stress : Ï„ð˜±. is exerted
here. So if I simply write the equilibrium
between the driving force of gravity and
the friction force, I will have PsinÎ¸
that will be equal to Ï±ghLsinÎ¸, p simply being
the density multiplied by the volume,
and I project here by sinÎ¸. This driving
force must be counterbalanced by the friction
forces so here the friction stress
multiplied by the length on which this
friction stress is applied. So
if you simplify here by L you obtain
the following relation : Ï„ð˜± = Ï±ghsinÎ¸
that constitutes the equilibrium condition.
Each time that we will have a river at
equilibrium, the bottom stress will be strictly
equal to Ï±ghsinÎ¸. Now, let's examine
what this equilibrium condition implies
if we examine the conservation Bernoulli's
principle. For that we will consider an
infinitesimal volume of length L =dx and
I will writhe Bernoulli's principle
on a small slice, here between a point
A and a point B. Again, what I must
have is that the gravity potential, i.e.
the bottom elevation + the pressure, i.e.
the water height + the kinetic energy
resulting in water height, i.e. uÂ²/(2g),
this sum must be conserved, if it isn't
that we now suppose an energy dissipation,
so here a head loss Î”H, that
must be negative. So we must have a
decrease of the head between the point A and
the point B, due to friction. If we suppose
that the height here is constant between these
points and that the velocity is constant, all
that we must have is that the elevation of point
A must equal to the elevation of point B
+ this head loss Î”H. As I have an
infinitesimal volume, I will be able to link
by introducing here the slope angle, so
i will be the slope, tangent Î¸. So what
I will have is that the elevation of point A
minus the elevation of point B is equal to idx,
and by using the previous relation
and introducing a friction slope,
so I assume that the head loss dH/dx
is equal to jð˜§, the equilibrium condition
if we use Bernoulli's principle is
that the slope must be equal to the friction
slope. It is a result that we will
use afterwards in the equation of
the backwater curves. We ask the question
now of knowing what is worth this head
loss, for that we will introduce the notion
of friction law, that describes
how the energy is dissipated, in other
words how  does the head loss varies as a function
of the flow variables u and h. So
there exists many formulations, many
empirical forms, in general taken from
experimental data obtained in laboratories.
The best known of these formulations is the
Manning-Strickler formula. This Manning-Strickler formula
for example links the wall
stress, or side stresses, as
function the average velocity uÂ² and as a function
of the water height raised to the power
1/3. There appears thus a friction coefficient
called Manning-Strickler coefficient,
if we refer to what we had
seen in the chapter dedicated to similarities,
what we can show experimentally
and that we can justify theoretically
is that this Manning-Strickler coefficient
is linked to the roughness scale of
the bed, so here a dâ‚‰â‚€, it means that
90% of the grains have a size smaller
than this dâ‚‰â‚€, and so the Manning-
Strickler coefficient is equal to 26/(dâ‚‰â‚€)^(1/6),
with units here that we will specify
afterwards. Now if I use
the equilibrium condition expressed in terms
of stress, we had seen that when the
river, the water flow was in a uniform
steady state, the stress at the bottom
was equal to Ï±ghsinÎ¸. If now
I use Manning-Strickler formula
seen previously, what I must have
when I equalize the two terms, it allows me
to calculate what the velocity is equal to as a function
of the height. Here what we show is that
the average velocity must vary as h^(2/3)
multiplied by the friction coefficient and
weighted by âˆši, i being the channel's slope. When
we solve this equation here we can reason
in terms of height instead than in terms of
velocity and we have in this case the height
in steady state, what we call the normal
height which will be equal to the flow rate per units
of width divided by the Manning-Strickler coefficient
and divided by âˆši, the whole raised to the
power 3/5th. During this third
module we have seen a couple of elementary notions
of hydraulics with free surface, mainly
the notion of specific head, the notion
of head loss and the notion of equilibrium
condition. We will now go
a little further by examining what is happening
in a river, when we are working at
constant flow rate but that the water height
can vary.