This is the last series of episodes
in this MOOC
"Introduction to object-oriented programming
in C++"!
In this last series of episodes,
we wished to present you
a problem in its entirety,
a very general problem,
to make a case study.
It will consist in presenting
different watches:
there will be analog watches,
digital watches, and watches that
will be both;
watches will have accessories such as
bracelets (straps), bodies, etc.
So a rather general frame which
could be used for example
as management software for a
jeweler's or as sales software,
or even for printing catalogs.
Through this, we will illustrate
different concepts presented all
along this course.
The themes we have chosen to
present to you
in these summary episodes
include first of all
the notion of design,
to model the problem from
an object-oriented point of view,
which classes have to inherit from
which other ones,
whether some abstract classes
are needed or not,
how to make the calculation
of the watches' price
polymorphic, or how to make
the output polymorphic.
Output will be treated in a
very specific way,
with an overload of the output operator,
and then we will review how
to implement an output
that adapts to each of the classes,
a polymorphic output.
We also introduced operator overloading
with the += operator,
which will allow us to add
components
to watches that we want to build.
Finaly, we will go over multiple
inheritance
with the different mechanisms,
the digital mechanism
and the analog mechanism,
or even double mechanisms,
which are both digital
and analog
and we will end with a last episode
that will present a problem that
we have not yet covered in the course,
the concept of polymorphic copying,
how to copy heterogeneous collections.
how do we copy watches that contain
different components,
each behaving in a different way
either with regards to the price,
or the output.
This is the menu for this
final week.
But let's start by presenting the problem
in more detail.
We want to model watches,
let's say that watches are products,
in the sense that a product is something
that we can sell, that has a price.
Besides, watches will have basic
mechanisms,
typically hands to display the time,
and will be made of different
accessories,
such as a body, a bracelet,
the glass, the clasp...
The products we discussed earlier
have a price,
and the calculation of this price
can vary
-- this aspect is interesting for
the design --
from a base value which should be
fixed at the level of the product.
All products can be displayed,
and this output can vary;
each product must be displayed
in its own way
Of course, behind these notions of
"can vary"
and "displayed in its own way", we
have the concept of polymorphism.
Then, we have the mechanisms which
we have just discussed,
and the accessories that make
up the watches,
these mechanisms and accessories
are also products.
We have used the
verb "to be" several times,
which refers to inheritance
relationships.
We could for example buy accessories
or mechanisms separately,
so each of these could behave
like a product,
each of these could have its
own price,
and its own way of calculating its price.
Fundamentally, there are
three sorts of mechanisms,
mechanisms we will
refer to as analog,
to represent watches with hands,
digital watches will have a digital mechanism,
and then we will have watches which
will be both analog
and digital.
Finally, for these mechanisms that we
call "double mechanisms",
we will suppose that they display
only one time.
So we can say that there is only one
time associated to a watch here,
and that it will have two ways
of representing it.
This is a point of view
chosen for this exercise,
we could of course have chosen
a different point of view
which would consist in associating a time
to each of the representation mechanisms,
either analog or digital,
but it is not the point of view
that we took here.
This way, we introduce an interesting
problem
when coding these classes.
To summarize, regarding classes,
that is, regarding the types of objects
that we will have in our program,
we will have watches ("Montre"), we will have
products ("Produit"),
mechanisms ("Mecanisme")
and accessories ("Accessoire);
accessories can be bodies ("Boitier")
or bracelets
All of these will be classes.
Regarding mechanisms, we can have
analog mechanisms,
digital mechanisms, or
double mechanisms.
That is the whole set of classes.
Regarding inheritance relationships,
we have seen that watches
are products,
so they will inherit from products.
We have seen that analog, digital and
double mechanisms
are types of mechanisms, so
all three classes here
will inherit from the mechanism
class.
We have also seen that mechanisms
and accessories
are also products.
All of this will lead us to the following
hierarchic model:
right at the top, we have the concept
of a product;
accessories, mechanisms and watches
are products (TN: "montre" means "watch")
However, a watch will have a mechanism
and will have accessories,
so it will encapsulate these classes.
Among the accessories, we have
bodies (TN: "boitier"), bracelets,
clasps, glasses (TN: "fermoir" and "vitre",
resp.), all of these are accessories.
Mechanisms can be analog
or digital, they are both mechanisms.
Finally, a double mechanism is
basically a mechanism,
but we have decided, as we mentioned
earlier,
that it would indicate only one time,
which we will certainly represent at the
level of the concept of a mechanism,
and they will behave both
as analog mechanisms and digital
mechanisms.
So naturally we can say that a
double mechanism
is an analog mechanism
and at the same time is
a digital mechanism,
all the while being just one
-- that was the remark on it having
only one time --
all the while being only one
mechanism
and not two mechanisms.
This is the constraint we wanted to
impose in the design
to have virtual inheritance here
to make "Mecanisme" a virtual class.
Let's see how all of this can be
translated into code.
By the way, we suggest that while
you watch these videos,
you take breaks from time to time
to write the code yourselves
in your favorite development
environment.
First point:
watches are products.
This is translated as a "Montre" class
which "is a",
which inherits from "Produit".
And of course, we introduce a "Produit"
class, from which "Montre" inherits.
And for now, we simply have an
empty "main".
Second point: watches have
a mechanism,
so they will encapsulate a Mecanisme.
Watches have a mechanism,
they are made of, so they have,
different accessories.
So, how do we translate
"different accessories"?
This is simply a collection of
accessories,
a vector of Accessoires.
This introduces two new
classes,
a "Mecanisme" class and an
"Accessoire" class.
That said, we know that these
"Accessoire" and "Mecanisme" classes
are very general classes; we want them
to be very general
to allow them to behave in a
polymorphic way
as we will have several accessories
such as bracelets,...
we will have several mechanisms,
and so here we certainly want
polymorphism,
so we will add pointers
to mechanisms
and pointers to accessories.
What we are doing right away!
In the version presented here,
we are using C++ 2011 pointers,
so-called "smart pointers".
So we will have "unique pointers"
to mechanisms,
and similarly, "unique pointers" for
the accessories,
which requires that we include
the "memory" library
(for the "unique pointers").
Of course, we included the
"vector" library as well,
for the vectors that
we need here.
And since we have just introduced
pointers in the Montre class,
we must have the reflex, as
programmers,
to think about
-- as soon as we use pointers,
we should indeed --
think about the question of copying:
"shallow copy" or "deep copy"?..
Let's leave this problem aside for a while.
we will discuss this in the very last episode.
For now, let's just say
that we cannot copy watches, nor
assign a watch,
nor use the assignment operator,
the "operator=".
So here, this is the copy constructor,
"Montre" in the "Montre" class
is indeed a constructor.
This is the copy constructor
that we delete,
and then the operator= is also deleted;
we will come back to this later.
Next aspect: products
have a price
So here, we could simply
encapsulate
a price naturally represented
as a "double",
but we have a constraint saying
that the price can vary,
which shows that we will have
to calculate the price.
For example, later on, we will
decide that the price of a watch
is the price of its mechanism
and the sum of the prices of its accessories,
And so a price can no longer be data
but shall become a function,
which we will represent as
a method (= member function).
Calculating the price of a product
will not modify the product as such,
so the method will be qualified
as "const".
Of course, it returns a price,
as a "double".
Then, we want the price to
be able to vary,
so this means that we will
want to have
a polymorphic behavior here.
Let's say that by default,
we will return the base price,
which will be defined here, "base value"
(TN: "valeur"),
what we had called "a price" earlier,
will simply become one component of the price,
its "base value".
By default, this "base value" will be the product's price,
but perhaps later,
in other subclasses of the Produit
class,
it will simply be used to calculate
the actual price of
other products that are subclasses
of the Produit class.
Moreover, all products
can be displayed.
This means, in C++, that we
will overload
the output operator for products.
Products can be displayed,
but each in its own way,
meaning that we will have a
polymorphic behavior
-- we will leave this for the next
episode,
we will come back to this in that episode.
For now, we will simply
write a prototype
to remember that we want to overload
the output operator for products.
Regarding mechanisms and accessories,
we said that mechanisms and accessories
were products.
So here too, we have an
inheritance relationship:
the "Accessoire" class inherits
from the "Produit" class,
which was defined earlier,
and the "Mecanisme" class also
inherits from the "Produit" class.
About mechanisms: there are three
kinds of mechanisms,
so here too, these three mechanisms
are of course mechanisms,
so we have "MecanismeAnalogique" which
is a mechanism,
which inherits from "Mecanisme",
"MecanismeDigital" which inherits from
"Mecanisme",
and "MecanismeDouble" which inherits
from "Mecanisme".
And finally, concerning "double mechanisms",
we will suppose that there is
only one time
for the double mechanism,
but that double mechanisms behave
both as analog mechanisms and as
digital mechanisms,
which we haven't represented
here at all,
and which will potentially change
this inheritance relationship,
but we will come back to
this aspect
in an episode specifically
dedicated to it.
Voila! This concludes this first episode
presenting the big picture,
the object-oriented design of the problem.
The next episode will focus on
polymorphic output and on filling
the "Produit" class.