In this episode, we continue
our case study
on watches -- Swiss made or not --
and we will attack the
polymorphic output
of the various products in our
hierarchy.
As a reminder, in the
last step,
we had drafted a product
hierarchy
and we will now focus on
how to make sure that these
different products
can be displayed in a
polymorphic way.
Basically, a product like a watch,
a mechanism
or an accessory will have its own
way of being displayed
and we want this display to
be polymorphic.
Meaning that if we put an
object
of type Montre, for example, in a
variable of type Produit
and we call the output method on
that variable,
the the output should automatically adapt
to the actual type of the instance stored
in the variable.
So each product will have its own way
of being displayed, and we want to
know how to procede
to implement a polymorphic output
We would like this output
to be made using the output operator.
So concretely here if we
imagine, for example,
that we declare
a pointer p to a product
[Silence]
we would like this, "display the
contents pointed to by p"...
to display the information specific
to the watch.
So, is it possible to program
this operator to have the desired
polymorphic behavior?
The answer is yes.
Of course, it is not the operator
itself which will be declared
as a virtual method.
It is not a method. It is a function
that is external to all classes,
so the operator itself cannot
be virtual.
However, nothing prevents us
from invoking a virtual, polymorphic method
on the operand it must display.
So the idea here is to make
our output operator
call a polymorphic method
which would be defined at
the superclass level.
In this case, in the Produit superclass.
Our operator allowing
the output of a product
will thus call an afficher method
(TN: "afficher"  means "display")
defined in the Produit superclass;
of course, this afficher method must
be declared as virtual
to allow polymorphic behavior
Remember that here, it is the
fact that this method is virtual
and that it is called via a reference
to a product
that allows it to have a polymorphic
behavior, as desired.
You will notice that the afficher method
is defined as public
first, because it makes sense to
offer this functionality
to the outside world,
but also because it will free us
from some constraints
related to programming the
output operator.
Typically here, since afficher is
a public-accessible method,
the operator can be programmed
to use it directly
and so, it isn't necessary to use
friend
to access this method of the
Produit class.
Once a method, in a class,
is declared as virtual,
it means that we can potentially
use instances
of this class in a polymorphic way.
And so, we must think about
destroying them appropriately
by introducing a destructor, which
will be virtual
We want want the output method of
a product
to display its price by default.
We could imagine writing the
afficher method
in such a way that it displays
the price of a product.
This solution, however, is not good.
Do you know why?
Indeed, the price of a subclass of
Produit could very well be different
from the base value
Using the base value to display the
price
will thus not be correct for all the possible
instances of Produit
including its subclasses.
Indeed, for subclasses of Produit such
as bracelets, for example,
we could perfectly imagine that the price
would correspond to the base
value of the product;
however, for watches, another
type of product,
we could imagine that the calculation
of the price would be more complex
and that it would be the sum of the
prices of all its components.
The correct way to proceed here
is therefore to use,
instead of values,
the prix() (means "price()") method, which will
itself of course
be capable of having a polymorphic behavior
and calculate the price of a watch
if the displayed product is a watch,
or the price of a bracelet
if we are displaying a bracelet.
If we go back to our initial example,
the one where we declared a pointer
on a product in which we stored
the address of a watch,
imagine now that we call the output
operator
on the object pointed to by p.
What happens here?
This will be translated by a call
to the output operator,
that we have overloaded for products.
It will call the afficher method,
knowing that now, this variable,
this parameter,
contains a reference to a watch.
The afficher method, as it
is defined in the Produit class,
will be called,
and it will itself call the price
calculation method, prix().
This method is polymorphic, so it
will automatically adapt
to the real nature of the object
on which it is called,
which it so happens is a watch here.
The prix() method is indeed virtual.
As we allow it to access the
real instance
through a pointer,
it can truly apply in a polymorphic
way
and we will have the desired result.
That is, the price for a watch will be
calculated as, for example,
the sum of the prices of all its components.
Now, let's finalize our Produit class.
Suppose that we wish to impose
the fact that
the base value of a product should
remain unchanged once we initialized it.
That way, a product's base value
would remain as
it was initialized, and it would be
impossible to change it
during the lifetime of the product.
This can be forced by labeling
the variable as constant.
We will be able to initialize the valeur
member variable, but once this is done,
we will no longer be able to change
its value
If we also wish to impose
that by default, a product has
a base value of zero,
we can do this by using a default
value
for the constructor's parameter.
So we would have
a default constructor for the
Produit class
which, when called,
would initialize the product's value with
a value of 0.
Finally, let's imagine that
we want to model
the fact that a product does not
exist as such,
that it is an abstract entity
in our design
and that we cannot create any instance
of Produit as such.
How do we force this constraint in
our design?
In C++, for a class to be abstract,
it must contain at least one pure
virtual method,
meaning that here, we would
need to have a method
defined as pure virtual.
We don't really have any reason
to create one here,
and creating one artificially would
not really make any sense.
A good candidate for a
pure virtual method
in a class is actually the
destructor.
The destructor can be declared as pure
virtual to ensure that
the class becomes abstract.
Since any class necessarily has
a destructor,
the fact of declaring it as pure virtual
saves us from having to create
an artificial method
simply to make the class abstract
Note that it is imperative to
give a body to all destructors
and note, at the same time, that nothing
prevents a pure virtual method
from having a body.
This syntax, however, is not valid C++
so it is not possible to specify the
body of a pure virtual destructor
within the class, like so.
We will have to define
the destructor of
the Produit class outside of the class, with
this syntax.
Meaning that within the Produit
class,
we declare the destructor as pure
virtual,
and we define its body outside.
So this body must be specified,
we must give a definition for the
destructor even if it doesn't do anything.
This is what we obtain, after this step,
for the code of the Produit class.
The constructor of the class allows
initialization
of its valeur attribute using a
value passed as parameter.
This constructor can be used as
a default constructor
since all of its parameters have
a default value,
a value of 0 here.
The Produit class provides
an output method
that can be used in a polymorphic way.
This method is declared as virtual,
so if it is used via a pointer or
a reference,
then it will exhibit polymorphic
behavior.
It then calls another potentially
polymorphic method,
the prix() method, also
declared as virtual
The output operator can
be overloaded
to display instances of Produit.
In order to have polymorphic behavior,
it simply has to call a polymorphic output
method in its body; a method
defined as public in the
Produit class.
Finally, to model the fact
that a product
is an abstract entity in our design,
we have declared the destructor
as pure virtual
and we did not forget to define it
even if we have nothing
specific to make it do, here.
And this concludes our episode
on the definition of products
and their polymorphic output.