In the previous episodes,
we presented the general problem
of the case study
we are now working on,
which is to model watches with
different mechanisms
and different accessories.
Then, we covered the more
specific problem
of overloading the output operator
and how to handle polymorphic output.
We also completed the "Produit" class.
In this video, we will focus on
overloading another operator, for
example the "+=" operator.
Then, we will build a first, real
operational version of the program.
Let's start by adding
the "+=" operator
to the "Montre" class
(TN: "montre"means "watch"),
which, remember, inherits from "Produit"
and has a mechanism, more
specifically a pointer
to a mechanism, for polymorphism,
and a dynamic array of pointers
to accessories
which we have called "accessoires" here.
The idea is to be able to add elements
to this dynamic array
by doing, for example for "montre", an
instance of the "Montre" class,
" montre += new Bracelet (...); ",
where, as you will recall, "Bracelet" is
a subclass of "Accessoire".
So we would like this to add a new
pointer to a "Bracelet"
into the collection of pointers
to "Accessoires".
Since a "Bracelet" is an "Accessoire",
a pointer to a "Bracelet" can be put into
a pointer to an "Accessoire".
That's the idea for this "+=" operator.
The prototype of this operator
will look like this:
we won't use its return value,
as we will never write things like
" z = (montre += new "Bracelet" (...)); ".
So here, we have a "void" return type.
This is the "+=" operator for the "Montre" class
and the operator must take
a pointer to an "Accessoire",
so here, "new" will return a
C-style pointer,
and we want to view it as a pointer
to an "Accessoire".
So here, in a very general way, it will
be a pointer to an "Accessoire".
Here, we added a bracelet, but we could
add a clasp,
a body, or any other subclass of
"Accessoire".
Now, let's see how we can write
its definition.
This pointer to an "Accessoire",
"p_accessoire", that we received,
we simply want to add it to the
dynamic array of accessories
stored in the watch.
So we will simply call "push_back"
with this pointer,
but here, since we received
a C-style pointer,
we will transform this
C-style pointer
to a "unique_ptr".
So here, we create a "unique_ptr"
which converts this C-style pointer,
"p_accessoire",
and we add it to the end, we "push_back"
on the "accessoires" vector,
in which all the accessories of
the watch are stored.
That's it for this very simple
overload
of the "+=" operator, which
now provides us with
a very compact syntax to add accessories
to a watch.
Now, let's try to write a first
operational
version of the program.
Let's try to finalize what we have
written up till now;
and for now, let's not add
any mechanism
or copy any watches.
We will leave these two aspects for
the next two episodes.
To be able to finalize the program as
we have written it up till now,
we would need a few more concrete
accessories
and we would have to finish the
"Montre" class
which is yet not quite operational.
And of course, we must use all this
in a typical "main".
We will go over all of these points
one after the other,
starting with a few more accessories.
Remember that we have an "Accessoire"
class, which is a product,
and let's say for example that
accessories need
a name to describe them.
To do so, let's say we have a name
that will not change
once it has been set by
the constructor.
And we will add a constructor to the
"Accessoire" class
which will take a name to refer to
the accessory.
And let's not forget that any product can
be sold and thus has a price,
and so it will take a second
parameter
to initialize the price of the product.
The initialization list in the
constructor for "Accessoire"
will start by calling the constructor for
the "Produit" superclass
passing it the second parameter
we received for the base value.
Then, we will initialize the "nom" member
(TN: means "name") with the name we received.
That's it for the constructor we decided
to give to all the accessories.
Now, let's decide on a way of displaying
the accessories
since, remember, all products can be
displayed
in a polymorphic way.
So we will overload the "afficher" method
that was inherited from "Produit".
We override it by adding
the "override" keyword.
And let's say that the output will
be their name and price.
So we will simply display the name,
then indicate how much it costs.
And we already know how to display
the price by directly calling
the afficher method from the
"Produit" superclass.
Here, we use the scope resolution
operator
to access the afficher method inherited
from the "Produit" superclass.
Because of course, if we simply write
"afficher" without this,
we will call the "afficher" method
from the current class
and we would have infinite recursion here,
where "afficher" would call itself.
And so, in the "afficher" method of the
"Accessoire" class,
to call the "afficher" method inherited
from the "Produit" superclass,
we need to unhide this
"afficher" method.
Next, since we expect a polymorphic
behavior
with virtual methods,
we don't forget to add the
polymorphic destructor,
the virtual destructor,
in the class for which we want
polymorphic behavior.
This way, if subclasses inherit from it,
as will be the case with accessories,
which need to have destructors
with specific behaviors,
then their own destructor will indeed
be called in a polymorphic way
-- and not the destructor
for the "Accessoire" class.
Finally, let's say that the price of
accessories
is the same price as a normal product,
that is, a very general product
as we had designed it
right at the top of the hierarchy.
At that point, we don't have anything
to do
since the "prix" method
that we inherited
from the "Produit" class is
enough here
and we don't need to override
it in the "Accessoire" class.
So here, we have completely functional
"Accessoire" class which corresponds
to what we wanted.
Now, let's define a few
accessories,
for example a "Bracelet". A "Bracelet"
is an "Accessoire",
so here, we will have an
inheritance link.
At the accessory level, let's say
that their name
-- remember that accessories
have a name, so
all accessories will inherit this
name --
let's say that we want each accessory
to have a name that marks
what they are.
For example, the name of a "Bracelet"
will start with "bracelet"
the name of a clasp will start
with "fermoir" (TN: means "clasp").
We will force this in the constructor.
For example, for the "Bracelet" subclass
of the "Accessoire" class,
we will take a name, which will be the
complement that we add after "bracelet",
for example "en cuir"
(TN: means "made of leather")
so that the complete name becomes
"bracelet en cuir" (TN: "leather strap").
And as a second parameter, the price,
which we also pass to the
superclass's constructor
in the initialization list.
And all of these classes can
potentially have
polymorphic subclasses,
so let's not forget the virtual destructor.
Similarly, we could define a "Fermoir" class
(TN: means "Clasp") inheriting from "Accessoire"
in which we define a constructor
taking a complement to the "fermoir"
name and a price,
to be able to call the constructor of
the "Accessoire" superclass.
The complete name will thus be
"fermoir" with this complement
that we received as the first parameter,
and as the second parameter, the
price that we received,
and as always, a virtual destructor.
There, we have finished with
the accessories.
Now let's try to also make the
"Montre" class usable
without mechanisms and without
copying
which we will leave to the side
for now.
At this stage, we have completely defined
the contents of the "Montre" class,
we have prevented copying,
and we have added the "+=" operator
allowing us to add accessories
to our watches.
To make this class operational, we must
add at least one constructor
since we have modified the
constructor here,
the default constructor, provided
by default, is no longer so.
We don't have the default
constructor anymore,
so we must at least add it here.
Of course, the default constructor
will do nothing
to initialize the mechanisms,
and so at this point we will
simply comment this out,
to avoid any problem with using
a pointer
that would not be initialized --
we will simply comment out
this line.
Regarding the vector of pointers
to accessories,
the default constructor
will create an empty vector
and so here, there is no problem.
We will be able to fill this vector using our
"+=" operator.
So the default constructor
suits us, as long as we
don't have this pointer
so we will comment it out for now
and come back to it in a subsequent
episode.
That's it for creating watches.
Now, let's decide how to
compute the price of watches,
and let's say that it is the sum of
the prices of its accessories.
For that, we will override the
"prix" method,
we override this "virtual prix" method
inherited from the "Produit" superclass.
We will decide that at first, the
price of a watch is its base value,
that we fetch through the original
"prix" method,
inherited from the "Produit" superclass.
Then we will add, to this
base value,
the sum of prices of the
different accessories.
To do so, we go through the
list of accessories
-- remember that to iterate over an
array of "unique_ptr"s,
it is crucial to use this syntax, to use
references -
here, fetching the price will not modify
the instances we iterate over,
so we will use a constant reference
Here, we will write a loop that iterates
with a constant reference
over the "unique_ptr"s of this dynamic
array of accessories.
And we add to the price, that we
had originally initialized,
the price each time, that is, the
result of the call to the "prix" method
of the object pointed to by
"p_acc" here,
so the object pointed to via
this pointer.
This is how we write the call to the
"prix" method
for something that is a pointer
to an object
providing such a method.
And finally, we return the
price that we have just computed.
Finally, let's decide how we
want to display the watches,
and let's say for example that
we want a message to say
that a watch is made of:
the list of its various accessories, ...
And at the end, we display
the total price of the watch.
And so here, we will also override
the virtual "afficher" method
inherited from the "Produit" superclass.
And remember that here we are
overriding it,
starting by displaying:
"A watch is composed of",
then by iterating over the vector of
accessories of the watch,
and for each accessory, we display
this little star
then we display the current accessory.
Question here:
are we allowed to write this?
Will this compile?
Have we overloaded the output
operator for this?
Yes, it is correct and it compiles.
And finally, we end by displaying
the message "total price"
and calling the watch's "prix" method,
which will compute the total price,
as we have just seen.
Finally, to have an executable program,
we need a "main", which we will
use here to test
the implementation of the objects
we have just created.
For this, we will declare a "Montre"
in the "main".
We can easily do this
since we have a default constructor now.
Then, we add various accessories
to the watch, like so.
Each of the accessories has a constructor
with its name or the complement to the name,
and its price
So here, we add for example
4 accessories,
and finally we output a message to
display the watch here,
with the output operator we saw
earlier.
This output operator, as we
have just discussed,
will call the "prix" method.
The execution of this program will thus
yield the following result:
first, we will display the message
"Montre m : ",
then we will enter the overload of
the operator for "Produit",
but with a call to the polymorphic
afficher method
for "Montre",
which will thus display:
"Une montre composée de: "
then a loop over its various
acessories,
and finally will display the
total price,
the sum of prices of its accessories.
For those who would like it,
all of the code is available on the
course website
This concludes the presentation
of this first operational
version of our code.
There are still two chapters to cover in
the next two episodes:
first, all of these mechanisms,
with multiple inheritance,
and then the concept of copying
a watch,
how to make a deep copy of the various
"Accessoires" of a "Montre".