Let's continue our case study
on watches
and cover this time,
multiple inheritance
through the modeling of the various
mechanisms considered.
As a reminder,
in the previous episodes,
the design on which we had
settled was
to model the watch by giving
it a core,
which is a pointer to a "Mecanisme".
An inheritance hierarchy
had been drafted
for the different mechanisms considered.
So we had the "Mecanisme" superclass
from which three types of
mechanisms inherit:
analog mechanisms ("MecanismeAnalogique"),
digital mechansims ("MecanismeDigital"),
and "double mechanisms"
("MecanismeDouble").
This first hierarchy, however, does not
quite reflect
our wishes concerning "double
mechanisms".
Indeed, in the constraints we
had set ourselves,
we wanted "double mechanisms"
to be both analog mechanisms
and digital mechanisms, while having,
while showing, only one time.
Making "MecanismeDouble"
inherit from "Mecanisme"
rather than making it inherit from
"MecanismeDigital" and "MecanismeAnalogique"
does not allow us to model what we
want properly.
So we will now update our
hierarchy
in order to make apparent the
link between
"double mechanisms",
and analog, as well as
digital mechanisms.
In C++, since multiple inheritance
is possible,
the path is quite clear,
we must make "MecanismeDouble"
inherit
both from "MecanismeAnalogique"
and from "MecanismeDigital".
If we set up multiple inheritance
like this,
we must be watch out for one thing.
We want a "double mechanism" to display
only one single time,
inherited from above.
The time is modeled
at the level of the "Mecanisme" class.
If we simply set up this
multiple inheritance:
"MecanismeDouble" inheriting
from "MecanismeAnalogique"
and "MecanismeDigital",
any instance of "MecanismeDouble"
will inherit the "heure" variable twice
(TN: "heure" means "time"):
once, as an analog mechanism
and once as a digital mechanism
However, this is not what we want
We want a "double mechanism" to keep
only one time.
So we must make sure that this
superclass is virtual
in order for the "MecanismeDouble"
subclass
to inherit from the "heure"
variable only once.
And for that, all the
inheritance links
linking "Mecanisme" to
its direct subclasses
must be declared as "virtual".
The new hierarchy we obtain
corresponds to the code that
you see here.
So we have a "Mecanisme" superclass,
which will provide the member
variable indicating the time.
From this "Mecanisme" superclass,
two direct subclasses will inherit:
"MecanismeAnalogique" and "MecanismeDigital".
So we make sure to declare the inheritance
links as "virtual"
in order to allow
the "MecanismeDouble" subclass
to inherit only once the attribute
coming from "Mecanisme".
"MecanismeDouble"
inherits both from "MecanismeAnalogique"
and from "MecanismeDigital".
To make our example a little
more interesting,
we will give our "MecanismeAnalogique"
"MecanismeDigital" subclasses
specific members
such as a date, for example, for
the analog mechanism
and an alarm clock for the digital one.
(TN: "réveil" means "alarm clock")
Note that in C++, a superclass
of which subclasses
inherit virtually
is called a "virtual class".
This should not be confused
with an abstract class.
The fact that "Mecanisme"
is a virtual class
has an effect on the construction
of a "double mechanism".
Do you know what effects?
In a class hierarchy with
no virtual classes,
a subclass's constructor simply
has to
invoke the constructors of its
direct superclasses.
However, in a hierarchy containing
a virtual class,
all the subclasses must call
the constructor of this virtual class.
So, let's start by defining how
mechanisms are built.
Up until now, we only had a
default constructor.
Let's refine the definition
of this constructor.
Given that a mechanism is a product,
and thus inherits from the "Produit" class,
it must initialize the base value of
the product, inherited from Produit,
and must initialize its own member
variable, the time.
Therefore, for the "Mecanisme"
class, we could naturally think
of making a constructor that
looks like this.
So, it would take as parameters
a value allowing it
to initialize the variable inherited
from "Produit"
and a second value
to initialize its own variable
We could also imagine giving
a default value
for this second parameter.
The constructor for the "Mecanisme"
class must of course invoke
the constructor of the superclass
"Produit"
and initialize its member variable.
Now, let's discuss the
subclasses' constructors.
First, the constructor for
"MecanismeAnalogique" for example,
which inherits directly from the
"Mecanisme" class.
This constructor will take as parameters
values allowing it to initialize all
of its member variables:
those inherited from above
and those that are specific to it.
And it will, in any case, invoke
the constructor
of its direct superclass,
which happens to be the virtual
"Mecanisme" class.
The constructor for the
"MecanismeDigital" class
will be written quite similarly.
The constructor for the
"MecanismeDouble" subclass
must invoke the constructors for
its direct superclasses
but it must first invoke the constructor
of the virtual superclass.
Do you remember what happens
with the call to the virtual
superclass's constructor
in the direct superclasses?
Now, let's have a look at how default
values are handled.
Remember that in the constructor
for "Mecanisme",
the parameter allowing us to
initialize the mechanism's time was
a default value.
If we want this default time to
be preserved
by the constructors of
"Mecanisme"'s subclasses,
we will need to take some steps.
Then we must make sure that
it is possible
to create an analog mechanism without
providing a time
and in that case, it would have
the default time,
the same as for mechanisms.
It should still have the option, of course,
of initializing its own member variable.
To do so, we should provide
a second constructor
that would take no parameter
linked to the time
and that would call the constructor
of the superclass,
initializing the default time
-- that is, without providing
any value for this time.
But wouldn't it have been easier
to give a default value
for this second parameter?
The answer is no, because the
last parameter, intended for the date,
doesn't have a default value
and all default values in
the parameters
must be at the end of
the list.
Note that it would also be very bad
to duplicate one default value in
two different places
for example here, in the
analog mechanism
and higher up, in the mechanism.
This would open the door
to problems
of bad maintenance
nd incoherence.
To correctly manage the default
value of the superclass,
the same reasoning we used
for "MecanismeAnalogique" should
of course also be used
in "MecanismeDigital" and in
"MecanismeDouble".
In the "MecanismeDouble" class,
where the constructors should
be overloaded.
So here, one takes a time as parameter,
and the other takes no
parameter for the time
and will call the constructor
of the superclass
which gives a default value for this
time attribute, "heure".
We have now finished
with the construction of mechanisms,
let's move on to displaying them.
Suppose that for these outputs,
we want all mechanisms
to be displayed following the
same model
a model that is imposed and
cannot be modified.
This model would, for example,
display systematically
the type of the mechanism,
followed by a display of the watch face
containing the time and
when applicable,
the date or the time of the alarm,
followed by the price for example.
But we also want each of
these parts,
each of the parts of this model,
to be adaptable.
What we mean by "part" would
typically be the part that displays
the type of the mechanism, or
the part that displays the watch face.
This description assumes that
there exists
a general display method for
all mechanisms
following a precise model
but that this method calls other
methods itself
and these could have an
adaptable behavior,
that is, a polymorphic aspect.
The idea is thus to allow these
methods to have
a specific behavior depending
on subclasses
meaning that we could have,
for example, a method for
displaying the mechanism type
that would be specific to each subclass.
Similarly, we could have a method to
display the watch face
that would be specific to
each subclass
and, thanks to polymorphism, they
would be able to adapt automatically
to the real type of the objects
on which they are called.
The fact that the same basic model
is imposed to all mechanisms
implies that once a method follows
this fixed model,
it must no longer be modified.
This should make us think
of final methods.
We also want to provide a default
version
of the watch face display for
all the subclasses.
So this method should have
a default definition,
typically right at the top of the hierarchy,
in the "Mecanisme" class.
This default version could, for example,
simply display the time
and be used in the subclasses
to display the time of course, and
possibly other information.
So here, we are moving
towards a method
for displaying the watch face that
would be polymorphic
but that would have a default
definition in the superclass.
However, to display the
mechanism type,
we want to force subclasses to
redefine it.
This, of course, should make us
think
of pure virtual qualifiers
This is how we could translate
these different constraints
into C++ code.
Our "Mecanisme" superclass
provides
a polymorphic display method
which overrides the one inherited from
"Produit" displaying the price.
Our "Mecanisme" superclass thus
provides a display method
that adheres to a precise model.
It will display the type,
the face and the price
via the method inherited
from "Produit".
To make sure that this model is
fixed once and for all
and cannot be overridden in a
subclass of the hierarchy,
we mark this method as "final".
"Mecanisme"'s subclasses will thus no longer
be able to override the "afficher" method,
so all the mechanisms will be displayed
following this precise model.
However, via new methods:
"afficher_type", "afficher_cadran"
(TN: "display_type" and "display _ace", resp.)
which will be of course defined
as "virtual",
we guarantee that the different parts
involved in this model
can be adapted and modified
in the subclasses.
You may have noticed, by the way,
that since the "afficher" method
from the "Mecanisme" class overrides
the "afficher" method from the "Produit" class,
we have used the "override" qualifier.
The "afficher_cadran" method,
as specified in the constraints that
we mentioned earlier,
provides a default version that
will display the time.
However, concerning the
"afficher_type" method:
we want to force its definition in
the subclasses,
but it is still an abstract concept at
the level of the mechanisms
and so it is declared as a
pure virtual method.
If we want the subclasses of
"Mecanisme" that have overridden
"afficher_cadran" to still be able
to invoke
the "afficher_cadran" method
inherited from the superclass,
then the access to "afficher_cadran"
must be possible in these subclasses
and this is the reason why
we labeled this method as protected.
Conversely, the "afficher_type" method
will not be invoked
in the subclasses of "Mecanisme";
it is pure virtual and has no body.
Therefore, it makes sense to declare
it as "private".
All the mechanisms with which
we want to be able to work
-- we want to be able to give an
analog mechanism as core for a watch --
must inevitably
override the "afficher_type" method
to be instantiable.
We can imagine that for the
"MecanismeAnalogique" class,
"afficher_type" simply displays
"analog".
The "afficher_cadran" method does
indeed have a definition in
the superclass,
but it can still be overridden in the
subclasses.
For example here, we can imagine
overriding it
in the "MecanismeAnalogique" subclass
in order to make it display the time
by calling the method inherited
from the superclass.
As a reminder, here is the syntax
using the scope resolution operator
allowing us to call the "afficher_cadran"
method from the "Mecanisme" class.
But we will also display the date.
Analogously, the "MecanismeDouble" class
will also provide a concrete definition
for "afficher_type".
It can also override the "afficher_cadran"
method
and it can benefit from the "afficher_cadran"
methods inherited from both "MecanismeAnalogique"
and "MecanismeDigital".
This way, we would display the
information specific to
the analog mechanism, that is,
the time and date,
and using this, display the
information specific
to the digital mechanism, i.e the
time followed by the time of the alarm.
And now, as we are now used to doing,
we can test the new features
using a small main program.
We can create an analog mechanism
using the default value for
the time,
meaning that we provide no time.
We can create a digital mechanism
that would have a non-default
value for the time
and specific value for its parameters.
And in a similar way, a "double mechanism"
by providing all the information
necessary to initialize it
like a time here, a date and
the time of the alarm.
The "afficher" method of the mechanisms
that we have just developed
will be invoked by
the overloaded output operator
that we specified earlier for the
products.
This method is polymorphic
and so it will adapt to
all types of products,
including to mechanisms.
These lines will allow us to test
our latest developments
on the constructors in "Mecanisme"'s
hierarchy.
And this line will allow us to
test our display method.
We can now give our watch an
actual core
we can for example imagine defining,
in the "Montre" class,
a constructor that would take as argument
the value of a pointer to a mechanism.
So we can create this mechanism
using the constructors that we
have discussed in this episode.
The display of the watch would
also be completed
in such a way to invoke the
display of its core.
The complete code for this part can
be downloaded on the course website.
And this concludes this episode
on modeling mechanisms.