Let's conclude this case study
with the problem of copying watches.
Since we know that our watch
has pointers
to its different components,
its mechanism and its accessories,
how do we copy a watch?
Up til now, we have forbidden copying
and forbidden assignment,
the equals operator
but now, we will look into how
to actually copy a watch.
This will lead us to a new problematic
which is polymorphic copying.
Let's start with the problem
of copying watches
and suppose, for example, that we have
two watches m1 and m2
such that m2 is a copy of m1.
So, we have the following
situation in memory:
the core, which is a pointer
to a mechanism somewhere in memory
and the accessories which are
a dynamic array of pointers
to different accessories in memory.
If we make a shallow copy of m1
into m2,
-- a shallow copy means that we will
simply copy
the different values of m1,
the values of the pointers --
so here, we will copy the pointer
to this element etc.,
and at this moment,
if this were possible
-- I will come back to this point
in a moment --
we would already have a problem
in any case
since the watches m2 and m1
share the same accessories
and share the same mechanism
which means that if, through
m1, we change
for example, the time of the watch,
then your friend's watch, watch m2,
will automatically
have the same time
If you decide to change the bracelet
of your watch, m1,
to have a leather bracelet, then
automatically
the watch m2 will also
have a leather bracelet.
What's more, with the architecture
that we defined currently, that
is, with the unique_ptrs,
we can in any case not make
copies
since unique_ptrs must
be unique in pointing
to their memory area.
We cannot copy unique pointers.
So in any case, we could not have
this situation in memory
and if we had decided to
use C-style pointers,
then we would run into the
problem I have just mentioned,
of having components that would
be shared by different watches.
So the conclusion for all of this
is that we must make deep copies.
A deep copy means that instead
of simply copying
the values of the pointers,
instead of copying the addresses,
we copy the pointed-to objects
themselves
and so for each component,
we actually copy
the current object
and we store in the copied object,
at the highest level, the pointers
to the copies of the components.
We will have copied, not just
at the surface,
but deep down.
And so here, we do not have copies
of the values of the pointers
but pointers to copies of
the pointed-to objects.
This is what we mean when we
speak of a deep copy
versus a shallow copy.
And so what we need is
indeed a deep copy
a copy of each component.
In those cases, it is also customary
to override the assignment
operator,
which is what we will do later on.
Let's start with the copy constructor,
that is, the constructor of Montre
that makes a copy construction.
So the parameter taken by
the copy constructor
is of course another watch.
The copy constructor should begin with
-- one must never forget this aspect --
a call to the copy constructors of
the superclasses.
Here, we only have one superclass,
the Produit class,
and so here we must call
the copy constructor
of the Produit class. Otherwise..
otherwise, we will call the
default constructor
at this point, if we had not
written this line.
So we would have a default
construction
of the Produit aspect of a watch.
Meaning that its price, for example,
would be set to zero
which is not always desirable.
So we must always start with a call
to the copy constructor of the
superclass.
Then the question is how to
continue,
when should we copy the
different components?
If we simply write this
and in a similar way for the
accessories,
then we will just have a shallow copy,
we will have copied the value
of the pointer, "autre.coeur",
into the pointer "coeur" of the instance
that we are creating.
This is exactly what we want
to avoid
so it is not the correct way to do this.
What we could imagine, then,
is to copy the object pointed to
by the core of the other watch,
that is, to copy *(autre.coeur).
Indeed, the access to the contents
of the other's core
is the contents of this cell here.
This is what we wanted to copy.
Copy this into the core of the
current instance
and to do so, allocate a new
memory area
whose address we would retrieve
and this new area will contain the copy
of the contents of (autre.coeur).
So this would be written like this:
coeur( new ??? (*(autre.coeur))
-- but new what?
Which object should be copied as
the core of the other?
Since I remind you that a core
is a pointer to a mechanism
and here, we would of course have
to convert our C-style pointer
into a unique_ptr to a Mecanisme.
But we still don't know what
this core that we are copying
should be.
Because this other core could
easily be
an analog mechanism or
a digital mechanism
or a double mechanism.
And so, what should we
copy this other core as?
What we could imagine
would be to copy it as a Mecanisme
but this means that we
would copy
only the Mecanisme part of the other's
core
and we would risk losing
all the specifics
of the instance that is actually pointed
to, such as the specifics of the analog mechanism
if the core is an analog mechanism,
the digital specifics, etc.
So we would lose the specifics.
So here, we cannot make
a copy like this
as a Mecanisme
The question, basically, is:
how do we copy each element
as it is?
That is, to copy them not just
as instances
of the Mecanisme superclass but
to copy them
as the subclasses to which
they belong.
And the question can of course
be posed
for all the accessories -- how do
we copy each of the accessories?
The bracelet as a bracelet, the
clasp as a clasp,
the body as a body etc.
The question is thus, how
do we make a copy
that respects the proper nature
of the instances?
That is, how do we make a
polymorphic copy?
The solution consists, as usual
when we have a particular task to do,
in defining a method that carries
out this task
and so, to define a copy method here
that is capable of making a
polymorphic copy.
A polymorphic copy of a Mecanisme here
and a polymorphic copy of an
accessory here.
And so of course, we will have
to copy each accessory
as they are, and so iterate over
the accessories of the other watch
one by one to be able to make a
polymorphic copy of them.
Let's see how we can write such
a polymorphic copy
taking the accessories as
an example.
So we have a dynamic array of pointers
to accessories
of which we want to copy each element.
Typically, we would copy them
like this
by making a call to a
polymorphic copy
of a pointer to an accessory.
So the polymorphic copy
will be defined
at the level of the most general class
for which we want to make
a polymorphic copy.
at this level, we will define
a copie method.
The copie method, as such, will
not modify the instances
-- it just copies them --
and we don't know how to define
it at such a general level.
So as we are in an abstract class,
we will say that
it is a pure virtual method.
The return value of such a method
is what we will put in this container
and so it will be a unique pointer
to an accessory
so here we will say that it is a
"unique_ptr"
And so in the subclasses
for example here in the Bracelet
subclass,
what we will do is to override
the copy that returns a unique_ptr to
an accessory
and say that we will return
a unique_ptr
to an accessory, so this here remains
a pointer to an accessory,
but this pointer, specifically,
is a pointer
to a new bracelet in memory which is
a copy of the current instance.
So I know that this syntax is very
difficult to understand
the first time one comes across it,
so let's explain it a little.
What we want to do with a copy
method such as this one
is to copy oneself as one is,
meaning, to copy oneself as a Bracelet
if one is a Bracelet.
To do so, we will call the copy constructor
of the Bracelet class
to copy the current instance.
The current instance is indeed
the contents of the this pointer,
so "*this" is the current instance.
It is the contents of what is pointed
to by this
and since this points to the current instance,
it is indeed the current instance
that we are copying into a new
Bracelet
So that gives us this part
of this line
and then we will do this by creating
a new memory area
and retrieve a pointer
to this memory area -- this is
done by the new.
So here, new Bracelet will
create a new bracelet
of which we retrieve the address
and this new bracelet is a copy
of the current instance.
Finally, we will convert
this C-style pointer
which is the result of the new Bracelet
copying the current instance,
we will convert it into a
unique_ptr-to-Accessoire.
We will see it, we will see this pointer
as a unique_ptr to an accessory.
So this is the syntax that is
very often used
to make polymorphic copies.
We return a pointer to the
abstract class,
the superclass at whose level
we want to make the copy,
of a new copy, and be careful here,
specific to the current class.
So here, we are indeed in the Bracelet class,
we write "Bracelet"
-- in the Fermoir class, we will write "Fermoir".
This is a copy of the current instance.
That's it for copying watches.
What if we also want to take
care of the assigmnent operator?
That is, for example, do
m1 = m2 .
To do so, we will overload the
assignment operator
the equals operator, in the following way.
In the Montre class, we follow the
model we presented
in the episode on operator
overloading
and so here, we have the typical
prototype for the equals operator
where we pass by value here
which means that when we write
m2 = m1,
that is, m2.operator=(m1)
we will copy m1 into
this new source.
So here, we use the copy
constructor
and it is this copy constructor,
which we have just defined,
that will do all the work
of making the deep copy,
then we just have to exchange
the newly copied instance
ex-m1, which is now source,
into the current instance
and to do so, we can for example
use the swap method
provided by the standard library
utility
to swap the core of m2, of
the current instance
with the core of the newly-created
source, created by copy
And so we will swap the array of
pointers of the current instance
with the array of pointers to
new components
created by the deep copy of this source
that was just created.
And we end with the standard syntax
which returns a reference
to the current instance
to conform to this prototype
which allows us to write things
like m3 = m2 = m1.
That's it for the assignment operator
and of course, all of this must
be tested,
which we will do by completing
our old main
in which we had defined a watch
with a call to the copy constructor
that copies m into m2.
Then we check that the copy
was made correctly by
displaying m2 here.
Then we would test the equals
operator.
First, we create a new watch, m3
with whatever in it, then we display
it,
then we assign m2 to m3.
And we check that this assigment
worked correctly.
On top of this, to check
that we have made
a deep copy with this copy here,
then we would add a method that
we haven't explained in this
video but that doesn't present
any difficulty:
a "mettre à l'heure" method (TN: means "set time")
which would set the time of watch m2
which would modify the time of
the watch m2
And so we would check that
in this assignment
m3 has m2's old time,
and is not affected by this change
of time in m2.
If we only had a shallow copy,
then m2.mettre_a_l_heure
would also modify m3's time.
So this line here effectively
allows us
to check that we have made
a deep copy
and not a shallow copy of m2
into m3.
All this code, the complete code
is again provided on the course website
This concludes this case study
and the whole course.