Hello and welcome to this MOOC on law enforcement
in protected areas.
As you know, protected areas are places that
conserve nature.
This conservation meets certain rules.
The goal of this MOOC is to give us the keys
to understanding what these rules are and
what are the principles regulating their implementation,
in theory and in practice.
Of course, a MOOC can’t replace in situ
surveillance, or more generally monitoring
infringements in the field.
But it can help us think about the context
in which this can be applied, about what behaviours
to have and about the best practices to develop.
In this MOOC, we will be looking at:
- How the laws, rules, conventions and codes
that supervise nature conservation in general
and protected areas in particular function.
- Then, we will talk about work ethics required
for law enforcement
- We will focus on corruption, a key element
of the failure of monitoring systems
- We will describe the methods on how to give
clear and organised orders to limit possible
mistakes
- Finally, we will see how all this can be
translated into field surveillance in a protected
area.
You’ll see, the classes include several
experts, lawyers, police officers, PA managers,
all professionals in their fields.
Each module is made of several sequences in
the form of videos divided by quizzes and
examples.
Further documentation is also available, which
can help you go in further detail according
to your needs.
A PDF document is also available for online
reading or for downloading to help you remember
the most important points.
Finally, if you pass the optional online exams
you will receive a certificate.
If you would like to receive the Certificate
of Open Studies, you can prepare for the classroom
exam of this MOOC.
All this is mentioned on the forum of the
MOOC platform, but also in the Facebook group
which I invite you to join.
You can also sign up for the monthly NAPA
newsletter.
There, we are available for you so don’t
hesitate to get in touch.
Have a great MOOC !