So far we’ve talked about regulation defined
by what it’s trying to protect – a particular
species or place.
Now we turn to regulation that addresses a
specific activity or threat, regardless of
where it is carried out or what species it
affects.
We’ve already discussed some mechanisms
used to regulate activities.
For example, hunting licenses may be required
in specific areas, or when hunting specific
species.
However, regulations on hunting may not be
limited to protected areas or endangered species.
Many jurisdictions have general hunting regulations
that set out processes for licensing and prohibit
certain methods or equipment.
Similarly activities that affect specific
ecosystems, such as dredging or filling wetlands,
may be regulated generally, wherever that
ecosystem is found, whether or not it is in
a protected area.
Or there may be general standards for activities
such as mining or logging practices to reduce
environmental impact.
One of the most familiar forms of threat-based
regulation is pollution control.
Human activity always affects the environment
– this is unavoidable.
Regulation must determine what level of impact
is acceptable.
It must balance the desire for innovation
and development with the need for sustainability.
It must also be able to adapt to changing
technology.
The simplest standard is a quota, cap or load
– a number that describes how much pollution
can go into the air, water, ground or atmosphere,
or how much of a resource can be taken out
of the environment.
A standard based on a specific quota can be
inflexible.
Alternative types of standards can be used
to respond to changing technology, or create
incentives for pollution reduction.
One common example is a standard based on
“best available technology” or “best
available practices”.
This standard requires operators to use the
best methods available to limit pollution,
emissions or other environmental impact.
In many cases it is qualified – operators
may not be required to immediately adopt any
new technology if it is prohibitively expensive
or otherwise unreasonable.
A common criticism of the “best available
technology” standard is that it can reduce
incentives for innovation, since any company
that develops improvements to reduce impact
will be creating a new legal requirement for
itself and the rest of the industry.
On the other hand, it can create a protection
for companies that do innovate, since their
competitors will be held to the same technological
standard.
Another option is to couple a cap or quota
with a trading scheme.
For example, polluters that exceed their quota
may be able to buy credits from others that
emit less.
This can create an incentive to improve environmental
practices, since companies can sell the credits
that they don’t use.
You can also find trading schemes in the context
of biodiversity.
Many governments have adopted a policy of
“no net loss” for wetlands, forests or
biodiversity.
Where this applies, operators may be able
to offset activities that cause loss in one
area by restoring or protecting a similar
ecosystem in another.
In the context of climate change, emissions
trading has created a global market for carbon
offsets.
Many of these offsets come from projects in
the developing world.
This offsetting raises complicated legal questions,
such as who owns carbon, who can sell it and
who can benefit?
It also creates opportunities for fraud and
corruption.
Taxes, such as a carbon tax or a pollution
tax, can be an alternative to direct regulation
or tradeable permits.
Taxes are one of the most efficient types
of market-based measures for regulating activities.
Another common tool in activity-based regulation
is the environmental impact assessment or
EIA.
Most countries have some form of environmental
impact assessment for activities that may
cause damage to the environment.
Some activities always require an EIA.
Others may be triggered by a specific threshold,
such as where an activity is likely to have
a significant adverse effect on biodiversity
or the natural environment.
The EIA process should be transparent, and
include opportunities for public comment on
the proposed activity.
All activity or threat-based regulation has
to deal with the question of how to evaluate
risk.
It can be hard to quantify the amount of harm
that will be caused by an activity in advance,
when deciding whether to allow it.
Sometimes it is only possible to say that
there is a certain chance of a certain level
of harm.
Regulation can provide methods to assess and
manage risk, and establish thresholds for
what levels of risk are acceptable.
They also provide for what happens if the
disaster or emergency actually happens: how
to respond, and who bears the cost.
This can give rise to legal liability.