As discussed previously, law exists at many
levels, from the local level up to the international.
International law is different from law at
national and sub-national levels, so in this
unit we will spend some time exploring what
international law is and how it is relevant
for conservation.
While national law binds individuals as well
as corporations, organizations and government
actors, international law primarily governs
relationships between States, at least in
theory.
Before explaining, I will quickly note that
here we are talking about public international
law – there exists a field of private international
law that governs international transactions
and relationships between private entities,
like corporations, but we will not focus on
that in this discussion.
In the traditional model of public international
law States make treaties and agreements amongst
each other, which are only binding on the
States.
Each State is responsible for implementing
and enforcing the obligations contained in
these agreements on its own citizens, through
national law.
This is based on a concept of State sovereignty,
in which each country has the exclusive right
to make law within its territory and control
the actions of its citizens.
However, this model is simplistic at best,
and doesn’t really describe the current
legal situation.
Multinational corporations have grown bigger
and stronger in international influence – many
have annual operating budgets higher than
the GDP of the States in which they operate.
The line between State and private entity
is not always clear, with many wholly or partly
State-owned corporations or public-private
partnerships.
NGOs and business interests now participate
in the negotiation of treaties as well as
their implementation.
Private governance has grown at the international
as well as the national level, through corporate
standards, labels and private certification
schemes.
Civil society and social movements can directly
regulate multinational corporations, through
consumer and shareholder decisions and public
shaming and boycotts facilitated by new forms
of media.
Today there is growing international recognition
of the significant role of non-state actors
in international law.
At this point it is worth taking a step back
and asking what is the purpose of international
law?
We can start by imagining a world with no
international law.
In this world, law is only created at the
national level or below.
What problems could this cause?
One problem might be how to deal with transboundary
resources.
Imagine a river that crosses a border between
countries.
How do the countries share the water?
What about the fish?
What if one country wants to build a dam,
or pours pollution into the river?
How could these problems be resolved?
We can also think of questions related to
global resources, like oceans or the atmosphere.
A striking example is climate change – a
global problem that cannot easily be resolved
on a national level.
Another category of problems relates to things
that happen entirely within one country, but
concern the rest of the world.
The most extreme example is activities that
are fundamentally shocking, to the point that
they go against what it means to be human.
I am talking about genocide, slavery, torture
and other crimes against humanity.
Where these crimes take place within a country,
should there be a way for other countries
to step in?
And what about other harm, like loss of an
entire species, or destruction of an irreplaceable
archeological site?
Should the international community be concerned
about this?
There are many other examples.
Sometimes solving a problem requires international
cooperation – such as when wildlife in one
country is killed because of demand in another.
Sometimes countries can’t manage a problem
on their own, and need help, including financial
and technical resources.
Can you think of other problems that would
exist in a world without international law?
We can think of many challenges that cannot
be solved by national and subnational law
alone.
Let’s think about how international law
can help solve them.
There are three main functions that international
law can perform.
The first is legislative: international law
can create norms and standards for the international
community.
These can include principles like the obligation
not to cause transboundary harm, and targets
like conservation of 11% of terrestrial areas
and inland waters through protected areas
by 2020.
It can also create procedural norms, such
as obligations to obtain prior informed consent
or conduct environmental impact assessments
for certain activities.
Not all of these norms are binding, but even
where they are not, they can create important
standards for governments and private actors.
The second function is administrative: international
law creates mechanisms such as international
bodies, processes, fora and funds for monitoring
and coordinating implementation of the standards.
This can include global bodies such as the
UN or multilateral bodies like river basin
organizations.
There can also be scientific bodies, such
as the IPCC.
The third function is adjudicative: international
law can provide mechanisms for resolving disputes
between countries.
This includes the international court of justice
and the international criminal court, but
also specific processes described in treaties
for managing disagreements.
So far we have discussed what international
law can do, but not what it looks like and
where it comes from.
There are three principal sources of international
law.
The first we have already mentioned: agreements.
These can have many names -- treaties, conventions,
pacts, etc.
Whatever they are called, they must be in
written form, and the parties must show an
intention to be bound.
The second source of international law is
customary international law.
Customary international law is legally binding,
even though it may not be found in a specific
binding treaty.
It is defined by two criteria: it must be
the general practice of states, and it must
be followed out of a sense of legal obligation.
There is often some discussion over whether
a particular principle has achieved the status
of customary law.
A well known example is the Law of the Sea,
which was based on customary international
law for centuries before its codification
in the 1980s.
The third source of international law is general
principles of law, which relates primarily
to procedure and today is mostly used to fill
gaps.
In addition to binding international law,
sometimes called “hard law”, there is
a world of international law that is not legally
binding but still carries some weight.
This is called “soft law”, and includes
non-binding declarations, resolutions, programs
of action, and memoranda of understanding.
Soft law can guide and influence the behavior
of states and other actors, and help coordination
around common principles and goals.
Soft law can also become hard law.
Soft law principles can be written into agreements.
Or, when soft law principles are followed
by States in practice, in a way that shows
acceptance of an obligation to be bound, they
can become customary international law.
In the next sequence we will look at specific
international conventions that are relevant
for environmental conservation.