In the last sequence, we discussed the purpose
of international law, what it looks like and
where it comes from.
In this sequence I want to discuss some specific
instruments of international law that are
relevant for conservation.
Global and regional agreements that address
environmental issues are often called “Multilateral
Environmental Agreements” or MEAs.
Most MEAs use the name “Convention”.
Some MEAs focus on a specific type of species
or ecosystem, such as the Ramsar Convention
on Wetlands of International Importance, Especially
as Waterfowl Habitat.
Others have a wider scope, like the Convention
on Biological Diversity, which provides a
broad framework for conservation.
Modern MEAs can have an extensive governance
structure.
At the core is the text of the Convention,
which contains legally binding obligations.
Sometimes the Convention Text includes Appendices
or Annexes that are more specific and easier
to modify than the main text.
For example, the Convention on the International
Trade in Endangered Species has three Appendices,
listing threatened or vulnerable species to
which varying levels of obligation apply.
Every two or three years, the Parties review
the lists of species in the Appendices and
decide whether to add or remove species.
A Convention may have one or more protocols.
These are additional agreements that are negotiated
under the auspices of the main agreement,
but may contain additional legally binding
obligations.
Parties to the Convention are not obligated
to join its Protocols, and often Protocols
have a smaller number of Members than the
parent Convention.
For example, the Convention on Biological
Diversity has two Protocols: the Cartagena
Protocol on Biosafety and the Nagoya Protocol
on Access and Benefit Sharing, both named
after the cities in which they were adopted.
The Cartagena Protocol even has a Protocol
of its own, the Nagoya-Kuala Lumpur Supplementary
Protocol on Liability and Redress.
MEAs normally set up a governance structure
to facilitate implementation.
The highest governing structure is the Conference
of the Parties, or COP, which usually is held
every few years.
Protocols have their own high level structure,
called the Meeting of the Parties or MOP.
The COP and MOP are typically held in the
same place, back to back or at the same time.
At the COP or MOP or COP/MOP, Parties come
together to make decisions about the interpretation
and implementation of the Convention.
They can adopt resolutions, decisions, plans
or strategies or modify the annexes or appendices,
or set up working groups or task forces to
investigate specific issues.
They can review and make decisions about financial
contributions and budget.
They can also direct the Secretariat to take
on particular programmes or tasks.
Which brings us to the Secretariat.
Almost all Conventions have a Secretariat,
responsible for managing and guiding the day
to day implementation work of the Convention
and its Protocols.
The Secretariat cannot make legally binding
decisions, but it can provide guidance and
support to Parties in implementing the Convention.