Now that we have a better sense of how MEAs
are set up, let’s talk about a few of the
MEAs that are important for conservation.
One of the key agreements is the Convention
on Biological Diversity, or CBD, which I’ve
already mentioned a few times.
The CBD is a framework convention – it creates
a broad set of principles and goals for biodiversity
conservation as well as structures for international
cooperation.
It sets out three key objectives: conservation
of biological diversity; the sustainable use
of its components; and the fair and equitable
sharing of benefits arising out of the utilization
of genetic resources.
Its two protocols provide more detailed obligations
relating to some of these objectives.
In 2010, the CBD COP adopted the Strategic
Plan for Biodiversity 2011-2020, including
the Aichi Targets.
The Aichi Targets are specific, measurable
goals to be achieved by 2020, across a range
of sectors.
For example, Target 11 states: “By 2020,
at least 17 per cent of terrestrial and inland
water, and 10 per cent of coastal and marine
areas, especially areas of particular importance
for biodiversity and ecosystem services, are
conserved through effectively and equitably
managed, ecologically representative and well
connected systems of protected areas and other
effective area-based conservation measures,
and integrated into the wider landscapes and
seascapes.”
Other targets focus on other biodiversity
challenges.
Target 6 addresses management and sustainable
use of fisheries.
Target 9 deals with invasive alien species.
Target 20 calls for mobilization of financial
resources, while Target 2 aims at integrating
biodiversity into development and planning
processes.
Let’s look at another agreement.
The Ramsar Convention was adopted two decades
before the CBD, in the 1970s.
It focuses on a specific habitat: wetlands.
Ramsar includes general obligations for wise
use of all wetlands within a country.
It also establishes a list of wetlands of
international importance, to which special
management and conservation obligations apply.
The World Heritage Convention also creates
a list.
The World Heritage List includes sites of
outstanding universal value.
Areas of exceptional natural beauty, outstanding
geological formations, significant ecosystems
and important natural habitats can all be
listed as World Heritage Sites.
It also creates obligations for Parties to
protect all cultural and natural heritage
in the country, whether or not it is on the
List.
Why would a country want to have a site listed
as a Ramsar site or a World Heritage site?
What are the benefits?
There is certainly a reputational benefit,
but there are also potential economic benefits
– a World Heritage site or Ramsar site might
attract more tourism, or more funding support.
Importantly, these international designations
do not protect the site by themselves.
Protection of these sites needs to be implemented
through national law, for example through
designating a site as a protected area, to
fulfil international obligations.
CITES – the Convention on International
Trade in Endangered Species – focuses on
a different aspect of conservation – addressing
international trade in species.
CITES lists species on three Appendices.
For species listed on Appendix I, like the
African Elephant, no international commercial
trade is allowed.
This means that any international trade in
elephant ivory violates CITES, with a few
exceptions, such as for ivory that predates
the Convention.
But remember, CITES only works if it is implemented
in national law.
Countries must create and enforce laws that
prohibit import and export of elephant ivory,
and effectively prosecute traffickers who
break those laws, for CITES to be effective.
The other two Appendices list species that
can be traded with appropriate permits.
Species listed on Appendix II, such as the
Hippopotamus, can only be traded with export
and import permits.
For species listed in Appendix III, such as
the Civet cat, only an export permit and a
certificate of origin are required.
The Appendices are reviewed regularly by the
COP, and species are added and moved.
To stay in compliance, countries must make
sure their national laws stay up to date.
One way to do this is to refer directly to
CITES in the national law.
For example, the Tanzania Wildlife Conservation
Act of 2009 states: “Any trade in violation
of CITES provisions is prohibited under this
Act and all specimens illegally traded shall
be confiscated.”
And translation into national law is only
the starting point: the law has to be enforced.
The Convention on the Conservation of Migratory
Species, or CMS, also includes Appendices
listing species, and the species listed under
CMS and those listed under CITES are not same.
CMS creates a framework for agreements and
Memoranda of Understanding among countries
where a particular species is found, or range
states.
It is intended to support coordination in
conservation of transboundary wildlife.
For example, the Gorilla Agreement aims to
conserve Gorillas across all ten range states
in Africa.
The UN Convention on the Law of the Non-Navigational
uses of International Watercourses also addresses
the problem of conservation of a transboundary
resource.
Like CMS, the UN Watercourses Convention creates
a framework and principles for agreements
among states that share a water basin.
There are other MEAs that we could discuss
here, at the global and regional levels.
The UN Convention on the Law of the Sea and
the UN Framework Convention on Climate Change
are particularly relevant.
And there are important regional agreements
such as the African Convention on Conservation
of Nature and Natural Resources, and regional
seas conventions, such as the Barcelona Convention
for the Protection of Marine Environment and
the Coastal Region of the Mediterranean.