In the last few sequences we have discussed
international environmental law, with a focus
on MEAs.
But these are not the only sources of law
relevant for conservation.
I want to talk about two other aspects of
international law: principles and human rights.
In a previous sequence, I introduced the concept
of customary international law.
A few key environmental principles have achieved
the status of customary international law,
meaning they are legally binding outside the
context of a particular convention.
One of the oldest recognized environmental
principles is the territorial principle, which
says, that States have “the sovereign right
to exploit their own resources pursuant to
their own environmental and developmental
policies, and the responsibility to ensure
that activities within their jurisdiction
or control do not cause damage to the environment
of other States or of areas beyond the limits
of national jurisdiction.”
In other words, a State can mostly do what
it wants within its territory as long as it
doesn’t hurt other States or areas outside
its territory.
Sometimes this is referred to as Principle
21, because it is clearly stated as the twenty-first
principle of the Stockholm Declaration of
1972.
The precautionary principle is another important
example.
This principle says that “where there are
threats of serious irreversible damage, lack
of full scientific certainty shall not be
used as a reason for postponing cost-effective
measures to prevent environmental degradation.”
Put another way, you can’t decide not to
try to prevent serious environmental damage
just because you’re not sure.
This principle is stated in the Rio Declaration
on Environment and Development of 1992.
A relatively new principle recognized in international
law is the principle of intergenerational
equity, which describes an obligation on present
generations to act as custodians of the earth
for future generations.
The last topic I want to address in the context
of international law is human rights.
Human rights, like international principles,
may be part of customary international law,
though they can be stated in international
agreements such as the International Covenant
on Civil and Political Rights or the African
Charter of Human and Peoples’ Rights.
Human rights can also be stated in declarations,
such as the Universal Declaration of Human
Rights.
The definitions of human rights are elaborated
and clarified by human rights tribunals, such
as the African Commission on Human and Peoples’
Rights and the Inter-American Court of Human
Rights.
Many well established human rights are closely
related to conservation of the environment.
In some cases, protection of the right to
life requires addressing environmental harms
that create lethal threats.
The European Court of Human Rights has found
that governments have a duty to address serious
environmental threats, from “any activity,
whether public or not, in which the right
to life may be at stake.”
The Inter-American Court on Human Rights has
found that the human right to life is implicated
“where environmental contamination and degradation
pose a persistent threat to human life and
health.”
Human rights are often invoked in cases involving
indigenous peoples.
Multiple international instruments recognize
peoples’ rights to self-determination and
control over their natural wealth and resources.
Development in their territory, and particularly
removal of a people from their territory requires
their free, prior informed consent.
This has also been connected to rights to
property.
The African Commission on Human and Peoples’
Rights has found that indigenous peoples have
rights to ownership over their traditional
land, and that States should take special
measures to secure such ownership.
There is an emerging discussion of a human
right to a clean and healthy environment.
Such a right could include procedural and
substantive components.
On the procedural side, it could incorporate
rights related to access to information, public
participation and access to justice.
On the substantive side, it could include
obligations to meet minimum standards for
environmental quality.
The questions of whether such a right exists
and what content it might contain are being
investigated by the UN Special Rapporteur.