Law is only effective if it is implemented,
and its rules, processes and obligations are
followed and upheld.
Making sure this happens is part of what we
call “Compliance and Enforcement.”
Compliance means adherence to legal rules
by the regulated entities.
Enforcement refers to measures to compel compliance.
Compliance does not always require enforcement.
A lot of times compliance is completely voluntary.
I don’t cross the street when the light
is red, not because I’m afraid of getting
arrested, but because I’m afraid of getting
hit by a car.
Or because of social pressure to comply.
I don’t attack other people because I don’t
want to and it seems wrong, not because I’m
afraid of going to jail.
And in some cases, I comply with a law just
because it’s the law and it seems like a
reasonable and legitimate law that I see no
reason to break.
However, voluntary compliance is not always
enough.
This is where enforcement comes in.
There are a few different models for compliance
and enforcement.
One model is based on the idea that most people
comply with law most of the time, as long
as the law seems legitimate and fair, and
compliance is relatively easy.
This is called the normative model.
Under this model, compliance and enforcement
measures should ensure that the system seems
fair and just, and help people comply.
The second model assumes that people are rational,
and will decide whether to comply or not by
weighing the costs and benefits involved.
Compliance and enforcement measures can improve
compliance by changing the cost-benefit analysis.
If it is more expensive, more dangerous, and
more difficult to break the law than to comply
with it, fewer people will choose not to comply.
This is called the rational model.
There are two sides to this cost-benefit calculation:
the costs of breaking the law should be higher
than the benefits lawbreakers get.
Flipped around, the benefits of compliance
with the law should be higher than the costs
of complying.
This gives us four basic approaches to improving
compliance through the cost-benefit model.
The first approach is to lower the cost of
compliance, by making it easy and cheap to
comply.
This requires making sure that everyone knows
how to comply – that they know what the
law is and what is expected of them.
For example, protected areas should be clearly
demarcated, and neighboring communities should
understand what activities are permitted where.
In addition, compliance should not impose
an undue burden.
Where a community entirely depends on activities
within a protected area for their livelihoods,
legally prohibiting these activities without
providing alternatives will probably result
in extensive non-compliance.
Addressing this will require considering the
needs of the community and how they can be
met while achieving conservation goals.
The second approach to improving compliance
is to increase the benefits of compliance,
through incentives such as subsidies, tax
exemptions, information or technical support.
One of the best ways to improve compliance
is to give people a share in the benefits
of conservation, so that they have a direct
stake in making sure it is successful.
Involving communities and other affected stakeholders
directly in management and regulation can
have this result.
A third approach is reducing the benefits
of non-compliance.
You may have heard the phrase, “crime doesn’t
pay”.
Unfortunately, non-compliance often does pay,
so reducing that payout can go a long way
to improving compliance.
One way to do this is by cutting down demand
for unsustainably sourced products like ivory
and rosewood.
Where environmental harm is driven by international
markets, as is frequently the case, demand
reduction can require transnational cooperation
and significant action on the part of importing
countries.
However, demand reduction can also be an effective
tactic at the local level, where unsustainable
products are headed for domestic markets.
For example, increasing availability of sustainable
energy can reduce demand for illegally harvested
charcoal.
Where the demand that is driving biodiversity
loss is local, it is important to understand
the local needs and acceptable sustainable
alternatives.
A final approach to improving compliance under
the rational model is increasing the cost
of non-compliance directly, through criminal
prosecution or administrative and civil measures
for enforcement.
Enforcement can serve three basic functions.
The first is punishment or retribution.
This can improve compliance under the normative
model, by making the system seem just.
Excessive or disproportionate punishment can
undermine this function, and make law seem
less legitimate.
A second function is direct prevention, by
making sure that the target of enforcement
cannot violate the law again.
It does this by putting the violator in prison
or taking away the means to carry out the
activity by confiscating equipment, revoking
licenses, or destroying financial means by
imposing fines.
Direct prevention makes the most difference
when targeting the biggest players causing
the most harm.
Removing a single poacher may not significantly
reduce noncompliance where there are a thousand
others to take their place.
However, removing a kingpin of a criminal
organization can have a significant effect
on the illegal market as a whole.
The third function of enforcement is deterrence.
Punishing violators sends a message to other
violators that if they break the law, the
consequences will outweigh the potential benefit.
This function might be the most important
function of enforcement, but it is also the
hardest to prove.
To be an effective deterrent, enforcement
must be consistent, and the penalties must
be sufficiently high to change the cost-benefit
calculation.
The risk of being caught times the cost of
punishment must be higher than the benefit
of noncompliance.
Compliance and enforcement works a little
bit differently at the international level.
When countries don’t comply with their obligations,
we can’t really put them in jail.
But there are ways to promote and facilitate
compliance with international obligations,
and resolve disputes that arise between countries.
Even though international law often doesn’t
have a global enforcement mechanism, like
a global judiciary, States usually comply
with it.
Compliance with international law takes place
for many reasons: reputation, reciprocity,
benefits of compliance, or high cost of non-compliance.
Like individuals, States may comply because
they feel the law is legitimate and fair or
because when they ratify an agreement this
entails a normative obligation they cannot
ignore.
The international order depends on the principle
of “pacta sunt servanda” under which international
treaties must be honored and states must comply
with them.
Nevertheless, not all States always comply
with international law.
International agreements can provide a limited
range of enforcement mechanisms including
penalties such as trade sanctions or withdrawal
of eligibility to participate in the mechanisms
of the treaty.
Many international treaties include dispute
resolution mechanisms, such as provisions
for arbitration, mediation or referral of
disputes to the International Court of Justice.
The International Court of Justice is the
judicial organ of the United Nations and the
most preeminent international court.
The Court’s role is to settle, in accordance
with international law, legal disputes submitted
to it by States and to give advisory opinions
on legal questions referred to it by the UN
and its specialized agencies.
According to the Article 94 (1) of the UN
Charter “each Member of the United Nations
undertakes to comply with the decisions of
the ICJ in any case to which it is a party”,
therefore, all judgments of the ICJ are binding.
Nevertheless, the ICJ has some flaws: Currently,
only 73 States have accepted the jurisdiction
of the Court.
Moreover, the ICJ has no power to enforce
its resolutions by itself – this power is
held by the UN Security Council, whose Permanent
Members have the right to veto any decision
or recommendation of the Court in which they
are allegedly responsible.
Most importantly, a case can only be heard
by the ICJ if the countries have given their
consent for the Court to hear it.
It is important to remember that at both the
national and international level the objective
of compliance measures is to improve compliance.
The goal is not to put more poachers in jail
or impose more international sanctions, but
to create a world where there is less poaching
and less violation of international law.
Enforcement measures can help with this, by
creating deterrence or promoting a sense of
fairness and justice, but the ultimate goal
is a world where all people and countries
follow their obligations to value and respect
nature and natural resources.