Hello, and welcome to this first module of
our MOOC on Law enforcement.
It will be presented to you by Lydia Slobodian,
Legal officer at the IUCN Environmental Law
Center in Bonn, Germany.
The goal of this module is to help us better
understand the laws and regulations that apply
to protected areas conservation.
We will look at where they come from, and
what their nature, scopes, limits and uses
are.
This topic is indeed important so the module
will be quite long.
Let’s have a look at the topics we are going
to cover.
First, we will see what Law is.
What form it takes.
What it is used for.
Then, we will try to understand its utility
and uses for conservation.
We will look at the connection between law
and protected area governance, and of course,
we will see the importance of good governance.
Then, we will look at the translation of law
into applicable regulations for conservation.
The ones that apply to certain geographical
territories such as protected areas.
The ones that focus on the species found on
these territories.
Finally, we will talk about the regulations
that cover the activities that take place
there.
We will then change scales to look at international
laws, what they are, what they bring, what
their importance is, and where they come from.
Then, we’ll quickly cover some international
agreements on the environment and see how
they work.
Among these, we will talk about the ones that
directly concern protected areas like the
CBD, the Ramsar or world heritage conventions,
the CITES and the CMS which we already talked
about in the MOOC on PA management.
We will quickly cover the principles and rights
that go alongside global laws, like the principles
of precaution or sovereignty, and more generally
human rights.
We will finish with a sequence on the principles
of law enforcement, an excellent introduction
to the next modules.
Of course, you can go deeper into all these
notions by reading the recommended documents.
Do the quizzes between sequences, or join
the conversation with other participants on
the platform or on our Facebook page, it will
certainly help you.
There, have an excellent first module !