Law is one of the most effective tools we
have to influence behavior, coordinate action
and achieve public goals, such as conservation.
But what is law?
Law is a body of rules governing human conduct,
recognized as binding, and enforced by a public
authority.
Law is different from morality and ethics.
I may think that it is immoral to eat meat,
or lie to your spouse, or cut to the front
of the line, but in most countries these actions
are not prohibited by law.
They are not enforced by a public authority.
At the same time, not all action by public
authority is lawful.
A corrupt policeman may put me in jail for
refusing to pay a bribe – this is not supported
by law.
Law takes many forms and exists at many levels,
from international law – including treaties,
principles and conventions – to national
law – including statutes, regulations and
judicial decisions – to local or community
law – including municipal codes and community
bylaws.
Not all law is written down.
In some places, religious codes or customary
rules have legal force.
For example, in many countries Sharia – Islamic
law – exists alongside statutory law, or
is incorporated into the statutory system.
In these countries, Sharia courts can judge
cases and order punishments.
In other places, customary authorities, such
as village chiefs or tribal councils have
lawmaking power.
Some places have many different types of law,
from different legal sources.
Depending on where I live, I may be subject
to national legislation, religious mandates,
local ordinances and tribal rules, all at
the same time.
This is called Legal Pluralism.
Laws also have a hierarchy, which determines
the order in which they are applied, and what
happens when they conflict.
Different laws are at different levels in
this hierarchy, sometimes called the Kelsenian
Pyramid.
The highest level of law in a country is almost
always the Constitution.
Lower levels in the pyramid may include general
legislation, special legislation and bylaws
and regulations.
If provisions contained in a specific regulation
contradict the text of a law, the regulation
will be declared null or invalid.
If a law contradicts the content of the National
Constitution, this law will also be considered
invalid.
Law performs many functions.
Substantive law creates rights and obligations.
It tells you what you can do and what you
can’t, what rights you have to your things
and your property, and even what taxes you
owe.
Procedural law creates processes within the
legislative, judicial and administrative systems.
It tells you how to get a driver’s license
or file a complaint or defend yourself if
you are arrested or sued.
It also gives judges, policemen, officials
and other government actors rules to follow
as they do their job.
Law affects every facet of life.
It creates the basic structures of government,
and the basic rights of people.
It regulates businesses, organizations, families
and individuals.
It determines how the State spends its money.
And, most importantly for our purposes, law
sets out tools, processes and frameworks for
conservation.