Law is an essential tool for conservation.
It sets up the basic framework in which conservation
operates, as well as processes for decision-making,
planning and management.
Law provides direct tools for conservation,
such as regulation of certain activities,
or requirements for protection in certain
areas.
Law also provides incentives for conservation,
such as subsidies or tax credits for certain
types of land use.
Many different types of laws are important
for conservation.
These include laws governing particular ecosystems,
such as wetlands, forests, lakes, seas, drylands
and coastal areas.
Also laws governing specific sectors, such
as mining, agriculture, water and fishing.
They include protected areas laws, biodiversity
laws, and framework laws for conservation.
And laws that recognize indigenous rights,
community rights and other rights related
to the environment.
As well as laws that address harmful activities,
such as rules for environmental impact assessments
and pollution and chemical regulations.
Also land use, property, tax and trade laws.
Even criminal law is relevant for conservation.
Another important set of laws, are laws that
define the structure of government, create
processes for decision-making and establish
procedural rules for resolving disputes.
Specific types of regulation will be discussed
later.
But it is important to remember that regulation
is only one way that law can support conservation.