Governance is a key part of conservation that
is closely associated with law.
So what is governance?
Governance can be defined as “The interactions
among structures, processes and traditions
that determine how power and responsibilities
are exercised, how decisions are taken and
how citizens or other stakeholders have their
say.”
Law creates the basic frameworks and tools
for governance.
In other words, law creates the rules for
exercising power and authority and ensuring
accountability.
Governance also describes processes for making
and implementing laws.
Many actors are involved in these processes.
We can talk about two dimensions of governance:
governance type and governance quality.
There are different types of governance system,
depending on who makes decisions and how.
For example, in the context of protected areas,
there are four main types of governance:
First, governance by government describes
a situation where the government makes decisions
and exercises authority.
This does not mean there is no participation
of relevant stakeholders or the public, but
the final decision rests with the government.
The legal framework designates and empowers
the appropriate government agency, and creates
processes and guidelines for decision-making
and management.
It determines the amount of discretion the
government agency can exercise in carrying
out its mandate.
Second, private governance describes governance
by a private entity, such as an individual,
corporation or private association.
Around the world there are many examples of
private protected areas.
Often these are the result of private landowners
voluntarily committing their land for conservation,
for altruistic or business reasons, and seeking
the appropriate designation and support.
Private protected areas are most effective
when recognized by law.
Clear and specific legal provisions should
provide frameworks and standards for private
conservation activities.
Legal recognition of private protected areas
creates both incentives and accountability
for voluntary conservation.
A third form of governance is governance by
indigenous peoples or local communities.
Indigenous peoples and local communities may
have ownership or governance rights over their
territory as a matter of law, set out in the
constitution, national legislation, or a treaty
with the national government.
Alternatively, the government may delegate
governance of a specific area to an indigenous
community through a contract or regulation.
In some cases, indigenous peoples or local
communities exercise de facto governance over
territory where they do not have formally
recognized rights, but like private governance,
indigenous or community governance is most
effective when it is strongly backed by law.
Finally, a significant amount of conservation
governance today is shared governance.
Governance authority may be shared between
a state and a private entity, indigenous or
local community, or another state.
These arrangements should be legally formalized
with clear definition of how power is shared
and how decisions will be made.
There are certain basic standards that apply
to all types of governance.
We call these the elements of good governance.
There is no universally agreed definition
of good governance, but in general it is governance
that demonstrates fairness, legitimacy and
accountability.
Key requirements for good governance include
participation, transparency, predictability,
equity and access to justice.
Good governance is closely associated with
the concept of rule of law.
Good governance is predicated on legal frameworks
that contain strong and appropriate substantive
and procedural elements.
Law should protect and respect human rights
and principles of non-discrimination and fairness.
For example, many constitutions list fundamental
rights such as the right to property or the
right to equal treatment regardless of religion,
race or gender.
Law should also create processes and obligations
to ensure transparency and provide opportunities
for meaningful participation and use of the
legal system.
For example, national legislation often provides
for access to government information, or requires
a notice and comment period for new government
rules.
Some people are beginning to discuss a third
dimension of governance: governance vitality.
Governance vitality would go beyond the requirements
of good governance, and describe the wisdom,
vision, adaptability and resilience of governance
actors and processes.