Law does not just tell us what to do and what
not to do.
It also creates and manages a system of rights
and obligations.
A right is a legal entitlement.
It creates a corresponding obligation or duty
on the part of others to respect that entitlement.
Some rights are human rights, which are recognized
as fundamental by the international community,
no matter what national law says.
The rights to life, to free speech, and to
freedom from discrimination are human rights.
Other rights are recognized in national law
or private contracts.
I have rights to the things that I own, rights
to act in certain ways, and rights to make
certain decisions.
These rights may be limited, and I may be
able to sell them or give them away.
Typically, I cannot use my rights in a way
that violates the rights of others.
I have a right to move my arm around in a
big circle, but I do not have a right to do
so if it would hit my friend in the face.
In conservation, one of the most relevant
categories of rights is property rights.
When we think about property, we often think
about ownership.
But in reality, property rights are much more
complex.
We can understand them as a bundle of sticks,
where each stick represents a different right.
One stick is a right to access the property;
one stick is a right to exclude others.
One stick is a right to use the resources
on the property; another is a right to sell
it.
There is the right to live there, and the
right to develop.
Different people may have rights to the same
property.
One person may have the right to farm the
property, while another has a right to cross
over the property to get to his pasture or
field.
The property itself may be owned by a third
person, or by the state.
Closely connected to the concept of property
rights is the concept of tenure.
Tenure describes the way in which people or
groups gain and hold rights relating to land
or other resources.
For example, a person may rent or lease land
for a specified time – this type of tenure
is called a leasehold.
Or they may buy some or all rights to the
property – this is called freehold.
A person or group may have rights to a property
through custom or traditional use – this
can be referred to as customary tenure.
Rights may even be allocated by the government
based on necessity or need.
Tenure can be public or private, individual
or communal.
Tenure rules can come from different legal
orders, and there can be problems where tenure
rules established by one regime are not recognized
by another – for example, where tenure from
customary law is not recognized in statutory
law.
Property rights are not the only type of rights
that are important for conservation.
There are rights related to specific resources,
such as water, mineral and fishing rights.
There are also rights relating to participation,
information and access to justice: these are
key to good governance.
And there are many important human rights,
including emerging rights to a healthy environment,
that we will discuss later.