When we talk about law, we also need to talk
about institutions.
Institutions are involved in making and implementing
law at every level.
There are different types of institutions
involved in law and governance.
Sometimes these are classified as legislative,
executive and judicial institutions.
Legislative institutions create law.
At the national level, a congress or parliament
might be the legislative institution.
At the local level, a city, community or tribal
council can perform legislative functions.
Executive institutions implement and enforce
law.
The chief executive of a country is normally
the president or prime minister.
Government ministries and agencies, including
law enforcement agencies and prosecutors,
are also part of the executive branch.
Judicial institutions, namely courts, interpret
law and resolve disputes.
Courts can exist at different levels and in
different types of legal system, and they
may have authority, or jurisdiction, over
different subjects.
The lines between legislative, executive and
judicial institutions are often blurred.
Executive institutions can create legal rules
through agency regulation, described below.
Judicial courts also create law, particularly
in common law countries where judicial decisions
have precedential value.
Institutional responsibility may be divided
by sector, particularly within the executive.
There may be different agencies responsible
for agriculture, water, forests, fisheries,
etc.
This can create problems, particularly where
environmental systems or challenges implicate
more than one sector.
For example, a mangrove forest may come under
the authority of forest, coastal, marine,
or freshwater agencies; or may fall into a
gap where no agency gives it enough attention.