As discussed previously, law performs many
functions in relation to conservation, from
creating rules for judicial proceedings to
setting up the basic structures of government.
But one of the most important and familiar
examples of environmental law is regulation
of activities that affect biodiversity and
natural resources.
There are many different types of regulation.
Two main categories of regulation are “command
and control” regulation and “market-based”
regulation.
“Command and control” regulation works
by directly prohibiting or imposing requirements
on activities.
Command and control regulation states what
is allowed and what is not allowed, and establishes
punishments for violating the rules.
“Market-based” regulation operates differently.
It tries to create enabling frameworks or
market conditions where certain activities
are more or less desirable or profitable.
Market-based regulation can use tools like
subsidies and taxes, or tax breaks.
Tradeable permits are also considered a type
of market-based mechanism.
Regulation can come directly from legislation.
For example, national legislation might state
that it is illegal to kill endangered species
or drain wetlands.
But often the specific rules that apply to
individuals and corporations are fleshed out
through regulations created by government
agencies to implement the legislation.
Permitting processes, quotas, descriptions
of regulated activities, and lists of protected
species are often found in agency regulations.
These agency regulations are usually easier
to change than the framework legislation.
This makes them more flexible and adaptable
to circumstances.
For example, if a species becomes more vulnerable,
it can be subject to stronger levels of protection
through regulation, and vice versa.
Creating or changing regulations usually requires
a participatory rulemaking process.
For example, there may be a requirement that
new rules are subject to a “notice and comment”
period, when they are publicly posted and
available for comment.
This is an important time for civil society
and concerned individuals to express their
views on the new regulations.
The regulating body may be required to take
public comment into account in reviewing the
regulations.
In some cases, specific permitting processes
are also subject to requirements for public
notice and comment.
Regulations may be based on geographical area,
species, or type of activity or threat.
Specific types of regulation will be discussed
next.