Area-based regulations apply to a particular
geographical space, that you can point to
or draw on a map.
Protected areas are a primary tool for area-based
regulation.
Law regulates access to protected areas, use
of protected areas and their resources, and
activities that threaten their conservation
objectives.
For example, a law might regulate hunting,
possession of a firearm, or destruction of
habitat in a protected area.
In some cases law can prohibit entry into
a protected area altogether.
How activities are regulated depends on international
obligations, conservation objectives and the
protected area category of a specific site.
For example, in a strictly protected area,
only scientific research or cultural activities
might be permitted or authorized.
Other activities might be prohibited.
In protected landscapes or seascapes, more
activities may be authorized or allowed with
a permit, including sustainable agriculture,
fishing or harvesting of forest products.
Different regulations may apply to different
zones within a single protected site.
Area-based regulation is not limited to protected
areas – it can also promote connectivity
through conservation between and around protected
areas, and conservation at the landscape level.
Spatial planning or land use planning and
zoning can be tools for area-based regulation
both within and outside protected areas.
Legislation can create systems of permits
or concessions for activities such as mining,
logging or tourism.
Environmental impact assessment requirements
are an important tool in making decisions
on whether to allow activities in a particular
space.
Market-based measures, such as tax credits
for sustainable private land use, or direct
payments for ecosystem services can also be
used for area-based conservation.
Area-based regulation may be provided for
in national protected areas legislation, or
land use legislation.
It may also be based on forest law, wildlife
conservation law or a framework biodiversity
act.
Marine and coastal areas, as well as wetlands
may be subject to special regulations.