Most countries have laws providing for protection
of specific species.
They may use different tools, from incentives
for habitat conservation to criminalization
of exploitation or trade.
But the common thread is that this type of
regulation defines what is permitted or prohibited
in terms of the species involved, rather than
where the activity takes place.
One of the most heavily regulated activities
involving species is “taking”.
Taking includes hunting, killing, catching,
gathering, fishing, poisoning, harvesting,
snaring, cutting, plucking or removing all
or part of a member of a protected species.
It may include harassing, disturbing or otherwise
harming a species or its eggs.
In some jurisdictions, actions that cause
a protected plant or animal to die, such as
use of pesticide, can also be considered a
taking.
Taking of strictly protected or endangered
species is often entirely prohibited, and
in many cases it is a crime.
More common species may be subject to different
regulatory requirements.
A hunting or fishing license may be required,
or hunting may only be allowed in certain
seasons.
Regulations may establish quotas for the number
of specimen that can be removed.
The size and gender of the specimen may be
regulated.
For example, regulations could only allow
taking of fish over 12 inches long, or male
deer.
This is to protect the natural reproductive
and growth cycle of the population.
Even for strictly protected populations, some
taking may be allowed under specific circumstances.
Traditional use by indigenous or local communities
may be allowed.
Or trophy hunting under controlled conditions
and subject to strict quotas may be used to
generate revenue for conservation.
In addition to regulating taking of species,
laws can also regulate possession, processing,
or transport of protected species.
This type of regulation helps address taking
along the trade chain.
It facilitates enforcement, as it is usually
easier to prove possession than to prove that
someone killed a particular specimen.
It also addresses the problem that the people
and organizations most responsible for loss
of species are not always the people holding
the gun.
Like taking, possession of a specimen or part
of an endangered species can be a criminal
offence.
When people hear this, they often ask, “but
what if it isn’t mine?
What if someone puts something in my bag and
I’m caught with it – can I go to jail?”
Usually the law takes this into consideration.
Possession requires both physical possession
– corpus – and intention to possess – animus.
In short, you can’t be convicted of possessing
something if you don’t know you have it.
The second question is a little harder: “What
if I have something, but I don’t know it’s
illegal?”
This is the scenario of the hapless tourist
who buys a piece of ivory or conch shell at
a market, or the subsistence hunter who shoots
the wrong type of antelope.
In this case the legal question is more complicated,
but there is a general principle in many jurisdictions
that ignorance of the law is no excuse!
A third category of species-based regulation
relates to trade.
Many jurisdictions regulate selling, offering
for sale, supplying, buying, bartering, trading
and even donation of products or specimens
of protected species.
This type of regulation can cover domestic
or international trade.
In the case of international trade, legislation
can create a system of permits or certificates
for import or export of protected species.
These do not need to be species that are native
to the regulating country, but can apply to
imported species.
The US Lacey Act, for example, provides that
it is unlawful to trade in wildlife “taken,
possessed, transported, or sold in violation
of any law or regulation of any State or in
violation of any foreign law.”
Sometimes, the list of species subject to
regulation may need to change, depending on
the vulnerability of different species.
The list of protected species may be regularly
updated by a government agency.
It may incorporate by reference an international
list, such as the IUCN Red List or species
listed under the Convention on the International
Trade in Endangered Species.
Listing or delisting a species may be subject
to a regulatory process that provides opportunities
for public consultation.
It is important for agents involved in enforcement
and the judicial process to be up to date
and have the capacity to correctly identify
protected species.
Enforcement can be easiest when all taking
or possession of a specific species is prohibited.
When some taking is permitted subject to regulations,
it is vital to be able to distinguish between
legally and illegally taken specimens.
This can be facilitated by requirements for
certificates or other appropriate documentation.
But there can always be problems of forged
certificates or permits, or exceeding allowed
quotas.