- Hello Philippe.
- Hello Geoffroy
- Here we are at the beginning of the module
on work ethics.
In a MOOC like this one, on law enforcement,
why is it important to talk about ethics?
- The idea here is to use a form of training
widely conducted in police academies.
It is more than just studying laws and identifying
what is authorized or not.
In normal circumstances, the agent in charge
of enforcing laws and regulations knows perfectly
well if he is facing an offender.
He also knows if he is acting like a professional,
within the legal framework.
- If each agent or manager already has the
tools to act lawfully, what are ethics for?
- Human beings are confronted with temptations,
frustrations and desires.
They are also bound by their education, their
social status, their culture and their environment,
and these elements can make them question
or doubt the laws in place.
At this point, the fact of knowing that a
behaviour is unlawful isn’t enough to help
them overcome their problem.
They need to find answers elsewhere.
This is why an ethical reflection is relevant
in addition to simply studying laws and regulations.
- So basically ethics add a philosophical
dimension to law enforcement?
- Exactly.
It also helps realize why we do certain things
or not, why we took a certain direction instead
of another.
It is obviously very relevant for people in
justice careers, where representatives are
given great power to be used with discernment,
for the common good and not for personal benefit.
- In relation to justice, how do work ethics
come into play?
P - For many years, I worked as senior officer
of criminal police in Switzerland and was
trained on the issue in the US at the FBI
Academy in Quantico, Virginia.
- In 2004, an organizational reform of police
training in Switzerland introduced a course
on work ethics to the basic training for policemen.
Based on my American experience and along
with other specialists in the field, we developed
a course approved at a national level.
- A course in which work ethics plays an important
role I suppose?
- During the training year, no less than 28
sessions are devoted to ethics alone.
As a complement, they are coupled with classes
on human rights covering 16 sessions.
Over the years, police students have become
increasingly aware of these topics.
While in 2004 many people were still quite
opposed to them, the new generation is very
open as they understand the stakes.
Behaviours are changing…
- So specifically, what are we going to see
in this module?
- “What must I do?”
– This is the first question we’ll be
asking ourselves.
- Then, we’ll define ethics more precisely
and position it in relation with other notions
like deontology, values, norms etc.
- After this, we’ll be looking at the principles
governing ethics,
- and we’ll talk about drafting codes and
charters to translate them into actions.
- Finally, we’ll consider the dilemmas that
can emerge when we move away from ethics.
- Many useful concepts to master… this should
be a great week.