Let’s start by determining why the legal
aspect of official agents’ activity within
a state or a semi-public organisation is essential.
Every worker, regardless of his field, acquires
technical knowledge that is specific to his
activity.
This stems from his specific vocational training,
and his likely previous vocational and academic
training.
This knowledge is required to complete the
tasks of a profession by respecting existing
standards.
It is called professional expertise.
Besides purely professional skills, some professions
also require the development of social skills.
These refer to the interaction between the
job in question and the impact on other members
of society, other citizens.
These interactions with the society in which
the workers grow can become problematic as
soon as they move away from professional standards
or adopt improper behaviours.
Everyone must be able to recognize the possible
faults committed by their colleagues, but
could also be tempted to adopt improper behaviours.
For these reasons, the reflection on work
ethics along with deontology were developed
over the past couple of years in all fields
of work.
In this MOOC, we will focus on activities
related to law enforcement in general, and
to protected areas in particular.
This touches on the work done by people with
specific powers (surveillance, arrest, search,
receiving fines, using force etc.).
They are mainly policemen, military and paramilitary
officers, forest guards, eco-guards, administrative
officials and private security agents.
The goal is to promote responsible behaviour
in the agent when confronted with real situations.
This is done by using practical examples to
reduce risks of behavioural blunders and mistakes,
but without always being able to eliminate
them completely.
Indeed, agents’ activity isn’t made of
theory or statistics, but of real actions.
In this framework, he must recognize the situations
where they can proceed, and the ones requiring
them to stop and think.
The type of responsible behaviour we are looking
for is influenced by many factors.
First, education received by parents is key.
The cultural environment, religious beliefs
and social background also play a role.
These influencing factors are permanently
set in the agent’s mind, consciously or
not, and mould an individual’s personal
values.
Professionally speaking, this same agent will
also be bound by the norms of his profession,
and by the values of his professional environment.
We will explain this in the next sequence.
These norms and values can be in contradiction
with his personal values.
In certain situations, the agent will have
to ask himself the central question of work
ethics: what must I do?
Let’s break down this important question.
First of all, you have to know the context
in which the question arises.
Our latitude of action must be known and defined,
either by ourselves or by our hierarchy.
This latitude is defined by our rights and
obligations as a citizen, a member of a community
or as a professional.
Finally, it must be clear that in the question
"What must I do" there is the word “must”.
This means that if you are a public official
with a mission, you must act, you have to
do so.
An official is indeed paid to take action.
DO, sure, but what?
In fact, once the obligation to take action
is recognized and accepted, the norms and
values in play allow to give a more concrete
answer to the question “what”?
The answer could then be: I don’t do anything.
Because the circumstances lead me to abstain
from any action.
For example, if a direct intervention can
result in aggravating a situation rather than
in solving it.
But this decision must derive from a consideration
on our latitude that I can justify with the
relevant norms and values.
The same goes when we decide to proceed with
concrete action.
In the next sequence, we will be going deeper
into the topic by suggesting structured ways
of thinking that allow to make a decision
but also to explain the reasons for it.