In the previous sequence, we’ve seen that
to give an answer to the question “what
must I do”, values and norms must be put
into perspective, which will lead to a full
ethical reflexion.
So now is the time to give a couple of definitions.
Ethics.
It is the thought process that allows to solve
situations in which values and/or norms are
in conflict.
For instance, some professional decisions
can have consequences in the private sphere,
if the people involved are close to us.
Deontology.
It intends to set the minimal standards of
a profession.
Access to the profession in question should
be forbidden if those minimal standards aren’t
met.
For instance, a deontological code could determine
if a public agent has the right to accept
gifts in kind for personal use.
Values.
These are notions or terms describing goals
to reach according to a group, an organisation,
a profession or a corporation’s ideals.
However, values aren’t accompanied with
rules to follow.
Everyone can achieve their ideal in different
ways.
Loyalty, professionalism and honesty are common
examples of ideals.
Norms.
They are texts gathered in laws, by-laws,
codes or any other form of document that authorises,
forbids, obliges or orders.
Norms determine the rules to follow and the
possible penalties if they aren’t respected.
The penal code is a norm.
Traffic laws as well.
Charters or codes.
Generally speaking, organisations want to
communicate about their proper functioning,
agents’ good quality of work and the service
they provide to the population.
To do so, they can publish their driving norms
and values in codes or charters.
This is when we talk about deontological code,
the charter of core values, the code of ethics
and so on.
A code of ethics seeks to define the ideal
of a profession by listing common values all
those who practice the profession are supposed
to adhere to.
A deontological code is a regulatory basis
that sets the basic requirements to practice
an occupation.
Not respecting the elements of such a code
can lead to administrative penalties and even
dismissal.
Let’s quickly get back to some of the values
that are usually recognised for a security
organisation.
Loyalty is often mentioned, as well as professionalism,
fairness, faithfulness, honesty and integrity.
These are professional values.
*At the same time, a person’s personality
is fashioned by his education, his social
environment and possible religion, which produce
his personal value system.
The same words previously mentioned are by
the way often encountered there: loyalty,
faithfulness and honesty.
However, these words don’t necessarily cover
the same notions.
Among the norms, you can discriminate between
formal and informal norms.
Formal norms are the ones that are clearly
announced, formalised and written down.
Informal norms are supposed to be known within
a group, a family, a corporation, without
having to be formulated.
These different notions are connected to each
other as it is widely accepted that:
Ethics are the basis of the law.
Deontology is a discipline of ethics.Deontology
is a norm.
It must respect the law and handle ethical
issues that haven’t been solved by the law.
Let’s get back to our question: “What
must I do?”
Most of the time, the question brings an immediate
response without requiring deep reflection.
We’ll see in the next sequence how personal
and professional values can be in conflict,
how they complicate answering the question
“What must I do?”.
At that point, we will be at the very heart
ethical reflexion.