There is plenty of literature on work ethics,
especially on security services like the police
or the army.
Many authors have developed concepts or principles
on how these organisations function.
We will be looking at the governance of a
state or semi-public organisation based on
the principles exposed by Cohen and Fledberg
in this book.
The authors consider 5 principles that must
guide the governance of a police organisation,
describing them as the 5 moral standards a
security organisation must follow.
This can perfectly apply to the sovereign
structure of a protected area.
According to the authors, the 5 principles
make up a form of social contract between
the population and the security organisation:
Fair access to government services.
This means each individual, citizen and litigant
must have access to services provided by the
dedicated structure.
The response given must be the same for all.
In all cases, the citizen’s approach must
be taken into account.
Public trust.
When the population grants specific power
to a security organisation, it must have the
guarantee, based on laws and regulations,
that the organisation will be used in the
interest of all and not for the benefit of
a few.
Public safety and security.
Protection of goods and people is the goal
to achieve.
It is the common asset to preserve.
Abuses that come along trying to reach this
goal are just as damageable as the omission
to take care of it.
Teamwork – Cooperation with all the partners.
A security organisation is only part of the
problem resolution chain.
It cannot act alone and must collaborate with
the population in the general sense, namely
with the local authorities, the judicial order,
political authorities, education officials
and so on.
*Objectivity.
Any action of a security organisation’s
agent must be driven by the target to meet,
without giving way to favouritism, discrimination
or negligence.
Now that we’ve established the 5 principles,
we can define communication actions that will
make the organisation more transparent to
the population, that will instil confidence
in its interventions and valorise the agents’
actions.
Now let’s see what concrete communication
actions can be taken.
Fair access to government services.
For such a principle to be adopted by the
entire organisation, rules must be set, and
for the population to know these rules, they
must be published.
A deontological code tells agents what their
rights and obligations are, and what the minimal
requirements are that habilitate them to practise
their profession.
By having access to this code, the population
will have a clear idea of what they can obtain
from the relevant institution.
Public trust.
Safety and security.
This is about managing the latitude given
to agents when exercising their given power.
Professionally speaking, agents must undergo
structured training, especially when it comes
to the use of force or coercion.
In the same way, leaders must manage staff
transparently and undergo proper training.
Here, the leadership’s responsibility, their
way of leading staff and the precision of
orders given are a matter of vital importance.
Also, at this point, a discussion must be
carried out on the relevance of controlling
agents’ personal lives to enable early detection
of risks of blunder.
Teamwork - cooperation with partners.
In a park, the organisation in charge of security
or surveillance is one of the components from
a wide selection of partners involved in conservation.
Ideally, these partners should meet regularly
to share problems, find solutions and implement
them.
This is the principle used by community policing.
The idea to set up meetings that the security
organisation can be led to organise.
This is when we talk about a local safety
and security council.
Objectivity.
This is when we tackle the issue work ethics
that must be subject to a published code of
ethics.
The nomination of an ethical officer supports
this element.
Purpose and governance.
The notions considered here are different
pieces of a puzzle within a Protected Area,
that will show externally that the area is
indeed achieving the mission it was given,
and internally, to determine what is expected
from agents and managers.
To tie it all together, the security organisation,
for example the unit in charge of the fight
against poaching, could draw up a yearly report
to the guardianship authority, which is destined
to be published and exposes the actions undertaken
in relation with the 5 standards and the results
obtained.