Developing and publishing codes or charters
are some of the tools an organisation can
use to communicate on its activities and work.
These codes are destined to the general public,
but also to the staff and leaders of the institution
in charge of drawing them up.
Here we are going to explain the logical way
of achieving these texts, namely based on
the notions of values and norms.
The idea is also to give these documents the
right size so that they are read and understood
by all.
Remember, each individual has his own personal
values.
In principle, when joining an organisation,
a person also accepts the values within.
This is the only condition that will enable
this agent to act in the way intended by the
organisation.
If the personal value system of the individual
is too different from the values of the organisation
he joined, difficulties will emerge.
It’s the case of A in the picture here,
where the personal values seem way off the
professional values of the organisation.
B will do better.
For this reason, the organisation must clearly
display its professional values.
Thereby, the values of the organisation and
of the people working within it are visible
to all.
This also helps people who may be interested
in joining the organisation to see, beforehand,
if these professional values aren’t in conflict
with their own personal values.
As we’ve see, ethics define the ideal of
a profession.
The agent must recognise himself in his employer’s
code of ethics.
We also remember that in a code of ethics,
ideas of loyalty, honesty and impartiality
are stated.
So how do you move from a code of ethics to
a code of deontology?
This is done by stating a company’s operational
standards, which stem from the values given
in the code of ethics.
You could say for example:
“the employee can’t accept personal gifts
for the execution of a specific task related
to his work.”
“the employee is held by official secrecy
in all circumstances”
“the agent treats every person he interacts
with fairly, irrespective of race, sex or
religion.”
There are still two important elements that
will guarantee the success of these codes.
First, as the codes are intended for the agents
themselves, they must be concise.
Avoid adding too many pages and articles.
The values must be limited to one page, as
the deontology will be more comprehensive.
If you want it to be read by the right people,
limit the number of pages to only hold vital
information.
Ideally, create a pocket format, a kind of
pocket card, that everybody can carry with
them.
The second element is participation.
These codes mustn’t be be an expression
of the power or direction set by the higher
levels of hierarchy.
Everybody must be able to recognise themselves
in these texts.
Thus, code of ethics and deontology writing
committees must gather people of all hierarchical
levels, including trade unions and minorities.
This certainly complicates the writing process,
but, in the end, the published texts will
be accepted by all the people involved.
The content can be very different from one
organisation to the next.
However, the following topics are usually
included:
The behaviour that all employees are expected
to conform to.
Leaders responsibility.
They must give clear orders, respect legislation
and the codes that have been set.
Employee rights, namely regarding refusal
to submit to illegal orders.
The guarantee that the organisation does its
best to ensure proper training for agents,
and thereby enabling them to act in the best
way possible, with comprehensive and recognised
professional skills.
That’s it for the important part!