Now we know the core aspects of ethics, deontology,
values and norms.
All these elements modify social behaviours,
but can also sometimes be in contradiction
with morals, cultural habits, or personal
situations.
The ethical dilemma poses the question of
choosing between the values that are opposed
in a given situation.
For example, in the case of staff working
for security in a park to fight poaching,
personal values can be opposed to professional
values.
So we will see how to recognize such a dilemma,
how to solve it, and above all, determine
which value prevails: the personal or professional
one?
And what is the role of norms in this type
of conflict?
Before we go any further, answer this questions
for yourself: whether we talk about a safety
professional, a police officer, a military,
a park guard, a doctor or a teacher: which
value must prevail?
Let’s try to find the answer together by
underscoring the tensions and dilemmas that
can exist between values and norms.
Consider a doctor.
A young lady wants to terminate her pregnancy
after a rape.
The law of her country forbids the termination
of pregnancy in all cases.
On a personal level, the doctor fights this
legislation, and is for the liberalisation
of abortion.
What must he do?
This doctor’s personal values are in opposition
with the values of his profession under the
country’s norms.
He must then make a decision: respect his
own values and break the law, or give up on
his personal values and respect the law.
He must weigh the pros and cons while being
aware of the consequences such a decision
can have.
Consider a park guard.
He is paid by the state to stop traffickers
of wood products and poachers.
He finds out his own brother is an ivory trafficker.
What must he do?
The guard must make a choice between loyalty
towards his family members or loyalty towards
the entire population who is represented by
the institution he serves and pays him to
fight crime.
There won’t be a good solution, but the
guard must make a choice.
There are several more or less complex methods
to analyse these dilemmas.
It will be interesting to go deeper by reading
the documents suggested by this MOOC.
In a nutshell, many aspects must be taken
into account to make a decision.
First, identify the main actors of the dilemma.
Here, the guard and his brother.
Also, identify the secondary actors.
Here, the trafficking network the brother
belongs to, his own family, his own colleagues,
the institution and the population.
Then, propose an alternative: must I arrest/denounce
my brother or not?
For each alternative, list the positive and
negative consequences for each actor.
For example, a positive consequence for the
brother can be to help him give up crime.
A negative consequence for me can be my family
may reject me.
Etc.
Also, in the same way, list the personal and
professional values affected for each opportunity,
as well as the norms concerned.
For example
The impact on the family involves a personal
value.
The impact on the organisation involves my
professional values and application of norms.
Identify the prevailing value.
At the end of this full procedure, you can
make a sound decision.
Then, assess this decision from your own perspective,
but also through other people’s eyes.
Ask yourself: am I satisfied with this decision?
If you can, ask a third party who isn’t
involved to share their opinion.
Imagine what the population will think of
your decision?
And your family?
Are you able to take responsibility for this
decision?
Will you be able to defend it?
Finally, make the decision with full knowledge
of possible consequences, and ready to take
responsibility for it.
Beyond this formal analysis, it is possible
to delay the final decision.
To do so, find an solution in between that
could mitigate the negative consequences on
the actors, particularly the main actors.
Maybe a good conversation with the poaching
brother could help, where you explain him
why he should stop his illegal activities.
Perhaps this will lead him to turn himself
in.
This intermediate step, where you explain
the conflict of values and norms in play,
may ignite something positive within the brother.
Alternatively, you will have to make the decision
decided upon previously.
And finally, the question asked at the beginning
of this sequence remains to be answered: which
value must prevail?
In principle, for a public agent who is paid
for his work, the professional values must
prevail.
If this agent has to cheat his employer to
follow personal values, he will quickly find
himself outlawed or outside of the norms.
He will become a problem for himself, his
hierarchy and the image of his profession.
If the professional values become that unbearable,
one solution remains: resigning.
Here is an historical example that shows how
conflicts of value and norms can become unbearable.
During the second world war, the Nazis asked
French policemen to arrest and imprison Jews,
as well as members of other undesirable communities
in the eyes of the occupant (homosexuals,
communists, artists…).
Some police officers accepted the mission
as their personal values didn’t seem to
clash with the new values and norms of the
institution.
Others resigned, and some kept their jobs
to cheat the institution and save lives.
These situations are extreme, but perfectly
show how far the ethical reflection can go
in special or degraded situations.
The ethical dilemma thus isn’t just a choice
between two alternatives like "should I go
on foot or by bicycle?”.
It is a choice between two solutions with
real consequences.
For a public agent, enforcing the law should
take precedence over other considerations.
In most cases, the solution to the ethical
dilemma of such particular professions will
be in respecting the laws.