- Hello Philippe.
- Hi Geoffroy
- In the previous module, we talked about
work ethics, and now, we are going to be looking
at corruption.
Corrupt government officials often make the
news, but what does it really mean?
- There is a general language misuse around
the word "corrupt” or “corruption”.
From a strictly legal point of view, corruption
is a specific criminal offense with clearly
defined legal implications.
We will talk about this in the next sequence.
- But indeed, we do describe people abusing
their State power as being “corrupt”.
These “corrupt” officials can steal, divert
money, scam, defraud and bribe.
This language misuse is rather convenient
as it clearly holds state or semi-public officials
responsible for any legal failure.
- So basically, we need to make a difference
between the common use of the word corruption
and its legal definition?
- Exactly.
For instance, if a state official in charge
of patrols prefers hiding in a quiet place
so he doesn’t get tired, his behaviour would
be questionable from an ethical perspective,
but he hasn’t really committed any concrete
criminal offense.
You can call him depraved, lazy, but he certainly
isn’t corrupt.
- So why does this notion of "corruption”
in its everyday use find itself associated
with so many illegal activities related to
government work?
- Let’s just say that it’s an oversimplification.
The reason why this language misuse has won
over the media and the people is clear: it
gives us one word to describe the fact that
somebody has serious shortcomings, and deserves
to be sanctioned for it.
But from a strictly legal perspective, a corrupt
person must be found guilty of corruption.
- Is corruption present all over the world?
- Unfortunately, yes, no country has been
spared.
For example, the corruption perceptions index
of Transparency International places Switzerland,
where I used to work, in a rather flattering
position.
But this doesn’t mean there is absolutely
no corruption.
I’ve actually had the chance to investigate
this matter, mainly on cases related to public
procurement awards, but also to bribes paid
to other countries to facilitate the conclusion
of commercial contract.
- Nobody is immune to it.
How can you detect criminal behaviour and
fight it?
This is what we will be looking at in the
coming sequences.
- First, we will see the different classifications
of offense that can be committed in the professional
environment, and we’ll explain what corruption
is.
- Then, we will be looking at some principles
that dictate the operations of organisations….and
reasons that can lead to corruption.
- After this, we will talk about the solutions
to reduce, unfortunately not eliminate, corruption
within organisations
- or on a personal level.
- Finally, we will talk about how corruption
can damage reputations, as it was the case
for the FIFA recently.
- A good legal and criminal overview ahead!
Have a great week.