We often talk about corruption.
In the media, police officers, politicians,
entrepreneurs, bankers and judges are often
accused of corruption.
But what does this mean?
Actually, the word “corruption” is generally
misused to describe all criminal behaviour
committed by a person who has power and abuses
it.
This is often how the media relays the acts
of political authorities, as in Brazil in
the example here.
However, somebody who takes equipment from
his employer for personal use or to resell
it is called a thief and his employer is the
victim.
The person who diverts money that has been
entrusted to him by his employer to finance
his own lifestyle is called a crook and his
employer is, again, the victim.
These criminal behaviours don’t fall under
the legal sense of corruption, which has a
very precise definition in the penal code
of each country.
Offenses of this kind have an interesting
feature.
The perpetrators of such offenses show a certain
perversity.
Indeed, they often know and see the victims
they harm.
If they harm their own employers, the perpetrators
will meet them every day knowing that they
are stealing from them.
It is probably easier to burglarize a house
or steal a car, knowing that we never have
to face the victim.
So together, we will look at the specific
case of corruption, which is one of the many
criminal activities a government official
can be guilty of.
The Swiss penal code, for example, mentions
many different elements that constitute the
act of corruption.
It takes two persons for corruption to take
place:
The corrupter, which is the person who corrupts,
the actor of active corruption.
The corrupted, the actor of passive corruption.
Two types of situations can be identified:
The corrupter obtains a free legal service
from the corrupted in return for payment.
Or, the corrupter obtains an illegal operation
Now let’s have a look at some typical situations
that will help us understand this better.
First case scenario: consider a protected
area that can be visited according to certain
rules.
Officially, entrance is free, and the duty
officer simply has to register the visitors
that come and go for security reasons.
The government official accepts this mission,
but even though the service is free, he requires
visitors to pay a fee which he keeps for himself.
What is the situation here?
Clearly, this is situation of corruption from
the public servant who takes advantage of
his inevitable location to extort an undue
fee.
The public servant is clearly outlawed.
The visitor as well, if he knows the pass
is free, and aware that if he doesn’t pay,
he won’t be able to enter.
Second case scenario: consider a PA in which
hunting is strictly allowed for a couple of
weeks a year, with no possible exemption.
A hunter wants to get permission to hunt outside
this time period.
He offers payment to the agents in charge
of hunting control so that they don’t denounce
him and let him hunt freely.
What is the situation this time?
The public servant grants an illegal authorisation
to the corrupt hunter in return for payment.
Here, both parties involved are clearly accomplices
in the act of corruption.
Third case scenario: in a PA, the agent in
charge of granting hunting permits follows
the rules.
He cashes in official taxes paid by hunters
and provides the corresponding permits.
However, to increase his personal income,
he doesn’t register all the permits so he
can keep part of the money paid by hunters
for himself.
What is the situation here?
Well, this is theft, possibly fraud at the
expense of the protected area.
The hunters, apparently honest, have probably
no idea how their tax is handled once paid.
Basically, you must learn to distinguish active
corruption from passive corruption, whether
it is to bypass legislation and regulations,
or to apply them but through undue fees.
Once the notion of corruption is understood
in the legal sense, the question is who can
be corrupt?
This notion mainly applies to government officials
or public servants.
It can also apply to private agencies who
have been assigned a job by the government.
However, for such a person to be corruptible
or susceptible to corruption, they must have
some form of power.
This person must have the power to authorise
or forbid, to grant and to refuse.
In addition, this person must have a key position,
meaning the service provided cannot be obtained
elsewhere.
This person must also have greater freedom
of action, and not undergo controls from their
organisation.
Finally, this person cannot be held responsible
for possible consequences.
In a nutshell, to be in a situation that is
favourable to corruption, you must have a
monopoly on an act, be able to operate discreetly,
and not be controlled or be held responsible.
These elements lead us to think about ways
an organisation must be set up to avoid risks
of corruption.
This will be the topic of the next sequence.