People aren’t naturally corrupt by birth.
So why suddenly or progressively, does a person
fall into crime and corruption?
This is what we will see in this sequence.
A child’s education has a decisive influence
on his adult behaviour.
Children act by imitating others, and will
consider it normal to imitate their parents,
even their most questionable traits.
Cultural and social environments also influence
a child’s education.
It may indeed be easier to resist criminal
temptations in a privileged and economically
stable social environment.
In an environment that was degraded by war
or a weak economy, a person would be more
inclined to behave inadequately.
Once he becomes an adult, the person is confronted
with his own ethical analysis: what must I
do?
The responsible adult must make choices.
He must be aware of the social and cultural
influences that guided his education.
He must now behave according to his own rules
he has full control of.
But what happens?
Why do some fall?
Why do they accept to be corrupted or take
illegal liberties?
This is what I call the backpack effect.
The backpack is carried by each person every
morning when leaving the house, and carried
back home in the evening to their families.
This imaginary backpack holds all the problems
and troubles individuals have to bear, but
also all the joys and satisfactions they’ve
experienced.
The bag’s content permanently influences
the person’s behaviour.
Because of it he can lose perfectly good habits,
and act in the heat of the moment.
Basically, the state of the bag can make somebody
commit unprofessional or criminal actions.
What is inside this backpack?
Inside, you’ll find the realities of life.
For example, family problems like the illness
of a loved one, a partner or children.
You’ll also find relational problems within
the family, conflict with the spouse or parents.
These problems can take an important space
in the mind of the person who lives with them
and can grow to the point that they become
more important than professional issues.
You’ll also find work-related problems,
like lack of consideration for a job from
the population, lack of communication with
colleagues, lack of support from leadership,
defective technical equipment in terms of
arsenal, clothing or connection.
Here too, an excellent employee may feel demotivated
and think his efforts have no point.
Finally, you’ll find all the problems related
to the financial situation.
Often, starting a family leads to great financial
burdens which can be difficult to face.
The birth of children, buying a house etc.
Alone with one partner, possibly with two
incomes, everything seems easy.
But building a family increase expenses.
Income may also decline if someone in the
household loses employment.
And the point of rupture can trigger frustration
and can make someone loose its ethical sense
to face everyday problems.
Frustration can be a powerful catalyst for
delinquency.
In our case, it leads to professional delinquency,
namely corruption or unlawful acts committed
in the work environment.
All workers show up at work with their own
imaginary backpacks.
It is good for leadership to know what’s
inside, at least in part.
However, employees have no obligation to share
this with their bosses.
If they do, it must be a result of dialogue
based on mutual trust.
If the leaders are informed, they will be
able to distribute the work among employees
by taking this information in consideration.
Based on these factors of frustration or influence,
different types of corruption can be defined.
Here, we will only describe three styles that
illustrate how corruption can appear.
First, the notion of "rotten apple" which
supposes that human beings are individually
responsible and inherently predisposed to
commit crime.
Organisations usually appreciate this vision.
It allows them to distance themselves from
situations, they don’t have to question
themselves, namely when it comes to controls
or considering the quality of managers.
The notion of "slippery slope" is also used.
You take a first seemingly trivial step in
the wrong direction, then by habit or laziness,
you go further.
To turn back, you will need to have the courage
to denounce yourself or your accomplices.
So instead, you let yourself go.
"Department corruption" describes the fact
that the entire organisation is dysfunctional.
The individual confronted with this environment
will be able to let himself go saying "if
everybody does it, why not me?”
Such behaviors have been found within police
units in various countries, of course not
only in France as in this example.
For people to realise this imaginary backpack
exists and that it is the cause of certain
behaviours, the staff must be equipped with
certain tools.
This includes basic vocational training on
work-related or technical tasks, but also
training on work ethics and deontology.
In the next sequence we will suggest a method
of analysis to create favourable conditions
for such training.