We’ve defined what corruption is.
We also saw that besides corruption, there
are other offences or crimes that can be committed
by public officials.
Corruption requires the presence of a corruptor
and a corrupted while other criminal activities
are the responsibility of one person alone.
Notice that the situations leading public
officials, managers and staff to fail are
often the same: absence of internal control,
temptation, a personal financial situation
considered unfair, lack of recognition by
leadership and/or by the population, frustrations
on career evolutions etc.
There are plenty of countermeasures.
At least some of them must be implemented
by the organisation.
This is what we will look at in this sequence.
First, each member of the organisation must
be clear on the general mission of the organisation
he serves and that pays him, as well was on
his own mission within this structure.
It is everyone’s responsibility to understand
these missions, regardless of the level of
leadership.
Senior executives as well as staff must know
the factors impacting the organisation’s
operations, as clarity and transparency are
the enemies of corruption.
Each element of an organisation has a clearly
defined area of work.
Literature in this field identifies many types
of factors that impact organisations.
In this sequence, we’ll introduce one of
these lists of factors, namely the PESTEL
analysis, which includes six main factors.
P for Politics.
Whether it’s the country or the organisation’s
politics, this is the main factor impacting
an organisation in its operations and in setting
the goals to achieve.
Politics determine the nature of the organisation’s
mission.
E for Economy.
The economic and financial situation obviously
influence the operations of the organisation,
namely the means at hand to fulfil its mission.
S for Social.
The social situation of civil society, its
customs, its culture and morals, limit some
aspects of the organisation’s operations,
but sometimes it can broaden them.
T for Technology.
The technology at hand can modify the organisation’s
operations and methods, by distributing the
logistics at hand more or less evenly.
E for Environment.
The weather, the field layout, urban development,
or on the contrary a very rural context or
an isolated location, all require special
adaptation from the organisation.
L for Legal.
By definition, the law is binding in many
fields, but it also leaves room for freedom
in other fields.
This flexibility is part of the mission analysis
and the goals to achieve.
The PESTEL analysis is only one of the possible
approaches.
But it illustrates quite well the different
constraints that an organisation and its members
may face.
Top leadership must also get its decisions
across to all the associates.
To do so it must explain the factors that
influences their decisions in a way or another.
Communication must hence be a key element
in the fight against corruption.
Staff must on the other hand must have a clearly
defined scope of action within their own field
of activity.
In this case, PESTEL may not be the most suitable
solution as its factors aren’t perceptible
enough or adapted to daily activities.
Instead, the organisation can focus on having
good work ethics and on making sure clear
and non-ambiguous orders are given by leadership.
These two elements limit the scope of action
of each person within the organisation.
We talk about this briefly in the next sequence
and see what it looks like practically.