We saw that corruption must be handled by
the organisation itself.
It’s the organisation’s responsibility,
through management, to implement controlling
measures, namely by adopting rules and norms,
by giving clear orders and by implementing
the required ethical principles and deontology.
Now we are going to try and see the difference
between what will contribute to effectively
fight against corruption, and the other types
of offences in an organisation.
First, all levels of responsibility must be
clearly defined, and powers in authority and
in decision-making must be known by all.
The instructions and rules of operations must
also be clear and consistent, in other words,
they must be written down and approved.
Operational order must respect principles
of engagement as well as the rights and duties
of the agents and litigants.
These responsibilities, instructions and rules
must be known, taught and practiced.
Everybody must undergo basic but also recurring
training to guarantee unity of doctrine when
implementing the organisation’s processes.
Training is hence the key to the success of
the fight against corruption.
It must namely include modules about:
The organisation’s goals and objectives
Legal bases (legislation and rules) governing
the organisation’s activities
Individual responsibility and consequences
Rights and obligations of members of the organisation
Internal investigations about malfunctions
and their legal (penal) and administrative
(dismissal, pay cuts) consequences
And, of course, work ethics and deontology.
Beyond this, training will of course include
the technical aspects of the job.
In other words, training requires time investment.
This investment not only trains future managers
and staff, but it also exists to test and
assess them throughout the training period.
Sometimes, this helps to detect individuals
who may have chosen the wrong career path.
Recruiting is therefore a first vital step.
Employment criteria must be known, published,
and above all, applied.
Effective recruitment requires selection based
on objective criteria, such as the level of
education required, the age limits for recruitment,
physical condition, required training, criminal
record.
Only the people who meet all these requirements
can be hired.
If at this point, special treatment is given,
nothing can guarantee future behaviours in
terms of corruption an ethics.
Obviously, these criteria must apply fairly
to both the junior recruits at the beginning
of their career, as well as to managers of
all levels.
To conclude, let’s remember that leadership’s
responsibility is key in the fight against
corruption.
Leadership must play its controlling role
actively, but must also undergo control itself.
People from the higher levels of the hierarchy
must also set themselves objectives.
These objectives have to be translated into
directives and orders that can be understood
by staff from all ranks.
The issue of the preparation and distribution
of these orders will be discussed in the next
module.