We’ve seen what a behaviour respecting a
certain work ethic looks like.
We’ve also mentioned the legal questions
regarding offences committed in the work environment,
namely corruption.
One thing that each and every one must include
in their reflection at all levels of leadership
is the great risk of damage to a reputation
these failures can present.
We’ve seen how to include the Cohen and
Feldberg principles to an organisation’s
governance.
But this relates to the situation where everything
goes well.
What happens when it doesn’t?
Recently, in Europe, there was a scandal about
a German car manufacturers who cheated their
diesel engine tests.
The question isn’t if you are for or against
diesel engines, that’s not the point.
The question is, how are our choices as consumers
free and informed if the factors supporting
them are forged by manufacturer?
Fundamentally, the damage is done.
Even if the car manufacturers do everything
they can to fix the mistakes, the reputation
of their companies are affected.
The offence is, obviously, criminal, but the
real problem started with a distorted ethical
reflection.
The same goes for this Peruvian policeman.
His behaviour made public discredits him AND
his corporation.
Even if this is an isolated case, the story
will spread and inevitably shed doubts over
his organisation and his entire profession,
or even all Peruvian public officials.
In the streets you’ll probably often hear
people say: “they’re all corrupt”.
These two examples give us an idea of the
consequences related to the failure of a senior
executive, like in the example of diesel,
or the regular employee like with the Peruvian.
Above all, we must realise that each person
within the organisation holds the same responsibility
and can trigger the same consequences.
Everyone within the organisation, whatever
their rank, should care about its image and
reputation.
The consequences of such failures are easily
identifiable.
Damaged reputations involve loss of confidence
and of respect from the population, the litigants
and the authorities.
Who would call on a government organisation
if the behaviour of its members is considered
unreliable?
This will create great distrust from the people
towards the ones supposed to serve them.
Also, if the organisation finds out it is
susceptible to external corruptors, internal
controls must be intensified, and will limit
employees liberty.
From a personal perspective, the individual
exposes himself to prosecution and internal
administrative proceedings.
He is at risk of dismissal and possible lawsuits
for damages.
He will lose his job and will have to explain
to his future employer why he left his previous
job.
These situations raise questions about the
gifts from private individuals to government
organisations.
At what point are these gifts no longer signs
of friendship and attention, but direct or
indirect payments?
It is about paying attention to the hidden
compensations.
It’s important to anticipate the donors’
expectations in future interventions.
Operational choices could be influenced by
such or such litigant who is more generous
and friendly than others.
A failure at that level will have the same
consequences as in the diesel example or of
the Peruvian police officer.
Moreover, this would cause major reputation
damages.
Thus, internal regulations must deal with
the principles of accepting gifts or benefits
in kind.
In conclusion, we’ll once again notice the
importance of training associates and managers.
This training must cover all these aspects,
technical but also ethical, deontological
and legal.
The individual’s survival is at stake.
We can consider that training in general,,
and trainings on ethics in particular, enables
the survival of an individual or the organisation
tactically and non-tactically.
Tactical survival is ensured by work skills
that are mastered through proper training.
It will enable the associate to survive practically
in his daily activity, to not be killed or
injured.
Non-tactical survival is based on social skills,
and will enable the individual to survive
in his job, without being dismissed for misconduct.
These two elements have long been considered
by the police and the military as opposed.
According to me, they are complementary and
go hand in hand.