- Hello Philippe.
- Hi Geoffroy
- Philippe, why do we need to add a module
specifically on giving orders?
- In the previous modules, we talked about
organisations’ responsibility to fight corruption,
and to develop work ethics.
I insisted on the importance of training,
and mentioned the need to issue clear orders.
- This is why we are now going to talk about
a method that helps giving orders drawing
from the organisation’s objectives.
These orders are more concrete and operational,
but the method also works for administrative
tasks.
- Is this method for anybody or do we only
target managers?
- Managers are more likely to give orders
based on this method.
However, all staff must be aware of it to
understand the meaning behind what they are
being asked, and how leadership makes its
decision.
- But the method can be adapted to all levels
of leadership on the basis of a good understanding
of the mission.
- So where does this method come from?
- I’ve applied this method at work throughout
my career.
It is the one taught at police and military
academies in my country.
Complete handbooks can be ordered from the
editors.
- Here I am going to adapt this method, because
I will only give the general guidelines.
To go deeper, it is best to imagine exercises
and scenarios to study, and experience them
as part of a group.
- Ok, so together, let’s look at the steps
of this systematic and structured methodology.
- First, you must understand the goals you
want to reach by giving orders.
- Then, to define the orders, you must analyse
the mission and understand the problem.
- Assess your own means and possibilities
if confronted with problems that can emerge
when executing the order.
- Then, we will look at how to make the operational
choices and decisions
- Finally, we will consider the plan of operational
orders
- Perfect, now let’s have a look at all
this!