To kick off this module about issuing orders
and instructions, we need to start by setting
the general context.
There are indeed several command and management
levels that imply different order classifications.
At every level, the most important part is
to make sure the common goal is reached together
by all subordinates, in other words, the mission
must be fulfilled in common.
A clear system must be used when issuing orders
to subordinates, so that they understand what
is expected of them and why.
As we’ve already said, there are many levels
of command – they are briefly described
in this table.
Strategic command is related to public authorities,
to the senior management of big companies
and to the high command of the police or the
army.
In this MOOC we won’t be looking at this
level.
Operative command involves commitment in synergy
with different bodies that have to take action
together.
This includes for instance joint action of
the police, firemen and health services during
large forest fires.
Generally, this requires the creation of a
special task force, as a staff, with its own
dedicated structure, namely facilities equipped
with means of communication.
Tactical or operative command focuses on the
work of units directly involved on the field.
Most of the time, at this level, the leader
can lead his team by himself, without the
help of a specially and formally established
staff or headquaters.
In this MOOC, we will move back and forth
between tactical command and operative command,
so it will be important to know what we are
talking about.
All security organisations like the army,
the police, private security agencies and
teams dedicated to the conservation of protected
areas, have a mission, a target to achieve.
In the example displayed here, the mission
is still quite general - the first line is
strategic, while the second one covers the
operative level.
It doesn’t state the concrete actions each
associate must carry out, so the mission will
have to be analysed and declined into concrete
actions for subordinates.
The mission displayed on the screen right
now is of a lower level, close to the tactical
level, but still covering part of the operative
level, as nothing is said concerning the means
at hand (staff, arsenal, duration).
This mission is a bit more concrete than the
previous one, but must be clarified to address
collaborators on the field.
Here we are at the tactical level of the squadron
commander.
He will have to give a couple of extra precisions
to the team leaders under him.
It will then be up to each team leader to
give further instructions based on the sector
they are in charge of (bush, mountain, urban
area).
Notice how the levels of command form a chain
reaction from top to bottom when it comes
to mission assignments.
Each level must be aware of this system, not
only executive officers as they apply it,
but also subordinates to understand it.
When the global operation is complex and involves
a lot of staff, the number of levels between
operation leaders and basic collaborator increases.
This order preparation system will help managers
have a standardised way of thinking, that
ensures all relevant parameters have been
considered, to guarantee the mission is fulfilled.
The more this method is practiced, known and
applied, the more the one using it will be
able to think fast and effectively, even when
he faces unexpected crises or finds himself
under time pressure.
Thus, during training, exercises must be as
realistic as possible, and involve both leaders
and their subordinates.
These exercises must be prepared by keeping
in mind what level of command should be applied:
operative, tactical, or both at the same time?
Finally, despite the very formal aspect of
what has been said in this sequence, the personality
of each leader influences the way he faces
and assesses problems.
His level of experience may lead him to choose
original or daring solutions, that a beginner
would hesitate on.
In the following sequences, we will be seeing
that the systematic method doesn’t exclude
the personality of actors involved.
We will also see that there are often different
possible options available to face a new problem
or achieve a mission.
We’ll see how to choose among these options,
namely by considering the risk assessment
that can impact fulfilling the mission.
Finally, ethics and human rights must fully
be part of each step of the process.