Before making his decision and establishing
a strategy, the leader must first make sure
to have properly assessed what is expected
of him, with the means, staff and equipment
he has been given.
The more complex and chaotic the situation,
the more holistically the problem should be
comprehended.
First, as soon as the mission is received,
an event occurs or when the situation changes
drastically, the problem must be comprehended.
This comprehension is divided in three parts:
detecting the problem, understanding the problem,
assessing the problem.
Detecting the problem consist in answering
the following basic question: What is it about?
To do so, you must consider the following
elements: what are the goals to achieve, or
what is the expected result?
What are the risks and the opportunities to
seize?
What is the level of difficulty?
What is the deadline in which the mission
must be accomplished - in other words, is
it urgent?
What are the different tasks required to fulfil
the mission?
When trying understanding the problem, the
person responsible for the operation distributes
the tasks he identified to several subordinates.
These will work simultaneously and give accounts
of the results from their work.
In a more complex operation at the operative
level, the command staff entrusts its thoughts
to auxiliary task forces, made of several
people.
When the situation isn’t as complex, the
leader simply divides the work between his
direct subordinates.
Understanding the problem gives a general
overview of all the aspects of the mission,
and makes it possible to choose solutions
with full knowledge.
Assessing the problem simply consists in describing
the importance of the mission compared to
other ongoing activities, its importance in
the general context, possible urgency in achieving
the mission, and setting the order of priority
of the different tasks that were identified
upon understanding the problem.
Once the mission is fully analysed, this is
what we have: a description of tasks to fulfil
and their order of priority, a vision of the
final desired state, first drafts of possible
solutions for the mission, constraints that
need to be considered and opportunities that
we can benefit from.
The thought process that we just discovered
seems quite heavy.
When the mission stems from a sudden and unpredictable
event that needs to be handled immediately,
the process can be shortened.
In this case, comprehending the problem can
be limited to: What is it about?
Must we act?
What tasks must be carried out?
What do I need to face this event?
Obviously, when the mission covers a longer
period of time and the operation is more complex
or expected to take place later, there is
more time for thinking and preparing.
The more time there is between the reception
of the mission and its deadline, the more
carefully each step of problem comprehension
can be followed.
During the thought process, it often seems
that measures must be taken immediately to
save time, to complete the information at
hand, to obtain extra means of support, to
avoid any further damage (during a catastrophe
for example), or to maintain a level of flexibility
(clearing the road for example).
These are called “immediate measures”.
Here, the need to take emergency action during
a sudden event mustn’t be confused with
what we call immediate measures.
These are one-time measures, to carry out
immediately.
They are ordered by the leader as soon as
the problem comprehension process is over,
according to the needs.
Now let’s see how these immediate measures
are carried out, who triggers them and when?
In theory, immediate measures aren’t needed
when you plan an operation that takes place
later in time.
They are used when the mission must be carried
out in a binding time limit.
AIMER, French for “love”, is an acronym
to help you remember the possible immediate
measures.
Depending on the operation, all measures aren’t
necessary:
A is for alerting.
Alert support teams like a special squad or
paramedics, transport means and so on.
I is for informing.
Inform the lower and higher levels in the
command hierarchy so that they can start with
preparations related to the new mission, or
inform the political level when there is a
potential media impact.
M is for putting into Motion.
Put into Motion preparatory actions (roadblocks,
operational structures etc.) or pre-existing
action plans.
E is for exploring.
Exploring means searching intelligence on
people (victims, witnesses, perpetrators etc.).
Who am I dealing with?
What do they want to do?
R is for reconnaissance, called sometimes
scouting.
Here, reconnaissance means looking for information
on the configuration of the field, the aspect
of built-up areas, the state of roads or adverse
infrastructures etc.
By triggering immediate measures, the leader
must make sure not to block his own future
possibilities to take action.
He must always try to preserve flexibility.
Based on if you are at the operative or tactical
level, immediate measures can be ordered verbally
or through a written order, by respecting
the format we will be looking at in the next
sequences.
All the steps that we just looked at must
follow one another logically over time.
The constraint in this case is the time available
until the operation is carried out.
Within this timeframe, the idea is to set
precisely when a given step must be undertaken.
You must also give subordinates the time they
need to execute the task they were given.
During this process of comprehending the problem
and the tasks stemming from it, routine meetings
must be set (in time and place) give subordinates
the opportunity to present the state of their
work.
Scheduling helps setting the same work pace
for all subordinates.
However it can be adapted based on the evolution
of the situation, or the progress of preparatory
works.
As said before, the more complex the event,
the more this process will be dense and the
more time and energy consuming it will be.
If all these steps are carefully fulfilled,
the event leader will have all the elements
at hand to consolidate his own position.