Let’s keep unpacking all the aspects that
can impact the mission we were given.
Once again, in this MOOC we are giving the
full method.
Depending on deadlines, or the lack of complexity
of the mission, this systematic thought process
can and must be simplified.
After the problem is comprehended, we move
on to assessing the situation.
In this phase, the different aspects that
must be considered are detailed, namely the
five groups of factors.
The mission is the core of the thought process
and must therefore also be assessed.
Its importance within the general context
should be considered by comparing it with
other ongoing missions.
The minimum and maximum expected results of
the action must be expressed, and the level
of flexibility of the mission must by questioned
by listing the constraints we are bound by,
and the freedom we are given.
Finally, we’ll go over the possible support
or partners we have.
A reflexion on legal foundations will help
identify if any form of action is needed,
if it actually falls under our jurisdiction.
The two basic principles of proportionality
and lawfulness must be carefully followed,
as well as human rights and ethics when the
situation might compromise them.
Deadlines are often a huge constraint.
All the time-related elements at hand must
be identified, such as the possible time the
adverse action would happen, the pace at which
the situation is expected to evolve, when
my possible back-up will show up, when it
is expected from me to implement the action
and when it is expected I would achieve the
set target.
To know how to act, it is important to know
how the sector of engagement is set.
This concerns its size and distance from our
own departure base, as well as the state of
the field, if it is a built-up zone, if there
are any roads or inhabitants.
The weather is also considered, as well as
communication networks, natural or manufactured
obstacles and the possibility to set up a
command post.
Will the action take place at night or during
daytime?
In short, this includes all the practical
aspects of the field in which you’ll have
to venture and the means you will have to
deploy to facilitate the action.
Whether you are confronted to a human adversary
or a catastrophic situation, it is important
to imagine all the possibilities the situation
can evolve towards, all the possible risks.
Ideally, list all these risks so that they
can later be confronted with our solutions
to minimize them.
It is important not to understand “adversary”
as “enemy” in the narrow sense of the
word.
Consider a victim for instance: they are not
an adversary, but will be taken care of concretely
and constitute a task to fulfil.
So, anything that will require some sort of
action on our part must be imagined using
the following lingo: opposing party.
Analysing a risk and assessing its importance
can be done by relying on the risk matrix.
The green part relates to the risks considered
insignificant, that won’t require specific
measures, except maybe a follow up on the
situation.
The yellow part relates to risks requiring
measures with a debatable scope.
The red part is about risks with a high probability
of having grave consequences - these must
be a priority until they are solved.
This step of risk assessment can be summarised
as follows: what is the most likely adverse
situation that could happen?
Which one is the most dangerous?
A simple method to assess our own means is
to confront every adverse risk with one or
more possible actions on our part.
This makes the thought process more concrete.
It doesn’t exclude listing our own possibilities
as such and not only as a tool for reaction.
The state of staff and management, available
equipment and possible back up teams, are
part of this assessment factor.
At this point, we should be able to tell if
our means are adapted to the situation to
handle.
And at any point of the situation assessment,
based on the identified problems, new immediate
measures can be ordered and the schedule can
be adapted.