After everything we’ve seen, its’s time
to move on to the part we all like: decision-making!
Many great military strategists in history
«felt » the situation and acted instinctively.
Unfortunately, we do not all have this ability,
hence the necessity to take time for reflexion.
This way, we would be able to explain our
decision, to justify it in light of the problem
comprehension, and the assessment of the situation.
From there, we have everything we need to
establish a written or verbal order.
In the previous steps, we considered possible
solutions, different ways of fulfilling the
mission.
This leads us to the following principle:
thinking in terms of options.
The fancy example you can see here illustrates
this.
There is no wrong option, but the consequences
are different.
The 2nd option will be more expensive, but
the family will make more friends happy to
participate.
The first option is more affordable, but the
people in the village will probably hold it
against us.
There is never only one solution, but rather
a couple of them, as each option has its pros
and cons.
Generally, we should choose an option that
has more pros and fewer cons, but it isn’t
as easy as it seems.
To analyse options, you can for example make
sure:
It is suitable, in the sense that it indeed
solves the problem and respects the mission
that was given.
It is exclusive, meaning that false options
that only paraphrase others must be avoided.
It is practicable in terms of means at hand,
of the level of staff training and deadlines.
It is acceptable in terms of objective risks,
but also in terms of risks related to breaching
human rights and work ethics, and affecting
our image in the eyes of the population.
If it is complete, in the sense that we tick
off all the boxes of needed parameters, deadlines,
place and how and who does what.
So, what is decision?
The finally chosen option consists in a couple
of words or sentences, often associated with
a draft that: sets the goal to achieve, how
to achieve it, it determines how the action
will unfold in space and in time, it sets
collaboration with possible support, it is
a synthesis of thoughts expressed in a concise
manner.
Reserved decision is a special case of the
main decision.
In fact, reserved decisions are the result
of simultaneous planning, they are ready to
use if the situation would radically change.
There can be several reserved decisions answering
the following question: “what do we do if…?”
In our fancy marriage example: what do we
do if the bride or groom doesn’t want to
get married anymore?
You can also change a rejected option into
reserved decision.