Here we are at the last step of our thinking
process leading to establishing orders.
Remember: the goal of the entire process is
to give clear written or verbal orders.
The process that we just went over, provides
all the elements you need for this.
Let’s see how.
In my country, we would generally consider
an order in 5 points.
Let’s see what they contain.
Let’s start with orientation.
Orientation gives indications on :
-The situation and possible developments,
-Risks associated with the adverse party and
its own possibilities or means,
-The missions received by the superior level
of hierarchy, respectively the mission that
you give yourself facing a situation that
occurs or evolves,
-Support from non-subordinate partners that
you may have.
- All these elements exist, because information
was collected and analysed in the problem
comprehension and situation assessment phases.
From these two steps, we gather relevant information
to explain the decision.
What about intention ?
In short, the person responsible for an operation
explains what he wants to do, how, and what
the means and deadlines are.
Terminology must be concise and illustrative.
The total explanation must be summarised so
that everybody understands what the common
goal to achieve is.
This is maybe the hardest thing to write down,
as ideally, you should try to be as comprehensive
as possible using only few words, as I’m
trying to show here.
And the missions.
A mission is assigned to each subordinate,
whether it is a colleague by himself, or a
group with a designated leader.
The mission is compulsory, and binding.
However, subordinates must always be given
some flexibility so that they can adapt to
unforeseen circumstances.
Again, the mission must be described concisely
and precisely.
Special requirements are part of the category
we could call "miscellaneous”.
The following information is indicated in
this category: The time and place of meeting
for the beginning of the action ; The possible
end of action (what time and under whose orders)
; The radio channels that will be used and/or
contact information of people involved ; Equipment
required per individual (weapon or not, winter
attire, helmet, etc.)
;Special guidelines like the rule about weapon
usage and other means of defence ;The behaviour
to have with people encountered, this is where
human rights and ethics are mentioned ; Rules
of communication with the media ; Administrative
rules like working time or possible benefits
; Housing details and supplies for a durable
commitment.
Finally, let’s talk about locations:
In principle, at least the location and the
contact information of the leader must appear
here.
The possible location of command facilities
is also noted, in other words the command
post along with the contact information.
Verbal or written orders?
All orders mustn’t necessarily be written
down.
For complex operations, with higher risks,
written orders help guarantee everyone has
the same information.
If the matter goes wrong, the subordinates
will be able to state they acted based on
the orders they were given.
It is a form of protection.
Facing the population and public authorities,
this helps showing management professionalism,
in the way they comprehend the problem and
assess the situation.
Different words can be considered to identify
types of orders.
Each organisation can create its own classification.
A general order could be about the organisation
of the company or institution’s structure.
An operational order will directly be about
a concrete engagement.
A prior order can help to give immediate measures
or advise different actors involved of an
operation to come.
Here, let’s give organisations the freedom
to choose their own terminology.
To establish standard behaviours within an
organisation, we can give a general order.
We can also draw up a practical document,
in pocket-format, that gives basic rules that
everybody must follow.
These rules of engagement frame the use of
coercion, force, and therefore the use of
weapons.
They also provide the legal bases to follow,
namely Human rights.
This is particularly useful when the organisation
is supported by people with different philosophies,
for instance, when the police is supported
by the military, whose rules on weapon usage
are slightly different.
Rules of engagement can be permanent or written
down specifically for a particular operation.
At the end of these sequences, we can ask
why we have to go through this entire process.
Well, as we’ve said, this helps to prove
the professionalism of people writing the
orders, and it also helps subordinates knowing
precisely what is expected of them.
In the end, everyone is more comfortable during
the action.
Obviously, when the situation is simple, an
order can simply be a: "goal, way towards
the goal, behaviour at the goal”.
Especially when the action is immediate on
the field.
At this point, reflexion is secondary, so
risks are greater.
Taking time for reflexion is never lost time.