Hello,
In this module we will look at how a key activity
related to law enforcement in a protected
area is carried out, namely, the fight against
poaching.
To learn more about poaching, you can also
have a look at the MOOC on species conservation
which analyses its form, causes and solutions.
This module is presented by captain Benoit
Koutouna Amon, in charge of mobile brigades
for the central region at the Ivorian Parks
and Reserves Authority
Together we will look at the following points:
- what is surveillance, what is it based on
and how is it organised
- Who are the actors involved and what are
their roles
- How is the fight against poaching planned
on the field
- And how do patrols manage its execution
- What equipment do we need
- And what vital role does intelligence play
to improve results.
- Finally, we will have a quick look at new
technologies that can help surveillance, a
growing and important topic.
At the end of this module, you’ll also find
the last exam of the MOOC!
Have a great week.