- For this entire module on surveillance,
you can refer to these guidelines to find
more information.
- In a protected area, surveillance enables
law enforcement, and it is also a key aspect
of protected area management.
- Generally speaking, the protection of values
involves restrictions, and these restrictions
require control of what is happening onsite.
- Note that this is not a requirement and
a protected area can do without surveillance
if there are no coveted resources, or that
that these resources do not face any particular
threats.
- A category 3 protected area for example,
a natural monument such as a cliff or a cave,
may be protected through its lack of accessibility
or because there are no exploitable resources
to be found.
Of course, this is not the most frequent scenario.
- Surveillance of a protected area can be
defined as the actions that are implemented
to enforce the rules applying to the territory
and to the resources within.
- The prosecution of criminal offenses in
parks is based on legal texts such as the
Environmental Code, the Mining Code, the Water
Code and legislation on human rights.
- But as we saw in the first unit, protected
areas are also governed by specific regulatory
texts that should be carefully enforced.
- In general, this legal or regulatory framework
is specific to a country.
There can be practical variations from one
territory to the next, but the logic remains
the same.
- Surveillance is carried out under the authority
of the judicial power such as the Public Prosecutor
and his deputies.
- It is therefore important for the park manager
to work closely with these actors, and for
himself to master the legal actions he can
take.
- Indeed, lack of knowledge in managing the
case has led many proceedings against poachers
to fail.
- The police report submitted to court can
be a problem if the facts aren’t recounted
properly, and if all the evidence gathered
during surveillance isn’t included.
- These reports are often the basis of the
decision made by the judge, and the slightest
mistake can cause the case to be dropped,
especially when this mistake is a technicality.
- Another main aspect is the choice of charges,
in other words, the grounds for prosecuting
the offender.
- Nature conservation regulations are a good
basis, but they aren’t necessarily the only
or most suitable framework to consider.
- For heavier sentences, it is sometimes best
to refer to other regulations such as the
one relative to carrying firearms, to money
laundering, to tax evasion and so on.
- This can also ensure there will actually
be a sentence, instead of risking dropping
the case due to lack of admissible evidence
or for another reason of prosecution.
- Finally, once the case has been introduced
to the judicial system, it is crucial to follow
up on it.
- In court, crimes related to the environment
aren’t usually considered a priority.
The length of proceedings can sometimes be
extended indefinitely due to failure to follow
up.
This results in charges being dropped because
of mere court inaction.
- Failing to follow up can also lead to multiple
offenders not appearing as such and facing
light sentences instead of the heavier ones
they deserve.
- Reports and evidence can disappear, be lost
or simply never be presented to the judge.
- When investigating a case, you need to master
the following aspects and there are solutions:
i) a good police report, ii) a solid case
and iii) a good follow-up of the investigative
process.
- The most important aspect is strengthening
the skills of all actors involved.
Of protected area managers of course, but
also judges so that they can be aware of the
seriousness of the crime committed.
- Protected area surveillance requires excellent
collaboration with the Public Prosecutor and
the criminal police officers.
- Guidelines can be drawn up to explain how
to write a good report, and which texts to
refer to if needed.
- Using the services of trained investigators
can save a case from failing because of a
technicality, and it will also help following
up on the case throughout the proceedings.
- In these fields, some national and international
NGOs provide useful technical support – the
EAGLE association we mentioned in the MOOC
GAP is a good example.
- In conclusion, let’s remember that it
isn’t reasonable to invest a lot of means
to arrest offenders in the field who will
not be prosecuted anyway.
- Following the case after finding the facts
can seem to be a formality that is not the
manager’s responsibility, but this isn’t
true; if the manager wants to be effective,
he must, with his team, follow the case until
the end.