- Field surveillance in a protected area relies
on different stakeholders with complementary
missions.
Once again, find more information by having
a look at these guidelines.
- Sworn officials are in charge of implementing
police actions.
They are usually recruited at a national level,
especially in State-governed protected areas.
-These agents must be selected according to
strict criteria: physical fitness, endurance,
ability to live in difficult conditions but
also mental capacities and especially their
love for teamwork and ability to follow rules.
- To choose the right selection criteria,
it is important to have identified the needs
you intend to cover.
- The idea isn’t necessarily to look for
qualified people or for people with specific
knowledge, but rather finding individuals
with the ability to work in a field that can
sometimes be very tough.
- Enthusiasm for nature conservation should
be part of the qualities, otherwise staff
rapidly loses their motivation.
- The selection process should also identify
field experience, like some people growing
up in rural areas which can be a great asset
for daily activities.
- Then they must undergo proper training that
is adapted to the context of the protected
area, like the fight against poaching for
example.
There are guidelines explaining the details
of this type of training.
- This practical training should cover all
the aspects of the ranger’s future missions,
and if possible, be carried out in the protected
area he’s been assigned to.
This way, his training can target effective
actions.
- Beyond the initial training, it is important
to maintain a training cycle to face the evolution
of means, but also of threats and of the context.
Over time, this can also be a source of motivation
for rangers and a way to maintain team unity.
- It is important to carefully consider the
number of agents to send out to properly face
the intensity and the dispersal of threats
inside the park.
- Some numbers are often suggested, going
from one agent for 1000 ha to 5000 ha, depending
on the intensity of threats, on the type of
ecosystem and the evolution of obtained results.
There is no absolute rule, the important thing
is to adapt.
- For example, in Tai National Park, there
are around 90 agents for 500,000 ha, in other
words 1 agent for 6000 ha.
This is quite a low number given the park
is mostly a forest.
- Often times, we try to complement the national
personnel pool with local agents with more
direct operational skills.
- These would usually be members of local
community that play different roles in patrolling
teams.
They are often called eco-rangers or eco-volunteers.
- Some are used as trackers or guides, by
making use of their skills in detecting signs
of poaching.
- Others carry out camping tasks, by transporting
supplies and preparing meals.
In Tai, there would be around 1 eco-ranger
for 2 agents per patrolling team.
- Other village stakeholders contribute more
directly to the enforcement of laws, by reporting
those who commissioned the crime.
- They would then receive bonuses for every
piece of information that led to finding a
crime or to the arrest of the commissioner.
We will see this in sequence 5.6.
- Patrol leaders are just as important as
rangers and eco-rangers.
They lead surveillance operations on the ground
and work towards achieving the targets set
by the mission.
- They must be carefully chosen and the criteria
must include personal management skills, good
ethics, excellent experience in the work they
need to carry out, and having received proper
training for the mission.
- The patrol leader can be formally designated
or changed from one patrol to the next.
In any case, he must have respect for and
confidence in his staff.
- Obviously, other bodies of public forces
can be solicited to bring their support and
expertise to deal with situations that exceed
rangers’ capabilities.
- This can be the Police force in the case
of certain legal proceedings, or the army
when the threat requires stronger intervention.
- Regardless, the persons in charge of surveillance
must have authority and responsibility over
surveillance so that the work can be carried
out effectively and fully assessed afterwards