- Just like other activities, surveillance
is part of the protected area management plan.
Have a look at these guidelines for more details.
- For reasons of confidentiality, the description
isn’t very detailed, but main activities
are documented.
- It mainly lists operations to carry out,
it identifies staff needs and skills to strengthen,
facilities that can promote surveillance,
and it explains surveillance’s monitoring-evaluation
and funding.
- An operation plan, usually carried out yearly,
details the activities to implement, with
clear indicators to assess the progress made.
- Surveillance patrol planning is based on
excellent knowledge of the field and of the
distribution of threats in the protected area.
- The area is sometimes zoned to target actions
better and face threats more effectively according
to their nature, their scale, their urgency
and so on.
- In this case, ecological monitoring provides
significant support because it gives information
on human-induced alterations and their location.
- Thus, updating data on the state of conservation
of the protected area steers surveillance
over time.
It is a field that requires adaptive management.
- Intelligence plays a key role.
Information regarding poachers and other park
offenders helps to anticipate their activities.
- Intelligence is therefore not only an opportunistic
activity, but must be planned and organised
to have the desired effects.
- Staff in charge of surveillance must be
adapted to the mission
and it is crucial to organise frequent evaluations
to make sure their skills remain up to date.
- The evaluation should focus on their physical
and mental capacities, on their motivation,
their endurance, on their skills related to
the field and consequently, their need for
training.
- This helps to proceed to new recruitment
phases, reassignments, and training.
All this must be integrated to the operation
plan.
The method of evaluation must be simple and
objective, based on measurable indicators.
- Of course, these rangers’ employment conditions
must be defined beforehand, as well as their
objectives, and indicators to assess.
- To be clear, the mission must be known by
every stakeholder so that he can perfectly
master his area of responsibility.
- In some difficult situations, bonuses or
other types of rewards can motivate agents.
These should be added to the operation plan
and explained to the beneficiaries.
- The role of this is to empower good staff.
A clear and just allocation system must be
developed, based on performance to effectively
target the deserving ones.
- If properly used this tool can be very useful
but it can also be counterproductive otherwise!
- Sometimes, special infrastructure and facilities
are needed to facilitate law enforcement actions
- this must also be added to the operation
plan.
- This includes base camps, stations to get
staff closer to threatened areas, new trails
to enable access, acquiring or maintaining
stock, getting proper communication material,
fences and so on.
- Frequent monitoring-evaluations ensure that
set targets are being achieved.
- Assessment criteria must remain simple,
and be easy to measure.
For example, they can refer to the effective
presence of rangers inside the park in terms
of men per day.
- The coverage ratio of patrols on the protected
area territory.
- The level of involvement of neighbouring
populations through the amount of information
provided or the number of initiatives taken
by communities to prevent infiltrations.
- Measuring animal flight-distance gives an
indication on their confidence, and thereby
on the level of aggression they are facing.
- The number of arrests or evidence of criminal
activity in the protected area and their spatial
distribution.
- The number of convicted people which is
an important indicator as it covers the entire
law enforcement process, from beginning to
end.
- The use of geographical information system
tools can be included to the operation plan
as they enable the collection of information
during patrols.
- These tools are more or less easy to use,
and sometimes, a frequently updated database
is enough.G - Finally, financing surveillance
is a factor that can sometimes limit the operation
plan.
- The State must engage by implementing enough
measures to sustainably manage the protected
area network.
If it doesn’t, financial and technical partners,
NGOs and foundations can help funding the
surveillance.
But this field isn’t the most eligible to
receive their funding, so it is better to
think of sustainable strategies based on lasting
resources, steady incomes or sales of environmental
services to ensure the long term durability
of surveillance.