As we mentioned in the previous sequence,
surveillance operations are subject to strategic
planning in the medium term, usually 3 years.
The strategy can then be implemented yearly
in the form of operation plans.
These plans are based on relevant spatial
and temporal information collected in the
protected area, as well as on the careful
analysis of reports from previous patrols.
A surveillance strategy for each park must
be defined with the stakeholders, by strongly
involving field agents.
This strategy must be very adaptable and able
to anticipate the changes in threats on the
field to avoid being stuck in “reactive”
responsiveness.
The primary objectives of patrols must be
accompanied by specific, measureable, accessible,
realistic indicators that can be achieved
in a certain time.
Tools can be used such as SMART (Spatial Monitoring
and Reporting Tool), a spatial monitoring
and reporting tool.
We will be looking into this later.
A system encouraging staff to achieve these
targets must be instituted to guarantee sustained
commitment of agents for the effective implementation
of the strategy.
Then comes the patrolling, then the collect
and analysis of data collected by these patrols.
It is essential to prepare management and
participants for patrols beforehand.
This preparation ends with a short and clear
briefing of the patrol team.
Every patrol team must be led by a mission
leader with good team management and reporting
skills.
Personal involvement of park managers in patrols
is also a key motivation factor for agents,
and a good way to control their effectiveness.
In Côte d’Ivoire for example, surveillance
activities are implemented at the level of
the Ivorian Parks and Reserves Authority regional
head offices, in other words at a supra park
scale, and they are then executed at the level
of each park.
At the end of patrols, team members are debriefed
to talk about the mission, the results, difficulties
encountered, possible recommendations and
also to plan future actions.
This is also an opportunity to congratulate
agents for the effort accomplished, to potentially
award them and encourage them to pursue this
work while guiding them.
The length of patrols can change, but in practice,
it is recommended not to exceed one week because
longer patrols can be tiring and require longer
recovery time for agents, not to mention their
loss of motivation as days go by.
Surveillance patrols are dissuasive or repressive,
and often require strong presence of agents
on the field.
If we take the example of Côte d’Ivoire,
the types of mission that can be organised
according to the targets to achieve are:
- the standard mission done by a Mobile Brigade
or a team of sector agents (5 usually) at
a fixed station,
- the inter-unit mission which is a monitoring
activity done by at least two Mobile Brigade
units,
- the joint mission which is a monitoring
activity carried out by one Mobile Brigade
unit and sector agents,
- The large scale mission carried out by more
than three Mobile Brigade units over 10 days
within a large protected area like Comoé
park,
- the control mission which is an offence
verification action carried out by at least
5 agents after receiving a piece of information.
Tactically speaking, surveillance must be
adapted to the level of threats faced by the
park.
Patrols can be carried out on foot or in a
motorised vehicle (cars, motorbikes), in an
amphibious vehicle, or with aerial support
(helicopter, plane) thanks to an effective
communication system.
More and more, units specialised in the fight
against poaching are trained to face poachers
when a more aggressive response is required.
These units should undergo more individualised
management compared to the rest of staff,
but they also need training and specific equipment.
They can involve elite (forest commandos)
or specialised units (canine units).
Team mobility must always be guaranteed by
making special travelling material available.
Unit agents should stay in base camps from
where they would carry out their operations,
and relay stations near or in the protected
area can be used to conduct surveillance activities.
In some reserves, surveillance stations are
arranged to receive surveillance agents temporarily
in the context of a rotational system of surveillance
personnel.
Others benefit from a control room that ensures
communication with teams on the field 24 hours
a day, thereby strengthening the effectiveness
of operations.
Certain parks would rather ban any form of
fixed station as they are rapidly identified
by poachers, and agents are prone to fall
into routine or even corruption.
In this case, only mobile teams are kept.
All this depends of course on the context
in which you work.
In the process of surveillance operations,
useful information is collected to guide future
operations, or for investigations to catch
criminals in the act and then prosecute the
arrested individual.
This information also helps writing operation
reports, but also writing police reports related
to the arrested person and make them available
for the public prosecutor.
This information must be collected on files
or smartphones and added to data bases with
spatial references for later use.
Among these databases we can mention the SMART
software which is a spatial surveillance and
reporting tool, specially designed to assess
the effectiveness of patrols and peacekeeping.
Some protected areas with a good cell coverage
use a real time information transferring system,
combining a Cybertracker and a software that
automatically analyses data and generates
a report – this completely automates patrol
monitoring.
This software improves the quality of collected
information and its future prospective use.
This is key to guiding surveillance decisions.
A good geographic information system enables
the achievement of set surveillance targets.
Patrol assessement criteria can include:
- the effective presence of agents in the
park in terms of number of men per day,
- the coverage ratio of each protected area
having undergone patrols,
- the level of implication of neighbouring
populations through the amount of information
provided to denounce aggressions and/or initiatives
taken by communities to prevent infiltrations,
- animal flight distances or evidence proving
the presence or number of mammals which is
an indicator of the level of threats,
- the amount of evidence of aggression in
the protected area,
- the spatial distribution of said evidence
in the protected area,
- the proportion of individuals convicted
etc.
In the next sequence, we will look at what
material is needed to conduct effective surveillance
in a park.