Surveillance relies on suitable material and
equipment to carry out operations on the field.
Field agents with proper individual and collective
equipment have stronger capacities of intervention,
and are more motivated to carry out their
mission.
Individual equipment includes uniforms, raincoats,
tents, sleeping mats and sleeping bags, backpacks,
camel bags, shoes, water bottles and weapons.
If possible, every agent is responsible for
the maintenance of his own equipment.
In Côte d’Ivoire, the State provides agents
with a yearly supply of outfits.
Projects in different parks support the acquisition
for each ranger of an additional outfit like
a tent and a sleeping mat.
Collective equipment ensures the accomplishment
of the mission by facilitating travelling,
bivouac and camping, good communication inside
the patrol team and with the base, but also
the collection of patrolling data.
Proper vehicles are required to facilitate
team travels and to improve responsiveness.
Unit mobility on the entire PA is key to face
aggressions and to ensure the security of
all.
According to the specificities of each park,
vehicles can consist in four-by-fours fitted
with special equipment and traction tools.
Chainsaws are also needed, as well as boats
equipped with life rings, jet skis and bikes
that can also be a good quick response tool.
In some parks, patrols are done with horses,
bicycles and even quads.
In some larger parks like the Kruger in South
Africa, several planes are deployed for proper
surveillance of the territory.
A maintenance and replacement plan guarantees
operational equipment, thereby ensuring agent
mobility at all times.
For bivouac and camping, kits need to be made
available for teams with kitchenware and camping
materials adapted to every type of environment.
These should be easily transportable for foot
patrols.
Food rations can be provided to agents to
ensure their daily food intake.
They can consist in specialised rations, or
in local meals with, if possible, some high-energy
dried foods.
To manage stocks, a good option is to set
menus.
For instance, in Côte d’Ivoire, two methods
are used: food is directly provided by management,
or money is provided so that agents can organise
food rations themselves for patrols.
A first aid kit with medication can also be
provided to each patrol team.
Communication materials include VHF radios
and their accessories or satellite phones,
or cell phones with solar panels and portable
chargers.
Radios enable secure communication with the
possibility to track positions and patrol
teams in real time, but they are expensive
and not always adapted to the forest cover.
For intelligence, digital cameras and voice
recorders can be useful to collect data and
build a case against suspects.
To guide teams on the field and to collect
patrolling data, technical surveillance equipment
is required.
This includes GPSs, compasses, tablets or
digital cameras.
CLIC
In terms of equipment, providing patrol teams
with weapons and ammunition is a real challenge.
Nowadays, poachers’ level of equipment requires
rangers to be properly equipped and trained.
This isn’t always the case in countries
where surveillance is delegated to paramilitary
forces, in spite of weapon training being
provided by the military.
When weapons are made available, an inventory
and strict management and maintenance system
should secure weapons in armouries and keep
them in good working condition.
Carrying out joint patrols with other units
(military, police) is essential when the threat
exceeds the normal intervention capacities
of forest guards.
Finally, infrastructures and facilities must
be designed specifically to facilitate surveillance,
such as base camps or a mechanical garage
for vehicle maintenance, and of course, landing
runways distributed throughout the park for
planes and ULMs.
Basically, to ensure optimal conditions and
effectiveness of surveillance activities,
equipment must always be in good working condition.