Intelligence plays a key role in planning
and implementing surveillance activities.
Information is indeed key to improving law
enforcement.
It helps to implement a preventive strategy,
planning and implementing better targeted
operations and carrying out more effective
cases against criminals.
However, the implementation and operation
of an effective intelligence system in protected
areas are often defective.
Intelligence must be conducted by dedicated
units, with personnel who is able to collect
and analyse data on crimes related to wild
species, and with all the technical, technological
and financial means at hand to effectively
accomplish their mission.
It is essential to work with the police and
other State security services to exchange
information useful to the investigation, as
well as getting support from NGOs or other
local community organisations.
Data collection relies on a discreetly managed
network of informants who remain anonymous
for their own protection.
These individuals are usually from the neighbouring
communities, but can really be any person
who has information (poachers, agents, merchants,
tourists etc.).
A system of incentives must encourage the
sharing of information: a financial or in-kind
award can be given to the person who helped
arresting the criminal.
In Côte d’Ivoire, if an information has
helped arresting a poacher, the informant
gets a financial compensation only if the
poacher is sentenced in court.
In such a system, proceedings must be carried
out until the end, with a solid case that
would not allow the defendant to be freed.
The system of incentives must therefore encourage
the provision of relevant information, especially
coming from people specialised in the matter.
If the award isn’t encouraging enough, the
risk is that informants give information on
agent plans to poachers or gold diggers.
Once collected, the information must be put
in a data base where they can be consulted
and analysed to plan patrols.
When there is a lot of information, it is
recommended to use specialised software, or
to make them more available to all levels
of park management.
Otherwise, in most cases, a table or a database
like Microsoft Access is enough.
A good intelligence system helps to collect
evidence better, and aims at officially prosecuting
the offender.
In some countries, when guards have found
a crime scene (and secured it), an investigative
unit specialised in environmental crimes is
in charge of carrying out investigations in
partnership with the police if needed.
This is the case in Kruger National Park in
South Africa, where agents collect and manage
all the evidence to build solid and effective
investigative cases.
Thereby, intelligence must also be subject
to standard operational proceedings to guide
the collection and the treatment of evidence
by investigators, as well as actions of different
actors before patrols.
Even though it is often neglected, intelligence
is a key factor of patrolling success, and
a relevant way to lower costs by allowing
better targeted and more suitable planning.
Studies have shown that informed patrols have
30 times more chances to find poachers than
simple patrols carried out at random.