New technologies can improve the effectiveness
of law enforcement in protected areas.
There is enormous unexplored potential, but
this sequence will only provide a short overview
of what is already out there.
Have a look at these websites to find out
more, especially on the WCPA website which
has a working group on new technologies.
So let’s focus on a couple of the most commonly
used solutions.
One vital aspect of these technologies is
their ability to connect with each other and
create a rapid flow of information.
Thereby providing a proper response in due
time.
This is a limiting factor in remote areas
where there is no cellular network.
But there are always relay solutions based
on private radio networks, or other technologies
like drones or satellites.
Another key aspect is data treatment automation
that frees up time for practical action.
This is based on the development of softwares
that can do a job better and faster than a
person would.
They can, for example, analyse hundreds of
hours of video to find a specific animal in
just a couple of minutes.
On this basis: 1- connectivity and 2- automation.
Many solutions are being developed.
They aim at protecting a territory or a species,
improving surveillance practices and tools,
reinforcing detection, information and communication
abilities as well, and ranger or visitor safety.
At a larger scale, satellites can be used
for surveillance…
namely by detecting changes in the habitat
or forest fires,
by monitoring a species equipped with a transmitter,
and even detect deep sea fishing.
One example of practical use is the cybertracker.
It is based on the GPS system which gives
the exact location of where the infringement
was detected – it is used in addition to
software such as SMART.
Closer to the ground, the use of drones is
spreading.
They are equipped with detectors, and can
virtually search and find anything you want.
They can have rotary wings, in which case
they are generally used to explore certain
perimeters with relatively low autonomy.
They can also have fixed wings, and in this
case, they are able to cover hundreds of hectares.
this is especially the case for solar-powered
models.
These drones can also be a relay for information
transmission when there is no connectivity
in the park.
For example, by overflying camera traps daily,
and by downloading the data obtained.
Even closer to the ground, sensors can be
deployed.
They would capture the information and transmit
it.
A good example are the camera traps which
we talked about in the MOOC on ecological
monitoring, which can be connected to a base
that receives all the images and videos.
A simple recognition software would then directly
process the photos and videos and extract
the ones, for example, where a human is detected
to immediately inform the anti-poaching patrol.
Acoustic transmitters can also be used – they
detect chainsaws, gun shots, human voices
or engine sounds.
They inform rangers in real time with the
exact location of the sound through simple
triangulation.
Sensors detect the vibrations on the ground
and send notifications when a vehicle drives
by.
The vehicle would then be followed by a drone
for identification, then by a patrol to arrest
the intruder.
Infra-red cameras placed at park access-points
detect body heat at night.
A recognition software will then distinguish
human from animal shapes, and alert security
rangers.
Nowadays, there are mobile towers thanks to
which these cameras can be moved when needed,
and elevated to enable a better coverage of
the area.
There are more and more solutions that contribute
to daily animal protection.
Tracking collars, radios, GPSs and satellites
adapt to large species.
Not only do they track their movements, but
also their biological parameters which detects
periods of stress to enable immediate action.
The same goes for microchips that can be implanted
to many animal or plant species such as a
tree trunk,
so that the day this tree is cut down and
moved, the chip will follow the movement of
the trunk and its location by sending notifications
through the cellular network.
Elephant collars, rhino bracelets, tags for
birds, chips on trees, drones for mapmaking,
radars for surveillance, specialised sensors
to detect movement, sound and heat, software
adapted to smartphones…
All these solutions already exist in the field
in Africa, and are being tested in Namibia,
Malawi, Kenya, South Africa, Burkina Faso,
Benin etc.
At another scale, DNA analysis during seizures,
wherever they occur, can trace back to when
the crime was committed, thanks to a worldwide
coded database of the different species.
This way, the point of origin of a rhino horn
or a shark fin can be found!
Science-fiction or near future, some projects
are developing mimetic robots that can place
automated guards near species for 24/7 protection
on the ground.
Possibilities are countless, and this already
shakes up law enforcement methods in protected
areas.