We’ve reached the end of our MOOC on law
enforcement.
I hope it met your expectation and helped
you understand what fields law enforcement
covers inside our protected areas.
The idea was to look at the legal documents
that apply to the conservation of these territories,
to understand where they come from, their
scope, their limitations…
To master the meaning of key concepts such
as values, ethics, deontology and corruption,
…but also to know the rules and procedures
to give and follow orders and instructions
properly.
And finally, we’ve seen how to translate
this in a park through surveillance and the
fight against poaching.
Of course, I would like to thank the speakers
involved in this MOOC: Lydia Slobodian, Philippe
Gitz and Benoit Koutoua Amon.
I’m not forgetting the PAPACO team, the
staff of the Digital Education Centre, and
our friends at MOOCs for Africa at the EPFL
without whom this programme wouldn’t even
exist.
If you have any suggestions to improve this
MOOC, please feel free to share them with
us.
And of course, stay connected by following
our other MOOCs, and by visiting papaco.org
and our Facebook page.
You can sign up to the NAPA newsletter if
you wish to stay in touch month after month.
Finally, I must also thank the organisations
that financed this MOOC.
The Ecole Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne
and the France-IUCN partnership, particularly
the French Development Agency.
C
There, I do hope we’ll be in touch again
through our other MOOC.
Have a great day!