All over the world, law enforcement is a key
aspect of protected area management.
These territories are indeed filled with values
to protect.
This protection is based on rules and regulations
defining what should be conserved and how.
Ethical, moral and professional principles
must be followed to implement these rules,
and strict methods must be used to give, assess
and execute orders.
On the field, all this is reflected in best
practices leading to good results.
This MOOC will cover all these topics over
5 modules that will help us:
1- know the laws, conventions, rules applicable
… their rank, their scope and their limitations.
2- discover the principles that go with
them, ethics in particular…
3- conversely, assess the disastrous impact
of corruption…
4- and understand the importance of precision
when giving orders.
5- Finally, illustrate how this is reflected
concretely in protected area surveillance.
We will present these modules with different
experts, namely lawyer, police officer, PA
manager.
Videos, quizzes, documents to read, a forum
to exchange, a Facebook group, online discussions. Everything
is ready for you to progress at your own pace.
There are no pre-requisites for registration.
And of course, you’ll have the possibility
to take the exams and receive a certificate
of completion.
There, join us now to explore this key aspect
of protected area management.
See you very soon!