So in this series of videos,
we're going to talk about
languages, language design in particular.
Domain-specific languages,
and engineered languages for one,
declarative languages,
and we're also going to talk about
interpretation, and compiler, and
interpreted side of programming languages,
and programming systems.
In this lecture, in this
video in particular,
we're going to start with
talking about engineered languages.
And the first thing
I would like to observe is,
there's actually a connection between
how systems people view computation
as a resource, and how
complexity theorists look at this.
So if you look into
the Saltzer Kaeshoek textbook,
you'll find among
system resources mentioned,
computation, memory, and messaging.
And that's a smart observation
because in a strong sense,
the analogous observation has been made
in computation complexity theory,
that there is fundamental resources
for computation
which are time,
space against memory use,
and computation complexity.
How much messaging is necessary
to actually get a job done
in this one scenario.
So these dimensions are not
completely orthogonal, not quite.
So for example, the time complexity
can be at most exponentially high
to the space complexity
of the computation.
Why? Well think of a big
memory system even right?
As a huge finite state machine,
which it is, as a localized system.
Unless you extend the hardware,
you got only so many states.
Now, if you take so much memory,
let's say, megabytes
or something like that,
there's only exponentially many states
in that size of the data
So if you've got n bits,
that are different.
there's 2 to the n different states
that these n bits can be in.
If you're talking about
the entire system's mutable state,
so that includes not just the RAM,
but also all the caches,
the registers etc.
Everything that belongs to the state
of such a computer.
So if you take this, this entire state,
and you've got n bits now,
n could be a huge number.
Then there's only 2 to the n
different things I can store.
So if you have a computation
that changes the state, and iterates,
and it gets stuck in the same state
and doesn't change anymore,
that's the final state.
We're talking about well-behaved programs
that the program, let's say, terminates.
Then after, at most, 2 to the n
computation steps,
you must get into a state
that you've already been in.
So understand there was an accepting state
you had stopped in before
you are in an infinite loop.
So that way, we see that time cost of any
well-behaved computation that terminates,
can be at most exponentially larger
than the space cost we have.
But leaving these aside,
these are the fundamental resources.
And once we have thought of it that way,
we can start kind of engineering
for a purpose. Because, remember,
there's this notion of
Turing-complete languages.
And basically, there's this so-called
Church-Turing thesis.
You have to decide something that
you cannot really prove in that sense.
But you see, that there's really
no computation possible
beyond what can be done
by a Turing machine.
And you have also seen
that many different models
correspond to Turing machines,
including, you know, our CPUs.
And it's very easy to write
a programming language
that is Turing-complete.
So all you really need is something like
unbounded looping,
if-then-else branching, and memory.
And you basically get a Turing machine.
Now you can actually argue
that in corner cases,
there's actually something
beyond the Church-Turing thesis.
For example, if you have a way
of generating true random numbers,
you actually add power.
Or the so-called Interaction machine.
If you have, you can make a physical
network of computers,
and this physical connection
means quantum effects
physical effects that makes things
unpredictable.
They get random delays, and so on,
that are truly random.
Out of the systems control.
And you add power.
Not really maybe useful power.
But probably you do, because you have
a way of generating true random numbers,
which you cannot do in a completely
deterministic system otherwise.
So this is this notion of Turing-complete,
and it becomes very useful.
Things that you think of
as classic programming language,
they are all Turing-complete languages.
C, Java, Scala, etc.
Now, you could artificially restrict
the languages.
For example, you could talk about saying
computation can only take so much time.
Or so much space,
as a function of the input size.
So you can talk about
the complexity class, time,
f of n for n the input size,
and f is some function.
For example,
polynomial functions.
That would be big o of n to the k.
The k is some constant.
That would be polynomials.
Polynomial time.
So we have heard this
in complexity theory lectures, right?
And you can think about
engineering language
to capture such complexity class.
You could also do this for space.
Or for messaging
as communication complexity.
For example, you could take
Loop-and-recursion-free Java.
And that's going to have
bounded running time.
Or you could have
Conditionals-free Java
that has no ability
to make true decisions.
So memory and time consumption
may be unbounded,
but you cannot really compute much.
So this unbounded computation
will not do anything of interest.
Or space-bounded Turing machines
for example, Datalog.
It has actually
bounded memory consumption.
We're going to see more about this.
Now let's think about
the domain-specific languages.
Now, what does that mean?
Well we have talked about
engineering languages
for a program while restricting it.
For example, if it doesn't consume
more resources than a particular amount.
That's one way of thinking about it.
That way you've got, generally,
less than Turing-completeness,
and it may still be acceptable.
That way, for example,
you're guaranteed a polynomial time
restricted class can only complete
a computation that runs with
polynomial time as it's terminating time.
That means, it cannot cost too much.
That might be good, right?
But let's pull at this abstract argument
about cost.
You might also do it
for a particular domain.
You've got a certain domain,
let's say, biology,
and you want to do certain kind of
biological computations,
or simulations, or so,
you might create
a domain-specific programming language
to make certain programming
in certain domains particularly easy.
You could think of SQL
as a domain-specific language
for the purpose of data-querying.
Out of the people who know databases,
people usually
call a domain something else,
like their business domain, or so.
Something like that.
And then the schema would be specific.
But from a different view point,
more high level,
you could say, well,
there's a domain of querying.
And for that, you got a domain-specific
language engineered for a purpose.
SQL is not Turing-complete.
It's weaker, and you get
something out of it.
The programming of those
typical jobs gets easier
because the language's constraint
doesn't allow it to do other things.
So you are guided along
as helped by the language design
what you're going to do. Usually you
are going to be more productive.
And certain things
that the language is designed for
will be very easy to write,
and short to write, so to say.
The goal of domain specific languages
can be of so much help
that typical tasks, tasks that support
the language,
are usually shorter than in
the general purpose language.
So there is growth
that you can achieve that way,
that are desirable.
High levels of abstraction.
You don't have to,
in a specific language,
that is, for example,
only about matrix computation,
there's no need to talk about,
maybe, some low-level
implementation details, and so on.
You may have matrix operations,
like multiplications and so on,
in that language.
And it's a seperation of concern
from low level aspects.
In a database query,
like SQL query language,
there's no need to have graphics,
and there's no need
for sockets and things like that.
A query might be distributed
but that happens below the hood.
So abstraction, seperation of concern,
are a big critieria for design of DSLs.
Domain-specific languages.
Simplicity and programmer
productivity, as we said,
by making the language
designed for a purpose,
you can make typical computations
shorter there.
And you can concisely capture
the essence of the system.
You can make it impossible
to program something
that is not intended to be programmed.
And that can allow you avoid bugs,
or do malicious code of some kind,
and things like that.
And that's, of course, also desirable.
Now, how do you capture the essence?
So you have to ask,
for the kind of system
that you want to support, or build,
or have a language for,
to kind of make it flexible,
what language would you need?
Remember that,
even graphical user inferfaces,
are actually languages,
they're visual languages.
So drag-and-drop, or moving files
on a device level,
they are basically
operations of a language.
And you can write programs that way.
And so are APIs, together with protocols.
Constraints on using them.
So these are languages designed
and engineered for a purpose.
So let's think about,
what do DSLs usually look like?
Well, many DSLs are actually
logic-based in nature.
SQL is one, we will have much more
to say about this later.
And conversely, most logic-based
languages are non Turing-complete.
Exception would be actually Prolog.
So you can create the DSL,
restricting an existing general-purpose
Turing-complete language.
Or, and maybe add a library
of domain-specific data structures
and methods to create the
domain-specific vocabulary.
For example, I could take Scala,
and say I would like to make it
the MATLAB style language
for kind of matrix computations
by saying, add a library
for matrix computations.
So there's a matrix datatype that is new,
and there is matrix multiplications,
and inversions, and operations
like this. Add it new.
And then in turn I forbid certain things,
like let's say, other certain datatypes,
they are forbidden to create lists,
for example.
We could do that, for example.
But if you have user-control
structures, and so on,
we might have individual
floating point numbers,
to take them out of reals and so on,
it can loop over things, etc.
And that would be a DSL.
And how do we get this?
It's basically a subset
of a general purpose language,
you take a language, you say,
maybe you forbid some feature,
you don't permit them,
and you add a library.
So that's one way to do that.
Why would you bother with this?
Well, obviously, such a language
might be easier to use.
And these restrictions
limit the search space
that a human has to explore
in their minds,
or in their brains, to find
the right program.
And it makes it easier
for unsophisticated users to program.
So for example, SQL is a language
that business people can deal with
that have not really learned
programming properly.
Also, such restrictions may make
certain optimization / analyses possible,
that are not possible, unfeasible
for general-purpose languages.
For example, there are certain logics,
for which equivalence of two
logical formulas is desirable,
or whether a formula is satisfiable.
It is undesirable to tell any
industrial property or general-purpose
programming language, like C,
for example, where it halts.
Or some general-purpose
correctness properties.
It is impossible to tell
for this very powerful language.
But by making the language smaller,
and restricting things,
you might be able to tell such things.
So you can, for example,
for a fragment of SQL,
not full SQL,
it's desirable to find
the smallest possible equivalent
program query in that language.
So why is this non-trivial?
Well, given a query of a certain size,
there's only finitely many
shorter queries.
But testing whether shorter queries
are equivalent to my query,
in general, is undesirable, even for SQL,
and certainly it's undesirable for C,
where two C programs
that were written independently
are equivalent for all possible
inputs. Undesirable.
But for restricted languages,
maybe desirable.
For example, for SELECT FROM WHERE
restricted fragment queries in SQL,
this is desirable.
So, again, a few more words about
interface versus language design.
You can really think of interface
and languages interchangeably.
In a sense, you can think of DSL
update by the general-purpose language
adding a particular kind of API
and library to it.
A bit like what you heard in visualization
about taking, so to say,
above the operating systems,
a Unix-like operating system.
you've got simpler machine language,
plus you've got a POSIX system calls.
It's extended, it's a library of things,
and this extends from the viewpoint
of an application program in a
Unix operating system,
that kind of, the language itself.
And you get a DSL
for Unix programming, so to say.
Now, so when you design
an interface, or a language,
you can switch backward
and forward between
this viewpoint of design language,
design the interface.
And it may help you to do a better job.
Of course, through layering,
creates interpreter stacks.
If you layer these kind of languages
on top of each other,
you get a stack of interpreters.
By the way, if you take a DSL
defined as a general-purpose
programming language,
plus a library, and that's your DSL,
notion here, the term used is,
that's called a "shallowly embedded" DSL.
So, I've mentioned SQL several times now.
It's probably the most successful
example of a DSL, so far.
So let me just say, we will talk
more about this concept of
declarative languages later,
But here's an example.
So we've got a language,
an example query in SQL that says,
SELECT student names, and course names,
and the grades of courses taken,
FROM triples of students tables,
courses tables, and taken tables.
Such that the student ID, the ID
of the student and the student relation
is the same as the student ID
and the taken relation,
and the taken course ID is the same
as the course ID, in the course.
So we say these two 'join', so to say.
If you're a database expert,
that's very obvious,
otherwise you might not completely
understand it from that description,
but the important thing is,
it is a very declarative statement here.
I say, SELECT what I want,
which comes to end in a WHERE clause,
and so on, but I'm not saying
how to compute it.
That's completely happening
under the hood of the database system.
So this is a declarative language.
And it's super successful, there are
huge, multi-billion dollar industry,
like the big part of the IT industry
really, because, I mean,
databases play a role
in all these applications, and SAP
and things like that.
There's a huge hardware and consulting
market around
so this is a gigantic market
for computer science.
And it really drives this nowadays.
And to some extent, it was an accident
that this happened,
because there was this gentleman
Ed Codd at IBM,
who advocated for
relational database systems.
Logic-based, with a clean
theoretical foundation.
And nobody wanted to hear that, really.
At that time, IMS was the big thing,
of the relational database systems,
something that has now almost died,
except for legacy systems
that you as a student probably
don't see very soon, but these,
so IBM, the management,
the marketing people,
were not particularly interested.
They were not convinced
by the implementations
that this kind of relational
database abstraction,
and declarative languages like this,
and so on, were such a good idea.
And what happened is, at some point
you want to deliver some product,
and IMS wasn't ready next version
and just a relational database
server was ready.
And that's how it got out, and then
it got lots of people started liking it.
So, and the nice thing is also that,
it's not just a query language
and things are easy to understand,
and you say "what", rather than "how",
and you don't have to have
technical skills.
Instead, the purpose of the
computer optimizing the system
to turn this into good execution scheme.
It's very short, and very succinct.
And it's only what queries.
You cannot write
something else in the query
in this kind of select statement.
So you cannot write evilly-behaved things.
You cannot really write a virus.
You might do something
like denial of service attack
on the database system
by just writing a very expensive query.
You could do that.
You cannot do graphs, you cannot really
make a graphical computer game in SQL.
But the very restricted scheme
and syntax of the language
makes it very easy to direct it
towards correct programs.
And it takes little skill to use it.
So that's of course a big success.
So we're going to talk
much more about this later.
But first, as a next step,
we're going to talk
a little more about interpretation.