So, to explain the distinction
between compilation and interpretation,
this is a bit difficult and artificial
because the distinction has been changing,
and, things have been converging
with time.
But from a certain viewpoint,
I could say compilation
is bulk translation between languages
and execution at the end.
So, that means I statically combine once
and then I might, as a whole,
execute in that translated form already.
A compiler from A to B,
will take an input in language A,
produce an output in language B
and then we can execute that program
in language B whenever we want,
as many times as we like.
And interpretation,
that's the kind of translation on the fly,
we do the translation transaction
operation by operation,
or statement by statement
of the language
then immediately execute it,
so to say.
It's one viewpoint, of course,
you can look at it from a different angle.
In the past, there was a great distinction
between compilers and interpreters,
but recently we have seen these kind
of staged ecosystems,
where there are all kinds
of hybrids happening
and multiple stages of compilation
and interpretation happen.
So, this, for example, has become
a lot more subtle.
Also, because there might be all kinds
of levels of virtualization
on all kinds of levels,
that might be akin
to interpretation or not.
The staging that is just-in-time
compiles special occasions
on (inaudible) distinction.
So, there are a number of terms
that are related.
Simulation, interpretation, emulation
and virtualization.
We've heard discussion of emulation
and virtualization, right?
Emulation is one of the tasks
maybe also virtualization,
emulation is of existing real hardware.
While you could say interpretation
is for programs.
Simulation essentially captures all of it.
Simulation is typically used, for example,
simulating the physical world
a biological system
or things like that.
So, all these terms
it makes sense to talk about.
So, we've seen in the previous module
about and heard about virtual machines
and virtualization,
there are, of course,
language virtual machines
specifically like the famous
Java virtual machine.
And they have a somewhat different
purpose from the typical purposes
of virtualization infrastructure.
They're primarily in place
to support things
like late binding and late compilation:
adaptive computation.
And to bring forth portability of code.
For example Java bytecode
is a language
for which there are virtual machines
that can execute this Java bytecode
on many different architectures.
So, we can use the same kind
binary codes, or pre-compiled codes,
loaded code on many
different architectures,
so it's very portable.
And that's the goal
of this virtual machine.
And it's less to virtualize resources.
It's less the task of a language
virtual machine.
So, language centric VMs also sometimes
don't really feel like machines.
Well, you could argue that
a virtual machine for Java bytecode
does feel like such a virtual machine,
but there's also, for example,
relational database managers
and career engines,
that you can think of as relational
algebra virtual machines, right?
Or that (inaudible)
some of them are very language-centric,
and these languages
are distinct from what you would think of
as something like a CPU,
so that it's reasonable to think of
it in different ways.
Let's talk about a few principles
of the context of interpretation
as a goal itself.
And one is, you know,
we want to interpret
to realize additional levels
of indirection.
So, we can use a virtual machine
or interpret a high-level language
to be machine-independent,
as we said, portability.
The system becomes portable
and can be separated
from legacy system components.
And Java Virtual Machine is an example.
When we are inlining a compilation result
is too big or too costly
to build in hardware.
An example would be microcode,
to delay a system's becoming legacy.
So, we want to support scripting, right?
On one hand you could write
a fixed, monolithic system,
adjust that a certain drop.
Or we could make it scriptable,
so that it accepts some kind
of permit authorization.
Permit authorization could be
flexible enough that you can
think of it as programmable,
first the parameter file,
but there is some kind of scripting way
to extend the modifier
to keep the system fresh.
So, that's a way of really fighting legacy
in the sense that you could argue
that any system
is not scripting at all,
is already a legacy system.
Of course there are
many examples of scripting.
We've seen many cases
and, of course, you can think
of scripting languages
as domain-specific languages, right,
and often enough they are easier to use.
That's why, for example, many first year
programming courses
nowadays in the US
use Python,
because you don't have to worry
about typing any more,
it's relatively easy to use and so on,
it's quite robust and so on.
Of course there are things
like the UNIX shell and command line tool,
which is really getting
scripting capabilities
in a sense to an operating system.
Or in database query processing,
is a set sequel engine.
Or that's maybe contestable,
but I could argue that maybe open floor
and software-defined networking
are a bit like this.
Particularly if it's flexible enough
that you can really script them,
it's not just some in parameters.
Another principle I already mentioned
in some ways, is staged compilation.
Once you have the ability to interpret
and make your way
from a program in a high-level language,
let's say, which you have programmed
to the machine code that is executing,
if you can make it multiple stages,
you have additional potential,
for example, for being adaptive
and being more efficient.
Classically, we had the choice maybe
to take either this kind of high-level
host language program
and run the interpreter
instruction by instruction,
apply its kind of template translation
and execute that.
Or a compiler could statically
take the input code
and produce machine code.
And there were things like Java,
where you go write Java bytecode,
you compile, statically, offline
to Java bytecode,
and that's what you ship
and that's what people see
and there's a lower virtual machine
that is rather efficient already.
But that machine might have behaved
like an interpreter
and more recently there was actually
a just-in-time compilation,
JITing happening.
Rather than taking the bytecode
and executing it instruction by instruction
like a machine,
we would still have
a low-level compilation
to real machine code
and it's done once and for example
you compile the loop once
rather than translate it every time
you execute for its instructions.
And there's of course potential there,
particularly since at that point in time
you might actually know quite a lot
about your data,
and might use this to further
do some loop unrolling,
or fusions and so on, inlining,
to actually make things more efficient.
On the other hand, concretely
for Java bytecode,
this actually doesn't work so well,
because Java bytecode is missing
type information
that would actually be very important
to do useful optimization
actually right now they're working
on changing the standards here,
to actually make more optimization happen
by having a typed version
of intermediate language.
So, of course, these kind of managed codes
that are run in a virtual machine,
can buffer for many kinds of protections,
memory protections,
garbage-collected memory
so that you don't have to worry
about memory leaks in a sense.
Memory protections, in a sense,
that you can't do overflows
or writing of protected memory
and so on.
Catch alloc-dealloc bugs and so on.
Array bound checking and so on.
Things like that.
So, you can get additional protection
and avoid certain bugs,
or at least damages resulting
from the bugs by such a system.
It does some debugging for you
so to say.
Now, some examples of such staging.
As we've already said, Java VM,
particularly Java Hotspot.
It's a really now supporting a compilation
a static compilation
and a virtual machine that does JITing
and adaptive optimizations in there.
It's hard.
LLVM is not a very famous framework
that is based on the C language,
and creating a new C compiler,
that actually basically compiles C code
in an intermediate, low-level presentation
in static single-assignment form.
Something, again, like a bytecode
representation,
in which there are actually tools
for doing all kind of analysis
and optimizations,
and also just-in-time compilation
to run the thing.
LMS, lightweight modular staging,
is something that has been developed
(inaudible)
and lives in the Scala ecosystem,
the Java ecosystem.
It's again staged compilation,
where you can basically lift
any Scala code,
you can easily write DSLs,
but basically making a superset
of the subset of Scala,
and adding new operations
or new library functions etc.
And you can stage compilation.
Every piece of code can be lifted
during presentation
and then you can have,
multiple stages of translation,
optimization, transformation
that might go from a lifted version
to a lift first,
so you can use
as many steps as you like
and at some point you emit code,
or you actually execute it.
So, you can build all kinds of multi-level
just-in-time compilers
and things like that
if you like.
So, there is this myth
that high-level languages
are necessarily less efficient.
If you write something in C,
it will be always faster
if you do a good job
and if you are competent,
than writing it, let's say,
in Java or Scala.
Although to some extent this is true
if you do a perfectly competent job,
but we have already seen,
for example, in register allocation
that a C compiler nowadays
outperforms even the best humans.
So, we won't even try to write
assembly code any more,
because in the time of your multi-core
super Scala, superpipeline processors,
it's actually, too hard for a human
to do this in practice.
It's impractical; C compilers
beat the humans nowadays.
And we're getting to do this somehow, slowly,
all the formal high-level language
and high-level aspects of compilation.
So, it's not necessary that we're slow.
For example, if you have heavy
allocation/deallocation of small objects,
continuously changing that,
and every time, for example, in C
you go through malloc,
which has huge overheads as a system code
to the writing system and so on,
lots of things happen there.
This can actually be much slower
than if you actually in bulk
allocate a big region of space
and then have your own management.
As, for example, the Java
virtual machine does it for you.
If you, for example, write heavily dynamic
data structure transformations
and so on in C++,
you won't actually be beaten
by Java off the shelf.
Another thing is that
the more high-level you are,
the more time and cycles you have left,
because you spend less time coding,
to actually improve
and add more intelligence
into your code, so to say
which then your system
can profit from.
A classical example here,
is the Singularity operating system,
from Microsoft,
which is an operating system,
written completely
in a high-level language,
actually a fragment--
a dialect of C#,
and that runs in a virtual machine
in the CLI,
the Common Language Interface.
And they have done all kinds
of interesting optimizations
and, actually, this operating system
beats classical operating systems,
even developed, implemented
like Linux, very substantially.
For example, process overheads.
Once you start implementing
your applications
and even in the operating system itself,
it is high-level language,
which is done in Singularity,
you've got the potential
for static analysis on this high-level,
for example, for merging processes
that don't need to be separate.
That you don't put into the process
switching all the time
in the operating system.
One thing it does
is called software isolated processes,
which are not isolated processes
at (inaudible) any more,
but it's compiled and you verify
that nothing bad can happen,
and then you don't have to do
so much process switching between them,
which is actually very expensive.
Switching the context in and out
and so on, for an operating system.
You can actually get better performance
in a high-level language
because of modern technology,
modern compilers and language technology
and because we've got more cycles
for doing intelligent optimizations,
because it's less code to write.