So there was an old belief in biology
that a self-describing program,
so to say, is actually not possible.
So the idea, the argument is,
if my genetic code
captures my full complexity,
it must occupy all my space, right?
How could I, where's any space left for me,
for myself, for that life form?
So it was actually an argument
against some pure mechanism
for biology and life.
And that there wasn't a need
for divine intervention
for life to exist
and actually to even procreate.
We know now, of course,
particularly in computer science
because we have learned
this from the start,
that this is a silly argument, right?
And if you look at molecular genetics
and life, these are machines, right?
There is the DNA that stores
our genetic code, right?
And there's transcription
of the DNA into messenger RNA
to transport our relevant genetic
information out of the cell's core
to a place where the messenger RNA
can be turned into a protein, right?
So that RNA travels to this factory,
protein factory, the ribosomes
which are themselves
collections of proteins, right?
And there, the mRNAs
turn the copy it onto a protein.
And these proteins
that you produce that way
are responsible
for all the mechanisms in life
including protein construction
and transcription and copying
and preserving the DNA.
This becomes
a self-perpetuating machine.
And that's a machine in addition
to the genetic code, of course, right?
And it's computation,
it's biological computation here.
So this is not coming
as a great surprise to us.
In computer science
we're actually used to this.
And you've probably heard
of self-replicating programs.
Let's take an example in English first.
Look at this: Write two copies of the
following sentence the second in quotes.
And then in quotes,
"Write two copies
of the following sentences,
the second in quotes."
If you think of interpret executing this,
you get the program back as an output.
Or similarly, the next line
is such a thing in C.
You get basically a C program
that outputs itself,
not trying to go into a file system
and reading this and so on.
It actually produces itself.
Now there is another term
in the context of theory,
the notion of a universal Turing machine
that really is able to self-integrate
in the sense that a Turing machine
that can execute description as data
on the tape of a Turing machine.
So it's an interpreter for
Turing machine by itself, right?
This is of course an important
notion, right?
Obviously this can be done
because Turing machines
especially in the changeable, let's say C,
where we can write such interpretive
that write themselves, right?
The important thing is that
these Turing machines
that are still universal
can be made very simple.
If you're not consisting of binary tapes
but after I think seven symbols,
different ones, then actually there's
a two-state universal Turing machine,
which is quite crazy to imagine, right?
So you can write that way interpreters
for Turing complete languages as well.
Now it's worth thinking about
self-interpretation
in the context of these paradoxes
that you might have heard about,
like Russell's paradox, right?
It's meant to be a set theory
but the popular description is, you know,
the barber shaves everybody
who doesn't shave himself.
And the question is,
does the barber shave himself?
If you think about this,
this leads to a paradox.
Now there's this famous
undecidability of the halting problem.
I'm sure you have learned about this
in the theory course.
So the halting problem is the question,
given a program,
can we tell whether this program
will terminate in all possible inputs?
Now we can, on these slides,
give you complete proof very simple
by self-interpretation
that shows by contradiction
that the halting problem is undecidable.
There cannot be a program
that decides the halting problem.
So how do you do this?
So let's assume there exists
a procedure "does_halt" function
that takes some code and says,
yes, it holds all inputs or not.
So let's assume
that this procedure exists.
Then let's look at this procedure
I've just written down here,
the two-part paradox,
and what it does is the following.
It takes some piece of code,
it's a string or a file,
and it tests if "does_halt",
this conjectured method
for checking the halting problem,
says yes on that code, then loop forever.
Otherwise, exit.
You can actually do that, right?
This is actually a program.
And on some random code,
it will do something maybe reasonable.
It's not a very useful program
because when it halts,
it gets into the infinite loop,
but whatever.
Think about the case that a code
that it receives is its own code, right?
Well if it's its own code basically,
in that case that the halting problem
says yes, then it doesn't
halt this code, right?
And if it says no, then it halts.
Which is a contradiction, right?
So it means that "does_halt" program
must have been incorrect,
so it cannot exist.
There cannot be a correct solution
for the halting problem.
It's a simple consequence of
even very limited programming languages
being powerful enough that such questions
have become nonsensical, right?
Which is unintuitive at first
because you think it is an actually
reasonable question.
It's even useful.
That's the halting problem..
You could avoid code that
gets into infinite loops, right?
But no, it doesn't make sense.
And this is self-interpretation, right?
And that was a complete proof actually.
Now the next thing is not about really
self-interpretation
but it's a step to the following slide
which again is, right?
So how about composing translators?
It's compilers, right?
Compilers are obviously functions, right?
They take programs in language A
to programs in language B, right?
And functions can be composed.
So if you've got a compiler
that compiles from A to B language
and a compiler that compiles
from language B to C,
then together composed they give us
a compiler from A to C.
And the same way for interpreters.
You can stack interpreters
and that way get any sequence
and any composition of interpreters.
And of course that is much easier
in a sense then the stacking
of virtual machines that you've heard
about in the virtual machine module
because we can assume that layers
between the interpreters are complete.
And they're completely protected
from each other.
We don't have to worry about deep down
some operation doing something bad.
Now this kind of composition
we can use for bootstrapping compilers.
The hesitation is the following,
the problem is the following,
suppose you've got a new programming
language, let's say Scala.
Nobody has ever written any translator
or interpreter for Scala.
You've just come up with this design.
How do you make a compiler
for it relatively easily?
One thing you could do of course
is you could write that compiler
in machine code but that
sounds like a wasteful effort, right?
What you could do
is you could take some compiler
another high-level language
which via a chain of compilers
where it leads down
all the way to machine code.
For example, a C compiler.
So you could write your compiler
for Scala in C.
Now after a while you might say,
"Well, I want to make better features.
I want to improve the optimizations.
And I want to make this a more
powerful compiler
but I've got a working
compiler written in C."
So what I can do is I can
rewrite that compiler in Scala.
Probably less code and easily
maintainable and so on
because it's more productive.
And then, I can throw away
the source code of the first C compiler.
I can take the Scala to Scala compiler
compile it with that Scala to C compiler
all the way down the machine code.
That way I've got a model
as good as the latest implementation
of the Scala compiler,
Scala compiler to machine code,
and then I can throw away
everything I had
about that Scala to C compiler, right?
And then in the end,
there's only a Scala to Scala compiler.
So nowadays if you look at the Scala
reference compiler,
it's written in Scala
and there's nothing else.
Well, there is still at least one Scala
compiler actually that's compiled, right?
But it can be only a binary, right?
So that's this kind of bootstrapping.
At some point, you know, nowadays
that's a good practice,
to write a compiler for a language
in the language itself.
It might be particularly natural.
So how, if you've got a completely
new architecture, new CPU
or a new whatever, piece of hardware,
how do we make a good compiler,
code generator, for it?
But probably you don't know the start
writing everything including
the operating system and tools
and so on from scratch
in machine code for this architecture.
It's not necessary.
What you want to do
is take an existing compiler
on a different architecture
and just write the code generated
packet data that emits machine code.
It's just the last piece at the lowest
level of that compiler.
So you can cross-compile.
Then you've got to compile in the machine.
You can also cross-compile
an operating system
and adaptions and so on, adaptations.
And once you have it on that
machine running, you're independent.
You want to write, you're done.
Alright.
And more crazy than that,
let's just think that the reference
Scala compiler, that compiles
Scala to Scala,
by repeatedly compiling itself
and not changing any code,
not improving any codes,
we can make that compiler better.
Particularly if it has strong
optimizations. How could that be, right?
Just imagine you've got an optimization
that actually is very expensive
and it takes long, if it does more
number crunching it produces better code.
The better code might be faster
as well, right?
So you spend some time
letting the compiler compile itself.
You get the compiler, but it's still
based on the same source code.
But by having this number
crunching for optimization
the compiler is faster
and can the next time it compiles itself
it gets more quickly
to even better compilation.
So you iterate this process.
You don't touch the code at all, right?
And the compiler improves itself.
So that's a possibility.
It's an extreme case.
You cannot expect it normally
but it's possible.