In this video we're going to talk
about declarativity in more detail.
So, what is a declarative language?
It's a language in which you
specify what you want to get
as a result rather than how to compute it.
So it describes the desired result,
rather than steps towards obtaining it.
Examples would be functional languages
in general and logic-based languages.
And to make that clear,
because there's sometimes
I would argue, misunderstood,
the distinction is between
declarative on one hand
and imperative language on the other,
rather than between declarative
and procedural.
So why would we
want to use declarative languages?
The reasons are the same as
why you would want to use DSLs,
and the reasons
are even stronger potentially.
We would like to have an abstraction
if possible and separation of concerns.
If there's low level
implementation details potentially,
low level things about how to do things,
we don't want to have to worry
about them if that can be avoided, right?
That increases, of course, simplicity
and programmer productivity
and we can more easily
avoid making mistakes.
That way we might be able to do
a substantial drop
in very few lines of code.
And we are able to concisely
capture the essence of the system
that this language supports, right?
So if we have really
designed a language
that very well captures
what I can do in a system,
then this language might also
explain the system so to say.
It is very easy to basically,
you understand the language
and you know what the system does.
And it's very easy to avoid
misusing the system.
If it's not possible to program things
that are not meant
to happen in the system.
So functional languages as said,
I would argue,
as being declarative,
since we have learned first
about functions in mathematics,
these are in a sense conceptual items.
It's not necessarily about
how to compute these functions,
that would be algorithms, right?
But about what they mean.
And so it is known,
there are reports of all kinds
that programmable activity
in functional languages
can be substantially higher
that in classical imperative languages.
This for certain examples.
Something like two orders of magnitude
has been reported.
A particularly good example
is compilers.
You can write a compilers
particularly easy, usually,
to do it in a functional language.
For example there's pattern matching, etc.
and constructed very natural
and widespread in functional
programmer languages which are making
for example, writing compiler very easy,
in a functional language
and it's much more complicated
usually in imperative language.
I'm not going to say much more about this
because I assume that
you know functional programming
and there's not much more to say.
Except for maybe this one qualification.
That you can think of functional languages
also as logical languages.
And clearly the pioneers
of computer science, for example,
Church-Turing and Lambda Calculus
thought that way.
And really thought of, for example,
lambda calculus as combination of logic
and functional programming so to say.
So what kind of logics are we
going to study in more detail?
Well first this class of classical logics.
By that I refer to classical semantics.
Semantics are consistent
with first order predicate logic
according to Frege.
So that includes first order logic
but also it's simplification
propositional logic
and also higher-order logics,
where I've got more powerful quantifiers
so in which I can quantify
and dilations and sets.
And also modal logics.
I've got modes of true, for example,
which give me interesting power.
Alternative to that,
there's logic programming
and it includes datalog and prolog.
We're going to talk more
about this in a separate video.
And there's nonmonotonic logics
which have semantics that is inconsistent
in the sense of classical logic,
but they can be very useful.
And there is nonmonotonic generalizations
of classical logics,
for example, positional
and first-order logics
but also off logic programming.