Now let's look at logic programming,
and specifically at Datalog.
We can think of Datalog as
first-order logic, with negation removed.
That means positive first-order logic,
negation removed,
and also universal quantification removed.
And instead we have recursion added,
the notion of recursion,
we're going to talk about this.
So, there's a more general notion
of Datalog, called Prolog,
which actually is older,
and it's really a full Turing-complete
programming language,
while Datalog is a restricted language,
which doesn't have
the full expressive power
of a Turing-complete
programming language,
and Prolog extends Datalog
by a notion of function symbols,
we'll see that later.
But Datalog--a program which
consists of a set of rules,
and a rule consists of a right-hand side,
and an implication to left,
the left-hand side is the so-called head,
the right-hand side is the body.
So if the body is true,
then the head must also be true,
that's the implication.
Now, the head and body,
they have variables inside.
It's really a fragment
of first-order logic,
so we've got these kind of
atomic formulas with variables inside,
and we're testing, so to say,
whether something is true
by unification--we unify variables
of constant symbols
for the input database,
so if I can make a unification,
a function that maps
every variable in my rule to constants,
in such a way that the body atoms
are all in the database already,
then the head atom,
that I also get by feeding the variables,
even replacing them by constants,
must also be true.
It can be conceptually added,
so to say, to the results.
So that's the meaning of single rule.
In general, rules can be recursive,
which means that the head's predicate
might also occur in the body.
So here's an example.
Here I've got a two-rule program,
that computes
the transitive closure of a graph.
The graph is given by
its edge relation, E here,
that's what we care about, E.
And we've got two rules--
The first says that every edge
of the graph is in a transitive closure,
and if I can connect two edges
in transitive closure,
and to the transitive step,
is again a transitive closure.
It means if the transitive closure
so far contains edges X to Y,
and Y to Z, then X to Z
must also be in a transitive closure.
And I can think of this as a recursive,
a recursive step,
and recursively
we add more and more stuff,
then we can add nothing more
and I've got the transitive
closure finished, so to say.
So I can think of
a fixed-point semantics here,
I add and add until I cannot get more.
But there is alternative semantics
to this Datalog language, again.
There is again this kind
of cryptomorphism.
We've got three different semantics
we're going to talk about:
fixpoint semantics,
proof-theoretic semantics,
and, we're going to start with that,
model theoretic semantics.
In the model theoretic semantics
we can think of the program,
the set of rules, as logical sentences
that state a property of the result.
It means that you take the rules
and you universal quantify
over all the variables.
So that way it becomes
self-contained sentences,
boolean sentences, boolean formulas,
and you take this kind of combination,
the end of all these universally
quantified boolean formulas,
and that's again a huge boolean formula,
and now we can ask,
"give me a set of facts,"
a relational database, let's say.
Is that big formula,
this combined program,
true on that, on that database,
If so, then this database
is called a model,
we have already said that, right?
And now we can talk about--
there might be many different models,
but there is a single, unique,
minimal model, and this minimal model
can also be obtained by computing
the intersection of all possible models.
So that's model theoretic semantics.
Now along with these three semantics
I'm going to talk about,
and I've mentioned to you,
the model theoretic semantics is
the only one that is truly declarative,
because there I don't have the idea
of iterating and computing recursively,
and so on--there's no computation here.
There is just a definition
of what you want to have.
What do I want to have?
The minimal database on which,
that is consistent to input,
and on which all these formulas,
all the rules, are true.
So the rules don't compute new stuff,
but they're basically just
implication formulas that say,
"if this is true, then this must be true,"
and otherwise, it's not a model.
And of all the models,
we take the minimal one.
So that's a truly declarative semantics.
We say what we want,
rather than how to compute it.
Example here, again,
this is again our principle example,
now I actually called
the edge relation G, not E,
but otherwise the same thing,
and I've got a concrete example.
I don't give it as a relational table,
I give it as a graph,
so on the right-hand side,
at the top, you got a graph,
you've got three nodes, 1, 2, 3,
and you've got edges,
one from 1 to 2,
and 2 and 3 have mutual edges.
Now, what is the transitive
closure of those?
Actually the leftmost
of the bottom solutions.
I just have to add a single edge,
from 1 to 3,
and I've got point loops at 3 and at 2.
This is actually very hard to see,
but there are point loops at 2 and 3.
Now, the middle one is not a solution,
because the edge from 1 to 3 is missing.
So in particular,
this is not a model at all.
And the right-hand solution
has everything that
the left-hand solution has,
plus some additional edge,
going back from 2 to 1.
So this is a model.
The formulas are true,
but it's not a minimal model,
so it's not a solution.
There's a unique solution--
it's the left-hand solution here.
So why do we take
the minimal model among all those?
Well, we can philosophically argue
that you have something
like closed-world assumptions.
Everything that you don't
specify explicitly,
that you don't add to the database,
you implicitly assume to be false,
unless the program forces to become true.
So in a sense, database
are incompletely specified,
you don't explicitly say--
in a database you've got
a finite set of tuples,
and implicitly you say
everything that is not in there
is supposed to be wrong
It would be very hard to enumerate
this infinite number
of tuples that are not true,
explicitly these are not true.
That is not possible in a finite database.
So the idea is that way, that we kind
of say closed-world assumption,
implicitly everything
that is missing is false,
and that leads us to
the minimum model semantics.
Also it is the only
reasonable, unique thing.
It's the intersection
of all possible models.
The union of all models would be infinite,
which also would be unique, of course,
but it's meaningless to talk about this.
Let's talk about the alternative,
fixpoint approach.
So the idea is that the semantics
of a program is defined
as a particular solution
to a fixpoint equation, so the idea is--
you can think of the end-type
program as a fixpoint equation.
Take a database, such that--
think of these rules as adding new stuff,
these rules don't add anything any more.
Everything that the rules could add,
given this database,
we have already added before,
so that's a fixpoint.
So fixpoint is not about recursively
adding stuff, bottom-up evaluation,
although in practice
we would do it that way,
but fixpoint is about saying,
"this formula doesn't
compute anything new."
It is happy with its result.
So being a fixpoint is a bit like,
what we have said before,
that it's a model.
And now we require
it's the minimal fixpoint,
and to get the minimal fixpoint
a kind of bottom-up relation,
forcing, forward chaining,
would use more tuples
from the initial input database,
and stopping, as we don't get
any more results forced.
That would be a fixpoint reached.
We've got the same example again,
and conceptually, what I do is
I look at my first rule,
initially my result is empty.
I've got the input database.
Here, in database terminology
we call the input
the extensional database.
That's the stuff that is there,
extensionally given explicitly,
using tuples,
and the IDB, the intensional
database, is the result,
that includes those that are
implicitly given by the rules.
So we're committing the IDB
and the input is to EDB.
So we start by taking,
let's say, the first rule,
because the second rule by itself,
given that there's nothing yet
in the results, in T,
we cannot commit anything new.
There is no unification of error,
there is no mapping for the variables
x, y and z to constants 1, 2, 3,
such that T becomes true,
because T is empty.
So initially, the second rule cannot fire.
But the first rule can fire,
and it can add all these three tuples,
all these three edges
that are in the input database.
So we can do this in the first step.
So this is conceptually,
a next iteration,
bottom-up.
If I apply this rule again
it doesn't add anything new, so to say.
We conceptually, in every step
can try this first rule again
but it will never present anything new,
so we can actually forget about it.
But the second rule can now
add new stuff.
What can it add?
Well, suppose you take
the tuple (1, 2) as G of sets.
So x is 1, and z is 2.
Then you can actually take
y to be 3, z must be 2,
and that way, going from
(x, y), from 1 to 3,
we can add this new edge.
But that's not the only solution.
I can also go from 2 to 3, that's G.
So x is 2 and z is 3,
and I can take y being 2,
z again is 3.
And if you take the path
from 2 to 3 and back to 2,
and that, as transitive closure,
gives me a loop from 2 to 2.
So I add this one as well.
And the same element can be taken
to actually add loop 3 to 3,
and from then on
there is nothing you can compute.
I iterate as many times as I like--
I've reached a fixpoint,
I don't require to add anything more,
so that's the solution.
And it's the same solution that you also
got by taking the minimal model.
Now let's look at the final semantic,
the proof-theoretic semantics.
This one is particularly interesting
because it's the only way
to give a semantics to Prolog,
the channelization of Datalog.
So the idea there is that we don't compute
the entire result, the IDB,
but we test for a single fact,
a single tuple,
whether it is to be in the result,
and how do we do this?
We are going to construct a proof tree,
top-down, so to say.
It could be thought of--
the computation of the fixpoint
is a bottom-up evaluation and now we're
going to do a top-down evaluation,
starting with a result,
we test it for the result,
we create a proof tree that shows
that it must be in the result.
So how do we do this?
So let's assume that we want to ask
whether (1,3)
is in the transitive closure.
So we're going to try to basically
build a proof tree
that it must be in there.
And at each of these intermediate nodes
we're going to say we have to choose
[inaudible] conceptually,
a rule that you're going
to use to expand the proof tree.
In this case we use rule 2.
That means we're going to have
to find a suitable G of (x,z),
but in this particular case,
I know already x must be 1,
because it comes from here.
Because x is on the left-hand side here.
We know what y is, and it's 3,
so actually y here, T, must be 3.
But we have to now guess a value for z,
and if we guess 2,
this is an non-deterministic technique,
otherwise you would, in general,
just kind of an exponential search,
or something like that,
but now for this, let's guess 2.
Well, if we guess 2, we can continue,
because we can now apply--
we can check, actually G(1,2)
is an input database, so we're done here.
That branch of the proof tree is done,
and was successful.
So we now have to continue,
and still have to prove
that T(2,3) must be in the result.
Well, actually we can do this
by actually just choosing that--
the first rule has to be used
here to expand it--
that means it just says then G(2,3)
must be enabled, or must be inferable,
in this case actions and inputs,
and we're done.
We've proved all the leaves,
and we're done,
and we've proved that T(1,3)
indeed is in the result.
So that's the proof-theoretic semantics.
So in summary, we've shown you
and discussed
three equivalent approaches
for giving a semantics:
the model theoretic,
the fixpoint theoretic,
and the proof theoretic semantics,
and they are all equivalent.
So the model theoretic one
was the truth declarative one.
The others, maybe a bit more
about how to compute things.
But they are all equivalent with, again,
there's this kind of cryptomorphism.
You've got an elegant "surprise,"
and that suggests
this is a robust language.
There are many different ways
of thinking about it, and there's
maybe different ways
of approaching different technical
problems, like evaluation.
Here's a more interesting example.
We're going to simulate
a finite state machine,
and we're going to model this as follows.
Actually the first part here,
is actually just
input modeling the input word
to the finite state machine,
it's a string machine,
and it says we've got
eight character positions,
and if modeled, these positions 1 to 8,
so we haven't [inaudible] explicitly,
otherwise we could, of course,
make this built-in, if you like.
There's a successful relation that says
first step one, then two,
then three, then four,
and so on, up to eight.
And we have labeled
these positions 1 to 8,
we have a character a or b here,
so actually the word is abababab,
an eight-character word,
on which we're going to run--
this is actually input, that's data.
It's written as unconditional rules,
heads with empty bodies,
if they're all true, facts,
or we could have thought
of them as database tables.
And as most of--that's also data,
which actually models
the finite state machine.
So what does it look like?
We've got the delta relation,
we've got the starts
and we've got the final states.
So we've got actually just
two states, q1 and q2,
q1 and q2.
The start set is q1.
The final state,
the only final state, is also q1.
The transition relation is--
well, I can get from q1 to q2
using either symbol a or c,
and I can get back to q1 using b.
So, in other words, obviously
a regular expression is
a or c, dot b, star.
And abababab
is a special case,
it's a word that this machine accepts.
So I clean up, and let's now
look at the final part,
which is actually the encoding
of the semantics
of the finite state machine,
So, remember, the standard definition
of the semantics
of the finite state machine
is given by the notion of a run.
So the run is a function that maps
every position in the word to a state,
and we accept if the final position
is mapped to a final state.
Actually we're going to have points
right after a symbol,
which is a position,
and we're going to ask
which state to assign to this.
So with the first rule
we're going to check.
first(P) only maps P to 1,
the start state is also going to be q1.
The delta function--let's now,
actually we can commit several things,
but we could make a run using c or with a,
but actually we the symbol
of the word at position a--
1 is a.
So we have a, q1, and that means
q must be--
[inaudible] the machine here--q2.
So we're getting at the end
of position 1 into q2,
so actually run will compute 1, q2.
Now the next step will be,
actually we're going
to apply the second rule,
we're going to make a step.
So we've got 1 and q2 here,
and we can pick the success of 1,
which is going to be 2,
and the delta relation for state q2,
for the next symbol,
the symbol position 2, which is b,
is going to be to q1,
because we have a position b being 2,
and symbol b there.
So we are going to thus compute,
at position 2, state q1.
So we are going to be next in state q1
Now we can actually recursively
use this rule a few more times,
and you're going
to compute state q2, state q1,
state q2, state q1,
state q2 and state q1,
that's all of the second rule.
And now we're in the position
that actually has a run, at position 8,
and we're in state q1,
and the last position is actually 8,
and the final state of q1, a final state,
so we are going to accept.
So we compute this final boolean,
predicate accept,
and if it would not be an accepting run,
then we would not be able to compute that.