Now let's look at Prolog.
Prolog channelizes Datalog.
The most important channelization is
that it supports function symbols.
What does this mean?
Well function symbols are a
way of taking so-called terms,
which are things that you can
build on constants, variables,
and functions symbols and
build larger terms of them.
So, here's an example, we've got a
right hand side in this first rule
that just looks like Datalog
p(x), x is a variable,
and if p(x) is true,
then actually you can infer
p of success of x
and success now is a so-called
function symbol.
So succ(x) will build a new term,
a new object, based on x,
which is different from the
other objects seen so far.
Unless somebody else
has computed succ(x).
F corresponds a bit to the kind of
binary relation success
that we had before,
but you need to explicitly give
this translation/relation.
Here you actually can kind of
compute it, let's say.
So the idea would be that using
also this kind of [inaudible],
that you could compute bottom-up,
conceptually the P relation consisting of
1, s(1),
s(s(1)), s(s(s(1))),
and so on ad infinitum.
This is going to be
non-deterministic
computation if you like
to think of it as bottom-up
or fixed points relation and you
cannot use that in Prolog,
but you can do a proof-theoretic
semantics where you say--
Question: is this fact--
this goal provable?
Well the answer's going to be yes,
by applying twice is the first rule
and once the second rule.
So if you give a proof of how
it could be inferred.
So there is a proof-theoretic semantics.
However, it gets a bit worse.
There's is truly imperative details
in the full standard,
there is in particular,
there's this so-called cut,
which allows you to basically kind of
cut below the search, and so on,
heuristics on and for--
understanding that you really
have to have a very precise,
low-level model of how
computation is done in Prolog.
So Prolog is not declarative,
it is however logic based
and you can be very succinct.
And it is a Turing-complete
programming language.
You can do anything you could do
in C, in terms of expressive power.
Is logic programming declarative?
We already said that Datalog--
while the fixpoint, semantically,
has an imperative flavor,
but there is the declarative viewpoint,
the model-theoretic semantics.
Prolog doesn't have this,
it's clearly not a declarative language,
but is logic based,
but it can be very succinct
and it allows to abstract away
from many things,
and focus on the core
of the computation.
So here's an example,
declarative networking.
There is some important work there
and research out that has been--
have some impact in both
databases and networking,
and the idea there is that you've
got some length that's essentially
something a bit like Datalog
and the most important thing
is that there is an
ability to create,
essentially using Prolog
function symbols--
new timepoints,
success is two timepoints basically.
That way you can kind of
model infinite protocols
and infinite computations.
And there is--
I'm modelling that way
I'm going to simplify things,
I'm not adding anymore new
syntax than is absolutely necessary.
You can think of these two
standardized columns
in each predicate, each relation,
that model locations
where some values is stored or received,
and times for which
they're first received.
So at which they are present so to say.
Here's an example.
So in general, schemas look like that,
there is a predicate
there's some general application
specific columns,
and then there's a special
destination column and a time column.
And here's an example,
it's kind of two examples--
think of this kind of "No U"
words in a mailing list.
Somebody says some--
makes an insult of the second guy,
the second guy answers "No U"
and the first answers "No U"
and that leads to a kind of
infinite repetition of "No U",
where these guys kind of
flood of "No U"s alternatively.
So we can do this as follows.
The rules at node1 would be that if node1
sees a "No U" at a certain timepoint,
then it sends a "No U" message to node2
that will be received next time.
So "No U" would be seen by
node2 in the next timepoint,
and at node2 it's the opposite,
if it receives at some timepoint, t,
and "No U" then it will
send it to the next.
So it will be in alternating timepoints,
always a "No U" received
at the other node.
So there is-- if you can nicely compute,
express protocols in a very succinct way,
and for example there is,
an example of what people have done,
implemented distributed hash table,
a redistributable hash table,
in about 200 lines of such code,
rather than tens of thousands
of lines of code in C.
So it can be very succinct and
Datalog-style syntax is convenient
because you can emphasize on
data and computation
and the rules look simple locally,
but overall,
these 200 lines of code for the
DHT is not readable--
very succinct and very strange.
Is it "declarative"?
I would say no.
There is no declarative semantics,
no moderated semantics in particular.
It has this Prolog stash,
it's not really Datalog,
despite what other people say.
But it's an interesting language.
Now let's look at nonmonotonic logics.
We've defined Datalog as being--
Datalog rules being first-order
predicate logic
minus negation or as the quantification,
and adding recursion stat.
So what is a nonmonotonic logic?
Well, think about, first-order logic.
It is actually nonmonotonic,
but it's classical.
So if you've got an input database,
and you have to query
a result for it,
for a given formula with
negation let's say,
now if you add more tuples to the input,
sadly it could be the query result
becomes less because of the negation.
Think about it, too,
we had an example where
students--
we've under-produced the students
for which there doesn't exists a
course that you have failed in.
So I might get a resulting
a student and now suddenly
add a tuple, that they are
failed in their course,
suddenly there, a student
has to go away from the result.
So further logic with negation or
quantification is nonmonotonic.
Now Datalog is monotonic,
if you add more stuff to the input,
you always get at least as much
as you had before in the result.
Now it would be nice to have
negation supported in Datalog
because you might
be able to express more,
but can you get a decent,
reasonable semantic somehow,
that can understand for that.
Well let's look at an example.
Here I've got two rules,
a program that has
negation and recursion,
it's propositional predicates here.
I say if the ground isn't dry
then it rains
and if it doesn't rain
then the ground is dry.
Now, is both propositions
being false a model,
no because for either case,
if one of them is false,
then the other one must be true.
This is two rules saying exactly this.
So the empty set of
propositions is not a model.
Is a set where both Rains
and GroundDry a model?
Actually yes, why not?
Because the bodies are not true,
nothing contradicts it,
but it's not a minimum model,
because for example,
just Rains and GroundDry being false,
Rains being true,
GroundDry being false is actually a model.
And GroundDry being false at--
so GroundDry being true
and Rains being false is a model.
So we've got these three models.
And the problem is,
there's two models that are--
have just one element in it,
one position being true.
There's not a unique minimum model.
So we've got alternatives.
Among minimal models,
this model where both Rains
and GroundDry is for--
it's not minimal in a sense,
it seems to be redundant,
but the other two are minimal,
but they're different.
So that is strange because
we had before,
the semantic where
single solution is there
and now this is basically a--
disjunctive semantics.
Either that is a good model,
a good minimum model,
or the other one is a good
minimum model
because there's two minimum models
and in the end not a unique, single one.
So that is strange,
but there is ways of defining it.
Basically the way we decided.
You can give semantics to
nonmonotonic logics
with recursion
where you basically have
multiple, alternative, correct
minimal model solutions.
And that leads us to what is called
answer set programming.
So we will be talking about sets of
answers that is the desirable solution.
And for that you can actually take such
Datalog with this additional negation
and give it decent semantics
and programming semantic
where you have extreme
high expressive power
only for model checking, so to say.
For query relation.
Or you can actually conveniently,
nicely, very succinctly express
in P-complete problems.
Here for example, I'll show you
some kind of so-called negation
with some kind of so-called
negation in the head,
or-- but this could also be modeled
by using this double negation,
as we have above here.
I modeled free colorability.
I'm saying, well, if it's a node,
it must be labeled: red, blue or green.
So x is a variable,
and red, blue, and green
are constants.
And there is actually a constraint, the
constraint is a body of an empty head.
That means if the body becomes true,
then the falsity is inferred,
that means it destroys that model.
It could do this in
different ways as well,
and then say it's not allowed that
two neighboring edges have the same color.
So this is a two-liner,
a very declarative definition
of free colorability and
a P-complete problem.
So by adding this negation together,
it's extremely high
power you have--
and this kind of alternative
minimal model
which is kind of weird
and sounds undesirable,
is actually a very good way of
finding solutions to
and P-complete problems where
there might be exponential alternatives.
And you see it is declarative.
I would really-- would say that
a classical textbook definition
of free colorability is really
whatever is just written down
in two very short rules.
So it's actually a very interesting
solution for a space of complicated,
potentially analytical queries
that you can express.
Of course, in general, it's very hard
to evaluate these queries,
but you can solve hard problems,
there is no way around it
and you can use such language
to build a channels solver,
for example, in P-complete
problems for that.
And that's an interesting--
another space for declarative languages.