In this video I'm going
to talk about some advice for --
give some advice for designing
or choosing a declarative language
for a particular purpose,
for a particular system.
Examples could be
some kind of query language,
a language for specing scripting,
a language for a formal method system,
a verification system,
a testing system, things like that.
So one thing is, you need to have
a thorough understanding
of what kind of logics there might be,
and which might be options.
The first thing that we always understand,
what I was talking about
in the past two videos.
It needs experience, so you want to read
papers where people have done this.
Examples were papers on
declarative networking,
on query relation, things like that.
Some formal methods papers,
CAF, computated verification papers,
and things like that.
You have to really understand
which problem you want to solve,
specifically, are you trying to solve
this kind of model checking problem?
Or the satisfiability or validity problem?
We've talked about this before.
And is the language meant to answer
questions about a static,
or a dynamic system?
And we're going to talk about
these things more.
Also, if you have multiple options,
if you might develop your own language,
this property of having
alternative characterizations
for a declarative language
is useful and important.
If you come up with your own thing,
if you find thinking about the problem
many different ways,
you convert to a different language
that end up being nearly the same,
or exactly the same expressive power.
You're probably on the right path, and
you have actually done something right.
It's not so easy to do that,
but if you have a clear problem in mind,
this may be possible to do.
The other thing is if you have, example,
alternative algebraic characterization,
and the logical characterization,
you can use the logical one
for people to spec,
and really do it declaratively,
and the algebraic one
for actually executing or implementing.
So there is, for example,
for certain logics that actually,
state-machine presentations
and things like that,
and all kinds of tricks,
alternative to algebraic presentations,
for doing things efficiently.
Or actually doing them practically
so that no non-determinism is needed
and things like that.
So you should think about that.
Is the complexity of the problems
that we're dealing with acceptable?
Some things are just undesirable,
others are a very high complexity.
It might be too high,
and then you might do a trade-off.
Some slightly weaker language
might do the job as well,
and might have much lower complexity.
And is the language simple
and easy to understand?
That's somehow a goal
of the design as well.
So regarding this model checking
versus sat and validity problem,
remember, let's call
the structure a "database".
Or a "snapshot" of the state
of the system, a system description.
That's really DATA.
For example, the Kripke structures
in the context of model logics.
These can move to state,
and to a specing system.
In a database, well the database
is the database, obviously.
So that's called a structure.
And secondly, there's the formula
in your logical language.
And model checking is asking,
given the input is a structured
and a logical sentence,
is the sentence true on that structure?
That's model checking.
Is that what you need?
For example,
database queries are of that kind.
Or checking whether a safety condition
is true on a finite-state system.
Alternatively, satisfiability and validity
are kind of, static analysis problems,
that don't need
a structured database.
You only look at the formula.
Is the formula general for all possible
structures satisfiable, or valid?
And remember,
there's an if and only if condition,
they are dual satisfiability and validity.
You've got this satifiability, exactly if,
if and only if it's not true,
that's the negation of the form is valid.
And visa versa.
It's a theorem if the negation
is unsatisfiable.
So, you have to understand
really what you need here.
And sometimes there is trade-offs.
You can actually sometimes
lift one to the other.
You might actually reduce
sometimes a validity problem
to a small checking problem,
or a satisfiability.
So these transformations
may be possible.
You have to consider that
if you want to kind of engineer
the complexity of the problem
that you're dealing with.
Regarding the static versus dynamic
scenario thing, the idea is, static,
there's a database, and you want
to do something with the database.
You want to ask questions about it.
Or you've got a specification
you want to ask a question about.
For that, there might be
a language like first-order logic.
There's also various kind of slight
generalization of first-order logic queue.
For example, take first the logic,
and add a special interpreted relation.
For example, the transitive closure
relation for a given relation.
So of course, you can implement
this recursion in Datalog,
but that might be overkill.
You might still have something
between FO and Datalog
by, for example, taking FOTC.
And that manages
languages and extensions.
Actually no.
If it is not a fragment of Datalog
because it has negation,
but FOTC is a fragment of Datalog
with negation.
And there's other such languages
that goes beyond the scope of this lecture
to talk about them,
but whether such language
might have been studied
is a good way to start looking
if you know what you want.
Non-monotonic logics, we said,
could be adding expressiveness
to make very highly, expressive,
powerful queries.
The alternative would be
that you've got something
dynamic to model the system.
And then you might do this
in two different ways, basically.
You could do it via logical programming,
or you could do it via model logics,
temporal/dynamic logics.
So by logical programming,
you could basically,
it'd be like in declarative networking,
you model a system
by actually doing
the computation of the system.
Simulating the system step by step.
And that could be done
with Datalog-like language.
Example of declarative routing,
as we said.
And the temporal/dynamic logic thing
would be simplified
at facilitating asking questions,
static questions,
about potentially
infinite computations.
Can something bad ever happen?
Is some kind of safety or liveness
property holding, and things like that.
Now, choosing for the dynamic case
between logic programming,
and temporal/dynamic logic
is the impression of how indirect
and declarative you want
your automated reasoning to be.
So, remember simplicity the goal must be
that it's simple, and not overkill.
The logics must be corresponding
to your needs.
You have the potential, though.
If you choose the right logic,
that are a way of creating
truly bug-free programs
and specifications
that could actually be possible,
because the logic carries
strong intuitions with them,
and they are very small and succinct.
So, while getting a hundred thousand
line of code program
perfectly bug-free might be
completely unrealistic,
but if the logical specification is short,
and it's very --
the language is perfect
for the purpose and so on,
you can actually get things right.
So, of course, a particular choice
of logical language
might not be right for the purpose,
but is it possible to fully comprehend
the logical specification implied,
and so on?
Yes, because it has this strong intuition,
and this kind of declarative flavor.
So it's possible
to get things right that way.
That's an important thing,
and it's a key to this formal method,
because if you want to do verification
of a program by reducing the problem
of doing this verification
in another problem,
writing these logical formulas,
and doing the right thing with them,
and that is as hard.
You have not achieved anything.
And yes, it's a matter of taste,
and a matter of experience.
You want to capture the essence
of the problem at hand.
There's going to be some kind of elegance,
and mathematical beauty,
and I'm not trying
to make you theoreticians here
of making the right choice.
Look at some the examples you have seen
in these past two videos,
where a choice of language was
commandeered to what you want to achieve.
And it's really capturing the essence,
the nature of the problems,
so things get very easy and intuitive.
You don't have to worry about
the hassle of programming it anymore,
because it's so natural.
That's something that you have to aim for.
And it's often possible to achieve,
and then you've got a good solution.
Often, you've got published research.
Succinctness, language should be
well-rounded,
you don't want to have awkward exceptions,
you don't want to have things expressed
with a language that don't mean anything
in the system.
And you want to understand what you
want to gain and design for that.
Is it user productivity?
Is it simple to use?
Do you want to get new insights
for making a system better?
Do you want to just provide abstractions
and clean interfaces?
All of these can be achieved
if you do it right.
It's a question of experience and taste.