(swooshing sounds)
♪ (eclectic downtempo music) ♪
♪ (music continues) ♪
Welcome to Week 4:
Raising and Managing Money.
And just to recap what we did so far:
we are already in Week 4
and the course has only five weeks
so remember this, we are almost done.
But in Week 2 we did talk about
entrepreneurial opportunities,
how you identify multiple opportunities
based on your technology.
Remember that term
technological fungibility
sounds fancy but it actually means
that you can apply your technology
to multiple ends, you know,
multiple customers' ends.
We talked about evaluation
of opportunities and developing
a road map to exploit your multiple
opportunities over time.
Right, then in last week, Week 3
we talked a lot
about entrepreneurial marketing,
we helped think about developing
a marketing plan, we wanted to know
who your customers are,
what your value proposition is,
and we talked about guerrilla marketing.
Which is actually quite an exciting
form of marketing,
it's more on the operational side.
It should be aligned
with your overall strategy.
But the underlying logic was
that you actually should say,
"OK, I have to be smart because
I do not have so many funds"
"like the larger corporations
to run my marketing campaign."
Perfect.
So let's look and see what we're going
to cover in the next week.
So, as Mark just said, you may be running
a guerrilla marketing campaign
and a very lean operation,
but it's still going to cost you
to get your company
off the ground.
So in the first part of this week
we're going to study:
How much money do you need?
That's going to involve making
some financial projections
for the next few years
and trying to understand
how much cash you're spending
and how much you're bringing in.
Therefore, what your overall
financing needs are
to get your company launched.
So in addition to doing
the financial projections,
you also have to know which type
of financing is available
and from whom you could get
the money that you need.
So in terms of type of financing,
you can think about debt financing,
you might even get gifts,
you might get equity financing,
there might be convertible debt.
This might sound technical to some
but we're going to walk you in detail
through each of these types
of financing in segment 4.2.
In addition we look
at the types of investors.
Right, so there'd be a big laundry list
here of investors.
Which is good news because people
who have money and want to invest--
Yes, there are lots of sources for you.
So what we'll do is we'll just walk
through the big picture
on the types of investors
and then we'll break it out by stage
which we'll discuss right now.
So in 4.3, we'll focus on the early stages
of your company,
before you're making any money
and you're really launching your company
and getting it off the ground.
So what kind of investors are going to be
most appropriate for those early stages?
It could be your friends and your family
because they believe in you,
they want to support you.
It could also be crowd-funding campaigns
and that's quite an important element
especially in this MOOC today.
It could be also startup competitions,
it could be angel investors
and all these types
of venture capitalists at some points.
So in 4.4, we'll focus more
on the later stages of the venture process
when you've already got a product
when maybe you've already got some sales
and you're basically growing the company
and we have the expansion financing
and there's a whole new set
of actors that are available
to help finance your venture.
So think about family offices,
think about banks, etc.
because these are actors that want to see
that you have proof of technology
and the proof of market, that there are
customers out there who are willing
to pay for your products
and that your technology actually works,
it does the things you promise it does.
Because then a lot of risk is taken
off the table for these types of investors
and that means that these investors
would be looking at companies
that have different risk profiles
and the investors that we just discussed
on the previous slide which would be
more of the investors
that look at early stage companies
and are ready and available
to actually invest in companies
that are less mature and have more risk.
So what we'll do is for all of these
we'll walk through how much money
you'd expect to raise,
what the time horizon is,
and lots of different
psychological aspects
of working with different
types of investors.
And the bottom line is that we want
to give you a very good understanding
of the funding universe that is out there
because without the funds of other people
you probably will not get far
with your technology venture.
So one important way of getting funding
nowadays is crowdfunding.
You remember that from the marketing
module; we introduced you to this concept
because it has important
marketing elements to it.
It helps you in launching your product,
it helps you in getting visibility
with your company,
but that's one aspect.
It has also a very important
financial aspect to it.
That's right, I mean entrepreneurs now
can, via internet platforms,
reach out to investors who happen to be
all over the whole world.
What we'll do in this particular segment
is we'll walk through how that works,
we'll talk a little bit
about some of the legal/financial
implications of having lots of investors
all over the world and how you can
expect to raise money from them,
going into details about how
some of the crowd-funding platforms work.
Exactly.
And that, it think, is a wonderful
opportunity for each and every one of you
to get your venture off the ground
and to make your first steps
as an entrepreneur.
So these crowd funding campaigns
give you access to potential investors
across the globe but never forget
that you actually need
to manage your cash because this is more
like an operational issue
but it's highly important.
It's like the air that you breathe;
the cash is the air that you breathe.
Because if you run out of cash, it's like
running out of air that you breathe.
And what happens if you run out
of air that you breathe?
You fall over and you die.
And if this were to happen to your company
it would just go bankrupt, you know,
so managing your cash is
our focus in module 4.6.
And this has a couple of other issues
that are related to it.
We'll talk a little bit
about the burn rate,
so how much you're spending
relative to how much you have.
We'll talk about having bank accounts,
how to look for a bank,
keeping your accounts separate.
We'll talk a little bit about shrinkage,
or your employees stealing from you
or you stealing from yourself
by mixing your funds,
and we'll go through a lot of details
on how to manage your cash.
And conserve your air in that way.
- Conserving your air.
So that's what's in your future
for Week 4 in Raising and Managing Money.
- Don't go away.
- Stay tuned.