Welcome back!
This is segment 4.4
on Growth & expansion financing.
So today what we're going
to do is talk a little bit,
recap what we did before about the stages.
We're going to give a little summary
of how to analyze
your options for financing,
and then we're going
to walk through step by step
four different types of growth
and expansion financing investors.
So if you recall
from the last several times
we've discussed this staging,
and we talked about
sort of the early stage of financing,
and then we have
sort of the later stages of financing.
The first ones are the seed stage,
or the start up stage.
Some people think about the seed stage
as being earlier than the start up stage
to help finance the initial cash outlays
of the business.
Although some people,
as I mentioned before,
use them interchangeably.
And the same thing
for growth and expansion.
At some point, when the business starts
taking off and making money,
then usually the entrepreneurs
are looking to grow the business.
So they would be looking for--
a lot of people call growth financing
and then eventually they are
past the break-even point,
and they are growing more rapidly,
and they make seek to expand.
So some people call that
the expansion financing stage.
Again, a lot of people use
the terms interchangeably,
but after the company's already got
something in the market.
They're already making money,
that's when you start looking
for your growth and expansion financing.
Alright, so here's our list of investors
that we've seen many times at this point,
and as you recall from the last segment,
we were really focusing
on the early stages of investors,
so the first half of this list here.
What we're going to do today
is talk a little bit
about some of the later stages,
the type of people who come
in at the later stage.
So we mentioned before
that the individual angel was often
associated with seed financing
and start up financing.
And angel groups can too,
but just to draw a little distinction
between the individual angel
and angel group:
some of the angel groups will often
come in later in the process.
So we're going to include them
in today's groups.
If we just look here, we're going to talk
mainly about this group of people.
Angel groups, family offices,
venture capital, and strategic partners
or strategic investors or corporate
venture capital investors.
So those are all the same.
So we showed this graphic
last time and time before
and just to give a rough idea
of the kinds of amounts
that you might expect--
and again it should be calibrated
to your own country's per capita GDP.
So these are sort of industrialized
country amounts.
$100,000 dollars or francs
which is roughly two times GDP per capita.
So we're going to start
from that piece of it.
So we're going to basically focus
on this part of the spectrum now.
So that's where we get
into the angel groups, family offices,
venture capital, and strategic partners.
So again, just to talk about how
to analyze your options.
This is exactly what we talked
about last time
and we're going to apply
the same criteria that we did last time
for the seed and the start up financing
to the growth and expansion financing.
We're going to look
at the financial criteria.
How much money can you raise?
How quickly can you raise it?
What's the time horizon of the investor?
What other costs are involved?
We're going to look
at management criteria.
Can they give you support
in the funding process?
in running your business?
Or can they add some other kind of value,
such as a reputational value,
credibility, etc.?
And then finally, we're going to look
at the independence that you gain
or that you maintain
depending on which investor invests,
and we're going to look at the degree
of separation between the source,
between the investor and your team.
In this particular case,
there's not going to be
a lot of variance there
because most of these investors
are going to be very distinct
from your team,
as opposed to your friends,
and family, etc.
But still, leave it on the list
as something to think about
when you are looking at any investment.
Alright, let's talk about angel groups.
An angel group is
a group of individual angels
who are wealthy individuals,
mostly former entrepreneurs,
who've already made money
and who want to give back in some way.
And they form a group,
an official organized group,
that meets on a regular basis.
Sometimes once a month,
or once every couple months
to screen ideas from entrepreneurs.
So what you're doing here
is you're making a pitch
in front of an angel group.
They might schedule
four to five different entrepreneurs
to come in and make pitches
and then, at the end of the presentation,
they would have a question
and answer period,
they would have a discussion
amongst themselves,
and then, they would have
some kind of vote or tally
to see if any of the members of the group
are willing to make an investment
in the entrepreneur's company.
And so that would go to the next level,
you would actually do due diligence
and then, they would basically
make a proposal to sell
some of the equity
of your company to this group.
So the ranges of this is going
to be typically $250,000 to $1.5 million,
which represents 30 times GDP per capita
with a typical amount
on the order of $500,000,
or say ten times GDP per capita.
The time frame can be relatively quick.
A lot of angel groups
advertise their existence
and have a process for applying.
Although it is recommended that you
do homework on the group,
find out what their specialities are,
find out what they like
before just sending out applications
to every single angel group.
It could be done in a month or two.
The time horizon of these angel groups
is often relatively patient.
It's on the order of five to ten years.
Sometimes, they would like to get it out
in a subsequent round
or before a real exit event.
But in many cases, that's not possible,
and they realize that.
Many times they are willing
to wait a little bit longer,
and they do tend to come in earlier
in the growth financing
or the late start up financing phase.
Let's talk about the advantages of having
an angel group as your investor.
One of the biggest advantages
is that you can get input or advice
from some of these angels.
You're going to have a broad talent base.
So you're going to have
a large number of people.
You get exposure and some of them
are probably going to be experts
in the same sector in which you are
already operating or proposing to operate.
So these people are going to be
very, very good people
for advice on running your company.
Beyond that, for the exposure,
imagine how long it would take
if you had to hit up, solicit,
one angel investor at a time.
It would take months.
Whereas you might be able
to walk into a room
of 10 to 50 angels all at once;
and some of them might be
interested in your idea.
And then, in addition to all these,
once you get the investment
this can also be considered
a positive signal for your reputation.
So it does have reputational benefits.
It gives you some credibility to say,
"I've received an investment
from an angel group,"
which tend to be more well known
than any individual angel.
Disadvantages: of course, here you are
--just like when we talked about
in the last segment--
you are going to give up a little bit
of control of your company.
And you're going to have to give up
sort of the decision rights
depending on your negotiation
with the group.
They'll be probably one lead investor,
one lead angel investor,
and that person will be
the primary point of contact
but you are going to have to deal
with several people
and the second disadvantage
is they may or may not all agree
with each other all the time.
Of course at the beginning
they're going to be very enthusiastic,
that's why they chose
to invest in your company
but over time, they may not always
agree with each other
and since they're independent individuals
you're going to have to negotiate
with multiple people at the same time
for the direction of your company,
management decisions, etc.
A family office is an investor
that invests the fortune
of a single family.
And so they're usually looking
for a portfolio investment
to diversify their own financial risk.
In many cases, the family office
would not be interested
in talking to an individual entrepreneur.
They may be more likely to be
a partner in a venture capital fund.
We'll talk about that in a minute.
But occasionally, family offices
do make investments
in individual businesses,
and it's becoming more common lately.
So this would be, again, you're going
to sell a share of your company
to a private investor
who represents a family fortune
and this is going to be
an equity based investment.
So they're going to take
a share of your company.
The amount range is relatively high.
That's because these investors
don't want to deal
with a bunch of small investments,
lots of companies,
lots of stakeholders, etc.
So in general, these are going
to be on the higher side,
probably a more
capital intensive business.
$5 million, which is
a 100 times GDP per capita
I would say would be
on the low end of that range,
and it can go up from there.
Hard to say what the typical
investment is here, really.
Because these are not public events.
Most people don't talk about them.
They're relatively private transactions.
So they are on the higher end
of the scale here.
Usually, it might take one to three months
to find and negotiate a deal
with a family office.
The time horizon, on the other hand,
could be quite patient
on the five to ten year frame.
So the advantages here are, of course,
they are larger amounts of money,
which is really nice especially
if you have some major capital needs
for your growth or expansion phase.
So what are the advantages of
receiving investment from a family office?
The first big one is: these are
relatively large amounts of money.
If you have a large capital need,
you need to buy equipment
or make an investment in a plant,
or maybe you just have
a big marketing campaign
which requires a lot of capital
then you can raise larger amounts
of money from them.
They probably are more patient then other
late stage investors,
such as venture capitalists.
The disadvantages though
is very difficult to gain entry
to find the family office business
and to talk to somebody,
to actually pitch to them.
I think it's actually a very tricky thing.
You have to work through
a network; usually.
They almost always work
on professional referrals.
So it's tricky
to get into a family office.
That's why ordinarily, we don't much
consider it to be a very credible source,
but on the other hand,
if you happen to run into one
or get access to one,
then you get all the advantages
we've just discussed.
You're going to relinquish
some control of your business.
These are going to be equity investors,
so they are going to have a say
in your management decisions.
On the other hand,
they're probably not going to give you
any kind of advice or input
but rather be on the more passive side
of the investing advice spectrum.
Alright let's talk about venture capital.
Venture capital lumes large
in the minds of most entrepreneurs,
even though most entrepreneurs
don't get it
or don't even need it in most cases.
However, it's so talked about
that I figured it would be good for us
to get the basics
of how venture capitalists works
and what are some of the plus
and minuses of it for this segment here.
The idea behind venture capital
is you are going to sell
a share of your company
to a professional growth investor.
These are going to be equity
in based investments
and so you are in fact going to relinquish
some part of the ownership
of your company.
And the amounts range on the higher side.
So usually on the order
of two to ten million dollars,
or let's just say 200 times
GDP per capita,
and it's hard to say
what a typical amount is,
but it could be on the relative
on the lower end of that $2 million area.
These are often staged investments
so that means even if you raise
two million from the venture capitalist,
they may not give it to you all at once.
In fact, they're almost never going
to give it to you all at once.
They're going to tie it
to milestones and deadlines.
They're going to check up on you,
and they are going to see if you are
following the plan that you originally had
or if you have some ideas
for how to modify the plan.
In terms of the time frame here,
usually two to three months.
Could be more, depending on how long
the negotiation takes,
and how long it takes you to find some.
The time horizon here is going
to be relatively shorter.
Usually on the order
of five to seven years.
That's because they are looking to get
a return on their investment
in a relatively short period of time.
We'll talk about that next.
So what are the advantages here?
They're definitely going
to give you advice or input,
and they can help you make decisions
on managing your business;
and what to do, strategy decisions.
They have a great network.
So they are able to hire people for you
or find people for you to hire,
bring people in from their other former
portfolio companies
or portfolio companies,
or other connections that they have.
Generally, have a lot of good connections.
aThe amount of money raised
is also favorable for companies
that really have a capital need.
Usually, we say
a venture capital business is
funding really high growth
or high expansion phase
for capital intensive businesses.
It's not for every kind of company.
The disadvantages here
it's the same as the advantage:
they're going to give you
advice and input.
In this case, you may not like all
the advice and input that you receive,
but they're going to definitely
give it to you,
and really, really keep track
of what you're doing.
They're going to follow
what you're doing carefully.
You're going to relinquish some control,
you're going to give up
some ownership of the company,
but you're also going to give up
some decision rights.
They're going to have,
usually, some kind of veto power
over major strategic decisions
that you're making.
So they're going to really, really look
into what you're doing.
Typically, they're never going to sign
a non-disclosure agreement
or other sorts of things
for secrecy pursposes
because of legal reasons.
So technically, your ideas
could be diffused.
They could legally talk
to one of their other portfolio companies
or talk to someone else
and maybe inspired
by something that you said,
give the idea away to someone else.
Although, again, once they've made
the decision to invest in you,
they want you to grow,
and to do well, and be successful.
They're not just going to try
and give your ideas away to anybody
but your ideas could leak,
let's put it that way.
And as I mentioned earlier,
the investments are going to be staged.
They're not going to give you
all the money at once,
and they're going to have
milestone planning
and they're going to give you
the pieces of the investment,
a small piece at a time,
every time you hit a milestone.
Let's talk about how
venture capital works.
Venture capitalists make investments
for other investors.
They usually raise funds
for a specific fund,
and they go and they talk
to different people,
pension funds, family offices,
other wealthy investors,
and they take the money from them,
and they create
a small limited partnership
with those funds,
and then they take that money,
and they invest it in start up companies,
in a portfolio of start up companies.
Usually, the way the deal works
with the limited partners
is that there is a time horizon
at which the fund must be liquidated
and all remaining amounts of money
in the fund has to be returned
to limited partners.
So that's why there's
some kind of pressure here
to make an exit event happen.
So as we discussed a few segments ago,
the exit event,
which could be a trade sale,
or an initial public offering,
or some other follow-on investment
is a way for the investors
to exit the business.
Not necessarily the entrepreneurs.
And so what they're doing
is they are making investments
in a portfolio of companies
with a specific relatively
short time horizon
on the order of five to ten years,
they don't make
all the investments at once,
at the very beginning.
Time goes on;
and then they are building
their portfolio,
but they know that within seven years,
finally by the time they make
all their investments
they're going to need
to liquidate that fund.
So therefore, they really,really want
to see an exit event
for some of the portfolio companies
in their portfolio.
And if a company isn't performing,
it doesn't look as if it's going
to actually make a good exit event,
they may cut back on the effort
and attention they want to give to it,
and focus on one that they think
it's a very, very good chance
of recouping their investments
and all other portfolio companies.
Because an IPO can more than pay--
one IPO can more than pay
for all the investments that they made
and a trade sale would probably
break even on the investments themselves.
So they go for a couple big hit home runs.
They look for a couple big exit events.
They look for a couple trade sales,
which breaks even on perhaps
that particular investment,
and overall, they have a very nice return
which then they give back
to the limited partners in the end.
So that's why venture capitalists
typically are looking for growth,
and they are looking for exit
at a certain point in time
on a finite time horizon.
OK, let's talk about strategic investors.
Some people call them strategic partners
and some people call them
corporate venture capital investors.
And it's basically all the same.
It's when a large company
makes an investment in a start up.
And so therefore you as the entrepreneur
are going to sell a share
of your company to a larger company.
This is also an equity based investment.
Now the amounts are usually relatively
large for these kinds of transactions.
So let's say $1 million to $25 million.
That's 500 times GDP per capita.
Quite a large amount.
Typically, hard to say
because it's very very big variance,
but let's say on the order of $10 million.
The time frame is a little bit longer.
Let's say two to five months
because you have to find the investor.
You have to get into the right person
inside the big company,
and then you have to negotiate the deal.
Some companies set up their own units
for making corporate
venture capital investments.
But other companies don't have
such a official organized program,
they're more ad-hoc in the way
that they make investments,
and those companies take even longer
to decide what to do.
On the other hand, for a time horizon
depends on the motivation
of the big company.
It could be eight to ten years
relatively patient,
very patient in general.
It also depends on what the purpose
of this investment is
from the company's point of view.
If they're looking for a financial return.
So they really want to see an exit,
they'll have a similar time horizon
to a venture capitalist.
On the other hand, if they're looking
for more of a strategic return.
In other words, is your company going
to stimulate compliments
that are going to stimulate
demand for their product.
They may be willing to wait a long time
before trying to cash
out of your business.
The time horizon could be a relatively
long and patient ten year period
before they would even think very much
about trying to exit
the business as an investor.
So what are the advantages here?
There are lots of advantages.
They might be your biggest
customer or supplier.
So if they're your customer,
then they might think
that if you sell a lot,
then they're going to sell a lot to you.
So that could be a big advantage.
Your incentives are nice and aligned
in such a situation
or a supplier could be the same.
They usually don't have
the exit pressure, usually, as I say here
unless they're really, really focusing
on financial return to your company
which most research has shown
is not a very good idea
and usually not very successful from
the big company's point of view either.
You're better off looking
for a company that's interested in
the strategic investment
as opposed to a financial investment,
and that will also help
on the time horizon side
because there will be less pressure
to try and get you spruced up to sell.
Disadvantages.
You do need to relinquish some control.
They are going to have some influence
on your decision making
and compounding their influence
on your decision making is
the speed of their decision making.
Some people are attracted to start ups
because they want to make quick decisions
and many big companies,
especially the kinds that can make
these kinds of $10 million investments
in small companies
have very slow decision making processes.
You have to factor that in
because when you want
to do something very, very quick,
they may not be ready for it.
It may take them a very long time to build
consensus inside their big company.
Final disadvantage here is--
I put strategic conflict.
What does that mean?
Basically what that means is
at the beginning it looks very good.
It looks very complimentary. It's perfect.
But over time, you may find
that your business interests
and the big company's business interests
are not exactly aligned perfectly.
In which case, it can create
a lot of distraction for the entrepreneurs
and it creates a kind of a conflict
between the two companies.
And since they are part owner,
you're going to be involved
with them quite a bit,
and so if the conflict escalates,
it can be a big distraction.
OK, so here's the last slide.
It's the overview of the sources
of funding and the process.
And basically just summarizes
everything that we just discussed.
So just to point out a couple things.
On the left here we have
the various sources.
How much money you would typically raise
and how quickly this would happen.
I could have put this one here in red too
just because it can take a lot longer.
And we could probably
put this one in green
because they're more patient perhaps,
a strategic investor.
They do take a lot of time.
They may take a lot of time to make
the initial investment decision,
and they may take a lot of time to make
on-going strategic decisions for you.
They will give you input.
In fact, all of these sources
are going to give you input
in managing your company.
And as I point out here, that can be good
because you can get good input
from a venture capital
but on the other hand,
you can also get a lot of input,
maybe too much input,
from a venture capitalist.
With a venture capitalist,
you do relinquish more control,
and they're going to be more involved.
On the other hand,
the reputational benefit of receiving
venture capital is very very good.
When you can claim
that you received venture capital,
it has a lot of other benefits when
you're dealing with suppliers, customers.
You say, "Oh, I'm a start up company.
Yeah, I don't really have any investors
I'm doing everything my own."
Versus: "I just got a major investment
from this company."
That can be quite useful when
you're talking with potential customers.
Just to continue on
with the venture capitalist here:
support in the funding process.
I put "Be careful!"
What I meant by that is the incentives
and the venture capitalists,
and the incentives and the entrepreneur
is not always 100% aligned,
especially when it comes
to funding the business.
Of course, if the business
does very well, everyone is happy,
and there's really no problem.
The only problem happens sometimes
when the business isn't taking off,
and then some of the structures
that you can get within your term sheet
you really have to look
those over carefully
to see how it happened.
In case things go well
and in case things go less well,
and they're going to take
an equity position in your company.
They're all going
to take equity positions.
But they're going to be
more active investors,
venture capitalists.
The only last couple things that I wanted
to say here about angel groups.
You can have many investors
and as it's a group, they're not working
together for the same company.
They are independent people and so you may
have to deal with many investors.
On the other hand,
they can give you advice
not only on the funding process
but also on management decisions,
and they also give you a good reputation.
If you can say, you've received
an investment from an angel group.
That could be considered beneficial
when you negotiate with other partners.
Independence, as I mentioned,
you're going to relinquish
some control no matter what.
You're probably going to relinquish
more decision making control
if you receive venture capital investment.
And in terms of the separation,
as I mentioned in the very beginning--
I didn't write anything here
because basically all of these sources
are very, very separated
from your typical team,
your founding team.
You're not related to them.
You're not working with them
all the time, etc.
So there's a very very clean separation
and they're all going to do
very, very careful due diligence,
which can take some time.
They're going to investigate
your business,
your business model, your business plan.
They're going to decide in a neutral way
whether it's worth it for them
to make an investment
because they're looking
for an eventual exit
or in the case
of a corporate venture capital,
they're looking for some kind
of strategic bonus for their own business
that will help their own business.
So let's have a look at an interview
now to talk a little bit about
some of these sources of financing,
and we're going to see you soon
for the next segment.
Thanks a lot.