Welcome back!
This is about Crowdfunding, Part II.
As you know, we already talked about
the marketing aspects of crowdfunding
a week or two ago,
and now we're going to talk
about the financial aspects
of crowdfunding.
Exactly, and like any good movie,
it has a sequel,
so this is Crowdfunding part II.
- Son of... Crowdfunding!
- Exactly!
(laughter)
Okay, as you recall
from our discussion of marketing,
crowdfunding is when candidates
or entrepreneurs
are exposed via internet platforms
to a wide variety of backers
that may help them financially
and otherwise in their campaigns.
Exactly, so when you think
about crowdfunding,
you can think about that in a more
systematic way in the following sense:
you have, on the one hand,
the entrepreneur,
on the other hand, the crowd,
and you can transmit project information,
potential rewards towards the crowd.
The crowd could provide you
with seed funding
and other non-financial resources
like reputation, etcetera.
We talked about that
in the marketing part,
but essentially it's enabled by the web
and that's why we see it
as a fairly new phenomenon,
but a phenomenon that has taken off
quite dramatically
in the past few years, and therefore
it's very important to entrepreneurs
in all kinds of directions
and regions on Earth.
(Chris) So, it's no surprise
that crowdfunding
has raised a lot of money
over the last five years or so.
In 2012 it was 2.7 billion,
in 2013 5.1 billion.
People projected-- they haven't
quite calculated for 2014 yet,
but almost double that again.
So it's a really, really important
phenomenon right now--
- Worldwide.
(Chris) Now, these players, of course,
they have their roles
as we discussed a little bit
in the marketing segment,
their different roles switch around.
Sometimes the entrepreneur
becomes a backer,
but in general, they're the entrepreneurs.
They're people who like to make things.
There are artists, there are fans,
and there are many other roles
people can back one
and receive money from another
and generally speaking, take part
in this crowdfunding ecosystem.
(Marc) Some people even just want
to spend time on a crowdfunding platform
because it's also fun to watch,
and then they become backers.
Just because it's fun to back others
with exciting plans.
(Chris) So we think about
the different ways
that you can raise money
through crowdfunding
and we've identified
at least five or six here
that use different mechanisms,
and on the left side of these slides,
what we've done is shown you examples
of different crowdfunding sites
that are actually out there right now
that use these different methods.
So the first one might be equity funding.
And by equity funding, what that means
is that you're really giving up
a piece of your company,
just as we discussed
already this past week.
It's not quite set up in most countries
in the world right now.
I think the UK and Australia and Italy
are examples of places
where it's already legal
and the US is moving
down that road right now.
The issue being that when you have
lots of equity backers,
that you might be thought to have
a publicly traded company.
So you have to have
special rules in place to say,
"Well, if it's a small amount of money..."
(chuckles) etcetera,
- Then you may not be considered--
- It's a complicated problem.
(Chris) It's a complicated problem.
So equity funding is one way of doing it.
Generally speaking,
it's not the most common way
- But it is something that you see--
- It's up and coming.
(Chris) It's up and coming, for sure
and more countries are doing it now.
Another kind is for debt financing,
and here your crowdfunding
is going to be soliciting loans for you
and you're supposed to pay them back.
(Marc) So it's an interest payment,
which could be much higher
than the current interest rates
you get in bank accounts.
(Chris) Yeah, usually it's
a lower interest or no interest loan
depending on the site,
but each one is different,
and it is one of the options.
Again, it's not one of the most common
types of crowdfunding schemes
but it is something to be aware of
in case you are able
to get that kind of financing.
The third type is called
reward-based crowdfunding
and that's where you make a donation
and you get some kind of reward back
for having made the donation.
(Marc) We brought some examples with us.
Yeah, this is actually something
that our assistant, Netra, did.
She actually went
onto this crowdfunding site
as you can see on the slide,
and in recognition
of having donated some money,
what she was able to do
is she got a photo of the artist
and she got a sample
of the textile that would be used
and then, eventually, she made
a donation and she received
this handsome mini purse as the reward
for having made that donation.
The next kind of schema is the pre-sales,
and we talked a little bit
about this in marketing.
This is where you have a prototype
or you are not quite ready for production,
but you are actually
selling your inventory in advance.
It's a great way of reaching your market
and of getting money to help finance
the manufacturing
or the growth of your business.
That was pre-sales.
Now, for sales, some sites like
Tilt here are setting it up
so that if you reach your goal,
you could actually continue to sell
as an additional sales channel,
like an e-commerce site selling
your products or services on their site
after you've reached your goal.
So then you've got your post--
you've got your pre-sales,
and then once you make your goal,
you keep selling through that channel.
(Marc) Which actually is
kind of a nice solution here,
because you can stay
on the same platform,
people know that you're on the platform,
so you can move from pre-sales
to sales very efficiently
and it's also kind of nice
for this platform
because they keep the companies
while they're operational.
So it's I think, a win-win strategy
by both sides.
The last scheme for crowdfunding is
what we're calling In-kind contribution.
That's where someone may say,
"Hey, I will do your
marketing plan for you."
or "I will help you advertise."
Basically, people donating their time,
and this is where
it's kind of this funny fine line
between crowdfunding and crowdsourcing,
because crowdsourcing is actually
trying to solicit services
or knowledge from people
across the internet, across the world,
and this is also saving you money,
because now you don't have to pay someone
to develop a marketing plan for you.
(Marc) Exactly, and it can help you
to figure out also for what other things
you might have to raise money,
because there's no one out there
who can help and support you
with your activities
or with the type of resources
you're looking for.
So you've seen all these examples
but you might still ask yourself,
"Why do I need crowdfunding?
Why should I do it?"
The marketing aspects are one thing,
but the financial aspects
are another thing.
Right, so I think that it's
a great source for seed financing
across a very wide range of dollar amounts
and except for the one case
that we discussed already,
where you have equity crowdfunding,
in most cases the backers
do not take equity in your venture.
Exactly, and you should remember
also that you are obliged
to actually use the proceeds
that you get from a crowdfunding campaign
according to the purpose you proclaimed.
So it's keeping your promise
to do these things
that you actually execute it
and promise to execute.
And if you don't do it, then, of course,
it can have really bad
reputational effects for you too.
So it's really important--
sometimes it's obligated,
and in most cases,
you want to do it anyways.
Now let's talk about
the funding options here.
We want to draw a distinction
between two types of funding options,
and it may influence how you set up
your crowdfunding campaign too.
The first one is called fixed,
which is all or nothing.
Basically, if you don't
reach your threshold,
you don't get any funding,
and the other is called flexible
which is where you get
to keep whatever you raise
regardless of what your goal is.
We'll talk about the pluses
and minuses of each of those next.
(Marc) For the fixed funding schemes,
the all or nothing,
the pros are fairly evident.
You have a solid dollar amount goal.
That's transparent for everyone,
for you and for others.
It creates some sense of urgency
and it could be a quick motivation,
especially if you're getting
close to that amount,
people might say,
"I'll help this guy,
I feel sorry for him
but he cannot reach it,
so I feel motivated now
to actually support him."
(Chris) You call all your friends
and you say,
(Marc) I just need--
(laughing)
It's straightforward for the backers
and it builds trust,
because you say "I only do it
if I reach that amount."
It's in a way communicating to others
that "If I don't reach that amount,
it's useless to start the project, even."
So it signals also that it's
very well thought through.
This option is offered on almost every
type of crowdfunding platform out there.
(Chris) In terms of the negatives here,
if you don't reach your goal,
you get nothing.
In general, there may be some options
in certain sites to make you pay
a higher fee and getting what you got
instead of your goal,
but in general, you don't get anything.
So there's definitely some pressure there.
There's also pressure
to deliver something creative
because you want to attract the backers
and you need them to give you the money,
or else you won't hit
your threshold target.
Lastly, this requires a lot of confidence.
You have to feel like you are really
going to get this amount.
You have to strategically think
about what is your threshold
that you're willing to shoot for
so you can get all the amount.
Now, usually, if in these situations
you raise more than the amount,
then you get to keep whatever
is above your threshold as well.
Let's talk about a couple of examples
here of some fixed schemes.
This one on the left shows a smart remote
and it looks as if they set
an initial target of $9,000 or something
and they ended up raising $33,000
or something around that,
and the second one was this watch
that was set to raise $60,000
or something like that
and ended up raising $372,000
and this became on this Indigogo site
called the in-demand option
which basically, as we mentioned before,
allows you to continue selling
through their channel
because you've exceeded
your goal by some vast amount.
(Marc) Let's move to the flexible
funding schemes now
and again there are pros
and cons towards that.
(Marc) I will talk about the pros.
(Chris) And I'm mister negative.
(Marc) You talk about the cons, okay.
The pros are fairly straightforward again.
It's because you do not have such a fixed
target that you're trying to fill,
this is not such an important
strategic move, to set that.
You can set one or the other goal,
but it's not important that it is reached.
So it's not as significant
as a strategic move.
You therefore worry less
about reaching your funding goal
and there's less timing pressure
for your campaign.
On the other hand there are cons.
(Chris) Yeah, so there's less
of a guarantee for backers.
It's not obvious that this whole thing
will be pulled off, in some sense,
and I think a lot of backers
don't perceive it to be
as serious of an endeavor
as a fixed funding
and there can be potential for higher fees
just because some platforms charge you
more for small amounts of money,
or if you don't make your goal
you may have to pay more, etcetera.
You still get it, but you have to pay
a little bit higher fees for it,
and it's not always offered
on every platform.
Basically, you don't have the opportunity
to always do a flexible funding option.
Here's a great example of a flexible one.
This was the "Flow-Hive"
and these guys invented a beehive
that would actually deliver
the honey to you directly
so you don't have to go inside the hive.
(Marc) A very secure option.
(Chris) Here you see they raised
8.5 plus million dollars,
and they're selling these things,
so for $600 you could have your own hive
and they're careful to note
that bees are not included.
(laughing)
(Marc) But the interesting thing is,
if you look closely,
is they had a $70,000 goal so that
was a big surprise to the upside.
You're asking for $70,000
and then getting $8.558 million.
So that's an amazing multiple there.
Right, so what you want to do is decide
which platform you want to be on,
and there are some big ones out there,
but there are also
a lot of smaller ones as well.
So there are lots of crowdfunding options
awaiting for you.
One key question is, who do you
want to compete with for the money?
Because if there are 5 million
other projects out there,
you're one out of 5 million
and these sites would have
fewer people competing for money
and that might mean getting
more attention to your project.
Also sometimes some
of these platforms are specialized.
They might have a certain
geographic scope,
some social goals, there may be
different kinds of backers
associated with the different sites.
So it's really important
to go through these things
and decide what's best for you,
what kind of site are you looking for.
Especially the question of what type
of backers you want to attract.
Some backers might be
on some sites and not on others
so this is quite an important
question to figure out.
For example, they could have
more customer oriented ones
that buy your product on one site
versus people who want
to make a donation on another site.
If you're trying to sell something
to people who want to make a donation,
that might not be the best possible match
toward the audience that you have there.
Now, the niches could be large or small,
so what you have to think these through
is how big is your audience?
What kind of potential
do you want to reach?
And what is the best site for you?
To give you some intuition
on what this means,
we've given you a few examples here.
For example, a geographic focus here.
There's this one called the Cheetah Fund
which is not accepting
new applications now,
but was basically if you were based
in Africa, had a good idea,
and you made a goal, they
might actually turn around
and match some of that.
(Marc) Here's another one.
(Chris) This other one is this Carrotmob,
for example,
a very interesting idea here is
you can create a mob that then
helps out the entrepreneur.
So if you have a small hotel
and you need to have money
for renovating the hotel,
you need people to stay in the hotel
to become more profitable,
someone, a backer, might organize
all their friends to stay in your hotel
and that would give you the money
that you need to make your renovation.
(Marc) So you just have to make sure
that they have a pleasant time.
(laughing)
(Chris) That's for sure!
Then, to think about your backer profile,
basically this is just advice
to think this thing through.
What kinds of person would you
like to attract to be your backer?
And then, trying to match that
with the backers
that are associated
with the various sites.
Here age, gender, interests--
we already mentioned geographical location
what websites do they frequent,
and some of their motivations.
What do they want to do with this site?
Do the backers want equity in your company
or do they want early access?
Do they want to really
test out a cool prototype
- or feel good about themselves?
- Yeah, some people just like to help
(Marc) which is a great character trait,
like Chris', always trying to help people.
(laughter)
(Chris) That's right!
I'm always helping.
(Marc) The backers are
one part of the equation
but the other part of the equation
is really the factors that attract backers
to your site and gain the backers.
It's one thing to get people interested
but another thing to get people committed
and there's actually research that shows
the factors that are driving
this process of gaining backers
and there are two major
elements in particular.
One is credibility
and the other one is appeal.
So in terms of credibility,
it's about your professionalism
and the feasibility of your project
that matters a lot,
and the appeal means, is this
a relevant issue, a relevant product
or a relevant social cause
that you're trying to address?
And your understanding
of the customer need and the desire.
(Chris) How compelling it is?
How compelling your story is.
(Marc) Exactly, so you have to tell a nice
and compelling story on the website
because people will judge you
based on how well that is communicated
so credibility and appeal
are two extremely important factors
and what is underlying all of this
that I'm talking about is the notion
that you have to prepare very well.
You need to understand
what is appealing to your audience
and how can you come across
as being a very credible entrepreneur.
This is not only important
on the crowdfunding platform.
It's important in any type
of social interaction,
but here in particular, because
people only see you on the net.
(Chris) That's all they get from you--
(Marc) Exactly, and you want money
from them, you know?
(Chris) So as Marc said,
these things take time.
You need to budget your time
to set something up that's compelling,
that's credible, and that's appealing.
Tell your story and tell
your team's experience.
(Marc) Because that engages the viewer.
They will share your experience.
They will understand why you're doing it,
for what cause you're doing it,
so they get enthused like you are.
(Chris) Right, be prepared.
You need to make a plan
and you need to know what to expect.
Finally, you need to be realistic
and relevant and creative in your rewards.
Think through what would attract somebody.
If they were to give me money,
what would I give them,
and how would they like that?
So you can be creative about these things
and you can sell some things, give gifts,
depending on the kinds
of platform that you choose.
(Marc) And remember what
we said in marketing,
because this is, in a way, also marketing.
It's like spend imagination
instead of money, in that sense.
Spend imagination
and your creativity and understanding.
What type of rewards might be particularly
appealing to your target backers?
(Chris) So bringing it back full circle,
we think that crowdfunding
is a very important topic
for entrepreneurs today.
That's also why it's
a major part of this MOOC
and remember, you are developing
your own crowdfunding campaign
here in this MOOC
which allows you to raise funds,
to get your company off the ground,
but it also allows you to win
some additional funding
because we secured some funds to actually
give the top performers in this course
the possibility to win
$2,500 in seed funding.
That's quite nice, no?
We're going to have
a whole little tutorial
about this specific details
of how to get onto the platforms
and how to actually integrate
the course material
with your crowdfunding campaign.
We're going to do that later this week.
Just as a footnote here, I think
this might be the only MOOC
where you can actually win some money
by learning something!
This is the only MOOC
where we pay you!
(laughter)
Exactly.
So stay with us and keep on pushing!
This is the segment on crowdfunding
and there will be other great segments
on financing coming up.