Today's armed conflict and resulting
humanitarian crises
are increasingly complex.
There are greater in number.
often in urban settings;
longer in duration;
and broader in regional impact.
They generate human suffering
on a greater scale;
disrupt essential services;
such as water supply or sanitation
and put health of large populations at risk.
[Music]
In order to tackle these challenges,
engineers and technical specialists
in water, sanitation,
electricity, environment
and other related fields,
play a vital role.
In the humanitarian sector,
they are called the public health
engineers;
and today they are increasingly needed.
Why is the public health engineering essential
in humanitarian crisis ?
And how are related activities carried out
in such a complex environment?
This is what this mooc is all about.
This mooc brings you expertise
of EAWAG scientists in water
and sanitation
and the humanitarian experience
of I.C.R.C Public health engineers.
In addition,
this mooc features a certain number
of real case studies
for you to gain a concrete
and pragmatic understanding
of the humanitarian challenges.
So interested to know more?
Are you interested to know
how you could use your technical
and engineering skills
to alleviate suffering of people
afflicted by humanitarian crisis?
Join us for this mooc.