Well done, you made it through the first week
of this course.
During this week, we have seen that communicable
diseases such as diarrheal diseases and malaria
are a major cause of mortality and morbidity
in humanitarian contexts.
Context where the populations particularly
at risk, due to various factors such as stress,
malnutrition, overcrowding, poor housing and
unsanitary conditions.
In order to tackle these diseases, it is crucial
to involve various disciplines and specialists.
This multidisciplinary approach is conceptualised
in the model of pyramid of health.
In this model, engineers play an important
role to stop the transmission of hazards in
their environment through the provision of
adequate drinking water supply, proper excreta management
runoff and waste water disposal, collection and disposal of
refuse and effective vector control interventions.
Public health engineering measures focus on
putting multiple barriers to prevent the creation of
hazards,
its transport and the people from being exposed to it
once encountered.
In order to do so, public ealth engineers
should have a good understanding of the environmental
transmission pathways of the diseases.
Such understanding helps to put the appropriate
barriers at the right time and at the right
place.
For instance remember that faecal oral diseases
we have seen with the F-diagram the importance
of having adequate sanitation measures,
proper hygiene practices and adequate quantity
and quality of water to ensure health benefits.
I hope you enjoyed this first week and
stay on board with us for the next week to
continue to learn how to respond to the needs
of people affected by humanitarian crises. See you!