Welcome to this course entitled introduction
to public health engineering in humanitarian
context.
My name is Christoph Lüthi and I work for
the Swiss Federal Institute of aquatic science
and technology, EAWAG, and I am responsible for Sandec,
the department of sanitation water and solid waste
for development.
I am Javier Cordoba and I am working for the
water and habitat training of the international
committee of the Red Cross.
A one hundred fifty years old humanitarian
organization whose mandate is to ensure humanitarian
protection and assistance for victims of armed
conflicts and other situations of violence.
The world is facing unprecedented humanitarian
needs; we are witnessing an increase in the number
of humanitarian crises that tend to be more
and more complex and often in urban settings,
longer in duration and broader in regional
impact.
These humanitarian crises cause intense sufferings,
disrupt essential services and put populations
at greater risk of infectious diseases.
In order to respond to these challenges and
growing needs, well trained engineers and
specialists in water sanitation, energy supply,
environment and in other related fields
are increasingly needed.
This is why the ICRC and EAWAG have
decided to combine their expertise and experience
to deliver this MOOC which explores the field
of public health engineering in the specific
context of humanitarian crisis caused by armed
conflicts.
We have designed this course for a broad audience.
The main requirement for this course is to
be curious and excited to know more about
humanitarian engagement and engineering.
You might be a student, a professional or
a practitioner already working in the humanitarian
sector.
Our wish is that at the end of the course
you will be willing to use your engineering
and technical skills to contribute to the
humanitarian efforts that is so much needed
in today’s world.
Let’s have a look at the learning objectives
of this five-week course.
After this course, we would like you to understand
the link between water, sanitation and hygiene,
so-called wash activities and health in order
to identify key measures to be taken to reduce
the mortality and morbidity due to infectious
diseases encountered in humanitarian contexts.
Besides the public health aspect, we would
like you also to get familiar with the features
of humanitarian response, particularly with
the challenges posed by essential services
such as water supply, sanitation or electricity
during protracted armed conflicts.
Finally in order to be able to define the
outline of the humanitarian response in public
health engineering sector, you should be able
to know the main technologies encountered
in the humanitarian contexts.
This course consists of video lectures given
by ICRC experts and EAWAG researchers,
bringing together years of research and field
experience.
In addition we have included a selection of
videos from EWAG MOOC series, sanitation,
water and solid waste for development which
were relevant to the topic of this MOOC.
If you would like to learn more on the series
please visit our website.
Finally, in order for you to get an understanding
of reality on the ground this MOOC contains
real case studies and situations faced by
ICRC engineers in the field.
Let's take a closer look to the syllabus of
this course.
In week one, we will introduce you to the
topic of public health engineering and see
how engineers can have a significant impact
to reduce the mortality and morbidity encountering
many humanitarian contexts.
In order to do so, engineers should have a
good understanding on how infectious diseases
are transmitted.
A case study on plague eradication campaign
in Madagascar will illustrate the topic of
this week.
In week two, we will present the humanitarian
contexts in which public health engineering
activities take place.
We will see how protracted conflicts affect
urban essential services such as the water
supply or sanitation, resulting in public health
issues.
A case study on Iraq will illustrate this
challenge.
Week three reviews water technologies commonly
used from the source to the distribution point
in order to provide water.
This week will be based mainly on the water
technology compendium currently being developed
by some Swiss researchers.
Some ICRC case studies dealing with water
supply in emergencies will also be presented.
Week four then presents a sanitation compendium
developed by EAWAG that will be illustrated
with ICRC case studies related to sanitation
challenges in humanitarian context.
In the last week, we will focus on a type
of solid waste that pubic health engineers
often encounter in humanitarian crisis: medical
waste.
Finally, we will discuss the critical issue
of behaviour change in emergencies and hygiene
promotion.
Given the time available, this course will
not be able to provide you with a wide range
of details on the different aspects presented.
Our goal is to introduce you to the topics
and provide a general overview.
This is why for each week you will be referred
to ICRC and EAWAG publications available
for free on the internet and the course platform.
In addition, we will also refer you to publications
from other organizations.
On behalf of all of the lecturers,
have fun learning this MOOC!
We are looking forward to working
with you over the coming weeks.
Let's start the course!