Welcome to this first week of this MOOC.
During this week we will introduce you to the topic
a of public health engineering and see how engineers
can have a significant impact to reduce the mortality
and morbidity encountered in many humanitarian contexts.
You will learn about the link
between health and water, sanitation
and hygiene, so-called wash activities. Engineers in
humanitarian assistance should have a good understanding on how
infectious disease are transmitted. This is why you
will be introduced to different environmental transmission pathways
of diseases
and we will see some measures to be
taken to prevent the spread of diseases.
In particular, we will
talk about water quality
and quantity requirements in complex
emergencies as well as vector control measures.
In this video, we
will answer to the
question why public health engineering matters in
humanitarian crisis. In order to do so,
we need to understand the public health
approach that guides humanitarian
assistance of many humanitarian organizations.
It will help us to explain
the role of the public health engineering.
Finally, we will learn to identify some of the risks that put health
population particularly at risk during humanitarian situations.
Public health is defined as the art and
science of preventing disease, prolonging life
and promoting health through the
organized effort of society.
How is it translated
into humanitarian action?
Let's go back to 1979 at
the thai-cambodian border
where more than one million refugees are gathered in refugee camps.
At that time humanitarian assistance was mainly devoted to
surgical and curative care. Activities dealing with water
supply, sanitation or nutrition were perceived as secondary.
Facing a higher rate
of mortality and morbidity in these
refugee camps due to diarrhea
and vector borne diseases, an ICRC doctor named Pierre Perrin,
came up with what we called the pyramid of health model.
An idea that helped to change
the way the ICRC
and other humanitarian organizations
respond to humanitarian crises.
This model advocated to move emergency health programs
towards a broader public health orientation in order to preserve
life and health
and ensure respect for people's dignity. At the top of
the pyramid of health are the activities related to curative
care. That is medical interventions, generally done
at the field hospital when people are already sick
or injured. In the middle are prevention
measures such as vaccinations, distribution of medicines
or health education. While at the foundation
of the pyramid there are two key building blocks: nutrition
and public health engineering, which usually in humanitarian
contexts, aim to provide an adequate drinking water supply,
a proper excreta management,
runoff and waste water disposal, collection and
disposal of refuse and medical waste
and effective vector control interventions.
The idea behind the pyramid of health is that it makes no sense
to manage health issues of vulnerable people only from the top
with medical corrective care if their immediate
environment is the cause of their unhealthy state.
Tackling the root of the problem, particularly for infectious
diseases rather than only treating patients, is much more
effective to reach out a large population.
This approach was implemented in the eighties and very well
documented researches are shown that
the provision of adequate food, clean water, sanitation
and shelter activities were much more effective
than most medical programs to tackle diarrhea
and vector borne diseases. This is why this
model advocates for public health engineering
and nutrition activities to be done in close collaboration
with medical activities in order to achieve a public health
objective.
In order to understand the role of the public health engineer,
we have to look at the interaction between a population
and its environment. All that
can be schematized in the following diagram.
We see that in one side, the elements
originating in the environment which are
necessary to maintain a population’s life
and health such as water, food, energy, raw
materials for walls, materials for building a shelter
and also vectors of diseases such as rats
and mosquitoes and on the other side the waste
that the population is discharging to the environment in
the form of human excreta, garbage and liquid waste.
Between these two poles a vicious
cycle may be created.
Infectious diseases can be transmitted by direct
contact within the population, but also through the environment.
I give you an example. If human wastes are disposed inadequately
to the environment, it can lead to a proliferation of
pathogens contained in the
faeces in the water for instance.
As a result, it may lead to an increase of incidence
of diarrheal diseases within the population, which itself leads to an
increase of the contamination of the environment, which
leads to an increase of pathogens and so on. A vicious cycle.
Public health engineering relies on the
concept that certain hazards to the infection pathogens
or chemicals move through the environment
and cause harm to humans.
Therefore, public health engineering measures
focus on preventing the creation of hazards, its transport
and the people from being
exposed to it once encountered.
In the case of human waste for instance which we
mentioned earlier, we cannot avoid its creation
but the public health engineering can reduce
the spread of human waste in the environment by setting for instance a
proper sanitation system.
It can also treat water
and promote proper food hygiene practices in order to
reduce the exposure of people to faeces contained in the contaminated
food or water.
Another example in the case of the cambodian refugee camp,
we have seen earlier in the video. The fact that the camp was
moved away from the breeding site of the mosquitoes,
results actually in the reduction of the malaria mortality by
half and the incidence
rate by two thirds.
Now we understand there the role of the engineer is
actually to put the barriers of the creation, transport
and exposures to hazards
to improve the health.
Now because one barrier rarely functions at one hundred percent,
public health engineers should put multiple barriers.
In order to know where and
when to put these barriers to stop the vicious cycle
of transmission of the disease, the public health engineers should
have a very good understanding of the transmission cycle of the disease.
In a humanitarian context, the role of the public health
engineer is crucial because the population are particularly at
risk of the vicious cycle.
Indeed, factors such as overcrowding to the
influx of displaced persons, deterioration of essential services
and infrastructures such as healthcare, water
and sanitation systems, poor housing conditions in temporary
settlements of damaged structures, lower immunity due to
malnutrition or lack of health care, all that
aggravates the vulnerability of the population
to infectious diseases.
Let's sumarize this first lesson.
Communicable diseases such as the diarrheal diseases
and malaria are a major cause of mortality
and morbidity in humanitarian contexts where the
population is particularly at risk of contamination.
In order to protect the health of those affected
by humanitarian crises, it is absolutely crucial to ensure adequate
shelter, water, sanitation and food
and provide basic health care. As such it requires the
collaboration between these different sectors to achieve a truly
integrated public health approach in the humanitarian response.
It is the role of the public health engineer to put
the barriers in the environmental transmission pathways of
diseases through the implementation of measures
dealing with water supply, excreta management,
runoff and waste water disposal, hygiene promotion,
collection and waste disposal of refuse and medical waste
and vector control.
Depending on the organization, this public health
engineer is called the environmental health specialist,
the wash specialist or the water and
habitats such as in the ICRC.
Now, in order to design a good public health engineering
intervention, the public health engineers require a very good
understanding of the transmission cycle of diseases.
And that is what we will explain in the next videos.