Welcome to this video on environmental transmission
pathways.
Infectious diseases are a main cause of mortality
and morbidity in humanitarian crises.
Tackling them is one of the main goals of
public health engineering interventions.
In order to do so, a good understanding of
transmission cycle of diseases is required.
This is why during this video you will learn
to classify different infectious diseases
according to their transmission routes,
get familiar with the so-called F-diagram
and finally you will learn to identify appropriate
prevention strategies to tackle
some infectious diseases.
In public health engineering, we often use
the so-called Bradley classification to distinct
four types of water related roots by
which a disease may be transmitted from one
person to another.
Water-borne diseases are infections which can
be transmitted through drinking water which
contains the pathogens.
Water-borne diseases include diarrheal diseases
which is the second leading cause of death
in children under five years old and is responsible
for killing more than half a million of children
every year.
It also includes infectious hepatitis or polio.
All these diseases are part of the so-called
faecal oral diseases.
That is to say that infections occurring
when pathogens from the faeces of a sick person
are ingested by somebody else.
There are many different pathways for the
faeces containing the pathogens to gain entry
into the mouth, some are direct and others
indirect.
The F-diagram illustrates these main pathways.
They are easily memorized as they all begin
by the letter F. Fluids such as drinking
water, fingers, flies, fields or crops and
soil and food.
In order to stop the transmission of these
diseases, primary barriers can be put to prevent
the initial contact with the faeces.
It is mainly done with sanitation intervention
which aims to contain human excreta so that
it is not free to spread into the environment.
Secondary barriers can also be put to prevent
faeces from being ingested by a new person.
For instance, by ensuring adequate water quality
or ensuring proper hygiene practices mainly
hand washing.
In this F-diagram you can clearly see the
importance of having adequate sanitation,
proper hygiene practices and adequate quantity
and quality of water to ensure health benefits.
The second type of water related diseases
are water-washed diseases.
Infections that are caused by pathogens whose transmission
can be prevented by improving personal hygiene.
Good personal hygiene requires availability
and use of water for bathing, clothes washing
and utensils washing.
Therefore, the transmission mechanism is related to
the quantity of water rather than water quality.
There are three types of water-wash diseases,
the ones associated with the faecal route
with similar diseases to water-borne diseases,
infections of skins or eyes that are not related
to the faecal oral route but also due to poor
hygiene such as trachoma which is the leading
infection caused by blindness worldwide.
And finally infections carried by lice and
which may be reduced by improving personal
hygiene such as typhus.
The third type of water related diseases is
called water-based.
Here the pathogen spends part of its life
cycle in the water usually in a snail or another
aquatic animal.
Pathogens usually enter the water from faeces
and urine of an infected person.
The pathogen is transmitted by ingestion or
by penetration of the skin.
The water-based diseases are all caused by
parasitic worms but not all parasitic worms
are water-based but two of the most significant
are the guinea worm and the schistosomiasis.
Schistosomiasis affects millions of people
each year.
People become infected when the larval forms
of the parasite released by freshwater snails
penetrates the skin during contact with infested
water.
Play habits of school age children such as
swimming or fishing in infested water made
them especially vulnerable to infections.
Finally, the fourth route of diseases spread
by insects which breed in water or by near
water.
Malaria, yellow fever and dengue are diseases
transmitted by these transmission mechanisms.
Knowing the transmission route for diseases
help to identify key interventions to be done
to reduce the spread of diseases.
For instance, to tackle water-borne diseases
we need to improve water quality by treating
water, preventing its contamination.
For water-washed diseases, we have to increase
access and availability of water to ensure
better hygiene.
For water-based, it is difficult to treat
infected water surface baddies but we can prevent
people from getting into contact with them.
For water related insect vectors, we can apply
some vector control measures that we will see further
in detail during this week.
Unlike the conventional biological taxonomy
which classifies diseases according to the nature
of the pathogens,
in public health engineering, we prefer to
classify infectious diseases according to
their environmental transmission pathways.
It is more helpful to identify the type of
environmental measures needed.
In this video we have seen the Bradley classification
to describe water related diseases but similar
classifications also exist for refuse related
diseases, vector related diseases or housing
related diseases such as tuberculosis which
kills more than malaria worldwide.
Remember, knowing the transmission cycle of
the disease is key to identify the appropriate
measures to be tackled.