There are hundreds, maybe thousands of organisms
which can cause water-borne diseases.
One useful way to classify these pathogens
is by biological type.
In this module, we will briefly talk about
four different classes of pathogens. The most
important ones are the protozoa, bacteria
and viruses but we will also give an example
of one helminth or parasitic worm which is
transmitted through drinking water.
The first thing to know about pathogens is
that they are small but human hair is about
0.1 millimetres or 100 microns
in diameter.
Protozoa, the largest class of pathogens, are
much smaller, usually about 10 to 50 microns
in size.
Protozoa are one-cell eukaryotes, that means
that their cell has a nucleus unlike prokaryotic
cells such as bacteria.
Some protozoa can form an egg like cyst to
survive harsh conditions such as exposure
to extreme temperature, chemicals or long periods
without water or food.
Many protozoa are parasites and cause diseases
like malaria and giardia. Here you see entamoeba histolytica
and cryptosporidium parvum, both of which can
cause severe diarrhea.
Entamoeba is the cause of amoebic dysentery
or bloody diarrhea.
This disease affects adults more than
children and only about 10-20% of those
infected with entamoeba develop symptoms.
It is estimated to cause more than a hundred
thousand deaths per year.
Recent studies have shown that cryptosporidium,
commonly called crypto, is one of the leading
causes of diarrheal disease among children.
A large and important research project, the
Global Enteric Multicenter Study or GEMS has found
it to be the second most commonly isolated
pathogen among children with diarrhea, after
rotavirus.
Cryptosporidium-form cysts which are about
5 microns in diameter and are highly resistant
to treatment.
The first human cases of crypto were reported
in 1976 and the disease became infamous in
1993 when an outbreak occurred in the northern
US city of Milwaukee.
Cryptosporidium overwhelmed the treatment
plants filtration system and chlorine has
no effect on crypto.
Over two weeks, 400,000 people
became ill and over 100 deaths were
caused mainly in people with compromised immune
systems.
Cryptosporidium is a major cause of death
among people with HIV/ AIDS.
The infectious dose for cryptosporidium and
other protozoa is low, even a single cyst can
cause disease.
Bacteria are organisms of a few microns in
size and of varying shapes such as spheres,
rods or spirals.
They are prokaryotes which means that, unlike
the protozoa, they do not contain a nucleus.
Bacteria are everywhere growing in soil, in
the deep ocean and even in acidic hot springs.
A gram of soil or a millilitre of water can
contain several million bacterial cells.
Although the vast majority of bacteria are
harmless or even beneficial to humans a few
can cause diseases such as cholera, trachoma
or salmonella.
Here you see the E. coli and vibrio cholera
bacteria.
They, like most bacteria, are about 1 or
2 microns in size.
E. coli is universally found in human and
animal faeces but is normally not pathogenic.
In fact, E. coli is the preferred indicator
bacteria used to demonstrate faecal contamination.
However some strains of E. coli do cause disease.
These are called pathogenic E. coli and one
group of these pathogens is the enterotoxigenic
E. coli or E-Tec. The GEMS project found E-Tec to be
among the top five pathogens isolated from
children with diarrhea and affects particularly
small infants.
The other bacterial pathogen most commonly
found by GEMS was shigella, a distant relative
of E. coli.
Together, shigella and E.coli are thought
to cause up to one third of the diarrheal
disease mortality globally.
Vibrio cholera causes the terrifying disease
cholera.
It can spread very rapidly under the right
conditions and can cause severe diarrhea and
death within hours if not treated.
Cholera thrives in conditions where there
is crowding and poor sanitation and hygiene.
Outbreaks can occur after natural disasters,
in refugee camps and in peri-urban slums.
There are an estimated 3 to 5 million
cholera cases and 100,000 to
120,000 deaths due to
cholera every year.
The smallest of the pathogens are the viruses
which are typically 0.1 microns, that is the
same as 100 nanometers, or even smaller
in diameter.
Viruses don't have an independent metabolism
they can only grow or reproduce within a living
host cell and cannot multiply within the environment.
Many viruses are host specific, causing disease
in humans or specific animals only.
Rotaviruses and Hepatitis A and E viruses
are the most widespread water-borne viruses
affecting humans.
Here you see rotavirus at about 75 nanometres and hepatitis
E which is quite small at about 30 nanometres.
You could line up thousands of hepatitis E
viruses and still be smaller than a human
hair.
Rotavirus is one of the main pathogens causing
diarrheal disease.
The GEMS project found rotavirus to be the
single most commonly isolated pathogen among
children with diarrheal disease.
It is particularly prevalent among
the youngest children.
Infected people shed large numbers of the
virus in their faeces, approximately 10 to
the 11 viruses per gram of faecal matter.
That is a hundred thousand of millions.
The viruses are highly effective, only ten
to a hundred virus particles are needed to
cause infection.
Rotavirus was estimated to cause over five
hundred thousand deaths each year in 2004
with more than 85% of these
deaths occurring in low income countries in
Africa and Asia.
Hepatitis A is spread through food, water
or direct contact with infected people.
Hepatitis E is mainly spread through drinking
water.
Both diseases are widespread in the developing
world, in countries with poor sanitation and
hygiene nearly all children are infected before
the age of ten.
Every year there are over 3 million acute
cases of hepatitis E and over 50,000 deaths
related to hepatitis E.
Finally, although it is nearly eradicated,
polio remains an important water borne virus.
There were only 223 cases reported in 2012
down from some 350,000 cases in 1988.
Only three countries remain polio endemic;
Afghanistan, Nigeria and Pakistan but as long
as a single child remains infected, children
in all countries are at risk.
Water sanitation and hygiene play an important
role in eliminating polio.
From the smallest of pathogens to the largest,
the helminths or parasitic worms which can
invade human intestines or other tissues.
Most helminth transmission is due to poor
sanitation hygiene but one particularly nasty
helminth is mainly transmitted through drinking
water.
This is dracunculus medinensis or guinea worm.
Its larvae live in fresh water and are eaten
by small aquatic insects called coppa pods.
The larvae are tiny but the coppa pods are
big, typically about 1 millimetre and visible
to the naked eye.
Once a person drinks water containing the
coppa pods, hydrochloric acid in the stomach
kills the insect and releases the larvae which
mature and grow into adult worms.
These can reach a length of nearly a metre
and be as wide as a spaghetti noodle.
The worms migrate through the body and emerge
through the skin often near the feet.
The worm has to be removed slowly winding
it up and pulling it out of the body bit by
bit over weeks.
This is extremely painful, it creates sores
and blisters and people often soak their feet
in water to relieve the pain.
The worm then discharges hundreds of thousands
of larvae into the water completing the transmission
cycle.
Major progress has been made towards eliminating
guinea worm.
Since 1986, the global eradication campaign
has been led by the Carter Centre in close
collaboration with W.H.O., the C.D.C. and UNICEF.
The number of reported cases has dropped from
3.5 million in 1986 to just 542
in 2012.
As of 2012, it is found only in a few hundred
villages in remote rural areas mostly in south
Sudan with a handful of cases in Ethiopia,
Mali and Chad.
Once guinea worm is eradicated, it will be
the only second human disease ever eradicated
after smallpox.
Unless of course polio is eradicated first,
which seems unlikely.
And unlike smallpox, guinea worm will be beaten
without vaccines or drugs through community
scale interventions which involve protection
and treatment of drinking water.
Because the coppa pods hosts are large they
can be readily removed from water, using simple
cloth or sand filters.
So in summary, we have covered four main types
of pathogens today.
We have talked a little bit about helminths
with the example of dracunculus or guinea worm
disease which is transmitted through these
very large coppa pods around a millimetre
in diameter.
The next biggest are the protozoa such as
entamoeba, cryptosporidium and giardia which
are 10 to 50 microns in diameter and can
form very resistant cysts.
Then we have got the bacteria such as E.coli,
shigella, vibrio cholera which are 1 or
2 or 3 microns in size and can cause
serious diarrhea and then finally the smallest
class is the viruses, rotavirus, hepatitis,
polio virus which are even smaller than a
micron as small as thirty nanometres in size.