Is this glass of water safe to drink?
Good question huh? So in order to answer this
very important question you are going to
see this video.
What are the standards to be used? What are
the main criteria to be used? And finally,
we'll talk about water quality analyses.
In any case, you must ensure that the quality
of water supplied complies with the national
water quality regulation in the country where
you are working.
In the absence of recognised national standards
you can refer to the values and recommendation
contained in the W.H.O. water quality guidelines.
These guidelines are available for free in
the Internet so don't hesitate, go on and consult
them.
Three main criteria are used in W.H.O
guidelines to assess if water is fit for human
consumption.
The microbiological quality, it is usually
the primary concern in humanitarian context
because the presence of some pathogens can
cause an acute effect on large number of people
in the short term.
Therefore, a bad microbial quality represents
a high risk of epidemics.
Some chemical components occurring in the
water supply can also be harmful.
They are usually a health concern after long
exposure.
The principal exception is nitrate.
Chemical contamination can be man-made due
to industrial or agricultural activities for
instance but some contaminants can also
naturally occur in the ground.
At a global scale, fluoride and arsenic are
the most significant chemicals each affecting
perhaps millions of people.
However, many other chemicals can be important
contaminants of drinking water under specific
local conditions.
Organoleptic criteria are related on
how water looks, smells and tastes.
It is not necessary because a glass of water
is not fully transparent or smells or tastes
slightly that water is harmful but organoleptic
criteria play an important role in the acceptance
of the product by the consumer.
In an emergency for instance, if people do
not trust the water quality they may change
to alternative sources which are less safe.
Obviously, water quality that is needed to
say water is fit for human consumption but
it is also needed to evaluate the quality
of a water source when you have to select
one.
Some parameters such as the conductivity,
nitrate, iron are often collected.
Some data are often needed to design
the treatment required.
For instance, the turbidity and the ph value
will impact directly the chlorination.
Therefore depending on the turbidity and the
ph, a pre-treatment before the chlorination
may be needed.
Data are also needed to control water treatment
process such as the residual chloride.
Finally data may also be needed to protect
the water distribution systems against corrosion.
However, be careful with water analyses.
It is only a snapshot which gives a single result
at a given time and a given location.
Some parameters can vary strongly, for instance
in some context turbidity and faecal pollution
increase more often in rainy season.
And some microbial and chemical parameters
can be easily measured in the field with specifically
designed portable laboratory and equipment.
However, not all the parameters can be measured
like that.
Some analyses require specific equipment in
laboratory and however, due to the lack of
resources not all laboratories are reliable.
This is why complimentary investigations are
required, local knowledge including medical
information is very valuable.
As well as a good understanding of water resources
through hydrogeological studies for instance.
Finally, sanitary survey and assessment of
risk of contamination are needed.
For further information you can refer to the
W.H.O. water safety plans, W.S.P., which are
quite comprehensive.
So to answer to our initial question is this
glass of water safe to drink?
Remember that we should look at three parameters,
the microbial, chemical and organoleptic.
National regulation defines the acceptable
values for these different parameters.
W.H.O. recommendations can also be used as a guideline.
You can measure the different parameters and
some of them with portable equipment.
However, do not forget that an analysis is
just a snapshot of the quality at a given
time and at a given location.
You should monitor quality over time and continually
assess the risk of contamination from the
source to your glass.
Meanwhile cheers and see you in the next video
that you will learn a lot about that of course.
Hoping that this water was safe.