Now you know about some of the specific pathogens
that can cause diarrheal disease and that
most of these pathogens originate in human
or animal faeces.
Well there are so many different pathogens,
It is impractical to try and measure them all
so what we do instead is we use indicator
species to indicate the presence of faecal
contamination.
Today, we will talk about those indicators
species. It would be impractical and impossible
actually to directly measure all the different
pathogens that could cause diarrheal disease.
So instead, we look for indicator species
that can show the presence of faecal contamination.
Some characteristics of an ideal faecal indicator
are that it should be something that is universally
present in the faeces of both human
and animals in large numbers.
Those numbers should be higher than the actual
numbers of the pathogens of interest.
And the indicators should not be harmful or
pathogenic in itself. It should be something
that's readily detected using simple
inexpensive methods.
And it should also persist in the environment
or water in a similar manner to faecal pathogens.
You wouldn't want it to actually grow in natural
waters because then you would get misrepresentation
and finally, if possible, the indicator should respond
to treatment in a similar fashion to faecal
pathogens.
One of the most common indicator species is
a bacteria class called total coliforms.
Total coliforms are bacteria that can ferment
lactose and produce acid in gas at thirty
five degrees Celsius.
There are many different families of coliforms:
citrobacter, klebsiella, hafnia and enterobacter
and for this reason, total coliforms is not
really useful as a faecal indicator because
many of these bacteria have non faecal sources.
However, total coliforms can be useful for
operational monitoring to demonstrate for
example the effectiveness of treatment or
overall cleanliness and integrity in the distribution
system.
Thermotolerant coliforms, as the name implies,
can tolerate heat and these are a subset of
the total coliform class.
Thermotolerant coliforms are what used to
be called faecal coliforms and they can ferment
lactose within forty eight hours at
44 degrees Celsius.
Faeces contain a large number of thermotolerant
coliforms but there are some indications of
non-faecal sources of thermotolerant coliforms
such as klebsiella and some species of enterobacter.
Also, there's evidence that thermotolerants
under some conditions can grow or die off
in water at ambient temperatures so it's not
a bad indicator but it has some limitations.
Escherichia coli or E. coli is one specific
species of thermotolerant coliforms that is
generally agreed to be the most suitable
indicator of faecal contamination.
There is some possibility that the E. coli
may grow in the environment in tropical settings
and it is only moderately persistent so the
absence of E. coli doesn't necessarily mean
the absence of faecal contamination.
However, on balance, considering all the different
ideal characteristics of an indicator bacteria,
E. coli is considered to be the
best available option.
Indicator bacteria are usually reported in
terms of the number of counts or colonies
in a one hundred millilitre sample.
Many drinking water standards and W.H.O guidelines
are set to be no detectable E. coli or thermotolerant
coliforms in a one hundred ml sample.
You can consider that water that has higher
levels of indicator bacteria is probably more
likely to have higher levels of faecal contamination
though there is not a very clear correlation
between indicator bacteria and pathogens on
the other hand.
Still, water having very high levels of E.coli,
more than one thousand counts
per 100 ml, is probably very risky for consumption.
Water having no detectable E.coli in it, however,
might not be completely safe because E. coli
is relatively less persistent and robust in
the environment compared to some pathogens.
For this reason, it would be preferable to
combine a measure of water quality, such as
E. coli measure, with some kind of assessment
of the system safety like a sanitary inspection
which identifies a number of risk factors
at a water source.
Then by combining a water quality measure,
on the vertical axis, and water management
measure, on the horizontal axis, we could make
a risk matrix and prioritize areas, water
sources for interventions.
Well, E. coli or thermotolerant coliforms
are the most commonly used indicator species.
Other indicators might be more relevant for
certain purposes.
Viruses travel in the environment very differently
than bacteria so one might want to look at
coliphage viruses that require a bacteria
host to survive as an indicator for viruses.
Faecal streptococci are more hardy, robust
bacteria compared to E. coli. so they could
persist longer in the environment and maybe
be a better indicator of long term faecal
contamination.
Traditionally, methods for enumerating faecal
streptococci have been more complicated but
this is changing with the
development of new methods.
Finally, protozoa can be very resistant to
disinfection, to heat, to chlorine, to ozone,
so E.coli is not a good indicator for treatment
efficacy but some bacteria like clostridium
perfringens or some bacillus spp. can form
spores which are roughly similar in size and
resistance to some protozoan pathogens.
Now, let's focus in on those pathways between
faeces and faces that involve water.
We can think about a safe water chain with
different stages where contamination could
be introduced.
Contamination could occur at the water resource
itself or during delivery to the consumer.
Faecal matter can also be introduced during
the collection and transport of water if the
source is outside the home.
When water is stored inside the household
it could become contaminated and finally the
drinking water vessel itself, a cup or a glass
might be dirty and introduce faecal matter.
Now let's look at an illustration of these
different stages in a safe water chain.
First, the water resource itself can be contaminated
from contact with human or animal faeces.
Surface water often contains faecal bacteria
but even ground water aquifers can be contaminated
by inadequately managed sanitation.
Even if the water resource is clean or if
water is purified at a treatment plant, it
can become contaminated during delivery to
the consumer for example in a piped water
supply, if there is not continuous pressure
in the distribution system contaminated water
may enter the pipes through cracks or joints.
Another example though could be an improperly
constructed rising main on a bore hole or
suction hand pumps which are primed with unsafe
water.
The point of collection itself can be contaminated,
think of a communal tap or borehole spout
which is handled and contacted by adults,
children and even animals. And when the point
of collection is outside the home, people
must use containers which themselves may be
dirty and people often rinse containers and
wipe them with their hands before filling
them up but if their hands are not clean this
may not help at all.
The containers must then be transported back
to the household giving another opportunity
for contamination.
Open containers are especially vulnerable
because it is easy to contact the water with
hands during lifting and carrying and also
dust or insects can enter an uncovered container.
Once the water is taken to the household it
is often transferred to another container
and may be stored on unhygienically, in open
containers or on the floor where children
and animals can introduce pathogens.
Point of use water treatment at this stage
offers the possibility of inactivating pathogens
introduced at earlier points in the water
chain.
But even after storage, contamination
possibilities exist.
Water may be retrieved from storage containers
using an unclean dipper or ladle, especially
if the storage container is uncovered.
Finally the drinking vessel itself, a cup
or glass or perhaps a gourd can be full of
faecal contamination.
Again, people may wipe the drinking vessel
with their hands before using it but this
might actually make the glass dirtier.
So there are many opportunities for contamination
between the original source of drinking water
and the actual point of consumption.
A big advantage of household water treatment
is that it offers the possibility of removing
any contamination that is introduced at the
water resource, the delivery system or through
collection and transport.
Many household water treatments don't prevent
recontamination so it is important to have
safe storage after a treatment step. And likewise,
good hygiene, especially washing hands with
soap, is important to minimize the possibility
of clean drinking water becoming contaminated
just before consumption by using a cup or
glass that is faecally contaminated.
So in this module we have talked about different
indicators of faecal contamination and how
E. coli is the preferred indicator bacteria
and we have talked about different stages
along the safe water chain from catchment
to cup where drinking water can become contaminated.