In this video, we will talk about
water quantity requirements.
What are they?
There is not a straightforward and universal
answer, it really depends on the context.
In order to assess what the water needs are, we
need to answer the following questions:
What is water needed for?
How much is needed and how do we have access
to it?
Obviously, life without water is not possible.
It is crucial to ensure health benefits. Adequate
quantity of water can also be crucial to ensure
livelihood such as in the picture taken in
Darfur in Sudan here where this water point
is also crucial to water the cattle.
Availability of water is also vital for some
cultural and religious practices.
The list of water uses can be very long and
competition of water between these different
uses and users exist.
It should be taken into account
in the assessment of water needs.
If we focus on public health aspect, water
is needed for drinking, cooking, washing clothes,
cleaning building, waste disposal such as
sanitation and personal washing.
The amount of water needed for these different
uses greatly varies depending on many factors
such as the local habits, climate or
sanitation technology used.
For instance for the toilets, in some contexts
you flush your waste and you need a high amount
of water and in other contexts, you don't need
water because you just do it above the pit.
In humanitarian assistance, most organizations
agree upon a minimum standard that is contained
in this book called “The Sphere Project”.
It also contains other standards for other
core humanitarian activities.
This book is free on the Internet so don't
hesitate, go, read it, check it, it is extremely
important.
According to the sphere project standards,
in humanitarian assistance at least 15
litres per day per person is required for
basic survival water needs.
It includes 3 litres per day per person
for drinking, 6 litres per day per person
for basic hygiene practices, and 6 litres
per day per person for cooking.
But be careful, these figures should be considered
as a minimum standard for survival and that
is during a very acute emergency generally
and not as a satisfactory situation.
Indeed priority should be given to quantity
while respecting quality in order to tackle
water-washed diseases that are due to the
lack of water for hygiene purposes.
If you look at the figures from the W.H.O.
you will see that with 20 litres per day
per person you should ensure drinking and
cooking needs and very basic hygiene needs.
However, it will be very difficult to ensure
laundry and bathing and other hygiene needs.
As such, the level of health concerns remains
high and that due to the risk of spread of
infectious diseases.
In order to lower these risks to less concerning
levels, at least 50 litres per day per
person would be needed according to the W.H.O.
Providing adequate quantity of water at the
water point does not guarantee that people
will have access to it.
As part of the assessment of water needs we
also have to look at the various obstacles
to this access.
Is it safe to access to it?
Can we access fully at any time?
Does everyone have access to it?
Especially the most vulnerable. Is the water
point accessible to everyone?
For instance, can a disabled
person access to it?
Is it affordable for the poorest?
Finally, time to get to the water point is
also very important.
As a matter of fact, time to collect water
will depend on the time to get to water point
which many depends on the distance,
the time to wait at the water point which
can be very long especially when there is
not enough water points and people have to
queue.
The time to fill the container which depends
on the flow of the tap, and finally the time
to go back home.
As shown in this graph, as a consumer if
you have directly access to multiple taps at home you
should not have to wait to get access to water,
then you should actually get access to a very
large quantity of water.
If water is delivered very close to your house,
usually less than one hundred meters, and that
you don't have to wait more than five minutes
to collect water, it is estimated that you
should be able to get access up
to 50 litres per day.
However, if you have to walk between let's
say one hundred and one kilometre to the water
point or it takes you between 5 to 30
minutes it is unlikely that you will get access
to more than twenty litres per day.
Then the longer the time the less the quantity
of water you get.
Let's summarize this video on water quantity
requirements.
We have seen that different population have
different uses for water and purities regarding
the location of water uses.
Therefore, the needs and demands should be
taken into account to defend the quantity
that is vital.
50 litres per day per person is a minimum
standard agreed by most humanitarian organization
for survival but we have seen that it is not
sufficient to stop the transmission of diseases.
Therefore in order to achieve a significant
health benefit, an increase of water availability
is required and finally we have seen that
access constraints should not be overlooked.
It will affect the quantity of water that
can be consumed.