Vectors are animals that are capable of carrying
disease pathogens from a reservoir, an animal,
a human or an environment to another host.
They are a major cause of sickness and death
in many humanitarian contexts.
In addition to transmitting diseases, some
vector may also be considered as a nuisance
because of the painful bite or due to the
large number. Sorry!
The objectives of this lecture is for you to
understand the transmission mechanism of diseases
through vectors,
know the main vectors commonly encountered
in emergencies and their related diseases,
understand the outlines of vector control
strategies.
A vector carries and transmits infectious
pathogens from a reservoir to another host.
The reservoir can be an animal or human or
the environment on which infectious agent
depends to survive.
The pathogen can be transmitted mechanically
to another host.
It means that the vector transmits the pathogens
by transporting them on its body.
Let’s take an example: a fly landing on
faeces with pathogens will then transmit this
pathogen to the human by landing on its side
or in the salad that the person is eating.
The pathogen can also be transmitted after
a biological transformation.
In that case, the vector is involved in the life
cycle of the pathogen which matures through
the vector such as the malaria.
In the transmission of vector-borne diseases,
infection can occur via biting, which for
instance, the malaria transmitting mosquitoes
or via skin penetration for instance, for
the scabies transmitting mites or ingestion,
food contamination by flies for instance.
In humanitarian context, displaced population
are particularly at risk of vector transmitted
diseases. Indeed the stress, the lack of good
nutrition and lack of previous exposure to
diseases are factors affecting the populations’
immunity to vector-borne diseases.
Overcrowding makes it easier for some vector
to spread diseases from person to person.
This is particularly the case for instance
for lice and mites.
Poor housing increases as well the risk to vector
exposure and poor drainage, poor solid waste
or poor sanitation management increase the
risk of having vectors.
The area that host displaced population can
also be an area that supports a significant
vector population and protracted conflicts
can also affect the capacity of authorities
to carry out traditional vector control measures
that used to be done in the past.
In order to minimize morbidity and mortality
due to vector-borne diseases, vector control
measures should be taken in epidemic zones, in
epidemic-prone contexts or wherever
there is a high presence of the vector.
Vector control strategies usually aim at reducing
vector breeding sites, reducing vector population
density or in order to reduce the risk of
human vector contacts.
In other words, reducing the creation of the
hazards, its transport and the exposure of
people to the hazard.
The vector control strategies may be classified
in four types: environmental control,
in order to alter breeding sites such as
draining or filling sites or also ensuring
a proper waste management.
There is also the mechanical control, for instance
using nets against mosquitoes, covering food
against flies or using traps to catch rodents.
The biological management which consists of using
living organisms or products against a different form
of the vector.
A typical example is the use of fish that
eat larvas for instance.
Finally, the chemical control for personal
protection such as sprays used as a mosquito
repellent or insecticides for
environmental control.
However, it is usually recommended to use
insecticides as the last resort.
Indeed it is much more efficient and effective
and less costly to collect and remove refuse
regularly than to depend upon insecticides
to combat flies or rat poison to limit rodents.
In addition, while using the pesticides it
is very important to ensure that the staff,
the communities and the local environment
are adequately protected and of course avoid
creating chemical resistance to
the substance used.
In summary in order to take effective actions
against a vector it is crucial to be familiar
with the vector life and its habitat.
The following table lists some common vectors
of diseases encountered in humanitarian contexts.
Mosquitoes with three main species responsible
for transmitting diseases.
The anopheles which breed in rather unpolluted
water such as pot holes or wells and which
transmit malaria.
The aedes which tend to breed in water receptacles
such as bottles or buckets and which transmit
yellow fever and dengue.
The culex which breed in second water loaded
with organic matter such as in latrines and
transmit filariasis.
Flies proliferate in old places where human
beings are living. They feed on decomposing
organic matter, excreta and fruits.
They play an important role in the transmission
of diarrheal diseases.
Actions against house flies include limit or
eliminate breeding sites, typically collect
refuse, improve compost heaps, protect latrines,
improve drainage.
In addition, sources of attraction should
be reduced and food well protected with lids.
Lice are found on hair and clothing, they
can transmit typhus which is fatal to ten
to forty per cent of untreated patients as
well as relating fever.
Actions against lice include improving general
hygiene, wash clothing and blankets and treating
all people with an insecticide boulder.
Fleas feed on the blood of mammals and birds.
They are found in beds, in the ground and
in clothing.
The rat flea is responsible for bubonic
plague and murine typhus.
Bed bugs do not transmit any diseases but
they nevertheless constitute a considerable
nuisance because they feed on blood.
They hide in cracks, in walls or wood and
also in bedding.
Insecticide is required to eliminate them.
As we have seen vector control diseases
are a major cause of sickness and death in
many humanitarian crises where population
are particularly at risk.
In order to reduce the transmission of these
specific diseases, it is very important to
know the life cycle of vectors and its habitat
in order to take effective measures at the
right time and at the right place.
For instance, if body lice, the vector of typhus,
have to be eliminated, they have to be attacked
on the body or on the clothing.
It is pointless to spray surfaces with the
residual insecticide.
But on the other hand to control bed bugs
and other crawly insects such as cockroaches
and flies, spraying walls or the furniture
and the floor is an effective measure because
these insects rest on such surfaces after
feeding.
However, remember that the use of chemicals
to control vectors is not necessarily the best
options.
Mechanical, environmental or biology measures
may be much more appropriate and efficient.
So in order to design a proper vector control
measure, a detailed study on the vector and
often expert advice are needed and should
be sought from national and international
health organizations.
Let's have a look now at a concrete example.
In the next video we will see the control
campaign carried out by the ICRC in Madagascar
prisons in collaboration with local authorities
and the pastor institutes.