Nowadays it's normal to think that the plague
no longer exists.
But in countries like Congo Kinshasa and Madagascar,
people die from this highly contagious disease
every year.
In Madagascar, people are still becoming infected
and the chance of a major outbreak has not
gone away.
Prisoners, often in overcrowded and unhygienic
prisons, share their quarters with hundreds
of rats and disease carrying fleas.
Although, the spread of
plague from rats via fleas to people
has been prevented in prisons,
the same can’t be said for the
rest of the country.
In rural areas, there is
little understanding
of the plague, often it is something to be
ashamed of and covered up.
As a result, not all cases are reported to
the authorities by this vulnerable population
spread out across a vast territory.
Rafred's daughter, [Maoli], is buried on the hill
close to the town centre,
where she died two years ago.
The grave is located 30 kilometres away from
her village.
Rafred won’t be able to retrieve his daughter’s
body until 2017 after observing a seven year
period imposed by the health authority.
Without steps to monitor and
check the spread of
the disease, the plague is
a danger
to
public health that can quickly get out of
hand. But the government has adopted a national
strategy to fight the disease.
They now keep national statistics for every
case of the plague recorded in Madagascar
which is then passed on to the World Health
Organization and with ICRC support, the
prevention campaign in prison goes on.
The challenge of this campaign is not to stop
in one single prison in the capital,
but to develop these preventive measures
across Madagascar.
and to get the entire prison system signed up
to this campaign, run by the authorities.