Welcome to the second week
of this introduction
on Public health engineering
in humanitarian context.
Last week,
we have learned the principle
of Public health engineering
and see how water, sanitation,
hygiene promotion
and vector control activities
can have of significant impact
to reduce the morbidity
and mortality during a humanitarian
crisis.
This week, we shift our focus on
the humanitarian context itself.
We would like you to get familiar
with your humanitarian environment
and its new challenges,
especially the one who leaked it
to humanitarian response
in urban settings during protracted
conflict.
In these video on the introduction
of humanitarian context,
you will learn to describe different
phases of humanitarian crisis
in order to understand the scope of
intervention needed accordingly.
We will also talk briefly about the main
stakeholders in the humanitarian system.
And finally we will discuss
the humanitarian principles and norms.
There are different types of disaster.
Some of them can be natural
with the sudden impact
such as the earthquake, tsunami;
or with the slow unset;
such as drought or famine.
Some disaster can also be man-made
such as with armed conflict.
and that will be the main focus
of this course.
Disasters interrupts the normal function
of a community or society
and cause loss of life and damage
to property and infrastructure
that exceed the community's ability
to cope using its own resources.
When essential needs to sustain life
such as water, food, health care,
shelter are likely not to be met,
action is required to save life;
prevent further losses and minimize risk.
This is what is done by humanitarian
action during a crisis.
Every humanitarian crises
has its own dynamic and evolution.
But traditionally,
humanitarian crises are schematized
into four main phases.
A pre-crisis where essential
needs are met;
but a risk exists that the situation
will deteriorate.
Therefore, preparedness measures
are sometimes taken.
Once a disaster occurs,
we enter into the acute crisis phase
where essential needs are not met any more.
During this phase,
there is a peak of search and
rescue activities
in the immediate aftermath of a disaster,
followed by emergency relief activities
aiming at stabilizing the survivors
physical and emotional condition.
The Primary focus is on life saving
activities
and the overall fifty community health
status.
This phase can take typically between
one to six months.
After we enter into a longer phase
which is the recovery phase.
The focus is on the rehabilitation
and reconstruction
to restore the level existing
before the crisis.
And finally, we enter into
the post-crises
where development activities take place. //
However,
nowadays, we see a complexification
of these traditional model
with a growing number of chronic crisis.
Instead of having an accurate crisis
followed by a recovery phase,
there is a succession of ups and downs
over several years;
even decades.
Essential needs are not completely met.
and there is a high risk that
the situation will return to acute crisis.
This is often due to protracted
conflict that lasts for many years
and that are currently a
major driver of humanitarian needs.
As a result of the increase of protacted
conflicts,
there is also higher probability of multiple
disasters,
natural and manmade,
occuring of the same time.
In such complex context,
the border between humanitarian action
and development activities
is getting very blurred.
In addition to the traditional emergency relief,
humanitarian organization have to respond
to the long term effect of conflicts.
It leads many organizations
to have to play beyond their traditional roles
and capacities
in order to meet the needs of people
affected by current humanitarian crisis.
In the humanitarian system,
they are also entities
which the primary mandate is to provide
humanitarian assistance
such as the United Nations
humanitarian agency,
International Red Cross and
Red Crescent movement
or national and local agencies with
responsibilities for crisis response.
There may be also other actors
that play a critical role in humanitarian
response
such as the private sector entities
or diaspora.
In an ideal world,
all these actors should work in
good coordination.
but it is not always the case.
Now let's focus on this humanitarian actor :
the International Red Cross and
Red Crescent movement.
It is a global humanitarian network
of eighty million people
that helps those facing disaster, conflict,
health and social problems.
It consists of three main components:
The International Committee
of the Red Cross,
the International Federation
of Red Cross and Red Crescent Societies.
And the 190 National Red Cross
and Red Crescent Societies.
Each component of the movement has
its own legal identity on the role.
but they are all united by seven
fundamental principles
of the International Red Cross
and Red Crescent movement
that guide their humanitarian action.
The seven fundamental principles
sum up the movement ethics
and are at the core of its approach
to helping people in need during
armed conflict,
natural disaster and other emergencies.
The first four principles:
humanity, impartiality, neutrality
and independence,
have been enshrined in United Nations
resolutions
in state commitments and in pledges
from numerous aid agencies,
making them a relying force in
the humanitarian community and beyond.
Another set of principles
that most humanitarian action
agreed to develop in the nineties,
is the sphere project.
We have already seen it last week;
Remember; it contains the minimum
standards of core humanitarian assistance
such as food security and nutrition,
health, shelter and water supplies
sanitation and hygiene promotion.
Its aim is to help improve the quality
of assistance
to people affected by disaster or conflict
as well as the accountability
of humanitarian actors.
Finally, an important set off laws that
influences humanitarian action
is the international humanitarian law (IHL).
Or also known as the laws of war
and the law of armed conflict.
We could talk hours about IHL but rather,
let's have a look to the short animation.
Since the beginning,
humans have resorted to violence as
a way to settle disagreements.
Yet through the ages,
people from around the world have tried
to limit the brutality of war.
It was this humanitarian spirit that led to
the first Geneva Convention of 1864
and to the birth of modern
international humanitarian law.
Setting the basic limits on how wars
can be fought,
these universal laws of war protect
those not fighting.
As well as those no longer able to.
To do this,
a distinction must always be made
between who or what may be attacked
and who or what must be spared
and protected.
Most importantly,
civilians can never be targeted.
To do so is a war crime.
When they drove into our village,
they shouted that they were going
to kill everyone.
I was so scared.
I ran to hide in the Bush.
I heard my mom was screaming
I thought i would never see her again
Every possible care must be taken
to avoid harming civilians
or destroying things essential for their survival.
They have a right to receive the help they need.
The conditions prisoners lived in
never use to bother me
People like him were the reason
my brother was dead.
He was the enemy and was nothing to me,
but then i realized that behind bars
he was out of action and no longer
a threat to me and my family.
The laws of war prohibit torture and
other ill treatment of detainees
whatever their past.
They must be given food and water;
and allowed to communicate
with loved ones.
This preserves their dignity
and keeps them alive.
Medical workers save lives sometimes
in the most dangerous condition.
Fighters from both sides were
wounded in a deadly battle.
We were taking them to the nearest
hospital.
At the checkpoints, a soldier threatened us
to treat his men only.
We were running out of time
and I was afraid that now
all of them were going to die.
Medical workers must always be
allowed to do their job.
And the Red Cross or Red Crescent
must not be attacked.
The sick or wounded have a right
to be cared for
regardless of whose side they're on.
Advances in weapons technology have
meant that the rules of war
have also had to adapt.
Because some weapons and
methods of warfare
don't distinguish between fighters
and civilians,
limits on the use have been agreed.
In the future, wars may be fought
with fully autonomous robots.
But will such robots ever have the ability
to distinguish between a military target
and someone who must never be attacked ?
No matter how sophisticated
weapons become,
It is essential that they are in line
with the rules of war.
International humanitarian law is
all about making choices
that preserve a minimal of human dignity
in times of war
and make sure that living together again
is possible
once the last bullet has been shot.
During this week, we have seen that
the traditional model of relief,
rehabilitation and development
is changing due to a growing number
of protacted conflicts and chronic crisis.
There are various factors not always coordinated,
that are struggling to meet
these unpresidented humanitarian needs;
the concept as well as practices of principle
humanitarian action
are increasingly being challenged;
especially current conflicts.
However in such a complex and
changing environment
these principles must remain
a reference tool
to guide humanitarian action.