You are carrying out a field assessment and
based on your findings it is clear that a humanitarian
crisis is occurring and an urgent intervention
is required. What should you do first? Should
you rush for addressing critical issues? No.
Before you start to address critical issues
you need to first formulate the strategy on
how to resolve these issues and achieve like
that the desired results. Hitting straight
into implementations without conducting relevant
analysis to determine technical feasibility,
resources and cost involved and other factors
could lead to failure in resolving the issue.
This is why during this course, you
will get familiar with the so called Result
Based Management approach (R.B.M.) and learn
to identify the different steps of
the projects item.
A significant proportion of humanitarian projects
have failed to respond adequately to the needs.
Some evaluations carried out found that the
main causes of failure where due to poor planning
and preparation. They highlight it in particular
that many projects where not relevant to the
beneficiaries, risks where insufficiently
taken into account and factors affecting the
longer term sustainability of project benefits
where often ignored. This is why many organisations
have adopted specific management strategies
such as the result based management or R.B.M.
to address these issues. R.B.M. is to manage
an intervention while trying to ensure its
relevance, efficiency, effectiveness, impact
and other quality criteria. In other words,
the R.B.M. approach implies a shift in focus
away from the actions to be carried out towards
the consequences of the actions. In the R.B.M.
logic, resources or inputs are used to carry
out activities. These activities produce specific
outputs. An example of output could be a percentage
of a targeted population in a given location
have access to sufficient number of functioning
sanitation facilities within reasonable proximity
and in line with local criteria standards.
Outputs are the immediate effects of an activity.
Several outputs produce outcomes which are
the likely or achieved major term effects of
an intervention output. An example of outcome
could be that in a given area, a certain number
of displaced people are protected against
the major environmental health hazards related
to water quality, water quantity, hygiene
and sanitation. Outcomes contribute to impacts.
Impacts are the long term effect of an intervention.
They can be positive or negative, intended
or unintended. An example of impact of an
interventions could be that the prevalence
of diseases linked to the environmental factors
in the displaced population is no greater than
that of the general population in the region
in peace time. In order to maximise the chances
of achieving the desired outputs, outcomes
and impacts, the R.B.M. recommends following
four main steps presented here in this item.
The first step is the assessment and the analysis.
In this step you collect qualitative and quantitative
data through a field assessment. Analyse the
data along with the information gathered from
your stakeholders’ conversation to identify
the highest purity urgent issues. The aim
of an assessment is to understand the situation
in order to identify the problems, the source
of the problems and the consequences of the
problems.
There are different type of assessments. The needs
assessment does not aim to identify an intervention but to
find out whether or not an intervention is
required based on identified needs. Such assessment
should at least provide information on who
is affected or concerned by certain issues,
how many people are affected or concerned?
Where are they located? What are the issues?
Why are they affected or concerned? You should
gather info on the courses, risk and vulnerabilities,
coping capacities and finally how will the
situation evolve.
Another type of assessment is the feasibility
assessment which aims to identify the possibility
of undertaking a given humanitarian action
such as implementing an engineering project.
It focuses on the factors likely to affect
directly or indirectly the implementation
and the success of the project. In such assessment,
you have to gather information on the enabling
environment such as the regulations, the capacity
of the service providers, information on the
features of the area, the state of infrastructure
and other relevant technical information needed
to carry out the project.
In the second step, you have to formulate
clear objectives based on context analysis
and your assessment and you should describe
measurable intended results. You should assess the feasibility
of your project. Particularly, attention should
be paid to the future operation and maintenance.
You have to plan activities and resources required
to accomplish the objectives. Then, based
on your plan of actions you could implement
your project.
Finally, you conduct evaluation and review
lessons learned from success or failure to
achieve intended results. According to the
results, you might have to restart the cycle.
Don’t forget that throughout the life of
the project, you should monitor and follow
up the activities in order to adapt the project
according to the evolution of the situation.
To summarise, there are many constraints in
the management of humanitarian projects such
as the lack of data and uncertain future. Urgent needs.
However, rushing to the implementation is
likely to result in inadequate projects to
address critical needs. The project management
cycle is a sequence of logic steps to help
you to maximise the benefits of programmes
for the beneficiaries. You assess, think,
plan, do and review.
Of course, in practice, the duration and importance of
each phase of the cycle will vary depending
on the context. Nevertheless, ensuring that
adequate time and resources are committed
to project identification and formulation
is critical to support the design and effective
implementation of relevant and feasible projects
for the beneficiaries.
Now let’s see some concrete examples of
the different steps of project management.
In the next two videos, some ICRC engineers will
share with you their experience of managing
programmes in rural environment and in an
emergency.