The results of an emergency can be very severe.
What we see often is people arrive, for example
in these displace camps with absolutely nothing.
They have walked for a long way and they can
arrive incredibly dehydrated, haven’t eaten
for a number of days, they desperately need
food and then, the other big one is shelter
as well.
Access to water becomes a life threatening
problem, so it is vitally important that at
that time we use the adequate resources to
give them what they need.
The biggest problem for us is to keep up with
the population of the camp.
What we see in a lot of cases is that the
camp starts at maybe a figure of 5000, 10000
people.
We start doing the work based on those figures
and people keep coming.
One of the options we use is water tracking.
As soon as we get the water tracking in a place,
at the same time we are already looking for
an intermediate solution.
So looking at digging wells, drilling of
boreholes and setting up the pumping station
from the lake or river.
It’s always very important to involve the beneficiaries
in the design of whatever we do.
It is quite surprising how quickly the camps
organise themselves.
It is quite often that committees set up quite
quickly and we work with them to make sure
we understand what the needs are and also
to pass to the population the messages about
the projects we are doing.
A minimum amount of water that a human needs to
survive each day is three litres, that’s
enough for drinking and enough for eating.
In actual fact what we should be trying to
do is supply five times as much as that.
Camps can be very difficult.
Basically, the biggest problem is the fact
that you have so many people in such a small
area.
So, you immediately get a much higher risk
of disease transmission.
Another activity we often do in camps is to
look at the sanitation.
So this is to look at construction of latrines
and construction of systems for waste disposal.
Linked to that as well is the hygiene promotion,
so we do hygiene promotion activities to pass
basic messages to people about how to use
the systems that have been installed in the
camp.
We are trying to ensure that the condition
that the water is installed at the household
level is safe, that they are protected against
mosquitoes and blankets and sleeping mats just
to prevent as well acute respiratory infections.
We have a very extensive logistics set up.
So if there is an emergency we need to send
materials or staff, we can react quickly.
Another advantage we have is the flexibility
which is given to us by our donors, so it
means that we have the money available if
and when we decide that we need to respond
to the emergency.
We like to think that the flexibility
with the donors is built upon trust from basically
the evidence that responses we have
done in the past.
Responding to an emergency, there is the vulnerability
to being used for political gain.
It is one of the skills that our staff have
picked up is to how to approach relevant people,
how to talk to them, how to explain to them,
what we are doing and why we are doing it and it’s
purely on a humanitarian basis.
For shelter, we can have a number of different
approaches based on the needs.
At the most basic level, it can be a distribution
of plastic sheeting either to protect them
from the sun or to protect
themselves from the rain.
We also can do a distribution of tents, so
these are basically a standard tent which
is suitable for a family.
Another type of shelter response we can do
is the construction of a more permanent shelter.
So technically, this can be iron roofing sheets,
timber for constructing walls.
In this way, they can have a shelter which
can be constructed quickly but also it is materials
that can be taken home in the end when they
return back to their villages and used to
perhaps, repair their shelters.
The first time you respond to an emergency
is very difficult but you learn an awful lot
the first time and after that, you build up
a knowledge, you build up an awareness of what
an emergency is about and that helps the staff
a lot in responding to future emergencies.