Now you are familiar with the concept of urban essential services.
Let's see how protracted conflicts affect these services.
In this lecture, you will learn to describe
the different types of feedbacks on essential urban services
encountered in humanitarian crisis.
Then you will be able to explain the resulting
impacts on civilian population and public health.
Protracted conflicts have different
types of impacts on urban essential services.
We can differentiate the direct impact which is the immediate
and physical impact caused directly by armed conflicts
such as the damages to essential urban infrastructure due to
a bombing.
The indirect impact which derives from direct
impact affecting an associated component of a system
usually in the short to medium term. An example is
the brain drain that occurs following attacks on staff.
This impact can accumulate over time
resulting for instance in a lack of maintenance planning
due to insufficient long term staffing.
Now let's see more into details how these different
types of impacts affect the three critical elements of essential
services.
One of the obvious direct impact on people is the
casualties among essential staff due to the conflict. As a result,
there are fewer staff reporting to work and fewer
staff willing to go to the field to conduct routine operations
and maintenance work.
Another direct impact on people is poor
or complete lack of access to a service component.
Here an example of the ICRC providing secured
access to municipal workers in order to perform emergency repairs.
An
indirect impact on critical people occurs when armed
conflicts and sanctions begin to affect the country's economy.
It often results in staff salaries being reduced or
delayed. As a consequence, staff services resign
or lose motivation reducing the likelihood of routine
operation and maintenance from being carried out.
We have seen the destruction or damage to infrastructure
and equipment is an example of direct impact on hardware.
However this pictures doesn't illustrate a direct impact
but an indirect one.
Indeed this pipe is leaking not because of explosive munitions
but due to the coping mechanism of people affected.
The inhabitants were no longer supplied by the main network
and they made holes in the nearest pipes
in order to have access to water.
Sometimes coping mechanism from inhabitants
can result in negative effects on public health.
Another example of an indirect impact on critical
hardware is this water pumping station.
In that case, functional equipment were removed gradually
by water utility staff to a more crucial part of the system in
order to respond to an emergency.
As a result, this water pumping was rendered completely inoperable.
We call this phenomena canibalisation of
critical hardware components.
Direct impact on critical consumables is related
primarily to the destruction such as in this picture of the
destruction of a warehouse of an
electrical utility following a bombing.
As a result the electrical company
lost its capacity to react to breakdowns.
Looting of water electricity providers warehouses
is a classic example of indirect impact on critical consumables
as you can see here in the picture
of the looted water treatment plants.
Cumulative impact is the long term deterioration
in the performance of essential services through
incremental direct and indirect impacts on one or
more of the critical components of the essential services.
Cumulative impact on essential services can be
seen as a vicious cycle influenced by direct and indirect impact.
The accumulation ultimately, affects public health
and may contribute to the very conflict which creates it.
The cycle of impacts therefore lies within the
cycle of conflicts that characterizes complex emergencies.
The cumulative impact of protracted armed conflicts on public
health is much more difficult to track than its impact on the
quality of coverage of any essential service.
One short disruption to the drinking water supply, as
might be expected at the start of the hostilities, can greatly
increase their probability of infection from diseases
already present in the environment if the quality of the service
was originally reliable.
As people’s immunities build up with repeated disruptions to
the water service, it is difficult to generalize the impact that
any disruption would have on general health of the
population. However, the risk of a sustained increase in the
incidence of endemic diseases is enhanced
as the conflict drives more people
and strains of illness into the city, particularly
when the movements of people are coupled with
poor general treatment of water and waste water
and incomplete immunisation campaigns.
Direct, indirect, cumulative.
I hope now that you are clear about the distinction of those
different types of impacts of protracted
conflicts on essential urban services.
Direct damage to infrastructure from
explosive munitions attract to the most attention
but remember, field experience suggests
that the cumulative impact is the most destructive
and the most difficult to recover from.