During the last videos, we have seen the external nature
of the impact of the deprivation of urban services during
times of armed conflict.
There is a need for remove from traditional assistance
paradigm to one that takes account of the longer term realities
and needs in urban areas affected
by ongoing armed conflicts.
In this video, we would like you to suggest
the way forward to best meet the challenges
and to ensure the right response
in the right place at the right time.
The main objective is to stimulate discussion on the
relevance of humanitarian response to essential
urban services disruption
in protracted conflicts.
The challenge of maintaining essential services in urban
context subject to protracted armed conflict is conceptualized here.
The figure shows that the quality of the service
or number of residents covered decreases cumulatively
and progressively over time as a result of direct
and indirect impacts. The impact on residents increases
exponentially over time. The duration of this challenge should be
taken into account in the humanitarian
response as well as the scale of the challenge.
Indeed, infrastructure is so complex in large cities that the restoration
of part of it can immediately benefit several hundreds thousands of
people but the option is often
too costly for municipalities
and humanitarian agencies that are geared
to more traditional emergency responses.
For instance, in case of damage
to water supply infrastructure,
typical relief response
such as water trucking to schools and idp camps take no
account of the repairs needed to the municipal network
and critical infrastructure which are essential
to ensure service delivery not only for
hustle but also for the emergency
response themselves.
However, distinctions between
the stages of relief rehabilitation
development response are not necessarily
relevant in urban contexts. Multiple types of programs may be required
simultaneously in the same city.
For instance in 2010 in Baghdad, the ICRC
intervention covered the full spectrum.
Large hospitals
and waste water infrastructure rehabilitation projects were
established to support the government's long term development plan.
Alongside, basic maintenance of existing health and
water facilities which could be labelled reconstruction.
And water trucking programs to informal
settlements of I.D.Ps, a typical relief activity.
Interconnectivity between essential services needs to be
understood and properly integrated into the humanitarian
response in order to avoid counter productive effects.
For instance, in this picture, retrofiting the broken
water supply network to the squatter, without addressing
the damage sewage evacuation network would increase the
exposure of the population to public health
risks by causing sewage to spill over into the streets.
Essential services rely on three critical
components: people, hardware
and consumables. Experience tends to show that of all the
three components of an essential service, people may be the most
crucial. Effective partnerships with local authorities
and service providers become indispensable in
complex urban environments, much more than for rural areas where people
can organize themselves around
less sophisticated services.
It is widely accepted that including
beneficiaries in the conception, implementation
and management is vital to the
effectiveness as well as to the
sustainability of an intervention. However, community
involvement in urban areas is very different from the common
understanding based on rural experience.
Working with local people to repair
or rehabilitate essential services in urban contexts also poses
some particular challenges. Humanitarian assistance should
not focus only on community based approach assistance.
It is arguably more beneficial to restore water to an entire
neighbourhood by repairing for instance a transmission line
than to assist household level coping mechanisms.
International Humanitarian Law, IHL,
offers a degree of protection. However, while IHL
protects all service components from the direct impact of armed
conflicts, there are specific challenges arising from its interpretation
and application in urban warfare, in particular the extent
to which IHL provides protection against the indirect
or cumulative impact of hostilities on
essential services. The ICRC
is actively seeking to address some of these challenges,
in particular through its work on the use of explosive weapons
in populated areas.
Donors should reconsider the funding scams to ensure that
they match the scale and duration of the challenge.
Relief, rehabilitation and development
efforts will be much more expensive
and take far longer if humanitarian agencies
in coordination with local service providers enable to
mitigate the consequences of indirect and cumulative effects.
Twelve months funding designed for disaster relief
or very short conflicts are not adequate to stabilise
or restore essential urban services in protracted armed conflicts.
To appropriately address the complexity of essential urban
services during protracted armed conflicts, larger
budgets that cover a longer period are needed.
Finally, more research needs to be conducted
on the impact of disruptions to urban services
on people's lives over time.
One priority area is the need to gain an understanding of
how disruption to services affect people's livelihood,
food security, human security and health.
Many humanitarian agencies have programs
targeting the direct impact of this destruction
but not the indirect or cumulative impact on the broader
nexus of interrelated humanitarian issues of concern.
I hope that this video has helped you to have a
much needed discussion on how to develop a better approach to assisting
people in urban areas that have been affected by
protracted armed conflicts. If you'd like to know more details on the
topic you can read this ICRC publication, which combines
current research with over three decades of ICRC
experience in urban areas.
Now in order to summarize these three videos, on urban
services during protracted conflict, let's watch this short
animation.