Iraq, the cradle of civilization.
The Tigris and Euphrates rivers join to form
the Shatt al-Arab waterway.
But despite this massive water course, the
region is essentially a desert.
The supply of water has always been a problem
for the Iraqis.
The series of wars and the ten year embargo
have blocked plans to develop modern efficient
water delivery systems.
This film is intended to give an account of
ICRC’s effort to combat the widespread deterioration of Iraq’s
infrastructure.
But recent events unfortunately got the upper
hand.
The latest round of conflict hit Iraq like
a tidal wave undermining all attempts to meet
the essential needs of civilians.
A task which, according to the Geneva Convention,
is the responsibility of the occupying power.
Now more than ever, water plays a critical
role in the resolution of the crisis.
The ICRC has been present in Iraq carrying
out its humanitarian mandate for over twenty
two years.
At the time of the Gulf war twelve years ago, the situation
reached catastrophic proportions and the ICRC
stepped up its activities extending its far
reach in water and sanitation program.
The objective has remained unchanged throughout
the years in this extremely difficult
context, to provide the civilian population
with a clean safe drinking water which is
essential for life.
In one conflict after another, major elements
of the electrical power networks were destroyed
resulting in the dropping capacity in the
water treatment plants and pumping stations.
If there is no electricity, you will see how
everything is here.
Everything depends on electricity.
If there is no electricity the whole plant
is going to stop.
Half of Baghdad will have no drinking water,
nothing.
The lack of spare parts, qualified help and
logistical equipment hasten the general deterioration
of Iraq’s infrastructure.
The sewage treatment and disposal system is
on the point of collapse and often reach its
full capacity.
The threat to public health is constant.
Waste is regularly discharged untreated into
waterways. The long term consequences for
the environment and public health are no less
than a time bomb.
Most members of the population already worn
down by the direct or indirect effect of ten
years of embargo also suffer from a shortage
of safe drinking water.
Recent conflicts have only aggravated the
situation while completely blocking the supply
of humanitarian aid.
The ICRC’s humanitarian activities over
the past twelve years in Iraq developed in
several stages.
During the 1991 Gulf war, the ICRC focused
its efforts on emergency water distribution.
Tanker trucks and mobile water purification units
succeeded in providing the population with
temporary relief.
But it was necessary to adapt to the changing
situation.
From 1991 to 1993, after an embargo was imposed
by the U.N, the ICRC contributed actively
to repair work on water installations by providing
desperately needed spare parts.
But from 1994 to 1997, in view of the alarming
deterioration of the water and sanitation
services and the logistical difficulties faced
by local officials,
the ICRC had to take some of the maintenance
and repair work into its own hands.
The program became more complex involving needs
assessment, financial resources and technical
know-how.
In 1998, the entry into force of the U.N’s
all for food resolution made access to spare
parts easier.
The Iraqi authorities could once again deal
directly with foreign supplies.
The procedures for buying spare parts remained
long and tedious and not enough supplies could
be imported to deal with the situation.
The ICRC was therefore obliged to take on an
even bigger role which nevertheless remained
complimentary to local water boards.
The ICRC gave priority to sewage treatment
plants, but it also worked to upgrade medical
facilities that could no longer provide essential
health care services.
Complimenting the easing of restrictions under the U.N’s
oil for food resolution, ICRC was able
to slow the inevitable deterioration of Iraq’s
water supply system.
But the great majority of Iraqis are still
forced to live with chronic shortages of safe
drinking water.
The existing supplies constantly threatened
by water-borne diseases which the existing
health care facilities are unable to treat
effectively.
The situation worsened during the recent war.
In March 2003, the ICRC was the only humanitarian
organization to remain in the country throughout
the conflict.
Thanks to its experience on the ground, sustained
relationships with the water boards and credibility,
the ICRC remained effective in an extremely
hostile environment which included not only
the violence of the fighting but also destructive
looting.
Although water treatment facilities suffered
little direct harm, damage to the power supply
caused major cuts in water supply from the
very first hours of the conflict.
People had to manage as best as they could
to get to the water they needed.
The immediate challenge for the ICRC is
to intervene without delay in areas where
epidemics of infectious diseases
are a real risk.
The ICRC has played a unifying and catalyzing
role between the occupying forces administration
and Iraqi professionals.
But effective work depends on maintaining
security and restoring a fully functional
local administration, both are the responsibilities
of the occupying power.
The ICRC’s tireless efforts are ensuring
that it can play a vital role in the reconstruction
of Iraq during the post war period.
But beyond emergency measures, the ICRC’s
main concern would be to ensure that the supply of clean
water can be guaranteed in a long term and
sustainable way through cooperation with Iraqi
water and health authorities and companies.
Only a rigorous self sufficient local economy
will bring about a durable improvement in
the situation, ensuring quality water and sanitation
services for everyone.