Congratulations! You made it through week
two about the humanitarian context.
I hope you get a better understanding of these
challenging environments.
During this week, we have seen that the
humanitarian system is complex with many stakeholders
not always coordinated.
Despite that, they are increasingly challenged, especially
in current conflicts. Humanitarian principles that are impartiality,
neutrality, independence and humanity must remain a
reference tool to guide humanitarian actions.
During this week, we have also seen that in a humanitarian context,
despite urgent needs, you should not rush to the
implementation of activities. Such behavior is likely to result
in inadequate projects to address critical needs.
You should ensure that adequate time and resources
are committed to assess and analyze the needs
and formulate a strategy in order to design effective
and relevant projects for the beneficiaries.
The project management cycle is a sequence of logic steps
to help you to maximize the benefits of project for the
beneficiaries. Humanitarian action has been
mainly designed to respond to the needs in acute
emergencies
and in rural environments. However nowadays we see
an increase in number of protracted conflicts that take place in
urban environments. It poses new challenges.
Indeed, people in urban
contexts rely on essential services.
The services are beyond the technical capacity
and the direct physical control of the residents.
It affects the resilience of the inhabitants.
These essential services such as water supply,
power supply, sanitation are interconnected, no electricity, no water.
This interconnectivity between essential services
needs to be understood and properly integrated into humanitarian
actions in order to avoid counterproductive effects.
Urban services require three elements
in order to function: people, hardware
and consumables.
Disruption to an essential service occurs
when the functions of any of the critical
people, hardware or consumables are compromised.
These three components can be affected
by direct, indirect and cumulative impacts.
Direct impacts such as damages to infrastructure
from explosive munitions attract the most attention
but field experiments suggest that the
cumulative impact is the most destructive
and the most difficult to recover from.
Humanitarian response in urban areas is
a major challenge of today's humanitarian crisis.
Further information of these critical issues
can be found in this ICRC publication.