Hello there and welcome to the summary
video of week 4 on sanitation.
I hope you enjoyed the lectures
and learned a lot over the course
of this week
so let's just quickly go through
the main learning
and key takeaway messages of this week.
so this week, we looked at sanitation.
we learned the definition of sanitation;
what a sanitation system is;
and its different elements.
We explored sanitation product terminology
and functional groups
then we moved to excrete the management
in humanitarian crisis
where we presented an example
of how sanitation system
can be developed over the course of
humanitarian response;
starting from the acute phase of response
that is fair minimal standards apply
to rehabilitation of existing infrastructure
in the recovery period.
Finally, we looked at which selection
criteria need to be considered
for choosing the best fit sanitation
service
and a technology that can be best used
for the task.
The importance of sanitation
and effect of the lack of it
were shown very impressively
in the case study from Gaza.
There, a wastewater treatment
plant was implemented
in order to treat the sewage.
This case study also shows
a humanitarian work
in the field of sanitation,
often goes beyond the construction
of on-site emergency latrines.
This graph depicts the five different
functional groups
that make a sanitation system
in order to safely use a toilet,
collect, store, convey, treat and use
or dispose each sanitation product.
a sanitation system is always built
using technologies
from these five different functional groups.
But remember;
not every system requires a technology
from each functional group.
This systematic thinking can help us
to organise and plan
the most appropriate system for
a given context.
During an acute humanitarian crisis,
it is not always possible to implement
a complete sanitation system from
the beginning.
We learned about the sphere minimal standards
that help us to understand the minimum
requirements of excreta management
during an acute humanitarian crisis.
The first goal is to create
an environment free from human faeces
in order to prevent the spread
of fecal oral diseases
such as diarrhea, typhus, and cholera.
The second goal is to provide
toilet facilities
in order for all affected people
to have adequate,
appropriate and acceptable toilets
that are safe and secure to use.
The case study from Liberia presented
an example of safe containment of excreta
with liquid waste that is contaminated
with Ebola.
There, we also saw that safe sanitation
goes beyond toilets
and that safe conveyance and treatment
are crucial.
The video also displayed the key
importance of community involvement
in the awareness raising during
such an intervention.
As there is no one-size-fits-all solution
to sanitation
and there is a high variability
of different contexts,
we looked at the criteria that influenced
the selection
of the most appropriate sanitation system
for a given context.
For this, we need to consider
the properties of the natural,
built and enabling environments
in order to make a well-informed choice.
In the second part of the week,
we got to know different suitable
sanitation technologies
for an acute humanitarian response
as well as collection, storage
and treatment technologies.
We saw how they work;
and what are their advantages
and disadvantages are.
If you want to learn more about different
sanitation technologies,
I would recommend our other
Eawag online course on sanitation planning
as well as reading the compendium
of sanitation systems and technologies
and other literature by other institutions.
You will find these links on the course page.
One example of the technology in the field
was seen in the case study of prisons
in Rwanda.
There, biogas toilets were implemented;
and the gas from the biogas toilets
is used for cooking in the prison.
If you want to learn more about sanitation
in humanitarian crisis,
please check out the literature
mentioned on the course page.
I hope you learned a lot this week
and are excited to test a new knowledge
in your working environment.
Let's provide improved sanitation
like done in the picture behind me,
in Ivory Coast.
So if you have any questions or feedback,
if you want to let us know about something,
please get back to us on the forum
and let us know your thoughts.
Thank you very much for your attention
during this week;
and I hope to see you again.