As Liberia looks towards
the nebular free future,
a serious challenge remains:
safely removing ebola waste.
I.C.R.C. is leading the way.
Specialized, these lodging trucks
delivering to this site
in the capital on Monrovia;
The only site in liberia capable of
safety storing and handling Ebola waste.
We had to put in place a system
which ensures that all the Ebola liquid waste
is treated safely.
All workers have to wear personal
protective equipment.
We also ran 5 or 6 training sessions
on pumping water as well as
emptying truck.
Workers must follow safety guidelines
scrupulously.
to avoid any spillage
as they decouple the holes.
Local people are kept well away
from the site.
From the onset of the project,
the community was in a lot of fear.
mainly what you hear about Ebola.
We recruited from the community
to serve as monitors.
We were trained and then came back
to our community
and explained to them the safety protocol
and that measure would be put in place
So that the fear of the community dwellers
could be wiped away.
We go from door to door
telling them that the people
are bringing Ebola waste here
but it's safely treated.
Yes the people believe us
because we are in the field.
We are their eyes,
so what we see, we tell them.