Welcome to this last week of the course.
Over the last two weeks,
we talked about water supply,
excreta management and vector control.
Our journey in the public health
engineering in humanitarian context
will not be completed without
two important activities
that we talk about during this week.
They are solid waste management
and hygiene promotion.
The accumulation of refuse such as
in this picture taken in Syria
can pose serious public health risks.
Indeed, refuse attracts flies, mosquitoes,
cockroach, rats and other insects and rodents,
which can transmit disease to man.
Diseases such as fecal oral diseases or plagues
as we have seen over the last weeks of this course.
Burning waste in the street
which often happen
when essential services as distrupted,
can also cause harmful smoke emissions.
In addition to health risks,
uncollected solid waste also create
an unpleasant environment.
Finally, solid waste inappropriately managed
can harm the environment by polluting
surface water and groundwater.
This is why adequate solid waste
management is so important.
There are different types of waste.
But during this week,
we'll focus only on one type
that public health engineers often encounter
in humanitarian crises.
This is the medical waste.
If you would like to know more about
solid waste management in general,
I recommend you to sign up to
the EAWAG mooc on olid waste management
which give a comprehensive picture
of this complex challenge.
To end this week,
we'll discuss the critical issue
of behavior change
and hygiene promotion in humanitarian
context.
Indeed, as we have seen during week 1
with the example of the fecal oral
diseases,
adequate hygiene practices
can contribute significantly
to reduce the risk of disease transmission
and epidemics.
However, changing people behavior
is not at all an easy matter.
This is what you will see
with Professor Mosler, from EAWAG
who is an expert in that field.
Enjoy your last week !