Welcome to this video on medical waste
management. The first of two on this topic.
Health care facilities are a means to
protect public health by treating patients
and controlling the associated spread of infection.
This generates waste which needs to be managed and such activity
entails some risks.
Medical waste management is a set of measures to address those risks.
In this first video, we will focus on data to be
collected in order to design a proper medical waste management
system. You will learn how to identify medical waste
risks, how to classify different types of medical waste
and finally how to estimate their production.
If you deal with medical waste, you will usually start with
something like this. Normal waste mixed with dressing,
needles, vials and sometimes some anatomical parts.
It can quickly transform into something like this.
Or something more insidious. In these
pictures, years of wild dumping
have formed a series of layers of
needles, catheter, plastic
and sharp objects, something that you might
happily discover when you start a building site
or something even more treacherous. Look at this picture.
These kids are dredging the bed of this urban channel to sell
at the market fine sand for plastering purpose. The problem is that
they are downstream the main hospital in town where
x-ray development liquid is dumped directly into the sewage.
Such liquid contains something that is called absorbable
organic iodinated compound which is
toxic to both human and animal
and can contain formaldehyde,
a known human carcinogen.
And of course you will also deal with
the waste area where incineration happens
and where a lot of smoke is produced. Usually
something not particularly appreciated by the neighbouring communities.
And of course activities should be controlled,
otherwise quite serious accidents might occur.
Trying to be a bit systematic, medical waste can
be meaningfully divided into categories based on the level of risk
associated as it is done in this WHO table.
Thanks to such a distinction, it becomes clear that
medical waste management is first and
foremost a set of risk mitigation practices.
This is the point defining the public health
to full scope of medical waste management.
The contamination risk associated to infectious waste
is properly contained inside the hospital site.
All the hospital users and the communities
around the health care facilities are kept safe along the process.
In fact, medical waste products can provide
the vector for the transmission of infection both inside
and outside the perimeter of an health care facility.
This chart illustrates the relation between the sources,
the environment, the vector of transmission related to medical
waste that helps the spreading of infection.
Maybe at this point, it's also important to state what
medical waste management is not. It is not cleaning or hygiene
promotion. Yes of course the activities are
all related, they concur to the overall same objective
but it is important to stress that it is the specific
and unique scope of infection risk reduction imbedded into
waste management. Multiple medical waste solutions can be
proposed. The best will always be the one that reduces
the overall risk of infection for all the community of users
involved.
OK, now after some theory let's try to be a bit more
operational. Let's classify medical waste in a way that is
functional to how we deal with it. Of course
it is easier to see than to do.
The nature of their waste products, their
treatment requirements, their occurence
or not in a given context, have created quite a
lot of different classifications.
Here we see the one used by
or not in a given context, have created quite a
lot of different classifications.
the ICRC. This is the one from M.S.F.
And finally the one from W.H.O.
or not in a given context, have created quite a
lot of different classifications.
the ICRC. This is the one from M.S.F.
And finally the one from W.H.O.
At the end really, there is no conceptual difference,
it is just a matter of terminology. For this video I will use
the terms proposed by the W.H.O. Sharps,
infectious and pathological wastes
and for simplicity, I will call chemical waste everything
referring to pharmaceutical, cytotoxic, chemical
and radioactive waste. Waste quantity varies a lot
according to the  count. This W.H.O.
chart shows how total medical waste, the squares, and
the infectious one, the dots, vary according to their gross national income.
As you see we are talking about a variability
that spans from six, even eight kilos per bed per day to just one.
Another factor is the type of health facility you
are considering. The table here, also from a W.H.O.
publication, illustrates for three different countries
the evident waste production rate per type of facility
and as again you can see a really big variation.
So at this point something is clear. If you have a real
work case the best thing to do is to start a measure campaign
to know how much weight is actually produced. A waste mapping
exercise or a category and per quantity. Each waste product
should be identified, where it is produced
and now it moves within the hospital. Here is the result of such
a mapping exercise for sharps. Here is for infectious
and pathological wastes.
For example, you can see how the operating
theatre, the dot in the middle of the plan, is a big
producer in this category. And finally, chemical waste.
In this case, the biggest producers are the lab and the radiology department.
In conclusion, to recapitulate this video, we can say
that there are different ways of classifying medical wastes.
But what really matters is the risk associated to each category.
The quantity of waste produced in an healthcare facility
depends on the level of medical care
and the type of facility concerned.
Among the quantity produced, about
10 to 25% is considered hazardous medical waste
or special waste. This entails significant potential health
risk. The rest is considered as general waste similar to a
household waste. Given the high variability of
data, quantity should be measured
and not estimated.
Finally, the assessment should also
include where the waste is produced.
Based on all this information, we can look
on how to implement a medical waste management system.