Congratulations !
You have completed this introduction
on Public health engineering
in humanitarian context.
During our journey,
we have seen that populations affected
by humanitarian crisis are particularly at risk
of infectious diseases;
which unfortunately remain a major cause of
mortality and morbidity in this context.
Public health engineers alongside
with medical workers
and food security experts,
play an important role
to tackle these diseases and save lives.
Public engineers contribute to stop
the transmission of hazards in
the environment
through the provision of adequate
drinking water supply,
proper excreta management,
solid waste management,
effective vector control interventions,
and hygiene promotion campaigns.
Based on a good understanding
of the environmental transmission
pathway of diseases,
public health engineers can put
multiple barriers
to prevent the creation of Hazard;
its transport;
and the people from being exposed to it
once encountered.
Thanks to the different lectures
and case studies,
we have also seen during this course,
different technologies encountered
in humanitarian context.
There is never a one-size-fits-all.
Engineering measures
should be adapted to the context.
Intervention could range from
a shallow trench latrine
up to a complex wastewater
treatment plant.
During this course, we've also seen that
there are an increasingly number
of humanitarian crisis
that tends to be more and more
complex
often played out in urban settings,
longer in duration and broader
in regional impact.
In order to address this unprecedented
humanitarian needs,
humanitarian response needs absolutely
to adapt and innovate.
And this is why, well trained and motivated
engineers
and specialists in water sanitation,
energy supply, and environment,
and in other related fields are increasingly
needed.
On behalf of all the lecturers of this course,
we hope that you enjoy it and
you are learned a lot.
Thank you for your participation.
And we hope to see you soon;
but in the field.
See you soon !