Hello, in this module we're still talking
about disinfection techniques.
Today we'll look at ultraviolet radiation
for use at the household level.
We'll look at both artificial radiation,
which needs electricity and lamps to
generate
the energy, and natural radiation, making
use
of the sun's energy for solar
disinfection.
Ultraviolet radiation is one type of
energy along the electromagnetic
spectrum, where different kinds of
radiation are defined by their wavelength.
Ultraviolet has wavelengths in the 100 to
400 nanometer range, whereas
the visible light is in the 400 to 700
nanometer range.
If we zoom in on this range we can define
some subcategories.
The lowest wavelength we call vacuum UV.
It only exists in the vacuum.
But then we have UV-C, or deep
ultraviolet,
where the germicidal peak at 260
nanometers is found.
Then you've got UV-B and UV-A shading
into the visible light spectrum from
400-700 nanometers.
Now in order to describe the efficacy of
UV light against
different types of pathogens, we need to
first define the dose.
And just as for heat, it's important that
the intensity of the disinfectant and the
time.
So for a UV radiation the units use,
in the US they use millijoules for
centimeters squared,
whereas in Europe and other parts of the
world the preferred units are joules per
meter squared.
Now DNA absorbs ultraviolet light in the
200-300 nanometer range,
and it has a large peak at 260 nanometers
in the UVC range.
So most of the commercial systems target
this wavelength then.
And UVC has been shown to be most
effective against bacteria followed by
protozoa and cysts.
And then, finally, against viruses and
bacterial spores, where you,
you need a bigger dose to inactivate those
kind of pathogens.
Typically, a dose, might be 400 joules per
meter squared, or 40 millijoules
per centimeter squared to get good removal
of even viruses and bacterial spores.
Here you see a graph of the efficacy of
UVC against different kinds of pathogens.
Here we've got the dose, and the log
inactivation, or LRV on the other axis.
Well the first thing you can see, is that
E. Coli
is very readily killed by
ultraviolet, very steep curve.
And total coliforms are related, bacteria
are
also fairly quick to die, exposed to UV.
Rotavirus takes a little bit more time to
kill.
But it's the Bacillus subtilis spores that
takes the longest time.
Now, I mentioned that there was a standard
dose
of around 40 Millijoules per centimeter
squared, that's about there.
So we can see that at this level you would
be having, you know, more than four
log removal of bacteria, almost four log
removal of rotavirus.
But only about one, a little bit more
than one log removal of the Bacillus
subtilis spores.
There are a number of different ways to
generate
UV-C radiation using lamps, which of
course require electricity.
Low-pressure mercury lamps emit light in a
very narrow wavelength band of
around 254 nanometers, which is close to
that DNA absorption peak of 60.
So, this is a very effective way to target
DNA.
Medium pressure lamps generate a broader
spectrum of UV-C, so not only the DNA
could be targeted, but proteins and other,
other kinds of DNA activation could take
place.
And then finally LED lamps are currently
under development.
These would also be very focused at a
particular wave length but hold out
the possibility generating UV radiation at
a lower cost, then mercury lamps.
UV-C is very effective in water, it's not
impacted by changes in
pH, though turbidity can shield microbes
from the radiation.
There's a modest effect of temperature
where a higher dose is
needed at low temperatures, but it's, it's
not a major effect.
There are many commercially available UV-C
systems
used primarily in middle or high income
countries.
Kitchen scale systems with a small UV
lamp.
And there's some interesting research into
developing versions of UV-C
treatment that would be suitable for low
to middle income households.
Here's one example, the Mesita Azul, which
was developed in
laboratory at Berkeley University and
trialed in Baja California, Mexico.
It consists of a small UV-C lamp that does
need electricity, that outputs 1200 Joules
per meter squared, us so three times that
conventional range of 400.
And there's a, a, a kit reservoir, where
water
drains by gravity through the UV tube into
a receptacle.
And along the way it passes in a channel
here,
underneath the UV lamp, that's not in
direct contact with the
glass but it's a thin layer so that the UV
can,
can come in contact with all the pathogens
in the water.
The flow rate is pretty high, about five
liters per minutes in the system.
A recent evaluation found that it was very
effective in
the field, water quality was better than
the same household before
the intervention, that are also then
controlled household, and better than
household that were using other kinds of
disinfection like commercial filters.
However, the exclusive use is pretty low,
that only about 40% of household.
While the Mesita Azul system is still
under development, there is another UV
disinfection process
that has been research extensively over
the past
30 years, both in laboratory and field
settings.
And this is called solar disinfection.
Solar disinfection works simply by taking
a clean plastic bottle, a PET
bottle, and filling it with water and then
lying it on a
flat service, maybe a rooftop, and
exposing it to natural sunlight for
at least six hours, or if it's a cloudy
day for two days.
After the sunlight exposure, the water is
safe to drink.
This SODIS technique then has been applied
in more than 20
countries and more than five million
people are using it today.
For more information about SODIS, visit
the
Swiss website www.fundacionsodis.org for
application in Latin America.
Now, solar disinfection doesn't make use
of UV-C radiation, and that's because
as sunlight passes through the atmosphere,
all of the UV-C
and even about 90% of the UV-B is absorbed
by
ozone, water vapor, oxygen, and carbon
dioxide in the atmosphere.
UV-A radiation is less affected by the
atmosphere.
Therefore the UV radiation reaching the
earth's surface is
largely composed of UV-A with a small UV-B
component.
Clearly then SODIS has to work differently
than UV-C
disinfection since UV-C isn't reaching the
earth's surface, thankfully.
And it does so with three main mechanisms.
First is UV-B radiation can still directly
inactivate cells.
It won't be absorbed so much by the DNA
but
other components within the cells, perhaps
proteins, enzymes, can be affected.
However, the plastic bottles used for
sodas, PET, remove much of the UV-B.
So on the special bottles I used, this is
probably a minor effect.
A more important effect is thought to
be indirect in activation through UV-A
radiation.
Where the UV-A is absorbed by some
intermediate species, and then goes on to
create
reactive oxygen species like hydroxyl
radical or hydrogen
peroxide, which cause the damage to the
microbes.
Those, reactive oxygen species could be
generated inside the cell if the cell
contains chronoforms, which are typically
present in bacteria, bacteria cells.
Or it could be external through, dissolved
organic matter, matter or dissolved iron.
And then finally, heat can play an
important role.
Of course, if the temperature gets up to
or 70 degrees, we're entering the realm of
pasteurization.
But even at 50 degrees, there seems to
be some synergy along with the effects of
radiation.
There are a number of factors that
influence how effected SODIS can be.
First around the radiation itself the sun
height is
important, and the higher the sun is the
higher the
UV radiation level and this varies with
the time
of day of course but also the time of
year.
So the maximum levels occur at noon during
the summer.
The latitude is also important radiation
does not fall equally on the earth.
And there are two belts from 15 to 35
degrees in the
Northern Hemisphere, and in the Southern
Hemisphere, where radiation is at a
maximum.
Also, the belt between 15 degrees north
and 15 degrees south has
quite high solar irradiance, and it's a
good zone for practicing SODIS.
Altitude at higher altitudes there's more
radiation, UV levels
increase by about 10% for every 1,000
meters in altitude.
Ozone in the atmosphere does reduce UV and
ozone can vary
specially it can vary over the year and
even across the day.
The ground can also reflect ozone, this is
more important maybe for, for sunburns.
But think about a rooftop reflecting
radiation back into a SODIS bottle.
And then finally the depth of water in a,
a water bottle.
It's important, because UV radiation is
attenuated by water.
So, if the bottle were too large and the
water column were
too, too thick, then UV wouldn't penetrate
to the center of the bottle.
Also characteristics of the water are
important.
When the water temperature reaches 50
degrees or so there's a
synergy and only about one hour of UV
exposure is needed.
However, turbidity can negatively impact
SODIS and
if the turbidity is higher than about
30 NTU, it's advised to pretreat the
water with filtration or perhaps
coagulation and sedimentation.
With all of the factors that can effect
SODIS disinfection, it's
not surprising that evaluations have shown
a range of removal values.
Most of the studies have been on bacteria,
especially E. Coli
and these tend to find three to five log
removal units.
Sequence studies have shown that
Salmonella is more resistant than E. Coli,
and that Shigella and Vibrio cholera are
relatively susceptible to ultraviolet.
Studies on protozoa have shown slightly
lower removal from two to four log units,
and both Giardia cysts and Cryptosporidium
spores have been shown to be inactivated.
There are relatively fewer studies of
viruses.
The methods are more difficult, and they
show a greater
range of one to more than five log removal
values.
Where we see that certain viruses like
Adenovirus and
the, the indicator virus phi are quite
resistant to ultraviolet.
Adenovirus is also resistant to UV-C
treatment and other viruses,
the human echovirus and the indicator
virus MS2 phage
are relatively easier to, to disinfect
with SODIS.
One of the countries with the longest
history of SODIS is that Bolivia, where
since 2001, Eawag and the Fondacion Sodis
have been promoting solar disinfection.
First with pilots in Cochabamba, and then
with
broader uptake through NGOs, through
health ministry, through schools,
health professionals and women's groups,
and Eawag estimates that
more than 700,000 people use SODIS
routinely in Bolivia.
However a 2009 evaluation in Bolivia found
that among those who had received SODIS
training only about a third of them were,
were routinely using SODIS treatment.
Concerns have been raised about exposing
plastic
materials to the sun for water treatment
because
of the risk that some chemicals present in
the plastic could leech into the water.
Now antimony, is a chemical that's used as
a catalyst in
the production of PET, but antimony only
leeches into water at
appreciable levels when the water's in
contact with the plastic for
many weeks, or longer or if the
temperature exceeds 70 degrees Celsius.
Now this doesn't happen during SODIS
treatment since treated water is only in
the bottles for a few days and the
temperatures rarely exceed 50 degrees.
Adipates and phthalates are used as
softeners in the
production of certain types of plastics
and packaging materials.
For example PVC, which is used in plastic
pipes.
And although these softeners are not
particularly toxic, they do
represent a threat to health if they're
consumed in large quantities.
However, adipates and phthalates are not
needed in the production of PET.
So they cannot leach from PET bottles into
water.
Aldehydes are formed when the plastic is
heated in the manufacturing process for
PET bottles.
A laboratory investigation of the
diffusion of aldehydes from PET bottles
into water found that exposure to the sun
has no effect on the
concentration of aldehydes that could be
measured, especially for acetaldehydes.
Though the concentration of formaldehydes
does increase with the length of exposure.
However the concentrations of these
aliphatic aldehydes remained far below
the state regulatory limit for drinking
water in all samples.
Formaldehydes and acetaldehydes can be
used can
be problems for bottled carbonated water
because the
higher pressure and lower pH within those
bottles can result in aldehydes in stored
water.
But again since the pressure and pH are
more moderate in SODIS' treatment,
these chemicals are not found at levels of
concern in SODIS treated water.
Then we have bisphenol A, a chemical
present in
some plastic bottles, that is suspected to
cause breast cancer.
But, bisphenol A is only an
issue with polycarbonate bottles,
polycarbonate plastic,
and not in the PET bottles that are most
commonly used for SODIS.
Another approach to assessing chemical
safety of water is not to look for
specific chemicals but to see if exposure
to the water results in
mutations in certain plants or protozoa,
or bacteria cells.
So this is a genotoxic approach to
water safety assessment.
And some of these genotoxic studies have
found that when water is stored in
plastic bottles for long periods of time,
like several months, cell mutations could
be observed.
But this happened with or without exposure
to UV radiation.
So while it might be an issue for long
term
storage and plastic bottles, it's not
directly pertinent to SODIS.
And this is similar to what we've seen in
those
studies looking at leeching of other
chemicals, various chemicals.
And since SODIS involves neither long
storage time
nor high temperatures, studies at Eawag
and other
institutes have not found any evidence
that SODIS
introduces any harm for chemicals to
treated water.
For more information, visit the
publications
page at the SODIS reference center.
The link is shown on the page.
So some considerations then for UV
treatment are
that, first, it's highly effective, both
UV-C and SODIS.
Though UV-C being more powerful energy is
more effective, especially against
viruses and protozoa, and both UV-C and
SODIS are limited to
low turbidity waters because particles can
shield pathogens from the radiation.
Furthermore, UV-C does require
electricity to run the lamps.
If we look at SODIS, some advantages are
that it's very simple to operate.
It's also quite inexpensive.
You need plastic bottles but not much
more.
However, it's highly dependent on the
climates, both in terms
of daily and seasonal variations and
different effects in different regions.
And it does take a significant amount of
time more in
the treatment than in the actual work done
to fill bottles.
An advantage of SODIS is that there's
quite a low risk of re-contamination
because water
is typically drunk from the same container
where
it's been treated, so less chance of
re-contamination.
However, it's only small volumes of water
that can be
treated at a time in a batch of SODIS
treatment.
In summary then, we've seen what
ultraviolet radiation is
today and how it works against different
classes of pathogens.
We've seen how UV-C intervention works and
how
they can be adapted for household water
treatment.
Currently most of the experience there is
in middle and high income setting but
there's
potential for application in low and
middle
income settings, especially as LED lamps
come out.
And we've seen the must more widespread
practice of solar disinfection, SODIS,
how that works and how it is being applied
in many countries in the world today.