We're going to take a quick look
at urban professions.
These include, of course, not just
city planners or surveyors,
there are also lawyers, architects,
engineers, land surveyors.
We'll look briefly at some
of these professions.
Why?
Simply to highlight the fact that
the various inputs in urban issues
are not always the same,
when it comes to discipline.
We should always keep this in mind.
The architect will, of course,
look at urban design,
as well as at the relationship
between things, spatiality,
while the economist will see only
a vast web of interchange
between people, between societies.
So ultimately the same aspect of the city
will be viewed from
totally different angles.
This must be kept in mind
when one begins to plan.
The goal of planning is not to favor
one discipline over another,
but instead to integrate and articulate
all of these urban professions.
In formulating my plan for the city,
I can in this way just as well focus
on questions of design,
on questions of economics,
of flow management,
engineering systems, etc.,
as we'll see when we continue.
First, the architecture.
We've found an old plan,
as you can see, one from
classical architecture.
Why are architects interested in
the relationships which exist
between objects.
The idea is to create a spatiality,
the representation is two-dimensional,
of course we represent
in two dimensions
a reality which is three-dimensional.
But the interest, as we've seen
in the last image,
is to see the relationship
which is established
between the different elements
which make up the city.
We have here a map of land allotments.
Here too there is no explanation
of its origin.
We see a certain number of parcels
with, each time, let me mark it...
We can see a certain number
of islets with parcels,
and then for each parcel,
there is a zone for the house,
and a zone for a garden behind it.
This is the plan of the surveyor.
The surveyor, also known as the
topographer, is fundamental.
The surveyor plays a key role
in the making of a city.
It is ultimately the surveyor who,
in the end, has the most impact.
There is absolutely
no recognition of this fact.
There is absolutely no recognition of
this power of decision-making,
but it is clearly the surveyor,
who subdivides, most of the time,
the parcels.
It is the surveyor who,
as a general rule, maps out road systems.
So the surveyor has his own
particular way of making a city,
but is one of the most important
elements in its making.
An engineering plan.
Now we're not aware,
not always aware,
We're here at ground level...
the people are here
And what interests us is this zone, here,
all that goes on underground.
And all that happens underground is
the domain of civil engineering.
All the networks, the pipelines,
electricity, drinking water systems,
waste water systems, if these exist,
all this happens here, underground.
So we can also imagine
an entire vision of the city
from the perspective of
civil engineering, and its grids.
In a very symptomatic way, here,
a carcass in a public space,
a cow's carcass.
A few donkeys, we see the problems
of waste management,
the problems of the environment.
And we arrive at the role of the engineer
of environmental sciences,
or the environmentalist.
He plays a role of growing importance
in the reflection on the city.
For a long time the poor relative,
it must be said.
There are still many cities
who can't even imagine that
they need to call in an environmentalist,
to imagine, to plan,
but this is, increasingly, a key role,
and is extremely important,
for the safeguarding
of natural environments,
to show how these
ecosystems can function,
the role within it for animals,
we can then derive from these
questions of hygiene,
the questions of public health.
Now, without illustration,
for we've already discussed this.
We have the economists,
who view themselves as a force,
the market forces.
The lawyers or the notaries,
all those in law professions,
who, finally, have an enormous influence.
Why? Because they draft the regulations.
Because the notary is
the one who delivers them,
or who permits their deliverance, perhaps.
Because the notary is directly
involved in, notably, land titling.
We have the surveyors,
who are more involved in
huge spatial mutations,
who are more involved in dynamics,
who explain the large movements
which circulate in the city.
Finally it is the sociologists
who will explain to us...
I exaggerate, of course,
but each profession has its own language,
and has its own code,
and the sociologists will explain to us
which are the social practices
that we'll find in the city.
Finally there are all the others,
who, directly or indirectly,
play an important role in planning
or in management.
A police officer has a very important
role in urban management.
As far as planning,
there are also related issues,
we were just discussing public health,
and we can find in a city, doctors,
veterinarians, or health specialists.
There is a whole armada of professions
which have, directly or indirectly,
an influence on these issues
of urban planning.
And in planning one should use
these different languages,
these different urban professionals,
in order to propose something
which is articulated within
these different disciplines.
To finish up, we'll take the historian,
who looks to the past
but who can equally help us
to understand what the past is made of,
and how we can better build and plan.