Hello
Today a history of urban planning.
A brief history, going back a few plans,
a few decades, a few large
types of plans,
from the first subdivision plans,
often colonial plans, right up to
current plans, strategic city planning.
We are going to divide it
into different stages.
The first was what we called the
first drawings, it is often
subdivision plans, we will show
an example a little later.
Then classical planning, which
we probably know best.
Classical planning simplified, the
project list or the shopping list.
Planning by discipline.
Strategic planning.
First example of planning, what we call
the first plans.
We are here in Abidjan, the first
plan of subdivision
of the city of Abidjan, it is a plan
of military genius.
Most colonial cities, we are not referring
to precolonial cities of course,
the first colonial cities had plans,
which were generally made
by military genius.
We are referring to
the subdivision drawing
with an exact description of the
roads and the size of the lots.
We have here, each time,
we know exactly the size of the street,
the boundaries of the roads, we also know
that the blocks
are well defined in a subdivision.
So we're really talking about
a spatial drawing,
where we try to organize things,
the large facilities, we have here
the hospital as well as
a number of plots
which are common plots
that could welcome
residents or facilities.
The second example here,
is what we call classical planning.
Classical planning, is a encyclopedic
planning of the city.
So there is no date on the side
on purpose, since we are
of course looking at the first plans,
in 1830, 1850, it depends
on the cities, but here we are
dealing much more classical planning.
We are still in Abidjan, however,
providing a date does not make sense.
Why?
Because this type of plan can be found
before in certain cities and well after
in other cities.
We can even say that this
classical planning
is still used today in any
number of African cities.
What are its special features?
We plan the networks, we plan
large subdivisions.
We see that it's mostly streets
that we have, we see that we plan
the new subdivisions that we have
the large roads, mostly, that exit
to the outside of the city.
So it's the road network
which is planned.
To do this planning, we use
a large amount of data.
The idea behind it is that if we have
encyclopedic knowledge of the city,
we will be able to plan correctly.
Same situation here,
we find ourselves a few years later,
it is the 80s,
in Nouakchott in Mauritania,
we are dealing with the same type of
planning, it's a classical planning
but based on an encyclopedic
knowledge of things.
So we know absolutely everything
about the city
and knowing everything
allows us to plan well.
Then, we go to another type of planning,
still in Nouakchott,
still in Mauritania, the so-called classic
planning but its simplified version.
We realize that after a few
classical planning failures,
finally, all of this encyclopedic data,
this mass of information,
is maybe not essential to
the planning of the city.
So we are going to do the same type
of road planning, of large areas,
of residential areas,
popular housing areas, but this time,
we are going to base it on data
that is much more insufficient.
So we are going to look to simplify,
both the diagnostic,
based on much less data,
and at the same time the result,
starting with the principle that
the simpler and the clearer it is,
the more possibilities
for planning to work.
So it's a secret for no one, we have
reduced the complexity so much
that we are now in situations where
planning is no longer effective at all
since it no longer represents
urban complexity.
Here an example of the project list
or shopping list.
We can see that we have
a particular element,
we see that at an intersection,
we see that we have here a bypass
that is drawn, we see
that we have sectors which without a doubt
will have to be restructured,
of particular elements.
Urban planning is seen, in this case, as
the succession of financeable projects.
So we no longer truly have
a comprehensive plan,
or rather the comprehensive plan
is not that important
compared to the whole of the project list,
and finally urban planning, planning
is done by superimposed projects.
Another example,
we go from the project list,
to a planning by domain
or by business sector.
Here we are in Nouakchott, Mauritania
with the road network hierarchy
in the long-term.
So we go eventually from a planning
that wants to include all
of the planning elements
which is broken down into different
areas of activity, the road network
being without a doubt the most
classic domain, really everything
that is transportation and mobility,
but this is often about hierarchy issues
of the road network in the long-term
which we primarily act on.
And finally the last invention
in the history of planning,
is strategic planning.
Here we are in Douala,
where we see that
we are talking about large sectors,
sub-sectors which are
secondary centers, a center
with a number of arrows
which show the dynamic that goes
in the direction of reinforcing
a number of precise ideas
that were put in place.
So we see that, we are dealing with
agroalimentary industry issues
with the plan, so we are also dealing with
plans that are often sector-specific,
there is rarely a plan that synthesizes
everything since it becomes
very complicated to read, but we realize
that we are no longer discussing
in terms of physical planning,
of project elements but of
a regional dynamic
that we put ahead of a plan,
with the use, in particular,
of a number of arrows,
as we can see them here,
as we have seen them in
the center of the plan.
So all of this to say that, in theory,
everyone has their own planning history.
Each time, it's said that up until now
we have been mistaken, that we are going
to make a new tool,
and that thanks to this tool,
the planning will be useful and efficient.
We realize eventually that, aside from
what I have called the first drawings
which are true subdivision plans,
which are plans of military genius,
but which shape the city, the urban shape,
so the spatiality is created
through these plans, however templates
are created, the size of the streets,
the size of the plots are created.
Everything else is after, after this first stage
of subdivision plans
which are the city's first urban plans.
After this stage, all the planning done,
from classical planning,
simplified, the project list,
all this planning that I spoke of,
that we saw in detail,
we have purely only done, exactly the same
thing, right up to the last plan
which is supposedly strategic, where
we have invented nothing else
than doing what we used to do
except that it's presented
in a radically different way since we're
trying to put forth the dynamics.
And then there is in the discourse
a way to make believe
that before it was being done wrong and
now we are going to do it correctly.
But strategic planning,
one must know,
is really the same as all planning.
And if the paradigm shift takes place,
it is not between what
what happened before and today,
strategic planning, but it's really between
the first plans, which were
subdivision plans,
which were urban plans,
which were an urban design;
there is a rupture between
this first part and everything after.
And the paradigm shift in urban planning
intervenes thus in this passing from
the first plans and the current plans
which are strategic plans.
There you have, quickly described,
a history of planning
without any date, which is distinctive.
Simply why?
Because the examples that I gave
were not necessarily created
in a linear manner.
The different stages of plans happened
in a linear manner
but some, like simplified planning,
was happening in 2000 in Mauritania
while for other countries
it was happening in the 80s, even the 70s,
even well before that.
So this whole history is not linear,
one must keep in mind that
we have these different stages and
that today we're almost everywhere
in a strategic planning stage.