Hello and welcome to our video.
Second part of what is Urban Planning.
The first part, we had it
the first week of registration
was an introduction to planning,
and we would like in this video,
to go a little bit further with you today.
To begin, we're going to quote
Saint-Exupéry, just this once,
who said: "A goal without
a plan is just a wish. "
This is the starting point from
which we would like to start,
that is to say, to have a goal
so that this goal transforms
in something possible, convincing,
it's about having the tool which allows
for the implementation of this goal.
The tool, most of the time, is a plan.
Then of course the planning is
not summed up by the plan,
but it is one of the main instruments
of this planning.
We could do planning with taxation,
with public politics,
with a number of other instruments
that are available,
but, traditionally, globally,
in the majority of cases,
when we are speaking of urban planning,
we are referring to plan: Master plans,
zoning plans, blueprints,
you name it,
it's more or less always the same type
of instrument that is used.
Let's go back to the actual context,
once again, we are not going
to go over what has already been said,
simply to clarify a little,
you must keep in mind,
an increase in areas of
substandard housing.
It is one of the urban problems today,
there is an impoverishment
of the population, but overall,
on the entire surface of cities
in Africa today,
in sub-Saharan Africa,
there is an increase
of surface area devoted
to substandard housing or slums.
Then, to take the second element,
we have an urbanization,
we've seen that this is created
without economic development,
but to speak in terms of urban planning,
particularly planning
that is disproportionate
to the need for transportation,
with the need for servicing, with
the overall need for networks.
There it is.
And in regards to this issue
of networks, of this issue
in particular of servicing
or of transportation,
usually public transportation,
there is a big deficit
in the African cities, to which the issues
of informality are added.
We also have already seen,
already had some hints of informality
being a system that is superimposed
on the formal system.
We have shown it very well
in most of our writing,
it is not informality on one side
and what is formal on the other,
but these two systems totally interlocked,
both playing the formal and informal,
depending on the situation.
We easily realize
that the literature presents
informality as being
more the domain of the poor,
which would really be
in the informal to compensate
for the lack of formality
or the possibility of formalizing
a number of things from the State,
so the poorest would be
more informal than the richest,
yet we have seen it
in very precise cases, particularly
in housing, it is mostly the elites
who are in the informal role.
Why the poorest?
Let's take the property for example.
When they have a plot would
inevitably like to have a land title
and will do anything to appear
in front of the the notary to have
the necessary papers
so that they cannot be criticized
or removed.
That they cannot be criticized for
not having or not being
the owners of the land.
Yet the richest do exactly the opposite.
No need for a building permit,
no need for a title, they begin to build
they build their property
and they know that, through
the informal system they will
be able very quickly to find themselves in
a situation that in the end will be formal.
But we see that formality
is not really the domain of the poorest
but of the richest.
So we have an urbanization that has
no ties to its own networks,
and its own networks and its own
means of transportation
are increasingly informal.
This is the context today in which
we find ourselves when
we must plan the city.
Last element of this context,
is finally, the planning,
even if it is relatively old
in the African cities, it is still at
the prototype level.
It is still to be tested
and it is emerging .
Of course the major capitals had
their plans very quickly, but the rest
of the cities had in principle very little,
if at all, of town planning.
So it's something relatively emerging,
it is a discipline
which is not constituted as a disciplinary field
but eventually comes
at the articulation of many disciplines,
which is its very nature,
which is all very well, but which
also means that it is
its weakness since it doesn't
have its own discipline that would
support this planning.
So there are definitely great challenges,
we have already seen it considerably
in the introduction, great challenges for
the cities, and there is a need to plan. ,
Why plan?
Why, simply because the city as such,
even it is the most beautiful of
living organisms, even if it's
a sort of ecosystem,
it would be the natural habitat,
as some would say,
the natural habitat of man,
even if the city appears
to be an ecosystem,
we realize that it doesn't
manage itself,
that it doesn't generate itself spontaneously
in a desirable way for the collective.
So we are obligated at any given moment
to clearly intervene,
in this development, so it's
a interventionist notion in planning
because things in and of themselves
are not done spontaneously
and those that are done spontaneously are
not necessarily those that are desired.
That is the first thing.
The second thing is from the Gestalt theory,
which is that the total is greater
than the sum of the parts.
This means that the individual
interests of some
do not form a public interest,
but that
the public interest is above all of this.
As a result, I cannot see in individual interest
but the total, the sum of the total,
that's something else and for this
I am obligated to plan not for the individual
interests but that of the collective.
The need for planning comes also from
that fact that
the resources are limited and that
changes are fast.
So I have to have a road map
to know where I am, at all times,
and to be able in this way to adjust
and react quickly depending
on the situation, depending on
an economic crisis,
depending on immigrant arrival,
this speed of urban changes.
Finally we are discussing limited resources,
which are also financially limited, and so
I have to plan to use them
in the most efficient way possible
so as not to waste or lose
the resources, the scarce resources
that I have available to me.
The very foundations of zoning plans,
is then about managing
or controlling the soil.
We are speaking of sustainable soil management.
Zoning plans also have to control
displacement, to try to reduce it
as much as possible.
Zoning plans give us indications
about the areas, about the type of areas,
that we would want in different parts
of the city, it's about housing, industry,
green space, not to mention only
the main area, the central space
and finally the plan must allow
for the management of resources and
the heritage that we have available.
So this, it's an important element,
the planning must especially
allow for the management of
natural resources as well as
the management of cultural resources
via heritage.
So we take what we have already seen,
the three types of plans,
the first, orientation requirement,
detailed orientation requirements and
the requirements for the soil usage.
So here, we have a limit
since this is what is
called binding against third parties,
which is the force of law,
while the orientation requirements
or detailed orientation are for
the administration but are force of law
for those that are private.
So often with the plans, there is a
legislative and regulatory context.
There are no countries where there
aren't countless regulations,
it goes against what we generally
believe because it says that cities
are not planned, certainly,
there isn't really a zoning plan,
on the other hand
there is a whole armada of
legislative texts
which provide a very important
legal framework.
And we could even imagine that,
seeing the number
of codes and laws
and orders and decrees in
planning or annexed areas
we don't need plans since in the end
all these legislative texts are
sufficiently abundant
to manage all of the urban issues.
So, depending on the country,
there may be Urban Codes,
Environment Codes,
Construction Codes,
Architecture Codes, often it's somewhat
the same thing, Water Codes,
the law instituting the urban community
when we have an urban community,
the decentralization laws
which determine the town governments,
in particular
there can be property laws,
a whole series of other laws
or other Codes
that are in one way or another related
to the issues of planning.
Finally, when we are talking about plans,
when we are talking about tools,
which are the orientation requirements
or land use?
We must quickly discuss
methodology since
we have a sort of basic plan
for the elaboration
of master plans and in general
we go from a first stage of training
and sensitization of stakeholders.
So this can be a ministry,
the urban communities
but anyone who will have anything
to say about the master plan.
It is very important that they
be conscious and
trained in the usage and language
of the master plan.
Then a diagnostic is established.
This is the current situation of the city,
the day that we look at the situation.
This means that we are at the
beginning of our planning.
The orientations are going to be defined,
we have already seen this.
On the basis of a diagnosis, we define
the orientations that we will give
once spatialised, a plan that will have
a horizon of 10 or 20 years.
Farther along, it doesn't really make sense
since we have already seen,
things change quickly
so we have a horizon of 10 years
or 20 years.
So we must pay attention that the
elaboration of the four stages
don't take 10 years alone
as we saw a few years ago
particularly in Abidjan
where preparatory studies
lasted almost 10 years.
This means that the first study
which was done, the diagnostic,
if 10 years later the plan is still not ready,
you are obligated
to do the studies once again
and this is never ending so all
these stages should be done
in a relatively short or very short
period of time.
It is better to do it several times very
short than a single time
where it's believed that formalizing
the issue is going to work
and finally we realize that at the point
where this formalization is finished,
it's no longer the same issue.
Once the plan is elaborated,
we put it in motion.
Instructions will be given to put
the plan in motion with a number of
accompanying measures.
A program with priority investments
will be developed.
So we should put it between
brackets like this.
Why?
Because it depends heavily
on donor funds.
Certain donors don't want to make
a priority investments program and
just want to do the planning.
Other donors find it important that this
planning be accompanied by
a certain number of projects
that are feasible right away,
and others feasible in the long term
but this planning without projects to be
completed is not good for anything.
The next stage of communication.
The one which is forgotten, in theory,
the fastest because
most people don't see the issue
there would be behind it.
When really this is an extremely important
stage since it is perhaps this stage
on which success rests and not on the plan
or in any case of it's being put in motion.
Finally, the evaluation stage.
So for this, one needs
to have precise criteria,
specific prerequisites.
What are we going to evaluate?
Evaluating for the sake of evaluating
doesn't do anything; evaluating if we
know what we are going to evaluate
is useful so we know if it was efficient
or not when we made our plan.
Here is a quick example of a plan,
Nouakchott plan in Mauritania still,
a 1983 plan with a horizon in 1990.
We see that it is in the detail there.
The plan is a little bit deformed
but that's okay.
We see the city center with a cutout of
the land by land use.
Another plan, the blueprint for
urban development, still in the city
of Nouakchott, we can see that
there are two types of different plans.
The first dates from 83, the second
from 2002 with a horizon in 2010.
We see that they are excessively different
in their shape and then with a
first horizon of the plan in 2010
and a second in 2020 where bypasses
have been drawn around the city.
The city of Nouakchott, the two examples
shown will be the focus
of a separate case study in a video this week.
So we will not go on here on the
case of the city of Nouakchott.
And then, to wrap it up, we will show
an example of the urban master plan
of Dakar, horizon of 2025 where we see
those who know it well,
Lac Rose, which is here and
15 years ago
it was difficult to locate,
to go to Lac Rose.
Today, urbanization has taken
the whole scope of Dakar.
We still see some green breakthroughs
a few unoccupied areas
but fewer and fewer.
The rest of the city of Dakar
is completely urbanized
or being urbanized.
So there you have the second part of
Urban Planning.
I'll see you in the following videos.