Here, we go one step further,
since we are going to go from
what is called classical planning,
that I call physical planning
of the city, to strategic planning.
So we're going to stop the suspense,
we are going to give the end of the movie,
meaning you will see, we will be talking
about physical planing
or strategic planning, there is no
paradigm shift.
We're dealing with the same type
of thinking, the same type of tools,
we have simply upgraded
the questions a little bit,
we have opened the box, to go from
a rigid physical planning to a planning
much more flexible which would bring
about the intervention of other players.
But, broadly speaking, the purpose,
which most of the time,
is a plan, is exactly the same.
Two definitions of strategic planning.
Strategic spatial planning is a process
of collective elaboration.
There it is, the big news is
that there is a participatory process
with a number of players
who have to be present.
And this is a city project carried out
by the political power, inevitably, here,
we are dealing with classical planning
since it was already the case.
We define a general framework consisting
of general guidelines
and principles of action to control
the development of an urban area.
This is the main objective, it is
the mastery of an urban area of the city.
That is the French Agency of Development
which in one of its documents,
which you will find referenced,
so all the documents
that are used for this type
of definition are, of course, referenced.
You will be able to see the references,
and when there is a PDF link there
and free of copyright, the link is
of course set and just go click.
Strategic planning provides
a methodology.
Once again, we are dealing with
new methods which allow cities
to identify the strengths
and weaknesses and then
we define the strategies
for local development.
It is the UCLG which gives
this definition of strategic planning.
We are not going to
make more definitions
since virtually each donor, each
association, has its own definition.
The planning aspect means that we
are looking to regulate development.
It's the very definition of planning.
Planning gives us a notion of time,
we try to imagine what the city will be
in the future and we try to imagine,
both spatially and socially
what the city will be.
We should not confuse planning
and programming.
Programming would be the
operative version under the guise
of a number of projects in a plan.
Let's keep for planning the idea
of frame-working, of mastering
a development, in time, both
socially and spatially.
Urban, why?
Because it is located in an area
which is the city area.
So we are dealing with spatial issues,
we are not interested in planning
what is not directly spatialized
or spatial or that would have
an important effect on
the spatial aspect of the city.
Finally, the concept of strategy,
it involves more the question
of process, of progress, to achieve
a goal that has been given.
So behind this, there is not
only the objective
but the means to achieve this objective
which is also important.
So the few keywords of this planning.
The question of priorities,
strategic planning demonstrates
what the city priorities are,
demonstrates these priorities in time.
So there is a notion of perspective.
The idea behind this, is that we will
distribute resources, we come back
to the question of priorities,
which resources are used first?
What resources do we use second?
There is there, behind the idea of
of ​​strategic planning a new instrument.
We were talking earlier about progress,
we were talking about the goal to be
achieved, but of the process
which allows us to achieve this goal,
it's there that there is
a new instrument to put in place.
A new instrument which is meant,
it is the goal of the planning,
which is there to
coordinate public politics.
So we are going to, thanks to this new
instrument, transform public action.
We must be able to see this
in a dynamic question,
it allows to coordinate and transform
public politics at the same time.
It can materialize in the form
of drawings, plans,
but also regulations or public policies,
as we have already said.
So the physical planning of the city,
this is also what we call sometimes
technical planning, in my opinion,
too reducing as a term, it's what
some call classical planning,
allowing for the assumption or
understanding that it's the old version
of planning and that strategic planning
would come on the scene as something
extremely new, there, in the middle.
We have seen it earlier,
there is nothing new in the strategy.
We saw it earlier,
there is nothing new in the strategic
urban planning tool.
There are new things that happen but
there is no real paradigm shift.
So planning, for me, is not classical
but it is what I call
the physical planning of the city.
This planning, it's here for,
both mastering the different uses
or the land uses and at the same time, to
manage the distance between these uses.
It is a very reductive drawing,
but it's true
that this drawing started from a
quantification of the elements.
So there is of course, behind this
an idea to quantify things,
an idea of modeling things, to be able to,
in this way, imagine their future.
So, physical planning, also known as
technocratic, also known as technical,
that is known to be flexible, finally,
it's what we wanted to put there.
Indeed, the plans are relatively rigid,
but nothing used to stop us before,
the invention of strategic planning
to make documents
or to make tools that were
much more flexible.
But it is clear that there is something
much more static.
And what we look for then,
is to go to something that
is flexible which corresponds much
better to the city's rapid changes.
We'll start, of course, from the question
of the new urban situation.
So each time that we want
to justify a new instrument,
we must of course say that
the situation has changed,
which is, in this case is true, really,
this doesn't even truly change,
there are few paradigm shifts.
On the other hand, there is
an acceleration of changes.
And we visibly have a change of scale,
where we have gone
from municipal management to a
management of towns and cities.
A change of scale, which doesn't mean
that the administrative network
has already changed.
Most of the time, we are still
dealing with municipalities,
a number of municipalities can
form an urban community,
or a district but it's rare that we have
an entire town that would be treated
as a single and unique city.
We have a redistribution of powers
due to decentralization.
So, often a power has been decentralized,
the financial means have
never or very rarely been decentralized,
which raises another concern.
We have in the context of globalization,
new centralities that appear,
so this is effectively
a fairly recent situation.
We have seen with global cities,
there is competition
of a number of cities.
The role of the civil society
that has increased,
the civil society will also get an input.
The emergence of new players who are
particularly private players.
So it's quite interesting to see
that they are considered
as new players in the African cities
or in the European cities.
If we consider urban planning in the USA,
we realize that
the city development,
particularly New York
was made with private players.
So in the USA, it's something very old.
In Europe, in Africa it's something
much newer, to take into
account private players.
In summary, the strategic planning
has an objective, the improvement
of quality of life, evidently, this
is not new either, this objective.
An objective, finally, little innovative
since it is the same in
almost all the cities.
With behind this,
notions of equity of area
of social equity, but it's about this,
the main objective is the improvement
of the quality of life
of all of the residents of the city.
It's very important, the last part,
all of the residents of the city.
If the goal, if the objective,
remains classical,
it's also a process, it's an instrument
that takes a different shape
since we are really dealing with
a planning process with
the new players as well
as the private ones,
civil society, all of these people
are player who become
important in planning.
So we have a goal that remains the same,
since the dawn of time,
in the end, the improvement of quality
of life is what we're looking for.
But we also have an instrument
that becomes dynamic
since it's no longer a finality but
it becomes an entire process.
Finally the shape of the instrument,
it is flexible,
simple and finally modifiable
rather quickly in time.
So in summary we have
a new scale of area, new players,
we have new themes, new thematics
and all this shapes an instrument
that's called strategic urban planning.
To conclude, some drawbacks
to this strategic planning,
which seems to
throw everything which was before,
quantitative, we have gone from
a quantification of area
to a qualification of area
by throwing the quantification,
I think that precisely
a smart tool should use the two,
so it is not against the other.
Strategic planning gives the impression
that it no longer wants to address things
from a model perspective, quantitative,
but above all with qualitative aspects.
I think they are actually very
important, but we need both.
Again when we want to believe
something is completely new,
we minimize what
has already been done before
to the point of caricaturing, for this
also there is a mistake,
there is a considerable bias
because we cannot say
that we are dealing with
something totally new,
it is just reflections
that go a little further, that take on
a few more player legitimately,
it's fine but we are not going to say
that nothing was happening
and that nothing was done before.
So we are really dealing with
strategic planning not being
a rupture but fits exactly in the
continuity and it should not be
made to believe that before this
there was nothing
and that today we found a solution,
it's absolutely not the case.
The proof is that the shape tool
remains a plan, a regulation, so
this is the unsurpassable framework that
even strategic planning has not suceeded
in surpassing, not succeeded
in proposing something new,
it's important to understand it,
and there is behind this,
a very important point that
I would like to highlight today.
In the global cities theories,
we have seen it,
the cities play on the competition
with each other.
And we have seen that for this there needs
to be a concentration of powers.
In each city which has wanted
to become a global city,
we have seen a reconcentration
of powers with a small group
that had their hands free to play
on this competition.
Yet what strategic planning proposes
today is exactly the opposite.
It's that this power be given
to the greatest number, that we have
a maximum of players.
So it's necessary to know that on
one side we have an opening,
it's the strategic urban planning
and on the other side global cities
so as to be able to play
on the competition, we realize that they
have to re-centralize the powers
and designate their actions
and their plannings according
to these global objectives.
So there is here a major paradox
with two situations
that do not lead at all to
the same type of city.
So if we wanted to continue to caricature
a little more, we would say that
if the African cities absolutely want
to become global cities,
play a role in the international scene,
there must be above all strategic planning
or rather the planning method
needs to be drastically changed
and the powers re-centered
to propose a planning
that is directly in total agreement
with the competition objective
with the other cities.
I am not placing
any value judgement on this,
I am not saying it needs to be
one more than the other,
one must simply be conscious that it
will not result in the same objectives.
There it is, we stop here for
strategic urban planning.
I look forward to seeing you
in the next video.