In our video we are going
to see the limits of plans.
We are going to see which
elements do not allow
the plans to be more
effective and more efficient.
There are blocking elements
that we will try to identify.
We will continue with general limits
that are inherent
not to the making process of the plan
but to the context,
and finally, we will talk about the method
as the success factor of urban plans.
In order to understand which levers
can be used to activate or modify the tool,
one has to understand the making process
of an urban plan or an urban planning plan.
We will see this step by step.
The different stages of the plan.
First, the plan is an element
in the development project.
It does not contain all the projects,
but is one project among others.
Then, the State and fund providers,
which can be the municipality but it's
generally the State,
decide to make a plan, un SDAU
a master plan, a sketch, an outline
and determine a budget
to create this plan.
Next is the writing of
the terms of reference,
often outsourced to a private consultant,
or done internally,
but in theory,
the terms of reference are written
and are eventually the guideline
of the future urban plan.
After this, calls are made
for expressions of interest,
where the interested organisations
are asked to express their interest.
Then, a short-list is created
according to the files of the companies
to decide which organisations
will be able to bid.
Then, the tenderer is being launched
the offers are analyzed,
negotiations with the best bid are made
and we have different stages of the project
and in the very end,
the structure of the plan is checked,
to see if the final product matches
the terms of reference,
if what was produced
matches what we wanted to produce.
It means that the key stage
in the making process of a plan
is the writing
of the terms of reference.
It is the only time
where it is possible to add innovation.
If you want to innovate
with the planning tools,
there is only one moment in the whole process,
and that's when you write
the terms of reference.
After they are written, everything
flows from these terms of reference.
There is no more possibility for change.
It is said that a number
of consulting firms
have a financial leeway and can be flexible,
it is true and false at the same time,
since at the end of the process,
we will check if the firm
or the people in charge
of the urban planning
have respected
the specifications, also called
the terms of reference.
So it is important to be aware of this,
it's the only time in the process where
it's possible to change something.
And when it's understood
that this is the only time,
it is interesting to think about
how to write the terms of reference.
It's at that time that we gather
to imagine how the process
will be able to develop.
We have seen one possible lever
for change,
to be able to inflect on the tools,
to change them
or to add innovation
to the planning tools.
We are now going to see
the limits to the plans.
By limits, I want to put forth
the elements which block
the plan or make it useless
since it is not made
according to the context.
The first thing to keep in mind
is that urban planning
is in direct connection
with the social structures
of countries and cities.
First, be aware and remember
that urban planning is directly linked
to the political
and social structures of cities.
It means that
there are as many social structures
as there are cities or countries.
This is the first element to take into account.
The second one is to keep in mind
that are being applied to African cities
only the tools which have been developped
elsewhere and especially in Europe.
It is easy to see that when
we are in Abidjan,
we are not in Lausanne,
when we are in Dakar, it's not Paris.
The idea is not to give a value judgement,
but simply state that we are not
dealing with the same reality.
We are not dealing with the same
social realities,
we are not dealing with the same
political realities,
there is no reason for the tool
being developed to be exactly
the same.
Another element - in planning,
the size of cities is never
taken into consideration.
Planning is different for a city
with 500 thousands people
and for a city with 5 million people.
The complexity is not the same,
the problems, the concerns,
the challenges
are therefore not the same,
so the answers
given with the planning tools
will not be the same.
Another element which largely limits
the extent of our plans
is that the climate
is not taken into account.
It is the same planning in
Douala, Nouakchott,
Ouagadougou, Addis Ababa,
and Bamako or Kigali.
Yet the morphology and climate
are extremely different.
And this must be taken into account
if we want to be efficient
in planning the city.
Same thing for economic issues,
they are never addressed,
yet urbanization has a cost.
The decisions made at the planning level
have a direct impact
on the local communities and
national finances.
And this is never negotiated,
it is never underlined
and generally,
planning is made
like if it was totally separated
from the economic system.
Finally, planning does not take
social practices into account,
be formal or informal,
they are important
and they generate spatiality,
but they are also
the very base of social life.
And if we don't understand
these social practices,
it's no use planning since we will
be missing the point.
I am going to use a very simple example,
real estate.
Most plans ignore the issue
of real estate.
Yet we know that it's a social practice
whether it be formal or informal,
traditional or modern,
it doesn't matter,
but the real estate issue
is fundamental.
If I don't take
the real estate issue seriously
it's useless to plan
since I will be missing the point anyway,
as real estate practices will be more
important than my practices as planner.
To conclude and sum up the limits,
this long list of limiting elements,
we must realize that
we never really plan the
existing situation.
We plan for what we could call
the average man, a man who
would be neither rich,
nor poor, a man who, in fact,
does not exist or is in minority
in African cities.
So there is an idea
of an urban resident type
which is modeled after
a few European cities,
of an average man, who would have a car,
a plot of land with a detached house.
Yet in African cities,
we are far from this,
and in all urban world
we are, in theory, very very
far from this situation.
So we plan for a man
who does not exist.
Not for an existing context,
but for one that does not exist.
And this is all the limits of the plan,
as we don't use the real social practices,
we plan for an archetype
which does not exist.
We ignore the climate
and morphological context,
the economic situation,
all these things
which really help planning the city.
So how to go about it?
We will see next week some recipes,
some don't like this word,
but I find it very appropriate to give
some recipes,
some very simple ones,
which include the different contexts
but one thing is certain,
if we want to overcome all the limits,
if we wan to rethink the object,
the planning tool
we need to reintroduce innovation in
the terms of reference,
and what we need is a method.
In fact, we could use almost
the same method,
it's a method which wants
to take into account
the particularities of each city.
In summary, there is no difference
between physical and strategic planning,
as seen in the History of Planning,
we saw that innovation can only be
introduced into the terms of reference,
and finally, all the limiting elements
showing that each city need its own plan
and that it is not possible
to copy paste elements between cities.
All this is brought together
with the question of method.
And the method must give
some rules,
it means that we will make a plan,
which should be done
within the administration,
where we have brought
some external experts,
as we cannot know everything
in the administrations,
in the large administrations and
this works well,
in the little ones, the number
of people is insufficient.
We also need external opinions
in order to mix ideas
but it's necessary for the people
who will manage the plan
to be the same as those who created it.
The person who creates it has
to take it on and manage it,
and this situation only
happens within administrations.
For this, we bring together a group,
there is a great experiment which
was done in N'Djamena a few years ago,
we will show some results
and we will describe
in the next videos the methods
that were used,
but the idea behind it is to have
a group that develops the plan
and introduces slowly their ideas into it
so they will be able in the future
to defend the ideas on a daily basis,
to colleagues or other partners
such as public authorities,
if the plan was not made
within public authorities.
It is definitely the idea that
there is one method allowing
to come up with a plan for a city,
and that this plan matches exactly
in its structure and idea,
the political and social structure
of the city,
taking the climate and else into account
to overcome all said limits.
Finally, one of the criteria of our method
that we will clarify later,
is that it is important
that all themes, subjects and problems
are managed at the same level.
There is no hierarchy in themes,
we have to approach
all themes and issues
that we will find while planning
in the same way and with great respect.