Hello. In today's video we'll do a
critical reading on issues of planning,
of the planning as practiced
today in African cities.
This planning, as practiced, is described,
this critical analysis is described,
in the work you see here,
"The West African City," which is available
in both a French and English version.
A small reminder of the different types
of planning, the different tools.
We'll see this as a table, with a cursor
which can go from land use to territory,
and from the questions of
programming to strategy.
If we have a clear land-use plan,
we'll be here,
and the master plan will come
from this side.
The old types of plans
were more programmatic.
We are here and are heading towards
the strategies of today.
So if I want a classic planning it
would be somewhere over here,
and a strategic urban planning,
such as that interpreted today
by large agencies and the World Bank,
would put us perhaps over here.
So there is a programmatic progression
from land use to the questions
of territory and strategy.
There you have it, a small reminder of
what we've already seen.
All of this is to say that we must pay
attention to the extremes, as always,
if we find ourselves there, or
if we find ourselves here,
we can easily realize
that we are inevitably
on the strategic and territorial,
but are, without a doubt,
moving too far away from
the programmatic questions.
And these tools should be,
at the same time,
useful as a road-map
for day-to-day planning,
for urban day-to-day management.
This is not just a strategic document,
disconnected from its context of land use
and those projects either
in progress or upcoming.
This is truly a tool which
should be pragmatic,
which we can use on a day-to-day basis.
So beyond a zone such as this one here,
it suddenly becomes
dangerous to go further,
and we obtain documents which are useless
for day-to-day management.
Now, as a reminder, for what purpose
does planning serve? Why plan?
To plan allows us to implement
the principles of sustainable development.
This is critical today.
To plan also allows us to have a vision,
for both the medium and long-term.
As for the very short-term, we are
instead dealing with questions
of management rather than planning.
It is the medium and long term which are
the effective time-frame for planning.
To plan allows for the rational
organization of resources.
It also allows for the communication
between a growing demand,
an increasing number of inhabitants,
and the protection of the patrimony,
the protection of greenfield lands,
the protection of nature.
So these are very classic issues,
which we've already addressed
many times in this course,
but planning should serve as
the basis of an economic activity.
It should allow for the development
of economic activity.
We'll deal, from this point on,
solely with the last chapter of the book,
with just a brief overview
of African cities,
which have a certain number
of similarities.
We'll adopt the plural form of the word,
these are African cities,
for they are numerous.
However, when we analyze
a large number of cities,
we find a certain number
of characteristics.
The first, within the colonial
foundation of the cities,
is the question of segregation.
Let's use as an example that of Abidjan.
We can see that the urban
mesh of the Le Plateau
and the urban mesh of the other side
of the lagoon, are clearly very different.
We have a meshing which
is not at all on the same scale.
The same in Dakar, where we have between
this zone here and that zone there,
much denser, a zone here which was
a buffer zone with notably large avenues.
The colonial city was formed
on the same principle,
which is the principle
of population segregation.
The native population vs. the European,
the administrative vs. the workers,
the rich vs. the poor.
We find ourselves in this model
and it is interesting to see,
in a city such as Nouakchott,
which is a new city,
its foundation begun in 1958, so recent,
to see how two years before independence,
the same model was used as a base,
which is a model of segregation.
So the African city is one
of apartheid by definition.
Depending on the times,
depending on the country,
this separation between populations
has been more or less significant,
more or less strong or loose, it depends.
There are extremely different contexts,
but in principle we had indigenous
populations, and European populations,
or the elites and the poorest
of the populations.
Next, the second similarity.
The poor have the same
strategies for implantation.
There are two strategies.
We see that the poorest, the shantytowns,
once developed, are normally
near employment areas.
The first strategy of implantation.
Or perhaps they are on vacant lots,
in nooks and crannies, on slopes,
in all areas that the city produces
as unbuildable land,
which in fact belong to no one.
And it is within these gaps where
the poorest populations insert themselves.
It is because of this, in the event of
a problem, in the event of landslides,
these very same populations,
the most vulnerable, the poorest,
are inevitably the ones most affected,
because they are often living on land
unsuitable for building.
We also have another similarity:
the same developers.
It is the same firms, the same
thinkers, the same people
who develop urban plans
from Nouakchott to Djibouti,
from Dakar to Djibouti, let's say,
from Ouagadougou to Harare,
these are large companies
who are in charge of this,
and we ultimately find
the same developers,
the same city-builders,
more or less everywhere.
We're not making value judgements here.
We're simply pointing out how this explains
why one also finds tools
which are extremely similar,
in the totality of African cities.
And this is reinforced, clearly,
by the fact that we have
the same financial backers more or less
everywhere, a few important investors
who play an important role in the manner
in which one makes a city,
and on the tools one puts
in place to plan this city.
So even if in general the investor
makes as though he remains
in the background,
we realize on a daily basis,
as we go about our work,
that the investor is extremely present,
likewise, on all technical questions.
There are plans, models, which
the financial backer applies,
and it is also because of this that
we find a certain number of similarities
in the whole of African cities.
We have cities which are practically
identical, with identical problems.
And the greatest problem today,
the largest problem,
and the one most often written about,
is the question of land use.
Land issues are different in
each one of these countries,
in each one of these cities.
In some countries there is the problem of
too important land sales by the state
of a certain number of parcels.
Too many land parcels
are put on the market,
which leads to speculation
and appropriation by a small group
of a certain number of parcels.
In other cities, we'll cite the case
of the school of Douala,
where there are issues between
the actual inhabitants and the owners,
the state being, in fact, the owner
of the majority of the land.
There is a game between the state
and the inhabitants, in certain cities.
But in all the cities that we cross,
in all the urban plans
which will be developed,
there will still remain one main problem,
which is that of land use.
We can see here this question of
unregulated land use,
for we are in a shantytown.
We see how the implantation of people,
of those who have occupied it,
as squatters on the land,
and how they've made a network of roads
in the interior of this field of shacks.
So this is the primary element,
that of land use.
The second element is that
of the environment.
We have an example here with waste.
At the bottom of the screen we see
some young people dealing with fish,
preparing it, cutting it, cutting off
the heads for their clients,
and doing all this on top of
a pile of garbage,
which brings us to environmental issues
of extreme relevance in certain cities.
This is but one example among others,
the environmental question
is also that of ecosystems,
is also that of the pollution
of air, of land, of water.
We can extend this to other domains,
but we see that in all these cases
the weakest link,
in Africa, is the environment,
and it is there where perhaps the most
work should be done in the years ahead,
to ensure a radical change
of this situation.
Another problem, that of circulation.
Difficult circulation, difficult mobility
in the majority of African cities.
Here we have a taxi station in Abidjan,
not too dense, we see that things
are moving along relatively smoothly.
That's when all is going well,
but there are other moments
with traffic jams which last
for hours and hours,
in the center of the city.
So the difficulty of movement,
the difficulty of circulation,
is extremely important today.
Now to the last problem, which is not
a problem in itself,
but which without a doubt
creates difficulties for people,
but which should not be placed on
the same level as a too-dense circulation,
which is the question of poverty.
It's important to have
a positive vision of this poverty,
otherwise one will
never build another thing.
But it is something to keep
in mind as one plans.
One must know for whom one plans.
And poverty is a major issue for
a large number of those in African cities.
We might now even say for the majority.
So it is something extremely present
in the day-to-day, for families.
And it is something which must
be looked at globally
as one embarks on urban planning.
Here we see the living conditions
in a poor neighborhood.
We've reached a common point,
the last of our series, on African cities.
What are the current limits on this plans?
The first is that one continues to work
by extension and by segregation.
From the moment the foundation
is laid in these cities,
in these large African capitals, the same
plan of segregation continues.
And one continues, in the same
manner, to build this city,
to produce subsequent extensions,
by subsequent parcels.
Thus the planning never reaches a moment
when it reflects on
the question of segregation,
which continues, decade after decade,
to be precisely the same,
just as the moment never arrives
to address the question of expansion,
which continues, lot by lot.
The second important limit,
by no means the least,
is that urbanization has no cost.
If we look at these plans as a whole,
at the master plans of today,
we realize that the question of the cost
of urbanization is simply not addressed.
This is one of the greatest
limitations of the system,
for if costs are not applied to
the actions one takes,
one never knows if one has or has not
the means to carry them out.
So it is truly critical to provide
numbers, to give a cost
to these different types of urbanizations
which one is about to put in place.
Another limits, one we just spoke of,
and a common point between cities,
is that of poverty.
We realize that the documents
of urban planning never mention poverty.
They make it as though
poverty doesn't exist,
that it is neither a specific element
of the city, nor of its planning.
When poverty is mentioned, it is in
the diagnostic part of planning,
forgetting later the fact that
these cities are composed,
by a huge majority, of the extremely poor.
Another element which
limits the scope of plans,
is that in order to plan, one has invented
what I call the "average man."
The average man is one who works,
who has a family, a vehicle,
who has a small house
somewhere in the suburbs.
It is the American style
of family, without doubt,
yet this average man, if we look at
the statistics of Africa,
simply does not exist.
Car ownership rates clearly show us that
the classic man does not own one,
that the man of the street does not,
today, have a vehicle.
So all this planning is done
for this average man,
who is the ghost, perhaps,
of a middle class
which does not exist,
or which barely exists.
And it is for him that one plans.
It is for him that roads are built,
for he has a vehicle,
while in reality, this man does not exist.
And even if he does exist,
he doesn't have a vehicle.
So this is extremely limiting in scope,
which is to say that one
does not plan for the people,
for those who live in the city,
one plans for this image we have
of a man who does not exist.
The next element is the link between
management and planning,
which is nonexistent.
Planning is only useful if
it guides urban management,
and if the two are coordinated.
one with the other.
This is extremely important,
because what one plans today
will need to be managed tomorrow.
So we cannot imagine
a disconnect between the two.
Today there is on the one hand
the city managers,
and on the other the planners,
and they are not one and the same.
Which means that
as long as these two areas
are not integrated into the same plan,
in the same way of conceiving
the future of these cities,
we'll never achieve anything because,
we have on the one hand the planners,
with their idea of a city, in 10-20 years,
and then we have the managers who,
in the end, have to manage these things.
Yet this never enters into
their management plans,
neither on the middle nor long term.
This, then, is the conclusion of
the book I showed you
at the beginning of the video,
at the beginning of this journey,
which is the question of
another way of planning.
We see that there are
a certain number of limits.
We have identical problems,
we have cities which
are relatively similar,
we have limitations to these plans,
so we must know what one can do,
despite all, in order to plan.
Because what we propose is a self-
organizing plan, one centered on people.
I will not dwell on this, simply that
this is what is behind the idea
that all social practices,
all land-use practices,
our relationship to the environment,
all the social practices,
should be integrated in a reflection
on the tools of planning.
We have a disconnect between
the practices of people in daily-life,
and urban planning.
There are two solutions.
Either it is the discussion which
is false, or practices which are false,
yet this discussion, what one says
one wants to do and what one actually does
are two totally different things.
Either we change the discussion
and tie it to our practice,
or we change our practice
so that it ties into our discussion.
We are, today, in a situation where
practice is of such importance
that it is difficult to change,
and what we propose here
is that we adapt, partially,
at least in the beginning, the discussion
to an informal one,
on the question of land use.
It is useless to wish, at all costs,
to formalize the informal,
unless one realizes that the majority,
the totality of people,
in their day-to-day relationships,
in their day-to-day social practices,
reside in the informal.
There is no point in attacking things
that cannot be changed.
These are not urban plans which
will change ancestral practices.
We must now readjust our discussion
in function of this,
go back to these practices, view what
people do and how they do it,
and revisit the tools of urban planning
in terms of these social practices.
It is not participation, it is not
a process of decisions taken by all,
but rather to be able
to integrate these practices,
those of the land owner, those of
the political elite, other practices,
and directly integrate them
in our planning tools.
Otherwise all this serves no point.
If you embark on planning without even
considering the question of land use,
and without trying to elicit
some sort of response,
we already know that your planning
will serve absolutely no purpose.
So in a few words, a brief overview,
I refer you to the book,
you'll find in its conclusions
all of the topics we've discussed here,
as well as other supplemental topics,
which we simply didn't have time
to explore in the course of this video.