Hello.
Here, I would love to share ten basic
principles while planning.
So we could give 20, we could give 50
we could give three.
I have come up with ten principles
that seem obviously essential
while planning.
So of course, they are not
directly operational to the plan.
We cannot draw the principles like this
but we must keep them in mind
when we are planning.
Always keep in mind these ten principles.
And then at each stage we can reconsider
our plan in the light
of these principles.
Do I realize the first principle,
the second?
And maybe if none of these great
principles mentioned here is used
in the planning,
maybe we need to look again a little bit
the plan which
is about to be put in place.
The first principle, we put it at number one
because it's important.
The importance of the pedestrian.
So this goes against everything
we do generally,
since we are more focused on
the importance of the car.
The planning creates new roads,
new highways,
new intersections, one more
prestigious than the other
with roundabouts, sculptures,
statues in the middle, but I would like
to put the emphasis on the pedestrian.
The majority of people in African cities
get around on foot.
If we want to make the city
for the majority of people
it's therefore a city for pedestrians
that must be created.
So let's keep this in mind as rule #1,
I favor the pedestrian.
We have seen it in
the city models,
throughout the introduction
to this course that there are
cities like Kuala Lumpur
that are already much more advanced
regarding pedestrian issues.
Why wouldn't African cities
be as well one day?
So it is not well seen for some
to take walks, but know that
the majority of city residents
go about on foot.
And it's for them that
we create the city.
The second principle, we must think spatially.
This is the risk when we are
dealing with strategy,
we forget the spatial question.
However, the purpose of the city is a
city ​​that is three-dimensional, a street
that goes from here to there,
that has dimensions,
the plots have dimensions.
So the spatiality is very important,
and we must think about
the spatiality we are putting in place
when we are planning.
We are not just dealing with strategy
and communication, we are also
dealing with physical issues,
real issues, spatial issues.
The planning serving above all
to organize the activities
which have a spatial impact
on the land.
So it is important to think about it and
have this as a basic principle.
Think about spatiality.
The third principle, you must have
a minimalist approach.
In all cases, the large majority
of cities have limited
financial resources.
We must have a a pragmatic approach
but minimalist as well.
We are thankful to some infrastructures
a basic structure.
Minimal structures that then allow
to complete, then to develop.
But basically, we try to see what
is the minimum that I can
put in place to have the maximum effect
and not the opposite,
as we see in most cities.
Another principle is that we need
efficiency in resources.
The resources are limited, we have to be
efficient in their use.
In all the resources, be they
financial, be they natural.
be they human, we have to
be careful to use
these resources the most
harmoniously possible.
The fifth basic principle, is that
opportunities must be developed.
What we are going to do, what
we are going to put in place,
the planning has to be supportive of
opportunities for further development.
We are not in something that is closed.
We are dealing with an open process and
the process must generate a number of
opportunities and that will then become
jobs, that will become other things.
But we have to provide the base to open
opportunities and not shut them out.
The sixth point, sixth basic principle, diversity.
We sometimes talk about mixing,
we need diversity in the cities.
The idea is not to have neighborhoods
with the same houses,
the same people who go around
in the same cars,
but rather mixing and diversity,
which allows the resident
to have a vast choice.
Diversity in the economy allows for
lowering of prices,
and having the choice of many products.
When there's only one product
which is on the market,
we don't have a choice, we have to
buy it, no matter what the price is.
Diversity allows to lower the costs
but diversity allows also
to liven up the city and to increase
the quality of life within the cities.
The seventh principle, equal access.
They are not those who have access
to the city​​, and those who have not.
It's important to give
all people who have a voice
when they vote, they must be given
equal access to infrastructures
and facilities.
This is a basic principle that must
absolutely be held onto.
We see more and more cities being born
from segregation,
access differentiated depending on
any number of criteria in the population.
We need a city open to the maximum
for all of the inhabitants of this city,
whomever they may be.
And this leads to the issue of
diversity of people, and it is
in this diversity that urban quality
surfaces and with it human quality.
Look at the big cities you know.
Look at the places you love to go to,
and you will see that these places
are built on diversity, built on
the quality of access.
Which brings us very naturally to
the eight point,
this quality of access as a main point,
also as a basic principle.
We don't only need one access,
we also need to have a quality
to this access.
And this search for quality,
it's the search
for quality of life, quality of
the urban environment.
So we have both quantitative issues,
or rather, do I have access or not,
and how do I have access?
And it's important, this notion of quality
which is difficult to define and
which we will not define here,
not right away, but it's of course one of
the main elements, is the quality of life
of the population.
So everything we are going to put in place
is to increase this quality.
The second to last principle,
sustainability of the action.
Everything we plan has to be
sustainable with time.
If we realize that it's not sustainable,
this means that we will quickly have a problem.
So we are going to put in place a number
of physical, spatialized elements.
We are going to plan, program things
that have to be sustainable in time.
And finally, the principle itself,
planning,
it's about working on the medium
and long term.
So we have said that we had to
be sustainable, but we have to
truly set as a principle, the work on
the medium and long term,
the short term being left
generally to the urban management who
manages the city on a daily basis.
What we are interested in is the medium
and this long term, indeed,
this very long term, even if
in the case of the very long term, there
is little chance we will get today
to plan something for the next 50 years
or 100 years.
So let's remain more reasonable on
the 10 or 20 years to come,
it's already a very faraway horizon.
The most result that we can have,
is two political legislatures.
So sometimes it's eight years,
sometimes it's ten, but we are
dealing with, in these waters, almost
a term planning, ten years.
There they are, the basic principles.
It's on these principles that we
are going to then build a plan.
So you have seen that certain ones
are directly linked,
for example the question of access and
the question of quality of access,
the question of sustainability
and the question of the medium
and the long term.
It's normal, all these principles
have a link, all these principles
have to be articulated which
then leads to a plan.