Hello, we are going to discuss
density, urban form,
and compact cities of present day.
We are going to discuss what
the English call "pattern".
And we are going to see what are the choices
that must be made when we want to design
or plan the city.
There are three possibilities to fit
into an existing urban structure.
Here is a city I'm drawing very quickly.
Here it is with a center.
Regardless, the first possibility is
to actually intensify
the fringes, okay, to open, of course
some new areas.
But we will try to build to the max
the city within the city.
Second possibility, let me go back
quickly to my drawing.
The second opportunity to implement,
the city center is further intensified
by building the city within the city
​​but on the outskirts
new areas are developed for
the new future populations.
It can be just about anywhere but it is
no longer desirable to have density
but rather a spread and then we continue
to build the city like that.
Know that this is the drawing being used
the majority of the time.
Finally, the third possibility
is the creation
satellites, new and future
centers
which then become, without doubt,
the new centers of the future
that will maybe have to be intensified.
So there they are, the three ways
to arrive at being inserted into
the existing urban structure.
Regardless of being by an intensification
of the existing city,
or by an implementation in the outskirts
of new plots of land,
or by multiplying the satellites,
the city satellites.
The first solution is without a doubt
the best one,
the one which we use 99% of the time
is the second solution.
What is density?
Two possibilities.
It is the development density or
population density.
Development density is not
of great interest to us.
This is more of a day to day.
Why?
Because we realize that there are
changes in the social structures.
Already residents of cities today in
African cities, the drawing where
three generations lived under one roof
tends to gradually disappear.
Which means that there is a need
for more housing
since each small entity,
each generation,
needs its own housing.
Also the number of square meters
attributed to
one housing unit per person tends
to increase in the last decades.
We realize that with any number of
difficulties, economic crises that
this notion can vary
relatively quickly but globally
the number of square meters
available of housing per person
is increasing.
Which means that for the same population
the number of households is increased
and the number of square meters per person
is increased
which creates an explosion
in built area.
This is the first densification,
the development density.
But this is of no interest at all to us.
What interests in the case of an idea of a
a sustainable city which would be
a compact city, a dense city,
is the population density which is
expressed by number of people,
by thousands of people by hectare
or square kilometer.
Some examples.
We see that density is expressed by
resident per hectare
with Dhaka to Bangladesh
555 people per hectare
and then 64 per hectare in Paris.
So we see that between Los Angeles,
extremely sparse,
Casablanca which has a very heavy density
and Dhaka or Hon Kong which
have hyper densities, this is a way of
urbanizing, a way of implementing
which is extremely different depending
on the cities we come across.
Here is an example of low density.
We see that in fact to go from
this plot of land
to these plots, we have a whole route
so if we go back to the infrastructure,
the linear meter, the distance from the road
compared to the number of inhabitants,
we see that it is very expensive
to have low density.
On the other hand, high density like this
has a number of advantages.
We are going to take a look at them,
it's the compact city but also has,
but also has a number of disadvantages.
It's a great cost also, a concentration
of pollution, we have already
discussed this.
And then we see in a drawing like this
that the public space
is clearly absent and the quality of life
therefore suffers.
So we see that between a low density
and a high density,
there are advantages and drawbacks.
We will talk about the compact city,
there is a current popular belief
which leans more in the direction
of density.
It's important to know and I will draw
the small diagram for you in the corner,
it's that we have both a hyper density
which costs in energy
and a very low density which is
equally very expensive in energy.
So between the two we have here an optimum
which remains to be defined.
And the optimum of the first city
is without doubt not the optimum
of city number two, and this optimum
depends clearly on the morphology
of the city, the meteorological context,
climate context particularly where
we will not have the same optimum
in the Sahelien cities as we do
in the tropical cities.
So the advantages of the compact city
is an accessibility, facilitated of course.
These are relatively low
infrastructure costs.
It is the possibility of preserving
the natural resources since
we are going to arrange it in a dense way
and then free other lands.
This facilitates social integration
and to finish
a facilitation in the financial
transactions since the people
are in co-presence, it's very easy
to negotiate, to buy
to make a number of transactions
from hand to hand.
The last point is the but.
But of course there is always an but
and this compact city we have
already said it
with high densities, there are
a number of
water waste management problems,
of pollution management.
Let's keep in mind that we have to have
an arbitration between the nebulous city
and the compact city.
And we have to take into account
all the evaluation criteria.
In regards to the accessibility issues,
it's of course the compact city.
In regards to climate change issues,
it's not necessarily
the compact city which best resists
to the climate change effects.
Another congruent element with density,
with the urban form,
is the issue of mixing and
that of diversity.
Mixing, it can be social,
it can be functional.
Urban history indicates to us that
social mixing often comes from
a sociologist fantasy since
there are only very few
moments in the global urban history
where populations
have not been clearly separate and where
there has been total mixing.
So the mixing is more or less great.
The extreme cases being apartheid
but w realize that the implementations
of the richest
with those of the poorest
don't take place
in the cities and this social mixing
which is an empty promise is
extremely difficult
to put in place and the examples of
urban history are there more so
to show us
that it is not possible to put in place.
On the other hand, functional mixing,
this is very easy to put in place.
What is it?
It's that we don't have
a neighborhood
that's only residential, a neighborhood
that's only business,
but that we have a big neighborhood
that is both business and residential.
And that is what we advocate.
The African cities are by definition,
mixed cities, they have
a functional mixing, this is what we need
to try and maintain and keep at all costs.
When we have created the urban form,
when we have chosen low density
or high density, when we have begun
to draw, future needs
must be anticipated.
We are not going to draw
the final form today.
We must imagine that what we are drawing
today is only a step and that
we will know the final form in 10, 20, 50
or 100 years or never but that
what we do today is but a first step
and as a result,
we must absolutely anticipate
what we will need tomorrow
so that the urban form may be able to
continue allowing
the implementation of needs in
services or infrastructures.
But it's of no use to just provide
a parcel for future installation.
The plot must still be secured.
In how many cities have we seen
subdivisions which have been built
on plots that were for the construction
of a hospital or a school.
So we must be able to then
secure the parcels
that have been identified
for future needs.
And finally when we discuss urban forms,
we are referring to drawings
of urban forms and we are discussing
the need for drawing public space.
Public space has become the poor parent
of the city and it's exactly
through public space that the city
must recreate and redraw itself.
So let's turn our attention to
the drawing itself, to the form
of public space, to the spatiality that
we are going to give it.
If we look at the big cities,
the big urban models,
the cities which win throughout
the world, the cities which are
taken as examples, you can see from
London to New York, from Singapore
to Zurich, you can all that all
these cities have made an effort.
The case of Barcelona is very
interesting for this.
All of these cities have made an effort
for public space.
And it's through this public space,
an space open to all,
that we will be able to recreate
the city of tomorrow.
So there it is for the issues
regarding pattern.
We are between the planning
and the design.
The English divide urban planning
and urban design.
We have a tendency in
the francophone world
to not separate them and to use
the same ways to react.
I think that it's necessary to see if
we are discussing
at a territorial and strategic level
or if we are discussing
a large scale project, about city design
and this video today was about this,
about the choice of patterns.