Hello, in today's video we'll discuss
transportation, travel, mobility,
and the link between transportation,
land-use planning and urban planning.
There is a direct and concrete link
between the transportation system
and the urban landscape.
It's the story of the chicken and the egg.
We don't know if it's the transportation
system which creates the urban form,
or the urban form which generates
the transportation system.
It's both at the same time.
I imagine one plays
on the other and vice versa.
But we must keep in mind this extremely
important correlation between the two.
There is an overlap between urban form
and its systems of transportation.
A concrete example: employment areas.
The densest areas are also the zones
where we find the most
public transport, for example.
Why is that? Because of issues
of cost-effectiveness.
For a public transport system to be
economically viable, or at least useful,
it requires a minimum number of people
within a given perimeter.
Without this, the transportation system
has absolutely no purpose.
And so we have this overlap
between population density
and the opportunity of having
public transportation.
What this also means is that
it influences land-use costs.
The more public transport,
the greater the connectivity,
the more networks,
the higher the land cost.
There is a correlation between,
on this side here, density,
and the number of trips per person.
If I am in my car, my density increases,
and the fewer trips I will make by car.
And if we look at the bicycle,
or of walking,
I am in the opposite position,
because the denser I am,
the more walking I will do
and also take public transport.
The denser I am the more I will walk.
So when we speak of transportation,
of cars, of trips taken,
we are speaking equally
of traffic congestion.
In order to avoid traffic congestion
we must ensure that
the road grid, the roadway system,
is extremely diffuse, hierarchical,
and that it connects all zones
of significant population.
On the contrary, we can imagine that
the best system of traffic control
is traffic congestion.
In principal, highway engineers,
transportation engineers,
jump up and down when they hear that,
but it is one way to regulate it.
Rather than expanding
the roadways each time
in order to allow more people
to pass through them
we might say, instead,
that the limit is reached,
to leave the congestion,
certain that new arrivals
will not take those routes because
they are already congested.
An American urban planner,
whose name escapes me,
said something which is very true,
which is that one cannot cure obesity
by loosening one's belt.
In the road system,
the more roads I make,
the more highways I build,
the greater the travel,
for the more cars I have,
the greater the need
for roads and highways.
We learn this relatively quickly,
but we arrive very quickly
at the saturation point
of the infrastructure we've put in place.
We are at saturation,
and we create new highways
which in a few years
will equally be at saturation.
So we must keep this
in mind while planning.
We must know what we are doing.
More is often the enemy of what is good,
for it is not because I create more roads
that the situation will improve.
And on the contrary, once again,
road congestion regulates traffic.
Second element after
congestion, car-free zones.
It is trending in European countries,
more and more in the U.S.
Let's take the case of New York,
where entire zones have been
returned to the pedestrian.
They began this way,
for there weren't many cars,
but the roadways and the right-of-way
was given to the vehicle,
so today the attempt is
to reduce the right-of-ways
dedicated to vehicles,
and give them to pedestrians.
This is a modern approach,
one that absolutely should be promoted.
This is one of our principles,
which we saw in an earlier video
on core principles for planning.
It is extremely important,
particularly for the African cities,
where the enormous majority
of people are pedestrians.
A quote that I like very much, which is
from the ex-mayor of Bogota,
who served between 2011-2012,
which says that "a developed country
is not a place where the poor have cars.
It's where the rich
use public transportation."
And it is truly here where
work needs to be done.
It is on this model,
the social model behind it,
and it is not the idea that
everyone will have a car,
since the rates of car ownership in Africa
are fewer than 100 vehicles
per 1000 inhabitants,
so this is a puddle compared to Europe,
which is at around 500 vehicles
per 1000 inhabitants,
or the U.S. where there are
more than 600 per 1000.
We see that when it comes to
the European and American models
there is a lot of latitude,
and the idea is not just
to utilize this margin,
but rather to reflect upon
which system to put in place.
We have transportation options,
for as we plan we must make choices,
and these choices depend on
a certain number of criteria.
Among the transportation options we have
the bus, the BRT, the light rail, the metro,
with investment requirements,
capacity, speed, travel time
and environmental impact.
And in each case we can classify these
as either low, medium, high, or very high.
So we know that with
the metro, for example,
we have a very large investment,
but a capacity which is also very high,
and a speed which is very high, etc.
On the other hand, the bus, which has
low investment requirements,
a medium capacity,
but also a very low speed.
So we find that, depending on
the choices one makes,
we will not have the same impact on
the environment, the same capacity,
and the interesting relation
is ultimately that between
on the one hand the capacity
and the investment,
which gives a cost per person
or cost per kilometer.
The modal choice, the choice of mode
of transport is an individual one.
The people will decide which
method of transport to take,
which they'll choose depending
on certain criteria, which include
the distance to travel,
the shape one is in,
Can I move about or not?
The time needed for travel,
if I have five minutes of travel time
it is not that same as if I have an hour,
so I will choose my method
of transportation differently,
My load---what do I have to carry?
Do I have just a bag or a full load?
Comfort level, security. Am I more secure
using one method or another?
And, finally, parking availability,
which is logical,
for if I take my vehicle I want
to know and be certain
that I will be able
to find a place to park.
Otherwise I might choose
a different mode of transport.
Here's an example, in N'Djamena,
between its northern and southern areas,
where we see cars, bicycles, motorbikes,
and, of course, all along it
the pedestrians who cross the bridge.
When we discuss modal choice
there is the question
of the individual who makes this choice,
but also the question of the collective.
What are the operative choices?
And what are the criteria used to make
these choices for the collective public?
In sum, we can go on foot,
on a bike, motorcycle, private car,
taxi, public transportation.
And all these modes,
whether public or private,
have, most of the time, their own
specificity, as we'll see.
And we should reflect today,
in terms of space.
Not all modes of transport
use the same space.
If I have here a lane which
measures 3.5 meters
we know that of pedestrians, we will have
19,000 who can pass per hour,
we'll have 14,000 bicycles,
So more pedestrians will pass
per hour than bicycles.
And we know that with mixed traffic,
only 2,000 people will pass.
So space plays an important role,
when I plan the space at my disposition,
the space which I want
to put at the disposition
of the people who travel through it.
Equity---which is extremely important,
particularly in the cities
of the south, social equity.
For the moment we give access to
the fastest, the heaviest, the richest,
and we can imagine a system
which grants access to the less costly,
the less polluting, the most fragile.
Why not?
This is truly the question of equity.
What do I favor and who will I favor?
The question of security
also becomes very important.
To lower the number of accidents is
an extremely important phenomenon today,
since the number of auto accidents
in cities is considerable.
The question of energy.
We know that the energy spent differs
depending on the mode of transport.
We must choose each time--
which will we use, which will we not?
The environment.
Clearly linked to energy,
but the impact on the environment
of certain modes of transport
is much greater than others.
The car has a significantly greater
impact on the environment,
logically, than the bike.
So these are the choices
one must make and, finally,
a very important criterion
to consider is that of cost.
These are not the same if we are walking,
on a bike, or taking public transport.
And it's not the same thing
if the cost is paid,
if the transport is paid
by private car or by taxi.
Who bears the costs?
And how much does this transport cost?
There is cost per kilometer, theoretic
cost, and then there is, finally,
whether it is the collective who
pays a portion of this cost,
or the owner who pays all costs.
So, a brief overview.
How do I plan? How do I make choices?
modal choices, individual choices,
collective choices.
And we must keep in mind
that the choices I make
are those of society,
of equity or inequity,
and above all, they will have an enormous
impact on the environment.
We can use the environment,
or energy as our main criteria,
but we might also take into account
multiple aspects, and utilize
in an articulate way all criteria
in order to make the best choices.
But always keep in mind that urban form
and transportation systems
are directly linked.
When we discuss climate change,
we'll keep this in mind.
When we discuss density,
we'll keep this in mind,
this question of urban form and
transportation or public transport.
And we know that the diffuse city
is the urban form least favorable
to public transport.