Planning infrastructure.
Infrastructure is actually
what defines how well a city is doing
what shapes a city,
determines planning.
It also conditions the city pattern,
so it is extremely important.
Infrastructure is central to urban planning.
We have transportation infrastructure,
drinking water infrastructure,
several types of infrastructure,
as we have previously noted.
What we'll do today
is to think about factoring
infrastructure in urban planning.
First of all, let's consider
that there are great discrepancies
between cities.
Why is it so?
Because there are discrepancies
between countries.
Some countries, some regions
are wealthier that others.
There are discrepancies between
urban areas and rural areas,
between capital cities and other cities.
Sometimes even within one district
there may be discrepancies.
Which means the approach we'll take
and the way to set up a facility
will vary according to the city,
and there are just as many situations
as there are districts.
To give a definition,
since we like to define
the words we use:
infrastructure refers
to all the facilities
that are useful to keep the city running.
Infrastructure and facilities,
broadly speaking,
are considered together,
as parts of the same thing,
which means we're talking
about roads as well as schools.
Infrastructure and facilities
are often considered separately,
but when it comes to operating a city,
the very definition shows that
it's exactly the same use.
When planning, we need to know
the needs in terms of infrastructure,
both in terms of quantity
and of quality.
Quantity is usually expressed
in square meters
when talking about inhabitants,
or in kilowatts per capita,
when talking about energy or water.
Quality refers to costs,
to the quality of the service provided,
to management, and to the quality
of the product provided.
Let's take water as an example once again:
the quantity and the quality
of the water matter,
but also the quality of the service provided,
meaning is there a 24-hour supply?
There may be good quality water
in large supply but only in the morning.
On the opposite side,
there may be a 24-hour large supply
of a very mediocre quality water.
These parameters need to be assessed.
They are what we call the needs.
What are the needs we are faced with
when planning?
We tend to consider
different levels of service.
We have the type of need,
what is needed
and then level 1, level 2, etc.
These are the response to the need.
When it comes to water,
there is a need of 30 liters
per day and per head,
which is the basic need,
a very small amount,
but let's take it as our base.
Then we define level 1
as providing 30 liters,
a service a bit better
would be providing 60 liters,
and then 90 liters.
The same goes for all other facilities.
Every time, there is the basic need
and how I respond to it
is the level of service I implement.
Then there are the standards
applying to facilities.
So, on one hand, we look at the needs
to determine a certain number
of levels of services,
and at the same time
there are standards for facilities,
with, for example
if we take primary schools
the maximum distance should be 1.5 km,
20 minutes walk,
and one school
for every 8000 inhabitants.
I gathered these standards here and there
and they do not apply everywhere.
The problem is that we give
too much importance to standards
whereas in fact we never managed
to apply these figures.
But you should know that they exist,
even though they're not
the best approach to planning.
However, you must bear in mind
that there must be hydrants,
sports ground,
and maximum distances to comply with.
When talking about infrastructure,
the customers, the inhabitants,
must have access to it
without paying a price that is too high
relatively to their income.
But suppliers must also make a living,
which means that investing in it
should be profitable.
Another phenomenon
is the impact on land prices.
The more infrastructure on a land,
with the limited nuisance it means,
the higher the prices of the land.
This eventually leads to social exclusion,
the poor not having access anymore
to the perimeter of the infrastructure.
The most striking example of this,
and it's an example among many,
we find this in New York, in Lausanne,
but in the case of the school of Rabat
where the people who are willing
to use the tramway
are a special category:
the higher classes will not,
for a question of prestige,
the poor will not,
for lack of financial means,
so it is the middle class who has
the means to use the tramway.
However, the tramway is
in the city center,
and the middle class
cannot live near it anymore,
because it pushed
land prices and rents up.
So those taking the tramway
cannot afford
to live in the areas
where the tramway goes,
all of it pushing the poor further
outside the city.
As a result, Morocco
and the city of Rabat
tried to adapt the fares
to offset this sort of things.
Let's remember this:
infrastructure can lead
to the social exclusion
of a large segment of society.
A brief overview.
We won't go into the details
of every type of infrastructure.
Keep in mind that there is a link
with the price of land, which matters.
The second thing
is that one must determine
a certain number of needs,
even though, unfortunately,
we're not always able
to meet those needs.