Today we'll talk about urban agriculture.
From the start,
there are three questions.
When saying urban agriculture
it involves first and foremost
acknowledging agriculture in cities.
It also involves planning spaces
and managing this activity.
In simple terms,
urban agriculture is working the land
within the boundaries of a city,
or the suburban area, most often.
It means taking advantage
of the gaps, of unused land,
of everything that lends itself
to agriculture.
Every possible resource is used:
land, water,
and afterwards the markets
to sell the products,
and all that happening within a city.
Urban agriculture appears
to be an oxymoron,
two contradictory terms.
Why?
Because, on one hand,
there is agriculture
strongly associated with rural areas,
where agriculture is done,
and on the other hand
the urban world,
which by definition is not rural,
and so should not have agriculture.
The conventional definitions of cities
do not take agriculture into account.
There are also many people
who are strongly opposed
to any agriculture within cities.
Why?
Because these activities
should not take place
within the city boundaries.
Then, there is the opposite point of view,
acknowledging the vital importance
of urban agriculture
for African cities today
and taking it into account
in the planning process.
We'll see that
there are some vexed issues
when planning agriculture
within city boundaries,
one of them being land ownership,
but the social stakes are very high
when it comes to urban agriculture.
Agriculture encompasses
social aspects,
issues of space, of resources,
of risks associated to it.
Let's go through every item
one by one.
First, the social issue.
Extremely important in social terms:
it's a source of income
that is not insignificant
for families that are, most of the time,
the most vulnerable.
There is a question of empowerment
behind this,
at least for some populations:
feeding oneselves,
even being able to sell some
of their produce to make a bit of money.
It does have an impact to be considered
on employment.
The issue of space is extremely important.
Why?
Because agriculture requires space.
Except for Cuba,
where during the Special period
every flower pot was turned into
a micro field planted with something
and every possibility to grow something
in the city was seized,
the usual pattern
is to use suburban lands.
Hence the question of space:
will I choose to build dense housing
or choose a more spread-out pattern
leaving room for agricultural production,
meaning income generation?
This is one thing.
The second thing is
that the denser a city,
the more pressure there is
on land prices.
At some stage, prices are so high
that it doesn't make any sense anymore
to grow a few vegetables,
and it drives people even further.
The issues at stake here
is the opposition between
spread-out cities and compact cities,
the issue of land use,
land speculation,
but also simply of land markets,
which, in most of the countries
and cities we are dealing with,
are open markets,
meaning they fluctuate
according to several factors,
but governments
do not have the power
to regulate land prices,
which poses a real problem
leading to pressure being put
on urban agriculture.
Let's move now
to the issue of resources.
Water is necessary.
Not only is there a need
for a sufficient amount of water,
but this water needs to be good enough, too.
We'll see the potential health problems
associated with urban agriculture.
The main health hazard
is that most of the time
waste water is used.
Waste water are good in that
they fertilize soils,
but there are also a certain number
of germs which are pollutants
and will pass into the plants
and in turn into humans.
So, there is the issue of water quantity
and also of water quality,
with a caveat regarding waste water
which can become a time-bomb.
It's both a fertilizer
and a potential health hazard
in areas with urban agriculture.
These are just a few quick elements
about urban agriculture.
There is much more to say,
but we won't go further today.
I would just want you to bear in mind
that there is an indisputable use,
a social use, to urban agriculture
but that it should be well thought through
depending on the density pattern
you choose,
on the transportation options,
or lack thereof,
and, in the end, on the ability
to retain ownership
over a piece of land in times
of growing land use pressure
in African cities.
In this week's classes
where we start to see how to plan,
we realize there is a certain number
of elements to take into account
and that these elements
don't always go in the same direction.
Which means there will be choices to make,
between the different options,
the different patterns:
spread-out cities with
room for agriculture,
which is very good for climate change
in tropical areas,
but on the other side
in terms of public transportation,
of increased commuting,
of the ozone layer,
since it is what it comes down to,
it should be avoided at all cost.
A dense city pattern is good
but it means there is no room
for urban agriculture,
which eliminates part of the resources.
What it all comes down to
is that there is no panacea.
But one must be aware of the need
to make judgment calls
between those elements
that must be factored in
in our planning of future cities.