In our video, we'll take another look
at climate change.
Another look, since we have already
mentioned this issue.
We'll talk about how this issue
can be planned.
We'll take a certain number of items
that we have mentioned previously.
Climate change summons up
two words:
adapting and mitigating.
Either we adapt to the changes:
the higher the sea level,
the more we'll factor it in in our buildings.
Or we mitigate,
which means we'll fight against
the effects of climate change.
So, either I adapt to rising sea levels,
or I prevent sea levels from rising more.
Then, from the perspective of populations,
there is a capacity for people to adapt,
but also from the perspective
of governments
there are financial, social capacities
to adapt to climate change.
At the other end of the spectrum
is vulnerability, being unable to adapt.
These are the four elements
to keep in mind
when discussing climate change
and urban planning.
What are the effects?
Let's take an example:
there are the effect itself,
the problem it poses,
and the the measures at our disposal
in terms of urban planning.
Example: rising temperatures.
The problem are the heat spots,
everywhere in the city.
the measures to be considered
are planting trees,
the shaping of public spaces,
air currents in the streets, parks.
Another example:
the rising number of insects
as a result of rising temperatures.
These are issues
that are not well-known yet
but that will be more widespread.
What is there to do?
We can fight against insects,
with chemicals,
but there is also the option
to drain certain wetlands.
Mitigating the effect of the change,
in terms of urban planning,
means to make some important decisions.
We mentioned compact cities
that are less energy-consuming
than spread-out cities,
with all the caveats I mentioned
and the several other factors
that need to be monitored,
but let's say that compact cities
would produce less green house gas
and, as a result, urban planning
is a way to mitigate.
On the other side,
the problem of heat spots
is a direct consequence
of the effect of climate change.
There is not much to be done
apart from adapting
with a series of measures
in terms of urban planning.
Let's take an example of adaptation:
I'm going to draw three coastlines.
The water is here,
and we have three options.
If my house is right here,
I can move it,
or ban construction on this land,
thus saying:
for now on, future houses
will be built there
and we'll take this out.
I can also decide that future houses
will be above ground, on stilts,
so that in case of floods
the water will be at stilt level.
Third option:
there is a house here and I build a dyke
so that if the sea level rises,
I won't face the consequential floods.
So, three examples
of possible adaptations.
I don't want to pass judgments,
yet some are more expensive than others
and some are more sustainable than others.
For the millions or billions
of people living along the coast,
throughout the world,
at risk of rising sea levels
and who are very vulnerable indeed,
we need to start thinking
about solutions.
In a previous video,
we talked about the relation
between abundant tropical rains
leading generally
to a spread-out city pattern,
whereas, when in the heart of Sahel,
we'll rather find compact city patterns.
That brings us again to
compact versus spread-out.
Then comes this dual judgment call
we are faced with
between urban patterns
and between adaptation and mitigation.
Will I choose to adapt my situation
to the problem ?
If so, to what extent
can my populations adapt
and how vulnerable are they ?
If I choose not to adapt
but to fight against the effects,
what are the elements
I implement
to truly work against these effects
and substantially reduce
the effects of climate change
in the coming years ?
Today we have these dual questions.
There is, probably,
a dual constraint, too.
In other words, it's either
working on adaptation
or working on mitigation,
because the effects or demands
to work in one direction or the other
are often two totally
opposite directions.
There will be choices to make
over the coming years, drastically so.
We should bear in mind
all the different elements
that we have mentioned
in previous videos,
with the competing needs
for a transportation system,
for urban agriculture,
for climate change issues,
for housing, for infrastructure,
all of which requires choices
based on needs
but also on what we want to develop
in terms of city pattern.
The final decision on the pattern
is yours to make, of course.
What we're doing here
is showing the mechanisms
and means of action
that can be used, or not used,
in order to change
the situation of cities today.