Welcome to the first week of our
new course on planning and design of
sanitation systems and technologies.
My name is Christophe Lüthi.
I am an Urban Infrastructure Planner
and I have been teaching and
and carrying out research for the
Swiss Federal Institute of Aquatic
Science and Technology, in Switzerland
for the last 10 years.
In the next five weeks, we will be
exploring some of the issues and
challenges in urban sanitation.
What makes urban sanitation
so different from rural contexts?
Urban settings feature a number
of distinct characteristics
that need to be considered.
Firstly, different urban contexts
or domains - from modern, inner-city or
planned areas, to the dense, informal
settlements and slum neighborhoods
found in most cities of
Africa, Asia and Latin America.
And finally, the fast
growing city periphery
also called the peri-urban interface.
These different contexts and settings
call for specific solutions when seeking
appropriate and sustainable services.
In this course, we will exploring urban
sanitation systems and services, and
why urban sanitation requires different
approaches, funding mechanisms
and distinct technology solutions.
Let's take a look at a typical
low-income area in an African city.
Some of the challenges found
in neighborhoods like these are
unsanitary environments
lack of space for sanitation facilities,
like the toilet shown here
and informal often unhygienic toilet
emptying, or urban open defecation.
So, what can be done about this situation?
In this course, we will focus on a
key concept of urban sanitation
the Sanitation Value Chain. We will
highlight the different components
and functional groups, as in
the example shown here.
First, the user interface
or pit latrine, in red
the safe storage of human waste
in the septic tank, in orange
followed by the collection and
mechanical emptying of the sludge
through the yellow exhauster trucks.
The safely collected sludge is
then brought to proper treatment
in a sludge-drying bed,
shown here in green;
and finally the reuse of hygienized sludge
in urban agriculture, shown in blue.
The Value Chain allows for a realistic
assessment of a range of sanitation
options and solutions, and its
technical and managerial implications.
Our five-week course will be examining
the issues around the planning and design
of appropriate sanitation
systems and technologies
proper management arrangements and the
and the financial implications involved.
The Sanitation Value Chain shown
here will be our guiding concept.
Let's take a look at the learning goals.
Firstly, we'd like you to get familiar
with urban sanitation planning tools
and approaches, and be able
to analyze case studies
and discuss advantages and disadvantages.
Secondly, we'd like you to know the
existing options of sanitation systems
and technologies, and be able to design a
technical project and analyze proposals.
And lastly, we'd like you to understand
which systems and technologies
are most appropriate
in different contexts.
We'll be looking at different systems
and technologies, the institutions,
and stakeholders that need to be involved.
We'll also be presenting
different projects and case studies
which exemplify different
approaches of urban sanitation.
And, we'll also be looking at
planning frameworks
and approaches, and the design of
sanitation systems in different contexts.
This gives you an
overview of the course contents.
In Week One, we will be
dealing with city sanitation
and looking at a number of
planning frameworks
for example: Sanitation 21, by the
International Water Association.
In Week Two, we'll be dealing
with different sanitation products
the five functional groups
of the sanitation chain
and give you an introduction
to different technologies.
In Week Three, we'll be dealing with
sanitation systems, the second part of
technologies, especially those dealing
with treatment and use or disposal.
In Week Four, we have three case studies
prepared from China, Indonesia and Nepal.
In Week Five, the last week, we will
prepare a talk show with a Q&A session
answering some of the questions that come
up during the course of these five weeks.
And then finally, wrap up and the
final exam, where you'll be able to
evaluate what what you've
learned in the past five weeks.
Here we list the required
reading for this course.
Firstly, the "Compendium of
Sanitation Systems and Technologies"
this is available in English,
in French and in Spanish.
Secondly, "Sanitation 21 - An Integrated
Planning Approach for City Sanitation"
available only in English; and lastly,
"CLUES - Community-led Urban Environmental
Sanitation Planning Framework"
available in English and Spanish.
All three documents are available
for download from this website.
On behalf of my team, I'm looking
forward to the course, and to hearing
your contributions in the forum.
Let's start the course now, with the first
module, about City Sanitation Planning
by Jonathan Parkinson.
Enjoy.