Hi, my name is Jonathan Parkinson
I'm a civil and environmental engineer
with 20 years of consulting
and research experience
working on international
development projects
focusing on urban sanitation.
This module focuses
on city sanitation planning,
which is a key part
to the development process
for city authorities
to make strategic decisions
about where their priorities lie,
what approaches are most appropriate
for that context,
and how best to ensure
that limited resources
are most efficiently utilized.
This module provides an instruction
to urban sanitation planning,
which firstly aims to promote
an understanding
of the existing sanitation situation
in cities in the developing world,
and secondly, to gain an appreciation
of the limitations
of conventional approaches
towards the design of projects
to improve urban sanitation.
First of all,
I'd like to draw our attention
to the existing reality in cities
in the developing world.
As a result of this,
city sanitation planning
is not an easy task.
As I'm sure many of you well know
from your own experience,
cities in the developing world are both
complex and chaotic.
A lot of this is due to the fact that
growth of cities
is unplanned in the first place.
How is it possible
to plan for improvement
for one specific municipal service
such as sanitation,
when the city as a whole is growing
in such an unpredictable manner?
And in addition,
there are frequently high levels
of poverty and social inequality,
which means that
there are many competing demands
for investments and improvements.
These competing demands
combined with a lack of resources
means that sanitation frequently is not
a high political priority,
even though we know that
to improve sanitation
can result in improvements
to public health
promoting social development,
enhancing the attractiveness of cities,
and all this combined together
to strengthen the economy.
In this slide,
and the following two slides,
we can see the scale of urbanization.
Here we can see
the urban population distribution in 1970.
Over the past half a decade,
as a result of
unplanned and uncontrolled growth,
many cities have been characterized
by a large proportion of population
living in informal settlements,
some of which, are illegal.
Here we see the projection
for the urban population in 2025.
Municipal authorities
struggle to deal with
the infrastructure and service
delivery needs,
and the level of growth
makes it very difficult to retrofit,
and urban planning for settlements,
which are already established
and developed in such a chaotic manner,
is very challenging.
Official statistics
show steady improvements
in sanitation coverage
over the past 25 years.
In this slide,
we can see the urban sanitation coverage
in the different regions in the world,
focusing particularly
on developing countries.
According to the statistics
from UNICEF and WHO in 2011,
the average access to improve sanitation
throughout developing countries is 74%.
In Latin America,
the statistics are as high as 87%,
and South-East Asia, 81%.
In Southern Asia,
the value is a lot lower, 64%,
and in Sub-Saharan Africa, only 42%.
But we need to consider that
the overall population in Southern Asia
is much higher, and therefore,
in absolute terms,
the number of people
without access to improved sanitation
in Southern Asia is greatest.
We can also see the level of sharing
of sanitation facilities,
which has great implications on
the quality of sanitation in these cities.
So in Sub-Saharan Africa,
30% of people are using shared toilets,
compared with the average of 17
throughout the developing world.
But these statistics don't necessarily
provide an adequate reflection
of the reality in many cities,
because they only focus on coverage.
The poor quality of sanitation facilities
combined with the lack of servicing
means that a significant proportion
of the population
are likely not to have achieved
the status of improved,
even though these statistics
may indicate that they do.
When the lack of these systems has
major environmental health implications,
affecting public health, productivity,
and socio-economic development.
These statistics that we see previously,
say very little about the arrangements
for waste water
and fecal sludge management,
and many investments
tend to focus more on construction
and rehabilitation of sewerage
and waste water treatment,
which overlooks the actual problem.
In this slide,
showing the fecal waste flows
from Maputo in Mozambique,
we can see that,
in fact, only 24% of the waste is related
to toilets discharging into sewerage,
whereas, a much greater proportion
is in fact related
to onsite sanitation facilities.
And here, we're talking about
pit latrines and septic tanks.
Only recently has the extent
of the problem started to be recognized,
and projects been designed
to respond to this situation.
In the next few slides,
we see examples of urban sanitation
that are common in cities
in the developing world.
In this photograph,
we see a basic pit latrine
where hygienic conditions are compromised
by poor quality design and construction,
overuse by too much sharing,
and a lack of handwashing facilities.
Although this latrine provides
a better sanitation than open defecation,
facilities like this are not considered
to provide adequate sanitation.
Thinking more widely in the public domain,
flows of untreated black water
from pits and tanks
flow into open channels or drains,
and this is often mixed with
solid waste and urban runoff.
This cocktail of waste results
in heightened disease transmission
in low income communities.
And then looking more widely in the city,
although more affluent households
are likely to be able to afford
to pay for a system or service
to collect waste water or fecal sludge,
and they can pay a private company
to take this waste away,
this waste is often discharged,
untreated into the environment,
due to lack of facilities.
In the previous slides,
we saw that status of urban sanitation,
and there have been responses
to deal with this problem,
but often that we see too much focus
on construction of sewerage
and waste water treatment systems,
whereas the needs and requirements
of people living in low-income communities
are overlooked.
Conventional responses to the problem
also tend to overlook the important role
played by the informal sector,
who are involved with various forms
of sanitation service delivery,
and also, the importance of operation
and maintenance.
The imbalance of supply and demand
for improved services
combined with the inability
of urban authorities
to provide sanitation services
has resulted in a sanitation crisis
in many towns and cities,
particularly unplanned, informal,
and low-income settlements.
In the next part of this module,
I will be talking about common elements
for good sanitation planning,
focusing on delivery
of sanitation services.
In the previous part of the presentation,
we saw how traditional responses
to urban sanitation challenges
have tended to focus more upon
solving urban sanitation problems
by the insulation of large-scale,
downstream infrastructure
and sewerage systems,
and the need for more focus
on onsite sanitation.
More recently, a new generation
of sanitation planning has emerged,
with examples from Indonesia,
India, and Brazil,
where three national sanitation programs
have been initiated,
to develop city sanitation plans
linked to funding and investment,
standardized planning processes,
and capacity building,
and technical support.
Based upon these experiences,
a set of common elements
for good sanitation planning have emerged,
one of these being
responding to expectations
for sanitation service improvement,
otherwise known as demand.
Another one being, planning for inclusion
and equitable sanitation services,
focusing on the needs
of vulnerable groups and the urban poor.
A third one being, ensuring that services
are affordable and financially viable.
There's no point making investments
in urban infrastructure
if these systems cannot be
maintained financially.
The fourth common element
for good sanitation planning
is focusing on behavioral change.
This includes behavior at all levels,
from the household
up to the city authorities,
change management
down to hygiene behavior,
are all key elements
of good sanitation planning.
And the final one, a key one,
is engaging with stakeholders.
It's clear, therefore,
that technology is only a means
to deliver services,
and meet customer needs.
It's about people, and not pipes.
In the urban sanitation planning process,
there is a need to take
onboard the interests
from a range of different stakeholders.
From the household domain,
to the community, and their interests,
up to the local authority
or municipality,
with their interests at city level.
And above that, there will be ministries,
perhaps the ministry of the environment,
with their main interest
on protecting and preserving
the quality of the environment.
What's clear is the need to focus on
delivering sanitation services
to customers that is acceptable,
appropriate, and affordable.
Technology is a means to an end.
But it is not the way in which
customers judge services.
What the technology does
is more important.
For sustainability, service delivery
must be customer orientated,
and services developed in line
with customer affordability
and willingness to pay.
City sanitation plans must focus on
supply meeting demand, i.e., the market.
Both suppliers and customers
may need access to credit
to be able to make investments
for improved sanitation.
Urban sanitation plans provide
a set of service delivery models
for different parts of the city,
including elements of
infrastructure development,
finance and cost recovery,
management and regulation.
In the next presentation,
we will see how a systematic approach
towards planning
can support the development
of a comprehensive and equitable
city sanitation plan.