Hi. Welcome back to the second part of
the lecture in Sanitation Planning Module,
focusing on the development of strategies
for city-wide sanitation improvement.
This follows on from the previous model,
which provided an introduction
to issues related to the development
of sustainable sanitation services
and the influences that these have on
urban sanitation planning.
We focus here on a more detailed
understanding of some of
the key principles of good planning,
and introduce some tools to support
the development of city-wide
sanitation plans
linking local level
with city level initiatives.
Sanitation21 is a document produced by
the International Water Association
in partnership with Eawag and Giz.
Sanitation21 presents a framework
for city sanitation planning
based on international best practice,
where planning has been key
to achieving improvements in
urban sanitation.
It sets out key principles and process
guidelines to help city sanitation
stakeholders develop appropriate
and affordable solutions to
sanitation problems, taking into account
technology issues,
management arrangements, institutional
challenges, and demand for improvement
from different stakeholders.
The Sanitation21 planning process
is presented around the following
five stages: firstly, building
institutional commitment
and partnership for planning.
Secondly, understanding the existing
context and defining priorities.
Stage 3 involves developing strategies
for sanitation system improvement,
this focusing very much on
the technological side.
Stage 4 involves developing models
for service delivery, management
arrangements, financing mechanisms.
And stage 5 involves preparing
for implementation.
One of the inherent challenges
with sanitation planning and subsequent
implementation of city plans is that they
require a range of institutions
and organizations to work together.
Consequently, the success of sanitation
planning activity will be strongly
influenced by the extent of collaboration
between the local authorities, utilities
and other stakeholders involved
in the provision or regulation
of sanitation services.
Planning is essentially about responding
to real needs and making informed
decisions about investments for sanitation
improvements, involving the prudent use
of resources to meet
recognized priorities.
Successful sanitation planning activities
need to be based on a sound understanding
of the existing situation, and respond
to demands for an improved sanitation
service at different levels.
Understanding the existing
context is critical.
In relation to technical considerations,
the following tools are recommended
as ways to support the sanitation
planning process.
One of the most essential ones,
and perhaps the most basic one,
is a process of sanitation system mapping,
which simply means mapping the existing
sanitation coverage and location
of facilities for collection and treatment
of waste.
Another tool, building on this,
involves supply-demand analysis.
So this looks in more detail at those
systems and assessing their capacity
in relation to the amount of waste
that is produced.
This provides a basis for identifying
what parts of the system are overloaded
and what parts of the system have capacity.
Another tool is the environmental health
risk assessment methodology.
This looks at sanitation interventions
and uses risk assessment to assess
which communities are most prone
to sanitation related risks, and this
can help to target investments
for these areas.
Additional tools can be used for financial
and economic analysis.
Sanitation market assessment
is increasingly used to look at
sanitation service providers and their
services in relation to demand
from different customers, dividing
customers into a range of different
segments and looking at how different
service providers meet their needs.
A key part of this is financial analysis,
looking at different options in relation
to the existing sanitation services,
the cost of them, and the affordability
of services.
In this diagram we see the varied nature
of settlements and cities, highlighting
that there is a need for a range
of sanitation service models
appropriate for different physical
and socio-economic contexts.
The characteristics of low income
settlements in informal and peri-urban
areas means that they are intrinsically
more difficult to serve, and as a result
conventional service delivery models
are often not viable.
This may be due to physical constraints,
such as low-lying ground, steep slopes,
or densely packed housing with very poor
access via narrow and irregular pathways.
In addition, there are frequently social
issues compounded by poverty, which means
that working in these areas requires a
different approach from other parts
of the city.
These areas are frequently left out of the
mainstream planning process and are likely
to be areas where there is a specific need
to work more closely with local
communities to develop sanitation
solutions appropriate and affordable
to their needs.
We will focus more closely on the
community-led urban environmental
sanitation approach in the next module
which is designed specifically
for this purpose.
In cities throughout the developing world,
due to the unplanned growth,
space is often at a premium.
Existing sites for waste disposal
are already heavily overloaded
and traffic congestion means that sites
for sludge disposal may be only available
at night.
Therefore the availability of space may be
a key determining factor on how
the sanitation system can be designed
for a particular city.
And indeed, no one type of technology
will be appropriate for all areas of the
city, and the outcome from the
application of the Sanitation21
planning approach is likely to lead toward
recommendations that on-site sanitation
is appropriate for some areas, whereas
decentralized, semi-centralized,
or centralized sewage
will be appropriate for other areas.
A financial comparison of different
technologies is a very important part
of the planning process.
If we consider different types of
sanitation system, each one will have
different capital investment requirements,
different cost for operation and routine
maintenance, and other costs associated
with capital maintenance which is involved
with larger scale refurbishment costs.
If we feed in this information to a
financial analysis on a life cycle
assessment we can compare these
different options and this as well as
some of the other aspects such as
availability of land may be the key
factors which determine what sanitation
system is most appropriate in different
situations.
The financial comparison can identify the
most cost effective solution and we can
use this analysis to identify affordable
solutions for different communities.
And also, it may highlight a need
for subsidy.
Sources of funding for capital investments
can come from many sides.
National and provincial funding is one
source, often supported by
international finance, development banks,
development agencies, and international
NGOs.
This funding can also be used to support
municipal development budgets.
In addition to this, for the local level
service provision and for household
facilities we also need to take into
consideration the funding from private
sector and from households and
communities themselves.
Each of these different service
arrangements can utilize a different
management option.
At the household level small-scale service
providers may be the most appropriate
option for de-sludging pits and taking
waste away.
But at the neighborhood level, private
companies, CBOs and NGOs may be involved
in different ways in providing services
and also collecting money
and regulating the service providers;
whereas at the city level utility,
public or private or a delegated
management arrangement
to a private company may be considered
to be the best option.
In all of these levels often
the interrelationships between
these service providers is what's critical
for maintaining and sustaining
adequate level of sanitation.
There is usually only one way in which
a system and its associated management
arrangement will work, but unfortunately
there are many ways in which it
may go wrong.
Therefore, in the planning process
we need to consider
some of the broader social, political
and economic processes.
Here we see a diagram of the enabling
environment which shows
the various facets that determine the nature
of sanitation investment and sanitation
service provision.
The city sanitation planning process is
very much influenced by national policy
and strategy, but it also has a strong
interface as we've seen with local level
planning activities.
Some of the city
sanitation planning will result in
proposals for municipal infrastructure
which can go directly towards proposals
for design and construction,
implementation of larger scale systems.
But clearly we see a need for local level
planning, where there is a need to engage
with communities and design systems which
are most appropriate for their needs.
In the next module my colleague
[Christoff Luty] will focus closely
on the local level planning part of the
sanitation planning process.
I thank you very much for your attention.