In this module, and the next one,
I will present the main elements
and structure of the CLUES approach.
The CLUES guidelines shown here
were published in 2011,
together with the Collaborative
Council in Geneva
and UN-HABITAT in Nairobi.
They are available for download
from different sites.
Check out the resource section
of our course [area] site.
At its core, CLUES is a pretty
straightforward planning process
that involves seven distinct steps
and three cross-cutting issues.
Let's take a look first
at the seven planning steps.
In the following, I will shortly go
through the six planning steps of CLUES.
Step one begins with process ignition
and demand creation.
This is where the community is mobilized
and demand is created
through a set of different tools.
Step two is the official launch
of the planning process,
usually in a bigger workshop.
Step three entails the detailed assessment
of the current situation,
usually put together in a report.
Step four, the prioritization
of the community problems
and validation.
This can be done
in either focus group discussions
or in a series of workshops,
followed then by step five,
the identification of service options.
This includes issues like costs,
cost recovery, but also technical options
and socio-economic
and sociocultural issues.
This can be done in usually
one or two workshops
that pulls together both experts
and community representatives.
Step six includes the development
of an action plan,
the action plan also put together
in a report format.
And then, finally, step seven,
which follows after the six planning steps:
the implementation of the action plan.
This can be kicked off, for example,
with a final workshop.
There are also three cross-cutting tasks.
The first one, and important one,
exposure and communication.
This is the constant exposure
of the community
and its representatives
to examples of good practice,
to other facilities and pilots
that have been built.
Capacity development.
The training and development
of skills at all levels,
not only at a community level,
but also a local authority level.
And then, lastly, the monitoring
and evaluation of the plan
and the assessment of the progress
of the planning approach.
This is separate
from the monitoring evaluation
of the implementation, which needs
its own monitoring plan.
A key concern of CLUES
is about clarifying the roles
and responsibilities
of the different stakeholders involved.
In most countries, this means
a mix of civic, or .org,
public, .gov, and private, .com--
stakeholders that all have a role to play
and need for better arrangements
for effective service delivery.
In the case shown here, this could be
NGO, or CBOs involved,
.gov, a utility working at citywide scale,
and lastly, .com, the private sector,
which also has an important role to play
in service delivery.
CLUES is not a theoretical approach.
It's been successfully tested
in quite a number of countries,
and claim to be the only
generic planning framework
that has delivered in urban
and peri-urban communities.
In the next presentation,
we are going to explain
the seven planning steps,
and provide some examples
in how it's been done in Asia and Africa.