This last module on local level planning
will introduce you to the basic
planning steps to the CLUES approach.
The seven steps are fairly straightforward
planning steps
that reflect common sense in planning
for the unplanned areas,
taking into account
multi-stakeholder setups
and weak institutional settings.
At the same time,
the generic planning steps
are flexible, and allow adaptation
and alteration
according to the individual settings.
The seven planning steps
are accompanied by 30 tools.
The 30 tools help the individuals
planning for the seven steps
and allow adaptation
to individual contexts.
Let's look at the seven steps in detail.
Step One begins with process ignition
and demand creation.
This is all about igniting
the community planning process,
sensitizing the community
about environmental sanitation
and hygiene issues, creating good momentum
and a basis for community participation,
conducting a first community meeting
and reaching an agreement on joint action
and then finally creating
a community task force
which can carry forward the planning
process and act as an interface
between the community
and other stakeholders.
A nice example is shown here,
from Nala in Nepal,
where the entire community
was brought together during
a one day sanitation exhibition,
or sanitation bazaar,
carried out here in 2009.
Also involved: national NGOs,
local initiatives,
community based organizations
working in the areas
of wash, water, sanitation and hygiene.
Step Two is about launching
the planning process.
This is the initial planning
and consultative workshop
where a common understanding about
the complexity of environmental sanitation
in the intervention area is developed.
This is usually done by conducting
a launching workshop that
is inclusive, well-structured
and creates public attention.
The outcomes of this workshop
are usually a protocol agreement,
agreement on which areas should
be planned for, and an agreement on
the overall planning methodology
and process.
Again, an example from Nala, Nepal,
where the entire community was invited
for the launch of the planning.
Step Three is then about
a detailed assessment
of the current status.
The assessment is done
in a participatory way
and includes both external
as well as internal community knowledge.
Here, understanding is developed
about the physical and social economic
environment of the intervention area.
Step Three involves community
and other key stakeholders
to gather and assess information.
The main output could include
stakeholder mapping, baseline data
from an interview, or thorough assessment
of the enabling environment
and current levels of service provision.
The outcomes of Step Three
are then gathered and summarized
in an assessment report.
A number of tools can be used,
from spatial maps, GIS maps, interviews,
to focus group discussions.
Prioritization and validation
is the Fourth Step.
This is all about reporting the outcomes
from Step Three of the assessment report
to the community and revising
the findings of the assessment.
And secondly, it's also about deciding
which services should be given priority.
This is usually done in a community
workshop to validate the priorities.
In some areas, this may be
storm water drainage
in others, the bad state
of environmental sanitation
and fecal sludge management
and in a third it may be the bad
or deficient water provision in an area.
Priority workshops don't necessarily need
to be carried out at a central location
they can be done in a subward
or street location like the one shown here
where people from a given area
of the neighborhood
come together to discuss the priorities.
Step Five is then building
on Steps Three and Four
and identifying the service options.
This is about identifying
environmental sanitation options
that are feasible
for the intervention area
and based on an informed
choice approach.
This includes issues
like technical feasibility,
and institutional, financial
and social implications.
The main outcome: an agreement on one
or two environmental sanitation systems
that should be studied in greater detail.
The agreement is reached by the community
together with local authority or utility.
Step Five is usually done
in a set of workshops.
This can be an expert workshop,
for example, the one shown here
on the right, from Vientiane in Laos,
where different feasible
sanitation solutions are being discussed.
Or it can also be done together
with communities at a larger scale.
This of course needs a bit more
time and preparation.
The compendium of sanitation systems
and technologies on the left
is a guiding document
that helps structure this planning step.
Important is the issue of affordability
of the options, especially
the capital expenditure or CAPEX.
On the table here,
we see the affordability
of different toilets in East Africa.
Four different income segments,
starting with the cheapest option,
the improvement of existing pit latrines
for example, the adding of a new door
that can be locked or the addition
of a concrete or plastic slab.
This usually costs around $90 to $100.
Next up the cost ladder
is a shared VIP latrine
with a stone superstructure
and a concrete slab shared
by two households, anything between $200
and $250 depending on country and location
And then, further up the ladder,
the private VIP latrine,
privately owned by one household
with stone superstructure and lined pit.
This will cost anywhere between $400
and $500 for the East African region.
And then, the last
and most expensive option,
the household pour flush toilet that
is connected to a simplified sewer network
starting at around $500 upwards.
These kind of prices and costs
should be compared
and also discussed with experts
as well as with the community.
Finally, Step Six is the development
of an action plan.
Here, a realistic and implementable
action plan is produced.
The main output is an action plan
that is costed and funded,
timed, and allows output based targets.
Very important, every action plan
for a given area must include operation
and maintenance management plan
to ensure the correct functioning
and sustainability
of the sanitation system and services.
Here the example of the plan
for Nala from 2011.
And then finally the implementation
of the action plan.
This includes incremental implementation
steps for different given situations.
On the left, the example
from Curridabat in Costa Rica
shows storm water drainage being put into
a low-income community in Curridabat.
In the middle, the connection
of pour flush toilets
to a communal septic tank,
and on the right the construction
of school toilets for primary school
in a low income area of Dodoma, Tanzania.
A key output of Step Seven
can be the production of catalogs
that offer choice and options
for different price ranges
and are combined with micro credit
or revolving funds for sanitation.
These have been shown to work well
in a number of countries around the world
and come up with doable
and implementable solutions.
So far CLUES has been tested and validated
or is being validated,
in a number of countries around the world,
in Asia, Africa and Latin America.
Summing up the main
CLUES advantages:
CLUES offers flexibility
and steps and tools
that can be tailored to a particular
local culture and capacity level.
It is a demand-led approach
that underlines the importance
of community demand for the project.
But, the community priorities
are established and responded to
during the process itself.
And third, CLUES takes
community participation seriously
and the community is significantly
involved in decision making and has
a high degree of control over
project outcomes and design decisions.
Technology choice. CLUES provides
guidance in decision making
regarding waste water management
and sanitation facilities.
O & M implications are also important.
It incorporates operation and maintenance
considerations and the long-term costs
for operating new facilities and services.
And then finally, communication,
the importance of culturally appropriate
forms of communication between
community process leaders,
local government, and ensuring the
transparency of the process.
This module gave you an in-depth view
of the CLUES planning steps.
We will be featuring an applied case study
from Nepal in Week Four of this course
to show you how CLUES was used
in a small town context.
Thanks for listening and we look forward
to hearing from you next week.