In this first week of the course,
we've learned about some main challenges
in urban sanitation,
and provided an introduction
to two distinct, but similar,
planning frameworks.
Both approaches recognize
the complex institutional realities
of urban areas,
bringing together
the different stakeholders
at different levels.
At the household domain,
the importance
of households, individual households,
for the choice of sanitation technology.
At the neighborhood level,
the importance
of the different actors
involved in providing
affordable sanitation services.
At the municipal or citywide domain,
the different actors
providing citywide services.
And, finally, at the regional,
or watershed domain,
the actors involved in dealing with
issues that impact
environments beyond the city level.
In this week, we've talked about
two urban sanitation planning frameworks:
Sanitation 21, introduced
by Jonathan Parkinson,
and the CLUES community-led
urban environmental sanitation
planning approach, developed
by [Eawag] with UN-HABITAT and WSCC.
Sanitation 21 provides
five planning stages.
First, defining the institutional
commitment for service delivery.
Second, understanding
the existing context and capacities.
The third stage assesses
different strategies
for the system improvement
and the costs that these imply.
The fourth stage then formulates
the management arrangements
and cost recovery mechanisms.
Lastly, how to prepare for implementation,
including institutional agreements
and planned dissemination.
We've pointed out the importance
of financial comparison
of options in Sanitation 21,
and the financial data that needs
to be brought together
in terms of capital investment,
operation and routine maintenance,
and capital maintenance
to conduct a proper financial analysis
and life cycle assessment
for the selection of affordable solutions.
CLUES, at the local level,
has seven planning steps,
beginning with process ignition,
and triggering of the community,
and ending with step seven,
implementation of improved services.
We've also pointed out the importance
of stakeholder participation
in the CLUES approach,
bringing together
the different stakeholders
during the different steps
of a planning process.
We've shown the importance
of enabling environments.
The government support needed,
the existing legal
and regulatory frameworks,
the institutional arrangements
between different actors
at different levels,
the skills and capacities needed,
the financial arrangements,
including issues like
microfinance tools and vehicles,
and, finally, the socio-cultural
acceptance of different solutions sought.
We will now ask you to wrap
your heads around a first exercise
on contextualizing urban sanitation.
We'll provide you with a typical image
of a poor, [informal settlement]
in West Africa and ask you
to answer three questions.
Good luck.