Before
we dive into quantitative phase
analysis,
we should first introduce the main
method
to use for this purpose,
"The Rietveld Method". This
lecture describes the basic
principles
of the method,
and builds further on the insights
into
x-ray part of the fraction that has
been
treated in Lecture Two.
The Rietveld Method was
originally developed by Hugo
Rietveld
in the late 60s.
This was done for a refinement
of the crystal structure using
nutrient powder
diffraction, only later
in the 70s,
it was extended to X-rays
and even later
like in the 80s,
it was eventually extended to
quantitative
phase analysis.
For cement analysis,
the first application of the
Rietveld method date back to the
early 90s.
The Rietveld method now finds its
use
in a wide variety of areas
as a characterization technique for
crystallite
solutes.
Next to it's use in quantitative
phase analysis,
the method can be used to derive
or refined crystal structures for
pure powder samples.
Also, crystallite size
and strain can be determined through
peak shape analysis.
In fact,
many key properties of solid
systems can be studied by Rietveld
analysis. Kinetic studies
for instance of reactions
or curing during cement hydration
or Polymorph transitions,
Thermal expansion,
behavior of ceramics In-situ
chemistry,
and Phase transitions can be
analyzed
easily using
the Rietveld methods. To do this,
the Rietveld method minimizes
the difference between observed
and calculated patterns at
each data point
high, in the diffraction pattern
using
the least squares approach.
Here are some of the statistically
weighted,
squared differences between the
observed,
and calculated intensities
is minimized over the whole pattern.
The calculated pattern takes into
account
crystal structure information,
phase concentrations,
and other sample characteristics
such as micro micro texture.
But also diffraction optics an
instrument
dependent parameters such as
X-ray source etc.
are being taken into account when
calculating
the X-ray part of the diffraction
pattern.
The calculated intensity
at a given data point in the
diffraction
scan is obtained as the
sum of the contribution of the
background
and all neighboring
reflections B of all 5
of phases J in
your sample.
This is also expressed in
the mother recreation of the
Rietveld method
shown here.
Here, one can see that as
of 'J' is the scale factor,
out 'P',
is a Lorentz polarization factor,
'F' is a structure factor,
'G' is the peak shape
function,
'A' the x-ray absorbtance
proficient,
and 'P' the preferred orientation
correction.
In lecture two,
we have treated each of these
factors
in more detail,
and we have explained what is the
physical
basis of these factors.
Now before we go into a
demonstration
and practice it is worthwhile to
reflect on what we really can
call a good fit,
and how we can actually evaluate
this.
This is needed because we want to
check that we are
going to in the right way
when doing the fitting,
and there is also any
hint to be able to compare between
different measures of goodness of
fit,
and maybe we also want to do this,
to be able to do this independent of
the quality
of the data.
To this purpose,
the most direct way of checking if a
fit
is good or going the right way is
by actual visual inspecting.
All this is by any means the most
powerful and direct wave evaluation,
it is also the most subjective
way.
What is for instance good in one
student's eyes,
may not be so for his supervisor.
Numerically access the fitting,
several numerical parameters,
or factor, or initials are
available.
Depending on the material itself,
the data quality,
and the purpose of the analysis,
one may prefer to use residual,
or R-factors,
or the chi
or goodness of fit indicator,
or for instance the Durbin-Watson
statistic.
Sometimes,
a very good fit is obtained
by allowing very large shifts
in crystal graphic parameters
such as unit cell parameters,
or increase of structure refinements
atomic positions.
In these cases,
it is good practice to
always check whether the
obtained crystal structure is
chemically
reasonable.
For instance,
it is known from a great many
of experimental data
and from chemical bond theory,
that a tetrahedral silicon
oxygen bonds should have a length
of about 1.6 angstroms.
Very large deviations for instance
1.8 angstroms
are therefore quite suspicious
and would require further
analysis and verification.
This slide shows the mathematical
expressions
of some of the numerical agreement
factors.
The pattern residual
and the weight of pattern residual
describe the
agreement between the observed
and calculated pattern at each
data point in the profile.
The residual pattern is therefore
much
affected by the signal to noise
ratio of the background noise level.
The residual related pattern
therefore accords a bit more weight
to
the actual signal
or the peaks to mitigate the
patterns
but still it is much influenced by
the
quality of the data.
To remove this patterns entirely one
can
use the goodness-of-fit indicator
that
normalizes the weight of pattern
residual
by an expect residual.
This expected residual
is an inlet that is calculated
for a best achievable
data fit of the data.
While the pattern
residual and the weighted pattern
residual
should reduce as much as possible
during the fitting,
the goodness-of-fit indicator should
obviously converge to a ratio of
one.
On the other hand,
that's the Durbin-Watson statistics,
and this is applied to residuals of
least scrags
analysis to detect any
waves of auto correlation between
the data.
As the value is closer to two,
than there are no indications of
autocorrelation.
If they're actually indications of
autocorrelation,
then the measures to increase the
signal to noise
ratio or resolution should actually
be
considered.
Let's have a look at how Rietveld
fitting operates in practice.
We will show you some snapshots
of a Rietveld refinement over a
simple
two phrase material consisting of
Alite
and Rutile.
To continue with the Rietveld method
We should have already done the
identification.
With the results from the
identification the
related to crystallographer
information
file,
namely the 'C file' must
be formed to perform the root for
the analysis.
The file can be found in the
commercial
database such as
Inorganic Crystal Structured
Database (the ICSD),
or the open database such as
Crystallography Open Database,
(the COD).
First,
create a new file,
then insert the data.
According to the identification we
did before,
mixture is made of Calcite
and Quartz.
Firstly, we import the structures.
Let's change the name Calcite
and then Quartz.
For each phase the skill factor,
units cell and profile should
be defined.
Constraints of one percentage of
rivalries
on the unit cell would applied
to secure refinements.
Another
constraint for the profile
W of 0.0001
to 0.2
was applied.
The application of constraints
to the refined parameters will
improve
the stability of the overall
refinement.
When especially we are
analyzing complex
sample, such as the hybrid cement,
do the same settings for
Quartz phase,
follow global parameters,
and specimen displacement,
background functions are refined.
For the background functions,
where the polynomial functions,
together with a flat background,
1/x together with
a fifth five,
together with a five co-efficient.
We use a manual mode for refinement,
as we set the parameters manually.
After all the parameters are set,
the refinement can be executed.
Open the additional graphics
for the difference plot
to visually check the fitting.
Change XY to square
roots to show more details on a
small piece.
You can evaluate the fitting by
checking
the equipment indices.
Name these R profile,
weighted R profile
and the goodness-of-fit.
The aim of the refinement is to
decrease
the rigidity of the fitting,
that's the value for R profile
and weighted R profile should
be lower better.
Typically, five to 15
percentage for the weighted R
profile is
acceptable for most of the cases.
Theoretically,
the goodness-of-fit should be one.
Practically, a value of one to five
can be acceptable depending on the
case.
Now the goodness-of-feet is 5.9
and the weighted R profile is
16.6.
If you check the residual plot,
the fitting at around 27
and 13 degrees is not
too good,
and this can be because of the
preferred
orientation.
If you locate a mouse on the peak
which
is not well fitted,
the crystal of plane must
be appear here along
with the name of the phase.
Here if it is a 104 plane for
Calcite.
To setup peripheral direction,
you can click on the Calcite
the refinement control,
then in Optic inspector
for calcite you will find them,
you will find the item called
'Preferred Orientation'.
The March-Dollase
model is recommended.
Specify the Direction h, k, l of the
plain for the preferred orientation.
After setting the direction tick
the refine for the march-dollase
factor.
Similarly,
too similar to the other
perimeter we put a limit for the
refinement of 0.7
to 1.
The value 1 means there is no any
preferred orientation,
the smaller the value is
the higher the preferred
orientation.
In most of the cases 0.07
should be enough,
if value is too small which
means a sampling is not really
done, a reputation of the XRD
data collection base more attention
on reducing the preferred
orientation
is recommended.
By refining, the fitting of the peak
is
much improved,
during a same on the
preferred orientation
of quartz.
The plain of the quartz
is 10-1,
and then refine.
There is some improvement for
goodness-of-fit
and then weighted R profile.
As you can see,
there are still some misfitting from
the
peaks of calcite
and quartz.
For calcite and quartz,
binary mixture to achieve better
fitting, more profile perimeters
needed
to be used.
Let's try all the profile
parameters for quartz,
and calcite.
Refinement mean the fittings is much
improved by using more profile
parameters,
and the calculated weight percentage
for the calcite and quartz are
getting closer
to the weight amount.
Save the HPF file,
press a button
with percentages,
you will have the quantitative
data output in TSD file,
in a default,
highscore class folder,
or simply look down the results from
the graphic window.
This is our X-ray diffraction scam.
Measure it on a conventional lab
Rietveld method, using copper K
alpha radiation.
We can see a multitude of peaks,
some single,
others overlapping.
In a first try,
a background function is fitted,
and the first residual is calculated
as you can see below the graph.
Obviously, this residual is still
very
high because we have not fitted any
of the red peaks.
In a second step,
we introduce rutile into the
fitting procedure.
Now you can see that only the
intensities
on the peaks of the rutile are being
fitted,
and this is done by adapting
the scale factor.
You can see that the
residual has decreased.
Then we will introduce
Alite as free clinic free
cals silicates into
the refinements.
Again you can see that only the
intensities
of the Alite are fitted,
and the
agreement index drops again,
but you can clearly see that there
is
still a visual mismatch of some
of the Alite peak.
We then allow the Alite
and Rutile lattice parameters
to be refined together.
Together
with the skill factors of each
as well.
Now,
we clearly see that the
weighted pattern residual drops
drastically
and that there is already quite a
good fit
when looking at
the residual.
This Residual curve
in gray below
the diffraction scan,
help us spot slight
meet mismatches
and see where there's some
deviations
from the new.
Now we also refined the next step,
the peak width for both Alite
and Rutile.
Again you can see that this
significantly
improves a fitting both in the
residual as
well as in the visual
appearance.
So the fine tuning of the Rietveld
refine
can now be done.
For instance, by adding the
displacement factor from the later
data. Then finally
we can include a preferred
orientation correction
for the Alite phase to achieve our
final fitting
results.
One can now see that the fitting is
really
nice and it's a residual curve is
quite flat.
In case of this sample,
we don't actually had about
27 percent of Rutile
and about 73
percent of citri X
the clinics citri x in
this mix.
This example shows that the
parameters
that we vary in quantitative phase
analysis
are first so-called global
parameters
such as the background
and a sample displacement
correction.
And then second,
phase specific parameters,
such as scale factors
that will fit to the observed beacon
intensities,
units out parameters that
will fit to the peak positions,
and peak profile functions that
will fit to the shape of the peak.
The use of intensity corrections
such
as preferred orientation functions
may be necessary
but will be included later in the
refinement
always.
The refinement of
other crystal structure parameter
such
as the atomic positions,
sites occupancies
are atomic displacement parameters
is not recommendable for complex
mixtures of phases such as cements.
This is because this may lead to
wrong results
due to strong correlations
and parameter variations
during the fitting
as the ratio between variables
and in the bond data strongly
decreases,
and the minimization problem
gets
under constraint.