This lecture concludes the course by
diving into quantitative phase
analysis
of cement.
First, the standard quantification
approach in the Reitveld method
is extended to what samples that
contain the amorphous material.
This we need because many
cements contain and then the
crystalline
phase
or an amorphous phase,
then we give a number of examples
that involve an hydrazine hydrating
cements along
with some practical guidelines in
the end.
It is very helpful to also have a
look
at a separate demonstration videos
in which you can follow such
analysis
step by step.
Let's go back to the intensity
question for
powdered diffraction experiments.
The scale factor is obtained in the
refinement,
scale linearly
with the phase volume fraction.
So if you assume that
the sum of crystalline phases is 100
percent then the phase weight
fraction can be calculated by
normalizing
the product of the scale factor
with Z the
number of formula units per unit
cell and the mass
per formula unit
and V the unit cell volume,
over all the sum of these products
over
all crystalline phases.
It should be noted that only
relative proportions of weight
fractions can be obtained if the
sample
contains amorphous phases,
or of any additional crystalline
phases
were not included into the Rietveld
refinements.
This approximation is often used in
quantitative
phase analysis of Portland cement
or Clinker,
one would expect only
small or negligible levels
of amorphous face.
However,
this assumption is not valid for
cements containing
SCMs which are mostly amorphous,
for instance as you can see on the
right hand side.
Different methods were developed
to take into account the presence of
nano crystalline or amorphous
phases,
presence of these amorphous phases
can be quite
easily seen in the figure on the
right
where you can see the broad amp.
which is indicative for
amorphous phase.
There are several ways to deal
with amorphous content,
here we will consider three
different
approaches.
The first one is to add a known
amount of internal standard into
the sample, this is called the
internal standard approach.
The second one is the external of
standard
approach in which the quantification
results are rescaled
based on a comparison to a
separately
measured monitor sample,
the external standard.
And then finally, the third method
that will be
introduce is the PONKCS method,
which stands for partially
or non known crystal structure
method.
This method requires separate
calibration
of the amorphous phase,
but on the other hand it enables
the quantification of different
amorphous phases more than one
in the same sample.
The most common approach is the
internal
standard approach.
In fact, in this method it is
required to do spike
the sample with a known weight
fraction,
known amount of a crystalline
standards.
Given expression
shown here on the top can be
used to calculate the absolute phase
weight fractions from
the scale factors. The
index s here identifies
standards,
Ws corresponds
to the Crystallinity
or the purity of internal standard
itself,
and fs to do
weight fraction of the standard that
was
added to the sample.
Alternatively, the weight fractions
can be calculated using the equation
below,
where the apparent weight
fraction of the internal standard
can
then be for instance
higher than the weight of the
amount,
for instance let's say 25 percent
when we added 20 percent
of Rutile,
and this indicates the presence of
amorphous or unidentified
crystalline material.
Or the second case
is that it can be equal,
so 20 percent for 20 percent
to the weighted amount,
and this indicates that there is no
or very little
amorphous or unidentified materials.
And then finding of the third case
is that there is
a lower amount
of standard quantified
than the amount that was weighted,
and this is of course
an indication that there was some
problem
in the experiment
or in the data analysis procedure.
The total weight fraction of all
amorphous
and or
unidentified components can
be calculated as a difference
between
the sum of all the crystalline
components
and one. So the
sum of all the crystalline
components
and the difference
with 100 percent is the
amorphous phase friction.
The internal standard method
requires appropriate
sample preparation.
For instance,
it is very important to
homogeneously
mix the standard into the sample.
If the sample
and standard are grounded together,
then one should take care
that there is no over-grinding of
the sample
by co grinding
with a harder standard material.
Over-grinding for instance
would lead to pig broadening,
pot broadening and partial
amorphisation creation of amorphous
content
by destroying softer phases
by the harder ones.
Especially hydrated phase in the
cement
base are vulnerable to this kind
of decomposition.
Not only by grinding
but also by dehydration in
combination
one make would really change
the hydrate assemblage
and one would not measure the
original
content of the hydrated sample.
Another property
is that the internal standard
should be of known crysallinity.
This actually means that this
amorphous content
should be known
and should not be present in the
sample.
Preferably,
standard materials should have a
high crystal
structure symmetry
and at peak should not overlap
with the main reflection peaks
and the phases present in the
material.
And in addition,
it's also good if there is no micro
absorption problems that
would occur, for instance if there's
a large
X-ray absorption contrast between
the phases in your sample
and the standard.
If this would
be the case the micro absorption
problems may occur
and one would have a falsified
or a biased quantification.
The obtainable accuracy
of the quantification of the
amorphous
and unknown phases strongly depends
on the amount of internal standard
addict.
Small quantities
of amorphous phase of a few percent
are
therefore very difficult to quantify
precisely,
while higher levels
can be quantified
with greater accuracy.
For hydrating cements
that may contain between about
30 and 60 percent of amorphous
and then a crystalline phases,
a good compromise between accuracy
on both amorphous
and crystalline phases would
be to use additions
of internal standard of around 28
percent.
And it has been demonstrated that
the presence
of a significant amount of internal
standard inside a hydrating
base itself changes
the kinetics of the hydration by a
filler
effect, it is therefore best
not to include the standard
in the sample,
and instead to include a sample
or add the sample after stopping the
hydration.
And mixing the sample into the
hydrated
material,
you should be very careful
not to alter the hydration products
and therefore the mixing operations
should be thorough
but gentle,
and sample exposure to air should be
as limited as much as possible.
Since this can be quite tedious
to do in practice,
perhaps the less labor
intensive external standard method
is preferable for routine
analysis.
In the external standard approach
phase quantification
is carried out through the
comparison
of the phase scale factors of a
sample through the scale factor
of a well-characterized standard
material
measured under identical
diffractometer measuring conditions.
In this procedure also the different
mass
absorption coefficients of the
sample
µm and the standard µs
need to be taken into account.
As can be seen in the expression
given
here,
the Ws
the weight fraction of the standard
phase in the external
cement material is also
to be known.
Although the obvious advantage of
the method to this external
standard method is that the sample
does not
need to be intermixed
with an internal standard
and it does avoid
some preparation
and homogenization problems.
This approach needs to
does demand the
MACs subscript coefficient
of the sample to be known.
In the most practical of ways
it is obtained by calculating the
MACs subscript coefficient for the
use X-ray wavelengths
or the chemical composition.
This can be seen for instance in the
table
here where for each oxides
from the chemical composition
one has the MAC the
MACs of subscript coefficient given
for copper k alpha
radiation.
The linear combination of the mass
subscript
coefficients with the mass fractions
will enable you to measure the
mass absorption coefficient of that
sample.
In the table
one can see the
calculation done for a white cement
which was not hydrated,
which comes from MAC of about 101.5
square centimeters program
one can also see how it's calculated
for a slag,
as the slag contains less calcium
which is a x-ray absorbing
compound because it's heavier
than, for instance the silicon.
One can see up here the
total mass absorption coefficient
is lower in the slag than
for the white
cement. For a hydrated white cement,
for instance on showing in the last
column
one can see that this next to the
cements
content there's also water
in there.
So, calculating the mass
absorption coefficient of the total
mix
will show that the for
hydrated mix the mass absorption
coefficient
is quite a lot lower.
A promising development is a
so-called
PONKCS method,
which stands for 'Partial Or No
Known Crystal Structure approach.
This methods takes into account the
contribution of a phase that has no
or no known
crystal structure by calibration of
a phase constant,
which is shown
below.
This phase constant can then be used
in combination with the refined
skill factor
to calculate the phase weight
fraction and on mixes.
This method was recently applied to
the quantification
of the grief reaction of the
metalkeline of
the activated systems,
but also to the quantification of
CSH by SID
in the early hydration of Alite.
The precision
and accuracy of the PONKCS methods
was that by making
muddled mixes of cement
and SCMs,
as for instance shown in
this graph.
You then mix of 40 percent
Portland cement and 60 percent
slag is shown,
one can clearly see
the crystalline phases in green from
the cement
and the slag contribution
in black in the x
ray diffraction pattern.
The weighed in
amount here is 60 percent,
by calibrating separately the slag
and calibrating the phase constant
for
the slag and using it in
a PONKCS method approach,
one can actually measure
directly the amount of
slag in the sample.
As you can see on the right hand
side
the results were very good,
we measured using the PONKCS
method at about 58.2%
of slag, while we weighed
in about 59 percent.
So in general for mixes
in which the SCMs were the
only unknown amorphous component
next to a number of
crystalline phases,
and excellent precision
is obtained of around
1 weight percent
and the accuracy over a large
number of samples was about 2
- 3 weight percent.
In more complex mixes the arrows
and detection limits are expected to
be larger.
A particular difficulty in
decomposing
hydrated systems is
acquiring a suitable
model for the CSH phase,
the figure shown here
you can see a white Portland
cement hydrated for seven years,
that was mixed
with a known amount of metalkline.
You can see
you can recognize some of the
crystalline
phases present in the hydrated
Portland cement such as
Ettringite or Portlandite,
and you can see also in green
contribution by the CSH phase
and in yellow contribution
by metalkline.
Again when we did the analysis
by PONKCS it curiously
and precision were very good,
this was mainly because
the CSH was the only
amorphous phase in the hydrating
cement
and we could construct a
CSH peak module that fitted
nicely
and could be used to decompose
also modeling mixes,
so meaning the hydrated
cement with a known amount of
slag or metalkaline
and so on and so forth.
However,
the situation unfortunately becomes
more complex
when we have different kinds of CSH
formed and blended cements
of different composition,
and therefore the peak profiles
such as chase
or there's the presence of
other amorphous phases that can
actually limit
or bias the quantification.
In blends
however,
synthetic bleds
the method can be used very well as
shown
in the figure here.
Method is an excellent correlation
of the
weighted amount of SCM
on the x axis
and the measured amount by
PONKCS analysis on the y axis.
This may be very useful for instance
in process
control, in the
production of tannery
or quaternary blended cements
where one needs to check whether
the mixing has been done
correctly.
Traditional XRD quantitative phase
analysis
method were based on
single peak heights
or on single peak
integrated heights
and one compared these heights
to the height of an internal
standard.
This has not been
very successful for cements,
why this has been introduced
before,
this is because there is a high
degree of overlap
between the main peaks of the major
phases,
and this gives significant
problems and significant error
when applying such simple methods.
There are a number of additional
problems such
as variability in composition
and crystal structure such as
the presence of polymorphs that
could
actually cause significant
variations
in peak positions
and also intensities.
For instance in the case of Portland
cements
one knows that there is a lot of
solid solution,
substitution of minor elements
such as alkalies
or magnesium or sulfate in
the major phases
and this is common
and it leads often to the
stabilization
of different polymorph which
is then difficult to relate
to a certain quantity.
Therefore, the development of hope
by the fitting methods
such as the Rietveld method
as enable to largely overcome most
of these peak overlap problems
and it has found such widespread
application.
Since the phase composition
such as the Alite content
can be related to properties such as
strength development
or durability,
these kind of XRD analysis
by the Rietveld method have found
really a lot of use in both
cement research
and production quality control.
For instance,
this figures shown here shows
a monitoring of Alite,
Belite and free lime contents
by XRD during a period of
Portland cement production of an
industrial
site.
And here you can clearly see that at
some point
there was some
for instance temperature lowering
the kill
and we can't see a drop in Alite
levels,
free lime coming
up and Belite increasing
as well.
As step by step demonstration
of phase quantification of
anhydrous cement will be shown
in one of the demonstration videos.
As we already did
identification of the cement,
now we need to import into the
structure
for each phases.
First,
import an inter phases for
refinement,
and put a structure for C3S
as seems in
name for each phase,
the scale factor,
units cell, and profile should
be refined. constreams
of one percentage of evaluation on
the unit
sell would be applied
to secure refinement.
Limit of 0.0001 to 0.2 to the
profile partly was applied.
The
application of constreams to
the refined parameters.
We will improve the stability of the
overall
refinements when
especially we are analyzing complex
samples such as the hydrated cement.
Do the same steps for the rest
phases, for example
the C2S, C3S
and C4F as well as some
other matter of phases.
And we keep the
two most common existed polymorphs
for C3A
namely that Kubic
and rhombic ones.
Alternatively,
if you already
have HPF file
with old phases you can
also copies the phases from one HPF
file to another.
Right click the phase,
copy to the new HPF file you need,
when we set
on the limits and the parameters
to be refined in the template,
in a template
with HPF file previously using
the same steps,
check all the parameters
for the phases. Secondly,
set a global parameters
as spaceman
displacement background function
are your need to find,
for the background functions the
polynomial
function with five point for
instance
were used.
We use manual mode for refinement
as ordinals of all parameters were
set
manually.
After all the parameters were set,
refinement can be easy created by
pressing
the refinement button here.
After the first rung,
you can see that there is no much
cubics
history here of cement.
Now we can kick it out for further
refinement,
as we have so many phases
in cement, it takes several ortho
to reach the global minimum for
refinement.
Open there additional graphics for
different plot to
uniquely check the fitting.
The most common mismatching is from
the
cloud or the peaks around 32
degrees.
In this range we have the main peaks
for C3S
and of course some other peaks which
were overlapped.
The mismatch is mainly because of
the preferred
orientation of C3S here,
we can find our direction by
pointing
the mouse down to the peak which is
not
well fitted.
Here is 60-6
plain for M3 Alite,
to set preferred
orientation you can check you
can click on C3S in the refinement
control then in the optic
inspector for C3S
you will find the item called
preferred orientation,
the much dollars module
is recommended.
Specify the direction H3F
HK Air of the
plain for the preferred orientation.
After setting the direction check
the
refinement for a much taller factor,
similar tools out of parameters,
we put
the limits for the refinement of
0.721 the value
1 means there is no preferred
orientation at all, the smaller
the more preferred orientation.
In most of the cases 0.07
should be low enough
if the value is too small
which means the sampling is not real
done
a reputation of the XRD pattern
connection
with more attention on reducing the
preferred
orientation in this case
is recommended.
By refining refitting of
this peak is much improved.
A lot of
phase can be easily preferred
orientated is the anhydride
do the same for the preferred
orientation
of anhydride for the
for the two 00 direction
refinement, early some
improvement for the goodness of
fitting
and we did R profile.
The R W P value is
now 6.9467
showing the additional graphics.
By pressing the button
with percentage you have zero
quantitative
data or output in THT file
in the default high scores
high school folder.
Here we don't consider a morphs
content
in anhydride cement,
as it is the same
one which
with lower morphs which is essence
splendid.
If we spiken the flash
with a lower amount of standard,
we will be able to determine
the morphs content based on the
Spike
and the refined amount of
the standard. Here we mix 15%
of Rutile
with opflag
open the skin then inserts
of phases we need namely the
molet,
codes in the flash
and a tool
and Rutile which is the standard
we mixed.
All the parameters need need to
be refined for the phases,
skill factor,
unit cell,
and the profile,
then a set of global variables,
specimen displacement.
For the background we
need to change the method to use
a bit of a background then
manually determine it.
Let's change the skill of the Y-axis
to north skew to see more
details on the background,
by adapting the granularity
of the blending factor,
we can get the background function
following
the train of same set of patterns.
Mixture at the background
should never go into the peaks.
When satisfied
with the background function we can
accept the background.
Now you execute the refinement.
The overall fitting is quite good
when checking in details,
we can see zero
sum peaks which is not real fitted,
for example the peak at
27.4 degrees
the main peak for
Rutile.
When placing the mouse onto the peak
it shows H K area of the
corresponding
peaks for the phase.
Here is the one one all blame
for Rutile, actually this is
a preferred orientation of the
Rutile.
When the preferred orientation is
sets much
dollase factor to refine.
Now the refinement is done with an
R W P value
or about 5.8 percentage,
which is very good.
To show the result in internal
standard,
go to customize fitting Rietveld
panel,
change the show to
which percentage tool has received.
Here we have three options;
normal refers to the default
route for output,
has received means being
normalized the internal standard
results. Finally,
the external low factor corrected
means the results based on internal
low standard. The last
step is to specify how much
internal standard we added
through the Rutile internal control,
locates general phase information,
there are there we have
the item called standard weight
percentage.
Types of actual weight, amount,
here is 48.1 as
a crystalinity of the Rutile we
use is 196.2.
Now the final results
show means analyzed view window,
exported data are using the weak
percentage button,
or simply load it down.
The basic
for external standard is that
the K factor can be determined
using the external standard
measured under the same condition.
Then the absolute content of the
crystalline
phases can be calculated using
the K factor method.
For Ks of the external standard
method,
you will need to insert the
patterns,
one for the sample
and another for the standard.
And we also need to know the
chemical composition for the sample
to compute the mass absorption
coefficient, the mac value.
The calculation was
provided in the template file.
Step 1: Refine
the flyash pattern,
open a scheme for flyash, insert the
phases,
name it Quartz
the moon light, change
the name of the phases.
Manually determine the background,
make sure the background is
following the
lowest point of the pattern
but it should not go into the peaks.
change the background
and function from polynomial to
use a variable.
For simpled Rietveld refinement
system with few phases,
we can start
with the automatic Rietveld
refinements
by clicking on the default Rietveld.
Now, automatic Rietveld we will
refine the field,
units skill
and the profile step by step.
After several rounds of automatic
refinement
then change the refinement to manual
mode to further refine the pattern.
Take a look at a peak at 16.5
degrees, now feel the peak
is because of the preferred
orientation of
course at 10-1 plain.
Sets the direction of the preferred
orientation
and set for refinement.
Also at limit for the preferred
orientation, then execute the file,
saves
the HPF file.
Step 2: calculate
and the K factor used in the
standard scan,
create a new file name the inserts
without scan,
there is only one phase in the
Rutile
this sort of face.
The standard scan is quite a simple
scan
to refine so the automatic route
for refinement is enough.
Save for the rung in the default
root field
of refinement is recommended
to get a global minimum.
After refinement saves the HPF
file under the same folder
as a sample we analyzed.
You may notice that I didn't refine
the preferred orientation for the
Rutile,
the standard was pressed
on purpose. You have some preferred
orientation
to compensate the amorphous content
in
the standard.
The Rutile we used contain 3.8
percentage of morphines content
that deliberately introduced
preferred
orientation results in
a K factor which is 100 percentage
of crystalline Rutile.
To present the rutule external
standard results,
go to customize form one
settings,
fitting Rietveld panel,
then you have three
choices to choose a week percentage,
normal as received
or external k factor corrected.
Take the external k factor corrected
for the external standard method.
Here the three choices are
normal, referred to as default
Rietveld output by
normalizing all crystalline phases
to
100 percentage.
As received means,
as we normalized into low standard
results by taking out the standard.
Finally, the external k factor
corrected means the results
based on external standard.
Now we have an amorphous content
shown in an
analyze view window,
the value is
strange now, as the K factor is not
updated yet.
We can check the K factors in
decustomised
default,
external low standard,
the K factor is a global parameters
for the high school plus,
which means we have to update it
whenever
the value is changed around the
place to find out the value of the K
factor is
here.
Click on the phase Rutile,
in Object inspector you
can find the derived data
where the K factor is located.
For this standard the K factor
is 791.28,
right
click on the K factor
and then choose take current
K factor as standard.
Now you should see the 0
percent of the morphines for the
standard,
which means that the k factor is
the right one.
Step three,
updates the Mac for the flyash,
after updating the K factor,
go back to your flyash scan,
there is a value for the morphs
content as values
and is not valid.
because of MAC value here is not
updated
yet.
Click on the global variables
in the Object Inspector find
the custom mixture MAC under
agreement indices,
change
the value to the calculate one using
SRF results.
Here is the Excel used to
calculate the Mac plus the cement
unit
materials.
You can also calculate the Mac using
the high
score plus Mac calculator in the
tools menu.
In the Mac calculator you can find
all
the Mac values you need,
the fundamental behen
is the same.
Update the Mac to 39.91
for the flyash,
now the amorphous content is
correct.
Next to analyzing
and anhydride cement of course also
times series of hydrating cements
can
be analyzed.
Here the figure shows the 3D
stack of XRD measurements
of a hydrating zeolite
blended cements.
You can clearly see the formation
of cement hydrates such as
Ehtrengite and Portlandite,
while Clinker phases
and Clanotelite Zeolite are
being consumed.
Processing these data
and by rietveld analysis,
gives you quantitative results on
the consumption
and formation of the solid phases,
and these data can then be used on
its turn as input
for hydration models
or to establish reaction mechanisms.
The video demonstration will show
you
step-by-step face quantification of
a
hydrated cement.
Advice you have a look at this,
this will show you the
major difficulties
and the major steps to be taken
in the hydrate
cement. The hydrate cement is a much
more complex
compared to the anhydride cement.
The existence of lynon crystalline
sulphate,
the
main hydrate of cements
is a first challenge for the
quantity of
collapses.
In most of the hydrated cement
or Blinked cement,
there are some there are also some
minor phases
which bring more difficulties for
the reflector analysis.
As the existence of the amorphous
phases,
here's a nylon crystalline sachet in
the examples,
the quantification
the quantitative analysis of
hydrated
cements needs to be done
with a internal standard
or external standard method.
The Rietveld analysis for hydrates
is
based on the analyze of that hydrate
cement.
Open the analyzed HPF file for the
hydrate
cement, you remove the scan for the
cement,
then insert the scan for the
anhydride cement.
For the refinements,
the refined will be constrained
within the range of 7 degrees to
the end.
Go to analyzed menu, fittings, edit
excluded regions,
create a new exclude region
from 0 - 7 degrees.
In this file,
we already have all the thinker
phases
so we need new phases for
the hydrides namely the Portland,
Ettringite etc..
We can import a phase directed
from the save files,
or we can copy the phases we
need from the templates
where we already have the phases.
The reason we use refined
phase from
the same cement is that
all the clinker phases will be
constrained
to use in the same cell parameters
and profile only the skill factor
will be refined in the hydrated
cement.
I apply such constraint
the refinement of the hydrated
cement
is more stable as a large
number of phases presented.
Specifically all the preferred
orientation of the Clinker phases
should be removed
and set to default one.
Removes the refined flak for the
outer
cklinker phases namely
the unit cell,
profile.
Now hydrate will be dissolved
quickly
within the first day,
so we also removed
it.
Right click any space in the
refinement
control, collapse Root Note.
For the high treat namely
Portlandite
the refinement unit cell,
profile as well as a skill factor
first, we will do
a final check of the refinement
of the Portlandite by refining the
preferred orientation.
Similar rules as will be applied to
the Entrendite,
as you can see the polynomial
function
is not powerful enough to fix a
wide hump from the surges contribute
in the hydrated cement.
So
we changed the background function
to
manually determine one,
click the global variable,
then background, change the type of
background
function in the object inspector
from polynomial to use available
background. In this way
we can define the background
function
by ourselves using the determined
background
by changing the granularity
and bending factors,
we should have our background curve
following the lowest background of
the pattern.
Refinement thing use to get
much better in fitting of the
pattern,
it refined a preferred
orientation of the of the
portlandite.
Now the fitting is much better
except
the classical of peaks at around 29
degrees,
we will deal with this later, as it
is mainly for the sachet nano
crystal hump. Overall, the manually
determined
background works for the hydrides
after refinement of the pattern,
we can output the result.
Now two steps,
update the mac value for the sample,
update the K factor.
Find out the calculated mac
for the hydrated cement,
here is 72.03,
in high score
box click on the global variable it
will you
the object inspector.
In our agreement indices
you can
find the item called custom
mixture mac,
update the value
to the calculated one,
here is 72.03.
The K factor was obtained within a
scan or Rutile under the same
condition as the sample scan
within the same day.
Inside the Rutile scan,
copies of phase Rutile to the Rutile
scan,
then you click the profile
feed,
default rietveld
twice.
Now you should be able to see
the amorphous content
update K factor,
where we updates the K factor in
the system showing you
and there are amorphous for the
standard
which means that you have the
correct
K factor for this measurement.
To export results,
we should actively the sample scan
by double clicking the scan in
scan list,
and then click the button
with percentage external standard.
This is a customized exporting
pattern
and you can find a way
to configure the button in hip
files,
otherwise no
longer value showing on fitted
window.
It's make our duplicate of the
defined
scan and label it as say
PC 28 days.
This is their technique to optimize
fitting of
the fitting for such a hump.
Instead of using the manual
background
we can introduce a profile for
sensage,
the profile was obtained
by fitting wall cement hydrate for
seven years using the 14
angstrom to promote the structure.
The extracted profile only
contribute
to the background fitting result
quantitative analysis without
quantitative
information.
We will only refine your skill
factor
was the extracted profile
for the sensage,
but keep all the other parameters
constant, as in general
most of the suasage amp are
similar.
The background function can be
simplified
to the polynomial one when the
sensage
profile was employed.
Let's change it here,
three parameters for the background,
the flat background
function.
While the X background
and co-exist one would be sufficient
enough to give us a good fit.
If flat you can add more
coefficients into your background
function.
It's refining,
now the RWP file
decreased
and the fitting is much better
especially the fitting around 29
degrees.
means where this sensage hump was
located.
Check the Key factor
and the Mac makes sure they are
correct,
then we export the result.
Here is a summary of the results for
the hydrated
sample, using a different background
may assert the
results from sensage background is
better as the improved fitting.
There are no much differences
in the Portland content,
the main differences are those
phases
present peaks close
to the sensage hump. For
powdered Hydration stack samples,
it's a little
bit different, so here I will show a
lot of
example
with the powdered
sample. There are
little much difference in the
refined
procedures for the patterned
obtained
and the hydration
stopped powder.
There are three aspect need to be
addressed
when analyzing hydration stopped
powder,
first,
per proof per page combination
of the samples,
second,
preferred orientation,
third,
normalization results.
We see the previous analyzed
based on the first disk as a
template,
then remove the scans
in the HPF file
there are only the phases
and the refined parameters next.
Actually, this is a way how we made
templates for the analysis
which will reduce a lot of work to
imports to
import and set parameters for
refinement.
Insert your scanned,
then refine.
You can see some
mac peaks around 10 degrees
according
to the identification we made
before,
this is the peak of a modern
Sulphate
enumenate. Here you copy the phase,
here is a kuzinite from
the template further refine the
pattern which is called kuzinite the
fittings is much
improved.
The preferred orientation was
important
that in the powder sample is much
severe compared to the refresh
state,
this is mainly because of the
sampling procedure when we are
doing powder samples.
There are also some preferred
orientation
for the Ettrindite phase,
find out the plain, it's
1006 to much
taller direction to 1046 and then
refine it.
Calculate the K
factor of the measurement
and update it.
Update the Mac value for the dried
paste,
the Mac value of the dried paste
should be should also be updated by
taking the remove of the free water
in
the sample.
Generally, you need either
result from TGA to back
calculate this updated
background.
The need for previous output TST
file
then output the results,
the drag bases should be converted
into the fresh paste
or the hydrate space for comparison.
The bound water from TGA results
will be needed to finalize the
conversion.
Alternatively,
you can direct the measures phrase
for the free water content to
finalize
the calculation.
A calculation templates using
the TGA bond water
were provided in
the template. The end.
Overall we
might conclude that quantitative
phase analysis of hydrated cement is
not
so straightforward,
and it's quite important to say that
XRD data
of complex systems would actually
not be
analyzed by black box approaches.
Experience has shown that
quantitative phase analysis
and the accuracy of the results
even for simple systems
depends really a lot
on the strategy
of analysis
and also the skill and experience of
the analyzer, the analyst.
You should try to have at least
a basic understanding of
the underlying crystallography,
and of course also of the cement
chemistry to be able to guide
the rietveld refinement
and to judge by the
quality of the results
is fine.
You can actually gain some of
this practical experience by
practicing
on simple model mixture that you
make yourself,
and you can also follow some
trainings
from more experienced researchers
in your group or of other groups.
So retold quatitative phase analysis
can be subdivided at least
into two parts.
So as we discussed this quality
phase
analysis spot in which
we identify which phases
is at present
and we select the crystal structures
that are most suited for the
quatitative
phase analysis that come next.
So the second step is quantitative
phase analysis
where we do the data fitting of the
whole powder pattern to a
calculated
pattern. So as general
guidelines we could say that it's
very
good to start
with good literate instruction
models,
and we have supplied in the
database a number of supplemental
supplementary materials
a folder which contains
Crystallographic information files
from which you can extract
the information you need
to run a rietveld analysis.
So it's very useful to have a look
at these,
because you can find a lot of
different
entries in the literature databases
and they may be more
or less applicable to cement
systems.
So we already made some sort of
pre-selection for you
and which you from which you can
start
and do your analysis.
What is quite important as well
is that at least initially,
but also
it's best to do this over the whole
analysis rietveld analysis is
that you minimize the number of
refined variables.
Why?
Well that's
often already 10 20
30 40 50 different
variables that are being filtered in
the rietveld
refinements
and that's
not that much information
that it can be completely
left and constraint.
Of course once you have selected
a number of parameters
that should be varied you should
in the final step of your refinement
refine them altogether so you come
to
your final optimized results.
So basically it means that you have
optimized all the variables
and you have at least
obtained a sort of
stable global solution.
So it's quite important that for
quantitative
phase analysis that
at least in the first steps that you
refine only scale factors
and lattice parameters,
and then later on you can include
other corrections perhaps
like a preferred orientation
correction.
Also it's quite important that
for lattice parameters
you constrain parameter
variation within a sensible
interval.
As discussed before one
can very lattice parameters to a
large
extent or the program could
do that.
And then you might end up
with the crystal structures which
are just chemically
and reasonable lengths
may be stretched while
you are changing too much while
you are changing or allowing
to change lattice parameter to
vary.
Also it's important to check
the fit and the contributions of the
different individual phases
visually.
Why? Because many would see what
a certain parameter
or change in a certain parameter is
really
doing in the fitting whether for
instance then a small
contribution of a minor phase is
really significant,
whether it's really there
or whether it's just a misfit of
another phase.
And also a good hand is to
when you have imposed this let's say
intervals for instance for lattice
parameter
you could say well it may
vary about 1.2%
from the literature
data,
that when you did the refinements,
when you rerun the refinement
and you check for parameter that
that hit these limits
that you have just pre-impose
that actually there you
might have indication for some
problems
maybe there is another phase,
maybe there is a problem
with your crystal structure model
that you selected,
or there can be other stuff.
So this table gives you some sort
of overview of
what you can vary during the
refinements.
So
basically we saw that
with phase scale factors,
units cell parameters, peak shape
parameters, and micro sexual
parameters,
and even needed preferred
orientation
parameters.
Of course next to the phase Bennett
parameters also is so-called global
parameters
need to be redefined such
as a specimen displacement
correction
and coeffience of the background
fraction.
In complex systems such as cement
the refinement of crystal structure
parameters
such as atomic positions
and displacement factors best be
avoided.
The crystal structure refinement
by the rietveld method should best
be reserved
just to peer systems.
The other in which the parameters
are very
generally dependent on the distance
to the final vary values is the
so-called
parameter chips.
But overall,
it is suggested that you
first start with the global
parameter to
be refined and then phase
dependent parameters.
In case of hydrating cements the
amount
of solutes varies during
the bundling of water into the
hydration products.
Therefore a finalized step into
quantification should be to rescaled
the
results to a common basis
such as the initial clinker content
or the cement content to
enable an easy comparison
and a straightforward comparison
which in different types
of reaction.
This is also called the dilution
effect.
On the figure here you can see how
for instance over time the amount of
solutes increases.
Now when you remove the free water
by
hydration stoppage you should of
course
account for this effect
and let's say that for instance 10
percent in the anhydrous cement
would not be the
same as 10 percent
on the
final solutes
in the hydrated cement.
This is a specially
and particularly important for the
calculation of the degree of
hydration,
but you would always need to of
course
refer to the same kind of basis
because
10 percent of Alite in
the initial system could be
different
than 10 percent of Alite in the
final system.
The formula given on the right side
here
gives you a way of how
to correct this Portland
cement.
Some of the recalculation formula
show that actually
depends they depend on whether
free water is removed to stop
dehydration
reactions. If the sample
is assumed to be underwriting cut of
fresh
slice,
then the great correction factor
should contain
the water to cement ratio of the
phase.
So what you initially put us
water into the cement.
If the sample
is dried the separate measurement of
the bond
water content ignited basis
by measured for instance by
demographic metrix is needed to
rescale
the results. The given
expressions here are developed
for the case of an underwrites
fresh hydrated sample
and for a dry hydrated sample.
And you can use this for your recalculation.