X.Ray diffraction has become a standard
characterization tool in cement material science.
If you properly used a wealth of information and cement phase
composition can be retrieved both qualitatively and quantitatively.
The solace in cement can be quantitatively characterized
and sample preparation is rather straightforward.
Another advantage is that measurement times are quite short and that XRD materials
is found in most material science labs.
Even more so it has found application of quality control of
cement production.
However, one should realize that cement
and hydrate cements are particularly complex  multicomponent materials.
This leeds to inherent limitations such as an
inaccuracy which is limited to about two to
three weight percent for major feature such as alite
and one to twenty percent for minor phases.
Also as in many techniques
when one is going beyond the state of the art or standard
practice, it is necessary to develop to some extent some
expert knowledge.
Definitely X. Ray diffraction analysis
will find an even broader use
and acceptance in the cement science community of the future
as many more researchers will have access to the equipment
and the supporting data analysis software will
definitely become even more performant and user friendly.
This will however not mean
that the cement inherent challenges
and practical problems will disappear. On the contrary,
even more attention will need to be big through education
and training to save guard the quality of the results
and to realize the full potential effect exactly.
As an outlook,
Major changes in XRD analysis
and cements of course difficult to anticipate. However
the predictable future path of XRD data analysis well
likely involve improvements of current.
Methods and databases to facilitate applicability,
more automatization and improved reliability, accuracy
and precision of the methods.
In this respect, it's also new a further
improved crystal structure that will be introduced.
And this were unable to further enhance the accuracy of
the results and widen the scope of samples
and problems that can be addressed.
It is also to be expected that cross checks the
XRD results, with other independent techniques become implemented, it
will become used more and more and automized
in the analysis software packages.
On a more methodological level and Rietvield
quantification methods such as PONKCS are read for them
but in summation that as a combined
will be developed further
and adopted to confront the most challenging systems
that remain today out of reach of the phase analysis by Xray diffraction.
It is clear that the extent the analysis
of cement still has not reached its full potential
and that future developments and
breakthroughs are still lying ahead.