Welcome to the second chapter of our MOOC,
Massively Online Open Course,
on basic steps in magnetic resonance.
Today’s chapter will be called
chemical shifts.
So chemical shifts are indeed
at the heart of magnetic resonance.
More specifically, they are essential
for most applications
of magnetic resonance
to chemistry and to biology.
In physics, they are perhaps
less important,
although that can be argued.
In fact, the origin of this effect
is what is known in good
English as serendipity
and in bad English, sheer luck.
It was, in fact, discovered by mistake
and against the wishes of the inventors,
that is Proctor and Wu,
who in the late 40s or early 50s,
wanted to measure the
gyromagnetic ratio of nitrogen.
More specifically, Nitrogen 14,
which is a dominate isotope of nitrogen,
And to do so, they decided to take
a material that would be full of nitrogen
and their choice turned
to ammonium nitrate
which indeed has lots of nitrogen.
And to their distaste, they found,
once they'd identified
the nitrogen resonance,
they found that there were
in fact two peaks and not one.
Now we know that one of these
nitrogen peaks
come from the ammonium group
and the other one
from the nitrate group.
But they didn't want that.
They wanted just one peak
and they wanted to measure the Gamma--
the gyromagnetic ratio.
The frequency of precession,
the transition frequency
in the absence of environment.
To them, the environment
was just a nuisance.
So nitrate, ammonium,
that was not their business.
They were not chemists.
And they wrote a paper.
They submitted a paper
where they mentioned this effect
as a dirt effect.
The editor then said, "Dirt effect is not
a very scholarly expression.
Would you please propose
another expression?"
And they said, "Well, let's call it
a chemical shift."
And it has been
a chemical shift ever since.
By the way, when I tell you
anecdotes like this,
I'm not too sure that they are genuine,
that they can be trusted.
Maybe the story was just made up
by somebody else.
But, you know,
“Se non è vero, è ben trovato.”
"If it isn't true, at least
it's a nice story."
You can find many of such stories
in the books of [Aberg Am],
of Casimir, of many other scientists
who have enjoyed themselves
writing up their autobiographies
and talking about the
fun aspects of research.
We shall now discuss the second
chapter of the book by Peter Hore,
which is dedicated to chemical shifts.
So chemical shifts can be discussed
in a purely empirical fashion
as a phenomenon that can be observed
without necessarily trying to explain it.
This, in fact, is a very important
approach in chemistry and in biology.
Of course, scientists
like to explain things.
And so they have thought about
the origin of chemical shifts
and they have tried to split
these chemical shifts
into different contributions.
And this is known as contribution
to nuclear shielding.
In fact, nuclear shielding
is another word for chemical shifts.
We’ll have a summary after that
and then some exercises.
Perhaps the simplest explanation
of nuclear shielding
and chemical shifts is if we consider
the example of simple gases,
noble gases which are basically
mono-atomic molecules
such as helium.
In fact, the isotope 3 of Helium
happens to have a spin I = ½.
This is a guess, of course.
It can be hyper-polarized
as we shall discuss later.
It can actually be used to do
images of human lungs.
Likewise, we could also consider 129 Zenon
which also has a spin ½ and also is used
for imaging of lungs of living humans.
Now, both have a spherical symmetry
and both have a simple nucleus
at the center and a cloud of electrons.
Of course, these electrons
move all over the place,
but there is a slight preference
for them to move in a plane
which is perpendicular to
the external magnetic field.
So this field B0 here,
is the external magnetic field
which is applied to the sample
by the experimentalist
usually generated by a large
superconducting magnet
to achieve a sufficiently intense field.
Now it turns out that
this external magnetic field
affects the electrons in such a way
that there will be a slight preference
for the electrons to move around
such a trajectory
which is perpendicular to the field
and where the electrons
move in such a way, that
the field that they induce
which is this B prime here--
this B prime, B prime,
is the induced field--
the field induced by
the circulating electrons.
And according to the law of Lenz,
this induced field
has a sign opposite to the external field.
The net effect is that the local field,
which is sometimes just called--
this is the local field
at the site of the nucleus--
is proportional to the external field,
but there is an attenuation factor here
which is written as 1 – σ.
If sigma is zero, which it
often is in simple cases,
then the local field is equal to
the external field
and there’s no problem.
But in many molecules,
the sigma has different values
depending on the environment,
the chemical environment of the nucleus.
The same thing can be expressed
not in terms of field
but in terms of the NMR frequency.
So this the precession frequency
of the transversed magnetization
or also simply the energy
of the transition between
the bottom state and the excited state.
And we can see that this is proportional
to the gyromagnetic ratio,
proportional to the external field
attenuated by the circulated electrons
and this attenuation is again
expressed as 1 – σ.
We can also look at the same thing
in terms of energy levels
where we see that the bare nucleus
has a transition frequency
which is determined only by
the applied magnetic field.
But as soon as the nucleus
sits in an electron cloud,
it is partly protected
from the external field.
And therefore we have
this shielding parameter,
the nuclear shielding expressed by
this attenuation factor here
which precisely comes from
the circulating electrons.
And as you can see, the splitting
between the bottom
and the top level is reduced
because of that.
Now, chemical shifts, as I mentioned
in my introductory remarks,
could be observed in many cases.
The one that I mentioned was
14 Nitrogen in an ammonium group
and 14 Nitrogen in a nitrate group.
And as I said, the physicists
who used this material
were very disappointed to discover
that these two nitrogens
had different chemical shifts,
as we now call them,
or different environments.
But for the chemists,
that of course, is wonderful
because that allows us
to distinguish them.
Now this is a typical NMR spectrum
and you could imagine
that this is the B and this is the A.
Or it could be any other molecule
that has two distinct
resonance frequencies.
In fact, a more popular, a more common
case would be a proton NMR.
A proton NMR is by far the dominant
version of magnetic resonance
today in organic labs
and particularly in chemistry.
And in proton NMR
we have a range of roughly
eight to ten ppm.
So this is the range of chemical shifts
expressed in the parameter delta.
And we see that if we have some protons
in different environments,
in different solvents,
for example this is benzene--
and this is--
well, different environments.
Tetramethylsilane is by definition
used so that the origin
of the scale is adjusted to be zero
at the frequency of tms.
Now this delta scale here
is defined more properly here.
It is simply the frequency
of the transition
minus a reference frequency.
So this would be for example
the frequency of Benzine
minus the frequency of tms
divided by the frequency of the tms.
So typically this might be 400MHz
and something minus 4
to 100 MHz a bit below.
Anyway, the reference frequency
and the ratio, of course,
is dimensionless.
It turns out that this dimensionless
number tends to be rather small,
on the order of 10 to the -6.
And, therefore, it is usually
by convention
multiplied by 10 to the 6
in order to get reasonable numbers.
And this gives you
the definition of delta,
known as the chemical shift to chemists.
And as you can see,
it is a dimensionless number.
But it is usually specified
that it is expressed in ppm to clarify.
I should warn you that
in much of the physics literature,
this convention is not the same.
They often use the parameter sigma,
the nuclear shielding parameter
and not the parameter delta
defined as in this expression.
So what is true for
the precession frequencies
is also true for the
shielding parameters.
And you can reformulate this equation
by saying that this is now
the sigma of the reference
minus the sigma of the
substance of interest.
And you will notice that this
runs in the opposite direction.
The delta runs in the opposite direction
as the scale of the shielding
parameters, which gave rise
to a great deal of confusion
between the literature of the chemists
and the literature of the physicists.
Now, chemical shifts are very often
considered as empirical parameters
without any attempt to explain them.
And as such, they are very well known.
Particularly to chemists and more
specifically to organic chemists
who have a tremendous ability,
the good ones anyway,
to recognize a molecule when
looking at the NMR spectrum,
the proton NMR spectrum.
This is not such an easy task.
You can see that the scale here
goes from zero to 10.
And for example, we find
the aromatic molecules,
I mean the protons
attached to aromatic molecules
span a considerable range.
Benzene is somewhere
near seven and a quarter
but depending on the environment,
the shifts can cover quite a range.
It is even worse for
hydroxy-aromatics, so aerials.
And you can see different molecules
have different ranges.
We note amusing things.
For example, that the acetylenic proton,
we shall refer to that later,
is towards lower chemical shifts
than the olefinic,
which is kind of surprising.
This is due to a very peculiar
effect sometimes called
the neighboring group effect
that we shall try to explain later on.
But basically this table is very important
because most organic chemists
have this, sort of,
engraved in their brain and
they go around the world
remembering this all the time.
And if you know this very well
and if you’re very familiar with
this kind of empirical material,
it allows you to recognize
the fingerprint of your molecule
and determine exactly what it is.
Now there are other things.
For example, the amplitudes
of the signals,
more properly called the integrals,
are proportional to the number
of nuclei within the molecule.
Some examples here.
So this is trimethylbenzene.
And of course we have protons here,
which are directly attached
to the aromatic ring,
so there are three of them,
and they’re a total of three times
three or nine methyl protons.
So the ratio of the methyl protons
to the aromatic protons
is three to one.
Nine to three is equal to three to one.
In the NMR spectrum,
we shall see a weak peak here,
close to 7 ppm and a much
more intense peak,
of three times more intense
peak just above 2 ppm.
And the fact that they have
these amplitude ratios
confirms what I just told you,
that there are indeed
three aromatic protons.
These three here directly
attached to the ring,
and nine methyl protons.
The transition, so you should remember
that we go from nine over three
equal to three over one.
What you observe is this
and what the chemist
would like to know is this.
And it takes a bit of chemical
intuition to go
from three over one to nine over three.
We have another example here.
This is a tetramethylbenzene.
Now, of course, there are
only two aromatic protons
that remain and they’re a total
of four times three.
So that’s 12 divided by two
methyl protons.
So 12 methyl protons
and two aromatic protons,
and of course, the ratio is six to one.
And you can see that indeed
we have the amplitude
of the aromatic peak is one-sixth
of the aliphatic peak.
So this kind of reasoning
can be extended to many,
many molecules.
In fact, these examples are
a bit oversimplified.
They have been chosen.
They are not cheated.
They are genuine examples,
but they have been chosen
because these particular molecules
do not feature any scale or couplings.
They do not have any
multiplets and therefore,
we can argue purely
on the grounds of chemical shifts.
If we have a more serious molecule,
such as a protein,
then of course, we have many,
many different chemical shifts,
many environments.
This particular protein was popular
in Oxford at the days of writing the book.
And it contains, in fact, 129 amino acids,
which is a fairly small protein
by biological standards.
But a large protein from
the point of view of chemists,
and also actually for NMR spectroscopists
this represents a challenge.
129 amino acids means roughly
that there are about 10 protons
for each amino acid,
sometimes some have more, some have less.
But roughly that means
about 1,000 protons.
And indeed we have about
1,000 chemical shifts.
Some of them pile up so that
you get a very messy profile here.
That means that many have been added
on top of each other.
Others are quite nicely isolated.
I presume this is the sum of
a few degenerate methyl groups.
And this looks like a rather
isolated proton attached
to a [inaudible], to a proton,
to a nitrogen, excuse me.
Typically, we would write this
something like this.
And this would probably
be something like this.
And this is an example of two assignments,
that is to say, the relationships
between peaks and chemical units
which are one of the great challenges
of protein NMR spectroscopy.
But a great deal of progress
has been made in this field,
particularly by combining proton NMR
with Carbon 13 NMR
and with Nitrogen 15 NMR,
by enriching the proteins
with these stable isotopes and then
recording so-called two-dimensional
correlation spectra that
allow one to assign--
each and every one of these peaks
can be assigned and identified.
The next gives a rather exotic example,
very far from biology,
no proteins at all.
There is a substance.
This is actually a metal cluster,
which contains four cobalt atoms
and a bunch of carbon monoxide.
And the question is, what is the structure
of this strange cluster?
And you could imagine something like this.
That we have the four methyls
in a regular tetrahedron
and that each of the four methyl
is surrounded by a local little cloud
of three carbon monoxides.
And the whole thing would have a symmetry,
that of the point group
of a tetrahedron.
If that were the case,
then there would be
all sort of symmetry elements,
planes of reflection, rotation,
all sorts of things.
And a conclusion of an analysis
of the symmetry of this molecule
is that there should be only one peak
for all oxygens that you see.
And by the way, also only one
peak for all the carbons
and one peak for all the metals,
if they happen to have a spin,
cobalt for example.
Now it turns out that if we look at
the Oxygen 17 spectrum,
that there are not one but four peaks.
So we can safely say this is no good.
This can be ruled out because
that particular simple symmetry
is incompatible with the fact
that there are four lines
in the oxygen spectrum.
By the way, oxygen is
a rather unusual nucleus.
It has a large quadrupole
and the lines are rather broad
because of rapid transverse relaxation.
And it’s not your favorite molecule,
your favorite isotope
in the periodic table,
but it’s very nice in this illustration.
Now you can speculate about other systems.
This has a symmetry of D2D.
It has some so-called bridging
carbonyls, which are here.
And it also has the so-called
terminal carbonyls,
which have a different environment,
as you can see.
And from the structure of this,
you conclude that
there should be, I believe,
two different peaks.
And this can also be ruled out.
Now when you look at this
final one here, it turns out
that here we have bridging carbonyls.
There are three of those.
And then you have some which
are in a sort of apical position.
They point out away from the metal
and they’re isolated.
Whereas, in this case,
we have three carbonyls
attached to the same methyl.
In this case, we have two carbonyls
I’m not sure how to draw this but you see.
I should have changed the color actually.
Now, this molecule, therefore,
is compatible with a spectrum,
an oxygen spectrum, which has four
distinct resonances.
It’s not easy to say which of these lines
belong to which environment.
That’s a difficult question
and it’s not the purpose
of today’s lecture.
Now, this is an interesting case
because it speaks of fullerenes,
sometimes called
buckminsterfullerenes or C60
as perhaps the most common expression.
And we now know that this is
a icosahedral molecule
where the carbons are arranged
on the pattern of a football,
and there are some surfaces
that have a hexagonal environment
and others a pentagonal environment.
Now what is remarkable about this molecule
is that is has an extremely
simple Carbon 13 spectrum.
In fact, you can convince yourself
that it has a very high symmetry,
an icosahedral symmetry,
and that therefore,
the chemical shifts of all Cs,
full carbon atoms, should be the same.
And indeed the spectrum
shows just a single line.
So the fact that that is a single line
is a confirmation
that the symmetry of the molecule
must indeed be very simple.
Now this was not obvious at all.
When this material was discovered
in 1919 by Harry Kroto in his environment,
and his co-workers, this was still
an uncertain matter
and it was not at all clear
that carbon could arrange itself
in such a structure,
such a strange molecule.
In fact, this molecule went unnoticed
for about two centuries
of modern chemistry,
and therefore, it’s quite remarkable
that it was found so late in history.
Kroto, by the way, got a Nobel prize,
probably mostly for this.
And if you are interested
in the origin of such things,
I vividly recommend that
you read this in ChemComm.
You can look it up following instructions
that I will give somewhere else.
So let’s take another example,
which I think is very well chosen
by Peter Hore from the vast literature
that describes such effects.
And this example uses Phosphorus 31.
That’s a very popular nucleus
because it is very abundant.
In fact, that isotope is
100 percent abundant.
It’s not radioactive, of course,
stable and it is found almost
everywhere in biology.
But it is also found
in inorganic chemistry.
And the example studied here
by Raymond Andrew,
who is a very famous English NMR
spectroscopist and physicist,
in a paper that I vividly recommend
you should read,
he and his team studied
this very simple molecule.
So this is phosphorus pentachloride.
If you consider that in solution,
it is a bi-pyramidal affair, like this.
The phosphorus, of course,
is in the middle
and the five chlorine sit
at the corners of this polygon.
And it turns out that there’s
a high degree of symmetry,
and that the phosphorus sits in the middle
and is quite happy to be there.
It has only one chemical shift.
But if you precipitate this material
and make a solid out of it,
then the molecule actually
disproportionates
and gives you this anionic species
and cationic species,
so PCL 4 minus and PCL 6 plus.
And they have different chemical shifts.
In fact, it turns out that this one
is shielded and this
one is deshielded.
And this is then plotted
on a ppm scale of delta
of Phosphorus 31.
Actually, to record
a Phosphorus 31 spectrum
in a solid is not such a simple affair
because as we shall see later,
the phosphorus
has an anisotropy of the chemical shift,
and therefore, in a solid
tends to give very broad lines.
And in order to get rid of
this line broadening,
Andrew invented a wonderful experiment
which is known as magic angle
spinning that allows you
to retrieve very narrow lines
from spectra solids that
otherwise would be broadened.
This is a very clever technique
and Andrew deserves
much credit for that.
This was one of the first
applications of that technique.
Now there are also applications
of Silicone 29 NMR.
And this is one that is
of some industrial interest
because we speak of aluminosilicates.
That is to say, porous solids
that are built of aluminate units,
AlO4 and silicate units, SiO4.
In this notation I mean that
the aluminium is surrounded
by four oxygen atoms, roughly
in a tetrahedral environment
and a silicone likewise.
But together these make up
a vast array of substances
called aluminosilicates.
Some of which are found in nature.
Some of which are only made synthetically.
And many of which
have interesting properties
as heterogeneous catalysts
because they have pores
and molecules can enter into these pores
and their chemical reactions
can occur on the inner
surfaces of these pores.
And the characterization
of aluminosilicates
is not an easy matter
because as you can see
at the periodic table,
aluminum and silicone
are very close together
and they have roughly
the same electron density around them.
So that makes it hard to distinguish
them with x-ray spectroscopy.
But of course, in NMR, the Aluminum 27,
which by the way has a quadrupolar spin,
is completely different
from the Silicone 29.
And what you see here,
is a range of Silicone 29
spectra of different zeolites.
Zeolites are an important class
of aluminosilicates with different
ratios of silicone to aluminum.
So in the bottom case,
we have mostly silicone
and very little aluminum.
In the top case, they are about equal.
And what we see here
is a distribution of different
chemical shifts of Silicone 29
where if there is no aluminum
in the neighborhood,
then we have this line here.
If there is one aluminum
next door, we have this line.
If there are two alumina
next door, then we have this line.
If there are three, then we have
the line to the left [inaudible].
There’s actually one more
over here, which is very weak.
So , the more aluminum,
that is to say, the lower
the ratio of silica to aluminum--
So we go up on this list,
the more, of course,
the distribution is favouring
the line which corresponds to silica
in the environment for alumimate centers.
Now, it’s interesting to look at
these distributions.
That is to say, the relative amplitudes
because they give a very refined,
a very subtle, very informative way
of characterizing these
zeolites or aluminosilicates
that are so important
in heterogeneous catalases
and particularly frequency used
in the petroleum industry
for cracking of heavy natural oil
to make convenient petrol
or gas as the Americans say.
You can find more about this in this paper
by Jacek Klinowski
and Colin Fyfe and others.
As you can see, we’ll try to provide
the key to that in our supplement.
Now, there is here a more
biological application
but it’s not just biological.
It’s really one of universal importance.
It was first described by Ian Campbell
and Raymond Dwek.
Ian Campbell, incidentally,
was teaching in Oxford
and he was the co-examiner of my PhD.
I wouldn’t say I’ve known him
very well, but he’s a charming person
who unfortunately died a few years ago.
Raymond Dwek, as far as I’m aware,
is still active in Oxford.
Now this discovery was very important.
This illustration is very important.
They were concerned with
looking at histidine.
Now, histidine comes in two forms.
It can be either protronated,
in which case it’s called HisH+.
And what we mean is
that they have a proton
attached to this nitrogen.
In fact, the molecule looks
a bit symmetrical
or nearly symmetrical
when it’s protronated.
But of course, the proton can drop off,
in which case it’s in solution,
and the nitrogen is then naked,
so to speak, with a long pair
sticking out here.
But this in itself is not something
we wish to observe.
What we shall observe is
the chemical shift of the proton
which is attached to
the neighboring carbon.
So here again, there is a chemical shift,
of the proton attached to
the neighboring carbon.
And it turns out that the chemical shift
of this so-called C2 proton,
or H2 proton, which is the one
attached to the C2 carbon,
is very sensitive to the question
if it’s protonated or not.
Now what you see here is spectra
of histidine in its natural environment
which is actually in haemoglobin.
So haemoglobin is the molecule protein
that carries the oxygen
in our blood and delivers the oxygen
and delivers the oxygen
to the organisms where it is needed.
And of course, it’s very interesting
to see what happens.
If the haemoglobin carries
oxygen, then it’s called oxi.
And if it has lost it’s oxygen,
it’s called deoxi.
So they’re two different forms.
But even before we start
about losing oxygen,
let’s talk about the deoxi version first.
We notice that the chemical shift
of this proton here
depends critically on the pH
of the solution.
And we see here that the chemical shift
as a fraction of pH
can be used a little bit like
we can use the potential
of an electrode in a pH meter,
in that we see that there is
a sort of a point of inflection
in this curve here
and this point of inflection,
that is to say where
the derivative changes sign,
is known as the pk.
And so we can determine
the pk of this particular
histidine but not just one histidine.
It’s in a histidine which is embedded
in haemoglobin.
Now it turns out that if
the haemoglobin is oxygenated,
that is to say it carries oxygen,
which is of course attached
to the iron atom in the haem,
well then it turns out that the pk--
we can do the same experiment again.
And as you can see, the pk
is shifted from 7.9 to 6.8.
That’s quite remarkable.
Now it turns out that
this is an illustration
of a very universal rule, which is
that the average chemical shift,
which is what you see
along the vertical sail,
so this is the average chemical shift,
is made up of a mixture
of the chemical shift
of the protronated version,
of this molecule here,
plus a weighted average
which also involves
the chemical shift of
the deprotronated molecule.
And this is very simple.
The protronated chemical shift is weighted
with the concentration
of the protronated histidine,
and the deprotonated is weighted
with that concentration.
And then you divide it by the sum
of the two concentrations
so that it becomes again
a dimensionless quantity.
And then you have
the average chemical shift,
which is what we measure here.
So this is a weighted average.
Now it’s done here, this equation is shown
specifically for the case of histidine,
but of course, it can be quite universal.
It’s true for any acid base equilibrium.
It is also true if we have
multiple equilibria.
For example, if you have phosphoric acid,
which can occur as PO4H3,
PO4H2, PO4H1, PO43-.
All of these forms have
different chemical shifts
and different concentrations,
and therefore,
the weighted average will depend
on the pH and on the pks
and we can determine the pks
by measuring the chemical shift
as a function of pH.
This is a very important observation,
very universal in its applications.
So this concludes
part one of this chapter.
Thank you for your attention.