Welcome back to part two of this chapter.
So chemical shifts are often considered
as imperical quantities
that escape any attempt to explain them.
But of course, that's not true.
People, and chemists in particular,
physicists as well, would like
to give an explanation.
And there are in fact a wide variety
of explanations.
Some of them are conflicting.
Sometimes they make sense,
sometimes they dont.
And one has to be very careful
to pick one's way
among this minefield of explanations.
But let me give you some of the elements,
so you can judge yourself
how sound the science is.
So, here we have
Pauling's electronegativity.
We all know there is a series from iodine
to Bromine to chlorine to Fluorine,
where the electronegativity increases;
that is, to say,
the electron withdrawing ability.
And it turns out
that if we take methyl halides,
Ch3x, where x is one of the above,
then it turns out
that the chemical shift
of the protons of the methyl group
follows a particular trend,
which is roughly linear
with the Pauling definition
of electronegativity.
So you might say, the stronger
the withdrawal, the larger
the chemical shift
of the proton that is attached
to the methl group
that is neighboring
to the halide. So far, so good.
This makes sense. I wouldn't use it
as a way of determining
the electronegativity.
But you could, if you wish.
Now, it turns out that
the electronegativity has an effect
beyond the neighboring methyl group.
In fact, if we take a chlorine
at the end of a long chain--
so this is now one of the halides
at the end of a butane molecule.
You can see that the first
protons on the neighboring
methelyn group
are shifted all the way to the left
but the second one is affected much less.
The third one is hardly affected at all,
and the methyl group is so far away
that it has essentially the same
chemical shift as the methyl group
in a simple propane molecule.
So, this tells you something
about the range of this
electronegative electron
withdrawing effect.
There is an important aspect
when one tries to rationalize
chemical shifts that sometimes
they go hand in hand with the chemist
perception of how
the molecule really looks like.
And when I say "the chemist perception"
I mean the so-called
"resonance structure".
Take this simple aromatic molecule.
We know that the NO2 group
is an electron withdrawing group.
And the organic chemist rationalizes this
by saying that some small fraction of this
is not in fact as drawn here but that
the double bond migrates
to the single bond and becomes therefore
a double bond, and, concommitantly
there is a positive charge
that appears here on
the neighboring carbon.
And you can use one more step,
you can cause this double bond
to migrate here and then
the positive charge appears
in para position with respect
to the NO2- group.
Well, these structures are known as
resonance structures
and they're very familiar
to organic chemists because
they allow one to rationalize reactivity,
where do certain substituents go,
and questions like that.
And in fact, these pictures
have been developed hand-in-hand
with the observation of
the proton chemical shifts.
And you see an example here.
Nitrobenzene which are
these three molecules here.
Actually there are three different
chemical shifts.
There's one that is strongly
de-shielded with respect
to benzene, that is the one in the
ortho position.You can imagine
that because the electrons
are being withdrawn there is a lack of
an electron cloud and therefore
it's less shielded, and, likewise
in the para position, that is over here
there's a similar effect, although
it's much less pronounced.
It's a bit paradoxical because
in the resonance structures
there's really no need to say
that the ortho+ is dominant over the para+
but you see that, at least empirically,
it turns out that the effect
is most pronounced for the ortho
and very little for the para.
Meanwhile, according to this argument
the proton in the meta position,
that's this one here,
should not be affected at all.
Well, it is also affected somewhat
with respect to benzene
but apparently that's a different effect
than the resonance effect.
Now, the beauty of this argument
is the exact opposite
to what you see in aniline.
In aniline we have an electron donating
group, so we have the loan pair
on the nitrogen here this loan pair
can go here, and then this double bond
will move into this postiton
so that we have an excess charge here.
And in the second step, we can decide
to put that charge here
and put this one over here
so that we now have an excess charge
in the para position.
And consequently, you expect
the ortho position to be shielded
because there are more electrons
than there were before.
You de-localize them and therefore
it goes toward the right,
and the para position would be somewhat
less shielded, and the meta position
should not be shielded at all
but nevertheless, it is somewhat shielded.
You notice that
it's not exactly symmetrical.
For example, the para is very close
to the ortho here
where that's not the case
on the left side.
So, that shows that these arguments
are essentially qualitative
and you should not give them
the status of a serious theory
just more to guide the intuition.
But chemistry is a great deal
about intuition, so there's nothing wrong
with using that type of thinking.
Here we have an example of carbon 13
chemical shifts of para carbons
in substituted benzenes.
So, with reference to these molecules,
we're talking now about the carbon,
not the proton, the carbon,
that is in para position
with respect to the substituent,
and now we vary the substituent,
so we can put this NH2 here,
which is like here, the amine,
or, we can put the NO2, like here,
the nitro group, but there are
all sorts of things in between,
and we can use this chemical shift
scale here as a measure of the ability
of the substituents to donate electrons
into the phenol group, or to withdraw them
from the same aromatic ring.
So, this is a very nice way of classifying
the electronegativity of those groups,
and also, to predict the reactivity
which, of course,
is essential in chemistry.
There is a more exotic example.
In fact this was published many years ago
by Ray Freeman,
Ray Freeman was my PHD advisor
and Rex Richards
was his advisor, so, in a way
he is my intellectual grandfather,
if I dare say so, and I vividly recommend
you look up this publication
in the Proceedings of the Royal Society.
It's quite a few years ago,
but, nevertheless,
of great current interest.
Now, what these people did, they knew
that cobalt complexes, for example
here, with the nitrile group
the ethylene diamine, or
the ammonium, and all the others
that they have different colors,
and different optical transitions.
And these optical transitions are due
to the transition--
the crystal fuel splitting
between the so-called t2g orbitals
and the eg orbitals in the cobalt complex
which is in these cases, as always
in a hexagonal environment.
And what they found is, they started
measuring cobalt 58 chemical shifts.
Something that is not at all
common in the literature, but clearly
a heroic attempt to discover
a new correlation, and they found
a wonderful correlation, between
the chemical shift of the cobalt
and the wavelength in nanometers
of the optical transition.
So, this is somewhere in the visible
UV visible light.
Then they said, "Aha,
this has something to do with--
this is a contribution to
the chemical shift,"
which they attibuted
to what is now known as a paramagnetic
contribution to the shift.
They noticed that it's inversely
proportional to the parameter delta,
which is simply the splitting,
the transition frequency of the
optical transition, and they also
considered that it should be relevent
to include an average over R3 where R3
is basically the radius of the size of
the electron cloud that is responsible
for the chemical shift.
Now this is a really
beautiful observation,
very interesting, very stimulating,
but unfortunately, there are not many
molecules that behave in such a clear way,
not many examples of this effect.
Now, in the meantime, people have been
trying to split contributions
to nuclear shielding
into different parameters.
The effect that I spoke about
at the very beginning of chapter two
the one that we find in helium 3 and in
xenon 129 which, by the way, is also known
as the Lamb shift, is more properly
known as a diamagnetic shielding.
So, in diamagnetic shielding the induced
magnetic field, induced by the circulation
of the electrons, is anti-parallel
to the external field.
But we also have situations
where the shielding is paramagnetic.
In that case there is a
local field which is actually parallel
to the external field and therefore
adds up to the external field.
Then, there are effects which are due to
remote groups, or remote currents,
or currents in remote groups,
and of course, other sources.
Now, it's very nice to make
a list of these, but it's very difficult
in practice
to split and observe chemical shift
into separate contributions.
Now, remember here that the magnitudes
of induced diamagnetic and paramagnetic
currents can be related to local
electron densities, and to electronic
excitation energies.
So, this is clearly inspired by the work
of Ray Freeman and Rex Richards on cobalt
but is not necessarily of
universal application.
Some of the most important contributions
to chemical shifts are so-called
ring-current effects, which are specific
to aromatic compounds.
You see in this scheme here this ring here
is supposed to represent a benzene ring
or, in fact, any aromatic ring.
You see that the induced field, the field
induced by the electrons that circulate
in this ring is opposite to
the external field, and if we could have
a proton right in the center of the
benzene ring, it would be shielded
because it experiences a field that is
smaller than the external field.
But in fact, protons in benzene rings
as you know, are on the outside
of the ring, and therefore,
they experience a local magentic field
an induced field, which adds to the
external field.
And the result of that is that they appear
de-shielded.
Now, one way of measuring this effect
is comparing benzene, where the chemical
shift is about 7.3 ppm with respect to tms
with a form here where one of the three
double bonds has been reduced by addition
of a hydrogen molecule, and consequently
there is no possibility
for these electrons to run around a circle
and they cannot sustain a ring current,
and therefore not induce a magnetic dipole
that is opposite to the external dipole.
Well, you see immediately that
the chemical shift of this proton goes
from 7.3 to 5.9 so it has become shielded
or less de-shielded, if you prefer.
A more spectacular example here.
This molecule is a rather contrived
piece of chemistry, it was made
in the days when people were trying
to find extremes of the most de-shielded
or the most shielded compound
and the most important part of it
is that this methyl group here is just
above the aromatic ring.
This is the aromatic ring,
and the methyl group
is just above that ring.
And it turns out that it's not just
a bit shielded, but it is more shielded
than Tetramethylsilane,
so it has a negative
value, if you wish, to the right of tms
in an ordinary proton spectrum plotted
on the usual scale.
At the same time, all the protons
the aromatic protons, which you find here
and there are quite a few of them
they are in this range, that is to say
they are very far to the left
of the spectrum, or strongly de-shielded.
Perhaps a cleaner illustration of this
comes from this aniline which has slow
inter-conversion of internal and external
protons through reorientation,
but the basic thing is that because the
protons are on the inside of the ring
where the current is circulating,
they have a negative value
of the chemical shift delta
which means that they are
on the right hand side compared to tms,
whereas the other ones here just like
in benzene, they are de-shielded
and therefore on the left of the spectrum
You notice that one goes form 7.3 to 8.5
or so to 9.28, so this goes
more and more pronounced.
Now there are also interesting things
that happen if we have triple bonds and
other exotic pieces of chemistry
but triple bonds are not exotic at all.
In this case we have to worry about
something else, and that is about
the orientation of the triple bond
with respect to the external field.
And this, in fact, introduces a property
of chemical shifts which is very important
when we do solid state NMR, and that is
the chemical shift depends
on the orientation of the molecule
with respect to the external field.
And it turns out that somewhat against
intuition, as far as mine is concerned,
if the triple bond is perpendicular
to the external field, then there are
strong currents within this conjugated
by electron system, and the net
effect of that is a paramagnetic shift
where there is a strong dipole
which is parallel to the external field.
And therefore, we have these arrows here
representing flux, and you can see that
they will affect, for example,
the acetylenic protons here and here,
where they have a situation
which is actually opposite
to what happens in,
for example, benzene.
But the situation is compounded
by the fact that--
the complexity is compounded
by the fact that
if the triple bond parallel to the field,
then we have to draw it this way.
It turns out that these electrons
circulate less freely in this situation
and therefore, the induced
paramagnetic dipole is weaker.
If the dipole were equal here and here
and if one then invokes isotropic tumbling
of the molecules so they can adopt
all possible orientations in space,
then there would be no net effect.
But there is an imbalance, you see.
Here the paramagnetic induced dipole
is strong and here it is weak.
And therefore, there is no averaging
when it tumbles over
all possible positions.
This has curious effects.
For example, if we take a famous series,
so this is just ethane CH3 CH3.
It is not very far from methane.
And it's on the right hand side,
close to 1 ppm.
If we now introduce a double bond,
we jump from here to here.
And if we introduce a triple bond,
you might think that we go even further.
Well, that's not true
in fact, we go back one step, so to speak.
And that is because of the anisotropy
of the triple bond of the electron
motion with the triple bond.
Such things can be represented in terms of
regions of shielding and deshielding.
So we can distinguish such cases
where the dipole, the paramagnetic dipole
for the parallel position is larger
than the dipole for the perpendicular
position, in which case we get
a distribution of fields like this
or the opposite case, where of course
we have opposite signs.
Notice that these are drawn
on these cones.
In fact these cones are schematic
representations of tensars
and they look a bit like orbitals.
You may notice that the angle
subtendance by these cones
is this angle here, we shall refer to that
as the magic angle, and in fact it's about
54 degree, and we shall see that if we
somehow orient molecules in a solid
along that line we get
a simplified spectrum that is also
the basis of magic angle spinning.
Now there are some implications of
these neighboring groups.
We spoke about acetyline.
We spoke about the proton
which is attached,
the acetylinic proton,
but more spectacular effects occur
in molecules such as this.
So this is the simple phenantrene
where this aromatic proton rosonates
at about 8 and something ppm
but here it is sort of squeezed
very close to the triple bond,
and you see it has a massive affect
of nearly 2 ppm, further deshielded
because of the anisotropy of the
neighboring group.
This is now the neighboring group,
and it has an affect on the chemical shift
which of course, does not occur
if the triple bond is absent.
So this is deshielding due to
magnetic anisotropy.
Now there are some things which are
perhaps more important to the chemist
and here we see a case of deshielding
due to hydrogen bonding.
Hydrogen bonding, of course, is essential
in chemistry and also in biology.
Remember that if we think of
double stranded DNA, the two strands
are held together by very, very weak
interactions called hydrogen bonds.
It is only because there are
so many of them
that these two strands hold together.
So, characterizing hydrogen bonds
is actually quite important in chemistry.
And here we see an example,
or two examples, actually;
we see that the proton here, which is
sort of sharing it's attention between
two oxygens- I'm not saying it's
symmetrically distributed.
There's a proper bond to this oxygen
and a weaker bond to that oxygen-
but you see that the electron cloud is
very weak and very diminished
around that hydrogen, and therefore
it is very much deshielded, and in fact
its chemical shift is 11
and something ppm.
A more simple example here,
we see that this hydrogen really doesn't
know where it wants to go,
because the whole molecule can be redrawn
the double bonds can hop around, and
the net effect is that this
hydrogen is almost bare.
There are almost no electrons
to shield it, and therefore
it turns out very heavily deshielded
because there are no
electrons to shield it.
And that, of course, is characteristic
of such hydrogen bonds.
And as I said, we find similar things
in DNA, deoxyribonucleic acids, and also
in RNAs which are very popular today
to study by Bio-NMR.
Now, there's another picture which
I think is very instructive, and I must
say that Peter Hall did a tremendous job
in selecting good examples, and this is
the one of ethanol.
Now ethanol, we all know, and some of us
know too well, which I can write it
like this, and I give it a little bend
because next to it, I shall be drawing
another ethanol molecule, very similar
structure but just drawn head to tail.
And this is known as an ethanol dimer.
And it turns out that the dimer
holds together with
these two hydrogen bonds.
And because there are these intermolecular
hydrogen bonds, the electron density
around each of these two hydrogens
is very weak, very diminished
and we are, in effect, in a position
similar to this, and so the chemical shift
of the hydrogen is very much to the left.
Or, it's very deshielded.
Well, that's why in ordinary ethanol
if we have one mole of ethanol in a
product solvent such as tetrachlorocarbon
then we have the OH, which as you can see,
appears about near 5 and something ppm.
But, as we dilute the ethanol to a tenth
of a mole per liter to a hundredths
to a thousandths, we see that the OH
resonance moves to the right.
And that is because, as we dilute
we can break up this dimer so that
it falls apart into monomers.
And because the solvent here,
the product solvent is unable of making
any hydrogen bonds with either of these
monomers, the hydrogen is less deplenished
or its environment is less depleted
of electrons and therefore
it's more shielded, and as you can see
it moves toward lower ppm values,
lower chemical shifts.
Now, you will notice that this is not
an experimental spectrum.
In fact there's no reference
given to it either in the book.
And the reason is that
it's not so easy to observe this
hydrogen because the hydrogen will also
exchange by chemical exchange,
and therefore, the very least that can
happen is that it would be very broad,
And sometimes it is also at a different chemical shift.
That depends on the entire structure.
But it's an interesting principle,
and the demonstration is very nicely done.
Now, let me take you to one of the last
examples, and this is unpaired electrons.
There are lots of systems
in organic chemistry, where we have
free electrons or unpaired electrons.
In organic chemistry we call them radicals
in metals we don't call them radicals.
Simply, they have electrons that are not
paired up in pairs in individual orbitals.
Iron is a good example of an atom,
of a metal, that often has
unpaired electrons.
Zinc, on the other hand,
has an even number of electrons
that are nicely paired up.
So, what you see here is a complex spectra
these are proton NMR spectra
of complexes such as this
where the four nitrogens hold the metal
ion in the middle,
And this metal can be
either zinc or iron.
And what we actually observe is the
chemical shifts of this Hx here
and of the Hy.
As you go around the ring you will see
there's really only two chemical shifts-
they alternate, so there's
two Hx's, an Hy--
But that's not important here.
The important part is that if we have zinc
in the center, then it's not paramagnetic.
There are no free electrons, and we have
a simple case where all these are
aromatic protons and they resonate
somewhere between 8 and 9 ppm,
which is fine, nothing abnormal.
But, if we replace the zinc by iron-
Iron 2 I believe it's in this case-
then, we see tremendous change.
They are dramatically shielded,
one could say, or shifted
towards the right hand side in this scale.
And X and Y no longer similar.
The near degeneracy that we have
in the zinc case is now lifted.
Now this is due the coupling between
the free electrons and these protons.
A long range coupling which
in fact is known as
hyperfine coupling and which leads
to a shift because the distribution
of the polarization between alpha and beta
states for an electron is not 50/50
but it's displaced towards the lowest
energy state following the Boltzmann rule.
And in fact it's the rapid transitions
between electrons in the alpha
and the beta state which
give rise to an average chemical shift,
if you will, or an average position
of the proton lines which depend
on the environment.
So, to conclude this second chapter
of Peter Hall's little book, let's look
at the summary that the author
has put together
at the end of the chapter.
First of all, we notice that nuclei
such as protons, are embedded
in molecules, and that that they may have
slightly different NMR frequencies
depending on the environment,
an effect that is known as
the chemical shift.
Such effects occur not only for protons,
but also for carbon 13, nitrogen 15
phosphorus 31, and depending on
the sort of system that we're looking at
silicon 29, and many other nuclei
in the periodic table.
Chemical shifts arise from
induced electronic currents
which can either shield or deshield
the nuclei from
the applied magnetic field.
The chemical shift parameter delta
is used to quantify the extent,
the degree,
of nuclear shielding or deshielding
with respect to a conventional reference,
sometimes detramethylsiline
for protons and carbon
and other nuclei have
different standards, of course.
So, the magnitudes of induced diamagnetic
and paramagnetic currents
can be related to local electron densities
and electronic excitation energies.
Chemical shifts can often be understood by
considering the effects of
electron donating
and electron withdrawing groups
by looking at the effects
of induced currents in neighboring groups
such as triple bonds or aromatic rings,
looking at charged or polar groups
at the role of hydrogen bonds
and of unpaired electrons
which have hyperfine couplings
to the nuclei that we are looking at.
Chemical shifts distinguish nuclei
in different environments in molecules
and therefore give information
both on the molecular identity
and on the molecular structure.