Welcome through these video on urban context
in humanitarian crisis.
The learning objectives of these videos are;
to understand why urban conflicts are so important
in today's humanitarian crisis, to understand
the concept of urban
essential services
and finally we discuss on the underlying vulnerabilities
of urban areas.
The world is getting more urban and the conflicts
as well.
Some fifty million people worldwide are afflicted
by armed conflicts in urban areas.
In addition, it is also estimated that eighty
percent of displaced people find refuge in
urban areas.
On top of that, there is a sharp increase
of protracted conflicts all around the world
resulting in an unprecedented level of
humanitarian needs.
Protracted conflict seen urban areas is a
challenge for humanitarian response.
Indeed humanitarian approach has been
many designed to address needs in camps or
rural contexts.
There is a lack of expertise
and knowledge for urban settings.
In addition current funding mechanism
and program in both million a yearly basis
are not adapted to respond to humanitarian
crises due to protracted
come conflicts.
Urban areas are undoubtedly complex and so
in it's definition as well.
Tokyo and the village of two thousand people
in Angola are both of usually classified as
urban.
There is clearly no agreed definition of the
term.
Definition of urban are normally based on
population density
or geographic area defined by municipal authorities.
In this course we adopt a different approach.
We propose that for humanitarian action urban
context to be defined as the
area within which civilians vulnerable to
the distruption in essential services reside.
And the network of complements supporting
their services.
As shown in this figure, critical components
of essential services for instance electrical
power plants, supply routes
water and wastewater treatment plants are
often located outside the city limits.
Very distant active combat can verse have
a dramatic effect on urban dwellers.
Essential urban services are understood to
be those services that are vital to ensure
the subsistence of the civilian
population including electricity, water, health,
waste water treatment and solid waste disposal.
All are banned services require three elements
in order to function.
People.
Meaning service providers staff, private sector
contractors or entrepreneurs
Hardware.
meaning the infrastructure but as well the
equipment and the machinery.
And consumables.
Meaning the fuel, the medicines etc.
Disruption to an essential servce occurs when
the function of any of the critical people,
hardware
or consumable are compromised.
Shut down distruption to an essential service
may not have a major impact on the survival
of the Syrian population.
Why?
It's a
deterioration over the long term pose a greater
risk as we see later on
Urban areas are very complex and characterized
by a number of features which result in the
residents being particularly exposed
and vulnerable to armed conflict.
The main vulnerability of people in urban
context is their reliance on essential services.
The services are beyond the technical capacity
of the direct physical control of the residents.
It affect the resilience
of the inhabitants.
The essential services consist of sophisticated
large scale infrastructure which rely on the
virility of special
expertise, a potentially fragile governance
structures or complex logistics.
Some essential services depend on others simply
not there to not to fail.
For instance, let's say the quality of health
services we depend on potable water on the
consumable and reliable power supply.
Another example ground water, which can be
as well contaminated by a properly maintained
landfill site.
Another factor affecting the vulnerability
is the scale.
Because of the relatively large special scale
of urban
context, distruption to
an essential service can have a large scale
impact.
The destruction of a single power line can
result in an electricity
blackout across an entire neighborhood comprising
maybe two hundred thousand people.
Finally densely populated urban areas are
not only at greater risk from epidemic, there
are also setting in
which people can more readily clash with each
other along opposing political, sectarian
or tribal lines
or across musical political borders as well
the authorities.
Humanitarian response in urban areas is a
major challenge of today's humanitarian crisis.
In other to summarize this introduction on
urban context.
Let's watch the following I.C.R.C.
Documentary on urban challenges.
Supplying water in an urban environment
is a unique, complex challenge.
Water is usually concentrated in one place
and is pumped
or otherwise taken
from its source to be treated.
All it takes is for a bomb to hit
the pumping station or water pipe,
and the supply to 100,000 people
is cut off.
Sadly, water supplies often
become strategic targets in conflict.
You cut the water and
you immediately drive people away.
The ICRC has a key role to play.
Firstly by reminding the parties to
the conflict to spare such infrastructure,
and secondly by restoring water supplies
when they are cut.
We have to be very creative.
We successfully built
a waste-water treatment plant
serving more than 150,000 people
in the city of Rafah.
Our engineers had the ingenious idea
of using bits of the old wall between
Egypt and the Gaza Strip
to lay the foundations
for the treatment pools.
It gave people hope to see that
it was still possible to do something
in Gaza despite the blockade.
that also enabled us to begin talks
with the Israeli authorities.
We succeeded in bringing in the machinery
needed to complete the treatment plant.
No power means no water.
It was a major challenge for the ICRC
to restore power.
during the fighting,
power cuts were frequent.
On several occasions,
for their own safety,
the ICRC escorted technicians
from Gaza city to installations.
Their job was to put damaged electricity
poles back up
and restore the power supply.
a gaza without power is a Gaza
without water
and without functioning hospitals.
It's straightaway a humanitarian disaster.
There is a direct correlation between
water shortages or poor-quality water
and diseases such as cholera.
We see this time and time again.
Whenever people face water shortages
or the water has not been treated
properly,
we immediately see outbreaks of disease.
Working in an urban setting means
trying to improve water supplies.
We do this in partnership with
the national,
regional and local water boards.
Their staff have often had to leave
the country because of conflict
and have to be retrained with our help.
the key here is communication,
dialogue and mutual understanding
both with the parties to the conflict
and with public services.
In Haiti, the ICRC's role was vital.
For years, we oversaw the installation
and repair of water supply points
in Cité-Soleil.
At the time, the neighbourhood
was controlled by gangs
and the authorities were unable to enter.
The ICRC also gave the authorities
the confidence to start working there
again.
Initially, we accompanied them when
they entered the neighbourhood
to repair the water-supply network.
We were the only ones able to carry out
such a large-scale project.
We're talking about providing
200,000 people with drinking water
for several years, thanks to this project.
The authorities have now almost
fully resumed control.
they enter the neighbourhood unaccompanied
and make repairs without ICRC help.
One of the trends observed by the ICRC
is rampant urbanization.
More and more neighbourhoods
are springing up
on the outskirts of cities
Public services cannot keep up.
Water supplies are often non-existent
or very inefficient.
The supply network often breaks down
and these are areas where tensions
often erupt.
This trend is set to continue.
We must maintain our expertise
and be ready to enter these neighbourhoods
to install or restore the water supply,
or to get the authorities in charge
to do so.
The results speak for themselves.
Restoring water to a frightened community,
facing the fatal consequences
of a lack of water,
is hugely satisfying.