Hello and welcome to the third week of the
course!
My name is Maryna Peter, I work for the University
of Applied Sciences Northwestern Switzerland,
Institute of Ecopreneurship.
I am a research scientist and an engineer
working in the field of drinking water supply
and treatment in the low-income country context.
This week we will focus on the drinking water
supply systems and technologies.
Although, the major focus is on the engineering
aspects, we should keep in mind that management,
organization, regulatory aspects as well as
user perception and participation are as important
as proper planning and engineering.
Let’s have look at the Learning objectives
of the week 3 of the course.Those are:
-To learn the six functional groups of a water
supply system
- Understand which technologies belong to
which functional group
- Understand basic principles and functionality
of each technology
Finally in order to be able to define strategy
in an emergency response, we will discuss
immediate and long term actions for the development
or rehabilitation of a water supply system
in an emergency context.
What is a water supply system? Lets see – there
is a pure spring in the mountains.
We protect it, and deliver water by gravity
to the village nearby, where it can be collected
at the standpipe.
Or we build an intake on the river down in
the valley, pump water up to the drinking
water treatment plant.
Treated water is pumped further and stored
at the tank, from where it is further distributed
to the town through a distribution system.
In the village further down the valley, people
collect water at the protected well with a
hand-pump.
They carry water in jerry cans home.
A local NGO has distributed the household
filters to treat water at home in this village
next to the river.
Few households also collect rainwater from
their roofs and store it in rainwater tanks.
All these different types of water supply
systems have different scale.
However, they have all the same steps:
Water source – spring, well, surface or
groundwater,
water intake structure – be it either a
protected river intake, spring catchment,
dug well or rainwater gutter
abstraction technology – such as hand pump
or motorized pump
water treatment – if it is required
water transport – either through a network
or with jerry cans
and water storage (rainwater tanks) or treatment
(HWTS) at the user level.
Most water supply systems can be structured
along these 6 functional groups.
The technologies from each functional group
perform specific tasks of the water supply
system and can be linked between each other
to show possible combinations.
It is not always necessary that water passes
through all functional groups to reach the
consumer.
In some systems treatment is excluded due
to high quality of source water, or water
is supplied by gravity and no pumping is needed.
However, water always moves from left to right
through the functional groups or from top
down within the group.
Here you see an example for a centralized
or a semi-centralized system supplying and
treating surface water.
Surface water is collected at a protected
or unprotected river or lake intake, is delivered
with means of gravity or motorized pumping
to the treatment plant.
there it is clarified and disinfected and
either is being sold at a water kiosk or fed
into the distribution network.
Safe water storage at home might be needed
to cover for interruptions for a decentralized
water supply system including use of high
quality groundwater, the system will be simpler,
excluding treatment step.
In some cases, household water treatment might
be included to reduce health risks due to
recontamination of water during transport.
What you have seen on this and past slides
are the system templates.
These kind of system templates can be developed
for different settings.
In general, we define 9 major different system
templates:
This different system templates as well as
information sheets to each technology are
summarized in the Compendium of Drinking Water
System and technologies from Source to Consumer.
The technologies presented in the compendium
and links between them are not exhaustive.
Planners and designers should try to make
the best use of available resources, optimize
or rehabilitate existing infrastructure while
taking into account local enabling environment
including local capacities and skills, financial
resources, regulations and socio-cultural
preferences and acceptance.
The following steps can be used to pre-select
potential water supply options:
1.Identify water sources which are available
and accessible
2.Identify system templates which include
and address these water sources
3.For each template, select a technology from
each functional group out of boxes with multiple
technologies.
In the functional group "Treatment", multiple
technologies depending on potential contamination
of water source needed to be selected.
The series (following the arrows) of technologies
make up a system.
Compare different systems and iteratively
change individual technologies or use different
system templates based on priorities of the
users or community, scale, environment and
resources available.
Sometimes, it can be useful to carefully consider
the geography of the area and divide it into
sub-areas depending on the availability and
location of water sources, population characteristics
and other environmental conditions.
The procedure can be followed for each of
the sub-areas and few systems can be chosen.
Usually part of water sources can already
be used and some infrastructure be available.
It is always recommended to integrate existing
infrastructure or services into the planning
process, but one needs to be flexible enough
to exclude it if user safety or acceptance
is an issue.
In an emergency, we can apply the same functional
groups considering that not all technologies
would be appropriate.
However, use of available resources, infrastructure
and skills gains even more importance.
It can be important to consider immediate
simple basic measures to improve current poor
water supply system first before planning
for a more sophisticated long-lasting infrastructure.
Protecting the source is one of the possible
measures.
Relocating defecation or washing areas as
well as animal access downhill can have a
strong immediate impact on water quality as
well.
Fencing, rainfall run-off trenches around
springs as well as walls and better access
pathways to open wells are another examples
of immediate improvement measures.
After protecting the source, we have to thing
along the water supply chain and try to organize
missing on non functional infrastructure such
as pumps and storage tanks.
Controlled distribution as well as making
containers for storing water available belongs
also to the immediate measures.
When water is likely to be polluted, chlorination
of water at the storage tanks or tankers,
dosing of water to water collection containers
or disinfecting water directly at the well
might be the only feasible way to prevent
disease outbreaks.
When basic measures are in place, further
upgrading of the system can be required.
Here, we have to think beyond the water source
only.
A properly designed water supply and distribution
system is often the next step and planning
it early enough helps to avoid unnecessary
efforts and expenditures for maintaining temporary
built possibly fragile and unreliable infrastructure.
In case we are talking about displaced population,
we should consider the needs and situation
of the local communities and possibly upgrade
the services for them as well.
As any water supply system, adequate source
or multiple sources with proper intake structures,
adequate storage capacity for uninterrupted
water supply as well as efficient distribution
are the main components of the system.
When basic water supply system is in place,
it can make sense to aim for the further improvement
achieving smaller distances and waiting times
at the water points for people, eliminating
direct contact to water source and, thus,
its contamination, lower wastage of water
at the source fairer distribution and sufficient
level of services to reduce water related
health risks.
And finally, probably, one of the most important
factors - we should safeguard and protect
water sources from a negative impact an increased
population numbers or disrupted sanitation
services can cause.
In this lecture, we have looked at different
water supply systems as a combination of technologies
from six functional groups.
Basically any water supply system can be pictured
so, independently on its scale.
However, flexibility is always required: adapt
your system to local needs, geography, availability
of skills and resources as well as preferences
and needs.
Never one size fits all.
Simple and fast measures to improve current
systems before designing and installing more
sophisticated water supply should always be
considered on a short term.
On a longer term, progressive improvement
of the supply system as well as safeguarding
it against contamination are further crucial
steps.
During the next lectures, we will move through
all functional groups,
its more or less detail
and discuss technologies of each group.
See you soon !