Previously, you learned different functional
groups.
Today I would like to talk in more detail
about the first functional group – water
sources.
We will get familiar with the water cycle
and different water sources, identify major
criteria for choosing a water source, get
familiar with immediate and long-term measures
needed and understand the advantages, limitations
and sensitivities of different water sources.
Lets look at the natural water cycle.
Rainwater falls onto the ground.
When collected directly from an available
roof structure or a constructed ground catchment
area can supplement other sources of water
even if it is not used as the main water supply.
Rain water becomes surface water as soon as
it reaches the ground.
Directly or as surface runoff it accumulates
in surface depressions.
While lakes, reservoirs or ponds are standing
or slow-moving water bodies, rivers or streams
flow by gravity across the land towards the
sea or another river or lake.
Surface water is the easiest source to access,
but not necessarily the easiest source to
use for water supply.
Rainwater falling onto the ground infiltrates
through the soil, fractures and openings in
rock until it reaches the water table and
joins the groundwater flow system.
The geological formation or layer consisting
of pervious materials and conducting water
is called aquifer.
There is always a balance between the amount
of water stored in an aquifer, the volume
of water which leaves the aquifer through
natural groundwater flow and abstraction by
pumping and the amount of water it receives
through recharge.
If the balance is negative and excessively
more water is pumped than recharged, pumping
will increasingly become more expensive and
the well eventually will run dry.
How do we select a water source?
First we need to identify water sources which
could be used without tinkering.
For each source, we consider four major criteria:
1.
Water quantity – what is a yield of the
water source and how does it relates to the
demand?
Is the source intermittent or strongly affected
by seasonality?
The minimum yield of the water source should
still be greater than demand.
If this is not the case, combination of several
sources to cover demand should be considered.
Sufficient storage capacity might help to
improve reliability of supply.
While this open well is full throughout the
year, during few month of the dry season,
water level sinks considerably.
Water quality.
Obviously, it is always advisable to choose
the source with the better water quality.
Surface water and often karstic springs are
likely to be affected by increased turbidity
and organic matter content, especially during
rain events.
High content of particles and organic matter
complicates water disinfection and overall
water treatment system.
Groundwater is rather likely to have low turbidity
and lower content of pathogenic microorganisms
compared to surface waters.
Although the goal is always to provide sufficient
amount of good quality water, it is not always
possible in an emergency context.
If there is an alternative, large quantities
of reasonably good quality water should always
be preferred to small quantities of very good
quality water.
Consider how water quality is and will be
affected in future by sanitation practices,
agriculture and possible point contamination
sources.
On this picture you see that water is obviously
turbid, and obviously is used by animals.
The third criteria is the type of the technology
and resources required for exploitation of
the water source.
In all cases – use the help of gravity to
avoid pumping water, if you can.
If technology is available in place, are there
also skills and qualified people for source
exploitation and for future maintenance?
The costs of source exploitation including
initial investment, operational and maintenance
costs need to be considered as well.
Time required for exploitation of the source
need to be taken into consideration in an
emergency context as well.
The forth important criteria is accessibility
and acceptance of the source.
Any obvious legal, security, social, political
or cultural constrains should be taken into
account.
If needed and possible they should be reduced
to a level acceptable to users.
It might take long time to influence or change
a certain culturally influenced behavior in
one case.
An in another case, sometimes a short intensive
hygiene promotion campaign can be very effective.
And the last, use of water source can have
environmental and health impacts which might
not be obvious at a first step.
If you plan for a long term - take environment
into the equation to avoid for example creation
of mosquito breeding places, or consider what
effect a failing dam might have on the downstream
population.
River is a natural flow of fresh water across
the land towards a sea, another river or lake.
A catchment area of a river is the area from
which any particular river receives both surface
flow and drainage water originating from precipitation.
Throughout the course of a river, the water
transported downstream is in constant interaction
with underlying groundwater system, and may
gain or loose water to groundwater.
Seasonal variations, up to complete drying
of a river are expected.
Lakes and ponds are standing or slow moving
surface water bodies which form naturally
from rain, surface run-off or river water.
Reservoirs are man-made lakes which are created
by flooding the land behind a dam.
Besides the interconnection between groundwater
and lake water which depends on soil structure,
losses through evaporation should be taken
into consideration.
River and lake water quality is highly variable
by nature due to types of rocks, vegetation,
climate, and human activities such as discharge
of wastewater, industrial waste and surface
run-off from fields.
In most cases, the quality of surface water
sources is poor and water requires treatment.
An exception can be upstream water close to
the source in mountain areas which can be
free of contamination and can be collected
and delivered through simple gravity supply
system.
For lakes and ponds, water quality in the
center of the lake might be considerably better
than close to the shore due to settling, natural
biological processes and sunlight degrading
contamination.
If surface water is affected by poorly treated
industrial wastewater discharge, it should
really be considered as the last possible
option as treatment of such water is highly
complex.
Rivers are multiple sources of water and water
is used for irrigation, bathing, washing of
clothes, industry and ecosystem services.
Development of water sources through dams
and intakes in many cases cause deterioration
of its quality, limited access of the downstream
population and degradation of ecosystem services
with numerous negative consequences.
Groundwater flowing naturally from the earth
subsurface to the surface forms a spring.
Flow may be identified at a certain point
which is called spring eye.
If it is rather more diffuse area, it is called
seepage.
The locations of the springs can change due
to changes in the water table during the dry
and wet season.
Green vegetation contrasting to the surrounding
sometimes can help to identify the springs
at a distance.
Otherwise, reading and understanding of geological
maps as well as practical experience will
be necessary to locate the springs.
Compared to other water sources, tapping springs
is rather cheap considering that construction
costs are comparably low and no pump is needed
for water abstraction.
A good well requires an appropriate source
of groundwater, but locating it is difficult.
Like surface water, ground water flow is influenced
by gravity, unless it meets less permeable
rock.
Thus, obviously, groundwater is likely to
be closer to the surface in the bottom of
the valley than on top of a mountain.
However, siting a well usually will require
a hydrogeologist with considerable practical
expertise, information on the local geological
formations and good luck.
Existing records on the available dug wells
and boreholes with soil data, yield and depth
might provide additional information which
can help to site the well.
Having located a good source of groundwater,
we would need to chose an appropriate well
construction method.
The flow of groundwater is slower due to resistance
caused by interconnected system of pores,
spaces, fractures and varies from few meters
per day to few meters per year.
It depends also on the hydraulic gradient.
The result of the slow movement of water is
that there is sufficient time to dissolve
chemicals from the rocks and soils it passes
through.
Water spending long time underground in rather
soluble rock areas will have higher total
dissolved solids which can lead to the increased
salinity of water.
Thus, salinity values measured by conductivity
probes might give an indication on the risks
caused by pit latrines and other possible
relevant sources of contamination.
Once groundwater is polluted, it is very difficult
to restore its quality.
Rainwater can be collected from roofs and
stored in rain water tank or collected as
surface run-off in rainwater catchment dams
or reservoirs.
It is rarely used as a major water source,
but rather to supplement existing sources.
The quality of rain water collected from the
roofs is usually good if it is collected through
an adequate rain water harvesting system,
properly stored and supplied.
Improper roofing materials, roof contamination
through bird droppings, dust and insects,
luck of first flush mechanism, poor collection
and storage design will inevitably lead to
recontamination, poor water quality as well
as algal growth and mosquito breeding in storage
tanks.
Seawater has a salinity of 3.5% meaning that
every liter of water contains 35 g of salt
per liter.
Total dissolved solids content is usually
used to describe the content of salt and minerals.
Brackish water forming usually in the areas
of mixing of salt water and fresh water, such
as estuaries or in groundwater has a TDS between
1000-10000 mg/L. To remove salt from water,
desalination is required.
Desalination has high energy demand.
Concentrated salt solution is produced as
a waste stream during some desalination processes
requires careful disposal, as it can lead
to strong deterioration of the environment
and cause risk of salinization of other groundwater
and surface water sources.
Due to high costs, high maintenance requirements
of desalination technologies, it is usually
advisable to consider desalination as the
last possible option and chose other available
sources.
To sum up:
- Water quantity, quality, technology required
for exploitation as well as accessibility
and acceptance are the major criteria we use
to chose a water source
- Surface waters are likely to be polluted
and often affected by seasonality
- Finding groundwater is not easy and requires
expertise.
Protection of sources needed.
- Desalination of sea or brackish waters as
well as using industrially polluted waters
should be the last possible option