In this lecture we will look in more detail
at different water intakes.
We will get to know most commonly used water
intake structures, will discuss applicability
of different intakes under certain conditions
as well as their major advantages and disadvantages.
Rain water collection systems include roof
water collection system if possible with first
flush mechanism to discharge possibly contaminated
fist roof run-off just at the beginning of
raining event.
Usually those are simple gutters connected
to the water storage tanks.
In dry areas rain water may become an important
or even major water source and surface runoff
is collected by constructing a rain water
catchment dam.
In dry areas rain water may become an important
or even major water source and surface runoff
is collected by constructing a rain water
catchment dam over a natural rain water catchment
area.
The dam blocks rainwater run-off and is collected
in an reservoir and stored over loner time.
The reservoirs are usually constructed in
a way that they provide sufficient water for
the whole year.
High contamination of water as well as risk
of mosquito breeding are the major disadvantages
of these system.
Surface water intakes differ depending on
the characteristics of rivers or lakes.
Usually these are simple and robust structures
generally located upstream of industries,
densely populated areas, intensively used
agricultural areas or wastewater discharge
places.
Unprotected river intake consists of a submerged
pipe placed on the bottom of the river (figures
a and b).
The outlet of the pipe is elevated from the
bottom of the river and protected with a screen
and a strainer to avoid sand, gravel or fish
entering the pipes.
Sand entering the pump can damage most pumps
irreversibly within seconds.
Protected river intake includes a number of
screens to keep out floating material such
as trees and branches . The protected intake
should be elevated to at least 1 m above the
riverbed to avoid entering of boulders and
rolling stones.
The inlets should be always submerged at least
0.3 m under the surface to avoid formation
of water vortices leading to suction of air
which could affect the pump.
Seasonal changes of water level should e considered
during design and planning.
Floating intakes are used to abstract water
near the surface to avoid silt loads which
form at the bottom of the water source . A
flexible plastic pipe is connected to a float
(‘pontoon’), which can be constructed
by attaching a steel or wooden frame to floats
made from empty drums or plastic containers.
Screens should be used to retain coarse material
floating on the surface which might clog pipes
and pumps.
Riverbank intake works by constructing a well
from the river (ca. 50 m riverbank) to tap
the sub-surface flow.
Since water is filtered through the river
bank, the microbiological water quality is
improved.
The top of the well should be sealed to prevent
contamination of the abstracted water.
Spring water collection systems are constructed
to catch and protect quality of the spring
water.
For gravity springs, a spring box is usually
installed which collects the water from the
aquifer and channels it to a single discharge
point.
From there spring water can be led to a storage
tank.
A spring box provides many benefits since
it protects the water from contamination,
stores the water and also acts as settling
basin of particles such as sand and silt.
Contamination from the surface is prevented
through a concrete seal on the surface and
through the placement of a drain which diverts
infiltrating surface water away from the spring
box.
When groundwater source is located an appropriate
well construction method should be chosen.
Depending on the retype of soil, depth of
groundwater, required capacity and availability
of technology and skills, wells can be built
in a variety of ways.
These included wells, hand drilled wells,
jetted wells, wells build by percussion, direct
or reverse circulation rotary drilling or
down the hole hummer.
In this picture here, you can see an example
of drilling truck.
Lets look at the few types of the wells in
more detail.
Dug wells are traditional methods to extract
shallow groundwater.
Dug wells are often excavated manually (‘hand-dug
well’) are large enough for persons to go
in and clean it or deepen it.
A protected dug well consist of a well head
and a well shaft which is lined with strong
material down to 3-4m below the water table
. The well head is the visible structure at
the surface and is composed of a concrete
seal, a well cover (‘apron’), a safe water
lifting device such as a hand pump and a drainage
channel.
Under the well head follows the well shaft
and the intake area where groundwater can
be accessed by the pump.
At least the top 5 m of the well shaft should
by lined to stabilize the well and ensure
that surface water entering the well has been
filtered during the passage.
A borehole is a hole drilled into the ground
reaching groundwater bodies.
Groundwater infiltrates the well and is extracted
with manual or motorized pumps.
After drilling a hole, several elements have
to be added before the well can be used.
The well head (‘apron’) and sanitary concrete
seal protect the hole from contaminants entering
the well;
Similarly like for the dug-wells.
The well casing stabilizes the well from collapsing
and infiltration from contaminants.
Steel and PVC pipes are normally used for
lining the well walls.
The well screen holds back sediments but not
water from entering the well.
When using PVC pipes for the lining, these
can be slit to create fine cuts acting as
barrier for sediments.
The gravel pack between the screen and the
borehole is required if the soil grains are
smaller than the screen slots.
Generally boreholes are less subjected to
contamination compared to dug wells.
Some of the drilling methods are faster and
safer compared to dug wells.
However, drilling needs expertise and availability
of the technology as well as more professional
and complex maintenance.
In contrary, dug wells have lower costs than
drilled wells for construction and maintenance.
So, to sum up, during this lecture we have
shortly reviewed different water intake structures
and their applicability for different type
of sources.
Surface water intake structures vary depending
if protection of the intake from rolling stones
or debris is needed or not, water level changes
as well as need of water pre-filtration through
water infiltration wells.
The rainwater collection system differ depending
if water is collected from roof and used as
a supplementary water source during the rain
season, or if year-lasting water supply is
needed and larger catchment area needs to
be used.
Variety of well construction methods exist,
which depend on soil characteristics as well
as required depth and capacity and availability
of tools and skills.
Dug wells are rather traditional, simple and
well accepted technology, which is lower in
costs than drilled wells.
However, construction of the drilled wells
is faster and safer compared to dug wells,
risk of contamination is lower and deeper
groundwater layers can be accessed.