Hello.
Water abstraction involves collecting raw
water at the source intake system and transporting
it to the treatment plant, storage tank, distribution
network or directly to the consumer, depending
on the scale and design of the system.
Today we will look at different water abstraction
technologies, such as gravity supplies, pump
types and energy sources needed to drive them.
We consider in more detail the basic working
principles of different pump types as well
as their applicability and limitations.
Finally, we will look at how to read and understand
the pump curves needed for selecting and specifying
an appropriate pump and consider main factors
influencing operation of a pumping station.
The best way to abstract water in many cases
is by using gravity.
Gravity flow water supply is a system in which
water falls due to its own weight from a source
situated above, to the users below.
The process is driven by the potential energy
water has due to its elevation.
Due to missing moving parts, relative simplicity
of the system, the gravity water supply schemas
do not require complex maintenance and are
rather robust and reliable.
To design a gravity flow water supply system
you would need to calculate the pipe diameter
required, considering the elevation difference
and losses due to friction in the pipe as
well as energy losses produced by turbulence
introduced by everything which is not straight:
valves, elbows, reductions.
Furthermore, you would need to study the topography
of the system to minimize high and low points
which can lead to the air trapping or accumulation
of sediments and to avoid negative pressures.
Break-pressure tanks might be required if
heights difference is considerable.
There are few softwares and freeware available,
which can help you to design a gravity flow
system, without having a full understanding
of the system hydraulics.
If location of the water sources and topographical
characteristics of the area do not allow the
use of gravity, pumps need to be used.
Pumps are used to lift water against the gravity
or pressurize it to move it through a pipeline
at a required flow rate.
A huge variety of technologies have evolved
and have been introduced for different uses
and needs.
The pumps are often grouped according to the
type of operation to manual and motorized
pumps.
For the motorized pumps, different energy
sources can be used to drive the pump, such
as diesel, electricity, wind, solar energy.
Furthermore, considering the method of displacement
of water applied by a pump, we can distinguish
between impulse pumps, positive displacement
pumps and velocity pumps.
Hydraulic ram pump uses highs difference and
water hummer effect to develop pressure which
allows a part of the input water to be lifted
up higher than the water source without any
external energy supply.
Each 1 m difference in the feed pipe, can
pump water almost 30 m up.
Hydraulic ram pumps require two things: a
reliable source of running water and a working
fall.
The pump works as follows: Water flows from
the source A by gravity thorough the drive
pipe B, picks up speed and kinetic energy
until the increasing drug force closes the
waste valve C. The momentum of the water flow
against the closed waste valve causes water
hummer.
The pressure in the pipe rises, and the check
valve D opens and some water is forced into
the delivery pipe.
With slowing of the movement of water, the
check valve closes, water moves back, and
forward again restarting the process.
The pressure vessel E, contains air to reduce
the hydraulic shock and improving efficiency
by more constant flow of water.
These kind of systems work for long time without
any maintenance as long as water is available.
Ram pumps a specially suitable for communities
in hilly areas with water sources located
lower than the community or on another side
of the valley.
A positive displacement pump makes a fluid
move by trapping a fixed amount and forcing
(displacing) that trapped volume into the
discharge pipe.
Basically, the pump uses a principle of expanding
space or cavity on the suction side and decreasing
cavity on the discharge side.
The volume remains constant during one cycle
of operation, which means that theoretically,
positive displacement pumps should produce
the same flow when the speed is constant,
independently on the pressure on the discharge
side.
Depending on the type of mechanism used to
move water, the positive displacement pumps
can be classified in three major groups: reciprocating
type positive displacement, rotary-type positive
displacement and linear type positive displacement.
Reciprocating type positive displacement pumps
are commonly used in a number of applications.
Many community hand pumps for dug wells and
boreholes are reciprocating piston or plunger
pumps.
When water is available less than 7 meters
below ground, suction pumps are often of an
interest, as they can be easily accessed at
the ground level to perform maintenance.
For deeper wells and boreholes, direct action
hand pumps or high lift hand pumps raising
water from the depth of up to 45or even 100
m can be used.
Rotary-type positive displacement pumps use
rotating mechanism that creates vacuum and
captures and draws water.
Rotary vane pump consists of vanes placed
in a circular rotor that rotates inside a
circular cavity.
The centers of these two circles are offset,
causing the vanes to slide in and out of rotor
creating chambers.
Progressive cavity pump also known as helical
rotor pump transfers water by progressing
it through the sequence of small sized cavities
when rotor turns.
These type of pumps are as well fixed flow
pumps, operating at a constant flow rate which
is proportional to the rotation speed and
almost independent on head.
The pumping head is directly proportional
to the power input.
This type of pump is robust and is less sensitive
to particles in water than other positive
displacement pumps and can be used even to
pump sludge.
Abrasive materials will however damage the
pump.
It is quite common pump used for motorized
pumping of water from boreholes.
A rope pump is a pump which consists of a
hanging rope placed in the well and drawn
up through a long pipe with the bottom immersed
in water.
Round disks - washers matching the diameter
of the pipe are attached to the rope.
Those pull water to the surface.
These type of pumps is commonly used in rural
areas on hand dug wells for community or self-supply
of water.
If the positive displacement pumps operate
by manipulating the available space inside
the pump, the velocity pumps operate by manipulating
the velocity of the fluid during its movement
through the pump.
A radial flow pump, also known as centrifugal
pump, first converts energy of a motor first
into velocity or better to say, kinetic energy
by a rotating impeller.
When impeller rotates, its spins the water
sitting in the cavities between the vanes
outward and provides centrifugal acceleration.
As water leaves, the low pressure area is
creating leading to suction of more water.
The kinetic energy of water coming out of
an impeller is afterwards harnessed by creating
resistance to the flow.
Water meets a stationary diffuser or volute,
which slows it down and converts the kinetic
energy into the pressure energy.
Axial-flow pumps differ from radial flow centrifugal
pumps in principle by the design of the rotating
elements.
The axial flow pumps use element similar to
a propeller, which moves (or pushes) water
axially and operate usually at much smaller
pressures and higher flows than centrifugal
pumps.
Mixed pumps do both – radial acceleration
and pushing of water., and let water exist
the impeller between 0 and 90 degrees from
axial direction.
This leads to higher operating pressures and
flow rates.
Both axial flow and mixed flow pumps are not
very common in emergency water supply applications.
A practical difference between velocity and
positive displacement pumps is how they operate
under closed valve conditions.
Positive displacement pumps physically displace
fluid, so closing a valve downstream of a
positive displacement pump produces a continual
pressure build up that can cause mechanical
failure and damage of pipeline or pump.
Velocity pumps differ in that they can be
safely operated under closed valve conditions.
Due to the different operating principle,
pumping head of positive displacement pump
theoretically does not depend on the pump
speed, while for velocity pumps, discharge
rates vary considerably with the head against
water is being pumped.
That is a reason why you need to read and
understand pump curves if you need to chose
and specify a centrifugal pump.
A typical Pump curve has two axes: horizontal
one which shows the flow rate through the
pump and vertical one, showing head, also
sometimes called pressure.
The first information we can read from any
pump curve is the flow the pump will develop
at any given operating head.
This curve is called also pump performance
curve.
Any piping system used to transport pumped
water can be characterized by a head loss,
which as well depends on the flow rate of
water in the system.
Head loss will increase with the flow rate.
This red curve is called system characteristics
curve.
The point where the pump performance curve
and system characteristics curves intersect
is called pump operating point or duty point.
At the duty point, there is a balance between
the system demands and what the pump can deliver.
For each pump, the manufacturer of the pump
will define the allowable pump operating range,
indicating the values of Minimum und maximum
flow rate Q min and Q max.
The operating point of the pump needs to be
in the operating range of the pump to provide
trouble free operation of the pump.
For centrifugal pumps, multiple curves can
be pictured on the pump curve.
Those show the performance of the pump at
different impeller diameters.
Impellers can be trimmed to match the impeller
to the head and flow needed in the application
within the given range.
In addition to head and flow, pump curves
will also provide efficiency information.
Efficiency is the relationship between the
input power and the water power being generated
by the pump.
Obviously, no pump has 100% efficiency, and
pumps require more input power than water
power generated by the pump.
The best efficiency point on this example
is 60%.
The middle part of the pump curve illustrates
the net positive head required NPSH, which
is basically, the suction characteristics
of the pump at different flows.
Each point along the curve shows the positive
suction head in meters required to avoid for
example cavitation which can damage the pump.
As you see on the picture, it does not differ
a lot for different impeller trims.
The lowest graph at the bottom of the pump
curve shows usually the power curve.
This curve indicates how much power the pump
will require at any particular flow point.
This information is useful for calculating
power consumption costs and ensuring that
selected motor is suitable for the chosen
pump.
Pumping stations belong to many water supply
systems which require delivery of water from
source to treatment or distribution network
and it cannot be done by entirely by gravity.
Interruption or a breakdown of a pumping station
leads inevitably to the interruption of the
water supply of the entire area.
In order to increase reliability of a pumping
station, adequate standby capacity is required.
Trained operators, regular servicing, reliable
energy sources and spare parts are the major
factors which need to be ensured.
Rehabilitation of the pumping stations belongs
to the common activities required in an emergency
context, especially in urban and peri-urban
areas affected by the crisis.
While in few cases, provision of fuel can
be already sufficient, in other cases, complex
service, repair and replacement can be required.
Hereby you can see a video from Lebanon, illustrating
the rehabilitation of the water pumping systems
in Beqaa.
During this lecture we discussed gravity water
supply, and learned that gravity supplies
in hilly areas are usually simple systems
which do not require high degree of maintenance.
Furthermore, we looked at the basic operating
principles and differences of various common
types of pumps such as impulse pumps, positive
displacement pumps and velocity pumps and
learned how to read pump curves of centrifugal
pumps.
Finally we mentioned major factors needed
for reliable operation of a pumping station.
See you during the next lecture.