Here is your source water.
How do we make it to look so?
And even if looks so, is it really safe?
During this lecture, we will find out about
different water treatment steps, processes
and technologies, understand basic principles
behind most commonly used technologies.
We will also discuss advantages, disadvantages
and limitations of each treatment process.
All water treatment methods can be divided
in five major groups which can function as
a single step treatment or should be applied
as part of a large multi-stage treatment.
The five groups of methods are structured
around the type of contaminants removed by
the method.
Those groups are clarification which is removal
of particulate matter, inactivation of microorganisms
also called disinfection, desalination, and
reduction of concentrations of geogenic and
anthropogenic contaminants to meet water quality
guidelines.
A meaningful combination of technologies is
in most cases necessary to achieve the WHO
water quality standards for safe drinking
water.
The choice of technologies or its combinations
we make depends on the many factors including
available water resources, their quality and
seasonality, legal requirements, scale, space,
financial resources, local availability of
products, consumables and skills as well as
available energy sources.
The purpose of clarification is to remove
as much as possible particulate material.
The conventional treatment systems usually
apply coagulation/flocculation combined with
sedimentation or filtration.
Rapid sand filtration without coagulation
is used as well on large centralized drinking
water treatment plants or community supplies.
In community supplies, roughing filtration
has been used successfully as efficient and
low maintenance pre-treatment.
Coagulation is usually a pre-treatment step.
Its goal is to change the fine dispersed particles
into larger agglomerates that can be removed
by sedimentation or filtration or both.
In coagulation process, a metal salt such
as aluminium or iron salts are added to water
containing dispersed often negatively charged
particles.
Aluminium or iron ions destabilize the particles
by neutralizing their charge.
Water is being mixed rapidly and pH might
need a correction.
The destabilized particles form flocks which
grow larger during slow mixing and finally
settle down or can be easier filtered out.
Another method of reducing particulate matter
content is a rapid sand filtration.
Water passes through the filter media which
is coarse or medium sized sand, which is loaded
over the more coarse gravel layer.
During filtration, solids get trapped, settle
or adsorb onto the sand material.
After trapped material accumulated in the
filter layers, the filter requires backwashing
– reverse flow of water to remove accumulated
material.
The filters are operated at linear velocity
of 1-40 m/h, which is considerably higher
than in slow sand filters which we discuss
later.
The filter can be constructed with locally
available resources and does not require consumables,
but proper design, adequate operational parameters
and maintenance are crucial for good performance.
For a rather turbid waters, roughing filters
can be used prior to rapid or slow sand filtration
or disinfection.
Differently sized coarse material is used
in roughing filters.
The size decreases in the direction of flow.
Gravel from riverbed, broken stones, rocks
or bricks, plastics, burnt charcoal or coconut
fibre can be used as filtration media.
There are different configurations of roughing
filters: up-flow, down-flow or horizontal
flow.
In an up-flow filter you see here, water moves
from down to top and the retained solids accumulate
predominantly in the bottom of the filter.
They can be flushed out by reversing the flow
or simply draining the filter.
They are quite simple to maintain, do not
require any chemicals and have low operational
costs.
Filter design, maintenance practices and raw
water quality fluctuations can influence the
performance to a large extent.
Disinfection of drinking water ensures that
bacteria viruses and protozoa have been inactivated
or removed from water so they do not longer
pose health risk.
Disinfection is always done after clarification
and not before, as particles reduce the efficiency
of many disinfectants.
Disinfection by chlorination is most commonly
used method.
Chlorine or sodium hypochlorite can also be
produced on-site by hypochlorite generators
by electrolysis of salt.
Ozone and UV light inactivate microorganisms
while slow sand filtration and membranes filtration
are based on filtration purely or combined
with biological processes.
When chlorine is dissolved in water, it forms
equilibrium between the chlorine Cl2, hypochlorous
acid HOCl and hydrochloric acid HCl by this
reaction forming:
When chlorine is added to water, it reacts
first with reduced compounds and is being
destructed.
At a higher dose, it reacts also with organic
matter and nitrogen species to form chloro-organic
and chloramine compounds, which at higher
dose of chlorine are partly destructed.
Breakpoint is the point at which complete
oxidation of all chloramine species occurred.
Figure summarizes the processes occurring
during breakpoint chlorination.
In short, at first chlorine residual increases
proportionally to the amount of chlorine added
until the mole ratio of ammonia to chlorine
is about 1.
Beyond that, addition of chlorine reduces
total chlorine residual due to oxidation of
some chloramine species.
Breakpoint (point C) is the point at which
complete oxidation of all chloramine species
occurred.
The location of this point depends on the
presence of organic matter, nitrogen and reduced
inorganic ions.
After the breakpoint is reached, free chlorine
residual proportionally increases with the
chlorine dose.
After the breakpoint is reached, free chlorine
residual proportionally increases with the
chlorine dose.
The part of chlorine which participates in
disinfection and is called chlorine demand.
The part which remains in water after chlorine
demand is satisfied is called total chlorine.
The free chlorine is chlorine which is present
in water in form of hypochlorous acid HOCl
or hypochlorite ion OCl-.
Free chlorine inactivates microorganisms or
kills them during a defined period of time,
called contact time.
Chlorine residual is the chlorine which remains
in water after the disinfection process has
been predominantly completed and acts as a
safeguard against additional microbial contamination
that could be introduced in the distribution
network or at the point of use.
Recommended residual chlorine concentration
is about 0.5 mg/L of free chlorine which should
be applied to water during at least 30 min.
Chlorine dose is being expressed in concentration
multiplied by contact time, called Ct value.
Ct99 means the concentration and time required
to kill 99 % of target microorganisms.
IN case of bacteria, the Ct values are low,
indicating the inactivation of bacteria occurs
relatively fast and at low concentration.
The time and concentration are considerably
higher to inactivate viruses, and very high
for protozoa, indicating that chlorination
is not very efficient for protozoa inactivation.
Cryptosporidium oocysts are resistant to chlorine
which often does not provide sufficient level
of inactivation to protect from a disease.
Presence of particulate matter in water leading
to high turbidity of water compromise chlorination
and water has to be clarified before it can
be disinfected with chlorine.
There are different forms of chlorine available,
and it can even be produced on site by electrolysis
of salt and water.
The choice of the most appropriate form of
chlorine will depend on such factors as scale
and water volume which needs to be treated,
skills available, safety management practices
and power supply reliability.
Ozone is highly effective oxidant, not only
disinfecting water but also reducing color,
micro pollutants content and other organic
contamination.
It is however expensive and does not provide
residual protection.
Due to high costs and relative complexity
it is usually not used in the developmental
or emergency context.
In contrary, UV disinfection is cheap and
relatively simple.
It inactivates microorganisms by damaging
their DANN and RNA.
In contrary to chlorination it is also efficient
against protozoa.
No supply of chemicals is also an advantage
of the method.
However, it does not provide residual protection,
requires reliable power supply and frequent
cleaning of the UV lamps which are the source
of UV light.
As well as in case of chlorination, it is
sensitive to turbidity and water should be
clarified before UV treatment.
Slow sand filters are operated at slower filtration
rates of 0.1-0.3 m/h compare to rapid sand
filters which are commonly operated at 1-40
m/h.
Slow filtration rates allow development of
a biological activity within the filter.
Thus the slow sand filtration is a combination
of different biological and physical processes
including Mechanical trapping, Adsorption
or attachment, Predation and Natural death
leading to reduction of solids but also micro
and macro organisms .Slow sand filters are
usually down-flow filters and are operated
by gravity.
Each filter requires ripening period of few
days to few weeks, until removal rates stabilize.
Mainly the top layer of the slow sand filter
contains a diverse microbiological community
and particles which is also called schmutzdecke,
where inactivation of microorganisms occurs.
The technology is simple, low cost and has
a long lifespan, but requires large area and
is sensitive to mal-operation or during the
periods of excessive turbidity or algal matter
in inflow.
During membrane filtration was is driven by
pressure difference between the feed water
and filtrate through a filter with pores of
a defined size range.
usually polymeric membranes and sometime ceramic
membranes are used.
Microfiltration has pores in the size of bacteria
or high and removes them and particulate matter
by siue exclusion.
Ultrafiltration membranes are more tight and
remove also viruses which is the size of 20-80
nm.
Nanofiltration requires considerable higher
pressure as the pores are small and is capable
of retaining macromolecules and larger ions.
Small ions such as salt ions can be removed
by reverse osmosis, requiring even higher
pressure.
For disinfection purposes, ultrafiltration
membranes are most common as an effective
barrier against pathogenic microorganisms
and particles.
Different configurations of membranes are
available.
In drinking water supply hollow fiber membranes
are commonly used.
Spiral wound elements – so flat membrane
is rolled together with a spacer- are more
often used in desalination processes.
Flat sheet membrane modules are more often
used in wastewater treatment in membrane bioreactors.
Membranes need to be frequently backflushed
to remove a layer of particles or microorganisms
accumulating on the surface of the membrane.
This layer is also called fouling layer.
The drinking water filtration systems offer
constant and reliable operation, which however
requires high degree of automation, reliable
power supply and relatively high costs.
There are also gravity driven systems on the
market and in development, more suitable for
remote applications.
Desalination is used to remove salt from sea
or brackish water.
If a semipermeable membrane is installed between
pure and saline water containers, pure water
be drawn by saline water creating osmotic
pressure.
In order to overcome this osmotic pressure,
external pressure which is higher than osmotic
pressure, needs to be applied.
Seawater has an osmotic pressure of about
25 bar.
Thus RO systems are operated at 30-70 bar
to achieve movement of pure water from saline
water through the membrane.
Thus, high pressure pumps and good power supply
are required, as well as pretreatment to protect
membranes from fouling.
Chemical contaminants are either naturally
occurring chemicals in rocks and soils such
as F and As or synthetic chemicals introduced
into environment through industrial waste
and wastewater, agricultural practices or
untreated municipal wastewater.
Adsorption on granular activated carbon, sometimes
ozonation as well as nanofiltration or RO
are common methods to reduce concentrations
to the acceptable level.
It is quite complex and costly processes and
it is advisable to look for other water sources
if this is possible if concentrations of synthetic
chemicals are too high.
Fluoride and arsenic are most commonly occurring
geogenic chemicals which pose a health risk.
There are few methods based on adsorption,
coagulation, ion exchange and membranes to
reduce concentrations of these chemicals.
All of them have advantages and disadvantages
and no best option exist yet.
There is a large variety of different treatment
technologies and part of these we have not
considered here.
Some processes are still in development or
few promising systems still exist as pilots.
Nevertheless in this course we considered
major conventional drinking water treatment
steps which include clarification and disinfection.
Disinfection is not efficient if water is
turbid, and thus clarification needs to be
done before.
Geogenic and anthropogenic contamination of
water require special additional treatment
steps, which adds complexity to the system
Desalination of sea water is complex, has
high energy demand and often only appropriate
in cases were ultimately no other water source
is available.
So, we clarified and disinfected this water.
Let’s drink it!