Previously, we covered functional groups from
source to treatment.
Today I would like to talk in more detail
about the last two functional groups – distribution
and transport as well as user safety.
We will get familiar with the water transport
and distribution systems in a developmental
and emergency context.
The user safety aspects will be considered
only in regard to storage.
If you are interested to find out more about
HWT, refer to the Eawag`s MOOC on household
water treatment and safe storage.
Transport of water in jerry cans is a reality
for many rural and urban families.
Depending on the location of the water source,
it requires often a lot of time which can
be used for other activities.
In areas where water sources are located at
longer distances, other water distribution
options should be considered first.
Transport of jerry cans filled with safe water
to home by water kiosk providers can be costly
but in general adequate option in case water
and jerry cans are disinfected and safely
sealed.
Usually this is not the case and deterioration
of water quality can be expected during transport
and use.
Chlorination of jerry cans at the point of
water collection can be an option to improve
the situation.
Water vendors range from individuals who carry
water in containers, pushcarts or bicycles,
or deliver it in jerry cans with charts driven
by animals or trucks.
Reselling of water can be either formal (water
trucks managed by utilities or communities)
or informal, such as individuals, buying water
or fetching it at the source and carrying
it to peoples home and reselling it at a higher
price.
Water vendors often operate as an extension
to public supply in urban areas performing
the service to fill the gap between demand
and supply.
In rural areas, high distance to water sources
often is the driving force for water vendors.
Higher price then water at the network, water
kiosk or borehole is often the drawback.
On this picture, water kiosk delivers water
to households as a part of services.
Water tinkering is still used in remote rural
settings without access to adequate water
sources, urban and peri-urban areas without
distribution networks or as an emergency water
supply when other adequate water sources are
not available.
In all cases – it is expensive, not easy
to organize and should be avoided whenever
possible.
If water is not chlorinated, water quality
is likely to deteriorate during transport.
And tinkering of water from contaminated water
sources can support spreading of diseases
in large areas within a very short time.
Thus chlorination of tinkered water as well
as shock chlorination of the tankers in times
of disease outbreaks is highly recommended.
It helps that known volume and water source
as well as mixing during transport make chlorination
of tinkered water rather easy.
Water distribution systems transport water
from the water source or water treatment plant
to the point where it is delivered or used,
such as community standpipe, yard connection
or household connection.
It is the most desired and convenient way
of delivering water to consumers.
It is also usually a safer way as contamination
is likely to be lower than in case of transporting
water by a jerry can or a truck.
Water demand in community distribution systems
varies during the day.
Water consumption is highest during the hours
it is used for personal hygiene, washing and
cooking and is lowest at night.
These variations need to be addressed by water
storage or pump control mechanisms.
In small community water supplies, the option
with the storage reservoir is preferred especially
considering that electric power or diesel
supply is usually unreliable.
Storage reservoirs accumulate water during
nighttime or when energy is available and
supply it during peak water demand hours.
The pressure of at least 5-10 m of water column
is needed to protect water in the network
from ingress of polluted seepage water and
assure sufficient pressure in the taps.
Intermittent supply leads to deterioration
of water quality as well.
There are two types of community distribution
networks: branched network consisting of one
or few mains which separate in a number of
dead-end connections and looped or "grid"
configuration which consists of one or few
main loops (rings) from which water is conveyed
to secondary loops or branches.
Branched networks and simple to design and
easier to install than looped networks.
Looped networks require number of interconnecting
pipes, valves and special parts, and are more
complex and expensive than branched networks.
Looped networks improve the hydraulics of
the system and are generally more reliable:
water can be supplied from different directions
which can be important when one of the loops
needs to be maintained, pressure variations
are reduced and accumulation of sediments
and risk of microbial contamination due to
stagnation of water are reduced.
Large scale distribution is basically a very
complex looped or mixed network.
They should be designed, and constructed in
a way that dead-ends are eliminated or designed
in a way that flushing is possible, prevent
cross-connections, prevent unauthorized access,
allow adequate disinfection and ensure that
water system capacity is sufficient to meet
domestic demand and other users, connected
to the network such as enterprises, public
organizations, fire protection, etc.
The planning, design and construction requires
high level of expertise, especially when multi-source
systems are needed and requires huge investments.
Rehabilitation of a large scale distribution
network is complex but is being done more
and more often also in emergencies as conflicts
frequently affect urban areas and are becoming
more often protracted….
Nearly 80-85 % of costs of water supply of
a city is used in the distribution network.
Water consumption at households connected
to a centralized water system with multiple
taps and often a flush toilet varies between
100 and 400 Liters per person per day and is considerably
higher than households collecting water at
public taps, wells or other decentralized
sources without household connection.
This leads also to a considerably higher water
wastage.
Supply breakdowns and interruptions are common
problems usually leading to recontamination
due to zero or negative pressure and depletion
of chlorine to 0.
People with intermittent supply tend to store
water at home in containers, which are not
necessary safe.
Water storage tanks are meant to ensure that
sufficient reserve of water is available when
needed.
Usually storage tanks are installed as a part
of a water supply system to cover for breakdowns
in water supply, balance peak demand, ensure
adequate supply of water treatment processes
or maintain pressure in the distribution system.
Water storage packs - circular tanks built
from corrugated iron sheets in which synthetic
rubber liner is hung as you can see on the
picture or flexible collapsible tanks are
often used to store water in emergency settings.
Water storage is also used at the user level
– at home.
Larger storage water containers are often
used by households relying on tankers or intermittent
water supply.
Smaller storage containers are placed in or
around households to store water carried from
the source, or collected through small rainwater
harvesting system.
The best water treatment and supply system
can not prevent health risk if water stored
at home becomes contaminated.
Taps to reduce contact of water with hands
as well as lids help to reduce negative effects
in small household tanks.
Appropriate design and lids, as well as periodic
cleaning or disinfection are required for
larger household water storage installations.
If water is of bad quality or has been contaminated
during transport, House Water Treatment might be an option.
Eawag`s MOOC on House Water Treatment covers this in detail and we do not discuss this further.
So, to sum up, during this lecture we have
discussed different distribution and storage
options.
One of the options is transporting water in
jerry cans.
This might not be most preferred option by
it is very common.
Re-Contamination of jerry cans during transport
and storage is a large problem, which might
be addressed with chlorination.
In areas without distribution networks and
reliable groundwater sources, water tinkering
is used.
It should however be considered as only an
intermediate solution or an immediate short
term measure in an emergency and avoided whenever
possible.
Distribution networks are most convenient
ways of transporting water to consumers.
These are complex systems requiring lots of
engineering, management and high investments.
Water consumption and wastage are considerably
higher.
However, rehabilitation of the complex distribution
networks is more and more frequently needed
also in an emergency as the conflicts are
getting more urban and protracted.