Hello and welcome to the last presentation
of this week summarizing the key messages.
During this week we have focused on the different
water supply systems and technologies.
We have learned almost every water supply
system at any scale can be presented as a
combination of technologies from 6 different
functional groups.
We have looked in more detail at every functional
group and discussed different technologies,
mostly applied in conventional water treatment
schemas.
Finally in each relevant functional group
we shortly discussed measures and technologies
rather specific for emergency water supply.
The six functional groups include source,
intake, abstraction, treatment, distribution
and transport as well as user safety.
By combining the technologies from left to
right, we can create system templates for
different water sources, scales and local
conditions, preferences and enabling environment.
Major drinking water sources include surface
water, ground water, rain water and sometimes
sea water can be used if no other water sources
are available.
The major criteria for selecting a water source
include water quantity, water quality, technology
required for exploitation and accessibility
and acceptance.
Water is collected from the sources through
an intake systems.
These can be water storage dams, protected
springs, dug wells or boreholes, as well as
protected and unprotected river and lake intakes,
as well as surface water infiltration wells
and galleries.
Springs are usually the easiest and comparably
low cost way of accessing groundwater when
it is possible as construction costs are comparably
low and no pump is needed.
For water abstraction, gravity water supplies
should be used whenever possible, as those
are usually low cost and reliable way of abstracting
water.
A large variety of pumps are available on
the market.
Required pressure, well depth or needed elevation
as well as available energy sources usually
define which types of pumps are feasible to
use.
Clarification combined with disinfection are
the conventional ways of treating water not
contaminated with geogenic chemicals or chemicals
from industry or agriculture.
If water is chemically contaminated it becomes
more difficult to manage the problem and reduce
contamination level to acceptable values.
Desalination of water is complex and expensive
and requires high energy demand and reliable
power sources.
If there other water sources, they should
be considered first.
Water distribution and transport can be done
in various ways ad scales such as delivering
water with jerry can from a nearby water source,
buying water from water vendors, supplying
water with tankers to the areas without access
to water sources or through a distribution
network.
Although jerry cans are not optimal and recontamination
of water is likely, it is still very common
in many places.
In case water sources are far or time for
collecting water is limited, water vendors
might provide a service of delivering water
at higher cost to the home.
Tinkering water is still being done in areas
without alternatives, although it is costly
and can become a logistical nightmare.
It should rather be avoided whenever possible.
Obviously distribution network is the most
desired, convenient and safe way of delivering
water to consumers.
However it is expensive, complex, requires
skills and expertise.
However, rehabilitation of distribution networks
becomes more often the daily business in an
emergency as conflicts move more to the urban
areas and are getting protracted.
When water sources are far or supply intermittent,
safe water storage at home becomes crucial
to avoid health risks due to recontamination
of water.
See you and goodbye.