Now we will look at the aerobic technologies,
which can be used as stand-alone systems
or to polish the effluent of anaerobic units.
Aerobic systems are biological systems which
rely on the action of bacteria
needing oxygen to live, like us.
Thus, in all of them oxygen provision is a
key aspect.
Without sufficient oxygen, the environment
becomes anaerobic,
which leads to processes such as described
in the last module.
Some aerobic technologies try to imitate nature,
such as the "waste stabilization ponds", or
the "constructed wetlands".
Some of these are more engineered,
such as the "trickling filter" or the "activated
sludge".
Let's start with the waste deposition ponds,
or lagoons.
It is a system that consists in a succession
of ponds
with different functions.
First one anaerobic pond, then one or two
facultative ponds,
and finally, one or two maturation ponds.
Let's look in more detail at the differences
between these three types of ponds.
The anaerobic pond is the deepest, with a
depth of two to five meters,
and also the smallest.
It is highly loaded because it receives the
rawest water.
The anaerobic pond has a hydraulic retention
time from one to three days,
and its main function is sedimentation
and anaerobic stabilization of sludge, thus,
settling.
The facultative pond or facultative ponds
if they are several, are shallower.
Usually, less than 1.5 meters,
but large.
The idea here is to maximize the oxygen supply
either through algae, wind, or artificial
aeration.
The hydraulic retention time there
is longer: from ten to twenty days.
Here, the main function is the aerobic degradation
of suspended and dissolved matter,
thus, degradation.
Finally, the maturation ponds are even shallower,
usually less than one meter, but large.
The hydraulic retention time is about ten
days.
Here the main function is the final sedimentation
of suspended solids,
the bacterial mass, and pathogens, thus polishing.
Waste stabilization ponds can treat high strength
wastewater
to a high quality effluent.
They are generally reliable and good functioning
and inexpensive, compared to either centralized
options.
However, they require a lot of space and may
generate bad odors,
especially the anaerobic pond, if poorly designed.
It requires expert design and supervision,
especially to avoid short-circuiting,
in which case, the effluent
goes from the inlet to the outlet without
mixing properly,
that is, not staying through the intended
retention time.
Besides, if they work at best in warm climates,
waste stabilization ponds are not always appropriate
for colder climates.
This picture shows large waste stabilization
ponds
for the city of Cuenca, in Ecuador.
A way to increase the performance of waste
stabilization ponds
is to provide artificial aeration,
which is done in Cuenca in the first pond,
upstream of this picture.
It is also a good way to upgrade the ponds
when then reach design capacity,
especially extension, is not always easy.
In aerated ponds, mechanical aerators provide
oxygen
and keep the aerobic organisms suspended
to achieve a high rate of organic degradation.
Increased mixing and aeration means that the
ponds can be deeper
and tolerate much higher organic loads than
the maturation pond.
The depth may be from two to five meters
and a retention time from three to twenty
days.
In some cases, it can even replace the anaerobic
pond,
thus avoiding the bad odors that anaerobic
ponds may generate.
The downside of it is that aeration implies
a high energy consumption,
and thus costs, and requires a constant source
of electricity.
Interruption of electricity service may cause
the pond to turn anaerobic,
thus changing completely the inner biological
processes.
We will now have a look at another family
of treatment technologies: the "constructed
wetlands".
"Constructed wetlands" aim to replicate the
naturally occurring processes
of a natural wetland, marsh or swamp.
We distinguish three types:
the "free water surface constructed wetland",
the "horizontal subsurface flow constructed
wetland",
and the "vertical flow constructed wetland".
Let's start with the "free water surface constructed
wetland".
In that case, the water slowly flows through
the wetland,
particles settle, and pathogens are eliminated
through the combined action of sun, settling,
adsorption,
and predation from higher organisms.
The organisms and plants utilize the nutrients.
This style of constructed wetland
is commonly used as a polishing step
after secondary or tertiary treatment processes.
It is only appropriate for low strength wastewater.
This is a really important fact.
The depth of the water is ten to 45 cm above
ground level.
Wastewater needs to be well distributed at
the inlet.
Good operation and maintenance is needed
for it not to turn into a mosquito breeding
area,
and to avoid short-circuiting.
Let's look now at the "horizontal subsurface
flow constructed wetland".
Its performance regarding reduction of BOD,
suspended solids, and pathogens
is higher than in the freewater surface constructed
wetlands,
and it does not have the mosquito problem
as the water flows only under the surface,
as its name indicates.
As in the previous technology,
the good distribution of the influent at the
inlet is very important.
The gravel bed is between 50 cm and one meter
deep.
The water level is maintained at 5 to 15 cm
below the surface.
As wastewater flows horizontally through the
basin,
the filter material filters out particles.
It acts both as a filter and as a fixed surface
upon which bacteria can attach, forming large
biofilms.
The plant roots play an important role
in maintaining permeability in the filter.
It is very important to have a good primary
treatment
before the wetland.
Otherwise, the risk of clogging will be very
high.
Expert follow-up is necessary to monitor the
plants,
especially the startup periods.
As a final remark, we have to mention
that the wetlands need a lot of space,
generally a surface of about five to ten square
meters per person equivalent.
This picture illustrates the last type of
constructed wetland,
the "vertical flow constructed wetland",
which is, of course, difficult to differentiate
from outside.
This is the most sophisticated and performance
type of wetland
By injecting the wastewater from above the
whole surface,
the distribution is greatly improved.
The water flows down and is collected by a
drainage system.
The important difference between vertical
and horizontal wetlands
is not simply the direction of the flow path,
but rather, the aerobic conditions.
The wastewater is applied intermittently,
four to ten times a day.
Thus, the filter goes through stages of being
saturated and unsaturated,
and accordingly, different phases of aerobic
and anaerobic conditions.
With this regime, there is less plugging risk
than in horizontal subsurface flow wetland.
Other than that,
the treatment processes are the same as in
the horizontal flow wetland.
Because of the mechanical dosing system,
this technology is most appropriate where
trained maintenance staff,
constant power supply, and spare parts are
available.
Constructed wetlands can reach a good performance
with processes close to nature.
However, one has to be aware of the risk of
clogging
and the management of the plants,
especially the startup and maintenance,
and beware high ammonia levels
which may prevent the plants from growing
properly.
In all cases, a good primary treatment is
crucial.
Before finishing this module,
we will look at two higher end technologies
which we may call Conventional:
the "trickling filter", and the "activated
sludge".
These systems are really performant in developed
countries,
but imply high capital costs,
operation and maintenance by skilled personnel,
and a constant source of energy.
The "trickling filter" is a fixed bed biological
reactor
that operates mostly under aerobic conditions.
After primary treatment, wastewater is continuously
trickled
or sprayed through the filter, for example,
through a rotating sprinkler.
Organics are degraded by the biofilm covering
the filter material.
The filter is usually from one to 2.5 meter
high,
but some filters may reach a height up to
12 meters.
Adequate airflow is important to ensure sufficient
treatment performance
and prevent odors.
The air can circulate vertically through the
filter.
The advantage of a trickling filter over the
technologies presented before
is the small land requirement;
however, flies and odors are often problematic.
The "activated sludge system"
is the best known and most widespread in Western
countries
under different forms, such as sequencing
batch reactor,
oxidation ditches, moving beds, or membrane
bioreactors.
It makes use of highly concentrated micro-organisms
to degrade organics and remove nutrients,
leading to a high quality effluent.
To maintain aerobic conditions
and to keep the activated sludge suspended,
a continuous and well-timed supply of oxygen
is required.
Aeration and mixing can be provided by pumping
air or oxygen into the tank
or by surface aerators.
Agglomerations of sludge particles called
flux
form in the aerated tank and are removed in
a settler
called in that case "secondary clarifier".
We are now at the end of this module
on aerobic treatment technologies.
We saw very different technologies
that can all perform well,
but have different requirements.
To sum up, we can say that the main decision
factors are:
the availability of space, financial resources,
skills, and electricity.