Hello and welcome to the week on sanitation.
My name is Samuel Renggli.
I work as an Environmental Engineer at Eawag.
And I will guide your through this week.
This week on sanitation you will learn about
the method of excreta management in humanitarian
crises.
You will know which sanitation products you
have to deal with and what functional groups
of sanitation technologies exist.
You will learn what criteria need to be considered
to select the most appropriate technology
based on the needs and the context.
In the second part of the week we do a review
of sanitation technologies for the humanitarian
sector.
The video lectures you will see this week
are a mix of new videos produced for this
course where the topic of sanitation in humanitarian
crises, including excreta management is presented.
In addition to the theoretical part, we have
ICRC case studies from Ruanda, Gaza and Liberia
to illustrate some challenges and practices
of sanitation in the humanitarian sector.
There are some videos that were already featured
in another MOOC by Eawag called Planning & Design
of Sanitation Systems and Technologies ((Insert
link to the MOOC as in-video quiz)).
If you are interested to learn more in depth
about sanitation, we recommend enrolling in
that course as well.
These videos are presented by my colleagues
Dr. Elizabeth Tilley, Lukas Ulrich and Philippe
Reymond.
On the Eawag homepage you find other courses
as well on household water treatment and safe
storage, solid waste management and faecal
sludge management.
The videos use the terminology of the Compendium
of Sanitation Systems and Technologies, a
publication by Eawag.
The Compendium presents a huge range of information
on sanitation systems and 57 different technologies.
It is currently available in English, French,
Spanish, Arabic, Nepali, Vietnamese and Korean.
Russian will soon be available as well.
The Compendium is currently being revised
and adapted for the humanitarian sector.
The update will include more technologies
specific for emergency settings as well as
more decision criteria for the humanitarian
context.
It will be published in 2018.
Furthermore there is a range of books and
publications on sanitation in emergencies
which you find on the course homepage.
Ensuring public health is the first goal during
any humanitarian crisis.
Sanitation plays an important role in preventing
diseases that can become an epidemic such
as cholera, typhoid and diarrhoea.
Transmission of excreta related diseases is
largely through faecal oral transmission,
therefore it is worthwhile to have another
look at the F-Diagram.
To ensure public health a multiple action
approach is needed consisting of water supply,
sanitation and hygiene promotion.
Sanitation is the first barrier to avoid faecal
pathogens of entering into the environment,
where they can cause disease infection.
((Draw the sanitation barrier)).
Sanitation has to be always coupled with hand
hygiene promotion.
A toilet facility is only complete with a
handwashing station accessible in an adequate
distance.
This in order to have a secondary barrier
from the hands.
((Draw handwashing barrier))
The third barrier is clean drinking water
((draw water barrier))
Handwashing and water supply are not part
of this week.
There is not one sanitation solution that
fits any context.
The challenge is to find the most appropriate
sanitation solution for each different context.
The context is given by the type and the state
of an emergency as well as the specific geographical
context.
For example a different sanitation solution
was needed for the acute phase after the earth
quake in April 2015 in Nepal than for the
prolonged humanitarian crisis in the Middle
East that is still going on.
In the city of Kathmandu, shown on the image
behind me, people from urban settlements were
forced to leave their houses after the earthquake.
People were temporarily displaced within the
city or just outside.
The existing sanitation infrastructure was
damaged, but not destroyed completely everywhere.
The sanitation response was to implement temporary
container based toilets and pit latrines,
while the existing infrastructure was rehabilitated
for the needs of Nepali people.
The average lifespan of a refugee camp is
20 years.
Therefore sanitation in the Zataari camp in
Jordan is very different from the solution
in Nepal.
The camp was constructed in the middle of
the desert for Syrian refugees.
As there is no end in sight to the humanitarian
crisis in the Middle East, the sanitation
solutions implemented there are longer term
and improved and upgraded incremental over
time.
In summary, the goal of this week is to learn
what criteria to consider
in order to find the most appropriate sanitation
solution
for each state
of each type of humanitarian crisis
in a given context.
You will also learn about different sanitation
systems and technologies.
Thank you for your attention.
and I hope to exchange with you in the forum
and I hope that you learned a lot this week.