Hello and welcome back .The goal of this module
is to learn about the different functional
groups, meaning the different steps of a sanitation
system.
You will get familiar with the different tasks
of excreta management over the course of
a humanitarian response.
This will allow you to know how sanitation
systems can be developed over the course of
an emergency.
During the acute phase of an emergency minimal
sanitation services are needed.
We will have a look at the Sphere minimal
standards for excreta management in order
to know the minimal objectives of sanitation
during an emergency.
There are several different sub-groups of
sanitation during a humanitarian response,
including wastewater management, solid waste
and health care waste management, excreta
disposal, dead body disposal and hygiene promotion.
The definition of sanitation by WSSCC considers
excreta, wastewater and solid waste management
as part of the sanitation domain.
Each of the sub domains of sanitation could
fill its own 5 week course.
In these modules we will focus on wastewater
management and excreta disposal, meaning all
sanitation domains linked to the waste disposal
from the use of toilets.
Over time, the goals of sanitation have changed
and do so in a similar manner over the course
of a humanitarian response.
During an acute humanitarian crisis the protection
of public health is the main goal of sanitation.
A public health crisis in the form of a cholera
epidemic or other faeces related diseases
must be avoided.
Conflicts of interest between public and environmental
health can arise.
For example vacuum trucks might dispose untreated
faecal sludge into the environment, due to
the lack of treatment facilities, in order
to get it away from settlements and protect
human health.
While this practice can be justified during
an acute humanitarian crisis, the protection
of environmental health, along with social,
institutional and economic considerations
should not be overlooked and try to be addressed
as soon as possible or even integrated from
the beginning.
Finally the reuse of sanitation products can
become a goal during the post crisis, when
new systems are implemented.
Before we start I want to remind you again
that sanitation is never complete without
hygiene interventions.
Hand washing promotion is a crucial part of
any sanitation project and a toilet without
a hand-washing facility including soap or
alcoholic hand rub is not a complete toilet.
This also became evident during the Ebola
crisis in Liberia, form where this picture
was taken.
However in this module we will focus on the
excreta management part of sanitation.
What are the functional groups of a sanitation
system?
A sanitation system is more than just a toilet.
There are other functions that need to be
covered.
Let’s have a look at the system on this
Slide and how different sanitation products
move through the system.
What you see is a dry toilet over a single
VIP.
The excreta, indicated by the black arrow,
is emptied and transported manually to a transfer
station outside the neighborhood or refugee
camp.
From there a truck takes the sludge to a thickening
pond, where the sludge settles to the ground
and the clear effluent stay on top.
Effluent, now shown with a blue arrow, is
further treated in Waste stabilization ponds,
while the sludge, shown with the brown arrow,
is put onto planted drying beds.
Once the sludge is dried it can be applied
in agriculture.
The now treated effluent is added the groundwater.
Now how can we categorize these technologies
and approach the mess on this Slide in a systematic
manner?
In the compendium of sanitation systems and
technologies we categorize all sanitation
technologies into 5 different groups with
the color code as seen on the image.
A sanitation system always consists of a combination
of technologies from several or all of the
5 different categories.
The first functional group is called user
interface, meaning the toilet itself.
So the interface between the user and the
rest of the sanitation system.
This can be a dry toilet, a flush toilet or
a urine diverting toilet.
Sanitation products have to be collected and
stored on site in some systems.
Therefore the name of the second functional
group.
There some treatment can already occur.
A widely used technology from this category
is the septic tank, in which some physical
separation of sludge and effluent occurs and
some anaerobic degradation.
Once the collection technology is full, the
sanitation products need to be emptied and
transported.
This yellow category is called conveyance.
All sanitation products need treatment, thus
all treatment technologies are categorized
in the fourth green functional group and finally
they can be safely reused
or disposed.
During a humanitarian crisis, resources are
limited and sanitation systems break down,
are inexistent or have been destroyed.
It is therefore not feasible to implement
a complete sanitation system from the very
beginning that takes into consideration all
functions.
The sphere standards provide guidance on the
minimal standards for excreta management during
a humanitarian response.
This can help to set priorities and provide
minimal services.
There are two standards for excreta management
in the Sphere guidelines which we will have
a closer look at.
Please go and have a look at the sphere standards
on their homepage on the link provided here,
to find out more about the exact indicators,
key actions and other WASH related standards.
(((As in video quiz: The sphere standards
are currently under revision and an updated
version will be available soon)))
The first goal of excreta management is to
create an environment free from human faeces,
meaning that all living areas are free from
faecal contamination.
The first key action is to implement appropriate
excreta containment measures.
With the lack of resources this can mean a
clean-up campaign, the demarcation of defecation
fields and the construction of public toilet
facilities.
All of these actions have to be implemented
in consultation with the affected community
as they have key information from the ground
and will be the ones to use the facilities.
Sanitation facilities have to be constructed
away from water sources and not too close
to the groundwater table.
Locations downstream of rivers or at the bottom
of a slope are preferred.
The second minimal standard in sphere is the
safe containment of excreta.
The standard says that all affected people
should have adequate, appropriate and acceptable
toilets, sufficiently close to their living
spaces to allow rapid, safe and secure access
at all times, day and night.
There are 3 key actions to take in the first
step.
Consultation with the affected community on
the planned actions and the provision of adequate
toilets and hand-washing facilities.
A toilet is not just a toilet.
There are several functions that a toilet
has to fulfill in order to qualify as adequate,
appropriate and acceptable.
A toilet has to be inclusive to everybody,
including elderly people, people with reduced
mobility, pregnant woman, children, staff
and everyone else.
A toilet should be safe to use and provide
privacy.
This can be achieved by constructing public
toilets not more than 50 m away from dwelling,
by sex segregated and lockable toilets.
Furthermore it has to fulfill basic hygienic
functions, such as the possibility for menstrual
hygiene management, at minimum through the
provision of water and a solid waste bin with
a lid.
Also hand-washing facilities and avoiding
that the toilet becomes a breeding nest for
flies and mosquitos is needed.
It should be ensured that the toilets can
be emptied when full and that transport, treatment
and disposal or reuse of sludge is warranted.
Toilets should not be a source of groundwater
contamination.
For public toilets there should not be more
than 50 people per toilet in a female to male
ration of 3 to 1.
However the goal of any long term intervention
is to provide household toilets, which are
organized by the community themselves.
Many prolonged humanitarian responses require
an action plan that goes beyond quick fixes
and immediate interventions.
A long term action plan is needed after immediate
actions were implemented.
This includes the rehabilitation of existing
infrastructure or the construction of new
one.
Implementation can be done step wise with
services that are upgradable.
Constant monitoring is required in order to
assure the success of the steps.
Especially in the acute phase of an emergency
public and environmental health threats need
constant surveillance.
The data for monitoring can be gathered through
community surveys, observations in the field
and expert interviews.
As mentioned before sanitation systems have
to fulfill different needs during different
phases and types of a humanitarian response,
which can require different technologies than
those needed at a different stage.
During chronic crises these different phases
cannot be distinguished and several interventions
might have to be implemented at the same time.
In the following example the goal is to show
how a sanitation system can be developed over
time.
This fictional example of an armed conflict
forces a city’s inhabitants to flee their
houses and resettle in an isolated, rural
area.
Water supply is not yet provided and the first
goal is provide a quick fix sanitation solution
that serves a large amount of people and that
safely contains excreta from human contact.
The proposed first step is to implement public
shallow trench latrines.
Together with hand-washing facilities next
to the latrines, the first standard of Sphere
can be fulfilled.
These interventions are complemented with
a hygiene awareness campaign in order to educate
people on public health threats.
Shallow trench latrines can be implemented
quickly using local materials.
Little construction work is needed.
The latrines are constructed far enough from
any drinking water sources, downstream of
the dwelling area.
The shallow trench latrine is only a feasible
sanitation option for an acute humanitarian
crisis and whenever possible other solutions
are preferred.
The shallow trench latrine will be explained
in more detail in a later module.
The technology should always be completed
with hand-washing facilities, like the one
you see on the picture from Somalia.
The public shallow trench latrines will fill
up quickly and adequate treatment and disposal
is needed.
On-site lime treatment can help to hygienist
the excreta.
Afterwards the trenches are filled and covered
and the site must be decommissioned and secured.
This will help to prevent human contact with
the contained faeces in the long term.
After the acute phase is over and more materials,
skills and capacities enter the newly formed
refugee camp, more appropriate sanitation
solutions can be implemented in parallel to
the shallow trench latrines.
A raised latrine can be constructed with a
holding tank below, as more material, like
tanks and toilet user interfaces are now entering
the affected area or have been produced or
organized locally.
On this image you see raised latrines, with
buckets beneath that can be emptied easily.
In the forefront a simple hand-washing facility
provides the necessary hand hygiene after
defecation.
These public latrines where implemented in
Haiti.
As these holding tanks fill up, a conveyance
method is needed.
Vacuum trucks will empty the holding tanks,
dispose the faecal sludge in an adequate distance
from the human settlement as no treatment
system is yet in place.
This simple service extension further can
guarantee public health in the camp.
As there are still no treatment options available,
the waste is disposed in the form of surface
application without treatment.
This is not an ideal situation as it threatens
environmental health.
This leads to the next extension of sanitation
services.
The goal is to provide an improved sanitation
system that covers all steps of the sanitation
service chain, is appropriate to the urban
community living in the camp and that provides
toilets on household level instead of public
toilets.
Furthermore the system needs to be up scalable
and resilient to future acute humanitarian
responses.
Therefore pour-flush toilets are constructed
at a household level, as the urban community
is used to water-based sanitation systems
and will not accept dry sanitation systems
in the long term.
Septic tanks are constructed in a first step.
To treat the sludge from the septic tanks
and the holding tanks, unplanted drying beds
are constructed before final disposal in the
form of now safe surface application of sludge.
The effluent from septic tanks is disposed
in the ground without treatment at this point.
As an intermediate step until unplanted drying
beds can be constructed, some short term sludge
treatment facilities can be implemented such
as sand drying beds, like the ones on the
image implemented by Oxfam during the 2014
emergency response in the Philippines.
Finally a simplified sewer can replace transport
of the effluent from the septic tank to treatment
in waste stabilization ponds.
The raised latrines can still be used in public
places such as school, markets health centres
etc.
Please note, due to time constraints that
we only talked about the technology part of
the sanitation system.
However a sanitation system not only consists
of hardware but also software, which also
has to be developed.
Users need to be informed and involved, staff
needs to be trained, financing of the system
has to be secured, including for operation
and maintenance.
All of this takes time and resources and has
to be taken into account.
This example shows just one way of how a system
can be developed.
This development always has to be based on
many different criteria in order to select
the best fit & the most appropriate system.
The criteria will be introduced in more detail
in the next module.
In this module you have learned why sanitation
service delivery is crucial for maintaining
public health during humanitarian crises.
You’ve learned about the different functional
groups that are needed for full sanitation
service delivery.
We then had a look at the Sphere standards
for emergency excreta disposal.
Remember that these standards are minimal
standards for an acute humanitarian crisis
and that implementing them will not provide
a complete sanitation system.
You will have to upgrade a sanitation system
over the course of a humanitarian response,
as the needs will change and there is no one
size fits all solution to sanitation.
We had a look at one fictional example on
how to develop sanitation over time.
I hope you learned a lot, thank you for your
attention and if there are any questions left,
please go to the forum where we can discuss
together on the topic.
Thank you very much.