Hello and welcome back to this module on selecting
the most appropriate sanitation technology
for a given context.
In this module, we will learn about different
criteria that need to be considered in order
to select the most appropriate sanitation
technology for a given context.
For this we will have a look at the objectives
and goals of sanitation during a humanitarian
response and how they can change over time.
There are many different types of Emergencies.
They differ in duration, in intensity, in
destruction, in number of displacements, in
risk and type.
Furthermore a crisis occurs in a specific
context.
The compendium of sanitation systems and technologies
counts 57 different established sanitation
technologies and 9 systems, not counting the
various emerging technologies and service
delivery models.
The task of finding the most suitable sanitation
technology for each context is therefore challenging
and requires a lot of experience and expert
knowledge of the context.
We will notice how different contexts can
be, when looking at the example of the Nepal
earthquake humanitarian response in 2015 and
the humanitarian crisis in the Middle East,
where Syrian refugees are displaced in camps
in Jordan,
Over the course of this module we will learn
how to categorize these different contexts
and find out the relevant criteria that will
help to determine which sanitation technology
to select.
When looking at a specific context there is
a variety of attributes we need to consider.
On one hand we have the physical environment
consisting of the natural and the built environment.
On the other hand, we have the enabling environment
consisting of everything we cannot physically
touch, like laws, skills, culture etc.
A lot of different questions will determine
which sanitation solution is the most appropriate.
Here are some of the questions you will need
to answer during an assessment of the natural
and built environment:
What are existing water bodies that can be
used as a source of water or as a receiving
water body for treated or untreated wastewater?
What is the demography of the population?
How many men/ women, children, disabled, elderly
people are there and what are their needs
in terms of sanitation?
What materials are available right now, in
a week from now, in a month from now?
What other resources can be used?
Are there matching skills and capacities?
Is there water available for hand-washing,
for flushing, for cleaning?
Is there enough space?
How much?
The example of a destroyed neighborhood in
Kathmandu shows how space can be a limiting
factor.
In this case camps were constructed in available
open urban spaces or outside the city, where
more space was available.
As the danger was over within a few days/weeks,
the sanitation facilities were of temporary
nature and the focus was on rehabilitating
the existing urban infrastructure, once the
threat of a public health crisis due to the
lack of sanitation was averted.
Other questions are:
What is the condition of the existing sanitation
infrastructure?
Can it be rehabilitated and how fast?
What are the soil properties, for example
the infiltration rate of clean water, of greywater
and of wastewater?
And how high is the groundwater table?
What is the topography of the area and the
rainfall patterns, as well as temperature?
What are the sanitation products, such as
toilet paper, anal cleansing water, menstrual
hygiene products, that need to be dealt with?
For the enabling environment the questions
are often more complex and the answers are
not straightforward.
Two initial important questions for a sanitation
system are if people are used to sit or squat
and what product they use to clean themselves
after defecation.
For example in India most people are used
to squat when using the toilet and clean themselves
with water after defecation, while in a European
context people usually have sitting toilets
and clean themselves with toilet paper.
This can be found out easily.
What happens if the question of toilet style
is ignored was seen in Germany during the
refugee crisis in 2016, when refugees from
Syria, used to squatting toilets and water
for anal cleansing, were faced with sitting
toilets and toilet paper in German cities.
There were even cases of open defecation due
to the lack of appropriate sanitation facilities.
In this case manufacturers reacted and came
up with a portable hybrid toilet suiting sitters
and squatters.
Other questions are more difficult to answer
and often have a political component.
Who pays for which service?
Can permanent structures be constructed or
not?
Are there technologies that are not allowed
or that are preferred?
Is there a governmental protocol on emergency
sanitation?
Gathering all of this information can be challenging,
especially during an emergency when the flow
of information is cut due to the lack of communication
methods, the lack of acting institutions and
general chaos.
An assessment should always try to gather
information from different sources in order
to cross check information.
In many countries a lot of data already exists
in the form of institutional knowledge, governmental
documents, information by sanitation service
providers or NGOs on the ground.
This literature can often be accessed before
arriving on the ground.
Once in the field, general observations of
the natural and built environment are important
as well as measurements and testing of soil,
topography and other physical parameters.
Mapping of the area can be done with drones,
by hand or maps may already exist.
Finally gathering primary data from key informants,
community leaders and the affected population
is crucial, as these people have a lot of
knowledge of the area and are the ones that
will use the sanitation system in the end
and therefore need to be consulted about sanitation
habits, preferred location of the toilets
etc.
Alongside the local context, key criteria
to consider are the type and phase of an emergency.
A crisis that requires an acute humanitarian
response, but will be over soon, for example
a natural disaster, will require a different
and maybe only temporary sanitation system
alongside rehabilitation of infrastructure.
This compared to a protracted armed crisis
that is expected to last an indefinite time
period.
The traditional model to look at a crisis
is to categorize it into different phases.
A growing number of “chronic crises” are
on the rise an make this traditional approach
often unfeasible, as these phases get mixed
up and acute humanitarian responses are needed
several times in sequence.
For simplification we will use the terminology
of the traditional phases of a crisis again,
while keeping in mind, that these are not
as clearly separated or even mixed up in a
chronic crisis
It might be that different technologies are
required over the course of a humanitarian
response.
With an existing sanitation system, the goal
will be to rehabilitate the existing system,
while immediate solutions cover the acute
and recovery phase.
With no previous system existing, a completely
new system must be implemented.
This can be developed over time.
It has to be noted again, that infrastructure
is only part of a sanitation services.
Skills and capacities of staff and institutions
have to be developed and their needs also
vary over the course of a humanitarian response.
Furthermore in order to assure the sustainability
of services, funding not only for implementation
but also operation and maintenance needs to
be secured.
Disaster risk reduction measurements for sanitation
services and building up resilience of systems
should be the main task before a crisis happens.
During the acute phase, systems are needed
that can be implemented fast with available
material and with the skills and capacities
of the staff on the ground.
During the recovery phase, existing services
should be extended and upgraded and consideration
should be given to financial sustainability.
Post crisis is to assure that the complete
sanitation service chain is covered and that
if infrastructure existed it is rehabilitated
or decommissioned.
In this module we learned that not only the
built and natural environment will influence
the selection of a sanitation system but also
the enabling environment consisting of users,
laws and regulations, skills and capacities,
the government, financial arrangements and
institutional arrangements.
An assessment of the context is therefore
crucial and should be done as soon as possible.
Furthermore the nature of the humanitarian
crisis and the context will influence the
technology that is chosen.
Thank you very much for your attention.
Let us know in the forum if there are any
questions left or if you want to share your
own experience of selecting sanitation technologies
in the field.
We are looking forward to exchange with you
in the forum.
Thank you very much.