Hi there and welcome back to the module on
on-site technologies for collection, storage
and partial treatment for the emergency context.
After learning the theory behind sanitation
in humanitarian responses, it is now time
to have a look at some of the technologies.
In this module you will learn about different
on-site technologies that are suited for an
acute humanitarian crisis.
Remember that there are many criteria that
will determine whether a technology is suitable
for a context.
We will have a look at one technology that
can be categorized as a user interface, the
shallow trench latrine a simple upgrade to
controlled open defecation.
Then you will be introduced to 5 on-site technologies
from the collection and storage slash treatment
functional group.
Please note that this list is in no way complete
and you should consult other literature in
order to find the best technology for your
context.
During an acute humanitarian crisis, it might
be that sanitation infrastructure is completely
destroyed or unusable in the short- to medium
term.
People will still need to defecate and until
another sanitation system exists, they are
often forced to defecate in the open.
This is a major health threat as it can spread
diseases such as diarrhoea, cholera or typhus.
Therefore, usually the first measure until
materials for improved latrine construction
are available is to control open defecation.
This means that designated areas should be
allocated where open defecation is allowed,
for example a field away from health centres,
schools or food places such as kitchens and
markets.
There are several easy measures to improve
a controlled open defecation field.
Digging shallow trenches will make decommissioning
of such a field easier, providing minimal
privacy with simple screens can make it more
dignified to use and hand-washing facilities
will further enhance hygienic conditions.
The way it works is simple.
Shallow trenches are dug.
People defecate into the trenches.
There needs to be a manager of the field that
can provide safety and decommissions a trench
when it is full by covering it with the dug
soil.
After the use of this technology, the soil
needs to be secured from the community and
finally treated.
This method can be a suitable option in the
immediate aftermath of a crisis, due to the
low complexity and low capital costs involved.
It can be constructed with very simple tools
and materials in a short period of time in
less than a day.
However, this solution should be quit after
a couple of days, as it is not considered
an improved and safe sanitation technology
and does not provide the security and accessibility
of an improved toilet as required by Sphere
standard 2 on excreta management.
The risk of cross contamination still exists,
as flies and other vectors cannot be kept
out.
The land used needs to be rehabilitated afterwards,
which can be very costly.
About 0.25 m2 of land is needed per user per
day.
This is about half a football field for 10’000
inhabitants per day.
This adds up very quickly over the course
of time and is therefore not a long term solution.
Slightly improved solutions are deep trench
latrines.
For this technology a deep trench of approximatively
1.5-3 meters is dug and several dry toilet
user interfaces consisting of a simple slab
are built upon.
The pit needs lining in order to prevent it
from collapsing.
This image shows how a deep trench latrine
can be lined with corrugated plastic sheets
and wood pillars.
This can also be done with local materials
such as corrugated sheet iron.
This technology has the advantage of quick
implementation time with local materials and
low skills and capacity requirements.
However, like all pit technologies it is not
suited for areas with a high groundwater table
or rocky, unstable or clay soils.
There is no ventilation possible and therefore
flies and odors remain a nuisance.
Sludge in a public deep trench latrine will
accumulate very fast and feasible emptying
and transport solutions are therefore needed.
Bear in mind that a deep trench latrine is
not considered an improved toilet facility
and should only be implemented in the acute
phase of an emergency when no other solutions
are possible.
A new service option that is being tested
by different organisations is container-based
toilets.
Users defecate and urinate into buckets with
a lid and are then emptied on a regular basis.
Container-based toilets can be prefabricated
with plastic moulding or constructed out of
readily available materials such as buckets
with a simple user interface.
The user interface can be a dry toilet or
a urine diverting dry toilet that separates
faeces and urine and collects them in two
different containers.
The main implication of this technology is
that a reliable emptying service needs to
be in place as these toilets fill up quickly.
This service can be provided by private companies
and can provide job opportunities for the
affected community.
A big advantage is that the toilets are mobile
and can be used in existing superstructures
with no need for sub-structures.
They can also be used within the household.
The mobile toilet can be accessed day and
night.
This is a major plus to reduce the risk of
gender-based violence by providing the safety
of the private space.
Furthermore, it can be used to manage child
faeces an issue often overlooked.
They are also appropriate for flooded areas
or where the groundwater table is very high.
A major implication is that the system depends
on a high quality and regular collection service
and further treatment is needed.
Users need to be well trained and have to
buy-in to this technology.
This might require substantial awareness raising
and there is a risk that users could reject
to use this technology.
Chemical toilets are another example of prefabricated,
ready to deploy toilet facilities that can
be delivered as a complete unit without need
for further construction on-site.
This image shows the deployment of a chemical
toilet on an escape route in the Ukraine.
In this technology, the excreta is hygienised
and stabilized in the toilet with the help
of liquid chemicals, such as Formaldehyde
and Glutaraldehyde.
There are also biological degradable solutions
that don’t have disinfecting properties
but can help reduce odors and unpleasant smells.
These types of toilets are usually public
and not suitable for private households.
Here, we are installing mobile latrines.
What we are trying to [inaudible], avoid people
going to the grass; going into the forest.
and i think that will save lives.
In the short video from Ukraine you just saw,
the toilets were installed, because the forest
along the road was a mine field and therefore
people couldn’t go there for defecation.
The big advantage of chemical toilets is that
they can be mobilized rapidly, if there is
a service provider in the region.
So far this is rather uncommon outside of
Europe, North America and parts of Latin America,
but mobile toilet businesses of different
kinds are emerging.
The toilets are usually well accepted,
And they are very appropriate where digging
a pit is not possible.
However, chemical toilets are NOT a long-term
solution and need to be replaced with a complete
sanitation system.
They need daily servicing and therefore a
service provider.
This can become very costly or impossible
if such a provider does not exist.
Furthermore, a waste water treatment plant
is needed to treat this sludge and laws and
regulations need to be in favor of dumping
the human waste from such toilets into waste
water treatment plants.
A borehole latrine is a technology that is
used mainly in the acute response phase, when
a large number of latrines need to be constructed
rapidly and the site conditions do not allow
for excavation of bigger pits.
With a borehole driller available, this can
be a quick way of digging a great number of
latrines within a short period of time.
A dry toilet can be used as a user interface
on top.
The borehole is then used like any other pit.
A lining of the pipe in the top section is
also required, especially with unstable soil.
For obvious reasons this technology can only
be implemented with a borehole driller available
onsite.
If so, it is very inexpensive and quick to
construct, easily understood and only requires
a small workforce.
The requirements for the superstructure remain
the same as with any other pit based technology.
As there is no ventilation, possible odors
and flies are often a problem.
The toilets are not suited for unstable soils
and high groundwater tables.
Also the lifespan of a borehole latrine can
be quite short and therefore a new system
is needed soon after their construction.
Lime treatment can be used for faecal sludge
treatment.
Lime is a fine white powder, of which a sufficient
amount is added to sludge and then mixed in
a container.
This increases the pH to 12.
A high pH over enough time disinfects the
sludge and slows down or stops biological
processes responsible for odors.
As mixing is crucial to the process the technology
usually consists of a tank and a mixing device.
On this image an open tank is used and lime
is added and mixed manually.
Workers are wearing protective gear, as there
is a potential health risk if not handled
properly.
The correct combination of dosage and retention
time of lime is crucial for this treatment
and depends on the total solids of the sludge
and other chemical characteristics.
Therefore the local faecal sludge has to be
tested in order to determine the correct dosage.
Typically it is around 20-35% of lime per
dry mass of sludge.
Lime costs around 100-800 US dollars per ton
in different countries.
Lime treatment is useful due to the short
treatment time of the sludge.
The process is simple and uses materials that
are usually locally available.
But it has to be noted that pathogen regrowth
will occur again once the pH drops below 11
and therefore lime treatment is rather a temporary
stabilisation than a long term solution.
In this video we learned about different feasible
technologies that can be used during an acute
humanitarian crisis.
Technologies that can be implemented quickly,
that mostly use locally available materials,
that can be replicated and upgraded and that
serve a large number of people are preferred.
Thank you very much for your attention.
And i hope to exchange with you on the forum
about different technologies.
Thank you very much.