In this lecture, we are going to look at technologies
for on-site blackwater and
Hi and welcome to the third module, on collection
and storage technologies.
greywater management, including the septic
tank and the biogas reactor.
These technologies are based on anaerobic
processes, and I will just
explain what that means.
The word 'anaerobic' describes biological
processes that occur in the
absence of oxygen.
These processes naturally take place in swamps,
marshes, ponds and other
standing water bodies.
They can easily be recognized
by the formation of gas bubbles, as shown
in these beautiful photographs.
The gas is formed, for example, at the bottom
of a pond, where the anaerobic
bacteria decompose carbon-rich organic substances
into methane and carbon dioxide
(also called 'biogas').
The gas bubbles then rise to the surface.
In cold areas, where the lake surfaces
freeze in wintertime, it can sometimes be
observed that
the bubbles get trapped below the ice surface,
as shown on the two pictures
on the right side.
In wastewater engineering, we often talk about
'anaerobic digestion.'
The term 'anaerobic digestion' refers to the
degradation and stabilization of
organic matter by microorganisms without oxygen,
leading to production of biogas.
Both anaerobic and aerobic processes are used
for wastewater treatment.
The aerobic ones need aeration systems to
provide enough oxygen and are technically
a bit more complex.
They are, therefore, not so commonly used
at the collection and storage level.
We will introduce those technologies later
in the collectors about centralized and
semi-centralized treatment.
So much for an introduction to the general
processes.
Now we want to look
at a few technologies.
The septic tank is among the most widespread
onsite sanitation technologies.
There are two important things you have to
know about the septic tank.
First - it is a water-tight tank, typically
made of reinforced concrete,
polyethylene or fiberglass and, second - it
has an outlet, through which
the clarified effluent leaves the tank.
In practice, people are not always aware
of those two aspects.
They may even call an open-bottom pit a septic
tank, which is actually wrong.
Blackwater and greywater enter the tank through
an inlet T.
Settleable solids fall down to the bottom,
where they accumulate as sludge.
With time, the sludge undergoes some stabilization
by anaerobic digestion.
It has to be removed every 3-5 years.
Floatable substances move up to the surface,
forming a scum layer.
The effluent from the clearwater zone, in
the middle, flows out through an outlet T
and is then typically infiltrated, for example,
in a leach field.
One or two separation walls in the tank can
improve the solid / liquid
separation process.
The good thing about septic tanks is that
they are passive and do not require
electrical energy to function.
This makes this technology quite robust.
Construction is relatively costly but the
technology has a long service life
and requires little maintenance.
The costs for mechanical emptying, however,
may be considerable.
Little space is required because this technology
is typically built underground.
On the negative side - it has to be mentioned
that the removal of
pathogenic organisms, suspended matter, organic
substances and nutrients is
relatively low, therefore, the effluent, as
well as the sludge,
require further treatment and / or appropriate
discharge.
To ensure optimum performance of the septic
tank, it has to be regularly pumped
as shown in the photo.
An anaerobic baffled reactor, or ABR, is like
an improved version of a large
septic tank.
Its functioning is very similar, but it is
equipped with baffles,
which form several anaerobic chambers to remove
and digest organics and improve
the treatment performance.
The treatment can be further improved by providing
1 to 3
fixed-bed filter units, which helps to trap
non-settleable suspended particles
and provide an increased surface for microbial
growth.
This technology is called "anaerobic filter."
An ABR, or an anaerobic filter, can be installed
at the small scale for on-site
collection and treatment, but also at semi-centralized
or centralized
treatment level.
More detailed explanations of these two technologies
will be provided in module 3.2.
In the septic tank, ABR (or anaerobic filter),
the gases produced in the anaerobic processes
are just released into the
atmosphere because their quantities are relatively
low.
The biogas reactor,
or anaerobic digestor, however, is designed
to generate as much biogas
as possible and to capture and collect it,
so that it can be used as a renewable
energy source for cooking or other purposes.
The blackwater from a toilet can be directly
connected to the digestor.
In order to produce significant amounts of
biogas, additional inputs like cow dung or
organic solid waste, are normally mixed in
at the inlet.
The substrate flows into the reactor, where
it has a retention time of,
typically, 15-to-25 days.
The biogas collects in the dome at the top
of the reactor, and is transported
to the point of use, through a gas pipe.
When new substrate is added to the reactor
or when the gas pressure rises, the digestate
flows into the expansion chamber
from where it can be removed.
In the photos, you can see some examples
of different biogas reactor designs.
Picture on the upper left shows a thick
stone reactor under construction.
This is another thick stone digestor, similar
to
the one previously shown on the drawing.
As you can see, the space requirement is
quite low, because it can be built underground.
On the right side, you can see a floating
dome reactor, where the
gas storage can move up and down, depending
on the gas volume inside;
and this one here is a biogas stove.
This technology has the clear benefit that
no energy is required for operation, but energy
is actually produced.
A high reduction of organic matter and particles
can be achieved.
The digestate is almost odorless and still
contains all the nutrients, so it
can be used as an excellent fertilizer, however,
the agricultural application
has to be done correctly and carefully because
the digestate may still contain
some pathogens.
This technology has many benefits
but its success depends on correct implementation
by experts, proper
operation and regular maintenance.
We have seen that there are several anaerobic
technologies that are robust
and easy to operate for on-site treatment
of blackwater and greywater.
I want you to remember two things from this
module:
First - septic tanks can be a good solution
but it is important that the
effluent is properly disposed of and that
the sludge is regularly removed.
The second thing that I want you to remember
is that the biogas reactor
can be an attractive technology, but the economic
benefits do not mean that it is
always automatically successful.
Whether or not the initial investment
costs can be recovered will depend on the
correct design and implementation
and their motivated operator.