Unfortunately, around the world, huge amounts
of waste water and sludge end up untreated
into rivers, lakes,
and into the sea.
What does it take to treat them?
I will now introduce you to the centralized
and semi-centralized treatment technologies.
The treatment process can be divided into
several stages.
The pre-treatment, the primary treatment,
the secondary treatment, the tertiary treatment,
or post-treatment.
Within these categories,
some technologies are based on biological
processes:
aerobic, anaerobic or both.
And some others on physical, chemical ones.
In this module, we'll have a look
at the different treatment stages
and then focus on pre- and post-treatment,
which can be implemented in any system.
we will review the anaerobic technologies,
The learning goals
of this series of modules on treatment are:
get to know the different treatment technologies,
understand the different treatment stages
and processes,
and understand the different functions
of the treatment technologies.
Let's start.
First, let's review
the different treatment stages.
The two main treatment stages
are called primary and secondary.
"Primary treatment" consists
in the liquid/solid separation.
For example, through sedimentation.
As for the "Secondary treatment", it consists
of the removal
of organic matter and suspended solids.
The "pre-treatment" is the preliminary removal
of waste water or sludge constituents, such
as oil,
grease and various solids, like sand and trash.
Pre-treatment is a must.
On the other hand,
the "tertiary treatment" and "post-treatment"
consist of removing elements like remaining
pathogens,
nutrients such as nitrogen and phosphorous,
or micropollutants from the effluent.
Tertiary treatment embraces a large spectrum
of technologies,
and most of them are not implemented in low-
and middle-income countries.
Too expensive and too complex.
Let's have a look at a few pre-treatment technologies.
Pre-treatment is a preliminary removal of
waste water
or sludge constituents, either before conveyance,
or before treatment systems.
It is meant to prevent the accumulation of
solids
in further stages and avoid blockages.
It can also help produce abrasion
of mechanical parts and extend the life
of sanitation infrastructure.
Pre-treatment technologies
use physical removal mechanisms such as screening,
flotation, settling,
and filtration.
"Screening" is used, for example, in the screens
to prevent trash
and coarse solids to end up in the sewerage
system
or the treatment plant.
"Flotation" is used,
for example, in grease traps and grids interceptors
to remove the fats, oil and grease.
Finally, "settling" is used, for example,
in the sand trap,
or grit chambers, to remove the heavier solids.
As you can see in this figure, grease traps
and grit chambers
can be combined in one technology.
On the other end of the treatment process,
there are different possibilities to polish
the effluent:
the so called post- treatment technologies.
Depending on the design and use of the effluent,
or on national standards for discharging water
bodies,
a post-treatment step may be required
to remove pathogens, residual suspended solids,
or its soil constituents.
This can be mainly achieved through tertiary
filtration
and disinfection techniques.
Filtration process can be classified
in two categories: first, the depth,
or "packed-bed filtration", as shown in this
figure,
where the effluent passes through a filter
medium,
such as sand or activated carbon.
On the other hand, “surface filtration“
removes undesired elements through sieving;
for example,
through membranes.
As for "disinfection", its target is the elimination
of pathogenic micro-organisms.
Chlorine is the most widespread technique.
Chlorine is mixed with effluent at the outset
of the treatment plant,
as shown in this figure, with a chlorine diffuser
and a chlorine mixer.
You can also do disinfection through UV radiation
or ozonation,
the two being more energy intensive.
However, you have to be cautious with disinfection.
For example, chlorine together with organic
matter
can form toxic byproducts, harmful for the
environment.
It should thus only be applied if strictly
necessary.
You don't want to create more problems than
you actually solve.
To sum up, we saw that treatment is a succession
of different steps,
the main ones being the primary and secondary
treatment.
Pre-treatment is a must, as a kind of preventive
measure,
either at the household level, at the street
level,
or at the inlet of a treatment plant.
Post-treatment is not always necessary,
and a pragmatic approach is recommended.
The effluent quality should match the intended
end use
practice, or the quality of the receiving
water body.