Hello to everybody,
I am Hans Mosler.
I'm a professor at the University
of Phyche,
working at the hawack in the department
of environmental social sciences,
and I'm the head of the Environmental
and Psychology group.
I would present you the module
about hygiene promotion,
using a systematic behavior
change approach and what this means,
I will show you in a
few minutes,
but let me share some
experiences
with you first.
There was
an implementation of water supply,
but people still
used unsafe wells,
I'm referring to Haiti after
the earthquake.
Building of toilets
but nearly no use
or very very inadequate use as you see here.
And we
introduced
hand-washing
and there was nearly
no or low compliance.
So the question arises,
how to introduce behavior change?
We do promotion
of behavior
and expect behavior change.
But there's a
very important statement- Behavior change
starts in the head of the people.
What does it mean,
that something in the mindset
of the persons has to change.
And what exactly has to change?
We call it factors,
behavioral factors
or psychosocial factors,
like knowledge,
perceived social pressure,
or attitudes,
beliefs about costs
and benefits and so on.
And very important is also
that we make use of
the difference between the doers
and the non-doers because
these are different.
They have to be different because they show
different
behaviors.
So here you see
that the doers
and the non-doers are different,
in factor C minus
and in factor B minus.
So, in a first step we need
to identify the behavioral
factors,
in the second step,
then measure
and we want to measure
and calculate these factors.
Then we select the behavior
change techniques accordingly,
and accordingly means
that we select
behavior change techniques which change
C
or B,
A we don't
have to change.
The we design
and implement a software,
and at the end we
want to monitor, we want to evaluate
behavior change
and the behavioral factors.
Whether we really change C
and B,
that's really the point.
So we have
four phases,
tools and outputs.
The last phase I will not introduce
here, because many times you in
emergencies you don't have the time
and the resources.
So, I begin
with the first step here:
Identify potential behavioral
and contextual factors.
First, I would like to go
with you tramp
with you in the promotional situation
like this one.
Imagine you are standing behind this desk
and you are promoting chlorination of
drinking water,
and before
you talk you have to think
what these people think.
So what might it be?
Am I at risk?
Why?
How to do it?
How should I do it?
Really.
What does it cost?
What does it bring? Chlorination costs
of course.
Do I like it, do I like to drink chlorinated
water?
What will others say
if I chlorine in my water?
Can I do it too
or do I need additional devices?
And how to manage it in in
the daily life?
So these thoughts can
easily be arranged
into five
blocks of factors.
Risk factors,
Attitude factors,
Norm factors,
Ability factors
and Self-regulation factors,
this is the run off model.
Risk factors are a person's understanding
and awareness of the health risk.
Attitude factors are of a person's
positive or negative stance towards
the behavior.
Norms factors are the
perceives represent to perceive
social pressure.
And,
Ability factors are
about the confidence a person has
in his or her ability to perform
the behavior.
And Self-regulation factors
are a person's attempts
to plan and self monitor
a behavior and to manage conflicting
goals and distracting cues.
On the left side
here you see the behavior change
techniques,
from which we know that we
can change exactly this
factors here.
These factors are the drivers of behavior.
On the right side behavior,
intention and habits.
Down here you have the context,
the moderating context which might influence
also the behavior.
I now know which behavior factors
I have to test,
and now I want to
determine measure
and determine these behaviors factors,
and we do that with a standardized questionnaire.
We have for example here
the norms
and the others effect other others disapproval.
People who are important to you
do they rather approve
or disapprove if you practice open
defecation,
or if you're using the latrine,
from one nearly all disapprove
to five nearly all approve.
Then we do have
doers/non-doers analysis.
You see here the doers are the
latrine users
and the non-doers are the non-users
of latrines.
And you'll see for person A to W
the score in perceived effort,
and the score in others approval.
Now we
can calculate the mean score
for both,
and then look
how big is the difference.
And here for the perceived effort the difference
is not that big,
so we can
leave this factor.
But the difference in
others approval,
there's a big difference.
So we have to target exactly this
factor.
OK.
We know now the behavioral factors
which we have to change,
now we select the behavior change techniques.
This we do we the catalog
of 36 behavior change
techniques. This is just quite
new for you,
that there's a catalog of behavior change
techniques. Normally you have a program
like C L T S
or C H C
or FAST,
but this is a catalog.
And the advantage here
is that for each of these
factors behavioral factors
you have behavior
change techniques which we know
that you can change this factor with.
So for example,
other behavior from public
commitment let people commit to
a favorite behavior
and make their commitment public.
Yes,
36 behavior change techniques
cover all the RANA's factors.
To conclude
here,
systematic behavior change enables you
first, to exactly determine
the behavior effect of which you have to change.
This is very very tailored to
your target population.
Then you have a focused selection of
the corresponding behavior change strategies.
And if you want,
you can also prove
the record of success by
the evaluation step which I did not present
so far.
How to apply it in
emergencies?
Well the key principles
are take into account all
sorts of behavioral factors,
not only health risk factors,
but also attitude norms,
abilities,
and self-regulation factors.
And perform the doer/non-doer
analysis,
asked both
kind of people.
And I would also
differentiate between
the acute phase,
the immediate response,
and in established settings like in camps.
For the immediate response,
you might do a rapid
assessment by conducting
a qualitative analysis
with 10 doers and 10 non-doers.
Or without any
evidence you apply behavior
change techniques out
of these five blocks,
you choose
two of each effect block
and apply these behavioral change
techniques without any evidence,
that's also possible.
In established settings,
you have time and resources I think,
then you conduct a survey
with hundred doers
and hundred non-doers,
and apply step
one, two, three or even four
of the RANA's approach.
Have a closer look at our own
guidelines about the systematic
change approach.
You can download it on our
Web page
and go through it
and get more
used to this kind of approach.
Thank you.