In the previous video, we have seen how to
classify, quantify and map the different waste
produced in a health care facility.
In this video, you will learn about the different
stages of medical waste management.
Since there is no universal answer, we will
also discuss how to choose between various
management systems and identify good and bad
practices.
Medical Waste Management can be divided in
five main stages:
The first stage is the Segregation:
The sorting of the waste in the established
categories must always be the responsibility
of the person who produce it.
Usually a clinical staff member.
Ideally as soon as the waste is produced,
it has to be disposed.
It must be done as close as possible to the
site where the waste is produced.
Of course, it worthy to mention that if the
waste is separated it means that the treatment
will be different.
There is no point in sorting wastes that eventually
undergoes the same treatment process.
The second stage is the Temporary Storage:
Waste must be collected regularly.
It must never be allowed to accumulate where
it is produced.
The volume , the capacity of the containers,
and the frequency of collection are the main
parameters to account.
The third stage is the Transport
…to the waste area: The waste are separated
in categories is transported to the waste
area.
In a way that reduces the possibility of accidents
such as spillages for example
The fourth stage is the Treatment:
According to the system in place, the waste
need to be reduced in volume or made not hazardous
anymore.
To reduce the public health risk such treatment
should be the responsibility of hospital and
done on site.
If no appropriate treatment infrastructure
exists in the vicinity.
Finally, the disposal.
The final and definitive step.
Usually it consists in buring it in a sanitary
landfill or in waste pit.
Here, an example of a plan with a specific
solution for each category and each stage.
Note that general waste is not included because
if not mixed with infectious one it does not
pose any risk.
The one presented here are solutions typically
encountered in a low income settings.
How do you come up with the most appropriate
plan?
Well, that’s indeed the tricky part.
Every context requires adaptation.
National legislation, when existing, must
lead the way.
When a legislation is not available, resources
exist to support the decision making process
Here, a decisional tree proposed by the ICRC
Here others examples of decisional trees by
the WHO,
This scenario illustrates an urban area with
access to modern treatment facilities
This one an urban area WITHOUT access to treatment
facilities
This applies to a peri-urban location
and finally a rural one.
You can later go through each on them in details.
What is common to all these decisional trees
is:
The existence or not of national regulations,
The availability of treatment facilities in
the area,
The space readiness,
The proximity of neighbor communities
And the existing financial and human resources.
The specific steps in the process may vary.
The objective is always the same: safely reduce
the risk of infection spreading.
So finally, how does a system of medical waste
management look like?
How do you do if you have to get rid of sharp
objects such as needles, scalpel or broken
glass?
Here one system for Sharps in low income settings.
We need to start with the segregation.
The simplest option might be to use only a
Safety box.
A paper carton box, widely available everywhere
in the world, specifically designed and labelled
to transport sharp waste.
Safety Boxes need to be transported into the
waste area.
They can be incinerated and finally the ashes
and the remaining needles disposed into a
sharp pit.
The operations behind each step need to be
correctly performed.
Hospital staff need to be properly equipped
and trained.
For example segregation requires to strictly
separate the different categories.
If this is not done, the consequence is simple:
all the steps down the line cannot work anymore.
You can see two examples.
One of a bad triage.
And another of a well-organized nurse trolley
with the proper medical waste containers ready
for segregation immediately after the generation
of the waste.
Same applies for all the other steps.
Here you see, a bad example of storage, while
there, a good one.
Let me stress what is the point here: the
first picture is an example of bad practice,
not because it shows an environment dirty
and not well kept, but because it does not
accomplish to principle of reducing the risk
for the users of the health facility.
Those boxes left unattended, are a temptation
for the kids, they can easy spill over and
therefore requiring remediation procedures,
which are adding extra risks.
Again,
guess in which picture it is easier to have
an accidental spill over of the sharp box?
Sometimes, very simple and low cost solutions
like a trolley, with a flat bed and security
railings can have huge impacts in reduction
of accidents.
No need to be always fancy!
Same question: which practice, in the pictures,
do you think entails less risk?
We have finally arrived in the waste area.
A space that needs to be controlled and properly
equipped.
Clearly there are some practices that are
not recommended and they can be extremely
dangerous for the operators and the surrounding
community.
The slow burning here is extremely unsafe.
A dangerous exposure to dioxins.
Maybe at this point, it is important to distinguish
between burning and incineration.
Burning is a thermal oxidation of waste able
to produce a reduction of the volume but not
is decontamination.
Only when incineration conditions are reached,
we can talk about destruction of the pathogen
load in the waste.
Oxygen, air flow, temperature and retention
time they should be in the right mix to allow
incineration to happen.
I’d like to stress a point that often come
up.
Medical Waste Management is often assimilated
with Incineration only.
Sometimes building or providing a new incinerator
is seen as a kind of miracle solution that
makes the all waste problem disappears.
Unfortunately, an incinerator is only a step
of a whole.
Actually, incineration should be limited as
much as possible, because it always comes
with important negative effects.
A comprehensive study on small scale incinerators
commissioned by WHO in 2004 proved the following
conclusions:
Single chamber incinerators (what I often
call pizza hoven) should be banned because
their emission level is not acceptable.
They don’t reach incineration conditions.
Double-chamber self combustion incinerators,
like this one, should be used only as a transitional
solution.
If chosen, the way they are operated is paramount
it can tilt the balance between the overall
cost benefit analysis.
The same machine is giving very different
results.
More advanced technologies such as assisted
combustion double chambers incinerators or
completely different technology, like small
autoclaving should be promoted as soon as
the proper conditions of financial and technical
sustainability exist.
Problem is that in many cases, these conditions
are very very difficult to meet.
They should be evaluated on a case by case
basis.
Here a table summarizing the suitability treatment
techniques by type of waste
So , now it is clear.
There is no standard solution.
Here another example of how to treat the same
waste, SHARP.
In this case, segregation is pushed further
within the same sharp category.
We now differentiate between needles, glass
and scalpel.
Each of them has its on dedicated container
that it is directly disposed with a dedicated
device on top the pit
Where the sharp will be permanently disposed.
This provides multiple benefits:
it reduce the manipulation of sharps in the
waste area,
it reduces the accidents due to glass explosions,
it reduces the amount of waste to be incinerated.
All very good points, but they need to be
counterbalanced by more attention required
by the staff, more follow-up.
Always a weak point in all systems.
Once again the most adapted solution depends
on the context.
Protecting public health through the management
of wastes can be achieved by a variety of
methods.
A context specific analysis should guide the
selection of an appropriate system.
A way to assess a change in the system is
provided by this reverted pyramid : the ‘waste
hierarchy’: illustrating the most desirable
method at the top to the least desirable at
the base.
Let’s see some examples of applications
of these principles.
Prevent:
For Example: many medical Equipments, such
as intravenous bags, artery catheters, blood
bags, dialysis bags and tubing contain Polyvinyl
Chloride (PVC) plastic.
Incinerated, they produce CHLORINATED DIOXINS
which are extremely potent, toxic substances.
Alternative products, PVC free, exist in the
market.
Their choice would prevent a mayor problem.
-Another example:
The use of digital X-ray imagery would totally
prevent the problem of the disposal of toxic
development liquid.
Reduce:
-The strict respect of segregation procedures
can dramatically reduce the quantity of waste
to be handled as medical waste.
No need to treat kitchen waste as infectious!
and finally Reuse.
this is a Reusable Sharp Container developed
by MSF.
It is safe in protecting medical operators
from accidental puncture, and it can even
be built with local materials, but more importantly,
it prevents to use of whatsoever treatment
(usually incineration) to safely dispose of
the needles it contains.
Its contents is dropped in a dedicated pit,
and kept out reach in a permanent way.
Use these principles as guidelines when designing
a Medical Waste Management system.
Keep in mind that, more often than not, you
will need to compromise in order to enforce
sustainability or to reduce costs, but always
choose the option reducing the overall risk.
In conclusion to recapitulate this video,
we briefly saw the actual steps of a waste
systems,
We saw how the overall system should be designed
according to the local resources available
And more importantly how each step should
be properly executed in order to obtain the
desired effect.
Finally we review the overall set of principles
that should be always at the basis of a sound
medical waste management system
For more information I invite you to refer
to these texts:
Here the World Health Organization “blue
book” on medical waste
Here the technical guidelines produced by
Médecins Sans Frontières with a very practical
approach
And finally, here in the french version, the
guidelines used by the International Committee
of the Red Cross.