Welcome back to part two of this chapter.
Now, we shall continue the
introduction of Chapter One
by giving you first of all
the historical picture
of the spectrum of ethanyl
as recorded in 1951.
So different isotopes
may have different spins.
First of all, there are
quite a few isotopes,
such as the ubiquitous Carbon 13,
which makes up about
99% of organic matter.
And Oxygen 16, also all over the place,
have no spin at all,
although they have
a charged nucleus, of course.
And of course the nucleus
may well be spinning around.
Why should it not?
It does not have a spin and so
the magnetic quantum number
cannot be different, can only be zero
and there's no transitions.
One cannot do any NMR at all.
But this is a long series
of important nuclei
that have a spin one half
and that are actually very popular
in NMR spectroscopy
and also in imaging.
Some nuclei, some isotopes
have a spin quantum number equal to one,
mostly Deuterium and Nitrogen 14,
also Lithium 6.
Some of them have a quantum
number three halves.
Typical examples are Boron 11,
Sodium 23, Chlorine 35 and 37.
By the way, sodium
can be used in NMR as well.
And then some have the spin five half,
such as Oxygen 17
and Aluminum 27 which is actually
very interesting to observe,
and aluminosilicates.
Finally, some have a spin three.
And there are some exotic
examples that go beyond.
Not only do they have spin,
but they have different gammas,
different gyromagnetic ratios.
So this is the gyromagnetic ratio.
This is an inherent property
of the different isotopes
and here you can see that
they've been given in the proper units
of adverse tesla and adverse second.
But that means that if you
multiply with a field of 9.4 tesla,
such that the proto-NMR frequency
appears at 400 MHz,
then automatically the
Deuterium NMR frequency
appears at about 61 MHz
and the Carbon 13 at 100 MHz.
You should remember that there is
a factor here of about one quarter
and you might also wish to remember
that there's a factor
of about one-tenth between the proton
and the Nitrogen 15 frequency.
So, these frequencies have
been given appropriately
in a field of B zero equals 9.4 tesla
because that in fact is quite routine
in the current world of chemistry
and physics.
There are many, many spectrometers
that operate at 400 MHz
because it's reasonably cheap
and yet very effective.
Now we also see that the natural
abundance of these isotopes
varies a great deal.
For example, Deuterium
is only found 0.015%
in ordinary sea water or in rain water.
So that's not very much
and you may wish to enrich it
if you want to observe Deuterium.
Carbon 13 is about 1%.
That can be observed directly
but, of course, you can boost it
by enhancing the population
or by labelling the molecules
with Carbon 13.
Nitrogen 14 may not be boosted
but it's very difficult to observe
because it has a very large
quadrupole splitting.
As you can see,
Notrogen 14 has spin one.
And this is one of the things we have
worked on in Lausanne
over the last few years.
Nitrogen 15 is very is very popular
in biomolecules
because you can introduce it synthetically
by cloning techniques
into molecules and proteins in particular.
O17 is still challenging.
Fluorine 19 is very popular
because it has a very high abundance,
100%, and also because one
can find Fluorine 19 in many
drug molecules but not in
natural living matter.
Silicone 29 is popular
for those studying silicates
and aluminosilicates.
And phosphorus is very popular
in biochemistry because there are
many important phosphates
moving around in organisms.
So you see, every isotope has a
characteristic spin quantum number.
Now, there are some rules about
these quantum numbers.
For example, if the number of protons
and the number of neutrons
are both even, then the resulting
spin quantum number is zero.
That is the case for Carbon 12
and for Oxygen 16.
But you can also have the case
where both the protons
and neutrons appear in odd numbers.
Then we have integer numbers,
quantum numbers,
such as one, two or three.
They could be even and odd
or odd and even
and in either case, we have
so called half integers spins.
Actually, these rules
are not particularly useful.
It is better to look at
the full table, like here.
Now the electromagnetic spectrum
is very vast.
It ranges from very high frequencies
and very short wave lengths
to very low frequencies
and very long wave lengths.
So in spectroscopy, it is
the gamma rays that are used
in Mössbauer spectroscopy
that have the highest energies.
Higher than x-ray, and high x-rays again
are more energetic than
ultra-violet and visible.
And then we have the infra-red range
and below that the microwave range
and much lower yet, we have the radio
frequency range.
So this has several consequences.
First of all, the radio frequencies
are largely innocuous.
Nobody really worries that when
you listen to a transistor radio
on the beach, that you might
get irradiated by the transmittors
or by the receivers, so radio frequency
is quite innocuous
and that has great advantages for MRI.
Radio frequency also can penetrate
through all sorts of tissues
including living humans.
Again, you can check with your radio,
that it works even if you lie
on top of it, and that is the reason
why MRI is so popular.
Whereas, with doing imaging
of humans with visible light
is, of course, very difficult.
Now, NMR actually also
had other advantages
in that we have a great
spread of frequencies
and here on a scale where 400MHz
would correspond to protons,
you see that Fluorine 19
is in the vicinity.
Phosphorous 31 is somewhat below
and then the ubiquitous
Carbon 13 appears at about 100 MHz.
But even if we have a
high resolution spectrometer
that can resolve different
chemical shifts,
then one can distinguish
various types of protons.
So for example, at the top end
we have the aldehydic protons
at the bottom end aliphatic protons.
Zero actually corresponds by convention
to Tetramethylethylene.
And all of this range spends about 4 KHz
out of 400 MHz
which corresponds to 10 ppm,
and indeed that is the common
scale used here.
So the frequencies of NMR transitions
are typically in the range
between 10 and 1,000 MHz.
Incidentally, the world's
most powerful machine
is indeed 1,000 MHz of protons
and you find it at Lyon in France.
Now we shall consider a nucleus
with a magnetic moment µ,
so this is a magnetic moment,
immersed in a magnetic field B.
We can arrange this magnetic field
so that it's parallel to the X-axis
or if you prefer, we can just
align the Z-axis
of our co-ordinate system
with a field.
In that case, all we have to worry about
is the product of the Z component
of the magnetic moment and
the amplitude of the field.
It turns out that this Z component
is determined by the product of M.
That's the magnetic quantum number.
H-bar, that's Planck constant
divided by 2 pi.
Gamma, the gyromagnetic ratio
and the amplitude of the field.
Remember that this M here
can be plus or minus one half
if i equal one half,
so if I equal one half,
it follows that m is either
plus or minus one half.
Now the splitting in energy
can be described as simply
H-bar times the absolute
value of Gamma times B.
And the NMR frequency
is the same as the splitting
divided by H-bar, by H,
so that we have simply
this divided by two pi.
Now for a spin one half
as I said, we have either
m equal plus one half
and we call this the alpha level,
or we have m equal minus one half
and we call this the beta level
and we have a single transition.
So this is the case for a spin one half.
But if we have a spin one,
such as for a neutron
or also for Nitrogen 14,
then we have three possibilities.
We have m, either minus one
or zero, or plus one,
and indeed we have three different levels.
It turns out that the obvious
nomenclature alpha beta gamma
is not common in our business,
so we just use these quantum numbers.
And we notice that if this spin
could be a deterium
or Nitrogen 14, is disolved
in an isotropic liquid,
then in fact it turns out that the two,
the energy splitting between the top
and the middle level
is exactly the same as the energy
splitting between the middle
and bottom level.
So these true transitions are degenerate.
So when we see a line like this,
it actually half of it
comes from the top transition
and half from the bottom transition.
Whereas in this case, for protons,
for example,
there is really only one transition.
So let's attempt to summarize
the main points
of the introductory chapter.
First of all, every isotope
in the periodic table
has a characteristic spin
quantum number i.
Some isotopes have i = 0,
in which case it is
just impossible to do NMR.
This is the case for Carbon 12
and the only way to rescue the situation
is by replacing the Carbon 12
with the Carbon 13.
Now every isotope with i
different from zero
has a characteristic magnetic moment µ.
Nuclear spins have 2i + 1
distinct energy levels
and these energy levels
are labelled by magnetic
quantum numbers, lower case m,
which can vary from minus i
to plus i in steps of one.
In a magnetic field,
the energy levels are split
by an amount that is proportional
to the size of the nuclear magnetic moment
and to the strength of the magnetic field.
So NMR spectroscopy uses
electromagnetic radiation
to induce transitions
between energy levels.
The frequencies of NMR transitions
are typically in the range
between 10 and 1,000 MHz.
The intensities of NMR signals
depend on the differences
in the populations of the energy levels.
These populations are determined
by Boltzmann law
and by the temperature, and by the field
and by the gyromagnetic ratio
and all of these parameters conspire
to make NMR a rather
insensitive technique and this is
in fact the Achilles heel of NMR,
is that one often needs
very concentrated samples
or very long experimental times
to get decent signals,
sufficient information.
And this is one of the driving problems
why so many NMR spectroscopists
are trying to improve the methods.
Thank you.