Welcome to our massively online
open course or MOOC
on basic steps in magnetic resonance.
As we shall see, magnetic resonance
offers a unique way of characterizing
matter in all sorts of forms
ranging from solid materials
like medicinal pills or catalysts
for the petroleum industry
to solutions of proteins,
suspensions of living cells
or indeed entire organisms,
such as living laboratory animals
and of course human beings.
MRI or magnetic resonance imaging
as it should be called
is perhaps the best known
to the general public
of the many, many applications
of magnetic resonance.
MOOC sounds like book,
indeed the two words rhyme,
and surely that's not by accident.
Now in our particular MOOC,
we have decided to base it
on a physical book.
The book that we recommend is a short
introductory text by Peter Hore,
lecturer at Oxford University.
I have used this book for third and fourth
year students at the École Polytechnique
Fédérale de Lausanne.
And for first- and second-year students
at the École Normale Supérieure in Paris.
Also at the Université Pierre
et Marie Curie.
We vividly recommend to all students
who wish to participate in this MOOC
that they actually buy Peter's book,
preferably from an old-fashioned bookstore
It should cost you no more than 20 euros
or equivalent in your currency.
It is not our intention to read
the full text of Peter Hore's book
sentence by sentence, for that
would be immensely boring.
To avoid this temptation we shall focus
on the figures drawn
from Peter Hore's book
and discuss them one by one.
We shall use these pictures as a means
to support our explanations.
We are aware of course that most students
who start a MOOC do not necessarily
continue to the bitter end.
In France, the percentage of dropouts
is estimated to be 80 percent;
in the United States, perhaps as high
as 90 percent,
but how many students actually read
an old-fashioned book all the way
from cover to cover?
Probably not very many.
In French a MOOC is also called a CLOM,
a cours en ligne ouvert et massif.
But the word CLOM reminds me mostly
of clumsy, so we shall stick to English
most of the time.
Let's now get on with it.
So this MOOC,
basic steps in magnetic resonance,
will be largely based on this
little book here that Peter Hore
wrote some years ago
and published at Oxford University Press
in a particular series
called Oxford Chemistry Primers.
In fact, there are many issues;
this one is number 32,
and you can find that
from your local bookshop.
Don't forget to tell them that
there is a new edition that will
come out in 2015.
The lectures that I will be giving here
are actually based on the galley proofs
of the book that has not yet appeared,
so those of you who listen to this
will listen to a book
that does not yet exist.
As you can see from the table of contents,
the introduction starts talking about
nuclear magnetism, which is a property
of all nuclei that is essential,
otherwise NMR would be impossible.
Then moves to the chemical shifts,
and it turns out that chemical shifts
are due to the fact that the nuclei
are partly shielded from their environment
by the cloud of electrons that is moving
about the nuclei.
We shall speak about spin-spin couplings,
which as you may know are responsible
for multiplets in NMR spectra.
And, perhaps, the most important chapter
in this book, because it's also referred
to on the title page is Chemical Exchange.
And it turns out that we can discuss
two side exchange in some detail
and follow this up with a great wealth
of very interesting examples.
Chapter five is dedicated to relaxation.
Relaxation is essentially the return
of the nuclear magnetization
to its equilibrium position.
And the speed or rate at which the spins
return to their equilibrium varies
a great deal from one case to another.
And it turns out that in most cases
this is due to rotational motion
in liquids known as rotational diffusion
of molecules.
It is that motion that drives relaxation.
And one of the important manifestations
is the nuclear overhauser effect
because that will allow us to determine
structures of macromolecules,
such as proteins
and nucleic acids in solution.
But there are many other examples
of relaxation studies that allow you
either to determine structures
or to characterize internal dynamics
of molecules.
And the final chapter
is about NMR experiments,
actually this is closest
to my own specialty.
Apart from the principles of experiments
there's a long discussion
of the vector model,
which is a way of representing the nuclear
magnetization and see how this
magnetization evolves when we perturb it
and apply various perturbations
and excitations.
There's a chapter on
the measurement of relaxation times,
on the enhancement of insensitive nuclei
by polarization transfer,
on two-dimensional NMR
and even a brief chapter
on three-dimensional NMR.
So we shall proceed from here.
Now as you can see from the preface
of the first edition,
this book was written some years ago,
and in fact, when I was using it
for my lectures at times I thought,
"well, it's about time to update it."
And, indeed, Peter Hore has taken
an independent decision to do that.
But before we go to the update,
let me briefly see in this introduction,
Keith McLaughlin was a lecturer
at Oxford University and indeed
the PhD advisor of Peter Hore.
Now this is relevant because Keith
is a specialist of EPR spectroscopy,
electron paramagnetic resonance,
which is in a way the electron counterpart
of nuclear magnetic resonance.
And, indeed, Peter Hore still belongs
to a school of thought
that is more concerned with electrons
than with nuclei,
and as a result,
when he started writing
his book on nuclear magnetic resonance,
he really had to do a lot of homework
to understand how that works.
And it's precisely because of that effort
that this book is so interesting.
Then there is a second
name here, Rob Kaptein.
Rob Kaptein is the biomolecular
NMR spectroscopist
at the University of Utrecht,
and Peter Hore spent some time with him
as a postdoc and this is where
he got his strong impact,
strong impression of biomolecular
applications of modern NMR.
And the third person he mentions here
is Ray Freeman, also a lecturer
at Oxford University in those days,
now emeritus professor at Cambridge.
And Ray Freeman not only lectured
to Peter Hore but also to myself
since he was my PhD advisor.
Now the second edition, you will read,
as you might expect, a revision.
Actually it's quite thorough.
There are not just errors and inaccuracies
that have been removed,
but there have been entire chapters
rewritten extensively.
You will notice that Peter Hore
has consulted some of his
most faithful readers,
one of them is myself.
But to be honest, I have only
pointed out a few errors in sines
and things like that,
whereas the person who really carries
the important name is Gareth Morris,
now a professor in Manchester,
who many years ago by the way
was a fellow PhD student
in the laboratory of Ray Freeman
at Oxford and he clearly put a lot
of effort into rewriting and suggesting
to Peter Hore how to improve this book.
Now the book that we recommend
for this MOOC is of course not
the only good book on magnetic resonance.
First of all, there is a second volume
which is sometimes called
NMR, Peter Hore, Volume Two,
but in fact is called The Toolkit,
and it has three authors:
Peter Hore, the same, Jeremy Jones
and Steve Wimperis.
Jones is a physicist.
Wimperis is now a professor in Glascow,
and he is an expert of liquid
and solid state NMR.
This book The Toolkit
is number 92 in the Oxford Chemistry
Primers series.
It also has a second edition that should
come out in 2015,
and maybe at one point I will be doing
another MOOC based on that book
because I've also used that book
extensively for undrgraduate
and graduate lecures.
But these books are very thin.
They're only something like 100 pages.
There are more substantial works
and this is a beautiful book,
Understanding NMR Spectroscopy
written by James Keeler,
another of Ray Freeman's former students,
now a lecturer at Cambridge University.
This contains more basic experimental
methods for one-dimensional
and two-dimensional NMR
and importantly contains
extensive exercises.
This book has recently been translated
in 2015 by Pascal Miéville
from English into French
and I can vividly recommend this book.
This is undoubtedly the best,
in fact the only modern book
on NMR in French.
There are other famous books.
This one, for example,
is called Spin Choreography,
beautiful title because Ray Freeman
used to enjoy inventing ways
to make the spins dance together
or not together,
and he invented this expression
of basic steps in high resolution NMR
and the basic steps,
as you may have noticed,
are also in the title of our MOOC,
and, indeed, Ray Freeman has given me
permission for using
those basic steps again.
This is, again, a very substantial book,
written by Malcolm Levitt,
perhaps one of the most creative
NMR spectroscopists in the world right now
He wrote this book on liquid state NMR,
although at that time, his real emphasis
in the laboratory was on solid state NMR.
So we again have a case where
someone steps somewhat outside
of his preferred field of interest
and writes a very beautiful textbook.
Let's come now back
to Peter Hore's first volume.
So this is simply called
Nuclear Magnetic Resonance,
and as you can see, the key parts of it
are angular momentum, nuclear magnetism
and NMR spectroscopy.
If we consider some nuclei which have
a spin quantum number equal to ½,
and the best examples are
an isolated proton, an isolated carbon 13
an isolated nitrogen 15,
an isolated phosphorous 31
and many others.
Well, then there will be
just two quantum levels
that are accessible.
The spins are either parallel
with the magnetic fields.
In fact, there will be many spins
that are parallel.
But there will also be a few spins
that are anti-parallel.
The spins in the ground state
are often referred to as
spins in state alpha,
or more properly they have
a magnetic quantum number
equal to m = + ½
The spins in the excited state
are said to be in the beta state
or more properly with a magnetic
quantum number - ½.
In most areas of spectroscopy,
such for example invisible spectroscopy
or UV spectroscopy,
the splitting ΔE is so large,
that all molecules are in the ground state
In NMR that is not so
because the splitting is very small
compared to the thermal noise
in the environment.
Therefore we have to worry about
the populations in the upper state
and more specifically,
about the difference between
the upper and lower states
because if the populations
were equal we would speak of
a demagnetized system
or a saturated system,
and it would be impossible to observe NMR.
The observation of NMR is conditional to
there being a difference in populations.
Now it turns out that the populations--
the ratio of the populations--
between the beta and alpha states
is determined by Boltzmann's law.
So this is an exponential function,
ΔE is the difference in energy,
kB is Boltzmann's constant,
and T is the temperature,
more specifically the temperature
of the spins which can be
distinct from the temperature
of the sample.
Now because the argument
is a very small number,
we can replace this exponential function
by a simple ΔE over kB of T,
and we can neglect higher terms
such as this one here,
which would read ΔE square
divided by kBT square.
So we can neglect this term.
This letter simplification
actually has a name.
It is known as high temperature
approximation.
Now this deserves to be set
in quotation marks
because it turns out to be okay.
This approximation is okay
as long as the temperature
is about, say, one kelvin,
so that's very, very cold indeed.
But technically speaking,
the approximation can be made
because the denominator here
is much larger than the numerator,
and that is because the temperature
is technically speaking high.
Now if that is the case,
then we can express the polarization,
so this quantity here, this p
if nothing else is the polarization.
That is at least the way we use
this word in our laboratory,
not universally recognized by everybody.
This polarization then is defined
as the difference in populations
between nɑ and - nβ
--so you know that the ground state
has normally higher population
than the excited state,
hence this definition--
divided by the sum of the populations,
which is usually one
if we define the "n"s to be
simple fractions.
And because of this high temperature
approximation, the polarization
is directly proportional to the difference
in energies and divided by kB times T,
that is to say Boltzmann's constant
not divide by the actual spin temperature.
So nuclei at the heart
of atoms and molecules have a mass.
They have a positive charge,
as you know.
They also have a rather
peculiar property called spin.
Initially, in the early days,
that is to say in the 1920s
when spin was first discovered,
it was believed that it was sufficient
for a nucleus to rotate about an axis
and a charged particle about an axis
if it rotates will generate
a magnetization,
and that was believed to be the origin
of nuclear magnetization.
It turns out to be
more complicated than that.
For example, it is not sufficient
to have a large charge in order to
have a high magnetization.
On the contrary, it's the smaller nuclei,
such as tritium and protons that have
high magnetic moments,
whereas heavy nuclei have small
magnetic moments.
Also, many nuclei have charge,
such as carbon 12 or oxygen 16
but have no spin at all.
So the relationship is not so simple,
and it turns out that we really should
think of spin as an independent
property in addition to mass and charge.
So spins come in different forms,
but many of the most popular ones,
from our point of view have a spin quantum
number, which we call I,
equal to ½.
This is the case for protons
and for carbon 13 and for many others.
And it turns out that if that is the case,
their magnetic quantum numbers
can only have two values,
namely m = + ½
or m = - ½.
And in a magnetic field,
if the sample is immersed
in a magnetic field, there is a splitting
between these two levels
called the Zeeman splitting.
And this Zeeman splitting
as it turns out is proprtional
to the magnetic field that we apply.
So if horizontally we draw B zero,
does the intensity of the external
magnetic field, the static magnetic field.
If this B zero were nil,
than the two levels would be
exactly degenerate and as the B zero
increases, the difference in energy
also increases.
It turns out that the slope here
is determined by a parameter called gamma.
The gyromagnetic ratio that we shall
speak about further,
which is a property that is distinct
for protons, carbons and all the others.
Now, the test turned out very early on
that there was some remarkable
observations.
This one is interesting from my
point of view.
Arnold, Dharmatti and Packard
were all working with Felix Bloch
when Felix Bloch was appointed the first
director general of CERN in Geneva.
He didn't last very long
because he did not like administration
and decided to return to his professorship
at Stanford Universty.
And this paper was actually
written at Stanford,
but it's a very important paper,
and also it was written in the year
that I was born.
So what you see here is actually
a proton spectrum of ethanol.
Now ethanol is a very popular molecule
in Lausanne and the environment
because this is a wine-growing area,
and therefore, it's not surprising
that they looked
at the spectrum of ethanol.
And what do we see?
Well, we see distinct resonances
for the hydroxy proton,
for the CH2 protons and the CH3 protons,
and they're in fact displaced
because they have different
chemical shifts.
Also as you can see,
the areas are different.
In fact, the areas under these three peaks
are roughly one to two to three
and allow one to decide
that there is only one of these protons,
two of this and three
of the methyl protons.
So that's a very important discovery.
You note that these lines
are rather broad,
and that is because scaler couplings
could not yet be resolved
in those days.
So this concludes Part One
of this chapter.
Thank-you for your attention.