♫ (lighthearted music) ♫
Magnetic resonance is
familiar to most of us.
In fact, many of us have
experienced an MRI scan
or at least know someone who has.
Magnetic resonance imaging,
as it is known officially
allows us not only to view
bones and tendons,
but also soft tissues,
nerve bundles, and tumors.
Magnetic resonance is not only
good for medical diagnosis,
there are many, many applications
to physics, chemistry and biology
that allow us to get a better
understanding of the world around us.
My name is Geoffrey Bodenhausen.
I'm a professor of chemistry and teach
nuclear magnetic resonance here
at the Ecole Polytechnique
in Lausanne in Switzerland,
and also at the Ecole Normale
Superieure in Paris, in France.
Within the broad field of magnetic
resonance, I have many interests
ranging from solids to liquids,
including new methods
for drug screening and many
other applications.
At both EPFL and ENS,
I have the pleasure
of leading two lively research groups.
This MOOC is based upon the second
edition of Nuclear Magnetic Resonance,
a little book written by
Peter Hore at Oxford University.
In the video lectures, I will be
covering the same range of subjects
as Peter has in his book.
And I will be following the same
structure, divided into six chapters.
I strongly recommend that you
get a copy of Peter Hore's book,
as it goes into much greater detail
than I'm able to do in this MOOC.
In addition to the subjects
covered in the book,
this MOOC also contains
a few extra lectures
that will be presented
by Sami Jannin.
These cover some cutting-edge,
state-of-the-art applications
of magnetic resonance.
Throughout the course, we will
be covering subjects like
chemical shifts, scalar couplings,
dipolar couplings, chemical reactions,
and the return of the
magnetization to its equilibrium,
a process that we call relaxation.
And also, of course, methods
for recording signals,
including Fourier
transforms and the like.
The main objective of this course
is to give you a basic understanding
of how magnetic resonance
actually works.
This information will be
helpful for a range of fields
from physics and chemistry,
to neurosciences.
To supplement the video
lectures, we will include
some downloadable information,
and also interactive exercises
so that you can test
yourself along the way.
I look forward to receiving
you all for this course
on Basic Steps in Magnetic Resonance.