This week we are in Mauritania.
Welcome to all the participants
from Nouakchott!
In our video today,
we'll talk about globalisation and cities
and about the impact
of globalisation on urban planning.
In today's world,
some cities have entered
a global competition to attract
as much influx as they can:
influx of people,
influx of goods or influx of capital.
This is what makes a city
truly global or not.
Which means we are going to measure
a certain number of indicators,
which may be indicators of airport traffic,
of capital flows, most of the time,
and, increasingly,
social indicators telling about
the quality of living are used.
In this international competition
to be a global city
strategies are about the same everywhere.
And this is what we're going to look at
in the following slides.
When it comes to globalisation,
there are competing theories.
Let's have a look at the most common one,
and the one that states
that globalisation is inevitable.
The inevitable globalisation
benefits everybody
through the trickle-down effect
from the richer to the poorer.
The globalisation of the economy
and of political interactions
implies the end of Nation-States.
It brings about a new political deal,
a new set of interactions,
not among nations,
but among cities and companies.
What impact does it have on planning?
Which is what we are interested in.
First, we may say that
city leaders
now want a global city.
Everyone tries to be a global city.
This implies a concentration of powers
and a new approach
based on marketing.
Cities become commodities
that are advertised and sold,
which requires an extremely strong power,
far from a participatory democracy.
We'll come back to all that.
But we do notice that it is the wish
of most city leaders
and that implementing this wish
requires power to be placed back
at the centre
and decision-making
to take place at the centre
whereas over the past few years
the tendency was to try to decentralize
and involve as many users as possible.
Which means, of course,
that the planning scheme
changes tack completely,
with radically different priorities.
Planning is different whether the aim
is a global city or a « classic » city.
One main aspect is the focus
on the richest.
The priority is more on high-end housing,
extremely expensive leisure
aimed at the uppermost classes.
Which means cities look for
maximization of profits
in such a global economy.
Each city is trying to position itself
within an idea of global competition.
Each tries to position itself
as far as the economy is concerned,
and to attract as many people as possible.
And companies are much sought-after.
There are several ways to attract companies.
One way is to try to put on the market
land that is fit for building.
The basic infrastructure, the land itself,
is made ready
so that we can say to such or such company
that would like to come
that we are ready, we have land available
and it's ready to be used.
Another way to attract companies
are projects that give a positive image
of the city.
These can be long-term projects,
or they can be events.
Think of World Cups,
Olympics Games, especially,
Summer or Winter Olympics,
that are associated strictly to a city.
Through these events or large projects,
the idea is to give or change the image
to give a positive image,
and especially a dynamic image,
to attract as many companies as possible.
Another way to attract companies
are fiscal incentives.
One idea is to lower taxes to make it
economically attractive
for such or such company
to settle in a city.
Another possibility is for the city
to offer a very high level of services.
It means everything is provided:
transportation, water supply,
power supply,
all of which is working well,
all of which is available to companies
wishing to settle here.
Yet another strategy
is to go for luxury housing.
This is betting, as I mentioned earlier,
on the uppermost social classes.
To do this, we put on the market
a certain number of properties
belonging to the type of housing
these categories appreciate.
Finally, another strategy
to attract companies is leisure.
The idea is to put on the market
a certain number of types of activities
that these classes, the elite,
like to practice.
Putting these activities on the market
and making them available
may attract people.
Of course, it's never a single strategy
that is implemented,
but it's a combination
of several strategies
that makes it possible
to position oneself
on the global market.
Here are the rankings.
This first one I have already
shown in a previous video.
We'll just gloss over them
to see that there are a few
Global Power City Index, and many more.
If we want to have a look,
just for the sake of it,
we see there are always London, New York
and Tokyo leading the ranking.
Then, usually, follow Paris and Hong Kong.
Depending on the ranking,
Paris and Hong Kong are higher or lower,
compared to New York and London.
Another one: Foreign Policy.
And the last one, which ranks the cities
as Alpha ++, Alpha +, Alpha +, Béta, Gamma
regarding a certain number of criteria
that are often economic ones
but may also be socio-economic criteria.
This is how they rank the cities.
So there is a major interest for cities
to feature in these rankings,
and to rank as high as possible.
As a comparison,
the exact same thing is being done
with universities today,
for which there are several types of rankings
to rank the best universities in the world.
Here is the image that captures
this global city: inside Dubai airport.
Dubai has concentrated its strategy
on welcoming influx of tourists,
and on welcoming influx of capitals.
This image sums up, probably,
how Dubai positioned itself
regarding globalisation.
And what about Africa,
will you ask.
In some cities we know very well
we are far from Hong Kong,
New York or London,
but we realise on a day-to-day basis
that more and more projects are trying
to set some cities
into this global city race.
Strictly speaking, if we consider
economic indicators or capital flows,
we'll have cities in South Africa,
probably cities in North Africa,
the few major cities,
but overall, most African cities
do not feature in the rankings
of global cities.
However, little by little,
there are intents,
to change the image of cities
through major prestigious projects,
to move from a chaotic city
to an international city.
The most striking example of this,
at the moment,
is the major project in Tchad
of the World Trade Center,
where we imagine an exhibition centre,
a symposium centre,
a ministry, office buildings,
a mall, a major hotel,
all of it next to
the airport of N'Djamena.
It is still just a project for the moment.
But it shows, with these 3D images,
what type of urbanisation
African cities want to undergo today.
This is an example in Tchad.
There is another one in Burkina Faso,
There are in Kenya, including in Nairobi,
a series of projects.
So the idea of the need
for an international architecture
for major economic projects
is now widespread
across all African cities.