In our video today, we will discuss
sustainable development.
Surely this is a broad field,
and we'll address
only a few aspects of it, only those
which will help us understand
more globally urban issues,
and the issues of planning, of course,
for this is our key topic.
In theory, there are three spheres:
the economic sphere, the social sphere,
and the environmental sphere.
These three spheres are independent,
the economy generally preceding
the social or the environmental,
for while the link between social
and environment exists,
it is much weaker than that between
the economy and the environment.
The basic pattern, these three
spheres, autonomous,
with links to one another.
The diagram of sustainable development
is one which utilizes
these same three spheres,
yet they overlap
and ultimately it is at their
intersections where we find
the questions of sustainability.
So in order to be sustainable,
we must take into account
economic, social and
environmental questions,
and their relation to one another,
paying close attention
that one does not take
precedence over the other.
When we discuss sustainable development,
or sustainable urban development,
there are two basic theories.
The first says that sustainable
development is impossible,
that the term is an oxymoron,
which is to say that the two terms
have opposite meanings.
Or there is a conflict between
development and the environment.
We cannot have, at the same time,
economic development
and environmental development,
or rather one cannot
preserve environmental resources,
if one is developing the economy.
This is the first theory, by those
who begin with the questions
of reduced or lowered
energy consumption.
The second theory says
exactly the opposite.
It says that sustainable
development is possible,
this mainly because of technology,
and the efficiencies it provides,
in other words we can use
technology to increase yield,
and in doing so, use less energy,
or use it more efficiently.
This is the second theory,
by those who are
positive about technology
and sustainable development.
As for these two theories, we
won't choose one or the other,
but will examine for ourselves
a certain number of criteria
which, we believe, will lead us
towards a sustainable city,
or in any case a sustainable
urban development.
First, though, if one considers the work
of Newman and Kenworthy from 1999,
they present the following hypothesis,
which is not really one,
for while they present and prove
that this consumer curve exists,
and that the annual fuel consumption,
per person, is directly linked to,
or has a direct relationship
to urban density.
The denser my city, the less fuel
I will use, as seen in Asian cities.
And the less dense the city,
the greater the fuel utilized.
This is the model of the American city.
We see this here, American cities,
and here, Asian cities,
and between the two there
we have the European city.
Another example offered by Benoît Lefèvre,
based on the work of the same authors,
Newman and Kenworthy,
those of Atlanta and Barcelona.
Similar populations, urban areas
which are calculated in
kilometers in Barcelona,
and hundreds or thousands of
square kilometers in Atlanta,
We see a very different consumption,
which proves that the denser the city,
with the same number of inhabitants,
the less fuel consumption or,
more globally, energy or CO2.
It depends which indicator is used,
but they are all linked to one another.
So, what does sustainability
mean to us?
It's from this point of view where
I would say that we are situated
neither with the first theory which doesn't
want sustainable development to exist,
nor in the second, where we think
that everything's fine,
it is somewhere in between
the two, since sustainability,
when one speaks of urbanization, is still
a reduction in energy consumption.
We've just seen the curve,
where density allows
this reduction in energy
consumption,
particularly in the preservation
of natural resources.
This is the starting point for a system
of governance which is sustainable,
sustainable over time, while all
rapid political change hinders
long-term project planning.
Its inverse, if the governance
is sustainable,
one can extend projects to
medium or long terms.
Financial impact, the same thing.
If we imagine that
urban sustainability leads to
financial stability in the long term,
and also has a long-term impact
on public health, on life expectancy.
We normally use economic
indicators, but we can also use,
as indicators of urban sustainability,
the life expectancy of its inhabitants,
and imagine that the more
elevated life expectancy,
the more sustainable the city.
This remains to be proved, but
can be an indicator among others.
Finally, sustainability, at any rate
urban sustainability,
is we can call a peaceful society,
or where numerous people live together
with mutual understanding,
without armed conflicts, guerrillas,
gangs, or those groups
who spread trouble and violence,
like we've seen in recent events.
So it is a peaceful society,
which is to say that living together
is commonly embraced by all.
So to reduce energy consumption,
because this is the crux of
the war, without a doubt,
it can be waged on construction,
on the building.
Let's take as an example those
buildings with little insulation,
where air conditioners are to
the max, where energy is consumed.
There exists, in bioclimatic architecture,
and without making any
value judgements,
possibilities to reduce
energy consumption,
most notably the electricity
consumed by air conditioners,
via natural means, of air
circulation, cooling methods,
which have been known
for a very, very long time.
But let's say that addressing the issue
of buildings is a starting point.
In the North it's a question of heating,
in the South it is generally around
the question of air conditioners,
because more often one looks
to cool rooms, rather than heat them.
We can also address mobility,
for as we've just seen there is
a direct dependence between
fuel consumption, on
the one hand, and density.
So finally, in planning
one can go further.
And, finally, the third aspect
relates to individual behavior.
There are some forms of consumption
which are causes of the urban model,
or those due to the architecture
buildings or the building methods used,
But energy consumption depends,
primarily and directly, on
human behavior, on lifestyle.
And it is on this last aspect where
one have the most influence.
There are many other areas were
we might initiate changes
to reduce energy consumption,
but these are the main ones:
human behavior, mobility
and built environment.
The symptomatic example of
what one should not do,
when it comes to energy consumption.
We are in the city of Dubai,
in the middle of summer.
45 degrees in the shade, outside.
On an artificial slope, inside an
enormous commercial center, we are skiing.
As far as energy consumption,
there is surely nothing worse
than skiing in the middle of the desert.
To finish up this very, very quick video
on the two or three aspects
of sustainable urban development.
To summarize, or to conclude
this video we could say that
what we're looking for are planning
methods which ensure long-term effect.
We also are looking for
decision-making structures
which allow this long-term management.
This is why we can take action
at once on these questions of energy,
on urban forms, housing,
human behavior, mobility,
but we must also influence
those government structures
which determine whether
or not to implement
these efforts to lower
energy consumption.
In our future videos on planning,
we will keep this in mind.
How can we, today, reduce
our daily energy bill?
Whether it is the cost of CO2,
or a financial one, a monetary one,
or of liters of fuel, or calories,
whatever indicator we might use,
but the key word is the reduction
of this energy amount, per person,
which one needs to live in a city.