The focus of this video
is climate change.
We will quickly see the link
one can make between
urban form, between urban spatial
systems and climate change.
To begin, we must
remember a few things,
which is that urban planning is not
an autonomous activity,
but is at once dependent on
demographics, economic changes,
political factors, technological progress
and, very recently, it is dependent
on climate change.
This is what we'll see.
Now, what are the types of effect?
There may be an elevation
in temperature.
There may be an increase
in sea level.
One can also have
increased river levels
or an intensification
of rain phenomena.
Finally, an increase in
natural catastrophes:
tsunamis, periods of
flooding or drought.
This chart is interesting because
it shows the types of effect
and finally their relation to
different human activities.
High winds, an increase in high winds
does not have a direct effect
on agriculture or habitat.
On the contrary, in transportation,
if we consider air travel,
there may be a direct impact.
Heavy rainfall may not necessarily
have a direct bearing
on the whole of human activity.
However, without doubt
it does on agriculture.
And in this graph we can see that
ultimately it is agriculture
which is subject to nearly
all these types of effects.
The same with transportation.
There are domains where
these climate changes
will have little effect,
and other domains
where the changes
will be greater.
So, when discussing climate change,
there are two attitudes
on these changes--
Mitigation and Adaptation.
Mitigation seeks to
reduce the effects
and adaptation tries
to adapt to them.
So while on the one hand
I look to reduce rainfall,
and flood frequency by
reducing, for example--
because there is a direct link
to energy consumption--
so I reduce my consumption
and with this I will reduce
the effects of climate change.
On the other hand I say, okay,
I will adapt to these changes,
and provide technological structures
which allow one, finally,
to live with these conditions
of flooding, drought,
of high winds or incessant rainfall.
So, with mitigation
one tries to reduce,
perhaps to begin with
those on compact cities.
With an urban mix, we will favor
public transport, promote walking.
We've seen just now
in this schematic
that there is a
direct link between
urban density and
energy consumption,
so one seeks to reduce
this energy consumption,
and adaptation,
this urban sprawl.
It is this diffused city which,
ultimately, is the model to use
as it favors ground absorption
in the case of rainfall or flooding.
It favors air circulation
in the case of pollution,
at the same time diminishing
the number of pollutants.
Therefore depending on
the strategy one adopts,
to reduce or adapt
to these effects,
the urban forms
will not be the same.
On one hand we have the compact city,
and on the other the diffused one.
Since we're talking about density,
about densification,
in other words attempts
to reduce, or the mitigation,
to reduce the effects
of climate change,
we must first determine
what we will measure.
Are we talking about gas?
Are we talking about CO2?
When we wish to say there is
a density, what is its metric?
What measure is used?
Next is the question of
low- and hyperdensity.
Low density is very energy costly,
while hyperdensity,
in the same way, is also
very, very energy costly.
There is without a doubt
an optimum which lies
between a too-high density
and a too-low density.
And while we speak of density,
we must also speak of
the social question.
What does it mean to live in
an extremely dense city,
in social terms?
When it comes to climate
and humidity levels,
we will have different answers
depending on urban forms.
We know that humidity makes heat
even more difficult to bear,
and that often when we
find ourselves in zones
where natural disasters are more
or less common--flooding, storms--
it is in tropical zones where there
is high heat and high humidity.
So the challenge is to find
a pattern, an urban form
which addresses the issue of
both heat and that of humidity.
First off, in very hot zones
we will try to reduce
the heating effect of
the sun with urban
and architectural elements.
We will try to achieve a
maximum natural ventilation
in the street or in the home.
And in the end, the individual home,
in a hot and humid climate,
can be a solution.
We'll start with the individual villa,
the single home, because it is
increasingly disparaged,
in a certain number of cities
because it makes up
the endless peripheries of
American cities and,
increasingly, European ones,
and is extremely energy
consumptive and on the move,
as an energy equally
and in principal, today,
where the tendency is increasing to
criticize the individual home, the villa.
But, if we return to a hot
and humid climate
we can question it might be
one of its solutions,
or one urban form which
can respond to all its criteria.
Finally, narrow, tall buildings
are another solution,
for, ultimately, the less
the sun's impact,
the more one can
avoid this connection
between humidity and sun.
Let's take a look at high winds.
A compact form will have
the greatest resistance.
Mid-height buildings, since
low-level buildings will not resist
and the higher ones will pose
a certain number of problems,
so the skyscraper is not
very appropriate,
for it will have an
acceleration effect
on the wind between high rises,
and neither is the low individual
home appropriate,
for it has a funneling effect.
High density allows for a reduction
in the effects of wind.
And finally, the effects dependent
on street orientation.
If your street extends
in the principal
direction of the wind,
it will have an
accelerative effect,
whereas if one is perpendicular
to this wind direction,
one will be protected
from violent winds.
We can also see, when
speaking of winds
and most notably their
urban forms,
the urban response will not
always be the same,
and suddenly, if we combine
the effects of heat, humidity,
and violent winds, we will
realize that we have no more
urban form which will allow us
to respond to all this.
Let's look at yet another example.
Flooding, the increase in
sea levels and the urban form.
The ground should be able
to absorb excess water.
We spoke of this just now.
So in the end the more natural
surfaces, the more I am diffused,
the more my urban form can allow
the absorption of excess water.
Let's limit once and
for all paved surfaces,
or asphalt surfaces,
any sealed surface
so that while one speaks,
particularly about flooding,
one can try to take into
account vast territories,
non-urbanized territories
which can be utilized
as reservoirs to act as
temporary buffer zones
so that the water can be stored
upstream from the city,
rather than in its interior.
And at the same time, of course,
the question of flooding
quickly depends on the question
of the morphology
of the site, of the land forms,
flat or sloping,
which clearly have different
responses to flooding.
Pizarro, in 2010,
proposed a matrix,
a matrix where one
will see these diverse responses,
when speaking of high temperatures,
of strong humidity, violent
winds and flooding,
and for each of these effects
one can ask what percentage
of ground cover,
of the distance required
between buildings,
the median height of buildings,
the templates,
the spaces, the topography,
the quality of sunlight.
In sum, a whole series which
I will leave for you to read,
but one can continue like
this, in graphic format,
to have percentages, knowing
the more one has, for example,
a high humidity or strong
winds, the more the
ground cover should be minimal,
by covering I mean asphalt,
a covering which does not
allow the passage of water,
so at all cost this percentage
of ground cover must be reduced.
So there you have a brief description
of some of the effects,
some of the responses
to urban form,
which is to say, when we continue,
that urban form is clearly
dependent on climate, and on context,
and that the response to climate--
and I'm speaking not of
climate change,
but of climate in general---
that the responses
should be different if one is in
a tropical, humid climate,
or a continental dry one.
So for each type of climate
there are different responses,
which makes it so that
for each climate zone
one should have
different planning.
What we will soon see,
is how our planning
should respond
to this context, to this
particular context,
and how it should respond specifically
to the context of climate.
We have lost this idea of an
architecture, a bioclimatic urbanism
decades ago, abandoned in
the name of modernity,
in the name of aseptic air
in commercial centers,
air-conditioned, regulated, but
today we must question
this model, which they try
to place everywhere,
versus a model which will be
contextualized,
with a planning that
will not be made
except in a precise context
with its own specifics.
In the end, while we're speaking of,
and we'll conclude here,
climate change, it is impossible
to view it from a local perspective.
It must be seen from
a global perspective.
And this without a doubt
poses a challenge
to a certain number of types,
democratic and participative steps,
and we must review
our system of governance.
So these climate changes
will not only lead to effects
on the land, but also
at a political level,
where the decision making
can no longer be local,
but most be on a global level,
between nations or even
between continents, on
an absolutely global scale
in order to rapidly respond
to climatic changes.