In our video we're going to talk
about urban environment,
from the perspective
of risks as well as
the issue of environmental deterioration.
To address this, we will talk about
households, neighborhoods, cities,
countryside, from the small scale
to the large scale.
What is the risk when it
comes to households?
The three main problems
they are faced with
are water and sanitation problems,
the issue of air pollution
within houses
and the problem of household waste.
The severity of these problems
may be explained by the generally
unsanitary and dense life environment,
as basic infrastructure is lacking
and authorities are
not very active about these
household environmental risks.
An example here: Nouakchott.
It is the shabby neighborhood of El Mina,
the Kebbe of El Mina after a rainfall.
The risks inherent to
underprivileged neighborhoods are:
the lack of sanitation systems,
natural disasters
(most of the time,
the areas that are built
should not have been built)
and there is the unchecked production
of toxic waste from informal activities.
An example here,
the niais of Dakar where we see
that natural sites are also
dump sites, with waste and garbage,
and the point is that this waste
and garbage create a backfill.
The risk at city level.
There are four major environmental
problems at city level.
Water pollution.
The whole water cycle, we may say:
supply, treatment,
the issue of surface waters
and water tables which are
increasingly polluted.
The management of solid
and industrial waste.
More than half of the waste
is left on-site.
Natural disasters of course:
hurricanes, storms,
earthquakes, the increase in heavy rains,
and industrial accidents and the
storage of industrial waste
as in Abidjan some years ago.
Finally, there is air pollution:
the release or dumping
without any treatment,
of heavy metals or carcinogenic residues.
This is the classic pollution that
can be found in all cities.
But here, there is not treatment
on the production of this pollution.
Finally, the risk
for the surrounding countryside
or the hinterland as we like to call it.
The environmental nuisances
generated by
a city have an impact
on a regional scale.
It implies over exploitation
of natural resources, water,
wood used for construction, fish,
you name it.
An unplanned urban sprawl
of some neighborhoods
on good arable agricultural lands.
Different forms of pollution,
as we have already mentioned.
And here we have an example, in
Nouakchott, of a carcass,
it's a donkey that died and was
left like this lying on the street.
These are sanitary and
environmental problems
which are extremely important and
yet not managed at all.
Another example, in another city,
where we find,
in the very center of the city,
in a little pit used to dump waste.
We have now covered the household,
the neighborhood, the city, the countryside.
Now, let's talk about some cross-cutting
factors of deterioration.
We may want to mention
the lack of awareness
and the weak involvement of civil society,
the relationship with waste
and finally the fact that
this waste management really
belongs to no one.
Or at least, this is what people think.
Legal loopholes and
overlapping institutional jurisdictions.
Obsolete property regulation
which is inadequate
with a rational use of natural resources.
Exclusively sectoral approaches
and implementations
which do not allow to take into
account all aspects.
Weak institutional capacity when it
comes to environmental management.
And finally, failing urban planning,
since it only rarely takes into account
the questions of the environment.
Here we have, in just a few strokes,
a few elements both
about the risks
and the systems
of environmental deterioration
We will have the opportunity
to come back to it later,
but for now we will stop here
as a first introduction
on urban environment issues.