In this video we will examine
the question of
transport and mobility,
once again not in an
exhaustive way,
but just enough to help us
in our urban planning,
to help us to understand
how this works.
When we speak of transport,
we speak of a
transportation system,
and this system is made up of
three elements, which are:
One, the services, the trams,
trains, buses, taxis,
but also the police, who
are part of this service.
Next we have the infrastructures,
the routes, the railways, parking lots,
and one has a network of users,
which are the pedestrians, drivers,
the cyclists, the road-users,
as well as the
mini-bus companies.
This network is made up of
these three elements.
On the question of mobility,
it is above all a necessity.
We need to be able
to go to work,
to go to recreational activities,
to go to the market.
It is above all a necessity,
but it is equally a right.
One has the right to
be able to get around,
its opposite would
make one a prisoner.
What we take of this is, above all,
is this right to mobility.
Even if I exercise this
right only partially,
even if I don't use it at all,
mobility is a right.
To continue, since we will deal
principally with public transport
in this question of
transport and mobility,
a quote from the
mayor of Bogotá,
the ex-mayor of
Bogotá, who said,
"A developed country is not a place
where the poor have cars.
It's where the rich use
public transportation."
We'll use this as a starting point
for our discussion,
Used as a base for our discussion
and of particular interest
is that today,
if we look at the major
trends in Africa,
we'll see that
the principal trend
lies in the increased
number of cars.
So the rate of car ownership
increases, slowly but surely,
in the majority of cities,
and in some very rapidly.
The margin, since
car ownership rates
are very, very low,
at this point,
the margin is still
excessively large.
Along with this increase in cars,
we see a decrease in
public transportation,
in walking and cycling,
in nearly all African cities.
And suddenly, as everywhere,
we find a diminishing
attractiveness of city centers,
because it is difficult
to get to them,
so ultimately it is the
periphery which wins,
the diffuse periphery where one
can fit the most vehicles,
and where the distance from
point A to point B is the longest.
So there you have
the actual trends,
and it is here where we
should begin our plans,
and to try to understand what
the possible means might be
to achieve eventual change.
So let's look at the impact
on the land, for each line,
each route, each space
given over to transport,
whether private or public,
has an impact on the land,
and its effect, for a strip of
3.5 meters in length,
the example we have here,
we'll note it somewhere,
can surpass 2,000 people
if it's in mixed traffic,
or if in suburban railways,
100,000 people.
So we can see that this gap
is excessively large,
and that in the end it will
have a huge influence
on the form of the city,
and a very large impact
on the land,
whether one chooses one mode
of transport or another.
Walking, as we just said,
we see that in certain cities
can reach 70%, while globally
more than 50% of travel
in African cities is on foot.
So what is the reason behind
this downward trend?
Because the city grows outward,
and distances are greater to travel.
The modal split, we'll see later on
that this is the model,
but we can clearly see that it is
the distribution between
the different types of transport,
between the private car, the bike,
walking, public transportation.
And we will find extremely
different situations
when it comes to each city.
In Johannesburg, the role
of the car is huge,
while in Douala or Dar es Salaam,
it is very small.
The role of informal transport
is huge in Accra,
yet in Douala it is very small
when compared to other cities.
So we will see that there is not
one model of the African city,
but that if we use several
examples we'll find that
there are already exceedingly
different modal situations.
There is a direct link
between the morphology
of the city, between
its urban form,
but also between its history,
its trajectory,
or in certain numbers of
choices made or not.
Within the schematic we can see
the number of private vehicles
as a percentage of travel,
as a function of the
gross domestic product,
in dollars, for each
of these cities,
for each country.
And we have here
the American cities based
exclusively on the car,
and then we have
European cities
which are cities based
slightly less on cars
but have the tendency to become
more and more so,
to Americanize themselves
and then we have here
some developing cities
where one has at the same time
modal parts of private vehicles
relatively weak for some,
yet with gross national products
which are very weak.
So the challenge here
is to figure out
if this group will end up
here or there.
So we see a significant margin today,
notably within African cities.
The schematic of Newman and
Kenworthy which we've already seen
shows the annual gas consumption
in relation to urban density.
The more dense my city,
the less gas I consume,
and this gives us some direction
on how it is done.
And, finally, we'll just touch on
the question of modal choice.
The modal choice is that,
for each time you go out,
you'll ask yourself which mode
of transportation you'll use.
Now some don't even ask
themselves; they have a car,
they have the means to have a car
and use it exclusively, all the time,
and others who on the contrary
do ask themselves--
Will I take my bike? Will I walk?
Will I take the bus,
or will I go in my car?
And these modal choices
will depend on
a certain number of criteria,
factors, we might say,
which include
travel time, distance, what
I need to transport, for example,
if I have a large bag
will I walk or take my car?
There will also be physical questions.
Am I in good enough shape
to walk or bike,
or must I take the car?
The cost issue, certainly
not negligible,
will often be considered when
it comes to public transportation,
rarely the cost of the car,
while there will be other
considerations, like parking.
If I take my car, will a
parking spot be available?
Also other questions
tied to security, for example,
I'd like to walk,
but it's dangerous.
It's dangerous because
it is on the highway,
or because there is
a real safety issue.
Thus my modal choice will be
influenced as well by safety issues.
So we've touched briefly on
the question of modal choice.
Some examples, of taxis,
here, in the center of the city.
Mini-buses, which await passengers.
A taxi, a mini-bus;
here we are in Dakar.
The same mini-bus which
awaits clients, still in Dakar.
Or here, in Abidjan, the large buses
which travel longer distances,
whose stops are preplanned
and known in advance.
Taxis, facing difficulties
in the rainy season.
Another type of station,
with buses, this time,
which travel to neighboring cities
or even cross several countries.
So to summarize a bit, we must keep
something very important in mind.
which is that the mode of transport
has a considerable influence
on the place where it is used.
The second thing to
remember is that today,
the role of the car in
African cities is very small.
It is growing, trending upwards
as we've seen,
but there still exists a choice
between on the one hand
a model which will be more
American, or more European,
or without a doubt a third model,
which will be clearly African.
Now that we are aware of
these different aspects,
we will integrate them
in our future planning.
What type of city?
Shall I make a city for the car,
or for the pedestrian?
Or perhaps for
public transportation?
These are the questions
we'll address next.