Welcome back to our MOOC,
Launching New Ventures.
This is Week 3
on entrepreneurial marketing.
And this is a highly important week
because in this week
we are going to discuss
how you are going to win customers
who will ultimately deliver the value
for your firm-creation process.
So, when you think about
entrepreneurial marketing,
it's marketing for new ventures,
and Peter Drucker said
something really nice
that I want to emphasize here.
He said, "The purpose of creating
a business is to create a customer,"
and not a product.
Marketing primarily is about establishing
exchange relationships
with a wide variety of stakeholders.
So that could be in the labor market
where you need to hire people,
or in the capital markets,
where you need to raise money.
So part of your marketing can be oriented
toward these different stakeholders.
Plus, there could be
other stakeholders as well.
But in this MOOC,
in this segment in particular,
we are going to talk about
the output markets.
How you market to your end customers
in order to achieve sales
because this is a vitally important
function in your firm creation.
What is important to understand
is that entrepreneurial marketing
is quite different from normal marketing.
It means marketing at larger firms
because of a number of reasons,
and we have listed a couple
of these reasons on this slide here.
One is, of course, you are a new company.
And as a new company,
you do not have any track record,
people might not trust you,
you don't have any reputation,
people don't know your product,
and you have to establish all
the exchange relationships from scratch.
Right. Plus, there is
also the smallness issue.
If you are a small company,
you may have limited resources.
I mean financial resources,
you don't have that many people,
your skills, you are limited on time,
people don't know you,
you have limited bargaining power,
a limited market power in general.
- So, it's a relatively weak position--
- And that's further complicated actually
by market turbulence and uncertainty,
meaning lots of new entrants
coming into these markets,
and your analysis
might have a short half-life.
The market can change all the time,
and therefore, it is difficult
for a small company to keep
on top of a rapidly changing market.
So we want to give you some intuition
of what this really means.
And if you look at these examples here--
think about the Google Glass.
Or think about the zero-blade technology,
this mobile wind turbine
that can do without having any blades.
Right. There is also a vacuum-cleaner
that doubles as a piece of art
for small apartments,
and a flavor clock that releases different
smells at different times of the day
so you can tell by the sense
of smell what time it is.
So, what do they have in common
if you try to market those?
Right. Essentially, most of these products
are difficult to understand at first.
People often have a reaction:
"What is this?!"
"What's going on with this?
I don't understand..."
It's hard to fully interpret the product
the first time it hits the world.
And if you are facing
these type of consumers,
they don't know which dimensions
are important in their buying decision,
in the evaluation of the product.
You need to educate them.
They don't have any idea of what features
they prefer or don't prefer.
So that complicates the whole
selling process from your side
and the buying process from their side.
We are going to walk you through
a systematic process for understanding
entrepreneurial marketing
and firm success.
And that all starts with the fundamentals
of the entrepreneur's distinctive
capabilities or competencies.
In other words, what is the entrepreneur
really, really particularly good at?
Perhaps better than other people, in fact?
And you probably remember
we discussed this exact topic last week,
we tried to understand what is
your technological competence
and how that could be leveraged
into different market segments.
This week is actually building
on the insights we gained last week.
Particularly in the strategy part
in marketing, you are going to decide
what are your specific target segments,
and how should this particular
target segment perceive you;
i.e., how should your product,
how should your company
be positioned vis-รก-vis that segment.
And that core strategic decision
will then be implemented
through a variety
of marketing approaches, marketing tools
like your distribution approach,
your pricing, your leaflets,
your promotional activities, etc., etc.
This whole scheme
will then give you a very systematic,
orchestrated approach to marketing
and that will help you to have a coherent,
clear message towards your customers.
So let's look at the set-up
of this week's MOOC in particular.
We'll start with developing
a strategic marketing plan.
Exactly. And that is then the basis for--
an ingredient of that, I should say,
is understanding your customers,
understanding your competitors,
because that type of knowledge is vital
to developing a good marketing plan.
And then, we'll talk about
the customer value proposition,
in other words, what are you giving
to your customers, users, payers, etc.?
What value are you bringing to them?
We will then move into
the marketing implementation part
where we'll talk about the marketing mix,
and one particularly exciting element
in the marketing mix,
which is the guerrilla marketing approach
that you might want to adopt.
It's a very creative approach
to marketing,
it's a less resource-intensive approach
to marketing, which is vital
for young companies
which are typically cash-trapped.
Right. And then,
we'll talk about crowdfunding.
This won't be the only time
we discuss crowdfunding,
but in this particular module,
what we are going to do is discuss
the marketing aspects of crowdfunding,
and also help you prepare
for a crowdfunding platform
that you'll be able to participate in
later on in the course.
And we'll conclude by talking about
market penetration,
that means you're going to want
to see your products
being adopted by the market
and generating
the type of growth that you aspire to
in your venture creation process.
So, we look forward to walking you through
all these exciting elements this week.
Thank you very much.
- Stay tuned.
- Stay tuned!