Welcome back!
In this segment we are going
to talk about understanding
your customers and your competition.
Two key issues that are of importance for
developing your marketing plan,
and for developing your accompanying
marketing agenda.
But, before we delve into this topic,
I want you to step back and think about it
from the customers perspective
and not the entrepreneur perspective.
Think about your daily purchasing
decisions for a minute.
You are in an environment where you get
constantly bombarded with new information
where you have lots of products
to choose from.
And sophisticated buyers actually
check out online
where the cheapest product is available.
So, what you're dealing with,
as an entrepreneur,
are these types of customers
that are much more educated
than they used to be.
They have multiple options;
they can buy off-line,
they can by online often times.
So, in that sense, you are dealing
with a subject out there that is,
first, of vital importance to your
firm's success.
But, on the other hand, also not
so easily graspable like it used to be.
So in that sense, market research
and competitor analysis
are of vital importance.
Market Research should give you the
insights on a particular customer
and Competitor Analysis should give you
the insights on what the competition
is doing to steal away
that customer from you.
They have attractive offerings, so you
need to beat the competition away.
So, ultimately, what we are trying to do
in this segment is to give you
an understanding of which kind of
information you're going to need
to understand your customers solidly,
in a very thorough way,
and which type of information you're going
to need to understand your competition,
and how the competition tries
to steal that customer from you.
So, lets start with looking
at your customers.
From the entrepreneurial marketing
perspective,
customer analysis is important
for two main issues.
First, for making sales.
Meaning, you have to understand your
customers in order to fulfill their needs.
In order to convince them
to purchase your product.
But beyond that-- and that is listed on
the second bullet point here,
the question arises, "What do your
customers expect from your venture?"
So, understanding customer needs also
has a venture dimension in the sense that
the customers will be in touch
with your venture.
And the customers will,
for instance, need warranty.
They need to have a safe person.
They like to have contact
with your venture.
And all of that, actually, shapes the
impression and their buying behavior.
On the other hand, you have an important
dimension towards understanding customers.
That is, customers should
create value for your venture.
That's beyond making sales,
that's value creation.
And, in order to understand how customers
create value for your venture,
there are a couple of questions to ask
and two of the most important ones
are listed here: "How much value do your
customers create for your firm?"
And "How should I invest my limited
resources"- including your attention,
towards different types of customers
so that I can actually
create value for my venture?"
So, why is it so important that you
understand the specific needs
of your target customers?
First, of course, you want to deliver
value to them.
So in order to understand what type of
functionality they need in a product
you need to understand their needs.
Second, you want to create
an exceptional customer experience.
It's not only an experience where the
customer purchases the good,
but beyond that, he or she should feel
excited buying your product
and enjoying using it,
because the greater the experience,
the more word of mouth they will create.
And finally, of course, you want
to beat your competition.
And by better understanding the needs of
your target customers,
you will have a better angle towards
that front that I've mentioned as well.
In order to understand your customers,
you can engage in a number of activities.
I'll provide you with some
easy guidelines, a three step process
that will help you ask the right questions
and note the right elements
in this process.
The first step would be interacting
with your customers
and trying on your customers' perspective.
It's a vital step; it's a step where you
dive deeply into your customer
and try to understand, "How does
your customer look at your product?
How does she compare between
alternative offerings?
How often will she purchase
your product service?"
And you should also look at your
customers' point of contact
with your future business.
Do they shop online?
Do they shop offline? Etc.
For the second step, you can then try
to track the customers journey.
And this is a bit challenging
with a new firm
because many of the processes that
the customers will experience
are not yet fully defined.
Some of them might exist,
some might not exist.
But note especially when their
experience is breaking down,
where the experience is strongest
and note also where improvements
can be made to that experience.
And, if you're in the venture design phase
still, you can say;
"Okay, what kind of cliffs would
I experience as a customer
when I would engage with my company?"
And, in asking that type of question
you can have very deep insights
at this venture design phase
about how to structure
your processes and relationships,
and your point of contact
with your customers.
The third point would then be to say,
"Okay, I've gathered this
type of information.
I've gathered the information from the
the interviews I did with my customers.
Now I can try to understand patterns in
the behavior of your target customers."
So, for instance, you can build
a database of all your interactions
with your customers.
All the information you collected
so that you have a good over view of
what you have learned.
And then engage in some meta-learning.
You can look at patterns in their
behavior and consider whether
you have segmented the market
in the best way possible.
And look out for ways to better
meet their needs.
Overall this is a learning process,
you are engaging
in a entrepreneurial venture
that is often times launching inovation
which then means, well, of course
I don't know everything in advance.
And, customer learning is one of
the most important learning processes
that you will face in your
venture creation process,
so take this very seriously.
In addition, you want to understand how
much value your customers are
going to provide to your firm.
You can analyze your customers
based on potential sales,
and thus understand how much
revenue you may get
from a given group of customers
and this type of analysis will help
you understand two things:
first, which customers are worth
your efforts and expenses.
Not all customers are worth while
being catered to.
And this actually provides you with a
second point here:
which customers could be better served
with lower cost approaches, for instance.
So, for instance, with customers that are
providing less value to your company,
you could say I engage with those
customers only in digital ways,
with emails, with website interfaces
and I could visit them less often,
less frequently
if you're more in a business that is
relying on direct customer contact.
Give them fewer phone calls
to remind them of a purchasing decision.
So on the one hand, you are trying
to understand your customers
in order to be able
to better cater to them.
And on the other hand, you're trying
to understand your customers
in order to create value for your venture,
meaning that, you're trying
to understand which type of customers
that are actually
producing that value for you
and which types of customers don't.
The second key element that I want
to discuss with you
in this segment is your competition.
And there are two big questions that
are related to this larger topic.
Number one, who are your competitors
in the first place?
This is often times not so evident,
especially if you are trying
to commercialize innovation.
And second, what do you need to know
about your competitors?
Once you know who they are, what
information do you need to gather
about them to get a solid
and well rounded understanding
of their activities and
their potential future activities.
So, the intended outcomes of this type
of analysis are straight forward,
I would say.
It's like first trying to understand
what these other firms offer,
so that you can make your product
services and marketing stand out.
It will allow you to get an understanding
of the competitors' pricing,
so set your prices competitively.
It will help you to draw up and develop
marketing campaigns that might be
more appealing to your customers
than those of the competition.
It helps you to access any threats
posed by new entrace to your market
and current competitors.
And, ultimately, also helps you to
be realistic about how succesful
you can be with your venture.
How much of the market space
is already taken up by the competition?
"Where do I have to fight hard
to overcome the competition?"
And this gives you a better understanding
also about your future growth potential.
So a number of key benefits that are
through competitor analysis
were rendered to your venture.
Your analysis of the competition should
include your main competitors,
and particularly, their strengths and
weaknesses.
So, look at their offering,
their prices, their distribution channels,
their reputations, their marketing methods,
their brand and design values,
who actually owns the company,
and what kind of person these people are.
Their strategies to build
customer loyalty,
whether they innovate products
and processes.
Their staff count and the caliber of
staff they can attract.
Their annual report
if they are a public company,
and their media activities.
Do they have a website, and would they
engage in local newspaper advertising,
radio and television, etc?
And the more information you have about
your competitors, the better it is!
Because it provides you with a more solid
ground for making your decisions about
where your firm is going to compete,
and how your firm is going to compete
against these firms.
So, often times entrepreneurs
come to me and say,
"Well, we do not have competition,
we have such an innovative product
that does not yet exist
in the market place."
And I have to say; "Well, in that case
you haven't done your job
thoroughly enough."
Try, really, to understand
your customers and your competition.
Because, even if it's an innovation, there
are other substitute products out there
that are catering to similar functional
needs of your customers.
There are alternative products,
and work-arounds that might exist.
So, they're saying, "Well, we do not have
any competition"
often times is only an indicator
that you haven't done
your homework well enough.
So, take this competitor analysis
quite strongly and to the heart.
And try to understand, "Well, this is an
opportunity for me to learn more
about my company and my market place."
What is particularly interesting is also
looking into your competitors' customer.
Who they are, how they have
segmented the market,
and what they sell to each segment.
Your competitors' strengths and weaknesses
as perceived by their customers.
Whether there are any long standing
customers that they are catering to
in which you might not be able
to win over immediately to your company.
Unless you have a very, very compelling
value proposition.
And if they have had an influx of
customers
recently because this is an important
indicator of whether,
they have something very
attractive to offer to the market.
So, you can combined this on the one hand
with your customer interviews.
You can understand very well
by talking to customers.
How they think and what they take into
consideration.
But you can also look at market reports
and other types of reports
to help make you understand
"Well, how are the trends
in my market evolving?" and
"Is my competition maybe
offering something
that's highly appealing to customers?"
This is vital information for the shaping
of your product
and for your marketing campaigns.
It ultimately comes down
to three main insights.
First, what can you learn from your
competition and do better?
Second, what is my competition not doing
as well I am doing it? Or plan to do it?
And, what are they doing
equally as well then you are?
So, if you look at all three elements--
these elements provide you with point on
where to improve, also where you can
potentially beat your competition.
Especially in the design phase,
you can say,
"Well, I designed my company in a way,
and my product in a way
that I attack my competitor
from their weakest angle."
But keep in mind the customer still needs
to value the dimension
of what you're trying to beat here.
And, what are you doing equally well as
your competition, you can say,
"Can I improve on that experience and make
it a differentiator of my business?"
So that the customers will actually say,
"This is a great point that your company
is offering that I've never seen at any
other competing firm.
So I am going to choose your product."
So in sum, what we have discussed in this
segment is actually--
it's pretty straight forward,
but it actually means a lot of hard work.
But I urge you to do this work,
engage in this type of work
because it presents you with
the nuts and bolts of firm creation.
Often times people say, "Well, your
business plan doesn't master
and doesn't survive
the first customer contact."
But only if you've never spoken
with a customer before.
You have to understand what your customers
want and who your competitors are
in order to develop a compelling
business plan and business concept.
And this is exactly where
this part comes in.
Market research and competitor analysis.
So, we've looked in this segment at
a couple of key steps
that you can engage in order
to understand your customers very well
in order to understand
your competitors very well.
Try them out, and I am curious
to find out what you've learned.
Good luck!