Welcome back to Week 3
and the segment
Guerrilla Marketing
and the Marketing Mix.
Today's session
is essentially about implementation
of your marketing strategies,
and that's also why I'm wearing my vest,
in order to signal to you
that this is a hands-on subject
that we're going to be talking about today
and that it actually should be aligned
with the strategy that you have developed
in the previous sessions,
meaning the segmentation of your market
and how your customers
should perceive your product,
either positioning of your product,
vis-à-vis the competition
towards your customers.
These two decisions
on the strategic level
really form the backbone
of what we will be discussing today
because they should give you
the guidelines, the general thrust
for what you will be implementing
in the marketing mix.
There are more creative elements
that you can also use
in entrepreneurial marketing.
We label them guerilla marketing,
like a guerrilla fighter
who's fighting with little resources
and tries to achieve maximum output
or maximum effects.
That's actually the situation
that an entrepreneur finds himself in.
What we will be discussing
is also some tools and tricks
that you can apply
in order to have a very efficient type
of marketing in new venture creation.
I have some very interesting,
nice examples to share with you.
When we think about the marketing mix,
conventionally, there were four P's:
price, product, promotion, place.
This has been enlarged to seven P's
in more recent editions of this concept.
Let me briefly walk you through
an overview here
and then focus on each
and every one of them.
The marketing mix
is really concerned with
the implementations suggested.
It's about how your product
will be designed.
It's about the pricing
of your product.
It's about the place,
I mean the distribution of your product.
It's about the promotional elements
that accompany your marketing effort.
It's about the process.
It's about the people.
It's also about the physical environment,
which is oftentimes referring to
the store environment in which
you may sell your goods.
Each of these elements
has a couple of decision points to them.
And as you see already by looking
at the name of these elements,
this is really hands-on as I said.
Let's walk you through
some of these decision points
and what you can possibly do
about the product, price, place, etc.,
what are common fallacies,
what are common recommendations
in that sense.
Let me also stress
that, at the end of the day,
these all need to form a coherent view.
This needs to be coherently set,
designed so that the customer
ultimately will see this
as a product offering
with right price
that is distributed
through those distribution chains
that are most appealing
to your customer target market, etc.
Let's move through this one by one.
One core element that is essential
in the entrepreneurial
marketing approach is,
of course, the price you set.
How much would a customer
have to pay for your offering?
This is a vital consideration
to the customer
because this determines
whether he or she wants to buy the good.
But it's also vital to you
as an entrepreneurial company
because the price the customer pays
and how many customers will find
that product attractive at that price
will determine your cash flows.
And that determines, of course,
whether you as a company can survive.
So the pricing decision
is one that is extremely vital.
There are also problems
that are associated with that
because it's not so easy to determine
the right price.
Oftentimes, an approach
that is recommended
is that you want to start
with understanding
how valuable this product is
to your customer.
This means the value
that you're creating for your customer.
That can be a starting point.
Then you can say, "Well,
this is my cost level,
and this is the value
I render to my customers."
Somewhere in between
should be the optimum price.
Cost-plus pricing
is also oftentimes done,
which means you have your cost,
and you add something on top
of your cost -- let's say, 20 percent.
Is this a good way of pricing?
Think about it.
It's not! Because the customer
might get much, much more value
out of your good
than what your cost base is
plus this 20 percent.
You're leaving money
on the table constantly,
which means, well,
the value accrues not to you
but to your marketplace,
which is nice for the marketplace.
But hey, you want to create a company
that is successful in gross.
In that sense, there are couple
of key issues that you can walk through.
We've provided some backup material
on our website that you can refer to
in order to understand
what is scheming pricing,
penetration pricing,
psychological pricing, etc.
We do not have the time
in the segment
to walk you through
each one of these elements.
But let me just point out
one key question,
which is the question that you should have
in the back of your mind.
The question: "Which price
actually maximizes long-term profits?"
This is, of course, an issue
that has to do
with segmentation positioning.
This is evident.
It's the strategic guidance.
There's also some psychological effect.
Your business model
has some implications,
the competition now or later.
Think about the markets you're in.
Oftentimes, these are
dynamic markets
so more and more companies
will enter those domains.
And of course,
the customer's perceived benefit.
That's what I exactly refer to
when I talk about value-based pricing.
Also, the price elasticity,
which means if I change my prices
for a certain percentage
like, let's say, 5 percent higher,
how many more customers
would actually buy my product,
or how many customers
would I lose that way?
If you have a luxury good,
maybe increasing the price
might make it more attractive.
And thinking about pricing,
take into account
that there are also options
where you actually give
the product away for free.
There's a freemium pricing model
where you have, for instance,
a plain vanilla version of your product
that is given away for free,
and then you have a sophisticated version
that allows professionals
to do many more things
with your product
for which you're going to charge
a certain price.
This is oftentimes a pricing model
that is useful for those markets
where you have to want to achieve
a rapid penetration.
Of course, with a product that's free,
there are some advantages
in terms of penetration.
This is one real example of a company
that dealt with that brilliantly:
it's Adobe.
They had the Acrobat Reader
that was given out for free.
Many of you probably use it.
Then there's the Acrobat Distiller
and other versions that are sold
and where the company
actually makes some profit.
Another wonderful example
about pricing is provided by Nespresso.
You may know the coffee capsules
by this company
that is actually owned by Nestle,
which is a company
just down the road here
from Lausanne, where I'm based.
What they are doing
is actually quite smart
because if you think about it,
Nespresso relies on the customers
having coffee machines
that are compatible with their capsules,
and it relies on the sales
of the capsules.
They could say, "Well, we price
the coffee machines highly.
And then we are profiting
from the sales."
That might hinder people actually
from buying the coffee machines.
That will then hinder the people
from actually using
and buying the capsules.
So in that sense,
in order to enter the market
and penetrate the market,
it's of vital importance to them
to keep the price
of the coffee machine low.
So they have
very low profit margins on those.
But they have much higher
profit margins, then,
on the capsules that are repeatedly sold.
In some estimates,
that's up to 85 percent of profit margin
on that coffee capsule,
which is amazing.
This is another interesting example
on that effect.
The second key element
that is of importance
here is the product.
The product has a number
of decision dimensions
that you need to think about
in your marketing mix.
It's about the design,
it's about the technology
that goes inside,
the quality,
it's packaging --
and a couple of others,
but these are oftentimes
the four most important ones.
Of course, these need to fit
the overall strategy.
Meaning, you target customers
and how they should perceive you
and your product
vis-à-vis the competition's product.
More concretely, this means
if your target market segment
would be affluent people
and you're trying to produce a product
that is on the luxury segment,
of course, this has to be visible
in its design, in its quality,
in the packaging of your good.
Otherwise, if your packaging
is a cheap type of packaging,
there's cognitive dissonance
on part of the customers.
They might not say,
"Well, this is a product
that actually fits my needs."
They would not consider buying it.
This has to fit with the segmentation
and positioning, too.
The third element is promotion.
What is important here to understand
is promotion is not just advertising.
It's many different things.
We listed them here.
It's advertising, of course,
but it's also having special offers.
It's direct mailing.
It's maybe a free gift.
It's leaflets. It's other things
that you might want to engage in
in order to actually promote your product.
There are multiple ways
of promoting your product.
Think about it.
Maybe in that way, they'll say,
"Okay, I want to transport
a message to you,
my potential customers."
There are multiple ways
of getting this message across.
Advertising is just one of them.
That guy with a loudspeaker
might be another option.
Free gifts might be also another --
a coffee mug with the branding on it.
If you're, for instance,
selling office goods
and they have this coffee mug
in their office
with the brand of that company
providing office goods,
that's all day long on their desk,
and they see this logo
a couple of times each day.
Their colleagues see this logo.
Of course, these people
are more aware of your company
and the product it offers
than other people's companies
where they are not on the desks often.
Then there's another form
of promotion
that is quite essential
to many start-up firms.
It's public relations.
This is a low-cost alternative
when you don't spend
much money on that.
It's perceived typically
as advertising
that is not being paid for
by the company.
For instance, press releases,
so you have a reporter
reporting about your innovation.
That's actually often something that
the reporters would like to engage.
They're in search
for good stories as well.
If you have a good story to tell
with your product,
why not approach newspapers
and press agencies
to talk about your product?
They might advertise it that way
in their article for free.
It's an important way
to build trust
because it's an outside party
reporting about your company.
It increases awareness.
It could signal potential for the future.
When you think about public relations
and the way you're going to transport
your message through PR,
think also about the different types
of people out there
who could be more or less helpful
in transporting that message.
There are some people out there
who have two million Twitter followers
while others have only a dozen.
Of course,
the ones who have two million
would be better in transporting PR
than the ones with a couple of leads only.
We typically say there are
some gurus out there,
key people in the market,
some authorities
who can influence many, many others.
Then there are some influencers,
maybe some industry peers, experts,
opinion leaders, key customers.
Then there are some additional
decision makers who get their messages,
either directly from you with the PR
or are shaped by what the gurus
and the influencers think.
There are oftentimes
companies in an industry
who look up to other companies and say,
"These other companies are leading
in terms of technology,
in terms of customer approaches,
in terms of their product.
We closely follow what they are doing
and then mimic what they're doing."
That's exactly
what I want to stress here.
Try to get the gurus and influencers
to talk about your company,
then these guys will relate the message
in addition to what your efforts are.
But also, think about what these guys
would take away from doing that.
Maybe they only want to have
an interesting story.
Maybe they want to have
other types of benefits
that are related to that.
Another element is the place,
i.e. where can the product be bought?
This is a key element for marketing,
market entry, and penetration.
It actually means the distribution channel
that you're going to adopt.
Is it retail? Is it wholesale?
Maybe mail order, Internet,
direct sales, peer-to-peer,
maybe multichannel approaches.
Whatever you decide, you make sure
that you are targeting
with your distribution channel
exactly the segment
that you want to address
so that you do not --
some segments actually have preferences
for one or the other channel,
so find out where they buy
and how often they buy,
if they would like to prefer
buying the good maybe in a different way.
It's not said that if they keep on buying
in a retail store
that they would not be willing and able
to switch to online buying, for instance.
Another key element are the people.
These are your employees.
It's you as the management,
it's the culture of your company
because all of these
will shape interaction
with your customers.
It will shape the impression
that customers have of your company.
It will shape how the customer service
is actually executed,
how customers will deal
with your company.
If you think about that,
that's actually of vital importance
because that shapes
the customer's experience.
They will come back if they are happy
with your company,
if they think you are doing
a professional job,
but they won't come back if you lose out
on the customer service.
Make sure that the people dimension
is one that you take into consideration
because it has a lot to do
with the solid implementation
of your marketing mix.
Then two more points.
One is the process.
The process element is of high relevance
for more service-oriented ventures.
Think about how the customer
would consume your service.
It also can be relevant
to product-related purchases.
You might have warranty issues.
You might have other inter-linkages
with your company,
on the website, etc.
The process dimension is also one
that you might want to consider
on that front.
Finally, it's also about
the physical environment.
That means the environment in which
the customer consumes the service
or gets in touch with your company
to purchase a product, or both.
Think about the interface
that is created by your company
to have the customer
on the site in a store.
Maybe it's your company store.
There's different levels of comfort.
The facilities may
or may not be posh, etc.
What this means is that
physical environment
actually shapes the perception
of who you are as a company quite a lot.
It also shapes the customer's experience
with your company quite a lot.
Ideally, of course, that should match
who you want to be seen as,
as a company.
Like, what is your positioning
and what is your segmentation?
These are the seven key elements
of the marketing mix.
It's a mix of elements.
They should be implemented
in an orchestrated fashion.
What's important to consider is that,
of course, it should be orchestrated
with the marketing strategy.
It also depends upon rivals' behavior,
global considerations,
cultural issues, religion, etc.,
in some nations.
Depending on who you are,
these type of elements,
as they are implementing the strategy,
should breathe basically the norms
and the institutional elements
of your particular geography.
Now, building on these seven P's,
you might ask yourself:
Are there more interesting ways,
more creative ways
of engaging in your marketing?
Everyone can spend
the normal amount of money
in order to implement it to marketing.
But the smart people spend imagination
instead of money.
That means, maybe
let's find unconventional ways
of pursuing the conventional goals,
meaning, achieving sales,
achieving market penetration.
That can actually filter down,
trickle down
to all the marketing mix elements.
Oftentimes, guerrilla marketing
is an approach
that is used mostly
with communication,
sometimes with pricing,
sometimes with product issues,
sometimes with distribution issues.
Most often, there are interesting ways
of communicating your product,
communicating about its benefits,
communicating about
its availability, etc.,
that will then make a splash
in the marketplace.
In other words, you're finding ways
in order to, with little effort,
make a big splash.
That means you need to be creative
because there are lots of people out there
who are trying to do exactly that.
Let me give you some intuition
and maybe even some inspiration
of what this means
in terms of guerrilla marketing.
This is one of my favorite examples.
Actually, this is a company
called YOC.
YOC is a firm located in Berlin.
It used to be a start-up.
It's grown up quite a bit.
But in its early days,
it faced a challenge
that was actually quite a big challenge.
They are a company that are providing
mobile marketing services for firms.
When you think about it, well,
they have a chicken-egg problem in a way
because where should they start?
They do not have phone numbers
of the customers.
They do not have references
in terms of great marketing campaigns
with which they could go to companies.
In a sense, they are lacking
in all of these dimensions.
What they did in order to create awareness
for the company
and also to collect
the customer information
is to create an event.
What's this Crash or Cash event
that YOC engaged in?
It's an event that they designed together
with Radio Energy,
a radio station in Berlin.
What they did is to say,
"Okay, we have an interesting event
happening out there
on the Potsdamer Platz,
which is right in the middle of Berlin.
We are doing the following.
We have this Porsche 911,
a wonderful Porsche hanging up there
at 50 meters high.
People could vote
with their cell phones,
whether this Porsche should crash
i.e. fall down these 50 meters,
or whether some of the people,
one person,
would actually win the car at the end,
which means cash."
There was an event, with bands,
with a large screen
for the status of the ballot.
The result was 53 percent said crash
and 47 percent said cash,
so you actually know what that meant.
The Porsche fell down.
I have a picture of that in a minute.
I think what the
important element here is --
and if you can think about it
beyond just this entertainment factor,
of course, it's wonderful
and it's interesting to see
this Porsche crashing.
But on the other hand, they created
a lot of attention for their start-up,
attention for their services.
There was a huge media echo.
If you think about how much
it cost them,
it was the sum of the price
for the Porsche.
Beyond that, they had all
the newspaper coverage they got;
all the TV coverage that they got
was a high multiple
of what they actually spent
for the Porsche.
In that sense,
it was a very smart way.
It was a little expense
relative to the output
and the outcome
they were able to achieve.
In that sense, a guerrilla marketing event
par excellence.
Let me show you now
what the Porsche looked like.
It looked like this.
You can still see that the Porsche
looks like a Porsche,
looks like fairly okay still,
considering that it fell,
it just fell 50 meters.
You'll see it on the crane.
This is actually quite high, 50 meters.
Just imagine that.
That's a guerrilla marketing event.
Is that in the textbooks
of marketing books?
No! It's not there because this is
very much out of the scope.
It takes creativity and ingenuity
to come up with something like this.
But this is actually fun to do.
Think about how your company
might be able to benefit
from some of these events
or some of these approaches.
Another interesting example
of guerrilla marketing
that might inspire you is ModCloth.
This is a social shopping community.
What they did is actually quite smart.
They said, "Okay, we are naming
our dresses after fashion influences
namely other bloggers."
Then these guys picked it up
and blogged about it.
In that sense, in retrospect,
it's a simple way of getting attention
and spreading the word.
But ex-ante, before the fact,
someone had to have this idea.
So be creative.
Find new ways, find interesting ways
to engage in guerrilla marketing.
Here's an interesting example.
It hurts a bit for the man
that's standing here.
It's called Fuzz Wax Bar.
This was a new bar
that wanted to enter the market.
The question is,
if you have a waxing bar,
when you tear out
all the hair on your body
to appear sexier maybe, if you want
to call it that way,
how do you create attention,
awareness for your company?
This is what this bar did.
The Fuzz Wax Bar, they send a person,
a plastered man in wax
down the streets of Toronto
in order to be waxed by strangers.
Not only did the potential customers
test the product,
but they surely remember that experience.
If you look at those up here
on the left,
what they were quite smart
in doing,
each of these papers
was actually a coupon:
"Get 25 percent off your next wax
with this coupon."
They actually created lots of awareness
in the environment
where this wax bar was located.
Here's another example.
It's a company called Varusteleka.
They are selling
Finnish army surplus products
to the public.
What they did to create awareness
for the company was the following.
They sent an open letter
in the form of a video
to Arnold Schwarzenegger --
yes, the "I'll be back" guy
who has been in lots of videos
with lots of guns,
so you see the association.
They invited him to visit the store
and introduce the stuff and the products.
In that sense, it was not a lot
of effort that they did,
but they had the idea.
This was then picked up
by the International Press who said,
"Oh, this is an interesting story
to report about."
If you look at the YouTube video there,
it had more than
600,000 clicks at the time.
We looked at it.
If you look at it as well,
this has many more clicks
in a few minutes.
Then here are some more examples.
I don't walk you through
all of these one by one,
but just look at that.
It's very creative ways,
very innovative ways
to even market some existing products.
Of course, this is not only a domain
that entrepreneurial start-ups
are engaging in nowadays.
It's also a domain
that established companies
have discovered for themselves
because they want to see
more effects, better outcomes
based on their marketing expenditures.
The traditional ways are just not enough
to get the attention of customers anymore.
This brings us already to the end
of an interesting
and also, I think, funny type
of segment here.
Let's just recap a couple of points
that I want you to remember.
First, the marketing mix
is the vehicle for you
to implement your marketing strategy.
We talked about this repeatedly.
The marketing strategy provides
the guidelines
for an orchestrated implementation.
It will make it much easier for you
to find a clearer way
of actually designing and implementing
your marketing mix elements.
We talked about some creative
low-cost approaches
that are often key to start-up success.
As a company, as a young company,
you often lack resources.
Guerrilla marketing
might be one way
of actually getting a lot
out of limited resources.
Ultimately, like in more
general entrepreneurship,
what is particular here?
Spend imagination
instead of money
and enjoy that intellectual challenge.
See you next time.