So welcome back, this is
already the final segment of this week.
Congratulations for making it so far!
This week was
on entrepreneurial marketing.
The customer as well as the competition
were central stage during this week
because you need to understand
both of these key players out there
in order to make your sales.
And I want you to remember
one important quote
that we have discussed
this week in particular,
and it's the quote
by Peter Drucker who said:
"The purpose of a business
is to create a customer,"
not another product or technology.
So, let's revisit
what we discussed this week.
Beyond that quote, I want you to remember
a key framework that we discussed
right at the beginning
and that we walked through
during this week.
It's this framework that shows you
how entrepreneurial marketing
can be structured in your head.
There are some fundamental issues
that you need to understand
about your business,
which is your company's
distinctive competence,
your competitive advantage
that you may achieve
based on your competence,
and then it's important to know
that there are some strategic decisions
in entrepreneurial marketing,
some operational
implementation decisions
that you have to take.
And this distinction is
quite important, as we discussed,
because segmentation and positioning
are fundamental decisions
that will then shape and affect
the other types of decisions
that you are going to engage in.
For instance, we've got
product/service development,
naming the company, your pricing,
distribution, sales force, promotion,
public relations, and advertising.
Let me briefly walk you through
each of these elements --
especially the strategic decisions,
and implementation decisions
and options --
in a few slides.
These strategic decisions relate,
as I've just mentioned,
to segmentation and positioning,
"Which is (are) my target market(s)?"
Typically, entrepreneurs have
one particular target market.
And the positioning question is:
"Why will someone in the target market(s)
buy my product or service
instead of the competition's?"
So it's how should I be perceived by
my customers vis-à-vis competing products.
Typically, as it's pointed out here,
these decisions are made jointly,
because you might think
about your target segment
and then come to the conclusion: "Well,
the positioning that I want to achieve
doesn't fit this target segment,"
or vice versa,
so this is really a joint decision,
and you might go a bit back and forth
until you really understand
your target market
and how the people, the customers,
and the target market will perceive you
vis-à-vis the competition.
Core to understanding segmentation
and positioning
is an understanding
of your customers and of your competitors.
And starting with the customer's side
you'll remember we discussed the benefits
that your product is able to render
to customers, to give to customers,
because the customers don't buy
the features, they buy the benefits.
And this is particularly important
in a technology context
where many people are tempted to say,
"This product has wonderful features."
The customer looks at the product
from the perspective of saying,
"Well, what does this product do to me?
What type of job
does this product fulfill for me?"
In terms of understanding your customers
there are two key features,
two key elements that are vital
to creating a successful firm.
One is, of course, understanding
your customers for making sales.
This has to do with understanding
customer needs
and we talked about this at great length.
The second element,
which is equally important
because you want to create
a successful venture that creates value,
is to understand customers
from a value-creation perspective
because not all customers create
the same type of value for you.
Understanding which customer segments
might be more valuable for your company
will help you to allocate
your time properly,
and especially
your resources and attention.
In terms of understanding
your competition,
there are two key questions that we put
to the forefront of our discussions:
one was, "Who are your competitors?"
and two was, "What would we need
to know about these competitors?"
Oftentimes, and that's also
what we discussed,
entrepreneurs have this hunch of saying,
"Well, we've produced an innovation,
and because we have that innovation
we do not have any competition."
But that's oftentimes an indication
that entrepreneur doesn't really
understand his competition well,
and also not his customers,
because customers typically make a choice
what to spend the money on.
So there is competition at least
for the money in their pocket.
The intended outcomes
of this type of analysis are manifold,
and just to repeat a couple of those:
first of all, you want to make
your products stand out.
You want to position,
understand how to position your company.
You also want to set
your prices competitively
and assess any threats of competing firms.
Ultimately, it also helps
if you understand your competition well,
it helps you to be realistic on how
successful you can be with your company.
And this helps you to judge resource
requirements, the sales targets, etc.
So, when you've collected
all of these insights
you have all the ingredients in place
to develop a compelling value proposition.
And we discussed the features
of a compelling value proposition
in a segment this week.
In a nutshell, the value proposition
can be stated very succinctly
within these one or two sentences
that you see next to me here.
The sentence says, "As a result
of our" offerings or product or service,
"customers"
-- you would fill in the profile --
"who are facing" some kind of need,
some kind of shortcoming,
some kind of customer pain,
"will" do, experience, something
"for" a certain cost
"and enjoy" the customer
benefits or some return,
within or by a certain timeframe;
and then the competitive element
comes in by saying,
"compared to" these types of alternatives.
"The advantages of using
our offerings are" bing, bing, bing.
So, within that one sentence
you can actually very succinctly portray
what your company offerings are about
or why the customer
should buy your offering
and not the one of the competition.
This sentence might sound easy to you,
but it's actually hard work to craft
a compelling value proposition.
But I urge you to do this
because you need to have clarity
in your mind what your company is about.
And remember what Drucker said:
your company is about creating a customer,
and not the product or the technology.
So in this sentence you have to understand
why and how you create
a customer and not a product.
And then, moving
to the implementation side
we discussed a couple of elements
in the marketing mix.
Remember the product, the price,
the place, the promotion, the process,
the people; and the physical
environment is the seventh piece.
And you can formulate those elements
in an orchestrated manner, once you have
these strategic decisions in place
about your segmentation and positioning.
We mentioned that in a segment.
As you remember, there are
a couple of interesting ways,
unconventional ways on how
start-ups can do the marketing.
We talked about guerrilla marketing
in that sense, which is oftentimes
a type of marketing that is related
to the promotional activities
that you do in the the marketing mix.
We discussed a couple of examples
to inspire you, but in essence,
what you can imagine in terms
of novel ways of marketing your product,
of getting the attention of customers,
where the idea is really one
where with a small budget
you create a strong leverage
in terms of the attention you get
for your company and its products.
So when we talked about
guerrilla marketing, we also mentioned
that your guerrilla marketing approach,
your implementation there
is oftentimes related
to your promotional activities,
but, of course, this should be in line
with your positioning of your company
and what your target segment
actually likes to see about your company.
Don't offend your target segment just
with any crazy type of guerrilla campaign
because that could be
highly detrimental for you
if it's to create a successful company.
In addition, we talked about
crowdfunding as a marketing tool.
Remember that we will come back
to this topic in another week
when we'll talk about
crowdfunding as a financing tool,
but from a marketing perspective,
crowdfunding has a couple
of very interesting aspects.
And as you may remember, it helps you
to test and validate your market,
put your ideas out there,
observe investor behavior.
It helps you to build a list of "backers"
and build relationships
to potential customers.
It also helps you build brand recognition,
and ultimately, to boost growth
and offer discounts
on new or current products
that you are developing.
Crowdfunding platforms are actually
providing lots of non-financial gains
and that's oftentimes overlooked,
so I think it's important
that you engage
in these types of activities
in order to launch your venture.
So we talked about two more elements:
technology adoption and growth hacking.
Technology adoption: remember
the technology adoption life cycle,
in particular, one element
that was crucial
which was the idea of crossing the chasm.
Remember, that we had a chasm
between the early adopters
and the early majority of people
in a target segment.
Remember also that these people
differ in terms of their responsiveness
and their willingness
to buy innovative products.
And where the trap oftentimes is located:
between early adopters
and the early majority.
And there is a trap in the following way:
you as an entrepreneur achieve
first sales, you are successful,
so the natural inclination is
to put even more money
behind your product,
your marketing campaign, etc.
But you overlooked
actually the next segment
that you want to conquer:
the early majority,
where you start making a lot of money.
That segment buys for different reasons.
So keep in mind
that in order to cross that chasm
you need to change
your marketing message,
how you communicate with customers,
what type of profile of related services
you might want to offer to them, etc.
And finally, we talked about
achieving significant growth.
This is obviously one key goal
that many entrepreneurs have,
and that's ultimately one key element
of entrepreneurial marketing.
In order to understand
how to achieve growth,
you have to understand
in terms of the venture design
the scalability of your venture,
and you have to understand
how you can accelerate growth
by relentlessly focusing on growth.
So you can look at the marketing
mix elements that we discussed
through a lens that allows you to grow,
and to try to design these elements
in a way that it allows you to grow.
Oftentimes this is referred to
nowadays as growth hacking.
So you can also think about creative ways
of how to piggyback
on the growth of other companies.
We discussed some examples
regarding this as well.
So this brings us already to the very end
of Week 3 -- time flies.
This was Week 3
with entrepreneurial marketing
as its core topic, as I pointed out.
This week we have learned
a couple of very important frameworks,
ways to understand
entrepreneurial marketing.
The marketing function is
of vital importance for your company,
so pay attention to it,
pay attention to designing your marketing
in the most favorable way,
and pay attention
to its execution as well.
So good luck with your marketing efforts.
I'll see you around.