In the previous episodes,
we have seen that the attributes
defined within the class
represent informations
specific to each  instance
of the class.
Let us go back to our little
example of the rectangle.
Each instance of rectangle, each
Rectangle-type object
will have its own width,
its own height.
Those are specific informations
characterizing each rectangle.
Now, what does happen if several
instances of a same class
need to access a same
information,
a common information?
This is the object of today's episode.
In order to illustrate the
problem we are interested in,
let us go back to our example
of counting instances.
We have already had the chance to
study it in the episodes
regarding the construction/destruction
of an object.
Our goal is to account for all
the instances existing
at a given time in a program.
For that, we need to have a
memory area
accessible by every instance.
It will be incremented
whenever an instance is created
and decremented every time an
instance is destroyed.
When we had discussed this problem
for the first time,
the only way we had to define
this memory area,
acessible by every
instance
in order to be incremented
and decremented was to use a global variable.
Formerly, we were not plainly
satisfied
with this declaration of a
global variable.
Indeed, using global variables
tends to be nefarious
in a program; it is a very
poor solution.
A global variable, such as this one,
is not attached to any entity
in the program.
Therefore, violates the principle
of encapsulation
and is a sign of a poor
modularization.
Moreover, this can induce harmful
side effects.
Indeed, such a variable can be
accessed
pretty much everywhere in the program,
without any control.
Therefore, we should avoid
this at all cost.
Alternatively, defining the counter
as an attribute of the rectangle class
is clearly not a good solution
either
since it would mean that each
instance of rectangle
has its own counter. This is clearly
not what we wish.
We wish to have a common area
accessible by every instance.
Therefore, this solution is not
good either.
The solution to this problem is
to define the information we wish to be
common to all instances of
the class
as a class attribute.
Unlike the attributes
relative to instances
(the ones we were used to
define up until now)
a class attribute is an attribute
defined
inside the class, but matched with
the reserved keyword "static".
Typically, let us us imagine a
program where severall Rectangle
instances coexist.
To make things easier, there
will be two.
The situation in the memory
is the following.
The "r1" object has its own
specific values
for its instance attributes :
the height and the width.
The same goes for the "r2" object,
having its own values
for the height and the width.
On the other hand, the class attribute "compteur"
(TN: means "counter")
is a unique memory area
accessible by all the
instances.
However, it only exists once
in the memory.
By the way, please note that the
visibility rules for a "static" attribute
are the sames as the non "static"
attributes.
This means that this memory area
is accessible even if no instance
has been created,
simply through the name of the class.
Very concretely, let us have a program
where we declare a "Rectangle" class,
like this, with a class attribute.
We can access this class attribute without
having previously
created any instance of Rectangle.
This can be done through the following
notation, this one :
We are accessing the variable
of the "Rectangle" class
called "compteur". We are doing this
through the scope resolution operator.
To sum up, in order to
define a class attribute,
we define an attribute and
precede its declaration
with the reserved keyword "static".
We have seen that a class attribute is
shared by all the instances.
It is a unique memory area shared
by all the instances.
This memory area exists even
when we have not created
any instance of this class.
We have seen we can access it
through this notation.
Also, a class attribute can,
like an instance attribute,
be either private or public.
The instance attributes are
typically initialized
upon the objects' initialization.
However, we have seen that a class attribute
may exist independently
from any object's construction.
In that case, how should we proceed
to initialize a class attribute?
To that end, we must resort to
a particular syntax.
Outside the class, we place
an initialization line
with this syntax.
It means :
the "compteur" variable,
of the "Rectangle" class,
of the integer type,
will be initialized to 0.
Such a line of code will appear
outside the "Rectangle" class.
For example, like this.
We will take this line outside the declaration
of the "Rectangle" class.
We resort to a particular syntax
since a class attribute exists even if we
have not declared any instance of this class.
This means we cannot have, for example,
a constructor
be in charge of the required initialization.
Resorting to a class variable in order
to account
for all the instances of a class
is naturally a relatively atypical
example.
Of course, there are many other
situations
where it is useful to share informations
between several instances.
However, most of the time, it will be
a constant.
Let us take an example.
This time, we will move away
from our rectangle example
and imagine a situation where
we need to
reperesent the employees
of a company.
This is more of an administrative
example.
Let us say that an employee is
characterized by an age,
the in-service date.
Also, let us say that there is
an information common
to all employees. This would be the
official pensionable age.
Where should we place this
information on the pensionable age
(for example 65 years) ?
This pensionable age of 65 years
is the same
for all employees.
Let us imagine we start by
declaring it
like an instance attribute,
like this.
This means that, every time we
create an employee,
this employee will have an
age (30 years old)
an in-service date,
and an official pensionable
age (65 years).
Same thing for the second
employee, still with 65 years.
And this as many times
as there are employees,
with the value 65 repeated
every time.
This information is thus uselessly
repeated for each employee.
There is thus code duplication;
this could induce maintenance
troubles.
For example, let us imagine that,
through a change of law,
the pensionable age is changed
to 67 years.
We would thus need to dive
into each instance
and modify this value everywhere.
Obviously, this may beget severe
maintenance problems.
The solution is obviously
to define this information
as a class variable
thanks to the reserved "keyword" static.
Typically, here, "age_retraite"
(TN: means "pensionable_age")
would be a memory area
commonly accessible by
all the instances.
However, it will not be duplicated
in each of the instances.
Typically, this will disapear.
The same goes for each instance.
To sum up, we have seen,
through the previous examples
that the class attributes are
typically very practical
and useful when different objects
(such as our employees)
need to access a common information
(such as the official pensionable age).
We have seen it lets us avoid
information duplication
and permits for a better maintenance
of this information.
Also, please remember the
case we had studied before,
regarding instance counting.
Here, the class variable was defined
as a non-constance
since we need to
decrement/increment this value every
time an object is created is destroyed.
Why, this situation is rather
atypical.
Practically, most of the
class variables
you will encounter will be used to
represent constants useful for
all the instances of a given class.
Now, you know what a class attribute is,
a "static" attribute.
Is it possible to do the same thing
with methods?
The answer is yes, and we will present it for
the sake of completeness,
even though  "static" methods are not
used very frequently.
Also, it is not recommanded to
use them in object-oriented programming.
A "static" method is simply
a method defined inside a class.
This declaration is preceded with
the reserved keyword "static".
In order to call an instance method,
that is, the the methods we were used
to work with until now,
we forced to have previously
created an object.
Only then could we call the method
on this object.
For example, in order to calculate
the surface of a rectangle,
we first need to create a Rectangle-type object.
Only then can we call the calculation
of this rectangle's surface.
On the other hand, a class method
may very well be called
if not object of the class has been
previously declared.
For example, let " A " be a class with
a static method
called "methode1". We may call this method
thanks to the scope resolution
operator
without having previously declared
any A-type object.
Here, we simply say
that we are calling "method1" of the
class "A".
Of course, such an instruction is not
valid for non-static methods.
For example, here, in the class "A",
we have a second method : "methode2".
It has not been declared as "static".
If we try to call it only
through the name of the class,
without passing by the creation
of an instance,
we will get an error.
In order to call the non-static "methode2",
we need an previously declared
A-type object
on which to call "methode2".
This is what we are doing here to
calculate the surface
of a given rectangle "r".
By the way, please note
that a "static" method method
may be called
either through the name of the class
(independently of the any instance's
creation,
as we have done here)
or it can be called through
an instance
(if such an instance exists).
Therefore, such an instruction is valid
albeit not frequent or recommanded.
Finally, this kind of instruction,
accessing a "static" member
through an instance is also
possible
for the attributes (if this attribute is
accessible, of course).
The fact that a class method may be
called independently
of the creation of any instance
begets a few restrictions regarding
what we may do within
such a method.
Indeed, since a class method cannot
presuppose the existence
of the current object on
which it is applied,
it cannot itself use
a method or attribute presupposing
the existence of an object.
It will not be able to use an
instance method or attribute.
In other words, this means
that a class method
can only access otehr class
methods and attributes.
A "static" method can itself only
use "static" members.
We may see class methods
as simple usual functions that have been
placed inside a class.
In languages such as C++, where
there is a non-object layer
where we can use usual
functions
without passing by the creation
of classes,
the use of class methods is warranted
only
in very particular situations.
We can imagine, as an example,
the need to create a class method
in order to print a few values
of class attributes.
We can imagine the need
to define a class method
in order to manipulate class attributes,
"static" attributes
who are non constant
and private.
In this case, it is necessary to define
such methods.
In general, it is almost always
preferable to use
usual functions in C++
rather than class methods.
Above, we should absolutely avoid
to have "statics" grow rampant
in a program.
Whyso?
Indeed, since a "static" member can be called
independently of the creation
of any object, it weakens our
oriented-object approach.
Voilà, this concludes our presentation
on "static" members
in a class; methods and attributes both.
We have seen that, practically,
most of the "static" attributes we will
encounter will be constants.
Also, we should remain careful
not to overuse "statics".