In this episode, as well as
the upcoming ones,
we will focus on operator
overloading.
This is a rather technical subject
which will make us able to define
our very own operators.
Let us begin with an example so that
we may see what purpose it serves.
For example, let us say we have
defined a "Complexe" (= "Complex")  class
in order to add complex numbers.
It does not matter what it is
exactly.
What matters, is that we wish
to add
complex numbers.
Let us suppose we have already defined
a few complex numbers :
z1, z2 and so on.
How should we proceed in order
to add these complex numbers?
For example, we may wish to store inside
z3, the result of " z1 + z2 ".
Of course, we would very much like
to write something like :
" z3 = z1 + z2 "
If we write this in our
usual classes
we will get a compiling error
since the " + " is indeed not
defined for z1, z2,
it is not defined for
complex numbers.
Until now, we would rather
have defined a function in charge
of the addition.
For example, we could define
a function called "add"
which would work like this :
add(z1, z2) and
" z3 = add(z1, z2) "
in order to store the result of the addition
of z1 and z2 into z3.
And if we wanted to store, into z4,
the result of the addition of
z1, z2 and z3,
we would have to write it like this.
As the first argument, here,
we add up z1 and z2
and then, as the second argument,
we will call the function "add" again
and add z3 here.
Unfortunatley, this way to write it
is rather unnatural.
It would be much more pleasant
to write " z4 = z1 + z2 + z3 ";
it is much clearer than something like
this with an "add" function.
Indeed, the goal of operator
overloading
is to let us write something like this,
using the " + " operator
with a class belonging to us,
that we have defined,
called the "Complexe" class.
Similarly, we could wish to print
complex numbers in an homogenous
way like this.
For example, printing the
message " z3 = "
followed by the value of the complex number z3
so that we may print z3.
Why, writing this is only
possible
if we do not overload the
printing operator.
We daresay it is better to write this
rather than having to cut out here
a printing of the message "z3 = "
and then calling a printing function
which we have defined for the
complex class.
Finally printing the line
break like this.
This here is the purpose
of operator overloading.
This will let us expand the
use of the usual operators
(the ones we deem most useful)
to the classes where we wish
to add these different operators
(addition, printing, multiplication)
according to our needs.
That said, operator overloading is
still quite a technical subject;
it can be rather complicated since we
are in the core of the language.
We will redefine elementary
operations :
the operators.
Therefore, according to your level
or to the restrains you find
yourselves in,
you have several ways to tackle
the operator overloading.
You can decide not to use them at
all and continue
using functions as you were
doing up until now.
Also, you may decide to introduce
only the operators
relatively simple :
additions, multiplications
without worrying about the so-called
auto-assignment
(that is, += , -=, x= ).
At this level, you may also decide to
overload the printing operator
if you find it useful.
At a higher level, you may start
to tackle
the overloading of auto-assignment
operators : += , -= and so on
but in a slightly simplified
version
with the return type "void".
We will go back to this in detail
in the different following episodes.
Here, we are giving the plan of the videos
we will be proposing.
Finally, at the highest level,
you may also redefine
these operators according to the
standard, at a much higher level.
The level targeted by this course
is the level 2.
We will thus do a relatively simple
operator overloading.
However, in the upcoming videos,
we will still present
the level 3 and the level 4 so that
you know they exist.
If you interested, you may freely
expand on the subject.
Now, let us dive into the heart
of the matter :
this famous operator overloading.
First of all, what is an operator?
Operators are signs used
to represent the operations
such as arithmetic operators.
For example, when you write
" z = a + b ",
you are using the addition
operator.
You have logical operators.
For example, if we write
" (a == b) and (x == y) "
here, "and" is an operator.
You also have comparison operators.
For example, if you write : " x <= y "
you are still using an operator.
You also have the auto-increment operators.
For example, when we write " ++i "
in "for loops".
You also have the assignment operator
of which we have not yet spoken,
but which is written here.
If you have : " z = something ",
it is indeed an operator.
This operator is overloadable aswell.
We will talk about it in
the very last video.
What you need to know is that when you write
an expression containing an operator
(the operator "==" here, the operator "and"...)
it corresponds to the call
to a function
or to a call to a method (class member function).
Every time you write  "a Op b ",
either you have the function
"operatorOp (a, b) ".
For example, when we write
" a + b ",
it means we have either a call
to the function " Operator+ (a, b)
or (we will see the distrinctions
later) the class method
of which a is an instance :
a.operator+
This means the method "operator+ "
where b is the argument.
Similarly, if we have
unary operators
(operators with only one operand),
for example, when we write " -a "
to take the opposite of a,
or when we write " ++a " to
increment a,
it is either a call to a function or a  call to a method.
In the case of "-a",
it is either the function "operator-"
with a as argument,
or the method of a class instance
written " a.operator- "
here without argument.
Similarly, " ++a" will either
call a function
according to what has been defined
( "operator++ (a))
or the method "operator++ " of the
class where a is an instance (a.operator++()).
To give more examples, when you
write "cout << a ",
you are either using the function
"operator<< " taking cout and a as argument
or (since cout is an instance
of class
called "iostream") the method
"operator<< "
of the class where "cout" is an instance,
that is, the "ostream" class
with a as parameter.
Finally, you need to know
that when you call " a = b ",
you indeed in this case here.
However, there is no function " = "
with two arguments.
Therefore, we are perforce
using the method " operator= "
of the class where a is an instance
called
with b as parameter.
Those were a handful of examples.
The set of the operators
you can overload
is given as a pdf complement
on the course website.
This is it for the operators.
Now what about the overloading?
The overloading is when a function
or a method
has the same name as another function/method,
both being distinguished by their arguments
For example, we can imagine a function
"max" taking two integers as parameters
and another function "max" taking
two doubles as parameters.
At this point, we say that the two
"max" functions are overloaded.
There are several functions
with the same name "max"
but distinguished by the types
of their parameters.
Regarding operators,
we will do the same thing :
we will overload operators.
For example, we will overload the operator
" + " for the "Complexe" class.
Here, it takes two complex numbers
and the addition of two complex numbers
returns here a complex number.
For example, if we are working
with matrices we wish to add,
we may overload the operator " + "
and take two matrices here.
This is the operator overloading.
It is the possibility to
redefine operators having the same name :
"operator something" for
different classes.
In C++, pretty much all operators
are overloadable.
Once again, the complete list
is given on the course website.
Therefore, you can freely overload
the usual operators
for your classes.
As we said, there are two ways
to interpret an operator :
either as a function
or as a method.
Indeed, there are two types
of overloading.
The so-called external overloading
or internal overloading.
The external overloading is the one
using usual non-member functions;
for example, "operator+ " taking
two complex numbers
in order to do, for example "z3 = z1 + z2"
which will be called "operator+ " :
" z3 = operator+(z1, z2) ".
This overloading is external to
the class; we call it
an external overloading by
opposition to the internal overloading
which is done inside the class
and is the alternative.
This time, we would have
" z3 = z1.operator+ (z2) "
where "operator+ " is a method of
the class of z1.
Therefore, in an internal overloading,
the operator corresponds
to a method (a class member function). On the other hand,
in the external overloading,
the operator corresponds to
a usual non-member function.
We will begin by presenting the external
overloading.
Then, in the next episode, we will
present the internal overloading
and decide which one is
more appropriate
and choose one of these
overloading options.