In the previous episode,
we have presented, in a very
general way,
the concept of operator overloading.
Now, we know that two kinds exist :
the internal overloading
and the external overloading.
In today's episode, we will
thoroughly focus
on the external overloading.
External overloading consists
of defining the operators
as usual functions (as opposed to class member functions).
For example, this function "operator+",
taking here 2 complex numbers
in order to define the addition operator "+"
for the class representing complex numbers.
Let us thoroughly examine this example.
Let us suppose we have defined
a "Complexe" (= "Complex") class.
We have declared 3 instances of
this class : z1, z2 and z3.
Now, we wish to compute the
addition : "z3 = z1 + z2 ".
In the case of the external overloading,
where the operator is a
function,
it corresponds, be reminded, to the
call " z3 = operator+(...) "
with z1 and z2 as arguments.
We thus deduce that the prototype
of the function "operator+"
will take two Complex-type arguments
and return a Complexe.
This si therefore a possible prototype
for the overloading of "operator+".
We may want to optimize this call
and avoid the copies due to
passing the parameters by value,
doing a passage by constant
reference instead.
Also, we may want to have
(this will be explained
in the third episode
on operator overloading)
as return type : "const Complexe".
For now, we take it as granted; it will
all be explained
in the last episode on
operator overloading.
Here is thus a second possible
prototype
for this "operator+" defined
in external overloading.
A third solution, which is
the optimial solution in C++ 2011
and will also be explained in
the third episode
on operator overloading,
would be to have the following prototype :
"const Complex" as the return value,
a passage by value for the first argument,
and a passage by constant reference
for the second argument.
Here, the passage by value may
seem
a little suboptimal and conter-intuitive.
Due to the specificities of C++ 2011,
particularly regarding the notion of move
instead of copy
(which stretch far beyond the content
of this course)
it is ultimately the better solution.
This leaves us with the following code.
Let us examine the details.
We thus have the "Complexe" class
which defines a complex number,
for example 2 here, "double".
It also has a constructor
permitting to initialize
its 2 attributes "x" and "y"
by receiving two values here.
For example, we could construct
a complex number like this.
Here, we are passing the value 1 for
"x" and the value 2 for "y".
This is the constructor we have here.
Then, we have a handful of
methods necessary
in order to manipulate complex numbers.
For example, we can retrieve the value "x"
and retrieve the value of "y".
Here, we have our external overloading
of "operator+".
The prototype we have previously
described
will be written like this.
Of course, when we write
"z1 + z2" like this,
we must define a new complex "z1 + z2".
The result of the addition of z1 and z2
is a new value
which is neither z1 nor z2.
We will here define this
new value
and build using our two-parameters
constructor.
Actually, the formula for the
addition of two complex numbers
is done by retrieving the "x" of z1
and the "x" of z2,
and adding up these 2 "x".
For the "y" component, we will
retrieve the two "y" values
and compute their addition.
Here, we are indeed constructing
a complex number
corresponding to the definition of
the addition of z1 and z2.
We return this complex number
as the return value of "operator+".
Also, the most advanced out of you
will of course note
(though it is a detail)
that we could regroup these 2 lines.
Thus, we could simply write
"return Complexe(...)", without giving any name.
"return Complexe(...)", with here an
anonymous "Complexe"
and a direct call to the constructor.
But, once again, this is advanced and does not
bring much.
We have seen that there are 2
overloading ways : external and internal.
In mose cases, we may choose
between
external overloading and internal
overloading.
In some cases though, we
cannot choose;
it is absolutely mandatory to use
the external overloading.
Let us look at these cases.
The first case is when we mix
different types.
For example, here, we would
to do the multiplication
of a complex number and a double.
For example, we have here a double "x"
and a complex number "z1".
We would like to retrive the
result of "x" times "z1" into "z2".
"x" is a double-type variable,
and "z1" is a Complexe-type variable.
In principle, we could choose
for the rewriting
between "z2 = x.operator* " with
an internal overloading (call to a method)
or "z2 = operator* (x, z1)"
(call to a function).
However, it is obvious that the
first line makes no sense at all.
Indeed, "x" is not a class
instance
but a so-called basic  type,
a double.
"double" is not a class, there are
not methods in "double".
This solution is thus impossible.
Here, we have no choice but to
resort to the external overloading,
thus using functions.
Similarly, in the case where we would
like to print a complex number,
for example doing "cout << z1 ",
using the overloading of the printing
operator less than-less than (<<),
we could have two possible ways to write it.
Either with the method "operator<<" of the
class where "cout" is an instance
(the class "ostream");
in this way, we are calling the method
of this "ostream" class,
or, we could use a function taking
here the 2 parameters "cout" and "z1".
However, here, we only care about
overloading the "Complexe" class
and definitely not about meddling
with the "ostream" class
where "cout" is an instance.
There, in this case, aswell,
we will never use the internal overloading
of the "ostream" class.
Instead, we will prefer the external overloading.
Let us thoroughly examine these 2 examples,
starting with the outer multiplication.
Be reminded that we have
declared a double, "x" here.
We also have two "Complexe" :
z1 and z2.
We wish to compute the multiplication
of "x" and "z1"
and store the result into "z2".
The equivalent call would be
"z2 = operator* (x, z1); ".
This gives us the prototype.
The function returns a
complex number.
For the same reasons, which
will be explained later,
we will rather pick "const".
We will have "operator* " and then,
we are taking a "double" and a "Complexe".
For optimization reasons, we will
pass it  by constant reference.
We thus end up with the following
prototype.
For the definition, we could
either write all the operations
explicitly
for the multipllication of this double "a" here
and this "Complexe" "z".
Or, if we suppose that the
inner overloading exists
(which is very possible for
complex numbers
but not possible for all classes).
But when it is possible,
that the internal overloading exists
(please note we have swapped the other
and started by multiplying by "z" ).
Since something exists able
to do "Complexe" times "double",
that is, either an internal overloading
of the "Complexe" class
taking a double,
or an already written,
external overloading,
the multiplication of "Complex" first
by a "double" then
(no matter which solution is chosen).
What matters is that
writing "a" times "z"
is mathematically the same
thing as "z" times "a".
In such a case, with this kind
of equality, we do not want
to write the same code twice but
instead use already written code.
For the printing operator,
we may wish, for example, to do
"cout << z1 ".
Here, z1, is of course a complex number.
Be reminded that the equivalent
call
would be an external overloading
of the function
"operator<<" with "cout" and z1
as arguments.
This gives, as the prototype of
the function :
"operator<< ". Here is the type of "cout"
and here a "Complexe" which we
pass once again,
for optimization reasons,
by constant reference.
By the way, "cout" is, an
instance of the "ostream" class,
is passed by reference.
Indeed, the very printing
"cout << z1 "
will indeed modify "cout"
since we will write informations
on "cout", thus modifying it.
Since we are modifying this argument,
we absolutely need to pass
it by reference.
We will give you the return type
of this function right away
so that you may write correctly
this printing operator. The return type
is also an "ostream&".
The reason behind this type will also
be explained
in the last video on operator
overloading,
regrouping all these subtleties.
Let us now move on to the definition
of this printing operator for
complex numbers.
The first solution is to use getters,
for exemple "getX" or "getY",
returning the attributes we
wish to print.
This leads to the following :
Here we have received, as the
first parameter,
the output stream on which we
wish to write.
We are using this stream to print,
for example, a parenthesis here.
Let us say we have a complex number
where "x" is 3 and "y" is 4.
The idea is to print " (3, 4) ";
this is the desired format for
the printing here.
Therefore, we write the opening
parenthesis,
then we retrieve the "x" of the complex
which we have received as the second argument
of this "operator<<" function.
We now print the comma.
Then, we print the retrieved value
for the attribute "y" of this complex
number "z".
Then, we finish with the
closing parenthesis.
Then we do not forget,
because of the return value
"ostream&" here,
to finish our function with a "return"
of the output parameter.
For now, please consider
this mandatory
in order to avoid unpleasant
"segmentations faults"
so that you can use "operator<<"
correctly
just like you do for int and double.
A second possible definition
is to use
a previously defined method
either to convert a "Complexe" into
a character string
or to directly print a complex.
Let us look at this first solution.
Here, we are again using the
received stream to print
the result of the call to
the method "to_string"
which transforms a "Complexe"
into a character string.
In its prototype, the return
type is typically a
a character string,
that is, "string".
The method belongs to the class "Complexe"
and is called "to_string".
It does not take any parameters.
Also, it does not modify the
current instance;
indeed, modifying a "Complexe" into
a character string
does not modify this "Complexe".
Therefore, we will call this method
here, in "operator<< ".
As previously, we finish
by returning the first received argument.
Another solution could to directly
have a method
"affiche" working just like "operator<<".
(TN: "affiche" means "print").
However, it would be a public
method in the class
receiving the stream on which
we print
and return this stream.
Therefore, its prototype is very similar
to the one of the printing
operator,
thus returning an "ostream".
It is a method of the "Complexe" class.
It is called "affiche", and it takes,
as parameter,
a stream it modifies.
The stream is thus passed by reference.
This method does not modify
the printed complex number;
when we print a "Complexe", we
do not modify it.
We conclude here with the
keyword "const".
Those were three possible examples
of definition of the printing operator
for our "Complexe" class.
You may freely draw inspiration
for your very own classes.
By the way, please note (we are
anticipating on a later subject)
that it is prefearable to use these kinds
of methods "to_string" or "affiche"
when we will be dealing with
polymorphism
which will come later.
When we are doing external
overloading,
it is sometimes necessary to
access private attributes
of the class on which we wish
to apply the operator.
Even if we think it is bad
programming,
and that we truly advise you
to only use getters
and the interface
(the public part of the class),
you may sometimes encounter this
kind of practice
(though we do not recommand
to write it yourself) :
here, you could be tempted to write
"z.x" or here "z.y",
that is, to directly access the
private attributes "x" and "y" of
the "Complexe" class.
In this case, we need to give
a priviliged access
to this function, since it is outside
the "Complexe" class.
to give a privileged access to
the private parts.
We call this : declaring a friendship
thanks to the keyword "friend".
Once again, we strongly recommand
that you rather
use getters,
that is, the public part of
the class
rather than the private part through
this indirect way
that is the keyword "friend".
However, since you may encounter it,
we will present it.
If you have to disregard our
advice and use a friendship,
you will put, in the very definition
of the class, a line like
"friend" followed by the prototype of
the function you wish to have
access to the private parts of
the class.
Thus, we do it like this :
"friend" followed by a the prototype
of a function.
This gives us the right to
access
the private methods and
attributes of the class.
Please note that the definition of these
functions
remains, of course, outside
the class.
Indeed, these functions have nothing
to do with the class.
We simply indicate in the class
that we are giving access rights to
these external functions.
Let us look concretely what it
would look like
for complex numbers.
Here, we have the "Complex" class.
The private parts
are the attributes "x" and "y".
Here, we have our printing
operator
for complex numbers.
All is as before.
However, we have not followed
the aforementioned advice
(we do not recommand you
do the same, of course).
Here, we are trying to access
the private parts.
If we do not do anything
particular,
we will end up with a compiling error here :
we are not allowed to
access the private parts
with an external function.
In order for this to work properly,
we need to add, in the "Complex" class,
a line giving access rights (giving
the "friendship")
to this external function.
We are simply putting its prototype
after the keyword "friend".
Adding this line
means the given function can
now access
the private parts.
Personally, we daresay this is
a very poor idea,
for it breaks the encapsulation.
This concludes our episode
on the external overloading.
In the next episode, we will
discuss the internal overloading.
Also, we will tell you in
which cases
you should prefer either
of these two overloading ways.
Finally, in a last video,
we will go back to all the
details
we have left aside.