In this episode,
we will keep discussing operator
overloading.
This time, we will focus on the
inner overloading.
In the previous episodes,
we have indeed learnt that an
operator could be overloaded
either outside a class
(in this case, it is a usual, non-member, function)
or inside a class
(in this case,
it is a member function belonging
to a class).
For example, let us say we have defined
the operator "+"
for complex numbers through
a function.
Then, when we write something
like "z1 + z2" where z1 an z2 are "Complex",
this corresponds to a call
to the function "operator+ "
taking z1 and z2 as arguments.
The first operand corresponds
to the first argument of the function,
and the second to the second
argument of the function.
A possible alternative would
be to defne the operator "+"
through an inner overloading.
This means we will place
this operator's definition
inside the "Complexe" class.
Since it is a member function,
we will need to call it
through an object.
Therefore, when we write
this,
it does not correspond to the same thing
as in the case of outer overloading.
This will be translated to
a call to a member function
which looks like this.
The first operand is the current object
on which the "operator +" is applied.
The second operand will correspond
to the argument of the member function.
As we can see, in the case
of inner overloading,
we only need one single
argument
which corresponds to the second operand.
Let us sum up. If we wish to realize the
inner overloading of a given operator,
we will place the member function "OperatorOP"
inside a class.
Just as we did for other member functions, we will
simply place,
inside the class,
the prototype of the operator.
Then, we will give the operator's
definition outiside the class.
In this external definition,
the operator will have
to be bound to the class
it belongs to through to scope
resolution operator;
this is essentially the same as
the other member functions we have seen.
A keypoint you have to
remember
is that the first operant of such an
operator is the current instance.
Therefore, this instance will not
be passed as parameter.
Member functions will only receive as parameter
a possible second operand.
Let us now see a concrete example :
the operator " += ".
We will proceed to its inner overloading
in the "Complexe" class.
Usually, the " += " operator has
the following semantics :
" add to z1 the value of z2 ".
Unlike the operator " + " which we have
discussed previously
and was tasked to create a new
"Complexe"
from these two existing complex numbers
(by summing them),
the operator " += " will modify
its first operand.
As we can see, the " += " operator we have
chosen as example
is an operator very close to the
objects of the "Complexe" class;
indeed it has to modify their
content.
In such a case, we usually resort
to an inner overloading.
This is translated into the following code.
The operator " += " is thus defined as
a member function of the "Complexe" class.
Its only argument is the
second operand.
For the purpose of readability, we will
place the definition outside the class.
However, this is not
mandatory.
The definition can be written like this :
To the attribute "x" of the current
object (that is, the first operand),
we will add the value of the attribute "x"
of the second operand.
We will do the same
for the second attribute.
Now, we know how to define
the operator " += "
by using the inner overloading.
Now, we are wondering :
How can we define the operators " += " and
" + " one with the other.
The fundamental idea is to establish a
semantic link between the two.
This link exists anyway, and we would
like to set it up
so that our way to add complex numbers
remains coherent from one
operator to the other.
By nature, the operator " += " requires les
processing that its " + " counterpart;
indeed it does not create any
new complex number.
It is rather natural to define the more
demanding according to the less demanding
rather than the opposite. This is
what we will do now.
In order to understand the body of the
"operator+" member function redefined through " += "
in the way we have proposed here, we
will use a simple example.
Let us suppose we have two
complex numbers
c1 and c2
initialized in a certain way.
Now, we are trying to write the algorithm
to compute the sum of c1 and c2
using the operator " += " for
complex numbers.
We thus wish to compute a new "Complexe",
let us call it "tmp";
it will be the sum of c1 and c2.
Let us ponder on how to compute the
value of "tmp" through the " += " operator.
We realize we simply have to copy
the value of c1 into "tmp"
and apply the operator " += " to "tmp"
in order to add the value of c2.
Ultimately, we obtain, inside "tmp"
the sum of "c1" and "c2" by
proceeding this way.
In order to make sure of this,
let's make a little drawing.
The declaration of this "Complexe" will
correspond to this situation in the memory.
We have a Complex-type
object c1.
Its members " x " and " y " will
be initialized like this.
Similarly,
the object c2 will look like this.
The "tmp" object
first build on this line by copying
from c1,
Its members x and y will initially
be the values copied from c1.
Then, we will apply the
operator " += " to "tmp".
Thus, executing this line,
we will apply the operator "+= ".
Thus, we will add to the " x " of "tmp"
the value of the " x " of c2.
We thus get the value 8.0 here.
Also, we will add to the " y " of "tmp"
the value of the " y " of c2.
Thus the value 5 here.
We can clearly see that the "Complexe"
computed through the operator " += "
corresponds indeed to the sum
of c1 and c2.
This is exactly this algorithm applied
in the version you can see here.
There is one subtlety,
related to this passage by value here.
Indeed, we are using this header
for "operator+",
which is the recommended header
since C++ 2011.
Thus, when we write something
like "c1 + c2"
(thus calling this operator " + " )
what will happen is that the value of
the "Complexe" c1 will be copied into z1.
z1 is an area local to the function
"operator+"
on which we can work and which
will be finally returned.
We thus realize that
z1 plays exactly the role of "tmp".
Therefore, it is pointless to redefine,
in the body of "operator+",
another intermediate variable
in which we could copy
the first operand here.
This role is already fulfilled
by the parameter passed by value here.
In other words, the copy of the first
operand c1,
done in an intermediate variable "tmp"
is realized de facto upon
this  by-value call here.
Naturally, the algorithm described here
is placed inside a function.
Once the computation is complete,
the value will be returned;
this is precisely done here.
We thus get a definition of
the operator " + "
done through  " += ". This definition
is very concise, elegant
and mostly establishes a semantic
link
between the operator " += " and
the operator " + ".
These two operators should not
be defined separately.
Please note that this way to define
the header using a passage by value
lets the modern compiler C++ 2011
to process many an optimization.
By the way, this new version
of the operator " + ",
defined through " += ",
has the edge of sparing us the
trouble of using getters
which were necessary for the
external function
to access the private attributes of "Complexe".
These getters are not necessary anymore
which is good for the encapsulation.
We know that getters running
rampant
can nefarious to the
encapsulation.
Thus, we can use outer overloading
or inner overloading for operators.
In certain cases though, we do not
have a choice as to how to proceed.
For example,
for the printing operator we have
seen in the previous episode,
we can only overload it with
a (non-member) function.
In some other cases, we may choose
between the two.
For example, regarding the operator " + ",
which we have encountered already,
it is perfectly possible to define it
through an inner overloading,
like this.
It is also possible to define it
through an outer overloading;
we have done just that in
the previous examples.
Be careful though,
we have seen that, during the
external definition of an operator,
we could be tempted to use
the "friend".
In the previous examples,
we have always avoided to do so.
Some people could be tempted
to do it nonetheless;
it is a very poor idea, breaking
the encapsulation
and not a good way to proceed.
This leads us to a few recommendations
regarding methodology.
This concerns the choice
between inner overloading
and outer overloading for
a given operator.
First recommendation :
it is usually recommended to
prefer the outer overloading
every time we can do so without
having to resort to the "friend" keyword
in the body of the function.
This means, every time we can
write the operator
through the member functions of the classe's interface
without useless copies.
This was the case with the operator " + " which
we could define
without resorting to the "friend" keyword.
In this case, it is thus recommended
to define this operator
through an outer overloading,
with a function.
On the other hand, if the operator
is close to the class,
as was the case before with the
operator " += ",
which required the instance to
be modified
and thus internal access,
and possibly supplementary
useless copies.
Then, in this case,
it is much better to use
inner overloading.
You now know all the basics
on operator overloading.
In the last episode,
we will discuss the sharper
aspects
and will bring the light on a few
points,
left in the dark until now.