In this episode,
we will bring you a few complements
on the aspects we have left
aside in the previous episodes
on the topic of operator overloading.
We will also give you several
practical advice.
First of all, let us remind you
how to practically tackle this
operator overloading
according your programming
expertise.
Indeed, operator overloading is a rather
difficult matter, for it is technical
and touches the core of the language.
Also, it is not necessarily useful.
At the beginning you therefore,
do without
operator overloading, just like we were
doing until now.
However, this topic is still
rather useful practically
- we hope to have have convinced
you of this fact in the previous videos.
Therefore we naturally advise you to
make good use of this tool.
At the first level of
overloading,
you will bring simple
operations
on those of your classes you wish to refine.
You'll bring these operations (such as addition,
multiplication...) without too much details
and without considering the corresponding
auto-assignment operators (such as += , -= ).
At this first level, you may also overload
the printing operator
so that you may print more easily
the objects of the classes
you have created.
At the next level, you will consider
the auto-assignment operators
( += , *= ), but you will overload them
while ignoring their return value,
thus using "void" as the return type.
Finally, at the last level, you will
overload the operators
while respecting the prototypes used
in the C++ norm.
For example, auto-assignment operators
shall return a reference to
an instance of the class.
This is it for the three levels
of overloading
(four if we include the fact not
to overload anything)
which we let you choose for your
own programs.
Let us examine a few short examples
at the last level
of the previous slide.
In the previous episodes, we have
already seen
the auto-assignment operator " += "
which lets us write
expressions such as "p += q".
On the outer overloading, we
have also seen the addition
which lets us write expressions
such as "r = p + q".
This here is the addition operator.
Similarly, we could define the
auto-subtraction
operator which would let us
write "p -= q".
Considering the subtraction,
we also have the "minus sign".
Here, it is not a subtraction
but the additive inverse.
For example, if we write "r = -p" it
is also an operator " - "
which will be internally overloaded
and which does not take arguments.
There is no second argument
to this operator.
This is called an "unary operator".
We have also seen the printing
operator
which lets us prints the instances
of our classes
the same way we would
print a double or an int.
We have also seen,
regarding the outer multiplication,
the left multiplication, by an
element of another class.
For example, here, " p " and " q " are
elements of class,
such as complex numbers.
However, here, " x " is an element
of another class
or a basic-type variable.
For example, we used a double here.
We could have, internally, a
multiplication
by one of these other types.
For a complex number " p ",
we could write "p *= x " where x is a double.
Here yet another example : we
could use the " == " operator
and write " p == q ".
In this case, do not forget to overload
tthe " != " [not equal] operator aswell
since it is closely tied to the " == " operator.
Therefore, define one with the other.
We could also use comparison
operators.
For example, we could write
" p < q ".
Here aswell, do not forget to define
the operator "less or equal to"
and, the same goes for the operators
"greater than" and "greater or equal to".
Thus, you will first define one
of the four operators and write the three others
out of the previously defined one.
Thus, we ensure the semantic integrity,
this means that the four operators
will function correctly together.
A few more examples, here with
the auto-increment operator
such as " ++p " with this instruction.
Now, we will discuss the
following issues :
Why have we added a "const" to the
retun type of the addition?
Why have we chosen this return type
for the printing operator?
What is the correct return type for the
auto-assignment operator such as " += ".
Why is there a reference to a class
instance here?
Ultimately, we will offer a few
practical advice
and will go back to the assignment
operator " = ".
Let us begin with the return type of,
for example, the addition operator.
Why have we added a "const"
to the return type of this operator.
Be reminded that this operator
lets us write expressions
such as " z3 = z1 + z2".
Clearly, the return type is thus
a complex number.
Why the "const" then?
The reason is not to permit expressions
such as "++(z1 + z2)"
(which contains the call to
operator+ (z1, z2) ).
Thus, this is indeed the return type
of the operator.
Then, we could imagine writing
something like this,
incrementing this return value.
What sense would it have to
do this?
What sense would it have to increment
the addition of z1 and z2?
The result of the addition of z1 and z2
is a result, a constant.
Therefore, we cannot increment it.
This is precisely in order to
prevent this kind of instructions
that we add the const to the return
type.
Thus, we prevent to write on
the left side of the " = " expression.
For example, without the "const",
"z1 + z2" would be a complex number
which we can put on the left
side of an equal sign.
Here aswell, this kind of expression
has no sense at all.
Thus, to prevent it to be placed
on this sign of the equal sign,
we define the return type as a
"const complexe",
that is, a complex number we cannot
modify.
The result of an addition of this
complex number.
We cannot modify the result of
an addition.
Second point :
Now, why does the printing operator
return an "ostream&" ?
Let us look, for example, a very
standard printing.
For a complex number " z1 " we would
write it like this :
" cout << z1 << endl ".
Let us take this expression and
call it " A ".
This line is thus of the kind " A << endl ".
This is indeed a call to the
printing operator :
" operator<< (A, endl) ".
Now, if we rewrite "A" for what it is,
which means " cout << z1",
the expression " cout << z1 << endl "
is equivalent to "operator<< "
where the first argument is the
result of "cout << z1 "
and the second  argument is "endl".
But this "cout << z1 "
is itself a call to the printing operator
with "cout" and " z1 ".
Thus, "cout << z1 << endl " is equivalent
to the call :
printing operator of printing operator
on "cout" and " z1 "
and then endl.
Here, we see that the return type
of " operator<< (cout, z1) "
is passed as the first argument
of  a " << " operator.
Therefore, this expression here must
be of the same type as the first argument
of the " << " operator.
All this expression must be of
the "ostream&" type.
This is why the return value of the
printing operator must be "ostream&"
so that we can reuse it in a
second call
or even a third one.
If you had used "void" as the
return type
you can never do successive calls.
Indeed, if you had used "void"
as the return type,
you could not write expressions
such as
"cout << z1 << endl ".
This second " << " could not
resolve
since the first expression here would
return a "void"
which means you will end up with
something like "void" followed by "endl";
this makes no sense at all.
It is thus in order to chain the
calls to the printing operator
that this printing operator shall return
a type compatible with its
first argument.
This is this a stream in which
we can write
an "ostream" passed by reference,
an "ostream&".
Third complement : what is the
return type for the auto-assignment operators
such as the operator "+=",
If we write something like
"z1 += z2",
remember that this is equivalent
to the call
" z1.operator+= (z2) ".
We see that this call is autonomous;
there is no expression before it.
We have no written something
like " z1 = z1.operator+= (z2).
It is precisely because we do not
write this
that we have advised you, at the first
level of overloading .
to simply use "void" as the return type.
This corresponds to the first
level of overloading
we have talked about in
the introduction.
However, let it be known
that, in C++,
every expression both "does something"
and "has a value", aswell.
For example, if we have an expression,
we may very well white
" x = this expression ".
This means that we can very well
write what we have suggested before :
" z3 = (z1 += z2) ".
Here, the expression " z1 += z2 "
does something,
namely, it adds the value of " z2 "
to " z1 ".
However, this expression does
also have a value
and can as be assigned -for example
to " z3 ".
So, what is this expression's value?
What you need to know is that
the value of the expression " z1 += z2 "
is the value of " z1 " after
the assignment.
This whole expression is therefore
a complex number
since "z1" and "z2" are complex numbers.
This is why, at an advanced level,
the return type of this operator
is not "void" anymore but a
complex number.
However, this complex number
does exist already.
It is "z1" after the result of
this assignment.
This means it is not a new complex number
but at already existing one.
Consequently, we will not create
a new complex number,
but simply pass a reference to
an already existing one.
Those are the reasons why the
more advanced return types
(compatible with the C++ norm)
for auto-assignment operators
are references on instances
(for example a reference on
a complex number).
Now, let us see how to
define this all.
We are writing an inner overloading
in the class of the " += " operator.
Its second argument
is the value we wish to add
to the current instance.
At an advanced level,
it returns a reference on a complex number.
We will use a reference every time
we return an already existing complex number.
It is not a new value.
In this expression here, we
return the value of "z1".
We will define this operator like this :
we begin here with the header.
Then, as we have seen before,
we add the value x of z2 to the
current attribute x.
Then, we add the value y of z2
to the current attribute y.
Now, the difference
is that we have a return type now.
What should we do return?
The current instance!
And what is the current instance?
It is the value stored
in our adress.
Here, "this" is a pointer
on the current instance.
Therefore, " *this " is the value
stored in the current instance.
Here, for example, it means the
value of "z1".
Let us finish with practical
considerations which should be important.
We have already defined the return
type as a reference on a complex number
since this complex number
exists already.
If we had not added the reference,
we would have created a new
complex number,
a copy of an already existing
complex number.
This would be a unnecessary copy.
In a general way, we can give you
the following advice.
Be very thorough when overloading
operators.
Be careful not to do unnecessary copies,
do not burden your code with
useless operations.
Indeed, operators are generally
used very often,
in many an expression and will
be repeated.
Therefore, something poorly
written in some code
as deep as an operator
could lead to globally
important repercussions
on the whole program.
Thus, use references effictively,
and avoid the unnecessary copies
such as this example's.
Here, we have two versions
of the auto-assignment operator.
The standard version, which does
not do any supplementary copies,
is the version we have proposed
in the previous slides.
Here, we have another version
which we will now detail.
This version does between
one and three useless copies.
We are not going to dive into details
but the number of copies depends
on your compiler's options.
Now, let us check this version of
the auto-assignment operator.
First of all, as the return type here,
we have chosen to return a
complex number
instead of a reference to a
complex number.
Then, on the side of
the argument here,
we have also decided to pass
a complex number
instead of a constant
reference.
This means that, when we
have an instruction
such as "z1 += z2"
which corresponds to " z1.operator+= (z2) ",
we have here a passage by value.
This could already imply
a first copy upon the passage
of this argument.
It can be optimized by the compiler,
though it is not certain.
It could thus possibly result in a
first copy here.
Now, regarding the return value here.
If let us say we wish to use this return value,
this means that we will write
an expression such as
" z3 = (z1 += z2) ".
Here, because of the return value,
a new complex number will be
created since we are not using a reference.
This means another copy
will be created.
Now, let us analyse the body of
the definition of this operator.
Since we have decided to return
a complex number here,
we need to declare it internally
so that we can return it.
The remaining operations here
are as usual
but in order to return a complex number,
we wish to return the current instance.
Thus we will create here a
third copy.
We copy the current instance.
Remember that this is the content pointed
by the pointer "this".
This is indeed the value of the current
instance which we copy here into "z3".
Those are the three possible copies.
Some of these copies may or may not
be optinized by your compiler.
However, in the better version here
we pass firstly by a constant reference.
This means we do not have any copy here,
but a reference on " z2 "
which is passed directly;
thus no copy.
Similarly, regarding the return,
we do not have any copy either.
Indeed, we have passed the
reference to the current instance.
Internally, we have not declared
any supplementary;
thus, we do not have this
third copy either.
To sum up :
be very careful when overloading
operators.
Now, we would like to conclude this video
on the complements about
operator overloading
by going back to a rather
particular case :
the assignment operator " = ".
This operator, which used, for example,
every time we write " a = b " or " z1 = z2 ",
is a little peculiar
since it is provided by default
for all the classes.
It is a "universal operator".
[The only one, actually.]
You do not have to redefine it;
it already exists for all the classes
you can create.
As we have already said
on the videos on the copy
construction and the destruction,
its possible redefinition, if you need this
operator,
is closely tied to the redefinition
of the copy constructor.
The difference between the copy
construction and the assignment
is that the copy construction
is a construction.
It occurs during an initialization.
On the other hand, the assignment
occurs on already existing instances.
Just like the copy constructor and
the destructor,
its default version does a shallow copy.
We will go back to this
notion of shallow copy vs deep copy
in the next lessons.
However, this shallow copy is sufficient
in most cases,
In most cases, you will not need
to redefine
this assignment operator.
However, it can sometimes be
necessary to plainly suppress
this assignment operator.
Let's assume we have to deal
with a huge class.
Such a class would trigger,
whenever an instance
is created, the usage of a lot
of memory.
Therefore, we do not wish for these
instances to be copiables.
One instance of this class
is plenty sufficient,
and we therefore wish to avoid
dealing with its copies.
To that end, we will suppress the
assignment operator
which is called "operator=".
We will thus use a syntax
we have already encountered when
we were suppressing the copy constructor.
Here is its prototype,
in the class (since
it is an inner overloading).
Behind this prototype, we will
add " =delete ".
This will thus prevent any assignment
between instances
of this huge class.
Now that we are here,
take a look
at the prototype of this
assignment operator.
Of course, it is called "operator=".
It is called when we are dealing with
expressions such as " a = b ".
Let us look at the corresponding call.
it is "a.operator= "
-- it is an inner overloading.
We cannot use outer overloading for
the assignment operator.
"a.operator=(b) ":
we are taking a parameter of the
same type as " a ".
Consequently, we will have the same class
as the one in which we are currently
overloading this operator.
In order to avoid a copy, we will
pass the parameter by constant reference.
In C++, it is perfectly valid to write
things such as
" a = b = c ".
In plain words, a = the result of ( b = c ).
Therefore, the expression (b = c) has
itself a return value
which is the value of "b" after the assignment,
that is, the value of "c".
Its type is, just like for " += " or " -=",
the very type of the class
in which we are currently
overloading this operator.
For the same reasons, the return
value will be passed by reference aswell
in order to avoid supplementary copies.
Finally, we have said that it was not
necessary to redefine this operator.
In the vast majority of cases,
the default one will be enough.
However, if you were to redefine
this operator,
we advise you to follow this method
in C++ 2011 :
We will use a function called "swap".
The "swap" function lets us...
swap two arguments.
Therefore, "swap(a, b)" will swap the
values of "a" and "b".
In other words, "a" will contain
the value of "b",
and "b" will contain the value "a".
You should redefine this "swap" function
for your class.
For example, in our class,
we have the attributes "X" and "Y" of
the types "x" and "y".
We will thus proceed like this :
The "swap" function does not return anything.
Its parameters are two instances of our class.
Since these arguments will be swapped
(thus modified)
we will naturally pass them by reference.
For exemple, we could use the "swap" function
provided by the "utility "library.
At the beginning our program, we would
thus add " #include utility"
in order to use this "swap" function
in order to swap the attributes "x"
of the instances "a" and "b",
the attributes "y" of the
instances "a" and "b",
and so on for all the attributes we
wish to swam.
Now on to the schema we suggest
for the redefinition of
the assignment operator.
It is a little different because of
optimizations reasons in C++ 2011.
These reasons stretch beyond this
course's frame but they allow the compiler
to either avoid the creation of copies
or even to use a so-called move.
Let us not talk about it for now.
This is simply a more advanced
optimization reason.
Here, there is indeed a passing
by value.
We will use this "swap" function
to swap the content
of the current instance with
the content of this variabe here,
which is the parameter
of the assignment operator
we are currently redefining.
Here, all is well: we are writing "a = b",
which resorts to a "swap"
between "a" (which is the current
instance since it is "a.operator= (b),
and " *this " plays the role of "a"),
and "source" which is either a copy
or a move of "b".
Now, we swap these two values.
Ultimately, we have indeed
stored the value of "b" into "a".
Be wary though, this swap is done
with the local copy "source".
This means that what happens is not the
value of "a" being stored inside "b",
but the value of "a" being stored inside "source",
where "source" is where we have copied "b".
Therefore we shall not be polluting "b".
Finally, for the same reasons as for the
operator +=,
we return here a reference on the
current instance.
Indeed, we may very well write things
like "c = a = b".
Voilà! This concludes this
last video sequence,
rather advanced and technical we daresay,
on all the complements
we wished to share on this
sharp topic
of "operator overloading".