In this second week
of our sanitation course
we presented sanitation products,
the five functional groups
of the sanitation chain,
and finally, a first introduction
to different sanitation technologies.
The primary input products
are those that are, for example,
generated by us human beings,
such as urine or feces.
Secondary output products
are those that are generated
as a function of storage
or treatment of different products.
Example, compost or pit humus.
We also provided an overview
of the different terminology
that we use in sanitation
differentiating between
blackwater and greywater
and between blackwater,
brownwater, and excreta,
and what is often confused, the difference
between urine, feces, and excreta.
We then went on to propose
the five functional groups
used to categorize sanitation technologies
starting in red on the bottom
with the user interface,
going on to the collection
and storage in orange,
the conveyance in yellow,
the semi-centralized treatment in green,
and finally, the use and disposal
of the treated waste.
In the second part of this week,
we've provided an overview
of different technologies,
starting with the user interface or toilet
and we showed a number of different
toilets that are used around the world --
dry toilets, UDDTs, urinals
or pour flush toilets.
We then went on to present different
collection and storage technologies
as the one shown here, the single
ventilated improved pit on the left,
or the double ventilated improved pit,
VIP, on the right.
We also presented some of the more
advanced anaerobic treatment technologies
such as the biogas reactor,
shown on the left,
or the septic tank, shown on the right.
Finally, we also provided an overview
of different transport
and conveyance technologies
ranging from the non-sewered,
motorized emptying and transport
shown here on the left,
to simplified sewers or sewers in general,
like the one shown here in Nepal.
Next week we'll be looking
at different sanitation systems
and providing an overview
of sanitation technologies, part two.