The goals of this module
are to first, know what the
five functional groups are;
secondly, to understand why
we use functional groups
for sanitation system planning;
and finally, to be able to identify
what functional groups some simple
technologies belong to.
Before we begin on functional groups,
let's quickly review what a system is.
A system is a set of things working
together as parts of a mechanism
or an interconnecting network;
a complex whole.
Building a complex whole requires
a way of organizing all of the parts
so that you're not putting the pieces
out of order or using more pieces than you
actually need.
Let's start with the example
of a computer.
First, you need some way to control it:
a mouse or a keyboard.
Then you need some way to see the output.
There's a variety of options here.
There needs to be some way
to power the computer.
And of course, some way to store
and process the information.
These categories could also be called
functional groups.
They help us to categorize the components
so that we include all the necessary parts
but don't end up with too many
that aren't necessary.
The same is true with the functional
groups for sanitation planning.
The first of the five functional groups
that we will discuss is called the
user interface.
In this, and subsequent lectures, we will
always use the same color for each of the
functional groups.
The user interface in our lectures
will always be red.
The user interface, just as in our
computer example, is how you
physically interact with the system.
It is where the products enter the system
so basically, the toilet.
But there are many different types
of toilets.
You can see five examples of different
toilets here.
Some use water, some do not; but because
they all serve the same function they are
all categorized into the user interface
functional group.
The collection and storage functional
group contains all the technologies that
collect and store the products that enter
into the sanitation system at the user
interface.
A simple pit latrine is an example of a
technology from this functional group.
It stores the excreta and the toilet paper
and doesn't do anything else.
It doesn't provide any type of treatment,
for example.
It just collects and stores.
One of the most important but least
considered functional groups is the
conveyance group.
Technologies in this category are
responsible for the movement of products.
The trucks that move fecal sludge that we
saw in the last module on products will
belong to this functional group.
Big sewers that run beneath
cities and transport black water
are another example.
The fourth functional group is where most
of the treatment takes place.
It is important to remember that a system
may include two or more technologies
from the same functional group;
or on the other hand, maybe none.
Depending on the number and composition
of the products that enter the system
several parallel or sequential
technologies may be required
from this treatment functional group.
Treatment for sludge and effluent
for example would be parallel treatment
technologies that would be required.
The final functional group is called
Use or Disposal.
This is a special functional group
because it includes not just technologies
but also processes or actions.
The application of urine, for example,
after it has been stored and hydrenized
can be applied as a liquid fertilizer
to crops.
The application of urine therefore
would be considered as part
of this functional group.
Let's look at a really simple system
and see how the functional groups
can be used to help explain
what's going on.
In rural areas of low-income countries
where there is little water but a lot
of space, a simple squatting slab
like this one can be placed over
a deep pit.
The slab is the user interface and the
pit, as you can see being built here,
is a technology from the collection
and storage functional group.
This simple system requires technology
from only two functional groups.
The sanitation system that exists across
most of Europe consists of a flush toilet
connected to a sewer; the sewer
transports the black water to a waste
water treatment plant where it is treated
to an acceptable quality before it is
discharged.
Here we can see that the system requires
a combination of technologies from three
different functional groups:
User interface, conveyance, and treatment.
What about the dense urban areas
of low-income countries?
How many functional groups would
be needed to design a sanitation system
here?
In fact, there's no single answer
to this question, as there are many
different factors and constraints
that need to be considered
on a case-by-case basis.
The rest of this course will focus on
thinking about the challenges and possible
solutions for urban areas
in low-income countries.
In fact, the sanitation systems required
can become quite complex so the
functional groups will become very useful
in helping us to organize and select the
technologies that will be needed
to build a complete system.
Here we can see a schematic of a dense
area with different technologies in place.
The technologies are color-coded to match
the functional groups that they came from.
First, you can see a pour-flush squatting
slab.
The black water from here flows into a
septic tank.
It is collected and stored until it can be
transported by the pump truck
to the fecal sludge treatment plant.
Once the sludge has been treated,
it can be mixed into soil to improve
the quality and potentially be used
in agriculture.
This is just one possible design, but it
demonstrates a system that includes
technologies from each of the functional
groups and illustrates how they can be
put together.
So, to summarize, we build our sanitation
system using technologies from five
different functional groups, but not every
system requires a technology from each
functional group.
The dense urban areas in low-income
countries are complex and, as such, there
is no strict formula for how to design
them, but we can use functional groups
to help organize and plan an appropriate
system based on the products
and technologies that we have available.
The next module will introduce you
to the different technologies that belong
in each of the functional groups.