Hello and welcome
to the second module
on conveyance
and transport technologies.
In the last presentation,
we took a closer look
at container based technologies
and got a glimpse into
manual and motorized emptying
of on-site sanitation systems.
We will now look at
the different types of sewer systems.
We distinguish between
three categories of sewer systems.
The simplified sewer system, or so-called
shallow or condominial sewer system,
the solids-free sewer system, or so-called
settled or small-bore sewer system,
and the conventional
gravity sewer system.
Basically, the differences
between the three systems
can be summarized
in terms of the size,
the depth,
and the slope of the pipes.
Let's have a closer look
at these three systems.
The best known system
is the conventional gravity sewer.
Conventional gravity sewers
are large networks of underground pipes
that convey black water,
gray water, in many cases stormwater,
from the houses
to the wastewater treatment plant,
using gravity and often pumping stations.
The sewer is designed so that
it maintains self-cleansing velocity,
which means guaranteeing a flow that will
not allow particles to accumulate.
Access manholes are placed
at set intervals above the sewer
at pipe intersections,
and at changes in pipeline direction.
When the sewer
also conveys storm water,
which is known as combined sewer,
sewer overflows are required
to avoid hydraulics charge
of the treatment plant.
However, nowadays, a separate
drainage system for rainwater,
or local retention and infiltration,
are recommended instead,
which leads to cheaper
and more efficient systems.
Conventional sewers involve
less maintenance than the other systems
but are very expensive
and require major works,
like shown here in Egypt.
The costs can reach often more than 60%
of the cost of the entire sanitary systems,
the treatment plant included.
Operational costs may be high as well,
depending on the pumping requirements.
For this reason, it is often
a too expensive
and capital intensive option
for low income contexts.
Wherever possible, simplified sewer
systems should be preferred,
as it is 20% to 50% less expensive
than conventional sewers
and much easier to implement.
A simplified sewer
describes a sewage network
that is constructed
using smaller diameter pipes
laid at a shallower depth,
and at a flatter gradient
than conventional sewers.
Simplified sewer can be installed
where there are no heavy traffic loads,
for example within a condominium,
in narrow allies, or at or near sidewalks.
Thus, they allow
for a more flexible design at lower costs.
Some of the main differences
with conventional sewers
are the minimum depth, which is
about 70cm instead of 80cm,
the minimum gradient,
which is about 0.5% instead of 1%,
and the minimum diameter of the pipes,
which is about 100mm
instead of 200mm to 300mm.
Another important difference
is that expensive manholes
are unnecessary.
Instead, simple inspection chambers,
or clean-outs, are sufficient.
Inspection boxes are also
built for each house connection.
Simplified sewers are especially
appropriate for dense urban areas
where space for
on-site technologies is limited,
such as in this picture.
The drawback of the lower gradient
and diameter of the pipes
is that repairs and removal
of blockages are more frequent.
However, this can be done
easily by locals at little cost.
Such a system can be
operated by the community itself.
It is important that the users
avoid disposing trash
or other solids into the system.
In all cases, occasional flashing is
recommended to ensure against blockages.
The last option is the solids-free sewer system.
As its name indicates,
the specificity of the system
is that solids are separated
before entering the sewer system itself.
This is done at house level.
For example,
with single chamber septic tanks.
Removing the solids dramatically reduces
the risk of deposition and plugging.
Thus, there is no need for a minimum
flow velocity and for a minimum slope.
This system
can even bear negative slopes,
as long as the downstream end
is lower then the upstream end.
A minimum diameter of 75 mm
is required to facilitate cleaning.
Storm water must be
excluded in this system.
The critical point is, of course,
is not to let solids in.
For that purpose, it is very important
that the interceptors
are regularly de-sludged.
Solids-free sewers
are the least expensive
of all sewer systems.
However, it requires good training
and acceptance by the users.
Otherwise, the risk of failure is high.
The choice of the appropriate sewer system
is a trade off between the price
and the maintenance requirements.
Conventional sewers
lead to little maintenance problems.
However, the price is often prohibitive.
On the other hand,
simplified and solids-free sewers
are much less expensive,
but requires more inputs from the users.
In summary,
the conveyance technology choice
generally depends
on the following factors:
The type and quantity
of product to be transported,
the distance to cover,
the accessibility,
topography,
soil and groundwater characteristics,
the financial resources,
the availability of service providers,
and management considerations.
To conclude this module
on conveyance technologies,
it is important to know that
if sewer systems are often seen
as the gold standard target to reach,
it does not always make sense
to use water to convey excreta in sewers,
especially in water scarce areas.
Non-sewered systems
are sometimes the best option.
In the next module, Chistoph Luthi
will sum up the learnings from the week.
As for me, I will join you again
for the treatment technologies.
See you then.