Hello.
First video of our first week
of the course, the first video in a long
series that will bring us, during
twelve weeks, to explore African cities.
We begin the course, this week, with Mali.
Welcome to the participants of Bamako.
To begin,
first off, some figures on the
urban population of the world.
Today, in the world, we have more than
50% of people that are urban dwellers.
But, pay particular attention,
it's a statistic reality that
is not the same on all continents.
And particularly, the African continent is
one of the least urbanized continents
since the figures for 2011 give us less
than 40% of people in Africa who
are urban dwellers.
We must keep going down since,
if we look by large African regions
we see that we have notable differences
between East Africa
which is urbanized at 23.7%
and North Africa which is
at more than 50%.
So, there also, we have enormous disparities
and if we take examples
of countries we come across Ethiopia,
17%, while the Ivory Coast
is at more than 50, like all the
countries of North Africa.
So we see that, behind
this figure of 50%
we have realities that are extremely
different and differentiated.
Before we
jump in, week after week, in the detailed
content of the
course, we are going to show major challenges of
urbanization in Africa.
We will try to give some answers.
We will address the issue
of population increase.
We will address the question of
economic development, urbanization
versus development.
We will address, of course, the issue of
climate change.
We will also address the question
of urban periphery.
And finally, we will address the question of
generalized mobility.
So we have, at the same time,
an urgency since the
number of people is increasing extremely
rapidly, so we must
confront this development,
this evolution of the
population, and then, at the same time,
another challenge is that
we find ourselves
in the situation of an urbanization without
necessarily an economic development.
We know that the model of European cities,
particularly, whether in
the secondary or tertiary, we know
that the development of
the urbanization happened
with an economic development.
We find ourselves, in a
number of African cities,
there are of course exceptions,
all the cities
are not the same, but we have
figures where we can find
an urbanization without any
economic development.
The next challenge, the question
of climate change.
Very in fashion, certainly, but it means
that at the environmental level,
at the climate level, we have major
changes that are expected
and so, the cities will have to either
confront these changes or not.
But it's a new challenge, and it's
without a doubt
one of the most important challenges
today for the African city.
A little quiz before we continue.
How many more people will live in
African cities in the
next 20 years? Answer one,
answer two, answer three.
Answer one, 250 million
more urban dwellers.
Answer two, 150 million.
And answer three, 400 million.
Well done, the answer
is 250 million. Indeed, there are now approximately,
in 2011, 610 million urban dwellers, in 2035
there will be 250 million
more, approximately 860 million urban
dwellers in all of Africa.
Why this question?
This means that the challenge of
urban peripheries will be great since
these extra 250 million city dwellers,
in the next couple of years,
will not all live in the city center, will not
all increase the density in the city
but they will continue to make the city
less dense, will continue to spread out
more and more in the peripheries.
And so the challenge is great.
Finally, the last challenge which we
must confront, will be the issue
of generalized mobility.
Actually, increasingly, people are
mobile, people move and that poses
a certain number of questions,
we are not going to say
problems but rather questions
about the way in which
we are going to plan the city
in the years to come.
There you have it, we are wrapping up our
short introduction by a view of Brazzaville.
I leave you to get familiar with the program
in the next 12 weeks on the Coursera website.
And as for me, I'll see you in
next video.