The high growth rates
that we see in the southern countries
are generally accompanied
by a strong migration
of the inhabitants living in rural areas
toward urban ones.
A correlation exists between poverty
and the proportion of rural populations,
and the speed of urbanization.
The longer I am in a poor country,
the more rural the country is,
the higher the urbanization rate.
This rapid urbanization in
the South, that we find mainly
in the South, as we said, is going to
create a certain number of problems
that we can list, and in particular,
the environmental degradation,
widespread informality,
an extremely strong spatial segregation
that leads to a fragmentation
of the territories,
public politics that we could qualify
as ineffective, a lack
of correlation at once
between city-dwellers' needs
and infrastructures,
and a weakly redistributive economy,
which is to say that it is an
economy that cannot
reach all the population strata.
We can view this urbanization in a
negative way, which is
what we just did by listing like that
all its main problems,
but we can also, today, the benefits
of urbanization, the potential
that can be found behind
this rapid urbanization.
One of the first aspects, is the question
of population concentration.
Which is to say that it opens
a range of possibilities, provides
opportunities to find a job,
to do business.
The more people, the more shoppers,
the wider the catchment area,
the more commercial possibilities.
Which doesn't mean that
it is always possible,
but we increase the chances
of being to do business.
Another thing we see in these questions
of rapid and accelerated
urbanization, is that public powers
don't always follow,
and new forms of democracies
develop, here and there,
participatory democracies that can
lead to participatory budgets.
Another important potential of
urbanization, is that,
even if the people's needs
are much greater than
the infrastructures at their
disposal in the city,
in relation to those in rural
areas, these proportions
are extremely important.
That means that, even if it is lacking
infrastructures, these are
eminently greater than those in rural areas
which gives a definite advantage, an
incredible potential of city versus country.
We can then imagine,
as well, that some forms
of decentralization, which accompany
these urbanization processes,
may eventually offer some
significant results.
So, for now, it is wishful thinking
that the decentralization would effectively
be put in place in all countries, giving
public authorities managerial autonomy.
And even if we have this, from a
legal standpoint, these communities
have the responsibilities
but not the means to implement
such reponsibilities.
So there are, for now, very few cities,
very few countries, that have
really implemented the
decentralization process.
The last important potential point of
urbanization is the question of informality.
We have seen it just now as a negative
but informality can also be seen
as an extremely positive given, because
at the end of the day, it is a type
of redistribution of an
economy, a way to manage
a territory, a city, which
are extremely different within
a formal framework, but
which hold within them,
equally, a potential
that is extremely important and
extremely interesting.
And without a doubt, we should
move much further
in the analysis of informality
to see how it is distilled
almost everywhere, that it is not only
the prerogative of the poorest,
but that we also find them in every
population strata.
Our recent studies even showed
exactly the contrary, which is,
finally, that informality is confined
to the richest, who can do without
laws, while the poorest, still
demand their right to
a legal framework and the security
that this legal framework can provide.
Here we have, in a few words, outlined
the questions of urbanization
in the world, the questions of urbanization
in Africa, with some points.
We must take away from this
one important thing,
which is that we have contexts that
are extremely different, both
between continents, and even
within the African continent;
between East Africa
and North Africa we have trends
in urbanization that are not at all
the same, and even within
these different regions,
geographical subregions in Africa,
we have countries that
are not similar, and within
these countries
we have extremely urban regions,
and extremely rural regions.
So, we have to be wary
of big numbers,
which offer indications, but we must
then reach down to the level
of the city, to the level of the
region, to truly understand
and identify the mechanisms
underlying this urbanization.