Urbanization is a process of
multidimensional changes
and centuries-old continuums which
affect the world even today.
Why multidimensional?
Because the changes are at once
spatial, demographic, economic,
cultural or even infracultural.
In the chart on the right we can
see the rates of urbanization.
For all countries, we can begin
with the middle column, the
one which most interests us
because it shows the current situation,
even though it dates back to 2010.
In the entire world we are
approximately 52% urban.
This means that one of every two people
who lives on the Earth lives in a city.
Africa and Asia are two continents
with extremely low levels
of urbanization, a bit behind
when compared to others.
And the least developed countries are
also those which are least urbanized.
On the contrary, Europe, whose urbanization
process is several centuries old,
is urbanized to an impressive degree.
So, this urbanization has not
played itself out
uniformly across the planet.
We have selected some images,
all African, to show how we have
extremely different contexts
if we are in the North or South
of the Sahara, if we are in
the Sahel or the tropics,
in Southern Africa or in Equatorial Africa.
So, when we talk of the process of
urbanization, we have the impression of
a sort of groundswell which is
the same everywhere, so we must
take into account the fact that
we have extremely different contexts.
So, any gathering of data, by region,
by continent, reveals realities
which are extremely differentiated
within each country, even within
each of the regions within
the different countries.
We can see, if we look again at the chart
in a slightly different way,
the percentages of urban
populations in 2011.
We can see that we have,
in North America,
in Europe and in Latin America,
very high levels, since here,
in North America, we are
at slightly more than 80%.
If we look at the four largest continents:
Oceania, North America,
Latin America and Europe, we are,
in all cases, at over 70%.
Looking at the whole world,
the limit is a bit over 50%.
And then, in Asia and Africa, we see that,
even if Asia slightly
surpasses Africa, one is,
roughly speaking, at less
than 50%, closer to 40% for Africa,
and globally 45% for Asia.
Let's look now at a few numbers
specific to Africa, from 2010.
Using the classical division of Africa into
East, Central, North, South and West,
we have a population of
slightly more than a billion.
And of that billion, 413 million,
or 40%, are urban.
We can also see that between
a very slightly urbanized East Africa,
and an extremely urbanized South,
there are enormous
regional disparities.
Finally, we find North Africa nearing
the world's average.
Still, the rate of urbanization
as it relates to global rates.
So here we are at
this column, here.
We have seen it surpass 50%,
to 52%, and then
in the future--these are, of course,
projections--by 2050 it should be
around 70%. So, it continues
with a curve like this,
and the rate of urbanization should not
weaken but instead continue.
In Africa, we are at about 40%, here.
We begin very, very low, and
then we must catch up slowly.
In other words the
differential, in 2050,
will be clearly less significant
than in 1950. So, in one century
the gap between the world average and
the African average has been reduced.
This means that there will be an accelerated
process of urbanization in Africa.
The rates of urbanization, once again
by region, in function of years.
If we look at the 1970's, we can see
besides Southern Africa, already
rather strongly urbanized,
based on it having a higher
percentage, in 1970,
than the combined percentages
of all of the rest of Africa in 2010.
The others, East Africa,
for example, which has a
very, very weak proportion,
roughly averaging
at around 20-plus percent in 1970.
In 2000, things are very different.
This is the current situation,
with Africa at 40% and with relatively
proportional growth, more or less,
across all regions.
The projections for 2050,
this time at 61.6%--this based
on the data of 2009
projected against 2050, but one
can see that it will be close--
besides East Africa which
will not have caught up,
but will be around 60-70%
of the territorial group.
The annual growth rate
is extremely important.
We can see this rate at 6%
in 1965, 1970, in East
and Central Africa,
and these rates will shoot up
rather spectacularly.
If we look at the whole of Africa,
we begin with a rate of
4.65, which falls
as low as 2.15. This number
is where we end up.
This is to say that the growth rate
is increasingly weakened
and will weaken further.
By comparison, today
we find ourselves,
at roughly 3.31, which is
an extremely elevated rate
in relation to those one might find
in Europe, where the
rate is well below 1%.
Another phenomenon, when it
comes to the size of cities,
is that urbanization is not
the same everywhere.
Look at the numbers from 2010
for Sub-Saharan Africa.
Finally, for the whole of Africa
we see more or less the same
proportions, were it not for the fact
that instead of two agglomerations,
Lagos and Kinshasa, with more
than 10 million inhabitants,
3 million for the whole of Africa,
there is Cairo, which has
come into play.
What is interesting to see, is not
the different absolute numbers,
this holds little interest for us,
but it is the percentages
of urban population.
Which is to say that,
today, in Africa,
57% of the population
---at least in 2010---
57% of the urban African
population lives in cities of
fewer than 500,000 inhabitants,
which we call intermediate cities.
Another very important number,
this 26%, which is to say that
26% of the urban African
population lives in cities
of 1-5 million inhabitants.
So, we can see very clearly
that between the two
we have the whole,
the very, very large
majority of urbanites,
and that the others
are very residual numbers,
because one has 17% in
other types of cities.
Therefore our task, as planners,
should be focused on,
above everything else
these intermediate cities of
fewer than 500,000 inhabitants,
so numerous that we have no
data here, which is very important,
and the cities, which are often capitals,
of between 1 and 5 million inhabitants.
It is within these two
categories of cities
where the majority
of urbanites reside.
Of course, in a very
media-centered way,
the focus is on the group of cities of
more than 10 million inhabitants.
We hear often of Kinshasa
or Lagos, and also of Cairo,
but in terms of percentage of
the urban African population
which actually resides there,
this is relatively low.
So to effect change, it must
be focused on those cities of
1-5 million inhabitants, and
those of fewer than 500,000.
The urban population of
Sub-Saharan Africa by city size.
It is the same schematic
we just spoke of, except
we are using a temporal perspective,
between 1990 and 2025. We realize
that in intermediate cities,
those with fewer than
500,000 inhabitants,
their proportion, or let's say
their relative importance
will clearly diminish,
from 57% to 43%,
So this is where they
become less important.
At the same time we find cities with
more than 10 million inhabitants
where, still, there is great ambiguity
because all it takes is to
add one city, and because
we go from two to three,
the proportions increase,
and the numbers grow larger.
We can also see that
in cities of 5-10 million,
all it takes is one city moving up a
category and then we lose one.
This likewise diminishes the number
of inhabitants from the next category.
So we can roughly say
that it does not move much.
It will continue. Let's take
for example the cities of
5-10 million or more,
who will continue to
increase in size, little by little,
gently, but with certainty.
So we have this curve.
And then we realize that,
in the end it is within these
cites of 1-5 million inhabitants
where the gap between 1990
and 2025 will gradually increase.
It is within this category of cities,
those with 1-5 million inhabitants
where we will see the greatest
development of urbanization.
Another important element,
which we will look at
in a moment is
how one looks, on a macro level,
at numbers, at the great
trends of urbanization,
without once mentioning
the living conditions in new
and future urban centers.
To offer an example, in 1900--
no, excuse me, in 2000,
the UN-Habitat gave the figure
that 32% of the world's population
lives in slums, within
developing countries 43%,
and in the category of
less-developed countries,
78% of inhabitants live in slums.
Therefore we have, at the
same time, numbers which
characterize world urbanization,
yet these numbers have
a very different meaning if one
is in the South or the North.
And, as one can easily see
and we'll discuss later,
one of the biggest problems of
this urbanization is the increase
in slums and of the population
who live in shacks.
Very good, this is the end of this first part.
I'll see you in the next video.