As a starting point,
there is the need to plan city development.
Why ?
Because, spontaneously, as some may say,
when alone, a city does not
develop in a rational way.
All the individual strategies and tactics
do not make a city
but a mesh of strategies.
If we want to integrate
the communities, activities,
services, infrastructure within one space,
we have at some point
to plan it so that
it all combines harmoniously.
When planning, there are
some challenges to meet.
First, there is always the same issue
of population growth.
We have to fit into a given space,
which can grow along the way,
an ever-increasing population,
or in some cases,
as seen in Detroit, USA,
a decreasing population,
which has to be managed
just as efficiently,
since a decline
is an issue that must be addressed.
We are here facing an issue
of rather population growth.
Then, it is important preserve resources:
water resources, social resources...
In that respect, an inclusive city
should be able to preserve these.
Services need not only to be developed,
but also planned within a territory.
Basic infrastructure, just as services,
needs to be planned
in the short, medium and long term:
what area, what part of the city
are we going to connect in priority,
whether to services or infrastructure?
The housing issue remains crucial:
where are we going to settle
all the city dwellers?
Activities, jobs,
since, we have seen it,
migrants come mainly
from the rural areas,
with the hope to find a job,
among others reasons.
Also it is easier to find
a job or a trade,
than in rural areas.
Then, there's an environment to preserve,
the city is not hanging in the void,
but is set in a geography with,
most of the time, a hinterland,
an immediate environment,
and one of the biggest challenges
regarding planning,
nowadays, is to deal with
the issue of the urban fringe,
that is to say, the relation between
the city and its immediate environment.
The definition, or the definitions
of planning.
It is defined as a tool used to reach
sustainable development.
For this purpose, we develop a medium
and long-term vision of the territory.
We never look in the short term,
when we want to rationalize
the means to reach the goals.
It allows us to link together the needs
of infrastructure and services with
the growth of the population or
the need of urban sprawl with
environmental protection.
We are going to work
within a limited area.
Planning offers a coordination framework
of public action and, to a lesser extent,
of private action,
for social and economic development.
In this sense, planning is organizing
human action having an impact
on the territory,
providing a framework to development
and mitigating adverse effects.
Here is the basic definition,
a bit long, admittedly,
of urban planning.
Planning is a source of vision or ideal,
or in any case,
a set of goals for the future:
a vision for the future.
This vision, in principle,
should be shared by the community.
This community is going to
mobilize around it,
in the best of all words,
because we'll see that it's not that easy.
This vision must be
a source of inspiration.
It means that it must lead projects,
give rise to other projects.
It must be both ambitious and realistic.
We have to, somehow, stir imagination,
since it is a long term vision,
it is an ideal, a goal to reach but,
we have to be extremely pragmatic
and realistic,
and have a vision
that everyone understands.
One of the goals of this planning,
is the good management of
urban development.
And this management features,
in principle,
prevention of or fight against poverty,
acceptable living standards,
well connected districts,
sustainability at the social,
and environmental and economic level.
There is a number of criteria,
that lead to good management.
And the planning is here to set up
this good urban management.
It is one of its purposes.
Another purpose, today, is
the strategic planning.
It's a tautology to me:
it is hard to imagine, indeed,
a form of planning that is not strategic.
What we want to do, is to see
how we are going to design
not just a plan, because planning
is not just about a plan;
its outcome is not the mere drawing
of a plan, but planning
is by definition strategic,
with our main goals included in it.
These goals are then turned into
realities on the ground,
into projects, into public policies,
urban policies,
a string of things,
but first and foremost,
we have to plan the strategy
for the future of cities.
This entails the need to
adapt to the context.
This idea will keep coming up,
which is natural, since
we believe from the start
that there isn't just one African city,
but several African cities.
The idea is that planning
should match a specific context.
Therefore there is not one type of
urban planning but several.
What we are trying to find out today,
are the methods
that we would put in place, everywhere,
and that would lead us
to different types planning,
depending on the contexts.
We are now going to take a look
at the major fields included in planning.
The first one being,
of course, the economy.
The economy, wide subject,
can be dealt with in different ways:
there are the very pragmatic,
down-to-earth issues of land use planning,
which then allows
the development of an economic activity,
of infrastructure, which also leads
to economic development,
and we could also think of
a certain number
of public policies which would facilitate
the setting up of companies
or make business environment better.
We can also bank on competitiveness
among cities.
These are more macroeconomic issues
or marketing issues.
Another major field:
environment.
We also have several takes on it.
We will not go through all of them.
We will go back to these issues later on,
but it ranges from ecosystem issues,
agricultural issues,
issues concerning the integration
of the city in a more global context.
We could talk about pollution issues,
energy issues and
energy choices
which would make the best of planning.
The issue of transportation:
there are multiple factors as well.
Individual transport, public transport,
the question of transport
as opposed to mobility,
and finally the central issue,
in most cities,
addressing transport for the poorest,
or mobility for the poorest.
Another major field large theme
is the issue of energy.
Then again, we will not go through
the multiple options here,
but we could make an energy assessment,
and the sustainable city would be,
in the end, the city which
consumes less energy.
We also have to think
of the distribution of energy.
In theory, it is not evenly
distributed across the territory.
Finally, the financial aspects.
This issue may be a little more technical
but just as important
as the other fields.
The idea is to spend a whole week
on financial issues.
Financing is about resources,
how to make the best
of financial resources
which can be derived from
management plans.
It means taxes,
or land-use plans,
but we may consider the issues of
taxation as well as
the issues of project creation
and the public-private partnerships.
The financial overlaps economics
but finance is very broad.
Finally, there is the issue of governance.
It is most of the time
at the heart of discussions.
To engage in planning, we have to
make sure we understand the stakeholders.
Because individuals alone,
when there are not integrated,
cannot make any planning.
Therefore, we need to understand
the interactions among
the different stakeholders,
how decisions are made,
where they are made,
and who does what,
so we need to know who governs what.
This is the end of the first part,
see you in the next video.