Welcome to our MOOC, our Massively
Online Open Course
on Basic Steps in Magnetic Resonance.
3÷
Today, we shall be talking about
chemical exchange.
That is the subject of chapter 4
of Peter Hore's book.
The author has chosen an example
of chemical exchange
for the title page of his book
so it is safe to assume that he found
this subject particularly interesting.
Like many other basic aspects of
magnetic resonance,
the effects of chemical exchange
were discovered in the 1950s.
The name of Herbert Gutowsky is often
associated with this discovery.
The theory was developed by
Felix Bloch and Harden McConnell.
As we shall see, chemical reactions
that occur during the observation
of NMR spectra lead to
characteristic effects:
line broadening, coalescence,
and line narrowing,
all of which allow us to determine
the rates of reactions.
Typically, one can study rates that
are comparable with differences
in chemical shifts.
The range of applications is
truly staggering.
From simple conformational
equilibria,
to internal mobility of biomolecules
such as proteins.
So, the word “chemical exchange” has
a particular meaning for
NMR spectroscopists which is
not shared by the entire
community of chemists.
To explain this point, let's consider
some simple examples.
All of us, in first year chemistry,
must have learned that cyclohexane
normally looks like this, if it is
drawn as a static molecule,
and that we have protons, or generally
speaking, substituents
sticking out from the ring in axial
positions and other ones
that are in equatorial positions.
Now, we also know that these can
interchange to give another
conformation which again
has axial and equatorial positions.
Now, what is curious is that,
in the static molecule,
if we could stop it from exchanging,
we would expect a different chemical
shift for the axial position
and the equatorial position.
One would expect them to have
different chemical shifts.
Let's not talk about the fact that
they are also coupled,
which is not of interest here.
Now it turns out that the chemical shift
of the axial proton
will be transformed into the chemical
shift of an equatorial proton.
Whereas the equatorial proton will
find itself in the position
of an axial proton. Consequently
there is an interchange
between their chemical shifts.
It turns out that this process is
extremely fast and therefore
difficult to measure with NMR,
unless we find some way
of slowing it down, which is actually
still a topic of interest.
I can take another example, of a true
chemical reaction.
Let's consider some carboxylic acid,
which looks like this
in the acid form.
And we have all learned that this
can be transformed into the
conjugate base by
giving a proton to the environment.
Now if we think of this carbon-13,
we can expect its
chemical shift
to be different from the chemical
shift in the conjugate base.
And indeed it is.
Again, such a process tends to be
very fast, and therefore not easy
to measure by NMR.
But it turns out that such processes
can be slowed down considerably.
For example, if this carboxylic acid
is hidden in the heart of a protein,
if it belongs to the side-chain of a protein,
to one of the amino-acids
in the protein,
the exchange can be slowed down
and can become measurable, which is
of great interest to NMR spectroscopy.
Now, in order to support this whole
discussion of chemical exchange,
I invite you to look at chapter four of
Peter Hore's book on
Nuclear Magnetic Resonance.
You will see that he distinguishes
symmetrical two-site exchange
and un-symmetrical two-site
exchange.
We shall see
what the difference is.
In this chapter, there is a great
wealth of interesting examples
that I will take some
time to discuss with you.
Let's first talk about symmetrical
exchange, which is
an exchange with equal populations.
Equal populations you will have if
the two forms in equilibrium
have the same energy.
So, if the energy is drawn as a function
of the degrees of freedom,
it turns out that you have the same energy
for the A and B forms.
If that is so, then the populations
will be equal, according to
Boltzmann's Law, and also the
interconversion from A into B
will be precisely matched by the
reverse interconversion
from B into A.
Such systems are very numerous.
Ee have for example
dimethylnitrosamine, where there are
two distinct methyl groups,
a methyl group which is on the
same side as the oxygen
or “cis”, and another
methyl group, which is
on the opposite side or “trans”,
with respect to the oxygen.
There can be a
pseudo-rotation about
this single bond (or partly single
bond), so that the oxygen will
go to the other side, and the methyl that was
in the cis position now ends up
in the trans position
Therefore they can be
labelled like this.
The point is that while this
pseudo-rotation is going on,
the methyl groups change their
environments, and in doing so
change their chemical shifts.
Because the energies
of these two conformers or rotamers
are exactly the same, the populations
are the same and therefore we have
a symmetrical situation where the
forward and backward exchange rates
are exactly the same. We can
write theme as k+ which is equal to k-.
We can also write the
equilibrium constant K, which in this case
is equal to 1.
Now, in this particular case, where
we have equal populations,
we can distinguish different regimes.
This picture is on the title page
of the first edition of Peter Hore's book.
First of all, it shows the spectra
that we see
as a function of the exchange rate.
You will note that this is a
logarithmic scale,
for example, this corresponds to one
jump per second,
while this corresponds to a thousand
jumps per second,
and of course we can go all the way
to 100,000 per second.
This corresponds, generally speaking,
to an increasing temperature.
There are other ways, of course,
of changing
the speed of a chemical reaction, but
temperature is certainly
one way of doing it.
At low temperatures we have
slow rates, and at slow rates we can
actually distinguish the chemical
shifts of site A and site B
as we have in previous examples.
In these
simulations, they happen to be
separated by a difference in chemical
shifts that is
50 Hz and which elsewhere is called
delta nu,
with a lower case delta.
So that's the abstract notation for
the difference in chemical shifts
delta nu is equal to nu zero of site B
minus nu zero of site A.
Now, what is interesting is that
if we increase the temperature
or otherwise increase the interchange rate,
then the lines
begin to broaden, and more surprisingly
they tend to move closer together.
It turns out that the distance between
these broad humps is smaller
than the distance between the two
narrow peaks at low temperature.
They get broadened to the
point that we see almost no signal
and then they turn up as a single
hump, the two lines appear merged
together into a single hump, a
phenomenon that we call
“coalescence” in our trade.
More remarkably, the single
line, which is initially rather broad,
will become narrower and narrower as
the exchange rate increases,
while at the same time, we end up
with an average chemical shift
which is simply half-way between the
two chemical shifts of the separate sites.
Aat the low temperature end, the line-broadening
effects are due to slow exchange.
Before we speak of line-broadening,
we have to define what exactly we
mean by the width of a line.
There are actually several definitions
in the literature but this is the one
that we shall use.
The height of the line, the peak height,
will be called H, and can be divided
by two. Next we measure the width
in Hz at the half of the height
of the line.
This quantity we call delta nu,
nu being the Greek letter that is used
for frequencies. The line width is simply
proportional to the exchange rate k
divided by the factor pi.
Since the exchange rate k is nothing
else but the inverse of the lifetime
of a particular conformer, or molecular
form, we can substitute that into
this equation, and come to the
conclusion that the line width
delta nu is equal to one over pi times
tau, tau being the lifetime.
Thus, the line width can be rationalized in
terms of the lifetime of the states.
Remember that a transition in NMR
is always between a ground state
and an excited state, but at
the beginning we have discussed
these as stationary states that have
an infinite lifetime.
In fact, if the molecule doesn't exist
for very long, the states don't exist
very long either, and they get blurred.
The shorter the lifetime,
or the faster the exchange,
the more severe the blurring.
On the left hand side,
they are only slightly blurred and
therefore the line is fairly narrow.
But in this case the blurring is
quite severe, the
differences in energy is also blurred
and therefore the line becomes
very broad.
This is a hand-waving way of
explaining line-broadening.
There are, of course, more satisfactory
ways of explaining the same thing.
So, for a two-site problem with equal
populations and equal forward and
backward reaction rates, we have the
following three distinct regimes:
In the slow exchange regime, we
simply have line-broadening
which is the same for both A and B
resonances, and in both cases
is simply proportional to the exchange
rate k, or if you prefer, inversely
proportional to the lifetime of either
of these molecules, or conformers.
In the fast exchange rate, we have
an entirely different situation.
In this case, the line width is
inversely proportional
to the exchange rate.
That means that the faster the
exchange rate, the narrower the line.
Furthermore, there is a very important
parameter.
The parameter delta nu is,
as before,
the difference in chemical shifts.
And as you can see,
it comes as a square.
Now that's very important because
that means that the residual
line width will be proportional
to the square of the difference
of the chemical shifts.
And this difference in chemical shifts
is, among other things, proportional
to the magnetic field into which we
immerse our sample or molecule.
Consequently if we go from, say,
a 400 MHz spectrometer
to an 800 MHz spectrometer,
that is to say, if we double the field,
then we also double the difference in
chemical shifts, and we therefore
quadruple the square, that is to say
the line width becomes four times broader.
This is one reason why chemists and
physical chemists like to have
spectrometers with different fields
in their laboratories.
You can also convert this equation by
saying that the line width,
apart from the square of the
difference in chemical shifts,
is directly proportional to the
lifetime of the states.
As we mentioned,
there is a critical
condition called “coalescence”.
In fact, that's the precise point
where the three extrema of these
curves merge into a single
extremum, a single maximum,
It turns out that this occurs
when the exchange rate is precisely
2.2 times the difference in
chemical shifts.
This equation is of limited usefulness,
because in the vicinity
of coalescence, the lines are often
so broad that you can barely see them,
let alone decide whether they
have merged or not quite yet.
We have discussed chemical
exchange between two sites that have
equal populations because
they have equal energies.
The discussion can be broadened
to encompass the more general case
where the populations are unequal.
Here we have a case where we have
the same methyl group, but
here we have replaced one of the
methyl groups by a benzyl group which
has CH2 attached to a phenyl ring.
And so these are clearly unequal and
therefore you would expect the molecule
to have different energies depending
on whether the oxygen is pointing
to the same side as the methyl or
to the opposite side.
And indeed, the energies are quite
different between these two forms
and therefore the populations are
going to be different. So there will
be more molecules in the lower
energy state than in the
upper energy state.
We can also say that the likelihood
that we move from left to right
is faster, the exchange rate is higher
than the other way around.
So this situation means that k_AB
is different from k_BA.
This will have some consequences on
the spectra.
When the populations are unequal,
this has dramatic
consequences on the exchanging spectra.
Here we have a case where the minor
isomer A has about half the concentration
of the major isomer B, but they still
have distinct chemical shifts.
In this case, the simulations refer
to a difference of 50 Hz
this is again delta,
which is nu zero A minus nu zero B
and as you can see, when the exchange
process begins to be felt, the
minor isomer broadens actually more
than the major isomer.
Furthermore, they tend to coalesce
and then narrow, as in the case before,
but the narrowed line is not positioned
halfway between the two chemical shifts,
but displaced towards the
major isomer.
In fact, the rule is very simple, the
average chemical shift is a weighted
linear combination, or a weighted
average between the two
chemical shifts, with the population of
the minor isomer and the population
of the major isomer which are
the weights of the two chemical shifts.
Remember that the sum of the two
populations is defined to be one,
because they are
probabilities of occupation.
As you can imagine, if the major
isomer becomes very dominant,
the minor isomer becomes negligible
and the average line will be essentially
indistinguishable from the position
of the major isomer. It becomes
therefore difficult to determine
exchange effects.
It turns out that this is
quite a modern picture.
I guess it was first drawn in the '50s
but there has been recent work
on proteins where one can
now distinguish the dominant major
conformation of a protein, and a
minor conformation which might
be activated, perhaps the conformation
that allows the protein to work
as an enzyme or to have a fruitful
interaction with its substrate.
This kind of argument is now used,
not only for protons but also for
nitrogen-15 and carbon-13 in proteins.
It turns out to be a very powerful way
to identify mobility of macromolecules.
If the populations are unequal,
as opposed to the equal case
we treated before, then
there are two different
line-broadening effects.
The line width of site A becomes
inversely proportional to the
lifetime of A and the line width of
site B is inversely proportional
to the lifetime of B.
If site B is dominant, then its lifetime
will be longer and therefore
its line width will be smaller.
If this is a minor conformer, then
tau A will be short and therefore
its width larger.
Furthermore, we have this average
population which is weighted
by the populations.  This is a
somewhat more scary equation
where we have the residual line width
in the high temperature limit
in the fast exchange limit.
Much like in
the case of a symmetrical exchange
it is still proportional to the square
of the difference in chemical shifts
and therefore, if we double the field,
this delta nu parameter will be
multiplied by a factor of four,
like before.
Furthermore, we see that we have p_A
and p_B, the populations
and the sum of the two exchange rates,
the forward and the
backward exchange rate.
Of course, this should converge to
a simple equation if we take p_A
and p_B to be one half each.
To summarize the first part of
chapter 4, we have discussed
the pictures that serve as front
cover for Peter Hore's book,
and we have discussed the fact that
if there are two isomers
with two different molecular forms, or two
partners in a chemical reaction that have
different chemical shifts, then these
lines will be broadened by
chemical exchange and the broadening
can go as far as coalescence, and beyond
to line narrowing at an average
position.  The line widths of these
different spectra can be used to
extract the chemical exchange rates,
which are, of course, of great interest
to chemists and physical chemists alike.