In the second part of Chapter Two,
I tried to summarize
the mathematics
that underlies the description
of the so-called
McConnell-Bloch equations,
which allow one to derive
such things as line broadening,
line narrowing, and coalescence
on a rigorous basis, rather than
in terms of a purely empirical discussion.
Now, Peter Hore shows
a remarkably well-selected
set of examples
of chemical exchange.
I would like to start with
an example that is
as one of the last
of his illustrations because I think
it's one of the
most important ones.
It happens to have been
discovered in Switzerland
at ETH Zurich by Kurt Wuethrich
whose name I wrote out here.
He got a
Nobel Prize for NMR of biomolecules.
This was in 2002.
He once said, in an
informal lecture, that the effect
that I'm going to explain
to you now, was one of his
most important discoveries.
I tend to agree
with that judgement.
He has done many, many things,
but this is very intriguing.
We are talking about
the motion of tyrosine
which occurs in proteins.
You have the protein backbone,
then you have the CH2 group, next you
have a phenyl ring,
with a para hydroxy
group. That is tyrosine.
There are four protons
in positions 2, 3, 5 and 6.
If the tyrosine is rotating freely,
as it would be in solution,
then you would expect
protons H3 and H5,
which are in meta-positions,
to have the same chemical shifts.
Likewise, you would expect H2
and H6 to have the same chemical shifts.
But Kurt Wuethrich did not record
these spectra in free solution,
but he considered tyrosine,
actually amino-acid number 35
in this protein, which is called
basic pancreatic trypsin inhibitor,
(BPTI), which has about 70 amino acids.
Number 35 happens to be a tyrosine.
There are other tyrosines,
but Tyr-35 is particularly interesting.
As you can see, you can
record spectra of BPTI
from very low temperatures,
just above freezing,
to very high temperatures
without significant
denaturation of the protein.
This is not obvious, since
many proteins would be denatured.
But BPTI is quite happy.
At high temperatures,
you see that
protons H2 and H6 occur at
the same chemical shift,
about 7.2 ppm.
Protons H3 and H5
also give rise to a single chemical shift.
The signal is actually split into
a doublet.
This doublet comes
from the coupling between
the ortho and the meta positions,
but that is not relevant
to today's discussion.
As you lower the temperature,
which is easy to do,
you find that that spectrum
gets more complicated.
And the first thing that happens, when
going from fast flipping to slow flipping,
is that this signal broadens,
and then splits up into
two distinct resonances.
One corresponds to the ortho position H2,
the other corresponds
to the ortho position H6.
These two protons now have
dramatically different chemical shifts.
The difference comes not from
the tyrosine itself,
but from its environment.
It turns out that the protein
environment on one side is distinct
from the protein environment
on the other side.
And therefore, the two protons H2 and H6
are exposed to different local fields,
and have different chemical shifts.
Something similar happens
if we look at protons H3 and H5.
These are in meta positions,
which I put in a square box.
So at high temperature,
they are simply degenerate.
The doublet structure
is irrelevant here.
And when you go to lower
and lower temperatures,
they broaden and split up
into two distinct resonances,
H5 and H3 here,
two distinct doublets.
Now the remarkable thing is that,
although the temperature scale
is the same,
the coalescence for the two
protons that are close together
at low temperatures occurs
at about 40 degrees.
Whereas the coalescence
of the two protons
that are far away from each other
occurs at about 60 degrees.
That is simply
a confirmation of the laws
established by Bloch and McConnell
and can be calculated
with the theory
that I explained in the previous part.
Actually, beyond a simple illustration,
this picture has dramatic implications
for proteins and the understanding
of protein dynamics
because this interconversion
really supposes that
the ring flips,
that the aromatic ring of the
tyrosine actually flips over.
Now that means that
it must be standing upright,
perpendicular to the plane
of the paper,
maybe for a very short interval.
But it has to be able
to flip over from
this flat position
to the flat position the other way.
so that the positions
of H2 and H6 can interchange,
and, likewise,
H3 and H5 can interchange.
Now that implies that
the protein must be dynamic,
that it must be able
to “breathe”, as it were,
in order to leave sufficient room
for such an exchange process.
Indeed, a quite remarkable observation.
There are more basic examples.
This one was probably already
discovered in the '50s,
possibly at CERN
by the early investigations
of Dharmatti and others,
who studied ethanol.
It turns out that if we consider
the multiplets of ethanol at neutral pH,
i.e., at pH 7,
we do not only see
the usual triplet
of the methyl group
that is due to the neighboring CH2:
the CH2 is not simply
split into a quartet
because of the neighboring CH3,
but it is, in addition, split into a doublet
because of the neighboring OH.
We can actually see
this OH proton.
It is split into a triplet
because it is scalar-coupled,
to the neighboring CH2.
It turns out that
you only have to add
a minute amount,
a trace amount of acid
for this effect to go away.
Then we observe
a singlet here.
And the multiplet of the CH2 group
collapses to a simple binomial quartet.
So the question is, why do we
observe such a collapse in the spectrum?
The answer is, if we consider
a single molecule,
the monomeric form of ethanol,
we may have a proton
called H_A,
which may well have a polarization
that is parallel to the magnetic field,
which we call alpha.
The external proton, the one that
comes from the water or from the acid,
could be called proton H_B.
In this hypothesis it has
the opposite polarization, namely beta.
If these two exchange,
and that is exactly
what chemical exchange is all about,
then, of course, the H_B proton
will become part of the ethanol molecule.
But it will retain its beta polarization.
Whereas the H_A proton will go out
into the medium
while retaining its alpha polarization.
From the point of view
of the CH2 protons,
it looks as if the neighboring
proton in the hydroxy position
has flipped from alpha to beta.
This flipping can occur
at a phenomenal rate
because acid-base reactions
are extremely fast.
Therefore,they can lead to a collapse
of the multiplicity of the CH2 group.
And that is exactly what we see here.
You will recall that this line
can also be broadened
because of exchange between
OH and the environment,
it's not easy to observe
such a sharp line.
But normally, we just see this part.
We should indeed see a quartet
and a triplet.
One of the best examples
that Peter Hore has cited in his book,
is due to David Grant
and others in Salt Lake City,
is cis-decalin.
This can be drawn
as a flat molecule.
It is not aromatic,
but it can still be drawn like this.
And if we do it that way,
we can number the positions.
We talk about
either carbons or protons,
in this case, the carbons.
This is the conventional
numbering of this molecule.
And if we draw it like this, it is not
surprising that the symmetry implies
that the chemical shifts
of these two sites are identical.
You can see that
the chemical shifts of this site should
be the same as of this site.
And this site should be
the same as this site.
Of course, the other
sites are distinct,
so we find that these sites
are all distinct from the previous ones.
In effect,
at 46 degrees Celsius,
the molecule can be
essentially considered
as interconverting so fast
that we are allowed to draw it on a flat plane.
At that temperature,
we only have one peak
that corresponds to these two
bridging carbons.
We have one peak that
corresponds to the four carbons
that I have circled here.
And there's one peak for the four carbons
that I have put in square boxes.
So far, so good.
Now it turns out that if
we go to a lower temperature,
from 46 to 16 to -12 to -29,
then the situation becomes
more complicated.
Like in the case of
Wuethrich's tyrosine, we see
that these lines split up.
The reason is that at
lower temperatures, we have
to consider these molecules as
separate rotamers, or separate conformers,
where the symmetry is reduced.
We still have a symmetry
between these two,
and likewise between these two,
that has been preserved.
Indeed this line doesn't move
at all as a function of temperature.
But we see now that this line,
although it's the same as this one,
it is no longer the same as that one,
and no longer the same
as that line.
So C1 and C5 still pile up together,
and C4 and C8 are still degenerate.
But they are no longer equal.
However, if we warm them up,
so you see that C1 and C5,
and C4 and C8 tend to coalesce
and end up in the positions
that I've indicated previously.
There is here a two-fold coalescence.
We notice that, in this case, the coalescence occurs
at about the same temperature.
Because the splittings between
these two and these two, by accident,
happen to be about the same.
This is a very good example.
In fact, at the beginning
of this chapter, I spoke about
the interconversion of cyclohexane,
which as I mentioned,
is too fast. But in cis-decaline
the exchange becomes slow enough so that you
can observe it
in the vicinity of room temperature.
The next example is much
more sophisticated.
This is known as bullvalene.
It's one of these molecules
that was probably designed
in order to get into the
Guinness Book of Records
for maximum complexity.
In fact, all we have to remember
is that we have a cyclopropane unit
with three
carbon-13 positions.
We also have a bridging position
which is a lone position.
There are all sorts of
so-called Cope rearrangements
where the double bonds travel
and the cyclopropane ring opens up.
I will not give you a lecture
on organic chemistry,
but you see that this cycle
turns up here and so on and so forth.
And in doing so, for example,
this site here, which was the isolated D,
now becomes a site A, which is typical
of the environment of cyclopropane.
And so indeed, there is an
interconversion between A and D.
And in fact, the entire process
can be summed up
in this topological graph,
showing that D goes to A,
while A goes to C, C to B, and B remains,
in part, equal to itself
in the course of this Cope rearrangement.
At high temperature, there's only one position.
But as we lower the temperature
it splits up into many lines.
And we can, of course,
determine the exchange rates
of these processes by doing
an analysis of the line shapes.
The next example in Peter Hore's book
should be more to the liking
of people who are interested
in organometallic chemistry.
Peter Hore cites an example
of a ruthenium complex
where you have a ruthenium
that is hovering
over this cyclooctatetraene ring.
In doing so, can be
attached to different positions.
We have two ordinary double bonds,
in these delocalized bonds
where the ruthenium is most strongly attached.
It turns out that the ruthenium
is not very tightly bound
and can move a little bit like the hands
of a clock around a dial.
At high temperatures,
we have a single line in carbon-13 NMR,
but as the temperature is decreased,
it splits up into a manifold.
Again, we can draw topological diagrams
which show the exchange rates between
these four different forms.
It turns out that the question here
is whether we have a 1-2 shift,
or a 1-3 shift, or a 1-4 shift,
or a 1-5 shift.
The spectra allow you
to rule out some of these mechanisms
and choose the one that is correct.
The next example in this chapter
has already been discussed
in an earlier chapter about
scalar couplings between
a spin S = 1/2, such as a carbon-13,
and a quadrupolar spin
such as lithium-6.
Lithium-6 has a spin I = 1,
therefore, it has three possible states,
m = +1, 0 or -1.
Consequently, the neighboring
carbon-13, if there were only
one lithium-6, would be split into
a triplet, with three equal intensities.
This is known
as a non-binomial triplet.
As we have discussed before,
four lithium atoms can make
a tetrahedral structure.
These tertiary butyl groups
can attach
not to the corners of the
tetrahedron, but to
the middle of each
of the triangular faces.
At low temperatures,
each carbon-13 will be coupled
to three lithium-6.
This results in a rather peculiar
non-binomial multiplet
at low temperature.
But the situation gets even
more complex if we heat it up.
If we go from low
to high temperature
it turns out
that these groups
can move.
They can hop from
one triangular surface to another.
Or, if you prefer, they stay
where they are,
but it's the lithium cluster
that rotates within the cloud
of carbon substituents.
Whatever the case may be,
it turns out that at 26 degrees Celsius,
we find that each carbon-13 is coupled
not to 3 lithium-6 nuclei, but 4 lithium-6 nuclei,
because all four lithium-6 nuclei, even this
remote one, will at one point
be close to the carbon-13,
and have a scalar coupling.
We see two interesting things.
First of all, the multiplet
becomes more complex.
In addition, the effective scalar coupling,
the splitting
is larger here than it was there.
It is actually reduced
because of the averaging.
So I'd like to summarize
Chapter Four
that Peter Hore
dedicated to chemical exchange,
which seems to be one
of his favorite subjects.
It is indeed one of the key aspects
of modern magnetic resonance.
Chemical exchange effects in NMR
can arise either
from chemical reactions or from
conformational equilibria.
In the slow exchange regime,
NMR lines are simply broadened,
and we can measure
that exchange rates by
looking at the line-widths.
The difference in NMR
frequencies between exchanging spins
can be averaged by fast exchange.
It is the magnitude of delta nu,
that is to say the difference
in the chemical shifts between
the nuclei that are involved
in exchange processes,
relative to the exchange rate constants
that determines whether
the exchange process is
in the slow or in the fast regime.
Chemical exchange effects give
information on rates and mechanisms
of chemical reactions, molecular
rearrangements and internal motions.
Now most comments in Peter Hore's book
refer to chemical exchange
between sites that are distinct
because of their chemical shifts.
But there are other ways
of distinguishing sites.
One of them, for example,
is the quadrupole interaction in solids.
Here, at the Ecole Polytechnique
in Lausanne, we have spent years
determining the spectra
of nitrogen-14 which
is a quadrupolar nucleus
with a spin I = 1,
and has a quadrupole interaction
that ranges
from 1 to about 5 MHz.
We have observed
exchange-broadening effects
between different sites that
are interchanging at very high rates.
When the exchange rate
is, say, 1 MHz,
that means the lifetime is
on the order of 10 to the -9.
That is to say nanoseconds.
Consequently, nitrogen-14 spectra
in solids are sensitive to processes
that occur on a timescale
of about a nanosecond.
It all depends which
nuclei you look at
and in which environments.
Chemical exchange is probably
one of the subjects that will live
for many years to come.
Currently, much attention is
paid to chemical exchange in proteins
and also in DNA, for it has been found
that the well-known double helix
is not as static as it appears,
and there are many exchange processes
that are worth studying
in large biomolecules.
Thank you for your attention.