Hello, and welcome to this segment
on market opportunity evaluation.
It's actually called
"Look Before You Leap!"
It's called that way because
that's exactly what you should do:
look before you leap
into a market domain.
What he have seen time and again
is that novice entrepreneurs
actually enter the first market domain
which they consider,
and this is actually not a process
that we can recommend,
because all of the results
that exist out there
tell you that you should first look
at multiple opportunities
and then decide which one
is the one you should exploit.
Building on that theme,
in this segment we want to understand
which is actually
a very good opportunity.
Which type of opportunity provides you
with the most fertile ground
for your firm creation processes.
As you remember,
not all opportunities are alike,
so we need to understand what features
are attractive in opportunities
and which features help you
to then create a successful firm.
In the last segment we talked
about the firm growth options.
That's exactly what
this picture here depicts,
and as you remember,
we had these multiple opportunities
that stem from your technology.
The question arises,
which of these market opportunities
is actually a good one to enter
for your organization?
You can break up this question
into a couple of core questions
and some additional questions
that we will discuss later on,
but in essence, it boils down
to an economic rationale.
Which market domain provides you
with the most fertile ground
for your firm creation?
Meaning some markets are more attractive
than others to be entered.
Second, it boils down to another issue
that is more on the organizational level.
The market you will be entering
shapes the identity of your organization,
who you are as an organization.
Depending on the type of market you enter,
this could come out fairly differently.
Thirdly, and we haven't
discussed that so much,
there might be some domains you feel
more passion about than other domains.
So, your passion is actually
a strong driver in entrepreneurship
because it releases energy,
you have much more attention
towards issues
that you are passionate about,
so you shouldn't forget
about that third component either,
and probably, you are already
drawn to domains
where you say
"I have a lot of passion for."
If these domains provide fertile ground,
this is wonderful.
But there might be a tradeoff
where these domains
do not provide fertile ground.
The domain you're passionate about
might not provide you
with the requisite number of products sold
that would help you create
a company that is successful.
Once it becomes a tradeoff question,
this is actually
an important question to consider,
because you might learn
to love a domain as well,
once you have seen
your success in that domain,
you might say, "OK, this is
a wonderful domain to be in,"
and now you start becoming
passionate about it.
OK, it's a little bit
like love at first sight,
and at second sight,
and at third sight.
Keep this in mind and we will look now
at some more detailed questions
that help you understand
how to evaluate
your market opportunities.
In order to understand
whether your opportunity
provides you with fertile ground
to grow and nurture your venture,
there are a couple of questions
that you might want to ask yourself
and address and think about,
and we have listed them on this slide.
These questions are,
of course, interrelated,
but it helps you to walk through
each one of these questions one by one
because each of these questions
address an important issue.
We have differentiated
between a Customer perspective,
the Market perspective,
the Economic perspective,
the exploitation perspective
and the Venture Development perspective.
The first one is the customer perspective.
The customer perspective
is a highly critical one.
As Peter Drucker said, you do not
create a company for creating a product,
you create a company to create a market.
The customer is really the starting point
for creating the market.
The key issue here is whether
the customer really feels pain
because he does not have your product.
How strong is his need for your product?
There are products that he says,
"I may have this one,"
and there are products where he says,
"I should have this one,"
and there are products which he says,
"I must have this one."
I think it's very obvious
that once you have a must-have product
that you could propose to the customer,
that this will be a much,
much easier sale.
The second point is that you
should try to quantify the benefit
that the customer gets from your product.
This is oftentimes much easier to be done
in a business to business settings,
where you, for instance,
have a more efficient solution,
but this can also be done
for business to customer relationships
where you are trying to understand
how much benefit does this customer
get out of your product.
For instance, if you create an app,
that app might facilitate the customer's
search for information and save him time.
That's a real value.
Or, link him up with new types
of information, which he would not have.
That's real value.
It boils down to the question,
do you have a customer
who has a strong need
for your product in front of you?
Or is this more like a should-have
or a may-have type of product?
If it's the latter two, there are ways,
in terms of marketing,
which can increase the feeling of need,
but there's only so much you can do there.
The next point here
is the market perspective.
The market perspective is one level up,
if you want to put it this way,
from the customer perspective.
It's basically the aggregation
of all the customers you have,
and the question is,
what is the market size?
How many people, how many companies
would be in this market
that could potentially buy my product?
And, over time, is this a growing segment?
Or is this a stagnating segment,
or even declining segment?
Of course, the growing segment
provides more fertile ground over time,
but also, if you have
a strong value proposition,
customer pain that you can address,
then even a declining segment might be OK,
but still, a growing segment
makes it easier
because you do not have to fight
head to head with your competition
about market shares that are declining.
The third element
that you want to consider
is the economic perspective.
This perspective, actually, is critical
to the viability of your venture.
It means that you protect costs
and try to understand
whether you can actually achieve
prices in your market
so that you can cover these costs.
Ideally, with a margin, so that it
can make profits over time.
The point here is one where you'd say,
"It's the business model
that I have for my venture,
it's the processes of the costs
and the profits leading me to say,
'This is a sustainable venture,
this is a viable venture.'"
So this economic perspective
is highly critical
and you should assess it.
Of course, you do not have
sufficient information
in all dimensions in the beginning,
but this is a learning journey
as we pointed out already before.
Another point is what is the speed
of revenue generation?
If you consider revenue generation,
this is cashflow coming into your company.
This is air that you breathe
in the company,
so this means the quicker
you are in achieving revenues,
the easier it will get for you
to actually survive with your company.
The fourth element discussed here
is the exploitation perspective.
It moves a bit more into
opportunity exploitation over time.
The question here is
that you need to ask yourself,
can you or do you already have
the competencies that you need to have
in order to produce your product
and commercialize your product?
The second issue is your network.
This is typically very critical
entrepreneurship too,
because you are relying
on network resources.
You hardly have any resources
in the beginning,
so you're relying on network resources.
It could be knowledge support,
financial support,
support in reaching
potential customers, etc.,
but it's highly critical.
So, the question is, some
of these opportunities that you will see
you could get a lot of support for
in your network,
and some other opportunities,
you could get little support for
when you try to exploit
those opportunities.
Finally, on that front you ask yourself,
"What are the chances
of winning in this market?"
Are there some ruthless competitors
that might out-compete you
because they lower the price
below any reasonable value,
just to keep you out?
Or, there might be markets
which are more benevolent
where you say, "OK, this is providing me
with some peace of mind.
I can move forward,
my customer likes the product,
the competition is not
so ruthless. Let's do that."
Finally, and let's move then more closely
into the venture development perspective,
you need to ask yourself,
is the window of opportunity open?
Is this actually a market
that I can enter now
and where customers are ready
to buy my product?
Or is this a market that might take
a little time to develop and unfold?
So your activities could actually
help you create that market,
but be aware that this takes some time,
because you are investing
in developing that market
and customers might not be
present so much
and ready to spend
significant sums on your product.
So, opportunities come and go,
so try to assess this timing dimension too
when you are looking at opportunities.
The other point
that you need to think of
is whether the market opportunity
that you're looking at
actually provides you with some grounds
to step into other domains later on,
where you could diversify.
So is that one market oportunity
providing you with this leveraging
potential for the future?
Think of very attractive markets
that help you shape
your organizational identity
in a favorable way, that other people
will look favorably upon your product,
and this favorable view of your product
could then translate into easier
access into another market.
Finally, the question arises,
can you defend your position over time?
There are some markets
where innovation cycles are so quick,
that you need to invest a lot
into updating your capabilities,
updating your products,
so that you might not be able to
defend your position over time
because competitors
might out-compete you
and provide even better products.
So that question is also one.
As you see, there are lots
of important issues to be considered,
so market evaluation is not an easy task,
especially when some
of these dimensions might be uncertain.
Some of these elements
you might not know.
This can never be
a completely scientific task,
saying, "This is exactly the opportunity
that provides me with the best option."
It's rather trying to give you
some intuition,
but it's more than intuition,
it is intuition that is
backed up with knowledge.
Between intuition
and complete understanding,
which market you want to address,
there is this middle ground
that you can occupy,
and that's where I ask you to go.
Try to get information,
make an informed opinion
as much as it can be,
before you can commit to your market,
because remember
what we said in the beginning,
it's look before you leap!
In conclusion, this is really the idea
"I have multiple market opportunities
that I could potentially exploit."
You see this here.
You evaluate these opportunities.
You choose the most fertile ground
where you say, "This is a field
I have passion for,
this is a field where I like
the type of organization that I create."
You enter that domain and then, over time,
if this one works out you can have
multiple ways of entering
other domains as well.
This is life as an entrepreneur,
it's an exciting journey,
and this journey does not end
and should not end
with the first market that you enter.
Rather, see this as
building a larger corporation
that is catering to many domains.
OK, thank you very much.
I look forward to seeing you
in the next segment.