Welcome to our
massively on-line open course
on basic steps on magnetic resonance.
Today, we shall be talking
about spin-spin couplings
that are the subject of chapter three
of Peter Hore's book.
The appearance of multiplets
in NMR spectra is familiar
to all practitioners of analytical NMR,
familiar to virtually all chemists,
to many biologists,
and even to physicists.
However, not all of them
are aware of the subtle aspects
of multiplet structures.
Spin-spin couplings were
originally discovered
by serendipity in the 1950’s
by Erwin Hahn.
He noticed that
spin echoes were modulated.
This observation came shortly
after Hahn's invention or
his discovery of spin echoes.
More about this subject in chapter six.
Such echo modulations
can be observed
even when the homogeneity
of the static field is too poor
to resolve the multiplet structures,
as indeed was usually the case
in the 1950’s.
Scalar couplings have a few
important properties.
First of all, they are “isotropic”.
That means that they do not
depend on the orientation
of the molecule with respect
to the external field.
They are also field independent,
that is to say, they have the same
magnitude at, say, 400 or 800 Mz.
They are mediated by electrons
via the so-called Fermi interaction,
and are said to be through-bond
as opposed to through-space.
It is still a challenge today
to calculate scalar coupling constants
with reasonable accuracy.
If the coupling constants are known,
the multiplets that due to scalar couplings,
can be predicted
with remarkable accuracy
by simple diagonalization
of the matrix representation
of the Hamiltonian in the product base.
The agreement between theory
and experiment is viewed by some
as a nice confirmation that
quantum mechanics actually works
perfectly in this case.
This perfection is due to the fact
that Hilbert space,
i.e., the space that comprises
all spin states, is of finite dimension.
Multiplets due to scalar couplings
give crucial information
about molecular symmetry.
They offer a great opportunity
to practice group theory.
Multiplets that are due to scalar couplings,
give unique insight into
populations of rotamers, and into
their inter-conversion.
Another fascinating aspect is that
averaging allows the chemist
to grasp the flexible,
and generally speaking,
dynamic nature of most molecules.
Chapter three of Peter Hore's
book on nuclear magnetic resonance,
is dedicated to spin-spin couplings.
In his characteristic fashion,
Peter Hore speaks first about
the manifestations of couplings
in an empirical fashion.
Next, he proceeds to explain
where they really come from.
These aspects are treated
one after the other.
So multiplets, particularly
those in proton NMR spectra,
are quite familiar
to the practicing chemist,
particularly to organic chemists
because multiplets allow them
to identify fragments of the
molecules they are trying to analyze,
that they have synthesized
or hope to synthesize.
We shall start with the
important example of ethanol,
but now observed in a magnetic field
of a modern magnet that has
a sufficient homogeneity
so that we can not only
resolve the three chemical shifts
of the OH, methylene and methyl protons,
but also their fine structure.
This fine structure is due
to scalar couplings.
As most chemists
will know, the CH2 signal
is split into a quartet
because the CH2 group
has a CH3 group as neighbour.
While the CH3 group
is split into a triplet,
because its neighbour
is a CH2 group.
This kind of logic has become
instinctive for many chemists,
but in fact, it's not so easy to explain.
And one of our objectives
is to go into some detail
in the course of this chapter.
Multiplets are perhaps best explained
in so-called hetero-nuclear systems
where we have for example,
one proton, which has a spin 1/2
with two states, alpha and beta.
And one carbon-13, also
We can take a molecule,
which only contains two such spins.
For example, the conjugate base
of formic acid, or formate, if you will,
with a singe proton and a single carbon-13.
About 1% in natural abundance,
or up to 100% if we enrich
the material.
There are two spectra.
If we take a field of 9.4 tesla,
the proton appears
in the vicinity of 400 MHz,
while the carbon-13 appears
in the vicinity of 100 MHz.
In both cases, however,
we do not see singlets,
but we see doublets.
So the proton signal
is split into a doublet
and so is the carbon signal.
It turns out that the two splittings
are exactly the same.
If we wonder where this comes from,
we have to look
at the energy-level diagram.
Remember that spectral transitions,
i.e., the lines in the spectrum
always correspond
to differences in energies.
If we consider a single isolated proton,
its polarization can be parallel
with the magnetic field.
We call this the alpha state.
Or it can be anti-parallel, in which
case we call it the beta state.
Of course, between the two energy levels,
there is only one transition
which is near 400 megahertz.
And consequently, we observe
a singlet.
But if we now have a carbon-13
in the vicinity, it turns out that
that carbon-13 itself can be in the alpha or beta states.
And in this case, we assume
that the carbon-13 is in the beta state,
that is to say, in
an anti-parallel configuration.
And remains in this
anti-parallel configuration
while the proton is
undergoing a transition.
It is a manifestation of the scalar coupling,
that the splitting between
these two states is larger than
the splitting between the two states
in the absence of a carbon-13.
Conversely, if we consider
a carbon which is polarized
parallel to the magnetic field,
i.e., in the alpha configuration,
then it turns out that the splitting
between the two levels, where the proton
flips from parallel
to anti-parallel, is reduced.
If we think of the spectrum,
the splitting is enhanced
from here to here.
Consequently, the line moves from
the central frequency to higher frequencies.
Remember that frequencies
run from right to left,
in NMR by convention.
On the other hand, the other line
has a reduced energy splitting
and therefore, a lower frequency.
So this line turns out
to be on the right-hand side.
The effect of the scalar coupling,
more specifically the one-bond scalar coupling,
because there's only one bond
between these two nuclei
in formate, is to split the line
of the proton into a doublet.
And likewise, through a similar argument,
to split the carbon-13 line into a doublet
with this same spacing.
We can generalize the argument
and include
arbitrary energies and arbitrary
numbers of spins.
For example, we consider
the energy of an arbitrary state.
Now we have many states
and these states are
specified by magnetic quantum numbers,
lowercase m, which
which can be either
plus 1/2, or minus 1/2.
Each energy level
is specified by two quantum numbers
and each of them can be
either plus or minus 1/2.
Having said that,
the energy level diagram
is primarily determined by
this expression.
This is the Larmor frequency
of spin A.
And that is
the Larmor frequency of spin X.
This is
Planck's constant,
the energy is expressed in joules, as it should be
in the international system.
Though, in practice, NMR spectroscopists
often express their frequencies in hertz (Hz),
which you can achieve by dividing
the energies by Planck's constant (h).
So we often write things is hertz,
which amounts to energy divided by Planck’s constant.
In this equation, the energy is
expressed correctly in terms of joules.
You see that the main effect
comes from the offsets,
i.e., from the chemical shifts.
But this perturbing
term is due to
the scalar coupling between A and X.
It turns out that if mA and mX
have the same sign,
we have a positive contribution.
If they have opposite sign,
we have a negative contribution.
We see this
very nicely on this diagram.
First of all, we start with a
molecule in the absence
of a magnetic field.
Then we switch on the field
for the A nucleus, so that we see a splitting.
This is the Zeeman splitting
of spin A, which could be a proton.
Then we have another
Zeeman splitting for spin X,
typically a carbon-13
The ratio of this splitting to this splitting
should be equal to the ratio
of the gamma of carbon-13 divided
by the gamma of the protons.
The effect of the coupling is
to increase this energy, because
the two magnetic quantum numbers
are minus 1/2 times minus 1/2,
which is plus 1/4.
So we have an increase here.
And here, because we have
a product of minus 1/2 and plus 1/2,
the product will be minus 1/4.
And indeed, the energy
decreases like this.
Here, it's again minus 1/4.
And here, it's plus 1/4,
and indeed, the energy goes up.
This is clearly a consequence
of this equation.
In practice, we see that for
the A transitions, in the absence
of a J-coupling,
there would be just one line for spin A,
i.e., for the proton.
And another line for the carbon-13.
But as soon as we introduce
this J interaction, the A signal
splits up into doublet,
and the X signal also splits up
in a doublet with equal spacing.
In this diagram, Peter Hore
has aligned these arrows
with the lines in the spectrum.
And this logic has been
used throughout.
It is interesting to notice that
Peter Hore likes to draw
energy level diagrams
in this vertical fashion.
Many NMR spectroscopists are tempted
to draw a diagram more
in the fashion of a lozenge,
where these would be
the transitions of one spin,
and these the transitions
of the other spin.
Some of us
think it's easier to remember this.
This is for
a homo-nuclear system.
For a hetero-nuclear system,
you would have large transitions
for spin A, and smaller transitions,
i.e., smaller energy differences,
for the X transitions.
Some people prefer drawing
a lozenge rather than a
vertical “ladder” representation.
In larger spin systems,
with three or more spins,
we have more complicated multiplets.
The multiplet patterns
can be “built up”, as it were,
from different splittings that are
invoked one after the other
in a sort of cascade of splittings,
sometimes called a 'tree'.
If we have a given spin that
resonates at a chemical shift A,
it will be split into a doublet
if we have a neighbouring spin M
with a coupling JAM.
And this doublet will be
split into a sub-doublet
by spin X with a coupling AX.
If we assign different
transitions to different polarizations,
it turns out that the left-most
line of a multiplet,
if all couplings are positive,
corresponds to a situation
where both M and X have negative m,
i.e., are both in the beta configuration.
For the second line from left,
spin M is still in the beta position,
but X has flipped over
from beta to alpha.
The transitions can be assigned in this manner.
This is a rather elaborate
way of interpreting
the different components
of a multiplet in terms of states.
At this level,
that one cannot describe all
***
energy level diagrams like this.
For example, for a two-spin system,
it would look like this.
If we have a third system,
it would be like this.
We have two lozenges,
and we can connect them like this.
It turns out that four parallel
transitions of the cube correspond
to transitions of spin A.
For example, these could be
the transitions of spin A
and the other transitions would be
those of spin M and spin X.
One of the purposes
of this picture
is to show that under certain circumstances,
the couplings J-AM and J-AX
may become equivalent.
Spin A can be coupled to a spin X,
and to another spin X, and in such a way
that the two coupling constants
are accidentally, or by symmetry, equal.
In this case, we have only one J,
and it's called JAX.
And you can see
what happens in this diagram,
the inner transtions of these
two doublets are
shifted on top of each other
and become degenerate.
This degeneracy means
that the central line is
twice as intense as the
individual lines.
We can take this
one step further.
We can consider the case
where A is coupled
to three different nuclei,
all with the same coupling constant.
This is known as an AX3 system.
In this case, we have
a quadruplet with a so-called
binomial intensity distribution.
And each line can be assigned to the
polarizations of the neighbouring X nuclei.
These multiplet patterns can be
generalized in terms of Pascal's triangle,
which is a simple way of rationalizing
a binomial distribution.
You probably know how
Pascal’s triangle is built up.
For example, this number three
is just the sum of numbers
one and two on the line above.
You can use that rule
systematically all the way down.
What you obtain
are binomial distributions,
the distributions
for different spin systems.
This is an A spin
in AX2, AX3, … systems.
You may think this is
purely formal,
but, in fact, it is not.
The rules go a long way further.
You could, for example,
consider a situation where
we have a silicon-29 nucleus
which has a spin 1/2,
which is surrounded by
four methyl groups.
This substance is called TMS,
or tetramethylsilane.
There are 3 x 4 = 12
equivalent protons.
So the system is actually
an AX12 system, and you
can imagine that you have
to expand Pascal’s triangle
a very long way to go that far.
By the way, these intensity rules
are not always easy
to identify on a spectrum because
the outer lines are very weak compared
to the central lines.
Sometimes you just
don't see the outer lines.
And one way of not being fooled
by the fact that the outer lines
may be drowned in the noise,
is to compare the lines
of the central components.
In this case, we have 15:20:15,
which is, of course, distinct from 1:2:1.
And therefore, we can identify on which
level of the Pascal’s triangle we are,
without actually identifying the full list of lines.
There are many cases
where couplings involve nuclei,
so-called quadrupolar nuclei,
which have spin quantum number I,
larger than 1/2.
The simplest example being
the deuterium nucleus, which has a spin I = 1.
The nitrogen-14 nucleus also has a spin I = 1.
Lithium-6 also has a spin I = 1.
Not to mention all the higher spins.
Now let's take a simple example
where we consider a carbon-13
attached to a deuterium nucleus.
We call the carbon nucleus-13 spin X,
while the deuterium nucleus
will be called spin A.
In the energy-level diagram
for the deuteron, which has I = 1,
the magnetic quantum
number m can be either
-1, or 0, or +1.
We find three levels corresponding
to m = -1, or 0, or +1,
the magnetic quantum numbers of the deuteron.
This transition is actually
degenerate with this transition
of the deuteron.
If we are in isotropic phase,
there is actually no evidence
that this is a quadrupolar nucleus.
But if we look at the carbon-13 multiplet,
we have
to take into account that there is
a splitting.
Let's call
this quantum number S
to avoid confusion.
In this case, m can be
m = -1/2, or m = +1/2.
These can be called
beta or alpha states.
Now we have
six energy levels, with
a certain number of transitions.
We see on the carbon-13 side,
i.e., on the X side,
three transitions.
These are nicely aligned
with these peaks.
There is a direct relationship between
the energy level diagram
and the spectrum.
Some people say that
a spectrum is nothing else
but a peculiar “projection”
of the energy-level diagram.
If we look at the A side,
it turns out that these lines
are still rigorously degenerate,
since they have exactly the same frequency.
So they end up as a doubly
degenerate line.
Likewise, these two transitions
are exactly degenerate
and pile up on top of each other
to give a doubly-degenerate line.
The remarkable thing
is that for the X nucleus,
i.e., of the carbon-13 nucleus, we don't
have a binomial triplet,
but we have a triplet with
equal intensities 1:1:1.
There are many other quadrupolar nuclei.
We have the example of boron-11, which has
a spin quantum number I = 3/2
The magnetic quantum number m of boron-11
can go from m = - 3/2
to m = - 1/2, m = + 1/2,and
finally m = + 3/2.
So there are four distinct
quantum states for each boron-11.
Consider this peculiar molecule,
known as diborane,
which comes from the condensation
of two BH3 molecules.
We have twice BH3 that give a B2H6.
The structure of this B2H6
is a rather peculiar assembly,
where we have 4 so-called
terminal protons.
Each of these terminal protons
only “sees” one boron-11.
(Incidentally, we assume that
boron-10 has been removed
by suitable synthetic preparation.)
Now each proton sees
just one boron-11,
and consequently the terminal
protons are split up into
a quartet of four equal lines.
This is a non-binomial
1:1:1 quartet.
that is characteristic of
any nucleus coupled
to a spin 3/2 nucleus.
But more peculiar is what happens
if we look at the bridging protons.
These protons actually
have equal bonds to two borons,
and also equal scalar couplings.
In fact, the whole molecule
is completely symmetrical.
And these protons and these
borons are magnetically equivalent.
If we want to understand
the fine structure
of the multiplet of the bridge proton,
we have to divide the signal
into four equal peaks,
and each of them has to be
subdivided again into four equal peaks.
Because the two couplings
are equivalent,
like in AX2 and AX3 systems,
there are two
ways of getting to this line:
either from here, or from here.
And therefore, the intensity of this line
is twice as high as the first line.
So we have rather peculiar multiplets,
with relative intensities 1:2:3:4:3:2:1,
which is
not a binomial multiplet.
This does not fit into
the logic of Pascal's triangle.
But you see where this comes from.
By way of exercise,
I would like to encourage you
to think of the next level.
What happens if a proton
were coupled to three boron nuclei?
Then of course, we have
an even more complex multiplet.
The challenge is
to determine its multiplicity.
This is not an academic question,
since there are actual molecules
that have such patterns.
So this concludes part one
of this chapter.
Thank you for you attention.