Welcome to our MOOC
on magnetic resonance.
This is the second half
of chapter three
where we shall speak
about spin-spin couplings.
We should address the tricky
issue of ‘equivalent nuclei’.
It turns out that these are very nicely
described in Peter Hore's book.
I think it's one of the best
books on this subject.
There are two forms of equivalence.
There is ‘chemical equivalence’.
That is fairly easy to understand.
That means that you have two nuclei
that cannot be distinguished
in chemical terms.
One cannot substitute one
without substituting the other.
One cannot replace one.
One cannot conceive of a reaction
that would affect one
without affecting the other.
That's one thing.
And then there is the concept
of ‘magnetic equivalence’
which is much more subtle
and more difficult to define.
Let us start with a simple application.
We have a
magnetically equivalent pair
the two protons
have the same coupling
to the two fluorine nuclei.
So if we consider this coupling
and this coupling,
it turns out that by symmetry
of the molecule,
these two couplings must be the same.
Likewise if we started
with the two fluorine nuclei,
they also have the same
couplings to the two protons.
These two couplings are the same.
But if we look at this coupling here,
which is a ‘cis’ coupling, it has a
different magnitude and
perhaps even a different sign
from this long-range coupling here,
the ‘trans’ coupling.
So these are distinct
and therefore, there are
two different cases.
Peter Hore has a wonderful way
of explaining how you
can check for the existence
of magnetically equivalent nuclei.
First of all, you define an ensemble
of nuclei
of which you want to decide
whether they are magnetically
equivalent or not,
such as in this case
of proton ‘a’ and proton ‘b’.
And then you define external nuclei,
if they exist.
This fluorine we call ‘z’,
Peter Hore uses that nomenclature.
He says:
If the J coupling between ‘a’ and ‘z’
is equal to the coupling
between ‘b’ and ‘z’,
and is also equal to the coupling
between ‘c’ and ‘z’, etc.
for all similar couplings,
we have magnetic equivalence.
And if that is not the case
as in this molecule,
then we have only chemical equivalence.
This distinction has dramatic consequences.
The test, where we compare
the scalar couplings
between ‘a’, ‘b’, ‘c’ and an
external nucleus ‘z’,
has to be repeated
for different external nuclei ‘z’.
For example we do it for ‘z’
and then we have to do it
all over again
for a nucleus ‘z prime’.
In practice it turns out that once
you have obtained a negative
answer for one of the nuclei ‘z’
you don't need to check the others.
Magnetic equivalence
needs to be
thought about carefully.
There are cases
that are not obvious.
For example this is a dodecahedron--
the molecule has the formula C20H20.
If all carbons are carbon-12,
which is not obvious,
unless it is depleted in carbon-13,
then we have no other nuclei
than the 20 chemically equivalent protons.
so there is
no external nucleus ‘z’,
and consequently we can't carry out the test.
Hence all 20 protons
are magnetically equivalent
and not merely chemically equivalent.
The same is true for a much more
mundane molecule
which is benzene.
which has six protons.
They are all equivalent
because there is no proton ‘z’
and no carbon ‘z’
that could make the six protons
inequivalent.
Multiplet patterns can be used
to check for molecular symmetry
or to confirm or reject a hypothesis
about the symmetry of the molecule.
Peter Hore has collected
some wonderful examples
of phosphorus-31 NMR spectra
of compounds which contain
only phosphorus and sulphur.
The large spheres represent
phosphorus atoms
and the small spheres sulphur atoms.
There are different arrangements.
Sulphur has no spin
at least its dominant isotope
has 99% abundance and no spin.
And therefore, we can ignore it
and we we only have to worry
about the chemical shifts,
and about the
chemical or magnetic equivalence,
of the phosphorus nuclei.
In a configuration like this,
there is
no nucleus ‘z’.
that could conceivably have different
couplings with the four
phosphorus nuclei.
Therefore all four nuclei ‘a’
are in the same environment.
They are chemically indistinguishable
and are
magnetically equivalent.
Therefore we speak of an A4 system.
This system has a different symmetry.
You immediately see
that these two
phosphorus nuclei are sitting
between three sulphur atoms,
whereas these phosphorus nuclei
have another phosphorus
as neighbour, and only
two sulphur atoms as neighbours.
So chemically, they're quite different.
In fact, they also have different
chemical shifts
but when it comes to the symmetry,
it turns out that the coupling
between one of these nuclei ’A’
and the two nuclei ’X’ is equal
and so we have an A2X2 system.
As a result, we have a triplet for A,
and for X we also have a triplet.
This is a more complicated case
where the phosphorus on top
has three neighbouring sulphur atoms.
A bit like what we had before
but at the bottom,
we have a phosphorus atom which is squeezed
between two other phosphorus atoms,
whereas the other phosphorus atoms
are squeezed between
a phosphorus and two sulphur atoms.
So clearly we have three
different chemical environments
and we have an AMX2 system
because the only magnetic equivalence
is between these two X nuclei.
You can see the consequences.
Nucleus A gives a large triplet
due to the coupling JAX between A and X.
where X are the two neighbouring
phosphorus nuclei
and a smaller coupling JAM between A
and the distant M nucleus.
So this is a wonderful example on how
we can look at spectra
and draw conclusions as to
the symmetry of the molecule.
There are also amusing cases
when we look at lithium-7
or at lithium-6.
Lithium-7 has a spin I = 3/2.
This is a little bit like boron-11
that we have discussed before.
In this case we consider
a strange molecule
which is actually a cluster
comprising four lithium atoms
arranged according to a tetrahedron.
It turns out that if you can attach
tertiary butyl groups,
that they are not attached
to one of the lithium atoms
but they tend to attach themselves
to the middle of the triangular surfaces,
to one of these sides of the cluster.
Very mysterious chemistry
but NMR is without any doubt
proving that this structure
is the true structure
and not the one that
you might draw intuitively.
It turns out that
because of this structure
if we look at the lithium-7 spectrum,
which has a spin I = 3/2,
we shall see an ordinary binomial quartet
because of the splittings
to three equivalent
carbon-13, since
each lithium in effect
‘sees’ three carbon-13 nuclei.
For example, if you take the lithium
nucleus at the top,
it ‘sees’ this carbon-13 and this one
and this one as equivalent.
And therefore, we have
this wonderful quartet.
On the other hand,
we could decide to enrich
the cluster with lithium-6.
Lithium-6 has spin I = 1,
so it will split a neighbouring
carbon-13 into three equivalent lines
with amplitudes 1:1:1
but since each carbon is coupled
to three lithium-6 nuclei
this gives rise to a strange non-binomial multiplet
which is comprised of three
interleaved triplets.
I vividly recommend that
you to look at this carefully.
This is similar to what
you have seen in diborane
except that now there are couplings
to three neighbouring nuclei.
In four-spin systems we have
more complicated structures
but they are fairly easy to rationalize.
In fact, we can simply take
the proton NMR spectrum
of dibromonitrobenzene.
This is a very simple molecule.
And we can see that
we have a proton A
which is squeezed between a proton P
and a proton M.
The ortho-couplings
are not exactly equal
but they are similar.
The proton X is across the ring,
so to speak, and has
a long-range
para coupling to A
and medium-range couplings to the
meta positions P and M.
And as a result, the A multiplet
will be split into what is sometimes
called the ‘pseudo-triplet’.
In fact it is a doublet of doublets
with very close couplings.
The doublet fine structure
is due to the para position X.
The proton M is split
into a large doublet
because of JAM,
and each line is split into a doublet
and again into a doublet
first because of P
and then because of X.
Likewise, the same logic applies
to spin P which is very similar
to spin M as far as the structure
of the multiplet is concerned.
Finally, spin X shows a pseudo-triplet
because the couplings to P and to M
are almost equivalent.
Each component is split
into a small doublet
because of the para-coupling
between X and M.
This kind of spectrum
allows you to determine
the molecular structure
without any help.
There is an interesting phenomenon
in scalar-coupled multiplets
that is known as ‘strong coupling’,
sometimes known
as ‘second-order coupling’.
We begin with a case
where the J splitting
is much smaller than the
difference in chemical shifts.
In this case we speak of an AX system
but when the chemical shifts come closer,
we notice that the multiplets
not only become closer
but also change
their amplitudes.
The inner lines become stronger
and the outer lines become weaker.
In such a case, we use
two letters in the alphabet
which are close together,
so we may speak of an AB system.
Ultimately, if the two chemical shifts
become degenerate,
we have only one line left over,
and we speak of an A2 system.
To understand strong coupling
we have to use a little bit
of quantum mechanics.
This is not treated in any detail
in the first volume of Peter Hore
that I recommended to you
but there is a second book
that you may wish to read
next year
that is written by Steve Wimperis, Jeremy Jones
and the same Peter Hore,
in the same Oxford Primer series.
This book speaks about
quantum-mechanical effects.
In this case we have to explain
how we start with an AX system,
where we have just two doublets,
and go to an AB system where
the two doublets move
close together so that the inner lines
become more intense,
to the limiting case of the A2 system.
It turns out that all three
can be explained in one equation
by saying that the bottom state
where the two spins are parallel
with the magnetic field
is not affected by this phenomenon
so they're always the same.
It is always a simple state
with alpha-alpha.
Likewise, the upper state
where the two spins
are anti-parallel is unaffected.
It doesn't matter whether the system
is strongly or weakly coupled.
But the intermediate states
called psi_2 and psi_3
are mixed.
In fact, they are neither alpha-beta
nor beta-alpha
but there is an admixture
between the two
with coefficients given by the
cosine of an angle chi
and sine of the same angle chi.
This angle is determined by the ratio
of the J coupling and the difference
in chemical shifts.
In terms of simple trigonometry,
we can draw the chemical shift difference horizontally,
in units of Hz (Hertz),
and we draw the scalar coupling
vertically, also units of Hz.
We can make a little diagram
and this angle is twice chi.
You can immediately see that
when the J coupling
becomes much smaller
than the difference in chemical shifts
then the angle chi goes to zero.
The limit of chi going to zero
means that
the cosine goes to one
and the sine goes to zero,
so this is a pure alpha-beta state.
Alpha for spin A and beta for spin B.
Likewise, if we take the limit
of chi going to zero,
only the cosine term survives
so this would be a pure state
where spin A
has a beta polarization
and spin B has an alpha polarization.
You can see from this
diagram that, the larger J
is compared to the difference
in chemical shifts,
the steeper the slope,
the closer the angle 2 chi
approaches 90 degrees
and therefore the angle chi
approaches 45 degrees.
It is interesting
to see the limit
where chi = 45 degrees.
We see that the cosine
and the sine become equal.
so the coefficients are just
1/(square root of two), times
(alpha-beta + beta-alpha).
Likewise, in the limit for chi
= 45 degrees,
when the J coupling is much larger
than the difference in chemical shifts,
the other function goes to
1/(square root of two), times
(- alpha-beta + beta-alpha).
We have minus alpha-beta
plus beta-alpha.
In the case of an A2 system,
you see there is a symmetrical
linear combination
that we have here.
This is symmetrical in the sense
that if you do a permutation
of spins A and B, the
wave function doesn't change.
It is invariant to permutation
and is known as totally symmetric.
Whereas for the other wave function,
the one that I just
commented on,
is anti-symmetric with respect to
a permutation of the spins.
It turns out that the symmetric state,
together with the top state
and the bottom state,
together form what is known as a triplet of states,
that is to say three states
with the same symmetry.
Whereas this state here
is known as a singlet state.
A remarkable thing is that
the peak that we see
in the spectrum is made up of two lines,
only two lines, that are degenerate
and appear on top of each other.
One line corresponds to the bottom
transition
of the triplet, and the other line
corresponds to the top transition
of the triplet.
Whereas the transitions from
the bottom state to the singlet state
are forbidden. This is represented
by dotted lines.
I cross them out to show
that these two transitions
are completely forbidden.
In fact, they are only
virtual, so to speak.
If you look at their frequencies,
they are a plus and minus J
away from the central component
but their intensities are vanishingly weak
and that is why we cannot see them.
This kind of quantum mechanics
has been known for decades
but has gained some renewed
interest very recently
because it turns out that the populations
can flow quite freely
within the triplet manifold
as a result of
longitudinal or spin-lattice relaxation.
Whereas populations that
are locked in the singlet state
cannot flow from the singlet
to the triplet states.
If one can contrive some way
of populating the singlet state,
then the populations
would be locked up,
and one can have
so-called long-lived states.
This is the speciality of Malcolm Levitt
in Southampton.
We have done a lot of work in Lausanne
to improve techniques
to populate singlet states.
This concludes part two of this chapter.
Thank you for your attention.