What is gonna happen with this
after I throw it away?
Do these pictures look familiar?
Piles of garbage
in neighborhoods and streets,
or smelly, burning and polluting
waste disposal-sites.
Unfortunately, this is
a frequent situation
in low andd middle-income countries,
especially in towns and urban centers.
Do you want to understand
the complex interaction
between stakeholders,
technical solutions
and governments?
And how this can contribute to improve
municipal solid waste management?
Then, this course is for you.
Sandec is partnering with EPFL
to bring you a series of online courses.
This is the Sandec webpage,
for more information on the series
Sanitation, Water
and Solid Waste for Development.
This course is dedicated
to municipal solid waste management.
Hi, hola, bonjour!
I'm Chris Zurbrügg.
I'm a research scientist at Eawag,
at the department Sandec.
I specialize in solid waste management
in low and middle income countries.
I will conduct this course
together with me colleague
Imanol Zabaleta.
In this course, we will cover
the two dimensions
of solid waste management.
The first invovles understanding
the physical components
of a municipal
solid waste management service.
We will discuss aspects
of the whole chain,
starting from generation of waste
to collection of waste,
treatment and disposal.
The second dimension analyzes
the governace aspects;
these include the roles
and responsabilities of stakeholders,
the financing mechanisms,
legislation and policies,
as well as socio-cultural aspects.
When analyzing the stakeholders,
we will present examples
of non governamental organizations,
the informal sector,
private enterprises,
as well as different government agencies
or even the role
of external funding agencies.
Throughout the course,
we will be covering issues
around recycling
and creating value from waste.
We shall put a special focus
on treatment options for biowaste
because in low and middle income countries
most often, more than half
of the municipal waste
consists of biowaste,
in other words,
waste which is biodegradable.
We will look
at more conventional approaches,
such as composting,
but also, at vermicomposting,
or anaerobic digestion.
What is the science
behind these processes?
What kind of challenges
do such projects face?
What are they a success
or why did they fail?
Did you know that there are
actually other innovative approaches
which are just in the phase of research,
or just recently being implemented
to treat this biowaste?
For instance, producing protein
from biowaste.
We will cover these and more issues
together with guess lectures,
who will present experiences
from the field,
for instance Félix Schmidt,
from CSD Consulting,
and Sanjay Gupta,
a waste management expert,
working for SKAT Consulting.
How is municipal solid waste managed
in your neighborhood and city?
What do you observe?
What do you contribute?
Why don't you share this with us?
We want you
to actively participate in our course
by sharing your experience
and get involved
in solid waste management.
We look forward to working with you!
You are just a click away
from registering.