Hi, my name is Rueben Snellings and I have a background in applied mineralogy
in particular I have spend more than 10 years using X-ray diffraction to study semanticiuos
Materials, in this lecture series. My fellow team members and me
want to introduce you into the basics of X-ray diffraction also called XRD
and how you can make use of this powerful technique to study the chemistry of cement, the use
of x ray diffraction as material characterization technique goes back a long time
major scientific progress was made by applying x-rays and crystals to study
how atoms are organized in crystalline materials, in short
x-ray diffraction studies have had an enormous impact on our understanding of
how nature works. Just by resolving the crystal structure from anything
like simple rock salt to very complex molecules such as
DNA, penicillin or insulin. Similarly
X-ray diffraction was applied to study the main phases present in cement such as C3S
C2S, C3A and C4F, it unable to
describe differences in atomic arrangements that underlie large changes
in chemical reactivity. One of the most striking examples of this
is C2S that changes from very reactive in the alpha form to largely
unreactive in the Gamma form of large spectacle impact is that X-ray
diffraction data can be used to quantify the composition of complex materials
such a cement. This capability has led to widespread
application of the power diffraction technique in research labs. Even more so
its ease of application has led to its introduction as a quality control system in
clinical production plants. This course aims to show you how X-ray
diffraction really works. How you can properly carry out the measurements and
then how you should read interpret and then analyse the collected data.
To obtain your desired results. This course is aimed at
the level of mases students, graduate students or professionals that are planning
to embark on x-ray diffraction studies to study cement.
Preferably, the student has followed introductory courses in chemistry
and materials science. Having followed the basic cause and crystallography is helpful
as well. This lecture series consists of two main parts in part
one the basics of X-ray diffraction are introduced and it is shown how part of the
diffraction patterns are collected and how one should read and interpret
the data. In part two more advanced data analysis methods are
explained and demonstrated. In particular it is shown how
X-ray diffraction can be used to quantify the cement phase composition. In
part one X-ray diffraction basics and measurements. This part
consists of four sections. First a brief history of X-ray
diffraction gives an overview of the underlying principles
next. The basic features of the diffraction pattern are described
and it is shown how these features can be related to material properties.
Then the third section explains and demonstrates how a laboratory
effect on water works and how to best prepare samples. This will be
illustrated with demonstration videos. Finally the principle
is of quality that if X and D data analysis or face
identification explains and example videos are
shown how to do this in practice. Part 2 advanced data
analysis and applications to cement consists of four sections as well. In the first
section the principles of quantitative phase analysis by read folk method are
described in a straightforward demonstration of data fitting scheme
in a second section we apply discrete felt method to analyze the face
composition of Portland cement, then even increasing the
level of complexity. In the third section we are going to look at how we can cope with some
present contain X-ray amorphous materials such as blast furnace slag or
calcium silicate hydrates. This way we can analyze
blended cements and even hydrate its limits. Several approaches are introduced and
practical advantages and disadvantages are discussed, concrete
examples on real samples will be given.
Finally in the last section collects and summarize its practical guidelines for data analysis.
This will enable you to develop the appropriate measurement and data treatment strategy
for your problem as a wrap up of this introduction. We would like to give you a clear
view of what are the main advantages and limitations of X-ray diffraction to study cement.
On the one hand XRD has become a standard not a trivial characterization tool
because one can characterize the phase assemblage in detail.
For instance, one can quantify what happens to individual phases during cement
Hydration. Further, soample preparation is
straightforward and measurement times are short. Making the collection of data
inexpensive and accessible and in fact most material science
departments or universities have XRD equipment available.
Finally significant progress in software development has made data
treatment less tedious and in some case semi-automatic routines can be
easily implement. On the other hand. One should be aware that there are
limitations as well. First of all the accuracy in terms of face quantification is limited
to about two to three weigh percent for major phases and around one to three
percent for minor phase. Also one should realize that for non-routine types of
analysis considerable expertise and understanding of the underlying theory
is needed. This cause really aims to get you started in
the measurements and also to transfer many practical tips and
tricks that usually do not find their way through to the specialized scientific
literature. Or handbooks on this subject.