The aim of this session is to give a first introduction on the application of X-ray diffraction
and to explain some of the basics underlying the diffraction of x rays on crystalline
materials. First we will illustrate how we can use X-rays
to study cement. And also we show what are the main challenges to be met
when applying this technique on Semanticist  materials on the left side of the slide.
You can see a typical example of pods of an x ray diffraction pattern of
Portland cement on the x axis. You can see the angle of diffraction and on the
y axis the intensity of the elastically scatted x-rays, the diffraction
pattern itself looks a bit like an intricate landscape of peaks and valleys
as will be explained in more detail later in the course characteristic series of
peaks can be related to individual crystalline phases. Intensity
of these sets of peaks scales with the concentration
of the corresponding phases. The main phases present in the cement
sample are Alight given in blue, Belight
shown in purple 0A or Aluminate in green and
ferrite as shown in red here. Fitting of the
intensity of these sets of peaks. Unable to extract the relative
concentration of the different phases this and this
example is done using a method called the reach out method and this method will
be introduced later in this course as well. The results of the
face quantification are shown on the right hand side
and looking at the sets of peaks and how they overlap it is very striking to
see that there is really very much overlapping and this is a
problem when we are treating the data and especially when looking at
Cements, this kind of problem of Peko overlapping is one of the
main challenges to obtain good quantification data
performing this type of analysis on a time series of measurements enables you to study
reaction kinetics and mechanisms in multi-phase mixtures such as hydrating
Cement. For instance the graph on the right side illustrates how Clinking
phases such as A-light and B-light get consumed over time during the
hydration of the cement. And how at the same time cement hydrates such as
Portlandite or calcium hydroxide or veterangite form
this type of information can for instance be used to unravel reaction mechanisms or to
serve as an input for hydration models for better understanding hydration of
Cement, not only changing concentration of solids phases can be measured
also Crystal structural saneness can be tracked and related to
external parameters such as changes in relative humidity or
differences in temperature. So the Often the live is unique data compared to
other common characterization techniques such as calorimetric, seminal
analysis or electron microscopy. These complementary
data can be used to unravel reaction mechanisms and
put all together analyze the kinetics of hydration or the
kinetics of Clinking. Let's take a step back and have a historical look at the
development of X-ray diffraction size. X-rays were first discovered by
Wilhelm Redken in 1895 doing electrical
discharge experiments with cathodes vacuum tubes. He noticed fluorescence
occurring on a barium Plotinus cyanide, even when the tubes were
completely obscured by cardboard. This new type of
electromagnetic radiation called by Redken himself. X-rays
as wavelengths that was significantly shorter than visible light typically
of the order of angstroms or a tenth of a nanometer
this discovery was first useful medical purposes, for instance radiology.
It was only later in 1912 that Max law in Munich
got the idea of positioning crystals in the X-ray beam in order to observe diffraction
phenomena. The idea was quickly picked up by Father and Son Bragg
to using the diffraction patterns to study crystal structures.
All of these pioneers were actually awarded the Nobel Prize in Physics for their
contributions making a leap in time to 1969
Ugur reach folks in the Netherlands developed a method to really calculate
neutron balder diffraction patterns. His
calculation method is based on fundamental crystal structural parameters
that in the calculation process can be adjusted or
as commonly called refined to come to an optimal fit with an
experimentally measured pattern in the beginning this method to us.
Computation is quite expensive and it was also specifically
developed for a special kind of diffraction, neutron diffraction. So it took
some time before the part of the method was realized by others in the fields and
that it was adapted to x-rays which are the more common type of lab defectormeters
even then after this extension was made
it took more than 10 years before the method was adapted by Howard to
enable measuring of mass based fractions insults.
Indeed it was the last extension that opened up a whole new field of quantitative phase
analysis. It is well to have a look at a few examples of what major scientific
achievements were made using X-ray diffraction studies.
One of the first chemists that mainly use X-ray diffraction to resolve the structure
of crystal was Linus Pauling through systematically studying the structures of
many minerals, he established a set of ground rules the following rules
that rationalized to how atoms organize into crystals
He then proposed concepts such as electro negativity as a
way to explain how outer shell like electrons of two given atoms would interact to
forming a chemical bond. Pauling then use these rules and concepts to
resolve ever more complex structures going from simple inorganic structures
to complex protein structures. This one so farther by
1952 Pauling was also engaged in the race to be first off the
structure of the carry of the human genome DNA. Unfortunately for him he came too
late. It was the rather obscure diffraction pattern of the complex DNA molecule made
by Rosalind Frank Franklin that formed an important part of the evidence that underpinned
the double helix model that was first proposed by James Watson and Francis Crick the
same year. Simultaneous to these great accomplishments made in other
parts of material science. X-ray diffraction was also applied to study Cements
and in particular as first the crystal structure of the phase is present in the cement. One of the
first studies on the matter was published in 1928 by Hansen Brown.
Over the years the structures of most phases present in the cement were reported.
But even up to now the structure of some complex hydrate phases are not yet
fully solved in terms of studying the relative concentrations of these phrasing cement. It
was only until 1993 that Taylor and Aldrich first applied retired matter to
cement compared to previous methods for face quantification the retired  method.
Consider the whole experimenter profile for fitting and thus unable to mitigate the
effects of peak Overlap. This really opened up X-ray diffraction
for cement science. Now let's have a look at some basic concepts of
X-ray the friction and scattering. X-ray diffraction is actually based on elastics scattering
of incoming radiation by a scatter usually an atom
or a plane of atoms. In elastic scattering, it is important to
remember that wave energy is conserved. This means that the energy of
The, or also called the wavelength of the incoming radiation is equal to that of the
skeptic radiation. So the scattering only changes the
direction of the wave. This change in direction or the scattering
angle. Is often expressed as Q, momentum transfer
while the scattering angle changes depending on the wavelength of the radiation.
Q is actually independent of this and directly related to crystal structures. You
can also be used to compare experiments that were done by different
wavelengths. It is important to remember that for diffraction phenomena to occur. The
wavelength of the incoming wave needs to be of the same order of magnitude as the size of the grid.
Similarly Crysis can be seen as three dimensional arrays of plates or a
lattice and this lattice can produce diffraction if a wave of the
appropriate wavelength is used. This was exactly what the Mexican law thought
of designing when he was designing his experiment in 1912.
He correctly assumed that the x-rays produced by cathode tube would be of the
same order of magnitude as the interatomic distances increases and indeed
placing a crystal in the incoming X-ray beam. Clearly a diffraction
pattern appeared on the photographic plate placed behind the Crystal.
This discovery was quickly picked up by Father and Son bragg that the mini immediately
applied this to the structure of crystals and common
minerals. The right side you can see an example of zinc blend
or the diffraction pattern of zinc blend. Further on some brag arrives a law that
stated the condition for constructive interference on a set of planes
having in it into plan or distance. Using simple geometry one
can be arrived in order for x-rays to be reflected on a set of planes. They need to
be in face. This means that the difference on the graph
on the lower side between ray AD and ray BC
are in effect the distance FG + GH
should be an integer value of lambda, the wavelength.
With both FG and GH equal to the inter plane and the distance D
times the diffraction angle, then the Bragq condition really reduces down
to n? = 2D sin 0. And this is
the famous Beckler. This relationship can be used to determine the geometry of a
crystal lattice and given some additional data such as the density of the
material and chemical composition it can be used to solve simple crisis structures
such as rock salt, zinc bland or diamonds. When doing x-ray diffraction
experiments on fine powders rather than on single Chrystal
the spots originally seen on the screen become concentric rings. This is
because the powder now consists of a very large number of randomly oriented
crystals that effectively diffract in all directions. As long of
course a bragg condition is obeyed. While we would not
take the camera image on the right hand side and recall the intensity of the
scatter radiation as a function of the distance from the center point or
equivalently as a function of the diffraction angle. Then we end up with the
conventional representation of x-ray Powder diffraction data as shown on the lower right.
The next session we will have a closer look of how we can read and extract information
from these kind of diffraction data.