In this session, we will have a closer look on what information is contained
in the powder diffraction pattern. We will look at the properties of the diffraction peak
or Bragg reflections that make up the defector of room. In brief we
will introduce what material properties determine the position
intensity and width of the peaks in the pattern. We will need this
as background knowledge to help us make the right decisions in data analysis and
interpretation later. Now let's have a look at the x-ray
the powder diffraction pattern of a substance vibrio known in cements.
This is part of diffraction pattern of Alight for instance. In this part of the
friction pattern we can see the appearance of a lot of peaks
and these peaks appear at a certain position and all a feature of these
peaks is OK they don't only have a position. They also have a height
and intensity. But that's also important to know as a characteristic
in what can peak differ as well. That is actually on the on width of
the peak. These are the three main properties of
one peak but also of sets of peaks that actually contain the
information that enables you to extract for instance crystallography
Information but also phase compositional information
yet. Now let's have a closer look at what
determines peak positions, peak positions are determined
by the size and the symmetry
of the lattice or the units cell. The unit cell is the basic
building units of your crystal. It has three dimensions
typically called A, B and C if they are different in size
and these between these three
dimensions we have angles, alpha beta and gamma depending on the
symmetry. What are your lattice. For instance cubic. Or
whether it's true clinic, one or more of these
parameters can be identical. The other important part you know
is OK one Konev and this is usually introduced in the
Crystallography course. It's what relates the distance between two
planes in your crystal and the appearance of a certain reflection.
HKL. HKL plane with a certain interplay and a
Distance D will diffract given
a certain wave like Lambda at a certain diffraction angle as is
established in Bragg’s law that says the wavelength equals
two times the independent distance times the sign of the diffraction angle
as seen in the previous section.
Knowing for certain plane HKL plane
What is the
distance. One can actually derive what is the units cell
parameter of for instance a cubic lattice using the formula
shown here. One can also derive the
lattice parameters of much more complicated
Symmetries, for instance trick symmetry in which we have A, B
C, alpha, beta and gamma which are all different values.
And then one would need to use this kind of formula. Of course there is gets to be
a system of equations where for a whole set of HKL
planes and their distances and diffraction angles connected and
one can actually computationally easily solve these kinds of equations
once one knows whether the crystal
investigation is of Cubic triclinic or other
Symmetry, that about peak positions. Now let's have a look at
peak intensities, peak intensities is determined by the positions of the atom and the units cell, so
this is really where your crystal structure information is used
for crystalline phase in a multiphase power sample for
Instance, one can actually have this kind of intensity equation
for each HGL reflection of that is this intensity quotient
consists of different factors most of which are not related to the
Sample crystal structure but rather to
set up of your instruments or decomposition of your
sample or for instance whether there is some preferred
orientation of particles in your sample or not. So there is a
general scale factor, I mentioned this there was a Lawrence
polarizations lecture which mostly depends of how the diffraction takes
place in your instrument. There is the absorption factor which takes into account how
much of the incoming radiation is absorbed by the sample.
And there is a preferred orientation factor that takes into account whether some
HGL reflections are over or under represented because of the effect that
for instance some crystallite that have a non-uniform
dimension for instance platelets or needles. They can actually be
solicited more than other kind of reflections.
Finally and most importantly there is the structure factor
looking a bit closer into the structure factor we see where actually all
the structural information is situated. So as seen in the
previous formula the intensity of a certain reflection is proportional
to the square of the structure factor. Structure factor itself for a certain age
scale reflection is actually the sum over all atoms and in a unit cell
and it takes into account for each atomic site for each
atom in the unit cell, the atomic cell factor, the
occupation of the sites by that atom, for
instance it can vary between 0 and 1. Let's say if you have a solid solution
series where you have 50 percent of the time ion and 50 percent of the time
aluminum and that size then the occupation site
number can actually distinguish between for instance the scattering between
of aluminum and that of ion. Important is the
interference term this term takes into account the atomic coordinate.
So where are these atoms located in your units cell? And finally
there is a D by wall effector or the atomic displacement factor that
takes into account thermal displacements of your atoms that can
actually kind of reduce the intensities of your structure factor.
Looking at the first of the parameters that is in the intensity equation
we have the X-ray for factors that actually reflect the nature of the
atom itself. X-rays in fact intersect with the atomic
electron cloud. The higher the number of electrons in this
cloud or the higher the atomic number z, the higher the
X-ray form factor will be. This is why this reflected
in the slides on the right hand side where you can see the periodic table
and in the periodic table the size of the spheres actually
Reflects the value of the atomic form factor.
So it also means that phases, minerals that contain
atoms with a higher atomic number will reflect
x-rays more efficiently or light phases will
typically have lower x-ray
Intensities, then phases that are typically
heavier. The x-ray form factor does not only depend on the nature of
the atom but also on the diffraction angle. This can be clearly seen on the right
hand side of the slides, where have a comparison between the form factors
Ion, oxygen, carbon and hydrogen as a function
of the diffraction angle, here normalize by the wave length to give
a more general treatment of the matter. One can directly
see that these form factors really
decrease sharply with diffraction angles this in
effect also explains why when we look at diffraction patterns for
X-rays intensities tend to be higher at the
low angle site than the high angle site. This is simply because
the atoms will reflect the
x-rays more efficiently at the lower diffraction angles, the other
part of the intensity equation is basically governed by the interference term
this interference term is actually reflecting the
position of the atoms in the units cell. One can see
the positions of the atoms reflected in this first formula. Now we see the
fractional coordinates X, Y and Z appearing.
These are the fractional coordinates of the atom in the unit cell
this interference term does reflects the underlying atomic structure
in the unit cell. Also called the motive. In fact the
interference term is the factor dot product between the position of the atom
and R M as one can see here and the
scattering vector Q HKL in which HKL is
a reflection plane. It is important to realize that this
interference term is not a smooth function of 20 and thus
reflections with similar D spacings may really have larger
or similar interference terms. This really depends on the
positions of the atoms in the units cell
and the interference with the scattering vector.
Most of the information effect that is used to calculate
the diffraction pattern of a certain mineral or phase
is written down in databases. And saved for
instance under a form like a  crystallography information files
one can see an example of this at the bottom sides of this slide.
These files, they contain lots of parameters such as
cell lengths A, B, C or cell angles alpha beta and gamma
they contain symmetry groups spays groups
and they contain also for each atomic sites, the
type of atom which is positioned at that sites for instance calcium
diffraction coordinates X, Y, Z and the
atomic sites of occupancy, for the calcium sites there is always
calcium atom sitting in that position. For instance for other
sites, for instance the ion aluminum one position they
occupied have the same atomic coordinates. However
85 percent of the time this side is occupied by ion and only
50 percent of the time is occupied by aluminum. All this
information is needed to calculate on this site
the position of the reflections and usually more on that side. The
intensity of the reflections, when we want to do a proper
fitting of a diffraction pattern. It is very important
that we have close reliable sorting models. Take for
instance we have a bad starting model, then the calculation
routine the fitting routine will have a very hard time in finding
the correct refines fitted parameters
in your x-ray diffraction experiments. The last parameter
in intensity creation onto Debye-Waller factors also called the atomic
displacement factors. This factor effect, reflects the
thermal vibrations of the atoms in their positions.
They are not frozen, they vibrate around the position which makes it
actually the size of the atoms, time and space ever which
is larger than they actually are. This actually leads to
destructive interference when your x-rays are being
deflected. And thus leads to a reduction of the peak intensities
expressions for this effect can be found here, one
of which uses the Debye-Waller factors as such, but other expressions exist as
well. For instance one which is more directly related to the mean
square atomic displacement and B which is often
preferred since it has values around is 1 and is thus easier to judge.
Typically when looking at atoms and that term of vibrations the general rule
is that the lighter of the atom is the larger displacement
displacement would be. Heavy atoms like Iran will barely move
smaller atoms like hydrogen will move a lot and spread out
their electron density or electron cloud.
this again adds up with the fact for instance that for hydrogen we have a very
low atomic form factor together with a
lot of thermal displacement, thermal vibration
it makes it very hard for X-ray diffraction experiments to actually see
hydrogen atoms, the impacts on the diffraction pattern will be
very low. The last property that we need to look at is the peak
width the peak width actually tells you more about the microstructure
of your sample not the crystal structure, the microstructure. Typically
The size of the crystalized that are defecting or the to string
these crystallize can be extracted from a analysis of
peak width, peak with and peak shape really depends
on the source of your X-rays, the instrument
the optics of your instrument you're using and also your sample itself.
The classical way of treating peak shapes and calculating and fitting
powdered deflection files are used are by using
analytical functions. Typically Gaussian and
Laurentian are mixed pseudo Voigt functions
and are used to model the peak shape.
So this did not really represent well
symmetric properties of x-ray diffraction
peak shapes. There are extended versions like with TCHZ on
a piece and seven that can take into account some measure of symmetry of the peak
on the right hand side we can see for instance what is the difference between a typical Gaussian` and a
typical Laurentian. A Gaussian actually has very
short tails while Laurentian has typically quite
long tails to both sides from the maximum. Mixing
those can give you a good representation of your peak shape
by X-ray diffraction. Actually peaks it shapes also really depend
on the diffraction angle. Typically they get wider the higher the
deflection angle is. So for both Gaussian and
Laurentian peak shape functions one needs to include a dependence
on the diffraction angle. The classical approach to this was made or
developed by Galeotti in 1958. And he
used for instance for the Gaussian dependence three parameters that can be fitted
U, V and W for the Laurentian he used two
factors X and Y and fitting those to the experimental
data. Unable to obtain a good fit between the full width of half
maximum at lower angles and that higher angles as well.
Using analytical functions is one way of coping with the problem of fitting and
modeling experimental diffraction data. Another way is the
fundamental parameters approach. Here, one
actually starts from the assumption that yes we can separate the instrumental,
the source and the sample contributions from each other
to do this one needs to know what is the source profile and what is the instrument
profile. The instrument profile can be calculated from
optical parameters. And they are actually established by typical
physical equations. Source profile is also usually known for
commercial sources. So one can easily fix those and then
just retain the contribution by the sample, the sample broadening.
So if we can separate contributions from the source the instruments
and that of the sample in the fundamental parameters approach. one can actually analyze a
sample texture, one can obtain information on what is the chrysalis
size and what is the strain on the lettuce for certain areas. This
can be very important for instance in deformation studies of metals, scientists can be
assessed through to share a formula. This formula uses the dependence
of the full width half maximum with the peak as a function of
the deflection angle and enables you to extract a volume weighted
mean crystallite size. And other formula can be used to extract
information on stream. In this respect the full width
half maximum as the tangents dependence on the deflection angle
having a look at how both vary over a wide range and diffraction angles
can enable one to separate strain and size contributions to the
broadening of your peaks. However this is only possible for
Pure or very simple
Metals, for instance or powders. When we look at complex mix mixtures of
powder such as a Portland cement typically the separation between size and strain
becomes impossible for a certain phase and we usually use as an
apparent crystallite size to muddle the broadening as a
function of 20. peak intensities and peak width
these are the main properties that can be used or looked at in part of diffraction
patterns to retrieve information on materials.
Peak positions relates to the unit cell dimensions and symmetry
peak intensities relate back to what type of atoms are contained in your unit
cell and what their positions really are.
and peak width goes back to what is the microstructure the micro
texture of your sample, how large are actually these crystallite
in your sample or what is defamation. The relationship between these
analytical properties of your diffraction pattern and the material
properties have been used in a very wide array of
Applications. In the next session we will actually look at how we can best
measure and X-ray diffraction pattern and then specifically applied to
Segments. We will look at the diffraction geometry, the
instruments. And then we will look at what are the best
settings of your instruments to measure A Portland cement sample for instance.
Also we will look at what is the best sample procreation procedure
for your problem.