X ray diffraction methods measure the interference pattern produced by the current
scattering of an incoming monochromatic X-ray by a three dimensional
periodic created material, here the crystal lattice for a
specific crystal lattice constructive interference. Peaks of scattered
X rays and the diffraction pattern takes place only at angles defined by the
specific distances on the letters as seen in the previous
lecture Braque’s law defines this relationship. X ray diffraction
experiments can be conducted on single crystals but also on powder's
powder diffraction has the advantage that mixtures of phases can be investigated
relatively easily and know relatively rare well formed
crystals unnecessary, instead in powder diffraction.
The original material is ground very finely and mounted on a sample
holder, the powder amount consist ideally of crystalline
particles in completely random orientation. If the organization is truly
random then for each characteristic repeat distance d
There are many particles that satisfy the Braque law. Flat
Powder amount are usually measured in reflection or so-called Braque
Brentano per focusing geometry
in this geometry, the incident beam from the line focus of the x
ray tube diverges until it is reflected by the sample, the
defective beam then converts from the sample as and is focused at the point
of focusing circle and the gun you meter circle intersect, here our
receiving slits positions to filter out any unfocussed radiation
secondary monochrometer can be used to ensure that only elastically scatter the radiation.
This is radiation that has the same wavelength as the source is allowed to enter the
detector device. The letter measures considerably
improve the angular resolution. This will make peaks
become narrower this showing less overlap with a reflection peaks. Various
Bragg Ventana configurations exist in the theta thither system, both the
X-ray source and the detector system rotates simultaneously along the goniometer
circle, the sample stage in the center of the goniometer circle is fixed.
Thus if the angle between the surface normal and the incidence being
has changed by 0 in fact the angle between the incident and
the diffracted beam has changed by 20 the peak to
background intensity and the peak resolution of the
most important parameters to assess the quality of a diffraction scan
increasing the peak to background ratio can be done by increasing measurement times
increasing X-ray source intensity or decreasing background scattering intensity
to improve the quality of the X and D data. Several so-called
optical devices are used to focus collimate and filter the
X-ray beam. Solo slits, diversion slits,
And the scatter slits and or receiving slits are all used to
condition the beam and remove background noise. Increasing the peak
resolution often involves cutting a part of the incoming and reflected intensity that
leads to big problem and this reduces overall peak intensities.
Thus in practice, a compromise needs to be found among different data
quality measures. Also taking into account practical considerations such as the available
time for measuring and the acceptable sample exposure time.
Finally in practice if you look at the X-ray powder the effect meter, it looks a lot
like in the pictures on the left side you can recognize the x rays
source on the tube. In the middle, the sample stage and on the
right hand side you see the detector. In between source and sample and
sample and detector optical devices are positioned, the x ray
tube requires cooling and is usually connected to an external cooling
circuit. The high voltage generator for the X-ray tube is usually positioned
underneath during the experiments the x rays are shielded off
by Leaded casing or lead glass to protect the operator
before you start data collection. It's important to check if the fact of that system is well
aligned and that a suitable measurement configuration is chosen in case of a
flat plate reflection geometry correct combination of optic elements and
sample size sheets and sure that media sample of transparency not beam
overflow at low angles occur. Data collection strategies
aimed at collecting a maximum of useful information from the sample. Therefore
the data collection range for Portland cements is usually chosen to be within let's say
5 to 70 degrees 20 for capercailzie for radiation. But it can be wider or
more restrictive depending on the problem. The 5 to 70 degrees
range provide ski information on hydrates face reflections at low angles
and covers the most intense reflections of both anhydrous and hydrous phases.
For most in-house diffractometers a step size of about 0.0 or
two degree city that is used. And the counting time per step is usually a
compromise between the optimal signal to noise ratio and
practical considerations such as the available time for measurements or acceptable
sample exposure. The development of high performance X-ray
detector systems in the last decades has allowed to actually drastically
reduce measurement times and thus to minimize exposure times of hydrated samples to
a couple of minutes. It is advisable also to spin
your sample in the horizontal plane to improve the particle statistics of the measurements when
doing powder diffraction. This figure give us an example of the
dependence of data quality on the type of radiation that you use
here a comparison is made between the diffraction patterns of two different Portland cement one measured
by a lab defectometer and the other by a synchrotron next.
The main advantage of using a synchrotron is the much higher
monochromatisity and the intensity of the X-ray radiation. This greatly
improved speak resolution enables much shorter data collects and
times and this is useful for instance for early age cement hydration
experiments where you want to have very short experiments measurements
for instance a couple of minutes you can discover the insides of a real lap defectometer
in this demonstration video, the video will also show you the
operation of the machine during an X-ray about infection measurement. So please
have a look at the demo.
Hello I am Dr. Reunee
And as you’ve been introduced, I will do the demo video. So here it
is our XRD diffractometer the X-ray
was generated by X-ray tube. Here we are going to use
use the characteristic reduces scene from copper the X-ray tube is
Cool, we use cooling water as the power of the X-ray.
defractometer was determined by the power of the tube and the processing
of the detector. Ideally the more powerful the better. Typical
a bold 3 X-ray tube is working at 45 kilowatt and 40 million M-B.
Unfortunately the age of the tube is limited because of the decay of the
intensity. Typically 10 percent per year. X3
passed through our set of opticals onto the samples then was
collected by that detector. the K.B. at the filter
namely that Neco filter is used to remove the key better radiation. The
set of metal plates called the soller slirt removed the
most diverging X-rays and leaving more parallel  X-ray to
pass. Our mosque is used to control the lens of the
extreme beams which is related to the size of the sample holder.
Rather important slirt called that divergences slirt is used to control the
viets of the beam which is related to the angular resolution of the
Pattern. The smaller the divergences the slirt we used, the higher
angular resolution. However the intensity of the diffracted
X-rays will be decreased when smaller divergences slirt was applied.
Sometimes the beam live just on top of the samples will be applied
to remove the scattering of the X-rays at more angles which is
important to the sample presenting peaks at lower angles.
Some of them post-state are equipped with the Sample spinner. Which rotates a
sample during that data acquisition. Whenever the spinner is available, It
is recommended to spin the sample to improve the statistics of the particles.
The configuration of the XRD are mainly to optimize the extreme beam to give the
highest intensity and the required angular resolution.
At the same time the beam over flow and the scattering at no angle
should be awarded. A range of 7 to 17 degree of two seater
using copper reducing for the data is usually enough to cover most
of the peaks for some cement related samples and scan speed can be wired from
lab to lab depend on the power of the XRD. Typically certain
minutes of scan within a range of 7 to 17 degrees is
good enough to perform the retail analysis. Well for
frist disks. The scan should be acquire within 15 minutes to (10:34)
drying and the combination of the free samples for some
specific cases such as a comparison of polymorphous tricalcium
syndicate enhanced angularity resolutions and peak intensity
for sneaked it's range of the pattern can be more used for instead of the four
pattern.