Now that you know how to prepare and measure your sample, it is time to have a look at the analysis
of the resulting data. The first step in this analysis is to
find out which phrases are present in your sample. This lecture will
give you a brief overview on how we identify phases
so-called qualitative phase analysis on your X-ray powdered diffraction data.
The qualitative phase analysis is based on a comparison of the peaks in
a measured XRD pattern to a large database containing Peak patterns
of many known phases usually a
database such as the powdered diffraction file database the PDF database published
by the ICDD. It's used. And this database
allows searching and matching in combination with chemical or categorical
filters to restrict the number of candidates that can match
your Pattern. Also open source databases exist such
as the COD database and the American mineralogist
database. As a general in help in phase
identification we have supplied you with a list of common phases in
funding cement. And this is also giving us a supplementary material to discuss.
This list can be used to build a custom database for cement phases for your
system and it can be used in combination with your specific
available such match software. Alternatively
there's also the classical way of doing such matching by rapid manual
identification by comparison for instance between a list of
XAD peaks of certain phases and peaks in your
pattern. We have also supplied such search match table
as a supplemental material to discus, and you can use it to
find difficult phases such as minor phases which have very low
peaks for instance. In the graph on the left side you
can see that there's the main problem of identification
which is peak overlap. If you look for instance at the overlap
between the C3S and the beater C2S Patten's
then you can see that the major peaks are actually completely overlapping which makes it very
difficult for any automatic face identification software
to find for instance better C2S in the system.
This way we also need to rely on other information such as
microscopic observations or knowledge of the poke sample
chemistry or just knowing what kind of phases can be present in your material
specifically for Portland cement and then hydrous Portland cements. It is very
useful to do some selective dissolution to identify minor phases. Having looked
at the example in this figure you can see that's for anhydrous Portland
cement. We have done two extractions through selective dissolutions that
either concentrate the calcium silicate. This happens with
a potassium hydroxide per sugar extraction in the green curve
or we did an extraction of this solution with salicylic
acid and methanol in which we have a residue, a solids residue that is
concentrated in the aluminates ferrites and alkali sulfates phases.
For instance when comparing the poke sample in purple
below with the SAM extracted sample, you can see that there is a
very large increase in the peaks of ferrites and of alkali sulfate phases
for instance ferrite around 12 degrees and alkali sulfate phases in the
range of twenty to twenty five degrees C theater. As
Well, this selective dissolution method can be used to
identify whether there's any polymorphs in your sample. For instance what might, one may
really look at any polymorphs of C2S or there’s autonomic or
cubic C3A in the Portland cement. Finally the
XRD pattern fitting procedures in quantitative phase analysis often
indicate a presence in the difference or residual curves of minor
retrace phrases that were previously hidden by extensive peak overlap
with major phases.
Therefore an alliterative procedure that goes back and forth between
phase identification and phase quantification is very common
and very useful in obtaining a complete analysis.
From this session on we will show you how do analysis using exactly data.
Here are the files we are going to use for the demo. You can find the templates
as well as that Commercial file and the Mac Cagney excel files
all of the cemented  data structures are available in zip files in this
Folder. The demo will be shown step by step. Part one
is the identification, part two use simple retroviral analysis
Part three where these are Wang’s quantitative phase analysis.
The samples used for demo videos are simple binary Mixer made
of calcites and corks, anhydrous Portland cement
typical Sims including flowers and snack and fernery hydrated
Cement. Them demo are mainly based on the software called
HighScore plus from panalytical, a quick demo on how to use the open source
software quite X-2 for identification. And this has2
for quantification we are also be covered to enable your own practice in case
there there's no access to HighScore plus. Let's get started with a
quantitative analysis. Simple demo using Coushatta and course
Mixture. open the HighScore plus software.
Then create a new file now inset the file. Now
Inset the data. You can change the scale of the y axis to any near
square root or a LOG scale to check the details of the peaks, more
details such as the configuration of the diffractometer in the skin
can be found in the optic inspector, to do the identification.
There are three steps. First determine the back ground of the pattern
second search the peaks in the pattern. You can see the peaks on top of the
Pattern, the black v marks means that the peaks
are a lot identified. Then the search match. There are a lot of cards in
the database. It is better to know some background information for the sample, such as
the category of the sample. For example inorganic or organic
chemical compositions, crystallography information and the potential phases in the mixture
those restrictions can be very helpful to improve the search match.
We wish you all these functions in the coming demo. Here we just
search high quality cards using star  and indexed after
Search match the candidates are sure in the candidates nest, the score
indicates how good the candidates and matches the experiment pattern.
You can check the details of this card by double clicking the sneaked cards.
We accept the first proposed candidate the calcites. The remarks are
removed for all order matched peaks with calcites. After taking the
next candidate's corpse most of the peaks are identified for each phase
we peaked. It is recommended to take a relative's transmit by I focusing
on the three strongest peaks the remaining tiny peaks are from the keep it all resito
The demo on quite X-2 for
identification. Import a diffraction data.
Then go to search to search match the candidates from the candidates nest and just
accept them matched phases similar to a HighScore plus were being applied
to Tick's matches of the peak, mixture or most of the peaks
are matched. MOR, flash and snacked
for this 2 demo, we wish you the typical pattern is for our amorphous humps
and the Samples are Mainer amorphous with a small amount of questioning phases. And it is more challenging to
make the decision of the final candidates since there are samples. If there is no
information about this samples. For such kind of samples, the
identification must be done with special care by taking as much information as possible
such as the chemical composition. For Flash, there are a
lot of amorphous content which gave us a hemp here. Will this case the
Back run function which should be modified to follow the hump and just keep
the peaks by changing pattern metres. The back run function should just follow
the trend of lowest points on the pattern but should not goes into the peaks
it starts peaks then search match. We can always peaks the star
and index cards in the identification Weser search match the best
matches was the moonlight falling by course. We accept these two
candidates for the match by dragging the candidate into the accepted
Area. However there is still some tiny peaks which is not matched.
For example the peaker on circling the race by taking the rest of the candidates and
another pornimorph of silicon oxide. Namely those states were right matches the peaks
now all the peaks are identified. For slack
we also see the amorphous hump. The strategy for the band wand is similar to the one
for Flash, follow the lowest point of the pattern but never
go into the peaks. You've researched peak quickening and there are only
three peaks in the pattern. We are applying the search match without any restriction.
Most of the candidates are quite stringent as the elements of those for sure that
they in the sample. This is mainly because of the relative no concentration of the
Crystal phasing in this sample. It's put some restrictions to
the search match. For example the search file minimal related carts, refine the
search match and then we got courts and on the top least
when taking the chemical comparison of the sample. We know that there are small amount of silicon
oxide in the sample. So the president of course is reasonable.
Then there are some other strange candidates such as the ice and some rare earth
elements compound the possible candidates. Would that be the calcium
calcium carbonate, namely the calcites.
According to the chemical compilation from XRF
A demo on Portland cement, for Portland cement the challenge for
authentication is from the complexity on the cemenality  of the pattern for C3S and C2S
a lot of peaks are overlapped which makes the situation more
difficult. We do the same steps for the data of Portland cement in search of scan
determine the backgroung and then search of peaks. As we load the cement so there
is a mixing of cement and hydration product is
applied. The first candidate is the solid
solution for C3S with magnesium and aluminum. The second why in C3
is both give similar match score while the C3S matches better
when taking the peaks and around 15 degrees. Right
click to accept the candidate. Following the anhydrate. Then use
the C4F. Namely in the Braam interrupts. If you take a quick look into the
details of the cart for the rest of the faces you can get help from the
different types of restrictions to not create. For instance
there might be some Free nan left in the cement, if the centuries is not build on
really that restricts in based on elements can be used. We Peak's the
calcium and oxygen in this sample, there is only very small amount of free
Nyree. For Portland cement, there must be some C2S as we
know a mineral name of the beater C2S is called larite. Let's try those
restricting using streams before we use a lot of restriction
premise one must be cleared. Indeed if we
apply the restrict base standard mineral name, it would be easier to
locate the exact phase, you free just use the
elements or restrictions for the same chemical composition, there are some polymorph
which needs to be distinguished and to allow most of the peaks are
identified. There is no C3A found in the candidates neast.
We put some elements restrictions to find the C3A. There is a C3A we need
all the peaks and matches a pattern, and them
all hydrate to cement. Now we take a look of the hydrate cement, you can see
clear his ham forces H around certain degrees with copper radiation.
So the bad ones should be treated similarly to the flours and snacks. Following are
trained of the patterns as we know it is cement hydrates. So we apply
subfiles restriction with cement anhydrate. In this statical matches are
Alight. Here it appears as a solid solution of the C3S with
some magnesium and aluminum. Then the Portlandite which is the main
hydrate for cement. Then you can find the ettringite nature which appears
as calcium aluminate sulfate hydroxide hydrate. Also checks a peaks
in the pattern.  The complicity of the
hydrogen cement. Sometimes the software can not find out the potential candidate.
Easing. Then the restrictions can be used to simplify the search match Persia
neuron a C4F rags snony during the hydration process. It's located
this phase with the mineral name of remunerate. Same routine can be used for the
C2S Namely lelouch. Up to now all the Crystal phases in the hydro
cement space was identified and surprisingly we cannot find
the candidates for CSH in the database. It is nano Crystalline with
present it or hump instead of a set of peaks. The closest
crystal structure to CSH are the 11 hamstrung and 48 hamstrung top or more right structure
which is the most used Starling's factor for more though the CSH structure.