Once you have set of the x-ray de facto motive for your experiment.
Selected the appropriate optics and chosen the suitable measurement program for
your experiment. It is time to prepare your sample for measurements.
This lecture will treat the preparation of samples for XRD analysis and emphasize
key factors that may influence your results, in order to obtain accurate and
precise results from XRD analysis, one needs to correctly prepared the
materials. X-ray diffraction is based on two basic assumptions
Namely, first that the sample consists of an infinite number of crystallite
and second that those crystallite are randomly oriented. For semanticists
samples. We need to add a third important point. This is
that the sample mineralogy should be preserved
Altogether this can be summarized as the Rule of Three. First the bugs should
be sufficiently fine to have a large number of crystallite able to deflect at any angle.
Second the sample should be mounted such that any other effects
are avoided such as preferred orientation. And third the sample
mineralogy should be preserved as much as possible. To do this it is often
necessary to solve the hydration or hydrate samples.
Let's have a closer look at these three rules.
So now looking at powder fineness in more detail it is obvious that not only
you have to look at the represent, taking a representative sample but we also need
to make a powder whichever, which has a high number of particles that
can defect.
If we have a powder that has a large number of fine particles then you get a
representative of the measurements in which peaks can be repeatably
measurements. Basically this means that in practice
particle sizes of about 10 to 20 micrometers or less are required.
Ideally even smaller, smaller than 1 to 5 micro meters
in the graphs on the right side. You can see for instance the effect of material
fineness on the XRD patterns. On the
upper right, you can see 2 XRD scans of the same
material and Alight, synthetic Alight grind for two types.
One was thirty seconds which resulted in a rod of course Alight with a medium
grain size about 36 micro meters. The other one was a long grinding
thing of about 20 minutes which resulted in Alight particles of about two tree
trimming. You can see that for the sample that has been ground for a
longer time. The peaks I read a little bit broader and they are actually, when
looking at it in a mathematical way, they are more regular. In fact
having two large particles gives something like a spiky pattern and results in
Misfit's which then again results in larger amounts of
unknown or amorphous contents. This can for instance be seen in the
figure the lower right there
as a function of particle size of the powder, one shows one has
the, on the y axis the non-content or amorphous content analyzed by
real fact analysis. Here clearly one can see that if one
has two large particle size this one is actually measuring
a apparent or artificial amorphous content. This is
not true and this is actually related to sample misfit's or
XRD pattern misfits. So just grinding the sample to the
appropriate findings will enable to give you a much more
accurate assessment of the amorphous face level. However
one should be careful in grinding because extensive dry grinding in a dry medium
may lead to a more sization of sensitive soft phases.
So therefore for any phases that cannot be affected.
What grinding is preferable? This can be done on any
kind of clinker, Alights, Limestone anhydrous phases for instance by using grinding
media like as a propanol or ethanol. However
this is not possible for hydrated cements. Even this kind of treatment may
change the vulnerable hydrates assemblage, and therefore in those cases
it may be preferable just to gently drying the material and measure it a search or
to actually cut a slice from a hydrated cement based and measure depth fresh
It should be mentioned as well that spinning this sample in
the horizontal plane improves the statistics enormously by a factor of about
5. So this is definitely to be encouraged
or to be advised.
In your data collection strategies in Man-Thing the obtain
powders and slices onto the sample holders for quantity XRD following
X aspects should really be considered. In flat plate Blake reflection geometry
cas should be taken that the sample surface area and thickness are large enough to avoid
any beam overflow at low angles. Also too small
surface areas will lead to an underestimation of the peak
intensities at low angles and thus cause also some
diffraction peaks or increased background from the sample holder.
In case smaller sample holders are used or are only
available then one can still say of defectormeter optics by for
instance choosing smaller divergent slit especially for
phrases that show high peaks in low angle regions such as
actingguides or AFM phases, this beam over flow problem will lead to an
underestimation of their content and quantity phase analysis.
Other requirements are that the mount surface to be flat without
roughness and not tilted.
In order to avoid peak displacement or broadening associated to do sample hide
differences or misalignments. For hydrated cements
where we use cut slices we should polish those slices to remove any
inhomogeneity at the surface. And also the slice surface
should be correct carefully positioned at the A-line sample height for the measurements. Otherwise
we will have shifts in peaks positions. It should be clear that the hydrate assemblage
of cement and then particularly hydrated cements
are sensitive to surface exposure as an example. This
figure shows it changes in mineralogy of a fresh slice that was measured
before and after a two hour exposure to air inside the defectometer
not only fresh samples but also samples of which the hydration was stopped are sensitive to air exposure.
Hydration stoppage does reduce the sensitivity so much that it cannot overcome these
effect. Most characterization techniques of hydrated cements need the
hydration of the cement to be stopped or the sample to be dried.
Even if the hydration stoppage is not strictly necessary for XRD based studies
this is common practice mostly for practical reasons.
Arresting the hydration enables sample storage and the characterization of the same sample at the same
degree of hydration by different techniques. The primary aim of the
various available methods for hydration stoppage is that the properties of interest
of the hydrating cement, the face composition and case of XRD are preserved as
much as possible. To Stop the hydration of cement
the unbound water present in the killpalary post needs to be removed
water present in smaller gel pores are chemically bound into the hydration products would
preferable to be retained as its removal may really
cause the alteration of the hydrates or even the decomposition and micro
structural changes. There are two main ways to remove the water
either by direct drying techniques such as oven drying, vacuum drying or
freezing drying. Or second group of measurements
by solvent exchange in which water is replaced by an organic solvent.
Mostly isopropanol which is then afterwards evaporated.
The figure on the right shows a working principle of the different direct drying techniques
in oven drying, the temperature has increased at constant pressure until the phase
boundary the boiling point is reached and water starts evaporating.
To the contrary in freeze drying the sample is rapidly cooled by immersion in liquid nitrogen
and then the frozen water is being removed by decreasing the pressure
and then heating the sample until reaching the phase boundary at which the water is removed
by sublimation. Then, in vacuum
drying.
Water is being removed by just reducing the pressure buy a vacuum
pump and evaporation at low vacuum conditions
the results of a round robin test and hydration stoppage clearly show
that none of the hydration stopwatch methods leave the hydrates assemblage entirely intact.
in particular ettringite and AFM phases
are affected by dry, oven drying, freeze drying and vacuum drying
results in the removal of structural water and thus the decomposition
of the ettringite in the AFM phases. Oven drying was observed to
be more destructive than vacuum drying. And it appears that all daring drying
methods result in the dehydration of cement hydrates
in case of crystalline products. This may lead to decomposition. And then the
under-estimation of the face come on the hydration stop samples
solvent exchange techniques represent a more gentle way of removing the water
and that preserves better to microstructure and the hydrates of sample age. In the
Figure, you can see that the ettringite peak can still be recognized quite
cleanly in the methods that have used solvent exchange.
However when we look at the quantification results it is clear that also the ettringite
is lower in the solvent exchange samples compared to a fresh sample.
However Portlandite is much more resistant towards hydration surface and remains within the hour
preserved. The effective hydration stoppage by solvent exchange
when the hydrates assemblage is illustrated by XRD patterns and quantification results
for 28 days hydrated blend cement containing fly ash and limestone as
shown in the figures below. A comparison is made here between cuts
slices and crushed powders that are either measured fresh immediately after
cutting or crushing the sample or after hydration stoppage by
isopropanol exchange during one week, the cut slices were measured
with and without surface polishing to see the effect of this bullshit action.
You can see that isopropanol exchange during one week resulted in a reduction
of the ettringite and Hemmy cub aluminates quantification results of about 50
percent. The monocub Illuminati in Portlandite phases appear
much more resistance to solvent exchange. Sample
crushing lead to a decrease in monocub aluminates peak intensities and quantities.
And unpolished fresh slices were deficient in Portlandite and contained
about one half of percent of calcite more indicating that there was
some surface carbonation or decomposition of Portlandite
during the cutting. It should be mentioned as
well. That procedure that involve a shorter solvent period
on finer powders may result in less Portlandite
decomposition. This slide really summarizes the advantages and disadvantages
of working with fresh or dried hydrated cement samples.
The major advantage of measuring on fresh slices is that the hydrate assemblage is practically
undisturbed. If one can measure us immediately and rapidly
this is not possible if that's how the measurements take time or if the machine is not
immediately available. On the other hand dried samples resist much more
a much better combination and offer more flexibility in terms of
timing of the measurement and storage of the samples.
However also there it is advisable to limit the time between stoppage
and measurements as much as possible. Samples stored for more than
two weeks in a protected atmosphere start showing signs of combination on decomposition
already. The major downside is thus, that the ettringite and
AFM reflections are being reduced by any drying operation.
In this video we are going to show you how to prepare a sample for
XRD analysis the typical sample use are powders
the findings of the powders should be at least in less than 20 micromes and nearly
one to five microme to ensure a particle statistics. If the
samples are not Powderly it, mortar and pestle can be used to communist's
the sample. Wait Granny's preferred if you want to ground the
particles very fine. Another way
to improve the statistics of the Powder is to spin the sample for
dried hydrate cement the surface as well as the ages of the
sample should be removed because they can be carbonated during
that storage and sample preparation. ForNodine should be the most widely
used sample preparation method even though it is not the best because of the
simplicity of the sample Holder and the sample preparation. Take the
sample and distribute it into the cavity first parade and sample in
the cavity with the aid of the sample live at the end playing
surface of the powders. Make sure the surface is the most and the powder is
Packed. Back loading is recommended for powder sample.
potentials preferred orientation is the preferred
orientation will be an issue for RIT for analysis even if we can correct it
Mathematically. It is better to our word during the sample preparation
clean the state fix the top part of the sample holder on those things
through the half of the cavity with the powder spread the powder and press
everything to make you pack them, then fill the rest space with more
powder. Further spread the sample in the cavity with the aid of the sample
Live. At the end. Claim the surface of the powders and remove the
excess  part. And Mark the top piece and put back
snore part of the sample holder current over a sample holder
turnover the sample holder to get the resist state. Rotate the sample holder or about 10 degree
and then remove it from the States. Clean the ages of the sample
Holder, when there are not enough samples to fill the
cavity of the sample holder, The so called Zero back one sample holder
can be used to support the limited amount of sample. First fix a
zero mag 1 slice to the sample holder spread the tiny
amount of sample on disc, try to make a smooth surface if possible
specifically for hydrate cement paste. The card snipes can be
directly used for XRD analysis. The refrace
flies was proved to be the best Sample stators for hydrate cement and
there is no damage for the hydrates that as ettringite. There
are free Snickers slice at specific ages is polish using a
number of hundred sandpaper to make sure the surface is flat and
what's new with distilled water or a piece of tissue is
immediately covered with slice to prevent the water
evaporation.
Know the piece of sample in the sample holder and fix it. In the case of
Fristics the data collection should be done as soon as possible to be Coney
within 15 minutes. This is to award a drawing and the combination
of the samples.
However to work with cost slice is more demanding to the availability
of the X-ray of.