Hello.
Today is about measuring impact
Why measure impact?
Because while planning,
we still don't know if our plan,
if our forecast,
has a positive impact,
whether we're going
in the right direction,
towards set goals.
Due to this, we need to measure.
In order to measure,
we need a number of key indicators.
This is what we'll discuss
in today's video.
The basics of monitoring,
when we want to understand,
we want to see how things
are going in cities,
we need a starting point,
we need a benchmark.
We need to know
what the starting data value was
and from there we can monitor
its development.
However, we need to have a starting point.
Clearly we need important data.
When it comes to measuring impact,
having two or three elements
of data won't suffice.
An array of data is needed,
and that data needs to be updated.
Again, there is no point
in having benchmark data
if we are unable,
if we don't have the resources,
we don't have the means
to update the data daily.
Monitoring, assessment,
is carried out to evaluate
our set objectives.
We're not looking to have
knowledge for its own sake,
we want to know whether or not
the goals we set have been reached.
Then, once we've looked at our objectives,
assessed whether our goals
were reached or not,
monitoring should then
assist the decision making.
It is therefore a cycle, like so,
where we will gradually understand
what is happening, see whether
we've met our objectives
and close the feedback loop
in order to redefine future objectives.
So this also helps in our decision making.
Measuring the impact of our plan
should help with the future decisions
of that same plan.
As we have already seen,
in order to measure impact,
to be able to measure,
to find that measurement,
we need an indicator.
An indicator could be
a figure, a percentage,
but it is an element of knowledge,
of a theme.
What is an indicator?
An indicator can be a measure,
a measure which links
information about a theme
or which can highlight specific issues.
But an indicator can also be a variable,
as information simplification.
And in this way we can also highlight
a certain number of trends.
An indicator can also be a model.
A model is a simplification
of a specific subject,
usually a complex one.
Therefore we're trying to model,
or in other words,
we're trying to render
relatively complex processes
understandable to the average person.
The role of these indicators,
is to enable assessment.
So it's at the same time,
from a diagnostics perspective,
it allows us to capture
the current situation of a city
and it also allows us
to assess impact.
Therefore, they're used both as
diagnostic tools and measures of impact,
two different things.
If we look at crime rates,
they are a measure of impact.
If I look at the square footage
of industrial areas,
it's not an impact, it's diagnostics.
There are two types of measurements,
two types of indicators,
some used more diagnostically,
and others as a measure of impact,
with an overlap area
in the middle, of course,
and some which belong
to both categories.
With time, indicators went from being
exclusively economic data.
It was the first type
of data we had regarding cities,
to more social and environmental data.
We've also moved away
from quantitative data
to more qualitative data.
Therefore, indicators can come in
many shapes or forms.
They can be in the form of raw data:
the price of bread,
the price of electricity, ratios,
the link between the number
of linear feet of roads
and the population of a city,
which gives us an idea
of the rate of development.
The rate of road growth and networks,
the recovery of roads
by the city's road administration,
based on the population, of course.
We can also look at percentages,
we've mentioned crime rates,
it may be the one used most often.
Percentages show the rate
of urban development.
There are other types of indicators,
however, we won't look at them all today,
but just keep them in mind:
ratios, percentages or raw data.
Examples of urban indicators:
infrastructures, linear footage,
the development of infrastructure
housing, the amount of housing built,
as well as parks and gardens,
which is a bit of an extreme case
for our African cities,
but could we imagine an indicator
of the same size as parks
or garden in cities.
As for measures of impact,
we look at percentages of course,
crime rates, everything that
has to do with the population's health
in its very structure,
as well as questions like air quality.
There you go.
Here, too, there are hundreds,
hundreds and hundreds,
there is a considerable amount
of indicators.
The point, however, was simply
to give you 2 or 3 indicators
to help to explain the difference
between indicators used for planning
and ones used as measures of impact.
Concerning impacts,
we can have various themes,
we are especially looking at
social and environmental issues,
as, indeed, we need to understand
what is being measured.
We can measure the extent
of public policy, for example;
it's one of the measurement
possibilities that we have.
We need a clear objective
in order to measure an impact,
which allows us to see whether or not
we've reached said objective,
as well as a report
on the current situation.
Trying to measure objectives is useless
if you don't know the current situation.
So, if I want to look at a theme,
we could look at transportation,
more specifically, we can look at
the number of subway stations
within a 500-meters radius,
and then, we know that
the objective would be
for 50% of the population to live
in a perimeter which is less than
500 meters from a subway station.
Currently, we're maybe at 12%,
therefore, we see there is a huge gap.
We're at 12%, and we need
to get to our goal of 50.
From here, we can therefore
gradually measure
where we stand,
year after year,
at year 1, year 2, year 3
at first we'll be at 12,
then maybe 16%, then maybe 20,
and then we may decide
that this goal of reaching 50%
is maybe too high, therefore,
we will re-evaluate,
and lower this objective to 45%.
We'll then go through the same process.
We'll re-evaluate the objective
and we'll make a loop, in this way,
to see whether or not
the objective we set is attainable.
An example of a theme: urbanization.
This may involve relatively simple
and obvious issues such as
square footage per capita,
size of land per capita , acreage used,
but we could say we want,
as large a ratio as possible
of water distribution per capita.
So, we know, for example,
that 10% of the population
has direct access to a water tap
and one of the objectives
would be to reach, within 10 years,
20% instead of 10.
So, these are simple things
which are relatively easy to set up.
It still requires us to know
the benchmark data, the 10% benchmark,
the current situation,
with the assumption that
we will continue to measure,
year after year or every 2 to 3 years,
to see the situation as it is, in order
to compare with that first figure.
Therefore, it is useless
to have the benchmark situation
if afterwards we don't monitor the project,
and if data isn't gradually collected,
we won't know how far we've come.
And during a plan's assessment,
if I haven't looked retrospectively
at the benchmark data
used to draw up the plan,
then it serves me no purpose.
We can say if it's good or bad,
if it works on not,
but we won't know whether or not
the objectives were set.
And in African cities a lot of work
remains to be done.
Not only do we have issues about
implementing urbanization plans,
but we are unable, today, to measure
the impact of what we're planning.
And this remains
an open field since, to date,
no one has truly taken it seriously.
Of course, we have lots of departments,
lots of ministries where these things
are being or will be taken care of,
but the true impact
of the urbanization plan is that
we're still having difficulties
finding a satisfying example.
Who uses what?
We have a list of different parties here,
a list of indicators, and certain parties
need a certain number of indicators,
others don't need any.
Let's look at two examples.
If I'm an urban planner,
a city's population
is a relevant indicator for me,
as I need to plan out the city.
The rate of urbanization
is also an important figure to me.
If I am in the private sector,
with independent concerns
regarding populaion
then maybe it wouldn't be
the indicator I would need.
If I'm a NGO, if I am
an international agency,
if I'm the mayor of a city or
a minister of urban development,
then my objectives aren't the same.
Therefore, for each different objective,
we'll have different indicators.
And so, for each party, there will be
different indicators.
So, once you have your indicators,
it's important to know
whom they'll serve,
in which conditions and which contexts.
How to select indicators?
How should an indicator be?
It should be broad.
It should provide a general overview.
It's not partial, it has to be descriptive
about the city as a whole.
An indicator should also be measurable.
It's important as we need to know
where we came from and where we're going
An indicator should be understandable.
If it is understood only by
a small number
of specialists, it's useless;
it should be understood by everyone.
An indicator needs to
take into consideration the poor,
clearly, as they make up
the majority in cities.
If all your indicators combined
don't establish a clear picture
of the situation
and don't include the poor,
then your indicators
were not chosen appropriately.
Indicators should also be independent.
They should not reflect bias,
They shouldn't serve a specific ideology,
but be fully independent,
And finally, they should be
available, obviously,
since an indicator which is not available
to everyone, to the parties who need it,
serves absolutely no purpose.
There you go, a few words.
Don't forget that if you want
to measure, you need indicators.
In order to use indicators,
you need a starting position
and an ending position,
which allows an in-between measure,
and for this data is needed.
This data is costly in human resources,
it is financially costly,
and that's usually where
the problem arises,
as we don't necessarily have the means
to carry out urban monitoring,
which allows us to know if our plan
was well implemented or not.
Therefore, we should start
on relatively simple systems at first
with fewer indicators, wait it out,
see if it works,
see if they're useful
when it comes to decision making,
if we're able to objectively measure
what we've set up,
and if it is so we can then
make it more complex.
But never start out
with something too complex
as you won't be able
to update your indicators.
That's it, we'll stop here.
We have now seen
how to design a plan,
how to measure our results--
We're ready!