Hello.
A synopsis, a few conclusions.
It's nearly the end of our course,
our second-to-last video,
and we'll very briefly review
the material we've covered,
not all of its elements, of course,
since it took us these last
12 weeks to cover them,
but I would like to focus today
on a few important points.
The first is that we must keep in mind
that urbanization,
this phenomenon that African cities
are part of on such a broad scale,
is a global phenomenon.
Africa is relatively behind when it comes
to the processes of urbanization
in other continents.
So there is enormous growth potential,
and thus it is in Africa where
we have the highest urbanization rates.
We must also keep in mind
the various contexts.
We indeed speak of African cities,
not of the African city, why?
Because, as we see in these few images,
the realities are extremely
different if we are in the Sahel
if we are in southern Africa,
if we are in English-speaking areas
or French-speaking ones,
in North Africa or the sub-Sahara.
So we have contexts and realities
which are extremely different.
Meanwhile there are a certain
number of commonalities,
which enable us to reflect
on African cities.
A few figures, always
a few figures to start out.
As we see, the percentages
of urban population,
which in Africa is less than 40%,
so there is significant room for growth,
and this is why one of the challenges
for the African continent
over the next few years
will surely be the issues
of urbanization.
Perhaps one of the most important charts
for an understanding of the African city,
shows that 57% in 2010, here,
57% of the African
population live in cities
of fewer than 500,000 inhabitants.
And finally that cities of
at least 5,000,000 inhabitants
represent only 7% of the entire
urban population of Africa.
So if we wish to study
the African city,
it is the middle-sized city
which should be studied,
and it is a city that has between
one and five-million inhabitants,
a city which is usually
the capital of the country.
So we find there is a very large
percentage of people
who live in cities of between
one and five-million inhabitants.
This urban phenomenon surfaces
along with the huge changes
which have occurred
over the last few decades.
The first is that the city is no longer
a closed and discrete system,
but instead a sprawling one
which extends beyond its borders.
The second change of this urban
phenomenon is that of lifestyle,
or rather consumption patterns,
where there we tend to find
certain types of lifestyles,
particularly among the elite,
on every continent,
in every country or African city,
we have the same lifestyles,
or perhaps lifestyles
which tend to be similar.
And then we have the emergence
of new centralities.
Old cities fade away, certainly,
to leave room for cities
which are much newer and more dynamic,
in economic or demographic terms.
So there is a reshuffling of the cards,
on a global level but also
on a continental one,
with the emergence of new centralities.
We've also seen in this course that
there are different forms of urbanization,
five of them,
which vary from shantytowns
to large business areas,
passing by residential enclaves,
gentrified neighborhoods,
and large residential suburbs.
So these are the forms of urbanization;
these allow us to understand
where people live.
Likewise, we have noted some of
the challenges which have emerged,
particularly that of an urbanization
implemented without economic development.
Urbanization, in the books on
the development of cities,
is normally tied to economic development.
There, this is not the case.
We have urbanization which breaks away
from this economic development.
A new factor is climate change,
which is not unique to Africa,
but affects all countries in the world,
but it is this new factor which
requires different planning
in relation to this climate change.
An important challenge: the periphery,
the pressure which will be placed
on the suburbs.
Here we are in the suburbs of Accra.
And the major challenge
of urbanization in Africa
over the next few decades
will be the existing urban periphery
of cities not yet subject to urbanization.
That's where the challenge is.
The challenge lies not in
the center of the city,
not in the densification of
existing suburbs,
it is in the periphery to come.
There is an important challenge
because we are speaking of surfaces
which are basically
a natural environment,
and the main challenge is
to propose a form of urbanization
which takes into account at once
the issue of nature
with that of building.
All this is done against
a backdrop of general mobility,
in which people are
more and more mobile,
they move more and more
with all that that entails,
which is to say that infrastructure
is needed to allow for this mobility.
We've seen four major challenges
when it comes to the city of tomorrow--
the right of every person to live
and move about in the city;
the challenge of climate, as discussed;
the decrease in mobility.
We know that mobility options
are ever expanding,
but we must reduce
and regulate these mobilities.
And, finally, to redefine
democratic forms.
When it comes to cities,
decision-making and urban management
will not take place without a
redefinition of democratic forms.
We've just discussed
the paradoxes of planning,
particularly in relation
to climate change,
with on the one hand its mitigation
which leads to compact forms,
and the adaptation of changes
which perhaps favors urban sprawl.
We've discussed energy issues, density,
and here the annual fuel consumption
in relation to density per capita.
The denser the city,
the less fuel it consumes,
the more fuel consumed, the least dense.
There too we debated
modal shares of transport,
in relation to the GDP,
where we saw different models,
the American, the European,
and cities in development where the GDP
is still relatively weak,
and then the role of travel patterns
also presents a challenge,
to know whether to go in the direction
of a model which may be targeted,
with reduced energy use
when it comes to travel,
or if one adopts the American model,
which is highly consumptive.
We reviewed the different
types of planning,
which range from the strategic
to the programmatic,
and which are based on
the issues of land-use,
its definition, to more territorial issues
in view of the planning,
which passed from this part to that part
over the last few years.
But there still remains one framework,
which is precisely that which we see,
the framework that remains
exactly the same in this table or that,
with the same types of planning.
So there has been no paradigm shift,
the universe won't change
if we go from here to there.
On the contrary,
we do basically the same things,
leaning towards those things that are
more strategic and more territorial.
This is one of the conclusions midway,
that the paradigm shift occurred
between the first urban plans
which were subdivision plans,
where one had spaced out the streets
with the subsequent plans which were
more strategic and programmatic
but in which spatiality
no longer had a role.
We won't review all these things now,
we've already discussed them,
but there are good reasons to plan,
one does not plan simply
for the sake of planning.
One plans because it is useful.
We've seen how cities were identical,
that they had the same
segregative modes,
here, the example of Abidjan,
the example of Dakkar.
We've seen how the poor have
the same strategies in their cities,
we've seen how developers
are the same everywhere,
as are their financial backers.
There is, therefore,
a great proximity in African cities,
the same people who work,
with the same basic materials.
And this even though the contexts
are extremely different.
We have identical problems,
one of which is land tenure.
We can see in an image such as this one
how difficult it is to regulate
land-tenure issues.
But we also have
the same environmental problems
of circulation, poverty, segregation.
But there are limits to this planning.
We've seen in current plans,
the costs of urbanization
are not taken into account,
we see this also in current plans,
there is no mention of poverty,
it's as if the city had no poor people.
We also see that in current plans,
it's as if there existed
some sort of average man,
the invention of the Average Joe.
who is an inhabitant of the city
but who is unaccounted for,
and thus we see the disconnect
between management and planning.
So normally what one plans
is what will be subsequently managed.
And if the link is not very clear,
this will quickly present us with problems.
So we've advocated for a type of planning
that would put lifestyle, people
and their social activities,
at the center of the discussion
for a subsequent reworking of the plan
in favor of one which begins with people,
which focuses on the individual,
and which comes not from the exterior,
as is the case today.
Now, having said and seen all that,
we have of course imagined,
that we had, as always, our city,
as it exists today, of course,
but the city we're planning here,
which means that we have a time frame,
and within this city we have
different systems which function,
now it's hard to show,
but we have a spatial system,
an economic system,
a system of actors,
so these are the three things
which should be taken into account.
We are not speaking of issues
of programming and spatial planning,
but there is a very important
economic fact,
and above all a fact of governance
or of the system of actors,
which is very, very important.
These cities present a certain number
of challenges, as we've seen,
the right to the city, as we've seen,
the decrease in mobility,
we'll indicate the challenges
with our little green marks here,
of course it's throughout the city
that we find challenges,
and then we have an equal number
of constraints, challenges,
which put pressure on us, here,
major issues, of course,
we know them well,
the issues of durability,
the issues of environment,
the issues of poverty,
or that of the climate.
There is a multitude of
very important, very diverse issues,
and these will affect our cities.
There you have it,
a brief summary of our city,
with the need for negotiation
between elements,
between different systems,
different stakes, different challenges,
between the questions we must pose,
the choice of societies,
we must negotiate these-- Why?
Because, to begin with, we must
link together these different elements
so that they can coexist,
yet we'll quickly realize that
there are a certain number
of roadblocks which are impassable.
that cannot be linked,
and at this point we must negotiate
between the two.
Will I choose to adapt to climate change,
or instead to mitigate it?
This is a negotiation, these are
the choices one must make.
And planning is simply
a series of choices.
It's nothing other than a series
of links and negotiations.
If we were to summarize it,
this is how we would summarize
this type of urban planning.
But we must always keep in mind
that we deal with what already exists,
but when we embark on any future planning,
we become part of a system of actors,
whether the inhabitants,
the politics, the NGOs, private entities,
we form part of a group of actors
whom we must consider,
we are part of an economic system,
who will pay for the city?
We are also in a spatial system
where we must make
a certain number of decisions.
There you have it.
We've summarized in a few minutes
our 12 weeks of class.
I won't revisit the impact
these plans have,
since we spoke of that
in the previous video,
but would like to quickly
refresh your memory
and show you two things of importance,
the linking of domains,
one no more important than the next,
and negotiation, which are
the social choices we will make.
We must be pragmatic
when it comes to planning,
basing ourselves on what exists,
we only do things
which can be implemented,
utopias are interesting,
but the urgency of planning in Africa
reserves the utopia for a future agenda.
The utopia is the final objective,
but we must be pragmatic today,
quick, but also reflective.
We should not rush things,
but reflect quickly,
respond rapidly,
and put in place these systems
which are sustainable and which
we don't need to alter every six months
because we've made mistakes.
So the main objective is
the sustainability of the system.