Hello,
A warm welcome to this MOOC course for electrotechnic 1
that I shall give during this semester
with Paolo Germano.
Electricity is a relatively recent
scientific and technical subject
that opened up in the 19th century
but that appears in many
technical achievements.
Several subdomains have appeared
that all depend on
applications of electricity,
ranging from communications to energy.
Electronics, which in itself can be distinguished
between control electronics
and power electronics;
the technical information that includes
the domain of integrated circuits,
the brains of information processing ;
remote transmission,
telephones, televisions and GPS ;
electrical energy, including
generation, transmission, distribution
and conversion of energy, the measures,
their transmission and their management.
All of these domains and subdomains
depend upon electrotechnics
that we shall discover
during this semester.
Before starting this course,
I would like to give you a preview
of what we do here,
at EPFL, in a laboratory,
the laboratory of integrated actuators,
that is part of the Microengineering Institute.
What is microengineering ?
Microengineering is at the heart of
a certain number of applications
such as watches, robotics,
applications that, of course
that combine precision,
that combine the link between energy,
between information,
between  mouvement
between sensors, between optics, etc.
You can see here, on the image
3 automata that we call
the Jaquet-Droz automata
-born in the 18th century-
which are, in fact, the first
completely mechanical robots,
born from the absolutely incredible
ingenuity of Mr. Jaquet-Droz.
Who was followed by a great
man such as Mr. Breguet,
who invented the perpetual
self-winding watch
and whereby, in the
Jura part of Switzerland
between the Vaud, Neuchatel
and Jura cantons
we find what is known as
the cradle of microengineering,
that of course also extends
to neighbouring France
and where we find a certain
number of businesses
linked to microengineering
that do, even today,
very high microengineering.
The laboratory finds itself in domains
at the heart of different subjects
such as electromagnetism, electornics,
mechanics, data processing
but also material sciences,
as we shall see later on.
Domains such as micro-motors,
energy transfer, electronics,
piezoelectric motors,
or even haptic devices,
are our topics of predilection
within the laboratory
of integrated actuators.
Quickly, we realized that one
of the key pieces
to enable miniaturisation,
is to be able to integrate
different movements
and different functionalities
within a system.
You have here several
images that show you
how these functionalities
can be integrated.
For example here, the lens of a DVD
reader, where the lens must focus
the laser beam on the optical disc
with a precision better than a micron.
And this must be done in
the vertical direction
but also in the lateral direction,
and you have here a microsystem
that allows the adjustment of
the position of the lens within a micron
in two different directions.
So here is an actuator.
Here as well, a micro-motor of
a few millimetres in diameter
that can nonetheless turn
at 100 000 rotations per minute
and its command electronics
are much bigger than
the motor itself.
Or even a hard disk motor,
here, alongside a coin
just to show you the
link between the size
and that currently allows us
a very powerful miniaturisation.
As I have mentioned, integration
is at the heart of our activities
to allow - not for this lens
of a DVD for example,
to add two systems one upon the
other to make an XY table -
but to combine two
systems together
allowing the combination of
ingenuity and microengineering
to solve a problem in proper manner.
Or even here, you can see a motor.
Here, a motor of an ancient belt DVD
with four coils that
you can clearly see here
that are in fact a transformation of
the information of the belt sensor
that transfers without contact the
information within the motor.
Another element that we work on
is transmission of
energy without contact,
here, a project that
we have worked on
where we can see the belts
a lateral belt here
- we can see them better here -
with a test bus that allows
supplying power to the cart.
These carts, as we can see, move along
an assembly line.
Thus, the goal is to make
assembly lines
with these small independent modules .
And to go to the cleanroom,
well, the rubbing of
these brushes on these bands
creates too much dust.
Thus, the idea here was to
create an entirely contactless system.
This contactless system is
reused here for a project
with a local business,
that we've managed to implement
with the help of the CHUV
hospital of Lausanne
with problems where
energy need to be transmitted
within the human body.
You can see here an in vivo
experiment where we placed a "secondary",
It's a coil, here, on a flex print,
directly attached to the intestine.
We close the intestine and, from the outside,
we will activate the intestine
for people who have
chronic constipation problems
or severe problems
of gut motility.
Another application that
we've managed to do
for the company Logitech
is here a testing bench, a table,
upon which we can
place any object
and this object will be
supplied in energy.
The laboratory also works
on micro-motors
or very special motors.
We've also had the
opportunity of working
for very ambitious projects
on artificial hearts.
You have here one of the in vivo
experiments that has been done.
This has been done
in collaboration with Montreal,
with, here, a motor
with its titanium shell.
Blood is used to
cool down the motor
and this part here, of the motor
will find itself completely immersed
within the left ventricle.
Several other applications :
we've worked on
a piezoelectric bistoury,
we shall see later on
what we mean by "piezoelectric".
It's a crystal that
we vibrate
and we got the idea
of making a bistoury
that can choose the tissue
that it is in the process of cutting,
in particular for high risk
operations, like for example,
working on the
intervertebral disks
with the spinal cord
that is very close here,
thus the risk of harming the
patient is relatively high
and to be able to have a bistoury
capable of selecting
a soft or hard tissue,
endues an immense advantage for
the surgeon that is operating.
Here is a piezoelectric
actuator
as I was describing it earlier
and that can
thanks to its vibrations
and to the fact that
we are acting based on a contact
between the vibrating part
and the stationary part,
finally create movement.
Thus you have here
a small linear actuator
that was created in our laboratory
and that make you better understand
how this system works,
we have prepared a small
animation, to show you
how, by increasing the vibration
at the tip of the system,
you can see here how it vibrates
"in the same manner as a fin",
like a fish in fact
and the tip of this "fin"
will touch the stator
and induce a movement.
And for two different frequencies,
we can create a going movement
or a coming movement.
We've also worked on
focusing lenses.
You can see here this lens in green,
with a small box
that doesn't measure
more than 5 by 5 millimetres.
And within, you have a small
piezoelectric system described here,
or even with a picture here,
with a matchstick to give
a sense of the size of this object
that will in fact, this small actuator,
make the lens go up and down
to focus on the image.
And here are some piezoelectric
elements that are used
in the industrial domain.
And finally, the use of piezoelectrics
can also be done to create
tactile impressions.
We've made here
- on an Ipod, a fake Ipod -
a wheel under which there
is a piezoelectric crystal
that is put in vibration.
The quarter, here, is shown to you
and you can see a wave
from this piezoelectric
that will happen on this wheel.
By placing a finger on this wheel,
the piezoelectric, through its vibration,
creates a film of air that will give you
the impression that your finger is sliding.
When in fact,
the matter has not changed.
By actuating and by
stopping this principle,
we can create an impression of
sliding, rubbing, sliding, rubbing,
and thus, give a tactile sensation
or a tactile impression to the user
and thus create a sort of
virtual tactile system.
Knowing that there are also
several modes of vibration,
we intend to continue work
for the next several years
to even give an impression
of patterns to this tactile impression
and not just an on/off
change of the state
of impression of sliding
and not sliding.
You also have here an image
of a robotic system
that takes pieces on a part,
here in color
- you have pieces, here, that arrive
on this part, that are dispersed -
we wish to, with the help of
this piezoelectric system,
move these pieces in a
given direction
and to know very precisely  the position
of this small pieces of balls
that are included here in the video.
A few other elements :
magnetic fluids.
You can see, here on top, a fluid
known as "magnetorheological",
this means that its
viscosity will depend
on the magnetic field
that goes through this fluid.
We are researching actuators
that use this principle.
And below, an small
amusing video
to show that we can also work
with these magnetic fluids
and make them climb, like so,
this conic structure.
You can see here,
an explanation of a haptic glove
where we've used
- here on this haptic glove -
a small system that works
with magnetorheological liquids.
The hybrid MEMS
motor can also show you
the integration on which
we are working.
We had the idea of making
a stator printed on silicon
with a magnet, we'll say "classical",
that we place above, here,
the silicon.
Why ?
To make an extremely tiny motor
and thus, finally, stators can be
made like hotcakes.
You can see here a nice photograph
where we can see a layer of copper
and behind, transparent,
the other layer of copper
and we can like this,
sandwich
different layers of copper
on each other
with here canals that are used
to link the different layers together
to create a true winding.
You have here the finished motor
along with a matchstick, again
to show you the size.
The efficiency is of more than 45%,
which, compared to the
currently used 15% motor
enables us to
extend the battery
life cycle from two
years to about six.
Thus, the ecological impact by making these
kind of changes or these type of
integration studies is phenomenal.
This allows me to arrive
- now that you have seen
all that can be done in electrotechnics
and it's not an exhaustive -
all of this applications
that I've shown you
use the basis of
electrotechnics.
And thus, it is one of the first
engineering branches
in the microengineering course.
but just there : mechanics,
materials, robotics...
All of these courses do
and use electrotechnics.
We can thus make a definition :
it would be
"the technical use of electricity,
either as a energy support,
or as an information support ".
And, as you have seen it,
an application to a very large
number of other disciplines
that use electric circuits
as a basic mapping.
Electrotechnic isn't that kind of
image where you can see that
to go straight,
you have to go left.
And you also shouldn't think to yourself
"Absolutely go here !", no.
We will try to give you clues,
provide you with methods
that will allow you to
make the best choice
when faced with a
electrotechnic problem.
And what you must also know,
is that electrotechnic,
as a discipline of electricity,
does not only apply
to electricity but
as I've mentioned
to electronics,
but also to electric machines,
to micro-actuators,
thus to electromagnetism.
And also, this may
seem strange,
to mechanical and thermal engineering,
because, in fact, we can
model thermal flow
by equivalent electric diagrams
and thus reuse
all this formalism
and methods studied
in electrotechnics,
with the help of the basics of electrotechnics
that we shall see here.
Thus, the writing, symbolic
and schematics that we shall see here
will be fundamental
elements to be able to make
a coherent engineer's language
for all disciplines.
Here again, for example,
a wonderful application of the engineer
that benefited from the works
of electrotechnics
and electromagnetism.
This is a hard disk motor
relatively ancient, from the 1990s,
and that shows you here two actuators :
one that enables
the rotation of the hard disk,
and one that will actuate,
you can see here the linear actuator,
the playhead or playheads
the support the sensor.
Another example of miniaturisation
that again calls for all of this
it's a watch that is made
by a Swiss company,
that's called the touch
and you have here, in fact
two actuators on this same watch,
on the front and back.
So first two-phased motors
that will allow each
to command a needle
-since these needles are
independent from each other
for the different functionalities
that are presented -
and then, a small vibrator, here,
that will allow to give out a silent
alarm within the watch.
Other natural phenomena,
such as here, this magnificent
double lightening on Lake Leman,
can be explained
or can be formalised
by what we will see
in electrotechnics.
But also, here, three micro-tornadoes
on Lake Neuchâtel, in Switzerland,
that can also be, using fluid
mechanics, approached by
simplified models that call
for the schematics of electrotechnics.
This is the program of the course
I shall be offering you,
it's to first tackle conventions
and symbols,
very important, since around the world
we don't all have the same way of
writing or conceiving the schematics.
Thus, to agree for
the beginning of this course.
Then, we shall see the laws of Kirchhoff,
the basis of electrotechnics
and electricity.
Afterwards we shall study
the analysis of circuits
that will lead us to offer you
a certain number of methods
that will allow you
to solve circuits.
You will have the choice
of the methods,
and it is through the
exercises that we will offer
that you will better feel the way
and which methods to finally use
for your own circuit solving.
Finally, we will move on to
sinusoidal steady state
that will later bring us
to the study of power
to finish the first course.
To conclude I wish
you all the best
and will re-join you in lesson
number two of this MOOC 1.