Hello and welcome to this third
lesson of Electrotechnics 1
dedicated to the fundamental
laws of electricity.
After an introduction, we will see
what are electric charges
and electric potentials,
followed by the capacitor,
the electric current, the
associated Joule losses,
we will discover Ohm's law,
Kirchhoff's laws and finally,
the inductance which will conclude
this chapter on the fundamental laws
along with a small conclusion.
The electrostatic charge is a
quantity of static electricity,
The representative symbol,
It's the letter Q
the unit of measurement is the
coulomb, whose symbol is C,
So we have one coulomb is equal
to one ampere second and this,
the letter Q, is
the electrostatic charge.
We can also
define a very
important element in
the laws of electricity,
it's the difference of
electric potential.
We will write here the difference of
potential between two points Va and Vb
that we imagine in a system like this,
bathed in a uniform electric field,
that we write like this, and
we have our electric field here
and our conductor, A and B bathed
in this uniform electric field.
We also define a
distance vector ds
here on this conductor
between A and B.
We can then write, I'll continue here,
the difference of potential
Va - Vb, as being
the circulation of the electric field
along the edge linking A to B
which becomes the integration from
B to A of this electric field
by this element of distance ds
or also, by reversing from A to B,
the minus sign disapears
and by definition this is the
difference of potential between A and B
that we also call voltage.
it is this voltage that will
keep us busy all along
these Electrotechnics 1 and 2 MOOCs,
and we will progressively start
saying only voltage
and by extension, no longer
the difference in potential.
The condenser is a very important
element in electrical engineering,
one of the three passive elements that
we will study all along this MOOC.
Its symbol is represented
by two vertical plates
upon which will in fact
accumulate, electric charges
that will characterize the
properties of the capacitor.
We can say that this property
of the capacitor, also known as capacitance,
this capacitance C
is defined as
the number of accumulated charges
between the plates of the capacitor,
these plus and minus that
are in front of each other,
divided by the voltage between A and B,
we will thus also define here
an A and B potential.
The symbol, the unit of the capacitance
is the farad, written F,
and one farad is worth
one ampere second per volt
in the units of the MKSA
international system.
We can now go one step further
and define the relationship
between voltage and current
for this capacitor
which will be very
useful later on,
we've seen with Ohm's law,
we will see it for the inductor,
we need this relationship
between voltage and current
to later on solve
electric circuits.
We've already seen the electric charge,
this electric charge
we know, is an accumulation of
charges, in other words
it's the integration of
the current over time,
since current is in fact this
progression of charges in a circuit,
we can define here, by substitution,
the voltage which is equal to
1/C
integral of of idt,
by replacing with the
equation seen here.
Or,  also write that the
current is the capacitance
times the variation of the voltage,
one or the other.
As we can see here
the relationship is nonlinear
and the voltage in a
capacitor is proportional
to the integral of the
current over time.
Let us now see the electric current
and the associated Joule losses.
The electric current, as we've
briefly mentioned it previously,
is an element that enables the quantification
of the number of electrons or charges
that or moving or flowing
through a conductor,
that we will write using the letter I,
here, an I
that I'm purposefully writing in upper-case,
dQ over dt,
in other words, it's the variation
of charges over a unit of time
that defines the electric current.
Perhaps one more very
important thing to mention
this electric current will be written,
or the symbol of current ;
this unit of current
is the ampere,
that is written as A, in upper-case.
We can also define by the letter J
the current density
as being this electric
current over an area,
so we have here the area
of the conductor through which
this current is flowing,
here we have the current
we've just defined
and here,
by definition,
we have the current density
whose unit is then
ampere per meter square.
This notation of current density
will be very useful for us later on
to also define from the point of view
of power, what we are permitted or not
in a system defined by
the cross-section of the conductor.
We can finally define the Joule
losses associated to a current
that is flowing through a resistor
and that will transform this
electric energy into thermal energy.
A phenomena analogous
to friction is occurring
which creates a heating.
The losses that result from it are
called Joule losses, or heating losses.
And these Joule losses, written P,
are equal to the resistance
multiplied by the current
flowing through, squared.
Thermal energy
which is dissipated by this power can be
characterized in the following manner :
we have the thermal energy
which is the integral over time
of this power : integral (RI²dt)
Here is the definition of Ohm's
law, certainly very well known
to a few amongst you, but it is
always good to be reminded
in the basis of this law and also
later on in Kirchhoff's laws
that will follow and which will allow
us to apply the conventions
seen during the
second lesson.
By definition, Ohm's law is so :
We have a voltage between
two terminals A and B
that is equal to this resistor
between terminals A and B
and the current flowing through.
In other words, the resistance R AB
is the relationship between
the voltage and the current,
thus we have a linear
relationship for the resistance
which will be
very pleasant
for all the next steps in
electrotechnic theory, this resistor,
or instead everything that flows
through the resistance and comes out
as the same image, in other words, whatever
may be the voltage at the entrance,
we will have this same
image on the current
which flows through this same resistor.
I arrive now at the definition of
meshes (or loops) and nodes (or junctions),
in general so as to later on
apply Kirchhoff's laws.
We will thus define here what
are meshes and nodes
and to do so,
we will take an example which
will enable us to properly understand
what a node, a mesh and
also a branch is.
So let's take an example in which
we have different elements,
that we haven't necessarily
completely seen yet
but which will allow
us, especially here
to define these meshes
and nodes problems.
So here is a first element,
I'm putting several random elements
to define here a circuit.
So we have here a
random circuit,
we will first try to define
what are nodes, or junctions.
Well, nodes, which we will write n
a node is the point of convergence of
three or more conductors.
So, where are the nodes
in my circuit ?
We've said three conductors
or more, so our first node is here,
the second one here and
the third node is here.
This is not node,
this is not a node,
there are no other nodes
in this circuit.
Second definition : a branch,
which we will write as b.
A branch includes the elements
located between 2 nodes
and through which the same current flows.
So it's the elements located
between 2 nodes
through which the same current flows.
So let us try here as well
to indicate where our branches are.
So between two nodes we have here
a branch, we have here a branch,
here a branch, and also here, and finally here.
Last element : the mesh, or loop,
which we will write as m.
It is formed by
several branches,
branches through which we go
through from one node and loop back to it
By starting from a node to go back to it.
Naturally, without passing twice
through the same branch.
So we can define here a first
mesh m,
we define here a second mesh m,
a third mesh m
and eventually we can go from this,
come back here and make the entire loop,
so we would still have one big
mesh m, that I will write here.
Here is by definition the node,
the branch and the meshes
which will allow us to tackle
as we've mentioned, Kirchhoff's law.
So, first of all, Kirchhoff's nodal rule.
The expression of this rule, or law,
is quite simple, universal
and absolutely fantastic ;
it says that the sum of
the currents at every node
is equal to zero.
An example.
We take here various currents
that all converge on a node,
So we will write here I1,
we will write I2, I3, I4, and finally I5.
What Kirchhoff tells us, is that
if we look at the sum of all
these currents at this point
it must be equal to zero.
so we write, first of all we have
I1 + I2 - I3, which exits the node,
+I4 and -I5 equal to zero.
Absolutely fantastic and which allows
us to systematically know that
in every node, everything that goes in
is equal to everything that comes out,
and thus, allows us to write
this kind of relationship.
We can, more generally speaking,
I will draw you another diagram ;
let's imagine a diagram in which
you have this kind of circuit
with an I1 here,
an I2 here and an I3 here,
but with an I5, I6,
and here an I4,
of course, we a first node, a second
node, a third node
on which we can write
many relationships
as I've written them earlier ;
but what we can notice is that
we can imagine here
this like a generalized node
and we will be able to write
in the relationship
that I1 - I2 - I3 is equal to zero
without worrying about what is
inside this green circle.
We call this a generalized node.
We will now see Kirchhoff's
second law, or rule,
which is Kirchhoff's mesh rule.
What does this rule say ?
It tells us that here as well
the sum of voltages in a mesh
are always equal to zero.
In other words, a sum of voltages
on the mesh is always equal to zero.
So we can here also make an example
by taking here a voltage U5,
a voltage U1 at the
terminals of the resistor here,
and a voltage U2 at the
terminals of a capacitor,
so I imagine here
a random circuit,
a voltage U3 on a supply
and also an element
with a voltage U4
finally, on this inductor.
Well, through Kirchhoff, since I
have here a mesh
going from this point
and returning to this other point,
In my case, I systematically
choose
the clockwise direction
to always make my mesh calculations
in the same direction,
all that is needed is to define once
and for all a direction for each of us,
we then arrive at the following equation :
U1 + U2 - U3 - U4 + U5 = 0
and you can see that using
extremely simple methods,
we can write equations either
on nodes or on meshes,
which allow us to solve a
certain number of things in
an electric circuit in an already
very simplistic and very evident way.
To finish this lesson,
we will talk about the inductor
or the manner in which we write and model
an inductor and its physical relationship.
The inductor is symbolized in
electrical engineering by a filled-in square
or sometimes also as a kind
of spring like this
since the reality of an inductor
is in fact a coil or
or a grouping of copper wire coils
within which will happen a certain
number of magnetic phenomena which
we will go into detail for now
but that very clearly link
the electric world
with the magnetic world.
We can, by definition, say that the
voltage at an inductor's terminals UL
is this definition of the inductance L
times the derivative or variation
of the current over time
flowing through this inductance.
In effect, the inductance acts
like a brake to the current,
or to any current variations,
it will thus create a difference of
potential at its terminals the higher
the variation of the current is big.
The inductance is written in,
or the unit of the inductance,
in henry, symbolized by the letter H.
This concludes our lesson,
we have thus seen the different
basic elements that in the end
constitute our different elements
in our study of electrotechnics,
in other words the resistor, the capacitance,
the inductor, the supplies, and the way
that they will interact with each other,
the physical aspects of every element,
the nodal rule and the mesh rule
in Kirchhoff's laws
which will allow us to
solve electric circuits
and finally, an application
of the conventions
already seen in previous lessons.
Good bye and see you in the next lesson.