Hello and welcome to this lesson
dedicated to the analysis and
resolution of linear circuits.
In this lesson, we will study
the combination of
simple linear elements.
First of all what is am element,
or elements,
in series like a network.
This elements in series for the resistor
for the capacitor, for the inductor.
We will do the same for
these elements in parallel.
And finally, we will make a
conclusion of this lesson and chapter.
Before starting with this combination
in series or in parallel,
I would like to define here,
what an equivalent dipole is :
Two equivalent dipoles have, at all times,
by definition, the same current
when they are submitted to the same voltage.
It is important to define this
to later on allow us
to render objects equivalent
in a Kirchhoff model.
For example, we will have here an element,
we know together
that it's a resistor,
but let's assume
that we don't know that,
a different element,
that I write like so ;
well, these two elements,
we can say that they are equivalent
if, submitted to a voltage u
and similarly
for your first dipole u,
we have a current I
which is identical on both sides.
In which case, we will say
that these dipoles are equivalent.
Now, the series connection of elements.
It is fundamental to understand,
in a more complex circuit,
the elements that can be put, or which
are, in a serial configuration,
or elements that are in a parallel
configuration to, later on,
reduce the circuit,
and to know how to reduce it
so as to not create more problems
than we are solving.
You have here the fundamental properties
of putting elements in a serial configuration.
We have on this line,
in this model,
put a resistor, a capacitor,
and an inductor.
The fundamental definition
of putting in series,
is to be able to say that the currents,
the three currents of these three elements,
are the same, or are identical.
Thus, placing elements in series,
means that the current flowing
through each element
is the same.
And then, another property derived
from Kirchhoff's equations,
is that if these elements are in series
and have the same current flowing through,
the sum of the voltages, which is here
between the resistor, capacitor and inductor
this sum of voltages is also the voltage
at the terminals of the complete dipole,
Between this part of the dipole
and this part of the dipole.
We will thus have the voltage u present
here which is equal to uR + uC + uL
Now that we've defined what is the
placing of elements in a serial configuration,
we will focus on
the three elements R, L, C
to separately see
what it means for
each of these elements.
Let's start with the resistor
and placing resistors in series.
What we wish for, in the end,
when we have resistors in series
with the same current flowing
through R1 to Rn,
is to replace this set of resistors
with a single resistor
known as equivalent, Rs,
through which the same current flows
and with the same voltage at the terminals,
so, it is the equivalence of dipoles
that we've seen earlier,
and in that instant, what can we say
about this new equivalent resistor ?
Well, knowing that the voltage u
is the sum of the partial voltages
from k to 1 up to n of uRk,
that this sum is equal to the complete u,
but that we can also replace
this uRk by this sum
from 1 to n, of the Rk times I,
the current being the same all the way through,
and we want this to be equal to
the Rs resistor times I,
from this, ensues an obvious fact that
most of you are already aware of,
that this series resistor in a series,
of several resistors in a series,
is simply the mathematical
sum from K 1 to n
of the separate resistors Rk.
We will do the same for capacitors
in a serial configuration.
So once again, we have an
equivalence of dipoles,
we which to render
equal these two dipoles.
We have a dipole of several
capacitors in a serial configuration,
through which the same current flows,
we have at the terminals of
this complete dipole a voltage u
and we which to replace this dipole
with a single capacitor,
in other words, a capacitor equal
to the set of all the capacitors
in the serial configuration, here.
How do we do this ?
we know that a voltage at
the terminals of the capacitor k,
is 1/Ck integral(from 0 to t)
i(t')dt'
+ the initial condition : Uck(0)
So know, we will sum
all of these voltages,
so we will have the global u
of the sum of all the voltages.
What is it ?
It's : 1/C1 + 1/C2
+ etc until 1/Cn
of the integral(from 0 to t) of i(t')dt'
+ a set of initial conditions [Uc1(0) etc]
And we want this to
be equal to 1/C,
the series capacitor Cs,
integral(from 0 to t)
i(t')dt' + u(0)
it of course follows that 1/Cs
is equal to the sum of k=1 to n of the 1/Ck
This is the same as writing that Cs
is equal to 1 / sum of k=1 to n of the 1/Ck
This is the rule of putting
capacitors in series.
We say one more thing about
the initial value of the
voltage at the terminals of the circuit.
This initial value, u(0)
is simply equal to
the sum of all the values of uck(0)
We can also say that the placing
of capacitors in a serial configuration
will insure that the final series
capacitor of all the elements
will  in general, necessarily,
according the equations here,
be smaller than each of the
partial capacitors.
Now, here is the placing of
inductors in a serial configuration.
So just like the previous ones,
you have understood it now,
between the resistor and capacitor,
we have here an equivalence of two dipoles.
We want this set of
inductors in series
to be equal to this single
equivalent inductor.
So then, we can write that,
knowing u is equal to L di/dt
in a general manner for an inductor.
we can write that the global u
of placing in a serial configuration,
is the sum of k=1 to n of the uLK,
which is equal to (L1 + L2 + etc Ln)
multiplied by di/dt ,
the i being common to all, it's the same,
and we want this to be
equal to Ls di/dt
It follows that the rules are exactly
the same as for the resistors,
that Ls is the mathematical sum
of k from 1 to n of the Lk.
An important element now is putting
voltage supplies in a serial configuration.
What can we say when we put
different supplies in series
and that we want to,
like previously
for the equivalence
of two dipoles,
we wish to replace
the set of supplies
by a single equivalent supply Us ?
Well, here like previously,
it's actually relatively obvious,
this global us, this supply
which replaces all the
partial supplies in series,
is the sum of k from 1 to n,
of the partial supplies uk.
We can make a small example
to convince ourselves, by saying :
well here we are, we have an example of 4
supplies in a serial configuration.
We wish to replace this element
of 4 supplies in series
by a single supply
to simplify the diagram.
What is the value of Us,
knowing that we have 3 volts,
we have 4 volts, we have 1 volt
and 2 volts, but with different directions.
Well, we will have 3V - 4V + 1V + 2V
and this gives us a Us = 2V.
So of course, take care with the
direction of the mathematical voltages
when we proceed with the sum and the
placing in series of voltage supplies.
It is obvious that it is not possible to
consider placing several current supplies
in series without violating
Kirchhoff's first law,
except if all the individual supply
produce exactly the same current.
In which case, the equivalent dipole
will simply be equal to
any one of of the
individual supplies.
Thus, what we can say here is that
the placing in series here is impossible,
except if all the supplies
are of the same value
and sign.
In this very particular case,
it is possible to put
current supplies in series.
And finally, an example of placing
several elements in series.
Once again, we notice
that all of these elements,
it's true that it's pretty obvious here,
having the same current flowing through,
all of these elements in series.
We group them based on families,
in other words, all the resistors together,
all the capacitors together
and all the inductors together.
We can then already proceed
to a simplification
of this model on the left through
this equivalent model on the right
with 3 elements
which represent the placing in series
of the all separate elements.
Let us now proceed to parallel
placement of elements.
What is the definition of putting
elements in parallel ?
You have a diagram with a resistor,
capacitor and inductor
which are in parallel.
The definition, is that
the 3 elements R, L and C,
have the same voltage at their terminals.
So this is the definition.
R and C are parallel,
similarly R and L are parallel,
similarly C and L are parallel.
Because the voltage at their terminals
is strictly equal.
Thus, the three currents that flow through
these elements are different,
but, through Kirchhoff,
the sum of these three currents
is necessarily equal to the total
current output here of the dipole,
so we can also write
that this current here,
is the sum of iR, of iC and of iL.
We will now go back to R, C then L,
and for each of these elements,
see what are the rules
to be able to simplify elements in parallel
of R, of C or of L.
First of all, putting
resistors in parallel.
Once again, we decide
to define 2 dipoles :
the dipole with the number of resistors
at n resistors placed parallel to each other,
because, as you can see here,
connected to the same voltage uAB,
and we wish to replace this
with a single resistor
equivalent to the previous dipole,
and this parallel equivalent resistor,
with a single resistor Rp.
How do we do it ?
We know that the current
as written previously,
is the current in R1
+ the current in R2
+ etc the current in Rn.
It's the total current of
the dipole that we have, i.
We also know that
this current must be equal to i
of the right dipole,
as written already here.
If we replace iR1, iR2, iRn
and so on, using Ohm's law,
we have u/R1
u/R2
etc u/Rn
and this must be equal to u/Rp
We define then the rules of placing
resistors in parallel,
which is the following :
it's that 1/Rp is equal to the sum
of k from 1 to n
of the 1/Rk
In other words, we can also write this
in another way, it's that Rp
is equal to 1 over
the sum of the inverses of Rk
for k from 1 to n.
We will now look at placing
capacitors in parallel.
We apply exactly the same rule.
We know that the total current
output here in this dipole,
is the sum of each of the
currents of each branch,
We can thus write i
is the sum of kfrom 1
to n of the ick
in other words (C1 + C2 + etc until Cn)
of the voltage variation over time.
And we want this to be equal to Cp times du/dt
Thus, we can write that Cp is equal to
the sum of k from 1 to n of the Ck.
So it's pretty simple
to calculate the placing
of capacitors in parallel.
It's simply the sum.
Finally, we need to calculate the placing
in parallel elements of inductors
before proceeding to supplies.
So we proceed once again
in the same manner.
We know that a current iLK
as a function of time
is 1/Lk integral(from 0 to t)
of u(t')dt'
+ an initial current iLK.
We can then write that this current i, that
we want in the dipole on the right,
is 1/L1 + 1/L2
and so on until 1/Ln
all of this in brackets,
times the integral of u(t')
+ all the initial currents,
[iL1(0) etc until iLn(0)].
And this, we want it to be equal
to 1/Lp integral(from 0 to t)
u(t')dt' + i(0).
What we can say and what we can see,
is that placing in parallel
will allow us to compute
the equivalent L, Lp,
1/Lp is equal to the sum of k
from 1 to n
of the 1/Lk
In other words, Lp is the
inverse of the sum of inverses,
from k=1 to n of Lk
And similarly, we will be able to say,
just like the resistor,
it's the inverse of the sum of inverses,
for inductors in parallel,
and add to this the fact that initial value of
the current flowing through the circuit,
and simply equal to the mathematical
sum of the initial currents.
So we will have i(0) equal to a sum
from k=1 to n of the iLk(0).
So now we have the rules
of putting in parallel elements
of R, L and C.
We will now see the placing in
parallel of current supplies.
So here also, it's pretty simple
since we apply Kirchhoff.
By wanting to equalize the left
dipole with the right dipole,
we can see that i, which is defined here,
is we sum the currents,
we will discover that ip,
we will call like this,
is equal to the sum of ik currents
by taking k=1 to n,
and we will thus define this i as ip.
So we have an equivalence here,
which allows us to,
once again, do a small example,
to show you in a practical manner
how this happens.
So if you have here a dipole ab
with 3 current supplies in parallel
that we wish to replace
with a single current supply.
What is the value of the iA current ?
We will have 3 amperes
which go up
- 1 ampere, 2 remain,
- 5 amperes.
Well, the current i is of - 3 amperes.
So this i is equal to -3A.
We continue with parallel placement
of voltage supplies,
and similarly,
we have a problem with putting
voltage supplies in parallel.
We cannot do this parallel placement
without violating Kirchhoff's second law
and once again, here as well,
except if they are all the same voltages.
If they all have the same voltages,
in this case we can
simplify it to a single supply,
which will be the same
supply that each of these defines.
And thus we can write
that putting voltage supplies
in parallel is impossible
except if they all have
the same value and sign.
To conclude, we've seen the
parallel and serial placement
of all the elements R, L, C,
of ideal current and voltage supplies.
As a conclusion,
I will show you here a table
which sums up what we've just seen
with serial configurations,
the definition of resistors in series,
capacitors in series, inductors in series,
voltage supplies in series,
and parallel configurations
with the resistor, capacitor, inductor,
and similarly for the ideal current supply.
Thank you