Hello. In today's lesson, we will present a method
whose goal is not to simplify or to
transform a circuit
but to consider its subdivisions and to
treat them separately, one by one,
and then to reassemble the partial results to
obtain a general result.
It is what we call the superposition principle.
To do so, we will see what are
the excitation
and the response of a circuit
to this excitation.
Then, we will formulate the
superposition principle.
We will then see what it means to
cancel out a voltage or current supply.
Then, we will see the aims
and mostly the advantages
of such a method.
And finally, we will do an exercise.
If we consider the following
two circuits,
we see that there is a part that we
can call the excitation,
it is this voltage supply here,
and the response of this circuit,
all this part here,
to this excitation,
which will be currents
in each branches
and voltage drops
at the terminals of each elements.
Likewise for a second example
in the case of a current supply,
so an excitation which is a current supply.
This supply will induce currents
in the circuit
and the response of the circuit to this supply
will be a series of currents
for each element
and also a voltage drop at the
terminals of each element.
The superposition principle states that
one of the most fundamental
properties
of systems made up of
linear elements,
whether they are electrical or not,
one must know that the response of
the system to a sum of excitations,
we see here several excitations,
some small, some big,
positive, negative,
well the response of the system to
a sum of excitations is equal to
the algebraic sum
-- so one must be careful about the
direction of the response to the excitation --
so the algebraic sum of the responses due to
each excitations considered separately.
Applied to the case of electrical circuits,
the superposition principle
lets us avoid a global analysis method,
often burdensome,
by replacing it by a succession of
partial calculations.
These partial calculations are done
on simplified circuits.
At each step, only one of the original circuit's
supplies is taken into account,
all the others are cancelled out.
The total result is the algebraic sum
of the partial results.
So in the notion of algebraic sum, one must
take into account the directions of the currents
or voltages.
We have just talked about cancelling
out a supply,
but what does that mean exactly?
Cancelling out and ideal voltage supply,
that I represent here,
the voltage u0 for example,
well, for the voltage to be cancelled out,
it must be null
so we will replace this supply,
to cancel it out, by a continuous line,
namely a zero voltage drop
between these two points.
It is the case of a short-circuit.
To cancel out an ideal current supply
such as this one,
that provides a current Icc,
well, cancelling out this supply
to get a current I equal to 0
corresponds to an open circuit
or an infinite resistance.
In this case, U is equal to 0.
In that case, I is equal to 0.
Lets now consider the following example.
It is question of a circuit composed
of two supplies,
such as represented here on the figure,
for which we would like to determine
the current i2 passing through
the resistor R2.
We see that the circuit's two excitations are
the current supply i0 and
the voltage supply u0.
Under the equivalence
of real voltage supplies and
real current supplies,
we could transform this middle
branch here
in a real current supply
and combine the current supplies that are in parallel.
However, if we wanted to transform this
real current supply
here, with this resistor R2,
we could make the transformation
but we would lose the information on the current
that is in the resistor R2.
So, we will apply here the
superposition principle.
To calculate the current i2
passing through the resistor R2,
we see that this current has two components.
A first component that we call i2a,
the subscript a
corresponding to a response due to the
excitation of the current supply,
plus a component due to
the voltage supply, that we call i2b.
According to the superposition principle,
we can redraw this circuits in two parts
that correspond to the two
components of the supplies.
We have a first component
that only corresponds to
the supply i0.
We represent the resistor R1
with the voltage supply u0
that is cancelled out
and the resistor R2 stays in place.
The current i2a is given here
and we can easily calculate it.
We have that i2 is the sum
of i2a plus i2b
and the current i2a, we recognise
here the current divider,
is i0 multiplied by
R1  over the sum of the two
resistors R1 plus R2
to which we add the component due to
the supply at the excitation U0,
and so we represent the circuit without
the supply i0.
R1 is here with the voltage supply U0,
the only one we consider in this
second exercise
of this second part.
And here, the part 0 which is from
i0 to have a null current
and so we have the second component i2b
which is given by the supply U0.
So this term i2b is simply
the ratio of U0 over the sum of
the resistors R1 plus R2.
In this particular example,
we see that the current i2a and the
current i2b are going in the same direction
which is why we add them,
but in another example
one of the two currents might be in the opposite
direction to the current one has made default
going towards the bottom in the
original drawings,
in which case we would have to
subtract this current.
In conclusion, we can say
that from a relatively complex circuit
composed of more than one excitation,
by applying the superposition principle
we can get circuits,
a certain number of circuits,
that are easier to deal with
and by adding the results we
get the global result.
One must keep in mind
that the elements must be linear
on one hand
and on another hand pay attention
to the signs of the currents
and voltages obtained.