Hello.
During this lesson, we will
present a method
that lets us handle tripoles.
We will consider partial circuits
composed of three elements.
We will first see particular circuits
whose element are difficult to combine
or to simplify two by two.
We will then consider three elements
that can be connected
either in "pi"
or in "T".
Then, we will see the equivalence between
these two types of circuits
in order to easily pass from one
to the other
and to then simplify the rest
of the circuit.
We will treat an example
and then formulate a conclusion.
If we consider these two
circuit examples,
we can see that they are
difficult to simplify.
Why? Because
if we consider this first circuit,
we see that the elements
are not in series
for R31 and R32.
Why?
Because there is an additional current
coming here, and so
it is more difficult to simplify the circuit.
Ideally, for this circuit,
that presents about the same topology.
We will see a method
letting us transform these circuits
for simplification later on.
We can evidently resolve these circuits
by applying Kirchoff's law at the
knots and loops,
but we will see a much simpler method.
Three elements can be connected between
them in two ways.
First way,
is a "π" connection
such as represented in the first figure.
We understand this notation
because the circuit
looks like a capital π.
If we represent this same connection,
drawn a little differently,
we see that it resembles a triangle,
which is why we also talk of "delta" connection.
We also use this notation,
the greek delta Δ
and in French literature, we rather talk
of a connexion en triangle.
The second method to connect
three elements between them
is the "T" connection.
On this drawing, we easily understand
why we give it such a name,
because the connection resembles
the letter T.
We also call it a "Y" connection
or a "star" connection.
On this drawing, we see that
the same equivalent drawing
resembles a Y shape.
In French, we talk about "connexion en étoile".
On this drawing, we represent the
two connections:
either in "T", or in "π".
We see that they are tripoles
with a first pole here,
a second pole and a third pole.
On the second representation,
we find these same poles.
Between these tripoles,
we connect the three elements,
three resistors in this example as it happens.
In T, we have a resistor R1
connected to the terminal 1;
a resistor R2 connected
to the terminal 2;
a resistor R3 connected
to the terminal 3.
In delta or in π,
we once again have
three elements:
R1-2 which is connected
at the terminals 1 and 2,
and so forth, the resistor 2-3 is
connected at the terminals 2 and 3
and the resistor 31 is connected
at the terminals 3 and 1.
What we would like to do here,
is find an equivalence
between the resistors R1, R2, R3
and the resistors R12, R23, R31
so that both circuits are identical.
To do so, we will proceed
in the following manner:
lets first consider that this terminal 3
doesn't exist,
and we will write the equation of the resistance
seen at the terminals 1 and 2
so that they are equivalent.
We can write that, here,  the
equivalent resistance,
they are in series since we deleted
the terminal number 3,
R1 + R2
must be equal to
this equivalent resistance
in the π connection at
the terminals 1 and 2.
And we see that these two resistors are in series,
since this terminal is cancelled out,
this equivalent resistance is in
parallel with the resistor R12.
So we can write that the
equivalent resistance is:
the product of this resistor over
the sum of these two
divided by the sum of this resistor
over the sum of these ones.
We then write that R12
multiplied by R23 + R31
divided by the sum of these
three resistors
needs to be equal to R1 + R2.
We repeat, here, the
result obtained
for the first equation
and if we proceed in an identical way
for the boundary pairs 2 and 3,
and 3 and 1, we get two
extra equations.
We are not making the development,
but the method is the same.
Two supplementary equations,
that give a system of three independent
equations with three unknowns,
from which we easily extract the
equivalence relationships
that let us replace a circuit in π
with a circuit in T.
We just need to do the sum
of these three equations.
So, lets take 0.5 times the first equation,
minus equation 2,
plus equation 3.
Having done all calculations, we
fall on this system of three equations
letting us pass from one circuit
to the other.
The resistor linked to the
terminal 1
of the circuit in T
is the product of two resistors linked
to the terminal 1 of the circuit in π,
so R12 and R31 here,
divided by the sum of
the three resistors.
And so forth for the resistors R2 and R3.
By doing a similar calculation at
the terminals pair
when the third one is
disconnected,
we get the equivalence relationships
that let us replace the elements
of a circuit in T
by a circuit in π.
These equations written in a slightly
different manner
give the ratio of
T double vector product of two
resistors taken two by two
R1 x R3 + R2 x R3
+ R1 x R2
divided by the resistor R3.
Let take the example that
we mentioned
at the very beginning of the lesson.
If we consider this circuit,
with this tripole composed
of three resistors,
well we can favourably replace it
by this equivalent
circuit
from which we can calculate
the resistors R1, R2 and R3,
by using the equations that we
developed,
namely the transformation from T to π.
It then becomes easy to calculate
the equivalent resistors
since the resistor R3 and the
resistor R4 are in series.
The resistor R2 and the
resistor R4 too,
that are in parallel,
and that we can put in series with R1.
We obtain the result for the
equivalent resistance
of the whole circuit
that is equal to
R = R1 +
these two equivalent resistances
in parallel,
so their product over their sum.
The product of these two resistors
in series
gives R2 + R24
multiplied by R3 + R34
divided by the sum of these two
equivalent resistances,
namely
R2 + R4
+ R3 + R34.
This is the final result.
Lets also note that we could have
seen the problem differently
by considering this time
these three elements, here,
which are three resistors connected in T
and that we could have
transformed in π
and also easily simplify the circuit.
We won't do the calculation here.
There, we have considered the case
of three elements
that are connected either in π,
either in T at its three boundaries.
We have the equivalence
letting us pass
from a π connection to
a T connection.
All this in the aim of simplifying this
circuit and continuing to reduce it.
We will see that this method
is very important
for three-phase systems
that we will cover in the next semester.