Hello, today, we will discuss
about a particular circuit
much used in metrology:
it is the Wheatstone Bridge.
This is the content of today's
lesson:
first of all, we will do an analogy with
another measuring device
that is the beam balance.
Then, we will describe the circuit that
builds the Wheatstone bridge.
Then we will establish a condition
for the bridge to be at equilibrium,
and calculate it's equilibrium condition.
Finally we will give
two application examples
and we will end with a conclusion.
The Wheatstone bridge is
an interesting circuit example
capable of satisfying, a particular
equilibrium condition,
a little bit like
balance beams.
So, here is the Wheatstone bridge.
It is a circuit that is essentially
made of
two branches of
two resistors in series.
And, the condition for the
bridge to be at equilibrium
is that the voltage between the points A
and B has to be equal to zero.
So if we connect a resistor
between these two points,
resistor that we can name R5
well, the current that crosses
this resistor, that we name I5,
must be equal to zero,
at equilibrium.
So if we connect a galvanometer,
which is a device allowing
the measure of the current.
If we connect a galvanometer in series
with this resistor her,
this last one will indicate a null value.
This condition is independent of the
value of R0 and of U0.
It should be noted that such a principle
can be used as continuous current.
This is what we are going to work on today,
to perform the measurement
of an unknown resistor,
or generalize an alternative  state to
define the unknown impedances.
The purpose is to cancel the voltage
between the point A and the point B,
this voltage U5, whatever  the values
of U0, R0 and R5 are
To get the equilibrium criteria,
we will first of all calculate,
the voltage that there is between
the terminal A and the terminal C,
and secondly, the voltage that
is between the terminal B and the terminal C
and by making these two voltages equal,
we will get a voltage U5
that is equal to zero.
The equilibrium condition is that
Vac must be equal to Vbc
which will give a current I5 equal to zero
and a voltage U5 also equal to zero.
We can also define this voltage U5 between
the points A and B as being:
U5 = Vac - Vbc
This must be equal to zero.
The voltage Vac is given
by the following relationship:
It is the voltage Vdc
between the point D and
the point C, the voltage Vdc
multiplied by the resistor R2
divide by the sum R1 + R2.
We recognize the voltage divider.
We do the same thing for the
voltage at the terminals of B and C.
So we have that Vbc is equal to Vdc
multiplied by R4,
divided by R3 + R4.
And again, this expression of
the voltage divider.
For the equilibrium condition,
the voltage Vac needs to be
equal to the voltage Vbc.
We can rewrite this equation
the following way:
[Silence]
that we can expand and that gives:
We can simplify this equation
by deleting these two products.
Which gives us the following
relationship:
The product R2 * R3 must be equal to
the product of R1 * R4
so that the bridge is in equilibrium.
Rather than embarrass ourselves with
indices which are, moreover,
not from a conventionality
we can clearly see here that
the indices R1, R2, R3, R4
can be arbitrarily
chosen
we will then remember the
following rule, that says that:
the equilibrium condition of the bridge
is reached when the cross
products of the resistors,
R1 * R4
is equal to the product of
the resistors R3 * R2
[Silence]
Now that we have defined
the equilibrium condition
we can see that we can use this circuit,
or this bridge, in two different ways:
either by adjusting the
resistors R1, R2, R3, R4
so that the voltage
Vab is equal to zero,
or by the equilibrium
of the circuit,
that satisfies this
equation her,
we look at the voltage
that appears at the terminals Vab
when we change one or
several of the four resistors.
So the first mode of use,
is the resistance measuring.
If we start with a circuit
where a first resistor is known
and a second resistor,
we can get the result,
the computation of a fourth resistor
simply by adjusting
the resistor, here, R3,
in a way that the voltage Vab,
that appears between these points,
becomes equal to zero,
namely that we satisfy
this equation here.
So the analogy with the
beam balance is total.
We have here an unknown
that we will like to know the mass,
we will simply add here calibrated
weights
such that the beam balance
comes back to equilibrium.
This is what we do here with the bridge.
If we know the reistor R1
and the resistor R2
The resistor R4 can be obtained
by adding or replacing R3
by known calibrated
resistor values,
so that the voltage AB
becomes equal to zero.
Which makes that the resistor R4
will be equal to the product
of the resistor R2
multiplied by
the equivalent calibrated resistor,
divided by R1.
R1 and R2 are known and
also the calibrated resistors.
The second application example is
an electronic scale,
a scale such as the ones
in trade,
that allows to measure
a force, or a weight,
by using strain gauges.
This scale, here disassembled,
is made of a deformable
mechanical structure
where a part is linked to the
stationary part of the balance, the table,
and another part that is
connected to the plate.
Schematically, here, this element here,
is what we call a bearing neck,
that is a deformable structure
with the four necks
that are here very thin,
and so we put a resistance here
on the part that deforms itself,
and when we will push here on the plate
all the structure will deform itself
and change the resistance.
We can see here a picture a little bit more
detailed of such strain gauges.
Here, schematically, to picture
the element in a better way,
we see that it is a coil
with L times the length of
a copper cable
and if we pull on this gauge her,
each of these strands will lengthen
and the section will decrease so the
volume remains the same
So we have a resisitance
that will change.
If we pull on the strain gauge,
the resistance will increase
and if we compress
the strain gauge,
the resistance will decrease.
We see here on these two
sketches the bearing neck
in its equilibrium position
and when we apply a force
on the plate
so we deform this extremity here
the other one remaining stationary
and so the resistance,
or the strain gauge,
that is positioned at this place
will elongate, so we will increase
its resistance,
while this one will
be compressed.
We will decrease its resistance
of a value ΔR.
Here is the circuit used within
the electronic balance.
We have four resistors
where two of them are known and fixed.
The two others are the strain gauge
resistors,
and that are capable to fluctuate.
At equilibrium, these resistors are equal
and so the bridge is at equilibrium
the voltage Vab is equal to 0.
Under stress, the bearing
neck will change.
The resistor R3 will increase,
the resistor R4 decreases,
and so at equilibrium Uab will be broken
and a voltage between these
two points will appear.
We find the equation that
we have expanded before,
with the crossed products
that must be equal,
the resistor R4 will be
changed of a value - ΔR,
the resistor R3 will be modified
of a value + ΔR.
We see in this equation that ΔR
can simply be changed here, compensate itself.
And the voltage that
appears at the terminals,
between the terminals A and B
namely given bay this equation that
depends on the fluctuations of the resistor
and therefore the deformation that
has been done on the scale.
There will the be a voltage between
the points A and B that will appear,
it is a little bit like the needle of the balance,
here that will
deviate from the equilibrium position
if we continue our analogy.
Note that we can arrange the
resistors in different ways
to increase the sensibility of the circuit,
eventually go from two gauges
to four gauges.
But anyway, the big
advantage of this set up,
is that it is indifferent to
external disturbances,
for example the temperature.
At equilibrium, if the circuit's
ambient temperature increases,
then the bridge stays at equilibrium
because all the resistors will
increase because of the temperature.
And therefore, the equilibrium will be guaranteed.
So we have seen a particular
circuit linked to metrology,
it is the Wheatstone bridge.
We have done the expansion of the
functioning in DC mode
but it is also valid for
the alternative mode.
We have seen that we could use this bridge
in two different ways
either by searching for the equilibrium
either by starting at equilibrium,
and moving away from this equilibrium
and calculate the resistance fluctuations .
This circuit has a lot of advantages,
as being indifferent
to the temperature.
It is clear now that, there are
many electronic devices
that allow to
measure the resistances,
and that make the circuit
a little bit obsolete,
but the structure of the bridge remains
used in many assemblies,
even in embedded electronics,
when it is not possible
to add another device.