Hello. Today we will discuss about
the power transmitted by a real voltage
supply to a load.
First of all, we will define the real
voltage supply and the load.
We will then calculate the power provided
by the supply to the load.
Then, we will calculate the maximal
value of the power
as function of the value of
the load resistance.
We will then define the condition
of adaptation.
And finally, we will calculate the
efficiency of the system
and we will and with a conclusion.
On this sketch, we see on the left part,
the ideal voltage supply
and the internal resistance that is both,
the real voltage supply
and on the right side,
the load resistance.
On this circuit we can define
two values:
the current that goes through the circuit,
there is just one loop,
there is just one current,
and the voltage at the terminals of the load
resistor that we call uR indication L.
By Kirchhoff we find very easily,
as long as
the two resistors are in series,
the current that goes through the circuit.
We have that i is equal to u0
divided by Ri + RL.
In terms of the power,
power that is dissipated
in the resistor RL,
we can write that this power is
the product of the voltage drop
at the terminals of the resistor
multiplied by the current,
therefore it is uRL multiplied by the current
and if we replace the voltage drop
at the terminals of the resistor
by the resistance times i,
u is equal to Ri, we get that
the power is equal to RL
multiplied by i squared.
By replacing the value of i by the
expression found here above,
we finally write that the power in the
load resistor is equal to
(u0^2 * RL)/(RL + Ri)^2
This is the first result.
If we analyse this function,
we see that in two extreme cases,
when the load resistance is zero,
then the power in this resistor
is also zero.
On the other extreme, if the load
resistance is infinite,
we have a power in this load that is equal to
the term RL becoming
much bigger than Ri
we can express Ri,
we have (u0^2 * RL)/RL^2,
it is equal to u0^2/RL
and it is also equal to zero.
Therefore we see that for two
extreme values the power is zero.
And in between, there is
necessarely a maximum,
it is this maximum that we will calculate.
Is repeated on this slide
the results obtained earlier.
We have represented the same sketch
and the power dissipated
in the load resistor is given
by this equation.
To get the maximum of this function
with the load resistor RL
as a variable, we just have to
derivate this function
with respect to the variable RL.
Therefore the maximum is found when
the derivative of the power
with respect to RL is equal to zero.
To calculate this derivative, we will
write that this power function
is equal to a numerator that
is a function f
divided by the denominator of function g
f is therefore equal to RL x u0^2,
it is the numerator.
The denominator g is equal to (RL + Ri)^2.
And to calculate this derivative, we know
that the derivative is equal to
(f'g - g'f)/g^2.
We now calculate the derivative
of the function f,
that we call f', derivative with respect to RL
that is equal to u0^2,
and the derivative of the denominator g' that is
equal to 2 (RL + Ri).
We can therefore replace these functions and
those derivatives in this equation
and is obtained for the derivative function
power with respect to
the variable RL
that it is equal to...
the numerator divided by
the denominator squared
which is equal to (RL + Ri)⇥^4.
And we will like to find a zero value of
this derivative
so we just have to say that the numerator
is equal to zero,
that we expand and rewrite here...
we can simplify it by writing it
like -RL^2 + Ri^2 = 0
and we then find the condition for what we call
power adaptation
which means that when RL is equal to Ri.
We have now found the power adaptation
condition
that is fulfilled when the value of the
load resistor is equal to
the value of the internal resistance.
In this case, we say that the
load is adapted to the power supply.
Now lets calculate the
efficiency of the system.
The efficiency is determinated by the ratio
between the useful power,
which means the power given to the load resistor,
it is here represented by this
little green arrow here,
divided by the total power
given by the power supply.
This total power given by the
power supply is represented here
by the big green arrow.
Therefore the useful power in the load
resistor is RL x i^2.
And the total power given by the power
supply is the current squared
times the sum of two resistors, which
is (RL + Ri) x i^2.
We can rewrite this formula in
a simpler way.
So the efficiency is given by the
load resistance divided
by the sum of the two resistors,
load resistor and internal resistance.
Let's look what is happening concerning
the adaptation efficiency,
so when the load resistance is equal
to the internal resistance.
We have the  adaptation efficiency that is
equal to RL/(RL + Ri)
but these two values being equal,
we simply have
that the efficiency is equal to RL/2RL
if we replace Ri by RL which are equal,
so we have a 50% efficiency
for Pmax and therefore 50% for the adaptation.
Let's take an example with
numerical values.
We recover here our real
voltage supply
with the load resistance,
let's take the case
of an internal resistance that is equal to 9 ohms.
We can calculate the power
as function of RL.
We have traced it here, it is the blue curve.
We see that the maximum power, here,
is for a value RL,
9 ohms.
We also see that for this load resistor
value,
the adaptation efficiency is 0.5
therefore 50%.
So on this graph, we can see that the
maximum power
that can be transmitted to the load
resistance RL is not only
depending on RL but it is also very dependent
on the internal resistance.
We can see that there is a limit to the power
given by the voltage supply.
If we take another value with a higher
internal resistance,
therefore a less performant real
voltage supply,
we see that the maximal power decreases
by this equation,
but most of all the maximum is now
again at a value
that is equal to the value of the
load resistance
that matches the value of the
internal resistance,
so 12.5 ohms, and again
the efficiency
at this value is 50%.
If we take a third internal
resistance
therefore a real voltage supply
of lower quality
with a higher internal resistance, the
maximum power is again
smaller but we recover the
same adaptation conditions
for the load resistor at the value
of the internal resistance
and the efficiency is 50%
at the value of the internal resistance.
If we consider a battery
to power a car
for example, electric,
this battery can be modelled
with a first approach by this real
voltage supply
with a no-load voltage
and an internal resistance
that represents the chemistry of
the battery, the connectivity,
the electrodes ...
worse the battery is
lower the power thus bigger the internal
resistance is
and less power can be transmitted to the
load
therefore to the electric motor.
We mostly see that we can not transmit an
infinite power
but a power that depends on
the internal resistance.
In conclusion, we can say two things.
First, a real voltage
supply
and its load are adapted in power to
one another if the internal resistance
of the real supply voltage is equal
to the load resistance.
And secondly,
The power transmitted by the supply
to the load is maximum
and secondly, the adaptation
efficiency is 50%.
We understand it well
because there is as much power
that is dissipated in the internal resistance
then in the load resistance
because they are equal
Thank you for your attention.