Hello and welcome to this lesson dedicated to
single phase sinusoidal steady state.
We will see in this lecture what the
single phase sinusoidal steady state is.
and in which circumstances we use it
and define its sinusoidal
values at all time
with a very specific way
to write them.
We will also see how the
complex calculation will help us
to solve some problems,
it can seem paradoxicall to use
vectors
to solve temporal problems
such as the single phase sinusoidal steady state.
By definition, we can say that the single phase
sinusoidal steady state,
or the steady state,
is when the external excitation,
current, voltage,
are sinusoidal functions
that are supposed established in time
from the infinite.
We therefore have sinusoidal functions
or in the same way,
co-sinusoidal
as it is the same function
out of step by π/2.
It is also interesting to note that the
sine and the cosine
are in reality the only periodic function
that have a derivative
or an analogue integral.
It is the reason why this state
is very particular.
It has an important role in electricity
and this prevalence is linked
firstly
to the fact that the industrial production
of energy generally results from
a mechanical/electrical conversion
realised by the rotation of
a winding
placed in an magnetic induction field
and the induced voltage is rightly sinusoidal.
It's this characteristic that allows
to assure
an economical and efficient distribution.
We will now see how to define
this sinusoidal function.
So here is a sine drawn as
function of time,
we took x(t) as function of t,
here, X can symbolise any sinusoidal value.
We have defined here all the elements that
we will now have to understand
to be able to use thereafter this
sinusoidal function x(t).
So if we write this function,
we can write that x(t) is equal to
x (peek)sin( (2πT)xt + α).
This is the equation of the function
drawn on the graph.
So we will be now able to define a certain
number of things.
First of all the amplitude.
The amplitude of this sinusoidal
signal is x (peek),
or x said peak,
that will be the maximal
amplitude of this sine,
the peak value.
We can also define the initial phase.
This initial phase for t which
is equal to zero,
we also call it the phase angle,
and this phase angle is identical
to the phase angle
and this is equal to alpha (α).
This is why the value that we see here
that allows to define the shift that
is between t=0 and - α.
We have another fundamental element that
is here: the period.
This period T corresponds to an
arithmetic sine
to the function 2π therefore we go
back to the beginning,
and we start another cycle again,
and this function T has for equation,
or connection with the frequency,
1/T.
Therefore this frequency will be
in hertz, of course,
and is equal to 1 divided by the period T.
So T will be by definition
called the period.
A few other elements
can now be calculated from this.
So we can now define the pulse,
that we will write down small omega ω,
and this pulse is defined as being
2π times the frequency (f)
which is 2π divided by the
period (T).
This is why we have previously seen in
the equation that I remind you
x(t) = x (peek) sin ((2π / T) x t + α)
Therefore we have a pulse that appears
and that allows
to define this value as an angle
in radians.
Therefore this allows to make
the transfer, or the transformation,
between time and radians,
between an angle and time.
So as we have said before, this is
the peak value
by definition.
And this now allows us to
explain, or to write,
for the first time a voltage
equation of a current voltage.
So for the voltage,
we will write u(t)
is equal to U (peek),
the maximum value of the voltage,
times cos(ωt + α).
So here is a typical equation of
a sinusoidal voltage.
And, by convention in
electrotechnics,
we will simply note it u.
So we will no longer write
T in brackets,
we will now see that
when we write a lowercase letter,
this means
that we are looking,
or that we are writing,
the function of time (t).
Therefore here for the current,
Î
cos(ω * t + β).
We will add another angle.
So you see that all the functions finally
have the same form.
It is always a cosine,
peak value,
and a value as function of time,
and an angle.
And another definition that we
will be able to write here,
is when we have a voltage and
a current in the circuit,
we will define phase shift
between these two values.
You can see these two values
are, here, at the same frequency.
Therefore all the values in the circuit
have the same frequency,
but the phase which is here,
so alpha (α) and beta (β)
can be different for the voltage or
for the current.
Therefore, by definition,
we will define the phase shift
between the voltage
and the current
as being the angle φ
that is equal to α - β.
Another definition is
when we say the word "phase".
The word "phase",
or" in phase",
which is a more accurate word,
means that all the values
have the same frequency,
it doesn't necessarily mean that
the phase difference is zero.
If the phase difference is
equal to π/2, then
we will say that these phases
are "in quadrature".
So I repeat, all the values
have the same frequency, and the
phase difference
is zero.
At this moment, we will say that the
system is in phase,
we will say "in quadrature",
and all the values have
the same frequency
but the phase difference is equal
to more or less π/2.
We will now define here a concept well
known by students
that is the mean value.
Everybody knows how to calculate
the average of their grades
to know if they get to pass or not
their school-year.
We will here calculate the mean of a signal with
its own definition of the mean.
So when we have a...
I repeat the equation x
that is equal to x (peek) cos (ωt + α)
if I am looking for the mean value of this signal.
By definition,
The mean value of a signal
that we will write X uppercase underline
is equal to 1/T
integral from 0 to T
of x(t) dt
So for a cosine,
if we integrate on 2/π,
so if we integrate on  2π,
we will get the mean value X(mean)
equal to zero.
We can also realize it.
So if we have here X(mean) and the time t
and that we have the sinusoidal
or co-sinusoidal signal
that is like this.
We can clearly see that the integral
so the part here under the curve
will completely cancel itself
so a cosine or a sine
always has a mean value on its
complete period that is zero.
We therefore see that the
information of a
mean value isn't very
interesting in electrotechnics
because it will always be zero for
periodic functions.
We will then imagine
another way to allow us
to have an information
especially an information that will be
linked, you will see, to power.
This will be the definition of the effective value
of sinusoidal values.
We have drawn here the power,
so you can see the current
i(t), that is
drawn here.
Then we did calculate Ri^2.
We know that the power is
the voltage (u) times the current (i)
If we are in a resistor,
and therefore that u is equal to R * i,
we can write that this
same power
is equal to u^2/R.
And if P is equal to u^2/R,
we then have u (peek)
cosine squared of
ω * t + α
divide by R.
We also have u^2.
So this the instantaneous power
that is represented here with
values that you have here,
so Ri^2, or u^2/R :
it's the same thing.
And you have this that is
strictly positive.
We can clearly see it here,
the mean of this function
is not zero.
It is determinate by
Ri^2
divided by 2.
We can calculate this to
convince ourselves.
Let's calculate the average power.
So the average power of
a resistor
1/T integral from zero to T
of the average power
so let's write u^2
cosine squared
ω* t + α
divided by R dt.
Imagine that we don't know
how to calculate the integral of cos^2,
we don't have a numerical index
on hand
we will say that
we shift this signal of π/2,
we will get exactly the same form,
but instead of having a cosine,
we will have a sine, but i'ts
the same thing.
Therefore sin^2 of
ω * t + α
divided by R dt.
Then we add both
because we want to get a well
known trigonometric connection.
So 2 times the average power
gives us 1/T integral
from 0 to T
of u^2 (peek)
I have not written it,
sorry it's a mistake
divided by R
times, first of all, sin^2 of
ω * t + α
+ cos^2 of
times dt.
What do we notice?
We take notice that this relation
sin^2 + cos^2 is equal to 1.
And therefore simplifies our
calculations.
So then we continue,
we get 2 times the average power
in a resistor
it is U (peek)^2
divided by R.
And then we find what we
are looking for:
the average that is equal to U(peek)^2/2R.
So we see here that,
contrary to the steady state,
so when we where in cosine
or in single phase
cosinusoidal or sinusoidal
but if we are in continuous,
we know that the power
of a resistor
is U^2/R.
We see here this difference
of notions between U^2 and U.
Finally, this doesn't give the same
value, or the same concept of
information on the power inside
of the circuit.
And this will lead us to
define a new relation, that we
will call the effective value.
By definition,
the effective value
is equal to this:
X
square root of 1/T
integral from 0 to T of x^2 dt.
What have we done?
We calculate the mean of the signal squared
and we take the square root.
So here is the definition of
the effective value.
So let's know see
for a sine or a cosine
what it can give.
An example:
for the sinusoidal value,
I take an X(t)
that is equal to
sin (ω * t + α).
And I look for the effective value.
So X is equal to
the square root of
X (peek)^2/T
-there is X (peek) missing
here of course-
X (peek)^2/T  integral from 0 to T
of sin^2 (ωt + α) dt.
This when we do the entire calculation,
will give to us
X (peek)/√2.
And by definition,
we will therefore say that this
is the effective
value of X.
We will now
take back the example that is here, on top,
and calculate, but with the
effective value,
this new average power.
If I replace now
my U (peek),
I know that it is
U(effective) times √2
by replacing here by the
effective value,
what do I notice?
I notice that by putting
the effective value
instead of the peak value
the 2 disappears thanks to the √2
and finally this effective value
represents an identical energetic
concept as the one that we had
in continuous current.
It is the value that will
be systematically used
in the calculation of powers,
but not powers only,
also general markings,
we will generally write down
that the effective value of
the voltage is equal to U,
the value of the current is equal to I.
We therefore have for the voltage:
√2 x U cos (ωt + α)
with U (peek) that is equal to
U x √2.
We have for the current,
√2 x I
cos (ωt + β)
with I (peek) equal to:
I x √2.
This √2 is the factor
to transform the effective value
into a peak value,
but the factor for sinusoidal values.
Warning, if we have a signal that is
square or triangle
or another, but
not sinusoidal,
well this factor won't be
equal to √2 anymore,
but to another value.
In a conventional network
that we have in a household
or in an industry,
we say that generally the value of
the grid is equal to 230 volts.
What does this U = 230 volts mean ?
This is the efficient value.
This means that the maximum signal
that goes in the phase that we
connect tot the network
is not 230 volts peak voltage,
but it is 230 * √2 so almost
300 volts
in peak value.
So the U (peek) is equal to:
230 * √2
in a conventional network.
We will now take every
known element,
the resistance, the inductance, the capacitance,
to determinate what is happening
when a resistor is crossed by
a sinusoidal current-voltage ;
same for the inductance,
same for the capacitor.
So first of all,
for the resistor,
let's imagine a resistor
where we will connect to
a voltage U = U(peek)
cos (ωt + α)
Between those two terminals,
will flow a current
inside the resistor.
Ohms law: U = R * i
is always true.
Therefore we can write this Ohms law
by replacing now
the different elements.
First, we have U(peek) that is equal
to cos (ωt + α)
= R * ....
The current must be the same kind
and the same frequency,
so we can already write
I (peek) cos (ωt + β)
There are unknowns here,
these are β and I (peek),
if we know the U (peek)
and the α.
We get that,
U (peek)
is equal to R * I(peek)
by doing the identification,
we see that it's the only way to
be able to solve this problem
And also that α
is equal to β.
This means that the resistor
doesn't change the phase angle
of the voltage.
In other words,
voltage
and current
are in phase in this
configuration of the resistor.
And this will be very handy
in the future
to always remember
that the resistor
doesn't change the angle phase.
Now in the case of the inductance.
Therefore we know that
the law that links the voltage
and the current in an inductance,
is the fluctuation of the current
as function of time
multiplied by L, which gives
the voltage at the terminals.
So if we draw this sketch again.
We have here an inductance.
Here at the terminals we will put
U = U (peek)
cos (ωt + α)
What about the current that goes through
this inductance here ?
We can write this
equation again.
First, the voltage equation:
U (peek)
cos (ωt + α) =
-so here we have a derivative, the derivative
of the cosine which gives a sine
with the internal derivative, ω that goes
up-front, and a minus sign-
so we have - ω * L * I (peek)
sin (ωt + β)
Now, we will put back
the sine and the cosine
to have an equality on both sides,
and therefore we transform
this - ω
sin (ωt)
by a + ω cosine phase
shifted of π/2
So we have an equal sign, here, at ω * L
I (peek)
cos (ωt + β + π/2)
By doing this identification again
on both sides,
we get to the following  conclusions.
First, U (peek) is equal to
ω * L * I (peek).
We have a ratio that
depends on the pulse.
Bigger the pulse is,
more this voltage will fluctuate
as function of the current.
Finally, α is equal to
β + π/2.
In short, the current and the voltage
will be in quadrature.
So a delay of the current
of an angle π/2 compared to the voltage.
So voltage
and current
in quadrature.
Finally, the case of the capacitor.
Here, we draw again the sketch.
We have here at the terminals,
a voltage U (peek)
cos (ωt + α).
We are looking for the current
that will flow through this capacitance,
the capacitor.
The link that we know,
is the fluctuation of the voltage
as function of time multiplied
by he capacitance will
give us the current.
So we write here, this equation
as function of the current.
First I (peek),
that will necessarily be a cosine,
ω * t + β
is equal to the derivative
this time, of the voltage.
So we get the same elements
as before
so finally ω * C * U (peek)
sin (ωt + α).
We convert this sine into a cosine
and we get ω * C * U (peek)
cos (ωt + α + π/2)
The result now is that
U (peek) is in the end equal to
I (peek)/ω * C
and that α is equal to β
minus π/2.
We therefore have here
the voltage
and the current
in quadrature.
Here the current
is ahead of π/2
on the voltage.
So now let's imagine,
the case of a more complex problem
where we have R and L at the same time
on a same circuit.
What can we write down?
How can we pull through
in this way ?
We will realize that if
we stay
with our simple Kirchhoff
calculation
like we did until now,
the system will become
very complex.
So rather see.
If we want to write here
the Kirchhoff equation,
of elements linked to this voltage,
we can write that U is equal
first of all to
R * i  +
- at the crossing in the inductance-
L di/dt
By replacing now the
different elements,
we get U (peek)
cos (ωt + α) =
here we already have a simple connection,
R * I (peek) * cos (ωt + β).
So we always assume that
when we are in the
same circuit,
the pulses have to be
all the same.
So our unknown,
their are two for the current,
it's the magnitude
and the phase β
plus
here L di/dt that becomes
minus,
because the cosine becomes sine:
ω * L * I (peek)
sin (ωt + β).
So you see here, that
it becomes pretty complicated.
We can not make an identification anymore
by saying to the left or
to the right of the equation,
because we have here three terms
and no longer two terms.
We must then simplify this
equation to be able to succeed,
we must break down the functions
sine and cosine
into sums.
Here come the following thing:
we have U (peek) that multiplies
the cos (ωt) *cos (α)
- sin (ωt) * sin (α)
and this is equal to
I (peek)
that multiplies
R * cos (ωt) * cos (β)
- R * sin (ωt) * sin (β)
- ω * L*sin (ωt) * cos (β)
- ω * L * cos (ωt) * sin (β)
You can see that we get to
very simple equations,
also called transcendental,
and that are not
very easy to use,
even if our circuit is "only"
an RL circuit,
so relatively simple.
If we must do all this work
for just RL,
we will see that this will
really complicate everything.
So now we can do
an identification
so we can write that
U (peek)
cos(α) is equal to
R * I (peek) * cos (β)
- ω * L * I (peek)
sin (β)
And the we have the other one:
U (peek) * sin (α)
is equal to
R * I (peek) * sin (β)
+ ω * L * I (peek)
cos (β).
So these are the two equations
that we can write by identification
and now by summing
the squares of the
equations that are here.
we will be able,
to find the following
terms by gathering them,
but after a lot of calculations.
We get:
U (peek) = I (peek)
√(R^2 + ω^2 L^2
So you can see that
it is relatively complex
to get to such a result.
And we will finally get to
α = β + φ.
But I will skip these calculations.
So the complexity of the result,
will lead us now to
another method.
We will now involve
complex calculation
In our different resolutions
of the circuit.
So I remind you the formulation,
or Euler's formula,
to write any number,
so I will write here X
that is equal to X(peek)  e^j θ
and this is what Euler's
formula tells us,
is equal to X (peek) * cos (θ)
+ j sin (θ).
So you can see that
in our different
sinusoidal connections,
whether the current or the voltage,
we have made it this form.
We have a part of this vector,
here it's a vector because we have
a real part and an imaginary part.
So this is the real part,
and this is the imaginary part.
And so, in our everyday lives
their are sines and cosines,
it is either the real part
or the imaginary part of
this vector or this relation,
that I write X underline
to show you here
that it's a vector or a
complex number.
The big advantage for
such a thing,
is that by noting Euler's formula,
we have here some derivatives
- if we derive this
complex number -
that takes the same form as
the first element.
And same for the primitive of
an integral, we get the same form.
It's always an exponential.
And this will paradoxically
simplify our calculations
when we will try to solve an
alternative single phased circuit,
is to use the complex notations.
So now, the idea is
to do this:
our voltage U
written U (peek) * cos (ωt + α).
This voltage that we will
decide to write differently.
We will write it U(vector).
We will make a complex
number with this relation.
What we are doing is
then purely conceptual,
and will allow us to solve
the problems of complicated calculations
that we had previously.
So by writing Euler's formula
U = U (peek)
e^j (ωt + α).
After all, we define our small u,
the real world as function of time,
it is the real part of this complex
number that we just made,
because it is only the part
of the cosine and not the sine.
So right now,
as an example,
let's try to do
exactly the same thing
for our example RL.
Since once we will finish
all our calculations,
but with complex numbers,
we will be able to come
back to the real numbers,
by saying that U or I
are the real parts of
complex numbers.
So we will now see
U that becomes U (vector)
= U (peek) * e^j (ωt + α).
The current will also have a
complex form :
i (peek) * e^j (ωt + β)
So we make complex numbers,
we work with complex numbers.
Our equation U = R * i + L di/dt
becomes
U (vector) = R * i (vector)
+ L di/dt
+ j ω L i (vector)
You see, we have here on top the current i
that is written with Euler's formula.
I (peek) e^j (ωt + β).
When we derive,
there is the j ω that comes up front,
and that simply multiplies
i again.
Therefore the derivation of a complex number
is the same thing as multiplying it by j ω.
We will write it later, to sum up.
So we can now write this
U (vector),
by putting everything together,
to R + j ω L times the current.
And we will call this new
complex number R + j ω L,
we will call it Z
if you wish.
So we will have U = Z * i.
In this Z, we can say that
R + j ω L is therefore this Z
that i just made
with Euler's formula,
it is Z e^j and we will
define an angle : φ.
So Z, the norm, will be
the square root of R^2 + ω^2 L^2
because here we have the form a + bj.
To look for the norm
it's the square root of a^2 + b^2 .
And the angle φ
is the tangent arc of ωL/R.
So we can now write what
we have here as a summary,
to be able to replace in the
equation of the beginning here,
and also in the equation
that I just wrote.
Here, we will replace U and I
by their functions.
This becomes:
U (peek) e^j (ωt + α)
on one side,
Z e^j (φ)
that multiplies the current I (peek)
e^j (ωt + β)
and this could be simplified into Z I (peek)
e^j (ωt + β + φ)
since the multiplication
of the two complex numbers here
will make the sum of the arguments.
We get to the following conclusion:
U (peek) = Z I (peek)
we have found in our I
if we had the U as data,
α = β + φ.
Finally, what interest us,
because they are
complex numbers,
we can come back to
real numbers by saying
that U is the real part of
U (vector), so it's
Z I (peek) cos (ωt + β + φ).
And you see that we have drastically
simplified the calculation of RL,
by finding here directly,
the answer of what we were looking for.
We can also represent, it's
interesting, the impedance Z.
This Z here, or written also here with
its complex form.
This Z that i remind you,
has for value R^2 + ω^2 L^2 ,
we can represent it
in the complex plane,
and the real or
imaginary components
make one vector which length is
equal to the modulus of the impedance Z.
So we will write here
that this length is Z.
Here it's the vector Z.
The length is therefore
the modulus of the impedance
and the angle φ, that is here,
is the tangent arc of ω L/R,
that will be also be the phase
shift definition
between voltage and current,
as we see here.
This φ is the phase shift between
the voltage and the current.
So to conclude, we saw the
single phased state, its definition,
how to represent these vectors
with complex numbers
that will help us paradoxicaly
to simplify calculations.
Therefore the advantages of complex calculations
for this differential equation in
steady-state resolution
which otherwise becomes
pretty difficult
if we use real numbers .
Thank you.