Hello and welcome to this lesson
dedicated to the second part of
sinusoidal single phase state.
During this lesson, we will first
resume an example
allowing us to better understand the
transit in complex calculations
to, paradoxically, simplify the
calculations seen during the first lesson,
then we will discover what the
admittance and the impedance are
and also Fresnel's representation that
will allow us to visualize
these elctrotechnic values, as
the voltage and the current,
in a complex plane,
that is to say vectors.
First, a small example and a
reminder to tell you
what we saw during this first
lesson dedicated to
sinusoidal single phased state.
We then saw that a
function of time,
such as the voltage at the terminals
of any element
in electrotechnics,
that is thus written...
and that represents in real time
the value of the voltage at any time
at the terminals of an element;
we will be able to transform
this variable in another variable
completely conceptual
that we will indicate by the u (vector),
underlined means that
we have a vector,
of an element in the complex plane,
that then takes the following form:
First of all, a real part and an
imaginary part.
This can also be written in
another form according to Euler.
Thus, we can work in this
plan said complex,
with real parts and
imaginary parts.
This element underlined represents then
the voltage with real numbers
and when we finish the calculations
with complex numbers,
we can then come back to real
numbers by taking the real part
of this element underlined,
of this complex voltage.
By taking the real part,
we come back to Û cos (ωt + α)
that matches with the real value
of the searched voltage.
We can of course,
it is just a suggestion
to take the cosine,
if we are more comfortable,
we can also do it
with sinusoidal variables
and the the transit between complex
numbers and imaginary numbers will be done,
not by taking the real part,
but the imaginary part
of this complex number.
I suggest a small simple
exercise to now
give the working method and
the different approaches
to use the complex calculations
during the resolution of a simple circuit
like here with an RC circuit.
We then have a voltage u
that will have the following form:
at the terminals of our R and our C
and therefore a current will be established
in the circuit, this current
will also have a
sinusoidal form, or co-sinusoidal,
with simply another phase shift
and we are looking here the value
of the current that flows in the circuit
and we are looking for an angle φ,
that is to say a phase shift between α and β.
How do we do?
In every circuit to analyse there is
often three first very simple steps
to take, that seem
sometimes to easy
and that we don't do,
but I suggest you to do them
systematically to help you
to understand the method right.
The first step, is
to redraw the sketch.
Of course here the sketch is very simple,
we will not draw it again,
but sometime, redrawing makes
the comprehension of the sketch
much better for the person
who draws it his way,
with the connections at the right places,
therefore it is often a step
that we avoid, but i recommend
you to do it each time.
The second important step,
is to establish the direction of the voltages
and the currents.
So if I already have the arrow for u,
the arrow for i,
We can also say that here
there is a voltage at the terminals of R
and here a voltage at the terminals
of the capacitance
and finally we can generally
apply Kirchhoff's law
to allow us to better understand the
circuit that establishes the equations
of the circuit.
For this last step,
we can then write
that u at the terminals of our circuit
is equal to U at the terminals of the resistor
plus U at the terminals of the capacitance.
We can also indicate what is equal
U of R, it will be equal to R times i,
and U and C, 1/C integral of i dt.
We can therefore,
to sum up these three steps,
write that the voltage u is
equal to Ri + (1/C) integral of i dt.
As we see , we have a
differential equation here.
Since we have an integral inside,
we come back to the same problems
that we have already met during
the first part of this topic
on the single phased state,
with a differential equation
and the complications linked
to the resolution of the equations
if we remain in the time mode
like here.
Then we now transit to complex numbers,
it is the step number four,
we transit to complex calculations.
What does it involve?
I remind you that u is
equal to Û cos (ωt + α)
will therefore become another u (vector)
that is equal to Ûe^j (ωt + α).
All of my equation found at the third step
with Kirchhoff's law transforms itself
into three elements that are now
all complex.
u (vector), complex voltage, is
equal to R * i (vector), complex current,
+ (1/C) integral of i (vector),
complex, dt.
The fifth step now is to
derive or to integrate.
It is this part here, of the integral
or in the case of the inductance,
we would have a derivative.
So let's work a little bit
on this derivative
and integrate to see what happens
when we have complex numbers.
What do we note?
We note that when we have
a derivative,
for example the derivative of a
complex number like this one,
if one has something of the form
Îe^j (ωt + β, by deriving
as the derivative of an exponential
always gives an exponential
but with the internal derivative,
we get jω Î e^j (ωt + β)
by taking the equation of the
current that we wrote before.
We notice that if it is
truly our i (vector),
we simply have jωi (vector) here.
So deriving a complex number
comes back to multiplying it by jω.
We can do the same for
the integral.
So now by integrating  a complex number
like here the integral of i dt,
we will have the integral
of an exponential
that is always an exponential
and by considering the integral calculation
we get (1/jω) Î e^j (ωt + β)
and we notice, again,
that here, if this is also
our i (vector),
integrating a complex number comes
back to dividing this complex number
by jω.
And now you see why it becomes easy
to transform our equations
in complex form, because
the integral that you see here,
in the complete Kirchhoff equation,
this integral solves itself very
easily by dividing i (vector)
by jω.
We therefore have our equation that becomes:
u (vector) = R * i (vector)
and we have (1/jωC) i (vector).
And you see as things
get easier.
We will now replace the different
suspected elements u and i, therefore unknown.
First Û e^j (ωt + α) is the voltage
of the beginning,
it is what is given,
it is equal to,
we highlight the i, we then
have [R + (1/jωC)] Î e^j (ωt + β).
We will here separate things to
understand better.
In the e^j (ωt + α),
here as elsewhere in the β,
we have a part that depends on the time
and a part that is a fixed angle.
When we have a sum here,
we can replace it by e^jωt . e^jα,
the rest doesn't change.
And we have the same thing for the current,
one part fluctuates with time
and another part is fixed.
Then we see that there is here
a left part and a right part
that is identical, it is this part that
fluctuates with time.
So we can simplify this equation
and solve an equation
that doesn't depend on time.
We may also be interested
for a moment
at this part R + (1/jωC),
that I will call Z,
it's a complex number,
we will then see what it represents.
And if we draw this element in
the complex plane,
so here imaginary and real
we see that we have a real part,
it's R, the resistance that is here,
and we have an imaginary part, (1/jωC).
Maybe to make things more precise,
when we have 1/jωC,
we can multiply by j and j
at the top and at the bottom
and we get j/ωC
and j times j makes -1,
so -j/ωC is something negative,
we will therefore have here a part
that depends on ωC but that will be negative
and finally, we have here this vector
that i will call note Z,
represented here.
The angle that is called here phi, φ.
Phi is therefore the tangent arc of
this imaginary part
on the real part, therefore -1/RωC.
and the norm of Z, it's the square root
of the real part squared
plus the imaginary part squared,
√R^2 + (1/ωC)^2.
That is, we have all the elements now
to solve and find
what we are looking for,
that is to say the phase shift
between voltage and current,
and the value of this current
that flows through the circuit.
We get to the sixth step
of our method,
that is to say solve and identify.
We have our Û cos α + j Û sin α on one side,
that is equal to our Z e^jφ,
I write this Z that I just
mentioned like this,
multiplied by the vector Î e^jβ.
So this, it is also what we
wrote Û e^jα.
So there is our equation
and we can now
determinate very simply the
solution first complex,
then the real solution,
Then the complex solution is real.
But first complex.
We are looking for the i here,
therefore this small i (vector)
that is equal to Î e^j (ωt + β)
is equal to (Û/Z) e^j (ωt + α - φ).
The final solution that we
are looking for
is of course the real i, this i here.
we know that to find the real i we
must take the real part
of my complex i and therefore
we will get:
(Û/Z) cos (ωt + α - φ).
It is the final answer to this problem
and you know the different steps,
that you will do faster once
you will be used to it,
and that allows you to finally
solve very easily
an electrotechnical problem with R,L
or C, or the three at the same time.
Now let's see by definition
what is the instantaneous complex value
and what are complex phasors.
We saw previously in
our small example,
a u (vector) Û e^j (ωt + α),
is by definition
the instantaneous complex value.
Instantaneous because it depends on time.
We also saw that it
wasn't very important
because we can eliminate
this temporal component.
We will therefore come up with a new element
that we will call a phasor
and that doesn't depend on time anymore.
This phasor that we will
write note by U capital.
Then there are two phasors:
the peak phasor,
with the peak value
as modulus of this vector,
or simply, the phasor
by taking its effective value
of this variable.
We will therefore work with
these three variables,
primarily the last two, or
even the last one, of these phasors.
We saw before, this instantaneous complex
value vector is a vector
that will rotate in the complex plane
because of the ωt.
How fast will it rotate ?
Well, it's the ω that determinates
how fast this vector rotates.
Then, we will decide to eliminate the e^jωt
on both sides of the equations,
since we have something
that doesn't depend on time.
By doing this, it's like if we
had photographed at an instant t
and we just look at the angle
of the voltage at this moment
in the complex plane.
And just, we stopped the current
and what interest us
is the angle difference between
this voltage or this current,
that allows us to determinate
different elements
that we are looking for
and that we would like to know
in the circuit.
This is what we can show
in the complex plane.
This current phasor here,
you have two of them that are marked here-
We did this photograph or
this snapshot.
Our voltage and our current
don't depend on time,
we don't need ωt + α or ωt + β anymore,
we just have α or β,
and therefore we have a snapshot,
a vector at on given moment,
same for U
with an angle β,
that we recover here,
another angle, α, here.
So we have a voltage and a current
and what we notice is
that this angle difference,
between voltage and current,
is what we are generally looking for,
that will depend on the elements R, L, C
in the circuit and that are equal to α - β,
therefore φ = α - β,
we have this angle difference.
Now, we can have
not only a voltage
but several voltages, we
also made earlier
a sum of voltages.
So we must be very careful
compared to what we saw
in the steady state where the voltages
and the currents are constant,
we can do the arithmetical sum
of voltages and currents.
When we work with
phasors,
when we work with
complex calculations,
we work with vectors.
The sum of two vectors is not
just an arithmetical addition.
So, if this vector U represents,
let's say 50 volts,
and that there is another U at another moment,
50 volts plus 50 volts do not
necessarily make 100 volts
when we add them,
unless these two vectors are
collinear.
Here's an example where
you can see different voltages
that we have, for example here, added,
U1 and U2 that will give us U3.
Therefore you have the first U1 that is here
with a certain angle,
a U2 that is here with
another angle.
And you see that
when we do U1 + U2,
we do a vector sum to
get U3
that is not equal to the
sum of U2 and U1
but that must be calculated by
the geometrical elements.
We will then see that it's pretty simple
in the case where it's orthogonal
because we can use the
well known Pythagorean relation,
but here it is not orthogonal,
we must calculate very precisely
in complex numbers, the sum of U1 and U2,
which will add a little bit of additional work
but  not to forget to be very careful.
So you see here on this image,
or on this animation,
on the right the imaginary part of the voltage
and on the left at the bottom, the real part
of this same voltage,
and on the top left, well, this vector
that changes as function of time.
You can see the equation
at the bottom right,
this vector representation of the voltage,
Û1 cos ωt + jÛ1 sin ωt.
So, at the top right, the sine,
at the bottom left, the cosine.
Then we can choose one or another
of these representations.
What will interest us is now
to always talk about
a cosine, it's the part
on the bottom left,
but that will be written in the
complex plane by a vector,
a vector that rotate as
you can see up here.
We can also decide to stop it,
this is what we do
when we talk about phasors.
Now we will see a second video
that will allow us to see
what is happening when
i put another signal.
So on this video,
we put three voltages
that are slightly phase shifted
one another.
You see in the real world,
that is to say always the drawing
at the bottom left,
these are cosines,
three cosines slightly phase shifted
of 20 degrees.
It is what gives us in the complex domain
these three vectors that rotate,
U1, U2, U3, at the same speed
but slightly shifted
and that follow each other.
If we prefer the sine representation,
that is to say the imganinary part,
we then take the top right
representation
and then we will always work with
the imaginary part of the vector.
Then on this last video I will
show here three vectors
phased shifted by 120 degrees from each other.
Why?
Well, because the single phased
sinusoidal steady state will follow after
in the three phase to allow us to
transmit energy.
And so, we will have these kind of signals
very well known and frequent
since it's the power supply of
most countries throughout the world
to use a network and a symmetrical
three-phase system.
You can now see the three vectors,
U1, U2, U3, that spin at the same speed
in a symmetrical way and
whose sum is always zero.
We call this representation of sines,
cosines and vectors,
Fresnel's representation and
is what we are going to talk about
when we also want to say
in the complex plane,
we can talk of Fresnel's
representation.
We will now see what
are the impedance and the admittance;
impedance and admittance  are
foundations of electrotechnics
that allows us to model the
different elements R, L, C
and also that leads us to
the famous Ohm's law equation
but here with complex numbers
as we have seen before
when we talked about constant
current and voltage.
This Z underlined, therefore the impedance by
definition, is equal to the instantaneous voltage
divided by the instantaneous current,
but what is also great about it,
is that it's also the voltage phasor
divided by the current phasor,
or the peak voltage phasor divided
by the peak current phasor.
These three relations are strictly
identical.
in the same way we define
an admittance
that we will define as the
inverse of the impedance
and that also has some
particular properties
that can sometime be used
easier than the impedance,
it's the reason for which we
will also define it here.
The properties of this impedance are
the following:
first, when we write our Z, that
is equal to the voltage phasor
divided by the current phasor,
we therefore have U e^jα
for the voltage phasor, I e^jβ
for the current phasor
and we have, by using the mathematical
property of exponential,
a new exponential that is
equal to α - β.
And we define this as being
the angle phi, φ.
Phi is therefore equal to α - β
as we saw before.
By identification, we have the
norm of this vector Z
that is here, is simply equal to
U over I.
We are not surprised because
it's the already known Ohms law
and this angle φ is α - β.
We can write the same way for
the admittance this time,
since it's the inverse of Z,
that it's a current over a voltage
and that it's equal to (1/Z) e^-jφ
or then Y e^-jφ.
Now let's see what happens inside
of this Z.
We say that this impedance Z is equal to Z e^jφ
therefore Z cos φ + j Z sin φ.
It's a complex number but
we can also write it,
as we see here a + j b.
We therefore have a real part, it's
this Z cos φ,
an imaginary part,
it's this Z sin φ.
We will call the part "a",
the resistance,
and we will call the "b" part,
the reactance.
The resistance is well known by
everybody,
therefore this Z cos φ is necessarily real,
there is just one element
that can represent this reality it's
the resistor R,
it is therefore the real part of Z.
We have this Z sin φ that can be represented
either by a capacitance or an inductance.
We will give it the symbol X and call
this the reactance
and this reactance would be equal to
the imaginary part of the impedance.
We symbolize this X,
or this imaginary part,
by, you have it here on the symbol,
a black square
that represents the fact that this
element here is imaginary
or has an imaginary component.
We therefore have, our impedance
that will always be written
as R + jX, with the norm of
this vector
that will be equal to √R^2 + X^2
with a φ angle
that will be equal to the tangent arc
of X over R.
We have a very clear
representation,
so you have the impedance Z,
its real part R,
here, drawn, a part of a positive
reactance,
this also means that finally
this reactance behaves
as an inductance, since
I remind you
that the inductance will have
a positive part,
it's the jωL.
So we will have ωL and we will have -1/ωC
for a capacitance.
Let's now take case-by-case
R, L and C do determinate
how they behave as function of
the impedance and the admittance
and that it will give us Ohms law
for each element.
The first case, very simple,
the resistor.
Let's admit that we know that
U = Z I, is Ohms law
but here with the complex case.
Our impedance for a resistor,
is simply R,
and is equal to U (vector) divided by I
(vector) written as previously,
or U divided by I.
Why?
because U and I are in phase
and that this phi of the resistor,
namely α - β, the phase shift
between voltage and current,
are equal to zero for the resistance.
And in the case of the admittance,
the Y of R that is equal to 1/R,
we sometimes call it G uppercase,
or conductance.
There is now the case of the inductance.
In the case of the inductance,
we have an equation U
that links the current I with a relation
that we have already seen before
and that is equal to jωL.
We therefore have U = jωL * I.
We can maybe explain for
a reminder,
the equation in time
is U = L (di/dt).
If written in vector,
U = L (di(vector) /dt).
We saw that to derive
it was simply
the current times jω.
So we have jω and the L that stays
and finally the small i.
We therefore have this U equal to jω L i.
And now if we remove,
or if these are two vectors
that spin as function of time, of ωt,
if we divide by ωt
on both sides, so if we do as I said
before
a photograph, well
we get phasors again,
it's the equation that I wrote here.
My impedance ZL is equal to U (vector)
divided by I (vector)
and therefore is equal to jωL.
It's the impedance of an inductance.
We therefore have ZL, the norm,
that is simply equal to ωL.
We have the angle φL, as it is
equal to the tangent arc of ωL/R,
this is just in the RL case,
but here in this case
of the inductance we have a j,
therefore one is perfectly vertical,
this angle is equal to π/2.
And for the impedance,
the resistor is zero.
Finally the case of the capacitor.
We have in the temporal case
i = C (du/dt).
We have the i (vector) that is then
equal to j ωC x u (vector).
Or then, I (vector),
we are now in phasors,
equal to j ωC x U((vector))
Said otherwise, the impedance Zc,
that is by definition,
equal to U/I for phasors,
will be equal to 1/jωC or -j (1/ωC).
We can write that the norm of the Z
of the capacitor
is 1/ωC, that the reactance of
the capacitor
is -1/ωC, the angle φc,
is negative, so it will be equal to -π/2,
and again
the resistance of C is zero.
To sum up, we sketched a graph
in the complex plane
of the three impedances R, L and C
that we just wrote.
You have here, in the first column
of this table,
the real part of Z and
the imaginary part.
In other words, the resistance
and the reactance.
Then the norm, the angle and finally,
the impedance written under the complex form.
We therefore have our first vector R
that is on the real part.
If you take a second element L
with a jωL,
there is a vertical vector,
the angle is equal to π/2.
And finally, with the capacitance
we saw that it was negative
because of 1/jωC or -j (1/ωC).
We have a perfectly vertical vector
but negative
so -π/2 for the angle.
The last thing we have yet to see
are the power supplies.
When we have a voltage supply
that works in alternative, in a
sinusoidal single phased steady state
we must ask what is happening,
as for the steady state or the DC voltage.
So in the same way as the DC
steady state,
an ideal supply doesn't work.
Therefore we always have a voltage supply
or a current supply
that must be associated
to an internal impedance
that is put in parallel of serial.
Therefore for the voltage supply,
we have here this element here
that is an internal impedance
of the supply.
This Zs is the internal impedance.
It is put in series with the supply
allowing us to have, this time,
a voltage supply said real.
In the same way for the current,
we must put a real impedance
in order to have a real current supply,
this impedance is said to
be internal to the supply,
and will allow us to define this
real current supply
and not ideal as before.
Therefore this Zp here is also
the internal impedance.
To finish, I suggest you
this small example
to picture what we just saw with
the supplies
and the calculations of impedances.
We have here a voltage of 500 volts,
a resistance of 2 ohms
and a reactance of also 2 ohms,
that I write here j2,
and our load Zch that would take
three different values,
either a resistance of 48 ohms,
or an inductance of 48 ohms,
or either a capacitance of 48 ohms
and you will see each time
that the impedance is different.
The first case, the case
where the resistance by itself.
We therefore have Zch that is only
equal to 48.
What is the total impedance?
Well here, these three impedances are in
series, we will then add
the internal impedance plus
the impedance load
therefore 2 + j2 + 48, be careful
to not add
apples and oranges, we have a
real part,
an imaginary part.
Therefore the real part is equal to 50
and the imaginary is always 2.
So my Z total, or the norm
is √(50^2 + 2^2)
which is about 50 ohms.
We can also calculate here the current.
So the current I is U/Ztot and is
worth 10 amps.
At the terminals of the load of
my resistor,
well, it's the Z of the load resistance
times the current
and we get 480 volts.
Let's get to the b case.
For the b case, we now have our Zch
that is equal to j48, it's different,
our Z total will then be added
with the rest,
but in the real part it's
2 only
and the imaginary part is 50.
So Z total but normed,
the norm of this vector,
square root of 2 squared plus
50 squared,
will also give the same number
as before, roughly 50.
And with the current,
we find the same numbers.
The U at the terminals of this
inductance is also 480 volts.
Last case is, the c, with this time
a capacitance, a capacitor.
Our Zch is -48 ohms,
our Z total will now slightly
change compared to before, because
we will have 2 + j2 - j48
and we get 2 - j46 and our norm
will be different
from the two previous cases,
about 46 ohms,
with a current that is then
equal to 10.87 A
and a voltage at the terminals
of this capacitance
that is 521,7 volts.
To sum up, we now saw all
the chapter
on sinusoidal
single phased state.
You saw the advantages of the
transit to complex calculations,
and finally the paradox of
easier calculations
when we write the elements
with vectors
where the different values,
as the voltage, current or impedances,
with vectors and this
Fresnel representation
that allows us to represent
these vectors in the complex plane,
that these vectors are fixed
or move as function of time,
allowing us to have a picture of
what is happening in the complex world,
but showing conceptually the reality.
Thank you.