Hello, and welcome to this new lecture
of the Electrotechnics course.
In the previous lecture,
we have studied and constructed
the geometric locus of an impedance.
We have seen a particular
point of this locus,
it is the point for which the impedance
is purely resistive,
without any reactive part.
Today, we will study in more
details this particularity.
We will then talk about
resonant circuits,
composed of elements L and C.
We will see two different
type of circuits LC,
the case of a circuit LC in series,
and the case of a circuit LC in parallel,
we will see their behavior
in terms of frequency and the resonance condition.
Finally, we will focus on
the equivalence of this dipole,
in series or in parallel,
and their frequency dependence.
A dipole composed of two elements L and C,
connected in series or in parallel,
is called resonating circuit .
We understand this name if we
refer to powers,
we have shown that the
reactive power
is periodically transiting from
one element to another, L or C.
If we make an analogy with
the mechanical field,
for example a resonating
oscillator,
made out of a mass and a spring,
in which there is a periodical exchange
between potential and kinetic energy
between the spring and the mass.
If we go back to our electric circuit,
as function of the frequency
when it is excited,
it's properties will be modified,
in particular because the impedance
changes value.
Let's take the example of an inductance
and a capacitance in series.
They are presented in this figure
and we will calculate the total impedance
of the circuit, of the norm,
and we will represent it in
the complex plane.
Therefore if we call Zeq the total
impedance of the circuit,
it consists of a first part, it is the reactive
part of the inductance,
plus, as it is in series,
the reactive part of the capacitor,
it is - j 1 over ωC.
We can write it differently,
by putting the two terms
under the same denominator,
we have j over ωC, and we
multiply it by ω²LC-1
We can calculate it's norm,
therefore the norm of Zeq is given
by the absolute value
of ω²LC-1 over ωC
The representation in the complex plane,
we have already done it many times,
is given by the sum of
these two vectors,
Therefore for the real part
and for the imaginary part,
we have the vector that is the impedance of C,
and the vector that is the impedance of L,
that is to say - j over ωC and jωL
We see that these two vectors have
a length that depends
on the pulse or the frequency at which
the circuit is energized.
If we analyse this equation that
represents the total impedance of the circuit,
we see that the pulse which the circuit is
energized the circuit tends to 0,
The equivalent impedance will
tend to infinity,
because we have a 0 at the denominator
and therefore this value becomes infinite.
Contrary to the other extreme,
if the pulse tends towards infinity,
The equivalent impedance also
tends to infinity,
because the term ω² is at the numerator
and therefore the norm of this term
will tend to infinity.
The resonance condition is achieved
for a particular point
when the numerator is here equal to 0,
that is to say, for a particular value
of ω that we will name ω0,
that is equal to 1 over √LC,
it is this numerator that is equal to 0
The resonance frequency that is
proportional to the pulse,
is equal to 1 over 2π
multiplied by 1 over √LC
Therefore ω0 is the resonance pulse
when the numerator is equal to 0
If we analyse this variable
as function of the pulse,
we see that the circuit is energized
at a pulse
that is inferior
to the resonance pulse,
we have that this term, the numerator
ω²LC is smaller than 1,
we therefore have an impedance Ẕ
that is a capacitive type.
The nature of the equivalent circuit
is capacitive type.
Therefore the circuit behaves in this case
as a capacitor.
Contrary if the pulse which
energizes the circuit
is bigger than ω0 for
the resonance pulse,
we will have that ω²LC will be bigger than 1,
and the equivalent impedance
will be jX2 type,
and in this case here, the circuit will
behave as an inductance,
this is positive, we say that the nature of
the circuit at this frequency, is inductive.
The circuit globally behaves
as an inductance.
Graphically, if we represent this
function in a ωZ plane
therefore Z as function of the pulse,
we will have that this Z,
as function of the pulse ω
for a particular value of ω0,
is the resonance condition,
the numerator is equal to 0,
and therefore this impedance Z is equal to 0.
However when we get further from
this resonance pulse,
that is to say towards 0 or infinity,
we have the norm of this impedance
that tend towards infinity,
which gives a curve that approximatively
looks like this.
If we look at the imaginary part of Z
as function of ω
we will have something that
describes the following shape,
therefore as function of ω,
the equivalent imaginary part of Z,
we said that the circuit behaves
in a capacitive way,
under the resonance frequency,
and in an inductive way
above the resonance frequency,
therefore we have a curve that looks like this,
thus here a capacitive behaviour, and
here an inductive behaviour,
the imaginary part is positive.
If we now consider the LC resonant
circuit but parallel,
we have this circuit here, we can again
write the equivalent impedance of the circuit,
that is equal, as the elements are
in parallel,
to the inverse of the sum
of the impedance's inverse,
which gives 1 over jωL, it's
the inverse of the inductance impedance,
+ jωC written differently to show the
scalar at the denominator,
it gives us this,
the denominator is equal to 1 - ω²LC
and jωL at the numerator
If we analyse again the behaviour of the
circuit as function of the frequency,
thus when we energize at a frequency ω
that is very small, therefore that tends to 0,
well we have an impedance that
also tends to 0,
because this term in the numerator
cancels this term here.
Conversely if the frequency which
we energized the circuit tends to infinity,
we also have the impedance that
tends towards 0
because the term ω
at the denominator
becomes very high and cancels this term here.
For the particular value that cancels here
the denominator,
for this particular resonance
pulse value,
ω is equal to 1 over √LC
thus we cancel the denominator,
this time the impedance
will tend towards infinity.
Therefore this is again
the resonance pulse,
it is said that the circuit is tuned,
and it's the exact same condition as
in the LC circuit in series
Again, if we represent the norm
of Z as function
of the pulsation to which the circuit
is energized,
we have this particular value ω0
the resonance pulse,
for which the impedance is infinite,
and beyond this frequency,
the impedance tends towards 0,
thus this is the norm of the impedance,
we have something schematically,
which is like this,
with again an inductive behaviour
of the circuit,
for small values under
the pulse ω0,
and has a capacitive type when we
go above the resonance pulse.
So if we look now
the imaginary part
of the equivalent impedance
as function of the pulse,
we have again this resonant
pulse ω0
for which the imaginary part
of Z is zero,
and the circuit is of inductive nature,
at low frequency,
and of capacitive nature,
at high frequency.
This circuit is also called
tank circuit,
because at the resonant pulse,
its impedance is infinite,
and therefore it will oppose to the
current flow at this frequency.
We have calculated by the real case
of a LC circuit in parallel ,
for witch we sketched the characteristic
with a simulation software,
we can see as
we had said earlier,
that we have this resonant
frequency here ω0
The circuit is inductive for
frequencies smaller than ω0
and capacitive for
longer frequencies.
If we power this circuit at a
pulse smaller than ω0
lets call it ω1,
the circuit will not oppose to
the current flow,
because the impedance is low.
On the other side, if we power the circuit
at a frequency of pulse ω2
which corresponds to the
resonant frequency,
no current will flow because
the impedance is infinite,
the circuit opposes to this frequency.
If we increase again the
excitation pulse of the circuit,
till a value, here for example, ω3
again the circuit will not oppose
to the transit to this frequency,
their will be an output signal,
because the impedance is smaller.
Now, if we change the circuit
parameters,
that is to say that we will
change the value of LC,
and that we lower its values,
the feature will move,
and will move to a value ω02
that is higher because
the LC pair is smaller,
and the signal at the pulse ω2
that was cut by the previous circuit,
is not for this circuit here because
the feature moved,
and it's now this frequency that
will be attenuated by the circuit.
We see that one can use the
elements L and C of the circuit,
to finally bloc the frequency
that we want to.
This is the principle of filtering.
As a concrete case we have
a signal which is composed of two voltages,
first and second,
it can simply be 2
power supplies,
on at a frequency ω1,
the other at a frequency ω2
that powers our parallel circuit LC,
or it can be a more general case,
for example an audio signal
which would include
many frequencies,
here we just have two but
it could be more,
if we add these two signals,
we find something like this,
a signal that has two or
even several components,
we see here the first component
at a certain frequency,
and the second component
at another frequency.
If now we power the
parallel LC circuit
where the resonant frequency is ω01
which corresponds in this case,
to a low frequency,
which matches to this signal here,
I power my circuit with the total
signal here, that is the sum of both,
this frequency ω0 corresponds
to the low frequency here,
it will be attenuated, cut,
and therefore as output result,
we will have a signal that will
mainly have
a high frequency signal,
with a small low frequency
signal that is attenuated.
If now we change the
resonant frequency of the circuit,
that is to say we change
the parameters L and C,
we decrease them so ω02 increases
and get the right frequency,
the high frequency of the signal,
well by powering the circuit
with this signal,
we will have the high frequency
that will be cut,
and a t the output, their will only be
the low frequency that remains,
here that is not attenuated by the circuit.
We can name two examples
from our everyday lives,
the first one is an ADSL link,
therefore it's a telephone link,
thus the human voice that has a
certain number of frequencies
between 16 and 15 kilohertz,
and on this signal we will superimpose
an information signal
to transit the information
of the network.
Well when we talk, we don't want to hear
all these frequencies,
we would rather only hear
the voice frequencies,
when we are on the phone,
we have this filter here,
that allows to cut the high frequencies
of the digital signals.
A second example, is what we
call Power Line Carrier,
that is to say that we will superimpose
to the 50 hertz domestic supply network,
we will superimpose a
high frequency signal
that is also an information,
and then this information,
we would like to split it
when it comes to the computer
for example,
we have the information signal
and not the 50 Hz signal,
thus again we use the filtering,
as we have explained previously.
We will address one
final point today,
those are equivalent dipoles.
We have here a dipole that is made of
a resistor R1 and an inductance
L1 in series,
we can determine the
equivalent impedance of this dipole,
we gave it in the previous lessons,
it is represented by the equation here,
and the circuit R2 L2 in parallel where
the equivalent impedance is given here.
You will also find this result
in the tables that we have given
in the previous lessons.
So that these two circuits
are equivalent,
it is necessary that firstly
the resistive portion of R1
must be equal to the resistive
part of the other,
and on the other hand
the imaginary part of one,
must be equal to the imaginary part
of the other.
Therefore R1 must be equal to this,
first condition,
and second condition,
L1 must be equal to this term here.
What is interesting to notice,
is that this equivalence
is true only at one frequency
because the term R1 depends on R2 and
also the pulse ω
same for the equivalent inductance
that depends on the pulse,
thus this is true only
at a given frequency,
if we change the frequency, we must
change again the parameters R2 and L2
for the equivalence
of the two circuits.
It is clear that the transition is done here
in the direction parallel series,
but could be done
in the other direction, parallel series,
by extracting the term R2 of
this equation,
and for the inductance, extract the term L2
of this equation here.
It's the same for the circuit RC serie
and RC parallel,
if we want those two dipoles
to be equivalent,
we write the relation that describes R
and the equivalent impedance,
it's this term here, we can
write it differently,
for the parallel RC circuit,
we have this equation here,
and for there to be equivalence,
the real part of one must be
again equal to the other
and the imaginary parts also
have to be equal.
We can rewrite the term R3
as function of R4 and C4,
and we have that R3 is equal to R4
divided by the denominator,
and for the equivalence
of the imaginary part,
C3 must be equal to this term,
it's the equivalence condition
of these two circuits,
but again, at a given
pulse or frequency,
because this equivalence
depends on the pulse.
We saw what were
resonant circuits,
what are their characteristics and under what
conditions they are in resonance.
We saw how to change
the characteristics,
and what we can do,
especially in the domain of filtering.
Finally, we saw the
equivalent dipoles,
and we saw that they depend
on the power supply frequency.
Thank you for your attention.