In this lecture, we're going
to talk about names,
which are a fundamental building block
of computer systems.
We will start by asking what a name is,
and we will also look at examples
of different naming schemes.
What is a name?
Let us look at a few examples.
A memory address is a name
that refers to a memory cell.
An IP address is a name
that refers to a network interface.
A web URL is a name
that refers to a web object.
And an email address is a name
that refers to an email account.
So, a name is a way
to refer to a resource.
Why do systems use names?
One obvious use is for specifying
which resource to read from or write to.
But there are other, more subtle uses.
Suppose we have an object stored in memory
which stores information
about a network architecture lab.
And we also have objects
that store information
about different members of the lab.
These objects need to
communicate between them.
In particular, the lab object on the left
needs to access the content
of the member objects on the right.
One way to do that is
to copy the contents
of the member objects into the lab object.
Another way is to assign names
to the member objects,
and store only these names
into the lab object.
Now whenever the lab object
needs to access the member objects,
it can use their names to find them.
For those of you who program a lot,
this example is akin
to passing a function arguments
by value versus by reference.
And by the way, a C++ pointer is
a name for the object it is pointing to.
So, systems use names
as communication and organization tools.
We said earlier that an IP address is a
name that refers to a network interface.
But there exists another way
to refer to a network interface.
A DNS name.
However, a DNS name does not
point directly to a network interface.
It points to an IP address
which then points to a network interface.
So an IP address can be a name
that points to a network interface,
and at the same time,
the value of a DNS name.
In this scenario, we are using a name,
in particular an IP address,
as an indirection tool.
Why is this useful?
Well, for one thing, it allows us to
dynamically change the network interface
that www.epfl.ch refers to
by changing only the IP address
that it is mapped to.
And this is the basic idea
behind dynamic DNS.
It changes DNS name to value mappings
so as to optimize network performance.
In this situation, the act of choosing
one of all possible values,
and mapping a name to it,
is called "binding".
Now consider the set of all possible
DNS names on the left,
the set of all possible
IP addresses on the right,
and the DNS system that maps names
to IP addresses in the middle.
We call the set on the left,
a "namespace",
the set on the right,
a "universe of values",
and the system that does the mapping,
a "name-mapping algorithm",
or a "resolver".
In the case of dynamic DNS,
to decide which value to map a name to,
the DNS system needs extra information.
For example, the location
of the requester.
We call this extra information,
"context".
Let's look at a couple more
examples of naming schemes.
A phone book maps human names
to phone numbers.
In the United States at least,
there is a different phone book
per county, so each county
is a different context
for this naming scheme.
To get back to computer systems,
a page table maps virtual memory addresses
to physical memory addresses.
And there is typically a different
page table per process.
So each process is now
a different context.
So, a naming scheme exposes
the following interface to its users.
The RESOLVE primitive returns
the value of a given name
in a given context.
The BIND primitive maps a given name,
to a given value, in a given context,
and it returns the status of the binding;
typically a success, or failure.
Some naming schemes support
other primitives as well.
ENUMERATE returns
a list of map names,
and sometimes also a list of map values
in a given context.
And the COMPARE primitive returns
"true" or "false", depending on whether
two given names are the same.
And we will later see
what "the same" means.
So, a name is a way
to refer to a resource.
Computer systems use names
as communication or organization tools,
and also as indirection tools
to make the connection between
two different objects more flexible.
Finally, designing a naming scheme
involves choosing a namespace,
choosing a universe of values,
and also choosing a mapping algorithm
that maps names or values.