We will now discuss the
design of name service
proposed by Butler-Lampson
in a classic paper from 1986.
We are studying this for two reasons:
first, as a name service design
it is arguably the most complete one
that has been proposed.
Second, as a system design in general
it is one of the most elegant ones.
And we will recognize in it
a fundamental design patterns
that underly many successful systems.
The basic design goals of this system
are scalability, reliability, performance,
and well-defined behavior.
We will examine them one by one.
The first design goal is scalability.
Which informally is the ability
to accommodate growth.
Our system should be able to store
mappings for an arbitrary number of names
and it should continue to function
well in the face of growth.
Let's see how this is achieved.
The role of a name service also called
a directory service is to implement
the general naming scheme,
that is map general names to values.
The names that Butler-Lampson
had in mind when he proposed
his design involve an entity
and a property of that entity.
For example, "Katerina's lab" is a name
and its value is "Network Architecture".
"Katerina's office" is another name
and its value is "BC120".
Moreover, the name "Katerina's lab"
involves "Katerina" who is an entity
and her "lab" which is
a property of "Katerina".
A directory is organized as a tree.
Each arch in the tree
is assigned a label.
Also each node in the tree is assigned
a time stamp and we will later see
the role of these time stamps.
At the second highest level of the tree,
right below the root,
the labels correspond to entities.
At the next level down,
the labels correspond to properties.
And at the bottom level,
the labels correspond to values.
For example, "Lampson" is an entity,
"Password" is a property of "Lampson"
and "vnxm56" is the value
of Lampson's Password.
To accommodate growth we cannot
put all the entities, properties,
and values in the world
into a single directory.
So we have multiple directories.
And the directories themselves
are organized in a tree.
Since we have multiple directories
we need a way to tell them apart.
And for that we use directory identifies
that are globally unique.
We also use directory names
that are unique locally,
that is within their parent directory.
Let me pause here.
I just mentioned two different ways
to refer to a directory,
using a directory identifier like "311"
and using a directory name like
"DEC" or "IBM" or "SRC".
Do not be confused by the fact
that one is called a directory identifier
whereas the other
is called a directory name.
Both of these are names;
they're different ways
to refer to directories.
The fundamental difference between
a directory identifier like "311"
and a directory name like "SRC" or "DEC"
is that the former is globally unique
whereas the latter unique within
their parent directory.
For example, "IBM" could also
have a child directory named "SRC".
So, we have global directory identifiers
and local directory names,
what about the labels?
Labels like "Lampson" and "Password"
are also name and they are local,
that is they are unique only in
the context of their parent node.
In other words, each directory
has its own private name space.
When new nodes and labels
are added to one directory
the other directories are not effected.
We said that the role of a name service
is to map names to values
but what kind of names?
I have already mentioned
three different kinds of names to you:
directory identifiers,
directory names, and labels.
The names that we can look up
in the name service belong
to yet another kind.
Let's see a few examples.
A name that we can look up in the
name service consists of multiple pieces.
It starts with a global
directory identifier, like "999"
which corresponds to the root
of the directory tree.
Potentially followed by local directory
names like "DEC" and "SRC".
Followed by an entity label
like "Lampson" and then
a property label like "Password".
This name specifies a node
in the directory tree.
The value of the name is
the label associated
with the child of the specified node.
Lets's look at a second example.
Here the node specified by
the name has two children,
in this case the value of the name
is the set of labels associated
with the children of the specified node.
And let's look at a third example.
Here the node specified by the name
is the root of a three level subtree.
In this case the value of the name is
the entire subtree rooted
at the specified node.
The fact that each directory has its
own name space enables distributed growth.
For example, directory 311 may be
stored in DEC infrastructure
and managed by DEC personnel.
While directory 552 is delegated
to IBM and directory 935
is delegated to a particular
subdivision of IBM.
So, scalability is achieved
through hierarchy.
Each directory has its own name space
and potentially its own administrator.
This enables distributed growth
in the sense that administrators
can add depth or breadth
to the hierarchy
without having to coordinate
with each other.