We are discussing Butler Lampson's
name service,
and the second design goal for the system
is reliability.
Whenever a user looks up a name,
that should be successfully resolved
even in the face
of infrastructure problems.
Let's see how that is achieved.
So far, we have seen that,
to its users,
the name service exposes the view
of a directory tree.
Under the covers, however,
things are quite different.
Each directory is stored
into multiple servers,
and each server maintains its own copy
of the directory contents.
Now let's zoom into the internals
of the SRC directory.
In the previous slide,
I implied that all copies
of the same directory
always have the same content.
In reality this may not be the case,
because different servers
may see different updates.
That is, different changes
to the directory content.
For example, suppose that at some point
the three directory copies look like this.
Then three updates occurred.
Update A reached all servers.
Update B reached only server gamma.
And Update C
reached servers alpha and gamma.
So, it is possible that
the directory copies
become desynchronized.
Which means that we need a mechanism
to periodically resynchronize them.
This mechanism is called a sweep.
And it periodically
reads all the new updates
from directory copies and writes them back
to all directory copies.
Let us see this visually.
The sweep arrives at server alpha,
reads the blue and orange updates
that have reached the server,
then moves on to server beta,
where there are no new updates to read.
Then moves on to server gamma,
where it reads the green update.
Each sweep has a timestamp
associated with it.
In this example it is five.
And every time it reads from
a directory copy,
it marks the directory copy
with its timestamp.
After reading all directory copies,
the sweep circles back to the beginning,
and writes to each server the updates
that the server is missing.
Every time the sweep
writes the directory copy,
it marks again that copy
with its timestamp.
So, reliability is achieved
through redundancy.
Each directory is copied
into multiple servers,
and it is enough for one of
these servers to be reachable
to enable successful name lookup.
This requires a bit of extra care,
we need to periodically resynchronize
the different directory copies.
That is because different servers
see different updates,
so we need a periodic sweep
in order to bring all
the different directory copies
up to date.