We are discussing
Butler Lampson's name service
and the third design goal
for the system is performance.
When a user looks up a name
they should get a response within say,
a few hundreds of milliseconds
even if the system happens
to be storing millions of name mappings.
Let's see how this is achieved.
To discuss the performance of the system,
we first need to look at
its operation in a bit more detail.
In an earlier slide, we said that given
the directory tree on the left,
this name maps to this value.
Let's see now what happens
when a user needs to obtain
this name to value mapping.
The first component of the name
is the directory identifier
of the root directory.
The assumption is that every machine
knows how to reach the root directory.
More specifically, every machine knows
how to reach at least one server
that stores a copy of the root directory.
The second component is DEC.
This is a local directory name
that only the root directory knows about.
So we need to ask
the root directory about it.
The root directory stores information
about the DEC directory in this form.
"DR" stands for directory reference.
311 is the directory identifier for DEC
and "delta" and "omega" are identifiers
for the servers that store copies
of the DEC directory.
So, from the point of view
of the root directory
DEC is an entity, DR is a property of DEC
and the information about DEC
is the value of the DR property.
Which means that to learn how
to reach the DEC directory
we need to look up this name in
the root directory and get back its value.
So now we know how to reach
the DEC directory
and we need to learn how
to reach the SRC directory.
This is again a local directory name
that only the DEC directory knows about.
So we need to ask
the DEC directory about it.
The rest is as you would expect.
The DEC directory stores information
about the SRC directory in this form.
So to learn how to reach
the SRC directory
we need to look up this name in
the DEC directory and get back its value.
Let me make a parentheses here.
This is one of the most elegant aspects
of the design of this system.
All the metadata that are needed by
the system are stored
within the system itself as entities,
properties, and values.
That is the name service
is using itself as a name service.
At this point we know how
to reach the SRC directory
so we can ask it about Lampson.
We already know that the SRC directory
stores information about Lampson
in this form so we need to look up
this name in the SRC directory
and get back its value.
So three names had to be looked up
in order for a user
to obtain the value of Lampson.
This means that in an application
that needs to obtain this value
may incur significant latency.
Because it has to wait for many
look ups to complete.
How can we reduce this latency?
Through caching.
A user of the system that completes
a successful look up can cache the result
for some period of time.
However, there is a
price to pay for caching.
If a user is allowed to cache
a mapping for say an hour,
this means that this mapping
should not change for an hour.
Otherwise the user will end up
with a stale mapping.
To ensure that no user ends up
with a stale mapping
each entry is assigned
an expiration time
and changing it before
that time is forbidden.
So, what the system does is limit
the rate at which the value of a name
can change in order to decrease
the latency experienced
when looking up this name.
So, performance is achieved
through caching.
Each user of the system can cache
their most recent name lookups.
This, however, restricts the rate
at which we can change
the content of the directory.
Each entry is assigned an expiration time
and it is guaranteed not
to change before that time.