We're discussing Butler Lampson's
name service
and the final design goal
for this system
is well-defined behavior.
When two users of the system
are trying to update
the same mapping at about the same time
the final outcome should be well-defined.
Let's see what that means.
First of all, an update always has
the form of a path like this.
Now let's see what happens
when a user submits
this update to the system.
First, the system identifies
in the current directory tree
a prefix of the update.
When I say a prefix I mean
a part of the directory tree
whose labels and time stamps
match exactly a part of the update.
In this particular example,
the entire directory on the left
is a prefix of the update on the right.
Second, the system discards
the part of the update
that matches the prefix
and attaches the rest of the update
to the directory tree.
Suppose a user now submits
this update and I am marking it
with green to differentiate it
from the previous one.
First, as before the system identifies
in the current directory tree
a prefix of the update.
Second, the system examines what
happens right below the identified prefix.
In the directory tree on the left
we have a password label
with time stamp two.
In the update on the right
we also have a password label
but with time stamp three.
The bigger time stamp wins,
so the system detaches
from the directory tree
and throws away the subtree
that starts with a password label.
Finally, the system discards
the part of the update
that matches the prefix and attaches
the rest to the directory tree.
Now suppose we swap the order
of these two updates.
So a user first submits the green update.
First, the system identifies in
the directory tree a prefix of the update.
Second, the system discards
the part of the update
that matches the prefix and attaches
the rest of the directory tree.
Then a user submits the blue update.
First, the system identifies in
the directory tree a prefix of the update.
Second, the system examines what happens
right below the identified prefix.
In the directory tree on the left,
there is a password label
with time stamp three.
In the update on the right there's also
a password label but with time stamp two.
The bigger time stamp wins so the
system simply discards the entire update.
So, the update semantics of the system
are such that whether we first submit
the blue or the green update
the final outcome is the same.
This property of a system
is called "commutativity".
We say that updates are commutative
when the order in which
they are applied does not
effect the final outcome.
Let us look at a couple more
examples of updates.
Suppose a user submits this update.
The system as before identifies
a prefix of the update
and attaches the right part of the update
to the directory tree.
Then a user submits this update.
Again, the system identifies
a prefix of the update
and attaches the right part of
the update to the directory tree.
Now suppose a user resubmits
the last update, the green one.
The system acts exactly as in
the previous examples.
First, it identifies
in the directory tree,
a prefix of the update
but in this case the prefix
comprises the entire update.
Second, the system discards
the part of the update
that matches the prefix,
that is it discards the entire update.
So, the update semantics of the system
are such that no matter
how many times we reapply an update
the final outcome is the same.
This property of a system
is called "idempotency".
We say that updates are idempotent
when reapplying an update
does not effect the final outcome.
So, the behavior of the system
is well-defined in the sense that
updates are commutative and idempotent.
This means that reapplying
or reordering the updates
does not change the final outcome.
Which enables concurrency control.
When multiple users try to update
the same name at about the same time
the user with the higher time stamp wins.
To summarize: we have seen
the design of a name service
that achieves scalability
through hierarchy,
reliability through redundancy,
performance through caching
and well-defined behavior in the form
of commutativity and idempotency.
As we will see in the rest of the course,
these are fundamental design patterns
that underly the operation of
many successful systems.