We will now discuss an
alternative Internet architecture
proposed by David Cheriton in year 2000.
It was meant to improve the performance
of Internet applications,
and at the same time, solve the problem
of IPv4 address depletion.
Interestingly, it would achieve
both of these goals by changing
certain aspects of the naming
used by the TCP/IP stack.
Let's see how that was supposed to work.
So, TRIAD addressed to fundamental
Internet problems by changing
certain aspects of the naming
used by the TCP/IP stack.
It would decrease connection set-up time
by merging the host-name resolution path
to the communication path.
And it would solve the IPv4 address
depletion problem by making
the namespace of IP addresses
local, instead of global.
It is a nice demonstration of how naming
can affect both the performance,
and the scalability of systems.