Welcome to this topic on
data center systems or, more specifically,
on a few selected areas in the area of
data centers and data center systems.
Now, data centers are not new,
they emerged with the first enterprise
mainframes and have
been housing data ever since.
But there was a significant
change of scale about a decade ago
with the emergence of Mega Data Centers,
as pioneered by Google.
The Data Center was no longer a machine
room within an existing building,
but was a building of its own
and with this change of scale
came a change of mindset.
The Data Center was no longer the place
in which you had multiple independent
computer systems, but the Data
Center itself became a system of its own.
So let's try to see what that
actually can mean.
What it can actually, specifically mean
to run a Mega Data Center today.
Now this slide is from a 2012
presentation by James Hamilton,
and Hamilton was a very
well-respected researcher
who is currently responsible
for networking architecture
at Amazon.
So let me read it to you:
Each day Amazon Web Services
adds enough new capacity to support
all of Amazon.com's
global infrastructure through
the company's first five years
when it was a $2.7 billion dollar
annual revenue enterprise.
So - Amazon itself was started in 1994,
so Hamilton is referring to the period
between 1994 and 1999 and
the aggregate compute capacity
deployed during those five years.
And he's comparing it with
the incremental daily capacity
of Amazon today.
So whenever I use this slide in a public
talk, I usually read the quote twice,
to make sure the significance of
the statement actually sinks in.
Hamilton is comparing
five years of aggregate capacity
with what is being deployed
on an incremental daily basis
every single day
at Amazon today.
So, since this is not a live lecture,
but on tape, I'll have you
rewind until the significance
of the statement sinks in.
So how do we explain
such a phenomenal disruption?
Whenever something appears
too large to be true,
it sometimes helps to step back
and try to think about it from
a 'first principles,'
or axiomatic perspective.
Here I selected three axioms,
three 'first principles'
that can explain the trend.
My selection is somewhat
arbitrary, and you'll notice that
they're not principles in the sense of the
Principles of Computer Systems
that we've been studying in class so far.
Instead, one of them is about
semiconductor density
and the other two are
fundamental principles of economics.
So first, Moore's Law, which is about
semiconductor density,
implies that new applications are possible
with every new generation of silicon.
Things that were not possible a few
years ago are now possible
because of Moore's Law - our cell phones,
our tablets, are possible today
because we are operating with
ever-increasing silicon densities.
Now the second law simply says that
innovation is expensive
and that ongoing innovation can only be
justified when there is high volume.
Said differently, it is relatively easy to
justify innovating once
and much harder to justify innovating
on a constant basis,
unless there is a
real high volume application.
The third law states, generically, that
economies of scale can be achieved once
a delivery process is automated and the
product becomes a commodity, or utility.
This is true, for example, when
energy became ubiquitous
as part of the Industrial Revolution.
So we can think about these three
principles as axioms
that are going to be true
in space and in time.
What's interesting here is to study
how these axiom apply
to the Data Center transformation;
and let's first study Moore's law.
Now we've learned to scale horizontally
across more and more cores,
because the cores themselves
are not getting any faster.
Now this has been possible, in part,
because Moore's law also applies to
networking, and we now have ASICs
with high port count
to switch between servers,
so we can put together a larger number
of servers in a machine room
and build effective applications
because these servers can effectively
and efficiently communicate with each other.
Actually in this area, Moore's Law
is sufficiently effective.
The switching logic of
the networking switches
is no longer the bottleneck, and instead,
complications in transmission
and coding are actually limiting
the increase in speed in bandwidth
and Data Centers today.
But Moore's law applies to much more
than simply processing -
it applies to memory,
and memory is now sufficiently dense
that everything that matters,
in effect, is in memory.
Here is an example:
the Facebook social graph,
which is quite large,
is stored in memory.
Not on the memory of a single server,
but in the memory of a data center.
Finally, Moore's Law applies to Solid State,
as well, which are quickly replacing
hard disc drives for durable storage
in theData Center,
as least for all forms of structured data
so you're relational database
is no longer stored on rotating drives,
but instead on much, much more efficient
Solid State drives -
again, because of Moore's Law.
So now let's look at the second axiom -
the notion that volume
drives sustainable innovation.
Now, one thing to keep in mind is that,
even though data centers
are extremely large today,
they remain a niche,
in the sense that there are much fewer
computers in data centers,
that we actually have computers in our
pockets, or carrying with us on our desks.
So, to be effective, modern Data Centers
are pragmatically built
using commodity components
that were designed
with other applications in mind,
and so we're leveraging the volume
of other applications in order to
effectively build data centers.
Let me give an example - X86 chips
were designed for desktops.
This was true and is still true today.
The desktop business at Intel drives
the main innovation in X86 chips
and the server line,
which Intel calls "Xeon,"
basically leverages and fine-tunes
that innovation for server application,
not the other way around.
Desktops is driving innovation in servers.
So if you follow the logic,
why not use cell phone chips
in data centers?
After all, they're much more power-efficient
than desktop chips,
and there's actually precisely
an active line of research
and development along that path.
Now, although this may sound
obvious, keep in mind that this is only
representative of modern
cloud-scale data centers.
Your typical data center
has a very different mix.
Rather than using desktop
or cell phone chips,
enterprise data centers still have a lot
of legacy servers and legacy technologies.
In 2011, the X86 server market
was only 50% of the dollar value
of the total server market.
The other 50% went to legacy technologies,
such as mainframe and RIS computers.
Now, similarly, enterprise data centers
use a combination of
networking technologies,
things like Fibre Channel,
whereas cloud-scale data centers
only use the same Ethernet standard
that is ubiquitous in campus network.
So here is another example
where we are leveraging volume
of technologies deployed
for a broader application,
in order to build a cost-effective
data center.
This actually has
a significant implication,
and that is because the
Law of Sustainable Innovation applies .
Because cloud data centers
are built using commodity parts,
the price performance gap,
with the classic solution
increases every year.
Now let's shift to the third axiom
that can explain the rise
in cloud-scale data centers.
And it is that they're actually
engineered as a system
that can deliver some utility at scale.
So consider the picture on the left,
of the hydroelectric dam.
The picture is actually from
the Grande Dixence in Valais.
One of the largest dam
of its type in the world,
and the pride of Swiss civil engineering,
and it delivers a utility,
which is hydroelectric
electricity at scale.
Now, the picture on the right
is a new Facebook data center,
somewhere in Oregon.
It is also engineered to deliver a
utility, the social network,
at a very large scale.
Similarly, Amazon's data centers
are also designed to deliver a utility,
infrastructure as a service,
or cloud computing,
or virtual machines, at a massive scale.
And put together these
three underlying technologies
and economic principles
have serious implications.
We have Moore's Law,
we have the notion
that volume drives
sustainable innovation.
We have the notion of economies of scale
and delivery.
Now, let's think about what
the implications are this time,
from the perspective of the domain
of computer systems.
And the implication is that
there is a massive
architectural disruption that is going on.
In particular, when comparing
a traditional enterprise infrastructure
with a cloud infrastructure.
So on the left, the enterprise
architectural model
was built around the notion that
individual computer systems
had to be: resilient,
available and serviceable.
In contrast, data center systems
just let the various components fail,
unrepaired, in lights-out data centers.
If a server in a Google
machine room fails,
it is simply going to be left in place,
powered off.
We've build 50 years of transactional
database systems based around
the notion of ACID transactions,
and the notion that
important data was on disc.
In the cloud, important data
is in memory and this data
is often replicated on
a weekly consistent basis.
The enterprise infrastructure model
has a lot of legacy technologies
that were designed at the time
when data was on disc.
The cloud is shifting toward a model
where everything is in memory.
Finally, the classic model consists of
individually provisioned components
that act as independent systems with,
typically, three completely
indistinct operational teams responsible
for their management.
The application team, which manages
the individual servers;
the networking team,
which manages the network;
and the storage team,
which actually manages the data
separately from the applications.
Now in the cloud,
there is no such concept,
since everything is automated.
In other words, the configuration
of the data center itself
is entirely done in software.
Now in the next modules, we will discuss
the implication of this disruption
and we'll specifically talk about some of the
design principles associated
with building these cloud-scale applications.
But to summarize this module
on infrastructure,
there's a lot of hype about a cloud
but below the cloud,
realize that there is a new data center.
And that new data center
is built on a certain set of principles.
It is designed to operate at scale
and it is designed to operate as
a system, and to deliver
a utility at a massive scale.
If you're interested in going further
into those topics,
I can recommend to you two books.
One by Barrozo and Hötzle,
two of the leading engineers at Google,
who've written a book on warehouse-scale
data center systems
that summarizes their experience at Google.
And the second book by Nicholas Carr,
called "The Big Switch,"
which makes the analogy between the
emergence of the mega data centers
and the emergence of
the electricity grid, about a century ago.