In this module, we're going
to go back about a decade
and study the architecture of the first
generation internet-scale services.
Now, these services are tiny
by today's standards,
but they were quite large at the time.
They were even described
as "giant-scale services".
And these were services that were designed
around the year 2000,
just as the first internet bubble
was bursting.
And they had a killer application
and that killer application
was "search".
So, today we associate search
with Google or Bing,
but at the time,
the leading search applications
were Altavista and Inktomi.
And Altavista was designed
by engineers at DEC,
who had access to,
what was at the time,
one of the largest 64-bit
machines available,
the ALPHA TurboLaser.
And they realized that they could
actually fit the web in memory.
And so Altavista,
which was the leading search engine
before the turn of the century,
could actually hold the entire index
of the web in memory
and serve the entire web,
or search application
to all the web's client
from the memory of that one machine.
Now unfortunetly this did not scale.
Around the same time Dave Patterson
and Eric Brewer at Berkeley
started the Berkeley NOW project:
Network of Workstations,
studying how you can actually
put a lot of cheap computers together
to build equivalent applications.
Out of the NOW project came Inktomi.
Inktomi was a commercial search service,
which was competitive with Altavista.
Today both of them are dead,
but in 2001 Eric Brewer wrote some
of the experiences
associated with the deployment of Inktomi
in a paper
called "Lessons from Giant Scale Services"
and this is actually what we
will be covering in this module.
So, this is what the basic model
looks like.
Now, although some of the elements
seem obvious today,
this was not obvious
at the time.
Now, the first comment about this figure
is the notion of a single-site server.
A collection of servers
actually serves a single function
and appears as a single server.
And the load manager in front of it
effectively hides the internal details
of that single-site server
from the outside world,
allowing for horizontal
scale out.
Now, the second comment about this figure
is that scale out applies
equally to servers
and to storage.
This means the elimination
of any notion of centralized storage.
This also a departure
from the Standard Enterprise model.
Now, let's study load balancing
in further detail.
Now, the purpose of the load manager
is to hide the internals
of the single-site server.
And this is realized by combining
different mechanisms.
The first mechanism leverages the level
of indirection in DNS
by returning different IP addresses
for the same DNS name,
based on the context of the request
or the load
or the availability
of the independent servers.
Now, this is, however, only a very
coarse-grain mechanism,
because of DNS caching,
so DNS load balancing is typically used
to identify another middle box,
another layer that hides the end servers,
which is called a layer 4 or 7
load balancer.
Now, layer 4 and layer 7 load balancers
are actually quite different
in how they are architected
and constructed.
A layer 4 load balancer maps TCP flows
onto different end servers,
could either terminate the connection,
or simply perform
network address translation.
A more sophisticated layer 7 load balancer
actually terminates the HTTP requests,
identifies the session cookie
of that HTTP request,
and uses that cookie
to determine the end server.
With that, you can actually guarantee
that different HTTP connections
correspond to the same session,
will be handled by the same end server,
which helps in the design
of some of the applications.
It's actually interesting to study
the evolution of the basic model
of 2001 with the solutions
that we see today.
My first observation is many
of the components are still relevant,
if anything, they're as relevant as ever.
Load managers, for example,
play a central role
in offloading the traffic
from the mega data centers today,
by caching some of the critical data
in edge locations.
Beyond that, there have been some changes
in the model.
Significant changes in the assumption
that an application
will be located in a single site,
that has been, in a pretty fundamental way
today replaced by the notion
that any large application is spread out
across multiple locations.
This has actually
significant implications,
in particular, around the notion
of the CAP theorem,
which we will study
in the next module.
But beyond that, there have been
other, subtle changes.
For example,
although we still have internal storage,
the notion that we would actually use RAID
as the building block
to ensure the durability of the data,
has been replaced
by the notion that we would partition
and replicate data three ways,
within a site,
across multiple machines.
And that's simply a result or consequence
of the increase in capacity in disk drives
and the increase MTTRs associate
with the repair of a disk drive
in a RAID group.
You can actually get much faster behavior
by replicating the data
across all of the machines of the cluster,
rather than within a single computer.
And finally,
in the original diagram,
we had a concept
of an optional blackplane,
which was used as a high-bandwidth
exchange mechanism between computers.
For example, as a storage fabric
or a compute fabric.
The idea was to provide scalable
bi-section bandwidth
to allow servers to communicate
with each other efficiently.
Now, the requirement has not changed,
and it's actually more present than ever.
However, the implementation has evolved
into IP based fabrics,
which can be efficiently realized
using commodity components and factories
And what you see on screen
is the new Tor spine architecture,
that is the standard
in today's mega data centers.
Now, to be fair, none of these changes
invalidate the original model,
if anything they are
incremental evolutions
that were necessary
to keep these servers scaling
with technology trends
and in a cost-effective way.
Now, giant-scale services introduce
actually a new form of metrics.
If you remember our module
on redundancy in fault tolerance,
we introduced a fundamental availability
and downtime metric.
The fact that downtime lowers the ratio
of the MTTR
over the sum of the MTTR and the MTTF.
And that metric makes a lot of sense
if you think about a single server
that is serving a particular application,
but it makes a lot less sense
if you have hundreds of servers
that are independently operating
in a co-operative fashion
in order to provide an answer
to an internet-scale service.
And those new metrics were actually
introduced by Eric Brewer
as yield and harvest.
So first, the yield is the ratio
between the number of queries completed
and the number of queries offered.
And note that the yield metric is not just
a metric of fault tolerance,
in that it is not only impacted
by failure.
Instead, the yield is a metric
that characterizes whether a site
is overloaded or not in its given state.
And the nice thing about that metric
is that it's an end to end metric,
which cloud providers can
and actually do measure.
Now, the second metric
is called the harvest.
And it is a different metric
that makes the observation
that not all data is necessarily available
by the cloud service
at any given point in time.
And it's based on the insight
that many queries can actually return
with a partial dataset.
Take, for example, search.
It's okay to return search results
that only considered
95 percent of the dataset.
And it's actually preferable to return
a good enough answer quickly,
than to delay a response
or have to tell the user
that the site is, overall, not available.
And so the harvest metric measures
what fraction of the complete data
that should be considered,
was actually considered, on average,
for each query.
Now, very much
like the fault tolerance model
led to a specific design process,
the harvest and yield metrics
lead to their own design process
and have design implications.
For example, many web services today
define yield
with a latency bound in mind.
A hundred milliseconds, or one second,
for example, for search.
Now this in turn has an impact
on the harvest,
since the dataset may not be processed
in time.
A great example, where harvest and yield
are taken into consideration
is the design and implementation
of an ad serving service.
Of course, you want to serve ads,
and of course you want
to serve them quickly,
and so you want to maximize your yield
under some SLA constraint.
You also want to personalize the ad,
but it's okay to only personlize it
to the extent that you don't violate
the SLA.
Which means that the harvest metric
may be compromized to maintain the yield.
So, this is a great example
of how both harvest and yield
can help with the design
of a cloud service
that we can effectively
get more effective ads.
Or it's a terrible one,
depending on your point of view.
Now the concept of harvest and yields
are actually linked,
because of a related principle,
called the DQ "Principle".
Now, I'm going to put "principle"
here in quotes,
because this is not really
a principle at all,
but more an observation that has led
to a useful generalization.
And the intuition is that every system
has a bottleneck.
And it's typically the network link
for frontend servers,
and it's typically the disk
for backend servers.
If every system, or every component
in the datacenter system has a bottleneck,
the implication is that the capacity
of each system
is actually very stable
for any given service.
And that it is the product
of the amount of data
consumed by each query
with the query rate.
So the DQ "Principle" states that D,
which is the amount of data per query
times Q which is the query rate,
is a constant.
So, think about the DQ value as a metric
for the capacity of a site.
If you add servers,
you increase your DQ capacity.
If you lose servers, you correspondingly
decrease DQ capacity.
If you have to take servers offline,
for any reason,
your DQ capacity also goes down.
Of course, the DQ value can have
a direct impact on either the harvest
or the yield of the service.
And here are some examples.
If you lose one server out of n,
the load would have to be redirected
to n - 1 servers.
And this can potentially overload
the remaining servers
by the ratio of n over n - 1.
Same observation holds
if you lose k servers.
And at some point the load
will exceed the DQ capacity
that is remaining
and this will in turn reduce your yield.
Now the similar argument could also hold
if you assume that the data is
spread out across the servers
and the data is not replicated.
Your harvest is then reduced
proportionally
based on the number of available servers.
Now, this might sound trivial,
and in some ways it is somewhat
obvious in retrospect,
the main value of the DQ principle
and the harvest and yield metrics,
is that they allow you to reason
about the implication
of certain operations.
Consider here, the case
where a site needs to be upgraded
and all the servers need to be rebooted.
Now, the picture shows
three different scenarios.
The first one is a fast reboot.
Now, during the reboot,
no queries can be served.
Of course, this impacts your yield.
The second scenario
is the rolling upgrade,
where servers are upgraded
one at a time.
Now, during a rolling upgrade,
a fraction of the data is unavailable,
unless you're replicating it,
and this would obviously
impact your harvest.
And the final model is what Eric Brewer
called the "Big Flip".
The idea here is to steer
all the new traffic
through one half of the nodes,
and then upgrade the nodes
while they are not serving traffic.
Your DQ value goes down by 50 percent
during the entire operation,
but if you replicate the entire dataset
on the half of the remaining servers,
it will not impact your harvest.
And as long as your DQ capacity
remains sufficiently large,
it will also not impact your yield.
Now, of course, this is the best case,
if you're not replicating the data,
your harvest will go down
by up to 50 percent.
And if you're overloading it,
your yield will go down
by up to 50 percent,
if you're actually overloaded,
and the Big Flip is the technique
they used actually
to upgrade the servers,
and in one case to move from
one location to another location
as they were operating the Inktomi
search service in production.
Time to wrap up this module
on internet scale services.
We saw the basic model of 2001.
Since then, if anything,
things have gotten larger
but also simpler, internally.
We also saw some new metrics,
the concept of yield, harvest
and the DQ "Principle",
as more applicable
to internet-scale services
than the classic metrics
of fault tolerance.
What we have not talked about
is any notion of consistency
of the data that is being served.
That's the topic of the next module
on the CAP theorem.