You can't have a week on
data centers without
a dedicated module on the CAP theorem.
But because you'll be reading about
the CAP theorem this week
I'm going to focus on
the history of the CAP theorem,
which is actually quite interesting.
It's interesting because it was
not introduced in the paper,
it was actually not
introduced as a theorem,
it was rather postulated by Eric Brewer
in his keynote at PODC in the year 2000.
And Eric first made the comparison
between ACID and BASE.
ACID are the traditional properties
associated with database transactions.
And BASE is the alternative
set of properties that
we associate with Internet scale services.
And BASE stands for basically available,
soft state, eventually consistent systems.
Basic availability means that the state,
the site should always be up
so the yield should be greater
than zero at all times.
Soft state means that the website operates
on some soft state that can be
reconstructed by some hard state
that may be stored elsewhere,
maybe using the transactional system.
A shopping cart is a great example
of soft state at any commerce website.
And eventual consistency means that
different clients may see
slightly different versions of the data
at any point in time.
For example, you may have
a slightly different view
of the number of seats that
may be available for a concert
as you are shopping through it
on an Internet website.
And the difference between
an ACID and BASE is helpful
to understand the context
of the CAP theorem.
Now as I mentioned, Brewer did not prove
the CAP theorem he simply postulated,
he had an intuition that this was true.
This was actually later formally proved
by two computer scientists
Gilbert and Lynch a few years later.
(Edouard) So what do we mean
by the CAP theorem?
Well it looks like the relationship
between three properties
of a shared data system.
"C" stands for consistency,
the properties equivalent
to having a single up to date
copy of the data.
"A" stands for availability
and specifically the ability
for updates to complete.
"P" stands for partition tolerance.
The ability to operate in the
presence of network partitions.
And so the CAP theorem
is that you have to chose.
You get two out of three,
but not all three.
And let's see what that means.
So maybe you don't care about
partition tolerance or otherwise
assume that you can engineer your solution
to avoid them in practice.
Now if that's the case, you can ensure
both consistency and availability
of a shared data system.
As a matter of fact, classic databases
use this as a design pattern.
For example, two phase commit allows
two distribute databases
to show a consistent view of data.
Unfortunately, two phase commit
cannot successfully commit a transaction
that involves multiple sites
in the presence of a network partition.
It would just hang.
Now if you assume that network partitions
can occur one design consequence
would be to give up on availability.
Majority protocols, for example,
are designed to operate
as long as a majority or quorum
can achieve consensus.
Of course in that case
the minority partition
can no longer make updates.
But if you think about it this
design point makes a lot of sense
in particular if the partitioning is due
to the lack of availability
of the entire minority site.
In that case the network partition
is actually a symptom
and the issue of the availability of data
in the minority site is actually
a non-issue because
the site itself is not present.
Now the problem with that design pattern
is actually its implementation cost.
Consistency is expensive.
Consistency across site is particularly
expensive because of the latency
that is involved in the protocols.
Now when consistency is expensive
and network partitions can occur,
the alternative design point is
to actually give up on consistency
altogether and design a system
that actually is always available.
And there are many examples of systems
that show those traits.
DNS systems, Web caching
are still relevant today.
In his talk, Brewer used Coda
as an example.
Coda was a distributed file system
that supported
offline operations and reconciliation.
If Eric were to give the same talk today
he would probably list Dropbox
rather than Coda
as an example of a system
that gives up consistency
for availability.
So this was the history
and the textbook level
explanation of the CAP theorem.
There are actually lots of nuances
in this topic and I encourage you
to read Eric's paper on his retrospective
on the CAP theorem.