Now when you think about
the web you typically
think about very high throughput,
millions of concurrent transactions
and search queries being processed
by thousands of computers.
And you intuitively can think about
throughput as being the leading metric.
And indeed the DQ constant that
we saw in the previous module
is a throughput metric. It basically
states that you can either have
more queries per second or larger queries
but that the product of the two
is a constant and is a function
of your infrastructure.
Now in reality latency
matters a great deal.
And we'll actually see why it matters
a great deal and why
achieving low latency is hard.
And particularly one key point
is that increasing the DQ constant
of a site will not necessarily translate
into a low latency for the queries
that are being served.
Now there are a number
of reasons for this,
And the first reason is that the
architecture of giant scale services
has actually evolved noticeably
since the basic model
was proposed over a decade ago.
What we see are two pictures;
on the left is the basic model
as proposed in 2001 and on the right
is an illustration of
a more realistic deployment,
at least as of 2009.
Now in the simple model on the left,
the load manager directs the load
among the various servers
which processes them.
Now assuming the DQ principle,
the latency of a rubber crest
would therefore increase
as the selected server reaches
some level of saturation
but if the servers are not overloaded
then the latency can
remain relatively low.
Now the reality is much more complex
and the picture on the right illustrates
that each webpage is actually
the result of multiple distribution
and aggregation steps among
multiple tiers of the data center.
At each layer there is a fan-out
to multiple servers of the lower layer,
followed by an aggregation of the results
into a single answer which is then
propagated back to the layer above.
Of course each server serves
multiple machines from the tier above,
so there's a fan-in request,
which can create contention.
This has a severe implication
which is known as the tail latency effect.
Now the notion of tail latency simply
states that the latency of a service
is determined by the
slowest fan-out component,
and Jeff Dean and Louis Barroso
who happened to be two of the most
senior scientists at Google
illustrated this in a recent CACM paper.
And their graph is a synthetic
analytical model.
Assume that you have a fan-out
involving N servers,
and that the response will be
a high latency with some probability.
On the X-axis is the number of servers,
and the three curves corresponds
to the scenario where
one in a 100, one in 1000,
or one in 10,000 requests are slow,
and the Y-axis is the probability
that any aggregate request would be slow.
In other words, that at least one of
the N requesting servers responds slowly.
So let's first consider the case
where N servers are involved
and one over N is the probability
of a slow response,
while the resulting probability
of a slow service is 63%,
and that occurs with 100 servers
at a probability of 100;
that's the blue line,
and 1000 servers,
the probability of 1000.
Now the green curve shows
the situation where the service
is really well implemented
and the probability of
a service response is extremely small.
It's one in 10,000.
Unfortunately what we see is that this
still has a significant overall impact
if the service depends on a relatively
small number of servers.
Now this is bad.
It's bad if the service is
the customer facing web request
because a fraction of the
web transaction would be slow.
But it's actually a lot worse
and totally unacceptable
if this is a middle layer service
since the upper tier
would then behave like the blue curve.
So if we have something
that is engineered
like the green curve at the layer below
but depends on a large number of servers,
we effectively have the behavior
and effect of the blue curve
at the layer above.
Now the importance of tail latency
has been known for awhile.
And one of the first major systems
that formalize and focused on this
was Dynamo which was published at SOSP.
The observation that human patience
is limited and that it ebbs
on customers tend to be very impatient
when making purchases,
and so a slow site means less revenue.
So the engineers
that designed Dynamo
and the core of the Amazon site
shifted their focus from
measuring throughput in yield
to measuring 99.9 latency
of the service request time.
Now the figure on the right,
which is taken from the paper,
measures both the average
and the 99.9 latency
of the distribution of
the Dynamo storage service.
Note that the graph
is on a log scale,
we see that their system
delivers a response
in the ten to 30 millisecond on average,
and those are the two curves below.
But it can take over 100 milliseconds
at the 99.9 percentile
which happens for
one in every 1000 queries.
So it turns out that achieving
low latency at the 99.9 percentile
is hard for a number of reasons.
We've already talked
about the long tail,
which occurs when
we have a lot of fan-out.
And we'll also talk about incasting.
But first let's close back on
this long tail question.
The figure on the right shows
that there is one order of magnitude
difference between the average latency
and the 99.9 percentile.
By definition one in 1000 requests
are above the 99.9 percentile latency.
And keep in mind that
Dynamo is a key value store
in that the upper layer applications
typically fan-out multiple requests
to a key value storage to build a webpage.
So we use a simple
model on the left
of the long tail to reason about
the impact of end user latency.
With one in 1000 off by
one order of magnitude
we can approximate the overall performance
by looking at the red line of the graph.
Now if the long tail problem
was not enough,
there is another very pesky issue
that could impact
the latency of a high fan-out application.
And that issue is known as
the TCP incast problem
and the corresponding throughput collapse
that can occur.
On the picture on this figure,
imagine that the upper layer server
is on the right and issues
a fan-out request
to a number of servers on the left.
Each of the fan-out servers
must then reply the response
back to the requester,
and if all senders attempt
to communicate at the same time
congestion will occur in the network
between and specifically on the link
between the senders and the receiver.
There is a bottleneck.
That bottleneck leads to what is known as
the TCP incast problem.
Now since there's a shared link,
there can and will be
congestion on the link,
but as we know
networking systems are designed
to handle congestion.
Switches have buffers that can
absorb instantaneous congestion
and TCP manages congestion
by reacting to dropped packets
and reducing the size of
the sliding window accordingly.
Now unfortunately this is precisely
what happens when TCP incasting
is measured and observed as shown
on the picture on the right.
As the number of senders increase,
the amount of useful traffic received
by the receiver actually goes down
to a tiny fraction of the link capacity.
So this is what we mean by
throughput collapse.
We're not talking about
percentages of capacity that is lost,
we're talking about orders of magnitude
of capacity that can be lost
as a result of this incasting problem.
So obviously a very bad thing
and actually one that
is reminiscent of congestion collapse
that was observed in the 1980s
on the Internet and led to some of
the adaptive algorithms
that have been critical additions to TCP.
So today the study of TCP incasting
in data centers is
an area of active
research and development,
and something to keep in mind
when thinking about
the scale-ability of high
fan-out applications.
Now let's see if we can
put this together.
This week you'll be reading a paper
on Thialfi which is
Google's massively scale-able
notification service.
A very nice paper based on
strong principles that describe
a system that is designed to serve
notifications to millions of online users.
So obviously scale-ability is a first
order of consideration of the design.
You'll actually note from
the figure on the right
that the paper evaluates
the latency of the service
as a function of
the number of online users,
and their evaluation shows
that the medium latency
for such a service to be 600 milliseconds.
Those are the blue squares.
So they're pretty much a constant
as the number of clients scale.
This is actually a
very impressive result at a massive scale.
So keep that in mind
when you're reading the paper,
this did not happen by accident,
but achieving a predictable
low latency for massively scale-able
service was only possible because
it was a first order consideration
from the beginning of the design process.
Time to wrap up this module on latency
for Internet scale systems.
Latency is important.
It's important to measure-
not just to measure the average
or the mean, but actually
to measure the distribution
captured in the 99.9 percentile
and in general capture
any jitter associated with
the latency of individual requests.
There's been a relentless pursuit
to measure latency,
there's also a relentless pursuit
to engineer systems that add scale,
and can deliver predictable low latency
and low latency jitter applications
for all of the various tiers of
the data center systems
that we have today.
We saw that there are
a number of really hard issues:
the notion of the long tail
and the tail out scale problem
makes it very difficult
to have a multilayer system
that operates with
predictable low latency.
We saw that there are not just
issues around application design,
there's also issues associated
with the network layer
in the context of the
TCP incasting problem.