In urban areas, faecal sludge
often looks like this.
It is extremely liquid and contains
few solids.
Often, more than 95%
of faecal sludge is water.
Dewatering of this sludge usually
requires a lot of space
that is commonly not available
in urban areas.
In this module we introduce you
to settling-thickening tanks
that can reduce the volume that
requires dewatering by more than 50%.
No, it's not by magic.
It is by gravity.
Following this module, you will
be able to explain
the treatment process and operation
of settling-thickening tanks.
Discuss operation and maintenance
requirements,
and name design parameters specific
to settling-thickening tanks.
This slide shows a cross-section of
a settling-thickening tank.
The treatment of settling-thickening
tank is based on sedimentation.
Faecal sludge enters the tank through
inlet at the front.
As an outlet for the sludge is only
provided at the back end,
the sludge has to travel
through the tank.
During its way through the tank
dense solids settle out at the bottom.
These solids are further compressed
by the weight
of the settled sludge layer,
as a result of these two processes
called settling and thickening,
the sludge that settle
at the bottom of the tank has
a higher solid content,
and the effluent leaving the tank,
a lower solid content
than the thicker sludge discharged
into the settling-thickening tank.
So all settling-thickening tanks
really do
is to separate liquids
and solids.
Usually between 50 to 80%  of
suspended solids that are discharged
into the settling-thickening tank
stay in the tank,
where as the remaining solids
stay in the effluent.
This means that both liquids
effluent and the solids
require further treatment.
So what is the benefit of
a settling-thickening tank?
Let's consider a hypothetical
example.
This slide shows the change
of sludge volume
as a function of the solids content.
As you can see from the slope of
the curve
the reduction sludge volume
is highest at low solid contents.
Let's assume we have 1000 liters
of sludge with a solid content of 1%
which is typical for septic
tank sludge.
How will this volume change when
we increase
the solid content from 1%
to 5%
of when we increase it from
1% to 10%?
These are typical solids contents
from settling-thickening tanks
in Accra and Dakar.
Increased solid content would reduce
the sludge volume to 200 liters
for 5% solids and 100 liters
for 10% solids.
This is a reduction of the initial
volume of 80 and 90%.
As the required space for dewatering
technologies, such as drying beds
uses the function of the volume
of sludge that needs to be dewatered
settling-thickening tanks can reduce
the required footprint
of sludge dewatering technologies.
Settling-thickening tanks are
usually loaded with sludge
for between 1 week to 1 month.
To treat the solid content
in a settled sludge
the sludge can be left for
thickening beyond this period.
This is usually done for several
days or weeks,
as shown here for anaerobic ponds
another type of settling-thickening
technology in Dakar.
Following this period, the sludge
that accumulates at the bottom
requires removal before
another cycle
of loading and thickening
can be started.
This sludge removal should be done
by pumps
to ensure protection of workers.
(INAUDIBLE), trekkers, or front-loaders
or a combination of those
may be applied when sludge
is too thick to be pumped.
This slide here shows a back hose
in the background removing sludge
from an anaerobic pond
in Dar es Salaam.
As you can see in this picture,
removal of sludge
from settling-thickening tanks
can be a challenge.
But is an absolute must to ensure
that they operate as designed.
This will be covered in more detail
in another module
with an example of
a settling-thickening tank.
Maintenance of pumps and tractors,
as shown in Kampala,
is the most important maintenance
activity for settling-thickening tanks.
In order to ensure that faecal sludge
can be treated
during thickening, sludge removal
and also maintenance activities,
2 settling-thickening tanks are
usually operate
in parallel or alternately.
In this picture from Dakar,
1 settling-thickening tank
is being loaded, while the other one
is left for settling and thickening.
What you also notice on this picture
is that this settling-thickening
tank is covered with a layer.
We call this layer the scum layer.
This layer also requires removal
and management
after settling-thickening period
of a settling-thickening tank.
The settling velocity and the solid
liquid separation effeciency
are design parameters that are
specific to settling-thickening tanks.
The settling velocity is an estimate
of the speed with which
solids settle to the bottom
of a settling-thickening tank.
If the speed with which the solids
travel through
the settling-thickening tank
is faster than the settling velocity
the sludge will leave the tank
with the effluent.
For example, with this pathway here.
If the settling velocity is faster
than the velocity with which
the solids travel through the tank,
the solids will settle out at the bottom.
Based on experience from Accra,
Kampala, and Dakar,
the settling will also equal
a smaller than 0.5 meters/second
seems to be appropriate for faecal
sludge in settling-thickening tanks.
But in contrast to waste water
sludge treatment
experience is lacking on
the appropriate design values
for settling velocity
of faecal sludge.
Due to the wide range of faecal
sludge characteristics,
from different on-site
sanitation technologies or cities.
In general, unstabilized faecal
sludge
for example, from public toilets
as shown here
appear to have poorer solid liquid
separation in settling-thickening
tanks, for example as compared
to septic tank sludge.
Due to this high variability
in characteristics,
the design of settling-thickening
tanks requires bench skill testing
with Imhoff cones,
when the actual sludge
that would be treated in
the settling-thickening tanks.
This slide shows 4 Imhoff
cones.
To estimate the sludge volume index,
1 liter of sludge
is settled in these Imhoff
cones for around 30 to 60 minutes.
The sludge volume index is then
calculated from the volume
that settles at the bottom of these
Imhoff cones
divided by the initial suspended
solids concentration.
Based on waste water sludge
treatment,
a sludge with a sludge volume index
of equal or smaller than
100 milliliters per gram TS,
good solid liquid separation
in settling-thickening tank
can be expected.
During such laboatory bench
skill test,
the solid liquid separation
efficiency can also be calculated.
It is an estimate of how many solids
settle at the bottom
and would stay in the tank,
and how much of the solids
would leave the tank with
the effluent.
A solid liquid separation effeciency
of smaller than 80%
could indicate that the sludge
in your city
has poor solid liquid separation
in settling-thickening tanks.
In addition, the solid liquid
separation effeciency
is important for the design
of settling-thickening tanks
and effluent treatment.
This picture shows the effluent of
a settling-thickening tank
in Dar es Salaam.
This effluent is further treated
in waste stabilization ponds.
It is important to consider that the
solid liquid separation efficiency
that you will have in full-scale
settling-thickening tanks
will be lower than
the ones you've obtained
in controlled laboratory
or bench skill testing.
A discharge area for sludge, as
shown here before
a settling-thickening tank,
can be a good way
for mitigating this turbulence.
In addition, (INAUDIBLE) at the inflow
and at the outflow
of settling-thickening tanks
can be a good way of reducing
turbulences and ensure that you have
good solid liquid separation
efficiencies in settling-thickening
tanks.
In this module we learned that
the treatment process
on operation OF
settling-thickening tanks
is based on sedimentation.
Frequent removal of sludge
is important
for settling-thickenings is only
operator designed.
This requires maintenance
of mechanical equipment,
such as pumps and front-loaders.
Design parameters specific
to settling-thickening tanks
are related to
the sludge properties.
And include the settling velocity,
and solid liquid separation efficiency.