Even after settling-thickening
technologies,
faecal sludge is typically
mostly water.
So how can you convert it into
a solid product like as shown here?
It could be used, for example, as
a soil conditioner or a solid fuel.
In this module we will cover how
to achieve this
with unplanted drying beds.
Following this module, you will
be able to explain
the treatment process and operation
of unplanted drying beds.
You will be able to discuss operation
and maintenance requirements
and name design parameters that are
specific to unplanted drying beds.
Welcome to the Niayes Waste Water
and Faecal Sludge Treatment Plant in Dakar.
Here, faecal sludge and waste water
sludge are dewatered
and dried separately on unplanted
drying beds.
You can see sludge on the surface
of the drying bed.
But the heart of a drying bed really
lies below the surface
in the filter media.
Let's have a closer look.
This slide shows a cross-section
of an unplanted drying bed.
The filter media in a drying bed
typically consists
of different layers of gravel
and sand in decreasing diameter.
The bottom layer is typically made
of different layers of gravel
as shown here as a layer
of coarse gravel
and a layer of fine gravel.
Based on designs from Kampala,
Dakar and Accra
the coarse gravel layer typically
has a depth of 15 to 20 centimeters
and the fine gravel
of 10 centimeters.
The size of the gravel is commonly
10 to 40 millimeters
for the coarse gravel
and 5 to 40 millimeters
for the fine gravel.
Below the bottom layer there  is
a perforated pipe
for the collection of the effluent.
This picture shows
the perforated pipe
and the coarse gravel layer
during filling in
at our pilot-scale research facility
in Dar es Salaam.
The top layer of the filter media
is typically sand
with a depth
of 10 to 20 centimeters.
Sludge is loaded on the surface
of the central layer
for solid-liquid separation.
This picture shows the surface of an
unplanted drying bed
next to a drying bed that has been
loaded with faecal sludge.
The treatment process on drying beds
can be separated into two stages.
Dewatering and drying.
During dewatering, liquids
and solids are separated by filtration.
The free water and sludge percolates
through the sand
and the gravel filter layers,
and is collected at the bottom
with a drainage pipe
for further treatment.
The sludge accumulates on top
of the sand filter layer.
Following dewatering during drying,
liquids and solids
are further separated
by evaporation.
Dewatering usually takes several
hours to days.
Where as the duration of drying
is usually longer
and takes several weeks to months.
Similar to settling-thickening tanks,
drying beds are designed for
solid-liquid separation, and not
sludge stabilization,
nutrient management or pathogen
inactivation.
From a mass balance perspective,
solids, organics, nutrients,
pathogens, for the most part
either stay in the liquids and leave
with the drainage pipe or the solids
on the top of the sand filter layer.
For example, typically 95%
of the solids remain on the surface
of the sand filter layer
as shown here in Kampala,
where as the remaining solids
stay in the liquid effluent.
These effluents also called (INAUDIBLE)
or (INAUDIBLE).
Depending on intended use, for
example in agriculture
both liquids and solids usually
require further treatment.
Solid-liquid separation on drying
beds is a batch process.
This means that beds are loaded
once with sludge
and once the desired silicone
has been obtained,
for example for use in agriculture
or for co-composting,
the sludge has to be removed from
the surface of the sand filter layer.
This can either be done manually
with shovels and wheelbarrows
or mechanically with front-loaders.
During unloading of sludge,
care should be taken
to not remove (INAUDIBLE)
with the sludge.
This increase the frequency
of the replacement
of the sand filter layer, and also
reduce the volume
of the sludge for resource recovery,
for example,  as a solid fuel.
Drying beds have relatively low
maintenance requirements.
But they are equally important
to ensure that
they operate as designed.
During each drying cycle, some sand
sticks to the faecal sludge
and is removed with it.
This means that the sand filter
layer needs to be replaced  regularly
as shown here at our facility
in Dar es Salaam.
A replacement of the sand filter
layer may also be required
when solids clog the filter layer.
The design and operation
of drying bed is typically based
on the hydraulic
and solid loading rate.
Hydraulic loading rate is the height
of sludge
that is loading on a drying bed
in one cycle.
It is usually between 25 and 30 cm.
The solid loading rate is the amount
of solids that can be loaded
on one square meter of drying bed
per year without risking clogging.
It is usually between 50 and 300 kg
total solids square meter a year.
In tropical countries
100 to 200 kg total solids
per square meter a year
are appropriate.
We'll use these design parameters
in another module
for the design of unplanted
drying beds.
So what is the dewatering time with
unplanted drying bed in your city?
Here are some important
considerations to determine
these times for your city
which are important
for the design of unplanted
drying beds.
It is important to consider
the dewatering properties
of faecal sludge in your city
as they can be very variable.
In our research,
we saw significant difference
in the dewatering properties
of sludge from pit latrines
in comparison to sludge
from septic tanks.
In addition to these sludge
properties, the local climate
also has an influence
on the actual drying time.
A high ambient temperature,
low relative humidity
so a dry climate,
are optimal for drying.
In climates with frequent rainfall,
dewatering
and drying times can be prolonged.
In these climates
with frequent rainfall
a cover over the drying beds
should be considered
as here shown in Lusaka, to ensure
year round operation.
Research from Ghana identified that
the dewatering time on a drying bed
will also depend on
the sand's diameter.
A coarser sand, say for example,
with a diameter of 1 to 1.5 millimeters
means faster filtration,
but an increased risk of clogging
to the accumulation of solids
in the sand filter layer.
In contrast, a finer sand,
for example 0.1 to 0.5 millimeters
means slower filtration, but also
less risk of clogging.
This diameter is often preferred
over coarse sand.
And ultimately, the drying time
will also depend
on the desired dryness
you want to achieve.
If you would like to use as fuel
90% dryness is usually required
whereas a much lower dryness
is required if you want
to do (INAUDIBLE)
or co-composting
or you want to produce the feedstuff
for fly larvae composting.
All these factors and different
drying by designs,
operations and conditions, explain
the large variability
in dewatering and drying times
reported in literature.
Literature values can provide
general references.
However, characterization of
the specific faecal sludge
and band skill testing
are always required
for the design of large-scale urban
treatment plants.
Based on operating experience
from unplanted drying beds
in various countries, some defined
element are specially important
to consider for reliable
and long-term operation.
Here they are.
As you can see here
Pumps transferring sludge
often have a high pressure.
This could disrupt
the sand filter layer.
This can be mitigated by flash point
or separate inflow chambers.
Next to the particle size
of the sand filter layer
the uniformity of particles
is important.
Fine particles need to be washed out
before they are used.
You can see this process
at our pilot -scale
research facility in Dar es Salaam.
Over here there were still a lot
of fine particles
which would then continuously
remove by washing.
This is important to prevent
clogging of the sand filter layer. .
It is worth to invest in
the development of a local supply
for the sand filter layer,
considering that it has
to be replaced regularly.
The design also has to ensure
the side walls are high enough
and correspond to the hydraulic
loading rate
used in design plus a freeboard.
In addition, a ramp can be helpful
when removing
the sludge from the drying beds.
Unplanted drying beds
require a lot of space.
For example, in comparison
to mechanically watering equipment
such as screw press
or filter press.
Modification of drying beds
have the potential
to reduce the treatment times,
and so also
reduce the treatment footprint
that is required.
This for example, includes turning
of the sludge
from the surface of the drying beds.
During our research in Dakar,
we could reduce
with these drying times by 20%.
In this module, we learned that
the treatment process
of unplanted drying beds is based
on filtration and evaporation.
Unplanted drying beds are operated
in batch mode and require
removal of sludge from
the surface of the drying beds.
In addition, the replacement
with sand filter layer
is required for reliable operation.
Drying beds need to be designed
based on the local climate
and sludge characteristics.
The most important
design parameters include
the hydraulic and the solid
loading rate.