This faecal includes the effluent
from the settling sickening tank.
Do you think that this effluent
is safe for discharging to water body?
Or for use
for irrigation agriculture?
What if I tell you
this is higher concentrates
of organics and nutrients,
and waste water.
And that the salt concentrates
could be harmful to plants.
In this module introduce you
to treatment technologies to treat
such an effluent.
Following this module, you'll be able
to name potential difference
between effluents
from treatment technologies
and compared to waste water.
You will also be able to name potential
effluent treatment technologies
and discuss potential challenges
with effluent treatment.
Because of high concentration
faecal sludge of solids and organics,
solid liquid separation technologies
are often the first treatment technology
at a treatment plant.
Followed by further separate treatment
of the solids and the liquid effluent.
This liquid effluent is also called
(INAUDIBLE) or supernatant
This table shows values
from the literature
for suspended solids
Chemical Oxygen demand
also called COD
Ammonium Nitrogen in the liquid
effluent from unplanted drying beds
Planted drying beds and in comparison
to domestic waste water
and common discharge standards.
There are three main messages
that you should take away from this table.
Firstly, the effluent concentration
can be very different
depending
on the treatment technology.
For example, based on this values
unplanted drying beds
were higher in COD and Ammonium
Nitrogen than planted drying beds.
This means that concentration
liquid effluents from different
solid liquid
separature technologies
need to be taken into account for design
of effluent treatment technologies.
Secondly,
Effluent concentrations do not mean
common discharge requirements
for suspended solids, COD,
and Ammonium Nitrogen.
And further treatment is required
to protect environmental health.
Liquid effluents also commonly
have high salt concentrations,
they can can harmful to plants,
and contain pathogens that require
inactivation before discharge.
Thirdly, even after
solid liquid separation
these effluents can have much higher
concentrations than influent
of a domestic water treatment plant.
For example, ways to suspend
solids concentrations
In the (INAUDIBLE) from drying beds
are somehow similar to domestic
waste water.
COD and ammonium concentrations
can be (INAUDIBLE) magnitude higher.
Technologies that are used to treat
effluents from the solid liquid
separation technologies
include different types of waste
stabilisation ponds, constructed
wetlands, planted drying beds,
anaerobic baffled reactors
and anaerobic filters.
Let's have a look at two examples
of currently operating effluent
treatment configurations
at faecal sludge treatment plants.
One in the Philippines
and another one in India.
This picture shows the feacal sludge
treatment plant in Damaguete
the Philippines that is introduced
in another module.
Damaguete is a treatment capacity
of 80 cubical faecal sludge.
Is mainly collected from septic
tanks by vacuum trucks.
Falling this chart through a screen
solids and liquids are separating
in one anaerobic waste stabilization
ponds.
Solids are then being dewatered
on drying beds.
The treatment chain for the liquid
effluent from the anaerobic waste
stabilization ponds include one
facultative pond,
two maturation ponds in series
and then a constructive wetland
prior to discharge.
Waste stabilization ponds
also called lagoons
treat effluents in large
engineer designed basins.
Facultative ponds that are used
at Damaguete
following solid liquid separation
have a depth of 1 to 2.5 meters
and are designed for move
of dissolved and suspended organics.
They are called facultative ponds
because (INAUDIBLE) into a top level
which is predominantly aerobic.
and a bottom layer which is
predominantly anaerobic, so has no Oxygen
At Damaguete maturation ponds
follow these facultative ponds.
Maturation ponds usually have
a depth of 0.5 to 1.5 meters.
Are aerobic and are designed
for inactivation of pathogens.
The hydraulic retention time
of these ponds is usually several days
to weeks.
Which explains why they are planned
intensive and require a lot of space.
At Damaguete the effluent from
the maturation ponds
is further treating constructed
wetlands as shown behind me.
This slide shows the schematic
of a constructive wetland.
Which is also called planted gravel
filters and is very asimilar
to a planted drying bed
in its design and operation.
Constructive wetlands are basins
filled with gravel and sand
which plants that can grow in these
conditions such as antelope grass
or Echinochloa pyramidalis.
Constructive wetlands can be
distinguished and operate as
horizontal flow, so when the effluent
flows from one end to the other end
horizontally.
Or vertical flow, where it flows
from the top to the bottom.
Similar to unplanted drying bed.
During its passage suspended
and resolved organics are separated
by filtration and removed
from the liquid effluent
by microorganisms attached
to the filter media and the plant roots.
The purpose of this plant
is to ensure permeability
of the filter media, provide surface
for growth of microorganisms
and take up nutrients.
Efficient solid liquid separation
required before the use
of constructed wetlands to prevent
clogging of the filter media.
This picture shows a research
facility of Sandag
at the university of Yaounde
in Cameroon.
Here are series of planted drying
beds where (INAUDIBLE) use
concentration organics and nutrients
by 80%.
You can download a publication
of this research
for free from our website.
This picture shows the faecal sludge
treatment plant in Devanahalli
north of Bangalore in India.
In contrast to Damaguete, Devanahalli
only has a treatment capacity
of 6 cubic meters per day and receives
mostly charge from pit latrines.
This is one reason why different
treatment technologies were selected
for the effluent treatment.
Following this shows through a screen
solids and liquid are separated
by a settling tank.
Following solid liquid separation
the solids are treated in parallel
by anaerobic digesters.
Followed by another settling tank
after which solids are dewatered
on unplanted drying beds.
Instead of waste stabilization
ponds used at Damaguete
the liquid effluent
from the settling tanks
is treated in an anaerobic baffled
reactor which is also called ABR
followed by a treatment in
constructed wetlands.
This slide shows a schematic
of anaerobic baffled reactor
as used in Devanahalli.
They are concrete or plastic
tanks with a series of baffles.
In the schematic they are 5.
They're designed for a move
of organics.
The baffles force the effluent
to flow down into next chamber
and up through a sludge layer.
The scum take increase the performance
of the move of organics.
For example, in comparison
to a septic tank.
We have now introduced you to some
treatment technologies
for the liquid effluent from solid
liquid separation technologies.
If you would like to learn more
about these technologies
you could have a look at these
three publications developed
for waste water.
They can be downloaded for free
from these websites.
Currently, the design
of the technologies discussed
in this module are based in existing
technologies.
They need to be adapted
for effluents from solid liquid
separation of faecal sludge.
This could carry certain risk
for reliable treatment
that you should consider.
For example,
organics in faecal sludge
may already be partially digested
which could reduce the effectiveness
of anaerobic treatment technologies.
Such as anaerobic baffled reactors
discussed before.
This is likely due to long storage
duration
in onsite sanitation technologies.
As discussed at the beginning
of this module
faecal sludge can have
high Ammonium concentrations.
As a function of pH and temperatures
this means that faecal sludge
can have high Ammoniac concentrations
that can be caused by bacteria
and algae and inhibit
treatment processes, for example,
in facultative ponds
or anaerobic baffled reactors.
With smaller faecal sludge
treatment plants as the one shown
in Devanahalli, India.
Hydraulic shock loads, for example,
by a discharge of one big vacuum truck
can also be a challenge because
it can flush out the sludge
and microorganisms
that are valuable for treatment.
Variable treatment characteristics,
for example, from septic tanks
versus the pit latrine are also
challenging for such technologies.
In this module we discussed
that treatment plants can reduce
several liquids that require
further treatment.
In general, these liquids
of high concentration organics
nutrients and (INAUDIBLE)
which are often high in waste water.
As shown for two treatment plants
one in the Philippines
and another one in India,
waste stabilization ponds,
constructed wetlands, and anaerobic
baffled reactors among the treatment
technologies used for effluent
treatment.
A low fraction of biodegradable
organics, high Ammonia concentration
or hydraulic shock loads
can be challenges with effluent
treatment and should be considered.