We have by now introduced you
to several treatment technologies
for faecal sludge.
Treatment that provides an adequate
level of environmental and public
health protection requires
the combination of several
of these treatment technologies
which are different treatment objectives.
In this module walk you through
process flow of this treatment plant
here in Kampala, Uganda.
And have a closer look at the design
of settling sickening tanks
and unplanted drying beds.
Following this module you'll
be able to draw a process flow
of the faecal sludge
treatment in Kampala
and design settling sickening tanks
and unplanted drying beds.
Welcome to the Lubigi waste water
faecal sludge treatment plant
in Kampala, which is being operated
by the National Water and Sewerage
Cooperation since 2013.
Thanks to Fishnam Water
and Transportation
that designed this treatment plant
we are able to share
the design example of this treatment
plant with you.
Which is slightly modified
for training purposes.
Lubigi is designed for the treatment
of 400 cubical faecal sludge
that are mostly delivered
by vacuum trucks
that collect faecal sludge
from septic tanks and pit latrines.
A characterization study conducted
before the treatment design
estimated average concentration
of solids, organics, nutrients
and pathogens.
For example, 26.4 kg total solids
per cubic meter of faecal sludge.
Following discharge at Lubigi
faecal sludge passes through
screens for (INAUDIBLE) of solid waste
and falls by gravity into settling
sickening tanks
for solid and liquid separation.
As discussed in another module
the design of settling sickening tanks
is based on the settling velocity
and a solid liquid
separation efficiency.
For Lubigi a settling velocity
of 0.125 meters per hour
and a solid liquid separation
efficiency of 80%
were used in the design.
These values were selected
from preliminary guidelines
developed at Sandag and its research
partners in Ghana.
The first step in the design
of the settling sickening tank
at Lubigi was calculation
of the surface area based
on the maximum amount of faecal
sludge per hour.
which is called the peak flow.
In the design of Lubigi
it was assumed that at some days
a maximum of 600 cubical faecal
sludge will be delivered per day
within ten hours of operation.
We can calculate the peak flow
by dividing the maximum daily
discharge volume
by the operating hours.
With this information we calculate
the peak flow to 60 cubic meters
per hour.
We can then calculate
the required surface area
by dividing the peak flow
by the settling velocity.
This results in an area requirement
of the settling sickening tank
of 480 square meters.
The second step in the design
of the settling thickening tank
at Lubigi was to determine
the tank depth.
This slide shows a cross section
of a settling thickening tank.
Settling thickening tanks are commonly
separated in the different layers.
These are called the scum layer,
the clear water of supernatant layer
the separation layer
and a thickening layer.
The scum layer is the layer
where the scum accumulates.
The clear water layer includes
the liquid effluent
and the separation thickening layer
is where settling & thickening occurs.
Based on the preliminary guidelines
developed in Ghana
for Lubigi a scum layer of 0.8 meter,
a clear water of 0.5 meter,
and a separation layer of 0.5 meter
was considered for the design.
The depth of the thickening layer
needs to be calculated
based on the volume of sludge
that needs to be stored in this layer.
The settling sickening tank
in Kampala was designed
based on the loading period
of 30 days.
With this information we can
calculate the mass of total solids
that will accumulate in the settling
sickening tanks during this period
by multiplying the average daily
discharge volume
by the total solids concentration
of the sludge
and the solid liquid
separation efficiency.
with 30 days.
This results in a mass of 253 tons
of total solids.
The design of Lubigi considered
that 50% of this sludge is pumped
once a week onto
unplanted drying beds.
And only the remaining 127 tons
total solids require storage capacity
and the four settling thickening
tank layers.
According to the design
the sludge that would not be pumped
would be removed falling
the 30 day thickening period
with front loader and transported
to covered storage areas
as shown here.
To calculate how much
of this 127 tons accumulate
in the thickening layer, the design
need to estimate the amount
of total solids in the four layers
of the settling thickening tank.
Lubigi assumed similar total solids
concentration in those included
in the preliminary guidelines
from Ghana of 160 kg
per cubic in a scum layer,
5 kg per cubic in a clear water layer
60 kg per cubic in the separation
layer
and 140 cubic per cubic meter
in a thickening layer.
With this information
and the surface area
that we calculated before, we can
calculate how much total solids
are included in the scum,
clear water and separation layer
by multiplying the area
with the depth
and a total solids concentration
of the layer.
As the total amount was 127 tons TS
this means that 77 tons total solids
will be stored in these layers
whereas 15 tons total solids
will require storage
in the thickening layer.
We can then calculate the volume
of the thickening layer
by dividing this mass by a total
solids concentration
in the thickening layer.
This results in 357 cubic.
By dividing this volume
by the surface area of the tank
we calculated depth
of the thickening layer
to around 0.7 meters.
This means that the settling
thickening tank has a total depth
of 2.5 meters
and a total volume of 1200 cubic.
The third step in design
of the settling thickening tank
in Lubigi was to select the width
and the length.
This slide shows the top few
of the two settling thickening tanks
With sludge throwing from the right
to the left side.
Settling thickening tanks
are usually 5 to 10 meters longer
than they are wide to allow
settling and thickening of particles.
At Lubigi settling thickening
tanks were sizes 10 meters wide
and 50 meters long.
This picture shows the settling
thickening tanks in Lubigi
as they were constructed.
Two tanks were constructed
to allow reliable operation
during sludge removal
and maintenance.
Faecal sludge pumped from the settling
thickening tanks during the 30-day
period requires further dewatering
and drying.
At Lubigi sludge from the settling
thickening tanks
is dewatered and dried
on unplanted drying beds.
As discussed in another module
the hydraulic loading rate
and the solid loading rate
are design parameters
that are specific to unplanted
drying beds.
For the design of Lubigi
hydraulic load of 0.3 meters
and a solid loading rate
of 300 kg total solids
per square meter in year
was used for the design.
The first step in the design
of the drying beds in Lubigi
was calculation of the drying bed
area based on hydraulic loading rate.
We calculated before that 127 tons
of total solids
will require treatment on planted
drying beds within the 30-day period.
The design assumes that sludge
pumped from settling thickening tanks
has a total solids concentration
of 80 kg per cubic meter.
Which means that 12.5 cubic meter
of sludge
are around 1 ton of total solids.
With this information
we can calculate the volume of sludge
that will be pumped on drying beds
within 30 days.
By multiplying the mass of sludge
to be pumped by 12.5 cubic meter
per ton total solids.
These are 1588 cubic meter.
Based on the local climate
design assumes that a loading,
dewatering, drying and unloading
cycle on these drying beds,
which are covered,
will take around 30 days.
With this information we can
calculate the required
drying bed area by dividing
the volume discharge onto drying beds
by hydraulic loading rate.
This means that 5,292 square meters
are required.
In the second step the required
drying bed area was validated
with the maximum
solid loading rate.
By dividing the number
of operation days per year
by the days of one drying cycle
we calculate the drying beds
will be loaded
around 12.2 times per year.
By multiplying the number of cycles
with the mass of sludge loaded
onto one drying bed per cycle
divided by the drying bed area
we can calculate
the solid loading rate
as 293 kg total solids per square
meter in year.
This isn't reason to the solid
loading rate considered
for the design.
This slide shows the drying beds
in Lubigi.
As you can see they were covered
and they drying bed area
was distributed to 18 equally sized
drying beds.
As shown in this picture
at Lubigi
effluents from settling thickening
tanks and drying beds
and waste water are co-treated
in parallel in 3 anaerobic waste
stabilization ponds.
Followed by 2 facultative waste
Sludge from this waste stabilization
ponds is then being dewatered
and dried on these uncovered
drying beds shown here.
In this module we walked you through
process flow of the Lubigi
waste water and faecal sludge
treatment plant in Kampala.
Where settling thickening tanks,
drying beds,
waste stabilization ponds
and storage
are combined for treatment.
We also introduced you the design
of settling thickening tanks
and drying beds.
These designs were based
on preliminary guidelines
developed in Ghana.
In the absence of clear design
standards or faecal sludge
treatment technologies
monitoring treatment plants
like Lubigi could be really
important to improve the designs
for future implementations.