If you buy vegetables from a vendor
at a market
what do you thing the vendor
does with this money?
Most likely vendors have to make
a number of payments with this money.
Some have to buy vegetables
from a farmer
or they have to pay to produce them.
Maybe they also have to pay
the employees,
pay rent for the stall,
or tax in the transaction.
We call of these payments
financial transfers.
In this module we introduce you
to different financial transfers
and flows in faecal
sludge management.
Following this module, you'll be able
to list different financial transfers
in faecal sludge management.
Name stakeholders involved
in financial transfers.
And be able to discuss different
financial flow models.
Money matters.
This is also true for the management
of faecal sludge.
In faecal sludge management
money's exchange
by different stakeholders
to cover their capital
and operational maintenance costs.
Let's look at some of these cost before
we look in how they are balanced
by financial transfers between
stakeholders.
Capital costs that are paid when
buying equipment or infrastructure.
Let's consider for example
this collection service provider
shown in this picture in Kampala.
Before you could start operating
he had to buy a gulper
for faecal sludge collection.
And a pickup for transport
of this sludge to a treatment plant.
In addition, he had to buy
other personal protection equipment
such as gumboots, face mask
and gloves
and other tools of trade.
Such as these blue barrels.
These are capital costs.
In contrast to these capital costs
which are paid one time
or only every few years
operational maintenance costs incure
more regularly
often on day to day basis
for operation and maintenance
of different faecal sludge management
services.
Let us consider again
our previous example.
What would be operational
maintenance cost
for this service provider?
Fuel for the pickup or payment
of the salary of his staff
are examples for operational
maintenance costs.
Replacing of personal production
equipment
or cleaning supplies
or paying of a discharge fee
at a treatment plant
are examples.
In this case the pickup is least
and the rent for the pickup
and additional operation cost.
Next to this example of this
collection service provider in Kampala
Kaplan operation and maintenance cost
incure for all stakeholders involved
in faecal sludge management.
This includes environmental
management authorities,
utilities, municipalities, private
companies,
non-governmental or community
based organizations
and household level users.
These costs can be at very different
magnitudes and frequencies.
So, whereas the capital cost
for the gulper
is usually several hundred
US dollars
depending on in which country
it is being manufactured.
A vacuum truck, as shown
in this picture,
may cost several thousand
or 10 thousand US dollars
And a city scale treatment plant
as shown here in Kampala
several million dollars.
So that faecal sludge management
service can be operated
over a long period of time.
Financial transfers need to balance
these costs of the different stakeholders.
For example, our service provider
would commonly cover
capital, and operational maintenance
cost.
Through a service fee that
he receives from a household
for the collection of faecal sludge
and transport to a treatment plant.
If this service fee is the only
revenue stream
and cannot cover its cost
it will likely result in poor
performance of the service
or it would go out of business.
The number of financial transfers
in faecal sludge management
strongly depends on the stakeholder
arrangement.
This slide shows different
stakeholder arrangements
for faecal sludge management.
Each block represents
one stakeholder.
In the first arrangement one
stakeholder manages the entire
faecal sludge management
service chain
and there are no financial transfers
between stakeholders.
In contrast, other arrangements
such as the last one
where four main, four stakeholders
managing
the faecal sludge management
service chain
includes more stakeholders
and also potentially more financial
transfers between these stakeholders.
This slide shows a common example
of institution arrangements
in faecal sludge management.
That consists of a household,
a private company for faecal sludge
collection and transport,
a public utility
for faecal sludge treatment,
And a farmer/industries that uses
faecal sludge treatment products.
In a common financial flow model
for this institution arrangement
the households pay a service fee
to the private service provider
for collection and transport
of faecal sludge treatment.
At a treatment plant, the company
pays a discharge fee.
This allows the service provider
to legally discharge sludge.
This fee is paid in return
for transfer and responsibility
managing the sludge
from the collection and transport
service provider to treatment
service provider.
The sale of treatment products
by the utility provides revenue
for the utility.
So in this example, the service fee,
the discharge fee,
and the revenue from the sales
of treatment products
are financial transfers.
The direction of the arrows
indicating which direction
the money flows.
This is why we also call this
financial flow models.
Financial traces have an effect
up and down the service chain.
For example, in a model
we just discussed
one application could be when
the utility chain has a very high
discharge fee.
It will likely be passed on
to the household
by a high service fee charge
by the collection and transport
service provider.
This could prohibit customers
being able to afford collection
and transport services.
Especially they're poor households.
Another implication could be
even when sludge is collected
collection transport service
providers illegally dump sludge
to avoid the high discharge fee
as shown here.
In addition, as the public utility
operates without financial effort
from the government authority
treatment could be less subject
to regulations which could result
in a poor treatment performance
or poor effluent quality.
How could this financial flow model
be modified
to reduce fees at the household level?
Ensure that faecal sludge is safely
collected,
reduce cost for the collection
transport service providers
that it can make sustainable business.
and ensure quality treatment.
One modification could be
budget support
of the utility
by a government authority.
The budget support could be funded
through a sanitation tax.
A sanitation tax if the payment
from households
to a government authority
in return for service such as water,
waste water or faecal
sludge management.
Sanitation's a public good.
And good sanitation has significant
health and economic benefits.
This justifies that a budget support
to the utility
can also be paid from other taxes.
Such as the property tax.
With this budget support
the public utility does not entirely
rely on the discharge fee
and revenues from treatment products.
It has initial revenues and thereby
can reduce the discharge fee
which in turn reduce the total cost
for this private collection
transport service provider.
And also maybe the service fee
for collection and transport.
In some parts of the Philippines
households paid 10 to 20%
of their water bill to cover
collection, transport
and treatment costs.
This means that households produce
less water
and which also maybe have less money
pay less for faecal sludge management.
This is one example how the social
economic realities
could be considered
in the sanitation tax.
In parallel to the sanitation tax
government authorities could
also consider issuing of operational
licences
for the collection and transport
service providers.
This would be in return
for the action of the discharge fee
to operate in a certain area
offer issuing of a discharge license.
Such licensing could be a first step
to formalize the collection
transport sector.
Improve standards and be enter point
for further interventions
For example, for schedule
faecal sludge collection.
As you have seen now they more or less
become more and more complex
and includes more stakeholders.
Reliable denotation of a financial
flow model with more stakeholders
and more financial transfers
requires good coordination
and management.
Such a model could be prone
to corruption
and relies on reliable tax collection
that can be challenging
especially in urban poor areas
with difficult accessibility
and tenure.
However, a sanitation tax could have
the benefit of providing a reliable
income for the public utility
that's required for reliable
operation and maintenance
of the treatment plant.
One tool to manage this
increased complexity
could be to make financial transfers
electronic.
For example, with phone based
money transfer.
At the treatment plant in Kampala
collection transport
service providers
paid a discharge fee
by transferring money
with their mobile phones
to their kind of utility.
So there's actually no cash being
handled.
These were some examples
of financial flow models
developed for training purposes
and based
on available literature
and our work in Uganda,
Senegal and Tanzania.
There's no single financial
flow model that has been shown
to be effective for faecal sludge
management all situations.
With a number of different
stakeholders that can be both public
and also private.
And the number of financial
transfers
A large number of different
financial flow models
could be developed.
In reality, as the urban areas
in which they exist
these financial flow models
can be much more complex
and dynamic will develop over time
and maybe also exist in parallel
to each other in one area.
In this module we learned
about different financial transfers
in faecal sludge management
depending on different
stakeholder arrangements.
Financial transfers include
a sanitation tax,
service or discharge fee,
budget support,
a discharge
and operational licenses,
and sales revenue from treatment
products.
We also learned to read and discuss
financial flow models.
What is the financial
flow model in your city?
We hope that examples provided
in this module inspired you
to explore what could work best
in your city.