Imagine have a bicycle.
What do you have to do so it run
smoothly over a long period of time?
You have to put air into the tire
or fix the tube in case
you have a flat tire.
Also you have to grease the chain
and maintain breaks
so it runs smoothly
and is safe in traffic.
And you also need to lock it.
Otherwise, it might get stollen.
As with the bicycle, operation
and maintenance is required
for faecal sludge treatment plants.
In this module we'll introduce you
to important considerations
for long term operation.
Following this module you'll be able
to list operation and maintenance
activities important for faecal sludge
treatment plants.
Explain a manifest system
and know what operation and maintenance
plans include.
Operation and maintenance includes
a long list of activities.
They are very depending on the size
and the technology of a treatment plant.
In general, operation refers to all
activities that ensure
that the treatment plant delivers
delivers treatment as designed.
Activities to ensure the operation
of a treatment plant starts
with coordinating
the sludge discharge.
This typically includes reporting
the sludge volume and origin
and payment of the discharge fee
by the collection or transport
service provider and coordination
of the sludge discharge.
By the private or public utility
managing the treatment plant.
This is shown here the faecal
sludge treatment plant in Kampala.
Many other activities associate
with the operation
of treatment technologies.
This, for example, includes cleaning
of screens at the inflow
of settling sickening tanks
or drying beds.
And also disposal of the solid waste.
Another example is the cleaning
of inlets and outsets.
For example, at waste stabilization
ponds, as shown here.
Other examples
are the loading/unloading
for example, of settling
sickening tanks
of drying beds
or the turning in co-composting.
Also treatment products need
to be managed.
You can see workers of a treatment
plant loading sludge from a drying bed
on a truck of a farmer for use
as soil conditioner in agriculture.
For more formalized resource recovery
from faecal sludge treatment product
this can also include
other activities.
For example, baying of the resource
recovery product
for example, compost
or marketing.
Operation of treatment technologies
may also require consumables
that need to be managed,
so they're available
when they're required.
They also might need to prepare
for their use.
Example of such consumables
are polymers aligned for conditioning
to increase the dewatering
properties of faecal sludge.
Next to all these activities
which are linked to the operation
of the treatment technologies.
Monitoring of the treatment process
is important to asses whether
treatment plant operates
as designed.
Monitoring, for example, includes
records of the sludge volume
that is discharged
at a treatment plant.
This is important to asses whether
the treatment plant receives small
or less largely designed and this
will affect the performance
of the treatment plant.
In addition to records on a sludge
volume, characteristics of faecal
sludge discharge
at a treatment plant
and of treatment products
from treatment technologies
can be used to estimate
the treatments performance.
So, for example, the settling
sickening efficiency
in a settling sickening tank
can tell you how good
that settling tank is operating.
Also other process parameters,
such as temperature in co-composting
can be important.
In co-composting the temperature
can be an indicator
for pathogen inactivation.
Such information is also helpful
to optimize the treatment plant
and potentially increase
its treatment capacity.
Monitoring of a treatment plant
is also required to assess the quality
of treatment products
before its use.
Especially pathogens such as
e coli and helminth eggs
and to report authorities
on discharge concentrations.
These include, for example,
Chemical Oxygen Demand,
suspended solids
and Ammonia Nitrogen.
In addition to recording the sludge
volume and characteristics
and to process parameters
a manifest system can be useful
tool for a treatment operator.
Let's have a close look.
The manifests form
has to be filled out
during the collection of faecal
sludge by the service provider.
It includes the name and other
details of the client.
And also includes the type of onsite
sanitation technology
from which the sludge
is being collected.
In this case from the Philippines
only septic tank faecal sludge
is collected
but it can also include
other sludge types
such as pit latrine sludge
or sludge from public toilets.
The manifest also indicate
if the sludge is collected
from residential, commercial-industrial
or institutional onsite sanitation
technologies.
The manifest form also includes
details on the service provider.
Following completion
of the collection service
the manifest form has to be signed
by a client.
Upon arrival at a treatment plant
the treatment operator has to approve
this manifest form in line with
the capacity of the treatment plant.
This could be a way to end
the defined industrial contaminations.
For example, when sludge
from industries is delivered.
The contribution of sludge
from different onsite sanitation
technologies, for example,
septic tank vs pit latrines
could also be important
as it has implications for treatment.
For example, the solid liquid
separation efficiency
on drying bed or in settling
sickening tanks.
The system should always
be complement of these visual
observations, such as the sludge
color.
Any other color than brown or black
could indicate industrial
contaminations which could disrupt
the treatment operation.
A signature of this manifest form
by the treatment operator
could also be a proof to the client
or government authority
that the service provider
discharge at legal location.
Maintenance activities ensure
the longterm operation
of equipment and infrastructure
at a treatment plant.
This, for example, includes physical
inspection of servicing of pumps
or tractors, or backup generators,
that are relevant for settling
sickening technologies.
Water replacement of (INAUDIBLE)
for drying beds.
This means that operation
and maintenance are interlinked.
Suboptimal operation can increase
the maintenance.
For example, by the failure of pumps
and suboptimal maintenance
will luckily lead to poor operation.
Every feacal sludge treatment plant
should have operation and maintenance
plans.
In general, operation and maintenance
plans document a procedure
of their operation
and maintenance activity.
It also includes tools that
are required to conduct the activity
and show how often the activity
has to be performed.
It also includes performance
indicators to measure
if the activity was successful.
And includes
health and safety precautions.
Such precautions should prevent
employees from getting sick.
For example, from pathogens
or electrocuted
from electrical devices.
An example of operation
and maintenance plans
are standard operating procedures
for the analysis of faecal sludge.
This can be downloaded
for free of charge from our website.
Documentation of the operation
and maintenance activities
document in these operation
and maintenance plans
in log books and data summaries
are really important for internal
and external reporting
and decision making.
Operation and maintenance needs
to be performed
once a treatment plant
has been designed and constructed.
But it's really important
to consider these activities
at the early planning stages
of a faecal sludge management program.
Otherwise, treatment plans can fail.
Let's take this example
of a settling sickening tank.
If a pump for sludge removal
cannot be operated
due to a lack of electricity
or the tank can't be maintained
because of the lack of funds
the tank will have a poor
performance.
This will affect subsequent
treatment steps and ultimately
the effluent concentrations
of the treatment plant.
This shows that the selection
of a treatment technologies
has to consider the operation
and maintenance cost
and require operational capacities
of the lifetime of a treatment plant.
As in a lot of contexts realistic
operation and maintenance plan
would likely demonstrate
insufficient capacities.
These could be developed in parallel
to the construction
of a treatment plant
to ensure a longterm
and reliable operation.
In this module we learned about
typical operation and maintenance
activities such as coordination
of the sludge discharge,
cleaning of screens and tanks,
and monitoring.
A manifest system can be helpful
tool to monitor the sludge discharge
into a treatment plant and to identify
industrial contamination.
These activities should always
be documented in operation
and maintenance plans.
Following these plans will ensure
that treatment plants operate
as designed and protect public
and environmental health.
In addition, to producing
marketable treatment products.