Imagine you're in
an urban area similar to this
where limited space
available for treatment.
How could you increase
the treatment capacity
of an existing plant?
Or how could you design
treatment plants
that need less space?
In this module, you will learn
about one technology
that could contribute towards
finding a solution.
Following this module
you'll be able
to explain conditioning
name types of conditioners
and understand considerations
for the design and implementation
of conditioners at fecal sludge
treatment plants.
Conditioning is the increase in
the separation of liquids and solids
in fecal sludge by
the addition of chemicals
before settling
and dewatering technologies.
These chemical lead to
destabilization of solid particles
called coagulation
and produce larger flocs
called flocculation.
Depending on the chemical used
these flocs have
a better settling thickening
faster dewatering or result
in increased solid concentration.
Conditioners have
been used for decades
in the dewatering
of the different types
of waste water sludge.
Polyelectrolytes, also called
Polymers, Lime
Ferric chloride or Alum
are common conditioners
for waste water sludge.
Conditioning can have a large
influence in sludge treatment
by increased settling thickening
conditioners can increase
the effluent quality
from settling thickening tanks
and thereby reduce the sold
and organic concentration
that require further treatment.
By increased dewatering,
conditioners can reduce
the time of dewatering and thereby
increase the treatment capacity
of existing treatment plants
or decrease the treatment (INAUDIBLE)
of new plants.
The selection of conditioners
and the optimal dosage
is specific to the sludge type
and dewatering technologies
for example, a centrifuge
versus the drying bed.
In comparison to waste water sludge,
hardly any experience is available
for conditioning of fecal sludge.
To transfer the use of
conditioners to fecal sludge
information for manufacturers and
laboratory experiments are required.
In the laboratory,
mixing conditioner
with fecal sludge in jar tests,
shown here, followed by
observing the settling
and thickening performance
in Imhoff cones,
as show here
by comparing unconditioned
fecal sludge
to conditioned fecal sludge
and determination
of capillary suction time
as shown here, can be used
to assess the performance
of the conditioner in dose.
The capillary suction time
is and indicator for the dewatering
raid of sludge
Similar experiments can be conducted
an a bench and pilot scale
with settling thickening
dewatering columns
as shown here.
Conventional conditioners
used for waster water sludge
are expensive and commonly rely
on a complex supply chain.
In a study in Dakar, Senegal,
we assessed the potential
of conditioners they
could be produced locally
such as moringa oleifera seeds
and Chitosan, that could be reduced
from shrimp waste.
The goal was to increase
settling and dewatering.
Locally available conditions were
compared to commercial products
used in waste water sludge treatment
such as Lime and Polymers.
This graph, for example,
shows the results of specific
resistance of filtration.
Specific resistance of filtration
is another metric to measure
the dewatering rate.
A lower resistance of filtration
means fast dewatering.
From this graph we can
draw two conclusions
firstly, the dewatering rate
od unconditioned fecal sludge
is significantly lower than
those compared to waste water
and water treatment sludge
results from the literature.
Secondly, moringa oleifera
and Chitosan were as effective
increasing dewatering than
commercial Polymers
used in waste water
sludge treatment.
In this study, conditioning
of septic tank fecal sludge
could be used to suspend
solids in the effluent
of settling thickening
technologies by 80-90%
The dewatering rate for the example
on drying beds could be improved
by 70-90%.
This could reduce the dewatering
time of sludge on drying beds
by 60-95%.
Next to the treatment performance
we also looked at the feasibility
of these conditioners
to be produced locally.
In Dakar, insufficient quantities
of moringa oleifera seeds
for conditioning of fecal sludge
at Dakars treatment plant
were available.
In contrast, it appears
that sufficient quantities
of shrimp waste could be sourced
and available for the production
of Chitosan as conditioner.
This study can also be downloaded
for no charge from our website.
Could fecal sludge conditioning
be a solution for your city?
Here's some additional
important considerations
for it's implementation.
Conditionings are commonly dosed
as a function of total solids.
This is challenging for fecal sludge
and it's highly variable.
Next to a tank for additional
storage and dosage device
a homogenization tank may
therefore be required.
Complete mixing of fecal sludge
with the conditioner
is important for optimal
conditioner usage
however mixing speed should be
selected to avoid floc destruction.
This should also be considered
during the selection of pumps
for example, for the transfer
of conditioned fecal sludge
from a settling thickening tank
to a drying bed.
In this module you have received
an introduction to conditioning
learned about the conventional
conditioners
and learned important considerations
for the implementation
of conditioners in fecal sludge.
These include identification
of the optimal dosage
and availability.