Can you believe that these
fuel pellets and these briquettes
were made out of faecal sludge?
I understand if you're skeptical.
In this module you will learn about
important considerations
for the production
of solid fuels.
Following this module you will be
able to describe
treatment products that can be
used as a solid fuel,
name characteristics that are
relevant to assess the potential
and understand what's to be
considered for it's implementation.
Why would someone consider producing
solid fuels from faecal sludge
especially considering
that it's 95% water?
Illustrated in this graph is the
market value of different
faecal sludge treatment products in
Dakar, Accra and Kampala.
The values are reported as U.S dollar
(USD) per ton dried faecal sludge.
The graph demonstrates that
solid fuels such as dried faecal sludge
from drying beds can generate
more revenues
in comparison to
other treatment products.
For example in Kampala, the values
of solid industrial fuel
was estimated to be
32 USD per ton
in comparison to 16 USD per ton
as a soil conditioner.
This study can also be downloaded
free of charge from our website.
Based on our more recent research
in Kampala we would even estimate
a higher price for dried
faecal sludge as a solid fuel
of 60 to 80 USD per ton.
Lack of financial resources
is a frequent reason for the failure
of faecal sludge treatment services.
Increased revenues
generated from solid fuels
in comparison to a soil conditioner
could be used to
partially offset faecal
sludge treatments costs
or discharge fees at
faecal sludge treatment plants.
Due to the low solid content
in faecal sludge
de-watering and drying are important
for the production of solid fuels.
Next to settling thickening tanks
and drying beds
innovative and established
technologies from waste water
sludge treatment such as
conditioning, pelletizing and
the use of green houses
as shown here, should be considered.
Let's have a closer look
into pelletizing.
Pelletizing is
the processing
of de-watered sludge into
a pellet form such as these.
As part of our research,
we implemented a bioburn pelletizer
at a faecal sludge and waste water
treatment plant in Kampala.
The research demonstrated that
faecal sludge from drying beds
could be pelettized at a moisture
content ranging from 40% to 60%.
Following pelettizing, we then
evaluated drying of pellets
to 10% moisture. 10% is the moisture
content of most solid fuels.
Drying of pellets only
took around 1 week
in comparison to weeks
or a month on drying beds.
Dried sludge in a crushed or in
a pellet form is 1 treatment product
that can be produced from faecal
sludge with drying technologies.
Here you can see dried faecal sludge
being used as a fuel
for firing of clay bricks in a
pale skillet kiln in Kampala.
Using dried faecal sludge
as a fuel, we were able
to achieve the required
temperatures for brick production
and the heating performance
was comparable to coffee husks
which are commonly used
in Kampala.
Char briquettes are another
energy recovery product
that can be produced from
dried faecal sludge.
The process of
char production
is called carbonization
or slow-pyrolysis.
Carbonization is a thermal
chemical conversion of
dry biomass
in the absence of oxygen
at temperatures ranging from
300 to 600 °C.
This is the same process that
converts wood into charcoal.
Carbonization products
includes gases
that can be used to provide heat
for the carbonization process
or sludge drying and char that can
be used to produce char briquettes.
Following carbonization, char is in
a powdery form in which it cannot
usually be directly used for energy
recovery in households or institutions.
Briquetting of char with a binder
such as molasses or
as cassava flour can convert
the char from a powder
in a form that is comparable
to wood-based charcoal.
In the market place solid fuels
produced from faecal sludge
have to compete with existing fuels
such as coal, sawdust,
coffee husks, char briquettes
and charcoal.
Let me walk you through a
few parameters that
you will be likely to be confronted
with when talking about solid fuels.
The calorific value, an estimate
of the energy content,
is an important
characterization parameter.
The unit of the energy content is
megajoules per kilogram
100% dried faecal sludge
(MJ/Kg).
This graph shows the energy content
of dried faecal sludge
in Kumasi, Dakar and Kampala
and compares the values to fuels
commonly used in these cities
such as coal, coffee husks,
rice husks and saw dust.
As you can see,
the calorific value of
dried faecal sludge is comparable
to other commonly used
biofuels.
On average, you have
17 MJ/Kg dried sludge
however depending on the
faecal sludge characteristics
and the treatment technology used
sludge can also have lower
and higher calorific values ranging
from 10 to 19 MJ/Kg dried sludge.
Among others, the difference in
calorific values can be explained
by the high concentrations of
inorganic material in the sludge.
Inorganic material is estimated
by the parameter ash content.
It is the proportion of fuel
that does not burn
and therefore does not
contribute to the calorific value.
Potential contributions to
inorganic material come from soil
in unlined or partially lined
pit latrines, from sand
and soil entering onsite sanitation
technology through a drop hole
and sand from drying beds
during treatment.
Ways to keep sand out of faecal
sludge need to be improved upon
to increase the energy recovery
potential of faecal sludge.
Carbonization of sludge also
increased the ash content
by removal
of volatile gases.
In one study conducted by Sandec
and in research partners
in Dar es Salaam and Kampala, char
produced from dried faecal sludge
had calorific values of
7 to 11 MJ/Kg dried sludge
and ash contents of 55 to 70%.
These are high
for use as solid fuels considering
that based on the literature
charcoal has a calorific value of
31 to 33 MJ/Kg
and an ash content below 5%.
Co-processing of char
produced from faecal sludge
and wood-based char dust
has the potential to increase
the fuel properties.
These pictures show charcoal and
briquettes from a fuel comparison
conducted in Kampala. In this study
which was based on calorific value,
ash content, the time to boil
5 liters of water and emissions
the performance of coal processed
faecal sludge char briquettes
were comparable to char briquettes
sold in Kampala
and produced
from agricultural waste.
The calorific value was
19 to 20 MJ/Kg
and the ash content
22 to 37%.
Do you think solid fuels could be
a good resource recovery option
for your city? Here are some
additional considerations.
Existing examples of the use of
fuels produced from
faecal sludge are few.
This means marketing
will be required to
demonstrate that these fuels
can be a competitive
alternative to existing fuels.
Large industries such as cement
or brick companies
could be important customers for the
use of dried faecal sludge
and they could provide a large
and consistent revenue stream
for treatment operators.
However, quantities of fuel
that large industries require
for full scale implementation
may exceed the quantities of sludge
that are currently being treated.
For example, in Kampala in 2015
around 4 tons of dried sludge
were produced daily at the Lubigi Waste
Water and Faecal Sludge Treatment plant
whereas interviewed cement companies
said they required at least
10 tons per day
for use fuel in their kilns.
Faecal sludge also contains elements
that can produce emissions
during carbonization and
combustion such as
nitrogen and sulfur oxides,
particulate matter or black carbon.
These can all have negative impacts
on the environment and
litigation needs to be considered
before implementation.
In this module we learned about
2 treatment products that can be used
as solid fuels. We also learned
about relevant characterization
parameters for these products
such as ash content
or calorific value. Important for
implementation will be
research on carbonization
technologies and related emissions.
In addition, marketing and increasing
available sludge quantities
are important for the success of
faecal sludge as solid fuels.