In the previous episodes, we have learnt
how to declare classes
and objects, that is, class instances.
For example, in order to declare a "rect"
instance of the "Rectangle" class,
we will write "Rectangle rect; ".
Now, we could wonder
how to give other values for the
default variables
(which is 0) to the attributes of
our rect instance. For example,
the attributes "hauteur" and "largeur"
(TN: "hauteur" means "height", "largeur" means "width").
Even better, we would like to initialize,
namely give an initial value of "rect"'s creation,
to the "hauteur" and "largeur" attributes.
Of course, we could resort to
the setter "setHauteur" and "setLargeur",
thus assigning
individually, one after the other, values
for each attribute. For example,
here, we have declared a "rect" instance
of the "Rectangle" class.
We have prevously declared a double "lu" and
ask the user to enter
the height on the keyboard. Then, through
the setter "setHateur", we will assign
the value read from the keyboard in "lu"
to the height of the "rect" instance.
Similarly, via user interaction, we will
assign the value of "lu"
to the width of the "rect" instance.
Obviously, this is a very poor
solution in the general case. Indeed, this
will either require for each attribute
to be part of the interface (which  will
break the encapsulation
as we have seen in last week's
episodea)
or for us to have a setter for
attribute.
This itself translates how the class
has been implemented
and breaks the encapsulation since we
need a setter for each
attribute. The goal of this encapsulation
is precisely to clearly separate
the interface from the implementation.
If we had, for each attribute,
a setter in the interface,  the
implementation choices would
spill over the inteface. In that way
does it break the encapsulation. Moreover,
we are bestowing the responsability
to initialize the attributes on the
programmer-user of the class.
This begets the risk of omissions.
It is the duty of the programmer-developper
to initialize the attributes
or offer
an interface permitting the initialization
of a few carefully selected attributes
for the programmer-user of the class.
So far, every time we have
indentified a specific task, we created
a specific method dedicated to this task.
Right now, this task is the initialization.
A solution is thus to create
a method dedicated to the
initialization. For example,
an "init" method, here. Of course, we will
offer it in the interface
so that programmer-users of the class
may use it.
This "init" method will thus be tasked
to initialized the two
attributes "hauteur" and "largeur".
To that end, it will receive two values
"h" and "l" to initialize the
height and the width respectively.
Typically, we would use this newly-
created initialization method
like this. We will declare a "rect"
instance of the "Rectangle"
class. Then, we will call the "init" method
in order to initialize,
for example, the height to 3 and
the width to 4.
This is definitely not a poor solution.
Actually, this is such a good solution
that the Java language offers a way to do
so properly.
Namely, letting us do a true
initialization. Such methods,
tasked with the instance initialization
are called constructors.
A constructor is a method which is systematically
called upon
an object's declaration. In other words,
it is called when an instance is born.
Its task is thus to do whatever is
necessary for the beginning of
an instance's life -particularly
initializing its attributes.
In order to declare a constructor, we
simply need to add a method
which name is none other than the name of
the class. Then, follow the possible parameters
required for the initialization. As usual,
the definition of the metod
then follows.
For example, for the "Rectangle" class,
we will define a "Rectangle" method
(the same is the same as the class)
which is thus a constructor.
It receives two parameters "h" and "l"
in order to initialize, in the body
of this method,
the attributes "hauteur" and "largeur"
respectively.
Constructors are very similar to your
average methods.
There are however three differences!
First of all, a constructor
has no return type.
We have no written anything here, not even "void";
this means that the constructor
has no return type at all.
The second difference is that
the constructor MUST have a name
identical to the name
of the class. Finally, a constructor will
systematically be called
every time a new instance is
created. It is called with a syntax
we will detail in an instant.
These are the differences.
However, constructors can,
like other methods, be
overloaded.
This means that we will have
several different parameter lists
for different constructors.
We may thus have several constructors.
We will go back
to this point later. For now,
we merely wish to stretch
that we talking about the
possible constructorS for a class.
There is not necessarily a
unique constructor.
Let us go back to our
starting example
and see how this is
concretely written.
We will declare only one constructor
in our "Rectangle" class.
To that end, we will declare the
"Rectangle" class as usual.
Its attributes "hauteur" and "largeur"
are in the private parts.
As usual, the different setters,
getters and methods
we have decided to put
in the interface.
However, we have now added
a constructor.
This constructor is a method with the
same name as the class.
Of course, this constructor must be part
of the interface since its goal is
to be called by  the people
using the class.
It needs to be accessible from
outiside the class.
In this case, it receives two parameter:
"h" and "l"
in order to initialize the "hauteur"
attribute and
the "largeur" attribute.
Let us now see a constructor is called.
That is, how will we declare
an instance which we will declare an
initialize at the same time.
To that end, we will resort to a
usual declaration of a certain
class' instance here. This declaration
will be followed by
" = new ", name of the class. This here, will
be a call to the constructor to which
we pass, between parentheses, the
different parameters
necessary for the constructor.
Here, in the example of our "Rectangle"
clsss, we will declare
an "r1" instance of the "Rectangle" class,
" = new ", call to the "Rectangle" constructor
which takes two parameters here.
Concretely, in this example we are following
from the start,
we thus have the "Rectangle" class with,
here, in public, a constructor
taking two parameters. It will be responsible
to initialize the parameters
"largeur" and "hauteur" of the class.
For example,
here, in the class "Example" where
we have the "main" we will declare
an "rect1" instance of the "Rectangle" class.
We initialize it directly
through a call to the constructor. We pass
the value 3 to the parameter "h"
in order to store it in "hauteur" and the
value 4 to the parameter "l"
in order to store it in the "largeur"
of "rect1".
Concretely, the following will happen
in the memory. "rect1" is thus
a reference on a rectangle. Upon this
"new Rectangle" instruction, we will indeed
create an "Rectangle" instance in the
memory with these two
parameter "hauteur" and "largeur".
The call to the constructor, here, will thus
initialize these to the values 3 and 4.
Voilà! This concludes our introductory
sequence on the constructors.
We still have a lot to tell you, though.
For example, we will discuss
the default constructor, which
is unique. We will discuss
the copy constructor and see
what happens at the end of an object's life.
And we will see how to compare
different objects.
This will be the subject of the
following episodes.