In this new episode, we will
focus
on the default constructor.
Namely the constructor which
are called when we do not provide
any initialization value,
no parameter. We will also
discuss what happens
if, in a classe, we do not define
any explicit constrcutor.
A default constructor is simply
a constructor which
has no parameter. You can see here
a concrete example.
We can imagine that, in the "Rectangle",
three different constructors
cohabit. This means, three different
ways to initialize a "Rectangle"-type example.
The default constructor -without
parameter- has for mission to initialize
the "hauteur" and "largeur" attributes
to default values.
Concretely, this default constructor
will be summoned like this.
We will declare an "r" object of the "Rectangle"
type. We will initialize it
by using the default constructor.
It will be call through
this instruction. Here, since we
are specifying that the constructor
is called with an empty argument
list, this means
we are indeed calling this
constructor here.
After this initialization, the
situation in the memory will be this one :
We will thus have an "r" variable
containing a reference on a
"Rectangle"-type object. Its "hauteur"
member will be initialized to the
default value 1.0 and its "largeur"
member
to the default value 2.0
The other constructors of the class
are not
default constructors; indeed, their
parameter lists
are not empty.
If, for example, we wish to
summon this constructor here,
we must use this particular phrase.
Thus, just like before,
we declare a "Rectangle"-type
variable "r1".
We call the constructor will
a phrase similar to the one
we have seen previously.
However, we precise, as argument,
the value we wish to give to
this parameter "c".
Now, what does happen if the
programmer of a class
does not code any explicit constructor?
Why, the object initialization is
considered so essential
that a constructor will be automatically
generated for this call.
This will obviously be a
default constructor.
We will call it the default default
constructor.
This automatically-generated constructor
is a default constructor because
it has not parameter. We call it "default"
itself because it is provided
automatically if there is no
other explicit constructor
in the class.
This default default constructor will
do a minimum work
regarding the initialization.
It will initialize all basic-type
attributes with
default values such as 0 , 0.0 or "false".
Regarding objects, they will all
be initialized to "null".
Let us suppose that we define a
"Rectangle" class. It will have,
as in our previously-seen examples,
two double-type attributes "largeur" and
and "hauteur". It will also have
another, more complex argument :
for example, an object (an instance)
of another class.
For example a "Position" class permitting
to represent the
Rectangle's position on a two-
dimensional screen.
Thus, in the "Rectangle" class,
there is no explicit constructor.
That means that the default default
constructor is generated;
we can use it to initialize
a rectangle.
For example, in another part
of the program,
we may declare a "Rectangle"-type
variable, a "Rectangle" object
and initialize it with the default
default constructor
which, of course, does not take
any parameter.
After this initializaiton, we will
have, in the "rect" variable,
a reference on a "Rectangle"-type
object. Its height and width
will be initialized to default values
since they are
basic-type attributes.
The height and width will thus
have the value 0.0
Also, the position, the "position"
attribute, will be initialized to "null":
since it is an object.
By the way, in order not to overburder
the writing of this example, we have not
precised the access rights.
Rigorously, for the better
encapsulation, all attributes
should be declared
as "private".
Be careful though!
This default default constructor
is not provided anymore as
soon as we define
at least one explicit constructor
for this class;
be this constructor default or not.
Concretely, this means that if, in a class,
we specify a constructor
which is not a default constructor,
we have no way to build
a object without providing
initialization values.
In other words, we cannot write
something like this anymore.
This instruction, calling a default
constructor is not valid anymore.
Why? Because the default default
constructor has disappeared.
This corresponds to something we
could wish. If we have taken the
time to explicitly program a
constructor in the class,
we do not wish for Java to inconspicuously
slide a default constructor
we never asked for; we never
explicitly specified
we wished to use a default
constructor.
In order to illustrate this, we will
now study three variants
of the same program differing
one from the others only
by the constructors.
In the first variant, the A variant, a
"Rectangle" class is defined
with two double-type attributes
"hauteur" and lsrgeur".
This class can have more content
but it has no
explicit constructor at all.
In the B variant, there are still
the same attributes. This time though,
we have an explicit constructor
which is a default constructor
because its parameter list is empty.
This constructor will initialize
the height and the width
to the value 0.0
Finally, in the C variant, the "Rectangle"
class has only one
explicit constructor which is not
a default construcotr anymore
since its parameter list
is not empty.
Here, this constructor expects one
value for the
height and another for the width. The
constructor will then assign these values
to the corresponding attributes.
For each of these variants, we will
ask ourselves the following questions:
Is there a default constructor?
Is it valid to initialize an object
with this instruction?
with this other instruction?
Let us begin by the first variant,
the A variant. Remember that,
here, we are only indicating the
constructors of the class; not the rest.
Here, we do not have any
explicit constructor.
As we have seen previously,
when a class does not define
any explicit constructor, a default
constructor is generated.
It is the default default constructor.
Therefore, the initialization
through this instruction is valid.
We are using a constructor
without parameter.
We have seen that, for basic-type
attributes, the default
default constructor initialize these
attributes
to the basic values.
Thus, the height will be 0.0
and the height will be 0.0
However, since the only available
constructor is the default default constructor,
we cannot initialize an object
with this instruction.
Since we are using a constructor
without parameter,
this instruction expecting parameters
is invalid.
Regarding variant B, we have, in the
"Rectangle" class
an explicit constructor; it is a
default constructor.
On the question asking if there
is a default constructor,
the answer is yes.
It is this explicitly declared
constructor.
Just like before, we can obviously
use this default constructor
with this instuction, calling a constructor
expecting no parameter.
Here, this constructor will have
the same effect as the
the default default constructor.
Indeed, it initializes the height
and the width to the same
values as the ones used by
the default default constructor.
On the same basic as for variant A,
this instruction is invalid;
there is indeed no other
constructor as the default constructor
in the "Rectangle" thus.
Therefore, no constructor expecting
two values could work here.
Finally, for the C variant, we have
an explicit constructor
which is not a default constructor.
On the question asking if there
is a default constructor,
the answer is no.
There is no default constructor.
Why? As we have said before,
as soon as we define
an explicit constructor -be it a default
constructor or not-
the default default constructor
vanishes.
Therefore, the only constructor
available in this class
is now this one.
It is thus not possible to
initialize an object with this instruction.
There is no constructor which
does not expect any argument.
This is thus invalid.
On the other hand, the second
instruction becomes valid.
It will initialize the height and
the width with the values
passed as argument. We will thus
obtain a "Rectangle" object
where the height will be 1.0
and the width 2.0
Let us now examine a few shortcuts
provided by the Java language
regarding object construction
and attribute initialization.
If there are several constructors
in a class, Java lets
any constructor summon
any other constructor
of the same class.
This is done with a particular
instruction : "this ".
We are thus using the reserved keyword
"this" and, between parentheses,
we provide the arguments corresponding
to those expected by the constructor
we wish to call.
For example, in this "Rectangle" class,
we have an explicit constructor
with two parameters.
We can define the default constructor
using this first definition
of the constructor.
Here, the default constructor, through
this "this" instruction,
summons the constructor expecting
two parameters -this one-
providing, for the first parameter,
the value 0.0
and 0.0 aswell for the
second parameter.
This is an elegant twist permitting,
in many a case,
to avoid duplicating code.
But please note that there can
only be one "this" instruction
in a constructor. Also, this
"this" instruction
must be the very first summoned
instruction.
We cannot put any other instruction
before the "this".
It is also possible, in Java,
to give default values to
the attributes, without passing
by the constructor.
This is done upon the declaration
of the attribute.
Here, for example, when we
declare the "hauteur" attribute,
we give it a default value : 1.0
Now, we summon the default
constructor of the class
with such a familiar instruction.
Like this.
In the default constructor, there is
no value
explicitly assigned to "hauteur"
or "largeur".
Therefore, the default values
will be taken.
After the constructor, we will have
an object in the memory.
A "Rectangle"-type object.
Its height has been
initialized to the default
value here : 1.0
The same goes for the width.
Let us now imagine that the default
constructor, instead of having an empty body,
initializes only the width member
to, for example, 3.0
After the constructor of a
rectangle with this
default constructor, we
will have, in the memory,
a "Rectangle"-type object.
Of course, the "hauteur" member
will have been initialized
to this value 3.0
And since the "hauteur" member does
not receive any explicit
value in the constructor,
it will take the default value
specified upon the declaration
of the attribute,
that is, 1.0
Please note that, in order to make
your programming intentions clear,
it is recommanded to initialize
the attributes in the constructors
instead of resorting to this
kind of twist.
Indeed, if each of the constructors
is tasked with all the
necessary initializations, it is possible
to understand what are
the realized initializations merely upon
the reading of these constructors.
It is not necessary to search everywhere
in the class
for other implicit initializations.
Voilà! We have no concluded this
sequence on the default constructors.
We will go back to them
in later episodes on the inheritance.
In the meantime, you will discover
other possible ways to build
an object through the
copy constructors.