In today's episode,
we will focus on a
particular constructor :
the copy constructor.
Thus, we will check what
happens
when an object is initialized
with a copy of another object
of the same class.
Indeed, Java lets us create
instance copies
such as here, for example.
Here, we have a first "r1" instance
of the "Rectangle" class
which we initialize through
a call to a constructor
taking two values.
This leads to the following schema.
"r1" is initialized to
the values 12.3 and 24.5
Then, we have another "r2" instance
of the "Rectangle" class.
r2 is initialized with a copy of r1.
We will thus copy r1's height
into r2
and copy r1's width into r2.
However, r1 and r2 and two
separated instances;
r2 has simply been initialized
with a copy of r1.
The copy constructor is
tasked with this kind of initializations.
The copy constructor is tasked
with initializing an instance
with copy of another instance
of the same class.
Its header is perfectly defined
since it is a constructor.
It has thus the same name
as the name of class.
And since it receives another
instance of the same class,
its parameter list is reduced
to one single parameter :
another instance of the
same class.
For example, in the case our
"Rectangle" class,
we would have a constructor,
which is obviously in the interface
of the "Rectangle" class. This
constructor is thus called "Rectangle".
Also, it receives, as its unique
parameter, another rectangle,
another instance of the "Rectangle" class.
This instance would, for example,
be the copy
of the height
of the rectangle received as parameter
into the height of
of the instance we are currently
initializing.
And similarly, a copy of the other
rectangle's width into the width
of the instance we are
currently initializing.
Let us go back to the previous example
where we had an r1 rectangle
with a height of 12.3 and
a width of 24.5
and an r2 rectangle
initialized with the copy constructor.
In this line we indeed have a call
to the copy constructor.
Here, the construction of r2
will trigger a call to the
copy constructor
passing, as parameter, r1
which is here "autre rectangle"
(TN: means "other rectangle").
In this case, it is indeed r1
passed to the copy constructor
of r2.
What happens is that,
here, the height of r2
will receive the height of r1
in copy.
Through this line, we will copy
the height of r1 into the width
of r2.
In the following line,
what happens is that we will
copy the width of r1
(the rectangle argument)
into the width of r2
(the rectangle we are currently constructing).
Here, we copy the width of r1
into the width of r2.
By the way please note
that, unlike other languages,
Java does not provide us with
a default version of the copy constructor.
This means that, if we do not
do anything particular
we are not allowed to do
copies, like these.
This constructor does not exist.
Therefore, if we want to do
copy constructions,
we need to write it explicitly.
Also, the copy constructor is not
the only way
to do copies in Java.
There is another way which is
more widely used.
It is the "clone" method, as you
can see here.
Through a call to the "clone" method,
we will clone the r1 instance
which we had previously initialized
with a usual constructor.
We will clone it into r2,
upon the declaration-initalization
of the r2 instance of the "Rectangle" class.
This "clone" method will be detailed
later in another video sequences
during the upcoming weeks.
This concludes this short episode
on copy constructors in Java.