The goal of this episode
is to present
a few complements regarding objects.
We know now how to build
objects. Now we will focus
on the end of these objects'
life.
We will also see that, since objects
are manipulated
through references, this
impacts the way
to print, assign and compare them.
Let us begin with the end
of an object's life.
First of all, what is the end
of an object's life?
In Java, an object reaches the
end of its life when the reference
associated to it is not usable
anymore in the program.
Let us illustrate this with a
simple example.
This example right here might
be a little artificial
but should make
things clear.
We can see a "main" method
calling an auxiliary method
"afficherUnRectangle". This method only
(TN: means "printARectangle")
locally creates a Rectangle-type
object "r" initializing it appropriately.
It then prints this rectangle.
The reference associated to this object
created in the method
"afficherUnRectangle" is not usable
anywhere else.
We never assign this reference
to another more globablly acessible variable.
Therefore, when the method
"afficherUnRectangle"
has concluded its execution, it is
not possible anymore
to access the reference locally created
inside the method.
Namely, once the method
"afficherUnRectangle"
has terminated its execution, the "r"
object, local to this method,
reaches the end of its life since
the reference associoated to it
cannot be used anywhere.
Thus, the memory associoated to
this object must be retrieved
so that it can be available in
other programs
or portions of the same program.
In some languages, the
memory retrieval
must be explicitly supported by
the programmer.
In Java, this is not the case.
There is a particular program called
the "Garbage Collection"
tasked with the very reclaiming
of the
memory associated with these objects
which do not need to be used
in the program.
Normally, this "garbage collection" is
completely transaprent.
You do not need to worry about
it at this point
of your programming learning.
The "garbage collector" program
is thus
regularly launched during a program
execution in Java.
What you must remember is that
the Java remember
does not have to explicitly
liberate the memory they are using.
However, this is not the case
in all languages.
Now, let us move on to
the object manipulation
via references and the implications
this can have.
Every time we create an object
in a Java program,
this object is manipulated, as we have
seen, via references.
If we declare a Rectangle-type
variable,
the situation in the memory is the following.
Let us call this Rectangle-type
variable "rect".
This variable is actually a reference
to an object
with its different attributes.
Now, we are focusing on the following
problem.
We suppose that we wish to create
an object "b" from an object "a".
Both will have the same type.
However, we wish for "a" and "b"
to be distinct objects in
the memory.
How can we do this properly
in Java when objects
are manipulated via references.
Let us take a concrete example.
Here, our "a" is the rectangle "r1".
From this "r1" rectangle, we wish
to create another rectangle
- thus with the same type. However,
we want both objects "r2" and "r1"
to be two distincts objects in the memory.
In Java, if we create a "r2" object
from "r1" object using
an assignment, the two objects
will be not be distinct in the memory.
Let us see why.
When we execute this
line of code,
we have the following situation
in the memory
after the execution.
In the "r1" variable, we have
a reference to a rectangle object
with particular values for
its width and height members.
Then, when we execute this
line of code,
we will create an "r2" variable.
Let us call "ref1"
the reference contained in "r1".
Upon this assignment, we will
simply copy
the value contained in "r1"
into "r2";
namely the reference to the
same object.
Concretely, this means that
we will point here,
on the same object in the memory.
"r1" and "r2" are NOT two distinct
objects in the memory.
Concretely, this means that
any manipulation
on "r1" will impact "r2" aswell
and vice versa.
For example, if we change
the value of the height of "r2",
this will impact "r1" aswell.
Therefore, if we wish for "r2" to
be
a copy distinct from "r1"
we cannot use the assignment
operator in Java.
Instead, we will use either the
copy constructor or the "clone" method
which will be discussed later
in the course.
We are talking about it here
because this is not systematically
the case in all languages.
In some languages, we can
perfectly create
two distinct copies through
the assignment operator.
In the previous episodes,
we have seen how
to write the copy constructor
in a class.
This very copy constructor
is used here.
This constructor creates a rectangle
from the values of another rectangle.
Thus, if we execute this line of code,
we are in the same situation as before.
"r1" is a reference to a particular
"Rectangle" object.
When we execute this line of code,
we are creating another "Rectangle"
object.
This is thus a distinct object
in the memory
where we will simply copy,
member by member,
the values of the first rectangle.
We can clearly see that this
not the same situation
as before.
Here, "r2" and "r1" are indeed two
distinct objects in the memory.
Still regarding objects
manipulated
through references in Java,
let us focus on the implications
for the printing of objects.
If we execute this line of code,
what is contained in our "rect" is
indeed a reference.
A reference is sort of like an
address
which a slightly peculiar format.
Now, if we try to
print the content of our "rect" object
through such an instruction.
This instruction will simply
print the content
of the "rect" variable.
What will result is somewhat
unnatural
and unpleasant to read. We would
probably prefear to print
the content of a rectangle, that is,
the value of its attributes
instead of its reference.
So, what should we do in
order to print the content
pointed by the reference
instead of the reference itself,
using exactly this same
instruction?
In order to make this possible,
so that such a line of code
may print the content pointed by "rect"
instead of this eerie referance,
we simply need to place, in the "Rectangle"
class, a particular method.
The header of this method is
the following.
This is the "toString() " method
with an empty parameter list
and returning a character string of
the type "string".
This " toString() " method will actually
be automatically be summoned
in order to convert this rectangle
into its representation
as a character string.
We are the ones deciding
what character string
will be produced by the "toString()" method.
Concretely, in the "Rectangle"
class, we will place
our famous "toString()" method as
public since we wish
to use from the outisde.
This "toString()" method will simply
build a character string
corresponding to the representation
we wish to have
when the object is provided as
argument to "System.out.println", typically.
Here, we have decided that
the string "String"
will be built as the concatenation
of the "Rectangle" string,
the value of the member "hauteur",
the value of the member "largeur"
separated by this character string here.
Thus, from now on,
every "Rectangle" will have
a representation built
with the "toString()" method.
This printing representation will be
a character string.
The execution of this line of code,
printing a rectangle with these
particular values as attribute,
will result in a printing of this kind.
This printing is much more
readable than the
previous one.
The fact that, in Java, objects are
manipulated through references
impact the assignment and
the printing of objects.
This will also impact the
object comparison.
This is the last point we
are now going to examine.
Let us now suppose that, in a given,
program, we create two rectangles
"r1" and "r2" with the same
attribute values.
The two will thus have the same height
and the same width.
What will happen if we try
to compare these two rectangles
with the " == " operator.
Will the values of the attributes
be compared or something
else?
In order to answer this question,
we have to see what is stored
inside the "r1" and "r2"
variables.
We have seen that, when we
create a rectangle
with this kind of instruction,
what we are retrieving
in the object variance is a
reference on an object.
We have this in the memory.
We thus have a "r1" variable
containing a reference, an address
on a "Rectangle" object.
Its "hauteur" member is 4.0
and its "largeur" member is 5.0
The same thing happens upon
the execution of the second line.
We will have an "r2" variable
in the memory,
containing a reference to a
"Rectangle" object.
Its "hauteur" member is 4.0
and its "largeur" member is 5.0
We can see that each of
these "new"
will actually create a distinct instance.
This means that even if these objects
have the same attribute values,
what will be compared through
the " r1 == r2 " comparison
is none other than the content
of the "r1" and "r2" variables.
These variables are distinct references
pointing on two different memory areas.
The result of this comparison
is the boolean value "false"
since we have two distinct
references.
However, in most cases, when
we wish to compare objects,
we do not wish to compare their addresses
but rather their content;
if these objects have the
same attribute values.
Thus, this not the good way to
reach this result.
If you have followed our previous
"MOOC" on the fundamentals
of Java programming, you have
seen how we proceed
in order to compare two character
strings.
In order to compare two strings,
we resorted
to the "equals" method rather
than the " == " operator.
We use this in case we wish to compare
the content of these strings
rather than the references to
these character strings.
As a reminder, let us examine
the following example.
The execution of this line
will allow us
to store  the reference on the character
string "Rouge" into the variable "s1".
After the execution of
these lines of code,
we will have a variable "s3",
the reference on a character string
built by concatenation
of the content of the variable "s2" and
the literal "ge".
The variable "s3" will thus have
the same content as "s1".
However, they both correspond
to disctinct references in the memory.
Comparing "s1" and "s3" through the
" == " operator, will compare
only the references in these
two different values
and will thus return "false",
even if their content are identical.
In order to compare their content,
we have seen that
we needed to resort to a predefined
methode for the strings.
This is the "equals" method. At this point,
if we use "equals",
we are comparing their content.
Thus, message "Chaînes identiques".
(TN: means "identical strings").
will be printed.
In order to compare the content
of two Rectangle-type objects,
we will resort to a similar solution.
We will thus use an "equals"
method.
The programmer of "Rectangle" will
have to define "equals"
correctly for rectangles.
How do we define "equals"
so that it returns "true"
if and only if the attributes of
the rectangles are identical?
The programmer of the "Rectangle"
class must concretely provide a method
testing the equality according
to the criteria we deem
sound for "Rectangle"-type objects.
When will we consider that
two rectangles are equal
according to their content?
One of the possible headers provided
by Java in the "Rectangle" class
in order to porgram the "equals" method
is the following.
We will more thoroughly on
an example
how to program this method in
the "Rectangle" class.
The "equals" method is a
method of the "Rectangle" class.
This means that will necessarily
be applied
on a Rectangle-type object.
Typically, we can imagine we have
declared an "r1" rectangle and
initialized it properly.
If we wish to compare "r1" with
another rectangle,
we will use the "equals" method.
This method will compare "r1" with
another rectangle provided as argument.
We imagine, for example, another
"r2" rectangle previously declared.
The "equals" method will thus take
a rectangle in argument
and compare it with a given
istance of rectangle.
It is the programmer's task to give
the body of the "equals" method,
to give the criteria to according to which
two rectangles can be equal.
The result is a boolean :
we expect it
to be "true" if the two rectangles
are considered equal
and "false" otherwise.
Concretely, we can imagine to
program the body
of the "equals" method as follows.
Usually, we take the precaution
to test if the instance
which we are trying to compare
the current instance is "null".
In this case, we will consider
that the comparison fails;
our "equals" method will thus
return "false".
A given instance cannot be
equal to "null".
Otherwise, we will return "true"
if the height of the current instance
has the same value as the
height of the rectangle passed
as argument.
And the same for the width.
Using the "equals" method
thus defined on two rectangles
with the same values for their
height and width
will result in the
boolean value "true".
Indeed,
"r2" is not "null", the values of the
heights are identical.
and so are the widths.
In this case, we will have the printing
"Rectangles identiques" (TN: means "identical Rectangles")
This was not the case when
we compared two rectangles
through the " == " operator.
In Java, the programmer of a class
is thus tasked to
define an "equals" method if we
wish to be able
to compare instances according
to particular criteria.
We will go back to this once
we have discussed
the inheritance and particularly
the predefined class "Object".
For now, just be aware that there
can be two possible headers
for the "equals" method.
The one we have just seen
where, in a given class called
"UneClass", we define the "equals"
method passing as agument
an object of the same type
as the class.
It is also possible to define
the "equals" method
passing as argument an Object-type
object.
We will go back to this
when the time is ripe.
This concludes our first chapter
on the fundamentals
of the object-oriented in Java.
In what comes next, we will
open another very important
chapter : the inheritance.