Hi, Professor Maneesha Ramesh,
currently the director for the
Amrita Center for Wireless Networks
and Applications (AmritaWNA),
also holds a position of Dean in
the National Program of Amrita University.
In this video, she will present
an affordable system for
landslide monitoring and early warning,
using wireless sensor network in India.
The system was developed in the context
of the European research project [Winsock]
initiated in 2006.
The pilots were conducted
in 2008 and 2009.
This whole work was given to us to look
into how wireless sensor network
can be used for disaster monitoring.
And the deliverables were
mainly focused on
looking into the lab setups
and developments.
So, our Chancellor has given us
an opportunity where she has,
she's a world renowned humanitarian
Amma.
She has asked us that this is
the opportunity for us
to save lives and serve humanity
and asked us to go and deploy
a system in the field.
That's how we were able
to deploy the system
in the landslide prone areas
and then work in the real time,
real world system.
Currently, the system is working
from 2009 onwards.
It was able to issue two times
the warnings,
2009, 2011 and even the latest is 2013.
And the system has a multi-level
warning system where it is able to
look into how it is progressing the slope
instability and based on that
it is able to give the warning to either
the researchers
or the government organizations
or the community
based on the intensity of the risk.
And the whole system consists of 150
geophysical sensors
which includes seven types of sensors
like raingauge, moisture sensor,
low pressure sensor,
tilt sensors, it has inclinometers,
it has rain gauges, geophones, etc.
And these sensors have been identified
in such a manner
that we're able to capture the real time
change in the slope stability.
These sensors help us to capture
those changes and with this data
are continuously collecting and using
wireless sensor network,
sensor node which is above ground,
whereas other sensors
are deployed beneath the earth.
There are sensors which have been deployed
almost 30 meters down, and you have
multiple sensors at multiple layers
with different parameters
has been considered in designing
the whole deep earth probe
which consists of the sensors.
These data are collected and transmitted
to our field management center in Munnar
and from there it is transmitted to
the control center at Amrita University.
There, the data is continuously checked
and evaluated using complex algorithms
which will help us to understand
the risk levels of the imminent landslide
and based on that, automatic warnings
are issued with the respect to
the risk levels which have been seen.
Now the major challenge in developing
such a system was that it needs
interdisciplinary knowledge.
Without interdisciplinary knowledge,
we cannot bring an affordable solution
which is capable of working in real time.
So we need to work together with
geologists, computer science,
mechanical engineers
to bring out the solution.
And while we were working,
we had to integrate
the different theories together,
knit them together, to bring out a result.
And based on that, one of the major things
which we were facing was how do
we make sure the system is functional
for a long time
because this is going to be a real time
monitoring in a hostile region.
You cannot go there and continuously
monitor and power the system.
So we were in a big challenge
of making sure in sustaining the energy
for the system.
This prompted us to develop
very unique algorithms, which were able
to capture the context and based on that
it was able to schedule
the different sensors to act and collect
the data at different rates
based on the changing context,
and make sure that even though they change
the amount of data they have collected,
it will make sure the reliability
of that data has not compromised
and we're able to give reliable warnings.
And once the warning is there,
the major thing there is, it was able
to communicate to the society directly
without any external, manual process.
It directly, automatically initiate
the different levels of warning.
And while building the system, one of
the major things which we have taken up
was providing awareness to the community
about the system.
So before even we started the projects,
first we had large scale of workshops
which is conducted for the police
and armed forces, for the administration
the district administration and for
the community, the Panchayat levels.
Where we have told them what is
the system, why are we doing,
how is it going to benefit them, and we
made them to participate and involve
in the development of the system.
So there were a lot of villages who have
taken part in developing
while we were developing the system
so they will help us
in maybe cutting the wood or cutting
the different materials we just needed
but by being part of it, they felt it
as their own system.
One of the major change which we
have seen in the community was
that the moment the rain comes,
they start waiting for our decision
because before the system was there,
what used to happen was
the whole set of population
used to actually evacuate themselves
during the monsoon season.
That is almost three months
they don't have job,
their kids do not have any education
and psychologically and emotionally
is it affecting their life.
And they used to go to different places,
stay there, and when the monsoon finishes
they come back because
they were afraid of the landslides
which can happen in the night,
which can take their life.
Because that's what happened in
the previous years in 2005 and earlier,
a lot of people have died because of that.
And after we had put in the system,
they believe in the system and even today
they stay in same place
without doing the evacuation.
They wait for our warning to come in
to take any decision.
So they believe in the system
and they have told us
that it is such a big relief for them.
Psychologically, emotionally
and economically it has helped them
to actually prosper in that place.
So, whenever we develop a system,
design, develop and deploy a system
which has to be used in real time,
one of the major considerations
we have to look into
is the robustness of the system,
the reliability of the system,
the scalability of the system
and how do you ensure
that these things are achievable.
So while developing this system
we have always looked into it
having redundant answers,
redundant notes which can cater to
the continuous data collection.
But we have brought in the redundancy
not only in sensor type,
we have even brought in redundancy
with respect to the number of data
you are going to sample and receive it
with respect to when you have
the different failures,
the expected failures, like node failure,
link failure and propagational effects
can cause loss of connectivity.
So we have come up with protocols
which will adaptively understand
how the climate is changing
and based on that which is going to be
my best neighbor which will be able
to capture my data
and send it with the minimum latency.
So always latency was another
major concern which we had to look into it
because you want issue
a real time warning.
So even though you may have thirty nodes,
you have to found out the best route
which will take through all the data
with minimum end to end and link delay,
with maximum reliability in the data.
And as you know that, these data had to
be sent during the worst climate scenarios
because the landslides happen
when there is heavy rainfall.
That's when you have the maximum problem,
and you will experience
the maximum propogational effects
for a wireless communication.
So we had used unique algorithms
or novel algorithms
which were capable to understand
the scenario ahead of time
so that they were able to constrain
and or they were able
to reduce the package loss
which may affect during such
harsh environment
and send the data through that.
And also, since these are like
low powered wireless sensor nodes
has been used for collecting data,
their transmission range is very less
and they get very easily affected
by the propagation effects.
So if you put it for a large scale area
this is going to create problems.
So what we had come up with
we came up with
a heterogeneous network architecture
where we have used zigbee Wi-Fi,
satellite network and
the cellular network to make sure the data
is transmitted at different levels.
So, we had a probe network
which consists of all
this intelligent wireless probe
integrated with deeper probes
consisting of all the sensors
which collects the data
and the probe gateway will transmit
all the data through the Wi-Fi network
to the field management center, and from
the field management center, the data
is transmitted to our university,
the control center
through satellite network and if there
is a fault coming up,
automatically from the satellite,
it will actually change
to cellular network
so that will be very able to make sure
that transmission is taken care of.
The other thing which we were
also looking into
was when you have these multiple networks,
you have to make sure how the traffic
is managed.
So now each of the networks,
the capabilities are different.
So based on that, automatically
this traffic is catered to
and we were giving priority of the data
which is necessary with the respect
to the change in the context.
That was another thing which we were
building into the whole system.
The third thing was,
whenever you have a data,
you have a problem of losing the data.
So, there was multi-level
of storage system
which was making sure that even if
we lose a link a one point,
whenever the link comes back
we're able to retrieve the data
which has been collected
and whenever a link fails, it will
automatically give the information
to the researcher, there
is a problem happening.
So the maintenance can be very quick.
And since it now has been running
for nearly now a decade,
we have learned, there was a lot of things
which we have learned in the whole process
and this helped us also looking into
how can we remotely configure the network,
how can we remotely trigger the network.
So we are able to actually control
each and every sensor in the field
when it has to sample, how much it has
to sample, what it is.
And also, the complete software system
has been developed at Amrita
and we made in such a manner that we're
able to remotely trigger the software
that means, the very time that you see
that there is a change which is needed
in a piece of software, we're able
to send the code from our University,
which is 300 kilometers away,
and then install it
in each and every wireless sensor node
which is there.
Rather than waiting for a risk to happen
and then do the management aspect
this is one of the system which has shown
it's capability to look into the changes
in the earth's system, understand
the changes and based on that changes
they're able to warn the people,
leading to reduction of risk in disasters.
And this technology has the capability
to be used in other disaster areas,
like flood monitoring,
avalanche, drought etc.
So we are extending this work
into other areas of deployment
so that multi-disaster probabilities
can be looked into it
and warning can be issued to reduce
the disaster risk.