Welcome again to our MOOC
on basic steps in magnetic resonance.
Today, we shall be talking
about spin relaxation.
That is the subject of Chapter 5
of Peter [Haugh's] book.
In order to observe NMR signals, as we
shall see in great detail in Chapter 6,
it is necessary to perturb
the magnetization
by applying radio frequency pulses.
Relaxation is simply the return
of the magnetization
to its equilibrium position
along the magnetic field.
Relaxation comes in two distinct flavors.
First, there is longitudinal,
also known as spin-lattice relaxation.
This is about populations.
Second, there is the transverse,
sometimes called spin-spin relaxation,
that is also known as decoherence
in the modern world of physics.
Like many other basic aspects
of magnetic resonance,
relaxation was first described
in the 1940s and '50s.
The names of [Maxness] and Bloch,
of Bloembergen, Purcell and Pound,
of [L. Ratfield], of Ionel Solomon,
of Anatole Abragam
and of Albert Overhauser
are closely associated
with these discoveries
and their rationalization.
As we shall see, relaxation--
that is, the return of the magnetization
to its equilibrium-- is driven
by rapid fluctuations
of magnetic interactions
such as dipole-dipole couplings
between the spins.
These fluctuations are due
to motions of the molecules.
Relaxation is a bit complicated
to explain, but, once understood,
is one of the most attractive aspects
of magnetic resonance.
Relaxation allows one
to determine structures
of all sorts of molecular assemblies,
ranging from very simple molecules
to large proteins and nucleic acids
and their complexes.
The opening picture of Chapter 5 starts
with this sphere here.
This sphere is not representative
of a nucleus or anything of the sort;
it is supposed to represent a spherical
or nearly spherical molecule.
The molecule that the authors
have in mind is in fact methane,
which has a carbon in the center
and of course four protons around it,
one of which is drawn
at the north pole of this sphere.
The idea is that as the methane
is moving about or tumbles about,
the vector that goes from the carbon
to the proton is reorienting
and in doing so describes
a chaotic trajectory.
It turns out that this motion,
which is known as rotational diffusion
in our business,
is responsible for relaxation,
hence the relevance
of this picture on the title page.
As you can see, Chapter 5 is subdivided
into a number of areas.
First of all, the authors will speak
about spin-lattice relaxation,
also called longitudinal relaxation,
because it is concerned
with the magnetization that is
along the static magnetic field,
also known as T1 relaxation,
following an abbreviation
invented by Felix Bloch himself.
One of the manifestations
of this longitudinal relaxation
is the Overhauser Effect, which
we shall discuss in some detail,
and which is very important
because the Overhauser Effect
enables us to determine structures
of molecules in solution--
in particular, of proteins
and nucleic acids.
Then, there is another chapter
about spin-spin relaxation,
which I prefer to call
transverse relaxation,
because it's about the magnetization
perpendicular to the magnetic field
and Felix Bloch called this T2 relaxation.
A short chapter on quadrupolar relaxation,
which I recommend that you read,
but there is not much
to say about it in pictorial terms;
and then there are two long chapters,
one that focuses on the applications
of relaxation to determine
molecular structure,
and another chapter
that focuses on dynamics,
more specifically
internal dynamics of molecules,
as studied by spin relaxation.
Chapter 5 of Peter [Haugh's] book
is concerned with spin-lattice relaxation.
I prefer to call it
longitudinal relaxation,
which is the current expression
in our laboratory,
or simply T1 relaxation,
which is the most common way
of describing it-- also in medicine,
because this quantity
is relevant for magnetic
resonance imaging,
and therefore known
to all radiologists around the world.
Spin-lattice relaxation
is concerned with populations,
and before we speak of populations
we have to remember
that if we have an isolated spin 1/2--
an isolated proton, for example--
then we have the energy,
which is different
for the excited beta state
than for the alpha state,
which is in fact the ground state.
For that reason, there are more spins
in the ground state,
that point parallel to the magnetic field,
than there are spins in the excited state.
Therefore, we should distinguish
the population of the alpha state
and the population of the beta state,
and we can define a quantity, Δn,
which is simply the difference
of the population in the alpha state
minus the population in the beta state.
You can see that in Boltzmann equilibrium,
n(α) is larger than n(β)
and consequently Δn should be positive.
Indeed, when it is in equilibrium,
this quantity is called Δn equilibrium.
In some magnetic resonance experiments,
we shall perturb the system
so that the populations
are actually equalized
at the origin of time.
Then, the spins will tend to fall back
from the excited state
into the ground state, and in doing so,
the quantity Δn, that is,
the difference between the populations,
will gradually recover
with an exponential law
so that it will ultimately converge
asymptotically to the value
at equilibrium.
It turns out that this law
that we see here
is expressed by this equation, so we have
the difference in populations
as a function of time,
ultimately we'll determine
by the equilibrium difference,
that is determined by Boltzmann's Law,
which depends on the field--
that is the space
in between the energy levels--
it depends on the gyromagnetic ratio,
it depends on the temperature.
Then, we have this little equation here
which simply describes the curve
that you see here, that is to say,
for T = 0 we simply have 1 - 1,
which is equal to zero,
and for T = ∞ this e^-∞ vanishes
so we have the equilibrium.
It turns out that this law,
in fact, is the solution
of a little differential equation,
which we have here,
which says that the time derivative
of the difference in populations
is proportional to the deviation
of the difference
from its equilibrium position,
and that the rate
that determines the speed
at which these things evolve is 1 / T1.
It turns out that 1 / T1,
which of course has units of seconds,
is also known as R1, and this is
the longitudinal relaxation rate,
and we should remember that this
is normally expressed in inverse seconds.
Please, do not confuse this with hertz,
because although it's the same quantity,
one should keep them separate
from frequencies in a spectrum.
Now, these expressions
could be perhaps recast
in a somewhat simpler form,
if we decide that we express
the longitudinal component
of the magnetization vector,
which is proportional to Δn--
that is to say, to the differences
we have seen upstairs
between the alpha and the beta states.
It turns out that it's now convenient
to define another quantity,
Δm(z), not to be confused
with this quantity here,
which is defined as m(z) at time T
minus m(z) equilibrium.
This quantity also evolves with time,
of course, and we can say
that Δm(z) as a function of time
is equal to its initial value at time zero
and now multiplied by -T / T1.
These equations are simply related
but it's perhaps easier to see
that all that we have to look at
is the distinction
between the asymptotic value
and the instantaneous value,
and it's this quantity which,
as you can see, decreases exponentially.
It turns out that the time constant T1,
which is the characteristic time
of this exponential recovery,
varies a great deal from case to case.
For example, T1 can be on the order
of a microsecond or so
for quadupolar nuclei--
which have very fast relaxation,
therefore also very broad lines--
such as, for example,
chlorine or bromine.
T1 might be on the order
of 100 milliseconds or so
for protons in large biomolecules
or T1 might be on the order
of a second for carbon-13
or nitrogen-15 in large molecules.
Then, in some cases-- in solids
in particular-- T1 might be
on the order of days
or even weeks in solids.
One example of that is the case
of lithium fluoride,
which, unfortunately, Professor Gorter
at the University of Leiden
in the Netherlands
chose for his very first attempts
to do NMR in solids in 1944.
He chose the crystal of lithium fluoride
where the T1 of the fluoride-19
is in fact on the order
of days or even weeks,
and for that reason,
once he saturated the populations,
they never recovered, and therefore he
couldn't see any signal at all.
Nevertheless, quite remarkably,
he wrote a paper about the failure
of an attempt to observe
magnetic resonance in bulk,
and the paper was published in Physica
and it is indeed a very remarkable paper
and therefore worth publishing.
Not many people can claim that.
Relaxation is driven
by motion, more specifically
by rotational motion in liquids.
Rotational motion is also known
by the experts as rotational diffusion,
as opposed to translational diffusion.
This can be illustrated by the case
of a methane molecule,
not in gas phase, but it would be
dissolved in some sort of liquid,
and then the methane molecule
could have a carbon-13 at its center,
and one of the four protons
could initially, at time zero, so to speak,
be aligned with the north pole
of this diagram.
That would be at time zero.
But, if we revisit the same molecule
some nanoseconds later--
in this case τ(c) is the correlation time
of the diffusional motion,
and if we wait one quarter of τ(c),
we'll see that there is a likelihood
that this C-H vector has changed
its position and reoriented itself
and now points somewhere else.
Most of the vectors still point
somewhere in the vicinity
of the north pole, but some of them
have already made
large excursions towards the equator.
If we wait four times longer--
that is to say,
a full correlation time, τ(c)--
then we see that the dots
are almost all over the place.
Although they're still clustered
near the north pole, that means
that many of the molecules have undergone
a tumbling of some sizable amplitude.
If we wait four times longer,
then we actually end up
with an almost isotropic distribution
of orientations-- that is to say
the C-H vector has forgotten
where it came from, except for a few
that are still clustered
near the north pole.
Now, this kind of rotational diffusion
is best described by considering
the scalar product
between the vector at time T
and the same vector a little bit later,
namely at time T + τ.
Now, we can normalize this by taking
the square of the amplitude
of that vector,
which we assume to have a constant length,
as indeed is quite reasonable
for a vector between a carbon
and its attached proton.
This, as it turns out,
is nothing but the cosine
of the angle-- which depends on the time τ--
the angle between
the z axis of this diagram--
that's the direction of the north pole--
and the instantaneous position
of the vector.
We can also take an ensemble average
of this quantity, so if we take
cosθ(τ) and we take an average
over all possible realizations
that we see here, then in fact we see
that in doing so we average
over many cosine waves.
There might be a very fast cosine wave
which goes like this--
that's a molecule which tumbles
very rapidly--
there might be a cosine wave
that's somewhat slower,
and there might be one
that hardly evolves at all.
If you add them up, and if you take
the average, you will find
that overall, the resultant
of these interfering beats,
as a function of time,
is actually a monoexponential function
which can be written -τ / τ(c).
This is not just t;
I should have written τ.
Now, the function that you see here--
we can actually give it a name.
We call it c(τ), and this
is typically called
a correlation function.
The correlation function
that was illustrated here,
starting with the simple scalar product,
refers to vectors,
or if you prefer, first-rank interactions.
In NMR, we are not really interested
in vectors; we are interested
in the time dependence
of dipole-dipole interactions,
and those transform
like second-rank interactions.
First-rank interactions,
like these vectors here,
look a little bit like p orbitals,
whereas second-rank interactions
look like d orbitals.
Whatever the details
of the mathematics, you can believe me
that one can also define
correlation functions
for second-rank interactions.
We define a correlation function
which has this type of time dependence--
that is to say it's
a monoexponential decay--
which, incidentally, is attributed
and associated with the name of Markov,
and, in fact, we cannot measure
the correlation function directly,
but we can transform this
into a so-called spectral density function.
The transformation of a function
that depends on time
into a function that depends on frequency
can be achieved with an operation
called a Fourier transformation.
We shall encounter
this Fourier transformation
in some detail in Chapter 6.
In Chapter 6, it's used for the analysis
of the signal so that we obtain a spectrum.
Here, it's used for a transformation
of the correlation function
into a spectral density function.
If the correlation function
of the second-rank interaction
has this particular form: -τ / τ(c),
where τ(c) is the correlation time
of the rotational diffusion,
then the Fourier transform
will give us a spectral density
which has a Lorentzian shape.
The Lorentzian function
is given here explicitly,
so you have τ(c) in the numerator,
and, importantly,
ω² times τ(c)² in the denominator.
Of course, we can draw such a function,
and it looks like this
if we do not use a logarithmic scale
but a normal scale.
If we have ω here, starting at zero,
then it turns out that the Lorentzian
will be looking something like this.
It turns out that the area
under this curve,
which we can, of course, express
as the integral from zero to infinity,
is nothing else but one,
which is actually the initial value
of the correlation function at time zero.
This unity here suggests
a probabilistic interpretation
of the spectral density function,
and we can say that if we consider
a certain interval, a certain surface
like this, then the partial area
of that surface corresponds
to the probability
that the motional diffusion
will be undergoing frequencies
between this lower limit
and this upper limit,
so let me call this i and j.
It turns out that a normal representation
as a function of ω of this quantity,
j(ω), it may be convenient
to replace the scale ω
with a logarithmic scale
where we have log of the ratio
of ω divided by some reference ω.
We can distinguish different regimes
τ(c) long, that is to say,
four times longer than 1 / ω0.
You see, the spectral density starts
at a high value and drops rather quickly.
We can have a correlation time
that is the inverse of ω0,
in which case we have
a sigmoid function like this,
or a much shorter correlation time,
in which case we have
a long plateau here,
and only a drop
of the spectral density
towards higher frequencies.
Spin-lattice relaxation
is driven by motion,
more specifically by rotational diffusion
of the molecules that we are looking at,
and, in fact, rotational diffusion
is quantified, or can be expressed,
in terms of this correlation time τ(c).
On this graph, the correlation time
runs from about a picosecond,
10^-12 second-- that is appropriate
for very small molecules
such as water-- to 10^-8,
which is ten nanoseconds--
that is appropriate for a protein
of a molecular weight
of about 10,000 atomic mass units
or 10 kilodalton,
as the molecular biologists like to say.
Now, you see that as a function
of correlation time, the T1,
that is, the longitudinal relaxation time,
initially drops, reaches a minimum,
and goes back up again.
This minimum is in the vicinity
of a correlation time
close to the inverse of ω0,
where ω0 is, in fact,
the Larmor frequency.
So, ω0 is 2π times μ0,
which is 2π times the gyromagnetic ratio
times the amplitude
of the applied magnetic field.
So, typically, if the applied
magnetic field is 9.4 tesla,
and if we are looking at protons,
then this will be
about 400 megahertz.
We're talking about frequencies--
this is expressed in hertz or megahertz,
this is expressed in radians per second,
but the ballpark is 400 megahertz,
so these are the frequencies
of molecular motion
to which NMR is sensitive,
depending on the field that we apply.
As a general rule, the relaxation rate 1,
which is the inverse of T1,
is proportional to the spectral density
taken at that particular value, ω0.
So, remember, the spectral density
is a function like this,
so this is ω, this is j(ω),
and somewhere on the scale,
we have the Larmor frequency
for the nucleus in the field
that we have chosen,
and at that frequency
the spectral density
achieves a certain amplitude.
We can, of course, move this around,
for example, by going to a higher field
or to a lower field, or by switching,
for example, from protons
to carbon-13 or to nitrogen-15, etc.
But, basically, for a given nucleus
in a given field, ω0 is fixed,
and we only measure this.
It turns out that the rate
is also proportional
to the square of the amplitude
of the local fluctuations
of the magnetic field.
In the particular case
of extreme narrowing-- that is to say,
if τ(c) is smaller than 1 / ω0--
that is to say, if we are
on the left side of this curve,
then we can have a more explicit form
for a case where the relaxation is driven
by the dipole-dipole interaction.
So, this A and X refers
to a pair of spins like this,
one spin A, one spin X,
both drawn like this.
There is a distance between them,
which we simply call r,
and there is a dipole-dipole interaction,
which in previous chapters was called rax.
This is the magnitude
of the dipole-dipole coupling.
It turns out that
in the extreme narrowing regime
where τ(c) is short,
the relaxation rate, which is 1 / T1,
is simply proportional to the square
of the dipole-dipole coupling
and proportional to the τ(c),
the correlation time
of diffusional motion.
We can replace this rax
by what it contains-- that is to say,
the square of the gyromagnetic ratio
of nucleus A, times the square
of the gyromagnetic ratio
of the other nucleus.
So, if the nuclei have
the same gyromagnetic ratio,
then it's simply γ^4.
Then, the most important part here
is that the rate is proportional
to the inverse of the sixth power
of the distance between A and X.
It is also proportional to τ(c),
but only in the regime
of short correlation times
which are shorter than the inverse
of the Larmor frequency.
This concludes part one of this chapter.
Thank you for your attention.