Welcome back to Part 3 of this chapter.
I have somewhat rearranged
the figures that Peter [Haugh] has chosen
to illustrate this chapter
by starting with an example
taken from proteins.
Indeed, the determination
of the structure of proteins
is one of the principal applications
of the Overhauser Effect today.
Recall that proteins are large molecules
and therefore tumble slowly
and therefore the Overhauser Effect
is predominated
by the w0 transition probability
between similar spin states,
that is to say, the flip-flop rate,
and the Overhauser Effect
leads to a loss in signal.
Now, proteins, as you know,
are basically polymers of amino acids.
Each amino acid contains
a number of protons
and these protons can be assigned
by methods that we
shall discuss in Chapter 6.
Since the Overhauser Effect
is predominantly driven
by w0 flip-flop terms,
it tends to attenuate signals.
So, the question really is,
if we irradiate selectively
a proton that is attached
to amino acid number a,
could it be that a proton attached
to amino acid number d
is partly attenuated
because of cross-relaxation,
because of the Overhauser Effect.
If that occurs, we must come
to the conclusion that amino acid a
must be near in space to amino acid d,
because the vehicle that allows
the Overhauser Effect to occur is related
to the dipole-dipole interaction,
which, as we have seen, decreases
as the sixth power of the distance.
So, we come to the conclusion
that it cannot be a linear chain
but in this case that amino acid a and d
must be close in space.
Likewise, we can do an experiment
where we irradiate a proton
belonging to amino acid b, and we find
that there is an attenuation of the signal
of the proton of amino acid f,
and we come to the conclusion
that b and f must be close
in space, and c and d, etc.
In fact, one can typically determine
hundreds or even thousands
of so-called distance restraints
by concluding that certain pairs
of amino acids must be
close together in space.
It is one of the merits of Kurt Wüthrich
at the ETH Zürich to have shown
that if you have a sufficient number
of such restraints, you can determine
a unique structure--
not just one structure
that satisfies all these restraints,
but there is only one good structure
that fulfills all of them
at the same time.
This is one of the many reasons
why Kurt Wüthrich
got the Nobel Prize in 2002.
Although applications to proteins
are very important nowadays,
we should not forget that we can also use
NOEs very fruitfully in discussing
stearyl chemistry in simple molecules.
This is a case where the simple molecule
here has been substituted
by introducing
a trimethylsilane group.
The question that these people ask
themselves is whether the silane group
is attached here at the top
or here at the bottom.
It's not so easy to distinguish these two
by any means that is known.
Of course, the molecular mass
is exactly the same
and many features resemble very much
between these two.
But, if we decide to irradiate
the resonances of the methyl groups
of the silane, then we see
in this case an enhancement
of this aromatic proton here
and an enhancement
of this aromatic proton here,
whereas, if we do the same experiment--
we saturate the transitions
of the methyl group attached to the silane
in this isomer, then we would only enhance
one aromatic proton.
So, the answer is very simply:
if there are two protons enhanced,
we're here, if there is
one proton enhanced, we're here.
We can confirm this by irradiating
this proton here,
which stands out in the spectrum,
and again, on the isomer
on the left-hand side, we would expect
an amplification of two aromatic protons,
whereas, in an isomer
on the right-hand side,
we would expect an amplification
of only one of the aromatic protons.
So, this is a very convenient way
of deciding where the new group
has been attached.
We don't necessarily have to use
Overhauser Effect to determine structures
and assign resonances.
Sometimes it can be useful
simply to measure
the T1 of carbon-13.
What we have here is adamantane,
a famous molecule,
and, in fact, there are
two different carbon-13 here--
this is in this position here
and in this position here.
The obvious difference is
that this one has one proton
attached to it, whereas this
has two protons.
Consequently, this one is exposed
to the fluctuating fields
due to the dipolar interaction
between itself and the attached proton,
whereas this is exposed
to more intense fluctuating fields
that stem from two neighboring protons.
Consequently, the relaxation
of this carbon is almost twice as fast
as the relaxation
of this carbon, or if you prefer,
the T1 of this carbon is
almost twice as short
as the T1 of this carbon.
So, this is a nice, elegant example
of how you can use T1 of carbon-13
in order to determine the assignment.
So, sometimes it's useful to measure
both the spin-lattice relaxation times,
or T1 relaxation times,
and the Overhauser enahancements
on carbon-13.
Take this molecule here,
where we see that the methine,
that is to say, the CH carbons
all have T1s on the order
of about two seconds or so,
whereas the quaternary carbons
have far longer T1s.
The obvious reason is that the protons
that are responsible
for the fluctuating fields
at the sides of these carbons, f to i,
are further away.
The reason is obvious,
namely that the protons
that are responsible for relaxation
of these carbons here
are further away, since the carbons
are quaternary, whereas these have
protons that are
directly attached to the carbons.
We can also see that
the Overhauser Effect here,
which, as you will recall,
η should be at best two,
which is the case here,
somehow vary from one situation
to another depending on the complexity
of the relaxation pattern.
For the quaternary,
the Overhauser Effects are very weak.
So, in some cases, T1 relaxation allows us
to get some rather subtle insight
in molecular behavior.
This, for example, refers to measurements
of the longitudinal relaxation
or spin-lattice relaxation of carbon-13
in these methyl-substituted benzenes.
In this case, the methyls
are not crowded together;
they can't touch each other,
they do not interfere with each other,
and as you can see, the T1 relaxation time
of those carbons is rather long.
In this case, however, there is
a steric hindrance
between the two methyl groups.
I wouldn't say that they touch
each other, but they interfere,
and this is sometimes known
as a cog-wheel interaction.
The idea is that the protons
on these two groups
almost touch each other, although that's
perhaps more a view of the mind.
Whatever the mechanism is,
it is striking that the relaxation
becomes much shorter.
Clearly, if we plot relaxation times
as a function of correlation time--
you will recall that there is a curve
that goes through a minimum--
in this case, we go
to shorter T1 relaxation
because the correlation time
of that cogwheel motion
is slowed down compared
to the correlation time
of the free motion
of the unhindered rotated methyl group.
There are some more exotic effects
which are worth understanding
to prevent misinterpretation
of many observations.
This paper here is concerned
with the T1 relaxation of carbon-13
in this rather strange
cigar-shaped molecule.
If you have a molecule like that,
then of course it's much easier
to have it rotate around this axis--
or the rotational diffusion coefficient
around that axis will be much faster
than the rotational diffusion coefficient
around a perpendicular axis.
So, there is in this case an anisotropy
of the rotational diffusion tensor.
In this case, the authors
have determined large differences
in T1 relaxation times, about one second
and about five seconds,
depending on if we are on the para
or on the ortho and meta positions.
We can explain that if we consider
the correlation time,
not of the overall tumbling
of the molecule, but the correlation time
that's relevant for the reorientation
of the carbon-proton vectors
that are either in the para position
or in the meta and ortho position.
If we recall this curve, it turns out
that for the para position,
we have a rather long correlation time--
remember that it takes
this slow tumbling here
to move that carbon--
whereas for the ortho and meta positions
we have a shorter correlation time,
and therefore a longer T1.
It is interesting that T1 relaxation
of carbon-13 gives us insight
not only into the molecular motion
but also the viscosity of the environment,
in particular, when the molecules
are capable of making
intermolecular hydrogen bonds.
So, take the simple case of decane.
In fact, there are only five
distinguishable carbons
because of the symmetry,
and they turn out to have
about equal T1s, and that's
not very interesting.
But, if we go to decanol, that is to say,
where the first carbon
has an OH attached to it, then we see
a vast range of T1 relaxation times.
The C1 carbon, which is really attached
to a neighboring carbon
through hydrogen bonds, has
a very short relaxation time,
and as we go down the chain,
the relaxation time
of the carbons increases.
There's also C20, which has
a smaller range of relaxation times.
Although there are no hydrogen bonds here,
the bulk of the molecule
is immobilized because of its inertia.
Relaxation is not limited to liquids.
It can also be studied in solids.
Indeed, Raymond Andrew
and his coworkers have done this
a very long time ago, in the '50s--
Raymond Andrew, who, by the way,
also invented magic angle spinning,
which is a remarkable invention
also studied relaxation
and line widths in solids
at low temperature.
Here, he studied an ordinary molecule
known as benzene and found
that if you freeze it, of course,
it looks like a crystal
or a powder or a glass,
but if you're in the temperature range
between 200 and 130 or so,
the lines are fairly narrow
because there is a motion, a rotation
around this six-fold axis in the solid.
But if you take the temperature
to go below 100 Kelvin or so,
you manage to freeze this rotation
and you have a true rigid solid,
at which point the line width
becomes much broader--
so, we're talking
about the proton line width.
Likewise, if you look at the T1 relaxation
of the protons in benzene,
you will find that there is a minimum
and that corresponds to a situation
where the rotational motion
has about the same frequency
as the Larmor frequency.
These minima can be shifted about
depending on the spectrometer
that you use for their observation.
So far, we have talked
about longitudinal
or spin-lattice relaxation
and in this chapter we now speak briefly
about transverse relaxation,
also known as spin-spin relaxation.
The main manifestation
of transverse relaxation
is that it leads to line broadening.
In fact, it's very simple: if that is
the dominant reason for the line width,
you just measure the line width
at half height and you find
that the T2 relaxation time
is inversely proportional
through this simple relationship.
It turns out that
the transverse relaxation rate,
called R2, which is the inverse
of T2, is made up
of two important contributions.
This first contribution we have seen
before, because that is also responsible
for longitudinal relaxation,
and it depends on the spectral density
at the Larmor frequency.
But, in T2 relaxation, there is
also a term that corresponds
to the spectral density
at the origin, at zero frequency,
or a lack of motion, if you prefer.
You will note that these two terms
both come with coefficients of one half,
so, if these two spectral densities are
equal, then you can lump them together,
but that is only the case
in extreme narrowing,
when the correlation time is much shorter
than the inverse of the Larmor frequency.
In general, when you go
from fast-tumbling molecules--
remember that 10^-12 seconds
is a picosecond, so that's characteristic
for water-- then T1 and T2 are equal,
and as we have seen before,
there is a minimum for T1,
and it goes back up again
as we go to large molecules.
That is not so for T2.
As you can see from this graph,
T2 inexorably decreases,
becomes shorter and shorter and shorter.
That means that the line widths
become larger and larger and larger,
and that means that, unfortunately,
it is impossible to observe
proton and carbon and hydrogen signals
of very large molecules
without doing very smart things.
So, to summarize Chapter 5,
we shall look at the bullets
that Peter [Haugh] has put
at the end of his chapter.
He says nuclear spins attain
thermal equilibrium--
that is to say, the Boltzmann equilibrium--
by a process known as spin relaxation.
Spin-lattice relaxation, also known
as longitudinal relaxation,
drives the populations
of the energy levels
back towards equilibrium.
Spin-spin relaxation, also known
as transverse relaxation,
results in NMR line broadening.
Spin-lattice and spin-spin
relaxation times
are known as T1 and T2.
Spin relaxation is caused
by the modulations of interactions
between spins due to molecular motions.
Dipolar couplings are rendered
time-dependent by molecular tumbling,
and they are a common source
of spin relaxation.
Dipolar couplings also cause
cross-relaxation, which leads
to the Nuclear Overhauser Effect.
T1s and T2s and NOEs give information
both on molecular structure and on motion.
Thank you for your attention.