Welcome to the second
part of chapter five
of basic steps in magnetic resonance.
One of the most important
manifestations of longitudinal relaxation
is the Nuclear Overhauser Effect.
Now, Nuclear Overhauser
Effects were postulated
by a theoretician,
Albert Overhauser, in 1953.
So initially, Overhauser
postulated that the effect,
that now carries his name,
would occur in solids.
And more specifically in conducting
solids, such as lithium metal.
He said that if we have lithium metal,
there are conduction electrons,
and some of them
have unpaired spins.
And therefore, there's an
EPR resonance and we can
saturate that EPR resonance
by microwave irradiation.
And Overhauser then predicted
that if you heat up
the electrons in this fashion,
you would cool down the nuclei
so that the amplitude of the NMR
transitions of lithium-6 or lithium-7
would actually be enhanced
by the irradiation.
This is a paradox, and many physicists
of those days did not believe Overhauser
until Charlie Slichter came along
and actually proved, experimentally,
that Overhauser was right.
And then it was discovered,
that this was not specific
to conducting metal,
but also possible in liquids.
And it is in fact, Ionel Solomon,
at the Ecole Polytechnique in Paris,
who proved this to be correct and also
developed the appropriate theory.
Now, in this chapter,
we shall not be concerned
with the case of metallic
conductors, such as lithium,
but focus on isolated pairs
of nuclei in a molecule
which is in a liquid, and the
molecule is tumbling
with a typical correlation function.
So, if we have two spins
emmersed in a magnetic field,
as we know, we have in states
where the two spins are
parallel with a magnetic field.
We have a state where
the two spins are anti-parallel.
And we have a case where
one spin is up and the other is down.
And of course, the reverse
is also possible.
So between these
four states, we know
that we have observable transitions.
In fact, we have two transitions
that belong to the X multiplet.
And we have two transitions
that belong to the A multiplet.
That, we discussed in the chapter
dedicated to scalar couplings.
But we also have longitudinal
relaxation processes.
And those go with rates,
which are called W.
And W in fact
is probability in German.
It comes from the word
Wahrscheinlichkeit.
And in fact, I believe that
it is Wolfgang Pauli
who used this W first to explain
relaxation in multi-spin systems
using the so-called master equation.
Now, this in fact is just
a transition probability.
And it turns out that you can
distinguish the transition probability
where a single spin,
namely spin A is flipping.
So from here to here,
only the first spin flips
from beta to alpha.
Whereas the second spin
doesn't move.
So this, we call the single quantum
probablity that A is flipping.
Likewise, this transition, is in
most cases, has the same probability.
Whereas these two transitions
are distinct in that it is now
spin X that flips but again,
with the single quantum flip.
And therefore,
we call this W1 of X.
More surprisingly, there is
also a probability, very important,
of a so-called flip-flop process,
also known as a zero quantum process
because there is no overall
absorption of any quanta.
One quantum is emitted
and one absorbed.
And therefore, we have zero quantum.
In this case, both spins A and X
participate, so this is known as a W0^AX.
And finally, there is also
the possibility that spins
that are in the beta-beta situation,
fall down all the way
to the ground state in the
alpha-alpha position.
And this is known as
a double quantum process
involving spins A and X.
So, the energy levels
for a homonuclear pair
of spin 1/2 nuclei, A and X, actually
hide a tremendous wealth of information.
If we wanted to see what happens
with the flow of the populations,
we have this so-called
master equation,
where we can write
the populations of these states.
For example, n-beta-beta,
n-beta-alpha, n-alpha-beta,
and n-alpha-alpha, we can
make a vector of those.
And we can say that there
must be some time dependence.
And then we can make
a matrix here, and look at
the deviations of these
different populations
from their thermal equilibrium.
So if these deviations vanish,
then we are in a stationary state
and nothing happens.
But if somehow, the deviations
are non-vanishing, then we shall have
a non-vanishing time derititive
of the populations driven
by the deviations from the
thermal equilibrium.
So all of these have delta nij
is equal to nij minus nij equilibrium.
And this matrix W is a four-by-four matrix
and you can easily fill
in the different elements here.
You should also know
that the diagonal elements
are equal to minus the sum over
the off- diag elements
on the same row, i different from j.
That means there's a conservation
of populations and if a population
is taken out of one of the levels
and put into another level,
overall, it is conserved.
So, with reference to
the matirix W of transition probabilities,
there are really only two that matter
to explain the Overhauser effect.
There is the double quantum probability,
where both spins A and X
flip at the same time.
And it turns out that this is
proportional to the spectral density
taken at twice the Larmor frequency.
So you will recall that
the Larmor frequency omega-0
would be two pi times
say 400 megahertz.
Then twice, that is 2pi
times 800 megahertz, etc.
The Overhauser effect is also
crucially effected by the flip-flop probability,
that is to say the zero
quantum probability.
And this turns out to be proportional
to the spectral density at the origin.
Or if you prefer, to the probability
that the molecule does not
undergo any rotational
motion at all.
So if we plot the spectral density
on a linear scale,
so not a logarithmic scale now,
then we see different behaviors.
A small molecule,
such as for example, H2O,
could rotate at very high speeds
without falling apart.
And in fact, it turns out
that the probability of rotational diffusion
is about equal at all sorts of
frequencies in the scale,
and we speak of a
white spectrum, an analogy
to the light that comes us
from the sun where all
colors are equally represented
so that their superposition gives
the feeling that the light is white.
While of course, these
are not visible colors.
These are radio frequencies.
But all colors are equally represented
and the spectrum is again white.
If, on the other hand, we look
at a large object,
such as a protein, for example,
then it is obvious that
it cannot undergo rotational
diffusion at very high frequencies
because it would fall apart.
It would sort of disintegrate
because of centrifugal forces.
And consequently, high frequencies
are essentially forbidden.
And the protein is compelled
to be content with slow motions.
And consequently, the likelihood
that it does not move at all,
which is represented by the
spectral density at the origin,
is much higher than it was
for the simple case of water.
Now we see that if we look
at the spectral density
at the Larmor frequency, for the
protein is not completely negligible,
but for it's much higher for water.
And if we look at twice
the Larmor frequency,
then it goes essentially to zero
for a large protein.
Whereas for water, it's still
about the same, regardless of frequency.
The dependence of the probability
W2, double quantum probability,
and of the zero quantum probability W0,
on the correlation time is as follows.
For the zero quantum, the flip-flop rate,
it is simply proportional to J of zero.
And it turns out
that this simply increases.
The bigger the molecule,
the slower the tumbling,
the higher that rate.
For W2, the situation is a bit
more complicated
because when we go from
very fast tumbling to slower tumbling,
W2 first increases, and then
reaches a maximum,
which is in the vicinity
of omega-0 equal to one over tauC.
And then, it drops again
to what's higher,
or to a slower tumbling or higher mass.
So clearly, there is a crossover point
where these two things cancel each other.
It turns out that there are
some analogies between
Overhauser effect, as we observe
them today in proteins,
and generally speaking,
in liquids and solutions,
and the Overhauser effect
that was originally predicted
to occur in conducting solids
such as lithium metal.
And what we see here
is the energy level diagram
of a two-spin system in a liquid.
And it turns out that if
the scalar coupling is zero,
then the two lines
of the X nucleus,
the two parallel transitions here,
are degenerate.
And in fact, we only see one single peak
at the chemical shift of spin X.
And likewise, the two transitions
of spin A are degenerate,
and we see only one line
at the chemical shift of spin A.
Now, we can instruct
our radio frequency source
in our NMR spectrometer
to selectively irradiate
the resonances of spin X,
the two superimposed resonances.
It turns out that if we do that,
we shall equalize the populations
across the X transitions.
And in fact, demagnetize those transitions.
And as a result, the signal
will vanish in all of these cases.
But if we look at what happens
with the A transitions,
in some cases, it is amplified,
as we see here.
So in other words, the peak
gets more intense.
Whereas, another case,
it's actually reversed.
This depends on the conditions.
And clearly, something very
peculiar happens
because you might expect
that irradiation of spin X
will warm up the spin system,
and therefore also saturate spin A,
but that is not the case.
And that is precisely the paradox
that Albert Overhauser discovered.
So the Nuclear Overhauser effect,
actually results from an interplay
between relaxation and irradiation.
And relaxation tends to drive
us back to the Boltzmann equilibrium.
Before we address the Boltzmann
equilibrium, we should look at
the ways of distributing the population
among the four states.
So, if we look at our two
two coupled spins again,
then we should focus attention
on the deviations of the populations
with respect to the demagnetized state.
If we have a demagnetized state,
then all populations, alpha-alpha,
and alpha-beta, and beta-alpha,
and beta-beta,
they would all have 0.25,
that's a demagnetized state.
And what we see here,
is these two white balls,
tell us that the beta-beta state
is depleted, with respect
to the demagnetized state.
Whereas, the alpha-alpha
state is populated
more than in the
demagnetized condition.
And if we do some accountancy,
we see that between the alpha-alpha state,
which has two black symbols,
and the alpha-beta state,
which has no symbol at all,
there is an advantage
of two minus zero, which is 2-delta.
The same is true here.
And it turns out the same
is true here.
We have zero minus minus two,
which is also plus two.
Now, the next thing
that we have to do
is that we have to saturate
the X transitions.
So here again, we have
the thermal equilibrium
with a depleted beta-beta state,
and the populated alpha-alpha state.
And if we now started
irradiating the X transitions,
that means that we deliberately
equalize the populations here.
So basically, what we do
is we promote one of these black balls
to the upper level.
And likewise, we also saturate
these two transitions,
which means that we basically
bring down one of these white balls
from the top to the beta-alpha level.
So at this point here, once
the saturation has been achieved,
which can be done
in a few milliseconds or so,
then we have a new distribution,
but we still have the simple difference
of 2-delta between this level
and this level.
That's plus one minus minus one.
Or here again, plus one,
minus minus one.
These transitions of spin A,
have not been changed.
Ok, so we have discussed
that we can go from
the thermal equilibrium situation here
to this partly saturated state,
where the X transitions
have been saturated.
That is to say, that their
population differences
have been annihilated
by irradiation.
Whereas, these have been preserved.
Now the Overhauser effect
comes about because we have
flip-flop of flip-flip transitions.
The probability here W0,
that's the zero quantum flip-flop transition
will tend to go from
right to left
in that the excess population
that we have in the alpha-beta state
will tend to fill up the deficiency
of the population on the beta-alpha state.
At the same time, of course,
this horizontal process
has no effect whatsoever
on the populations
of the top state and the bottom state.
And consequently, these are preserved.
Whereas, the central states are depleted.
One of the consequences of this
is that the difference in populations
between plus one minus zero
is now just 1-delta.
Whereas, it was two 2-delta here.
Whereas, in this case, the population
difference is zero minus minus one,
which is also plus one 1-delta,
so, instead of 2-delta.
In other words, we see an attenuation
of the difference in populations
across these transitions
compared to what they were
before the W0 process set in.
A more puzzling aspect occurs
when the double quantum probability,
W2AX is dominant.
We shall see that this
is only possible for small molecules.
So this is a pathway
for small molecules.
Whereas, this pathway was
predominant for large molecules,
such as proteins, for example.
As we know, small molecules
have a large flip-flip probability, W2,
and that means that there
will be a tendency for the populations
to go from the top level
to the bottom level.
Now you might say, "There is already
a difference in populations."
"So why should we go to
a larger difference?"
Well, the reason is that
in thermal equilibrium,
there was indeed a larger difference.
We had difference
of plus two minus minus two,
which is four, from 4-delta
between these two extreme transitions.
And since, relaxation tries
to return to thermal equilibrium,
the result of W2 relaxation
is to increase the deficit here
from one white ball
to two white balls.
And to increase the population
from one black ball to two black balls.
Now this is quite remarkable because
now we see that the difference
in population across
the A transition here
is plus two minus minus one,
which is 3-delta.
And likewise here, it is
one minus minus two,
which is 3-delta again.
So now we have, with respect
to the 2-delta difference here,
we have an amplification here.
Amplification of the difference
in populations,
and also of the signal
that we shall observe.
Whereas here, we have
a simple attenuation.
So the Nuclear Overhauser effect
is often described
by this perimeter eta here,
which is defined
as the intensity of the signal
that we observe in the presence of
rf irradiation minus the intensity
that we observe in a normal spectrum,
normalized by the intensity
that we observe in the normal spectrum.
And it turns out, that if
we have an amplification,
then eta will be 0.5, this is
typically the case
for a homonuclear system
in a small molecule.
But if there's an attenuation,
then we can go all the way to -1,
and that is the case for
slow tumbling in large molecules.
We're talking here about
a steady state Overhauser effect
which is somewhat distinct
from the transient Overhauser effect
that we shall exploit
in micromolecules.
Now it turns out that such things
also exist in heteronuclear systems.
And in that case, eta is
1/2 of the ratio
of the gyromagnetic ratio
of the spin X
that we irradiate, divided by
the gyromagnetic ratio
of the spin that we observe.
It turns out that there
are Overhauser effects
in heteronuclear systems.
In which case, this parameter eta,
is equal to 1/2 of ratio of the gamma,
the gyromagnetic ratio of spin X
that we irradiate, saturate,
divided by the gamma,
the gyromagnetic ratio
of the spin that we observe.
So, if we consider carbon-13
as an observable nucleus,
then the eta that we obtained
when we irradiate the protons
would be equal to 1/2
of the gamma of the protons
divided by the gamma
of the carbon-13.
And this is about 1/2 of roughly
four and this is about two.
And consequently, when you
look at the equation, we have
a three-fold enhancement because
the amplitude goes from one to three.
But be careful, if we look at
other nuclei, for example, nitrogen-15,
which is very popular in biomolecules,
then the eta that we obtained
when irradiating the protons
is equal to the same ratio.
And it turns out that
this is 10/-1, because
the gyromagnetic ratio
of nitrogen-15 is negative.
So this turns out to be
about -5.
So this means that if we have
a nitrogen-15 spectrum
with a small positive peak,
if we do not irradiate the protons
we may observe a large negative peak
if we do irradiate the protons.
Which is rather surprising.
In fact, this is one thing
that I didn't believe myself
until I did the experiment
many years ago.
We should remember, by the way,
that the Overhauser effect
is not always 100% efficient.
And sometimes we get
less then the predicted maximum,
and sometimes we get exactly zero
if we stick halfway between
positive and negative.
This case, I forgot to say,
that the carbon-13 spectrum
goes from this to about this,
which is an enhancement of a factor three.
That is very commonly observed
and indeed very welcome.
This concludes part two
of this chapter.
Thank you for you attention.