This is Sami Jannin of the EPFL.
Welcome to our MOOC
on basic steps in magnetic resonance.
Today we shall be talking about
dynamic nuclear polarization
and this is going to be
the second part of this chapter.
Today, we shall be talking about
the electron spin system
and the nuclear spin system
that are the two key players
in our DNP experiment.
So what about
the electron spin system?
Let's take our nitroxide molecule
that has a free radical sitting
on the N-O bond.
Let's first assume that
this nitroxide molecule
is distributed in a matrix,
and that all these nitroxide molecules
have exactly the same orientation.
Well, in this case, one might observe
a very narrow ESR line,
because all the electron spins
will have the same frequency.
While in reality,
the frequency of the electron spins
strongly depends
on the orientation of the molecule
with respect to the field: B-Zero.
So that in a real experiment,
where all the molecules
are distributed randomly
in the matrix [of the gas].
The ESR spectrum is not any more
a narrow line, but a broad line
and each of these frequencies here,
correspond to a certain orientation
of the molecule
with respect to the field.
There is another mechanism
that broadens the line
that is the hyper-fine coupling.
In this particle or example
in this nitroxide molecule,
there is a coupling
between the electron-- here,
and the nitrogen
that has a spin-- Spin One,
and this coupling gave rise
to a splitting
that you can observe here,
on this spectrum.
These two broadening mechanisms
are usually called
inhomogeneous broadening.
There is another broadening mechanism
that we call dipolar,
and that depends
on the coupling between electrons
from one molecule and the other molecule.
This broadening mechanism
is usually called homogeneous.
So most of the broadening is due to the
inhomogeneous broadening in our case.
So is due to the Zeeman interaction
and the Hyperfine interaction.
And for this nitroxide molecule,
the broadening is typically
on the order of hundreds
of megahertz per Tesla.
So, say you have an
inhomogeneously broadened ESR line,
so instead of having
very well defined energy levels,
this population
sitting on one level- here,
and one level- here,
in reality you have a distribution
of the energy level
that is quasi-continuous.
And the population distribution
amongst this energy level is, of course,
described by the Boltzmann Law.
Now, what happens if you shine microwave
on one of these transitions?
Well, we are going to see
that what might happen
is that you're going
to dig a hole in the ESR line.
So you are going
to saturate the electron spin,
at well-defined frequencies.
Now, looking back at our energy levels
and population distribution,
what happens is that by shining microwave
at a specific transition frequency,
for example, here--
you are going to tend to equilibrate
the distribution of population
among those two energy levels, here.
And that's what digging a hole, means.
Now, I told you that there was
a third broadening mechanism
that was also very important,
and that is called
the homogeneous broadening.
The width of the homogeneous broadening
depends on the strength
of the dipolar coupling
between the electron spins,
which grows with
One over R - to the power of three.
R being the distance
between the electron spins.
And it turns out that this broadening
is usually much weaker
than the homogeneous broadening
in the case of nitroxide radical.
It is about 0.2 megahertz
per millimolar of radical.
So if we increase
the concentration of radical,
you're going to decrease
the distance between the electron spins
and this is going to increase
the widths of the homogeneous broadening.
What is the consequence
on the saturation behavior
of the ESR line?
Well, now when you are going to shine
microwave at a specific transition,
you're going to hit
a specific electron spin
that has the right frequency
and the right orientation,
but thanks to the dipolar coupling
this saturation may be transferred
to other electron spins by spin diffusion.
So what happens is
that when you shine microwave
at a specific frequency
this perturbation
actually might propagate
across the ESR line
by what we call spectral spin diffusion.
There is another
very important phenomenon
that happens at the same time.
That is the T-one relaxation.
So at the same time
you try to saturate your ESR line
with microwave and you try
to equilibrate the population
amongst the energy level,
and at the same time this perturbation
tends to travel across the EPR line
by spectral spin diffusion.
The T-one relaxation
tends to bring back the population
towards the Boltzmann distribution.
So the saturation of the ESR line,
which is a crucial step in DNP,
is a competition between saturation,
spectral spin diffusion-
that propagates the perturbation
across the line and T-one relaxation
that tends to bring back
the distribution of population
towards the Boltzmann distribution.
Now, let's talk about
the nuclear spin system.
So we have discussed the presence
of free radical molecules in the sample,
but these free radicals,
that are usually present
at the millimolar concentration,
are surrounded by molecules
that contain nuclear spins.
For example, proton spins.
In our example, we chose to talk about
the pyruvate molecule
that contains methide group here,
with three protons.
So, the first important feature
in this nuclear spin system
is that the polarization
will possibly redistribute
amongst those spins
by nuclear spin diffusion.
So in a sense, all these molecules
in the solid state
at low temperature,
might talk to each other,
and the polarization might be transferred
from one molecule to the other.
To give a pictorial idea
of what spin diffusion does,
let's take just a line of spins--
so we have a line, here, of molecules,
and we just assume
that at a certain time
some molecules have their spin
polarized down,
and some molecules have their spins
polarized up.
So that when we look at the polarization
of the proton spins along this line,
we see a big step function, here,
with a negative polarization, here,
and a positive polarization, here.
So what spin diffusion is going to do
is, that, it is going to re-distribute
the polarization in such a way
that the polarization is homogeneous
on a microscopic scale.
Now, if by any means,
you manage to polarize molecules
on this side of the line,
with microwaves or with DNP,
what spin diffusion is going to do,
is it's going to propagate
this polarization through the line,
in such a way, that you might end up with
almost all the spins
polarized through space.
This spin diffusion process
is characterized by a diffusion constant.
And in a static solid at low temperature,
this diffusion constant
is about 10 to the 5 angstrom/second.
So that the length
that the polarization can travel,
is proportional to
the square root of D times the time.
That means that if you wait
about a second,
your nuclear spin diffusion
might lead you to the transportation
of your polarization
over typically, 10's of nanometers.
Now, in a typical DNP sample,
the average electron-electron distance
is typically on the order of
a few nanometer
when you have about
10's of millimolar concentration.
So it is important here to realize,
that the nuclear spin diffusion,
is going to propagate the polarization
on a scale which is already larger
than the electron-electron distance,
within only a second.
So now, let's take our line,
of nuclear spins in our pyruvate molecule
and let's add an electron spin,
here, a nitroxide.
So what we said before
is that the nuclear spin diffusion
might transport the polarization,
especially from one molecule
to the other.
Now, let's see how this is working.
Let's assume here we have a spin
with a high polarization,
and here, a spin with a low polarization,
and let's assume,
that you have a dipolar coupling
in between those two spins
that is going
to be enabling spin diffusion.
Well, as you can see, the spin diffusion
is going to drive transition
between this energy level
and this energy level,
which is an
energy conservative transition
and will tend
to equilibrate the population
amongst those two energy levels.
But now, if we get closer
to the electron, what might happen
is that the coupling between the electron
and the nuclear spin
is going to shift the transition energy
of the nuclear spin
via the dipolar coupling.
And in these conditions,
if we consider the coupling
between this nuclear spin
and this nuclear spin,
we see that the zero-quantum transition
is no more an energy
conservative transition.
So in a sense, the polarization
cannot flow anymore
from one molecule to the other
because of the effect
of the electron spin
on the energy transition
of these nuclear spins.
So what we usually say,
is that there is a region of space
around the electron spin
where the diffusion is stopped.
The spins that are inside this space
are said to be quenched
or bleached because
their frequencies are shifted away
from the usual NMR frequency
and the limit between this area of space
and the bulk area of space
is usually called the diffusion barrier.
And this diffusion barrier usually
has a radius of about half a nanometer.
So in our sample,
you have electron spins;
around these electron spins
you have a diffusion barrier,
so that the nuclear spin inside
won't talk to the nuclear spin outside,
but most of the nuclear spins
are sitting in a space
where the dipolar interaction
with the electron is relatively weak
and we call this the bulk nuclear spins.
In a typical DNP experiment,
the ratio between the volume of bleached
or quenched nuclear spins
with respect to the total volume
is typically only a few percent.
It is interesting to note
that the highest probability
to have a DNP transition
is at the diffusion barrier
where the coupling between the electron
and the nuclear spin
is the highest,
but where still spin diffusion
between nuclear spin is allowed.
So, there are two very important questions
that I want to ask
and try to give a general answer here;
is nuclear spin diffusion efficient?
Well in principal, yes.
It can propagate polarization
over a scale that is larger
than the electron-electron distance
within a few seconds, unless,
your nuclear spins are very diluted,
so if your concentration of nuclear spin
is on the order of micromolar,
you might run into trouble.
The second thing is;
is the bleaching important?
In principal, no, there are only
a few nuclear spins that are bleached,
unless your electron concentration
would be very high,
in the hundreds of millimolar range.
So today we talked about
the electron spin properties
and we saw that the saturation
of the ESR line
was involving spectral spin diffusion,
also T-one relaxation,
and at the end it was
a kind of competition
between those two effects.
We discussed about
the nuclear spin properties
and we saw that nuclear spin diffusion
was a very important feature
that would propagate the polarization
across the whole sample in space
and we talked about the interaction
between the electron and the nuclear spin.
We introduced the concept
of a diffusion barrier,
and of bleaching and quenching.
Thank you for following our MOOC
on basic steps in magnetic resonance.
This was the second part of a chapter
dedicated to Dynamic Nuclear Polarization.