Welcome back to our MOOC
on basic steps in magnetic resonance.
Today we shall talk about
dynamic nuclear polarization
and this is going to be
the third and last part
of this chapter.
Many free radical molecules
can in principle be used
for dynamic nuclear polarization.
Here I give you four examples.
The Trityl free radical
molecules with an electron
based on the carbon, here,
the BDPA molecule,
the Galvinoxyl molecule,
and the Tempol molecule.
It is interesting to see
that these molecules
have very different ESR spectra
because the electron
has a different coupling
with surrounding nuclear spins
but also because it has different
J anisotropy.
We can separate these radicals
in two classes,
those with broad ESR line,
such as Tempol and Galvinoxyl
and those with narrow ESR lines
such as BDPA and Trityl radicals.
These lines are broad or narrow
with respect to nuclear
Larmor frequencies.
For example, the Trityl and BDPA radicals
are narrow with respect to the proton
Larmor frequency
and are on the order of the carbon
number frequency.
Whereas, the Tempol
and the Galvinoxyl radicals
have ESR lines that are very broad
compared to the carbon frequency
and are on the order of the proton
Larmor frequency.
And because they have different
ESR features,
they're going to yield
different DNP mechanisms.
So, let's start with the simple
case of a narrow ESR line
of very dilute radicals
that don't have much dipolar couplings
between each other.
This is most likely to yield
what we call the solid effect.
So, in order to understand
what the solid effect is about,
let's consider an electron spin
with a narrow ESR line--
here, the Trityl radical--
coupled to a proton
of a Pyruvate molecule.
Here, see, the four energy levels
of this coupled two-spin system.
And you can already see
that there is a large
electron polarization
across these transitions.
Whereas, the nuclear polarization,
across these transitions,
is close to zero.
So what we're going to do now,
is going to shine
microwave frequency
at a low frequency
and we're going to increase
this frequency until something happens.
The first thing that's going to happen
is that we're going to match
what we call the Zero Quantum
Transition, here.
By matching the Zero Quantum Transition,
we are going to drive
transition of population
so as to equilibrate the population
amongst those two energy levels.
And this is going to yield
a net nuclear polarization
across this transition
and across this transition here.
Looking at the ESR spectrum, here,
and at the microwave frequency, here,
we're going to sweep through
these different values
until we reach the Zero Quantum
Transition, here.
And this is going to yield
a net positive proton polarization
that will look exactly like
the ESR spectrum
but will be shifted by the proton
Larmor frequency.
Now, if we keep on
increasing the frequency,
we're going to hit another transition
that is the electron frequency.
By doing so, we're going to drive
transition of population
amongst those energy levels
so as to equilibrate
the populations there.
So, looking again at the ESR spectrum
and at our frequency,
we're going to sweep
right on the ESR resonance.
and we're going to saturate
the electron resonance.
This is not going to yield
nuclear polarization
in this particular case.
Now, we can keep on
increasing the frequency
until we hit another
transition that is called
the double quantum transition, here.
And by doing so, we're going to again
drive transition of population
among those energy levels
until we equilibrate the population here.
And this is going to yield
a net negative polarization
on the nuclear spins
along these transitions.
So again, looking at our spectrum,
we keep on increasing the frequency
and we're going to observe
a negative lobe
with a negative proton polarization.
What is interesting to see here
is that the distance between
this positive and negative
DNP enhancements are separated
by two times the Larmor
frequency of the proton.
Now, say you have a broad ESR line
with respect to the proton frequency,
but you still have very dilute
electron spins,
such as nitroxide radicals.
In this particular case,
we might observe
a differential solid effect.
So, the effect is very similar
to the resolved solid effect
that we've seen before.
The difference is that
instead of yielding a very narrow lobe,
we're going to yield a broad lobe
at different microwave frequencies.
And in the same way we managed
to yield a negative lobe,
we're going to do the same
in a broad manner.
The result is that instead of having two
well-resolved lobes
in the positive and negative side,
we're going to have a superposition
of constructive
and destructive DNP effect
that will give rise
to a differential positive
and negative DNP lobe.
Again, the difference in frequency
between the maxima
will be at about two times
the nuclear Larmor frequency.
So, now, if we look
at another nuclear spin,
such as carbon-13, instead of a proton,
the difference between
those two maxima
will shrink down to two times
the carbon-13
Larmor frequency.
So, the solid effect is a pure
electron nuclear spin process
that does not require
electron-electron interactions.
It is a second-order
microwave-driven transition
that has, therefore,
a fairly low probability
and, therefore, usually requires
a high amount of power.
Now if one has a broad ESR line,
such as Tempol,
and, in addition to that,
has a moderate electron-electron coupling,
due to a moderate electron concentration,
one can observe the cross effect.
So, starting from one single electron
and one single transition
with a high polarization,
and then bringing in again
another electron spin,
we see that our spin system
can be described by four energy levels
and that those two transitions
can be described by the electron
frequency of the spin one,
omega electron-1, here,
and the electron frequency
of the spin two,
omega electron-2, here.
Now, what happens
when you drive microwave
precisely at the electron-1 frequency?
Well, you're going to
tend to saturate this transition
and equilibrate the distribution
of population
among these energy levels here.
At the same time,
T-1 is going to tend to drive back
your population
to the thermal equilibrium,
which is here,
the highly-polarized state.
And now, if you consider a coupling
with a third spin,
for example the proton spin
of this Pyruvate molecule,
your energy level system
will be described now
not by four, but by eight energy levels.
If by chance the nuclear Larmor frequency
is about equal to the frequency
of the electron-2 minus the electron-1,
something interesting might happen.
So, again, let's shine a microwave
on the electron spin 1
and let's saturate those transitions.
So, again, one way to relax now
would be by T1 relaxation.
But here, since we have a coupling
with a third spin--
with this nuclear spin--
you can see
that those energy levels
have exactly the same energy.
So, there is a transition here,
that we call cross effect,
that might be allowed.
If this happens,
population might flow freely
from this level to this level of energy
while T1 will of course tend to bring down
the populations to the ground
polarized state.
So, if you think carefully,
by saturating here,
we start to populate those energy levels.
The cross effect tend to bring
some of the population
on this energy level,
and the T1 relaxation
tend to bring those spins here
down to the ground state.
And if you do that on the long time-scale,
longer than T1,
longer than the cross effect time,
you might end up with all your population
distributed on those two energy levels
which would result in a very high
nuclear polarization
along these transitions.
Now, we can look at that
from another angle.
Here you see the population
distribution on all the energy levels,
according to Bolzmann's law,
in a highly-polarized state.
When we shine a microwave
at a specific frequency,
we tend to equilibrate
the distribution of population
along this transition here.
Now, again, we have a nuclear
Larmor frequency here
that matches the difference in energy
between these electron spins here
and those electron spins there.
And cross effect will tend to
redistribute population
amongst those energy levels here.
And this is going to create a net
proton polarization.
So, again, we can look at our ESR spectrum
and our microwave frequency,
and we're going to change
the microwave frequency
until we see here a positive
proton polarization.
And if we keep on increasing it,
we will yield a negative proton
polarization here.
And what's interesting
in this cross effect
is that the difference in frequency
between the two maxima here,
positive and negative,
is about the proton Larmor frequency.
So, again, if we look at C-13
instead of proton spins,
we'll see that
this is going to shrink down
to the Larmor frequency of the Carbon-13.
So, cross effect is an electron-electron
nuclear spin process.
It requires moderate
electron-electron interaction.
and involves, simply,
allowed electron spin saturation.
So, in summary, we have
introduced the solid effect
that gives rise to well-resolved
positive and negative DNP lobes
separated by two times
the Larmor frequency.
We've introduced
a differential solid effect
that gives rise to non-resolved
positive and negative lobes,
also at the nuclear Larmor
frequency times two.
And we have introduced the cross effect
that requires some electron-electron
dipolar interactions
and that give rise to a DNP
microwave spectra
with positive and negative lobes
separated by simply
the nuclear Larmor frequency.
Thank you for following our MOOC
on basic steps in magnetic resonance.
This was the third
and last part of our chapter
dedicated to dynamic nuclear polarization.