Hello and welcome to the second module
of this MOOC on protected areas management
in Africa.
This module covers the specific topic of management
planning for protected areas.
So, the module this week is structured as
follows:
the first lesson will cover
actual planning for protected areas,
its purpose, how you prepare it, how you implement
it,
how you assess its effectiveness, who needs
to be involved.
The second lesson will look into planning
for networks
or for protected area systems.
It raises the same questions, but on a different
scale:
at the national level, regional level or even
at an office level.
In the third lesson, we will examine the impact
of these different planning methods:
the results we obtain and the progress we
make.
The fourth lesson will fit the topic of protected
areas
into a wider context,
that of land use planning:
what they add and what they endure,
how they interact, what to do so that everything
works.
The fifth lesson will specifically deal with
the topic
of transboundary protected areas.
They come with a whole other level of planning
and of stakes at play.
The last lesson will cover our weekly agreement
and we will talk again
about the biological diversity convention.
We will particularly focus on the priorities
it currently highlights
that are the Aichi targets.
Finally, we will briefly summarise
the important aspects mentioned this week
through a short animation
and we will give you the information for this
module's assignment.
That's it.
We hope you have an excellent second week
with us.