(birds chirping and car engine)
(camera clicks)
Good Morning!
Today, our course will be on the planning
of protected areas.
the book to consult as reference,
will be the guidelines of IUCN for the management
planning of protected areas,
edited once again by the world commission
of protected areas.
You can also find a lot of information in
our study of management plans
in french-speaking Africa on our website papaco.org.
Today, two colleagues from IUCN PAPACO will
help me.
It's Bora Masumbuko, who is based in Ouagadougou,
Burkina Faso,
and Lacina Kone who is based in Niamey, Niger.
Both have good experience in the preparation
of management plans.
So the first question that we are going to
ask ourselves,
is to know what this management plan is for.
The management plan, is a document that helps
to guide the Manager
on how he should manage his protected area.
It documents and identifies the values to
preserve in the protected area.
It clearly establishes the goals that must
be achieved
and identifies the actions that must be in
place to achieve those goals.
It is a document that allows to plan in time
and is interested in the present and future.
It allows to respond concretely to the following
questions:
What will be done?
How will it be done ?
and when will it be done?
It is therefore an essential tool to help
the Manager.
And for this, it must remain concise and clear.
The plan is a useful tool
to improve the management of the protected
area.
it allows a better use of financial and human
resources,
as it allows to plan activities in time,
therefore the cost and the need of human resources
are equally evaluated.
Finally - and this is very important-
the management plan increases the manager's
responsibility,
in obtaining results.
It also improves the communication between
all stakeholders,
involved in the management of protected areas.
OK, all that is easy to understand.
So, what are the principles that should guide
us
when we wish to create a management plan for
a protected area
and if possible, of course, a very good plan.
To develop a management plan with efficiency
and transparency,
it is essential to include a number of principles.
First of all, all the stakeholders have to
participate,
given that their level of involvement may
have an impact on the success
of the planning exercise.
At first, one must identify all of the participants
involved
then approach them with transparency to involve
them in planning.
Next, the documents which will be use as the
source of information.
should be elaborated in a clear accessible
manner
and should take into account cultural or linguistic
constraints.
Furthermore, communication is a key element
when approaching stakeholders,
because they must perceive that they are an
integral part
of the planning process.
They must be considered as partners, and not
obstacles
of nature conservation.
Thus, it is important to respond positively
to meeting requests,
to consider all points of view,
and to give each party time to formulate their
opinions.
If it becomes necessary,
undertake some research before taking a decision
that is not consensual
and then return the result to interested parties.
Regardless of the complexity of the management
plan,
it needs to apply those simples principles
to guide the planification process
and to guarantee that eventually the management
plan will be a useful document
accepted by all.
We know now what the plans are for
and we know the principles of their preparation.
Let's see the steps to follow.
When we are consulting different plans
we see that they do not all contain the same
informations
or, are not presented the same way.
This is not a serious issue.
To help elaborate those documents,
IUCN published guidelines
for management planning of protected areas.
This document presents, in 13 steps,
how to prepare such a plan.
Those 13 steps can roughly be summarized as
follows:
First of all, the pre-planning phase,
data collections and initial fieldwork;
then comes the evaluation of data
and information on the ressources
to form sufficient arguments
that will help in the identification of the
protected area values;
then we move on to identifying pressures and
threats
that the values previously defined are facing,
and we identify constraints
of the protected area territory.
From this analysis of values,
and the number of threats they are facing
we deduct a long term vision for the protected
area
as well as short-term management goals
and the activities helping to achieve those
goals,
i.e activities that will stop the threats
to resources
and to heritage values of the protected area.
It is then, that we write
a first draft of the plan we want to launch
and make it available to all the different
stakeholders
for a public consultation.
The plan can then be rightfully approved and
endorsed.
We must understand the development of a management
plan
is an evolving process.
In general, a plan is designed for a period
of 5 to 7 years
and is regularly revised
to adapt the management of the protected area
to the realities of the field.
All the steps in the management plan are important,
but we will spend time on some key steps of
the process.
The pre-planning is the step that allows the
preparation
and the logistics for the development of the
management plan.
It must lead to the establishment of the terms
of reference,
of the budget and method to follow.
It also allows helps to identify the team
for the preparation of the plan
- this is a crucial point,
because too often it comes down to entrusting
the work to an outside expert,
while it is essential that managers themselves,
the actors of the area themselves, feel involved
in this work.
Obviously, an outside expert can be an added
as support,
but should never be the main leader in the
planning.
Within this phase of pre-planning
we also identify a provisional timetable
for the process of preparation of the management
plan
up to its approval and then we make it public.
Step 3, is about the protected area’s values.
This assumes that we are engaged in the process
and have already collected data on the protected
area.
Then what is the heritage value of the protected
area?
It is simply what justifies
the creation and existence of this area
in other words, it is a heritage,
i.e a value that belongs to everybody,
and that is important to preserve for future
generations.
They are identified from known informations
and data
on the protected area in a participatory manner
with all parties of its outskirts involved.
It is obviously essential
to know the heritage values of a protected
area,
because the purpose of the protected area
is precisely to maintain those heritage values.
Then let us ask how
we can establish the heritage value of a protected
area?
It's simple, we have to ask ourselves for
example,
if the area is home to exceptional cases
of natural, scenic, cultural, scientific,
ecological, floristic values
or of essential resources for the local communities
or of rare and indigenous
animals and plants.
This 3rd step is crucial but difficult to
implement,
because those values can be subjective, misunderstood
or poorly advertised.
Yet it is those values that will form the
basis
in identifying the threats and constraints
that affect the protected area and will guide
the choices
of actions undertaken to preserve the area.
All the other steps
will ultimately be linked to the results
of identifying the values.
The last step of the planning process
is the review of the plan.
It consists in deciding when and how
we will update the management plan.
This implies that all other steps
were realized correctly including the monitoring
and review.
In numerous case, the plan is updated at least
every ten years.
The review usually starts around one to two
years
before the scheduled end of the management
plan,
to leave the necessary time
to collect the data on indicators,
to analyze them,
to consult all the stakeholders
and to validate a new plan.
In case of delay, we will continue to use
the previous version of the plan,
and this cannot differ from the pursuit of
essential activities.
So, we know now the most important part.
Take time to consult the management plans
of parks that you are familiar with,
and if you do not have access to those documents,
Look at what we have made available to you
on the platform.
Analyze their structure,
identify their strength and weakness if there
is any,
think about what you would change.
This is the end of this class.
the next episode will be
on the planning of protected areas network.
This implies a change of scale
to plan at the level of several areas.
Have an excellent day!