Hello.
Today, we will consider
system and network planning for protected
areas.
The documents you should look at to complement
this lesson,
are the IUCN guidelines on system planning.
This document is currently only available
in English.
So, why are we interested in planning protected
areas at this scale?
Béatrice Chataigner from IUCN PAPACO, based
in Nairobi, will explain it to us.
It is important to understand today
that natural resources are increasingly in
demand
and increasingly exploited by the human population
which is also increasing exponentially.
We therefore need to ration the use of these
natural resources
so that they can be used sustainably in the
long term;
this rationed use is needed for all territories,
and, in particular, protected areas, and all
the more
since the populations most affected by the
exponential use of these resources
are those that live in the outskirts of these
protected areas.
And it is these populations that are the most
vulnerable
and that need these resources to survive from
day to day.
That's something we often hear,
but which natural resources are we actually
talking about?
Which natural resources are we willing to
protect?
Of course, there are exploitable natural resources,
whether they are renewable or not, whether
it is wood, ores, water, fauna...
These exploitable resources are advantageous
mainly
to those who sell and to those who buy them,
and that's usually a very limited number of
people.
There are also, all the natural resources
that aren't exploitable
and yet that we use every day and that are
beneficial to everyone.
And what are they?
It's the quality of the air we breathe, the
purity of the water we drink,
the fertility of the soil we cultivate,
it's the natural barriers against flooding
or other climatic events,
and they are extremely important to preserve.
This is made possible by these ecosystem services,
and these ecosystem services exist only
because the ecosystems that produce them are
in good health.
And so, the fundamental tools to keep these
ecosystems healthy,
are actually protected areas and the link
that exists between them,
to form an effective and relevant network
for protecting these ecosystems on a large
scale.
If we look at the practical aspects rather
than the theoretical ones,
how do we efficiently plan this network of
protected areas
by considering land development issue?
When we mention planning a system of protected
areas,
the procedure we will use is exactly the same
as the one that we will use for single protected
areas.
This means that we will first identify the
values
of the protected area systems.
This happens with all of the interested parties
involved in the system and from that,
we will be able to determine the pressures
they endure today
and those they will endure tomorrow, called
threats.
From this analysis, we will be able to determine
what we have to do
to thwart these pressures, and therefore,
to preserve these values.
This allows us to determine conservation objectives
for protected areas systems,
and therefore the actions required to reach
these objectives.
Specific tools exist to take into account
these aspects,
for example, the gap analysis approach that
you can read about.
It allows to identify the key ecosystems
and the possible connections between these
ecosystems.
It therefore means we can determine what we
need to prioritise
in terms of conservation through the protected
areas network.
It's fascinating, but to be honest, it's a
bit complicated.
I asked Lacina to briefly explain all of this
to us.
The way that we produce, what we call a gap
analysis
allows us to compare the appropriateness of
the distribution of protected areas
and of the distribution of the key biodiversity
areas
to be preserved in the territory.
By compiling the available data on biodiversity,
we can then identify the biodiversity areas
based on vulnerability and irreplaceability
criteria.
What makes a site irreplaceable is its unique
character,
this means no other site can play the same
conservation role
as that site in that territory.
A site or a species' vulnerability
is linked to the threats that that site or
that species endure
and that are in danger of making them disappear
definitively
if the sites or species are not protected.
Then, we superimpose this key biodiversity
areas network
and the current protected areas network to
map the gaps,
i.e. the key biodiversity areas that are not
yet included
in the protected areas network.
Finally, we just need to prioritise the required
actions to fill the gaps
and to formalise them into a national conservation
strategy.
This will allow us to adjust the national
protected areas networks
based on the gap analysis results.
You've understood correctly; this approach
means
we reflect on the protected areas network
to then eventually be able to modify it
depending on conservation priorities.
All of this will be reflected on maps, like
Lacina told us.
Let's take the example of Cameroon.
Let's overlap various maps taken from the
Forest Atlas of Cameroon
where first of all, we see here the country's
vegetative coverage,
and then the different types of forests established
in Cameroon.
For example, the forest reserves, here in
light green,
the community forests that I am circling in
red,
the communal forests here in brown, that have
just been added.
Let's then add the protected areas network
which is quite familiar to us,
here is the Dja River, the Faro River, Bénoué,
Bouba Ndjida, etc.
Let's add the active logging zones over the
top,
and there are a lot of them.
You can see them here in brown,
and then, for example, the hunting zones
that we see here in orange.
These territories, hunting zones or logging
zones,
bear witness to the use of the territory in
relation to nature.
Finally, we can also, for example,
consider all the mining permits that exist
currently in the country.
So, if we overlayed all of that on the key
biodiversity areas,
we could finally draw a coherent protected
areas network
that takes into account, not only the ecological
stakes,
but also the main pressures like those we
have just seen.
We will therefore be more prepared
to address this country's conservation challenge.
This process must obviously be participatory
and must take into account all of the participants
connected to the management of protected areas
near and far.
The main difficulty is actually to have, at
the same time,
all of the data needed to decide where the
priorities are
and to gather together all the people in on
place
to take these decisions.
Gap analysis is therefore a powerful tool
to determine a network, to draw it and build
it,
or at least it is in theory.
But once this network exists,
how can we evaluate how it functions and eventually
its efficiency?
Once the protected areas network is under
way
and that the system has been launched, we
have another question to answer:
are we really achieving the goals we wanted
to
by implementing this network
in terms of the conservation of the country's
ecosystems?
To know whether or not we manage it, we'll
put in place
a monitoring and evaluation system of the
network management actions.
Some tools exist to do this, like RAPAM, for
example,
which allow us to understand this efficiency.
RAPAM has been implemented
by protected area management agencies themselves,
and it allows them to regularly monitor their
protected areas system
and therefore to gradually correct it.
There are also other monitoring and evaluation
tools
that exist for protected areas,
but they are more tools for just one site.
It's therefore another approach, where other
participants are called upon
to evaluate the efficiency of this management.
To summarize, a protected area obviously only
protects
part of the ecosystems that are necessary
to insure
that all of the values of a territory are
preserved.
We therefore need to develop representative
and comprehensive systems
just as the Convention on Biological Diversity
asks us to do
through the conservation targets they have
set,
the famous Aichi Targets,
that we will look into at the end of this
course.
We see an interesting example in the marine
protected area network
that was developed on the Atlantic side of
Africa.
We already know Charlotte Karibuhoye who is
one of the key players
of this network and will quickly tell us
about how the network developed and how it
works today.
RAMPAO is the Regional Marine Protected Area
Network for West Africa.
The network has given itself the mission
to maintain a coherent entity,
for the critical ecosystems that are important
for the ecological processes to function.
This is to preserve biodiversity,
but also to insure that the legacy
and the associated ecosystem services are
maintained.
So, just like I said, it's a network that
hopes to cover
the West African marine ecoregion that covers
seven countries
in the West African sub-region.
So there's Mauritania, Senegal,
Gambia, Guinea-Bissau, Guinea,
Sierra Leone and Cape Verde islands.
This network therefore tries to finally combine
all of the sites
that have already been developed into marine
protected areas.
There is therefore a bio-geographical or - physical
aspect, if you prefer -
but there is also a human aspect, because
it gathers people,
representatives, managers from all these sites
that are therefore members of
that network.
The Regional Marine Protected Area Network
RAMPAO
has been set up within the PRCM framework.
PRCM is the Regional Program for Coastal and
Marine Conservation in Western Africa,
now known as the Regional Partnership for
Coastal and Marine Conservation.
RAMPAO was therefore created after a long
consultation process
between different participants
because the participants noticed they shared
many of the same problems,
and the same challenges
in terms of preserving marine and coastal
resources.
They shared a lot of cross-border habitats.
It is also noticeable that there are migratory
species
that cross the borders.
So we see that finally even, for example,
the users, the fishers
don't necessarily respect the political boundaries.
The participants from these countries thought
that there needs to be a joint approach to
be able to battle these problems.
From 2002, there were therefore several meetings,
several...consultations...
Namely, in 2004, 2005, and 2006, there were
specific meetings
for the managers of the marine protected areas
to think of goals and think about how the
network would work.
And all of this culminated in 2007 when the
network was officially created
during the consultative assembly
in Cape Verde in April 2007.
And so, we see that, today also,
this network was able to also gain political
recognition,
since there was a regional strategy for marine
protected areas.
This was established in 2002 and was officially
approved
by the ministers in charge of the protected
areas,
of fishing and of the environment in those
countries.
They signed a general policy declaration
that emphasized the importance of this network.
The advantages of the Regional Marine Protected
Area Network
for preserving MPAs are numerous.
We can organise them into two different groups.
I see it that we can have a group called "the
social benefits"
and a group simply called "the ecological
benefits".
I'm using the term social because we are referring
to human beings.
I'm particularly meaning strengthening abilities
of the managers
of marine protected areas since the network
was able to implement
a series of activities for strengthening abilities
in key areas
that are very important for preserving marine
protected areas.
This is mainly in terms of management plans,
the development of management plans,
the development of business plans, marine
supervision,
which is important for marine protected areas
of course,
and the issue of shared governance.
All of these are questions that really were
addressed
in a systematic manner to train the managers
of these marine protected areas in these domains.
But there are also the exchanges, the mutual
reinforcement,
there is particularly the economies of scale.
This means that, finally, instead of each
country or each site
organising training,
there are training sessions that will benefit
many people.
But there is also the fact that the network
was able to represent,
at a national and an international level,
the needs of the marine protected areas
of the sub-region, and really make known the
progress
but also the challenges that the marine protected
areas face.
At an ecological level, I think it is completely
obvious,
this network today covers almost 5 million
acres
of marine and, of course, coastal areas.
Over half of it is in fact maritime.
Then, there are 27 sites that are protected
and that are members of the network.
There were projects before the creation of
the network
that showed the link, the connectivity that
exists
between these different sites.
So the network finally contributes to protecting
species
that need all of these sites to develop.
There are species that are born in one site,
that develop in another, and that will reproduce
elswhere.
All of these species benefit from
this network.
There are also some important ecological processes:
species migration, larval dispersion...
All of these are benefits that this network
is offering.
But there is also an issue that is topical
at the moment,
we're talking a lot these days about climate
change
and like me, you know that healthy ecosystems
are more resilient to climate change.
So the network allows, on one hand, to preserve
a sample of healthy ecosystems
but also, as a network,
it can preserve several samples from the same
ecosystem,
from the same habitat.
This means that if anything were to ever disturb
a site,
it still has the ability to be resilient.
That resilience is maintained
thanks to several samples existing from that
same habitat.
All that is to basically say
that this network has very clear and very
obvious ecological benefits,
that we will have to, of course, I think,
measure and quantify
in a much more systematic manner.
Consider the protected areas networks
that you know of on a country or region scale
like RAMPAO
that Charlotte has just spoken to us about.
Are they complete, are they logical?
What were the important aspects in forming
the network?
Are they simply opportunistic?
It happens.
Do they meet the objectives we have just mentioned?
There we go, that's the end of this lesson.
The next video will look into following up
on results
and the impacts of planning.
Have a brilliant day!