Hello.
This sequence will be on monitoring results
and management planning.
First, we will go over different principles
of monitoring,
its definition, its role,
the different types and levels of monitoring,
who takes part and conducts them.
Then we will spend a few minutes on
two points in particular, a bit more innovative.
I have chosen an example of
participatory monitoring and one example of
a monitoring chart.
Let's look at this together.
What is monitoring?
It's a regular observation over time
of the same elements, on the same sites so
that one can follow and measure
the long-term evolution of these elements.
Usually, in relation to a reference condition
established in advance.
Allow me to emphasize important
words in this definition
First of all: regular.
Same elements, same sites, to measure the
evolution in the long run.
These elements are important.
These mean that monitoring cannot be improvised.
It must be planned and organized.
It requires financing, competence
and long-term commitment.
Let's take a look at the reasoning behind
and the use of this monitoring.
The results are important for a number of
stakeholders.
As you can see here, monitoring has 3 essential
functions:
To guide the managers, to adapt, adjust,
evaluate and prepare the next management plan.
It's in this case
a feedback process towards the different departments
and functionalities of the protected area.
Secondly, to inform more extensively the decision-makers
and the backers.
These means providing feedback to the board
of directors, to the donors,
who will ask questions like "What's the use
of the protected area?"
"What's its purpose?" or "How are things going
in your area?"
Here we are looking for elements of efficiency,
performance, elements
about the site's value and impacting measures.
Finally, monitoring has a role in raising
awareness.
The goal is to inform all of the actors contributing
to the management of the protected area.
It's an effort of communication and appropriation.
It is then necessary to build upon the information
by using
communication and organization tools: debriefing
meetings,
brochures like this one, to inform all the
stakeholders.
I would like to emphasize the 2 levels of
monitoring that I think are important:
the first one is the monitoring of management
efficiency
and of the management plan implementation.
Here we need to identify if the management
plan
is correctly executed, if its goals are met,
if its progress is appropriate,
at what level of financial efficiency and
effectiveness of means,
we need to learn from its implementation,
the processes underway,
from what worked and what didn't work.
At what point the management cycle failed
or succeeded.
It is also about adapting the management's
decisions
when problems occur in the implementation.
Monitoring can be used to redistribute resources
and efforts
differently to improve the implementation.
Note that these issues will be studied more
in detail in the sequence 4.2.
The second level is about monitoring impacts
and the site's evolution.
This monitoring of course is also linked to
the previous one but it has
specific characteristics that I would like
to point out.
It goes further than the previous one.
We take into account, if possible
the impacts of the management, but also the
evolution of the context, threats
and changes in the environment.
This kind of monitoring goes further
in the evaluation of the results and in protecting
the site.
It also intends to study the changes taking
place.
Different types of
impacts monitoring can be implemented.
Firstly biological and ecological monitoring
which will measure the health
of the environment; for example the reef,
the species population,
and biodiversity.
Sequence 4.4 will bring you more on this subject,
such as how to conduct ecological monitoring,
etc.
Very important but rarely used:
socioeconomic monitoring,
which allows the measuring of the socioeconomic
status
of communities living inside or outside of
the protected areas.
This allows to identify usage of space and
resources,
actors' perception, pressure and improvements
brought
by the protected areas on the quality of life,
economic health and well-being of the populations.
Of course, most of the time we also study
some iconic species: turtles, some mammals,
birds,
representative of the protected area.
Lastly, I think that it is also important
to emphasize
the monitoring of some activities relevant
to the protected area.
For example, in the case of an AMP,
we will keep an eye on fishing activity.
In other protected areas, touristic activities
are important.
Who will conduct those studies?
Who will monitor them?
Generally, these studies are conducted by
scientists,
managers and by the park staff.
Sometimes with the help of the populations.
We will talk about this more later.
Note that some of these monitoring activities
require some very scientific methods.
Most of the time, the monitoring must be thorough,
and done in a consistent way.
This requires important financial resources
and sophisticated skills.
Other times, it needs to be suitable for a
less knowledgeable public.
The level and quality of information will
therefore
substantially change, and so will its purpose.
One needs to manage these different levels,
the different capabilities of the protected
area,
and the funding available.
I will now present two examples of monitoring
with different approaches:
first, an example of participatory monitoring,
which will involve communities, and then a
second
example that will focus on the restitution
and communication of the results.
For this first example, we will look at an
example of participatory monitoring.
Again, note that the scientific method must
be thorough,
but in this case, a large part of the work
is given to the communities.
Here, in this example in West Africa,
these women have been trained
and asked to conduct the monitoring of shellfish.
Note that the implementation of such a task
is interesting
to mobilize communities,
to strengthen their relation to their surroundings.
It can also be less expensive, but be wary,
it's not always the case.
Note also that this method usually requires
more time
because of the training and
the supervisory staff needed.
I would advise you to study this document
wich is entitled: "Guide de suivi participatif
des coquillages exploités en Afrique de l'ouest"
for a more detailed explanation.
$$(Jingling sound from the shells in the bucket)
Sorting by size is carried out for each bucket.
Sorting is done thanks to a column of sieves
and there are 13 buckets,
12 of which have holes which vary between
.5 and 6cm.
The last one traps remainders.
$$(The woman is counting out loud)
Numbers in each bucket are logged
and the data analyzed
so as to obtain figures on population density,
average size
and population structure.
For this second focus,
I would like to introduce you to an initiative
from
l'Agence Française des Aires Marines Protégées,
which has been producing monitoring charts
for some years now.
Let me remind you again that the principles
used for this monitoring
are the same as those given at the beginning
of this session:
thoroughness, method and consistency.
Here we have a rather interesting example
of
a restitution.
This tool has been developed thanks to a partnership
between the managers,
scientific associates, communities and in
partnership with
several marine protected areas.
Note that this tool is very useful
in a communication process.
It's very visual.
All of the data is gathered.
Therefore we have a dashboard with the evolution
of all the factors.
The graphical aspect makes it easy to follow.
This allows for an easier way to communicate
with all audiences.
What is also interesting in this example
is that the monitoring has been done on 2
levels:
on both the scale of a single protected area,
and of a network of protected areas,
to provide some degree of consistency.
In summary, I would like to insist on some
aspects of this monitoring.
First there is a strong concern in measuring
the management impacts.
For that reason, what we just saw, biological
monitorings,
and socioeconomic monitoring are very important,
even if they are not often used and if they
need a lot of resources.
Please also note that several levels of monitoring
are generally put in place
in protected areas: the monitoring of species,
the monitoring of management indicators,
the monitoring of the general context, the
monitoring of global impacts;
all of this implies
a strong and efficient coordination and sometimes
a prioritization,
due to means and resources not always being
available.
Finally, note in summary the need to build
up on the monitoring.
It's not enough to have all the data,
you need to also analyze and communicate these
results
to all the parties involved.
You should not hesitate to use graphic tools,
charts, visual tools to render this information.
That's it, this sequence is completed, have
a nice day!