Hello.
Today, we will talk about transboundary protected
areas.
This will help show some of the aspects
on how to plan protected areas and their outskirts
that we have studied in this module.
The reference book for this class is the guidelines
of
the World Commission on Protected Areas,
on transboundary conservation.
First of all, a transboundary protected area
is a protected area.
It is therefore a territory dedicated to nature's
conservation.
We can see here a map of the regional area
W, spread across three countries
- Burkina, Niger and Benin - and formed by
three parks
that have the same name, and are all of category
2.
A transboundary protected area is specific
in that it spreads beyond
a national border, so there is no more separation
between the countries involved.
Therefore, the flow of people and animals
are usually freely possible.
We are going from managing each park separately
to creating an area with a relatively shared
management.
We might - roughly- see three types of transboundary
areas.
The ones that gather two adjacent protected
areas
- I draw them here as an example -
These protected areas are then simply separated
by a border.
These are transboundary protected areas.
For example,
The W,that we just studied, evolves toward
this pattern.
Another type of transboundary protected area
gathers
two or several protected areas connected by
territories of another status;
this complex is called a transboundary conservation
landscape.
The W parks are a good example, because they
are transboundary parks
that are connected to other parks - such as
Pendjari, Arly's park etc -
by territories
of another status:
reserves, hunting areas, and pastoralism areas.
It all shapes a landscape called the "W Arly
Pendjari",
named after the main parks it's composed by.
Such as the the combination named KAZA, which
stands for Kavango Zambezi,
in Southern Africa that spreads out over several
countries - Namibia, Angola,
Zambia, Zimbabwe and Botswana - and is composed
of certain
famous parks such as Chobe in Botswana Kafue
in Zambia
or Hwange in Zimbabwe.
All these territories which are parks, are
connected through other areas
of different status, and shape this transboundary
landscape
which is delineated by the white line here
and that is obviously huge.
The
third type of transboundary protected area
gathers different territories,
some of which are protected - but not all
of them are -
and that are necessary to maintain migrations
of certain species,
for example here, zebras or wildebeest in
Eastern Africa.
In that case, it's more a transboundary conservation
area rather than
a transboundary protected area strictly speaking.
Having several countries working together
for conservation makes sense
when we know that a third of important biodiversity
areas
straddle at least one border.
Over 300 transboundary parks are now formally
established in the world,
such as here the big Limpopo that connects
Southern Africa and Mozambique.
Trans-national collaboration is a logical
necessity, when, for example,
we look at a species like the lesser flamingos
that migrate between
Kenyan lakes in the Rift valley but reproduce
in Tanzania.
All of them.
Working on one side of the border without
looking at the other side
wouldn’t make sense in that case.
Collaboration of parks beyond borders
helps spreading the collectively protected
surface area,
developing shared activities, such as patrols
against poaching,
or improving the overall park resilience and
its capacity to adapt to change.
Brice is giving us the example
of TNS in Central Africa.
TNS gathers a few protected areas, three national
parks of category 2,
between Congo, Cameroun and CAR.
We already have seen the progress:
an anti-poaching squad was created by the
three states,
protocols about free movement of TNS employees
were written,
and there is an eco-toursim tour.
Not to omit the FTNS fund
that was created to finance activities at
the three transboundary desks,
like in RCA, Cameroun.
Also, cross-border collaboration helps make
a location more attractive
and grow its economic potential; for example,
for tourism or other
economic activities.
We can see here Mara's plains connected to
Serengeti.
Even though there isn't a transboundary collaboration
yet,
the ecosystem is overall important.
Off course, establishing transboundary collaborations
happens to be relatively
complicated, because it demands high level
agreements, between governments
of different countries.
Also, after a concrete collaboration
on the field, between protected areas
from each side of the borders.
The challenge is to build transboundary governance
systems
that are operational.
The model has been developed
in Southern Africa, as we see here, around
the TFCA that stands for
Transfontier Conservation Areas.
We can see here the KAZA,
that we studied five minutes ago.
Sometimes, the idea that
these territories might reinforce peace between
countries
triggered the creation of such areas.
These are the famous "Peace Parks",
that have developed between several countries
of this district.
They helped connecting wide conservation territories,
reopening the crossings for animals and bringing
human closer - in theory.
We can see here the opening of big Limpopo,
of which we talked -
between Southern Africa and Mozambique- by
Nelson Mandela in 2001.
In francophone Africa, the movement isn't
that advanced but begins to take shape.
The W example is interesting, and is briefly
introduced
by Pierre Kafando, who was the W conservator
in Burkina
during a few years.
The W regional park is well protected.
It overlaps three borders
of three states: Benin, Burkina and Niger.
This area was specifically created to protect
and maintain
biodiversity, and associated national and
cultural resources.
The park spreads out over a 10 300 km2 area
and
is part of one of the biggest protected system
of African savannah: the W-Arly-Pendjari complex.
The W regional park was created during the
colonial period, which is
when these three countries belonged to the
territory
of French West Africa.
The area of the W was poorly populated
because of the tsetse fly, that gives sleeping
sickness,
and other diseases such as osteoporosis We
can add to this
the richness of the area wild fauna.
It's only in 1927 that it was classified as
a sanctuary park.
Between 1952 and 1953
the High Commissioner of the Republic, general
governor of West Africa,
signed national by-laws, making this sanctuary
park
a state classified forest and a wildlife reserve.
One of the challenges of this collaboration
is the reinforcement of regional
integration through the theme: conservation,
management
and appreciation of biodiversity.
For the W regional park, this appreciation
goes though tourism
development, some products exploitation, acknowledged
as common right
by the resident communities, and handcraft,
agricultural and
socio-cultural activities on the outskirts.
The socio-economic advantages are: revenues
to the states,
especially public funds, private operators,
tourist camps
guides and managers, hunt guides in the ouskirts
zones,
and outskirts communities, organized as associations.
There is also the reinforcement of the stakeholder's
capacity:
touristic guides, hotels camps managers, and
collaboration between populations
on each side of the borders.
There were travels, people who helped organize,
which also helped
diminish the conflict about the use of resources
and trades
in these communities.
Finally, there is the populations
participation to different land-use and monitoring
activities,
which allow the empowerment but also appropriation
of activities, and generates revenues.
That's the end of the class, next episode
will be about the
Aïchi targets, linked to the Convention on
Biological Diversity.