Hello and welcome to all.
Today's lesson is about the Aichi targets
as defined by the Convention on Biological
Diversity.
We will go through the history of these targets,
then look at the guidelines of one of the
targets,
and then consider the usefulness of Aichi
Targets.
I invite you to read these thoroughly on the
CBD website,
and to look more broadly at their corresponding
strategic plan.
Please listen Martin Yelkouni on the history
of Aichi targets.
It was during the 10th
Conference of the parties of the Convention
on Biological Diversity
in Japan,
that the Aichi targets, as part of the strategic
plan
for Biodiversity 2011-2020 were adopted.
Aichi refers to the name of the Aichi Prefecture,
Japan.
This is a general strategic framework on biodiversity,
not only for biodiversity- related conventions
but also for the United Nations as a whole.
The Parties agreed to translate this general
international framework
into national strategies and action plans
for biodiversity.
It seeks to live in harmony with nature looking
towards 2050,
that by then, biodiversity would be valued,
conserved, restored and used wisely,
thus maintaining the services provided by
the ecosystems
which keep the planet healthy,
and providing essential benefits to all peoples.
So we are talking about
extremely important aspects of conservation
overall
but also, more specifically in Africa.
And these directly affect our work in protected
areas.
You will definitely hear Aichi mentioned in
different models.
The 2011-2020 Strategic Plan for Biodiversity
is based on 5 main goals,
including the 20 Aichi targets for Biological
Diversity.
These are the following:
First goal: Address the underlying causes
of biodiversity loss
by mainstreaming biodiversity
across government and society.
That means increasing awareness
of the value of biodiversity
and its integration into developmental planning,
resource mobilization for the conservation
of biodiversity,
and the application of sustainable production
and consumption measures.
Targets 1 to 4 are part of this goal.
Second goal:
Reduce the direct pressures exerted on biodiversity
and promote sustainable use.
This means reducing the degradation and fragmentation
of natural habitats,
managing agricultural resources, forestry
and aquaculture
in a sustainable manner,
to reduce pollution and eradicate invasive
alien species,
and to maintain wetlands inland, coastal and
marine.
Targets 5 to 10 are part of that second goal.
3rd goal: Improve the status of biodiversity
by safeguarding ecosystems, species, and genetic
diversity.
This means that well-connected and managed
ecologically representative networks
and protected areas should cover 1/10th of
marine areas
and 1/5th of terrestrial areas,
avoiding the extinction of species
and maintaining genetic diversity of useful
domestic species.
This goal covers the targets 11, 12 and 13.
4th goal: Enhance the benefits of biodiversity
and ecosystem services.
This means that eventually,
ecosystems will provide services essential
to man's welfare,
improving carbon storage
and implementing the Nagoya Protocol.
targets 14, 15 and 16 are included in this
fourth goal.
5th goal: Enhance implementation through participatory
planning,
knowledge management and capacity building.
This means that by 2020,
we will have the implementation of national
action plans for biodiversity,
the integration of traditional knowledge and
practices
of indigenous and local communities in the
conservation of biological diversity,
and the improvement of scientific and technological
matters.
Targets 17-20 are part of this fifth goal.
The strategic goals are relevant
for the creation, governance, and restoration
of both protected terrestrial and marine areas.
Of the 20 Aichi objectives, there is one you
should be aware of
as it directly affects protected areas, and
that is the objective 11.
It states that by 2020,
at least 17% of terrestrial and inland water,
as well as 10% of coastal and marine areas,
especially areas of particular
importance for biodiversity and ecosystem
services,
are conserved through effectively and equitably
managed
ecologically representative and well-connected
systems
of protected areas and other effective area-based
conservation
measures, and integrated into the wider landscape
and seascapes.
A set of guides on the Aichi targets have
been developed
to provide parties and other stakeholders
with an introduction to each of the Aichi
Biodiversity Targets
by briefly explaining key terms,
highlighting the implications for the establishment
of national targets,
by providing ideas for preliminary national
actions,
by identifying progress indicators
and identifying additional resources.
These guides are important to consider,
if you need to work on Aichi Targets, do not
miss them.
Take for example a directive for target 5
of the Aichi Targets
pertaining to biodiversity.
Example directive on Goal 5 of the Aichi targets.
Target 5: By 2020, the rate of loss
of all natural habitats, including forests,
is at least halved and where feasible, brought
close to zero,
and the degradation and fragmentation
is significantly reduced.
The guide will help us understand this article
by putting it in context:
Habitat loss, including the degradation and
fragmentation
is the most important factor
in terms of the loss of biodiversity globally.
Similarly, slowing and possibly halting
the impoverishment of habitats
is essential for the protection of biodiversity
and maintaining ecosystems essential to human
wellbeing.
Then the guide explains the target:
It applies to every natural habitat including
forests.
Finally, the guide suggests ways to achieve
this target.
For example, the rate of loss of natural habitats
must be reduced by at least half and brought
to near zero if possible.
Another example:
The degradation and fragmentation of natural
habitats
should be significantly reduced.
Please follow the usefulness of Aichi Targets
with Abdou Salam Kane.
The Aichi targets were developed, based on
an analysis of the benefits
that nature provides in terms of human welfare,
so they go beyond
the mere conservation of biological diversity.
The Aichi targets highlight the connectivity
between biodiversity and sustainable development.
The strategic plan of the Aichi objectives
are the essential instruments
which have been negotiated and adopted by
193 Contracting Parties
which gives them a strong legitimacy.
They are an excellent basis for the objectives
of sustainable development.
Other arrangements and agencies part of the
the United Nations system
endorsed the Strategic Plan and its objectives,
so as to ensure consistency among these instruments.
So the inclusion of the Aichi targets in the
sustainable development goals
ensure essential international policy coherence
so as to facilitate the implementation and
attainment
of different multilateral environmental agreements.
The strategic plans of the Aichi targets
are being implemented through strategies
and national action plans for the conservation
of biodiversity.
Some countries have therefore already included,
or are in the process of including these obligations
in their national planning system
across government departments and sectors
which are the developmental bases in their
country.
These provide institutional infrastructure
and resources
to implement these elements
and then make the expected results for achieving
the objectives
of sustainable development.
The strategic plan and Aichi targets are currently
being implemented
through strategies and national plans for
biodiversity.
Some countries have therefore already included,
or are including these obligations
in their national systems,
in various ministries and sectors
thus providing the institutional infrastructure
and resources
to implement these elements
and to report on them.
In conclusion, significant progress has been
made
in the achievement of most of the Aichi Biodiversity
Targets.
Some elements of the targets,
such as protecting at least 17% of terrestrial
and inland water
are well underway.
However, in most cases, these advances are
not enough
to achieve the targets set for 2020.
Additional measures are necessary to keep
the 2011-2020
strategic plan for biodiversity on track.
The main measures recommended to achieve each
goal
are presented in the 4th edition
of the Aichi Targets Passport on biodiversity.
Here, the class comes to an end.
The next episode will be the module's conclusion
in the form of a short animation,
and will present this module homework.
In the meantime, have an excellent day.