This module allowed us to understand how much
the planning of protected areas
is an important tool that allows
protected areas to achieve their conservation
purpose.
To be effective, the planning must follow
a consistent approach,
simple and universal.
The goal is to evaluate the values of the
protected areas
and the pressure they are up against,
and then define a vision and goals
that we wish to attain to preserve those values
in the long term.
The organization of management activities
will then follow naturally.
Two rules, among others are necessary.
The planning must be done in a participatory
manner,
including all stakeholders, in and around
the protected area,
but it should also be implemented directly
by those
who will put it in practice and not just outsourced
to experts.
Whatever the scale,
around one protected areas or an entire network,
or even more in cases including regions combining
both development and preservation,
this approach will stay the same,
determining first the values and then their
conservation.
Of course, the stakeholders involved in the
process will be different people.
For a given site, it will be all the actors
directly influencing the area and its surroundings:
the managers, the communities, the private
sector.
For a good network of protected areas, there
should be a detailed consultation,
and the planning will be based
on an analysis of the shortcomings at the
national level
to determine the key zones
to protect and preserve the biodiversity in
its fullness
as well as the connectivity between these
areas.
The network will try to include all management
categories,
and all kinds of forms of governance to be
more efficient.
Lastly, for the integrated planning of a land
in its entirety,
a judicious development should be chosen
which will allow to protect resources in the
long run
while taking into account the inhabitant's
needs.
Thus, the planning will involve all of the
participants
in the development and land-use planning of
the concerned area.
The monitoring of the protected areas is a
decisive part of the planning.
A wise choice is needed from the start of
which indicators to measure
to be able to evaluate the impact on the management
actions.
Those indicators, measured during the implementation
of the management plan, will allow us
to understand what works and what doesn't,
and adjust the actions along the way.
It's a
repetitive process called adaptive management.
This monitoring will have three essential
functions:
guide the manager, as previously explained,
fully inform the decision-makers
and raise the awareness of the stakeholders
concerned about the management of the protected
area.
Finally, the Convention on Biologic Diversity
allows us
to plan for conservation on a global scale
by fixing quantifiable targets, like Aïchi
targets;
it helps us define conservation strategies
for each nation,
to building protected areas networks
which will include all the important ecosystems
present on Earth.
That's it, you can now starts the test of
this module.