Congratulations, you've completed Week 4.
Let us quickly look what we
have covered in this week.
We looked at biological
biowaste treatment options.
We looked at vermicomposting and
processing with black solider flies.
We looked at thermochemical
conversion of organic waste.
Then we also looked at hazardous and
healthcare waste and
concluded with e-waste.
In vermicomposting,
we looked at the worm's cycle as a start.
Here shown in this picture.
Then we look to the environmental
conditions suitable for vermicomposting,
such as aeration, moisture,
also the need to be shaded, and
the daily feed rates of about
50% of worm weight per day.
We also looked at case studies and
looked how this technology is constructed,
such as the example here
from the Philippines.
Then we looked at the products
of vermicomposting,
the vermicompost, the worm tea,
and the worms themselves.
Then we looked at another
approach of biowaste processing
using blank soldier fly larvae.
First, we looked again at
the life cycle of the insect.
Then on how to manage the colony and
how to operate the treatment process.
Then we looked a the BSF products,
the residue which is similar to
vermicompost and the larvae, which
have a high protein content of 40% and
fat content of 30% and are a high value
product, especially for animal feed.
In the module on healthcare
waste management,
we started off by looking
at the waste amounts.
Remember only 15-20%
is actually hazardous,
the rest is typical municipal waste.
Segregation is a main priority.
Then we looked at how to enhance this
source segregation, by color coding and
the provision of containers,
for instance, for sharps.
Then we looked at healthcare
waste treatment options,
mostly referring to this book,
The Compendium of Technologies for
Treatment and
Destruction of Healthcare Waste.
We looked at different systems,
autoclaves, but also incineration and
finally, ending with a special
pits of landfilling.
In the module on thermochemical processes,
we looked at the different options and
they're different parameters,
temperature, air and retention time.
But we also looked at the products from
these processes and their quality.
After looking at the processes and
the parameters,
we also looked at the value chain.
Starting off with primary products through
to conversion to finally the market,
looking at different products of value,
which we can sell in the market.
Then the module on e-waste,
where we looked at the relevance
of e-waste on a global scale but
also the risks of e-waste recycling and
how this can be improved.
Stay with us for an exciting fifth week,
where we will be talking about strategic
planning, benchmarking city performances,
looking at waste and climate change,
and also the issue of circular economy.