Hello and welcome to this Mooc on the management
and the governance of protected areas in Africa.
This Mooc is a general training course
on the way these particular territories are
being managed.
It will help us thinking about
and better understand their contribution
to the conservation of nature on the continent
and to the sustainable development of the
territories around them,
because protected areas are more than fauna
and flora reserves.
They also provide resources,
goods, useful services to the local populations,
and beyond them, to all humankind.
Three key people have contributed to the development
of this Mooc
and they will coordinate it with me: Sylvie
Goyet,
Paul NDiaye from the Cheikh-Anta-Diop University
in Dakar
and Paul Ouédraogo from the RAMSAR Convention
Secretariat.
Several other speakers will share
their experience through interviews or videos.
Their names will be listed at the end of this
introduction
and you will soon see them on your screens
of course.
So, this Mooc has 7 modules spread over 7
weeks.
Each module contains 6 sequences
allowing us to address a specific topic,
and reading material is also provided for
you to go deeper.
So, depending on your expectations
you will have the possibility to go more or
less into detail.
At the end of each module, an animation sums
up
the important points of the week, and an assessment
test
is available.
It is optional,
but if you succeed, you will receive a certificate
of achievement.
Those who wish to will be able to take a final
classroom exam
and get EPFL certification.
We will talk about this during the Mooc,
don't worry.
The first module will introduce a few key
concepts
to really understand what protected areas
are:
their nature, their importance, their role,
their specificities.
The second module will be more specifically
about their management:
planning, networks,
the use of the land around and between the
areas,
transboundary protected areas.
The third module will be about their governance,
a cucial topic:
who does what and how to manage those territories.
We will talk about State, communities, private
sector etc.
In the fourth module we will cover some of
the aspects
regarding the areas' effectiveness:
surveillance, ecological monitoring,
raising awareness among partners and also
recognition of good practices
thanks to the green list.
The fifth module will cover a few specific
aspects
of these protected areas:
the link with culture for instance,
the importance of training, the marine environment,
species conservation and also tourism.
The sixth module will be about funding
conservation activities in and around protected
areas.
We will talk about the economic values (and
others)
of protected areas, about financial planning,
the sources of funding and its mechanisms,
compensation and so on.
Finally, the last module will be dealing with
topical issues related to African protected
areas.
We will talk about climate change, connectivity,
ecological restoration, gender and equity,
corruption and all kinds of traffics.
Each week, an important international convention
will be presented:
The Convention on Biological Diversity
and its related agreements like
the CITES, the RAMSAR Convention,
the World Heritage Convention,
and also the Convention on Migratory Species
(CMS).
This Mooc will be the opportunity for us to
share
our experiences through the discussion group
put in place.
We count on you for sharing your opinions
and suggestions
to improve this course.
Don't wait until the end of the Mooc to talk
to us.
All good ideas are welcome.
Finally, I'd like to thank the organisations
and people
who made this Mooc possible.
We benefit from the financial support of André
Hoffmann,
of the Ecole Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne
and of the partnership between France and
the IUCN,
in particular the French Development Agency.
This Mooc is the result of a technical collaboration
between
the EPFL, the IUCN, the Cheikh-Anta-Diop University
and the RAMSAR Convention.
That's it.
Here we go, for 7 weeks that we hope to be
fascinating.
Have a great day!