Hello and welcome to the first module of the
Mooc
on protected areas management in Africa.
This module introduces
a few important notions to know beforehand,
a few key concepts that will be helpful throughout
the module.
So, this week, the module works as follow:
The first class will be about the history
and importance of protected areas:
where they come from, what they have become
over time,
what they represent today for nature conservation.
The second class will deal with their very
role:
what their purpose is,
how they help to preserve nature.
In the third class we will see how a protected
area is defined.
Knowing exactly what protected areas are
will allow us to better understand them
and to better identify the tools, the methods
adapted to them.
The forth and fifth class will allow us to
classify them
into management categories to distinguish,
to better understand their identity
and better understand their specificities.
The last class will be about the convention
of the week.
We will talk about the Convention on Biological
Diversity,
an essential convention, when dealing with
protected areas in the world.
Finally, we will have a brief summary of the
items we discussed
this week in the form of an animation
and we will present this module's homework.
Here we go,
have a great week with us!