Hello.
Today, the class will help us better understand
the importance and the role of protected areas
in the world and in Africa in particular.
The publication to be read additionally
is the annual report on the state of protected
areas
called the Protected Planet Report (as you
can see here)
and the World Database on Protected Areas
hosted
on www.protectedplanet.net
First, let’s talk about history.
Nowadays, more than 15% of the planet
is under some sort of formal protection.
We call these territories protected areas.
The protected areas are seen in green on this
world map
and the marine areas are in blue.
The first park formally recognized in the
modern sense of the word
was the Yellowstone, in North America in 1872.
Its designation comes from the American pioneers'
ambition to preserve an exceptional landscape
that colonisation would no doubt have damaged.
It is about preserving nature in its original
state.
But, obviously forms of protection already
existed,
some more or less formally.
For instance, natural sites that were considered
sacred
were pioneers in the preservation of nature.
Even though it is hard to say when they first
appeared,
some of them have been known and recognized
for hundreds or thousands of years.
But in general the protection of territories
responded above all else
to a targeted use, like for example
hunting reserves, which were created for a
certain elite
in the Middle Ages in Europe.
The sudden increase in number of protected
areas,
and the surface they cover,
is a really recent phenomenon.
Their number went from a few dozen at the
beginning of the 20th century
to progressively more than 200,000 today,
spread across the globe.
The graph here depicts this evolution,
that is almost exponential since the 50’s
and that doesn’t seem to decrease
as the recent international commitments appeal
to cover more surface.
Changes in the future will lead towards more
protected areas
and more covered surfaces.
So, the recent history of protected areas
in Africa
and in particular French speaking Africa
can be split up schematically into three periods.
During the colonial period and until the end
of the 50’s,
a lot of classified forests were created
according to the model of state-owned forests
in Europe.
The goal of these forests was mainly the preservation
of a resource, generally wood,
but sometimes their goal included the preservation
of the ecosystem as a whole.
Nevertheless, a few forests would only be
protected for their wood,
for instance, to feed the rail transport with
coal.
The reserves or hunting reserves, on the same
principle,
protected the game for growing the animals
as trophies or for commercial purposes,
like ivory for instance.
This is what lowered the number
of a lot of African species.
Of course, there are exceptions, like for
example,
the natural reserve of Mount Nimba in Guinea.
We can see here that its establishment dates
back to 1944
and that it was fully protected from the beginning.
The decolonisation is followed, generally
speaking,
by a neutral period as far as creation
and management of protected areas are concerned,
simply because the young States had other
priorities
and few means to invest in this sector.
We have to wait until the 80’s and especially
the 90’s,
after the Rio Conference, for a new momentum
to begin with
the creation of new protected areas
in countries which used to have none.
For example, we can see here the Lopé National
Park in Gabon.
Another example: in the 2000's,
Guinea Bissau formally established its park
network
and the agency managing it today, the IBAP.
This recent period in time also showed the
evolution of some territories
from one status to another, including classified
forests,
that were often classified for the preservation
of a resource,
and sometimes become national parks directed
toward tourism,
like here in the Deux Balé forest in Burkina
Faso.
Above all, in this period of time the management
of
abandoned protected areas was addressed, at
least in theory,
and sponsors started supporting them again
and in some cases continue to do so today.
So, let’s have a closer look at the history
of a park
like the Niokolo Koba in Senegal because it’s
representative enough
of what happened, at least, once again, in
the French speaking Africa.
The Niokola Koba was created in 1926 as a
hunting reserve.
It then evolved from a strict hunting reserve
to a classified state-owned forest, and, at
last, in 1954,
to a national park.
In 1969, after extensions, the Niokolo Koba
reached its current surface area of 2,256,072
acres
and evictions led to the removal of a number
of villages
such as Badi, Damantin and Nionghani.
In 1981, thanks to its rich biodiversity
the Niokola Koba became
a World Heritage Site.
In 2007 due to pressures from human activity
such as poaching, the expansion of agricultural
lands,
and livestock wandering,
but also the threat of the Sambangalo dam
project
the Niokolo Koba was listed as endangered.
Today, the situation in Africa is quite contrasted
for historical reasons (we saw it),
for legal reasons (we’ll see it)
especially between French-speaking Africa
and the English-speaking one,
for cultural reasons too,
sometimes for security or geopolitical reasons,
and finally due to opportunism.
The map here gives you the current protected
areas coverage.
The darker it is, the more protected areas
there are.
The more green spots there are, the more it
is covered by protected areas.
But there is no real reliable data
and the reality on the field can be very different.
Generally speaking, let’s remember that
today there are
more than 7000 protected areas in Africa,
that represent more or less a 14% land coverage
and almost a 4% sea coverage.
In reality it is probably even more as the
data comes
from the World Database on Protected Areas,
which is obviously incomplete.
This coverage is not homogeneous nor representative
at a global level and at Africa’s level.
Some of the territories are underrepresented,
like deserts or coastline areas that,
even though they are very important for biodiversity,
are often not protected, simply because
they are densely populated and harder to deal
with.
For instance, on the left, these maps show
important areas for birds
whereas on the right,
we have the protected areas
for the same area, West Africa.
Taking a closer look, we can see that a number
of areas
that are important and should be preserved,
but are not.
There is no overlapping of these two approaches,
of these two maps.
So, as I told you today
the data on protected areas is gathered
in a world database whose acronym is WDPA
for World Database on
Protected Areas.
You will find this database on the website
www.protectedplanet.net.
Take your time, read the information
on protected areas that you know.
I chose, for example, the page of the Comoe
Park in the Ivory Coast, here.
Go to the website, use the tool on a few parks
to learn how to use it well.
It will be really useful throughout this course.
Unfortunately, you will see
a lot of information is still incorrect.
It’s up to you to make it right.
That’s the end of the class.
The next class will be about the role of the
protected areas
in the world and especially in Africa.
Have a great day!