Hello.
Today, this class will help us better understand
the role played by protected areas in Africa.
The additional reading for this class
is once again the annual report
on the state of protected areas entitled “the
Protected Planet report”.
You can also read the reports of the studies
done by Papaco in Africa in the past few years.
They are on our website www.papaco.org.
Protected areas are known today
to be a useful tool to manage
and to preserve the biological diversity.
Some people even say they are the cornerstone
of conservation strategies.
This explains their dramatic increase in number
and in surface over the recent years.
These protected areas preserve species,
sometimes threatened species, as we can see
here,
specific ecosystems, or rare habitats.
They are trying to preserve the environment
in its natural state
or at least with as little change as possible.
This historical vision of parks and reserves
has changed, though.
From glass case protected zones, protected
areas,
or at least some of them,
are gradually becoming territories of sustainable
environment management,
where human activities,
for instance fishing, when compatible
(and this is very important to underline)
can be integrated
into the management of protected areas and
therefore strengthen their future.
There is obviously a paradox that everyone
can notice:
while the number of protected areas on the
planet
is growing, biodiversity continues to decline.
Let’s have a look at this census analysis
of large mammal species in some parks of Africa,
like in West Africa, as shown here.
Their number decreased by 85% in 35 years
and today there is only 15% of of what was
left in the 70’s
when the number was already quite low.
Let’s remember that this is the case in
protected areas.
Imagine the situation elsewhere!
Let’s also look at this analysis of the
Panthera NGO
in the Mole National Park in Ghana.
We can see that the changes in number of some
herbivores
is catastrophic.
We go from this situation to this one.
There are now many species whose population
is more important outside the areas that are
supposed to protect them
than inside, like the tiger for example;
the number of tigers remaining in the wild
(more or less 3000, in India, in Malaysia,
Russia etc.)
is below the number of tigers held in captivity
in gardens of individuals in the United States
(it is estimated at over 5000)
An example closer to us is the Oryx Dammah,
that we can see in this picture.
He has vanished into thin air.
It only exists in captivity whereas before
it was found in Senegal, in Mali, and in Niger.
However, it is currently subject to a reintroduction
program
in Senegal and in Chad.
The question we can legitimately ask
is whether protected areas are really useful.
I'll let you think about it.
Take 5 minutes to answer this question
for yourself based on your field knowledge.
Gather your arguments.
This is not a pointless question, because
critics of protected areas
are everywhere.
Among the reasons mentioned to explain this
situation,
first there was the fact that some protected
areas are not effective,
either because they were poorly built,
because they lack the means or because they
are poorly managed.
Anyway, they do not achieve their conservation
goals.
Some protected areas are even purely virtual,
hardly existing as a single line on a map,
such as the giraffe reserve of Ansongo Menaka
in Mali,
that I'm showing you here, where there has
been no giraffe
for a long time, and, in reality, no reserve
anymore either.
Here, we can clearly see that the territories
outside
and inside the protected area are the same.
There is no difference between the villages
and the park.
There are many other examples like this one.
We will come back to it.
Another reason commonly mentioned
focuses on the system of protected areas globally
and not on individual sites anymore.
Often incomplete (which means that they do
not include
all places where strong biodiversity issues
exist)
these systems are also often not representative.
Take for example Benin, whose map we can see
here,
and where the two national parks in the country,
the Pendjari here or the W,
are in the same ecosystem in the far north
of the country.
Consequently, other areas, that are different
and
potentially valuable are not protected.
Finally it is these territories' governance
that is questioned,
especially their failure to gain support
of the local populations directly affected
by their existence,
making their protection all the more difficult.
This concept is taking more and more space
with the development of protected areas of
category 6,
where the exploitation of natural resources
is possible,
as we'll soon see.
But be careful, it is not necessarily always
realistic
to think we can consistently associate local
participants;
some protected areas are created to prevent
all human activity,
making the local population's involvement
rather complicated.
But the functions, the roles of the protected
areas
go beyond their simple and essential role
of preservation.
They are places of recreation and of nature
discovery
and they raise awareness among people, young
and old,
on the challenges of conservation.
This is an absolutely essential function,
often underestimated,
while the future of these territories, of
our protected areas,
actually depends on the support of others.
They also offer relatively preserved territories
to conduct the necessary research actions
helping us better understand the world around
us.
They provide goods and services to us all,
to people living in and around protected areas,
of course
(which is easy to understand)
such as forest produce,
bamboo, honey, medicinal plants, etc.
But they also provide to distant places, because
they play a role
in purifying water
in keeping the air devoid of human pollution,
etc, etc.
In this respect, they are also actors of
climate change mitigation
and open laboratories of nature’s evolution
during these changes.
There is a lot to learn about the ecosystem's
ability to adapt.
That’s what we call resilience.
Protected areas also preserve sites
of cultural or spiritual value.
And increasingly, culture and nature intertwine
to form the global value of the territory.
For example, some archaeological sites,
like here in the Great Rift Valley in Kenya,
are preserved within protected areas.
Another interesting example comes from Madagascar,
where some people recognize lemurs,
like this Sifaka, as their ancestors
and thus provide them very strict protection.
Culture and nature can therefore totally support
each other.
Finally, these territories represent today’s
commitment
to the future, the ability to put aside
some resources and wealth for future generations
that may meet their needs when the time comes.
It’s not the least important function of
protected areas
but it’s certainly not the easiest to understand.
Protected areas have so many roles that add
up,
as we have just seen.
Yet they are not sufficient to stem the erosion
of biodiversity,
and fortunately there are other environment-friendly
forms
of territory development
which may also contribute to conservation.
For example, sustainable practices in agriculture,
balanced management of forests,
and infrastructure limiting their impact
on species and on places.
All this must be added up in an attempt to
achieve the expected results
and we can’t rely only on protected areas
if we wish to preserve our environment as
a whole.
So, fortunately, the areas of highest priority
for conservation
are generally well known today.
There are several ways to identify them.
For instance, the eco-regions we can see here,
which were determined by WWF.
Another approach is key biodiversity areas.
The most well-known of which are the important
bird areas,
defined by Birdlife and that we can see
on this map in green.
Based on this data, it is actually quite easy
to prioritise where and how to intervene.
One way to do it is certainly to create new
protected areas
but then again, they alone cannot meet all
challenges
and nature conservation must be understood
as a whole.
Protected areas are only one aspect of it.
That’s the end of the class.
The next episode will focus on the precise
definition of these protected areas.
Have a great day!