Hello.
In today's class we'll look at the definition
of protected areas.
This may seem incidental to you and yet,
it is extremely important as we're going to
see.
The document to consult as a complement to
the class
are the IUCN Guidelines
on management categories.
They are published by the World Commission
on Protected Areas.
So, why should we be interested in this definition?
Well, because, as we have seen,
there are more and more protected areas.
Over 200,000 today covering more than 20 million
km2,
as shown on this graph.
They are more and more complex
as we will see when we look at management
categories
and forms of governance.
Here, we can see the different categories
that will be presented
in our next class.
So, it has become necessary to clarify what
is
and what isn't a protected area so that the
tools,
the knowledge and the practices that are developed
specifically for their management or good
governance
may be put to good use.
The work to define protected areas
already has a relatively long story
which starts in the 1930s,
when experts started to try and clarify
the terminology used to name
all the protected areas then in existence.
Many works followed afterwards,
in the course of international congresses,
parks,
and various meetings that took place,
with a constantly improved definition
that has progressively adjusted to the evolution
of these territories.
The definition currently in force,
which we will look at today,
was set in 2008,
during the World Conservation Congress organised
by the IUCN in Barcelona.
So, let's have a look at this definition.
Charlotte Karibuhoye,
vice-president of the World Commission on
Protected Areas
for Western and Central Africa, presents it
for us.
A protected area is a clearly defined geographical
space,
recognized, dedicated and managed, through
legal or
other effective means,
to achieve the long-term conservation of nature,
with associated ecosystem services,
and cultural values.
It is extremely important to properly understand
each word
and what they represent.
The best way to do that is yet again
to read the Guidelines on the definition carefully.
This isn't very long.
It is covered in chapters 1 and 2 of this
book.
Less than 10 pages in total.
Every word in this definition is important.
I would like to insist here on a few of them
in particular.
They are the words "defined," "recognised,"
"managed"
and of course "conservation of nature."
So, "defined": a protected area
is a territory that can be identified.
We know where it starts and where it ends.
So, this means that its boundaries can be
identified
but this doesn't necessarily require markings,
signs or fences.
Sometimes, it can actually be very difficult
to follow the boundaries of a park,
especially when they are associated with
natural elements like a river or a forest
that can of course change with time.
For example, the Mount Nimba integral reserve
in Ivory Coast:
a part of its boundary was created artificially
in 1944
by planting a bamboo line.
It has of course evolved over time into a
full-blown forest,
which makes it hard today to know where the
reserve starts precisely.
Ok, that might seem of little importance but
when there are mineral resources
which location depends on a few dozen meters,
this can become a serious issue.
This scenario is actually quite frequent.
Let's listen to Isidore talk about it.
The location of the Khuzi-Biega
is confusing in its low altitude part.
Decades ago, at the end of the 1970s
or in the early 80s, we ran experiments.
We lacked solid markers,
so we planted bamboos along the boundaries.
The land is fertile, so over time the bamboos
grew on both sides
of the boundary,
covering at least 30 to 40 meters.
Until today, we are struggling to find the
exact spot
where we planted the first bamboos.
The stump has developed, it's a plant that
thrives very fast.
The stump developed and it's still causing
problems today.
It is often not advisable
to put a plant marker, especially those that
grow fast.
That is really a serious problem.
Let's look at the word "recognised."
A protected area is a human construction.
It may include various territories, ecosystems,
associate various stakeholders,
but it must be recognized at a certain level,
national, international or local.
However, that doesn't necessarily mean there
must be a text -
a decree or a bylaw for example.
So, a protected area may be recognized
by a traditional authority such as for instance
the community of a specific area or sacred
sites
and there are many of them in Africa.
Of course, a protected area may also be recognized
by a private entity
that owns it or an international or local
NGO.
As for the word "managed," a protected area
is a defined recognised territory, as we've
just seen, and it is managed.
This means that decisions are made for this
territory,
so it can't be a mere line on a map,
like those famous paper parks we've mentioned
and will certainly discuss again.
However, this doesn't necessarily imply interventions,
as a management decision may consist for example
in leaving the ecosystem
without any human intervention,
as is the case in some sacred sites that are
completely
off limits or in island reserves
like the Aldabra island in the Seychelles
which you can see here.
Finally, let's talk about the "conservation
of nature."
It is of course the most crucial notion in
the definition.
A protected area is a defined territory
that is recognised and managed to conserve
nature.
So, it is about preserving the environment
as a whole in-situ and long term.
It is nature that is concerned as a whole,
globally.
A zoo for example protects animals but outside
of their environment.
It is not a protected area.
Another example: a military area where grazing
has been deferred for years
will gradually host a wealth of different
species of fauna
and flora.
It's obvious.
But it remains a military area that may be
used as such overnight.
So, it is not a protected area.
There are of course many possible names for
protected areas.
Let's take a few examples that are found in
Africa:
national park, natural reserve, classified
forest,
community area, sacred site, game sanctuary,
marine park.
What matters in order to know whether those
territories are protected areas
is not their name but their final goal.
Some classified forests are protected areas
because they were classified to conserve a
complete ecosystem.
But other forests are only for the production
of timber,
eucalyptus for example, and are not protected
areas.
This applies to all designations.
In conclusion, a protected area is a territory
with certain specific characteristics, as
we've just seen,
and the primary goal of which is the conservation
of nature.
Other territories may also be useful
to protect the environment.
Let's not forget that protected areas
only cover about 15% of the planet.
It's already a lot but it isn't enough.
Fortunately, other areas
also contribute to the preservation of nature.
Now, take some time to think about the different
sites
that you know and try to apply the definition
to see if they are protected areas or not.
Do it with 3 or 4 sites to get used to the
definition.
Also try the reverse exercise and find sites
that are important for nature
but are not protected areas.
You know some of those for sure.
That's it.
We've reached the end of this class.
The next episode will be
on the management categories of protected
areas.
Have a great day!