Hello and welcome to today's class, which
is intended to help us
better understand what the protected area
management categories are.
The reference book to consult as a complement
to the class
is once again the Guidelines
for applying protected area management categories
developed
by the World Commission on Protected Areas.
You can see the publication here.
Let's take this opportunity to listen to Charlotte,
who gave us the definition during the previous
module
and is going to tell us a bit more about this
commission that is very important for us
and which we will discuss again later.
Visit the website of WCPA which I'm showing
you here
as you will find a lot of useful material
there
over the course of this MOOC.
WCPA is the World Commission
on Protected Areas.
It is one of the six specialist groups of
IUCN.
It was created in 1958 and today,
it is managed by the global program of IUCN
on protected areas.
The commission today counts about
1,800 members in 140 countries in the world.
What is interesting is that its mission is
to set up,
or at least promote, an international representative
network
of marine and terrestrial protected areas
that are managed efficiently.
For Africa, we consider that there are two
regions
at the level of WCPA.
There is the West and Central African region
and of course, the East and Southern African
region.
So, I'm going to talk to you mostly about
the West and Central African region
which counts today about 110 members
coming from some 20 countries.
Unfortunately, we have a few countries
that are not yet represented.
But what is great is that in this Commission,
we have members who come from different categories
of stakeholders.
For example, you have directors of protected
areas,
You have specialists – practitioners as
you say –
the protected area managers themselves.
We also have people working
in international organizations.
We have people working in NGOs,
non-governmental organizations.
We also have other experts who don't necessarily
work
on protected areas but work on
other themes in connection with biodiversity
and the protection of nature.
So, it's a really dynamic and inclusive network
that seeks to gather all of the expertise
that we have at the regional level
in terms of protected areas management.
In order to become a member of the World Commission
on Protected Areas,
you must be ready to take an active part
and contribute to the Commission's mission
voluntarily.
So, it's really volunteer work.
To become a member, there are two steps.
First, you must complete an online form.
It is a form you can find on the IUCN website.
The applicant will complete this form
and provide information on his interests,
his expertise and also the way he wishes to
contribute
to the different components of the Commission.
Next, he or she
must send a resume
to the IUCN Secretariat which deals with members.
Then, the resume together with the form will
be analyzed
by the management of the Commission at the
level of
West and Central Africa.
Finally, the person will receive a response
from the Secretariat confirming or not
whether he is officially a member of the Commission
and he will receive at the same time information
on what is expected from a Commission member
and all the advantages you may enjoy as a
WCPA member.
In the previous module, we have learned to
identify what
a protected area is, according to the definition
that I remind you here.
Working on the categories means first inquiring
about the nature of the territory as these
categories only interest us
if the territory is indeed a protected area.
So, the first step is always asking yourself
whether it is indeed a space which main objective
is the conservation of nature.
It is essential.
So, what is the use of these categories?
As we're going to see, they have several possible
uses
but the main one is simply to make it possible
to classify the different protected areas
into rather homogeneous boxes
based on their common characteristics.
Let's take a simple example.
Imagine that one day, you develop a cataract.
You then go to your local clinic
to see your usual ophthalmologist.
But once at the clinic, his secretary tells
you that he's gone on holiday
and will not be back for another month.
But she has an idea and suggests that you
get an operation
from his obstetrician colleague who, granted,
has never performed surgery on an eye but
is always up for a new experience.
In addition, he's very dexterous since
before becoming a surgeon, he was a lumberjack.
What are you going to do?
Are you going to entrust your eyes to this
enthusiastic experimenter?
Are you going to look for another ophthalmologist?
Well, the same holds for protected areas as
for clinics.
They all look alike but they don't all have
the same role,
the same objective or the same management.
So, classifying the more than 200,000 protected
areas of the planet
in different categories, as described on this
graph
that shows the surface covered, will help
us
better identify them, work more specifically
on each of them and develop tools
that are better adapted to their management
or governance style,
according to the different categories that
you see here.
Even if many believe that to be a park custodian
is like being the custodian of any park,
that is not true and there are actually different
jobs,
different profiles, different responsibilities
according to the different protected area
categories.
Being able to distinguish sites according
to their main management objective
is therefore the central function of these
categories.
Now, let's have a look at other possible uses.
By identifying different protected area categories,
you are able to know whether the network
that you manage includes precisely all the
possible methods of management
or whether it is monospecific,
which may suggest that it is incomplete.
On this map for example, we can see the network
of the Ivorian Office of Parks
and Reserves, which includes 14 parks.
You see them here in hatched but all these
parks
belong to only two categories: category 1
and 2.
Why exclude other management methods?
Another similar function relates to governance.
Even though categories refer to the management
objective of a site,
it is often directly or indirectly
related to who will manage the territory.
Having different management categories
is a good way to expand the list of the various
stakeholders
that you will involve in the network.
For example, by creating around the Pendjari
national park -
that you see here - various protected areas
of other categories
(hunting, villages, etc...
another hunting area here),
other areas that are protected areas
but of other categories, the co-management
with other stakeholders
(for example the populations or the hunting
concessions),
may take place
while it would be difficult if you took into
consideration only the park itself.
Another very important function is to be able
to better organize the collection and analysis
of data from the parks.
Since data is better collected when targeting
specific categories,
they are easier to read and to compare between
sites.
Similarly, comparative park evaluations
should only concern sites of the same category,
at the risk of comparing mangoes with bananas
:
an additional good reason to classify our
protected areas
into boxes that make sense.
Other functions are appearing all over the
place.
They are interesting to take into account
for the future in Africa.
In particular, you may create one regulation
for each category and then simply
make a list of parks by category.
In this way, instead of having a usually unreadable
text,
like this text on the Mount Nimba dating from
1944,
or even a lost text, you only have to manage
a list of sites
for which everyone can easily check what is
authorized or not
according to its category.
This leads to more clarity, more transparency
and brings us back to the idea that the staff
of a park should not
move from one site to another at the whim
of transfers
but instead actually go where their skills
are the most needed.
So, categories simply aim at improving the
management
and organization of protected areas by classifying
them better.
And if somewhere, the use of these categories
leads to
the opposite result, it is simply that they
are being used badly.
In particular, you can't decide to change
the category of a park
in order to limit its uses or evict its inhabitants
who had the right to live there until then.
You don't assign a category to a park
to decrease its level of protection.
None of this is the proper use of these categories.
To sum up, categories are simply a tool to
assist
the planning of protected areas.
They are related to the management objective
of the territory,
which is given to us by the classification
text
for a traditional site or the decision
of the authority in charge since - it may
be an oral tradition
in the case of a sacred site for example.
So, you must refer to the objective
in order to determine the management category.
We've reached the end of this class.
The next episode will focus on the categories
themselves.
Have a great day!