Hello and welcome everybody.
Today's class is devoted to the presentation
of the Convention on Biological Diversity.
We are going to review the history, the bodies
and a few recent decisions
of the Convention on Biological Diversity.
I invite you to read the text of the Convention,
which includes only 42 articles,
but also to visit the website of the Convention
which is indicated here.
Biodiversity or biological diversity
means the variability among living organisms
on three levels:
genes (these are genetic resources),
species (the species level) and ecosystems
(the habitat).
The biological resources of Earth are vital
for the economic and social development of
mankind.
Consequently, there is an increasingly greater
recognition
that biological diversity is a global asset
of incalculable value to present and future
generations.
At the same time, to date, the threats to
species
and ecosystems have never been greater.
The extinction of species because of human
activities
has continued at an alarming pace.
In 1988 the United Nations Environment Programme
convened
the ad hoc working group of experts on biological
diversity
in order to explore the creation of an international
convention
on biological diversity.
The Convention was opened for signature on
5 June 1992,
during the United Nations Conference on Environment
and Development,
the Earth Summit of Rio.
Nowadays, 196 countries are contracting parties
to the Convention on Biological Diversity.
The Convention on Biological Diversity has
three main objectives:
the conservation of biological diversity,
the sustainable use of its component
and the equitable sharing of the benefits
arising out of their utilization.
These are its three main objectives as stated
in its article 1.
These three aspects, conservation, sustainable
use
and sharing of benefits,
are at the root of the whole philosophy of
conservation
since the Rio Summit.
It is important for you to know this and assess
its impact.
Other articles are important to us.
For example, article 8 on in-situ conservation,
article 9 on ex-situ conservation and article
10 on the sustainable use
of components of biological diversity
are very relevant for protected areas.
Article 8 has 13 paragraphs that are all of
interest to us.
Pay them special attention.
In particular, paragraph a of article 8
on the establishment of a system of protected
areas,
paragraph b on the development, where necessary,
of guidelines
for the selection, establishment and management
of protected areas
and paragraph h on the prevention of the introduction,
control or eradication of alien species which
threaten
ecosystems, habitats or species.
Through these articles, what does the CBD
remind us?
Protected areas are the cornerstone
of the conservation of biodiversity.
They preserve key habitats, offer sanctuaries,
allow for the migration and displacement of
species,
and maintain natural processes
in the whole landscape.
Protected areas don't just safeguard
the preservation of biodiversity.
They also ensure the well-being of mankind.
Protected areas allow some 1.1 billion people
to survive,
are the main source of drinkable water
for over a third of the world's largest cities,
and offer a major guarantee for global food
security.
The bodies of the Convention are the following:
the Conference of the Parties
(it gathers all signatories
and meets every two years
in order to review the implementation of the
Convention);
the Subsidiary Body in charge of providing
scientific, technical and technical advice;
the Intergovernmental Committee for the Nagoya
Protocol
which we will discuss in a later module;
the Working Group on Protected Areas
(as there is a specific programme
of the Convention in charge of protected areas).
The Convention has a Strategic Plan
for Biodiversity for 2011-2020,
in which are defined the famous Aichi Biodiversity
Targets,
which there are 20 of.
We will talk about this in more detail in
the next module.
The CBD also has mechanisms for implementation
and a framework for cooperation and partnership.
The Conference of the Parties is the governing
body of the Convention.
It advances implementation of the Convention
through the decisions it takes at its periodic
meetings.
Over 23 years, the Convention on Biological
Diversity has taken
a little more than 250 decisions, including
several on the creation,
governance and restoration of terrestrial
and marine protected areas.
Recent decisions taken by the Convention illustrate
topical subjects.
For instance, integrating biological diversity
in the United Nations Development Programme
and the sustainable development goals,
ensuring that biological diversity serves
the fight against poverty
and for sustainable development,
promoting the sustainable use of biological
diversity,
for example through bushmeat and the sustainable
management of wildlife.
Other types of decisions:
the inclusion of gender equality concerns;
an increasingly important issue also focuses
on the conservation
and restoration of ecosystems;
and finally, the CBD recognises the need to
improve the efficiency of the structures
and mechanisms of the Convention,
in particular the work of the Subsidiary Body
on Implementation.
The Convention on Biological Diversity is
a multilateral agreement
on the environment which seeks to protect
and restore the global environment
and contributes to sustainable development.
The work undertaken under the Convention has
increased in volume
and specificity and has an increasingly important
impact,
especially due to the growing attention paid
to issues
of implementation.
More and more, governmental officials from
all over the world
participate in international negotiations
in the framework of the Convention on Biological
Diversity.
Their work, their decisions, their recommendations
have a daily impact
on what we do or want to do in protected areas
in Africa.
But we have to remember that this is first
and foremost a multilateral agreement,
which requires a lot of consensus and that
this may sometimes limit
the impact of the decisions that are taken.
That's it.
This is the end of this class.
The next episode will be the conclusion of
this module in the form
of a short animation and of course,
the assignment suggested for this week.
In the meantime, have a great day!