Here we are now at the end of the first module
on the general presentation of protected areas,
and on a few essential concepts
for a good understanding of those territories.
The key points that we have addressed this
week
are the following:
First off, there are more and more protected
areas
and they are more and more diverse.
From a few ones in the dawn of the 20th century,
they are now more than 200,000
all kinds of them, big and small,
forest, mountains, marines and deserts.
This diversity is their strength,
but requires more skills
from their managements,
and more efforts to conserve them.
Those protected areas are indispensable tools
for nature conservation.
And even if they do not always
halt the decline of the biodiversity of the
planet,
they are part of the solution that will eventually
help us achieve this
and, as such, they deserve our full attention.
However, they are evolving and turning more
and more
towards the inclusion of local populations
and the production of related natural services.
All territories called protected areas have
something in common.
The reason why they exist: the conservation
of nature.
There are many other territories
that can contribute to protect the environment,
but the specificity of protected areas is
that this is their main purpose,
it is somehow their trademark.
Finally to help us better understand and identify
them,
those protected areas are grouped into six
categories
based on their primary objective of management.
For category I, what prevails is nature protection;
For category II, it's to preserve nature
in organizing activities like tourism, research,
or education.
Category III aims at conserving a natural
monument
like a cave or a mountain.
In category IV, we actively manage the environment,
to maintain a particular environment or a
species,
Category V, is interested in preserving a
landscape, an ecosystem
that has been shaped by man.
Finally, Category VI, allows for
the sustainable use of natural ressources
for the benefit of populations.
These categories range from a very strict
preservation of ecosystems
to the sustainable use of ressources
that accommodate many interventions of man.
But the first intention is always the conservation
nature.
There you have it, you can now start the homework
of this module.