Welcome back to part two of this chapter.
We shall continue the
discussion of Chapter One
by showing
the historical picture
of the spectrum of ethanol
recorded in 1951.
Different isotopes
may have different spins.
First of all, there are
quite a few isotopes,
such as the ubiquitous carbon-13,
which is found in all organic matter.
Oxygen-16, also all over the place,
has no spin at all,
although it has
a charged nucleus, of course.
And the nucleus
may well be spinning around.
Why should it not?
Yet it does not have a spin and so
the magnetic quantum number
can only be zero
and there are no transitions.
One cannot do any NMR at all.
There are a series
of important nuclei
that have a spin one-half
and that are actually very popular
in NMR spectroscopy
and MRI imaging.
Some nuclei, some isotopes
have a spin quantum number equal to one,
mostly deuterium, nitrogen-14,
and lithium-6.
Some of them have a quantum
number I of three-halves.
Typical examples are boron-11,
sodium-23, chlorine-35 and chlorine-37.
By the way, sodium
can be nicely observed in NMR.
And then some have the spin five-halves,
such as oxygen-17
and aluminum-27 which is actually
very interesting to observe
in aluminosilicates.
Finally, some have a spin three.
And there are some exotic
examples that go beyond.
Not only do they have spin,
but they have different gammas,
i.e., different gyromagnetic ratios.
The gyromagnetic ratio
is an inherent property
of different isotopes
The different gammas have been given using proper units
of inverse teslas and inverse seconds.
That means that if you
multiply them with 9.4 tesla,
the proton NMR frequency
appears at 400 MHz,
and the
deuterium NMR frequency
at about 61 MHz,
and carbon-13 near 100 MHz.
You should remember that there is
a factor of about one-quarter here
and you might also wish to remember
that there is a factor
of about one-tenth between the proton
and nitrogen-15 frequencies.
These frequencies have
been given
for a field of 9.4 tesla
because that is very common
in the current world of chemistry
and physics.
There are many, many spectrometers
that operate at 400 MHz
because that is reasonably cheap
and yet very effective.
We also see that the natural
abundance of these isotopes
varies a great deal.
For example, deuterium
is only found in 0.015%
of ordinary sea or rain water.
So that's not very much
and you may wish to enrich it
if you want to observe deuterium.
Carbon-13 is about 1% abundant.
It can be observed directly
but, of course, you can boost it
by enhancing the population differences
or by labelling the molecules
with carbon-13.
Nitrogen-14 has nearly 100 % abundance
but is very difficult to observe
because it has a very large
quadrupole splitting.
As you can see,
nitrogen-14 has a spin I = 1.
And this is one of the isotopes we have
worked on in Lausanne
over the last few years.
Nitrogen-15 is very popular
in biomolecules
because you can enhance it synthetically
by cloning techniques
in proteins
but it is still challenging.
Fluorine-19 is very popular
because it has a very high abundance,
100%, and also because one
can find fluorine-19 in many
drug molecules but not in
natural living matter.
Silicone-29 is popular
for those studying silicates
and aluminosilicates.
And phosphorus is very popular
in biochemistry because there are
many important phosphates
in living organisms.
So you see, every isotope has a
characteristic spin quantum number.
Now, there are some rules about
these quantum numbers.
For example, if the number of protons
and the number of neutrons
are both even, then the resulting
spin quantum number is zero.
That is the case for carbon-12
and oxygen-16.
But you can also have cases
where both protons
and neutrons appear in odd numbers.
Then we have integer quantum numbers,
such as one, two or three.
They can be even and odd
or odd and even
and in either case, we have
so called half-integer spins.
Actually, these rules
are not particularly useful.
It is better to look at
the full table.
The electromagnetic spectrum
is very wide.
It ranges from very high frequencies
and very short wave lengths
to very low frequencies
and very long wave lengths.
In spectroscopy, gamma rays are used
in Mössbauer spectroscopy
that uses very high energies,
higher than x-rays, which in turn
are more energetic than
ultra-violet and visible light.
Next we have the infra-red range
and below that the microwave range
and, much lower, we have the
radio-frequency range.
This has several consequences.
First of all, radio-frequency fields
are largely innocuous.
Nobody really worries that when
you listen to a radio
that you might
get irradiated by the transmitters
or by the receivers. Indeed, radio-frequency
irradiation is quite innocuous,
which has great advantages for MRI.
Radio-frequencies also can penetrate
through all sorts of tissues
including living humans.
Again, you can check with your radio
that it works even if you lie
on top of it, and that is one reason
why MRI is so popular.
Whereas imaging opaque
humans with visible light
is, of course, very difficult.
NMR has other advantages
because we have a great
spread of frequencies.
On a scale where 400 MHz
corresponds to NMR of protons,
you see that fluorine-19
appears in the vicinity.
Phosphorous-31 is somewhat below
and then the ubiquitous
carbon-13 appears at about 100 MHz.
But if we have a
high-resolution spectrometer
that can resolve different
chemical shifts,
then one can distinguish
various types of protons.
So for example, at the top end
we have aldehyde protons,
at the bottom end, aliphatic protons.
Zero ppm actually corresponds by convention
to tetramethylsilane (TMS).
This range spans about 4 kHz
out of 400 MHz
which corresponds to 10 ppm,
and indeed that is the common
scale used here.
So the frequencies of NMR transitions
are typically in the range
between 10 and 1,000 MHz.
Incidentally, the world's
most powerful machine
has indeed 1,000 MHz for protons.
You can visit it in Lyon in France.
We shall consider a nucleus
with a magnetic moment µ,
This magnetic moment is
immersed in a magnetic field.
We can orient this magnetic field
so that it's parallel to the z-axis
or if you prefer, we can simply
align the z-axis
of our coordinate system
with the field.
In that case, all we have to worry about
is the product of the z component
of the magnetic moment and
the amplitude of the field.
It turns out that this z component
is determined by the product of m,
the magnetic quantum number,
h-bar, Planck’s constant
divided by 2 pi,
gamma, the gyromagnetic ratio,
and the amplitude of the field.
Remember that m
can be plus or minus one-half.
If I is equal to one-half,
m is either
plus or minus one half.
The splitting in energy
is simply
h-bar times the absolute
value of gamma times B.
And the NMR frequency
is the same as the splitting
divided by h, and
divided by two pi.
Now for a spin one-half, we have either
m equal plus one-half
and we call this the alpha level,
or we have m equal minus one-half
and we call this the beta level
and we have a single transition.
So this is the case for a spin one-half.
But if we have a spin one,
such as for deuterium
or for nitrogen-14,
then we have three possibilities.
We have m = either minus one,
or zero, or plus one,
and indeed we have three different levels.
It turns out that the obvious
nomenclature alpha, beta, gamma
is not common in our business,
so we just use these quantum numbers.
If a nucleus with I = 1,
which could be a deuterium
or a nitrogen-14, is dissolved
in an isotropic liquid,
then it turns out that the
energy splitting between the top
and middle levels
is exactly the same as the energy
splitting between the middle
and bottom levels.
So these two transitions are degenerate.
When we see a single line like this,
actually half of it
comes from the top transition
and half from the bottom transition.
Whereas in this case, for protons,
for example,
there is really only one transition.
So let's attempt to summarize
the main points
of the introductory chapter.
First of all, every isotope
in the periodic table
has a characteristic spin
quantum number I.
Some isotopes have I = 0,
in which case it is
just impossible to do NMR.
This is the case for carbon-12
and the only way to rescue the situation
is by replacing carbon-12 nucleus
by a carbon-13.
Every isotope with I
different from zero
has a characteristic magnetic moment µ.
Nuclear spins have 2I + 1
distinct energy levels
labelled by magnetic
quantum numbers m,
which can vary from minus I
to plus I, in steps of one.
In a magnetic field,
the energy levels are split
by an amount that is proportional
to the size of the nuclear magnetic moment
and to the strength of the magnetic field.
NMR spectroscopy uses
electromagnetic radiation
to induce transitions
between energy levels.
The frequencies of NMR transitions
are typically in the range
between 10 and 1,000 MHz.
The intensities of NMR signals
depend on the differences
of the populations of the energy levels.
These populations are determined
by Boltzmann’s law,
thus by the temperature, by the field
and by the gyromagnetic ratio
and all of these parameters conspire
to make NMR a rather
insensitive technique.  This is
in fact Achilles’ heel of NMR.
One often needs
very concentrated samples
or very long experimental times
to get decent signals and
sufficient information.
And this is one of the reasons
why so many NMR spectroscopists
are trying to improve the methods.
Thank you.