Hello my name is Francois Ave and I will show you in this MOOC, the different information
you can get using scanning electron microscopy characterization of the
microstructure of semanticist material.
We first need to understand how a microscope works and what happens when electrons are sent to
assemble and heat the surface of the material.
So the first question we could ask is Why do we use electrons rather than visible light.
The first approach for observing the macro structure is to use an optical microscope, using
light as the source of emissions. However the resurrection of
light microscope is limited by the wavelength of visible light between 400 to 800
nanometers. The wavelength of electrons is actually much smaller
around 1 to 10 Pico meters. It is to observe much smaller objects
and to get a much better resolution in the case of electron microscopy the
resolution is actually not limited by the wavelength of electrons but by the
aberrations inside of microscope which are kinds of physical deviations
caused by the microscope lenses. The most common type of microscopy to observe the
microstructure of semanticist materials is the scanning electron microscope which is
actually more accessible and easier to use when transmission electron microscopic
in a scanning electron microscope, electrons are emitted from
the different source the best for a series of lenses which focus them
and then the electrons reach the surface of the sample.
And they go a series of elastic inelastic collisions with
the atoms of the simple, different
signals can be collected from these collisions. When we talk about the scanning
electron microscope it means that actually the face of a simple would be analyze
point by point and the final image is actually
the assemblage of the information from all this point.
An insolent electron as you can see here, faces a series of interactions
before its energy is fully dissipated. Thus all these
interactions from this incident electron and the elections of the sample
does not occur exactly the entering point of the electrons
but occur in a more global volume which is called the interaction volume
these interactions can be either elastic we've no energy loss or
Inelastic, the first kind of interaction which can occur between the
electron and the atoms of a simple is if an incident
electron, as one here, collides with an electron
Of the atom of the sample, from this collision the incident
electron deviated like this, and bound electron is ejected
this ejected electron is called a secondary electron or also called SE
the energy of the secondary electrons is typically lower than 50 electon volt
which is actually very small, verse if electrons
want to be collected by a detector. They have to be formed very close to the samples surface
even deeper in a sample then electrons would face some interaction
before reaching a simple surface that would be absorbed in the sample due to very low
energy and they would not be collected by a secondary electron detector.
So verse the contrast we can obtain will be secondary electrons is a
typography contrast as you can see here. Here is shown three
points where incident electrons are sent
and you can see that actually this volume here is a volume where secondary direction can
escape and then be then detected. And you can see that at the edges
more electrons can escape the surface. And this verse can be collected.
This means that on the image on these specific points
we get more signal and we have a brighter contrast.
This is called the edge effect. Another kind of interaction which can occur
is when an incident electron feels the Coolum
interactions with a nucleus of an atom of assemble this incident
electron is deviated because of this Coolum interaction.
If this division leads to higher angle diffusion, then the
electron can leave the surface and it can be
collected by the backscattered electron detector. So this electrons which is
scattered back is called backscatter the electrons or BSE
this interaction is almost elastic. There is almost no energy transfer
which means that the energy of the back scattered electrons is very similar to the energy
of the incident beam, so which information can be obtained with
backscatter electrons?
Well, the Coolum false, we have a nucleus increases with the
atomic number that, indeed with increase of the atomic
Number, the number of positive charges of the atom increases, thus the incidence
electron has a higher likelihood to be deviated if more electrons are
deviated more will also be collected, thus the contrast will be brighter
at the image for a higher set of the atom. This graph here shows
you that brightness increases with the atomic
number which is even best character coefficient which is related to the intensity of the signal
as a function of the atomic number and you can see that if you have a material
with a higher average said inside, then you see that actually you will see something
brighter on your image because you will collect more backscatter electrons.
The third kind of interaction which is very useful for the characterization of a microstructure
of semanticist materials is the formation of characteristic X-rays
after the ignition of a secondary electron shown here.
An electron is missing in the layer of
the atom. This atom is ionized.
If this missing electron originates from an inner electron shell of the atom
this atom is energetically unstable. In order to reach a
more favorable energetic level, energy form falls
from an outer shell with a higher energy to
fill the vacancy, these release of energy during this
relaxation phenomenon leads to the formation of an X-ray.
And what is important is that the energy of the X-ray is related to the
energy difference of the two shell levels here.
Thus the energy of these x rays is characteristic of the atom they come
From. Every element these x rays come from can first be
identify and the atom content can be quantified for a selected
spot of microstructure. This image shows you
how the chamber of a microscope looks like. So you have here the end of a column, So
this is the incident beam coming here, leading from the hall to the
Chamber. So the sample holder is right below here. So you sent elections to the
sample you will have all these interactions which will be corrected by different defectors
We have here the secondary electron defector which is green on top
the Golden plate here is this BSC detector and the EDA detector is that it
is right at the back of it hidden. So we can collect all of its information in
one microscope. These three types of interactions are very useful to
characterize the microstructure of semanticist materials, even next session you
will see how to set a nice image and some applications of these three types of
interactions for semanticist materials. The first application
for secondary electrons is the study of the mythology of
particles. You can see here. You have two very nice
images showing you of a mythology here of killing night  particles to an
anhydrous material. And here for the growth of CSH. So we choose
hydration product at a very early age of hydration.
These secondary entrance are used because of its topography contrast which permit to really see
Nicely the morphology of a particles. This analysis is only
qualitative. We can't get any quantitative analysis from this study. But still.
It permit to really have a look the
different mythologies we can find in some indigenous materials. So after talking about.
Secondary electrons, we can now focus on backscatter electrons.
To do so, It's always better to prepare
Simple as a polished cross-section. As you saw
before in the Sample preparation, of course.
So the sample is put in a sample holder like this we just Clip it.
And then we will install it Inside a microscope. So the chamber of a
microscope is always in the vacuum to avoid any contamination.
And first vacuum was broken using nitrogen gas. And then the sample
is gently put on the sample stage. We
use a small giraffe, just check the height of a simple to make sure that we're not too far
from the good focus and then we close the chamber and we apply a vacuum
again. So now the sample is inside of a
microscope and we just waited for a good vacuum to be done to make sure that
we won't have any contamination. Moreover it's very important to have a good vacuum
otherwise the electrons which are sent to a sample could
interact with air molecules inside of a chamber. So it's very important to remove as much as possible
air molecule present inside the chamber. When the
vacuum is good enough we can start applying a voltage which
will lead to an emission of a current, emission of electrons sent
to a simple you just click HV here, And we will see an
image appearing on the screen. We start collecting
Backscattered electrons and this is the contrast. You can see there. We have some really great
Contrast showing the backscattered electrons collected and
So the different phases we've seen some semanticist material. As you can
see the image is a big blur.
Because we're not exactly in focus. So first we need to set the focus to make
sure that we have the best resolution possible. So to change our focus. We
Simply adjust the z position of the stage to make sure that the symbol is a
good height, and the working distance. So we can see
here the typical microstructure of a plane Portland cement sample
for which the hydration was stopped at 20 days, so
different areas can be clearly distinguished. We can first observe
bright gray areas.
These bright areas correspond to anhydrous Clinker grains
between these anhydrous grains a metrics of hydration products
fills the space, fill with porosity with time
so in these bright grains we can clearly identify (12:29) with this angular
shape of grains which can also see that for some grains we
have not only one great contrast but civil at the same time which means
that actually Clinker grains are polyphased and not all monophased
so I put on this screen some faces which are likely to be
There, with b c you cannot directly know what is what. But we can
demonstrate it we can prove it later.
Doing and EDX on these phases. Concerning the
hydration products you can first easily identify bottom diets or
calcium hydroxide or C.H. Is this kind of uniform microstructure you can see
here. Uniform Greeneville
which is actually brighter than the other hydrate, otherwise the
main phase filling the rest of porosity is this CSH phase as you can
see everywhere we can see either outer CSH.
Also inners CSH which grew inside the initial boundary
of clinker grains
Intricate can also be absurd.
This kind of needles Yeah.
And the rest which is black is the
porosity which is dark is the porosity. Why is the porosity
dark? simply because we are sending electrons to response and we do
not collect anything back which is why the contrast is darkening this.
another question we could ask is why is the contrast of anhydrous phases brighter?
because hydrated phases contain water.
Which significantly decreased the average age coefficient of the phrase.
Or less dense which makes them look darker on the
image. So we can have a look at plane PC systems but also that
means the rest of using it seems to look at over type of balance. Here is an
example of limestone calcined clay cement or LC3 at one day of hydration.
In this system the clay used is not a pure calcined clay of pure
matter counting but it's a clay with only 50 percent of
of kaolinite calcined inside. So the microstructure
shows some differences. Compared to the plane cement of 74.
First we can observe limestone particles here, here, here,
also there. We've got a regular shape with a small rim of
CSH green and the surface.
In LC3 in limestone calcined clay cement.
Also of course observe calcined clay particles. And what you can see with these
Calcined clay particles like here, here, here, also there, there also
is that the grille all is not uniform everywhere.
Why so it means that we have actually impurities in calcined clay, as I said
before this clay here contains only 50 percent of gelignite which means that the rest
is impurities. For instance this particle here on the top
of this image shows a much brighter area on the right side.
And this indicates that there is likely to have
elements with higher atomic number or higher Z  in this area
which is likely to be actually a narrow any impurity in the calcined clay
so we have best scattered electron imaging we can have very
nice information on the repetition of the
phases in the microstructure. But for the identification of phases
we do not have any evidence, any clinical evidence of a phases.
Let just try now to carry out immediate analysis on this macro structure to
identify several phases that we assumed to be present before
on this video is shown the quantification of A-light phase
we spots several points of
A-light in these grain here and we're going to start.
With the EDX analysis to get the chemical composition of a phase
as you can see the quantification is very fast. And now we can have a look at the
results for EDX there are some tricks
to be aware of. First it is impossible to quantify hydrogen
as we saw before. To form an X-ray we need to
have an negatron fall from an upper player of the atom, for hydrogen
is impossible because there is only one electron. So we cannot quantify hydrogen.
EDX another thing is that the quantification of oxygen
and other light elements is not extremely reliable.
Because of the extremely low energy you need to ionized
oxygen and the other light elements. So it's not very
accurate. Thus it is better actually to
use atomic ratios from the chemical analyzes than
direct values collected on the software.
For instance fossil ferrous here instead of looking at the absolute value of things
we can have a look at the calcium to silicon ratio. We know that in a light
we should have calcium  to silicon ratio close to three not to make calcium to silicon ratio close to three
which is the case here. So
this evidence is the presence of C3S in this grain
we can do so for all of the other phases and hydrous or hydrates to evidence their
presence in the microstructure.
The main issue for EDX analyzes is the
interaction volume we talked about at the beginning of this talk
When a specifics sport is pointed actually the information which we
collect does not come from this point only but comes from the
interaction volume related to this point which is a few microns. Right.
So if we are pointing just at the border between two phases it is very likely to have information
from both phase.
This is an issue of a determination of a C(-A)-S-H
composition so CSH and C(-A)-S-H are roughly the
same thing. It's just that when very the significant incorporation of aluminum in
this CSH we call it a C(-A)-S-H, in the case of LC3
For instance we call it C(-A)-S-H. So when we point the CSH
Here, it is extremely likely to have information on other phases
at the same time. Thus the
idea to get an accurate composition of a CSH is to use
2D scatter plots to deal with intermixing problem.
How does it work? The best way of doing it is to plot's the aluminum
to calcium ratio here, the atomic composition aluminum to calcium ratio as a function of a
Silicon to Calcium ratio. Why do we do that?
Because the intermixing which can occur with Portlandite or calcium hydroxide
can be directly observed. These phases I
just mention are present on the left axes here because they didn't contain any
silicon this way we can isolate the points which
are really CSH from points which are coming with a bit
of information of these pure phases here. But on that engaging
in and if you do that. So this is for
a new PC system at 20 days of hydration and 93 system of 20 day of hydration.
We can collect approximately 200 points per system
and we get these kind of clouds of data
so if we have to look closer to the PC system for instance we have a cloud of
data around this composition here. And we have some point deviating and
going for instance here towards spot on that if we take for instance this point
here which is roughly in the middle between CH and this cloud of
SH it means that for this point we have information
approximately about half of from C.H. from part on that and the from this CSH.
Now how to find the exact CSH composition
you have a cloud of data here. The more you are on the left
side of his cloud the more you are in damage with other phases
which means that's the rights correct CCH composition
is at the right age of a cloud.
So you can use these tine lines from Compton
from these phases we've fixed stricken metrical composition to help you
to find the re-composition the intersection of these lines from pothlandite, atrogite
and A.F.M phases should give you a very good CSH composition
and what you can see when you can apply it to different systems which is the case here.
So we have OPC and this is the system and what we can see is that we have really strong
differences in terms of CSH composition within the system. We have a strong
silicon and aluminum incorporation in the CSH. This is a kind of
valuable information you can get from EDX analysis
another thing which you can do with EDX which is more global I'd
say is to get a phase distribution not only on some
points but on the whole map in your system which is an example is
shown here for an OPC system.
So you simply select the elements you want aluminum, silicon, calcium, magnesium,
Iron, oxygen, potassium, sodium, sulfur and you can
actually acquire and ADX but not on a couple of points but on
each point of your map so of course this takes more time.
But this also gives us some valuable indication on the phase distribution inside your
microstructure. So that's a very nice example
of how we can use microscope for semanticist materials.
There are many other applications which can be
studied with a scanning electron microscope for instance
we serve a porosity scan of dark area and the microstructure
This porosity which is of course a kind of curve porosity like Kosovan
approximately one micron can be quantified using image
analyzes and we can get a rough estimation on the porosity of a system
the size distribution of particles can also be determined. It's qualitative
busted. It can be. It can give us an idea about the distribution of
of a particle size. Another thing we can do with
them is to look at the Grealy whole sense of know see
what you can see here that is just microstructure for instance with temperature
we can see that we know that the density of its porosity changes and depending on the
agreeable intensity we can't celebrate it and know how much it changes
with temperature. Finally mapping can also
be very useful to characterize the damage. For instance or actually see care reaction.
It is extremely useful to follow the direction of a song
and to know where the damage is and what really happens then we to better understand
mechanisms of these interactions. To sum up what is so
stunning electron microscopy is one of the most powerful technique for a study of
semanticist materials. We can do really many different
things with scanning electron microscope from Topographic imaging to
Basket electron imaging from chemical analysis. And there are really many
applications for which scanning electron microscope pretty pennies to better
understand what's going on in a semanticist is material.
Thank you for watching.