Let's continue now to explore
an elementary vocabulary,
useful to address space.
In contemporary societies,
realities can be classified
into three major categories--
actors, objects and environments.
Let's define each of these terms.
Actors are the opposite of agents.
The notion of actor means that societies
are animated by operators,
who are endowed
with a strategic competence.
The emergence of the actor
in social sciences
has also been called
the pragmatic turn.
Its concrete significance
is mainly that individuals
can be actors of their lives--
certainly not at a hundred percent level,
but not at zero percent either.
In spite of its oversimplicity,
the image of a moving cursor can be useful
as it makes a variability of a given
actor's power and capabilities
easily understandable.
Besides, actors are actors also,
because of their reflexivity,
which allows them to take
advantage of situations
where they cannot get everything,
but have to arbitrate between
different imperfect options.
This approach is actually underpinned
by the criticism of
the structuralist paradigm,
which was dominant in the social
sciences of the 1960s and 70s.
Structuralism does not recognize
the existence of actors,
but only of agents.
Structuralist approaches encompass
four major theoretical bodies--
Marxism; psychoanalysis;
structural anthropology--
which gave birth to culturalism;
and structural linguistics.
After several attempts
to impose themselves,
separately or together,
as an orthodoxy in social sciences,
these theories have experienced
a dramatic decline.
However, in the North American mainstream,
in geography or sociology,
the structuralist approach
is still deep-rooted.
It is often self-denominated
as post-structuralist,
but it could be called
neo-structuralism,
because new structures,
such as race or gender,
have been added to
the traditional notion of class,
in the Marxist approach.
A generalization of the ahistorical vision
proposed by structural anthopology
has also been incorporated
through the polysemic
and slippery term of 'culture'.
If we look at what social sciences
consider as dynamic realities,
objects are also something new.
The philosopher Bruno Latour
uses the term actants
to make more tangible the idea
that manufactured items,
natural, non-human realities,
or mental and immaterial realities,
are active in social interactions.
In the case of artefacts or machines,
as well as for institutional realities,
such as organizations, religions
or political ideologies,
their creator's intentions are obviously
embedded in their very flesh
and interact with users' intentionality.
However, even in the case of objects
coming from the biophysical worlds,
we find realities that are not
intentional at their starting point,
but which are included
in systems of social actions.
For instance, a bear is not an actor,
and is not part of the same
intentional complex,
if it lives in the wild,
in a natural reserve,
in a zoo, or in a circus,
but in each case, it plays an active
role related to the performance
of different human actors involved.
Finally, the notion an environment
can seem neutral and banal,
but is significant by its own existence.
The decisive point is that
an environment is approached
on the same level as actors and objects.
An environment is an encompassing reality,
that conditions, partially determines,
and pre-figures the realities,
objects and actors it encompasses,
but these encompassed realities
are active too,
and can modify the environment.
In other terms, an environment
can condition the actors,
but actors can destroy an environment.
Societies are of course environments,
but the components of our societies,
such as the working place, or a family,
can also be considered environments.
Space is an environment.
There are natural environments,
but there are also purely artificial ones.
As we can see in this diagram,
there are different combinations
of the relationship
between an individual actor
and the environment, the society
as a whole, represents.
At one extreme, milieu--
a weak actor needs society,
embodied in welfare state
or public policies, to survive.
At the other extreme,
the citizen actor maximizes
their capacities
in order to try and change
the societal environment
through political agency.
In between, we find climates
and affordances,
where the respective powers
of actors and the environment
are more balanced.
Till now, we have used space
as a generic term,
meaning any kind of reality
is defined by distance relations
between other realities.
At this stage, it can be useful
to distinguish space and spatiality.
Space is an environment defined
by relations of distance
between its components
and with other spaces.
Spatiality is the part of human agency
related to distance relations.
Thus, space is spatial
as an environment,
and spatiality is spatial as a set
of actions, as agency.
Spaces impose their conditions
to actors,
and actors develop spatialities
that modify those spaces.
The notion of geographicity appear
then as an overarching concept,
encompassing both space and spatiality.
Geographicity can be defined as a spatial
dimension of the social worlds,
that is, human worlds.
An important distinction
should be made now
between place and area.
A place is a type of space in which
distance is non relevant.
An area is a set of places separated
by a relevant distance.
From microlocal situations
to the world,
any space can be seen either
as a place, or as an area.
For instance, a city is a place,
if it is addressed as a whole
interurban approach,
but it is an area when understood
as a set of districts,
or neighorhoods--
intra-urban approach.
This distinction is fundamental
because it gives a concrete, pragmatic
significance to scale thresholds.
We switch from a level to another
when we consider, as in the case
of intra-, inter-urban,
that what was a place becomes
an area-- downscaling.
Or what was an area becomes
a place-- upscaling.
Scale is a relation between
the size of spatial realities
and other characteristics
of these realities.
It defines significant thresholds
that make a space switch
from place to area.
A metrics is a way of measuring
and managing distance.
There exists an infinity of metrics.
We can classify the different
categories of metrics
from their internal style,
or from the perspective of their limits.
Traditional geography was obsessed
with a country model,
that is to say, a territory locked
by clear cut borders,
but many other types of spaces exist.
We can observe that there are
many other combinations of metrics.
Territories and networks
are the simplest and the most significant
distinctions between spaces.
Finally, everything in a society
has a spatial dimension,
but society possesses other dimensions.
Substance identifies the non-spatial
part of spatial realities.
Substance matters.
The space generated by a company
is not the space of an individual,
or of a State.
A major distinction among substances
is between society--
social world as totality,
and social-- social world
as a component of a society.
Scale, metrics and substance
are inter-related.
You can't define one of them
without considering the others.
Taken together, they represent
the minimal compulsory set of attributes
of any space or spatiality.
In other words, it's impossible to define
an elementary spatial configuration,
or chorotype,
without any of the three components.
If we consider now how spaces
interact with each other,
we can identify three major
categories of inter-spatialities.
Interface is the most classic.
It connects horizontally
juxtaposed spaces.
An example-- two countries meeting
each other at their joint border.
The second inter-spatiality is nesting.
It's characterized by the inclusion
of one space in another larger space,
like Russian dolls.
The arrangement of political territories
is a common nesting configuration.
In the case of federal systems,
we have mimetic, non-hierarchical nesting.
As a matter of fact,
each tier reproduces
the same kind of institutions
as below and above,
and enjoys comparable competences.
Finally, cospatiality
is a vertical connection
between different spatial layers,
through connectors.
For instance, a railway network
and a city,
thanks to a railway station.
We can imagine a superposition
of layers without connectors,
and in this case, cospatiality
doesn't occur.
For instance, individual layers
in a city may not interact
if there are no opportunities
for them to do so.
In this case, the city of each individual
cannot become the city of all.
Similarly, the global economic network,
and the territorial partition of States,
are not directly connected.
They are not cospatial.
We will see in Session 6
that synchronization may be seen
as a fourth category of interspatiality.
So far, we have placed some cornerstones
that help us to address the spatial
dimension of social worlds.
By doing this, we have taken on,
in an implicit way,
a particular concept of space which
underpins these first statements.
This table shows that, historically,
conceptions of space have been
controversial on two major points.
The first one is about the absolute
or relative nature of space.
Is space a pre-existing box
where things are located?
Or is space a changing configuration
linked to what is spatialized?
The second position
is about the positional
or relational character of space,
where the measurement
of a space be the same,
carried out, for instance,
through Euclidean geometry,
independently from interactions
between the realities that compose it?
Or is redefining the rules of measurement,
each time we observe
a new set of spatially interacting
realities, required?
These debates were very active
in the 17th and 18th Centuries
but eventually the practice of scientific
research settled the argument.
As the table shows, although
contemporary social sciences of space
have not completely converged on these
fundamental conceptualizations,
we can contend that, by and large,
the relative relational conception--
that of Leibniz,
has clearly got an overwhelming
cognitive advantage,
because it is consistent with
a dimensional approach
to social realities.
Space is a dimension that, as others,
goes through every single social reality.
The Leibnizian approach to space
is also clearly dominant
in relativist physics.