EXPLORING HUMAN'S SPACE
AN INTRODUCTION TO GEOGRAPHICITY
In the first session
we will address space
first from reality that are
easy to identify ourselves
then we will ask why space
plays a role in social life.
Finally, we will do some social theory
of space
through the definition
of key concepts.
SESSION ONE: SPACE AS PRACTICE,
PROBLEM, AND THEORY
Look around. In an
underground train carriage
passengers play themselves as far
as possible from each other
In a city, we find a concentration
of people and big objects.
These pictures show the
various ways we use to welcome
or conversely reject density
in our daily life.
How can we account for
this variety of situations?
1.SPACE IS US
We are spacial realities.
Our censorial apparatus
makes up various spaces.
Our body's a complex system
that forces and helps us
in creating fixed and moving spaces.
For instance, in a given context
the range of our sight
is not the same as the range
of our hearing.
You can hear something you can't see
and vice versa.
In other words, the kind of space
produced by our visual devices
is not the same as the one
produced by our auditory system.
Sounds and images constitute the base
of two different constructions,
that combine with each other and
with other senses
and form the representations we have
of our environment.
Now, if we add the senses that our
body in motion uses,
we discover different relations to
the outer world the body makes possible.
And it's no big deal to understand
there is a strong tie between
our biological equipment and our
representations of space.
Without such a biological couplet,
would the concept of space as it exists
in almost all languages have
been invented?
Probably not, and this is what
18th century philosopher Emanuel Kant
expresses when he says that
space and time are
the a priori forms of sensible intuition,
that is perception.
Thanks to these different senses,
we can generally, in our practical life
give a meaning to both notions of contact
and remoteness
which are the basic figures of human
spacial realities.
As a matter of fact,
the simplest descriptions
CONTACT/REMOTENESS
of distance relations are actually
contact, that is to say - non-distance
and remoteness when distance
is effective.
Our bodies have three major
spacial characteristics.
First of all, as we just have seen
there are multi-sensorial senses
that is to say, multi-dimensional
detectors of the outer space..
Secondly, they are active,
that is to say, mobile.
In contrast with some objects
and environments they interact with.
And finally, they are vulnerable.
They can be destroyed,
either by natural causes,
or social operators
at the risk of the annihilation
of the inhabitant the human being.
In short, you, me, we all our
spacial operators.
We are constantly changed
by space
and we constantly change it
through our acts.
We experience, as well as
we create contact,
remoteness, and in between
different kinds of nearness.
WAKE UP! QUESTION
HOW DO YOU SELECT YOUR SEAT
IN A RESTAURANT?
-I ACCEPT THE WAITER'S SUGGESTIONS.
-I SIT AS FAR AS POSSIBLE
FROM NOISE SOURCES.
-I TRY TO GET THE BEST OUTLOOK
ON THE WHOLE RESTAURANT HALL.
-I AVOID LOCATIONS WHERE I WOULD
TURN MY BACK TO POTENTIAL DANGERS.
-OTHER.