Distance, non-distance,
this position is one of the foundations
of human spatial dimension, but why?
Why distance?
Let's try to answer this question.
We can notice that contact is required
to produce a reproducible society.
The bringing up of children,
cooperation at work,
social cohesion, or cultural diffusion,
all suppose interactions,
and, more specifically,
interactions between human beings.
These interactions imply contact,
that's to say, a non-distance situation
between individuals.
By the way,
traditional sexual reproduction
supposes negative distance
between bodies.
However,
human history is also full of situations
where people have been forced
to be separated,
or were separated
for natural or social reasons
that were out of their control.
In the 19th and early 20th century cities,
for instance,
industrial pollution had a repulsive power
on geographies of housing for those,
of course, who couldn't afford a more
expensive location.
More generally, we can observe
strong tendencies
that make the rich of the dominant groups
keep their distance from the poor
or dominated groups,
or confine them in ghettos,
like the Jews in medieval Europe,
or the Palestinians in Jerusalem,
and the rest of the West Bank today.
In the case of the apartheid
in South Africa,
which was officially established in 1948,
but, actually, present a long time before,
and abolished in 1991,
this unequal separation
was strongly formalized in the law system,
embedded in public policies,
such as spatial planning,
and overwhelmingly present
in every single act
of people's daily lives.
Either or not, a distance
between two or more given realities
things, people, ideas,
that is the fundamental question
that arises in any geographical situation.
Space is a social reality
defined by the relation of distance
that links it to and/or separates it
from other social realities.
Let's complete an elementary vocabulary
useful for the understanding
of the concept of distance.
Ubiquity, landlocking, fixed, mobile,
copresence, mobility, telecommunication.
Ubiquity defines the situation
where an operator
has an immediate access to,
and a possible simultaneous presence in,
all locations of a determined space.
Landlocking defines a situation
where an operator can have an access to,
and a possible presence in,
only one location of this space.
A fixed reality, such as, for instance,
a city or a state,
is a social reality
that would be affected in its nature
if it were moved away,
while a mobile reality,
like a banknote or a smartphone,
can be easily moved without there being
any negative consequences
on its existence.
In the case of human beings,
movement is a competence
and an experience
that empowers their autonomy
at any scale.
As a result,
let's immediately notice this.
It's an error to assign the smallest scale
to the individual
just because the human body is tiny
in comparison
with a city or a state territory.
The relevance case of the humans
are not reducible
to the size of their bodies,
but they are multiple,
as are multiple
the ways we can reach the outer world
by the mobility of our bodies
and through immaterial vectors too.
More details will be given on this point
in the next sessions.
Now, how do we manage distances?
Since the Neolithic Revolution,
12,000 years ago,
there are three major ways
of managing distance.
Copresence, everything in the same place,
mobility, material realities are moved,
and telecommunication,
where immaterial realities are moved.
The city is the expression
of copresence within a societal scope.
Telecommunication did not begin
with the internet, or even the telephone.
Letters provided an efficient,
asynchronous mode of communication
well before emails.
Furthermore,
contemporary telecommunication
is not only synchronized online.
Books, including e-books, CDs, DVDs,
and everything that is downloadable,
or uploadable,
are good examples of current
offline forms of telecommunication.
This diagram presents the three modalities
as related to each other.
It is true that they can be seen
as alternatives to each other.
For instance, if you want to eat
Thai cuisine,
you can do it in a Thai restaurant
round the corner,
go to Thailand,
or download a Thai recipe from a website.
However, the three modalities
can be approached as complementary too.
As an example, the best way to profit
from a city
is to walk, ride,
or drive to take advantage
of the different locations
that are part of a city,
and to use the phone, or the internet,
to synchronize your encounters
inside the urban area,
so, if the main objective is copresence,
the two other ways of managing distance
will be used as means to attain
this objective,
thus e-commerce wouldn't be possible
without logistics,
and it's made easier by the concentration
of customers in large urban spaces.
We can now introduce the term
of coopetition
to sum up the complex relationships
between the different ways
of managing distance.
Coopetition defines a situation
where a mix of competition
and cooperation can be observed,
for example, the institutional relations
between universities.
There is cooperation
within many research projects,
but competition for attractiveness
and global rankings.
The Randstad urban network
in the Netherlands,
Rhineland in Germany, Po Valley in Italy,
or polycentric megalopolises
in Honshu, Japan,
or in northeastern USA,
are spaces where the rationale
is the coopetition between cities.