Hello everyone, and welcome to the introductory
lecture
of our MOOC on designing a smart specialization
strategy.
My name is Andrea and I'm a project manager
at Bak Basel economics.
And I'm also one of the teaching assistants
of this MOOC.
We are very excited to be able to offer this
online course,
since we believe this approach has great potential
to assist you,
policy makers, experts, as well as public
agencies,
in structuring their policy and development
programs.
This course will equip you with the most fundamental
methods
and techniques to design a smart specialization
strategy for your region.
This introductory video will give you a general
overview,
as well as an idea on how the course is organized,
and what you can expect from us.
Also, I would like to point out what we expect
from you.
I presume the information on this slide is
not much news to you.
This MOOC is led by Professor Dominique Foray
And Martin Eichler,
both experts in the field of smart specialization
strategies.
Dominique, who co-authored the concept during
his time in the
knowledge of growth expert group In the European
commission.
And Martin in turn, who engages himself in
regional benchmarking
as chief economist at Bak Basel economics
since many years.
Teaching assistants are Camille and me.
If you have questions or suggestions regarding
the course,
please just drop Camille or me an email
to the following email addresses.
Let's have a quick look at the general objectives
of the course.
During the course we will propose not only
a systematic approach
to understand the Smart Specialization concept,
but we will also explain how to apply it,
in concrete terms, through case studies.
And we will identify the different stages
necessary for the designing of a Smart Specialization
Strategy.
In addition, we will present the analytical
tools,
methods, and data that permit the development
of a knowledge base,
essential for the implementation of this strategy.
What you see here is the basic structure of
our MOOC.
We put a lot of effort in this because we
believe that
the application of the presented methods and
tools is crucial.
We base our tools on of course the lectures,
the storyboards, and the recommended reading.
Also, since we consider you experts in the
field of
smart specialization strategies,
we would like to get as interactive as possible
in the next five weeks.
therefore, we offer a wide range
of different learning activities, in which
you can express yourself.
We prepared a storyboard for each week.
It not only describes what will happen during
this week
but also sums up the most important learning
objectives
of the respective week.
It also includes the bibliography of the week,
as well as the topic of the peer reviewed
assignment.
Now let's discuss the learning activities
proposed in our course.
As I already mentioned before, we consider
you experts
in the field of smart specialization strategies,
or regional economic development in general.
We do not only want to teach the concept,
but also would like to give you the opportunity
to share your experience
in order for us to, together with you, learn
from it.
Your expertise is part of our teaching material.
We therefore offer several channels in order
to make our online course
as interactive as possible.
In order to test yourself with respect to
the required knowledge,
after every module, you will solve a quiz
in the form of multiple choice questions.
We would like you to think outside of the
box
and reflect on what you've learned.
For this reason we will have special forums,
where we will start an interactive discussion
on a specific topic related to this content.
Note that there will always be a general forum
for each module
where you can ask questions, or share your
thoughts and suggestions
with us and your peers.
Furthermore we will have formative assessments,
and a graded assignment
reviewed by your peers at the end of every
week.
The purpose of the formative assessment
is to prepare you perfectly for the final
assignment
at the end of the five weeks.
It will give you the opportunity
to reflect on your knowledge and update it
along with the course,
and therefore learn in a very effective way.
All those channels of learning activities,
together with the peer-reviewed assignment,
will enable you, together with us,
to take very much advantage of this MOOC
and interact with each other as much as possible.
Our goal of this course is not only to teach
the concept,
and its implications, but also to learn about
your experiences,
and practical knowledge, since your expertise
matters a lot
for this MOOC to fulfill its purpose.
And therefore, we are very much looking forward
to the following five weeks that we will spend
with you.
We very much hope that you will enjoy it as
much as we do,
and did, during the production of this course.
Thank you for your attention and see you soon.