Hello everyone and welcome to
this introductory lecture of our MOOC
on "Designing a Smart Specialization Strategy".
My Name is Larissa and I’m a Project Manager
at BAK Economics.
I am also one of the two teaching assistants
of this MOOC.
We are very excited to offer this online course
since we believe that this approach
has great potential
to assist you in structuring your
policy and development programs.
This course will equip you with the most
fundamental methods
and techniques to design a Smart Specialization
Strategy for your region.
This video will give you a general overview
on how the course is organized.
Also will I clarify what you can expect and
what we expect from you.
This MOOC is led by Professor Dominique Foray
and Martin Eichler.
Both are experts in the field of Smart Specialization
Strategies.
Dominique co-authored the concept
during his time in the “Knowledge of growth”
expert group in the European Commission.
Martin is the chief economist of BAK Economics
and has been engaged in regional benchmarking
for many years.
The two teaching assistants are Camille and I.
If you have questions or suggestions
regarding the course,
please don’t hesitate to write one of us an email.
Let’s have a quick look at the general objectives
of this course.
During the course, we will approach the Smart
Specialization concept systematically.
We will explain how to apply it in specific terms.
We will also identify the different stages
of the design of Smart Specialization Strategies.
In addition, we will present analytical tools,
methods and data that permit the development
of the knowledge base
essential for the implementation of this strategy.
This is the basic structure of our MOOC.
The different learning tools and activities
are very carefully chosen
as they are crucial to the learning success.
Additionally to the lecture videos,
for each module we have a storyboard
and we recommend some extra reading.
As we consider you experts in the field
of Smart Specialization,
we would like you to be as interactive
as possible
during the next twelve weeks.
Therefore, we offer different learning activities
in which you can express yourself.
We prepared a storyboard for each module.
It not only describes what will happen during
the module
but also sums up the most important
learning objectives of the respective module.
It also includes the bibliography of the module
as well as the topic of the module assignments.
Now, let’s have a look at the learning activities
proposed in our course.
As I already mentioned before,
we consider you experts in the field of
Smart Specialization
or regional economic development in general.
We do not only want to teach the concept of
Smart Specialization,
but would like to give you the opportunity
to share your experience
in order to learn from each other.
See your expertise as part of our teaching
material.
We therefore offer several channels
to make our online course as interactive
as possible.
In order to test yourself with respect to
the acquired knowledge after every module,
you will solve a quiz in form of multiple
choice questions.
We would like you to think outside of the
box and reflect on what you’ve learnt.
For this reason, we will have special forums
where we start an interactive discussion
on a specific topic related to the content
of the module.
Note that there will always be a general forum
to each module
where you can ask questions or
share your thoughts and suggestions.
Furthermore, we will have a graded assignment
reviewed by your peers
at the end of every module.
To give you a detailed idea of what you can
expect from the next twelve weeks,
we have prepared an agenda.
You have two weeks available to complete a
module.
We recommend to watch the lecture videos
during the first week
and to do the module assignment in the second week.
The quizzes and forums are optional,
but of course quite a good help to apply
the knowledge from the lectures.
At the end of the second week of each module,
you have to hand in your module assignment
and during the next week
– which is the first week of the next module –
you have to evaluate the assignment
from one of your peers.
Each module assignment has a maximum
of 9 points.
After module 5, you have three weeks to do
and hand in the final assignment which has
a maximum of 64 points.
To successfully complete the course, you have
to get at least 80 of the 100 possible points.
Our goal is not only to teach the concept
of Smart Specialization Strategies
and its implications.
Our course is unique thanks to
the general validity
which means that the communicated knowhow
is adaptable to any kind of region
in combination with the academic atmosphere.
In this course, we want to deepen the knowledge
by applying it in the assignments,
by swapping ideas and by learning more about
the experience of every single one of you.
And therefore, we are very much looking forward
to the following twelve weeks
and hope that you will enjoy it as
much as we do
and did during the production of this course.
Thank you for your attention and see you soon!