We have just seen that the activities that
we desire to specialize in are not known in
advance.
They must be discovered.
The Government needs information
to make decisions
in terms of priorities and projects.
Not only a general and abstract information,
but a concrete information,
from entrepreneurial practices themselves.
It is the entrepreneurial discovery process
that has to provide this information,
useful to both the Government
to base its decisions for public actions
and also to companies
to help them in their investment decisions
of R & D and innovation.
In this short video,
we wish to briefly see the heart of the entrepreneurial
discovery.
Its theory will be discussed next week
and its operationalization
during the third week,
by Martin EICHLER.
The process consists of two phases,
in any case, two logics.
A logic of identification of priority areas,
and a logic of exploration of each area
thanks to projects, platforms and collaborations
representing somehow the embryo of the critical
mass
which is the goal,
which also helps learning
on the potentials of this area.
Here is the fundamental diagram that will
be often used during the course.
The first phase
is the analysis of the real economy,
the existing structures,
the major societal,
technological, environmental trends,
the entrepreneurial activity in the region.
We have to do a systematic analyze
of economic and industrial structures,
based on relatively standard data and indicators.
This analysis produces various types of information
on the strengths and weaknesses, relative
specializations,
disparities in terms of dynamism.
Martin EICHLER will present the method developed
by his institute BAKBASEL,
very useful and fruitful to realize this analysis.
This analysis must itself be combined
to the analysis of entrepreneurial resources.
More detailed, qualitative and contextual
information,
that we can not always draw from the statistics
and which are held by regional actors.
It could be about
information on the particular dynamism
of a group of companies
or the presence of a successful actor,
for example a Technological University active
in such and such a field,
or again of the quality of some cooperative
networks
with entities outside the region.
This combination of systematic information
and a more profound and qualitative
knowledge of entrepreneurial resources
is the basis of interactions
and dialogues that have to lead to the identification
of priority areas.
But the entrepreneurial discovery process
does not stop at the identification
of these strategic areas.
We still have to discover if new and high
potential
for innovation and transformation activities
can be developed.
In these fields,
we must mobilize, stimulate
and organize the actors of innovation
so that they implement concrete exploration
projects
which will themselves be relatively linked
or related
to form the beginning of a critical mass.
This block
forms what is called
the entrepreneurial discovery.
From this entrepreneurial discovery process,
new specialties
and transformative activities will emerge
and grow
to reach the structural change.
For here is the ultimate goal:
to promote transformative activities
which appear most promising at the end
of these different entrepreneurial discovery
phases.
Let's make a few more comments on this fundamental
diagram.
The formal structural analysis
as already said,
must be complemented by a more contextual,
more specific
knowledge of entrepreneurial resources,
which is not necessarily shown in the statistics.
We will need to ask the right questions,
during the dialogue between all the stakeholders.
What structural changes appear to be the priority
for the region?
What kind of transformative activity
would lead to these changes?
Are there enough potentials and entrepreneurial
resources
for this activity to be developed here in
a credible way?
The analyzes and knowledge bases
should allow to get a robust
and transparent decision process.
Within the entrepreneurial discovery
the difference between the identification
of priority areas
and
the exploration or realization of these areas
is very simple.
The identification of priority areas is the
result of formal analysis
and consultation.
It is work “in the office”.
And then,
real investments must be made in R & D and
innovation
to concretely explore the possibilities
and the capacities for transformation,
with projects, platforms, networks in each
area.
The entrepreneurial discovery is only the
first step
of the smart specialization strategy,
because the ultimate goal
is to promote the most promising
transformative activities
to concentrate
and agglomerate complementary resources and
capabilities,
to make critical masses emerge.
The transition to a significant activity,
the scaling up,
allows to get to a smart specialization.
This scaling up process
is crucial. If it does not happen,
there will be no impact on structures.
Note also that scaling up, Agglomeration and
coordination, can only be done if the potential
field
of specialization is not too wide.
In too wide a field,
for example a field that we would call
transformation of the energy sector,
there is nothing that can prevent
the scattering of experiments and projects,
and so ultimately,
there won't be any critical mass.
We also see that such a priority is sectorial;
which is not pertinent,
as already noted.
However,
an area that we could call development of
flexible technologies
for the textile and shoe industries
is a field that is much more circumscribed.
We would be then
at the level of a transformative activity.
In this fairly narrow field,
some experiments and projects
would be connected in different ways.
This would lead to the formation of a critical
mass of actors
and services.
Finally let's not forget
that smart specialization strategy
is a living document.
And the entrepreneurial discovery process
is therefore restless.
New priority areas can be identified later,
whereas areas that fail to materialize
will have to be abandoned or at least redirected.
Similarly, in each area, some inconclusive
projects
will be interrupted.
Others will be able to be stimulated more
strongly.
This principle of flexibility and its operationalization
will be presented during the fourth week.
This principle obviously requires mechanisms
of rigorous
and continuous evaluation.
These actions of monitoring
and evaluation which cover all the process
sequences
will also be presented during the fourth week.
We can finally observe that
this process of entrepreneurial discovery
is the "bottom up" element of a strategic
action
in which the role and place of the government
are essential.
We are neither in the pure "bottom up"
because the Government decides ultimately
the priority areas
and stimulates the projects in these areas,
nor in the total 'top down'
because the entrepreneurial discovery brings
to the process of decision,
in a decentralized manner,
decisive information.
We are therefore in an intermediate process
which aims to consolidate entrepreneurial
initiatives,
and their coordination,
in a framework established by the Government.
The diagram that we just outlined is really
central.
Variations are certainly possible,
but the principles announced -
the importance of knowledge
on industrial economic structures
and on innovation;
the analysis of entrepreneurial resources;
the interaction and dialogue
about the potentials and opportunities;
and the double phase of discovery -
the strategic fields
and then the opportunities
and capabilities within each field -
are essential principles.
These principles allow to profoundly renew
the political action
when the latter aims to intervene preferentially
to promote certain strategic activities.
We will often see this diagram.
It will be further discussed and operationalized
by Martin EICHLER,
during the third week.