Specialization.
The big word is out.
It is also a bit of a rude word too,
even if we have just seen that specialization
is a source of efficiency
in the field of knowledge and innovation production,
and also in the field of the government action.
But this word can also mean
standardization,
monoculture,
impoverishment of the potential of evolution.
The big question is : if we need to specialize,
on what should we do so?
How to make choices?
When should we start this process?
Let's start with "On what should we specialize?"
Does that mean
choosing two sectors
among the five or six that count in the region,
according to their relative importance,
and
give it all for these two sectors?
But in this case we drag the region
in an impoverishment logic,
A logic of shrinkening the knowledge base
Why neglect the other sectors?
This is a question that can be asked.
The spirit of smart specialization,
its philosophy is that this concentration
of resources
on critical areas
is an opportunity to transform.
Smart specialization is therefore not done
at sector level
but it focuses on ways to transform these
sectors
or create new ones.
A track is identified to transform a sector
and we concentrate resources,
not on the sector itself, but on this path,
this track of innovation and on the actors
and capacities
involved in this transformation.
We can call this track "transformative activity"
or "new specialty".
This activity does not concern an entire sector
but the part that is mobilized for this.
I will take the example of Galicia, in northwestern
Spain.
A region
which is not among the most developed in Europe.
It is classified in the group of moderate
innovators.
In Galicia, there are many things.
There is tourism.
There are maritime resources.
There is a large university campus
dedicated to the sea.
There are also a large number of automotive
sector companies,
important food and energy
activities.
What could Galicia
develop as transformative activities,
as smart specializations?
I discussed with my colleagues of the University
of Saint-Jacques,
Carmela Sanchez Carreira in particular,
and we thought that
it would be nice if we could, for example,
promote the development
of the application of biotechnologies
to improve the productivity and quality of
fishing activities
and canning factories.
It would be good too
if we could better integrate information
and communication technologies
in the touristic offer for the development
of digital cultural products.
Or,
develop applications of information technology
for the food industry
to improve the quality of local products.
In all these cases, we see that a smart specialization
emerges through the integration of knowledge
from regional capacities
to transform existing sectors.
Sometimes certain required skills are lacking.
They must therefore come from outside.
We will have to get them.
This is for example the case
of the development of new components
for the car industry
and the companies that will be part,
which requires the cooperation of major contractors
located in other regions,
as well as consulting
services
from a famous University, the MIT.
So,
the food industry in Galicia or the car industry
are not smart specializations
just because it is important.
However, the exploration and discovery of
the potential
of information technologies to modernize
certain parts of the food industry,
or the mobilization of small and medium sized
automotive sector companies
for the development of new products,
can become smart specializations.
In all these cases
the sector does not constitute a smart specialization
but the activity of transforming it
can become one.
Most often, these innovation tracks, these
activities,
are connected to existing structures
and aim to transform them.
It consist in entrusting the smart specialization
strategy
these modernization or diversification objectives,
for the existing industrial structures.
We speak of related varieties
and we will come back to this concept
next week.
We can also have more rarely the exploration
of a new area
from almost nothing.
That is what we will call a radical creation.
The strategy does not describe an inanimate
structure
of the best industrial branches.
This is not a shop window
where we want to place the most beautiful
things in the area,
but it expresses a process
and reflects the ability of a region to generate
new activities
or specialties to transform structures.
This is the strategy!
It is all of these transforming activities
which have been selected
and on which we will concentrate resources.
And at some point in time,
the strategy does not necessarily express
all the potential of the region,
all of its strengths, its objectives,
but it reflects what at that time
is the bearer of concrete promises for structural
change.
Let's now talk about the "how".
We have observed
that specialization was not sectoral
but it is at the level of transforming modes
of these sectors.
By definition, these ways of transforming
sectors
these tracks of innovation are not known in
advance
and they can not be decreed by the Government.
They will have to be discovered
by the actors of the innovation.
We will speak of entrepreneurial discovery.
It is a question of interaction between the
Government and the actors
of the innovation.
The Government does not decree the new specialties
to develop.
It has no ex-ante knowledge to do so.
It will base its decisions
on what this process of entrepreneurial discovery
will reveal.
We will dedicate the next video to describe
this process of entrepreneurial discovery.
Finally, last question,
When ?
When should we start a strategy?
Nothing is fixed in a smart specialization
strategy.
It is a living document where new priorities
can always
be added or withdrawn,
according to new opportunities
and what we learn constantly
from the entrepreneurial discovery process.
This flexibility is the logical consequence
of a changing world
in which potentials and opportunities change
constantly.
The answer to the question "When?", is "all
the time".
We have briefly looked at the vast question
of "how to specialize"?
On what should we do it?
How to choose ? When to start?
At the heart of smart specialization strategy,
there is the constant discovery of these strategic
areas
which represent opportunities or ways to transform
and in which we will therefore concentrate
resources,
form specific capabilities
and generate a critical mass of actors and
activities.
You have understood that the discovery of
these priorities and actions to undertake
is the central point.
We will talk about it a bit more
in a final video.