Hello ! In this module,
we want to achieve a feat,
almost say all in three short videos
on smart specialization strategies
so that from the start, we can share
a minimum of common notions and convictions,
to detach from some beliefs
and therefore to adhere to some principles
that describe the essence of these strategies.
Let me start with an example :
the Oulu region in Finland.
A region specialized in the exploitation
of natural resources and mechanical
engineering in the 50s and 60s.
In 1960, Nokia installed a cable factory.
Here is the industrial structure,
simplified of course, in that region at that
time.
From there and thanks to the commitment of
the local University
and the famous VTT Research Institute
and also thanks to regional policies,
a high-tech activity develops in development
and production
of mobile and wireless communication system.
This business develops and grows
to the point of transforming the economic
structures.
We now speak of Oulu as the Silicon Valley
of the North.
The concentration of resources and the integration
of different actors
helped transform the structures.
Nokia has played a vital role,
but also part of the local industry,
the University, the research centre, the public
agency.
However, from 2008,
Nokia stops playing the leading role
because its new strategy favours the relocation
of R-D capacities.
Given the risk of decline,
new activities emerge from the Silicon Valley
of the North
to lead up to
the development of green information technologies
whose applications are found naturally in
the mining sector
which experienced a revival in the 2000s.
We see how, in each period,
the economic structure has changed,
through building of new capacities
in new strategic areas.
Capacity in information technology
then in clean technology.
We are at the heart of a smart specialization
strategy
even though the concept was not used at the
time.
The Oulu region gradually discovers
its potential and opportunities.
Strategic areas are identified
and we specialize according to these potentials
and these opportunities
to transform the structures.
Structural change is an essential perspective,
it is the opposite of rigid and mired structures
in ancient productive modes
which do not allow businesses to be competitive
or to create modern and attractive jobs
that young graduates look for.
We will see in the next module
that the structural change can occur spontaneously
thanks to the initiative of companies
and their capacity for collective action.
It works in some cases,
especially in the most advanced regions.
But in most cases it does not work.
The smart specialization strategy
offers to create the conditions and to set
up a process
to mobilize the actors of innovation,
to embark them in collective action
to develop these new specialties
which will allow the evolution of structures,
transforming some sectors, diversify the economy,
establishing new ones according to a certain
vision of the future.
Develop oneself new specialties
that will transform its economy,
it is the motto of the smart specialization
strategy.
They are not necessarily
new tools, new instruments,
it is rather a new "mindset"
characterized by an additional intentionality
and action to establish priorities
and to facilitate coordination
for the development of new specialties.
It is a new approach of the innovation policy
which requires new knowledge
new information on the region's economy,
its potential and opportunities.
In this module, we will talk about the four
basic elements
of a smart specialization strategy
which refers to the question of "why, what,
how and when".
Let's start with the "why".
There are actually two reasons that come together
to justify or motivate a specialization process
in the field of research and innovation.
First, when we look at what determines productivity
and the effectiveness of research and innovation
activities,
the logics of scale and spatial agglomeration
economies
are still there.
There are important indivisibilities
in the field of R & D and innovation,
particularly in terms of a territory.
This means that research and development and
innovation
require many services, infrastructures and
skills
whose availability is possible
only if enough activities are undertaken.
And then there is the constraint of spatial
agglomeration.
The innovation remains highly dependent
on the interactions between people, informal
communication,
whether they are planned and repeated meetings
or accidental and surprising encounters.
The greater the agglomeration
of people, researchers, businesses,
the more the interactions and communications.
With these indivisibilities and these agglomeration
effects,
the concept of critical mass becomes essential.
But a medium sized area can not generate
critical masses everywhere.
Admittedly, a region can be tempted to do
a little bit of everything
but this is not enough. Besides, when we do
a bit of everything,
we try to do more or less like everyone else,
because we are not specialized in a particular
field
we have a lack of specialty,
we do not stand out, we do not particularize.
If we do a bit of everything and more or less
the same as the others,
we endanger ourselves to remain subcritical
in every field of research and innovation
and we are therefore not so efficient and
innovative.
And on the whole, for example, the European
Union,
we will have a map
with a lot of weaknesses and few strengths.
By using the economists jargon,
I will try to avoid it, most often,
we could say that the rare resources here
are the agglomeration economies.
And they dissipate
when all the regions are in competition
to attract the same resources and so ultimately,
most remain under criticism.
We will be able to distinguish ourselves
only by deepening certain tracks, certain
activities.
This is the first reason of specialization.
We will need to make choices, set priorities
and specialize to create these critical masses
necessary for the efficiency of research and
development,
creativity and innovation.
Specialization is nothing but a mean
to generate these critical mass effects
in the regions that can not do everything.
There is a second reason that reinforces the
first one.
It takes the limited capacities of the government
in front of the complexity
and the specificity of innovation systems.
When we seek to form a critical mass
in a specific field of R & D and innovation
we also try to form an innovation system.
The innovation system
is somehow the other face of critical mass.
An innovation system
are companies operating in the same field,
or connected fields, a few big actors,
companies and research centers specialized
in this area,
additional services and capabilities also
specialized
and finally the extra-regional networks
which allow local actors
to increase their ability to benefit
from knowledge and resources available elsewhere.
But all these elements of the innovation system
are specific
depending on the technological field,
the specialty that is to be developed.
Each innovation system is different
in its composition and its content,
depending on the sector or the technology
area.
The development, as in Oulu,
of a new information technology specialty
involves creating certain capabilities
and certain infrastructures that will be different
from those that should be provided for another
specialty.
But the government will not be able to do
everything,
solve specific problems in each area,
in terms of new infrastructures
and required capabilities
to develop something new.
Again, we must choose.
And so you see that the argument of complexity
and specificity of each innovation system
joins that of critical mass
to motivate a certain specialization
given the limited resources
both of the regional economy and the regional
government.
We will talk about the three other questions
in the next video
whether it is necessary to specialize, on
what, how and when.