In this module,
we want to draw your attention to the following
difference:
the difference between a spontaneous dynamic
entrepreneurial discovery and structural change
and a smart specialization strategy.
This difference is important to understand
two things.
The entrepreneurial discovery in the sense
of identification
and exploration of a new strategic area,
of opportunity
which eventually leads to a structural change,
is not a new phenomenon.
These entrepreneurial discoveries have allowed
in all time
for industrial structures to evolve and transform
in a spontaneous dynamic framework.
We shall see with examples taken from the
history of innovation.
What is new is the idea that
today, we need very often, a strategy
or a policy for organizing these entrepreneurial
discoveries
and lead structural change.
We come back here to a graph already seen
and we remove everything concerning the organized
part
of the entrepreneurial discovery.
We have left what concerns the real economy.
The transformation of a sector by an entrepreneurial
discovery
which occurs naturally or spontaneously
thanks to firms capabilities
to identify new strategic areas and to exploit
it,
and thanks to the fact that the activity or
the specialty that is generated
can grow without much difficulty.
In other words, the structural change
can be driven by the natural ability of firms
to diversify and create spin-offs
which explore new areas
by the arrival of new players, etc.
And history is full of these spontaneous processes
which often start
by entrepreneurial desire to diversify
and which result in a structural change
that benefits an entire region.
I'll give you some examples.
These are ancient examples
that appear to you far from present realities,
yet they offer each a particular version of
a spontaneous entrepreneurial discovery process
which leads to a profound structural change.
It is located in Morez, French Jura,
in the factory of Pierre Hyacinthe Cazeaux,
1790.
This one has a small nail factory.
He will soon discover that his production
system
can be adapted fairly easily to the production
of eyeglasses.
This is the critical moment of the entrepreneurial
discovery
which focuses on technology but also on the
market opportunity.
Indeed, the market for eyewear
is a market on the verge of phenomenal growth.
Pierre Hyacinthe is transforming his production
workshop,
and goes into the eyewear.
This entrepreneurial discovery informs
the entire local community
so that other companies enter this new market
and complementary capacities are made available.
There is therefore a rise in scale and agglomeration.
A few decades later, Morez will appear
as a world capital of eyewear.
The entrepreneurial discovery of Pierre Hyacinthe,
and his transformation into new specialty,
have created a very significant structural
change for the entire region.
The entrepreneur has explored a new area
on the basis of important investment
relative to its capacity and has assumed great
risks.
In the case of Morez
we speak here less of diversification
than transition from a declining area to
a growing field.
Let us now visit Hannibal Abrantes
in the small Portuguese town of Marinha Grande
in 1920.
Hannibal had a mold manufacturing company
for glass.
But its main market stagnates.
And Hannibal also observed
the flood of new objects on Europe,
plastic objects.
Hannibal will travel across Europe to bring
to Marinha Grande
all kinds of plastic products: toys,
utensils, other products.
And he decided to convert his production facility
to start production of molds
for the emerging plastics industry.
This entrepreneurial discovery
that is, once again, technological and economic,
borns a structural change of which we still
see today
the traces in Marinha Grande.
Two interrelated clusters,
molds and plastics industries.
Now we go to a map which I love because I
am
native of this city and I would like to mention
the Lyon-based companies of silk.
The Lyon silk, modern heirs of the Canuts,
occupy a prestigious and secure place
in the tapestry market, sailing and luxurious
fabrics.
Again, the market declines.
But a group of silk entrepreneurs
observes from 1950
the advent of composite fibres and polymers.
In collaboration with the Lyon chemistry,
they will explore a new area:
combine their knowledge with those chemists
and develop the specialty of technical fabrics.
Technical fabrics whose markets are of aeronautic,
transportation equipment, sporting goods
or medical technology.
Famous products like the nose of the Concorde,
Airbus A330 drift
or sailing for some boats of the America's
Cup
symbolize the success of this process of entrepreneurial
discovery.
Again, exploring a new area,
spontaneous entrepreneurial discovery
led to a major structural change.
Move quickly to Finland now,
to quickly evoke the pulp industry.
Here again, a spontaneous entrepreneurial
discovery is observed.
These companies facing problems
of productivity and product quality
come together to explore the potential of
nanotechnology
in order to improve their operational process
and control and regulation,
Here again, a spontaneous entrepreneurial
discovery
which will provide additional modernization
in the sector.
A final example of spontaneous dynamics
but this time not about the modernization
of industry
or the diversification of some companies
but rather on the radical creation of a new
activity.
We're in the Basel region,
northwest of Switzerland in the 60s.
A region known for its chemistry and pharmacy,
and also near an exceptional industrial base
in the high quality metallurgy
and micromechanics domains, especially related
to the activity of watchmaking.
I'll tell you the whole story.
These are surgeons who want to revolutionize
how they heal fractures
at a time when road accidents
and those of winter sports multiply.
They bet on osteosynthesis.
Internal fracture fixation with plates and
screws,
early functional exercise of the patient.
A project whose artistic vision
is due to one of them, Martin Allgöwer.
It also combines micromechanics SME,
including that of Robert Mathis to make tools
and instruments of high quality standard.
This entrepreneurial discovery is at the origin
Of the Swiss medical technology industry
that counts today
several world leaders.
These stories are very different.
Morez, Marinha Grande, Lyon, Finland, Basel
and Biel.
They are much more complicated than what we
said.
But our simplification
helps to discover a common structure.
In all cases, there was an entrepreneurial
discovery,
opening and exploring a new area of ​​opportunity
and this entrepreneurial discovery turns
in a new business and a new specialty
which grows by feeding on the entry of new
firms,
and the agglomeration of complementary activities
of suppliers,
specialized services, adequate training,
which results possibly
to the transformation of existing structures.
History is full of cases
of smart specialization
With very little public action.
The exploration of a new strategic area
to transform a sector or create a new one;
and this exploration is provided spontaneously;
for example, when it happens within a large
company,
which looks for some diversification,
or when it takes place
through collective action of SMEs
or tthanks to the persuasiveness and organization
of a very entrepreneurial university.
However, history also abounds in blocked industrial
structures
and missed opportunities;
an industrial base that fails to renew itself.
This may concern companies that are weakened
and therefore, have poor entrepreneurial capacity.
This would be the opposite of all the examples
that we had just seen.
But this can also involve a cluster
and there will be no taboo in this course.
We know of many situations of stiff clusters
and a little bogged down, which can no longer
lead
these entrepreneurial discoveries
that would allow them to renew;
with, as results, structures that don't evolve
any more,
do not renew any more, do not diversify any
more.
We would then need
a smart specialization strategy.