The objective of structural change
is, without doubt, reachable without deliberate
policy
by simply betting on the ability of companies
to diversify
on the dynamism of startups, on the mobility
of people
and the motivation of firms to cooperate and
combine their knowledge.
All of this can work in certain conditions.
But this does not always work.
We talk now, and to finish,
about the failures and structural blockages.
The signs of a failure of entrepreneurial
discovery
and structural change are numerous.
Weakness of new activities and new industries
creation,
employment structure which remains dominated
by traditional jobs and skills.
Paula Stephan, a colleague, an economist in
the United States,
analyzed what she called: the "Midwest syndrome".
She described this situation of the midwest
states of the US
which are states of rich industrial tradition.
These states have invested heavily in an infrastructure
of public
and scientific training research.
Important and well equipped doctoral programs.
They attracted excellent scientists.
The problem is that those who are trained
in advanced research fields
will then go to find their first job elsewhere
on the west coast, on the east coast.
The figures in this brain drain are striking.
In the 2000s, these states retained on average
only 3% of their PhD.
These figures express
a big gap between research and quality training
and outdated industrial structures,
which have not been able to renew by spontaneous
processes
of structural change and are therefore unable
to offer
the attractive jobs that these young graduates
are looking for.
These failures can come from multiple sources
:
Lack of entrepreneurial discovery:
Potential new areas of diversification or
modernization
are not identified or explored.
There are problems of information externality,
sorry for the jargon,
we'll talk about it again in the second week.
There are also problems of capacities, risks
and financing.
There can also be cognitive problems,
of creative myopia linked, for example,
to the phenomenon of "Company town".
There is only one large company in the region
and it tends to overestimate its own capacities,
it neglects the external inputs
and will have difficulties in engaging in
new strategic areas.
There are also problems of collective inertia.
In this case, it is a group of companies
which have been successful in a certain field,
and because of this exact success, have difficulties
to engage
and explore new directions.
We can also think about coordination failures
and difficulties of all kinds
which prevent an entrepreneurial discovery
to turn into a new activity
to reach a critical size
and to eventually lead to a structural change.
It is certain that the importance today of
science,
and technology in innovation
and the complexity of the relevant knowledge
bases
force to go more than before through partnerships
and collaborative networks.
Which makes the entrepreneurial discovery
less spontaneous obviously.
Morez is gone, remember.
Pierre Hyacinthe who does everything alone.
The financing of activities,
aiming to open and explore a new area,
activities that are, by definition, risky,
is also more difficult.
Global competition also increases the level
of demand.
It is less easy to find a competitive niche
and to keep it for a long time.
Even a cluster is not a guarantee,
an insurance against all risks
that we will be able to produce enough entrepreneurial
discoveries.
A cluster is just a structure
which has certain spatial concentration characteristics
and from which a certain dynamism is expected
thanks precisely to its virtues of proximity.
But there is no magical effect.
And a number of clusters are not so dynamic
and do not represent the expected engine
to trigger the dynamics of entrepreneurial
discovery
because the simple spatial juxtaposition does
not do everything, far from it.
I will take the example of the wind power
cluster in the Basque Country.
This cluster has a hundred firms
specialized in different stages of development,
design and manufacture of wind turbines.
But in front of the competition with new actors,
including Chinese actors, few are doing well.
And most of the cluster companies are in danger
due to not engaging in exploration of new
technological opportunities activities.
Hence the need for a smart
specialization strategy or policy
which puts in place a process
aiming to identify priority areas
which will be realized through concrete coordination
projects
for the development
of new transformative activities.
This is precisely the case
of smart specialization strategy of the Basque
Country
whose one of the components is the energy
as a general priority,
which brings together several research and
innovation projects
in the field of wind power cluster.
Offshore, turbines and technology of production.
The spontaneous sequence, the entrepreneurial
discovery
the new specialty, the structural change,
is a big classic of the history of innovations.
But it is probably more difficult today than
yesterday
and therefore, the spontaneous dynamic
of entrepreneurial discovery, of structural
change
are probably rare.
Most often, we must do much more.
We must put in place a process
to identify strategic areas for the future
and to stimulate projects in these areas
and activities that will allow, ultimately,
to obtain a change in structure.
Hence, the importance today of policies
that run and coordinate the entrepreneurial
discovery process
to identify the strategic areas
and generate new transformative activities
which the region needs.
To make sure also, and we will come back to
it,
that the maximum information about these areas
and their potentiality are diffused.