Quickly to conclude this long introduction,
we want to review
the main message of smart specialization strategy
already mentioned.
Identify a few strategic areas to build capacities
which will lead to structural change.
Thus,
smart specialization strategy has two facets.
First, lead the structural change,
that is to say the transformation of structures
of economy
in a positive direction.
Diversification, modernization
or establishment of a new industry.
We have seen the different types of structural
changes
which may seem desirable to preserve
or increase the vigor and dynamism of a regional
economy.
Diversification,
as the passage from the manufacture of molds
for glass,
to molds for plastic in the case of Marinha
Grande.
Modernisation, as the example of the sector
of ​​pulp
thanks to nanotechnology in Finland.
Transition,
as the example of the silk industry moving
to technical fabrics in Lyon.
Finally,
the radical foundation as the creation of
a medical technology sector
in the regions of Basel and Jura.
And the other face of the strategy,
is the building of new local capacities
to lead to these structural changes.
We identify a desirable structural change
based on the entrepreneurial discovery process
and we will build capacities
in the strategic area concerned,
open and explore this new area and if successful,
move to a larger scale of activities or new
specialties.
Of course, one can always
import factors of structural change.
For example, it can modernize its tourism
sector
by buying the services of a large consulting
company
that can provide a complete service.
This is a sectoral policy which may have its
relevancy,
but this is not a smart specialization strategy.
Smart specialization strategy implies
that part of the necessary capacities
for structural transformation
be located in the territory considered.
It is upon the policy to decide,
where, in what areas,
to what sector it would be important to set
up
a smart specialization strategy
and where can we settle for a “simple”
sectoral policy.
This depends on the potential and opportunities,
productivity, innovation, and entrepreneurial
activity.
In some cases,
perhaps it is better to outsource structural
change
because we do not see too much in the system
who could take charge.
In other cases, it's worth to bet
on local capacities to lead structural change.
The methodologies presented during the third
week
will help us to make such decision.
Take the example of tourism.
Many regions dream of placing tourism in their
strategy.
But there is often a confusion
between the fact that,
we must modernize the sector,
diversify it, find new services,
and that this can be done through potentials,
capacities,
transformative activities developed locally.
In some cases, indeed there are
potentials and opportunities
for the development of smart specialization
linked to the tourism sector.
A few months ago, I visited
Heraklion in Crete,
where there is a first order research institute
called FORTH.
This institute
develops world-class research
in information technology and biotechnology.
And the integration of tourism in the smart
specialization of Crete
is possible on this basis.
There is a range of opportunities of application
of information technology
in the management of knowledge for the archaeological
heritage
or of application of biotechnology to tourism.
A striking example,
is the project design and demonstration of
an artificial oasis
to promote diving activities.
The exploration of this area mobilizes the
Department of Biotechnology
and marine resources of FORTH, specialized
services
and actors of scuba diving.
This suggests that the potential and opportunities
present locally justify
the development project of this transformative
activity.
Another example,
the Centre-Val de Loire region and its famous
castles -
Blois, Chambord, Chenonceau and many others.
Why the integration in the strategy
of an activity linked to tourism
would be relevant here?
There is in this region a large number of
companies,
some large, specialized in the restoration
of monuments.
There is therefore an industrial dynamics
and a capacity of innovation at least potentials,
Within the sector of tourism and cultural
heritage.
And one can well imagine
a transformative activity to modernize the
sector,
thanks to new technologies
(laser, optical fibre, IT).
This in direct connection with the local market;
that of restoration of castles and other monuments
and also historical research, which is brilliant.
But in many cases,
the tourism sector may be economically significant,
but the capacities for innovation and entrepreneurial
activity
are very low.
And therefore, there is no real prospect
of smart specialization
because if structural change there must be,
this can only come from the outside.
The effort of constructing innovation and
entrepreneurial capacities
would be too great, probably unrealistic
and economically irrelevant.
So we find this problem of being able to give
up,
even if the sector is important in the region,
based on the analysis of existing capacities
and entrepreneurial activity.
The entrepreneurial discovery process is the
key mechanism
that permits to decide what is worth to undertake
in terms of capacity building in strategic
areas
and what it might be reasonable not to do;
always with the possibility of coming back
to the initial choices,
the first priority and the first renounciation,
as we will see later
when we will deepen the principle of flexibility.