Hello and welcome !
I'm Dominique Foray,
professor at the Federal Polytechnic School
of Lausanne in Switzerland,
I lead the Chair of Economics
and Management of Innovation.
I would like to say a few words about
the courses I offer with Martin EICHLER.
This course is called
"Design a smart specialization strategy."
Bonjour et bienvenue !
Mon nom est Martin EICHLER.
Je suis l'économiste en chef
de BAKBasel,
Un institut privé de recherche
économique de Bâle, en Suisse.
You know that innovation
and innovation policies
are
critical determinants
of economic performance in
the regional level.
But each region is different.
And in most areas, we can not do everything.
It can not be good for research and innovation
in all areas. It's just a major problem,
of size, of resources.
I had the chance to write
the first article on this issue
in 2009, with my colleagues Bart van ARK
Paul DAVID, Bronwyn HALL.
This concept has spread rapidly,
particularly in Europe
but also in many other countries.
L'expérience du travail
avec diverses régions depuis
de nombreuses années
nous ont permis d'intégrer rapidement
les idées de spécialisation intelligente
dans l'analyse de la région
et le renforcement de la stratégie.
There has been great
excitement around these ideas,
and also some
diversity of approaches and procedures.
It seems therefore it is time
today to propose a course
on how these strategies can be devised
and practiced,
on why
and especially on the how.
During the course we will share
this experience with you.
Nous proposons non seulement
une approche systématique
Mais aussi comment l'appliquer pratiquement
et la différence nécessaire
des étapes dans le processus.
En outre,
nous allons vous montrer une paire d'outils
d'analyse et des méthodes,
ainsi que les données dont vous avez
besoin pour accomplir
la base solide de preuves,
qui est un élément essentiel
pour la construction du succès S3.
grâce au cours,
vous comprendrez cet ensemble
de méthodes et d'outils
que vous pouvez ensuite utiliser
en définissant vos propres
stratégie de spécialisation
intelligente individuelle.
Bien sûr,
comme la stratégie est individuelle
ainsi est l'analyse.
Mais la boîte à outils de base
que nous fournissons
sera très pratique une fois
que vous avez commencé.
We look forward to meeting you
during this course.
Join us for this journey
that takes you through many areas,
observe many situations, meet many people
and test tools and methods
all this in relation
to smart specialization
strategies.
Nous sommes impatients
de vous voir bientôt en ligne.
Nous vous voulons
pour la spécialisation intelligente.