Hello and welcome !
I'm Dominique Foray,
professor at the Federal Polytechnic School
of Lausanne in Switzerland,
I lead the Chair of Economics
and Management of Innovation.
I would like to say a few words about
the courses I offer with Martin EICHLER.
This course is called
"Design a smart specialization strategy."
Hello and welcome !
My name is Martin EICHLER.
I am the chief economist
of BAKBasel,
a private economic research
institute from Basel, Switzerland.
You know that innovation
and innovation policies
are
critical determinants
of economic performance in
the regional level.
But each region is different.
And in most areas, we can not do everything.
It can not be good for research and innovation
in all areas. It's just a major problem,
of size, of resources.
I had the chance to write
the first article on this issue
in 2009, with my colleagues Bart van ARK
Paul DAVID, Bronwyn HALL.
This concept has spread rapidly,
particularly in Europe
but also in many other countries.
The experience of working
with various regions for many years
able us to
quickly incorporate the smart specialisation ideas
in the region analysis
and strategy building.
There has been great
excitement around these ideas,
and also some
diversity of approaches and procedures.
It seems therefore it is time
today to propose a course
on how these strategies can be devised
and practiced,
on why
and especially on the how.
During the course we will share
this experience with you.
Not only we propose
a systematic approach
but also how to practically apply it
and the difference steps
needed in the process.
Furthermore,
we will show you a couple of
analytical tools and methods,
as well as the data
you need to accomplish
the sound base of evidence,
which is an essential for building
the successful S3.
Thanks to the course,
you will understand
this set of methods and tools
that you can use then
in defining your own
individual smart specialisation strategy.
Of course,
as the strategy is individual
so is the analysis.
But the basic toolbox we provide
will come quite handy
once you get started.
We look forward to meeting you
during this course.
Join us for this journey
that takes you through many areas,
observe many situations, meet many people
and test tools and methods
all this in relation
to smart specialization
strategies.
We are looking forward
to see you online soon.
We want you
for smart specialisation.