This week's lectures
are particularly difficult
because we are going to introduce
how spatial information
is encoded by magnetic resonance imaging.
And as you will see,
this is done slightly differently
than the X-ray imaging techniques.
First, however, I want
to start out with a recap
of what we know
about magnetic resonance.
We have so far introduced
the static magnetic field.
The static magnetic field,
which is always called B0,
is necessary to create
equilibrium magnetization.
So as you enter the magnet
you will build up a nuclear magnetization
that's this equilibrium magnetization.
We're typically talking about
field strengths of 0.1 to 12 T.
As a reference here, you have
the earth's magnetic field,
which is, as you can see,
much smaller than the fields used for MRI.
Then what we do is,
this static magnetization,
the equilibrium magnetization
we've seen is not very interesting,
produces no signal, so what we need to do
is to excite the magnetization,
that is flip the magnetization
into the transverse plane,
and this is done using
a radio frequency field,
which is applied at the Larmor frequency.
The radio frequency field
is always denoted B1.
It typically has a magnitude of 0.05 mT
and it is applied on-resonance.
So this is compared to B0
in the order of tesla,
here we're on the order of millitesla,
there's a considerable
difference between the two.
After the excitation with the RF field
we have the magnetization transverse plane
and then this signal is being recorded,
and this we have introduced last week,
this is known as the free induction decay.
We have seen that after this excitation,
we are no longer
at thermal dynamic equilibrium,
we have to get back
to thermal dynamic equilibrium,
this is done by relaxation,
T1 and T2, or T2 and T1.
T2 describes the decay
of the transverse magnetization, Mxy,
and T1, the return to equilibrium
of the z magnetization, Mz.
So the detection of the signal,
the FID, that is done
also with the RF coils.
So both the excitation,
the production of B1,
the radio frequency field,
and the detection of the signal
is done with the same piece of hardware.
So this is what we've had so far
with magnetic resonance.
We have seen that the RF coils
are used to measure the signal
from the entire body.
We have not introduced,
therefore as such, spatial information.
The means of detecting the signal
is done by observing
the precessional frequency,
which is the Larmor frequency
given by γ B0,
under the influence
of a static magnetic field.
And we have seen last week,
with this gives us also additional
chemical information.
So now how do we encode
the spatial information?
How do we get spatial information
into our observation of the signal?
And here the key is, let's suppose
that we have the magnetic field,
which is along z, the B0 field,
and we'll add a small field
that varies linearly with space.
So that's the Gx times X term here.
So now this magnetic field varies along x.
What happens now?
What we now have is that
the Larmor frequency
becomes a linear function in position.
So if we write the magnetic field along z
and we produce it
to vary spatially with x, y, and z,
this spatial variation, we can define as
the derivative of the z component
of the magnetic field--
remember static field is always along z--
with respect to position x,
with respect to position y,
with respect to position z,
each of those derivatives
are the components of a vector
that we shall call G here.
So in general terms, then we have
the static magnetic field,
r of the function of position
is given by the static field B0,
plus this linear term, and here is
the scalar product of G times r.
This is in all generality, the description
of the magnetic field now.
So for this case
that we had here on the left,
we use the vector G
that was equal to (Gx, 0, 0),
so just along x that we had
a spatial variation.
So if you look along x,
here is the x axis,
the magnetic field starts from
the center point, B0,
and varies linearly
around the position zero.
Here we have taken
the rotating frame representation
so at center there is no magnetic field.
Along y, so here's the y axis,
we have a linear variation.
And finally, along z,
we have the z component
of the magnetization along z
that increases in opposite directions.
So now this vector G,
we call this the gradient field,
and the question is,
"How is this gradient field
actually physically generated?"
Well, I'll recap here, the definition.
The gradient vector is given by
the derivative of the z component
of the magnetic field
with respect to the position
in each of the directions,
that gives the components of this vector.
To give you an idea
what we're talking about here,
this gradient field is typically
on the order of 10 to 50 mT/m
and it can be switched in a timescale
that's typically on the order of 100 μs.
And this is used to determine
the spatial position of the signal,
as we have seen from the Larmor frequency.
So how is this gradient field generated?
It is actually generated by
a set of three additional coils.
They're so-called gradient coil.
So these three additional coils,
they are put into one additional coil
and that's the gradient coil.
So what we have here in green,
is the z coil that produces
the linear field in z,
in red, a linear variation of Bz along x,
and in yellow, along y.
In blue here, you have also
the RF coil indicated
and the subject is now lying here
in this scheme inside the magnet.
So to give us an idea
how this is achieved,
we'll take the z-gradient coil principle,
just to give you an idea
of how this is done,
and we'll use the Helmholtz pair here.
So what we have first,
we have a ring current
that's rotating, in this sense,
counterclockwise.
And then at a certain distance,
we have a ring current
of the same structure, same diameter,
but now the current is rotating
in the opposite direction.
The B0 is along z
so it's in this direction,
but parallel to the axis of the two coils.
From B0 sub r we can calculate,
given the current
in the orange and red coil,
we can calculate exactly
the magnetic field that's being produced.
I'll just recap here the law
for completeness sake,
but we'll just take a very
qualitative argument here.
And basically, we'll now draw here
at the exact center
between these two coils,
the magnetic field generated
by the orange coil,
that's the magnetic field
indicated in orange,
and by the red coil,
it's indicated in red.
And now if we go along at the axis,
center of the axis
will move in this direction
and in this direction.
So if we move upwards,
the field from the orange coil increases,
the opposing field generated
by the red coil decreases,
so the magnetic field
increases in this direction.
Here at the center for symmetry reasons,
the two magnetic fields
generated by the two coils
are equal in magnitude
but opposed, so it is zero.
And if we go downwards
in the direction of the red coil,
we have the contribution
from the red coil that increases
and the contribution
from the orange coil that decreases.
And that, in the end, in this situation
generates a, more or less,
linearly varying magnetic field along z,
and this is the z component.
So what does this look like in practice?
In practice, one has a former
and then the coils are bound in copper
on top of this former here.
So this is a coil
that corresponds to the x coil,
here is the single gradient coil
that we have here on this structure.
If we look at the complete gradient coil
then we have the complete structure.
All the coils wound on top of each other.
You can see here this z-gradient
is produced a bit more complex
than we have introduced.
Note that the y-gradient
and the x-gradient, these two,
they are, construction wise, identical
except one is the rotated version
of the other, rotated by 90-degrees.
So here are the three gradient coils.
Now, have you been in an MRI scan?
Have you been a volunteer
or do you know of someone of a volunteer?
Well, if you haven't been a volunteer,
you might have heard
that MRI scans are loud.
And why are they so loud?
We'll go after this question
with the following three experiments
that illustrate the basic principle
that's behind the generation of sound
during an MRI scan.
Okay, in this experiment
we have a permanent magnet here,
and we'll be running a current
through this structure here.
And I will turn on the current
and it will invert its polarity,
one can see the force
that the magnetic field exerts
on the conducting structure.
First in this way, it's attracted
towards the right.
And now if I reverse the polarity,
it is pushed in the other direction.
That's a demonstration of
the Lorentz force
that's exerted on the structure
that carries the current.
This is what we have also
in the MRI experiment.
Okay, so in this experiment
we have a coil here.
I'll be pushing this button here
and this will introduce
a magnetic field rapidly.
This magnetic field
induces a change in flux.
This flux will induce eddy currents
in this aluminum ring,
which in turn, those currents,
through the Lorentz force,
will interact with
the magnetic field of the coil
which will push back the ring
and the ring will fly upwards.
So I will go 3, 2, 1.
(metal ringing)
And here we go.
If the ring is cut and cannot flow--
I'll do the same experiment here
so now we have no ring current
so there is no current that can flow,
push the button and nothing happens.
Conversely, if I run an AC current
through the coil here,
then I have a change in magnetic flux,
and as I increase the current,
that is the change in magnetic flux,
then the force increases,
that is acting on the ring.
Okay, so in this experiment
what we're going to demonstrate here,
is, again, the Lorentz force.
We have a coil here, and there's
a big capacitor underneath.
This capacitor will be charged.
This will take some time,
and then I will release the charge
that's stored in the capacitor.
This creates a surge of current in here,
which creates an enormous
flux change through this coil,
which in turn induces
eddy currents in the Coke can,
which through the Lorentz force
will contract and be split in two.
So we will now start charging.
And this process takes a while,
we can see over here on the dial
the increase we have to charge
to roughly 10 kV.
Okay, so we reached a steady-state.
3, 2, 1.
(bang)
And now if you touch this,
you can feel that it is
actually quite hot.
(scanner buzzing)
So here in this video,
is a practical example.
So we can hear,
the scanner as it is going.
And you hear bzz, bzz, bzz, bzz.
That's the typical sound
of an MRI experiment under progress.
(buzzing)
So where does the sound come from
in the MRI scanner?
And the thing here is that,
as we've seen with the experiments,
we're looking at the Lorentz force
of the B0 field, let's say it's 3 T,
so it's a very strong magnetic field,
on rapidly switched current
in the gradient coil.
So this force builds up.
Because the current
in the gradient coil is switched rapidly,
the force builds up rapidly,
and this is like...
(knocking on table)
...a hammer knocking on a structure.
Here it's the copper structure
that hammers on its support.
That support doesn't move
like if you hammer on a table,
like this table here.
The support cannot move
but you still have this knocking sound,
and that produces very strong forces,
The examples with the Coke can
are just mere illustrations
of the kinds of forces that are in there.
And so to give you an idea
what we're talking about here,
one switch is typically
100 A in about 100 μs.
That's the kind of forces
that we're looking at.
Now, without engineering attempts
to reduce the sound inside the scanner
it would be much louder,
and over the years
the scanners have become
considerably quieter
than they used to be 10, 15 years ago.
So there's continuous research going on
and development in trying
to reduce the noise.
But in general, it is advised
to go into an MRI scan with the ear plugs
so that one does not have
some unpleasant surprises.
Now before going into
how the image is reconstructed,
I want to illustrate here
with a simple example,
I want to illustrate
how slice-selection is achieved.
So we have seen
in the previous two courses
that the radio frequency field B1,
which is applied at a frequency ω_RF,
it is capable of exciting
the magnetization
into the transverse plane
if ω_RF matches the Larmor frequency
of the precession of the magnetization.
So if ω_RF is equal to ω_L
then one is capable of flipping
the magnetization
into the transverse plane.
What we're looking at here now, is a cube.
If you consider this part of an object,
it's a 7x7x4 matrix
and each of these voxels contains
the magnetization vector.
We have the z direction here,
we have the x direction,
and we have the direction in y.
Now we'll consider that we are here
and that we have a position z0
that corresponds to
the gray voxels here in our object,
and we consider that
the Larmor frequency at this position
is given by γ B0 + γ Gz times z0.
So the Larmor frequency is equal to that,
then if we set the ω_RF
equal to that Larmor frequency,
then we are capable
of flipping the magnetization
into the transverse plane.
This is done on-resonance,
as we have seen,
that the magnetization
that is off-resonance, that precesses,
is not touched by the RF pulse,
by the B1 field,
but only those that are on-resonance,
so in our rotating frame,
which is always set to
the frequency of the B1 field,
this magnetization can be flipped
into the transverse plane.
So in this case, we can see
that the magnetization
that corresponds to the gray voxels,
applying an RF field with this condition,
will flip the magnetization
transverse plane for all the gray voxels,
and the others are untouched.
And then it becomes a simple fact,
a simple means of changing
the frequency of the synthesizer
to change the frequency of the RF field,
and that alters the position of the slice.
So here's now in
the rotating reference frame,
so this term does not appear.
The ω_RF equals γ Gz times z,
and then we select, in our object,
this slice here.
And now if we change
the frequency of the synthesizer,
we will change the position of the slice,
and as we see here in this animation,
it moves up and down with position
as we change the frequency.
Here I would like to make a side point
and that is, which is important,
we should not confuse two things.
Typically we refer to x and y,
to their positions in real space,
so z is this direction,
x is typically this direction,
and y is typically this direction.
Mxy or M or M_perpendicular
refers to the transverse magnetization.
Here, x and y denote
the transverse components
in magnetization space.
So this is different than real space.
If we put ourselves into
a rotating reference frame,
we do that in magnetization space,
and not in real space,
and we're dealing here
with two different coordinate systems.
However, they do share the z component.
So this is important
that we keep that in mind
for the rest of this course.