So now the question is
what is the basic principle
of encoding spatial information?
We have during detection,
in the presence of a gradient,
we have a spatially varying
resonance frequency.
So the z field is equal to
B0 + Gx times x.
And so if we plot this as a function of x,
we have a magnetic field here,
and here.
It increases, et cetera,
so that's γ Bz(x).
Our transverse magnetization
now will precess, it will be given by
the transverse magnetization
at position x times e^(i γ Bz) times t.
So this is in general terms,
this is how this is written here.
We have the B0 term
and we have the gradient term.
Now what we'll do is we'll put ourselves
into the rotating frame
to describe that so that
we don't need to consider the γ B0.
Remember, γ B0 is much bigger
than γ Gx times x,
so we have now just
a magnetic field that varies with x,
so it's the z component.
So now we can write the precession
of the transverse magnetization,
given by the transverse magnetization
at position x
times e^(i γ Gx.x) times time.
So if we look here at this position,
our magnetization vector will precess here
with a certain precessional frequency.
If you go at this position,
the magnetic field is stronger
so here, it's precessing faster.
And finally, at this position we have
an even stronger magnetic field
and here the magnetization
precesses faster.
So this is what we are detecting.
We have precessed
different precessional frequencies
and they depend on the position
of the magnetization.
Now the signal that one detects
is given by the sum
of all precessing magnetization.
So what we now have to do is
to get the signal as a function of time,
we have to integrate
over the object, here along x,
the magnetization
at time zero at a position x,
times the evolution term here,
so that's the phase evolution.
And here we're basically saying that
the real part is, for example,
corresponds to the x component
of the transverse magnetization
at the imaginary, the y component.
So we'll do this integration
over position.
So what does this equation resemble?
Have you seen a similar equation already?
Does it ring a bell?
How about this equation,
does that ring a bell?
You have most likely come across
this type of equation,
and that's an inverse Fourier transform.
Essentially looking at a signal
that we are detecting,
is the inverse Fourier transform
of the magnetization
as a function of frequency,
and here frequency and position,
they are linked through this equation,
linearly linked through that.
So this is a Fourier transformation
of the object's magnetization
that we detect.
So we can rewrite this equation
that we have here.
I'll write it as S(k),
which is proportional to the integral
over the object magnetization
again at time zero times e^(i k x) dx.
And here we're using
the term k for k-space,
this is the conjugate
or pair variable to position x,
so here x and k are linked
through Fourier transformation,
they are a Fourier pair,
like in this example,
ω and t are the Fourier pair.
So if we take now
the Fourier transformation
of the signal that we record with time,
or, we can also say as,
that we record as a function of k-space,
this gives us the magnetization along x.
If we write this now for a 2D object,
then the magnetization at
a given position x that we observe,
so we obtain Fourier transformation
of this, we obtain M(x),
and this M(x), if we look at
the two-dimensional object,
is then given by the integral
of the magnetization in (x, y) along y,
because we cannot distinguish,
in the y direction, the position
if we apply a gradient along x.
Now this equation,
does that look familiar?
You have certainly seen it
in the first part of this course.
We have introduced it
for computed tomography
and this is a Radon transform.
So in principle I could stop here and say,
"Well, once," like I've said before,
"once we see that the signal
corresponds to that of a Radon transform,
we know we can reconstruct
an image with that projection."
So in principle the reconstruction
can be done here,
as in computed tomography.
However, this is not the general case
and I will not stop here
the lecture for this week,
and we will go into the way
that the images are reconstructed.
So first I want to come with a 1D example.
And we'll take here, the example
of two point-like objects,
these could be capillaries,
so they are very small dimension.
Here they are.
We'll give the position along x here,
and without encoding,
that is the magnetic field
which is plotted here,
is constant in position.
We have a constant
magnetic field in position,
and we'll record a nice
free induction decaying signal.
The frequency is the Larmor frequency,
and the decay is T2.
Now, if we apply encoding,
then the magnetic field varies
linearly with space,
and we'll take here the encoding along x,
so we have applied a gradient along x,
so it's a spatially varying
magnetic field,
and this produces now,
an oscillation of two frequencies.
We have two capillaries, two positions,
we'll assume they're point-like
so they're two
very well-defined frequencies.
This is gives a beating pattern
of two frequencies,
and that typically looks like this.
Now if you imagine you have
a more complex object,
it is not so obvious just to see
from the signal that's recorded,
what is being observed.
So what is done now is we apply
the Fourier transformation,
that is we decompose the signal
into its frequency components.
That's what Fourier transformation
does for you.
So we'll take the signal,
Fourier transform it.
Here we get a single resonance.
We have a constant magnetic field,
we have no information on the position,
and in the presence of
a spatially varying magnetic field,
we're getting two peaks,
two resonance positions
two frequencies according to the position
of these two capillaries in this example.
And so these projections
that we obtain, like I've said before,
we could, in principle, reconstruct
the image using back projection.
And this was indeed,
in the very first experiment
done by Paul Lauterbur,
a physical chemist, in the early '70s,
this is actually how
he produced the first images.
He used MRI with back projection.
The other person that is
noteworthy to mention,
also in the early '70s,
that took a different approach,
that was a physicist, Sir Peter Mansfield.
Paul Lauterbur and Sir Peter Mansfield,
they shared the Nobel Prize
in Physiology and Medicine in 2003,
for their groundbreaking work
in making imaging possible
with magnetic resonance.