To understand the basic imaging sequence--
to understand how basic information
is spatially encoded with MRI--
we need to deal with the question on
what is the effect
of the gradient on the signal,
and how do we make, for example,
the signal maximal
under the influence of a gradient?
Let's first look at the signal
as a function of time.
So we have an object,
we have a gradient along y here--
now I'll use y,
just because it pleases me;
we don't always have gradient along x--
so we have the magnetization along y.
This is the equivalent equation
that we had two slides earlier.
If we now look at this equation
then we can see that for--
this is our complex numbers,
so again, the real part is x,
the imaginary part
represents the y component
of the magnetization or of the signal--
and if we look at this equation here
then we can see that at time_zero,
this term is 1 and then we are getting
the signal as a function of time
is the magnetization, it's constant.
However, if we apply the gradient
and we look at times bigger than zero,
then we have, increasingly,
one magnetization vector corresponding
to a positive y position,
moving in one direction,
the other magnetization
rotating in the other direction
or in a complex plane.
Now the complex numbers
according to their position along y
will have a different phase
and they will no longer add co-linearly.
And this is called dephasing.
So our signal is maximal
at the beginning.
So let's look at a gradient--
and I will here take a gradient along y.
I'll have it at zero,
then I'll have it at a negative value,
and then I'll put it to the same value
that is positive here.
We're going to consider
these three time points here
where we switch the current
in the gradient coil
and we're now looking at
the phase of the magnetization--
that is this term here, over time,
starting here at time_zero,
where we have
this magnetization here in phase.
So we're looking at the phase:
that's this term here just before the i.
So if we take one position along y
then we are getting a phase
that evolves this way,
I will plot here...
In terms of position, we have y and x.
So we'll have this position--
we're looking at one position in y
so we'll take this position, y is small,
and here we have all the magnetization
at time_zero are in phase
so they're all co-linear.
Now we'll take the next position in y
which is a bit further away,
so G_y y is bigger,
so the phase is bigger,
the slope is bigger here
and here the slope is inverted
because we invert the sin of G_y.
For the third position, we have this--
and we'll just continue equidistantly,
that's the fourth,
and that will be the fifth here,
the sixth, this position,
and the seventh, at this position.
And now what we see is-- because here
the slope is proportional to position,
and here the slope
is also proportional to position
but the slope here
is equal to the negative of that slope,
so since this time here
equals to this time,
and so we'll have a point here
where all the magnetizations
are again in phase--
they have a phase of zero,
and this creates a maximal signal,
and that's what we call echo formation
and what you would typically see
in the computer--
the digitized signal that's observed
is something like this; it's an echo.
That's what is called an echo.
So if we look at the phases,
we have dephasing.
Dephasing means that
the magnetization vector's
spread out in the transverse plane,
they no longer act co-linearly
so signal decreases,
and then, when they all
come together again,
we call this phase
of the evolution rephasing.
And so, if we look,
what happens over time,
then we have rephasing,
here we have echo, all is in phase,
now we have dephasing--
you can see they're not in phase--
now they are reversing their orientation
and they are in phase again.
So we have dephasing--
the magnetization vector's spread out,
then they come together again--
here they're again together.
And this is happening
if the area of the gradient here
equals the area of the gradient here
or if the integral sum of all the gradient
over time here equals to zero,
in more general terms.
So if we have equal area,
positive and negative,
then we have echo formation.
And this time here, from here to here,
is typically called the time of echo,
or echo time, TE.
And if we go on afterwards,
then of course we have dephasing
and now the vectors are all dephased
and they are no longer producing
a measurable signal
after a certain amount of time.
So if we call this time here tau
then from here to here tau is equal to
TE/2 in our particular example.
So we can write the magnetization
at this time point
is equal to the transverse magnetization
at time_zero
times the phase term
and this is now being done
by integrating along y.
We have the minus here
because the gradient is negative,
so G_y is the magnitude of the gradient.
The gradient during time t--
time t is this time here...
that denotes this time here--
the signal during time t is proportional
to the transverse magnetization:
that's the sum of the
transverse magnetization over the object.
So we sum along dy,
it's the magnetization along y
at time tau
times this term here.
Here it's subpositive because we have
changed the sin of G_y.
And now we'll put this together--
that is, we'll insert this into here--
the magnetization at the time tau
is proportional to this.
We'll put this in here,
and in the equations I have just assumed
that they are equal--
this is really a proportionality;
then we have the magnetization
at time_zero here--
the transverse magnetization
times these two terms.
So this term we can understand:
that's the magnetization rate
after the RF pulse and here,
what about these terms?
So I will look at these two terms
and I will re-write them into the exponent
and so we now have e to the i gamma G_y y
times t minus tau.
And so this means-- this term here,
if you look at this integral,
with the same argument that we had here--
if this phase term is zero,
then we have maximal signal
and that is happening when t equals tau
and so we have echo formation
and this is given at this point.
So this is what is being observed.
Okay, so this is a graphical,
mathematical demonstration
that, in a simple experiment,
where we have a gradient that's negative
and then we put it to positive,
that after two times this period tau
we echo formation how it occurs.
Now this is not easy to understand
and one has to really think about it,
how to visualize that, and I'm going
to now try to take a different approach.
So let's try to look
at echo formation here,
under a different viewpoint.
And what we're going to do here is
we're going to suppose
that our magnetization vectors
are represented by--
the position of our magnetization vectors
are represented by a tortoise here,
and a hare.
And we're going to
make them run on a circle
because they're magnetization vectors--
the tortoise and the hare represent
the tips of magnetization.
And they're going to be running
at a certain velocity--
that is, they are going to have--
this velocity is given
by angle of velocity
times radius of the circle.
So this is like track and field--
instead of having an oval,
we're running in a circle.
So, at time_zero
they're both at the same position.
Now we'll have the hare running fast
in one direction,
and the tortoise running slow
in the other direction.
So that is the precession
of fast and slow magnetization.
At time_zero they're both up here,
so they're here,
and now we'll have them run
for a time of TE/2 seconds,
or milliseconds if you want.
Since the hare runs faster,
he will have run a bigger distance
than the tortoise, which is much slower.
And here, for simplicity, we'll assume
that the tortoise is running
in the opposite direction as the hare--
so tortoise has run until here,
the hare is until here,
they have run in this direction.
Now, after TE/2 seconds
we give the command
to reverse the direction--
so that is a 180-degree turn.
We're telling them, instead of running
as you've been running,
now you run in the opposite direction,
still on the circle,
but with the same velocity.
So this is a 180-degree turn, turn around,
and now we're running back to--
we're letting them run again
for the same amount of time.
Now, the distance
that they're going to run on the circle,
for the same amount of time,
since they are running at the same speed,
the distance traveled is going to be
the same but in the opposite direction.
So, after time TE-- after TE seconds--
they're both going to end up again
at the same position, like this.
Okay, so is this now clearer?
So we have had a tortoise
slowly running on a circle
and a hare running fast on the circle.
We've said these represent
the tips of the magnetization vectors,
of two magnetization vectors.
Now the argument that I've made here
is assuming two different velocities
for tortoise and hare--
so two different precessional
frequencies-- that's the omega here.
Now we can imagine
what we have in our organ of interest,
we have literally hundreds of thousands
of different tortoises and hares
and they're all running
at different speeds
and different directions, etc.
I have made no assumption whatsoever
on the specific circumstances
on the speed of the tortoise or the hare,
so this is valid for any two pairs
that we compare
that they will arrive after time TE
at the same original position
that they had.
So this is, in general, the case.
The only thing that we've imposed is,
they're always running at the same speed
and after half of the time,
they reverse the direction.
That's the influence of the gradient.
And so the time TE is also called
the echo time
and that's what we will refer to
very often from now on.
So I hope this is now a bit clearer,
how echo formation is done
under the influence of a switched gradient
where we change the polarity.
There we changed--
with the polarity of the gradient
we changed the direction
in which the magnetization vector,
at a given position,
is precessing.
To understand better the diagrams
I am going to be showing after this slide
I have to address one question,
and that is:
Is it important when exactly
a gradient is being applied?
What is its influence when the gradient
is being applied, on the signal?
We'll consider here an experiment
where we have a gradient along x,
it goes from negative to positive--
doesn't actually matter
exactly what we're doing here,
but we'll take the same example
as we had before,
so if these two areas
are equal in magnitude,
then we will have, at this time point,
we will have echo formation.
And this time here
we call the echo time, TE.
And we will put a note here,
the start of this time counting here
as the time tau.
And this time here will be 2 tau.
Now I will take a gradient along z
and I will switch it
just before the green gradient along x,
so this gradient here
is applied just before,
it's turned off at the time tau.
This is its effect on the phase.
So that is what we call
the sequential application
of two different gradient orientations.
Now we'll take the same experiment again.
We have the gradient along x,
we have echo formation,
and we'll apply now
this same gradient along z
but we'll apply it at the same time
as we apply the negative lobe
of the x gradient.
So everything is identical
except the timing for the red gradient.
Here's again the echo time, TE,
and this is what we call
the simultaneous application
of the gradient.
And now the question is:
Is there going to be a difference
on the echo that we record here?
Does it make a difference?
Can we tell from
the signal that we record here,
whether this gradient's been applied here,
or whether it's been applied here?
So let's look at the magnetization
in the left example after time tau--
it's given by the magnetization
at time_zero,
times e to the gamma G_z z times tau--
this is the effect of this gradient here--
and on the right side,
the magnetization at the time tau
is still the magnetization at time_zero,
we have not done anything
to the phase of the magnetization.
This is always done
in the rotating reference frame
so we don't consider the effect of B_0.
It makes it easier to write less terms.
At times 2 tau we have the magnetization
at times tau here, that we start with--
we're always talking about
transverse magnetization of course--
times e to the minus gamma G_x
times x times tau.
We have here the time here,
from here to here, is tau.
So that's the magnetization
at times 2 tau.
And we can now substitute M of tau--
magnetizaton of time tau--
into this equation here,
we get this term that is over here.
On the right-hand side, the magnetization
that is now recorded times 2 tau
is the magnetization at times tau
times e to the gamma G_x x
plus G_z z times tau.
And what we have used here
is just a general term--
that's the magnetic field-- the B_0--
in the presence of a gradient,
now we take the B_0 out because
we're in a rotating reference frame,
but the variation
of the magnetic field in space
is given by gamma times the scalar product
of the gradient vector times position.
And here the gradient vector
has components along x and z.
So we can rewrite this now:
M_z m of tau is M_0.
We'll write these terms here
and we'll split them according to x and z.
And now what we will notice
is this term here,
and this term here.
Upon inspection, we notice
that these two terms are identical.
So the magnetization M of zero
in both cases is the same--
we start out here,
we don't know yet what's happening
so the magnetization at that point
has to be the same.
The conclusion here is the application
of two gradients that are orthogonal--
say x and z in this particular example,
could be any two directions--
simultaneously or sequentially,
doesn't matter,
it produces the same phase for the
transverse magnetization subsequently.
So what this means, basically, is
that we have the magnetization
described here or described here.
These two diagrams, in terms of
what's happening to the magnetization--
the transverse magnetization--
to its phase, are identical.
So if we have difficulty understanding
the diagram on the right
we can always suppose that this,
on the left, is happening.
So at time TE, the magnetization is given
by the magnetization at 2 tau
times this term here,
and we can write this now,
we may put in the magnetization of 2 tau
into this term here,
and then we get
the magnetization of time_zero times
e to the i gamma G_z
times z times tau.
The effect of x of course,
the gradient is nullified exactly at TE,
so we only have the influence
of the z gradient.
Okay, so this is just to bear in mind
if you see the diagram where the gradients
are in two different directions,
are applied simultaneously.
If this creates conceptual problems
you can always think of that
you have much more space
to draw them sequentially
like on the left-hand side
if that is easier to understand.
I didn't do it because
it makes the display of what is to come
very crowded and very difficult to read.
So now I will introduce the basic elements
of the so-called gradient echo sequence.
We'll start out, of course,
with a RF pulse--
this is what we do with the RF pulse,
we flip the longitudinal magnetization
by alpha degrees
into the transverse plane.
We start out with
a magnetization at time_0
which is just the z component
before the RF pulse.
This defines one time point here.
We will now have
the frequency encode gradient,
we have it negative and then positive,
so that's essentially the situation we've
been discussing in the previous slides.
The negative area here
equals to the positive area here.
When this is matched then we have,
at this time point,
we have echo formation,
and that is the echo time.
So this is what we observe here--
we have the signal as a function of time
and we have echo formation
exactly at echo time.
Now this is an experiment
that we've discussed implicitly--
I have not drawn the RF pulses--
now we want to do slide selection,
and as we've discussed
earlier in the course,
this is done by applying,
at the same time as the RF pulses,
to apply a gradient, and here
we'll call this gradient the z gradient.
So what this alpha pulse now does--
alpha degree pulse--
it will flip the magnetization
by alpha degrees
into the transverse plane
at the Larmor condition defined
by the radio frequency of the RF pulse.
And we have a positive gradient afterwards
and a negative gradient subsequently.
Now why do we have to deal
with this gradient switching
in the slide selection?
Wouldn't it be just enough
to turn on the gradient,
we do the slide selection,
and we're done with it?
Well, the situation is also--
Here you can see.
that previously we have assumed
the gradient switched on instantaneously,
and here you can see
in this gross exaggeration,
that the gradient switching
takes some time.
And this has to do with the question of
why do have to have echo formation?
We have, after the RF pulse,
the gradient is on.
So the magnetization
is in a transverse plane,
it will spread out, if we turn it off,
the magnetization will stay spread out.
If it's spread out,
that means it's spread out
according to the position along z,
the magnetization vectors
no longer act co-linearly,
and therefore the signal is reduced.
What this negative gradient here does
it takes into account
this dead time here that we have
and makes them run
in the opposite direction,
the magnetization vectors,
and with a matching condition,
they will be all co-linear
and we will have maximal signal.
So, let's look at the effect if we don't
turn on this negative gradient,
the signal is given by
the transverse magnetization
across the slice,
times e to the i gamma and
G_z times z over tau
integrated over z.
So this term, with time,
will eventually go to zero--
that's dephasing.
So we can not record
the maximal signal, the signal decays,
and it actually decays rather fast.
It is a decay that is almost like a FID,
it's not T 2,
it's the effect of the dephasing
from the different positions
along the slice.
We can rephase this term,
we can make the magnetization
co-linear again by rephasing,
that is, by applying a gradient
with opposite polarity--
here it's strong negative--
and this leads to echo formation.
And if we write this in general terms,
and for this slice,
if we integrate over this slice,
we have the magnetization,
times e to the--
in general terms the phase is here given
by phase of time,
the phase is given by the integral of...
for a given position
of gamma G_z T over time.
And we want this to be maximal--
that's what gives us echo formation.
So this phase term,
this term must be maximal
and there is actually
a nice condition for that
and that is that
the integral of the gradient,
from zero to a certain time
of the gradient
is equal to zero.
So that basically is
what's depicted here--
this area equals to this area,
that's the same thing as saying
it's the integral over time
is equal to zero, and that leads
to echo formation.
So in this example we have
the slice select, the slice orientation,
the slice gradient
is perpendicular to the read,
or frequency encode gradient,
so x and z are presumed to be orthogonal.
Whether we call them x or z or y and z
and so on, whatever we call them,
doesn't matter-- the main condition here
is that they are orthogonal.
Of course, at some point,
the ADC is opened up,
the data is sampled,
that is done here,
and then the recorded signal
that is recorded in the scanner
looks like this.
What is crucial here is
we don't just record
from the maximal echo and then onward,
we record also the first half of the echo.
This is done because this is--
at very little cost of time,
one can increase the sensitivity
because there's more data points
that are being sampled.
So this is your basic imaging sequence,
the basic elements,
and this describes what's happening
every TR seconds.
That's your basic imaging sequence.