In the previous section,
I introduced the principle
of slice selection
and frequency encoding
with gradient switching,
and I said, this is almost the essential--
the basic imaging sequence.
What I haven't told you is,
how do we get
the second spatial dimension encoded?
So, let's recap what we've seen.
We have had an RF pulse,
that flips the magnetization
to transfer spin by α degrees.
We have the slice select gradient
with the rephase.
I will not comment on here.
The frequency encode,
with echo formation.
This is the condition of zero integral
for the gradient,
so this defines the echo time, TE.
This is the signal that is produced.
The data sampling is done
over this time period,
and this is what is the sample signal
that arrives in our computer.
Now, what we see here is
that this produces us a slice selection--
that's what this does--
and an encoding of a projection,
in one direction.
But where's the second dimension?
So, for the second dimension,
we turn on the phase encode gradient
here along Y.
We just turn on the gradient
at this position
for a certain amount of time,
with a certain amplitude.
And this is now the entire experiment.
However, this gradient is applied--
this phase encode gradient
is applied with a certain amplitude.
That does not give us spatial information.
So, this is repeated,
with a changed amplitude.
So, here, reduced
by an amount ΔGz. Uh, Gy.
And we repeat it again.
We'll repeat it every TR seconds,
that's the repetition time.
We increment or decrement by ΔGy,
and so forth.
We go through zero, we go
into the negative values, and so forth,
until we have scanned the number
of phase encode steps that we want.
So, what we have here now
is three gradients.
The slice selection gradient,
perpendicular read gradient,
and the phase encode
is perpendicular to both slice and read.
This gives us a Cartesian encoding
of the signal.
So, we are distinguishing three phases
of the imaging sequence.
We have-- first part is excitation.
Since all the spatial manipulations,
the spatial encoding,
is done on the transverse plane,
we need to get the magnetization
into the transverse plane.
During excitation, typically there is
slice selection that's being done.
The next phase is phase encoding,
so that is the encoding
of the second dimension,
and then we have frequency encoding
and echo formation,
that is the encoding
of the first spatial dimension.
So, we have slice selection,
frequency encoding, and phase encoding.
All this together,
repeated every TR seconds,
with the phase encode gradient
changing after every RF pulse--
this gives us the information
to generate an image.
Now, to understand
how this phase encode gradient
produces the information
that allows us to reconstruct an image
is not trivial, and I'm going to try,
in the next following slides--
try to explain this.
It is difficult to understand
how this phase encoding gradient allows
to encode the second spatial dimension.
So, and that's exactly the question
we're going to look at now.
So, let's say we have
a two-dimensional object, along X and Y.
We're looking at the voxel magnetization--
the transverse voxel magnetization
in our two-dimensional object.
It's a seven by seven object, here.
Now, if we do apply
a phase encode gradient along Y,
then we apply it for a certain duration,
with a certain amplitude,
then we have-- along Y,
we have phases that change.
For all the positions along X,
they have the same position,
so they have the same phase,
but along Y, it depends
on their position in Y.
These guys have not changed,
the others have changed.
These turned to the right,
and these turned to the left, below.
Now, we'll repeat this
with twice the gradient strength.
So, this means that,
if we repeat this experiment
with twice the gradient strength,
for each of the positions,
the vector moves by twice the angle.
Now we'll say
we have applied this gradient for time τ,
and we'll express this
in imaginary and real compositions,
in the complex plane.
So, we'll say, the X magnetization is...
real, and the Y magnetization
is imaginary.
These X and Ys,
that's in magnetization space.
This is the real space
that pertains to here.
So, if we look at a given voxel,
then its position--
its phase is given
by the position along Y,
the duration τ, and the gradient Gy.
So, the phase here
is given by this term here.
That's what's happened
after applying this gradient Gy
for a duration τ.
Now, after we have applied
this phase encode gradient,
Gy for τ seconds,
we have this phase term here.
I'll re-write this here.
This is the situation that we have.
And now, we want to look at what happens
during the application
of the read-out gradient.
And here, we're not going to deal
with the complexities
of the need to generate an echo;
we'll just start at what's happening
at the time of the echo.
So, at the time of echo,
we will start with a phase evolution
that's determined now--
because it's under the influence
of an X gradient,
that's determined by the magnitude
of the gradient,
the position, and the time variable τ.
So, I'll plot this,
and as the gradient is turned on along X,
then we will see, now,
that the magnetizations along Y...
they have the same
precessional frequency here,
but along X, their precessional frequency
is different.
These turn clockwise,
these turn counterclockwise,
and here, on the resonance,
they don't move.
They just have the phase difference
that was induced by the Y gradient.
So, clearly, if we now
Fourier transform this signal,
this is what we are observing here,
we will get the different frequencies
as a function of X position.
We'll now take these two terms here,
and we'll re-write them,
and we'll re-write them
such that we introduce
the variables Kx, Ky here,
the Fourier pair variables
to X and Y, to the position.
So, this we can write
as e ^ (Kx ∙ x + Ky ∙ y) ∙ i.
That's the... re-writing here,
we have used here the definition
for the K space vector in this case.
So, that's the phase
of our voxel magnetization,
and that we have
for a position X and Y that is given.
Ok, so we have seen that applying
a gradient for a short time along Y,
in the phase encode direction,
produces a phase twist
according to the position in Y.
And then, applying the gradient along X
induces precessional frequencies
that are being recorded,
that depend on the position in Y.
And now, how can we understand
how this generates the necessary
information for image reconstruction?
What we're now going to do is,
we're going to look at the phase
of a single pixel in the X-Y plane.
Ok, we'll say we'll take
the magnetization phase of a single pixel,
at a given position-- you can consider it
a pointwise object,
a capillary or something--
just a pointwise object,
idealized, with no dimensions.
We'll just take a single pixel.
And we'll plot,
on the horizontal axis here,
we will plot the time.
During that time, we have the readout,
that is the gradient Gx is on,
so we have Gx ∙ T, is the phase,
dependent on Gx ∙ T.
So, we'll start out here.
We apply the gradient
along X, and we will have,
over time, as we apply the gradient,
we have the phase of our magnetization
that changes with time.
This is simple precession.
The phase increments,
for this particular voxel--
remember, we're just looking
at one single voxel,
one single pixel in space.
We're just considering that case.
And so, now, we have the evolution
of the phase with time.
That's basically our representation of...
precession.
So, we can say we are digitizing,
here, seven time points.
We're looking at seven time points.
Now, we'll do step one.
We will apply gradient along Y.
That gradient will induce a phase twist,
according to the position of the voxel.
So, after having applied this gradient,
the magnetization of our voxel
starts out at this position,
and now, during the time
where we apply the X gradient,
there is the same phase twist
that's applied on the magnetization
of our voxel, of our pixel,
that's happening.
So, the relative phase of this,
relative to this, is the relative phase...
of this to this, but this twist here
is due to the position in Y,
to the application
of the gradient along Y.
We'll do the next step.
So, we have twice
the gradient amplitude along Y.
So, the phase
is twice as big here, to start with.
We'll just draw
the seven time points along X,
and as we apply the gradient along X,
then the magnetization
develops along X, as we see here.
We'll do the third step, and we'll have
a phase evolution during the Y gradient.
Now, for each of the end steps,
the gradient that's applied here
is proportional to ΔGy,
so it increases...
linearly with time.
If we go in the opposite direction,
we'll have the starting phase
of the magnetization
in the opposite direction,
twice the opposite direction,
and three times the opposite direction,
again with the phase being twisted
by the readout gradient.
So, here we have no evolution along X,
so we see the starting phase
of the magnetization
for each of the gradient
applications along Y.
Here was no gradient application along Y.
Here, we have the pure effect
of the X gradient.
Now, the question here is,
does the computer that will digitize
this seven-by-seven matrix here--
will the computer
be able to distinguish...
whether these seven points
have been recorded sequentially,
or these seven points
have been recorded sequentially?
Look at the magnetization vector here,
and the magnetization vector here,
and you will see that those...
this particular column
and this particular row, they are--
in terms of magnetization vector,
they are indistinguishable.
We cannot distinguish their positions.
So, from a standpoint of computer--
the computer is a stupid machine.
At least, those computers
that we are talking about here.
It does not know
how the data was acquired.
It just gets the data.
If it now examines this data set,
it will not be able to say
from this seven-by-seven matrix,
we've been encoding
these seven time points sequentially,
or we've been encoding
these seven time points sequentially.
So, in essence, when you store the data
in the computer in this fashion,
then the way the data is stored is,
the role of phase encode
and readout gradient are interchangeable.
They can no longer be distinguished.
And so, the phase encoding amounts,
essentially, to frequency encoding,
which is what we're doing
in the X direction, in the same way.
Now, this comes
from the simple fact that,
if we have a change in phase
with time, like here,
this corresponds to a precessional
frequency that we have seen.
That's very simple, but if we now
introduce the second dimension,
also a time component,
then this phase evolution here
will also correspond to a frequency--
a precessional frequency.
Except that it's not real time,
it is the time variable introduced
by phase encode steps
one, two, three, et cetera.
So, if we look at the signal
of the voxel we have here,
we can attribute this to a time ΔT,
so we can introduce, along Y,
a second time component.
Or, in general, our signal is given
by the nth gradient,
phase encode gradient N,
the increment
of the phase encode gradient,
ΔGy, which is constant--
this is proportional
to the transverse magnetization
at the beginning, at the position X and Y.
That's this particular XY.
This is the effect
of the phase encode gradient,
so it's γ ∙ N ∙ ΔGy, is this amplitude Gy,
and e ^ (i ∙ γ ∙ Gx ∙ X ∙ T),
that's the evolution
during the readout gradient.
Again, here we have not considered
echo formation.
We are assuming
that we're starting at the echo.
The principle here
is more important than exact detail.
So, this is our signal
of the individual voxel.
Now, we'll introduce the definition
of two variables, Kx-- that's γ ∙ Gx ∙ T,
and Ky, which is γ ∙ Gy ∙ τ.
These are the phases-- the phase terms,
proportional to the phase terms.
With these definitions,
we can rewrite our signal
as a function of Kx and Ky.
We have the transverse magnetization,
that's this term,
and now the phase term here changes,
and you can verify
this gives us the (Kx ∙ X + Ky ∙ Y) ∙ i.
That's our signal of our voxel
with the transformation of the variables.
Here, this is what we relate
to the experiment.
These are mathematical
variable transformations.
Ok, so far this is the signal
for a single pixel.
Pointwise object.
How about the signal for an entire object?
Well, we're going to have to integrate
along X and Y,
so we'll do a two-dimensional integral
across our object, in X and Y.
Our signal along the Kx, Ky is given by--
is proportional to the transverse
magnetization at that position,
times e ^ i ∙ (Kx ∙ x + Ky ∙ y).
Well... what does this resemble?
Maybe you've come across
similar expressions already?
Well, this is the Fourier transformation
of the object.
Or, to obtain the MR image,
we have to do the Fourier transformation
of the signal.
Remember, this is the signal we record.
This is with the variable transformation.
We have a Fourier representation,
to get this from this,
we have to do the Fourier transformation,
so we get the magnetization
by doing the Fourier transformation
of the signal here in K space.
So, K space and real space,
that's like Fourier space and real space.
It's like reciprocal space,
that's the K space, the term here.
X and Y are the real space,
but the image--
the process of acquiring the image--
with MRI, essentially
what we are acquiring
is the Fourier transformation
of the object.
And to obtain from the data
that's stored in the computer--
to obtain the image, what one has to do
is a two-dimensional
Fourier transformation.