Let's look at how this spacial information
is encoded in MRI.
We have introduced the fact
that we are scanning Fourier,
or reciprocal space, or k-space.
This is the frequency direction along x--
I'll use the same variables and along y,
the phasing code direction.
So, along x we are looking
at the gradient here.
We are not going to bother again
with the dephasing
and rephasing, or the echo,
we are just going
to simplify here the diagram,
and we have the phasing code gradient.
This is our sample signal
that we have here,
we are acquiring at this point.
So, if we apply the phasing code gradient,
then we have a ky that's non-zero,
and we will encode kx
according to time here.
So these are the points in kx.
So we have acquired here one line
in k-space, or reciprocal space.
We will repeat it
with a different amplitude
for the y gradient;
then we encode the second line of k-space
so the gradient is reduced,
so ky is reduced;
the third line,
and each time this is stored in
a two dimensional matrix;
fourth line, fifth line, sixth line
seventh, eighth, et cetera,
and as we acquire this.
And then we do this much faster,
and this is the sound that you hear:
"Bzz, bzz, bzz, bzz, bzz,..."
As you hear the sound from the MRI,
this is how the k-space matrix
is being filled up.
So, we don't have here the RF pulse--
we have not drawn this
but, of course, we have an RF pulse,
each time that we have to apply.
And so this means,
we have one line of k-space
that's been acquired per T R,
T R being the time between RF pulses.
T R, as we have seen, is determined
by the longitudinal relaxation time,
so it is typically
on the order of seconds.
The acquisition here, this is typically
on the order of milliseconds.
So this is very fast done--
these data points are fast acquired,
and here every line
is acquired every T R seconds.
So, if we are looking for a 256^2 matrix,
the re-dimension is in milliseconds--
that does not count--
but if we have 256 phasing code directions
and we take typically T1 of one second,
our T R is on the order of seconds.
Then an image 256^2 matrix,
it takes roughly four minutes
to acquire that data.
Conclusion: MR scans are long
and motion-sensitive.
They are long because the acquisition
has in large part to do with T1.
T1 is not very short,
and motion-sensitive because every time
you acquire a k-space line here,
you acquire information
on the entire object.
If this part of the matrix does not fir
this part of the matrix,
then, of course,
they don't reconstruct very well,
and this produces a mismatch
and therefore motion artifacts.
So, here is an example of a subject
that moved during acquisition.
[inaudible] this is a sagittal cut,
the nose is here,
the brainstem is here,
so this is the brain
and you can see here these bright areas,
here these streaking artifacts,
one has so called ghosting,
so that signal that does not belong
where it is being observed--
there is no signal outside of the head--
or ringing artifacts
that are being observed.
So, there are few things we can say
about the image matrix.
So, the maximum kx or ky
that one acquires,
that determines the resolution,
and the increment, the Δ k,
that is either Δ kx or Δ ky,
through the Nyquist theorem
determines the field of view.
So if we have closely spaced samples,
then one gets a big field of view,
if one has a lot of samples,
one gets a high spatial resolution.
So, this whole process,
since what has been acquired,
is the Fourier transform of the object.
In this process of image reconstruction
there is no influence on the resolution.
The resolution is uniform
across the entire image
and also the sensitivity as such,
once a signal is acquired,
the reconstruction process
induces a uniform sensitivity.
So, in principle we could acquire an image
with 8,192 pixels in one direction,
and 8,192 pixels in the other direction--
we are not limited
from the acquisition process
to the size of the matrix.
However, the limitation that we encounter
is the voxel magnetization.
As we have seen a few weeks ago,
the sensitivity is maximal
for thermodynamic
equilibrium magnetization,
and that is determined
by the magnetization in the voxel--
that's the number of molecules et cetera,
so there is the fundamental limit.
We have in the k-space matrix
we have one particular point to consider,
and that's where kx and ky
are equal to zero--
that's the center of k-space.
At this point kx and ky are zero
and this point is of particular interest--
that's where the image is maximal--
we have no dephasing in any direction
of the magnetization.
Let's look at the properties
of the k-space matrix.
Here is an image of an MRI,
the data acquired
at 512 x 512 spatial resolution,
that's the reconstructed image,
that's the 2D Fourier transform,
that's x, y space,
and this is k-space here, kx, ky.
If we now take the center eight points,
eight by eight,
and reconstruct this,
we are getting a very blurry image.
If we take the image and we eliminate
those central eight points,
we get more or less
sharper features of the object.
We do the same thing now
with just taking
the first 16 points at the center,
reconstruct, and here we eliminate
the central 16 x 16 points,
and we are starting to see the edges here
and here we are starting to see
some of the structure.
32 x 32, and it's already quite amazing
how much contrast we have
at this point, 32 x 32,
that's a very small matrix
compared to 512.
We are starting to see already structures
here, in this brain scan,
and eliminating the first central 32 points
gives edge features.
Now, the one thing
that we have to bear in mind
is that the center k-space point
determines the contrast of the image.
And this comes from the center
of the k-space,
that's S (0, 0), kx, ky = 0,
is given by this expression here
with kx = 0 and ky = 0.
So this is the Fourier transform
of the magnetization--
that's what we are detecting.
If we look at the discrete
Fourier transformation,
and the discrete Fourier transformation
we employ the fact here
that it is periodic
over the sample time period
and we can do a time shift.
With a time shift--so here is the signal--
that's the echo that we record
we can in the discrete
Fourier transformation
this signal is going to be
the same signal here
in that magnitude as this signal,
so we've taken this half,
shifted it to the left
and that half, as we shift,
we fold it around
and put it on this side.
And now we have seen,
before, for the Fourier transformation,
that the signal at time zero
is proportional to the magnetization.
Here is our time signal, zero,
so this signal here
is proportional to the magnetization
and therefore is proportional
to equilibrium magnetization
and the effects of relaxation.
Okay, et's go on; we have 64 x 64,
the image gets sharper
and we are getting more and more,
outside of the 64 x 64
are very sharp features,
the high frequency component,
128 x 128, really now only
seen the sharp edges
and here the image is almost
the same quality as this image here,
and we are left with very sharp features.
So, what this means
in terms of data acquisition,
if your subject moves here
close to the central k-space points
you are going to have
a very big impact on the image,
whereas, if it moves here at the edges,
where there is
a very little signal out here,
the impact is much less.
So crossing through zero k-space point
defines a contrast
and also the magnitude
of the motion artifacts.
I want to summarize the spatial encoding
with the gradients.
I'll try here a depiction that is more
on a mathematical basis.
So, we will have here the RF pulse--
that's done by the B1.
We have a flip angle α,
and we will look now
at the magnetization
at the time point specified,
magnetization at time one.
That's just z magnetization.
This is being rotated by the RF pulse
by α degree about x,
so at the time point two
we have rotating about x
in rotating plane,
so the y component is Mz sin α
and the z component is Mz cos α.
And now we'll just be interested
in what's happening in transverse plane,
so we'll forget about
the longitudinal component.
We'll just consider now
the transverse magnetization.
This transverse magnetization will precess
depending on the gradient
with γ Gy y or γ Gx x.
So the precessional frequency here
is given by γ (B0 + G (t) ･ r).
So I will take the gradient along y,
we'll apply it here
for a certain amount of time,
with an amplitude of n Δ Gy,
and we have the gradient along y,
first applied negative.
We will define here the time points,
we will define this time point,
number three,
and this duration
between two and three shall be τ.
So, at this time point between
two and three
the magnetization in the transverse plane,
we're just looking at the traverse plane,
is the My magnetization that we had here,
this magnetization,
times sin of the phase
and for the x component
and for the y component cos of the phase--
that we have here.
So, this is the phase x,
so if we take influence of the gradient
we will call this phase.
So, now we will have the inverted gradient,
so now the B field becomes + γ Gx x.
During this time we have the precession
according to the position in our area
and so we will have a rotation,
so rotation of the magnetization along x
by an angle + Φx.
So, what we have here
we have written here--
we have not considered
the effect of the y gradient,
just considered the effect of x gradient.
This gives the rotation by - Φx.
If we have now inversion
of the polarity of the gradient,
this rotates the magnetization
by an angle + Φx.
So, this gives us
a maximal signal at TE = 2 τ
that's this time here.
And we'll assume here for this argument
that Δ G y = 2 0.
And now we are looking
at the fourth time point.
For Δ G y = 0
the magnetization is now given
by Mz sin α for the y component
and Mz cos α for the z component,
where we have echo formation.
So, we can work in these equations
fully for the mathematically
for the effect of the gradients.
Now, the signal at time τ or t
it is for the phasing code gradient,
we have the influence
of the phasing code gradient,
magnetization at the start and influence
of the [inaudible] gradient,
so we have T here, τ here
so it's τ +T is the influence
of the gradient,
and we can rewrite this
as the signal in k-space,
again, with appropriate
variable transformation.
So mathematically MRI--
this is the key take-home message--
MRI measures the 2D
Fourier transformation of the object.
That's what is being registered.
What is also key is that measuring
the second spatial dimension,
that requires time, and this time
is strongly influenced by T1 [at hand],
which are typically
on the order of seconds.
So, this is very complicated,
I understand,
so understanding phase encoding
is not a very easy topic.
We will try to rehash
the process of phase encoding
under a different perspective
at the beginning of next week
to look at this
with a slightly different optic
so we can digest this factor
and understand
how spacial information is being encoded.