Welcome back!
In this session we will now talk
about the concrete management
of the urban electricity utility.
And this is generally done historically
by an electricity managing utility,
which is integrated and operates the grid
as well as the selling of the electricity
In most of the countries
this utility is standing alone,
but in some countries
it is the same utility
that also manages the gas,
the water, the cables
and sometimes even urban public transport.
The utility is generally
traditionally a public entity
owned by the municipalities.
As of recently with liberalization,
with market based approach,
some of the activities
have been outsourced
to private operators,
especially electricity selling
and purchasing.
But we will see that.
Now, what I will do concretely here
is to proceed in four steps.
So, what are the major managing tasks
in operations and management
of the urban electricity grid
in terms of grid development,
in terms of customer relations
and in terms of energy purchasing.
Let's first talk about the grid.
The biggest challenge
that urban electricity
infrastructure managers confront
is the challenge of balancing
demand and supply.
You know that electricity cannot be stored.
That means there needs always
to be the same amount of electricity
being fed into the grid
as being consumed.
So the big challenge is
to make that balance.
If there is too much electricity,
there is a blackout,
If there is not enough electricity,
there is a blackout.
That is the big, big challenge.
This challenge is exacerbated
by self-generation.
So you all know that electricity
is not consumed in the same amount.
There are peak hours.
During the day there is more electricity
than there is produced.
And that creates an inbalance
at some certain peak hours
during lunch time, during evening time.
All this balancing activity
is exacerbated by self-generation,
which has to be factored in
when balancing the electricity.
And it is further exacerbated
by intermittency.
That means, especially if you produce
with renewable energies,
of course, solar energy
cannot really be planned as well--
Solar electricity production
cannot be planned as well
as nuclear electricity production,
which can be clearly forecasted.
So intermittency, renewables, all this
exacerbates the balancing challenge
that urban electricity managers have.
And some of this actually
requires grid reinforcement.
Historically the electricity grid
is a top down grid.
You go from high voltage to medium voltage
to low voltage to consumers.
But with self-generation actually
consumers also produce
and therefore you need
to plan grid reinforcement,
and that helps me to make the link
to the next big challenge,
which is the grid development.
Especially in the case of rapidly growing cities,
let us say, you add a new city
or part of the city,
10,000 new inhabitants
or 50,000 new inhabitants.
You need to develop new connections.
This needs to be planned,
the electricity needs to be brought
to these new areas
without destabilizing the rest
of the urban electricity grid.
Grid development is especially
a challenge for planning.
You cannot put these grids in overnight,
so you need to plan, you need to buy,
to ensure the financing,
and this is really the next big steps,
and often the financing
of the traditional grid activities
is not sufficient
in order to generate the money
to roll out new grids
to totally new areas.
So as a manager you have to make sure
that you get the finances
to develop the electricity grid.
We have talked
about public-private partnerships,
but alternatives are also to have
the developers of these new cities
contribute to the financing
of the electricity grid--
a new big management challenge.
The third big management challenge
pertains of course to the customers,
the way you relate to the customers.
Electricity must be metered, measured
and then billed to the customers.
That is how ultimately
the utility makes its money.
It better make sure
that it is correctly metered
in order, for example,
to avoid complaint by the customers
which have to be handled,
and that is timeconsuming and annoying
and of course they have
to be billed correctly, in time,
not too late, so as to generate
the money that is required.
There are several more challenges here
in terms of customer relations.
There are non-paying customers
or customers that are paying too late.
At some point you have to decide
as an electricity manager
whether you want
to hook them off the grid or not,
whether that will cause you problems,
whether that is even
politically allowed or not,
whether you want to offer paying plans
to the non-paying customers,
but this is a big issue
because hooking off customers
has also a cost.
There are things in some countries,
more rather in emerging countries
and developing countries,
known as electricity theft.
People hook onto the electricity grid
before the meter,
and actually consume electricity
without paying for it.
It can be an important factor
which of course results in revenue loss.
But also it results in loss of predictability
when you try to balance
the electricity system.
This must of course be addressed.
And in some cities, in some countries
you actually have social tariffs
in the sense that some customers
do not pay the same amount of money
for the same amount
of electricity consumed.
This has to be handled.
Social tariffs are ordered
for political reasons.
They will result in a revenue loss
for the electricity operator,
but the operator then has to go
after the political authotities
to make sure that he is being compensated
for the social tariffs
he is forced to offer.
Now, the fourth big management task
pertains to purchasing of electricity.
As I have already said,
the city is generally not producing
its own electricity.
It is buying it from somewhere.
And it is important, as you understand,
that is makes the right buying decisions.
And this buying traditionally happens
by way of contract.
You are contracting with a producer.
We have seen that in the session before,
but this carries risk.
You may have the wrong contract.
You may buy electricity too expensively
when later it becomes cheaper.
So buying the electricity,
purchasing the electricity that is needed
for a whole city is actually
a complex managerial task
which increasingly is made more complex,
because now you also have power exchanges,
traders, as we have seen before.
You can buy from them.
You may get actually a better price
buying from traders,
but at the same time
this carries more risks.
In other words, electricity purchasing
is becoming a big managerial activity
of a local electricity utility.
Now, we have seen previously,
in previous blocks and sessions,
we have talked about the main dimensions
of managing urban infrastructure systems
So balancing would
rather be a technical task,
pertain to the technical dimension
of management,
the whole grid development
rather pertain to technical
and economic dimensions
the managing the customers pertains
to social and political dimensions
and the whole purchasing
of course pertains to economic
and also to environmental dimensions.
For example, in the case
where you are trying to buy
green energy, green electricity
because this is something
that your customers may require.
In this session I have basically talked
about the four main management functions.
And, very simplistically, they pertain
to the grid, the development of the grid,
the maintenance of the grid,
the operations of the grid,
and then they pertain
to the energy itself, electricity itself,
the customers that consume it,
the traders, the sellers,
the producers of the electricity
that produce it.
These are both big management tasks
of urban electricity managers.
Now, these functions will evolve,
and we will see this in the next session.
These functions will evolve
because there are new challenges.
What I have described before,
is basically a relatively static view,
but there are new challenges
on the horizon:
like climate change,
like information communication technologies
we have talked about,
and these challenges may actually
also be new opportunities for urban
electricity infrastructure managers.
Stay tuned.