Hello, in order to better illustrate
this course
and especially the chapters
describing the methodology,
we need to introduce
a practical example.
We have decided to focus
on diagnostic imaging
and specifically on radiology.
In this video we will explain what
is radiology and why it is needed.
However, we will only give you the
very basic information
on X-ray radiology that we need to
be able to illustrate the concepts.
It is not the purpose of this course
to give you a complete presentation
on this topic.
Those of you who are interested to
learn more will find
additional material
on the website.
Let us start by having a brief look
at the invention of this technology
Wilhelm Conrad Röntgen was
a German physicist born in 1845,
he was the first to discover
a new type of rays,
which he called X-rays.
He was awarded a Nobel prize in 1901
for his discovery.
In the picture on the right, you
can see the very first X-ray image
of a human body part. For instance,
showing his wife's hand wearing a nice ring.
When she saw her skeleton
she was shocked and she exclaimed
"I have seen my death!"
This picture was taken in 1895
well over a century ago
it marked the birth of medical
radiology.
Let us now see how X-rays
are used in medicine.
X-ray is a high energy ionizing radiation
which can travel through human tissue,
where it can be more or less absorbed
depending on the tissue's density.
For example, bone tissue has higher
absorption than soft tissue,
such as the lung.
More generally, materials with high
atomic numbers
have high absorption properties. Lead,
for instance, has a very high atomic number
and is thus used to block X-rays,
which, due to their ionizing properties
can potentially be harmful
for humans.
X-rays are generated in a vacuum tube,
shown on the left ,
in this tube there is a cathode
and an anode.
The cathode,
which is a tungsten filament,
is heated up with an electric current.
When enough energy is transmitted to
the cathode's atoms some electrons
will be emitted through
a thermal ionic effect.
If we now apply a large voltage difference
between the cathode and the anode,
typically 40 to 100 kilo-volts,
the electrons will be accelerated
at a high speed away from the
cathode in the direction of the anode.
Once they hit the anode, the electrons
are slowed down by the anode material,
which causes the emission of X-rays.
The process requires a lot of power
as only 1% of the energy
is effectively transformed into
X-rays and the rest is lost as heat.
There are several different
configurations of
medical X-ray systems. In one
frequently encountered configuration,
the tube is mounted on a stand
with a swiveling arm,
such as the one shown here.
This configuration allows to ensure
that the tube remains aimed
at the image recording device
at all times.
The system also includes a power
generator and a control panel.
In an other configuration, the tube
is mounted on a pointing device
attached to the ceiling
or to the floor,
with a rail system to enable
moving it around.
Some systems include a table where
the patient can be examined
in a lying position, and where the
image recording device is integrated.
Finally, there are also mobile systems
on wheels, which can be moved
to the patient's bedside.
Let us now go back and talk about
the image recording device.
Once the X-rays have traveled through
the patient's body they have
to be transformed into an image
that the radiologist can see.
This can be achieved basically with
two different processes,
which are both still in use today.
In the first process, the X-ray image
is converted into visible light
by means of a screen placed close
to a photographic film,
this screen is made of special
crystals and it is also known
as a scintillator screen.
When the X-ray beam containing the
patient's image hits the screen,
visible light is emitted, which
exposes the photographic emulsion of the film.
The film on the screen are located
inside a tightly closed frame
called a cassette.
The second technique generates
a digital image directly,
there is no film involved.
Let's look into these two techniques
in some more details.
Here you can see a chest radiography
being taken in a hospital in Cameroon,
as you can see the radiographer on the
right is wearing a protective lead apron.
Here, he's using a mobile radiography system.
Note that one has to distinguish between
a radiographer and radiologist,
these are two different jobs.
Basically a radiographer is a technician
trained to make radiological images
and the radiologist is a medical
doctor trained to interpret the images
with the purpose to come up
with the diagnosis.
The patient stands in front of
what is called a "Wall-bucky",
where the cassette with the film
is located.
The radiographer aims the tube
at the patient and exposes the film.
Once this is done, the cassette is
retrieved and taken away for development.
The processing of the film usually
involves steps of developing
rinsing, fixing, washing and drying.
This must be done in a dark room and
involves the use of specific and
toxic chemicals.
The timing and temperature of the
process need to be controlled
precisely, otherwise the image
quality will be degraded.
The film can be processed either
manually or automatically,
using a film processor, in which case
there is no need for a dark room
but the processor requires
electricity and maintenance.
For either manual or automatic
processing the total cost
of the film and chemicals needed for
one image is around 3.50 US dollars.
In many low and middle income countries
the patient will also have to pay for
the diagnosis itself, which
can typically cost 15 US dollars.
In a digital imaging process
the film is replaced
by a photo sensitive detector. The
technology involves a conversion of
the X-ray image into either visible
light or charges that can be
captured by some electronic sensor.
The current state
of the architecture technology
relies on large detector plates
called flat panels.
The detectors have exactly
the same size as the image
they capture, because it is
very difficult to focus X-ray beams.
In the detector, a layer of
scintillator material
converts the X-ray into visible
light. Directly behind
the scintillator layer is
a sensor array of which each pixel
generates an electrical signal
in proportion to the light received.
This electric signal is encoded
in order to produce
an accurate digital representation
of the X-ray image.
Flat panels have the disadvantage
of being very expensive and fragile,
in addition, their performance degrade
quickly when temperatures increases
above 27 to 30 degrees celsius.
There are other types of X-ray
imaging devices based,
for example, on CCD  or CMOS detectors,
which are similar to the technology
that can be found
in your digital cameras.
They tend to be more cumbersome and
less sensitive to X-ray radiation
than flat panels.
Sensitivity is an important
parameter, because due to
the potentially harmful effect
of X-rays,
one has to limit the patient
exposure as much as possible.
while still being able
to generate a good image.
Being able to process, store,
review, and transfer digital images
is certainly a great advantage, this
requires a so called PACS,
which stands for: Picture Archiving
and Communication System.
The PACS also allows to manage
the workflow of patient exams.
In modern hospitals, the radiographer
can take an image in some location
and the radiologist can review it
on a workstation located elsewhere.
As a a consequence, a PACS generally
requires that some information
and communication capabilities
are available in the hospital.
In summary, let us say that analog
film screen is still very much in use today,
and overwhelmingly so
in low and middle income countries.
However, like in film photography,
it is a technology
that will most certainly disappear
in the future.
It's main disadvantage is the fact
that it relies on consumables,
such as films and chemicals for development,
which can be difficult to obtain.
In addition, while the purchase cost
of the system itself is quite low
compared to digital solutions, the
recurring cost of those consumables
makes this quite an expensive
solution in the long run.
Finally, it is a slow technique which
requires quite a bit of know-how
to be able to make good images.
Digital solutions are more expensive
to purchase and more complex to use
and maintain. Due to the increased
complexity, the need for maintenance,
and calibration, are also increased,
which requires skill and resources.
The great advantage is, of course,
that the image can be easily transferred
over the internet, the flip side of
the coin is that this requires
access to information technology,
which may not be available.
The cost of making a digital
image is virtually zero,
and the acquisition time
is a couple of seconds,
which allows to increase the number
of patients diagnosed per day.
Finally, in both cases, adequate
training is essential for
three categories of personnel.
The first is for medical doctors
or radiologists to able to interpret
the images,
the second is for radiographers to
be able to make good quality images
and in a safe way,
the third is for technicians to
be able to service and maintain
the system, as well as the related
infrastructure.
Now that we have seen the basics
of medical X-ray imaging,
let us discuss it's importance
in health care.
According to the World Heath
Organization, X-ray radiology
together with diagnostic Ultrasound,
cover 80% to 90% of the needs
for diagnostic imaging in general.
X-ray, in particular, is very much
used for diagnosing trauma.
As we have seen in a prior video,
road traffic accidents
are very frequent globally,
There are about 20 to 50 million
victims of road accidents every year
and 90% of them live in low and
middle income countries.
Another crucially important
application of X-ray imaging
is for the diagnosis of pulmonary
conditions.
Tuberculosis, for example, still
represents a huge problem worldwide.
According to the WHO, in 2015, over
ten million people fell ill with TB
and 1.8 million died
from the disease.
Over 95% of TB deaths occur in low
and middle income countries.
There are many other uses of
diagnostic X-rays such as:
orthopedic conditions,
foreign bodies or cancer.
This is really an essential
modality in medicine,
but how available is X-ray
on the global scale?
The World Health Organization
estimates that over two thirds
of the global population lack
access to safe, reliable
and competent radiology
services.
This is a shocking number and even
more so when we take into consideration
that this technology was invented
by Röntgen over 120 years ago.
This technology is a great example
for our course.
It really epitomizes all of the five
challenges which we encounter in the context
of low and middle income countries,
and which we have seen in a previous video.
The first challenge, as you remember,
is a lack of quality infrastructure,
X-ray machines can consume a lot
of electrical power,
typically between 30 to 50kW
In many hospitals we have seen,
the available power is barely enough
to cover just the power needs for the X-ray
system alone,
let alone other needs,
such as lighting.
The facilities where the X-ray
system is located often also lack
adequate protection against
harmful radiation.
Finally, the quality of the water
needed to develop the film
is often below standard, due to poor
quality water supply infrastructure.
The second challenge of the context
is the lack of financial resources.
The cost of some X-ray machines can
go from US$20K or US$30K for a film
screen system, and US$100K
to US$200
for a complete digital solution.
This is far too expensive for most
primarily health care structures.
In addition, since regular maintenance
is usually needed, maintenance contracts
over a ten year lifespan can
easily cost as much
as the initial purchase price.
Sadly, one has to mention that most
manufacturers won't assure
maintenance in remote places anyway.
For these reasons, X-ray systems
which are found in low
and middle income countries are often
donated second-hand obsolete devices.
In Cameroon, which is a lower income
country with a population of
roughly 20 million, less than 10
radiologists are trained every year.
There is also a permanent lack
of trained radiographers
and biomedical technicians.
Even when simple maintenance or
repairs are needed,
it is unlikely that anything can
be done locally due to this problem.
The lack of trained personnel is
our third challenge, as we have seen.
This is the control panel of an
X-ray system in an African hospital.
As we can see, it was not
designed to resist the harsh climate
found in these contexts.
Harsh environment
is our fourth challenge.
It takes a heavy toll on X-ray machines,
with little possibilities for repairs,
as we have seen.
Our last challenge
is poor governance.
In the case of X-ray technology,
we have heard of many cases
of corrupt local representatives
of X-ray manufacturers
or maintenance companies appointed
by the manufacturers.
These organizations sometimes
request huge bribes from hospitals,
in spite of existing and already
paid up maintenance contracts.
Also when X-ray systems are
purchased, this is mostly done
through tenders, due the high
amounts of money involved.
This is an area where corrupt
practices are very frequent.
Now that we know more about
the lack of access to radiology,
how can we approach such a problem
and develop a sustainable solution?
We will try to respond to that in
the remainder of this course.
Goodbye.