What are the reasons
that explain why there are not
enough x-ray machines available
in the district hospitals?
I can see multiple factors.
The first one being
the supplied equipment
was obsolete, too old,
they are often given
so they are old and poorly installed,
and barely work
or not at all.
The environmental elements
that compromises a longer life
of the donated equipment
in our context
is firstly the electric network
and its instability too.
The supply is not constant
there are often power cuts.
And as for the instability
the frequent variations
of electric tension.
I think that this is  on one of the main sources of
trouble.
Now secondly, the climate issues
that are not always taken into account
when the equipment is made:
the heat
that compromises the viability
of certain imaging detectors,
the dust getting in,
and also the humidity,
in certains departments.
For the heat
it is not just because the zone is tropical
globally, these are hot countries
but another problem is,
the lack of means
we can't always use an air conditioner,
and even when we manage to get one
you need money for the maintenance,
and good quality electric energy
for it to work.
So there are elements
that are related to the environment,
But there are also elements linked to humans
because these are machines
that are essentially fragile,
you need to be well trained
to use them,
then,
the structures
need to have sufficient means
for the maintenance,
particularly preventive maintenant.
Even if we have the means
for the preventive maintenance
we need properly trained
biomedical engineers
and enough of them
available.
So the factors are multiple.
We can dream of
having x-rays here,
the equipment needs to come first.
Meaning the equipment
that is adapted
to our conditions
and our environment
and that we find everywhere.
So the GlobalDiagnostiX project
from my point of view,
is a bit of a crazy dream,
the dream of some well intentioned people
that found out
that although the need is
in southern countries
the ressources
are mainly in northern countries.
Well intentioned people
who noted that in southern countries
we have a lot of diseases
illnesses,
that need x-ray equipment,
at least standard radiologie machines,
the accidents, the lung diseases,
certain types on emergencies,
that need the presence, the availability,
of x-rays
and yet this is not available
in most hospitals
on the outskirts,
especially in the district hospitals.
It's therefore the crazy dream
of people who hope to fix that,
to bring solutions.
The GlobalDiagnostiX project,
in a common initiative
of people in Switzerland and Cameroon
who are trying to make available
as quickly as possible,
standard radiology machine
but that it is digital
and able to resist
to all the strains
that the currently available machines go under
and with a global cost
including the maintenance
the amortization cost,
which is reasonable,
maybe even less than what is already available.
The GlobalDiagnostiX project
will offer a standard x ray machine
able to withstand the electric current,
working on battery power
for certain lengths of time
so staying on
even if there is a power cut,
a machine that is mechanically
solid,
designed to be airtight
to dust infiltration
with a detector designed
to resist against high temperatures,
with controls based
essentially relying on mechanical movements
and not electronic ones,
like the previous machines,
these electric controls
being a primary source of break downs.
An intuitive radiography equipment
because we are planning a work station
that guides the operator
given that there won't be one
in every district hospital
people trained to do
standard radiology
the machine could indicate
what steps to take
for someone
who hasn't been properly trained.
The machine will also contain
module to help
interpret the typical images,
to recognise
the good quality pictures.
And as for the marketing,
the GlobalDiagnostiX
associated
with a company
that will commercialise the machine that has already been created,
which will be offering
equipment that has already been sold
not one year
but a few years warranty
ideally around a 6 year.
Also
preventive maintenance is
included in the sale price
that comes also with
a training course
for the technician
but also for the local consultant
to use the equipment properly.
So not to drag on,
this project is based on concrete observations
of the difficulties we face
and is offering to answer point by point
the principal difficulties.
And what we forgot to say,
is that in its conception,
the local teams in Cameroon,
chosen as the pilot country,
are implicated at each stage
whether it be the in design of the machine
or for the interface for obtaining the images
whether it be the questions
linked to the norms of radiology
benefitting from the expertise
of the national radioprotection agency
or for the contextual elements
or anthropological aspects
its acceptability by the personnel in a tropical area, etc.
So at each stage
we are consulted
and every time when it is necessary
the parts of the machine come to Cameroon
to be tested
in their future place of use.
Globally the GlobalDiagnostiX project,
is trying to propose to southern countries
a swiss army knife for radiology
or, according to us,
an untameable lion (Camerooninan soccer team) of imagery
so that is the GlobalDiagnostiX project,
according to us.