Hello. These images were taken
from a project to develop
a diagnostic radiology system for
low income contexts.
Let us assume that you have a
project idea which involves
technology innovation to tackle
a development issue.
Your goal is to generate a positive
impact for people living in poverty.
How should you proceed to maximize
your chances of success?
What are the steps you need to
consider?
And the tools at your disposal?
What are the hurdles?
What are the good practices that
you can take advantage of?
In this video we will give you an
overview of the process.
It will lead us from a very early
stage, when all you have is a rough
idea, all the way up to deployment
and scaling up of your technology.
Before we look at the process itself
we would like to briefly discuss
the question of profit versus
impact.
First, we should remember that the
impact we want to make
must not only be positively affecting
a large number of people,
but it must also be sustainable.
The problem is that at the end of
the day someone will have to pay
for the technology.
Funds will be needed for
manufacturing, maintaining
and servicing the technology, as well as for
commissioning and training
of the users. This is why two things
are necessary.
One - a sustainable source of funds,
and two - a vehicle responsible for
implementing the technology
innovation.
This vehicle could be a company or
some other form which may or may not
involve profit generation. But it
must be sustainable.
Entrepreneurship can be a great
way to generate a positive and
sustainable improvement for the
poor.
In the traditional view, we have two
worlds, which are completely separate
from each other.
On the right there are the
traditional for-profit companies,
which only strive to maximize
shareholder value.
And on the left we have not-for
-profit organizations, such as
foundations and NGOs, which
depend on subsidies and are only
interested in impact. In this view,
the former are sustainable,
but do not necessarily bring a
positive impact. While the latter
are more likely to bring a positive
impact, but are not necessarily
sustainable. This is a very outdated
view. Indeed, one should rather see
things as a button slider. Since
there are many possibilities
in between those two extremes.
These intermediate models, which are
sometimes called social businesses,
strive to leverage market forces in
order to generate a sustainable
impact. We believe that this offers
great opportunities, but also
some difficulties. As an entrepreneur
using this kind of model, you may be
confronted with a difficult choice.
Do you prefer to maximize impact?
Or profit? You will have to decide.
Fundamentally, there's nothing
inherently bad about making profit
if we provide solutions to unmet
needs.
On the contrary, if you're able to
combine profit and impact,
this is a situation where you can
generate your own fuel for growth
and extend the reach of your impact.
Making profit is required anyway, if
you need initial or later stage
funding from investors. For this
course, we will consider that
the slider in this figure will not
be at either of the two extremes.
It's somewhere in between.
In conclusion, let us take into consideration
that achieving a sustainable and large
scale impact will involve developing
a profitable business model.
Let's move on and discuss the
process.
We will look at all the steps in
detail in later videos, but for now
let us keep a helicopter view and
discuss general principles.
Here you can see the three main
phases of the process,
with the impact we're
trying to achieve at the end.
The process starts with a choice of
a development challenge, which we
want to solve using a technology
innovation.
We then develop a concept which we
validate through some feasibility
prototyping and various tests.
Finally, we move to implementation,
which includes deploying our solution
scaling it up, so that it
sustainably reaches as many
beneficiaries as possible.
Looks simple, doesn't it?
As always things are a bit more
complicated than that.
And we will get there.
But prior to that, let me make
a few general remarks.
We need to remember that innovation
necessarily involves change.
For example, changing behaviors
or habits.
Bringing about change is hard and it
follows that innovation inherently
includes risk. Obviously, the risk
of failing is highest
at the beginning, when the only
thing we know is what kind of
development issue we want to
tackle.
At that stage we know very little
about how to generate this much
desired impact. As we move forward
in the project, we learn about the
context, the needs of the people
we are trying to help. The social,
political and cultural background.
And so on.
The more we know, the more
control we have on the risk of failure.
As a consequence, this is essentially
a learning process.
The best way to learn is to
cooperate  with people who know
the needs and the context.
Third, due to the high level of
unknowns at the start, one thing we
can be sure of is that the process
won't be linear or smooth.
The unfolding of the project will
most certainly involve many
iterations, trials and errors, and
sometimes a complete change of
strategy. This is why we need to be
agile and adjust quickly.
Let us now look at each phase
starting with the concept.
We have to start by identifying
the target beneficiaries.
Once we have done that, we need
to select a pilot country or region
or community.
It is important that our project
has both an ambitious and,
if possible, a global impact goal.
But also, that it is strongly
ingrained in local knowledge.
This is the only way we can learn
all we need to know for our project.
We need to identify local stake
holders and experts in the specific
field that we want to address. And
to involve them in the project.
For example, for diagnostic imaging
we selected Cameroon as the pilot
country. And we identified as a key
stakeholder, the head of the
diagnostic imaging division at the main
university hospital there.
In this phase we also need to
honestly and painstakingly take
stock of existing solutions or
alternatives.
We need to understand what works
and what does not work. And why
it does not work.
Finally, we need to define detailed
requirement specifications
for our technology innovation.
These specs need to be quantitative.
For example, the diagnostic imaging
system must allow to diagnose 40
patients per day and still work at
temperatures of 45 degrees C.
As we will see, all of this
information will allow us
to establish the long-term goal we
want to reach and also the pathway
to get there.
This is commonly referred to as
the theory of change.
And it is discussed in more detail
later in this course.
In the second phase we will
essentially want to develop solutions
and test them as much as possible
together without partners.
This really involves 1) developing
the technology and 2) developing a
sustainable business model.
In both cases we will have to go
through multiple trial and error
loops. It is crucial to test our
hypotheses in our pilot country.
And with the key stakeholders we
have identified.
It is great practice to build simple
and cheap models which can be put
to test and deliver quick answers.
We need to be agile and to quickly
adjust the strategy when needed.
Sometimes, as for medical devices
or pharmaceutical drugs,
real tests can't be performed on
patients, because at that stage
the technology has neither been approved
yet by the regulatory authorities, nor
has it demonstrated its compliance to applicable
norms and standards.
Nevertheless, many aspects can still
be tested. Without applying the
technology to actual patients.
Finally, we need to closely involve
key opinion leaders and stakeholders
into our project early on.
This will not only improve our
decision making, but also facilitate
uptake of the solution later in the
implementation phase.
However, we need to keep the
global objective in mind.
Will our solution also be adapted to
all the communities?
Because, what we want is as much of a global
impact as possible.
The two key deliverables in this
phase are: 1) a prototype of the
technology demonstrating that it
is feasible, 2) a complete business
model. Both deliverables are
closely related and they will have
been subjected to as many real life tests
as possible.
At that stage we have to decide
between two main strategies.
Either the technology will be
implemented by an existing company,
or we decide to create our own
venture.
For the rest of this course we will
consider the second option.
Yet the methodology applies equally
well if the implementation is made
through an existing company.
The last phase is when the rubber
hits the road.
At that stage we have demonstrated
feasibility of both our technology
and our business model. However,
it does not mean that there is no
more risk involved, of course. But
it will have been reduced as much
as possible. We can now go talk to
investors.
They'll come on board if they foresee
a sufficient financial return.
And if the related level of risk
is deemed acceptable.
The technology is then made into
an industrial product, which can be
replicated and sold. It needs to be
made compliant to safety standards
and regulatory constrains which can
be quite a lot of work.
The implementation of the business
model also requires resources,
such as personnel, office space
and material.
The first crucial success will come
when our initiative stops losing
money and reaches what is called
break-even.
After that the more we grow and
scale up, the more our investors
will be happy. And ideally the more
impact we will have.
When investors are involved, the
question of both maximizing
sustainable impact and profitability
will always remain an important
concern. Ideally, there needs to be
a direct link between the amounts
of our technology deployed and
the impact generated.
If this is the case, then the more
products we sell,
the more impact we have.
This is a somewhat idealized
situation and things can derail
very quickly. For example, when
our beneficial impact is outweighed
by environmental concerns, or when
our initiative is finally so
attractive in rich countries that
the initial intent to serve the poor
is lost. This is the reason why we
must closely monitor impact at
all times. We will discuss this in
more details later.
Since accurately characterizing
impact often represents an important
challenge. Finally, let's go back
and look at the whole process again.
In general, as we said in the beginning
this is not a linear or smooth
process. And that is also what is
exciting about it.
As we have said, this is about
reducing risk and about learning.
As a consequence, the best practice
to remember is to make many tests,
fail often, fail cheap and
fail early.
We must make many rough and
ready trials. Both for the technology
and the business model.
At all times, we must remain focused
on impact and have our impact
metrics defined in detail.
All of this requires strong
determination.
You must be convinced that there's
not only plan A and plan B, but all
of the 26 letters of the alphabet.
If that's not enough, be ready to
start with the Chinese alphabet
as well. As a conclusion to this
video, let me remind you of the
three key guiding principles of
this process.
1. This is a learning process. We
need to acquire knowledge to
mitigate risk.
2. It requires cooperation.
We need to involve local
stakeholders and beneficiaries.
3. We need to be determined
and agile.
We need to experiment a lot & adjust
without losing sight of the goal.
Goodbye.