Today, the vast majority of ventures
bringing in
technology knowledge-based
innovation products to the market
will develop a business plan
at the very beginning
of the venture activity
which is essentially a road map
that outlines the commercial goals
of the product, and details
how you plan to achieve these goals.
This includes the necessary
financial and human resources,
as well as a description
of key events, or milestones,
that need to be achieved
along the way.
Which also serve as indicators
of progress
towards the stated commercial goals.
It is also well-known that
a business plan is a living thing.
In other words, it keeps changing
and needs to be updated
several times along the way.
The business plan also enables
the entrepreneur to estimate
and provide a quantitative
value of the company.
Or what is termed,
Company Valuation.
Where the return on investment
is one of the key metrics,
for example, that is used
to estimate the potential valuations
and also in deciding which company
to invest in by investors.
In general,
any venture needs to be
commercially viable
to be sustainable over time.
As you may remember
this course aims to assist
those wishing to develop innovations
that can make a contribution
to sustainable development.
Therefore, commercial success alone
is not sufficient.
Positive social impact is also
equally important in that equation.
Now the business plan provides you
the blueprint
for the commercial objective.
Now how do you generate a blueprint
for assuring social impact?
That's the crux of this lecture.
Now the definition and measurement
of impact is by no means
a trivial matter.
However,
there are specific methodologies
or tools that have been developed
to address this.
And we will spend the rest
of this lecture outlining them.
In order to ensure
that your innovation venture
provides a positive social benefit,
it is necessary that you define
the long term goals or impact
you desire, at the very onset
of your activities.
If you are unclear on this,
take the time to carry a research
to understand what it is exactly
that you wish to achieve in society
with your innovation
in the long term.
Here, beware of the common trap
with new technologies.
That is a hammer looking for a nail.
In other words,
a new technology looking
for an application or social impact.
Make sure to confirm
as meticulously as you can
that there is a match between
your innovation and the impact
you wish for.
Once you have defined
your long-term goals
or desired impact,
you need to spell out in detail
the sequence of events to get there.
In other words,
much like the business plan,
you need to generate an impact
framework plan,
or impact value chain,
as your blueprint
to impact attainment.
One of the most widely used methods
to help you map out
your impact framework plan,
or impact value chain,
is one that is known as
the Theory of Change.
What is theory of change, exactly?
Theory of Change, or simply ToC,
is essentially a comprehensive
description and illustration
of how and why a desired change
is expected to happen
in a particular context.
You develop your theory of change
by first identifying
the desired long-term goals
or impact.
And then working backwards
to identify and define
all the necessary and sufficient
conditions or sequence of events
that are required
and must be in place
for the impact to occur.
This gives rise
to a set of sequential
interdependent outcomes
that are sometimes
termed collectively
as a "Pathway of Change".
In the next slide,
we illustrate the canvas tool
for describing
this process systematically.
Globally,
your impact framework,
or impact value chain canvas,
can be thought of as two parts:
The organization's planned work
or interventions
and the organization's intended
results and changes.
In order to construct the full
impact framework,
or impact value chain,
it actually requires 5 steps
or stages.
The first stage is inputs.
Which can be defined as
the resources that must be deployed
in order to enable
the implementation of tasks.
This could be human, financial
or other types of resources.
The second stage is to specify
a set of actions or tasks
that your enterprise or organization
needs to perform
in order to help realize
and support your impact objectives.
These are collectively known
as Activities.
The third stage is to specify
your expected outputs
which can be defined as the tangible
products and services
that result from the activities
undertaken.
And the fourth stage
is your expected outcomes,
which essentially refers
to the changes or effects
on individuals or the environment
that you expect to follow
from the delivery
of products and services.
Then we come to the impact,
which are the effects and/or changes
in society or the environment
that follow from the outcomes
that have been achieved.
Now in putting together
your impact framework,
there are various assumptions
you need to make at every stage
of the process.
The question that always arises is
whether these were
the right assumptions.
In other words,
did these assumptions provide
all the necessary and sufficient
conditions at every stage
to ensure successful progression
to the impact objective?
As we move down the framework
and produce outcomes,
it remains necessary
to check and explain
if and why they are necessary.
We also have another
very important step.
Which is to measure and monitor
the implementation and effectiveness
of our initiative.
By collecting data
on each segment of the chain,
the initiative can identify
what is or is not happening
and find out why.
This may require interrogating your
assumptions and modifying them
accordingly, if required.
Now in order to carry out
your measurement and monitoring
of your progress,
you need to establish
suitable indicators.
An indicator is basically a metric
that provides information
to monitor performance
and measure achievement.
It tracks information
about outputs and outcomes
and includes quantitative
and qualitative data.
Your indicators should be specific,
simple and practical,
and show changes over time.
Try and use established
standard indicators where possible.
The list and guidance on indicators
is provided in the references.
However, in general,
be aware that the ability
to collect good quality data
about social performance
of a project,
can be a major challenge.
This can be a complex
and costly process,
which has had the effect
of deterring and discouraging
many enterprises and organizations
from doing it well,
or doing it at all.
We will now try and illustrate
the impact framework concept,
which a rather simple example.
Let's go over these five components
and we will use a highly simplified
example to illustrate them.
The first thing to do
is to define the impact
you wish to have in a specified,
defined social group or community.
Now in our example,
we have a problem
of high proportions
of overweight teenagers
in a certain village.
Overweight levels
have been determined
from the Body Mass Index,
or BMI,
BMI is obtained from the height
and mass of a person
as a ratio of mass in kilograms over
the square of your height in meters.
So our long-term objective,
or social impact,
is to reduce teenage obesity
in this village.
So our theory of change statement
becomes:
If teenagers receive a football
and football lessons,
offered by football icons,
for example,
then they would start
playing football,
and if the village teenagers
play football regularly
then they will lose weight,
and teenage obesity will be reduced,
which is the desired impact.
Now let's try our theory of change
statement into an impact framework,
which is comprised of 5 stages.
After defining the problem well,
the first stage
of the impact framework is inputs.
Which can be defined
as the resources
that are deployed in order to enable
the implementation of tasks.
In our simple example,
we define the resources needed
as the availability of footballs,
fields for playing,
and financial resources
to pay for these.
The next thing we need to specify
is activities.
Which can be defined as the actions
and/or tasks that must be performed
in support of specific
impact objectives.
In our example,
this could be actions undertaken
to produce sufficient footballs,
one football for every child,
and to attract teenagers to come,
such as by carrying out
a publicity campaign
that, for example,
may include the participation
of famous football icons
in the region, who pledge
to come and give football lessons.
After that,
we must describe the outputs,
which can be defined
as the tangible immediate practices,
products and services that result
from the activities undertaken.
In our example, this could be,one,
footballs autographed
by the football icons,
which are available for distribution
to every teenager
as part of our "one child,
one football" campaign.
And, two, the number of teenagers
registered for lessons and teams
following the publicity campaign.
Then we define the outcomes,
which essentially refers
to the changes
or effects on individuals
or the environment
that follow from the delivery
of products and services.
In our example,
the key outcome would be the change
in the amount of time the teenagers
now spend playing football, instead
of being couch potatoes at home.
We then need to establish
our impact drivers.
That is, what are we going to do
in order to influence, or to ensure,
that this outcome
is indeed achieved?
For example,
we might provide a pickup service
that comes to pick up
each of the registered kids
at certain times during the week.
Then we come to the impact,
which are the effects or changes
in society or the environment
that follow from the outcomes
that have been achieved.
In our case,
the impact desired
would be the reduction
in teenage obesity
and overweight levels
as well as the continued
enjoyment of playing football.
So overall,
the theory of change process
enables better planning,
and better evaluation,
and even allows the possibility
to also measure progress
towards the achievement
of longer term goals
that go beyond the identification
of program outputs.
In the next lecture,
we will try and illustrate
this methodology
with a concrete example
involving the GDX,
Digital X-ray Imaging system.
Goodbye.