This lecture is a continuation
of the previous lecture that
introduced the Impact
Framework Canvas before.
Here we will continue
with our example
of the digital X-ray imaging system
that we introduced recently.
To facilitate continuity
we stick with our logos
from the previous examples
to represent the various stages.
Again, as we did in our
simplified example,
before we begin, we start
by defining the problem at hand.
In this case the problem we have
is that today there are about
15 million road traffic accident
victims per year
of which 90% live in low
and middle income countries.
While pulmonary diseases account
for 14% of all deaths world wide.
X-ray imaging radiology
is the gold standard for
the diagnosis and care of patients
with pulmonary diseases
and for trauma victims
from road accidents.
However two thirds of humanity
still have no access to radiology
and this lack is mainly in low
and middle income countries.
In response to this critical
social health problem
we have coined a long term
objective or desired social impact,
which is to reduce illness
and deaths from trauma related
and pulmonary morbidities
in low and middle income countries.
And how will we do this?
By increasing access
to radiology for the diagnosis
of these indications
through the availability
and use of a cost-effective
robust digital X-ray imaging system,
that is the GDX machine
described before.
But also, along with training
and maintenance or repair services
that are critical for the continued
function of the machine.
We then need to work backwards
in order to identify and define
all the necessary and sufficient
conditions or sequence of outcomes
that are required and must be
in place for the impact to occur.
As we saw before the whole
impact framework consists
of five stages.
The first stage is inputs,
which refers to the resources
that need to be deployed in order to
enable the implementation of tasks.
In our case, we identified
the following vital inputs.
One, context information.
As discussed in an earlier lecture
this essentially refers
to the information
about the context of the low
and middle income regions
which is related to economics,
infrastructure, personnel
and environmental
and physical factors
as well as governance issues.
Expertise, notably
Engineering and Medical expertise
in order to carry out the required
R&D to produce the prototype.
Capital, in order to fund
the required operations.
The next thing
to specify is Activities,
which we can define
as the actions and/or tasks
that must be performed in support
of specific impact objectives.
In this case the key activities
that we identified were
to develop an affordable and robust
medical X-ray imaging system,
the GDX system
and also to develop
a training module
to enhance proper use
and machine longevity
as well as develop a maintenance
& repair plan and infrastructure
to ensure annual maintenance
and prompt repair when needed,
while also developing
a marketing plan to promote
the GDX machine
to buyer stakeholders
and enhance it's uptake.
After that we must describe
the outputs which are essentially
the tangible products and services
that result from the activities
undertaken.
In our case this would be
a fully certified GDX X-ray system
that is available in low
and middle income regions
as well as tutorials
and other support modules
that would be on the machine
or online along with
the certificate bearing
training program
that is accredited by
the relevant national authorities
whenever possible.
Also a deployment plan,
which includes marketing
and other plans in order
to create awareness
and promote sales
and uptake of the machine.
Then we come to the outcomes,
which essentially refers
to the changes or effects
on individuals that follow
from the delivery
of products and services.
Here our expected outcomes include
an increase in
the number of hospitals,
especially rural hospitals,
who have the GDX system
that the personnel operating
the GDX system have
appropriate skills
to operate it.
An increase in the number
of diagnosed patients
showing up with morbidities
linked to orthopedic trauma
in the hospitals that have
the GDX imaging system.
Increased access overall
to radiology and diagnosis
of trauma related
and pulmonary morbidities
in low and middle
income countries.
In this case we also define
an intermediate outcome
which is basically
the aggregate result
from the outcomes
just before your impact.
In this case you have defined
it as the sustainable
and effective use and maintenance
of diagnostic machines
by population
which is expected to be achieved
if outcomes listed before do occur.
So we have now established our set
of sequential
inter-dependent outcomes
that collectively comprise
our theory of change.
Now the next step is to identify
what our basic assumptions are.
Bearing in mind that documenting
and justifying assumptions
is a continuous
and often iterative process.
As we progress through our
framework and produce our outcomes
it remains necessary
to check and explain
if and why they are necessary.
And here we do not list all
the possible assumptions
but only the key ones.
Our first assumption is that
if the GDX machine is available
in the market, then our
potential buyers
such as governments or NGOs
will actually buy it.
And another related assumption
to this is that the potential buyers
will actually have availability
and/or access to funds
to acquire machines.
We have also made an assumption
that the contextual situation
will remain largely as it is
and that there will be
no radical contextual changes,
such as political, social,
environmental, or economic changes
in the countries and regions
we're interested in.
If any of these assumptions
turn out not to be correct
our progress to impact
might be severely hampered
so it is very important
to continuously verify
your assumptions and be prepared
to adjust them
accordingly, if necessary.
The next step is what we called
step four in
the introduction lecture,
and it is about identifying
the interventions that
our initiative will perform
to create our desired changes
that is, outcomes and impact.
Earlier on we listed our
intermediate outcomes to
include sustainable
and effective use
as well as maintenance of
the GDX machines by the hospitals.
So what will be
the key impact driver here?
Of course the availability
of qualified personnel
to operate the machines
is very essential to ensure
sustainable and effective use.
Certainly we can intervene
here by making sure that
there is continued training
of the personnel involved
with the X-ray machines,
such as technicians and doctors.
This can also be a mechanism
to address the problem
of high personnel turnover that
can be prevalent in these regions.
As we said in
the previous lecture
you need to establish
how you will measure
and monitor the implementation
and effectiveness
of your initiative.
By collecting data on
the results as you go along
you can identify what is
or is not working
and find out why.
This is accomplished
by using indicators,
which you will monitor
or measure at the various points
when they occur.
In the case of our GDX machine
one of the initial and most
important indicators will be
the number of GDX machines
produced every year.
Because, unless a sufficient
number is produced every year
the rest of the planned
activities cannot occur effectively.
And subsequently
even if the condition
of adequate supply is true,
if there are not enough hospitals
actually acquiring the machine
then we have a problem towards
our impact and objective.
Thus the number of hospitals
acquiring the GDX machines
produced every year
as well as the number of X-ray staff
completing training per year
are both very important indicators
to monitor and measure.
Of course,
if all these ideas are true
then the next key question
is the number and increase
in the number of patients
that are actually being diagnosed
with the GDX machines per year.
So, finally our GDX impact framework
looks like this after
we add the indicators as well.
Before we conclude the section
on impact definition
I also want to briefly introduce
another emerging
but potentially important
related concept
namely the Social Return
on Investment.
In all likelihood most of you
will need to raise funds
to help execute your projects
and fund raising can be done
from foundations as grants
or from investors or other
financial sources as equity or debt.
In order to help your project
to become more attractive
to the potential funder
or investor,
it may be helpful if you also
attach some kind of monetary value
to the impact you aim for.
To help you do this, a widely
used method
is to calculate what is termed
the Social Return on Investment
or SROI.
Which, if you like, could be
conceptually equivalent
to a Return on Investment
in a traditional business plan.
Social Return on Investment is
an essentially a method
for measuring non-financial value
relative to the resources invested,
that is, value such as environmental
and social factors
that would not be reflected in
conventional financial accounts.
The SROI is usually presented
as a ratio, the SROI ratio,
which is simply the numerical total
value of benefits over the value
of inputs or investments.
Impact investors and funders
may use this metric to prioritize
projects or ventures to fund.
For you, you can also use it
to prioritize which innovations
or applications
to develop or focus on
if you are confronted with
various options, for example.
We will not have the time
to discuss an example
in this lecture, unfortunately,
but we have provided
a comprehensive list of references
that we highly recommend
you consult for further details.
So to summarize, SROI
is generally used as a tool
to provide
a numerical estimate
of the social value
of the project.
Similarly to the computation
of the expected return
from a project in finance.
Expected return is used to gauge
the potential value
of the given project prior to it's
selection or implementation
and it can help select
or prioritize projects.
Similarly, social return
on investment metric
is used at the beginning
of the whole process
but not generally
to measure outcomes at the end.
So, to conclude, we hope
that the two lectures
have given you a fundamental insight
on how to use the impact canvas tool
to develop your impact
framework for your project.
We will revisit the use of this tool
and see how it can be integrated
with another powerful canvas tool,
the business model canvas.
in order to give rise to,
what we term
the sustainable business
model business canvas tool.
Goodbye.