Welcome to Simi's lectures on Transmission Electron Microscopy for material science.
Continuing on the theme of the basics of electron diffraction,
in this lecture I will introduce the reciprocal lattice,
which together with the ebounce sphere,
will form our framework for understanding,
and interpreting electron diffraction in the lectures to come.
To consider the reciprocal lattice,
I'm going to begin by considering the geometry of the diffraction vector,
that was introduced in last time.
From there, I'm going to go on and look at reciprocal lattice vectors,
and then the basis vectors of the reciprocal lattice a*, b*, and c*.
These form the reciprocal lattice units cell,
and have certain properties which will be discussed briefly.
Then finally, going from there,
to looking at an illustrated schematic of a reciprocal lattice,
which will then take further in the next lecture on the ebounce sphere.
As a way towards understanding the reciprocal lattice,
I'm first going to look at the way vector diagram for proving bragg diffraction,
that I discussed in the last lecture.
If you remember, in this diagram we have an incident way vector_k_i,
where the modulus of a general way vector_k equals 1/λ.
As we saw last time,
this incident way vector_k is scattered at an angle theta,
by the bragg difrracting plane.
Such that in the diffraction pattern,
we would see two spots;
one for the direct beam,
corresponding to the incident way vector_k_i,
and another spot for the diffracted beam,
corresponding to the diffraction way vector_k_d.
And then joining these two,
I introduce the diffraction vector_g,
where I use g as a shorthand for ghkl.
Now if we look at this diffraction vector_g,
we can notice two things;
The first thing, we just consider that bragg diffracting plane.
It is evident that the direction of the diffraction vector_g,
is perpendicular to the bragg diffracting plane.
By the way, so I have a modulus of g is one divided by the plane spacing.
Well in this case, g corresponds to a particular diffraction vector.
I'm not going to introduce a general vector,
called the reciprocal lattice vector,
which will correspond to any possible diffraction vector.
So, each plane hkl will have his own reciprocal lattice vector.
Evidently, this reciprocal lattice vector
must have the same properties as g.
In other words,
the reciprocal lattice vector will be perpendicular to
its plane hkl,
and will have a length,
which is inversely proportional or the reciprocal of the plane spacing.
To understand reciprocal lattice vectors and where to draw in
some reciprocal lattice vectors for hypothetical planes in real space,
such as we have in this diagram here,
where we have plane d₁ in red and plane d₂ in blue with an origin here.
We're going to define a reciprocal lattice vector for a plane d as d*.
Now, first considering the plane d₁,
we know that the reciprocal lattice vector will be perpendicular to the plane d₁
and since starting at the origin will look like this.
Now, instead considering the reciprocal lattice vector for the plane d₂, firstly,
this is going to be perpendicular to that plane d₂,
so in a different direction to d₁*,
but also we can see that the plane spacing for d₂
is smaller than the plane spacing for d₁.
So for d₂* we will obtain a longer reciprocal lattice vector like this.
Just for clarity, I will now redraw these two reciprocal lattice vectors over here,
so we have the d₂*,
perpendicular to the plane d₂ and d₁* perpendicular to the plane d₁.
These are just the reciprocal lattice vectors for two planes,
where we can continue on considering other planes.
So we shouldn't do that here.
Here I have again marked on the planes d₁ and
d₂ and their reciprocal lattice vectors d₁* and d₂*,
but now going to add another plane d₃.
Now if the plane d₁ has an hkl of (h₁, k₁, l₁),
and the plane d₂ has a hk and l of (h₂, k₂, l₂),
the fact that the plane d₃ intersects these two planes,
one plane is facing from the origin,
means that d₃ will have an hkl
of (h₁+h₂ k₁+k₂ l₁+l₂).
I'm now going to mark in the reciprocal lattice vector for this plane d₃.
So once again, of course this reciprocal vector will be perpendicular to
the plane d₃ and have a length which is inversely proportion to this planes facing.
Its planes facing is even smaller than that of d₁ or d₂,
so it's reciprocal lattice vector is even longer.
Now, this vector can be marginal on this cleaner diagram over here and there.
Once we done that we can notice something,
that the reciprocal lattice vector d₃* equals reciprocal lattice vector
d₁* plus the reciprocal lattice vector d₂*.
Therefore, for this relationship of the planes miller indices, we have
a vectorial addition that d₃* equals d₁* plus d₂*.
Now we have looked at a general vector for a lattice plane hkl,
we're going to look at the basis vectors that form the reciprocal lattice unit cell.
While the real space lattice has units cells basis vectors: a, b,
and c.
In the reciprocal lattice we will also have a unit cell,
and this will be defined by its own basis vectors, a*,
b*, and c* to find as follows; that a*=d*₁₀₀.
Clearly, a* will therefore be perpendicular to the 100 plane.
It will also have a length of one divided by the plane spacing of the 100 plane.
Similarly, b*=d*₀₁₀, and will have
a modulus equal to 1/d₀₁₀ plane spacing.
And we have c*=d*₀₀₁, where again,
the length of c*=1 divided by spacing 001 plane.
These reciprocal lattice basis vectors can then be used
to define the reciprocal lattice vector for a general plane with miller indices hkl.
To understand why, we can consider the following; first of all,
we will consider our plane with a miller indices hkl equal to 2_0_0.
Now, this 2_0_0 plane is going to be parallel to the 1_0_0 plane.
However, if we instead think about plane spacings,
we know that the 2_0_0 plane will have
a plane spacing which is half that of the 1_0_0 plane.
So, d₂₀₀= d₁₀₀/2.
Now considering reciprocal lattice vectors,
since the planes are parallel,
the reciprocal lattice vector for the two zero zero plane will be parallel to that of
the one zero zero plane but it will have two times the length.
So we will have a reciprocal lattice vector, d star two zero
zero equal to two times d star one zero zero.
Now as we saw previously,
d star one zero zero is defined as the reciprocal lattice basis vector a star.
So, d star two zero zero,
simply equals two times a star.
Generalizing this finding a bit further,
we go to a planes with miller indices of h zero zero,
or alternatively zero k zero.
Starting with the h zero zero plane,
taking this derivation a bit further,
it can be seen that it has
a reciprocal lattice vector d star h zero zero equal to h times a star,
the first or the reciprocal lattice basis vectors.
Going on now to the zero k zero plane, similarly,
that has a reciprocal lattice vector d star zero k zero equal to k times b star,
the second of the reciprocal lattice basis vectors.
Finally, we can also consider the zero zero l plane.
And that in turn, will have a reciprocal lattice vector d star zero zero
l equal to l times c star.
Now taking these findings,
together with the vectorial addition for
the reciprocal lattice vectors that we saw earlier,
for a general plane with miller indices hkl,
we obtain a reciprocal lattice vector d star hkl equals to
d star h zero zero plus d star zero
k zero plus d star zero zero l so equal to h
times a star plus k times b star plus l times c star.
Thereby relating this plane's reciprocal lattice vector to
the minute indices hkl and the reciprocal lattice basis factors a star b star and c star.
On this slide we will now look in a bit more detail
at these properties of the reciprocal lattice basis vectors.
Already, we have established that d star hkl equals ha star plus kb star plus lc star.
We also know that a star is the normal to the plane,
which contains the real lattice axes b and c. And we
will have time to scalar product a star dot b equals zero and a star at c equal zero.
Equally b star a equals zero b dot c equals zero
and c star dot a equals zero and c star dot b equals zero.
It can also be easily obtained the a dot a star equals 1. b dot b star equals 1.
And c dot c star equals 1.
Finally, because a star is perpendicular to b and c,
it's clear that a star is going to be parallel to
b cross c. And with a bit more derivation,
it can be shown that a star equals b cross c divided by V_C,
where V_C is the volume of the unit cell.
And similarly, for b star and c star.
The previous slides have introduced the logic
behind the reciprocal lattice vector and discussed
the derivation of the reciprocal lattice basis vectors a star, b star, and c star.
However, what's more important in the lectures to come is to understand
the reciprocal lattice as something visualized by a series of reciprocal lattice nodes,
where each node represents the reciprocal lattice vector for
a plane hkl in what we will call reciprocal space.
To illustrate this idea,
I'm going to show a section of a reciprocal lattice for BCC metal.
And then later on, we have the origin 000.
I'm now going to say that the basis vector b star lies along here. And has this length.
And the basis vector c start is here.
Because it's cubic, the lengths of b start and
c star are identical to each other and they have a 90 degree angle between them.
Now considering the systematic absences for BCC,
if we go along the vector b star,
then the first diffraction plane we can have with a normal parallel to
this vector will be zero to zero plane.
And we know that the 020 plane will have a diffraction vector,
which will be two times the length of b star,
since b star corresponds to d star 010.
Therefore, we represent the reciprocal lattice vector for that 020 plane as a node here.
Note that rather than drawing a vector to that node,
we just represented it as a spot,
which corresponds to a possible diffraction event.
If that is the node for the 020 plane on this axis,
parallel to c star,
we will have the 002 node here.
Between them, we will have another node for the 011 plane.
We can carry on identifying these different nodes.
By symmetry here we will have the zero zero bar two and here the zero bar two zero.
Here, the zero one bar one and so on.
Now for simplicity, this is
just a two dimensional section of what would be a three dimensional lattice.
And we'll see next time how by interacting
this three dimensional lattice with the Ewald sphere,
we can identify which planes
are going to refract under certain conditions or for instance,
sample orientation with respect to the electron beam.
To summarize, I have introduced the concept of
the reciprocal lattice vector for a plane hkl.
And further seen how this reciprocal lattice vector d star hkl can be described in terms
of the reciprocal lattice units own basis vectors a star, b star, and c star.
Further to that, by assigning the reciprocal lattice vector for each plane a node,
we can consider schematically or
a three dimensional reciprocal lattice made up of a framework of nodes,
where each of these nodes represents a possible diffracting plane.
Finally, as a last note I'll point out that
the reciprocal lattice is in fact the Fourier transform of the real lattice.
And this is something that will become important for
understanding the nature of electron diffraction in a few lectures time.