Welcome to lectures on transmission
electron microscopy and
the lecture on the Ewald sphere.
In the last lecture, I introduced
the concept of the reciprocal lattice,
a lattice of nodes in reciprocal
space where each node corresponds
to a possible diffraction vector from
a plane with [INAUDIBLE] indices HKL.
This reciprocal lattice forms
the first half of our framework for
understanding and
interpreting electron diffraction.
In this lecture, I'm going to introduce
the second half of the framework, namely,
the eval sphere.
To understand the Ewald sphere,
we're going to consider that
electron diffraction corresponds
to elastic scattering.
The incident electron beam is
effected by the of the sample.
And during this diffraction event,
there is no energy loss.
Therefore, at the scattering event,
the energy of the electron beam and
hence its wave length,
both remain constant.
However, as we have already seen, there
is a momentum change during the fraction.
We can describe this on
a wave vector diagram.
So here, I have a wave vector for
the incident electron beam kI.
Whereas, we have previously seen
the length of kI is modulus
= 1 over lambda,
the wave length of the electron beam.
I'm going to say that here,
I have some diffraction event.
Now, the scattering from this event could
occur in one of many different directions.
So, for instance, we could have
a diffracted wave vector here.
Equally, we could have
diffraction in this direction, or
this direction, or
one of many different possible directions.
Now, while the angular scattering
may change, of course,
the length of these diffracted
beam wave edges cannot change.
They all have the same length as that of
the incident electron beam, 1 over lambda.
So looking just at this plane of
scattering, we can see that all
these different possible scattering
wave vectors will inscribe a circle.
That's just looking at one plane.
However, we could also have
diffraction out of plane.
And if you consider the out of
plane scattering wave vectors,
we can see that together,
they will inscribe a sphere.
And the sphere of possible diffracted beam
wave vectors is called the Ewald sphere.
Since the radius of the Ewald sphere
has a length of 1 over lambda,
we can see that the Ewald sphere
has reciprocal dimensions.
And we're now going to interact this
sphere with the reciprocal lattice.
To look at this interaction,
on this slide,
I have drawn both the Ewald sphere and
a reciprocal lattice.
Looking first at the Edward sphere,
again, here, we have the wave
vector for the incidence electron beam kI.
If there is no scattering, then the wave
vector carries straight on, here.
We know that in the back
focal order fraction plane,
that the incident electron beam is a
direct beam in the refraction pattern 000.
000 also forms the origin
of this reciprocal lattice.
So I have also placed this origin
at the end of the wave vector for
incident electron beam.
Now, if we look at the interaction of the
Ewald sphere with the reciprocal lattice,
we can see that here,
there is a node in the reciprocal lattice
that is intersected exactly by
the surface of this Ewald sphere.
Now, for this node, we can draw in a wave
vector for the diffracted beam, kD.
And since I am saying that
this is the wave vector for
the diffracted beam, I can also draw
in here the diffracted vector g for
this particular reciprocal lattice node.
Now, we're going to look at
the geometry of this scattering for
that particular reciprocal lattice node.
First of all, we're going to
look at the angle of scattering.
And I'll say that the semi-angle
of scattering is theta.
From this diagram and by trigonometry,
it's clear that the modulus of g,
the diffraction beta,
divided by 2 = modulus
of kD times sine theta.
Now we know that g,
the diffraction beta equals D star hkl.
Therefore, the modulus of g equals
the modulus of D star equals 1 over D.
So, you can see that this becomes
1 over 2 dhkl = the length of kD =
1 over lambda times sine theta.
And this expression should
look very familiar to you,
because if we rearrange it,
we obtain lambda = 2dhkl sine theta.
In other words, we have obtained
the Bragg equation by theta = theta B,
the Bragg angle.
Thus, we see that when the Ewald
sphere intersects exactly through
a reciprocal lattice node,
the plane corresponding to that reciprocal
lattice node is at the exact Bragg
condition, and so will diffract strongly.
Cleaning up that diagram, we can
represent this scattering as follows.
So we have the incident wave vector kI.
Here, I have drawn in some Bragg planes
at the angle theta b relative to kI,
scattering at the Bragg angle,
leading to diffraction for
a plane corresponding to that
reciprocal lattice node.
In this representation,
I have had to make an exaggeration
to make the representation compact.
Specifically, We know
that the electron wave
length lambda is much smaller than
in the typical plane spacing dhkl.
Because of that,
the length of this wave vector k,
Is going to be much
greater than the typical
reciprocal lattice spacing, d star hkl.
So the radius of this sphere for
a realistic representation must be much,
much greater.
Moving on with that, I make that realistic
representation of the Ewald sphere and
the reciprocal lattice
in this diagram here.
Here, we have the incident wave vector kI,
the diffracted beam wave vector kD,
and I have drawn them assuming
that we have 200 keV electrons.
With 200 keV electrons, the wavelength
lambda is approximately = 2.5 pm.
To complete the illustration,
I have taken a reciprocal lattice for
body-centered cubic phase of iron.
This particular node here is
once again at the Bragg angle,
and this node is for the 020 plane.
And for BCC iron,
d020 is approximately = 0.14 nm.
The net result is that the length of k,
the wave vector,
is approximately 50 times greater than
the reciprocal lattice facing d star.
When we draw that in with
this very long radius,
we can see that the surface of
the Ewald sphere is almost flat.
And while this reciprocal lattice is still
inclined relative to the incident electron
beam, the angle of that
inclination is very, very small.
As an exercise, you can calculate
that angle of inclination.
And the Bragg angle of theta b and
the scattering angle 2 theta b, for
this case of 200 keV electrons and
BCC Iron when exciting this
020 reciprocal lattice note.
To summarize,
I have introduced the Ewald sphere,
a sphere in reciprocal space, so
the radius of k = 1 over lambda.
And we have seen that when we interact
this sphere with the reciprocal lattice,
and when servers of that sphere
intersect exactly through the middle
of a reciprocal lattice node,
the plane corresponding to that node
is at the exact Bragg condition,
and so will diffract strongly.
So far, we have only looked at this in
the case of two beam electron diffraction.
Where only one of the reciprocal lattice
nodes is intersected by the Ewald sphere,
and hence, we only have strong
refraction on one plane.
Giving a diffraction pattern such as this,
where, in this case,
the 200 plane is excited strongly
giving an intense diffraction spot.
In this case,
that plane is inclined at an angle,
theta B,
relative to the instant electron beam.
However, in electron diffraction,
we can have another scenario.
Where instead of the instant electron beam
being in inclined relative to a particular
crystal plane, it is in fact parallel to
many different crystal planes at the same
time with the e beam aligned on a low
end axis of the crystalline sample.
And in this case, we obtained strong
diffraction on many different planes,
giving a diffraction pattern
with many bright spots, so
called multibeam electron diffraction.
And that's what we will look
at in the next lecture.