Hi. Welcome to POCS.
My name is Ed Bugnion.
Now this week in POCS,
we'll be studying layering.
The layering in computer systems
is a deceptively simple concept.
And that's because we all
have an intuition as to what a layer is.
We all learn in our classes
the difference between
applications and operating systems,
or how file systems are layered
on top of disks.
Now we're actually going to revisit
all these concepts in the various modules.
But more importantly, we're going to
look at the principle behind layering.
Because there are actually a fair number
of nuances and subtleties
behind this deceptively simple concept.
So the lecture this week is broken up into
four distinct modules.
First, I'm going to go over
the concepts themselves in the abstract
We're going to learn
about layers, stacks, buses.
Then we'll go in depth
into two important stacks
that each consist of multiple layers:
the compute stack
and the information stack.
Then we'll talk about another way
in which you can layer a system together.
Which is by having clients talk to servers
and form a relationship
in the client/server model.
And then we'll wrap up this module
with a session on the various layers
of the networking stack.
So let's get started.
Well, first, layering builds on the notion
of modularity abstraction in naming.
We've covered modularity and abstraction
in the previous lecture,
and you'll actually learn about naming
and going depth in naming
in a subsequent lecture.
But here we're just using these concepts
to formalize the notion of a layer.
So a layer is a piece
of a computer system.
Could be a hardware component,
could be a software component,
but it generally
has the following characteristics:
first, it exports
a well-defined abstraction.
By well-defined we mean something
that is defined in one particular domain.
For example, a file system, a database,
or a disk are examples
of such an abstraction.
But a link list is not a layer.
It's just a module or library,
it's a piece of code.
It serves a function,
but it is not a layer
in the context of computer systems.
The second is, a layer typically
relies on a single lower layer.
Now there are exceptions to that rule,
but, in general,
layers are organized as a stack
with each layer relying on
a single lower layer.
For example the file system layer
is built on top of the block layer.
Now the block layer itself can have
multiple distinct implementations.
And there's a runtime binding
between a file system
and the underlying block layer.
But for every instance of a stack,
there is a hierarchy
with the file system being layered
on top of one instance of the block layer.
And the third defining
characteristic of a layer
is that it generally manages a distinct
and well-defined namespace.
As I mentioned, we'll be spending
an entire week on naming,
so I won't dwell on this here.
But just think of it
as the access mechanism to the objects
that are exposed by the abstractions.
So a classic example,
the namespace of the file system layer is,
as you would expect,
the set of directories and file names.
The name space
of the virtual address space
consists of 64-bit values that
can be dereferenced by the processor.
And so on, and so on.
So our first example
comes from the compute stack.
Take, for example, a JVM emulator.
It provides a distinct layer
implemented in software.
And that layer allows Java applications
to run on the machine.
Now the JVM itself
runs directly on the hardware ISA.
And in this example the hardware ISA
is an X86 CPU.
Of course the X86 CPU is a distinct layer.
This one is implemented entirely
in hardware.
It's a piece of silicon
with a well-defined interface,
the instruction set architecture
of the X86 processor.
That CPU manages the namespace.
Which is the architectural state
of the machine.
The registers, the memory,
and the interrupt subsystem.
And at the same time, the X86 processor
hides all the implementation details
of the processor from the layers
running on top of it.
For example, an X86 CPU
has an out-of-order execution engine,
it has a cache hierarchy,
but all of that is abstracted from
the layers that are running on top of it.
So you have a hardware layer,
and you have a software layer.
And they're layered on top of each other.
When we study system software,
the processor instruction set architecture
is typically the lowest layer
that we study.
However, when we study
computer architecture,
the processor is further broken down
into architectural components
that play a direct role
in the performance of the software.
And below them, into micro-architectural
implementation elements.
Now, onto our second example.
And actually file systems
are the canonical example
often used to discuss layering.
And that's because
the file system abstraction itself,
as well as the implementation
of file systems on disks,
are two good examples of layered systems.
Now a file system also meets
the general criteria of a layer.
There's a well-defined API,
there are well-defined abstractions,
things like files.
There's a well-defined namespace
with files and directories.
And we take
all these abstractions for granted.
But keep in mind that systems had to
evolve to the point where we are today.
Mainframe systems, for example,
had records and exposed blocks directly.
In slightly more recent time,
digital VMS operating systems
had a built-in versioning system
that exposed directly
the different versions of a file
into the namespace of the file system.
Turns out that that feature
proved not to be sufficiently useful
so it doesn't exist anymore today
in current operating systems.
So although we take layers for granted,
they often take a while to gel
and to evolve into the state
where they are today.
And our one key point here is that
we're talking about the file system layer,
not about any particular
specific file system.
And specifically not on any particular
layout of the file system on disk.
So, for example, if all the most files
in the namespace are stored on disk,
that's not always the case.
And that's because the file system layer
is not built directly
on some storage abstraction,
but rather on some intermediate layer,
which is called VFS in Unix,
which provides extensively
by connecting drivers into the namespace.
We'll actually revisit this
in the next section.
So let's expand actually on the difference
between file system layer
and individual file systems.
As I mentioned, the POSIX API
has a single namespace,
but the use of mount points
allows multiple file system drivers
to coexist.
And each materialize
a portion of the namespace.
Now, internally within the kernel,
these drivers register themselves
into the VFS link.
And that's a different layer
that is internal to the OS,
and the way they register
into the VFS layer is via callbacks.
If you actually recall George's lecture
on modularity and abstraction,
George showed that the source code
of the debugfs file system driver
it's kind of a coincidence,
but is shows precisely how
the debugfs file system driver,
connects into the VFS layer.
So each file system driver
is a layer itself,
and each one of them
relies on a lower layer.
And now the example that you see on screen
is a dump of the mount table
of a completely vanilla Linux system.
What we see is that the ext3 driver
relies on a block layer as its lower layer
but we also see that there
are other file systems
such as tmpfs that implement
a shared memory abstraction
that does not rely on an underlying
actual block device.
We also see that /proc and /sys
are two file systems
that expose the internal structure
of Linux as a file system to applications.
But the key point here is not
in the details of tmpfs, proc, or sysfs,
it's that all these things
are file systems.
And they all respond
to the file system operation,
the same file system operations.
And they all can be stacked together
as part of a file system stack.
Now in the previous example,
we showed how a virtual layer,
similar to an abstract class
in object-oriented programming,
enables extensibility in systems.
Now here we're introducing
another technique,
which uses layering to reduce modularity.
Now the idea here is to avoid
having point-to-point
connections between a collection
of unrelated modules.
As this approach is not scale,
it makes it very difficult to organize
and reason about the various layers.
And in step systems,
architects have developed the concept
of a bus layer.
Which allows seemingly unrelated modules
to communicate with each other indirectly
by going through a bus.
So buses can actually be implemented
either in software or hardware.
And I'm going to start
with a software example
and my software example is XMPP.
Which is better known
as the Jabber protocol.
And XMPP allows
a scalable number of entities
to exchange messages with each other
and to communicate their presence
within the bus.
And by doing that, you eliminate
the need to have any need
for a direct connection between peers.
And yet you create the illusion of having
point-to-point communication.
And of course, XMPP is used to build
highly scalable instant messaging systems.
And I'm sure many of you have used that
as part of your favorite
instant messaging system.
But XMPP is actually
not only used for humans
to communicate with each other
and to create an ad hoc network,
but it's also used for
machine-to-machine communication
in complex distributed systems.
Here again, by introducing a bus layer,
we're simplifying the design,
by allowing machines
to have the appearance
of talking directly to each other
when in reality,
they are only talking to
a single lower layer in the stack.
Now here's another example of a bus.
This one is taken from the textbook,
and as you would expect,
this is the computer system bus
which is the canonical example
of a bus in hardware.
Now rather than connecting
the different pieces of a system
directly to each other,
each component
is connected only to the bus,
and a bus protocol
enables point-to-point communication
between any two entities on the bus.
And this is how
we have all learned the basics
of computer systems organization
on the hardware side.
Now, this picture is,
of course, very simplistic,
and as you know, in practice,
a modern computer,
at least a server,
has a few specialized buses.
For example, one that separates
the CPU to memory communication
from the I/O communication.
But, nevertheless, the concept of a bus
in hardware is absolutely fundamental.
So, so far I've shown a few examples
that show how layering can help
simplify the complexity
of computer systems.
Now, it's time to look
at the bigger picture
and formalize
some of these concepts again.
I mentioned that each layer
exposes an abstraction,
is modular, and typically
manages a namespace.
The implication is a layer has to be
consistent and self-contained.
Now when a layer is externally visible,
people often talk about the architecture
associated with that particular layer.
For example, the IP routing layer
in networking
is an extremely well-defined
combination of protocols and standards
that defines what people call
the layer three layer of networking.
But if you're building a component
that is not externally visible,
that is internal to a particular product,
you can still have a distinct layer.
If you're managing an abstraction,
if you have a module implementation,
and if you're managing a namespace.
And often people talk about
those principles that are exposed
to the upper layers as the theory of
operations of the particular component.
That's not where you're
describing the implementation,
but that is where you're describing
the abstraction
and the API that you're exposing.
The second important notion is that layers
can be, and generally are, a stack.
And that each layer generally relies on
a single underlying layer.
So we're not talking about
hierarchical composition
that actually introduces
a fair amount of complexity,
we think about a layered system,
typically you should actually
think about it as a single stack
with single dependencies
from one layer to the layer below.
And if you actually can't think
about it in this particular way,
maybe it's time to refactor the system
so that it follows
this particular mental model.
Now this model's not overly restrictive
because you have the ability
through runtime bindings,
to compose different implementation
onto the same layer.
And the example that we gave
is VFS which allows different file systems
to be implemented on top
of a single hierarchy of layers
that form the file system stack.
And there's a third important prinicple
which we'll revisit when we
talk specifically about the compute stack.
It's that when building a stack,
it is important to avoid
bypassing layers.
If you have three layers in your stack,
an A, B, and C,
and A depends on B and B depends on C,
your implementation,
you should have no explicit
or implicit dependencies
between the A and C.
And whenever you actually
have one of those subtle dependencies,
this is often the cause
for complexity and problems.
Now you notice that I
use the "C" word again, complexity.
We're always going to go
back to complexity in this class.
Now, unfortunately the operational
complexity is one of the key
undesirable emergent properties
of a layered design.
The more layers, unfortunately often,
the more complex
the management of that system.
Now because a layer is self-contained,
it is always designed so that it
can be independently managed.
Now managed can have a different meaning
depending on the context.
Now here the best way
to define management
is via the ISO FCAPS management model.
And FCAPS is the acronym for
Fault, Configuration,
Accounting or Availability,
Performance and Security Management.
It represents all the tasks
that need to be applied
to a particular device
or to a particular layer
when you're actually
using it as part of a system.
Now systems management
is often overlooked in research.
Because we tend to design systems
for ourselves and build prototypes.
But when you build products,
the management interface
is at least as important
as the functional interface of the layer.
And when you're using products,
that actually applies to us
as well in research.
The management interface is often
one of the main point of complexity
that we actually have to deal with
as researchers as well.
Now things get even more complicated
when you have not a single layer
to manage but obviously a stack
of multiple layers.
And that is because vendors
typically build management interfaces
for their own layer.
That makes sense.
But, unfortunately, by doing that
vendors often push the complexity
of managing an entire stack
to end users.
Consider a stack that has three layers,
built by different vendors.
They each have their own
management interface,
but the end user is responsible
to make sense of the combination
of these three layers.
And if you go back to the FCAPS acronym -
Fault, Configuration, Accounting,
Performance and Security -
each one of these tasks has to be composed
across the layers of the stack.
But in this example,
consider the simple stack
that has a file system
mounted on top of a raid volume.
First, provisioning for that raid volume
must be done in a precise order.
First the volume and then the file system.
When that's in place,
normal operations are easy to reason about
because of
the strict layering of the system
and because of the abstractions that
are exposed by the two different layers.
The file system is built on
the namespace of blocks,
and these blocks
are not physical disk addressees
but instead virtualized adressees
that materialize by the raid layer.
So, so far, so good.
Troubleshooting is where things
become a lot more complicated.
Consider for example
the loss of a physical drive.
The raid layer enables
the continuous operation of the system
but not in a totally transparent manner.
Going back to the FCAPS model,
at the very least,
the fault needs to be reported
and on top of that the performance
might be degraded.
Now one of the key lessons here
is that the management
and troubleshooting process often
requires going through the stack manually
and to do so in the inverse
order of operation.
When we layer a stack,
we typically use the stack
from top to bottom functionally
during normal operation,
but we typically have to troubleshoot
going back in the other direction.
This is a big deal.
As a matter of fact,
it's the number one cost center
in large data center operations today.
Well, we've covered a lot of ground
in this first module.
But let me give you a closing thought.
I'm sure you've heard of
the principle of indirection.
Often attributed to Butler Lampson,
who actually himself attributes it
to David Wheeler.
But let me read it out to you
completely with the amendment.
Any problem in computer science
can be solved by adding
a level of indirection.
But this usually creates another problem.
Now this obviously applies to layering.
It applies more broadly
in computer systems,
but it applies unambiguously
and completely to layering.
But this actually has to me
two fundamental implications.
The first one is designing
the right layer is extremely hard.
It's extremely hard to get
the abstraction right,
to get the functionality correct.
To create a layer that is useful
and lasting
and can be deployed in the area
of computer systems.
But if you can actually
nail the right abstraction
and identify the right layer,
this could be transforming.
And by that I mean industry-transforming.
Now the second thought
that I want to make sure
you take away from this first module,
is that the composition of layers
into a stack
is an extremely difficult task
with some unfortunate emergent properties.
In particular the management
of a complex layered systems design
can be extremely difficult
and challenging.
Thank you.
Next up we'll talk about the compute stack
and the information stack.