Welcome again, we're still talking about
layering, but this time going in depth
on two important stacks,
the compute stack
and the information stack.
Now since these lectures
are about layering,
it's not how the layers themselves
are implemented but rather how the stacks
are organized and composed
and the relationship between
these varying stacks.
But first a word of caution.
Compute and information tend
to be overloaded terms.
Depending on your community,
you may associate compute
with a processor or CPU
and information with memory
or the memory hierarchy.
And if you were to look at it
from this perspective you may be
tempted to actually create an association
between the compute
and the information stack
and actually specifically
an association that would look like this
which is a diagram
of the Finaman Architecture.
And I'm not sure if I need to explain this
in detail but the fundamentals
of the Finaman Architecture
could be summarized very simply,
as saying that the program itself
is stored in memory and the processor
has a program counter
to fetch connect instructions
from memory.
So compute and information
in the context of the Finaman model
are closely related concepts.
If you were actually to expand
on this, you may actually assume
that by the compute stack we may talk
about the internals that constitute
a processor in by the information
stack, we may talk about the internals
that form the memory hierarchy
and provide good performance.
If you were to do so,
you would actually be spot on
in thinking about locality,
which is going to be a topic
of a lecture in a couple of weeks.
But you would be actually missing
the point when we are talking about
layering which is the focus
of this lecture today.
So with that being said,
let's talk about the compute stack.
So to represent the computing stack
I'm using a figure taken directly from
the Saltzer and Kaashoek textbook.
And it shows that there
are three layers and two interfaces.
The hardware layer below exposes
an Instruction Set Architecture
to software, and the software itself
is organized as two distinct layers.
There's the operating system layer
and the application layer.
Now the computing stack is unique
in that it is customary for one layer
to bypass a lower layer
and directly execute instructions
on the hardware layer.
So specifically, applications execute
instructions directly on the CPU
without having to go
through the operating system.
Now that is what we call direct execution,
commonly called direct execution.
Now in general, layer bypass
is frowned upon.
But direct execution is actually
necessary in the computing stack
from a performance perspective,
because otherwise the operating system
would be left with the task
of having to interpret the instructions
of the applications.
Now direct execution is however
only acceptable
if the lower software layer,
which is the operating system,
can create a secure sandbox
that contains the upper software layer,
the application
to a well defined set of resources.
And that containment is generally done
and enforced by hardware.
But it can be done in software as well.
So in this simple example, which is
in this figure, the hardware layer
exposes primitives that are available
only through the operating system.
In particular, some privileged instructions.
Only the operating system can issue
these privileged instructions.
By doing so, the operating system
can ensure the integrity of the sandbox
that it creates for
each application process.
Now all reasonable operating systems
today provide that kind of protection,
and that kind of layering, so even though
you have direct execution
from an implementation perspective,
in reality, the layering is maintained.
But keep in mind that this
was not always the case.
Windows 95, which ran on the world's
desktop and which a few of you may be
old enough to remember,
is a perfect counter example.
Even though the hardware
had all the right primitives,
Windows 95 chose to expose
some critical in memory data
structures directly to applications.
As a result, applications could directly
compromise the integrity of the sandbox,
exposed by the operating system.
Now fortunately, Windows 95
is not that interesting anymore.
What's interesting these days
in current architecture is that
the notion of protection and bypass
is remaining as relevant as ever.
For example, virtual machine architectures
have added a new layer in the hierarchy.
Now we have to think
of at least three layers,
which we're showing in this picture.
We now have an application
layer like before.
We have an operating system
layer like before,
but rather than running
directly on the hardware,
the operating system is actually
running on top
of a virtual machine monitor.
Yet both the operating system
and the application can still issue
instructions directly, so that you have
all the performance benefits
of directly executing on the CPU.
Now it means now that direct execution
now applies across potentially two layers,
allowing an application
to bypass both the operating system
and the hypervisor to directly
issued instructions.
In the last few years processors
have added explicit hardware support
for this feature so that it's easy
to build a virtual machine stack
and make the overheads
of virtualization negligible.
That means that a hypervisor
or a virtual machine monitor
can run at the most privileged
level, an operating system
at some intermediate level,
and the application like before
with the most reduced
set of privileges possible.
Yet all three can execute,
direct the instructions on the CPU.
Now that type of innovation
has had a huge impact
on the research community
since we can now use those new
hardware features to think about
new layers and to compose new
layered stacks in innovative ways.
Here a few examples.
For example you can use
the hardware to create
recursive virtual machines.
There's an interesting paper
that actually has a virtual machine
monitor running a virtual machine
monitor, running
a virtual machine monitor,
finally running an operating system
in an application, that's a lot of layers
and the paper was
actually called "Turtles".
There's another example, you can run
a virtual machine monitor or hypervisor
below that hypervisor, and you would
do that so that you wouldn't have to
trust the mid-level hypervisor
for security perspective,
so that you can have a guarantee
that the mid-level hypervisor
could not spoof on the content
or inspect or spy on the content
of the virtual machine
and that interesting paper was called
"Cloudvisor" it was
an SOSP paper in 2011.
What you can actually use the hardware
differently to use virtualization
to not create virtual machines
but the sandbox processees
from the operating systems,
so create a mid layer between the OS
and a process, that is there
to provide an additional level
of isolation guarantees,
not implemented by the operating system.
And there was a system
called Dune published
at OSDI in 2012
that leverages
this hardware capability.
Now we have a full dedicated
lecture cycle on virtualization
in a few weeks, for now
we'll pause on the layering
of the compute stack and shift gears
and talk about the information stack.
By information stack, I'm going
to narrowly focus on the stack that handles
structured data, there's an equally
important information stack
to think about unstructured data,
but it's very important to start by
having a good handle on how
structured data is generally organized
or typically organized today.
So in doing so I'm specifically focusing
on a layered architecture that includes
a relational database since this is
such an important use case.
By that I mean that database
is not an application as far
as the field of computer systems
is concerned but actually is part
of the system domain.
Let's look at the stack.
In this picture, there are four layers,
the database layer, the filesystem layer,
the block layer, the volume layer,
and then finally, the disk layer.
I'm also listing here the APIs
exposed by these various layers.
Application make sequel calls,
typically over some RPC protocol
such as JDBC.
That's the first API,
on the UNIX system
the database typically
relies on POSIX API,
so system calls to access files.
Here I'm asumming a persistent
file system if you remember
the introductory module
so the information stack
typically goes to another
two different layers,
first the file system layer,
and then the volume management layer.
Now both these layers are internal to the
operating system but they
actually are very clearly
separate distinct layers.
Underneath the volume layer,
the block driver layer issues
block commands and that typically
uses the SCSI protocol which is
a hardware defined protocol
to access those drives.
Now one thing to note is that
two of these layers expose
the same interface, and that is
the block interface.
Both the SCSI protocol as well
as the volume management layer
expose a block interface and that is
because volume management is
a layer which exposes the same obstruction
that the resource that it relies upon.
That's a very specific form of layering
called virtualization and again,
as I mentioned, we'll have a dedicated
lecture on virtualization in a few weeks.
If we look at this picture here at this
level detail, we have four layers.
But in reality, many of these layers
can be each expanded into multiple,
distinct layers of their own.
So let's start with the data layer.
The data layer is the layer that manages
the information as databases.
Such databases typically
follow what is known
as the ANSI-SPARC
three layer model.
In that model, the individual presentation
layer, the conceptual schema layer,
and the internal representation layer
are each architected into different layers.
As with all good layers, each layer
provides it's own level of abtraction,
each layer relies on the layer below
and each layer manages a namespace.
So starting from the top, the presentation
layer includes query languages,
access control and many other elements.
Below, the community view manages
the community view that is,
the externally visible elements
of the schema, that is the namespace,
that is exposed.
Now internally, the community view relies
on objects such as indices and logs
that are provided by the physical layer.
And finally, the physical layer itself
implements these internal objects
on top of physical resources
and this picture on the right
it is a disc, although in reality
most databases are stored
on file systems, as it's shown on the left.
Let's move down one level, let's move
specifically to the filesystem layer.
In the previous module we talked about
the POSIX layer and the VFS layer
as two distinct building blocks
of the storage stack.
Here we're looking at the on-disc
implementation of a specific filesystem.
In other words the implementation
of a specific filesystem driver.
In this picture which is also taken
from the textbook, illustrates the way
the block layout of
a UNIX filesystem is organized.
What's interesting to note here
is that the designers of the UNIX
filesystem chose to architect
the solution through
a precise layering, by separating
inodes from directories.
Let me expand.
The lower layer which is the inode
layer allocates blocks and exposes
the abstraction of a file.
But in such a filesystem,
the files are not named.
Instead the meta data of each file
is indexed
with an array of anonymous inodes.
Now in the upper layer, the directory layer
the UNIX filesystem represents directories
as files, so a directory is nothing more
than an array of records
that map a filename onto
a particular inode.
Now that strict layering is not
accidental, instead it's the result
of a deliberate effort to control
the complexity of the design.
For example, when a filesystem
is corrupted, or simply when a filesystem
needs repair after a crash, each layer
can be independently managed and verified
starting from the lower layers.
That's precisely what tools such
as what FS check do today
on modern systems.
Now let's move down another level below.
File systems are laid on top
of a block device abstraction.
This could be any block device
obstruction whether it's persistent
or not and often file systems are laid
on top of volumes.
And a volume is nothing more than
the virtualization of one or more
physical disc drives.
Now a single drive can be multiplexed
into multi partitions and multiple disc
drives can be aggregated into
appearing like a single device.
There's many ways to do this
as there are RAID options.
From a layering perspective, the thing
to note is that the underlying resource
and the exposed abstractions
are identical.
And again this definition
of virtualization,
so from a layering perspective,
both in theory and in practice,
the volume management layer
could be trivially nested, recursively.
Because you can trivially nest
these layers recursively,
you get combinations such as
striped mirrors and mirrored stripes,
which are common terms
if you're looking at
managing enterprise storage.
In the first case you have RAID Zero
which is layered on top of RAID One
and in the other case you have
RAID One layered on top of RAID Zero.
To be honest with you,
I always have to think about which is which.
You can look it up too.
The point is that you have layers that can
be trivially nested and recursed
with each other because the
abstractions are all the same.
So let's move down one layer below.
By now you're probably hoping
that this module is over,
after all we are at the bottom
of the stack, we're at
the disc layer.
Well, not quite.
Actually, depending on your point of view
things are just now
starting to get interesting.
That is because, like many terms
in computer systems,
storage is overloaded.
So I prefer the definition of storage
as a SCSI target.
It's a little narrow since
SCSI is only one possible protocol
but the idea here is to define storage
as an abstraction that is materialized
by a well defined protocol,
and in this case the protocol is SCSI.
Now SCSI is nothing more
than an RPC protocol.
You have requests, you have response,
the client's side is called initiator
and the service side is called the target,
there's a lingo associated with SCSI
but it really is nothing more than
an RPC protocol.
Storage is really about being
on the target or on the service side
of that protocol.
The target can be an actual disc,
the two and half inch drive
in your laptop is a SCSI target.
The target code could also be
a dedicated hardware component
for example a RAID controller
which is connected to multiple disks
and in that example, the volume
management and the RAID function
that was previously described
as part of the operating system
is now implemented by the hardware itself.
But storage target can
and often is actually
a much larger device.
As a matter of fact,
it's a computer of its own.
Now the picture here
is that of an enterprise
class array and chances are
your bank transactions are stored
on either that device or the device
made by one of their competitors.
Now to put things in perspective,
such a device literally weighs a ton,
can have hundreds or thousands
of disc drives, typically has
at least four independent
computer systems internally,
that's because you have
two redundant front end computers
and two redundant back end computers
and these are very complex systems,
for example they automatically send
you an email when something goes wrong
and they definitely cost more
than an apartment,
even an apartment in Los An.
So the point here, is that despite
the immense internal
complexity of that device,
this is a device that exposes
the abstraction of a disc.
You have the same abstraction that
ranges in terms of a price,
from 100 francs, which would be
the cost of a two and a half inch drive,
to something that costs well over
multiple millions of Swiss Francs.
If you think about the importance
of identifying the right layers
and exposing the right abstractions,
the storage industry which is a
multi-billion dollar industry exists
because of this well defined abstraction.
Because it allowed them to innovate
and change things and deliver new
capabilities, and yet still maintain
the appearance of just being
nothing more than a disc drive.
So I've talked about SCSI a few times
already and if you remember,
SCSI is nothing more than an RPC protocol,
it was originally designed
to be implemented on a hardware bus
that is what parallel SCSI is today.
But as a protocol, it could also
be layered on top of other networking
protocols, and that field of work
is actually a pretty broad area,
it's called storage networking,
these are networking protocols
in stack that carry storage traffic.
Now I'm not going to go through
the stacks of this picture in detail,
what's important to note
is that you have multiple
different options, you have at least
six stacks shown on this picture
and there are many more,
they each use different
length network and end to end
technologies to communicate.
They also each have different management
model, one important management model
is called Fiber Channel which is
a way to name initiators,
targets and disc drives to create
storage area networks.
This is actually again as I mentioned,
a relatively broad field and some people
spend their entire careers focusing
on that particular
sub field of computer system.
And this brings up the final observation
in this module about layers.
We tend to think of the layered stack
as consisting of layers
that each provide a distinct function.
A little bit like a layered cake
where clearly the crust plays a role
that is different from the filling,
that is different from the frosting.
You may have multiple layers of filling
in the middle but at the end of the day
the crust is distinct and the layer
above is clearly distinct.
And yet from an implementation perspective
the better mental analogy
may actually be the Russian doll.
Anytime you double click
on the layer below you actually see it has
all of the components, attributes
and some of the issues
that you actually had to add a layer above.
The example we use is that clearly a disc
is not a computer, they're two completely
different abstractions, and yet a disc,
from an implementation perspective
very much looks like a computer.
So it's time to summarize.
We talked about the importance of layering.
I made the point about the fact that they're not
that many layers in computer systems,
takes a tremendous amount of effort
to define a properly architected layer.
If you can do that, it can have
a significant impact on
the overall industry or on the field.
Now even though there are not many
elementary building blocks, there's a near
infinite way in which you can combine
different layers into interesting stacks.
So there's flexibility in the composition.
And then finally we saw the Russian doll
example in the complex and the fact
that if you double click on the layer
you typically get all of the same
attributes of the layer above.
Now there are some cautionary points
some of which we discussed in the module,
some which we did not.
Obviously you may have an intuition
that layering adds overhead.
It's important to minimize these overheads
and sometimes you have techniques
such as direct execution
to minimize overheads.
We also saw that layering adds
complexity, unfortunately there's no
silver bullet to the complexity problem,
this is often one of the limiting elements
associated with a layer design.
Sometimes adding a layer can
actually create more than having
sort of a linear or proportional overhead
it can actually create a non linear
or sort of performance cliff.
For example, if you have a filesystem
that assumes rotating media
and you deploy it on a flash drive,
you may actually get
quite poor performance
or if you conversely deploy a filesystem
that is optimized for a flash drive
on a rotating media, the performance
may actually be poor.
And that is because the abstractions
generally don't convey the underlined
internal characteristics of the layer
that is because it is abstraction
that actually eliminates
the internal implementation details.
Even though sometimes these implementation
details have a first order impact
on performance.
So we did not cover this in the lectures
and that is because you will be
reading a paper from Mesnier and others,
it's an SOSP paper from SOSP '11
on Differentiated Storage Services
which is all about reconciling
the performance problem in the "A" layer
design and doing it over
the SCSI interface which
we did discuss in detail in this module.
Next up, we'll talk about client server.