Hello again, this is [Topaks]
still talking about layering,
this time, how two layers
talk to each other.
We're no longer looking at the broader,
bigger picture of how you compose a stack
made up of multiple layers,
but the very basic question of how
two layers can communicate
with each other.
And the general answer is,
they communicate through their API,
their interface.
There are actually three broad ways
in which this can be done.
First, the two layers can share
the same address space
and the same protection domain.
That's the case, for example, if a layer
is a C++ class and the other layer
is another C++ class
that depends on it.
And in that case, the interface is merely
that of a local API.
But sometimes the two layers
are protected from each other.
That's specifically the case
of the system call interface.
The client, which is the application,
makes system calls that execute
in a blocking, synchronous matter
by the operating system.
And there's a last case,
which is an interesting case,
where the two layers communicate with
each other over some kind of a channel.
And we refer to this
as the client/server programming model.
And we'll see it's generally based
on Remote Procedure Calls, or RPCs.
Now there are multiple ways in which
this channel could be implemented.
This could be done in hardware,
it could be an I/O bus,
it could be done over the network,
it could also simply be two different
processes that are running
on the same computer
but are communicating with each other
over a local socket.
Now the client/server model
is one that enables layering,
but also enforces modularity.
It actually enforces differently
than when the two layers
are part of the same address space
and communicate using a local API
because now the modularity is enforced
and is no longer discretionary.
Now this, in turn,
has a number of advantages.
And specifically, you can always reduce
the client/server model
as being that of two systems running
on two different computers
using only messages to communicate
even though the two entities may actually
be co-located on the same computer itself.
Now, in this mental model it actually
enables a sweeping simplification
in the design.
And that is because all forms
of communication and errors
are actually modelled as messages
and the modules are
isolated from each other
and so they fail independently
from each other.
And so the use of the client/server model
even within a local computer
actually is one that generally
enforces a good design
because it makes it impossible,
in practice,
to bypass any particular abstraction.
Also makes it impossible for one module
to corrupt, inadvertantly,
the data structures of another module.
There's actually a trade-off in the cost
associated with this enforced modularity,
and that is typically that the granularity
of a layer is typically much coarser
when the modularity is enforced
than if the modularity is discretionary.
And that is because of the overheads
of message space communication.
And those overheads must be amortized
over a more complex computation.
As long as you run within a single address
space, layers of abstractions are cheap,
and they're a good programming practice.
But if you actually need to linearize
any single communication,
any single call over a communication
channel, then this could become
quite expensive.
But if the modularity is actually in force,
there are key design trade-offs.
For example, how much client state,
or session state should be kept
on the servers.
This is sometimes required for performance
or for correctness,
but it increases the complexity
of the design.
So one of the key attributes
of the client/server model,
unlike the shared address space model,
is that the components may fail
independently of each other.
In other words,
they don't share the same fate,
and each side must determine
how to respond to the failure
of the other side.
Now the client/server model is typically
implemented using Remote Procedure Calls,
and RPCs were introduced in a 1984 paper
by Birrell and Nelson.
And the idea is to wrap both the REQUEST
and the RESPONSE messages
to look as much as possible like the call
and return of a normal procedure call.
And the picture here shows how
the sequence is deployed.
First, the clients marshalls,
which is a technical term
to copy all the arguments
into the message,
and then the message itself is sent
by some underlying communication
mechanism on the channel.
Now there on the right, the server
processes messages that have been
fully received, and does not process
partially received messages.
But when a message is fully received,
it then unpacks all the arguments --
this is the unmarshalling step --
and then each message comes with
an identifier for the [ro-it]
function to call.
And so at that point the server calls
the corresponding function
and that is known as the compute step.
And then once the compute step is done,
then it returns by sending the response
back to the client.
And that is similar to the request,
the arguments of the response
are marshalled to a message,
which is sent back to the client
over the communication channel.
And generally,
until it receives a response,
the client typically is simply waiting
for that response to come.
And that would be known as the
synchronous RPC model.
There's also an asynchronous variant
which is becoming more and more
popular these days, especially for people
programming in JAVA Script.
If you think about this model,
it's very easy to use
because there are tools that simplify
the programming model.
In the older days,
two or three decades ago,
the simplification was done by stubs
that were automatically generating
by programs, and represented
in languages such as XDR.
So you typically had a way of expressing
RPCs using XDR that would layer
directly on top of either UDP or TCP/IP
communication protocol.
In the more current era, we've moved
to web services, RESTful APIs or AJAX,
all of which are RPCs implemented
on top of HTP base protocol.
The success of RPC is because of its
relative simplicity.
It is designed to look as much as possible
like local procedure calls.
However, there are obvious differences
between the two,
and one of them is that there is no global
shared address space
or ability to pass pointers.
So each request must be self contained,
the data structure must be fully
marshalled, or linearized,
since the server has no opportunity
to call back the client
for missing information.
So that is one important difference.
There's a second important difference,
which is the lack of shared fate
that I mentioned before.
And by that I mean that either the client
or the server may fail
at any point in time
when the other side does not fail,
and as we will see,
this creates complications.
Now because there's no shared fate,
any RPC may fail.
And because of that, either the client
or the server must somehow
decide the semantics of an RPC that fails.
Now it turns out there's no single,
universal answer.
Actually this is a case, or an instance of
the application of the enter in principle
which you will learn about soon, in which
the application generally knows best,
and when in doubt, leave the problem
of deciding the semantic of a failure
to the end-to-end applications
rather than the RPC,
which is merely the communication
subsystem.
And because of this end-to-end principle,
or the application of that
end-to-end principle,
there actually are three, generally used
semantics to deal with RPC failures.
The first one is known as
the at least once semantic.
And the semantic, in this case,
is that the client will actually,
in the case of a failure by the server,
will keep re-trying until the RPC
is proven to be successful.
And so this actually has consequences.
First of all, an RPC may hang
for an indefinite amount of time.
And also that the operations themselves
may be idempotent
because they are going to be applied
at least once,
but possibly multiple times.
But yet, this is a very popular way of
expressing the semantics of RPCs.
There's another mechanism which is
the at-most once semantic,
and this is actually doing the opposite.
The client will actually attempt at most
once to issue the RPC,
and if for any reason something fails,
they'll simply notify the application
of the failure of that RPC.
That is actually the common approach
to the web today.
An HTTP request will either succeed
at most once, or fail.
And if it fails, then you get either
an error code
or you get some kind of a time-out message
that you were not able to send the message
through.
There's also the ability to have
exactly-one semantics,
but this actually cannot be done
in a universal way
by the communication subsystem itself,
rather, it actually requires that the clients
and the servers keep some kind
of a persistent state
that is coordinated between the two so
that they know how far along they've gone
in their exchanges and so it can guarantee
that every RPC is delivered exactly once
to the client.
So let's wrap this module with an example
that puts it all together.
And the example that I chose is NFS.
And the NFS paper is simply brilliant
because it has the elegance of the earlier
era of papers in computer systems.
Now what's important to [ ] put into
perspective is at the time
NFS was by far not the only proposal
for distributed filesystems.
As a matter of fact, there were many
other proposals in flight,
many of which were more complex,
had more features than NFS itself.
But one of the reasons why NFS won
is because it was the simplest
possible way in which you can design
a network filesystem protocol.
And it was simple in multiple ways.
First of all, it was a very
clean RPC design.
You had requests and responses.
They developed XTR as part of this
in order to simplify the description
of the messages themselves.
And then the protocol allowed for a
stateless server design
which means there was absolutely no
per client-specific state that was kept
on an NFS server.
They also simplified the communication
relationship so the clients
never had to talk to each other.
And servers managing different filesystems
also never had to talk to each other.
Different clients only talked to their
respective NFS servers.
And that also eliminated
many of the issues
associated with coherency that were
present in other filesystems
simply because NFS didn't provide
as strong coherency semantics,
but did not attempt to provide as strong
coherency semantics as other filesystems.
And then finally it was brilliantly
simple in its use
of the at least once semantics
for RPC failures.
The server was down;
the client would just keep trying.
And so at the time you had these
server down messages
that would pop up because some of these
NFS servers were not that reliable.
But it made for a very simple design
because it actually maintained,
allowed the operating systems running
on the clients to actually thing of an NFS
filesystem just like they would think
of a local filesystem.
And that's the last point that was
indicative of the success of NFS
which is it was well integrated into
an existing filesystem,
an existing operating system
using the VFS layer
that is internal to the operating systems
themselves which we covered
in the previous module.
So in many ways, NFS
is a brilliant example
of a very simple,
minimalistic design.
HTTP is another example
of a minimalistic design
that implements RPCs today.
So if you actually want to look at what
NFS looks like in greater detail,
this is a picture that I took
from the original paper.
Note that I actually did not
tilt the picture myself.
But instead this paper sold that the only
copies available are some scans
of a not-so-aligned version of the paper
that was printed a few decades ago.
But this picture actually allows us
to review many of the concepts
that we've seen so far.
We see the distinct layering of system
call layer and the VFS layer within UNIX.
This is a form of soft modularity
and layering within the operating system.
We see the VFS layers' ability to
virtualize different filesystem drivers
below a common interface, and to create
a unified namespace
that captures multiple files coming from
different filesystems of different types.
Third, we see the layering of the NFS
on top of RPC and XDR.
That's the ENT N layer of the networking
stack that provides the communication
mechanism.
And fourth, we see the use
of the network layer below
to connect the client and the server.
The link is not shown but that is expected
since the design only relies
on the Network layer
as its lowest layer.
And that wraps up this module.
Next, we'll actually go into the next
level of detail in the networking stack
and talk about the different layers
in networking itself.