Hello again, I'm still Ed Bugnion.
This is still POCS.
This is still layering.
This is actually the fourth module
on the layering section,
the final module,
and right now we're going
to talk about networking.
Actually we're not going
to talk about networking,
because that
is a controversial topic of its own,
but we're going to talk
about networking layers,
because that itself
is a controversial topic of its own,
and this is
about the layering principle.
So, let's get started.
And to get started,
we're going to first talk about
something you're most likely
familiar with at some level,
which is the OSI model.
So, let me give you the scoop.
The OSI model is obsolete,
and should not be referenced,
and yet we all do that
in our everyday language.
As a matter of fact, I'm going to make
references to the OSI model in this module
because it's very difficult
to talk about networking
without referencing
some elements of that model.
And yet, the model is obsolete,
and should not be used.
So bear with me with the contradiction.
So, for example, we have an intuition
as to what layer two might mean,
what layer three might mean,
or even what layer seven might mean.
You actually can commercially buy products
such as layer seven load balancers,
because from a marketing perspective,
it's sexier to call something
a layer seven load balancer
than simply an http proxy.
In reality, they're generally often
one and the same thing.
And if you're even luckier,
you may have heard one day
of the layer eight model.
Of course, if somebody talks to you
about the layer eight model,
that person is implicitly assuming
that you:
a. know that there are seven layers
in the OSI model and not eight,
and that the layer eight model
refers to the invisible political layer
that drives all bad decisions
in a company.
But, after this caveat, the OSI model
is not, strictly speaking, completely bad.
It did serve a purpose,
and one purpose that it did serve
is it helped
the networking industry organize itself
to standardize various aspects
of the system in a modular fashion,
in a layered fashion.
And so, let's go through an example
that actually worked reasonably well,
and maps reasonably well.
And the example
I'm going to use is Ethernet.
So, Ethernet is not a standard.
As a matter of fact, it's the
combination of multiple standards.
In order to have any Ethernet stack,
you need multiple Ethernet standards
to work together.
The most important standard is 802.1,
which defines a frame format,
the MAC address, the namespace,
the semantics for unicast and multicast.
And that standard is generally mapped
with a layer two model in the OSI model.
And as another example,
the central standard
for Ethernet switching
is 802.1D, and that is also
a layer two model.
Now, the IEEE also standardized
the lower layers of the networking stack;
that's why you need the combination
of IEEE standards to have
an Ethernet solution that is done
by other working groups,
such as 802.3 for wired links
or 802.11 for WiFi,
and you combine these two things
and you end up
having an Ethernet solution.
So this is all pretty good, right?
In the way the model--
I don't know to what extent
it had a direct influence,
but certainly the model
the industry aligned and used,
the terminology of the model
at the lower levels of the system.
But this breaks down,
and specifically this breaks down
at the upper layers,
and that is largely because today,
the winning design in networking,
at the upper layers, is the result
of a community effort,
not the result of a competitive effort
among industry competitors.
Of course, the winning design
I'm referring to is the Internet,
and the community is IETF.
And there's a very different set
of perspectives and philosophies
if something emerges from industry
rather, when something emerges
from a community.
And to emphasize this, I found
this interesting quote in an RFC,
called "Layering considered harmful."
And this is worth just reading
so that you get a sense of what I mean.
So this RFC states:
They even state a corollary,
which is pretty funny to read.
Alright, so I rest my case on this.
But the point is
that OSI had many strict layers,
and IETF was about architectural elegance
and about striking a balance.
Now in the textbook,
we actually don't have
a seven-layer model,
we don't have
necessarily an IETF model.
We actually are using
a simpler, three-layer model.
Now, the authors themselves
are sometimes questioning
whether this is the right model,
but this actually has a lot of merit.
It's very good to help think about
how and where things land
in the context
of a layered networking design.
And certainly,
three is probably the lower bound.
Everybody will agree that three
is the minimal number of layers
that you need in order to build
any form of a network system.
And so what are those three layers?
Well, the lower layer is the link layer,
and it has a single function,
which is to carry frames on links,
maybe between a NIC and a switch,
or between a radio and an access point,
or potentially between links
between two switches.
But this is only the link layer;
it doesn't worry about
where things should go,
where things should be routed,
or it doesn't worry about
what the hosts are going to do
with the data once they receive it.
It's only responsible to carry links.
At the layer above,
the network layer is only responsible
to carry packets between links.
And the way you do that is
you route connecting links together
according to the network's current view
of the network topology.
This is a hard problem.
And importantly,
the network layer is designed to be
distributed and resilient.
You have protocols that, basically,
deal with the issue of reconciling
the actual current network topology
with the network layer's view
of the networking topology.
In particular, this is hard
when things like routers will fail
and links would go down.
So there's a lot of
complexity in that layer,
but the good news is it relies on
a simple abstraction of the lower layer.
You can actually use
different link layer technologies
in different parts of the network
in a transparent fashion,
and you expose
a simple interface or abstraction,
to the end-to-end layer.
And the end-to-end layer,
which is implemented in the hosts,
is largely, at least in this model,
a set of RPCs between hosts.
You send and receive messages
via the network layer
without having to worry about
the topology of the network,
and obviously without
having to worry about
the link level technologies
that are used below.
So here again there's a significant amount
of complexity in the end-to-end layer,
but it can rely on a simple abstraction
offered by the network:
simply the ability to send a packet
to its destination by giving it
some kind of address
associated with the destination.
Now the three-layer model
is somewhat simplistic;
maybe a little too simplistic to capture
the reality of the system.
And actually, the authors themselves
describe this end-to-end layer
as serving three different functions:
presentation, transport,
and session management.
So these three functions
are not different layers;
they are all part of the end-to-end layer.
And then another note is that
they basically restrict their view
of the networking stack
to the very basic capabilities
that could be offered
by a networking stack,
when in reality, the domain of networking
actually grows up
with layers built on top
of those very basic end host capabilities.
So I just want to make a side note
so that people don't get confused.
When I talk here
about the end-to-end layer,
I actually do not talk
about the end-to-end principle.
There's a relationship between the two.
The end-to-end principle
is applied broadly and in many areas,
and it's about
pushing complexity to the applications
because they know best.
The end-to-end layer is performing
a well-defined function
within the three-layer
networking model of the textbook,
and it uses the end-to-end principle
specifically to simplify
the implementation
of the networking layer.
So in the case of the networking stack,
the network's end-to-end layer
applies the end-to-end principle
by handling all host-specific issues
within the host,
and TCP is the canonical example
for an implementation of that.
And then the transport layer
handles both the congestion management
and the flow control,
freeing the network and the link layer
from having to worry
about these two considerations at all.
And this is a simplified view
of the core principle
behind layering and networking.
As a matter of fact,
it's a pretty good proxy
of deployments in networking.
Now of course, as you would expect,
there are nuances,
complications, and applications.
So I'm going to first talk
about one complication,
and then
two interesting applications
of this model.
The first complication is that
there's an unfortunate difference between
the architectural beauty of standards,
and the implementation in reality
in products that you buy.
And this actually applies broadly,
but it actually applies
in a pretty clear way
in the networking domain.
Standards bodies are very good
at focusing on a particular area.
Both IETF and IEEE have work groups
with well-defined charters.
They solve one problem,
and then these problems
can be layered together
from a layering perspective
in order to form
a complete solution stack.
But in reality, the people
that are building products
actually tend to build products
that use different functions
from different layers into a single set--
single-function device
that serves multiple purposes.
And sometimes this is not a problem,
does not create operational complexity;
if anything, simplifies
the operational model.
And sometimes it actually can create
some substantial complexity
by introducing a great degree
of flexibility in the implementation.
So let me give you an example
that actually works reasonably well,
that you probably all have at home:
some kind of a home router,
that may look somewhat like this.
If you actually look at it
under the covers,
this involves a whole set
of different networking standards
operating at different layers.
At the link layer, we have 802.11 WiFi,
and various sub-versions of it.
We also have, since you have
some wired ports,
you also have some 1GbE
or 100 megabit Ethernet standards
that specify the links.
Now, this device is also
a layer two Ethernet bridge,
and so it basically incorporates
all of the layer two switching standards
between the radios and the wired ports.
And this device is also a router,
and that is because you need to NAT
in order to connect to the Internet,
to have a single --
since you have a single,
externally-routable IP address.
And so this is typically
a higher-level function
that is implemented
within that same device,
and then, although this one
doesn't do it in particular,
but other devices routinely
also incorporate DSL modem capabilities
into the same product.
So this is a case where you have
product integration
using different standards in a way
that is actually simplifying
the operational model.
But there are many counterexamples,
and actually data center networking
is a good counterexample,
where people have actually implemented
into a single device
products that have
multiple different functionality
from different standards
at different layers
and can be configured
into arbitrary, complex ways.
And so let me give you an example.
This picture shows a leading,
probably the best,
highest density data center switch
you can buy in the market today,
and these are some of the specs.
And if you actually
read through the specs,
what you see is these are
all Ethernet-related standards, right?
We talk about link rates,
10 gigs, 40 gigs, 100 gigs,
and we specifically talk about Ethernet,
and certainly "E", the capital "E"
stands for Ethernet in this context.
Now in reality,
this is not an Ethernet switch.
This is a router,
or this could be a switch,
or this could be a combination of the two.
And as a matter of a fact
you can configure your solution
to be some combination hybrid
between layer two switching
and layer three routing -- and again,
I'm using the OSI terms
that actually we should not be using
but people use them anyway --
into a solution.
Now, those combinations tend
to dramatically increase
the level of complexity you have
in the network.
It's what people call
the god boxes of networking.
You can do many, many things with them,
but it's extremely difficult
to reason about them into engineering,
because we've effectively subsumed
so many different functions in it
that is intended to be distinct,
into the same system.
And it's very difficult for people
to reason through
some of the possible interactions
between the different layers.
Now that we've done
this detour in product reality,
let's go back to the sound principles,
and specifically the sound principles
of the Saltzer/Kaashoek textbook
and this three-layer model of networking.
And that model actually allows
for a number of interesting use cases.
And the first one I want to go through
is relatively simple, but very important.
It's the concept of
what they call map composition,
which basically is an application
of the layered model
where rather than having
one end-to-end implementation,
one network implementation,
and one link implementation,
either the network
or the link implementation
actually uses two independent layers,
one mapping directly onto the other.
And so map composition
could either apply at the link layer,
or it could apply at the networking layer.
The mechanisms used
to implement them, by the way,
are not exactly the same.
Let me give you
just a very simple example.
You can map one link technology
onto another link technology.
This was done, for example,
for AppleTalk,
which was a legacy networking technology
by Apple,
which was then mapped
on a link-by-link basis,
on a packet-by-packet basis,
onto Ethernet networks.
Now this was over a decade ago.
More recently, and
something I'm intimately familiar with,
we were able to map Fibre Channel,
which was a proprietary,
or at least
a specialized networking technology
used in the storage world,
and we were able
to map Fibre Channel frames
onto Ethernet frames.
That is done by combining
an encapsulation mechanism,
as well as flow control on the link,
link-level flow control,
at the Ethernet layer,
which enabled this map composition,
link to link.
The other examples are
network-to-network map composition.
So again, you have
within the networking layer
two different layers,
one relying on the other.
One example which is commonly used
is the mapping of IP subnet
onto Ethernet broadcast domains.
So even though I'm saying Ethernet here,
this is clearly a networking layer
within the three-layer model
from the stack, from the book,
and an IP subnet can be officially mapped
onto an Ethernet broadcast domain,
specifically so that
you can efficiently implement
a thing like IP multicast on top of that.
Another example of map composition
is the ability to compose
two different networks
that are each autonomous,
and to have them peer with each other
in order to allow communication,
in a transparent fashion,
between any host
on either side of the network.
That is what we call bridging
between autonomous systems,
and that is the fundamental principle
behind the Internet.
And this is a form of map composition,
because you have a--
within the networking layer
you have an autonomous layer
which is responsible for routing
within the autonomous system,
and you have an external layer
which is responsible for peering
between autonomous systems and making,
and appropriately routing the packets
across these two layers.
The other application, from the textbook,
of the three-layer model is,
in my opinion,
a little bit more interesting
and intellectually challenging,
and it is the notion
of recursive composition.
So let me first read the definition.
Now obviously,
the concept itself is recursive,
so that the link layer
of the first network,
which rests on the end-to-end layer
of the second network.
Now the link layer
of the second network itself
can obviously rest
on the end-to-end layer of a third network
and you can create your Russian dolls
as deep as you need
for your particular application.
So this is a way to think about
the application of that model.
It's specific to communication systems,
specifically specific
to this three-layer model,
but allows for a recursive composition.
It has many applications,
things that we use on an ongoing basis.
Both dial-up and DSL are cases
of recursive composition because
the link layer of the first network,
which is what we think of our access
to our gateway device
from our home router
to the access gateway,
it actually rests
on an end-to-end protocol
implemented between the two DSL modems:
the DSL modem and the DSLAM aggregator.
And so you have a case
where one's link
is somebody else's end-to-end network.
This can also be used
in peer-to-peer networks,
where the link between two nodes
in a peer-to-peer network
actually rests on, obviously,
the end-to-end layer
implemented by the operating system,
typcially TCP or UDP sockets
that allow you to communicate
between end hosts.
That end-to-end layer
exposes an abstraction that is used
as a link in a peer-to-peer network.
The notion of these peer-to-peer networks
leads to the concept of overlays.
Overlays are becoming very popular
right now with software-defined networks
in which you can create
the abstraction of a network,
maybe a layer two or a layer three network
that is actually implemented
as an overlay
on top of an existing physical network.
That has many applications,
in particular for multitenancy
and cloud applications.
And it's also being used for Voice over IP
and it's also being used by VPNs.
Now this is actually such an interesting
and such an important topic
that one of the papers
that you'll be reading next week--
this week, sorry--
is around an overlay network.
As a matter of fact, it's one of the first
overlay networks that was proposed
within the systems community.
And one of the interesting aspects
of this paper is that
it is to be put in the context
of the scale of the Internet,
and the number
of advertised autonomous systems
within the Internet.
And this is a chart that actually plots
the growth of the Internet,
not in terms of end hosts,
but in terms of autonomous systems.
Now, the paper that you're reading
is pretty old because
it was the first paper
in overlay networks,
trying to add resiliency to the Internet.
It was published at SOSP in 2001,
so it's well over a decade old.
At the time, the Internet was small.
And so, when you read the paper
and as you read the paper,
ask yourself the question:
are the use cases
that are presented in this paper
more applicable today,
with the rise of the number
of autonomous systems?
Or are they less applicable today,
and if so, why?
So this is something to think about
as you're reading this paper.
So, let's summarize
what we've covered in this module.
We talked about
the importance of judicious layering.
There are two extremes,
and from philosophy perspective,
the OSI model and the IETF model.
Then we actually went in-depth,
and I encourage you to read the portion
of the texbook that covers it,
the three-layer model
of the Saltzer/Kaashoek texbook.
We did a detour to talk about architecture
and the difference
between architecture and implementation.
And then we talked about
two applications of the model,
in particular recursive composition,
which you will be exposed to
in the paper you're reading.
And this wraps it up for this week.
Thank you very much.
Enjoy the papers.