Hello and welcome to this third module of
the MOOC
on protected areas management in Africa.
This week, we will talk about protected areas
governance.
It is an extremely important subject, as we
will see with Paul NDiaye,
who is a lecturer at the University of Cheikh
Anta Diop University in Dakar.
So this week, the module will be structured
as follows:
the first class will be introducing the notion
of governance
and different types of governance
that we come across in protected areas.
As for the second lesson,
it will introduce governance by government,
which applies to the majority of protected
areas in Africa these days.
Less frequent, but just as important, is private
governance,
and this will be the topic of the third lesson.
The fourth lesson will be about governance
by communities,
the one that enables local populations
to take control of managing a certain number
of protected areas
more and more frequently.
The fifth lesson will deal with shared governance,
a type of governance
that brings together several types of actors
in the decision-making schemes.
They are sometimes complex,
but they are always rich and innovative.
It is also being developed a lot at the moment.
The last lesson will be on our weekly convention.
Once again, we will be staying in the field
of the Convention on Biological Diversity
with a specific focus, here as well, on local
communities.
We will be looking at how people access and
share the advantages,
and we will deal with the famous Nagoya Protocol.
Finally, we will have our brief weekly summary
in the form of an animation,
and then the assignment for this module will
be explained to you.
There we go, it is now time for this module
on governance.
Have an excellent third week with us!