Hello and welcome to this lesson
which will today be dedicated to a quick presentation
on governance of protected areas.
Governance is of course a decisive factor
in explaining the successes but also the failures
of protected areas.
To find out more, it might be helpful to refer
to the guidelines published by the World Commission
on Protected Areas.
In particular for this lesson,
look at the first chapter of the document
which explains the relationship between the
definition
of categories of protected areas, that we
have already seen,
and governance,
and which rapidly also identifies some important
concepts
to be familiar with this subject.
Other interesting documents to consult
the 84th edition of the NAPA letters,
which summarizes a study by PAPACO conducted
in French-speaking Africa
on the conditions of governance of protected
areas.
This study and this letter are available in
full
as usual at papaco.org.
As announced, Paul NDiaye will be helping
me
throughout this module.
So, the notion of governance is a difficult
concept to define
and focuses more on who manages the protected
area
than what managers actually do.
We often talk about the quality of governance:
what we call good governance.
As we have already mentioned,
the types of governance were established
historically, based on dirigiste settings,
but over time, we have moved from a philosophy
of preservation,
based on the exclusion of residents,
to a philosophy more oriented towards the
sustainable use of resources
linking the population to conservation,
or sometimes, the private sector.
We have therefore expanded the list of actors
involved in the management of protected areas.
Of course that is not always possible everywhere,
it is important to remember,
but it is nevertheless the current trend.
Let's listen to an account on this subject
from Senegal.
Governance is already a vague concept,
when applied on a local scale,
such as a protected area.
It defines the way
the exercise of power is structured.
Furthermore, there are mechanisms and frameworks
which define the arrangements for the participation
of different actors.
In Senegal, we can say that this governance
has been dynamic.
And all over Africa, we can see cases
of delegation, simply through
the creation and implementation
of tools for management.
So we talk of participatory governance
with more and more actor participation or
with the
involvement of other actors, who can be private
actors or others.
In any case,aspects of decentralization
are strong elements in the dynamic
of protected areas governance in Senegal and
in other places in Africa.
Governance intends to be effective and efficient
and when we talk of governance, we think of
an ideal,
which means that there are many elements
which must figure in this model.
A good state presence, the absence of corruption...
sustainable management of resources,
but also sound planning documents,
which express the effectiveness of the governance
of protected areas.
That said, what does this governance relate
to
in the context stricto sensu of protected
areas
and what applications can be drawn from it?
The governance of protected areas
leads us to questions of power, relations
and responsibilities.
From a practical point of view, we are able
to understand this
by asking this question:
Who has the authority and the responsibility
for managing,
and must report what has been achieved?
It has little to do with managing,
which is “what to do to achieve the goals
of the protected area”.
But it tells us about the decision-makers
and those ultimately responsible
and what has been done or not been done for
the protected area.
Governance also can also answers the following
important questions:
How are decisions for the protected area made?
What norms are applied?
Which approaches, values and principles serve
as a guide for the decision makers?
The answers to these questions and others
inform us
about the quality of governance.
It helps us understand if we are dealing with
good governance or not.
IUCN defines four broad types of governance
of protected areas,
which will allow us to define the framework.
Let's look at these types with Paul.
We do indeed have four types of governance,
all of them are legitimate and important for
conservation.
Protected areas, under the authority of the
government
whether at regional, national level, or at
supranational level,
are an example of governance by the government.
Protected areas under the authority of several
interested parties,
is what we call shared governance.
Protected areas under the authority of the
private sector,
that is, in general, landowners
or owners of the natural resources concerned,
we call that private governance.
And finally, protected areas under the authority
of indigenous people
or local communities, whether settled and/or
mobile,
with common law and/or legal rights,
this is called governance by indigenous peoples
and local communities.
We will look at each of these types of governance
one by one
in the following sequences.
A general description, an overview is also
given in chapter 4
of the guidelines.
You can see how these different types of governance
are organized
into a sort of continuum.
It ranges from a governance, essentially in
the hands of the state,
here on the left,
which as we have said,
concerns the majority of national parks in
Africa, for example
to a governance of protected areas
in which the state is no longer involved,
at least in theory.
We can find this here, on the right.
These are in general private protected areas
or community protected areas, where the rights
have been transferred to the local actors.
At this stage, we can examine what we gain
from this classification.
We observed in unit one
that the protected areas are arranged into
six categories,
one, two, three, four, five, six,
that we already know and which are now here
on the left.
We can see that they are also broken down
into four types of governance.
All that can therefore be easily summarized
in a comprehensive table,
that you can see here, containing 24 boxes,
a sort of matrix,
which describes all the types of protected
areas, that you can find.
So for example a park of category II, a type
of national park,
managed by the state will be found in this
box,
whilst a sacred site, whose access is forbidden
by the community
to preserve the environment in its natural
state,
of category I, will be here.
Another site, managed by indigenous people
for example,
where there is sustainable fishing,
so a category VI, will be here.
This matrix helps us to categorize protected
areas
that we come across
and eventually to form useful groups,
for example, to organize meetings and training
for managers, who share the same preoccupations
in terms of management and governance.
Unfortunately, protected area governance is
rarely listed
in the world protected areas databases.
Present estimations relate therefore
to less than 30% of protected areas in Africa.
The results give us at least 80% are state
protected areas,
in blue on this map, we can see them all over.
The rest, a small percentage of PAs, of shared
governance
or community governance, or private governance.
And we can see here, this varies depending
on the region.
In general, state protected areas are the
largest, as we have said,
and the private ones are mostly found in English-speaking
Africa.
This map here summarizes all that,
but keep in mind that the vast majority of
protected areas in Africa
has no type of governance assigned to it here.
If we do not yet know
all the types of governance at a continental
scale,
we know, on the other hand, that governance
evolves.
It is in fact obvious that no type of governance
is unchanging.
Changes in status happen over time,
which force changes to occur
that result from a concern to improve governance
to create efficient conservation conditions
Governance can be learned,
can be experimented with and can be tested
and certainly other models still need to be
invented
to address the challenges of today and the
future of our protected areas.
Going into detail on the different types of
governance,
in our next sequences,
we will be able to better reflect on that.
You must understand that governance and above
all its quality,
is a determining element of the ability, or
lack thereof,
of a protected area to play its role.
If governance is lacking
even if the best management strategies are
put in place,
results will be mediocre, or even nonexistent.
Management is the easiest to master
as we now have most of the technical solutions
for the parks.
There are 1000 examples of protected areas
that could do infinitely better
than they are doing, if only they changed
their governance
and of course those who manage it,
This brings us back to the notion of responsibility
that we have raised whilst studying categories.
Think carefully about this and ask yourselves
for the sites that you are familiar with,
in what way could a simple change of manager
change their results radically.
We are at the end of this lesson.
The next episode will be about protected areas
governed by government
Have a good day.