Welcome to today's lesson
on analyzing the governance by government
of protected areas.
Its role in the conservation of nature in
Africa turns out
to be crucial.
Of course, you can refer
to the WCPA guidelines on governance
to find out more, and especially chapter three.
I also recommend the 87th edition of the NAPA
letters,
here,
which summarizes a study we have recently
done
on the governance model in Africa.
You can download both of them on our website
papaco.org.
We will have a look at the history, the special
features and some weaknesses
of governance by government, with our friend
Paul Ndiaye.
Nearly everywhere in French-speaking Africa,
as well as in other places,
the first protected areas created in the beginning
of the twentieth century
are a result of public initiatives
in places such as Senegal, Ivory Coast, French
Sudan,
Guinea-Conakry, Upper Volta, Dahomey, Niger,
etc.
They enabled the first state protected areas
to be created.
Up until now, these state protected areas
have
the most widespread form of governance in
Africa,
as we have already said.
Although this is progressively evolving.
Colonial administration took some initial
decisions,
which were not reconsidered
by the independent African States,
which replaced them mainly from the 1960s.
History does in fact allow for the state initiative
to have a large role in terms of creating
protected areas.
On top of this, it seems important to formulate
two statements.
First of all, the new state protected areas
that were created after countries became independent
are limited in number,
except for a few countries, like Guinea-Bissau
especially.
But, even in this case,
the size of the areas is much more modest
everywhere
than those of the previous generation.
Then, there's the conditions the state protected
areas were set up in
that are constantly affecting them through
an authoritarian approach.
This generates a lot of frustration,
which is at the origin of the continuous conflicts,
something which we will talk about later.
State governance exercises a prominent influence
in the national protected area networks, which
are organized everywhere in Africa,
particularly, but not only, in French-speaking
Africa.
Therefore, for example, the large parks in
West Africa,
like Niokolo-Koba in Senegal, or Comoé in
Ivory Coast, etc.
Mole National Park in Ghana, W-Arli-Pendjari
that we have already seen,
well, all of these parks are governed by the
state.
Historically, governance of state protected
areas,
whenever the different entities may have been
established,
does not suffer from any ambiguity in any
of the countries.
It is exclusively protected by the public
authority,
directly or by delegated services,
such as the Water and Forestry Service, or
the National Park service.
Sometimes relatively autonomous entities have
been created
as an attempt to give them more flexibility.
That is the case with bureaus, agencies autonomous
public institutions, etc.
But this type of governance always seem authoritarian
and rigid.
These were the essential ingredients to produce
the success
that it received initially, at least.
All of the French-speaking states have applied
this model,
sometimes without changing it, up until recently.
Most of the English-speaking countries have
done the same.
This approach, which involves imposing decisions,
presupposes
that two conditions be met:
have the means and the technical ability as
well.
Means include first of all legality and legitimacy,
essential for recognition by all relevant
actors,
in one way or another, by the protected area.
The state has the legal rights to decide to
create a protected area
and to manage it alone.
However, having the legal right to do it
is not necessarily acknowledged by the local
population,
especially if they were evicted
when the protected areas were created.
The technical ability refers to managing human
and financial resources,
which are also necessary for establishing
their authority.
Strangely, this ability has frequently caused
problems for the states.
They have found themselves in other emergency
situations,
where they have been unable to mobilize personnel
and provide sufficient budgetary allocations
to cope with the needs for managing them.
Governance by the state is weakened
and state protected areas are threatened in
every way:
by trespassing, by poaching,
by livestock straying.
This last point partly explains the reality
of the situation
that has brought the African states to loosen
up on exclusive governance,
which they had been strict about up until
then.
The conditions surrounding the creation of
the first protected area networks
greatly justify the primacy of state protected
areas,
which still exists.
However, their inefficiency in some situations
has ended up negatively affecting this type
of governance in many places.
That's why they have been extended to other
actors,
private or community actors,
as we will see in the next videos.
There are large differences between countries
or regions.
There we go, that's the end of the lesson.
The next episode will examine
another type of governance of protected areas:
private protected areas.
Have an excellent day.
Partnership between André Hoffmann, École
Polythechnique Fédérale de Lausanne,
IUCN (France-IUCN partnership)
This MOOC is an academic collaboration between
the following institutions:
Produced within the RESCIF framework
and from the EPFL MOOCS for Africa initiative.