Welcome to today's lesson
where we will be introducing private protected
areas,
which are pretty rare in Africa, especially
in French-speaking Africa,
as we have already said.
As usual in this module, I suggest that you
refer
to the World Commission on Protected Areas
guidelines,
to find out more.
You could also look
at the 85th and 86th editions of the NAPA
letters,
which summarize a study undertaken by PAPACO
on the topic,
and that you can download once again from
the website papaco.org.
Let's now turn to Paul who will explain it
all to us.
The appearance of private protected areas
demonstrates an important change
in strategies for organizing conservation.
Through them, the number of protected areas
have generally diversified and cautiously
increased.
This type of protected area
is much more widespread in English-speaking
countries,
than it is in French-speaking countries.
For IUCN, private governance includes all
governance
that is not undertaken by governments,
not by indigenous people, and not by community
groups,
Private governance is also governance
that isn't shared between these different
actors.
Governance of private protected areas can
therefore include
property and management by individuals
or groups of individuals,
by NGOs,
by companies, by existing commercial companies,
or by companies created by groups of private
owners
in order to manage the private protected areas
together.
It could also be done by owners of protected
areas who manage them to make profit,
for example ecotourism companies.
It could be done by research entities, such
as universities,
or a fieldwork department etc.
And finally, it could be done by religious
entities;
it is rare, but it happens.
We have said it before, the history of conservation
in Africa
has been one of progressive expansion
towards new actors, and so to more than just
the state.
Even though they were never really absent
from protected areas,
for example, they managed hotel establishments
in the parks,
these private actors were not really in a
governance position
up until recently.
The decay of these infrastructures in the
private areas of the state,
the drop in the number of visitors,
the unavailability of public financial resources
for the renewal of equipment, the pressure
from sponsors, etc.
have caused public officials
to call on the private sector more and more.
This has had mitigated results for some of
the African countries,
and there is a high dependence on the quality
of the governance set up.
These private sector companies are often considered
to be more able
to respond to urgent situations quickly due
to their ability to mobilize funds.
In reality, when possible, the acquisition
of a territory
dedicated to conservation, by a private actor,
normally leads to private governance being
implemented.
However, the situation is not as simple on
the ground.
The responsibility that results from having
a private status
is rarely maintained solely by the owners
of the state-controlled protected areas.
Property and fauna have differing statuses
in many French-speaking countries,
which is why it is hard to identify the type
of governance.
This means a strictly private governance is
hard to recognize.
Reality strangely imposes a shared governance
formula
with the state or with local communities
and it could just be to secure
the investments made.
We particularly find examples of private governance
in the strict sense
in English-speaking Africa, like in Kenya
for example.
Indeed, in Kenya, many conservancies.
have private owners
which can bring many problems
especially in terms of handing over,
over time
Let's have a look at the example of Lewa,
which is a conservancy,
nestled at the bottom of Mount Kenya.
An essential quality that
private actors possess
involves their expertise
and their ability
to mobilize significant financial means quickly.
In fact, these means probably prompted them
to be interested in protected areas being set up.
because profitability is sometimes important.
Investing in protected areas
equates
with an additional motivation.
The political and financial context
in the end of the 20th century
goes hand in hand with a trend
for the private sector
to be increasingly interested in African protected areas.
The private sector's interest
in conservation
provokes legitimate questions about the conditions,
the amount of and the type of participation.
Is it a strategy
to involve the private sector
or should we start talking
about the privatization
of protected areas?
The state could consider
surrendering public land
to private entities,
especially in the form of long leases.
The emblematic cases
most often involve classified land.
Examples of these can be noticed
nearly everywhere in Africa,
like in Senegal for example,
in the classified forests Bandia or Fathala.
Be careful though as these territories
are managed more like zoos
where animals with diverse origins
are brought together
and it is therefore ex situ conservation.
And so, they are not really
protected areas.
Some conceded hunting zones
in classified forests
that are managed sustainably
by private entities
and that match the description
of a protected area,
would be classified in that category.
This type of plot,
when it is managed optimally,
can however have a serious negative impact on the local population, for example.
Ouaba lives in Naboandaga,
a waterfront village
in the east of Burkina Faso,
in the Singou Wildlife Reserve
that covers an area
of nearly 500,000 acres.
Since it was created in 1955,
access to the park
is subject to restrictive rules
for the local population.
With time, new boundaries
have been put in place
which further reduce the residents' access
to the resources.
Here, we are at the boundary of the park.
Our fields were on the other side before.
The néré and shea trees, amongst others,
are also in there.
Our fields were in there, so it was like we
had lost our fields.
My husband, who has livestock, can no longer
bring his animals here either.
If animals enter the park, they are seized.
He doesn't have anywhere for them to graze
anymore
and we have far fewer livestock too.
These are also cases
where the state's strategy of involving private
entities
involves asking them to take over a private
area from the state.
For example, that is the case with Fazao park
in Togo,
which is entrusted to a private Swiss foundation.
It also happened in Central Africa, where
certain parks in DRC,
like Garamba or Virunga,
which are also entrusted to be managed by
certain NGOs.
The results are proportionate
with the level of investments from these partners
and these investments usually vary from one
site to another.
At the other extreme, it can be regarded as
an abandonment or a total transfer
of land rights by the state and the communities,
which results in the complete privatization
of the land.
And yet, land issues turn out to be a particularly
sensitive topic,
especially in the event they are occupied
in the very long term,
which is inkeeping with the spirit of conservation.
Furthermore, in the spirit of legislation,
in Senegal or Kenya for example, fauna still
belongs to the state.
Like we have already said,
examples of this type of governance are quite
rare in French-speaking Africa,
due to the current law.
In any case, when they are governed by private
entities,
the territorial extension of protected areas
is generally quite limited
and they are not always governed very well.
You should know that private governance is
developing unequally in Africa.
It is possible to find good examples of NGOs,
companies and individuals,
who are genuinely investing in conservation,
just as it is possible to find bad examples
of it
with individuals with no principles, who loot
public resources
under the guise of conservation.
Of course, it all depends on the quality of
the governance system
and on the other actors' abilities -- especially
the state's--
to ensure that the private actors are not
free to make all the decisions.
Some of the decisions could be at the expense
of conservation.
We need to remember not to criticize the model,
because some individuals misrepresent it,
but let's try to promote good practice.
Consider the protected areas governed privately
that you know of
and think about the promotor's motivation
and how that finally influences the results
for conservation.
There we go, that's the end of this lesson.
The next episode will be on protected areas
governed by communities.
Have an excellent day.