Welcome to today's lesson
about governance by local communities.
It's a type of governance that has enjoyed
a definite interest
throughout the whole of Africa for at least
the last 30 years.
Of course, a good way to find out more would
be to have a look at
our now familiar guidelines on the governance
of protected areas,
edited by the World Commission.
In particular, take a look at the end of chapter
three,
which focuses specifically on different forms
of governance,
including community governance.
To complement this reading, it could also
be useful
to consult the report of a study carried out
by PAPACO
on community protected areas in West Africa,
and the 25th edition of the NAPA letters,
which has a short introduction about them.
Let's now see with Paul, the context for the
increase in the number
of community protected areas in Africa.
The difficulties met by states to extend protected
areas governed by the government
has offered many opportunities
for community protected areas to develop.
It's in fact a process that is supported
by a context of taking responsibility for
local issues;
a process that is strengthened itself by decentralization
policies
that involved some of environmental fields,
including the management of natural resources.
Community protected areas
represent a recent and interesting form of
governance
due to the hopes for positive responses
to the various shortages discovered
by the state protected areas that were already
in place.
The recent willingness of the African states
to concede their powers to local collectivities
has been the first stage
in the decentralization in terms of conservation.
These collectivities have sometimes benefited
from it
in order to create local protected areas,
just as the law gave them the possibility
to do.
The community protected areas,
which are the result of a process of decentralization,
are roughly the following:
the governance system is controlled by the
local communities;
the legal status is recognized,
and of course, it's within a well defined
space.
Also, the management objectives prioritize
conservation,
and the recognized usage rights are to the
advantage of the people.
Of course, the community protected areas can
be terrestrial.
That's the case, for example, of community
natural reserves
which were established in Senegal.
But these protected areas can also be aquatic.
That's the case with marine community protected
areas.
Or land and water can be combined:
That's the case of the famous marine protected
area of Bamboung,
in the Saloum Delta.
So, let's have a look at the special case
of this Bamboung reserve,
which causes quite a stir in Senegal.
Its manager will tell us a bit more about
it.
Yes, the community marine protected area of
Bamboung
is the first marine area created in Senegal
by the people.
These populations managed these lands for
a long time,
before there was a presidential decree.
And now, the arrival of the decree has enabled
populations
to have a collective conscience.
They also knew about the commitments that
the state of Senegal have made,
and that have empowered them in their way
of managing the area.
Now a collective conscience was born from
this,
and the behaviours
that really did not coincide at all
with managing the environment well
were forbidden by the people themselves.
And that is thanks to management rules
being applied and implemented,
rules which were pre-established by the people
themselves,
and which were adopted by state authority.
So that enabled the populations
to integrate the whole of the 14 outlying
villages
of the community marine protected area of
Bamboung.
This was through village meetings, where their
representatives were designated.
These representatives are currently in what
we call a management committee.
And this management committee is comprised
of all of the delegates
from the 14 outlying villages, and there is
an executive committee
with its functional commissions.
This has enabled them to take a big step forward
and progress towards conservation.
Regarding protected areas, local populations,
who were previously considered
to be predators or destroyers of what conservation
has already achieved,
have progressively changed their attitude
after being faced with a shortage
of easily accessible natural resources.
Due to the impulsiveness of motivated groups,
the initiative of creating community protected
areas came about.
This brought the advantage of producing a
significant increase
in land dedicated to conservation.
We are not lacking in examples to demonstrate
this change,
and as Paul has just told us,
it is a wonderful source for extra protected
areas, in spaces
that the state could not have or would not
have wanted to manage anyway.
Let's look at an example in the south of Benin.
We have noticed that, at the regional level,
and in the Mono Delta, there are no protected
areas.
Loss of habitat and poaching are the biggest
threats.
For their subsistence, local communities depend
on the nature that surrounds them.
Consequently, they are the key to successfully
preserving nature.
My name is Dhossou Alain,
I am the coordinator for the NGO Africa Mobile
Nature.
Here, we are in Gogohondji village,
located in the commune of Houéyogbé, in
the Doutou county.
It's a waterside village by the Toho lake,
where a community reserve is in the process
of being formed.
We are pleased to welcome you to our village.
We will show you around the reserve that is
being created.
It is a reserve rich in biodiversity.
There are many species, including the sitatunga,
crocodiles, boas, turtles, and other aquatic
animals...
We started, for example, raising awareness
after we noticed that poaching was placing
a burden on the animals.
We are starting to grow closer to the hunters
and we have started to identify them by where
they live.
And we have started to have discussions with
them,
and we have grown closer to the authorities,
to certain authorities
that are closer to the reserve
and that will be able to intervene in the
zone anyway.
Since we intervened here, we have really noticed
that, these days, the poaching rate has decreased.
There are still numerous constraints though:
the small size of each community protected
area
considered individually, insufficient coordination,
networks that need to be created,
technical abilities that need strengthening,
changes in objectives that need to be monitored,
a valuation that needs to be set up, etc.
This governance model is in the process of
being developed,
and it will probably continue to evolve.
The positive aspect is it enables certain
cultural practices,
which are positive for conservation, to be
valued,
as we will see in a later sequence of this
lesson,
which will mainly be about culture.
A good place to demonstrate this is the Bissagos
Islands in Guinea-Bissau.
Augusta Henriques from the NGO Tiniguena will
explain it to us.
The Urok community area possesses essential
characteristics
regarding community.
Cultural inclusion:
Management rules are inspired of traditional
management rules.
And within traditional management, women have
a role
in all the stages of exploiting strategic
resources,
for example, shells for food security.
We cannot be efficient when managing resources
if women are not included.
So it isn't so much a question of equal rights,
but more a question of efficiency.
It has to be said, thanks to the impulse from
collectivities or local communities
more and more community protected areas
are being set up
with different aspects depending on the country,
depending on the laws in place and depending
on the habits.
But we also need to specify that decentralization
does not explain everything.
With regards to this, the marine space very
rarely has concessions made for it
by the state.
That is particularly the case in Senegal.
It has however not stopped community initiatives
to spring up
for conservation in the marine field
with the support of state technical services.
There's a nice story told to us from Senegal.
That's the end of the lesson.
The next episode will be
about shared governance of protected areas.
Have an excellent day.