Welcome to this class.
Today we will talk about shared governance
of protected areas,
which concerns a type of governance in which
many actors share
the responsability of the land.
For further information, once again, please
refer
to the World Commission on Protected Areas
guidelines.
In particular, chapter 3 shows different possible
patterns
of shared governance, and provides interesting
case studies.
Also please refer to the 88th edition of the
NAPA letters,
which summarizes a study
that we have conducted in Africa on the matter
very recently,
and that you can download, as usual on papaco.org.
It is important to stress that shared governance
cannot be decreed:
no convention or rule enforces it,
however some situations can obviously favour
it.
Shared governance relies on a few principles,
for example, a necessary equity
between the parties involved in decision-making.
Paul will explain that to us.
The equity principle is essential for shared
governance to develop,
but it remains difficult to respect,
because governance in itself is based on relationships
between actors that do not perform the same
functions
although their functions may be complementary.
The existence of relationships suggests mutual
trust,
which needs to be built and maintained over
the long term
between the actors who end up being forced
partners.
A big part of the problem in the setting up
of shared governance actually lies at that
level.
We will discuss equity in detail, especially
its different types,
in module seven.
We have observed in the previous sequences,
which were about different types of governance,
that the different parties involved played
different roles.
Three roles are crucial here.
First, there's authority, which is generally
enforced by the State.
The State ensures that commitments are kept.
Decentralization policies in Africa have strongly
reduced this role
to the benefit of other kinds of stakeholders,
as we have observed with community governance,
in the previous sequence.
Their second role involves mediation,
which is no individual stakeholder's prerogative.
Yet, communities that claim
they have unextinguished rights on some lands
devoted to conservation
play a crucial part in the process that leads
to establishing
a lasting agreement.
The last role is that of participation;
private stakeholders participating in the
governance of protected areas.
The financial resources, the private sector's
technical skills
give them the ability to intervene.
This must however be regulated by a legitimate
authority,
and benefit from intercommunity mediation.
To put it simply, very simply, there are two
major types
within this shared governance,
that represent a bigger or lesser involvement
in the collaboration between the different
parties,
once again, a continuum.
Generally, there are two scenarios.
In the first situation, where collaborative
management is used,
the State and the communities are bound
through a brief
or a management contract.
The communities, in this case, are responsible
for planning activities and for implementing
them.
However, annually,
they are to produce a report
that they must share with all the other actors.
Besides, still in the same scenario,
it is the communities that decide how to manage
the resources
extracted from the protected area,
which means that they are also expected to
inform the other partners
of how the resources, originating from the
protected area,
are being managed.
In the second situation, we talk about joint
management.
Here, the state and communities are not bound
by a contract or a brief.
But there is a statutory authority that is
accepted and acknowledged by all,
through which the stakeholders will be able
to plan
and implement activities.
And they will also specify, through this meeting,
each actor's role in implementing activities.
It is also during this statutory meeting
that the stakeholders will decide
how to share the profits from the protected
area.
Shared governance thus comes out as an exercise
based on equilibrium,
and in most protected areas where they have
attempted
to implement shared governance
difficulties have come up,
which took time to solve.
The transfer of responsibility thus remains
a thorny subject.
Let's listen to Arsène, who will share
a good example from Burkina Faso.
To illustrate the aforementioned concept of
shared governance,
we can use the example
of the Mare aux Hippopotames Biosphere Reserve,
located at about 60km
from Bobo, in Burkina Faso.
It is a special Ramsar site
because of the diversity of its flora and
its fauna
but also because because of the fact that
many of its species are endangered.
Fishing seems to be the only activity currently
authorized
within that reserve, and it is an important
activity,
in terms of food security and income that
benefits the communities.
Regarding the actors that are involved in
this initiative,
two are identifiable.
First, the State, through OFINAP,
which is the National Office of Protected
Areas;
it's the national body in charge of the implementation
of territorial policies
regarding protected areas.
But on the other hand, we also have the AGEREF,
which is the Intervillage Association
for the Management of Natural Resources and
Fauna.
It is comprised of communities from ten villages
bordering the reserve.
The relationship between these two stakeholders
is much more like a joined management system.
Indeed, the State, through OFINAP, sends representatives
to the association's general assemblies,
during which the future directions,
in terms of protected areas management are
defined.
Now, to take on the matter of the benefits
for the communities
from their involvement with managing and governing
this protected area,
there are two things that stand out.
The benefits can appear at an institutional
level.
Thus, currently, AGEREF is involved with the
protected area's
management and governance dynamics.
It is therefore a good example of shared governance.
Even more than that, we hope, given the current
dynamics,
if there was a concession, that AGEREF could
be the first stakeholder
to step up to insure the good management
of this natural resource.
Benefits are also identified by and listed
under
their socio-economical aspect.
Indeed, we can already notice that many jobs
have been created
which is linked to the presence of this biosphere
reserve.
They include, among others, eco-guards who
protected the villages,
tourist guides and camp managers.
All of these are jobs are created
in the communities that live on the fringes
of that reserve.
Another point relative to socio-economical
development
is the generation of additional income in
favor of the communities.
Indeed, these earnings originate from the
ecotourism activity,
through, notably, an entrance fee to the reserve,
an increase in the value of non-timber forest
products,
an increase in the value of fishing products.
So all these activities revolving around ecotourism
enable income to be generated, which is redistributed
according to an allocation formula
between the various stakeholders involved
in the initiative.
We will now discuss the problems met by the
association.
They appear here on many levels too.
First, we can bring up the association's limited
power,
or ecoguards' struggle when faced with poachers.
Indeed, arresting poachers is the State's
forestry services' prerogative,
which, by nature, may reduce, sometimes,
the association's ability to be effective
in its efforts to fight against poaching.
Another challenge that exists
and that deserves a deeper thought process
in order to solve it,
is, oftentimes, the tense relationship between
the association's tech teams
and some members of the communities, who sometimes
express very important needs
in terms of exploiting natural resources,
which often do not allow for those resources
to last.
It is therefore necessary to keep thinking
about those matters of conservation
so that these initiatives take into account,
just as much,
the preservation of these resources,
while allowing the neighboring communities
to live from these resources next to their
territory.
Finally, we can bring up a point regarding
the fact
that, currently, the AGEREF has no official
document
that underpins its involvement
in the management and governance of this protected
area.
We hope that, with the concession, which,
when it is implemented,
will allow the creation of a document which
could be signed
by the many stakeholders,
a document in which each party's obligations
would be specified.
Such a document would enable, indeed, a better
management
of the association's intervention in the biosphere's
reserve.
Shared governance remains a constant objective,
because its conquest is also permanent,
any asset remains fragile
because of interests prone to evolving.
This is why the stakeholders must keep their
dialogue systems efficient,
they must function according to each party's
interest,
and with, always, in mind
the preservation of what we have gained from
conservation.
It is a real challenge, because it demands
habit-breaking,
for reticence, incomprehension and fears to
be overcome.
However, sharing governance is a vital way
to help protected areas to evolve
towards fairer, more sustainable mechanics,
that guarantee more solid results in the long
term.
Yet we know that it will be hard, especially
for certain State structures
to go beyond their own interest,
in order to be open to encouraging prospects,
but that are often off-putting for people
unprepared for this kind of work.
Another aspect to consider is the cost of
implementing
such a governance system.
It can sometimes be very expensive,
in terms of effort to gather a panel of stakeholders
to make decisions,
and, in the end, this will turn out to be
crippling.
Because even if shared governance can seem
desirable,
it is not always possible everywhere, or at
any given time.
There, I couldn't have said it better.
Thank you Paul for all these elements.
This is the end of the class, in the next
episode,
we will talk about the Nagoya Protocol and
we will find another Paul.
Have an excellent day.
Partnership between André Hoffmann, Ecole
Polythechnique Fédérale de Lausanne,
IUCN (France-IUCN partnership)
This MOOC is an academic collaboration between
the following institutions:
Produced through the RESCIF framework
and from the EPFL MOOCS for Africa initiative.