Hello and welcome everyone!
Today's lesson is dedicated to the Nagoya
Protocol
on access to genetic resources
and the fair and equitable sharing of benefits
arising from their utilization
in relation to the Convention on Biological
Diversity.
We will go over: an introduction to the protocol,
the importance of genetic resources,
access to and sharing of benefits,
which are called ABS in English,
the benefits and the scope of the protocol,
the mechanics and the link between ABS and
protected areas.
You can consult the website of the Convention
on Biological Diversity
for more detail on the subject.
What is the Nagoya Protocol?
It is an international treaty, which follows
on from and affirms
the Convention on Biological Diversity,
notably, one of its three objectives:
the fair and equitable sharing of benefits
arising out of the utilization of genetic
resources.
It is an historic agreement
on the international governance of biodiversity,
relevant to different commercial and non-commercial
sectors,
dealing with genetic resources.
It is based on the fundamental principles
of prior informed consent
and mutually agreed terms
conferred by the Convention on Biological
Diversity.
This came into force on 12 October 2014,
after the ratification of the protocol by
12 countries.
Why the Nagoya Protocol is important:
it provides a greater legal certainty
and more transparency for providers
and users of genetic resources.
It helps to ensure benefit-sharing,
particularly when genetic resources leave
the supplying country.
It establishes conditions for access to genetic
resources
that are more predictable.
What are genetic resources?
All living organisms: plants, animals, and
microbes
are carriers of genetic material which could
be useful to humans.
These resources can originate from wildlife
and domesticated animals,
and wild and cultivated plants.
You can find them in environments where they
flourish naturally,
that's an in-situ case,
in collections of human origin,
it's an ex-situ case,
for example: botanical gardens, gene banks,
or seed pools
or collections of microbial culture.
The importance of genetic resources.
Genetic resources are important
because they represent a crucial source of
information
to better understand the natural world.
They can be used
to develop products and services for human
use.
The access mode to genetic resources
and sharing of benefits, arising from their
usage
can create incentives for conservation
and sustainable utilization of biodiversity,
the creation of a fairer and more equitable
economy.
Access and benefit sharing:
it is done in a way that is possible
to give access to genetic resources.
It is also done in a way
that the benefits arising from the utilization
of genetic resources
can be shared between people and countries
using the resources,
called "users",
and between the people and countries, which
make them available,
called "providers".
The benefit of the Nagoya Protocol:
it encourages the furthering of research on
genetic research
which could lead to new discoveries.
It offers incentives to preserve and use
genetic resources in a sustainable way.
It increases the contribution of biodiversity
to human well-being and development.
The scope and central aspects of the Nagoya
Protocol:
it applies to genetic resources,
to traditional knowledge associated with genetic
resources,
and benefits arising from their utilization.
Its central aspects are:
access, benefit-sharing,
compliance, and traditional knowledge.
The mechanics:
the ABS is based on prior informed consent
given by a provider to a user.
Negotiations between the parties regarding
development,
and mutually agreed terms,
with the aim of ensuring fair and equitable
sharing
of genetic resources
and its associated benefits.
This makes reference to the way access to
genetic resources is obtained
and the way the users and providers come to
an agreement
on sharing benefits arising from their utilization.
Users wish to have access to genetic resources
for the purposes of:
firstly, scientific research, for example
taxonomy,
secondly, development of commercial products,
for example medication.
The providers of genetic resources allow access
in exchange for an equitable share
of the benefits arising from their utilization.
The link between protected areas and ABS:
protected areas and ABS have the common aim
of biodiversity conservation.
The Nagoya Protocol is legally binding,
therefore, it is a strong opportunity for
protected areas.
Protected areas can benefit from research
and bioprospection.
Protected areas are the hub,
which connects community, conservation,
and traditional use of biodiversity.
ABS can contribute to conservation and sustainable
use.
Protected areas and ABS are two frameworks
that address the common challenges of governance.
The benefits arising from the utilization
of genetic resources
can be monetary,
when research and development lead
to the commercialization of a product,
an example being the royalties or state payments,
non monetary, for example, technology transfer,
skill improvement in terms of research.
ABS can contribute to sustainable development
and the struggle against poverty.
An information kit in relation to access to
and sharing of benefits
has been developed to raise public awareness.
This kit is available on the website
of the Convention on Biological Diversity.
This is the end of this lesson.
The next episode will be an overview of the
governance of protected areas.
Meanwhile, have a good day!