Governance is the process of decision-making
relating to managing protected areas,
and not the actions of management themselves.
It concerns therefore who makes the decisions
and how they are taken.
This is a fundamental notion to understand
the strengths and weaknesses of protected
areas.
we can roughly identify four types of governance.
Governance by the government is the most frequent
in Africa,
and this is the case,
where decisions are made by the government,
whether at ministry level,
or by an independent public body or a decentralized
department.
In general, the state owns the area
and it can choose to consult the other stakeholders
when managing these protected areas, but ultimately,
it is always the state
who makes the decisions and takes responsibility
for them.
Shared governance is when decision-making
involves several parties,
who all have responsibility for the final
decision.
This sharing of responsibilities can go as
far as complete delegation
of protected area management by the state
to a third party,
such as a private entity, an NGO or a community.
But, most often, the state is reticent to
delegate authority,
even when it does not succeed in exercising
that authority,
and it continues to be the dominant party
involved.
Private governance concerns the areas either
controlled by,
or whose property is maintained, by an individual,
an NGO or a company
whether it is for the purposes of profit or
not.
In this case, the authority to manage protected
areas and for their resources
goes back to the owner who determines management
goals,
develops plans and retains control over decisions
as long as they respect relevant legislation.
This is still a fairly rare form of governance
in Africa,
but it is now becoming more common.
Finally, governance by communities concerns
protected areas
where local residents are responsible for
management,
by means of various institutions,
or by formal or informal customary rules.
In such a case, the area is under the control
of the local community,
who is responsible for reaching goals,
even if the protected area is not recognized
in a legal document.
By allowing the locals to be users
and custodians of their own resources,
we hope to generate more effective support
for conservation of protected areas.
No matter who is in charge of governing the
protected area,
whether he is alone or he shares his mission
with others,
governance is based on the notion of responsibility.
Too few of the decision-makers in protected
areas in Africa
are accountable for the decisions that they
make
and on the way that they make them,
and this greatly weakens
management results on the field.
Evolving towards better governance of the
conservation sector requires
more responsibility and transparency by the
relevant actors.
So let's now start the test
on this module.