Hello and welcome!
My name is Phil Willmott.
I will be guiding you through the world of
x-ray science and its applications in this
introductory course “Synchrotrons and x-ray
free-electron lasers - techniques and applications”.
I am a physicist by training, but have been
exposed to many other disciplines both over
the last decade-and-a-half working at synchrotrons,
but also earlier in my academic career.
Presently, in addition to being an adjunct
professor at the University of Zurich, I am
responsible for running the Materials Science
beamline at the Swiss Light Source at the
Paul Scherrer Institute in Switzerland.
This course is partly based on my introductory
textbook on synchrotron radiation, which is
available through most online bookstores,
or the publisher’s website, John Wiley and
Sons, for those who would like to review many
of the concepts presented here at their own
leisure, using the more traditional medium
of the written page, or read deeper into aspects
of particular interest.
In this first, introductory, week, we will
cover the following topics.
After a brief description of who might be
users of synchrotron radiation (including
glimpses into some applications), the range
of wavelengths (or, alternatively, photon
energies) typically produced by synchrotron
facilities within the context of length and
energy scales in the material world will be
outlined.
Lastly, a short overview follows of synchrotron
and XFEL machines and what makes them so desirable.
In this video a cartoon of the generation
of synchrotron light is shown and will be
described in detail later in the course.
Stated simply, synchrotrons provide intense
sources of electromagnetic radiation over
large ranges of wavelengths, typically spanning
values marginally shorter than that of visible
light (i.e., beginning at approximately 100
nm in the so-called vacuum ultraviolet regime)
to hard x-rays with wavelengths that are one
to two orders of magnitude shorter than typical
chemical bond lengths.
This brilliant source of tunable radiation
is used in a myriad of ways to investigate
manifold properties of innumerable sample
types!
Shown here are just some recent examples spanning
disciplines as varied as art history to magnetic
nanostructures.
In this course I will use the terms “light”
and “electromagnetic radiation” interchangeably
and synonymously to cover the range of wavelengths
covered by synchrotron facilities that spans
approximately five orders of magnitude.
Who might be interested in using synchrotron
radiation?
Before about two to three decades ago, synchrotron
science was almost exclusively the province
of physicists and physical chemists.
In contrast, modern-day synchrotron users
come from all walks of scientific and academic
life, from art history, palaeontology, and
cultural ethnology, to molecular biology,
materials science, and high-tech industry,
as shown clearly in this pie chart.
To accommodate this growing demand, there
are now several tens of synchrotrons around
the world, of which some of the more prominent
examples are shown here in yellow; along with
the six free-electron lasers operating in
the UV or x-ray regime presently either under
construction or in operation, shown here in
red.
The impact of x-rays and synchrotron light
on society is reflected in the number of Nobel
prizes that have been awarded in this field.
Since the first Nobel prize in physics was
awarded in 1901 to Wilhelm Röntgen for his
discovery of x-rays, 21 prizes have been awarded
for x-ray science.
Of these, nine have been in the field of molecular
biology,
of which the four most recent (awarded in
2003, 2006, 2009, and 2012, all for chemistry)
used synchrotron light as a primary tool in
their investigations, a fact which I believe
reflects the emergence of synchrotrons in
the last two decades as one of the primary
reach tools in the natural sciences and beyond.
From this, it should be clear that synchrotron
science represents one of the premier examples
of interdisciplinary research.
It is my belief that this diversity of potential
applications would be further expanded if
(a) the power of synchrotron science were
more effectively disseminated to the wider
community; and (b) those contemplating using
synchrotron light were not so intimidated
by the perceived complexity of this powerful
tool.
One of the primary aims of this course is
to tackle both of these obstacles.
Let us return to the last of the examples
shown in the previous video – the “Nobel
trilogy of life”.
How does nature construct a living thing from
simple chemical components?
For example, how does a human emerge nine
months after the unique mixing of its parents’
genetic material contained in a single fertilized
egg?
When I was a child, these questions were only
just beginning to be answered.
Indeed, just five months before my own birth,
the Nobel committee announced that the 1962
prize for physiology or medicine would be
awarded to James Watson, Francis Crick, and
Maurice Wilkins for their elucidation of the
structure of deoxyribosenucleic acid (DNA)
and (quoting from the Nobel committee’s
announcement) “its significance for information
transfer in living material”.
It was Rosalind Franklin’s famous x-ray
“photograph 51” of DNA crystal diffraction
which provided the final clue to the structure.
Franklin would sadly die of ovarian cancer
before the Nobel prize was awarded.
DNA resides permanently within the nucleus
of a living cell.
How then, is its information conveyed
to the rest of the cell and elsewhere in the
organism; how is new living material subsequently
synthesized; and how do initial (“stem”)
cells differentiate into specialized cells
as diverse as ganglions, muscle cells, or
skin?
Major steps towards answering these questions
were made in research that would result in
Nobel prizes in chemistry in 2006 and 2009.
The first step in carrying out the commands
encoded in DNA is its transcription into so-called
messenger-RNA, which then leaves the confines
of the nucleus to the protein-producing parts
of the cell.
How mRNA is synthesized and carries the genetic
information with high fidelity, via a very
special macromolecule called RNA-polymerase,
was reported by Roger Kornberg and co-workers
in 2001, for which he received the 2006 Nobel
prize in chemistry.
The following step, that of protein synthesis,
uses the blueprint of the messenger RNA, plus
raw material in the form of amino acids attached
to small transfer-RNA (tRNA) molecules in
a chemical factory called the ribosome.
The detailed description of the mechanisms
by which this highly complex biomolecular
process occurs won Ada Yonath, Thomas Steitz,
and Venkatraman Ramakrishnan the Nobel prize
in chemistry in 2009.
This course is not about molecular biology.
It is, however, concerned with diverse aspects
of a tool now considered indispensible to
molecular biologists – synchrotron radiation.
The thematic link between the above works
is that of structure – atomic structure
– and its implicitly inherent importance
in determining biomolecular activity.
X-rays and, in recent years synchrotron radiation,
have played a central role in this enterprise.
The relevance of these studies goes well beyond
that of pure academic understanding – the
detailed description of the DNA transcription
process, as well as a knowledge of the biochemical
function of the ribosome, are already having
a huge impact on the design of novel antibiotic
substances and other drugs, plus a deeper
understanding of how some cancers arise and
how they might be tackled.
The year that Yonath, Ramakrishnan, and Steitz
were awarded their Nobel prize (2009) also
saw first light at the first hard x-ray free-electron
laser, the Linear Coherent Light Source (or
LCLS) at the SLAC facility in Stanford, California.
The first report of an entirely new biological
structure, cathepsin B, determined using the
LCLS was reported a little over three years
later.
XFELs provide x-ray beams with unique properties
regarding pulse duration, peak pulse intensity,
and beam cross-section.
Using a technique coined “diffraction-before-destruction”,
crystals with sizes orders of magnitude smaller
in volume than hitherto possible can now be
investigated.
The application of this technique at XFELs
represents a new paradigm shift in this field
of research, and is indicative of how x-ray
science continues to develop unabated over
100 years since its inception.
Almost immediately since their discovery at
the end of the 19th century, x-rays have played
a central scientific and technological role
in society.
Barely two weeks after their discovery, Dr
Otto Walkhoff of Braunschweig undertook the
first dental radiograms of his own jaw.
The first exposure was for 25 minutes and
resulted in a very blurred image, due mainly
to the fanlike nature and large size of the
source of x-rays.
Modern radiograms expose the patient for durations
typically well under a second and can distinguish
features well under a millimeter in size.
Radiography is today one of the primary diagnostic
tools available to medicine and dentistry.
Other common uses of x-rays are in security,
such as at airports (we are all familiar with
this, sometimes frustratingly!!); in the aeronautical
industry to investigate fatigue and weathering
of components such as turbine blades; and
in the pharmaceutical industry, to characterize
drugs for their atomic structure, functionality,
and purity.
So why are x-rays so used?
We discuss this in the next video.