In this second video of the first week of
this course, we consider why are x-rays so
ubiquitous in society and in scientific endeavours.
Before we answer this, a distinction should
be made between x-rays of different energy
ranges, as their interactions with matter
vary strongly accordingly.
Typically, one speaks of soft, tender, and
hard x-rays.
Soft x-rays begin after the visible and ultraviolet
regime and cover a wavelength range of approximately
100 nm down to 0.6 nm; hard x-rays have wavelengths
shorter than 0.3 nm.
Perhaps counterintuitively, it is
soft x-rays that in general interact much
more strongly with matter than do hard x-rays,
and it is this property which has resulted
in their distinction.
Because the transition between soft and hard
x-rays is not abrupt and is anyway somewhat
arbitrary, depending strongly on the material
being irradiated, the concept of tender x-rays
was introduced to bridge these two regimes.
Normally, however, one characterizes x-rays
by their photon energy E rather than their
wavelength λ.
A photon is the indivisible quantum unit of
light characterized by the light’s wavelength
or frequency, and was first postulated by
Albert Einstein in 1905.
The relationship between energy and wavelength
is given by the Planck-Einstein relation E
= hc/λ, where h is Planck’s constant = 6.63
x 10-34 J.s and c is the speed of light in
vacuum = 2.9979 x 10^8 m/s.
See the supplementary table for a list of
the physical constants most commonly used
in this course.
Inserting these into the equation, one sees
that even for the hardest (that is, the most
energetic) x-rays used in synchrotron science
(which have wavelengths of the order of a
picometer), photon energies are of the order
of a tenth of a thousandth of a billionth
of a Joule (i.e., 10-13 J).
The Joule is therefore obviously not a convenient
energy unit to use when discussing x-ray photon
energies - I would never tell my doctor, for
example, that I weigh 4.27 x 10-29 solar masses.
Instead, we use the electronvolt.
This is the gain in kinetic energy of an electron
when it is accelerated across an electric
potential of 1 Volt and is equal to 1.6022
x 10-19 Joules.
Using this unit of energy, one can quickly
derive this simple practical relationship
between photon energy expressed in electron
volts and wavelength expressed in nanometers,
given by E in eV = 1239.84/lambda in nanometers.
Because many x-ray scientists prefer to use
the length unit Angstrom (0.1 of a nanometer
= 10-10 m), we can also re-express the relationship
as E in eV = 12398.4/lambda, where lambda
is now expressed in Angstroms.
So, for example, the photon energy of one-Angstrom
hard x-rays is 12.3984 keV.
We will use this expression many times in
this course, so I recommend you become familiar
with it.
The different x-ray regimes shown earlier
are redrawn here, but now in relationship
to the photon energy.
The vacuum ultraviolet and soft x-rays produced
at synchrotrons begin at 10 to 20 eV and continue
up to approximately 2000 eV.
Hard x-rays conventionally begin at 4 keV,
while the tender regime spans the gap between
2 and 4 keV.
Hard x-rays are used at airports and in medicine
primarily because of their large penetration
depths through matter and changes in these
according to the density of material being
irradiated, as can be seen in this graph – as
a rule of thumb, the lighter the material,
the more transparent it is to x-rays, while
the shorter the x-ray wavelength (or, in other
words, the higher the x-ray energy), the more
penetrating it will be.
It is often said that x-rays are “nondestructive”.
This is true insofar that they allow one to
see the inner structure and composition of
an object without the need to open or slice
it, though on another level, they can most
certainly be harmful, due to chemical processes
that are induced after their absorption.
A useful unit to describe absorption of x-rays
is the Gray (Gy).
One Gray is equal to one Joule of absorbed
radiation energy per kilogram.
A dose of approximately 5 Gy in one exposure
(equivalent to approximately 400 J absorbed
radiation for an adult weighing 80 kg) will
usually result in death within 14 days.
To put this in perspective, the same amount
of deposited energy would warm a cup of tea
up by about 0.5 degrees Celsius; or is equal
to the sunlight absorbed by a sunbather on
a sunny day after approximately half a second…
This remarkable difference in the impact of
the same amount of total absorbed energy is
due to the fact that the x-ray photons directly
channel their energy into the release of otherwise
bound electrons, that can wreak havoc by inducing
chemical reactions, often in a cascade effect,
depending on the details of the absorption
process.
Perhaps the best definition of hard x-rays
is that they have wavelengths comparable to
or shorter than typical distances between
atoms (that is, the bond lengths).
The shortest bond length under normal pressure
is that of the H2 molecule, at 0.74 Angstroms;
while bonds between heavy elements can exceed
3 Angstroms, the wavelength of 4-keV photons.
Shown here is 10-keV x-radiation passing over
carbon-carbon single, double, and triple bonds.
This property of hard x-rays makes them useful
in investigating the atomic structures of
materials, in techniques such as x-ray diffraction.
Lastly, hard x-rays have energies similar
to bonding energies of core electrons in atoms.
In this figure, the four most tightly bound
electron shells are plotted as a function
of Z, the atomic number from Z = 1 (hydrogen)
to Z = 92 (uranium).
The hard x-ray regime can access all elements
with atomic numbers above Z = 20 (the atomic
number of calcium).
This property can be exploited in hard x-ray
spectroscopies and also in crystallography,
as an aid to solving structures from data
recorded at specially chosen photon energies.
What are then the main attributes of soft
x-rays that make them useful tools in investigating
the properties of matter?
The lower photon energy of x-rays means that
they interact primarily with light atoms and
the outer, or valence, electrons of heavier
atoms.
This is exploited to investigate many different
properties of materials such as, for example,
the electronic properties of metals, semiconductors,
and superconductors; the chemical composition
of heterogeneous systems; or the imaging of
magnetic domains down to the nanometer scale.
Summarising this video, we have discussed
the wavelengths and photon energies associated
with ultraviolet radiation, soft, and hard
x-rays, how they interact with matter, and
thereby provided a brief insight into hoe
they might be applied in the natural sciences.
In the next video, we encounter synchrotrons
for the first time - what they look like,
with an overview of their components.
Four simple attributes synchrotrons are introduced
as it is these that make them so popular.
From this, the concept of “brilliance”,
or “brightness” will be introduced as
a figure of merit for the performance of synchrotron
facilities.
A brief summary of the progress in brilliance
over the last 100 years will lead us also
to the two “new kids on the block” in
the world of x-ray science, namely x-ray free-electron
lasers (XFELs) and diffraction-limited storage
rings (DLSRs).