So, what are synchrotrons?
Simply stated, they are very brilliant sources
of light, or electromagnetic radiation.
Although some synchrotrons offer tunable radiation
in the infrared and visible regimes, this
is quite unusual and will not be discussed
further in this course, as, from the near
IR, through the visible, to the near UV range,
conventional lasers tend to dominate *******. As
already mentioned, it is at higher photon
energies, beginning at about 10 to 20 eV,
where synchrotrons come into their own *******, providing
radiation all the way up to approximately
one mega-electronvolt photons.
OK, we now know qualitatively what synchrotrons
provide – very brilliant beams of radiation
– but what actually are synchrotrons?
How do they look like?
Here is a schematic of a synchrotron facility.
To put this into perspective, the larger ring
structure shown here typically has a circumference
of the order of a few hundred meters.
Let us break down the components of a synchrotron,
beginning with a source of electrons, the
so-called electron gun, which may be a heated
metal filament ejecting electrons by thermionic
emission.
These electrons are then accelerated in an
evacuated linear accelerator, or “LINAC”
(it should be noted that, in order that they
are not scattered by air molecules, the electrons
always experience ultrahigh vacuum conditions,
with pressures typically of the order of a
thousandth of a billionth of an atmosphere
or less).
The electrons then enter a so-called booster
ring in which their energy is further ramped
up until they attain the design energy of
the main “storage” ring,
into which they are injected and where they
remain (or are stored, hence the term “storage
ring”) and are used to generate synchrotron
radiation.
The design energies of the electrons in the
storage ring are typically measured in giga-electronvolts,
that is, billions of electronvolts.
At these energies, the electrons are highly
relativistic (that is, their velocities are
exceedingly close to the speed of light),
which, we will see later, has important consequences
on the nature and direction of the electromagnetic
radiation that is produced.
Now, in both the booster ring and the storage
ring, the electrons are required to remain
on a closed path (shown here in blue).
This is achieved using bending magnets, highlighted
here
in red.
As we shall discuss in detail later in the
course, forcing electrons to execute a curved
trajectory causes them to emit electromagnetic
radiation – this is your synchrotron light!
It is perhaps worth repeating here that the
energy of even the most energetic photons
produced at synchrotrons is less than a mega-electronvolt,
three orders of magnitude or more smaller
than the energies of the electrons that produce
them.
In addition, the straight sections between
the bending magnets are used to insert alternating
arrays of north-south, south-north magnet
dipoles, shown here in orange.
These so-called “insertion devices” are
even more brilliant sources of synchrotron
radiation than are the bending magnets.
Tangential to the BMs and IDs are positioned
the beamlines, that use the radiation (normally
x-rays, and shown here as yellow and green
beams) produced by the magnet devices in the
storage ring.
A typical synchrotron might have anything
between 10 and 50 beamlines, depending on
the size of the facility.
For most experiments using x-rays, or indeed
most measurements using any kind of electromagnetic
radiation, four properties are in general
desirable.
The beam should be intense, as monochromatic
as achievable, parallel, and emanate from
as small a source point as possible.
Accordingly, a figure-of-merit called “brilliance”,
or “brightness”, encapsulates these attributes
and is equal to the intensity expressed in
photons per second, divided by the product
of the horizontal and vertical beam divergences;
the source size; and the relative spectral
bandwidth.
The precise definition and units are discussed
later in the course.
As an example, however, it is instructive
to consider the following.
A medical x-ray machine may generate as much
as a kilowatt of x-radiation for radiography,
some two orders of magnitude greater than
that used at all the beamlines together at
a typical third-generation synchrotron facility.
However, when the sources’ sizes, divergences,
and bandwidths are factored in, just a single
beamline at a synchrotron will have a brilliance
some 12 orders of magnitude higher than that
of the medical x-ray machine!
An illustrative experimental example is shown
here of a so-called x-ray powder-diffraction
pattern of calcium phosphate.
The lower pattern in red was recorded over
nearly three hours using a lab-based x-ray
tube source, and has been expanded vertically
by a factor of a thousand.
The upper trace in blue was recorded in five
seconds at the Materials Science beamline
at the Swiss Light Source.
The peak line widths are almost a factor of
two narrower.
A direct comparison in intensity is inappropriate,
as the two patterns were recorded using detectors
based on different operational principles.
Nonetheless, one immediately sees that the
quality of the SR-based measurement is far
superior, which can be directly attributed
to the differences in the sources’ brilliances.
Since the first synchrotron-based experiments
began in the 1950s, the available brilliance,
which until then had more or less stagnated
since shortly after the discovery of x-rays,
increased meteorically by some 13 or 14 orders
of magnitude over less than five decades,
due to the introduction of sophisticated magnet-based
sources, in particular insertion devices called
wigglers, and then undulators, which we shall
consider in detail later in the course.
***** More recently, beginning in 2009 at
the LCLS at the SLAC facility in California,
x-ray free-electron lasers began operation,
while so-called diffraction-limited synchrotrons
(DLSRs) are just beginning to see first light.
***** These remarkable advances in x-ray brilliance
over the last half century can be compared
to the much-vaunted improvements in computer
power, encapsulated in Moore’s law, which
observes a two-fold gain in computer power
approximately every eighteen months.
The same doubling in x-ray brilliance has
occurred on average every ten months during
the last three decades.
X-ray free-electron lasers, or XFELs, are
new sources of x-radiation, with peak brilliances
approximately ten orders of magnitude greater
still than those of modern synchrotrons.
In addition, they produce trains of pulses
with durations between a few femtoseconds
to a few tens of femtoseconds (a femtosecond
is 10-15 of a second, that is, a millionth
of a billionth of a second).
This is over three orders of magnitude shorter
than pulse lengths produced by synchrotrons,
and sufficiently short to follow chemical
reactions as they occur in real time.
Thus XFELs marry the temporal advantages of
femtosecond lasers in the visible and near-visible
regime with the spatial resolution associated
with x-radiation.
The exceedingly high brilliance of XFELs compared
to synchrotrons means that in general, changes
in the approaches to experiments using XFELs
compared to synchrotrons are not incremental
in nature, but rather represent a completely
new paradigm shift.
Synchrotrons and XFELs are thus complementary
to one another and one should not think that
XFELs will replace synchrotron sources.
The architecture of XFELs is also very different
from that of synchrotrons.
A short electron bunch is generated by irradiating
a metallic target with a femtosecond laser
pulse.
This is accelerated in a LINAC and then undergoes
one or more bunch compressions to make the
pulse shorter by approximately a factor of
100.
The shortened electron pulse is then further
accelerated along a long LINAC to several
GeV energy and then enters a long array of
alternating north-south, south-north magnet
dipoles.
As we will discuss later, this magnet array,
called an “undulator”, is essentially
identical to devices also used in the straight
sections of synchrotron storage rings (the
“insertion devices” mentioned earlier
in this video in the context of synchrotron
facilities), apart from the fact that they
are over an order of magnitude longer, typically
several tens of meters long.
For reasons that will become apparent later
in this course, this long magnet array is
required in order to induce a phenomenon known
as self-amplified spontaneous emission, or
SASE.
The result of SASE is that, after exiting
the long undulator magnet array, the electron
bunch has been altered such that it is now
divided into many microbunches, each having
a duration of only a few femtoseconds.
These bunches produce the femtosecond x-radiation
characteristic of XFELs.
The latest development in synchrotron technology
has focussed on improving the brilliance not
by increasing the photon flux, but rather
by reducing the source size and divergence
of the beam.
**** Diffraction-limited storage rings promise
approximately a further two orders of magnitude
increase in brilliance compared to third-generation
synchrotrons **** by gentler steering of the
electrons in the storage ring - in other words,
by using more bending magnets, each magnet
forcing the electrons to bend through a smaller
angle.
This seemingly prosaic change actually has
a significant beneficial impact on the beam
properties, but has only recently become possible
with advances both in computer-controlled
machining and in vacuum technology, which
have allowed the necessary miniaturisation
of components in the storage ring to achieve
this goal.
To summarize the first week of this course,
it should now be apparent why x-rays are such
a useful tool for investigating the material
world, why synchrotrons and XFELs are the
premier examples of such tools, and why synchrotron
science is such an interdisciplinary endeavour.
You should now be comfortable with the concept
of photons, that is, that light can be described
as consisting of indivisible quanta of energy,
the photons, whose energy is inversely proportional
to their wavelength.
According to how these photons interact with
matter, in particular with regards to their
wavelength compared to that of interatomic
distances; and their energy compared to that
of electrons bound to the atomic nuclei, different
x-ray regimes are defined.
Lastly, we have qualitatively described the
anatomy, or architecture of synchrotrons and
XFELs, which will prepare us for that part
of the course in which we discuss machine
physics.
Next week, we explore in detail how x-rays
interact with matter, which will lay the foundations
to understand x-ray techniques used in modern
synchrotron and XFEL science.