Welcome to Week 2 of this introductory course
on synchrotrons and x-ray free-electron lasers!
This week, we will explore the basic features
and physical description of the interaction
of x-rays with matter.
We shall begin by relating cross-sections
and attenuation lengths for a given process
and how one can calculate one from the other.
The only three relevant physical processes
concerning x-ray interactions with matter
are then introduced, of which that of Compton
scattering is only very briefly described,
as we will not consider this further in the
course.
The remainder of this, the first video of
this week, will be concerned with the description
of elastic scattering of x-rays by quasi-free
electrons and the introduction of the concept
of the atomic form factor.
In the second video, refinements of the atomic
form factor are added to account for the fact
that the electrons in a material are generally
bound to the nucleus with well-defined binding
energies.
Just as visible light is bent, or “refracted”,
as it passes from one medium to another, x-rays
are also similarly affected.
How the refractive index in the x-ray regime
is related to the atomic form factor will
be covered in detail.
From this, quantitative predictions can be
made about refraction and reflection of x-rays.
Lastly, absorption effects resulting from
excitation of electrons to unoccupied energy
states, and subsequent relaxation processes
will be discussed.
Just a brief note about the tone of this week
- although it contains some mathematics, none
of this is complex and should be understandable
even for a high-school student, so please
do not feel intimidated by the introduction
this week of some more mathematical expressions.
Let’s now begin by discussing the concept
of cross-sections and attenuation lengths.
Consider a process P (as yet undefined) occurring
when x-rays pass through a block of material
of depth L, containing a number density rho_a
of atoms responsible for this process.
Each atom has a cross-sectional area sigma_P
associated with the process P. Due to this
process, the beam intensity will exponentially
decay as photons are removed or scattered
from the beam as it travels through the medium.
The attenuation length Lambda_P is defined
as being equal to the length the beam has
travelled through the medium before the original
intensity I_0 has been reduced by a factor
equal to the natural logarithm e = 2.718.
The relationship between this and the cross-section
is simply Lambda_P = 1/(sigma_P rho_a).
In order to better understand this, let us
consider the example of a 10-keV x-ray beam
passing through cobalt metal.
From the density of cobalt (8.9 g/cm3) and
its atomic mass (58.933), the atomic number
density can be directly calculated to be 9.09
x 10^10 atoms per cubic micron.
***** The graph on the left of the photoabsorption
attenuation length shows this to be 6.2 microns
at 10 keV.
Using the equation from the previous slide,
we obtain a photoabsorption cross-section
sigma_PA of 1.77 x 10^-12 square microns.
As there are 100 million square Angstroms
per square micron, this equates to 1.774 x
10^-4 square Angstroms.
An even more convenient unit to use is that
of the “barn”, which has an area of 10^-28
square meters, or 10^-8 square Angstroms.
Cobalt therefore has a photoabsorption cross-section
of 1.774 x 10^4 barn.
Incidentally, a barn is approximately equal
to the capture cross-section of uranium nuclei
in fission reactions - the term “barn”
comes from the colloquialism “as big as
a barn door”, as scientists performing wartime
research into uranium fission considered this
to be particularly large target (and therefore
a prime candidate for development of the fission
bomb).
Even more whimsically, there exist (admittedly
rarely used and certainly not mentioned again
in this course) related cross-sectional units,
the “outhouse” (equal to one microbarn),
and the “shed” (one yoctobarn).
So, which processes should we consider when
discussing the interaction of x-rays with
matter?
Nuclear- and pair production only begin to
dominate at photon energies above the highest
presently available at synchrotron facilities
and can be entirely ignored.
This leaves Thomson and Compton scattering,
and photoabsorption.
All these processes involve the electron and
the electron only.
The nuclear core can be entirely disregarded
due to its relatively very large mass (a single
nucleon is some 1800 times heavier than an
electron).
We begin with a brief description of Compton
scattering.
This is a quantum-mechanical effect in which
some of the energy and momentum of an incident
photon is imparted to a free electron, which
thereby receives a change in its momentum.
The energy lost by the inelastically scattered
photon results in a lengthening of the wavelength
and depends on its scattered angle psi and
initial photon energy h-nu_0, given by the
equation shown here.
The cluster of constants h/mc = 0.0243 Angstroms.
The relative energy loss therefore only becomes
significant above a few tens of keV, and for
large angles psi, as can be clearly seen in
the graph to the right
and only begins to dominate above approximately
100 keV.
This threshold energy is related to the rest-mass
energy of an electron, mc^2 = 511 keV for
electrons.
As such, we will no longer consider Compton
scattering in this course, although it shouldn’t
be forgotten when performing high-energy-photon
synchrotron experiments.
Now we have seen that it is the electron which
is the only particle of interest regarding
interaction with x-rays, let us begin by considering
how a free electron responds in the presence
of an electromagnetic field.
For nonrelativistic electron velocities, we
need only consider the electric-field component
of the incoming radiation.
The electron will respond to this, moving
in the opposite direction to the E-field (the
force is equal to MINUS the elementary charge
times the electric-field amplitude).
This causes the electron to reradiate coherently
with the incident beam, with the same phase
and frequency, for reasons we will discuss
later in the course in the beginning of the
section on synchrotron physics.
The intensity of the reradiated or scattered
radiation depends on the polar angle of observation
chi according to cosine-squared chi, shown
here.
Hence an observer viewing along the E-field
vector at chi = 90 degrees will see no scattered
intensity, as the E-field has zero transverse
component in this direction.
Conversely, in the plane perpendicular to
the electric-field direction, scattering is
maximised.
Again, the reason for this spatial distribution
will be made clear when we begin to discuss
synchrotron, or “machine”, physics.
This response of the free electrons to light
is the reason why, among other things, mirrors
reflect, radio antenna transmit, and, importantly,
synchrotrons produce light.
As I just mentioned, the reasons for this
will become clear soon.
This elastic scattering by electrons, that
is, with no loss in photon energy, is referred
to as Thomson scattering.
Although the photon energy remains invariant,
the direction, or momentum, can change.
Let us consider scattering of a photon by
an angle 2-theta
The vector difference between the incident
and scattered photon wavevectors (each of
which have a magnitude equal to k = 2pi/lambda)
is equal to Q, which is referred to as the
scattering vector.
The magnitude of Q is easy to calculate as
follows: Half of Q is simply equal to k sin
theta.
As k equals 2pi/lambda, Q is therefore equal
to 4pi/lambda sin theta.
How strongly incident radiation is scattered
by a free electron is given by the Thomson
scattering length.
This is determined by equating the classical
electrostatic energy of a charge e at a distance
equal to r-zero, the Thomson length, to the
rest-mass energy of the electron, mc-squared.
The Thomson length thus turns out to be equal
to 2.82 x 10^-5 Angstroms, and can be thought
of as the classical radius of an electron.
The cross-section of a free electron is determined
by integrating over all angles of the dipole
radiation, and turns out to be equal to about
2/3 of a barn.
We now progress from the case of a free electron
to scattering from an atom.
We begin by making the dubious assumption
that all the electrons associated with the
atom can respond entirely unhindered by the
fact that they are actually bound to the atom’s
nuclear core.
We first consider the limit of the x-ray wavelength
being significantly larger than the extent
of the electron cloud around the atom.
In this case, all the scattering elements
will scatter coherently (that is, in phase)
because any differences in positions in space
of the different cloud elements is very small
compared to the wavelength.
As there are Z electrons in the cloud, the
scattering cross-section is simply Z^2 sigma_T,
which is independent of wavelength.
So, for example, the low-energy limit of Thomson
scattering in the forward direction, shown
here for barium, is 56-squared, or 3136 times
the cross-section of an individual electron,
which is approximately equal to 2000 barns.
As the photon energy increases and the wavelength
shortens to distances comparable and then
less than the size of the atom, however, scattering
from the different elements dV in the electron
cloud begin to interfere partially destructively,
resulting in a drop-off of the scattering
cross-section and intensity, which follows
approximately an inverse square relationship
with respect to the photon energy.
The gradual crossover from the lower-energy
limit of constant scattering cross-section
to that of one dropping off is at x-ray wavelengths
comparable to the size of the electron cloud,
of the order of 3 Angstrom, equating to an
energy of about 4 keV.
The precise drop-off is given by the atomic
form factor, or atomic scattering factor,
f.
This describes the elastic scattering amplitude
as a function of angle, wavelength, and atom
type.
More accurately, f is normally expressed as
a function of Q or sin theta/lambda, as this
is the appropriate independent variable.
If one performs one experiment at a certain
energy and one observes the scattering at
a certain angle 2-theta, then if the energy
is then, say, increased (lambda decreased),
then the same interference (i.e., phase difference)
between any two scattering elements dV of
the electron cloud will be the same at shallower
angles.
So, for the example shown here for phosphorus,
an atomic form factor of 10 electrons will
be observed at high angles for low energies
and low angles for high energies.
Note also that in the forward-scattering direction,
all the scattering elements in the electron
cloud will scatter in phase, and the amplitude
will be that of the individual electron multiplied
by Z, in other words, the total charge surrounding
the atom.
The intensity, proportional to the square
of the amplitude, thus increases as Z-squared.
The dependence of f on Q (or sin theta/lambda)
can be conveniently expressed as the sum of
four Gaussians plus a constant, and values
for every element for these expressions can
be found in the International Tables for Crystallography.
Summarising our discussion of elastic scattering
so far, we should take home the following:
The electrons respond to the electric-field
component of the incident x-rays and reradiate
as a consequence at the same frequency - the
process is elastic.
At large wavelengths compared to the size
of the atoms scattering is independent of
the photon energy, as the cloud can be approximated
as being a point source.
However, as the wavelength becomes smaller
(photon energy increases), scattering from
the different volume elements within the electron
cloud begin to be out of phase with each other,
resulting in increasing destructive interference.
As an approximation, the cross-section drops
off as 1/E^2, and is described in detail by
the atomic form factor, f, which is normally
expressed as a function of Q, or sin theta/lambda.
In the next video, we will consider how the
situation changes if we account for the fact
that the electrons are not entirely free to
respond to the incident radiation, but are
in fact bound to atoms.
This will lead to the phenomena
of refraction, reflection, and absorption.