Welcome back to the second part of Week 2
of this introductory course on synchrotrons
and x-ray free-electron lasers!
In this video, we will discuss how we must
refine the atomic form factor to account for
the fact that the electrons in a material
are generally bound to the atomic nucleus
with well-defined binding energies, and what
consequences this then has on the phenomena
of refraction, reflection, and absorption.
In order to do this, we add two so-called
dispersive corrections, so named because they
depend on the photon energy.
We finish this section on the interaction
of x-rays with matter, by considering the
fate and subsequent products after absorption
of x-rays, in particular the emission of fluorescence
and electrons.
At the end of the last video, we described
the atomic form factor of the elements as
a function of the scattering vector Q (or
equivalently, sin theta/lambda) using the
expression shown here.
Note that f has a superscript “zero”,
highlighted here in red.
This denotes that this expression is the simplest
description of f, which assumes the electrons
are unhindered in their response to the incoming
x-rays by the fact that they are bound to
atomic nucleii.
For photon energies much larger than the binding
energy, this is a valid approximation.
(Turn to slide to the side) However, this
is not always the case, as can be seen here
for the most tightly bound electrons in the
so-called K-shell (with principle quantum
number n = 1) for all the naturally occurring
elements.
The binding energy of the K-electron (indeed,
the only electron) of a hydrogen atom is 13.6
eV.
The binding energy of K-electrons of the rest
of the elements increase as the square of
Z, the atomic number, due to the increased
Coulomb attraction, which means the K-electron
of uranium, the heaviest naturally occurring
element, is above 100 keV, accessible at only
the highest-energy synchrotron storage rings.
So it should be clear that in many cases,
depending on the photon energy being applied
and the elements present in the sample under
investigation, the assumption of free motion
of the electron, that is, that it is not influenced
by being bound to the atom, is invalid.
We can model the response of a bound electron
to an incident electromagnetic field to that
of a forced oscillator, such as shown here
as a ball on the end of a spring being forced
to respond to an oscillatory driving force
via a handle.
The spring with ball on it has a natural oscillation
frequency, given by omega-zero.
If the driving frequency omega is much smaller
than w0, the spring will remain stiff and
the ball will move in phase with the driving
handle.
In the other extreme on the right, the spring
will react essentially instantaneously with
the handle before the ball can respond, due
to its inertia, and the ball’s motion will
therefore be exactly out of phase, that is,
lagging by 180 degrees.
When the ball is driven at the natural frequency,
the system is said to be in resonance and
the ball moves at a phase 90 degrees lagging
the driving force, and will have a maximum
amplitude.
Note however, that although the electron moves
out of phase with the E-field at high photon
energies, the re-emitted radiation is in phase
with the incident radiation, as the driving
force is -eE, that is, it is negative.
An electron in an atom will respond similarly.
Because it cannot respond unhindered by its
attraction to the nucleus, its response will
be damped accordingly.
This means we need to add a negative term
f’ to f0 to represent this reduced response.
The sum of these, f1, is thus generally smaller
than f0.
This reduction is most pronounced at resonance,
where the photon energy equals the binding
energy of the electron to the atom.
In addition we must consider absorption.
We include another component f2, which increases
abruptly at resonance and is also shown here.
Importantly f2 lags f1 by 90 degrees, which
is mathematically expressed by it being an
imaginary term.
The total structure factor is thus a complex
number, consisting of both real and imaginary
components.
Exactly why the component representing absorption
is imaginary (that is, lagging by 90 degrees)
will become clear shortly.
We can represent the change in f graphically
in a so-called Argand, or phase diagram.
For those of you unfamiliar with this construct,
a document can be found in this week’s supplementary
information.
It is certainly worth taking your time to
understand Argand diagrams, as we will use
them extensively in the part of the course
on diffraction, especially with regards to
anomalous effects.
Briefly, the original zeroth-order value for
f, f-zero, is reduced by an amount f’, to
a new value f_1. 90 degrees out-of-phase to
this is the imaginary component f_2, or if_2,
the square-root of -1, i, representing this
phase shift.
The vector product of these two components,
f1 and if2, is the total structure factor
f.
So let us summarise these concepts here.
f0 is now modified by two correction terms:
f’ is a negative term reducing the scattering
amplitude by the fact that the electron is
bound.
f1 is the sum of f0 and f’ and is thus smaller
than f0, as f’ is always negative.
The second term f” = f2 is 90 degrees lagging
f1 and increases sharply at resonance, that
is, when the photon energy equals the electron’s
binding energy.
The total atomic form factor is thus a complex
value which depends on both the scattering
vector Q and the photon energy hbar omega.
How does f2 depend on the photon energy?
It turns out that f2 = sigmaPA/(2 lambda r0).
We know that sigmaPA, the absorption cross-section,
increases suddenly at resonance, and thus
these features are referred to as absorption
edges.
In addition, away from these edges, the absorption
cross-section falls of as 1/hn cubed.
But because f2 is inversely proportional to
lambda, which is itself inversely proportional
to the photon energy, f2 is therefore proportional
to the inverse square of the photon energy.
The double logarithmic plot shown here thus
has a gradient of -2.
The dependence of the absorption cross-section
and thus f2 on the element type away from
absorption edges increases with the fifth
power of Z for lighter elements, slowly changing
to Z^4 with increasing Z.
Shown here are two real examples for the elements
Ga (Z = 31) and As (Z = 33).
Let us begin with f2, shown in green and red.
The K-absorption edge (i.e., the binding energy
of its 1s electron) for Ga lies 1500 eV lower
than that for As, as its attraction to the
less positively charged nucleus is weaker.
f1 is shown in blue and yellow.
Note also that I have plotted two curves each
for Ga and As, in order to underline the fact
that f1 depends not only on the photon energy,
but also on the scattering vector Q. The two
values of Q chosen here are 2.223 (for the
upper blue and yellow curves) and 4.446 A-1
(for the lower blue and yellow curves), which,
by the by, happen correspond to maxima in
the diffraction pattern of GaAs.
We need not concern ourselves with this extra
information here, but we will return to this
later in the course.
Note also, that both f1 and f2 have detailed
features, consisting of small oscillations.
These are not experimental artefacts, but
are infact important features from which detailed
information can be drawn in methods such as
EXAFS, also covered later in the course.
So, how do these additional refinements to
the atomic form factor affect the properties
of x-rays travelling through matter?
The phenomena we will be most interested in
are refraction, reflection, and absorption.
We begin with refraction.
We are all familiar at some level with refraction
in the visible regime.
Visible light travels more slowly in a transparent
medium than in vacuum.
Imagine a platoon of soldiers walking in formation
that come across a ploughed field at an oblique
angle.
The first soldiers that begin to walk across
the ploughed field will slow down.
As a result the distance between the rows
of soldiers in the field is shortened, and
their direction is altered.
Analogously, the wavelength of visible light
is shortened; the velocity is smaller in a
transparent medium by a factor n, known as
the refractive index; and light beams are
bent to steeper angles when entering the medium.
This simple concept explains why, for example,
an object partially in water seems to be abruptly
bent at the air-water interface, shown step
for step here.
The change in angle of light travelling across
a heterogeneous interface is given by Snell’s
law, shown here.
Let us consider the simpler case where the
lighter medium has a refractive index nR = 1
(it is actually a vacuum).
First, it should be clear that refraction
acts equally when the the light enters the
medium or exits it.
Now let us reduce the angle alpha’ until
the angle alpha outside the medium is reduced
to zero.
The cosine of zero degrees is 1, and hence
cos alpha’, which we relabel in this special
case to alpha_c, is equal to 1/nR’.
Below this angle, which is typically about
40 degrees for water, all light impinging
on the interface will be reflected back into
the medium.
This phenomenon is known as total internal
reflection, and is used, for example, to channel
light along optical fibres in telecommunication.
This is shown nicely in the video on the left
- the water surface acts as a somewhat wobbly
mirror, reflecting the carapace of the turtle.
So that was refraction in the visible.
We now consider the refractive index of matter
for the case of x-rays.
This is a complex number, containing a real
part nR and imaginary component inI.
We will now see that the real part of the
complex refractive index is responsible for
refraction of x-rays, while the imaginary
part describes absorption.
Remember that we have just also stated that
the atomic form factor is also complex?
This is no coincidence.
It turns out that the refractive index n for
x-rays is related to the atomic form factor
by this expression.
But we know that f = f1 + if2, so we can insert
this into our expression for n, and immediately
identify the expressions for nR and nI.
We simplify the expression for n as n = 1
- delta + i beta.
Let us begin by considering the sum term.
The real part of this is simply the sum over
all elements i within the material of their
number density Ni, multiplied by the real
part of their atomic form factor in the forward
direction (Q = 0).
Far from an absorption edge, f1i(0) is equal
to Zi, the atomic number of the i-th atom
type.
Thus the sum is nothing more than the number
density of the electrons in the material in
units of electrons per unit volume.
Even close to absorption edges, we can equate
the sum to the EFFECTIVE electron number density.
So we insert rho into our expression for delta.
From this, we should immediately recognise
that delta is inversely proportional to the
square of the photon energy, as all the other
elements of the equation are (far from an
absorption edge) independent of hn.
As we discussed earlier, however, f2i is itself
inversely proportional to the square of the
photon energy, and hence beta falls of with
the inverse fourth power of hn.
We will return to this fact of this differing
dependence of beta and delta in the technique
of phase-contrast tomography towards the end
of the course.
The next thing we should do is estimate how
large delta and beta are, in other words,
how much does the refractive index for x-rays
differ from unity (i.e., no change at all).
We already know that x-rays pass relatively
unhindered through matter, so we might (correctly)
suspect that these dispersion corrections
are small.
First, because Z is always close to being
half of the atomic mass, and because interatomic
spacings in condensed matter do not vary wildly,
one can easily generate a very rough and ready
rule of thumb that the electron density is
of the order of Z/20, expressed in electrons
per cubic Angstrom.
For one-Angstrom radiation, the rest of the
expression for delta is approximately 4 x
10^-6 cubic Angstrom, which thus yields a
value for delta of 2Z x 10^-7.
Thus, even for the heaviest elements, delta
is of the order of 2 x 10^-5, much less than
unity.
Beta varies more strongly according to the
sum term, but is even smaller still than delta
in most cases by up to three or more orders
of magnitude, depending on both the element
and photon energy.
So, in summary, the refractive index in the
x-ray regime equals unity minus a tiny amount,
plus an imaginary component of even tinier
magnitude.
Before we apply these new insights to the
phenomena of refraction, reflection, and absorption,
a small but important issue should be mentioned.
The more attentive student might object to
the fact that the refractive index is less
than one for x-rays.
Doesn’t this imply that the velocity of
x-rays in matter exceeds c, the speed of light
in vacuum?
Indeed it does.
However, this is referring to the PHASE velocity,
the speed at which the peaks and troughs of
the electromagnetic train move.
The GROUP velocity, however, is equal to cn,
which is less than c, and it is this that
describes the propagation of energy or information,
or here, the speed of the “packet” or
envelope of light.
Einstein’s theory of special relativity
remains inviolate!
So, now let us consider Snell’s law for
x-rays.
Because n is less than unity, the x-rays are
bent to shallower angles when traversing from
a lighter to a denser material.
Using the same arguments as earlier for visible
light, there will therefore be a critical
incident angle alpha_c for which the x-rays
will be entirely externally reflected at the
surface.
This means mirrors can be constructed for
x-rays.
How large is alpha_c.
From Snell’s law, we see this is equal to
the real component of the refractive index,
nR = 1 - delta, which we know to be only very
marginally less than unity.
The Taylor expansion of the cosine function
can be very accurately approximated by 1 - x2/2
for x being a small angle (given in radians,
NOT degrees!)
For those of you unfamiliar with the angle
unit the radian, there are 2 pi radians in
a circle, therefore one radian = 360 degrees/2
pi = 57.296 degrees).
Hence we can state that 1 - alpha_c^2/2 = 1
- delta, and therefore alpha_c is equal to
the square-root of 2 delta, when expressed
in radians.
So, for example, a block of silicon ***** will
reflect 10-keV x-rays at incident angles shallower
than 0.179 degrees.
***** ***** So if an x-ray beam has a height
of 1 mm, ***** its footprint along the mirror
will be very long, ***** of the order of 30
cm.
X-ray mirrors at synchrotrons are therefore
generally large components.
Because they also need to be exceedingly flat
on both a macroscopic and atomic level, they
are also very expensive!
Lastly, it should be mentioned that even at
incident angles shallower than the critical
angle, the x-rays do penetrate a short distance
into the reflecting surface in an evanescent
wave.
This should be intuitively obvious, as the
x-rays must interact at some level with the
material to “know” that they will be reflected.
Close to an absorption edge, this will result
in a reduction in the critical angle by a
factor equal to to the square root of the
jump in beta at that edge.
This is shown here for rhodium below, above,
and at the K-absorption edge at 23.22 keV.
It will also result in some absorption and
a lowered reflectivity.
We now move on to absorption.
When an x-ray wave passes into a block of
material, the wavefronts will increase their
separation by a factor 1/nR = 1/(1-delta),
while the amplitude E0 of the electromagnetic
radiation will drop off exponentially due
to absorption.
How can we relate this exponential decay with
the absorption index, beta?
The description of the propagation in time
and space of a plane wave in vacuum is given
in the Eulerian formalism
by E(z,t) = Eo exp(i(k0z - wt)).
When travelling through matter, one must include
the refractive index n on the spatial term,
highlighted here in red.
But n = nR + inI, so inserting this into the
equation, we can break it down in to an exponential
decay term with exponent (-inIk0z) and an
temporal or oscillatory term.
The amplitude of the x-ray wave thus decays
such that after a distance (1/nIk0), it is
1/e (or about 37%) of its original value.
However, the intensity of the beam, the thing
we actually measure, is proportional to the
square of the amplitude, and hence the beam
intensity will decay to 1/e after only (1/2nIk0).
This factor is the absorption length.
The absorption coefficient mu is the reciprocal
of this and is therefore equal to 2nIk0.
Because nI = beta is proportional to the inverse
fourth power of the photon energy, mu is therefore
proportional to the inverse third power.
As one can see from the graph on the right,
depending on the electron density of the material
and the photon energy, the absorption length
can vary from the order of 10 nm for lead
at low photon energies, to centimetres for
beryllium in the hard x-ray regime.
We finish this video by considering what possible
subsequent processes might occur after removing
an electron by absorption of a photon.
For the purposes of this course, we consider
four main products, namely the photoelectron
itself, fluorescence, Auger emission, and
secondary electrons.
The photoelectron is the direct product of
absorption.
The promoted electron may actually reside
in an unoccupied orbital if the photon energy
is only marginally larger than the electron’s
binding energy.
Such orbitals are accessed and the information
used to work out both chemical and orientational
information in the technique of XANES (also
called NEXAFS), which we discuss later.
If the electron leaves the atom entirely,
it can be detected, its kinetic energy determined,
and from this and a knowledge of the photon
energy, the binding energy of the electron
calculated.
Subtle changes in this value provide invaluable
chemical information in the technique of XPS
(also called ESCA), while the dependence of
the yield as a function of both photon energy
and exit angle of the electron in single-crystal
samples, yields detailed information on the
sample’s electronic structure in angle-resolved
photoelectron spectroscopy (or ARPES).
The removal of a core electron can cause another
electron from a less tightly bound orbital
to relax into the “hole” left behind.
The excess energy produced by this can be
channeled in one of two ways.
Firstly, this energy can be removed as a photon
in the form of fluorescence at characteristic
photon energies, which is exploited in x-ray
fluorescence techniques.
Alternatively, the excess energy can cause
yet another electron to be ejected.
As the kinetic energy of this so-called Auger
electron depends only on the energy difference
between the initial hole state and that of
the relaxing electron; and the binding energy
of the Auger electron, its kinetic energy
is independent of the incident photon energy,
which distinguishes it from direct photoelectrons.
Auger processes tend to dominate for low-Z
atoms, while fluorescence occurs more commonly
for heavier elements.
Finally, any ejected electron will on average
collide with other electrons after a certain
characteristic distance, measured in nanometers
or at most tens of nanometers for most kinetic
energies under consideration.
This makes Auger spectroscopy and photoelectron
spectroscopy very surface sensitive.
If, however, the ejected electron is generated
deeper in the sample (remember, the penetration
depth of x-rays is normally significantly
larger than the escape depth of electrons)
then it will undergo multiple collisions,
producing a cascade effect and the production
of many more secondary electrons which have
been thermalised and have energies measured
in fractions of an electronvolt.
This signal is often used as an indirect measure
of absorption strength, such as in the spectromicroscopic
technique of photoemission electron microscopy
(PEEM).
Summarising this second video for this week,
we have seen how an electron bound to an atom
responds differently to incident x-rays than
in the free-electron model we introduced in
the last video.
This causes scattering to be reduced, particularly
when the photon energy is close to the binding
energy of the electron.
The resonant component causes energy loss
and absorption to occur.
We then argued how these dispersive corrections
to the atomic form factor are correlated to
the phenomena of refraction, reflection, and
absorption of x-rays, and provided quantitative
expressions linking the atomic form factor
with the complex refractive index in the x-ray
regime.
Lastly, we briefly summarised which processes
can occur once a photon is absorbed, and how
these can be used in synchrotron methods to
investigate the properties of material.
Next week, we will discuss the physics behind
the generation of synchrotron light, often
referred to as “machine physics”.