Welcome to Week 3 of this introductory course
on synchrotrons and x-ray free-electron lasers!
This week, we will discuss fundamental features
regarding the generation of synchrotron light
and relevant aspects of machine physics.
To begin with, the forces acting on a charged
particle through an electric or magnetic field
are summarised. Following this, I will explain
why it is that charged particles, in our case
electrons, generate electromagnetic radiation
when they are accelerated. This leads us on
to the surprising features of light emission
from electrons moving at relativistic velocities,
such as found in synchrotron storage rings,
in particular the greatly enhanced emission
in the forward direction to produce a pencil-like
beam.
Storage rings are just that - closed rings
that maintain electrons on a closed path.
How the electrons are steered and manipulated
so that they remain on this path will take
up the remainder of this first video of the
week, including descriptions of the magnet
lattice and the energy source for the electrons
within the storage ring, namely the RF cavity.
More advanced aspects are discussed next week,
including an overview of the two newest kids
on the block, x-ray free-electron lasers,
and diffraction-limited storage rings.
By convention, a linearly polarized electromagnetic
plane wave propagating in the positive z-direction
will, for an observer looking in the forward
z-direction, have its magnetic-field vector
always rotated +pi/2 (90 degrees) clockwise
relative to the electric-field vector. So,
for example, if the magnetic field points
in the positive y-direction, the E-field will
point in the positive x-direction.
In which directions do the electric- and magnetic-field
components of the electromagnetic radiation
act upon an electron? The force imparted by
an electric field on an electron (with its
negative charge) always acts perpendicular
to the direction of propagation and (because
of the electron’s negative charge) in the
opposite direction of the electric-field vector,
that is F_E = -little e the elementary charge,
times big E, the electric field amplitude.
We now discuss the magnetic Lorentz force
acting on a moving electron with velocity
v. First, you should note that the conventional
current is opposite in direction to the electron
motion, and that the positive direction of
the magnetic field B is defined as being from
the north to south pole. Hence, bending magnets
in synchrotron facilities in which the electrons
circulate in a clockwise sense (viewed from
above) will have the north poles above the
south poles, and vice-versa for “anticlockwise”
storage rings.
The direction of the magnetic Lorentz force
F_L acts perpendicularly to the plane defined
by the electron’s direction of motion and
the magnetic-field vector B. It is proportional
to the cross-product of v and B. If, as in
the case shown here, the electrons copropagate
in the same positive z-direction as the EM-field,
then the Lorentz force will have its maximum
magnitude F_L = eBv and in a direction opposite
to that of the electric force.
From classical electromagnetism, it emerges
that the relationship between the
magnetic-field amplitude B and the electric-field
amplitude E of an EM-wave is B = E/c and hence
from this and the expressions for the electric
and magnetic forces
we immediately observe that the ratio of the
two forces is simply -v/c. As a consequence,
the Lorentz force only becomes non-negligible
compared to the electric-field force for electrons
travelling at relativistic velocities.
We now move on by asking the question “why
does a synchrotron, which is in essence simply
a collection of electrons moving at very high
velocities around a closed path, produce electromagnetic
radiation?” First of all, it should be mentioned
that typically, the kinetic energies of the
electrons within a storage ring of a synchrotron
all have the same value within approximately
0.1% of each other, which might seem to imply
that they are not being accelerated. Don’t
forget, however, that acceleration also includes
a change in direction, even if the magnitude
of the velocity remains constant, such as
in the case of a ball being whirled round
on the end of a string. The centripetal force
always acts at right angles to the ball’s
motion, as does the associated acceleration.
So when we ask why a charged particle produces
light when accelerated, we should consider
three cases - the conventional interpretation
of acceleration, i.e., an increase in speed;
the opposite, that is, DEceleration; and lastly,
centripetal acceleration. This third case
applies to synchrotron light.
OK. we still haven’t answered our question.
Let us begin with a stationary charged particle.
From hereon in, I will assume for simplicity
that the charged particle is an electron.
The electrostatic electric field lines radiate
out from the electron equally in straight
lines in all directions and at the speed of
light. Any observer looking at the electron
will see no transverse component of those
electric field lines because, as I’ve just
said, they point directly from the electron
to the observer’s eye. But electromagnetic
radiation is a transverse wave, that is, the
electric (and magnetic) field lines are perpendicular
to the direction of motion. So we can conclude
that an observer will never see light emitted
from a stationary electron. For simple reasons
which I will not dwell on here, the same is
true of an electron moving at a constant velocity.
Now let us consider the case where the electron
bounces off a wall and reverses its direction.
Clearly here, it has undergone an acceleration
(or in day-to-day parlance, a sudden deceleration
and acceleration). An observer will see no
electric field until a time after the electron’s
bounce, equal to the distance between the
observer and electron, divided by the speed
of light. But at this moment, there will be
an abrupt lateral shift in the electric-field
lines - the observer sees a lateral component
in the electric fields, which is synonymous
with the generation of light. Note also, that
although an observer at position B sees this
pulse of light clearly, an observer at A will
continue to see nothing, because the acceleration
was along her line of sight. This is an important
fact to keep in mind - light generated by
acceleration of charged particles has zero
intensity in the direction of that acceleration.
Let us extend this idea further by allowing
the electron to bounce repeatedly back and
forth between two walls. The resultant field
lines will include abrupt lateral components
(light) that appear regularly after each bounce.
Now, if instead of the electron moving with
constant speed between two walls, we instead
drive it sinusoidally, the resulting electric
field will have the same frequency and thus
mimic the driving acceleration. So if the
driving acceleration of the electron is itself
caused by the electric field component of
light, the electron will re-emit light at
exactly the same frequency. This is identical
to the elastic, or Thomson, scattering of
light by electrons we covered in last week’s
lectures. It is for this reason that metals
reflect visible light and therefore why mirrors
work - the essentially free conduction electrons
in the metal that allow it to conduct electricity
respond to incident light and re-emit it with
high fidelity.
Note once more that along the axis of acceleration,
the observer will see no light. The electric-field
amplitude follows the cosine of chi, the polar
angle between incident beam’s direction
of propagation and the axis of the observer,
as shown here. This is referred to a dipole
radiation. The light INTENSITY varies as the
square of this, that is cosine-squared chi.
So, how would the emitted radiation from an
electron executing a circular path look like?
The acceleration is towards the centre of
the circle, hence the symmetry axis of the
doughnut, or “horn torus” form of the
dipole radiation also lies in this direction.
This doesn’t seem to look much like the
pencil-like radiation distribution associated
with synchrotron light, so what’s missing?
What’s missing is relativity. Before we
get to this, we need to know what the typical
energies are of the electrons circulating
in the storage ring of synchrotrons.
In this graph, a selection of synchrotron
facilities has been chosen that cover the
typical range of electron energies, expressed
in GeV (billions of electron volts). As one
can see, these span about 2 to 8 GeV, and
provide photon energies over almost 5 orders
of magnitude, from ultraviolet photons at
10 eV to almost 1 MeV. On average, the higher
the storage-ring energy, the higher the range
of photon energies.
If we were to calculate the electron velocities
using Newtonian mechanics (that is, not taking
relativistic effects into account), we would
equate the electron energy to 1/2 mv-squared,
where m = 9.11 x 10^-31 kg is the rest mass
of an electron, and would, say for 3 GeV electron,
obtain velocities of approximately 3.2 x 10^10
m/s, over 100 times faster than the speed
of light.
But because we know the speed of light is
Nature’s ultimate speed limit, it’s clear
we need to apply relativity. The relationship
between the electrons’ relativistic kinetic
energy (given by the storage-ring energy)
and the velocity is given by the expression
shown here. The ratio between the electrons’
velocity and c, the speed of light is called
beta.
An important parameter, which we will use
repeatedly to determine several aspects of
synchrotron light, including its divergence,
its intensity in the forward direction, and
the relativistic mass of the electron, is
gamma, defined as the ratio between the electrons’
kinetic energy and
mc^2, the rest mass energy of the electron
(highlighted here in red).
In special relativity, this is the amount
of energy (other than the energy residing
in mass itself) that would be created if an
electron at rest was annihilated. If one plugs
in the known values for m and c into this,
one obtains a value for mc^2 of 82 fJ, or
511 keV. So, for example, if an electron and
positron meet, they annihilate one another,
and create two x-ray photons, each of energy
511 keV.
Because mc^2 is a constant for a given particle
type (here, an electron), we can reformulate
our expression for gamma in practical terms
as gamma = 1957 multiplied by the storage
ring energy expressed in GeV. So, for example,
a 2-GeV storage ring facility would have a
gamma of 3914, that is, each electron has
an energy almost 4000 times its own rest-mass
energy. Remember our original expression however,
relating the electron energy to its velocity
(or beta = v/c).
From this, we immediately see that gamma = 1/sqrt(1
- beta^2).
If we square both sides of this, and perform
two trivial algebraic steps, we can instead
express beta, the ratio of v to c, as a function
of gamma, as shown here.
We can simplify this still further as follows.
We know that in general, gamma is a large
number for synchrotrons. For essentially all
synchrotrons, it assumes a value somewhere
between approximately 2000 and 16000. gamma^2
is therefore exceedingly large, of the order
of several million to a few hundreds of million,
and so the reciprocal of this, 1/gamma^2,
is tiny.
In the supplementary document listing useful
mathematical equations and approximations,
the Taylor expansion for (1+x)^n is provided,
and, to a very high degree of accuracy, is
equal to 1 + nx. In this instance, x = 1/gamma^2,
and therefore we can approximate the top equation
here being approximately equal to beta equals
1 - 1/2 gamma^2. The inaccuracy to this approximation
is about than one part in 10^15. . . accurate
enough, I’d say!
So let’s now consider what numbers emerge
for the real example of the MAX-IV facility
in Lund, Sweden, which has just come online
this Summer. From our practical expression
for gamma, we immediately see that this assumes
a value of approximately 5900. From this,
we obtain a value for beta, the ratio of electron
velocity to the speed of light, of 1 - 1/6.89
x 10^7, in other words, exceedingly close
to one. In fact, from this, one can directly
determine that the difference in velocity
of a photon and a MAX-IV electron is only
a little over 4 m/s.
To obtain a feel for this, imagine a photon
and electron in a straight out sprint race.
A little more than a second after the gun,
they have gone past the moon, and the photon
is still only about 5 meters in front of the
electron. Usain Bolt often beats his opponents
by this margin after less than 100 metres!
So, what other consequences are there related
to the weirdness of relativity? First, in
the frame of reference of a stationary observer,
the electron has assumed a mass of gamma m,
that is, several thousand times that at rest.
In the case of MAX-IV, this is almost equal
to the mass of a tritium atom. This might
still not seem much, but if I were to travel
so fast, you would see me as having approximately
the same mass as three blue whales combined.
. .
Also, importantly, space becomes distorted
- it wraps forward; things that lie in front
of you become brighter and bluer, while those
behind dim and are red-shifted. A mathematical
derivation of this special-relativistic effect
caused by time-dilation and space contraction
lies well outside the remit of this lecture
course, so I ask you to accept this as an
admittedly very weird, but certainly true,
fact.
This is shown schematically here for a spaceship
travelling at small and at relativistic velocities.
A homogeneous distribution of stars at low
speed looks very different when travelling
relativistically.
Now, remember from earlier in this video the
dipole distribution sketched for an electron
moving in a circular orbit, and our concern
that this doesn’t look much like the pencil-beam
radiation of synchrotrons? Now we should understand
why fast electrons distort this.
For the purposes of this course, you need
not know the exact mathematical description
of the spatial distribution of dipole radiation
at relativistic velocities. Instead, it is
shown here graphically for velocities between
1% and 99% of the speed of light. Remember
that at synchrotrons, the electrons travel
only approximately one part in 10^7 less than
the speed of light, hence the forward radiation
distribution is much narrower still than that
shown here for the electron at 99% of c.
Theory tells us that the angular power density
in the forward direction scales with the sixth
power of gamma. Hence, all other parameters
being equal (in particular a = c^2/rho, the
centripetal acceleration), a doubling in gamma
will produce a 64-fold increase in power density
on axis.
The angular range of radiation scales as 1/gamma.
Even for medium-energy storage rings, the
opening angle 1/gamma in both the horizontal
and vertical planes is of the order of 1/5000
of a radian, or approximately 1/100th of a
degree. This means that, for a point source,
the beam will have a lateral extent of approximately
4 mm at a distance of 20 m - synchrotron radiation
is indeed very collimated!
We will see later that in reality, the divergence
of different sources at synchrotrons (in particular
bending magnets and undulators) differs somewhat
from 1/gamma for reasons we will discuss in
detail later.
The next topics I would like to discuss in
the second video are how the electrons are
maintained in a closed orbit, and will show
using back-of-the envelope calculations that
the use of electric fields to bend electrons
is impractical and that instead magnetic forces
are used. When electrons emit synchrotron
radiation, they lose energy. How this energy
is replenished via a radio-frequency cavity
is also explained.