Welcome to the second video of Week 3 of this
introductory course on synchrotrons and x-ray
free-electron lasers!
In the first video of this week, we covered
basics of the electric and magnetic fields
acting on electrons, and, by heuristic arguments,
showed that accelerating electrons causes
them to radiate light, of which synchrotron
radiation is one example. The characteristics
of synchrotron light were shown to depend
on several parameters, including the electron
energy and the magnitude of the centripetal
acceleration.
We begin the second video by investigating
this aspect in more detail. The bending magnets
used for this, and other elements associated
with the storage ring, comprising together
the so-called magnet lattice, are described
in more detail. Lastly, we show how the energy
lost by the electrons because of their emission
of light is replenished in a radio-frequency
cavity installed in the storage ring.
Let’s now begin by considering how we steer
electrons in a closed path. The electrons
must experience a centripetal force acting
at right angles to their motion in order to
maintain them on a closed orbit. Note that
this force need not be applied along the entirety
of the storage ring, but can be broken up,
with straight sections in between. Remember,
indeed, that third-generation synchrotrons
are defined by these straight sections, as
it is here that insertion devices are placed,
which provide the most intense sources. We’ll
talk about these in detail next week.
For now, let’s concentrate on getting those
electrons on a closed path. The centripetal
acceleration is a = v-squared/rho, where v
can be very accurately approximated by c,
the speed of light, and rho is the radius
of the bending orbit. Note also, that because
the electron is traveling at relativistic
speeds, its mass from our perspective is gamma
times its rest mass, which we’ve already
established typically increases the mass by
several thousand. The force is therefore gamma
m c^2/rho.
Two at first obvious candidates come to mind
for imparting the centripetal force - an electric
field, such as also used in old-fashioned
cathode-ray tubes in TVs dating back to the
end of the 20th Century; or magnetic fields,
such as used for electric motors or loudspeakers.
Let’s first consider the use of an electric
field. First, don’t get confused with E
here, which denotes the electric-field strength,
or amplitude, with E, the electrons’ kinetic
energy. As we will see in just a moment, we
can discount the electric field as a reasonable
candidate for steering electrons, so let’s
tolerate this slight ambiguity for the meantime.
If one plugs typical values for rho and gamma
into our force equation, and using the known
values for the physical constants m, c, and
e, we obtain electric-field strengths which
must be of the order of a billion volts per
metre to do the required job. The breakdown
field strength of dry air at 1 atmosphere
is approximately 3 million volts/m, over two
orders of magnitude weaker, while that of
pure silica is up to 40 MV/m. It should therefore
be clear that using electric fields as a steering
mechanism is impossibly hazardous.
Which leaves us with the Lorentz force of
magnetic fields. In the last video, we established
that this is equal to evB, or for our highly
relativistic electrons within the storage
ring, approximately ecB, assuming the magnetic
field points perpendicular to the electrons’
motion. Equating this to gamma m c^2/rho,
the centripetal force, and then rearranging
this, we see that the bending radius rho equals
gamma mc/eB.
But gamma mc^2 is equal to the electrons’
kinetic energy E, hence rho = E/ceB. We can
re-express this in practical units such that
rho in metres equals 3.3 x the storage-ring
energy expressed in GeV divided by B given
in Tesla.
Hence an electron travelling in a horizontal
plane that experiences a constant B-field
acting vertically, will be steered in a circular
path of radius rho. From our practical expression
for rho, we see that a few-GeV storage ring
containing magnets with field strengths of
the order of a Tesla, will bend electrons
along a path with a radius of the order of
10 meters. The fan of radiation in the horizontal
plane will subtend the same angle as the arc
of the bending magnet itself. Only a small
angular fraction of this passes through an
aperture to a bending-magnet beamline. Because
the fan angle is so much larger than the typical
acceptance angle of a beamline, more than
one bending-magnet beamline can be served
by a single bending magnet. ***** waaaaaaait.
. .
What are typical magnetic field strengths?
The earth’s magnetic field varies considerably,
but is strongest close to the poles and can
reach around 60 microTeslas. Indeed it is
the combination of this higher field strength
and energetic charged particles from the solar
wind (primarily energetic electrons) that
generate the aurora as these particles are
funnelled by the Earth’s magnetic field
to the polar regions, where they collide with
molecules in the upper atmosphere, causing
them to fluoresce.
At a more mundane level, typical kitchen magnets
have field strengths approximately three orders
of magnitude stronger. The soft-iron permanent
magnets used at synchrotrons bending magnets
are one to two orders of magnitude stronger
still, at around a Tesla. Significantly higher
fields can be achieved using cryogenically
cooled superconducting intermetallic compounds,
such as Nb3Sn, which needs to be cooled to
less than 18.3 K, in the form of coil windings
in superconducting bending magnets, or “superbends”.
As we shall see very shortly, increasing the
magnetic-field strength can bring substantial
benefits, particularly for experiments demanding
high photon energies at low- or medium-energy
storage-ring facilities.
The spectrum and intensity of bending-magnet
radiation depends on several parameters. Firstly,
we need to know the angular frequency of the
orbiting electrons, that is, how many radians
per second they rotate during those times
they are being redirected by a bending magnet.
To simplify the determination of this, let’s
assume that the orbit is perfectly circular,
although even for real storage rings consisting
of straight and bent sections, the result
holds true. The orbit’s circumference is
2 pi rho, and a relativistic electron with
a velocity close to c will thus execute c/(2
pi rho) revolutions every second. But every
revolution contains 2 pi radians (because
there are 2 pi radians in 360 degrees), hence
the number of radians swept through per second
is 2 pi c/2 pi rho = c/rho. Inserting typical
values into this, we obtain an angular frequency
for the storage-ring electrons of the order
of 10^7 to 10^8 radians per second.
The critical frequency is a value associated
with the synchrotron-radiation spectrum (NOT
the electrons, although it is determined by
their energy and the bending radius rho!).
It emerges that this is equal to three halves
gamma^3 omega_0. We can re-express this either
by substituting omega_0 with c/rho, or indeed
one step further, by remembering that c/rho
= eB/gamma m, which we discovered a little
earlier in this video when we equated the
Lorentz and centripetal forces.
This leads us to the expression omega_c = 3/2
gamma^2 eB/m. Inserting typical values into
any of these equivalent expressions yields
a critical frequency of the order of 10^19
radian/sec. If we multiply this by h-bar we
obtain the photon energy associated with this
critical frequency. Converting this to electronvolts,
we obtain a photon energy of the order of
4 keV. In actuality, this can vary strongly,
due to its square dependence on gamma, the
Lorentz factor describing the storage-ring
energy, plus its linear dependence on B.
To repeat, the critical energy is linearly
proportional to B and varies with the square
of the storage-ring energy. A practical expression
for this is provided here. For a given magnetic
field strength, a bending magnet at SPring8
will have a critical energy some 18 times
greater than the same magnet at the ALS, as
the ratio is simply the square of their storage-ring
energies, that is (8 GeV/1.9 GeV), all squared.
The
red dots ***** show the critical energies
for two bending magnet beamlines at the two
high-energy storage rings SPring8 (8 GeV)
and the ESRF (6 GeV). In order to compensate
for their more modest electron energies, facilities
such as the Swiss Light Source (2.4 GeV) and
the Advanced Light Source (1.9 GeV) have installed
superbends (shown here as blue dots) in order
to access higher photon energies than would
otherwise be possible using normal bending
magnets.
But what precisely does the critical energy
describe? From our discussion so far, it is
probably already clear that it is somehow
linked to the bending-magnet spectrum. Before
this is shown explicitly, let us have a little
think about what we might expect the radiation
spectrum from a bending magnet to look like,
at least qualitatively.
You should remember from the first video this
week that an electron undergoing sinusoidal
acceleration from a harmonic driving force
(such as, for example, the electric-field
component of an incident x-ray beam), will
re-radiate light at the same frequency. In
other words, the electron scatters the incident
light elastically - it has the same frequency.
Imagine now an observer of the electron tangential
to the bending magnet. From her perspective,
the electron is first moving along the straight
section upstream of the bending magnet with
constant velocity - it is not being accelerated,
so we should not expect her to see any radiation.
But once the electron enters the gap between
the dipole of the bending magnet, it experiences
a pulse of centripetal acceleration towards
the centre of the ring due to the magnetic
field. In contrast to the case of sinusoidal
acceleration, this “pulse” of acceleration
cannot be described by a single frequency,
but instead is composed of a continuous spectrum
of frequencies, and the electron will emit
this in response. For the more mathematically
predisposed of you, you might recognise that
the spectrum that emerges from this pulse
of acceleration to be proportional to the
Fourier transform of the temporal description
of that acceleration. . . For those of you
less familiar with such insights, don’t
worry!
As a consequence, we can expect the bending-magnet
spectrum to be broad. Shown here are three
curves for different storage-ring energies
and magnetic-field strengths. Note that the
only difference between the spectra for a
1-Tesla bending magnet in a 4-GeV ring and
a 4-Tesla BM in a 2 GeV ring is the intensity,
which differ from each other by a factor of
four. Their critical energies, highlighted
as circles, are identical, as the products
of the square of the storage-ring energy and
magnetic field strength are equal. Note again
that high-energy storage rings, such as shown
in blue for a 6-GeV facility, easily access
high critical energies on account of the square
dependence on the storage-ring energy.
It turns out that half of the integrated radiative
power produced by a bending magnet lies below
the critical energy, and half above. But what
we haven’t yet discussed is how the spectral
flux is spatially distributed.
In general, the centre of the cone of radiation
is the most intense and most blue-shifted
to high photon energies. As one moves off
axis, the radiation becomes weaker (remember
that the beam only has a width of approximately
+/- 1/gamma, of the order of 0.01 degrees)
and the maximum is red-shifted to lower photon
energies. Obviously, in the case of bending
magnets, for which the horizontal angular
spread is equal to the angle subtended by
the magnet and is measured in degrees, the
fan of radiation in this plane at the beamline
is determined by the opening angle of the
aperture to the beamline, always much smaller
than the fan angle, but on the other hand,
also much larger than 1/gamma.
The total integrated radiative power output
of a bending magnet is given by the equation
shown here, where L is the length of the electron
path passing between the magnet poles. As
the entire storage ring requires bending magnets
to provide a closed orbit for the electrons,
the entire power output of all the bending
magnets together is given for a length L = 2
pi rho, where rho is the bending radius. Note
again, that this is NOT equal to the storage-ring
circumference, as the bending magnets are
separated by straight sections. There is also
radiative power production by insertion devices
in the straight sections, which we will discuss
next week, but here we are concerned only
with the bending magnets.
So, for example, a 3-GeV storage ring using
1-Tesla bending magnets will have a bending
radius rho = 9.9 m, for which 2 pi rho = 62
m. If the electron current is 0.4 amps, the
total power output due to bending-magnet radiation
will be 283 kW. Any one bending magnet port
may only accept, for example, approximately
5 mrad of this (or less than 1/1000 of 2 pi),
or in other words, 225 W. If this is further
monochromatized to select a narrow band of
energy, as is more often than not the case,
perhaps only of the order of 10 mW may then
remain. This might not seem very much, but
equates to, for example, approximately 10^13
10-keV photons per second, several orders
of magnitude more than can be provided by
laboratory-based x-ray sources.
To finish this video, we will now consider
the ratio between the power consumption caused
by the generation of synchrotron radiation,
which we have just calculated to be of the
order of 300 kW for bending-magnet radiation
alone, and might be double this when the insertion
devices are also accounted for, and the stored
power of the electron circulating in the storage
ring.
The stored energy is simply their kinetic
energy, or storage-ring energy, E, multiplied
by the number of electrons within the ring
at any one time. This is simply the current
in amps divided by the elementary charge of
the electron, multiplied by the storage-ring
circumference, big C, divided by the speed
of light, little c. This turns out to be of
the order of 10^12 electrons, hence the stored
energy is approximately a kJ. The stored power
is simply E x I, which is measured in GW.
One might therefore think that the power loss
through radiation is relatively slow, as the
radiative power is four orders of magnitude
smaller than the stored power. However, it
only requires a small deviation from the nominal
storage-ring energy for an electron to enter
an unstable and open orbit, and crash into
the walls of the vacuum chamber making up
the storage ring. Hence, the electrons require
a steady replenishment of this lost energy.
We finish this video by discussing this now.
Inserted in the storage ring is a radio-frequency
cavity, running typically at a few hundred
megahertz. Within this resonant cavity, the
electric field oscillates sinusoidally from
pointing in one direction to the other. Along
the central axis, this means the electric
field is either opposite to or in the same
direction as the electron path. Remember that
an electron is accelerated when the E-field
points in the opposite direction to the electron’s
sense of motion, due to its negative charge.
Therefore an electron entering the cavity
when the field points maximally in the upstream
direction will cause the electron to be maximally
accelerated, as shown schematically in the
figure on the left.
Now let’s consider two electrons, one of
which (A) has a little less energy than the
other (B), due perhaps to the fact that it
has emitted a couple more photons in their
last circuit round in the storage ring. B
enters the cavity first and is accelerated
by the cavity’s field. Electron A enters
a little later, at which point the field amplitude
has increased in its sinusoidal cycle by an
amount just enough to accelerate it to the
same energy as electron B. If the electrons
had entered the cavity at a significantly
different part of the RF cycle, the acceleration,
or indeed deceleration they experienced would
have caused them to become still less stable
in their orbit, and they would soon be lost.
*****
From this, it should be apparent that only
a very particular time window of the RF cycle
is suited to bringing the electrons back to
the nominal storage-ring energy. As a consequence,
the electron current in a synchrotron is not
continuous, but instead is composed of bunches,
each separated by 1/f, the period of the RF
cycle, and having a temporal width of approximately
one hundredth of their separation.
It is a trivial exercise to show that the
number of electrons within any one bunch is
equal to the current divided by the product
of the RF frequency and e, the elementary
charge, which turns out to be of the order
of 10^9 to 10^10 per bunch.
To summarise this second and last video of
the third week, we have reasoned that only
a magnetic Lorentz force is a reasonable way
of steering electrons into a closed path in
a storage ring. The characteristic, or critical
frequency omega_c and energy E_c were determined
and shown to depend on the square of the storage-ring
energy and linearly with the bending-magnet
field strength. The radiative power generated
by bending magnets and thus by the whole storage
ring (excluding other components such as insertion
devices) was determined and shown to be a
small fraction of the power stored within
the ring. Nonetheless, losses associated with
radiation production need to be replenished,
and the mechanism by which this is done, namely
the use of a radio-frequency cavity, results
in the electron current separating out into
bunches with bunch durations two orders of
magnitude shorter than their separation.
Next week, we define the important photon-beam
parameters of flux, emittance, and brilliance,
further discuss components of the so-called
magnet lattice, namely double- and multi bend
achromats, quadrupoles, and sextupoles; and
insertion devices, in particular undulators.
The use of multi bend achromats in so-called
diffraction-limited storage rings, or DLSRs,
defines the next generation of synchrotron
facilities and is discussed in some detail.
Lastly, we provide an overview of XFEL physics
and architecture and the radiation it produces.