Welcome to the first video of Week 4 of this
introductory course on synchrotrons and x-ray
free-electron lasers!
This week covers more details about machine
physics, that is, the generation of synchrotron
radiation by storage rings.
We begin by discussing properties of the x-rays
generated at synchrotrons, then progress in
the second video than overview of the magnet
lattice and insertion devices.
In the third and last video of Week 4, we
will familiarise ourselves with the latest
tools to be developed for x-ray science, namely
diffraction-limited storage rings (DLSRs)
and x-ray free-electron lasers (XFELs).
So, let’s begin with a detailed description
of some of the most important properties of
x-radiation, namely the flux, the emittance,
the combination of these, called the brilliance,
and lastly, coherence.
As we have already highlighted qualitatively
earlier in this course, for most experiments
using x-rays, we would like the beam to be
intense, parallel, have as much as possible
a single wavelength, and originate from a
small source.
The flux associated with an x-ray source is
simply the number of photons it emits for
a standardised relative spectral bandwidth,
delta E/E, where delta E is a range of energies
around a central energy E. This expression,
incidentally, can be equivalently expressed
in terms of the wavelength, that is delta
lambda/lambda, or in terms of the frequency
delta nu/nu (or indeed the angular frequency,
delta omega/omega).
The brilliance is simply the flux divided
by the source size in units of area, and also
by the divergence in the two orthogonal planes
perpendicular to the beam axis, given in units
of angle-squared.
Conventionally for synchrotrons, the beam
propagates along the positive z-direction,
while the x-axis lies in the plane of the
synchrotron ring and the y-axis is perpendicular
to both x and z.
As we will see, the product of these two properties,
that is, the source size and divergence, is
known as the emittance.
The brilliance is therefore simply the flux
divided by the emittance.
We now look at these different properties
of x-rays more quantitatively, beginning with
the flux.
By convention, the flux is defined as the
number of photons emitted per second within
a 0.1% bandwidth around the central energy
(or frequency, or wavelength).
This concept can be at first confusing for
nonspectroscopists, so let us consider an
example, involving a so-called silicon monochromator,
one of the most commonly used devices at synchrotrons.
In general, the spectra emitted by synchrotron
sources are far from being monochromatic - as
we shall see later this week, bending magnet
radiation is very broad, while even that for
the generally most desired sources called
undulators, consists of spectral peaks regularly
spaced in energy, each peak itself having
a width that is more often than not too broad
to be used without further monochromatization.
Monochromators are therefore used at beamlines
to clean up the spectra so that only a very
narrow range of photon energies get through
to the experiment.
Perhaps the most common of these is the silicon
monochromator.
It need not concern us for the present how
these instruments work (it is by diffraction,
but we’ll get to that next week).
Let us consider my own beamline, the Materials
Science beamline at the Swiss Light Source.
After monochromatization, we have measured,
for example, an average power output of 34
mW at a nominal photon energy of 7 keV.
The energy of each photon is easy to calculate
and is equal to 7000 eV x 1.6 x 10^-19 J/eV
= 1.12 fJ.
The number of photons/s is therefore 34 mW
divided by the photon energy = 3 x 10^13 ph/s.
Now, in order to determine the flux, as defined
above as the number of photons/0.1% bandwidth,
we need to know what the bandwidth of photons
is that a Si monochromator allows through.
It turns out that this is a constant, equal
to 1.4 x 10^-4.
Now this is SMALLER than 0.1% by a factor
of 0.14.
The flux is therefore equal to the number
of delivered photons DIVIDED by 0.14, as the
silicon monochromator has a narrower b bandwidth
that that defined for flux, and is therefore
equal to 2.17 x 10^14 ph/s/0.1%BW.
Now let us move on to the property of emittance.
In the two orthonormal directions to z, the
emittance is the product of the standard deviation
in source size and the standard deviation
in divergence.
In order to keep consistent bookkeeping, the
definition of standard deviation sigma is
shown here.
Briefly, sigma (or sigma’ in the case of
divergence) is defined as shown here for a
beam with Gaussian profile, a fair approximation
for synchrotron light.
The width 2 sigma is a little smaller than
the full-width at half maximum by the factor
sqrt(8 ln 2), or 2.355.
Now the emittance actually has two sources;
one due to the electron source size and angular
distribution, and the other from the photons,
in other words, that associated with synchrotron
radiation emission.
In general, the electron emittance, in particular
in the horizontal plane (i.e., the x-direction),
tends to dominate.
Because the sources are independent of each
other, their contributions add orthogonally,
as given by the equations shown here.
The photon emittance has a lower limit known
as the diffraction limit equal to lambda/4
pi, and is a consequence of Heisenberg’s
uncertainty principle.
For example, this is equal to 8 pm.rad for
1-Angstrom radiation.
On the other hand, the electron emittance
can be substantially larger, especially in
the x-direction, as it is in this direction
that the Lorentz forces from magnets in general
act.
This will increase both the electrons’ effective
source size and the divergence.
One of the aims of machine physicists in the
last decade and a half has been to minimise
any residual horizontal magnetic fields in
the plane of the electrons’ orbit caused
by imperfect magnet alignment, which would
couple part of the horizontal emittance to
the vertical emittance, blowing this up as
well.
Several facilities can now say that the magnet
alignment has been so perfectly tuned that
the vertical total emittance is essentially
equal to the theoretical minimum.
As we shall discuss in the last video of this
week, the improved performance promised by
diffraction-limited storage rings (DLSRs)
in the near future is based on efforts to
minimise also the electron emittance in the
HORIZONTAL plane and increase the brilliance
accordingly.
So a given storage-ring facility will have
a certain electron emittance, which is preserved
along the entirety of the ring.
The lower limits to this are determined by
several factors, and we will touch on these
later when discussing DLSRs.
For the moment, we should consider the following.
If a storage ring has a given emittance, how
can this be “expressed”?
As the emittance is the product of the source
size and divergence, we can either sacrifice
source size for a very parallel beam, or vice
versa, squeezing the source size to be as
small as possible, and accepting a larger
divergence.
Or, indeed, any combination between these
two extremes.
These are referred to as having a high beta,
or low beta, respectively.
The question is now, what to do when?
The so-called beta function is simply the
source size divided by the divergence.
A large beta function therefore corresponds
to a large source emitting parallel radiation,
while as small beta describes a small but
divergent source.
Shown on the right is a graph of the variation
of beta and sigma in both the x- and y-directions
along a sector spanning a little more than
80 degrees of the Swiss Light Source.
As one sees, both beta and sigma vary strongly
with position along the ring, due to different
elements of the magnet lattice squeezing,
focussing, and chromatically correcting the
electrons.
For example, along the parts of the ring which
contain the straights (used normally to accommodate
insertion devices), the beta functions are
minimised in order to bring the electrons
exactly to the centre of the insertion devices
for optimal operation.
Now we have defined both the flux and emittance,
we can state that the brilliance is defined
as the flux given in photons/s and 0.1% bandwidth,
divided by the values for sigma_x and sigma_y,
each given in mm, and sigma’_x and sigma’_y,
expressed in mrad.
I repeat: the brilliance is the flux divided
by the total emittance.
So let us make an order-of-magnitude calculation
for the brilliance of an undulator in a “typical”
third-generation undulator.
We have already calculated the flux for the
MS beamline at the Swiss Light Source, so
let’s take a similar value of around 10^14
ph/s/0.1%BW.
Typical horizontal and vertical emittance
are around 0.01 and 10^-4 mm.mrad, respectively,
which results in a brilliance of the order
of 10^20 ph/s/0.1%BW mm2 mrad2.
This value sits squarely in the middle of
the graph shown earlier describing the improvement
of brilliance in the last Century or so.
The brilliance offered by XFELs is several
orders of magnitude higher still, due both
to the highly parallel nature of the beam,
and also to the exceedingly high peak flux
that really defines XFELs.
As already mentioned, DLSRs owe their improved
brilliance primarily to the reduction in horizontal
emittance using newly available technologies.
Both these aspects will be discussed in the
third video of this week.
We finish this video with a description of
coherence.
Coherence describes the relative phase relationship
between different parts of the x-ray source,
or, from a quantum mechanical viewpoint, of
the photons.
A source is said to be coherent if the emitted
waves are all in phase and (by necessity)
have the same wavelength.
Lasers, for example, have in general a very
high degree of coherence.
In contrast, synchrotron sources are in general
only partially coherent, and might have a
so-called “coherent fraction” less than
0.1% for hard x-rays.
One of the exciting properties of XFEL beams
is the high degree of so-called “transverse”
coherence, explained shortly.
Coherence is an attractive property in many
instances, as this allows macroscopic objects
to be irradiated, and their three-dimensional
architecture determined, by recording the
scattered signal, without the need for a lens.
As we shall see later in the course, x-ray
lenses that would be sufficiently strong to
magnify an object so that its structure can
be determined on a nanometer or Angstrom scale
are impossible to construct, due to the fact
that the refractive index of materials in
the x-ray regime differs only very marginally
from unity, meaning refraction by lenses is
very weak.
So techniques which dispense with such optical
elements, such as x-ray diffraction, small-angle
scattering (SAXS), coherent x-ray diffractive
imaging (CXDI) , and ptychography, are highly
attractive as x-ray imaging methods.
The size of the object that can be measured
depends on the degree of coherence - x-ray
diffraction is concerned with objects of the
order of a few Angstroms to a couple of tens
of nanometers (the unit cell size), and in
general, it is easy to prepare x-ray beams
with sufficient coherence to record high-quality
diffraction data.
In the case of coherent x-ray diffractive
imaging of an object of characteristic dimensions
measured in microns, however, one must take
careful measures to ensure the beam is coherent
enough that the scattered signal (called “speckle”)
contains the required information to regain
the sample’s structure.
In general, if the sample is smaller than
the coherence volume, defined in the next
slide, lensless scattering imaging of that
object becomes possible.
Indeed, in the case of ptychography, a burgeoning
field in hard x-ray science, objects substantially
larger by orders of magnitude than the coherence
length can also be investigated with nanometer
or near atomic resolution, by scanning across
the sample and using a sophisticated mathematical
algorithm which links successive images recorded
during the scan.
All these techniques will be covered later
in the course.
The coherent volume is spanned by two transverse
and one longitudinal coherence length, as
shown here, resulting in a coherent volume
. The transverse coherence lengths are determined
by the divergence of the beam, while the longitudinal
value depends on the monochromacity of the
beam.
We discuss these separately now.
The longitudinal coherence length is defined
as the length required for parts of the beam
with different wavelengths (or energies) that
begin in phase to be entirely out of phase
and then in phase once more, as shown here.
The phase difference between the two energetically
different parts of the beam is thus 2 pi.
Note that this is just one definition - in
the literature, on can find the coherence
length as being defined as that after a phase
difference of pi (180 degrees), or even one
radian (about 57 degrees).
In our definition of a phase shift of 2 pi,
the longitudinal coherence length is given
as being equal to lambda^2/Delta lambda , which
for 2-Angstrom radiation after monochromatization
using a silicon monochromator with a value
of Delta lambda/lambda approximately 10^-4,
is thus of the order of a couple of microns.
The transverse coherence length is determined
similarly as the lateral distance between
parts of the wavefront separated by a phase
of 2 pi, due to the source divergence.
Obviously, the more parallel the beam (small
Delta theta), the larger the transverse coherence.
As Delta theta is equal to D/R, where D is
the source size and R is the source - sample
distance, beamlines constructed for scattering
experiments of mesoscopically sized objects,
such as in SAXS, CXDI, and ptychography, tend
to have long source - end-station distances
(i.e., D) and small source sizes (R).
Because the divergence of x-ray beams is generally
larger in the horizontal plane than the vertical,
the vertical transverse coherence length is
concomitantly larger than that in the horizontal
direction.
As an example, the transverse coherent lengths
for 2-Angstrom radiation at the cSAXS beamline
of the Swiss Light Source are given here.
Even the smaller horizontal value is an order
of magnitude larger than typical longitudinal
coherence lengths, and it is therefore the
transverse coherence which tends to be exploited
in such scattering experiments.
In the above calculations determining the
transverse coherent lengths, the divergence
was assumed to be that of the source.
However, the wavefront can be further scrambled
by imperfect optics, such as for specular
reflections off an x-ray mirror, caused by
that mirror not being perfectly flat.
Beamlines exploiting coherence take great
care in minimising such artefacts.
Lastly, the coherent fraction as a function
of the electrons’ and photons’ source
sizes and divergences is given here.
In “normal” third-generation facilities,
this expression is dominated by sigma_x^e
and sigmal_x^e’, and coherent fractions
of the order of 10^-3 or less are typical.
If, however, one is able to reduce these,
and the equivalent values in the y-direction
to those associated with the photons, then
one can obtain coherent fraction of 25%.
The next-generation storage rings, DLSRs,
promise to make a quantum leap in this direction,
obtaining coherent fractions of a few percent,
that is almost two orders of magnitude greater
than presently possible.
In the case of XFELs, the electron emittance
is significantly smaller than the photon emittance,
and coherent fractions close to unity are
achieved.
In summary, we have discussed in detail in
this video the pertinent properties and characteristics
of synchrotron beams, namely their flux, emittance,
brilliance, and coherence.
In the next video of this week, we discuss
the magnet lattice of the storage ring, that
is, the set of dipole bending magnets, quadrupoles,
and sextupoles responsible for keeping the
electrons on a well-defined closed orbit,
before considering insertion devices (that
is, wigglers, and most importantly, undulators),
the magnet arrays placed in the straight sections
of the storage ring that produce the most
intense beams.