Welcome to the second video of Week 4 of this
introductory course on synchrotrons and x-ray
free-electron lasers!
This video reviews the magnet lattice and
insertion devices.
The magnet lattice is responsible for keeping
the electron beam on a closed orbit, including
focusing it and chromatically correcting for
electrons of slightly different kinetic energies.
The dipole bending magnets also produce synchrotron
radiation.
While in general being less brilliant than
insertion devices by two to three orders of
magnitude, they are still highly brilliant
sources of synchrotron radiation and are used
extensively in most facilities.
It is the insertion devices, however, which
are generally (though not exclusively) most
sought after.
We will finish this video by examining these
in detail.
Shown here are “mugshots” of typical bending
magnets, quadrupoles, and sextupoles at third-generation
synchrotron facilities.
They are mounted on girders and can be subtly
repositioned and realigned in order to optimise
the magnet fields relative to the electron-beam
orbit.
Typically, bending magnets come in pairs in
a given arc-section of the storage ring, or
sometimes in triplets, at third-generation
facilities.
It is briefly mentioned here, and discussed
in detail in the next video, that the next
generation facilities, DLSRs, are characterised
by not having pairs or triplets of bending
magnets, but clusters of five, seven, or even
nine in an arc section of the ring.
In order to understand why dipole bending
magnets are never single, we begin with the
simplest configuration, that of the double-bend
achromat, also called the “Chasman-Green
lattice”, named after its inventors.
Imagine electrons of different energy entering
the magnetic field of a bending magnet.
The energy difference, as we have already
mentioned, may be as much as a couple of thousandths
of their nominal storage-ring energy.
So a 3-GeV ring may have electrons with an
energy spread measured in a few MeV.
Due to this spread in energy, the electrons
will execute different paths as they travel
through the bending magnet , the faster one
being less bent than the slower ones, which,
if left uncorrected, will blow up the electron-beam
in the horizontal plane by an unacceptable
degree.
This is resolved by placing a focussing quadrupole
magnet (FQM, described in detail shortly)
after the bending magnet, then a mirror image
of this bend downstream of the FQM.
This refocusses the electrons back onto a
common path and is called a double-bend achromat.
With this manipulation of the electrons is
associated a certain emittance, given by the
formula shown here.
Theta is the angle of a single bending magnet,
expressed in radians.
So, for example, a 10-degree turn of a bending
magnet, and a gamma-value of 4700 yields a
lower limit for the horizontal emittance of
approximately 3 nm.rad.
Note that this is significantly larger, by
almost three orders of magnitude, than the
diffraction limit of 1-Angstrom photons of
approximately 8 pm.rad.
The magnet lattice design and its optimisation
therefore largely determine the horizontal
emittance of the facility.
The central element of the DBA was the focussing
quadrupole.
We now consider quadrupoles in more detail.
Quadrupoles are just that - a four-pole array
of magnets, with alternating north and south
poles facing inwards, as shown here.
If we recall the Lorentz force and its sense
of direction from the first video of last
week, we can see that electrons moving out
of the screen towards you (indicated by the
blue dot and circle) will feel different forces,
depending on its position.
Exactly in the quadrupole centre, all the
forces cancel and the electrons should remain
unaffected.
Deviations in the electrons’ position up
or down from the central plane will cause
them to experience a restoring force to the
centre - they will be refocussed, in other
words.
In contrast, if the electrons are left or
right of the centre, the forces will accentuate
this deviation - they will be defocussed.
The action of focussing or defocussing in
the horizontal plane defines the naming convention
for quadrupole, so, the example shown here
is a defocussing, or D-quadrupole magnet (DQM).
If the array is rotated by 90 degrees, however,
the electrons are focussed horizontally and
defocussed vertically, and this configuration
is called a focussing quadrupole magnet, or
FQM.
By the correct placement of a FQM (here labelled
F-4) and a DQM (or D-4) after each other,
the electron beam can be focussed both vertically
and horizontally, though at different positions
along the central axis, according to the electrons’
energy.
This longitudinal dispersion can be subsequently
chromatically corrected using sextupole magnets,
which have focal lengths that are inversely
proportional to the distance of the electrons
from the central axis.
We now move on to a discussion of insertion
devices.
As has been mentioned several times already,
insertion devices are sources of synchrotron
radiation consisting of arrays of alternating
N-S, S-N dipoles placed at the straight sections
of the storage rings.
There are two sorts of insertion device - the
wiggler and the undulator.
Although at first glance they seem similar,
differences in the amplitude of the oscillatory
path executed by the electrons as they pass
along the array of magnets result in strikingly
different emission spectra.
The periodicity of the magnet arrays in wigglers
and undulators are lambda_w and lambda_u,
respectively, and are of the order of several
millimetres to a few tens of cm, depending
intimately on the magnets’ B-field and the
range of photon energies the insertion device
has been designed for.
Perhaps the parameter that best distinguishes
undulators from wigglers is the so-called
K-parameter.
This expresses the ratio between the maximum
angular excursion of the electrons due to
the magnet array, phi-max, to the natural
opening angle of the synchrotron radiation,
1/gamma.
K is therefore equal to phi-max times gamma.
It emerges from a simple calculation of the
Lorentz forces that this is equal to eB0/mck_u,w,
where k_u or w is the wavevector 2pi/lambda_u
or w, of the magnet array.
This can be expressed in practical units as
being equal to 0.934 times lambda_u or w in
cm multiplied by B0 in Tesla.
Insertion devices for which K is a large number,
that is, the electron angular excursions far
exceed the natural opening angle 1/gamma,
are wigglers.
Undulators have much smaller K-values, typically
somewhere between 0.3 and 3.
We begin with a description of wigglers.
One can think of a wiggler simply as a bank
of bending magnets in series.
If the wiggler consists of N periods of lambda_w,
there are 2N bending magnets.
The output power would thus be 2N times as
powerful as a single bending magnet having
the same design parameters.
The horizontal angular spread of radiation
emerging from wigglers is equal to phi-max
and is measured in a few mrad.
Also, the spectral features of wigglers are
essentially the same as from a bending magnet
- the spectra are broadband, although the
flux is larger because of the 2N poles.
The power output from a wiggler has a very
similar form to that already provided for
bending magnets in the second video last week.
The factor of 0.633 is half that of that given
for bending magnets, 1.266, because in this
expression, the MAXIMUM B-field B0 is given,
and this drops to zero in between the poles,
whereas for the bending magnets, B is constant.
If one plugs in typical values for the electron
energy, magnet field strength, wiggler length,
and beam current, one obtains an output radiative
power measured in several kW, and can be an
order of magnitude higher still for the most
powerful of these devices.
Thermal management of this is therefore critical
in order to avoid optical elements downstream
of the wiggler at the beamline being destroyed.
The output power after monochromatization
is of the order of 10 mW, thus the efficiency
of wigglers when operated at a quasi-single
wavelength is of the order of 10^-6.
Their brilliance typically span a range of
10^13 to 10^17 ph/s/mm2/mrad2/0.1%BW.
How does one transition from a wiggler to
an undulator?
As already mentioned, undulators have a much
lower K-value, being close to unity.
From the expression for K, we see there are
in principle two variables we could change
to achieve this.
Either one decreases the magnetic field strength,
or otherwise, shorten the ID period, lambda_u
or w.
Reducing the magnetic field strength is a
bad idea, as this will be associated with
an unacceptable drop-off in the power output.
Instead, undulators generally have shorter
periods, lambda_u (though they remain still
of the order of several cm when designed to
generate soft x-rays and ultraviolet radiation,
as we shall see shortly).
So, although undulators may seem at first
glance to look similar to wigglers, the main
differences being in a shortening of the magnet
period and a consequent reduction in K, the
spectra look very different the wigglers produce
broadband radiation, while undulators are
characterised by narrow peaks of high intensity
at regular intervals in energy.
This begs the question, Why?
The reduction in K means that the emission
lobes with natural opening angle +/- 1/gamma
will now overlap.
This overlap means that they interfere with
one another, and consequently only certain
wavelengths will interfere constructively.
So what is the condition for constructive
interference?
Consider this schematic figure.
Radiation is emitted at time t = 0 at point
A. After a time t = T’ the electron has
moved one undulation downstream to point B
along the path S, while the radiation that
originated at A has propagated a distance
cT′.
The difference in these two distances is cT′
− lambda-u, and only that radiation with
a wavelength λn equal to an integral fraction
1/n of this will interfere constructively.
The precise derivation for this condition
for destructive interference is straightforward
but fairly long winded - for those interested
in understanding this more deeply, it is given
step-by-step in my text book “Introduction
to Synchrotron Radiation - Techniques and
Applications”.
For now, however, the condition is given without
derivation here for radiation along the central
axis of the undulator.
This expression can be re-expressed in practical
units, as shown here.
As a rule of thumb, for most 3rd-generation
facilities, the fraction 13.056 lambda_u/E^2
in cm/GeV^2 is close to (normally a little
larger than) unity, lets say, four, and thus
nlambda_n is approximately 4 + 2K^2.
This is only an exceedingly rough guideline,
and can change substantially depending on
the undulator design.
Let’s go with it for the time being (it’s
not a bad approximation, for example, for
the undulator serving the Materials Science
beamline at the Swiss Light Source).
Let us consider, for example, the fifth harmonic
(n = 5), and a K-value of 1.5.
This results in 5 times lambda_5 = 8.5, and
therefore lambda_5, the wavelength selected
at the fifth harmon = 1.7 Angstroms.
But this seems to imply that one can only
select very specific wavelengths.
If for one reason or another one wants to
access a wavelength in between the maxima,
shown schematically here with the yellow arrow,
or indeed if one wants to SCAN the energy
continuously, how does one go about this?
Again, the clue is in our expression for K.
We cannot easily change either gamma, the
storage-ring energy, or lambda_u, the undulator
period, but we CAN change B0, the maximum
B-field.
If, for example, we increase the field by
driving the upper and lower jaws of the undulator
magnet array together,
K will increase.
The term on the right hand side of our expression
for the condition for constructive interference
also increases, and thus for a given n, lambda_n
will also increase (and the photon energy
will DECREASE).
We therefore need only to adjust the gap size
so that the spectrum contracts along the energy
axis until a spectral maximum lies at our
energy (or wavelength) of interest.
Undulators are therefore tuned by varying
the gap between the poles of the magnet array.
So, for example, a gap size of 5.5 mm might
produce an undulator-spectrum such as shown
here, while decreasing this to 4.5 mm will
access a different set of maxima.
One cannot decrease the gap size to arbitrarily
small values.
Below a certain gap, the weak halo of electrons
that generally surround the main electron
beam will collide with the magnets and quickly
destroy them, and also produce a high flux
of so-called Bremsstrahlung, containing photon
energies as high as the storage-ring energy,
in the hard gamma-ray regime.
So any given undulator will have a design
minimum gap size.
In order to tune from low to high energies,
therefore, one proceeds as follows.
The gap is closed to its minimum allowed value,
here 4 mm.
In this example, the first harmonic is inaccessible
as the beamline was designed for energies
above about 5 keV.
So we begin with the second harmonic.
This will drift to higher energies from, in
this example, approximately 4 keV to 5.5 keV,
as the gap is opened, as shown here.
Opening the gap still further is thereafter
no longer profitable, as the energy now becomes
accessible using the next harmonic, the third
harmonic, at the smallest gap, for which the
power output is highest.
Thus, one jumps repeatedly from one harmonic
to the next as soon as that next harmonic
can access the energy with the smallest allowed
gap.
The photon emittance of undulators is the
narrowest of all 3rd generation sources, being
approximately equal to 1/sqrt(nN) gamma, where
small n is the harmonic number, and large
N is the number of periods in the undulator
array.
This is measured in a few microradians to
a few tens of microradian.
Don’t forget, however, that in the horizontal
plane, the emittance is much larger due to
contributions for the electron beam.
Even in the vertical direction, the electron
contribution will dominate, but less so.
In addition the relative spectral width of
the odd harmonics (which for subtle reasons
that lie outside the scope of this introductory
course, are more intense and narrower than
the even harmonics), is given by lambda_n/Delta
lambda_n = small n times large N.
The spectrally integrated power from undulators
is much less than that from wigglers, by an
order of magnitude, while their peak intensities
are generally significantly higher.
Undulators are, at about 10^-4, therefore
approximately 100 times more efficient than
wigglers and pose a less severe problem regarding
thermal management, though this can still
be significant if one considers that the beam
divergence is much smaller than for wigglers,
hence the areal power density on the first
optical elements before monochromatization
can be higher still than for wigglers.
The brilliance of undulators is approximately
10^18 to 10^21 ph/s/mm2/mrad2/0.1%BW, three
orders of magnitude larger than for wigglers.
We finish this video by briefly mentioning
that the polarisation of the light produced
by undulators can be adjusted so that any
desired polarisation can be achieved regarding
both its angle around the emission axis (i.e.,
anywhere between conventional linear horizontal
polarisation and linear vertical) and its
degree of ellipticity, between linear and
fully circular.
This is achieved using a so-called APPLE undulator.
Both the upper and lower magnet arrays are
split lengthways in two, and one subset can
be shifted longitudinally with respect to
the other.
Shown here are just five possible configurations.
of linear horizontal (LH), linear vertical
(LV), linear tilted (LT), right-circularly
polarised (RCP) and left-circularly polarised
(LCP).
This capability can be crucial to the success
of certain spectroscopic techniques such as,
to name just one example, in x-ray magnetic
circular dichroism (XMCD).
In summary, you have learnt in this video
how electrons are steered, focussed, and squeezed
in the magnet lattice, while the physics of
insertion devices has also been described.
In the next and final video of this week,
the physics of diffraction-limited storage
rings and XFELs will be covered.