Welcome to the third and final video of Week
4 of this introductory course on synchrotrons
and x-ray free-electron lasers!
This video completes our discussion of synchrotron,
or machine physics, with a description of
the two new kids on the block, diffraction-limited
storage rings, and x-ray free-electron lasers.
Diffraction-limited storage rings, or DLSRs,
represent the next refinement in synchrotron
performance, the “fourth generation” facilities.
The name perhaps slightly over-eggs their
performance, as none of the planned facilities
will be truly diffraction limited, at least
for photon energies much above a few keV.
Nonetheless, they are a major step towards
this goal, and promise game-changing improvements
in many techniques.
In the Summer of 2016, the first of this next
generation, MAX-IV in Lund, Sweden, came on
line, and others follow close behind, notably
Sirius in Brazil, and upgrades to the ESRF
in Grenoble, France, and the APS at the Argonne
National Labs in Illinois.
Following these are, among others, the ALS
in Berkeley, the Swiss Light Source, and SPring8
in Japan, to name just three.
So what defines a DLSR?
In simple terms, it is a significant improvement
in the horizontal emittance compared to that
of third-generation facilities.
Remember our discussion in the first video
of this week about the relative contributions
of the electron and photon beams to the emittance?
Associated with the bending magnet double-bend
achromat system is a lower limit to the electron
emittance in the orbital plane, which for
typical bending angles of the order of 10
degrees, is about 5 nm.radians.
This is substantially larger by over an order
of magnitude than that in the vertical direction,
which causes the photon beam to have a very
flat elliptical cross-section.
For many applications,
it would be highly advantageous to have a
significantly rounder beam.
A cursory glance at the equation describing
the horizontal emittance of DBAs should provide
a clue as to how we might achieve this.
The emittance depends on the third power of
the bending angle theta associated with a
single bending-magnet dipole, hence a reduction
in this by a factor F would decrease the emittance
by a factor F-cubed.
One can also reduce gamma, as the emittance
depends on the square of this.
However, the flux increases strongly with
gamma, so only a moderate reduction can be
tolerated.
For example, the upgrade of the APS to a DLSR
is likely to involve a reduction of the storage-ring
energy from 7 to 6 GeV.
Reducing theta to improve the emittance seems
such an obvious route to follow, you might
wonder why this wasn’t taken long ago.
The reasons for this are purely technological.
Until recently, the machining, engineering
and vacuum capabilities were limited such
that dividing a given arc sector from a double-bend
achromat, or at best a triple-bend achromat
(such as employed at the Swiss Light Source)
to an arc sector containing, for example,
seven dipole magnets, would have increased
the length of such a sector from 10 to 20
meters to perhaps sixty or seventy, taking
up valuable and expensive real-estate.
In addition, the potential for small misalignments
along the storage ring with so many more elements
involved would almost certainly have cancelled
out any theoretical advantages.
Advances in computer numerical control of
machining of magnet yokes and other metallic
components, however, now mean that dipoles,
quadrupoles, and sextupoles can be fabricated
in a small fraction of the size previously
possible, and with micron precision with regards
to their relative positions.
So, instead of making separate components
and joining them together, each element being
independently adjustable, the sectors of DLSRs
are made of just one or two components, each
machined from a single block of metal, and
containing several magnet-lattice elements
together.
In this manner, multiple-bend achromats (MBAs)
containing up to nine bend magnets per arc-sector,
can now be fabricated.
The second improvement that has allowed this
change in fabrication approach has been in
vacuum technology.
Accompanied with miniaturisation is a reduction
in pumping efficiency through side ports to
vacuum pumps.
To circumvent this, many DLSRs now employ
coatings on the inside of the vacuum vessels
called nonevaporable getters, or NEGs, which,
below a base pressure easily achieved using
conventional pumping, can then obtain the
desired ultimate pressures of less than a
picoBar (or 10^-9 mBar) by chemically trapping
the residual gas molecules.
So, many third generation facilities are now
either undergoing or planning to undergo upgrades
to use multiple-bend achromats, producing
an improvement in horizontal emittance by
one to two orders of magnitude, ***** as shown
here.
An interesting figure of merit M = ehC3/E2,
is plotted here as a function of storage-ring
circumference, big C. From our equation describing
how the emittance varies with bending radius
theta (which is approximately proportional
to the storage ring circumference) and the
storage-ring energy, we should expect that
large rings with moderate ring energies should
produce the lowest horizontal emittances.
This figure of merit, M, weighs the achieved
emittance by these two factors in order to
“level the playing field”.
In other words, although a large ring at moderate
or low energy might have a better performance
than a smaller ring with high storage-ring
energies, if one factors the circumference
and energy in to this, one sees how well the
facility operates given its fundamental limitations.
This is shown in this graph.
So, which fields are likely to profit most
from the improved emittance of DLSRs?
Although the large majority of techniques
will profit at least modestly from this, some
will undergo a quantum leap in performance.
The low emittance associated with DLSRs means
that either the source size or the divergence
can be reduced significantly, or indeed, the
improvement can be divided between these two
properties, as desired.
A smaller source size for a given divergence
compared to 3rd generation facilities means
that scanning techniques such as scanning
transmission x-ray microscopy, scanning x-ray
absorption spectroscopy, or scanning x-ray
fluorescence spectroscopy, will all profit
by an amount similar to the improvement in
emittance.
This will mean, however, that the optics used
to focus the beam to the sample have specifications
that match the beam properties - it is pointless
having an almost perfectly parallel and tight
beam if the optics then blow this up to values
associated with third-generation facilities.
Minimising the horizontal divergence will
increase the transverse coherence length in
the horizontal plane by one to two orders
of magnitude and increase the coherent fraction
accordingly.
So techniques which exploit the coherent properties
of the beam will especially profit from an
upgrade to a DLSR.
In addition, because the divergence is so
much smaller, the footprint of the beam on
optics such as reflecting or focussing mirrors
will be smaller, relaxing a little their performance
specifications.
As an example of how a trade-off between divergence
and spot size can sometimes be the best solution,
consider the case of macromolecular crystallography.
Often protein crystals have dimensions measured
in microns, demanding a tight focus of the
incident beam, either resulting in flux loss
if this is achieved by slitting the beam down
to smaller cross-sections, or otherwise a
higher divergence, which means that the diffraction
pattern can become unacceptably blurred (we
discuss this in more detail later in the course).
On the other hand, if one instead focusses
not on the sample, but instead on the detector,
in order to sharpen up the pattern, the beam
may be unacceptably large at the crystal itself.
The reduced emittance of DLSRs means that
both the spot size at the crystal sample and
the desired small size of the diffraction
maxima can be accommodated simultaneously.
We now close this, our second week on machine
physics, with an overview of x-ray free-electron
lasers.
Four such facilities already exist, whereby
the LCLS and SACLA provide radiation down
to one Angstrom.
A further three facilities that will also
provide both soft and hard x-rays are under
construction in Switzerland, Germany, and
South Korea.
XFELs are defined by their exceedingly high
peak brilliance, some 10^9 or even 10^10 times
that achievable using synchrotrons.
The pulse produced by XFELs are very short,
typically between a femtosecond and 100 fs.
What is the motivation for the construction
of XFELs?
X-rays provide resolution down to the Angstrom
and sub-Angstrom scale, but are limited in
their temporal resolution to that of the pulse
width of the bunches, measured in a few tens
of picosecond.
However, many fundamental and technologically
important processes are known to occur at
significantly shorter time-scales - many chemical
reactions occur on the time scale of molecular
vibrations, and these are measured in femtoseconds.
Hence the motivation to build XFELs was to
combine the spatial resolution of x-rays with
a temporal resolution down to the fs-scale,
previously only possible using lasers in the
visible, or near visible regime.
This table summarises some of the most pertinent
differences between synchrotron and XFEL light.
Let’s consider this line for line.
First, the repetition rate of the x-ray pulses,
which is fairly constant in the case of synchrotrons
at a few hundred megahertz, can take on greatly
different values at XFELs.
This is because the electrons pass just once
down the XFEL linac instead of being stored
in a ring, so are not constrained by this
condition.
So, for example, LCLS-I and SACLA have repetition
rates of approximately 100 Hz, while the planned
pattern for the European XFEL in Hamburg is
to deliver packets of a few thousand pulses
at 4.5 MHz (each packet therefore lasting
0.6 milliseconds) 10 times a second.
One of the two most important features of
XFELs, as already mentioned, is the pulse
duration, which is three orders of magnitude
shorter than at synchrotrons.
The average number of photons per second,
and therefore the average radiant power, is
fairly similar between a single harmonic peak
from an undulator at a synchrotron and from
the LCLS.
For many experiments, such as macromolecular
crystallography at the CXI station at the
LCLS, this unfiltered radiation, with an average
bandwidth of a few tens of an electronvolt
for hard x-rays, is used without monochromatization.
Most experiments at synchrotrons do use monochromator,
however, which cuts down the arrival rate
of photons to approximately 10^13 ph/s.
For those experiments at XFELs which do monochromatize
the beam, the arrival rate can vary between
approximately a tenth of the unfiltered radiation
to nothing at all.
This is because the bandwidth of the monochromator
typically used at XFELs is typically narrower
than gaps in the single-shot spectra produced
by SASE at XFELs, explained a little later.
Much effort is being devoted to improving
this situation in new seeding techniques and
novel optics.
The second highly important difference between
XFELs and synchrotrons is the number of photons
delivered per pulse, which is five orders
of magnitude or greater for XFELs than for
synchrotrons, even before monochromatization.
The peak power emerging from XFELs is therefore
approximately 10 orders of magnitude greater
than at synchrotrons.
Such enormous values mean that XFEL experiments
can be fundamentally different to those at
synchrotrons, as the samples are often obliterated
by a single shot from the XFEL.
We discuss this in detail towards the end
of the course.
Interestingly, however, XFELs are far less
wasteful than synchrotrons with regards to
their efficiency.
As was just mentioned, some XFEL experiments
use the entire available number of photons
without monochromatization, which at the LCLS-I
equates to half a watt.
Even those experiments that monochromatic
the XFEL beam work at up to 10% efficiency.
In contrast, the difference between the unfiltered
power output from an undulator beamline, at
approximately 1 kW (three orders of magnitude
higher than that of the entire LCLS) and that
emerging after the monochromator, approximately
30 mW, is approximately four to five orders
of magnitude!
Shown here is a quick reminder of the overview
of the architecture of XFELs shown in the
first week of this course.
Let us discuss the most important components
of this, beginning with the low-emittance
gun.
Electron bunches are produced by irradiating
a semiconductor or metallic surface with a
femtosecond laser to produce photoemission.
The timing of this laser pulse is so chosen
that the resulting electron cloud is then
accelerated by an RF cavity, which reduces
the impact on the emittance of space-charge
effects.
The emittance emerging from this system is
of the order of magnitude of 1 mm.mrad in
both transverse directions, while the peak
current is approximately 50 amps.
However, in order to induce SASE, the process
responsible for the formation of the high-intensity
femtosecond x-ray pulses, the peak electron
current needs to be several kiloamperes, in
other words, two orders of magnitude higher,
as it enters the XFEL undulator.
This increase in current is achieved using
one or more bunch compressors.
The RF phase in the first accelerator LINAC
after the low-emittance gun is adjusted to
allow the electrons to ‘surf’ down the
slope of the sinusoidal RF field — the leading
electrons are thus accelerated less than those
electrons towards the back of the bunch (this
phenomenon is referred to as ‘chirping’).
Nonetheless, the electrons’ velocities are
so close to the speed of light that their
differences are far too small to allow the
faster electrons at the back of the bunch
to catch up with the slower electrons positioned
further forward and thereby squeeze the bunch
length.
Instead, the bunch passes through a magnetic
four-dipole chicane.
The trailing (high-energy) electrons execute
a shorter path on account of their being less
deviated by the magnetic field.
In this manner, they are able to catch up
with the less energetic leading electrons,
which are more deviated by the magnet chicane.
This compression, or compressions, depending
on how many bunch compression stages are included,
thus shortens the bunch length and increases
n_e by a factor of approximately 100.
Once the electron beam has achieved the required
peak-current, it enters the undulator.
Let’s briefly recap the forces an electron
will experience in the presence of an electromagnetic
field.
You may recall that the ratio of these two
forces is equal to -v/c, or -beta.
In this figure, the electric force is shown
in red, while that of the magnetic Lorentz
force is in yellow.
For the highly relativistic electrons entering
the undulator, the ratio of the forces is
to all intents and purposes equal to minus
one.
If the electrons are moving coaxially with
the beam of radiation they have produced by
acceleration, the electric and magnetic forces
cancel out and they will remain unperturbed.
Now let’s perturb the electron beam’s
path by introducing the magnet array of the
XFEL undulator.
This causes the electrons to oscillate, as
we have already discussed in the last video.
Now, because their trajectory is no longer
exactly coaxial with the beam of radiation
(although the deviations shown here are greatly
exaggerated), the electric and magnetic forces
will no longer entirely cancel out.
For the case where the electric component
of the electromagnetic field of the radiation
points in the negative x-direction, the magnetic
field is on the negative y-direction, and
the forces will be as shown here
while half a cycle later of the electromagnetic
field, the forces are a shown here.
The consequence of these unequal forces is
that the electrons begin to be bunched together
to form microbunches (within the conventional
bunch generated by the low-emittance gun and
bunch compression), separated by a distance
equal to the wavelength of the light they
generate and are bathed in.
In the laboratory frame of reference, this
is equal to the pole magnet periodicity divided
by gamma, hence is of the order of a few microns.
Each microbunch therefore has a duration of
a few femtoseconds to a few tens of femtoseconds.
FELs deliver femtosecond x-radiation.
As the
microbunches begin to form, the electrons
become more squeezed together, resulting in
an increase in the instantaneous current.
This therefore produces a intenser undulator
radiation, which in turn acts more strongly
on the electrons, further enhancing the micro
bunching process.
This runaway effect is called SASE - self-amplified
spontaneous emission.
So why are these SASE radiation microbunches
(the XFEL pulses) so intense?
Before the SASE effect kicks in, emission
from individual electrons is purely stochastic
- in other words there is no correlation between
their emission regarding the phase - the system
is noncoherent, just as at synchrotrons.
The total electromagnetic field amplitude
is therefore a vector sum of the individual
contributions, each having the same magnitude,
but a completely random orientation.
From statistics, we can predict that this
vector sum, the total magnitude, is proportional
to the square root of the number of contributing
emitters, n_e, the number of electrons in
the bunch.
The INTENSITY, which is proportional to the
square of the amplitude, is therefore proportional
to n_e.
Now, in the case of the bunch after the SASE
process has induced the formation of the microbunches,
these microbunches are separated form each
other by integral numbers of the radiation
wavelength, hence emission is highly coherent
- the emitted wavelets are all in phase, and
therefore the vector addition of these contributions
all lie in a straight line - the amplitude
is proportional to n_e.
The intensity is proportional to n_e squared,
and is thus n_e times more intense than for
the non coherent bunch.
But n_e is of the order of 10^9 or 10^10,
and thus XFEL pulses are more intense by a
this factor.
The performance of an XFEL is encapsulated
in the dimensionless so-called Pierce parameter,
or XFEL parameter, given here.
Although different XFELs might have quite
disparate values for lambda_u, gamma, and
K, the one-third power dependence means that
the XFEL parameter is fairly constant between
facilities, at around 5 x 10^-4.
This value describes both the instantaneous
bandwidth of the XFEL radiation, and the ratio
of the photon-beam power to the electron-beam
power.
The XFEL gain length L_G is inversely proportional
to the XFEL parameter, and typically takes
on values of a few meters.
It describes length along the undulator required
to increase the radiative power by a factor
e, or about 2.72.
As the potential total power increase before
saturation of SASE begins is typically seven
or so orders of magnitude, the undulator needs
to be a length no shorter than the natural
logarithm of 10^7 times L_G, which equates
to several tens of meters!
This is nearly two orders of magnitude longer
than undulatory used at synchrotrons!
Lastly, let us take a brief look at a typical
SASE spectrum.
Although the instantaneous bandwidth is, at
5 x 10^-4, similar to that provided by silicon
monochromator at synchrotrons, the centre
of the spectrum can jump back and forth by
a few tens of eV, depending on which mode
was randomly selected by the SASE process.
The time-averaged spectral width is therefore
an order of magnitude larger, at around 5
x 10^-3.
So, although XFELs provide radiation with
exceedingly coherent radiation in the transverse
direction, due to its unmatched parallelity
and small source size, the longitudinal coherence
length is poor.
In summary, this video has provided some insight
into the operational principles behind DLSRs
and XFELs.
DLSRs promise significant jumps in performance
compared to 3rd-generation synchrotrons, and
may thereby also open up some entirely new
experimental methods.
XFELs, because of their short pulse lengths
and high intensities, represent a paradigm
shift in x-ray science, and promise new experimental
vistas, particularly in time-resolved studies
in fields as diverse as macromolecular biology
and heterogeneous catalysis.
Next week, we will discuss how synchrotron
radiation is further manipulated regarding
monochromatization, reflection, and focussing,
plus other instrumental aspects associated
with beamline design.