Welcome to Week 5 of this introductory course
on synchrotrons and x-ray free-electron lasers!
Last week, we finished our discussion of the
generation of synchrotron light and its properties.
This radiation as it emerges from the source,
be that a bending magnet or an insertion device,
is, to a greater or lesser extent both divergent
and polychromatic.
This week, we discuss how we manipulate this
radiation at beamlines, including the role
of the so-called “front end”; mirrors
and other focussing optics; monochromators,
including the suppression of harmonics; and
finally different types of photon detectors.
This first video is primarily concerned with
the most important features of the front end;
and then a discussion of mirrors and other
focussing optics.
So, let us begin with an overview of elements
of a beamline.
The generic setup shown schematically here
is just one possible configuration, but most
beamlines follow this concept in general terms.
In the discussions this week, we divide up
the beamline into the front end,
primary optics, including mirrors and monochromators,
and beamline instrumentation, in other words,
those components most commonly (though not
necessarily always) found in the experimental
hutch, the furthest point downstream of the
beamline.
The purpose of the front end is to “clean
up” the source radiation before it impinges
on the primary optics and other components.
Its primary functions include monitoring the
position of the x-ray beam, normally at two
or more positions, so that the position can
be triangulated and the stability monitored,
also allowing feedback to improve this, if
necessary.
In most cases, very high-energy gamma radiation
up to the energy of the electrons within the
storage ring is produced as an inevitable
consequence of the electrons occasionally
colliding with the residual gas molecules
that remain even at pressures as low as 10^-10
mbar.
This radiation, although only generating a
total power measured in a few tens of mW throughout
the entire facility, is highly ionising and
must be blocked.
Due to the very high energies, Bremsstrahlung
is not deflected by, for example, the first
reflecting mirror, but simply passes through
it.
So the desired synchrotron radiation (with
photon energies typically well over three
orders of magnitude lower) IS deflected by
the mirror, so the Bremsstrahlung blocker
can be placed behind this.
This needs to be made of a block of heavy
metal (typically tungsten) with a thickness
measured in several tens of centimetre.
Only such a dense obstacle is sufficient to
absorb Bremsstrahlung.
The acceptance angle of the beamline is defined
by a beam-defining apertures, discussed in
a little more detail shortly.
Radiation in an unwanted spectral region can
also be removed using filters.
Finally, in many, but not all, instances a
window that is transparent to the x-rays of
interest for the beamline is placed as one
of the final components of the front end,
in order to protect and isolate the storage
ring in case the vacuum at the beamline suddenly
fails, thereby preventing the entire ring
from venting, which would result in the entire
facility being out of operation for days.
Beam-position monitors can come in various
shapes, sizes, and working principle.
The simplest is simply a thin wire that can
be traversed across the beam, which generates
a photocurrent proportional to the beam intensity.
This provides one coordinate of the beam position;
the orthogonal coordinate can be obtained
by placing a second wire monitor at 90 degrees
to the first.
Both x- and y- coordinates can be simultaneously
determined using four blades in a configuration
as shown here.
The beam halo is sufficiently intense to generate
a photocurrent in the blades.
By moving the four blades together left/right
and up/down, the difference in the photocurrent
between oppositely facing pairs can be equalised
using comparator electronics, and the beam
position thereby determined.
Lastly, a more modern approach is to use thin
transparent windows (often diamond) coated
with an array of ultrathin metallic pads.
This delivers not only directly the beam position,
but also the profile of the beam.
The acceptance angle of the source needs to
be defined.
This is obvious in the case of bending-magnet
sources, as they sweep angles far larger than
typically desired for experiments, as we discussed
last week.
Even for undulators, however, the radiation
does not immediately fall to zero outside
the angles +/-1/gamma, but instead contains
a substantial amount of radiation, especially
of softer x-rays.
Remember, it is the soft x-rays that interact
most strongly with matter, so often (at least
in the case of hard x-ray beamlines), the
aperture cuts this out.
In order to cope with the high heat load associated
with this, the aperture is normally conical,
thereby spreading the absorbed energy over
a larger area, and is water cooled.
Nonetheless, the central part of the beam
that passes through the aperture may still
contain an unacceptably large fraction of
unwanted x-rays (usually soft x-rays) that
need to be removed.
This can only be performed using a high-pass
absorption filter.
The specifications for this are strict - it
should efficiently absorb soft x-rays (typically
up to approximately 5 keV), and will thus
heat up substantially, meaning the filter
must have a high melting temperature and remain
mechanically robust.
This heat also needs to be efficiently dissipated,
requiring good thermal conductivity.
Essentially there is only one material that
fits all these requirements - diamond (which,
incidentally is the best known heat conductor,
even surpassing copper or silver).
Thin, artificially grown, diamond windows
are commercially available, and can be brazed
onto a water-cooled vacuum flange, as shown
here.
Obviously, this high-pass filter is not used
for beamlines operating in the tender or soft
x-ray regime.
We now turn our attention to the primary optics
and other focussing elements.
For the remainder of this video, we will discuss
x-ray mirrors and x-ray focussing elements.
The topic of monochromator will be dealt with
separately in the next video.
The primary optics typically include one or
more mirrors which may or may not also focus,
plus a dispersive instrument, the monochromator,
used to select a certain, normally narrow,
range of wavelengths.
In the second week of this course, we established
that at sufficiently shallow incident angles,
x-rays can be made to reflect off a flat surface
via total external reflection.
The upper limit to the incident angle, you
will remember, is given by the critical angle,
alpha_c, which is equal to the square-root
of 2 delta, where delta is the refractive-index
decrement.
delta is itself directly proportional to the
electron density rho of the reflecting material
and to the square of the x-ray wavelength
(and thus inversely proportional to the square
of the wave vector or photon energy).
So alpha_c decreases as 1/the photon energy
and increases with the square root of the
electron density.
Even the most collimated synchrotron beam
has a finite cross-section, with a height
typically of the order of a millimetre at
the primary optics, which may be 20 m or further
downstream of the source.
This means, as the photon energy increases,
the critical angle gets smaller, and the footprint
of the beam becomes longer and longer as one
is forced to reduce the incident angle.
Below an angle (given in radians) equal to
the beam height divided by the length of the
mirror (normally measured in a few tens of
centimetres), in other words, a few milliradians,
or between 0.1 and 0.2 degrees, a substantial
fraction of the beam will spill over the ends
of the mirror.
Normally, fabrication of the x-ray mirror
is limited to approximately a metre or less.
This overspill problem is resolved not by
making longer and longer mirrors, but instead
by coating the mirror (made almost always
either from silicon or fused silica glass)
with a layer of high-density material, most
commonly rhodium and/or platinum, in order
to bump up the critical angle, which, we’ve
just reiterated, is proportional to the square
root of the electron density.
Mirrors thus commonly have stripes of coatings
of different density, so by a simple lateral
movement of them, one can switch from one
material to another.
So, for example, the uncoated part of a silicon
mirror has a critical angle approximately
3 times smaller than that part coated with
a platinum layer.
This aspect of the energy-dependence of the
critical angle can be used to advantage.
When one selects a certain photon energy,
h-nu, using a monochromator at a beamline,
harmonics of this radiation, that is, at 2
h-nu, 3 h-nu, etc, will also be selected.
Radiation from synchrotrons is polychromatic
- in the case of bending magnets and wigglers,
it is broad band, but also even for undulators,
the maxima are integer multiples (m) of the
fundamental energy.
Therefore, harmonic signal will also pass
through to the beamline unless measures are
taken to circumvent this.
Some other strategies are detailed in the
second video this week, but one of the most
effective ways to achieve harmonic suppression
is explained here in the context of mirror
reflectivity.
Let us consider a particular photon energy,
highlighted here with the red arrow.
If we set the incident angle to be only marginally
below the critical angle for the mirror at
this photon energy, then the double of this
energy, i.e., the second harmonic, . . .
(shown here in green) will have its critical
angle BELOW the incident angle and will be
only inefficiently reflected.
The 3rd harmonic (here shown in blue) will
be still less reflected.
As an example, a silicon mirror tilted at
an angle of 0.2 degrees will efficiently reflect
8-keV radiation, for which the critical angle
is 0.23 degrees.
However, the critical angles for the second
harmonic at 16 keV and third at 24 keV are
0.114 and 0.076 degrees respectively, both
above the incident angle.
Their reflectivities are, approximately 8
x 10^-3 and 1.4 x 10^-3, respectively.
In some instances, such as in most diffraction
experiments, a still higher degree of harmonic
rejection is required.
One commonly-used approach is to allow the
radiation to bounce off a second mirror at
the same angle, thus squaring the degree of
reflectivity, which in this instance would
be 6.4 x 10^-5 and 2 x 10^-6, respectively.
Before we move on to discuss aspects of focussing,
it is briefly mentioned here that the reason
that mirrors are not fabricated with lengths
much more than a metre is because their quality
deteriorates.
The two main properties defining mirror quality
are the so-called “slope error”, i.e.,
the amount of wobbliness of the surface over
macroscopic distances (typically measured
in microradians); and the atomic roughness,
measured in a few Angstroms.
This does not mean the surface needs to be
atomically flat without any imperfections
along the entire length of the mirror, but
it should maintain on average the desired
specifications within at least one or two
multiples of the coherence lengths of the
radiation being reflected, which can thus
be of the order of several hundred microns
in the case of transverse coherence.
We now turn to aspects of x-ray focussing.
Before we discuss specific examples, some
fundamental features need to be clarified.
The two shapes of primary concern for us will
be the ellipse and the parabola, and, in a
moment, their spherical or cylindrical approximations.
Ellipses and parabolas are conic sections.
An ellipse is a section for which the sectional
plane subtends an angle greater than phi with
the cone axis, where phi is the opening half
angle of the cone.
A parabola is described by the intersection
between a cone and a plane for which the cone-axis
- plane angle is exactly phi.
Their mathematical equations are shown here.
Ellipses and parabolas are interesting because,
when using ray optics, they can focus to an
exact point.
Note that ray optics do not represent reality,
as diffraction effects (i.e., wave optics)
means that no focal spot can be of zero size.
Nonetheless, diffraction effects excluded,
these shapes are in principle aberration-free.
An ellipse will focus a point source to a
point focus if the source lies on one of the
foci of the ellipse, +/- f’ (the prime is
used here, as this is NOT the same as the
focal length, denoted by f).
The distance defined by the reflected rays
between the source and image are all equal
in length (Indeed, you might remember that
one can draw an ellipse by pinning down a
piece of string at two point which then define
the foci, and then putting the string under
tension with a pencil, and moving this from
one end to the other).
Consider the symmetrical path between the
foci, highlighted here in red.
***** This path subtends the shallowest angle
with the ellipse where it is reflected.
This angle is equal to the arctangent of b/f’
and needs to be shallower than the critical
angle for total external reflection.
It is therefore clear that b must be much
smaller than f’, by about three orders of
magnitude.
In this case, f’ is approximately equal
to a, the semi-major axis - in other words,
the foci are exceedingly close to the left
and right hand apexes of the ellipse, and
the ellipse is much, MUCH wider than it is
high.
Ellipses are therefore excellent shapes for
refocussing a small source via reflection.
Parabolas, on the other hand, focus PARALLEL
light to a point, as shown here on the right
hand side.
Although some optics are indeed manufactured
to have either an elliptical or parabolic
profile, especially secondary optical elements,
it is technologically very demanding to fabricate
mirrors and larger focussing elements with
exactly these shapes.
Instead, one often approximates the surface
of ellipses and parabolas with that of a circle
(or sphere for two-dimensionally focussing
elements).
It can be shown, for example, that a cylindrical
surface with a radius R_m equal to a^2/b ***** has
only a very marginal deviation from the elliptical
surface at the symmetrical reflection point,
which was shown in red in the last slide.
Similarly, a circle with radius 2f ***** closely
approximates the profile of a parabola of
the form x^2/a at its apex.
The geometric ray optics described until now,
in which a point source can be perfectly focussed
to another point, are, unsurprisingly, unachievable.
Due to diffraction, no beam with a Gaussian
profile can be focussed to a perfect point
with no physical extent, but instead will
have a minimum beam ‘waist’ diameter 2w_0,
shown here.
The Rayleigh length z_R is the distance along
the propagation direction (z) between this
waist and where the beam’s linear extent
is larger by a factor of square-root of 2
(i.e., where the beam cross-section increases
by a factor of two), and is given by z_R = pi
w_0^2/lambda, where lambda is the beam’s
wavelength.
The validity of this equation assumes w_0
remains significantly larger than lambda,
which certainly holds true for hard x-radiation
of wavelengths of the order of an Angstrom.
The depth of field is twice z_R.
The beam radius w_z at a distance z from the
beam waist is given by w_z = w_0 x sqrt(1
+ (z/z_R)^2),
From this, it can be demonstrated that the
FWHM divergence, big Theta, is related to
w_0 and z_R by Theta = 2w_0/z_r.
Using this relationship, and substituting
for either z_R or w_0, their relationship
to the beam divergence can be derived, as
shown here.
The more focussed the beam (large Theta),
the smaller the focal spot, and the shorter
the depth of field.
As an example, a Gaussian beam of 1-Angstrom
radiation, focussed using parabolic optics
with Θ = 10 mrad (0.57 degrees), will produce
a spot size of 6.4 nm with a depth of field
of 2.55 μm.
A ten-times more gentle focus of Θ = 1 mrad
can only be focussed to 64 nm, although the
DOF will increase a hundredfold to 255 μm.
The cost of strong demagnification is thus
an accompanying rapid (inverse square) reduction
in the depth of field.
The lensmaker equation states that the reciprocal
of the focus of a lens, 1/f, equals the sum
of the reciprocals of the source - lens distance
p and lens - image distance q.
The degree of magnification is q/p - hence
values greater than unity will blow up the
image size compared to the source, while demagnification
with q/p less than one, will focus down the
image to sizes smaller than the source.
Note also that an m-fold demagnification (q/p
= 1/m) will be accompanied by an m-fold increase
in beam divergence, and vice-versa.
This is merely a restatement of the fact that
the beam emittance will remain constant.
The Coddington equations relate p, q and f,
with the bending radii R_m and R_s.
R_m is the “meridional” bending radius
in the plane perpendicular to the mirror or
reflecting element (including, for example,
a diffracting crystal) which also includes
the beam axis.
R_m thus focusses in the transverse plane
perpendicular to the bending plane, which
in the case shown here is the vertical direction.
R_s is the sagittal bending radius required
to focus in the direction perpendicular to
the meridional focussing, here horizontally.
As we should now know, theta is in general
small for mirrors, as will be sine theta.
Hence R_m for mirrors are typically measured
in kilometres, while R_s, which is directly
proportional to sine theta, may only be a
few centimetres.
Focussing can also be achieved by bending
gratings or crystals in monochromators, as
we will see in the next video.
In general, the incident angles on dispersive
monochromator elements is larger, and the
meridional and sagittal radii less radically
different from each other.
A convenient shape for achieving sagittal
and meridional focussing in one element is
the toroidal mirror.
This is a cap-section of a ring torus with
ring radius R_s and torus outer radius R_m,
as shown here.
As R_m is in general significantly larger
than R_s, particularly for mirrors, the ring
torus is very thin, much like a bicycle inner
tube.
In general, toroidal mirrors have fixed surfaces
machined out of a solid block of material,
that is, neither R_m or R_s can be varied.
Kirkpatrick-Baez, or K-B, mirrors provide
independent orthogonal focussing using two
cylindrically bent surfaces.
This has the advantage that vertical and horizontal
focussing are decoupled.
Indeed, it is possible to dynamically bend
the mirrors using a flexor system, thus allowing
adjustment of the position of the focal spot.
The separation of focussing into two stages
does, however, make K-B mirrors more bulky.
We finish this video with a discussion of
refractive and diffractive focussing elements.
Compound refractive lenses, or CRLs, in their
simplest form, consist of holes drilled out
of transparent material such as beryllium.
The focal length is given by the hole radius
R divided by 2 times the number of holes,
n_h, and the refractive-index decrement, delta.
This last parameter is equal to about 2 × 10−6
for Be at 12 keV.
Hence a CRL consisting of an array of thirty
200 μm-diameter holes has a focal length
of approximately 70 cm.
CRLs have the advantage that they are easy
to align in the x-ray beam, they do not divert
the beam axis, and elements can be stacked
after one another to change the focal length.
Their main disadvantages are (a) that the
focal length is proportional to the square
of the x-ray photon energy, which means that
they must be repositioned, restacked, or replaced
if the photon energy is changed; and (b) that
the transmission is in general fairly poor.
A 100-hole CRL made of Be, with walls of 100
μm thickness separating adjacent holes has
a transmission of 0.5 at 12 keV.
In addition, because refraction of x-rays
is so weak, the hole diameter R needs to be
quite small in order to achieve a reasonably
short focal length.
But this can often mean that the beam propagates
through the sides of the holes, where the
deviations from a parabola are large, resulting
in significant optical aberrations.
Much effort has been made in recent years
to fabricate CRLs with parabolic surfaces,
using sophisticated mechanical milling, or
even focussed ion-beam milling.
Lastly, the choice of material depends on
the photon energy range for which the CRL
is being manufactured, the required focal
length, and the acceptable loss in flux due
to absorption.
So, for example, although the attenuation
length of diamond at e.g., 15 keV, is 5 times
smaller than for beryllium, its refractive-index
decrement is more than double that of Be.
Fresnel zone plates, or FZPs, are diffractive
focussing lenses consisting of a set of concentric
rings.
These rings can either be opaque, in which
case light passes through the gaps in between
them, or, in the case of so-called phase-FZPs,
have a specific height for the thicker rings,
in order to enhance diffractive effects by
adjustment of the optical path length.
The general approach of FZPs is to design
them so that light being scattered as it passes
through different parts of the FZP will always
have an integer number of wavelengths path
difference at the focal spot.
So, in the figure shown here, light passing
along path P_n+2 will be longer than that
passing through P_n by an integer number of
wavelengths.
The conditions for constructive interference
and thus the radii of the rings in an FZP
are given here.
See also the website given at the bottom for
a more detailed description.
The width of the outermost ring, Delta r_N,
is equal to the square-root of the wavelength
times the focal length/divided by large N,
the total number of rings.
An FZP of diameter r_N = 100 microns, consisting
of 4000 rings will have an outer ring thickness
of 50 nm.
Such a delicate structure is synthesized by
electron-beam lithography.
Note also that the ultimate resolution of
an FZP is determined by Delta r_N, the outer-ring
thickness, and is equal to a value a little
more than this, by a factor of 1.22.
FZPs are used when requiring the tightest
focus, and values in the range of a few tens
of nm for hard x-rays has been recently achieved.
Lastly, it should be note that the inverse
dependence of the focal length on lambda implies
a linear dependence with photon energy.
This is less severe than the square dependence
of CRLs with energy, which can make FZPs more
attractive for use with unmonochromatized
XFEL radiation, which can have a substantial
bandwidth.
The efficiency of FZPs is in general only
moderate.
The theoretical equation for this is given
here for phase-FZPs, where nu is the ratio
between the absorption index beta and refractive-index
decrement delta and phi - 2 pi delta t/lambda
is the phase shift induced by the x-rays passing
through a ring of thickness t.
The actually achieved efficient is in general
lower than this, as this equation has assumed
that the thin rings of the FZP have zero thickness.
Summarising this first video of week 5, we
have covered the function of the front end;
features of both reflecting an focussing mirrors;
plus a description of compound refractive
lenses and Fresnel zone plates.
In the next video, we cover monochromatization
of synchrotrons using gratings, crystal, or
multilayers.