Welcome to the the second video of Week 5
of this introductory course on synchrotrons
and x-ray free-electron lasers!
In this video, we will familiarise ourselves
with monochromators and the handling of harmonic
signal.
What are monochromators and why do we need
them?
Monochromator, often called “monos” for
short select a certain bandwidth, or set of
bandwidths, of frequencies from synchrotron-radiation
sources.
Bending magnets and wigglers provide very
broadband radiation, and for the large majority
of experiments, only a small fraction of this
in the form of a narrow range of energies,
is used.
Even the bandwidths of undulator spectral
peaks as they emerge is more often than not
insufficient for many types of experiments
and require further monochromatization.
For example, x-ray absorption spectra contain
subtle features that can provide invaluable
chemical and orientational information.
The pre-peak in the XANES spectrum of copper
at its K-absorption edge, highlighted here
with an asterisk, provides information on
the oxidation state.
The width of this peak is approximately 1.7
eV, in other words, approximately one five
hundredth of its energy.
In order to resolve such features, the spectral
bandwidth Delta nu/nu must be better than
this.
On the right a typical macromolecular diffraction
pattern is shown.
If we blow up a portion of this we see that
diffraction spots are only very slightly angularly
separated, and would overlap if the degree
of monochromacity were an order of magnitude
worse.
Depending on the photon-energy range of the
beamline and the demands for flux, different
monochromator types are used.
Soft x-ray beamlines use gratings, while most
hard x-ray beamlines employ monos based on
crystal diffraction.
The tender x-ray regime is also mostly served
by crystal monos, though can use so-called
multilayer monochromators as well.
Multilayer monos are also employed fairly
extensively in the medium hard x-ray regime
as a means to obtain more flux through their
intrinsically larger bandwidths.
A selection of different but representative
monochromator types from synchrotrons around
the world is shown here as a function of photon
energy and periodic spacing, d.
One sees immediately the strong correlation
between photon energy and d-spacing.
This should come as no surprise - a high photon
energy is associated with short wavelengths,
for which one needs a diffraction element
of similar periodic dimensions.
How do grating and crystal monochromator differ
from each other?
Gratings can come in various flavours regarding
their groove profiles, of which three examples
are shown here.
Gratings are typically fabricated via advanced
lithographic and etching techniques on glass
substrates.
Scattering off grating features leads, at
certain angles, to constructive interference
when the difference in the optical path difference
, d(sin theta_i - sin theta_r) is equal to
an integer number of wavelengths.
As we saw in the previous slide, typical grating
periodicities are anywhere between a couple
of hundred nanometers to a few microns.
In the case of a crystal, for which d is a
few Angstroms, interference of hard x-rays
is between successive layers of atomic planes
perpendicular to the scattering vector , which
therefore follows the famous Bragg law .
How is the performance of grating monochromators
affected by the number of illuminated facets
N_f.
To understand this better, we resort to the
use of Argand diagrams again.
We assume that illumination of each facet
is the same, and that therefore the scattering
amplitude is the same.
How these scattered wavelets add up depends
on their relative phase, in other words, how
they interfere with each other.
Let us consider first the case of illumination
of four facets.
If the optical path difference between scattering
off adjacent facets is an integer multiple
of wavelengths, the phase difference will
be an integer multiple of 2 pi, and the scattering
amplitudes will all add up in one direction
to produce a total amplitude four times the
length of the individual scattering amplitude
from one facet . Now let us change the incident
and/or exit angle so that the phase difference
between adjacent facets is pi/12, or 15 degrees.
The vector addition of the four contribution
will begin to curl round on itself and the
total amplitude will decrease .
We see this is still more pronounced for a
phase difference of pi/6, or 30 degrees . Indeed,
at a phase difference of 90 degrees (pi/2),
the vectors will form four sides of a square,
and cancel each other out entirely, shown
here .
At pi and 3pi/2, the same complete destructive
interference will occur, until after a shift
in phase of 2 pi, a maximum is again reached.
Using the same arguments, a similar situation
arises when 8 facets are illuminated.
But now, for a given phase difference, the
degree of destructive interference increases
more rapidly as one moves away from a phase
difference of 2 pi, as more individual scattering
amplitudes are involved and the vector addition
curls round on itself more - the position
and size of the total amplitude as a function
of phase difference between 0 and 2 pi is
shown in the animation in the centre for 8
facets.
The result is that the condition for constructive
interference becomes stricter and consequently
the interference maxima become narrower.
Indeed it can be shown that the relative bandwidth
lambda/Delta lambda is directly proportional
to the number of illuminated facets, N_f.
In modern soft-x-ray monochromators, N_f can
easily be several thousand and bandwidths
comparable and often superior to those demonstrated
by crystals such as silicon, can be achieved.
As was briefly mentioned in the first video
of this week, it is possible to bend dispersive
elements in order to simultaneously disperse
the radiation (monochromatize) and to focus
it.
In spherical-grating monochromator (SGMs)
the grating surface has a concave spherical
form with a radius R_b.
The grating grooves, or lines, are perpendicular
to the so-called Rowland circle, which lies
tangential to the centre of the grating and
has a radius R_R half that of the spherical
grating.
Any source lying somewhere on the Rowland
circle will select a certain wavelength and
refocus it at another position on the Rowland
circle.
Different energies can be selected by moving
the source around the Rowland circle.
Crystal monochromators use single crystals
to select a given energy using Bragg diffraction.
The most common crystal material is silicon.
Silicon has a reasonable thermal conductivity,
and can be efficiently cooled by liquid nitrogen,
in order to minimize the mechanical strain
induced by a local thermal ‘bump’, where
the incoming, polychromatic, beam impinges
on the crystal surface.
Importantly, Si can be produced as a near-perfect
single crystal with linear dimensions up to
tens of centimetres, thanks to its ubiquitous
use in the semiconductor industry, where large
and exceedingly perfect wafers are produced
en masse.
The most common crystallographic orientation
is the (111).
Bragg’s law predicts that if one were to
have a perfect, non-absorbing and very weakly
scattering crystal of infinite depth, and
a perfectly collimated incoming polychromatic
beam, the bandwidth of the selected radiation
would be infinitely narrow.
However, there is always some residual beam
divergence, slightly misaligned crystallites
making up the (imperfect) single crystal (this
is referred to as the ‘mosaicity’), and
finite absorption and extinction depths.
These all contribute to a given crystal always
selecting a bandwidth Delta lambda greater
than zero.
In the case of silicon, the contribution that
normally dominates is due to the finite extinction
depth, resulting in a so-called “Darwin
width” of the Bragg reflection, which results
in a relative spectral bandwidth a little
larger than 10^-4.
Hence 1-Angstrom radiation, with an energy
of 12.398 keV, has a minimum bandwidth of
approximately 1.7 eV.
Note that the corresponding width in theta,
the Bragg angle is Delta lambda/lambda x tan
theta, and thus the crystal also accepts a
fine angular range, of the order of a thousandth
of a degree.
This leads us to the concept of dispersive
or nondispersive configurations in monochromator.
We have already argued that the incoming radiation
is polychromatic and divergent to a certain
degree, and that the crystal thus selects
a band of wavelengths from this incoming beam.
We would therefore expect a range of photon
energies to be reflected off the crystal,
the lower-energy photons being selected at
steeper angles, and those with higher-energy
at shallower angles, according to Bragg’s
law.
These will be reflected specularly with respect
to the diffracting planes . If we now place
an identical crystal in the path of the reflected
rays, we can adjust its orientation so that
all of those wavelengths selected by the first
crystal are preserved after reflection of
the second crystal.
This is a nondispersive configuration.
Now let us consider an alternative setup.
We concentrate to begin with on the central
energy, shown here in green . In the previous
slide, this was intercepted by the second
crystal and reflected back parallel to its
initial direction . But we could also reflect
the beam in the opposite sense, shown here
.
Now, what about the other energies?
In this new setup, these no longer impinge
on the surface of the second crystal at the
same angle as on the first crystal , and as
a result, they will be lost or strongly attenuated
. This is a dispersive setup, as a narrower
range of wavelengths is selected by the second
crystal than by the first.
This configuration is therefore more monochromatic,
but at the cost of flux.
A similar effect can be achieved by using
a different crystal type or crystal orientation
for the second element.
This is succinctly explained using so-called
“Du-Mond” diagrams, for which I direct
you to the reference given here.
There are different types of crystal monos.
A common configuration is the double-crystal
monochromator, using two identical crystals
in the nondisperive mode.
This not only provides greater flux, but also
allows the beam to emerge from the mono parallel
to the incident beam.
If the offset in the monochromatized beam
is to remain constant for all photon energies,
not only do both crystals have to rotate to
the Bragg angle, but also one of them (in
this figure, the second) must be translated
along the beam axis.
Channel-cut monos are fabricated using just
one single crystal which has had a central
channel milled out.
The adds simplicity and speed to changing
the photon energy, requiring a single rotation
stage, a definite advantage when performing
rapid energy scans in certain types of spectroscopic
experiments where physical and/or chemical
changes are to be followed rapidly, with as
many as 40 energy scans per second in modern
beamlines.
The disadvantage is that the exit beam’s
height will change as the CCM is rotated,
though this can be made to be minimal by making
the channel width D to be as small as possible,
and scanning over a not too large range of
photon energies (which in turn determines
the angular range of theta).
Lastly, the problem of a varying exit-beam
height can be overcome by using a four-bounce
configuration, shown here on the right.
Here, the disadvantage is that this is a dispersive
setup, associated with a certain loss in flux.
Finally, we discuss multilayer monochromators.
Crystals diffract x-rays through scattering
of planes of atoms - it is a 3-dimensional
system, exploiting the periodicity in the
direction parallel to the scattering vector.
In the case of multilayers, scattering is
produced by a contrast in electron density
at the interfaces between heavy “reflection”
layers and lighter “spacer” layers.
The only required periodicity is in one direction.
Indeed, in many instances, on an atomic level,
the materials which make up the reflection
and spacer layers may be amorphous, with no
periodicity at this spatial scale of Angstroms.
What motivates a beamline scientist to use
a multilayer monochromator?
First, the reflectivity can be very high.
This, coupled with a bandwidth which may typically
be 100 times larger than that provided by
single crystals, means that the flux output
from multilayer monos can be very high.
Techniques such as x-ray computed tomography
profit from this, as in few cases does a narrow
bandwidth bring advantages, while rapid data
acquisition can access morphological changes
on the sub-second, or even the few-ms time
scale.
Lastly, we will also see that the larger periodicity
of multilayers compared to crystals by an
order of magnitude can lead to refraction
effects that can be exploited in suppressing
harmonic contamination.
There are several design parameters which
determine the performance of a multilayer
mono.
We have already mentioned that one requires
heavy reflecting layers made of heavy metals
such as Ru or tungsten, separated by low-Z
spacer layers made of boron, carbon, or a
combination of these.
The strength of the reflection is determined
partly by the ratio of thicknesses of the
thick to thin layer.
Too thick layers means that the x-rays cannot
penetrate deep enough into the multilayer,
while too thin layers reduces the reflected
intensity.
A common ratio of thicknesses is 0.4:0.6 heavy
to light , though this can vary, depending
on the applications.
The total periodicity big Lambda is typically
measured in a few nanometers, while the number
of layers is commonly of the order of one
hundred.
The total thickness of the multilayer structure
is equal to N Lambda.
Making this too large means that the x-rays
cannot penetrate to the bottom of the structure,
obviating any advantages.
Lastly, the layers should have atomically
smooth interfaces in order to perform properly.
The wavelengths that are selected are approximately
given by the equation shown here, that is,
small lambda, the photon wavelength = 2 times
big Lambda, the multilayer periodicity divided
by m, the order of the reflection, times sine
theta.
This is in essence identical to the Bragg
equation used for crystals.
An example of a multilayer installed at the
ESRF BM5 beamline is shown here.
The reflectivity at an incident angle of 1.15
degrees is shown on the right.
Because the reflection and spacer layers are
of equal thickness, all even harmonic reflections
are suppressed (this phenomenon is called
a systematic absence, outside the remit of
this course, but an important feature of crystallography).
The first harmonic is at 8.01 keV . The 3rd
harmonic, however, is not at three times this
value, 24.03 keV, as we might have expected
from our equation shown in the previous slide,
but instead at 23.27 keV, 760 eV lower . The
reason for this is, as I just mentioned, the
previous equation is an approximation.
The exact equation is shown here, where the
second, correction, term in the brackets,
K Lambda^2/m^2 accounts for refraction effects.
One might ask why this is not also employed
for the “normal” Bragg equation for crystals.
First, in some cases requiring the highest
accuracy, it actually is.
However, the deviations are much smaller,
and this is due to the fact that the wavelengths
being selected in multilayers are very much
smaller than the periodicity, resulting in
shallow angles and a larger refractive effect,
in other words, a larger change in angle of
the x-rays as they cross the interface between
spacer and reflecting layer.
This phenomenon means that multilayers can
be used to suppress higher harmonics.
This brings us to the last topic of this video,
that of harmonic suppression strategies.
In most experiments, we would like to suppress
integer multiples of the photon-energy of
interest, though because both the undulator
and the monochromator harmonics are spaced
evenly in energy, this cannot be done by normal
monochromatization alone .
Although we have seen how this can be done
using a multilayer, and also, in the last
video, by one or more reflections off mirrors,
what other possibilities are there?
One simple approach is to use crystals which
suppress certain higher energies because the
associated reflections are forbidden, in so-called
systematic absences.
For example, for reasons of symmetry, the
reflections highlighted in red for Si(111)
and Si(001) crystals are all nominally forbidden.
I say “nominally”, as their complete suppression
assumes that the electron cloud surrounding
the atoms have perfectly spherical symmetry,
which we know not to be 100% valid - for example,
the electrons associated with covalent bonding
are far from spherically distributed.
Hence, these reflections tend to be very weak,
but not ENTIRELY absent.
Another approach, is to slightly detune the
monochromator.
The width (the Darwin width) of each reflection
in the family m(hkl) (for example, the (111),
(222), (333), (444), reflections, etc of silicon)
is given
by w_D = K/m^2 times F. F falls off with increasing
m, hence the Darwin width gets rapidly narrower
with m.
So only a moderate detuning (and modest loss
of flux) of the mono at the fundamental (m
= 1) will mean that the higher harmonics are
much more detuned.
Monochromators are the heart of x-ray optics.
This video has been devoted to their description.
We have now covered the generation of synchrotron
light over the previous two weeks; and its
filtering, focussing, and monochromatization
in the first two videos of this week.
We complete this week’s videos in the third
instalment, by discussing x-ray detectors.