Welcome to the third and last video of Week
5 of this introductory course on synchrotrons
and x-ray free-electron lasers!
In this video, I will introduce you to aspects
of x-ray detector science and technology.
What do we want an x-ray detector to do? It
needs to be able to detect x-rays and convert
this captured signal into a form which can
be subsequently read out. The first such detector
was the photographic plate. More recently,
conversion of x-rays to visible light via
scintillator or phosphor screens meant that
the signal could be detected by scientific
devices used also for optical spectroscopy
in the visible and near visible regime. Most
recently, CCDs and hybrid pixel detectors
allow direct detection of x-rays via the production
of electrons in the x-ray absorption process.
An ideal detector would be able to resolve
the spatial distribution of the x-ray signal,
have a high quantum (or capture) efficiency,
deliver signal strengths directly proportional
to the x-ray intensity, be able to record
both weak and strong signal simultaneously
(that is, have a high dynamic range), record
data rapidly, and be devoid of internal artefacts.
Before describing different detector types
and technology in detail, we first cover the
topic of noise. Any stochastic or random process
composed of a series of discrete events, such
as the arrival of x-ray photons on to a detector
element, is subject to statistical, or ‘Poisson’
noise. If the average number of events in
a measurement (say, the number of photons
recorded in a detector pixel after a fixed
length of exposure time) is N, then the scatter
in the data (or, more precisely, the standard
deviation) is +/- N^1/2. So, for example,
if the average intensity of a Bragg peak maximum
on average after many identical measurements
is 10000 counts, approximately 68 % of the
results will lie within sigma = +/- 100 counts
of this value. However, for a static (time
independent) experiment, the signal strength
itself increases linearly with exposure time.
A consequence of this is that in order to
achieve a factor X improvement in the signal-to-noise
ratio ∆N/N, one must record X^2 times as
long. The careful experimenter must therefore
decide how best to invest his or her precious
beamtime – does improving the signal-to-noise
ratio of a given signal by, say, a factor
of two, justify the necessary fourfold increase
in acquisition times, or would this time be
better invested in recording other data points?
Consider the simulated images shown here.
The numbers correspond to the average number
of photons/pixel across each image, which
have been scaled linearly from black to white.
The insets are blowups of the most prominent
crater in the image, close to the edge of
the day/night shadow. Note that the image
quality improves significantly between the
first and fourth image (corresponding to an
increase in exposure time by a factor of 100),
while subsequent increases in exposure time
by first another factor of 25, and then a
factor of 16 (that is, a factor of 400 with
respect to the fourth image) reap only dubious
benefits.
What we have described so far is called shot
noise - fluctuations associated with the signal
itself. Most detectors also have another source
of noise called dark noise, which occurs even
when there is no incident signal. For example,
photosensitive diodes such as CCD pixel elements
exhibit dark noise, caused by crystallographic
defects in the depletion region of the diode
device. The level of dark noise can thus vary
from pixel to pixel, depending on the defect
concentration in each element. A dark-field
profile can thus be generated by recording
in the dark sufficiently long to produce a
statistically reliable response array. It
is noted that some modern area detectors have
effectively zero dark noise on account of
the fact that they are not based on diode
technologies.
Readout noise is a source of spurious signal
in CCD detectors produced in the on- chip
amplifier used to convert the collected charge
produced by absorption of x-rays to a voltage
(via a capacitor) in the readout process after
the exposure. This becomes particularly critical
when reading out very weak signals.
In general, a measured intensity I will be
composed of the signal of interest, S, plus
a background signal, B, which may be dark
noise, but might also be a real background
associated with the experiment. The noise
associated with I, S, and B, are all the square-root
of those values. If, then, the noise associated
with the total signal I is larger than that
associated with the signal of interest, i.e.,
the square-root of S, then the signal will
be lost in the noise. Two approaches to resolving
this are (a) reduction of B if at all possible
- perhaps it is caused by fluorescence of
diffuse scattering of the incident beam from
a chamber wall - in which case measures can
be taken to remove, or at least, reduce this.
If, however, the background is either intrinsic
or impossible to remove, the exposure needs
to be increased until the noise becomes smaller
than S.
Another important property of detectors which
can spatially resolve the signal is that of
the point-spread function, or PSF. If a detector
element has a spatial response function which
is not infinitely narrow, then the spatial
distribution of any signal, as recorded on
the detector, will be a convolution of the
original signal with the form of the detector-element
response function. So if the element were
used to detect a signal of zero width (or
for practical purposes, a width known to be
much smaller than the element size), then
the recorded signal is the detector’s point-spread
function - the name is self-explanatory - a
point is spread to a finite-sized function.
The minimum point=spread function of a 2D
pixel array is the pixel size, as within a
given pixel, any spatial variation is lost.
Before discussing more modern technologies,
some older solutions are mentioned here, as
they are still used extensively, if nowadays
more for diagnostic purposes than for actual
experiments.
Photographic plates were used to spatially
resolve x-ray signal for many decades until
the advent of image plates, and then CCDs.
They have many drawbacks, including difficulty
in obtaining quantitative relative intensities
due primarily to a nonlinear change in transparency
of the photographic plate with signal intensity;
a poor dynamic range; poor spatial resolution;
and the very long readout times.
Scintillators, such as Ce:YAG, convert x-rays
to visible light by absorbing them, and, via
a dopant rapid relaxation through non radiative
processes to low-lying energy levels, which
only then relax by emission of a visible or
near-visible photon. Scintillators can then
be installed in front of a photomultiplier
tube, which detects the visible light and
produces a signal through an avalanche process
in a cascade of dynodes.
Such a detector has no spatial resolution,
other than that provided by slitting down
the response area. This is a so-called point
detector.
In the central image, both a point detector
and a 1-dimensional are shown . In traditional
x-ray powder diffraction experiments, the
0-D point detector is scanned over an angular
range, which may only cover a few degrees,
but may also be several tens of degree, and
require scanning times of several minutes
to several hours. The 1-D detector shown here,
called Mythen, consists of an array of 30’720
strip detector elements, each covering an
angle of 0.004 degrees. Acquisition is in
parallel, and takes several orders of magnitude
less time to record data. This has revolutionised
powder-diffraction experiments at synchrotrons,
allowing time-resolved studies that were utterly
unthinkable before its conception.
Two-dimensional photon detectors are commonplace
at synchrotrons, not least at macromolecular
crystallography beamlines, such as shown here
in the right hand image.
Even larger angular ranges still are now accessible,
such as shown here for the 12-million-pixel
Pilatus detector developed and custom built
for low-energy protein crystallography experiments
at the I23 beamline at the Diamond Light Source.
Two different approaches to recording x-ray
intensities are summarised in this slide,
those of photon counting and integrating detectors.
Imagine a train of photons incident on a detector.
There are two different photon energies, due,
for example, elastic scattering of the incident
beam, and lower-energy fluorescence signal
at characteristic energies. These two different
photon energies are shown here as spikes of
two different heights.
The philosophy behind photon-counting detectors
is shown on the left. Each detected photon
produces a short-lived voltage spike in a
solid-state amplifier, the spike height being
proportional to the photon energy. Internal
electronics allow one to distinguish between
these photon energies by setting a threshold
voltage and comparing this to that produced
by the absorbed photon. If the comparator
registers that the photon spike is larger
than the threshold, a digital one is generated
, and sent to a counter. If the photon produces
a spike smaller than the threshold, no signal
is registered. This feature is greatly advantageous
in minimising fluorescence background in some
diffraction experiments.
CCDs and other integrating devices operate
by accumulating charge each time a photon
is detected. So the photons are not read off
one by one, but instead, the total generated
charge in each pixel at the end of the exposure
is converted to a digital signal using an
analog-to-digital converter (ADC). The amount
of added charge for each incident photon is
proportional to the photon energy.
Let’s look at CCDs a little more closely,
as they remain the most common modern area
detector type. They have proved to be so important
and ubiquitous in both science and society
at large (there is one in every modern mobile
phone) that their inventors Willard Boyle
and George Smith would win the Nobel Prize
in physics in 2009.
One can think of CCDs as arrays of buckets,
buckets that collect electrical charge. As
already mentioned, the amount of accumulated
charge due to absorption of photons during
the exposure time is proportional to each
photon’s energy and how many have been detected.
After the end of the exposure, this total
“integrated” accumulated charge is read
off.
Shown here is a cartoon of a 1-D array of
CCD “buckets”. After the exposure , the
charge in each bucket along the row is read
off one after the other by shifting the charge
one bucket at a time towards the read-out
ADC. A CCD is therefore a “shift register”
in the jargon of semiconductor electronics.
Associated with this shifting of charge and
reading out is a readout noise, which may
be significant.
The analogy of a CCD pixel being like a bucket
extends to the fact that, just as a bucket
can carry only a finite volume of water, a
CCD pixel can accommodate only a limited electrical
charge. If, during the exposure, a CCD pixel
is exposed to too many photons, the excess
charge spills over into adjacent buckets - this
undesirable artefact is called “blooming”,
which is particularly observed in the readout
direction, resulting in streaks of saturated
signal. Blooming is especially troublesome
in CCDs for experiments where weak (but important)
signal lies close to much stronger signal.
Photon-Counting devices have their own limitations.
The spikes generated in the amplifier decay
again in a finite time of the order of 100
ns *****. If two photons arrive within this
time, the second of these will not be registered.
But synchrotron pulses from the direct but
monochromatized direct beam contain approximately
3 x 10^4 photons over 30 ps. The average temporal
separation between photons is therefore only
about 1 fs, some 10^8 times shorter than the
recovery, or “dead”, time of the spikes.
So, for example, if the entire direct beam
is incident on just one detector pixel, it
is necessary to attenuate this using filters
by a factor of approximately 10^8 in order
to record this with any accuracy.
The situation is in fact still more serious,
as the arrival rate of photons is not perfectly
constant, but in fact stochastic. So although
the average rate of arrival may be N_0, this
will fluctuate strongly. One can correct for
the observed intensity, or number of photon
counts, N_obs, for this statistical fluctuation
using the equation shown here and plotted
on the right-hand side. For average incident
rates equal to the reciprocal of the dead
time, tau, the curve of N_obs has a gradient
of zero. Hence, in order to ensure one remains
to the left of this, the real arrival rate
N_0 should, as a rule of thumb, not exceed
1/(2 tau).
The relative performance of photon-counting
and integrating CCD detectors is shown here.
First, because photon counters count photons,
they have an intrinsic dead time. Integrating
detectors do not suffer from this limitation,
an important aspect we discuss in just a moment.
In most other aspects, including the dynamic
range, readout times, noise, photon-energy
discrimination, and the point-spread function,
photon counters perform better than integrators.
However, CCDs can presently provide smaller
pixel sizes by an order of magnitude.
But let us return to the issue of the dead
time of photon counters in the context of
XFELs. The instantaneous arrival rate of photons
within XFEL pulses is 11 orders of magnitude
higher still than at synchrotrons. This would
therefore require attenuation by 19 orders
of magnitude of the XFEL direct beam in order
for it to be detectable using photon-counting
technology, which would completely obviate
one of the primary features of XFEL radiation.
Photon counters cannot be used at XFELs, and
integrating devices must instead be employed,
ones with high sensitivity and a large dynamic
range.
With this in mind, the Jungfrau detector has
been recently developed. Although it is an
integrating device, it is based on the same
pixel technology of the photon counting Eiger
detector. The required high dynamic range
and sensitivity is achieved by the Jungfrau
automatically changing its sensitivity according
to whether the signal is weak or strong.
This begs the question, how does this work?
No electronics is capable of reacting within
the few tens of fs of XFEL pulses. The answer
is that a buffer layer on top of the Jungfrau
pixels first absorbs the photons , after which
the generated electrons require of the order
of 20 ns to drift across to the pixels themselves,
plenty enough time for modern electronics
to respond.
How this is done exactly is shown here. As
the charge accumulates in a first capacitor,
the voltage increases. Once this reaches a
certain threshold, a switch is closed to include
a second capacitor in parallel. The total
capacitance of individual capacitors wired
in parallel is simply their sum, hence by
adding the second capacitor, the capacitance
increases, and the voltage drops according
to V = Q/C. A third range of charge is accessible
by the inclusion of a third capacitor.
Until now, we have discussed (if somewhat
implicitly) mainly experiments in which one
photon energy is of interest, as is normally
the case in scattering and diffraction experiments.
In many spectroscopic experiments, not least
in x-ray fluorescence, the spectrum emitted
by an irradiated sample is of interest, for
which one requires a dispersive setup. One
approach, called wavelength dispersive spectrometry
(or WDX) is to scan the energy using a crystal
and exploiting Bragg’s law - the crystal
is rotated and the diffracted intensity measured
using a point detector rotating at twice the
crystal rotating rate. This approach is slow
and with low sensitivity, as only a small
angular range of the emitted radiation is
captured. Its one advantage is that it has
a high resolution.
In energy-dispersive spectrometry (EDX), the
photon energies are converted into voltage
spikes with amplitudes proportional to the
photon energy within doped semiconductor devices.
Different energies can be recorded in parallel,
and the detector can capture a large angular
cross-section. EDX is thus cheap, fast, and
highly sensitive, though it has a resolution
two orders of magnitude worse than in WDX.
A comparison between EDX and WDX spectra for
a clay mineral shows this dramatic difference.
A nice example of EDX is shown here of a fossil
fish excavated from the Green Rive formation
of Fossil Lake in Wyoming. The sample was
irradiated with focussed 17.2 keV x-rays and
the fluorescence signal recorded as the fossil
sample was rastered.
Shown here is the result of selecting a narrow
section of the EDX spectra at 12.97 keV, corresponding
to the thorium L-alpha fluorescence signal.
The high levels of thorium are are caused
by its substitution for calcium in the phosphate
mineral that composes the bone, fluorapatite.
Lastly, a modern alternative to EDX and WDX
detectors combines some of the most attractive
features of both. Von Hamos spectrometers
operate by collecting a large angular cross-section
of fluorescence on a cylindrically bent single
crystal. The bend radius, R_b, has its origin
on the same axis containing the sample and
a 1-D or 2-D detector. This configuration
means that von-Hamos detectors have a high
sensitivity, while the use of a 1- or 2-D
detector allows parallel acquisition of the
entire spectrum. These detectors are being
used increasingly for high-resolution and
time-resolved x-ray emission studies, not
least at XFELs.
In summary, this last video of Week 5 has
covered some basic but important aspects of
different types of x-ray detectors to complete
our discussion of beamlines and optics.
In these first five weeks, we have learned
how x-rays interact with material, how synchrotron
radiation is generated and what its properties
are, and in this most recent week, how this
is subsequently manipulated for synchrotron-based
experiments. In the next three weeks, we will
discuss aspects of synchrotron experiments,
including scattering and diffraction, x-ray
spectroscopies, and x-ray imaging. We begin
next week with x-ray diffraction and scattering.