Welcome to Week 6 of this introductory course
on synchrotrons and x-ray free-electron lasers!
This week is concerned with x-ray diffraction
and scattering and its use at synchrotrons.
After some introductory remarks about why
diffraction is attractive, particularly using
synchrotron light, I will recap some basic
concepts required to understand the remainder
of this week’s contents.
This will be followed by three types of diffraction
experiment, namely single-crystal and powder
diffraction, and macromolecular crystallography
(which is actually just a certain sort of
single-crystal diffraction, but of such high
importance, that it is covered separately).
Lastly, small-angle x-ray scattering and x-ray
reflectivity will be detailed before a brief
overview of how diffraction and scattering
experiments at XFELs differ from those at
synchrotrons.
In this first video, we ask what is diffraction
and why is it used; how diffraction at synchrotrons
opens up experimental approaches excluded
to lab-based sources; and then a brief review
of some diffraction basic concepts.
A knowledge of the detailed atomic structure
of condensed matter is exceedingly important
in many fields of the natural sciences.
In many cases, a knowledge of the atomic structure
leads directly to the functionality of the
system, as exemplified by the now famous understatement
of Watson and Crick in the penultimate paragraph
of their Nobel-prize-winning Nature paper
on the structure of DNA in 1953: “It has
not escaped our notice that the specific pairing
we have postulated immediately suggests a
possible copying mechanism for the genetic
material”.
This correlation between structure and function
is not limited to biology however, and many
insights to physical and chemical properties
have been made in the fields of electronics,
for example in the strongly-correlated electron
systems based on perovskite structures; or
in energy/catalysis and the role of open structures
such as zeolites.
So, given the need to obtain atomic-resolution
to understand the physical properties of a
given system, what should be our approach?
First, it should be stressed that in order
to observe features of a certain characteristic
size, one needs to use a probe with a wavelength
of similar dimensions.
This means, for electromagnetic radiation,
x-rays.
So can we use an x-ray lens?
Let’s consider how much we need to magnify
an object in order to directly image it.
Interatomic spacings are of the order of a
few Angstrom, while detectors presently have
at best pixel sizes of a few microns, that
is, 10^4 times larger, which thus defines
our magnification q/p.
But no x-ray lens is capable of such a huge
magnification factor, hence full-field direct
imaging on the Angstrom scale is excluded.
What can we do to circumvent this problem?
The scattered x-ray signal of an object past
a certain distance from that object is actually
nothing more than the Fourier transform of
the object . A lens refocusses this scattered
light back into an image - one can thus consider
a lens to perform an inverse Fourier transform
on the scattered signal to regain an image
of the original object.
Now, instead of using a lens, which we’ve
argued is anyway impractical for hard x-rays,
we simply capture the scattered signal from
our object using an area detector . We send
this scattered signal to a computer which
then performs the operation of the lens using
mathematical algorithms . This is called “phasing”
the signal, as the detector measures not the
signal amplitude (including the phase), but
the intensity.
We have therefore lost half of the information,
the phases between the individual components
of the scattered signal.
Strategies for regaining these are varied
and sophisticated, and we will touch on some
of these later in the course.
Once phasing is completed, however, the original
structure is recovered.
Diffraction and scattering experiments at
synchrotrons profit from synchrotron radiation
for several reasons.
The low divergence and high flux of synchrotron
radiation compared to lab sources means that
better angularly resolved and much higher-intensity
patterns can be recorded, much facilitating
the process of phasing and obtaining an atomic
structure.
The two powder-diffraction patterns on the
right highlight this difference - the top
one was recorded in 5 seconds using synchrotron
radiation and a 1-D Mythen detector, while
the lower one (blown up by a factor of 1000
here) was recorded over nearly three hours
at a lab-based source, and exhibits a significantly
broader signal, by approximately a factor
of two.
The low emittance of synchrotrons can also
be exploited to obtain tight focusses, of
the order of a micron, for investigation of
very small crystalline samples, such as the
lysozyme crystals shown in the upper image.
The low emittance can be otherwise exploited
by allowing a large working distance by parallelising
the beam as much as possible, in order to
accommodate complex experimental setups, such
as that shown here in the lower image.
High photon energies up to a mega-electronvolt
are accessible at high-energy synchrotron
storage rings such as the ESRF, APS, and SPring8.
The high penetration lengths of this radiation
means that larger objects such as aeronautical
components or large fossil specimens can be
probed.
A unique property of synchrotron light is
its tunability.
As we discussed in detail in the second week,
the scattering amplitude and phase of a certain
atom type changes abruptly and sometimes very
strongly close to an absorption edge of that
atom, that is, at an energy equating the binding
energy of one of the atom’s electrons (normally
a core electron).
By recording diffraction data in this region,
techniques such as multi-wavelength anomalous
diffraction, MAD, and single-wavelength anomalous
diffraction, SAD), can unambiguously solve
the phase problem mentioned a few slides previously.
MAD, which exploits the tunability are only
possible at synchrotrons and XFELs.
SAD, which uses a single wavelength, can in
principle be carried out using a lab source,
and indeed the first ever report of SAD was
using a copper K-alpha source.
However, the subtle differences between pairs
of signals means that in most cases, only
data from synchrotrons have sufficient signal-to-noise
ratios to extract meaningful information.
The remainder of this first video will be
devoted to a recap of some essential diffraction
basic concepts.
This course is not a treatise on crystallography
but does, in particular this week, describe
crystallography experiments at synchrotrons.
As a result, some basic rules of diffraction
should be explained, which include a description
of crystals, the concept of reciprocal space,
Bragg’s law, and the Ewald sphere.
We begin with a description of crystals.
We concern ourselves here with the classical
definition of crystals, invoking translational
symmetry, although it should be noted that
a new class of material, quasicrystals, were
discovered in the 1980s, which also exhibit
sharp diffraction patterns, but which never
repeat themselves through translational symmetry.
A crystal is defined as consisting of a framework
of evenly spaced points in space , known as
the Bravais lattice, plus a so-called basis
of atomic positions associated with each Bravais-lattice
point, to generate a crystal.
The separation in three dimensions between
adjacent Bravais-lattice points is defined
by the three lattice vectors a, b, and c (of
which a and b are shown here in this 2-dimensional
representation).
The translational symmetry of crystals mean
that they remain invariant under a translation
by a vector T = the vector sum of integer
multiples of the lattice vectors.
In the 2-dimensional example shown here, T
= 3a + 2b.
The volume of a unit cell, that is, the repeat
unit in 3-dimensional space, is the cross
product of one lattice vector (here, c) with
the area defined by the scalar product of
the other two vectors (here a dot b) . In
this vector algebra, the relative angular
orientations are implicit.
The other three lattice constants are the
angles alpha, beta, and gamma, where alpha
is the angle opposite a, subtended by b and
c, and so forth.
Armed with this information, the unit-cell
volume is given by the expression shown here.
Note that in high-symmetry cases, such as
cubic or orthorhombic crystals, this expression
becomes much simpler.
A lattice plane, or more accurately, a family
of parallel lattice planes, intersect with
the Bravais lattice at three non-colinear
points that are integer fractions of the lattice
vectors that define that Bravais lattice.
The integers defining these fractions are
the Miller indices.
So in this first example, the (100) plane
intersects a at h = 1, but never intersects
b or c, which implies k and l = 0, as b/0
and c/0 equal infinity - the distance required
before b and c are intersected by the (100)
plane!
Using similar arguments, the top-middle and
top right examples are clearly the (110) and
(111) planes, respectively.
Bottom left shows the (200), because the in
the a-direction, the plane crosses a at a/2.
In the bottom middle example, the intersection
points are at 1/2, 1/3, and 1, hence this
is the (213) plane . The last example is the
(012) plane .
The separation between crystallographic planes
is given by the lattice constants a, b, c,
alpha, beta, and gamma, plus the Miller indices
(hkl) according to the expressions shown here.
Again, although these seem complex for the
general case (for a so-called triclinic crystal,
which exhibits the lowest symmetry), things
become much simpler for those cases where
one or more angles are right-angles and/or
two or more of a, b, and c are equal to each
other.
Examples of families of four different crystal
planes in 2-dimensions are shown on the right.
Now we have described crystals, we should
see how x-rays scattered from them look like.
Let us begin with a single point scatterer.
The far-field pattern (remember, this is the
Fourier transform of the object) is a modulated
Gaussian.
Interference between scattering from two adjacent
spots results in interference fringes much
like seen in the famous Youngs’ double slit
experiment.
and increasing the number of evenly spaced
scatterers will sharpen that interference
signal, just like the maxima of a grating
monochromator sharpen with the number of scattering
facets, described in the second video of last
week.
Extending this motif to a second dimension
causes the pattern to change from being a
set of fringes to being a set of spots.
. .
while the angle between scatterers is reflected
at 90 degrees in the interference or diffraction
pattern.
Also importantly, the larger the separation
between the scatterers, the smaller their
angular separation, or separation in reciprocal
space, and vice versa.
Hence, crystals with small unit cells such
as NaCl have widely spaced diffraction features,
while protein crystals, which have characteristic
repeat dimensions two orders of magnitude
larger than NaCl, have very crowded diffraction
patterns.
In the second week of this course, we described
Thomson scattering and the scattering vector
Q, that is the vector difference between the
incoming and scattered wavevectors.
The direction of Q is ALWAYS at right-angles
to the scattering planes responsible for the
scattered signal in the direction of k_out,
while its magnitude can be expressed in a
variety of ways.
We determined Q to be equal to 4 pi/lambda
sin theta, and, combining this with Bragg’s
law, lambda = 2d sin theta, we see that Q
is equal to 2 pi/d_hkl.
So, for example, Q for the Si(004) reflection
has a value of 2 pi/d(004).
d(004) is equal to 1.3578 Angstrom, hence
Q = 4.628 A^-1.
A convenient practical expression for Q is
also given and is equal to 1.0135 (close to
unity) times the photon energy in keV times
sin theta.
Because the incident and scattered wavevectors
have equal magnitude (we are concerned here
only with elastic scattering), one can use
the construct known as the Ewald sphere.
The incident beam obviously points in the
(000) direction, whereas the scattered beam,
if at a Bragg peak defined by the Miller indices
(hkl), terminates on that Bragg maximum.
The orientation of the crystal that will result
in the hkl Bragg peak lighting up is when
this point in the diffraction pattern sits
on the Ewald sphere.
Let us consider one such example to make this
clearer.
Consider a crystal at some random orientation,
and we are interested in looking at a certain
Bragg reflection (hkl).
We can now rotate the crystal, which will
also cause the diffraction pattern to rotate
in exactly the same manner.
When the rotation angle is such that the (hkl)
spot sits on the Ewald sphere, in other words,
when the size of the wavevector along the
scattering direction is equal in magnitude
to the incident wavevector, we will see the
corresponding Bragg maximum.
So, by rotating a crystal around an axis while
recording the pattern using an area detector,
different Bragg maxima will light up and can
be recorded, as shown schematically here.
This is the basic approach to most single-crystal
diffraction experiments, in particular in
macromolecular crystallography.
In this first video of Week 6, the arguments
for the need of diffraction experiments, in
particular at synchrotrons, have been laid
out.
The basic rules needed to understand different
types of diffraction experiments have been
covered.
This leads us on in the next video to a discussion
of the most common synchrotron-based diffraction
methods.