Welcome to the second video of Week 6 of this
introductory course on synchrotrons and x-ray
free-electron lasers!
This video is concerned with three of the
most common variations of synchrotron-based
diffraction, namely single-crystal diffraction,
powder diffraction, and macromolecular crystallography.
Before discussing different types of synchrotron-based
diffraction experiments, it is worth to first
pause and consider the myriad types of samples
that can be investigated using diffraction,
as an understanding of these helps in deciding
the type of experiment to undertake.
We can divide sample types into three broad
classifications, namely (and in increasing
degree of disorder) single-crystal, textured,
and powder samples.
Within each class, however, there are strikingly
different manifestations.
Take, for example, single crystals.
Even the highest-quality silicon single crystal
still contains crystallographic defects (including
vacancies, interstitials, dislocations, and
mosaic domains), hence in reality there is
no such thing as a perfect single crystal.
At what level of imperfection does one begin
to regard a system as being no longer a single
crystal?
Of course, there is no well-defined boundary,
and depending on experimental methods, preconceptions,
and “what you’re used to”, the transition
between one system and another may be quite
different.
So high-quality large crystals such as diamonds,
micron-sized protein crystals (which, incidentally,
size-for-size, are far more valuable than
diamond!), or heteroepitaxial thin films grown
on single-crystal substrates and fabricated
for microelectronic applications are all,
in their own fields, regarded as being single
crystals.
This fuzziness in boundaries extends all the
way to nanocrystalline powder samples and
semi-amorphous structures.
A well-known phenomenon in single crystals
is that of twinning, in which two crystals
share crystal lattice points at a boundary
in a symmetric manner.
The resulting diffraction pattern of the twins
(there can be more than two twins, depending
on the crystallographic system) becomes more
complicated.
For example, each diffraction spot of an untwinned
system may be split into two or more closely
lying features.
One can therefore consider twinning as the
first step towards disorder and eventually
to powder samples.
Textured samples exhibit an intermediate degree
of order, with preferred directions for certain
crystallographic planes.
This may be due, for example, to a ‘brushing’
effect in the fabrication process of the sample
(such as in polymer fibre pulling), to the
synthetic process, such as in natural fibres
such as flax, or because of energy-minimization
reasons.
Powder samples consist of crystalline grains
that have no preferred orientation in space,
and are significantly smaller than the illuminated
volume.
For some samples, this latter condition may
be only poorly met, in which case the sample
can be spun, in order to record a spatially
averaged signal.
Note that for undulator radiation, the focussed
beam cross-section might be only of the order
of a square micron, and the sampled volume
may be less than 100 cubic microns.
When the characteristic size of the individual
grains is reduced to only a few unit cells,
such as in nanocrystals, the widths of the
diffraction peaks broaden accordingly, producing
diffuse ring patterns.
This lower limit in crystallinity often best
represents the grim reality of ‘real’
systems, and as such is a burgeoning area
of research in 21st-Century crystallography.
Synchrotrons are playing a leading role in
this enterprise.
Let us begin with three different approaches
to studying single crystals.
Each method is suited for different applications.
Although the majority of x-ray diffraction
methods use (quasi-)monochromatic x- rays
and a sample which must be rotated in space
in order to satisfy the diffraction condition,
it is also possible to record diffraction
patterns of stationary single crystals using
a broad spectrum of x-rays, a technique known
as the Laue method.
Indeed, the Laue method is historically the
oldest and was used in the original discovery
of x-ray diffraction and is named after its
founder, Max von Laue (see Figure 1.8).
After the development of monochromatic sources
using characteristic radiation from x-ray
tubes, Laue diffraction fell somewhat into
disuse, except to orient single crystals and
to determine their crystal quality.
However, with the advent of synchrotron radiation
(especially from third generation facilities),
and enormous improvements in computing power
and detector technology, Laue diffraction
has enjoyed a renaissance as a technique which
provides a fast and efficient means to record
diffraction data, and is being used to great
effect in dynamical studies of transient crystalline
states.
Consider a diffraction pattern, that is, a
regularly spaced set of diffraction maxima,
or Bragg spots, in reciprocal space, with
the (000) direct beam spot in the centre.
If we irradiate the crystal with a quasi-monochromatic
x-ray beam, it is unlikely that the crystal
will be oriented such that a diffraction spot
lies on the surface of the Ewald sphere (remember,
this is the pictorial representation for satisfying
the Bragg condition of constructive interference).
In the case of macromolecular crystals, the
density of Bragg spots is so large, with separations
in reciprocal space often well over hundred
times smaller than the radius of the Ewald
sphere, that some spots are likely to intersect
the Ewald sphere.
But, for the moment, let us ignore this and
consider the more sparsely populated reciprocal
space shown here.
In this case, no Bragg spot sits on the Ewald
sphere, and no diffraction intensity is recorded.
Now let us consider the case where a band
of photon energies irradiates the crystal,
such as one can generate from bending magnets
and wigglers.
The Ewald spheres of the lower and upper limits
of the band of energies will have radii equal
to 2 pi/lambda_max and 2 pi/lambda_min, respectively.
All diffraction spots that lie within the
volume between these two spheres (which touch
tangentially at the (000) direct beam) will
produce diffraction signal.
Which angle will a certain Bragg spot (hkl),
highlighted here in red, subtend with the
incident beam?
To determine this, we need to find the Ewald
sphere that meets the Bragg condition, in
other words, the precise energy within the
energy band.
This is a sphere which is intersects both
the (000) and (hkl) spots, and is symmetric
around the incident beam direction, as shown
here with the dot-dashed circle . The two
radii of this circle that connect with circle’s
centre to (000) and (hkl) subtend an angle
2-theta_(hkl).
A large subset of all the possible detected
diffraction peaks can be accessed by rotating
the crystal and recording the signal frame
after frame.
An example of Laue diffraction is shown here,
in which the video on the right shows differences
in the electron density map compared to the
static state after a carbon monoxyhaemoglobin
crystal was irradiated with a nanosecond laser.
The laser causes the carbon monoxide molecule
to photodissociate and the structure rearranges
itself in response to this.
This is probed by taking single pulses from
the synchrotron storage ring and varying the
delay between the laser pulse pump and x-ray
probe.
This experiment is made possible by the fact
that the dissociation of CO is reversible,
allowing the experiment to be repeated at
different time delays.
In some experiments, one is interested in
recording only a subset of the diffraction
data, using the so-called selected Bragg-peak
method.
An example might be orbital, charge (i.e.,
valence), or even spin ordering of electronic
states in future electronic materials, which
increases the crystal periodicity and thereby
introduces additional (and usually very weak)
Bragg peaks at nominally non-integral positions
in reciprocal space.
In such experiments, the crystal is carefully
oriented to light up a certain diffraction
peak.
Because these can often be weak, synchrotron
radiation is normally required.
In addition, by tuning to the absorption-edge
energies of the atoms responsible for the
phenomenon of interest, the signal strength
can be enhanced using resonant elastic scattering
effects.
We have already come across the rotation method
in the first video of this week.
It is only mentioned explicitly again here
in order to highlight some technical improvements,
although it should be mentioned that a macromolecular-crystallography
experiments carried out at synchrotrons use
the rotation method as well.
In the “old days”, a crystal would be
rotated and an exposure recorded over a certain
angular range of the order of a degree.
Any Bragg peaks crossing the Ewald sphere
during the exposure would be recorded.
Exactly where they lay within the angular
range covered was normally lost, while whether
they were intense and sharp or broad but weaker
was also ambiguous.
After the exposure, the recording device,
normally a CCD, would read out the data, which
could take several seconds to several tens
of seconds.
The next angular range, starting where the
previous one left off, would be recorded by
slightly rewinding the crystal and ramping
up the rotation rate before starting the next
exposure.
In this manner, a full dat set could take
several minutes to some hours, depending on
the crystal type, size, and intensity of the
beam.
With the advent of modern detectors, with
readout times in the range of a few milliseconds,
a new approach called fine phi-slicing became
possible.
In this mode of operation, the exposures were
over much narrower angular ranges by an order
of magnitude, and the crystal was allowed
to rotate continuously, as the dead time between
exposures was sufficiently small.
Nowadays, a full data set can be recorded
in just a few seconds, or even below a second.
Because the angles covered by each exposure
are typically smaller than the angular width
of the diffraction signal (in the case of
macromolecular crystallography), the peak
shape and position can be accurately determined
using fine phi-slicing.
For some materials, it may prove to be very
difficult or indeed impossible to grow macroscopic
crystals of sufficient crystallographic quality
to be investigated using single-crystal diffraction.
In such instances, powder diffraction (also
called the ‘Debye-Scherrer’ method) is
an invaluable technique.
Powder diffraction suffers from the fact that
because the microcrystallites making up the
powder sample are randomly oriented, the angularly
separated information one obtains in single-crystal
diffraction is projected on to a single coordinate,
complicating the identification of the Miller
indices of the Bragg peaks (so-called “indexing”).
In addition, diffraction signals that are
separated from each other in a single-crystal
pattern will overlap in the powder pattern
if they are associated with the same lattice
spacing.
It should not be thought, however, that powder
diffraction is a ‘last resort’ technique
only to be used when large, high-quality,
single crystals are unavailable.
Powder diffraction not only provides a rapid
and nondestructive means to identify the composite
parts in multicomponent mixtures or complex
system in fields as disparate as metallurgy,
archaeology, pharmaceutical sciences, mineralogy,
catalysis, and condensed-matter physics, but
is also indispensable in extreme environmental
studies, where phase changes are studied as
a function of temperature and/or pressure.
In such cases, information can often ONLY
be extracted from powder samples, which due
to the microcrystallites’ large surface
area-to-volume ratio, can accommodate phase
changes under these severe conditions by relaxation
and propagation of crystallographic faults
far better than can larger single-crystal
samples, which most often degrade unacceptably,
and in an anisotropic manner.
In addition, powder diffraction lends itself
to time-resolved studies, whereby the projection
of the crystallographic information in to
one dimension can be considered in this case
to be positively beneficial.
The time-resolution of such studies has been
extended into the sub-millisecond regime since
the advent of novel detector types such as
the Mythen microstrip detector.
For example, the dynamics of self-propagating
exothermic reactions in nanoscale metallic
multilayers have been followed from powder
diffraction patterns over a 120 degree range
with 0.004 degree resolution and with a complete-pattern
frame-rate of 8000 Hz.
Let us consider how powder diffraction data
is generated.
Consider first a single crystal which contains
a set of angularly separated Bragg maxima
in reciprocal space.
Let us look at this setup from the perspective
of the incident beam . It should not be a
surprise that, if we rotate the crystal around
the incident beam’s axis, the diffraction
pattern will rotate in exactly the same manner
. Now let us replace the single crystal with
a large set of randomly oriented crystallites
. So now, instead of rotating the single-crystal,
which would rotate the diffraction pattern,
the large number of crystallites will provide
all the different orientations simultaneously
- the Bragg spots are therefore swept out
into rings, called Debye-Scherrer rings.
Because of the cylindrical symmetry of this
method, all the necessary information can
be recorded in a narrow strip of the rings,
that is, along one coordinate, 2-theta.
So, in summary, the large ensemble of crystallites
means that some will be coincidentally oriented
such that they meet the Bragg condition for
diffraction at a peak (hkl), that is, the
hkl planes of those crystallites lie perpendicular
to the scattering vector Q of magnitude 2
pi/d_hkl.
Due to the cylindrical symmetry of this condition,
the diffraction signal forms a set of concentric
cones, detected as
rings on area detectors, as shown here for
the calibration standard material lanthanum
hexaboride.
Although powder patterns can be recorded using
area detectors for certain applications, traditionally,
they have been recorded using a point detector
rotated around a single axis.
This can take anything from a few minutes
to several hour, depending on many factors
scubas the desired resolution, the powder’s
scattering strength, and the range of angles
to be covered.
Beginning about a decade ago at the Swiss
Light Source, a new approach to powder data
acquisition began, in which an entire powder
pattern in one coordinate, 2-theta, could
be recorded in parallel, reducing acquisition
times to seconds, and in some cases, below
milliseconds!
A simple example of the benefit of using a
1-D so-called “microstrip” detector, is
highlighted here.
The powder pattern of the anaesthetic drug
bupivacaine was to be recorded to investigate
its level of purity.
This was performed with both a point detector
(“zero dimensions”) and a Mythen 1D detector,
covering an angular range of 2-theta = 120
degrees.
First a short range of 2-theta was recorded
at a rate of 3 minutes/degree.
This was repeated a second time , and the
resulting pattern was seen to be both substantially
weaker (here it is blown up in the y-axis
by a factor of 5) and exhibit subtle different
peak shapes and positions.
This was strongly indicative of radiation
damage, a common problem with organic-based
matter, with their on average relatively weak
bond strengths.
A fresh sample was then exposed for only one
second using the Mythen microstrip detector.
This showed clear differences in relative
peak intensities and positions, even compared
to the first point-detector pattern, especially
in those regions highlighted here in yellow
. It in fact emerged that exposures in excess
of about one minute exhibited radiation damage.
This means that a reliable pattern could only
be simply recorded using the 1-D detector,
as the serial acquisition of the point detector
would mean that a fresh sample would need
introducing every 30 seconds or thereabouts.
We finish this video with a brief description
of macromolecular crystallography.
A young and ambitious student contemplating
which line of research to pursue for a PhD
program could do worse than choose macromolecular
crystallography, or MX.
Of the 21 Nobel prizes awarded to studies
or inventions involving x-rays as a tool,
nine have been in the field of biomolecular
structure, including all five prizes which
have used synchrotron radiation.
No other discipline comes close to the recognition
MX has so rightly earned by the Nobel committee
for its impact on society; it can also be
argued that MX is the raison d’etre synchrotrons
are funded at all...
Macromolecular crystallography is the study
of macromolecules such as proteins, viruses,
ribosomes, and other macromolecular assemblies
such as DNA and RNA, and is often also called
protein crystallography, or PX, as proteins
make up the majority of the types of studied
structures.
The transition from ‘small molecules’
to macromolecules is somewhat vague, but lies
at around a few thousand Daltons (or atomic
mass units).
Some solved macromolecular structures lie
orders of magnitude above this threshold;
for example, the 80S yeast ribosome is composed
of 45 peptide chains and has a molecular weight
of over 1.8 MDa.
It is the folding and thus the three-dimensional
structure of proteins that lend them their
catalytic activity that drives metabolic reactions,
genetic-code replication, and the body’s
response to internal or external stimuli,
among other functions.
The study of protein structure is, therefore,
of paramount importance in understanding the
foundations of molecular biology.
MX is a form of single-crystal diffraction
which uses the rotation method.
What, therefore, is the justification for
discussing this separately?
As mentioned above, the determination on an
atomic scale of the three- dimensional structures
of proteins and related biological molecules
is fundamental to understanding biological
processes at the most basic level; how macromolecules
interact in a ‘lock-and-key’ manner, and
how enzymes catalyze reactions.
The economic drive to synthesize new and increasingly
effective drugs based on this detailed knowledge
means that MX-beamlines are the most ubiquitous
in third- generation synchrotron facilities.
Despite this and the burgeoning number of
facilities being built, there remains a high
overbooking factor for MX experiments.
Another immediately obvious qualitative difference
between MX and XRD of crystals with smaller
unit cells is exactly that – the complexity
of the basis within the unit cell.
When the basis contains several thousand molecules,
conventional approaches to solving the structure
through methods such as Rietveld analysis
become entirely impractical, and other more
sophisticated techniques must be brought to
bear on solving the phase problem.
Details of approaches to this at first seemingly
insurmountable problem will be covered in
the more advanced lectures towards the end
of the course.
Here, it is merely mentioned that this obstacle
is further compounded by the fact that, because
diffraction-peak intensities scale with the
square of the number of coherently illuminated
unit cells, and because the unit cells in
MX can have linear dimensions up to two orders
of magnitude larger than those of small inorganic
structure, the signal intensity in MX is concomitantly
smaller for a given crystal size.
The large unit-cell dimensions also mean that
the diffraction spots in MX are separated
by much smaller angles and that many more
diffraction peaks will lie on the Ewald sphere
and thus be detected.
For example, a protein crystal with a unit-cell
size of 200 Angstroms, irradiated with 12.7
keV x-rays, will have angular separations
of approximately 0.3 degrees.
As many protein crystals exhibit a mosaicity
of similar magnitudes, this can lead to overlapping
signals.
Finally it is mentioned that the preparation
of protein crystals can be exceedingly difficult,
and many proteins known to be exceedingly
important in the chemistry of life, such as
membrane proteins, have, to a large extent,
resisted efforts to crystalline them in sufficiently
large sizes and quality.
Over and above this, the high brilliance of
third-generation synchrotrons and indeed,
the even higher intensities associated with
diffraction-limited storage rings cause these
highly valuable crystals to be destroyed in
seconds due to radiation damage.
The advent of XFEL radiation and the ability
to detect strong signal from crystallites
smaller than one cubic micron, is opening
up this field enormously.
This, too, will be described in more detail
towards the end of the course.
Macromolecular crystallography is the foremost
method of choice when studying protein or
enzyme structures – indeed over 85 % of
all the presently known protein structures
have been solved using MX.
The growth of depositions of protein structures
into the Protein Data Bank, shown here and
including some of the more seminal structural
discoveries over the last 60+ years, has followed
an near exponential path since its inception
in 1971 and shows little sign of slackening.
The molecule on the right, cathepsin B, was
the first de-novo structure to be solved using
XFEL radiation.
What resolution can we expect for an MX experiment?
The maximum scattering angle 2-theta_max is
given by the arctangent of the area detector
radius, big R, divided by the sample-detector
distance, Z_D.
From this, it is a trivial exercise to show
that the maximum scattering vector Q_max,
which equals 2-pi divided by the minimum detectable
feature, a_min, is equal to 4pi/lambda sin
theta_max, or a_min = lambda/2sin theta_max.
The smaller lambda and the larger theta_max,
the better the theoretical resolution.
I sat “theoretical” advisedly, as this
assumes that the scattered signal strength
is sufficient to be detected at the edge of
the detector.
But we know that the scattering strength on
average drops off with Q in a quasi-Gaussian
manner and that high energies (small lambda)
are associated with a high Q-value.
Let’s assume for example that 2-theta_max
= 50 degrees.
For photo energies of 5-keV (the red curves
on the right hand side graph), the maximum
Q-value is a little over 2 reciprocal Angstroms
, equating to an a_min of approximately 3
Angstroms *****. This may be sufficient to
obtain an atomic structure, though some details
may be missing.
The atomic structure factor of the carbon
atoms is approximately equal to 4 electrons,
not far from the maximum value of Z = 6 electrons.
Now we might decide to record with a higher
resolution, so we switch to 12.66 keV (this
is the K-absorption edge energy of selenium,
an atom often substituted for sulphur for
anomalous diffraction experiments, described
later in the course).
Here, the maximum accessible Q-vector is 5.4
reciprocal Angstroms, and we obtain a resolution
of a little over one Angstrom, sufficient
to obtain a detailed atomically-resolved structural
model.
However, at 5.4 reciprocal Angstroms, the
atomic form factor is less than two electrons
. Remember that the scattering intensity scales
with the square of f, and hence the trade-off
we have to accept for increasing the resolution
is a reduction in intensity at the edges of
the detector by more than a factor of four.
Hence the experimentalist must consider what
resolution is necessary to obtain a full structural
model.
There are several complementary methods o
assist in this enterprise, such as molecular
replacement, described in more detail later.
In summary, the periodic nature of crystalline
systems lends them physical and electronic
properties that can only be understood in
terms of that periodicity and the configuration
of the atoms within each period.
At the same time, this periodicity provides
the necessary scattering conditions for diffraction
phenomena.
X-ray diffraction is a nondestructive structural
tool with unsurpassed resolution.
The primary obstacle to reconstructing structural
information from diffraction data is the ubiquitous
phase problem.
The approach to how this is solved essentially
encapsulates the whole art of crystallography.
An impressive arsenal of tools has been developed
over the last century to crack this problem,
and in no more a breathtaking manner than
that used in macromolecular crystallography,
which nowadays can determine the structure
and provide insights into the functionality
of biological systems consisting of tens to
hundreds of thousands of atoms.
These tools will be described detail towards
then end of this course.
Diffraction techniques continue to play leading
roles in modern synchrotron science.
Indeed, with the advent of the free-electron
laser, scattering methods will undoubtedly
enjoy a renewed prominence, particularly in
the field of ultrafast time-resolved studies.