Welcome to the third and last video of Week
6 of this introductory course on synchrotrons
and x-ray free-electron lasers!
This video is concerned first with the complementary
scattering methods of x-ray reflectivity and
the more general technique of small-angle
x-ray scattering; then finally, with some
insights into experimental approaches unique
to diffraction and scattering experiments
using XFEL radiation.
X-ray reflectivity does exactly what it says
on the can - one measures the specular reflectivity
of x-rays as a function of incident angle.
The range of angles typically lies between
a little below the critical angle for total
external reflection, and a few degrees.
From this data, diverse information can be
extracted, including the electron-density
profile down to the penetration depth of the
sample, surface roughness and, in the case
of layered systems, the interface roughness,
layer thickness, and layer density as well;
the properties of multilayer structures; and
even real-time kinetics experiments monitoring
film growth down to pm/s growth rates or even
slower.
The reflectivity amplitude (remember, we actually
measure the intensity, proportional to the
amplitude squared) is given by the Fresnel
equations for reflectivity and transmission,
and is equal to the difference in incident
and transmitted angles across the surface
divided by their sum.
Exactly at the critical angle, therefore,
alpha’ = 0, and the reflectivity is unity,
as we would expect.
We should also recognise that the reflectivity
will drop off thereafter very rapidly with
the incident angle, as the difference in angle
between the incident and transmitted beam
rapidly becomes very small.
From this, it can be easily demonstrated using
the relationship between delta and alpha,
that the reflectivity intensity, big R, is
equal to the expression shown here top left.
For angles significantly larger than alpha_c,
this is accurately approximated by R = alpha_c/(2
alpha), all to the fourth power.
Because alpha is proportional to the scattering
vector Q, the reflectivity curves drop off
with the inverse fourth power of Q.
Note also that because the electron density
of material in electrons/cubic Angstrom oscillates
around approximately Z/25, a very rough and
ready rule of thumb emerges that the critical
angle in degrees is equal to the square-root
of the average atomic number divided by 30,
times the wavelength in Angstroms.
The reflectivity drops off even more rapidly
if the x-rays are being reflected off a rough
surface, even for roughnesses of the order
of a few Angstroms.
If we describe the average roughness as a
Gaussian distribution with a roughness standard
deviation sigma , the reflectivity above the
critical angle drops off as the perfectly
flat surface, multiplied by the Fourier-transform
of the roughness function, that is, the exponent
of [-2k alpha sigma all squared].
For the more maths-adept student, it is briefly
mentioned that this can be explained by the
convolution theorem - the surface is the convolution
of a flat surface with a Gaussian roughness
function, and therefore the scattering pattern
is the Fourier transform of this convolution,
in other words, the reflectivity curve of
the perfectly flat surface multiplied by the
Fourier transform of the roughness function.
The example on the right shows the reflectivity
of silicon for 10-keV photons as a function
of angle and surface roughness.
Thin films grown on materials have many applications,
such as in heteroepitaxial growth of electronic
devices, tribological coatings, protective
layers, and in lipid biology, to name just
a few examples.
A characterisation of these layers is of high
technological importance.
The condition for constructive interference
is as always - that is, the optical path difference
shown here as solid red lines must be equal
to an integer number of wavelengths.
This is essentially a restatement of Bragg’s
law, where alpha equals theta and we approximate
sine alpha with alpha for the shallow angles
relevant to x-ray reflectivity, and the “d-spacing”
is simply the film thickness Delta.
This causes the reflectivity curve to exhibit
oscillations known as “Kiessig fringes”.
The separation between fringes is simply lambda/2
Delta (though the fringes do deviate from
this in the first few oscillations due to
dynamical effects, not covered in this course).
The film thickness can thus be directly obtained
for the Kiessig-fringe period.
On the right, the reflectivity curves for
10-nm films (first element) on atomically
smooth substrates (second element) are shown.
Note that the phase of the Kiessig-Fringe
oscillations differ by approximately pi for
Au on Si compared to Si on Au.
This is because in the latter case, the reflection
at the interface undergoes a pi-phase shift
when the film is less dense than the substrate,
while when the film is denser than the substrate,
no such phase shift occurs.
A simple example is shown here.
An quasicrystalline alloy TiNiZr was grown
on an atomically flat sapphire substrate to
a thickness of approximately 120 nm.
This was then measured some days later, whereby
in the intervening time, the film had been
exposed to air.
The rapid Kiessig oscillations associated
with the film itself
were further modulated by a much slower oscillation,
which was associated with the upper 4 nm of
the film being oxidised during its exposure
to air.
The decrease in reflectivity with surface
roughness can be exploited in in-situ XRR
experiments to monitor film growth.
If the film grows in a layer-for-layer manner
(called Frank van der Merwe growth), then
the roughness will vary sinusoidally, being
maximally rough when each new monolayer is
half complete.
By monitoring the reflectivity during growth,
therefore, the growth can be followed monolayer
for monolayer.
If the material is crystalline, a good angle
to choose to monitor growth is half way between
the direct beam (zero degrees) and the first
Bragg peak in the specular direction (i.e.,
the 001 Bragg peak, if it is not a systematic
absence).
Here, the reflectivity is at a minimum, but
also varies most strongly with roughness.
Because of the weakness of the signal, the
use of synchrotron radiation is important.
Indeed, note that in the curve on the right,
every second roughness oscillation is stronger
- this is due to Kiessig fringes passing through
the point of observation as the film grows.
A movie of the growth in real time is shown
here as an example.
Note, first, that the intensity initially
INCREASES at the start of growth, indicative
that the substrate material on which the film
grew was not perfectly atomically flat and
that the first part of the growth filled in
this incomplete monolayer.
Also note that with increasing film thickness,
the oscillation amplitude wanes - this is
due to the fact that growth is not perfectly
layer-for-layer, and that with time, the film
accumulates an underlying roughness.
This is called Stranski-Krastanov growth.
X-ray reflectivity is in fact just a special
form of small-angle x-ray scattering.
We discuss this technique now.
X-ray scattering from larger objects up to
about a micron in size can also provide important
structural and dimensional information.
Consider an object with a characteristic length
D. The ratio of this length to that of the
x-ray wavelength being used can, depending
on the system, be anything from about 20 to
several thousands.
Scattering is thus typically over angles lambda/D,
which can thus be anything from a couple of
thousandths of a degree to a couple of degrees.
Importantly, the samples investigated using
SAXS need not be crystalline, and the large
majority of experiments are on noncrystalline
samples.
Scattering occurs, just as it does in x-ray
reflectivity, through electron-density variations
Delta rho, and not from individual atoms,
the case in diffraction.
Typical information extracted from SAXS include
characteristic shapes and sizes, surface-area
to volume ratios, and in special cases, the
relationship between two well-defined sizes,
such as between the radius and thickness of
a circular platelet.
Just as the scattering intensity in diffraction
scales with the square of Z, the atomic number,
SAXS signal increases with the square of Delta
rho.
In general, one assumes the individual scatterers
in an ensemble of these, investigated with
SAXS, are well separated (i.e., with neighbour
distances larger than the coherence length)
and can be regarded as separate entities,
in which case the scattering intensity increases
linearly with N_p, the number of illuminated
scatterers.
SAXS has many applications, for example as
an adjunct to protein crystallography, in
order to determine the overall shape of a
given protein structure; in cell biology;
colloidal and polymer sciences; in nanostructure
grown either naturally or specially fabricated
on thin films, to name just a few disciplines.
We have already determined that scattering
angles are measured in small fractions of
a degree up to one or two degrees, hence,
it should not come as a surprise that the
ratio of the distance between the sample and
the detector recording the SAXS signal and
the detector linear dimensions is large.
The sample - detector distance is typically
measured in a few meters.
It is important to avoid spurious signal arising
from other elements at the beamline, such
as forward scattering from x-ray windows or
indeed air!
So, for example, the path between the sample
and detector is normally evacuated using a
long flight tube, while the entrance window
to that flight tube is typically fabricated
not from amorphous material such as kapton,
which would produce its own SAXS signal, but
from thin sheets of highly crystalline material
such as diamond or mica.
Scattering from cleanup slits upstream of
the sample must also be suppressed.
Just as in “normal” crystallography, the
scattering vector Q connects the direct beam
with the scattered beam and, as before, is
equal to 2 k sin theta, or simply 2 k theta,
if theta is expressed in radians.
The SAXS signal tends to be circularly symmetric,
as a large number of randomly oriented particles
are probed simultaneously.
It is therefore the radial signal that is
of interest.
There are three regimes in SAXS: small Q-values,
for which Q is much smaller than 2pi/D, where
D is the characteristic scale of the object
being investigated, large values, for which
Q is much larger than 2pi/D, and an intermediate
regime.
The intermediate regime can provide information
on fractal scaling in systems with nested
characteristic length scales.
The low-Q regime is known as the Guinier regime.
Because the length scales probed here are
generally much larger than the characteristic
length D, details of the particle shape are
completely lost.
Instead, one obtains only information in the
Guinier regime on the overall size, or, more
specifically, the so-called radius of gyration,
R_g.
The radius of gyration is equal to the radius
of inertia in classical mechanics, and is
the radius of a spherical shell of zero shell
thickness, with the same mass (or, more accurately,
scattering power) as the object under investigation.
Guinier’s law states that, at low Q, the
intensity follows the form I(Q) = I_0 exp(-Q^2R_g^2/3),
and is valid for all objects, as long as a
is much larger than D. A plot of the natural
logarithm of I(Q) as a function of Q^2 therefore
results in a gradient of -R_g/3 in the Guinier
regime.
The Porod regime describes the other end of
the scale at large Q, where length scales
much smaller than the object are being probed.
If this is small enough, the x-rays will “see”
the object as being smooth on this scale.
As scattering occurs where there is a change
in electron density, this regime is equivalent
to that of reflectivity, and the intensity
should fall off as 1/Q^4.
A plot of I(Q) v 1/Q^4 should thus produce
a straight line with a gradient equal to 2
pi A, where A is the sample surface area.
This regime is hardest to probe, due to the
associated low intensities.
We finish this week with a brief overview
of diffraction and scattering experiments
at XFELs.
As early as 2000, it was predicted that crystallites
could survive irradiation by XFELs just long
enough before exploding.
This was experimentally confirmed in 2011
for nanocrystals of photosystem I, recorded
at the LCLS.
This concept of diffraction before destruction
led to the method of serial femtosecond crystallography,
in which successive diffraction images of
freshly delivered and randomly oriented crystals
are recorded.
The delivery method may be through some sort
of liquid jet, an aerosol, or on a fixed membrane
system.
Each method has its advantages and disadvantages.
For example, liquid jets are prone to freezing
as they expand into a vacuum, plus only a
very small fraction of the crystallites are
ever irradiated - firstly, the jet moves at
a few meters per second, meaning that, at
the LCLS, running at 120 Hz, the jet moves
forward by approximately 5 or 6 cm between
XFEL pulses, a stretch of material that can
contain several thousand or even some tens
of thousands of crystals.
Increasing the repetition rate helps only
so far, as the jet itself is ripped apart
by the XFEL jet and requires some time to
heal itself and flow continuously once more.
On the other hand, narrow liquid jets have
a relatively low background caused by the
water or other solvent the crystallites are
travelling in.
Because the crystal orientation is random,
each pattern must be ascertained individually,
and sophisticated programs have been developed
to perform this automatically.
As we shall see in the next slide, this is
exacerbated by other factors associated with
the XFEL pulses.
In order to obtain a complete diffraction
pattern with a resolution that allows identification
of individual atoms, several hundred thousand
or even more partial patterns must be recorded.
So, what are the motivations for performing
macromolecular crystallography at XFELs, and
what obstacles other than sample delivery
stand in the way?
First, because the crystals anyway explode
immediately after irradiation, cryocooling
becomes entirely redundant.
The increased mosaicity of protein crystals
caused by cryocooling is therefore bypassed.
Also, because the XFEL pulses can be routinely
focussed down to sub micron dimensions, very
small crystal sizes excluded to synchrotron
experiments can be used, which opens up access
to new systems which have resisted crystal
growth to dimensions of the order of a few
microns or larger.
The large class of proteins called membrane
proteins is a premier example.
Also, if one assumes a given density of crystallographic
defects per unit volume in a crystal, smaller
crystals will be crystallographically purer.
Perhaps most importantly, XFELs allow one
to follow chemical dynamics on a sub-picosecond
time scale, even down to a few femtoseconds,
which is highly relevant for many biochemical
processes.
Biology is all about change - the response
to internal and external physicochemical stimuli
- which is excluded to more conventional synchrotron
studies of cryocooled systems.
Only XFELs can provide this avenue of research.
Accurate data interpretation is hampered by
many issues, however.
first, there are large fluctuations in the
energy of individual pulses, which can vary
by several tens of percent, although this
aspect is slowly improving.
Secondly, the central energy of any single
pulse may fluctuate by a few tens of eV due
to the random nature of the SASE process in
XFELs.
This means that the shell of the Ewald sphere
increases in thickness with Q, varying approximately
as sin^2\theta between 0 in the forward direction
and 2Delta k in the backward scattering direction,
whereby Delta k is the difference in the minimum
and maximum wavevectors associated with the
energy difference.
Because each diffraction pattern is recorded
over a few femtoseconds, there is no possibility
to rotate the crystal during exposure.
This means that diffraction spots are likely
to represent only a partial integration over
the entire diffraction Bragg peak - this is
most obvious in the forward scattering direction,
where the Ewald sphere is still very thin,
and less so as Q increases, though these peaks
become increasingly weak.
Lastly, the size of the crystallite responsible
for any one diffraction pattern is unknown
- is the signal strong because the crystallite
was large, the XFEL pulse energy large, or
due to a coincidental alignment of the Ewald
sphere with the diffraction pattern in reciprocal
space?
Actually, this randomness in crystallite size
can be turned to advantage - after many, many
shots, numbering the hundreds of thousands,
each diffraction peak will have been partially
sampled many times at different positions
relative to the Ewald sphere and originating
from many different crystal sizes.
The crystal can thus be modelled as having
a kind of Gaussian cloud form, representing
an average of all the crystallite sizes and
orientations.
Single-particle imaging using XFEL radiation
was one of the first long-term goals when
funding for XFELs was being sought.
Single-particle imaging is the coherent cousin
to SAXS - the whole mesoscopically-sized particle
is irradiated coherently and the scatter pattern
is recorded.
This is essentially the same as coherent x-ray
diffractive imaging, the major difference
here being that each particle is obliterated
after each shot.
XFELs have 100% transverse coherence, making
it possible to record the coherent scattering
pattern, or “speckle”, of substantially
sized objects, in particular noncoherent objects.
The Fourier transform of that speckle, assuming
one can solve the phase problem, should provide
a 2D slice of the object associated with its
orientation relative to the Ewald sphere.
A complete reconstruction requires that all
orientations have been sampled to a sufficiently
high angular accuracy.
The problem with nonperiodic objects is that
they have no Bragg peaks with which to index
them and through this determine their orientation.
To overcome this, sophisticated iterative
algorithms have been developed, based on the
EMS, or expand, maximise, and compress”
paradigm, explained in detail in the references
below.
Single-particle imaging is also fraught with
technical and experimental obstacles.
First, the sample holder can potentially add
spurious signal to the already weak signal
from the actual sample.
In addition, it is important that any forward
scattering off clean-up slits or other optical
elements is entirely avoided.
Lastly, it is important that sample-to-sample
reproducibility is high.
If a significant fraction of the samples have
a different architecture on the scale to which
the object is to be resolved, the reconstructed
model will contain features of both.
With this, we finish our discussion of scattering
and diffraction experiments at synchrotrons
and XFELs.
X-ray reflectivity and SAXS offer complementary
methods to crystallography methods, not least
in the field of noncrystalline and mesoscopic
objects.
Scattering experiments at XFELs promises a
bright future, especially in those studies
of dynamics of systems such as conformational
changes in proteins under in-vivo-like conditions.
XFEL science is still in its infancy.
The unprecedented jump in peak flux associated
with XFELs opens up new avenues as yet unexplored
in the field of protein structure, and we
can be confident that great new science will
emerge as a consequence of this.
Next week, we turn our attention to spectroscopy
experiments at synchrotrons and XFELs.