Welcome to the first video of Week 7 of this
introductory course on synchrotrons and x-ray
free-electron lasers!
This week, we discuss different spectroscopies
available at x-ray facilities.
Synchrotrons are unique insofar that one can
tune the photon energy, allowing experiments
to be performed that are excluded to lab-based
x-ray sources.
In this first video, we will cover some basic
concepts in x-ray spectroscopy, including
energy balance considerations, and the properties
of photoelectrons.
The second video is primarily concerned with
absorption spectroscopies, which absolutely
require the tunability of synchrotron radiation.
The third and final video is concerned with
spectroscopies that probe different products
resulting from the absorption process, most
importantly x-ray fluorescence and photoelectrons.
So let us begin with a discussion of different
spectroscopic methods and basic ideas behind
spectroscopy.
We can distinguish spectroscopies of tunable
x-ray sources into three main categories.
Absorption techniques require one to tune
the incident radiation.
The range of photons being tuned relative
to absorption edges differentiates XANES (near
the absorption edge) from EXAFS (further above
the absorption edge).
Standard x-ray fluorescence measurements are
typically carried out at fixed incident photon
energies and can be performed using other
sources, including electron excitation.
Resonant x-ray inelastic scattering is a photon-in
- photon-out technique where the fluorescence
spectra as a function of the incident photon
energy are recorded.
Lastly, the energies of photoelectrons caused
by x-ray absorption can be recorded in x-ray
photoelectron spectroscopy, while if the sample
is a single crystal , the signal can be resolved
also as a function of angle relative to the
crystallographic axes of the sample in x-ray
photoelectron diffraction for harder x-rays,
yielding information on near surface structural
conformations; and ARPES, when using ultraviolet
radiation and very soft x-rays, providing
insights into the electronic properties of
the sample.
At the highest photon energies, hard x-ray
photoelectron spectroscopy, or HAXPES, provides
important information structural, chemical,
and electronic information, particularly for
buried structures that are normally inaccessible
to techniques using lower photon energies.
Before we begin our discussions of individual
spectroscopic methods, the difference between
spectromicroscopies and microspectroscopies
is clarified.
Spectromicroscopies image an object at chosen
energies, be the energy that of the incident
radiation, fluorescent signal, or Auger or
photoelectrons.
Each of the 2D images in the vertical stack
here are spectromicroscopy results.
In micro spectroscopy, on the other hand,
the spectral response at a microscopically
defined position is probed, such as at positions
S1 or S2 in the schematic figure.
Commonly, beamlines are equipped to perform
both of these in a single experiment.
XANES and EXAFS are techniques that provide
information on local chemistry, surface adsorbate
configurations, and local structure out to
a few atom-distances.
Both require synchrotron radiation.
By using tightly focussed incident beams,
the response as a function of sample position
can be recorded in scanning techniques.
X-ray fluorescence provides information on
chemistry, and, more commonly and depending
on the detection technique, elemental content.
This is also amenable to scanning methods.
XRF can be performed using lab sources, though
the enhanced brilliance of synchrotron radiation
opens up a much broader palette of methods
and allows access to energies inaccessible
to lab sources.
RIXS, for example, has only become a practicable
method since the advent of high-brilliance
third-generation synchrotron facilities.
Photoelectron spectroscopy is a technique
used widely using lab sources.
However, by tuning the incident radiation,
new variants such as resonant photoelectron
spectroscopies have become available.
The difference between X-ray absorption and
photoelectron spectroscopies is shown here.
XAS promotes core-level electrons to unoccupied
valence-state levels and thereby probes these
upper states by varying the incident photon
energy.
In contrast, in XPS and UPS, the electrons
are directly promoted into the vacuum and
their signal intensity as a function of emitted
electron energy (or binding energy) is recorded
for any given incident photon energy.
This yields information about the core- or
valence state from which the electrons originated.
Hence, each point in an XAS spectrum includes
all the possible processes occurring subsequent
to absorption of a photon of energy h nu,
and can thus be thought of as being the energy-integrated
intensity of an XPS spectrum recorded using
the photon energy associated with that point
in the XAS spectrum.
Pauli’s exclusion principle requires that
the final quantum state Ef was unoccupied
before absorption took place.
In addition, quantum mechanics shows us that
the probability Pif of an optical transition
by the absorption of a photon from an initial
state (labelled as the state vector or ket
psi i in the commonly used Dirac formalism)
to a final state psi f is proportional to
the square of the transition dipole matrix
element shown here in both the shorthand Dirac
formalism and more conventionally as an integral
of the complex conjugate of the final state
psi f, the dipole operator er, and the initial
quantum state psi i over all volume of the
electron wavefunctions.
The dipole operator allowing the transition
of the electron from the original to final
state is er and is antisymmetric.
The wavefunctions are either symmetric or
antisymmetric, hence it should be clear that
the integrand needs to be symmetric for the
integral to be nonzero, which in turn requires
that one wavefunction is symmetric (even parity)
and the other antisymmetric (odd parity).
So, for example, the integrand 1s er 2s consists
of two symmetric wavefunctions and one antisymmetric
operator, and is thus itself antisymmetric,
meaning that its integration over space, the
probability of that transition, is equal to
zero - in other words, a dipole transition
between two symmetric wavefunctions is forbidden.
It is briefly mentioned that other transition
operators such as the quadrupole transition
operator, is itself symmetric, allowing transitions
between two sates of the same symmetry.
These are, however, in general much weaker.
From a quantum-mechanical perspective, free
electrons exhibit both particle- and wavelike
properties.
The wavelength lambda_e of an electron, or
indeed any particle with momentum p, is given
by lambda_e = h/p, where h is Planck’s constant
equal to 6.63 x 10^-34 J.s.
This is the de Broglie wavelength.
Because the wavevector associated with a wavelength
lambda is 2 pi/lambda, p is equal to hbar
k, where hbar = h/2pi.
The kinetic energy of a non relativistic particle
is simply 1/2 mv^2, but because p = mv, this
means that the KE is equal to p^2/2m, or hbar^2k_e^2/2m_e
for an electron.
But the kinetic energy of an electron is what’s
left over from the photon energy after the
original binding energy of the electron to
the atom is subtracted.
We can rearrange these relationships to obtain
an expression for lambda_e as a function of
the photon energy and binding energy, as shown
here.
This can be further modified to obtain the
simple expressions lambda_e in Angstroms = 12.28/square
root of E_e in eV, or the wavevector in inverse
Angstroms = 0.512 x square root of E_e in
eV.
So, for example, an electron with a 100-eV
kinetic energy, would have a de Broglie wavelength
of 1.228 Angstroms.
The binding energy of an electron E_B depends
on orbital it occupies and the elements atomic
number (i.e., nuclear charge).
The binding energies for all the elements
and for the lowest five core levels is shown
here.
The soft- tender- and hard-x-ray regimes are
shown in yellow, green, and blue, respectively.
Note that even the most strongly bound K-electron
of uranium can be accessed at some synchrotron
facilities.
An important parameter, especially in the
fields of photoelectron spectroscopies and
EXAFS, is the so-called inelastic mean free
path, or IMFP, which is the distance through
which an electron must pass in a material
before it is scattered inelastically with
a probability of 1 - 1/e = 63%.
When an electron has high energies, its small
de-Broglie wavelength means that it has a
smaller effective cross-section and larger
IMFP.
Conversely, the dominant mechanism to induce
inelastic scatter of electrons is through
excitation of so-called “plasmons”, or
collective oscillations of electrons in the
(normally metallic) material.
At energies much lower than 10 eV, the electron
has insufficient energy to excite these plasmon
modes, and the inelastic mean free path increases
rapidly.
Between approximately 10 and a few hundred
to a thousand eV, the IMFP takes on values
of a few Angstroms to ten or so Angstroms.
This is of the order of the top few atomic
layers of the sample, and hence techniques
that record such photoelectrons are in general
highly surface sensitive.
This means that such experiments have highly
stringent requirements on the purity of the
surface and quality of vacuum in which the
experiment is performed, as we will touch
on again later.
The variation of the IMFP at a given electron
energy between different elements is fairly
modest.
The reason for this is that it is primarily
dependent on average electron-electron distances,
which are proportional to the cube root of
the electron density, which for most materials
varies no more than a factor of approximately
30.
The cube root of 30 is a little over three,
hence the spread of data points lie all fairly
comfortably within this range (note the logarithmic
ordinate axes).
This is why this plot is referred to as the
“universal curve”.
Lastly, it should be noted that the penetration
depth of photons in a material is in general
significantly higher than the IMFP, and hence
it is the latter that determines the depth
resolution for those experiments probing the
photoelectron energy.
The density of and interaction between orbitals
depend on whether the system is isolated,
as in a dilute noble gas, or involves inter-atomic
interactions, such as in molecules and even
more so in condensed matter.
The well-defined valence orbitals of an atom
become less well defined in molecules due
to interaction of orbitals and the formation
of bonds.
When a system contains numbers of atoms similar
to Avogadro’s number, the valence orbitals
are so densely packed that they form bands.
Just as two separated orbitals of two electrons
combine together in the formation of a bond
to form a bound and anti bonding state (the
first being at lower energy and occupied,
the latter at higher energy and unoccupied),
the interaction of many, many atoms in condensed
matter produce a valence (occupied) band and
a conduction (unoccupied) band, at least at
absolute zero temperature.
How the valence and conduction bands sit relative
to one another determines whether the system
is a metal, semiconductor, or insulator.
In a metal, the top of the valence band and
bottom of the conduction band meet, allowing
the promotion of electrons to the otherwise
empty conduction band even with the tiniest
of excitation energies.
In semiconductors, there exists a band gap
that can be overcome by a certain fraction
of the valence-band electrons, spending on
the size of the gap and the temperature of
the system.
In insulators, the band gap is so large that
effectively no electrons can access the conduction
band without heating it up so much that the
material thermally breaks up.
Core orbitals, however, remain fairly inured
to the “outside world” and remain well-defined,
even in condensed matter.
Above the K-edge, associated with the 1s lowest-energy
core level, the orbitals are split into sub-levels,
manifesting themselves as sub-edges, as shown
here for the L-edge of Zr.
This is caused by the nonzero orbital angular
momentum of some of the orbitals (such as
p- or d-orbitals) coupling in different configurations
with the spin angular momentum of the electrons
in a process called spin-orbit coupling.
So, for example, the L-edge is composed of
an unsplit 2s-orbital, plus two spin-orbit
split 2p 1/2 and 2p 3/2 orbitals.
We finish this first video with a schemaitc
of a generic setup for x-ray spectroscopy
experiments.
Monochromatic synchrotron radiation is allowed
to impinge on a sample.
X-ray absorption spectra can be performed
by measuring the amount of light that passes
through a thin sample.
The x-ray intensities before entering the
sample (I0) and after (I) are measured using
ionization chambers (IC) or other beam-intensity
monitors, and is particularly suited for samples
that cannot be placed in vacuum, such as in
biological or catalytic experiments.
The total electron current through an ammeter
between the sample and ground can also be
used to indirectly determine the absorption
spectrum.
In this case, the sample and detectors must
be in vacuum.
X-ray fluorescence spectra can be recorded,
either using a crystal monochromator (XM)
in wavelength-dispersive spectra (WDX), or
by using a dispersive solid-state semiconductor
device (EDX).
The integrated fluorescence yield can also
be used as a measure of absorption strength.
Unwanted detection of elastically scattered
x-rays is best achieved by placing the detector
on the polarization axis of the synchrotron
radiation.
The kinetic energy of photoelectrons and Auger
electrons can be determined using electron
energy-dispersive analysers.
In summary, this first video has prepared
us for a closer discussion of individual spectroscopic
methods.
In the second video, we will concentrate on
different variants of absorption spectroscopy.