Welcome to the second video of Week 7 of this
introductory course on synchrotrons and x-ray
free-electron lasers!
In this video, I will introduce you to different
absorption spectroscopies, which absolutely
require the tunability of synchrotron radiation.
We can divide up absorption spectroscopies
to the so-called XANES regime that lies within
a couple of tens of eV from the absorption
edge, and the EXAFS technique, which ranges
from approximately 50 eV above an absorption
edge to several hundred eV, or even a kiloelectronvolt
above this.
We start by discussing XANES.
XANES is short for x-ray absorption near-edge
spectroscopy.
It also goes under another name, NEXAFS, or
near-edge x-ray absorption fine structure,
though I prefer to avoid this, as it is both
redundant, and its orthographical similarity
to EXAFS, an absorption technique based on
entirely different principles, can be the
source for confusion.
In addition to “simple” XANES, the variants
STXM, PEEM, XMCD, and XMLD will be discussed.
XANES is a technique in which the photon energy
is so chosen that a core-level electron can
be promoted to an unoccupied but bound or
quasibound orbital of the system.
Depending on the system, these unoccupied
states can be diffuse, but can also be fairly
sharp, especially for example, for molecule
that are weakly adsorbed on a surface and
may only weakly interact with that “host”
material.
The absorption cross-section for photoexcitation
of a core-electron to the near vacuum exhibits
oscillations in the neighbourhood of the absorption
edge caused by excited bound states and also
the quasicontinuum just above the ionization
threshold, which exhibit large fluctuations
in their density of states.
This is the XANES signal.
For the low photoelectron energies typical
of XANES, the inelastic mean free path becomes
significantly larger than at higher energies
- remember the universal curve shown in the
previous video.
XANES therefore ‘sees’ a large range of
absorber–scatterer distances.
This results in multiple scattering of the
photoelectrons, which means theoretical modelling
of XANES still remains a significant challenge.
XANES spectra are therefore mostly interpreted
and not quantitatively analyzed.
The lowest-energy XANES signals actually occur
below the absorption edge, and are referred
to pre-edge transitions.
Pre-edge features are strongly influenced
by the symmetry of the local environment around
the absorbing atom.
To understand this, one must first appreciate
that orbitals in molecules and solid-state
systems can assume the character of a mixture
of atomic orbitals and are related to the
symmetry of the local environment, such as
the simple example the famous tetragonally
symmetric sp3-orbitals of diamond formed by
hybridization of one 2s- and three 2p-atomic
orbitals.
Those orbitals around an atom which are allowed
depend on the symmetry of the local environment.
In general orbitals exhibit a so-called ‘parity’
of (−1)^l, where l is the orbital angular
momentum quantum number - it is equal to 0,
1, and 2, for s-, p-, and d-orbitals, respectively.
An orbital has positive parity and is symmetric
if it is invariant under the operation of
moving each volume element of the orbital
amplitude wavefunction from r to −r – it
is said to be inversion symmetric.
Hence, the spherically symmetric s-states
have positive parity (as do the d-orbitals),
while the p- and f-states are antisymmetric
and have therefore negative parity, as we
touched on in the last video.
One can also have local environments which
are inversion symmetric, such as any of the
atom sites in a rocksalt crystal.
In such environments, atomic orbitals with
different parities cannot hybridize, as the
symmetry of such hybridized orbitals does
not match that of the environment.
So, for example, an sp3-orbital is incompatible
with an inversion-symmetric environment.
Consider as an example a material for which
a transition between a symmetric K-state (1s,
l = 0) and a bound excited state of mostly
(symmetric) d-character is observed with high
intensity.
We have already argued that in the dipole
approximation, only p-states (antisymmetric)
are accessible from s-states.
Hence the upper bound state must have both
p-type (antisymmetric) and d-type character.
From this we learn that the environment around
the absorbing atom cannot be inversion symmetric
because of the partial antisymmetric p-character.
The presence of bound-state resonant absorption
peaks therefore provides important information
on the local symmetry of the system.
6.
We now show two illustrative examples of information
that can be extracted using XANES.
The XANES spectra of the five 5d-metals Re,
Os, Ir, Pt, and Au is shown here.
The ground-state electronic configuration
of Re is that of [Xe], plus 6s2 4f14 5d5.
As one moves to the right in the periodic
table from Re, the remaining five available
5d-states are filled.
In gold, these states are fully occupied.
In the elements Re to Pt, the bound but unoccupied
5d-states, which are below the ionization
threshold, are seen as intense peaks, though
this become weaker as the d-orbitals are successively
filled.
As gold has no such unoccupied states, excitation
is necessarily directly into the unbound continuum,
and its XANES spectrum is consequently much
flatter.
In the second XANES example, it is shown that
orientational information can be extracted
by observation of changes in XANES spectra
according to the polarisation of the x-rays
used.
The probability of a photon being absorbed
depends on the orientation of the electric
field vector (the polarization, P) of the
electromagnetic field of the x-rays relative
to the polarization direction of the orbital
being excited.
So, for example, the pi-orbital of the formate
radical shown top centre lies perpendicular
to the molecular plane, and is most efficiently
excited if P has the same orientation.
Because the electric field is always perpendicular
to the propagation direction of the x-ray
beam, this means that the latter must lie
in or close to the molecular plane.
In contrast, the sigma orbital is responsible
for the C-O bond and lies along that axis,
top right.
The strongest excitation of this orbital thus
requires the polarisation to be in the same
direction.
The formate radical binds strongly to the
surface of Cu(110) shown top left.
The orientation of the molecule was unambiguously
determined by the change in the XANES signal
with x-ray polarization orientation and incident
angle of the x-rays on the surface.
Importantly, when the x-rays strike the surface
at a glancing angle of 20 degrees and P is
parallel to the ⟨110⟩ crystal axis of
the copper, excitation of the pi-orbital is
suppressed, but is strongly enhanced if the
sample is rotated so that P is parallel to
the ⟨001⟩ direction.
This leads to the conclusion that the formate
radical is oriented with the molecular plane
perpendicular to the surface and parallel
to the ⟨110⟩ direction, shown bottom-right.
Further details of this beautifully illustrative
example can be found in the reference given
here.
Since the introduction of high-brilliance
radiation in third-generation synchrotron
facilities and the development of high-quality
x-ray focussing elements such as Fresnel zone
plates, x-ray focal spot sizes of the order
of a micron or even an order of magnitude
smaller have become routinely achievable.
With this, so-called ‘microspectroscopy’
methods have flourished, in which the chemistry
of heterogeneous samples can be mapped out
with high spatial resolution.
One of the most important of these to emerge
is scanning transmission x-ray microscopy
(STXM), particularly in the field of polymer
chemistry and physics, where phenomena such
as segregation and heterogeneous morphology
must be understood at a submicron scale.
STXM can be thought of raster-scanning XANES
operated in the transmission mode.
There are many problems in biology, organic
chemistry, and polymer physics which require
detailed chemical analysis at a submicron
scale but mapped over macroscopic areas.
Although traditional methods such as infrared
spectroscopy and nuclear magnetic resonance
can differentiate chemical species (by observing
subtle differences in bond strengths caused
by the local chemical environment), their
spatial resolution is limited to the millimetre-scale.
STXM is a technique for spatially mapping
with submicron resolution the chemical contents
of organic samples.
This is particularly important for experiments
performed within the energy range defined
by the so-called ‘water window’, which
lies between the K-edge of carbon at 284 eV
and 543 eV, the K-edge of oxygen.
In this energy range, biological and in-vivo
specimens absorb approximately an order of
magnitude more strongly than water and can
therefore reside in an aqueous environment
and need not be stained with heavy metals
or sliced (both of which are common procedures
in the preparation of organic specimens in
transmission electron microscopy).
Note also that the L-edges of several biologically
relevant elements, in particular potassium,
sulfur, and calcium, lie within the water
window, while phosphorus’s L1-edge is sometimes
also accessible at 189 eV.
STXM is frequently used to characterize polymer
films, because of the very rich and informative
C 1s XANES spectra of polymers.
Examples of XANES spectra for three common
polymers are shown here.
Note that the aromatic polymer PEEK and the
unsaturated polymer neoprene, both of which
contain pi orbitals, contain sharp pre-edge
carbon peaks associated with the lowest unoccupied
pi* orbital, while the saturated polymer polythene
contains signal associated only with sigma
bonding.
Such differences when scanned across polymer
films provides important information on the
polymerisation process and degree of inhomogeneity.
Photoemission electron microscopy (PEEM) is
a technique that images the spatial distribution
of electrons emitted from a sample due to
x-ray absorption in the XANES region.
Although the technique uses photoelectrons
for its signal, it is not an electron-spectroscopy
technique.
Photoelectron spectroscopy detects photoelectrons
from the near-surface region that have not
been inelastically scattered.
In contrast, in PEEM the energies of the electrons
are not distinguished.
Instead, the absorption coefficient is indirectly
measured via the yield of secondary electrons,
that is, those electrons released by the system
after multiple scattering events in a cascade
process originating with the directly produced
photoelectron from the absorbing atom . This
initial photoelectron may derive from an atom
relatively deep in the material, as the x-rays
can penetrate to depths of several tens of
nanometres.
The initial photoelectron can only travel
a few Angstroms, however, before interacting
inelastically with its surroundings via one
of several scattering phenomena, which produces
a cascade of ‘daughter’ electrons with
ever decreasing energy.
As the electrons’ kinetic energy approaches
only a few eV, the mean free path increases
rapidly and they can escape the surface with
higher probability – a typical graph of
yield versus energy shows a maximum just above
the work function, which then drops off with
energy.
The majority of emitted secondary electrons
therefore have energies of the order of an
electronvolt.
Although their detection does not yield absolute
results for the absorption coefficient, the
spectral dependence is adequately reflected.
This secondary-electron signal is collected
using electron optics similar to those used
in electron microscopy
A PEEM experiment essentially consists of
tuning synchrotron radiation illuminating
an entire sample in vacuum and imaging the
spatial variation of the subsequent secondary-electron
yield using the electrostatic and/or electromagnet
lens system.
As such, PEEM is a form of ‘spectromicroscopy’
– full-field images are recorded at different
photon energies, in contrast to STXM, a microspectroscopy
technique in which the focussed x-ray beam
is rastered across the sample.
The secondary electrons are imaged using a
2-D detector.
In contrast to scanning electron microscopy,
PEEM does not use a scanned probe electron
beam, but instead the sample surface is uniformly
illuminated by the x-rays.
The magnified image of the surface can therefore
be observed directly and in real-time - stroboscopic
time-resolved experiments can therefore be
performed using the time structure of the
synchrotron down to time scales well below
a nanosecond.
Because the IMFP of the secondary electrons
is of the order of several nanometers or more,
PEEM is in general not surface sensitive,
although this can be induced by irradiating
the sample with x-rays at very glancing angles
theta, thereby reducing their penetration
depth below the sample surface by a factor
sin theta.
The best resolution of PEEM lies around 25
nm, and depends on the acceleration high voltage
of the objective lens and how close this is
to the sample.
X-ray magnetic circular dichroism and x-ray
magnetic linear dichroism are two variants
of PEEM commonly used to investigate domain
formation in ferromagnets and antiferromagnets,
respectively, by detecting differences in
their absorption spectra according to the
type and orientation of the polarisation of
the incident x-rays.
XMCD functions because magnetic materials
have an imbalance of electrons with spin up
and spin down in the valence band.
So, for example, the transition from a 2p
core level to the unoccupied states 3d band
via absorption of an x-ray photon will contain
two components, one from the 2p1/2, the other
from the 2p3/2.
These are allowed, as the change in orbital
angular momentum, Delta l = 1.
One must take a further selection rule into
account which states that for dipole transitions,
spin flips are forbidden.
This rule is not entirely strict for condensed
matter, but is sufficiently observed to induce
dichroism.
To obtain the XMC signal, one uses circularly
polarized light.
in the case of domain 1, an incident RCP photon
has its orbital angular momentum pointing
forwards (in the direction of propagation,
and will preferentially excite the 2p3/2 (or
L3) levels over the 2p1/2 (or L2) levels.
The opposite case arises for LCP photons,
whereby the 2p1/2 states are favoured.
If we now focus on region 2, the whole story
reverses, as now the spin-down 3d-subband
is shifted to higher energies than the spin-up
subband.
By recording PEEM images of ferromagnetic
domains with RCP and LCP x-rays and dividing
the intensities of one image, pixel-for-pixel,
by those of the other, the domain structure
is revealed with maximum contrast.An example
is given here for magnetic structures fabricated
from thin films of Ni-Fe.
The pyramid-looking contrast indicates the
formation of a closed loop of magnetic domains,
a mimimum-energy configuration.
X-ray magnetic linear dichroism probes the
domain structure of antiferromagnetic (AFM)
materials, which are characterized by having
antiparallel orientations of neighbouring
magnetic moments and thus no net spin, but
nevertheless a defined magnetic axis below
a critical temperature (the Neel temperature),
as shown here for nickel oxide.
XMLD signal arises from the fact that, due
to spin-orbit coupling, the spatial distribution
of the electron density is marginally distorted,
providing the necessary dichroism depending
on whether the linear polarization vector
is parallel to or perpendicular to the magnetic
axis.
The effect is usually small and detecting
XMLD is more challenging than XMCD.
It has a cos^2 theta dependence, where theta
is the angle between the polarization vector
of the x-ray light and the magnetic axis of
the domain.
The maximum XMLD effect therefore occurs when
the signal for the polarization parallel to
the magnetic axis is compared to that perpendicular
to the axis.
We now move on and up in energy to EXAFS techniques.
Extended x-ray absorption fine structure begins
approximately 50 eV above the absorption edge
and consists of oscillations in the absorption
up to as far as a keV above the edge.
If we remember our equation for the de Broglie
wavelength, we see that EXAFS probes electrons
with wavelengths of the order of 0.4 to 1.5
Angstroms, similar to if slightly smaller
than interatomic distances.
The mean-free path of electrons in this range
is short, of the order of a few Angstroms,
hence EXAFS only probes the immediate neighbourhood
of the absorbing atom.
EXAFS is therefore an important technique
in noncrystalline solids and liquids, as it
yields information of the short-range structure.
It is much used for investigating liquids,
clusters, biological materials, low-concentration
impurities down to 10 parts per million, and
catalysts, although it can also be used for
well-ordered structures, and is thus complementary
to diffraction.
EXAFS is caused by single backscattering events
by nearest-neighbour atoms of the outgoing
photoelectron produced through x-ray absorption.
The scattered waves interfere with the original
photoelectron wave, which results in a change
in the electron density at the absorbing atom
and consequently leads to a modulation of
the absorption strength mu(E) as the photon
energy is scanned.
The most important parameters in addition
to the atomic absorption coefficient mu are
the electron wavelength lambda_e, the number
and type of nearest neighbours, and the distance
R between the absorbing atom and neighbouring
atoms, as shown schematically here.
The EXAFS oscillatory signal increases with
the number of neighbours in a given shell;
while the oscillation period dilates with
decreasing shell radius.
Consider first the absorption coefficient
of an isolated atom, μ0(k), which varies
monotonically and smoothly with wavevector
(or energy) above the absorption edge.
In condensed matter, however, the absorption
coefficient μ(k) is modulated by the so-called
EXAFS function χ(k) because of interference
with backscattered waves, and so mu(k) = mu_0(k)
times (1+chi(k)), which we can rearrange to
obtain chi(k) - mu(k) - mu_0(k) divided by
mu_0(k).
Chi(k) is therefore an expression of the effect
on an isolated atom’s absorption characteristics
caused by it no longer being isolated.
More precisely, the effect of a given shell
j is the sum of the N_j atoms in that shell,
assuming their contributions are isotropic.
An illustrative example of the effect of neighbouring
atoms is shown on the right for the K-edge
of krypton in its gas, liquid, and crystalline
solid phase.
We now present the standard expression used
for χiso(k) and then justify its content.
The EXAFS equation is shown here.
Although this might seem at first intimidatingly
complex, we can break to down into individual
components as follows.
First, the summation is over j shells - as
the EXAFS electrons only have short mean-free
paths, we need not consider any shell radii
much larger than this, that is, a few Angstroms.
Each shell contains N_j backscattering atoms.
while the scattering amplitude of these atoms
is expressed through the term t_j(k).
The
heart of the EXAFS equation is given the sinusoidal
term expressing the interference between the
outgoing and backscattered electron waves
- it is this part which, through Fourier analysis,
yields the interatomic distances.
The 1/R_j^2 is simply the inverse square law
of a spherically expanding signal, and should
be self-explanatory - the further out the
scattered atom at a distance R_j, the weaker
is the backscattered wave at the initially
absorbing atom.
The Gaussian term here accounts for the fact
that the neighbouring atoms are not stationary,
but vibrating with an amplitude sigma_j parallel
to k.
This is the well-known Debye-Waller factor,
and is normally only marginally below unity
for samples at room temperature.
Lastly, the exponential term accounts for
inelastic and multiple scattering of the electron
wave (mainly by plasmons and phonons) on its
round trip of 2Rj, where Λ is the electron’s
mean-free path length.
The entire equation is shown again here with
the visual prompts, for completeness.
Data analysis of EXAFS spectra proceeds as
follows.
The oscillatory function chi(k) is extracted
from the raw data mu(E) by removal of the
background signal fitted to the pre-edge signal
and then the monotonically varying signal
mu_0(E) above the absorption edge.
The EXAFS function is then re-expressed as
a function of k instead of E_e and weighted
to enhance the weak oscillations at higher
k by multiplication of chi(k) by k^2 or k^3.
This function is then Fourier transformed,
which converts the data from being expressed
in terms of frequencies (proportional to k)
to a plot which reveals characteristic lengths,
associated with the interatomic distances
R_j.
EXAFS is a useful technique to observe chemical
changes, particularly in poorly crystalline
or entirely noncrystalline materials.
Two methods in particular are used.
In quick-EXAFS, or QEXAFS, monochromatic tuning
of bending-magnet or wiggler radiation is
achieved using a channel-cut monochromator.
***** These sources and this type of monochromator
is used in order to achieve the highest speeds
- the sources are broadband and so do not
require variation of the gap size associated
with undulator photon-energy tuning, which
would slow things down significantly; the
channel-cut mono is used, as it requires the
rotation of a single motor, again thereby
avoiding the need to mechanically change synchronously
several components, as would be the case in
a double-crystal monochromator.
In energy-dispersive x-ray absorption spectroscopy,
or EDXAS, a divergent white x-ray beam impinges
on a bent crystal or grating sitting on an
ellipse defined by its foci being at the source
and the sample.
This selects different wavelengths from the
white beam, depending on the angle the divergent
beam hits the bent crystal.
This dispersed radiation is focussed by the
bent crystal on to the sample, and the transmitted
signal is detected using a one- or two dimensional
detector.
There are no moving parts in EDXAS, hence
very rapid changes can be monitored.
The disadvantages of EDXAS are that even very
small distortions of the polychromator crystal
due to thermal drifts or other effects will
cause the dispersed signal to drift spatially.
This sets exceedingly stringent specifications
in EDXAS for mechanical and thermal stability.
EDXAS is also often used for studies at extreme
conditions of pressure using diamond-anvil
cells, which have small volumes and limited
acceptance angles.
A limitation of EDXAS is that it assumes that
the sample is homogeneous across the focussed
spot.
If this condition is not met, artefacts will
arise in the recorded spectra.
This completes our discussion of absorption
spectroscopies.
In the third and last video of the week, we
consider spectroscopies that probe products
of absorption, namely fluorescence photons
and photoelectrons.