Welcome to the third and final video of Week
7 of this introductory course on synchrotrons
and x-ray free-electron lasers!
In this video, we discuss techniques that
probe either photons or electrons resulting
after absorption. Specifically, we will discuss
the photon-in - photon-out techniques of x-ray
fluorescence and RIXS, plus variants of photoelectron
spectroscopy, in particular x-ray photoelectron
spectroscopy, angle-resolved photoelectrons
spectroscopy, and hard x-ray photoelectron
spectroscopy.
Fluorescence spectroscopies are photon-in
- photon-out techniques and can be carried
out on both conducting and insulating samples.
As a result, these techniques can often be
applied under ambient or indeed in-vivo environments,
depending on the energy range of interest.
X-ray fluorescence generally probes the fluorescence
spectrum resulting from absorption at a fixed
incident photon energy, although excitation
can also be via impact of energetic electrons.
Resonant inelastic x-ray scattering, on the
other hand, probes the emission spectra as
a function of incident photon energy.
X-ray fluorescence probes the photons emitted
as a consequence of relaxation of the system
after photoabsorption.
The energy ranges of XRF and XAS are related,
insofar that where XRF ends, XAS begins. This
is because the emission spectrum probes the
highest-energy occupied states, whereas XAS
spectra only begin at the lowest-energy unoccupied
states.
X-ray fluorescence is a powerful method for
determining the chemical composition of objects
that are either too thick for transmission-absorption
measurements, or are insulating and therefore
preclude photoemission techniques. XRF is
used widely in geochemistry, archaeology,
forensic science, and investigations of rare
or ancient artefacts. It exploits the ‘fingerprint’
characteristic radiation of the elements for
chemical and elemental analysis.
In x-ray fluorescence spectromicroscopy, the
dispersed XRF signal is mapped out spatially
using a focussed beam. This can be performed
either using EDX or a von-Hamos spectrometer.
WDX setups, in which the fluorescence energy
is serially scanned, are too slow.
XRF signal is strongly absorbed by air for
emission below approximately 2500 eV, which
corresponds to Sulphur or Chlorine K-alpha
emission, or thereabouts. For emission signal
below this photon energy, the path to the
detector should be evacuated to avoid absorption
by the residual gas, such that the product
of the sample–detector distance and pressure
is less than approximately 1 Pa m (note that
there are 100’000 Pa per atmosphere, or
100 Pa per mbar). A sample-detector distance
of 10 cm would thus require pressures of the
order of 0.1 mbar or lower.
If the XRF spectra are energetically well
resolved, requiring either a WDX or von-Hamos
setup, subtle peak shifts and splittings can
be detected, much as in XANES. For example,
the K-alpha lines omitted by 3d-elements,
produce two lines, K-alpha-1 and K-alpha-2,
caused by spin-orbit splitting of the core
2p-electron energy level. This is still energetically
removed from the valence states, the states
that are most affected by chemistry, and thus
provide little or no chemical information.
In contrast, relaxation from the 3p electron
levels (the so-called k-beta lines) ***** exhibit
more subtle splittings and shifts, due to
the significantly stronger interaction between
the 3p-states and the 3d-valence band. If
the spectra are recorded with an energy resolution
of the order of an eV or better, valuable
information of the local oxidation state and
chemical bonding can be gleaned.
An example is shown here of x-ray fluorescence
microspectroscopy carried out on the famous
fossil specimen of archaeopteryx thermopolis
at the SSRL in Stanford, recorded with incident
energies of 3.15 keV and 13.5 keV for low-Z
and high-Z elements, respectively, and a spatial
resolution of 100 microns.
Results show that portions of the feathers
are not merely impressions, but are in fact
remnant body fossil structures, that, remarkably,
have maintained elemental compositions that
are completely different from the embedding
geological matrix, indicating elemental retention
in soft tissue (through the presence of phosphorus
and sulfur), as well as trace metal (Zn and
Cu) retention in bone structures over many
tens of millions of years. In addition, information
about the likely fossilisation process (known
as “taphonomy”) could be extracted.
Both XRF and x-ray absorption spectroscopy
are sensitive to local electronic structure
and bonding around the absorbing/emitting
atom. When one combines these techniques,
further detailed information becomes possible,
in the relatively new technique of resonant
inelastic x-ray spectroscopy, or RIXS. RIXS
has many analogies with Raman spectroscopy
in the visible and infrared regime.
The energy difference between the emitted
photon and the incident photon can range between
some meV and a few eV. This energy loss, plus
the momentum transfer and change in polarization
between the incoming and outgoing photon is
directly associated with the production of
an electron-hole pair, induced by one or more
important processes related to electronic
and superconducting properties, such as phonon,
magnon, or low-energy electronic excitations.
Like I just said, RIXS is the marriage of
conventional x-ray absorption and x-ray fluorescence
in a single experiment. RIXS signal can be
directly generated following resonant absorption
of a photon by an atom promoting an electron
to an unoccupied conduction-band state, followed
by relaxation of a lower-lying state to the
core, resulting in the formation of an electron-hole
pair.
Indirect RIXS signal occurs when absorption
and relaxation are between the same two states,
but, when the atom is in the excited intermediate
state, a strong electrostatic screening potential
around the core hole ‘shakes’ the atom,
resulting in the promotion of an electron
from the valence- to the conduction band and
an energetic rearrangement of the absorbing
upper level.
XAS and/or XRF alone cannot probe the electron
momenta and can therefore yield no insights
into the material’s electronic bandstructure.
The reason for this is essentially because
a core hole is involved — in the case of
XAS this hole is in the final state after
absorption, while in XRF it is in the initial
state. due to the local formation of a hole,
this results in a breakdown of the crystal’s
translational symmetry at exactly the location
where the measurement is being made, which
has the consequence that k, the electron momentum,
is no longer well defined.
In RIXS, neither the initial or final states
contain a core vacancy and thus momentum remains
a good quantum number. This makes RIXS an
important adjunct to ARPES, described later
in this video, as a probe for the electronic
bandstructure of a wide variety of materials.
In addition, because RIXS excitations are
second-order and involve the virtual absorption
of a photon, certain excitations (such as
the d − d excitation between 3d-states in
transition-metal oxides) are allowed, but
which are forbidden in direct optical processes.
A unique feature of RIXS is the very large
range of energies and momenta that can be
transferred to the system under investigation
in the inelastic scattering event. This is
because photons instead of electrons (used
in photoelectron studies) are used as probes.
For a given wavelength lambda (be it the de
Broglie wavelength of the electron or the
photon wavelength), or more conveniently,
the wavenumber k, which equals 2pi/lambda,
and is directly proportional to the momentum,
the ratio of the photon- to electron energy
is hnu/Ee = hbar c k divided by hbar^2k^2
over 2m, which equals 2 mc/hbar k, or in practical
units 517.3/k, where k is expressed in reciprocal
Angstroms. So for typical wavevectors of the
order of 1 reciprocal Angstrom, the range
of energies and scattering vectors Q available
to RIXS surpass other x-ray methods by approximately
two orders of magnitude.
One distinguishes two types of energy-loss
features in RIXS, according to whether they
vary or not as a function of the incident
photon energy hbar Ω. Features which are
independent of hbar Q appear as vertical lines
in a two-dimensional plot of energy transfer
versus incident energy, shown here schematically.
They represent electron-hole pair excitations
associated with two well-defined states and
are therefore products of RIXS processes.
Their analogy in the optical regime are Stokes
phonons in Raman spectroscopy, from which
they obtain their name of Raman peaks. In
contrast, those features which exhibit a constant
emission photon energy are called x-ray fluorescence-
or emission lines. In the plot of energy transfer
versus incident energy, these lines have a
gradient of unity.
We turn now to photoelectron spectroscopies.
There are many variants of PES. Ultraviolet
and very soft x-rays probe the most weakly
bound, valence electrons of a system, and
can provide important information on the material’s
electronic band structure, particularly when
the electron momentum (that is, it’s emission
direction relative to the crystal lattice
from which it emerged) is also recorded.
At higher photon energies, core electrons
can also be accessed, providing information
on the sample chemistry in the technique of
x-ray photoelectron spectroscopy, originally
named electron spectroscopy for chemical analysis,
or ESCA.
Scattering phenomena of the photoelectrons
as they emerge for the sample surface can
provide invaluable structural information
of that surface and near-surface region.
Hard x-ray PES, or HAXPES, uses high-energy
x-rays, not to access information of the chemistry
via excitation of core electrons, but instead
to probe the electronic properties of the
sample via the valence electrons, similar
to the case of ARPES. However, because the
photon energy is high and the valence-electron
binding energies low, the photoelectron energies
will also be high. This brings us towards
the high-energy regime of the universal curve,
for which the inelastic mean-free path is
higher. As a result, HAXPES probes not the
surface region, but instead the sample’s
bulk properties, or, indeed, the electronic
properties of interfacial regions in thin-film
heterostructures.
We begin our discussion of PES with the physical
process responsible for the generation of
photoelectrons, the photoelectric effect.
This is the phenomenon that electrons can
be emitted from the surface of a metal, but
only if the wavelength of light used is shorter
than a critical value. Light of longer wavelengths
than this fail to eject electrons, even if
higher beam intensities are used. Although
both Heinrich Hertz and JJ Thomson observed
aspects of the photoelectric effect, it would
take the insights of Albert Einstein to explain
it. Einstein invoked the concept of there
being a minimum packet of energy associated
with light of a frequency nu, and that light
consisted of these packets, or quanta, of
light, called nowadays photons. This paradigm
shift in the description of light as consisting
of particles instead of being a wave would
earn Einstein a Nobel prize in physics in
1921.
The threshold upper wavelength for electron
emission, or, more intuitively, the lowest
frequency, is associated with the so-called
work function. The work function arises because,
as an electron originally residing in a state
at the top of the valence band is removed
from the surface of a material, it is attracted
by its positively charged mirror image that
is produced by a rearrangement of the surface
charge resulting from its departure.
Only at distances of more than about 100 Angstroms
does this electrostatic image force become
negligible. This image potential is the reason
why electricity does not ‘leak’ out from
metals and electrons do not shoot out of kinks
in current-carrying wires; so, for typical
work functions of 5 eV, one would require
electric field strengths of the order of 100
MeV/m to electrostatically remove electrons
from metal surfaces.
The energy of the photoelectrons is thus equal
to the photon energy minus the electron binding
energy and also minus the work function. Both
UPS and XPS in general produce electrons with
kinetic energies between a few tens of eV
and approximately 1000 eV , for which the
IMFP is less than a nanometer. In the HAXPES
regime, the photon energy is generally significantly
larger than the binding energy, resulting
in electron kinetic energies well in excess
of a kiloelectronvolt . In this regime, the
electrons’ IMFP is significantly larger,
and bulk properties of the sample can be investigated.
The electron kinetic energies are determined
using concentric hemispherical analysers,
or CHAs. For an electron of energy E_e to
exit through the centre of the exit hole of
the CHA, the conditions given by the equation
here must be met. However, electrons with
lower energies will be more deviated by the
electric field between the concentric domes,
while those of higher energies, less so. By
using a larger exit aperture and an area electron
detector such as a multichannel plate, a two
dimensional plot can be recorded, in which
the energy is dispersed in one direction,
and angular differences in emission are distinguished
in the perpendicular direction. In this manner,
large regions of both energy and momentum
can be simultaneously recorded, accelerating
data acquisition, particularly in the technique
of ARPES.
Ultraviolet photoelectron spectroscopy (or
UPS) uses photon energies of the order of
10 eV up to approximately 200 eV. In this
regime, mainly the valence electrons are probed,
as the photon energy is insufficient to eject
core electrons other than those in the very
lightest elements, which are in any case strongly
affected by bonding.
The valence electrons are in general responsible
for the electronic properties of materials.
By also recording the direction of the photoelectrons
relative to the crystallographic structure
of single-crystal samples, a detailed description
of the electronic properties can be made.