Now how are UV photons used ?
There are several reasons.
First, they allow a better energy resolution
of the electrons in the CHA.
Perhaps most importantly, because the energies
of UV photons are close to that of valence-band-electron
binding energies, the absorption cross-section
of UV photons is large.
The reference binding energy of 0 eV is defined
as the Fermi energy, that is, the energy of
the highest occupied state of the system at
0 K. Note that this depends on the direction
of the electron momentum with respect to the
crystal structure.
Note also, that E_F is lower than the vacuum
energy, the energy of a free electron having
zero kinetic energy, by an amount equal to
the work function.
This leads us on to the concept of the Fermi
surface, that is, the plot in reciprocal,
or momentum, space of the Fermi energy, in
other words, as a function of the wavevector
k of the electron.
k has three components k_x, k_y, and k_z.
Not surprisingly, the Fermi energy changes
according to which direction the electron
is moving through the crystal, depending on
the interaction between it and the ionic electrostatic
potential in that direction.
Even for the most simple elemental metals
such as copper, the Fermi surface can assume
complex forms, as shown here.
To understand this 3D-plot a little better,
we make a slice through the Fermi surface,
for which the cross-section is shown on the
right.
The centre, which has zero momentum, is called
the Γ-point, while the two crystallographic
directions (111) (denoted ‘L’) and (100)
(‘X’) are also shown.
Let’s consider this more closely.
We look along the Gamma-L and Gamma-X directions
The Fermi surface never crosses the Γ–L
line and in this direction all the states
are below the Fermi energy and therefore a
gap opens up between the occupied states and
unoccupied states.
In contrast, in the Γ–X direction, the
Fermi surface crosses the Fermi energy, and
copper is thus conducting in this direction.
Angle-resolved PES, or ARPES, attempts to
determine the electron kinetic energies as
a function of angle.
With this information, the electrons’ momenta
p_x, p_y, and p_z can be accessed, which should
lead to a complete picture of the electronic
structure.
Synchrotron radiation provides two further
variables excluded to lab-based ARPES experiments,
namely the possibility of tuning the incident
photon energy, and the possibility of varying
the polarisation.
The momenta in plane in the k_x and k_y directions
for a given electron binding energy below
the Fermi energy can be plotted in a Fermi
surface map, or FSM, as we have already met
in the previous slides on the Fermi surface
of copper.
Alternatively, one can plot the binding energy
as a function of the electron wavevector in
a given direction, in a momentum-distribution
curve, or MDC.
For a fixed k-value, the intensity as a function
of energy can be plotted in an energy-distribution
curve.
These two plots can be combined in a two-dimensional
map called the energy-distribution map.
Finally, all these plots can be combined in
a 3-D plot, shown on the right, from which
any planar section can be viewed.
Ultraviolet photoelectron diffraction (UPD)
and x-ray photoelectron diffraction (XPD)
are techniques used to obtain direct structural
information in the neighbourhood of the photoelectron
emitter in single crystals.
The techniques depend on the strong forward-scattering
nature of photoelectrons by neighbouring atoms,
particularly for the higher kinetic energies
found in XPD, which thus delivers sharper
data than UPD.
UPD and
XPD are now an established and invaluable
tools for investigating surface absorbates
and heteroepitaxial thin films on single crystals.
In an XPD experiment, the outgoing photoelectron
wave can reach an electron detector on a direct
path or can be scattered by the atoms surrounding
the emitter.
The intensity measured at the detector is
given by the interference of the direct and
the scattered wave parts and changes as a
function of emission direction (theta_s in
the figure on the left), or electron kinetic
energy.
These modulations can be used to determine
the local structure around the emitter.
Prediction of the angular distribution of
the signal in photoelectron diffraction is
much simplified by the well-known phenomenon
of the enhanced forward elastic scattering
of photoelectrons - the scattering signal
is strongest for theta_s = 0.
For high-energy electrons in the range from
a few hundred electron volts to several keV,
elastic scattering from the electronic clouds
around adjacent atoms is associated with only
a very small phase shift.
Hence in the forward direction, interference
is constructive, while at larger angles, partial
destructive interference causes the scattering
amplitude to drop off sharply.
This forward scattering results in an amplification
of the scattering intensity along low-index
crystallographic axes, where the photoelectrons
regularly meet atoms.
XPD and UPD therefore provide direct real-space
information on the directions between neighbours.
Because of the high sensitivity of surfaces
to contaminants and the typical kinetic energies
of the photoelectrons, XPD and UPD only work
for the near-surface region of single-crystal
samples kept in ultrahigh vacuum.
An example of XPD is shown here.
The single-layer sp2-hybridized material hexagonal
boron nitride is isoelectronic with graphene,
and is of high technological interest, as
it can form a corrugated “nanomesh” when
deposited on the surfaces of certain transition-metals.
These nano meshes can act as trapping centres
for other molecules, or indeed induce periodic
segregation on a nanometer scale when alloys
of metals are used as the substrate material.
In order to fully understand their physical,
chemical, and potential catalytic properties,
their structure should be known with high
accuracy.
One very important parameter is a knowledge
of d_A-S the distance between the h-BN layer
and the top atomic layer of the metal, as
this provides information on bonding strength
and the redistribution of electron density
across the nano mesh, and also provides important
starting information for theoretical calculations.
The nominal structure of h-BN on Ni(111) is
shown on the top right, both in plan and side
view.
The recorded XPD signal from the ejection
of the Nitrogen 1s electron is shown bottom
right.
Strong forward scattering in the direction
of the N-N bonds and the N-B bonds can be
seen in the hemispherical plot of the XPD
intensity.
This was modelled, for which the best fit
was for a distance d_A-S of 2.11 +/- 0.002
Angstroms.
XPS at synchrotrons is not in general used
for high-resolution chemical analysis (ESCA),
as this can normally be performed quite satisfactorily
using a lab-based source.
The exception to this rule is high-pressure
XPS (HPXPS), also called ambient-pressure
PES.
Although photoemission is a highly powerful
tool for investigating clean surfaces under
ultrahigh-vacuum conditions, many interesting
processes occur on surfaces, and surface chemistry
under realistic reaction conditions have pressures
several orders of magnitude higher than those
typically used for traditional XPS experiments.
Such “ambient” experiments are thus excluded
from investigation using standard PES spectrometers.
This has been in recent years the spur to
develop the APPES technique.
A typical example of the application of APPES
is the investigation of the surface chemistry
and its change under different reaction conditions
(in particular gas pressure and type) of heterogeneous
catalysts.
The mean free path Lambda of an electron travelling
through a gas depends on the gas pressure
P and the electron’s kinetic energy E_e.
For a given gas type and electron energy,
the product of Lambda and P is a constant.
An example is shown here for electrons travelling
through oxygen gas.
So, a photoelectron with a kinetic energy
E_e of 400 eV would have a mean free path
in 100 Pa (or 1 mbar) oxygen of approximately
4 mm.
XPS measurements at higher pressures are made
possible by employing one or more differentially
pumped stages between the sample surface and
the electron analyzer.
The diameter D0 of the primary aperture is
decisive for the fundamental scales of the
experiment with regards to observable photoelectron
energies and maximum possible pressures.
There is a fine balance between placing the
aperture too close to the sample, thereby
perturbing the chemical environment, and positioning
it too far away, when scattering of the primary
photoelectron by the gas becomes highly probable,
and the solid angle subtended by the aperture
becomes so tiny that the captured photoelectron
signal becomes unacceptably small.
In practice, the ideal separation between
the sample surface and the primary aperture
is a few times D0.
The maximum ambient gas pressure is inversely
proportional to D0, hence reducing D0 allows
a higher ambient pressure, but at the cost
of photoemission signal, which scales with
D0^2.
Typical modern APPES chambers have apertures
in the range of 0.5 mm, sample–aperture
distances of the order of a few mm, and hence
maximum working pressures approximately 1000
Pa (10 mbar).
The introduction of electrostatic lenses in
the differentially pumped stages in order
to collect a larger fraction of the photoemission
signal represented a breakthrough in APPES
technology.
In addition to reactions occurring on solid
surfaces, chemistry from a liquid jet is another
possibility, whereby the jet is collected
in a catcher with a narrow entrance.
Such experiments have the added advantage
that the liquid surface is being constantly
refreshed.
We complete our overview of photoelectron
techniques with a brief synopsis of hard x-ray
photoelectron spectroscopy, or HAXPES.
“Normal” UPS and XPS depends intimately
on the properties in the near surface region,
given by the inelastic mean-free path of the
photoelectrons, which in most cases is less
than a nanometer.
This means that samples must be kept exceedingly
clean with well-defined crystallographic and
chemical properties, while any structural
differences of the surface region, and through
this, also of the chemical and/or electronic
properties, can often mean that such experiments
might not represent the properties of the
bulk material.
Below approximately 2 nm from the surface
of a single-crystal sample, one can generally
assume that the properties are essentially
bulk like.
In order to access these depths, however,
electron kinetic energies (and therefore also
photon energies) in excess of a keV or even
higher must be used, according to the universal
curve.
These high energies are, unfortunately, associated
with low absorption cross-sections, which,
away from absorption edges, drop off as 1/hnu^3,
as you might remember from the second week
in this course.
In addition, the detector efficiency drops
off as 1/E_e, while in order to maintain the
desired chemical sensitivity through subtle
chemical shifts of the order of 0.1 eV, the
analyser specifications are tighter still
than in normal XPS.
Despite all these technical difficulties,
there are several important advantages to
HAXPES.
First, because the bulk is being probed, the
need for ultrahigh vacuum conditions, required
in normal XPS in order to maintain surface
cleanliness, is obviated.
Secondly, this increase in the probing depth
increases the periodicity “seen” by the
electron in the direction perpendicular to
the surface, which thus reduces the uncertainty
of the wavevector of the electrons in this
direction.
This allows a more precise definition of the
full 3-D wavevector k_e than is possible in
“normal” ARPES.
Lastly, because the photon wavelengths at
these high energies are generally significantly
smaller than typical interatomic spacings,
the photoemission matrix elements reduce to
atomic cross-sections, thus simplifying data
analysis.
The momentum of photoelectrons in HAXPES can
be significant, causing the emitting atom
to recoil.
According to the conservation of momentum,
the apparent binding energy will shift due
to this recoil, which must be taken into account,
in particular for light elements.
Summarising this week’s videos, spectroscopic
techniques that use synchrotron radiation
have the unique advantage that the incoming
x-rays can be tuned and/or scanned in energy.
This adds an invaluable new dimension to experiments
excluded to those based on laboratory x-ray
sources and has been exploited to full advantage
in many of the above-described methods, not
least in XAS, ARPES and RIXS.
Indeed, all XAS techniques are only possible
using tunable synchrotron light.
The high brilliance of third-generation sources,
coupled with the ability to focus
down to the nanometer scale, has opened up
new vistas in synchrotron spectroscopy.
Enormous progress has also been made in the
performance of fast, energy dispersive detectors,
and it is expected that the range of experiments
available will continue to burgeon as rapidly
as has been experienced in the last decade.
Spectroscopy using x-rays will remain the
most prominent and sought after general synchrotron
technique because of the detailed information
that can be gleaned about the chemical and
electronic properties of matter.
In an era where ever more novel and unexpected
materials are being tailored and synthesized,
synchrotron spectroscopy will continue to
play a central role in materials research.