Welcome to the first video of Week 8 of this
introductory course on synchrotrons and x-ray
free-electron lasers!
This week, we will discuss x-ray imaging techniques,
including different flavours of x-ray tomography,
coherent x-ray diffractive imaging, and ptychography.
In this first video, after some introductory
comments, the basic concepts behind x-ray
tomography are presented.
The first point to mention is that the choice
of the methods described this week is perhaps
a little arbitrary, as a large fraction of
third-generation synchrotron-based experiments
can be said to be imaging methods.
In fact, synchrotrons are often presented
to the general public as being exceedingly
powerful microscopes.
For example, photoemission electron microscopy
directly images absorption maps via the secondary
electrons that are emitted; scanning-x-ray-fluorescence
plots the intensity of certain photon energies
associated with emission from selected elements
as a function of sample position; while even
x-ray diffraction provides “images” of
unit cells from diffraction data after solving
the phase problem.
X-ray computed tomography, and the two related
techniques of CXDI and ptychography are covered
here, because they sit rather uncomfortably
within the techniques described to date, although
CXDI and ptychography are closely related
to small-angle x-ray scattering, and ptychography
also has much in common with scanning transmission
x-ray microscopy.
It is the relative transparency of condensed
matter to hard x-rays that makes them such
a powerful tool for investigating the internal
structures of objects in a nondestructive
manner.
Indeed, this benefit of x-rays was the first
to be recognized and which caused such a sensation
immediately after their discovery more than
a century ago - imagine the frisson of wonder
or even horror the public must have experienced
at the first display of the radiograms of
Roentgen’s wife’s and of his colleague
von Kolliker’s hands!
Medical radiographic imaging remains the most
widespread application of hard x-radiation
well over a century later.
The word ’tomography’ is derived from
the Greek words ‘tomos’ meaning ‘to
slice’ and ‘graph’ meaning ‘image’.
Tomography in its most general sense is the
generation of a three-dimensional image by
analyzing several transmission radiographic
projections taken of a specimen at different
angles.
This requires radiation which has an absorption
length of the same order of magnitude as the
size of the specimen under investigation.
Nowadays, computed tomography with a resolution
of approximately 500 microns is a standard
diagnostic medical imaging tool in hospitals
around the world.
Approximately 100 million CT scans per year
are performed in the United States alone.
High-resolution x-ray tomographic microscopy
is a synchrotron-based nondestructive microscopy
technique for creating quantitative, three-dimensional
images of solid objects, including their detailed
internal architecture, with a spatial resolution
which can extend well below the micron range.
It is useful for a wide range of materials,
including inorganic substances such as rock,
concrete, ceramic, or metal, and also for
objects made from bone and soft tissue.
In recent years, optimization of tomography
beamlines using high x-ray fluxes has driven
the speed of data acquisition to such an extent
that it is now routine to record entire tomography
scans in a few seconds or even, in favourable
circumstances, in the subsecond timescale.
Time-resolved biomedical studies using tomography
of processes such as breathing or blood circulation
are now possible, and processes on timescales
well below a tenth of a second are beginning
to be probed.
Tomography provides a deeper insight into
the structure of bodies.
Now, when one sees a radiograph of a hand,
it is immediately clear what this is - a hand.
It would be a very strange object indeed that
looked so much like a hand but actually wasn’t.
Now let’s consider the simple example shown
here . This radiograph would be consistent,
for example, with this 3-dimensional object,
viewed from in front.
However, it would be also compatible with
this object here, in which the bottom row
of two blocks are separated, or indeed, with
this object here, a more radically different
object than the first set of blocks.
Viewing these structures from the right reveals
their differences and provides the necessary
added information to unambiguously reconstruct
the real bodies.
For more complex bodies, more angular perspectives
are required to unravel their structure, both
internal, and their envelope.
This is the basis of tomography.
The basic principles behind tomography are
shown here in this cartoon.
The x-ray transmission image, or radiograph
of an object placed in a parallel x-ray beam
is recorded on a scintillator.
The visible output of the scintillator is
then imaged (and magnified) on to a CCD array.
The object is then rotated by a small amount
and a new radiogram is recorded.
This process continues until the object has
been rotated through a full half-circle (180
degrees).
For each row of the CCD, the pixel response
of that row can be plotted out as a function
of the object angular orientation in a so-called
sinogram.
As we
will discuss in the following slide, the sinograms
are analysed using a computer, each sinogram
thereby providing a 2-D slice of the object
in the horizontal plane at a height given
by that of the row of pixels that generated
it.
Let us look more closely at these sinograms.
Consider an object irradiated from a certain
angle, alpha_1, producing at a certain height
(or row of pixels) an absorbtion profile,
which we label profile 1.
The transmission at any pixel along the row
is proportional to the inverse exponent of
the integrated absorption coefficient along
the path of the x-rays travelling through
the object to that pixel.
We consider one of these paths l_1 that passes
through the red dot at (x,y), which has a
certain absorption coefficient mu(x,y).
The transmitted intensity is expressed mathematically
here.
At another angle alpha_2, we obtain a different
profile, profile 2 . The intensity at the
pixel at the end of the path l_2 that also
passes through the same red dot at (x,y),
is given by a similar expression . Note that
both the integrands mu(l_1) and mu(l_2) contain
this common point mu(x, y) where they intersect
with each other.
Hence the value that mu(x,y) can assume has
been a little constrained by these two conditions
of the recorded intensities I(alpha_1, l_1)
and I(alpha_2, l_2).
By recording many different angles, the value
of mu(x,y) becomes more strictly constrained,
as indeed do all other positions of this section
of the object.
Johann Radon provided the mathematics to extract
the spatial distribution of mu in a so-called
Radon transform . The mathematical details
behind this were translated into English and
published in the reference provided here bottom
left.
What advantages does tomography confer over
transitional radiographic projections?
Let us consider two adjacent rows of “voxels”
within a tomographic slice.
Voxels are the three-dimensional equivalent
of pixels within the 3-D tomographic reconstruction.
The size of the voxel is given by the pixel
dimensions and the angular step size.
In the radiographic projection, the two intensities
correspond to the sum of the absorption contributions
of all the voxels in their respective lines.
The sums result here in very similar transmissions,
although the individual voxels in the two
rows are substantially different - so for
example, the two absorption strength of the
voxels highlighted here are very different
from each other.
In other words, the contrast between individual
voxels in the tomographic reconstruction is
in general much higher than that in a radiographic
projection.
And, of course, one gets to see the detailed
three-dimensional internal architecture.
An alternative approach to obtaining tomographic
slices
has become possible with the emergence of
modern and powerful computers, which are capable
of performing so-called fast Fourier transforms
(FFTs) and inverse FFTs exceedingly quickly.
The approach is based on the so-called Fourier
slice theorem.
This states that the Fourier transform of
the 1-D projection (in this coordinate system,
along x) of an object at a certain height
(here, z) through that object is equal to
the central line section through a 2D Fourier
transform of a slice through that object at
the same height, z.
One thus repeats this procedure at different
angles until all of Fourier space is mapped
with the desired accuracy.
However, what one now has is an uneven distribution
of points in the Fourier transform, so you
need to interpolate the data from this polar
distribution to orthogonal Cartesian coordinates.
From this, the inverse Fourier transform yields
the tomogram slice.
Lastly, improved contrast in tomographic images
can be achieved by recording below and above
an absorption edge of a material known to
exist in the sample, such as here for a caesium
plume in igneous rock.
By subtracting one from the other , an enhanced
image for that material is generated.
Summarizing this first video, we have demonstrated
that tomography is a powerful technique to
nondestructively image the 3-dimensional internal
architecture of bodies with a high contrast
that is inaccessible to standard radiographic
methods.
In the next video, we will discuss two variants
of tomography, namely phase-contrast tomography,
and high-speed tomography.