Hello, and welcome to this, the second video
of week 8.
In this video, we will discuss important variants
of synchrotron-based tomography, namely phase-contrast
methods, and high-speed tomography.
Shown here are the absorption lengths of different
materials at different photon energies, with
representative objects corresponding to typical
lengths scales shown on the right.
High-density samples absorb strongly, even
for fairly high-energy photons.
Hence, for example, medical radiographs of
bones or teeth use a broad band of energies,
but peaking in the range of several tens of
keV.
On the other hand, traditional radiography
and absorption tomography, while providing
invaluable information on a wide spectrum
of materials and objects, runs into problems
for samples which are small and/or composed
of low-density material.
The attenuation length of flesh, for example,
is around 2 to 3 mm at 10 keV, and an order
of magnitude larger at 25 keV.
This means that some of the most scientifically
interesting biological samples provide only
poor contrast.
In addition, objects which absorb only weakly
tend also to absorb fairly homogeneously throughout
their internal structure, even if this is
composed of distinct heterogeneous components.
So, a strongly absorbing object will show
a clear absorption profile , while little
or no observable contrast will be seen for
a weakly absorbing sample . Again, this is
exemplified by biological samples, where objects
with quite distinct biological functions and
structures become almost indistinguishable
with regards to their x-ray absorption coefficients.
So, if absorption becomes an increasingly
poor metric for small and weakly absorbing
samples is there another phenomenon we can
exploit to obtain the necessary contrast?
Well, yes, there is, namely refraction . This
is exploited in phase-contrast tomography.
Remember that any material has a complex refractive
index in the x-ray regime, given by n = 1
- delta + i beta.The effect of this is on
the one hand, to attenuate the beam through
the beta term, but also to increase the x-ray
wavelength within the medium by a factor of
1/(1-delta).
The graph shown here is of the transmission,
refractive-index decrement delta, and absorption
index beta, of 1 mm of flesh as a function
of photon energy.
Note first, that above 10 or 15 keV, the transmission
rapidly approaches unity, that is, very little
absorption occurs.
This is good regarding radiation damage of
the soft, biological sample, but bad for absorption-contrast
measurements.
Note also, that the drop-off of beta with
photon energy follows a 1/hv^4 dependence,
while that of delta is only 1/hv^2.
But how exactly does refraction provide the
desired contrast?
We begin by assuming ray optics only, ignoring
diffraction effects.
Although this does not represent reality,
it does provide some insights into what we
might expect to see.
Let us imagine a block of material of length
L and real part of the refractive index (that
is, the part responsible for refraction) 1
- delta.
Consider two identical (i.e., coherent) plane
waves, one of which passes through the block,
while the other passes by it.
Although the phases of the two waves are identical
as the first enters the block, refraction
causes this to advance relative to the second
block travelling through vacuum.
How much is this advance?
Well, the number of wavelengths associated
with the second wave travelling through vacuum
a distance equal to the block thickness, L,
is simply L/lambda.
The number of wavelengths passing through
the block, on the other hand, is L(1-delta)/lambda,
hence the difference between the waves is
simply L delta/lambda.
Let us consider an object that is 100 microns
long, and has a value for delta of 7 x 10^-7
at 20 keV (a photon energy which equates to
0.62 Angstroms in vacuum).
The
difference in the number of wavelengths is
thus 1.13 periods, or 7.1 radians.
If the block presents a nonnormal surface
to the incident or exit waves, refraction
will bend the beam, causing it to overlap
with the beam passing by the object.
A more realistic description of the effect
of refraction on the transmitted beam is consider
diffraction phenomena by using Huygens construction.
This states that, given a certain wavefront
form, the subsequent wavefront in the direction
of propagation can be constructed by adding
secondary spherical wavelets of the same wavelength
to each point along that wavefront.
So a plane wave will generate another plane
wave, as shown here on the left.
Now, if some obstacle blocks the path of the
wavefront, as shown by the black bar in the
central figure, the wavelets in this region
are removed, and interference between the
remaining unblocked wavelets results in fringes
forming as they propagate in the forward direction
- at sufficiently large distances, Z_0, this
is, in fact, the diffraction pattern, or Fourier
transform of the edge.
At very short distances, on the other hand,
for example, if a detector butts up against
the absorbing block, little or no diffraction
effect is observed.
Using approximations, it is a simple exercise
to show that the distance x_1 of the first
minimum after the geometrical end of the absorbing
block is given by the square root of Z_0 lambda/2.
Let us consider two examples of Z_0 for lambda
= 0.7 Angstrom.
For Z_0 = 10 mm, x_1 = 0.59 microns.
For Z_0 = 1 m, however, x_1 = 5.9 microns.
Any detector with a pixel size larger than
about half of the fringe separation is unable
to resolve this interference phenomenon.
Hence the detector would need a pixel size
smaller than 0.3 microns and 3 microns, respectively,
for the short and large detector distance
from the object.
Why then, don’t we simply move further downstream
of the object until the fringes are large
enough to match the detector we might be using
at the time?
The problem is, that the propagated scattering
pattern evolves gradually from being a more
or less faithful reproduction of the absorption
profile at very short distances , that is,
distances much smaller than a^2/lambda, a
being the typical size of fluctuations in
the architecture of the sample (This absorption
profile, remember, is, however, almost undetectable
for weakly absorbing samples), to being the
true diffraction pattern of the object at
very large distances , i.e., much larger than
a^2/lambda in
the so-called Fraunhofer regime . It is at
the sweet spot between these two limits where
Z_0 is of the order of a^2/lambda, that the
sample profile is still preserved, but for
which the boundaries between heterogeneous
components are highlighted, not by the insignificant
absorption, but by interference fringes.
This is called the Fresnel regime.
This technique of phase-contrast tomography
is beautifully demonstrated by this example
of prehistoric insects trapped within an opaque
amber block.
In this first image, recorded at a distance
of 50 mm, using 30-keV (or 0.413 Angstrom)
photons, little or no detail can be discerned
in this radiograph.
The first fringe separation x_1 is at a distance
of one micron, whereas the detector used at
the ID19 station of the ESRF had a pixel size
of 5 microns and was thus incapable of respiring
these fine diffraction fringes.
Increasing the distance to one metre, however,
meant that the fringes are separated by a
distance of approximately 5 microns, just
enough to provide a one pixel-width intensity
contrast.
The emergence of exquisite detail by optimising
the sample-detector distance is wonderfully
clear.
Phase-contrast tomography is likely to profit
significantly from the emergence of 4th-generation
diffraction limited storage rings.
This is because the technique exploits the
coherent fraction of the synchrotron beam,
which, in 3rd-generation facilities, is a
small fraction of a percent.
The coherent fraction of DLSRs is inversely
proportional to the emittance, and will thus
increase accordingly, that is, by approximately
two orders of magnitude, allowing much higher
data-acquisition rates.
This leads us naturally on to the subject
of high-speed tomography, in which the three-dimensional
structure of an object is recorded as a function
of time.
Two sorts of experiment can be performed - either
irreversible processes, or cyclic ones.
The former requires that any changes during
the process be recorded with sufficient speed
and accuracy.
This is presently limited to ten or 20 Hz,
with up to possibly another order of magnitude
envisaged in the next few years.
In cyclic processes, faster frame rates are
accessible by using a stroboscopic approach.
Imagine a rubber rod being repeatedly compressed
and then releases to its relaxed state.
Instead of trying to record a full 180 degree
rotation for each time interval Delta T during
the cycle of duration big T, radiographs are
recorded in one orientation only as quickly
as possible over time T.
The sample is then rotated by a small amount,
and the cycle repeated.
The tomogram for each time interval Delta
T is then obtained by selecting the appropriate
radiograph from each set of nonrotating images.
There are, needless to say, several technical
obstacles associated with high-speed tomography.
First, the exposure between frames needs to
be long enough to obtain sufficiently non-noisy
images.
Secondly, rapid rotations will impose significant
forces on the object.
Consider, for example, a sample with a 2-mm
radius rotating at 20 Hz.
The centripetal acceleration is omega^2 r,
where omega = 2pi nu = 126 radian/second.
This equates to an acceleration of 31.6 m/s^2,
or 3g, the acceleration experienced by astronauts
on the space shuttle.
For soft or liquid samples, this might be
unacceptably severe, and must be taken into
consideration.
Thirdly, imagine an irreversible process being
recorded at a time resolution of 50 ms (again,
corresponding to 20 Hz) within which 400 angular
orientations are to be recorded.
This results in a frame rate of 8000/second.
If we assume that each radiograph requires
1 Mbyte of storage, this means that data transfer,
either directly, or to a buffer, must be capable
of at least 8 GB/s.
An intensive beamtime can therefore produce
hundreds of terabytes per day, far in excess
of what a “standard” PC can handle.
The problem of data management looms large
in tomography, and also, in ptychography,
described in more detail in the third video
of this week.
We finish this second video with an example
of high-speed tomography, in which the flight
muscles and breathing network of a blowfly
are followed.
At the start of the video, the insect is facing
to the left (the head is out of the field
of view so appears clipped) and the attachment
point of the mount on the fly’s back is
visible at the top of the thorax.
As the view orbits the flying insect, the
deformations of the thorax are clearly visible
as the wing moves up and down, in particular
the pitching and heaving motions of the bristle-covered
structure behind the mount.
Also visible are the beating halteres (dumbbell-shaped
structures modified from the hindwings), which
oscillate in a void covered by the calypteres
(semi-transparent membranous structures, with
an opaque border).
At 30s, a sagittal clipping plane is introduced
computationally.
This first reveals the dorsoventral flight
muscles, coloured blue to purple, that power
the wingbeat, along with the dorsolongitudinal
flight muscles (not coloured) that become
visible as the clipping plane moves further
into the thorax.
An inverse threshold filter is then applied
to reveal the tracheal network and other cavities
within the flight muscle (shown in green).
The clipping plane then continues to move
through the thorax until the steering muscles
that provide fine control over the wingbeat
are visible (coloured yellow to purple).
This second video has introduced you to two
powerful variations of tomography.
Phase-contrast techniques are employed in
order to highlight the boundaries between
heterogeneous components of an object by differences
not in their absorption, which can be very
small, in particular for low-density biological
samples, but instead by differences in the
refractive index, which remains more sensitive,
even for low-Z materials.
Both absorption tomography and phase-contrast
tomography can be carried out at high speeds
if (a) the flux is sufficiently high; and
(b) the acquisition rates are high enough
to capture temporal changes in the object
with suitable resolution.
This method is becoming increasingly popular
in the real world where changes are the norm,
not the exception.
In the final video of this week, we will discuss
two techniques, coherent x-ray diffractive
imaging and ptychography, which are based
not on direct imaging like tomography, but
instead on lensless techniques, which allow
the experimenter to bridge the spatial-resolution
gap between tomography and electron microscopies
and crystal diffraction, while also allowing
the internal structure of the sample to be
probed.