Hello, and welcome to this, the final video
of week 8.
In this video, we will discuss the related
imaging techniques of coherent x-ray diffractive
imaging, and ptychography.
Coherent x-ray diffractive imaging, also called
lensless imaging, or diffraction microscopy,
has many features in common with x-ray diffraction
and small-angle x-ray scattering.
In XRD, the samples have translational symmetry,
and as a result, the far-field scattering,
or diffraction, pattern consists of a set
of sharp diffraction maxima, from which the
structure of the repeat unit, or unit cell,
can be gleaned by solving the phase problem.
Typically many unit cells are illuminated
coherently within the coherence volume.
The resolution of the atomic positions can
be established with a resolution of the order
of an Angstrom, or indeed much better than
this in the case of small unit cells containing
a modest number of atoms, while the unit cell
size can often be determined with femtometer
accuracy.
CXDI follows the same general principle as
XRD, though because the objects under investigations
are typically larger (note that this may not
be the case in so-called Bragg-CXDI of nanoscale
crystallites, discussed in a moment), the
scattering angles are smaller; and, in the
case of noncrystalline samples, the scattering
pattern is continuous, containing small grainy
features collectively called “speckle”
. The upper limit to the size of the object
that can be investigated with CXDI is given
by the coherence volume of the incident radiation.
Big increases in this are expected once DLSRs
come online in the immediate future.
Inhomogeneities with an irradiated object
are the sources of scattered signal of the
incident beam.
Interference between these scattered wavelets
result in a so-called speckle pattern in the
far field, which is the absolute square of
the Fourier transform of the object.
By performing an inverse Fourier transform
of the speckle, the real-space reconstruction
of the sample is possible, once the ubiquitous
phase problem has been overcome.
The ultimate resolution of the reconstruction,
Delta x, is equal to 4 lambda Z_0/D, where
Z_0 is the sample-detector distance, and D
is the lateral detector size.
The resolution cannot be arbitrarily improved
by increasing the detector size, as associated
with this is an increase in scattering angle,
or scattering vector, Q.
But, as we recall from Week 6, the scattering
intensity drops off with the inverse fourth
power of Q, hence in most instances, the signal
towards the edge of the detector is so weak
that no sensible data can be recovered here.
As we have just stated, speckle is the result
of interference between wavelets produced
by scattering of a beam of x-rays caused by
spatial variations in the electron density
within an object.
To obtain a stable speckle pattern, the object
must be coherently illuminated – if this
is not the case, the speckles become averaged
out due to fluctuations of the form of the
wavefront incident on the sample.
In the forward direction around the direct
beam, this incoherent signal is simply the
small-angle x-ray scattering (SAXS) signal
described in Week 6.
There are three characteristic length-scales
related to speckle: the wavelength lambda
of the x-rays, measured in Angstroms; the
typical linear dimensions of the sample a,
which should be smaller than the transverse
coherent illumination cross-section (of the
order of 10 to 100 μm); and d, the typical
length describing the variation in electron
density (or distribution of ‘particles’)
within the illuminated object, which can range
between approximately 10 and 1000 nm.
The x-rays are on average scattered through
an angle of the order of lambda/d, which can
be as small as 100 μrad (less than 0.01 degrees).
The speckles arise through interference between
all the scattered wavelets across the coherently
illuminated area and therefore have angular
separations that can be as small as lambda/a
of the order of 1 μrad.
Note that in order to resolve such features,
a detector having 50 μm-sized pixels would
need to be at least 50 m downstream of the
sample, for hard x-radiation in the Angstrom
range.
Normally, however, the illuminated area is
limited to only a few microns, and sample–detector
distances of approximately 10 m are more common.
Alternatively, softer x-radiation can be used,
although the increased absorption at lower
photon energies sets an upper limit to the
thickness of objects that can be studied.
You should note also, that because the speckles
arise from interference between the scattered
wavefronts from all the particles in the sample,
the entire speckle pattern will change even
if only one particle moves.
The speckle pattern therefore contains information
on the positions of all the particles, which
can be obtained by inverting the pattern,
which, like I say, involves solving the phase
problem.
At this point, it is worth introducing the
concepts of oversampling and redundancy.
Imagine a scatter pattern that has an intrinsic
spatial “graininess” associated with the
speckle of a size Delta Q. The spatial frequency
range of the signal, although it is random,
will extend up to approximately f_max = 1/Delta
Q. The minimum spatial frequency of the detector
recording such a pattern needs to be 2f_max,
according to the so-called Nyqvist theorem.
In other words, the pixel size needs to be
no bigger than half the speckle separation.
If the detector pixel size is smaller than
1/2f_max by a factor beta, one says that the
signal has been oversampled by this amount.
beta determines the resolution of the real-space
solution.
The redundancy, on he other hand, determines
how ambiguous any one solution might be.
If the experimental data provides M independent
values, and the object under investigation
has N unknowns (for example, N “voxels”
of electron density, the linear size of the
voxel corresponding to the minimum spatial
fluctuation of the density of the sample),
then the redundancy is given by M/N. The larger
the redundancy, the more likely one is to
obtain the correct solution.
Note also that equating M to the number of
pixels in the detector is the absolute upper
limit.
In nearly all cases, the intensities towards
the outside of the detector are so weak that
they can be discarded.
Also, if the pixel size is significantly smaller
than the typical speckle separations (relating
back to the concept of oversampling) then
one cannot assume that adjacent pixels record
“independent” values.
CXDI can be used to investigate both noncrystalline
and crystalline objects.
In the former case, the 3-D speckle pattern
associated with the 3-D Fourier transform
(squared) of the object is recorded by rotating
the object (and therefore also the scattering
pattern) through 180 degrees and recording
simultaneously until all of the pattern has
passes through the Ewald sphere . This sets
very stringent specifications on the mechanical
stability of both the rotation table for the
object, and the position of the incident x-ray
beam.
In the case of small- or nanocrystalline objects,
the crystal diffraction pattern has features
to it not normally observed in larger crystalline
objects.
Consider a homogeneous nanosized object, ignoring
to begin with that it may be crystalline.
The scattering amplitude pattern of such an
object is simply the Fourier transform of
the shape of that object, called the shape
function.
A cartoon of how a shape function of a cubic
object may look like is shown here on the
right - fringes arise due to interference
of opposite faces of the cube, to produce
a star-shaped object (with six stellations,
of which only four are shown here in this
2-D representation).
If we now imagine that the nanocube is a single
crystal, then we can expect to see Bragg peaks
- in other words a diffraction pattern.
But this diffraction pattern doesn’t consist
of narrow Bragg peaks, but instead, each Bragg
peak exhibits the form of the shape function.
The reason for this is that in real space,
the nanocrystal is the multiplication of an
infinite crystal with the envelope of the
nanocrystal, which, by applying the convolution
theorem, means that the scattering pattern
is the convolution of the Fourier transform
of an infinite crystal, in other words a perfect
diffraction pattern consisting of infinitely
narrow Bragg peaks, convoluted with the Fourier
transform of the nanocrystal shape, that is,
the shape function shown in the previous slide.
This finite-size effect is also exploited
in grazing-incidence small-angle scattering
and in surface diffraction.
Now let us return to our experimental setup
for recording CXDI data, this time for a crystalline
object.
Now, instead of looking at the signal around
the (000) forward scattered direct beam , one
can move the detector to a Bragg peak (hkl)
and record there . This so-called Bragg-CXDI
method for crystalline samples has four important
consequences.
First, coherent diffractive imaging can be
carried out far away from the direct beam,
which means one can dispense with a beamstop
(which excludes features in the reconstruction
above a certain size).
Also, artefactual diffuse scattering in the
forward direction produced by other sources
than the sample is avoided.
Thirdly, because the Bragg peak shape is only
affected by the electron density of the crystalline
part of the object, it is highly sensitive
to crystalline defects and strain fields.
And lastly, one need only rotate the sample
through a much smaller angular range than
in the case of noncrystalline samples, in
order for all the features to pass through
the Ewald sphere , significantly relaxing
the technical specifications of the rotation
stage.
We finish this last video of Week 8 with a
discussion of ptychography.
Remember that in CXDI, the sample size is
limited to being smaller than the coherent
part of the beam.
The real-space structure is then calculated
using some sort of iterative algorithm which
cycles between real space and reciprocal space,
varying real-space constraints in each cycle
until consistency is arrived at, that is,
no further changes are needed in the real-space
solution in order for it to agree with the
diffraction pattern in reciprocal space.
Ptychography is scanning CXDI, largely though
not exclusively of noncrystalline samples.
Importantly, ptychography allows large-scale
structures, many times larger than the coherence
volume of the beam, to be investigated with
the same resolution as offered by CXDI.
The upper limit to the size of the sample
under investigation is given by technical
issues, in particular the volume of data generated,
the computing power needed to solve the structure,
and the accuracy and reproducibility of the
scanning stage of the sample.
The approach to ptychography is simple.
A coherent beam typically of the order of
a few microns in diameter illuminates a part
of the sample , and the speckle pattern is
recorded.
The sample is then shifted to illuminate a
new region , for which a different scattering
pattern is recorded.
Importantly, this region should overlap with
the previous spot.
This, logically, means that any correct real-space
structural solution for both of these speckle
patterns MUST contain a common region regarding
their detailed structures where they overlapped.
This imposes a strong constraint and provides
added redundancy to the algorithm used to
solve the structure.
If the overlap is too large, little added
information is gained and the scanning procedure
is slowed down, while if there is too little
overlap, the degree of ambiguity of the solution
increases.
As a rule of thumb a 40% areal overlap is
close to being optimal.
Ptycography and CXDI will benefit significantly
from the increase in coherence of DLSRs compared
to 3rd generation facilities.
This can be exploited in one of two manners
- either a reduction in exposure times to
obtain the same information; or access to
finer detail.
The resolution improves with Q, but the intensity
drops off approximately as 1/Q^4, so a hundredfold
increase in coherent intensity would allow
a factor of 100^1/4, or approximately 3 in
Q, bringing the finest details down to the
low nanometer regime.
Indeed, further tricks not directly associated
with the increased coherent fraction of DLSRs
are liable to increase the speed or accuracy
of ptychography by up to another 3 orders
of magnitude, through, for example, an increased
bandwidth of radiation allowed through the
monochromator - remember, this only affects
the longitudinal coherence, and it is the
lateral coherence that is of primary interest.
Secondly improvements in undulator technology,
in particular magnet materials; and thirdly,
more efficient optics, for example migrating
from Fresnel zone plates to K-B focussing,
will all contribute to significant improvements
of this burgeoning imaging technique.
Imaging using x-rays is an enormously profitable
enterprise, in which insights on the sub-micron
to nanometer scale can often be rapidly obtained
– indeed, the first demonstration of the
power of x-rays was made by Roentgen with
his radiographs of human hands.
The impact these must have had on society
can hardly be appreciated in a modern world
in which medical radiographic imaging is so
commonplace.
However, the detailed architectural information
provided by tomography on a microscopic scale
can still both surprise and delight.
The immediacy of the feedback and the relative
ease of an at least qualitative interpretation
supplied by x-ray imaging makes it one of
the most attractive modern synchrotron techniques.
As still more powerful and coherent x-rays
sources such as DLSRs begin to come online,
their associated enormous power densities
means that any optical components such as
focussing lenses will be circumvented if they
are not absolutely necessary.
Lensless imaging, in particularly CXDI and
more recently ptychography, is emerging not
just as an attractive alternative to conventional
x-ray microscopy, but may in many cases be
the only realistic approach in investigating
complex and large-scale structures on a near-atomic
scale.
This drive promises still more exciting developments
in the near future.