Welcome to the first video of Week 9 of this
introductory course on synchrotrons and x-ray
free-electron lasers!
This week, we will discuss approaches to phasing
in macromolecular crystallography.
After some introductory remarks and a recap
of some essential tools needed to understand
this week’s topics, the methods of molecular
replacement and multiple isomorphous replacement
will be covered in order to demonstrate general
approaches to phasing in MX, as essentially
the same mathematical approach is used also
in the further three techniques we will discuss,
namely multiwavelength anomalous diffraction,
single-wavelength anomalous diffraction, and
native-SAD.
We finish the week by looking at current trends
in this field.
So, in this first video, we begin by familiarizing
ourselves with basic concepts and approaches
to phasing in MX.
As we have already mentioned several times
earlier in this course, the interpretation
of diffraction data is hampered by the fact
that half of the information, namely the relative
phases between the diffraction components,
is lost, because one measures the intensity,
not the amplitude - this is the phase problem,
which can lead to multiple possible structural
solutions, depending on how complete the diffraction
data set is, and how complex the atomic structure
is within the unit cell.
In the early days of diffraction, simple structures
such as rock salt or diamond could be `relatively’
easily solved using trial-and-error approaches,
arguments of symmetry, and invoking physicochemical
limitations, such as known reasonable ranges
of bond lengths between atoms.
A nice personal review of this by Max Perutz
can be found in the reference given here bottom
left.
As the atomic structures in the unit cells
became increasingly complex, a more systematic
approach was needed, in particular Fourier
analysis and so-called Patterson maps, used
extensively by Dorothy Hodgkin in her seminal
works, among others, on the structures of
penicillin and insulin.
The use of Patterson maps remains one of the
cornerstones of phasing in macromolecular
crystallography to this day.
An interesting approach to the phase problem
that was first developed in the 1950s by Jerome
Karle and Herbert Hauptman is that of the
so-called direct methods.
In general it is based on iterations that
cycle between real space and reciprocal space
by the actions of Fourier- and inverse-Fourier
transforms.
When in reciprocal space, the diffraction
amplitudes emerging from the FT are replaced
with the square-roots of the experimentally
determined diffraction intensities, and the
phases remain untouched.
Conversion of this via an inverse-FT to real
space will result in a structure which is
then examined for its reasonableness, using
arguments such as, for example, that the electron
density cannot be negative anywhere, that
most electron charge is concentrated around
the nuclear core of atoms (this constraint
is called `atomicity’), and that the structure
must fit within a reasonable support and have
physically reasonable bond lengths.
This iterative cycling continues until self-consistency
is reached, that is, no changes need to be
made in either real or reciprocal space.
Direct methods succeed only up to an upper
limit of complexity, presently at around 1000
atoms, though improvements in both the quality
of diffraction data and computer power is
likely to push the envelope in the future.
For the foreseeable future, however, direct
methods and certainly trial-and-error approaches
will certainly fail for larger structures
such as proteins.
For example, the molecular weight of the human
ribosome 80S subunit is approximately 3.2
million Daltons, containing of the order of
200’000 atoms (excluding the hydrogen-atoms).
For these systems, novel approaches needed
to be brought to bear on the problem.
In all cases other than molecular replacement,
the two general approaches are either (a)
to change the structure in a controlled and
known manner, and observe how this induces
changes in the diffraction pattern, or (b)
see how the diffraction pattern changes as
a result of being close to an absorption edge
of one or more atom types within the structure.
So, in multiple isomorphous replacement, or
MIR, specific components are replaced, or
additional material added, but for which the
structure otherwise remains invariant - in
other words, the other atom positions don’t
move and the unit-cell size remains constant
- this is the meaning of isomorphous.
Multiple-wavelength anomalous diffraction
(MAD) works by observing changes in the diffraction
pattern as one varies the photon energy around
an absorption edge.
In single-wavelength anomalous diffraction
(SAD), differences in certain symmetry-related
diffraction maxima within the same diffraction
set are exploited to solve the structure.
All of these methods also use molecular replacement
(MR), which relies upon the existence in the
structure of a previously solved protein fold
which is homologous, or similar, to part of
the structure to be solved.
Before we introduce the concepts of the Patterson
function and then Friedel’s law, it’s
worth spending a moment to recap how one uses
Argand, or complex plane diagrams.
Imagine a unit cell containing three atoms.
We flood this with x-rays of wavelength lambda
. Note that in the Bragg condition, the phase
at the same point in different unit cells
must experience the same phase of the x-ray
plane wave, such as shown for these three
equivalent atoms highlighted with crosses
(wait 2 secs) . The phases of scattering from
each atom can be estimated by seeing where
their centres lie relative to the incident
beam - the blue atom is at 0, the green at
pi/3, or 60 degrees, and the red atom at 3pi/2
(270 degrees).
The scattering amplitudes can therefore be
added up in an Argand diagram vectorially
with the appropriate angle corresponding to
the phases.
So scattering from the blue atom is represented
by an arrow of certain length (proportional
to the atom’s scattering strength) and at
zero degrees . The green atom is a weaker
scatterer with smaller scattering vector at
an angle of 60 degrees , while the scattering
vector of the large red atom points downwards,
at 270 degrees . The total structure factor
is therefore the black arrow shown here .
We now introduce the Patterson function.
Even though we cannot determine the structure
of a unit cell from the diffraction pattern
intensities alone, it turns out that it can
nonetheless provide valuable information.
Arthur Patterson showed in 1935 that the inverse
Fourier transform of the diffraction-pattern
intensities yields a centrosymmetric real-space
structure consisting of peaks separated by
the relative positions between atoms.
In the example here of the molecule fluoroselenoformaldehyde,
SeCHF, 13 maxima are to be seen.
In fact, it can be shown that these relative
distances are a result of the convolution
of the molecule’s electron density distribution
with its inverse.
Let’s look at this simple example in a little
more detail in order to understand the general
properties of Patterson functions, or Patterson
maps, as they’re also known.
First, because the Patterson map is the convolution
of the electron density with its inverse,
it is always centrosymmetric, with equivalent
points at r_ij and -r_ij between atoms i and
j . The intensities of these maxima are proportional
to the product of their atomic numbers, Z_i
and Z_j - this means that if there are heavy
atoms in the structure, their contributions
will dominate.
The central spot is by far the most intense,
being the sum of the convolution of all the
atoms with themselves (that is, therefore,
at zero distance) . Lastly, there are N(N-1)
+ 1 maxima, which for a molecule which may
easily contain 100’000 atoms, means the
pattern is extremely crowded, containing approximately
10^10 contributions.
Needless to say, the Patterson map has, for
proteins, essentially a continuous distribution.
We show here some simple examples based around
the aromatic molecule benzene, and how these
change according to whether one or more hydrogen
atoms have been substituted for heavier atoms.
In this case, we substitute with bromine.
Benzene has a Patterson map that is highly
symmetric, with six-fold symmetry.
By substituting one hydrogen with bromine,
the symmetry is reduced , and one clearly
sees how the C6 ring is `picked’ out by
the bromine atom.
Adding another bromine opposite the first
in 1,4 dibromobenzene changes the pattern
primarily by introducing the strongest signal
(except at the central spot) at the uppermost
and lowest positions, equating to the distance
between the two bromine atoms.
Lastly, on 1,2, dibromobenzene, the pattern
changes ***** again due to the closer proximity
of the tow bromine atoms.
Take your time in studying these in order
to get a feel for what Patterson maps provide.
We complete this first video by discussing
Frieden pairs and Friedel’s law.
Consider a Bragg maximum at (hkl) , with scattering
vector Q . The opposite Bragg peak in reciprocal
space is at (h-bar k-bar, l-bar) and the scattering
vector for this must point in the opposite
direction.
Now let’s consider this from the perspective
of the unit cell and the hkl-planes . Remember
too, that the phase difference between equivalent
points in adjacent unit cells has to be 2pi
for constructive interference, that is, for
the Bragg condition to be met.
For reflection off the hkl planes , the scattering
vector is, as we know, perpendicular to these
. The atomic scattering factors of the atoms
between the hkl-planes add up vectorially
in some manner to produce a structure factor
F_hkl associated with the hkl-reflection and
a phase phi_hkl.
Remember, the intensity is proportional to
the square of F_hkl.
The Bragg peak at h-bar k-bar l-bar is generated
by approaching the atoms from below - Q is
in the opposite direction, as required.
Now, what are the phases of the individual
scattering vectors.
Let’s first consider the blue atom.
This has a phase phi_1 relative to the upper
hkl-plane, which means its phase relative
to the lower plane is 2pi - phi_1, which is
equal to -phi_1.
The atomic scattering vector for the blue
atom for the h-bar k-bar l-bar reflection
is therefore the mirror image of that for
hkl . Obviously, the same holds true for all
the other atoms , and therefore the magnitude
of Fhkl and Fhkl-bar is identical, and their
phase is opposite, that is, phi_hkl-bar = -phi_hkl.
So, in summary, Friedel’s law says that
Bragg peaks at hkl and hkl-bar, known as Frieden
pairs, are equal in magnitude and their phases
are opposite in sign.
Diffraction patterns are therefore centrosymmetric,
though as we will see, Friedel’s law breaks
down if the pattern was recorded in the neighbourhood
of one of the atoms’ absorption edges.
Before we see why, I quickly cover the case
of centrosymmetric crystals (don’t confuse
this with centrosymmetric diffraction patterns),
as they have special properties.
Consider the 2D cartoon of a centrosymmetric
crystal shown here.
As we know, the phase difference between the
hkl-planes needs to be 2 pi in the Bragg condition.
For convenience’s sake in order to make
our arguments easier to follow, we choose
to show this phase change to be from + pi
to - pi . Let’s now consider the scattering
contributions in an Argand diagram from pairs
of atoms which are opposite each other through
the centre of symmetry.
We begin with the two atoms highlighted here
and labelled `1’ . If one of these has a
phase phi_1 , then the other must have a phase
-phi_1 . Their contributions therefore cancel
out in the imaginary direction in the Argand
diagram, and their summed scattering contribution
is real . This holds true for all other pairs,
for example the green atoms labelled with
a `2’ , as shown here . If the centrosymmetric
crystal contains an atom at the centre of
symmetry, this has, by definition a phase
of zero, and is thus also real.
The take-home message is therefore that structure
factors of centrosymmetric crystals are real,
as long as they are far from absorption edges.
OK, so let’s return to the general case
of crystals with any symmetry.
What happens to the structure factors of Frieden
pairs if one includes the correction terms
f’ and f”, which become non-negligible
near absorption edges.
So let’s begin with our uncorrected structure
factors and now add the correction terms.
In this cartoon, the atom with an absorption
edge close to the used photon energy is the
one that produces the red atomic scattering
vectors.
In the case of the hkl structure factor, the
f’ term reduces the magnitude of the red
vector by this amount , as we’ve discussed
before.
f” is then added on to this, but at an angle
of +90 degrees, or pi/2 . The vector for Fhkl
has therefore changed .
Now let’s see what happens to the hkl-bar
structure factor.
The f’ term needs to be subtracted from
the red vector, as before , but now, the addition
of f” is in the same sense, +90 degrees
. This means that both the magnitude of Fhkl-bar
differs from that of Fhkl , and that the phases
are no longer equal in magnitude and opposite
in sign.
In other words, by recording diffraction patterns
close to absorption edges, they lose their
centrosymmetry.
Lastly, what changes occur in centrosymmetric
crystals due to absorption?
As we argued three slides back, without the
correction terms f’ and f”, the structure
factors of centrosymmetric crystals are real
and therefore Fhkl and Fhkl-bar have the same
magnitude and lie along the real axis (in
other words, phi = 0).
So adding f’ and f” will change Fhkl and
Fhkl-bar identically . The structure factors
may no longer be real, but they do remain
the same both in their magnitudes and in their
phases . In other words, centrosymmetric crystals
ALWAYS have centrosymmetric diffraction patterns,
independent of photon energy.
As we shall see in the third of the video
this week, this means that SAD experiments
cannot be performed on centrosymmetric crystals.
Fortunately, almost no proteins produce centrosymmetric
crystal structures, due primarily to their
chiral nature (chiral structures cannot exhibit
centrosymmetry).
In summary, this first video has prepared
us by introducing the concepts of Patterson
maps and Friedel’s law, for the different
techniques used to solve complex protein structures.
In the next video, we will discuss the first
approach developed for this, pioneered by
the two Nobel-prize winners Max Perutz and
John Kendrew, namely multiple isomorphous
replacement, or MIR, including the construction
of Harker diagrams, which themselves use Argand
diagrams.
In addition we will briefly describe molecular
replacement, as this remains the `working
horse’ of solving protein structures.