Welcome to the second video of Week 9 of this
introductory course on synchrotrons and x-ray
free-electron lasers!
In this video, we will describe in some detail
the methods of molecular replacement and multiple
isomorphous replacement, the latter also setting
the foundations for how the phase problem
is solved in the two more modern methods discussed
in the last video of this week, namely multi-wavelength
anomalous diffraction, and single-wavelength
anomalous diffraction.
Molecular replacement is an approach to solving
the structure of a protein by taking chunks
of protein structures that have already been
solved and testing them out to see if they
might be part of the unsolved structure under
investigation.
A protein fold is the manner in which so-called
secondary structures order themselves in space.
Secondary structures are the helices and sheets
commonly seen in depictions of proteins. In
the snippet of a protein shown here, I have
coloured the alpha-helices gold, and the beta-sheets
blue. Although one fold may look very similar
or essentially identical to another, this
does not necessarily mean it has the same
chemistry, that is, the same amino-acid sequence
- two such folds are said to be homologous.
Despite Nature’s seemingly infinite variety,
it seems that she creates using a limited
collection of building blocks. 1400 protein
folds have to date been discovered, and the
last of these was in 2008. Although the possibility
remains that there could be many more still
to discover, for example in the relatively
unexplored class of membrane proteins, this
seemingly rather circumscribed selection of
folds thus lends itself to the approach of
molecular replacement. As a rule of thumb,
MR is often relatively straightforward if
the unsolved structure shares 40% or more
sequence identity (that is, the amino-acid
sequence) with the known structure.
So, if one suspects that a structure might
contain a certain fold, how does one go about
testing this, and also finding out where exactly
the fold might sit and in which orientation?
The approach is one of “divide and conquer”,
and it uses the Patterson map to achieve this.
Consider the cartoon on the right. A block
of a solved structure is suspected to be also
present in some unknown position and orientation
in an unknown protein structure for which
a set of diffraction patterns has been recorded.
In principle, one could then directly compare
this pattern to that of the known structure
for all possible orientations and positions
of that structure within the unit cell. A
good best match between the two would provide
valuable information about the unknown structure.
Such a procedure, however, would require varying
three rotational and three translational parameters
with sufficient resolution (given, respectively,
by the rotation angles between diffraction
images in the data set, and by the resolution
of the electron- density map of the known
structure). This six-dimensional search is,
for anything other than the smallest structures,
computationally too demanding.
Instead, we exploit the fact that Patterson
maps provide information on the relative distances
and directions between atom pairs. We define
“intrachunk” signal in the Patterson map
as being between atoms within the known molecular
motif that is being tested, and “extrachunk”
signal as lying at distances outside this,
that is, outside the circle with a radius
equal to the largest extent of the molecular
chunk.
Importantly, the intrachunk signal depends
only on the orientation of the motif being
tested, and not on its position in the unit
cell. This will mostly affect the centre of
the Patterson map out to the intrachunk radius.
It is therefore this central part of the Patterson
map that is optimised between the test and
unknown structures in order to determine the
angular orientation. This only involves varying
the three rotational degrees of freedom.
In contrast, extrachunk vectors between atoms
inside and outside the protein fold depend
both on its orientation and on its position
relative to the rest of the structure. So,
in the second step, the extrachunk vectors
can be exploited in the outer parts of the
Patterson map to determine the translation
vector.
By exploiting this property of Patterson maps,
the six-parameter search can thus be reduced
to two independent, three-dimensional searches
of first a rotational operation, and then
a translation within the bounds of the unit
cell. It is important to appreciate just how
beneficial this simplification is. Critically,
the complexity of optimization search routines
increases not linearly with the number of
parameters, but exponentially. As an example,
if a one-parameter search spanning one hundred
values of that parameter requires one second
of CPU time, adding a second parameter with
the same range of values increases the CPU
time to 100 seconds. A similar six-parameter
search would require three hundred years!
In contrast, two three-parameters searches
would be complete after only six hours.
The power of modern computers and the ever-growing
database of high-quality, atomic-resolution
protein structures means that the majority
of protein structures are at least partly
solved using MR. Indeed, this predominance
of MR is likely to increase with computing
power, the introduction of novel software
tools to automatically perform the rotational
searches, and, in a self-fulfilling process,
the expanding volume of reliable structural
data.
We now describe multiple isomorphous replacement,
the historically first approach to determine
the structure by observing how the diffraction
pattern changes when controlled structural
changes are made to it.
Let’s consider a protein-crystal unit cell.
This produces a certain diffraction pattern
with its own set of intensities. Now imagine
the same unit cell , but in which a heavy
atom has either been added or which has substituted
a native atom or small molecular chunk. This
new structure containing the heavy atom produces
its own diffraction pattern , which will differ
from the original native structure.
So let’s concentrate on one particular Bragg
peak of the original structure, highlighted
here . The Argand diagram consists of many
vector contributions, one each from each atom
in the native structure. We add all these
up vectorially to produce F_P, the native
protein’s structure factor for that particular
reflection, proportional to the square root
of the Bragg-peak intensity . Now, what about
the same Bragg peak for the derivative structure
containing the heavy atom? Apart from the
addition of this atom, the rest of the structure
should remain unchanged (this is the “isomorphous”
aspect, and cannot always be guaranteed).
So we can add on the vector for the structure
factor of the heavy atom F_H, to produce the
structure factor of the derivative structure
F_PH, proportional to the square root of the
Bragg peak intensity in the derivative’s
diffraction pattern.
OK, now let’s look at this structure factor
of the derivative heavy-atom structure. We
can rearrange the vectors like this without
removing the generality of our arguments.
F_P, F_H, and F_PH all remain the same regarding
both their phase angles and magnitudes.
So, the structure factor of the native structure
F_P lies somewhere on the blue circle shown
here - its actual phase angle is given here,
but we don’t know what this is (that’s
the problem with the phase problem!!) We now
add the vector F_H , from which we can construct
F_PH , which lies somewhere on the orange
circle shown here. There are therefore two
possible orientations of F_P (and also F_PH,
not shown here in order to keep things uncluttered).
But which of these is correct? In order to
determine this unambiguously, a second derivative
structure must be prepared and the diffraction
pattern recorded. We can then draw a third
green circle with a radius corresponding to
the square root of the intensity of this particular
Bragg peak |F_PH2|^2. This will overlap only
one of the two possible solutions obtained
from the first two diffraction patterns, thereby
removing the ambiguity .
Now, the more critical of you might have noticed
that the arguments given here are predicated
on knowing the amplitudes and phases of the
two heavy-atom contributions F_H and F_H2,
in other words their magnitudes and angles
in the Argand diagram. How do we get these?
We discuss this briefly now.
We redraw the vector addition of F_P with
F_H to produce F_PH once more, including the
phase angles .
We define |Delta F|_iso as being equal to
the difference in magnitude between the square-roots
of the intensities of F_PH and F_H at the
diffraction spot. The angle between F_H and
F_PH is simply phi_H - phi_PH . Now if we
draw a line from the end of F_P to F_PH, perpendicular
to F_PH, we immediately see that the difference
between F_PH and F_P is approximately given
by F_H cos(phi_H = phi_PH). This is valid
if both F_P and F_PH are significantly larger
than F_H, and is also approximately true for
relatively large F_H, as long as phi_H - phi_PH
is small. For most instances, one or both
of these approximations hold fairly well.
So, what next? First, we take our approximate
equation for |Delta F|_iso and square both
sides. Next , we use the trigonometric identity
that the square of the cosine of an angle
is equal to the cosine of double that angle
plus one, all divided by two. Substituting
this into the top equation yields DeltaF_iso^2
= F_H^2/2 + F_H^2/2 times cosine(2(phi_H - phi_PH)).
But phi_H and phi_PH are not correlated, which
means the cosine of the second term can take
on any value and therefore the second term
produces only background noise. This leaves
us with the first term F_H^2/2. This is a
usable Fourier component. By doing this calculation
for all recorded Bragg spots, one can therefore
generate a “difference” Patterson map
of the heavy atom, or atoms, only!!
So, in conclusion, by performing the above
straightforward mathematical manipulations,
we can obtain the Patterson map of the heavy
atoms and obtain the phase angle and magnitude
of F_H. This was the necessary information
that we needed in the previous slide (which
might now seem a long time ago. Sorry!) in
order to obtain the phases of the original
notice protein structure phi_P.
Let’s now work out a “typical” order
of magnitude for differences in Bragg-peak
intensities as a consequence of introducing
a heavy atom. I say “typical”, but this
can of course vary hugely, according to how
many heavy atoms one can introduce in a unit
cell, and how heavy the total native structure
is. In this particular example, we assume
a molecular mass of the native protein of
50 kDa, while the derivative structure contains
a single mercury atom.
As we said already, there is no apriori correlation
between the phase of the total structure factor
F_P of the native protein and that of the
heavy atom, so F_H will sit anywhere on a
circle centered on the end of F_P and having
a radius equal to the magnitude of F_H. One
possible outcome is, for example, here. The
limits of the values F_PH can assume is therefore
between FP _ F_H and F_P + F_H .
We show a plot on the left of the atomic form
factors of hydrogen, carbon, nitrogen, oxygen,
sulphur, and mercury as a function of scattering
vector Q. Note that the heavier the atom,
the more slowly it drops off as a function
of Q. The form factor for carbon at seven
reciprocal angstroms is about 28% the value
at Q = 0, while for mercury, it is still about
56%. This means that the relative contribution
of the heavy atom increases with increasing
Q - larger relative differences in the diffraction
pattern Bragg-peak intensities are to be seen
further out in the pattern, even if the absolute
intensities drop off.
We also assume an “average” protein chemical
composition as shown here.
For reasons which will become clearer in the
third and last video of this week, the average
structure factor of the native protein can
therefore be calculated using this equation.
This is a statistically averaged result based
on the assumption that the positions of the
atomic form factors of each atom are entirely
uncorrelated with the incident x-radiation
- it would be a remarkable and very odd situation
if this were not so! In actuality, the real
structure factor magnitudes will vary around
this value (like I say, the equation is a
statistical average). Using this equation
for F_P, we can either add or subtract F_H,
then square this up to get the upper and lower
limits of the derivative intensities. As you
can see, this can be large, up to +/- a few
tens of percent and therefore very easy to
detect. Like I say, though, a larger protein
with a lighter heavy-atom substitute or addition
will produce weaker effects, while the opposite
is true for smaller proteins and/or heavier
atom substitutes, or for the case that there
are more than one heavy atom per unit cell.
In summary, multiple isomorphous replacement
functions by changing the Bragg-peak intensities
by addition or substitution of one or more
heavy metals in the unit cell. The validity
of the approach depends on the heavy atom
being able to be inserted into the structure
and that this does not disrupt the size or
shape of the remainder of the protein structure,
that is, the native part. Famous successful
examples of using MIR that won the users of
this technique the Nobel prize include insulin
and penicillin by Dorothy Hodgkin, and myoglobin
and haemoglobin by John Kendrew and Max Perutz,
respectively.
MIR needs at least two derivative structures,
and this aspect could often represent an insurmountable
obstacle. Interestingly, when Martha Teeter
and Wayne Hendrickson attempted to use MIR
in the protein crambin in the 1970s, they
were unable to produce any reasonable derivatives.
In desperation, they tried to see if they
could identify any differences in intensities
between Friedel pairs in the diffraction pattern
of the native structure, and serendipitously
thereby invented the technique of single-wavelength
anomalous diffraction, covered in the next
video. It was this, and initially in particular
multiwavelength anomalous diffraction, both
of which are based on anomalous effects, that
would supersede MIR, especially once the use
of synchrotron radiation became more widespread.
We discuss these two methods in the next video.