Welcome to the third and final video of Week
9 of this introductory course on synchrotrons
and x-ray free-electron lasers!
In this video, we discuss techniques that
depend on the change in the structure factor
because of absorption effects.
The technique of multiwavelength anomalous
diffraction only works using unable synchrotron
or xfel radiation.
SAD in principle does work for a fixed-wavelength
lab source, but in practice is never done
using lab sources due to the weakness of the
SAD signal and therefore the need to obtain
very clean data with highly reliable diffraction
intensities.
Lastly, we will briefly discuss current and
possible future trends in macromolecular crystallography.
In the graphs here, various important aspects
of the atomic form factor of selenium are
shown.
Selenium was chosen here as it is one of the
most common elements that is substituted into
protein structures via selenomethionine, the
selenium-substituted version of otherwise
sulphur-containing methionine, one of the
human essential amino acids (which, incidentally
has a natural abundance of 1.8%).
Top left is the atomic form factor of selenium
with values at 0, 2, 4, and 6 reciprocal Angstroms
highlighted by the coloured circles.
Top right is the change in f’ and f” in
the neighbourhood of the K-absorption edge
of selenium, centered at 12658 eV.
An alternative plot is shown bottom left,
in which f” is plotted as a function of
f’.
The photon-energy values of points on this
curve that lie as far from each other as possible
have been highlighted.
Lastly, the magnitude of the complex atomic
form factor as a function of energy and Q
is shown in the dashed lines in the bottom-right
curve, for the four values of Q highlighted
top left.
The corresponding change in phase compared
to energies where the anomalous contributions
are insignificant is shown with the solid
lines, and is equal to the arctangent of f”/(f_1
= f^0 + f’).
Take a little time to absorb this information
and understand it, as we will be using it
repeatedly from hereon in.
The beauty of multiwavelength anomalous diffraction
over multiple isomorphous replacement is that
(a) only one heavy-atom structure is required,
and (b) isomorphism is guaranteed insofar
that no physical substitution is needed to
change the structure factors.
Instead these change due to one or more heavy
atoms modifying their atomic form factors
as one passes across an absorption edge.
MAD experiments require one to record three
or more diffraction data sets around the absorption
edge of the heavy atom . F_H will change its
magnitude and phase and cause F_PH to do so
also.
In addition, for any one photon energy, the
Friedel pairs will also show differences for
the reasons outlined in the first video of
this week.
This is, actually, SAD signal, but we’ll
discuss this more later.
One potential setback with MAD, though no
more so than in MIR, is that the reliability
of the data depends on the crystal not being
radiation damaged to an extent that this swamps
the MAD differences before the minimum of
three data sets are recorded.
For any one energy in MAD, we can construct
the Harker diagram like we did in the last
video for MIR.
Let’s look at how we obtain F_PH^+.
To the native structure factor we add the
heavy atom structure factor . But we have
chosen the photon energy to be around the
absorption edge of this atom or atoms.
So we need to subtract f’ and add f” at
90 degrees to this . This is our final structure
factor F_PH^+ . Now, what about the Friedel
pair F_PH^-?
Well, we proceed as before . But now let’s
pause before adding on f”.
. . Now, we don’t continue to reproduce
the mirror image of what we did for F_PH^+,
but instead, add f” in the other direction
. If we mirror flip this across the real axis,
we see clearly the difference . The complex
conjugate of F_PH^- is distinct from F_PH^+
. The vector difference between them has a
magnitude of 2 times f”.
Their magnitudes differ too, as shown here
by the dashed circles . And now we rearrange
the vectors in the same way as we did when
when we introduced Harker diagrams in the
last video .
From hereon in, the procedure is much the
same as in MIR.
This is done for other photon energies, the
impact on the Harker diagram depending on
the changes in f’ and f” as one crosses
the absorption edge.
Multiwavelength anomalous diffraction thus
exploits these changes in the anomalous signal.
Single-wavelength anomalous diffraction exploits
only the fact that Friedel-pair intensities
differ if f” is not too small, and as such
requires just one diffraction data set at
one energy.
As such it is the method that, to date, requires
the shortest acquisition times and therefore
suffers least from radiation damage.
SAD can be performed on a heavy-atom derivative,
or if one is lucky, there may be a naturally
occurring heavy atom such as iron.
The latest developments in SAD, called “native”
SAD, exploit anomalous signal from lighter
naturally occurring elements, most notably
sulphur, but also phosphorus in the case of
studies of DNA- or RNA-containing biostructures.
Because of the weakness of the SAD signal
in lighter atoms, native SAD in particular
requires the highest accuracy in recording
diffraction structure factors.
In the Harker construction of SAD, which we
also looked at in our discussion of MAD, there
remains an ambiguity.
. .
caused by the two possible solutions that
emerge from the overlap of the two Harker
circles . Which of these is correct?
. The beauty of SAD is the lack of need to
record more than one data set, so how does
one overcome this ambiguity?
The approach used is an iterative method called
solvent flattening.
A “typical” protein crystal does not contain
protein structure packed to the hilt, but
instead contains approximately 50% by volume
of protein folds, etc, and 50% solvent molecules.
The former are fixed and repeat more or less
faithfully from unit cell to unit cell - it’s
for this reason we can obtain protein diffraction
data.
The solvent, however, has no long-range order
and is instead composed of completely randomly
oriented solvent molecules.
Over many unit cells, therefore, the average
electron density of the solvent should be
flat and featureless.
The average electron density of the solvent
is in general lower than that of protein - the
former is 0.33 e/A3 for water , while for
protein it is 0.43 e/A3 . Any half-way decent
model will therefore show islands of higher
average electron density in a sea of, on average,
lower electron density, though it might be
difficult to distinguish the coastlines, if
we extend the metaphor.
In addition, before a really good structural
model is obtained, the “sea” may be very
choppy.
The goal of solvent flattening is to obtain
`dead calm’.
. .
After recording a SAD data set, with experimental
values found for F+ and F-, a difference-map
can be generated and for each structure factor
there will be a pair of possible phases phi_A
and phi_B.
This is our starting point.
As an input, we take our experimentally determined
structure-factor magnitudes, and a random
selection of either phi_A or phi_B for each
structure factor.
This is Fourier transformed to produce a real-space
structure.
Those regions which appear to be protein by
dint of their higher electron density are
“shrink-wrapped” and preserved, while
the remainder is deemed to be solvent.
Any noise to these regions is then either
flattened, or, in an alternative approach,
flipped around the expected average value
for the solvent being used.
This modified real-space model is then inverse
Fourier transformed , and the resulting calculated
structure-factor magnitudes replaced with
the experimental values . The choice of phi_A
or phi_B is determined by which is closer
to the newly calculated value.
This cycle is repeated until consistency arises
between real and reciprocal space.
In conventional SAD, which tries to get as
large a signal out of the f” form factor
component as possible, certain energies and
atom types are of particular interest.
In addition to selenium SAD, significantly
stronger signal can be obtained if one is
able to insert heavy elements such as platinum,
gold, or mercury in an isomorphic manner.
This supplies a SAD signal 2f” of 10 electrons
or larger.
At lower energies between approximately 3
and 7 keV, the f” values can exceed 50 electrons
nd the SAD difference between Friedel pairs
may be very large indeed.
However, lower photon energies are associated
with more radiation damage, more absorption
and scattering from ambient air, other gas,
or solvents, and a reduced access to reciprocal
space.
Nonetheless, this is a highly interesting
new direction, and a large cylindrical Pilatus
detector containing 12 million pixels has
been installed at the I23 beamline at the
Diamond Light Source, and is beginning to
produce first data in 2016.
Because of the increased absorption of air,
the detector is placed in vacuum, which also
imposes potential problems of denaturing of
the protein crystals in such an environment.
As already briefly mentioned, the most modern
SAD experiments attempt to solve the phase
problem and extract the structure via the
weak anomalous signals associated with atoms
that are native to the protein, in particular
sulphur.
Indeed, as already mentioned, the first ever
demonstration of SAD was both using sulphur,
and, more remarkably, using a Cu-K alpha lab
source at 8.04 keV, some 5 and half keV higher
in energy than the sulphur K-edge.
At this energy, 2f_2 is less than 1 electron
. Now, there WAS a gap of eight years between
recording the data and eventual publication,
a sign of how weak the SAD signal was and
how difficult the phasing using this must
have been.
Nonetheless, it does show that one doesn’t
have to be all that close to the absorption
edge to see an effect, particularly for clean
and intense data recorded at synchrotrons.
One of the reasons why crambin lent itself
to sulphur-SAD was its unusually high concentration
of sulphur - some three times higher than
seen on average in proteins.
Me!!!!!
The
next step is to see how strong native SAD
signal is, and how contributions from all
native atom types are (apart from hydrogen,
which is far too weak to contribute significantly).
Before we proceed, we assume an average protein
chemical formula given here.
This was calculated by summing the chemical
formulae of the 20 naturally occurring amino
acids in vertebrates, weighted by their relative
abundance, then normalising this to one sulphur
atom.
In addition, as we found out in the second
week of this course, the value of f_2 scales
with the fourth power of Z, which means, for
example, that sulphur has an imaginary anomalous
contribution that is approximately 50 times
larger than that of carbon.
So how do the individual vectorial form factors
add up on average?
In native SAD, sulphur obviously has the largest
value for f_2.
At 5 keV, this amounts to about 1.3 electrons
. The f_2-values for carbon, nitrogen, and
oxygen at this energy are 0.028, 0.05, and
0.09, respectively, in other words between
one or two orders of magnitude smaller than
that of sulphur.
Does this mean we can ignore their contributions
to the SAD signal?
This depends very much on the sulphur content
in the protein.
If we take the average chemical composition
of proteins given in the previous slide, we
see from the table here that, for example,
a 50kDa protein has almost 100 times more
carbon atoms than sulphur.
So is carbon’s small value for f_2 compensated
by its abundance?
Let’s begin with the carbon atoms.
Like I already said in the last video, there
is patently no correlation between the incident
plane wave of x-rays and the positions of
the atoms, so their scattering phases must
be entirely random . We can therefore say,
that on average, the vector addition of one
type of atom to produce a structure factor
for this, will produce a vector with a magnitude
equal to that of an individual atom of this
type at this Q-vector, multiplied by the square
root of the number of those atoms . So far,
I have assumed no anomalous terms.
How can we include these?
First, f’ becomes very small if one lies
even only a few hundred eV above an absorption
edge, so we ignore this for all the native
atoms considered here.
f_2 drops off much more slowly, however.
Because this is always at +90 degrees to the
real part of the atomic form factor, the sum
of f_2 will also be at +90 degrees and will
also be proportional to the square-root of
the number of atoms of that type.
So, in the case of carbon, the square-root
of 1949 is approximately 44, so the real part
of F_C = 44 x 3.07 = 135 electrons, and the
imaginary part of F_C = 44 x 0.028 = 1.23
electrons.
If we make the same calculations for nitrogen,
oxygen, and sulphur, we get the following
results . From this, we see that sulphur has
a summed f_2 value equal to approximately
twice that of oxygen, and a little over four
times that of nitrogen or carbon.
How does one add up the contributions from
carbon, nitrogen, and oxygen?
- clearly not linearly, as this would imply
that their summed vectors all lie in the same
direction.
It turns out that on average, their vector
addition is the square-root of the sum of
their squares, which in this instance equal
3.27 electrons, about 60% of the contribution
from the sulphur atoms.
Importantly, the values for the sum of f_2
for C, N, and O are more statistically reliable
than for the sulphur atoms, on account of
there being many more of them.
Hence, the summed f_2 values for sulphur may,
with a higher probability, tend to deviate
from the statistical average, either positively
or negatively.
Perhaps more importantly, if the protein happens
to have less than the average abundance of
sulphur, this will also have a large impact.
The take-home message is, therefore, that,
with increasingly accurate data acquisition,
SAD might soon be possible even for those
structure that are entirely devoid of any
atom types heavier than oxygen.
Is “CNO”-SAD the ultimate phasing technique
for the experimental macromolecular biologist?
We finish this video with a summary of how
the popularity of different phasing methods
has evolved since the advent of third-generation
synchrotron facilities.
First, , single isomorphous replacement, and
multiple isomorphous replacement waned rapidly
once unable and intense synchrotron radiation
became available.
Computer-based ab-initio methods have remained
mainly unchanged, despite John Kendrew’s
prediction in his Nobel speech that speculated
that, ‘although this day will not come soon’,
a protein’s structure could be predicted
based solely on its amino-acid sequence, and
that x-ray crystallographers can go out of
business, perhaps with a certain sense of
relief’.
Over sixty years later, we still await this
momentous day.
. .
As SIR and MIR waned, multiple isomorphous
replacement waxed . As detector technology
improved and further incremental steps were
made in synchrotron brilliance, SAD techniques,
which circumvent the need to record three
or more data sets, became increasingly popular,
as it allowed smaller crystals to be investigated
due to the reduced recording times.
Nowadays, approximately 80% of synchrotron-based
MX experiments are based on SAD.
Within SAD itself, the move towards native
SAD is just beginning to take off after a
hiatus of nearly two decades after Teeter
and Hendrickson’s seminal paper in 1981;
and now sits on the verge of being the “first-choice”
phasing method.
As an example, the crystal structure of the
tubulin-stathmin-TTL complex is shown, which
has a molecular mass of 266 kDa and contains
118 sulphur atoms, 13 phosphorus atoms, and
three Ca2+ ions.
This is the largest structure to be solved
by native SAD to date.
This week has concentrated on phasing techniques
in macromolecular crystallography, and how
these have developed as the complexity of
the structures under investigation and the
sophistication of the x-ray sources have increased.
The still further increased brilliance of
DLSRs will allow the investigation of micron-sized
crystals, thus opening up a vista of new types
of biomolecules that until now have been excluded
to investigation, due to the limited size
to which they could be crystallised.
The experimental approaches with these small
crystals are likely to be based on serial
millisecond crystallography, the synchrotron
sister-technique to serial femtosecond crystallography
used at XFELs.
The future remains truly bright.