- Okay, welcome back! I'm Chris.
- And I'm Mark!
We're going to answer
some of your questions
that you've been tweeting
and sending,
and posting on the fora.
We've made a big list
of all the questions that we've received
and we're going to get through
as many as we possibly can
in the next few minutes.
Okay, so let's start with first one
which was post
when we did Panel 3 on Funding,
The first question
by Philippe in Paris.
Hi Philippe!
Your question was:
Crowdfunding platforms are numerous.
How should we choose between them
for our projects?
Which criteria should be taken
into account?
Okay, so crowdfunding
platform choice is important
and we did discuss this
in one of the sessions on Crowdfunding
or actually in a couple
of different sessions
we touched on this issue.
But basically the quick answer here
is you need to take into consideration
the kind of crowdfunding it is,
the kind of thing you're looking for.
Are you looking for gifts?
Are you looking for pre-selling inventory?
Are you looking for donations?
Loans? Low-interest rate allowance, etc.
and then you got to decide
on the kind of platform,
the kind of-- is it all or nothing funding?
Or if it's Take what you can get funding?
And you also have geographical
and mission focus.
There could be a geographical area
where it's certain,
one, is you're really getting people
in that area,
and then there's the mission focus
which is about the specific topic.
So all those things are all factors
you must take into consideration
when choosing your platform.
I would even suggest
you surf a bit on the net
and try to look at multiple platforms.
Definitely
By doing so, you actually have
a pretty good idea
of which type of platform
will suit you needs best.
It's like which type of platforms,
or which type of movies
that you see there,
clips that you see there,
are actually appealing you
and would most fit
to your own venture.
- Yeah. Have a look at them.
- Have a look at them.
- They have their different personalities.
-Exactly.
Okay. What expenses in manpower
does a good crowdfunding campaign require?
How many people should we recruit
for the process
and which skillset
should they ideally have?
That's all from Philippe in Paris.
(laughing)
Quite interesting crowdfunding.
The crowdfunding clip should be appealing
and it should transport the passion.
And we have seen research that shows that
actually the passion
that you get across on the camera
is something very vital
to getting other people
interested in your idea.
So if you think about this idea
that I just outlined,
how many people would you need?
It's should be you behind the camera,
like we're sitting here.
- Cheap operation (laughs).
- Cheap operation.
It doesn't have to be like
a big Hollywood production.
Quite the contrary,
that might offend some people
because they say, "okay, we want..."
if you see an authentic person
out there shooting this clip,
and then being conservative
with the money,
that sends a signal too.
And also you don't want to spend--
The people on the crowdfunding platform,
we are interested in your product
and your company don't want to spend
their own money
for you being
in a luxurious Hollywood studio.
They want to see that
you're getting something out of the money.
It's not so much about
recruiting other people.
Right. I don't think
you need to recruit anybody for that--
- Exactly.
- For that particular aspect of it.
Ask your friends to stand behind
the camera and do that.
What skills should they ideally have?
The sales skills.
Try to be authentic on the camera.
Try to have a nice storyline
in your crowdfunding clip
to excite people,
and maybe practice a couple of
variations with your friends
and see how they would react.
- Nice.
- That was for Philippe.
And now we're going to Guatemala
just to the other side of the world.
Why do some ventures that we can see
at Crowdfunding pages
such as Kickstarter
look like a very bad idea
but still get what they ask for?
That is an interesting one.
Christian asked that.
- Christian from Guatemala.
- Yeah.
You know that's really interesting (laughs)
- Why do they get money?
Why do they get money?
It's a bad idea (laughs)
Well, I think it's a good idea to me
if they got money for itself.
They've convinced other people
to actually dig deep into their pockets
and give them some money.
So it maybe that they are very good
in execution,
they could be that
they have very good passion
There lots of factors why people give.
It could be that they think the person
got a very good business sense,
and would be responsible with the money
and can change later on
if something else happens
that these ideas terrible.
But in general I don't know--
A bad idea is a subjective thing.
Being able to make money from it,
not everyone is going to agree.
I think that's part of what they're
excitement about entrepreneurship.
You know some ideas
could be appealing to a niche
And you just don't understand
why that niche ever finds
this product interesting
but they love this product
- Right.
- It's a small niche
and these people say
"Finally, something's solves my needs".
- Right.
- That's all.
- You think about a rare disease--
- The cure. (laughs)
You know cure for rare disease I mean,
most people say
"look that's your relevant, that's stupid".
- But people with the rare disease--
- They care a lot.
They like it. Yeah. (laughs)
Okay.
Next is another Philippe.
This one is from Bordeaux France.
Could it be possible to reward
early "Crowdfunders"
by giving them pre-stock-options,
which they could exercise?
And then someone else wrote the same,
Is there any source
of financing mixing crowdfunding
with angel financing to approach people
not with gifts but with equity?
Will it be of any interest
if it doesn't exist yet?
I think here we discuss these a lot
in Week 4.
And you know it depends on the country,
the platform etc.
There's a lot of trickiness here
about giving away equity
in your crowdfunding campaign.
But it is possible in many countries
right now,
and it's getting more and more
possible over time.
So yes it is possible
to do crowdfunding camapaigns
but it's not in every single country.
Watch that little segment again
in Week 4
and look up the rules
in your geographic locations.
I just could to that its--
if you give up equity
that's quite an expensive way
of funding. (laughs)
So there might be other ways
lets say you give them product
at a discount way actually make sale.
So think about equity as one form
you can play with.
But they're others,
take others into consideration
and carefully list that pros and cons
before you go the equity route.
Yes.
Then we have a question in French.
So I prefer to speak
in French now.
From Romer of France.
(In French) If we want to launch
a product in a market,
how do we know if our idea
is compelling
without doing an expensive market study?
So the translation that is
If we want to launch a product
in a new market, how do we know
if our idea is compelling
without doing an expensive market study?
That it is my question.
- Yeah.
In French and in English (laughs)
- Exactly.
How could we know that?
The point is you want to get
a good idea
about the target market
you want to serve,
What does the target market
that you want to serve find appealing?
With a lot of reflection
and desk research
you can also figured out
which type of target market
could be the target market
you want to address.
But it's ultimately you need to talk
with these people.
- Right.
- It doesn't have to cost a lot.
I agree.
But you have to make sure
that you talk to the people
in your target market
and then get their feedback
because their feedback is vital
and then you're reflection meets--
actually the experience
from the market and that typically
or most often makes you think
about how to improve your product
maybe re-positioning your product
to another target market.
It doesn't have to cost a lot.
You don't have to have like a big company
interviewing 500 people,
5,000 people for you
that's not the idea.
It can be a few people
but think smartly about the questions
you want to ask them,
what you want to get
out of these interviews
and what do you want to learn.
So that you improve the match
of your product to the market.
- Get out there and talk to people.
- Exactly.
It's not gonna be that expensive
to do that.
Follow them around,
see how they uses things like that.
Exactly.
Okay, let me ask another question
from Stephan Karlovac.
Which is how big do you think
an impact on crowdfunding
on small businesses in Switzerland is?
Do you know some successful
business stories?
Okay, so that's a very detailed question
which I think refer as...look (laughs)
We're usually prepared here for this.
Like we looked at these questions
for the first time.
But in any case,
we did look up a little bit.
As you know from Week 4,
crowdfunding is a really growing rapidly.
It's 10 Billion Dollars in money
was given to crowdfunding
platforms last year.
There are three relatively big ones
and three smaller platforms
in Switzerland right now,
which even that number is going up.
The number that the amount is raising
within Switzerland is tricky to know
because people outside Switzerland
then go donate into platforms
inside Switzerland
and people inside Switzerland
donate platforms outside Switzerland.
So it's a tricky question to know
the exact volume in Switzerland.
By I did look up a couple success stories
including one called "Suit Art"
which raised on a platform,
a big platform in Switzerland
called "See Crowd".
They raised the 500,050 Francs
which is roughly 600,000 Dollars or so.
And that enable them
to operate a franchise system
and expand to eight cities
in Switzerland.
So they had a individual model
and then they crowdfunded
to do an expansion
and they got money
and then they did they're expansion.
So it's a tailor. it's a--
- Like suit.
- Making suits.
Yeah. Suite Art.
So there you go,
there's an example
of at least one small company.
I had a feeling that's not the only one
that was just very quick
searching around for things like that.
Okay, so we have a couple of questions
all related to the panel 4 that we did
out of fund raising
and one question from Jay.
- Sounds American or UK.
- Jay.
- it doesn't say where he's from.
- Where ever you are from.
Here's your question.
How to raise finds for Non Tech Startup?
Well it's a-- the question is more
is it a growth story
that you'll looking at here?
You know it could be a growth story,
it could be Non Tech.
Often times the growth stories are Tech.
But the growth story could be non Tech.
If it's growth story
that is appealing
and we talked about venture capital
and business angel in the MOOC,
This could be your target audience
in the fund raising.
If you have a growth.
If you don't have a growth story
then the story is different.
Because then what would you do
with if you don't have a growth story?
People would not want to invest for equity
because the equity shares
are not increasing
- Anyway you might do crowdfunding.
- Anyway, you might like it.
Crowdfunding.
You've got friends and family.
Yeah.
Maybe if you have
some valuable stuff at home.
Maybe even your house
that you put mortgage
you can get bank loans,
and all sorts.
Its the typical, debt financing.
Speaking of Debt Financing
we had a couple questions on that one
from Glen in Lausanne,
and then one from Lucas
in Los Angeles.
What options exist for debt financing?
And what chances there
are the bank lending a startup money?
Okay, you're right in a sense
that banks in the MOOC in Week 4
we talked a lot banks and debt financing.
However, much less used,
it is possible for firms to issue debt,
to issue their own bonds.
That would be another option
but I would say for startup company
in general,
debt financing is going to be
relatively difficult.
Especially non-collateralized
debt financing.
While a big corporation
can issue a bond,
small companies are going to have
a very difficult time to do that
and going to a bank
is really the only option
and then the question
will banks lend to startups?
And the answer is very limited.
You have a checking maybe
or you can--
High interest rate,
highly collateralized.
Some startup use multiple credit cards
that they pushed to the max.
Then you get huge interests on that.
but still it's not the typical way.
Those are debts,
those are all debt financing.
-Exactly.
- So those are examples.
But it's not super common
I would say in that point of view.
Almira from San Francisco.
What to do if the management team
doesn't have a lot experience?
Yeah, how tricky.
Very good question.
You definitely want to expand
your management team,
you know over time,
and you do want search
for complimentary skills.
However, I think you also have
to be very careful with making sure
that you have a kind of a personality match
and kind of a vision match
so that you can work together carefully
and maybe even be more important
than the skills.
The skills, I mean,
somebody might be able to learn
complementary skills
or maybe branch out a little bit
from where they are,
but it's really hard if you have
an ethical problem with somebody.
Like you're not sure
if the person is a crook or not
to have them learn to be a good person
is probably less likely.
- Yes.
- So I would say --
So that's why I would say
that in general, you want to--
- Make sure that you get along.
- Make sure you get along.
And you have kind of advisers--
In many countries,
there will be consultants.
For instance in Switzerland,
the State,
the government has funds
that pay for consultants for start-ups.
They help to fill-in the gaps
in knowledge.
I think be honest with--
I like your question
because it means you are:
"I'm honest with my skills.
I'm honest with my lacking skills."
Because most entrepreneurs
often fool themselves
and trick themselves for saying,
"Well, we have all the skills,"
and then after time, they realize
they lack the skills.
Then it's too late
because they made errors
on the course of venture creation.
In short, be honest to yourself,
try to understand which skills you lack,
which skills are lacking in your team,
and if you want to raise funds
for a venture capitalist, be honest too
because they will find out
that these skills are lacking
from your team.
Sometimes investors
will also suggest people they can trust.
Exactly. Some have an HR function
in the venture caps,
some of the venture capitalists
And they will help you fill in the slots
because they know lots of people.
- So where are we?
- For the last one...
Besides a strong business plan
and good financials,
what are the soft skills required
to convince investors?
This one may also be
from Almira in San Francisco.
So if you think about the soft skills,
it's how the team works together.
It's one important soft skill.
Like when there are critical questions
for instance,
an investor pitch.
How does the team handle those questions.
How does the team react?
Do they react as a team
or is it like five people,
three people
who are like one man show,
one woman show.
Try to be a team working
in a cohesive manner.
The soft skills can also be sensitive
to customer feedback,
sensitive towards the feedback you see
from all kinds of stakeholders.
What other soft skills could be there?
I think some of the main ones
it's certainly some leadership skills.
- Right.
If you have employees,
it's a matter of motivating them
because you have to figure out
or realize that these people
also take risks
by working in startups.
The startup might not be alive
in a few years, a few months even.
So they take some risks
and be sensitive to their needs too.
- They need some --
- Have people skills.
Presentation skills in general,
interacting with people,
potential investors, etc.
It's good to have that down.
I think another question from Almira.
You ask lots of questions
which is great by the way.
Or maybe from someone else,
we don't have a name here.
How important is it to think about budget
during the planning phase?
I think it's- of course, I mean,
if money is no object,
then it's not important
to think about budget.
But if you are in any way
constrained by money,
then you really have to start thinking
about this straight away.
- So that means--
- Which is the case with most ventures.
Yeah. I mean you think about
the cash position that you're in.
We've talked about this
ad nauseam I think in Week 4.
- But you got to decide --
- Go and watch Week 4 again!
You know how long do you have
before you run out of cash.
Maybe they wrote the question
before they watched the week.
- It could be.
- And that you'll regret that day.
You have to know how long you have
before you run out of cash.
I think that's the budgeting aspect.
I mean, it doesn't have to be
this detailed thing,
you're looking at every single last detail.
But if you can gross up your costs
and you can take a look
at your cash position,
and you can figure out
your burn rate, as we discussed,
then I think there
is where you need to do it.
And I don't think that you need to go down
to the level of specific categories
and then an accounting software package.
You really need to think about
where your gross costs are coming from.
That's where the budgeting comes in.
I think that's pretty important.
Another Philipe.
Okay, this is from Philipe
in Bordeaux.
According to your experience
or intuition,
what could be a key element
to scale up a business
usually run on a service model,
like consulting or coaching?
avoiding a slow growth
and only by hiring more and more people?
What tools or what approach?
Please feel free to share your insights,
especially the none obvious ones.
(laughing)
- Yeah, that's a tall order.
- Only non-obvious ones!
You are setting the bar high
in terms of our capability
to answer questions here.
I think your question is right to the point
because we talked about scalabiity
in one of the weeks.
And a human capital driven model means
well you have to add new people
to be able to grow.
And while if you have
a more product-driven model,
like you do maybe on the internet,
you just add another server
and you cater to a million more people.
These are different scales,
scalability issues,
challenges that we face here.
But for the human capital driven model,
it's either you can think about
creating--
putting some of your offering
to a product offering.
- To a back-end.
You're moving,
packaging it somehow differently.
That might be
thinking out of the box
and you could be the first one
in your industry who does this.
- Yeah.
- Which is fine.
There's always pioneers
who are needed.
Or you might think about ways
to scale up
your human capital-driven model
by saying we do franchising?
Think about the audience immobilier
or the realtor... what that..?
- Yeah, real estate.
- Real estate agencies.
What they do now
in order to be able to grow,
they say we'll do a franchise model
and we are using that model
across the country.
And also in that sense,
try to think of ways that other people
will have to have the hiring problems,
management problems,
and you are copying in a way
your system.
That's another way of growing.
- Any other ideas?
- They also automate.
I mean if you go and look
to rent an apartment
then you're on a website,
and then that's backend.
They're not a person showing you around.
So real estate agencies in fact
have migrated a little bit
from the real, person-to-person,
low-scale businesses,
to some combination
of high touch person-to-person
and low-touch which is like a backend.
So there, you're searching on the backend,
and you're trying to narrow down
to maybe four of five,
and then you contact the person,
then the person shows you an apartment.
You may be able to do something like that,
a consulting type
or a coaching business.
Maybe there's a backend thing
that you can do that's automated
that reaches more people
and then you can come in
and give specific pointers
with on a person-to-person level.
- That was definitely not an obvious one.
- Okay. That's not an obvious.
I don't think that's obvious at all.
The next two questions come from France.
Two from Abdiram and Antoinne
Yuganne from Boulogne,
and the first one was from Paris.
They've asked the same question.
Is it possible to raise money
when you don't have any customers?
It's possible to raise money
even when there's no customers.
The problem is
you are going to be giving up more
of your company to get money
when you have no customers.
- Exactly.
- High risk situation.
High risk means higher potential reward
for the investor.
Put yourself in the investor's shoes.
if there's no proof of market,
would you invest in that?
There's some investor that will say,
"Well, we are joining
the ticket as Business Angels
and we're developing the prototype
and help you get the customers."
But that comes at a price.
But it's not impossible.
Quite to the contrary,
think about ways of maybe
even your potential first customers
can help you find
if they have a high need for that product.
There are lots of examples
like that out there.
- Great.
- Jay from San Juan.
What problems are associated
with raising too much money?
(laughter)
That's a good problem to have.
That's a very good problem to have.
Well, you have to be diligent
with your funds
and you should not waste that.
You might be tempted to waste your money
if you raised too much money.
if you're disciplined,
then there's really,
almost never a problem
with raising too much money.
But if you're throwing lavish parties
with the funds--
Then, this will backfire.
--then maybe it's not so great.
So you end up wasting your money
and it's not so great.
And if you think about
having too much money,
this buys you time
until your next financing rounds.
So be happy about it
because you don't have to think about
getting additional finances.
For some, more time, you know,
so for a little while.
Farras from Tyrone.
How can we start a startup
with profits from the beginning?
Okay that's a nice.
One of the best business
is when money just comes into Paypal
or the check comes into the mail
and you just go about
your daily activities
to how much money arrived.
I mean, if you don't have
an initial cash position
it's really hard to start.
Because you're going to have some costs
that you're going to invest in
to get your first product,
or service, or whatever.
It could be that you have
a pot of money to start with
then spend a little bit of that
and you immediately generate
some revenues.
It has to be a low capital
intensive business.
So you already own a computer
and you can use it to program something,
and you can make a phone app
or something like that
that people want to pay for,
then yeah, I mean it's doable.
But even then, you're going to spend
some amount of money at some time,
unless you say it's
'I already own the equipment.
It's fine. I'm not spending anything
out of my own pocket right now.'
It's kind of the boot-strapping idea
which i think is a good one.
If you can do it, It's always great.
It's just that usually,
you require more capital
because you have to pay people,
you have to pay for services,
you have to buy some more equipment,
and you have to spend
a little bit of money at the beginning
so it's harder to just come out
straight out of the gate,
profitable from the very beginning.
Then you can look it
from the customer side.
They will buy your product
if you have some kind of advantage,
vis-a-vis, the existing product.
And this advantage needs to be generated
somehow upfront.
So it's like you have to do
some investment.
The question is how much investment
do you have to do
based on the occuring status.
How far or how long are you already?
So from that perspective
it's tricky.
I think it's really--unless
you have invested a lot in the past.
You already paid for the equipment.
A software, or something like that.
You're not going to start a car company
and be profitable from the Day 1.
A pharmaceutical company,
there's just- that was just too capital.
- Exactly. Maybe some human capital.
- Maybe if you're lucky in software.
And service businesses way,
you can say,
well I do grocery shopping
for elderly ladies,
and you can do this
with your current skill set.
All of you have to do
is talk to elderly ladies on the street
or while they cross the street.
Right. I guess that's true,
you can walk with them,
but if you buy a car, you know,
then you're okay...(laughing)
Alright, let's move on.
What are the typical elements
to keep in mind
in order to generate trust in the project?
- That's coming from Geneva.
- Jaime in Geneva.
Sound Spanish or Portuguese.
Trust is a key element
in the new venture
because you have to do--
Creating a venture is social activity
and you are engaging with people
who give you funding,
all kinds of stakeholders -
with your customers,
potential customers,
with suppliers,
people who give you funding,
potential employees.
In order for them
to trust in your business,
they first have to trust you.
So you are for them,
the business.
It's a person-based trust.
It's not like company-based trust.
Well, the company is not there.
Face it, you know.
You better make sure that
they can trust you,
that you have a solid appearance
vis-a-vis your stakeholder,
and once they trust you,
they will trust later on the company
when it's there.
You are the face of the company.
You are the company.
And that was an issue
that we also discussed
in the crowdfunding part.
Which is that if you don't deliver
on your promises
that you make
when you're crowdfunding,
for example, you've promised them
delivery of a prototype
and you don't follow through,
then that's bad for the trust out aspect.
- Exactly.
- It would be really hard to win that back.
That can burn the trust
in your whole company
because that can go viral as well,
in forms, etc.
So, make sure that you follow up
on your promises
in the crowdfunding campaign.
The next question, from Gregory Ayecs
from Port-au-Prince.
- Hello to Port-au-Prince.
- In Haiti, wow!
Yes. Is it easier to raise capital investment
from angel investors
than venture capital firms?
And if yes, why?
Alright, we also talked about this
a lot in Week 4.
These are different sources
and they have different needs.
Is it easier?
I mean, you're usually not looking
for a venture capital investment
early, early on.
You might be looking
for an angel investor early on.
Early on, yes.
It's easier to raise money from an angel
than it is from venture capital.
Venture capitalists, in general
are not going to touch
an early stage business.
a really early seed stage business.
So later on, hard to say.
People might say, "Well,
you're capital demand is too high,"
and so an individual angel might just say,
"Forget it. I don't want to go in on that."
So it might be easier in some sense, later.
It just depends on lot of factors
that you just can't compare them.
They're not apples and apples.
Apples and oranges.
Something like that.
Base it on the stage
that you're in.
Exactly. I think stage
is on one of the keywords here.
Yeah. Okay, here's Marco
from Ljubljana, Slovenia
who is living in Abuja, Nigeria.
Excellent.
What would be the best advice
to entrepreneurs
concerning money management?
I think the best advice is that
you look at the money in your company
like the air that you have to breathe.
It's so vital.
If you run out of money,
your run out of air to breathe.
And also cash flow management
is of vital importance.
Monitor your cash outflows,
and monitor your cash inflows.
Try to also analyze them.
Why does money come from
a certain set of customers?
Why do they spend more money
on your products
and others for instance,
why do they do repeat purchases?
So try to understand your money outflows,
your money inflows.
Get a good grip
on your money management,
your cash flow.
- Because it is the air that your breathe.
- Perfect.
Gregory again
from Port-au-Prince,
another question from you.
Should I raise some more money
than I need and why?
That's related to the question
we had before.
- Yeah.
I think it's always try to raise a bit more.
First, investors might cut your wishlist,
and second, it buys you time
until you have to raise funds again.
That buys you time
to actually start working
and keep on working
on your company,
and getting your product out,
talking to customers, etc.
It depends on your revenues
and cost streams.
Your costs are always
going to be constant
I mean, they're always
going to be there.
Your revenues might be coming in
every once in a while.
If there's a slight delay
in your revenues,
then you might up spending more
than you thought you are going to.
I think the general rule of thumb
is people want to give money,
they want to make investments
in businesses
that don't need investments.
So I think that's the -- yes.
If you can get more than what you need
any moment in time
but don't burn it
as we said in the prior question.
Then the next one is interesting.
Who would you say
is the Marco Polo of our time?
So if you watched the Week 5,
last segment,
the last two minutes,
you know who the Marco Polos
of your time are.
(laughing)
- Go watch the end of Week 5.
- It starts at 5:18.
- The very last second.
- Then we give this away.
But give it-- second to those guys.
In every country, you will probably have.
This is the global MOOC
I would say that there is not--
You can always think about
the big characters that we have
in entrepreneurship
Without telling the names,
each of you has names in mind.
Think about Elan Vasco,
Steve Jobs, whatever.
Generally, it's like--
I think entrepreneurship nowadays
is a very democratic and pervasive
and a much encountered phenomenon
across the globe.
So each and every country
has its Marco Polo's.
Each and every country has its
adventurers who...
Risk any curse.
Risk-takers who embark
on their entrepreneurial journey .
Of course these big examples,
these well-known examples are inspiring.
But there are lots of entrepreneurs
who are doing it on a smaller scale,
who are doing something
extremely innovative,
They deserve a lot of respect too
just because we don't know about them
and read about them in the news.
They are fantastic entrepreneurs
that run great companies
and I think they deserve
a lot of admiration too.
So, a long story short,
yes, these people exist,
the new Marco Polo's,
but on the other hand,
their entrepreneurship
is a much bigger phenomenon.
The secret will be revealed
in the last segment of Week 5.
Question 9: Zierch Itoki
from Yaound, Cameroon.
I have one point to you.
Don't ask these long questions.
This is like eight lines.
Turning idea into value
has always been my passion. Great.
I always told myself that it is better to
deploy your potential and passion
than just to be employed.
We can agree to that.
That wasn't the question.
But in our country,
it's very difficult to put together passion
and real possibilities.
In my country, young people
are very interested
about creating tech ventures,
but our critical questions
are always returned.
Is Africa really ready for Tech ventures?
I think they skipped a line here.
Which types of tech ventures
for whom Africa is ready
to work on for good profits?
Which type of tech ventures
work in Africa, in short?
So you've been...we've been to Africa.
What can I? I'm hesitant
to give advice.
To make such prognostications
about the entire continent of Africa.
But I have traveled around Africa a bit
and I visited different parts.
I was able to observe
co-working spaces,
and startup hubs,
and I see that tech ventures
are starting to take off
even in Africa.
And yes, you have to take
into consideration the fact
that not every single person
is going to be
"internet connected" all the time.
So the infrastructure maybe
is a little bit less
than what we will be used to.
But that doesn't mean
that there's no possibility.
Some of those
are interesting opportunities for people.
And if you want some, as an inspiration,
go to this website, My African Startup.
There are a lot of examples on there.
And then Google sums up
some startup competitions.
Yeah, I saw a lot of great examples.
Software products, apps,
systems for monitoring inventory
in factories.
Systems where it would tell people
the right time to plant crops
based on small chips
that will detect the weather conditions
and knowing what kind of seeds
are supposed to be planted,
and then send an SMS,
"okay, now is the time to plant."
So that's a tech startup too.
There's a lot of exciting things
going on in Africa.
I agree, you should be passionate about it
and I think if you look around
you're going to find some things
that you'll be able to match up
your interests
will some latent needs
that we don't realize that we have yet.
- So keep on pushing Zierch.
- Yeah keep going Zierch.
What's your favorite example
of viral marketing?
Can it be done tastefully?
(laughing)
I know my favorite example
of viral marketing.
Tell your favorite example.
My favorite example
is MCI Friends and Family.
It's not a recent business, right?
This is the thing on the phone
long distance service in the 1980s.
- When he was young.
- Yeah.
I don't know if I was even
young back then.
Okay. I was younger
in the 1980s.
They'd call you
and they would offer a discount
if you and your friends and family
had worn the plan, the MCI plan.
And so people would give the names
of their relatives
to the person who's calling
on the phone, to the operator
and they would take them
and they would get discounts.
And that created a list.
That was a very early, early on
viral marketing campaign.
So for me, that's a very
interesting example.
And actually in our forums,
on the Coursera forums
there are some very nice examples here.
I think this was
a very humorous discussion
that the people had on there.
How much time is it okay
to spend on building my product?
So that's one of these questions
that is of course related
to a minimum viable product.
It's like a question, "How big is a fish?"
Yeah (laughter).
There's small ones,
There are big ones.
It depends on the product of course.
Some products, you can do
a minimum viable product
because your customers actually
will be able to give you feedback.
But with other products,
especially oftentimes B2B setttings,
business to business settings,
your customers don't want to work
with a minimum viable product.
They want to have the full proof,
the fail-proof version.
So it really depends
on your target segments.
There is no one single, good answer.
Of course if you can test
your products' attractiveness
and get feedback from the customers
with a low-key, minumum version,
go for that
because you're not wasting money.
- Front-end, very nice.
- Exactly.
If you have contacts
even in a business B2B setting,
you might be able to do
a front-end and get feedback.
But I think the more interesting question
is how much time did you have for
before you run out of cash?
Then that's going to determine a lot.
Try and go as fast as you can.
But remember it's going to cost you.
I think that's part of the--
maybe just underlining
this comment a little bit.
What is a good idea?
Is it one that is more profitable,
more innovative,
more available, or more useable?
- It's like a multiple choice question.
- Right.
- You're testing us.
- They're giving us a quiz now.
I think the best idea is an idea
where your customers
are willing to pay you.
Presented more than once in the MOOC.
You don't create a business
for creating a product.
You create it for creating a customer.
So from that perspective,
think about your customers.
Think about what your customers want.
If they are willing to pay
for your product,
for the functionality in your product,
for the benefits of this product.
This actually brings us
to the final question.
It says, "You say, 'customers
do not buy features, they buy benefits.'
What does this mean?"
Yeah. Basically, what this is referring to
is that the customers don't care
about the features per se.
All they care about is
how they can use it.
Is it valuable for them?
Does it save them money?
Does it save them time?
Does it meet their need?
And so having an extra feature,
what we're talking about
a little bit before hand,
one idea is like a battery.
You're changing a battery on a phone.
That's kind of like a feature.
It's a replaceable battery.
That's great. That's a feature.
But that's not really
what the customer wants.
The customer wants a long battery life.
The customer wants the phone
to go a very long time.
So maybe that feature helps
what the customer wants
because they can carry spare batteries
or something like that,
then thus giving them more time.
But you got to focus on the part
that the customer wants,
not the part that bells and whistles
that you add,
unless it solved the problem.
And that's quite important
with the marketing campaign.
Because you could say,
"This phone or camera
can replaceable-made batteries,"
and I was like...
What the customer wants--
the customer only understands
when you say,
- "With this phone you can --"
- talk for five days!
- That's what he cares about.
- Right.
So that was already all the questions.
Yeah. I think that's basically
the questions for this week.
Thanks for watching the MOOC's
and for sending in the questions.
Some of them will be handwritten.
We'll send you
some handwritten responses.
Exactly. To make this also
moving back to the old world.
- So thanks very much.
- Thanks for joining us.
Thanks for joining us.
See you back in MOOC-land.