Hello Ladies and Gentlemen.  Welcome to the
electrotechnique 2 course.
Throughout these different lessons
we will study three-phase sinusoidal rating circuits
as well as all the theory that will allow the understanding of transitional effects
in electrical networks
In this first lesson
we shall give a general
introduction on networks
how, with a few examples,
we can produce electrical energy
in particular here with
a synchronous generator, motor or
anything else
linked to some form of electromechanical conversion.
I will start here with an example.
An example where you can see the stator of a turbine.
This turbine can be rotated due to several effects.
Heat and steam, essentially, a steam engine
Or a hydraulic turbine, where we
rotate the turbine using
water pressure or we can also use
a wind turbine, or a nuclear power plant.
You can see here the size of such a stator
that shows you that to currently
generate Europe's electrical grid
it is necessary to have
increasingly bigger generators.
Here you can see the the generator of
the Marèges Dam in France.
Another example of
gigantism
is shown in this photo,
you can see in one of the
hydroelectric power plants of Itaipu, Bresil
one of the biggest hydroelectric
power plants in the world.
The rotor of this machine, with
around the stator, the staff that
allowed the construction of
this power plant.
We can see here the size
of the workers compared to the
size of the rotor that you can see here
being placed by
an overhead crane.
This is quite exceptionnal
for the Itaipu Dam
This allows the supply of electricity
to a large quantity of households
and thus a large part of the country.
Let's go back to Switzerland
We have here two typical examples of a grid
or grids, in the case of Switzerland.
On the left you have the
Grande Dixence Dam, in Valais
famous for the length of its lake
but also for the hight of its wall, one of
the tallest in world
and on the right you have the Emosson
Dam in Valais which is an arch dam.
These two dams
have the particularity of producing,
both, electrical energy
by
accumulating water and finally by using
the waterfall, pressure
and water flow
to rotate the generator downstream
but these two dams
do not supply electrical
energy at the same frequency.
We will see
that the Grande Dixence Dam
helps provide the grid
that can be called "urban"
available for everybody, in other words
at a frequency of 50 hertz
while the Emosson Dam on the
right only supplies
16 2/3 hertz, a second parallel
grid in Switzerland, used for
the Swiss Federal Railways,
the SBB's, grid.
So we have, in Switzerland, different
dams that are dedicated to either
the urban grid at 50 hertz, or
the SBB grid
for transports at
16 2/3 hertz.
How does a hydroelectric power plant work ?
You have here a sectional view
of a standard power plant
On the left, there is the accumulated water
the wall that retains this water
mass
and finally
a water collum
or penstock
that brings water, in this case, pressurized
at very very high pressures
which allows us
to have a very high flow rates
and rotate a propeller
a turbine, we shall see later
different types of turbines
connected here to an alternator,
generally a synchronous machine
which enables
the conversion of the mechanical power given by
the water flow into electric power
and the rotation speed of the rotor here
enables a very precise control of the frequency
injected in the grid.
Afterwards, a distribution system
must be organised to bring
this energy to the end user.
Here are several examples of turbines
in particular
for the first, the Pelton wheel,
these turbines function in the following
way, they are logically
realised using small cups
wherein in fact, the injector
with pressurised water arrives
hits the cup and
rotates the turbine.
You have here different shapes
of cups
which more or less allow
to control the wear that there is here
which can be relatively high
if the water is not perfectly
free of impurities
or here also, another Pelton wheel type
turbine
There are also other types of
turbines, we won't go into
the details here
but, on the left you have a Francis turbine,
on the right a Kaplan turbine
that are used for different
types of power plants
Run-of-the-river power plants
or other types of power plants
where the water flow
can be variable or for example
control of the tides to also
produce electricity using the
back and forth
of the tides.
A relatively new factor in the
past ten year in our countries
is the usage of wind with wind turbines
and therefore more and more wind
turbines are now placed in Europe
with a peculiarity compared
to dams.
Dams enable us
to debit water on demand
and thus, produce energy on demand
whereas in the case of wind turbines
the electricity producer is always
tributary to the local wind where
the wind turbine is placed.
Therefore behind all this
is an analysis for the energy storage
for when the wind occurs
to enable it to be distributed
at the time of usage
at the right time, at the right place.
In the Nordic countries, Denmark in
particular, there is a high
sensitivity to now use
wind farms.
You have here offshore wind farms
in the North Sea. Another farm here,
the London Array
where you can see the sea being
literally covered by
wind turbines and you can also
see the size of the turbines with
the small boat that is present here
on the sea
and you can see that the diameters can
reach several tens of meters
to generate, to
produce this energy.
Of course, we must
connect all of these wind turbines
on dry land
to be able to tap into this energy and
afterwards redistribute it to the end user
you have here another photo of the
North Sea that shows you better
the dimensions of a wind turbine
compared to a boat
and in the
most recent improvements
made on wind turbines
there are direct drives that
were implemented
where the synchronous machine,
in other words the generator, is
directly incorporated inside
the wind turbine itself.
Therefore, we greatly save
energy
by eliminating a gear train that
would be placed between a generator
placed at the bottom of the wind
turbine and the propeller at the top
Thus, wind turbines are
increasingly produced in the following way
with a direct drive
therefore, the generator is
directly
connected to the propeller.
Let's not forget nuclear power plants,
even if
two thirds of the energy in Switzerland
is produced by hydroelectricity
we still have nuclear power plant which
also allow the production
of electric energy using the same
system.
A nuclear power plant,
using nuclear fission,
heats
water
and it is then used just like a
steam engine to rotate
a generator of the same kind
that you could find
in a hydroelectric power plant.
With, however, a major disadvantage
compared to a hydroelectric power
plant, the regulation of the energy.
The regulation in a
nuclear power plant can only
be done
very slowly.
The fission reaction being
implemented over several days and
thus cannot be
changed or modified
significantly
in a few minutes.
In the case for hydroelectric
installations
it is possible to start, or stop them
extremely fast
since we have control over the water
falling directly on the Pelton wheel
and thus the alternator.
In conclusion
we can see that there are several
ways of generating electric
energy in a grid by using a
synchronous motor. The first way
that we saw is the hydraulic force
through a dam
the accumulation of water, a turbine
is then directly connected to the grid
wind power which enables the
conversion of energy from wind
the wind's mechanical energy
Steam engines whose heat
can be produced either by
coal plants
or gas or nuclear plants
and yet a number of other elements
for which we do not want
to go into details here.