Hello
In this second lesson
we will focus on the
generation of a polyphase system
and define the different elements
that charecterise
the idea of having a polyphase system
We will then after a
brief introduction
describe these polyphase systems,
define what a polyphase
system is
and show several examples and
end on a conclusion.
Polyphase systems are
in fact a set
of a certain number of values
Thus, we can define a polyphase system
as the set of m values
of voltage or current.
Further more, the definition of a
polyphase system of these m values
is that they
all have the same frequency
Naturelly
in a sinusoidal manner
Further more, if we now wish
to characterise this system and
give more descriptors, we can
say that a polyphase system
will be symetrical or
balanced
if the effective value (RMS) of the values are equal.
We will now also define the order
of succession of the phases
this order, we shall call it "k"
this order of succession of the phases
will also allow us to get
the corresponding
phase shift angle
between the different voltages or values
of the polyphase system.
In order words, this phase shift
will be equal
to this order, k, multiplied by 2π/m
m being the number of values
of the polyphase
system.
Will shall see further on that generally
we will focus
on a three-phase
system
but that it is possible to have
networks of polyphase systems of
2, 4, 5, or even more phases.
Another interesting element is to
define
the order of succession of the phases
or in which direction
this succession happens.
Thus, the phase change
will allow us to define the
forward system or the
reverse system.
First of all, the forward system will
be defined
as the succession of phases
in the negative trigonometric
order
Logically, the reverse system
will then be in the
forward trigonometric order.
We shall now see an example
that allows us to show
different polyphase systems
and what is
their succession order at this moment.
Before that, I will show you
a simple diagram
that illustrates two
voltages, you have here
U2 in a temporal manner
and, another voltage
U1
phase shifted compared to U2.
I remind you that this temporal
diagram
can be represented in the
complex plan by vectors
called phasors
and thus the U1 vector
aligned here
with the origin 0 of the omega(t)
find themselves
with this vector on on the real part
and U2 phase shifted
by π/2
finds itself here.
We can clearly see the order of
succession of the phases that goes from U1
to U2, first of all m is equal to 2
we only have 2 values
here
the order is equal to 1 since we have forward succession
order.
So here is an example
of a two-phase system, we can
call it two-phase because we have
only two phases and here
for example
2 currents associated
with a circuit to which this polyphase system
could be connected to.
We will also study a particular case
before showing two
more examples.
It's when the order of succession, k,
is equal to zero.
A system with an order k
equal to zero
means that
all the values are aligned on themselves
from the perspective of the phase.
In other words, all the phasors are
confounded with each other.
For this particular case
we will say
that the system
of order 0 is
homopolar.
You have here two examples of
polyphase system networks.
The first: you can see here that
we have 5 values, all
of equal RMS amplitudes.
So 5 values mean that we have
m = 5 phases.
the order of succession is 2, so
k = 2 in this
particular case since we have
first of all, U1 followed by U2
then U3, U4, and finally U5.
Thus for this system
k = 2.
You have here a classical example of what
I've mentioned earlier, the very
particular case
where all the values U1, U2, U3 are confounded on the same
phasor.
We shall thus call
this polyphase system "homopolar" and the order of succession
of the phases k = 0.
The generation of energy transmission
is more effective in polyphase
systems, it is
the reason why in the
majority of countries
a polyphase system
is used to transmit electric energy.
There is also another reason
that a polyphase system is used:
it is the fact that we can generate
a rotating field, thus generate
a electromechanical conversion by
using a polyphase system.
We can explain, demonstrate
that the generation of a polyphase system offers
the possibility of creating a magnetic
wave rotating inside
an electric motor.
Which is the beginning or basis
of mechanical generation in a system.
Another very important
element in polyphase systems
for those that are symmetrical,
in particular three-phase systems
is that the instantanous power in
these systems
is constant
Everything being symmetrical
the power being constant, we
can negate all vibrations linked
to a possible
mechanical alteration or mechanical
pulsation linked to a torque that
is created
in a manner
where there is a dissymmetry.
It is clear that in Europe
we have the necessity
of having a polyphase system, in
particular three-phase, that allows
an easy electrical, mechanical
transformation
for all objects requiring
the placing of an electric
motor
In conclusion
the system is polyphase if
we have m values of same frequency
we will say that a system is
symmetrical
is all the values and the phase
shift between these values
is equal.
And finally, we will call k
the order of succession of the phases
and in particular when it is equal to zero
we will say that the system is homopolar