Hello
After a general view of polyphase
systems
we will now focus and more
particularly study
symmetrical three-phase systems.
In this lesson
after a short introduction
we will define
what is a symmetrical
three-phase system
define what a line voltage is
a phase-to-phase voltage, and
similarly for currents, and
compute the relationship between
these different values.
And finishing
on a conclusion
We have here a
classical case of a three-phase
symmetrical system that we have
carried over on a phasor diagram
with
over here
the U1 voltage
U2
U3, in a forward system
with U1, U2 and U3 in the reverse
system that we
have seen
in the previous lesson.
So we clearly have here
for the order of succession of the phases,
a k equal to 1.
The number of phases equal to 3
and a symmetrical system because
the three values U1, U2, and U3
are equal
We can particularly see that
the order of succession of the phases
or phase-shift between the
different phases, is 120 degrees,
or 2π/3. We will now
be able to
characterise these 3 phasors and
write the equation
for the 3 phasors
in this symmetrical three-phase system.
First of all, the first phasor
U1
is equal to Ue^(jα).
I'm leaving the angle α on purpose
to allows us
complete freedom later
on
the position of U1 in the complex
plane. While on the drawing that
we have here, in both drawings
for the forward or reverse system
we have U1 with a null angle.
But let's leave, in a general manner,
α
thus
the other two phasors
U2 and U3
become
for the former
Ue^j(α - 2π/3), we have a
phase shift of 2π/3
and the
lastr one as well
also
also of 120 degrees. So here are
the three phasors that will be the basis
of our
symmetrical
three-phase system
Now if we observe
in a temporal manner
what these 3 values are worth
we will notice one thing.
Already on this phasor diagram
you can see it here
if I combine
these three vectors
I will return to zero.
This means that, at every
instant, every moment
these three vectors
are equal to zero when combined.
In other words, we can write
at all times
phasor 1
of the voltage, plus the second voltage,
and the third voltage
are always equal to zero.
Even more surprising
we can also do this
for the temporal part,
at all times
the three instantaneous voltages
are also equal to zero.
And this we shall now see
in the following graph
where we have represented the three
voltages U1, U2 and U3
in a temporal manner
What do we see?
We can see that
at any point of
time
that I choose, here, for example
on this curve, if I add
at the instant
I've marked with the red line
if I add U2 and U3
we can see that the 2 values are
exactly equal to
the value of U1.
The sum of these three voltages
is zero, as expected.
Let's take another instant
and once again, here, the sum of
these three
voltages of
U1, U2 and U3
we find zero.
We can again do
a last one, by really taking a
random line
the sum of this voltage
this voltage and this voltage will
give us exactly zero.
This system thus has an undeniable
advantage
being symmetrical
we will have some form of
equalization of the energy due to
the fact that the sum of these voltages
is always equal to zero.
We must now model
this source
and we will define some
number of values that are
linked
to a symmetrical three-phase source
that I present to you first of all
according to a model
that we give here in a wye setup
We can see that
our three voltages presented
previously, are represented by
sources, here, U1
U2
and U3
that they are all connected to
each other through a common point
and that we have three
outputs, so we can see, of the
voltages that we call lines.
We will define, on these lines
different values.
First of all, we name
these lines by letters
that allow us
to navigate later on with
a three-phase symmetrical source.
First of all, here
the R line
the S line, and the T line.
with the common point that we name
N, and that symbolizes the
neutral point.
About these different
values
we can say one thing, firstly,
U1, U2, U3 will have the same
effective value (RMS value)
will have the same frequency, and the three
will be phase-shifted
by 2π/3.
We can still characterize a certain
number of elements.
First of all, we can see
that there is a
voltage between the R line
and the neutral, the S and the neutral,
the T and the neutral
and that we can compute or measure
the voltages between R and S
directly, S and T or T and R
Well, with all these different values
we will need to name them in order
to navigate
and characterize these different
elements.
The first elements that we will give
are
the voltages between
the lines and the neutral.
We will have here
a voltage that we will call U_rn
and then we will have
U_sn
and finally U_tn
These are complex values
thus, we underline the values.
Another possibility, as I have mentioned
it earlier, is to take values
directly here.
We will thus have U_rs
we will have here
U_st
and finally
the value U_tr.
We will name the voltages that are
directly taken between the lines
composed voltages
By extension, we shall also call
them line voltages.
And for the voltages between
R, S, T and the neutral
We will call these
voltages
simple voltages.
Also by extension, we will call
these voltages
either simple voltages,
or phase voltages.
Three elements must still
be mentioned
once the voltages are defined
we can still define the currents that
flow
in the different lines.
First of all, we will define the three
currents
that are really flowing in the
lines
Ir, Is and It
and a fourth element can
still be mentioned
it's the return of current on the neutral
that we will name In
but we will quickly see
that this current In is often null if
the entire system is balanced and
symmetrical
the current will always be null
sometimes even, the neutral
will not be connected.
We will once again mention here what the
simple voltage is
or what the line voltage is
according to the diagram
that we've just seen about the three-phase
source.
First of all, the simple voltage
that we define as being
the measure of the voltage
or the definition of the voltage
between the R line and the neutral,
likewise for every
line.
In the same manner, the composed voltage
is defined this time directly between
the lines
namely
U_rs
U_st
and U_tr
Now, if we can calculate the relationship
between the simple voltage and
the composed voltage
We will simply apply Kirchhoff
on the previous diagram.
We then find
3 relatively simple
loop equations that are
U_rs = U_rn - U_sn
and similarly for the other two equations.
We will take this first
equation
and write, for this first equation
what is the result
of the subtraction of these two vectors
or these two phasors
By definition, we have,
U_rn
equal to Ue^(jα).
and we have U_sn
equal to
Ue^j(α - 2π/3).
We can then write
and bring out
Ue^(jα) for both
elements and finally write U_rs =...
We bring out Ue^(jα)
firstly, we have U_rn, from where
the 1 is issued
minus
and then the second part
so, e^j
and simply
-2π/3.
This being said
we can transform this
equation, now,
into a a+bj relationship, that will
gives us the following result
U_rs will be equal to Ue^(jα)
and that multiplies 3/2
plus
j * (√3/2).
By reconverting everything
in the form of a Euler type phasor
we then have
finally, U_rs equal to
√3U * e^j(α + π/6).
We recongnize here
Ue^(jα) which is the
simple voltage, and thus
the composed voltage
is actually √3 times
the simple voltage U_rn
that underlines it
with a phase-shift of
π/6.
We shall see that for the other three,
for other two line voltages,
it's exactly the same, thus
everytime
all of these values
are simply
raised by a √3 factor
compared to the simple voltage and
phase-shifted by a factor of π/6.
Essentially
we can write in a completely
general manner
that the line voltage
is equal to √3 times
the effective (RMS) value of
the simple voltage
By taking now
a diagram
in which we have
put all of these different
phasors
one after
the other in a complex
diagram
we will observe a certain number
of elements
first of all, we can recover
our three simple voltages
U_rn
U_tn and U_sn
We've aligned here the simple voltage
U_rn with zero.
You have here a circle
that defines the value of the RMS of the U grid.
If we apply, in this case in a
completely graphical manner
what we have done
earlier, meaning
U_rn - U_sn
we can observe and obtain here
a new phasor that is the
composed voltage U_rs
that we have just calculated.
We discover that
this value is
√3 times bigger than the effective (RMS) value of the grid.
or than the previous voltage, the simple voltage
and that
it is phase-shifted by π/6.
Similarly
the three composed
voltages will now form
a new symmetrical three-phase
system
where the amplitude is √3 times
greater than the simple voltages
and all of them phase-shifted by π/6.
It is the foundation of
every sinusoidal
three-phase symmetrical
system to have this relationship between
simple voltages and composed voltages.
I remind here the extremely important
expression that the line voltage
will always be √3 times
the simple voltage
In the most common type of domestic
power supply grid in Europe,
the modulus of the simple voltages is
generally normalized to
220 volts.
So, simple voltage
at 220 volts
generally, this 220 volts is more
often included between 220 and 240 volts
and can oscillate throughout
the year generally
Thus if we compute now
the composed voltages linked to
these simple voltages
we can observe that if we multiply the composed
voltage by √3
it is now at 380 volts
since it is 220 multiplied by √3
since we can have 220 volts version
and a 240 volts version
the composed tensions will oscillate
between 380 and 420 volts
Thus, in a three-phase system, we always
have available either a simple voltage
around 220 volts
or a composed voltage of
380 volts.
There is another way
of showing or modelling
a symmetrical three-phase source
Instead of using a wye circuit
like we've done previously
it is posisbly to show that
by connecting the source, here
U1, U2 and U3 in a delta
we also get R, S and T at whose
terminals we find
our three line voltages
and the line currents that
are flowing in an indentical manner
compared to our presentation
in a wye circuit.
The big difference compared to a
wye connection
is that here, in this schema there
is no common point, thus no neutral
and to bring up the neutral, it is
necessary to
construct
a system built using three very
high impedance resistors connected in
a mid-point that recreates
an artificial neutral.
In the end, the only important
element
is to create three
lines : R, S, T that will be
useful later for connecting loads
and thus, in the end, that our source
is connected either in a wye connection
or in a delta connection
this will make
or will have only little difference.
Thus, I advise you
for the comprehension of
the next part of this class
to keep a mental picture of this
wye connection that allows us to
more simply bring up
the common point of the neutral.
We still need to
mention a word about the current of the neutral
that is this connector that
recieves
the three lines so as to
recover the energy coming
from the load connected on R, S and T.
I will re-draw here, for a better understanding
the three lines R, S, and T
that exit our symmetrical
three-phase grid.
We have R, we have S,
we have T
we also know that there is a return
the neutral
that will allow us us to bring back
this energy
If now
we write here
the line current Ir
the line current Is
and the line current It
we can write that
once we have connected a R, S, T load
and a neutral current
using Kirchoff, it is possible
to write
this relatively simple equation
it's that the sum of the currents
Ir, Is and It
is equal to this neutral current
We will see
and we will demonstrate thereafter
that when these currents are
perfectly symmetrical, thus phase-shifted
by 120 degrees and of equal amplitude
the neutral current, as we've mentioned
it previously, will be null
To conclude
we have seen in this lesson
that a symmetrical three-phase system
is relatively simple
to study since
we only need to concern ourselves with
a single element everytime
and the others are simply
phase-shifted by 2π/3
we have defined the phase voltage,
the composed voltage
we have seen what the line current is,
that the sum of these line currents
gives us
the neutral current
and that the ratio between the composed voltage and simple voltage
is √3.
We will thus, in the next lessons
study the loads connected to this
symmetrical three-phase source