Hello, welcome to the 6th lesson,
dedicated to conversions between
wye and delta systems in a three-phase state,
We will see how to adapt a network to a charge
that we will be able to change to wye or delta, and adapt
to a network having a different voltage or how to convert
a wye set up into a delta set up.
In practice, if the sources are
generally connected in a wye set up
the user has two different choices for
the charge's coupling mechanism.
Either wye, or delta, and the switch between
the two lets for
a brief power reduction or an
adjustement to an electrical circuit
√3 times higher.
Thus, we can say that in practice
we have a wye connection
and that this wye connection can be
transformed
into a delta connection.
But, we can also have the opposite case and
switch from delta to wye.
We will now see three different cases
that will show us this possible adjustement from
one way to the other.
Here is the first case that we will study:
the power decrease
absorbed without changing the line voltage
nor the phase impedances.
We will see how the power will change during
the wye to delta circuit transformation
and we will see that the factor change
is equal to 3.
I have prepared a table here,
with on the left
all the values that we will analyse in the
wye
as well as these same values in a delta.
We will then start with the phase voltage,
which is equal to
the line voltage divide by √3 in a wye,
as we have already seen in the previous lessons.
In the same way,
this same voltage phase,
but this time in a delta setup
will be equal and confused with
the line voltage.
What is it with the phase currents ?
The phase current, by definition, the voltage phase
divided by the impedance Z
We can now replace the phase voltage by the line voltage
that we have just calculated,
this gives us U_l/(√3*Z).
For the delta setup,
lets calculate the phase current and
the phase current is equal to the phase voltage
divided by Z, simply in our delta
the phase voltage is equal to
the line voltage, and so
we get
the following result : the phase current
is simply the line voltage
divided by the norm of the
impedance Z.
Lets calculate now the ligne current.
The line current, I_I
is equal to the phase current.
It is a property of
wye systems, so by replacing this, since
we just found the value, it is the same
result as before:
line voltage divided by √3*Z
for this line current.
However, the line current in a delta system,
as we know,
is √3 times the phase current.
By replacing this, we get √3
times the line voltage
divided by the norm
of the impedance Z.
We want to analyse this impedance
and compare it between the two setups.
First of all, we will have
S that is, by definition, equal to √3 times
the line voltage, line current
that is equal to, by replacing the
line current
with the previous calculation,
simply
U_l^2/Z for a wye setup.
We do the exact same thing for the delta
by replacing, in the same way,
by definition, √3*U_l*I_l.
When we replace this, the √3*√3
is at the numerator and we find
3*U_l^2 divided by Z.
These two values, are then
three times
bigger.
So, without changing neither the line voltage
nor the charge
that we connect
when passing from one setup
to the other
the absorbed power
of a factor 3
which gives the user all sorts
of possiblities
to adapt the power or, for example,
to start a machine at a lower power
than that of its nominal rate.
We will now do a small example
of a charge that we take
symmetric with an impedance norm equal to 18 Ohm.
We decide that the electrical circuit's line
voltage is equal to 380 V in
this example with
cos(φ) = 0.8.
The active power, in delta, is
equal to
20 kW.
The question is now to know,
if we connect this charge in delta instead
of wye,
do we have a reduction by a factor 3
on the absorbed power ?
First of all, we calculate the line
current
in delta
and this line current is equal to √3 times
the phase current.
The phase current
is then
the phase voltage
divided by Z, which gives
√3*(U_ph/Z)
and the phase voltage
in delta is the line voltage
which is equal to √3*(U_l/Z).
The line voltage, just as the impedance norm,
are given in the example
so we can do the numerical calculation
and we get 36.6 A.
On the contrary, if we now want to calculate
this for a wye conversion, that we
often symbolise with Y
since it sounds like the letter Y,
which is equal to the phase current in this setup.
The phase current is equal to
U_ph/Z and the phase voltage in
a wye
is: U_l/(√3*Z).
We get 12,2 A. We can already see here
that the consumed current is
decreased by a factor 3.
We can then calculate the power in a wye
set up.
This calculation is relatively simple,
we use the definition
of the active power, namely √3
line voltage, line current
times cos(φ).
By replacing these
three elements that we have now,
either from the data
or from the calculations that we have just made,
we get 6.6 kW.
This is
equal to three times the
active power that
we had in a delta.
This can be written
in another way. This is equal
to the power
divided by 3, and shows the
adaptation possiblity
between a wye and delta setup.
The second case that we will
now study is the adaptation
to a higher network, without changing
neither the powers
nor the impedances.
This can happen when a machine has been designed
or calculated for a given network, and that by
changing continent or country,
we have a different network voltage
that we wish to adapt
to the machine of this new network.
Then, in the same way, I have created a
table that lets us compare
a wye or delta setup, and then we will take
the netwrok we have in Europe,
the classical network,
in a wye or delta setup, with a line
voltage of 380 V.
Lets imagine
our
phase voltage, that is equal to the line voltage
divided by √3 in a wye setup,
will be equal to 380 V divided by √3
namely
the 220 V that we usually see.
Lets admit that we want to connect our
machine on a
phase voltage, once again at 220 V,
but that will then be
our line voltage since we connect
the same charge in a delta setup. In such a setup,
as a reminder, the phase voltage is
equal to the line tension.
Our phase current, in the wye setup,
will be equal to
the phase voltage divided by the
norm of the impedance.
The phase voltage being equal to 220 V,
it is simply
220 divided by the norme of Z.
What about the phase current in a delta setup ?
Well, in the same way, it is
the phase voltage
divided by the norm of the impedance Z, and
we realise that it is exactely
the same thing.
This is what we hope for.
We hope, as said beforehand,
not to change the absorbed power
with the charge.
We can also be convinced by
calculating the apparent power that will
be equal to,
by definition,
three times the phase voltage,
times the phase current
and in both cases,
we will get three times
220^2 divided by Z, and if we look at
a delta setup, we will get
exactely the same thing:
three times
the phase voltage times the phase current,
which gives us  3*(220^2)/Z
Then, we see that the devices that work on
an old network
for example 220 V in a delta setup,
will be able to be used
on a modern network with 380 V line voltage,
providing that we pass in a wye setup.
The last case that we will study
is the replacement of the three-phase
charge to get, this time, the same power
when the line voltage does not change.
This time, we will change the impedance to
keep the power absorbed by the system.
In the same way, in the table
we will have on one side
all the values of a wye setup, and on the other
all the values
of a delta setup.
The calculation of the line voltage
is still done in the same way
but this time we start with the apparent power,
that I remind you
needs to be constant in our small example, S
and then we have a relation between the line current,
the apparent power and
the line voltage, in this way.
This ratio, or this equation, is strictly identical
in a delta setup.
We can then write that I_I is also equal,
in a delta setup,  to S/√3
times the line voltage.
For the phase current, now, we are starting to
have a certain habit
is equal to the line current in the
wye
setup
However, for this same phase current in
a delta setup
we have a ratio of √3
between the line current and
the phase current.
It is exactely the opposite for the
phase voltage, so here
the phase voltage
is equal to the line voltage divided by √3.
Whereas in the delta
setup
the phase voltage is equal to
the line voltage.
All this now lets us, by reassembling
these three element,
to write that
the impedance that we wish to get to
maintain and garantee a constant
absorbed power.
We will then write here that
Z
in a wye setup
that is equal to the phase voltage,
by definition on the phase
current
will be equal to the line voltage
divided by √3
times the line current.
We calculate exactely the same value,
Z
but this time for a delta setup.
We can write, by definition, that
it is the phase voltage
divided by the phase current,
and by replacing with
the elements that we have calculated,
(U_l*√3) / I_l.
What do we see ?
We see that
the ratio between Z in a delta setup
is equal to three times
Z in a wye setup.
The ratio can be seen here,
you have a
ratio of √3 in the
numerator
of the impedance in a delta setup.
It is at the
denominator for
the impedance in a wye setup.
The ratio between the two gives exactely
a ratio of 3
between these 2 impedances to get
the same power
when the voltage does not fluctuate.
We can even go further and
write that the norm
that we wrote before, as being
the norm in a delta setup equal
to three times the norm in a wye setup.
We can
show that this is also valid
for the complex value
which means that the complex impedance Z
the vector, is equal to three times
the complex
impedance Z in a wye setup.
And then, of for example, we have
a battery of capacitors,
this battery of capacitors has
a
reactance equal to 1/(cω).
We can write
that at this moment, by multiplying
by three
to get a battery of capacitors this
time in a
delta setup, times ω.
Then,
we can say that
the capacitance that needs
to be chosen
in a delta connexion mode
will be equal to the capacitance
of a wye mode, divided by 3.
The ratio 3
exists in this case.
We will now do an example,
to show you how this
can be done in a complete way
with a
complex
impedance and we will observe this ratio 3.
For this example, we will then take a
symetrical three-phase consumer, whose active power
is equal to 20 kW
and whose apparent power is equal to 30 kVa.
The supply voltage
of a line is equal to 500
volts.
We ask to calculate the
unknown impedance Z in a wye and delta setup.
Knowing that
we have this inductive system.
We then start with a wye coupling.
In a wye coupling, we can calculate
the apparent power.
We start by calculating S.
S is equal to √3 times the line voltage,
times
the line current.
We can then extract the line current
from this equation, which is equal to
S_l / (√3*U_l).
And that because, I remind you,
we are in a wye coupling.
It is also
the phase current.
So if we have a line current that is
equal to,
by definition,
500 V,
the phase current is equal to, numerically
in our case,
34.6 A.
We know that,
by definition, the impedance Z is R
plus j*x, and
we also have P, the active power,
that is equal to 3*R*I^2.
From there we extract
the calculation of the resistance that we
are looking for since we want to
discover R and x to completely
determine the impedance
Z
and we have
the active power consumed by
the circuit.
R is therefore equal to, by extracting
it from the previous equation,
R is equal P
divided by
three times
the phase current squared.
We have all the elements needed to calculate
this resistance, which is equal to 5,55 Ohm.
We can do, in the same way,
the calculation
of the reactive, and so of the reactance x.
Firstly, the reactive is calculated starting from
the fact that it is √(S^2-P^2),
which gives
the reactive Q
and we get
+22,36 kVAR.
I say +22
because we have
said previously, and it is given,
that the system is inductive, so the
reactive must be positive.
Then,
we also know that Q = 3*x*I_ph^2.
We can therefore determine x
by writing, in the same way, Q
divided by three times
the phase current squared,
namely
6,21 Ohm.
We then have Z,
to finish,
by substitution,
is equal to 5,55 Ohm
+ j*6,21, namely
8,33*e^j(48,2°).
To finish, our impedance
has been determined
thanks to this wye coupling.
Now in a delta coupling,
in a delta coupling, a certain number of
values will change.
We still have by definition that
the apparent power is equal to √3 times
the line tension, times the line current.
However, this time,
the phase current has a ratio of √3
with the line current.
We can then determine a certain number of
values from this starting point.
The active power is always calculated
from the Joules losses,
namely three times
R, times the phase current squared.
And then
3 times R
times the line current
squared, divided by √3*√3
that is 3
so finally R*I_l^2.
We can then say that
R, if we now want to choose and
calculate R, is equal to P
divided by I_l^2.
What is I_I worth?
We wrote it just on top here
S is equal to √3*U_l*I_l. S squared
is 3 times
U_l^2, times
I_l^2.
And we can then replace this here
which gives us 3*P*U_l^2 / S^2.
We have all the elements to calculate
and we get
16,7 Ohm.
We directly see that it is equal to
3 times the resistance
that we had previously
with the wye coupling.
We can of course do exactely the same
thing, by calculating with
the reactive x
that is 3*x*I_ph^2
et we will get x = Q/(I_l^2).
Finally, we will discover that this is
also equal to
18,6 Ohm.
We obtain our new impedance Z,
this time in
a delta setup and coupling,
which is equal to
16,7 + 18,6j,
namely
25*e^j(48,2°).
We see that
this
impedance in
delta is equal to
3 times the impedance Z that we have
just calculated
preivously in a wye setup.
We also remark that these two vectors are
collinear, the angle is
exactely identical,
the norm is just multiplied by three,
as we have seen here with the change
between R
and x
that generally have a ratio of 3
between the wye and delta setups.
To conclude, we have seen three
different modes that show you the
possibility when changing from a
wye or delta coupling, to either adapt
the charge to a different network
or to modify the power, or even
to adapt the charge in a change of mode
from wye to delta
all the while keeping
exactely the same absorbed power
with an identical network.