Hello, during the previous lessons, we saw what transient states
are and how they are mathematically defined
We have also seen the fundamental physique principles that governs
the ideal components R,L
and C.
A few applications showed the importance of those transient states.
In reality the elements L and C can't
exist alone, they are always combined
by a parasite resistor
a resistor also has a parasite capacitor and inductance.
During this lesson, we will elaborate a resolution method
to find the step response
of a circuit including elements R,L
or C
subject to a jump.
We will see, first of all, the mathematical fundamentals to solve
differential equations
derived from this method.
The resolution method that we propose, conist in three main blocks
First of all, the processing of the circuit sketch.
Lets start by sketching.
Then we define all the values that
are on the drawing.
Then reduce it, if necessary
write down the voltage and current
equations
that is to say, the characteristic equation of each element
R, L, C.
And finally
apply the Kirchhoff laws, that is to say, the laws of the bounds between
each element
derived from the formatting of the equations as the sum of
derivatives.
The resolution of the differential equations
is done by
the search of the solution of the homogeneous  equation
the search of the particular solution
in steady state, a settled state
and the sum of both
which leads us to the general solution.
The third block consists in defining the integration constants
that is to say, the expression of the impossibilities
either a current jump in an inductance, or a voltage jump of a capacitor terminal.
Finaly, we solve the whole system
to lead to the final expression of the solution.
The differential equations that we will deal with, are
linear differential equations
until the second order, and with constant coefficient.
The differential equation is chararcterized by the sum of
the derivatives of an unknown function x
with constant coefficient.
We can write a such equation, wher
the coefficients
a_j
are constant coefficients
and the function f(t)
is as function of time
which is known.
The solution is
the sum of two partial solution.
The homogeounous solution
that is given by
a_0*x
plus a_1
dx/dt
plus a_2
d^2x divided
by dt^2
is equal to 0.
And the particular
solution that satisfies
the equation (1).
The solution of the homogeneous equation is a sum of exponential functions
of the form
x_s(t)
is equal to A times
the exponential
of λt.
By replacing
this expression, this homogeneous solution
whose sum of derivatives of first order is equal to 2, it comes that
after simplification
by e^(λt)
a such equation has n solutions, here, n is equal to 2
n solutions λ_j
real or complex. The final solution of the homogeneous equation is therefore
given by:
For the particular solution, its form is
directly linked to the function
f(t).
We will deal with two particular cases that are
specially useful in this application and that are
easy to solve.
It is
first of all
a constant function
f(t) = K.
It is here
a constant continuous voltage of a power supply.
A second kind of
time function.
For a constant function the particular solution is
constant
and given by
x_p
where the p stands for particular and is equal
to K
on a_0.
For a sinusoidal  or cosinusoidal function, the solution is
a function of the same kind.
The resulting solution is the sum of the homogeneous
solution
and the particular solution.
Which gives us:
The integration constants
a_j and λ_j
that are given by the initial conditions that are linked
to physical impossibilities
depending on inductances and capacitors, which mean
that we can not do a current jump in an inductance
and that we can not perform voltages jumps of the capacitor
terminals.
Applying these conditions lead to a linear system
of equations allowing to define the coefficients a_j.
We will now see a few properties of the exponential.
An exponential with a negative exponent
has one of the two following forms:
f_1(t)
is equal to A times
e^(-λt)
or
f_2(t) is equal
to A times 1 minus
e^(-λt).
If we consider the first function f_1(t)
and that we define its initial
slope it is equal to
th derivative of f_1(t) as function of time
at the time t=0
and this is equal to -Aλ.
The intersection point
between the asymptotic value, which mean the intersection of the time axis
and its tangents, is given by the following equation.
0 = 1 - λ*t_asy
or
t_asy = τ = 1/λ.
And this, is the time constant, that we call τ (tau).
The graphical representation, gives us
the following curve
as function of time
the function f_1(t), which is
an exponantial
but if we consider the slope origin
its intersection with the asymptotic value
which is the time axis
is done
at the time τ.
For the second function
that we have considered
in the time domain
here, the equation is very simple,
the equation of the tangent is very simple because it goes through the origin.
It's simply the slope
the intersection with the asymptotic value, which is, the stabilized and permanent
value of the
system
is done at the time
t = τ.
If we picture a such equation
like, for example,
u(t) = A*(1-e^(λt)) and we vary the first
parameter A
we can see that
the parameter A
influences the amplitude
of the signal.
We vary A, we see that the amplitude of the signal
decreases, increases with A.
Using the same equation
and this time
by varying the parameter A
we see that
the influence of this  λ  parameter doesn't effect the amplitude anymore
but the
speed of the rising of the curve
till the asymptotic
value.
And it's for this reason that the λ is associated
with the time constant.
During this lesson, we have seen the method to describe
mathematically
a circuit, and how to put it under an equation form, in this calculation purpose and the evolution of
the current or the voltage at a particular spot of the circuit.
Once the solution found, we have analyzed this solution and brought out
some noteworthy elements
as the slopes at the origin
the asymptotic values, or particular points.
During the following lessons, we will apply those methods on
circuits of the type RL or RC.