Hello, during the first lesson, we have laid the theoretical bases of the
resolution of a problem in transient state
we will move to a concrete example with several components.
We have seen how a resistor, capacitor or an inductance
behaved alone, subject to a voltage or a current jump.
In reality the elements
L and C can't exist alone, they are always combined with a parasite resistor
and even a resistor always has a parasite capacity  or inductance.
We will see a method that deals with these combined elements.
The example that we will see, during this lesson, is a
circuit with a resistor in series with a capacitor.
It's the classical and widespread charge or discharge of a
capacitor. In other words, stocking electrical energy
in a capacitor, or an accumulator or even a
supercapacitor.
Let the following circuit, made of a resistor in series with a capacitor, that we will
switch on a constant voltage supply U.
We begin by writing down all the values in the circuit, which are
the voltage
at the terminals of the resistor U_r, the voltage
at the terminals of the capacitor
U_c
knowing that the loop is traveled by a current I
in this direction.
First a condition is placed,
at the time t = 0
there is a residual voltage in the capacitor U_c, that is equal to
U_0, it is the initial condition of the circuit.
We then write the characteristic equations of each element
which means that U_r
is equal to
R*I
and U_c is equal to
1/C
times the integrale to -infinity to t
of i(t)dt
that we can express by seperating the integral from -infinity to 0 and from 0 to t.
Knowing that the part from -infinity to 0 is in reality, the initial condition of the capacitor, that we can write U_0.
So this is equal to U_0 plus 1/C, multiplied by the integral from 0 to t
of i(t)dt.
We can now write the binding equation, which means that, on the single loop
of the circuit, we apply Kirchoff's theorem, and we have therfore that u(t)
which is here
u(t)
is equal to U_r + U_c.
And, this is equal to U
for t > 0, which means, after the interlock.
We can develop this,
in the form
U is equal to R*i plus
1/C multiplied by
the integral of i*dt.
We derive in this equation
and we get that
0 is equal to R multiplied
by di/dt
+
1/C times i.
We see that this is a first order differential equation
whose solution is given by i(t) is equal to
A*e^(λt).
With A and λ being integration constants.
Once this general solution is found, we have to define the integration constants.
We rewrite the equation
which is the general solution, i(t)
is equal to Ae^(λt)
and its derivative
that stays an exponential
and that is equal to
λ, the internal derivative, multiplied by the equation
itself, the exponential itslef.
A, λ,
remaining to define.
We proceed the following way, we replace i and  (di/dt) in the binding equation
which gives us
R times (di/dt)
plus 1/C times i is equal to 0
and this becomes
R multiplied by λ times
Ae^(λt)
plus 1/C that multiplies i(t), it is Ae^(λt).
This is equal to 0.
By dividing by this term, we get
Rλ
is equal to -1
divided by C
or, express differently
λ is equal to (-1/RC)
and this is equal to 1/τ
the time constant.
To define the constant A
we proceed the following way, we solve the equation at the time t=0.
U_c is equal to U_0.
The initial condition for t=0.
By rewriting the equation at the time t=0,
we get U_c
is equal to U
minus R_i, and this is equal to the interlock, at U minus
R*A, exponential of
-t/RC
this term
is equal to 1 at the time t=0
so it comes that
U
minus R*A
is equal to U_0
or, the term A
that is equal to U
minus U_0 divided by R.
We have defined the two integration constants
and can therefore, now, write the equation for the current that is equal
to i which is equal to
A, which means U-U_0
divided by R
multiplied by the exponential of
-t/λ, which means -t/RC.
We will notice that the permenant solution
is equal to 0
simply because the current in the capacitor in DC is equal to 0.
i is equal to U
minus U_0, divided by R, multiplied by
e^(-t/RC).
We see that, for
t=τ
well, there is a a current depreciation
in a ratio
1/e
Why? Because i
at the time t, is equal to τ
this is equal
to (U-U_0)/R
multiplied by
e^(-1).
This current equation is pictured
in the time domain
by this slope here
a zero  current before
the interlock
and a current that does an instant
jump
like this
this is i_c(t).
We can calculate the tangent at
the origine
and calculate what is its its intersection with the stabilized value
which means, in our case, the axis t.
This intersection is done at the time t=τ
indeed, we can write that the derivative
of the current at the time t=0
di/dt
is equal to (U-U_0)/R
that multiplies (1/-RC)
multiplied by e^(-t/τ).
At t = 0,
What do we have?
We have that the derivative, di/dt
is equal to -(U - U_0)/R^2*C
The equation of this tangent
is given by
i'
which is equal to U
minus
U_0 divide by R
it's the value
at the time t=0
minus the slope, time t.
Let's calculate, now, the evolution
of the voltage on the terminals of the capacitor.
We have the equation at the terminals
of the capacitor that is given
U_C that is equal
to the initial condition
U_0
plus 1/C
multiplied by the integral from 0 to t
of i*dt.
By replacing the value of i, by the found solution
we get the following equation, U
minus U_0
divided by R
multiplied by the integral from 0 to t
of e^(-t/RC)*dt
By solving this
we get U_0
plus
U - U_0
divide by RC.
We calculate its antiderivative
that is the same value with
the internal derivative
taken from 0 to t.
And this
all calculations done, gives us, U_0 minus
plus U minus U_0
that multiplies
e^(-t/τ)
which means that RC, minus 1.
Written in another way, which gives us
U_0
plus U minus
that multiplies
1 minus e^(-t/RC).
If we picture this slope in the time domain
we get the following thing
U_C(t), as function of time
we start with an initial value
U_0
no matter what happened before,
the moment of the interlock
the value of the capacitor is at U_0, and this curve
this exponantial, has this appearance.
A jump that is equal to an asymptotic value
U-U_0, and a tangent
that cuts the asymptotic value
at the time t=τ
is equal to RC.
That's it, we have followed all the steps
to calculate the evolution of the current I_c(t)
and the voltage U_c(t)  for a RC circuit in series.
We have seen the noticeable elements as the slope,
the asymptotic values and particular ponts.
We note that we didn't calculate the voltage
drop at the terminals of the resistor
because it is very easy to calculate, it is simply R multiplied
by the current I that we have calculated.