Hello, in today's lecture, we will
study the RL circuit in series.
This is an important subject as
the circuit is omnipresent in the field
of motors, transformers or power electronics.
As for RC circuit, we will first
deal with the case
where we apply a continuous voltage jump
to a circuit
then, we will apply to a circuit
a voltage jump
sinusoidal
Let's start with a continuous source
We consider the following circuit, composed of a resistor in series
and an inductance, in series,
switched at time t=0
under a supply voltage U.
We write
all the values according to the circuit
First of all
the current in the circuit
unique loop i(t)
the voltage across the resistor
that is equal to U_r
the voltage across the inductance
equal to
U_I
and the total voltage
across both elements which is
equal to u(t)
To deal with a general case, at time t=0
We will consider that
the current in the inductance is already equal to I_0
at t=0
i
is equal to I_0
We then write all the characteristic
equations of each
element, which means that for U_r
this is equal to R*i
and for U_I
the voltage across the U_l is equal to
L * (di/dt).
These are the characteristic
equations.
Then we consider
the loop and write the binding
equations
Which means that
u
is equal to
U_r + U_l
is equal to U
At time t = 0 and after (t>0).
Therefore, this binding equation
is written here
as R*i plus L
di/dt
is equal to U
We've seen that such equation
has
an homogenous solution, of
exponential type
and permanent solution I_p, equal to
for the settled state
U/R, the inductance
doesn't see any current fluctuation,
the voltage
across the inductance is equal 0,
and therefore, the current
in the loop, is equal to U/R.
This leads to
the general solution that is equal to I_s + I_p,
meaning that i
is equal to A
times e^(λt)
plus
U/R
that is, after derivation,
equal to λ, the internal derivative of the exponential, times
the same exponential
times the constant A.
If we substitute these equations of i
and di/dt, we obtain in the
binding equation
to find the constant λ,
that R_i + L *(di/dt) is equal to
U
substituting
i(t) and di/dt
in this binding
equation, we have
R times i,
meaning A
e^(λt)
plus
U/R
times R
plus L times di/dt, meaning that, L times
λ
times A
e^(λt)
is equal to U.
We can simplify
these two termes, as well as
these ones
divided
in both sides of the equation by
this term
and therefore, R
is equal to -L
times λ, or
expressed differently
λ is equal to
-R/L, which is equal to
-1/τ.
τ being time constant
which is equal to
L/R for a circuit
RL in series.
We should now define the
integration
constant A
and to do so, we move to t=0
at the interlock where there is no
current fluctuation
then, at t=τ, the exponential is equal to 1,
and we can write to following equation :
I_0 = U/R + A,  therefore A
is equal to I_0
moins U/R.
we finaly rewrite the equation
of the current which is equal to
i(t)
which is equal at the permanente solution
U/R, plus
the current expression
already determined.
Graphically represented
in the time domain, we get
the following curve
i(t)
as function of time
the curve start from
I_0
an unknown value, that we can choose to be negative
and will tend
to the asymptotic value
and reach
U/R, which is the permanente value
that we call B for the computations
that will follow.
The intersection
between the slope at the origin
and the asymptotic value
is at time
t=τ, which is equal
to L/R.
Now let's compute the slope
at the origin.
We repeat current equation
i(t)=U/R
that we have substituted by B,
I_0
minus B,times e^(-λt)
and its derivative
di/dt, that is equal to
-λ
I_0
minus B
times e^(-λt).
At t=0, this slope is equal to -λ(I_0 - B)
the right hand side is therefore
given by the expression
-λ plus the absciss
Now, we can compute the
intersection
between this slope at the origin and the asymptotic value.
Meaning
that we should solve
the following equation : i' = B
B is therefore equal to
-λ(I_0 - B)
plus I_0.
Then, B - I_0
is equal to -λ(I_0 - B)*t.
The intersection occurs at time
t = 1/λ = τ.
L/R being the time constant.
Finally, we will calculate
the value of i
for t = τ
which is the time constant
if we substitute in the current
equation, the time t by τ, we obtain
the following equation
i = B + (I_0 - B)e^(-1).
and this is equal to t/τ.
If I_0 is equal to 0, then the current
i is equal to
B times (1 - e^(-1))
or written under this form,
B(1 - 1/e) is equal
to 0.632 times the asymptotic value.
Now, let's compute
the case of an interlock, not under a continuous voltage supply, but
under a sinusoidal voltage supply.
For such interlock
we will consider initial conditions.
Only the permanent
component changes
and is given
by the complex calculation associated to the circuit.
We rewrite the binding equation
the supply voltage written under a
complex form is
U and is equal to
the effective value times e^(jα).
If we rewrite the binding equation
considering the supply voltage,
we have
U = R * I
complex
+ jωLI.
It is also equal to
(R + jwL)*I
this is equal to Z*I.
expressed differently
The impedance Z, which is equal to R + JωL
Z times e^(jφ)
with
Z equal to
√(R^2 +ω^2*L^2)
and the angle phi, given by the arctan
of the reactance over the resistor.
And finally, the current is given by
U/Z
can be expressed as
U*e^(jα)
divided by Z*e^(jφ)
which is equal to U/Z
times e^j(α - φ).
If we go back to time domain, we can rewrite this equation
which is the inhomogeneous
solution of the current
I_p = √2*(U/Z)*sin(ωt + α - φ).
As I have already mentioned before
only the particular value changes
Therefore, the solution
of the second membre stays,
we can then write the equation of
the current
which is the particular solution
plus the permanent
solution
Again, we should calculate
the integration
constant A
and to do so, we should move to time
t=0, at the interlock,
assuming i=0
We have A
equal to
-√2*(U/Z)*sin(α - φ)
And finally,
the solution is given by
the current which is equal to
This is the final expression,
we notice that
the moment
of the switching
with respect to the sinusoidal voltage
is very high
we will see that in the graph of
the following page.
The temporal graphical representation
of the solution, for the current, is
given by that figure.
We see
a sinusoid
this term
which is added to an exponential function.
The sinusoid corresponds
to the sinusoidal power supply, and the exponential corresponds
to the interlock.
It is the transient state
with its time constant.
We notice the overcurrent
due to the interlock, here
that we also notice in case of
triggering, and that depend
on the switching moment α, here
and here
with respect to the supply voltage.
We will look in details at the effect
of the parameter α.
We see in this figure, in blue, the sinusoidal supply voltage, with an angle
α = 0.
Below, in red
is plotted the permanent
current in the circuit
if the system was stabilized.
we put it as reference for
the understanding of these explanations.
We note that the phase shift φ
the phase shift φ
which is introduced by the impedance
RL, φ is a circuit constant.
If we switch the circuit
at the represented instant here,
at the axis t=0
we obtain, in orange, the previously
described curve, meaning that
no current
here, before the switching, then
an equation, which
have a sinusoidal term,
and an exponential term.
Once the transient state is finished,
the system is stabilized
we still only have the permanent
solution and therefore
the solution, here that we found,
is confused with the
permanent
solution
we note that there is no
current jump at the switching, here
because the circuit is composed of
an inductance in series.
We note, here again, the over-current due
to the exponential.
If we switch, not at a=0,
but at a bigger
value, therefore later
on the voltage sinusoid, here
we see, we note that the over-current
decrease slightly, which is normal because the term
α - φ, in absolute value, becomes
smaller.
If we switch the circuit further
in time, here
we see that
the exponential term decrease again.
An overcurrent
decreases.
If we switch even further, until
we finally arrive at a particular
value, α = φ
in this case, the term sin(α - φ) = 0
we notice that
the term next to the exponential
becomes equal to zero et therefore the transient
state
doesn't appear.
We see
in the curve, here
that the solution that we have found,
is confused with the particular solution, there is
no transient state.
This is obvious, because
we actually
switch at the passage of the current
by 0, and then, there is no current
jump.
This is called cross
switching 0.
This approach is very important
in the power electronics
where the switchings occur at many
kilohertz, even dozens of kilohertz, because they
allow to
handle the components, avoiding
the overload, either of the current,
or the voltage.
If we switch even further, with respect
to the sinusoid, the transient
always reappears, but this time
in negative.
And, again a little bit latter
the overload
here, is more important.
In conclusion, we see that a term
corresponds to the sinusoidal power supply
of the circuit, it is the
permanent solution
A second term corresponds to
the switching, it is the exponential
part of the solution.
The general solution corresponds to the cumulation of
these two effects.
Moreover, we have seen the importance of the switching
instant with respect to
the sinusoidal voltage, that could, more or less,
stress out the electronic
components, because of
an overload.