Hello, in the previous lectures,
we have treated the case of RC or RL
circuits that
lead to some differential
equations of the 1st order, and then
to homogenous solutions
of exponential type.
During today's lecture
we will see the case of a voltage jump,
continuous voltage, in an RLC circuit in series.
For the equation layout of the circuit, the
methodology stays the same, but the
solutions that we will find will be very
different because the differential
equation resulting from the circuit
proposed, is of the 2nd order.
Let's consider the following circuit,
made of a continuous voltage supply,
of a switch
and of three elements R, L, and C
in series.
We start with
the values
of the circuit.
i(t)
the voltage drop across the
resistor
U_r(t)
the voltage drop
at the inductance terminals
U_l(t)
and, the voltage drop at the terminals of
the capacitor
U_c(t)
the voltage at the terminals of the three elements,
that we call U(t).
For a time t >= 0, we could
write the following equation
U is equal to
R*i + L*(di/dt), the voltage drop
at the terminals
of the inductance, plus the voltage drop at the
terminals of the capacitor : 1/C * ∫[-∞, t] i(t)*dt.
By deriving this equation, we get
the following equation
L * (d^2*i/dt) + R*(di/dt) + 1/C * i = 0,
the derivative of U.
At this 2nd order differential equation
we can associate the following
characteristic equation
λ^2 * L + λ*R + 1/C = 0.
It is a 2nd degree equation
we will then determine the solutions λ_1 and λ_2.
This equation of second
degree, present two solutions
λ_1
et λ_2
that are given by the
constant terms of
the characteristic equation
with a difference
a + for the first solution,
and a - for the second solution.
For visibility matters,
we will substitute the square root
with the term ω, and we then get
λ is equal to
-R/2L ± ω.
Supposing these two equations
we can rewrite the current equation
i(t) is equal to
A_1*e^(λ_1*t) + A_2*e^(λ_2*t)
The constant A_1 and A_2 have to be defined.
In order to determine the integration constants
A_1 and A_2, we position at time
t = 0
knowing that at that instant there is
no current jump in the
circuit, because of the inductance in series.
Writing the equation of the current at
time t=0, we get the following equation
this equation, allows us to determine
a first relation between A_1 and A_2,
that we substitute
in the temporal equation of the current, that
leads us to the following relation:
We can develop this equation
knowing that
the constant λ_1
is equal to
-R/2L + ω.
the same for λ_2, if we substitute in the previous
equation, we get the exponential term
-R/2L
times (e^(ωt) - e^(-ωt)).
For this case, we put the conditions
at time t=0
but we know that the current at time
t=0 is equal to 0.
The voltage at the terminals of the capacitor at time t=0, is equal to 0
the capacitor is initially empty.
This gives us, the voltage
across the resistor
at time t = 0
is equal to R times
i(0) is equal to 0
and, the voltage at the terminals of the capacitor
at time t=0, is equal to 0.
we therefore still have
for the binding
equation at time t=0
U, the supply voltage which is equal to
L*(di/dt), the two other terms
disappear.
At this instant of the development
three cases have to be considered
as function of the value of the discriminant
under the scare root
this discriminant Δ is equal to
(R^2/4L^2) - 1/LC.
the three cases are the followings:
Either the discriminant is bigger than 0
in that case
we get two real solutions.
That solution is called 'over-damped'.
In the second case
the discriminant is smaller than 0
we will find two complex solutions,
we are dealing with a "damped oscillation"
solution
And in the third case , when the
discriminant is equal to 0
we have an unique and real solution,
we are dealing in this cas with a
"critical damping" solution.
We started dealing
the case of an RLC circuit in series
switched under a
continuous supply voltage
The used methodology remains the same
The nature of the current leads
to a differential
equation of the 2nd order.
The solutions for
the current i(t) will be dependent
of the discriminant.
The link between the values R, L and C
will determine the nature of the
solution, and of the current.
During next lecture, we
will deal with the three cases of the discriminant
will lead us to three
different solutions.