In this last lesson, we will see how to
approach much more
ambitious projects than those we
have considered until now.
Thus, we'll see how to split
such a project into subproblems,
easier to solve,
until we may write the
final program.
In order to make our point clear,
we have chosen a "Connect Four" game.
You probably know the rules
of the Connect Four.
This two-player game
requires a 6 high, 7 wide grid.
The players take turns,
dropping disks of their own color
into the column of their choice.
The game will keep going until a player
manages to connect 4 disks of his own color
or until the grid is completely
filled.
First of all, please note
that we are not
going to develop a fancy
graphical interface.
Here, we are interested
in programming the game
mechanics
and will thus merely print
the grid and the disks
using characters. The end result will
look like this.
In a general way,
how should we proceed
when confronted with a substantial
problem such as this one?
Above all, we should not try
to write the whole program in one go;
it would just not work.
We will have to split
the problem into subproblems.,
writing the program step by step.
At every step, we will test the
newly-written code
in order to continue with solid bases.
First of all, we will need to identify
the types necessary
to the program to run,
that is
needed to represent the data
needed by the program.
In the case of our example, we
will essentially need to
represent the grid.
Then, we will have to indentify
the functions related to these types,
write these functions and test
them as we go.
And, if we are confronted with
a particularly complicated function,
we may introduce
a subfunction for each
difficult point.
As we said, we have to start
by indentifying the types.
What does it mean, concretely?
Well, we will start by identifying
the data required by the program
and find a way to represent
these data.
In this case, for our
Connect Four program,
the main data is the grid and the
disks it contains.
More exactly, we wish to know,
for every square, what this square contains:
Is it a red risk,
a yellow disk
or nothing at all?
There are several possible ways
to represent the grid.
A way to proceed is to see
the grid as
made of rows
where each element of a row
corresponds to a square.
Namely, we will
represent the lines
as arrays.
There are several possibilities
to represent arrays in C++
We remind you that you can
either the use the "array" type,
or the "vector" type.
Here, since the number
of squares, or rather, the number
of possible elements for each row
is known a priori,
that is,
we know that each row
will contain 7 elements,
we will rather use the "array" type
to represent a row.
In order to store all the rows, we
may use another array
whose elements will contain the
rows of the grid.
And, since the number of rows
is also known a priori
(a Connect Four grid has always 6 rows)
we will, once again, resort to
the "array" type.
The type representing the Connect Four grid
and its content is thus an array of arrays,
or, more exactly,
a 6 elements array, whose elements
are themselves 7 elements arrays,
corresponsding to a row
of the grid.
Now, we still need to define
the type of the elements of a row,
that is, the type of what is
contained in a square of the grid.
Before that though, please
note that,
although we have decided to represent
the grid as a 6 rows array,
we could have proceeded differently.
For exemple, we could have represented the grid
as a 7 columns array.
In general, there are several
ways to write
a program tasked with
solving the same problem.
Here, we will give you one solution
of a Connect Four program;
obviously there are many other
ways to produce the same result.
Now, we will use the "typedef"
keyword in order to define a new type
"Grille" (TN: "grille" means "grid") which
is an appropriately sized
array of arrays for a
Connect Four grid.
Thanks to this new type,
we will be able to define variables
which will be array
of arrays
representing a Connect Four grid.
The question now is:
How will we represent the
elements of the grid?
For example, we could
use the int type
and come up with a convention that,
if an element contains the value 0,
this element corresponds to
an empty square.
If the element contains 1,
it will correspond to a square
occupied by a red disk.
And if it contains 2, it will correspond
to a square occupied by a yellow disk.
Also, we could use
a char-type
and decide that, for example,
a blank space corresponds
to an empty square;
the character "O" corresponds
to a square occupied by a yellow disk;
and the character "X" corresponds
to a square occupied a red disk.
However, these two solutions
beget an incovenience:
If, for example, we choose
the int type, nothing prevents
an element of the grid to contain,
for example, the value 3.
However, the value 3 does not correspond
to anything in our program.
Even if we choose the char type,
an element of the grid could
contain the character "z"
which does not correspond to
anything in our game.
In such a case, it's much better to define
a new type using the "enum" keyword,
thus limiting the number of
possible values
for the elements of
our grid.
Indeed, in C++,
we can give names to the entities of
an enumeration. An enumeration
could, for example, be all the possible
colors for a disk
or the list of a continent countries.
This will be done thanks to
the "enum" keyword,
respecting the following syntax.
First comes the
keyword "enum"
followed by the name we wish
to give to the enumeration,
followed by, between braces,
the list of the names for the
enumeration values,
the names being separated
by commas.
The instruction is concluded
by a semicolon.
In our program, we will use
the enumeration we define as follows:
"enum" followed by the enumeration name.
In our case, this enumeration will
be used to define
the value of the elements of a grid.
A good idea would be, for example, to call
this enumeration "couleur (TN: means "color")
These elements will correspond to
an empty square,
a square containing a red disk
or a square containing
a yellow disk.
Thus, for the names of the enumeration
entities, we will simply use
"vide" (TN:"empty"), "rouge" (TN:"red)
and "jaune" (TN:"yellow").
Once this enumeration has been defined,
we can use it just like
any other type
in order to declare variables.
This instruction, for example,
will declare a
Couleur-type
variable called "element"
initialized to the value
"vide".
We can then change the value
of this element
thanks to an assignment.
In this assignment instruction,
we are changing the value "vide"
to the value "jaune".
We may also test what the variable
"element" contains
with such a condition:
does the variable "element" contain
the value "rouge"?
In this case, the test
is obviously false.
The types in our program will thus be
our new "Couleur" enumeration
as well as the type "Grille"
which we can finally define
like this.
As you can see, we have here
used the type "Couleur"
in order to define the element type.
Now that our "Grille" type has
been defined we can use it
to declare variables.
Here, we declare a variable
called "grille".
This variable, an array,
can then be modified
through instructions such
as
these ones.
This instruction assigns
the value "jaune"
to the index 3 element
of the index 2 row
of our "grille" array.
However, we must know what element
of the grid we are referencing in
this assignment.
For that, we must
make a choice.
Does the index 0 row
of our "grille" array correspond
to the uppermost row of the true grid?
Or does the index 0 row
correspond to the lowermost row of the true grid?
There is no unique correct way to
make the decision;
no way is strictly better
than the other.
Therefore, we will arbitrarily
decide that, in our case,
the 0 line corresponds
to the uppermost line of the true grid.
Now we can understand
the result
of this assignment
for our true grid.
Considering the row 0, 1, 2
and the index 3 element of this row.
This element has the index 0,
this one the index 1, 2 3.
Therefore, our assignment will
modify the value of this element,
giving it the value "jaune",
meaning that this square
now contains a yellow disk.
In the next video, we will discuss
how to write functions
letting us initialize and print
the grid.