The coding of an application,
whatever it is,
requires a careful thinking
of the involved data
and of the fundamental functionalities
which will enable to implement
the desired processing.
In the previous episode., we have already started this thinking
about the coding of the Connect Four game.
This has lead us to identify
the fundamental types
in order to represent the game grid.
Today we will expand our
reasoning
and focus on the
basic funtionalities.
Little reminder: in the previous
episode,
we have paid attention to
the types of the involved data.
Very naturally, we have contemplated
the modelling of the game grid.
Thus, we have introduced the
new type "Grille" (TN: means "grid")
as a two-dimensional array.
We have also modeled the cells' content
of all the array's elements.
This has lead us to introduce a
new enumerated type,
the type "Couleur" enabling us
to represent
the content of each
array cells.
The grid's size being fixed,
we have naturally chosen
to use the "array" type, introduced in C++2011,
letting us
represent a fixed-size array.
We have simply declared the
type "Grille" as
representing a two-dimensional array,
its size being fixed with
6 rows and 7 columns.
Each element of the grid is of
the type "Couleur".
"Couleur" being an enumerated type allowing only
the values "vide" ("empty"), "rouge" ("red") and "jaune" ("yellow").
Once these types have been
introduced, we can easily, in our program,
declare a Grille-type variable
and assign values
to its different elements.
These values will be taken among
the ones of the enumerated type,
that is, "vide", "rouge" or "jaune".
The fundamental types having
been defined,
we will now focus on the
first functionalities
we will operate on our grid.
At the beginning of the game,
we will probably want to start
playing with an empty grid.
Therefore, we will have to focus on the
initialization, letting us initialize
each of the array cells to the
value "vide".
Also, we will have to allow
the printing of the grid,
so that players may have an understanding
of their advancement in the game.
In the this episode,
we will focus on implementing
concretely these two functionalities.
We will forsee the coding of a function
"initialise" (TN: means "initialize)
initializing the grid
as well as the coding of another
function called "affiche" (TN: means "print")
which will print the grid.
Let us begin with the initialization.
Let us imagine how to
concretely use
this "initialise" function
in a program.
We can imagine that, in a program,
we have previously declared
a Grille-type variable "grille". In order
to initialize this grid,
we can imagine to write
a function
which can be called like this.
We will call the function "intialise" taking,
as paramter, the grid
in order to modify its content.
How will be modify its content?
Well, simply we will fill each of its
cells with the value "vide".
Now, let us focus on the coding
of the "initialise" function.
We can see that the function "initialise",
the way we see it,
does not need to return any result.
Its purpose is to modify the grid,
to initialize it.
Naturally, we will describe an
"initialise" function whose
return type is "void",
for we do not need
to retrieve a value after
the execution
of the "initialise" function.
We will write the "initialise" function
passing a Grille-type parameter.
The "initialise" function
will have to modify the grid.
Therefore, once we have finished
executing the function,
at this point of the program,
we will retrieve a grid, the contet of which
has been modified.
For this reason, we will
have to resort
to  passing by reference
so that the grid will indeed be
modified by the initialization function.
By the way, please note that this way
to code the "initialise" function
is obviously not the only
possible solution.
We could imagine that, instead
of working directly on
the provided grid,
the "initialise" function
could return a
correctly initialized grid.
This would correspond to the following call.
Here, we would replace the two
lines of code we have written here
by something like this.
We could call the
"initialise" function which,
instead of modifiying a provided
grid, would return a new grid.
At this point, the return type
would no longer be "void"
but  "Grille" instead.
Also, any parameter would no longer be necessary
since the "initialise" function would
return a grid.
This is another way to proceed,
a way we have already discussed
in the course about "structures",
with the example of the function
enabling
to "give birth to a new person".
In this episone, we have chosen an
alternative conception,
especially illustrating the idea
of by-reference passing.
The header of the function is now
clearly defined
and we can move on to developping its body.
Let us focus on the content
of the function body.
What this function has to do
is, for each row of the array,
to iterate on each cell and assigning
it the value "vide".
Let's see how we can proceed
to initialize a single row.
Let us imagine we are trying
to do so for the first row of the grid.
Obviously, we will need
to write a "for loop".
This loop will iterate on each
element of the row.
We can imagine a range-based for-loop
which is written like this.
As a first introduction. we will first do so
for the first row of the grid,
iterating square by square.
This is written like this.
We will fill the content,
assigning the value "vide" to it.
At this point, as an exercise,
we have written the lines of code
initializing the first row of the grid,
storing the value "vide"
in each cell.
Here, we can simply
close the function.
By the way, please note
the use of a "reference" type
for the iteration variable in the
range-based for-loop.
This is mandatory if we
want the
content of each square to be modified.
If we compile the program as such,
we will however encounter
a tiny problem.
The identifier "case" (TN: means "square"),
although very natural in French in order to identify
a square of the array is actually
a reserved keyword of the C++ language.
We are therefore not allowed
to use it as a variable identifier.
Therefore, we will have to
make a slight change
so that the program may effectively
compile.
We will change the
identifier name.
We way take the precaution
to comment the reason behind this choice,
explaining that we are not allowed
to use the reserved keyword "case"
since it is a reserved keyword of the language.
Obviously, we will have to rectify
the identifier wherever it is used.
Like this.
Obviously, this processing
we have implemented to initialize
the first row of the grid must be
repeated for each row
so that we can initialize
the whole grid.
It is natural to imagine
imbricating these processing
in a first "for loop"
which will be tasked to iterate
on all the rows
and realize exactly the same processing.
Let 's write this first "for loop"
iterating on all the rows
of the grid.
Once again, we can use a range-based for-loop.
Therefore using a variable "ligne"
(TN: means "row") iterating
on each row of the grid.
For each row,
we will have to replace "grille[0]" by "grille[ligne]".
We are realizing the same
processing as before,
thus storing the value "vide"
inside each square.
We correct here our identation.
Finally we have all these
lines of code,
enabling us to iterate on all the rows
in order to modify
their content.
By the way, please note the passing by reference
for the range-based for-loop variable, so that
the grid will indeed be
modified.
We are now able to initialize
a previously declared grid
thanks to the Grille-type defined
during the previous step.
Let us now focus on the
printing of the grid.
As before, let us imagine the
concrete utiliization
of this printing function.
It is always recommended to start off
by imagining how the function
will be used before its
effective coding.
Typically, we can imagine that,
once the grid has been initialized,
and other processing done on the grid,
we will need to print it.
It is natural to imagine calling an "affiche" function
(TN: "affiche" means "display"/"print")
taking, as parameter, the grid "affiche".
Let us now focus on the prototype.
As before, the type "void" is natural
since the printing function
will simply print the grid
on the terminal
and does not need to
return any result.
Here, we pass the grid as parameter.
Now we are wondering :
Under what form should
we pass the parameter "grille"?
Should we resort to passing
by value or by reference?
The printing function's purpose
is to print the values
of the different squares
of the came grid.
Its goal is therefore not to
modify the content of the grid.
Therefore, it rather natural to
imagine
to resort to passing by value
for the parameter "grille".
Indeed, it is not necessary
for the printing function to
modify the grid's content.
However we have seen that,
when passing by value, a copy
of the argument passed to the
function is made
in an area local to the "affiche" function.
If the object passed as argument is big,
this copy can be quite resource consuming.
At this point, we therefore
resort to an alternative,
an optimization consisting
of passing the parameter by reference.
This will let the "affiche" function
work directly
on the memory area corresponding
to the passed argument,
without any copy.
However, we take the precaution
to pass the argument by constant reference
in order to make sure that the "affiche"
function,
even if it operates directly
on the argument,
will not modify its
content.
For example if, within
the body of the "affiche" function,
we attempt to modify the grid's content,
it will result in an error
upon the compiling.
By the way, please note that we could
very well have written this:
This notation is perfectly
equivalent to the former.
We can use both notations
indefferently.
This here is an optimization
letting the function
work directly on the argument but
adding in stead certain
railings
hindering the function to
modify the grid's content,
for this is not the purpose of the function.
This precautation was essential in C++98.
In C++2011 however, it is not
always the case.
However, these practice considerations
stretch beyond the range of this course.
We will simply settle for implementing
this precautation:
good practice in order to avoid
the unnecessary copy.
Here, the prototype of the "affiche" function
will use the
passing by constant reference in order to
avoid the copy.
Let's now proceed to code
the body of the "affiche" function.
Here, the coding is rather natural.
It is rather similar to what we have
done for the "initialise" function.
The goal will be to iterate
on each of the grid's rows.
Then, for each of the grid's row,
we will iterate on each square
in order to print its
content in a particular format.
Here, we will not do any graphical display
but will simply print the content
of each cell
on the terminal, following a particular
convention.
In order to iterate on all the
grid's rows,
a range-based for-loop is rather natural.
We know exactly how many rows and
how many columns there are in the grid.
So here, for each of the grid's rows;
this is written like this, with a range-based for-loop;
we will iterate on each square of
the considered row.
We will thus print the content
of each square,
in a particular format.
We will have to resort to tests
in order to know, depending on the content,
what is to be printed.
For example, if the square contains
the value "vide",
that is, if the value of the enumerated
type "Couleur", is "vide",
we can choose, by convention, to print
a blank space on the terminal.
Otherwise, we will resort to other tests.
If the value of the square corresponds
to the value "rouge" of the enumerated type,
second possible convention,
we can choose any convention,
here, for example, an 'O' for the value "rouge".
Otherwise, last possible case,
we know that it contains the value "jaune".
We make a printing choice:
for example, an 'X'
signifying the value "jaune".
Here, we conclude the body
of the first "for loop",
the inside "for loop".
At this point, we have
printed the content of one row.
We take the precaution
to generate a line break,
separating the different rows,
once a row has been
printed entierely.
This closes the body of the
very first "for loop".
Then, we will end the
body of our "affiche" function.
You will note here, that it has not
been necessary
in our range-based for-loop
to resort to the ampersand symbol ('&').
Why is that?
Because we are only consulting
the content of the different elements.
We do not aim to modify their content.
In this case "auto", withtout the
by-reference symbol ('&')
is amply sufficient.
As good programmers,
we will now
comment the "affiche" function.
Indeed the printing choices
we have resorted to
are not necessarily forseeable.
It is therefore useful for someone
consulting our code
to know the used conventions
without having
to read the whole function
body.
At this point, we take the
precaution to comment our code,
explaining the conventions
adopted for the coding.
We precise that we will print an "O"
for a red square and "X" for a yellow one.
Testing the functionalities
as we progress
in the coding of an application
is absolutely indispensable
in order to produce
a sturdy and high-quality code.
This recommandation has been
given
at the very beginning of our case study
regarding the Connect Four.
We will thus begin testing
our first functionalities,
namely the grid initialization
and its printing.
In order to test the aforementioned
functionalities,
we simply need to write
a little main program,
calling the functions "initialise"
and "affiche" on a previously
declared grid.
Here, we call the initialization
and printing
functionalities on our grid.
It could be natural to wish
to test the printings
of all the possible forms.
If we simply initialize the grid
and print it directly,
all the squares will be empty.
At this point, it is interesting to make sure
that all the cases are correclty covered.
We will try to cover all cases
by filling the grid,
at certain places with yellow disks,
at others with red disks.
We are doing just that here,
on randomly chosen squares.
The expected printing, following
the program execution
should look like this.
Here, for every square of the grid,
excepted the ones we have
explicitly assigned,
we should print a blank space.
We are representing this here
with this symbol for more clarity.
However, please note that, in reality,
only a blank space will be printed.
And, for the two particular squares
we have filled
with red and yellow disks, we will
have particular printings.
Here, the square on the 2nd row,
3rd column must be yellow;
this corresponds, according to our
printing convention to an "X".
Here, we indeed have the row
index 0, 1, 2.
This corresponds to this row number.
The column index 0, 1, 2, 3,
which corresponds to this.
Similarly we should have the
printing convention
of a red disk on the 2nd row,
4th column.
Concretely, in our Connect Four
game, this playtest allows
to create a grid with a yellow disk here
and a red disk here.
The bases have now been set and
we can start
to focus on more cosmetic aspects,
tweaking aspects.
Here, the printing of the grid
is rather dry.
It is not easy to distinguish
columns,
Also, the separation between blank
spaces is somewhat hazy.
Therefore, it would be nice to
improve this printing;
this can be done by completing
the existing code,
adding the following aspects which
we will now comment.
This should provide a more
explicit printing.
Especially separating the different
columns with vertical bars
and explicitly numbering the
different columns
below the grid in order to make
it easier to visualize
the content of our game grid.
What were the necessary additions
leading to this printing?
Well, we begin, before each row,
to print a blank space
followed by a vertical bar.
This will allow to print
each of these elements for each row.
Then, following the printing
of each case's content,
be it "vide", "rouge" or "yellow"
we print a vertical bar
just after this printing.
Therefore, we will print
each of these vertical bars here.
The reamining processing
is rigorously identical.
Then, once the whole
grid has been printed,
we will focus on printing this
part above the grid.
This is fulfilled by these lines
of code here.
Let us comment them.
We begin by printing
an equals symbol, this symbol.
This is a particular case,
not corresponding to the
content of a column.
It simply corresponds to the
blank space preceeding the first column.
Then, thanks to a "for loop",
we will iterate on all the rows
in order to print their number.
We preceed the printing of each
number with the equals symbol.
Actually, this "for loop" here
will let us print
each number preceded by the equals sign.
Here, we took the precaution
to number the columns
starting with 1, making it
more readable.
Once this "for loop" has been executed,
we will have printed
the last column number,
preceeded by the equals symbol.
If we wish to close the printing
harmoniously,
we still have to print
this double equals symbol
which you can see here.
This is followed by as many
line breaks as necessary.
At this point, we have
tweaked our printing,
thus making it more readable.
Please note that we are
not iterating
on all the grid's values.
We are iterating as many times
as there are columns in the grid.
At this point,
we are using a classical iteration
and not a range-based for-loop.
The "i"variable will take as many values as
the number of columns in the grid.
The number of columns is
a size-type element;
this is represented in C++
with the "size_t" type.
This is good practice
for the coding of such processing.
We have no reached
the end of this step.
We have been able to model
a Connect Four grid.
We also know how to initialize
it and print its content.
We can now move on to
the heart of matter
which will be the object
of the following sequences.