Right now, we are nearing the
conclusion of
our Connect Four game.
We have managed to let
both players play alternatively
and to test if a player has won.
Now, we still have to tweak
a little our main program
in order to indicate to our
players who has won.
Also, we will have to deal
with the draw situation.
This will be the topic of this episode.
As a reminder, our Connect Four
game is a struggle
between two players : the player
'X', in charge of the yellow disks
and the player 'O', in charge of the
red disks.
These two players play alternatively.
Thus, we have made sure that,
after every loop iteration,
the current player's color will
alternate between red and yellow.
Both players will keep playing
until one of them has won.
We still need to tweak our
program a little bit.
The first natural thing to do is,
once the loop has finished its execution
-- which means that either one of
the two players has won --
is to indeed signify who has
won the Connect Four game.
Another thing to do is
to consider
the situation where no
player has won.
The draw situation is not yet
covered by our program;
which does not correspond
to a realistic simulation.
Let us now obviate these
two holes.
Let us now begin by having
our program indicate who
the winner is.
Therefore, after the loop, we will have
to add a few instructions,
testing the color of the
current player.
If the color of the current player is
yellow, for example,
we will print the the winner
is the red player.
But, why the red player instead
of the yellow player?
Well, remember:
at the end of the loop iteration,
we switch the color of the current player.
Therefore, if the current player's color
is the yellow color,
that means the winner
is the player with the other
color, that is, red.
This means that the red player
has indeed  won the game
when the current player was
the yellow player.
This explains why,
in the case where the
color of the current player
is yellow,
the winner is indeed
the red player.
We will cover the situation
where the yellow player has won similarly.
We have thus covered the
two possible cases.
Now, we will take the precaution to comment
this particular test
indicating that we have first
switched of the players' colors, which
explains the conter-intuitive
nature of this test.
Also, as we have said
at the beginning of this episode,
there are situations
where both players will be playing
and eventually fill out the whole grid,
without anyone having won.
This corresponds to the
draw situation.
Consequently, we have to
deal with this situation aswell,
thus exiting the loop if
one player has won or if
the grid is full.
We thus have to complete our code
so that this case will be
covered aswell.
If we do not, the program will behave
incorrectly
and keep on looping even once
the grid has been filled,
forever asking the same player to
indicate a column number where to play.
This does not make sense
since the grid is full
and it is not possible
to drop disks anymore.
This corresponds to an erroneous
situation we have to correct.
The modifications required
in order to solve this problem
are rather natural.
Thus, we have to signify that
we are iterating,
looping, as long as we do not have
a winner
-- this part is already covered -- and
as long as the grid is not full.
This can be written this
way.
We will be foresseing the existence
of a function called "plein" (TN: means "full")
which will test if the
grid is full or not.
This will also require a few
modifications
after the execution of the loop.
Indeed, at this point,
once we have exited the loop, we will not be
confronted with a unique situation anymore
where, fatally, one player
has won.
Now, there is another possibility aswell:
a draw which we will have to
signal.
Therefore, we will have to modify
our program so that
if there is a winner, then we will
find ourselves in the situation
where we will signify who has won.
However, this will not always be the case;
it is also possible not to
have any winner.
In this second case, we will indicate
the game ended in a draw.
Now, we have covered all the
possible situations.
Let us now move on to the
coding of the "plein" function.
Remember that our program will
ask the red and yellow player
in what column they intend to drop
their disk.
Let us suppose that it
is the yellow player's turn.
If, for example, they decide to
drop their disk down the first column,
the filling will occur from bottom
to top.
Namely, the disk will be
automatically placed
on the first available square,
starting from the bottom.
Therefore, in order to test
if the grid is full,
we do not need to test
all the squares of the grid,
testing if they are occupied
by a particular color.
We simply need to test the squares
of the very first line.
Indeed, in the case
where the grid is full,
we will have filled all
the columns starting from the bottom.
This means that all the squares
of the first row
will also have been filled.
Now, we should be able to
effectively code our "plein" function.
Methodologically speaking, we have
briefly wondered,
since it is a rather
simple function,
about the "what":
what does the "plein" function do?
In the main program, we have
planned for this function
to take, as argument, the grid
and to test whether it is full or not.
This corresponds naturally
to the following prototype:
the function returns a boolean
indicating if the grid is full or not.
The only parameter of the function
is a grid.
In the previous episodes,
we have seen that, for all the functions
having, as parameter,
a rather voluminous object
used only in reading, in consultation,
which we did not want to modify,
it was a good idea to resort to
passing by constant reference.
We will do just that here.
Here, the "plein" function aims only
to consult the content
of certain squares of the grid
in order to know if they are filled or not.
It thus does not aim to
modify the grid.
This is precisely the reason
why are resorting to
a passage by constant reference here.
Let us now focus on the "how".
How should effectively write the body
of this "pleine" function?
We have already sketched the algorithm
on the previous slide.
Namely, if we encounter an empty
square on the first row,
we know that the grid is
not yet full.
This is what we will
concretely code.
We will iterate square by square
on the first row, "grille[0]", and test the squares.
If one or more squares are empty, then we know
that the grid is not full.
Therefore, the "plein" function
will return "false".
Otherwise, obviously, the
grid is full
and we will thus return
the value "true",
signifying that the grid is full.
Now, we have finished coding
our little
Connect Four application.
The goal of this case study was to
show you how to tackle
the programming of such an application
when we are programming begginers.
Several key ideas are to be
remembered.
First of all, always proceed
bottom-up.
Start by identifying the
essential types,
the fundamental functionalities
before dealing with the details.
Each fundamental function
can then, at its turn,
be modularized, call other
functions or more details
helping to fulfill the process.
For each function, proceed
with methodology.
Ask yourself "what",
what is the role of the funciton
in your program?
What informations does it need
in order to perform effectively?
What will the function deliver
as return information?
Then ask yourself "how"
and consider the algorithm
which will help to realize
the desired processing.
Focus on the essential aspects
before dealing with cosmetic
tweaking aspects.
Finally, last essential point,
be systematic when testing
the different functionalities
as you are progressing in the development of the
application program.
Voilà! These were some
of the key points
we wished to illustrate through
this case study.
We hope they will prove useful
to you once you will be facing yourselves
the programming of such applications.