Hi. Marco Albertini
is one of the coordinators
for the WatHab Engineering Department
of the International Committee
of the Red Cross.
In this video,
he will present the case
of "Build Back Better" Shelters
after Typhoon Haiyan.
The response was launched
just a few days after the typhoon
hit the central region of the Philippines
as a continuation of
an earlier emergency response
based on immediate food needs,
healthcare and assistance.
And it followed just after a few weeks,
as soon as people could
start coming back to their life.
At that point, the most
immediate need was shelter,
and we decided to start our program.
In an area like Samar
in central Philippines,
where typhoons and strong natural hazards
are of natural frequent recurrence,
it was necessary to offer a solution
to the beneficiaries that would last
more than the single event.
They were trapped in a cycle of poverty,
and so poor means of reconstruction,
and again, destruction
brought by following events.
In order to try to break this,
we wanted and it was necessary
to "build back better".
And this included giving them the means
to have something that was stronger
than before the typhoon,
in order to increase their resilience
to the next event.
The scale of the typhoon was so big
that many, tens of agencies
and organizations
came into the country suddenly,
each of them bringing
a different set of knowledge,
expertise, skills,
and also practical means
to rebuild houses.
In order to standardize the response,
the Department of Social Welfare and
Development of the Philippine government
issued technical guidelines
that all partners involved
in shelter reconstruction
should respect.
The three key messages were at the core
of these guidelines:
Appropriateness-- it stood for giving
an answer of the proper size
according to the number of components
of each family;
something that would be adequate
as well to the condition, to the climate;
and also something that would look at
accessibility of services.
It was necessary to yes,
rebuild the house,
but the house should have access
in proximity to education opportunities,
to livelihood opportunities,
and to healthcare facilities as well as
water supply and sanitation.
The main idea of building a storm
resilient house
was to have a core structure of the house
that would be able
to withstand any future events,
up to strong events of
250 kilometers an hour,
as well as small earthquakes.
Besides these core structures
it was then possible
to add additional elements--
like a veranda, like a kitchen--
additional external elements
that could be potentially destroyed
and easily rebuilt.
But the core structure remains intact.
And that's exactly where our program
focuses,
in offering immediately
the construction of the core structure.
How to reach the target
of such a resistance--
this was made through bringing
technical elements,
in particular focusing on the foundations,
on the roof, on the bracing,
on the tie down,
and on other practical devices
like a hurricane strap.
All of them bringing the house
to be one element,
and this unique element
to be solidly anchored to the ground.
Besides the technical elements,
two other factors improved
the storm resilience of the house
and they were the choice of the location,
as the house would
have to be in a safe zone,
safe at a certain distance
from riverbanks or from the seashore,
and from potential landslide;
as well as the choice of material--
this second element
was also very important,
as we needed to find good material
but still affordable;
so the right balance
between quality of material, cost,
and affordability by the beneficiaries.
The model of shelter was chosen
learning from our recent experience
from Typhoon Bopha
that hit another region of the country
just 18 months earlier than Haiyan.
The model was later proposed
to the beneficiaries,
prior to the construction,
and all the main input coming from
the communities were, as much as possible,
included in the new design.
On top of this,
our engineers brought up also
new advice in terms of additional elements
that would still reinforce further
the wind resistance.
The other main challenge of this response
was on the technical side in terms of
finding the right model and
designing the right model of house.
There were equivalent
management challenges
for a program that had set
very ambitious targets
of delivering 4500 houses in 18 months
in an area that was totally devastated
by the typhoon,
where many infrastructures were disrupted,
where even the means of communication
were very limited.
To do this, it was necessary to set
structure that would just work on this
and they included more than 100 people,
specifically hired for this program,
on top of more than 1000 carpenters,
trained and involved
in the construction of the houses.
All these had to be perfectly synchronized
on the logistic side,
on the financial aspects,
and on the reporting
and communication side
there were many departments involved
for a common purpose over the 18 months.
These management challenges
were as difficult as the technical side.
On the technical side,
the validation of the chosen design
happened at different levels--
if inputs from the communities
were taken in the design,
engineers validated them several times
up to coming at level
of headquarters of the ICRC
so that all the design
and the proposed ideas
would match with the standards
set by the Philippine government,
but also with the standards
set internally
in the Red Cross and Red Crescent
Movement response.
Additionally, several laboratory tests
were carried out
by the Shelter Research Unit of the
International Federation of the Red Cross
that was deployed specifically
for the period of time on the field
to monitor the quality of CGI,
corrugated iron sheet and nails.
The choice of materials was
an essential element in the process,
as these would directly affect
the feasibility of the construction,
but also immediately impact
on the cost of the operation
and on the affordability
for the beneficiaries
of all necessary maintenance
in the future.
For this principle, we tried to keep
local materials in the design
as much as possible.
and all the main elements
were made of local materials.
Amakan, the splitting bamboo,
was used for the walls.
The coconut wood was chosen
as the main element,
as more than 33 million trees
were destroyed by the typhoon
and this was also an opportunity
to reuse the fallen trees,
to give also integrated
opportunity of livelihood,
and to free space
as well from the fallen tree
and allow planting again of new trees
or the new farming season.
As well as CGI, the corrugated iron sheet,
were the most important
and most costly element,
and it's the one that would determine
the most, the strength of the house.
We tried to exactly strike a balance
between quality of the chosen material
and cost,
as well as feasibility--
some materials locally,
some materials were imported,
but everything would have to respect
the 18 months target--
deadline that we had fixed
at the beginning.
We thought that keeping the model
as flexible as possible
was important
so as to allow beneficiaries
to develop the core house,
around the core house,
all the main infrastructures
that they needed
according to their own needs.
Some of them opted for a kitchen,
some of them built additional verandas,
others extended the space
with additional rooms.
But in this way,
once received the core house,
each beneficiary
could make it his own house
and so personalize,
answer to his own need,
and also increase the feeling
of ownership of the house.
Our objective, in making a house
storm resistant,
was to re-engineer
a local traditional house.
And we did this through
a few main elements.
First of all, the foundation,
as it was necessary to anchor
the house to the ground,
and then to tie down all the elements,
starting from the roof
to the foundation together,
as well as adding bracing,
internal bracing, short and long bracing,
as well as finding a proper slope,
wind-resistant, for the roof
that would also develop on four sides.
And this was different
from the traditional construction,
a simpler and cheaper construction
that many would easily afford
of two-sided roof,
but we did this through training
and through community involvement
so that they would
understand the difference
between different sizes and
different shapes of the roof.
With regards to technical materials,
it was possible to re-propose a design
that would already bring all elements
known by the beneficiaries.
Only one additional element was proposed
to the communities--
that was the hurricane strap.
But as simple as they were,
they could also be replicated locally
just using different materials.
And all communities were trained on that.
Hurricane straps are simple devices.
Metal straps that are used to tie down
all the elements of the house to the roof
so that it will never blow away because
it is anchored to the rest of the house
that is then anchored to the foundations
in the ground.
In the shelter response,
it was important to add
a component of sanitation
in line with the principle
of "building back better".
Rates of access to sanitation facilities
were very low before the typhoon
and this was indeed the opportunity
to help communities,
to answer to their ambition
of having their own sanitation facilities.
As soon as the program was launched
and it reached its cruising speed,
we then went back and built a toilet
with a septic tank for each house.
The principles that guided the response
are of general interest:
sustainability of the operation;
a focus on choice of materials;
attention to the cost and
the cost of future maintenance;
the involvement of the communities
as well as the training
of the beneficiaries--
all these are elements that have
a general value, in wide terms,
and are applicable to any response.
Specifically looking at
the design of the house,
this matches with the environment
of rural context in Southeast Asia,
so it could be chosen and modified
to respond to the specificity
of other tropical, rural contexts
in Southeast Asia.
It was possible to improve
flood resilience of the shelters
through two main choices:
the first one in the design was to
elevate the house on stilts,
so they could resist flooding,
also because they were anchored
to the ground through the foundations;
but also we need to think
of the location of the house.
So as houses in areas that were considered
not safe for reconstruction
would not be rebuilt in the same places.
Remembering that most
of the victims of the typhoon--
more than 6000 people--
were victims indeed of the flooding,
brought by the tsunami-like effect
after the typhoon.
The Samar region, that was
the center of the shelter response,
is recurrently hit by typhoons
during the year,
specifically, just 13 months
after Typhoon Haiyan,
a new typhoon of lower intensity
but still important magnitude,
hit the same area passing
almost on the same path.
Typhoon Hagupit was the name
and it gave us the opportunity to test
the houses that we had just completed.
As a result, only four of them,
out of 4461, were damaged--
it's below 0.1%--
and they were immediately reconstructed.
So as of today, all 4461 houses
are standing strong.
The technology that we chose
was a compromise
between engineering inputs,
advanced carpentry,
as well as local knowledge.
And we tried to have the balance
that would respect feasibility
in terms of time and cost.
The technology could improve further,
of course,
but we need to see if the limits
in terms of cost
and affordability by the beneficiaries
are respected.
This goes in contrast
with the tendency of bringing
other models, prefabricated models,
in an emergency
as a response from outside,
sometimes often from different countries,
and affording, then, a long-term
sustainability of the project.
Our choice in the technology
was to have some limits in the design
but invest in long-term sustainability
in that specific context.
The design of the house was based,
as much as possible,
on local knowledge,
even if new elements came in
in terms of re-engineering
the carpentry of the construction.
Beneficiaries were consulted
and each of them had to state
their acceptance of the model,
and eventually also have to
bring in their inputs
in the face of assessment,
so prior to the construction of the house.
All beneficiaries were also trained
on the construction of the house
and specifically more than
a thousand carpenters in the area
were involved, trained,
and then involved in the construction,
so as to leave a legacy of knowledge,
not only through the beneficiaries
but also through the technicians
who would then remain in the area
so as to replicate the elements
that were brought in
to increase and improve
the storm resilience of the houses.
The cost of each house
is about 1500 Swiss francs;
to this we need to add about 750 [francs]
for the construction
of the sanitation facilities,
to a total that reaches
about 2300 Swiss francs.
Even if this amount
might seem very important
for the beneficiaries in the field,
it is much cheaper than
many other proposed interventions
that were brought from outside.
So the idea as well to use
as much as possible
local materials and local resources
was indeed to keep also as much as possible
the cost contained
within a certain ceiling.
The ICRC and PRC,
as implementer of the program,
paid for the technology,
but of course many donors
and also many other members
of the Red Cross and
Red Crescent Movement
contributed to the response.
On top of this
we cannot forget the contribution
of the beneficiaries themselves
as they were asked
to participate to the cost,
with contribution mainly in terms of
supply and handling
of the wood component of the house.
Not all agencies
involved in the response did this,
but for us it was a specific choice.
It worked; it didn't leave anybody
out of the program
as in the cases where the most indigent
would not be able to contribute,
the communities themselves
would help each other
and bring the wood for the families
who could not afford it
and nobody was left, at the end,
out of the program.
The reason of the choice of asking for
a contribution from the beneficiaries
would answer to two main reasons:
first, it was an opportunity
to mobilize people
to use the wood-- as I mentioned,
there were millions of trees fallen
that would occupy all the farming land--
it was an opportunity to help people
to move on and start clearing the land;
and also, participating to the project,
involve them, enormously,
it made them feel their house,
their own house, as they worked for it.
The positive aspects of the technology
are mainly in the choice of a design
that would completely suit the environment
and immediately answer to the needs--
so being feasible in terms of
construction in a rapid time,
but as well, respect all the main elements
for that specific climate and conditions.
That allowed the immediate acceptance
from the beneficiaries
and of course, respecting all the input
of technical re-engineering of the design
increased their capacity
of resisting to the next typhoon
and so improved their resilience.
I would mention that on the negative side,
one limit was indeed, in the technology,
in the choice of the main material,
that was coconut wood,
because in construction coconut wood
is not an ideal material,
but this was a specific choice
due to the availability
of millions of trees
and the need of removing them and
using them as much as possible immediately.
So no need of bringing wood from outside
but using local resources,
even if not ideal.
The choice of using local materials,
as well as building a core house
that would be as simple as possible,
aimed to allow beneficiaries to afford
any future intervention for maintenance.
Indeed, we know that every few years
it will be necessary to replace the walls,
made of Amakan, local materials,
but this is perfectly normal
and people are used to do that already
for their traditional houses.
Other elements can also
be replaced and maintained
with periodic painting
to extend their longevity,
but any needed intervention
is, and must be,
affordable by the beneficiaries
considering their average income level.
The shelter response must be
considered within a much wider frame
of response of the entire Red Cross and
Red Crescent Movement in the region,
that included other components
such as water supply,
access to health needs,
access to food and opportunities
for restarting livelihood activities.
The ICRC was also present in the region
before the typhoon
because of its specific mandate,
carrying out activities of protection
and assistance of the population,
and will remain present within the region
even after the project is completed.
And that allows us for a continuous
monitoring in the coming years
of the results of the project.
Among the many positive aspects
brought by the response,
I think two are of particular importance:
first of all, the intervention
allowed 4400 and more families
to have their house rebuilt
just within 18 months since the typhoon
and so allowed them
to restart their normal life;
second point is that
the respect of the principle
of "building back better"
helped them to have houses
that were stronger than before,
and so they could break the cycle
of poor reconstruction
induced by poverty, and in this sense,
improve their resilience
to the next events.