Hi again, science and technology
can be used to increase
disaster risk reduction knowledge
which is a prior step
to the development
and implementation of structural
and non-structural measures
to mitigate risk.
In this video I will give an example
on the use of tools and technologies
within the context of seismic risk.
I will mainly focus on the application
of experimental testing,
which ideally should be combined
with appropriate
numerical simulation techniques.
The pacific ring of fire
is a long stretch of area
along which most of the world's
largest earthquakes
and volcanic activities take place.
Colombia is located in this region
and it is therefore
a seismically active country.
In its long history of earthquakes,
the first seismic event
that we know of
dates back to 1541.
Since then, there have been
many large magnitude earthquakes
hitting the country,
among which the one of 1906,
with an estimated magnitude
of around 8.8, ranks high
within the list
of strongest earthquakes ever.
More recently, the Armenia earthquake
of 1999
with a magnitude of 6.2
set a death toll of almost 2000 people.
This figure shows the epicentral location
of earthquakes in Colombia
taken from a catalog
containing 9000 seismic events
with magnitude above three.
The seismic zonation map included
in the Colombian construction code
reflects this historical epicentral
location of earthquakes.
The country is divided
into three main regions,
with low, intermediate,
and high levels of seismic hazard.
Although major cities
are fortunately located in regions
of low to medium seismic hazard,
almost 40% of the population lives
in areas of high seismicity.
In these areas, the building code
requires engineers
to design the structures
such that they can resist
to horizontal forces equal to half
of their own total weight.
This is the case of the city of Cali,
the third largest in Colombia,
from where the next photos
were taken.
Over the last 10 to 15 years
the increasing demand of housing
for low income population in Colombia
associated to the significant increase
of cost of land
has prompted construction companies
to massively build medium to high rise
reinforced concrete wall buildings.
These structures are made of concrete
and reinforcing steel
and require a relatively non-specialized
and cheap labor.
Comparatively, the cost of materials
is high and has pushed
to the development and application
of construction techniques
that minimize its use.
It is therefore not surprising that most
of these new residential buildings
have been constructed with walls
that have thicknesses
as low as 80 millimeters.
Besides, there are typically only lightly
reinforced often with just a single layer
of steel rebars
instead of the more common
two rebar configuration.
The end result are walls
with very large ratios
between their height
and their thickness
raising concerns regarding
the possible development of instability
when the earthquake strikes.
That is,
to say seismic loading.
It is a bit like holding a playing card
in between your fingers
and compressing it.
Since the card is quite thin
and very elongated,
it will buckle or bend in direction
perpendicular to it's own plane.
Something similar can happen
with thin reinforced concrete walls
but we will see more about it soon.
This failure mode
was observed in the recent earthquakes
of Chile in 2010
and of New Zealand in 2011,
which caused significant damage to some
modern reinforced concrete walls.
These pictures show examples
of buckled structural walls
after the ground shaking
suggesting stability problems.
In Colombia, since the walls
are significantly thinner
than those used in Chile
or in New Zealand,
it is legitimate to fear that similar,
out-of-plane deformations,
and even failure could occur
during a future earthquake.
Additionally, the use of a single layer
of reinforcement
in some of these Colombian buildings
may increase the vulnerability
to out-of-plane instability.
So, how does out-of-plane
instability occur?
When the earthquake pushes the wall
in one direction,
nearly horizontal cracks form
in the bottom-edge region
due to the large tensile strains
that are imposed.
As these cracks open,
the vertical steel rebars
inside the concrete
yield in tension.
When the ground shaking
pulls back the wall,
the plastic tensile strains accumulated
in the rebars
during the prior push phase
prevent the cracks from closing.
This means that the compression
force in that part of the wall
is resisted solely by the rebars
and not by the concrete.
As this compression force increases,
the rebar may yield,
leading to an abrupt reduction
in out-of-plane stiffness
and the consequent increase
in the corresponding
out-of-plane displacements,
which can potentially lead to failure.
This was a very simplified explanation
of the instability phenomenon,
which unfortunately has been
insufficiently studied in the past.
Therefore, many aspects
are still not clear,
which we should strive to understand,
but how?
The most obvious answer,
perhaps the best is, experimental testing.
These tests can be carried out
in walls or in a cheaper and simpler way,
in actually loaded columns
that are equivalent
to the boundary element
of the wall.
This is where tools and technologies
step in.
The Earthquake Engineering
and Structural Dynamics Laboratory of EPFL
has teamed up with a few different
Colombian universities
to address this issue in two projects
financed by the Cooperation &amp; Development
Centre of EPFL, CODEV.
In the first project
a thin reinforced concrete wall
was tested using the test setup
that one can see in this sketch
and in the picture on the right.
The test unit represents
the portion of the wall
on the ground story
of a multi-story building,
and therefore the applied
boundary conditions and loading
should reproduce those
in the real building as much as possible.
To do so, the test unit
is loaded with three actuators.
Two vertical ones, which simulate
the weight of the stories above
and, in a way, how they rotate
during the ground shaking,
and a horizontal one, which applies
a cyclic displacement history
of increasing amplitude that simulates
the earthquake's loading effects.
The wall was designed and built
such that its geometrical dimensions,
the material properties and the detailing
of the reinforcement
are similar to what we could find
in a recent Colombian building.
Note the low thickness of the wall,
only eight centimeters,
the use of a single layer of vertical
and horizontal rebars
and the presence of a flange
in one of the extremities.
In terms of measurements,
these small dots in the figure
represent a dense grid of optical
light emitting diodes
that monitor the evolution
of the 3D displacement field
throughout the loading.
After the experiment has been conducted,
we can post-process the data
obtained with these LEDs
and obtain plots such as this one.
It shows, on the horizontal axis,
the value
of the imposed horizontal displacement
at the top of the wall.
To the left, when we're pulling
towards the wall side
that does not have the flange,
which is when instability can occur,
and to the right, when we are pushing
towards the flange.
The vertical axis displays
the out-of-plane displacement
at the height where maximum
out-of-plane displacement was measured.
It can be observed that the maximum
out-of-plane displacement
was higher than 45 millimeters,
that is, more than half
of the wall thickness.
In addition, this plot shows that,
for each cycle of increasing amplitude,
the maximum out-of-plane displacement
is attained approximately
at 0% in-plane-drift,
after which the wall straightens up again.
The next time-lapse
shows this structural behaviour
during one half-cycle,
over which, the wall is pulled
towards the side
that does not have the flange.
The out-of-plane displacement
progressively increases
up to a maximum value
reducing after.
At the end of that half cycle,
we can also see some concrete crushing
and spalling at the base of the wall
which was partially triggered
by the large, out-of-plane
deformations previously attained.
Finally, all these information
and data that we manage to gather
from experiments can be used to develop
and calibrate numerical models.
They range in their complexity
from shell finite elements
with advanced
nonlinear material models
to beams, where the cross section
of the member
is discretized into fibres
among other even simpler approaches.
Our studies have shown
that many of these models
do a pretty good job
in simulating wall instability,
which means that they can be used
by practicing engineers to design
and access the vulnerability
of walls and buildings.
To sum up, in this video
we saw how thin reinforced concrete walls
with a single layer of reinforcement
are extensively used
in modern construction
in Colombia.
They can be prone
to out-of-plane instability
with unknown and possibly
serious consequences
on the seismic vulnerability
of buildings.
Science and technology can
and should be used
to better understand the behavior
of thin walls,
combining experimental tests
using new instrumentation techniques
that provide detailed information
on the local member response
with advanced
numerical simulation models.
If needed, structural measures
such as seismic retrofit
or nonstructural measures
including changes to the design codes
or the development of new tools
for design engineers,
should be implemented.
Overall, technologies can greatly improve
seismic risk reduction knowledge
which helps defining long-term strategies
for the prevention or mitigation
of the adverse effects
of earthquakes.
Thank you for watching
this video.