Hello.
In our video we will talk about
one of the forms of urbanization,
which is the shantytown.
Shantytowns,
which we will define briefly.
But to preface it,
we should note that, in principle,
shantytowns are too complex
to be defined by only one criterion.
Because of this, normally we use
a battery of criteria
to define the shantytown,
at times with the whole
of criteria present,
and at others, only the one, two, three,
four, six criteria present.
Shantytowns are also defined locally.
What is considered a shantytown
in one country or city,
may not be in another country or city.
So we cannot have certain global criteria
which are applicable to the whole planet,
but instead have
particular, local situations.
We must also keep in mind
that the criteria can change with time.
What one day is a shantytown
may no longer be one
a few years, or a few decades later.
And, conversely, what was not one,
based on changing norms,
based on periods, can become
a precarious zone.
We'll use shantytown
and precarious zone as two synonyms.
We'll avoid, however, speaking
of informal settlements, because,
as we'll see, this housing
has nothing spontaneous about it,
It's a term one finds, generally,
used when speaking of shantytowns in Africa,
when speaking of informal settlements.
So it become common usage
even though, in fact,
its meaning is essentially false
within the African context.
There is nothing
spontaneous about, on the contrary,
this slow settling
of this form of housing.
A few current statistics.
In the world we have 923,986.
We are of course, in thousands,
of a total of 7 billion,
which corresponds to 31.6%,
the percentage in relation to
urban population.
So of the total urban population in 2000,
which was 2,000 million,
861,000, we have 31%,
or 923 million
who live in shantytowns.
If we look now at Africa,
at all of the African nations,
we'll end up at 187.562
million inhabitants,
and this represents, globally,
61.3% of the urban population.
The number is huge, and means
that 6 out of 10 people living in cities,
in Africa, live in shantytowns.
For comparison, let's look at Asia,
where 539.917 million
of urban dwellers are living in shantytowns,
which corresponds to 40.1%.
There we have,
we won't continue, we could see
how the most developed regions
and the less developed,
share Africa in a certain
number of sub-regions,
we would have numbers
which would be relatively different,
if one is in a more developed country,
or in a less developed country.
What we must remember here is that,
there is nonetheless
a high proportion, a majority,
more than 50%;
one of every two people
living in an African city
lives in a shantytown.
Of course this number is one which
we'll try to reduce as much as we can
at the same time that, as we've seen,
urban population numbers continue to increase.
Let's start with some definitions.
The first we'll find in the document
UN-Habitat, The Challenge of Slums.
UN-Habitat, The Challenge of Slums
We'll see if what they use
as criteria for their evaluation,
when vetted against
their diverse criteria of shantytowns,
will allow us to determine
if the zone we are studying
can be considered a precarious zone,
or, on the contrary,
if it in no way meets the criteria,
then it is not.
Now one of the first points is, of course,
the lack of basic services,
the precarious habitat
high population density,
minimal living conditions,
difficult conditions, land insecurity,
poverty and social exclusion,
and small-sized parcels.
A certain number of criteria,
we could add others.
But we can already see
that we are under conditions
at the same time
of spatial precariousness,
which is the question of land,
and at the same time
with questions about habitat,
about construction systems,
also relatively precarious.
Then we can look at the different zones
and see whether or not
they meet all criteria, or not.
And we can imagine
it must meet all criteria
to be considered a shantytown.
Otherwise we can well define,
as long as we have
three or four criteria,
the zone to be a precarious one.
Another group of experts from the U.N.
uses other criteria, this from 2002.
We'll see some examples.
It's in English, the criteria
are defined in English.
But we have questions about sanitation,
questions about access to water,
questions about latrines and waste water,
about quality of habitat,
questions of overcrowding
and, as we saw in the beginning,
questions of security of land tenure.
We define the major characteristics,
then a certain number of indicators,
and then we define
in a more precise manner.
We will not get into detail on this chart,
but we should keep in mind
that we are dealing with questions
of access to water, waste water
and infrastructure,
questions of habitat quality,
of overcrowding,
Now, what causes the emergence
of shantytowns?
and, of course, of land issues.
We can assign three basic categories:
the first, second and third.
The first is demographic,
a natural growth,
an increasingly large urban population.
The next is economic, rural exodus,
ever increasing, land speculation
and, finally, the balancing
of supply and demand.
We must keep in the back of our minds
that we are in the process
of the pauperization of societies,
that there are more and more people
for an economic development
which has yet to take place.
This means that for each person
there is impoverishment.
And all the people
who don't have access
to the land market, as we are in
a free land market, all of those who
don't have access
to the land market because
it is too expensive, must find situations
where they can live, and this often means
a squat, or land occupied
by those who do not own it, and it is
the emergence of precarious
and illegal zones.
Finally, there are legal questions,
with, as we've already said,
the question of land tenure,
and, finally, of private property.
If you occupy land
which you do not own,
and which has a private owner,
you are squatting,
and you are not
legally living on the land.
To wrap up our quick journey
through the shantytown, the most famous,
without a doubt, in Africa,
and the largest, in Kenya: Kibera,
with its very recognizable rail line
and its shantytown,
which formed along its huge periphery.
So, there are no official numbers,
some claim it has 1 million inhabitants,
others 500 thousand.
What we must remember
is that we are in a shantytown
covered extensively by the media.
But despite this, we haven't noticed
any apparent change, difference,
restructuring, or upgrading
of the shantytown.
We are still, more or less,
in the same situation,
and this despite the presence
of dozens of NGO's,
who for decades have worked
in the very heart of the shantytown.
A quick introduction to the shantytown.
We'll now look at a specific case,
the restructuring of a precarious zone,
the Kebba of El Mina, in Nouakchott,
a program over the last 10 years,
the last 15 years,
which is a rather symptomatic program
because it began as urban sprawl,
affecting thousands of people.
And we'll see the basic plan
of this type of program,
divided between the restructuring,
resettlement and, finally,
the habitat program aid
for the population.