After an introductory video on slums,
we are now going to take a look,
by way of a case study,
at the restructuring of a slum.
This slum is the Kebba of El Mina
in Nouakchott,
a restructuring process that
took place in the lat 15 years.
So there are different types
of irregularities.
I'm talking about land irregularities.
Two scenarios.
The first is when the residents
squat lands which are owned by the State.
Second scenario, when the residents
squat lands which are are privately owned.
We can realize that the degree of
instability is not quite the same.
And we are dealing with a much more
significant instability when
there is squatting of lands
which are private, which
are owned by people
who can the claim them at one point.
Meanwhile, when we are dealing with
lands belonging to the State,
we know that there is a leeway
which is a little bit bigger and
that we will be able to
deal with the State and maybe we
will stabilize the situation.
The example we are going to use,
we were talking about
private lands, so dealing with
instability on a very large scale,
meaning that the "hardening process"
of housing
that goes from housing made from
excessively unstable materials,
made from planks and sheets, to housing
which is done by hard cement blocks,
this hardening process, which is a neologism,
this process doesn't take place
while the land is
an exclusively private land.
On State lands, we will see that
this process takes place
much more rapidly because the residents
almost have the guarantee of
never being driven out.
So here, in a normal urban fabric
we can clearly see the slum areas.
So we are already in
a period of restructuring.
We see that we are dealing with
a framework here
while we are dealing with another type
of blueprint which is lower.
Second scenario, also compared to
unstable neighborhoods, why?
Because they are largely under-equipped.
So indeed have a screening,
of lots, of roads, a regular framework,
but we have all the other characteristics,
aside from the land ones, which are
the characteristics of a slum.
So the lack of infrastructure, poverty,
housing instability ,
all these indicators which we have
previously seen,
we find them once again, the only one
that we do not is
the land issue since the resident
is the owner of his plot of land.
All the other criteria, we also
assimilate it to the slum.
A photo of a slum that is
a little bit bigger.
It matters little where it is located.
We see that it is quite characteristic
of housing
which is scattered or dispersed
here and there.
And we are dealing with housing
that is relatively dense.
So if we do the density we will be more
at 350, 400 residents per hectare,
which is relatively high.
Two images of this type of density.
The top one, in the fringes of the city.
The second, about the slum
that we are going to look at,
the Kebba of El Mina,
where we see that there are
two types of materials,
firstly there are units, which are
metal canisters,
which are unfolded, we find, which form
the units, and then there are also
the old wooden port crates
which are now replaced, little by little
by containers,
but which have allowed the building
of shanties that are passable.
So we have shanties that are in
very precise units,
which are the metal canisters,
or the wooden crates.
So let's get to the heart of the matter with
this slum in Nouakchott
and make an inventory of
the current situation.
So for the moment, before the project,
of course, we were dealing with
a powerless voluntarism to resolve
the issues of slums.
There was a will but it wasn't enough,
and a total powerlessness
in the face of this situation,
given the magnitude
of slums in the city of Nouakchott.
Here we are in 2000, 2002.
And we are going to see that we will need
10, 12, 14 years in order to, little by little,
like this, make this slum
a full-fledged part of the city.
Another thing, there was also a sort of
acceptance of informal practices.
Really, we let it happen and
we watch what happens.
Everything we let happen, it's everything
the State does not have to manage.
So that situation in which
we found ourselves in 2000,
is a situation in which we let
informal issues happen.
And at this time also, we found ourselves
in a situation where
we had tried to resolve some
problems of precarious housing
more by supression.
So we had the people flee manu militari.
The context of the city.
It's important to know that
there was a deficit of land,
of housing, of infrastructure.
and support for the local economy.
What we are going to try to do
with this project, it's exactly
to allow the stabilizing of
land tenure, it's exactly
the upgrading of housing,
meaning to raise standards.
And we are also going to see
a reinforcement of facilities
and infrastructures, which
really structures the space,
as we already saw, with the establishment,
at the same time,
of a number of activities which
can generate revenue.
It's perhaps the greatest difficulty,
this one, it's often a pious hope,
but it is extremely hard to develop
income generating activities
in the poorest of neighborhoods.
The main principles of restructuring.
Above all, it's keeping a maximum
of populations in place,
that is without a doubt,
the number one principle.
Then, we try to adapt
the norms and standards
that we are going to put in place to
the financial capacity of the residents.
This is very important.
Otherwise this means that
the residents are then going to,
after the restructuring of the slum,
find themselves in
an even more difficult, more restrictive
situation than before.
Which is absolutely not
the aim of the game, of course.
Another principle, is to give
visibility to the interventions
that are made.
It's not about sprinkling some
interventions here and there,
but it's about being systematic,
and above all
being pragmatic in the way
of doing things.
And finally, often a pious hope,
since it is rare that this works,
but the idea is to always use
the HILO method,
High Intensity Labor Force,
to put to work a maximum of people
in the restructuring of the road.
So we will choose as in certain cities,
notably in Porto-Novo,
we will choose paving rather than
asphalt for the road
since we know that for
the labor force to do the paving
is much more important than when
we are asphalting an entire street.
So it's not always possible
to do cement paving,
rock paving, the conditions
that must be met
so as to be able to get to this,
but the aim of the game would be
that all these rehabilitation programs
benefit the greatest number of people.
Let's now go to the neighborhood,
in the Kebba of El Mina,
located in the Moughataa of El Mina,
Moughataa is a municipality of Nouakchott.
Surface area of the neighborhood
which was looked at was 128 hectares.
An estimated population between
36 and 50 thousand residents.
An estimated density between
280 and 390 residents per hectare.
Unstable living conditions, of course
since it's the neighborhood
that's going to be restructured,
so it's left to be assumed that
it fulfilled a certain number
of criteria which made it a slum.
And a total absence of structure
and internal organisation,
internal organisation, meaning, official,
public, this does not mean
that there were no interest groups,
tontines, and these kinds of things,
as can be found in all neighborhoods.
Finally, one of the characteristics,
was the very strong land occupation
by the residents.
The role players.
In such a restructuring project
of the slums, we always have a contractor,
a delegated contractor, financing,
technical studies,
meaning a consulting firm that will
do that.
We will make a resettlement action plan,
there needs to be a specialist
in action plan resettlement.
A social impact study, there needs to be
an specialist in social impact studies.
A census of the entire population,
and supervision of the census.
So the main role players were,
at the time,
the City Hall of Nouakchott,
the Commissioner of Human Rights,
of Poverty Reduction and Integration,
the World Bank which was financing
via the PUD,
the Project of Urban Development,
was financing the neighborhood,
the restructuring of the neighborhood,
a consulting firm, URBAPLAN,
which did all the technical studies,
and a certain number of experts
who intervened,
throughout the process
for particular input.
What is interesting to see here,
is the number of players.
It must be said that there is not just one
City Hall that mandates an office,
but that there are many, many players
which are all partners, with whom
there must be discussion, who must be
convinced and one must articulate all
of these opinions and all these partners
so as to succeed in developing a project.
Quickly, a few images of
the diagnosis of the situation.
On the right, an image of the neighborhood
already restructured
since we have opened here, the roads,
we have the presence of
utility poles, which show
the presence of electricity.
And then here, an image, it's a well
with carters
who go to get water from the well
and then go and sell it.
So there is little or no network
of internal roads,
no network of water distribution,
no sewage system, no public lighting,
no waste pickup service, very few
primary and secondary classrooms,
no structured market,
no recreation space or
other types of developments.
So we are really dealing
with unstable situations.
Here we see carters who are waiting,
around the well, to go and deliver
or mainly fill their canisters to then
go and deliver them to
the neighborhood.
The example of spreading in a
non-structured market is that
we see extreme poverty and instability
of installations in front of the product.
Same conclusion on the issue of housing:
extreme poverty.
A few images.
So we see that the materials used
are mostly
sheet metal and wood,
as we have said previously.
Here we see a latrine, but most
of the dwellings,
of the concessions, the groups of shanties
have absolutely no latrine,
nor do they have fences,
nor foundations, nor hard materials.
And so we have an omnipresence
of materials like wood, sheet metal,
or as we can see here, even tissues
or sheets.
The principles of restructuring
which will be put in place,
we are going to create a road network,
a drinkable water supply system,
an electricity system.
We are going to build classes, classrooms,
primary schools, secondary schools
and a little market.
The principles of restructuring which
will be retained: is that we are going to
create a road network, a drinkable water
supply system, electricity.
We are going to build classrooms,
health centers.
We are going to build little structured
markets, put in place public lighting.
That is the restructuring piece.
Then for the regrouping of lands in situ,
we are going to have to, inevitably,
displace some people to
a resettlement area, which is just next to
the area that we are going to deal with.
The idea here is that we're going to
minimize the impact of the displacement.
The goal is to keep everyone in place.
And when it's not possible,
we are going to put them
on plots in the vicinity, and not displace
them in resettlement areas,
as we see in numerous cities,
which are kilometers away from
the primary area where the people live.
And so, the people that are going to
be displaced will have a land security
which people being displaced
don't always have.
So, finally, the fact of displacing people
will allow them to have a plot
with a land title.
So there is the perimeter, here,
circled in black that interests us.
And then, we have this area which
will become the resettlement area
for the population.
So we are going to create a system here,
of roads, very simple.
And then, all the people
who will not be
on these roads, will stay
in these parts here.
On the other hand,
all these dwellings here,
all these concessions here, are going to
have to migrate, then, in this zone here
which will also become a subdivision,
as we will see consequently.
The road network put in place,
we see the real right of ways
better here,
we see that all the concessions
will have to eventually leave
little by little so as to
settle in this area here.
If I take my right of way roads,
it is possible that
this shanty here belongs
to the same group, it's a family who
has a concession with three shanties.
And here if I am on a right of way,
this one here, this part should go,
this one here also.
Finally it's all three that are going to
have to move since we are not going to
let just one and move the other two
on another plot.
So we are going to have to, the impact
is not just on this road,
these right of way roads, but maybe also
much greater since we are going to
look to the left, to the right, each time
other shanties which belong
to the same people who are themselves
on the right of way roads.
Some will be paved,
some exist.
Typically we have here the existing ones.
All of this is paved, of course,
this also and this one also.
What has been done, in this case here,
is that we have tried to minimize
the impacts and be able to reattach this
to the existing urban fabric.
So we have a number of routes that
we have simply prolonged here,
which are roads which almost existed.
Then, we subdivided, in large parts,
so as to find the routes,
and then subdivided in two
these same routes, each time in two,
by large frameworks with
compacted pathways.
So what was in green, the pathways which
were not paved, and the large
pathways were paved.
Water system: there is a stand-post here,
joined with another.
We have a tertiary system which comes to
a much larger system here,
in a loop, which ensures the water supply
in all cases, which is grafted on
a larger system, which is
a primary system,
which was already existing since the water
left for the port,
so we have a system which
existed previously.
Same goes for electricity.
We review that it is, somehow,
the roads framework.
Inevitably we will use the primary,
secondary and tertiary roads
to put in the public lighting system,
this appears logical.
To put in the water system, it simpler
to create a drinkable water network
on the roads network rather than have to
go from the interior of the neighborhoods.
And then, the restructuring plan, that's for
when we open the road network.
The resettlement plan is
a plan of subdivisions
for the area which we are creating.
So, all of the people that are here,
on the road network,
are going to find themselves
in this area here, where we created,
we see each time blocks with plots
and then there is a number of other types
of plots which are stand-posts,
facilities, latrines,
commercial activities.
In brown, what we see most,
is of course, the plots for the dwellings.
So if I find myself here, I would have
without a doubt a plot somewhere here.
There you have it, the overall
restructuring plan.
We have the opening of
the road networks.
We have our facilities, our stand-posts
and our electric transformers.
We have the greatest facilities,
for example schools,
a market which will be here,
a health center, schools.
We have a range of facilities
and infrastructure to implement,
that is grouped in a synthesis plan
which is the restructuring plan.
With each time, do not forget,
the legend and of course the title block
since we need visas
and these plans have to be,
at one point given,
approved by the authority
in charge of restructuring.
Here we have an example where
this is a new route,
this is a road opening, a school
that has been built in the neighborhood
and we see that, little by little,
the people settled in these areas
which are this time, parceled with
plots that are rectangular plots.
And then, there is again the presence
of a certain number of shanties,
the people having clearly moved
their shanties.
We see that, in this area here,
there is a big difference
with what was there before, which is
the area that was really the slum.
Some images, quickly.
We are on the edge of the neighborhood.
A resettlement area, completely
unoccupied, completely flat.
A plan, which is an old plan since
we have shown the most recent plan.
But we see that we are going trough
various phases, the plan doesn't happen
at once but it is the object of numerous
negotiations and discussions.
And then, once we have defined the plan,
that we have defined what
we were going to do, we are then
going to begin the restructuring
by opening the roads.
Each person finding themselves on the road
will have to be displaced
and go in the area of resettlement,
as we say.
Previously to this, the census must
be done of all of the households
which are in the neighborhood, before
even being able to displace them.
It seems logical, to displace people,
we must know who they are beforehand.