We have seen that our magnetization
is the result of the sum
of the individual dipole moments
of all the molecules
that are present in our voxel.
Now the molecules, in general,
and certainly our body temperatures,
the molecules are moving around,
they are diffusing around.
So we have diffusion,
we have motion of the molecules
during the MR experiment.
And I want to first discuss
the nature of this motion,
and then we will go into the description
on how this affects the MR signal.
So here we have a random path,
we have a molecule,
and this will undergo some random path.
Or in more general terms,
we start at a time zero,
the molecule is here,
and after time Î” it will be
at a certain distance
displaced from its original origin.
This is the effect of self-diffusion.
So if we look at here an example,
we have at time Î”, which is 100 ms,
and in this case, this gives us
a mean displacement
of the molecules of roughly 20 microns.
If one waits for a longer time,
of course, the molecules
will diffuse further away,
and here we have, then, a distance
of 45 microns if we wait half a second.
So the molecules
will diffuse further away,
on average than with longer time.
And here, if we take an example of 1 s,
then the mean displacement
is 63 microns, and this gives
a larger extent of the motion.
This random motion diffusion
was described by Einstein.
It's the Einstein random walk,
and this mean displacement
is given by the square root
of 6 times a constant D
times the time big Î”.
D is called here
the self-diffusion coefficient,
and r is the root means square
displacement after Î” s.
So the self-diffusion coefficient
depends on a number of parameters,
it depends also on
the size of the molecule,
how easily does it diffuse,
smaller molecules move more
than bigger molecules,
and we're going to illustrate this
in the following experiment
with two different types of fluids
to illustrate the effect.
So what I'm going to do
is I'm going to take
some colored alcohol here,
pour it in, and we can see how
it starts to distribute the color.
And here we have a colored water solution.
I'll pour it in.
And now we can see the clear difference.
On the alcohol side, it's already
distributed, so fast diffusion.
The color has already distributed,
whereas with the water we can see
this is going to take quite some time
until the color is evenly distributed.
We can see that now
several minutes have lapsed,
and we can see that on the alcohol side
it's uniformly blue,
so it's very well diffused,
whereas for the water
colored solution that we put in,
it still hasn't mixed
with the uncolored water,
so it's very slow diffusion on this side.
This illustrates the effect
of molecule size on the diffusability
of the molecule.
Okay, so we've seen that molecules move,
we've it in the experiment
with the colored dyes.
They move, this motion
can depend on molecule size.
But now the question
is how does this affect
the magnetization,
in particular the phase?
We've seen that bulk motion
affects the phase in a coherent manner,
which allows us to determine
the velocity of a molecule.
And we'll go here and we'll
stick with the same principle,
we're going to look at
the magnetization phase
in complex plane.
And we're looking here now
at an experiment,
we'll do a 90-degree pulse,
we'll just, for simplicity,
assume it's a 90-degree pulse,
and now we'll turn on
the gradient in any direction,
x, y, or z, you can call it
whatever you want,
it doesn't really matter.
What is important here
is it's the same strength in both cases,
one's positive, one's negative,
or negative and positive,
and the duration is the same.
So the area is the same for
the two gradient pulses that are applied.
As we have seen before, this is a--
in terms of magnetization phase
for molecules that don't move--
is a dumb experiment.
The effect of the gradient is nil,
there will be no net phase accrued
after these two gradients
for a stationary molecule.
So let's look at the stationary case,
graphically.
We'll have the after the 90-degree pulse,
we have the magnetization all in phase.
The 90-degree pulse flips them all,
and they are all colinear.
And we have just plotted here
three positions along the gradient.
Now during the gradient period
indicated by the letter b here,
so we turn on the gradient.
What now happens
is that the magnetizations
undergo a phase evolution
depending on their position,
and that's indicated here
by the three positions.
Then comes the period c,
and this period c,
we just wait a certain amount of time.
So nothing happens,
we still have the same phase,
and we're neglecting relaxation here
in the consideration.
And now finally comes period d,
we turn on the gradient
with opposite polarity.
So we turn it on,
and now what happens is since
the gradient has opposite polarity,
the three magnetization positions--
the magnetization at the three positions--
will turn with a same precession velocity,
the Larmor frequency
but in the opposite direction,
and after the duration of this gradient--
so this area is equal to this area,
or the same amplitude,
the duration is the same--
they will all be aligned, again,
as in the original position.
And this is what I said,
this is the dumb experiment,
there's nothing interesting going on here.
We have echo formation, of course,
which is a nice feature.
Now let's look at what happens
if we allow the magnetization
to undergo motion.
So we start out with
the magnetization stationary,
here.
We turn on the gradient pulse,
so we have the encoding,
so we have the different phase.
In this case, the experiments
are the same.
And now during period c,
we will assume that there is
motion of the molecules.
So, as you can see,
the colors have changed.
So the blue molecule is now
where the orange was,
and the orange is where the blue was.
So we are assuming here,
that the molecules are being displaced,
and in this case, a very simple situation
to illustrate the principle,
we've just interchanged the position
of two of our magnetizations here.
So these are the two
that we have interchanged.
Now what happens when
we turn on the positive gradient,
we change the polarity.
Now the blue one will rephase
with the precession velocity
corresponding to this position,
but it has not had initial phase
that corresponds to this phase,
so it will actually overturn here,
whereas the orange one,
which had a bigger phase
to start with from this position,
now will only go back
according to the blue position here
so it will not completely turn back.
Now, can you guess what the effect
is on the net magnetization?
Consider here, there's no motion,
we have nice echo, we have
maximum amplitude.
Here we have the magnetization vectors
are no longer colinear.
And since what we are observing
the total magnetization
is the sum of all
magnetizations in our voxel,
the voxel magnetization is reduced.
So as a consequence,
the effect of diffusion,
which happens here during time period c,
is to reduce the signal amplitude.
We have assumed here
in this whole procedure,
that the time c is long
compared to the gradient.
This is not likely strong here,
we'll assume this is very short,
this is very short,
and this is relatively long,
so we'll only consider motion
during the time period c.
So now I want to do this
with magnetization vectors.
The animation will
start here in condition a,
so we have all the magnetization
vectors lined up,
they are colinear,
and the net transverse
magnetization is maximally.
As we go through the gradient,
we have dephasing,
according to their positions.
Then we will look at displaced spins,
so we have them colinear
at the beginning,
we have also dephasing,
so this is the same.
Now we'll assume
that for the displaced spins,
for these guys, that they will
change position among each other,
so similar to the case here,
so they will be returning back
but now with different
precessional velocities.
Here, we'll consider
the static magnetization,
they are not exchanging position.
So when we do now, and this
has happened now for these spins here,
here nothing has happened,
here they have changed position.
And now we'll turn on
the positive gradient.
For the static magnetization
we come back to the maximum
magnetization possible,
but for those who have
undergone diffusion,
they no longer end up colinear,
and now if we do the vector addition
of these vector sums here
of these magnetizations,
we end up with a net magnetization
that's not equal to four times here,
and so the transverse
magnetization is reduced.
So this is the consequence
of random motion on the MR signal,
there is an amplitude reduction,
this is fair to say.
So let's look at this magnetization--
the effect of diffusion on magnetization,
I'll take another view on this.
We have time here,
we turn on the gradient,
one's positive, one's negative.
And we'll consider now, for a time T,
both with the same amplitude
but positive and negative,
and we'll look at the effect
on signal amplitude.
So we have reduction of signal amplitude,
and then when the second
gradient is turned on--
now it's the letter T
is turning on the red--
then we have an echo formation.
We have, again, dephasing
during the first time period,
then when we turn on
the second gradient,
we have rephasing that is
in the absence of incoherent motion,
that is for static magnetization.
So how do we display this
in terms of phase?
So we'll plot the phase here,
for six isochromats.
The phase is being built up
according to the six different positions
during the first gradient time.
So this is here.
Then it stays constant during
the time here between the gradients.
And when we turn on the negative gradient,
the slope is equal but opposite,
so they all come back to the same phase.
And so here that means
if the phase is the same
for all magnetization vectors,
we have maximum amplitude,
and echo formation,
maximum echo amplitude.
So now let's look at the effect
of incoherent motion,
and here I'll plot a matrix of 5x5 voxels.
We apply a gradient
in the horizontal direction,
so now, according to that position,
they are undergoing a differential phase.
This is during the first gradient.
And now what we have
during the period between the gradients,
and here we'll assume these gradients
are very small in duration,
this period is very long by comparison,
and again, this is relatively short.
So now we have no gradient
during the time between the gradients,
but we will assume during this time,
that some molecules undergo diffusion.
Of course, we cannot draw 10^23 molecules
so I've just taken three pairs here
that during this process
we'll have assumed
that they have exchanged positions
to illustrate the case.
This is all in the direction
of the gradient,
which is in the horizontal direction.
It doesn't matter
what you call this direction,
x, y, or z, whichever, it's just
the direction of the gradient.
So now these three pairs
have exchanged positions,
and when we now turn on
the negative gradient,
what is the effect that we see?
According to the position
that they have now,
the phase is turned back to
its original position.
So for the static magnetizations,
we can see here they're all colinear,
these guys here, these guys,
these guys, et cetera.
They're all colinear, so that is for them
is maximum signal amplitude.
But for these magnetizations,
which have undergone diffusion
in this animation,
their magnetization vectors
no longer are colinear,
and therefore, if you now sum
all the 25 magnetization vectors here,
the net magnetization,
the amplitude has been reduced.
So if I draw now this phase
as a function of time with diffusion,
so we'll look at the phase,
it's a build up,
and then when we go down
with a negative gradient,
the slope is no longer the same
for all these six isochromats
because they have exchanged positions.
So we end up at the end
of the second gradient,
with a magnetization and phase dispersion
that is no longer the same,
and therefore we have at this point--
because they're not all in phase--
we have a reduced echo amplitude.
So this is the graphical
intuitive explanation
of what happens during diffusion.
So, now how do we describe
the effect of diffusion on the MR signal
in a more quantitative way?
We'll do this here, and we will have
a consideration on
what it is that reduces the signal.
Now we have to think about here,
the reduction of the signal is a fact
that the molecules are displaced
by a certain distance during a time
between the two gradients.
This distance of displacement
is the sole mechanism by which
the amplitude is reduced
because when we're
refocused with a gradient,
they are at different position
and the difference in phase
compared to the initial phase
is what reduces the signal.
So what are the factors
that reduce the signal amplitude?
One is, of course, the strength
of the diffusion process.
If the diffusion process is very strong,
that is the molecules diffuse easily,
then we have a large displacement,
so it's the diffusion process,
and this is the diffusion constant.
Now if we look at an experiment
with a positive gradient here,
of amplitude G, and a negative gradient
of same amplitude G,
the duration of the gradient is small ğ›¿,
and they are separated by this time big âˆ†.
Then what is the next factor
that influences the distance
at the beginning and at the end
of the experiment, the mean distance,
that's the time between
the dephasing and rephasing gradient,
that's the time big âˆ†.
And finally, the phase is also dependent
on the strength of the gradient.
It's precisely not just the strength
but it's the integral of the gradient.
So if we have a strong gradient
for a long time period,
the magnetization vectors spread out
much more.
And then we apply the same gradient,
so for the same position
the phase difference between
original position and the end position
is going to be bigger,
and therefore the signal
is stronger attenuated.
So it's the area of the dephasing gradient
that influences, as well,
the signal reduction.
Now I'm going to--
this is the example of a gradient echo
that's sensitizing the diffusion process--
now I'm going to give you
the mathematical formulation of this
but not the derivation of this.
We're just going to concern ourselves
with the result of this process.
So the attenuation of the signal,
due to diffusion
in the direction of the gradient--
of course, if there's
diffusion perpendicular,
we won't be able to measure that,
there's no influence on the signal phase--
is actually described by a signal
in the absence of diffusion, S0--
that's this term here--
times e^(-bD).
That's a simple equation,
[an empirical] equation,
it works very well for a free liquid
that is like the color dyes
that we have seen.
D is the diffusion process,
b is an experimental parameter,
and b is the so-called
b factor or b value,
and here is the exact value given.
So it's first the accrued phase,
so it's gradient times duration
times Î³, squared,
times big Î” minus small ğ›¿ over 3.
So if the small ğ›¿ is small,
the duration of the gradient is small
compared to this time,
then this is essentially the duration,
this is the gradient area,
that's this area here, squared.
That's the b factor and, like I said,
I don't want to go through
the mathemetical derivation
of this expression here,
we'll just satisfy us
with the equation here.
So b is the parameter
that the operator can choose.
We can choose the big Î”,
we can choose the small ğ›¿,
and we can choose the gradient strength.
That's the experimental parameter
that we can choose,
and D describes the diffusion process.
Now in this case, it's not
the self-diffusion coefficient
in magnetic resonance,
it is called the apparent diffusion
coefficient or ADC
because it's an apparent diffusion
that one measures
and it is not necessarily the true
diffusion of the molecule.
Although, in the case of free water,
for example, we can very well
quantitatively measure this ADC,
and from the ADC measurement--
because this changes with temperature--
we can actually determine,
to a very good precision,
the temperature of the water sample.
Now the sequence
that I've shown you here--
that's diffusion weighting, it introduces
this weighting into the signal--
can also be done with a spin echo.
So we have the two gradients,
now they are positive
because between them
we've inserted a 180-degree pulse.
So, as you remember,
for static magnetization,
positive gradients, the effect
of 180-degree pulse
is to refocus the static
magnetization here.
So that would be the equivalent
sequence with a spin echo,
above we have the gradient echo,
and the spin echo has the advantage,
it is only dependent on T2,
and T2 is always longer than T2*,
so one can use longer diffusion times,
big Î”, with this approach.