So, for the situation of a liquid sample,
a fluid that's stationary,
the situation is fairly simple.
Now, in reality, in living tissue,
we're confronted
with a more complex situation,
and that is we have cells,
we have membranes,
and so the water molecules
cannot diffuse at their free will
in all directions as they wish
as they would in a beaker.
So we're considering here two cases:
one is an axon, so that's the nerve fiber
that connects neurons in the brain;
or muscle cells, muscle is myofibrils.
These are one-dimensional structures.
Here's the example of myelin,
so the axon is in here
with the microtubules and neurofilaments,
we have cell membrane,
and then the myelin sheath
encasing the axon.
So it's a one-dimensional structure,
you can think of it as a tube,
and we'll consider the membranes--
this is simplification--
but we'll consider them
for the sake of the argument--
that they are impermeable
to the water molecules.
In three-dimensions
this is what a bundle of nerves,
or muscle cells, would look like.
They're one-dimensional,
for the nerve cells in the axons,
here is the myelin sheath,
they are lined up like this.
And now what we are going to consider
is the motion in the cells.
And so we have inside the cell,
we have the molecule
that is confined to the cell,
and between the cells
the molecule can move
a little bit further.
So a molecule that is between the cells,
it can essentially move
in the extracellular space
from my right here, to my left here.
If it's inside the cell, it's stuck
to the volume of the cell.
And the following experiment
visually demonstrates this with a colloid,
the motion of particles,
and you'll see that some particles
can move more freely than others.
So what we see here
is there's some particles
that are fixed by the glass
in the microscope.
They're colloids, but you see
the smaller objects
that are moving between them,
the smaller particles,
and this is similar to the water molecules
that we have in the tissue.
They're diffusing around
in the free space,
but you can also see
that there are some molecules,
or some of the smaller particles,
they bump into the bigger ones
and they can't pass them.
This is akin to the situation
that we have in living tissue
where the water molecules
bump into cell membranes,
and they have to go around the membranes,
or they're stuck within the cells.
So consequence is, if you look here,
in this is a cut
perpendicular to the cells,
the molecule here is inside the cell,
is stuck to the dimensions of the cell--
this is typically a micron--
extracellularly it can diffuse further,
although it has to diffuse
around the cells.
If you now look at a cut along the axon,
here along the cell structure,
now the distance is pretty much
much longer, and pretty much unrestricted.
So consider the motion here,
and the motion here.
Here the mean displacement
can be much bigger
than the mean displacement is here.
So with a restricted motion
by cell membranes
in one-dimensional structures
like we see often in nature--
in the brain and in the muscle--
the motion is restricted by membranes,
and the membrane structure
is not isotropic,
the cell structure is not isotropic.
So what does this mean?
We are getting, clearly here,
this distance is much smaller
than this distance,
we're getting an anisotropic
mean displacement,
and from Einstein's equation,
we're getting an anisotropic
diffusion coefficient.
So what does this mean?
This means that depending
whether I measure
in the direction of the axon,
or perpendicular, that is if I apply
the gradient perpendicular--
I mentioned the motion
perpendicular to the axon--
here the motion is restricted
to a small distance.
If my gradient is along
the direction of the axon
in this direction,
the mean displacement is larger,
and so depending
what type of gradient I apply,
I get a different apparent
diffusion coefficient,
and this is spatially anisotropic.
So consequently, the diffusion coefficient
that one measures,
the apparent diffusion coefficient,
depends on the gradient orientation.
This is mathematically--
a good approach
is to describe this mathematically
by a diffusion tensor D_i_j.
What is this mathematically?
Well, basically, it's a 3 x 3 matrix,
and here it is.
So this is what describes
the diffusion process.
Now let's look at some examples
to convince ourselves that this is real.
So here's a diffusion-weighted image,
so we're looking at just
the diffusion weighting,
the gradient is applied along z.
So this means it is going
perpendicular to the plane.
Bright means very little diffusion,
dark means a lot of diffusion.
So here we have a lot of diffusion,
here we have very little,
and here, in this area,
we have substantial diffusion,
the signal is strongly attenuated.
So bright is less attenuation,
dark is a lot of attenuation.
Now, the next image is the diffusion
in the x direction,
so this is horizontal.
And now, notice this area here.
I'll go back.
Here, it's the same image,
here we had not so much diffusion,
and here it gets essentially dark,
so there's a lot of diffusion.
And this is the area
of the corpus callosum.
The corpus callosum, if you think of it,
that's the bus, that's the ribbon cable
that connects the nerve fibers
from the right hemisphere
and the left hemisphere.
It's like a ribbon bus.
In this direction are the orientation
of all the axons,
and they're very colinear aligned,
so we have a lot of diffusion,
right-left in this direction.
And that's why, if we apply the gradient
in right-left orientation,
this signal is strongly attenuated.
Here also, as you can see,
it's very much not attenuated,
so it's bright, and here it gets dark,
the same area.
So also here we have
right-left orientation
of the diffusion process.
And, finally, we're looking
at the diffusion process
from front to back,
so from here to here,
and now we can see, again,
corpus callosum
is regaining its intensity here,
here again.
And now we have these areas
that are losing intensity,
here and here.
Can you guess what we're looking at there?
So this is the back of the head,
here, is the back of the head,
the eyes are in the front.
Now, what we are looking at here
is the optic nerve,
the connection from the eyeballs
to the back of the head,
the primary visual cortex
where the primary processing
of visual information occurs.
So we're seeing that directionality here.
Notice that in all three images
this area is always dark.
That's the ventricles,
it's filled with cerebrospinal fluid,
so it behaves like free water.
It's isotropic,
and since there's no membrane restriction
for water in that space,
it will have a much higher
diffusion coefficient in that area.
And that's why it is seen dark
and isotropic in all three cases.
So this is isotropic diffusion
for the cerebrospinal fluid, or CSF.
Now, we have seen the diffusion tensor,
and there's one property
that this diffusion tensor has:
it's a symmetric tensor.
Now, here we have to make use
of some things that you might remember
from your linear algebra course--
or then you have to accept it here--
if you have a 3 x 3 matrix
that is symmetric,
and so real numbers,
then we can characterize it
with three orthogonal eigenvectors.
And if we choose to describe
this diffusion tensor in a basis system
where x corresponds to one eigenvector,
y to another one, and z to another one,
then the mathematical description
of the diffusion
is given by the eigenvalues.
So here, we have one eigenvector
in this direction,
usually λ_1 is the biggest one,
and λ_2 and λ_3
are the two other eigenvectors.
And if we choose that
as our coordinate system
for describing the coordinates,
then in this coordinate system
our diffusion tensor now becomes
a diagonal matrix
with these three diffusion processes
describing the diffusion
along the first eigenvector,
second eigenvector, and third eigenvector.
And so this is the experiment
that one can do,
one can actually obtain
this diffusion tensor.
One can obtain the mean diffusivity.
This is the trace of the tensor,
and that overall is actually
a not very interesting information.
We can see the cerebrospinal fluid,
but the rest of the image,
as you notice here, is pretty much gray,
so there is not a huge difference
in mean diffusivity across the brain.
Take now here, an example.
This is the fractional anisotropy--
that's another parameter
which one can characterize--
and typically we have the situation
for one-dimensional structures,
that λ_2 and λ_3 are small,
they are corresponding
to a small displacement,
λ_1 along the direction of the axon
is the big displacement.
So if we look at the difference of this
to the other two,
this gives us the fractional anisotropy--
the two formulae are different,
but I don't want to go
into the details here,
I want to stick with the principal--
what this measures is the difference
between the biggest eigenvector
and the other two,
the fractional anisotropy.
And now we can see there's
a lot of spatial information here.
So it basically measures,
how much is this ellipsoid,
described by the three eigenvalues,
how much this is cigar-shaped,
or it is round.
So fractional anisotropy that is zero
means isotropic diffusion.
So zero is here, so we have
isotropic diffusion.
We have also, largely
in the gray matter, isotropic diffusion.
This is, however, a reflection of the fact
that we no longer have
an oriented structure in the gray matter.
But now we can see corpus callosum,
like I mentioned, this is the bus,
very ordered structure,
the fractional anisotropy is very high.
Optic nerve here,
we've seen that example also.
It's essentially
the white matter structures
where we have the fractional anisotropy,
and this is where the axons,
the cabling between
the brain cells, occurs.
Now, finally, therefore, in each voxel
we can determine the diffusion tensor.
Once we've determined
the diffusion tensor,
we can determine in each voxel
the direction of the major eigenvector,
so that is the direction
of the largest eigenvalue,
and then color the image
with pseudocolor intensity.
So this gives us
pseudocolor directionality.
Here's the image, we're going to now
look at a box cutout here.
And if you look now in this box here,
we can see for each of the voxels
an ellipsoid describing the orientation
of the diffusion tensor is drawn.
We have in red, left-right,
we have in green, top-bottom,
and blue, front to back.
Actually, I'm sorry, this is
the other way around.
In blue is top-bottom,
and in green is front to back.
Red is right to left,
and this is a generally accepted norm,
how this is pseudocolored.
So if one now takes this image here--
so this diffusion tensor
image of a brain--
and color codes onto directionality
of the principal eigenvector,
we have here, of course, right-left,
we have here, top-bottom,
as we've seen on the previous image,
here is right-left again,
and green is front to back
in this case.
Actually, here it's different,
the blue is out of the screen.
This is an example of a rat brain,
so, again, color-coded.
And we have here, now, the rat brain
has very little white matter.
The white matter is essentially
this structure here,
and the rest is gray matter,
yet we can see directionality.
Let's look at this,
so red means right to left, here,
and here we have top to bottom,
but this is gray matter,
this structure here, that's cortex.
So what does this mean?
In here it goes between red and blue,
the color changes.
This basically means
that the diffusion process
is perpendicular to the surface.
There's a directionality
of the diffusion process
of the water diffusion in the cortex
in the gray matter of the rat
that is perpendicular to the surface.
And this reflects some
of the neuronal structures
which are very laminar-columnar
in organization,
so the cells are perpendicular
to the surface,
protruding through the cortical layers.
And this directionality can be picked up
with diffusion imaging,
and displayed as such.
So I want to give you some examples
of what has the neuroscience community
very much excited,
and that is the ability
to quantify this anisotropy.
So, if one does an image
of the diffusion anisotropy,
we have the ellipsoids
in each voxel here-- that's a cutout--
the color-coded maps of the diffusivity,
the direction anisotropy.
And now what is being done
is determining each voxel
the principal direction of diffusion.
Then we do it for the next voxel,
which may be like this,
and then the next voxel.
And we'll suppose that this diffusion
is provided by a bundle of nerves,
of axons, that go along the direction
of the principal eigenvector,
the vector with the biggest eigenvalue.
So in this case, we would get a connection
of the voxels in this direction.
And this is then done to connect
the adjacent voxels,
and one obtains with that,
spaghetti-like images.
So here is a cut from the brain,
so we're looking on the top of the brain,
this is the left side,
this is the right side.
And here we can see the corpus callosum,
the connection between right and left,
and these are all the projections
of white matter into gray matter.
And this is now a view from the top,
again, we have the optic nerve going here,
we have the corpus callosum
being connected,
and we have some other connections
perpendicular.
So this gives us a spaghetti-like
representation of the connections.
One can establish with that
the fiber tracks,
and, finally, one can ask the question,
"Which part of the brain
is connected to which part?"
This provides information on probability
that if we take a brain region here
and another brain region here,
what is the probability
that there indeed exists a connection,
in terms of cabling,
between these brain regions.
Thus leads to a whole brain structural
connection network,
or also known as a connectome.
So these are applications that have
neuroscience very excited.
One gets inside in the individual subject
on which parts of the brain
are connected somehow,
how they are connected,
and, in some diseases,
how much these connectivities
are perturbed by the disease in question.