In this section
I'd like to do a comparison
of the bio-imaging modalities
that we have treated in this course,
both Part 1 and Part 2,
put them in juxtaposition,
so we have an easy overview
of which imaging modality can do what.
Now, there's a question
that one always has:
what is the best imaging modality?
Did you guess it?
Well, you might know that we are doing
a lot of magnetic resonance imaging,
so you might expect
that the politically correct answer
is MRI.
Well, that is wrong.
There is no such thing
as a perfect imaging modality.
And what's really important here
is each one of them
has its strengths and weaknesses,
has its domains of application,
and therefore is best used
for certain applications.
So I want to first discuss here,
the contrast mechanisms and limitations.
So on the left we'll have
the contrast mechanisms,
and on the right the major limitations
for each of the techniques.
Computer tomography, or X-ray,
primarily has as its contrast mechanism,
the electron density
and the effective atomic number Z.
What are its limitations?
It is essentially limited
to strong electron density differences--
so it's bone tissue
or air tissue interfaces,
where we have strong
electron density variations.
The other limitation
is that it uses ionizing radiation.
If we look at the emission
computer tomography techniques--
SPECT, single-photon emitters,
and PET, positron emitters--
the contrast mechanism here
is the distribution
of the exogenously-administered
tracer in the tissue.
So we administer a radioactive substance,
a decaying substance,
measure its radioactivity, measure
that distribution of the radioactivity,
in the tissue.
These techniques are limited
to the γ emitters that are available,
and, in general, they don't have uniform
spatial resolution and/or sensitivity;
we have seen the impact of collimation
on the spatial resolution for SPECT;
we have also seen the impact
of the scintillation crystal dimensions
on spatial resolution of PET,
and that sensitivity
is not necessarily uniform either.
How about magnetic resonance?
Magnetic resonance is, the signal is
proportional to equilibrium magnetization,
so, in essence, physically it measures
the spin concentration.
I'm not putting it here
as a contrast mechanism fully;
it's in parenthesis because
there is not a lot of contrast
from the spin concentration--
that is, the concentration
of water in tissue, per se.
The major mechanism that we have discussed
and that is being used
are the relaxation processes--
the relaxation of magnetization
is the major mechanism
that produces contrast.
We have also seen that with spectroscopy
one can distinguish
the chemical environment
of the hydrogen nucleus in the tissue,
and for MRI, the major application here
is to distinguish whether the signal
that one observes is due to fat or water,
based on the chemical shift.
We have also--that is this week--
discussed the effect
of motion and diffusion.
So these are the major
contrast mechanisms
that we have discussed in this course.
But I'll put etc. here--
there are, of course,
many more contrast mechanisms for MRI
that we have not discussed in this course.
We have stuck here
to some of the main features
of mechanisms
that contribute to contrast.
There are, of course, many more
that can be exploited in MRI.
The limitation of magnetic resonance
is its sensitivity.
While we can imagine
imaging a few picomolar
of positron emitters in the body,
a few picomolar of spins is not
going to give us a measurable signal;
we're stuck here
with a low-sensitivity technique.
This is compensated by using the signal
of water with the Boltzmann distribution.
This gives, however, then,
again, a strong signal.
The other part is, the measurement
is time-consuming and motion-sensitive.
It typically, for an image,
takes a few minutes.
It's very motion-sensitive--
compare this with CT where the image
can be obtained in a few seconds.
And another limitation is,
it is of course, a complex methodology.
We have so many different mechanisms
that contribute to contrast--
that means we have so many different
ways of manipulating the magnetization--
that this results, in the end,
in a complex methodology
that needs to be
carefully mastered and controlled
to produce reproducible results.
Lastly, the ultrasound technique,
which we introduced at the beginning
of Module 1 of this course,
it detects the boundaries
between two tissues
with different mechanical properties
from the acoustic impedance.
That is determining
the creation of an echo.
The down-side is that ultrasound
does not penetrate hard objects--
so, not through bone.
If you want to do
an ultrasound of the brain,
it is not easily done in adults.
It is done in newborns
where the skull is still open,
this bone has not closed yet.
Someone can put the transducer
here on the top of the head
and obtain an ultrasound of the brain
in newborn babies.
So, I want to continue with the comparison
of the techniques here
and first address the question,
how do we maximize sensitivity?
For computer tomography,
this is actually relatively simply done--
we increase the radiation dose;
we bombard the organ with more photons
then we increase the sensitivity there.
So we increase the radiation dose;
practically, this is done
by increasing
the filament current and voltage.
For the techniques SPECT and PET,
we can increase the tracer dose--
so this will increase the number
of radiotracers in the tissue
and therefore increase
the number of events, the photons,
that one can detect.
And, finally, for magnetic resonance,
we can increase one parameter
and that's the magnetic field.
Remember, the sensitivity
for magnetic resonance
is determined
by the equilibrium magnetization--
that's the strongest signal one can get--
and that is proportional
to the magnetic field;
that is the major factor with which
one can experimentally
increase the sensitivity.
So, what are these increases limited by?
In CT, essentially nothing,
except for, in human application,
the radiation dose--
we cannot just bombard our patient
with unlimited amounts of radiation.
Same holds true for the emission computer
tomography techniques like SPECT and PET;
however, there is another effect--
even if you stay within the limits,
as you increase the number
of decays in the body,
the probability of scattering increases
and therefore the probability
of random events increases,
and therefore, the dose is limited
by these kind of events;
we have only a finite
coincidence interval for PET,
it cannot go for infinitely short
coincidence intervals,
and at some point the randoms
and the scatter will take over
the gains in sensitivity from increasing
the tracer dose, and it goes down.
So there is a optimum sensitivity
that one can get.
And magnetization?
For MR, it is limited
by the equilibrium magnetization
due through the Boltzmann distribution.
Those are the limits there.
Now, we have to think of the cost
or the implications of this:
increase in radiation dose:
increase in the filament current.
That is just dialing up
the current on the filament,
so it's heating the filament more.
Increasing the tracer dose
is more expensive;
we inject more molecules,
[inaudible] have to synthesize more.
Increase in the magnetic field--it's not
just increasing the current in the magnet,
it is actually building a new magnet,
and this is very costly
and not easily done.
So it is a trend of our time that
we go to higher and higher fields.
Now, what about
the cost of these techniques?
We had ultrasound, which is not
on this list here because I excluded it;
ultrasound is the cheapest modality
of the modalities discussed.
Then it's CT.
Then comes SPECT
for instrumentation purposes.
The next more expensive technique is PET,
if one neglects the cost
of producing the isotopes.
If you include the radiochemistry unit,
that produces the isotopes on site,
then you have to think of a cyclotron
that you have to buy and maintain
and a team of radiochemists--
that makes the cost different.
If you can buy it from elsewhere
then the scanner itself
is a bit more expensive
than the SPECT scanner.
And, finally, MRIs are
the most expensive instruments to buy.
There the price increases
with magnetic field.
We have high-end academic
or clinical MRIs at 3 Tesla,
and some scanners now are available
for human experimentation at 7 Tesla.
So the cost goes--
as we have introduced the techniques
in the course, the cost has increased.
So, image reconstruction--
I want to look
at how image reconstruction is done,
summarize that.
For CT, SPECT and PET,
the image reconstruction
depends crucially on knowing
the directionality of the photon.
In CT it's done by the emission
of the photon and the detection,
this gives a line;
together with an anti-scatter grid,
this gives us the directionality
of the photon--there it's defined.
For SPECT we do collimation--
this defines the directionality
of the photon.
And for PET we have coincidence detection;
from the simultaneity of events,
the directionality of the photons
are established.
And we have seen,
once we have the directionality
of the detection process, of the photons,
we can write the signal
that is being measured
in the form of a Radon transform,
and once we have a Radon transform,
we can use projection reconstruction
to reconstruct the image.
So for these techniques,
projection reconstruction
is a major method of image reconstruction.
For magnetic resonance,
the image reconstruction
is based on a different mechanism,
it's based on the precession
of the transverse magnetization,
under the influence of a gradient.
So the precession frequency
depends on position,
and one does a frequency analysis
of the signal that's being registered.
A frequency analysis
of the signal being registered
basically means
we're doing a Fourier transform.
So while we have,
for the X-ray techniques,
projection reconstruction as the
preferred image reconstruction approach,
for magnetic resonance
we have Fourier transformation
which is the widely used
gold standard in this technique.
Finally, a word on contrast agents.
As a reminder, contrast agents are
substances that are injected into the body
that change the contrast
of the image modality.
We've had, in CT and X-ray,
the contrast agents
are typically compounds with high Z.
We have seen the example in Lecture 3
that just a few millimolar
of a high Z component
can produce a strong change
in the linear attenuation coefficient.
Most compounds that are used
are iodine-based for CT,
but we've also had
the example of gadolinium.
And, for magnetic resonance,
the contrast agents are compounds
that shorten the relaxation times,
be it T_1, T_2, or T_2 star.
There is no contrast agent
that can prolong the relaxation time.
The contrast agents in MR
are typically lanthonides like gadolinium,
they are molecules that are paramagnetic,
they have unpaired electrons in the atoms.
These unpaired electrons
carry a magnetic spin,
so they increase the fluctuation
of the magnetic field
and therefore, they can only do so
by shortening the relaxation times.
So these are the major contrast agents
that we have discussed in this course.
So now, what is the
right bioimaging modality?
This is a question that one
is very often confronted with
and it is useful to know
some basic considerations.
These are general considerations,
they may vary in specific cases,
but I've tried to do here a sort of
a general chart to guide us a little bit
on what we would consider.
Well, if we want a rapid
and least invasive assessment
of a tissue that's fairly close
to the surface--
so rapid, least invasive,
least intrusive,
nearly bedside, or bedside,
and it's tissue close to the surface--
in this case, ultrasound is the technique
that one would want to choose.
There's a limitation though--
if, between the tissue
that you're interested in,
and the detector, the transducer--
if there is air or bone between,
that creates artifacts,
in that case it's not a good choice.
I mention the air here because
this is one of the major reasons
why one uses the ultrasound gel
on the transducer,
put on the skin so that there are
no air pockets in there
that produce these artifacts.
If one is interested in a rapid scan
with high spatial resolution,
and/or contrast between air tissue
and bone tissue,
then the technique to use is X-ray.
We've discussed here in the course
the 2-D imaging technique,
computer tomography.
This can scan very rapidly
and the primary contrast that's produced
is between air tissue and bone tissue.
Finally, if one is interested
in metabolism, imaging receptors,
glucose metabolism,
transport and perfusion,
then one has SPECT and PET
as the techniques to be used here--
the metabolic imaging techniques
and blood flow imaging techniques,
the emission computed tomography, SPECT,
and positron emission
tomography techniques.
If you'd like to know something
about the biochemical information
of tissue,
then we have NMR spectroscopy,
the chemical information
that magnetic resonance provides
can give us important insight
into the biochemical composition
of tissue,
for example, in diagnostic MRI,
the distinction between fat and water
is very often used.
If you would like to have
exquisite soft tissue contrast
with millimeter spatial resolution,
in rodent's 100 microns,
the exquisite soft tissue contrast,
then MRI is your technique to use.
Contrast this with X-ray--
it's fast, but the soft tissue contrast
and what is between soft tissues,
the electron density
doesn't vary enormously,
it is much more difficult to see.
MRI there provides an abundance
of contrast in the tissue.
The limitation for MRI
is that immobile spins,
although they carry a magnetization,
their magnetization, once it's excited,
the transverse relaxation,
be it T_2 or T_2 star,
is so fast that for practical reasons,
it's very difficult, if not impossible,
to reliably image.
Some specialized acquisitions occur
but as a general rule of thumb,
it is not observable,
so membranes, cell membranes,
don't produce a measurable signal,
although they carry a magnetization,
and bones typically doesn't.
So compare that to CT--
bone is the major contrast mechanism;
in MRI, bone is not contributing
to the signal.
If one wishes to get
functional information,
then the technique to use here is MRI,
particularly in the brain
with functional MRI
or BOLD fMRI-- we've discussed that.
This is based on the deoxygenation
of the blood vessels in the brain.
It has, 25 years ago, replaced PET
as the premier functional
imaging technique,
this is now being done
with magnetic resonance imaging.
This technique, T_2 star-weighted imaging,
is not very applicable
close to air tissue interfaces,
so the sinuses in the head,
the ear canals,
these produce, on these images,
signal fallouts,
which are not easily recoverable.
So it's hard to measure activation
very close to these tissue interfaces,
such as the nucleus accumbens
in the brain,
the olfactory bulb in humans--
in rats it's easier, the olfactory bulb
is just sitting under the snout.
And finally, if one wants
to image moving blood--
that's angiography--
we actually have a number
of techniques available.
With MRI--I've given you
in this week's lecture at the beginning
an example of how MRI
can encode moving blood.
But there are multiple ways to do this
aside from what I've shown you today.
In computer tomography,
one can depict the blood vessels
with contrast agents
and, of course, with Doppler ultrasound,
we can also detect moving blood,
and there, we can even do it in real time.
So these are some rough charts.
What is our interest?
What is the preferred technology there?
We have to consider some limitations
for the X-ray techniques
and that is multiple exposures
limit it's applicability--
you do not want to go
ten times a year into a CT scanner,
if you're a healthy young volunteer.
However, if the condition
is life-threatening, it may matter less.
I'll come with an example.
And for everything that has to do
with magnetic resonance,
we have to consider
that we have a big magnet,
if you carry a pace-maker,
an insulin pump,
a defibrillator, in your body,
or metallic implants,
then this is not the technique
for you to be used.
You're excluded from this technique.
So consider, as an example, you have
a subject that comes to the clinic.
He's unconscious,
probably had a stroke in the brain,
and one wants to determine
the extent of the stroke, for example,
or whether it's indeed a stroke.
Typically, one way to detect this
is the mid-line in the brain
is displaced in one direction.
The person is an elderly person,
you do not want to put them
necessarily into an MRI
unless you're absolutely sure
there's no pacemaker
or any metallic implant in the body--
the consequences are devastating.
However, to just detect
whether the mid-line is displaced
in the CT there's sufficient contrast,
this is done in a few seconds,
it's also fast, gives you
a fast assessment in this case.
So there you would use--
even though the soft tissue contrast
is not very good, it is sufficient
to detect the medical question at hand.
Likewise, if you have a tumor
with a chance for treatment,
and a PET or SPECT scan
allows you to determine the area
of the neoplastic cells--
that is the cells
that multiply and divide--
you might have the choice between
not being properly treated and dying,
or the choice of being
overexposed to X-rays,
and potentially dying from cancer later,
induced by the X-rays.
So in this case, the choice is a question
of which one is worse,
or the choice of the lesser evil,
and one might want
to stick with the CT techniques.
So that's the overview of the techniques.
In the next section I will just do
a visual summary, with examples,
of the imaging modalities in the course.
Let's look at an example
of the different modalities for the brain.
If we look at the skull--
for X-ray imaging,
the skull has a lot of electron density,
calcium, so there's more scattering,
it get's in the way of brain imaging.
So it is not as good a technique.
And so here we're looking at an image now,
this image has been skull-stripped,
now this is not what it implies,
physically,
it's not stripping the skull
off the patient,
it's stripping it by software means,
so we don't see the signal from the skull,
we're just looking at the soft tissue.
And you can see on the left,
we have exquisite contrast
with the gray-white matter,
and on the right, on the CT scan,
it is essentially grayish
for the same slice in the same subject,
we're seeing not as much contrast
on the CT scan.
Here we compare a PET scan on the right--
we have an area of high uptake,
and on the T_1-weighted image,
we're seeing here an alteration
on the image here,
and what the PET scan tells us,
the location of where there is
the uptake
of this particular tracer, FBPA.
Here's an example from a macaque brain,
this is a T_1-weighted image
of the brain--
we see some gyrification.
This is a T_2-weighted image--
we see alteration here;
this image is flipped,
so we have here
the uptake of the PET tracer
corresponding to this area.
Looking at contrast agents,
we can see four images here.
Take a few seconds and guess
which one is the CT scan,
which one is the MRI scan...
Did you guess it?
Guess which one has the contrast agent:
which one is before, which one is after?
Okay. So the top row is a CT scan--
we can see the bone very bright,
the soft tissue contrast is not exquisite,
on the MRI we see the fat
and we have exquisite soft tissue contrast
in the MRI.
And we see, on the left,
the pre-contrast agent administration--
so that's the native image,
we see something is going on here--
now here on the MRI,
the contrast agent tells us,
at the periphery of this lesion,
there's a lot of uptake
for the contrast agent.
Contrast agents for MRI
are typically limited to the blood,
so if we see uptake into the tissue,
it means that that part of the
blood-brain barrier has been ruptured--
these are, of course, brain scans--
and this is typically the zone
where the aggressive cancerous cells are.
The inside does not have much blood flow,
so it's most likely a necrotic core.
Likewise, here with the CT scan,
one can see some alteration
of the normal structure,
and the one sees here,
where the arrows point,
the uptake of the contrast agent
at the edge of the tumor--
this is where the blood-brain barrier
has been ruptured,
where there is vascularization
and aggressive growth of cells.
Here's an example
of a high-grade astrocytoma.
We have four different contrasts
to consider:
T_1-weighted image
after contrast administration
gives us here the rim of the tumor--
this is post-contrast;
we have the T_2-weighted image,
at 30 milliseconds,
one sees something going on here--
80 milliseconds very clear,
that T_2 in this area of the brain
has been prolonged.
A longer T_2--and T_2-weighted image
bright means longer T_2--
a longer T_2 means disruption
of cellular membranes,
of proteins and so on,
there's less of that,
the fluid content of the brain
has increased.
This is a hallmark of tumors
but it's also a hallmark of edema,
so these two cannot be distinguished.
Well, we see here, there's
a diffuse hyperintensity in this area,
all over the area,
we see there is a rim of high-uptake
of the contrast agent,
there's the vascularization,
and, if one now includes the FDG-PET scan,
one can see the uptake
of glucose at this point.
This is the point where the cells are
that have a high glucose metabolic rate,
they are most likely
the cells that one wants to get out
to stop the proliferation
and the growth of the tumor.
Most likely, what we have in here,
inside here,
is necrosis and we can indeed see
there's very little uptake
of glucose at this point.
The rest that shows up bright
on the T_2-weighted image, hyperintense--
like I said, it's a reduction
of relative presence
of membranes and so on--
is most likely a reflection of edema--
so it's peritumoral edema--
that creates the increase
in T_2 in this image, most likely.
So the arrow here highlights the area
where one would go for, say,
surgical or radiotherapy treatment.
Now, I want to give
some final examples from the body.
This is a whole body PET scan,
on the left,
and a whole body MRI scan;
they are clearly different contrast--
MRI being soft tissue,
PET, depending on the tracer
that one uses,
one traces a different process.
Here's a higher resolution--
a 3-D CT of a mouse.
We can see the skeleton
very nicely depicted,
grayish is the contrast
of the other things,
but the skeleton depicts very nicely
in three dimensions.
SPECT images of the heart
measuring heart perfusion on the bottom--
so this is indicating
a perfusion in the muscle--
this in the MRI is the muscle
and the bright area here,
that's the ventricle filled with blood;
that's what we're pumping
roughly every second
through our circulation.
That's the job of the heart.
Here's an example of the lung--
it's a cystic fibrosis example--
we have on the top:
can you guess what modality that is?
We can see bone,
we can see the ribcage, so it is CT,
and on the bottom we have MRI.
And we can see here in this case
that there is something inside the lung
that shouldn't be there--
the lung should just be air.
So it should not be detectable
with MRI and with CT,
and this is, in this case
of cystic fibrosis,
is a major complication of this disease.
Some of you might have had pneumonia--
when you have pneumonia,
very often there is a chest X-ray
being performed just to determine
to what extent
there is fluid accumulation in the lung,
which you have to cough out
in the course of the disease.
And the final example I want to show here
is the liver--this is an ultrasound.
The liver is, of course, there's no bone
impeding the image to deliver,
so ultrasound's a good technique,
and there is also MRI here.
This is a typical structure
of a liver lobe--
this is the front of the belly,
here's the spine,
and there is some
hyperintensity in the liver,
so that can also be used for MRI,
and ultrasound is, of course,
much faster in this case.
So I wanted to give you some examples
of different techniques,
by example, by showing the images,
to put ourselves in the context
of these image modalities
that we have seen in this course.
And this concludes the entire course.
Thank you very much.
I hope you have enjoyed it.