In a previous episode we saw
that to program is to describe a
task that we want the computer to execute,
and that this task can be broken down into
data that will represent real life variables
on the one hand,
and a number of computations,
manipulations,
and operations on the other hand.
We have seen how some
computations
could operate on the data.
But if we really want it to be
a program, the
data must be able to influence the
computations.
This is what are called control structures, and it's
what we are going to have a look at
in this episode.
Until now, our programs
were simply made of instructions
that were
executed one after the other, and the
data had no influence on
the processing.
To have influence, so that the
values
of some of the data, some of the variables,
are able to alter
the strictly linear flow of the execution,
we use
what are called "control structures".
Fundamentally, there exists three
types of control structures.
First of all, the conditional branches,
which we are going to have a look at
in this episode, and which allow
to select a sequence of code
or another, depending on certain values.
Next, we have the iterations, which
allow to
repeat an entire sequence of instructions.
Finally, we have
the conditional loops, which also let us
repeat
a sequence of instructions, but
with a condition.
Let's begin with the conditional
branches, which let you skip
certain
parts of the program, or let you choose
what parts of the program to execute.
Let's take a concrete example.
Suppose for example you want to do
one thing or the other
depending on an a value
entered by the user.
Suppose for example that you want
to execute a certain sequence of
instructions if n is less than
five,
for example to print out that the
number is less
than five, and contrariwise if n
is greater or
equal to five, then you want to execute
another sequence of instructions.
Well this right here is what
we call
a conditional branch, and we are now
going to detail it's use.
To this effect, you first have
a part that begins with
the keyword "if", that will make
this branching.
Here, this "if" will let you make
a choice.
If the condition that follows it
is true, the "if" will execute the
instructions indicated below.
You could
optionally have an "else part",
which is used with
the keyword "else", which is here.
If the condition isn't
true, then this second part will
be executed.
The general structure is the
following.
We have the keyword "if", that is followed
by a condition given in parentheses. We'll
come back later on the conditions. Then
we have an opening brace, a block
of instructions that we want to
execute if
the condition is true. When the
condition
is true, this block of instructions
will
be executed. Then there's a
closing brace.
Then, we can optionally have
the keyword "else", another
opening
brace, another block of instructions, here
in blue, that will be executed
if the condition is false. So
that's the
general structure, but let's have a step-
by-step look at a particular example.
In this example, the control
structure, the conditional
statement that we are interested in, will
be found here. Before, we
start by declaring a int-type variable n
that we didn't initialize,
so here we don't
know it's value yet. Then we print
the
message "entrer un nombre" (= "enter a number")
on the terminal, followed by
a line-break. Then we wait for an
input
of type integer from the user.
Lets' suppose the user
inputs the value 3.
So now n has value 3.
We now come to our conditional branch,
which is
introduced by the keyword "if",
here,
and which has it's condition in
parentheses: n smaller than five.
We ask ourselves,
is n stricly smaller than 5?
3 is strictly smaller than 5.
Here the condition is
thus true, and we execute the code,
the block that
immediately follows the "if".
So, what happens is that we
arrive at the execution of cout,
"votre nombre est... (= "your number is...)
...plus petit que 5" (= ...smaller than 5"),
is the message that will be displayed.
The execution then continues after
the block.
In other word we skip directly
to the
instruction here that prints the message
"Au revoir" (= "Bye"), and the program ends.
What about if at this step
here, the user had entered the
value 7?
At this stage, the program will
check again, whether
7 is strictly smaller than 5.
But now the condition is false.
7 is not strictly smaller than 5.
As the condition is false, the if
will this time skip to the else part,
and completely ignore the previous
part and branch directly (hence
the name "conditional
branch"), to branch directly here
at this display line
that will print that the number n
is greater or equal to 5.
Then we continue the execution
of the program
after the block, the part of the
program
that follows the conditional
branch,
and display the last message
"Au revoir".
The curly braces are used to
define
the block of instructions that is
going to be monitored,
either the block of instructions that
is executed when
the condition is true, or the
block
of instructions that is executed when
the condition is false.
The block of instructions is the set
of instructions
that we want to monitor, on which
we want
to branch, and we can
gather many instructions, as
many as we like,
in one block. Let's suppose for
example that we
not only want to print that
the number
is smaller than five, but also print
the value of the number.
In that case, when the condition is
true, we'll simply, in the block
monitored by the condition, when
the condition is
true, here, add a line to this
block.
This is perfectly possible and
lets us monitor many instructions
with our
conditional branch.
When a block includes a single
instruction, the curly braces are
absolutely optional.
I urge you however to always
use these blocks and always
put these curly braces, in order
to keep the code
readable and maintainable. But I'm
just pointing out that these
curly braces are optional, in case
you come upon this kind of code.
Likewise, the else block is
also totally
optional, we can have an
if without any else. In that case if
the condition isn't
true, then we'll simply continue
the execution of the program.
We'll do a particular thing only
if the condition is true.
If the condition is true, then we'll
additionally execute
the block monitored by the
if.
If I take an example, again with
the input value typed on a keyboard
of an integer, with the test without
the else,
so if the input value is strictly smaller
than five, for example
three, in this case we'll branch here
and execute the display of "Votre
nombre est plus petit que cinq", then
we'll continue with
the rest of the program, so here
we'll print "Au revoir".
Contrariwise, if we input a greater value,
strictly greater or
equal to 5, for example
the value
7, at that moment the test
is false and
we simply don't execute anything
in
particular, we simply continue
by
ending the program by printing
the message "Au revoir".
To sum up, the general structure of
a conditional branch in C++ is
the following : we have an if
instruction followed by
a condition in parentheses, then a
block of instructions here,
in curly braces, which are the instructions
that are going to be executed if
the condition is true, and
optionally the keyword "else"
followed by a block of instructions which
are executed if the condition is false.
And the instructions here that are
in the
blocks are absolutely ordinary C++
instructions, they can in particular
contain if statements themselves,
which are so-called nested
statements.
Let's take an example, suppose for
example
that we have three values
x, y and z,
and we want to test their
equality,
test if x is equal to y, test if x
is equal to z, or test if the three
variables are equal.
We'll start for example by testing
if x is equal
to y, and here you see we'll have a
block
going all the way to here, so this is the
case where x is equal to y and if x is
different from y, at that moment this
other block will be executed.
If x is equal to y, then we can
enter a
block of instructions and have
another
instruction which contains its own
sub-block
of true conditions, here, and optionally
an
else for a sub-block of false
conditions.
So if y is equal to y, we enter the
block, and
if y is equal to z, then
in this case we print that the
three values are equal.
Otherwise, if y is equal to y but
y isn't equal to z,
in this case we print
this, only the two first values
are equal.
We could also do so in the case
where x is different from y.
Obviously, we shall not abuse this
kind of solutions.
In practice, if you have more than
three levels, then
the programs becomes
quickly unreadable.
Let us now illustrate concretely
the previous example with, for example,
the case where we have three variables
x, y and z, all with value one.
We begin with the first if: is x equal to y?
Yes, one is equal to one, so we enter
the block here,
so we are going to execute our second
if here : is y equal to z?
So we ask ourselves the following
question :
are the two values equal?
In this case they are, 1 is equal
to 1, so we enter here this
line, and message that
is going to be printed is "les trois valeurs
sont égales" (= "the three values are all equal").
Then the program will continue and
execute what follows.
Here, there isn't anything to
execute afterwards.
Execute the following of the first block,
of higher level, there
still isn't any following, so the program
end here.
Now suppose we have different
values, for example that we have
the
value 2 in z and y, and the value
1 in x.
So here the first condition
will be
tested, is 1 equal to 2?
Of course not, so the condition
is false and we
branch here on the corresponding
else statement, and we execute
this block here, with the test
of
a second condition : is x equal
to z?
Is 1 equal to 2?
This is also false; so this second if
will branch on
a block that will be executed, which
is this block here,
which begins with a third
if
statement, which will evaluate
its condition. Is y equal to z?
2 is indeed equal to 2.
So in this case we execute the
block that
is monitored by the true condition,
so here we
print that the two last values are
equal, then we
end the program's execution, which
means
we end the execution of the
instructions here
that followed the if.
There isn't anything, then the end
of the instructions of this
block, there isn't anything either,
and finally the instructions
of the higher level block, nothing
either
in this particular case, and that's
how
the example's program would
execute.