In a previous video, we introduced
the conditional branch instruction,
the if.
We also saw that in order to
work, this instruction needs to
express conditions.
The conditions we used
until now were simple conditions,
which
consisted of, for example, comparing
the value of a variable with a value.
We are now going to see that
in C++,
it is possible to express more
complex conditions.
Here you see an example of a
condition branch instructions, an
if, as we have already seen
previously.
We can see that in order to write
down this instruction, we need
to formulate a condition, as we can
concretely see here.
The condition in the present case is
a simple condition, which
consist in comparing the value of
a variable n to the value 5.
Small syntactic detail : the condition
in a conditional
branch instruction is always
surrounded by
parentheses, as we can concretely
see here.
A condition in C++ is in fact a
sort of
expression whose particularity is
to return two possible values.
These values are either "true",
or "false".
Simply enough, a condition will be
evaluated to "true" when
it is true, and evaluated to "false"
when it is false.
Let's take a concrete example.
Let's imagine I have a variable n
whose value is zero,
and I write the condition n smaller
than five, that I want to evaluate.
Here the value of n, zero, is less
than 5, which means
that this condition is true when I
evaluate
it it will therefore return the
value "true".
Now let's imagine n has a value
of 10.
I evaluate the same expression.
Obviously this isn't verified
anymore, the condition is false,
therefore the evaluation
of the condition will return the
value "false".
Let's begin by examining in
a more exhaustive way
how to formulate simple conditions
in C++.
The purpose of a simple condition is
to compare two expressions.
and to do so we need to use
comparison operators.
"Less than", "greater than" are two
examples
which you already had the opportunity
to see before.
So obviously C++ offers a whole
range of predefined operators to
formulate simple
conditions. Let's imagine for example
that I have two variables x, y. I want
to know if the value of x is less than
the value of y. Naturally,
I'm going to use the "less than"
operator
and write my condition like so.
Similarly, if I want to know if the
value
of x is equal to the value of y,
I am going to
use the comparison operator ==,
which lets me test this condition.
You have the operators "less than or
equal", "greater or equal",
and "different than", which let you express
all sorts of simple conditions.
Here's a little warning : in C++, the
operator used to check
if two values are equal is defined by
two "equal" symbols.
Don't confuse it with the = symbol,
which is used to formulate an
assignment.
If I want to check if the value of
a variable n is 5, I'm going
to use the operator ==
to formulate my
condition, and not the simple
equal operator.
You must be aware however that this way of
writing a condition
is considered licit by C++ compilers, we
are going to examine why in
the next slide.
Licit indeed, yet discouraged, at
this stage of learning at least.
What you must know is that in
C++, every expression
whatsoever does something, but
also has a value.
Let's examine this wtih a
concrete example.
Here we have an expression,
n =
5, this expression clearly does
something.
What it does is assigning to a variable n
the
value 5.
In C++, this expression also has a
value.
It's value is the the value of n after the
assignment.
Thus, the expression "n = 5"
has value 5.
That is why it is perfectly licit to
write something
like this : m = n = 5,
5, which aims to assign to a
variable m the value of this expression,
that is 5.
It is
therefore totally correct to write something
like this : "if (n = 5)"
which is the same as writing
"if (5)".
Knowing that in C++, every
non-zero value is
equivalent to "true", this condition will
always be evaluated as true.
Note that in terms of best practices,
it is totally discouraged to
do it this
way. I have shown you this in detail
and explicitly only because to confuse
== and = to
perform a comparison is a mistake
beginners often make.
So in absolute, this way of doing it
is to
avoid, even if it is tolerated
by the compiler.
Now let's illustrate the use of
simple conditions in C++
on small examples.
Here we have a small program that begins
by declaring two
variables a and b and affects initial
values to them, respectively 1 and 2.
We then encounter a conditional
branch instruction, which tests
if the value of a is the same as the value
of b with a simple condition.
This is done with the comparison
operator ==.
Since this
condition isn't verified, the result
of the condition's evaluation
will be the value "false", which will
result in
branching the execution on the else
block of the if instruction, therefore
causing to print the message "cas 2",
which we can see here.
We then continue the execution of
the sequences,
and we encounter a second
conditional
branch instruction, which will this
time compare the
value of two times a to the value of b.
By the way, we can here observe that
the comparison
operators not only allow to compare
the values of
two variables, as it is the case here,
but also
the values of two expressions, in a more
general sense.
Here if we evaluate two times a, we
obtain
the value 2, which is the same as the
value
of b, and the result of the condition's
evaluation will therefore
be "true", which will have as a consequence
to branch
the execution on the positive block,
the true block of the if instruction.
This will cause the message "b
est égal au
double de a" to be printed, as can be
seen here.
In terms of good practices, we here have
a relatively
simple expression. You will however note
that it is recommended,
when the expression becomes more
complex, to use parentheses, as
we could already do here, by adding
parentheses around, for example, this
part of the expression, which makes the
expression more readable.
We have just seen how to
use
simple conditions by using
comparison operators.
In practice, it is often necessary to
combine many
of these simple conditions to formulate
a more complex condition.
To combine simple expressions, we
need
to use another type of operator,
the logical operators.
For example, the logical operator AND,
which is defined in C++ either
by the key-word "and", or by the
symbol
"&&", is an operator operating
with two operands, which are
two logical expressions, that is to say
expressions returning either "true"
or "false".
The result of the evaluation involving
the and is "true"
only in the case where each operand
has the value "true".
In every other case, let's say for example
that one of the two operands, and a
fortiori the two, are "false", the result
of
the global expression's evaluation will
also be "false", here.
Now let's have a look, with a concrete
example, at how to use the logical
operator "and".
Here an example of a small
program, which asks the user to
enter a
number, and we want this number
to be between 1 and 10.
The number is read from the standard
input, and stored in a variable n.
We want to verify that the number
entered by
the user meets our expectations, is
between
the boundary numbers in question,
and that's why
the two following conditions
must
simultaneously verified.
The entered number must be
greater than or
equal to 1, and less than or equal
to 10.
Since we want the two conditions
to be
simultaneously verified, we must
use the logical operator AND.
Now let's imagine that the user has
entered the
value zero, this will mean that
this expression's evaluation
will return "false". An
expression that involves an and
returns "true"
only if its two operands are "true", which
isn't the case here.
So here, the result of the
evaluation of the
expression with the and is also
"false".
As a result, we will branch on the
else part of the if, and print
"incorrect"
to show the user that he hasn't
entered a number according to
our expectations.
Contrariwise, if the user now
enters
the value 5, this expression's
evaluation
will return "true", the evaluation of
this second
expression will also return "true",
which
will mean that the evaluation of
the expression with the and
also returns "true".
At this moment, we will branch on the
positive part of the if and print
"correct" to tell the user that the
entered number is indeed correct.
Another usual logical operator, the OR,
which
is defined in C++ either by the reserved
word or,
or by a double vertical bar.
As with the logical operator AND, the
logical operator OR requires two
operands, which are the logical
expressions, meaning that they return
"true" or "false".
The expression's evaluation with an
OR returns "true" if one or the other,
not necessarily the two, one or the
other of the operands is "true".
It is therefore quite clear that the only
situation or logical
expression involving and OR returning
"false" is
a situation where the two operands
return "false".
In this case, the expression with the OR
also returns "false".
Now let's illustrate the use of the logical
OR with a small concrete example.
Here we have a small program
which asks the user to choose two
values.
These two values are entered from
the standard input and are stored
in two variables m and n.
In the present case, we want one
or the other
of them to be positive, as we only
need
one of the two values to be
positive.
We test these conditions by using the
logical operator OR.
Initially, let's suppose that the
user
enters the values 1 and -1.
In this case, the
first operand
will be evaluated as "true", because it
is indeed positive, and therefore
the expression's evaluation returns
"true", as it is sufficient
that one or the other of the operands
be "true"
for the result to be "true" for
the global expression.
Therefore, it is indeed the message
"au moins
une valeur est positive" that will be printed
in the present case.
Now let's suppose that the entered
values are
-1 and 1.
In this case, the evaluation of this
first
expression will return "false", and the
evaluation of the second
expression, on the other hand, will return
"true", as it
sufficient that one or the other
of the operands
be "true" for all of it to be "true".
The global expression's evaluation
returns "true", and
once again the message "au moins une
valeur est positive" is printed.
Last case : let's imagine that the user
enters
the values minus 1 and -1
for each variable m and n. In this
case, the evaluation of the first
expression
will return "false", the evaluation of
the second expression
will also return "false", as the two
operands
are evaluated as "false", the global
expression also returns
"false" and in this case, it's the
message
"les deux valeurs sont négatives"
that will be printed.
Last usual logical operator, the NOT,
the negation, which is
defined in C++ either by the reserved word
not, or by the exclamation mark.
The logical operator NOT is a
unary logical operator, which
means that it expects only
one operand, which is once again
a logical expression returning "true"
or "false".
The purpose of the logical operator NOT
is to return the negation
of the value of its operand.
For example, let's suppose that the
operand is evaluated as
"false", which means that a is
greater than or
equal to b, the global expression's
evaluation with the
not will return the negation of "false",
namely "true".
Now let's suppose that the evaluation
of this operand
returns "true", the global expression
will this time return the
negation of "true", namely "false".
We'll have the opportunity to see
many examples of the use
of the operator NOT in the following
chapters of this course.