Now let's have a look at various
mistakes often made by
beginner programmers, when it comes
to writing conditional branches.
The first trap that awaits you is a
trap into
which probably every beginner has
fallen,
it's the fact that the equality test
is written with two equal
symbols, and not a unique symbol, which
is itself for the assignement.
For example, this code here
is accepted by the compiler, but won't
test if one is equal to one.
To achieve this, we should have
written a equal equal one.
Moreover, it will assign the value one
to the variable a.
So, even if the compiler
accepts this code, most of the compilers
will display a warning.
That is, a warning message.
For example, g plus plus, with the
option Wall, will
print this message here, or this one here,
if you have a french version of the compiler.
So, if you get one of these two
messages, you
will know that you too have fallen
in this trap.
Perhaps, you see the error in this
new piece of code, there
shouldn't be two semicolons, here.
And, if you put all the same a
semicolon, the message "a
vaut un" will be printed, whatever the
value of a.
So why ?
Because in fact, this semicolon is
considered as an instruction, an
instruction
that does nothing.
And this code will be interpreted in
the following
way, that is that the semicolon,
this instruction that does
nothing, will be considered within the
conditional branch, and
the instruction cout will be considered
only after the conditional branch.
This means that if a has the value
one, we
execute the empty instruction, that is,
we do nothing.
And whatever the value of a, execute
the instruction cout, that is, to print
the message "a vaut un".
And watch out, in this case the compiler
doesn't give any warning during  the
compilation. You'll note that if we had
used curly braces, there would have
been a single instruction in the conditional
branch, and the error we have just
discussed would have less likely
happened.
It is therefore a good idea to
systematically use curly braces, even
when there's only one instruction
in the block.
A third possible mistake is
precisely
to forget the curly braces, in the same
way as in this code.
Having indented these lines,
that is,
to have shifted them slightly
to the
right, is not sufficient for them to be
considered as
inside the conditional branch,
unlike
other languages.
In your opinion, what happens if
I try and compile this code ?
Well, the compiler will print this
warning message, meaning that he
thinks that there's a syntax error,
before the key-word else.
So, why ?
That's because, in fact, this code
is
interpreted in the same way as this
code here.
That is to say, the first cout instruction,
here, is considered
as being within the conditional
branch.
This is what I represented here.
But this second instruction is
considered as being after the
conditional branch.
This is what I represented here.
The compiler then comes upon
the key-word else,
and, from its perspective, there
isn't any if instruction
related to this else key-word,
as we have already left the conditional
branch.
It therefore thinks that there's a syntax
error around this part of the program,
and will print this error message.
Now let's do three quizzes.
First of all, what does this code print
when it is executed ?
And when the user enters the value one
for the
variable n, and the value two for the
variable b.
In your opinion,
what's the correct answer ?
The correct answer is the answer C.
Let's have a look why.
If you think you've understood, you can
go directly to the next quiz.
So, let me remind you that, in order
for a condition with an
and to be true, the two operands
must be true.
And in order for a condition with an or
to be true, it is sufficient for
only one of the two operands to
be true.
I said earlier that the user enters one
for n, and two for p.
This condition is therefore true, because
one is strictly less than two.
This expression, two times n, simply
has the value two.
Two is greater than or equal to two.
Therefore, this condition is true.
So the overall expression is, here, a
condition that is true.
We are therefore going to enter the
conditional branch,
execute this cout instruction, which
prints one, one.
We then go to this conditional
branch.
This condition is, well, the same as
before, it is still true.
The overall condition
uses an or.
Therefore, I don't need to look at
the value of this condition.
I know that this overall condition
is true.
And as it is true, well, we
execute this instruction, which prints
a two.
We then advance to this third
conditional branch,
which uses, once again, the same
condition.
We know that this condition
is true.
We are therefore going to
enter the conditional branch, and
execute this part.
This expression has the value two.
p still has the value two.
Therefore, this condition is true.
We are therefore going to
execute this part
of the conditional branch, and print
three.
We are then going to arrive at the
end of this conditional branch,
move to this instruction, which simply
prints an newline.
Another exercise, another code.
This time, the user enters the values
one for n, and three for p.
What is going to be printed ?
The correct answer is the answer B.
And we are going to have a look why.
This time, the user enters one for n,
and three
for p. This condition is therefore
true, as one
is strictly less than three. This
expression two times
n has the value two, p has the value
three. Therefore, this condition is false.
As this condition uses a single
and, this condition is false.
We are consequently going to skip
the conditional branch, and move on.
This condition is still true, like
before.
The overall condition uses one or.
Thus, I don't need to consider
the value of this condition.
I know that whatever its value,
this entire expression, this entire
condition, is true.
We are therefore going to
enter the conditional branch, and print
two.
We then move on to this conditional
branch.
This condition is true, once again,
so we enter
the conditional branch to execute this
part.
Therefore, this expression has the value
two, p has the value three.
Thus I already know that this condition
is false.
As this
condition is false, we move on to this
part of the conditional branch, and
print four.
We arrive at the end of this
conditional branch, to then
move on to the cout endl, which simply
prints an newline.
One last time, still the same code.
This time, the user enter the values
two for n, and one
for p. Which is the correct answer ?
It's the answer A.
For this last time, the user
enters the value
two for n, and the value one
for p.
This condition is therefore false, as
two isn't strictly less than one.
As the overall condition uses an
and, I don't have to consider
the value of this condition. I know
that it's all necesseraly false.
We therefore skip this first conditional
branch.
This condition is always false.
On the other side, I this time use
an or.
Therefore, I am obliged to consider
the value of this condition.
This expression has the value two
times n. That is, two times
two, so four. p has the value one.
Thus, this condition is true, as four
is greater than or equal to one.
Therefore, the overall condition is
true.
We are therefore going to execute
this instruction, and print two.
We then move on to the next
conditional branch.
This condition is always false.
We are therefore going to skip what
is inside the conditional branch,
and move on to this part of the program,
which simply prints an newline.
Let's end with the bool type, bool for boolean,
which is the type of conditions.
This type will let us declare
variables which will contain the value
of a condition.
A variable of
type bool is often called a boolean.
And a boolean has only two possible
values : either true, or false. Or
more specifically, in C++, we are going to
use the literal values, true and false.
In this example, I begin by declaring two
variables of type int.
a which will be initialized with value one.
b which will be
initialized with value two. In this third
instruction,
I declare a variable which is called
test un, which is of type bool.
Like with all variables, I can
represent
test un with a box. And
test un will be
initialized with the value of this
condition : a equal b.
As a has the value one, and b has the
value two, this condition is
false. test1 will therefore be initialized
with the value
false
This last
instruction declares a variable test
deux, of type bool.
That is, a boolean.
And test deux is going to be initialized
with the value of this condition.
a has the value one, b has the value
two. This condition is thus true.
test2 will therefore be initialized
with the value true, or
more specifically, true, which means
true in
English.
Some students have problems with
booleans, others sometimes have
a mental block.
So, remember that a variable of type
bool is a variable like another.
That is, you can represent it as
a box.
It turns out that this box can only
contain two possible values,
either true, or false.
We can also use logical
operators, and, or, not, between variables
of type bool, and we can also
use these variables as conditions in
conditional branches,
and that's what we're going to have a look
at in this example.
As in the previous example, I begin by
declaring a variable called a, of type
int, and initialized with the value one,
and a
variable b, also of type int, initialized
with the value
two. In this instruction, I declare a
variable of type bool, which is called c,
and is initialized with
the value true. Then, here, I
declare a
value of type bool, which I will call d,
initialized with
the value of the condition "a equals b". a has
the value 1, b has the value 2.
The condition is therefore false, and
has the value false.
d is therefore initialized with
the value false.
Then, here, I declare a variable of type
bool, called e, initialized with
the value of this condition.
d has the value false.
This condition, a less than b, is true.
It therefore has the value true. The
logical operator is here an or.
Thus, all this condition
is true, and has the value true.
e is therefore
initialized with the value true. Then,
in this conditional branch,
the condition is the value of the variable
e of type bool.
e therefore has the value true.
The condition is this true, and
we are going to
enter the conditional branch, to
execute this instruction,
which will print the message :
e has the value true.
That's all for the moment, concerning
booleans.
But booleans are helpful in many
problems, and we'll
encounter them in concrete examples
in following videos of the course.