Programming means
writing programs.
A program is a sequence of instructions,
which will be executed by the computer.
For a given task, the programmer
will have to create a program
well suited to accomplish this task.
However, it is the computer's
microprocessor
which will execute the instructions
constituting the program.
Yet, the microprocessor can only
execute very simple instructions.
These are too elementary
to be efficiently used by
a human being.
Fortunately, programmers
can write their programs
in programming language, such as Java,
more accessible to a human being.
This language will automatically be
translated into instructions
the microprocessor
will understand and execute.
More precisely, a program
in the Java language
is made of one or several text files.
In the case of the Java language,
a compiler will translate
the text file(s) into a
bytecode program,
which is an intermediate representation
of the Java program.
This representation is independant
from the computer where
the program has been compiled.
The bytecode program will then
be interpreted
by a program called
a virtual machine.
The virtual machine will translate
the bytecode into instructions
the microprocessor will be able to execute.
Since the bytecode program is
independant from the computer
where it has been created,
it can be executed on
another computer.
In this course, you will learn
to analyse a problem
and write a program in a
high-level language.
This language will thus be the Java language.
But we will endeavor to remain general
and teach you principles valid
for most programming languages.
For a given problem, you will
first have to ponder
the sequence of instructions
the computer will have to execute.
You will then write the
Java program
corresponding to this sequence
of instructions
and compile your program to
generate a bytecode program.
It is possible for the compiling to fail
because your program does not respect
the rules of the Java language.
You will then go back to your
program and correct it.
Fortunately, the Java compiler
will provide error messages,
which will guide you along this correction.
Once compiled, you will be able to
test your program on the virtual machine.
At this point, it is possible that your program
will not do what you expected
because you have erred somewhere
in the initial sequence of instructions.
You will then go back to the
analysis of the program you have done,
correct this sequence of instructions
and continue the cycle we have
just presented.
Now, let us create
our first Java program.
First of all, we need to open
a development environment.
There are several possible environments.
You will find more details on this
course's website.
For this episode, we
will use Eclipse.
Our program starts like this :
"public class HelloWorld", opening brace
Do not attempt to understand these
lines right now,
just be aware that they are necessary
for our program to compile.
Then comes : "public static void main,
opening parenthese, String, brackets, args,
opening brace." This will make more sense
in the lectures dedicated to functions.
The tradition, when learning
a new language
is to create a program printing
the message "HelloWorld".
We will follow
this custom.
In Java, printing such a message
is done as follows.
System.out.println("Hello, world");
The braces opened by
the first lines
must now be closed.
You may have noticed that Eclispe
has added them automatically,
but this is not the case
for all development
environments.
Therefore, do not forget to add them
if need be.
From now on, be careful to clearly
present your programs.
Despite not being being mandatory for the
program to [compiler not to] perform correctly,
it is important for readability.
For example, we started these lines
on the first column.
These two braces are aligned
and these lines in the braces
are indented to the right.
This line between these
two braces,
also aligned, is indented
to the right aswell.
Several rules are possible,
simply try to be coherent
and readable.
Now, let us compile
our program.
On Eclipse, this is done
by clicking this button here,
launching the compiling
and executing the program
if the compiling has gone without problem.
Since our program is correct,
the compiler has been able
to create the bytecode program.
Eclipe has then automatically
executed this bytecode program
and you can see that our program
has indeed printed
the "Helloworld" message.
You can also see that the
compiling has created
a file called "Helloworld.class" which
contains the bytecode program
created at the compiling.
Now, it is quite possible that,
while typing your first program,
you have made a typo.
What happens in such a case,
and what should we do?
Let us suppose, for example,
that you have omitted the semicolon here.
if we try to compile this program,
you can see that the compiler
has printed an error message.
This error message informs us
that a semicolon is missing
and it gives us the line
where the semicolon is missing.
Now, if we put back the semicolon
and recompile the program,
we will obtain the "Helloworld"
message again,
signifying that the compiling
and execution have gone without problem.
Now, if you have forgotten the quotes,
several error messages will
be printed.
There is no need to panic, one should
always start with the first error;
often an error is caused by
an another error,
higher in the program.
This is the case here.
If we put back the quotes,
all the mistakes will vanish.
To sum up, be very rigorous
while typing your programs.
Also, please mind the presentation.
In case of errors, always
start with the first error and recompile.
It will probably correct at least some
of the following errors.
In order to find your error,
start by checking the line number
and try to interpret the
error message
displayed by the compiler,
so that you can solve the problem.
If you have not done so already,
we encourage you to open
your development
environment
and to create your own
"helloworld" porgram.
In the upcoming episodes, we will
see more complex examples,
manipulating data.