In our introduction, we have
discussed the different steps
leading to the creation
of a program.
We know that we should start
by thinking, conceptualizing,
and planning the sequence of instructions
we aim to realize.
Then, we will translate this conception
into a known programming language,
such as Java.
Then we will go through several steps,
of compilings, testings
until we finally reach
the creation of program,
executable on a computer.
Now, we will enter the heart of the matter
and acquire the tools necessary
to begin writling
little Java programs.
A program is simply
a sequence of instructions
operating on data.
The notion of "sequence of instructions",
is closely realted to the notion of processing.
Processing operate on data,
they can modify these data's values.
In turn, the data impact
the processing,
since, depending on
the nature of these data,
different processing will
be performed.
Let us suppose, for example,
that we wish to write
a brief program able
to solve a quadratic equation
of this kind.
Let us think of the the adequate
sequence of instructions.
The first step is probably
to ask the user to provide
us with the coefficients b and c,
which will let us know
concretely
what equation we're
going to solve.
I now have the first data.
Starting with these data,
we can perform other processing,
such as, for example, calculating the delta.
Then, depending on
the value of this delta,
we will perform different processing.
For example, if delta is negative,
we will simply print that
there is no solution.
Otherwise, we will treat the other cases.
For example, if delta is 0,
we can calculate the unique solution
and print this solution.
Otherwise, we have the case
with two solutions,
which we will not discuss
here explicitly.
Here, we can clearly see that
processing
impact data.
For example, here, the processing held
compute an arithmetic
expression.
This processing indeed
impacts the data,
for it will calculate a new
data, which is delta.
The other way around, we can also see
that data impact processing.
Typically here, depending
on delta's value,
we will perform different actions.
We can draw two important
observations based on this example.
The first one is the notion
of expression, which is fundamental
in order to start
expressing processing.
The notion of expression will
be a chapter
later in this course.
The second one is
bound to the notion of data.
Here, the data "b² - 4c" is stored
in  a container, delta.
We need to associate this data
to the name "delta"
since we use delta several
times in the program.
We want to be able to find
this data, whenever we need it.
The fact to associate a name
to a data, delta to b² - 4c
is what we call in programming,
the notion of variable.
This will be the topic of
this episode.
The goal of this introductory course
is to introduce the basic tools,
permitting to formulate
basic processing
and to manipulate data
in an adequate way.
We have seen, in the
previous example,
how important the notion of
expression was,
to which the notion
of operator is related.
We will discuss operators later
in this course, though.
Today, we will discover
the notion of variables,
associated with the notion of data.
The notion of variable will let us
associate data with a name
in a program.
You have here a small glimpse
of the remaining fundamentals,
which will be studied during
this introductory programming course.
In programming, a variable is
a named memory area
usually called the identifier,
where we will store a value.
We can see this here.
A fundamental fact is that
variables must be associated with a type.
Java is a language demanding
that we specify
the type of the data
we wish to manipulate.
When we wish to
use a variable,
a named area in the memory,
it will be necessary
to specify its type,
what type of data we want to use.
For example, it may be necessary
to use data
of the integer type,
of the character string type.
Every time we wish to
manipulate data
of a particular kind,
we will have to specify it
through the type.
How should we proceed, in a Java program
if we wish to declare a variable,
namely to memorize a data
through a variable ?
You have here, a
little shell of a program
ready to welcome your instructions.
Now, let us declare a variable.
First of all, we should decide
the name of this variable;
if possible, this name should be eloquent,
somehow describing the role of the variable.
Here, we will call this variable "nombre".
(TN: nombre means number )
Now, we should come with an initial
value, for example, 4.
And, of course, we should
specify its type.
Here, I will precise
that the number is an integer.
In Java, we write integer "int".
This line of code, we have
just written in the editor
corresponds to what we call,
the declaration of a variable.
In a program, we have to declare
that we wish to use a variable
of a given type.
You have here two examples
of valid variable
declarations in Java.
In the first case,
we give an initial value
to the variable at the
moment where we declare it.
In the second case,
we simply declare a variable
without giving it
an initial variable.
We can see here the fundamental
syntax elements we have
introduced earlier.
The variable type must
necessarily be specified
Same goes for its name,
its identifier.
As we have seen, during
its declaration,
a variable can be initialized,
namely, we can give
it an initial value.
This corresponds to this
situation in the memory.
It is good practice;
indeed, it is always desirable
for a variable to have a known value.
We have just seen that it
was entierely possible, in Java,
for a variable to be declared
without any initial value.
Here, we are declaring
a variable
nCarré, of type int.
(TN: nCarré means nSquared).
We are not giving it an initial value.
This corresponds to this
situation in the memory.
We have here a variable nCarré,
not storing anything known.
What we should know
is that Java does not permit,
in a program,
to use a variable which
has not been initialized.
For example, if, after having
declared this variable nCarré,
We try to print its value
(we are anticipating on
the next episodes,
regarding the printing
of a value).
So, the printing of the variable nCarré
will be realized as follows.
If we try, right after the
declaration of a variable,
to print its value,
we will obtain an error
upon compiling.
The compiler will call us to order,
signifying that nCarré has
not been initialized.
Therefore, we cannot use it.
However, this implies that,
after declaring a variable,
without giving it a value,
we have the possibility to give
it a value later in the program.
This is what we will
discuss now,
introducing the assignment
notion.
This will make it possible,
after this instruction,
to modify, to store a value
inside the variable nCarré
through the so-called assignment.
Regarding types, we already
encountered,
in the previous examples,
the integer type,
spelt "int" in Java.
Thus, if we wish to use a data
corresponding to an integer
we will use the int type.
Naturally, there are other
usable types.
For example, if we wish to
use decimal numbers,
we can use the predefined type double,
which will allow us to work
with decimal-type
variables.
What you have to know,
is that once we go through a
declaration such as this,
each variable has its own type.
This type, will remain unchanged
for the whole course of the program.
We cannot change the type
of a variable
once the declaration has been made.
Concretely, this means that
our variable n here, can only
contain integers.
Similarly, the variable x can
only contain decimal numbers.
let us review these essential points.
In Java, the declaration of a variable,
follows this syntax.
We specify the type of the variable,
follow by its identifier, its name.
And we do not forget the famous
semicolon
which closes the declaration.
We have also seen that it is
always recommanded
to give an intial value to our
variable,
during the declaration.
We will generally adopt
a declaration-initialization
instruction,
which goes as follows :
The variable type, followed by its name,
then, after the =,
the initial value
and, of course, the semicolon at the end,
closing the declaration-
initialization instruction.
Once the variable type has been defined,
it is clear that we can not
change it later.
In Java, it is valid to declare
several variables on the same line.
We will declare, on the same line,
variables of the same type.
Therefore, we only specify
the type once.
Here, we declare int-typed
variables p and q,
separating the declaration of
the different variables
with a comma.
You have here a second example
where we declare two
double-typed variables on the same line.
The difference from the previous example,
is that, for the variable y
we do not specify an initial value.
This is also possible.
Regarding methodology,
keep in mind that it is not
recommanded to overuse these sorts
of formulation, for they impede
the program's readability.
There are a few rules,
by which you must abide
when choosing a variable's
identifier.
This identifier can only
be constituted
of letters, digits
or either of these specific characters :
underscore (_) or dollar ($).
The first character has
to be either a letter.
It can also be one of the specific
characters
underscore (_) or dollar ($),
however, this is not part
of the usual conventions
of Java programmers, which
we will discuss later on.
Naturally, the identifier
cannot be one of the
Java reserved keywords.
Capital letters are authorized,
but they are not equivalent.
For example, if we choose the identifier,
"ligne" with a lower case "l",
it is not equivalent to the
identifier "Ligne",
with an upper case "L".
You can see here examples of
valid identifiers.
Here constituted of
letters only,
here constituted of
letters and digits.
Here, you can see some
invalid identifiers.
Here, an identifier can neither
contain a blank space.
nor the symbol minus (-) and cannot
begin with a digit.
In addition to the naming
rules imposed by the Java language,
which are to be strictly respected,
there are certain usual
conventions,
not required by the compiler
but nonetheless respected
by most Java programmers.
Typically, you will see the
variable naming
with this form here.
If the name of the variable, the identifier,
is constituted of several words,
we will separate the words,
starting every word with
a capital letter.
Also, the convention is that
every variable's identifier
is to start with a lower case letter.
Thus, you will encounter this
type of formulation,
rather than this one,
starting with a capital letter,
or this one,
using underscores (_).
We have already understood that the notion of type
is essential for variable
declaration in Java.
The two elementary types
for the manipulation of numerical data,
that is, the declaration of numerical
variables,
are int and double; we have already
encountered them
in several of our previous examples.
Naturally, there are many
another predefined type.
For example, if, in a program,
we wish to manipulate the usual
characters of the alphabet,
for example A and Z,
we can resort to the
predefined type char.
We will have the opportunity,
throughout this course,
to expand on predefined
types in Java.
Now, you know how to
declare a variable,
making it possible to
memorize a data,
usable in a program.
Now, how should we proceed,
if we wish to change the value
of a variable, previously declared ?
To that end, we will resort
to the notion of assignment.
We have already had
the opportunity to encounter
a few informal examples.
In order to realize an assignment,
we will use the symbol equals (=),
respecting the following syntax :
On the left side of the expression, we
specify the variable's identifier.
Then comes our equal
symbol (=)
and, finally, the new value
that we wish to store inside
our variable.
It is very important to understand -
we will come back to this later -
that an assignment is not a
mathematical equality.
its purpose is to modify
the value of a variable,
in the course of the program's execution.
Let us suppose that, in a program,
we declared two variables n and nCarré.
n has been declared and initalized to 4
while nCarré has not been initialized.
We wish to store a value inside nCarré,
using the assignement notion.
How will such an assignment
unfold ?
You must understand that the
execution of such an instruction,
will occur in two distinct steps.
The first is the evaluation
of the expression on the right-hand side of
the =  symbol.
Here, this evaluation will
give us the value 16.
In a second time, we will store
the value thus computed
in the  variable nCarré.
As a result,
the variable nCarré, will contain
the value 16.
To sum up, the assignment syntax
in Java is as follows :
we specify the name of the variable,
followed by the equals symbol (=),
followed by an expression, valid in Java.
This expression can be something
elementary,
such as a literal value, like here.
It can also be much more complex,
like here.
We will come back to expressions and further
discuss them later.
The critical point is that
the type of the value
computed by the expression
must be  the same as
the variable's one
Another syntactic detail :
do not forget the semicolon (;)
at the end of the assignment instruction.
Now, let us go back
to the comparison between the mathematical
equality and the assignment.
Both use the equals sign (=)
and the notion of variables.
Self-evidently, if, in mathematics, we write
such an expression,
we signify that the variables a and b
will always have the same value over time.
On the other hand, the assignment in programming
is a different mechanism entierely;
it is dynamic
and will thus depend on time.
Let us take a concrete example.
Let us imagine that a contains the value 1
and b contains the value 2.
If we execute now this first instruction,
we start by, as we have just seen,
evaluating the expression on
the right-hand side of the assignment;
this will give us the value 2.
Then, we will store this value,
this 2, inside the variable a
which leads us to this result.
Now, let us analyze the
second instruction
with the exact same starting
conditions,
that is a containing 1
and b containing 2.
Now, if we execute this instruction,
as before, we start by evaluating what stands
on the right side of the assignment,
returning 1.
Then, we store this 1 inside b,
which results in this situation.
Thus, we see that in programming,
in both cases,
a and b have the same value
but these values are not the same
over time.
Moreover, if, at some point,
one of the two variables is modified,
the other remains unaffected.
For example, if a is
then modified to 3,
b will keep its value, for example 1,
in the second assignment.
Another example : if, in mathematics,
we write such a relation,
it means that a and b will awlays
verify this relation, regardless of the time.
However, if we write the exact
same thing in programming,
we will see that the result for a
and b is decidedly different.
Thus, here, we start by executing
this instruction,
resulting in the variable
a contaning 5.
Then, we execute this
assignment instruction.
As we have seen before, we
will start by evaluating "a + 1",
returning 6 and storing this
6 inside the variable b,
resulting in this situation.
At this point, a and b indeed
verify this relation.
However, if we move on
to the next instruction,
we will modify a's value
to 2.
We now see that the relation
is not verfied anymore.
Due to what we have just seen,
it is licit, in programing to resort
to similar formulations.
By the way, this formulation,
which you will often encounter,
along our examples
is particularly useful.
Now, what happens if we execute
such an instruction ?
Let us start with a concrete
example, with a initialized to 1.
As we have just seen,
we start by evaluating this part
of the assignement, returning 2.
In a second time, we will
store this 2 inside a,
leading to this result.
Thus, when we write that
kind of things in programming,
we do not signify, as is the
case in mathematics,
that the relation "a = a + 1"
must always be respected,
(in the context of mathematics, this particular expression
may lead to problems)
In programming,
we simply signify that
we are adding
1 to the value of a.
Now to the last chapter regarding
variables :
the notion of constant.
We have seen that the assignment
permits to modify
the value of a variable
after its declaration.
There are situations, though,
where this is not desirable.
Let us suppose that, in a program,
we need to work
with the speed of light.
We all know that the speed of
light is a constant.
Its value will thus not be modified
over the course of the program.
Therefore, we will precise that this
data cannot change.
In such a case, we proceed
by adding the reserved
keyword "final" just before
the variable declaration.
This means that, once an initial
value has been attributed,
we cannot modify the value of the
variable anymore.
Here, in this example, we declared
our constant as follows :
the constant VITESSE_DE_LA_LUMIERE
(TN:vitesse de la lumière means speed of light)
If, later on, we try to modify
the value
through an assignment, this will
result in a compiling error.
By the way, there are
certain conventions
regarding the naming of constants in Java.
Here, the identifier of our speed of
light constant
is constituted by different words,
all written in capital letters
and separated by underscores (_).
This is a usual convention regarding
the naming of constants.
We warmly recommand you to follow
these conventions.