Until now, we have learnt how
to declare, initialize
and assign a variable.
Today, we will learn how
to print a variable
and read its value from the keyboard.
Let us begin with the printing.
Paying attention to this example,
the printing lines are
these three lines here.
Let us examine them thoroughly.
The line interesting us
is the following.
If we suppose that we have an
int-type variable n,
containing the value 4, this line
will print the message :
"La variable n contient 4."
(TN: meaning "the variable n contains 4.")
This line is composed of two parts.
First of all, the description,
in the Java language
of the technically called
"standard output" or terminal.
The second part is the message
to be sent to the terminal.
This message is split in
several pieces.
Between quotation marks,
we have a literal string
which will be written as such on the
output. Then comes a Java expression,
that is, something which
will be evaluated before the printing.
The evaluation picks up the value of n,
thus printing 4.
Then comes the third and last
part :
another literal string, reduced to a period
which will be written as such.
These different parts are composed
with the sign '+' .
Be careful though, the '+' sign, simply
assembles the messages one after the other (= concatenates).
If we write "un", between quotation marks
followed by "message", this corresponds
to the string "un message"
(TN: means "a message").
'+' stands thus here for
message concatenation.
It is a stacking of the messages,
one after the other
and not at all an addition.
On the other hand, we have
the terminal description :
"system", period, "out", period and then
a function, a method, println()
which means "print line". This instruction
will print the message
and trigger a line break
just after.
If we do not want this
line break,
we can use the method
"print() ", simply (without "ln"), which
which will not trigger a line break.
To sum up, if you wish to print
an expression, a message,
type "system.out.println()" if you
want a line break;
then, between quotation marks,
the literal messages
which will be printed exactly as
you write them
and expressions, concatenated,
combined with the '+' sign.
If you have no desire
for a line break,
use the function "print()"
instead of the function "println()";
the different messages will then
be printed one after the other,
glued together and not
line by line.
We can use this system
to simply print
the value of a variable, reduced
to the expression of this value.
But we can also combine variables using
any Java expression.
For example, we can print
a message starting with
"Le double de", then evaluate the value of n
(TN: "Le double de" means "The double of" ),
add the message "est" and evaluate
(TN: "est" means "is")
an expression as complex as
you desire, which value will be printed.
Previously, we insisted on the fact
that the sign used to glue,
concatenate strings was not
an arithmetic addition.
So, how do me make an addition?
For that, we absolutely need
to resort to parentheses,
so that the expressions in parentheses
will be evaluated in an arithmetic
way and not in the way
of strings glued one
after the other.
For example, if n is 4 and nCarre is 16,
this expression will evaluate
n, which contains 4, +, in an arithmetic sense,
16; thus returning the value 20.
This value will be printed
as such.
The final printing will thus be
"n plus nCarre = 20"
However, if we
omit the parentheses,
we will print "n plus nCarre =",
followed by the value 4,
immediately followed by the value 16.
We thus get the message :
"n plus nCarre = 416".
This is clearly not what we wanted.
In order to make sure that the evaluation
of "n + nCarre" will be done in an arithmetic way,
we need to protect it with parentheses.
Now, let us unfold the course
example step by step.
We begin by declaring a
variable n,
intialized to the value 4.
Then we declare a variable nCarre
which we do not initialize;
we do not know its initial value.
Now, we execute an assignment,
evaluating the expression "n * n",
that is, 4 times 4, returning 16.
This value 16 will be copied
and stored inside nCarre. In the memory,
we thus have the value 4 inside n
and 16 inside nCarre.
Now, we will print the message
"La variable n contient", then
evaluate the expression "n", that is,
replace it by the value of n.
We will thus get the message"La variable n
contient 4" (TN: means "The variable n contains 4")
Now, we move on to the next
line, printing the message :
"Le carré de n", then evaluate the expression "n",
(TN: "le carré de n" means "the square of n")
that is, replace it by its value 4
and add the literal string "est".
Then, we evaluate the expression "nCarre",
thus replacing it by its value 16
and concatenate, push back the literal
string containing the period.
Therefore, the final message will be
"Le carré de 4 est 16."
Finally, in the last line,
we will similarly
print the message "Le double de n est".
(TN: "Le double de n est" means "the double of n is" )
By the way, please note that it is the letter n
that will be printed since it is
included in the quotation marks.
This is the word "n" and not an
expression such as here.
"Le double de n est", followed
by the expression "2 * n".
We will thus search for the value of n,
that is, 4 and multiply it by 2, returning 8.
We thus get the message "8",
followed by the message "."
and, finally, a line break
due to "println()"
A little question now.
Let us detail step by step
the execution of the question code.
We begin by declaring an int-type
variable a, initialized to the value 2.
Then, we declare an int-type variable
b, initialized to the value 1.
Now, we move on to an assignment,
evaluating a, that is, 2 then
evaluating "b + 2", that is "1 + 2" returning
the value 3.
We thus get the value "2 * 3" which will
be stored inside b.
To sum up, this expression will be evaluated to 6
and the value 6 will be stored inside b.
Now, we move on to the last line
which will print the expression a, that is, 2,
then the string "," then the value of
b, that is, 6.
Another question now.
Let us examine the step by step
unfolding of the question code.
We begin by declaring an int-type
variable a,
intialized to the value 1.
Then, we declare an int-type variable b,
intialized to the value 2.
Now, we move on to an assignment,
evaluating the expression b, thus returning 2.
We will store this 2 inside a and
evaluate the next expression, a
and copy this expression inside b.
Therefore, during the printing, we will
evaluate the expression a, that is 2,
then the literal string ","
then the evaluation of the expression b,
that is, 2. The printing will thus be "2, 2".
At this point, we could wonder how
to swap the value of two variables.
Indeed, in the previous example,
we have not swapped the two variables,
but simply copied the value of b
inside both variables a and b.
Comparatively, we could wonder how
to swap the content of two glasses.
Let us suppose that you have a glass
of grenadine and a glass of mint.
The mint glass will be called b
and the grenadine glass, a.
How to proceed in order to
swap the content of both glasses ?
The correct solution is to introduce
a third glass called "tmp".
It is not any more difficult
in programming.
In order to swap the content
of two variables, we simply
need to introduce a temporary variable,
making it possible to transfer the values.
For example, a is initialized to 1
and b is initialized to 2.
We introduce a temporary
variable "temp"
in which we will copy the value of a.
Then we will copy the value of b inside a.
Since the value of a is
saved inside "temp",
we can now replace the initial
value of a by b's.
And, finally, we will copy
the value saved in "temp"
inside the variable b, namely we store
the value 1 inside the variable b.
Initially, a contained 1 and b
contained 2;
we have thus swapped the initial
content of the two variables a and b.
Now, let us move on to the reading of the
value of a variable from the keyboard.
Let us reuse our example of the calculation
and printing of a number's square or double.
Let us suppose that, this time, we do
not want the value of n to be 4,
but instead ask the user to enter the value
of n through the keyboard.
How should we proceed ? Well,
we will simply replace the line
assigning the value 4 to n
by a few lines
which we are going to detail soon.
These lines will
permit to assign a value, read from
the keyboard, to the variable n.
First of all, we need to import the
so-called "Scanner class"
by adding this line once
at the beginning of the program :
import java.util.Scanner;
This line added,
you can declare a Scanner-type
variable "keyb" and initialize it
by binding it to the keyboard.
This is technically called the standad
input device.
This input is represented by "System.in".
All you need to do
is to write this line : Scanner,
followed by a variable name (e.g, keyb)
= new Scanner(System.in);
Thanks to that, you can use
the variable "keyb" in order
to read variables from the keyboard.
This line will be written once and
only once in the whole program.
You only need to create the
link towards the keyboard once.
At this point of the course,
you will write it in the "main".
From this line, you can
use the variable keyb
in order to read variables.
We may want to read an integer from
the keyboard in order to initialize a variable
like we do here: we declare an int-type
variable n and initialize it
with a keyboard reading.
This is written as follows:
keyb (the Scanner-type variable we
have previously declared),
period, and the reading of an integer
nextInt() in order to read the next integer,
parentheses and a semicolon to close the
initialization instruction
of our variable.
This might all seem technical but you
merely need to follow
this three steps procedure which
we will go through once more.
First of all, you add this line once at
the very beginning of your program.
Then, you write this line once where
you need it; here, in the main
in order to declare a Scanner-type
variable which you will use
every time you need to read an
integer thanks to "nextInt()".
The "nextInt()" method works as follows.
It begins by momentarily
stopping the progess of the program.
Then, it will wait until the user
types a value and
hits the "enter" or "return"
key.
Then, it will read the value as an integer,
convert it into an integer.
This integer-type value, converted from what
has been entered through the keyboard will
be assigned to the variable n during the third step.
The program will then resume.
"nextInt()" is what we call a
method, a function,
a processing, associated to the Scanner object.
It is possible to read
many other things,
many different types of values.
For example, if we want to
read a decimal-type value,
a double-type value,
we will use the function "nextDouble()".
In order to initialize a double-type variable
x to a value read from the keyboard,
we will write the declaration double x
and the initialization = keyb.nextDouble();
which will read a double-type
value from the keyboard.
Let us take a step by step example.
We start with the usual
declaration line,
creating a Scanner which will associate
the keyboard to the Scanner "keyb".
Then, we will warn the user that
we expect him to enter a value.
We will print for him, with the way
we have just seen, a message :
"Entrez une valeur pour n"
(TN: "Enter a value for n")
We will read a value from the keyboard
thanks to the method nextInt()
of the previously declared object "keyb".
Let's assume that the user
types the value 2 on the keyboard.
This method will be evaluated and
will read the value 2 from the keyboard.
2 will then be stored as the initial
value of the variable n.
At the next step, we will evaluate
"n * n", that is, 4.
We will store this 4 inside the variable nCarre
and print the message
"La variable contient" and
evaluate the expression n.
Thus, we will print
the value of n.
In addition to nextInt(), reading an integer
and nextDouble(), reading a decimal,
a useful function is the
function nextLine()
permitting to read a whole
line in one go.
Let us take an example.
As usual,
we declare a Scanner-type variable
keyb, associated to the keyboard.
Once this declaration has been done,
we can call our function
keyb.nextLine(); thus reading
a whole line.
If the user has typed a message such as
"bonjour tout le monde !" (TN:"hello everyone!")
the call to the function nextLine() will
read the whole line entered by the user,
every character typed,
until the user has pressed
the enter or return key.
The question is, in what variable
will we store this message?
What is its type?
For now, anticipiting on forthcoming
material,
we ask you to copy this line where
"String" is the type of the variable s,
used in order to save the message.
s is the name of the variable.
Once we have typed the  line
String s = keyb.nextLine();
s will contain all the characters
entered by the user
until they have pressed the return key.
Be careful though when using
the nextLine() method: it is not  very
compatible with nextInt() or nextDouble().
For example, if we declare
an int-type variable i
and initialize it through
keyboard reading
with nextInt() and that, right away,
we wish to read a message,
an entire line with nextLine() which we
store in s1 and that we read another line
similarly, and store it,
initializing a variable s2.
The idea is to read an integer and then
to read the end of the line and then another line.
If we type the message "25 francs",
line break,
followed by "23 francs" what will happen
is that we will start by reading an
integer. i will thus contain 25.
Only then will we read the end of the
line until here, "francs".
Thus, s1 will indeed contain
"francs".
Finally, we will read a whole line,
that is, "23 francs".
Until now, no problem.
Now, if we type 14, line break, "euros",
line break,43 what will happen ?
Let us analyze step by step.
We want to read an
integer : i will thus contain 14.
Then, we will read the end
of the line; it is empty here.
s1 will be empty and we will read the next
line : "euros" will be stored inside s2.
So, s2 will contain "euros".
What we see here is
that the combination of
nextInt() followed by nextLine()
does not always work properly.
Especially since, here, the user
has generated a line break
right after the integer 14 and the reading
of nextLine() after nextInt(), typed on the keyboard
will read the end of the line,
corresponding to the line break,
the return key typed by the
user.
This occurs because nextInt() ends its
reading just after the integer, here, 14
and does not read the return character,
the return key.
How should we proceed, then?
Every time you wish to read a number
with nextInt() or nextDouble() and that
the next reading is a line,
you need to anticipate the non-reading
of the line break
by nextInt() or nextDouble() by adding
a reading of the end of the line,
a supplementary nextLine() inserted
between
the integer/decimal reading
and the reading of the next message,
which you really want to read.
You add a reading in a variable,
previously declared to that effect
String s = keyb.nextline();
Later, once you will be
familiar with
control structures, especially with
conditional branches
or conditional loops, you will be
able to make sure that the reading of s
is indeed an empty character string, or, if not,
you will take it as the message to read.
If s is empty, you will take the next line
as the desired message.