Let us now go back to
expressions and operators
which we have already
seen in previous episodes.
We can find expression in
assignments, for example.
The expression is necessarily
on the right-hand side of the = sign
and will calculate a value
of the same type
as the variable on the left-hand
side of the = sign,
since the assignment will give the value
calculated by the expression to the variable.
So, an expression can simply be
a literal value,
like 4 or 3.14
More generally, an expression
is a mathematical formula
implementing operators,
such as here.
Here, we multiply the value of the
variable n by itself.
By the way, the asterisk
is the multiplication symbol.
Here, we thus simply obtain n².
More generally,
an expression can be expressed using
several operators and parentheses;
precisely like a
mathematical formula.
The type of the expressions is thus important.
It is also essential to be
aware that
literal values have their
own type
exactly like variables.
For example, if we write
the literal value 1,
the type of this value is "int".
However, if we write 1.0
the type of this value is double.
By the way, please note that we can
write the shorter " 1. "
which is strictly equivalent to 1.0,
thus of  type double.
Thus, we can simply write,
for example, this declaration
which is strictly equivalent
to this declaration here.
However " 1.0 " is a lot
more readable than
the short version " 1. "
Therefore, prefer " 1.0 "
We may also use the so-called
scientific notation.
For example, we can
write " 2e3 "
which is strictly equivalent to 2x10³ (2x10^3),
that is 2000.
In genere, " aeb " is
equivalent to ax10^b
For example, in this declaration,
we initialize the variable x
to the value 1.3x10³
that is, 1300.
In this declaration here,
we initialize the variable y
to the value 1.3x10^-3
that is, 0.0013
Regarding operators,
we have at our disposal,
first of all, the four usual operators.
For addition, we will simply
use the + symbol.
For subtraction the - symbol.
As we have said, we use
the * symbol for multiplication.
And the division is written with
the / character.
However, there is a trick
regarding the division.
If both values involved in
the division
are of  type int, it will be
the integer division.
For example, in this division,
1 and 2 are both of  type int;
this is thus the integer division.
This means that we will obtain,
as the division's result,
the value 0.
Why is that ?
Because 1 = 0*2 + 1
and this 0 is the result
of the integer division.
Another example : 5/2
5 and 2 are both of  type int.
Therefore, the result will be 2,
for 5 = 2*2 + 1
and this 2 here is indeed the
result of the division.
However, if at least one
of the two values
involved in the division is
of  type double,
it will be the standard division
we are familiar with.
In this example, we will thus
obtain the result 0.5
as we would have expected.
In Java, we may also use
the operators
+=
-=
*=
/=
For example, we may write "a += 5"
where a is a variable;
this is stritly equivalent to writing "a = a + 5"
Another example : we
may write "a *= b",
where b is another variable;
this is strictly equivalent to
writing "a = a * b"
In the case of int and
int only,
we may also use an operator
called "modulo",
written with the character %
returning the remainder
of the integer division.
For example, if we write "11 % 4",
that is, 11 modulo 4, we will obtain 3.
Why so ?
Because 11 = 2 * 4 + 3
This 3 is the remainder
of the division 11 by 4,
and thus the result of "11 % 4".
Now, if we calculate "12 % 4",
what will we obtain, in your opinion ?
Why ?
Because 12 = 3 * 4 + 0
The remainder of the division
12 by 4 is thus 0 .
Therefore, the value of 12 modulo 4
is indeed 0.
We may also use the
operators ++ and --
called the increment and decrement
operators.
Namely, they will add 1 to
or subtract 1 from
the value of a variable.
For example, we may write " ++i "
which is equivalent to "i = i + 1"
In other words, we will add 1
to the value of the variable i.
We could also have written " --a ",
which is equivalent to "a = a - 1".
Namely, we will subtract 1
from the value of the variable a.
These two operators are
frequently used
with "for loops", a notion we will
expand on,
in an upcoming lesson.
Up until now, we have always considered
decimal values -the double variables-
and integer values -the int variable-
separately.
Now, what will happen if we try
to assign a decimal value
to an int-type variable.
Actually,  in Java,
it is impossible to assign
a decimal value, for
example of double typed value
to an int-type variable.
For example, we have declared
here a double-type variable x.
Now, we are trying to assign the value
of the expression "3 * x"
- which is of the type double -
to our int-type
variable n.
The compiler will simply refuse
to compile this code
and will produce an error message
"possible loss of precision"
informing us that through this assignment,
we will use the value
after the period.
On the other hand, it is possible
to assign an int-type value
to a decimal-type value, for
example of the type double.
Here, we have declared
an int-type variable n.
Now, we're trying to assign
the value of the expression "2 * n"
- which is of the type int"
to our double-type variable x.
In this case, the compiler will
automatically convert
from int to double, which is
perfectly possible.
Indeed, in this case, there is
no loss of precision.
Now, let us go back to the
trap of the integer division.
Here, we have declared a double-type
variable x, represented here.
Through this assignment,
we assign the value of the
expression 1/2 to our variable x.
In your opinion, what will x
contain after this assignment?
1 and 2 are both int-type
literal values.
This division is
therefore the integer division
In the case of the integer division
1 / 2 is 0.
We will therefore assign
the value 0 to the variable x.
By the way, please note
that there is an automatic conversion from
int to double since this
0 here is of the type int
and the 0 assigned to x
is obviously of the type double.
Therefore, the fact that x is of
type double,
has no influence of the evaluation
of the expression 1 / 2
The problem will occur in practice
when we try, for example, to calculate
the average of two integer values.
In this example, we have an int-type
variable note1 (TN:"note" means "grade")
initialized to 4.
note2, also of the type int,
is initialized to 5.
Now, what will happen if we try to
calculate their average through this declaration?
In this expression,
note1 and note2 are of  type int.
Their sum is therefore also of type int.
So, their sum is 9,
an int-type value.
This 2 here, to calculate the
average is an int-type literal value;
this division is thus
the integer division.
Therefore, we will calculate the
result of the integer division 9 by 2
and obtain the value 4, assigned to our
variable moyenne (TN:"moyenne" means "average")
This is problematic; we expected
the average to be 4.5
A possible solution is to
start by calculating the sum
of the two int-type variables.
here, we have "note1 + note2"
assigned to the variable moyenne
"note1 + note2" is 9, of the type int
which will be assigned to the variable moyenne.
Following this instruction, which is
equivalent to
"moyenne = moyenne / 2 ".
2 is an int-type literal value.
However, moyenne is a double-type
literal value.
Therefore, this division is the
standard division
and we will, this time, obtain 4.5
in our variable moyenne.
Let us conclude by saying
that we may use functions
and mathematical constants
in Java expressions.
To that end, you simply
need to respect the following notations  :
For example, if we wish
to use a function,
we will start by writing "Math."
followed by the function's name,
followed by the values
needed in the function.
In the case of constants,
we start, once again,
by writing "Math."
followed by the constant's name.
For example, if you we want to
calculate the sine of an angle,
we will write "Math.sin()" in order
to use the sine function,
followed by the angle which
sine we want to calculate.
In Java, the trigonometric functions
expect a value in radians.
For example, if we have a 10
degrees angle, here,
we first need to convert it into
radians before feeding it to the sine function.
To that end, we simply need to multiply
it by "pi" and divide it by 180.
We did just that here.
In order to obtain the value pi,
we simply wrote "Math.PI"
By the way, this is not an integer
division
but the division we are familiar with
because Math.PI is of the type double.
If you are interested, you will find
all the available Java functions
by clicking this URL.