So welcome back. In this module, we'll be talking
about the hydration reactions. And this is clearly the fundamental
aspect which is responsible for the behavior of cementations materials.
In this first module I'm going to give you an overview of what hydration is
the different phases we have present and how they
contribute to this hydration process, in later
videos. We're going to look in more detail at these individual hydrate phases and
then the mechanisms of hydration. So before we go on we have a
question of nomenclature, now cement chemists are a little bit lazy
and because we're generally dealing with oxides we have a
shorthand to shorten the chemical formula. Now you need to know
this but it is really quite simple. Basically, calcium
oxide or lime which is rationed Ca0 in full
chemical notation becomes simply C.
Similarly, silicon dioxide or silica which is as SIO2
the form location becomes S, aluminum
oxide or alumina AL2O3 becomes A
iron oxide becomes F, sulfate becomes
S or S dollar or dollar sign and water
becomes H. So could you give some examples or you can see how
the formula was shorted or shortened. So if we talk about the main
phase that is reacting important cement, this is called tri calcium
silicate or a light. And in the full chemical formula this
has to be mentioned as Ca3SIO5. is quite
long but this can be simply shortened by the chemical. The cement
chemist notation C3S and it's often also known
by this name C3S. if we look at
another re-active mineral that we may find in Calcium sulfate or Illuminati's
cements. This is called Yellow miters the mineral name and the full chemical
formula is even more complex Ca4 Al6 SO16
and this can simply be shortened to C4A3S
and that is often known by that phrase. C4A3S but
still a bit of a mouthful but not as bad as this one over here.
If we now go on to the hydrates notably calcium silicate hydrate
which is making up the majority of sematiouse micro structures
we have a further complication that the stoichiometry of this
phase is not fixed, this varies quite widely as we'll talk about
subsequently in the full chemical formula. I've represented that
variability by the X’s and y’s but on the right here
we see the way it's usually written by cement chemists that we use
hyphens here to denote that the ratios between these different
elements are not fixed and we normally call this phase C S H.
So this is very important to remember this terminology.
OK. So let's go back to the schematics. We saw these in the earlier
lecture to give a very basic idea of how cement
works and I really want to stress that it's all to do with volumes. So
when we mix the gray powder with water what we have is these gray cement
grains floating about in water and then the cement
grains are dissolving in the water. This is exaggerated in the next picture
here where you see the grains get smaller. So the ions that
are in the cement grains are passing into the water and then they're making
new combinations and those combinations are precipitating
as the hydrates which we've seen here in red. So now
we see the basic idea that these red hydrates are now
joining the cement grains together and by joining the cement grains
together you get a rigid solid which has strength but you will still have
some areas where there's no material may contain water, may contain air.
And these are known as porous. So it's very important to
keep this basic idea of hydration as this change in
solid volumes in your head. We can look at it another
way. First of all in a real microstructure. So this is a picture of a
real cement grains. And what you can see in the cement
grains is that they've got different levels of gray which means they've
got different chemical compositions. And typically in cement we can
identify four main phases. So we see this phase
here which is called a light or C3S. This is the
majority phase and we will make up between 40 and 70
percent of the cement. Then we see some other grains like
this one down here, a more rounded and this grain is made
of what we called B light or C2S. So this is another calcium silicate face
but has somewhat less calcium than the C3S, this also means it's
less reactive. And then in addition
to these A light to B light we can see this darker phase which is the illuminate
phase. Or C3S and this very
bright face. It's very bright because this is the face which contains the ion which
is called ferrite. And this is usually written as C4AF
although you should be aware that the ratio of aluminum to iron
is not fixed at 1 to 1. So these are the four faces that
make up our Portland cement. So then what we see
here is the different reactivity of these different faces we
can see that the compressive strength coming from C3S is by far the
highest. And this is why generally we tend to try to maximize the amount of
C3S in our port in our Portland cement clinker
to us is very very much slower. And as we saw in the
one of the earlier modules, this is why really it doesn't make any sense
to make cement with high content and B light from an environmental
perspective. It may make sense from a point of view of having low heat cements
The illuminate faces and the ion faces. We need some calcium sulfates
This is why we have the gypsum juried grinding has been mentioned before.
These tend to react quite fast but they don't give such high strength as the C3S
So now off the hydration
there's great clink clinker grains transform to
give us the microstructure of the hardened cement paste.
We can still see cement grains which haven't reacted. These are the bright
areas here. But now in between these grains we can see the
hydrates and we can identify in particular two
different types of hydrates we can identify these areas
here which are lighter gray than the rest of the hydrates but still darker
than the anhydrous. And these regions here are what calcium
Hydroxide, calcium hydroxide as a very simple and simple formula
of 1CHOH2. And
this is one of the main faces formed from the calcium silicates
and then apart from the calcium hydroxide the rest of the hydrates have this
kind of dark gray levels. We can still see that they're lighter
than the pools which we can see in black such as here. And
this other hydrates we can say it's
majority CSH around the cement grains we can see
these nice rims. We call these rims have formed in the place of the
cement grain which is reactive. And this is caught in a CSH
Whereas now between the grains we have what we call out to
hydrates and this is a very fine mixture of CSH of
AFM and of AFT faces which we can't distinguish from each
other at this level of resolution here.
As I said before it's really these volume changes at its critical, the
ratio between cement and water are usually expressed by weight. But we're
interested in the volume ratio. So typically our
water to cement ratio in weight terms would be said to be
0.5
And this means for each gram of cement present we add 0.5 grams of
Water, but the development of properties is controlled by the filling
of space which is related to the volumes. So I think it's a nice little
exercise if you can translate that water cement ratio by
ways of 0.5 into volume. And I think you can switch off the
video here. You can make this calculation for yourself. I'll tell you that the
relative density of the cement is around three. I hope you know that the relative density of
water is one and then you should be able to make a nice simple calculation
to calculate the relative volumes of cement and water just after mixing.
So I hope you manage to work that out. But when we have a water to cement ratio
of 0.5 by weight this means that the relative volumes of cement
and water at the beginning we have about 40 percent cement and about
60 percent water. So you see we actually have more water by
volume than we have cement and we need that amount of water by
volume to give us the fluidity. You know if any of you have made a
cake that you have the grains of flour and you need to add a
certain amount of liquid to make a floatable cake mixture
and make a cement paste is really exactly like that you have this gray powder which is the
cement. You have to add a certain amount of water to fill the spaces
between those cement grains and give you this floatable  cement paste
so we can go. Nowadays we can go to somewhat low water cement ratios
particularly if we use admixtures like super plasticizers will come back to
that in another module.
But if we don't have any super plasticizers then we
would typically use this more cement ratio of 0.5
So that's the ratio between the solid and the liquid
at the start. What then happens is we have this hydration
reaction and during this hydration We action. We have roughly
a doubling of the solid volume so that this 40 percent
here this becomes now 80 percent
and the rest that doesn't get filled by these hydrates will
still remain as poor.
And this is then why these hydrates occupy a higher volume.
They can then bridge the cement grains together. They can give us this rigid poor
solid that has strength. So please I really cannot
emphasize enough just how important it is to think in terms
of volumes. Now if we look a little bit more detail
at the different phases. What comes from what? what we have here
on the left is we have the approximate compositions of a typical
Portland cement 70 percent C3S or A light
16 percent C2S or B light, 8 percent C3A
and 7 percent ferrite face.
And then roughly speaking the C3S reacts to give us
this phase CSH and calcium hydroxide. We also get these
two phases from the C2S while
the illuminate face and the ferrite face react to give us these
faces we call AFT and AFM faces, and
in subsequent videos we're going to see what is the chemical
composition the crystal structure of all these different hydrate faces.
But what's really important to see is that CSH is
really the most important in a typical cement paste, mature cement paste. This
makes up nearly half of the solid material. Now
this kind of one to one correspondence is what's
usually written down but in fact all of these
Hydrates, all formed what's called flu solution. So first of all
as we saw in the schematic, the cement faces dissolve. They
form these different ions which go into the solution
phase and you see in the solution we then get these ion of
calcium of silicate of alumina hydroxide sulfate et cetera
and then these ions combine in the different proportions
to give us these hydrate faces which then precipitate from the
Solution, another way we can look at these
hydrates is in this term tree diagram where we plot the different
hydrates in this triangle here of calcium
oxide or in the hydrated form calcium hydroxide (14:45)
the ALOH3 illuminant hydrated illuminant gel and up here
hydrated silica gel, and again here we can
see that we have a very important phase of CSH
CSH. Well we have quite a wide range of chemical compositions will discuss in the
next video CSH. We can also contain quite significant
amounts of aluminum and then down here
we have the various illuminate hydrates. Now if we look at the composition
of Portland cement which is shown by this blue area here we can
see that this composition of the Portland cement lies in this triangle
bounded by CSH here by Portlander to calcium hydroxide
here and by the illuminator hydrate faces here.
Here we come back to the kinetics of the reaction we've already mentioned this but in the
context this is a very important aspect of Portland cement because this
really determines their technological use. So we
look at the kinetics of reaction we generally measuring the amount of heat evolved
and we see initially we get this very short burst of heat but then the
heat evolution is quite low during a period of several hours
and this period of low heat evolution means that we have the time to mix our
cement or concrete and to transport it to the building site put it in
place to build our walls et cetera. And then after
three hours or so the rate of reaction starts to increase rapidly
and we get this main reaction which occurs during the
first day and in subsequent videos we're going to be looking
at what are the mechanisms determine these different stages of the reaction.
So to finish this video and just to summarize what we're
seeing here is hydration reaction involves the reaction of cement with water.
And the critical aspect to this is the increase in solid volume which reduces the
space between grains forming a rigid solid. So the calcium
silicates C3S and C3S generally form calcium hydroxide in CSH
while the illuminated ferrite faces lead to the formation
of these faces we call AFT and AFM. So in the next few modules
we're going to look at the structure of these hydrates in detail and the mechanisms control the
kinetics So we'll hope you'll come back to listen to those.