So welcome to the second video
in the hydration module
and in this module, this section
we're going to talk about the C.S.H. phase
which as we've seen in the overview is the most
important hydration product.
so just as a reminder, what we saw in
the overview was that when we have the trial
some silicate faces hydrating that's to say C3S
and C2S, We form two hydrates.
we have calcium hydroxide, has lots of
different names. Often referred to as
Portlandite or as CH.
and This form is about ten to
twenty percent of the hydrated paste.
and then we have this phase calcium silicate hydrate,
which is written in this numenclature C-S_H.
Which is a rather complex but even though
it's complex we have to understand it
and this is making up as we've seen more than
half of the cement paste. So what we're going to talk about in this video
we're going to talk first of all
about the atomic structure of the composition
and then we're going to talk about the Mesa structure
and then we're going to talk about the microstructure.
Now the first point I really want to emphasize is the C.S.H.
Truly is a definite phase
with the reproducible behavior
when I came into the field more than
thirty years ago, people often talk about C.S.H.
Like it was this complete random unknown
material. But what we didn't know before
but what has been really clearly established
that it is a phase with a reproducible thermodynamic behavior.
And that's what I'm trying to illustrate on these two graphs here.
On these two graphs you see the results of many many
different experiments carried out over the last
Eighty years or more on examining the C.S.H.
and Always although there's a lot of scatter because
of the experimental measurements always we see that we get the
same behavior of C S H.
And the other thing this very important home this slide
is we see that we have this variation in the calcium to silicon
ratio of the C.S.H.
Depending on the composition of the solution.
So this variation in the calcium silicon ratio of the C.S.H
is shown by the green boxes on these graphs. On
the left of the green box we have the C.S.H.
Co-existing with silica gel
and on the right of the box we have to CSH
co-existing with Portlandite or calcium hydroxide.
And the co-existence with Portlandite
is of course the situation we are closer to
when we're talking about cement pastee.
Now what's important here is that people who have tried to.
Produce calcium silicate hydrate in the laboratory,
that's to say we often call that synthetic C.S.H.
Mixing different solutions together,
they really can make C.S.H.
With calcium to silicon ratios of 1.7
to about 1.5.
However, when we go to cement paste,
we can clearly see that in fact we have C.S.H.
Of much higher counting to silicon ratio
in the range of 1.7 to two
and this is still somewhat of an open question today why
we can get these much higher calcium to silicon ratios, we now
think it's really connected to the
difficulty of precipitation of calcium hydroxide.
For a long time it's been
realised the C.S.H is related to the.
Natural mineral tobermorite
and Tobermorite is so called because it was found on the
Toba Maury which is located off the coast of Scotland.
And this is the crystal structure of Tobermorite.
It has a calcium to silicon ratio of 0.83.
And the main characteristics of this crystal structure
of the following. First of all we have these layers of calcium
and oxygen so this is what you see here
you see the calcium atoms in this kind of turquoise color
and the oxygen atoms in red.
So this is the layers of calcium oxygen
and in fact these layers are very similar to the layers
you have in calcium hydroxide. It's probably not a coincidence.
And then all of these layers what we see is these chains
of silicate tetrahedra So the silicate atoms are at the center
of those blue texture Hedron and at the
corners of these tech we have oxygen atoms.
And this tetrahedral organization of silicon is very
common in nature it's what you have in cause, it's what you
have in lose, so you know it's
really how silica prefers to be
But in this job a more right what
you see is we form these long chains
and these chains have a repeating pattern of three. So for the
repeating pattern of three we use the word driketan which in German
means three chain. And you see we have to atoms
which are attached to this calcium auction layer
and then we have one tetrahedra
which is sticking out from that layer.
Then the third element of this Tobermorite structure is what
we call the interlayer, that's this region in here.
And this region in here contains water molecules
and also can contain calcium ions for example
and in more complex cases there are other eye on such
as alkali ions which can come into this space. So this is the
structure of Tobermorite. We know the structure of the
very high degree of confidence because we can make single
crystals of Tobermorite and examine the by X.Ray diffraction.
So the question then is how do we go from this tobermorite
structure to the structure of C S H?
And the main problem here is of course we see here we have a calcium
silicon ratio of 0.83,
but we know that in the C.S.H.
We have in cement paste the calcium silicon ratio is
generally much higher than that. In pace it can be up to 2.
So what people have really looked at is the ways
in which we can change the calcium to silicon ratio.
And I'm going to try and illustrate that
in the following slides.
Now the first and most simple way of varying the calcium
silicon ratio is to emmit these bridging tetrahedra.
So we see these bridging tetrahedra here, if these are emitted
So for example here you see this one is missing, then we start to
change the calcium silicon ratio we have
less silicon the same amount of calcium
and as we go through this sequence you can see on the
right here it's telling you the calcium to silicon ratio
and you see it's going up.
So that's the first way we can introduce
defects which increase the calcium to silicon ratio.
But this is nowhere near enough
to take us through the
kind of calcium silicon ratios we know we
have in cement paste. We need other mechanisms
and the second mechanism we can
have is that instead of these
hydroxide ions terminating here, we can replace these
two hydrogens here with a calcium atom. So calcium is a double
charged ion, hydroxide is singularly charged,
so we can go from two hydroxide ions to one calcium line.
And this then because now we have more calcium to the amount
of silicon again, the calcium to silicon ratio is increased
And here we see by replacing all the hydroxide with calcium,
we can get quite a significant increase in the calcium
silica ratio.
But what we see here with this version is that
even though we've now emmitted all the bridging sites,
and we've got calcium replaced in the hydroxide
this is still not enough to get us through the calcium silicon ratios
we see in C.S.H.
So the next mechanism is
to work on this into layer
and you know to have calcium ions in this interlayer.
So here we see various different versions with calcium in the interlayer
and now we're starting to really approach the calcium
silicon ratios we find. So this example here is a calcium silicon
ratio of 1.5, which is round about
the upper limit we find for C.S.H.
Precipitation from solution in the laboratory.
So just to summarize here, what we've seen is that
there are three kinds of defects we can put in tobermorite.
We can have missing regime tetrahedra. We can have calcium
replacing terminating hydroxide and we can have calcium in
the interlayer.
And really what's important is that there's no unique
way to get a specific outcome silicon ratio, we can have
different combinations of these
three kind of defect mechanisms.
And what we think is that the structure probably
has a really random organization of these defects,
This could be one reason for the low crystaline
see the fact that we generally don't see C.S.H. By
X.Ray diffraction. Also the in tropic effect of having
this random organization of different defects could probably be an
important element in stabilizing the C.S.H. Structure.
So here we show just some examples of the full unit
cells of different calcium silicon ratios.
here we see this one here calcium silicon 1.4.
Here we see calcium silicon 1.72
and here we see calcium silicon 1.94. So this
is right now coming to the upper limits. You see that we have
most of the bridging sites disappeared we have mostly
calcium ions terminating the tetrahedra
and we have some calcium in the interlayer.
The other aspect which is important
to talk about is the presence an allumium.
So when we make micro
analysis in the S.C.M.
This is what is shown on the left here. Then we can
quite clearly see that this cloud of points here which corresponds
to the C.S.H. This cloud of points has a
displacement along the Aluminuim into calcium axis.
So we can see that the intersection of
these lines from ettringite to monosulfate is coming at it
and now I'm into calcium ratio of about 0.05.
And this corresponds to an aluminium into
silicon ratio of roughly 0.1
Which is to say about one in ten of the silicon atoms are
replaced by aluminium. In other studies have
shown that
the aluminium tends to be located in these bridging sites,
that is to say the tetrahedral positions which are facing out
and not in the positions which are
attached to the calcium oxide sheets.
And this ratio of about one to ten which we find
portland cement paste can go quite substantially higher
when we have supplementary cementitious materials which
contain a lot of aluminium such as for example MehtaKalen.
Now I hope you have a fairly good idea of
the atomic structure of composition
and now we're going to
look at the meso structure.
And this area of Meso structure is probably
the area where we have still quite a few open questions
and need to advance our understanding.
So why do we think that C.S.H.
Has a particular meso structure?
Well the experimental evidence for
this goes back quite a long way.
First and foremost is the observation that we have no
long range order. That's to say in normal cement paste, We
don't see specific peaks from the
calcium hydroxide by X.Ray diffraction
The second thing which was pointed out already
by powers back in the 1940's was that C.S.H.
Has this intrinsic porosity. OK So what do I mean by
intrinsic prosity? What I mean is that when you form the C.S.H.
The same amount as you increase the amount of C.S.H.
that is formed, you increase the
amount of this particular type of prosity.
and this particular type of prosity
is often referred to as gel pores.
And now in the last twenty or so years,
we've had a lot of evidence from different scattering
experiments from neutrons scattering, from small angle
X.Ray
scattering and most recently from ProtonNMR,
which indicates that this gel porosity has a
characteristic size of about four to five nanometers.
And if we look at the kind of
spectra we have from proton
and a more then we can see a specific peak.
OK, so now there are two schools of
thought about the structure of C.S.H.
So on the left here, we see the very widely
cited model that originated with Jennings.
And Jennings did a lot of work around
this idea that you have this Cloyd role model of C S H.
So what do we mean by this Cloyd role model?
we mean in this model the little areas of CSH
are discrete nano particles, which are not linked together.
And these discrete nano particles are
made up of about four or
five layers of the C.S.H.
On the right here what we see is the what's often called
the feldman sterada model. Although not all aspects that
we're going to talk about here were
explained like that by Feldman and Serada.
And this Feldman and Serada model, we have
nanocrystalline regions where the layers of C.S.H.
Are quite well aligned
and then those layers extend from one
Nanocrystalline region to another crystalline region.
And this kind of arrangement of the layers leaves pockets
where we have higher amounts of porosity, which we could relate
to the gel porosity.
OK so this model on the left
iss somewhat similar to what you have in Semi crystalline
polymers for those of you who have made studies in
polymers.
Now we have to say well what's the evidence for one
or the other of these model?
Well for me seeing is always believing
and I think the best evidence
is really coming from
and now from transmission electron microscopy. So these show
you two transmission electro micrographs from cement pace.
At this very fine level people are often distinguishing
two types of morphology. The morphology we see on the left here
with these kind of fibrils of C.S.H. and The
morphology we see on the right which is
said to be kind of like foils.
But in neither of these cases even though we are quite
high resolution here of two hundred microns, in either of these
cases do we really see any evidence for these colloidal
particles. of course we don't see the C.S.H.
Layers either, so we don't yet have a full understanding
of how this kind of microstructure a model at this level, might
relate to this Feldman and serada model either.
But nevertheless, my personal feeling is that we have much
more similarity, much more chance that the real structural
C.S.H. At that level is something like what we see in
the Feldman and serada model than it is in the Cloyd own model.
But at the end of the day, I think it's more important
to focus on the similarities between these two schools of thought
in contrast to the differences.
So I've tried to show those similarities here that
this is the colloidal model on the left where we
have these Part Nanocrystalline regions which are not connected.
This is the kind of alternative model on the right
where we have nano crystalline regions which are
connected
and you know for many points of view it's probably not
so important which one is correct in terms of mechanical
behavior for example, we would expect to have quite
high forces between these colloidal particles, which would be of the
same order as breaking
a few sheets on the left.
So that's probably what we can say at this
point in time for the meso structure of C.S.H
So finally in this short video,
we're going to look at the microstructure.
Here we now I think have a very clear picture
and our very clear picture really shows us that we
have to microstructure a distinct forms of C.S.H.
So this picture of the top on the left here, this is
what is often shown this is this kind of needle like sea urchin
morphology and this is the kind of C.S.H. That forms early
on in the hydration process, is the kind of C.S.H.
that nucleates on the surface of the cement grains and
that's why we call the C.S.H. outter Product or early C.S.H.
And Then we're quite clear that at later times
we get this C.S.H, this much more dense C.S.H.
Which we can see in this bottom micrograph on the left.
We can see this is the outer C.S.H.
Here and underneath it's this more dense C.S.H.
and It's more clear to see these two different forms
in a cross section such as shown on the right, which is then
imaged with backscatter the electron
images in backscatter electrons.
So here we see
an hydrated cement grain. You can see this dent thick layer
of inner product. It is called in a product because it's formed
in place of the cement grain
and just on the surface of that you can see this fine
outer early product. Now those of you who have looked in the
literature somewhat may also have noticed
that there are all these terms high density
and low density. Of course from a simplistic point of view,
we can say that the in a product is clearly high density
and certainly in the initial stages
the outer product is low density
but there's still quite a bit of debate as
to whether we can make a direct analogy between high density
and low density and inner product and outter product.
So that's still something under discussion.
But these two different forms are quite clear.
00:21:00,30
So if we now come to look at an
overall microstructure of a typical
cement paste, we can clearly identify the original cement
grains, So for example here we have a cement grain, here we have
a relational cement grain
and in this paste dehydration is quite advanced,
so we have a some some regions of an hydrated cement paste such as
here and here and these are surrounded by
quite dense regions of the innner C.S.H.
And Then in the space between these large grains,
we can identify this kind of well to C.S.H.
but still we can see indications of this needle
structure that formed very early in the beginning.
So to summarize all that far,
we've seen today, we've looked at the atomic level structure
This is now really very were understood through
contributions that have been made from Silicon enema
We've seen that this is based on these sheets of
calcium oxygen with mainly dimas of silica
tetrahedra attached
And then we also may have aluminium
substitution of the silicon in the bridging site.
The Meso structure, we still have some
open questions we have either none of crystal lights
or none of crystalline regions with the characteristic
size of somewhere in the region of five microns.
And finally in the microstructure we can clearly identify
first of all what we call out a product which forms early for
a solution and then in a
product wish forms at later times.
00:22:47,20
So I hope that given you
some insight into the C.S.H. Hydrates
In the next video we'll look at the illuminated hydrates.
Thank you.