OK. so welcome back and welcome to this module on the illuminate for
Hydrates. In the last slides we saw about
these hydrates that formed from the hydration of the calcium silicates spaces that's to
say C3S mainly and C2S later on. And in
this module we're going to look at the hydrates that formed from the
Illuminates, that’s to say the C3A face and the ferrite face usually called
C4AF if these faces are not as prevalent as the ones from the
calcium silicate faces but nevertheless quite significant. So in this slide
we see the faces that are formed from a typical ordinary Portland
cement. And while the face is from the calcium silicates that's to say calcium
hydroxide and CSH are making up about 65 percent of
the volume of the final paste the hydrates coming from the
C3S and C4AF that’s to say this AFM and AFT are still
accounting for about 25 percent by volume. So this is a quite
significant amount of the final volume of the paste. Now these
illuminator hydrate sprawly come in three families. First we have these
routes which are called austenite. Now the formula of austenite is
as written here as to say for each molecule of C3A we have
three molecules across him sulfate and then a lot of water.
And in what we're going to see in a lot of these hydrates we can have a
replacement of the aluminum ions by ion ions. These are very similar
elements from a chemical point of view and because of that as well
as the term austenite which means perform with Aluminum and we also
have this term AFT, so A and F means the
possibility for having either Illumina or iron oxide and
T is the other anions. That's to say in
this case the calcium sulfate. And here we have three calcium sulfates. So
three gives us the word tri. Now the second family
has many more variants depending on the different anions that we find.
And for this reason we tend to use more often the generic word
A F M standing for Aluminate ferrite Maula face.
And finally we don't usually have very much of it in common cement
pace. We have the hydrocarbons and in the next slides we're going to look at each of
these families in turn and see in more detail about their crystal structure
and the possibilities of solid solution. Austenite was first found
in the town of Austyn hence the name and in nature it conforms these
very big crystals so if we look at this picture here we can see we can get these really
huge crystals which have this hexagonal cross-section
and we can see the crystal structure is like this. So we have
columns and in these columns we have Illumina and we have the calcium
surrounded by lots of hydroxide ions and then in between the columns
we have these sulfate molecules. More generally the formula
is like this, so we have three calcium’s either aluminum or
iron and then these hydroxide groups and the water molecules
and then the X3. This can be a divergent A9, in this
case we're talking about here. It's sulfate. But another possibility
is carbonate. So Eshun guide forms early on in cement
pace and some may later transform into the AFM phases that we're
going to see later depending on the amount of sulfate and carbonate we have in the
paste. So in most cement pace and indeed most
blended cements there's not much variation in fact in the
Composition, the composition we find is pretty close to the story here
metric austenite. So even though we know we can have this solid
solubility between aluminum and ion in actual cement pace
because of the high alkalinity of the poor solution not much of the iron actually
goes into the austenite phase is pretty much just the pure aluminum form.
We have some salt solution as I've mentioned between carbonate ion and
sulfate and this can be stabilized at low
temperature so at low temperatures we tend to get more carbonate going into the
AFT phase and the other important aspects about austenite
of it has this high water content as we've seen. And because of this it actually has
quite a low density. Okay, and because it has low density this means fills up a lot of
space. So in terms of filling space it makes a very positive
contribution to strength development and other properties.
Now in terms of stability the stability of austenite thermal terms is
very very similar to that of the CSH. Here we see the thermal
decomposition curves by DTA for entering CSH. And we
can see that the peak for the two is in a very very similar position at
120 140 around that kind of temperature. Now
as we move to the second group AFM phase. These are part of a much
larger group of hot hydrates called layered double hydroxide. Some of you may have
heard of lead double hydroxide because they're really research quite a
lot nowadays for the interesting electronic properties. And in this layer
double hydroxide. We have layers of
M2 and M3 ions and then between the layers we have
these anions and the fact you can put in a lot of different anions leads to what's
called parley typist. So in this larger a family of layer double
hydroxide is quite a large number of groups have been
defined purrfect age groups with this what's called hydro
tower site supper in the super groups So this hydro tower sites where you have
three to one divalent to trivalent ions the queen ion
group where we have two to one divalent to trivalent so on. And
finally we come to the Hydra catamite group which is what interests us where these
divalent ions are calcium and the trivalent ions are
Aluminum and they exist in the ratio of two to one.
So this is the AFM face is this is the kind of layer we
have in those AFM phases is a distorted layer similar to what we have
in bruce sites with two calcium to one Alumina. And then
the add on that can go in between. That gives us the AFM faces
most commonly. Well I mean the first one that gave its name to this group
are the Maula sulfates where the line is sulfate. But probably in fact
more common today is where we have carbonate ions as
in mono carbonate and we can also have hydroxide ions as is high at titrate calamite
we can have chloride ions as infidel's salt and even
complex aluminum silicate ions as instructing
as we will see. Now one of the key questions in understanding
these faces and particularly how much of forms and what is their
contribution to space filling We need to know what is the
extent of solid solution. So if we take the three most
common or if we take that the most common
substitution which is between sulfate and carbonate we have
these three phases we have mono sulfate we see at the top we have the carbonate
we see at the bottom on the right and the Hemy carbonate which we see at the
bottom on the left. Now because of the different anions
in the interlayer you can see that the interlayer
spacing for these crystal faces is
quite different. 8.9 for the mono sulfate. 7.8 for the
carbonate an 8.2 for the Hemi carbonate. So these may
not seem that big but they are big enough such as in fact
we find that these differences mean that we get really no
solid solution between these different faces and the transformation
from one to another really occurs by dissolution and the
precipitation of the new faces. And if we look more
broadly also in cruising the hydroxide phases the hydro
calamite face down here. This shows us that really
the only regions of solid solution we have are on this axis between
the Hydro calamite and the and the sulfate form
where we can have some solid solution. Otherwise there's really very little solid
Solution, as I said classically when
people are thinking about cement hydration they think about austenite   forming.
And then most of the textbooks say yes there is more a sulfate forming
and this is what we can see happens in cement without
limestone here you can see that on one day and seven days
austenite is dominating but by the time we get to one year we clearly
have a lot more sulfate faces. Now most cements made
today do in fact contain a small amount of limestone 3 or
4 percent is typical because this amount of limestone has been shown to
improve properties at the same time gives us a slight reduction in
the net CO2 emissions. And when we have those cements with
limestone then we can see the picture changes quite dramatically. And
instead of the more sulfate phase here we have instead forming
First of all Hemy carbonate at about 7 for about seven days. And
later on Mono carbonate, and this is what is one
reason why we get improved performance with this small amount of limestone
because small amounts of limestone can react with the calcium illuminates from
the cement forming these extra phases and this means we have more
space filling and more strength. Ok so finally in this AFM
group we're just going to have a quick look at this phase called Strectlinghyde eyes and
this phase call strectlinghyde  has this very complex alumina
silicate groups in the interlayer. You can see now that this has
increased quite dramatically the spacing of these interlayers from
about seven or eight we had in the mono sulfate molar carbonate cases
to this value of 12.6 And this can be quite an
important phase where we have very high contents of
alumina and silica reacting in blended cements and (11:49)
it only forms once all the Portland diets being consumed.
But in reality we can often find stretching. Well we still have small amounts of
Portland diets presence. So finally in this module we're going to look
at the hydro garnets and the classic
formula for hydro garnets this formula C3AF6
which is also known as the mineral catalite. And more
generically what we see. Again we can have solid solution between
alumina and iron but now we can have a solid solution between
one silicate group and two water groups. So this is why they call
hydro garnets, because if all the water was replaced by silicate this would
be the garnet's structure, and in reality we always have quite a bit of
water. And in this case this is actually the
phase where most of the iron goes to in Portland cement pace. So I said that
the iron because of its low mobility in high alkaline solutions didn't
go much into the austenite, doesn't go much into the AFM phase but it does
form the salacious hydro Garnett's which that ends up being quite a lot of. But it's
rather poorly crystalline. So not often well tested by xrd.
Now other important aspects about this phase is it's got a low water content
and because it got low water content it has a high density and this means that
it's less space filling. So what if we had a lot of hydro garnets as we would get if we
Cure's high temperature this also contributes to the
relatively poor strength and high temperatures because this phase occupies less
space. So here are some other pictures of the crystal structures of
the hydro garnets we have in the it's a sort of three
dimensional structure in which four fold four cores native
silicon connects the six coordinates of the Alumina
is predicted to form quite a lot in blended cement. But as I said really
not  much except for the ion
So if we summarize this module what we see in this module is that if the
illuminator contain hydrates are a very important part of this hydrate face assemblage
they make up about typically about 25 percent of the volume and mature pace
they do contribute to space filling and therefore the contribution strength development very
much in the same way as CSH in pace as long as we have a
continuous CSH phase with austenite and
Mono Sulfate finally buried in it then they are contributing in
same way to strength development. Austenite can be formed
with different substitutes. But in most Portland cement paste most  blended cement pace
it's really very close to the  stoichiometry formula in AFM phases
on the other hand Solid solution is much more important and limestone as we
find almost ubiquitously present in molten cements that favors the
formation of carbon illuminates rather than Mono sulfate faces as you've
properly learnt in the past. Final type hydro garnets
forms only at long ages or at high temperatures. OK. So thank you very
much.