In the previous video, we introduced
some basic cosmology notions
and we tied the notion of red shift
to the expansion factor of the Universe.
The challenge is now to link redshifts
to distances
because they can be calculated or predicted
by comological models.
If we can measure distances,
we can test cosmological models
by confronting the predictions of the models
to the observations
and by looking at models which are best capable
to predict the measured distances.
We will see in this video
how to measure the distances
and what the signification of these distances
are.
We will see that there are essentially 2 available
methods for this :
one is founded on what we call standard rulers
and the other on standard candles.
In the case of the standard ruler,
the principle is to measure how the angular
size of an object
varies with the red shift.
If also know the physical size of this standard
object,
we know its distance.
It's what is drawn here
where we see a galaxy with an intrinsic size
and an apparent size.
The intrinsic size will not change with the
distance,
but the measured size, the angular size of
the sky
will change and it's like this that we will
be able to measure the distance.
We can hold the same logic
and measure the apparent luminosity of an
object of which we would know also
the intrinsic luminosity, i.e., the absolute
magnitude.
It's what is shown here: a standard candle
with a well defined intrinsic luminosity
whose apparent luminosity will diminish with
the red shift and the distance.
It's thanks to these standard rulers and standard
candles
that we can link the red shifts
to the distances and make cosmological measurements.
What are we searching for in cosmology ?
We are trying to establish a connection
between redshifts
and the time that passes after the Big Bang.
So the time after the Big Bang is summarized
in this slide :
we have here the time beginning at time "zero".
The beginning of time is the Big Bang, which
is around here.
and then time passes after the Big Bang :
we arrive here for example at a red-shift
of 4
which corresponds to 1,5 billion years after
the Big Bang.
So time flows in this direction.
At present time, we are around 13,8 billion
years
and we will try to establish a connection
between the redshift
and time after the Big Bang, so the distance.
To do that, we need more and more powerful
observatories
So here we have the evolution in time of different
observatories.
Here's the Mount Palomar observatory with
a 5m telescope in diameter
which allowed to reach redshifts of the order
of 1
with cameras that had the sensitivity of the
90s.
Then from space with more and more sensitive
cameras,
as more and more servicing missions to the
space telescope allowed
to replace the cameras that were used with
the telescope.
We were able to go to ever greater distances.
Here, we see that we added the infra red.
Why?
Simply because the spectrum of the galaxies
we try to observe,
will be more and more red shifted
to the point of reaching the infra red domain.
We therefore need infra red detectors
if we want to observe at extremely large distances.
That is the actual space telescope
with optical and infra-red detectors.
and then there is the next generation space
telescope, the James Webb space telescope,
which will have only infra-red detectors.
It will be able to see extremely distant galaxies.
The diameter of the James Webb telescope is
also much bigger,
three times the actual space telescope diameter
which has a diameter of 2,4 meters.
What we try to do in observational cosmology,
is to use the fondamental relation
we established in the previous video.
between the redshift z or actually 1+z
and the expansion factor of the universe α(t)
and what we can measure: the cosmological
red shift
measured by Doppler effect.
That is the wavelength of an object as we
would observe it
and that is the emission wavelength of a signal
in the object's frame of reference that emitted
the signal.
The cosmological models give us the possibility
to determine
the distance to the objects, which will be
a function
of the red shift or the expansion factor,
and the cosmological parameters.
These cosmological parameters will be essentially
H zero
but also the density of the different components
of the universe.
These components will include the repulsive
dark energy
which is responsible for the accelerated expansion
of the universe
and dark matter.
Now how to define the distances ?
I said that we have standard rulers and standard
candles.
For standard rulers, we will suppose that
we have an object
of which we know the intrinsic radius
and then we observe this object at a given
distance d from us
and this object will underlie a solid angle,
the object has a given radius, which underlies
a certain solid angle ω
it is at a given distances from us, and that
is of interest
and we will have a relation between these
three quantities.
It's simply the relation
between the solid angle and the radius of
the object :
ω (the solid angle) will be equal to πR²
(R is the radius of the star)
and D is the distance that we are interested
in.
So by measuring the solid angle,
if we know the intrinsic radius of the object,
we get the distance we will call the angular
diameter distance,
DA(z) will be equal to the square root of
πR² over w (w is an angle).
This is what we call angular diameter distance.
We also said that we have standard candles.
If we look at what happens at the level of
the standard candles,
how we will define the distance?
If we have a standard candle,
we do not have anymore a stellar object with
a well known,
well callibrated, well determined radius
but we have a certain luminosity which will
be the standard luminosity.
We have already seen how to measure the flux
of an object
with a certain well known luminosity L
the object has an isotropic radiation at a
certain distance D from itself
and sends us a flux diluted over a sphere
like this
and the flux is simply
F is equal to L / (4πD²)
This allows us to define a second distance.
If we measure the flux of an object,
we know its intrinsic luminosity.
We deduce from it the distance we call the
luminosity distance
which depends on z (red shift)
measured by the Doppler effect,
so we will have D equal to L over 4π times
the measured flux.
This is what we call the luminosity distance.
So we have two possible definitions of the
distance,
one based on standard rulers,
and the other on standard candles.
So objects that have either a well known size
or a well known luminosity.
It's like this that we will define distances.
So let's see how the models
(we use a given cosmological model
without giving the details of this model),
here the curves that link the redshifts
to the distances in this case luminosity distances
and in this case angular diameter distances.
We have two types of distances.
In the case of luminosity distances
we have DL(z) equal to the square root of
L over 4πF
If we know an object of luminosity L
and place it a different redshifts,
we will measure a given flux
and deduce a given distance.
This is the predicted distance by a certain
cosmological model.
We have the angular diameter distance on one
side,
which will be equal to πR², so the intrinsic
radius,
which we are supposed to get by an independent
method,
and the solid angle which underlays the object.
We see that we do not have the same relations,
we do not have the same curves.
We have in fact a relation between the different
distances,
we have DL(z) = (1 + z) ² times DA(z)
it's for this that the curves are different.
They are different but not incompatible .
We just have two ways of defining distances.
It's important to define how we look at distances
:
either with angular diameter distances,
or with luminosity distances.
In both case, we have to confront the correct
observations,
to the correct theoretical predictions.
Here we have models that predict luminosities
or apparent fluxes.
Here we have models that predict apparent
solid angles
for reference objects.
It's important to know what distance we are
talking about.
There is also something that might seem counterintuitive
:
in the case of luminosity distances, an objects
gets fainter and fainter
as the red shift gets higher.
Here when the red shift goes up, the angular
diameter distance to an object
will get to a peak and then go down.
This means in practice: ω the apparent diameter
or apparent radius
of an object in the sky, when its red shift
gets higher
the apparent diameter will first go down
ω goes down, and then goes up in this part
here of the curve .
An object that we will put further and further
will have the tendency of getting bigger and
bigger in appearance.
However, its apparent luminosity will continue
to diminish.
and the distances are linked by this equation
here.
Now we will concentrate on the standard candle
methods
to measure distances.
We will link the velocity to the distances,
with Hubble's law,
valid for small shifts up, small z
or in other words we will try to link the
distances to a function
of cosmology (z) and cosmological parameters.
Here z is measured by Doppler effect.
Cosmology are the parameters of a model
and when we change these parameters, we change
the prediction of these models.
D is what we try to measure with standard
candles.
We have a very useful tool for that: the distance
module μ
the difference between the apparent magnitude
and the absolute magnitude of an object
which is equal to 5 times the log to the distance/sec
minus 5
So the method is very simple from here on:
if M is known, (for a standard candle)
and if m is measured, then we can deduce the
distance.
The standard candle method is extremely simple
:
we use the distance modulus
we measure it by measuring the apparent magnitude
of a celestial body
of which we know also the absolute magnitude
and we get the distance.
There are a series of objects which we can
consider
as standard chandles.
The most famous are the cepheides stars
and we will also see the supernovae.
First the Cepheid stars :
are gigantic stars that are extremely bright,
so we can them from far away and they will
be pulsating.
If they pulsate, their radius varies periodically.
We have the famous relation L = 4πR²σT4
If the radius varies, the temperature also
varies a little bit
but it's the luminosity in the end that will
vary.
There is a relation between the period and
the luminosity
of the Cepheid stars.
If I show you this on a graph :
here is what could be the absolute magnitude
of a Cepheid star,
the time is here,
and the light curve of the Cepheid star.
We have a given mean value,
we have a mean m,
we also have a period
and the Cepheid stars also have a link
between their absolute average magnitude and
the period.
So we have an average m which is equal to
a function of the period.
Also the luminosity grows with P
So M decreases with P because it's in magnitude
and the exact relation is m average in the
v band
is equal to minus 2,43 times (the decimal
logarithm of the period - 1) minus 4,05
This means that if we measure for example
observational points,
on a curve like this.
I take a galaxy in which there is a Cepheid
star,
I regularly measure its photometry
and then I will have what I call the light
curve.
I will be able to measure the period and so
have the absolute magnitude
that I will be able to inject in the distance
module.
Here is again the formula of the distance
modulus:
we will be able to inject m average here in
the formula of the distance modulus
and get the distance.
It's a relation that was first measured
by Henrietta Leavitt, in the years 1910-1920.
It's not something recent but it's only recently
that we could apply this method with the Hubble
space telescope
to measure distances to galaxies
to around 40 - 50 megaparsec from us.
There are some very well known stars that
are Cepheid stars :
obviously the δ Cephei star which is the
archetype of Cepheid stars
but the polar star is also a Cepheid star
The star towards which the rotation axis of
the earth points, the polar star,
is a pulsating Cepheid star.
As I said before, we used the space telescope
to observe the Cepheid stars.
We also need to separate the stars in the
Messier 31 galaxy in this case here,
to distinguish between the Cepheids and other
stars.
I said that Cepheid are very bright, here
is one
If we measure the luminous flux of that Cepheid
star in time,
we see that from here to here the star has
grown in brightness.
We measure the light curve, we measure the
period,
and we deduce the absolute magnitude.
For the Andromeda galaxy, the measured distance
is 778 +/- 17 kg/sec
and the recession velocity measured by Doppler
effect
is around 301 +/- 7 km/s,
so the Andromeda galaxy flees from us at an
approximate velocity of 300 km per second.
We know other standard candles which will
be
even brighter, so we will see them from even
further away :
which will be type 1a supernovae
I'll skip the details here on how supernovae
work.
They are two types. Type 1 supernovae stars
:
those are white dwarfs which are in orbit
around a common gravity centre with giant
or super giant stars.
Matter will go from the giant to the white
dwarf
and matter will accrete.
After some time, we will have a sufficient
critical mass
for a supernova explosion.
This is a type of supernova i haven't talked
about
in the previous videos.
What we had until now, were type 2 supernovae
which we call core-collapse supernovae.
We have seen that for massive stars
we have nuclear reactions up to the iron fusion
reaction
which takes place from here on,
the iron reaction being endothermic the core
of the star collapses
and we have a supernova explosion.
This is what we saw in the previous chapter.
chapter 5 on stellar evolution.
The supernovae of interest for us are type
1 a supernovae,
which are fact white dwarfs, so binary stars,
white dwarfs,
around a giant
and matter will fall, attracted by the white
dwarf,
spiral around the white dwarf
and so accrete matter
After some time,
we will reach the critical mass of the white
dwarf,
the critical mass is 1,44 Solar Mass
also called the Chandrasekhar mass.
Each time the white dwarf has accreted enough
matter,
that is 1,44 times the mass of the sun,
we will have a supernova detonation.
Since the critical mass is always the same
we will always have the same luminosity.
Actually it's the explosion peak that will
always have the same luminosity.
What is of interests here is what we call
the light curve of the supernova as in the
Cepheid stars case.
But this time on the axes we have the time
here
the luminosity here, and also the absolute
magnitude that would be here.
When the supernova explodes, it will grow
in luminosity,
reach a peak and then go down.
If we calibrate this curve, we will see that
at a given moment,
we have a luminosity peak that
will correspond to an absolute magnitude in
the v band of -19,3
So when a supernova explodes, we take some
measurement points,
we have a light curve,
we make the adjustment by least square over
the light curve,
we measure the peak and that gives us the
absolute magnitude in the v band
another time, that is what we will inject
in the distance modulus
to determine the distance to the supernova.
Here are some supernovae examples :
here we have a spiral galaxy at a relatively
short distance.
We have here the distance C measured through
supernovae
of 15,5 +/- 0,6 megaparsec
that is already a lot further away than the
Andromeda galaxy.
We would not be able to see Cepheids in a
galaxy like this.
The recession velocity here is much larger
: 602
so exactly twice that of Andromeda
so 602 km per second
and if we take a spectrum of that supernova
we will find that there is no hydrogen line.
Instead we will have silicium II, i.e., silicium
ionized once,
that can be found at the wavelength 6150 Å
It's these two caracteristics
that are the spectral signatures of type 1a
supernovae.
When a supernova explodes, we can do two things
:
we take a spectrum, we look if there is no
hydrogen
and if there is silicium
and we measure the light curve to get the
apparent magnitude
of the supernova, which will worrespond to
a given absolute magnitude.
So we will have the distance modulus
and the distance to the galaxy where the supernova
is.
Here is another galaxy NGC 3370
The distance is beginning to be a bit higher
:
we have a distance of around 30 megaparsec
We have here an observation taken by a ground
telescope,
with a supernova that exploded,
and an observation taken with the spatial
telescope
with the supernova before or after the explosion
in any case not present on the image.
The recession velocity of this galaxy is even
higher than the others :
1279 km per second for this one
Now if we go even further,
we'll be able to see the true usefulness of
the supernovae tool
We have galaxies at a red shift of around
1,
the red shift is around 1
and we have different supernovae here :
we see an extremely bright one here.
In fact many times brighter than the galaxy
in which the supernova is, which we barely
see.
We have another here which is in an interacting
galaxy.
Another one here, with a relatively blue supernova
spectrum.
And here another one.
So thanks to these supernovae
we will be able to measure the distances to
all these galaxies.
The further we go, the better we will test
the cosmological models.
What will be important here, thanks to the
Cepheids or supernovae,
is to construct what is called a Hubble diagram.
This Hubble diagram links the distance modulus
to the red shift.
Here is how one of these diagrams looks like
:
these are not observations or predictions.
It's just a qualitative schematic.
We will have here a red shift.
Here the distance module m minus M
So for the Cepheids, we measure the mean apparent
magnitude
and we know, thanks to the period-luminosity
relation,
the absolute magnitude.
For a supernova, we know the absolute magnitude
of the luminosity peak at the explosion.
We measure the apparent magnitude of the explosion
peak
and obtain the distance modulus.
Now we of course have theoretical predictions.
I draw like this,
theoretical models which link the red shift
to the distance modulus.
Then, we have to take sufficiently precise
observational points
to be able to discriminate between the different
cosmological models.
We can already see here that the further one
goes in red shift,
the more one will be able to discriminate
between the different models.
If I take points too close to us
we will not be able to discriminate between
the cosmological models,
while there we can do it.
Of course it is harder to measure distant
points
since we need bigger telescopes
but we also test the cosmology better.
The prediction of the models, the difference
between the curves,
will be the cosmological parameters so H zero
but also the different energy density parameters.
70% dark energy, 25% dark matter
and 5% baryonic matter or normal matter.
So the difference between these models here,
are the proportions of these different densities.
If we manage to measure μ and z,
we can differentiate between the different
cosmological models.
Since the years 2000, we know that we live
in an universe
in accelerated expansion, so we were able
to discriminate between the different curves
in these Hubble diagrams.
A word about what we call the distance scale
:
we have seen that we have different methods
to measure distances.
The goal is to go to high red shifts.
We have high red shifts, large distances here
We are somewhere in the Milky Way.
Then we can measure parallaxes in the Milky
Way.
We will be able to go to distances of around
40-50 megaparsec.
We will be able to use Cepheids.
and then further, we will use supernovae
We have a certain number of inter calibration
zones, let's say :
for example here a zone where we have measured
parallaxes
for Cepheid stars.
So we will be able to establish a period liuminosity
relation
for Cepheids by measuring their distances
with parallaxes.
Then we have a zone here where we have galaxies
in which we have Cepheids.
From time to time these galaxies will have
a type 1a supernova
These are very rare, each galaxy has around
one type 1a supernova per century.
So these objects are extremely rare,
we know of approximately 10 at the present
time.
It's thanks to this that will be able to correctly
calibrate the relation
between the supernova luminosity at their
peak
and the distance.
Further away we use only supernovae
as distance indicators.
We have three essential indicators :
parallaxes, Cepheids, supernovae
which will be calibrated between each other
in some zones where we have two different
indicators available at the same time
and then at a larger red shift,
we only have access to extremely bright supernovae
allowing us to go very far in our distance
measurements.
We have seen how crucial,
it is important to measure distances in the
universe.
it's one of the rare methods in fact the only
one
we have at our disposition
to test the cosmological parameters,
the parameters of the models
which describe the relation between red shift
on the one hand,
measured by the Doppler effect,
and the distance on the other hand,
so what we predict through cosmological models.
there are a given number of obstacles to this
but fortunately they are not insurmountable.
What we need in practice
are bigger and bigger telescopes
to capture as much light as possible
and so see further and further standard candles,
standard candles which will send us less and
less photons
due to their distance.
That is not all, we also need ultra fine images,
at very high resolution,
as shown here, a galaxy taken with the Hubble
space telescope.
In these images, we will be able
by zooming, to isolate interesting objects
from the surrounding objects.
For example we will be able to see
the image of standard Cepheid candles
a crowded stellar neighbourhood.
In this sense, the Hubble space telescope
is
absolutely crucial for cosmology.