In this very last video, we will see a natural
phenomenon
which is extremely useful to astrophysicist
and cosmologist,
the gravitational lensing phenomenon.
It's a phenomenon also known as gravitational
"mirage"
by analogy with the optical mirages observed
in the desert.
As the name suggests, it is about the deviation
of light
not due to a changing refraction index
in the propagation medium, but due to a strong
gravitational field,
as the one created by a galaxy, a star, a
cluster of galaxies.
As it passes near a massive object in the
foreground,
the light coming from a distant body will
be deviated so that
the background object will be distorted by
the foreground object,
and by studying the manner in which the object
is distorted,
we can deduce the matter, visible or not,
in the foreground object
which is then called a gravitational lens.
We have already seen gravitational lenses
during this class.
For example in the galaxy cluster here with
a Redshift of 0,397
with a mass of 10^15 solar mass,
this is an excellent gravitational lens.
By zooming on the external parts of the cluster,
we can see that there is a whole series of
blue arcs which are
the distorted image of distant galaxies by
gravitational lens effect
in the background of the galaxy cluster, which
you see here and
which is shown in greenish colours
So we will see in this class how the gravitational
lens
effect works and why it's such a precious
tool
for an astrophysicist.
We have seen that the gravitational lens effect
is essentially
a light deflection effect.
We will see how to draw this.
So a light ray arrives in the proximity of
a mass,
here the Sun, which I represent arbitrarily
The ray will be deviated, we have for example
here a velocity vector
which will be the light velocity.
The ray will be deviated.
and to get that deviation we will have an
acceleration.
So acceleration does not mean we will have
velocities
faster then light,
but we will have a deviation of the light
ray,
we will have a changing velocity.
We will have a photon that arrives with the
velocity of light.
We will have a photon leaving, after deflection,
with the velocity of light
and then we will have a velocity difference
vector.
So the photon will be accelerated for a while.
We will get back later on this "for a while"
the photon arrives with a certain impact parameter
that we will call B, relative to the Sun
or any mass that deviates light.
What we intend to compute is the deflection
angle
we call alpha^ here.
So this deflection angle, if we do some trigonometry
we see that alpha ^ = the norm of Delta V
over the norm of our velocity vector, c.
Keeping in mind that alpha ^ is always very
small,
of the order of a few tenths of an arcsecond,
or of one arcsecond
in the strongest cases.
Now delta V, what is it?
It's the acceleration of the photon due to
the Sun in this case here.
So GM/ b² during some time delta t.
So this, is the acceleration during some time,
it is indeed a velocity.
Now the "some time" is just an order of magnitude
here.
We can say that the photon feels the acceleration,
will be under the influence of the gravity
field of the Sun
during "some time" which will be of the order
of magnitude b/c.
Beware, this is simply an order of magnitude.
Now if we take all these equations together,
we will find that a is proportionnal to GM/c²b.
But what we especially see is that the deflection
angle depends only
on the lens mass, the impact parameter and
physical constants
and in particular, á does not depend on wavelength.
rather á ^, sorry.
So, counterintuitively, the deviation
of a light ray does not depend upon energy
or wavelength.
In this case here, the result is that, if
we put an observer
here, instead of seeing the source where it
was without the Sun,
namely in this direction, we will see the
light source
so if we had a light source here, one would
see it in the direction
of this ray here, hence in this direction
here.
Here we also have á ^.
The deflection angle of light by a massive
object was measured
for the first time in 1919 during a Solar
eclipse.
Note that these ideas are not new.
Actually, Newton had already raised the possibility
of light deviation by mass.
But it is in fact Einstein who predicted the
phenomenon
for the first time in unpublished notes in
1912.
However, the observation only came later on.
The observation, which actually provided evidence
for Einstein's general relativity theory,
was made in 1919 by Arthur Eddington,
an English astrophysicist, during a solar
eclipse.
Note that the measurement principle is simple:
we choose a stellar field.
So, if we observe it during the night, we
will of course see stars
at certain positions relative to the Sun.
So this is a moment when the Sun is not in
the field of view.
The white points are the positions where the
stars would be
if we observed them during the night.
Now we put before the stars a certain mass,
but since the Sun is bright, we will only
see the stars during a solar eclipse.
So here, during the eclipse, light rays coming
from the stars
will be deflected by the Sun and what we will
see are stars
fleeing the sun radially like this.
I'm drawing arrows of different lengths and
the length of each arrow is
inversely proportional to the impact parameter
B,
namely the projected distance on the sky between
star and sun.
So here is the deviation angle of light,
each time in the radial direction.
So the new star positions with the sun present
in the field of view,
will be the new positions indicated by red
dots.
Now, how far does this validate general relativity
?
If we measure, or rather predict, the á ^ angle
using Newton's theory,
namely the little demonstration we made earlier,
we would predict 2GM/c²b
but á^(Einstein), using the general relativity
theory
gives back twice that value,
that is 4GM/c²b,
where M is the Sun's mass and b the Sun's
radius
and if we took a star which would lie just
at the edge of the Sun,
assuming that we can perfectly measure a star
at the edge of the Sun.
Otherwise we would need to rescale by the
factor b that we have here.
So now the numerical values we have,
are that á^ is 1,75 arcseconds in solar mass
units.
Therefore, if we put solar masses here, b
/ (solar radius ^ - 1).
That, provided we express b in solar radius
units.
The measurement taken by Eddington gave 1.75
arcseconds, which is
actually the numerical value predicted by
general relativity .
So the fundamental difference between á(Newton)
and á(Einstein)
is that, using Newton's theory of gravity,
we have photons following curved trajectories
in an Euclidean space.
In the framework of the general relativity
theory
we find that photons travel along straight
trajectories
in a curved space, in other words trajectories
that minimise the travel time of photons,
so what we call geodetics; and these trajectories
are those
of shortest travel length in a curved space.
So we have two radically different interpretations
of gravitation,
and this is what is crucial, and has given
all the legitimacy
to the general relativity theory,
since we construe gravitationnal fields
as acceleeration fields and not anymore as
forces
that masses feel.
So here we have a beautiful confirmation of
the general relativity theory,
simply because the angle measured by Eddington
is exactly equal
to the angle predicted by the general relativity
theory.
So now let's see how all this works in more
details.
We have three important planes,
if we draw the situation simply.
We have a source represented in orange
which is affected by the lens effect, here
on the lens plane.
This lens can be anything:
a star, the sun or another star, a galaxy,
a cluster of galaxies,
or even, as we shall see, the great structures
of the universe.
So the source can be imaged.
So light will be deviated by an angle alpha
^ that we computed earlier
and the source will be displaced and distorted
by the gravitational lens effect.
Now the source is located on the sky by an
angle â
relative to an arbitrary position.
We will take here a reference point.
The position of the images on the sky, as
seen from Earth,
is located by an angle è
and then, we also have an angle á which of
course depends upon è.
We also have different distances here.
We have the distance from observer to source.
the distance from lens to source and the distance
of the lens.
And these distances are angular diameter distances.
Now we have a very simple relation between
those three angles.
That is the lens equation.
We have â = è - á(è).
That is what we call the reduced deflection
angle.
Beware, it's á, not á ^.
It is of course related to á ^, we will see
that later.
Now we can also express things as a function
of linear distances
in the different planes.
we will put ç here and æ there, which will
depend upon è,
because if è changes, æ changes accordingly.
We can even rewrite the lens equation.
So here we have angles, there linear distances,
and
playing a bit of trigonometry, we will find
this :
ç = Äl/Äl æ - Äls á ^, so there, the
á^ appears.
Thus, the relation between á(è) and á ^,
again by doing some trigonometry in the similar
triangles here,
we get á(è) = Äls /Ä s * á ^ (æ).
So there are some different forms of the very
simple equation
that is called the lens equation and which
relates the different angles,
or angular positions.
Let's consider the angular positions of the
various objects on the plane of the sky,
â for the source,
è for the images, and á, the reduced deviation
angle.
we can also relate the linear distances to
the different planes, but for
that we have to know the
angular diameter distances between the different
objects.
An extremely important, characteristic quantity
is
Einstein's radius.
If the source, lens and observer are aligned,
then we have â = 0, where the â angle represents
the position of the source on the sky.
So, if everything is aligned, we have â = 0,
which means that
the lens equation is greatly simplified.
So we have è = á(è).
It's a simplified version of the lens equation.
So now á(è), we have seen that it was Äls
/Ä s * á ^(æ).
with æ, if we look at the earlier figure
again,
and if we do some trigonometry, we have that
æ is linked to è through
the distance to the lens, from Earth to the
lens.
What does it mean exactly? It implies that
è = Äls /Ä s * GM/c²æ.
that is á(è), which we linked to á^
So all that will be equal to Äls /Ä s * GM/
(c² è Äl).
Here, we have a è here, a è there,
This è on the other side, i will have a èe
which will be Einstein's radius
equal to √(GM / c²) - M is the lens mass
-
and we will have a distance ratio Äs/Äl.
So èe is Einstein's radius.
that means that, if we have
a source aligned with the observer
and then we have a lens, a small spiral galaxy
for example,
then the light will be able to go through
the lens.
Since we have a totally symmetric situation,
we have a cylindrical symmetry
and this angle here, is the Einstein radius
èe.
That means that the image of the source,
seen from Earth, when we have a situation
where â = 0
so where all objects are aligned, the lens
equation has
an infinity of solutions which are distributed
over a circle
with a diameter 2èe
and so the source has an image taking the
shape of an annulus
around the lens galaxy.
As an example, here is a real object which
is precisely in that case.
The mass indicated here, M, is the Mass within
Einstein's radius.
So we see immediately that in this particular
configuration,
one can measure the mass of a lens galaxy
included in the Einstein radius
which is materialised by a circle; the latter
is the shape taken by an object
affected by the lens effect in case of perfect
alignment
between source, lens and observer.
It turns out that èe, is also a characteristic
quantity
that gives an idea of the separation between
the images of a source
in a gravitational mirage, even if â is not
exactly zero.
Now let's consider again the lens equation
and look at a simple case where we can solve
it.
So we have â = è - á(è).
We see that á(è), if we look at the previous
slide,
can also be expressed like this as a function
of èe.
I said that èe is a characteristic quantity
of lenses.
One can simply rewrite the lens equation in
a different way
so that here one will have : â = è - (èe)²/è.
Here, we are solving it in one dimension.
One could of course have 2-dimensional angles.
For example in x and y, if we want to thoroughly
represent everything.
Anyhow, for a point mass lens,
we have cylindrical symmetry even spherical.
So the choice of coordinates does not matter
much .
Now this is equivalent to a second degree
equation in è.
If we solve this equation here, we will get
a discriminant which reads
â² - 4 è² * (èe)².
So â² +4(èe)²
this is a positive quantity, so we have two
solutions and the solutions --
We will call them + and - and they will be
equal to 1/2 (β ± √(β²+4θe²))
So now, we can also divide everything by èe
to have everythin in èe units.
since we said that it was a characteristic
quantity of lenses,
so we have the angles as a function of the
Einstein radius.
There, one has 1/2 (β ± √(β²+4θe))
we are not forced to do that, but it is common
practice.
So now this, I can call it d. We will write
d± for the signs here.
That is a displacement vector which will be
slightly bigger than this one here.
What does that mean? It means that if I have
a lens somewhere in the sky,
and I have the Einstein radius which is like
that...
Here I show the Einstein radius, that does
not mean that the source
takes the shape of a circle, but it is the
characteristic quantity
associated with a lens of mass M.
If i place my source somewhere â/èe,
if we measure everything in arbitrary Einstein
units,
so if I take an arbitrary â, it will be â/èe,
which can be found again here.
If I add d+ to this quantity here.
I will have a mirror image that will form
here,
this is d+, that will be the è+ image,
è+/èe since we measure everything as a function
of the Einstein radius
and then, so my source is here, I will write
a quantity d-.
equal to the norm in the other direction,
so on the other side,
so I will get somewhere around here, I have
d-.
This will be the second mirage image of the
source, that I will call è-.
So we see here that in the case of lenses,
we have a point lens,
which means that the whole mass is concentrated
in one point.
M is constant as a function of the radius
è.
If the lens is a point-mass, we'll have two
mirage images
on either side of the source.
So, these are the two mirage images of the
source
which was here originally,
and this is where was the object that is the
lens.
As we have just seen, photons can be deflected
by gravitational fields.
So on this figure we see
a gravitational lens effect on a distant quasar,
the very bright bright nucleus of a distant
galaxy,
hosting a supermassive black hole.
When light rays from the quasar pass
near the lens galaxy, the foreground galaxy,
they are deflected, and the image of the background
object - the quasar - is modified.
We have seen in the previous slides that in
the simple case
of a point-mass lens, we predicted two mirage
images
of the background object, the quasar in this
instance.
But actually, when the models are a bit more
realistic, we predict
that we always get an odd number of images,
3 or 5
depending on the shape of the foreground lens.
In the animation shown here, one sees in fact
4 images of the quasar,
the fifth image lying between the 4 images
distributed around the lens galaxy;
and the lens galaxy, because of its brightness,
masks the fifth image.
So we talked earlier about Einstein's rings
we have just seen in the video, in the previous
animation,
4 mirage images of a quasar.
Now what happens if instead of a point like
source,
the latter is slightly extended
and if the source is perfectly aligned with
the lens?
We obtain in that case of a situation like
this, a perfect Einstein ring.
Here is a lens galaxy with a redshift zl of
0.45.
We have a source, the red shift of which,
zs, is equal to 2.38 in this case.
And we see at once, here, the Einstein ring
materialize.
I'm drawing it here in red but it is already
very well-defined
by the blue background galaxy at z=2.38 which
appears
as a very distinct Einstein ring.
What we see here is the Einstein ring.
Now, we have said that θe = √((GM / c²)(Dls/Ds*Dl))
and
we have a distance ratio here.
So we have distances, and we need to convert
the red shifts
into distances using a cosmological model.
So if we have that equation here then we inverse
the equation
and we deduce from it the mass inside the
Einstein ring.
Now it's the mass inside èe but the Virial
would also give us
the mass within a certain radius R that can
be chosen arbitrarily.
So, if we measure the velocity dispersion
of the stars
within a certain radius R, we have seen in
the chapter about dark matter
that mass is related to the dispersion of
the radial velocities in this way here.
This means that if we measure ór through
the Doppler effect,
in an aperture as shown here,
here we have a certain radius, a certain ór
measured by Doppler effect.
We'll have the mass within a certain radius
and the mass inside the Einstein ring which
is here.
So we'll get two mass estimates inside different
radii
meaning we'll have access to the mass gradient.
It's extremly important to constrain the models
of galaxy formation that are produced through
numerical simulation.
The mass gradient measurment is possible partly
through this gravitational lens effect combined
with the velocity dispersion in well chosen
apertures.
We already see that the strong gravitational
lens effect,
strong because it produces large mirage images
of background objects;
we see that the gravitational lens effect
is an extremely powerful tool to measure mass
as a function of radius
and we can measure the luminous mass and the
total mass thanks to this phenomenon
of gravitational lensing, since it only depends
on gravitation.
We do not need to see the mass to measure
the effect it has
on background objects.
Last example, there are in fact multiple applications
of the gravitational lens effect, we will
not describe them all here.
We have seen the strong gravitational lens
effect,
which produces multiple images of background
objects,
namely Einstein rings.
Now we'll see the weak gravitational lens
effect.
it's an effect which causes weak deformations
of background objects, but it is also present
everywhere in the Universe.
Here we see a slice of the Universe, it's
a numerical simulation.
We see different slices of the Universe at
different red shifts.
We see evolving structures.
We have a red shift of 0,
this is the present epoch.
Here we have a red shift, it's a numerical
simulation.
In the numerical simulation, the red shift
was of 1.4.
And here we have a red shift of 5.7.
Now if we take some light rays
coming from far away.
The light rays will intercept each plane.
We'll have a deviation of light
which arrives for example here in this plane
here.
It will be deflected again by a mass lying,
for example, here.
It will arrive at the plane, around the present
epoch.
If we have the image of a background object
here, for instance,
we'll see its distorted image by lens effect
and we'll see it
distorted at its arrival, hence at the present
time
where we observe the background source.
So this effect is very weak, we need to measure
it on a lot of galaxies
and take an average to see it, but it is something
detectable.
Of course the effect will change as a function
of what we put
in the different slices of the universe.
The deformations predicted by the cosmological
models
will change as a function of H0,
of the composition of the Universe, of the
composition
in terms of dark energy and dark matter.
We will not have the same predicted universe
and so will not predict the same deformation.
The point here, the goal will be to measure
the distortions of these
extremely distant galaxies, using this mirage
effect, which is weak.
We of course exaggerated the light deviations
to be able to constrain
the cosmological models.
In practice, how will we proceed?
We take a slice of the present universe.
This is a simulation, in practice we do not
see the simulated filaments.
Actually, the galaxy clusters, here we have
gigantic scales,
the galaxy clusters can be found at the connections
between the filaments.
But filaments are essentialy composed of weakly
luminous matter
and dark matter.
Now, assuming that the background galaxies
are round like this.
I'm placing them like this.
They are of course billions, I only have a
few.
Some of them are near each other,
others are far away from each other;
each time the rays are deflected, what will
happen is
that a circular galaxy will be distorted
into a small ellipse by the lens effect.
The distortion will be tangential with respect
to the direction of the mass.
A round galaxy,
and some mass here,
it will be distorted by lensing effect,
I'm exaggerating the deformation a lot but
in this manner
Here, if we have a massive filament going
through here,
the distortion will be like this.
Here the distortion will be like this.
We can draw a lot of others, I cannot show
them all.
But here for example, we have several galaxies
distorted
by approximately the same filaments.
Here, there is another like this.
We can see that the shapes of galaxies which
are affected by the same filament,
will obviously be more correlated than galaxies
distorted
by filaments lying very far away, angularly
on the sky.
So here, between two galaxies, we have an
angle è, there another angle è,
what we'll be able to measure in practice
is what we call
the 2-points correlation function of the shapes
of the galaxies.
This correlation function, we'll omit the
details here,
we'll call it æ(è).
We have here the è angle, the typical scales
are 10 arcminutes
to 100 arc minutes on the sky,
hence the importance of taking wide field
images.
We want to measure the correlation function
over very large scales;
so for small angles, we look at the correlation
of the shapes of galaxies which are separated
by a certain angle è.
Then, of course, the galaxies that lie close
to each other feel a lens effect
due to the same filaments, so the correlation
is very strong.
Galaxies lying far away from each other, hence
at high è, will be
much less correlated.
What we expect to see is a correlation function
that will decrease like this.
The goal is to measure the distortions of
all galaxies over the whole sky
and to measure the shapes of all galaxies
over the whole sky
and to measure the correlations at every scale.
The idea is to take the most precise measurement
points, here,
to discriminate between the different curves,
the different correlation functions
here, which are predicted by the cosmological
models.
The cosmological models will predict a correlation
function
or a power spectrum which will be a function
of è of course,
of H0, and then of cosmology.
Cosmology is, among other things, H0,
but also the densities of the different components
of the universe
namely dark matter, dark energy.
Thanks to these measurements of weak gravitational
lensing
and of the correlation function of galaxy
shapes
everywhere in the universe,
we can constrain cosmological models, provided
we have, as far
as possible, a map of the whole sky with a
very high spatial resolution.
The gravitational lens effect manifests itself
at all mass scales
and at all spatial scales :
from stellar scales or even planetary ones,
to galaxies or even galaxy clusters.
We have even seen that the largest structures
in the universe,
the cosmic filaments, produce a weak but measurable
lensing effect
and that these measurements allow us to determine
the cosmological parameters,
the parameters which describe how the universe
is evolving
and what its composition is.
The data, for this ambitious goal, will be
produced by the Euclid satellite of ESA
which, starting from 2020, will measure, with
exceptional quality,
the shapes of billions of galaxies to see
statistically
how the images are distorted by the whole
of the cosmic structures
over a field of view which corresponds to
a third of the whole sky.
So for now the future of cosmology depends
on our ability to map the whole universe and
not
just some well targeted areas as we were able
to make until now.
This concludes this week of lectures
and our MOOC of introduction to astrophysics.
We have introduced a large variety of topics
and described physical concepts
hiding behind astronomical observations and
their interpretations.
The goal has been to understand the principles,
rather than
the detailed mathematical developments.
I hope this goal has been achieved.
But I especially hope that you took as much
pleasure
in following this course as we had preparing
it.