Hello!
Welcome to this new lesson
of the course, Introduction
to programming in C++.
The objective of this new lesson
is to teach you
to organize your code
by modularizing it
using what we call functions.
Functions are a part
of C++ programs,
just like expressions and operators,
and control structures,
which we have studied previously.
Generally, functions operate on data,
and these data will
influence the functions.
Up until now, the programs
that you have written
were made up of a
linear sequence of instructions
with no global organization
and no sharing of repeated tasks.
For example, if the task consisting of
asking the user for a number,
as the following code does,
were to be executed several times
in our program.
For example to ask once
for a number of points,
for a time,
and for an age.
What would you do?
You might be tempted to copy the code
as many times as necessary
to the appropriate places,
but, of course,
this is a very bad solution.
One must never duplicate
code when programming.
Do not be tempted by the copy-paste.
What you would like to copy
should be put into a function.
Why must one never duplicate code?
It makes the program
unnecessarily long,
hard to understand,
and especially, hard to maintain.
One would have to apply every
modification to each of the copies.
This is why every
good programming language
provides means to allow
reusing parts of a program.
In C++, this is done
using functions.
Let's consider for example
the following program:
This program begins
by asking for a number of points
obtained by a player.
As you can see, it does this
by using a do / while loop
to force the user to input
a value between 0 and 100.
Next, the program continues by
asking the user
to enter the time spent by the player.
This time,
it is a value between 1 and 60.
Then, from the number of points
obtained by the player
and the time he took,
the program calculates
the score of the first player.
Then, the program repeats these
operations for a second player.
It asks for a number of points,
a time,
and calculates the score of the second player.
Finally, the program compares
the scores of the two players
to announce who, of
player 1 or player 2, has won.
You can thus see
that in this program,
the code which consists in asking
for a number of points, a time,
and calculating a score from
the number of points and the time
is repeated twice,
once for each of the two players.
In such a case,
one must use a function
to avoid code duplication.
For this, I will first put to the side
the code that I am interested in.
The code I am interested in is this,
the code which asks for a number of points,
a time and which calculates a score.
So I will put this code to the side.
For example here.
This code will constitute what we call
the body of my function-to-be.
We will have to name this body,
to be able to refer to it
in the rest of the program.
I will call it, here, saisie_et_calcul
(TN: saisie_et_calcul means input_and_calculation)
and this will become the name
of my function-to-be.
I now want my function
to be able to
pass on a result
to the rest of the program.
The result, in this example,
is the player's score,
which was calculated by the function.
I will start by removing the references
to player 1,
since my function is now
valid for any player.
I will use the return keyword
followed by the variable name score_joueur
(TN: score_joueur means score_player).
to say that my function must
return the value
contained in the variable score_joueur.
Dont worry, we will go over this
in detail in the rest of the course.
My function can thus return a value
to the rest of the program.
This value has a certain type.
I must tell the rest of the program
what this type is.
The value returned by my function
is the value contained
in the variable score_joueur.
score_joueur was defined
with a double type.
So I have to indicate
that my function will return
a value of type double.
And this is done by adding,
before the name of the function,
the type of the value returned,
which is, here, double.
Another aspect of functions
is that they can use
values given by the outside
to work.
Our function, saisie_et_calcul,
is relatively simple,
it doesn't need
any such values.
To indicate this, we add,
after the name of the function,
opening and closing parentheses.
Our function is complete.
I will now use
my saisie_et_calcul function
to ask the user
for a number of points, a time,
and to calculate the score of player 1.
For this, I will return to the place
where I had extracted the code
that I used
to create my function.
That is, here.
I will declare a variable
which will contain the score of player 1.
I will use the function which
I named saisie_et_calcul
and this will be written like so.
The instruction that I have just created, here,
is thus a declaration
of the variable score_joueur1
(score_player1)
and I initialize this variable
by using the function saisie_et_calcul.
This is known as
function call.
The call will return the result
of the execution of the function.
Which is, here, the player's score.
This value can then, for example,
be stored in a variable,
as is the case here.
I can do exactly the same thing
for the second player.
I can remove the code
that corresponds to my function
that is, this code, and replace it
by a call to my function saisie_et_calcul
to initialize the variable score_joueur2.
You can see that the code
is now much more concise.
For the moment, my function saisie_et_calcul
is defined at the beginning of the program.
That is, here.
But I could define it
elsewhere in the program,
for example at the end.
Like so.
But if I want to use my function
to initialize the variables
score_joueur1 and score_joueur2,
(TN: score_player1 and score_player2)
the compiler must know this function
at the moment of the function call.
To be able to declare this
function before its call,
I will simply repeat the first line
of the definition of my function.
I will put this first line before the
function call, somewhere here,
and end this line
with a semicolon.
This way, now, when I call
my function,
the compiler already knows
the name of the function
and the return type of the function,
i.e double, here.
This line that declares a function
is called a function prototype.
Creating the saisie_et_calcul function
allowed me to avoid duplicating code.
It is also interesting to use a function
to focus on a somewhat
difficult part of the program,
such as, here, the calculation
of a player's score.
So I will extract, as before, the code
which calculates a player's score.
And from there, I will create
a function in the same way
as in my saisie_et_calcul function.
This new function will
return the player's score,
so a value of type double.
I will call this new function,
simply, score,
and for now I will put
opening and closing parentheses
after the name of the function.
I will put the code that I have just
extracted between braces.
As before,
I will use the return keyword
to indicate that my function
must return the player's score.
It will be written like so.
The difference with the first
saisie_et_calcul function
is that this new score function needs
the variables nb_points
and temps (TN : temps means time)
to calculate the player's score.
For this I will add these two
variables between parentheses.
This is written like so.
What I have just added between
parentheses, here,
is called parameters.
These are the parameters
of my function.
Like before, I will go back
to where I extracted the code
to create my score function
to call this score function.
I can do it, for example,
just after the return keyword.
I will call my new score function.
This new function requires
the number of points,
which is this variable here,
and the game time, which I will
but between parentheses here.
To sum up, I first identified the code
that was to be put into a function.
I extracted this code to create
my new function which I named.
I identified what we needed
as inputs to the function
for the function to work.
I also identified what my function had
to return to the rest of the program.
Now I can replace the part
of code that I have extracted
by a call to my function.
A function is thus
a reusable fragment of a program,
such as the saisie_et_calcul function.
or important as-is,
like the score function.
It is characterized by a body,
which the program fragment
which is reused or emphasized.
It is characterized also by its name
which will allow one to refer
to that function.
It can have parameters,
which are the set of variables
external to the function
and which the body needs in order to work.
The function can also
return a value,
and this value must have a type.
And finally, the use of a function
in the rest of the program
is known as a function call.
A function thus has three aspects.
First, its prototype, which
we can see as a summary
of what the function does.
Since it contains the function's
name, its parameters,
corresponding to the values
needed by the function
to work;
As well as the type of value
that the function must return.
A second aspect is the effective
creation of the function, or its definition.
Which starts like a prototype but
which also contains
what we call the function body,
which is the code which will be executed
when we use the function.
The final aspect is thus the use of
the function, or its call.
We will use the function
by giving it actual values
for these parameters.
The function will return a value
that we can easily assign to a variable.
In practice, the developer,
that is, the person who will write
the definition of the function,
is not necessarily the same person as the
programmer,
who
will use the function.
The programmer using the function does not need to
know the body of the function.
All that he needs to know is the
prototype of the function
to be able to call it.
The prototype thus acts as a bridge
between the programmers using functionnalities
and the developers of these functionnalities.
The (user) programmer must respect
the function's prototype
when he calls the function.
The developer must
make sure that the prototype
corresponds to the problem
that other programmers want to solve
by calling the function.
Let's take a new example of a program,
which uses a function called moyenne (TN: mean )
to calculate the mean of two values.
I think that you are now able to
identify the three aspects of this
mean function
in this new program.
First, we have the
prototype of the function.
As you can see,
the function has two parameters
which correspond to the two values
that we want to average.
These two values are of type double.
So their mean will also
be of type double.
The value returned by the moyenne
(mean) function
will also be of type double.
We then have a call to our
moyenne function.
We can call this moyenne function
in this part of the program
because the prototype was
placed earlier in the program.
We give the values of two variables
to this function,
note1 and note2 (TN: grade1, grade2)
which were first given by the user.
This instruction displays the values
returned by the moyenne function.
Finally, we have the definition
of the function here,
with its body, that is,
the code which defines how the function
will calculate the mean of the two values.
We will now go over
the three aspects,
the three aspects of functions.