In a previous episode, we
introduced the concept of functions
and their usefulness in programming.
Today, we will look into what happens
when we call a function.
At this point, we know that the concept
of a "function" is associated
with 3 aspects: the prototype,
the definition and the call.
We now will detail what goes on
at the moment we call a function.
Let's go back to the
mean calculation example.
Here, we have a little program which
asks the user to input
two grades. It reads these two
grades from the standard input
and displays the mean of these
two grades.
The calculation of the mean is
done by calling a function,
as you can see here,
and it is the specific mechanisms
of this function call that
we will now study.
Let's take a concrete example where
we wish to calculate the mean
of two numbers, passed to the "moyenne" function
as C++ expressions. ["moyenne" means "mean"]
The arguments passed to the "moyenne"
function upon calling it correspond
to the parameters which the function
expects in order to run.
Note that we usually call the data
needed by the function to run
correctly as described in its
prototype as "parameters", whereas
"arguments" refer to the values
that we actually pass to the function
at the moment we invoke it, at
the moment we call it.
So we will now dissect the different
steps that follow
such a function call.
First step: we start by evaluating the
arguments passed to the "moyenne" function
at the moment of the call.
In C++, we cannot know in advance
in which order this evaluation
will take place. In this example, let's decide that
it is the second argument
which is evaluated first.
So we evaluate the second argument,
which works out to
give a value of 4.25.
Then, the first argument is evaluated,
which gives
a value of 2.3.
Second step: the arguments
supplied at the function call
are matched with the parameters
expected by the "moyenne" function.
This match is mediated by
an assignment -- we will assign
to x the result of the evaluation
of the first argument, that is, 2.3.
And we will affect to y the result
of the evaluation of the second argument,
that is, 4.25.
The "moyenne" function now has actual
values in x and y,
with which it will be able to
work, to run.
Third step: we start the execution
of the "moyenne" function.
Here, all the instructions preceding
this final statement,
this return statement,
will be executed/run.
In this case, there is no instruction
preceding the return statement,
so the third step doesn't
do anything in particular.
Finally, the return statement
is executed.
We start by evaluating the expression
following the return keyword,
so here, this expression is
evaluated with
actual values for x and y,
which produces
a value of 3.275.
Last step: we make this value, produced
by the expression, available
to the one who invoked the
"moyenne" function by means of
the return statement, which means
that the function call can now
be replaced by the
value produced by the function call,
that is, 3.275.
So, after this last step, the variable
z now has a value of 3.275.
Here is a small summary of the various
steps we have just examined.
When a function call happens in a program,
five steps follow in the most general case:
first step: the expressions which
are passed as arguments to
the function are evaluated.
Second step: the results of these
evaluations of expressions
are affected to the parameters of
the function.
Third step: the parameters of the function
now have actual values
which which the function can work --
the body of the function is executed.
Fourth step: the expression which follows
the first return statement encountered
during execution is evaluated and the result
of this evaluation is returned
as result of the function call, which basically
means that this value replaces
the function call.
This is what happens in the
most general case.
The case where a function needs,
to work, data as inputs in the form
of arguments, of incoming parameters,
and returns an actual value.
That is the most general case.
There are situations where this five-step
scheme is somewhat simplified.
First situation: there exist cases
where a function can, for example,
return a result, but
does not need any input
to work.
So, in this case, since there is no
use for input arguments,
steps 1 and 2 do not happen.
Second situation: there are cases
where a function
can do work, but without returning
any actual value.
For example: a function can display
a certain number of outputs
on the terminal, but without
returning any values [to the core program].
In this case, steps 4 and 5 do not happen.
There is a specific argument-passing scheme,
called "passing by reference",
which we will examine later on,
where step 2 does not happen.
We will go over this in detail
a little farther in this lesson.
Here is another example which illustrates
that a function can
call another function when running:
we have a function "affiche score"
[means "display score"] the job of which
is to display the score of a player.
It needs 3 inputs,
it works with 3 parameters:
the player, represented here by an integer;
the number of points that he
won during the game;
and the time he spent to
gain these points.
And the "affiche score" function
will simply display the score of the player,
which is calculated by using a call
to the "score" function.
The "score" function's job is to
calculate the score and return it as an
integer, calculated from the number
of points and the game time.
So, this shows that
a function can absolutely
call another function.
The only thing to respect,
the golden rule, is to
prototype the function before
calling it. Here, before calling the
"score" function, we must have
prototyped it.
Finally, here is a small summary
of function calling.
So, a function that was prototyped
beforehand can be called
in a program.
Here, it happens to
be called in the body of another function.
At the moment of the function
call, there is a match being made
between the actual arguments
and the parameters of the function.
Here, what happens is that the argument
y is copied into the parameter x.
The parameter x now has an actual value
with which the body of the function
can be executed.
The expression following the return
keyword is evaluated and made available
to the program which called the function,
by means of the return statement.
So here, the function call is
replaced by the result of the evaluation
of the return statement an can
be assigned to variable of the program
which called it.
You will have no doubt noticed,
during this episode, that there
exists a jargon, a terminology
associated to function calls.
I spoke of "calling" a function,
of "passing" arguments
to a function.
Let's summarize this jargon
now.
You surely understood that when I speak
of calling a function, I refer to
the actual fact of using it.
Here, I am using the function f to
calculate a value which I then store
in a variable x.
When I say that a value is passed as
argument to a function,
I mean that this value is copied
into a parameter of the function.
And finally, when I say that a function
returns a value y, I mean that
the expression of the function call is
effectively replaced by the returned value.
Let's take a concrete example here:
let's imagine that, if we are dealing
with a small function f which returns
a result y, let's imagine that,
at the moment we call this function,
the value of y is 5.
Saying that the function returns 5 here
simply means that I can replace this
call by the return value,
that is, 5.
So I can just as well say that
cosine of 0 returns the cosine of 0, or
cosine of 0 returns 1.