In a previous video,
we went over the
three aspects of functions.
We also detailed function calls.
In this episode,
we will focus on the prototype aspect.
In the course example,
the example with the computation of the mean,
the prototype the moyenne function
is this line here ("moyenne" means "mean").
We will now examine
prototypes in detail.
In C++, just like variables,
functions must be declared
before they can be used.
In the case of functions, this
is known as a prototype.
The prototype's purpose is to declare
three things to the rest of the program:
the name of the function, how it will be called;
the parameters we must pass it,
for the function to work;
and finally, the return type,
that is, the type of value that the
function will return to the rest of the program.
The general syntax of declaration of a
prototype is as follows:
first, we declare the return type,
that the function will send to
the rest of the program.
Then, we provide the name
of the function.
And finally, between parentheses,
is the list of all parameters
that the function must receive
in order to work.
This list can be empty
if the function does not
need any parameters.
As an example of a prototype,
we can reuse the code example
given in the previous slide,
which is the mean calculation.
Here, we will calculate
the mean of two numbers.
For that, let's say the function returns,
to the rest of the program,
a value of type "double",
that it will be called "moyenne" ("mean")
and that it will take two parameters:
a parameter x of type double,
and a parameter y of type double.
We end the prototype declaration
with a semicolon, ";".
The part preceding the semicolon
in a prototype,
is what we call the "function header".
And when the header is followed by a
semicolon, then it is called a "prototype".
The list of parameters
can be empty.
If, for example, we have a function
which must ask the user for an integer,
we could say that it must
return an integer,
that it must ask for a number.
And to ask for a number,
it doesn't need to receive any parameter.
Now, the prototype will be as follows,
with two empty parentheses
and no list of parameters; simply
two parentheses stuck together.
The purpose of the prototype is
to announce to the rest of the program
what the function will do.
For this purpose, the function
must do only what it was designed to do.
It must not have any hidden effects,
what is known as "side effects".
For example, if you imagine
the square root function,
which calculates the square root of a number,
its prototype, as we can find it in the
standard library,
says that it expects an argument
of type "double";
that it is called "sqrt",
and that it returns a "double".
You expect this function
only to compute a square root value,
and not to pollute the prompt
with messages.
These are known as "side effects".
These are unexpected effects.
Once we have clearly specified
what the function must do,
then we must choose a suitable name
which illustrates exactly what
the function does.
Finally, a last piece of advice:
always start by writing the
prototype of a function.
Writing the prototype of your function
will allow you to clarify
what parameters it must receive,
as we have seen earlier,
and also what it must provide,
the type of what it must return.
This way, you will already have
specified two things
before you even have to think about
how you will implement
what the function must do.
Now, let's sum up the different aspects
of the syntax
that we have seen up til now in this lecture.
If you write an expression
which starts with a type,
followed here by a name and a semicolon,
then it is the declaration of
a variable.
However, if you add, between the name
and the semicolon,
some parentheses without arguments,
then it will be the prototype of a
function, and not a variable.
This might seem a little more natural to you
if I write it in this fashion here,
int f();
Here, we can see more clearly, maybe because
of its name, that it is a function.
Or better yet, if I write, like
in the previous example,
the function "demande nb" ("ask number"),
which doesn't take any arguments.
Be very careful,
this is indeed a function prototype.
And it has nothing to do with a variable.
This is a common mistake.
If, however, between the parentheses,
you enter a value which
is compatible with the type
which is at the beginning of the line,
then you have a variable declaration again,
and this time, with a value
is also an initialization.
So this line is actually very
close to the first line.
Here, we are simply adding a value
for an initialization.
And it has absolutely nothing
to do with the second line.
So be very careful with
this sort of form.
Finally, for a function call,
if we put a name with no type in front,
-- there is absolutely no type in front --
or we can have an "=" expression in front,
for example z = a(5),
but there is no type here,
then it is of course a function call.
It might have seemed more natural to you if
I had written z = f(5).
There, you naturally recognize a
call to a function f.
Or if I had written z = sqrt(2.0).
There, you recognize a function call.