In the previous episodes,
we went over the three aspects
of functions.
We've seen what a function call is,
and we have also seen,
in another episode,
what a function prototype is.
In this episode,
we will focus on the definition.
If I come back to the example
of the mean calculation,
the definition of the "moyenne" function are these lines here,
at the bottom of the program. ["moyenne" means "mean"]
We will now focus specifically on this.
The definition of a function,
as its name implies,
serves to define a function technically,
that is, to specify the body
of the function,
the set of instructions
that make up this function.
Specifically, the definition of
a function will start with
the header of the function,
that is, the beginning of the prototype,
without the semicolon
where, as you already know,
we first define the type,
then the name of the function and
finally, between parentheses,
the set of parameters that
we wish to pass to the function.
This header is followed,
for the definition, by the block
which is the body of the function.
This body is a set of
usual C++ instructions
which we put into a block here
and which contains
one or more return statements
which will end the execution
of the function body.
If I take, as an example,
the "moyenne" ("mean") function,
we can see here the function header
with the double return type, meaning
the function will return a double;
its name and a list of two parameters.
Here, we will calculate
the mean of two numbers x and y.
In the definition, we have the body
of the function which is this block,
which is, here, simply one single
return instruction and nothing else.
The body of the function is simply
a block in the C++ sense,
that is, a set of C++ instructions
contained between an opening brace
and a closing brace.
The only difference is that in this
block, we have access to extra variables
which are the parameters of the function.
We can use these in this block
as if they were any normal variable.
The value returned by the function
is indicated by the return instruction.
This instruction is followed by
an expression in the C++ sense,
which will be evaluated and will
give the value which the function will return.
This expression must be of the same type
as the function's return type.
In the mean calculation example,
we have here the body of the function
which is this block here,
which is very simple in this case,
as it contains only one
return statement,
which will evaluate the expression here,
where you can see that we have
access to the two parameters x and y.
The expression will be evaluated,
we will calculate x + y,
then we will divide by two,
and the result will be of type double
and will be returned by the function
to the rest of the program.
The return statement does two things:
it allows us to specify the type
of the return value
which will be given by the function
to the rest of the program
and it ends the execution
of the function body.
As soon as the first return is
encountered, the function halts
and returns the value corresponding
to the expression.
Very often, you will find relatively simple
return statement
which are just variable names,
such as return x where x
is a variable name.
Or even values, such as return 3
to return a value of 3.
But this is a specific case,
and we can perfectly,
as we have seen earlier,
use a complete C++ expression.
And this is the general case: the
evaluation of a complete expression.
x and 3, here, are simply
particular expressions.
A few remarks about the
return statement
on which it is important to insist.
First, we can place several return
statements
in one function.
Let's look at a simple example of
a function which will return
the biggest of two values, let's say,
a and b.
I call my function max2 simply because
there already exists a function
named max in the C++
standard library.
Let's look at the body of this function.
We start by declaring a variable m
and then, if a is bigger than b,
then we copy a into m
and if b is smaller than, or equal
to a,
then the value of m
will be the value of b.
Then, we return the value of m.
However, we could have written this
code with two return statements,
in a somewhat more compact way.
The prototype remains the same,
but here, if a is bigger than b,
we return a, which means
that if a is bigger than b,
we will evaluate this expression
and return it, and we will stop here.
The return ensures that we stop here.
If, however, b is smaller than
or equal to a,
then what will happen is that
this if instruction will directly
jump here,
and now, it is this return
which will be executed.
Please note that there is only one single return
executed for a given function call.
Second remark, the expression which follows
a return instruction in a function
must of course be of the same type
as the return type indicated
in the function header.
For example, here, if I have a function f
which does not take any arguments
but which returns a double, then
all the return statements in this
function must be of type double.
Here, I have an expression which returns b,
of type bool. This is incorrect,
and it will generate an error.
Third remark concerning
the return statement:
it must of course be the last
instruction executed
since the return statement
ends the execution of the function.
It makes no sense to put
instructions after the return statement.
Let's take, for example, this lire function
["lire" means "read"], which must return
a double after reading it
from the standard input.
It begins by displaying a message
on the standard output
and then. it declares a variable of type
double called n and initializes it
with a value of 0. It reads the value
of the double on the standard input
and finally, it returns to the rest
of the program the value of n.
After this, the lire function ends.
So there is absolutely no reason to
put an instruction after this,
it would be completely wrong.
Fourth and last remark concerning the
return statement.
The compiler must always be able
to execute a return statement.
Here is the example of the lire
function again, written
slightly differently.
We see, again, the request for the
user to input a number,
the declaration and initialization
of the variable n,
the reading, from the keyboard,
of the value of n;
but here, we have a simple test to
check if n is strictly positive.
If so, the function will execute the return
statement and will thus end
and return the value of n.
But what happens if n is negative?
It is quite possible for n
to be negative,
we can absolutely assume that
at this point,
the user might have entered a
negative value.
In such a case, this test here will be false
and so the function will jump to the line after
the if statement and will end
up here. And you can see that from
here, there is nothing left to execute.
The function will thus end without a return
value. This is impossible,
so the compiler will throw
you an error.
The compiler verifies that
the function will always end
with a return statement,
which returns a double, here, since
it is the function's return type.
In this particular case, what
we could have done
would have been to correct the function
by adding, for example, a loop here
that would go back to the top
of this block as long as, e.g.,
the value of n is negative or zero.
Then we would repeat the block
that asks the user for number and
assigns it,
which would allow the function to end
with a legal value every time.
More specifically,
since we first want to ask the user
for a value before testing whether
it is positive or negative,
we obviously need a
do while loop.
So, let's write the  do while loop here,
with, as condition,
that we ask the question again as
long as we get a bad answer.
Originally, we wanted n
to be positive
to have a good answer.
So we will repeat the loop while,
as long as, n is negative. While it is
negative, we must repeat
this loop and as soon as n
will have a positive value ,
we will be able to return the value.
So we can already write the return statement.
Then, in the loop, we will
get the user's input --
first we ask them the question,
and then we save their input.
This is what the loop will do.
We write the message here,
and we read the value into the variable n.
Now, we still need to declare this
variable n
since we use it here as
a condition for the while statement
which is outside of the do while
loop and since we also use it here for
the return statement; we will declare this variable
outside of the block to be able to use it
outside of the block. So we will declare
it here, and initialize it with a value
that makes sense, for example, 0.
So, here is the precise form, which
corrects the previous mistake.
Now, let's go over a few special
cases of functions.
Let's start, for example, with
a function
which has no return type.
I must remind you that a function in
programming has nothing to do with
a mathematical function.
In programming, a function is simply
a set of instructions
that we have put to the side,
and named.
This set of instructions
can certainly have
no return value.
It will return nothing to
the rest of the program.
Such a function is sometimes called
a "void function". [In French, there is a special word
for it: "procedure", not used in English]
Such a function will need a specific
kind of declaration.
The declaration of its type,
since it returns nothing,
will be done with the reserved word
void to indicate
that it has no return value.
If I take the example here,
at the bottom of the slide,
the function "affiche racine"
[means "display square root"] will simply
print something to the terminal
and has no need for a return type,
since it does not need to return anything
to the rest of the program.
We will, if you will, "define its return type",
indicate the fact that
it does not return anything,
by using the reserved word void.
Since such a function does not return
anything to the rest of the program,
it needs no return instruction,
and the return statement is
optional in these functions.
However, it could be useful to halt
the execution of the function
prematurely, for example, depending
on the result of an if statement.
Here, we can certainly put a return
statement in the function body --
and this return will
be followed by a semicolon.
If I go back to the "affiche racine" function
here at the bottom of the slide,
which returns nothing at all,
since it simply displays on the screen
the square root of the argument
received.
If "a" is negative here,
then we should simply display nothing,
since the square root of a negative
number is not defined.
So here, we will
halt the execution of the
function body
with a return statement
which returns no expression,
which is followed by nothing.
If "a", for example, is positive,
then the if will not be executed
and the function body will continue
normally by displaying its square root.
Another special case of functions:
functions with no parameters.
We can of course define functions
which need no external parameter
to work,
to do their job.
We have already seen this during
the lecture on prototypes:
all we have to do is give an empty
list of parameters,
which is simply a pair of empty
parentheses, like this: ().
For example, if I want a "saisie" function
["saisie" means "input"]
whose job is to ask the user
for a double
in the terminal.
This function must return a double
but needs no parameter.
So we will declare a variable here,
for example, a number of points,
that the user will input, which
we will define with type double.
Here, the type we will use is
the same as the type of the return value
since it is this variable
that we will use
to return the value to the rest
of the program.
We declare this variable here, "nb_points"
["number of points"] and initialize it to zero.
Then, we ask the user
to input a number of points.
We will read the number of points
as supplied by the user.
And as long as the number of points
is negative or larger than a certain
threshold,
we will loop and ask the user
for input again.
When we finally have a correct value,
we return the number of points
supplied by the user
to the rest of the program.
As you can see, the program which
will use, which will call "saisie" [means "input"]
does not need to pass any arguments to
that function.
The "saisie" function works
completely autonomously.
Last special case of functions:
the main function.
"Main" is a function like
almost any other.
It is simply the function which is
called right at the beginning of the program.
This function has a special prototype.
Actually, it has two,
but the prototype that we will use
in this course is this one:
it must return an integer, int,
and receive no argument.
The standard way of defining main
is like this:
This integer, int, here,
which we return to the rest of the program,
is what we return to the program which
called our program, that is,
the environment
in which you will execute
your program.
And this return value will typically be an error code.
By convention, the value 0
indicates that the program was
executed correctly.
It means that there was no error.
It might be a little surprising,
but it is a common convention. Zero
means that there is no error.
Generally, we use error codes
bigger than zero, one, two etc.
to indicate that there is an error.
But that is outside the scope of this lecture.
I will just mention the other prototype,
the only other prototype accepted
for "main",
which we sometimes encounter.
In some development environments.
it is the one you will get
by default.
It is a prototype which takes
two arguments.
But it would take us a bit too far
to explain what these two arguments
are now.
In short, they are parameters that we
could receive
from the environment in which
we execute our program.