In this episode, I would like to sum up
the general methodology
that I advise you to follow to
design and write a function.
First of all,
I ask you to clearly identify
what the function must do.
It is a very important point.
You must start by identifying what
the function must do.
It is useless to try
to write a function
if you don't know clearly
what it is you want to do.
So this is a very
conceptual point.
There is no line of C++ to write here.
But the point is to design,
with the help perhaps of a piece of
paper and pencil to draw diagrams,
to design what the function will do.
Here, we are really interested
in what the function does.
We are interested in the "what" and
for the moment, we do not concern
ourselves with the "how", that is,
how the function will be implemented.
And this is the stage where it
is important to watch out for what
we have seen in a previous episode
on prototypes, the so-called
"side effects".
In other words, the function
must do exactly what it was
designed to do, no more, no less.
If, for example, you have designed
a sqrt function whose
goal is to calculate the square
root of a double,
for example x here,
and whose call would correspond
to something like z=sqrt(x),
then the sqrt function here must
only calculate the square root of x
and return it to z.
It must not pollute the output
in the terminal
with displayed messages.
It must only calculate, without displaying anything at all,
the value of the square root of x.
Then, once you have done this,
you should ask yourselves:
what should the function receive as inputs?
What are the arguments
that the function needs?
Say, for example, I go back to our example
moyenne function ("moyenne" means "mean").
In the beginning, I clearly decided
that this function's job
was to calculate the mean of two
real numbers.
It would take two real numbers as inputs
and it would calculate the mean
value of these two real numbers.
So at this stage, I'm thinking that
it will take two arguments of type double.
For example, I can call them x and y.
Then, you will ask yourselves whether
you should pass your arguments
by value or by reference.
Let me remind you briefly that there
exist two ways of passing arguments:
passing by value, which creates a copy
and thus does not allow the function
the modify the arguments received;
and passing by reference,
which is used when one wishes to be
able to modify the arguments in the function.
So here, if I take the example of
a call to the "moyenne" function,
where we would pass two arguments
a and b,
the question is: will "moyenne"
modify a or b?
The answer is clearly no.
So here, we will pass them
by value.
If, however, you think
that your function
has to modify the arguments that
it received,
then you should use passing
by reference,
as we have seen in the video
about function calls.
Then, optionally,  you can wonder
if it makes sense to give
a default value to each parameter.
This will be treated in
a subsequent video,
but it is at this point that you
should ask yourselves this question.
Fourth step:
ask yourselves which type
of value
the function must return to the
rest of the program.
For this, you can write the code
in your head like this:
z = "function call",
with the various arguments.
Does it make sense to write
z = "function call"?
So, for, example,
does it make sense to write,
z = "the mean of a and b" ?
In our case of course, it makes sense,
and the sense is that z, at that moment,
will be the mean of a and b.
So if it makes sense, the return
value must be of the same type as z,
when this expression makes sense.
So here, it will be a double
and this means that the
moyenne function
must return a double.
Sometimes, such an expression
makes absolutely no sense;
it makes no sense to write
z = "function call".
For example, would it
make sense to write
z = "display" ? We had the example,
earlier, of "display square root".
Would it make sense to write
z = "display square root of 2" ?
Careful, I said "display",
and not "calculate square root of 2".
What would z be in this case?
Personally, I don't see what it could refer to.
"Display" displays something and that is all!
It has nothing to return here.
So this expression, in my opinion,
makes no sense
and in this case, the return type
-- we call this a procedure --
the return type would be void.
Fifth and final step, at last.
Now, and only now, you
can start to preoccupy
yourselves with the "how":
how to write the function body,
how the function will do what
it's got to do.
Until now, we only worried about
the "what"
and it is only now, right at the end,
that we attack the "how".
Let's take the example of the moyenne
function, which I know
thanks to the previous steps,
must return a double.
It is called moyenne,
it takes an argument x by value,
since this argument must not
be modified,
it takes a second argument y.
We will know think about
how to write this function.
So here I suggest that you start,
for example,
by declaring a variable which
we will call resultat (means "result"),
which we will initialize with a value
that makes sense, let's say, 0,
and to immediately write a return
statement
which uses this variable.
I encourage you to proceed like this
every time you have such
a function which returns a certain
type, for example double.
You should define, right away,
a variable
that you will use as
return value.
This makes writing the function
body easier.
Then, that is now,
we will think about how to
calculate this result.
So here, we could write
result = (x + y) / 2.
Suppose that we wanted to
write a function
which asks the user for a number
between two bounds.
The first step is to specify clearly
what the function must do.
For this, we can start, for example,
by writing a comment
indicating what the function will do.
So here, we will indicate
that it is a function
which asks for a number
between two bounds,
for example an integer
between 1 and 10.
So we will name this function, for example,
demander nombre (ask number).
Suppose, now, that we have
understood well enough
what the function must do.
We can now go on to the second
step,
which is to specify
the parameters of the function.
Here, since we want to ask
for a number between two bounds,
the parameters that the function
needs to work are,
of course, the two bounds.
Suppose that we are working
on integers, here.
Then the two bounds will be an
integer "borne inférieure" (= "lower bound")
and an integer "borne supérieure"
(= "upper bound").
So we will receive two integers.
Then, we must ask ourselves whether
the two parameters passed
must be modified by
the function or not.
If they have to be passed by value
or by reference.
It seem clear, here,
that the lower and upper
bounds
will not be modified by the
action of asking for a number,
and so we will pass them by value,
as indicated here.
We can now proceed to step
number 4,
which is to know what the return
type of the function should be.
A good way to answer this question
is to ask ourselves: how will
the function be called?
And here, typically, it would be
called with an integer i
and we would make a call
like this:
i = ask_number(between, we said,
1 and 10).
When we have assignments such as
this one which can take the return value,
where it makes sense to retrieve
a return value from the function,
then, naturally, the return
type of the function
must be the type of the variable used
in such an assignment.
So here, it would make sense
to write what I wrote.
The type of i would be int,
which means that the return type
that we will specify for the function
will be an int type.
We can now return to
our program, here,
and specify the return type
as being an integer.
I can now go to the
last step.
Now and only now,
I will attack the function
body.
For this, I start by writing
the body and,
small piece of advice here,
when your function has a
return value,
I suggest you immediately
declare a variable
which will be used for the return.
Ideally, you should also
initialize it directly
and specify that you will
return this value.
And you can now concentrate
on how exactly the function
body will be written,
you can preoccupy yourselves
with the "how".
How should we ask for a number
between
the lower bound and
the upper bound?
I will leave you to do this
as an exercise.