Let's end with two fairly
easy-to-understand notions.
First, default arguments.
In function prototypes, we can
give default values
to some parameters of
the function.
And in that case,
it becomes unnecessary
to supply values, that is,
arguments, to these parameters
when we call the function.
To define such a parameter
with a default value,
all that is needed is to add, in the function's prototype,
an equals sign ('=')
after the parameter,
followed by the default value
that we wish to give
to this parameter.
Kind of like an assignment.
And be careful,
these parameters with default values
must absolutely appear last
in the list of parameters
of the function.
Let's take as an example a function
which will display a line
of several characters.
The prototype of this function
is here,
the name of the function is
affiche_ligne (TN: means "display_line").
This function takes two parameters:
the first parameter will define
the character
that we wish to repeat on the line.
The type, char, simply means that
the parameter elt will
contain a character.
The second parameter of the function is
the number of times that we
wish to repeat the character.
And you can see that
this parameter has a default value
of 5.
Which means that when I call
the affiche_ligne function
in this way,
that is, with a single argument,
where the first argument is the
'*' character (star),
The parameter elt
will contain the star character.
Since I don't have a second argument
in this call to my affiche_ligne
function,
the second parameter nb
will take
the default value of 5.
And so, this call to the
affiche_ligne function
will display a line with
5 stars.
Now,
the second call
to my affiche_ligne function
has two arguments,
where the first argument is
the '+' (plus) character
and the second argument
has a value of 8.
In this case,
the parameter elt will
contain the '+' character
and the second parameter nb
will not take the default value
of 5,
but the value which is passed
as an argument here,
which is 8.
And so this call to my
affiche_ligne function
will display the '+'
character eight times.
Two remarks on this concept
of default arguments:
arguments with default values
must be specified
in the function prototype
and not in the definition
of the function.
What's more, upon calling a
function with several parameters
with default values,
omitted arguments must be
the last ones
and omitted in the order
of the parameter list
For example, look
at this function
which has a first parameter
called "i"
which has no default value,
a second parameter "c" which
has the character "a"
as default value;
and a third parameter "x"
with a value of 0 by default.
If I now call my function "f"
in this way,
that is, with one single argument,
then the parameter "i" will
take on the value of 1,
the parameter "c" will take
the default character, "a",
and the parameter "x"
will take its default value
which is 0.
I can also call my function "f"
in this way, with
two arguments.
"i" will take
the value of the first argument,
that is, 1,
"c" will contain the second argument,
that is, the character "b",
and the third parameter "x"
will still take its
default value
of 0.
Now, if I try to call my
"f" function
in this way,
the compiler will refuse the call
because the second argument
here is of type double.
The compiler will try to assign this
double-type value
to the second parameter "c"
which is of type char,
so this call will be refused
by the compiler.
Now, we might be tempted
to call our "f" function
like this,
that is, by omitting
the second parameter.
Unfortunately, the compiler will
refuse such a call.
And finally,
if I try to call my "f" function
like this,
with these three arguments,
what will happen?
The parameter "i" will take
a value of 1,
the parameter "c" will contain
the character "b",
and the parameter "x" will take
the value of the third argument,
a value of 3.
We will finish by talking about
overloading of functions.
In C++, it is possible to define
several functions with the same name
if these functions have
different parameters.
That is, if the number or types of these
parameters are different.
This will allow the compiler to
distinguish between these functions.
This is called function
overloading
and it will come in very
handy when we use functions
which have similar tasks,
but operate on different kinds of data.
So, in C++, what determines the
difference between functions
is not only the names of
these functions,
but also the types of their parameters,
which is technically called the
"signature" of the function.
Note that the return type
is not part of these distinctions.
You cannot have two functions
with the same name and same
parameters
and simply with different
return types.
So I can have two functions "f",
where the first function has
a parameter of type int,
and where the second function
has a parameter of type double,
and where the return type
for these two functions
is the same, for example int.
However, I cannot have two
functions "f"
which both have a parameter of type
int for example,
and which vary only in
their return type.
For example int for the first
and double for the second.
To sum up, in C++, one can have
several functions with the same name,
as long as they have different types
of parameters.
For example, I can have three functions
which are all named affiche
(display).
The first function has a
parameter of type int,
the second, a parameter of type
double,
and the third, two parameters
of type int.
These are indeed 3
different functions.
Now, if I call affiche(1),
since the argument 1 is of type int,
it is the first function,
which has one parameter of type int,
that will be called.
And in this case, I will
get the message
"entier : 1".
(TN : means "integer: 1")
If I now call affiche(1.0),
since the argument (1.0) is of type double,
it is the second function,
which has one parameter of type double,
that will be called,
and it will display the message
"reel : 1" (TN : means "real : 1").
If I call d'affiche(1,1),
since both arguments have the same
int type,
it is the third function
that will be called
and I will get, on the display,
"couple : 11".
Careful: I cannot define these
2 functions
in the same program.
The first function has a parameter
of type  int;
the second has two parameters,
both of type  int,
but the second parameter has
a default value.
If I now call affiche(2),
it is impossible to know whether
I want to call
the first function "affiche"
by passing 2 as an argument
to the parameter "x",
or the second function,
by passing 2 to the parameter "x1"
and using the default value of 1
for parameter "x2".
There is an ambiguity
between these two functions
in this call.
This is why
defining these two functions together
in the same program
is forbidden.