The exception handling is an
important chapter for basic programming.
It renders our programs
sturdier and more resistant
towards abnormal or error
situations.
Exception handling is not per se a concept
of object-oriented programming. However,
its implementation resorts
to the use of these concepts.
The goal of this episode is to present
the fundamental aspects
of exception handling in Java.
In this chapter, we will discuss how
to handle errors
or abnormal situations in a program.
We will see that exception handling
let us anticipate
the errors and abnormal situations.
Thus, we will be able to react
appropriately.
Let us begin by illustrating the usefulness
of exception handling
through a simple example.
We wish to code a function "f" which
calculates the inverse of a given number.
We wish for this function to handle the case
where the entered value is 0
as an abnormal situation,
an error situation.
We also wonder how to handle
the error itself.
Here is our first attempt :
We can have it so that, in case the
entered value is 0,
we return a value chosen in advance.
To mimic the fact that this result would be
close to infinity, we could decide
-- in an arbitrary way -- to return
the biggest "double" possible.
In Java, there are other predefined values
to mimic the infinity (such as "infinity").
However, this is not our point here.
Unfortunately, this way to proceed is
not satisdactory at all.
Firstly, this does not let the user know
that his input has resulted in an
abnormal situation for the function "f"
since "x" is 0.
Here, the user is never warned of this fact.
Also, the returned result is
necessarily inexact.
The use of this "f" resorts to an
arbitrary convention
which is not necessarily known
by other programmers.
Here, the choice of the return value
is such a convention.
To overcome this lack of information
that the user of the function "f" is facing
when we are divide by 0,
we could imagine to have our function "f"
print an error message
whenever the entered value is 0.
We would have our function print
that there is an error situation :
a division by 0.
However, this does not solve all
the problems
of the previous version. Indeed, we
still have no idea
what we should return in an error situation.
This solution can also face criticism since
it triggers so-called
"edge effects".
This means that the function "f", which is
only supposed to return
the inverse of a number is now
generating printings
in the terminal; this is not its
usual task!
Indeed, let us imagine we are using
"f"  within a graphical program.
In this case, we do not want for an
abnormal situation
to be reported by a message on
the terminal
but rather by the opening of an
alert window, for example.
Finally, even though the function "f"
is the juncture of the program where
the error is detected,
it might not be the place to handle
this situation properly.
Indeed, a division by 0
could be harmful enough
to require the program to be stopped.
Also, it is possible for a division by 0
to be handled
according to the context of utilization.
This means that it is the juncture
of the program calling the function "f",
informed of the context, that could
give the appropriate measures
in case there is a division by 0.
A last option would be to rewrite
the function "f"
so that it rather returns an error code
indicating if the division has been
computed correctly.
Then, it will return the result of the
division only in a normal situation,
when there is no error with the parameter.
This way to proceed is better
than the previous ones.
Indeed, this way, the function calling "f"
is able to decide what to do
in case of error.
The function "f" itself should not be the one
taking this decision;
it should simply inform its caller
upon the execution.
Then, the caller will decide what to
do in case of error.
Unfortunately, this way to proceed
renders the use of the function
much less intuitive.
Instead of writing something simple
which would mean
let us store into "y" the result of
the inversion of "x"
computed by the method "f", we should
resort to
more complex instructions.
First, we should know that "f" returns
an error code
and that the normal utilization result
is stored in the second parameter.
This is clearly less intuitive
than this way of writing things.
Moreover, when a method calls another
which then calls another
and so on, each call could potentially
result in an error code.
In this case, we must then handle
the combinations
of all these error codes. Obviously, this
quickly becomes unpleasant.
Now, we wish to get our hands on
a mechanism
which would let us report an
error situation
without triggering any of these undesired
edge effects.
We also wish to possess a mechanism
letting us handle the error
at another place than the one
where it is detected.
This should all be done while keeping
utilization flexibility,
an intuitive intuition of the different
functionalities
we wish to have in our programs.
Execption handling meets all
our needs.
At the place where the error is detected, we
will be able to trigger an "exception".
This "exception" can then be handled at another
place in the program.
Also, we are not compelled to explicitly
integrate any error code
in the different functionalities we wish
to implement.
The mechanism of exception handling
works according
to the three points
developped here.
Whenever an error or abnormal
situation is detected
somewhere in the program,
we will warn the rest of the program
by "throwing an object"
containing all the useful informations
so that we can potentially handle
this error or abormal situation
elsewhere in the program.
"Throwing" or "triggering an exception" concretely
means creating an object
which becomes available for
the rest of the program.
This object can then be "caught",
which means "used",
elsewhere in program so that we can
handle this abnormal situation,
completely or partialy.
Finally, if the "thrown object"
is never "caught",
it will trigger the stop
of the program.
An unhandled thrown exception always
triggers the stopping of the program.
Let us illustrate this with a concrete example.
Let us imagine, for example, that
we have a main program
working with temperatures.
These temperatures are aquired
through, for example, a meter.
These temperatures are then stored
in an array. Our program's task
is to draw a graphic of the inverse
of all the aquired temperatures.
Let us imagine these temperatures
are aquired
through a not fully reliable meter.
Therefore, every once in a while, it
could fail to measure
the temperature correctly
and would, for instance, add null values
into our temperature array.
The main program realizes its processing
by calling
another function called "graphiqueInverse"
(TN: means "invertPlot").
This function will iterate on all the temperatures
of a provided array
and display the graph of their inverse.
This method thus resorts to another
method
which calculates the inverse
of a double.
The method "inverse" is absolutely not
aware of its utilization context.
It does know not what to do
if the provided value is zero.
It corresponds to this value
in the array.
However,
the main program knows in
what context this method is called
and is therefore able to
solve the problem.
For example, it could decide
that if the display of the temperatures
has failed,
which means that the aquired
temperatures were corrputed,
then we must recover them anew.
The idea motivating exception
handling is that the part of the program
detecting an abnormal situation,
while remaining unable to treat it locally,
will report it to
the rest of the program
by "throwing an exception".
The "exception" is a particular object
provided to the rest of the program.
If this thrown object is not caught
anywhere else in the program,
its execution will be canceled :
we could not handle the error.
Obviously we can also have another
part of the program,
aware of the error's context,
"catch" this object and
dealing with it appropriately.
The main program will have to show
that it is receptive
to the "thrown" objects, and that it can
receive with them.
In this case,
it will be able to "catch" the object
and deal with it
if, of course, the object has been thrown
during the execution of the receptive block.
In order to develop such a process,
we need to realize four
elementary tasks.
The first is the signalment of
an error.
This is what our "inverse" method was doing
when it was "throwing" an object to
warn the rest of the program of this abnormal situation.
The error signalement was thus what was
going on at this step of our example.
The second task is to mark the areas
receptive to the errors.
This is what our main program
was doing here
to indicate it is able to "catch"
and deal with such an object
corresponding to an abnormal sitatuion.
To each area receptive to errors,
abnormal situations,
we need to provide a tool to actually
deal with these errors.
This means "catching" the object
and dealing with it.
In our example,
each receptive block has
been provided
with a set of instructions able to
deal with the object, catching it.
Finally, in certain cases, it can
be necessary to do some cleaning
after a block receptive to errors.
For example,
we could need to liberate some resources
which have been used but not
properly liberated
due to an abnormal situation.
To each of these four tasks, there is
a coresponding Java keyword.
In order to to report the error,
we use the keyword "throw".
In order to make the areas receptive
to erros, we use "try".
In order to provide the block receptive
to errors
wich a handling bock, we
use the keyword "catch".
And finally,
in order to make some room,
we use the keyword "finally".
The detailed description on the
use of these keywords
will be presented in the next episode.
To make things clear,
the program area detecting the
error will "throw" the object
thanks to the reserved keyword "throw".
Later, we will see what is "thrown" exactly.
The area receptive to the throw objects
is delimited with the reserved
keyword "try".
This means each block receptive to errors
is indicated with this keyword.
Then, to each of these blocks,
we must associate a block able
to deal with the error.
The error will be caught with
the keyword "catch".
As said, we will see the precise
syntax
in the following episodes.
As you have probably noticed through
our little example,
the reporting of the errors thanks
to the keyword "throw"
and the solving of these mistakes through
the blocks "try" and "catch"
generally happen at distinct
areas in the code.
Actually, this is precisely the appeal
of exception handling.
In our example,
the "throw" is placed in the "inverse" method.
The blocks "try" and "catch" are
placed in the main program.
In the next episodes, we will see that
to each "try",
a "catch" must be associated or
possibly even
several "catch" blocks.
To sum up, an exception is thus a
way to report an event
requiring particular attention
in the program
This event can be a severe mistake
requiring for the whole program to be stopped
or simply an unusual situation which we
will solve appropriately.
This was the case in our previous example.
There, a division by zero
corresponded to an unusual situation.
Here, it does not correspond to
a dramatic situation
and can be solved, for example, by
retaking the measures
without having to shut down the program.
Exception handling will be a tool
letting us improve
the sturdiness of our programs and will
make it possible to separate the code
dedicated to error handling
from the code realizing the
other processing
happening in a normal situation.
Exception handling will also
let us
force an answer to particular errors.
For example, here,
with an unusual situation we need
to solve appropriately.
Unlike the solution presented at
the beginning of this sequence,
where we were dealing the abornoam situations
so that the methods of functions return
error codes,
exception handling provides quite
a few advantages.
Among the most important is that
the writing will be easier,
more intuitive, more readable.
For example, our method calculating
the inverse
can still be used in a very natural way.
Thus, it is not necessary
to pollute the code by
adding
other parameters solely
dedicated to error handling.
The propagation of the exception
to higher call levels
will be done automatically.
It is thus not necessary for every
intermediate call level
to deal with the error.
For example, if the exception thrown
by the "inverse" method
is not caught by the calling method,
named "graphiqueInverse",
the object will be automatically
thorwn to the upper call level
which will then be able to deal with
it like the main program.
An error can now occur at
any call level
while still being carried over to
the rest of the program.
As we have just seen,
exception handling presents
many an advantage
in order to solve error situations,
abnormal situations in our program.
However, the underlying mechanisms
do come with a certain cost.
Thus arises a methodological rule
which will be discussed in the
following episodes.
The rule is this the following:
If an error can be dealt with locally
(this means that, at a certain place,
we are fully informed
on how to solve the error),
then we should immediately
do it locally
without using the mechanism
of exceptions.