In the previous episode, you learned
that when we want to generate
exceptions in Java,
we basically seek to do
four things.
Signalling errors at the place
they occur.
Marking places that we want to
make receptive for errors,
and associating to each of these
places a way of handling these errors.
This is a big advantage of
exception handling
We separate error handling
from the place where they occur.
Finally, the fourth thing
we might want to do
is possibly to clean up after each
error-aware bloc.
We will thus have four words
in the language
that will be dedicated to each
of these elementary tasks
that we want to take care of.
In this episode, we will
present how to use
each of these four words one by one
starting of course with the throw keyword
which allows us to indicate an error.
We will say that throw  throws an exception
The syntax of throw to
throw an error,
to signal an error, is the following.
throw then an exception.
What is an exception?
It is an object of type Exception.
The Exception type is a type
which exists in the Java API
and which is provided by the
java.lang library
that contains many subclasses which we
will present in a moment.
So an exception is an object of
type Exception
which, when the throw
statement is executed,
is, so to speak, thrown.
This means that there is a mechanism
which will create such an object
that will be able to be handled
by the other keywords
in the exception handling mechanism.
This is what it means to
"throw an exception".
There is a fairly special treatment
of these peculiar objects,
these errors to be handled,
on the level of the program.
For example, we could have
a line such as this one:
throw new Exception,
so we create a new exception
Then for example, by calling
its constructor
taking as parameter a character
string
indicating an error message, "Quelle Erreur!".
(TN: means "What an error!").
This message is now associated to
this new instance
of the Exception class.
What does it really mean to
"throw an exception"?
It means that the throw statement
will skip the normal execution
sequence of the program
and will jump either to the next catch
bloc directly linked to a try bloc.
We will talk about catch and try in a moment.
For the moment, the important part to
remember is that it will jump
to another place in the program.
Or, if there is no such
try/catch bloc,
then the program will exit entirely
by ending with what we call
an exception.
So throw throws an instance
of the Exception class.
This Exception class is itself a subclass
of the Throwable class
that inherits from Object.
Exception is not the only
subclass of Throwable
that has multiple subclasses
whose goal is to indicate different types
of possible errors or exceptions.
For example, there is the Error
subclass
which has 12 direct subclasses
and which serves for example
to indicate memory errors.
The error class serves to indicate
fatal errors
which are not supposed to be used,
to be handled by the programmer
with a try/catch bloc.
On the other hand, we have Exceptions,
which must or can be
handled by the programmer.
The Exception class has
75 direct subclasses
among which there are
74 Checked Exceptions
which must be treated by the programmer.
They indicate exceptional circumstances,
often, but not always, errors
They must thus be handled at the level
of the program with a try/catch bloc.
There is also the RunTimeException
subclass,
whose treatment is not necessarily
handled by the programmer.
We call these Unchecked Exceptions,
and they have 49 direct subclasses
to treat different error cases that can
be avoided with good programming,
such as, for example, indices that
exceed an array's length,
or divisions by 0, etc.
This sort of error can be handled
by the programmer,
but it is not strictly necessary.
Actually, the next episode will go
over these Checked/Unchecked Exceptions
and how to handle them.
At the more general level,
right at the top of the hierarchy,
the Throwable class offers
two constructors,
one default constructor and one
constructor that allows to indicate
an error message in the form
of a string.
It offers, among others, two
interesting methods,
a getMessage method that allows
us to retrieve the error message
initialized using this constructor,
and a printStackTrace method
which allows us to display the stack
in the terminal, that is, the sequence of
events which led to the error.
That's it for the throw statement.
Now, let's move on to the try statement.
We have seen that if the throw
statement is not caught,
that is, not handled by a try/catch bloc,
the program is ended.
So in many cases, we will want
-- especially for Checked Exceptions --
we will want to handle them with
an exception-handling bloc.
This is exactly what try is used for.
try makes portions of code
compatible with exception handling.
Suppose that I call a method f
which can throw exceptions.
Either it can throw exceptions directly
or it can call methods that call methods
that call methods that throw exceptions.
No matter the depth of the call,
in this call to the method f,
we have a throw.
Somewhere below this call, we will
have a throw.
Then, if such an expression
if such a call to a method that
can throw exceptions
is in a bloc that is declared as
a try bloc,
then we will be able to setup
an exception-handling mechanism
and so the throw which exists
somewhere here, below,
will finally jump to the next catch
bloc associated to the try bloc
in which we are requesting
exception handling.
catch is thus simply the keyword
that is used to introduce
the set of instructions we wish to execute
in order to handle the exceptions.
Every try bloc must have at
least one catch bloc associated to it.
We will see in a moment that
it can have several.
These must handle the exceptions
thrown in the try bloc.
If an exception is thrown by
a throw statement,
but is not intercepted by a catch,
if there is no try and no catch
corresponding to the exception
that is thrown, then
the program will halt and indicate
that an exception
was thrown and it will display where
it was thrown,
indicating that this exception was
thrown but not caught.
The syntax of a catch bloc starts
with the word catch
followed, as with method headers,
the type and the equivalent of
a parameter, in parentheses.
We will only have one parameter
for this catch header.
Then, behind this, we have the bloc with
the instructions that we want to execute
for all exceptions of the type
we specify.
It is best to look at an example.
Here, we have a set of instructions
that we want to make aware
of exception handling with a try,
and right behind it, we will have a
catch statement to catch the exceptions
of type ArithmeticException
and another catch bloc that is also
associated to this try bloc
to catch very general exceptions
of type Exception.
So here, in this bloc, we could have
a variable age,
and if the age is too high, then we will
throw a very general exception.
And if the age is lower than 150,
we will continue execution.
We would have another variable, x.
If x equals 0, then we throw
an ArithmeticException
Otherwise, we continue.
This ArithmeticException will be
intercepted by this catch here.
We will execute the instructions that are
here and display
the error message that we had put
in the ArithmeticException,
then, for example, print the
call stack.
However, if it is this very general
exception that is thrown,
it is this catch which will be executed.
At that moment, we will display a message,
for example:
"Who can live to be that old?"
An important thing to note is that catch
blocs associated to a try bloc
will be sorted by level of exception, from
least to most general.
We will first have exceptions that
are very specific,
then the most general exceptions.
Remember that there is a hierarchy
in exceptions, like so.
The processing in the catch will
have to start
by the most specific exceptions,
then go to more and more
general ones.
If you place catch blocs with the most
general exceptions first,
you will get a compiler error.
Now, let's see in detail how all
of this is executed.
What is the flow of execution?
What do we do in the different
possible cases?
If the exception is thrown; if
it is not thrown.
First, the general principles are
as follows.
A catch bloc is executed only if
an exception corresponding
to the type specified in the catch
is thrown
from the corresponding try bloc.
Otherwise, the catch bloc
is simply ignored.
We will not execute what
is in this catch bloc.
In the absence of a finally,
of which we will speak in a moment.
If the catch bloc is executed, then
the execution of the program
continues after the catch bloc.
In no case do we come back to
the try.
We will continue after the catch bloc.
For example, if we have a try bloc
that is made aware
of exception handling,
in which is executed -- either
directly
or through a method call --
in which an exception is thrown.
If this exception is thrown,
if this line is actually executed,
then at the end of this line,
we will jump straight here
to the first line of the catch bloc
directly following the try bloc
and corresponding to the type of
the exception.
Here, where the type corresponds.
So the exception will be as follows:
We arrive here.
We execute this exception throwing
We jump to this place here
if an exception was thrown
If however no exception was thrown
that is, if this line here was
not executed,
for example, because it was
protected by an if
whose condition was not true
then, we execute the code
This line is not executed.
So we continue, of course,
by executing the whole bloc.
Let's suppose that there is
no throw farther on.
Once we arrive at the end of the
bloc, here, we will continue
with the normal execution
of the program.
We will simply ignore the
whole catch bloc
that is executed only if
an exception of the corresponding
type was thrown.
On the example we had earlier,
the flow of execution would be this:
Suppose that in the beginning,
we have an age variable,
and that the age, to start off with,
is not bigger than or equal to 150.
The age is lower than 150.
Thus, we continue.
We do not go into the if bloc,
we do not see the throw, we continue.
Suppose that we have a variable x here,
which is not equal to 0.
At this point, we continue normally.
We arrive here.
So if no exception was thrown,
"case n°1 : no exception thrown"
then we will continue the execution
down here.
This is what happens if the age
is under 150
and if x is not equal to 0.
Now, let's see what happens if, for
example, the age
is still below 150 but x is 0.
What will happen is that, since the
age is under 150,
we do not enter the if, we continue
Here, since x is worth 0, this
condition is verified.
We execute this throw, which
means that, from here,
we will plug into the exception
that was thrown
We threw an ArithmeticException,
so we will jump to the bloc that catches
ArithmeticException.
Here, we will continue the execution
by displaying the associated message
and by displaying the call trace
Once we have done all of this, then
we will continue with the normal execution
after all the catch blocs
associated to the relevant try blocs.
Third and last case, if the age
is bigger than or equal to 150.
What will happen is that we will arrive
in this if, whose condition is true
so we will execute this
exception throwing.
So here, we throw an object
of type Exception.
Which means that from here, we will
jump to the catch
that handles Exceptions.
This flow will continue here
by executing the display of
"Who can live to be that old?"
Then, as always, the execution
will continue normally
with the remainder of the program.
Let's go over a third
example
where we will put throw, try and catch
in one same method.
This is a special case that
can nevertheless be useful.
So here, we have a lireEntier
(TN: means "readInteger") method
whose goal is to read an integer
and return it
and that takes as parameter
a maximum number of attempts,
and whose header must be extended
with this syntax, throws Exception
which we will explain later on.
So here, we have the whole
body of this method
in which, as you can see,
we have a try bloc,
to try to read an integer from
the keyboard.
We want to read an integer.
What we will do is intercept any throw
that could occur
when we try to read this integer,
in case the input fails.
This happens, for example, if the user
inputs something else,
for example a character string.
In this case, the input will throw an
exception of type InputMismatchException
which is defined in the
java.util library.
If the input fails, then an exception of that
type will be thrown,
so we will jump to the catch, since we
had put that in a try bloc.
This will allow us, for example, to
display a message
"Try again to input an integer."
Then, with this expression, we clear
the input buffer
of the characters left by the
previous, bad input.
Finally, we increment the
number of tries.
The program will thus
execute in the following way.
In the beginning, nbEssais has
a value of 1 (TN: "nbEssais" means "number of attempts")
We will be in a loop while
the number of attempts
is lesser than or equal to the maximum
number of attempts we received as a parameter.
We ask for an integer.
We try to read an integer and each
time this input fails
we will jump to the catch bloc which
handles the corresponding exception
So we arrive here at the end of the catch
bloc if we had an input error.
We continue the execution.
We continue as long as nbEssais has not
reached the maximum number of attempts.
In case the input works, no
exception is thrown.
So the execution continues normally.
We return the value that was read
and we exit the program at that level.
Finally, if we make so many mistakes
that we exceed the maximum number of attempts,
the following will happen:
we will have another error which
will throw the exception
which will be caught by this catch here.
We will increment the number of attempts.
At the end of the catch, we continue
with the normal execution.
But this time, nbEssais will
be larger than
maxEssais.
So we will exit the while loop and
continue execution
by throwing a new exception this time,
and this exception will be passed
on higher to other methods
that will have called lireEntier
and that could possibly
catch this exception and handle it.
Let's end with a few remarks.
First, since Java 7 there exists something
that is called multi-catch.
We can write:
catch Exception1 or Exception2, etc.
Then, something that I already
told you,
when you have several catch blocs,
you must absolutely always
write them from the most specific
exception, from the lowest one in the
exception hierarchy,
to the most general one,
that is, the highest one
in the inheritance relationship
of exceptions.
Finally, let's end this episode
on Java syntax
for exception handling by this
point number 4,
where we might want to cleanup
after a catch bloc
with the finally keyword which
indicates, optionally, what to do
after an error-handling bloc.
This finally keyword thus controls
a bloc which is optional
and which follows the catch
blocs associated to a try
and which contains code that
should be executed
whether an exception was thrown or not.
The point of this bloc is to clean up,
for example to close files,
close connections etc.
In case an exception is thrown, it
guarantees that everything is cleaned up.
As an example, we have a little
program here
that we can call in different ways.
This is the first time we use
arguments passed manually.
This allows us, for example,
to pass different arguments
or even no arguments at all,
at the moment we execute this
Inverse program.
The way this is done is simply to
pass a string array
which contains the arguments
when we call this program
which we will name Inverse.
Here, we have a try bloc that
will try to read the different arguments
Args here is an array of strings.
args[0] is the first element of this array
of strings
Thus it is the first argument passed
to the program when we execute it,
as I explained earlier.
We will try to read an integer
in this first argument.
Then, we will divide by b.
Then, we display 100 times the inverse
of this number c
that we have just calculated.
If the first argument that we receive
is not an integer,
this expression will throw an exception
of type NumberFormatException
and so this will cause us to
jump to the catch bloc
corresponding to this type of exception.
We will indicate, for example,
"An integer is required!".
If however we manage to read an
integer from this first argument
then we pass here, we do this calculation
where we risk a division by 0.
If b equals 0, this division
will indeed
throw an ArithmeticException.
and we will jump to this
bloc that reacts
to exceptions of type
ArithmeticException
If we divide by 0, we will display that
the result goes to infinity.
Then, whatever happens, whether
we have an exception here,
or an exception there,
or nothing at all in this exception-aware bloc,
we will execute this mandatory segment.
We will execute the finally bloc
linked to this try bloc.
Let's look at all this in detail
on different ways of calling
this program.
If for example we call our program
with 4.1 as an argument,
which is of type double, then
here, we will not succeed in reading
an integer.
We jump here, we display "Il faut un nombre entier!"
(TN: means "An integer is required!")
Since we arrive at the end of the catch
bloc, we go on to the finally bloc.
Here, we write "passage obligé" (TN: means
"mandatory passage") and we end the program.
On the other hand, if we passed
an integer but that it is worth 0,
then we do manage to read an
integer, so we continue;
here, we divide by 0, which results
in an ArithmeticException
that is thrown and intercepted
by this catch bloc.
So we display that the result
goes to infinity.
Then we continue, as always,
with the finally bloc
which indicates that we have a
mandatory passage
Third case: we call our program and
pass it an argument
which is a non-null integer.
At that point, we do succeed
in reading an integer.
We continue. We complete
the division with no problem.
So we can display that 100 times
its inverse is 25.
In this case, we also finish by
passing by the finally
which is executed in any case
since we are in a try bloc.
Here, at the end of the execution
of this try bloc,
we will continue by executing
the finally bloc
and displaying that we have
a mandatory passage.
To finish, here is a last example.
We pass no argument, and so the
following happens:
we will want to read an integer in
the first element of the array A
But it so happens that there
were no arguments passed,
so this array is empty
There isn't even an element
at index 0.
We have an out-of-bounds index
and so an exception
will be thrown,
which is the ArrayIndexOutOfBounds
exception.
So this exception will be thrown,
but as you can see,
before that, we will have passed
by the finally.
Indeed, here we are in the try bloc
and as we will exit it here
by throwing an exception;
this exception is not caught
by any of the catch statements
However, we pass by the finally bloc.
We always pass by the finally bloc
associated to a try bloc.
So we display this, before continuing
with this exception
which is not caught and hence
ends the program's execution
with a message meaning that
the exception was not caught
followed by the call trace
at the place where this
exception was thrown.
So you can see that regardless
of the execution sequence
of the try bloc, we always
pass by the finally bloc.
In this case here, such a finally
is not very useful.
But if we had allocated ressources,
or opened files in this try bloc,
we could guarantee, by
closing these resources,
by freeing these resources
in the finally bloc,
we would guarantee that regardless
of the execution sequence of this try bloc,
the finally bloc will correctly
free the resources.
This is typically what a finally
bloc is used for.
This concludes the episode on exception
syntax in Java.