In this episode, we will discuss
several complements
on exception handling.
We will begin with the notion
of rethrowing.
That is, how to partially
handle an exception
and rethrow it further.
We will also discuss a particular
rule in Java :
the handle or declare rule.
We will also see how to
declare our own exception classes.
Let us begin with the rethrowing.
You probably remember our little
introductory example.
In that example,
the lowest level method "inverse"
was throwing the exception.
This thrown exception was not
caught by the intermediary level
which was simply tasked with the
graphical printing of the temperatures' inverse.
However, we suggested to intercept
the thrown exception
in the main program
so that we could handle it there.
If we decide to handle the exception
at this program's level,
we will know if an exception has
been thrown,
if something abnormal has occured while
trying to execute "graphiqueInverse".
However, we will not have much information
on the precise conditions
behind this abnormal situation.
For example, we might want to know
what is the array position of the
value
that triggered the issue.
The part of the program knowing
where in the array
the exception has been triggered is
actually this one.
It could be interesting to have it so
that this part
reports to the rest of the program
that there has been a problem
at this part of the array.
Thus, this method could intercept
the thrown exception to handle it here,
reporting to the rest of the program
at what index the problem has occured.
For example, we could imagine
to intercept the exception here.
Unfortunately, this method is not
aware
of the context of its call.
Therefore, it cannot take decisions
regarding the array.
It cannot run the same processing
as the ones performed
in the main program
(for example deciding to aquire
all temperatures anew
since the formers are erroneous).
The sole possible action
of this method
is to relay the problematic
index
to the rest of the program,
and to rethrow the exception
to a higher level;
this level being more knowledgeable
on how to solve this abnormal situation.
Consequently, the method "graphiqueInverse"
could itself
throw an exception, informing
the rest of the program
at what index the problem has occured.
For example, like this
(we are stretching beyond this course's
frame; we will manage though).
Of course, we need for the
index to be handled.
For example, we can proceed
like this.
From now on, whenever an exception
is thrown during the loop's execution,
the main program will intercept it
and receive a message
potentially informing on
the index
at which the problem has occured.
An intermediary part of the program
has decided here
to rethrow an exception which
is more informed than the previous one.
This way, a more informed
part of the program
will make better use of it.
Here, we have partially handled the
original exception.
As we have seen in this example,
an exception can be partially
treated
in an intermediary level of the program
with a dedicated "catch" block.
Then, we will wait for a subsequent
handling.
To this end, the intermediary level
must "rethrow" the exception,
the same one or a more informed one.
Naturally, the higher level must
be equipped with a corresponding
"try" and "catch" blocks
able to intercept and handle
the rethrown exception properly.
The idea is that, at an
intermediary level of the program,
we intercept an exception thrown
level.
Then, we will handle
it partially,
and decide we do not have enough
information to handle completely.
Thus, we will rethrow either the
same exception
or a new one with another message
or content.
Now, you know that an exception
can intercepted
at an intermediary level of the program,
be handled partially,
and be rethrown at a higher level,
more informed of the error context.
Now, we will move on to
another topic :
the rule "handle or declare",
which is specific to Java.
When a method throws an exception,
and delegate its handling
to a higher level of the program
(thus, it does not handle the
exception locally),
it must, in genere, inform that it
is throwing an exception.
Thus, whoever uses this method
at a higher level
knows that it can throw the exception,
thus getting ready either
to handle this exception
or rethrow it to a higher level.
So that a method may delcare
and potentially throw
one or several exceptions,
we have to use a particular syntax
after the method header
indicated by the reserved
keyword "throws",
followed by the list of exceptions
this method can throw,
separated by semicolons.
For example, here, the "inverse" method
throws an exception
when a division by 0 occurs.
It does not treat this exception
locally;
there is no "try" and "catch" block
catching this exception inside
the "inverse" method.
Therefore, it must report it
to the rest of the program,
thus granting it the
handling of
this type of exception it has thrown.
This is done through
the reserved keyword "throws"
followed by a list of the exceptions
thrown by this method.
In Java, we shall apply the following rule:
every exception which is neither
a "RunTimeException" nor an "Error"
must respect the
"handle or declare" rule.
Concretely, this means that
exceptions must either be
directly intercepted in the method
where they are thrown
(this is only possible
in certain situations)
or they must be "declared" by the method
to inform the rest of the program
that the method delegates
exception handling to the rest
of the program.
This means that, in Java, if an
exception's type
is neither "RunTimeException" nor "Error",
and it if is now intercepted
in the method where it is thrown,
nor declared by the method,
the compiler will return an
error message.
In this case, we talk of "Checked exceptions".
These are exceptions controlled
by the compiler
by opposition to "Unchecked" exceptions
for which the compiler does not
necessarily enforce
a specific processing or indication
once such an exception has been thrown.
These controls enforced by the compiler
are tasked
with forcing exception handling.
However, the compiler does
not wish to force
the handling of exceptions
of the types "RunTime" or "Error".
Indeed, "Error" corresponds to situations
the programmer is not able
to handle himself :
for example, not enough
available memory on the computer
on which the program is executed.
Thus, it makes no sense for
the compiler
to force the programmer
to handle these kinds of exception.
On the other hand, "RunTimeExceptions"
very often correspond
to situations that can be solved properly
simply through better programming.
For example, when we go past
the possible indices in an array,
or when we execute a division by 0,
it can corresponds to situations
solvable
through better programming.
However, they can also be situations
we whish to handle through exceptions.
The problems that can be solved
by better programming
should be solved this way
rather than by exception handling.
This is why the compiler is not
forcing us
to declare or handle the
"RunTimeExceptions" either.
Java provides a wide range of
possible exceptions;
it is recommanded to use them
in the more informative way possible.
This means, we should use the exception
type more suited to the problem
we wish to invest or handle
through exceptions.
However, in certain situations,
it can be useful
to define our own exceptions
classes.
The language provides us
with this possibility.
In order to define our
own exception classes,
we simpy have to have them
inherit from the exception
or one of its derived classes.
As we have had the chance to see it
in a previous episode,
the exception class offers
a method "getMessage".
It is useful to call it in order
to give informations
on the nature of the exception.
The message returned by "getMessage"
is initialized by the constructors
of the exception class.
In order to have the message
associated with our own exception classes
correctly initialized, it is thus
recommanded
for a custom exception class without
other content,
to contain at least the two
following constructors.
The default one will initialize
the message with a default value.
The other constructor will take a string
as parameter and use it to initialize the message.
This way, we will preserve
the behavoir expected from "getMessage".
Naturally, when we define our own
custom exception classes,
it is to provide them
with more content.
At our level, we are compltetely free
to add as many methods or attributes
as we wish to.
For example, it could be useful
to add, inside the class,
attributes referring to error codes.
Also, we could add informations
on the content of exception detection,
and so on.
Let us now see a concrete example.
For example, let us imagine
we wish to create
an exception class able
to handle
abnormal situations regarding
temperatures.
Thus, this exception class
will contain informations
indicating which abnormal temperature
has been detected.
Then it will give instructions
regarding this temperature:
What should we do concretely
in case of such or such
abnormal temperature.
By the way, you will note
that, in Java,
it is recommanded to call our
exception  classes
with a name ending in "Exception".
I think we here reached a limit in the naming coventions
that combine French and English!...
But we can live with it.
Our class can also include
any content potentially useful
for the handling of such exceptions.
Typically, here,
a constructor able to initialize
the obtained temperature
and the associated order.
This constructor will also have
to call the constructor of
of the base class
in order to initialize the associated
message.
This message could naturally
be a parameter.
Here, we have chosen to give
it a default value.
We can also add any method
we deem useful.
Here, we have simply chosen
to add a "getter"
for each of the attributes;
that is, one for the temperature,
another for the order.
Let us see an example of its use.
Let us imagine that the temperature
reaches a critical level.
We could imagine throwing
such an exception
of this newly-defined type
by initializing it with the abnormal
obtained temperature
and a particular order to follow
when this temperature is
encountered.
Thus, the intercepting block
will be able to provide several
interesting informations
on the nature of the exception.
It will be able to report the
abnormal obtained temperature.
Then, it will, for example here,
give instructions
on what to do regarding this
temperature here.
We could also imagine giving
more informative messages.
For example here, we have
obtained a temperature of
150 degrees
[TN: Celcius, which is here supposed to be too high].
In this case, the order is to verify
our meter.
Voilà! We are just about
done with the complements
we wish to share on exceptions
in Java.
To close this chapter, we will
simply review
the little introductory example,
coded in Java this time.
This is our program tasked with
printing the inverse of a few
measured temperatures.
Let us begin with the coding
of the main program
the way we can imagine it in Java.
The main program will store
a few measures
in a dynamic array of doubles.
Those temperatures are aquired
through a method
tasked with the filling of the array.
Now, we wish to print the
inverses of these temperatures
stored in the array.
If the array of measures contains
null values,
the printing of these temperatures' inverses
will result in an error.
However, we wish to give
a few chances
to the program user.
Thus, we will let him input
the array with new measures
if an abnormal situation
has occured.
We will grant them only
two trials
to try and input a new array that does
not contain any null values.
The idea is the following :
we know that the call to this
method may result
in the triggering of an exception.
We will indicate that this instruction is
a block receptive to errors.
Thus, we will frame it with
a "try" block.
If the array of measures contains
a null measure,
this method's execution will
trigger an exception.
Let's assume that this exception's
type is "ArithmeticException".
It will then be caught
by a corresponding "catch" block.
We have not yet reached the maximum
amount of trials,
we will simply inform that the user that
they are to reinput the values.
Otherwise, we will tell them,
with another message, that they have
ran out of trials,
and that we will consequently give
up on aquiring the measures.
We thus close the execution
of this "catch" block.
the execution continues sequentially
until it reaches the evaluation
of the "while" continuation condition.
The "while" will keep looping
if the number of attempts has
not yet been reached.
This will make it possible to reinput
the array of measures
as long as the maximum number of
attempts has not been reached.
The method tasked with printing
the inverses of the temperatures
thus takes an array of temperatures
as parameter.
It will iterate the elements in this array.
For each index 'i', it will print
the inverse of the temperature
stored at position 'i'.
Since the computation of the inverse
can throw an exception
(here, we suppose its type to
be "ArithmeticException" ),
we take care to indicate that
this instruction
is an error-receptive block;
thus framed with a "try" block".
This will make it possible to report
that the problem
has occured with the index 'i'.
Since, at this level, we do not know
how to solve this problem
completely, we will rethrow
the exception.
Here, we rethrow the exception
just as we have received it.
We could have created another one.
By the way, you may have noticed
that we have declared the exception
potentially thrown
in "plotTempInverse".
Was that truly mandatory here?
Well, in fact it is not compulsory to
declare the exception thrown here.
Why? Because "ArithmeticException"
is of the type "RunTimeException",
and is therefore not subject to
the rule "handle or declare".
Here, declaring it simply provides a little
more information.
Someone reading this method's header
will see that it can throw
an "ArithmeticException",
thus taking measures accordingly.
Now, let us go all the way
for this example.
We will suppose that there is
a drawing method
stricto sensu, able to draw
a point.
We thus imagine that there is a
graphical method,
able to fulfill this processing.
Of course, we also have our
famous method "inverse"
which returns the inverse of a number.
We have also chosen, here, to declare
that it throws an "ArithmeticException".
Once again, it is not necessary since
it is a "RunTimeException".
Now, if the given number is zero,
this method will thow an exception
of the type "ArithmeticException"
with an appropriate message.
The execution stream is the following.
Let us imagine that there is a null
value in our array of measures.
Now, we will thus call "plotTempInverse",
which will call the method calculating
a number's inverse.
Now, if the number is zero,
the method will throw an exception
of the type "ArithmeticException".
This exception will now be caught
at a higher level,
that is, in "plotTempInverse".
Now, it will print "Problème à l'indice i"
(TN: means "Problem at the index i" ).
The exception is then rethrown
to be caught again at a
higher level.
This time, "plotTempInverse" has
thrown the exception. We will thus
connect on the corresponding
"catch" block in the main program.
Now, we will start counting the
attempts of our user.
This is how such a program
will unfold
when exceptions are thrown.
Now, to wrap this chapter
on exceptions,
let us tell you that exception
handling
is an extremely flexible
and practical approach
in order to deal with abnormal situations.
However, this way is significantly
more resource-expensing
than the good old "if... then... else".
The general rule is that, if at all possible,
do deal with the error where it occured
without passing by exception handling.
For example, let us imagine that,
in a program,
we ask the user to enter values
between 0 and 100.
Now, our wayward user decides
to enter a value greater than 100.
Obviously, we know how to deal
with this error locally,
ordering the user to reenter
the values.
This means we do not have to
pass by exceptions
in this case.
Finally, when we can choose
between several exception types,
it is better to go for the
most specific:
this will be more useful and informative.
This concludes our episode about exceptions.