We have introduced the HR diagram, the colour-magnitude
diagram
and we have seen where each type of star is
located in it
depending on its mass, luminosity, colour
and size.
In what follow we will see in a very simplified
manner
how stars evolve in the diagram during their
life,
how they are born, how they burn
their hydrogen into helium and how they eventually
die,
depending on their luminosity and their initial
mass.
How do stars form ?
By fragmentation of a cloud of dust and gas.
We have here a cloud which fragments into
several pieces
the size and mass of which obey some distribution.
The cloud fragments
and the resulting pieces have to meet Jeans'
criteria :
you remember that, in the previous chapter,
we had introduced Jeans' mass and Jeans' radius.
If the fragments are large or massive enough,
they may collapse and contract.
The initial clouds have some mass distribution
that we can represent on a log/log scale here.
The curve has usually this shape and is called
the initial mass function.
This initial mass function gives the distribution
of nebula fragments
in units of solar masses.
We have on this axis the decimal logarithm
of the number of fragments.
This point is more or less two,
here is the 0 and here is minus 2.
There are many fragments of small mass and
a few fragments of large mass.
We have here more or less 0.1 solar masses,
here are 100 solar masses and finally here
is the 0
since it is a logarithmic scale.
The zero corresponds to one solar mass.
Most stars weigh roughly one solar mass.
This is the initial mass function, giving
the mass distribution
of the fragmenting clouds.
These fragmenting clouds appear
in the colour-magnitude diagram
along a roughly vertical sequence that I schematize
here.
This sequence is called the Hayashi track.
This sequence is isothermal, everything is
at the same temperature.
We have here the log of temperature, the log
of luminosity,
the absolute magnitude is represented here
and decreases upwards,
therefore the luminosity increases upwards.
Here is the colour index
with rather blue stars in this area on the
left and red stars over there.
The nebula fragments will spread over the
Hayashi track.
Their mass distribution is given here and
they are distributed
along this line.
Imagine here, on various locations, various
stars with different masses
which are actually protostars.
At this stage, stars are convective.
The motion at the centre of the star
is turbulent, going in all directions.
The material inside is mixed and the star
contracts.
At this stage there is not any nuclear reaction
yet.
Remember that according to the Virial theorem,
if the radius decreases
the temperature of the core increases
and it will do so until igniting the nuclear
reactions.
At this point the contraction is slowed down.
The contraction is slowed down by two phenomena
: radiative pressure
due to photons emitted by the contraction
of the star
and the internal heating of the star, and
of course the gas pressure
due to the turbulences.
When the star contracts, it becomes
more and more opaque. The medium becomes opaque
which means that the luminosity decreases.
The Hayashi track is an isothermal curve,
which means that
during the contraction T stays constant.
Remember that L = 4πR²σT^4.
L decreases while T is constant
and all other quantities but the radius are
constants.
Therefore R decreases.
The star's luminosity decreasing at a constant
temperature
implies that the star is contracting.
While the external temperature stays constant,
the star is contracting
but the temperature increases in the centre
up to the point of starting nuclear reactions.
For each star, with here a massive one as
an example,
the star's luminosity decreases when it contracts
and the nuclear reactions start.
When the nuclear reactions ignite, the star
increases in temperature until reaching a
position
on the main sequence.
So on this point we have the start of nuclear
reactions.
Of course at the start of nuclear reactions
the temperature increases very quickly
until reaching an equilibrium between the
radiative pressure
of the photons, the gas pressure and the gravity.
The ignition of nuclear reactions
is as fast as the star is massive.
A star of small mass will drop slower along
the Hayashi track before moving to the main
sequence.
Stars of even very small mass tend to migrate,
to start very slowly their nuclear reactions.
We see that we left from a mass sequence
defined by the initial mass function
and we reach another mass sequence, which
is the main sequence.
The heavier stars are at the top and the lighter
stars at the bottom.
What happens once on the main sequence ?
Stars burn their hydrogen.
We have thus nuclear reactions
of fusion of hydrogen nuclei into helium nuclei.
This can happen in two different ways
with a more or less complicated reaction chain.
The limit between the two possible reactions
is at 1.3 solar masses.
Over 1.3 solar masses, stars burn
their hydrogen into helium following the CNO
cycle.
Under 1.3 solar masses, we have
the proton-proton chain.
Contrarily to what the name suggests,
the CNO cycle produces neither carbon, nitrogen
nor oxygen.
The proton-proton chain involves essentially
protons.
but the outcome of both reactions is the fusion
of four hydrogen nuclei
into one helium nucleus.
The CNO cycle requires higher temperatures
than the proton-proton cycle.
We have therefore a limit in temperature which
corresponds of course to a mass limit.
What is really important to remember is that
when a star is on the main sequence, it burns
its hydrogen into helium.
This is what stars do during the longest part
of their life.
On the main sequence, there is an equilibrium
between gas pressure,
radiative pressure and gravity.
In the star, there is
hydrogen burning into helium
and emitting photons in all directions.
Then there is the gas pressure.
And finally in the opposite direction there
is the star's own gravity
which tends to make it collapse.
What are the phenomena occurring in stars
when they are on
the main sequence ?
There are nuclear fusion reactions along the
whole main sequence
with different kinds of reactions depending
on the mass being
above or below 1.3 solar masses.
Another important limit is at 8 solar masses.
We will see that this limit determines how
the stars die.
Let us consider a star on the main sequence
and heavier than 8 solar masses.
The star is burning its hydrogen into helium.
I draw here this star.
It burns hydrogen into helium
and is in a state of equilibrium between pressure
and gravity.
Once the fusion of hydrogen stops,
both gas and radiative pressure decrease
and gravity wins.
Two things happen at this stage. First the
star cools down
and second the external layers are ejected.
The core will in turn contract
and the external layers expand
Now two things happen.
First, the radius of the star increases.
At the same time, the external layers cool
down, T decreases
and the star becomes redder.
Meanwhile the core warms up.
Heating continues until igniting the next
nuclear reactions.
The core of the star begins to fuse helium
into carbon.
While the star is still on the main sequence,
the hydrogen reactions stop,
the stellar radius increases and the surface
temperature decreases.
This means that a star
tends to move to the right of the diagram
to the domains of lower temperatures and redder
surface colours.
Another star here will follow the same pattern.
For a very massive star, the core contracts
and starts the reaction fusing helium into
carbon.
This happens roughly in this area.
At this stage the star obviously warms up
and we have therefore a "knee" in direction
of hot temperatures.
There is a succession of nuclear reactions.
We have the burning of helium into carbon.
When this reaction stops, the star moves again
to the right of the diagram
and the next reaction starts, etc.
Each reaction is shorter in time than the
previous one.
After a while we reach the reaction of iron
fusion.
The iron fusion reaction is endothermic
rather than exothermic.
When the iron reaction starts in the core
of the star,
not only there is no emitted photon and no
pressure
directed outward but there is also energy
absorption.
The star will therefore quickly collapse
and eventually releases a supernova.
For stars heavier than 8 solar masses
there is a succession of nuclear reactions.
There is a succession of nuclear reactions
and core contractions
until reaching the endothermic iron reaction
and thus the explosion of the star.
Beyond 8 solar masses all stars follow such
a trajectory.
They become giants and zigzag.
The number of zigzags, namely the number of
distinct nuclear reactions depends on the
mass.
And we have then an explosion into a type
II supernova.
If the star is originally extremely massive,
there may remain after the supernova explosion
a neutron star or a black hole.
What happens for stars of smaller mass ?
The mass limit is 8 solar masses.
What happens now for stars below 8 solar masses
?
Actually it is more or less the same thing
as before.
Stars evolve into giant stars
and cool down to a certain location
on the colour-magnitude diagram.
They first get redder.
Then the external layers inflate and the core
contracts
probably up to start a new nuclear reaction
but without going all the
way to the iron reaction.
Iron fusion is not possible because the mass
of the star is too small.
Other reactions than hydrogen and helium burning
can then start
but without going to the iron reaction.
What happens is that the external layers inflate
and the core contracts.
The external layers are expanding.
As for the core, it contracts until
it cannot ignite the following nuclear reaction
and the star simply dies.
The external layers turn into a planetary
nebula
with at its centre a dead star, a white dwarf
that radiates simply as it cools down.
There are also stars with an even smaller
mass.
There are other mass limits : 0.08 solar masses
and 0.26 solar masses.
Those are stars that form directly into white
dwarves
from the protostellar cloud
with a mass in this range, and do not form
from the cloud
left by a massive star dying into a white
dwarf.
We have thus a white dwarf, which is located
roughly here
on the colour-magnitude diagram.
If the mass is even smaller than 0.08 solar
masses
the mass is not large enough to start nuclear
reactions
and we witness the formation of a brown dwarf.
Such a star shine only under the effect of
its gravitational contraction
which is what we saw in the slides about
the Kelvin-Helmholtz time scale
There is simply a conversion of potential
energy into radiation
as the star contracts very slowly
under the effect of its own gravity.
But there is not any nuclear reaction.
Let us now see how the colour-magnitude diagram
can be used to date a star population.
A star population is simply a bunch of stars,
for example
a globular cluster that we saw several times
during the course, or an open cluster
and these stars are all formed at the same
time.
Stars are distributed along a mass sequence,
the main sequence.
Stars on the main sequence are burning their
hydrogen.
Be attentive that the more massive a star
is, the faster
it burns its hydrogen.
In other words, a star will leave the main
sequence quicker
all the more massive it is,
the higher they are on the main sequence.
We have what are called evolutionary tracks.
Stars will evolve and reach
different locations on the diagram, more or
less like that.
I draw shorter and shorter tracks simply because
they cool down :
a star of smaller mass ignites the nuclear
reaction
following the hydrogen to helium one
faster than other stars.
We have evolutionary tracks that look like
that,
I am not drawing them exactly.
We have then these tracks here.
The most massive stars
leave the main sequence very quickly.
Stars with a slightly smaller mass leave it
a bit afterwards
and so on and so forth.
If I link all these points I have what is
called
an isochronous curve, which as the name suggests
links stars with all the same age.
I can here draw an isochronous curve like
that.
You see a knee on the isochrone.
There are stars leaving the main sequence,
having the required mass to soon leave the
main sequence.
I may also have another isochronous line
such as this one, and so on.
The higher the knee, the smaller this distance
and the younger the cluster is.
If it follows the main sequence the cluster
has an age of 0
and stars are starting to migrate towards
the giant branch,
doing so as fast as they are massive.
Of course, the lower the knee on the main
sequence is,
the older the cluster is.
Here are a few examples of isochronous curves.
This one is the isochrone we had on the previous
diagram
which corresponds to the main sequence of
very young stars,
of the order of 10^6 years old.
Here is the isochrone for 10^9 years and another
one for 10^10 years,
namely 10 billion years, almost the age of
the Universe.
Notice that on a 10^9 years old isochronous
line
there is not any star at the top of the diagram
any more
because all these stars have disappeared.
They had a large mass
and burned all their hydrogen. They were probably
more massive than 8 solar masses
and have therefore all exploded. 10^9 years
afterwards, there is no
more star of this kind left on the colour-
magnitude diagram.
The remaining stars on this sequence have
smaller masses.
Here is the giant branch.
Some stars are still on the main sequence
and are still burning their hydrogen
but the more massive ones have moved to the
giant branch.
If we wait a little more, there subsists only
stars with a very small mass on the main sequence.
Almost all stars have evolved toward the giant
branch.
This way, just by looking at the location
of the knee,
one can know the age of the cluster, simply
because the age of the cluster
is the age of the stars leaving the main sequence.
Thanks to colour-magnitude diagrams and by
assuming that the sequences
we observe here come from a star population
of the same age,
one can date the age of star clusters.
Either very young star clusters, 10^6 years
here
or star clusters that can have ages of the
order of the age of the Universe.
To summarize, stars form from
the fragmenting of a gas and dust cloud.
They collapse
and this collapse warms up the centre of the
protostar
up to the point of starting the reactions
of nuclear fusion of hydrogen into helium.
They spend most of their life burning hydrogen
into helium.
At this stage, they are located on the main
sequence we talked about
several times, which is a mass sequence
with the most massive stars at the top
and the least massive stars at the bottom.
Once the hydrogen has been consumed, the equilibrium
between the
gas and radiative pressure outwards and gravity
in the opposite direction
is broken.
The core of the star tends to collapse
while the outer layers expand
and the star becomes therefore a giant star.
At this stage, it undergoes a succesive series
of contractions
and ignitions of nuclear reactions
that each produces heavier and heavier elements.
If the star is beyond 8 solar masses, it explodes
in a supernova, a remain of which we see here
in the background.
If the star is below 8 solar masses
such as our Sun with one solar mass,
it produces a nebula such as the nebula Messier
that we have already seen in the first chapter,
at the center of which
rests a white dwarf.
Finally, stars with very low masses, less
than 0.08 solar masses,
remain as red dwarves
or brown dwarves at the bottom of the colour-magnitude
diagram
and they will keep shining for billions of
years.