So hello again.
Having looked at the different hydrates that forms
Calcium hydroxide, Calcium silicate hydrates, these
phases that come from the illuminates; now we're going to
look at how these different hydrates form in time the kinetics
of the hydration reaction.
Here we're going to look first of all at the
hydration of the calcium silicate phases.
And this shows the typical hydration curve
from Tri calcium silicate.
What you see is that initially we get a very
high rate of heat evolution and
then very quickly the rate of heat evolution
let's say the rate of reaction falls away and
we get this period of very slow reaction during a few hours
and this is usually called the induction period.
Now from a practical point of view this is very
important because this
induction period gives us the time to mix our cement or
concrete to move it on to site to place it in the forms
and produce the kind of concrete element
we want to have in our buildings.
And then after typically something like three hours
the reaction takes off again.
We have what's called the acceleration
period after about ten hours then it starts to slow
down again and what we call the deceleration period
and after the first day
or so, the rate of heat reaction is really quite low,
even though a twenty four hours we may only have formed about
twenty five percent of the
or less of the final strength of our concrete.
So there's quite a lot happening off the first day
but it's happening much more slowly, so it's more difficult
to follow from the point of this heatevolution.
And in particular in terms of these kinetics,
there are two questions that have occupied the researchers.
First of all this
initial slowdown.
why do we get this initial slowing down.
Then why did we get this second
slowing down for the deceleration period.
And in these modules we're going to look individually at
three separate periods.
We're going to look at this first period
of the initial heat evolution
and the induction period, then we're going to
look at this main heat volution peak here.
And then we're going to look at the slow ongoing reaction.
There is quite a lot happening in this final period.
In fact a lot of the strength is developing during this time
but it's quite difficult to see because it's quite difficult
to measure what's happening due to the very low rate of heat evolution.
Right so in this first one on the kinetics,
we're going to look at this induction period.
It seems kind of
old that the reaction should start
Fast and then slow down
and to explain this what is classically being advanced
has been this idea that we have this protective membrane forming
around the grains.
And many people over the years have advanced this kind
of hypothesis, then there's been all kinds of different theories
as to why they slash or suddenly disappear
and this is why fact one of the main weaknesses of this theory,
that nobody really has come up with a coherent idea of
why the membrane forms and then
suddenly disappears after some time.
But nowadays it's more important to realize that there is
really no evidence for this protective layer.
Back in the sixty's
when people first came up with this idea.
The fact we couldn't see it
wasn't really too much of a problem
but nowadays where we have very advanced characterization tools,
this is really a big issue.
I mean it's like the
emperor's new clothes.
Here we see a picture which I think is
Particularly important was lent to me by Luc Nicoleau
and what we see this was made in a cryo S.C.M.
So in a cryo S.C.M.
What happens? You take a cement paste you freeze it,
you break it, you put the broken frozen sample into the microscope
and then sublime the water. So it's a kind of gentle way of drying
but you do have to eventually remove the water because electrons
can't penetrate through water, so you have to remove the water first.
And what we can see here, we can see this
isn't alite grain here which is being fractured.
Along the
surface of this alite grain we see the hydrates.
So here is C S H here.
We don't really see much calcium hydroxide here,
we see a little bit of ettringite for
example down here a little bit
up here.
But very clearly these hydrates don't give a
continuous membrane on top of this cement grain.
And in fact we can see these pits, we're going to
come back to these pits they're very very important.
And particularly on these pits we can see
there's no indication of any kind of covering.
And this micro office of quite a high resolution the
bar here tells you about one hundred nanometers scale so you know
even if there was a layer only a few know made to
stick we would expect to see some indication of it.
So really this theory of the protective membrane
that most people have been promulgating for a number of years now
really just doesn't hold up to examination.
And here's another sequence where we can see in this case
what's happening under water.
So this sequence was taken in
the Wet cell of
atomic force microscope.
And as we run the sequence as we do here here,
here to run the sequence we can see that we get this rough area
forming here and then after a while we start to see the steps.
OK the steps here
and the steps are moving as we
have the dissolution at those steps.
Those are the particular important things to observe here,
first of all a rough area forming
and then moving to this steps which retreat.
Now another observation which completely
to my mind refutes the protective layer theory
as this experiment we did about annealing.
So we took alite
and one part of the Alite was then heated up
to anneal it, to remove the effects
and you can see here this dramatic effect the annealing
has on the hydration kinetics.
It really extends this induction
period,
but almost to this induction period,
then the hydration seems pretty much the same
as it was for the unannealed sample.
And over here we see the first peak
and we see for the anneal sample the initial Heeat evolution
is much lower then from the normally anneal sample.
Now how could this be explained
by a protective layer theory.
If we were going to say well maybe the layer is thicker in
the case in the anneal sample, that doesn't correlate with
what we see from the
first evolution peak.
And you know if we had a different kind of layer forming,
why should we expect the hydration to be the same afterwards.
This is just one example of experimental results
that cannot be explained by this theory
and more results are discussed in the paper by ......
which can be found in the references.
So the alternative theory is really just to say
well we have nucleation and growth and nucleation
and growth is a Well known phenomenal in many reactions,
in metals, in acqeous solutions, many many chemical
processes,
we can make a simple model of nucleation
and growth as is shown on the left here
where we have these little islands
which ar represented in the
nuclei of C.S.H.
and As they grow, they give this acceleration peak.
So in terms of the acceleration peak as we'll see in the next module,
This can be very well explained by nucleation and growth
but what we're missing here is any explanation of why
we have to slow down from the first dissolution.
So to understand
the slowdown better, I think we need to go through the work
that has been done in geochemistry.
Now here I want to introduce
this idea of dissolution being a negative form of growth.
And the little diagrams over on the left here will
probably be familiar to those of you who started
classical metalogy
and material science
and have looked at the solidification of metals.
So it's well known in the solidification of
metals solidification of
just about anything in fact that we don't get the solid
forming exactly the melting temperature temperature of fusion
as indicated here.
And this is because we have super cooling
and we need this super cooling because we need to
go to this point here where there is
energy difference between the liquid and solace,
and that energy difference is sufficient to give the surface
and history to form the first nuclei.
So those of you are familiar with that just look at any
classical material science textbook
you'll find a more detailed explanation.
When we come to think about dissolution,
if we have dissolution from a smooth surface,
this is always also going to require energy
for forming the extra
surface, so here we have an imaginary surface
and here we have a little bit of dissolution going on
and you see dissolution means that
we have to get this extra surface that is show there.
And then in this case, this extra surface energy
needs to come from the under saturation of the solution.
That's to say
if the solution contains less ions than it can do it
saturation, it has a higher energy it can be used can be used to
produce this extra surface.
So this analysis has been developed quite
rigorously in the theory of geo chemistry
and in the next slide we see two examples from
work published in this area.
So the first example shows pictures of the
different modes of different dissolution of course.
Standard quite high temperature,
and I really want to underline that because of this idea of
dissolution as being the negative of growth,
we see that the
under saturation is
increasing as we go to the left
and the dissolution rate is increasing as we go down.
So this is kind of the opposite to what we'd expect on a normal
axis system.
And then we see here for the course that a very high
degrees around saturation we've got a lot of excess energy due to
saturation so we can form a lot of
these very small piece these etch pits Vacancy islands.
As we move a little bit closer to saturation,
we see that these etch Pits tend to focus on dislocations
or other kind of defects we have in the crystal structure
and as we come close to saturation, we change radically
the mode dissolution and instead of forming pits, we form this
step retreat and remember that picture we saw in the A.F.M.
Of the zoning alite, how we saw that first of all we formed
a rough surface which is similar to the first
three pictures here and then we went to step retreat.
Now on the right here, we see how this translates quantitatively
in terms of the rate of dissolution as a function of
the Delta G.
Now the delta G
can just be derived from the difference
between the equilibrium saturation
and the actual under saturation.
So what you see from the experimental points
here is we get this sudden transition
from a fast dissolution at high delta Gs
to a slow dissolution and this transition occurs
when we're still in fact quite far away from the
equilibrium saturation which is here.
And this step function cannot told be captured by
these other lines on here which shows what you would predict from a
classical transition state theory, as used in chemistry.
So this transition between forces solution
and slow dissolution is quite abrupt.
Now the question is this is being well proven for many minerals,
but doesn't it apply for cement minerals.
Well you know my first question is Well
why not you know if it applies for all
other minerals, Why should the minerals we form
have in cement clinker be any different.
And in fact we see that they're not any different
this is a classical experiment done by Patrick ....
a few years ago in my laboratory.
What we see in the middle here, we see
The alite which was freshly produced in the laboratory.
And then he took this fractured alite
and when he dipped it in pure water and
when we diffuse impure water as you see on the left hand side,
what we see is that very quickly we get this
very rough surface forming
With these etch pits because we've got a high under saturation
with the pure water.
We rapidly form these experts
and we can see the scope very strong Crystal graphic relationship,
because we've actually got to alite grains here
and we can see that one grain is being heavily attacked
whereas the other grain is remaining relatively unattacked
because it's probably in the wrong orientation.
Whereas on the right hand side here,
if we take exactly the same alite
now put it in saturated lime solution, so saturated lime solution
is getting much closer but under saturated with
respect to a light, we see that now we no longer got
the energy required to give us these etch pits
and we've got really just smooth surface.
So there was really the refining experiment and then
when we made a theoretical analysis, we could see on
this left here from this classical paper of Julian et al in
2009,
we see that this is the under saturation
and the dissolution rate has this step function
which occurs around the level of saturation of Portlandite.
And then Luc Nicoleau and Andrei Norna really show
that we could have exactly the same behavior Experimentally.
So here, we have a theoretical treatment
here experimental treatment here,
And then Luc Nicoleau and Andrei Norna really show
that we could have exactly the same behavior Experimentally.
So here, we have a theoretical treatment
here experimental treatment here,
and quantitatively, they really match extremely well.
We could then take the same theoretical framework
but apply it in a completely different way,
so if we then take a model
where we're trying to fit for the calorimeter
curves,
we can find that we get the best fitting here
when we get values for this step function,
exactly the same as I showed you in the previous slide.
Coming to the summary here,
I think what's very important in this module is that
they most common theory you're fighting old textbooks really
is just not true.
I mean I'm sorry I know this is very destabilizing
for people trying to learn about cement chemistry,
but it's really very important you know.
It's not uncommon in science for one theory
to be proven for a long period
of time and then somebody to come along and
say that no it's not like that.
And those of you who study the history of science maybe
know about the fliginstan which was kind of a negative
oxygen,
which was believed to explain a lot of things in in metals.
You can go read about that in your spare time
but really I want you to come away.
From there to really understand that there is no protective layer forming,
there's no experimental evidence for it
and mails to the experimental
results cannot be explained by that.
That on the other hand we can explain this initial slowdown
by dissolution as a function of the under
saturation.
And this has a very sound theoretical framework from geochemistry.
This excellent agreement between theory experimental
measurements and what we can do with modeling
and really we can explain all the experimental observations.
So thank you and I hope that's been useful for you.