So OK Welcome back. Now we're going to look at the main hydration peak.
So in the last module, we
looked at the induction period, how that this is not related
to protective membranes is just related to under saturation
and dissolution theory.
And now in this more show we're going to look at
this main hydration peak,
That's to say the period between about three
hours and twenty four hours in which we have first
this very strong acceleration in the race of reaction
and then this deceleration.
And the main question that's really posed in this
Period is why do we go from this acceleration.
Why is it just continue accelerating to the
decceleration because the
amount of reaction at the peak here is still relatively modest.
So in terms of what's happening in acceleration I think
the situation is quite clear that here we're looking at
the nucleation and then the growth of C.S.H.
So on these slides, we can quite see at about two hours,
we can see these little tiny nuclei all the C.S.H.
Which are forming and then those nuclei grow over time.
And as they grow over time they grow in this
what we often call a kind of needle morphology,
Where this looks a little
bit like a sea urchin.
Now I'm going to use the term needles
but depending on the different conditions, sometimes they
can look more like furs also even here we can imagine
those needles are actually tapered foil,
so you know don't worry too much about
those those differences we can find
quite a lot of variation
but it's all this kind of out good growth.
People have been studying nucleation
growth for a long time. These
images
here summarize the theory of Avrami
and Avrami was one of the first people to really quantify
these processes.
I was wrong he was doing he was studying
solidifying methods and in solidifying method you have a liquid
and then these nuclei represented in here grow a form and then they grow
and the rate of growth is proportional to their surface.
So as first of all they get bigger the growth rate goes up
and then as these nuclei grow into each other
you can see the surface available for growth goes down so you get
this deceleration.
So he analyzed this process in quite some detail,
came up with some very powerful equations
and this just shows a couple of his equations.
And because this kind of form of reaction where
we have this peak this looks rather similar to what we've got in
cement paste.
For about fifty odd years, people have been trying to say
well can we apply this quantitative analysis to cement paste
and indeed because it's such a simple shape,
you can quite easily fit this to cement hydration.
but the problem is that then you come up with
parameters that have no physical meaning
and vary enormously from one cement to another.
So this really underlines the fact that to really understand the right
mechanism,
you have to do a very wide range of experiments
and you have to analyze those quantitative.
Now in terms of doing the quantitative analysis,
it's very useful to be able
to rely on computer models.
And one aspect which we need to well capture in computer models
is the fact that we have a very wide range of particle
sizes.
We have some cement particles that are about sixty microns
in size, some are less than a micron size
and this means that in a typical.
Well so this would be a typical box of one hundred microns,
we may have many millions of particles.
And this short here shows the more we call Mike.
Mike is this a model developed a G.P.S.
Fell by shushing Bishnoi and it has this cute little logo,
it's written like this
but that's because it's Mike for microstructure.
OK so we can use this modeling platform to test
different hypothesis.
The first hypothesis we tested was this classical
idea sometimes called Boundary nucleation
and growth, where we have our surface
which is alite,
we have the C.S.H.
Growing on the surface and the growth rate is proportional to the surface of the C.S.H.
So that eventually growth will slow down
when material from one grain impinges with the other.
If we look at the results from this
and what's quite important in these results
I'm going to show you, is that we tested this
or no range of particle sizes from the same alite.
So these numbers here, tells you the average particle size of the
different alite, but in fact we had the whole particle
size distribution wish we could simulate in the model.
And what you can see here is that in this morning
we can capture very well this accelerator a period
but after the peak we get a very poor
correspondence between the more the model shows
and what the experimental result says.
Basically we don't get the deceleration
and if we look at the screenshot of the model
and the peak,
You can see here there's a very small amount of product,
so it's support not surprising we're not getting
much impingement between the product.
So what can be an alternative?
Well classically,
many researchers have proposed that what happens at the peak
is that we switch the mechanism, we go from a
nucleation growth control mechanism,
to the fusion control mechanism.
And the idea is that we have our cement grain here,
we have our solution out here,
we have a product in between
and that either the water has to diffuse in,
all the products have to diffuse out properly both
but we don't know which one is rate limiting.
So that's again seems quite a nice hypothesis.
It's a hypothesis that fits very well in a number of other reaction
studies. And we can use our modeling platform
to look at that and here we see the results.
And our first glance this looks OK because you see the model
now fits fairly well with the experimental results
but and this is a very important
but, because we did the simulations all know this wide range of different particle sizes.
And we see if you get them all to fit,
we've got to vary all the fusion coefficientby ten times,
now this makes
absolutely no sense what so ever because this is
exactly the same alite with forming exactly the same C.S.H.
And there is absolutely no reason that
this diffusion question all that C.S.H.
Should change by an order of magnitude.
Clearly what this shows is you know
you can make a lot of mechanisms fit
but you have to go further to really see what can be the right theory.
So we really have to.
Abandon this idea of diffusion
and there are a number of other reasons why we should do this.
So here we have the first reason I showed in the last
slide that there
no reason why this diffusion coefficient should change by an order of magnitude
but also those of you who have perhaps looked at different ways
of calculation maturity will be familiar with the idea
that we can use a single activation energy
throughout that main hydration peak
and we wouldn't expect that if we had a transition in mechanism.
So if we went from a mechanism which is like
nucleation
and growth,
which is to do with bone breaking and making,
this would have a typical activation energy around forty k/j
per mole, which is typically have the same all of what we
find in cement pastes, well as transport control processes
such as diffusion, how much lower activation energy is less
than around twenty kilo joules per mole.
So there's no
evidence from this activation.
And thirdly, if we look at a micrograph, this is a taken one day,
so we know we're well past the the heat peak here.
And what we can see this is alite grain on the right here,
this is our C.S.H.
Form and we have got this kind of shell here
but we really cannot in any way defend that
the shell is acting as a diffusion barrier,
because if the shell was acting
as a diffusion barrier we'd know it now expect to
see this region of low density behind the shell,
we would expect this
to be right in contact with alite grain.
So this many reasons really are evidence
that diffusion is not becoming the
rate determining mechanism at this stage of the reaction.
Then with the work of Bishnoi, we really look at this formation
of product
and this formation of product you can see,
it's not really all that uniform
that's to say that the kind of an average
density out here is quite a bit less than
the density close to the particles.
And so we put forward a new hypothesis that C.S.H.
Was for first forming in a low density way
and then subsequently densifying.
Now because it's got this low density,
then it can occupy more space
and you can imagine to have impingement between the hydrates
much earlier than you would otherwise expect.
And this theory was developed quite rigorously and quantitatively
and we see from these results here that it really appears
to work very well and in 2009
we published this paper, where we put forward those nice hypothesis.
Unfortunately, as is often the case in science,
we then come to a counterexample
which really shows that this new theory
was not right either.
The critical experiment is this one which we did with Amalie Bazzoni
but has also been done by a number of other people,
where you can see we have a very different
water to cement ratio, so
here we have hydration with water to cement ratio 0.4, 0.8 point.
According to this densifying growth theory, we
would expect for the water cement ratio
0.8 that to be a lot more space and
therefore to have a lot more hydration before this downturn.
But in fact we don't see this we face a just a little bit more
hydration before we get this downturn so unfortunately
we have to abandon this new hypothesis.
Also in the thesis of Bazzoni,
But certainly we had another source of alite
which gave us a different a different perspective on this question.
And this was really where we had a lights
which on the one hand contained small amounts of zinc.
And on the other hand small amounts of magnesium
so we had the pure system magnesium and zinc.
And what you can see.
We in the calorimetry curves here that the presence of
lower amounts of the zinc,
gives you this first increase in the
amount of hydration that's occurring in this first heat evolution peak.
So there must be something different
that's occurring with the zinc dope sample, which is
telling us about what's controlling this main Heat
evolution peak.
So when we made them
or these health investigation by transmission electron microscopy,
what in fact we see here we see these needles that
are growing out from the C3S
Surface much longer in the case of zinc than
in the case of magnesium and the pure case.
And we could quantify that. So here we see the quantification
of the needles length you know don't know exactly the
mechanism
but we could see that the zinc is really incorporated
into the CSH stage, whereas the magnesium is not really being
incorporated to all, it's just occurring as these
little isolated crystals.
So this gave us a new hypothesis, yet
another new hypothesis that the idea is we get this C.S.H.
Growth in needles on the surface of the grain.
By the time you get to the peak the
surface is covered so no more needles can grow
and there's no more needles can
grow the rate of hydration starts slowing down
and you get the formation of inner product.
But as I've already said, the critical test of any hypothesis
is whether it works quantitatively.
And for this we're now working on a new model, which is called
the needle model which is being worked on by Alexandra
Musea in our lavinda minute.
And this hypothesis is we have CSH growth is Needles.
What's very very important is that all the parameters can
now come to experiment.
There's no fitting.
And what I'm going to show you here.
And because it's an algorithmic more or rather than a
Computer model, a model that works in terms of having a real
microstructure, we can also calculate much more difficult
complex form for the grains and
take account of the consumption of the small grains.
And when we do that you can see now in these different simulations.
This really works beautifully throughout the whole
range of different variations we've already seen.
It can really well
capture this water cement ratio variation
and it can really well capture the effect of the zinc in the open.
So hopefully, this is now the hypothesis which can be
validated.
Of course we're not at the end of the road because
there are important open questions. So if this mechanism is
controlled by these needles that grow
and then stop what's controlling this?
Unfortunately day we can't that question
but with work we have underway looking
at the much more atomistic level,
I think pretty confident we'll be able to
answer this in a year or so as time.
So let's come to the summary on this main peak the first
and foremost thing is that just because you can do occur
fitting that doesn't mean the hypothesis is right.
You can take
many many equations they had 'this simple form of peak
and you can they look right. If you go on to differentiate
between these different hypothesis you need to look at
hydration with a wide range of variables. You need to work
very water cement ratio/ particle size distribution look at
the door opens, all these different things a really
really important to give you the range to test your hypothesis.
And ideally you need to have physically measurable
parameters because if you can do that and if you can avoid.
The thinking step then you can really be much
more confident that your hypothesis is working.
And having followed that process over the last few years
we're now fairly confident that we can explain this by this
growth the needles to a critical length,
as me in the best hypothesis for this main hydration peak.