Hello and welcome back
In this module, we're going to look at the longer
term hydration.
Previously we've looked at the induction
period up to about three hours
then we've looked at the main hydration peak
and we've seen that this is controlled by nucleation and
growth of CSH.
Now we're going to look in the longer term.
And this period is really not been studied as anywhere
near in as much detail as has this induction period in the main
hydration peak. Perhaps because it's rather difficult
to study because in terms of what you can measure for example the
heat evolution is shown here,
there's not much going on.
Or at least it seems so
but that's very deceptive, because at this point here about
one day the degree of hydration would typically be about
fifty percent
and the amount of strength would be maybe twenty,
twenty five percent of the final strength.
So there is an awful lot
going on in this later period
here beyond the first day.
And in this module we're going to try
and look at what some of these things might be.
Although, I have to tell you now that we still
don't really know that much.
If instead of looking at Curves in the differential form,
as we saw previously, if we now we look at the intricate
curves, accumulative heat curve we can plot for example
the variation of the water cement ratio
and we can plot different mixtures with
different substitutes of course.
And we can kind of identify three different regimes.
We can identify this regime here which we've already looked at.
We've called this preriods
"periods one and two"
and we can see that even though the details of this
main hydration peak might vary a lot as we saw in the previous two
modules, it's fairly similar.
And then over here in the long term,
we also see a very similar behavior
for all the systems.
And we'll come to that at the end of this module
but at the minute we're calling this period
of the densification period for reasons I'll explain.
And then in the middle here, we see that this is where
we get the biggest variation for all these different systems
and what we've really done in these different systems
is vary the amount of space available for the hydrates to
deposit in
and this is why we call this middle regime,
which are called 3A here, we call this a
space controlled regime.
So basically what this means is that hydrates
are continuing to form
until they've used up all
the easily available space.
And this occurs amount about six days for a water cement
ratio of 0.4.
Now we get other very interesting
insights only this regime if we use this technique
called proton Nuclear Magnetic Resonance.
So what we do with Proton
Nuclear Magnetic Resonance is we depend on the
behavior of protons which are basically hydrogen atoms
and by applying a magnetic field,
we can align those little spins of these nuclei
and then we can remove the magnetic field
the spins relax they go back to the kind of
random orientation they were in
the first place and by looking at the timing of this relaxation,
we can make various deductions about the poor sizes.
And the real strength of this technique is that
we don't have to dry the sample.
So most techniques that been used
classically microstructure you have to dry the sample
before you look at it in this case is exactly the opposite in
fact the poor need to have
water in them to get the signal.
And what we can do we can do many different
measurements in situ from the same sample.
And here we see a sort of little schematic of a poor
structure and you see these big Pores and smaller pores
and the essential aspect is that we have
water molecules in these pores moving around
and if they hit the surface then they relax very very quickly.
So this means if we have water like you may have in a
bottle of water this will have a
relaxation time of about four seconds.
In as we move to smaller pores then because the
water will have a very high probability of
hitting the surface before
too long, we'll go to shorter relaxation times,
small poor the shorter relaxation time still
and the shortest relaxation times are for
bound water which is found in the crystalline hydrates.
And this is explained in a lot more detail in these references
that were given here.
These are results from the work of
Ana Muller.
And we can see how these
spectra evolve over time.
And what we can identify in the spectra is different
populations.
So we start with the shortest one with the shortest
relaxation time.
And by analogy with this diagram here the shortest
relaxation time is expected to come with water that's firmly bound
in crystals.
And this we can show to be the case by quantifying
the signal here, we can see that it corresponds to the water which is
in Portlandite and in ettringite.
And I should perhaps have said at the beginning here,
that what's important in this series of experiments in the spectra
is in fact we can quantitative measure all the water in the cement paste.
So this is the found water.
This has the
shortest relaxation time and as you see here it matches
really very very well with water in the calcium hydroxide
and the ettringite.
So logically the next shortish relaxation time
has to be coming from the interlayer water in the C.S.H.
So this is the interlayer water in the C.S.H.
and from analyzing the signal, we can see that
this is coming from dimensions of a round one nanometer, which
is roughly what we'd expect to be the
area for water in the interlayer the C.S.H.
So this next clear population we can
see here which starts a little bit bigger
and then comes down to this defined size.
Is in fact what we call the gel water.
When we looked at CSH we talked about the gel porosity
in those gel pores is the gel water,
and we see this has a quite well defined characteristic
size of about three to four nanometers.
And finally, the rest of the water over here is now
capillary waters.
So going back to the beginning, we can see in the
beginning we start with just capillary water,
then we start to form C.S.H.
And then finally the gel Pores
and at the end in these experiments
which are done with Seal pace,
we have very little capillary water.
So we can look in more detail at how those
populations evolve over time in terms of their amount
and also in terms of their size.
So if we look at the capillary water,
what we see is over the first day of courses
corresponding to this main heat evolution Peak
we've been talking about,
the amount of capillary water decreases very
sharply and also it's size increases.
So it starts off with the characteristic
size of a round seventy three microns
and here already after one day,
it's gone down to about ten microns nanometers.
And then all of to this point here at
about two days, we see that the amount decreases
but the sign is no longer decreases.
The size really stays constant as a size
of aboiut eight nanometers.
And because of this consistency of size,
we then decided to give a new name
to this area we call this interhydrate pores.
Now why do we call it interhydrate pores,
because if you look in the T.M. and
You see these needles of C S.H
We talked about in the previous modules,
you can see between these needles,
we have spaces of about eight Nanometers.
And we really feel now that this is making up
most of the capillary pore space of a well
cured mature cement paste
is this very complex spaces between these C.S.H. Needles
We can see a similar picture by using a very
different technique which is mercury intrusion poor symmetry.
And many of you have probably heard a lot of
negative things about mercury in trees and poor symmetry but
when we've compared Mercury intrusion pore symmetry to proton
Nanoma, we actually have now a lot of evidence
that mercury is giving Mercury intrusion pore symmetry is giving us a
very good picture of what's happening in the poor space
and so long as you dry your samples correctly
and I really need to stress this point,
because if you dry your samples by putting them in the oven,
you form a lot of cracks,
you get any or kind of thing by M.I.P
If you do it by this technique we use which is called
solvent exchange, where you dry your samples in
then you can get really nice reproducible results.
And what you see is that this breakthrough diameter here
when the mercury really starts to penetrate into the sample,
this is going down quite rapidly during the first few days
but by the time
we're at about three days or
or fourteen days then after that point it doesn't go down anymore.
So it goes down to a certain critical pore
entry size
and then it doesn't go down more even though the overall amount
of the capillary porosity is continuing to decrease.
So we
think this fixed Critical pore entry size here,
is the same as the interhydrate space we saw here.
Now if we look at what's happening in the hydrates,
we can now look at the Interlayer water.
So the interlayer water is
between these sheets of C.S.H.
Shown in red here. And unsurprisingly during
the main hydration this is going up quite fast
and then subsequently it's going up more slowly.
We add the gel water as we see here
and at the beginning in the acceleration
in the main hydration peak the gel water
is going up in parallel
in the same ratio as the amount of insulin water
but from this point at 2.2 days in this case of
this white cement we see that the gel water is really
patterning.
And a very long ages it maybe even goes down a little bit.
So the amount of gel space, Gel pores is not a constant
amount in a world C.S.H.
The amount of gel porosity varies if formed
we form a lot of the beginning
and then really no more after a certain time.
Very probably, this is related to formation of outer C.S.H.
Those needles we've been talking about quite a lot
and then afterwards when we get the in a C.S.H.
We really see that this doesn't contain gel porosity.
And from all these measurements, we can get now
quite a lot of more detail about what's happening in our C.S.H.
We can look for example at the density
and we can look at the density of this kind of solid part,
these of these nano crystalline regions we talked about
quite a few lectures ago and we can look at the amount
that's forming in the bulk as we see with the gel porosity here.
And the solid has quite a constant density over time of
about just below 2.7, 2.8. Whereas
the bulk
the average density is increasing because the proportion of gel pores
is decreasing.
So at the beginning we have quite a
low density below one point eight.
And by the time we're getting to a high degree of hydration,
we're seeing that this is going to have the density of
about 2 to 2.1. which is very much in line with the kind
of densities that have been estimated from other techniques.
We can look also at the amount of water contained in the C.S.H.
So again for the solid nano crystalline regions,
the amount of water content is around 2 for each solid chain
unit, whereas for the bulk the amount of water on average
is decreasing because we have less water proportionally in the gel pores.
So from all this, we need to really make an update of
the repetition of the solid volume over time, so this
was done already about sixty years ago by powers.
And he measured the proportions along times
and then said
"Well OK I'm just going to draw straight lines
as a function of the degree of hydration".
And we find very good agreement between our repetition of
the volumes along ages here with what powers found except
that now we can differentiate the solid that he just
measured as one single hydrate into C.S.H.
Here
and calcium hydroxide and ettringite here.
The main difference we see is the amount of
gel water is not a linear function
of the degree of hydration.
But it increases very rapidly at the beginning
and then stays constant there after.
So let's go back to cummulative heat curves,
to these different stages.
We've looks in this middle zone zone three A
here and we see that this is controlled
by the amount of space available
but what's happening in this very long term?
Well again we can analyze the slope of
these curves
and we really don't see any indication that it
fits with the kind of kinetics we would expect from diffusion.
What we could hypothesise the station, I stress this is very very
tense to versa as an idea for a mechanism is that what
perhaps we have we have initially C.S.H.
Like this,
where we have there are none across lime regions gel pores
and then a very long ages those gel pores are
getting filled there by extra layers of C.S.H.
So the amount of extra hydration between
here and here is really very very small
but it's contributing to this densification
and to some gain in mechanical properties.
So I stress this is still quite a tentative idea here
but needs to be worked on more in the long term.
So to summarize what we've seen in this lecture we've looked at what's
some ideas of what's happening in the long term.
And what really seems to be important certainly
in the first few days, is is the amount of space available for the
hydrate form which a term determining the rate of reaction.
and after about few days, say about six days,
this is a typical Wall to cement ratio of 0.4, We only
have pores below quite a small size which are left.
And the small size does not allow the growth of hydrates in the
classic way that we've talked about previously.
And this kind of
Slowing down of the reaction then means we transit
to a regime in which we have really more densification of the
C.S.H.
And that's really highlighted by the
studies we've done on Proton
NMR,
which also indicate that we need to
refine the powers model, because the
amount of the capillary and gel porosity
are not linear functions of the degree of reaction.
So after these few days we get this very slow reaction,
which the mechanisms are still unclear
and still are subject of ongoing work.
So now we've really seen the mechanisms,
we've been concentrating most of all on
the silicate phases
and what remains now is to look at
the reactions of the alluminates phases,
how this fit in this will be in the next
module.
and then finally we'll bring this all together
to look at how the microstructure can be visualized in the scanning
electron microscope for example.
So thank you and see you next time.