Hello and welcome back.
So in the last module, we looked at the kinetics occurring
in the main hydration peak
and the mechanism for that.
And before going to look at what happens in the long term in
this more show we're going to look at what's called the
filler effect, this is the impact that supplementary
cementitious materials have on the hydration,
not because they are
themselves reacting, but because of their physical
presence in the mixture.
So during the first day
or so most supplementary materials are not reacting,
their physical presence affects the hydration of the clinker
and this is what we mean by the filler effect.
So we can see that by looking at this data here coming from different
mixtures.
So the first one in black is the reference cement
and then we took this reference cement
and we mixed it either with fifty forty percent
quartz as shown in blue here.
Always forty percent slag as is shown in orange here.
And then the slag and the quartz were chosen
but they had about the same particle size distribution
as you can see by these images here.
So we can see in the first
day that when we take this calorimetry curves
and we normalize them by the cement content, that's very important
this is just as if there was one hundred grams of
cement, reference cement in all cases. You can see that the
reaction of that cement is enhanced in both cases.
It's enhanced
by the quartz,
it's enhanced by the slag
and pretty much in the same way in the two cases.
Which really emphasizes that it's a purely
physical effect because the
quartz is not reactive.
We've checked that the amount of reaction
even at twenty eight days is barely measurable.
After the first day or so we can see now that
the slag reactivity starts to be higher
and this is indicating this is actually the slag itself reacting.
So over here we have the filler effect,
here we have later on the chemical reaction.
When we look into the micrograph, Why did we do this?
The reason we did this was that most people have proposed that this
filler effect is coming from the extra
surface providing extra nucleation sites to C.S.H.
And when we look in the um, This seems to be the case.
So this was a system of cement
and quartz there hydrating together,
so the pictures are taken exactly the same sample
and here we see a cement grain,
you can see these little nuclei forming on the surface
and then you can see
this needles of C.S.H. forming.
And here we see the quartz grains
It looks really the same.
We got they C.S.H.
Nucleons surface from very early times
and then from those little nuclei C.S.H. Is forming.
So the hypothesis seems to be correct.
However,
when we look at it now more quantitatively it's not so good.
So this graph here shows how the slope is to say the the
slope of that acceleration part varies with the amount of surface.
OK So this is the reference Portland cement down here.
OK and if we increase the amount of surface by two times,
so here we got twice the amount of surface,
but we've only increased that acceleration slope by twenty percent.
So it was just the fact we had extra surface just
doesn't add up because we would expect it to be twice as much there,
which is clearly not the case.
What can we suppose?
Well if we now go back to look at
Mortars versus cement pastes,
cement paste where we just have water
and cement grains versus mortars where we have
water cement grains and sand,
we can see a similar acceleration
or increase of that acceleration slope.
And if we look at the pictures in the S.C.M,
We can see that here we've got just the plain cement,
we've got some bits of C.S.H.
but Also some bits of quite smooth surface.
Here in the mortar we've got a much more confused picture with many more
small nuclei on the surface of the cement grains.
Just by the presence of those large sand grains.
And this picture here looks very very
similar to what we see in the quartz cement system.
So what we can suppose is
that in the mortar system,
the presence of the sand grains during in the mixing phase,
is knocking those little nuclei off the surface, it's
redistributing these nuclei through the space
and by that shearing effect
and redistributing the nuclei I then
we're getting more nuclei on the surface
and we get then we get to accelebration effect.
And again we can test this quantitatively. So now we can
look at a variety of different systems of different courses
with slag with fly ash
and we can plot all these results against the relative
to the different share rate between the particles.
And we can see as the shearing rate is going up,
the slope values is going up.
So this is now aren't our idea of why we get this physical filler effect.
And as we see on this graph, the slag and the fly ash
Really act in very much the same way as we get with the quartz.
However, if we now go through the effect with limestone
we see that with limestone we get a very different reaction.
We're getting much much more accelerating effect from the
limestone, even when we do have the same shear rates.
And now if we go in the S.C.M.
a look at this effect, we can see that on the limestone
grains,
we've got this very very dense covering of nuclei.
Much much denser than we have for the cement grains.
And what is serious is that the
low but measurable dissolution of the limestone grains is
increasing the calcium concentration close to the surface
and that helps to stimulate the new creation of C.S.H
And once before and that much more
dense number of nuclei here,
then these grow as this dense
or clusters of needles.
So this really emphasizes how limestone
can have this very particular effect.
So if we just summarize that module here,
Although they are inert these supplementary cementitious
materials do have a very significant
effect on the new creation growth of C S H, We have a small
increase in new creation sites due to high shearing
conditions.
But some surfaces for example calcite,
also favor the nucleation of C S H
and change the growth path.
So now we've looked at the main hydration peak
and what happens with supplementary cementitious materials.
Next time we'll look at the longer term hydration.
Thank you.