So welcome this is the last module
in the sequence about hydration reactions
and in this one we bring together everything
we've seen in the previous modules to
look at how this results in the
microstructure we have in hardened cement pace.
Now we're not going to talk about
here is of course properly regulated
cements enough soluble calcium sulphate
added, And as we saw in the last module
This means that the illuminated, main aluminum reactions occurs of the
silicate reaction.
And it therefore means of hydration
and structure development is really dominated by
the reaction of C3S4A light.
Now this is the
Calorimetry heat evolution curve, we've seen several
times before, we talked about the mechanisms that control the
reactions throughout this. First of all the the
induction period controlled by the buildup of iodine solution,
then
acceleration deceleration controlled by
the growth of the C.S.H.
Needles on the surface and
finally the slow ongoing reaction.
And just to relate that to the physical properties, the setting
of the cement is usually occurring at middle to beginning
of the acceleration period. Now let's look at
how this heat evolution curve is linked to
what we see Micro structurally.
So if we first consider the case for the silicates,
what we see at the end of the induction period
is we get this
first formation of C.S.H. Starting to grow
on the surface of the grades.
And then that C.S.H.
Develops rather very rapidly as these needles
so by ten hours we see these long needles
from the surface.
And then the hydration goes on
and finally we end up with the microstructure like this,
where we have the cement grains which are embedded in this
matrix mainly of C.S.H. and.
Atrinite, which is all this stuff here,
and then some calcium hydroxide
which is this stuff here.
Now if we now add in the Aluminite, So we have portland
cement rather than alite during
the very early reaction of the alite we can form some.
Very small etronite needles
but this again I'd like to stress that it's not
those very small needles that are inhibiting
the reaction, its the
absorption of sulphate ions
on the surface.
And this absorption of sulphate ions on the illuminates
suppresses the eliminate reaction so that it allows the
silicates to react,
so here we see the silicates
reacting as before and then
when we come to the shoulder peak here we see
very clearly the second growth of etronite
we see these long, etronite needles which
are formed during that shoulder peak.
And then as we go on we may not always see it
but in this case
we've got a small hydration hump here
and this is associated with the formation of the monosulfate.
Now another aspect I want to mention is this formation
of so-called Hadley grains. Now Hadley was a student
working in the 70s who noticed that sometimes you could see
that you had these kind of
shells which appeared empty.
And in fact we see that generally if we look at
these transmission electron micrographs,
we can see even from very early
ages even as early as five hours,
we can see we get the small separation
of the shell and the reacting grain.
So what happens is we seem
to form this Layer of hydrates here.
And then they and
Hydra scraping goes on reacting
but the products are deposited outside,
probably because we have this preferential
growth of the C.S.H.
Needles that we
discussed a few modules back.
And this is just another micrograph this time
taken with best electrons, where you can see just how generalized these
gaps are around the hydrous grace.
Now we don't really know exactly
why these form like this,
but we can say that it's very much
amplified by the presence of illuminates.
We get a small separation in the case of pure C3S
but it's very much more apparent
when we have a Portland cement
when we have the city case
illuminates reacting together.
And here are some other ones pictures again by
transmission electron microscope.
We can see that if we now have a
very careful specimen preparation.
We can see this very kind of fragile looking share of hydrates
but in fact the space in between, its not
completely empty. It seems to be filled with a very
dispersed diffuse product.
And another interesting aspect is this
and hardest grain here is not reacting evenly
on the surface that's actually quite deep,
itching along certain
Crysler graphic directions.
So what happens to these
separated shells, all these have the grains over time really
depends on the size of the grains.
If we have very small
grains,
Five microbes or less then these will
very quickly react during the main hydration peak
and there leave this kind of shell of hydrates
which persists in definitely.
If the grain is a bit bigger, so in the second case
here we have a grain maybe about ten to fifteen
microbes then after
the main heat evolution peak, this
hydrous material will continue to react
but it may leave a small
shell hole in the middle.
And finally if we have large grains greater than
say about fifteen to twenty microns,
then during the later hydration
this separation between the shell and the enhydrous
grain completely fills in and disappears.
And we can see those in this micrograph here, if you look
carefully at this micrograph you can see many little hollow
shells which the small grains which completely reacted.
So we've got this one here for example, we've got one down here
was just right larger and therefore
we've got a slightly thicker shell,
we've got another one here
and the more you look you can really see
that these little hollow shells everywhere.
But for the lower to grains notably this one in
the middle here, this separation has completely filled then
and we get this thick rim of in a product.
We can still see though that the surface
of the reacting enhydrous grain
is still quite rough.
This roughness that emerged really quite early
on is persisting because it seems we can have
probably defects along Crystal graphic directions,
which make that the more soluble.....
Of course in
this micrograph we can also see that of course we got
the reaction of the alite here we've got the interstitial faces
the ferrite and the illuminated.
Now close to the surface the alluminate
has all disappeared,
but here where it embedded in the ferrite,
we can still see small regions of illuminated phases
that have not reacted yet.
These aspects are brought together in this drawing,
I made quite some years ago now, which really summarized the micro
structural development around one grain of cement.
Another aspect which is important to talk about is to look at the
different phases, so really we very much emphasize
the reactions of c3S And then of Aluminite because these are
the ones that react most. So in this graph here you see greater
from the literature for the form A phases so we have
alite Here, we have aluminate here, Belite here and ferrite here
and then we have very similar data for four different
cements which were started in the Ph D. Of the Knesset Kocaba.
Now what's very important is you can see that
the Alite is reacting most early on, that's to say
one day we have degrees of reaction between
forty percent and seventy percent. Really very very high.
And then that's increasing at say about
twenty eight days to about eighty percent
and as we go on to ninety one hundred days,
it's approaching one hundred percent.
The illuminate reaction, also very fast.
You see we have high degrees of reaction one
day, again between forty
and eighty percent
and in some cases it's very quickly going up to
one hundred percent in just a few days.
In other cases where
it's more imbedded in ferrite for example
then it may take somewhat longer.
So now we come to the other two
phases we haven't discussed at all
and we see in general the reaction of these
two is much slower. Notably the Belite.
And this is very important. Like I said several times
before that it doesn't make any sense to produce high Blite
cements because of the slow reactivity of the Belite
But we all must see that there really
is this interaction between Alite and Belite.
That that's to say that while we have just fast reaction of
Alite as we see here, the reaction to be light is hardly
happening at all.
So Alite reaction actually suppresses the Blite reaction.
And it's really only after ten days
and more that when the daylight is more
or less all reacted that the Blite reaction
is starting to have any impact at all.
Fairly, it is a kind of intermediate case in fact
we see the one day the degrees of reaction may be quite high about
forty percent, that's similar to the illuminates
but then it really slows down.
And the reason for this is that this low solubility of ion in alkaline
solution so that offer a bit of the ferrite
faces acted you kind of clogged up the surface with first
of all amorphous high hydroxide, which really stops the
rest of the Phase reacting. That's just summarized
here that we have little reaction before ten days
and that's actually thermodynamics control,
because of the reaction of the Alite phase,
it suppresses the dissolution of the Belite phase.
The Alluminates is fast, but it can be slowed
down by the presence of ferrite grey cements.
And the ferrite is slow but it can't
quite be significant even at one day.
Now if we look at the reaction of these phases in the microstructure,
the Belite often gives us this very interesting
pattern of reaction we can see with the certain
strayations have reacted, while others have not reacted.
And the reason for this is you general cooling of Belite,
you get these multiple phase transformations,
which often occur by twinning
and then so you tend to accumulate
in some twins and not in others
and it's the generally the parts which have
the high solute content, which are more reactive
and can react.
So you see that the depth the reaction
here is about is several microns
but then we store water kernel
in the middle which is on reacted.
And this you can see even in very whole cement,
this micrograph here on the right comes from
a piece of concrete that's
about thirty years old and you can see these large
clinker grain, it was a cluster of belite, this is quite typical
and cements.
You want to minimize these grains
but they do occur and you see in this cluster of
Belite that quite a bit of the Belite
still hasn't reacted even after thirty years.
Now in that micrograph,
his is like a zoom out of the one before.
Now the only unreactive phases we see in this
thirty year old concrete, are really belite
and of course the ferrite phase. This is the ferrite phase,
these bright areas here.
in three look at this Best gas electron
image which is what we see in the previous slide,
it appears that the ferret hasn't reacted even though
when we go to the X. Ray diffraction, it shows us
that with a ferrite phase has disappeared.
And what Happens is a the alluminated calcium
components kind of leach out,
they disappear and form the normal hydrates
and even this relic of
ferritic siliceous hydrogarnent.
And this is what has been seen in quite old pace
even after a few months or so,
but the dominant phase from the
ferrite is this siliceous hydrogarnet.
Now coming back to the overall microstructure,
we've shown this micrograph several times
and what I want to do here is to remind you that this
hydrate phase that's between the grains everything that isn't
calcium hydroxide is really a very fine mixture of C.S.H.
With ettringite, with more L.F.M.
phases, monocarbonate, monosulfate, really mixed
at this very fine scale below one micron.
and we can see further evidence of this by looking
at these microanalysis, if we make microanalysis
and then we plot them on these graphs of alumina calcium
versus silica to calcium
or so for to calcium versus alluminate to calcium, we can see
that what we have here, we have this cluster of points, we see
here
and we see here which is C S H, But the fact we get points
extending along these lines is really showing us that we have
mixtures either of calcium hydroxide with
Portlandite with calcium had rock side along this line
or with C S H with ettringite
or monosulfate
and we can see more clearly in this graph down here
that we can differentiate much more easily between whether we have
mixtures with ettringite and monosulfate. So here
this is at twenty eight days, we see we still got
quite a lot of ettringite intermixed with the C.S.H.
A little bit of monosulfate and
as we go on first to one year
and then to three years,
we still see this very gradual shift
and as further ferrite probably reacts to now getting
much more points along the monosulfate line,
but we always see this persistence of
this the spread this cluster C.S.H.
Point due to the intermixing and you know I want
to emphasize that what we analyze here in the S.C.M.
We're always analyzing a volume of one to two microns in dimension,
which is why we see together these
several different Phases.
So just summarize this microstructure part,
what we saw at the beginning was the same as what we
saw in the reaction of the alluminate part that the presence
of sulphate modifies the reaction we get a smaller
initial reaction and then this
in the long induction period.
When the sulphate in solution is exhausted,
we get the second burst of aluminate formation.
And then finally in the monosulfate
monocarbonate formation.
And what we also saw in this model, we talked a little bit
about hadley grain formation where we get these
separated shells we talked about
the rates of reaction of the different phases
and really emphasize that the belite reaction is very
slow only significant health for about ten days because this
inhibited by alite.
Talked about the ferrite, seems to be on reactiveness
certainly not move much it stays in the same place
but in fact seems to react to form this
poorly crystalline for this siliceous hydrogarnet.
And then at the end we emphasize the
fact with the aluminated phases where the ettringite or A.F.M.
phases are mainly find
dispersed within the C.S.H.
So that's the last one in this series about hydration.
I hope you found something interesting
and enjoy the rest of the course on
characterization methods.
Thank you very much.