OK So hello and welcome back.
So far we've talked mainly about hydration of the calcium silicate systems.
In this module we're
going to talk about what happens with the aLuminate systems.
Many of you probably already know that if you just take
tricalcium Aluminite
and you add water, then what you get is a very very
violent reaction.
You get these large platy hydrate
and the result of that is that we
have what's called very rapid stiffening or flash set.
Now this shows some actual pictures of the reaction of C3A.
You can see either by the transmission
micrograph here or in this scanning electron microscope
you can see these platy hydrates.
and these precis hydrates are normally
described as C4AH10 or C2AH8.
These are a metastable AFM
phases and over time they will transform to the hydrogarnet phase.
So that's what happens without sulphate
but that's not really what we're interested in
for the purposes of cement.
Because of course in cement we have gypsum
and the reason for adding this gypsum is to control
this reaction of the alluminate phase.
So here we see the pattern of
reaction with sulphate. This is an experiment
where there was 40% of sulphate, 400% C3A
And that's roughly
or even a bit lower, the same as the sulphate C3A ratio
you would have in cement because typical Portland Cement
contain around six to eight percent C4A
and around five percent gypsum.
And here we can see that we have a pattern of reaction
where we have the last initial peak.
And then we have this very long period,
Aired more than a day in which
there's almost nothing happening
and then we have this second peak here.
OK so this period in which there's nothing
happening is extremely important
because we need to have this period of long
period of induction to allow the silicate to react.
Now most textbooks say that the reason for this
long induction period is because we have the
formation of ettringite.
Now we do have the formation of ettringite,
we can see in this picture here,
these little rods, these ettringite,
but these are not forming a barrier,
you know it would be like trying to block water with
or a dam of suigetit.
The water can infiltrate through the spaces between the rod.
So this is not the reason why the
reaction slows down and in fact other experiments have shown
that the real reason is because we have sulfate ions
absorbing directly on the surface of the C3A,
which slow down the dissolution of the of the C3A.
Then in this case after about two days,
we get the second reaction
and during the second reaction,
we get the formation of this phase
calciummonosulphure alluminate.
Now if we look at the chemical equations of these reactions,
the formation of extreme right is usually written like this
we have C3A with the gypsum
and water which forms this complicated formula here of ettringite,
we discussed a few modules back,
but in fact we should always remember that like all hydration
reactions in cement, the reactions really going through a
solution.
We have calcium and alluminate ions sulfate ions and
and hydroxide ions which all come
together to form this mineral ettringite.
And in fact these calcium ions here don't necessarily
come from the alluminate phase,
they could come from the C3S
For example.
And I really want to stress that again a common myth
in many textbooks is this idea you can get top of chemical
formation of ettringite
and this is really absolute nonsense because the crystal structure
of this phase is so completely different from what
you have in the enhydrous materials.
There is absolutely no way this is possible.
And then the second reaction here, can be described as a reaction of C3A
with some of the ettringite already
formed, to give us this calcium monosulphur aluminate.
So we see that for the reaction of C3A to continue,
some of the ettringite gets used up to form monosulfate.
But not all the ettringite disappears.
So this micrograph that here clearly shows that
we still got a lot of ettringite in this space out.
Here whereas inside this hydrate shell
we've got see these plates of monosulphur aluminates.
So it's not all the
ettringite that disappears.
As we talked about in the previous module,
Nowadays we have usually small additions of limestone in the cement
and the small additions of limestone means that instead of forming
monosulfate which we see here in the cement without limestone,
what we actually form is now Hemi or monocarbon aluminate.
So generally
Hemi and monocarbon aluminates are replacing
monosulfate in most cements you see today.
You won't really be able to
see any difference in terms of the micro graphs here,
because the morphology of hemimonocarbon aluminate is very
similar to what we have with monosulfate.
We describe the differences between these A.F.M.
phases in the previous model on the aluminate hydrates.
That's not the end of the story because
when you put the alite and the C3A together,
you get quite a lot of complex interactions.
So this blue curve here
shows the heat evolution we get from a synthesized clinker,
which composed of alite and C3A but no ferrite
And the pure C3A and gypsum on its own.
And what we see in the mixture, we can actually identify three peaks
which are related to the reaction of the aluminate phases.
We can see this kind of shoulder peak which we call A1,
then we can see this quite pronounced peak A2,
And finally this is rather small in defined peak,
which we call A3.
Now this a one peak
has often been said to be the formation of monosulphate
but that's actually not correct as we're going to see.
So before we go into that in more detail,
the important point to emphasize is the need to
have enough gypsum in your
mixture, in order to make sure that the aluminate reactions
or the main Aluminite reactions are occurring after the silicate reactions.
So here we see these same mixtures with progressively
larger amounts of gypsum, and as we add more
and more gypsum, you see this very strong peak here
shifts later in a different time.
Now if we have very low or too low
amounts of gypsum, then you see this big
aluminate peak occurs before the silicate peak.
And as a consequence, that silicate peak which was
here in the properly sulfated once it gets
shifted to much later ages
and it's much lower.
So this violent reaction of the aLuminate
really inhibits the reaction of the silicate phases
and will be very damaging in terms of strength development.
So this is very very important that we need a proper amount
of sulfate to make sure that this main Aluminite peak
is well of the silicate peak.
In this case here, it would be
preferable to go for this system here where
which is four point one percent gypsum,
where you see the large peak is
occurring really well after the silicate peak.
If we went for this one here we would have a a risk that we could
destabilize this sulfation when
we have any admixtures in the system.
And this is a very common problem
particularly in North America where people.
Adding not only admixtures but often
supplementary cementitious materials like fly ash
at the concrete stage, and when you have all these
things coming together, you can quite easily destabilize the reactions
and have this aluminate reaction occurring too early,
with the consequence of really impeding the reaction of the silicate.
So let's come back now to this peak A1.
And here we see the calorimetry output,
we can see this show repeat just here this A1 peak
and then this A2 peak here.
Now it's really quite complex what's happening.
If we look at the soul of gypsum which is
this green line here, we can see
that the solid gypsum is more
or less to exhausted just at the point where
we start to help the onset of this A1 shoulder peak.
But, even though the solar gypsum seems to been exhausted,
we can see that during this a one peak here, the main solid
phase that's forming is in fact still ettringite.
And see here on this yellow curve,
the amount of ettringite is continuing to go up.
And it's not really till somewhat later we can see
significant formation of the monosulfate, more associated with
this A2 peak.
So how can this be? How can it be that even though
the solid gypsum has been exhausted, we can still go
on forming ettringite?
Well the reason is this that sulfate can be
absorbed on the calcium silicate hydrate.
So during the acceleration part of the curve,
the silicate is reacting. It's forming C.S.H.
and As it's forming C.S.H,
because the Sulphate in solution is quite high,
quite a lot of it gets absorbed on the C.S.H.
Here you can see Measurements taken in the
SEM of the ratios between sulphate and calcium in the C.S.H.
So we can see here on the sulfate on the C.S.H.
Is quite high
and then as we come through this A1 peak you can
see it's really dropping.
So this is the extra source of sulphate
that we needed to keep forming ettringite as
we're seeing in the previous slide here.
Let's come back to this peak here.
We can now really confirm that this
is A1 peak is the formation of ettringite
and this a to peak is the formation of monosulfate.
And it's also important to observe that
this impact of sulfate being absorbed on the C.S.H.
Also changes the time of this A2 peak, compared to a
pure system.
So here we see what was happening in a binary
mixture of C3A And forty percent gypsum.
We had this model so fate peak at about fifty hours
and now in this mixture, Where we've got the equivalent
of more than sixty percent of gypsum compared to the C3A
This is A2 peak is only
about twenty five thirty hours.
And the reason for that it's come moved up here is
that a lot of the sulfate is lost to the system because it
gets absorbed on the C.S.H.
So we've got quite a lot of complex interactions and
you may have noticed I haven't yet said anything about the P.K.3
because we still don't
really know why we have this Peak here,
it's not really been possible to associate that with any of this reaction.
So what are we seeing in this
module is known very important that the sulfate present
from the addition of gypsum, more drastically modifies the
reaction of the aluminate and the ferrite phases.
Get a small initial reaction during which
sulfate ions are absorbed on the surface of the
illuminate and then induction period
and what's important is that this induction period
must be long enough to allow the silicate to react.
If it's not long
enough, you'll inhibit the silicate reaction and
get very big problems of strength development.
And then the solid gypsum is slowly reacting and
when the sulfate in solution is exhausted,
you get a second burst of the aluminate reaction
but you still forming a tree night with sulfate that
was previously absorbed on the C.S.H.
And then later typically after a few days,
we form calcium aluminate, monosulfate or more typically
Hemimonocarbonate aLuminate
when we have small amounts of limestone in the cements.
So that was the last module on the reaction kinetics
and then the final one in this group are hydration,
We'll talk about bringing all this together to look at the
microstructure formation.
Thank you.