Hi. My name is Zhangli Hu.
In previous session, you have a knowledge about cement hydration
including phases assemblage and the microstructure evolution.
In this section, I will give you a bit more detailed
information about the Heat release of cement hydration.
Most specifically in a practical point of view,
we will have a closer look at the placation of isothermal
calorimetry in Cement field.
To make goal of this module is to introduce two DAB lows
and two etchs focusing on bridging the isothermal
calorimetry resides with the hydration
characteristics of cement.
Two Dablows are; those are what is Isothermal Calorimetry
and why do we use it in cement field.
Two etch represent;
how do we perform a calorimetry test
and how do we treat the data in
order to get the information we want?
Calorimetry is the measurement of
heat and heat production rate.
There are several different kinds of
calorimetry are commonly used in cement field,
Isothermal Calorimetry is one of them.
Besides this one,
which we will mainly focus on today,
techniques such as Adiabatic
and semiadiabatic calorimetry,
solution calorimetry and
differential scanning calorimetry.
techniques such as Adiabatic
and semiadiabatic calorimetry,
solution calorimetry and
differential scanning calorimetry.
All can be seeing in the
applications in cement field.
The first of two types or three kinds of Calorimetres are
the most frequently used calorimetic methods.
All can be seeing in the
applications in cement field.
The first of two types or three kinds of Calorimetres are
the most frequently used calorimetic methods.
Both of them are quantifying the hydration kinetics
and the way for realizing it is different
In Isothermal Calorimetre, The heat
production rate is directly measured.
That's why it is also
called heat conduction calorimetry.
While the semiadiabatic
calorimetry for example
is isolated and temperature is
the signal which is being recorded
and later transformed
to the right of him to release.
The advantage adiabatic calorimetry is
sized isolation as the same in semiadiabatic.
The calorimeter is also
surrounded by other adiabatic shop
and the flow of heat from
the specimen is prevented.
The easiest way to distinguish them are the
different time, temperature trajectories and sample sizes.
As indicated in the figure shown here,
temperature is controlled to be constant
in isothermal calorimetry
While in other kinds of calorimeters, the temperature is evolving.
Small samples such as cement pastes are commonly used in
isothermal calorimetry,
while in others examples like mortars and concrete are often used.
Let's have a look at the
instruments for isothermal calorimetry.
There are several commercial instrument brands.
We will use ten air, produced by TA instruments
company in your house as an example.
If you order an isothermal calorimetry,
it basically looks like a sealed box.
It is composed of a body of channels for samples
and operating temperature control panel
If you inside, then we can see
different parts of the instruments.
These three of these are more used
for getting our thermal state of environment.
Principly the most important part of the calorimetry
is the heat collector place where we circle with a red ring.
If we zoom in on this part, we can see samples and references
are placed in a heat flow sensor and both are on top of a heat sinc.
The heat is produced by the sample will be collected
by the censor as heat is conducted through the heat sink.
Placed in a thermal environment
And this moment we can start to ask ourselves
why do we want to use these instrument?
Calorimetry is a heat mattering machining,
it is actually a Generactic way of studying processes.
All processes, physical, chemical and biological
are generally related to enthalpy change.
In addition, Cement hydration is an exothermic reaction which
are associated with hydration of different main clinker phases with water.
The pictures on the right side are typical
curves we can obtain from calorimetry measurements.
In cement field, isothermal calorimety is often
used on these purposes
such as following hydration processes, adjusting gypsum
content of checking the pozzolanic reaction
of the supplementary cementitious materials.
From now on we will go through all the
steps for performing a calorimetry test.
In order to give a vivid explanation,
some videos have been inserted in the module.
Before we can perform a test, making sure that
the instrument is in a good condition is very important.
This can be done by calibration.
Isothermal calorimetry is actually a very stable instrument
but proper calibration will help to significantly reduce noise.
This can be done by calibration.
Based on heat flow matchment principle,
the thermal P is proportional to the voltage
signal from the sensor U.
This can be done by calibration.
Based on heat flow matchment principle,
the thermal P is proportional to the voltage
signal from the sensor U.
As indicated in the equation, to establish their
relationship, two parameters near to be determined.
By their calibration coefficient
baseline, and baseline for the U0.
Baseline is measured by electrical calibration.
usually we do these every three months with the software.
U zero is a signal with no heat
produced in the sample but a referencing side.
The calibration should be done when we
change the temperature, the file or samples.
There is another calibration called time constant,
which is typically one hundred to one thousand seconds.
The calibration should be done when we
change the temperature, the file or samples.
There is another calibration called time constant,
which is typically one hundred to one thousand seconds.
This calibration is not necessary for cement hydration
since the timescale of cement hydration is much
longer than this time constant.
Complete isothermal calorimetry measurement
is composed of two main steps.
First step is preparing the reference and performing
a baseline.
The second a step is casting the specimens and starting the experiments.
There are basically two ways
for prepare in the specimen.
So-called ex-situ and in-situ.
As the name implies, in the case of ex-situ,
specimens are cast externally and being poured inside of
the glass amper.
In the case of the insitu, the specimens are mixed with
the L-shaped mixer inside of the amper placed in the channel holes.
In order to get good reproducibility,
ex-situ your preparation will be shown in this section.
First thing we need to do now is
to select a reference and prepare it.
The principle for choosing a reference is that the reference
should have no heat production during temperature change.
Commonly used references are
water and quartz samples.
please remember to not use old hydrated cement samples,
since the hydration of cement even when
it is mattered will not be ended completely
To ensure a stable baseline and reduce background noise,
the sample
and reference amp polls show to have the same thorough no response.
This is the draw for calculating the mass of the reference.
Here is an example of calculating a reference for ten grams of
cement paste with water cement ratio of 0.4
By knowing the specific heat capacity of water and
cement powder the mass of the reference can be calculated.
References for different starters systems should be
calculated based on the components
and mass of the whole samples.
So you're sure use different reference
water for different systems.
I'm supporting the reference water in the ample,
when your interests well as you can see on the slide.
So you're sure use different reference
water for different systems.
I'm supporting the reference water in the ample,
when your interests well as you can see on the slide.
Then we place it into the referenced side
of each channel in the instrument.
That's what all the diagram altogether,
which shows this process.
Different brands may have different design in turn
Iowa there are different number of channels for different uses.
We use in this demo, is a channel ten instrument.
Each channel has sample size and
reference side marked as A
and they respectively.
First
of all we open the plastic black lead use
a steel hook to hand the heat sink plug out.
Then we put the referencing, make sure it is going
to the bottom sitting right on top of the sensor.
After all these we can place the plug back and close the lead.
To start the initial baseline, we will need to create a new experiment.
In the case of ten IR
software being used is called Temp I R assistant.
You can see this icon on the slide.
Double click to open the software and at home page,
you can click on experiment in new menu
or click the green Icon on the top let.
After put in the name of the sample
and operators now the experiment
all these are will be activated.
It will guide you through a number of steps such as
selecting calorimeter and Channeled.
In next window, you will be reminded to put
the reference watering side.
And also you need to put Baseline
duration and signal stability condition.
Different conditions tell the ant of the baseline
when different conditions are met.
Usually at twenty degree the boys line
with this condition takes around thirty
minutes.
If temperature difference between the
reference water and the instrument is higher,
Then this tie ofcourse will be longer.
In the end you can see a window shows the
recorded baseline, until the baseline recording is finalized,
you will be instructed to put the samples into their
calorimeter.
Now is the time to prepare our samples.
In order to get reasonable results for Calorimetry,
really presented raw materials is critical.
We need to avoid the phases change
due to cabonation or humidity.
Briefly, three suggestions can be used
for getting good raw materials materials.
Keep raw materials sealed,
use on the recent batches,
and sample the amount you plan to use from a
big container to avoid always opening the container.
In this section, we are going to cast
the cement paste to with water to cement ratio of 0.4.
and sample the amount you plan to use from a
big container to avoid always opening the container.
In this section, we are going to cast
the cement paste to with water to cement ratio of 0.4.
For one ample, Usually we use approximately
ten gram of cement paste.
This amount will be changed with different types of materials.
One principle is to have high enough signal in order to
lower the error to signal ratio.
Here we weighted thirty two gram of water
and eighteen gram of cement powders. Two hundred fifty millimeter
plastic container.
In our case we only have cement
powder by you you have several different kinds of components of materials,
to get homogeneous examples, it is better
to first dry mix them.
We can chose Dry hand mixing or
machine mixing before casting.
For mixing the sample, it is not mandatory
to use one specific type of mixer
but the most important thing is
to keep using the same mixing spades and duration time.
To figure shows the difference for using
different speeds because of differential rates as mixing
energy.
Samples which makes do with higher mixing
spares shows higher heat flow.
Before casting, we need to prepare a mixer,
a suitable postering powder all for
different sample sizes and a stopwatch.
In our protocol, we use mixing speed of 1600 R.P.M.
and The mixing time is two minutes.
Here is another demo, shows how we can
make the sample for calorimetry test.
First of all we need to adjust to the position of the paddle
to make sure you have a good mixing efficiency.
We put the water into the simmer
and quickly put the 250mm plastic
container under the mixer.
While mixing, we need to move up and down or left and
right to make sure the sample is homogenized.
Don't forget to write down
the time you pour the water inside.
After the cement paste is ready, we will need to put
a certain amount of pacing side of the ample.
The weight of the pacing ample is important in order
to a later normalize the total heat rays.
In this step, we will need to prepare
a glass ample, a key pad and a balance.
We have another demo showing how we usually do for the step.
For Ike city of preparation, the sample
need to be Fluid enough otherwise,
You have a some difficulty to put it inside of them sample.
We cut and bath the puppet and place the ample on the
balance and tailor balance.
Exam pays to with the people that claim their outside with a tissue blowy plies the people inside of
the ample of the just the position
and screws the paid up people doing this until you reach the mass you need drag down the exact months after we finish
waiting we slightly top the sample
and learn suit low sample with a laid by using our kept pointing to all then we can lower their ample in the sample
side of the channel with the same way as we did for the reference water here we have some good
and bad examples for the sample preparation since the sensor is on the bottom of the AM posting it is a battle to put
the sample to the botton to make sure that the hay the generated is completely collected by the sensor now all
experiment is going on we can use the experiment always add to check how the experiment is going.
When the experiment finished we need to do the final baseline prissily it is the same as the initial baseline
and there is another reason we are guided you for the steps just remember before you do the baseline union to take out
of the sample ballot if the referencing site.
To explore the data you need to select which experiment you want to have the data
and click export ing file money obviously acting information which you want to have you can access father data as
C.S.V.
Vile or Excel file in this file you can have the time for the experiment on it for all
and cumulative here to release him a legit hate release is obtained by calculating the integrate.
Of the hateful don't forget to at the time join the sample perpetration Slide twenty six the last part of the section
we will have a look together at the huge flaw resound of a normal Portland cement.
Conventionally the whole heat flow curve Gulf to four
or five stages of cement hydration during each of them there are different mechanics science behind it therefore it
will help us to understand the hydration properties of cement the first two stages are called is a low shin paired
and induction period these two stage SAS are associated to the dissolution of the arms from Sully's the dissolution
rate controls the kinetics and the dissolution is higher
when the I am concentration in the solution is a lot more obvious some time
when I am concentrating goes higher the dissolution
or loss than factors such as the furnace of the body go density of critical defrags temperature
and I am a sturgeon well all in for one's the duration of this tooth stage after the first two stage const of very
important stage called acceleration period this is the May pig of c three as hydration
and the rate of acceleration can chose by the precipitation annual Asian of C.
As age sis age precipitates
when the degree of supersets ration reached their maximum value this is the period which are affected by the mixing
right finalists of the party goes temperature
and the amount of a separate month recent issues materials the fourth stage is scored at the exaggeration period in
this period hit for our age that to decrease we can see a shudder we should present the Sergant reaction of eliminate
this one can be used for the judge just saying the amount of chips
or the march of some we put inside the later shows still dominate.
Pick the antis people combine the fourth stage
and fifth stage together since during these days the hits for all are always decreasing as the summary will listed side
advantage than disadvantages of these ice of another color matter Mashonaland one thing you may need to pay attention
is that these measurements is still very repeatable.
But after several days because of the low signal their test is not very reliable That's all for this model Thank you.