Hello everyone.
This course is not on
space law but I think it's still worth
addressing a space law subject in this
video: the Outer Space Treaty of 1967.
First of all, let's ask ourselves the
question: Where does Space start?
Space, of
course we know, is very high up there;
where the density is nearly zero
whether it's vacuum mainly.
But if you
want to be more precise when you go up
in the atmosphere, there is one point
where you have the boundary between the
atmosphere and Space.
And if you consider
an airplane flying high and high the
atmosphere.
It has to fly faster and
faster to compensate for the lowering of
the density in order to sustain a lift C
equal to the weight of the airplane.
A Hungarian physicists, sir Theodore Von Kármán,
determined that for a certain height
around 100 kilometers, the velocity of an
airplane to sustain lift, is equal to
the orbital velocity and this has been
determined as being the boundary between
atmosphere and Space and the so-called
"Kármán line".
And the "Fédération Aéronotique Internationale"
- the FAI, has put that
limit as being 100 kilometers exactly or
63 miles above the Earth's surface.
That's where Space starts.
And if you
go above that limits, above that Kármán
line, you are an astronaut.
So you go 101
kilometer and you have your
astronaut wings.
Let's talk about the
outer space treaty of 1967.
This is
during the development of the Apollo
program; and before the first moon
landing in the summer of 1969, the Treaty
is on principles governing the
activities of States in the exploration
and use of outer space including the
moon and other celestial bodies.
As you
can see on the map in green, you have all
the ones that have signed this treaty;
all the spacefaring nations on one hand
and nearly all nations in the world
107 countries totally, excluding some
countries in Africa and in Latin America,
some in the Middle East and Southeast
Asia as well.
I will not address each of
the articles in this Outer Space Treaty
but just mention some key points.
The
treaty in particular bars the state from
placing weapons of mass destruction in
orbit around the earth, installing them
on the moon or any other celestial body.
The idea is to use space exclusively for
peaceful purposes.
The Treaty however
does not prohibit the placement of
conventional weapons in orbit and we
could still have potentially destructive
attack strategies.
This hasn't happened and
hopefully will not happen but this is
allowed through the Treaty.
And also
another important point is that
Space is accessible by all nations in
the world.
No country can be prevented
from having access to space; Whether it's
for practical utilization or exploration.
Another important subject is that pretty
much like for Antarctica, there can be no
national appropriation by claim of
sovereignty on any part of a celestial
body.
Let's talk about the space debris.
The space debris is obviously a pretty big
problem mainly in low Earth orbits.
Low
Earth orbit being between two hundred
kilometers above the Earth's surface all
the way to two thousand kilometers.
It's
also a problem around the geostationary orbit,
36,000 kilometers above
the Earth's surface and around that area.
Now the space debris population and
density is increasing with time and
something has to be done in order to
mitigate this space debris problem and
reduce the density of debris and the
critical areas of space.
It's interesting
to see that article 9 of the Treaty
addresses the legal base for debris
mitigation and for so-called ADR (Active Debris
Removal).
The idea is for nations to conduct space exploration
so as to avoid harmful contamination
and also adverse changes in the
environment of the earth resulting from
the introduction of a matter and where
necessary these nation shall adopt
appropriate measures for this purpose.
One important measure that has been put
in place for mitigation of the space
debris problem is that 25-year post
operational life limit.
Which means if a
satellite has a lifetime of let's say 10
years, and after that it becomes a space
debris because no longer operational.
Then 25 years after the end of this
operational time, it has to be de-orbited
by some means.
Several institutions and
companies are pursuing Active Debris Removal
technique development.
The moon Treaty of
1979 has not been as successful as the
Outer Space Treaty.
it specifically
addresses the situation of the moon and
other celestial bodies in the solar
system or even beyond.
The idea being that
have to they have to be used exclusively
for peaceful purposes pretty much in
line with the Outer Space Treaty.
One
controversial point in the Moon Treaty -
and that the reason why it hasn't been
signed by a number of nations - is that it
stipulated the moon and its natural
resources are the common heritage of
mankind and the harvesting of those
resources is forbidden except through an
international regime.
This obviously was
not to the taste of a number of nations
and in particular the states that are
engaged in space exploration; at least
most of them, United States, Canada, nearly
all the members of the European Space
Agency, Russia, China and Japan have not
signed it.
Now obviously in the near
future, we'll have exploration the solar
system by human spacecraft and Space
lawyers are working on the subject to
provide a legal frame for future moon
mass and asteroid human missions in the
next decade including by private
companies like SpaceX.