Hello and welcome to this
module on private sector involvement
in municipal waste services.
This can be a quite
political sensitive topic, given the
relevance of solid waste
management as a public good.
But let's be clear from the start.
In this module, we are not talking
about transferring responsibility
of solid waste management.
Responsibility, independent
of who operates the service,
always remains with local government.
Regarding private sector
involvement: in literature, you will
often come across the
two terms PSP or PPP,
Private Sector Participation
or Public-Private Partnerships.
This can include a lot of things
in terms of scale of enterprise,
starting from the very
small and informal,
to the large national or even
international enterprises.
There are also different levels of
privatisation being joint-venture
of an enterprise with the public
sector, or even the involvement
of community groups or
non-governmental organizations.
This is also the
object of another module.
In this module, I shall focus on
the formal private sector involvement,
as seen from a municipal
viewpoint, but also cover the opportunities
of small and medium
enterprises in waste management.
My main message, in this
module, is not to advocate blindly
for the private sector, but
rather show what conditions should
be considered so to allow the
private sector participation
that it has a good chance
to improve the situation.
Why would a municipality consider
engaging with the private sector?
From a municipal viewpoint, a
frequent reason for engaging with
the private sector is increasing
efficiency and lowering cost.
However, efficiency is
driven by competition.
The private sector, usually,
also has more flexible procedures
and procurement rules,
less bureaucraty.
Increasing efficiency, may
also allow to expand coverage
to areas not yet serviced.
Experience from Latin America,
Malaysia, for example, has shown
a decrease in cost, by 20 % to 50 %.
One other aspect may be the easier
access to the private sector to capital
as compared to a public utility;
also, the flexibility in deploying
human resources, for instance
in hiring the necessary
expertise, if needed, or laying off
personnel which is not performing.
Finally, another reason may be to free
solid waste from political interference.
One key precondition for
successful private sector participation
is a balanced partnership
with the municipal authority.
If the private sector is
very dominant, then,
there are risks for disaster.
The same if the municipal authorities
are very dominant and can decide
in contractual terms over the private sector.
Besides balanced partnership,
another precondition
for successful private sector
participation is competition,
competition by different private
sector enterprises.
This keeps prices low.
If there is a monopoly by one enterprise,
that might even increase the price of service.
Further preconditions are
clear objectives and precise contracts.
What that means is a very careful
preparation of the tender
documents by the municipal services.
What it also needs is adequate
monitoring and enforcement by
the client, the
municipal, authorities, and
to ensure regular
payment to the private sector
for the services rendered.
Finally, the last precondition
I want to mention here is public involvement.
The residents, the public are
actually the beneficiaries of the service.
Involving the beneficiaries, especially in monitoring,
and giving feedback on service quality is essential,
but also in preparation of
private sector enterprise involvement
in solid waste management services.
This table shows different
options of collaboration with the
private sector by the municipality.
Contracting, where a
fixed term contract is awarded,
based on competitive procurement,
and the service is paid by government.
Similarly, franchising,
where, however,
the revenue sources come through direct
charges to the beneficiaries.
And finally, to highlight
maybe the open competition, where
the government grants a
license, and allows the private sector
to compete for service provision.
Private enterprises built the
service directly to the customers.
One special case is the
involvement of small and medium enterprises.
One advantage is that small
medium enterprises are close to home.
That means they're quite closely
connected to the beneficiaries.
Often, they are
people from the same neighborhood,
working in the neighborhood.
They can also adapt their
services to the individual needs of
the beneficiaries, of the
people in the neighborhood.
However, usually their services are
limited to neighborhood service.
That means primary
collection and recycling in the neighborhood.
And because they're limited to
the neighborhood service,
they have to coordinate with the
next step in the waste management chain
which is
typically the municipality.
For the municipality,
engaging with many small enterprises
is quite difficult to manage.
One solution forward is
to build larger groups,
cooperatives, or consortiums.
Let me highlight one case study
from Douala and Yaoundé in Cameroon.
Here, the municipality gave contracts
to the private sector.
Exact targets and even
the schedule frequency
were defined in the contracts.
The tonnage of waste
collected was monitored daily
for neighborhoods which were
difficult to access by large trucks.
The enterprise entered into
agreements with community-based
organizations, for primary collection.
Since private sector
involvement, the collection coverage has
now increased up to 80 % to 90 %.
The private enterprise was
given a five years contract,
so they were also able to
recover their investment costs.
The company now has contracted
with fourteen towns and cities
throughout the country, and
it has won the Africités prize
for Waste Management in 2009.
Another example is the
municipality of Maputo in Mozambique.
The city of Maputo is divided
in two different administrative districs.
The
municipality provides waste collection
services across the city.
Inner city waste collection
and secondary collection in
the suburban areas are covered
by a private large scale operators,
with public containers and compactor trucks.
The city councils own
operation covers the residential areas
in the inner city with
door to door collection.
The city councils own
operation covers the residential areas
in the inner city with
door to door collection.
Based on various experiences
with NGOs, the city council
implemented primary collection
system for the suburban neighborhoods.
Primary collection in these areas
is provided by micro enterprises,
with manual door to door
collection and hand cars.
The city's ambition was to
extend primary collection to areas
that would be difficult to reach
with modern collection equipment.
Monthly waste fees are
attached to the electricity bill.
This module is particularly
interesting, because fees increase
according to the social
economic level of the users.
Currently, thirty five micro
enterprises or associations are
contracted by the Maputo city
council and are servicing over
900 000 people living
in the suburban areas.
This model has become a
great success for the government.
And here is one example of micro
enterprise involvement in Managua, Nicaragua.
Collection services are
provided by the municipality,
but only on the main roads.
However, collection by motorized tricycle
is provided to the households
through these small entreprises.
Revenues are from user fees
and mainly from recyclables.
What is
important, however,
is that the municipality ensures that
there are transfer stations
available for these micro enterprises,
which are operated by the municipality.
This even includes sorting and
storage sheds for the recyclables.
Let me summarize what we
talked about in this module.
We looked at private sector
involvement as opportunity
for increasing efficiency and lowering cost.
We also saw that it needs a lot
of capacity at local government level
to prepare the tender documents,
but also to monitor and supervise the service.
Competition helps a lot to
keep prices low,
and it's important to include the
public in the whole procedure.
Finally, we ended with
showing a few case studies.
If you're interested in reading
more about private sector involvement
in solid waste management, I
can recommend these three books.
They are available on our
website for free download.