Hi!
It's my pleasure
to introduce Sanjay Gupta.
In this module, he will present the case
of a public awareness campaign in India.
Sanjay Gupta, the floor is yours!
Thanks, Chris.
This is the story of a campaign
in a 1 million plus city
called Coimbatore in India,
where a mass awareness program
was organized
for improving segregation and recycling
using the Guinness Record as motivation.
My name is Dr. Sanjay K. Gupta
and I work with the [Start Consulting]
in Switzerland,
and I provided the key
conceptual and strategic guidelines
for conducting this campaign.
Most of us know
that getting people to participate
in segregation and recycling practices
is often a big challenge.
We also know that typically,
awareness campaigns are activities
organized and [inaudible]
by either municipalities
or NGOs as a one-time affair.
So, there are awareness campaigns
for [inaudible]
and there are awareness campaigns
which sell [inaudible] to entire community.
In this module, I would like to present
an example of such a campaign
where a reason was shared
with a large community.
It is called the Coimbatore Guinness
Championship Campaign 2015.
The attempt was made
as part of achieving
the Guinness World Record
for largest recycling lesson
at a single venue.
As I stated, Coimbatore region in India
is one of the most industrialized
cities in South India.
It is the second largest city
and urban agglomeration
in the state of Tamil Nadu,
which is the eleventh largest state
and the second largest economy in India.
Coimbatore City Municipal Corporation,
or CCMC as it is popularly called,
has taken several steps to improve
solid waste resource management system
in compliance with the municipal
waste management and handling rules.
Though CCMC has good infrastructure
for waste management,
it did not spark
resource segregation and recycling.
Resource recovery watch
are a mere six persons
due to lack of awareness,
training of LX&Q
and absence
of appropriate collection methods.
As the world is moving toward 3R principles
of reduce, reuse, and recycle,
CCMC envisioned a unique campaign
to bring awareness and capacity building
of all stakeholders
including municipal staff,
citizens, civil society organizations,
with a key emphasis on students
at the schools and colleges.
Its objective was to create
a more sustainable
solid waste management system
focusing on resource recovery
and recycling
and Guinness Book of World Records
was used as an attraction and motivation
for the community
to be part of this history,
and it mainly targeted the next generation
of ten to 18 year old students
as the change agents;
and it was an attempt
at a culture and behavior
change initiative
to get community stakeholders aligned
with the new waste management
system of the city.
As you can see, the campaign organizers
shared the vision [inaudible]
with the stakeholders.
You can see all the logos
of those organizers which were part of it,
ranging from elected representatives
to industry, market associations,
resident associations, local NGOs,
and they were able to garner
the maximum support.
Many of them also pitched in
financial contributions
to support the campaign besides
their own time and voluntary work,
and many of these had never
partnered with municipality
or contributed financially,
but this time they did
after setting the regional
waste management services for the city.
The Guinness campaign event was
widely publicized through various media
including print, banners, leaflets,
radio, local television, website,
SMS, Whatsapp group, mobile missed calls,
on and offline registration forms.
Whatsapp group messages and radio
turned out to be very effective mediums
to make people aware on what is going on.
As the campaign got closer,
the publicity was intensified
to capture the attention of the public,
again using the same mediums
and constant and consistent reminders
were sent to SMS and Whatsapp messages
and also it included mobile vans
that went around the city
informing the public about this campaign.
Here we see the commissioner of Coimbatore
explaining the rules for setting up
this Guinness Book of World Records.
The event was conducted
as per the stringent rules
of the Guinness Book of World Records
through video recording of all evidences.
It had also an independent team
of qualified auditors
for physically verifying
each and every aspect of the attempt
before declaring the results.
Here we see a massive turnout
of students and participants
queuing up to enter the hall,
to attend the recycling lesson session.
The participants' entry was video recorded
with electronic barcode machines
and mobile labs
and the final electronic count
of participants stood at 12,994.
The lesson plan was designed
for 45 minutes
divided into four distinct
interactive sessions.
These are some of the snapshots
of the largest recycling lesson
in progress.
The methodology included
visual slide presentations
on large LED screens,
verbal instructions from facilitators,
and demonstrations
which were live streamed.
Interactivity was built in
to ensure participation
and a set of activity flash cards
that were given to the participants.
This was followed by explaining
what is the methodology of CCMC
that has adopted to collect waste
in a very source-segregated manner
from the households.
A practical demonstration of the post card
with all the segregation system
was put there that you can see
in picture three and four of this slide.
This, you can see another picture of
the largest recycling lesson in progress.
The first part of the session
was an icebreaker
to a funny anecdote involving Yamarāja
or the god of death
according to Indian mythology.
As the caretaker of Hell,
Yamarāja is faced with a space crunch
and he tries to find
another plug-and-play space for hell,
and he stumbles upon
dump sites in the country
which are even worse than hell,
to punish those who commit sins.
He describes the current behavior
of waste management by people as sins
and the dump sites as hell on Earth.
The participants were to answer,
"Where the hell
are the dump sites in their city
and what is the name of that hell,
or the place, the dump site?"
The second part was an interactive session
of source-do-and check activity
that's explaining
for identifying different major streams
into organics, inorganics and hazardous
to provide a clear understanding
of the segregation.
From the set
of colorful pictures and flashcards,
the participants identified types of waste
which needs to be put in appropriate bins.
A formative assessment
was built into the session plan
to check the correctness of their choice
and learn from their own mistakes, if any.
This picture was to reinforce
the role of the citizen,
what they need to do
and what they need to promote
as green ambassadors
for their own localities.
One key element of this campaign
is that the students were requested
to take the contest card home
and practice it for seven days
and also doing the segregation
at their own home.
They were informed that 1,200 postcards
with six category source separation
has been pressed into service
for litter free and bin free system
for most of the wards.
After the lesson was completed,
the adjudicator or Guinness
accepted that the record attempt
has been successfully completed
following all guidelines, and handed over
the certificate to the commissioner.
This is the photo where you can seeº
the adjudicator giving the certificate
to the commissioner.
This is another picture showing
the Guinness Book
of World Records certificate
and how many people and organizations,
volunteer associations
who contributed and participated
in this record-breaking attempt.
Recycling girth since then has gone
from a mere 6% to 23 %
in the last few months.
That means dumping of recyclables
and compostable waste reduced by 23%,
or nearly 120 plus tons
per day in this city.
This one single campaign
encouraged other similar campaigns
like Zero Waste Wars
and Happy Street Campaigns.
You can see it in the pictures,
where the roads were cleaned,
they were decorated,
children played games over it
and Coimbatore also became
the first city in India
to segregate waste
in six different categories
partially by the households, and partially
by the trained collection team.
As I stated, the Guinness campaign
triggered many more such
community [OMS]
initiatives in Coimbatore.
No Food Waste became
one of the hit campaigns
that picked up steam, actually,
after this campaign was completed.
The leftover food from five star hotels,
restaurants, marriage parties,
were collected, kept very safely,
and distributed to the poor in the city.
This is still going on.
Many engineering graduates,
who had read in the past about recycling,
chucked their jobs and took it
as a social enterprise,
the business of recycling
as a social enterprise after the campaign.
To conclude, I can say that it requires
a very well thought out strategy
to run any campaign
and get the momentum going
to get any tangible results.
It is also important
to install the system in advance
to get the public familiar with it.
The idea is the system should be in place
before organizing a campaign
so that people can start practicing
immediately after learning the lessons
or the messages of the campaign.
One should also find a way
to share the results of the campaign
with the public.
For example, one can share
the recycling weight.
One can also share with them
that a new door to door collection system
has been put into place.
One can also share how much
organic waste is being composted now
so that you can ensure further action
both from the municipal staff
as well as from the citizens.
Finally, thank you
for giving me this opportunity
to share the experience with one and all.
Thank you.