Welcome to this module
on community members
in solid waste management.
By now, you should be aware
that keeping a solid waste service
running is financially demanding
and requires know-how and infrastructure.
Public and private
solid waste service providers
often fail or are unable to supply
an adequate service,
especially in areas that are difficult
to access by conventional services
such as low-income neighborhoods
or in rapidly growing residential areas.
Consequently, in many cities
around the world,
neighborhoods organize themselves
to find a solution to the waste problem
and obtain services
for their own benefit.
Members of communities,
for example residents,
are key stakeholders in the solid waste
management process,
since they generate and store waste,
benefit from the service,
and in many cases are also the client,
the payers for the service.
In this module, we will focus on
the involvement of community members
in the solid waste management service,
which is of utmost importance
and is often neglected.
Let's start clarifying some terms.
What is a community?
In this context, a community is
a group of users of a service
who live in the same area
and have access to and use
the same service.
This could be households
in a neighborhood, for instance.
When these communities
share social features,
such as cultural and religious ideas,
or have similar socio-economic interests,
the concept of community
becomes even stronger.
This often helps to stimulate
participation of people.
Community members can play different roles
and present different
levels of involvement.
Let's see some examples.
Community members can change
their sanitation behavior.
For instance, adapting
to the collection timetables,
keeping their house
and immediate surroundings clean,
or source separating.
Problems arise when residents
give low priority
to solid waste management
and have low willingness to co-operate.
Often, residents had bad experiences
with solid waste services
and do not want to have any of these
activities next to their homes.
This is also called "Not In My Backyard".
These issues have often been tackled
organizing competitions at city,
neighborhood or household level
or providing discounts for those
who participate in solid waste management.
This was done in SIRDO Recycling
Projects in Mexico, for instance,
where vegetables were sold
cheaper to those households
separating organic waste.
Community members can also contribute
directly by paying the fees regularly,
donating equipment,
or contributing in labor.
Concerning payments of fees,
low ability to pay and low willingness
to pay are common issues.
The second one occurs especially
when communities perceive
that fees are unfair,
or that the waste service is unreliable
or not satisfactory.
Three possible solutions for this
are paying the collectors
based on their performance,
to change the ways fees are collected.
For instance, combining them
with other utility bills,
such as the water or the electricity bill,
or to cross subsidize.
They can also participate
in service and consultation
organized by CBOs to talk about
the needs and problems
of the community regarding
solid waste services.
And finally, participating
in administration and management,
which is the highest level
of community participation.
To this end, community members
may take part in a city-wide
stakeholder meeting or committees,
become members of CBOs
directly involved in the provision
of waste collection services
or environmental education,
or participate in decision-making
during meetings.
We would like to point out three
types of community members.
These are leaders, women, and youth.
Let's have a look
to how they can influence
the solid waste management system.
Community leaders might manage
solid waste services
by becoming members of committees
or CBOs established for this purpose.
They can also keep in contact
with the municipality
in order to communicate
about the co-ordination of primary
and secondary collection systems
or exercise political pressure
or forward complaints.
And finally, they are the key stakeholders
to keep in contact with the community.
In many cultures, women
are responsible for keeping
the home and it's immediate
environment clean.
But their voice is seldom heard.
And their participation
in community decision-making
should be improved and highlighted.
Unemployed adolescence discovered
the income generating potential
of solid waste services.
Normally the youths want a material reward
for their participation or effort.
Children, too, often carry out daily tasks
such as bringing waste
to the communal collection point,
as shown in the movie.
Until now, we talked about the community
and some specific community members,
such as leaders, women, and youth.
But what happens
when they organize themselves?
Then we talk about
community-based organizations
also abbreviated as CBOs.
These are formed when some
community members
organize themselves to provide,
for instance, a solid waste
service in a specific neighborhood
or village in a rural context.
They can be driven
by different motivations,
such as cleaning up
their neighborhood,
or earning an income
from solid waste.
The most common example
is the primary collection of solid waste.
Other examples may include
the sale of recyclables,
recycling on its own,
and composting activities.
CBOs can present different
organizational structures.
They can work together
with micro enterprises,
where generally, the CBO
has a management
and supervision task,
while the micro enterprise is responsible
for operating the service,
driven by its income generating aspects.
Government institutions can assist CBOs
by providing them supervision,
financial control or support.
While the CBO carries out the operation
and management of the service.
Or CBOs can be combined with NGOs.
In this case, NGOs usually set up a CBO
as a development project.
which later they supervise,
provide financial assistance
and technical support,
and also train and recruit
members of the management
committee and operators.
CBOs operate the service.
Setting up a CBO is often not a hard task.
The difficulty is to keep it ongoing.
Why? Because various problems might arise.
Here we distinguish management problems,
operational problems, financial problems,
and failing co-operation
with municipality.
Management problems occur
when there is low willingness to manage,
which was often solved by training
and providing exchange visits
of the management committees,
increasing their motivation
or by ensuring assistance
and moral support
on behalf of the municipality.
This is an issue of particular importance.
Often CBOs are a voluntary activity
carried out by a motivated individual.
Voluntary actions by experience
show not to be long lasting
since these schemes often stop
when the individual gives up the activity.
However, solid waste management needs
to be ensured in the long run.
That's why an enterprise approach
is often more sustainable.
Problems might also arise
when the management board
is not representative
of the community, ethnic groups,
there is gender imbalance,
or it consists of outsiders.
Having seen management problems,
now let's have a look
to operational problems.
Operators are often unsatisfied
due to low salaries,
the low status of the job,
and bad working conditions.
Possible solutions to these issues
include increasing collected fees
by using cross-subsidizing schemes
for example
or by providing special
benefits to the operators,
such as medical assistance,
food, accommodation, etc.
And providing them,
of course, with facilities,
gloves, boots, collection cards, etc.
On top of being unsatisfied,
operators often have no or little
expertise in solid waste
management issues
and are, therefore, unprofessional.
This can be solved by providing
them with training.
The previous two problems often
lead to an unreliable service
on behalf of operators.
Involving them in decision-making
appears to be an incentive
for them to perform better.
Also, paying them based on
their performance improves the service.
Other operational problems
might arise from competition
on behalf of the private
and the public sector.
And finally, space seems to be
an important constraint
for waste treatment and sorting projects.
Financial problems might arise
due to the following issues:
low ability to pay
on behalf of households,
which could be avoided
by cross-subsidizing schemes,
or due to inadequate fee collection.
This is often due to the lack
of rigorousity of fee collectors.
Other reasons could include
the absence of sanctions
for non-payment and lack of legal
obligation to pay.
Both issues involved lead
to cost recovery problems,
which are discussed in the modules
about financing mechanism.
Problems might also arise
when co-operation with municipality fails.
Many times it is difficult
for big municipalities to connect
and co-ordinate with hundreds
of tiny CBOs.
However, sometimes a municipality
or solid waste agency
can also obstruct CBOs in various ways.
Either directly by hampering
the performance
of community-based services.
The bad co-ordination
between primary and secondary collection
is one of the most common examples.
Or indirectly by refusing assistance
to provide legal, financial
or promotional support.
Why is community management
desirable at all?
Several benefits exist
of having communities
manage their solid waste service.
First, it creates social cohesion
and networks among residents.
Second, it can trigger some peers
social pressure to participate.
Third, it facilitates cross-subsidies
for those that cannot pay.
For instance, in Karachi, Pakistan,
widows that have very little income,
are exempted from payment
but still got service from the CBOs.
Fourth, it adapts the service
to the local needs and conditions.
And with the priorities and capacities
of the men and women concerned.
And ultimately, when co-operating
with the private and the public sector,
it allows to provide solid waste
services to a larger population.
This is the end.
In this module we learned about
community members
and the roles in solid waste management.
Community-based organizations are formed
when residents of a confined
area are organized.
These CBOs can provide different
services to the community
including solid waste management.
They can be driven by different
motivations, such as having a clean
neighborhood or earning some money.
We also saw different
organizational structures of CBOs.
They can partner with micro enterprises,
local government agencies and NGOs.
Finally, we mentioned several social
and management problems CBOs face,
as well as some of the benefits
of community management.
We hope you learned something.
This module was prepared
using this document shown here.
Those of you who would like to get
more insights on the topic,
I recommend you to have a look
to it on the Internet.