What happens with a plastic bottle
when you throw it away?
Well, it might end up
in a landfill
however it could also be collected
often by the informal sector,
transported to a processing site
washed and shredded
into small pieces.
These pieces could then
be used as a raw material
in the production of fibers
for clothes, carpets
or new plastic bottles.
This process is a form of
resource recovery
that is probably
happening around you.
In this module we will introduce you
to similar forms of
resource recovery
for fecal sludge.
Following this module,
you will be able
to list different treatment products
identify ways in which
they can be used
and learn important characteristics
of resource recovery products.
For over 2000 years
excreta and fecal sludge
from animals and humans
have been used in
many parts of the world
as soil conditioner in agriculture.
The water, organic matter
and nutrients in fecal sludge
are beneficial for soil properties
and plant growth.
The organic matter is beneficial
for water retention
which can increase
water holding capacity
and reduce the effects of drought
reduce erosion of soils
and benefit
the soil microbial community
and the water and the nutrients
such as nitrogen, phosphorous
and potassium
are essential for plant growth.
However, there are also
other possible uses
and types
of treatment products
than just soil amendments.
Products from other established
treatment technologies
include compost from
co-composting of fecal sludge
and organic solid waste
plants, for example from
planted drying beds
and affluent, for example
from waster stabilization ponds.
In addition,
treatment technologies exist
that are innovative
and in development.
These products
and treatment technologies include
Bio-gas, Bio-diesel, and Syngas
for example from
anaerobic digestion of fecal sludge
insect larvae from the treatment
of fecal sludge with fly larvae
and Char from carbonization
of fecal sludge.
These treatment products
can all have different uses.
We already mentioned the use
of Dewatered or dried sludge
as soil conditioner,
ranging from deeper entrenchment
or untreated fecal sludge
as soil conditioner.
In addition this treatment product
can also be used as a component
in building materials
or for the production
of solid fuels.
Compost and fertilizer can be used
as soil conditioner, agriculture
horticulture or (INAUDIBLE)
plant as animal feed
effluent for irrigation
in agriculture
or for parks or golf courses
Bio-gas, Bio-diesel, and Syngas
as liquid bio-fuel
insect larvae as animal feed,
such as chicken or fish
Char as a component for Bio-fuel
brickette production
or as soil conditioner.
The aforementioned
treatment products
can also be further processed
to increase the market value.
For example Char
from the carbonization
of fecal sludge
may be used for a soil conditioner.
Further processing of Chat
into brickettes puts into a form
that could make it suitable
for recovery of it's energy
in households or institutions.
Other examples include
the combustion of Bio-gas or Cyngas
to produce heat or electricity,
or pelletizing of compost
or dried sludge.
Pellets are more
homogeneous in size
they have a higher density
of nutrients or energy
in comparison with the sludge
or compost before pelletizing
and then therefore be easier
to transport and store.
Characterization
of treatment products is important
to ensure that they
meet market needs
and protect public
an environmental health.
On the next slide we will summarize
what parameters are relevant
for the different
treatment products.
Nutrients such as Nitrogen,
phosphorous and potassium
are essential for plant growth
and important for
the use of affluent for irrigation
and soil conditioner,
compost or fertilizer.
Heavy metal such as
Lead and Cadmium
and the salinity are important
as they can be toxic to plants.
Indicators of pathogens
such as E coli for affluent
and Helminths eggs
for soil conditioner
composts of fertilizer should be
determined to ensure
that resource recovery
adequately protects public health.
The calorific value, a measure of
the energy content of the fuel
is important for
the characterization
of treatment products as solid fuel.
The ash in fuels is
an important indicator
for the amount of inorganics
contained in fecal sludge.
it is the proportion of
the fuel that does not ban
and therefore does not contribute
to the calorific value.
Helminths eggs as an indicator
of human pathogens in sludge
is also an important parameter for
the use of fecal sludge as fuel.
The Methane content
and the Carbon Dioxide content
and the calorific value
are important parameters for Bio-gas
a higher Methane
and lower Carbon Dioxide content
increases the calorific value.
The Protein, Fat
and the Mineral content
are important for
the use of insect larvae
and plants as animal feed.
These parameters can be used
to compare
the product characteristics
to the nutritional requirements
of animals.
Indicators of human pathogens
such as E coli and Helminths eggs
should also be regularly monitored
for animal feeds in order to ensure
that pathogens are
not transmitted to animals.
In this module we have learned
what some products
from treatment are
and how they can be used.
This includes affluent for
irrigation and sludge
compost as the soil conditioner,
solid and liquid Bio-fuels
plants as animal feed
and as a component
in building materials.
Characterization
of treatment products
for parameters such as
the caloric value as a solid fuel
and the ratio of nutrients
as soil conditioner
compost of fertilizer
are important to meet market needs.
Helminths eggs and E coli
are important indicators
to ensure the protection
of public health.