If I asked you how many fish
were in this lake
could you tell me?
Even more complicated,
what if I asked you how many
of each type of species there were?
It's pretty difficult since you
can't even see them.
This is a similar problem
that faces us with
the quantification of fecal sludge.
Following this module,
you should understand the importance
of reasonably accurate estimations
for quantities of fecal sludge
on a city wide scale.
Be able to explain the difference
between produced, accumulated
emptied, dumped,
or discharged fecal sludge
and explain methods that
could be used to estimate
quantities of fecal sludge.
To understand why
quantification is important
let's go back to our
engineering design approach
where to select
and design technologies
we first need to know
treatment objectives
so we know what
we are designing for
and then we need to know
what is coming into
the treatment plant
so we can appropriately size them.
So quantification is very important
for the management and treatment
of fecal sludge.
But how can we do this?
For waste water it's relatively
straight forward to make assumptions
as it is typically know
how many household connections
there are to a sewer
and average per capita water usage.
But for fecal sludge
they are typically not records
of the existing situation,
and so we do not know
how many on-site
sanitation systems there even are
or how many different types
of containment technologies
like septic tanks, cesspits,
lined or unlined pit latrines
how many people are using them,
how frequently they are emptied
and other factors
such as usage patterns
that affect characteristics.
We need to think about how
to start making good estimations now
for the design of infrastructure,
but also consider what type
of actions need to be put in place
so that in the future we can
even more accurately assess
the management need.
Starting with the current situation
let's first thing about
the different places
in the service chain where
fecal sludge could be quantified.
Number one is the amount
the excrete that's produced
which is not fecal sludge
but can be readily estimated
based on the literature.
Number two is the amount
of fecal sludge that's produced
So what is going into containment
along with excreta
like cleansing material
or flush water
and can also be estimated
if you know enough about types
of containment and water usage
patterns in the city.
Number three is the amount
of fecal sludge that actually
accumulates
in containment technologies.
For the development
of the fecal sludge management
on a city wide scale,
number three is the number
we want to know,
but it is too difficult to calculate
because it is a rate equation
that varies depending on
lots of different factors,
such as inflow and infiltration
rates of biological degradation
which are also affected
by temperature, moisture, Ph
redox potential, etc.
Number four is fecal sludge
that is emptied but not collected.
So for example when
people break a containment
and let it drain directly out
into the environment.
This is very difficultly to estimate
but mostly we just
want to eradicate it.
Number five is the amount
of fecal sludge that is collected
but not delivered to treatment.
This could be manual
or mechanical emptiers.
Reasonable estimations can be made
if dumping is concentrated
in a few areas
or if the current number
and operating capacity
of trucks and emptiers
in a city is known.
And number six
is what we want to see.
Fecal sludge that is collected
and delivered to a treatment plant
or legal discharge location.
This should be very easy to estimate
based on operating records.
The reason why number three
is so important
is that it tells us
the full magnitude of the problem
so we can develop
sustainable management.
For example, if a treatment plant
design is based on volume estimates
for the current demand
for example current emptying
practices in a community
what is going to happen when
a treatment plant opens?
The current demand will
immediately increase
because now there is
a legal an convenient option
for the disposal of fecal sludge.
As it's frequently been observed,
this means as soon as
the treatment plant opens,
it will already be under capacity.
This is why it is important
to evaluate the current demand
but also the future demand,
which is based on
the total fecal sludge
accumulation.
So if we cannot precisely calculate
rates of fecal sludge accumulation
in containment technologies,
how could we estimate them
with the current lack of records?
One way could be to survey
a select representation
of the city wide distribution
during emptying operations.
You could ask
the household questions
like when did they last have
their containment emptied
how often do they have it emptied
how many people use it,
what is the containment volume
was it full, was it fully emptied?
You could simultaneously ask
the emptying service provider
if they full empty the containment
if their truck is full or barrels
with the manual emptier
the truck volume
and emptying practices
like did they add water
while emptying and how much.
Based on the possible answers
with the emptying frequency
you can then estimate
accumulation rates.
Depending on the infrastructure
in your city or community
estimates like this will be
easier or more complicated.
For example if a community is
all on septic tanks
built at a similar time
with a similar design
with regularly scheduled emptying
and equatable water usage
then sludge accumulation could
also be estimated based on factors
such as influent COD
and hydraulic retention time.
Or in a small town with
similarly sized pit latrines
and usage habits, like whether
or not there's household water
estimates will also be more similar.
Other difficulties with estimating
future demand for
fecal sludge management
include rapid urbanization
and rapidly growing cities
commuting populations,
meaning many cities
actually double in size
during the day
with people who come in for work
and another important consideration
the people frequently
do not consider
is non-household
sources of fecal sludge
from commercial enterprises
like restaurants, hotels,
public toilets
toilets for employees of factories,
the commuting population
depending on the context
this could easily be half
of all the fecal sludge that
is delivered to treatment.
What can be done
to improve estimations
of quantities in the future?
The implementation
of data management.
For example,
instituting a GPS database
of all existing on-site technologies
and maintaining GPS-based records
of how often and the volumes
when they are emptied.
And one more very important point.
Quantities of fecal sludge
can not be considered
without simultaneously
considering characteristics
because as we know,
fecal sludge is highly variable.
This is especially important when
designing treatment plants
as on a mass balance basis,
the concentrations can have
as much to do with loading
of treatment plants as volumes do.
Setting up a sampling plant
for fully understanding
city-wide characteristics
can be just as or even much more
complicated than quantification.
Some of our unpublished research
indicates that one way to do this
could be through
designing sampling plants
based on spatially
available demographic data.
So stay tuned for further results.
In summary, in this module
you've learned about the importance
of estimating quantities
of fecal sludge  for designing
sustainable management options.
The differences between produced,
accumulated, emptied, dumped
and/or discharged fecal sludge
and possible approaches
that could be used for estimating
quantities of fecal sludge.
Thanks for joining,
see you next time!