How are you moving
around in your city you live in?
By (INAUDIBLE),
by bicycle, on foot, bus
(INAUDIBLE), train, or even by boat?
Or could it be
a combination of those?
Similarly, the collection
and transport of fecal sludge
uses a variety of technologies
based on local context.
For example, how do you collect
and transport fecal sludge
from a dense neighborhood
to a treatment plant?
Following this module,
you will be able to explain
why urban areas rely on
a range of collection
and transport technologies
name existing
established technologies
for collection and transport
and discuss which technologies
are appropriate based
on the local context.
Urbane areas include
different physical
and socio-economic realities
influencing fecal sludge
collection and transport.
Among others, the sludge
characteristics, access
the transport distance
and economic status
are important for
collection and transport.
For example, in my city
of Kampala, Uganda
examples of our on-site
infrastructure include
panned middle and high income areas
with good road infrastructure
which are mostly connected
by sewer or septic tanks
with a low solid content.
Unplanned densely populated
low-income areas
with poor accessibility
in fecal sludge from pit latrines
has got a very high solid content
and peri-urban areas with
a low population density
and therefore long
transport distances.
These different realities explain
the large range of collection
and transport technologies
that exist and will be introduced
in this module.
Collection technologies can
in general be categorized
into manual,
manually operated mechanical
and fully mechanized technologies.
Manual collection with buckets
or shovels is often unsafe
and unhygienic.
Frequently it involves the workers
interact directly into the on-site
sanitation technology.
However, manual collection can be
an important part of providing
fecal sludge management services,
especially for the poor.
In addition, it can collect
thick sludge that is difficult
to collect with
the mechanical technologies.
Implementing minimal standards
and their enforcement
licensing, training
and capacity development
can improve the safety and hygiene
of service providers
and the community.
For example as shown
here in Lusaka, Zambia
where workers wear protective boots,
gloves and face masks.
The gulper shown
in action here in Kenya
is one manually operated
collection technology.
In comparison to manual
collection with shovels and buckets
this can increase
the safety and hygiene
by preventing human contact with
the fecal sludge during collection
and increase the amount of sludge
that can be collected per day.
With the gulper,
the sludge is pumped out
manually by moving a plunger,
up and down.
The plunger contains a valve
which opens when the plunger
is moved downwards and closes
when the plunger is lifted upwards
moving the sludge towards
a collection vessel.
Manual collection technologies
need to be combined
with appropriate transport
technologies to ensure sludge
reaches a treatment plant.
Commonly, manually collected sludge
is pumped into drums
and transported by trolleys,
carts, or on pickups
as shown here.
These barrels commonly have the size
of one hundred, two hundred liters.
To allow sludge collection
in these areas
smaller trucks, shown here,
commonly referred to as vacutugs
have been developed.
A common size of these tanks
are between 0.5 and 2 cubic meters.
The technology considered
for transport
of manually
collected sludge
must take into account the distance
to the next treatment plant.
For example, carts are at most able
to transport the sludge
for a few kilometers.
Transfer stations as a way
to improve sludge logistics
are covered in another module.
Mechanical collection technologies
are pumps driven
by electricity or fuel.
These technologies can pump
large amounts of sludge per day
than manually operated technologies.
Pumps that are mounter
on tractors and trucks
as show here, are the most common
mechanical collection technologies
and allow transport of
the sludge over long distances.
The vacuum pumps the sludge
through a hose into a tank.
Common sizes of these tanks are
between two and twenty cubic meters.
Vacuum trucks often
have difficulties
accessing on-site
sanitation technologies
that can only be accessed through
narrow roads and alleys.
In some areas, different sludge
collection and transport
technologies
have different opportunities
and challenges.
Best on sludge characteristics,
economic status of the customer
access and transport distances
that can be covered
it is up to you to select one
or several technologies
for your neighborhood or city.
Manual collection
and transport technologies
can collect sludge with
a high solidus content
such as from pit latrines,
and can access narrow lands.
However, these technologies
only collect small amounts of sludge
and transport of this sludge
to a treatment plant
can be a challenge.
This can result in the discharge
of the collected sludge
into the urban environment.
Mechanical collection
and transport technologies
are often only appropriate for
sludge with a low solidus content.
In addition, access of on-site
sanitation technologies
can be a challenge.
In general, per volume
of fecal sludge
manual collection and transport
are more expensive
compared to mechanical technologies.
This is due to the time and work
spent accessing the on-site
sanitation technology,
and the low volumes of sludge
collected and transported
for treatment.
This is an inequality for
the urban poor that
should be considered.
In this module, we have learned that
a number of different collection
and transport technologies
are used in urban areas
corresponding to different physical
and socio-economic realities.
In addition, a number of different
collection and transport
technologies
were introduced that are appropriate
for different local context
considering accessibility
transport distance,
and service costs.