After your second week
at this introduction
to fecal sludge management,
do you feel like you already
have a grasp on fundamentals?
Are you ready to move on
to the treatment technologies now?
You now know the four
treatment objectives
we will focus on in this course:
Solid-liquid separation,
Stabilization
nutrient management,
and pathogen reduction.
How do they relate to health
and environmental impacts
and the physical, chemical
and biological mechanisms
for how they're achieved.
Developing and understanding
of treatment mechanism
is very important,
as it is a basis for applying
existing fecal sludge
treatment technologies
developing new ones
and adapting existing ones
from waste water
and sludge treatment practices.
We will start exploring examples
in more detail next week
with established treatment
technologies that rely
on physical mechanism
such as gravity filtration
and evaporation,
biological metabolism
applied for stabilization,
nutrient management
and pathogen reduction,
mechanisms of pathogen reduction
and chemical treatment.
The number one goal
of fecal sludge management
is always public health,
but also related and important
are environmental health,
and resource recovery.
You now know multiple ways
in which treatment products
can be used for resource recovery,
which ones are at different levels
of established, innovative
or in development
and in way in which
they can be used.
Designing for the final end use
or disposal option
of treatment products
is critical to ensure that affluents
and end products achieve adequate
and appropriate levels of treatment
that systems are not over-designed,
wasting financial resources
and that systems
are not under-designed
risking public
and environmental health.
in addition to setting
treatment objectives
resource recovery can
offset treatment cost
and help ensure sustainable
operation of treatment plants.
In many cities treatment
does not yet exist
and hence treatment
products do not yet exist.
So how can you determine
potential markets for something
that doesn't exist yet?
This is why you learn about
the concept of replacement
or surrogate products that have
an equivalent resource value
and can be used
as proxies to explore markets.
Were you able to download
and review the guidelines
for the implementation of
the market driven approach?
We use the example of Kampala.
Have you thought about which
treatment products have
the greatest market
attractiveness in your city?
Please add your comments
in the discussion forum.
You also learned
about the importance
of designing management options for
the actual quantity
and characteristics of fecal sludge
based on the local context.
Without reasonable estimations
you cannot accurately design
a management plan.
You also learned about
the different places in
the service chain or characteristics
and quantities can be assessed
to evaluate current and future
demands for management needs
to help ensure long term
sustainable management.
You know what parameters
of characterization are
can select relative parameters
depending on
the management question
such as treatment objectives,
type of end use, or collection
and name important characteristics
of treatment products
for resource recovery,
including irrigation
soil conditioner, compost,
fertilizer, solid fuel, liquid fuels
animal feed.
Were you able to download
(INAUDIBLE) or PRG resources?
Also in week two, you learned about
manual and mechanical ways
in which fecal sludge is collected
and transported from
containment to treatment.
Why urban areas rely on
a range of technologies
and which are appropriate
based on the context.
In week five, we will visit this
in more depth with two more modules
one on collection and
another one on transport.
Based on week two, what ideas do you
have not for implementation
of fecal sludge management
in your city?
Ideas for resource recovery
how would you attempt
to quantify fecal sludge?
Please share you ideas
on the discussion forum.
Please, also visit
the platform website
for a complete list of
additional resources.
So, now we're ready
to move on to week three
where you will learn about
treatment technologies
for the centralized
to semi-centralized
treatment of fecal sludge.
The week will start out with
an overview of technologies
based on their level of development
whether they are established,
transferring from other technologies
or innovative in development,
in an overview of their different
treatment objectives and how they
need to be linked together
to achieve overall objectives.
When thinking about
treatment objectives
keep in mind how they relate to
different types
of resource recovery.
We will present a number
of established technologies
and for each one you will learn
about the treatment process
important operation and maintenance
requirements and design parameters.
The week will then wrap up
with an example of how
a number of technologies can
be combined in the design
of the treatment plant.
Treatment technologies will again
be covered in more
detail in week five.
Thanks for joining,
see you next week.