In other modules
we've introduced you
to treatment objectives
for fecal sludge
and markets for treatment products.
In this module we will provide you
with an overview
of treatment technologies
to meet these objectives
and market demands.
Following this module you'll
be able to explain different levels
of technology development,
list technology based
on the level
of technology development
and group technologies
by treatment objectives.
Many technologies exist for
the treatment of fecal sludge
such as planted drying beds,
co-composting, fly larvae composting
paralysis , or lime treatment.
These different technologies
have different levels of research
design, operating
and maintenance experience.
for example, unplanted drying beds
have been extensively researched
and implemented for
fecal sludge treatment
in the past twenty years.
This (INAUDIBLE) research facility
in Dar es Salaam, Tanzania.
Such research has produced knowledge
for treatment design and operation
for example, on influent of sand
filter diameter and filter depth
on the treatment performance.
Here's an example of
a full scale construction operation
on drying beds for fecal sludge
treatment in Kampala.
Examples like this
provide further information
or example how to best remove
sludge from drying beds
or dewatering
and drying times.
Such information can then
improve further treatment
designs and operations.
We call technologies with this level
of development
and operating experience
established technologies.
Other established technologies
include planted drying beds
co-composting, setting-thickening
tanks and deep row entrenchment.
In contrast to
established technologies
technologies that are available
that are established for
the treatment of other waste,
such as waste water
and solid waste.
We call these technologies
Transferring technologies
as information operation
is currently still being
transferred and adapted
for fecal sludge.
These technologies include
anaerobic digestion, incineration
vermi-composting, lime treatment
and mechanical
dewatering, as shown here
for a fecal sludge
treatment plant in Manila.
These technologies can
be used for treatment
by less reliable information
available on their design
and operation with fecal sludge
compared to
the established technologies.
Fecal sludge management
is a really dynamic field
and many innovative technologies
are also being developed.
For example pyrolysis,
ammonia treatment
fly larvae composting,
or pelletizing, as shown here
the fecal sludge
treatment plant in Durban.
These technologies are currently
in their research stage
in preparation for scaling up.
So why do we distinguish
technologies as established
transferring and innovative?
The level of technology development
is and important indicator
in selecting
an appropriate technology
based on the level of adaption,
research, innovation, as well
as design, operation and maintenance
that will be required for successful
implementation of this technology.
Established technologies can
be more reliably implemented
but much less information's
available for the transferring
and innovative technologies.
Therefore, established technologies
should selected when
limited capacity
for this adaption, innovation
and research and development
are available.
For transferring technologies
and innovative technologies
the increased risk,
due to the lower level
of technology development
needs to be considered
and managed, this could be,
for example done through
public private partnerships
or research collaborating
with a university.
This could pay off as transferring
innovative technologies
have the potential
to be more efficient.
For example, in space requirements,
and they can also produce products
that have a higher revenue potential
that could off-set treatment costs.
You might be overwhelmed
by the large number
of treatment technologies
presented here, and you
just want to know what technology
do I need for drying out sludge
or to inactivate pathogens.
To answer this question,
it is best to group technology
based on treatment objectives,
Solid-liquid separation
sludge stabilization,
nutrient management
and pathogen inactivations.
Technologies for
Solid-liquid separation
include drying beds, mechanically
dewatering technologies
and Settling-thickening tanks.
These technologies are designed
to separate solids
and liquid material
in fecal sludge.
For example, on this planted
drying bed in Thailand
sludge is loaded on the surface
of the sand filter layer.
Solids and fecal sludge
remain on the surface
of this filter layer
while the liquid passes
through the liquid layer
and is collected at the bottom of
the filter in the drainage network
for further treatment.
Treatment technologies typically
achieve several
treatment objectives.
For example, for plated
drying beds sludge can remain
on the surface for up to ten years
and also become stabilized
as you can see with the stabilized
sludge on the surface of this
planted drying bed.
Other treatment technologies
of sludge stabilization include
co-composting,
anaerobic digestion
fly larvae and Vermi-composting
and incineration
and pyrolysis.
Technologies for nutrient management
can include co-composting
deep row entrenchment,
and fly larvae and vermi-composting.
As always, the appropriate level
of inactivation of pathogens
for the intended use
of treatment products
must be a priority
to protect public health.
Co-composting, storage,
lime and ammonia treatment
and incinerating and pyrolysis
are technologies that achieve
high levels of pathogen
inactivation.
Frequently fecal sludge
is mostly comprised of water.
So all technologies for
solid-liquid separation
and also for example,
anaerobic digestion
produce liquid effluents
that require further treatment.
Technologies for effluent
treatment include infiltration
planted drying beds,
waste stabilization ponds
anaerobic baffled
reactors and filters
and constructive wetlands.
if treatment is located adjacent
to the waste water treatment plant
you can also include co-treatment
with waster stabilization ponds
or even technologies based
on activated sludge process.
Treatment that adequately
protects public
and environmental health
requires combinations
of different treatment technologies
with different treatment objectives.
Let's look at one example.
This picture shows the Dumaguete
treatment plant in the Philippines.
It has the capacity to treat
80 cubic meter of fecal sludge
from septic tanks per day.
At Dumaguete, the sludge (INAUDIBLE)
into an anaerobic waste
stabilization pond.
Following the effluent from
this waste stabilization pond
is further treated in facultative
and maturation waste
stabilization ponds
and constructive wet lands.
The solids that settle in anaerobic
waste stabilization ponds
are dewatered
and dried pm dying beds.
In separate modules
you will learn more
about these treatment technologies.
This will enable you
to select technologies
for a complete fecal sludge
treatment plant
and know important
design considerations.
You now have a good overview
of treatment technologies
for fecal sludge, but remember
technology is only
a part of the solution
next to the level of technology
development and treatment objectives
presented int his module,
consideration like capital operation
and maintenance cost
the existing institution
arrangements and capacity
the enabling environment
and socio-economic characteristics
need to be considered and will
be discussed in separate modules.
In this module, you were introduced
to different treatment technologies
for fecal sludge.
Technologies have different levels
of technology development
based on existing level of knowledge
of research, design,
and operation and maintenance.
This should be considered when
selecting treatment technologies.
Knowing the treatment objectives
for treatment technologies
so for example, solid-liquid
separation from unplanted drying bed
of sludge stabilization,
nutrient management
and pathogen inactivation
for co-composting
are important to select
and combine fecal sludge
treatment technologies
for a complete fecal
sludge treatment plant.