Composting is the controlled
decomposition of raw
organic material into biologically
stable humic substances.
This is carried out by
micro organisms
and invertebrates in
the presence of oxygen.
The final produced compost is stable
doesn't degrade further
and is an excellent soil amendment.
In fact the use of compost as
a soil amendment is
o well established
that it was first documented
2000 years ago.
Following this module,
you'll be able to explain
co-composting treatment
processing operation
discuss operation
and maintenance requirements
and name design parameters.
Since composting
is so well established
there's already a wealth
of information available.
If you want to know
about the science
operation, or technologies
of composting
I recommend watching
the composting modules
in the third week of our
MOOC on municipal solid waste.
You could also download
the decentralized composing
book from our website
and also the international water
management association
or IWMI series
on resource recovery and reuse
specifically volumes 2, 3 and 15.
in this module I will not focus
on composing science
I will focus on the factors that
are specific to co-composting
of fecal sludge, based on
the operating experience of IMWI
with co-composting in Ghana
who helped me to prepare this module.
So why do you need to co-compost?
Why not just compost
fecal sludge on it's own?
The Carbon to Nitrogen
or C to N ratio is too
low in fecal sludge
so you need to mix it with
carbon rich organic matter.
For example, in Ghana the dewaterd
fecal sludge that IMWI
is working with
has a Carbon to Nitrogen ratio of
11 plus or minus 3
so input materials to compost
actually need to have a C to N ratio
between 25 to 1 and 35 to 1.
Let's stay in this table
for your reference
are types of organic waste that
you could use for co-composting
depending on their availability,
cost and qualities.
Qualities such as moisture,
carbon to nitrogen ratio
and particle size.
the qualities will also affect
required composting times
to achieve stabilization.
For co-composting IWMI
is using food waste with
the Carbon to Nitrogen ratio
of between twenty-eight
to thirty-two to one
and sawdust with the Carbon
to Nitrogen ration of about fifty.
Another important
operating consideration
is that fecal sludge
is mostly moisture
and so it needs to be dewatered
prior to co-composting
for example, with drying beds.
IMWI is starting with
fecal sludge that is 93-99% water.
Shown here is the sludge in Ghana
just being loaded into drying beds.
It's also important to consider
the source of the fecal sludge.
A sludge that is very fresh,
with short storage times
will not dewater as well
for example public
or commercial toilets
so then it needs to be mixed
with more stable sludge
that has a longer storage time.
It also needs to be considered that
the two different types of sludge
will have different total
solids concentrations.
Following dewatering
the sludge from these beds
is 20-35% total solids
or 65-80% moisture.
In general it is removed from
drying beds when it is spade-able
meaning that you can shovel it.
The residents time
on the drying beds
depends on the climactic conditions
and in Ghana varies
between 7 to 21 days.
The food or market waste
also needs to be sorted
to remove inorganic waste that
you want to keep out of the compost.
And in the case of IMWI
also needs to be air dried
for two days to reduce
the moisture content
from as high as 75%
down to 50% or less.
Sawdust on the other hand
typically does not require drying.
Compost feed in general needs
to be around 50-60% moisture
like a damp but not wet sponge.
The next consideration for
pre-treatment prior
to the composting process
is particle size.
Feed stock that is too large
will take too long to compost
but if the pieces are too small
it can also reduce pore space
and oxygen transfer.
Shown here is manually breaking up
food waste prior to co-composting.
If the dewatered fecal
sludge is in large clumps
it also needs to be
broken down first.
So now you're ready to build
your own compost pile.
Which technology will you use?
Obviously prior to this step
a decision would have to been made
on technologies.
Factors influence the decision
of a technology including investment
maintenance, space, time and labor,
also volumes need to be considered.
This decision matrix is covered in
the solid waste management MOOC.
Other important design
factors include a roof
to ensure the compost does not
get too wet in the rainy season
or dry out too fast in the sun.
Prior to making your compost pile,
you need to determine the correct
ratio of fecal sludge and
organic waste to end up with
the proper moisture,
Carbon to Nitrogen ratio
and particle size for composting.
In the case of IMWI
they are mixing 1500kg
of organic waste to 500kg
of dewatered fecal sludge
to make a pile that's 2000kg.
Alternatively they measure
by wheelbarrow, 48 wheelbarrow
organic waste to 16 wheelbarrow
of dewatered fecal sludge.
These two streams are
mixed together in a heap
with around 13L of water,
sprinkled in with the watering can
and then it's all mixed together.
Here's a heap that was made
with market waste, sawdust
and fecal sludge.
During the processing you will
need to control the temperature
and moisture.
This is done by turning,
aeration, and adding moisture.
PH also needs to be monitored
as does temperature with time
as an indicator
of pathogen reduction.
The temperature needs to be
maintained at 50 degrees Celsius
or higher for more than four weeks
to achieve adequate
pathogen reduction
which is especially important
when composting the fecal sludge.
However, you also do not
want the pile to get too hot
because although
heat kills pathogens
it can also be bad for
the organisms doing the composting.
In IMWI 90-100%
of helminth eggs are inactivated
during an 80 day composting period.
And for heap composting
stabilization takes
two to for months
depending on the feed stock.
Depending on the technology
and management however
the processing time varies
and it could even be up to a year.
Compost piles are turned
by moving them from
one place to another,
to ensure that all parts are
evenly treated.
This is important
for stabilization
and also pathogen reduction.
You see, this pile is still
in the active phase
and it's steaming.
Water is also added
during the turning process.
Prior to selecting composting
as an option
it is important to evaluate
the potential end users
and the market demand,
as it drives the continuity
of the whole system.
If it seems viable,
then other factors to consider
include waster volumes,
availability, quality
economic viability, and local laws.
This book, Marketing Compost,
can also be downloaded from
(INAUDIBLE) website.
Depending on the market demand
one way to increase
the market potential
of compost is to create a product
that is fortified with nutrients
so that it is a fertilizer.
In addition because
the compost is bulky
transportation costs
need to be considered.
IMWI addresses this by
creating pellets
with added nutrients
from the finished compost,
that they call fortifier.
In summary,
variables that are required
for designing a composting facility
include waste streams,
availabilities
total volumes, total carbon
and total nitrogen
moisture
particle size and porosity
and markets.
Important parameters
for operation include
temperature
moisture
turning
aeration
PH, and indicators for things,
such as maturity and quality.
In this module we learned about
co-composting treatment process
and operation, design parameters
and operations
and maintenance requirements.
Important points to remember
about co-composting
include that with properly
maintenance temperature
you can achieve
pathogen reduction
and stabilization
dewatering the fecal sludge
is mandatory prior to composting
composting technologies
are low cost
but also require space
and the end product is a compost
which has the same uses
as any compost.
Thank you for joining,
see you next time.