Can you imagine trying to get from
one side of your city to another,
if all of a sudden traffic did not
follow any rules at all?
Depending on where you live,
certainly sometimes
it feels like this, but the reality
could be much worse.
What if there was no consequence
for parking cars in the middle
of the street, or trucks driving
on the wrong side of the road?
What if anyone could drive, even
5-year-old children?
Certainly with no clear laws,
responsibilities or enforcement
the system would be
much more dangerous
and would not provide as much
protection of public health.
Following this module, you will
have an overview
of the importance of legal
frameworks
for regulating and enforcing
roles and responsibilities.
Be able to explain difficulties
in implementation
with overlapping or gaps
in responsibilities,
and understand advantages
and drawbacks
to different institutional
arrangements.
As presented in other modules,
there are untold examples
of ways that faecal sludge management
service chain is not working.
From the household level,
when people cannot afford
to have faecal sludge removed,
manual and mechanical emptiers
who dump faecal sludge throughout
the urban environment
because they cannot afford transport,
lack of treatment plants,
or failed treatment plants,
and unsafe end use or disposal.
Like the traffic analogy,
this is because
faecal sludge management and on-site
sanitation are frequently
not recognized in law  with no one
mandated to deal with it.
So people are just doing the best
they can by themselves,
frequently with awful results.
Even when there are adequate laws
protecting public
and environmental health, they're
frequently not in force
and many projects only consider
one aspect of the service chain.
Subsidizing septic tanks
or building a treatment plant
but without considering
the organizational or financial
aspects to coordinate the entire
service chain.
To get where we want to be with
a fully functioning service chain
the system needs to be overseen
and monitored
by an entity with a clear mandate.
This is why it's so important
to have legal recognition
with a specific framework that
includes faecal sludge management.
Laws are required for defining
responsibilities
of each stakeholder, regulation,
enforcement, managing treatment plants.
Basically, adequate functioning
of the entire service chain.
Another frequently encountered
problem with incomplete,
institutional and regulatory
frameworks,
is overlapping responsibilities
or gaps in responsibilities
throughout the service chain,
resulting in a lack
of ownership or incentive
to fulfill roles.
If jobs and roles are not clearly
defined, how can people fulfill them?
How can they be monitored
for effectiveness?
Or if two people are responsible
for a job, maybe neither one does it
or one rejects the authority
of another?
To illustrate, I'll give you
a few examples.
Imagine in your city, you're designing
a faecal sludge treatment plant.
You need to find out
the requirements for the level
of treatment required
for use in agriculture.
Where do you go?
Ministry of Works?
Water? Sanitation?
Ministry of Health?
Ministry of Agriculture?
Environment authority?
You want to use treated faecal
sludge as a soil conditioner.
You need to find out if this
is allowed.
Where do you go?
Ministry of Agriculture?
Ministry of Health?
You are interested in starting
a  faecal sludge management company.
You need to find out if you are legally
allowed to start your own company.
Where do you go?
Ministry of Trade and Industry?
Registrar of companies?
Municipal Sanitation Department?
So you can see the current reality
in many cities
is fractured, duplication and gaps
in roles and responsibilities
and a lack of incentives on behalf
of decision makers
to change the status quo.
This figure from the faecal
sludge management book
represents a hypothetical
example of the number
of different stakeholders
that could be responsible
for aspects of the service chain.
As you have more stakeholders
involved, it provides
for more operational flexibility
to meet the needs at each step.
But also is increasingly complicated
in terms of enforcement,
monitoring and coordination.
For example, different stakeholders
for collection and transport
maybe results in more job creation,
but complicates
the delivery of collected sludge
to transport.
Or different stakeholders
responsible for treatment
and resource recovery, maybe results
in more effective marketing
and distribution, but then
the treatment goals
and end use goals need to be
carefully linked and monitored.
One entity responsible for
everything could ease coordination
but requires highly developed
managerial skills
and financial resources,
and relies on regulation
and enforcement to protect
public health.
This table, from the faecal sludge
management book
summarizes stakeholders and possible
responsibilities
in the organization of faecal
sludge management.
There are advantages
and disadvantages.
The optimal roles in different
countries and cities,
will depend on
the local stakeholders
and their intrinsic strengths
and weaknesses.
For example, a private company
might be able to provide
excellent design, build, and
operation of treatment technologies.
But obviously, should not be
responsible for setting the laws
regulations or enforcement
regarding treatment standards.
The private interest of a company
is to maximize profits
where sanitation and protection
of public health are of public good.
Enforcement needs to have clearly
recognized authority and be impartial.
Different arrangements also impact
financial transfers
which is covered in its own module.
So what can you do?
What are steps to take in your city
or country to tackle this issue?
First, you could get
politicians interested
in a previously unrecognized
sanitation approach.
Work on technical aspects
to draft a content.
Develop legal frameworks.
Obtain approval from politicians.
And enactment.
This process is long
but necessary and worth the effort
for sustainable solutions.
For example, based on the experience
of my colleague
working for the World Bank
in Maputo,
this was 1 year for step 1,
2 years for step 2,
6 months for step 3, and 18 months
for step 4 and 5.
What are further steps
you could take?
You could negotiate an agreement
with the relevant authorities
to legally make an exception
to a project.
This is called the moratorium.
The success of the project
could help
eventually change
the law or standards.
For example, the law on dumping fees
was lifted
for small faecal sludge
management operators,
developing services for
low income areas in Maputo.
Critically review the law
and regulations.
Laws are not usually black or white.
You can consult with key
stakeholders to see if an idea
fits into the legal framework.
Other possibilities include thinking
of ways to organize more efficiently.
For example, if collection and
transport is by private companies
it's more efficient to organize
if there's a strong association
for engagement, outreach, education,
regulation, and enforcement.
Also important is to build trust
with the emptiers
and consult them on project design
and solutions.
For further guidance on action steps,
a valuable reference
is the World Bank's faecal
sludge management tools
which provide application, diagnostic,
and decision support tools
for achieving city-wide sanitation
presented with case studies for how
they relate to five different cities.
This is where SANDEC's technical
expertise
on faecal sludge management
is included.
Tool 4, Service Delivery Action
Framework explains what it means
to conceptualize institutional
interventions.
This table from the Service Delivery
Action Framework
walks you through action steps
for your city
based on where they are in
the development of services.
It addresses the national and local
levels, and citizens,
the users of sanitation
infrastructure.
It highlights action steps
based on current levels of basic
intermediate, or consolidating
service provision.
It is useful to help you address
the 'what next',
build on what currently works,
and identify areas
to prioritize and focus actions.
I recommend downloading the tools.
For additional information,
please refer to chapter 12
of the faecal sludge
management book.
The case study of Lusaka, presented
in this module of the SANDEC
Planning and Design of Sanitation
Systems and Technologies MOOC
for an example of a bottom up
approach to incrementally
improve service provision.
What types of things can you start
to implement now in your city?
And this module, for the case study
in Indonesia
as an example of a national program
starting up and going to scale.
In conclusion, in this module
you learned about
the importance of legal frameworks
for regulating
and enforcing roles
and responsibilities.
Difficulties with overlapping
or gaps in responsibilities.
And advantages and drawbacks
to different institutional arrangements.
Thanks for joining.
See you next time.