Close to the Earth's surface
we have a magnetic field
which resembles, in terms of its shape,
a bipolar magnetic field,
typically the one
that you would get from a magnet
with a North Magnet Pole,
and a South Magnet Pole.
Now, the expression of the amplitude
of the magnetic field
is depicted here as a function
of the distance
to the center of the Earth,
and the so-called "magnetic latitude",
which is pretty much like
the Earth's latitude,
with zero degrees at the Equator,
and a +90 at the North Magnetic Pole,
and a -90 at the South Magnetic Pole.
So you see, you have this factor
1 + 3 sin&sup2; of the magnetic latitude,
and the square root of that
times the B_0,
which is the magnetic fields
on the Equator,
and at the distance
from the center of the Earth
equal to the radius of the Earth,
so on the Earth's surface.
And R is the distance
to the center of the Earth.
So this is an expression of B
as a function of R and λ.
And here we have a depiction of this shape
of the magnetic field lines
in the vicinity of the Earth.
Again, I'm talking
about the vicinity of the Earth
being typically one,
up to two Earth radii,
because beyond that we have
variation due to the solar wind,
we'll talk about that later.
But this is the shape
of the magnetic field lines.
You have the Earth,
North Magnetic Pole
to South Magnetic Pole here.
And what you have is a set
of so-called "radiation belts".
This is the inner radiation belt,
and outer radiation belt.
These are regions where
the magnetic field of the Earth
is creating some regions
where you have an increased density
of charged particles,
mainly protons and electrons,
and they are moving
to the North and to the South,
they are reflected,
due to the increased density
of magnetic field lines,
they are reflected,
and they come to the North
and they go back to the South,
and to the North, and the South.
They are really trapped in these regions.
And these are regions,
which are important,
because you have an increased flux
of protons, electrons.
Electrons are are not too harmful,
but protons could be.
And you also have an increased
amount of radiation
coming from outside of the solar system,
typically galactic cosmic rays
that could be trapped in these regions.
The lower boundary
of the inner radiation belt
is about 550 to 600 km
above the Earth's surface,
so it's above the altitude
of the International Space Station.
The ISS is not going anywhere
in the radiation belt,
but I remember when
we had the Hubble mission,
up to 600 km altitude,
we had, sometimes,
a manifestation of the effect
of this inner radiation belt
by flashes in the eyes, for instance.
Now, as I indicated already,
in the inner radiation belt
you have protons and electrons.
In the outer radiation belt
it's mainly electrons.
So the outer radiation belt
is not as harmful to electronic systems
than the inner radiation belt.
The energy of these particles
in these belts
is bigger than 30 keV,
and all the way to 100 MeV.
Now, this is an artist depiction
of the magnetosphere,
which is the geometry, and a region,
I would say, around the Earth
which is dominated
by the Earth's magnetic field,
which magnetic field,
is as mentioned before,
pretty much like a dipolar,
bipolar magnetic field
in the vicinity of the Earth.
But it's significantly distorted
when you go away from the surface.
Typically of the order of 5,
up to 10 Earth radii toward the Sun,
there's a significant distortion,
in the anti-Sun directions also.
So on the left-hand side you have,
it's not up to scale,
but you have the Sun,
you have the solar wind flowing
in all directions from the Sun,
and when the solar wind,
which is made of charged particles,
interacts with
the magnetic field of the Earth
it distorts it completely,
and the boundary
between the magnetosphere
and the flow of particles
from the solar wind,
which is mainly protons, electrons,
is called a "magnetopause".
And it's interesting to see
that you have certain regions
where you have the possibility
for charged particles
to get in the vicinity of the Earth.
Basically, the charged particles
follow the magnetic field lines,
and in the equatorial regions of the Earth
we have protection
against these particles,
because the magnetic field lines
are pretty much horizontal.
But in the region of the Magnetic Poles,
you have a possibility
for these particles, the solar wind,
to get into the low atmosphere
and create aurora,
or Northern Lights, or Southern Lights,
as we will see afterwards.
In the anti-Sun direction
what is interesting
is that the magnetic field lines
of the Earth seem to be open.
They are open to the interstellar medium.
Now, this is a very nice picture
of Northern Lights
taken from
the International Space Station.
On the upper right,
you see one of the large solar arrays
of the U.S. segment of ISS.
You have the Earth horizon,
you have the airglow,
which we mentioned before,
at about 100 km altitude,
and then you have this magnificent
green light, Northern Lights.
Now, the Northern Lights
and Southern Lights are produced
by excitation of nitrogen,
and mainly oxygen atoms,
by the electrons flowing
from the solar wind.
And typically the Northern
and Southern lights
are produced at about
the altitude of the airglow,
100 km altitude and above,
and somewhat below,
but mainly above the airglow altitude.
It's nice to see on this picture, also,
just above and to the left of the center
you have the constellation Orion,
with the three aligned stars
of the Orion's Belt.
This is a view of the Earth
from the International
Space Station, taken recently.
We are over the Indian Ocean:
it's at night.
We have the landscape
illuminated by the Moon,
and we have a beautiful view
of the Southern Lights.
We are in the vicinity
of the South Magnetic Pole,
which is somewhat
on the right-hand side of the picture,
and a very clear view
of the Southern Lights,
and also of the airglow,
which gives you a scale
of the height of
the Southern Lights themselves,
the airglow being at 100 km
above the Earth's surface.
It's accelerated motion.
It's been taken so that you have
about 10 times increase
in the velocity of the Space Station
versus the Earth.
We move fast, but not as fast
as you can see here.
It's interesting to see the vertical line
in the structure of these Southern Lights,
which are along the magnetic field line,
which, in the vicinity
of the South Magnetic Pole,
are close to the vertical.
You see also a lot of dynamics
in the Southern Lights.