Hello and welcome to this new lesson
of our course, introduction to
Java programming.
The objective of this new lesson
is to teach you
to organize your code by
modularizing it
using your own functions.
Functions are an aspect
of processing,
just like expressions
and operators
and control structures, which
we studied previously.
Functions operate, in general,
on data,
and the data will influence how these
functions work.
Up until now, the programs
that you have written
were made up of a linear sequence
of instructions
with no global organization
and with no sharing of repeated tasks.
For example, if the task consisting
in asking the user for a number,
as the following code does,
had to be executed several times
in our program,
for example, once to ask for a number
of points,
once for a time, and once for an age,
what would you do?
You might be tempted
to copy the code
as many times as necessary to
the appropriate places,
but of course, this is a very
bad solution.
One must never duplicate
code when programming.
Do not be tempted by the copy-paste.
What you would like to copy should
be put into a function.
Why must one never duplicate
code?
It makes the program
unnecessarily long,
hard to understand and,
especially, hard to maintain.
One would have to apply every
modification to each of the copies.
This is why every
good programming language
provides means to allow
reusing parts of a program.
And in Java, this is done by using
what we call functions.
Let's consider for example
the following program:
This program starts by asking
for the number of points obtained
by a first player,
using, as you can see,
a do..while loop
to force the user to input
a value between 0 and 100.
Then, the program asks the user
for the time taken by the first player
which will be, in this case,
a value between 1 and 60.
And from this number of points
and this time,
the program calculates the score
of the first player.
Then, the program repeats these
operations for a second player.
It asks for a number of points, a time,
and calculates the score of the second player.
Finally, the program compares
the scores of the first and second
players,
to display which of these players has won.
You can see that in this
program,
the code which consists in asking
for a number of points, a time,
and calculating a score from
the number of points and the time
is repeated twice in the program,
once for each player.
In such a case,
one must use a function
to avoid code duplication.
For this, I will first put to the side
the code that I am interested in,
that is, the code which asks for
a number of points, a time
and which calculates a score.
I will put this code at the
end of the program,
but before the last closing brace.
I will put this code between
an opening brace
and a closing brace.
This code will constitute what
we call the body
of my function-to-be.
We will have to name this body.
I will call it saisieEtCalcul
(inputAndCalculate).
This will allow us to refer to it in
the rest of the program,
and it will be the name
of my function-to-be.
My function must give the score
that it will calculate
to the rest of the program.
For this, I will start by removing
any references to the first player,
since my function will be
valid for any player.
I will add the return keyword to
the end of my function,
followed by the name of the
variable scoreJoueur (TN: playerScore)
to indicate that my function
must return the value
contained in the scoreJoueur variable.
Don't worry, we will go over
this in detail
in the rest of the lecture.
The scoreJoueur variable was
defined with a double type,
and so the function will return a
value of type double.
We must indicate this to
the rest of the program,
and this is done by adding double
before the name of the function.
Another aspect of functions
is that they can use
values given by the rest of the
program to work.
Our function, saisieEtCalcul,
is relatively simple,
it doesn't need any such values.
To indicate this, we add,
after the name of the function,
opening and closing parentheses.
Now, all I need to do is add the static
keyword to the beginning of this line,
for reasons we will see later on
in this course.
That's it! We have created
our first function.
I will now use
my saisieEtCalcul function
to ask for a number of points,
a time,
and to calculate the score of the first player.
For this, I will return to the place
where I had extracted the code
that I used to create my function,
that is, here.
I will declare a variable scoreJoueur1
(player1Score)
which I will initialize
with the value given
by the saisieEtCalcul function.
To do this, I will indicate
the name of the function
followed by opening and
closing parentheses.
This instruction initializes the
scoreJoueur1 variable
with the value given by the
saisieEtCalcul function.
This use of the saisieEtCalcul
function
is known as a function call.
I can do exactly the same thing
to initialize the second player's
score.
I can replace all of this code
by a simple call to my
saisieEtCalcul function.
And you can see now
that the program
is a lot more concise.
Creating the saisieEtCalcul
function allowed me
to avoid duplicating code.
It is also interesting, however,
to create a function
to be able to focus on a somewhat
difficult part of the program,
such as, here, the calculation
of a player's score.
As before, I will extract the
code I am interested in,
put it in between braces,
and my new function will return
the player's score,
a value of type double.
I will name my new function,
simply, score.
For now I will put
opening and closing parentheses
after the name of the function.
As before, my function
will return the player's score,
thanks to the return
keyword.
But the difference, compared to what
we had before,
is that this function now needs
the variables nbPoints
and temps (TN : time).
So in this case, I will
add these variables
between these parentheses here,
which will constitute what we call
the parameters of the function.
I will return, again, to the place
where I extracted the code
to create my function, and
call my function there instead.
I can do that here, for example,
I will call my function by supplying
it the values
of the variable nbPoints
and of the variable temps.
This is how it's done.
To sum up, I first identified the code
that was to be put into a function.
I extracted this code to create
my new function,
which I named.
I identified what we needed
as inputs to the function
for the function to work.
I also identified what my function had
to return
to the rest of the program.
Now I can replace the part
of code that I have extracted
by a call to my function.
A function is thus
a reusable fragment of a program,
like the saisieEtCalcul function,
or important as-is,
like the score function.
It is characterized by a body,
which is the program fragment
which is reused or emphasized.
It is characterized also by its name
which will allow us to refer
to that function.
It can have parameters, which are the
set of variables
external to the function and which the
body needs to work.
The function can also
return a value,
and this value must have a type.
Finally, the use of a function
in the rest of the program
is known as a function call.
In  object-oriented languages
such as Java,
the term method
is usually used
in place of function.
From now on, we will say
method rather than function.
A method thus has three aspects.
First, its header, which
we can see as a summary
of what the method does,
since it is made of its name,
of its parameters,
which correspond to the values
which the method needs
to work,
and of the type of value which
the method will return.
The second aspect is the
definition of the method,
which starts with the header,
but which is also made up of the body
of the method,
which contains the code
which will be executed
when we use the method.
The last aspect is the use
of the method,
or its call,
where we will use the method
by giving it actual values for its
parameters,
and where the method will usually
return a value
that we will be able to use, for example,
to initialize a variable.
In practice, the developer,
that is, the person who will write
the definition of the method,
is not necessarily the same person as the
programmer
who will use the method.
The programmer using the method does
not need to know its body.
All that he needs to know
is its header, to be able to call it.
The header thus acts as a link between
the programmer using a functionality
and the developer of this functionality.
In Java, we speak of APIs, for
application progamming interfaces
which describe the interfaces for
using a set of data.
The programmer must respect
the header of the method
when he calls the method,
and the developer will ensure
that the header corresponds to the problem
that the user wishes to solve
by calling the method.