In a previous episode, we introduced
the notion of functions, of methods,
and their use in programming.
Today, we will focus on what happens
when we use, when we call a method.
Basically, at this stage, we know that
the concept of a method is
associated to three aspects: the header,
the definition and the call.
And today, we will look in detail
into what happens
at the call.
Let's go back to our example
on calculating means.
Here, we have a little main program
which asks
the user to input two grades.
These two grades are input by the
user via the keyboard,
and the mean of these two
grades is displayed.
The calculation of the mean is done
here by calling a method,
the "moyenne" method.
[TN: "moyenne" means "mean"]
And we will now study the mechanisms
involved in such a call.
Here, we have a real example of a method
call, where the method called
is "moyenne", which we call by
passing two arguments to it,
in the form of expressions which
will of course correspond
respectively to the two parameters
of the method.
Note that we usually name "parameters"
the data which
the method needs to work as described
in the header of the method,
and we name "arguments" the actual data
passed to the method
at the moment it is called.
So the goal here is to examine
what happens at the moment a call
like this is made.
The first step that is executed actually
consists in evaluating
the different arguments and in Java, this
evaluation will systematically be done
left-to-right.
So here, the first argument
is evaluated.
The expression is evaluated, which will
return a value of 2.3.
Second expression.
This will produce a value of 4.25.
Then, second step, a link will
have to be established
between these arguments and the
parameters of the method.
This is what happens during the
second step.
So, during the second step, the
parameter x will be matched with the result
of the first expression. x will be worth 2.3.
And y will be matched with the
evaluation of the second
expression: 4.25.
We are thus in the situation where the
parameters x and y have
actual values with which the method
will now be able
to work and run.
Third step: the body of the method
is executed.
Here, the body consists in a single
instruction which is the return,
the return statement right here.
So here, the body doesn't actually
execute anything in particular other
than the return statement.
Fourth step,
the expression which will serve as
a return value will now
be evaluated.
So basically, (x+y)/2 will be
calculated,
producing the following result.
And this value is now returned by
the method to make it
available to the program
that called it.
So actually,
this whole method call is replaced
by the result returned by the method.
So last step,
z takes a value of 3.275.
We have thus seen the five steps
that usually occur
when we call a method.
First step: the expressions which
are passed as arguments
to the method are evaluated.
Second, the values of these expressions
are assigned to the parameters
of the method.
The method then has access to all
the information that
it needs to work, and its body can be
executed.
Fourth step: the expression which follows
the first return statement encountered
during execution is evaluated and
the result of the evaluation of this
expression is then returned as
the result of the call.
These five steps occur in the most general
case; there are situations
where the process is somewhat simplified.
We know that in the most general case
a method needs
parameters, input data, and produces
a result as output.
However, there are some situations where
the method does not need any
input data. In such a case, of course,
steps one and two,
which consist in evaluating the expressions
passed as arguments and assigning
them to the parameters, no longer apply
(for a method without arguments).
Then, there are situations where there
is no output data, where the method
returns no result. And in this case, the
steps which consist in
evaluating the expression following the
return statement and returning this result,
i.e. steps 4 and 5, do not occur.
A method can easily call another method.
This is the case in this
little example where you have a "afficheScore"
(TN: means "displayScore") method which
takes as parameters a player, identified by
an integer, a number of points won
by the player and the time he spent playing,
and which will display
the player's score.
Here, it so happens that the score is
calculated according to the number
of points and the time spent, and the
calculation is done by a method.
The method is defined elsewhere
and takes as parameter the number of
points and the game time.
You now know the different steps which
are executed
when a method is called in a program, and you
now can see
a little diagram which summarizes
these various steps.
Here, we have a method "f"
called by a method "g".
The match between the parameters
of the method and the calling arguments
is done at the moment of the
method call.
So here, when we call the method, the
argument is copied into the parameter
of the method which uses this to
fulfill its job.
In the most general case, the method
calculated a return value
and this return value is transmitted to
the calling method which will be able
to use it to carry out its instructions.
You will no doubt have noticed all
along this episode that
there is a certain jargon, a terminology
associated to a method call.
Let's now summarize this jargon.
You will have understood that when I
speak of "calling a method", I mean
that I use the method; here, I am using
the method f to calculate
a result that I then assign
to a variable x.
When I speak of "passing a value"
as argument to a method, I mean
that this value is simply copied into
a parameter of the method.
And finally, when I say that a method
"returns" the value of y, for example,
I mean that the expression of the function
call will simply be
replaced by the returned value.
So if we take a real example now,
suppose that we have a
method "f" whose last instruction
is this one
Suppose that this method is called
like so, and that at the moment
of the call, the value of y is 5.
To say that the method
returns the value of y -- that is, 5 --
is the same as to say that we simply
replace this call by the return value,
i.e. 5.
And so, I can equally say "cos(0) returns
cosine of zero",
or "cos(0) returns 1", for example.