In a previous episode,
we examined the different steps
that follow when we call a method.
In the examples we have seen up until now,
the arguments passed to the method were
either simple values,
or expressions to evaluate.
We will now go into more detail
and see what happens
when the argument passed to the method
is a variable,
especially in the situation where
the method modifies the parameter
passed to it.
So let's consider the following concrete situation.
Suppose for example that we are
in a main program which declares
a variable v1 of the same type as
the one expected by the method.
When then invoke the method by passing
it an argument, the variable v1.
We saw in the previous episode that v1 was
copied into v
and [let's assume that] this method's purpose
is to modify v.
So the question we now ask
ourselves is:
when this method ends, is the
variable v1, declared in
the main program, modified by
the method or not?
In programming in general, we say that
v is "passed by value"
if the answer to this question is no,
and on the contrary, that v is
"passed by reference"
if the answer to this question is yes.
In the case of passing by value,
what happens is that the method
will work on a local copy of the argument
it is passed, v1.
So, when the method is called, when we
call it, the variable v1
is simply copied into a local area v,
local to the function,
and any modification of this local area
has no effect on
the original variable
In Java, let's first ask ourselves
what does it means to "modify v", exactly.
Because the answer to this question
will depend on the nature of the type [of v].
During an earlier episode on types,
we learned that in Java,
elementary data types were not
manipulated in the same way
as advanced data types.
By advanced data types, I mean for example
arrays
or strings.
Consequently, if I am manipulating
elementary-type data,
modifying v has only one
possible interpretation
If I try to modify v by assigning it
a different value,
then the memory area named v will clearly
contain a value
that is different from its previous
value, which actually is a value
of 10, here.
On the other hand, if I am working
on advanced-type data,
the situation is different.
Indeed, we have seen that values of
advanced data types were manipulated
via references, via indirections.
For example, if I manipulate a String-type
variable, I am not manipulating
the character striing directly,
I am manipulating a reference
to the character string.
Thus, when I speak of "modifying v",
what do I mean exactly [in this case]?
Am I modifying the reference?
Or am I modifying the memory area
pointed to by the reference?
Let's now place ourselves in the
situation where our method takes
a parameter of advanced data type.
For example, we can imagine that "type"
corresponds to an array of integers,
and in this case the reference v is
an indirection, a reference
to an array of integers that we can
represent in this way.
There are thus two possibilities for
modification here.
The one that comes most easily
to mind, perhaps,
consists in putting a different
value into v.
This would mean that we are
modifying the reference
itself, which would result, since I
am modifying the reference itself,
in making v point to another
array.
Second possibility for modification:
through the reference, I can modify
the referenced object, for example by
writing this, which would result in
a modification of the second element
of the array, like this.
So in Java, there are actually  two questions to
ask, rather than one.
First question: if my method
modifies the reference,
is the variable, the reference passed
as argument, modified
at the end of the method?
Second question:
if I modify the object referenced by
v1 via v, is the object referenced
by v1 modified?
It is important to know that in Java,
there exists only passing
by value, which means that a method
is always working
with only a copy of the argument that
is passed to it
when it is called.
In the case of advanced data types, it is
indeed a reference that is copied.
If I place myself in the situation where
I have a method "m",
without a return type here,
which takes as parameter
a variable of some undefined data
type named "x",
suppose for example that in a main
program, I call this
method in the following way, where I declare
a variable "val" of the correct type.
I then call my method, passing it "val"
as argument.
It is important to know that at
this moment, the value of val
is copied into an area local to the method.
So, let's go back to our original question,
by examining the case where "type"
is an elementary type.
For example, we can imagine that type
corresponds to the integer type, "int",
and so the routine modifying v could
simply be an incrementation
of this nature.
In our main program, v1 would be
declared with an integer type
and assigned an original value,
and we would invoke the method on v1.
So in this case, we find ourselves with a
variable v1 which contains
a value of 3 and at the moment
the method is called,
v1 is in fact copied into an area local
to the method, named v.
So here we would have a copy of the value.
If we then execute the body of
the method,
we would modify the content of v
since we are working on v
and we see that at no time is the value
of v1 affected by this modification.
So when the type is elementary,
the answer to this question
is no because of the passage by value.
So, let's now place ourselves in the
situation where our method is working
with an advanced data type.
As an example of advanced data type,
let's take an array of integers.
So here, in our main program, we would
write something that
looks like this.
Here, we end up in the following memory
situation; so we have
a variable v1 which contains a reference,
the address, in a way, to
the array 1, 2, 3.
So at the moment this method call is made,
we have seen that in Java,
we know only passing by value, which
means that v1 will be copied
into a local area v, local
to the method.
So here we have a memory area v,
local to the method, and in which
we will copy the contents of v1, i.e
the reference to the array.
We clearly see here that both v and v1
point to the same array in memory.
This means that for example, if I try
to modify the object
referenced via v, so if I try to do
this in the method,
if I modify the array
via this link,
since both v and v1 point to the same
area,
modifications done through
v are visible through v1.
This means that in the case where I
carry out a routine in the method
that modifies the referenced object, the
answer to this question is yes.
Let's now look at the second situation,
let's try to write
code which will modify, in the method,
the reference itself.
So here, due to passing by value,
at the moment of the method call we
have a copy of v1 in v, which means
that we are in this
situation here, where we have copied
the reference in v,
the reference to the array.
Now, let's attempt to modify this reference.
This can be done
for example like this: I declare another
array t, which has other
values, and I modify the reference
itself so I am making
this assignment here.
So here, I am in this memory situation,
I have a variable t which
contains a reference to another
array, so I have this link, and I make
this assignment, meaning that I
modify the reference itself.
This means that if I break this link,
this link doesn't exist anymore, and
now my local variable points to
the array referenced by t.
We thus see that with this manipulation,
since we modified the
reference on a local copy, v1 is not
affected by this modification;
when the execution of my method ends,
at that moment I still have
the address value within v1.
Which means, basically, that if I carry
out an instruction which modifies
the reference itself, the answer to this
question is still no, still
because of the passage by value.
Let's illustrate this discussion with real
cases, with real examples.
So, here we have a small main program
which begins
by declaring a variable "val". This
variable has an elementary type,
"int", which means that the value that
is associated to it is directly
stored in val. There is no abstraction,
no reference.
The second instruction invokes a method
m by passing it val as argument.
We have seen that in Java, there exists
only passing by value, which means that
the value of val is copied into an area
local to the method which is named x here.
So we are in the situation where x contains
the same value
as val, but in a different
memory area.
Then, the first instruction of the body of
the method is executed,
resulting in an incrementation of x. We
thus end up with a value of 2
for x, and when we display the value
of x, we can see that it does indeed
contain a value of 2.
Then, when the method ends,
if we want to display
the value of val, we realize that this
value is left unchanged.
It was not modified due to the passage
by value.
All this to say that the modifications
in this case are
effected inside the method and do
not affect the external
variable val.
Here is another situation, where
we modify a reference in the body
of a method.
Here, we have a main program
which declares a variable tab of
advanced type, an array of integer.
Advanced types are manipulated via
interactions,
we are thus in this memory
situation here,
where tab points to an array which,
in this case, contains one single
element containing 1.
Then, there is the call to the method m
which is executed, and we have seen
that there is only passing by value in
Java, meaning that tab is copied
into an area local to the method
which is x.
So we are now in the situation where
we have
copied the value of tab into x and so
x points to the same array in memory.
When the body of the method
is executed,
the first instruction encountered is the
one that creates a new array.
It will thus point to the new array
in memory with another
reference, which in this case contains
one single cell containing 100.
The second instruction tries to modify
the reference itself, so we
assign to x
the address of the new array, which
results in breaking
this link and creating a new
one to this array.
If, now, we display the value of the
first cell of the array x,
x[0], given the newly-created link,
obviously has a value of 100.
Once the method has finished executing
and we display the value
of the first cell of the tab array, we
can see that the modification done
on the reference itself is not
visible on the argument
because of the passage by value and
thus the value of tab[0] remains
unchanged and is still 1.
So the result of the execution of this
program show us that
modifications done within a method
on the reference itself are not
visible outside of the method, still because
of the passage by value.
Last situation: modification
of the referenced object in
the body of a method.
So we are now in the same situation
as in the previous example,
where the main program creates an
array containing a single cell worth 1.
When the method m is called by passing
it tab as argument, still because
of passage by value, tab is copied into
x, where x is an area local to
the method m.
We can clearly see here that both tab
and x reference the same array
So here, when we execute the body
of the method m, the first instruction
encountered will alter the first cell of
the array pointed to by x
which will modify this cell.
And we can see that the modification made
on the first cell of the array x
is also visible in tab.
So the execution of this display instruction
will clearly display
that x[0] has a value of 100.
When the execution of the method ends
and we pass to the next display,
since both tab and x point to the
same array,
displaying the value of tab[0] will
also output 100.
So the situation here is that the
modification made inside
the method is also visible outside
of the method despite
the passage by value.
Why?
Because both the area local to the
method and the argument
actually point to the same array.