In a previous episode, we went over
the three aspects
of methods.
We also talked about
the call (of a method).
Now, we will concentrate
on the concept of "method header".
Consider, for example,
the following complete example
where we wanted to compute the
mean of two numbers.
The header of the moyenne method
is this line here ("moyenne" means "mean").
A method is characterized
by a header,
that is, a description of its name;
the set of parameters that the
method must receive from the rest
of the program to be able to do the job;
and by the type of its return value
which the method will send back
to the rest of the program.
The syntax for the declaration
of a header is the following:
we start by the return type
of the method,
followed by the name we chose
for it and, between parentheses,
its set of parameters, which
can be empty,
parameters the method must receive from
the rest of the program in order to work.
In this lesson, we will also add
the static keyword
in front of the header;
here, in front of the return type.
This is specific to this introductory
course,
but will become an exception
and will be explained in the
object-oriented programming course.
Here are a few header examples.
This is the header of the example
mean-calculating method which
we went over in the previous slide.
Here we can see the name of the
method, moyenne;
the return type, double, preceded
by the static keyword here;
and finally, between parentheses,
the two parameters
which we pass to the moyenne
method
to compute the mean of these
two values.
Another example here, with a method
which does not take any arguments:
here, we simply give an empty set
of parameters to indicate
that the method which draws
a random number
does not require any information
from the rest of the program to do its job.
Here are now a few tips
for good practices
concerning writing method headers.
First, choose relevant names,
names which are descriptive, which
tell what the method actually does.
This will make your code clear
and easily understandable
and easier to maintain.
But of course, this supposes
that the method will do only what
it was designed to do.
It must not have what is called
"side effects",
that is, undesirable effects.
For example, if you have a method
which calculates the square root of a number,
which would be called "sqrt" and which
would take a parameterx of type double,
and which would return the square
root of x in the form of a double,
you would not expect
this method to write the
value in the terminal,
or to print error messages.
You expect it to do only one thing:
to calculate this value
and to return it to the rest
of the program
without polluting the outputs
or doing anything unwanted,
any "side effect".
Finally, last tip,
always start by writing the
header of your method
before writing the body
of the method.
Think first of the "what", that is,
the name,
what the method needs as parameters
to work,
and what it needs to return to
the rest of the program
before thinking about the "how",
that is, the specifics of the method's body.