In a previous episode, we learned
about the three aspects
of methods.
We discussed calling methods,
as well as
what a method header is.
In this episode, we will
concentrate specifically
on the concept of method
definitions.
If I go back to our usual example of
the mean calculation, the definition
of the "moyenne" (TN: means "mean") method
is this group of lines beginning with
the header, and comprising all the lines
here that follow the header, between braces.
The definition of a method serves, as
its name implies,
to define what the method must do,
that is, to specify the body
of the method, i.e the set of instructions
which are the reason why
we decided to isolate this method, to create
it in the first place.
From a syntax point of view, we will
start by providing the header,
-- as a reminder, this is the specification
of the return type followed by the name
of the method, followed between parentheses
by the list of parameters --
but in the definition, this header will
then be followed by a bloc which
will contain the instructions that will
allow the method to work,
which describe how the method will run.
Among these instructions, we will have
one or more "return" instructions
which will terminate the execution
of the body of the method
If I go back to the example of the "moyenne"
method, we can see the header
of the method, as we have seen it in the
previous examples, followed here
by the set of instructions which
allow the "moyenne" method to actually
do what it is meant to do, which is reduced
here to a simple "return" statement
which will calculate the sum of these
two parameters, x and y, and divide it by 2.
The body of the method is thus simply
a bloc of Java code,
that is a set of instructions between curly
braces which define
what the method must do. And in this bloc,
we can use the parameters of
the method as variables.
The value returned by the method
is indicated by a particular expression,
which is what we call a "return statement",
and which begins
by the keyword "return" and is followed
by a Java expression that is
evaluated and that will define the
return value of the method.
It must thus of course be of the same
type as the return type
of the method.
If I take the example of the mean calculation,
the return type we have here
is "double", for the mean,
and so we will have,
behind the "return" keyword, a Java
expression of type "double" which
will be the value returned upon
calling the "moyenne" method.
The return statement actually
does two things: it starts by defining
the return type of the method and
then the first return statement
ends the execution of the method
in which
it is called.
The return statement is sometimes
reduced to a single variable; for example
we could come across expressions like
"return x;" or even simply
a value, such as "return 3;".
These are only specific cases
with simple expressions, a single
variable or a particular value,
but it is by far not the general case and,
as we saw in the previous example,
in the general case it is a full Java expression
which is found after the "return" keyword.
A few comments about return statements.
First of all, it is easily possible to have
several return statements in the body
of one method. For example if I have a
method here which will return
the maximum of two "doubles", 'a' and 'b'
received as parameters, I can write
this method in the following way. I declare
a variable 'm' here that I will use
to return the maximum of
'a' and 'b'.
If 'a' is greater than 'b', then
I copy
the value of 'a' into 'm'; otherwise,
if 'a' is lesser than or equal to 'b',
this "if" statement jumps here and it
will of course be the value of 'b'
which will be copied into 'm'.
But we could absolutely have defined
this method in a more compact way,
as "max2" here, with simply two
return statements. This works
like that: if 'a' is greater than 'b', then we
will enter here and execute the
"return a;" statement and so this
statement will end the execution
of the body, and the maximum of 'a' and 'b'
in this case will be the value of 'a'.
However, if 'a' is lesser than or equal to 'b',
the "if" statement here will jump
to the "else" and so we will execute this
return statement here which will return to
the rest of the program the value of 'b'.
Second comment concerning the return
statement: as mentioned earlier,
the return type following the "return"
keyword must be the same as the type
declared in the header.
For example here, if I consider a dummy
method which takes no parameter
and which returns a "double".
Then I cannot return
an expression which would evaluate to
a type different from "double", for example
here I cannot return a "boolean" value.
It would throw an error
during compilation.
Third comment concerning return statements:
a return statement
must be the last instruction that the compiler
will encounter.
There cannot be any statements beyound
the return statement.
If we take, for example, this method whose
goal is to read a "double" [from the keyboard],
this method does not receive any parameters;
it will first ask
for a number, then read a number from the
standard input, the keyboard
typically. It will then assign to a "double"
declared here as 'n' the value read
from the keyboard, represented here as "keyb",
and will return this value 'n'.
But we find here in the "lire" method
[TN: "lire* means "read"]
a display of a line break.
This is absolutely impossible, we
cannot have such an instruction
following a return statement.
The return statement must be the
last statement to be executed,
otherwise the compiler will throw an error.
Last comment concerning return statements.
The compiler must guarantee that we can
always execute at least
one return statement. So for example
if I take another version
of the "lire" function that we have just
encountered, whose beginning is
exactly the same -- we will read a "double"
from the keyboard --
but assume that here, we only
want to return positive numbers.
So we add a condition here,
if 'n' is strictly positive.
If 'n' is strictly positive then we will
return 'n'. Up until now there
is no problem. However, at this stage,
it is possible for the user
to have entered a negative number,
for example they could easily
have entered -1. This would cause
the "if" condition to be false
and so we would jump over the "if" bloc,
and end up here
by executing nothing. The compiler
will not always be able to execute
the return statement.
It will thus throw an error.
A possible correction for this code
would of course have been
to bunch together the request for a number
and the return value into
a "while" loop for example. While
'n' is lesser than or equal to 0,
we would repeat the request for
a positive number, thus guaranteeing that
we will always end with a "return"
when the number
entered is strictly positive.
More specifically, since we will start
by asking the user for the value
before being able to test whether
this value is positive or null,
it will actually be a "do while" loop,
which we will be able to write here.
Then we can wonder about the condition,
which is here to return, to stop
when we have a strictly positive
number. This means that we will
want to loop, to repeat
the question as long as the number
is negative or null.
We will repeat this until we reach the condition
we wanted to have to return.
OK, so here we will add the "return n;" and
while 'n' is not how we want it to be,
while 'n' is negative or null, then
we will repeat, we will loop.
We will first display the message, so, this line,
then we will read the answer,
so we will add this line here.
Concerning the variable declarations,
we have to declare the scanner
and declare 'n', all these lines here,
outside the loop since
we don't need to repeat the scanner in the
loop and we only need to
declare 'n' once.
So basically, this gives the following code:
we will start by declaring
the scanner, once and for all, for the
keyboard input; then we will declare
the variable 'n'. It must be declared
outside of the loop since we will
use it here to return it. We also use it in the test,
which is outside of the scope of the loop's body.
So we declare this variable and
initialize it to a value which makes
sense, let's say 0. Then, we write
the loop bloc here,
the bloc which we want to repeat,
in which we will display
the message which asks the user to enter
a number. Here, we can even
specify our intentions exactly so that
the user knows what to do, we can say
that we want a strictly positive number.
Then, we read this number into 'n'
from the keyboard and so we loop while
we haven't received the right answer,
while 'n' is negative.
This is how we could have corrected
the error of the missing "return"
when 'n' was equal to or lesser than 0.
Let's now present a few specific examples
of methods; starting with
methods without return types.
I must first remind you that a method
in the Java sense has nothing
to do with a mathematical function.
A method in Java is simply a piece
of code that we reserved to be able to
use it, to avoid repetition,
and in this sense, this piece of code does
not necessarily need to return
anything to the rest of the program.
If this is the case, then we will specify
the fact that the method returns nothing
by using a specific return type,
the "void" type, to indicate
that we will not return anything
to the rest of the program.
In such a case, the "return" instruction is
now optional. We can absolutely
include no return statement at all in the
method's body. If we really need one,
for example in an "if" statement, in order
to stop the execution of the
body at a precise moment, then we
will be able to use a return statement.
For example, let's take a method which I will
call "afficheRacine" [TN: means "displaySquareRoot"]
and whose job is to display the square
root of a double-type parameter received
here and named "a".
If 'a' is negative, then as you know, we
cannot compute the square root and thus
there is nothing to display. So in this
case, if the condition for 'a' to be negative
is true, then the "if" will go to this
return statement
-- there is only a single "return" here -- and this
will thus end the execution of the method.
Note that since the return type of the
"afficheRacine" method is "void",
the "afficheRacine" method has nothing to
return to the rest of the program
and you can see here that the "return"
keyword is not followed by any expression
-- it would make no sense to have one,
we wouldn't know what to put after this "return".
If however 'a' is positive or null, then
the "if" condition is of course false
and at that moment, the "if" bloc
is simply ignored
and the program will continue after
the "if" to execute the display of the
square root of 'a'. And we then arrive to
the end of the method, where we
did not write any return statement. The
method will end here, and it is not at all
necessary to add any "return" here;
such a return statement is totally optional.
Other specific example of methods:
methods without parameters.
We already discussed these a little
but I would like to go over them again.
These are methods to which we do not
need to supply values from the
rest of the program in order for
these methods to work.
And in that case, we simply need
to specify, in the header,
the empty parameter list by writing
an opening parenthesis followed
by a closing parenthesis with nothing
in between.
Let's take an example of a method
whose only goal is to ask the user
for an integer and return it
to the rest of the program.
An example of a call to this method could
be as follows: here, we have a variable
of integer type which we initialize with the
result of the call to
"saisieEntier" [TN: means "inputInteger"].
This method doesn't need to receive anything
from the rest of the program; it can work
completely autonomously by declaring
a variable locally in which it will store
the user's answer.
It will display the request to enter an integer
for the user,
read the integer input by the user on the
keyboard, and put it into the temporary,
local variable, named "i" here, and
return this variable 'i'
to the rest of the program
You can clearly see that to do all of this,
the method did not need to receive
any information from the rest of the program,
it is thus a method without parameters.
As a handy aside: up until now,
we only needed the scanner
in the "main" method. We only had one method
up until now and we used
the scanner in the "main" method.
That is why
we declared it there, in the "main" method.
Here, we need it in another method,
the "saisieEntier" method.
So of course we could declare a scanner
like this in the
"saisieEntier" method, but it is not really
a good idea because each time you
call "saisieEntier" -- and the idea of this
function is that it will be called several times --
every time you call it, every time you
use the "saisieEntier" method
then this line which declares the
scanner will be executed every time
and you will re-declare a keyboard
every time. However, we have only
one keyboard, so the idea would be
to share this keyboard across the whole
program and thus to put this line here outside
of the class, outside of the method here.
So we find the declaration here, "static
scanner clavier etc.", with the link to
the keyboard "System.in". We will add,
for reasons which will be explained
in the object-oriented course, the
"private" keyword here,
for good practice.
At this stage, if you need a scanner in other
methods than the "main" method,
I encourage you to follow
this syntax here.
To finish, I would like to talk about the
"main" method. Yes, it is also a method!
It is simply a method whose name and
header are imposed.
It is the method with which any Java
program will start,
it will be the first method to be executed
when we start the program.
The header imposed for the "main" method
is as follows where, without
going too much into detail, we can see that "main"
takes, as an array of character arrays,
a list of arguments that would come
from the outside,
that would come from the program which
calls another program. But this
would lead us a bit too far, and we will
not use it in this class.
All that you need to know is that the
prototype of "main" must be
the one indicated here.