Let's end with a relatively simple concept,
method overloading.
In Java, it is possible to define
several methods with the same name,
provided that they don't have the
same list of parameters.
That is, if the number of parameters
or the types of these parameters,
are different.
This is known as method
overloading
and is very useful when we need
to write methods
which have similar tasks,
but whose specific processes
depend on the type of these parameters.
So in Java,
what sets these methods apart
is not necessarily their names
but also the types of their parameters,
which is technically known as
the signature of the function.
Note that the return type
is not part of this distinction.
You cannot have two functions with the
same names and the same parameters
and simply with different
return types.
This means that I can declare
2 functions f
where the first one has one
parameter of type int,
and the second, a parameter
of type double.
These two functions can have the
same return type
However, I cannot have two
functions with identical names
and which both have one
parameter of type int,
but which vary only in
their return type.
For example int for the first
and double for the second.
So to summarize, in Java, one can
have several functions with the same name,
but with different sorts of parameters.
For example, I can define these 3 methods
which are all named affiche (TN : affiche means display).
These are indeed 3
different methods,
since their lists of parameters
are different.
The first method has one
parameter of type int;
the second, one parameter of type
double;
and the third, 2 parameters of
type int.
When I call affiche(1), since the
argument 1 is of type int,
the first method will be called
and will display entier : 1.
When I call affiche (1.0), the
argument is of type double
and the second method will
be called,
thus displaying réel : 1.0.
And when I call affiche (1,1),
the third method will be called.
x1 will have a value of 1
and x2 also,
meaning the method will display
couple : 1,1.
Let's end this lecture with an
overview of the final version
of the example with which
we began this lecture.
The goal is mostly to show you
how the program is structured,
that is, where the different
methods are,
and where the declaration of the Scanner-
type variable is placed, for example.
At this stage of the course, a Java program
is made of one single class,
which contains the main
method here.
The other methods serve to
modularize the main method.
The idea is to have a main program,
a main method,
that is as concise as possible, and
auxiliary methods to make it modular.
Here, we have 3 auxiliary methods
which we placed after
the main method
but still within the only class
which makes up our program.
Actually, it could be made
more modular.
The saisieEtCalcul method could
use an extra method
which we could call saisie (TN: saisie means input)
and which would take as arguments
the bounds within which the
value should be input.
saisieEtCalcul could then invoke
this saisie method,
once to input the time and once
more to input the score,
which would avoid code
duplication in the while loop.
As you can see, we have only declared
one variable of scanner type,
outside of the method, right at the
beginning of the class, right here.
This variable is named clavier
(TN : clavier means keyboard)
and is available to all
the methods
defined between this
opening brace
and this closing brace.
In other words, this clavier
variable
has a global scope in the
entire class.
Indeed, this clavier
variable is used here and here,
in the saisieEtCalcul method.
But we can perfectly imagine
that it might be useful
to other methods of the program.
Declaring a single scanner-
type variable
is common practice for
simple programs
with a single class containing
a main method, as we have here.
Since this variable corresponds
to the computer's keyboard,
this is quite logical, as a computer
only has one keyboard.
This was the last video of our
lesson on methods in Java.
I now invite you to answer the Quiz
and to do the exercises.
Good luck!