Hello and welcome to this course on
municipal solid waste management
in developing countries.
My name is Chris Zurbrügg, I
am a researcher at Eawag.
Eawag is the Swiss Federal Institute
of Aquatic Science and Technology.
At Eawag, I work in the department
of Sanitation, Water and
Solid Waste for Development
abbreviated by Sandec.
I have over 18 years of research
and practical experience on
various issues involving the
topic of solid waste management
in low income countries.
This course is the third in a series
of e-learning initiatives jointly developed
by Sandec at the Eawag and EPFL.
The series covers the full range
of Sandec research activities.
For more information on other
courses, please visit our website.
With this first short introductory
module, I would like to introduce
you to the 5-week course program on
municipal solid waste management
in developing countries.
And on the way, we would like to
present it to you in a series
of video lectures, in video
quizzes and exercises.
We designed this course for
quite a broad audience.
The main requirement for taking
this course is that you are
excited and passionate
about this topic.
You might be a student or a
practitioner working in an NGO
or as a consultant or even in
national or local government.
Our hope is that with this course,
you, wherever you are and
whatever you do, can make
a change for the better.
This change is desperately needed.
Increasing population and urbanization
results in increasing waste generation.
Most cities are finding it difficult
not only to cope with
the existing situation but also to
anticipate future trends and
prepare and plan for this.
No or unreliable waste collection
results in waste accumulating
in neighborhoods and in
dangerous public health.
Deficient treatment or disposal
severely pollutes the environment
and contributes to global warming.
Before describing the program, let
us first look at the learning
objectives of this course.
We hope that, after this course,
you understand the current
situation and relevance of
municipal solid waste management.
Remember, this course focuses on
low and middle income countries
and does not provide much information
regarding waste management
in OECD countries. Besides this
overall understanding, at
the end of the course, you should
be able to comprehend the key
issues of waste management, which
on one hand covers the physical
elements, starting with waste
generation collection transport
treatment and/or recycling, and
landfill disposal as well as
the role of stakeholders, key
management issues, as well as
governments and financial aspects.
Besides understanding the challenges,
you will learn about appropriate
and already applied solutions
through selected case studies.
So at the end of the course, you
should also know what can be
done and how to improve the situation.
The course will give a lot of
space to organic waste treatment.
And after the various modules on
organic waste treatment,
you should know about the basic
principles of each and have a good
understanding of the pros
and cons of each option.
Finally you should be able to understand
some selected broader issues.
Now I shall pass the word to
Imanol Zabaleta to introduce
you to the concepts that underlie
the framework of this course.
Thanks Chris. Hi, my name
is Imanol Zabaleta.
I'm a researcher and project
coordinator at Eawag working together
with Chris at Sandec and also
dealing with issues pertaining
to solid waste management
in developing countries.
As Chris mentioned, waste
management does not only involve
the waste related services
and infrastructure.
It also involves people, their
behavior and interactions, money,
laws and other aspects which are
often overlooked or neglected.
Having a comprehensive and
well-structured overview of all aspects
involved in solid waste management
and their interactions
is therefore of utmost importance.
The integrated sustainable ways
management framework shown here
behind me provides such an overview.
This framework which was developed
in the 80's has been iteratively
improved since then.
The most recent version of the
framework, shown here, consists
of two overlapping triangles that
represent two sides of a solid
waste management system: the hardware
of the system, also called
physical components, and the software of
the system, the governance aspects.
This framework is becoming the norm
in discussion and assessment
of solid waste management systems
in different countries but
especially in low and
middle income countries.
We will use this framework throughout
the course as our backbone.
We adapted it into this
animated figure.
In week 1, after discussing
the relevance and importance
of this course, we will focus on
the physical elements
in the municipal solid waste
management chain.
That covers generation, collection,
treatment, tripollar components,
(phon) reduce and
recycle and disposal.
Week 2, we will then focus on
the governance aspects covering
various stakeholders involved with
their roles and responsibilities,
financial mechanisms as well as
institutional and policy aspects.
Week 3 and 4, we will then tackle
the different options for
treating organic waste. Throughout
the course, we will also
refer to it as biowaste, organic
material and biodegradable waste.
And finally week 5, we will
conclude with modules on selected
broader issues such as circular
economy, strategic planning,
performance benchmarking and the link
between the waste and climate change.
Given the time available, these
courses will not be able
to provide a larger level of details
on the wide range of topics
in municipal solid waste management.
Our goal is to get you really excited
about the topic and wanting much more.
In the various video modules
therefore we will refer to readings
on specific subjects which
typically can be downloaded on
the internet for free or else are
available on our website.
And remember that learning is fun,
and when sharing with others
then the added value of learning
significantly increases.
In that sense, we really
welcome you to join the forum.
In the forum, you can share your
experiences from your hometown,
from your travels and discuss
these issues together with other
colleagues enrolled in the course.
The course has quizzes during the
videos and homework quizzes.
Take these to test your learning.
We look forward to working
with you on this course.