Why is this course important?
Let's see if I can convince you.
Provision of good solid waste management
is a tremendous challenge
all over the world,
but specially in developing countries.
Our society needs knowledge
in solid waste management
since we need solutions
in the coming decades.
Some of you might still be doubting
whether to follow this course or not.
If you worry about the following facts,
or if you think that they deserve
some attention, then join us.
It is time to bring
solid waste management
to the attention of the general public.
Did you know that there are
two billion people
whose waste is not collected
from their homes and neighborhoods?
Or that three billion people lack access
to controlled disposal facilities?
Many communities, city dwellers,
living organisms and ecosystems
are direct victims of environmental
and health impacts of this situation.
Let me point out two sad stories.
The first one is about
the city of Surat in India.
In 1994, the city of Surat
suffered an outbreak of plague
like disease caused by major flooding,
as a consequence of uncollected waste
blocking the drains.
The outbreak resulted in 56 deaths,
0.3 million people migrated in two days,
and the country suffered
as much as two billion US dollars
in economic losses.
The good side of the story
is that they learned from their mistake.
In the next 18 months,
the city administration
transformed the city
into one of the cleanest in the region
winning the Best City Award
in the Annual Survey
of India's City-Systems in 2013.
The second story is about
the municipal dumpsite in Quezon City,
in the Phillipines.
In July of 2000,
after ten consecutive days
of heavy rain,
a slope of the dumpside
collapsed on a slum community.
The landslide killed
nearly 300 people
and left hundreds of families homeless
and without a source of livelihood.
The slope failure was the result
of a bad management of the dumpsite.
No daily cover, no compaction,
too steep slopes,
no [leach] collection, etc.
Can we do it better?
We must!
Currently, it is estimated
that we generate
around seven to 10 billion tons
of urban waste per year.
Can you imagine?
And predictions do not forecast
a much better future.
By the end of the century,
global population is predicted
to rise up to nine to 11 billion people.
90% of this growth
will take place in Africa,
and 83% of the world population
will be concentrated
in Asia and Africa alone.
Right where most of the developing
countries we're targeting are located.
Of course, more people
automatically implies more waste.
Besides, it is also interesting
to mention that waste generation
is significantly greater
in urban than in rural areas.
And how the urbanization trends look like?
Let's have a look.
Have a look at this map.
See how the percentage
of people living in cities grows
almost in every country of the world.
The darker the color,
the higher the percentage of people
living in urban areas or cities.
At the same time, the size of cities
is also rapidly growing.
In 1970, there were only
three mega cities,
cities with more
than ten million inhabitants.
All of them in the north,
in Japan and the United States.
By now, there are 28,
and by 2030, the number
will have rised to 40.
32 of these will be in the global south.
And of course, this will have
serious implications
on resource consumption
and waste generation.
Now that we mention
resources, look.
Have a quick glance
to this infographic.
Check first the diagram in the center.
It shows the number of years
we have left of different resources
considering the global
current consumption rate,
and health of the consumption rate
of an average US citizen.
On the right side,
we see the proportion of consumption
that is met by recycled materials
in percentage.
The infographic shows
some astonishing predictions.
Did you know that,
if consumption rates keep equal,
we will soon run out of indium,
required for LCD screens?
And almost no recycled nowadays.
Or that phosphorus reserves are predicted
to deplete in a few centuries?
These might sound quite a lot,
but notice that our agriculture production
depends heavily on phosphosrus
subtracted from mines.
No phosphorus means
lower food production,
and who knows what problems
we will then face.
Silver is left for nine to 29 years,
tin 17 to 40 years,
copper 38 to 61 years,
and not high recycling rates
for these resources
are achieved currently.
Much of them are just being dumped.
We might want to start
doing something about this.
The world is in need
of well prepared waste managers.
Unfortunately many waste-related decisions
are taken without much thought.
Obsolete, abandoned, non-functional
and mismanaged technologies,
such as this drum composter
in Kathmandu, Nepal
are common place in many low
and middle income countries.
In this particular case,
the installation was too technical.
It had a rotating drum,
conveyor belts, etc.
and all of them broke down
and needed replacements.
Besides, as usual, there was no market
or demand for compost.
So in the end, the whole activity
was too expensive
to maintain and operate
and now it is used to store motorbikes.
There are infinite reasons
why these technologies fail.
And many of them could be avoided
by having a proper assessment
of the characteristics
and needs of each location.
This course intends to bring
some light to these issues.
Do you also think that we need
to start looking for solutions
to the previous issues?
We need everybody to take part in this.
We need as many people as possible
who are not only dedicated
and motivated to solve
the waste problem,
but who also understand
the complexity of the system,
and have the tools to improve it.
Tell your friends, colleagues,
or anybody who's interested
or involved in solid waste management
to join the course.
Understanding solid waste
management systems
is definitely a preliminary pre-condition
and hopefully this course
will contribute to cover that doubt.