In the past modules we have heard
about the high costs of collection.
But also of the high optimization
potential with vehicle types,
loading, and routing strategies.
However, we want to ensure
collection services to all,
and for this sometimes it is
necessary to use approaches
which remain non-optimized, but achieve
the objective of service provision.
Why? Because sustaining
a hygienic environment,
and ensuring public health are key
functions of municipal waste collection.
It is a main driver to ensure
that waste management services
are provided to all,
independent of the cost.
Not having collection service
would affect the wider public,
and thus counteract the
objective of the service.
Collection in certain areas
can be extremely challenging.
Let us look at these few examples.
Here is an example from Mumbai, India.
Just by looking at
the settlement pattern,
this extremely high population density
with very limited road infrastructure,
you can easily imagine that
it is impossible to move around
in this neighborhood with
a waste collection truck.
Or this example from a
neighborhood in Caracas, Venezuela,
located on a very steep slope,
making access for waste
collection trucks very difficult.
It is in fact quite typical
in many cities of the world,
that the low-income
neighborhoods are exactly in those areas,
which are so difficult to access.
They have very limited road
infrastructure, narrow lanes,
which are often
unsealed or even washed out.
Solutions for waste collection
in such areas of difficult access
is a split of waste
collection into 2 steps:
primary collection, which
provides services in the neighborhood
with smaller vehicles or
more simple technology;
then the transport of this
collected waste to a collection point,
where it is stored in
larger containers,
and then secondary collection,
which removes this waste regularly
for transport to the treatment
or disposal facility.
Primary collection can
have different variations.
The first is shown here:
actually not a collection,
as it relies on the residents
themselves bringing the waste
to the collection point.
Another approach can be that
the people bring their waste
to the collection vehicle when
summoned, for instance, by a bell.
The other approach shown
here is a curbside service,
or even a door-to-door service,
by a primary collection service
using a simple collection vehicle,
which can be human powered,
animal powered, or even motorized.
Let us look at a few examples of
such primary collection vehicles.
Here is an example of a very
simple collection by wheelbarrows
in a slum of Karachi, Pakistan.
You might notice the boards,
which are used to increase the
loading capacity of the wheelbarrow.
Or this handcart, in an example
of primary collection in Indonesia.
Here is an example from the
handcart in Abidjan, in Côte d'Ivoire.
Notice how one sidewall can be removed
for easier emptying of the vehicle,
and also notice the wide tires,
that are better suited for the
very sandy roads in this neighborhood.
Here is an example of a
bicycle cart from Warangal, India.
What you see here is a design that
allows collection of segregated waste.
Or here, a bicycle collection
cart from Bangalore in India.
A special feature of this
collection vehicle are these blue bins,
which on one hand allow
collection of segregated waste,
but also allow easy emptying
of the collection vehicle,
as each bin can be removed
separately and emptied.
Or here from India, a motorized option,
using a three wheel transporter.
Or here, an improved
version from Managua, Nicaragua,
which allows tipping of
waste for easy emptying.
So, remember, sometimes
to ensure waste collection
in areas that are difficult to access,
the option of primary
collection is a good solution,
although it may not
really be cost-optimized.
Primary collection has the advantage
that it is typically a simple approach
and it can be easily adapted to
the specific local, topographic,
or road or lane conditions.
This service is very close
to the clients, the people,
and often the residents pay
for this collection service.
Remember however, that primary
collection, given the type of vehicles,
is limited in transport distance.
Waste is delivered
to a collection point,
which then needs to be emptied
by a secondary collection system.
Given this interaction
between 2 collection systems,
coordination is essential.
So that was all for
primary collection.
Thank you for listening.