Hi.
Last time, we saw the main elements
of waste collection and transport.
Today, we will see a little bit
more in detail as a possibility
of optimization and how to proceed.
Why is waste collection
so important in fact?
It's firstly a question of quality
of life for the population.
People have a strong requirement to live
in a clean city and clean streets.
One has a better self-respect
living in a clean area.
Waste collection is a basic service
for the population but it's
also a question of health protection
and of long term environmental
protection. Waste collection is
also a short term question of
protection against natural hazards.
The accumulation of waste in canals
and water pipes will strongly
increase the floods in the
city and their effects.
In the last lecture, we saw how much
waste collection and transport
are important in the cost structure
of waste management because
optimization is also a key factor
to improve the sustainability
of the waste management service.
The organization of waste
collection is also a typical case
for introducing good practices
in municipal governance.
The optimization of waste collection
will have two main objectives.
First, to improve the quality of
the service to the population.
Secondly, to reduce the cost.
As we saw, it is possible
and yes, we can do it.
What we learnt from
different European cities.
Some years ago, we made a comparison
of the efficiency of the
waste collection system between
seventeen different middle cities
of Europe, from 50,000 to
600,000 inhabitants.
Using simple street area, we were
very surprised by the results.
As you can see, we noted a huge
difference in efficiency between
different cities from one to
three or from one to seven.
In Switzerland, also, we found
some similar big variation
with collection costs varying from
one to ten by inhabitant or by
town between 80 communes.
Why are these differences so big
between cities having a similar
level of services?
The cities having the better
efficiency had generally, first,
accepted to analyze the reality;
secondly, accepted to change
their habits; thirdly, to make
clear choice; and finally, worked
on a good organization and
supervision of the work.
At the opposite, the cities having
a low efficiency are usually
working as they always did; the
city has changed, but this system
stayed on the same old level.
This important variability shows
once again the potential of
cost reduction that exists
in most of cities.
So, how to proceed?
First of all, it is necessary to
collect and analyze data to
know your city and to analyze
the present service as it is in
order to have clear data on
what we're speaking about.
After analyzing the data, we have
to develop a new strategy.
For that, we have to develop a
collection strategy in order
to reduce loading time and the
time of heating the truck.
For that, we will increase the
number of containers – they are
much cheaper than trucks.
We will introduce bigger and
standardized containers.
We will introduce also, perhaps, some
bigger containers in strategic
places – like markets
or shopping centers.
We will introduce bigger trucks as
much as possible, technological
trucks with loading system
and compacting systems.
We will reorganize routes and
timetable in order to avoid the
peak hours of traffic. And, for
example, we will collect the
city center in the night and
the suburbs in the day.
As a second point, we want to reduce
the distance travelled by the trucks.
For that, we will optimize the
collection routes in order to
have all trucks full at one
hundred percent at the end of the
route and to reduce
time and kilometers.
We want also to try to limit the
waste collection in main streets,
to reduce the number of collection
points, avoiding a full door-to-door
collection system and defining a
maximum distance for the citizen
to reach the bins – for
example 100 or 200 meters.
After, we will optimize the
time of use of the trucks.
For that, we have to organize a
preventive maintenance of the
trucks and of the bins in order
to reduce the frequency and
the duration of breakdowns.
We have also to operate in two
or three shifts per day – it's
a decision – or six or seven
days per week, for example.
We can also decide to operate
out of the city centers in the
peak hours or to create a transfer
station for long transports
and organize a transport with bigger
and cheaper forty-ton trucks.
The next point is to improve
the management of the service.
For that, we have to define a
new rule system, defining tasks
to the citizen, tasks of the
businesses, of the construction
company who is producing waste,
but also the collection team.
The important point is to organize
a good supervision of the
service, night and day, with an
adequate reporting of older
data and use of this data
to improve the service.
We have to organize a training
of the staff: the drivers,
the workers and the supervisors. We
have to organize a communication
campaign in order to inform the
population about the new service,
about the timetable of the service,
the new rules, the tasks
of the citizen, the tariffs, etc.
Sometimes, the service can be made
by a public company or sometimes
by a private company but, in any
case, the task of introducing
planning and supervision
are more or less the same.
Here is an example of an optimization we
made in Shkodër, in North of Albania.
The previous situation was very
bad and only part of the city
was covered by the service.
Introducing a reasonable solution,
we can improve the service
to one hundred percent of the
population and reduce by forty
percent the cost of the service.
The challenge was to organize
a service and the supervision
and to introduce new bins in
sufficient quantities and good
position and to organize the
maintenance of trucks and bins.
In this second example, we see
how we can work on the timetable
of the use of the
trucks and the teams.
In this analysis, we can see what
times are used for each activity
of the trucks in the day; and
with this analysis, we can show
where we could try to reduce
useless time taken by the trucks
in order to increase the collection
time of the trucks and make
it more efficient. The idea is
that trucks should work most
of the time of the day and that,
at the end of the route,
they are one percent full before
to go to the landfill.
Together, with routine analysis,
the time analysis allowed step
by step to reorganize the truck
use in order to maximize the
collection time for each truck.
After analysis of the data of
your city, you have to propose
a clear strategy and perhaps
different scenario, and make it
approved by the authorities. Be
clear on private or public services
frequencies, type of containers,
maximum distances of the service
for the population.
It's important to avoid the
multiplication of different services
but to focus on basic service
at lower cost as possible.
Also, it's important to avoid
beautiful solution or containers
as they are proposed in the
market but to develop a step by
step approach in line with
available finances of the commune.
It's important also to develop
a cost calculation and annual
budget so that the authorities
take decisions in line with
the financial possibilities
of the municipality.
We will see how to make a cost
calculation in another course.
After, we have to define the
tariff and the tariff collection
system because it's crucial to
define how to collect the money
– the financial resources which
are necessary to finance the
investment and the operation
of the service day by day.
Warning: don't think it's easy.
Buying trucks is only one little
step but more difficult is
to organize, make function, supervise
the system of collection and transport.
And, warning 2: changes are
difficult everywhere, so for change
management you need a
strong political support.
As a summary, we can see that cost
reduction in collection
and transport is generally
everywhere possible.