Hi, and welcome to
this module on recycling.
Recycling is one of
the three components
of the resource
recovery aspect, or triple R.
This includes:
Reduce, Reuse, and Recycle.
Reduction is mainly
achieved by policy interventions.
As an example, we can mention
the prohibition of plastic bags
by the government of Zanzibar in 2011.
Whereas reuse of waste is
practiced every day all around the world,
and it is easy to
understand what it means.
Here you see a picture of how
electronic waste can be reused
to make beautiful jewelry.
Reduce and reuse, are
pretty straightforward terms.
Consequently, this module
will focus on recycling.
We will see how 4
of the main municipal
solid waste fractions are recycled:
these are paper and
cardboard, glass, plastics and metal.
We will see all this
with real case examples
from low- and middle-income countries.
Let's start with paper.
Paper and cardboard,
which are produced from pulp,
derived from plant
fibers, primarily wood,
are used for many different products
such as for packaging material,
newsprint, and advertisements.
Most of these products
have very short lifetimes,
and thus constitute a
major fraction of most waste.
We distinguish 3 types of waste paper:
post-consumer paper, these are for
example newspapers and magazines;
corrugated board, most of the
times obtained from commerce;
and high-grade paper,
printing paper for instance,
often coming from businesses.
The paper recycling
process involves several steps.
Let's have a look to
some Asian examples.
The very first step is
sorting and removing impurities.
Waste paper has different prices,
depending on its color and thickness.
These 2 women in Philippines are
breaking books apart, page by page,
and sorting them
according to their color.
The next step is
repulping or grinding,
which can be done mechanically,
as shown in this plant of
Campul in India, or chemically.
Mechanical repulping yields lower
quality paper than chemical repulping.
After repulping, the paper is
mixed with water to produce a slurry.
This slurry is then
thickened before being pressed.
Bleaching or whitening is optional.
After being pressed,
the paper is dried,
and is then ready to be
sold as sheets or rolled.
Recycling of paper will never
be able to close the loop fully.
This is due to 2 reasons:
first, paper mass is being lost by
the storage of paper in archives,
offices, in building materials etc.
And second, the shortening
of fibers during repulping
induces to a quality loss, in
particular with respect to strength.
To compensate, recycled paper
should weigh 5 to 15% more per area,
or should be mixed with virgin pulp.
Let's mention some interesting
figures about paper production
and trade in the world.
Total world consumption of
paper and paperboard in 2012
was around 400 million tons,
to which Asia
contributed 45%, almost half.
Europe contributed 26%
and North America 21%.
But now, how much of all this
amount is actually recycled?
Hard to tell.
It seems that the majority of
paper worldwide is landfilled.
Although, it is also
true that recycled paper
is an important part
of the raw material
used in the pulp and paper industry,
and is traded on a
market that is global.
Transboundary trade totals 40
to 50 million tons per year,
around 10% of the total production.
This trade is now dominated by
the People's Republic of China,
who imported a net quantity
of 30 million tons in 2012.
This is around 70% of
all transboundary trade.
Okay.
But, how beneficial is
recycling paper for the environment?
This table here shows
us the inputs needed
in terms of wood
for example, or water,
and electricity, and
the residues and emissions
generated in the
production of 1 ton of newspaper.
However, we compare how much
it would cost to produce it
from virgin materials and
from recycled materials.
And then the last column
shows us the comparison.
Here we see that actually the
production from recycled materials
is able to reduce wood consumption,
as well as water and
electricity consumption.
However it increases
considerably the energy consumption,
as well as the residues
and emissions emitted.
In any case, according to
several life cycle assessment studies,
recycling has a better
environmental performance
than landfilling and
incineration of paper.
Especially, when the logs
not needed due to recycling,
continue in the natural
cycle acting as carbon sinks.
Finished with paper.
Now, what is all
about glass recycling?
Glass is used for many purposes,
but in the waste, system
glass is predominantly found
in terms of beverage
and food containers.
There are 3 types of glass:
soda-lime glass is used for
bottles, jars, drinking glasses etc.
It is produced in 3 different colors:
clear as in the
picture, green, and brown.
The second type is crystal glass,
which is used for high quality
drinking glasses, vases and art.
And finally, we have
borosilicate glass, also called Pyrex,
which is used for
laboratory glassware.
This one is corrosion
and temperature resistant.
Only soda-lime glass matters
in waste, due to its big amounts
and it is the only one that
can be recycled by re-melting.
Should not be of course mixed
with the other 2 glass fractions.
Glass can either be
reused, which will be ideal,
or recycled in 2 different ways.
Glass can be broken, and then
this broken glass is called "cullet",
and it is remelted and used for
the production of new bottles.
But glass can also be used as
substitute of other building materials,
such as gravel and fillers.
Let's have a closer look to a glass
recycling plant in Manila, Philippines.
First, the cullet is
obtained from storage,
and it is manually
separated and washed.
Then, this broken glass is
introduced in the furnace, to be remelted.
The melted glass is just
for production of new bottles
which are later sold again.
Cullet has advantage that
it prolongs furnace life,
as it melts at lower temperatures.
As long as contaminants are removed,
there is no quality loss of
glass in the recycling process.
Once colored cullet is mixed
however, the quality degrades.
Compared to paper,
that we already saw,
or plastic and metals,
that we will see later,
the global market of
glass is not so big.
Virgin materials are
abundant and accessible
in most parts of the
world at a reasonable price.
Here again, we have a similar
table comparing the production of glass
from virgin materials
and from recycled glass.
We see the different amounts
of inputs that are required,
and the different amounts
of waste water and emissions
that are generated.
The results show that, actually,
recycling reduces most of these inputs
and also the outputs
in considerable amounts,
meaning that recycling glass
has environmental benefits.
Let's now talk about plastics.
Plastic is produced from fossil oil.
As a curiosity,
about 4% of the petroleum
consumed worldwide each
year is used to make plastic.
And another 4% is just to power
plastic manufacturing processes.
Plastic is used for
many different products,
many of which have
very short lifetimes
and thus constitute a
major fraction of waste.
In plastic production, fossil
oil is distilled to fractions
containing a mixture
of hydrocarbon chains.
These are cracked into repeating
molecular units, called monomers.
The monomers are
synthesized into polymers,
forming the base material,
for example granulate or powder.
Based on their chemical difference,
we distinguish
different types of plastics,
which are shown here with their names
according to the Plastic
Industry Trade Association.
Plastic recycling presents 2 problems:
on the first hand, it
contains plenty of foreign items
and contaminants,
such as organic waste.
On the second hand,
different plastic types
are often mixed together.
When mixed plastics
are recycled together,
the material loses
its cardinal feature,
which is great strength and
flexibility at small dimensions.
In any case, plastic recovery can
be divided into 2 overall classes:
energy recovery and material recovery.
Energy can be recovered in the
form of heat and electricity.
Material recovery can be
done in 2 different ways:
either chemical recycling,
also called feedstock recycling,
or mechanical recycling.
Chemical recycling breaks down
the plastic into its monomers,
and then these monomers are used in
refineries to produce new plastics.
Whereas in mechanical recycling,
we distinguish the following steps:
the first step is sorting.
These operators in Bangkok are
sorting different plastic colors and types.
Then, sometimes material needs
to be prepared for transportation,
and that requires compacting.
This can be done with a truck, as
shown in this movie from the Philippines.
Once the material arrives to the
installation, it needs to be washed,
in order to remove organic
waste remains and impurities.
The washed plastics are later dried.
Once they are dried, the
plastic is cut into chips.
The chips are then
ready for extrusion.
When mixed colored chips
of plastic are extruded,
we obtain a black
plastic as shown in the movie.
This finalized plastic is
then ready to be palletized.
Some global facts:
the plastic global production
in 2014, was of 300 million tons.
40% by weight of world
production takes place in Asia.
China on its own, produces
25% of the world production.
North America and
Europe cover each 20%.
The annual volume of globally
traded waste plastics is around
15 million tons,
less than 5% of the
new plastic production.
This shows that recycling of
post-consumer plastic waste is
still in its infancy.
Is it better to burn
plastics or to recycle plastics?
Depending on the plastic type,
the production of plastic
containing 1 unit of energy as materials
can take approximately 1.
8 units of energy to produce.
Therefore, the environmental
benefits of incineration of plastic
in global terms should be questioned.
Here again, we have one table
comparing the environmental impacts
of producing 1 ton of high
density polyethylene granulates,
both from virgin materials
and from recycled materials.
Except for solid residues,
which are increased considerably,
the production used
in recycled materials
reduces all the other
environmental parameters measured here,
in very big amounts.
This concludes that
recycling plastics has in general
more environmental benefits
than not recycling plastic.
Our last fraction for
this module is metal waste.
Iron and aluminum and the
main metals found in waste.
They are produced from mineral ore
and used for a range of products,
some having very short
lifetimes such as packaging of cans,
foils and containers and
others having a very long lifetimes,
such as materials in
buildings and construction.
The types of steel and aluminum that
are being recycled are metal scrap,
originated in industries,
constructions and demolitions,
end of life vehicles, and
post-consumer waste, mainly
packaging.
This last fraction is
the least attractive
because it is very
mixed and not clean.
The recycling process of
metal involves several steps.
The very first is
cleaning the material;
this might involve the
tinning, the coating,
and the oiling.
Once the material is
cleaned and sorted,
this is introduced in the
furnace and is smelted again.
In this video we see
how operators in Bangkok
introduce metal scrap in the furnace.
The smelted metal is then
used to generate new products.
It is interesting to point
out that a clean metal scrap
can be recycled
without loss of quality.
Recycling of post-consumer
metals has a long history.
More than a third of all the aluminum,
as well as of all the steel
currently produced globally,
originates from old
traded and new scrap.
The trading market of scrap is global
but it's again
concentrated mainly in Asia.
Approximately 50% of all the
recycling plants existing in the world
are located in the Asian continent.
17% are located in Europe and
20% are located in North America.
One of the environmental
impacts of metal recycling:
the virgin materials for steel
and aluminum production are limited
and are not easily
accessible and have high energy costs.
Re-melting the scrap
saves a lot of energy,
making room even for long
distance bulk transportation
around the world for its recycling.
Once more here we see the
comparative table of producing steel
from virgin materials
and recycled materials.
We see that in this case, except
for the amounts of scrap consumed,
which obviously increase for the
productions based on recycled materials,
all the other parameters
again will reduce considerably,
both emissions and input materials.
This means that, obviously,
recycling still has
more environmental benefits
than producing it
from virgin materials.
Now that we saw how
materials are recycled,
let's have a look to the
recycling rates of 39 different cities
around the world.
This data covers both dry
recyclables and organics and,
where possible, rejected
amounts were corrected.
The figures show no clear relationship
between recycling
rates and income levels.
Indeed, the highest
recycling rates are achieved
in high-income countries.
But many middle- and low-income
countries also achieve high recycling rates.
This is the end of the module.
In this module we learned
recycling of municipal waste.
We mainly focused the module on
4 very common waste fractions.
Those are paper,
glass, plastic, and metals.
We covered some production data,
we also saw the recycling
process of each waste fraction,
we saw some interesting
global facts about each one,
and we also mentioned some
important environmental aspects.
For those interested in getting
more information about the topic,
we recommend to consult
the following key readings.
Much of information used in this
module was also taken from here.