The era of absolute
urbanization is ending,
and, from now on,
what can be found,
on the horizon of urban agency,
is relative urbanization.
The city is not a new phenomenon
in human history.
Cities appear
roughly at the same time
as farming, writing, money,
and the state.
The invention of the city
can be seen at the outcome
of the Neolithic Revolution
due to the existence of food surpluses,
allowing for new
and totally artificial settlements.
However, as Jane Jacobs
and Henri Lefebvre argued,
the emergence of cities
as political, religious, commercial,
or cultural areas,
can also be understood
as the cause of this revolution.
In brief,
a city is an amazing spatial machine.
All throughout
the process of urbanization,
the very idea of a city
has triggered some negative attitudes.
There has been a long tradition
of rejecting urbanity.
The history of the city
entered our minds through a spell.
The curse on the city, and on density,
and, indeed, on globalization too,
had already been announced
in the Old Testament.
The God of the Jews and Christians
was the first enemy of density.
Then, the curse upon density
was maintained,
and given fresh impetus,
by an important European
puritanical-communal tradition.
This tradition was represented
at the highest philosophical
and literary levels,
by Jean-Jacques Rousseau,
who wrote:
This tradition continued in Europe,
and increased under the influence
of agrarian states,
which perceived emerging large cities
as dangerous political rivals.
This was particularly the case for France,
where the alliance
between the central state and rural notables
kept Paris and other major urban areas,
in a state of subjugation.
In many European countries,
the imagined community
underpinning national identity
was nothing more than the myth
of a self-sufficient, nature-friendly,
prolific, and harmonious countryside,
unfortunately,
undermined and threatened
by messy, artificial, and sterile cities.
This myth migrated to America,
conveyed by people who,
from the day they landed,
began to build
an overwhelmingly urban environment,
while remaining
proud and ardent militants
of their puritanical cause.
This probably explains a paradox.
The North American version
of the anti-urban narrative
is embodied, if not by a city,
then, at least, by a town-like landscape,
that of Main Street America,
with its parochial
single-street community,
and its farming hinterland,
but not exactly with the plow,
plowing, and plowman,
of European mythologies.
‘Parochial’ was the word
used by Lyn Lofland
to designate
the kind of fake public space
where anonymity is impossible.
We will explore this idea
more in-depth during this session.
In Walt Disney's images,
the discourse
may seem to have been secularized.
However, when one reads
the following statement,
in a Dearborn published article
by Henry Ford,
stigmatizing the pestiferous growth
of the city,
one discovers
an unquestionable continuity
with the Bible's inspiration and style.
On the academic side,
the libertarian utopia,
epitomized by Melvyn Webber,
in the 50s,
or the cybermythology
proposed by the early William Mitchell,
joyfully celebrating the end of the city,
completes the picture.
Why so much hatred?
An attractive hypothesis is that the city
is the hyper-realistic expression
of human agency.
In a city, everything is artificial,
including, of course, nature.
Hatred for urbanity
is hatred for society,
and, more specifically,
for the inevitable exposure to otherness
which a city harbors
in each of its dimensions.
Lyn Lofland has called the city
a ‘world of strangers’.
A city is the kind of place
where people are forced to entertain
limited relationships with unknown others
who, nevertheless,
belong to the same society as ours.
Cities mark the end
of the communal dream - or nightmare -,
a world where any people tossed away
are known and watched,
as we are known and watched by them.
In any city,
even in communally-organized societies,
the perspective of a society
of individuals,
with more society and individuality,
is both possible and conceivable.
Tell me what you think about cities,
and I will tell you
what is your social attitude
and, if you are a scholar,
what is your social theory.