Urbanity consists of virtuality
and serendipity.
A large city is characterized
by the significance of its virtuality
and serendipity,
and both are impossible without density.
Firstly, there are so many things to do,
that a choice must be made,
which means eliminating certain things.
When you are not in a movie theater,
you are not the same person,
whether there are one
or three hundred films to see.
This is virtuality, which should
not be confused with simulation,
or approximation.
The greater the degree to which one lives
in an urbanity-rich environment,
the larger the gap between
what could be done,
and what is actually done.
This is the golden burden of urbanity.
In this context, chance can offer
a partial solution.
The non-actualized component
of the possibilities offered by the city
is made available
through random encounters.
‘The Three Princes of Serendip’
is a medieval Persian tale,
popularized by Horace Walpole
in the 18th Century.
The princes in the story used
two alternative strategies
to get through difficult situations.
The first is to take advantage
of the unexpected situations
they encounter along the way,
while the second is to employ
a skill for arranging accidents -
an expression of their sagacity,
to use Walpole's words.
Robert Merton and Umberto Eco
have both taken this phenomenon seriously.
We could even go beyond mere observation
to consider how serendipity
could be arranged.
Transforming chance into productivity
is what John Udell, a blog specialist,
calls ‘manufactured serendipity’.
In an urban context,
the conditions to be met
for efficient serendipity to exist,
could then be identified.
I the activation and involvement
of all of our perceptive sensors,
indeed, all of our sensorial apparatus,
in order not to miss any information.
Pedestrian metrics are the most
suitable for that purpose,
although their suitability
can be challenged
by physical or digital libraries,
and even more by search engines.
II an exposure to otherness,
which assumes the existence
of otherness, diversity,
its accessibility, density,
and of course its acceptability.
III the cognitive skill to usefully
interpret the information received.
Thus, reciprocal reinforcement takes place
between urbanity and serendipity.
Serendipity is all the more necessary
because urban space generates
a rich set of virtual resources.
At the same time, serendipity is made
all the more possible
because of the density
and diversity of urban space.
This is a clear case of a virtuous,
positive feedback loop.
To the contrary, if the level
of urbanity is reduced,
the efficiency of serendipity,
as well as its usefulness, is weakened.
N x(n - 1), or approximately n2,
is a formula defining the number
of potential non-reciprocal links
between n realities.
It permits an understanding
of why city size matters.
Nevertheless, size is not everything:
n can be large but with no reason
for people to meet,
either because they are too similar,
or too different,
with nothing to exchange,
or because they lack sufficient
accessibility to come into contact.
Hence there is an absolute,
size-dependent urbanity
and a relative urbanity,
independent of size.
This means that urbanization can be
defined as a creation of urbanity,
in relative as well as in absolute terms.
Urbanity can be injected
into existing cities
through the creation
of density or diversity.
‘Urban renewal’ or ‘urban renaissance’
are movements typical of relative
urbanization processes.
Public space is a special, quintessential
component of urbanity.
It is a specific way
of creating politics:
that is, civility.
Public space is a strange
multi-scalar object.
Let's see how strange it is.
Public space can be defined as
a small component of a local society,
which possesses the same
level of diversity
of the society as a whole.
This means that entering a public space
involves a high degree of otherness,
in terms of population and activities.
Any public space then,
has at least two scales:
its own, and that of the reference space,
whose diversity it concentrates.
Public space can be approached
as the quintessence of the city,
as a concentrated urbanity.
Etienne Tassin showed
the contradictions encountered
if public space is to be looked at
through a communitarian lens.
Public space does not belong
to an exclusive community
benefiting from its exclusive usage.
That which defines the public
in terms of space,
as in other domains,
is a fact that it does not
belong to anybody,
because it arises from
society in its entirety.
Writings on public space
are surprisingly recent.
Public space remains
relatively peripheral
to the otherwise foundational
works on urban action
by Ildefons Cerdà
in the late 19th Century,
and very marginal to
the works of Le Corbusier,
and the modern movement
in the mid-20th Century.
The beginning,
reflections on public space
were confined to the domain
of urban design.
In French, and sometimes
in English literature,
public space suffered
a misunderstanding,
due to a bad translation
of the Kantian notion,
which was taken up
again by Jürgen Habermas,
of ‘Öffentlichkeit’,
which means public,
or public sphere, in German.
This was confused with 'public space',
which is ‘öffentlicher Raum’,
and this notably led
to lackadaisical confusion
of the agora, as a material metaphor
of the political scene,
in the context of direct democracy,
and public space, as it exists
in inhabited environments,
without any specific relation
to institutional political life.
This confusion in turn
prevented an awareness
of the political component
proper to the public space,
which may be called ‘civility’.
Civility is entirely political,
without referring to institutional
political life at all.
Aristotle defined the possibility
for liberty through equality.
This liberty is made possible
through the creation of
an egalitarian environment,
where the words and actions of each
person carry the same weight.
This is the principle of ‘polis’,
according to Hannah Arendt,
who defined politics as
the freedom to organize a space.
Urban public space is a good
expression of a political universe:
that of civility, which, while not
democratic in its apparent,
and purely interactive,
form of organization,
is nonetheless founded
on the principle of equality.
When this equality
is fundamentally missing,
such as in India and Africa,
there is no public space present.
One of the particularities of civility
lies in the fact that it is entirely
expressed through interaction.
It is through the exposure
of vulnerable human bodies
and their protection by others
that inhabitants transform public space
into a political environment.
In a square, on a street,
or in a subway car,
norms of spatial organization
are constantly being renegotiated,
by placing one’s body in such and such
a way in relation to others.
A conflict implies a challenge
to the interactive norms between people.
Yet, whether the protagonists
of this joust reach an agreement or not,
the argumentative phase will not
tip civility over into deliberation.
Deliberation means a collective,
explicit process of decision making,
which cannot occur in public space.
The being-inhabited nature of public space
is in fact volatile by definition,
since it’s open to everyone,
and not only to regulars,
but to all of those who, to some degree
or another, occupy the space.
The ethics of interaction work
in all sorts of spaces.
They consist of preserving
autonomy within integration,
as much in private space (the protection
of individual integrity
and minimalist benevolence via politeness,
which is etymologically an urban value),
as in public space (protection of intimacy
and favorable exchanges
lending value to publicness).
What has emerged can now be summarized
into a set of characteristics,
making public space a very peculiar
and fascinating object for geography.
First of all, the efficiency
of a public space
is based on the interaction of those
provisionally inhabiting it.
Public space is open to changes
in its norms and uses,
as carried out by the practices
of those inhabiting it.
These changes may either reinforce
or weaken its public character.
As a result, designing
and building a public space
is neither necessary nor sufficient
to make it exist.
Secondly, public space is a public good,
characterized by the possible presence
of a level of population,
and functional diversity within it,
equal to that of the larger
reference space, or spaces:
a neighborhood, a city, the world.
Thirdly, pedestrian metrics -
walking plus public transit -
are the characteristic
metrics of public space,
which can be fixed or mobile.
Finally, public space protects
and reinforces intimacy.
Places marked by the necessity
of pre-existing links
between its inhabitants,
like compulsorily belonging to
any kind of communality,
cannot be public spaces.
Thus there should be a distinction
made between the two pairs,
private/public and intimate/‘extimate’.
Family housing is commonly a place
of privacy without intimacy,
domestic violence being dominant
among all violent practices,
while urban public spaces
offer intimacy without privacy.
Urbanity can be defined, as we have said,
as a combination of density and diversity.
Those terms refer to population:
urbanity being higher when different
social categories are more mixed,
as well as to functions:
urbanity being made up of
a heterogeneity of activities,
sectors, and dimensions.
In consequence of these characteristics,
public space can be seen
as an excellent generator
and indicator of urbanity.
Since public space
is supposed to concentrate
a similar level of diversity
as a whole urban area
into a small part of this area,
it can be considered as
a concentration of urbanity.
Like urbanity in general, public
spaces express weak ties.
This also means that we are not
dealing with the major flaws
of social redistribution,
nor with the main features defining
an individual within society.
This apparent inconsistency has
sometimes led to misunderstandings.
Certain commentators do not
perceive weak ties
to play major roles
in social construction,
and complain that urbanity
does not solve
the problems resulting from
economic inequalities.
They denounce research into
social diversity as a myth,
since it does not solve any problems.
Increasing diversity is not a policy
for the redistribution
of separable private goods,
but a contribution to equality
of access and capacity.
Public space does not distribute
money to the poor,
but it gives to the poor, as to the rich,
the possibility of experiencing
productivity and creativity
through exposure to otherness.
That is all it does,
but that is already something remarkable.
Public space does not create
an easy experience.
The more successful the public space,
that is to say, the greater
the degree of diversity
to be encountered therein,
the more it enables a visible
and felt heterogeneity,
agreeable or not,
which defines society, and to which
all of those within the space belong.
Public space can raise awareness
of the otherness of the social world.
A public space is not
a designer’s creation.
It can be useful for an urban designer
to plan its materiality.
However, this does not
guarantee its viability.
To the contrary, public spaces can exist
ephemerally and nomadically
in a non-constructed manner,
during exceptional or periodic events.
It can be assumed that public space
is a moment of justice,
a weak moment,
but whole in the fact that it makes
equality possible in act.
Conversely, urban planning
linked to power politics
seeks to make such moments
of justice impossible,
by creating grand squares
devoted to formal gatherings
and military parades.
Urban planning aiming at
fragmentation and separation
forgets about public space
and privatizes everything possible,
while demolishing in its path
everything required,
the multi-sensory exposure to otherness
proper to the pedestrian.
However, a style of urban planning,
aiming at adding value
to existing urbanity,
and producing new dimensions
of urban being-together,
focuses, almost exclusively,
on public space.
The main features of public space
can be summed up through
fifteen theses on public space,
which have been the outcome
of a collective research
project on the concept.