Finally, public space
logically constitutes
one of the markers in a debate
on the conception of the city.
Although there are certain nuances,
on the whole,
there are clearly two opposed tendencies
in any city in the World today.
The opposition between ‘Amsterdam model’
and ‘Johannesburg model’ is very simple.
One assumes urbanity,
in its various dimensions of exposure
to otherness, density, diversity,
public space, and public metrics,
while the other assumes
a dispersed fragmentation
and a generalized privatization of space,
notably through adherence
to a car-oriented system.
The Amsterdam model takes predominance
when living in a city
implies a continuous making of society.
By contrast, the Johannesburg model
demonstrates a refusal
to take responsibility
for the societal consequences
of the technical options
preferred to living
in a concentrated space.
The following table suggests
that cities endowed with a high degree
of fixed or mobile public space
are also compact, mixed, productive,
and nature-friendly cities.
Serendipity, which allows value
to be added to creative processes,
and consisting of cognitive and emotional
displacements and deviations,
belongs more readily
to the Amsterdam model,
along with environmental protection,
which provides benefits
to all of its components --
air, water, soil, and biodiversity --
when faced with the urban parsimony
of surface conception.
The prevalence of these models
can be differentiated as three scales.
The Johannesburg model is predominant
in North America and Africa, small towns,
and in situations
with weaker levels of urbanity
(less density, less diversity),
such as in peripheral suburbs or exurbs.
Conversely, the Amsterdam model
is predominant in Europe and Asia,
large cities, and city centres,
with the other spaces being more uncertain.
Thus the contrast between models
is at its height between city centers
such as Tokyo and Paris,
on the one hand,
and the outer periphery,
or little Texan or South African towns,
on the other.
Everywhere, and without exception,
the process of increasing development
has firstly meant choosing the automobile,
which has automatically led
to de-densification
and a loss of diversity
in less interesting neighbourhoods,
and a lack of attention given
to public space and the natural environment.
After this initial stage, however,
certain fundamentals
of social life take over.
Thus, in ‘hydraulic’ rural Asia,
there was, and still is,
a distinct value given to density,
where people constantly reinvest
into soil through human labor,
proximity through the distance
between industrial
or agricultural and residential locations,
and spatial arrangement
through compact collective practices
which are found in its cities.
Japan, Singapore, Hong Kong,
and South Korea
have become creative places
for the re-evaluation of urbanity.
China displays a surprising situation
in which the Johannesburg model
continues to prosper,
even though public policies
are already and unambiguously orientated
towards the Amsterdam model,
with reinforced densities,
functional diversity,
public transit, and public spaces.
Moreover, this movement is affecting
the peripheral cities of the Pacific Rim,
marked by Chinese immigration,
such as Vancouver and Sydney,
which have been resistant
to this approach for a long time.
Who chooses these models?
All of the urban society does
and, naturally,
its most expert or powerful actors.
The distribution of these models
across the map
points to the modes of organization
of inhabited space
profoundly linked to a certain manner
of conceiving liberty and equality.
The Amsterdam model
makes all the inhabitants in a city
its actors working continuously.
The entire city becomes a public good,
available to all,
and ceaselessly growing in its uses.
In a society of actors,
where life choices become part
of a process of arbitration
amongst those actors,
the pragmatic adoption
of one model over another
is clearly translated
into political choices.
In developed countries,
housing choices
have progressively been added
to individuals’ spheres of arbitration.
This means that a majority of households
have a certain affordance,
in the meaning used
in cognitive psychology,
that is to say,
a useful grip inside an environment,
possibly at a high cost
to the poorest layer
of an extended middle-class.
Being located within an urban area
has become one criterion, among others,
like ownership status, owner or renter,
housing style (flat or house), or size.
Consequently,
the place where most people live
is not merely the result
of an externally directed
process of fatality,
but, at least, partially the outcome
of the people concerned.
We were able to show
that votes for populist
right-wing parties in Western Europe,
which are xenophobic nationalists
and anti-European Union,
were strongly correlated
with peri-urban residential environments,
beyond contiguous built up areas,
all things being equal.
From the same perspective,
the present day political map
of the United States
shows an extreme and novel polarization
between two contrary spatial size,
low-urbanity territories
associated with Republicans,
and high urbanity networks
associated with Democrats.
Furthermore,
formal modelling of residential choices,
centred on inhabitant individuals
and constructed with realistic economic
and geographical parameters,
gave spectacular results.
While ‘allophilia’ - that is the search for,
or acceptance of exposure to otherness,
through choices to live
in a socioeconomically
diverse neighborhood -
prevails,
a compact city in conformity
to the Amsterdam model is created.
Conversely, in the case of ‘allophobia’ —
the refusal of diversity
in urban cohabitation -
the result is a sprawling
and fragmented city.
During iterative processes,
the model makes the decisive role
played by upper and middle
income groups clear.
If those capable of arbitrating
do so with an allophilic tendency,
then diversity is maintained,
otherwise the poorest inhabitants
cannot achieve this end
since the other social groups
flee from them.
This is where attention to ‘bobo’
(bourgeois-bohème) logic is due.
Those disposing of high income
who seek diversity for some reason
play an essential role
in the maintenance of diversity.
This model allows for an evaluation
of the specific effects
of urban public policies.
It shows that if allophobia is dominant,
then public action is ineffective,
and individual actors bypass it
to continue pursuing
their project of separation.
If allophilia sets the tone,
diversity-oriented residential
and family policies
can accompany and enhance it.
It may be concluded that,
within heavy and complicated
machinery-like cities,
little actors play a major role.
The balance between
spactialities and spaces,
that is to say, between spatial actors
and spatial environments,
is better-assured than we could believe.
This means that major actions,
deciding the place accorded to values
of justice and development,
may decreasingly be the result
of technocratic choices or structures
beyond reach, and increasingly,
result from the multiform deliberations
of ordinary citizens.
A recent evolution in urban planning
illustrates this point.
It’s daily becoming more difficult
to make decisions
and to implement urban projects
without a minimum of participatory
processes and rationales.
In this context,
public space appears
both as the quintessence of urbanity
and as a potentially continuous space
connecting all areas
within and between cities.
As a matter of fact,
if we consider
public transportation systems
as the mobile part of public space,
intra-urban and interurban
public transport
both requires and provides public space.
In an urban network
characterized by the Amsterdam model,
there is a continuity between public space
inside and between cities.
This contributes to adding
a third scale to any public space,
beyond its own micro intra-local scale,
and the urban society to which it belongs,
that is, at a local level.
Public space forms part of the integration
of an interconnected, interurban system
whose potential size could be
the global urban archipelago,
and which is also a scalar
measurement of a public space.
This means that a global scale
can be present,
in different ways in a public space,
for example, in people, activities,
products, and cultures,
as tiny as that public space might be,
and especially in metropolises.