In this episode and the next,
we are going to focus less on the processing,
and more on the data.
As you already know, in a programming language,
data are represented by variables.
And in C++, variables are typed.
At this stage of the course, we have mainly introduced
the int type, to represent integers,
the double type, to represent
real variables,
and we also evoked the bool type
to represent truth values.
These types, int, double, bool, which are called the elementary types,
are used to represent simple data of the world,
like dimensions, sums, logical
expressions.
But how about more complex, more
structured data ?
Suppose we'd like to manage
the ages of the students
following this course.
Or suppose we'd like to
manage population statistics,
how would these statistics be represented ?
How would be represented a set, an array, of data (ages) ?
Or in the case of statistics,
how would a person involved in the statistics
be represented ?
In both cases, we'll use what is known
as  data structure.
As another example, how would we represent
the names of the persons involved in the statistics
using the types we have seen until now ?
We wouldn't know how to do it.
This episode will look at arrays.
We'll see later in other episodes,
how to represent sequence of characters,
and then how to represent
structures,
namely, how to represent a line in
such an array.
But let us begin with arrays.
Let's suppose that we want to create
a game program
and that we have to manage the
players' scores,
we would like for example to display the
score
of every player,
as well as the  deviation
of these scores from the mean.
How would we proceed ?
Let's modestly begin by handling
the case of a two-player program.
What we would do, of course, is
to introduce
a variable for the score
of each of the two players.
So, let's say that their scores are here
integers,
which will be initialized using
a particular function here.
This function would  calculate and
return the score.
The score is computed like this
for the first player.
Similarly,  computing the second
player's score
is done using  the parameters
associated with this second player.
And then, as we want the
deviation from the mean,
we compute the mean of the two players by using the function
moyenne (TN : moyenne means mean)
that we have already illustrated
in previous episodes.
This function would take the scores of
our two players as parameters.
The mean is  stored  in a variable
moyenne_joueurs of type integer.
And finally, we could print the
scoreboard,
by printing the first score and
the deviation from the mean,
and then by  printing the second score
and its deviation from the mean.
Two players is not bad, but the
question is,
how can we improve our program
to accept more players ?
We could simply use several
variables.
So for example, if we wanted to
pass to five players,
we would then typically use
five scores : one for each player.
We would then compute the score of
each player
using our function (with the players' specific  parameters).
And we  would compute the
mean of all these players
by changing this time the mean
function
and passing the five scores to the
new mean function,
then we would write the scoreboard
like this.
Here, any good programmer
would immediately
thinks of using a loop,
and will therefore modify this
part of the program
to introduce a loop here.
The loop would go from the first player
to the fifth one,
it would iterate on each player,
and print the score of every
player,
as well as its deviation from
the mean.
The question is how to do it
concretely ?
Because firstly, writing scorei
like this, from the previous
program, isn't valid.
scorei would be here a variable name.
It can't be used with different values of i.
scorei cannot stand for  score1 or score2.
So this is something that
doesn't work.
Also, how would we do if we moved
to 100, 1000 players ?
It would quickly become tedious
to write 100 variables,
modify the mean function to
take 100 parameters,
so it's just impossible in practice.
Finally, how would we do if the number
of players is unknown at the beginning ?
You wouldn't know if you had to
deal with  five, two, or ten players.
The answer to fulfill all these needs is actually the same,
it's introducing a new type,
the array type.
Let me give you by way of preamble
the version
with an array of the players' score
program,
but of course we'll detail all this
later on in this episode.
So, we would declare an array
of players,
then we would loop,
we again encounter this notion of
loop to compute the score
of each player,
then we would compute the mean here,
this mean could take an array
of scores,
and finally we would print the
final score
with here a for loop which
iterates on all the values of the array.
Let's have a look at these different
elements one by one.
Let's begin with the notion
of array.
An array is a collection, a set
of values
which all have the same type. We speak
of homogeneous collection,
to say that they are all the data of the collection are of the same type.
For example, the array of scores in which
we were interested previously,
if we take the case of four scores,
it would be an array
containing four integers.
I decided that my scores
are integers.
So, all the elements of my array
are  here of the same type (int).
When would we use an array in
a program ?
When we need to use several
variables of the same type,
like, for example, the scores of our
previous game with players.
In C++, we can create arrays of any type,
arrays of integers, array of
doubles,
we can create array of any
available type,
arrays of bools, and even
arrays of array, once we'll have
defined this new array type.
Generally speaking, there are
four kinds of arrays,
depending on two questions :
at the moment of writing the program,
before using the array,
do we know its size or not ?
And, once known, can this size
vary, or is it fixed ?
Let's examine the different cases in turn.
Let's begin with the case where
the size isn't known
at the moment of writing the
program,
and where the size can vary when
the program is executing.
It's typically the example of the
set of ages
of the students following this course.
At the beginning, I have no idea
of how many students
will attend this course.
Then, at a given moment when I
have the array
of all the students'ages,
I can have other students who
register for the course,
and therefore add ages, or
unfortunately,
I can have students who leave
the course,
and therefore have ages which
disappear.
So here we have the case where
the size can vary,
and it isn't known beforehand.
Now let's illustrate the extreme
opposite,
where we suppose that the size is
known beforehand,
and that it can't change.
Typically if you want to program a
linear algebra application,
if you have 2D vectors, you
know that such vectors
always have two coordinates, so they will
always be arrays
with two numbers representing
the x and y coordinates.
The size is known, it is
a priori two,
and the size won't change,
it will always be two.
In the case where the size isn't
known at the beginning,
but once set, the size doesn't
change,
we could take the example of a game,
with a fixed number of players.
At the beginning we don't know
how many players we'll have,
if three people will participate in the
fame, or ten people,
but once the number of players is
set,
we can't change it anymore.
So here the size isn't known
at the beginning,
but once it is known,
it can't change during the program's
execution.
Finally, the last case, maybe
the little rarer one,
and more difficult to
illustrate,
is the case where we know the size
a priori,
at the moment that we write the
program,
but that size can still change.
This would typically be if we wanted
to create a program
which stores statistics for,
for example,
the number of "cantons" (TN: "districts" or "states")
in a country, it's something we know.
At the beginning we have 26 cantons (ed. in
Switzerland), and maybe, one day,
another canton will be created,
or two cantons will merge, so the
number would decrease.
It's a limit case, and I confess that,
indeed,
this case is much more rare.
Two complementary remarks,
to conclude with arrays.
First note that if we know how to
do
arrays with a non-fixed size, and which
can vary,
then we can obviously create all the other
arrays with this one,
that's a first remark.
Then, second observation :
practically no programming language
offers the four variants explicitely.
For example, in C++, we only have two kinds
of arrays,
we have  dynamic arrays, represented
by the vector type,
and static, or fixed-size ones,
which are, since C++ 2011,
represented by the array type,
or else a former type which is inherited
from the ancestor of C++,
which we call C, so the "C-type"
arrays.