In this episode, we are going to
study the dynamic array of C++,
known as "vectors".
A dynamic array is an array,  a homogeneous collection,
a set of elements of the same type.
It is said to be dynamic because its size can vary
during the execution of the program.
For example the array of the
ages of the students
attending this course could
evolve during the execution,
as new students register for the
course.
Dynamic arrays in C++ are
represented by the "vector" type.
In order to use the "vector" type, we
must indicate to the compiler
that we want this type, and therefore
include the corresponding library
with the #include
directive at the beginning of the program.
In order to use a dynamic
array,
you must of course declare a
variable of this type,
namely,  a variable of
type "vector".
That is done as usual, by indicating
the name of the variable
preceded by the type and here the
type is vector,
with between signs like this (chevrons),
between less than character and greater than
character, the type of each array element.
So for example, if I want to declare
an array which will contain integers,
what I am going to do is to declare
a variable here,
which of type vector,
int being the type of each
element of the array.
Beforehand, don't forget, so that
all this compiles,
to include the "vector" library.
As already mentioned, the type of the
elements of an array
can be any type available in C++.
So what you put here between chevrons
in the definition of the type
is any valid type,
including eventually another array,
we'll come back to that later.
When you declare a variable of
type array,
you also think, like for any other
variable,
about initializing it.
Their exists in fact, since the new
C++ 2011 standard,
five ways of initializing a dynamic
array.
You can either initialize it as empty,
or explicitly give the list of values
that you want to use at the beginning,
or give it a size with eventually
an identical value for all elements
that you put in this array
at the beginning,
or make a copy of an already
existing array.
Let's have a look, in turn, at these
different ways
of initializing an array.
To initialize an empty array, it's
very simple :
there isn't anything in
particular to do.
You only have to declare a variable of
this type, vector,
if, for example, you want an array
of integers,
but without adding anything at the
end of the declaration,
without putting an explicit
initialization.
At that moment,
the array will be an array initialized
by the compiler
as being an empty array without any
element.
Contrariwise, if you want to initially
give it values,
for example put the values
20, 35, 26, 38 and 22 already at
the beginning in your array,
the fact remains that it's a dynamic
array, it will be able to evolve.
But if you want these values
at the beginning,
you'll use the syntax
which gives here an explicit list
in the initialization.
So between the two opening and
closing curly braces, a list of values.
Of course, the values you give in this
list must be of the same type
as the type you have specified for your array.
We can also write,
although it isn't tolerated by all
the compilers yet,
instead of having here an
initialization syntax
as we have always had for the
other variables,
have a syntax here which initializes
with the character =.
Third case of initialization, if I want
to set a size at the beginning,
at that moment the syntax will
be the following :
we are, here in parentheses, not going
to set a list of elements,
but set an integer, a size.
So for example,
if I want my dynamic array
to have with five elements at the beginning,
I'll declare a dynamic array of integers,
called here "tab",
and behind it here, I'll specify
that it begins initially
with five elements.
Anticipating a bit with a syntax that
will come later,
you must pay attention to the fact that
here it is indeed a dynamic array
that initially contains five elements
and that it has nothing to do
with a static array
that would always contain
five elements
and which we couldn't
make the size vary.
Here we are still talking about
dynamic arrays
and not at all about arrays whose
size is fixed and which can't evolve,
yet.
So a dynamic array, you can give
it a size.
If we only give it a size,
the array is initialized at the beginning
with elements which are all null,
with that size.
But we can also initialize them
with different elements
of the same value.
If for example I want to begin my
array, which stays dynamic,
with five elements which will
all have the value 1.
At that moment,
I'll declare my array as a dynamic
array of integers
with five elements
which all have the value 1.
So here, this second element is
an element with a value which
has to be of the same type as the type
of the dynamic array,
the type of the elements of the
dynamic array.
So here I put a 1, of type integer,
which causes the five elements
that I initialized to have the same value, 1.
Whereas the 5 here, can be nothing but an integer, since  it's
a size.
Whatever the array's type is,
it's always a size that I give.
Finally, last way of initializing a
dynamic array.
We can also initialize a
dynamic array
by making a copy of an already
existing array.
So for example here I can declare
an array
called "tab2", which will be a copy of another array.
So here we'll copy element by
element the array "tab1" in "tab2"
but we'll indeed have two arrays which,
at the beginning, are in the same situation.
"tab1" and "tab2" both have
five elements
that each have the value 1
at the beginning.
But then each of these two arrays "tab1"
"and "tab2" will evolve separately.
And for example we'll be able to
eventually modify elements in "tab2",
and vary "tab2" as we wish,
independently from "tab1".
They are indeed two completely
separated arrays.
We here have a copy of "tab1"
in "tab2".
So to sum up, we have the five
following ways
of initializing a dynamic array :
Either empty, we don't put anything,
I insist on this,
after the name of the variable in its
declaration.
The array will here be empty.
Or initialize it with an initial sequence
of values.
To do this we use an opening
curly brace,
a closing curly brace in the
initializaion parentheses.
Or initialize it with a given number
of null elements.
At that moment, in parentheses,
we'll just put an integer.
Or initialize it with a given number
of elements,
so we'll give its size, but with a value
different from 0.
So here we'll provide a value
which is of the same type
as the type announced for every
element.
Or, finally, make a copy of an
already existing array,
and make a copy element by
element.
So there are the five ways of
initalizing a dynamic array.