When we have declared and initialized
a dynamic array,
we'll of course want to use it.
In order to do this, we can either
use the array globally,
or element by element.
To use an array globally, it isn't
very frequent,
but I can be useful occasionally,
we'll simply globally assign
an existing array
to the array that we want to
manipulate.
So this will be done simply with
the usual assignment syntax (=).
Let's take an example.
Suppose that we have an
array tab1,
that we've declared beforehand,
and initialized here with
three values.
It's an array of integers.
So this array tab1 will contain,
at the beginning,
three integers,
which have as values 1, 2, 3,
because of this initialization here.
We then declare here a dynamic
array tab2,
which is the empty array.
The declaration we have done here,
as it has nothing after it,
declares an array initialized to
an empty array.
It's an array without elements.
We'll then make different computations,
and finally, at a certain point,
we'll maybe need to make a copy
of tab1 in tab2,
so we'll make a copy of tab1 in
tab2,
which means that now, tab2 will
contain the elements 1, 2, 3.
Once again, this is a copy, so
starting from this line,
tab1 and tab2 will continue to live
separately,
if I modify tab1, there won't be any
modifications on tab2.
If a modification is made here,
there isn't any modification in tab2.
tab1 and tab2 are two completely
separated arrays.
That's for the global assignment
of an array.
But in general, we'll rather manipulate
arrays element by element.
To designate the element of an array,
we'll use the following syntax :
the name of the array, followed
by, in brackets ( [  ]),
the index of the element that we
want to select.
Be careful, the indexes of an
array's elements,
are between zero and the array's
size minus one,
they begin at zero
and go to the array's size
minus one.
If for example, I have an array
with five elements,
that contains 4, 3, 2, 7, 1,
the element 4 here,
is the element with the position
zero in the array.
If this array is named tab, I'll use
tab[0],
to designate this 4.
Then, I have tab[1], here I have
tab[2], tab[3], tab[4].
This array has a size of five.
The last element of the array is
tab[5 minus one], namely tab[4].
The indexes do go from zero
to the array's size minus one.
The first element of the array is therefore
indeed designated by tab[0],
and the tenth element of the array is
designated by tab[9],
as we begin at zero.
Be also careful with the fact that there is no control at all
if you are in a situation of array overflow.
If for example, you write with
the previous example tab[10],
nothing will tell you you have overflowed
here the array's size.
So be careful when you write
something like tab[i],
to be sure that i is between zero
and the array's size minus one,
or is strictly less than the array's
size,
or else you may encounter this
fatal error,
that we call segmentation fault,
which indicates a memory
access error.
I'm telling you, you may encounter it,
because it isn't even guaranteed
that the segmentation fault happens,
the error is there, but it isn't even sure
that the program will detect it.
Anyway, if the detection happens,
at that moment, you'll have a
segmentation fault,
with here the typical example,
that we encounter a lot
in beginner programmers' programs,
which is the following : we declare
a dynamic array, of doubles, which I
name v here,
that is initialized to empty,
as there's nothing after the
declaration,
so we initialize an empty array,
so this array is strictly empty, there's
nothing in it.
It's an array with zero elements.
In general, the programmer who
have written a program,
will rarely make the mistake just after
it, but the error is still of this type,
he'll write something like
v[0] = with an assignment,
to try and put 5.4 in the array,
but as this array is empty, we
don't even have a v[0],
v[0] doesn't exist in the empty array,
so here you'll get a segmentation
fault.
A common way of accessing the
elements of an array,
is to iterate over the array.
In C++, we have three ways of
iterating over an array.
Since the new C++ 2011 standard,
we have a way that let's us iterate
simply over all the values.
We'll detail it in a moment.
You could also, of course, with the
iteration
you have seen until now, the standard
for loop,
iterate over the different
explicit indexes of the array,
so if I designate these indexes using  i,
l'll do a loop iterating on different values for i,
i will begin with the value 0,
and will go for example one by one,
till the last element of the array,
the last element, let me remind you,
if t is the array's size,
has the index t - 1.
So here we'll do a loop
that goes from 0 to strictly less than
the array's size.
The question is how are we going to
represent this size,
how are we going to know this
size,
I'll detail that to you in a moment,
too.
I'll also explain what this new size_t
type represents.
Finally, third way, much more
advanced,
which will not be presented in this
course,
is to use what are called
iterators.
Once you want to iterate over
an array,
the question you'll ask yourself,
is which of these two previous ways
to choose.
In most cases, I recommend you
to choose
the first way of proceeding, to use
the C++ 2011 iterations,
which we will now detail.
If you can't, in this case
you use a standard iteration.
So, let's move on to the iterations introduced
in the new C++ 2011 standard.
These iterations also use the
key-word for,
as well as parentheses ().
But in parentheses,
we'll this time use the colon
separator (:)
instead of the semicolon, and we'll
have two parts,
instead of three parts.
Before the colon, we'll have the
declaration of the variable
that we want to use to
iterate over the array,
and after the colon, simply the
name of the array
that we want to iterate over.
If the iteration over this array
must modify the elements,
you'll have to add between the
reserved key-word here,
auto and the variable name, add
the modification symbol,
like we used to indicate to a
function f
that its parameters could be modified
by the function.
Let me remind you that if for
example we have a function f,
that takes a parameter x, which we
want to modify,
what you must do, is to pass
it by reference,
so here we used the reference
symbol
to indicate a pass by reference.
It's exactly the same thing here
in this for loop,
we'll use the reference symbol to
indicate that the iterated array
can be modified through the variable
used to iterate it.
Let's go to an example.
Let's suppose we want to manipulate
an array of integers,
which we will name ages here, in the
plural form,
which is a dynamic array containing
integers,
and which we initialize at the beginning
with five integers all with the null value.
At the beginning, we'll want to
fill this array
with values requested from
the user.
To achieve this, we iterate over the
array with a for loop.
But as we are going to modify the
array,
it is important to iterate over the
for loop here,
with the modification symbol, with
a reference to the array.
The syntax is therefore the
following,
we'll have the key-word for,
followed by a parenthesis,
followed by the array's name, ages,
that is after the colon,
and before we'll find again auto,
and the name of a variable, so here
we declare
a new variable age in the singular
form,
that will iterate over the array.
Then, in the block associated with the for,
you can simply use this variable age,
it's the name we have given to the
variable which will store the different values of the array.
Like any variable, it is going to
alternately
iterate over the different elements
of the array,
it is going to iterate over the array
step by step.
Every step will print the intended
message,
the age of the next employee, to ask
the age,
and stored in this variable age here,
which, alternately,
will go over every element of the
array.
What will happen is that the first
time
the loop is executed,
the variable age will indicate the
first element of the array,
and we'll ask a value for this variable.
Let's suppose that the user inputs the value 5,
at that moment, we'll put 5
in this cell of the array.
We then redo the iteration,
its the role of the for loop to
iterate,
and at that moment, age will move
to the second entry of the array.
Let's suppose that here, the user
inputs 7,
at this moment we'll have 7
that goes here,
and so on, until age has iterated
over the entire array,
until we fill the whole array.
We'll then be able to print it using another iteration,
so we begin here
by displaying a message to say that
we are going to print the array of ages,
then we redo an iterative loop with the
key-word for,
the parenthesis, the colon which
separates on one side
the array's name, ages in plural form,
and on the other side,
a variable. which I can call again
age,
it's another variable age, it has
another scope,
it will have the scope of this for
loop here,
while the previous age variable had
the scope of this first for, here.
And we use this age variable to
iterate over the array,
like any other variable, simply,
what will happen
is that at the beginning, this age
variable will indicate
the first element of the array, and
then alternately,
will take the value of the different
elements of the array,
so we'll begin by printing 5
here,
then we'll print 7...
until we have iterated over the
entire array.
This way of writing loops is
therefore very useful
because it is compact,
it suffices to simply write the key-word
for to indicate that we want to iterate,
to put the name of the variable,
a colon, the array's name,
like we had written previously,
simply write for "(auto", indicate that
we have a variable age
which iterates over the array of
ages.
Voilà, nothing more to write, so
it's very compact.
This way of iterating doesn't allow you
to iterate over several arrays at a time.
Indeed, we here have a single array
over which we can iterate,
so we couldn't for example
compare arrays
or insert an array in another...
We can't access several
elements either,
because at one single moment, we
have a single variable
that indicates a single entry.
So we can't shift for example
the elements of an array by taking
an element
and its following element in
a same loop.
Finally, we can't skip elements
of the array.
This way of iterating goes over
the different elements of the array
one after the other,
we can't skip an element
to go to the next element.
So if we need one of these
three cases,
iterating over several arrays, or accessing
several elements,
or skipping elements during an
iteration,
we'll have to use another for
loop,
use the for loops we saw in the
course
about control statements.
In this type of for iteration, we'll
typically need to
indicate the array's size,
for example to indicate the last
element,
which has the index size minus
one.
So how can we indicate the
array's size?
To achieve this, we'll use what are
called specific functions,
in object-oriented languages, we
speak of methods,
which can return the array's
size.
a specific function is simply
a function
that is associated to a variable,
and that we use in the following way,
if I have a variable, a dynamic
array named tab,
to know its size, I'll use
tab.size(),
the function size is applied to
the variable tab,
tab being the array's name.
The return type of this specific
function, size,
is a new type which is known as
size_t,
it's just a particular int, which
has the garantueed
property, by the standard, to
always be positive.
As the standard says that the
return type
of the specific function size, of the
dynamic arrays, is size_t,
you have to declare, when you are
using variables
to store such a size, you have to
declare them of type size_t.
For example, we'll write with
a standard for,
as we have seen in the course
about control statements,
with three parts separated by
semi-colons,
the declaration of a variable of
type size_t,
as we are going to store in it the
size, which we name here i,
which will iterate until the
array's size,
so here strictly less than the
as the indexes must go to
the array's size minus one,
we'll stop just before
tab.size().
And finally in the iterative part we'll
go one by one,
so if I take the same example as before,
with the array, ages,
initialized with five integers,
all null,
to input them, we'll for example,
with  a standard loop,
write "for (", the declare size_t i, a
a positive integer,
and  initialize it with zero,
that is, we'll begin with the first
element of the array,
so the index is zero. Then,
the "test" part of the iteration,
while i is strictly less than ages.size(),
as the index of the last element
must be the array's size minus one,
we'll write strictly less than
ages.size(),
for example, we'll iterate one
by one.
And what are we going to do?
We'll ask the question,
(what is) the employee's age. Here humans
rather count from one to n,
instead of from zero to n minus one,
we'll print here i + 1,
which will print 1 first, then 2, etc.
until n if n is the array's
size,
and we'll get the element at the
index i of the array ages,
with the syntax on the array's access
that we have seen.
That's it ! Perhaps all this is a
bit too much,
the next episode will illustrate
these cases
with typical examples.