In this episode, let's have a look
at typical simple applications
of the concepts presented until now
related to "dynamic arrays" [a.k.a. "vectors"].
Let's assume, for example, that we
have
a dynamic array that contains "doubles",
that we name "tab";
it is initialized  at the beginning
with 10 "doubles", all null.
How can we print the
elements of the vector?
If you don't need to print
the indexes,
for instance to print "the element at position 0 is"
or "the first element is",
but only print the contents
of the vector,
you can use an iteration
as introduced in C++ 2011.
So, for example, begin by
printing a message "Le tableau contient :"
[TN: means "The vector contains:" ]
then use a C++-11 loop with the columns (':')
[TN: a.k.a. "for-range loop"]
here, which separate
on one side the vector that we
want to iterate over,
named "tab" and then,
on the other side,
choose a name of an element
to iterate through this vector
so we'll name it here "element".
Here we have a loop
that will stop at this point
and that uses
the variable name "element"
to indicate the different elements of
this vector "tab".
As here
iterating through the vector to
print it
doesn't modify the vector,
we don't need to add
the reference character between
"auto" and the variable name.
On the other hand, if you need
to make the indexes explicit,
it will be necessary somewhere
to indicate this index
and therefore have an additional
variable.
To achieve this, we'll declare a
variable i.
We'll use a for-loop
like we have seen at the beginning,
in the course about control
statements,
which will declare i of type size_t
beginning at the index 0,
the first element of the vector is
at index 0,
separate the for into the three parts
with the semi-column (';')
After the first part, we have the
condition:
here, it's "as long as i is strictly less
than size";
actually we go to tab.size() minus 1
and, here, one by one.
Therfore, this allows us
in the loop, to print the index we
are
iterating over, the index of the elements
we are iterating over.
For example, it will print "l'élément 0
vaut" (= "the element 0 has the value")
followed by the value of the first
element stored in the vector,
stored at the index 0.
In these two examples in which we print
the elements of the vector,
we don't have to modify the elements
of the vector.
Now, let's see an example
in which we want to, for example,
affect the value,
to all the elements of the vector,
the value 1.2, for instance.
If we want to use a C++-11 loop,
we'll declare here "for(auto"
with the symbol to indicate
that we are going to modify,
a variable name ('&')
-- I had chosen "element" beforehand,
here, I choose "el" --
the column (':') to separate the two parts,
and then the name of the vector.
In this loop, we'll therefore
be able to use
"el" as a variable name
that will alternately iterate over
the different elements of the vector "tab"
and therefore, here,
for each element, we put the
value 1.2.
We could also with a vector
if we wanted to directly assign
the whole vector,
we could also use
-- but this goes beyond the scope of
illustrating for-loops --
we coud also use
a global affectation of one vector to another.
So here we are going to overwrite
the vector,
the old value of the vector,
by the new value of a vector
that is,
so, we have a look here,
element by element :
a vector
that contains doubles
which we initialize, at the
beginning,
with a certain size
which is the former size of the
vector tab
-- so we pass tab.size() --
all the elements of which
have the value 1.2.
It does indeed create a new vector
that has exactly tab.size() elements
and with every element
having the value 1.2.
It's the same as if you had declared
using two lines:
first a vector "tab2"
which is a vector of doubles,
initialized with the size of tab,
that is, tab.size(),
all with the value 1.2;
and that you then had made
a copy of "tab2" into "tab".
We can write it like this,
on a single line, in a compact way,
by declaring here what is called
an "anonymous vector".
We haven't put any name here
where we would have normally put
the name "tab2"
if we had declared it using two lines.
It's a vector without a name,
an anonymous vector.
Such an expression, like this one,
can perfectly be written,
it's an existing vector
that is promptly created
before being copied into "tab".
Another typical example of
modification
of the elements of a vector,
is when we ask their values to the
user.
Again, we have two cases.
Either we want to explicitly print
the indexes,
the indexes of the elements of
the vector,
or we simply want
to ask them,
the elements of the vector,
one after the other,
without making the indexes explicit.
Let's have a look at these two cases.
If we don't have to make the indexes explicit,
then we can use
a C++-11 for-loop [a.k.a. "range for-loop"].
But as we want to modify the vector,
as we are going to input the values,
we are here going to use a loop
with references.
We recognize the column (':') of the
C++-11 loops,
and the two parts,
the vector "tab" that we want
to modify
and here the declarative part
with the name we have chosen
to iterate over the vector's elements,
for example, "element".
Then, in this loop
-- I mean, in the body of this loop, indicated
by this block here --
in this loop, we're going to
print the message
"Entrez l'élément suivant"
[TN: means "enter the next element"],
for example,
and then input in the variable
"element".
The variable "element" will
once again
iterate over
the different elements of
the vector
beginning with the first,
then, when we'll do the second
iteration,
with the second element of the vector,
then, when we'll re-loop
in the third iteration,
we'll have the third element
of the vector, etc.
until we arrive
at the last element of the vector.
If we want to make the indexes explicit,
we'll use
the standard for-loop
separated into three parts with
the semicolon (';').
Here we declare as usual an
integer i
of type size_t, at the index of
the first element,
that is the index zero.
While i is strictly less than tab.size()
we increment it, here, 1 by 1.
Then here we print
the index,
-- as wanted,
that's why we introduced i! --
so we write: "Entrez l'élement 0"
(= "input the element 0"), the element 1, etc.
Then, finally, we get from the keyboard the value
of the element at the index i
in the vector "tab"
so "tab[i]", which indicates this element.