Regarding loops on arrays,
we have already seen how to retrieve
the size of the array.
For that, we used a specific function
called "size".
There are actually many
specific functions
associated with dynamic arrays.
We would like to introduce
you to a few ones.
Specific functions are always used
the same way.
That is, the name of the array, followed by
a period (directly glued to the array's name),
followed by the name of the specific
function.
This specific function may, for example,
take arguments
if need be.
In the "size" function, there is
no argument to be provided.
However, we will see examples
where we will need to
provide arguments.
For example, the "size" function
is a specific function
we will apply to an array.
Here, we have declared a dynamic array
called "mesure" which can contain
doubles.
If we want to retrieve this size,
in order to use it in a variable,
remember that the return type
of the "size" function is "size_t".
Thus we will declare a variable
for example, "nombre de mesures" of the
type "size_t".
We will intialize it to 0, for example.
Then, we may use it to retrieve
the return value
of this specific "size" function.
There are several other
specific functions
related to dynamic arrays.
For example, the "front" function will return
a reference to the first element.
For example, if we have
an array called "tableau",
"tableau.front() " is exactly the same
thing as having written  " tableau[0] ".
Of course, there is the symmetry :
"back " returns the last element.
So, what is the last
element of an array ?
It is "tableau[the size of the array - 1]".
Thus, the last element is :
" tableau[tableau.size() - 1] ".
There is also a function testing
if the array is empty or not.
Thus, the specific function "empty",
will return a boolean-type value
"true" if the array is empty
and "false" if the array
contains something.
You have the specific function "clear"
letting us suppress
all the elements of the array
on which we apply it.
Still with the same syntax :
"the_name_of_the_array.clear() ".
After the call of this specific function
"clear", the array is thus empty.
You then have functions letting
us add or suppress
elements from an array.
For example, the "pop_back" function
lets us suppress the last
element of an array.
Also, the "push_back" function
will add an element at
the end of an array.
Be reminded that we are talking
about dynamic arrays here;
their size can therefore vary.
This means we can add or
suppress elements.
In order to add an element to an
array, we need to indicate its value.
Therefore, the "push_back" function
will receive here the value
we wish to add to the array.
For example, let us consider
a dynamic array "v",
a dynamic array of doubles
initialized with three values :
all 4.5
For example, if we do a "pop_back"
to this "v" array,
"pop_back" will suppress the last element.
We thus end up with an array
only containing two elements.
If we then do a "push_back" on
this same array,
pushing back a certain value, let us
say 5.6,
"push_back" will add an element
behind this array.
Our "v" array now contains
4.5 , 4.6 and 5.6
Now, if we do a second
"push_back", here, with the value 6.7
this means that we add, at the
end of our array, the value 6.7
The array thus now contains
the four values 4.5 , 4.5 , 5.6 and 6.7
And if, finally, we do
another "pop_back",
"pop_back" will suppress the last element
we have just added.
We thus end up with this array
here containing three elements.
Let us take an example using
several of these specific examples.
This example, will revolve
around writing a function
initializing or reinitializing
a dynamic array of integers.
It will ask the user to
enter values
according to the following conventions.
If the user enters strictly positive
numbers,
we will add them to the array.
If the user enters 0,
we will cancel everything
and start all over again.
If the user enters
a negative number,
we will simply suppress the
last element of the array.
For example, let us suppose we
ask the user to enter three values.
The user initially enters
the value 5,
They will thus create a dynamic array with
one single element : 5,
Then, the user will enter the value 2.
We thus add an element : 2
Then, the user enters 0.
According to our convention,
we go back to square one,
and restart with an empty array.
Then, the user types 7.
We thus recreate a dynamic array with
one single element : 7.
They then type 2 and -4.
This is the second convention
according to which,
we simply suppress the last element
of the array.
Then, the user types 4
and 12.
We have thus reached the three values
we were expecting.
The program stops; the array
indeed contains 7, 4 and 12.
We are trying to write this function.
Let us remember the different steps
in order to write a function.
We have just clearly specified
what we wish to do : the "what".
The second step is to focus
on the prototype.
Let us look at typical examples
of calls to thus function.
Let us suppose we have a dynamic
array of integers called "tab".
We could, for example,
use our function (let us call it "saisie")
(TN: "saisie" means "input").
We would like to use this
function, indicating "tab",
and the size of the array;
for example, 5 elements.
For example, we could arbitrarily decide
that if we do not give the size,
this means that we will have to enter,
for example, 4 elements.
Another possible utilization example
would be to have a dynamic array
which is already initialized.
Here, the difference is that "tab"
was an empty dynamic array
while "tab2" is a dynamic array containing
12 elements.
In this case, we could, for example, decide
to enter, in "tab2", the 12 elements.
Namely, the "tab2.size()" elements it contains.
Thus, we will reenter them, using
its size as the second argument.
Those were a few different examples
on how to use the "saisie" function.
We will have to write it, now.
In order to write the "saisie" function.
We start by wondering what its
prototype should be.
First of all, the parameters.
As we seen in the exemplary call,
we will pass an array as the first
argument.
Also, the second optional argument
is a size.
This leaves us with the following
two parameters :
an array and a size.
What is the type of the size?
We will respect the custom
according to which the size of arrays
are of the type "size_t".
Thus, we declare "taille" of the "size_t" type.
(TN: "taille" means "size").
Can the size take a default value?
Yes! as we have seen in the calls,
the size may have a default value.
This means that we are not forced
to specifiy the size.
We will thus arbitrarily decide that
this default size is 4.
Let us move on to the first parameter.
The first parameter is
the dynamic array "vect".
Should this array be
modified by the function.
Yes! it is the task of
our "saisie" function
to input values into the array.
Since the array is modify, we
will pass it by reference.
Its type is a dynamic array of integers,
passed by reference.
We are now done with the parameters
of our function.
Regarding the return value,
we ask ourselves the usual question :
does it make sense to write
" z = saisie(tab) " ?
Does it make sense ?
What would be the value of z
in this input of an array?
Personally, we fail to see
what sense it makes.
Therefore, the return type
will be "void", meaning that
the function will not return anything.
We are now done with the prototype.
Now, we can focus
on the body of the function.
To that end, we will begin
with the empty vector.
That means we will start
by emptying the "vect" vector here
received as argument (we are using
the same name, here).
We are going to empty it with
the specific function "clear".
Then, will print "saisie de" to the user.
(TN : "saisie de" means "input of")
and the number of elements we wish to input.
Thus, "saisie de", for example 3 values.
Then we will start looping as long
as all the desired values
have not been entered.
That means, as long as the current
size of the "vect" array
-which we are manipulating-
is strictly less than the demanded
size.
At this point, as long as the
condition is "true",
we will print "entrez la valeur".
(TN: means "enter the value").
But what value?
At a given time, let us suppose
that the array is partially entered.
For example, we have
already entered the values 7 and 2.
Now, we would like to ask
for a third value here
which will then be added.
What is the position of this
to-be-added value?
The position of the last element
is "the size of the array - 1".
Thus, this upcoming position
is indeed the size of the array.
Thus, we will write vect.size().
And we will print "vect.size() " meaning
to enter the value of the desired index.
Then, we will read, through the
keyboard,
the value entered by the user.
With these lines, we
are reading this value.
Now, we are to treat the
three cases
chosen by our convention.
As we have said, if the value
is negative,
we need to suppress the
last element.
To that end, we first need to make
sure that there is a last element.
That means, if the value is negative
and the array is not empty.
Here, you can see that we are
using the specific function "empty"
testing if, yes or no,
the array is empty.
And suppressing the last element
if the array is not empty.
We thus write "the array is not
empty" : "not vect.empty() "
At this point, if these
two conditions
(the entered value is negative
and the array is not empty)
then we will,
with the specific function "pop_back",
suppress the last element
of the "vect" array.
Otherwise, if the entered value is zero,
our convention is to
destroy the whole array.
This is done with the
specific function "clear".
We thus do "vect.clear() ".
Otherwise, either the value
is strictly positive
or it is strictly negative and
the array is empty.
In order to eliminate this last case
and only keep the case with
a strictly positive value,
we are testing if "val" is
strictly positive.
In this case, we will add the value
with a "push_back".
We will push back this value,
adding it as the last element
of the array.