In a previous episode,
we have seen one-dimensional
dynamic array,
that is, dynamic arrays
of values.
For example, the different ages
of this course's students.
How should we proceed in order
to represent
multi-dimensional arrays?
For example, an array of
all the grades
of all the students for
for all exams.
For example, we could build
an array for one student
containing the different grades
for the different exams.
Then build a second array
for another student,
also containing the grades
for all their exams.
Then build a third array and so on.
Globablly, we would thus have
an array of ... arrays.
Each element of this array being
an array of grades itself.
For example, let us suppose
that we wish to have
an array for 5 students.
And that, for example,
each of these students will
have passed 6 exams.
Finally, we thus have 6 grades.
We will thus end up with a dynamic array
of 5 arrays of 6 marks.
We will thus declare a dynamic array
which we will call "tab".
This dynamic array will itself contain
a dynamic array of integers.
The integers are our grades.
The dynamic array of integers
is the array of a student's grades.
And the dynamic array of the
dynamic arrays of integers
is the array of the arrays of
all the students.
We will initialize it to the number
of students.
We have 5 students here.
What is each of these 5 element
actually?
It is itself a dynamic array
of integers,
representing a student's grades.
Each of these elements will
contain 6 grades.
Finally, we have a dynamic array
containing 5 dynamic arrays
of 6 grades.
The syntax used here in order
to give an initial value
to each array of grades,
each student,
each subarray
is the same as the one
we have already encountered
during the  copy of an array.
It is the anonymous array.
It is like writing :
" vector  tab2 ",
initialized with 6 ints, all with the
initial value zero
except that we have suppressed the name.
We thus end up with an
anonymous array.
Here, we did not name
our dynamic array of 6 null integers.
Now, let us look at our
dynamic array
of dynamic arrays of integers
that we have declared here
and called "tab".
" tab[i] " is thus an element of this
dynamic array
corresponding to an array of grades.
" tab[i] " is thus a itself a dynamic
array of integers,
It corresponds to the type
we have given here :
a dynamic array of integers.
Also, we have given the
initial value here.
Thus "tab[i]", for example "tab[0]"
is this array of 6 integers.
" tab[i][j] " is the element
at the position "j".
Therefore, it means that it is
the (j+1)th element of the "tab[i]" array.
Thus, starting from this array here,
the dynamic array of
dynamic arrays of integers,
if we take "tab[i]",
" tab[i] " is itself a dynamic
array of integers.
We are looking for the (j+1)th element,
the element at the position "j".
As usual, we represent " tab[i] [j] "
as the element on the (j+1)th
row and (j+1)th column.
We do not need to forget that,
here, we have
a dynamic array of dynamic
arrays of integers.
The dynamic aspect of these rows
is still there;
indeed, each of the rows
may have elements
added or removed from it.
Finally, this means that
the dynamic array of
dynamic arrays
does not necessarily have
rows of the same size.
For example, we may very well
have a first size for " tab[0] " here
(it is indeed a dynamic
array of integers),
a different size for " tab[1] "
(a second dynamic array of
integers)
and so on.
Let us now thoroughly
look at this example.
We will thus declare
a dynamic array of dynamic
arrays of integers.
We will call it, for example, "tableau".
(TN: "tableau" means "array").
If we wish to initialize it
to the value of the example
we have drawn here,
what we will do is to
give an initial value as
a list of elements.
Each of these elements being
a dynamic array of integers.
We can see  the first row here.
Then the second row
and so on for the third row
and the fourth row
of our dynamic array of
dynamic arrays of integers.
This initialization corresponds exactly
to the drawing here on the right.
A little digression regarding the syntax :
When we declare a dynamic array
of dynamic array of integers,
we need here to glue together
the closing of the two types
with the two "greater than" signs,
glued together like this.
This is only allowed in C++ 2011.
If need to write it in a compiler
which is not C++ 2011,
then you will have to put
a blank space between these two signs here.
Indeed, the syntax with the two "greater
than" signs
glued together like this
is not supported
by older compilers.
Now, let us see how to go through
this array.
For that, we will use a
C++ 2011 loop
with the colon.
The array we wish to go through
is "tableau" here.
Here, we are declaring the variable
which will go through the rows.
We call it "ligne".
(TN: "ligne" means "line" or "row").
This will let us go through
the array row by row.
Then, going through a row,
we will explore all the elements of
a given row.
For example, if we are on
the first row,
we will then go through the
different elements of this line here
in a second "for loop".
This loop will, this time,
go through the array "ligne" we have
declared here
which is a given line.
We will go through this row,
naming it
"element".
This "element" variable will go
through the different elements of a row.
This is what we have written here.
We can then use this
"element" variable
in order to go through the
different elements
of a row.
Finally, let us illustrate the
fact that the elements of the array
are indeed dynamic arrays
by giving the size of the
different rows
of the different dynamic arrays.
To that end, we will use
a usual "for loop".
As usual, we will start with " i ",
declared as a "size_t" to the value 0.
As long as " i " is less than
the array size
(the array we are talking about,
the initial array, here),
as we have done countless times,
" i " will be incremented 1 by 1.
What we will do
is to print
" tableau[i] ".
Thus, we will print "tableau[0].size() ",
"tableau[1].size() " and so on.
Then, we can use, as such,
"tableau[i]" which as array
".size()", returning the size of the array.
The following will thus be printed :
5 for " tab[0].size() " ,
3 for " tab[1].size() " ,
2 for " tab[2].size() " ,
and, finally, 3 again
for " tab[3].size() " .