In the previous episodes,
we have mostly focused on
dynamic arrays.
Namely, arrays whose size
can change
during the course of the program.
Let us now focus on arrays whose
size is known a priori.
A priori means, at the time when
we are writing the program.
Then, the size cannot vary
during the usage.
For example, if we are trying to code
a program on two-dimensional geometry,
with two-dimensional vectors,
our arrays will always contain
two coorddinates.
This number is known a priori :
it is 2,
It does not vary during the course
of the program.
Another example: if you wish to program
a chess game.
A priori, before you start writing
the program,
you know, for example, that there
will be two players.
You know that this number will
never change.
You also know that the chessboard
has 8 rows and 8 columns.
You know these numbers a priori and
they will not change.
We are in the case where the size is known
a priori and does not evolve.
Thus, in this part here of the table.
We call those "static arrays"
or "fix-sized arrays".
In C++, there are, since the new
C++-11 norm,
two types of fix-sized arrays.
The "array" type introduced with this
new norm in 2011,
and the arrays inherited from C++'s ancester:
the C language.
We call those the arrays "à la C".
In this episode, we will now
focus on the C++-11 "arrays".
The "arrays" have been introduced in
the new C++-11 norm
since the arrays "à la C", also called
"building arrays"
beget a few inconveniences.
First of all, they are systematically
passed by reference,
even if we do not put the '&' sign
of the passage by reference
to the function arguments.
The arrays "à la C" are passed
by reference.
Secondly, they are never aware
of their own size.
On the other hand, for C++-11 "arrays", just like
"vectors",
we have an easy way to know their size.
Also, arrays "à la C" cannot be globally
manipulated.
If we have an array "tab1" and
an array "tab2",
we cannot do, with arrays "à la C",
" tab1 = tab2 ".
Also, we cannot have a function
return an array "à la C",
The return type of a function cannot
be an "array à la C".
Finally, "arrays à la C" have a particular
initialization syntax
which is not as general as,
for example, the "vectors.
Consequently, we daresay that,
since the 2011 norm,
since the new "arrays" type, the "arrays à la C"
no longer have any use in C++.
However, they used to be widely used,
and therefore, by inertia,
by habit, they will still be
widely used.
For the ones of you who would
like to study this topic,
we will add an annexe on the
"arrays à la C".
Let us now move on the "arrays" of
C++-11.
We want to use a fix-sized array,
an array whose size is known when
we are writing the program.
This is the decisive question you need to ask
yourself when hesitating between "array" and "vector".
In order to declare a fix-sized array,
we will use the "array" type.
Of course, our program will need
to start with
the directive "#include ".
Then, we will declare our array
with the keyword "array".
Just after, we will write the type and the size,
which is indeed known.
This size is what is new compared
to "vectors".
Indeed, it is known when we are writing the program.
Then, as usual, we will finish with
the name we wish to give to the array.
For example, if we wish to declare
an array containing doubles.
An array whose size is fixed 3,
and containing doubles only,
we will write :
" array " and, just after,
the name.
For example, here "vecteur_3d ".
Beforehand, we have included, at the
beginning of our programm the "array" library.
We this declaration, we thus have an "array",
which is a fix-sized array.
Its size will not be able to evolve.
The size given at the very
beginning
will be the size during the whole
run of the program.
It contains enough room to
store three doubles.
Another example, if we wished
to declare the inhabitants
of a certain numbers of districts
(known a priori).
We can very well declare it like this,
a constant expression.
"const", the number of districts.
It is of the "size_t" type
since we know
that we are indicating an
array size here.
Thus, "nb_cantons", the name of the variable.
[TN: "canton" means "district"]
Here, we can initialize it to 26.
[TN: there are 26 districts in Switzerland].
This then allows us to make good use
of this variable here,
as the number of districts
in our dynamic array here :
An "array" of "unsigned int".
Those are positive integers.
The number of inhabitants is
a positive integer.
We are indicating the name here.
Therefore, "habitant" is an array containing
exactly
26 unsigned integers
(26 unsigned int ).
We have just seen how to declare
a fix-sized array.
Of course, we can also initialize it.
This means we can give it values
when we declare it.
For that, we use a usual syntax, rather
similar to the one encountered for the vectors.
Between parentheses here, the
value for an array,
that is, all the values.
Of course, we should not forget
the braces
for a set of values indicating the initial
values of the aray;
each value being separated by a comma.
For example, if we wish to declare
an array with 5 integers,
a static array, a fix-sized array
of 5 inzegers,
we declare, here, "array".
Each element will be of the int type.
Then, we will pass the size which is known
while we are writing the program.
Here, we have previously
declared it
as a constant expression of
the type "size_t".
We decided to call it "taille" [TN: means "size"],
and it contains 5.
Thus, we will declare an array
containing 5 integers.
We call this array "ages".
Then, we initialize it between parentheses
with the values given
as a set of values with the braces.
The set of value is separated
by commas.
Thus, 20, 35, 26, 38, 22; which will give us
the array represented here.
There is a second way to
initialize arrays.
We had seen it already for the
dynamic arrays.
It is the equals sign.
Then, again, on the other side
of the equals sign,
the set of values between braces and
separated by commas.
In the previous example, we could
have used this way.
Of course, we cannot use both
ways at the same time.
It is an alternative.
But, we could have declared
our "ages" array
and initialized it with the equals
sign and braces.
By the way, certain compilers will
only tolerate this
second initialization way.
Others tolerate both ways.
Also, please note that an
uninitialized fix-sized array
may contain just about anything. This
means we do not know what it contains.
Now that we have declared and
initialized our fix-sized array,
we may start using it.
There is here nothing more in comparison
with "vectors".
The syntax is truly the same.
If we want to use an element at
the position "i" of a static array
called "tab", we will use " tab[i] ".
This is exactly the same as for
vectors.
We can also iterate on a
static array
with an exact similar syntax as the
one used for vectors.
We can either use the C++-11 "for" :
for(auto element : tableau)
or with a classical "for".
The "array"s have also a specific
function "size"
returning their size.
Again, we can very well write,
as we did for dynamic arrays,
" tab.size() " to obtain the size of a
static array "tab".
We can also use global
assignments.
Globally assign an array "tab1" to
another "tab2".
If we have declared an array of integers
"tab1" which size is 3
- its size will not change -
initialized to the values 1, 2 and 3.
We can very well copy
it directly
into another static array of the
same size (3, here)
by writing this : " tab2 = tab1 ".
This will fully copy "tab1" into "tab2".
Of course, they still remain two
completely separated arrays.
it simply copies "tab1" into "tab2",
but "tab1" and "tab2" will still live their
own life separately.
If we modify "tab1", "tab2" will naturally
not be impacted.
As you can see, the utilization
of arrays
is very similar to the one of "vectors".
The sole difference is that the size
of "arrays" is fixed from the start
and cannot be modified.
Similarly, while we could build
"vectors" of "vectors",
we can also build "arrays" of "arrays" :
static arrays of static arrays.
Then, if need be we can of course
combine the two :
building static arrays of vectors,
vectors of static arrays and so on.
Now, let us have look at static
arrays of static arrays,
"arrays" of "arrays".
What  we did for "vectors"
of "vectors",
we can do for "arrays" of "arrays".
The only difference is that we will
have to indicate the sizes.
For example, we can have
an "array" of 2...
Of two what?
Of two "arrays" of two doubles.
We thus have a matrix which
we will call "rotation".
This is a matrix we are wont
to represent
as a 2x2 arrays containing
4 elements.
It is indeed an array of two
"arrays of two doubles".
Here is the declaration of a 2x2
static array.
Of course, we can come up
with many other examples.
We could build an array
collecting
statistics on the districts.
We will thus have the first-dimensional
array containing the districts.
Its size being the number of districts.
Then, each districts will itself have
a certain number of statistics.
For example, two statistics
such as the surface and the
number of inhabitants.
We can even build more
complicated objects.
such as three-dimensional arrays :
arrays of arrays of arrays.
Mathematically, this corresponds
to tensors.
What matters is to truly
understand the different sizes.
We will have an array of 3,
of 3 arrays of 2,
arrays of 2,
arrays of 4 elements.
This layer of 2 * 4 elements is
reproduced
three times in the initial array.
Certainly, this is rather complicated
and uncommon.
The goal is to simply show
that we may generalize
to virtually any number of arrays
and mostly to indicate the
order of the different sizes.
Let us now illustrate the use of
these multi-dimensional arrays.
Let us go back to what we had
called the "rotation" matrix.
It is 2x2 array of doubles
which we represent like this.
The utilization is exactly similar
to the one of the "vectors".
We will use the the brackets
with two dimensions.
Let us look at "rotation" of 1.
Please remember that the size notation
starts with 0 and ends with "size - 1".
Here, we have  rotation[1]
In "rotation" of 1, we will seach for the
element at the position 0.
To this element here, we will
give the value 0.231 .
Here, we are indeed focusing on
the element : " rotation[1][0] "
Similarly, let us go back to our
array of statistics
Here, " statistique[i] " is thus an *array"
containing "nb_statistiques" ints.
It is an "array" of "nb_statistiques"
integers.
Itself, is an array which size
is "nb_statistiques".
This is rigorously similar to how
we used to proceed
with vectors of vectors.
Nothing new here, except that
the sizes are fixed.
All rows thus have the same
size/length.
However, a little specifity in
comparison to "vectors".
This regards the initialization
of "arrays" of "arrays".
The syntax currently suppored
by the compilers
only tolerates one single brace
in the initializations.
For example, if we build a
static array of static array,
for example, 4 times 3 integers.
Here, we are putting integers
we wish to initialize.
Unlike vectors,
we will have to initialize simply
with one single brace.
Inside, we will put
the set of values
we wish to declare, in
the reading order.
Here, for example, 0, 1, 2
and then 3, 4, 5
simply separated by commas.
Voilà, this is the syntax
currently used to initialize
static arrays of static arrays.
To conclude, let us sum up
the different syntaxes
between static arrays and
dynamic arrays,
between "arrays" and "vectors".
The size of dynamic arrays
can vary
while the program is being
executed.
On the other hand, the size
of static arrays must be known
while we are writing the program.
The dynamic arrays are of the
type "vector".
The static arrays are of the
type "array".
When we declare a dynamic
we can declare it empty
- it is fully possible to declare
an empty dynamic array -
or we can give it an initial
size, for example, 5.
However, this size may vary during
the course of the program.
We can very well add or
remove elements.
For static arrays, the size must
absolutely be known.
We can either write it like this,
or use a variable.
One way or the other, this
size must absolutely be known.
Here, we only have one syntax
for static arrays.
Then, in order to
use the elements of an array,
the syntax is the same for
static or dynamic arrays.
For one dimension : " tab[i] ".
If the array has two dimensions :
" tab[i][j] "
In order to know the size of an array,
static or dynamic,
we use the function "size".
In order to go through an array,
dynamic or static,
we proceed the same way :
we can either use a classical
"for" loop
or use a C++-11 loop with
the colons.
If we wish to go through the array
without modifying the elements,
we will write "for auto" followed by the
name we wish to use for the elements.
If we wish to modify the elements,
we should not forget to add the ampersand ('&').
This is the same for
a static array
or a dynamic array.
Then, in a dynamic array,
we may possibly add
elements.
This is only possible for dynamic
arrays
and does not exist
for static arrays.
We cannot modify a
static array.
For dynamic arrays, we add elements
with "push_back".
This will add the value we have given
to "x" at the end of the array.
We will thus copy "x" at the end
of the array.
If we wish to remove the last
element of a dynamic array,
then, we will use "pop_back".
Of course, this does not exist
for static arrays since we cannot
modify them.
Finally, a last difference,
regarding the initialization
of dynamic arrays of
dynamic arrays.
We can use the syntax supported
by all compilers
of the initialization with an array
of arrays between parentheses.
For static arrays of static
arrays,
we will have to use the
"equals" syntax
with only one level
of braces
with the list of the desired values.
Like this.
One behind the other.