In the last episode,
we considered the fundamental aspects
of object-oriented programming (OOP).
In this video,
we will start to code
all this in Java.
So we saw that  OOP
uses the concept of class
which is the result of the process
of abstraction and encapsulation
as we saw in the example,
the definition of the class Rectangle
that had the data members "largeur"
and "hauteur" (TN:"width" and "height")
and had a method "surface" to calculate
the area (TN: "surface" means "area").
A class, in programming languages,
defines a new type that allows for the
creation of variables of this type
for example three variables
rect1, rect2, rect3
that are called in object-oriented
language instances or objects.
So how do you code this in Java ?
To declare a new class,
we will use the special keyword
"class".
For instance, we will write "class Rectangle"
to declare a class that we decided
to call Rectangle,
followed by its definition
as we will specify later on.
This expression "class Rectangle"
defines a new type,
that we can use just as we would do
with any other type,
to declare, for example, variables.
We will use the name of the type,
that is, the name of the class,
followed by the name of the variable,
that is, the name of the instance.
For example, to declare an instance
that we name "rect1",
of the class Rectangle, we simply
write "Rectangle rect1".
In OOP terminology,
a variable corresponds
to an instance.
In Java, the instance's name,
corresponding to "rect1"
in this case,
is actually a reference
to a real object in the memory.
All this will be explained
in more detail in the course.
But where do we write
these lines?
You have two solutions available:
You can declare all your classes
in one file,
or you can declare one class
in each file.
Let's examine the first case,
with all the classes declared
in one unique file.
Suppose that we want
a class "Dessin" (TN: ="Drawing")
that uses the class Rectangle.
All this is declared in
one unique file,
that we decided to name "Dessin.java".
Thus we have here the
entirety of the file "Dessin.java".
We can declare a class Rectangle,
here, like this,
and a class Dessin.
Concretely, to compile it,
we use the command
"javac Dessin.java" that
you can directly
enter into the command line,
or you can have an integrated
development environment (IDE)
like Eclipse do it for you.
This compiling will produce
however two new files.
A file "Dessin.class" and
a file "Rectangle.class",
and then to execute all this,
the method main being
in the class Dessin,
we will enter "java Dessin"
in the command line,
or you can simply execute
the class
from Eclipse for example.
So this is the first solution
to declaring your classes.
Another solution consist
of declaring one class per file.
So each time you have a class,
you have a separate file,
thus you would declare
the class Rectangle
in, for example, the
file "Rectangle.java",
the class Dessin in the
file"Dessin.java".
And in this case, if you
are using a command line,
you would have to compile
each file separately.
Of course, in an IDE,
these two files would
be part of the same project,
and would be compiled
independently
by invoking only once
the command "Build".
And Eclipse will take care of
compiling the two files,
and will result in,
like in the first solution,
two files ".class".
To execute this files from
the command prompt,
we would enter "java Dessin"
because it the class Dessin
has the function main.
This is also what Eclipse
would do for you
if you did the execution from there.
If you wanted to try "java Rectangle",
Rectangle doesn't contain a method main,
to in this case, you wil
get an exception,
that says that the class Rectangle
doesn't have a method main.
Let's see how to fill this part
of the program,
that is to say, how to include
data members and methods in our class.
Let's start with data members.
The properties of the class Rectangle
are width and height.
To declare these data members,
simply put the type and the name of the
different data members.
Here, for each variable we declare the
variable's type and name
followed by a semicolon.
In the example of the class Rectangle,
this gives
double hauteur, double largeur
(TN: "hauteur" means "height" and "largeur", "width").
It's as simple as that!
Likewise, for using
the data members of an instance,
we have the name of the instance,
followed by a period,
followed by the name of the data variable
that we want.
For example, to use the
height of the rectangle rect1,
we write rect1.hauteur.
Let illustrate this with
an example,
given here in one file,
that contains a class Exemple
that has the method main,
as well as a class Rectangle,
in which we
declare a variable "hauteur" of type double,
and a variable "largeur" also
of type double.
The class Exemple will create
an instance of the class Rectangle.
To this we have to
use the following syntax.
The declaring-initilalizing an istance is
done
by using the name of the class
followed by the name of the instance,
followed by "= new",
the name of the class,
and parentheses, like this.
For example,
we saw in the last example,
to create an instance "rect"
of the class Rectangle,
we would write "= new Rectangle( )".
Which would generate all
the data members
and initialize them to the
following values.
If we had variables of type int, they
would be initialized at the int value 0.
For doubles, at the double value 0.
For booleans,  at false.
And for objects, at the special value "null",
which we will come back
to momentarily.
In the last example, here,
rect1 has a width and height of 0 before
modifying them.
Now let's examine
the declaration of methods.
Methods are simply functions,
that are embedded in a class.
In the case of the class Rectangle,
we will
add the method "surface".
(TN: "surface" means "area")
A method is declared just
like a function
with the return type,
the name of the method,
then in parentheses,
possibly a list of parameters;
all this is the method header
followed by the actual definition
of the method: the method body
in braces.
The only difference, is that methods
are declared inside the class itself.
In our example,
the class Rectangle,
the method "surface" is
included here in the class Rectangle
with, its return type double because
this method returns a double, its name,
but no parameters,
and returns the product of the
height and the width.
We could ask ourselves
"Don't we need parameters ? "
Indeed, if we had written an
ordinary function,
like we did before, outside
the class,
we would have had to pass
the height and width as arguments
to the function,
so that their values can
be used in the calculation.
So why for this method in
the class Rectangle,
do we not need to
pass any parameters ?
The answer is that
the height and width
are data members of this class.
Since "surface" is
part of the class Rectangle,
the method has access to
the height and width
of the class Rectangle.
Technically, this is called
"the scope of the class",
that is, that all the data
members of a class
are accessible from any
member of the class
and in particular
from each of its methods.
For example, all the methods of
the class Rectangle
can access the height and length.
Therefore it is unnecessary to pass these
variables as arguments to the methods.
In summary, a method is
simply a function
that is specific to a class,
so is put in that class,
but also has access to the
data members of the class.
This is typically a beginner's problem
when writing their first methods.
It is very important not to
pass attributes as arguments
to class methods.
In our example
we have exactly this,
we have a method "surface"
that does not take any parameters
but can access Rectangle's
height and width
That were declared previously in the class.
That said, it's not because
we don't need to pass
the data members as arguments to
these methods
that the methods never have
parameters.
Of course, if the method
needs certain parameters
from outside the class to
do its work,
then parameters would
need to be declared.
For example, suppose that we
have a class "FigureColoree" (= "ColoredShape")
and in this class,
we would have several data members
as well as a method "colorie" that colors
the shape (TN: "colorie" means "color")
and that would receive a color
and would modify the instance
of the class FigureColoree
to color them with this color,
"Couleur" being itself another type
that we would have defined
with a class or a typedef.
We could for example declare
a shape, an instance of the class
FigureColoree,
and rouge (TN: means "red) , an instance of the
class Color.
And, anticipating on the syntax,
color the shape rouge.
What I want to show you
is that the color rouge comes
from outside the class FigureColoree
and is not part of the class
FigureColoree.
That's why here we have
to pass it as argument.
It is not a data member
that we need to pass
as parameter to the method colorie.
So now you know how
to declare and define
methods of a class.
But how do you use them?
Namely, how do you invoke them?
To do this
we will use a syntax similar to
that for data members,
and similar to what you have
seen in other contexts
such as when you called
the method "size" of a dynamic array.
If you write "tableau.size()" you are
indeed calling the method size,
of a dynamic array.
The usual format is
"name of the instance"."name of the method"
then in parentheses,
the list of arguments that you want
to pass to the method.
For instance, to invoke the method "surface"
on the instance rect1
of the class Rectangle,
we will write "rect1.surface".
Here, because the method surface
doesn't take any arguments,
the parentheses are empty.
Let's come back to
our comprehensive example.
We have, like before,
the class Exemple
that uses in the method main,
an instance rect1
of the class Rectangle.
In the class Rectangle, we have
added a method "surface".
To invoke this method surface
on the instance rect1
of the class Rectangle,
we simply write "rect1.surface",
which returns a double,
that we could print with
a message like "surface :"
In this case it would write
"surface :"
and 12 which is the result of
3 times 4.
Each instance has its own
set of values for its data members.
If, for example, I declare
3 instances rect1, rect2, rect3
of the class Rectangle,
and assigned the value 3
to the height of rect1,
the value 4 to the width
of rect1,
and 11.5 and 3.8 for rect2.
We would have another
memory location
for the value 34.3 of
the width of rect3,
and a value for its height.
So we would have 3 different
variables existing in the memory,
and when we call "rect2.surface",
its the general method surface
of the class rectangle
that will be applied
to the instance rect1,
which means that in
this method surface,
when it is called,
"largeur" implies "rect1.largeur"
and "hauteur" implies "rect2.hauteur".
If I call in another place
"rect2.surface",
then in this call, "rect2.surface",
then "hauteur" will designate
"rect2.hauteur",
and "largeur" will implie "rect2.largeur"
Note that strictly speaking,
these representations of instances here
are not exactly correct,
because the variables refers
to objects in the memory,
but the aim here is to show
that when a method is called,
it has access to each of
these data members.
We will consider later
in this course
how things
are stored in the memory.
So this concludes
this video.
We saw how to
declare objects in Java,
we saw how to declare
data members
and how to declare methods.
That is to say, that we saw
this axe of this chart.
We still need
to see
the differences between the
user interface and implementation details,
that is, this axe,
which will be the
topic of our next episode.