In the last episode,
we learned how to
code declarations of classes
how to define their
data members and methods, that is,
on this graph summarizing
OOP, essentially this axe
that we have examined
in the last video.
But how do we in Java
materialize the notion
of interface, the visible part
of the class, and the implementation
part of the class, that is hidden.
How do we implement this axe
of the chart?
This will be the topic
of this video.
Concretely, if we look at
the class Rectangle from before
we decided to have a method surface
that was part of the interface
and that could be used
anywhere in the program
and we also have two private
data members "largeur" and "hauteur".
In Java, the private components
are declared like this.
We will add the keyword "private"
before each data member or method
that we want to hide,
making them inaccessible outside the class.
These members will
therefore not be in the interface.
Inaccessible from outside a class
simply means
that if, for example, in the
method main or
in another class we wrote this,
(we declare an instance of the
class Rectangle, and we try to
directly access the height like this)
in this case the compiler will
return an error message
saying that the field "hauteur"
is declared private in Rectangle.
Note that if nothing is specified,
like for this method surface,
then it will have a
default access
that I will elaborate on
in a few minutes.
So we saw that to declare
the private implementation part,
we use the keyword private,
and inversely for the public interface
that we want to have available
externally,
and accessible from all the other
classes we use the keyword public.
So the method surface,
being part of the interface of Rectangle,
we will add "public" before the header
and definition of the method surface.
If I take up the last example
of a method main,
that declared an instance rect
of the class Rectangle,
this instance would be able
to invoke the method surface
and store the return value
in a variable.
This is possible because the
method surface is declared public.
If it had been declared private,
then I couldn't have
done this manipulation: accessing
surface outside of
the class Rectangle.
I would like to remind you of
some programming guidelines,
and important principles in OOP.
One is to declare all the
data members private, even if
there are some exceptions
that we will not consider here,
and are not important in this context.
Thus it is absolutely indespensable
to not have any data member public
and declare private any method
used internally to
modularize the class implementation,
and only have a few hand-picked
public methods
in the interface.
The core of a good conception is to make the right choices
for the public methods.
A small technical annex
on access rights:
programs in Java are usually
organized around the notion of "packages"
that is not presented in
the introductory videos but
is presented in the course complements.
Even if you don't declare a package,
you are, in fact, in a default package.
If you don't declare
a data member or method private,
then this member is actually
accessible in any class that
belongs to the package.
It's as if it were declared public for
the entire package and private
for everything outside the package.
This is what is called
"friendly access rights".
If for example, in a default package,
you have
a class Rectangle that
contains a data member "hauteur"
but isn't declared private or public,
and in the same package, you
also have a class Dessin that uses
the class Rectangle, then this
class Dessin will have access
to "hauteur" and to any other
data members and methods that are
declared without access rights
because Dessin is in the same package.
Thus Dessin can directly access
the member variable "hauteur"
of the Rectangle rect,
which I find is not great.
That is why we recommend that
you explicitly specify public
before each data member
and methods that you want to
have in the interface.
These will be public, not only
for this package, but also
for other packages.
Everything private will be
reserved for the implementation details.
So this is all I want to say
on packages.
It's a technical aspect of Java that
is perhaps a bit premature for this course.
That said, you could say
that if all the data members are private,
how will I be able to use them?
For example, if we wanted
to modify the height of my rectangle,
this in itself being debatable.
Do we really want to change
But let it be so.
Suppose that we want to access
the height of the rectangle
just to know its value.
How can we obtain the values
of the dimensions of the rectangle
if they are private data members
if we can't access them
outside the class?
I can't do something like this:
declare a new rectangle and
try to print its height.
This is something that I cannot do
because the variables are private.
To solve this problem,
we will include in the interface
a few methods necessary to this end
[called setters and getters]
so for example a method to
modify the height,
a method to access the width, etc.
For example, here, we want a
method that returns the value of hauteur
and we would write something like this
with a method getHauteur.
I would like to insist on this important
aspect of writing a program,
that you don't have to systematically
include methods
to modify or even to access
the data members of a class,
but you have to decide which
variables can
be modified or accessed
from outside through methods
like these.
Methods that only access the value
of the variable are called "accessors".
And methods that modify the values
of the data members are "mutators".
Accessors, also called "get methods" or
"getters", return the data member's value.
So if we need to access the value
of the data member "hauteur",
"hauteur", being of type double,
the method will return a value of the same type
a double, with "double getHauteur",
and we will write "return hauteur".
Recall that all methods of a class
can access the data members of the class,
so here it is the height of the current
instance (that called the method).
In the same way, we can declare
an accessor for the width.
Mutators, also called "set methods" or
"setters" modify the data members
by assigning them a value.
To do this, they have
to first receive the value
from outside, and this received value
will then be assigned to the variable.
So this value is received as parameter
and doesn't return anything,
because its purpose is not
to return something but to
assign a value.
So for example, value of the parameter
"h" is copied to the variable "hauteur",
and likewise, the value of the parameter "l" is
copied to the variable "largeur".
Let's illustrate this
with an example.
We have as before, a class
Exemple, with its method main
where we use the instance rect1
of the class Rectangle,
that has in its interface
a method surface, as well as
two get methods.
Here an accessor getHauteur that
doesn't take any arguments
because it doesn't need any values,
however, it returns a double,
(double because the value of the
returned variable is a double).
hauteur and largeur are
as before in the implementation part
and are declared private.
Similarly, we have an accessor
for the width, and in the public part
we also have a mutator setHauteur,
that receives the value to assign
the data member from outside,
through the parameter h.
To use these methods,
for example in the method main,
we will, for instance, call getHauteur
which will return the height
of the instance rect1.
We will have assigned beforehand
the value 3 to the height of rect1
by writing "rect1.setHauteur(3)".
The value 3 will then be copied into the
data member "hauteur" of rect1.
Likewise invoking setLargeur on
rect1 will sett the width of rect1.
Another comment students
frequently make is
"Why do we have to do all this?
It's too complicated to write all this!"
"Why not keep largeur
and hauteur public?"
"Like this, we can use them
however we want!"
But it's using them in whatever
way that's exactly the problem!
For example in this case, if I declare
an instance rect1 of Rectangle,
I could very well assign
the invalid value -36
to its height.
While, if instead of assigning this
value to the data member,
I had passed it to the method setHauteur,
we could have had in this method
a mechanism to verify whether
the value is positive and valid,
and in this case, assign the value,
or if the value is negative or zero,
then to, for example, report the error.
Using this set method allows for
a verification process
that guarantees the validity of the data.
Suppose that we also have
a data member a bit more complex,
here, a String "label", for example,
that contains some information
and that we use externally
by writing for example "rect.label.length"
using methods associated
with the type String.
Suppose now, that we write
400 lines of code like this
directly accessing "label".
If the class programmer decides
to substitute the String
with an ArrayList, we would have
to throw 400 lines out
and write everything from scratch.
But if we had only used the interface,
which isn't supposed to change,
and that we do not access the
class fields directly,
but only through the interface,
then if the class programmer
changes the String to an ArrayList,
our 400 lines will not be effected
because they respect
the class interface.
It's for these two fundamental
reasons:
the ability to verify the values
assigned to different fields,
and the ability to modify the
program independently (modularization)
that we recommend to use
getters and setters
and to not put data members
in the interface,
but to have the exclusively
in the public part of the class.
It's clear that doing this
in small exercises
doesn't make much sense,
but does in a big project.
Moreover, it is in this context that
OOP was invented.
And so it is with this objective
in mind
that we learn these principles.
So follow these guidelines,
and try to separate to the maximum
members constituting the interface
from those that are implementation details.
To close, let's examine another
technical aspect: shadowing.
Shadowing occurs when an identifier, a name,
for one variable
shadows a name used
for another variable.
This happens typically in OOP,
when a parameter,
such as "hauteur" in the
method setHauteur,
hides the data member
for height "hauteur".
In this context, we would like
to designate the data member
with this "hauteur" and the parameter
with this other  "hauteur".
But in this situation, the compiler
will not know the difference
and so writing this is not correct.
So what to do?
Well we can simply
use different names,
like we did before,
with h being the name of the parameter.
In that case there isn't any ambiguity.
Or else you can use a technique which removes
the ambiguity by
by resorting to the keyword "this"
to refer to the current instance,
so "this = current instance".
In the last example, to illustrate,
if we call the parameter
of the method "hauteur",
then we will have to unmask
the name "hauteur" referring to
the data member by saying "this.hauteur"
meaning "this current instance's hauteur"
so "this.hauteur"
designates this height.
In this situation, it is obligatory
to put "this",
but I recommend to avoid this
kind of situation,
by choosing different names,
that are clear and avoid
any ambiguity.
Let's summarize what we
have learned about access rights
as well as the scope of data
members and methods of a class.
We saw that the keywords "private"
and "public" determine the access rights.
private defines what constitutes the
hidden implementation details,
only accessible from within a class,
while "public" defines what is part
of the interface,
accessible from outside the class,
from the main, and other classes.
So here the scope of the data
members is limited to the class,
x and y are accessible
anywhere in "MaClasse" and
particularly in any method of this class.
For example, here "y" refers to
the data member of the instance
that the method would
apply to.
Shadowing can also occur here,
if we reuse the name of
the data member,
like here with the parameter.
So then, because of scope
resolution, x will locally
refer to the parameter x.
So if we want to refer to
the data member x, we have
to use the word "this" to unmask x.
"this.x" then refers to the instance
to which the method is applied.
Let's end this video, with
another technical aspect:
how objects are represented
in memory.
This technical aspect is
nevertheless important
when writing code.
I recall, like we saw earlier,
in the first course on programming,
that objects like Strings or arrays,
are represented in the memory
through references.
For example, if I declare a
String v initialized at "Welcome",
then we can see the storage
like this,
v is a reference to a
certain memory location
where the value "Welcome"
is stored.
In the same manner, if I declare
2 Rectangles, rect1 and rect2,
in the memory I would have
2 references to 2 memory locations
that effectively contain
its height and its width.
Now if we assign the values 3 and 4
to rect1's height and width,
and also initialize the dimensions
of rect2,
for example 11.3 and 2.7.
We will have this depiction
of the memory,
with objects being in fact
references to locations
where their values are really stored.
This is paramount to know
when comparing objects,
because we have to know if we are
comparing the references or their values?
At this stage, we are only comparing
references if we don't do anything.
If we copy an object into another
we are in fact doing this,
with rect2 = rect1.
And if I print an object,
only the reference will
be displayed even
if we wanted the real values
displayed.
We will come back to this aspect
later in the course.
Variables being references, they
can also be a reference to no object,
In this case we would
use the keyword "null".
So for instance, I can declare
here an instance rect
of the class Rectangle
and say it is null,
which means that it
is a reference to nowhere,
which can be represented like this.
So we can frequently
see this kind of code:
if rect == null then do
something, such as
assigning it a
new rectangle.
Or else you can have,
if rect is not null,
than in this case use it
for example to call
the method surface.