In the last episodes, you learned
how to write a class in Java.
Now you know how to define
data members and methods,
and you know how to implement different
aspects of encapsulation,
such as defining what
is publicly accessible,
and what is inaccessible.
In this lesson, we will anchor
these notions with some examples.
And we will see that encapsulating
properly requires taking
a certain number of measures.
At this stage, defining
a class in a program
implies defining a new type that is
characterized by data members and methods.
In order to encapsulate this class you'll have
to define everything that constitutes
the implementation details
as private, and everything
that is part of the user interface
for external access
as public.
It is important to examine
how this is enacted through
a real example, and this is
the goal of this video.
If we want a program
to be able to work with the notion of rectangle,
the first thing to do is to
is to define a class Rectangle
by defining its properties
with data members,
and its abilities with
its own methods.
Another thing to do is to decide what
will go into the user interface,
and what will constitute the
hidden implementation details.
So here is one possible
implementation of the class Rectangle
that was our introductory example.
To define a class, we use
the special keyword "class",
followed by the name
that we chose for our class,
with the convention in Java,
that the class name is capitalized.
Then, we defined
some data members
specific to the class,
as well as some methods.
We implemented
some aspects of encapsulation
by deciding what constituted
the implementation details,
typically the data members,
and what constituted the interface,
that the external user can use
that we specified using
the keyword "public".
This class Rectangle right here
will provide a number
of functionalities
that allow the user to access the
data members of an rectangle,
modify its values,
and calculate its area.
Note that it is
generally not necessary
to systematically define get/set methods
for each of the class data fields.
Here we defined them because
at this stage of the course,
we only know how to interact
with a class rudimentarily.
We have tried here to respect the
guidelines for encapsulation,
which means that only
allow the user access
to the class functionalities
through the interface.
This means that
the class programmer
has the freedom to modify
the implementation details.
Here I can decide to change how
the rectangle is represented,
for example using an array with
2 doubles to store
the height and width.
And in this case, it's my job,
as class programmer to
adapt the class methods.
For instance, instead of returning
"hauteur", I would return "dims[0]".
It's my responsibility to
adapt the methods so that
the user can continue using
the class without being effected.
He can continue using
getHauteur, setHauteur,
and surface without even
knowing that I had made
internal modifications to the class.
And because the user is
forced to use
these predefined methods,
to manipulate an object, a certain
number of measures implemented
in these methods can prevent
the user from incorrectly
manipulating the object
and its contents.
So do you see how the class
can be improved in this aspect?
Here you have the code
of the class programmer of Rectangle,
who conceived this
new data type.
Let's see what happens on
the user's side.
The user can be the same person who
coded the class Rectangle,
but not necessarily.
The code that you have here,
is the implementation of
a class "Geometrie"
that uses the type Rectangle
of the class Rectangle
that was just defined.
This means that Geometrie can use
this type just like any other type.
So here I can declare a variable
rect of type Rectangle.
This declaration follows the same
syntax as declarations
of variables of normal types.
We also saw,
at this stage of the course,
that to initialize an object,
you had to use an
expression like this in Java.
We will learn what this means
in the next episode.
For right now, it's unavoidable.
When this line is
executed,
we will have this situation
in the memory.
We have a variable called rect
that contains a reference or address
to an object of type Rectangle
that has 2 fields:
one for the width
and one for the height.
Of course, the first thing we want
to do here is initialize these fields
that are right now set at 0
to particular values.
This can be done by
asking the user
to enter some values for
the width and height
on the keyboard.
Once the user has
introduced a value for the height,
we can put this value into
"hauteur" of the object rect
with the method setHauteur.
We use this notation
which means that we invoke the
method "setHauteur" on the object rect
to set its value.
Imagine that the user enters
the value 5.0, which leads to
this situation.
The same goes for these lines
that initialize
the width of the rectangle.
Now we have an object
properly initialized.
Now we can use other
functionalities of the class Rectangle
for example, to compute
the area.
We use the dot operator again like
this to compute the
area of the rectangle
that have just declared and initialized.