A well thought-out user interface of
a class is key to a good design
of an object-oriented program.
Indeed, a poorly-designed interface that
gives the user too much access
to implementation details can be just as
risky as leaving data members public.
In this video we will compare
two possible interfaces for a class.
In the first interface, the
functionalities are too low-level
and reveal to the outside user
implementation details of the class.
While in the second interface,
only indispensable functionalities
are provided.
We will see, of course, that
the second option
is much better than the first one.
So we want to program a class
that allows us to play
a game of tic-tac-toe.
(TN: "jeu du morpion" means "tic-tac-toe")
As a reminder, it is a game for two
players played on a 3 by 3 grid,
with the first player placing Os while
the other player playing Xs.
The 2 players take turns and
try to
get three of their pieces in a row
either across, diagonally,
or vertically.
In this first version of
the class "JeuMorpion",
the programmer has a
minimalist vision of what
functionalities he offers
to the outside world.
When he designed the class, he looked
at what characteristics it had,
so he said to himself that
logically he needed a grid,
then for the class functionalities,
he provides the external user
a public initialization method to be
able to start with an empty grid
in order to start playing.
He also provides a function
that gives access to the grid
in order to place tokens
on it from outside the class,
such as red Os and blue Xs.
Let's examine more closely
how the programmer
implemented this class JeuMorpion
and how he represented
for example the grid.
Here, we see that he uses
a one-dimensional array.
This is a possible, but perhaps not
a very conventional choice.
So in this modelization,
a grid is actually an object
with a reference
to a one-dimensional array.
So here, imagine for example
that we use the first 3 positions
of the array for the first line,
the next 3, for the second line,
and the last 3 positions for
the last line of the grid.
The method to initialize the grid
creates an array with the default
values being zeros in each slot.
So everywhere we have zeros.
The class programmer made
the effort to declare the
data member "grille" private, as he
should have, which means that the
external user of the class
cannot directly access this field.
So if outside the class,
we declare an instance of JeuMorpion
called "jeu", we will not be able
to directly access the grid
with this notation.
However, he provides
the method getGrille,
because the user needs to interact
with this grid
in order to fill it.
For example, the user can declare
a one-dimensional array
that will be the grid
he will play on,
and assign it
what is returned by getGrille,
that is, a reference to
the array representing the
tic-tac-toe grid.
We will see that through
mechanism,
the user will be able to
do manipulations
that are unwanted.
So want can the user do?
So like we said before,
he can declare and use a
variable of type JeuMorpion,
and he will then use
available functionalities
to manipulate this variable jeu.
Imagine that he wants
to place an O on a particular
box.
One of the first things he will do
is to decide what conventions
he will use to fill the grid.
For example, for him, 1 means that
there is an O in that box,
and 2 means that an X
is in that position, with
0 meaning the slot
is empty.
If the user wants to put an O
in the first position of the grid,
he will have to access
the variable "grille"
through the method getGrille
and use this reference to the grid
to put the right value.
So he has to know that
getGrille give him access to the grid
as implemented in the
class JeuMorpion,
and that the first 3 positions
represent the first line of the grid
and following his conventions, he
will place an O in the right place by
putting the value 1 in the
first position of the array.
So the idea is we access
the grid,
and we assign the value 1
to the first position.
By using these functionalities
and accessing the grid,
indirectly through a method,
the user can perfectly achieve
a playable game of
tic-tac-toe.
But it is his job to enforce the
game's rules,
take turns with another
player,
and to place the tokens
at the right locations.
So if he is careful enough,
he will be able to
play a real game of tic-tac-toe.
However, if we examine
this setup more carefully,
we will see that this approach
is fundamentally flawed.
For example the user
of this class JeuMorpion
cannot use it at all without
knowing the class's internal
implementation details.
He has to know under
what form and with what conventions
the representation of the grid is stored,
for in this case a 1D integer array with
each 3 positions representing
a line.
He will also have to adopt some
arbitrary conventions of his own
such as that  "1" represents an "O",
and "2" an "X".
The user has to know
meticulous implementation details.
Furthermore, the resulting code
of the class "JeuMorpion" is
completely opaque.
This line is incomprehensible
like this
to anyone who reads it.
What does an "0" mean?
What does a "1" mean?
This line can only be
understood by looking
inside the class "JeuMorpion".
And what will happen
if the class programmer
decides to change his
implementation choices?
If he uses a 2-dimensional
array
instead of a 1-dimensional array
(which was granted not
very intuitive),
this line of code would have
to be rewritten like this.
So the class user
would also have to modify his code
to concord with that of the class JeuMorpion
and if he had written
many similar lines,
well then he would have to
revise all of them.
Lastly, a very important and serious
point: the class programmer
provides an access to the
reference of the grid.
Which means that by using
this functionality,
it is possible for the user
to access the reference of grille
which allows him
to access the array itself and
modify its contents however he wishes.
So even if the class programmer
took the precaution to
declare the data member
grille private,
which prevents this type of manipulation,
the exact same thing can be done,
in a more indirect manner,
through the method getGrille
that he chose to provide.
So accessing grille through
the method getGrille
comes to the same thing as
leaving grille public.
More generally, when
a data member is an object,
like grille in this case,
providing an access to the
object's reference via a getter
just as in this case,
comes to exactly the same thing as giving
direct, public access to the data member,
because the object can be
manipulated through the given reference
This unanticipated access
given through the reference
to the grid can result in all
kinds of disasterous consequences.
For example, the user can
inadvertently enter the wrong
index for the grid and do this
kind of thing.
At this point, the program
would stop abruptly
and send back an error message
relatively hard to decrypt.
This access can through the reference
also allows the user
to enter all sorts of ficticious values
in the grid.
Such as instead of putting a 1,
he puts 42 or another value,
which he can do because
the value is verified intermediately.
So imagine that the user
also programs
a method getJoueurGagnant
that goes through the grid
to determine if there  is a winner
with 3 pieces in a row.
This method getJoueurGagnant
expects the values 0, 1, and 2 in the grid,
and if it finds a value 42,
it will not know what to do
and will behave incorrectly.
Last of all, if the user
desires to cheat,
and replace an O with an X,
(a move that is normally forbidden,
because once a token is placed,
it cannot be replaced),
here, again, with the access
to grille via the reference,
nothing stops him from doing
this dishonest move.
So all this shows that
the methods provided by the programmer,
namely getGrille,
allow an uncontrollable access
to the implementation details.
All these manipulations can be
done without any of them
being validated, which manifests
the bad class design.
To properly encapsulate
the class JeuMorpion,
it is imperative that the class's
implementation choices are not
revealed in the user interface
provided for the user.
Furthermore, internal
implementation choices
such as
how to represent the grid,
or how to modelize
tokens on the grid,
are the responsibility of the
class designer and programmer,
and not the user.
We will now move on to
the 2nd version that is
a bit more refined than
the last version.
So to properly program this class,
several decisions need to
be made in implementing the grid.
Here we choose to implement it
a bit more explicitly
than in the last version
with a 2-dimensional array
which is closer
to the real tic-tac-toe
grid.
We have to decide how
to encode the data
to place the pieces
on the grid,
and here it is best to always
clarify the choices we make.
For example, this can be
done by introducing
a certain number of constants
with explicit names, so that
the meaning of the different
numbers in the array is clear.
Next, instead of, as in the
last version,
relying on the default values
of the array
to initialize the grid,
here, we make the initialization
as clear-cut as possible,
like this.
So in reading this code,
it is obvious that we
are filling the tic-tac-toe grid
with empty boxes.
(TN: "vide" means "empty")
Next, the idea is to
provide the users of this class
with only 2 well-chosen methods
that allow the player to
interact with the grid, without
however, knowing how
it is implemented.
For example, we can provide "placerRond" (= place an "O")
and specify that the user has
give the line and column
which is intuitive.
Then internally we implement
how to place an O at a given
line and column on the grid.
In the same way, we can
provide the public  method
placerCroix (= place an "X") that allows  the
user to place a cross
simply by specifying
the proper line and column.
Placing a piece on a
certain line and column is done
with the exact same process
whether the token is an X or an O,
so it is intuitive to
modularize the procedure
by having a method placerCoup (= place a token)
whose job it is to place the piece
on a certain line and column.
The methods placerRond
and placerCroix are sufficient
to place the tokens on the grid.
Consequently, it
is unnecessary to
provide an access to placerCoup
like getGrille in the first version.
Placing tokens can
be done with
these 2 methods alone,
which constitute the interface.
This means that the method
placerCoup can be declared
private because
it simply helps the other methods
in their tasks
and is not a functionality
itself that is
provided to the user.
Because it is the class user who
will give the line and column
where he wants to place his
token,
it is necessary, in order for the class
to be robust in the case of an error
to anticipate invalid moves that
do not correspond to
a position on the grid.
So typically, if the line's index
is negative
or greater than or equal to
the grid's size,
than a message should
be sent back.
So anticipating and managing these
errors makes the code more robust.
Once the line and column
provided by the user
are validated,
we still have to verify
that the line and column
is really empty.
Indeed, in tic-tac-toe,
you are not allowed to
place a token on a box
that is already occupied.
If this is the case, then this
error also needs to be signaled.
placerCoup returns a boolean
to indicate whether or not
a move was placed on the
requested square.
The methods placerRond
and placerCroix will use this boolean
returned by placerCoup and
to return it
to the user to indicate
if the token was placed
or not.
Let's see the repercussions
of these modifications
for the user.
As before,
a programmer uses
the class JeuMorpion
is to declare a variable of
this type and initialize
it with the method provided
but most importantly to place
a token. And to do this
he will be able to very
explicitly use functionalities
like placerRond which
require no knowledge
on his part of how the
data is encoded internally.
So if I want to place an O,
I indicate that I place an O
on the grid on the line 0
and column 0
and I will be notified
if the O was successfully
placed or not.
Placing an X on the grid
would proceed in the same manner.
This 2nd version of JeuMorpion
is much more robust and explicit
but still requires that
a certain number of
conventions be used.
For example here, we impose
that the user of this method
respects a certain enumeration
system
for the lines and columns.
We could have of course
chosen a different system than this one.
So these conventions have to
explicitly be documented
in the user interface.
Nevertheless, this 2nd
version of the class
has many advantages compared
to the 1st version.
Firstly, it verifies
the data.
For instance, it is impossible
in this version
to put an invalid number
in the array.
And how is this?
Well, because the user
of JeuMorpion
doesn't even know that
an empty slot is encoded with a 0,
and that 1 and 2 represent
Os and Xs.
So he simply uses the methods
placerRond or placerCroix
and it's the internal implementation
details that
take care of assigning the
right values.
Secondly, it is impossible
for the external user
to place a piece on an
occupied square of the grid.
We saw in the definition
of placerCoup that this method
verified that the square was indeed
empty before placing a new token.
Another important advantage,
which is key to a well-designed
object-oriented program,
is what is called
separation of concerns:
the user of the class JeuMorpions
does not need to know how
the grid is internally represented
and implemented or how
a token is placed on the grid.
He only needs to concern himself
with the game's logic,
and how he will place
Os and Xs.
Yet another advantage is that this
code is comprehensible, even
to someone without
a programming background.
If, I write "jeu.placerRond(0,0)"
I don't need much explanation
to know what this expression
means.
This wasn't the case in the
last version where placing a piece
necessitated very cryptic
expressions
like this.
Compare the two.
Do you see that this first expression
is much more clear and explicit?
And a last advantage is that
all errors are
accounted for, and in these situations
a comprehensible message
will be returned.
In the first version, when
for example, we tried
to place a token outside of the
grid, the execution of the program
was interrupted abruptly,
and a incomprehensible message
was sent back.
So now it is possible with the
error message for the user
to know what exactly
he did wrong.
This closes our case study
of a game of tic-tac-toe.
This example demonstrated
the importance of encapsulation,
how it is necessary to hide
the implementation details,
and to only provide methods absolutely
indespensable to the user
which do not give any
openings for the user
to modify or change
the implementation details.