The aim of this module is to go a little deeper
into the strategy operationalisation.
Last week focused on how
entrepreneurial discovery can be organised
in terms of
priorities or strategic areas.
This module will now focus on the second stage
of entrepreneurial discovery which lies within
each
priority area.
As we have already said,
the entrepreneurial discovery does not stop
when priorities
are established, but it concerns the exploration
of every area
on the basis of coordinated research and innovation
investments as well as
the development of specific infrastructures
in order to
facilitate this coordination.
All of this without
losing sight of the ultimate aim that from
each priority area
a transformative activity is constituted which
will take off
and reach a certain critical mass to lead
to
a structural change.
What are the precise objectives
of this second stage of entrepreneurial discovery?
In each priority area it is a case of learning
about
the effective potentials and opportunities
with the aim
to develop a new transformative activity.
It is also about improving coordination amongst
resources and involved parties with the aim
to produce
the first effects of critical mass agglomeration,
of synergy.
It is also about building the additional capabilities
and fill a few gaps, overcoming a few weaknesses
in the knowledge base,
in the service infrastructure, or in the coordination
tools.
Finally the connection between the considered
priority area
and the extra-regional resources and skills
must be ensured
by supporting new links and partnerships with
other regions.
As we have already seen an important condition
for these
coordination and agglomeration efforts to
be productive
is that the chosen priority areas are not
too large.
In an overly large area,
the projects and other initiatives will inevitably
be
scattered, with little hope of synergy and
agglomeration.
In a more narrow area, for example the area
of
flexible technology in the shoe industry,
which we have
seen in the Northern Portugal case, we can
expect a better return of the strategy in
terms of
the scale of agglomeration and spill overs,
which is a very important goal.
Let's continue with an example: the Basque
Country.
This example will be explored further in the
fifth week,
as this region will be the object of an entire
case study.
In the smart specialisation strategy of the
Basque
Country, there are seven priority areas which
have been
selected, including advanced production
and industry 4.0 technologies.
Here we are not interested in the reasons
for choosing
these priority areas, but in what happens
once the
choice has been made.
The first thing to remember is on an organisational
level, the creation of a steering committee
which includes public and private actors.
With this committee, a space for decision
and initiative is
created to identify key problems to be resolved,
to choose relevant plans.
We will then examine this in the case of the
Basque
Country and this priority strategy.
We will also identify current projects, relevant
entrepreneurial activities for the considered
strategic area.
This committee should also instill a dynamic,
an effervescence so that all of those involved
in the area
come together and propose initiatives.
In order for the effects of synergy and agglomeration
to be generated and a truly new activity to
take off,
to form a certain critical mass.
Here is a list of the identified projects.
This list is quite heterogeneous.
It includes projects of research, platform
and
infrastructure development, training and education
initiatives, liaison projects with other priorities
of the energetic-environmental strategy, as
well as
initiatives looking towards the international
market.
If we do a little bit of sorting, we can identify
the
following mechanisms which can be implemented
in
any smart specialisation strategy.
Firstly, any action or initiative needs leaders.
These potential leaders must be discovered
and supported
so that they take control of these different
initiatives.
It can be a case of, as in the Basque Country,
a
university who leads training initiatives,
professional association, or the management
structure of a
cluster, or even a specific company, or a
motivated entrepreneur.
The second mechanism, the call for projects
for
the development or the demonstration of such
and such
critical technological feature, is a well-known
mechanism.
Mobilising public financing, criteria for
this
have already been looked at in the second
week.
This public financing is particularly necessary
when
it involves undertaking a collective action
which involves
several different parties with the aim to
integrate
and combine separate knowledge.
We cannot lose sight of the fact
that we are in an entrepreneurial discovery
logic, the second stage, therefore that
the companies which are helped must accept
the diffusion of
information relating to these projects.
The third mechanism is the development of
research and
innovation infrastructures to facilitate the
provision
of necessary complementary capabilities for
innovation,
as well as coordination between projects.
We have already highlighted that a rich innovation
ecosystem
should provide these capabilities that the
majority
of businesses cannot produce internally, specialised
services,
basic research, test systems, etc.
The fashionable term here is "platform".
We can think of platforms centered on a general
objective
technology, such as information
technologies, which can
serve several priority areas.
We can also think of platforms to produce
synergies between different priorities, rearranging
platforms.
This is the case in the Basque Country in
terms of advanced
energy production and advanced environment
production areas.
The article by Finnish colleagues from the
Universities
of Aalto and Lahti which is referenced in
this module shows
that in Finland there is a tool systematically
deployed
within the smart specialisation
strategies in the majority of Finnish regions.
These coordination initiatives go beyond the
region
to facilitate the links between regional projects
and some external resources.
This is the case in the Basque Country with
multiple
international partnerships who have found
a new
purpose within the smart specialisation strategy.
The fourth mechanism is a fundamental action
which
concerns the development of new skills and
the necessary
specialised knowledge for the growth of the
selected area.
These actions concern training and education.
This is the case in the Basque Country.
Neglecting these specific investments is an
error
that we mentioned during the last module in
the second week.
Of course, part of the solution to this adjustment
problem
in terms of human capital comes from the exterior,
the call for engineers, for scientists from
outside the region.
But when a priority strategic area has been
identified,
the specialised human capital that corresponds
to this area
becomes a really fundamental asset for the
region.
It therefore makes sense that the region gets
involved
in activities in favour of its endogenous
development.
Let's move on to the fifth mechanism: it is
definitely
also important to mobilise the cluster(s)
which are concerned in each priority area
in order for it to
lead coherent actions relating to the smart
specialisation strategy, so that their objectives
are
aligned with these priorities.
A cluster can be a useful tool in the service
of a
strategy's objectives, but it has to be mobilised.
We could say the same thing for regional localisation
or
attraction policies which should be harmonised,
in line with the smart specialisation strategy.
Finally, the universities in each region can
represent
a formidable tool in the service of the smart
specialisation strategy, in terms of research
of course, but also of coordination, infrastructure,
and also obviously training.
Therefore it is necessary that universities
get involved
in priority areas and become main parties
within
each of these areas.
Here is the list of mechanisms to use in
order to put initiatives and actions in place
that can be
financed within a priority area in
the smart specialisation strategy.
That is how we go from, as in the Basque Country
case,
identifying a priority area to the more concrete
stage of entrepreneurial discovery
with a large number of projects, activities,
infrastructures development.
In the end, we aim for the development of
new
activities characterized by a certain critical
mass and
effects of agglomeration and spill overs.
We have just tackled the operationalisation
of a
critical stage in the process of entrepreneurial
discovery.
The stage that allows us to learn specifically
about
the opportunities and the potentialities
within a specific strategic area.
The example of the advanced
production technologies area in the Basque
Country's
strategy is interesting.
But it is only one example.
The list of mechanisms that we have commented
on is only one list.
Every priority strategic area is different,
and we must therefore
think about mechanisms adapted to these specificities.
Depending on the existing structures: are
there
clusters?
Are there big companies?
A technological
university?
Depending on the potential
leaders, the entrepreneurial dynamism already
present,
potential gaps and weaknesses, we must
focus on one mechanism rather than another.
What will be pertinent in one area will not
necessarily
be in another.
It is simply important not
to lose sight of the ultimate aim, which is
to
really progress within each area towards the
creation and growth of a new transformative
activity.
Thank you.