Welcome everybody.
Let's have a look at
monitoring and evaluation.
Although it is not really
part of a strategy design
process and often happens
only after the strategy has to
be defined it is a crucial
element for a successful strategy.
But often it's not really
taken seriously and that might
be due for two reasons.
The first I already
mentioned because it only starts
after the strategy is
defined, in some cases even after
the program has been finished,
but that, of course, is an error.
You should have evaluation
and monitoring right from the
beginning of the
definition of strategy.
I'll come back to that in a minute.
Secondly, it is a very
challenging task and sometimes, it
seems to be too
challenging to really follow it up.
But as Roderic puts it very
nicely, it is not because the
application of the most
rigid and academically recognised
methods is not possible
that all attempts of assessment
should be abandoned.
Clearly here it's stated
that we should assess even if we
do it not optimally.
One of the big challenges
the identification of the
effects of a program or put
in other words, the causality
of these effects, and again
Roderick gives a hint to us
how we can solve at
least partly this problem.
We must at least establish
ex ante clear benchmark and criteria
for success and for failure
at the various levels of the
strategy.
The definition of what is a
success and what is a failure
might help afterwards to
identify, not the causality
itself but the effect of the program.
Let's have a quick view on
a couple of fundamentals on
monitoring and evaluation.
What is the purpose of evaluation?
Actually we talked in
the last video a lot about
flexibility, and during the
complete online course, we
talk a lot about entrepreneurial
discovery and the entrepreneurial process.
But without information
both the flexibility and
entrepreneurial process won't work.
The monitoring and
evaluation is the source of the
information which we need to
really make these processes work.
A second fundamental issue
is that it is part of building
this strategy or
designing the strategy to keep
monitoring and evaluation in mind.
That's what also
Roderick already told us.
You have to define
clearly the objectives of your
strategy: what do
you want to achieve?
What are the goals?
They must be explicitly clear.
And also already
through the strategy designing
process you should define
the metrics, how you will
measure success or
failure in your objectives.
That helps you to define
more clearly your strategy when
you have to think
about what the metrics are.
So you have to define the
objective of the program.
You have to define the
metrics how to measure the success
or failure of these
objectives, and last not least you
have to define the data
generation process: where do you
get the data from for the
metrics so that you have the
necessary data at the
end available when you do
evaluation and monitoring?
Evaluation and
monitoring have to be
flexible, that's the third
fundamental issue. The
strategy itself is a very
flexible tool, it can have
a lot of different ways how
the strategy might work,
you a lot of different areas
where it may apply to and
therefore also the evaluation
has to follow up that differences.
It's not a one size fits
all once more, but you have to
adapt the evaluation
process to your strategy.
There is a question often
raised if the evaluation is to
be quantitative or only qualitative.
But actually it's qualitative and
quantitative which you should follow.
Some things can only be
defined qualitatively or measured
or observed qualitatively,
but you also need quantitative
measures wherever possible
because it provides more information.
We already defined four
steps of monitoring or
evaluation when we
defined the process to build a
strategy, so that it's clear
right from the beginning on
which points you have to
take measurements and controls.
Let's go through these four
in a bit more detail and look
for examples for each of them.
The first stage in the
monitoring process is what we call
the Strategic profile of
the region evaluation, here we
control particularly if the
priority areas chosen are the right ones.
Of course they are the
result from an extended analysis
of the base of evidence and
entrepreneurial resources but
still there might
be changes necessary.
It might be necessary that
changes are due to a changing
world, that's always
changing and it might be you need
new other priority areas.
It might also be due to
the results of the monitoring
evaluation of the other
stages which should then feed
back into the priority areas
and at some point might tell
that one or another priority
area should not be followed anymore.
There's also a nice
little test to the priority
areas which we like
to apply in this stage.
We call it the x test and
the ones of you who speak
German would know it from
the saying of x beliebig why we
call it the x test.
It takes your strategy,
your priority areas and the
reasoning behind them and
then replaces the name of your
region with another region.
And if you do that and the
strategy still sounds sensible
then it's probably not
define a precise enough for your
region but follows too
much the general trends.
In that part, this kind of
evaluation, of course, starts
immediately after defining
the priority areas but is a
continuous process.
The strategy actually is
never finished it's a rolling
process or rolling a
strategy and priority areas might
change at any point in time.
This notion of the rolling
strategy shows that this is
not really an evaluation or
an ex post evaluation but is a kind
of a rethinking of the
strategy and choices you did.
Therefore also the notion of
causality problems which we
discussed above is no issue
here, there is no causality
in that case but we just
evaluate if we had the right
process to come to the
same results of the strategic
process, not of the outcome
of strategy implementation.
The results of the strategy
implementation, a part of the
second stage of the
evaluation and monitoring process,
here we look at the classical
projects and activities evaluation.
This is something which is
very usual and there is a big
literature, we don't need
to discuss that a lot, there
are typically questions
asked like finances and
accounting all right in the
programs, what kind of
activities are there,
monitored activities achieved
through the programs,
like for example meetings or
contacts made,
webpages or information, tools
produced, things like that,
and also the output of the
program, so counting how
much contacts you reached, how
many meetings were held, how
many people you reached, or
with patents or
publications, they can give you
information on the outcomes.
But, of course, this is not
the objective of the smart
specialisation strategy,
it's not meetings or webpages
or contacts which you
should count, we have other
objectives, but they
provide you good information on if
the projects and
activities work right.
The method here is often
self-reporting either by the
management of the program
or by the participants of the
programs themselves, and the
measurements can be defined
fairly easily because
this information is readily
available, and causality is
not a big issue because there's
a direct link to
between program and outcome so
causality is rather clear here.
But that's not the end, also
many evaluations of programs
and of strategies stop
at that point, this is not
specialisation strategy,
we have more to monitor.
The third stage of the
monitoring process is
what we call the
critical mass evaluation.
As we recall by now very
well I'm sure, is that critical
mass is an aim of the smart
specialisation strategy, to
achieve structured change in
the economy in the end, and
we should try to measure
these steps to our overall
objective, the
critical mass generation.
Evaluating the critical mass
is much more difficult than
evaluation for
example of the project side.
While in a project, we have
a relatively clear linkage of
causality between outcome
and project imputs, it's much
weaker on the critical mass side.
But if you think about
critical mass as building up
capacity, we can also
find indicators which help us
measure that. Although the
causal link might be weaker,
we still see if the capacity
changes in the region or not.
Now how can we measure capacity?
That is not really
straightforward and it is not a
well-established way to
measure it, but there are a
couple of ideas
around how to do that.
But again depending on
your strategy and the focus of
your strategy, there might
be different ways you measure
the capacity change in your
region to be achieved by the
strategy but maybe the
examples I have gives you an idea
how that could be done.
One way of capacity is
building networks, the closer you've
worked together that is
well established higher your
output is particularly in
a knowledge economy or a
knowledge generation
process. You have actually
increasing economies of scale here.
And there are a couple of tools to
measure network and network development.
One example is you take
social platforms, business
platforms like LinkedIn
or Xing in Germany or other
platforms available around
the world and measure how many
people are taking part of
that program in particular, maybe
of the profession or in the
jobs which are interesting
for you as much smart specialisation
strategy is this increasing
how active are they on the
platforms and measurements
like that, that could
give you an indication if the
network capacity increases.
The generation of knowledge,
the reliability of knowledge
in the region is also a
fundamental issue of capacities.
And again we look here at
indicators or we can look here
at indicators depending on
your precise strategy which
are already well-known.
Patents can be such an
indicator, papers in
publications can be another one but
trademarks, new products
can be further indicators.
All the start-up companies
are a kind of a knowledge
generation and can be
counted in here as well.
A further issue increasing
the capacity in the region
might be through building
trust and then in the next step
forming cooperations.
And cooperations can be
quite well measured, there are
many different ways
to really look at them.
Again it could be
patents for example, co-patents
between two companies or
co-patents between an academic
institution and the
company might be measurement for
cooperations or
increased corporation.
Or you might look at the
subsidised project which is
often by definition involves
more than one player and if
they increase in size or in number.
And there are many other possibilities
(all of the above discussed ones)
for examples of the social networks
can also show up of cooperations.
You can also follow people
who do social networks when
they work for different
cooperations that could be
another issue increasing
the capacity in the region.
Now as these examples
already show, this is not the
measurement of the capacity
building or the measurement
of the critical in mass, this
is not a single number away
you can put everything in.
You need to understand
the system and then we
find the measures
which reflect that system.
Therefore it is not only an
evaluation ex ante but the
information you gather here
are also an important steering
instrument for the
implementation of your strategy and
actually even to go back to
the strategy itself that was
the first part of the
evaluation process there, strategic
profile of the region.
To do so, of course, you
need indicators which are timely
available, not with a long
delay only but the ones we
discussed in the last few
minutes are usually quite
quickly available and
so you can use them for
monitoring and evaluation just as
well as for steering your strategy.
With the fourth stage of
the monitoring process we are
actually getting close to
the core objective of this
smart specialisation strategy.
We want to achieve
structural change in the economy, we
want to improve the
development of the economy.
Now the objectives here are
rather clear and they clearly
relate to measurement as well.
For example, you want to
generate jobs or maybe not just
jobs but usually sustainable
jobs, jobs with a future and
well-paid jobs. At all
this can be measured easily.
Our objective is to
rise a new industry or to
re rise an old one.
Again this can be easily measured.
You might also aim the
shifting focus of an industry for
more domestic to an
international export
player or from a lower
part, technology part of the
industry to the high-tech part.
Again measurement is
straightforward here.
Ultimately we want to
increase the competitiveness,
the international
competitiveness of the industries in
the regions of the program and
again here are measurements available.
We discussed all these
kinds of measures when we
discussed the base of
evidence analysis and the same
information can be used again here.
But there is, of course, a
big but to it otherwise it
would be too easy, the
causality between the program
and the objectives or the
measurements are very weak if
there are hardly at all, it
can't prove the causality.
Still we should monitor and
evaluate that probably best
done in a benchmarking
setting that we at least allow for
common trends to be filtered
and for overall cyclical
effects to be filtered and
not put through the project
that allows us to
elevate the overall structural
change.
Now we went through the
four stages of the measurement
process individually and we
saw also they differ a lot
for each stage it is
possible to find the right
measurement and to do
monitoring and evaluation.
Of course in some cases we
need to be creative to find
the right measurements
and the measurement has been
adapted to the individual
strategy but it is possible to
monitor and evaluate all of this.
But there's a note of
cautionary necessary.
We get what we measure.
When we define a measurement
we give incentive to program
implementers to program managers and
to people participating in the program.
If they are evaluated for
their success or failure that
will be done by the
measurement not by the objectives.
And therefore they tend to
maximise the measurements and
at least possibly
ignore the objectives.
That means you need to
define the measurement very
carefully so that
measurement and objectives are showed
going in the same
direction and we have to define the
measurement completely,
meaning that all objective are
part of the measurement.
For example, if the
focus the measurement on only
projects and activities
evaluation like output of a
program or activity in
the program or the correct
accounting then the
program managers or the strategy
managers will focus on
that as well and not look that
much at the long-term
objective of the program which is
actually what is the
objective of smart specialisation is
not successful programs but
it's critical mass and then
structural change. And it
might be missed by defining too
much evaluation in the short term
and not enough in the long term.
That has to be carefully
defined but also completely
defined the measurement.
It's very important to take the
four steps of the
evaluation process seriously and not
stop after the
second or the third one.
Summing up on the
monitoring and evaluation process, we
looked at the four stages of
the process individually and
discussed them. Also they
differ from each other quite a
bit, in the methods, in the
metrics and in their causality
towards the program still
all of them are essential for
the smart specialisation strategy.
One thing we haven't
discussed yet is the timing between
them because that also
varies between the different
stages of the monitoring.
The first step to a strategic
profile actually takes
place already throughout the
definition of the strategy
and then continues through the
whole period the
strategy is evaluated.
So it's probably
appropriate to say after one year you
have the first answer first
evaluation result on the strategic profile.
For the project stage of
the evaluation it takes some
more time, project has to
be defined, implemented and
started before you
can start evaluating.
So after two to three years
you probably have first result.
But, of course, it doesn't
mean that you have to wait two
to three years to start to
monitoring and evaluation process.
Quite the opposite you
should plan right from the
beginning and start right
away with the strategy to
collect the necessary data.
But the first results, the
first judgement can probably
made of two or three years.
Even more time it takes
naturally to evaluate to new
activities and the
generation of critical mass or how we
put it the capacity
building in the region.
As many different
programs and activities a project
should contribute to that
it's probably fair to say after
three to five years you
might be able to see first
results not much earlier.
And then the overall
objective, the structural change
even takes more time five
to eight years, is probably
appropriate here to really
have first judgement on the
overall success of the strategy.
Now monitoring and
evaluation is crucial and also it only
takes place later on and
you only get on those, much
later after starting the
strategy you should think right
from the beginning and
you define your strategy.
For one reason that the
measurements fit the objectives
of the strategy perfectly
for the other reasons that you
gather the necessary data
to really do the evaluations
and define the data generation
process right from the beginning.
Therefore evaluation and
monitoring is one topic when
defining a strategy
also it's done on later.
Thank you very much
and see you again.