A smart specialization strategy
is underpinned by a principle of experimentation.
And this experimental nature that we will
promptly address
has two strong implications in terms of operationalization:
flexibility
and evaluation and monitoring.
That's what we'll talk about now.
On what consists the decisions made
in the case of a smart specialization strategy?
Decisions on priority areas
and then decisions in each area.
Basically, these are bets.
These are adventures.
After an entrepreneurial discovery process
robust and transparent,
the decisions made always involve an element
of risk.
There is still a belief dimension
and even a certain amount of faith
when choices are made,
both in terms of priority areas and in terms
of project
within each field.
We can appreciate here the difference with
a horizontal policy
where the choices are not so risky.
The bets are not so risky.
A R&D tax credit is not a very risky decision.
We are pretty sure it will result in additional
R & D expenses
by companies.
In the case of a smart specialization strategy,
we undertake experiments and as all experiments
some can fail.
The development of a smart specialization
strategy,
is therefore a fragile construction.
And that's good.
If the choices were not risky,
that is to say that private investment profitability
was certain,
any policy would be superfluous.
So the risk of failure should not be eliminated
but the costs of possible failures should
be reduced.
And this determines
two principles, two imperatives:
the flexibility already mentioned
and the monitoring and evaluation.
Let's therefore look at
the operationalisation of the principle of
flexibility.
We have already spoken several times about
it,
especially as part of good design of a policy.
This principle enables to preserve the dynamism
of the strategy,
an ability to adjust and adapt to opportunities,
which can occur any time.
It also enables to reduce risks of distortion
often associated with policies that lead to
unlimited duration of
preferential interventions
in such and such technology area,
in favour of such and such project.
This flexibility goes both ways.
It first concerns the fact that preferential
support can
or has to stop at some point.
And there are three reasons for this.
What establishes public support
is the new nature of the activity.
It is the fact that it is "new" that creates
risks, uncertainties,
coordination difficulties.
So, whether the activity is a success or a
failure,
it doesn't matter from the flexibility point
of view.
What matters is that after four or five years,
it is no longer new
and should therefore no longer be eligible
for special
and non-neutral support.
Leaving the strategy after a certain period
does not mean that it is a failure,
just that business is now mature.
This does not mean that the activity is interrupted.
Participants in this activity will still fund
their R&D
with horizontal instruments.
Rodrik speaks of a “sunset clause for withdrawing
support”
after a certain period of time.
Second reason
the world changes and what appeared to be
an essential priority
can seem less relevant
several years later.
Finally,
third reason after a few years,
the results just are not up to standard. The
project has failed
and perhaps by extension,
the priority area itself seems less promising
than expected.
In the other direction, the flexibility concerns
the ability of the strategy
to continuously stimulate entrepreneurial
discoveries
and to be ready at every moment to assess
them,
select some of them and welcome them into
the strategy.
This ability to generate new options
obviously concerns the project level
within each domain but also the priority level
itself.
Here is the general principle of flexibility
which expresses the fact
that the smart specialization strategy is
a living document.
It would be quite irrational and absurd to
engrave it in marble
the first decisions and never to return to
them,
as if nothing could happen later.
The idea of ​​smart specialization strategy
is to hold this never-ending to-and-fro
between new activities which enter the strategy
and mature activities which come out.
From there,
the problem of operationalization arises
and the questions are very specific.
The dilemma of flexibility opposes the principles
we have just explained,
including the fact that an activity after
some time
is not new anymore,
to the entirely reasonable principle that
we need time
to form this new activity
and give it its development.
However,
this dilemma is probably not that bad,
if we understand the fact that stopping
a preferential intervention,
which has already been provided for five or
six years,
does not mean that the activity will stop.
This simply means
that other financing arrangements will be
better
adapted to the new phase of innovation.
The key point here is the complementarity
between smart specialization strategy
and horizontal instruments
which must take over
when activities mature.
But this principle of flexibility
will also give a central role
to evaluation and monitoring.
We'll come to it.
Just before
a note to the attention of European regions
who can find it difficult to conciliate
this flexibility and the apparent rigidity
of the operational program they have submitted
to the European Commission.
The regions are indeed linked
by what they have decided initially and by
the operational program
which determines
the outlines of what will be funded.
In this regard, potential areas of specialization
represent the essential constraint.
Can we change a strategy during the operational
program?
To address these somewhat technical problems
and that only interest the regions
of the European Union.
I refer you to a document annexed to this
module.
Deciding to stop a domain,
some projects,
deciding to continue,
deciding to start and open a new field;
all this must be based on rigorous and continuous
evaluation mechanisms.
We will talk about it in the next video.