So what I have tried to do so far,
Is to look at debates on the state.
Secondly, I've looked at key aspects
of the smart state.
And now finally I want to
turn my attention
to some good examples of regions
which are trying to do
innovative things
through smart state policies.
I've been working for many years
with regional governments
and regional development agents
throughout the European Union,
and I've identified a number of
good practices over the years.
For twenty years, I've been working
in the Basque country,
which has been one of the pioneers
of regional innovation policy
in the European Union.
And it's developed, in my view,
one of the best Smart Specialization
Strategies in the European Union.
And these good practice
examples include
the policy continuity which has been
established in the Basque country.
For over thirty years, the
Basque government
has committed to spending on
research, design, and development.
And that has created an
R&D infrastructure
which allows firms to
engage with that infrastructure,
and to use it as a platform
for their own R&D investments.
A second example from the Basque
country would be policy novelty.
Not only have they had
policy continuity,
but they've introduced new
aspects to their policy mix.
For example, like
cluster associations.
Now they're introducing
entrepreneurial discovery processes.
And in these entrepreneurial
discovery processes and spaces,
businesses and technology centers,
and regional government
work hand in glove. And the key
aspect of the Basque strategy
that I think merits attention is the
idea of distributed leadership.
That is to say, at the
beginning of the strategy,
the Basque government
will play  a strong, forceful role
by establishing the
rules of the game.
Once it's established that,
the rules of the game,
it will step back and allow businesses,
universities, and research centers
to come forward and take the lead.
That's a very important example of
a Smart Specialization Strategy
which is a regional strategy rather
than a governmental strategy
my second example comes from
South Moravia in the Czech Republic.
When I've worked in South Moravia,
I've worked with a JIC, which is
the regional innovation agency.
And when I've asked them
to sum up, to distill,
the lessons of their success,
this is what they've said to me:
they've emphasized, first of all,
the role of strong, stable
political commitments
to regional innovation policy,
just as we saw in the case
of the Basque country.
Stable political commitment,
they say, is a must.
Secondly, keeping a
strategic focus on results.
Knowing what we want to do first,
because the money comes second,
they emphasize.
Whereas many regions,
the first priority is
securing the money,
sometimes when they don't have ideas
what to do with the money.
Thirdly, the need to get the
best people on board
in these new innovation networks,
because without the
best people on board,
you don't get the
trust in the process.
And trust, as we know,
is a unique asset
in development, because
trust has  value but no price.
You can't buy trust.
You can only earn it,
by discharging your
obligations to your partners.
What the Americans call,
"Walking the talk".
Another example of
their success, they say,
is being constantly in the field,
being exposed to
new actors, to new ideas.
And feeding back, that word again,
feedback.
Honest, rapid, real-time feedback,
to keep the policy fresh. And new.
And relevant.
Another example from them,
from South Moravia, would be,
the need for robust
government structures
to protect the space around
new policy initiatives.
To give it the oxygen it
needs to develop.
And then finally, being close
to state of the art research.
The South Moravians have
always been close to these projects.
Projects called,
"Creative Regional Advantage"
the Smart Specialization
platform in Seville.
And our own project, "Smart Spec",
a project led by Cardiff University,
and funded by the
FP7 European program.
All these things are
examples of good practice
from South Moravia.
And in my view,
they all constitute key aspects
of the Smart State.
My final example comes
from my own country, Wales,
where there's been a major change
in regional innovation
policy over the years.
We used to have a
top-down and state-led
regional innovation policy,
which led to some big disasters.
Like our Technium network,
for example,
which we described looking back as a
"cathedral in the desert"
because it created large technology
centers which were underutilized.
Learning from that example,
the Welsh government now
tries to build an ecosystem
of innovation, in which firms,
government, and universities
work closely together.
That's sometimes
referred to as the triple helix
in regional innovation
policy studies.
And two examples from Wales:
First of all, from my own university,
Cardiff University,
where we're trying to build
a new innovation campus,
where the accent is on
translational research,
research which is close to market.
And there, we are working with IQE,
a world leader in compound
semiconductor technology,
which makes the smart,
energy efficient chips
which go into all of our
smartphones, for example.
Working with partners like IQE
gives us what we'd never had before:
which is to say,
a demand-side partner
that could help us to valorize, or
commercialize, our knowledge.
A second example from Wales would be
Swansea University's work
in the Specific Project,
which is about
creating a renewable energy
ecosystem
where, once again, firms are
working closely with a university,
particularly with its
Materials Science center,
a world-class center
of Materials Science.
Both in Cardiff and in Swansea,
we see that these partnerships both
aim to integrate demand and supply,
And they are the keys to
the valorization of knowledge,
which help us to
overcome the problems
of the university science silo,
which I identified earlier on.
These three examples from the Basque
country, South Moravia, Wales,
are just three examples
of where the regional state
is trying to act in new ways.
To try to act as an animateur
and a curator of innovation.
And these are examples
of the regional state
playing a more catalytic role in
the smart specialization process,
by building organizational
capacity in the public sector,
by using its convening power to
broker new networks in the region,
and by using its curating capacity
to foster translocal networks
and value chains,
like the Vanguard initiative
in the European Union,
which is an attempt for regions and
firms to work across different regions
to develop new technologies in
advanced manufacturing, for example,
in 3D printing. It's a good
example of regions coming together,
to work across borders.
To sum up, smart state bodies are valued
for their competence in the network,
not for their status in the hierarchy,
as used to be the case in the past.
And now these smart state bodies are
learning to deploy their soft powers.
Powers like their curating capacity,
like their convening power.
To deploy these soft powers
in concert with hard powers,
like tax, regulation,
and procurement,
and these are the secret
ingredients, I think,
of the smart state in action.
So what I've tried to
do in this session,
I've tried to do three things:
I've tried to look at new debates
on the role of the state,
in economic development
and innovation.
Secondly, I've tried to look at
key aspects of the smart state.
And thirdly, I've tried to
look at good practice examples
from regions around
the European Union,
particularly the Basque country,
South Moravia, and Wales.
And in this final slide,
I simply want to sum up
by emphasizing three key points.
Firstly, smart states can
make a big difference
to innovation and development,
if they have the
institutional capacity
and the political
leadership to do so.
I believe this is a point that's
been recognized throughout
the history of political economy,
from the days of Adam Smith's
"Wealth of Nations" onwards:
The leading role of
enlightened government.
The second point I want to emphasize
is that while smart specialization
presupposes a smart state,
a smart state is far from
being the norm today,
in the European public sector
because it's stymied
by the lack of monitoring
and evaluation mechanisms,
the lack of feedback, the low
priority attached to learning,
and above all,
by the fear of failure.
And my final point is this:
shrinking the state
is counterproductive,
because a smart public
sector is a key actor
in this era of place based innovation
and societal challenges.
Challenges like healthcare.
Like the built environment.
Like renewable energy,
sustainable mobility.
In all these sectors,
these societal challenge sectors,
the state looms large,
especially in our lagging regions.
Thank you.