Hello, and welcome everybody.
In the last two weeks,
we discussed a lot the design
of a Smart Specialization Strategy
And how we can get operational with it.
Also Smart Specialization
is a special strategic tool.
Many of the issues we discussed are
relevant for any kind of
regional economic strategy.
For example, the strengths and
weaknesses that are summarized
in the smart analysis for a
region usually
should be the starting point for any
kind of regional economic strategy
and not only for Smart
Specialization Strategies.
But Smart Specialization is special
and has special properties,
which we might have forgotten a
little bit about in the last two weeks
with all that detailed discussion on
design and how to get operational.
Therefore, I think it is worth the
time to repeat
some of the most important
properties of Smart Specialization.
Again, keep in mind what we know
about operationality now.
The first point is the overall goal
of Smart Specialization.
It is to achieve structural change
in the economy.
Smart Specialization has a lot to do
with innovation, with entrepreneurship,
with new developments, but it's not
the goal by itself
to have new developments, you always
have to keep in mind
that you want to achieve
structural change for your economy,
and not only to create new activities.
That might be part of
how to get operationally,
but the overall goal is
always the structural change.
One of the most important properties
of Smart Specialization is
that you have to make choices.
Smart Specialization forces
you to set your priorities.
That is, because smart specialization
relies on achieving the scales
necessary to come
to structural change:
the scales in entrepreneurship,
the scales in innovation.
If you try to be best in class
in any kind of field,
in every possible area, then you'll
probably never achieve
the necessary scales in any of these
to really arrive at structural change,
so you have to make your choices,
you have to focus on certain areas,
and rely on these areas for the
Smart Specialization Strategy.
Not making these choices
is also some kind of choice,
to do everything, and that
won't be very fruitful.
So, make your choices
and set your priorities.
It is important that you do your
choice on the right level.
It is not on an industry level,
for example, the tourism industry
or the investment goods industry,
are too broad for a Smart
Specialization Strategy.
It's such a broad field that
you probably won't
arrive at the advantage of scale
in these fields,
and therefore not generate the
momentum to
really come to structural change.
On the other hand, you should not
look at the project level,
this is too narrow to
really have the power,
even if you have scale within that
project, it's probably too narrow
to have the power to
achieve a structural change,
therefore, it is somewhere
in between.
Of course, an in-between
is not clearly defined,
and there's probably not
a right and a wrong,
but a continuum of better suited,
less suited priority areas,
but it is clear that it is somewhere
between the industry and project level.
If you take the above serious,
then the next property of Smart
Specialization is already clear.
But still it is very important
and I want to therefore point
again to it: you need a sound base
of evidence to design
a Smart Specialization
Strategy successfully.
If your choice is to not rely
on such a base of evidence,
then the chances that your choices
are not the best ones for your region
are much higher than when you
have such a good base of evidence.
Therefore, the analytical part of
designing such a strategy
is a crucial element of it.
But the base of evidence, the
economic structure,
the location factors, what is
available in the region,
is not all you need.
When you design a Smart
Specialization Strategy,
it's not your task to find the new
innovation policy,
to do innovation yourself,
or even invent new technologies.
It is about combining existing
opportunities.
And to know the opportunities,
you not only need to base off
evidence, the economic side,
but also you need to know
the entrepreneurial resources
available in your region.
They might be from the university
area, or innovation or research labs,
there might be startups or
entrepreneurs active in your region.
All these resources should be applied
in a Smart Specialization Strategy,
and the goal is to combine them
in such a way that
you achieve the scales necessary
to come
to our overall goal
of structural change.
Within a Smart Specialization
Strategy, you make choices.
Choices can be right or wrong,
there's always a risk.
Of course you should make
well-informed choices,
this is what the two above
properties are from,
the base of evidence and the
entrepreneurial activities.
But still, you won't have all
information you might need
for the best choice, for the
optimal choice.
And there will be wrong choices.
Therefore it is important that you
understand Smart Specialization,
not only as using
entrepreneurial activities,
but as an entrepreneurial
process itself.
That's what we call the
entrepreneurial discovery process.
This also implies that priority areas
are not there forever.
In a certain time,
maybe five years, maybe ten years,
but in a certain time, you should
define, within your strategy,
these priority areas either
should  be successful,
entrepreneurially successful,
and then have grown so much,
and led to structural change, that
they're not any more part
of a Smart Specialization,
but, if necessary,
might be supported
by other kinds of policies,
or, they haven't achieved that goal.
Then after a certain time it's not
worth following that path anymore,
and you should probably
discard them.
Finally, there's the question for
which region
smart Specialization Strategy
is appropriate.
It is very easy, because we
talk about entrepreneurship,
and innovation, to think for a region
that's a high tech industry,
say, very good in ICT or in
internet of things,
To define a Smart
Specialization Strategy.
But for many other regions, it's not
that straightforward
because they do not have
the ability to be top in class
in these high tech areas.
Still, the thinking of Smart
Specialization,
the concept and the strategy
building,
is valid for these kinds of regions
as well,
it's just about combining the
existing economic structure
with applying the new technologies
to the existing industry,
the existing assets in the region,
which will lead to
successful priority areas.
Also, the overall goal
is structural change.
So is a Smart Specialization strategy
only good for regions
which really indeed need a
structural change?
No. Structural change is something
which happens always,
and even a successful region
can profit from more
structural change,
towards more competitive, to higher
productive industries.
So the thinking of Smart
Specialization, the concept,
can help any kind of region,
regardless of their focus areas,
regardless of their economic
structure,
and regardless of their
development stage.
It is a way to improve the economy,
regardless where you start from.
Now from these properties,
what can we derive to the process
how to design a Smart Specialization
Strategy from  that?
First of all, it should be a
structured process.
It has a lot of elements, a lot
of demanding elements actually,
and so if you don't
structure the process up ahead,
it will probably be very difficult
to reach the best solution.
Secondly, it involves many
people, many stakeholders.
We look at the economic structure,
we have the government,
the people who define the Smart
Specialization Strategy,
you also need the entrepreneurial
resources,
so there are many people,
many stakeholders involved,
and the process should reflect that.
Involve the stakeholders,
give responsibility to them,
and make them part of your
Smart specialization Strategy.
Finally, the strategy
needs evidence and data.
We discussed that often enough.
Now as the process
has to be structured,
there are certain elements which,
in our opinion
are very important to be part
of such a structuring.
The first element of the five
we identified,
the first element is
to define the region.
It is that everybody knows for
which region, for which definition,
the strategy should work.
And it also creates commitment
towards this region,
and towards the strategy therefore.
Then we have two analytical blocks.
The one is the base of evidence, the
economic structure,
the assets we can build on,
the location quality,
the competitiveness
of the industries.
On the other side we have the
entrepreneurial resources.
Entrepreneurs, startup companies,
Innovation, universities,
all these kinds of players.
Both sides have to be analyzed,
detailed,
and put together for the strategy.
Then it is very important
to make choices,
and this is by choosing
your priority areas.
There should be more than one, but
there should not be too many,
depending of course on
the size of the region,
of the potential you have
to follow such a strategy,
there can be a few
more or a few less.
And finally, with the
thinking of entrepreneurship,
also for the
Smart Specialization Strategy,
not only applying it
in the strategy,
But also thinking of the whole
process as an entrepreneurial process.
You must monitor,
evaluate, and, if necessary,
adapt your strategy. It's not
a one-off for all times,
but do that.
So these are the five steps.
Define your region,
analyze your economic structure,
assess the entrepreneurial activities
Available in your region,
choose priority areas,
and finally, Monitor and evaluate
the development of your strategy.
Now as the base of evidence is one
of the central elements
of designing a Smart
Specialization Strategy,
we want to have a look in a
bit more detail in this again.
And we identified six steps
which might be useful
to generate or to achieve
that base of evidence.
The first step is the
economic performance,
where does the region come from,
What has been achieved in history?
What are the starting
positions here?
Then, second, we will look where we
are at the moment.
What are our location qualities?
For what kind of activities
is the region attractive?
For other kinds it might
be less attractive.
Third, we look at the
industry structure,
in particular about the
competitiveness of these industries.
Can they compete on a global base,
or are they more local oriented?
What are their properties?
Now all these three steps are
usually done in a comparing mode.
You look at your relative position
compared to other regions,
to other economies.
Particularly with competition that
is just at the core of the concept.
But we do need a more detailed
analysis,
a step further into
details within the region,
and that is the fourth step here,
we really look into the region,
Where are the
industrial focus areas?
Specifically, in more detail, where
are clusters,
and what is the region's
innovation system,
which we can build on?
Then in the next step
we broaden our view again.
We look at the global megatrends
and general purpose technologies.
These are development traits that are
the same for all types of regions.
The general purpose
technologies like ICT,
or the digitization of the economy,
or megatrends like aging, all
regions are hit by that,
or influenced by that,
not necessarily hit.
But every region is differently
exposed to these trends,
and can make different use of them.
So therefore, it's not only knowing
these trends,
but also analyzing them,
what do they mean for my region,
given all the above
information we already have?
And finally, the sixth step, and
quite important,
is to bring all that
information together.
Many of these informations
influence each other,
and we need to have a
complete overview of them,
and that's what we do
with a SWOT analysis,
an analysis of strengths,
weaknesses, chances, and risks.
Now that sounds like a very complicated
process, and indeed it is.
It is not easy to come to a
Smart Specialization Strategy,
particularly not a good Smart
Specialization Strategy.
But don't worry too much.
One of the properties of Smart
Specialization is
the entrepreneurial thinking.
Just try, make the best choices you can
given the information you have.
Follow them up, monitor them, and,
if necessary, adapt them.
And with that, it will work.
So, don't worry.
Think entrepreneurial.
Thank you.