Welcome to the second week.
During this week, we will talk
about smart urban energy systems.
The week is structured as follows:
First, we will conceptualize smart
urban energy systems.
putting them into the larger context
of urban systems
and there will be an interview
with an urban utility company.
Then we will take our three layers.
First the energy
infrastructure layer,
and here also,
we will have an interview
with an expert on smart grids.
Then we will talk about
the energy services layer,
and after that, we'll talk about
the data layer,
or the digital layer.
There will be also an interview
with a global firm
that is active in
smart energy systems.
And finally,
I will conclude the week
talking about the managerial
and policy takeaways.