So let us first move
to the conceptualization
of smart urban energy systems.
And we will do this in three steps
First,
we identify the drivers
towards smart urban energy systems.
Then we will conceptualize
the evolution of the urban energy
smart system.
And finally,
we will present
the three layers of transition.
Now let's look at the drivers.
So the smart urban energy systems
are the result of three main drivers
and they are all at the same level.
But let's first mention
the evolution of urban
infrastructure technologies.
There are energy technologies
that are changing,
and we will talk
a little bit later about that.
But with decentralized production.
Renewable energies.
There are technologies in transport
that are changing,
that affect urban energy.
Like electric vehicles,
electric buses,
electric bicycles,
electric charging stations
that go with it.
There are housing technologies
that are changing.
Houses become more self-sufficient,
are producing themselves energy
or electricity.
There are changes in
district heating.
In pump storage.
So the first
important driver
is really the fact that technologies
around the energy sector
are changing.
The second driver
is of course
climate change
resource efficiency.
Cities are big polluters.
And are one of the drivers
of smarter urban energy systems
is of course the desire
to reduce Co2 emissions,
and to become
more energy self-sufficient.
And the third driver
is as core of our MOOC,
of course,
is digitalization.
Actually digitalization
as we will see
is the vehicle by which
urban energy systems
can become smart.
Now let's look at the main dynamics
of these urban energy systems.
Now, traditionally,
energy works like this:
It is produced
in a very centralized way
by big power plants.
Then electricity is
transmitted into the city
And in the city
it is distributed
to households and to firms,
to areas, to airports,
to shopping malls.
It is very linear
from centralized production
to decentralized
distribution process.
Now what is changing?
First thing that changes
is the production process.
We are moving
from centralized production
to decentralized generation.
Of course there is still
centralized production,
but it becomes less important
as areas, factories, households
are generating
their own electricity.
And are feeding
some of this electricity
back into the grid
at certain times.
The second major change,
is from plant production
to intermittent generation.
And this is basically the result
of production of electricity
thanks to renewables.
Here in the examples
of solar and wind.
Now these kind
of electricity production
can happen at a decentralized level,
but it can of course
also happen
in very massive plants
at the centralized level,
and then fed back into the grid.
The third major dynamics
is one that relates to prices.
Rather than having fixed prices,
increasingly, we have price signals.
And this relates to consumption,
in the sense that
consumers household areas
they can now store their energy
at decentralized batteries,
feedback the energy
and maybe it is stored
in a dam somewhere.
That is when prices are high,
the energy is fed
back into the grid.
When prices are low
it is consumed again.
And all this is being automatized.
And this is one of the core features
of smart urban energy systems.
Is this automatic reaction
of devices to price signals.
Like the fridge turning off
at moments when prices
are passing a certain threshold.
And turning on again when prices
get cheaper.
Now what are
the main layers of transition?
Now here we have
the urban electricity system first.
As I present it before
it is an integrated system
where firms, areas, households
are self-generating,
feeding into the grid,
and of course there is still
electricity coming from outside.
But what is interesting
in urban energy systems
is the fact that
there is a larger environment
that is all related
to energy and electricity.
The urban sociotechnical system.
Let us take examples:
Factories.
Not only do they produce and store
but they can themselves be active
in energy matters.
Cars.
Cars are running on electricity.
They charge electricity
at certain hours.
The same for electric buses.
For electric bicycles.
Households are totally...
Houses are related.
Buildings are related
to the electricity system
by consuming and feeding back in.
The gas production
is related to
the electricity system.
Water.
Water, waste water,
you can make energy from waste.
And all this together
forms sort of the urban ecosystem
that influences
the smart urban electricity system.
Now the layers of transition
are the ones that
we have already identified
in the previous week.
Namely,
first the layer of infrastructure
and here we start to now
talk about smart grid.
This is the grid that is capable
to handle all this intermittency.
A grid that is capable to handle
the flow's bidirectional flows.
Then we talk about
the service's layer,
smart urban energy services.
Basically meaning that
we don't just have a consumer.
Consumers are at the same time
prosumers.
And the services
become much more complex.
Not just simply buying electricity.
It's also about saving electricity,
about managing,
And then at the core of it
is of course the digital,
or the data layer,
which makes these
kinds of things possible.
Which makes smart urban
energy systems possible.
So we will, from here
go into these three layers
in detail.
Stay tuned.