Welcome back to the course.
It is my pleasure today
to discuss with Yves Corrodi.
He's the Head of Strategy
of IWB
which stands for the Utility
of the Region of Basel.
This utility is original
in the sense that it is integrated.
It covers several infrastructures,
water, telecommunications,
district heating
and of course, electricity.
Another key feature of this utility
is that they source 100%
of their electricity
from renewables.
So welcome Yves .
Thank you for the invitation.
So, as an integrated utility,
what kind of links do you make?
Or do you foresee between
the electricity,
the smart electricity system
and the other infrastructure,
urban infrastructure systems?
There are a lot of interference
within a lot of dimensions.
Regarding a technical dimension,
There are, phenomenally
you can observe
within the electric grid itself
such as an increase of PV,
local PV Systems, but also between
other infrastructures
such as heat pumps,
as a new heating source,
or storage systems
of different medias,
or, are as example,
electrical mobility.
This will interfere with each other
and it is our role
to combine these trends.
So those, I mean, those
are the technical linkages you see,
but how about, we always
in this course talk also about
social-technical system,
the institutional aspects,
what are other linkages
on the institutional side?
There are a lot other dimensions
such as the political dimension.
I'm thinking of the CO2 agreement,
the Paris agreement
about the CO2 emissions
which sets clear goals
which are inline with
our company goals
or I'm thinking about
the economical dimension.
There are a market liberalizations
in the electricity markets
such as we have observed in Germany
which will affect us,
or there are simply social,
the social dimensions.
We want to provide a good
living quality,
a good infrastructure and services
to our inhabitants and customers.
So, for an integrated utility
like yours, I mean,
what kind of opportunities
do you see in linking
the smart urban electricity system
with the other infrastructures.
There are a lot of trends nowadays,
I mentioned previously
that decentralization,
but there might also be
the digitization which has
to be mentioned
For example, we have this
initiative together
with the local trade association
Smart Regio Basel
Smart Regio Basel,
but we want to increase
the sustainability,
the living quality,
the efficiency within
the area of Basel,
and probably, there might be
in general three initiatives
at the beginning.
So, of course we want to increase
the smartness of our infrastructure,
the inter-connections
between these infrastructures,
but we might also want
to provide data
based on this infrastructure
and might also provide data openly
which could attract new businesses.
But, first idea might be
to establish a new market place,
a digital market place where can be
services locally exchanged
and in order to keep the value chain
within the region.
So, in order to seize
all these opportunities,
what kind of challenges
do you foresee?
There are a lot of challenges;
there are financial challenges,
there are regulatory challenges,
there are challenges
about competences,
But probably at the very beginning
of this association,
the goal should be to bring
the people together,
to have a collaboration between
all these actors and stakeholders.
So you say that we should
start with collaboration
but you know, there are many actors
that could organize
why do you think utility
and integrated utility like yours
is well particularly
well positioned to organize
such collaboration.
Of course, there are a lot
of stakeholders
that can start such an initiative,
however, I would,
you could think about layers,
so there's an infrastructure layer.
There might be a data layer on top
based on this infrastructure
and based on the data
and the infrastructure,
you can provide applications
and projects
of this information and data.
So like a project or innovator layer
and of course,
utility brings in a lot
of infrastructure and a lot of data.
So I think we have possession
to support this association.
Okay, thank you very much
for your insights.
Thank you very much.