Welcome back to the course.
Now, in this session,
we're going discuss the challenges
that result from the transition to
smart urban energy infrastructures
and we will do this in two steps.
First, we will put the urban
energy infrastructures into context
and then we will outline
the main actors
that are involved in managing
these infrastructures.
Now let's look at the context.
Now, we have already presented
the three main drivers
of smart urban energy systems.
The decentralized generation,
the intermittent generation,
and then the changes in consumption
due to the price signals.
Now, let's look at this in
a little bit more concrete fashion.
So, we have four things.
First, we have alternative
urban energy sources.
We have talked earlier about
wind energy,
about local wind production,
local solar production,
but we should also mention
geothermal energy
that is increasingly important
in cities, as well as,
energy produced from waste.
Then, we have much more
efficient,
energy efficient
consumption patterns,
This results from more
efficient houses,
more efficient areas,
more efficient factories,
more efficient transportation,
more efficient recycling
and waste management.
Third, we have semi
or entirely
off grid electricity operations
that is electricity operations
that at times consume,
at times feed back
into the urban electricity system,
and finally, we have new
emerging storage solutions
that can be in vehicles,
that can be in houses,
that can bigger, even in factories.
Now, all these four elements
lead to challenges
in managing
the urban energy infrastructure,
the urban energy grid,
something that is called
smart grid today.
So let us now look at the different
actors that are involved
in urban electricity systems.
Now we have already talked about
the whole production chain
from extraction to conversion,
to transmission
that would be outside of the city
to distribution, storage,
and producing and consuming
inside the city.
Those would typically be
the urban energy infrastructure.
Now, there are a series of actors
that are involved here
and these actors all
interact with each other
and ultimately have
to be coordinated.
Let's start with from bottom to top.
So there are the prosumers
as we have said,
the ones who consume electricity
and produce electricity
at the same time,
Those can be household
and industry.
Then, we have decentralized
electricity producers
who can be the same
as the prosumers,
but they can also be producers
on their own
in the sense of waste facility
that produces electricity.
Then we have storage operators
which can be transport operators
or storage operators on their own.
Then we have distributors.
Typically, we have an urban
electricity energy distributor
but with off and semi off grids,
we may have new distributors
that have to interact,
that have to be coordinated.
But the challenge is not
just limited to the city
because also the transmission system
operator, or operators,
there may be several,
are concerned, namely,
those are the actors that
feed the electricity
into the city and at times may even
take back electricity
to be stored in one of the dams
as we have seen before.
Then there are the centralized
electricity producers
that need to be coordinated,
and finally, there are the traders,
the ones who fluidify consumption
and prosumption of electricity
by linking all the actors together.
Now, the challenge here
is to manage  these interactions
and to coordinate all these actors
among themselves,
and digitalization is both
the cause of this
and the answer to this.
It is thanks to digitalization
that all these different actors
can even emerge
and play a role
in smart urban energy systems
but it is also thanks
to digitalization
that these actors can now
be coordinated and managed so as
to make smart urban electricity
infrastructures function.
Now, in the next session,
you will hear
from a colleague of mine at EPFL
who is an expert on smart grids,
stay tuned.