Hello.
And welcome back to the course.
Today I have the pleasure of talking
to Professor Mario Paolone,
who is chairing the Distributed
Electrical Systems Laboratory at EPFL.
He's an expert on
the topic of smart grids,
and he's doing
very interesting research at EPFL.
Thank you very much, Mario
for being with us.
It's a pleasure Mohamad,
to be with you.
As the first question,
I would like to ask you
about the key challenges in managing
smart grids for cities?
Okay. Well, in smart grids as you know,
there is a built in assumption
mainly, that a big fraction
of the electricity is being generated
in a distributed manner.
Essentially true in renewables, mainly PVs,
that can be roof top
can be centralized power plants,
wind turbines, etc.
Now, the integration of these resources
poses two challenges.
The first one is that
these resources are not centralized,
namely, they are dispersed
on the territory.
They are very large in number,
and they are stochastic.
In the sense that they are
difficult to control.
Not from the technical point of view,
but from the aggregated perspective.
Therefore, there are
two essential requirements
in technology needs of smart grids.
The first one are the tools
that we call situation awareness tools.
Essentially, you need to have
a way to provide the sensing
as well as the  situation awareness
to automators, or to operators
that knows exactly
which is the status of the asset
in quasi real-time, and with a
very high refresh rate.
A refresh rate that I can mention
are in the range of
tens or hundreds of milliseconds.
Okay?
In systems which are pretty big in size,
that can be a neighbourhood, a city,
a country,
or even an entire continent.
So, that's the first requirement,
to observe
and to sense the system status.
A little bit is how
automatic cars are doing
with the technology called auto-pilots.
You have to build the kind of situation
which is surrounding the vehicle.
The second requirement, the second
technological requirement
is the capability
to control the systems
with bulk stochastic generation
in a controlled fashion.
And this means to use storage.
The set where we are now,
it's a battery.
It's a Lithium titanium battery.
And this is one
of the asset that we need
in future smart grids
to enable the controllability
of stochastic resources,
to be able to control,
to provide services to the power system
at the local level.
And this, the second element,
that you need to develop.
Good.
As the second question,
you mentioned the role of technology
called challenges that we have.
But can you also
elaborate a little bit more
on how technology
is also providing
the solution for these challenges?
Yeah. I go back to the
first technological aspect/dimension
namely the sensing.
I make you a comparison with the -
again, the example of a car. Okay?
So in the car you have a system
that has a physical system.
That's a size of a few meters.
So, the sensors are
essentially located
nearby each other.
So, you don't need
to synchronize them.
Because the physical dimension
of the system is rather small.
In power systems, in smart grids
as I said, your system can have
the minimum size of a neighborhood,
or it can go up to a country,
or a continent.
Now, if you sense quantities which are
that are collected in a fashion,
in points which are separated
by kilometers,
or hundreds of kilometers.
You know speed of light is finite.
So, you end up in having delays
in collecting this information.
So, what we typically do
is that we adopt
state of the art
time synchronism mechanism,
that can be either GPS,
namely satellite synchronization system.
Satellite like GPS, GLONASS,
or Galileo systems,
or can be time synchronisms
which are brought into the internet.
There are protocols called
Precision Time Protocols,
PTP technologies, that you typically use
to synchronize the clock
of your computer, right?
With time accuracy
which is relatively low
we look for technologies which are
much more deterministic than this one.
For instance,
we are taking a technology
that is used by CERN
to synchronize their oscilloscopes
on the Large Hadron Collider,
is called the White Rabbit,
the name of this protocol.
And we are taking it and adapting
to time synchronization
in smart grids.
With these kinds of protocol,
you typically have jitters
of the measurements
in the range of few nanoseconds.
So this enables you to collect
and time align
all your measurements, and then feed
the situational awareness tools
that are essentially reconstructing
the system state
with a very high fidelity
and a very high frame rate.
So, that's the first kind
of technology that we make use.
What do you do once we have that?
Essentially, you share
this situation
of your system
with the automators.
And the automators are essentially
local intelligence
that are taking
the control of your small asset,
your small TV, this battery,
a controllable load,
analytical vehicle charger,
and whatsoever.
So, you share this to the system,
and these devices
they, by knowing the state
of the system
they essentially
take intelligent action
by negotiating each other. Okay?
So, this is more on
the software development part.
Then you need also physical systems,
like this battery.
As I said, having the capacity,
the capability
of storing energy
in a very efficient way
and release it in a,
also controllable way,
it's one of the key aspects
of smart grids.
So this kind of battery was
not really imaginable few years ago.
It's a device
that has round-trip efficiency
above 95 percent. Okay?
Just to give you a number.
Irrespective of the state of charge,
and of the power
that you are extracting or injecting
into the system.
It has a ramp rate,
so it can generate a ramp of power
of about 20 megawatts a second,
which is a ramp of power
which is very similar to
state of the art large turbines.
But this is an asset
that you can take and move it.
So, it's a very peculiar system.
And the third aspect
that you have is that the cost
of this kind of technology
is going to be down
with the almost aquadratic law
So if you look at the cost
of this device,
was in the range of several thousands
of Swiss Francs,
or Euros if you want,
a few years ago,
Now we are talking about hundreds
of US dollars per kilowatt hour.
And, last but not least,
the life cycle of these devices.
This asset in particular can do
more than 15,000 cycles.
So if you measure to a cycle a day
it will last 15,000 days,
namely several decades.
Which is a good aspect,
and fundamental aspect for utilities.
Because in the power industry,
the assets,
typically, they last
for 20, 25 years.
So having a storage system
can have similar performances
in terms of life cycle,
it's fundamental.
Great.
So the technology is somehow there
you know, to have the smart grids.
But also, you know, the institutions,
regulation, and management
is often a challenge
in these socio-technical systems.
Can you elaborate a little bit
on the managerial
and regulation challenges
in smart grids?
That's also very good question.
So talking about this asset,
for instance,
we're talking about energy storage.
So typically, these kind of devices
will be used by power utilities.
Which are not supposed
to own energy storage
because you know
in unbundled markets
they can do energy arbitration.
In the sense,
they can influence the demand
and they can purchase energy
and store energy.
When if the market is very cheap,
they can know it in advance
and then resell the energy
when the prices are higher,
to their customers.
So this kind of asset
which are meant to add flexibility
to the systems,
they should be using a different way.
In this specific case,
the regulatory bodies
that have to develop tools
to certify
that these kind of assets are used
only to avoid grid reinforcement,
namely in support of the grid,
and not to do energy arbitration.
Just to make an example.
The second example
I can make about regulatory needs,
is about the use of smart meters,
for instance.
In situational systems,
nowadays technology allows us to infer
the state of the system, including
the nodal power injection absorption's,
even if you don't directly meter it.
Which means I can observe
what the customer is doing
even if I don't place a meter
in his house.
And this might generate
privacy issues and discussions
for this kind of application.
So, yep, there is a lot  to do.
And last, but not least,
it's how the regulatory board
will fraction and divide
the costs of the grid
between transmission, distribution,
(INAUDIBLE).
Having these kinds of assets
means that you give to the operators
the opportunity
to locally balance the power flows.
Meaning that the transmission system
will be used less in the future,
but with a cost
that the rent will be even higher.
So, who is paying for this cost?
How we transfer these costs
to the customers,
with which mechanisms?
These are questions that I don't know
whether are still open.
Great.
Thank you very much Mario.
It was very insightful
for our participants.
Thank you Mohamed,
and thank you again for the invitation.