Welcome back.
In this session, we will talk about
smart urban energy services.
In particular, we will talk about
what these services exactly are
and who can provide them.
Let us look now at what these
smart urban energy services
exactly are.
So, we have already mentioned
in session two,
the three main dynamics that
are taking place in urban energy.
The move from centralized production
to decentralized generation,
the move from planned production
to intermittent generation
and then all these price signals
that relate
to the whole automatization
of this process.
Now, there are four types
of customers
of such smart urban energy services.
There are households,
you and me.
There are entire buildings
with a lot of households in it.
Then, there are commercial
or industrial areas,
like for example, an airport
or a shopping mall,
and then there is another
type of customer,
those are the distribution
and transmissions system operators
who will buy balancing energy.
So here you have three
types of services;
smart energy services.
The first one, very clearly
attributable to the grid operators
is the balancing energy.
The energy that these operators need
in order to keep the grid stable.
Then there are the services
that relate
to demand-side management.
At this point, those are purely
services in terms of electricity.
Basically, you offer the services
to households, buildings,
commercial and industrial areas,
in terms of managing
their demand of electricity
much more efficiently
in relationship to price signals,
for example.
And then, a little bit broader
are the smart and integrated
services
and urban energy services.
Those are the services that now link
the electricity,
urban electricity system
with other systems,
with the water system,
with the transport system
with the batteries for the car,
with the waste,
with the recycling and also there,
the same customer households,
buildings, commercial areas,
can receive these kinds
of integrated
smart energy services.
Who are the providers
of these services?
Now, in the core,
we have of course as we have said,
the dynamics, the digitalization
that favors all this
and you will see how that
affects the providers.
So, typically,
the traditional providers
are the electricity distribution
companies within a city.
They can offer demand side
management
to all the different customers
that we have seen
and they also to a certain extent
offer smart
and integrated energy services
by venturing into other,
into waste, into transport,
for example,
if they operate the charging station
of the local bus system
or if they operate some sought of
batteries for shopping malls
and other commercial areas.
But those are legacy operators.
Then, we have urban utilities.
By that, we mean the type
of companies
that are not traditionally
in the electricity,
in the urban electricity business,
but they are
in our urban water distributors,
urban waste managers,
urban public transport operators,
and they can now offer these
integrated energy services
and offer also balancing services
by linking the consumption patterns
of the household, and linking that
to energy consumption.
And then, there are what
we call intermediaries.
Those are new operators
that have not been
in the urban business at all.
They basically, produce devices
or have information
like telecom operators
for example.
They have information
about your
electricity consumption
and they can manage that consumption
and sell the services
both to you as a customer
or as an industrial area,
and to the balancing,
to the great companies
that need balancing energy.
That is actually an interesting
business model
that we see appearing
in many cities.
But this is also possible
thanks to what we call
peer to peer operators.
That is also called energy commons
or electricity commons
where customers get together
and do this kind of demand side
management together.
Sought of taking out
the intermediaries themselves.
Now, we can see new comers
in all of these areas,
and so potentially,
the smart urban energy services
can be provided increasingly
by operators that come
from outside the city,
operators that have no history
in infrastructures.
And I think that's the real novelty
in smart urban energy services.