Welcome back.
In this session, we will now talk
about urban energy systems
data layer, that is the real novelty
in smart cities
and in smart urban energy systems,
and we will do this in three steps.
First, how to think this data layer
Then, the two visions
that one can apply to this
and then, thirdly,  the  questions
that this two visions have raised.
So, lets fist look at how to think
the urban energy systems
data layer.
Now this picture, we have already
seen in week one,
where we said that the digital
or the data layer
is the novelty of smart cities,
or smart urban energy systems
in this case.
Now, first, there are data
being generated
and these data
are basically generated
from three different sources.
There are data about user behaviour,
there are data general electricity
or energy generators behaviour.
how much is consumed,
how much is produced,
and then very importantly,
there are data about the behaviour
of the grid, in this case,
the distribution grid,
as a function of user
and generator behaviour.
On the basis of this data,
there are urban,
smart urban energy
services providers,
and this looks like this,
the services as we have seen
in the previous session
are offered to different,
different types of customers
and there are different types
of services that are being offered
but all they have in common
is that they use the data
that has so being generated.
Now, let's look at the two visions
that are possible for this,
and the first vision, really
pertains to the,
and it's an integrated view
of data generation
and data usage
for services provision.
This is typically the vision
that can,
that is held by
electricity utilities
that have the data about generation
and that also want to provide
the services
on the basis of these data.
There may be some related companies
that access to the infrastructure
but basically here the vision is,
that this is integrated.
All the data generation
and the services are integrated,
and there are
the different companies
that own these data
and offer the services
are competing against each other,
not sharing this data.
The second vision is
totally different
in the sense that
there are data platforms
and the different data generators
feed all these data
into the platforms, and then
the services providers
take the information from
these platforms
and develop different
types of services
to different types of customers
as a result of that.
Now, this leads to very
different questions.
The first question on the left side,
if we have integrated
data generation and services,
this basically considers data
as a good.
It's something that somebody
has produced,
that somebody uses in order
to create services
and basically the question here is,
who owns the data?
The users, the utility,
the devise producers, for example.
And this raises the question
of regulation,
but from this point of view,
regulation is basically
a competition regulation.
You need to make sure that
there is sufficient competition here
and that ownership rights
are respected
in this kind of competition.
No market distortion,
no tendency to monopoly,
things like that
On the other side,
if we data as a platform,
as a shared platform,
the question is,
who owns this platform, or not even
necessarily owns the platform
but who manages this platform?
And in terms of regulation,
the approach also is
totally different
because you will end up
with some sort of
infrastructure type regulation.
Access to the data,
availability of the data,
transparency of the data,
prices of the data,
all questions of that sort.
So we can see that there are really
two different types of visions
leading to two different types
of regulating
dealing ultimately with this data.
Now that we have discussed
the three different layers,
let's ask Schneider Electric
how they see
the smart urban energy system.
So stay tuned.