Welcome back.
Now to conclude this second week,
we are gong to talk about
the managerial and policy
takeaways
from our discussion about
smart urban energy systems.
Let's first talk about
the managerial takeaways.
And we have structured this
along the three layers
and the main relevant dimensions.
So the first big challenge
for managers
from a technological perspective
is of course
the question of great stability.
Because of intermittency,
because of renewable
decentralized production,
because of price signals and
increasingly volatile price signals,
the whole grid stability becomes,
I would say,
the main challenge for urban,
smart urban energy systems managers.
Then from an economic perspective,
there is the whole question
of allocating the cost
of moving to smart
urban energy systems.
The upgrading that
need to be done,
who ultimately pays for what?
On the services layer,
it's normally an economic question
in the sense of these
smart urban energy services,
what are the underlying businesses
of these services,
who will pay for these services,
who wants to pay for the services,
is there a market for the services?
And more from
a social perspective,
this is the question of
user acceptance
or ultimately, user uptake.
Will they use or buy
these kind of services?
On the data layer,
there are technological questions
in terms of status standards,
interoperability of data
and questions of data security
that managers have to face.
And finally, also from
an economic perspective,
this is the whole question
of the pricing of the data.
What is the right pricing
of this data
so that ultimately the market
will uptake the services
and at the same time,
the cost for upgrading,
for moving into a smart
urban energy systems are covered.
So let's now look the takeaways
for policy makers
along the same structure
as previously;
the different layers,
the different dimensions.
I think the first challenge
for policy makers
are the whole question
of legacy cost.
We have traditional energy systems,
big power plans,
transmission grid,
costly transmission grids,
and as a result of
smart urban energy systems,
more independent may be
less consumption,
the question comes up as to who
bears these legacy costs
and how to finance
these legacy costs.
Then, more from
a jurisdictional perspective,
it is of course also the question
of the relative independence
of an urban energy system,
We know that all energy
and electricity systems
are interconnected with each other
and so the question,
the policy question here
is really what is
the relevant entity?
Is it the city in itself,
but we know that the city
is a political entity and often
from a system perspective
does not necessarily make sense.
May be more the metropolitan
area here.
On the services layer,
and from an economic perspective,
there is the whole question
of regulating certain services
and certain prices of services,
for example,
we have seen that balancing services
is one of the smart urban
energy services
that is being offered,
but balancing energy
is heavily regulated,
and so there  is policy action
and policy is challenged also
in this area.
From the social perspective,
there's the whole question
of Universal Services Obligation.
Is there a minimum amount of energy,
smart urban energy services,
that the citizens are entitled to,
at what price,
how affordable is it,
when can they be cut off,
for example?
And then on the data layer,
there are a series
of policy questions
The question from
a technological perspective,
it's also the question
of access to data,
rights of access to data.
On economic,
from an economic perspective,
it's the whole question
of data ownership.
Who owns the data?
What are the prices for that data,
and then, of course, the whole
question of financing
the different digital
infrastructures
that have to be put into place.
On the social side, I think the big
policy challenges
are privacy, which of course,
will affect
whether the users will ultimately
use the services or not.
And to conclude, I think
the most fundamental questions
that policy makers have
to ask themselves
is whether they want consider
in an urban system
that the data on smart
urban energy data as a good,
as a commercial good,
or as a platform,
and this kind of question
will have the answer
to this kind of question,
will have huge regulatory
implications
which then policy makers
will have to follow up on.
To conclude this second week,
we have seen the three main layers
of smart urban energy systems.
We have talked about
the infrastructure layer,
the services layer
and the data layer
and have illustrated this
with a series of presentations
and interviews with experts.
Then, we have seen what the main
managerial and policy
takeaways are form this.
Now, in the next week,
we will talk about
smart urban transportation systems.
So stay tuned.