Welcome back to the course.
We have the pleasure of having
Mr. Matthias Bölke with us today.
He is the CEO and country president
of Schneider Electric Austria
and Switzerland.
Matthias, thank you very much
for having us.
Thank you for having me !
My first question is the following,
what do you see
as the main differences
between the management
of legacy energy systems
and emerging smart energy systems?
Right.
So the existing legacy system
in place,
is in place since the beginning
of the electrification,
you can say, right.
So, that means we have three
main characteristics;
the production of the electricity,
the grid itself towards distribution
and then the sales.
The production is basically,
was and is still,
done by big power plants
using basically coil, oil,
water, and nuclear resources,
right.
That's what it is today,
and those power plants
are then injecting the current
in the existing grid.
Then it comes to distribution,
the second part.
The distribution is basically
a top down grid today
where you can say the current
is almost flowing every time
in the same direction from
the power plant to the end user
and it's a grid which is today
more electro-mechanical
than anything else.
Some automation is into stabilize
the friction of the grid,
to balance the between
the power plant
and the end user I'd say,
between the user and the load.
And the third part is the sales.
Legacy was a regulated system,
for sure.
Power plant and grid in one end,
so, regulated prices as well,
stable prizes, high margins
and also end users could not
really change the supplier, right.
So, this ecosystem,
this whole ecosystem
is now a huge transformation,
basically because of two things,
First, we have now an affordable way
to alternative energy.
And second, we have digitalization
in the electricity
which is as you can imagine,
a big, big thing.
Driven, all that, by sustainability
because we know
that we have a growing
population on earth
especially for cities.
We're talking about
smart cities, right?
We have now the figure, we've
doubled our energy consumptions
to  2050 from now.
We have to divide CO2 emissions
if we want to stop climate change,
and this is now changing
really dramatically,
the ecosystem of the energy grid
for the future,
and already happening now.
And it's influencing
all these three things, production,
distribution and sales.
The production, we'll go away
from these centralized power plants
to a decentralized way to produce.
The distribution grid is really
a change from vertical topology
to  horizontal grids,
highly automated, highly digitalized
and for the sales,
ecosystem will go away
from a regulated system
to a deregulated market,
open market, where the end user
can choose his supply
of electricity and energy,
right.
Where a lot of more trading happen,
a lot of more flexibility happen,
so that really,
the whole system is
changing dramatically.
Matthias, what do yo see
as main benefits and risk
associated with the emergence
of smart energy systems for cities?
Well Maxime, clearly I see much more
benefits and risks, right?
But, let's talk about both, right.
Listen, if you see
a smart grid deployment,
a smart campus deployment
in a given city, right,
is for me a highly attractive,
right, for  a major
or for the official bodies
of the city for instance.
If you see we have this,
this sought of production.
We have the smart energy grid,
we have new ways of trading
between producers
and consumers, right.
We have prosumers which are
even out of the scene.
The same guy can produce the energy,
sell the energy, use energy
or buy the energy,
all of this in a very smart way.
I mean here, so,
are lot of new functions,
new business to come,
new jobs to come, right.
But this is highly attractive
and a big benefit
for a given city, right.
We have stability in the grid,
which is decentralized
approach as well.
and we have the suspect
of sustainability,
and sustainability is for me
an also clearly attractiveness
of the future of a given city,
right.
Now, if you see more digitalization
and more smartness
in the grid gives us
much more visibility.
So visibility means we can see
where for instance
we are wasting energy, right.
So this is also a clear benefit
and if we even can correlate
then process data, this energy data,
I mean process data
for instance, for production,
can be SAP ordering system
in plants,
or can be a patient system
in a given hospital,
can be data about moments
of people in a hotel.
If you correlate those
process data, then again,
we see energy view in real time,
you really can save energy,
you really can make the system
much more efficient.
and you can have also
some good inputs
to the effectiveness
of the process itself,
which is also a huge benefit.
So on the technical level,
I see also
a lot of different benefits.
Now it comes to questions
to risks, right,
so that, we're talking about
much more data now once a system,
much more digitalization software
and so on.
So people tend to think and to say
that we have highly risk,
and may be also instability
of this kind of things
which is in my view not the case
because a true network
of things is always more stable
than centralized
or legacy system here,
when the plant
is not operating anymore
you have a huge problem,
Instead in a decentralized way,
when one producer
is not going well,
the rest of the system can
be very very stabilizing,
right.
And then,
there are data in this.
There is this question about
data security, cyber security,
data privacy as well,
for sure.
This is certainly a risk,
but the business model
and the driver behind
this new world,
this new world change is so big
and so important
that I truly believe that
those two points;
cyber security and data privacy
will be solved.
Matthias, last question.
What would you say are  the main
technical and institutional
conditions
to guarantee a successful transition
for legacy energy system
to smart energy systems?
Now Maxime, I think the technical
preconditions are there almost,
right, so we're building today
such smart city approaches already
and smart energy approaches,
we have today.
There are a lot of components
available in the market today
where you have highly
intelligence in.
The electrical grid can be equipped
today by a lot of components
which have incorporated a chip
which is measuring the current
and imitating data
in the same time, right.
So this is not very expensive
and you have by definition
a huge visibility,  if you do it
right from the start
you have the preconditions,
and then you have software on it,
this data handling big data
aggregation,
and such kinds of things
which are already today
available too.
and you can use it,
we are doing this already.
So I would say on the technical way,
a lot of things are available today.
Now, you need to make sure
that you stay
with an open system
that you can collaborate.
You need to integrate new things.
We have to think about
just for instance
electrical charging infrastructure
for electrical vehicles,
so we need this to be extended.
Batteries are playing
an important role
but you need to implement
for instance traffic control.
You need to integrate
a water system.
You need to integrate may be
a city information system
to the city center service.
That's why it's very important
to choose an open system
and to have a big collaboration
between relevant players
in a given part, right.
Then you asked about governance
or out the legal aspects, et cetera.
For me it's very important
that you have,
that you can gather important player
around the table
to design, to build an agenda,
and then to roll out
such a kind of project.
So this is who?
This is basically the governance
of a city, of a region,
of a state, so governmental aspect
is important.
We have private investors,
investment banks,
development banks,
but also private guys
in a given city
which can contribute a lot.
We have guys as us, me,
you know, industrial suppliers.
So, we are doing electricity
but we also have ICT,
we have other service suppliers
in the city,
so the private sector
I would say.
And then, very important
from the beginning
is certainly, the integration
of the citizens in the city.
So you have a good buy-end
in the concept,
Those people are contributing
because it's all about behaviour.
it's about the perception
of what it can be, changed,
so that you take
the people on board.
And this can be either through
associations for instance.
Think about the relevant
associations you have.
You can take them in,
NGOs as well.
So you have the voice
of the customer
in your project, right.
Then you have very
important utilities
which are delivering energies
to the system,
water, gas, electricity,
but also more services,
partly ICT services
and other services, because they are
transforming a lot now,
so they can have
with really a stake in it.
And last but not least, you need
really guys which are planners
infrastructure planners
but also electrical guys  which can
plan the whole system then
and can design it, and can then
bring it to an agenda.
So, I would say then
to have a good governance,
on a smart city project
or on an energy campus project,
you have different ways to do it.
You can for instance have
a performance contracting
where a city is outsourcing
the contracting part,
and you have a pay with them
for party things,
you can have a designed built
operate model
where really the city is going
to gift the whole thing
to an external supplier,
and who would then take care
about the running model
of your system.
There are software as a service,
It's a big thing coming
where we are using cloud services
and where the data you need,
are some how
in a clear governance,
and can be used
for next steps of services.
So that also very important.
So I think the name of the game
is all about,
let's say collaboration,
about integration,
having the right stakeholder
around the table,
as much as you can.
Of course there's a question
of governance and to take it forward
but, our experience has said
this collaboration
and integration of
all the stakeholders
is really mandatory
to be successful then
in such kind of  projects.
thank you very much Matthias
for answering our questions.
You're welcome,
thank you.