If I told you,
this is a picture of a man
transporting faecal sludge
in Nairobi, Kenya,
from the site of collection
to a transfer station
for delivery to treatment.
Could you tell me
what's inside of his barrel?
In this model,  you'll learn
how to answer that question.
Following this model, you'll
be able to distinguish
varieties of sludge.
Name factors influencing faecal
sludge characteristics,
and name the main constituents of
faecal sludge related to treatment.
To better understand
what fecal sludge is,
I think it is helpful to walk through
3 definitions.
Excreta, Faecal sludge,
and waste water.
And what's different about them.
So excreta, is urine and faeces.
This is different than
faecal sludge
which contains excreta,
but in addition
includes anything else that goes into
the on-site containment technology.
And anything else really means
anything else.
From flush water, cleansing materials,
menstrual hygiene products,
(INAUDIBLE) your kitchen water,
garbage,
or municipal solid waste.
So this then, is the faecal sludge
management service chain.
Waste water on the other hand,
also contains excreta,
but it is transported
via a flush toilet to a sewer.
And then transported via sewer
to a treatment plant.
So waste water, and faecal sludge
have entirely different service chains.
In addition, waste water
contains less municipal
solid waste or garbage,
because it is difficult to flush it
in the toilet.
And in addition, it can include
storm water management.
Another way to think about it,
is to think about
different types of sludge.
Sludge...
could be transported in a sewer
and be part of the waste water
service chain.
Or,
It could be transported
without a sewer
and be part of the faecal sludge
management service chain.
Waste water sludge,
could be sewer sludge,
while it's still been transported
in the sewer.
Or it could be after
it's been received
at a waste water treatment plant.
Examples of this could be
from a waste stabilization pond,
from activated sludge,
or following final treatment
which is commonly referred
to as Bio-solids.
Types of on site technologies,
Can include septic tanks,
and also
pit latrines.
Septic tank sludge
is also commonly referred
to as septage.
And it includes the sludge, that's
in the septic tank,
the scum layer,
And also the liquid
that's in there
while it's been emptied.
So this chart, is not in
anyway comprehensive.
It's just to provide some examples
And show the reason why
faecal sludge is so highly variable.
Is it because it comes from
the individual household level,
and is not homogenized
during transport in the sewer.
Also, it's so highly variable
because it means literally
any type of technology
that's not connected to the sewer.
From dry toilets to flush toilets,
to with or without grey water.
What else contributes to
the variability of faecal sludge?
Things we've already mentioned
like pit latrines
versus septic tanks.
This is the type of containment.
What is going into the containment?
Is it excreta in black water?
With or without forms of grey water?
Meaning it can all be a slurry, or
mostly water, all the way to a semi solid.
This is the contents.
The emptying frequency which
affects level of stabilization.
For example public toilets,
or commercial buildings,
where the containment is emptied
as frequently as daily to weekly.
In contrast to systems with emptying
frequencies of years.
This means that faecal sludge can
range from fresh, to raw,
to partially stabilized.
Which is due to
the storage duration,
but also, how is it emptied?
Was it fully or partially emptied?
Was water added, to help
remove the sludge?
These are emptying practices.
Characteristics are also affected
but if technologies are performing
as designed.
This is treatment performance.
How well technologies were constructed?
Are they lined or unlined?
Are they really water tight?
This is quality of construction.
Infiltration, or in flow
from ground water,
and temperature, which affects
(INAUDIBLE) degradation.
So what does all this variability
actually mean in terms of quantification?
This figure illustrates COD values
plotted against Total
Suspended Solids
to Volatile Suspended Solids
for faecal sludge analytical
results.
from some of SANDEC's
research studies.
In comparison, it also shows values
for in-fluent of waste water
treatment plants
taken from the METCALF
and EDDY reference.
Note also, that it's in
a logarithmic scale.
What you see here, is that faecal sludge
is up to 2 orders of magnitude
more concentrated than waste water
in addition to being highly variable.
The same technologies will have
widely ranging characteristics
in comparison to each other.
And areas within the same city will
have widely ranging characteristics.
The main constituents
of faecal sludge
that we will mostly focus on
in regards to treatment objectives
are solids and moisture contents for
de-watering and drying of faecal sludge.
Forms of organic matter for
the stabilization of faecal sludge.
Nutrient management
and Inactivation of pathogens.
Because there's still
a general lack of information
on faecal sludge characteristics,
we thought it would be useful
to compile this report
of 76 samples that we analysed
in Kampala, Uganda.
The samples are presented in
increasing concentrations of COD.
For each sample, there is a picture
of where the sample was taken,
and what it looked like
in the laboratory.
There is characterisation
information on solids,
nutrients, organics, and also
qualitative information.
Like how viscous did it appear?
And information on the type
and usage of on site containment.
You can see in these photos, how (INAUDIBLE)
the COD concentration
goes from 1,000 milligrams
per litre,
to 9,000 milligrams per litre,
to 26,000 milligrams per litre.
The visual appearance
is also quite different.
Qualitatively, you can already get
a rough idea of characteristics
based on appearance.
Hopefully, you'll find
this report useful
to get an idea of the range of
faecal sludge characteristics.
It can be downloaded for free
on our website.
So now, if I ask you
what's in the barrel
that the man was transporting
in Nairobi?
Could you answer?
I hope so.
Actually, I hope your answer
would have to do more
with why you could not say
exactly what's in there.
Because faecal sludge means
so many things
but provides some insight as to
what could be in there.
Because in this model,  you learned
about the wide varieties
of different sludge types.
Factors influencing faecal sludge
characteristics,
and the main constituents of faecal
sludge related to treatment.
Thanks for joining.
See you next time.