Treatment processes occur by
different mechanisms.
Some treatment relies on physical
forces, such as filtration,
evaporation, and gravity.
Some treatment relies on the
metabolism of living organisms
such as microorganisms, invertebrate
animals, and insects such as
these black soldier fly larvae.
And other treatments relay on
chemical reactions, such as redox
reactions and altering
chemical bonds.
Following this module you'll know
the difference between physical,
chemical and biological treatment
mechanisms. And be familiar with
mechanisms for solid liquid
separation, stabilization,
nutrient management and pathogen
reduction.
What are the most important
treatment processes and fecal
sludge management is dewatering.
Dewatering is based on physical
processes such as evaporation,
evapotranspiration, filtration,
gravity, surface charge attractions,
centrifugal force and pressure.
Gravity is probably the most
commonly employed method
of liquid solid separation, for the
separation of suspended particles
and bound water.
Particles that are heavier than
water set decreasing conditions
at rates based on size of particles,
suspended solids concentrations,
and flocculation
These are the basic fundamentals
used in the design of settling
thickening tanks in grit and
sand chambers.
Filtration is also a commonly
applied mechanism for dewatering.
Many different types of filtration
media are used for water,
waste water and treated sludge or
biosolids processing.
The most common for the treatment
of fecal sludge are drying beds,
and planted drying beds. Drying beds
used sand and gravel filter media to
to trap solids on the surface of the
filter bed. While the liquid
percolates through the filter bed
and is collected in a drain or
evaporates.
Water that can be separated through
gravity or filtration is free water
that is more easily separated from
solids. This is analogous to water
that can be run out of a towel. If
you need more liquid removed from
the sludge, then you also need
drying. For example, by the sun
thorough evaporation under surface
of drying beds.
Evaporation occurs when water is
released into the air as a vapor.
Transpiration occurs when plants
release vapor to the air as part of
their metabolic processes.
Evapotranspiration is a combination
of these two processes. Evaporation
can also occur from other sources of
heat, such as thermal drying
or even somewhat from other physical
processes, such as centrifugation.
Ok, so next on to biological
mechanisms.
Biology is essential in a
transformation of organic matter
and nutrients. Biology is also
essential for understanding
pathogens and pathogenic activation.
Biological treatment harnesses the
metabolism and growth rate of
microorganisms. And even
invertebrates' unnaturally occurring
processes. And employs them in
controlled situations to optimize
the desired outcomes. Treatment
systems usually rely on complex
populations of microorganisms.
As the microbes grow, they are
dynamically altering the system by
modifying forms of organic matter
and releasing and binding up
nutrients. They also release gasses
and other byproducts that can affect
the environment.
Here we see viruses, bacteria,
protozoa and invertebrates.
The biodegradable organic matter
in fecal sludge varies depending on
the source. But usually needs to be
stabilized prior to final end use or
disposal. Stabilization involves the
degradation of readily degradable
material, leaving behind more stable
less degradable organics.
This is important in order to reduce
the oxygen demand, produce stable
and predictable characteristics,
reduce odors, and allow for easy
storage and manipulation.
Stabilized organic matter does not
have an exact agreed upon scientific
definition. But in general, it
refers to resistance to further
biodegradation. Stabilized sludge
consists of particles like cellulose
lignin, inorganic matter, and the
cellular material of microorganisms
that consume the readily degradable
organics. Whereas, unstabilized
sludge contains easily degradable
compounds, such as carbohydrates,
proteins, and sugars. Stabilization
can be achieved through multiple
types of aerobic and anaerobic
treatments. For example, composting.
Nutrient management can also be
achieved thru biological treatment.
For example, through the
mineralization of organic matter
as it is degraded releasing
nutrients into the environment.
Or, through the immobilization of
nutrients as they are taken up
during growth into new cellular
material.
Further information on the role of
biology and Nitrogen and Phosphorus
cycling can be found in the book
Fecal Sludge Management.
Biology is also very important in
managing pathogens.
As these disease causing organisms
are also biological.
It's important to have an
understanding of all of the
interrelated ways to reduce
pathogens during treatment.
As they can also affect the
performance of treatment technologies.
The main mechanisms of inactivation
that we're concerned with are:
Predation from other organisms.
Starvation as they run out of food.
Temperature, for example in
treatment processes like composting
thermophilic anaerobic digestion
or even Lime treatment.
UV in cases where light rays can
penetrate, such as the surface of
waste stabilization ponds. But not
in tanks and ponds where solids at
the surface are high enough to block
significant transmission of rays.
pH, or other chemical changes, as
most microorganisms thrive only
within a range of 2-3 pH units.
Time is important in processes
that have long retention times.
Like planted drying beds of up to
10 years.
Desiccation or dehydration.
For example, in processes like
palletizing that can get to 90%
dryness and could be combined with
time as storage or temperature as
external heat to achieve safe levels
of pathogen reduction.
Pathogens can also be reduced
through sorption. For example,  when
helminth eggs sorbed solids, then set
aloud in settling thickening tanks.
or remain with the sludge layer on
a drying bed.
OK, and finally chemical mechanisms.
Chemicals can be mixed with fecal
sludge to improve the performance
of other physical mechanisms.
Or to inactivate pathogens and
stabilize fecal sludge.
Examples include addition of
polymers or other conditioners to
increase the flocculation and
settling efficiency
Anemonia or Lime to increase
pathogene reduction.
Both types of chemical reactions
are covered in more detail in other
modules.
So, in summary, in this module
you learned about physical,
biological and chemical mechanisms
that occur in treatment processes.
And about treatment mechanisms
that are occurring during these
four treatment objectives for fecal
sludge. Solid-liquid separation,
stabilization, nutrient management
and pathogen reduction.
Thanks for joining! See you
next time!