Imagine you and your family had a
peanut farm.
What would you do with the peanuts?
Peanuts can be roasted and eaten,
used to make oil, butter or flour
or even used in industrial
products like paint, oil, soap
or cellulose for paper. Would you
sell the products raw?
At the local market? To an
industrial manufacturer?
Would you invest in machinery to
refine them yourselves?
One thing you probably do know,
is if you wanted advice on how to
make this decision, would you seek
out a sanitary engineer?
Probably not.
Following this module, you will
find out how you could answer those
type of questions for the products
from fecal sludge management.
At the end of the module, you'll
be able to explain how to implement
market driven approach and
understand how this kind of tool
fits into an integrated engineering
design approach.
We wanna to know more about markets
for products that could be made from
treated fecal sludge. Realizing that
we're engineers, we consulted
experts in merging markets,
financial models and business
development to develop a method
for the quantitative evaluation
of potential products resulting from
the treatment of fecal sludge.
This method is called the market
driven approach.
And the developed manual and
calculation tool can be downloaded
from our website. The manual
contains all supporting info
for the implementation of this
method.
In the absence of clear legal
frameworks for fecal sludge
treatment products, identifying the
greatest market attractiveness
provides a method to help select
products of treatment.
Once treatment products are
identified, then treatment
performance goals can be defined for
safe end use to ensure protection
of public and environmental health.
In addition to greatest potential
to generate revenue, this can also
help ensure the design of adequate
treatment, and promote sustainable
operation as plant managers have
to meet customer demand.
In a market driven approach, market
attractiveness takes into account
both the current market volume and a
future for potential market growth.
Market volume is defined as the sum
of the value of all available
products in a given market. For
example, for animal feed that
would be the price and number of
units sold in a defined geographical
area. Market growth is defined as
the growth of the type of product
over a specified period. As this
cannot yet be determined,
the historical growth of a product
can be extrapolated to estimate
future growth.
A major difficulty with determining
market attractiveness of fecal
sludge treatment products is that
due to the general luck of fecal
sludge treatment products don't yet
exist. And, hence, the markets for
them also do not exist. To deal with
this, we use proxies, they can help
us to estimate market variables.
To do this, we're no longer thinking
as engineers, and we're not thinking
about what type of treatment
technologies we would use.
First, we focus on the type of
resource recovery that can be
achieved. Energy, food, material
nutrients, or water.
Then we think about what type of
products could fill that resource
need. For example, solid fuels vs
liquid fuels. Or soil conditioners
vs fertilizers. Then we think of the
form that treatment products could
take to fill that need. For example,
animal feed could be produced
by black soldier fly larvae,
fish from aquaculture, or
plants from drying beds.
Maybe that all sounds a bit
abstract. So, let's look at a real
life example from Kampala, Uganda
to understand a bit more how this
method can be implemented.
The first step is to review the
list of fecal sludge treatment
products.
From this list we want to decide
what treatment products are actually
relevant for our city. In Kampala,
all these products could potentially
be produced from treatment of
fecal sludge.
The second step is defining the
product application.
Ask yourself, where can these
products be used?
In which industry? Or is it used on
a household level?
Then list each application. For
example, In Kampala, the product
solid fuel is used for cooking and
households and is also used to
feed in the brick factories.
The third step is defining products
that are currently used.
Because faecal sludge treatment
products do not exist yet,
we cannot identify their market
volume directly. So, for example,
as a solid fuel in Kampala, currently
charcoal, firewood, coffee husks
are used. These are substitute
products that could be replaced by
dried faecal sludge.
In the forth step we calculate the
current market volume for each
substitute product. To do this, we
review literature and conduct
interviews. So, to calculate the
market volume, you could have
the average price per product times
the number of product sold in a city.
Alternatively, you could have the
average price per products
times the number of products
sold by suppliers times the number
of suppliers in the city. In Kampala
the market volume for charcoal was
found to be approximately
73 million.
You typically cannot calculate in
exact number, but this method
can give you a reasonable estimation
with the aim to be as accurate as
possible with further crosschecking.
The fifth step is assessing the
market growth for each substitute
product. In some cases, there are
trend forecasts available.
In others, it's estimated by
extrapolation from previous years
together with interviews. At the
time of our implementation the
estimated marked growth of charcoal
in Kampala was 9 %.
In the final steps we compare the
market volume and the market growth
or each product. By combining
market volume and market growth
we can make a judgement as to
which product has the highest
market potential or market
attractiveness.
Each substitute product identified
in step 3 is here.
The higher the combined market
growth and market volume,
the greater the market
attractiveness is.
In Kampala, the market for solid
fuel is very large and growing
rapidly compared to other treatment
products.
So, you could conclude, that faecal
sludge as a solid fuel has
the greatest market attractiveness.
in this case, charcoal release stands
out. This indicates that charcoal as
a treatment and product would be
a suitable choice.
So, now that you know how to
evaluate market attractiveness
a faecal sludge treatment products,
how can you use that information?
Just like your peanut farm, what is
important to remember is that
this information cannot be used in
isolation.
It needs to be incorporated into a
comprehensive design approach
for selection of treatment
technologies to help make
intelligent design decisions. With
the number 1 goal always of
protecting public health.
The engineering design approach is
not only about resource recovery.
So, you have to take this information
from the financial perspective of a
resource recovery. As just one tool
in a whole process.
Consider it with other factors.
Such as local laws and regulations
availability of financial resources,
human capacity, land area available
for treatment technologies and
the faecal sludge quantities and
characteristics that will be coming
into treatment facilities.
All of these are discussed in more
detail in other modules.
The social and cultural acceptance
of treatment products is already
incorporated as part of the
methodology. To further understand
the market driven approach we
recommend that you download it
from our website and review it.
So, in summary, in this module
you learned about the market driven
approach. How it was developed from
economic perspective. And how it
fits into an integrated design
approach. Thank you for joining!
See you next time.