Hello, and welcome to this module
on faecal sludge management planning.
If you're in charge
of putting in place
a faecal sludge management system
in a city like this,
what should you do?
Where do you start?
In this module, we will see
how to start
and how the different activities
fit together.
In the two next modules,
we will then look
at the assessment
of the initial situation
and how to analyze and engage
the stakeholders in the planning process.
Later, the institutional, financial
and management aspects
will be reviewed in more depth.
You may know me from our MOOC
on sanitation planning.
My name is Philippe Reymond
and I'm working at (INAUDIBLE)
on the planning side of sanitation,
looking at which systems
are best appropriate for which context
and the necessary conditions
for successful sanitation
projects and programs.
In this module, I will explain
what is an integrated planning approach
why you should follow
a participatory process
and how it can fit
in the whole planning.
And finally,
how the different activities
can be molded
into a coherent planning process.
Cities in low-
and middle-income countries
are often highly heterogeneous.
Roughly, we can distinguish
between middle-
and high-income settlements.
informal settlements
and the peri-urban interface.
We can add
to these three categories
the newly-planned urban areas.
Sometimes, the different contexts
are clearly separated
in large neighborhoods.
But sometimes,
they are also more scattered,
like some pockets.
Each context may require
different sanitation solutions.
Often, when you arrive
in a city,
the city center is served
by a sewer network.
The main question is then
what to do
with the area surrounding
the city center?
Shall we try to connect them
to the sewer network?
Or shall we keep
on-site sanitation systems
and plan for proper
faecal sludge management?
Or maybe you would prefer alternatives,
such as decentralized sewer systems.
So, what's an integrated
planning approach?
First of all, it means planning for
the whole sanitation supply chain.
as demonstrated behind me
from the latrine to (INAUDIBLE) disposal.
Too many projects have failed
because they only considered
one component, typically latrines.
You may recognize on this drawing
the colors representing
the functional groups of the compendium.
If you want to learn more
about this system approach sanitation,
I would recommend you
to have a look at this book,
or follow our MOOC
on sanitation planning.
An integrated planning approach
means also to have a holistic view
where technology
is just one component,
as shown in this figure.
A view that takes into account
the different socioeconomic context,
people's aspirations
or the available financial resources,
skills and management capacities.
We need to understand
each area of a city
with its specificities
and then see how all can fit together
under one roof.
All the elements I just mentioned
build what we call
the enabling environment.
The enabling environment
is a set of conditions
that make your scheme work.
As you can see, you need support
from the government,
the proper legal
and regulatory framework.
You need institutional arrangements,
you need to check
the available skills and capacities,
define financial arrangements,
and see if your proposal
is socially and culturally accepted.
This is a kind of checklist
for you to identify the gaps
and see how they can be filled.
How would a situation look like
in your city?
Let's start to plan.
You know the project cycle.
First, you may have
an exploratory study,
which we could also call
the process ignition.
Then, you have the preliminary
or pre-feasibility studies
where the detailed assessment
of the initial situation takes place.
After that,
we have the feasibility study,
where the main tasks
are the identification
of service options.
And once the options are selected,
you move to the detailed
project development,
which finally opens
the way to implementation.
So now the question is
where do we fit
all the necessary activities?
Clearly, every context is different,
and where you start off
will vary from place to place.
In the faecal sludge management book
and in your course materials,
you will find this figure
called "FSM from A to Z".
There, we listed all the activities
to be carried out
from the quantification
and characterization of sludge,
to the involvement of stakeholders,
and fit them
into each planning step.
These activities often take place
in parallel.
What is important
is that at the end of each phase,
you have all the information
you need
and that  you have the stakeholders
on board.
Let's take a closer look.
On the left side, as you can see,
you have the standard project phases.
In the middle,
we detail the activities.
to be done in each phase,
as well as the main outcomes.
Each activity is linked
to the respective chapters
in the book.
On the right side,
we show how these different activities
fit into two of the main
participatory planning frameworks.
Clues, which is the planning guideline
for community and neighborhood level.
And Sanitation 21,
which is the planning framework
at city level, endorsed by
the International Water Association, IWA.
The key participatory activities
in the process
are highlighted, as you can see here
with initial launching workshop.
All these activities
can be embedded
in any planning framework
or terms  of reference.
Experience shows that
participation of the stakeholders
is crucial for the success
of sanitation projects and programs.
In order to be able to lead
a successful planning process,
you often need to create
a city sanitation task force.
That is a way to have
all the main stakeholders on board
and to avoid blockages
during the process.
You will learn more in the modules
on stakeholder analysis and engagement.
and institutional arrangements.
For now, please try to identify
the activities related
to participation
in the "FSM from A to Z" synthesis.
Remember that the main goal
of the exercise
is to reach, together,
a city sanitation plan
or an action plan that can be funded
and that can be implemented
without problems.
For that, you need to engage
the stakeholders
to understand their needs
and constraints
and, in the end, to be able
to define a design
clear roles and responsibilities,
with a clear commitment from them.
In this module,
you were introduced
to the importance of adopting
an integrated planning approach
which includes considering
the entire sanitation supply chain,
then taking into account
all the elements
of the enabling environment.
We saw a proposal of how
to translate this approach
into the planning process.
The FSM planning from A to Z,
which I really recommend you
to have a closer look at.
Finally, we underlined importance
to adopt a participatory approach.
In the next module, I will describe
in more detail
how to conduct an assessment
of the initial situation.
See you then.