What do you think is special
about the flame on this cookstove?
It's filled by biogas
from the anaerobic digestion
of faecal  sludge.
Following this module
you will be able to discuss
methane potential of faecal sludge,
understand concerns
with centralized treatment.
and about the design overview
of digesters.
This module focuses
on possible applications
of anaerobic digestion
of faecal sludge.
It does not go into depth
on types of technologies,
other types of anaerobic treatment
or the fundamental science
as that has been covered thoroughly
in many other publications.
If you would like to learn more
about this topic
I would recommend starting with
the anaerobic digestion modules
in the third week
of the Sandec MOOC
on municipal solid waste,
the Sandec publication
on anaerobic digestion
and basic engineering textbook
on wastewater treatment.
There's not been a lot of research
or implementation
of the anaerobic digestion
of faecal sludge
compared to other more
well established technologies.
So what are the possibilities?
Let's start with methane potential,
the amount of methane produced
per gram of COD
which will depend on the level
of stabilization of the sludge.
So what does this mean
for faecal sludge?
Well, we cannot say conclusively
because there are not a lot of results
for methane potential
of different types of faecal sludge.
But intuitively, one would guess
that fresh sludge
with very short retention times
in containment,
like many public toilets
or restaurants.
would have higher methane potential
than sludge that has been sitting
in a septic tank
for ten years,
undergoing digestion.
These preliminary results
from researchers
at Cranfield University
show the results
of biomethane potential
from 11 pit latrines,
two public toilets
and ten portable
or container-based toilets
compared to primary
wastewater sludge.
They seem to indicate
that our intuition is correct
but based on that
we also would've predicted
the public ablution blocks
would've had
higher methane potential.
This highlights the need
for further research
and also more results
to confirm
whether results are
due to factors
such as the seed
that was used for the test.
This graph show the variability
of methane potential
just from the pit latrine samples
used in the study.
This is also not surprising
since we know that faecal sludge
is highly variable.
It also illustrates the need
for further research
if we are to better understand
the methane potential
of faecal sludge.
So what does this mean
for the anaerobic digestion
of faecal sludge?
I'm going to make a division
of three levels of implementation
based on the scale,
the degree of centralization,
the required management level
and operational skill.
A high level
for all of these categories
is centralized,
like digesters
that are commonly found
at large centralized
wastewater treatment plants
for the digestion
of wastewater sludge.
Medium is community scale.
Reactors that
are not fully optimized
for operational parameters
and treatment performance,
so require less operation
and capacity.
And low are
household-level systems
that are seen in rural areas,
which are small, passive systems
mainly treating manure
and food waste
with some co-treatment
of faecal sludge.
There are millions
of implementations
in India and China
with mixed results
when applied in other areas.
I'm not going to cover
household examples
in this module
as it's not relevant
for our focus
on dense urban areas.
So what about the possibility
of operating
large centralized
anaerobic digesters
for faecal sludge?
Well, it hasn't been done before,
but to evaluate the feasibility
one of the first questions is
will there be enough
methane potential?
These are some basic considerations
for designing an anaerobic digester.
First, you know
the temperature
at the ambient air.
Then you have your reactor
and you know the temperature
you want to operate
the reactor at.
For example, mesophilic.
You can also then select
your solid's retention time
based on your treatment
objectives.
You know your lodines.
What's gonna be coming
into the reactor.
The total solids concentration
and mass loading of the sludge.
You also know
the degradability of the sludge.
Based on this,
then you can calculate
the reactor volume
and you can also calculate
the amount of biogas
that will be produced, including
the methane concentrations.
You can then evaluate
whether or not
the methane that's produced
is going to be adequate
to generate heat
to bring the reactor
up to the necessary
operating temperature.
The problem is, we don't,
with faecal sludge
have reliable data
for the degradability.
The temperature is critical
as it affects the growth
of methanogenic bacteria.
At lower operating temperatures
you need much longer retention times
or they cannot grow in the reactor.
They will be washed out
and you will not get treatment.
Primary wastewater sludge is
around 75% to 85% degradable.
And secondary sludge,
around 70% to 80%.
If the sludge is not
degradable enough
there will not be enough methane
production to heat the reactor.
This is even more of a concern
if you want to operate
at thermophilic temperatures
for pathogen reduction.
Required temperatures and SRTs
for digesting a faecal sludge
are questions
that need further research.
An additional problem
that is just as difficult
is that anaerobic digestion is
easily upset.
And as we know, faecal sludge
is highly variable.
What are things
that can upset a reactor?
Toxics, like nickel or zinc,
phenolic compounds
or even high concentrations
of free ammonia.
PH, a build-up
of volatile fatty acids,
fats oils and grease,
and shock loadings
resulting in a rapid change
of the digester contents.
If a large scale
centralized reactor is upset,
it is a management nightmare.
Potentially what all of this means
for the anaerobic digestions
of faecal sludge
at a centralized scale
is that it could only be applied
with codigestion
with other organic waste streams
that are more degradable.
And in small concentrations
relative to the other organics
to dampen the variability
of faecal sludge going into a reactor.
Examples could be brewery wastes,
spent grain,
market waste,
or even wastewater sludge.
Community-scale digester
are easier to operate
because they are not
optimized for space,
temperature, gas production,
or treatment capacity,
but provide an option that is
potentially better septic tanks
or other types
of anaerobic treatment
as they are designed to capture
biogas for resource recovery
and reduce greenhouse emissions.
CDD and BORDA have implemented
community-scale systems
in India, Nepal and Tanzania.
There are not yet enough
operational results
for detailed design recommendations,
but hey have been sized
up to a maximum
of a 6 meter diameter,
based on solids concentrations
collection capacity
and frequency of emptiers.
Solids and hydraulics
retention times
are requirements for affluent
and solids treatments.
This is the schematic
for an anaerobic digester
built and operated by BORDA
in the Mlalakua area
of Dar es Salaam, Tanzania.
The capacity of the plan
was based on estimations
from operating a similar reactor
in the Kigamboni neighborhood
with the collection and transport
of faecal sludge for the community,
as shown here.
The size of the digester
was also based
on the available land area
and the desired
complexity of operation
so that it could operate
at a community scale.
The resulting design capacity is
five cubic meters a day
or what is thought to be
twenty thousand
population equivalents.
This is the access road.
First, there is 30 square meters
for receiving station
for the trucks to discharge,
then there is another
five square meters
for the screening of the sludge.
The dome is constructed to be
50 cubic meters
with the expansion chamber,
another 21 cubic meters.
The liquid from the reactor
then goes to an anaerobic filter.
The sludge goes here
to drying beds
which take up another
55 square meters.
And then, the liquid
from the drying beds
and the anaerobic filters
goes here
to a banana plantation.
which takes up another
170 square meters.
Here are some pictures
of what it looks like.
The gate coming
into the facility.
The receiving bay.
Bar screen cover up the dome
and expansion chamber.
The covered drying beds
and the banana plantation.
For more information,  please refer
to the CDD and BORDA websites
and this biogas curriculum,
a tool for trainers to train
masons and technicians
on the complexities of the gas-tight
construction of digesters.
In summary,
benefits of anaerobic digestion
include reduced sludge
and required footprint
compared to aerobic treatment,
reduces methane and sludge
for resource recovery,
it can destroy pathogens depending
on the operating conditions.
And drawbacks include
that the process is easily upset.
It operates best at controlled
and consistent conditions
and it requires knowledge
and skill for operation.
In this module we learned about
the methane potential
of faecal sludge, and the design
and operating concerns
with centralized
and decentralised treatment.
Thanks for joining.
See you next time.