Hello, we've already talked about
the functions, today we will
go into details, to better clarify the
writing conventions, the difference
between define and functions, speak
of the internal execution and
see the different types of functions.
Concerning the rules of writing,
the habit is to have
the constants in uppercase, and
we have already seen OUTPUT, HIGH,
I do not really respect
this Convention, since, with
explicit names,
it's pretty heavy as a writing.
The variables, the rule is to have
the lower case, we already saw the
I in the for loops, counter, max level,
some prefer to put underlines,
it's up to you
to decide. On the definition side,
we have a first
letter that is capitalized,
and the definitions apply
to the hardware. On the functions side,
there are also
capital letters in
the first position, but they
are, a function that will designate
an action.
So here I insist, and I will insist,
the definitions are
concerning the hardware,
the functions concerns the functionality.
And, in some languages,
there is a subtle difference between
procedures and functions, C,
does not make that difference.
So, I come back again:
define to describe the material,
function for functionality,
I take an example, with a simple robot.
This simple robot has two engines,
if you look
at the rear of the engine,
where the wires leave, you have a plus
and a minus, and
if you send the current on
the plus, all the engines of
the same manufacturer, will turn in
the same direction.
So I define here, the plus of my
motor, will be on pin 4,
the minus on pin 3.
And now, for the engine
to advance, that is for
this motor to rotate in the direction
that will advance the robot,
I must put on fuse 4 a 0, on fuse 3,
a 1.
And this will not be accepted
by the compiler,
since, I did not put capital letters
as it is recognized.
So now I will define the same thing
for the left engine, but the left engine,
for it to move, I will have to swap
here, these two definitions,
the motors are symmetrical.
So on the right engine,
If the positive fuse must be at 0,
well, on the left engine, the
positive fuse will have to be at 1.
Then, you can grope, and then get out
the soldering iron, to move the wires,
but see that if we think well,
we will have something that is,
correct, that will react according to the
definition of the material.
And now if we want to move the
robot, and well there is an action,
which requires to have both engines
that are advancing, we have
defined what made them advance,
There is no need to worry
about the wiring and the hardware.
So now we can add a function
that is to make a
round trip, with a certain duration
that will fix the distance of travel.
Let's continue,
we wait, we move back,
we wait, the duration being
a parameter of this function.
And in the main program,
and well, we're going to have,
make a round-trip,
the duration of action, and of course,
it is a quite simplified case,
which clearly shows
the hierarchy of functions.
What we have just done
is descending programming,
we started from the material
to go towards complexity.
In real cases, one is concerned first,
of the application, its specifications, the
structure of the main program,
system calls
that we will use, which themselves,
will make calls to
simpler functions,
which will rely on the hardware,
therefore, top-down, or bottom-up,
these are the two options.
How does it work internally?
The program has been stored in memory, and
You have an address counter,
the PC, which points
the instruction that will be executed.
This address counter increases each
time the instruction has been executed,
and during execution
of the program, we will refer
to the arithmetic unit,
we'll access the variables to do
the function that interests you.
You come across an instruction
that will allow
you to make a loop, in assembler
it is called Jump, Jump A1.
The effect of this instruction, well,
it will be to copy the value A1 which
is found in the instruction in the PC,
which will return to
the address 3A1, to re-execute the loop.
Well, now, if we have a function call,
it's a little different,
the instruction is Call
in assembler, and at the memory,
the compiler
reserved a place for the functions,
following the program.
So we have the program, it continues with
the functions, and I call
the first function which is in 7,1F,
so the PC will be loaded by
the 3F instruction, so it will continue
its execution, in 7, 1F.
And now, what is important is
to return to the main program,
in assembler, it is
the instruction Return, Ret,
which is used, and
at this moment, how do you know
where to go?
So there is a small additional
operation characteristic of Call,
which is to save in the PC the return address,
which will be 3A2, the next address.
The PC increases as soon as
it has read the instruction, so we
saved the instruction that would have
been executed if it was not a Call.
And, the Return instruction,
will have the effect of
SavePC in the PC
and the execution will continue.
So now, in every function, you may need
variables, and here you may
need to use variable i,
which will occupy this position.
You can have here
another function, which will also
need a variable counter that I call j,
which I call k, which I could call i.
Why reserve another memory location,
a new memory position, in each function?
At the moment of access here,
this variable j,
we could very well access
the same memory position, which had
been used by another function,
since it will not run at the same time.
Thus, we distinguish between local variables,
and global variables that are
used by the program, defined
at the beginning of the program,
while the local variables are defined
at the beginning of the functions.
And now what is still happening is that
when you call a function,
for example, the delay function,
there is a parameter,
which is the duration of the delay,
which has been prepared in
the program and thus the function
will need.
Then, this parameter can be transferred
as a global variable, it can be
transferred as a local variable,
but, the parameter we put
in a function, we will save it with
the return address, in what is called,
the stack, in the background.
And this stack, with the address counter,
that is what is being prepared,
at the moment of the function call,
so that the function
can work with this data set
and return to the program,
possibly with the addition of data.
So let's take examples,
starting with the simplest things.
You have the function
"Blink once", you call it by,
Blink once, there are no
parameters that will be transferred,
on the stack, the parenthesis is empty.
You have the function BlinkXtimes,
there you have a parameter
and it is necessary to say what will be
the name of this parameter, but it is a local name,
it's a name used only in that.
On the other hand, it was necessary
to specify the size to be reserved in the
Stack, to transfer this parameter,
and, when we call, and
well, we have blinked so many times,
the parameter one constant or one
variable, but, of type byte,
if we put a number too big here,
the compiler should grumble.
Then you can have two parameters,
which do not necessarily have the
same type, want to blink x times,
with a certain period.
We'll give the byte type for the number of
times, the byte type for the period,
and we will have both parameters.
And we can test now, this program,
we must always test the
functions when they were written,
with a small loop,
we blink three times, and then
we do nothing.
If you delete this while, what happens?
You blink three times, blink three times, blink
three times, you feel
that your program is wrong.
A delay must be added here,
so that after each
blinking three times, well,
you have a space that allows you to
verify the start of the function call.
So now we can have
an output parameter, that is, the
function has prepared, has calculated a value
that must return to the main program.
And, it will be necessary to reserve space
in memory, to say what is the result, and
there may be local variables
that need to be declared.
So an example to illustrate things,
here I rely on
something we had already seen,
read the pushbutton, read a pushbutton.
One can make a function of it, what we read is
Activated pushbutton, inactivated,
it is actually a Boolean variable. It can
be written like that, even if it's not usual.
And then this function, will make
the state of the pusher,
pressed or not pressed, and,
it is the return statement,
in the background, that allows
to point out this fact.
So if we had a function
a bit more complex here,
and well, we could define a
boolean variable, statePush
to describe the state
of the Pusher,
it is the state of our pusher with
the digitalRead, and
I will return the variable that
has been declared. So this is where
you should see it clearly,
we reserved space,for something
that will be returned
that will be of the same
Boolean type, and, as can
be stated, we can declare a
variable that will be returned,
which must be, of course, of the same type.
At the call level, well, we write
if Push On, parentheses,
since we did not send parameters,
but you remember the define, with
the define, this parenthesis isn't there,
the behavior will be exactly
the same, so when you call
the actions, you have to
know whether they were defined
by a define, or by a function.
Here, I took a Boolean example which is a
little unusual, but it was
so that we would cling to
something known. The example
that is explained to you very
often, is the multiplication,
where you are told: you
want to multiply two numbers a, b,
and then it will
give a result; Then, you need to
naturally define a equal 3, b equal 4,
and say
what are their types. So
these are global variables, and
so now, at the time of
the call for multiplication, well,
it will be necessary
to repeat this type. And now I can
return this value, by writing
return, a times b; but
I need to warn
the compiler, to reserve space, for this
value a times b. So we're going
to put here, the whole type,
and here is a function
that will pass in its most simplest form.
If now I want to
introduce a variable, and
I say, I will, define that the product is a
variable of type c, I will calculate c equal
at times b, and I will return
the result c, and finish my
function. Well, we have seen how
a function is run and we highlighted,
the importance of defining
clear names, in French, English,
in a mixture, I think it is very difficult
to define clear names.
So we can now use
the functions in our next examples.