Hello!
It is clear that microcontrollers are ideal
for carrying out automation tasks.
In the French-speaking world,
when we talk about automatism,
we always talk about Grafcet.
And then, often my students tell me,
"Oh, if I want to do a Grafcet,
then I have to buy
a programmable controller."
Et bien pas du tout !
The Grafcet, it is quite as
possible to program them,
and that is what we are going to do today.
So, I will not repeat the Grafcet theory,
it would be too long.
I will just give a few reminders
that will help us for what we have to do.
Then we will see how to program
in C a Grafcet?
And of course we will apply
it to the example we
see for the fourth time,
the famous example of the drill
that goes down and goes up.
Then you recognize here
an example of Grafcet.
Compared to the state graph we used,
there are a number of differences
that are details:
The stages of the Grafcet
are what were called stages:
The initial step,
the initial steps, we will see why.
Transitions are the same
as in state graphs.
We speak of receptivity,
it corresponds to the condition
linked to a transition.
We may have divergences in OR,
this is the case here.
This is the same as in state graphs.
From this stage, we can
arrive at that one
or arrive at that one
according to whether this transition
or this transition will be crossed.
However,
the divergences in AND
are some things that do not exist
not in the state graphs.
Here, if this condition
if this transition is crossed,
we will activate both
this step
and this step.
This means that you can have
two or more active steps
at the same time.
While in a state graph,
one and only one state
was always active at a given time.
This generalization is
extremely interesting,
extremely powerful,
it is in a way the multitasking
of automatism.
So let's start writing our program in C:
We will define
the number of steps
we will have in our Grafcet or the maximum
number, the number of
transitions that will appear
in such a way that we can create
a table that s 'Calls Steps
and a second table called Transitions.
In fact, these 2 arrays will contain
Boolean values
thus considered as True or False.
If a step is active,
the corresponding value will be true.
If it is inactive,
it will be false therefore equal to 0.
The same for transitions
If a transition can be crossed
then the value that is in this table
will be true.
As in all programs,
there will be a procedure of initialization
of the inputs and outputs.
I will not go into details,
it will obviously depend on
the processor used.
We have a procedure here
that allows to read
The inputs, the set of inputs.
The idea is at one point,
to read
all entries, one and only once.
Then,
We will be able to look
at the logical conditions
on these inputs
on which the transitions depend.
But if we did several readings,
we could have inconsistencies
so it is extremely important
to have a variable
that will contain
the value of the input
read at the beginning of the procedure.
I look at the main program:
Initialization of inputs and outputs.
Initialization of the steps:
they will all be inactive
except the step (s),
here perhaps the first,
which will be activated.
But I remind you, there could
be several initial steps.
The principle of the Grafcet
allows to have several
active steps at the same time.
Then we have an infinite loop
that will repeat these procedures.
First thing: I affect the outputs.
Like the first time, I already
have at least one active step.
I can, according to
the active steps from where active steps,
affect the outputs correctly.
I remind you that
the output values depend only
on the step or the active steps.
then,
We will perform this procedure
which binds the inputs
and which stores in these variables
the values of the inputs.
And then, we go successively,
calculate the transitions:
are they crossable?
Next,we will deactivate the steps
for which a transition
passable
justify deactivating it
and activate the steps
that are the result of the
transition transition.
This is the very principle
of the Grafcet,
it is the rules of evolution
of the Grafcet.
You find this principle in all...
the documents that describe
what a Grafcet is.
So I go back to the details
on these few procedures.
The one that calculates the transitions,
it will be necessary to look
for a given transition,
of which stage it depends?
At what stage is it connected
up, up, upstream?
It is necessary apply the receptivity,
we must make the logical AND
of these 2 conditions
And it is memorized whether this
transition can be crossed.
Then for the deactivation,
again, it will be necessary to look at
the Grafcet
and to look that if this transition
can be crossed
then this stage must be deactivated.
And in the same way,
if this transition can be crossed,
at what stage, what next step
must be activated?
And finally, assign the outputs
according to the step that is active.
If this step,
and it will be done for the following ones
is also active,
then  we write
the output values
according to the definition of the step.
Perhaps an example, where we
will facilitate understanding.
Our drill,
I hope you remember,
we had described it by a graph of states:
Stop, descent, climb,
three transitions.
Let us design a perfectly
equivalent Grafcet:
Stop, descent, climb.
Transitions with Start receptivities,
bottom and top
And for each of the steps,
the output values:
Advance is activated,
that's what we have there.
Backspace is activated, that's
what we have there.
So let's look at how we can write
this program for the drill.
Our variables: steps and transitions,
the names of the steps
that will also be the
indices with the enum,
the variables in which
the entries will be stored,
it is precisely in this procedure
that these variables are read.
For the calculation of the transitions:
for each of the transitions,
we will look at
what is the previous step?
What is receptivity?
Logical AND
is set and the value is stored.
Here, the stop
corresponds to Start.
When we're going downhill,
it's low we'll wait.
When we are climbing,
it is Haut that we will wait.
We will then be able to deactivate the steps
which can be crossed.
If this transition can be crossed,
So
then the previous step is deactivated,
in the same way for the other transitions.
Similarly, we will activate
the steps that must
always be in function of the transition.
And here, we go downhill,
uphill and off.
And finally the procedure Affects Outputs
will simply take into account
the different values.
I have to write the Advance
downhill
value and the Retreat uphill value.
We finally have the main program
that looks the same as
what we had earlier.
Initialization,
resetting, inactivating all the steps,
activating the first step
and this loop which continuously
performs these procedures:
Assign outputs, read inputs,
calculate transitions,
disable steps that have been crossed,
activate the following steps.
So, you might tell me it's
very complicated
for this program
of the drill that we managed
to write infinitely simpler.
True, for a simple Grafcet,
it's too complicated
And for a complicated Grafcet,
it's going to be much simpler,
because the method,it is systematic.
We take care of the stages,
we take care of the transitions,
we take care of the entrances,
we take care of the outings.
Once we've done everything,
it works the first time
if we do not make mistakes.
It is often necessary to
add timers
in the Grafcet.
And our system lends
itself perfectly to it.
It will suffice to add a delay
in the main loop.
You remember, we have done that
on several occasions.
For example, 1/100th of seconds.
and then
In the main loop for each Timer
that has been initialized
at the beginning of 0,
we will write
if the Timer is greater than 0
then it is decremented.
So it is necessary to understand that at
the moment when one enters for example
in a step
which requires a Timer,
the timer is initialized
with the right value
and then it will suffice
to test if it is equal to 0
to know if the time in question
has been expired.
When we have several Timers,
we will proceed in the same way
with a Timers array
that is initialized to 0
for the number of Timers we have planned
And in the main loop,
again for each Timers,
we will test s 'they are greater than 0
and decrement if this is the case..
Here is the Delay, waiting
for 1 / 100th of seconds
from the main loop.
And for example, for the
calculation of a transition,
we can add if Timer number 3 is equal to 0
then we will do this or that.
So I wanted to show
you that it is possible
to program Grafcet with a microcontroller.
With the habit, it is not complicated
and sometimes it is much cheaper
than buying a PLC.