Hello, the environment Arduino,
should be recognized, is great to start
with microcontrollers, it's simple
to use, it's convenient.
However, when you have a little
bit more experience, you
often want to go to programs
written entirely in C.
And then, there are a few
difficulties I would like
to try to explain today.
First of all, I would like to remind
that the word Arduino actually
has three
quite different meanings:
Firstly, it is a question of
a microcontroller card, you know it well.
Secondly, this is a programming environment;
besides there are other
environments similar to
the Arduino environment
for other microcontrollers.
Today we will use the environment
Energia for MSP 430 processors.
And the third meaning of the word
Arduino is the Arduino bookstores,
they are the calls, the functions,
the procedures that are in the
Arduino library that you know well,
such as Pin Mode, such as
Digital Read, Digital Write and is
sometimes called the Arduino language.
So let's look at the simplest program
which has already been used several times.
So you know this program well,
that's how it is written,
there is the Setup procedure
which initializes the output tab, and
successively in the loop
a Digital write to turn on the LED,
an expectation, a digital write to
turn off the LED and wait.
I will keep the essence of this program
so that we can see what is going on.
We will compile it, then
we will run, more exactly,
upload it, and you can see
that the small lamp is flashing.
You know that we do not like writing
programs in this way,
which, moreover, require
comments, because it is not easy to
understand what this digital
write corresponds to.
We prefer this way of writing
where we define Led1On with its digital
write, and inside the program
just call this definition.
And you see that I even removed the
comments which, in my opinion,
are no longer truly useful.
The program, of course,
works in the same way.
I suggest you start by editing a little bit
this program to make it
a little more complicated.
We add here the reading
of the push-button of such
So that the flashing can
start by pressing the button.
So, naively, I initiated the
leg of the push button in input,
I made a digital read
of this, this paw, and you will see
that the program does not work.
The lamp is on, I press the button,
nothing happens, if I stroke
the legs here, things happen,
it's really quite mysterious.
So of course, we know what it is,
we have to modify the program in this
way: I put here INPUT_PULLUP
for the utilization mode
of the push-button, in such
a way that there is thus this resistance
which gives a steady state
when the button is not pressed.
I have also benefited
from correctly defining the call
Push 1 On and I also added
the inversion of this digital read reading
in such a way that when
The button is pressed and
therefore has a logical zero state
The input which is given by the wiring,
one obtains a true condition so
that it may have a meaning.
And this time, the program should work.
We see that when I press
the button, it actually starts to flash.
Let's try to replace all these calls
Pin mode, Digital read,
Digital write by direct access
to the microcontroller register.
We see here that we have defined the bits in port one,
for the led on the one hand, for
the pushbutton on the other hand,
we defined Led on / Led off with a seven
bits on the corresponding bit, with a clear
bit on the corresponding bit, we
used P1 In playback with masking of the
bit of the push-button
for reading the push-button.
The main program, of course, does not change,
the main loop is completely identical to
that we had earlier, however,
the setup I acted directly on P1 Dir
to put the led out, I took advantage to turn
it off at the beginning of the program and
I also activated the pull-up resistance by
acting on P1REN and I indicated that it was
about a pull-up resistance, so pull-up
putting one in the corresponding
bit of P1OUT.
So this program should
work just like the other.
Let's see earlier we had 714 bytes for this
program, I compile it, we have now,
we will see it very
exactly at the time of uploading, only 410
bytes for a program that does
the same thing rigorously.
When the button is pressed,
the lamp lights up.
So we see that it is relatively interesting,
we gained space in memory.
Now, there would remain a final step,
to get rid of the setup and
loop and directly write
the main hand program.
Let's try to do it.
This is how this program could be presented,
with the hand that contains this
famous instruction for
the initialization of the watchdog
Timer, which was previously in the setup, an
while loop one,
and what was previously in the loop.
So we'll see if it works.
Then my lamp is off, it's a good
Sign, I press the button,
it lights up, but it does not flash.
Why?
Well, we made a serious mistake,
we forgot that the
Delay call was also a call unique to
the Arduino environment,
and for it to function
the Arduino environment
must initialize a certain
number of things, in this case timers,
and as we have written ourselves
the main routine, the hand,
these initializations
did not take place and
the program did not work.
Then we will have to rewrite
ourselves the, the delay procedure.
So here I called it MS wait as I used to
do it, but we understand
that it is the same functionality.
So we have this routine, so with
a volatile variable for it to be, hum.
that the loop, here central,
is actually executed
even when it is empty, which will take a
little time, and then my main program
here with these expectations,
and this time it should work.
I press the button, it flashes.
So do not fall into the trap
you have to choose.
Either you use the Arduino environment
and you use the setup and
loop, or you get free of
the Arduino environment,
you access directly the
processor registers, you write
the hand procedure and an infinite while loop one,
but then you no longer have
the right to use Arduino calls.