Hello!
We continue the course
"Understanding Micro-Controllers".
And today, we'll talk of
drawing resistances.
What is that odd word?
Maybe you already know
them under the name
Pull up resistor.
We will recall
the principle and the usefulness
of these pulling resistors.
We will then speak in more detail
pull up resistors which are integrated
in a large number of microcontrollers.
Then, we will look in more details
how it is implemented
on the AVR and on the MSP430.
Once is not a custom,
we will begin this lesson with a quiz.
You have this diagram.
It is very simple.
It seems to you perhaps
a little odd since this leg
is connected to nothing at all.
It's in the air.
Here, we simply
have an LED as we're used to using them.
The program therefore corresponds
in its set-up part
but the red LED
in output,
we are accustomed to this syntax.
In the main loop,
we have a variable
which is the value
which is read on the digitalRead
on the entry and underlined 3
and this same value val
is copied with a digital Read
on the light emitting diode.
So we have a program that constantly
copies the input to the output.
So my question:
with this setup and this program,
what will we see on the LED?
Do you think it will remain off ?
Do you think it will, for example,
be turned on?
Do you think it will rather
be flashing
or that it's condition will fluctuate?
And if for once
we let the material answer us?
Watch this short video.
So you notice the small wire
that is connected
on the input P1.3.
You notice that
to a certain number of things,
the light diode changes.
We feel there are movements.
These movements are seen
to be made by one hand.
See here my finger.
It approaches but does not touch
this small wire
and you see that the output changes
at a certain time.
Let's try to understand what happened.
We're using microcontrollers
which use C-MOS technology.
And the C-MOS have high-impedance inputs.
And therefore, an unconnected input
captures all kinds of parasites,
any kind of electromagnetic influences,
any kind of static charges,
even very small ones
Which will make it change state
in a way that seems a bit random.
It is therefore not possible to leave
an unconnected input.
It is essential to avoid
these entries in the air.
What solution can be proposed
to solve this problem?
What we are seeking is to diminish
the impedance of the system
and a resistor
which must be linked
to one of the power supplies
will ensure a known potential
at the moment when
the entrance is in the air.
Then, 2 diagrams are possible
since there are 2 feeds.
The solution with the pull-up
in English pull-up
and it can be seen that the resistor
is connected to the positive
power supply.
And the solution with the pull down,
pull-down in English.
It can be seen that
the resistor is connected
towards the 0 volt towards the ground.
In both cases,
between
a supply point
and the entrance of our system,
we have a resistance
which avoids this problem
of high input impedance
of our micro-controllers.
In fact, this technique is well known
to electronics technicians.
and it remains for us to ask
ourselves the question
is there
between these 2 pull-up
and pull-down solutions
one that is preferable to the other?
So,
right away, I will tell you
that the one that is most used
and by far, is the pull-up.
How can I justify the fact
that we should use a pull-up
rather than a pull-down?
Consider the simple case
of an end-of-travel switch
which is going to be at
a certain physical distance
of the electronic board
containing the micro-controller.
We thus have:
a push button
and this push-button must be connected
to our electronic card
with in this case
a connection to the input
and an earth connection.
In the other case,
we always have our push button.
We always have a connection
towards the entrance.
And this time, the second connection
must be towards the most.
Admitting
that this cable
or that this cable are relatively long cables
and that they move
along the frame of our machine,
which solution will we prefer?
Transfer the signal
and the positive voltage
or on the contrary transfer the signal
and the negative voltage,
that is, the earth.
And we prefer this solution
since generally the earth is actually
connected to the machine frame
and electronic technicians have the habit
of using this pattern.
Moreover, a number of microcontrollers
offer
built-in pull-up resistors
whereas they are more rare those that
offer both
a pull-up resistor or
a pull-down resistance.
Indeed,
many manufacturers incorporate
draft resistances directly
in micro-controllers.
The value of this resistance
is generally about 50 kOhm.
So we see here on this diagram
that the resistance is
not placed here on the outside
but is placed inside.
Of course,
it must not be permanently connected
and it will be necessary
to find a mechanism
to engage
or trigger
this pull resistance.
Unfortunately, there is not
a single method
to engage these pull resistors.
Each manufacturer
proposes a technique.
I will take the example for AVR processors
of the company Atmail.
I think you remember
this table.
We talked about it
when we talked about inputs and outputs.
You recall that
In the Dir register
for each leg,
the respective bit
is used either to
have an entry
when it is at 0,
either to have an output
when it is at 1.
In this case, it is the OUT register
which allows the output to be set to 0
and set the output to 1.
On the other hand, it should
be noted that these two lines
are the same
and whether the OUT is 0 or 1,
when the Dir is 0
does not really matter.
And some manufacturers
have just had the idea
to distinguish
these two cases by saying
in the case where DDR is at 0,
if PORT is at 0,
then this is a normal input
with high impedance.
On the other hand, if PORT is 1,
always with DDR
which is at 0,
then, we move to an entry
with pull-up.
To make it extremely easy
to trigger the input,
it will suffice to activate
the corresponding bit
of the port
as long as
we have the DDR (INAUDIBLE) at  0.
I remind you that on the Atmail,
the direction PORT is called DDR
(Data Direction Register)
and the output PORT is simply called PORT
so we would have
for example
D-D-R B
if it is PORT B
and then PORT B
correspondent
I could have shown you the internal diagram
of the AVRs.
It is very complicated
but we still recognize it here
this pull resistance.
It is seen that it is operated
by a transistor
and connected at most.
So we have a pull-up resistance
which can be interlocked.
Here,
we have an inverter that matches
to the inversion
of this transistor.
Here, then, we have a logical function,
a door (INAUDIBLE).
To get a 1 here
and therefore the transistor
conducts
and the resistor is active,
we must have here
the value 1 since there is no small circle.
We must have here the value 0
where there must be a small circle.
This value 1 here
corresponds to PORT.
This value 0 here
corresponds to the DDR.
So we are well
in the logic I have just explained.
When DDR
the corresponding bit is 0
and that the PORT bit
corresponding is at 1,
these two conditions,
we have  (INAUDIBLE)triggers
the intrlocking of our resistance
of pull-up.
Another micro-controller,
a different way
to manage the resistors.
The MSP430, offers
pull-up and pull-down
on each leg.
It's new.
It is interesting in some cases.
It is true that we
use much more often
the pull-up as the pull-down
but there are certainly applications
interesting for the pull-down.
In this case, an additional register,
a special register was used.
It has the particular name of REN
which means
Resistor Enable.
So, interlocking
of the resistance.
And when we decided
to interlock the resistor,
we choose if it is a pull-up
or a pull-down
with the value of OUT.
So I remind you in this table,
when Dir is at 0,
We always have an entrance.
When Dir is at 1,
we always have an output.
When it is an output, it can be at 0
or at 1
according to the OUT, nothing has changed.
However,
the input is at high impedance
and in the normal state
when the OUT is 0
and that the REN is also at 0,
on the other hand,
one or the other of the resistors
with the REN to 1.
This will be a pull-up
with the 1,
a pull-down with the 0.
I would caution you
if values ​​that are different
of those
cited in this sort of truth table
that I have just drawn.
Let's take an example .
I did not mention the case
where we would have a 1
on the Resistor Enable and a 1 on the Dir.
And what will happen,
I can not give you the answer.
The answer can be found in
the manufacturer's documentation.
It will vary from one manufacturer
to another of course
But be extremely careful
To use the modes that
are provided by the manufacturer.
Obviously, all this is described in
the documents that
the manufacturers give us
and which describe with great precision
but in a very large number of pages
the exact operation of all parts
of micro-controllers.
Let's take an example .
In fact, we have already seen this program
but there were 2 lines
which had not been very clearly explained.
Let us first read the second.
Here in the register REN,
I will activate the bit 2
and bit 3.
So I will interlock
the resistors
Now I decide by acting
with a 7 bits
also on bit 2 and on bit 3
to select pull-up type resistors.
Can't the Arduino
not solve our problem?
In a certain sense yes
since the primitive
that the pinMode function we know
does not only allow
a leg in the OUTPUT
Or a leg on the input.
But I tell you today,
it is also possible to set it to the mode
INPUT_PULLUP, that is, an input
with a return resistor upwards.
Unfortunately, they did not
anticipate the pull-down resistance.
So,
this line will work perfectly well
on an AVR of Atmail,
on an MSP430 with
the environment (INAUDIBLE)
but we can not
use the pull-down
which is yet physically
available on an MSP430.
And it's still interesting.
This allows you to have a syntax that
works on all micro-controllers
which have resistors
of recall at the top
of the pull-up resistance.
In summary
we have just seen
that the pull resistances
are essential
whenever a leg is likely to be in the air.
We have also seen that
many micro-controllers
integrates these draw resistors
within the integrated circuit.
And we also noted that each manufacturer
proposes its own implementation
for these pull-up mechanisms
and possibly pull-down.