Hello and welcome to this fourth block.
In this block, we will talk
about the management of urban
transportation systems,
the challenges these systems face,
and all this more or less
in the context of efficiency.
Now, this block is composed
of five different sessions.
So in the first session, very briefly,
I will introduce you to the main features
of the urban transportation--
the building blocks
of the urban transportation systems.
Then we will talk in the second block
about managing these systems.
We will hear from an expert
on what the challenges are
for managing these urban
transportation systems,
and then we will hear from another expert
what the challenges are
from an operator's perspective.
Finally, I will talk about
the broader challenges
and the opportunities that arise
in the context of the new things
that are recently happening,
that are recently affecting
urban transport.
Now, the first block, as I said,
is basically about the basic--
the main features
of transportation in cities.
It is quite simple,
but it is, nevertheless,
essential to understand these features.
I would like to first talk briefly
about how transport
relates to the structure of the city
and then about
the physical infrastructure:
the transportation modes
and the interfaces.
Transport is clearly the most structuring
infrastructure of a city.
Remember when we talked about energy,
and electricity in general,
we said that this
is the lifeblood of the city.
But transport
is the structure of the city.
And it basically has two elements.
One is housing.
Housing, or the built environment
more generally,
is closely related to transport.
The way the city is structured
in terms of housing
will determine what kind of transport
you can develop.
So if you think, for example,
of a medieval Italian city,
what kind of transport
infrastructure possibilities
do you actually have there?
What kind of mobility possibilities
do you have there?
Or if you take a big city
that has been developed
after the second World War,
the houses are structured,
the way the houses are arranged,
structures transport
very very differently.
but it also works the other way around.
So if you have a good transport offer,
let's say a very good
metro system into suburbia,
that will affect the way
the housing is being developed,
or the industrial and the commercial
development that happens.
You build shopping malls
where the metro stations are.
Transport is also a significant driver
of urban energy consumption.
We have seen in the last section
that transport consumes
25% of the energy
that goes into a city.
And so whatever you do with transport,
it affects energy consumption,
and it will affect pollution.
Now let's quickly go into
the basic infrastructures of transport.
There are underground
transport infrastructures,
like metro tracks, like train tracks.
Then above the ground--
the majority of the things
are above the ground,
like surface train tracks
or surface metro tracks.
But the big chunk of the city
is taken away by roads.
Yet, on the roads you have several things.
You have the tram tracks,
you have the light metro tracks,
that take off some space from the road.
You have dedicated bus lanes on the road.
You have sidewalks that are on the road,
and then you have, sometimes,
dedicated bicycle lanes on the road.
So this, together, makes the basic
infrastructure of the city.
Now, on top of that,
you have the main transportation modes
that use these infrastructures.
So you have public buses, trams and metros
that use the road
or the underground tracks.
You have cycling
that uses the sidewalks or the street,
because there may be no sidewalks,
you have driving cars
which basically use up most of the roads,
but are recently being pushed back
by other transport modes,
you have taxis that use the roads
and you have pedestrians
that use the sidewalks, if they exist,
or also the road,
in which case this is dangerous.
And then you have, of course,
the trains and the metros
and the trams that use the surface tracks.
Now, the third element here
are the interfaces.
And the interfaces take other space -
infrastructure space.
You have bus stops.
Bus stops use a piece of the road,
but we know that actually bus stops
often use a piece of the sidewalks
or even of the bicycle lanes.
We have cycling stands,
we have parkings,
which use up a lot of space in the city,
because actually most of the time
the car stands still.
It drives into the city in the morning,
it drives out in the evening again,
and during the rest of the day it occupies space
without actually any
active productivity of the space.
Taxis use taxi stands,
pedestrians use sidewalks,
and then we have stations
above and under the ground.
Those are the main interfaces,
and all these things together
make up for the transportation
infrastructure of a city.
In this session, we have basically
looked at the main features.
It is quite trivial.
You have the key elements here,
but it is essential to understand
how things are then managed from there.
In the next session,
I will talk about the management
of these urban transport
infrastructure systems.
Stay tuned.