Let us now briefly conclude this course.
We have talked about the importance
of managing urban infrastructures.
We have given you the different features
of managing the urban infrastructures.
And we have shown you especially
two particular cases:
urban energy, in particular, electricity,
and urban transport,
what are the main challenges there
and what should be done
by urban infrastructure managers
to address these challenges.
Now all what we have done
in this course
is part of a broader research
and education endeavor
that we are doing.
It is called IGLUS -
Innovative Governance
of Large Urban Systems.
If you are interested in it,
if we have triggered
your interest with this course,
so please follow us
on IGLUS.org
I also would like to take this opportunity
to thank a series of people
who have helped us realize this course.
First, the partners who have
contributed to lecturing in this course.
I would also like to thank
four collaborators
who have made this course possible:
Maxime Auduoin,
Alejandro Nunez Jimenez,
Mohamad Razaghi,
and Cyril Wendl.
And, most of all,
I would like to thank you
for having followed this course.
Thanks and I hope to see you again
in a follow-up MOOC
on managing urban infrastructures.