The big challenge to cities
in the mobility sector is definitely
that their population is growing.
More people are coming to the cities
and they have to travel around the city.
Therefore, the mobility network
has to adapt itself
and has to accommodate
these additional people.
This can't be done in private car traffic
because roads are already saturated.
More traffic will lead to even more
congestion and more problems
and also more environmental
and social damage
through pollution and noise,
and more accidents.
Therefore, the solution is really
in building more capacity,
more lines and more offering
in the public transport system,
especially in the mass transport
aspect of it in the metro lines,
in the suburban rail, in trams,
and in higher capacity bus lines.
We need this additional capacity
to accommodate the additional people
and also move current car drivers
into the public transport system
in order to improve the city life
and the quality of life for the citizens.
Now, after the investment
in mass transit systems
which really will create the backbone
for the whole mobility system in the city,
we can then add to that
combined mobility solutions
in walking, cycling, car sharing,
other forms of transport
which are much cheaper to realize
and will offer
the last-mile solution for the cities
on top of a public transport system.
It is important to realize this as well,
but they can't be the only solution.
They can't be alone.
They have to come on top
of big infrastructure investments
in public transport capacity,
which is really the main solution
to the challenge of the city in mobility.
The realization of integrated
mobility system in a city poses,
of course, how to bring together
all these different actors
and work them together efficiently,
and this is a very complex problem
because there are a lot of actors
coming into the field of mobility.
The traditional operators
of different modes of transport,
the planning side,
of course, from the city,
and the new operators
from the combined mobility solutions:
bike sharing, car sharing,
and other associations as well
that are important to be integrated.
Therefore, how to work
together efficiently
is really the challenge that poses,
and I am convinced that even
the best city planning department
can't do everything by itself,
but has to delegate some competence
and some, even, freedom of management
to the different players
and treat them as partners,
and work together with them as partners.
Of course, there needs to be
some formal arrangement
in the form of a contract
that regulates the main aspects,
financing aspects and performance aspects
that then can be followed on
and measured concerning
if these different actors
make a good job or not.
An important part in that,
that I am convinced,
is that these contracts,
objectives and arrangements
have to be made public.
They have to be fully transparent
to the citizens, and to the users,
to the passengers of public transport
in order for them to follow up
what your goals are
and if the different actors
make a correct job in realizing this
and if this is not the case,
there have to be consequences,
financial consequences
in the form of incentives and penalties
and even if everything goes wrong
and no corrective action is efficient,
they have to be changed,
and I think it is important
even for us as operators,
public transport operators,
to know that we can be replaced
if we don't do a good job,
but we have to have a certain freedom
in achieving our goals,
and we have to know, of course, our goals
for several years ahead
in order to be prepared and to plan ahead
and be able to realize them well.
In order to realize all these
important objectives and goals
for an improved and more efficient
public transport network,
we need, of course, everybody
to work together towards that goal.
People have to realize that the priority
should be public transport
as a backbone, as a base
for the success of their city,
economically, socially,
and environmentally,
meaning at the end, also
for the quality of life in the city.
So, city managers, city politicians,
but also other levels of government
on a regional, national level,
have really to come together
and define together public transport
as a priority for the success
and for the future of their city
and if that is done, then the conditions
can be set accordingly,
and the laws can be put right
in order to allow for public transport
to be developed and to be financed
and to be successful in the future.
I believe that this is happening right now
and people are coming together
and are seeing that the priority
should be on public transport development
in order to become a successful city.