Hello, and welcome back
to this last session of our fourth block
on Urban Transport.
In this session we will talk
about the big challenges
and opportunities that arise
for urban transport management,
and these challenges and opportunities
basically arise
from three different angles.
The first angle is the urban sprawl
and the corresponding mobility needs
that are created
because of urban sprawl.
The second type of big challenges
arise from the environment,
especially from climate change.
The third type of challenges,
and especially opportunities,
arise from the information
and communication technologies
that have been developed
so rapidly over the past 28 years
and have entered
the whole transportation sector.
Now, each of these challenges
will be opportunities for managers
to address them,
and what we will briefly show here
in this last session
is how they will address this.
Now, let us first talk about urban sprawl
and the corresponding mobility needs.
It is clear that mobility has become
a driver of urban sprawl.
Think about the development
of the American cities
after the Second World War
with overall car use.
The whole housing system
has been developed
outside of the city because of big roads
and because of cars becoming available,
and it is clear that mobility,
the ability to move,
has been driving the overall urban sprawl.
On the other hand, the mobility needs
have increased because of urban sprawl.
Once the people live outside of the city,
far from their workplaces,
they have to move back into the city
and by doing that, create
all kinds of mobility problems,
transportation problems,
congestion problems.
A few examples here.
In India the number
of motorized vehicles on city streets
is growing at an annual rate
of more than 20%.
Imagine what that means:
20% more cars every year
on the streets of the city.
You can calculate by when
the whole city will be clogged.
In Mexico, for example,
two new cars enter into circulation
for every newborn child.
Those are figures of 2011
but it hasn't improved ever since.
I think that the urban sprawl
and the related growing mobility needs
are the main challenge
of urban transportation managers
in the years to come.
It is simply not possible
to continue to develop mobility,
especially by way of private cars,
further into the future.
What can they do
to address this challenge?
The main challenge will be here
to resist investing into further
urban road infrastructure
to put ever more cars onto the streets.
Sooner or later this will lead
to collapse, to traffic collapse.
What should they do instead?
Resisting is one thing,
doing something positive
is something else.
What do they have to do instead?
I think the first big task is to do
an integrated transport
and housing planning.
As we saw before, urban sprawl
and mobility are closely related.
It makes no sense to plan
these things separately,
to plan housing building separately
from planning transport,
or to plan transport separately
from how housing is planned.
The second big task
of urban public transport managers
will be to actually increase
the share of public transport
in the overall mobility mix.
This has two aspects: one is
to incentivize use of public transport.
We have seen that before; public transport
needs to become more efficient
and more attractive,
so that the inhabitants of a city
actually find it attractive
and efficient to use it.
The other aspect is, of course,
to disincentivize the use of the car
to make it more difficult to use the car
by creating bus lines,
reducing the available space for cars,
reducing the available space for parking,
creating bicycle lanes, things like that.
But this incentivization, of course,
needs to go hand in hand
with the development of other
public transport opportunities.
It makes no sense to disincentivize
the use of the car
and then not offer any alternative.
This will only make the transport
more difficult for the users.
The second big challenge
are the environmental challenges,
and here, especially climate change,
the emissions but also
the overall pollution reduction
is just another driver, another pressure
for urban transportation managers
to develop public transport,
to make it more attractive,
to make it more efficient,
to incentivize the use
of public transport,
to disincentivize the use
of the private car.
In addition to that, of course,
there are also other things
that urban transport managers need to do,
namely, to create public transport modes
that are less polluting,
that are more energy efficient,
that use cleaner technologies,
for example, by favoring
electric vehicles, electric buses,
or even electric taxis for that matter.
And here, the second big aspect also
is the creation of what we call
"soft mobility",
to create dedicated bike lanes,
to create public bicycle offerings,
to create dedicated pedestrian ways.
These are not really alternatives
to the urban mobility
but they are certainly useful
complements to urban mobility.
Often the big problem here
is the last mile.
You get to a metro station
but your house is still 500 meters away
or your office is still 500 meters away
and easily accessible bicycle
will make all the difference
and allow you to have
an integrated mobility chain
where soft mobility is complementing
the traditional public transport modes.
The third big challenge
that urban transport managers
have to face are the ICTs,
but the ICTs are actually
really an opportunity for them.
The ICTs have the unique potential
to address the two big challenges
that transport managers have to face:
namely, discouraging the car use,
and the ICTs, how can they do that?
They can do that by creating
mobility pricing schemes
which can incentivize
better mobility behavior.
For example, you pay
for congestion pricing,
you pay for entering into the city,
you pay more at certain peak hours
than you pay at low peak hours,
and the way the ICTs technologically allow
for pricing the mobility of the people
who move around in the city.
Then this money can be used
to generate the necessary investments
to develop or to subsidize
public transport in the city.
The second thing that the ICTs can do
is to make public transport
more attractive.
Clearly, the ICTs
can improve the intermodality,
that is, the moving from one
transport mode to the other.
They can do that by having
a more integrated planning,
either for the users,
who can now plan their travels
across the different modes smoothly.
Sometimes the app will also give you
an indication of alternatives
in case there is a problem with a train
or in case there is congestion,
but they better allow for better
integrated planning of the city.
For example,
across different jurisdictions
because thanks to the data
that you now have generated,
you can actually plan
the whole mobility much better.
Secondly, it improves intermodality because
the ICT improve integrated ticketing,
so you can now buy a ticket
that crosses all the transport modes,
or actually, get rid
of the ticket altogether
because you are billed on your credit card
or some other urban integrated ticket,
which allows you to use
all the transport modes
and this ticketing you actually
can combine back
with what I said before,
with mobility pricing.
Then the ICTs can create new services
such as car sharing services,
bicycle sharing services,
ride sharing services, that is,
those are services that complement
the traditional public transport modes
but allow the users
to move much more easily across the city.
In this last session we have now seen
the big challenges of urban transport
and what the urban transport managers
can and should do
to respond to these challenges.
We have seen that the ICTs
are a big opportunity
in doing precisely that.
We will now say a few words
to conclude the overall course.
Stay tuned.