In this episode,
we will discuss
a new data type, pointers.
In this first video, we will go over
the general aspects of pointers
and how they are related
to references.
Then, in the next video,
we will present in detail
how to use pointers.
Pointers have the unfortunate reputation
of being considered hard,
whereas this is really not the case.
Actually, you already use pointers
in everyday life, perhaps without
even knowing it.
For example, when you are interested
in a web site,
what do you do?
You will certainly not copy the
entire website
onto your computer, will you?
You do not copy the site.
Instead, in your browser,
you have a bookmark, a link
which will point to the web site.
This web site still exists independently
of this.
Well, a pointer is nothing more
complicated than a bookmark
in your web browser.
So, in a program, whenever
you want to make a link,
a reference to an object
which exists elsewhere,
-- not a website this time,
but a variable for example -- in your
program,
you will use a pointer or
a reference.
Any time you want to reference,
to indicate,
to make a link to another variable
in your program.
Pointers -- I am talking about pointers
in the generic sense, that is,
meaning both real pointers and references,
we will distinguish them later.
So pointers, in a program, serve
essentially three purposes.
First, they can serve as
a reference,
exactly like the example of
a bookmark for a website.
Here is an object drawn in red,
which I will call a.
Say, you want to reference it in
several places
of your program.
For example, in the case of the
website,
a represents a website in
your browser.
In your browser, you
have a link to this site,
and in one of your friends' browser,
there is another link to this site,
and in a third browser belonging
to someone else,
there is also a link to this site.
All of these are pointers, they refer to
the object
that we want to reference.
This is the first use case
of these pointers.
The second use case of pointers
is what I call
using pointers for genericity.
The drawing is kind of symmetric
to the drawing in the reference case.
Here, you have several objects
which you don't necessarily know
in the beginning,
so for example an object a, an object b
and an object c, and you want to describe
these different objects in a
generic way, at a given
moment in your program.
In this case, you will also
use a pointer.
The pointer will, at a certain moment,
point for example to object a.
At another moment, it can point for example
to object b.
Finally, at another point in your program,
the same pointer can point to
object c.
Here's an everyday example
of this:
you have your friend's number, and you
store it in an addressbook.
At that moment, your friend has
a certain number,
but then, he changes operators,
changing phone numbers.
In your address book,
you will change your friend's phone number
to the new number.
This is what I call using pointers
for genericity.
We have a generic pointer which
describes one or another,
or a third object, at different times
in the program's execution.
The third use case for pointers is
a little technical.
It relates to what is referred to
technically as scope
and lifespan.
Scope, I will remind you, is the
set of lines of code
in which an object is defined.
Lifespan is the time during which
an object exists in memory
during the execution of the program.
Let's illustrate once again with
a small drawing.
If I represent, on the horizontal axis,
the time during which the program is
executed,
then at a certain time, the program will
execute a code fragment
contained between curly braces.
If, in this code fragment, I had for example
declared an integer-type variable,
named a, then the lifespan of this
variable would be equal to
the execution time of its
scope.
Its scope, remember, is the block in
which it was defined.
And if I look at the execution of the
program with respect to time,
the lifespan of this variable
is thus equal
to the execution time of its scope.
The compiler will destroy this variable
as soon as
it doesn't need it anymore, i.e as soon
as its scope is finished.
Well, if you want to increase the lifespan
of an object,
-- we will see how to do it exactly later --
if you want an object
to be available in memory
from this moment here, but have
a lifespan
greater than its scope,
then you will use what we call dynamic
memory allocation.
This is the third use case of pointers.
So, to sum up, pointers are used essentially
for three things.
Either an object can be referenced from
several places using pointers,
or one single pointer will point to
different objects at different times,
or we will want to manage
memory ourselves,
to decide what lifespan to give these
objects in memory, using what we call
dynamic memory allocation.
These three ways of using pointers
are not exhaustive, and we can
absolutely combine several, but what
counts is to always keep in mind
the reason, or the reasons, for
which you
want to use a pointer in your
program.
In C++, and especially since
the new C++ 2011 standard,
there are in fact three types
of "pointers".
There are references, which aren't
strictly speaking real pointers
and are actually fundamentally quite different
from real pointers,
in the sense that they are completely
managed by the compiler,
and that they are very secure objects
which are not manipulated
by the programmer himself
but by the compiler.
Then, we have, since the new C++ 2011
standard, intelligent pointers,
so-called smart pointers. And finally we
have the old pointers
inherited from the C language, the ancestor
of C++,
which are very powerful,
all-around pointers.
These are the ones we simply call
pointers
when we don't explicitly specify
which sort of "pointer" we are
talking about.
Before going into detail about
each of these new types,
the question we can ask ourselves
is which ones to use
in which situation.
The general rule is to use references
whenever we can
and to use pointers when
we must.
Let's go over each of the use cases
for pointers again.
In case number one, where we want to use
pointers as references,
then we should of course use real references
instead of pointers. We could also
use
C-style pointers, since these pointers
are universal and
can be used for everything.
But as a beginning programmer,
if you have the choice and you
are in the use case of a reference,
then simply use references,
which we will go over in the next
video.
If you are in use case number two,
that is,
you want to use a generic pointer
to describe
several different objects which you don't
necessarily already know of,
then, what you should use is a C-style
pointer.
But there is another way of referring to
these objects,
which we want to describe generically.
I called them a, b and c in the
last example.
So, suppose that these objects
already exist,
and suppose that they have
been stored
in an array.
At this point, you don't even need a
pointer anymore,
you can simply use the indices,
the positions in the array,
to describe them in a generic way.
So for example, using size_t i
to refer to them. If i equals zero then
it will describe a;
if i equals 1, it will describe b;
if i equals 2, it will describe c.
So, it can be useful to keep in mind
this way of doing things,
which simply requires an extra
data structure,
an array in this case.
If these objects already
exist when we
create the array,
or if we add them as we go
into a dynamic array using
push_backs and pop_backs,
then we can also refer to them
generically by using an extra
abstraction which is the index of the
element in the array
rather than the element itself.
And if you really want to use pointers,
so, if you are in use case number two,
then you will need to use C-style
pointers.
In use case number three, dynamic
memory allocation,
then you will of course have to use
pointers -- that is
what they are meant for -- and in this case,
I suggest you use C++ 2011
and smart pointers.
Specifically, I suggest you use
unique_ptr, which we will go over in
a subsequent video.
This concludes the different use
cases
of all sorts of "pointers".
The following videos will go into
detail
about references,
C-style pointers
and finally smart pointers described by
the C++ 2011 standard.