A reference is simply another name,
a synonym, an alias,
for an object which already
exists in memory.
If, for example, I have an object,
a variable of integer type
which is called val and
which contains the value 1.
I can give another name,
for example x,
for this same area, for this same variable
in memory. This is a reference.
A reference is simply used
to refer
to another object in memory.
This is exactly what we used
when we passed arguments
by reference.
If, for example, we had a function f
which took an integer a by reference,
which we wrote like this, with
the & symbol here,
we were passing this argument by reference.
If, somewhere else in the program
I defined an integer, for example,
named b and
initialized to 3,
and that I called f(b),
then b was passed by reference
to the function f
through the variable a,
a parameter of function f.
This passing by reference
means that
it is the same object that is referred
to inside and outside the function.
This is what it means to
pass by reference.
The general syntax for declaring
a reference is the following.
We can generalize
this syntax, used
for passing arguments by
reference to functions,
by adding a & symbol after the type
and the name of the reference.
It is not a new variable.
It is just a new label for a variable
which already exists.
Here, we link it to an identifier.
If I go back to a previous example,
with a variable named val
of int type, containing
a value of 1.
Now, I can declare
a reference which I will
call x
and which is just another
name for the variable val.
This declaration, this
syntax, means that
x is another name for
the variable val
It does not create a new variable x
in which I would copy val,
but it creates a new flag,
a new name,
a new label,
for something that already exists
in memory, that is, the variable val.
From now on, I can refer to this variable
by the name x or by val.
These two names will indicate
the same variable.
So be careful of possible
confusions and traps
linked to the fact that a reference
is not a variable.
It is just a label on a variable.
For example, the = sign can be a trap.
Let's compare two fairly
similar pieces of code
where we have a variable i
initialized to 3
and a reference j
which is a reference, an alias of i,
and the other case, where we have
a second variable j.
What will happen?
In both cases, we have
a variable i
which is initialized and
contains a value of 3.
In the case of the reference, we also
have a reference j,
that is, another name for the
same variable,
for the same memory area.
In the right-hand side case,
we have a variable j
which is very different from the
other case.
In this case, what will happen is that
we initialize j with the value of i.
We copy the value of i into j.
Whereas in the left-hand side case,
in the reference case,
it is the same object, the
same variable which is referenced.
This means that if we assign
4 to i
in the case of the reference,
what will happen
is that both i and j will
have a value of 4.
j will also have a value
of 4.
Whereas in the right-hand side case,
we only have i here;
once the copy has been done,
this arrow should not be here anymore.
The copy is over.
So, it is i and only i
which has a value of 4.
j still has a value of 3.
Similarly, if we modify j,
in the reference case,
modifying j also modifies i.
So here, if I modify j, then
i will also have a value of 6.
Whereas in the case of two completely
different variables,
modifying j will not modify i
and so i still has a value of 4.
Second little trap that can often
lead to confusion:
the meaning of const.
We have already insisted several times
on the fact that const means
that modifications are
impossible through the
object which we described
as const.
But this object can be modified
from elsewhere.
This is the case with references.
Let's look at it with an integer i
initialized with a value of 3.
Here, we declare a const reference
on i
which we name j.
In other words, we have
defined another name, another flag,
another label.
Through this label -- I will
draw it thicker --
we cannot modify the content.
This doesn't mean that the content
cannot be modified elsewhere.
If I want to modify the content of
this variable
which is named i and j, for example,
by an assignment with a value
of 12,
I will not be able to. This line will
be forbidden by the compiler.
It is forbidden because, here,
j is const,
which means that I cannot effect
any modification through j.
However, I can still modify this memory
area through i
and I am allowed to do:
i = 12,
which will put 12 in the memory
area i
which is also the memory area
named j.
j also has a value of 12.
To summarize, it is important
to realize that the keyword,
the reserved word const applies
to the object,
to the name we are talking about
and not necessarily
to the object in memory behind it.
It applies to the object only through
this name
and not to the object itself.
I said in the introduction sequence
that references were
not real pointers
as such, and that they
were quite different objects.
This is why, incidentally, they have a
different name, "references".
So I would like to insist on the
specifics of these references.
The first of these is that a reference
must absolutely
always be initialized.
It always refers to an existing object.
A pointer, on the other hand, could
point to something that does not exist.
Here, I declared, again, a variable i
of integer type,
and here, I declare a reference ri
on the object, the variable i.
Which means that it is
another name for i.
But I cannot declare a
reference rj
which would be linked to no object.
This is invalid.
To what is it a reference?
We do not know
what it refers to.
We cannot declare references
which refer to nothing.
It would lose all its sense.
Similarly, a reference can be
linked only to one object.
This is another big difference
with pointers.
Let's go back to our example
with the variable i.
Here is a reference ri
which refers to this variable i.
Here, I declare another variable j
initialized to 2.
I cannot use ri, which is
a reference to i.
It is already used. It refers
to an object i.
I cannot move the label to j.
If I draw this, I have the variable
i which contains a value,
we do not know which,
it has not been initialized.
I attached the reference ri
to it.
Then I declared another variable j
which I initialized to 2.
I cannot move a reference, it isn't
possible.
We are not allowed to
do this sort of thing.
However, this line, ri = j, compiles.
It is quite legitimate in C++.
What does this do now?
Let's go back to the fundamentals.
What is ri?
It is another name for i.
It is as if I had written i = j.
If I had written i = j,
what would have happened?
We would have copied the value of j
into i and so here, in the same way,
we will copy the value of j into ri.
So this line here, ri = j,
does not mean
that we move the label of ri to j and
that we have another reference on the object j.
It mean that we are copying
the object j
over to the object which
is named ri.
Proof: if I modify the value of j, for
example if I give it a value of 3,
then if I display the value of i
you will see what will be displayed...
I encourage you to test this
program on your end.
You will see that it will display 2.
2 because it is the value which
we assigned to the variable,
which is named both i and ri.
Third specificity of references: one
cannot refer to a reference.
A reference is not an object
in memory.
It is just an additional label on
an object in memory.
So we cannot get its address, we cannot
refer to such an object.
If I go back once again to our example with
the variable i
which I initialize to 3, and
to which I assign another name.
If I take a reference named ri
which refers to i.
What we are asking ourselves is,
can I take
a reference on the reference ri?
Well, no. ri is not an object as such.
We cannot say that we will take
a reference on a reference.
This does not refer to ri as
pointers would do,
but actually to i, to the variable i.
Even if this line compiles and
makes ri
another reference to i,
it does not do what we
wanted it do to originally.
That is, a reference on the label
ri itself.
Even if I changed the type
to say that I wanted
a reference on a reference,
this wouldn't work.
We are not allowed to do that
either.
It is just as wrong, since
this label ri
does not really exist.
It is not an actual variable
in memory.
ri is just another name for
a variable which already existed.
The consequence of all this,
is that we cannot make
arrays of references.
We cannot put references into
an array.
I have an advanced remark however:
the syntax int&&
with two ampersands
exists since C++2011, but it is not at all
a reference on a reference.
It is a much more advanced concept
introduced in this new standard
which is an rvalue reference.
This is much too advanced for
this course
and will not be covered here.