We have seen references in detail.
Now, let's pass to real pointers.
The main difference is
that a pointer
is a variable
which actually exists in memory.
It is not just a label for
a variable which already exists,
it is a new variable.
To understand what pointers are,
one must first know that variables,
generally, are identified by
an address in memory.
Suppose, for example, that I have
a variable x which exists in memory
and which contains something,
anything, and that I look
at memory like this as I
go along.
At a certain place, the value of x
will be written to memory
in binary form,
and at another moment it will be
something else, some other variables.
Well, this variable x is
identified by its address,
the place in memory where it begins.
So, we can take the address in
memory of a variable.
And a pointer is just that,
precisely,
it is a variable which contains the
address of another object in memory.
A pointer is simply a variable which contains
the address of another variable.
It is a sort of variable of variables, just
like a bookmark
for a website, which I took as
an example in the introduction,
is the address of a site
which exists elsewhere.
And so this way,
references and pointers are
fundamentally different.
A reference is not a variable which
contains an address,
it is just another label.
There is a big difference between having
another label on the same drawer
and another drawer which contains
the address of something.
A pointer thus has an extra level,
a level of abstraction.
A pointer is really like a book
from an address book.
A page on which we could write only
one address at a time.
And I would now like to
use this analogy
to illustrate a whole bunch
of practical applications
for pointers in programs.
These different cases will be
illustrated with C++ syntax
that you have not encountered
yet and that will be presented
in the next video
which presents the more practical,
technical aspects.
Still, we left them here
in case you might want to
review this video
or review the slides once you will
have learnt about this syntax.
It could be useful.
Let's start with the first case:
declaring a pointer.
I told you that a pointer was
a variable
and so we can declare a pointer.
What does it mean to
declare a pointer?
It just means that we are adding
a page to our address book.
But careful, adding a new page
does not mean that there
is an address written on it.
Adding a new page is just
adding a new page
without specifying what
will be written on it.
There will likely be something written
on it, but we don't know how to interpret it.
Second point:
assigning a pointer.
What does it mean to assign
a pointer?
It means giving an address,
writing an address on the page
of our address book.
We sometimes speak
of allocating a pointer.
What does it mean to allocate
a pointer?
Allocating a pointer means,
to go buy some land somewhere.
It is allocating memory and
building a house in it.
That is, putting a value there
and getting back the address of this house
to copy it onto the page of
our address book.
That's what allocating a pointer means.
But note that here -- this
is a common mistake --
the pointer is neither the
land nor the house.
Those are two completely
different things.
The pointer is just the page
of the address book
which contains the address
of the house.
It is not the house itself.
In other words, the pointer does
not equal the value pointed by it.
Those are two completely
different things.
In the case of the page
of an address book
which contains the address of the land
that we bought, that we allocated,
freeing a pointer
simply means
that we authorize the memory to
re-use this area,
that this area is no longer
our property
and that it can be re-used
freely somewhere else.
And so this area is no
longer our property.
So careful, freeing a pointer
is actually a misnomer,
it actually means freeing the
land it points to,
it does not mean that we have
erased the page of our address book.
The address is still there, but it is
a common mistake
to reuse the address of a piece of land
which does not belong to us anymore.
This is why, later on,
we will encourage you to
erase the page of the address book
once you have freed the pointer.
Copying a pointer
is what you do
when you give an address to
someone you know.
When you give an address to
friends,
they copy the address that you give them
into a page of an address book.
They will not copy the house whose
address it is.
You do not give them your house.
You give them only the address,
you copy the address.
That's what it means to copy
a pointer:
it is an exchange of addresses.
And finally, erasing or
cancelling a pointer
simply means that you are
erasing the page of your address book.
Note that if this address was the address
of a piece of land
that we had allocated in memory,
erasing the pointer would not
free this land.
The land is still occupied, it
is still used.
So first, we have to destroy
the pointer before erasing it.
There, I hope this analogy will
help you to use pointers
more easily, to understand
what is going on.
The next video will show you
how to apply this practically
by going into detail on how
to use pointers.