With our address book analogy,
you now know of most of the
operations we can do
on pointers.
In this episode, we will go over all
these operations
one after the other and
discuss
how to use them in C++ language
syntax.
To declare a variable in C++,
we know we can
use the following syntax.
So, name of the type, for example
"int" for integers
followed by the identifier associated
to the variable, i.e "x".
For a pointer, the notation is
the same, except that the type
will indicate that it is a pointer
to a particular data type.
So for example if I want to
declare a pointer
on an integer, the associated
type will be: "int*"
to mean "pointer to an integer",
followed by the name of the pointer,
so of the pointer-type variable
we are creating.
Similarly, if I want to declare a
pointer on a "double"
I will use the following syntax.
I will write "double*" as the type
followed by the identifier for
the variable, "ptr".
So here, I declared a variable named
"ptr", the type of which is pointer
on a variable of type "double".
This is for simple declaration. If I want
to initialize at the same time,
the syntax is analogous to the one
I used up until now.
For example, if I want to write, declare
and initialize a variable "x"
of integer type, initialized to 4,
I use the following syntax.
Well, the syntax is quite
analogous for pointers.
I must indicate in parentheses
the value of the pointer.
And this value must be an address.
So here are three examples of
declaration-initialization situations
on pointer-type variables.
Here, we are taking a bit of ahead
start on what will follow in this episode
and the following ones, by seeing
how to obtain the address
of a given memory area,
in this case the address of the memory
area named "i", the variable "i";
and how to dynamically allocate
a memory area
capable of storing data of a
certain type, in this case an integer.
So of course, we will review
these concepts
in much further detail when the time comes.
First line here, I am
declaring-initializing
a "ptr" variable of type pointer
to integer
So the "ptr" variable can contain
the address of an integer
and we initialize this variable
using a special value
which is "nullptr" meaning
that the "ptr" pointer
points to nothing.
So remember our address book
analogy.
Here, we have a page of our
address book which is empty,
which is initialized to nothing,
which contains nothing.
Second instruction,
I initialize a "ptr" pointer
using the address of an existing
memory area,
of a variable which exists in memory.
We will come back to this later.
And here, I initialize my pointer
using the address of
a dynamically allocated memory area.
These concepts will be the focus
of the following episodes
and of the rest of this sequence.
By the way, please note that the special value
"nullptr" can be assigned
to any type of pointer --
be it a pointer to a "double",
pointer to an integer, pointer
to any other type
of data defined in C++.
In either case, it means that
the pointer points to nothing.
C++ provides two fundamental
operators
for pointer manipulation.
The '&' operator (ampersand),
and the '*' operator (star).
The role of the '&' operator
is to return the memory address
of the value of a variable.
Let's see what this means on
a real example.
Here, we have a small program which
starts by declaring
a variable 'x' of integer type, and
initializes it to 3.
We know that to each variable of a program,
an address in memory is assigned.
Let's name this address "adr".
Then, we declare a second variable "px"
which is of type pointer-to-integer.
Meaning that it is capable
of containing the address
of a memory area containing an integer.
So we have this situation.
And here, we will start by initializing
the variable "px"
using the special value "nullptr".
Which basically means that "px"
is capable of pointing to a memory
area containing an integer,
but that at this moment,
it points towards nothing.
It points to nothing at all.
Now, the third line of the program.
And this is where our "&" operator
comes in.
We assign, to the variable "px",
the address of the variable "x".
We have seen that this address
here is "adr",
so this is what we end up with.
We will assign the address of the
variable "x" to "px".
We are establishing the link between
pointer and pointed-to area
with this assignment.
So to sum up, "px" returns the address
associated to the variable "x".
The '*' operator allows us
to get the value pointed to
by a pointer-type variable.
Earlier, we learned about the '&'
operator.
So "&x", where "x" is a variable,
will return the address of "x"
in memory.
Now, imagine that we have a pointer
"px".
This pointer points to, contains the
address of, a memory area
containing a certain value, for example 3.
And we wish to find the value pointed to
by using the pointer.
For this, we need to use the
'*' operator
applied to a pointer-type variable.
This is what will allow us
to get the value pointed to
by this pointer.
So if we go over our small example
from the previous episode again,
we go through the first instructions
and we find ourselves in the following
situation.
A variable "x" initialized to a value of 3,
of integer type and which has an address.
A second variable "px" which is of
pointer-to-integer type
which we begin by initializing
to "nullptr",
meaning that it points to nothing.
And to which we then assign the
address of "x"
which will establish the link
between pointer
and pointed-to variable.
Then, last instruction,
and this is where we call
our famous little '*' operator
which will allow us to establish the
link between pointer
and pointed-to value.
So here, we have "*px".
we use the '*' operator on the pointer,
which will allow us to get,
through the pointer, the value
pointed to by this pointer.
Now, imagine that I have a variable
of type "int"
named "i" which contains a certain value
and which has an address in memory.
If I write "&i", I will get a value
of type pointer-to-int
which is the address "adr".
Now, if I write " *&i ",
I will apply the '*' operator to
this pointer
which will return the value stored
at that address,
which is 3.
So writing " *&i " is exactly
equivalent to writing "i"
since I directly access the value
contained in "i".
C++ has the reputation of being a
language with a somewhat complicated syntax.
The '*' and '&' operators which
we have just seen
are a first example of that.
In fact, depending on the context in which
they are used, these operators
do not necessarily always mean
the same thing.
Let's see why.
There are now two contexts in which
we use the '&' operator.
The first context is when the ampersand
follows a type name
and the second is when the &
precedes the name of a pointer-type variable.
In the first case, we will use
the '&' to declare
a reference, either
when we pass
a variable by reference to a function,
or when we declare a reference on its own.
For example, I can declare a variable
"i" of integer type
and I can declare a reference
to this variable named "id".
This simply means that "id"
is now
another name for the variable "i".
So, first context of use,
we use the "&" to indicate that
we are declaring a reference.
Second context of use:
when the ampersand symbol
precedes a variable name.
We have just seen
that in this case, we will
simply obtain
the address of this variable.
And this address can of course
be assigned to a pointer-type variable
to establish the link between a
pointer and a pointed-to variable.
So here, we have a context
of use which
is completely different from
the first and which
leads us to a totally different
situation.
So, first potential for confusion:
two possible contexts for use
of the ampersand which means different
things in C++.
Second example where C++
uses the same symbol
to represent two different things: the star '*'.
Indeed, we saw earlier that
when a '*' follows a type name
as it is the case here,
it is simply used to declare a variable
of pointer type.
For example, if I write something like
this in a program,
I am declaring a variable
named "id"
and this variable is defined
as having a pointer-to-int type
thanks to this '*'.
This means that it can store,
potentially,
the address of a memory area
containing an integer.
Like so.
So "id"
is a variable of pointer type
declared using '*'.
If, however, the '*' precedes
the name of a variable,
this supposes that
the variable considered
is a pointer-type variable.
And the '*' will serve to return
the value pointed to by the pointer.
And here, this is the situation we are in.
We have a pointer-type variable
which contains
the address of a certain memory area,
which contains a value.
Let's say that this variable is an integer.
So "*id" will simply return the value of 3,
the value pointed to by the "id" pointer.
So here, the '*' serves to find
the value pointed to by a pointer.
It is a context of use
which is quite different from what we have
seen up until now.