In the introduction episode on
pointers, you learned
that they serve essentially three
purposes: they allow
referencing, that is, to point
indirectly to a memory area;
genericity, to choose, to select
an element that is unknown
at the time of programming; and finally,
they can also be used for what we call
dynamic allocation. This is what
we will focus on now.
When a program needs to manipulate
data, it will have
to allocate memory to store this data.
And in C++, you have two ways of
allocating memory.
The first, which you already know, is
what you do
when you write a line of code like this
one, a variable declaration.
At this moment, a so-called static
allocation is made.
Why static?
This means that we do
not need
to wait for the execution of the program
to know the memory requirements.
Here, when we compile this line of code,
we already know
that the program will need a
memory area dedicated
to storing an integer, and which
is named v.
There are however situations where
the memory requirements are known
only when the program is executed.
And a typical example is linked
to the use of dynamic arrays
of vector type, which
you have already encountered.
Suppose that we come across a
vector of integers v, in our program.
I can easily add, during execution
of the program,
a new element, a new cell to my
array, using a line
such as this one.
At the moment I execute this line of code,
this routine
will allocate the memory necessary
to store this new integer.
So it is only at the time that this
line is executed that allocation
happens, that the new memory area
is reserved for the needs
of your program.
So of course in this case, we speak
of dynamic allocation,
because we need to wait for the
program's execution,
and not just its compilation, to know
the memory needs.
Why? Well, we aren't sure that
this line will necessarily be executed,
so we cannot, at compilation time,
know what memory area to reserve.
We must wait for execution.
Here, the memory area that we
allocated dynamically via the push_back statement
was allocated to contain a value of 3,
and we are thus
in this situation.
Note that in the case of pointers,
dynamic allocation
allows us to manipulate data without
them having to be associated
with explicit names -- they don't have
to correspond to variables.
For example if, in a program, we have
declared a pointer named px,
it can easily store the address of an
object that we allocated dynamically
during the program's execution.
We can absolutely store the address of
the new object in this pointer.
And what we notice
is that it is not necessary
for this object to have a name.
We can simply access it via
its associated pointer.
Basically, if you want to do dynamic
allocation
in a C++ program, then you can
use two operators
defined by the language: the new
operator which allows you to allocate
the memory you need, and the delete
operator, its converse, which
allows you to free this memory once
you do not need it anymore in your program.
Usage of the new operator
follows this syntax:
one writes the name of a pointer
which will
store the address, and one uses
the following syntax:
new followed by a type name.
This will reserve a memory area capable
of storing data of this type,
and will return the address
of this memory area, allowing it to be assigned
to the pointer.
Let's look at a real situation.
Imagine, for example,
that a program contains the following
line of code:
this line declares a pointer capable
of pointing to an integer.
So I will now use the syntax
that we have just seen
to do dynamic allocation.
So I take the name of my pointer
and I write px, followed by "="
and followed by my new
little instruction: "new type;".
Here, my pointer is a pointer to an
integer,
so "type", corresponding to the type to
which my pointer can point,
will be "int".
What I have just done is what
we call dynamic allocation.
So, how will this happen, really?
When you compile this line of code,
-- compile, not execute -- you will have
a static allocation
for a variable of pointer type, named px,
and capable of storing
the address of an integer.
However, it is at the moment you execute
this line of code that you
will have a dynamic allocation.
And at that moment, you will have allocated
a memory area for an integer,
which is this area.
This area will have an address,
and it is precisely this address
that you will store in px like so.
So this happens at the moment...
So what we have here is
a static allocation.
However here, you have
a dynamic allocation.
It is this instruction, the "new int",
which allows this,
which effects this allocation
If we use this syntax to do dynamic
allocation,
the newly allocated area is reserved,
indeed, but it does not contain any value.
So if, when we allocate memory, we
also want to assign a value
in the memory area, we must use
the following option:
for an instruction for dynamic allocation.
If we refer to the example we used
earlier,
so for example if I have a px pointer
declared in a program,
we can use this variant of the dynamic
allocation instruction.
Like so.
We write "px = new int;". So, I
reserve a memory area for an integer
and I put a value in it,
for example a value of 3.
When this line of code is executed,
this will
reserve a memory area for an integer,
which is what "new int;" means.
We put a value in it, that is, 3.
"new int(3)" returns the address
of the newly-allocated area,
and the assignment will make sure
that this address is copied into px.
You now know how to allocate
memory dynamically.
What should you do to free this memory
when you do not need it anymore?
Actually, first, why is it necessary
to free this memory?
Let's take another real example.
Imagine that in a program,
in a bloc,
I declare a variable
which I use in that bloc.
I obviously use static allocation.
Since I am declaring a
variable,
I can know my memory requirements
at compile time.
We know, thanks to the notion of
scope, that this variable
is not accessible outside of this bloc.
So, when we execute this set
of instructions,
and we reach the end of this bloc,
then we know that this variable v
will never be used again.
And so, statically-allocated variables
have the property
of being deallocated automatically.
You do not need to worry about
what will become
of the memory area which is, here,
no longer accessible.
Let's look at an analogous example
but where, this time,
we use dynamic allocation.
So here, say I declare, for example,
a pointer px.
Then, in a bloc,
I decide to dynamically allocate
memory that I retrieve
in the px pointer.
What is important to note here is
that the memory area
that you have just allocated
is not destroyed, it is not freed
as long as you have not
done it explicitely.
So, when we reach the end of this
bloc here during execution, this memory
area stays totally accessible as long
as you do not deallocate it.
This is what makes it possible
for dynamic allocation to
create memory areas which have a
lifespan greater than the scope
in which they were created.
And if, at any given time, we wish to
free this area,
it is up to us to do it explicitly
and for that, we will need to use
the delete operator.
So for example, I can decide after this bloc
that I do not need this memory area
anymore, and I can free
the area by calling delete on
its associated pointer.
Basically, imagine that in a program,
you have a px pointer
that points to a dynamically-allocated
memory area.
Imagine that this memory area contains
3, and of course
px contains the address
of this area.
What happens when we free
memory
by deallocating the memory area
associated to px by using this statement?
Remember the little analogy with
the houses on a piece of land.
well, when we call delete,
we destroy the house.
Which means, really, that the contents
of this memory area
are no longer predictable and can no
longer be used safely by the program.
Your value of 3 might well stay
there for a little while,
but you cannot be sure, you
cannot predict
what the contents of this memory area
will be.
So we see here that by simply
using delete px, we are in a situation
where this memory area no longer
has usable content.
However, of course, the address
still exists in memory
And this address is still stored, at
this point, in the px pointer.
So this justifies one of the guidelines which
I highly recommend that you follow:
that every delete instruction
must be followed
by the instruction, "pointer = nullptr;".
Which will translate to something like
"px = nullptr;".
This means that you are explicitly
saying that, as of that moment,
px points to nothing valid and you do
not keep,
within px, an address which means
nothing for the program
which cannot be used safely
for the program.
To summarize dynamic allocation,
and to return to our little analogy
of the address book, what I am doing
when I execute a statement
such as this one,
is to add a new page to my address
book, a page named ptr.
What exactly am I putting on this ptr
page? Well, I am writing down the address
of this dynamically-allocated area.
So allocation can be viewed, in the context
of the address book,
as reservation of land, of the memory
area that will store the value.
I build a house on this land; we can
see this house as being
a bit like the value 3 that I am storing
in the int memory area.
And what is returned is the address
of this memory area,
which I am storing in my address book.
I can, in a program, allocate memory
areas dynamically
for any type of data, and it is
up to the programmer to make sure
to free the memory area once
he needs it no more.
For example, if I do not need
this memory area anymore
then what I must do is to call
delete ptr
to deallocate, to free the memory area.
This means that my land no longer
contains any usable data.
And that it is now available
to anyone else.
If I simply do this, then
in my address book, I will still
have the address of this piece of land
which is for sale, which is available
to someone else.
So, I must absolutely take care
to indicate
that ptr no longer points to anything
by assigning nullptr to it.
This is analogous to removing the
page from my address book.
I am deleting this link,
which is no longer relevant
or useful.
If however we assign the nullptr value
without having first deallocated
the linked memory area, we
will end up in
the following situation
Suppose that on the analog
of this page from the
address book, we wrote "ptr3 = nullptr;".
Well, we know now that this means
that we are erasing this page
and that the link to this area is lost.
This means that I cannot access
it anymore via this page
from my address book, but
that the area itself is intact.
The land is not made available to anyone else,
and is left as-is.
So if, for example, no other page from
my address book references
this memory area, then this area is
lost, it cannot be reused
in my program. It is not available
for reuse
and this causes what is known as a
memory leak.
This is something that must absolutely
be avoided in any program.
To end on good practices: Any
memory area that was allocated dynamically,
i.e, that was made using new,
must imperatively be deallocated,
as we discussed earlier. Indeed,
a memory area that was
allocated dynamically is not freed
until we do it explicitely.
There, now you know a lot of
essential information
about pointers and we will summarize
all of this with a small example
Here is a program we will go
over step-by-step.
Here, we declare a variable px
which is a pointer
that can point to an integer, and I
take the precaution
of initializing it to nullptr,
which means that it points to nothing.
Second line of code,
there is a dynamic allocation.
This dynamic allocation reserves
a memory area capable of
storing an integer.
And this memory area has an address,
and this address is returned by the
execution of "new int".
This is the address I will
assign to px.
So now, I am making the px pointer
point to this
newly allocated memory area.
Then, third instruction.
I use the famous little star to access
the content pointer to by px.
The content pointed to by
px is this.
In this pointed-to content, I will
store the value 20,
which corresponds to this.
Then, I want to make sure that
I have stored the right value
in this memory area, and so I
want to display its contents.
Once again, I access the content that
px points to with the star operator,
and this will simply display the value 20,
followed by a newline,
a line break.
Then, I suppose that I no longer need
my memory area, and so I call
delete,
which means that this memory area
no longer has any usable content.
And I want to make sure that px
doesn't point towards obsolete content,
that it doesn't point to an address that
cannot be used safely and so,
once again, I assign nullptr
to the pointer's value.
The first version of the program that
we have examined can be written
in a more concise way, given that these
two instructions, which consist
in allocating memory and storing
a value within it,
can actually be written as a single line
with this syntax.
To make it shorter still, I can replace
these two lines of code
by a single line, this one.
In this line, I start by declaring
the pointer,
except that instead of starting by
initializing it to nullptr and then
assigning to it the result of
"new int(20)", I simply
put the value of "new int(20)"
directly into px.
This means that I spare one
statement.
When you write your first
programs with pointers,
and even for the following ones, it
is likely that, from time to time,
you will encounter a dreadful error,
the "segmentation fault", which will cause
your program to crash.
What is it?
Typically, "segmentation fault"-type
errors will occur
when we try, via a pointer,
to access a memory area
which was not reserved.
If we look at this example,
this statement
declares a px pointer but does not
reserve any allocated memory area.
There is no initialization,
no new, no nothing.
So here, the contents of px are unknown
and here, what we are trying to do
is to access the content pointed
to by px,
which does not exist, since we
never allocated it, and
to store a value of 20 in it.
Obviously, this is impossible and
it will result in a segmentation fault
error, causing your program to crash.
The correct solution would of course
be to allocate some memory
to associate to the px pointer,
which is done like so,
at execution time. So we allocate the
memory area, and at that moment,
our px pointer will contain the address of
this newly-allocated
memory area.
So of course, once this memory
area exists, we can
access it with no trouble, to store a
value of 20 in it.
So now, this statement will execute
without any errors.
We have just seen that it is essential
to allocate before using;
some advice follows,
good practice concerning
initialization of pointers.
It is recommended to always
initialize pointers,
even just to the nullptr value.
Thus, if, when we declare the pointer,
we do not yet know
where it will point to,
it is recommended to initialize it
by using nullptr, which means that
the pointers points to nothing,
but that it is known explicitly.
And thanks to this initialization,
it becomes possible to implement
a certain number of safeguards.
For example, before accessing
a memory area pointed to by
a pointer, I can now
take care to check if this pointer
does indeed point to
something or not.
Thus, it is possible, thanks to this
initialization, to test
whether the pointer points to something
before accessing this area,
as I could do here.
So we see that, thanks to this
initialization, a certain number
of safeguards can be implemented
to protect access to memory areas
pointed to by pointers.