The pointers we have studied up
until now are good old
"C-style" pointers, which are without
a doubt the most versatile
and most powerful, but also the
most dangerous pointers.
Indeed, as we have seen, their use
requires a lot of discipline.
Everything that is allocated by the
programmer as memory that is pointed to
by these pointers must systematically be
deallocated by the programmer.
And this discipline is sometimes
hard to respect
systematically.
If we want to allocate memory
dynamically, as of C++11,
we can use pointers that are somewhat
more comfortable to use
and which require less precautions
of the programmer.
These are so-called smart pointers,
and I will briefly
present them now.
"Smart pointers"
can be used
by including the memory library.
They have the advantage of deleting
themselves when appropriate.
This means that they manage deallocation
of their associated memory themselves.
The programmer
does not need to worry about freeing
memory anymore, which
avoids problems related to forgetting the
delete statement
as with C-style pointers.
The memory management of smart
pointers uses
so-called garbage-collecting techniques.
There are 3 kinds of smart pointers
in C++11.
unique_ptr, shared_ptr and weak_ptr.
The difference between these
pointer types is essentially
related to the number of pointers
of a given type that are able
to reference a same memory area.
For example, in the case of unique_ptrs,
only one unique_ptr can point towards
a given dynamically allocated memory area
such as this one.
The situation where we would have a
second unique_ptr pointing to the same
dynamically allocated memory area
is not possible.
On the contrary, with shared_ptr and weak_ptr,
one can have several pointers
that point to the same dynamically
allocated memory area.
The difference between shared and weak_ptr
will be explained briefly
soon.
C-style pointers can do everything.
For example,
in some situations, it is possible
for two different pointers
to reference, to point to the same
memory area.
This means that the programmer
must show discipline,
and be very careful.
Imagine for example that in one part of
the program, I call delete p2
This will deallocate the memory area
pointed to by p2,
which is also pointed to
by p1.
So it is up to the programmer to
be sufficiently careful
to guarantee that freeing memory in
one place will not have any
ill effects on another part
of the program.
If we want to avoid this kind of problems
and if we know in advance that
there will be no need for several pointers
to reference, to own
a same memory area, then we should
use the C++11 notion of
unique_ptr.
We saw that these pointers are such that
only one single
unique_ptr can reference a given
dynamically-allocated memory area.
So the situation where two unique_ptrs
reference the same area
is not possible; the situation we discussed
earlier
is not possible with these.
This will avoid confusions such as
the ones we described.
A fairly logical consequence that follows,
given that one and
only one unique_ptr can reference
a given memory area, is that
unique_ptrs cannot be copied.
Basically, in C++11, if I want to declare,
to initialize a unique_ptr,
then I will have to use the following
syntax.
So, unique_ptr. I must indicate what type
of memory area the
unique_ptr can point to.
So here I declare a new unique_ptr that
can point to an integer, and
of course I give it a name.
To initialize it, since it is a pointer, I
need an address
and so I can initialize it with the
address of a dynamically allocated object.
This is something I know how to do for
an integer for example, via
this kind of statement.
Now if I try
to create a copy
of this unique_ptr, by declaring a pointer
p1 and by copying the value
of p2, this is illegal in C++11.
This is to guarantee that there
cannot be two unique_ptr-type
pointers pointing to the same dynamically-
allocated memory area.
Thus, unique_ptrs cannot be
copied, but they can be
moved, that is, passed on farther.
C++11 implements this with the so-called
move semantic.
This concept goes beyond the scope
of this lecture, but I will
briefly outline it later.
So, about the syntax: to establish the
syntax, let's look at a small example
of declaration and initialization of
a unique_ptr.
Here, I declare a unique_ptr px,
which can point to an integer.
A unique_ptr is a pointer like any other
in the sense that it will contain
an address; here, it contains the address
of a dynamically-allocated memory area
for an integer.
Aside from that, unique_ptrs will be
used like any other pointer
we have discussed up until now.
For example, we can access the content
pointed to by the unique_ptr
by using the star operator, as we did with
C-style pointers.
We can of course also declare a vector,
a dynamic array
of unique_ptrs.
Here is an example of a dynamic array
named noms (TN: nom means "names")
and whose elements are unique_ptrs
capable of pointing to
memory areas with a character array type.
When we initialize this vector,
we make use of
dynamic allocation to get to the
following situation
So, our noms array contains two
elements, two cells, each of which
contains the address of a
dynamically-allocated object.
The first element contains the address
of a dynamically allocated area
containing the character array "Pierre",
and the second element of the vector
contains the address of a dynamically-
allocated memory area containing the
character array "Paul".
So here, each element of the array
points uniquely to a character array
thanks to the concept of
unique_ptr.
Last example to illustrate among others
the concept of moving
versus copying.
Here, imagine that in a program, we have a
Personne type
which is for example a structure
representing the concept of a person
and one of whose fields would be, for
example, the name of the person,
with a character array type.
Through the naissance (TN: means
"birth") function, we want to create a new object
of type Personne, and to return the address
of this object, stored in
a unique_ptr.
The line of code that handles creation
of this object is as follows.
Creation of the object is done
using dynamic allocation.
We dynamically create an object
of type Personne.
The address of this object is stored
in the bb variable which is of type
unique_ptr-to-Personne.
So let's imagine that afterwards, we
make the necessary initializations
for the bb variable, for example by
giving the name of the data structure
with the name passed on to the function,
and then we supply to the outside world
the address of the object that we
have just created.
So we end up in this situation.
We have a bb variable which contains the
address of a dynamically-allocated object
of type Personne, so the type that is stored
is Personne.
Now, let's place ourselves in the context
of use of this "naissance" function.
Here, I declare a variable adresse_quidam
(TN: means "address_individual") of
type unique_ptr-to-Personne, and
I initialize it using the
unique_ptr returned by the call to
the "naissance" function.
So here, we could imagine that we are
in this situation,
where the variable bb
contains the address of a Personne, a
person whose name is Pierre.
And here, we can imagine that what
we are doing in reality is
copying to value of bb
to another variable of type
unique_ptr which would be named
adresse_quidam.
So this might well appear to be a copy,
but in reality what is happening
is a move, meaning that the value
which was stored
in bb is moved to the new variable,
adresse_quidam
and that the variable bb is no
longer usable as-is,
i.e that we still have only one single
object pointing
to the personne object and that
we have not broken the fact that
only one unique_ptr can point to
a given object.
So here, we implicitly used what is known
in C++11 as the move semantic.
What happens in this particular context
is not a copy, but
a move.
C++11 knows, indeed, that at this step
we are effecting a move
and not a copy because the value that
we are assigning to the object of type
unique_ptr is in reality transient data
originating from a function call.
It is this transient data originating from
this function call which is assigned
to the unique_ptr, and in this case,
we know that a move was
made, and not a copy.
Unique_ptrs are smart pointers,
meaning that the
memory which was associated to them
is freed automatically, we do not
need to worry about it.
If however, we wanted to free this
memory explicitly,
it is also possible to do so, i.e to call
delete ourselves,
and so in this case, we would use a
instruction that is specific to these pointers,
the reset statement.
At that moment, call ptr.reset(), which
will result in freeing the memory
associated to this pointer
and assigning the nullptr value
to the smart pointer ptr.
Unique_ptrs are very secure; we have
just seen that they guarantee that
each pointer is unique in pointing to a given
memory area and so, this
guarantees a very secure use. This means
that it is recommended to use them
in any situation possible.
However, they obviously will not
cover every need
and in some cases, it is completely
inevitable to guarantee that two
different code fragments point to,
use, the same memory area.
In those cases, one will need other
types of smart pointers,
such as shared_ptr for example.
A shared_ptr is such that several of
them can point to the same
memory area.
Here we can imagine the situation
where we have
a code fragment "code1"
and a code fragment "code2"
which both point, via a pointer of type
shared_ptr, to the same
dynamically-allocated memory area
which is this one.
Technically, for it to be possible to
automatically free a memory area
referenced by shared_ptrs, it is
necessary to keep track of the
different code fragments,
which point to this memory area.
Thus, we can only deallocate this area
automatically once
no-one uses it anymore.
And there can be cyclic dependence
situations where we cannot
manage to free the memory correctly
when we use shared_ptrs.
In those cases, we will have to also
use weak_ptrs which will
allow us to break these cycles brought
about by the shared_ptrs.
This is of course highly advanced
compared to the contents of this lecture.
The essential message I wanted to pass on
is that these sort of tools exist,
without necessarily going into detail
about there use.
What is important to remember
is that if, in a simple situation,
we wish to use smart pointers and
we do not need
several pointers to be able to point to
the same memory area,
the preferred solution is definitely
unique_ptrs, which are secure and
hassle-free compared to other types
of smart pointers.
Pointers are a wide topic, and there
is still a lot to say,
especially about smart pointers.
We have simply presented these
briefly so that you know
that they exist.
For most cases, we focused
on understanding
classic, C-style pointers,
which you will get to encounter
very frequently in the literature.