We are now, in this section
of the course, Section 2.,
we are going to talk about
magnetic resonance imaging.
As you will see,
this is distinctly different
from the X-ray-based techniques
that we have discussed in Part 1.
I want to start now the introducing
of the magnetic resonance
of MRI.
I want to start out with, first,
some examples;
we'll start with examples
of animal models.
This is a high resolution scan,
MRI scan, of a mouse.
It's a whole body scan
at very high resolution,
and you can certainly appreciate
all the fine details
that are observable here,
particularly, in the soft tissue.
Here is another example
of blood vessels,
so here contrast agents were used
to depict the blood vessels here
in this mouse embryo.
Another example here
is brain function.
We are looking at the vascular
blood vessels inside the brain.
Here's the brain,
here's another brain scan,
looking at the activity
in the brain tissue
that can also be done with MRI.
Here's an example of a longitudinal study
looking at a stroke in the brain;
the development of the stroke.
One can see some bright areas here
and this is the Nissl staining that shows
the death of neurons--
that's done after the MRI scanning
has been done.
And finally, another example
that one can look at
is chemical compounds,
here phosphorus--
phosphocreatine ATP,
using spectroscopy of, in this case,
the rat brain.
One thing-- and this is really
an important message here--
is one thing that distinguishes MRI
from the previous modalities,
the other modalities,
is it has one instrument, one magnet.
But basically, it has
many modalities built into it.
Or, as we would call it,
many different contrast mechanisms.
Let me illustrate this
with the human brain.
We have here contrast mechanisms
exploited that's called FLAIR.
It highlights certain processes,
typically from multiple sclerosis.
Then we have here,
a contrast agent application;
we have here an image
of cerebral blood volume changes;
we have a mechanism called MTR that's
Magnetization Transfer Ratio imaging;
We have diffusion,
apparent diffusion coefficient or ADC
that's being measured here--
this is all the same patient--
and finally, we have
a biochemical measurement
of choline to N-acetyl aspartate
concentrations--
a map, showing changes here
always in the same lesion.
So, we take this, this has been
all done in the same patient,
pretty much in the same session,
and we're obtaining six different views
of the same process that's going on--
and this is exploiting the same principle,
the same detection principle,
the same instrumentation principle--
but there are many ways in which one
can manipulate the contrast with MRI,
and therefore,
what is important to be stressed here,
what I like to stress here,
is we have one magnet and many modalities.
We don't have an MRI as such.
An MRI as such does not exist,
and MRI comes always with a definition
of what particular contrast mechanism
is being imaged.
Let me go on with the example
of one magnet, many contrasts
in the rat brain.
We have phase imaging--
so we have a normal image here,
this traditional image--
and if one looks at the magnetic field
within the tissue,
one can see the different cortical layers
inside the brain.
We can look at the distribution
of glutamate,
which is the major excitatory
neurotransmitter in the brain.
One can look at transport of calcium,
by means of a tracer--
in this case it's manganese--
this is in response to activation,
showing higher activity
in cortical layer 3 and 4
upon a stimulation,
upon a specific task.
Or here, is finally an example
of quantifying cerebral blood flow
in the brain,
using a technique called
arterial spin labeling.
This is in an animal
anesthetized with α-chloralose.
This is a normal animal, and this is
an animal subjected to hypoglycemia,
that is low blood sugars.
So also here, not only in a human brain
but also in the animal brain,
we have many different contrasts
that we can obtain,
all with the same scanner and different
depictions of what is going on,
and these are just the examples
for the brain--
this of course holds true
for all the other organs as well.
So then, what are the essential
components of an MRI scanner?
And I want to give out here a scheme
that gives you an idea
of what's inside an MRI scanner,
and I will also highlight
the aspects of the MRI scanner
that we are going to deal with
in this series of lectures.
So here is a typical MRI scanner,
again covered in a nice cover--
patients don't want to see
the physics or the engineering--
and this is where you enter
the magnet room as a patient;
what you would typically see.
So, what is inside the scanner?
We have inside the scanner a magnet--
it's magnetic resonance,
so there's a big magnet inside the scanner
that's inside here.
You are going inside the magnet.
Inside the magnet we have
gradient coils, RF coils,
the patient table we can see here.
This is the equivalent of this scanner
for animal scans here;
so we use this smaller opening--
as we've seen
with all the other imaging techniques,
when it comes to small animal imaging,
rodent imagining,
the dimensions of the scanner
are being reduced,
at least in terms of the hole.
So, we have the magnet,
which is here, and this is the magnet here;
we have the gradient coils--
they are inside the cover,
we will not see them as patients--
they would be here.
And we have the radio frequency coil,
which is this thing here,
that pretty much looks like
a bird cage laying flat,
and it's actually called a bird cage.
If we take a magnet,
if we take the cover away,
then we'll look at the open cut,
then we can see quite a bit
of engineering and physics behind this;
a lot of copper, et cetera, that is
the magnet when you cut it open.
We don't see the magnet yet,
we just see the insides,
so that's the gradient coil system here.
So, if we take the entire system,
we plot it out,
and we look at all the components,
then we see lots of different components
that are important
in making a scanner operate
and yes, it is a complex machine.
However, we will not focus
on all the aspects
of what's involved in running
an MRI scanner.
We'll touch upon them where necessary
to understand a few of the consequences,
but we will not go into every detail.
What we will focus on
is the major elements of MRI,
and that is the nucleus,
we'll focus on the magnet,
we'll focus on the RF coil,
and we'll focus on the gradient coil.
Those are the elements of this scanner.
We will not focus on all the rest here,
the addition, the important engineering,
we'll not go into much detail
for the purpose of understanding
the fundamentals of MRI.
One thing with an MRI is it is a magnet,
and that magnet is typically,
in practice, always on.
It is typically cooled
by superconducting wires
that are cooled to
liquid helium temperature,
so, 4 Kelvin;
so it's cold inside there,
and the current will stay in there
for 1,000 years.
As it is superconducting,
the resistance of the wires
is essentially zero,
so the current will stay in there,
and the magnet is never being off.
So what are we looking at here--
what kind of magnetic field?
[inaudible] the magnetic field generated
by the MRI magnet.
The unit here is Tesla.
The Earth's magnetic field is roughly
5 times 10 to the minus five Tesla--
that's the magnetic field we're all
constantly experiencing.
Electromagnets-- so you take
just the copper wire, winded like this,
run a current through it--
you can produce such magnets,
but they will have a limit
of magnetic field strength
that is for imagining purposes,
typically below 1.5 Tesla.
For MRI, what we are looking at
is magnetic field strengths
in the range of 1-7 Tesla.
And this has a consequence:
we have a powerful magnet,
it is superconducting,
so this powerful magnet is always on.
We cannot come into the room,
and quickly turn it off--
unlike a CT scanner
where we can turn off
the X-ray tube
and we won't have radioactivity
being produced.
[inaudible] spec scanner
if we don't have traces in our bodies,
we are not exposed to any radioactivity,
but if you enter into a room
with an MRI magnet
you are entering a powerful magnet,
and this requires some precautions
that I want to illustrate now,
that one has to be cautious
around the magnet.
You can't smell the magnetic field,
you can't necessarily feel it,
and so it can have some surprises
in the observation,
when being around the magnet
without the necessary precautions,
and that just explains why we are asking
subjects, or visitors,
that come close to the magnets,
the take some extra precautions.
So, let's look at this example here.
In this video, what you are seeing
is an aluminum block that's placed
in front of the magnet
on the patient bed.
As the aluminum block is tipped over,
it falls over.
If you now look at the aluminum block
placed inside the magnet,
or close to the magnet--
so inside the magnetic field--
and as the aluminum block is tipped over,
it falls very slowly.
What is happening here is
that as the aluminum block falls,
changes orientation,
the magnetic flux in the aluminum changes,
so we have Faraday's law of induction.
So there are,
because of the magnetic field,
orientation across that block
is changing,
we have induced currents.
These induced currents are producing
themselves a magnetic field
that counteracts the main magnetic field,
and so, this produces a force
that opposes the motion of the magnet.
This principle is used in
electromagnetic braking for example
in the more modern hybrid cars,
when we brake without using
the physical contact,
or in electrical trains.
Here, in this example,
what is being done here,
is a tennis ball filled with nails--
nails are ferromagnetic,
so they are attracted
by the magnetic field--
and the person is letting go
of the tennis ball
filled with ferro magnetic nails,
and it goes tunk-tunk-tunk into
the scanner and then sticks to the side.
What is happening here
is the more critical effect--
that is, we have
a ferromagnetic iron object
that is exposed to a change
in magnetic field,
so if we have a difference
in magnetic field across that object--
and therefore, it exerts a force
on the object,
and that object is being attracted
such that it ultimately enters
into the scanner.
The next example is a video surveillance
camera of a friend of mine,
who posted it on his YouTube channel.
So you see the two gentlemen here
were asked to enter the magnet room
and put up a support structure, a frame,
for putting some shelves,
so one can put blankets and cushions,
et cetera, into the room.
Notice the one person who has
in his hands a battery-operated drill.
So they obviously want to do
some drilling on this structure,
or tightening some screws.
As we are watching this video,
you might notice at a certain time point
that he is now without the drill,
and as you are observing the two gentlemen
they are now looking inside the magnet.
So, what has happened?
The drill has, most likely,
some ferromagnetic components to it--
or at least the battery,
batteries are typically ferromagnetic--
and as he was moving around in the room,
he wasn't paying attention to the magnet
that is in the back of the room,
and as he got too close to the magnet,
the magnetic field attracted the drill;
he could no longer hold onto it,
and it flew inside the magnet.
In this case, there was nothing
of major consequence happening--
the drill was removed and aside
from the scare, nothing happened.
However, in the context
of medical application,
this is a far more serious issue.
And here is an illustration
of an experiment
showing the same effect,
with a gas bottle,
just an ordinary gas bottle,
oxygen bottle, you have
lots of oxygen bottles in the hospital.
They are placing this bottle
on the patient bed,
and as you can see,
instead of putting a patient
they are putting a watermelon
as our subject
inside the RF coil,
where the head would be.
The experiment that was here done,
is to illustrate what happens
if a magnetic object
is being put too close to the magnet,
when it starts to get attracted
by the magnet,
what then happens.
Obviously, when it gets closer,
as we've seen with the drill,
or the nail-filled ball,
as it gets close to the magnet,
the difference in magnetic field
creates a net force on the object.
And the force as we see
in this demonstration,
accelerates this gas bottle,
it accelerates it towards the watermelon.
It has an impact on the watermelon,
and the watermelon is being crushed.
We see this at the end of the video,
where they go to the back of the magnet
and they show how much
this watermelon has been crushed.
So, extreme caution is necessary
with ferromagnetic objects,
and this is particularly difficult
in the medical context.
This happened in the beginning
of this millennium
in the state of New York;
that a subject, a cancer patient,
for control purposes was being scanned.
A nurse heard the word
"oxygen bottle,"
went to the hallway,
grabbed the oxygen bottle, walked with
the oxygen bottle into the room;
the oxygen bottle got attracted,
and unfortunately, for the subject
..the subject was still in the magnet--
that created, of course,
an unfortunate death of this subject.
The difficulty here is,
as medical professionals are trained
to react in emergency situations,
they are not all trained to work
and live around the magnet,
and so, the first response
is to help the patient,
and so, yes, you grab the oxygen bottle,
you run into the room,
and the oxygen bottle is being attracted;
that's the situation here.
It requires specific measures;
the measures are to take off
all magnetic things that we carry
on ourselves,
and in the case of a medical emergency,
in an MRI scanner--
what one would do is actually,
the first reaction,
is to take the subject out of the magnet
and out of the magnet room,
and then only start coming in
with medical equipment.
CPR is obviously fine,
but one has to be extremely vigilant
because we do not feel, we do not smell,
we do not see the magnetic field.
So, to give you an illustration,
here's an example of a magnet,
with a chair attached to it.
This chair has obviously a lot
of ferromagnetic material
and you can see
the quite considerable effort
that it takes to remove that chair;
it's a chair with wheels on it,
so it somehow got too close
to the magnet,
was suddenly attracted, and bang!
it went into the magnet.
And you can appreciate from
the effort that's being done
how strong these forces are
on the chair.
And obviously, once one is away
where the magnetic field
doesn't vary a lot,
then this force is
substantially being reduced
and we have less to consider.
It really is a matter of the vicinity
of the magnet,
where the magnetic field changes
very strongly.
So this is a danger of MRI scanners.
It's not a biological risk, it's a danger;
it's just like walking
up and down the stairs--
if you don't pay attention,
you can fall and break your neck.
Here we have to be around the magnet,
we have to be cautious, making sure
that ferromagnetic objects
stay far away from our subject
and from the scanner,
and then, we are OK.
Another issue that I want to address
is of some historical interest,
especially with the perspective of Europe.
But the question is-- let's say
we forget about ferromagnetic objects
and we're just ourselves
walking around the magnet.
The question is what kind of exposures
of magnetic field changes
can we subject ourselves to?
I want to make here the example,
by comparison,
comparing the effects that we see
with transcranial magnetic stimulation.
Transcranial magnetic stimulation
is a technique used in neuroscience
to investigate the functioning
of certain brain areas.
It is allowed in healthy volunteers
and these policies
are applied quite frequently.
I want to relate what we are--
if we move around the magnet,
what this means in relation to TMS.
Here's a TMS scanner;
here's the coil that produces
the magnetic field;
the subject here.
What is being done
is one produces a magnetic field,
B_zero, with this coil
that goes from zero to two Tesla
in roughly 100 microseconds.
If we take a conservative estimate,
this amounts to 20,000 Tesla per second
change in magnetic field, dB/dt.
What I want to do with this calculation,
just to give you an idea,
to produce a similar change
in magnetic field,
how fast would we have to walk
to a 7 Tesla scanner
over a distance of 1.4.meters?
We'll assume we go over 1.4 meters
from zero to seven Tesla,
and we want to expose ourselves to
the same change of magnetic field per time.
So we have a change in magnetic field
per distance, which is 5 Tesla per meter,
we have 7 divided by 1.4,
so this gives us 5 Teslas per meter.
We want to now have a change
in magnetic field per time--
so that's velocity over distance--
that gives us per time
times the change in magnetic field.
We want this to be 20,000 Tesla per second.
We can solve this,
so we can calculate what velocity
would we need
to produce a magnetic field change
of 20,000 Tesla per second.
The calculation here,
as you can easily verify,
produces a velocity of 4,000 meters
per second, or 14,000 kilometers per hour.
This is essentially, ten times
the Earth's rotational speed.
That's a tremendous velocity.
This is is very crude,
and is, by no means, meant to be correct,
but let's go a little bit
into finer details.
And we'll look at Faraday's law
in more detail.
We have Faraday's law, which says
the induced voltage
is equal to the area times the change
in magnetic field per time.
So we're obviously having--
with the transcranial magnetic stimulation--
we’re not having the same area exposed
to the magnetic field
as we have with our body,
as we run towards the magnet,
so we'll correct for the surface area.
The TMS coil with a radius of 5 cm,
we can calculate an area of .008 m2.
We'll estimate that the upper trunk
is roughly half a square meter
of surface area-- we'll correct that;
and then we are getting, from correcting
for the fact that our area is bigger
than the area of the TMS coil,
to have the same induced voltage
in our body,
we are obtaining a velocity
of 63 meters per second,
or 220 kilometers per hour.
So, if we run towards the magnet,
and we go from zero to seven Tesla
over a distance of 1.4 meters,
we are going to be exposed
in the upper trunk to voltages
that correspond to those that
we are exposed to in the brain with TMS
at 220 kilometers per hour.
What we have to consider is
for most modern magnets
most of the static magnetic field
is actually within the bore of the magnet--
that is, within the structure--
so we actually, if we are on the outside,
we can't even expose ourselves
to the full 7 Tesla.
That also means that most of the changes
happening in there,
we don't start at zero Tesla,
we don't end at 7 Tesla.
We have also the fact that the distance
is more like 7 meters
over which we approach the magnet,
and not 1.4 meters.
So, if we actually wanted
to expose ourselves
to the same effect
around a magnetic field,
then the equivalent speed to produce
the same voltages as we have with TMS
would be several-fold higher
than 220 kilometers per hour.
And, let's be honest, in reality,
our speed is going to be
already two orders of magnitude
lower than what is here.
So it is my opinion here
that the considerations about motion
around a static magnetic field--
around an MRI scanner--
are so low, the induced voltages
are well beyond any concern
that we should have and are having.