So the question that now arises
is how is nuclear magnetism generated?
What is its basis?
And we will here
talk about the classical view,
more on a classical view
than the strict quantum-mechanical view
but I will make some references to
the underlying quantum-mechanical theory.
Now it is known from nuclear physics
that a nucleus typically has
an angular momentum,
which we know from our physics classes
is denoted L but here it is called P.
So we can envisage
we have the nucleus here
and the nucleus has an angular momentum.
Now we have with an angular momentum,
classically--
now we'll take here the classical view--
classically we associate
with an angular momentum
a rotating motion.
So we have a rotating motion
and we'll stick with the classical view
because this gives us an intuitive feeling
where the magnetism comes from.
So if we feel like in the description
that the nucleus is rotating,
since the nucleus is positively charged,
there is a rotation
of the electrical charge.
As you can imagine, it's like the earth--
it's positively charged, it's rotating
so at the equator the charge is moving
and moving charge implies a current.
So here is the angular momentum
and since we have a rotating current--
here's the rotating current--
so we'll associate this
with a rotating current
and such a rotating current
now is associated with a dipole moment.
It's just like a current.
This is again the classical picture.
It's not perfect
but it helps us understand
where nuclear magnetism comes from.
So we'll associate it
just like with a ring current
with a dipole moment mu
that we'll call mu here.
Now in terms of magnetism
we can picture the nucleus
as if it was a bar magnet.
The magnetism of the nucleus
acts as if it is a bar magnet.
It's not a bar magnet per se
but it acts electromagnetically
like a bar magnet.
It has a dipole magnetic field
associated with it.
So that's the intuitive reason
why with some nuclei
we have an angular momentum.
Once we have an angular momentum
we have with it associated
a dipole moment.
Now if we look at a magnetic moment
of an individual spin in a induction field
so this dipole moment,
this magnetic moment is given by mu,
is equal to gamma
times the angular momentum.
Gamma here is called
the gyromagnetic ratio,
it's an empircal constant.
There's a more profound theory behind it
on what dictates the gyromagnetic ratio
for a given nucleus,
but for our intents and purposes
it suffices to say that
this is an empirical constant.
Now what we know from quantum mechanics
is that the angular momentum
of a nucleus is quantized.
So it has, for the z component
of the angular momentum,
it has 2I + 1 values
and they take on the values m-i.
So here is, for example, where i can go
from minus the angular momentum--
the z component,
the quantum number m here--
can go from minus i to plus i
and increments in values of 1.
So here, in this particular example,
we go from minus 3/2 to minus 1/2
plus 1/2 plus 3/2, that's the z component
of the angular momentum.
We can calculate
the total angular momentum
and this is given by this equation here.
So it's the quantum number,
the angular momentum number here i
times i + 1 times h over 2 pi.
So if we take this for a spin 1/2,
so the spin 1/2 can take the values
1/2 and minus 1/2 the angular momentum.
In this case, the total angular momentum
is times the Boltzmann constant
times square root of 3/4 pi
that we can verify
by putting here into i: 1/2.
So that's for a spin 1/2.
So let's look at some isotopes
and the gyromagnetic ratio gamma.
And first we want to introduce
some isotopes that do not carry
an angular momentum.
Those are carbon-12, oxygen-16, et cetera.
They have typically even mass
and even atomic number.
So they don't carry a nuclear spin,
they don't carry
a nuclear angular momentum.
Then we have nuclei with spin 1/2.
These are the proton,
the hydrogen nucleus H-1, C-15,
and nitrogen-15.
Another one is phosphorus-31.
They are characterized by a spherical
discharged distribution in the nucleus.
And then we have the spins
that are larger than spin 1/2.
Deuterium is an example, boron-11,
sodium-23, lithium-6 is another one,
lithium-7, et cetera.
Depending on whether they have
odd or even mass
and an odd atomic number
they carry either half integers--
so they're 3/2, 5/2, et cetera--
or a whole integer,
their spin 1, 2, 3, et cetera.
What's particular about these nuclei
is that they have
an ellipsoidal charge distribution.
They generate within the nucleus
in a electric field
and it's a so-called
quadripolar electrical field.
They have distinct different properties
typically than the spin 1/2.
Now let's look at some examples here.
So we have the isotope listed.
We have the spin,
whether it's spin 1/2 et cetera.
The gyromagnetic ratio.
And here we list the gyromagnetic ratio
not as the gyromagnetic ratio
but we divide it by 2 pi
so this gives us a number
that relates the Larmor frequency to the--
that relates the frequency to the teslas.
And finally we have the abundance.
So what do we see here?
We have hydrogen spin 1/2,
gyromagnetic ratio is 42 MHz/T
and it's basically
every hydrogen atom is a H1.
Then we have deuterium, this has a spin 1
so it's a quadripolar nucleus,
very low gyromagnetic ratio
and the abundance is about 0.01%.
Phosphorus-31 is a spin 1/2,
gyromagnetic ratio is about 40% of that
of the hydrogen--of the proton--
and the abundance is 100%.
Sodium: 100% natural abundance here.
It's a spin 3/2
and the gyromagnetic ratio is roughly
a fourth of what the same holds
for carbon-13,
but the abundance for carbon-13 is 1.1%.
And fluorine-19 is almost the same
gyromagnetic ratio as protons
and the abundance is also very high,
we just don't have a lot of fluorine
in our bodies.
Now for reasons of the abundance
and the presence
we will be mostly concentrating
this course on considering
the hydrogen nucleus--that is the proton--
as the source of the MR signal.
And for all intents and purposes
suffice it to know
that there are the nuclei around,
how to understand them
but most of what we are going to deal with
is focusing on the hydrogen nucleus,
that is the proton.
It has spin 1/2.
It has a high gyromagnetic ratio,
and we'll see shortly
why this is important.
And what's also important,
it is present in our bodies
in raw abundance.
So far I've explained that some nuclei
carry an angular momentum,
they therefore carry a magnetic moment
but now how does this generate
a macroscopic nuclear magnetization?
And that's the question
we're going to address here.
So let's look at the energy
of a magnetic dipole
in an external magnetic field
and we'll stick here
to the classical description.
The energy is given by the scalar product
of the dipole moment
with the external magnetic field.
And it is given by mu times cosine--
that's because of the scalar product--
or if we say mu cosine
that is the z component
of the dipole moment times B-0.
That is the energy of a magnetic dipole.
Now this energy is minimal
when the magnetic dipole
is aligned with the magnetic field.
That is actually used.
Where is that used? Or where was it used?
Well think about Christopher Columbus,
he needed to know where the North Pole is
so he had to use a way to identify
the magnetic North Pole
and this was done with magnetized needles
orienting in a liquid
parallel to the earth's magnetic field.
So that was used in navigation.
Now what's behind this
is that a dipole will align itself
to find the minimal energy
and there's a torque exerted on the dipole
that is given by the magnetic dipole,
is vector product of magnetic dipole
with the external magnetic field.
So let's just demonstrate this
in the following experiment
where we will demonstrate the force
of the external magnetic field
on the dipole with a magnetic dipole.
As mentioned in the course, the energy
of a magnetic moment in atomic--
a nuclear magnetic moment
in an external magnetic field
is not dissimilar to what happens
with a macroscopic magnet
in external magnetic field.
And I want to illustrate this
with this experiment here.
We have a magnet here which can rotate,
so it can freely rotate.
Here is a--it's attached here
to show the torque.
And here we have two electromagnets.
These two electromagnets
will develop the magnetic field
when I turn them on.
So right now there is no force on this.
The magnet is like this.
And when I now turn on the magnetic field,
you can see that the magnet
tries to align itself.
If we didn't have here this force meter,
it would align itself perfectly
with the magnetic field.
If I reverse the polarity
of the magnetic field,
the motion is in the other direction
in this sense.
I can see if I can illustrate this
if I loosen this,
then now here you can see
the perfect alignment if I don't have
the force attached to it
which is meant here to illustrate
the development of the force.
So like a macroscopic magnet
in a magnetic field,
nuclear magnetic moments have a tendency
to align themselves
in one direction or the other
and their energy that they have
in the magnetic field
depends on their orientation
but the minimum is found when the moment
is as much aligned as possible
with the magnetic field.
Okay, now we have stated the energy
as a function of the z component
of the magnetic moment.
So it's this term here--mu-z times B-0.
So we will now look at
the quantum mechanical description
and we know that the z component
of the angular momentum
therefore of the magnetic dipole
is quantized,
has discrete values
and it's given by this expression.
This is the gyromagnetic ratio
and these are the terms
that we have introduced
for the angular momentum
just in the previous slide.
So we have energies that depend on
the level of the z component
of the magnetic moment
that is the angular momentum.
Again, m-i can go from minus i to plus i.
For a spin 1/2 it's minus 1/2 to plus 1/2.
So if we said for spin 1/2
we'll take the energy level below
so that is minus gamma,
h over 4 pi times B-0
here's the energy level.
This is for the m of 1/2
and we'll say that our m2
spins in that energy level.
Then we have the higher energy level,
that's where the dipole is opposite--
in opposite orientation--
here the energy is now positive.
It's spin 1/2 so it's plus minus 1/2.
The calculation's given
so m equals minus 1/2.
You can verify this
with this equation here.
And we'll say we have m1 spins
in that energy level.
We now have an energy difference.
Whether the nucleus it spins
pointing upwards or downwards,
it has an energy difference
depending on its orientation
that is given by the gyromagnetic ratio
times Boltzmann constant divided by 2 pi
times the magnetic field B-0.
Now we know from Boltzmann statistics
or a Boltzmann distribution,
we know that we are going to get
an unequal population of energy levels.
This is dictated
by Boltzmann distribution.
And the relationship between
the number of spins
in the higher energy level--that is N1--
to the number of nuclei
in the lower energy level,
this relationship is given
by e to the minus
the energy difference divided by
the thermal energy, which is kT.
K is the Boltzmann constant,
here is its value given.
It's not really important.
But what is important
if you look at this ratio,
and you do the math, you plug this in,
you calculate the delta E divide it by kT,
at 310 kelvin--which is roughly
our body temperature--
you'll find that at a field of 1 Tesla,
if we look at the proton spins
so we take the gyromagnetic ratio
of the hydrogen-1 nucleus--the proton--
then you find that
for every million protons
in the higher energy level
there's a million protons,
a million and one proton
in the lower energy level.
That makes a difference,
an excess in difference
between the two energy levels
of one out of a million.
So basically, as a rough approximation,
we can say N1 is the number of spins
in the upper energy level
is almost equal to the number of spins
in the lower energy level
where N--and we'll call this N/2--
where N is the total number of spins
or hydrogen nuclei present in our voxel.
So this is the Boltzmann distribution.
Now if you look at the situation here,
if we are now looking at
the distribution of the spins
we have them all in the lower energy level
and none in the higher energy level.
Is such a state even possible?
Well, in theory it is.
This basically means
that N1/N2 goes to zero
and this is if we let
the temperature go to zero.
Then e^-(1/0) becomes e^-(infinity)
that becomes zero.
So if we cool our sample down
to micro- or nanokelvin,
you'll be essentially getting something
at approximative state.
This is the ground state of the system.
For us in biomedical imaging,
this is not very interesting.
We cannot really cool down
our subjects for imaging.
So if we raise the temperature
now gradually,
what we have is that the thermal energy
will bump some of the spins
into the higher energy level.
And as we increase the temperature
we have more and more
in the higher energy level.
We'll still have a certain difference
in the population
unless we have the temperature
go to infinity, at very high temperatures,
then they are truly equalized.
That we can see again here
if the temperature goes to infinity,
this goes to zero, e^-0 is equal to 1.
So we have this population difference
that is generated
between the nuclei
in the higher energy level
and the nuclei in the lower energy level.
And this difference is important.
Before we go on though,
I want to make the point here
that we have also these transitions
between the energy levels
is induced by photons.
Photon is the interaction boson
for electrodynamics.
So we can associate
this energy difference here to delta E
with a photon in the [h mu]
and then we can look this up
what this value is, to relate this
to the x-ray techniques
that we have been discussing
in the first half of this course.
And then we can see actually
that for NMR--nuclear magnetic resonance
or magnetic resonance--we have
the energies are in this range.
So they are in this wavelength range here.
We are well beyond microwave wavelengths,
so it's a very long wavelength.
And what is important here--
we are working with non-ionizing radiation
in magnetic resonance.