So now we have dealt with
the difference in population,
we have dealt with the introduction
of a magnetic moment.
Now we are going to have to
address the question:
"How does this generate
a macroscopic magnetic field?"
And this is what we call
the magnetization.
So how do we see this motion?
Now we'll do--by the following analogy
again, to classical physics--
we'll view each spin, each nucleus
as a magnetic dipole mu--
that is, we can visualize it
without it having any resemblance
to the actual situation.
It's just the electromagnetic properties
but we can think of it
as a virtual tiny bar magnet.
Now classically, as I mentioned before,
the magnetic field
exerts a torque on that dipole,
a torque tau
and this torque is given by
the vector product
of the magnetic moment of that spin
with the external magnetic field.
Now we'll take the second law of rotations
and here P denotes the angular momentum.
So we know from
the second law of rotations
that the derivative of angular momentum
with time is equal to the net torque.
Here we have one torque.
And we can now use this
and substitute the angular momentum
with the magnetic moment.
We'll do this on both sides
and then we are getting that
the derivative, classically, of a spin.
The derivative of its magnetic moment
is equal to the magnetic moment
times gamma B
where B is the external field.
So this is the motion
for an individual spin equation
of motion, classically.
Now if we sum over
all the magnetic moments
that are in our voxel,
all the hydrogen nuclei,
all the protons that we have in there,
we sum all the magnetic moments
then we get the macroscopically measured
magnetization.
So this is--we define this magnetization
as the sum of all magnetic moments
present in our voxel.
Then we can do the summation
over this differential equation
that we have here and we obtain
the so-called Larmor equation,
which is given here by the derivative of
the magnetization with time
is equal to minus gamma B cross M,
that's the vector product.
Now what does this Larmor equation
describe?
Have you seen a similar equation already?
Well, let's look at this.
So what does this Larmor equation
describe?
And to make the analogy, I'll go back
to your first year physics course
and we'll look at rotational kinematics.
We'll do a brief digression here.
We've had, for a circular motion,
we had the relationship between velocity,
angular velocity and the radius
of our circular motion.
And if you look at this in vector form,
we had velocity is equal to
the vector product of the angular velocity
with the position of our object.
Now I can rewrite this equation
for our circular motion
by replacing the definition of velocity,
which is the derivative
of the position with time,
and that is equal to
the vector product of omega cross r.
Now this motion, we have seen
in the first year course,
this describes the rotation
of the vector r about the vector omega
with a frequency of omega divided by 2π.
So we have here
the angular velocity vector.
I will draw now the position vector r,
here.
I'll put the tip of the position
of our object in motion.
That's our object-- so the vector r
describes the position of this object.
And that's exactly the motion that we see.
We have the component of the position
perpendicular to omega,
which moves in a circular motion,
it rotates.
And the component that's parallel
to omega is stationary, it is constant
because we can see here,
we can always decompose the vector r
into one that's parallel
and perpendicular to omega,
the one that's parallel,
the vector product is null
so that component
does not change with time.
So that's essentially that motion
that we classically have
for the position vector.
Now in this equation here,
I can substitute the position vector r
with any quantity,
be it angular momentum L,
be it the magnetization vector,
and I'll have an equation
that is formally equivalent
to what we have here.
I'll substitute r with M,
I'll substitute omega with minus gamma B
and you can see that mathematically,
the two equations
are perfectly homologous, analogous,
they describe the same motion for now,
for a different vector.
So if the r does--around omega--
does a motion like this,
then the M--the magnetization--
will do a motion around B
in the same fashion.
And this motion we call precession
so what we have now
is the Larmor equation describes
the precession of the magnetization
around the magnetic field B
with a frequency that's given
by gamma B over 2π.
So this is important,
this motion of precession
of the magnetization
about the magnetic field,
this relationship is very important.
We're going to use it
over and over again in the next weeks.
So what is precession?
And here I'll go back again
to classical mechanics.
We'll take a very simple experiment.
We'll have a wheel
that is suspended on a string.
The wheel has a certain mass
and the wheel turns
with a certain angular velocity.
So if it turns with this angular velocity
the wheel will develop, here,
an angular momentum L,
here indicated by the blue vector.
The wheel is suspended at the point O
and we can now make some observations
in the experiment,
and this we will demonstrate.
Okay, as mentioned in the course,
we have an analogy
in the motion of magnetization
with classical mechanics
and this is the experiment
I want to illustrate this.
We have the wheel suspended here
at the yellow wire.
The yellow wire
will maintain its position here.
I will give it a spin so it will develop
an angular momentum
and from the equations of motion
that we've discussed
from classical mechanics,
there will be a torque
from this string tension
that will force the angular momentum
into a motion of precession.
We've established in classical mechanics
that this motion of precession,
of the angular momentum vector
corresponds to one of precession.
So I will now spin it this way
so the angular momentum
points in this direction.
So here we have the wheel now turning
and now when I cut the wire here,
we can see that there is now the motion--
the angular momentum vector
is now going on a circular motion.
That is the motion of precession.
This motion does require
the presence of an angular momentum.
If there is no angular momentum
associated with the wheel
we of course have--
it just falls down as such.
So I can also start this experiment
this way.
I don't need the wire. Again,
this demonstrates motion of precession.
Now as we have seen in the demonstration
the motion of the axis of the wheel
is circular about the point O
and it has a constant angular velocity,
which is vertical to the angular momentum.
Here's the center of mass of our wheel
and we will now calculate the motion here.
Now the motion that we've seen
for the angular momentum is circular
so we know that the precession equation--
that is here again
now for the angular momentum--
is valid in describing
the motion of the angular momentum.
Now we want to calculate here
the precession frequency
because it bears some analogy
to the magnetization.
So we have our angular momentum.
Our center of mass is a distance r
away from the suspension point.
We have the mass here, that's one fourth.
The wheel does not fall
as we've seen in the experiment
so we have the string tension,
which is the same,
is the weight of the wheel upwards.
Now we can calculate the derivative
of the angular momentum,
which is equal to the torque.
We have only one torque that acts on here.
Whether we use point O
or the center of mass as a reference point
we'll end up with the same equation,
so I won't make the distinction here.
It is r cross force,
so this minus if I put the force
before the r.
That's the definition of torque.
So we have the torque in this direction
and this gives us the orientation
of the change of angular momentum.
Now I'll rewrite the equation here
by dividing by the norm of the vector r
and multiplying by its length.
So length here, length here,
but I'll put it here.
Now, the vector r divided by its length
is basically a vector that has unit length
so it's a unitary vector.
And I will use the fact that the axis,
the orientation of the axis of the wheel
and the orientation
of the angular momentum
are largely colinear so I can replace
r over r with L over L,
which is what we are now going to do here.
And this gives us this equation here.
So we now have replaced this term here
by this term
and then we get this equation.
If I regroup this then we have
the derivative of the angular momentum
is some term times the angular momentum
and this is essentially
our precession frequency.
I'll use the definition
of the angular momentum,
so it's I omega,
I as being the moment of inertia,
and then we have the precession frequency
is equal to the radius times the mass
times gravitational acceleration--the g--
divided by I omega.
So that's our precession frequency here
derived.
Compare this to the equation
that we have here--
we have the omega here,
we have this value--
and to the equation of the magnetization.
It is basically our magnetization
does a motion just like a spinning top.
And hence, we can look at now
some factors that increase--
if you look at the wheel,
if the mass of the wheel increases
the precession frequency increases.
Well, this is linked to--
plays the same role as--
the gyromagnetic ratio
and hence, because the motion is similar
to that of a gyroscope,
the gamma is called gyromagnetic ratio.
And then we have also
the gravitational pull,
if we have more gravitational pull,
our wheel turns faster
so the gravitational pull takes the role
of the external magnetic field.
So this is illustrated in this video
that we are seeing.
So we are first seeing--
what we are seeing is a gyroscope,
a spinning top rotating
just like we have here on the animation,
rotating first vertically.
It's put in an elevator
and this elevator is then let fall
in freefall to the ground.
The first experiment
is not very interesting.
We see that the gyroscope
detaches from the support.
The second experiment
that we are looking at--
the second gyro-drop--
here we have the gyroscope precessing
just like we've seen for the wheel
and that gyroscope--
the minute it is no longer exposed
to gravitation,
the minute there is no longer a torque
exerted on the gyroscope,
it stops immediately precessing.
That's as if we had magically turned off
the gravitation--same effect--
or if we had turned off
the magnetic field.