By now we have learned quite a bit
about magnetic resonance,
and I want to recap the essentials,
as we know them so far.
We have a nuclear equilibrium
magnetization M_0 that develops.
If you enter a magnet,
your nuclei in your body
will develop a nuclear
equilibrium magnetization.
This magnetization
is given by the difference
in the number of spins
in the upper and lower energy level--
the difference between two
times their magnetic moment.
I will rewrite this equation here--
so, will write it in this form:
I will have now N_1 / N_2,
where we can use
the Boltzman distribution.
So, N_1 / N_2, the Boltzman distribution
has been used here.
And now what we will do is,
we will use the linearization
because we have said Δ E / k T
is very small,
so e to the - x
can be approximated by (1 - x),
if x is very small compared to 1.
And then with this linearization
of the equation
we have, the magnetization
is given by this term here,
and then I will substitute the Δ E
with the term
that we have seen previously,
and this is now the nuclear magnetization,
macroscopic equilibrium magnetization
that we have.
Now we will substitute for the fact
that N_2 is essentially
half of all the spins--
this is to a very good approximation true,
and then we obtain this expression here.
So the magnetization is given
by some constants of the system:
Boltzman constant, temperature
we can assume as constant,
Boltzman constant, Planck's constant,
the dipole moment
and then we have gyromagnetic ratio,
B_0 and the number of spins.
So this is the resulting relationship,
and I will stress here--
it is good to understand
this relationship,
some dependencies here.
And we have the magnetization here
increases with the following terms:
the number of spins--
so that is essentially
the number of molecules.
If we increase N,
then the magnetization increases.
If we increase the magnetic field,
then the magnetization increases--
that's this term here B_0.
If we increase the gyromagnetic ratio γ,
then the thermodynamic
equilibrium magnetization increases.
So, taking all this together,
for magnetic resonance imaging,
which nucleus
is the most favorable to look at?
If we look at these three values here,
we can control experimentally only one--
that's the magnetic field
that's produced by the magnet
that we construct.
The number of spins
is given by the organ under investigation,
the gyromagnetic ratio by the nucleus.
So we need to find a nucleus
with a high gyromagnetic ratio
and a high number of spins.
And so this is essentially
the hydrogen nucleus,
H1 is the proton, has the highest γ,
as we have seen before,
and water is highly concentrated.
Whether we like it or not,
typically 80% of our body is water.
So for MRI we are mainly focusing
on imaging the hydrogen atom in water.
So, we will take the Larmor equation here,
and here I want to introduce the term
that we have--from this we can glean--
the Larmor frequency,
which is given by γ B_0 / (2 π),
that's in hertz, so it's a frequency;
if we take angle velocity
in radian per second
then the ω_L,
the Lamor frequency, is γ B_0.
This we have to bear in mind.
One thing that is non-negotiable
in magnetic resonance
is a convention
about the reference system,
the coordinate system.
The static magnetic field B_0
that we generate with our magnet
the static magnet, the magnetic field
generated by our scanner.
That magnetic field
is by definition always along z.
We do not negotiate
this convention--it is fixed.
So that is always
along the magnetic field--it's along z.
Then we have
the equilibrium magnetization
is also along z.
The thermodynamic
equilibrium magnetization
is always parallel along z.
And I want to give a great credit here
to Edward Purcell,
who discovered nuclear magnetic resonance
and received the Nobel Prize
for Physics in 1952.
Quantum mechanics will tell you
that the spin will never align
with the magnetic field--
there is always a transverse component.
However, the thermodynamic
equilibrium magnetization
is always along z and does not have
a transverse component,
and in the Appendix that we provide
as PDF on this course
the explanation is provided
by the random phase approximation
of equilibrium magnetization,
so why there is no
net transverse component
of the magnetization
at thermodynamic equilibrium.
We need a magnet to generate
a magnetic field that's along z.
This results in a separation of the spins
in the upper and lower energy level,
which creates a thermodynamic
equilibrium magnetization M_0.
We will call the main
magnetic field always B_0,
and we will call
the equilibrium magnetization always N_0.
Now, if we look at the energy difference
here, the Δ E,
we find it is actually very small,
and if you calculate this,
you will find that this is on the order
of micro-electron-volts.
So, there is one consequence,
we are using non-ionizing
electromagnetic fields
for magnetic resonance.
So, that' good--that is different
from the X-ray techniques.
But given that this term here depends
on the magnitude of the Δ E here--
this enters linearly,
so as we increase the energy difference
between the energy levels,
we increase the magnetization--
there is also a consequence--
it is insensitive.
So the following statement
is certainly true:
MR, magnetic resonance, is safe--
we are dealing
with not ionizing radiation--
but it is insensitive.
We cannot imagine to do an MR experiment
with concentrations
on the order of picomolar--
there are just not enough molecules there
to produce a measurable
nuclear magnetization
that we can reasonably detect in the body.
So therefore we would ideally like
to increase the sensitivity,
and how can we do that?
We have seen just on the previous slide
that the equilibrium magnetization
depends on a number of factors
that are given by the nucleus
and some universal constants,
and temperature, if course,
which is more or less also given.
So, the only parameter
that is open for manipulation
is the external magnetic field B_0.
And here is an example
of comparing a scan of the lower abdomen
at 0.2 Tesla and 1.5 Tesla.
If you look here, the image is grainy,
and it gets much sharper
here, at 1.5 Tesla.
If we take the spine here,
we have, again, 0.2 Tesla here--
grainy image--we see very nice details,
but a very crisp image at 1.5 Tesla.
So, comparing the image, the sensitivity
at lower field and higher field,
we notice a clear improvement
in sensitivity.
Here is another example--
that is brain function--
it's functional imaging--
we will discuss that in Lecture 12.
This is a comparison of 1.5 with 4 Tesla--
clearly, the sensitivity
increases substantially
with higher magnetic field.
Here we have an example
of MRI of the breast.
This is a standard MRI.
We are seeing something here
that is suspicious.
It's a bit clearer here,
but this is a standard breast image,
and here is a breast image
with the fat signal removed--
we will discuss that in two weeks,
how this is removed--
and then one can see clearly
at 3 Tesla here compared to 1.5 Tesla.
One can clearly see
the potentially neoplastic lesion here,
because the signal is not related to fat,
so clearly an improvement in specificity
with the higher magnetic field.
Now, one thing that we need to remember
for this course, this week and so on,
the theoretically
maximum possible MR signal
is dictated by the equilibrium
nuclear magnetization M_0.
This is a given of the system.
We cannot go beyond that.
So, any mechanism to generate contrast
results in a reduction in magnetization.
We will discuss in the weeks to come
how this happens.
So, we are limited by the thermodynamic
equilibrium nuclear magnetization M_0
in our sensitivity
that gives us a maximum signal
that is possible.