Now, we are going to explore the motion
described by the Larmor equation.
And for understanding
the motion of magnetization,
it is important to introduce a concept
on how to simplify
the description of the motion--
how to make it more accessible
understanding what exactly happens.
And this simplification is based on
using a rotating reference frame.
And why do we want to do this?
Well, first I want to go and explain
what is a rotating reference frame.
A rotating reference frame is a frame
that rotates about the z axis
in the laboratory frame--
so that's our reference frame
will rotate around the z axis--
we'll assume the magnetic field
is vertical in this case.
So why would we use
a rotating reference frame?
We've seen that the equation of motion,
the Larmor equation,
gives us a rotation
around the magnetic field.
So if we have a magnetization that is not
parallel to the magnetic field,
then it will rotate around
that magnetic field
just like the bicycle wheel
that we have seen rotating.
This is similar to a carousel--
so we are on a carousel,
and if we look at a carousel,
the motion of people on the carousel
from the outside--
it's fairly complicated because we have
any motion on the carousel
superimposed by
the motion of the carousel itself.
That's what we see from the outside.
And if we now put ourselves
on the reference frame on the carousel
anything that happens on the carousel
with respect to the carousel
is stationary.
What we do in classical physics,
I'll do the analogy here,
is that we are sitting--
let's say we are sitting
on a chair without motion,
then we have a force,
that's the centripetal force
towards the center--
that's the force of the chair
that pushes us and maintains
the circular motion that we have.
But we feel from our inertia
that there is a force
that pushes out against the chair.
This is not a physical force,
it's purely the inertia that
our visual system senses;
it is a fictitious force.
So we have, similarly
to the motion on the carousel,
we have the magnetization vector
here it turns here in the lab frame,
and if we are in the rotating frame,
the magnetization vector is stationary.
So we can, just like in the carousel,
if we have our magnetization
that is precessing
around the magnetic field B zero,
we can put ourselves
into a reference frame
that rotates with the magnetization
and there the magnetization
becomes stationary,
just like the person here on the carousel.
So what are the consequences
of using a rotating reference frame?
I'll start here with making
the analogy to classical physics.
In this video you see kids
throwing a ball at each other,
first seen with a camera from above--
the ball goes pretty much
in a straight line--
and then when the camera
is put on the merry-go-round
you see that the ball
goes in a very curved motion
which seems odd.
I will show in the following,
with an animation, this effect.
And basically the situation
we're considering here
is that we have a pendulum
that swings with an amplitude
equal to the disk radius
and a period that's equal to
that of the disk that rotates below.
So here's the disk. The triangle indicates
the motion of the disk.
Now we have the pendulum swinging--
its period is exactly
to the period of the disk.
That's the equivalent
of the merry-go-round.
So we're throwing
the pendulum in a straight line--
this is the bird's-eye view,
it's in the inertial reference frame,
everything is the way we normally see it.
Now what we're going to do
is we're going to put ourselves
into the rotating reference frame
of the carousel.
And to help your eyes see the motion
I have indicated here
the coordinate system
by the spokes on the carousel.
We'll take away the motion
seen from the outside
and now train your eye--
do you see what motion you see
with respect to a carousel?
Here it is.
So it is indeed a circular motion.
Our object, seen from the carousel,
undergoes circular motion.
And just to convince you
that I'm not cheating here in any way,
I'll put back the horizontal line--
so seen from the outside,
we still see the motion
of the object of the pendulum
swinging back and forth
in a straight line.
But from the carousel--
seen from the carousel,
from the merry-go-round--
we see it as circular motion.
So that's essentially
the motion that is seen
if our reference frame
that describes our motion
is equal to that of the merry-go-round,
the carousel,
or the rotating reference frame.
Now what we have done here is
we have just changed
the mathematical framework
on describing the motion.
We go from straight motion
to circular motion
depending on whether
we describe the motion
in a reference frame that rotates.
That's a purely mathematical description
of the motion.
And we still want to have
a proper description of the motion,
and to do that we want to look
at the motion in our merry-go-round--
we want to add all the forces
that act on our ball, or on our object--
and in the end we still want to have
a proper calculation of the acceleration--
that's Newton's second law.
So to get to the proper
acceleration here--
to describe this motion here,
to get the proper acceleration--
we have to add two fictitious forces:
centrifugal force and the Coriolis force.
Now bear in mind, those two forces
have nothing to do with physics, as such.
They are the consequence of the fact
that we mathematically change
our reference frame
from an inertial frame--
that's a typical non-moving
reference frame--
to one that rotates around the axis z.
These forces have to be added
so that we can describe
in the reference frame that rotates--
this one here--
that we can still arrive at
calculating the proper accelerations
with Newton's second law.
Now you might ask why am I transgressing
into classical physics--
what is the link to magnetic resonance?
Actually the link is there.
We have a mathematical description
in a reference frame that rotates.
In classical physics,
we need to subtract
or add two fictitious forces
and, as you will see in the next slide,
we have to do a similar thing
for the proper description
of the magnetization
in the rotating reference frame.
Except that we're not
going to deal with forces.
We are rotating
in the rotating reference frame,
not in a physical reference frame;
it's a reference frame
linked to the magnetization.
So how does the equation of motion
for the magnetization change
if we change the reference frame?
So we'll now say, we're going to
put ourselves into a reference frame
that rotates with omega_RF--
that's in radians per second.
And in that reference frame
we observe the magnetization
rotating with a Larmor frequency,
a big omega here which is given by
the Larmor frequency gamma B zero
minus this omega_RF--
that's the angular velocity
of the rotating reference frame.
We can now associate to this omega--
this observed Larmor frequency,
[inaudible] can observe--
we can relate this to a magnetic field
and we'll call this magnetic field
delta B.
So big omega is equal to gamma delta B.
Or, if we now stick this in here,
and we use omega_L equals gamma B_zero,
the delta B is given by B_zero--
the external magnetic field--
minus omega of the rotating frame
divided by gamma.
In the lab frame,
where our rotating frame does not rotate--
that's the lab frame--
omega_RF is zero, and the Larmor frequency
that we observe in that reference frame
is equal to omega_L
and delta B is equal to B_0.
So now what we want is,
in our rotating reference frame,
independent of the frequency
with which I take
my reference frame to rotate at,
I want the Larmor equation to be true.
For it to be true,
I have to increasingly subtract
a fictitious magnetic field.
And this magnetic field is this term here:
omega_RF over gamma
that we have to subtract from B_0.
So this is not unlike
the classical mechanics
where we take our physical forces;
once we're in the rotating reference frame
we have to add or subtract--
depending on how you look at it--
the centrifugal force
and the Coriolis force.
Here, in order for
the equation of motion to work,
we have to subtract
a fictitious magnetic field--
that's a consequence of the motion--
to make the equation of motion work;
we still want this equation to be true
in any of our reference frames.
So how does this work?
We'll look first at the lab frame.
We are far away from the Larmor frequency
so this is our rotating reference frame--
let's say it is at zero--
here's our Larmor frequency
on the horizontal axis is frequency.
Then this difference in frequency
is given by omega here.
And if we look in this reference frame
at the motion
we have a delta B
which is given by this term here.
So if we say omega_RF,
the reference frame frequency is zero,
then the delta B is equal to B_0.
Now what is the motion of magnetization
that we observe?
Here's the magnetization--
we'll say it is in the transverse plane,
so xy--
and if this magnetization's
a transverse plane
then it will precess
at a very high frequency
dictated by gamma delta B
around the magnetic field B_0.
This is what we call off-resonance.
We're far away with our rotating frame
from the Larmor frequency.
Now let's get a little bit closer.
And we'll go closer
with our rotating frame frequency,
and now the motion is slower--
we're starting to approximate
the Larmor frequency.
This is as if we have first started out
observing a carousel--
it turns, and now we're starting,
with our reference frame,
starting to move in the direction
of the rotation of the carousel.
Then the carousel,
from that reference frame,
will turn at a slower frequency
and this is what we see here
with the magnetization.
As we have increased our omega RF--
we have increased this term--
we have to subtract this fictitious field
as a consequence
of the rotating reference frame
[it will become] omega RF
divided by gamma.
So our delta B is now reduced.
If we go even closer,
then we're now relatively close
to the Larmor frequency
the precession will be
noticeably slowed down,
and we have to subtract omega_RF
as it's increased
a bigger fictitious field
omega_RF over gamma,
and the delta B is now decreased
because this motion here
dictates the frequency of precession here.
And now if we go essentially
on to the Larmor frequency
then our big omega goes to zero,
and our magnetization no longer turns--
I'm still showing
a turning magnetization here,
otherwise it's a very boring animation.
But essentially, if our omega RF is equal
to the Larmor frequency
then our magnetization, we are rotating
exactly at the frequency
with which the magnetization
rotates around B_0
and in that reference frame,
the magnetization is stationary
so it does not move.
If the magnetization does not move,
then it is stationary
in that reference frame
so the derivative
for the magnetization with time is zero,
so omega has to be zero,
and that means that omega_RF
is equal to omega_L,
delta B equals zero
and this case we call on-resonance
where omega_RF
is equal to the Larmor frequency.
That's the on-resonance situation.
That's the situation
as if you are on the carousel
and now your reference frame is moving
exactly with the motion of the carousel.
And so I want to show this precession
of the magnetization,
the Larmor equation,
with a simulated experiment of precession.
It's a macroscopic experiment--
it simulates how spin precession works.
We'll just take the view of the lab frame
in this experiment that follows.
This is an experiment
which simulates the motion of precession--
the Larmor equation--
on a macroscopic scale.
We have in this yellow ball,
we have a magnet
and that magnet will align itself
based on the magnetic field.
However, it is required that it has--
just like the nuclear spin--
that it has an angular momentum.
If I don't have an angular momentum here,
and I turn on the magnetic field,
the ball will just go down
as we have seen with the wheel experiment,
the suspended bicycle wheel.
So now what I will try to do is,
I will try to give this ball a spin.
I'll set it into circular motion.
Nothing happens now,
now I turn on the magnetic field
and you can see
it is turning around in one way,
and if I stop the magnetic field it stops,
it just turns around its axis,
and if I invert the polarity
of the magnetic field
it turns the other direction.
And those are the properties
of the Larmor equation
demonstrated here with this
macroscopic experiment.
We have today, in the course,
talked about that the equilibrium
thermodynamic magnetization is along z.
And we want to look
at how we can get the magnetization
to change its orientation.
And this I want to do
for the end of the lecture,
we'll resume this description,
but it's an example
of describing the motion
in the rotating reference frame.
I want to illustrate how the magnetization
can be manipulated.
So if we're putting ourselves
into a magnet
we will develop a thermodynamic
equilibrium magnetization M_0.
If we take the reference frame
that rotates with the Larmor frequency,
that's the on-resonance case
as we have described it,
then we have to--
In that reference frame,
we have no net magnetic field
so the magnetization is stationary--
we have no B_0,
the omega_RF over gamma
just cancels the B_0 term.
Now, in this reference frame,
we will apply an additional
constant magnetic field
with magnitude B_1--
we'll give it the name B_1--
and it shall be somewhere
in the transverse plane along x or y.
It doesn't matter
whether it's along x or y
for the purpose of this discussion,
and we'll apply this additional
magnetic field B_1 for a time tau.
So, question:
What motion can we observe
for the magnetization
in our rotating reference frame?
Well, let's look
at the equation of motion.
We have said it is always the same--
the derivative of the magnetization
is equal to minus gamma the magnetic field
times the magnetization,
and the times here is the vector product.
Since we are rotating
in the reference frame
that rotates with the Larmor frequency,
the B_0 term does not exist
in the equation
and we've said the B_1 here is constant--
it is in the transverse plane
so it is perpendicular to B_0.
So what motion can we observe
for the magnetization
if we start out
with equilibrium magnetization?
The motion is the same,
and in this reference frame
the magnetic field is constant,
so the motion that we observe--
this is what we've discussed--
this equation says
that the equilibrium magnetization
will now start to precess about B_1.
So it will rotate about the vector B_1
at a constant angular velocity.
So this angular velocity
in radians per second gamma B_1
has the frequency of gamma B_1
over 2 pi
and it has the period
of 2 pi over gamma B_1--
of course: this is the relationship
between frequency and period.
So let's visualize this--
we're in the rotating reference frame,
we have our coordinate system
in the rotating reference frame,
we have this constant B_1
in this rotating reference frame,
we have the equilibrium magnetization M_0
and now we have applied this B_1
for a period of tau.
After this time tau, the M_0--
the magnetization--
has precessed about B_1
by an angle alpha.
If the B_1 is along x
then M_0 will precess in a zy plane
and after time tau it has undergone
a rotation by the angle of alpha.
This angle is important.
As I'll define it here,
this angle is called the flip angle--
it describes the angle of rotation
induced by the...
in this case by this B_1 field
that was applied for tau seconds.
What are the special cases
of the flip angle alpha?
Special cases are 90 degrees.
If alpha is 90 degrees,
we call that excitation,
or full excitation,
that is, all the magnetization
that is along z, here in this example,
this equilibrium magnetization,
is rotated into the transverse plane.
So we rotate M_0
from being along z into magnetization
in the transverse plane
and we often call this M_xy
for the transverse magnetization.
So that's this case here.
We have rotated the magnetization
into the transverse plane.
If we now double the duration
so that we get an angle of 180 degrees
then that is called an inversion.
We go from an equilibrium magnetization
that's along z like this
to an equilibrium magnetization
that's opposite:
minus M_z in the minus z direction,
and that is called an inversion.
So that's the situation here
after 180 degrees.
And if we leave the B_1 on,
then the magnetization
will precess around B_1
for as long as we leave this B_1 field on.
Now B_1 is called
the radiofrequency field.
Why?
Can you picture this?
Why is this called a radiofrequency field?
It helps here to remind ourselves,
we've said B_1 is stationary--
that does not change with time
in the rotating reference frame
that rotates with the Larmor frequency.
What does that mean
if I look at it from the outside?
What form does the B_1 have?
Well, my hand's already telling you
it's rotating.
So, in the lab frame,
seen from the outside,
we have actually,
the B_1 is a time-dependent field.
It is given by B_1, the amplitude,
and it rotates exactly
with the Larmor frequency, omega_L.
Now, why do we call this radiofrequency?
Because, if we look at
the Larmor frequency,
we take for protons the gyromagnetic ratio
which is 42MHz per Tesla,
we calculate the Larmor frequency in Hertz
and we'll find that this is typically
on the order of 100MHz--
so it's perfectly in the range
of radiofrequency.
Actually, here it is in the range of,
truly, the radiofrequency of 100MHz.
And that's why the B_1 is called
radiofrequency field.