The topic of today's lecture is
Energy as an Essential Technology.
It is estimated that nearly 1.3B
people do not have access to
electricity. And this has great
consequences. According to statistics
from the WHO around 3B people
cook and heat their homes using
open fires and simply stones. They
burn coal and biomass such as wood
animal dung and crop waste. And over
4 million people die prematurely
from illnesses attributed to
household air pollution
from cooking with solid fuels.
While more than 50% of premature
deaths from pneumonia among children
under 5 are caused by particular
matter such as soot, which is inhaled
from household air pollution, and 3.8
million premature deaths annually
from non-communicable diseases
including stroke, ischemic heart
disease, chronic obstructive
pulmonary disease and lung cancer
are all attributed to exposure to
household air pollution.
Therefore the lack of access to power
is truly a major global concern.
Before we continue, let's briefly
look at how the global energy supply
chain is structured in general. It
consists of primary energy sources
that include Coal, Oil, Gas, Uranium,
Hydro, Biomass, Solar, Wind,
Geothermal, Ocean energies, etc.
These primary energy sources need
to be converted and processed into
energy carriers such as Heat,
Electricity and Fuels.
The energy carriers may be stored
and then distributed to the final
consumer for usage. For example,
fuel stored in specialized tanks
as it is combustible.
And then distributed via road, rail
and the sea. Whereas, electricity
requires and extensive great network
for distribution.
And surplus grid electricity's mainly
stored in dams as hydroelectricity.
Surplus electricity may typically
arise from energy sources which
produce electricity intermittently.
Where intermittent energy sources
are those sources whose supply can't
be controlled by the operator
to be continuously available as
needed. Which is the case with a
variety of renewable energy sources.
Such as the wind, solar, tidal waves.
Therefore, when they are available,
one may wish to generate a maximum
of energy, which you can store and
retrieve upon need.
There are a variety of uses of energy
in all phases of our daily lives, which
include: transport, construction,
industry, domestic use, agriculture
communications, etc.
Let us now look at who produces
energy around the world.
As can be seen on the map, North
America and most of Asia dominate
energy production capacity.
Let us now look at who consumes
energy around the world.
With respect to terminology, we know
that global energy produced actually
differs from the world final energy
consumption because much of the
energy that is acquired by humans
is lost as other forms of energy
during the process of its refinement
into usable forms of energy,
And it's transport from its initial
place of supply to consumers.
For instance, when oil is extracted
from the ground it must be refined
into gasoline so that it can be used
in a car, and then transported over
the long distances to gas stations
where it can be accessible
to consumers. So, global energy
consumption refers to the fraction
of the world's primary energy that is
used in its final form by humanity.
We see that the global distribution
of energy consumption is almost
a carbon copy of the energy
production distribution maps.
In particular, we note
that some
of the poorest countries, notably
in Africa and South Asia, score
the lowest in both production
and consumption levels.
According to the 2016 report from
the International Energy Agency
fossil fuels account for a share of
about 81% in the total of primary
sources of energy. Which can be
broken down into 31.3% Petrolium
28.6% coal, and 21.2% natural gas.
Amounting to a total of 81.1%
share for fossil fuels in the primary
energy consumption in the world.
Well, non-fossil sources include
10.3% from biofuels and waste,
4.8 % from nuclear, 2.4 % from
hydroelectricity.
Now, although fossil fuels are
continuously being formed via
natural processes, they are considered
to be non-renewable resources
because they take millions of years
to form. And the known reserves
available today are being depleted
much faster than any new ones
are being made. However, the use
of fossil fuels has been linked to
serious environmental concerns, as
the combustion of fossil fuels is
set to produce a net increase of
10.65 billion tons of atmospheric
carbon dioxide per year. And carbon
dioxide is one of the main
greenhouse gases that is set to
contribute to global warming.
And hence, there has been a global
movement towards advocating
the use of renewable energy sources
to produce energy.
And where the favoured renewable
energy sources include solar,
wind and geothermal sources.
And most of these sources
happen to be in abundant supply, in
fact, in some of or all the poorest
countries that still lack energy
supply today.
The majority of energy today is
derived from fossil sources.
The generation and use of energy
has been accompanied by collateral
damage to the environment, however.
The burning of coal, natural gas,
and oil for electricity and heat is
the largest single source of global
greenhouse gas emission. Greenhouse
gas emission from the transportation
sector account for about 40 % and
primarily involve fossil fuels
burnt for road rail and marine
transportation.
Almost all of the world's
transportation energy comes from
Petroleum based fuels. Largely
gasoline and diesel.
Thus, there's an urgent need for
technology innovations
that are environmentally clean.
Renewable energy sources such as
solar, wind and geothermal look
to be the ideal candidates to fill
this global energy gap,
as well as address the concerns we
have with greenhouse emissions.
However, in reality, progress has
been alarmingly slow, especially
in developing countries which have
abundance of these energy sources.
One major issue relates to
economics, in fact.
While the cost of the infrastructure
itself has been going down
dramatically recently, it's still
very difficult to match the overall
cost of generating each kilowatt
when compared to using fossil fuels
such as coal. For example, a solar
energy project in Rwanda that cost
about 24 million US dollars to build
generates electricity at a rate of
24 cents per kilowatt hour.
While industry experts claim that
if natural gases is used instead,
it would generate electricity at half of
that cost.
Now how do you determine solar
energy generation cost?
A common metric is the levelized
cost of electricity, LCOE.
which is simply the sum of all cost
over the lifetime of the facility.
divided by the sum of all energy
produced over lifetime by that
facility. Now, since the costs afer
installation, are minimal for solar
electricity, then the relevant costs are
the equipment purchase price,
installation cost and the cost of
land, that is capital cost.
Equipment components of a
typical solar system comprise
solar modules and other equipment
such as an inverter,
connection devices
and storage devices.
One of the main cost factors has
been the price of solar cells,
which are used to make the solar
modules.
But from 2006 to 2014 the worldwide
average prices for solar modules
have dropped by about 78 % to
the extent that it is anticipated
that PV (photovoltaic) solar cost will
reach conventional Coal Parity
by 2017, which simply means that
the cost of generating one watt of
electrical power will be similar
for coal and solar energy.
This factor is expected to encourage
a shift to more solar energy
electricity plants being built in
the future.
And less nuclear plants being built.
And the continued advancement in
technologies for distributed
electrical systems and energy
storage will also have a major
impact on the adoption and
integration of renewable energies
into power utilities.
Transportation currently accounts
for about half of global
oil consumption in over 1/4 of
global greenhouse gas emissions
from fossil fuels. Of even more
concern though is that carbon
dioxide emission derived from
transportation have increased more
rapidly than the total global
emissions in the past 2 decades,
according to a report from
International Council of Clean
Transportation.
This report also states that
world's motor vehicle population
will double over the next 2 decades.
And the transportation sector
is a hole, which also includes
commercial trunks, rail, marine,
and aviation.
It is also expected to continue to
grow at a similar pace
over the same period.
This forecast that does underscore
the importance of current and
future strategies that target
reductions in oil consumption
and greenhouse gases from the
transportation sector.
Now, from a technology viewpoint
various alternative initiatives
are ongoing towards reducing and
replacing fossil fuels
in transportation.
These include biofuels, electric
and hydrogen powered vehicles
all of which still have their pros and
cons today.
For example, biofuels have low
emissions in general,
however, they are typically made
from vegetables and food crops
such as rapeseed for biodiesel.
And thus can adversely affect
the food prices. Unfortunately,
the most farm equipment
involved in crop production
typically runs on Petroleum.
thus reducing the net benefits.
While cars running on hydrogen
fuels may give out zero greenhouse
emissions, besides water vapor,
unfortunately hydrogene is very
expensive to transport. And also,
currently hydrogen fuel is primarily
made from natural gas, which is non-
renewable, and also uses processes
that create significant
CO2 emissions.
As we said earlier, there are still
over 1 billion people without
electricity today. In sub-saharan
Africa the overall average urban
electrification rate is 60 %
compared with only 14 % in
rural areas. So, one of the biggest
challenges is how to reach
and provide electricity to the rural
and poorer communities that are
typically off the electricity grid.
There are various promising initiatives
in East Africa worth mentioning,
that have intelligently benefited
from mobile telephony for
their success. One such example,
is the social enterprise M-Kopa
which operates in 3 countries
currently, namely Kenya, Uganda
and Tanzania. M-Kopa offers a
package of useful appliances,
such as LED lights, mobile phone
charger, and a radio.
All powered by a solar panel and a
storage battery.
Payments are made via the mobile
phone and instead of paying up
for the package upfront, the client
pays monthly installments.
Where the amounts are typically
less than the monthly cost of Kerosine
for lamps. And once the full amount
is paid, the package then belongs to
the client and they can go back later
for bigger and more sophisticated
appliances, such as a flat screen
television.
So, the main trick and secret for
success is that they have managed
to convince the customers that are
buying the appliances that they are
buying the appliances rather than
paying for electricity.
M-Kopa intends to offer a low energy
refrigerators that could also help
the customers start up a
small restaurant
or grocery stores and other forms
of businesses.
There are various other inspiring
and innovative initiatives taking on
the challenge of rural electrification
in developing countries,
which have been provided in the
reference section at the end of
this lecture. And you're highly
encouraged to consult them
especially if taking this course for
credit.
This now brings us to the end of
this lecture today. Goodbye.