All the hospitals
should have water,
the water
from the national supply.
But we can't count on that water.
so we use the wells,
and using
mechanical pumps
it's difficult
we have to get
the water from the ground
before using it.
And now,
some hospitals have started using
an electric pump
with the water tower.
And theres still the same problem
with the quality of
the electric energy,
when the pumps breaks
from time to time
and it needs changing
that is what happened in Mfou
even when we were already there
but we also changed it
two or three times
and that depends on the commitment
of the personnel and managers
and on top of that,
the amount of revenue
that the institute can make.
For now,
the hospital uses a water well
with a manual pump,
so you have to manually pump
to get water.
And we have drills like that,
one is very efficient
the water is pure,
and another that we
just restored
because it was
also broken
but the water is
a bit dirty
so now there are two drills
that the hospital uses
and the biggest problem is
about this sort of drilling
is that the surrounding population
also comes to take
their water here.
So we have to close
the well that has clean water,
in the morning, we open
between 6am and 8am
and after,
we must close it
and in the evening at 6pm
till 7pm
afterwards we close it
so that not all the water is used
and the hospital lacks water
afterwards.
The real problem,
is the hygiene issues.
That is the main problem
the worst problem
and the most dangerous.
All the rooms do not
have water in them.
That means that,
even hand cleanliness
cannot be respected at all levels.
so we have to leave a room
to go into another room
to find a tap
to be able to clean our hands,
that is a real problem!
Now, on top of that
the toilets
the toilets don't work.
So that is a huge
hygiene problem
in the structure.
The second problem
is the drinking water,
there is none.
So we have no water
to drink
because the drilling water
cannot be ingested.
It is usually used
to clean the floor,
or clean the tiles
and what not.
so we have no drinking water
for drinks,
We have to stock
up in stores
with mineral water,
which is a lot
more expensive
and that cost is for the patient,
it is not the hospital
that will buy the
packs of mineral water
because it hasn't been
counted in the budget
to buy it so regularly.