Hello.
This lady in Cameroon
has to go fetch water at the river
for her laundry.
She doesn't have access
to clean water,
nor does she have access
to basic sanitation.
In this video, we will speak
about the vast domain
of water and sanitation technologies.
Access to enough safe water
is a precondition to human existence
and technologies
that help provide it
are indeed essential.
By the time water has been used
by humans, however,
it will be loaded with all sorts
of household or industrial waste.
It will thus need
to be properly cleansed
before it can be safely discharged
into the environment.
That is the role
of sanitation technologies
as we will see.
Water is so closely linked
to development
that, for the SDGs,
one specific objective
has been defined just for water,
Objective Number 6.
However, water
and sanitation technologies
have also an important influence
on almost all the other objectives.
Take, for example,
Objective Number 3, "Good Health":
waterborne disease causes
over 840,000 deaths each year
from diarrhea, with almost half
of them being children under five,
as a result of unsafe drinking-water,
inadequate sanitation and hygiene.
A study by the World Health Organization
in 2012 calculated
that for every one dollar invested
in sanitation,
there was a return of $5.50
in lower health care costs,
more productivity
and fewer premature deaths.
Water is also
crucially important for food,
which is our sustainable
development goal number two.
Agriculture accounts for 70%
of all water withdrawn
by the agricultural, municipal
and industrial sectors.
Before we talk about technologies
related to water and sanitation,
we need to briefly tell you
about the hydrological or water cycle.
In a very simplified view,
the water cycle describes
how water moves on earth,
above earth and below earth.
The sun drives the cycle
by heating and evaporating water
from the oceans
and from lakes and streams.
Water is also transpired by plants
and evaporated by the soil.
As the water molecule is less dense
than other atmospheric components,
the vapor will rise and cool down
as the pressure is reduced
at higher altitudes.
It then condenses and falls back
on earth in the form of precipitation
which can be rain or snow.
It can then accumulate
as ice caps or glaciers
and remain stored there
for thousands of years.
Some of the rain will flow directly
as surface runoff
and form stream and rivers
which will, in turn,
replenish lakes and flow back
to the ocean.
Another fraction of the rain
will soak the ground,
where it will
replenish the groundwater.
Groundwater will sometimes find
openings in the land surface
and come out
as freshwater springs.
Human activity will generate
a second, smaller cycle,
where water pumped from the ground
or from a river
is used by humans for drinking,
for flushing the toilets,
or for irrigation in agriculture
or in industry.
Often, it will get loaded
with impurities and waste
in the process.
It is then ideally treated
and eventually discharged
back into the natural water cycle.
We will now take a closer look
at some essential technologies
involved in this human segment
of the water cycle.
There are many technologies
allowing to catch water,
which obviously depends
on the source itself.
One such technology
is the water well.
A well will allow you to get access
to water that has percolated
through the ground and is stored
in the so-called "aquifer".
An aquifer is
a porous underground layer
saturated with water.
Water then needs to be retrieved.
There are simple mechanical ways
to do that,
such as a mechanical hand-pump.
Pumps can be electrically powered,
for example, with solar panels.
The well can be susceptible
to yield fluctuations
and there are technologies
which allow to monitor
and optimize the water use.
Then, water needs to be transported
in a safe and hygienic way
and stored so that
it can be used on demand.
Generally, water from any source
will contain unwanted components.
For example, a well
can be contaminated
by a pit latrine located nearby,
as we will see.
It will thus need to be treated
before it can be safely used
for human consumption.
Here, you can see a reverse-osmosis
water treatment plant
serving a town
of roughly 10,000 people in Iraq.
There are many different technologies
to remove living pathogens
such as bacteria or parasites,
or unwanted dissolved chemicals
such as arsenic,
or simply dissolved salt.
Depending on the available water quality,
the choice will be made
between the different options
such as filtration, ultra-filtration
or reverse osmosis.
UV light can also be used
to kill bacteria.
These water purification technologies
are sometimes quite expensive, though,
and complex to set up
and maintain in proper function.
Water also needs
to be transported.
Unfortunately, quite
a large quantity
is often lost in the process.
There are sophisticated technologies
to detect leakages,
which is very important
to maximize the availability
of this precious liquid.
Once water has been purified,
there is a risk
that it won't remain safe.
Usually, the addition of chlorine
will allow  to keep it protected
against germs for a while.
There are technologies that allow
an automated dosage of this chlorine.
Yet another set
of important water technologies
allow to assess the quality
of the obtained water.
Here, you can see a team
from the International Committee
of the Red Cross in Sudan
assessing the level
of chlorine in water
with a very simple pool test.
Water quality assessments
can involve multiple parameters,
which can be monitored with a variety
of technical instruments,
such as a spectrophotometer,
which allows to analyze
the chemical composition
of the water.
There are many more technologies
related to water.
However, drinking water technologies
is just one segment
in the cycle which includes also
sanitation, hygiene,
as well as waste management.
Let us look at a few
sanitation technologies.
The toilet is really
an essential technology!
Here, you can see migrants in Mexico
cleaning the latrines in a shelter
before continuing their trip.
There are several modes
by which human excreta
can be collected
in a safe and hygienic way.
What happens with the excreta next
is an important question
as it will have to be stored,
transported, treated
and disposed of
in a safe and convenient way.
In many cases,
mainly in rural environments,
it is simply stored in the pit
under the latrine.
When the pit is full, it is closed
and the latrine is moved
to another place with a new pit.
This will often raise concerns
about pathogens infiltrating
the groundwater.
Generally, in fact, human waste is -
or should be -
transported to a wastewater
treatment plant,
such as the one shown here.
In this plant, it undergoes
a series of treatments
until it can be safely released
into the environment
or utilized as fertilizer.
In cities of industrialized countries,
sewage systems will be used
to transport the water
to the treatment plants.
However, this solution is expensive
to build and maintain,
and might be very complex to apply
in poor areas such as slums.
Fecal waste can also be put to use
to generate biogas
in a "digester",
such as the one you see here
under construction in Zimbabwe.
Biogas can then be used
as an energy source,
for example, for cooking.
We now understand the importance
of water and sanitation technologies,
but how widely available
are they on a global scale?
Let's have a look.
Global water scarcity
is a crucial problem,
which is made worse by demographics
and climate change.
Water quality is also a big problem
as we can see in this map
which shows the percentage
of population having access
to  "improved" water sources.
Improved water sources are defined
as those which adequately protect
the source from outside contamination,
particularly fecal matter.
For example, a well without
a sealed protective top cover
is not an improved water source.
As you can see,
there are still 660 million people
who do not have access
to such improved water sources at all.
Having access
to an improved water source
doesn't mean it is safe.
The World Health Organization
estimates that, globally,
at least 1.8 billion people
use a drinking-water source
which is contaminated with feces.
Having piped water is often
not an assurance of quality either,
since a substantial proportion
of water supplied
through pipes is contaminated.
This is especially true
where water supply is intermittent,
treatment is inadequate,
or when proper sanitation
isn't available.
Let's look at the global access
to sanitation.
This map shows the percentage
of global population
which has access
to "improved" sanitation facilities.
"Improved" sanitation means
that the facility is able
to hygienically separate
human excreta from human contact.
According to the
World Health Organization,
in 2015, one third
of the world's population
had no access to such
improved sanitation facilities.
Of those, almost half -
or 950 million people -
still have to defecate in the open,
for example in street gutters,
behind bushes,
or into open bodies of water.
This perpetuates a vicious circle
of disease and poverty,
where people get re-infected
again and again,
by pathogens present
in the population.
Benefits of improved sanitation
extend well beyond
reducing the risk of diarrhea.
It promotes dignity
and boosts safety,
particularly among women and girls.
School attendance is also improved,
especially for girls,
with the provision
of separate sanitary facilities.
As you can see,
we need innovative solutions
for both provision
of safe drinking water
and adequate sanitation.
I would like to conclude
by telling you
about an innovation
that was developed
to solve the problem of access
to toilets in the poorest countries.
The Blue Diversion Toilet
is an ambitious project
conducted by a team
at the Swiss Federal Institute
of Aquatic Science and Technology,
a design company EOS,
the Paul Scherrer Institute,
and several other partners,
with funding from the
Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation.
It works without the need
for grid electricity,
nor running water, and was developed
for the context of urban slums.
One of the key efforts so far
has been to design it
so that it is culturally acceptable
and appealing to people.
This modular and sophisticated concept
also involves
a complete self-sustainable
business model
by which local entrepreneurs
can earn some money
from taking care
of the installed systems.
So, how does it work?
The technology separates
solid and liquid waste, or urine,
and flush water.
Flush water is cleaned
by ultrafiltration
and made available for re-use
inside the toilet.
Urine and sold excreta
are separately recycled
into fertilizing products
which are then sold.
I think this is an example
of a very interesting
essential technology project
in a world
where more people have mobile phones
than a toilet.
After this short discussion
of water and sanitation technologies,
I hope you will feel motivated
to imagine and experiment
many more inventions in this
essential technology domain.
Good bye.