The topic of today's lecture is
Information and Communications Technologies
What is Information and
Communications Technology exactly?
or ICT?
In very simple terms
ICT refers to any device or system
that allows the storage, retrieval
manipulation, transmission and receipt
of information signals.
Common examples include computers,
television, telephones, radios
and several others,
as the list keeps growing everyday.
ICT devices are today indispensable
in our daily lives.
And the concepts,
methods and applications
involved in ICT are constantly evolving
on an almost daily basis.
In 2016, 3.9 billion people
or about 53% of the world’s population
is not using the Internet.
If we break it down by regions,
we see that almost 75% of people
in Africa are offline
while only 21% of Europeans are offline.
In the Middle East and Asia and the
Pacific and the Arab States
the percentage of the population
that is not using the Internet today
is about 58%.
The gender gap in global Internet
usage
grew from 11% in 2013 to 12%
in 2016.
The gap remains largest in the
world’s Least Developed Countries
at 31%.
In 2016, the regional gender gap is
largest in Africa
at 23%, and smallest in
the Americas at 2%.
In general, globally we see that
the average price of a basic
fixed-broadband plan
is more than twice as high
as the average price of a comparable
mobile broadband plan.
But, paradoxically, mobile
broadband prices
are about 2.5 times higher
in least-developed-countries
than developed countries.
In developed countries, over 75%
of fixed-broadband subscriptions offer
speeds of 10 Mbit/s and above.
While In the LDCs, only 7%
of fixed-broadband subscriptions
offer similar funds.
We saw the paradox
in the previous slide
where the poorest countries still paying
outrageously higher prices
for broadband services.
Why is that?
There are many factors, of course, at play.
But one of them is that
most African countries
installed their first internet Gateway
through satellite links.
This made Africa rely on satellites
and Very Small Aperture
Terminal (VSAT) earth stations
for most of its connectivity,
which resulted in high prices
and slow performances
as compared to other technologies.
However, there are several
multi-country projects
initiated to lay down undersea
fibre optic cables around Africa,
linking it with the Middle East,
Europe and beyond.
The use of fibre optic technology is
expected to significantly
boost bandwidth capacity
of the African closest to the cables.
A submarine communications cable
is a cable laid on the sea bed
between land-based stations
to carry telecommunication
signals across stretches of ocean.
Modern cables use optical
fiber technology
to carry digital data,
which includes telephones, Internet,
and private data traffic.
And with respect to potential
impact on surrounding environment,
previous studies have indicated
that cables actually can pose minimal
impacts on life in these environments.
And as you can see on the map
on the screen
the diagram is very busy
and we will not take the time to
describe it fully
but I invite you to examine in
more detail after the lecture
and the related references
that are listed
But briefly, some of the first
submarine cable projects
include Seacom on the East Coast,
EASSy, which stands for Eastern
Africa Submarine Cable System,
and WACS for West Africa Cable System.
The Chinese company, Huawei Marine,
announced earlier
that it had completed
upgrades on
the West Africa Cable System (WACS)
which is the largest submarine cable
directly linking Africa to Europe
using a 100G transmission solution
that will enhance network connectivity
and operational efficiency.
In a similar vein, Huawei Marine
has commenced marine installation of
the Nigeria-Cameroon Submarine Cable System (NCSCS),
which is Cameroon's first wholly
owned submarine cable,
with investment provided by
the Cameroon Government.
The cable, which spans
approximately 1,100 km,
will link Cameroon directly with
Nigeria
delivering 12.8 Tbps
of capacity to broadband users
in both countries
And according to the head of Cameroon
Telecommunications Corporation
the direct connection to Nigeria
will enhance Cameroon's position
as the major hub of bandwidth
in the region and internationally,
to Europe and beyond.
In the sessions of Essential
Technologies for Health and Energy
we saw already the power
of mobile telephony
towards some of the challenges
in those sectors
in developing countries, especially.
Perhaps the area where many believe
that mobile communications
technology will have
a truly transformative impact
is Digital Finance.
Now, according to a new report
from the McKinsey Global Institute
digital finance could be
a powerful tool
for driving inclusive growth
in emerging economies.
The report states that widespread
adoption
and use of digital finance
could increase the GDPs of
all emerging economies
by 6 percent
or a total
of $3.7 trillion, by 2025.
Digital finance
could provide access
to 1.6 billion unbanked people,
of which more than half
would be women.
And an additional $2.1 trillion
of loans
to individuals and small businesses
could be made sustainably,
as providers gain newfound ability
to assess credit risk
for a wider pool of borrowers.
One of the pioneers and most successful
digital finance platforms to date
is M-Pesa.
Where M stands for mobile,
and pesa is Swahili for money.
M-Pesa is basically a mobile
phone-based money transfer,
financing and microfinancing service,
launched in 2007
by some of the largest mobile
network operators
in Kenya and Tanzania.
It has since expanded to Afghanistan,
South Africa,
India, Romania and Albania.
M-Pesa allows users to deposit,
withdraw,
transfer money and pay
for goods and services
with ease using a mobile device.
The service allows users to
deposit money into an account
stored on their cell phones,
to send balances using PIN-secured
SMS text messages
to other users, including sellers
of goods and services,
and to redeem deposits
for regular money.
Users are charged a small fee
for sending
and withdrawing money
using the service.
The service has been lauded
for giving millions
of people access
to the formal financial system
and for reducing crime
in an otherwise largely cash-based
society.
That brings us to the end of
this lecture
Goodbye!