Hello. Inadequate access
to basic health facilities
in hospitals, is the cause
of an estimated 75%
of birth-related child mortality.
Today, we will talk about
sustainable transport technologies,
which can be defined as transports
which are safe, clean,
affordable and which contribute
to economic development.
Transport of goods and people
is an essential driver
of economic and social development.
It brings opportunities for the poor
and enables economies
to be more competitive.
Transport technology
connects people
to jobs, education and healthcare.
It enables global and local trade
by supplying goods and services.
It also allows social interaction
between people
and promotes social inclusion
of the poor.
Let us define a general framework
to help analyze this vast subject.
The basic function of transport
is to move people, animals
and goods from
one place to another.
There are of course multiple ways
to achieve this function
and these are called
transport modes.
Main modes of transport
are air, land and water.
Each mode can be separated,
roughly speaking, into three elements
which are infrastructure,
vehicles and operations.
The last element refers to how
the transport mode
is operated and by whom.
Of course, another crucial component
of sustainable transport is missing,
which is the policies
and governance dimension.
However, this subject would take us
too far away
from our focus on technologies.
As we think about technology
innovation in transport,
it is useful to have this
simplified framework in mind.
Technology is heavily involved
in all three elements
and all three modes of transport.
To make things a little clearer,
let us fill in the table
with some examples,
and discuss the main issues
and opportunities
for technology innovation.
Air transport is very important
for business,
as it allows efficient trade
of perishable goods,
such as  fresh food or flowers.
In Kenya for example,
over half a million people
depend on flower business
for a living.
Air transport, very importantly,
also opens the way for tourism.
Having a strong
air transport sector
will also attract
international businesses
to set up offices
and manufacturing sites
in the country,
which creates jobs.
Air transport infrastructure
involves, for example,
airports, control towers
and navigation systems.
Over the ten years to 2005,
both passenger travel
and air freight
have increased by about 55%.
This strong international
growth in aviation
is straining the capacities
of many low income countries.
It generates high costs for countries
who struggle to maintain
the capacity for proper function
and meet the demand.
As a consequence, there is a risk
for degradation in safety,
which is extremely important
to the development
of aviation services.
West Africa, for example, has
an aviation accident rate
thirty times that
of the United States.
As far as vehicles, we can mention
airplanes and helicopters.
Of course, this sector has
an impact on the environment.
Emissions represent 12% of all
CO2 released in the transport sector.
In  terms of operations, air traffic
is operated by both public
and private operators, who rely
on a series of technologies to track
freight and passengers, to assure
security and to minimize delays.
Technology innovation can be
an important contributor
in improving safety, which is crucial
to the industries
that depend on air transport.
New technology can also contribute
to reducing emissions,
which remains a big issue
in this industry, as we have seen.
Finally, innovative drone technology
will most certainly play
an important role in this sector.
And there are many experiments
currently being conducted
by companies and research institutes.
Since the beginning of human history,
land transport
has underpinned economic progress
and remains
an essential contributor
to development.
It involves a wide variety
of infrastructures, such as roads,
bridges, tunnels, railways,
train stations, fuel stations
bike lanes and walkways,
but also pipelines,
which can be used
to transport fluids.
In Africa, road transport accounts
for 80% of the goods traffic
and 90% of passenger traffic.
This leaves a lot of room
for improvement, for example,
in railway transport, especially
for long distances and high volume.
In rail transport,
infrastructure construction
and maintenance costs remain a big
challenge for low income countries.
For land transport there are
many vehicles, but we can cite
of course, cars, trucks,
buses, bicycles and trains.
Again we should mention that pipelines
are both
a piece of infrastructure
and a vehicle.
Land transport can be operated
by individual car owners,
bus companies,
cities or even states.
Internal combustion engines
have revolutionized transport
yet they account for an estimated 15%
of global greenhouse gas emissions.
In large polluted cities such as
Kuala Lumpur or Jakarta,
it is estimated that
the total economic damage
of air pollution represents
up to 10% of GDP.
Traffic congestion is another
very problematic issue,
which we
will discuss a little later.
Every year, around 1.3 million people
die as a result of road accidents,
and 78 million more
require medical care.
Low and middle income countries bear
over 90% of that burden.
People who may not be poor
to start with, may become poor
due to a handicap or loss of life
of the family's breadwinner.
Technology innovation would
be especially welcome in three areas:
improving safety, reducing pollution
and preventing traffic congestion.
Recent developments in making
vehicles such as buses,
or intelligent systems capable
to predict and prevent crashes
are very promising in this regard.
Water transport involves not only
maritime transport infrastructure
such as ports, lighthouses,
container cranes, but also
inland waterway infrastructure,
such as canals and locks.
As for land transport, pipelines can
be used as submarine infrastructure
to transport fluids such as
oil, gas or water.
Vehicles can be ships, barges,
small boats and pipelines.
Operations may involve
maritime companies
or simply individuals owning
a boat, or port authorities.
Maritime transport is the backbone
of international trade,
as it represents 90%
of global trade by volume.
Because of the presence of rivers,
canals, lakes, inland waterways
also play an important role
for freight and passenger transport
in China, Brazil, Vietnam,
Uganda and other countries.
One great technological innovation
in this sector
is certainly the ISO container.
Since it has been
internationally normalized
it can be easily handled by standard
cranes and other equipment worldwide.
This has made global
supply chains extremely efficient.
Due to the great importance
of water transport in trade,
technology solutions that
can further reduce costs,
improve speed and reliability,
will be very important
contributors to development.
Here is now our complete table.
This is, of course, by far not
an exhaustive view, and it reveals
something else which is
quite obvious but yet very important.
In many cases, there will be several
transport modes involved,
or more precisely,
transport vehicles.
This is called multimodal transport.
It is very important that
the transfers from one mode to another
are as efficient
and seamless as possible.
As we discuss transport technologies,
let us keep in mind
that according to
United Nations forecasts
by 2050, more than 67%, or
two-thirds of the word’s population
will live in cities.
Today the number of private cars
is over 900 million worldwide.
And it will reach an estimated
1.6 billion by 2035.
The largest increase will
take place in developing countries.
One consequence
is traffic congestion.
Traffic congestion plagues
all major cities
and has a great impact
on economic development.
Innovative ideas and incentives
are urgently needed
for efficient traffic management.
It is, for example, crucial
to shift mobility away
from individual private cars,
towards more efficient
public transportation, such as
bus rapid transportation systems.
Today, in many cities of Africa
and Asia, the proportion of trips
made without cars is 90% or more.
This raises again the issue
of road traffic accidents:
more than half the road deaths
in these urban areas
are pedestrians and cyclists.
These facts lead us to emphasize
the importance
of efficient solutions to protect
and support non-motorized transport
in cities and especially in slums.
After this glimpse at
the urban context, let us now look
at the rural world, where still
a large fraction of today’s poor live.
In order to measure access
to transports
we use the Rural Access Index.
The Rural Access Index
measures the number of rural people
who live within 2 kilometers
of an all-season road,
as a proportion of
the total rural population.
Two kilometers is typically
equivalent to
a walk of 20-25 minutes.
An “all-season road” is a road
that is motorable all year round
by the prevailing means
of rural transport, for example
a pick-up or a truck which
is not a four-wheel-drive.
By this measure, globally,
about 1 billion people
don’t have access
to adequate transportation.
In Africa, two-thirds of
the rural population
about 300 million of
the world’s poorest people
do not have reliable access
to an all-weather road.
Most are thus locked
into subsistence living
and have disadvantaged access
to reliable health care and education.
As we said in the beginning
of this video,
the isolation of those communities
prevents them from an easy access
to health facilities
in the case of emergency.
I would like to speak about
a simple and yet innovative technology
that tries to address this need.
According to the World Bank,
between 40 to 60%
of the people
in developing countries
live more than 8 kilometers
from a healthcare facility.
In poor communities, the majority of health
facilities don’t have ambulances.
When they do, these vehicles
can’t access the patients
due to a lack of adequate all-weather
roads as we have just seen.
A company called eRanger has noticed
that in many places where cars
and pick-ups didn't have access,
motorbikes were still working.
The company has thus designed
a motorbike ambulance,
which has a side-car
for one patient.
It is light in weight,
rugged in design,
and able to negotiate
the roughest terrain.
It comes with a complete set
of equipment, tools and spares
so that it is sustainable
in the bush,
miles away from anywhere.
Over 2000 of these ambulances
have already been distributed
through major aid agencies, such as
UNICEF, UNHCR and Save The Children.
The complete ambulance sells
for around US$ 6000,
including training, which makes it
a very affordable solution.
According to a study performed
in 2015 in a district in Uganda
where 26 such motorbike
ambulances were deployed,
22,000 referral trips were made.
This has had a massive impact
on infant and maternal mortality.
I hope you now have many ideas
of innovative transport technologies.
Good-bye.