The topic of today's lecture is
Construction
as an Essential Technology.
I start this lecture
by asking you a simple question:
The most consumed substance
in the world is water,
but can you possibly guess
what the 2nd
most consumed substance is though?
Let's talk more about
construction technologies.
Construction technologies
are used for the building
and assembling
of infrastructure.
This includes public
and private buildings,
such as housing,
schools, hospitals
as well as the construction
of roads and bridges.
And the industrial infrastructure
may include...
refineries, mills,
power generation,
and industrial
manufacturing plants.
Now in order to arrive
at the stage
of being able
to construct a building,
let’s take a brief look
at the organization
or value chain
of the Construction Industry.
It can basically be divided
into three sectors.
The first sector is
Primary Activities,
which involve the extraction,
processing
and use of raw materials
from the earth.
The second one is
Secondary Activities,
which includes the manufacturing
of finished goods
and the actual
construction activity itself.
While the third sector is
Tertiary Activities,
which is essentially
logistics and distribution.
Now some of the world’s largest
construction materials companies
are actually vertically integrated
across all three sectors.
In other words,
they carry out all the activities
from primary to tertiary.
Extracted materials
may include
sand, gravel,
limestone, slates,
clay, gypsum, feldspar,
quartzite and more.
One of the main
Secondary Activities
is making cement.
Cement can be made by heating clay and chalk
to fuse
these materials together.
The resulting fused materials
are then ground into powder,
that then forms cement.
Cement is a key ingredient
in concrete.
And concrete is the 2nd most
consumed substance in the world
after water.
Concrete is made
from aggregate,
cement and water and can either be mixed directly
on building sites
or supplied ready-mixed
from a concrete plant.
And aggregates are made
from sand, gravel and crushed rock
and they provide the base
for all types
of construction products.
Besides concrete, other products produced
in the Secondary Activities
include asphalt
and concrete products.
Tertiary Activities,
on the other hand, involve
the distribution of raw materials
and finished goods
to customers for the construction
of various types of buildings
and transportation links:
Cement is sold in bulk
to make ready-mixed concrete
and concrete products,
but it is also sold in bags
to builders’ merchants
for individuals to buy.
Ready-mixed concrete
and concrete products
are sold to residential,
commercial
and public contractors.
By 2030, there will be
about 3 billion people
in need of proper housing
and access to basic infrastructure.
Which means
we need to complete
about 96,000 housing units
per day.
What exactly is the driver
for this housing crisis?
Of course,
there are various factors,
but urbanization is
the principal culprit!
The graph on the screen
shows the percentage
of urban populations
living in slums
and we’ll talk more about
this subject in the next slide.
According to
the World Bank estimates in 2011,
over 90% of urban growth
is occurring
in the developing world,
adding an estimate
of 70 million new residents
to urban areas each year.
During the next two decades,
the urban population
is expected to double
in the two poorest regions
in the world,
South Asia
and Sub-Saharan Africa.
Unfortunately,
a significant portion
of the urban population
in these regions
do not have proper housing
and live in slums.
For example, in Asia,
30% of the urban population
resides in slums,
and this continent is
currently home to half
of the urban population
of the world.
While in Africa,
about 62% of the urban population
live in slums,
And the Central African Republic
is the country that has
the highest proportion
of urban population
living in slums,
which is 96%.
Therefore,
there is a massive task ahead
to build enough houses,
in order to provide
a dignified home for all.
And this challenge is highest
in the poorest regions
of the world.
So, whatever solution
is proposed has to be
cost-effective
and affordable.
But unfortunately,
the construction industry,
as we will discuss shortly,
has been a major contributor
to non-sustainable
environmental actions.
So, it would be ideal
if the adopted
building construction solutions
of tomorrow were also
environmentally sustainable.
Now speaking of sustainability
in the construction industry,
what is the environmental impact
of construction activities
to our dear universe in fact?
The construction industry
is involved in creating
the physical assets
which are the basis
of virtually every aspect
of development,
but the construction sector is also
one of the largest exploiters
of natural resources.
Around half of all
non-renewable resources
that humankind consumes119
are used in construction,
making it one of the least
sustainable industries in the world.
Apart from its share
of fossil fuel use,
the construction industry is
a heavy user of several metals,
whose remaining exploitable reserves
are limited.
Almost 50% of all global energy
is used in buildings.
And about 50%
of all global water used
is also utilized
in buildings.
Construction activity contributes
to the loss of soil
and agricultural land
through activities such as:
Quarrying and mining
for the raw materials used
in construction.
Conversion of agricultural land
to other uses,
whether for urbanisation,
for roadbuilding,
dams or other
civil engineering projects;
And it may also be degraded
as a result of the local pollution
or waste generation
associated with construction
and building materials
production.
Buildings contribute 40%
to drinking water pollution,
and 50% to landfill waste.
Furthermore, construction
contributes to air pollution
through emissions
of dust, fibre,
and toxic gases
from site activities
and building materials
production processes.
And it contributes 50%
to global ozone depletion
by the use and release of
chloro fluorocarbons in buildings,
and by the emission
of carbon dioxide
and other greenhouse gasses.
Thus the construction industry
contributes significantly
to each of the areas
of environmental stress.
As we saw
in our early slides,
cement is the key ingredient
for making concrete,
which is the main material
for making buildings
and other infrastructure
and the 2nd most consumed item
after water
However,
one out of every 20 tonnes
of human-made CO2
that enter the atmosphere
comes from the kilns
of cement factories.
The sources of emissions
in cement production
are actually threefold:
One, from the production
of the electrical energy
used to grind
the raw materials;
Two, these raw materials,
such as limestone and clay,
are then heated
to 1450 in a kiln
in order to form
a compound called clinker,
which is subsequently crushed
and blended with gypsum
to make cement.
The heating process
of this step
is also a major source
of emissions.
Now the third source is from
the process emissions.
For example,
when the limestone is heated,
it is converted into lime and CO2.
And these emissions
actually represent
up to 65% of total emissions
linked to cement production.
So, all together,
if we can reduce the amount of clinker
used in making cement,
we should potentially reduce
the amount of CO2
in the atmosphere.
And now there is a new
cement innovation in fact
that is based
on this concept.
Specifically it is based
on a blend of limestone
and calcined clay,
and it is called LC3.
Now, in the LC3 cement,
the amount of clinker needed
has been reduced by 50%.
So, overall,
the LC3 cement innovation
is attractive due to the following
features and benefits:
One, it can reduce
the CO2 emissions associated
with cement production
by about 30%,
Two, it is made using limestone
and low-grade clays
that are in abundant supply
and tend to be readily available.
Three, it is cost effective
and does not require
capital intensive modifications
to existing cement plants.
LC3 can be produced with
existing manufacturing equipment,
thus only requires a marginal
additional investment
for the calcining equipment.
So, altogether,
this cement innovation seems
particularly suited
to the developing countries
as well,
as it meets
the criteria we mentioned before
relating to cost
and sustainability.
And there are
currently ongoing
pilot implementation projects
in India and Cuba,
which are showing
highly promising results
and are being used
to build houses,
as shown in the pictures
on this slide.
You can obtain
more information
on this exciting project
at www.lc3.ch.
In the references,
I have also included a link
to another interesting
innovative building technology.
The Moladi Construction System.
At the beginning of this lecture,
I asked the question
as to what the 2nd most consumed
substance after water?
And I'm sure
you have the answer by now,
but in case you don't,
then the correct answer is:
Concrete.
As symbolized by the picture
you see on the slide
which is a water tank
and a concrete house.
Water and shelter
represent, perhaps,
the most important foundations
of contemporary humanity!
Goodbye.