This session aims
to provide an overview
of the essential technology domain
of pharmaceuticals.
Before we begin,
let's try and clarify a few terms
and expressions that we will
be using widely in this session.
What is
a pharmaceutical drug exactly?
For the purposes of this course,
a pharmaceutical drug is any substance
or compound that is used to cure,
treat, or prevent disease.
It may also be referred to as
a pharmaceutical product,
medicine, medication,
or simply a drug.
We can distinguish between
two broad categories of drugs,
based on the manner in which
they are produced and administered.
Small-molecule drugs
are low-molecular weight compounds
that are chemically synthesized
and then formulated into a tablet
that is given orally to the patient,
whereas biological drugs
or biologicals
are high-molecular polypeptides,
proteins and antibodies
that are produced via
biotechnological or recombinant means,
and are typically administered
by injection.
How are pharmaceutical drugs
developed?
For simplicity, we can consider
the drug development process
to be divided into 3 broad stages:
It starts with
Preclinical Development,
which essentially occurs entirely
in the laboratories,
in order to eventually produce
what is termed
a New Chemical Entity or NCE.
This is then followed by
the Clinical Development stage,
which primarily occurs
in hospitals and clinics.
It essentially involves
testing the NCE
from the Preclinical Stage in humans
for Safety and Efficacy
against the intended
disease or diseases.
At this stage,
the NCE is now referred to
as the Investigational New Drug
or IND
upon approval
by a suitably accredited
national or regional regulatory body,
such as the Food
and Drug Administration or FDA
in the US
and the European Medicines
Association or EMA in Europe.
If the Clinical Development stage
goes well
and the clinical trials
are successful
a New Drug Approval is granted,
which leads to the final stage,
that is a Branded Product and the
post-approval and marketing phase.
Now, the time it takes from
the commencement
of Preclinical Development
to the Approval of a new drug
is about ten to fifteen years, and
costs about 2.6 billion US dollars,
based on the last study, in 2014,
from the Tufts Center
for the Study of Drug Development.
So, the development of a new drug
is lengthy and very expensive,
but also a highly inefficient process
with very low success rates.
Given the high costs
of drug development,
prior to the start
of the Drug Development Process,
a patent that protects the drug
is then filed.
This patent is valid for twenty years,
afterwhich the drug becomes available
to any other parties who may wish
to produce and market a copy
or generic version of the drug,
usually at a lower price
than the branded product.
Consequently, most of the leading
pharmaceutical companies
from developing countries
are primarily involved
with the manufacture
of generic pharmaceutical products
rather than the development
of new drugs entirely.
Thus, the development of new drugs
is almost exclusively confined
to companies in the highly
industrialized countries, such as
the US,
Western Europe and Japan.
This also inherently implies
that most of the available drugs
are mostly tailored
for those populations
and often less adapted
to the rest of the world population,
especially developing countries.
Since the creation of the modern
Food and Drug Administration in 1938,
there is almost 1.500 drugs
that have been approved.
Therefore, for any country wishing
to establish a repertoire
of essential medicines
that the country must aim to have,
in order to ensure adequately
meeting national medical needs,
choosing which medicines to prioritize
can be a significant challenge,
especially if lacking the suitable
expertise for such a task.
In order to confront this challenge,
the World Health Organisation or WHO
judiciously assembled
an Essential Medicines List.
And WHO defines Essential Medicines
as those medicines
or pharmaceutical products
that satisfy the priority
health care needs of the population.
They are selected
with due consideration
to public health relevance,
their safety and efficacy,
and cost-competitiveness.
In other words, essential medicines
are intended to be available
within the context of functional
health systems at all times
in adequate amounts,
in the appropriate dosage forms,
with assured quality
and adequate information,
and at a price the individual
and the community can afford.
Thus, the Essential Medicines List
aims to serve
as a Model Medicines List
or some sort of template
that countries can then adapt
and develop their own national
Essential Medicines Lists.
It can assist national decision-makers
in reducing costs by helping them
identify priority medicines
to meet their country’s health needs.
And in, in high-income countries,
the list helps to provide
insurance companies, for example,
with a neutral,
gold-standard list for reimbursement.
We now look at
the link between poverty,
disease and access
to essential medicines.
This slide shows that
the countries with the lowest
per capita health expenditure,
indicated in red and dark red,
are also some of the poorest
countries in the world.
Pharmaceuticals account
for up to 30%
of health expenditures
in transitional economies,
while this figure rises to as high
as 66% in low income countries.
Clearly, a lower per capita
expenditure on health,
implies less
availability of essential medicines.
Interestingly,
according to the WHO,
a previous survey
carried out in Uganda
showed that for certain nationally
listed essential medicines,
out-of-pocket prices for patients
were over thirteen times higher
for branded products than
the international pricing reference.
And even for generics,
the prices were still almost
three times higher
than the international reference.
This is clearly a surprising
finding, and reveals a vicious cycle,
where the Poor will simply
get poorer and sicker.
Besides the general diseases
that tend to affect the whole world,
in general, tropical and subtropical
regions have additional diseases
that are particularly endemic
in those regions,
collectively known as the Neglected
Tropical Diseases or NTDs.
The term “neglected” highlights
the fact that the diseases affect
mainly poor and marginalized
populations in low-resource settings.
NTDs are a diverse group
of communicable diseases
that prevail in tropical and
subtropical conditions
in over 149 countries.
They affect more than
1.4 billion people,
including more than
500 million children,
costing developing economies
billions of dollars every year.
These diseases are to be contrasted
with the big three diseases,
HIV/AIDS, tuberculosis and malaria,
which, relatively speaking, receive
greater treatment and research funding.
There are about seventeen
neglected tropical diseases,
and examples include: chagas,
dengue and chikungunya,
sleeping sickness, and trachoma.
NTDs thrive in areas where
there is lack of basic sanitation.
Thus, Water, Sanitation
and Hygiene services
are also critical to care
for the people
who have many of these diseases,
and for accelerating
and sustaining progress
on neglected tropical diseases
overall.
Besides infectious diseases,
an emerging and potentially greater
health challenge
is in the form of Non-communicable
diseases or NCDs
NCDs account for 63% of all deaths,
that is 36 million out of
57 million global deaths.
And 80% of NCD deaths occur in
low and middle-income countries.
So, NCDs are not only
a health problem
but a development challenge as well.
Within the NCDs,
cardiovascular and mental health
are increasingly posing
immense challenges.
Within cardio-vascular diseases,
Type 2 diabetes is increasing
at an alarming rate.
The number of people
with Type 2 diabetes
has risen from 108 million in 1980
to 422 million in 2014.
In particular, diabetes prevalence
has been rising more rapidly
in middle and low-income countries.
Diabetes is one of the leading
causes of death today, in fact,
and the majority of these deaths
indeed occur
in low and middle income countries.
In Mental Health, Epilepsy and
Depression are particularly noteworthy.
Epilepsy is a chronic non-
communicable disorder of the brain
that affects people of all ages.
Approximately 50 million
people worldwide have epilepsy,
making it one of the most common
neurological diseases globally.
Nearly 80% of the people
with epilepsy
live in low
and middle-income countries.
However, about 75% of people with
epilepsy in low
and middle- income countries,
do not get the treatment they need.
Another mental health disease
of high significance is Depression.
According to WHO,
depression is the leading cause
of disability worldwide,
and is a major contributor to the
overall global burden of disease.
It affects around 350 million
people worldwide
and this number
is projected to increase.
Fewer than half
of those people affected
have access to adequate treatment
and health care.
The issue of improving access
to essential medicines
to developing countries is a massive
and multi-factorial challenge.
And one of the biggest issues
remains economic:
cost & affordability.
But even if the budget for medicines
is available sometimes,
other factors may undermine
the ultimate mission of access
Such factors may include fake medicines
and lack of suitable infrastructure,
for example, such as
cold chain for vaccines.
Fake medicines account for almost
a third of medicines in Africa.
One study, published by the American
Journal of Tropical Medicine and Hygiene,
found that in just one year,
fake and poorly made malaria drugs
contributed to the deaths of more
than 100,000 children across Africa.
The British think-tank,
International Policy Network,
estimates that, globally,
700,000 deaths a year
are caused by fake malaria
and tuberculosis drugs.
Now, a company from Ghana,
mPedigree,
has been hard at work
to tackle this serious problem.
How does it work?
Pharmaceutical manufacturers
can sign up
on to the mPedigree scheme platform,
where they can upload the
pedigree information
of each pack of medicine
into the central registry.
When consumers buy a product made by
a manufacturer participating
in the scheme,
they are able to query
the pedigree information
stored in the registry
by means of a free SMS message.
An automatic response
from the registry
certifies whether
the particular product
is truly "from source" or not.
Today,
mPedigree claims it has labels
on more
than 500 million drug packets.
And Clients also include
giant drug companies,
such as AstraZeneca,
Roche, and Sanofi, and more
There are various other technology
initiatives that promise to improve,
access to much needed essential
medicines, which we cannot cover,
unfortunately, during this lecture,
due to time constraints.
However, references for further
reading have been provided at the end
and they cover other initiatives
to fight fake drugs,
to provide cold chain to ensure safe
access to vaccines and, and more.
This now brings us
to the end of this lecture.
Good-bye.