Electrical energy is the primary
problem,
the energy is insufficient.
which leads to recurrent power cuts
and from these power cuts,
there are voltage variations
when it is turned back on
and a lot of expensive
devices are damaged.
So that is the first issue.
Once we lost
at the same time
the water pump, that supplies
the water tower,
because the power generator had
been overloaded
and it started delivering
over 600V,
it damaged a lot of
hospital equipment,
even the x-ray machine
was damaged.
So the primary problem
is energy.
It causes multiple
machines to break down
the oxygen extractors
are burnt out,
incubators are burnt out,
but equally in the
post-mortem service,
there are recurring break-downs
because of the fluctuation
problems with electric energy
And it is the same for the equipment:
lamps among others,
burn out often
and that is an added
cost for the hospital upkeep.
So, it's not easy!
When I got to this hospital,
the power generator didn't work
and even today there is a failure
with this generator
I haven't been able to find
the right part for 2 weeks.
So in terms of power cuts
we
really need to find it.
because, considering
our resources
I cannot buy the brand new part.
It costs around a million,
so I am hesitant,
I am getting people to look
on the second-hand market
if we can find something,
it will be that!
The most tenacious
and recurrent problems
from our point of view is,
the unavailability of
electric energy
the series of consequences
is imaginable
even by someone who
doesn't work at the hospital
and who came to be
treated at the hospital.
When there was a power cut,
the machines are fragile
and can break down.
From this point of view,
there are statistics provided
by institutions
like the World Health Organisation
or the World Bank
Even a lot of hospitals are
not connected
to this source, before we even talk
about availability problems.
So the diagnostic devices
are weakened
there are for example
preservation chains
for products, for reagents,
that can be broken
and you would thus lose
these reagents
and you can lose the
machines as well,
not to mention a pending analysis
and when there is no more electricity,
the consequences are imaginable
by everyone.
You see the work done
by CURES for example
at the University Research Center
for Energy in Healthcare
at the National Advanced School
of Engineering
is trying to address a major issue
in the district hospitals,
The energy and the
quality of the energy,
we know that a lot in the quality
of the service
depends on the quality of the energy.
And innovative solutions
are being researched at the moment
in this research center to
really bring
something revolutionary to
our environment
even if that seems
unimportant in other environments
but we are here
and we need these revolutionary
solutions,
locally revolutionary
that allow us to
keep a good quality of service
the quality and functionality
of the equipment,
and the sustainability
of these equipment
and in the end save money, in the
long term,
for the whole country.
That is what this
research center is for.