Hello. The little girl we just saw
had an x-ray taken
in a large hospital
in Cameroon.
Perhaps have you noticed that
she had to climb on a stool
to be at the right height in front
of the x-ray imaging detector?
The reason was that the electrical
motors allowing to position
the height of the
detector had failed.
The hospital does not have
the resources to have it fixed.
This story illustrates a
great problem in hospitals
in low and middle
income countries:
the lack of proper access to
essential medical devices.
Medical devices are really
an essential technology
in the sense
of our MOOC.
Let me now define this
category a little better.
According to the
World Health Organization
there are over 10 000
types of medical devices.
They range from the simplest
tongue depressor or thermometer
to the most complex
nuclear medicine machine.
It is not easy to give a
general definition
of what is or is not
a medical device.
Basically it is an article,
instrument, apparatus or machine
that is used in the prevention,
diagnosis or treatment of
illness or disease or for
detecting, measuring,
restoring, correcting or modifying
the structure or function of the body
for some health purpose. Typically,
the purpose of a medical device
is not achieved by pharmacological,
immunological or metabolic means.
This is the World Health
Organization's summarized
definition of medical devices
as there is actually a longer one.
This definition shows how vast
the domain is.
In order to understand
the importance of medical devices
we must try to better understand how
they fit into health care processes,
and in particular
into health systems.
Let us take a step back and
consider the outcomes of
an important international
conference which took place in 1978
in the city of Almaty in Kazakhstan
or Alma Ata as it was then called.
This conference stressed health
as a basic human right
and called all of the World Health
Organization's member states
to urgent action to reach
health for all by the year 2000.
This goal has obviously
not been met.
However the conference delivered
another very important message.
It stressed the key role
of primary health care,
particularly
in developing countries.
The famous Alma Ata Declaration
which resulted from the conference
includes a series of
very important principles
which are still highly pertinent to
the organization of health care today.
In particular, it defines primary
health care as :
"Essential health care based on
practical, scientifically sound
and socially acceptable methods
and technology made universally
accessible to individuals
and families in the community
through their full participation
and at a cost that
the community and country
can afford to maintain
at every stage of
their development,
in the spirit of self reliance
and self determination,".
The declaration goes on
to say that
"it is the first level of contact
of individuals,
the family and community
with the national health system
bringing health care
as close as possible to
where people live and work
and constitutes the first element
of a continuing health
care process,".
The declaration also states that
primary health care is a
central function
and main focus
of the country's health system
and that it is
closely intertwined with social
and economic development.
This declaration, although it is
a high level document,
has very practical implications.
In particular,
it gave the fundamental principles
of how health systems
must be organized.
Health systems are not only composed
of public hospitals providing
diagnosis and care.
Primary health care stretches
far into the community
as we know that determinants
of health can be found in
domains as diverse as
education, communication,
agriculture,
infrastructure and so forth.
It involves a variety of very
important roles,
such as promotion of proper
nutrition, supply of safe water,
family planning and education
concerning prevention
of major health problems.
Also, health systems involve
not only public but also
private health structures,
which can be operated by
faith based organizations or
charities as well as
for-profit enterprises.
We will remain focussed on the
public health care system
for the purpose of this course.
Every country has it's own way
to organize the different layers
of the public health system
but in general it is or should be
influenced by the principles
of primary health care,
which we have just described.
These different layers can
be represented in the form
of a pyramid to express
the number of facilites
at each level as well as
the degree
of specialization.
One generally finds a first contact
point at the base of the pyramid,
which is the primary level
properly speaking.
In other words, if you have a
health problem that is where
you will enter into contact
with the health system.
If your case cannot be treated
at the primary level,
you will be referred to the upper
layer called secondary health care.
This will typically be a
regional hospital
with capacity to perform more
advanced surgical interventions
and to perform more sophisticated
diagnostic procedures.
The tertiary layer
is for more complex cases,
which require highly
specialized services.
These will typically be found in
larger structures
such as central hospitals.
The primary level is ideally where
a majority of the health problems
affecting the community
will be taken care of.
It may involve independent
general practitioners,
health posts operated
by community health workers,
health centers
or small district hospitals
located close to
the communities.
This level will, for example,
include the capacity
to assist child deliveries,
to diagnose frequent and simple
conditions and provide basic care.
Ideally the health services
at this level should also include
the capacity to perform
basic surgeries such as C-sections.
As we think about
improving health
and reinforcing health systems
with innovative medical devices
this layer is precisely where we
should focus our attention first.
Crucial technologies here
will include for example
ultrasound for antenatal exams,
sphygmomanometers to
detect high blood pressure,
oxygen concentrators for
acute respiratory destress or
radiology for diagnosing trauma
from road traffic
accidents.
This is also where a close
follow-up of patients,
such as adherence to medication
should be provided.
Many other crucial medical
activities should take place
at this primary level;
close to the communities
such as campaigns for vaccination,
screening campaigns for
specific diseases or awareness
campaigns for reproductive health.
Now that we know the different
layers of a health system
focused on primary health care,
let's look into the conditions
which make them function well.
The World Health Organization
has defined a framework
of 6 building blocks
for health systems.
Each of these building blocks
is of crucial importance.
First a health system needs
adequate health services,
which means services that deliver
effective, safe quality
health intervention with a
minimum waste of resources.
The system also requires
a well performing workforce.
That is, one that is well trained,
sufficiently staffed
and fairly distributed.
Health information systems
must be in place which ensure the
production, analysis, dissemination
and use of reliable information
on health determinants,
health system performance
and health status.
As you can see, our fourth block
involves having equitable access to
essential medical products,
vaccines and technologies
of assured quality, safety,
efficacy and cost effectiveness
and which are
scientifically sound.
This is crucially important.
It is out of question
to rely on sub-standard solutions
just because the country is poor.
The next block
concerns health financing,
which is not only about raising
adequate funds for health,
but also about protecting
people from impoverishment
associated with having
to pay for health services.
Finally, leadership and governance
involves ensuring
strategic policy frameworks exist,
combined with effective oversight,
as well as regulation
and accountability.
As we can see, reinforcing
health systems will necessarily
involve the provision of
adequate medical devices.
However we need to carefully
assess the insertion
of these medial devices
into the system
in order to ensure that
they contribute
to strengthen it as a whole.
As we will see, it is for example
absolutely crucial to know
who will provide maintenance and
repair for these medical devices.
I would like to discuss yet
another important angle
from which we need to consider
the importance of medical devices.
It is related to what is called
the burden of disease.
There are different metrics
available to characterize
disease burden, but let us just
have a look at the overall mortality
per 100 000 people
over all age groups.
Here we have a graph showing
the 10 main causes of death
recorded by the
World Health Organization for
low and lower
middle income countries in 2004.
There are 3 different
types of causes:
infectious diseases,
highlighted in orange,
non-communicable
diseases in blue
and injuries and in particular
road injuries in green.
Note the importance of
non-communicable diseases
such as cardiovascular
and respiratory diseases,
as well as diabetes
and cancers.
They represent an overwhelming
majority of the causes of death
represented here with 60%.
Also note the importance of
road traffic accidents which will
tend to increase in the coming years.
Finally, there is still
the important number of deaths
related to perinatal conditions;
that is deaths of newborns
which are not shown here.
According to the World
Health Organization,
perinatal deaths - of which the
main causes are prematurity,
asphyxia and infections - will represent
over 8% of all deaths in 2030.
This table gives us a blueprint
on how to determine
where priorities must be set
as we think of
developing essential
medical devices.
Now that we understand the
importance of medical devices
in the framework of health systems
let us get a sense
of how available medical
devices really are.
As you may have suspected,
medical devices are not available
to a large fraction of
the world's population.
This graph shows you an estimate
based on 67 countries,
which account for more than 90%
of total medical devices
sales revenues.
As you can see
the Middle East and African market
is virtually non-existant,
in spite of the high
burden of disease in these regions.
Even in Asia the numbers are bleak
when we realize that in fact
Japan alone consumes 10%
out of the 17% for Asia.
In fact, in 2009 only 10 countries
accounted for over 80%
of the world's sales revenues
with the US alone
consuming 40%
followed by Japan, 10%
Germany, 8%
and France, 4%.
The imbalance is absolutely
striking and the numbers
speak for themselves. Nearly 2/3
of the global medical devices
are consumed by these 4 countries
alone while they represent
less than 9% of the
world's population.
The design of medical devices
is very dependent on
the context for which
they were intended.
Medical devices developed to
work in industrialized countries
rely on quality infrastructure,
sufficient financial resources,
adequately trained personal
and controlled
environmental conditions.
You will have recognized
the main challenges caused
by the context of
low and middle income countries.
As a consequence
there is a large mismatch between
what low and middle income
countries need and what is
available in the market today.
As we have seen, the need for
adequate medical devices
is phenomenal and we hope
that many of you
will now start to think about
innovative medical devices.
Goodbye.