Now we'll hear from Dr. Heiko Gebauer,
leader of the Business Innovation
for Sustainable Infrastructure
Services Group at Eawag.
He'll be joined by Caroline Soule,
a researcher at Eawag's Department
of Environmental Social Sciences
and together they'll present
their work on market-based approaches
for delivering sustainable water services
in low income countries.
During these days
you might heard quite a lot
about the word business model
and business model innovations,
so it became quite popular.
If you hear business model
you might already have
some association in mind
what it actually means.
Basically business model
more or less describes
the logic of organization,
how to create and capture value.
In the next couple of minutes
we try to answer three questions.
First of all,
what are business model innovations
and how can they actually contribute
to household water treatment systems?
Finally, how can different elements
in the business model be altered?
So business models, to be clear,
refer to non-profit organizations,
but also the profit-oriented companies.
And naturally in the household
water treatment systems
we somewhat
quite often talk about non-profits.
But non-profit doesn't necessarily mean
that you don't charge your people,
so you also try to recover
some of your cost,
and organizations like OSHO,
the Oromo Self-Help group in Ethiopia
are trying to give
their water filter there for free
but then try to charge the [inaudible]
charge for the material to their customers.
And customers make a nominal contribution
to the water filter as well.
Profit-oriented companies
like Unilever, of course,
they try to make money
with the water filters.
The idea is to sell them above
the manufacturing cost
so you have sufficient
revenues and profits
to finance your company.
And in between non-profit organizations
and profit-oriented companies
an interesting new type of business model
is actually emerging,
and this business model
are so called social businesses.
They're innovative in a way
because they try to combine economic
but also social goals.
An example would be Hydrologic
from Cambodia
and the social goal is to make
household water filters affordable,
but also desirable
for rural families in Cambodia,
but, on the other hand,
also to recover their costs
and to finance the distribution channels
and the manufacturing of the filters.
If you work with business models,
the most common way is to do it
with the business model canvases.
For profit-oriented companies
these canvases normally
have nine elements.
You start from the right to the left,
from the customer segments,
to customer relationship,
to distribution marketing,
and also the value proposition.
And then you take your key activities,
key resources, and key partners as well.
These elements are based on
the fundamental of every business
that's about revenues and costs.
And if you want to work with that
you basically have to answer
three questions.
First of all, what value
do I deliver to my customers?
What value do I offer to my customers?
And how do I capture value,
and how do I finance my business?
And for non-profit organizations
these canvases might look
a little bit different.
Here you decide or distinguish into
Donor model canvases,
Beneficiary model canvases.
For Donor models
it's very much about
the value propositions
for the donors,
and for the Beneficiaries
is about the impact metrics,
so what kind of social impact
you try to achieve,
and you try to combine
these different business model canvases
in order to make your whole approach,
your whole implementation
of business model financially sustainable.
As part of any of these business models
for social businesses,
non-profit organizations,
or profit-oriented ones,
it's important to understand
who is your actual customer,
and what's your market environment.
And this market environment
is typically called the BOP market.
BOP stands for the Base of the Pyramid.
The base of the pyramid describes
people living close to the poverty line
with a handful of dollars per day.
The question is,
how you can understand the benefits,
but also the needs
and the preferences
these people actually have.
And we don't want to go
into any details here,
but there's a lot of literature
actually describing,
based on the pyramid's strategies,
subsistence marketeers,
market places,
but also how you could get out
of poverty,
or even how you make
business solutions for poverty.
Here are just examples of books
and links, your guide for follow-ups
in order to better understand
how you can really make
your products and services affordable
for the BOP market, but also desirable.
So let's come to the next question.
How can business model
innovation actually contribute
to household water treatment systems?
If you look into how household
water treatment systems
should go into the market,
how can we penetrate the market,
you typically start with a pilot phase
that hopefully you can prove
that the distribution and sales
of your household water treatment system
become financially sustainable.
And then when the pilot
becomes successful,
you try to scale up to reach
a higher market penetration
to sell more filters.
Then finally that you can scale up
in terms of social impact
but also in terms of
your financial contributions
and the finances you need
to get from a pilot to a scale.
Unilever started
the CSR business model.
In the CSR projects,
for years they experimented,
they're finding new ways
in creating a mini water treatment plant
that can finally become
a basic household water filter.
They made a lot of design changes
and a lot of cost reductions
in order to make this kind of
household water filter,
the Compact 14 Liters filters;
desirable but also affordable.
By introducing it to the market
and by also looking into
the first commercial successes,
but Unilever actually saw
that it becomes quite
an interesting business for them.
So they re-integrated it
into the normal business units.
By seeing actually
the commercial success,
Unilever decided to change
the business model
to a commercial business model.
A key element
of this business model was
going through different kinds
of sales channels,
like your door-to-door
but also traditional retail channels
to reach a high number of customers.
And if you talk about
high number of customers,
until now about 57 million people benefit
from this kind of filter.
But it also went
for Portfolio extensions.
So instead of just going
for one filter or maybe a couple of them
they really increased
the product portfolio.
And this product portfolio
no longer addresses only
the low income segment,
but also more into the middle income
but even higher income segments.
All these filters have an
aspirational design
so they look nice,
people really want to desire it
and they're nevertheless
also affordable.
And when it comes to affordability,
Unilever implemented an interesting
business model innovation.
This business model innovation
is actually quite close
to what I initially introduced
with the printer and the ink.
Unilever makes money
with selling the filter
but also selling consumables,
or what we call Germ kill kits.
So after an amount of time
we have to replace your Germ kit
in your filter,
and Unilever makes money
of selling these kits
in order to finance distribution channels
and to have a blink
to the existing customers.
By Phase 2, as I said ,
Unilever business model
became financially successful
and could scale up as well.
Now let's look at the last example.
This is from a Social business.
Social business Hydrologic
in Cambodia.
Hydrologic started initially
with the idea
"We want to make very cost-effective
household water filter."
And by making it very cost effective,
they went for a simple design
in order to make it very affordable
for the people.
And the idea was to sell
this kind of design to NGOs
that, more or less, can give this filter
to the beneficiaries,
either by charging for it as well
or maybe even giving it away for free.
What they try to do was --
of course that is NGOs
if they don't sell it,
we have to subsidize the price.
So the NGOs also have to invest into it.
And the whole set up was finally,
fortunately in a way,
that the manufacturing cost
of the household water filter,
Hydrologic Hat,
was above the sales price.
And above the sales price means,
Hydrologic had needed donations
to finances its business,
but also the NGOs needed donations
to subsidize the water filter prices.
And now it's the question:
"How we can change this kind of thing?"
Can you, for example,
make it more attractive
by adding financial services
like micro-credits to it
that people might not be able
to invest into it
but maybe micro-credits
might solve the problem?
But interestingly,
Hydrologic changed even more
than just like a financial service.
What they did is really going
for aspirational design.
So instead of making the product
more cost effective, more affordable,
they changed the whole mindset,
saying: "No, we want to have something
that is aspirational, and which is easy
to use for our customers."
And the making aspirational
it becomes attractive
also for commercial channels.
So today you can buy these filters,
not from the NGO
but through traditional
retail channels in Cambodia.
And by selling more to people
Hydrologic experienced
that interestingly,
the manufacturing cost went down
because by producing more,
it means you have higher
economies of scale
and to reduce your manufacturing cost.
So Hydrologic was actually in the position
that the sales price was higher
than the manufacturing cost finally.
And the making money with the filter,
the whole business model
became financially sustainable.
In about two years,
about 100,000 filters could be sold.
So Heiko has spoken to you so far
about what are business models,
what are business model innovations
and how can they contribute
to household water treatment systems.
Now I'm going to discuss
some of the trends we're seeing
in business model innovations
for water treatment systems.
We published a paper in 2014
which classifies implementation models
for water service provision
and identify some ways
organizations are innovating,
which include diversifying
their offerings, securing payments,
increasing cost recovery,
and extending their distribution channels.
Diversification can mean
adding additional water treatment products
targeted at different customers segments,
selling additional products
like shampoo and hygiene products.
and securing financing
via unconventional avenues
such as carbon credits, or green,
or social impact bonds.
Securing water payments can be achieved
by a partnering
with mobile payments services
such as M-Pesa,
and allowing people to access
treated water using prepaid cards
during times when water retailers
would usually be closed.
Cost recovery, an increase
in cost transparency
can be achieved through
local production of equipment
and training local staff for repairs.
Additionally, by increasing the density
of the distribution of units
repairs and replacements
can be attended too quickly
which reduces losses
which would be incurred
if there was down time.
Developing professionalized
distribution approach
can involve multi-channel distribution,
which means you can sell door-to-door
buy also in supermarkets.
This would involve individual
distribution targets,
margins and sales volumes
for each channel.
Additionally, distribution centers
can become service centers
which also handle the marketing
of new products.
In summary, we've explored
what are business models,
business model innovations,
and what aspects of them
can be altered
in order for household
water treatment systems to reach scale
by exploring the journey
of three different organizations
who have been producing successful
household water treatment systems.
I hope you enjoy
the rest of the course and the week
and good luck on your exam.