Welcome back.
I hope you had a nice weekend.
Me, I went out and got a haircut.
Last week, you were probably all saying I
needed one.
Well, I got one.
But anyway, this week, let's get down to
business.
Now that we know all about the different
technologies for household water treatment
and how they work,
let's talk about how to get these
technologies into
the hands of people, of many people at
scale.
In today's module, we'll look at different
implementation strategies which
are dependent on the main objective of
whoever is promoting HWTS.
And regardless of the objective, there are
three key ingredients that are required
for uptake.
Those are supply and demand, and
financing.
Muhammad Yunus, the Nobel prize winning
economist, is
one of the driving thinkers behind social
business models.
He proposes a framework for considering
business
models depending on whether the principal
objective
is to maximize financial profits, or to
maximize some other social good like
public health.
Traditionally, businesses have aimed to
maximize profits of course while
not-for-profit organizations for example
charities,
have aimed to maximize social goods.
Yunus proposes a middle way, a social
business
model in which the principal aim is still
to advance a social issue but while
covering
costs from its operations to repay any
invested capital.
So social businesses are not charities and
they aim to be financially sustainable.
However, surpluses are not returned to
investors
as dividends, they're reinvested in the
business.
And therefore, ultimately benefit the
target population
through lower prices, improved service, or
greater accessibility.
This framework applies nicely to HWTS.
And I'll give some example of these three
different approaches.
Of course these three classes are
theoretical, and real world organizations
usually
fall somewhere on the spectrum in between
two or three of the classes.
Well, applying this framework to HWTS, I'm
going to
restrict our discussion to the low and
middle income markets.
There's quite a market for household water
treatment in
rich countries, but that's not the focus
of this course.
In the last ten years or so, there's been
quite a lot
of excitement about the market potential
in low and middle income settings.
Even though these people don't have a lot
of money, there
are an awful lot of them and they do spend
money.
The economist C.K. Prahalad kicked off
this interest with his article called The
Fortune at the Bottom of the Pyramid and a
book of the same name a few years later.
Now it's more commonly called the base of
the pyramid.
I, I guess it sounds more respectable that
way.
But the key insight here is that there
around 4 billion people who make less
than $2,000 per year, and that
conventional
markets are not reaching these people at
all.
Here, India is particularly important,
because while
there's an emerging middle class in Indian
cities, there are more people living in
poverty in India than in all of Africa.
And those 4 billion people spend a lot of
money on water.
This 2007 report
estimated that the BOP water market was at
$20 billion and growing rapidly.
Of course, that's not all spent on HWTS,
but these kinds of numbers
are large enough to generate interest
among
social businesses, and even conventional
profit-oriented organizations.
When a conventional business wants to
enter a new
market, there's a well-established path
which looks something like this.
Businesses start by trying to exist and
survive, making
investments, but not seeing much in the
way of returns.
Hopefully, they then start to succeed and
scale up, and finally reach a
certain stage of maturity, especially when
producing something durable like a water
filter.
There are heavy investment costs for
things like plastic moldings, and large
economies of scale that can be
realized only after achieving some
commercial success.
Now this model doesn't work terribly well
for BOP markets.
Some of the basic assumptions and
rationales in conventional business
thinking don't apply.
Traditional innovation management is very
good
in creating needs in existing markets.
If there's a market, traditional
innovation management can
describe how to design new products and
services.
But with the BOP, there may be needs but
as yet no existing market.
The creation of markets requires the
business model to innovate.
A business model is a holistic picture of
the logic of a company that describes
the various pieces which build the company
and
collects them to the business and
institutional environment.
It also links the different business
elements to the customers and
enables thinking about different ways of
integrating customers into the value
proposition.
Well, if companies want to succeed in the
BOP market, they have to innovate not only
in products and services, but their entire
business
models at multiple stages along the, the
curve.
They have to be innovative in finding ways
to link their business to local
institutions and other businesses, and in
finding
ways of integrating customers in the value
creation.
This involves a lot of risk.
And business model innovations are much
more
likely to fail, than to be successful.
Whether the aim is to maximize profit or
some social good, to recover investment
costs or not.
Organizations that want to succeed in HWTS
need to have business models
that include three core elements: demand,
supply, and financing.
People have to want to use HWTS.
They have to be able access HWTS products,
and somebody needs to pay for
the product as well as for the expenses of
getting it to the eventual users.
If we draw some tips from the business
world, you'll
often hear about the four Ps, which are
product, having
the right product at the right price,
promoting it effectively,
and having a good place where people can
access the products.
This is another way of organizing those
three elements of demand, supply, and
financing.
UNICEF has taken this four P approach and
added two Ps in the context of HWTS.
These are population, finding the right
population, and program monitoring and
evaluation.
You can read more about it in this
document.
How does a profit-oriented business look
at HWTS?
So far, the focus has been on the demands
of those most able to pay high prices.
And these are upper class consumers,
typically in urban areas who tend to be
drawn to high end products and durable
goods more than to consumables.
There are many products that require
electricity and cost hundreds of dollars.
Using processes that we've looked at like
reverse osmosis or ultraviolet
disinfection, sometimes together.
And companies create demand for these
products
through commercial marketing, using highly
aspirational images.
They strive to create effective messages,
and locally relevant value propositions.
While these products are available through
well established supply
chains devices can be bought in
supermarkets or appliance stores
and specialty shops, and are primarily
sold at a retail price which
includes a margin for distribution
marketing and profit.
Durable goods tend to be expensive but
some companies cross-subsidize by charging
less for the initial hardware and relying
more on consumables for revenue.
This is sometimes called razors and blades
model like handheld razors where the
handle is
very cheap or even free but the
important revenue stream comes from the
consumable blades.
Most of the products sold with this model
are filters.
Typically, in combination with a
disinfection
step like chlorine or maybe UV radiation.
And these are a few of the main commercial
companies
with, with products, but it's not at all a
comprehensive list.
Most of these products belong to larger
families of
businesses and started life as a corporate
social responsibility innovation.
Let's take a look at one of these in a bit
more detail.
Hindustan Unilever is part of the huge
Unilever Group worth over 40 billion
Euros.
Hindustan Unilever by itself is a big
business family with more than 35 brands,
mostly
in consumer non-durable products like
soaps, detergents,
and shampoos, but also tea and ice cream.
It's based in India and it has a huge
market.
Since the 1990s, Hindustan Unilever's
Corporate Social Responsibility program
has been working on a product to improve
drinking
water, recognizing that both in urban and
rural India,
people did not have access to safe
drinking water.
And importantly, there weren't any
effective
options available that were well accepted.
Boiling was the main option, but unlike in
other parts of the world, boiling was
perceived as a burden, expensive, time
consuming,
and giving treated water an unpleasant,
flat taste.
In 2000, the first product was launched.
The Purit Classic with a capacity of 23
liters and available in royal blue and
burgundy.
This cost 2,000 rupees, or about $44 at
the time.
Soon after, an autofill product was
launched for customers with access
to tap water, even if the tap water might
not be continuous.
And in 2010, the industrial giant, the
business giant Tata came
out with a household filter called Swatch
priced at a 1,000 rupees.
And Unilever, Unilever, immediately
followed suit
with its Compact model, shown here.
In the same year though, Unilever also
aimed at more affluent customers
with its Marvella unit, which looks
very fancy but also doesn't require
electricity.
The Purit product was sold through
existing stores where Unilever had
strong distribution channels, but also
through direct to home network sales.
Which required hiring a force of 10,000
demonstrators who
were paid through a combination of salary
and commission.
Marketing was aspirational but with a
health-based
dimension, using the slogan, as safe as
boiled
water.
By 2010, Unilever had sold nearly 4
million units, and over the next
several years, they further refined the
product
introducing new variants targeting
specific customer niches.
In 2014, this is what the Purit family
looks like.
You still have these Classic models.
Compact is now called Classic as well.
And there's a new lower cost model called
Intella.
There's also something a little bit higher
end, 3,100 rupees.
Marvella is still there, but there but
there are higher
end Marvella products that do require
electricity with UV or RO.
So the entire family spends quite a
spectrum of different types of consumers.
Most of Purit sales have probably been to
relatively well-off customers.
Next, let's look at social business
models.
Here the objective is a social good which
is to
improve health by reducing exposure to
pathogens and drinking water.
To do this there need to be three elements
in place, people drinking unsafe water,
an effective HWTS product, and consistent
use of that product.
Social businesses working on HWTS may face
that problem of needs without markets
and have to find ways to create demand,
supply, and financing instruments.
For demand creation, social businesses
typically rely on social marketing
approaches.
Targeting particularly vulnerable
populations such as
rural areas in the base of the
pyramid who are more likely to face health
problems from unsafe drinking water.
Social marketing can be done through
multiple
channels, typically involving mass media,
but also
reinforced through visits to communities
and households
where demonstrations and trainings can
take place.
Products are typically branded and
advertised with aspirational messages and
images, and done in line with theories of
behavior change communication.
Instead of focusing exclusively on health
outcomes and negative reinforcement
like, you will get sick unless you use
this product.
Social marketing of HWTS products invests,
involves campaigns that focus on
aspirational messages on beauty and
cleanliness, overall health and aesthetic
improvements.
On the supply side, products are sometimes
produced in country.
For example, liquid chlorine solutions and
quality control is important.
Distribution channels often have to be
built
up and may make use of non-commercial
human resources like NGOs, health workers
or
community-based groups in addition to
local entrepreneurs.
For financing, social businesses aim to
recover costs,
at least the cost of the product
distributed.
Often other costs like promotion, training
and monitoring are subsidized, so
that prices don't rise beyond the reach of
the vulnerable target populations.
There have been a few attempts to tap
into Micro-credit especially for larger
expenses like filters.
In the module on ceramic filtration, we
looked at two Cambodian companies
RDIC and IDE which could be said to follow
a social business model.
Population Services International, or PSI,
is one of the
largest social marketing organizations in
the world and has
extensive experience with different HWTS
products including the Safe
Water System, Medentech's Aquatabs, and
the P&G Purifier of Water.
They've described some of their main
lessons and best practices in this nice
report, and let's now take a bit closer
look at the purifier of water.
Procter & Gamble, or P&G, is another huge,
multi-national company.
They manufacture and market over 300
different products around the world.
P&G spent millions of dollars developing
Pur, a combined coagulant flocculant
and disinfectant product in its corporate
social responsibility program, and then
tried to establish it as a commercial
product with testing, test
marketing for several years in Vietnam,
Guatemala, the Philippines, Morocco, and
Pakistan.
It cost P&G about $0.04 per sachet to
produce Pur which can treat ten liters of
water, and they tried to sell the product
for 0.08 to $0.10 cents per sachet.
P&G learned a lot from these experiments,
but after three years when sales
did not meet targets, they concluded that
the product wasn't likely to become
profitable.
So P&G reconsidered its business plan for
Pur and
in 2005, committed to a non-commercial
approach, where sachets would
be sold at production cost, to programs
targeting people
without safe drinking water, especially
children in low income countries.
This proved to be a more successful
approach and within a few years, they
had sold 57 million sachets compared to
only 3 million during the commercial
trials.
NGOs and social marketing groups like PSI
are key partners now.
And in addition to distribution through
social marketing
channels, Pur has been very popular for
emergency
response, in part because it can treat
highly
turbid waters which cause problems with
other products.
P&G is also experimenting with sales to
campers in high income
settings with the aim of cross subsidizing
the main BOP market.
Pur has now been re-branded as the P&G
purifier of
water and sits firmly in P&G's CSR
portfolio.
Well, what about those charities or pure
not for profit groups described in UNICEFs
framework.
Well, there are not really many groups out
there today
who don't care at all about cost recovery
from consumers.
It's become conventional wisdom in large
part because of the
successes of social marketing initiatives
that when people pay something
for products, they become aware of the
value and in
turn are more motivated to use and
maintain them carefully.
So even purely charity driven
organizations
today will often expect a nominal
contribution from users either in cash or
in kind through labor and time.
Two examples of not for profit HWTS
initiatives are SODIS
and Biosand filters as promoted by the
NGO, Clear Cambodia.
With SODIS, the cost of products the
plastic bottles, is very small.
Though in some areas, purchasing plastic
bottles is a barrier to uptake.
But the main costs of the program are
training and social mobilization
typically through household visits, and
these
costs are subsidized through donor
support.
Similarly, Clear Cambodia is supported by
the
charity, Samaritan's Purse, in its Biosand
filter projects.
Clear Cambodia had distributed more than
60,000
Biosand filters in rural Cambodia, by
2010.
They received additional funding from
Samaritan's
Purse to implement another 15,600 new
filters.
So they created demand through social
mobilization visits to
schools and villages, with demonstrations
of the Biosand filter technology.
And they trained community health
promoters to solicit requests for
filters and were tremendously successful,
generating
150,000 requests, almost ten times as much
demand as their supply plan.
Clear Cambodia then traveled from village
to
village and built concrete Biosand filters
on site.
And then after implementation filters were
monitored repeatedly
with four visits in the year after
installation.
The full cost of one Biosand filter in
this project is about $60, including all
of the
costs associated with distribution and
monitoring, and this price
is well out of reach of their target
population.
Clear Cambodia does sell filters at full
price to other
NGOs and government, but filters for the
poor are heavily subsidized.
Clear Cambodia does ask for user
contributions
including a nominal cash contribution of
about
$4 US, as well as in-kind contributions of
time and materials such as sand.
Also people have to arrange their own
transport to the
household level which is not trivial,
these are heavy things.
And they must also commit to joining
promotion meetings and follow-up visits.
Unlike the profit-maximizing approaches of
other filters, the main cost
of a Biosand filter is the initial
construction and distribution.
There are no recurring expenses, and
operation
and maintenance are relatively easy and
free.
One of the biggest barriers to getting
HWTS technologies in the hands of BOP
consumers is the high capital costs,
especially for durable goods like filters.
Both for-profit companies and social
businesses are actively experimenting with
innovations in financing that could allow
this barrier to be reduced.
A few companies, including Unilever, have
tried micro-credit, with initial promising
results.
Others have looked at payments and
installments or group saving approaches.
And there's a lot of interest in mobile
payments, especially in
East Africa where the mobile payment
programs MPesa, has seen tremendous
success.
And finally, one original approach is to
attempt to
cross-subsidize the cost of HWTS through
carbon credit revenues.
The idea here is that a household
practicing HWTS doesn't
need to boil the water to make it safe to
drink.
So there are savings in terms of biomass
burning and carbon dioxide emissions.
However in 2012, the global price of
carbon
credits crashed and hasn't recovered to
its earlier highs.
So it's not clear if this strategy will,
will be productive in the future.
The largest example of carbon credit
financing in HWTS
is that of Vestergaard Frandsen's Carbon
for Water project,
in which nearly a million Lifestraw family
filters were
distributed for free throughout western
Kenya, in entire communities.
Distribution was accompanied by massive
social
mobilization and education and training
programs,
and the filters alone cost Vestergaard
Frandsen about $30 million US dollars.
Vestergaard Frandsen estimates the total
ten year lifetime
cost of the program at about $120 million.
In order to get carbon credit revenues,
there has to be a strict monitoring
program.
Twice a year teams visit ten to 15,000
randomly
selected households to see if filters are
actually being used.
Vestergaard Frandsen expects to receive
credits for reducing
about 2.6 million tons of carbon emissions
per year.
They've already received their first
carbon credits, but
are a long way from showing a profit.
In any case, profits would be channeled
back into
the project in line with their social
business orientation.
In this module, I've drawn a lot from an
HWTS
training package put together by WHO's
Western Pacific Regional Office.
They have nice materials both for the
trainers
and the participants, that you can
download here.
Regarding drinking water and BOP markets,
these are two very useful reports produced
by the IFC and the World Resources
Institute again available on the internet.
I've also used a number of journal
publications
about business models and bottom base of
pyramid markets.
Some of these are available for download
on the internet as well.
I can especially recommend my colleague at
Eawag, Dr. Heiko Gebauer, who
works on business model innovation in the
water sector in developing countries.
Check it out.
And finally if you're interested, piqued
by the topic,
you can learn a lot more about the
economic
side of water and sanitation in developing
countries by
signing up for another MOOC right after
this one finishes.
This one, on water supply and sanitation
policy
in developing countries is taught by a
Professor
Dale Whittington from the University of
North Carolina
at Chapel Hill, and it's going to be
great.
You should all sign up.
I already have.
We've only just scratched the surface on
the topic of implementation strategies,
but I've tried
to organize implementation approaches
along the lines
of the different business models suggested
by UNICEF.
And these are also developed further by my
colleague at Eawag,
Dr. Heiko Gebauer in his article listed on
the last slide.
Check it out.
But, keeping things simple, whatever the
business model, you need to make sure that
demand, supply, and financing are all in
place for HWTS to succeed.
[BLANK_AUDIO]