In the last module we talked
about different strategies
for promotion of HWTS.
If the objective
is purely to maximize profit,
any reductions in disease that result
are nice, but are secondary.
If, on the other hand, the goal
is to maximize a social good,
like reducing diarrheal disease,
then interventions will often aim
to target the most vulnerable populations,
those who are consuming unsafe water.
And of course, the HWTS technology needs
to be effective, and applied consistently.
We've already looked
at the base of the pyramid
but a good strategy can be
to promote HWTS in special settings
where either people
face particular health risks
or where they're more likely to take up
and consistently apply a new behavior.
Today we'll look at some
examples of this approach
in schools and integrated
with health interventions.
There's been a lot of interest
in improving water, sanitation
and hygiene in schools.
One reason is that many children
suffer from diarrhea
and other diseases related to poor wash.
Another argument is that
inadequate wash facilities
prevent students, especially girls,
from attending and completing school.
If there are no latrines and girls
can't urinate privately during the day,
they may simply not go at all.
School boys, on the other hand,
often have no problems
urinating in the open.
It is somehow more acceptable
in many cultures for boys than girls.
Finally, a third argument
for wash in schools
is that by reaching children
when they are young and impressionable
good habits can be established
which will last a lifetime.
So there are many reasons
to work with wash in schools
and there are more and more examples
of combining and integrating
HWTS with school settings.
Demand is generally created
through school level demonstrations
which may involve water quality testing
to demonstrate
the effectiveness of treatment,
and in some cases, children are asked
to bring some messages
back to their homes,
or for example, to demonstrate
SODIS to their parents
in an effort to stimulate demand
within the broader community.
School interventions
tend to be supported technically
by a NGO or other development partner,
but in at least the initial phases,
but there's always close collaboration
with the relevant government partner,
such as the ministry of education.
Costs are generally
not recovered from the students
and schools themselves
usually require financial support,
especially during the startup phase,
but even during routine implementation
when financial resources are needed
for operation and maintenance.
The SODIS reference center at Sandek
has developed
the Safe Water School Project
along with Antenna Technologies,
Helvetas Swiss Intercooperation,
and supported by the Swiss government.
The project launched in 2011
and reached 143 schools
in Bolivia, Kenya, and Haiti.
In Bolivia, the project is headed
by the Fundación SODIS
and covers all 40 primary schools
in Tiquipaya, a city of 50,000
near Cochabamba.
The project has recently expanded
into six secondary schools
and surrounding communities,
as well as a second municipality.
The intervention takes
an integrated approach,
covering water, sanitation and hygiene,
including different types of HWTS,
mainly SODIS and chlorination.
Each school develops a safe
water station for every classroom,
like the one shown here,
and demonstrates both SODIS, you can see
some of the plastic bottles down here,
and chlorination using
electrolytically generated chlorine
with a mini-WATA generator
developed by Antenna,
to produce a chlorine solution
from salt and water.
The project also trains people
to make their own soap,
which is apparently fun,
as well as good for hand-washing.
The safe water school project
is planned and implemented
with local authorities,
in this case, the municipality
and the district education
ministry of Tiquipaya.
The project is monitored
at the school level
by safe water committees
with two to three teachers
and ten students per school,
and at the municipal level,
the Fundacion SODIS,
the support NGO, monitors the project.
After the project is complete,
this is taken over
by the district education authorities.
A key part of the intervention
is water quality testing.
This serves to help monitor
use of HWTS at the schools
as well as to create
demand for safe water.
The schools mostly use piped water,
but the supply is intermittent
and there is almost always
some detectable E. coli in the water.
Here you see a student from one
of those safe water committees
testing for residual chlorine
with a safe storage container there,
and below, these are some of the E. coli
testing plates that are used.
Students and teachers alike
enjoy the water quality testing,
and it has proven very effective
at convincing people
that the treatment
is important and works.
The safe water project provides
initial training
and support for monitoring,
but once the program
is well established,
the municipality will take over
with the NGO, Fundacion SODIS,
available for technical
support on request.
It's hard to measure the impact
of such interventions.
Conceptually, at kind of the top level,
having safer water could lead
to improved enrollment,
attendance, and completion of school,
and perhaps better academic performance.
One might also expect
less diarrheal disease,
though there are many exposures
outside the school environment.
It's perhaps more realistic
to look for improved water
and sanitation conditions in the schools
and possibly in the homes of students
and at a minimum,
to have increased awareness
about drinking water quality and wash.
One of the most rigorous evaluations
of wash in schools to date
was done by Matt Freeman
at Emory University.
He and his co-authors
did a randomized trial
in 185 primary schools in Western Kenya.
This picture is from a different
wash in schools project, also in Kenya.
All of the schools, except for controls,
were provided with hygiene promotion
and an HWTS system
consisting of safe
water storage containers
and a year's supply of WaterGuard
liquid chlorine solution.
Half of the schools were also
provided with additional latrines.
If schools did not have a year-round
water source within one kilometer
and no improved water source
within two kilometers,
they were considered water scarce
and the project provide them
with a new water supply facility,
either a bore hole
or a rain water harvesting tank.
At a follow-up visit six months
after the intervention,
all of the schools,
including the control schools,
had better access to improved
sources of drinking water
and about two thirds of water samples
included residual chlorine,
indicating that water treatment
was ongoing.
Students reported much greater
availability of drinking water,
hand washing water, and soap,
which was also confirmed
by the evaluation teams.
There was also a significant
reduction in diarrheal disease
by more than 50%, but this was found
only in the water scarce schools
which received a new water source.
So, at least in this one case,
we have evidence
of improved knowledge and behavior,
at least after six months,
which may not alone be sufficient
to reduce diarrheal disease burden.
It's a natural idea to link up
HWTS with health interventions.
HWTS is, after all,
a health intervention itself
to reduce diarrheal disease.
And some of the people
most vulnerable to diarrheal disease
might already be in contact
with the health care system
so reaching them could be
easier and more cost effective
through an integrated approach.
HWTS promotion may be more credible
when it comes from a health worker
rather than a water engineer or an NGO,
and finally, there can be
mutual reinforcements
so that not only is HWTS
more effective when paired
with another health intervention,
but that other intervention
could also benefit.
Otherwise, there would be little reason
for them to take on
the additional messages of HWTS.
We'll look at two kinds of integration
with health care systems.
First, around child and maternal health
taking the specific example
of antenatal care,
and second, with the context
of HIV/AIDS management.
There are other potential linkages,
for instance, diarrheal disease compounds
and is compounded by malnutrition,
so there's interest
in integrated interventions there
and there are even potential links
with water-related diseases
like dengue fever, since the mosquitoes
that carry the dengue virus
like to lay their eggs
in water containers.
A key intervention for vector control
is promotion of household
water storage containers
with tightly sealed covers.
But in the interest of time,
today we'll just look
at antenatal care and HIV/AIDS.
First, antenatal care, or ANC.
This example is from Malawi,
where Population Services International
had been marketing WaterGuard since 2002,
but several years on awareness was high,
but uptake was still low.
In 2007 the Ministry of Health
launched a project to promote HWTS
alongside antenatal care visits.
15,000 pregnant women attending
their first antenatal care visits
were given hygiene promotion
and free hygiene kits
which included
a plastic bucket with a tap
and samples of WaterGuard.
The women were then visited in their homes
afterwards by health workers.
And if they returned to the health clinic
for their second, third
or fourth ANC visits,
they were given free WaterGuard refills.
They also got refills if they delivered
their baby in a health care facility
or made post-natal care visits.
Now, the maternal and child health
care sector in Malawi was very concerned
since most women attend
one antenatal visit,
but only about 20% complete
the recommended round of four ANC visits
and less than three quarters of them
deliver in a health care facility,
and less than half make
a timely post-natal visit.
The US Center for Disease Control
evaluated the intervention
with follow ups one year and three years
after the intervention,
which included surprise visits,
testing for residual chlorine,
and visual confirmation
of WaterGuard bottles.
After one year there was a tremendous
increase in confirmed use of WaterGuard
from one percent to 62%
among the women in the program.
Use of the safe storage containers
was almost 100%,
and the evaluation also
looked at the practices
of close friends and relatives
with young children
and saw a large increase there as well,
up to 27% confirmed use.
It seems like pregnancy and childbirth
represent teachable moments
when mothers are very concerned
about the health of their new child,
there are a lot of changes,
and they're changing many behaviors.
If you are a parent, you know very well
that once you have children,
especially your first one,
you change a lot
of your routine behaviors.
And that is an understatement.
Anyway, those same households
were revisited two years later,
and while there was a substantial
decline in confirmed use
among both direct participants
and the close friends and neighbors,
these numbers still represent
fairly high sustained use.
Qualitative research confirmed
that the health care workers
that were involved in promotion
were considered to be
highly credible by the women
and that this influenced them
to continue using HWTS.
What is very interesting about this study
is that the women who were enrolled
were much more likely
to return to the health clinics
for repeat ANC visits.
More than half of the women
completed the full four ANC visit cycle,
90% of them delivered
their babies in a health clinic,
and 90% also made
a postnatal checkup within six weeks.
These numbers are much higher
than average for that region.
This HWTS intervention turned out
to be extraordinarily effective
for the maternal and child health people,
not only for those more concerned
about water and diarrheal disease.
And where both parties benefit,
integration is much more likely to succeed
and this pilot has since
been scaled up in Malawi.
If one's strategy in optimizing
health gains from HWTS
is to target the vulnerable,
it makes a lot of sense
to work with interventions on HIV/AIDS.
People living with HIV have
weakened immune systems
and are particularly vulnerable
to infections, including
water-borne diseases.
They may become sick
with lower pathogen loads,
and an infection that could be minor
in a healthy person,
can be life-threatening.
Cryptosporidium is a particular risk,
and a recent review of people living
with HIV/AIDS in low resource settings
found Crypto to be the most common
waterborne pathogen causing diarrhea
and was a significant cause of mortality.
So, HWTS has been recognized to be
an important element of preventative care
for people living with HIV/AIDS.
While there are not
many studies out there yet,
there is increasing evidence
that HWTS uptake is higher
in interventions with people with HIV/AIDS
than in conventional interventions,
and that there is significant reduction
in diarrheal disease.
There are even a few studies showing
that HWTS may slow
the progression of AIDS.
One study, for example,
found that people with HIV
who received
an insecticide-treated bed net
and a Life Straw water filter,
experienced less severe drops
in their CD4 count, which is an indication
of the severity of the disease.
Participants were 27% less likely
to have their CD4 counts drop
to a critical level
within the study period.
Here's an example
of an integrated intervention.
I'd like to thank Rachel Peletz
for this example
and for the use of her photos.
Rachel conducted
a randomized control trial
in peri-urban Zambia,
which enrolled 120 households
with children under age two,
including 100 HIV positive mothers
and 20 HIV negative mothers.
Half of the households were provided
with a water filter
and safe storage container
and the other half were used as controls,
though after one year,
the control households
also received the intervention.
Here you see the water filter,
and by now, can you all tell me
what kind of filter this is?
Post it on the discussion forum.
Participants were trained
by the project field workers
who made monthly
follow-up visits for a year,
after which the control households
received their filters.
Then, a final follow-up visit was made
two years after the initial distribution.
Follow-up visits were unannounced,
and involved water quality testing
as well as recording of diarrhea
and reported use of the filter.
In addition, an objective
nutritional measure was used
called the Weight for Age Z-score.
Throughout the evaluation period
filter use was extremely high.
People reported using
the filter in 96% of visits.
This was confirmed by the field workers
in around 85% of visits.
On the very last visit,
after two years of use,
92% of households were confirmed users.
Of the people who reported
using the filters,
95% reported not using any other source
of drinking water in the last two days,
either for the mother or for the child,
and these are very high numbers
compared to other studies.
They could have been even higher
except that two of the filters
were eaten by rats,
the plastic tubing part.
So, the evaluation found that the filters
showed more than two log removal
and here it's likely that there were
detection limit problems
preventing measurement of higher LRV's.
You see, if the raw water
contains 100 CFU per 100ml,
and you measure
less than one CFU per 100ml,
all you can say is that there was
at least two log removal.
You don't know if it's three
or five or nine log.
If you compare
the geometric means of water
in intervention and control households,
you can see something like
two orders of magnitude difference.
The evaluation also found
more than a 50%
reduction in diarrheal disease
which again, is high
compared to other studies,
and also found that people
consuming more contaminated water,
more highly contaminated water,
experienced a higher risk of diarrhea.
However, they didn't find
any significant difference
in the Weight for Age Z-score.
This module has drawn heavily
on a few scientific studies
and you can find the full articles here.
Many of them are freely available online,
and the PDF version of this lecture
has the hyperlinks for you.
These are more general resources
which were very useful
in putting together this module.
Again, the PDF's include the hyperlinks
for all of these reports.
So to summarize, there's a lot of interest
in integrating HWTS promotion
with other interventions.
There may well be a better chance
at realizing health gains
because it is easier to reach the people
at the higher risk of infection,
and because those people might trust
the people delivering the message more
if they're respected figures,
like teachers or health care workers.
It's also more cost-efficient
to reach these people
by bundling interventions
into an integrated package.
There is suggestive evidence
and a lot of enthusiasm so far
for integration into school programs
but there's stronger evidence that shows
that when HWTS is integrated
into other health initiatives,
both objectives can have
a better chance of success.
In the next module
we'll look at another kind
of targeted application of HWTS,
which is Emergency Response.
This module will be given
by guest lecturer Dr. Daniel Lantan
from Tufts University in the USA.
Don't miss it!