Welcome back to part two of this chapter.
One of the challenges of NMR
is that we start by observing
a free induction decay such as this,
and that the human eye
is not well equipped
to perceive the frequencies
that are contained in the signal.
And, therefore, one needs a transformation
from the time domain signal
that we have here
into a frequency domain signal
that we immediately recognize,
in this case, a quartet.
And it turns out that
the transformation to go from
free induction decay
to this spectrum is known as
a Fourier transformation,
which we write like this.
And let me try to explain
how this really works.
First of all, we have a signal,
which could be something like this:
S(t) is the initial amplitude--
in this case,
we'll consider a real signal--
times cos- Omega- T, (ΩT).
So the raw signal that comes
out of the spectrum,
it looks like a cosine wave.
Now the first step
of the Fourier transform
consists in multiplying this S(t)
with an artificial cosine wave
that we can call Omega Test times T.
And this, of course, will be
the product of the initial function
times a new function.
And if these two frequencies,
the actual resonance frequency
and the test frequency are different,
then we have a beat pattern.
So in this case, Ω test
is different from Ω, the frequency.
But if they are equal,
then of course, the net effect
is that we have a cos square.
So this is the case where test = Ω
and in that case we see that we have
a square of the cosine function.
Now the difference is that,
in this case, if we integrate
over all of these values
then we get zero
or something that will converge to zero,
whereas if we integrate
over a positive function,
it will be nonzero.
So in this case we have resonance,
when Ω test = Ω.
So the idea now
is to take the raw function
and vary this Ω test systematically.
So Ω test could be
something like:  n ∆ Ω test
So this would be the increment here
and n would be a number of steps,
n going from zero to one to two,
all the way to (N - 1).
And at each value of n,
we do this operation again
and when they are different,
when Ω test is different from Ω,
we plot something that is zero,
so Ω running
from left to right in this case,
there's no effect here at all
except maybe some noise,
and then suddenly we hit
a condition where Ω test is equal to Ω,
in this case called (Ω0)
and we have a peak
with an amplitude A.
And if the Ω test function goes beyond
the resonance frequency
it becomes zero again.
So this, in a nutshell, is what
the Fourier transform is all about,
and it turns out that we can define
the spectrum and frequency domain
as the integral of the spectra
of the signal and the time domain
times Cos Omega Test T.
∫ s(t) cos (Ω test t),
brackets like this,
integrated from zero to infinity.
So this is a simple wave
looking at the Fourier transform.
You can also do this
simultaneously for the cosine
of the sine component, in which case
you need a complex Fourier transform
which is indeed what
modern spectrometers use.
Now once the Fourier transform
is understood, you can use it
to analyze signals.
So this nice beat pattern
actually corresponds
to a proper binomial quadruplet.
This more complicated pattern
actually corresponds
to some arbitrary distribution
of chemical shifts
and it would be very hard
to recognize by eyeball
what the frequencies
are that are contained
in the time domain signal,
and that is why the Fourier transform,
in this case, is essential
to make the information readable
to the human.
Fourier transformation makes it
very simple to do signal averaging,
although signal averaging
has really nothing to do
with Fourier transforms.
Let me first explain
what this is all about.
It turns out that if we record
the same quadruplet four times,
then the signal will
be essentially the same
from one scan to the next,
but the noise will be different.
The noise is stochastic.
If we then add up the four,
this signal will be four times as intense
as of the individual components,
whereas the noise
will be in proportion to the square root
of the number of records
that we have added together.
So, in this case, if we take
four different noise traces,
then the square root
of four is equal to 2. (√4 = 2)
and, therefore, the noise level
only increases by a factor of two.
Now, it turns out that
in Fourier transform NMR
we use this all the time
because we apply pulses
observe the free induction decay,
apply a new pulse,
a new free induction decay, et cetera,
sometimes hundreds
or even thousands of times
and that allows us to benefit
from this advantage.
But you can do the same in the old days
of continuous wave NMR
and you can do it
in virtually any form of spectroscopy,
and this is well-known to all people
who observe signals that are very weak,
such as routinely
the case in astrophysics.
Now there are a number
of important experiments.
First of all, there are experiments
that have been designed
for the measurement of T1,
that is the longitudinal
or spin-lattice relaxation time,
and this experiment
is known as Inversion recovery.
So in inversion recovery,
we apply a 180 ° pulse
to the magnetization
so that it turns upside-down.
And then we wait a variable delay Tau (T),
which can be varying
from milliseconds to seconds,
whatever the case may be used for,
and before we apply
another 90° pulse
and observe the signal.
Note that after the 180,
there is no transverse components
so there is no precessing magnetization.
Now, depending on
the duration of Tau-- T1, T2, T3--
the longitudinal magnetization
may be still upside-down
and somewhat shorter.
It may then almost convert to zero.
It may already have become positive,
or it may have completely recovered
to its equilibrate position.
Whatever the case may be,
the subsequent 90 ° pulse
will rotate in this magnetization
from its position
to positive minus zed axis
into the positive Y axis,
or if it has already recovered
from the positive zed axis
to the minus Y axis.
And consequently,
the signals will be negative
in up to the zero point crossing,
and then become positive.
And it turns out, as we know
from the relaxation chapter,
that this will converge
to an asymptotic value,
which is the equilibrium position
of the magnetization.
And the curve that we see
here is simply given
by the exponential.
So the deviation here,
this deviation Delta is given by
Delta-- it's original value
--times e to the minus T over T1
Mind you, this experiment
also works if the initial inversion
is not perfect.
It could be that the negative component
is a bit shorter than
the positive component,
and therefore we would
perhaps not start at minus one,
but we would have
a slightly different decay.
We can still measure
the deviation accurately.
The only point is that we have
to introduce a variable
fudge parameter here in such cases,
which are quite commonly encountered.
Inversion recovery
is a very rewarding experiment
because it's easy to do
and it gives you immediate insight
into the relaxation
of the different sites.
So here we're looking at
different protons in this dinitrobenzene
and you can immediately see
that some of them recover very quickly.
For example, the H5 proton, which is here,
which is actually squeezed
between the H4 and the H6 protons,
and therefore it benefits
from rather strong
dipole-dipole couplings.
And, as a result,
it recovers very rapidly.
You see the zero passage is
already achieved after a few seconds.
H4 and H6 are less lucky.
Both of them have
just one dipole couple partner
and, consequently, the zero passage
is somewhat delayed
and the recovery here is slower.
And, finally, H2
is kind of isolated out here.
It has no immediate proton neighbor,
and consequently its zero passage
is even further delayed.
Now, of course,
these pictures can be recorded,
and, in fact, they can be
interpreted as follows:
one of them goes very rapidly,
another one goes slower,
and the third one goes very slowly.
So this would be as a function of Tau (T).
This is the equilibrium magnetization
and you can always extract
a different relaxation times T1
from these different recovery curves.
Now if we are concerned
with the measurement of T2s,
that is to say
transverse relaxation times,
also known as spin-spin relaxation times,
then we have to learn
how to do spin echoes.
Spin echoes were invented
in the '50s by Erwin Hann,
initially by accident.
This is known
as a serendipitous invention.
And the idea here is that
instead of doing like inversion recovery
at 180 first and then to 90,
here we start with 90
in order to generate
transverse magnetization,
and we then apply a 180.
Now, remember that
the signal has decayed here,
partly because of its natural
true transverse relaxation time, T2,
but partly also because there is
a distribution of resonance frequencies
due to the inhomogeneity
of the magnetic field.
And it turns out that this decay,
inhomogeneous decay,
can be reversed and, in fact,
this reversal leads
to an increase of a signal,
the formation of an echo,
followed by the natural decay
of the signal again
due to inhomogeneous distribution.
So how does this work?
Well, the first thing to do
is to take magnetization
in its equilibrant position.
We then rotate this through 90°
about the X axis
so that it ends up along
the minus Y axis here.
And then, depending
on where we are in the sample,
some macro factors may rotate slowly,
others a bit faster,
and others are in a great hurry
and will be far ahead
because they are experiencing
a larger frequency.
Then we apply a 180° pulse
around the Y axis,
so that would be like this,
and as Erwin Hann would've said it,
this amounts to flipping the pancake.
So the entire picture is
simply reversed, as by symmetry,
by a plane of symmetry
along the zed- zero- Y axis.
So the C vector ends up behind here,
and so does the B and the A,
but they continue to rotate
at their specific speeds.
So it turns out that they always
continue to rotate counter-clockwise.
So it turns out that
the path described by A here
is exactly the same as
the path described by A
in the defocusing period.
B, in the refocusing period,
will have a longer path,
but it also had a longer path
in the defocusing period,
and C has the longest of all,
which corresponds to
the large excursion.
And when Tau, the refocusing period,
is precisely matched
with the duration
of the defocusing period,
then all three vectors
end up along the same axis.
That means the interference between
these two vectors is constructive
and that means that
the signal will be intense.
And it turns out that we can extract
a T2 from this by comparing
the signal here, which is
the signal at the time of the echo,
and comparing it with the signal here,
which is at the beginning
of the experiment.
And we notice that this decays
as a function of two Tau (2T),
which is the overall time
between excitation and echo
divided by T2.
Now, to understand how this echo forms,
it may be convenient
to draw a diagram of the phase
as a function of time
of these three components.
Let's start with component A.
So during the defocusing period,
it starts with a phase zero
and it builds up a phase,
which is what we see here.
Because of the refocusing pulse,
the phase suddenly changes sine
from Phi to minus Phi (Φ to -Φ),
and that corresponds
to the reversal of this sine here
to the opposite position.
And then during the refocusing periods,
it will converge and come back
to a vanishing phase.
So this would be for A.
In fact, this slope is nothing else
but the frequency of A.
We can do the same thing
for the component B,
which, as we have seen,
precesses faster and therefore builds up
a phase difference more faster.
And this will be reflected
into a symmetrical position
and then continue its precession
in the refocusing periods
and precisely catch up
with A at that point.
And component C is even more dramatic.
C will diverge more rapidly, refocus here,
and all three components
should end up at the same time,
at the same phase,
at the time of the echo.
This concludes part two of this chapter.
Thank you for your attention.