Welcome to the third
and last part of chapter 6.
So chapter 6 ends
with a brief discussion
of polarization transfer.
In fact,
this expression,
INEPT,
means Insensitive Nuclei Enhanced
by Polarization Transfer.
This is typical of so-called acronyms;
that is to say, short words
that are made up of the initial letters
of a long expression.
And this has become very popular,
a fashion that was started
by my PhD advisor, Ray Freeman,
and has since taken
over the entire world of NMR.
It’s full of acronyms that
you may wish to remember;
or some of them
you may better forget.
Now, INEPT is an idea
that is applicable
to heteronuclear systems
with protons and carbon 13,
or perhaps nitrogen 15,
or some other funny nuclei.
And the idea is that
the inherent sensitivity
of the protons is better
than the inherent sensitivity
of the carbons
because the protons
have a higher gyromagnetic ratio.
And the basic idea is
to apply a pulse sequence
which starts by exciting
proton magnetization,
then allowing that to refocus
by forming this echo.
And at the top of the echo,
apply a pair of pulses,
which have the net effect of transferring
the transverse magnetization
from the protons to the carbons.
And this corresponds to a gain
in the amplitude
of the carbon spectrum.
So to understand why one
should like to apply INEPT
to a heteronuclear system,
we first have to look at the populations
in thermal equilibrium,
according to Boltzmann’s Law.
The idea is that,
in Boltzmann’s Law,
the differences in population
are proportional to the difference
in energy.
So the carbon transition here
has a small splitting,
and consequently,
if we have six balls here—
that means the most populated state
is the ground state—
and only five balls here,
there’s a difference of—
6 minus 5 is equal to plus 1;
whereas if we look
the proton transition here,
we have a difference
between 6 minus 2 which is 4.
And consequently,
the difference in populations
is four times larger
across the proton transition
thatn across the carbon transition.
Likewise, we have plus 1 here,
and plus 4 here,
so this distribution here,
with these little balls,
represents a Boltzmann distribution.
And it’s immediately obvious
that this is unfavorable
for the carbons,
and favors the proton transitions.
Now the idea is that the INEPT
will reorganize the populations
in such a way
that the protons transitions
will become antiphase,
so one will be plus 4
and the other will be minus 4,
whereas the carbon transitions
will be considerably amplified.
Instead of plus 1,
we have minus 5 here,
and instead of plus 3,
we have plus 3 here
as a difference in population.
So this is achieved, as you can see,
by swapping populations.
For example, the two balls here
and up here,
and a single ball here
ends up down here.
And this can be achieved
with the post-sequence
that you see here.
We note in passing that,
in this case,
if we consider the doublet
of the carbons,
we have a positive polarization
of three units,
and a negative signal
of minus 5 units.
But if we then add a normal
carbon spectrum on top of that,
then we have 3 plus 1
is equal to plus 4,
and minus 5 plus 1 is minus 4.
So this restores a symmetry.
This is not symmetrical,
not anti-symmetrical.
But this is now
perfectly anti-symmetrical,
and indeed that is one of the things
we can do in practice.
We do that by alternating the phase
of this pulse here.
It turns out
that the INEPT experiment
can be explained in terms
of semi-classical magnetization vectors.
That means that in fact
we associate a magnetization vector, M,
with each and every single
quantum transition.
In other words, that
if we have a pair of energy levels,
we consider that
as a so-called fictitious spin one-half
and we assume that we can
associate a magnetization vector
with each of these transitions.
In fact, it turns out
that a more powerful way
of looking at these things is in terms
of density operators,
and more specifically,
in terms of product operators
that will not be discussed
in this book,
but are the subject of the next volume
in Peter Hall’s series.
But if we consider
semi-classical vectors,
then in the thermal equilibrium,
we have in fact not one
but two proton vectors corresponding
to the two parallel transitions,
and they are both aligned
with a magnetic field.
We start by applying
a 90-degree pulse around the x-axis
and we find that the two proton vectors
are flipped over along the minus y-axis,
as you would expect.
Then we wait for a delay.
This delay, tau, is in fact one over 4J.
That’s the coupling, Scaler coupling,
between the carbon-13
and the attached proton.
And after that, it turns out
that these vectors
will have precessed in this interval
through different angles,
like this.
So one of them goes all the way
to this position here,
that is in great hurry,
and runs quite quickly.
The other one only has gone
through a small phase difference.
At that point, we can apply
a 180-degree pulse to the protons.
And the net effect of that is to rotate,
to flip the pancake,
as Irwin Hand would have said,
and cause the...
proton vector, H-alpha,
to end up in a symmetrical position
with respect to the Z-O-X-plane.
And likewise, the beta vector ends up
in a symmetrical position
to where it was before this pulse.
The next thing we have to do
is apply a 180-degree pulse
to the carbon 13.
And the net effect of that is simply
to swap the labels of H-beta
to H-alpha,
and H-alpha becomes H-beta.
If we did not do that,
then the echo would form
and there would be no refocusing—
there would be no effect
of the Scaler coupling.
But because we have done that,
it turns out that the two vectors
will continue to diverge,
and the H-alpha vector will end up
along the plus axis,
whereas the beta vector
will be ending up along the minus axis.
Now at that point,
we have two vectors in opposite sign
in terms of density operators.
We said that we have
an A-x carbon-z.
At this point here—
so this is point F,
so that makes the connections
with the more sophisticated
density operator,
or we can also call this—
in fact in should have a nom
in front of it—
and this could be called I-x
for the proton and S-z for the carbon.
Now at this point, we’re going to
apply the 90-degree pulse along y.
So we simply rotate
through 90 degree around this axis,
the net effect being
that the H-alpha vector goes
to the south pole,
whereas the H-beta vector returns
to the north pole,
in fact to the same position
where we started off.
So the overall effect from here to here
is simply to invert the magnetization
of the H-alpha line while leaving
the magnetization of the H-beta line
in tact.
But the reason why we do all this
is that we can achieve that effect
for different chemical shifts.
So it works for all multiplets,
for all doublets at the same time.
Now, this position
here can be described—
so, position g—
can be described in terms
of density operators as a H-z C-z term,
or if you prefer, an I-z for the protons
and an S-z for the carbons.
This is also known as
a distribution of populations,
called longitudinal two-spin order.
It turns out that we can consider
the proton transitions,
but we can also consider
the carbon transitions
that correspond to this state.
And then we can apply another pulse,
this time along the x-axis,
to flip the carbon magnetization
down to the minus y-axis,
and at the same time,
flip the C-alpha magnetization
along the plus y-axis.
Now, there are many
interesting experiments that go together
under the expression
of two-dimensional NMR,
which we simply like to call 2D NMR.
And in fact, two-dimensional spectra
have two distinct frequency domains,
omega-1 and omega-2.
It turns out that they can be obtained
by recording a signal in time domain
with two distinct variables, t-1 and t-2,
and that we can apply
a free (inaudible) transfer from t-1
to generate omega-1
and to t-2 to generate omega-2.
But we shall not go into any details
on how this is actually recorded,
but just note that in general,
we have to decide
on some preparation technique,
in the simplest case,
this might be a 90-degree pulse,
like in the INEPT, for example.
Then we have periods in which
there is usually no perturbation at all,
where we allow the spins
to evolve freely.
And then we need some sort
of a mixing interval,
it could be a simple 90-degree pulse,
before we detect the signal.
So it turns out that
the simplest realization is this 90 t-1.
90, and this is known as COSY,
or also Correlation Spectroscopy.
And you may wonder
what this is good for.
Well, it turns out that a COSY spectrum
for a 2-spin system looks like this.
So the single quantum
ordinary 1-D spectrum
has simply two doublets,
one centered
on the chemical shift of spin-A,
the other centered
on the chemical shift of spin-X,
both split by 2-pi-J,
if we use units of radians per second.
And it turns out that
the resulting two-dimensional spectrum
has a diagonal about which
it is symmetrical.
There are multiplets here
that are known as diagonal multiplets
that we shall not look at in great detail.
But more importantly,
there are these off-diagonal multiplets
which tell us that
the multiplet here, centered at x,
is actually connected
with multiplet centered at A.
So the existence of this multiplet here,
this is considered as the proof
that J-a-x is different from zero.
So whenever we see
a multiplet here, we can say,
“Uh-huh, there must be a coupling.”
And that is very important
for the assignment
and many applications of chemistry.
Actually, the spectrum that you see here,
all the multiplets are in phase.
This is not achieved
by such a simple technique,
but this is achieved
by a more sophisticated technique
known as Total Correlation Spectroscopy.
Or TOCSY, we can also write
that down.
As you can see that
acronyms are flourishing.
And it turns out that the basic idea here
is to do some longer mixing period
between t-1 and t-2,
which allows one to get in-phase signals
rather than anti-phase signals.
So the two simplest experiments
that we can do by two-dimensional NMR
are the COSY experiment, which really
means Correlation Spectroscopy.
Maybe should write it out.
Correlation Spectroscopy.
And it’s actually not a good acronym
because it uses the first
and the second,
this first, and the last letter here.
But it’s a nice word;
was popularized by (inaudible)
and has now been widely accepted.
And the other experiment will be
Nuclear Overhauser Effect Spectroscopy,
the same idea.
You can also write the last Y
with a capital to make it plain
that those belong to these two letters.
And these are the two basic experiments
that are most routinely done.
Now it turns out that
in the COSY experiment,
we simply apply a 90-degree pulse
to excite transverse magnetization,
which will then evolve under the effect
of its chemical shifts and J-couplings.
But we choose not to look
at the magnetization,
we do not put the free
induction decay in the computer,
we just ignore the signal,
and apply a 90-degree pulse
which converts
that transfers magnetization
into transverse magnetization
of connected transitions.
The NOSEY experiment is built
on a different principle.
Here we also have the same idea
of a precession
of transverse magnetization,
but in this period here,
we have longitudinal magnetization of,
for example, spin A.
And the idea is that in this period here,
because of Overhauser Effect,
the magnetization
will partly travel spontaneously
from spin A to spin X,
and as a result, when it arrives here,
the transverse magnetization will oscilate
at the characteristic frequencies,
the chemical shift here of spin X,
or here we have a multiplet centered
on spin frequency of spin X,
whereas here we have a multiplet centered
on the frequency of spin A.
So the COSY experiment
is normally used for homonuclear systems,
so we can consider
our familiar energy level diagram
for the two-spin system.
And the magnetization
that we initially excite would be here,
in these two parallel
allowed single quantum transitions.
And the idea of this 90-degree pulse
is that they can be converted
into transverse magnetization
of these two transitions.
And this conversion actually goes
from here to here,
and from here to here.
You can argue whether that actually goes
through the populations or not,
but the basic effect can
be described beautifully
with somewhat
more advanced methods.
In the NOSEY experiment,
it’s a slightly different situation.
Here we have again homonuclear case.
So we have again magnetization,
transverse magnetization
in these two parallel transitions.
And the net effect here is to convert that
into population of these levels,
and then allow the NOSEY effect,
that is to W-0 flip-flop of the two spins
to connect the central populations
of the central energy levels.
And then from those central energy levels,
we can generate
the transverse magnetization
of these connected transitions.
So there are many applications
of COSY,
or Homonuclear Correlation Spectroscopy.
We can apply COSY
to proton spectrum
of molecules such as this.
This molecule here was chosen possibly
because it has many
almost-degenerate protons.
In fact, it’s a bit like a sugar,
since we alway have carbons
with one OH and one H attached.
And indeed, sugars represent
a particular challenge
because the chemical shifts
are very close
and it’s not so easy
to identify couples neighbors.
Sugar chemistry has greatly benefited
from the invention of COSY.
Now we don’t actually see
the molecule,
but what we can determine
from the two-dimensional spectrum
is a diagram such as this
which actually represents
the topology of the coupling network.
That means specifically that proton D
is coupled to proton F and to proton I.
F is coupled to D and I.
I is coupled to B.
B is coupled to A, etc.
And this we can immediately determine
by looking at the spectrum.
For example, between
the chemical shift of A and B—
so the protons are here,
the proton A
and the proton B are up there.
So we see a cross-peak here.
And this cross-peak
in fact corresponds to the fact
that there is Scalar coupling
between A and B.
But we could also look at proton H,
which is somewhere over here.
And we see another cross-peak here,
and that other cross-peak
corresponds to this bar here.
So those represent the J-couplings.
And it turns out that with the help
of the COSY spectra
and the determination
of the coupling network topology,
one can very often
draw immediate conclusions as
to the nature and the structure
and the connectivity of the network
of the protons in the molecule.
Homonuclear Correlation Spectorscopy
is often applied to protons,
but it can also be applied
to exotic nuclei,
such as boron-11,
which actually has
a spin quantum number 3/2,
and therefore is a quadropolar nucleus,
and therefore the transverse
relaxation is very efficient,
the lines become broad,
and the multiplets are not easy
to detect in one-dimensional
boron spectrum.
But it turns out that if we consider
a cage such as this,
or a half-open cage rather,
we can immediately record COSY spectra,
and find that there are in fact
off-diagonal peaks, such as this one,
which obviously connect boron
in the 4-position
and boron in the 3-position.
And so this corresponds
to a J-coupling between 3 and 4.
And we find that same J-coupling here,
there’s a degenerate.
And it turns out that the interpretation
of the spectrum allows us
to reconstitute,
to predict what the cage was,
to determine what that cage is.
So, Nuclear Overhauser Effect Spectroscopy
is now a very popular method.
But in fact, when it was invented,
it was first applied to a problem
that has nothing to do
with Overhauser effects,
but has to do with chemical exchange.
And in fact, in it’s early version,
NOSEY was called EXSY,
which stands for Exchange Spectroscopy.
And this is a beautiful example
of how exchange spectroscopy
can be used
to investigate relaxation mechanism,
or to rearrange mechanisms.
This is a beautiful example
that shows how exchange spectroscopy
can be used to explore
rearrangement mechanisms.
This is a heptabenzolbenzanonium
molecule where there is
in fact one CH3 plus methyl group
in excess,
and it doesn’t quite know where to go,
and therefore travels around the ring.
Now it turns out that one,
this methyl group here,
hops from the one position
to the ortho position next door.
Then the protons that are attached
to the methyl group
that stays behind will move
from this crowded environment
into a different environment,
which is in the ortho-position
with respect to the new
crowded environment.
So you would expect the chemical shift
of the methyl protons one
to be different from the chemical shifts
of the methyl protons in position 2.
And indeed, if we look at the spectrum,
we identify the proton chemical shifts
of these two methyl protons.
So this is the crowded,
and this is the ortho-position,
and we find here a cross-peak,
which is indicative of the fact
that this group here has indeed shifted
from the so-called 1, 2 shift
from one position to the other.
It turns out that the pulse sequence
that was originally invented
to monitor exchange phenomena
can also be applied
to monitor Overhauser effects
in homonuclear systems.
So recall that in a large molecule,
the Overhauser Effect comes primarily
from the flip-flop
transition probabilities
that we called W-0 A-x
between the two up-down
and down-up positions of the spins.
And we also know that this W-0
flip-flop probability is proportional
to the inverse of the sixth power
of the distance between the two spins.
And consequently,
if these spins are far apart,
this sixth power
will be a very large number,
and the flip-flop rate
will be vanishingly short.
Conversely, only when this R is
in the vicinity of 3,4, 5 angstrom
can we actually expect
to see the significant flip-flop rate.
And it turns out that
if we do a NOSEY spectrum
of a large protein,
typically a protein is composed
of amino acids,
and an amino acid might have up
to about ten protons or so.
So if a protein comprises
100 amino acids,
we would have about a thousand protons.
And indeed here, along the diagonal,
we would expect to see
about 1000 distinct chemical shifts
of 1000 different protons.
Not all of them are connected
but if we take a little peak like here,
we can immediately come
to the conclusion that that peak
must be at the the intersection
of two chemical shifts,
for example A, here,
and X, here.
And the amplitude of that peak
is directly proportional
to the flip-flop rate,
the W-0 of the pair, A and X.
And therefore, the amplitude
of this peak is actually proportional
to the inverse of the sixth power
of that distance.
So, any one of these peaks
tells you that these come close,
so we come to the conclusion
that if we draw a molecule
as a loose chain like this,
that A and X must be
somehow close in space.
And you can see
from this 2-D NOSEY spectrum
that in fact there are hundreds
or even thousands
of little cross-peaks here,
and therefore,
we have thousands of restraints
that allow us to determine
the 3-D structure of the protein.
This is quite remarkable
because the protein is in solution.
The solution is isotropic
and homogeneous,
so there’s no need
to make any crystals;
there’s no need to go to a synchrotron
to look at x-ray diffraction patterns.
We can do all this in solution.
Now HSQC is another
barbarian expression
that means Heteronuclear Single
Quantum Correlation Spectroscopy.
And in fact what it means is that
it allows you to correlate the spectra
of gamma-alpha protons,
which have a high gyromagnetic
ratio gamma with other nuclei,
such as nitrogen-15
or possibly also carbon-13,
that have a lower gyromagnetic ratio.
The first part of it is simply the same,
identically the same as INEPT,
so we find INEPT here.
So if you will return to that page,
you will see what that means.
And then we have an evolution here
of the nitrogen-15 magnetization
until we apply another pulse.
In fact, it turns out that
if we add another pulse here,
then we have here exactly
the same sequence.
This is actually can be considered
as retro-INEPT.
And if fact, if we summarize
what happened with INEPT,
in fact, we were converting
the transfers magnetization
from the protons to the nitrogen.
And what we do here is
we convert the magnetization
from the nitrogen to the protons.
This little pulse here, I’ve added simply,
for the sake of symmetry,
this could be the symmetrical
position of this, a 90x.
So this would be a 90x.
And then immediately after that,
we have a 90 minus x.
So the sum of the two
actually vanishes, no operation,
and this is simply a trick
in order to see the symmetry
of the sequence between the INEPT
and the retro-INEPT.
The important result of this
is that we get a map
where we can correlate the chemical shifts
of protons on the one hand,
and correlate chemical shifts
of the nitrogens on the other hand.
And you see there
are many little peaks in this map.
And each peak corresponds
to the polarization being transferred
from an amide proton—
in a protein we have this kind
of situation here….
So this is the beginning of a protein,
goes on and on and on.
And what we see here
is a correlation
between the chemical shifts
of the amide and the amide nitrogen.
And of course there are as many
such groups as we have amino acids.
In fact, one way of counting the number
of amino acids is simply counting
the number peaks in the spectrum.
It turns out that this pattern
is very sensitive to the environment,
and therefore we call this
a fingerprint of the protein;
and the implication is,
and that is correct,
that there are no two different proteins
will necessarily
have different fingerprints,
and therefore,
can be recognized as such.
It turns out that such HSQC spectra
can be used in drug screening,
because if we take a protein
and we combine it with a ligands
that has some affinity for this protein,
then we’ll have
a protein-ligand complex.
In fact, the affinity will be described
by a dissociation constant,
which would be simply the product
of the concentration of the free protein
and the free ligands divided
by the concentration of the complex.
And one of the issues
in drug research is to find a ligand
that has a very small
dissociation constant,
maybe as small as nanomol/liter.
Now, in doing this kind of research
it turns out that we can do a titration
where we observe the protein spectrum,
the HSQC spectrum of the protein
and titrate the ligands.
And if we do that, then we will see
that if we increase gradually
the concentration of the ligand,
that peaks such as this will move.
In fact, we can see them move
around in space,
and we can map that motion.
So, if there’s no ligand,
we have some chemical shift.
And then when the ligand comes in,
we have a change in chemical shift;
so this is a change in chemical shift.
In the absence of ligands,
we have the pure protein.
When it’s saturated with ligand,
we have only the complex,
and in-between,
we have the Sigmond curve,
and you can imagine,
like with a pH tritration,
that this infection point informs us
of the stability of the complex.
In other words,
the very stable protein-ligand complexes
would do something like this.
And very fragile ones
would do something like that.
And the job of the pharmaceutical
industry could be summed up
by saying that you go
from a bad ligand to a good ligand,
a non-specific to a specific,
a weakly-binding
to a strongly-binding ligand.
Now there are many experiments
that are built on the principle
of combining two
two-dimensional experiments
in order to obtain
one three-dimensional experiment.
All of them have this idea that you start
with a two-dimensional experiment
that is somehow
achieves a useful purpose,
and that would have
a preparation and evolution,
a mixing and a detection period.
And then you take another experiment,
which has it’s own preparation,
evolution, mixing, and detection;
and you simply remove the detection period
of the first experiment,
and you remove the preparation
of the second experiment,
and you stitch them together.
As a result, you then get sequence A,
where you have a preparation,
a first evolution, a first mixing,
a second evolution, and a second mixing,
and then you detect
the signal at the end.
Typical example, this could be an HSQC
that would combine,
for example, protons and N-15,
and then we know that we go back
to protons.
And then we can do
a NOSEY after that;
and that would be
combining protons and protons.
So that would be
an HSQC/NOSEY experiment.
Now it turns out that there are many,
many such combinations,
and they can be used
for all sorts of purposes.
One important idea is to assign
the spectra of proteins,
and there is
a particular challenge here.
Now, this is just one application.
There are many other applications
in proteins, for example,
if we would like to assign the proteins,
we could do things like this,
we could go from the amide proton
to the amide nitrogen.
Then we could do a transfer
to the alpha-carbon here.
And we could go to the beta-carbon
in the side chain.
And we could do a transfer here,
and a transfer here,
and come back to this,
come back to this,
and end up here.
So this is already
six consecutive transfers.
And that would actually allow us
to correlate the proton
of the amide group
with the beta-carbon in the side chain.
These are typical experiments
that are currently being developed
in order to assign and interpret spectra
carbon proton nitrogen spectra
of large molecular assemblies.
So let’s try to summarize
the main features of chapter 6,
dedicated to experimental methods.
First of all, the vector model turns out
to provide a simple picture
of many elementary
NMR experiments.
The vector model can be used
to describe the effects
of radio frequency pulses,
of periods of free precession,
and above all, of spin relaxation;
that is to say, the return
of the magnetization vector
to its equilibrium position.
The rotating frame
is a crucial simplifying feature
of the vector model.
NMR spectra can be obtained
by applying a Fourier transformation
to the free induction decays
so that when transformed
from time domain
into frequency domain.
Spin-spin, or transverse relaxation,
corresponds to a lose of phase-coherence.
T-1 and T-2 can be measured
using either inversion recovery
or spin-echo pulse sequences.
Now it is possible to enhance
the sensitivity of spins
with low gyromagnetic ratios,
such as carbon-13 or nitrogen-15,
by polarization transfer techniques
such as INEPT from spins
with high gyromagnetic ratios,
such as protons.
Two-dimensional spectra
can be obtained by measuring signals
as a function of two time variables,
and transforming them
by double-Fourier transform
into two frequency variables.
The two-dimensional COSY
and NOSEY experiments
reveal correlations
between homonuclear pairs of spins.
COSY allows one to identify
Scalar couplings or J-couplings,
whereas NOSEY allows one
to map out dipolar couplings,
through the Overhauser Effect.
HSQC,
which means Heteronuclear Single
Quantum Correlation Spectroscopy,
can be used to reveal correlations
between carbon-13 or nitrogen-15
on the one hand,
and protons on the other.
Two-dimensional NMR experiments
can be combined
to produce three-dimensional
NMR experiments.