Welcome back to our MOOC
on basic steps in magnetic resonance.
Today we shall be talking
about experimental methods
that are the subject of chapter 6
of Peter Hall's book.
This final chapter explains
how NMR is really done in practice.
We shall see how the magnetization
is excited and then observed
and how the time domain signals
can be transformed into spectra
by Fourier transformation.
We shall explain how one can measure
the return of the magnetization
to its equilibrium, inversion recovery,
for longitudinal relaxation
and spin echoes,
for transverse relaxation.
There are a few examples
of more sophisticated methods
such as INEPT, Cosy, Nosy, and HSQC.
Finally, the idea of three-dimensional NMR
opens almost infinite possibilities
for novel experiments.
Chapter 6 is built up as follows--
we start with a brief discussion
of how the experiments are actually done.
To understand these experiments, one
has to see what the magnetization does.
And the magnetization
is best represented in terms of vectors.
Now equipped with experiments
and vectors, we can consider
how to measure relaxation times, both
longitudinal and transverse relaxation.
And then we can move to some
more sophisticated experiments,
such as this one-- this acronym means
Insensitive Nuclei Enhanced
by Polorization Transfer.
It is one of the most fundamental steps
of modern NMR.
Then there are several cases
of two-dimensional NMR
that will be discussed in some detail-
and very briefly, a discussion that we can
go from two to three dimensions
and thus open the way
to a very large number of possibilities.
So the basic NMR experiment
as it is done routinely nowadays,
consists very simply
in applying a radio-frequency pulse
to the sample and immediately after
detecting a time domain signal
which is known as free induction decay.
The rationale is that before we apply
the pulse, we have to wait
for the magnetization to get aligned
with the external magnetic field
and achieve an equilibrium value
which is determined by Boltzmann's law.
The function of the radio-frequency pulse
is to generate a transverse magnetization,
either Mx or My
which is perpendicular to the o z axis
along which the magnetic field is aligned.
Now neither Mx nor My are
in an equilibrium positions
and therefore the magnetization
will try to return to where it came from.
And in doing so, it will actually
precess and induce a signal
in the radio-frequency coil which
will then be amplified
and stored in a computer.
Now it turns out that the human eye
is not well-equipped to detect
frequencies such as this, in contrast
to the human ear
which can do that very nicely.
Therefore, it turns out if we want to see
the frequencies contained
in a signal like this, we have to do
an operation called a Fourier transform,
sometimes written with an italic F
or spelled out as Fourier transform.
And this transformation will convert
the time domain signal
into a frequency domain signal
which we routinely call a spectrum.
And in this spectrum
individual resonances will lead to peaks.
It turns out that the experiment
is not ideal--first of all,
we have the sample in a tube--
typically a five or ten mL tube,
depending on your NMR spectrometer.
And it turns out that this is immersed
in a magnetic field and surrounded
by a set of radio-frequency coils.
The magnetic field, the B0 field
is parallel with the axis
of the sample tube
whereas the B1 field
which is the radio-frequency field
will be perpendicular to the z-axis.
In this arrangement, it turns out
that it is mostly the sample
that is within the radio-frequency coil
that will contribute to the signal,
whereas the sample
that is at the bottom of the tube
or above the R-F coil will not
significantly contribute.
Furthermore, if we look at this tube again
it turns out that the B0 field
is not perfectly homogeneous,
so we could imagine
that the lines of flux go like this.
And, consequently they
are not uniformly distributed.
Now, that's important because
if we consider the magnitization
in a volume element,
also known as a voxel,
in the center-- it will be exposed
to a more intense field
than if we consider a volume element
that is somewhere
at the edges of the sample.
And it turns out that in the spectrum
this volume element here
will give rise to a higher frequency
going from this contribution here.
So this here will stem
from this voxel here.
Whereas this voxel here which is exposed
to a less intense magnetic field
will give rise to a somewhat
lower frequency.
And, clearly, because there are
many voxels, we have a distribution
and a resultant line shape, which can,
in fact, be described by this width here.
Now it turns out that the width
of the filled component here
is the inherent width, or the true width
that is known as delta-mu.
It is the inverse of pi T2,
you might want to call this the true T2,
a genuine, or homogeneous T2
whereas the width that we have here
is the apparent width delta-mu star
which is one over pi2 star
and so this is the apparent width.
And much of NMR is concerned
with fighting this
inhomogenous broadening,
as it is known-- that is to say
that the apparent width is broader
than the true width.
This is something that one has to keep
in mind throughout chapter 6.
So the key to the understanding
of most NMR experiments
is that the magnetization vector
has three components--
so M is comprised of Mx, My, and Mz
and by definition, the longitudinal
component z along the z-axis
is parallel to the static magnetic field.
Now if the M vector only has a z component
and x and y are zero,
then it is aligned with the static field
and it is in equilibrium
and nothing will happen.
So if we want to observe a signal
we have to perturb the magnetization
and make it transverse.
If it is transverse or if it has
a transverse component, x or y,
then it will be starting to precess
around the magnetic field.
Curiously, the precession frequency
is determined by the splitting
in the energy diagram divided by h-bar.
Now, that is not obvious at all.
It turns out there is a splitting
between the ground state
and the excited state, so this is delta-e
and this delta-e determines the speed
at which the magnetization will precess.
This is a rather peculiar thing
and perhaps a a bit difficult
for the beginner, but one
gets used to this.
Now the sense of precession as you can see
in this picture is assumed
to be rotating clockwise.
It turns out that there is a bit
of an argument about that.
Basically, the clockwise rotation
was common in the NMR literature
until the mid-80s-- it was mostly used
by Ray Freeman who had made
many beautiful pictures that used
that notation-- and then suddenly
in the mid-80s, Richard Ernst
at ETH Zurich decided that was wrong
and that we really should
rotate counter-clockwise.
Now you might say that this is irrelevant
but, in fact, it turns out that there is
a lot of confusion in the literature
about it because people
have mixed these two conventions.
This reminds me of a little anecdote
about Wolfgang Pauli--
Wolgang Pauli once gave a lecture
in the 30s about the sense of rotation
of the plane of polarization
in some complicated experiment.
And before he started his lecture
he predicted that the plane
would rotate towards the left
and then two hours later,
after filling the blackboard
with many complicated equations,
he found that the plane
was rotating the other way.
And he stepped back from his blackboard
and said, "Well, ladies and gentlemen,"
"I'm afraid I must have made
a mistake in sign somewhere."
And then at the back of the room
there was Professor Paul Dirac,
another Nobel laureate,
who raised his hand and said,
"Dear colleague, I fear you have made
an odd number of mistakes in your signs."
That is very cruel, of course,
but very appropriate.
In fact, in NMR, one can make
many, many sign errors and with some luck
they compensate each other
but if you are out of luck, they don't.
In this case, Peter Hore has kept
a picture which is actually an old one,
likewise here,
but in the next slides he will move
to the continental description.
So in a sense, remember that
if you rotate this way,
you're OK if you're in a roundabout
in England but if you do this
in the continent, or the United States,
you will be in deep trouble.
So it turns out to understand
this precession and the mutation
of the magnetization about the field,
we have to look at the resultant
of the effective field which results
from the vectorial addition
of the static field, which by convention
is always drawn along the z-axis,
and the radio-frequency field B-one,
which is always in the perpendicular
plane, the xy-plane.
So this B1 field is a magnetic
component of the electromagnetic field,
which is normally applied
as an oscillating field
along some arbitrary axis.
And this oscillating field,
which is a linearly polarized field
can be decomposed into two
counter-rotating components
and it turns out it is sufficient
to retain only one of these components
which rotates in the same direction
as the magnetization
and we can neglect
the counter-rotating component.
Now, it turns out to be convenient
to represent what's going on
in a so-called rotating frame,
often abbreviated as ROT,
which is a frame that is officially called
x-prime, y-prime as opposed to x, y
although those primes are often
dropped in practice.
The frame is defined in such a way
that the B1 component
which is moving here
now appears stationary.
This means that we move with the vector.
If we step on the carousel,
we move with the horses
so they appear stationary,
whereas if we are not on the carousel,
we see the horses as moving around.
When we do that, the external field
gets reduced in effect
and we only have a residual field here.
And at the same time the effective vector,
which is still the resultant,
the sum of this vector and this vector,
is now tilted through a different angle.
In the laboratory frame, this angle theta
is very small, in fact the effective field
is almost parallel to the z-axis
whereas in this case, this angle
can be easily made to 90°.
We achieve that by adjusting the frequency
of the rotations so that the residual
delta-B field disappears.
It turns out that we can redraw
this picture in the rotating frame.
In fact, if we start here and we end up
here then we simply move like this
from the transverse component
to the longitudinal component.
If T1 and T2 are equal,
we actually go the shortest way,
whereas this pathway here,
this curved trajectory corresponds
to the situation
where T2 is shorter than T1.
That means that the transverse
magnetization is lost
before the longitudinal
magnetization recovers.
We can record these signals either
by putting an observer here or here.
In this case we would have a cosine wave
and in this case it would be a sine wave.
In fact, in modern NMR spectrometers
we can detect both x and y components
at the same time and we can cook up
a complex number
which is simply the linear combination
of the x component plus i
times the y component--
i is the square root of minus one.
And this is built on the principle
of the shift operators
like Ix plus Iy-- this is the model,
a pretty classical counterpart of that.
Now you see that, in fact, we have
simply a cosine and sine wave.
Or, if you prefer, we could write Mx of t
which is a complex number
that contains both
the amplitude and the phase.
So this would be the initial value.
It will evolve with the chemical shift--
we could call this i omega zero t
and it will also be attenuated
by i e to the minus t over T2
where T2 is the time constant
of this decay that we see here.
It is interesting to see what happens
if we apply a radio-frequency pulse.
So this is the equilibrium position.
This shows what happens if we have
a rotating frame where the B1 field
that is the static component
of the magnetic field
of the oscillating electromagnetic field.
If we arrange the rotating frame
so that the B1 field is parallel
to the x-axis, then we have
counter-clockwise rotation,
this is the continental convention,
of the magnetization
towards the minus y-axis.
In fact, in general it will undergo
a rotation through a so-called flip-angle,
properly called a mutation angle,
but flip angle is the common word,
and this flip angle is simply
proportional to B1,
the strength of the field,
and the duration of the pulse
multiplied by the gyro-magnetic ratio
of the nuclei of interest.
So beta can be chosen either
to be 90° in which case we end up
exactly here but we can
also have a 180° pulse
We can also have beta equals 270°
in which case we end up
on the plus y-axis.
And actually most surprising
is the 270°-- if we keep going,
we end up at the original position
so we can have a 360° pulse.
That surprisingly means that the situation
is exactly restored as if there were
no pulse at all-- some people
have worried what happens
with the radio-frequency energy
that you have put into the system.
It must somehow go in at one point
and come out at some later point.
Now if we are in the rotating frame,
the magnetization that was initially
flipped along the minus y-axis
will start precessing and in effect
will build up a phase
that we can call phi which is nothing else
but the product of omega times t.
And we should remember that this omega
is in the rotating frame
so it is simply the true precession
frequency in the laboratory frame
from which we subtract
the precession frequency
of the rotating frame.
And in fact this turns out to be
linearly proportional to time
so it is sometimes convenient if we draw
time like this and the phase like this
we simply have a line
with a constant slope
and the slope is given by omega.
For the time being this is not very useful
but in more sophisticated experiments
it will be useful to have
such a phase-time diagram.
This concludes part one of this chapter.
Thank you for your attention.