So far we have seen the process
for the development
of a meaningful innovative
technology in the context
of sustainable development.
We also showed you tools  to ensure
that the technology you develop
will fulfill its function
in reaching the intended impact.
However, your well-crafted technology
will never have any impact
if it remains in your garage
or if only a single prototype
is ever fabricated.
Again, in this course,
we subscribe to the notion
that the wider the essential
technologies are deployed
and the more people
have access to them
the greater the impact.
So now that you have seen
how to develop
an innovative technology,
the question is
how you plan to deploy it
at scale, that is, as widely as possible
over the long run.
The impact value chain canvas
that we presented
earlier in this course helps you
to set your social target goal
and define the necessary steps
to get to it.
It also helps you to identify
the stakeholders
that you have to involve
in the process.
The product value chain
that was presented
in the previous videos
allows you to map out
the different phases
in the life-cycle of your product
along with the corresponding actors
or partners,
while taking into account
their constraints
when designing your product.
This helps you to establish
the technical specifications
of your product and enable you
to think through the issues
related to its production,
usage, etc.
But none of these tools
will help you think through
how you will deliver your product
to your customers or beneficiaries
and how to get paid,
by who and why.
Remember, unless your entreprise
can generate excess revenue
or profit from its operations,
it is unlikely for it to remain
viable and sustainable.
So you need to understand
how to define, as clearly as you can,
how you will derive revenue.
This is generally referred to
as your business model.
However, there is a lot more around
your business model
than simply collecting revenues,
which is the endpoint.
Firstly, you make a certain promise
to the customer
by way of your Value Proposition
then you have to make sure
that your operations
for realizing the product are
economically viable
to enable you to honor your promise
or Value Proposition to the client.
Thereafter, you have to ensure
that the product is delivered
in a manner consistent
with the promise
or Value Proposition,
which may require setting up
a set of relationships
that will ensure this objective,
for example,
sales and distribution channels.
This then finally triggers
the revenue or payment event,
and hopefully
the commitment to a series
of ensuing revenue events
at a predetermined frequency.
But very importantly,
you must ensure
that the overall operations
is sustainable on all three pillars.
That is economically,
socially and environmentally,
which is termed the Triple Bottom Line.
Now the sustainable
business model canvas tools
that we'll be discussing
in the next two to three videos
represents all these issues
around your business model
in a single page.
The Sustainable
Business Model Canvas we present
is a slight variation
of the original business model canvas
developed
by Alexander Osterwalder
and Yves Pigneur
in Lausanne, Switzerland.
The canvas tools is made out
of several boxes
that are all interconnected
in some way.
The main difference between
this version and the original one
is that we also treat
the aspects of social impact
and sustainability.
Whereas, the original version
confines itself primarily
to economic issues.
It may look complex but in fact
it's a great tool to help you answer
the key questions we evoked before.
This tool is really intended
to be used as a team
involving your colleagues
and ideally
some of your key stakeholders
as well
around good food and drinks.
But be prepared for lively
and passionate discussions though.
The exercise itself involves using
post-it sticky notes to represent
the answers to the questions posed
during the exercise.
The canvas itself can be split
into three broad categories.
The first part represents
the overall mission
of your enterprise.
While the second category is
about the activities
or operations of your enterprise.
And the third category is about
performance metrics of your activities.
The purpose of each individual box
is to enable to ask questions,
organize the answers
and see how they influence
each other as we will see.
The overall mission
of your enterprise
should be well defined by now, using
the Impact Framework tools
that we previously introduced
earlier in the course.
So by defining what social impact
you wish to achieve,
or which sustainable development goal
you wish to target
with your technology.
This will help you also define
who will benefit
from your technology
But knowing
who your beneficiaries are
is only a starting point.
One of the first questions
to ask yourself is:
Of all the needs
your beneficiaries may have
which ones
are you actually addressing?
At this level
it is also important to reflect
what your real priorities are
for your enterprise activity.
Is it impact first-and-above profit?
If so, that may mean
you may be prepared
to give up higher profits
in order to achieve more impact.
Coming back to profit,
before we said that profit
was necessary, in general,
to ensure
long-term viability.
But remember profit can be used
in various ways.
In the most common case,
profit is a self-serving benefit,
if you like,
where the excess revenues received,
may be appropriated
to a few shareholders
of the enterprise.
Alternatively,
all the profit can simply be
reinvested into the enterprise.
And in this case
be regarded as an engine
for growing
the scale of the impact.
This is usually the case for a lot
of not-for-profit foundations,
for example.
So this part of the canvas
allows for you to consider
and factor in these issues here.
Later on we'll also discuss
the issue of trying to strike
a balance between the financial,
environmental and social aspects
when doing a cost/benefit analysis
for the enterprise.
So to summarize,
thus far we emphasize once more
the importance
of correctly understanding
who your beneficiaries are,
their needs
and which ones you are aiming for.
And making sure in the process
not to confuse the beneficiary
and the customers as always being
the same entity.
For example,
the beneficiaries can be
all those patientes
who are resistant
to antibiotics,
who may stand to benefit
from your new pharmaceutical product
that is effective
with all bacteria.
In this case, you will generally
never sell to the actual beneficiary,
which is the patient, directly.
But your customers
are rather the wholesalers
and distributors,
state health departments
or health insurance companies,
who accept to pay for your product
when prescribed.
And finally,
we would like to remind you also
that enterprise values and mission
are very important aspects
for you to define early.
They will help you determine
what is priority
for your enterprise,
between impact and profit,
which may have consequences
on how you define
what profit levels
are acceptable for you
from enterprise operations,
for example.
We will explore this aspect again
later on.
Goodbye.