In the previous lecture,
we developed and discussed
the key building block
of your business model,
namely, the customer, who is the king
of your business model.
We also discussed about the promise
you pledge to the customer
to solve a problem, or satisfy
a need they have,
which is conveyed via your
value proposition.
In this lecture, we will
examine things
from the enterprise or company
perspective.
In other words,
we will examine all the key
building blocks
that go into the process that
allows the enterprise
to generate a value promised
to the customer.
These can be classified broadly
speaking into 3 categories.
Key Activities,
Key Resources,
and Key Partnerships.
Now if we look at the overall canvas
we will see that we are
discussing primarily
the left middle part,
labelled Operations.
Which basically pertains to your
company or enterprise
and it's operations.
One of the first aspects
you have to confront
is what are the most
essential tasks, or key activities
that the company
has to carry out themselves
towards generating the proposed value.
Depending on the type of product
you are involved with.
Key activities for example could
entail product development
and production, if you are dealing
with a physical technology product.
Or software development if your
product is software based.
The other issue you
then have to confront
is what are the key resources
or the most critical assets
required for you to succeed
with your key activities
and proposed value generation.
For example, for a technology
based product
you will likely require
human expertise,
as technology based products
are generally knowledge intensive.
Intellectual property,
patents, copyrights, etc.
And perhaps a manufacturing facility.
Of course, in order to realize
your operations you will always need
various strategic or
key partnerships.
Key partners could be
your suppliers,
sub contractors,
e.g for contract manufacturing.
But remember you don't have
to do everything.
Certain things may best
be sub contracted
and you may wish to keep only
what is core
and most critical or sensitive
within the company.
Such an approach may allow you
to scale up cost effectively
and efficiently.
So, be sure to assess that very carefully
when defining your key activity
to determine which activity really
has to be done within the company.
And which ones can be outsourced
to key partners,
who may already be highly experienced
and running cost effectively
than you ever would for
the given activity.
Now the bottom left part
of the canvas
is concerned with cost structure.
This essentially refers to all the cost
incurred in all of the operations
to generate your proposed
value and delivering it
to the customer.
There are various types
of cost structures,
but for simplicity, we'll limit our
discussion to 2 basic categories.
That is, cost-driven, and
value-driven cost structures.
Cost-driven cost structures entail
minimizing costs
as much as possible, enabling
to pass on those savings as
a value proposition
to the customer.
Ostewalder and Pigneur, in their book, give
examples of No Frills Airlines
such as Easy Jet,
and Ryan Air
in Europe, for example.
Whereas value-driven cost
structure on the other hand
position themselves as
premium luxury
brands,
that can sometimes be laden with
all sorts of bells and whistles.
And here, think of a Rolls Royce
car, for example.
But it turns out that
in reality,
most cost structures fall
somewhere in the middle
of these 2 extremes.
Now in the
traditional canvas,
the cost structure is limited
only to financial costs.
However, in reality,
operations may also
likely engender a cost
to the environment.
Either by way of excessive emissions,
which may not necessarily
be intended, of course.
It could also happen that your
operations may have
unintended social
consequences as well,
or social costs in the communities
where they operate.
Therefore, given that you aim to
achieve not just only financial viability,
but also environmental
sustainability
and social impact,
it is very important that you are
able to establish metrics
that can enable you to monitor
and even quantify
environmental and social costs.
Hence, the original canvas
has been updated to also reflect
costs coming from
environmental and social factors.
Now the currency you use
for financial aspects
is revenue streams,
as measured in your
particular currency such as dollars,
or euros, or what have you.
While the currency for
environmental and social factor
is Key Performance
Indicator scores,
or KPI scores.
Key performance indicators can be
basically grouped into 4 categories,
namely,
Emissions to air,
e.g green house gasses.
Emissions to water.
e.g heavy metal emissions.
Emissions to land.
e.g pesticides.
Radioactive waste,
and intensive usage of naturally
occurring resources.
e.g water, oil, forestry, etc.
Just as much as you wish to
minimise your total financial costs
and maximise your total
revenue streams,
when assessing your cost benefit
ratio for each product,
you should also strive to make sure
that your environmental and social costs
do not out-weigh your environmental
and social KPI scores
respectively.
The extent to which you wish
to tip the cost benefit scale
one way or the other
will be largely influenced by
the mission and strategy
you set yourself
at the beginning,
which is reflected at the top
left hand corner
of this adapted canvas.
We have now gone through the whole
sustainable business model canvas.
In this last part, we have seen how
the company can create the value proposition
that it will deliver
to it's customers.
We have discussed, in particular,
the idea of what key resources
and key activities
should be part of your core business
and a key to creating this value.
And which ones can be sub-contracted
or outsourced
to external partners.
Finally, we have seen that
similarly to benefits,
which must be measured not
only at the financial level,
but also at the environmental
and social levels,
that is the costs linked to
your company's activities
must be evaluated on all these 3 levels.
The bottom line of this
sustainable business canvas,
as opposed to more traditional
business model,
is that in order to be
truly sustainable
your business must be balanced
not only
at the financial level,
but also regarding it's
environmental and social aspects.
In order to achieve this, you will
have to make some trade offs.
And deciding which ones are acceptable
for you will be determined
by your own values and mission.
The next lecture will illustrate
this tool by way of an example
using our X-ray imaging
system example.
Goodbye.