Hello, in the previous video,
we saw how to set the objectives
of our enterprise in terms
of the impact we want
to achieve and the target
beneficiaries we want to help.
Now, let us dig a little deeper
and see how our enterprise must
be set up to reach these
beneficiaries and achieve impact.
In many business sectors
the person who buys a product will
directly use it and benefit from it.
However, in other sectors there
is a difference between the people
who will benefit from our technology
and the people who will actually
make the decision to buy it.
As we think about how we can fill
the unmet need of the beneficiaries
we are trying to help, we need to
find out who will pay
for the technology.
We need to find a customer or buyer.
For example, a local hospital may
need to acquire a new medical
equipment and yet we may find out
that it is the ministry of health
which will purchase it.
In that case, the government is
our customer and our beneficiaries
would be the patients who
get a better treatment.
We must clearly understand how
and by whom the purchase decision
is made.
Another very important aspect is
what is called the job to be done.
The exact motives why a buyer would
want to buy our technology, may be
different from the pure wish to
fulfill the unmet needs of
a beneficiary.
For example, let's assume
the hospital in our previous example
is privately owned and that it wants
to acquire the medical equipment
to propose it to wealthy patients.
The purchase decision will then
largely be influenced by
the potential of this new
equipment to generate profit
for the hospitals owners.
In this example, the benefit for
the patient would not be the only
reason why the hospital makes
a decision to buy the equipment
the hospital's job to be done would
then simply be to generate cash.
If we want to assure that our
technology will be made available
we must clearly understand
the exact motivations of our buyer.
What are his or hers pain points?
Can we help solve them with
our proposed technology?
Are there any potential gains that
we can help our customer achieve.
Of course when the beneficiary is
directly the buyer, we also need to
clearly understand
his job to be done.
And this may differ significantly
form what we had in mind.
Once we start looking into
who can be our customer
we generally quickly realize that
there may be different customer
groups sometimes totally
unrelated to each others.
These groups are called
customer segments.
Each segment maybe interested
in a different effect that our
technology will have on
their own activities.
Each segment may just have
a different job to be done
as we have seen with our public
and private hospital example.
It is very important to identify all
our potential customer segments.
Some may be beneficiaries directly
as we have seen, others may be
organizations located
in our pilot country
still others may even be customers
located in rich countries using our
technology for a completely
different purpose.
identifying them all allows to
determine the best strategy
to maximize our impact.
Indeed playing with different
segments can offer some
very interesting opportunities to
increase our reach in
low income countries.
let me briefly explain
this mechanism.
Let us assume that we decide to
sell a fraction of our products for
a higher price and margin
in rich countries.
This additional margin could then
be used to balance our deployment
in poorer areas, where could then
accept to have a smaller profit
margin and lower prices.
Along the same lines, increasing
our customer base will have as
a consequence to increase
our production volumes.
Larger volumes will offer a chance
to negotiate better pricing from our
suppliers, which in turn will
make us more competitive
and thus be able to offer
reduced prices for the poor.
After we have identified all
the possible customer segments
we will most certainly
have to make a choice
of which segment we want to serve
and which ones we choose to ignore.
This is a strategic decision that
the team has to make and which
depends on many factors.
The danger here is that
we need to be careful
not to spread ourselves too thin
by wanting to pursue too many
segments at the same time.
Once we know our customer
segments as well as their specific
needs we can determine how our
product could be able
to fulfill these needs
in other words, we can determine
what is the value that our products
can bring to our customer.
This is what the "value propositions
block" is about in the canvas.
Each customer segment would
typically require a different
value proposition.
This does not imply that our
technology is different though.
But the offering can be different.
In other words, and I'm citing
Osterwalder and Pigneur:
"Each value proposition consists of
selected bundle of products and
or services that cater to
the requirements of
a specific customer segment."
The value created for the customer
can be quantitative such as price
or speed of service, or qualitative,
such as enhanced user experience.
As an example, let's assume we
intend to develop a medical
device for patients in low
income countries.
For a local hospital the job to
be done would be to be able
to continue providing patient care
in spite of power cuts and with
a lack of trained personnel.
In this case, the value proposition
could be the combination of
a robust device able to work on
battery and a training workshop
offered to key hospital personnel.
The same technology could also be
proposed in industrialized countries
To work for example as
an electrically autonomous
medical system in ambulances.
In this second case the ambulance
personnel needs a rugged device
that can be taken out of
the ambulance to be
applied to the patient
on the accident's site.
In this case, the value proposition
could be the same technology
without the training, but with
and adapter that allows the device
to be easily and solidly
attached to the ambulance.
Now, having a match between what we
are offering and what our customer
wants is not quite sufficient.
We will still need our customer to
be aware of the existence
of our product offering
and also to be able to
purchase it and receive it.
This is broadly speaking the role
of distribution channels.
As you may recall from our product
value chain video, this is not only
about deciding how to transport
the product, but also and even more
importantly about defining if
there will be intermediaries in
the distribution process.
Will we directly sell the product
to the customer, or will we sell it
to a re-seller who will then provide
the product to the customer
there are, for example, wholesalers
who will buy a large quantity of
goods and then sell them to
retailers, who finally sell
to individual customers.
Some international companies have
been successful in deploying their
products in low-income countries
because they decided to sell through
small village groceries.
This is a very important question
as independent intermediaries
may give us access to a wide local
customer base, which is
great as we strive to scale up.
But they will also keep
a margin on the product sale.
Alternatively, would we rather want
to have our own local subsidiaries
close to the customer which will
increase our operation's costs
and complexity, but offer
the advantage of a more
direct contact with our customers?
Getting the product to our customer
can be a challenge and needs to be
carefully thought out.
There are multiple innovative
techniques which are being
used by companies such as direct
sales through the internet or
mobile phones.
This of course works
well for software.
When tangible goods are sold,
it will of course always involve
transporting them to the customer.
As we have seen in the product
value chain video, setting up such
a channel can be a challenge
typically for delivery
to remote areas.
However, it can also be
a matter of innovation, per say
and become a part of
our value proposition
if we manage to develop our
own efficient distribution channel.
Once the product has been delivered,
we also have to think about how
the after-sale relationships,
such as repairs, customer questions
and complaints will be handled.
This brings us to the next block.
The canvas allows to raise another
important question, which is
the relationship that the company
needs to have with it's customers.
Here we have to reflect how we want
to acquire customers, what strategy
we have to retain them and also
how we can work together with
customers to improve our technology
and increase our reach.
These customer relationships
are extremely important
since they allow to measure and
improve customer satisfaction
which can mean great success
or rapid failure of our company.
As you can see in the canvas,
the box is actually bi-directional
which really underscores
the importance of the mutual
interaction between the company
and it's customers.
We need to find out how to learn
from the customer as well as even
co-develop solutions.
Customer relationships need to be
taken very seriously and nurtured.
I'm insisting on this aspect,
because it is a frequent cause
of failure in business in general.
Finally, we need to make sure that
our company will be sustainable
on a financial, environmental
and social level.
The revenue streams box basically
asks what our customer will pay for
how much they will pay and when.
Will they have to pay
a recurring annual fee?
Will they pay for your product
itself or for the right to use it?
For example, if our company
wants to provide a water purifier
to small water kiosks in rural
villages, will we sell the machines?
We could also propose to
lend or lease them. In that case
the local owner of the water kiosk
will sell the water and pay for
the rent of the machine with
a part of his revenues from sales.
In that example, our company would
also provide maintenance and repair
as a part of the value proposition.
Generally there are two different
types of revenue streams.
Transaction revenues from a one-time
sale, or recurring revenues from
ongoing payments, such
as the water kiosk example.
The environmental, and social
benefit must also be assessed
with the same rigor.
We need to clearly identify how
our technology will benefit to
the environment and to the social
issue we want to solve.
For this, we can go back to
the analysis performed with
our impact canvas tool.
Measuring financial revenue
streams is quite straight forward.
However, we also need to define
one or two metrics which we call
key performance indicators,
or KPIs for our environmental
and social returns.
For example, it is not sufficient to
claim that our technology will
reduce CO2 emissions or that it
will improve cardiovascular health.
We need to have metrics to
quantify this claim, like
the number of tons of CO2 that won't
be emitted, or the percentage
improvement in mortality
caused by cardiovascular problems.
As we have said in the past videos
it might be very hard to
clearly measure impact.
We can just decide
to measure outcomes
as a proxy for impact
if that is easier.
But we need to be cognizant
that this is a simplification
and could lead us to
misinterpretations.
As a summary this part of
the sustainable business
model canvas is focused
on the customer.
We need to remember,
that if we want our customer
To be interested in buying
our products, there must
be a good fit between our customer's
"job to be done", and our
value proposition.
The key to achieving such
a good match is to understand
exactly who our customers are,
their pains as well
as their potential gains.
Once we understand this we can
determine what it is, in and around
our product, which is of
most interest to them.
We need to remember also that
different customer segments
will have different
"jobs to be done"
and will thus be interested in
different aspects of our product.
This will lead us to specific value
propositions for each of our
customer segments.
Finally of course, earning
money is important.
If only to assure that our
enterprise will be durably
active and capable to grow.
However, we also
regularly need to assure
that we are really and effectively
reaching the social and
environmental goals that we have
set to ourselves in the beginning.
We need to check if our
beneficiaries really benefit
from our initiative.
We need to keep in mind that
we have a triple bottom line
where the focus must
be on all three criteria.
In the next video we will see that
this triple bottom line obviously
also has a counterpart as
costs in financial, environmental
and social terms.
Goodbye.