Hello. As with the previous tools
presented in this MOOC,
we will now see how the sustainable
business model canvas
applies to our example of a
diagnostic x-ray system.
Of course. For the sake of
simplicity
we can only address things partially
in this video,
and we can't explain the complete
business model in such a short time.
In this sense, and although
the project is a real one,
and the company has effectively
been created,
this should only be considered
as a simplified example
inspired from the real case.
Our goal is to give
you a feel
of how this tool is applied
in practice.
As we have seen, when applying
the impact canvas to this example,
out impact target is to reduce
the mortality,
and morbidity, resulting from trauma
or from pulmonary diseases.
The beneficiaries of this technology
are of course, the patients
themselves,
since a pertinent diagnosis
would allow them to receive
a more adequate treatment,
and not suffer
from complications.
As for the fundamental need
addressed, in this case,
it is access to quality health care,
and in particular, to adequate
x-ray diagnosis.
Let us now get back to the canvas.
You can see the targeted impact
and beneficiary needs
pasted on the canvas
as sticky notes
with keywords only.
This is really the way to use
this canvas.
Print it as a poster,
hang it on the wall,
and start adding sticky notes
as ideas shoot up
from you and your colleagues.
One of the first questions
you need to ask yourselves
is, what is your company's mission?
and what are the common values
shared by you and you team mates?
Here, the mission of
the company
is to provide robust and
affordable medical devices
for the global market, and
especially for emerging
and developing countries.
Note that this mission statement
implies that the company may
sell other devices,
not just x-ray systems.
Values are very personal
and yet some of them must be
shared within your team.
This will for example lead to
an agreement
on how the company's profit
should be used.
Here the team decided that
part of the profit
would be constantly reinvested
in pursuit of the company mission.
The team also agreed on
the type of investors
they would like to partner with,
which are impact investors.
Finally, the team also agreed that
they did not want
a short term sale
of the company, or exit.,
at least not before
break-even was reached.
A first customer segment for
this machine is
the Ministry of Health
of the targeted country,
which is Cameroon.
The Ministry of Health is in charge
of the public hospitals,
and it's job-to-be-done
is to provide the population with
access to health care
including diagnostic capabilities.
However, it has very
limited budgets.
Both for equipment,
and for training.
And virtually no budget for
maintenance of medical devices.
The hospitals run by the Ministry,
must also often deal with
poor infrastructure,
such as dysfunctional
electrical power grids.
These are what we call the "pains"
of the customer segment.
Another customer segment is local
or international NGOs.
Some of them are supporting one,
or several hospitals from abroad.
Some are locally based and manage
complete hospital chains
with donor support from
industrialised countries.
An NGO located in
an industrial country
may decide to purchase a batch
of x-ray systems
to be then commissioned in several
hospitals,
even if that NGO
has no real presence
in the country.
This customer segment
has specific concerns.
It wants  to maximise the impact of
donor money.
It also needs to show clear metrics
of this impact,
on the health of beneficiaries.
International NGOs
have more flexibility
in resources allocation than
the Ministry of Health,
and their decision processes
are usually much shorter.
Yet another type of customers
who might be interested in buying
such an x-ray machine
are national and international
development aid agencies.
Like the SDC in Switzerland,
USAID  in the US,
the GIZ in Germany,
the JICA in Japan, or like
the African Development Bank.
The basic job-to-be-done
by these institutions
is to foster the development
of less developed countries,
and to strengthen international
cooperation.
They are concerned that the money
they put into projects,
has a long lasting positive
impact,
and that it empowers people
in the targeted countries.
Note that we are using different
colours for each customer segment.
This is important, because we know,
that each segment
will potentially have to be dealt
with in a different way,
as we build up the complete canvas.
For the sake of simplicity however,
we will only present the business
model for the first customer segment
in the rest of this example.
Now that we have seen which customer
segment we want to target,
let us see which aspect
of the x-ray machine
can be interesting to them.
We have seen that the hospitals
have limited budgets
to buy new equipment and usually
no budget for its maintenance.
We thus have to come up with
an attractive pricing proposition.
In general, x-ray systems
are sold together
with a maintenance contract which
can be very expensive,
and represents typically 10% of
the initial purchase price
to be paid each and every year
to the manufacturer.
Also, there is the cost
of the consumables
such as films and chemicals.
If the customer wants to reduce
the total cost of ownership,
it means to reduce the sum
of all these costs.
Since our concept is digital,
the costs of films and chemicals
are spared,
which reduces the total cost
of ownership.
Also, since it has been redesigned
for the local context,
and it is very robust,
maintenance and repair costs
will also be reduced.
Our value proposition is thus
a reduced
total cost of ownership or TCO.
The second element is an inherent
robustness of the design
including features such as
a power supply
which resists the local
electrical instability
and a battery to allow
continuous work
in case of a black-out
for up to an hour.
This robustness reduces the frequent
downtimes
experienced with other systems,
not designed for this context.
Now as we claimed that our
technology is more robust,
and also to address the lack
of maintenance budgets,
we introduce an extended warranty.
In other words, an additional aspect
of the value proposition
is to include the maintenance fees
in the selling price of the device.
The Ministry will pay only once
to acquire the machine
and then maintenance and repairs
will be provided free of charge
by the company for up to 6 years.
The last crucial element
of the value proposition
is the fact that
the system is digital
which enables the possibility
to transfer images
through the internet when available
or via the cell phone network.
This feature offers the possibility
to transfer images
to a remotely located specialist
for a second opinion in case
of doubts on a diagnosis.
This is called tele-medicine,
or in this case, tele-radiology,
and it is particularly interesting
for hospitals
located in remote rural areas.
By definition,
local hospitals are located
directly in our target country
or countries, possibly
in remote areas.
Unless the government buys
a batch of machines centrally,
and takes care of dispatching them
in the country,
which is usually no the case,
we must manage to deliver the x-ray
machine ourselves.
As we have seen in
the product value chain,
the distribution channel can be
either a direct sale
from the company to the customer,
or the product can be sold
though an intermediary.
This intermediary, can be
an independent partner
or a subsidiary of our own company.
In our case, we decided
to create
a local subsidiary,
through which we will sell directly
to the Ministry of Health.
This has the advantage of keeping
a tighter control
over the activities, especially with
regards to maintenance and repairs.
We decide to accept the challenge
of running a local subsidiary
because we already have a strong
local network.
And we have identified
a local expert
who we want to put in charge of our
operations in Cameroon.
He will be responsible for the sales
to the government,
as well as for the commissioning
of the equipment,
the training of the users, and
the maintenance activities.
As we have seen, maintenance
activities are very important here.
Since we have decided to provide
an extended warranty for the device
in our value proposition.
Our company must thus
remain very close
to its customers.
Such a local subsidiary
represents also an obvious advantage
in terms of customer relationships.
A local subsidiary will
be able to establish
closer relationships with
radiologists
and government representatives
in the country.
It's employees can travel more
easily inside the country,
even to remote areas
to provide rapid
local customer service.
They are also likely to share
a common culture
and language with the customers.
A local subsidiary is in
a good position
to relay country specific issues
that the main company will not
be aware of from a distant country.
All this helps to keep customers,
and acquire new ones.
But the next step in acquiring
the first customers
is to involve them into
the creation process
as we have seen.
This co-creation of the device
with local practitioners
with relevant experience
has 2 effects:
On the one hand it ensures
that the device is truly fit for
its purpose and context of use,
on the other hand, it ensures
the adhesion of the local
practitioners to the product,
which counts a lot because they may
be the future customers themselves,
or at least be in contact
with customers.
Typical business models in
the medical technology sector
comprise 3 sources of revenues.
One, the sale of the medical
device itself,
which is a one-off sale.
Two, the regular sale of consumables
such as reagents
or probes, which is called
recurring sales.
And finally the sale of services
such as installing software upgrades,
performing regular maintenance,
or calibration.
Such a recurring sales model can
be very profitable for the company,
but it leads to a high total cost
of ownership for the customer.
And it does not fit well with how
health care budgets are planned
by governments in many
low-income countries.
Our revenue stream will thus
be made solely
from the sale of the device
which will include 6 years
of warrranty
as we had said before.
As far as environmental benefits,
there are 2 of them.
First, as already mentioned, the
fact that we use digital
rather than analog radiology,
eliminates the need for chemicals
which would end-up being thrown
into the environment.
One performance indicator
in this regard
would be the amount
of chemicals saved
with each radiology done
by the machine.
Another point is the innovative and
long-lasting power source
built in the machine,
which does not rely on
lead acid batteries.
Such batteries are very polluting
and must be replaced frequently.
Here, the number of lead acid
batteries avoided
can be used as a metric.
Finally, the social benefits brought
by each machine
is actually the very impact that
was originally targeted.
As discussed earlier in this MOOC,
it is difficult to disentangle
the impact coming solely
from our initiative, from other
simultaneous initiatives.
For example, improvement in
road safety laws,
could also contribute to a reduced
morbidity and mortality
due to road traffic accidents.
To solve this problem, and even if
we know this is not perfect,
we can use proxy metrics
for access to radiology instead.
Such as the number
of working machines,
or the number of radiographies
performed.
Now that we have seen the customer
side of the business model,
let us turn to the company side.
This will help us understand
what it will take
to provide the value to the customer
and the beneficiary.
The system will be designed
or engineered in our company.
Engineering will also include
keeping the technology up to date,
with regards to obsolescent components
and technology evolution,
as well as certified
according to standards.
It will then be marketed before
being shipped
as separate modules to the local
subsidiary in Cameroon.
There, it will be assembled into
the complete x-ray system,
tested, and delivered
to the hospital.
Our local subsidiary, will
also be responsible
for commissioning the device
at the hospital.
And for providing training to
the different types of users.
We have seen that
the proposed product
includes 6 years of maintenance.
So this will also be a key activity
of the company
through its local subsidiary.
These are actually a lot of
different activities
and in order to perform them all,
several resources will be necessary.
Let's look into that.
The first key resources we will need
are of course humans.
We will mainly need engineers,
technicians, and administrative personnel,
as well as, a strong sales force
especially in the local subsidiary.
We will not need to
build a real factory
since we will not manufacture
the devices in-house
as we will see.
However, we will need a facility for
the storage of product parts
in Cameroon.
The same facility will be used
for the final assembly,
as well as for repairs that will
eventually have to be performed.
Lastly, some key resources
of the company,
will be its intellectual property
such as patents,
and its in depth knowledge
of the country's context.
These intangible key resources
have been acquired
during the concept and feasibility
phases of our project.
As well as, through the network
of stakeholders
that have been involved.
We have already reviewed all
the key stakeholders involved
when we explained the product value
chain canvas
which is the best tool to
identify them.
We now see which ones we need
to closely partner with.
Since we have decided not to manufacture
the x-ray systems ourselves,
as it will be too costly to setup
a complete manufacturing plant,
we need to find what is called
a contract manufacturer.
This partner will manufacture
the system's modules
such as the power supply
and the detector,
in compliance with the required
regulatory constraints.
Once all the sub-assemblies
are available,
they need to be transported
to Cameroon
to be assembled into
a final product.
This means we need to partner with
a freight forwarding company.
We also saw that training
was extremely important for
this customer segment,
and this is why we have to
partner
with the professional association
of radiographers
as well as with the faculty
of medicine
of the University in Cameroon
to develop adequate training
for radiography.
Up until now, we have identified
all it takes
to provide value
to our customer
and fulfill our beneficiarie's
unmet needs.
Now comes the itchy part.
The financial, environmental,
and social costs involved.
In order to get our company
to be productive,
we must plan on paying
the salaries of our employees.
We must also plan on the costs
of manufacturing,
and shipping the goods,
and we have to pay rent for
our warehouse in Cameroon.
Environmental costs
in our case,
would include the CO2
emissions generated
due to shipping the parts overseas.
At this stage, we might
suddenly remember that
there are some toxic components
in the system itself,
such as the oil used
in the high-voltage transformer.
That is a typical example in which
we no have to go back
and think about what would be needed
to recycle the transformer.
This could for example lead us to plan
on some additional financial resources
to take care of decommissioning.
Finally, in terms of social costs,
making x-ray diagnostic available
to as many people as possible
should not come with
a lot of downsides.
We should however make sure
that people do not abuse
the machine, and maintain
a reasonable level of exposure
to x-rays.
Indeed, the digital imaging sensor
makes it very easy
and quick to retake an image
if something was not absolutely
perfect the first time.
This could lead to over exposure.
This problem should be mitigated
through adequate training.
The very last step is now
to see if our canvas
is balanced or not.
Of course, this would require
that we go a bit further
and start to plug numbers
into the triple bottom line.
For example, we would
need to know precisely
how many x-ray system we could sell
and at what price?
Then we will have to calculate all
the costs on the left hand side
of the canvas such as salaries,
cost of manufacturing,
shipping and so forth.
For the social and environmental
lines as well,
we would need to find clear numbers
to better characterise the impact.
With these figures, we would then
be able to verify
if the costs are really outbalanced
by the benefits.
In conclusion, I would like
to state that
this canvas should be seen
as a framework
to tell a story.
As you have seen, we have constructed
it in a particular sequence
which kind of tells the story
of our business model.
We can use this as
a mental guide
when we have to pitch our model
to an investor.
We hope that with this example,
you will now have a better idea
of how to use this canvas with
your team.
It is a very powerful tool
as it triggers important team
discussions about the strategy.
Just like the other tools
presented in this MOOC,
it should be used regularly to
reassess the strategy
to make sure the model
is still valid
in spite of a rapidly
changing environment.
Our most important
advice though, is...
have fun using it!
Goodbye.