(Rich Johnston)
Welcome to the second week of this course!
Today we will talk about
drinking water safety.
But first, what does water safety mean?
In fact, what does safety mean at all?
Is it safe to swim in a lake?
To walk from your home to school?
Is it safe to eat
a plate of chicken curry?
Is it safe to fly in an airplane?
Well, none of these things actually,
in fact, nothing in life at all
is completely safe.
There is always some risk,
however small,
that something can go wrong,
and that while doing
any of these activities
your health can be harmed.
However once we acknowledge
that all activity has some risk,
the critical question becomes:
What level of risk is acceptable
and how can problems be identified
and controlled before they occur
to manage risks and keep them
on an acceptable level?
If you go on an airplane flight
you are assuming
that the plane won't crash.
And why do you think that?
Because there are guidelines
and regulations in place
to keep risks to acceptable levels.
The airplane pilots have to go
through rigorous training program
long before they can fly a real plane.
The aircraft itself
has to be regularly inspected
and preventive maintenance checks
must be performed routinely.
There are auditing systems
and inspections to make sure
that these safety measures
are applied correctly.
And once the safety measures
are all in place,
traveling by plane is very safe.
It's not ever 100% safe,
but on a major airline today the risk
of being involved in a fatal accident
is much-much less that one in a million.
And most people would consider that
to be a safe level of risk.
Well, the same concept
applies to drinking-water.
The World Health Organization
has a definition of safe drinking-water.
"Safe drinking-water is that
which does not represent
any significant risk to health
over a lifetime of consumption,
including different sensitivities
that may occur between life stages."
Now notice, the definition does not say:
"does not represent
any risk to health", it says:
any significant risk to health".
The WHO guidelines
for drinking-water quality
include recommended maximum levels,
or guideline values,
for 90 different chemicals.
And these guideline values
are normally set
to represent a tolerable level of risk,
which in the guidelines is taken as
one DALY per million person-years.
Do you remember DALYs,
disability-adjusted life years?
Well, this risk level means
that if a million people
drink water for a year
with the chemical at the guideline value
then the chemical
will cause health effects
with the disease burden of one DALY
over that population.
And chemicals that cause cancer
are treated in a similar way.
A lifetime of drinking-water
at the guideline value
should cause no more than
one excess cancer case per 100,000 people.
Now, this is not zero risk,
but it is considered a tolerable level.
Put it another way,
risks smaller than this
are considered not to be significant.
WHO guideline values of course
are not national standards,
and it is up to each state to determine
its own acceptable level of risk.
Now, health outcomes
for water quality guidelines
linked to health outcomes
are two examples of health-based targets,
which define an acceptable level of risk.
There are other kinds
of health-based targets,
such as performance targets,
which specify a certain level of removal
for a contaminant or a pathogen,
or specified technologies,
for example, saying that surface water
must always be filtered
before further treatment.
Let's look a bit more
at performance targets
since those will be important
in the context
of household water treatment.
The main example of a performance target
is a Log Reduction Value, or LRV.
This is the number of log units by which
a chemical or other contaminant
is reduced through treatment.
Now, you can easily calculate LRV
by taking the ratio of the contaminant
before and after treatment
and then taking the base 10 logarithm.
Now, if the concentration
is unchanged by the treatment
that means, there is no removal,
and the LRV is zero.
It's also possible for a contaminant
to increase during the treatment,
in which case the LRV is negative.
Hopefully that does not happen too much.
Now, if a hypothetical contaminant
was reduced from a million
to half a million counts,
and here it does not matter
what units are used
as long as they are consistent.
That would be an LRV of 0.3
since 0.3 is the logarithm of 2 roughly.
And if were reduced
to a 100 000, that's a 90% reduction,
that would be a 1 log reduction.
So you can see that if you talk about
reducing something a hundred-fold, by 99%,
that would be a 2 log reduction.
And to go from 1 000 000 of something
to a single unit
would be a 6 log reduction.
So performance targets can specify
the amount of log reduction values
that should be achieved
for a certain class of pathogens,
for example, a 3 log removal of bacteria
would mean removing 99.9% of bacteria.
At the target of 5 log removal
would be a 100 times more strict.
(Sara Marks)
To find the total effectiveness
of a multistage treatment system
you will calculate the LRV for each stage
as in a formula on the last side
and then simply add the LRVs together.
(Rich Johnston) So that's a quick
introduction into health base targets.
Health base targets are one part
of the water safety framework
describing the WHO Guidelines
for Drinking Water Quality.
In brief, the other main components
are System Assessment,
Operational Monitoring,
Management and Communication,
and these are then confirmed
by water quality testing, or Verification.
Idially the verification step is done
by an independent authority
and not by the service provider.
Information from the verification step
can then feedback
into setting of health-based targets
and acceptable levels of risks.
The three steps in the middle
are the actions
that can be done
by the water service provider
and taken together
they can constitute a Water Safety Plan
for a particular water supply system.
First, in order to prevent risks
we have to understand
all of the components
of a water supply system
from catchment to consumer
by examining each step
in the water supply chain.
Potential hazards can be identified
as places where something could go wrong
or where microbial contamination
could occur.
For each hazard a control measure
can then be put in place,
which defines the acceptable performance.
Once control measures are established
system operators should routinely monitor
that the control measures
are being applied.
And if anything goes wrong,
it is noticed quickly.
This might include testing for E. coli,
but it's more likely to include
very simple actions
like keeping pumping logs up to date,
checking turbidity levels
after filtration
or measuring residual chlorine,
as finished water leaves the plant.
Think of the airplane example.
You don't want the measure
of air flight safety to be:
"Hey, the plane did not crash,
it must have been safe."
You want the airline
to be routinely monitoring
all of those safety measures
that they have put in place.
Management plans mainly describe
the routine operations
that are done under normal conditions.
But it's also important
to know what to do
when a problem or incident occurs.
Incident response plans
should be developed
and should be well known by operators
so if there something bad happens,
the operators know exactly what to do
and unsafe water
is not delivered to consumers.
Good records should be kept
of both routine operations
and any incidents that occur.
And such information
should be shared with consumers,
and there should be channels
for consumers
to give feedback
to the system operators.
There is a lot more to be said
about Water Safety Plans.
In fact, it would be a good topic
for a full MOOC,
but for our purposes Water Safety Plans
are important as an example
of how water safety
can be conceptualized.
At a very simple level
the water safety framework
consists of health-based targets
to define an acceptable level of risk.
Some systems for identifying
and managing risks,
that's the Water Safety Plan Part,
and independent verification
that the risk management system
is in fact working.
In this framework there is a need
for measuring water quality,
but mainly as a verification measure.
Most of the work to ensure water safety
is in the system assessment
in the developing of control measures
and operational monitoring
to make sure they are being applied.
If you only do water quality measurements,
you can't be sure
that the drinking water is safe,
even if you don't find any E. coli.
People often make the mistake that
if they've checked the drinking water
for E. coli and did not find any
they assume that the water must be safe.
In fact, water without E. coli
could be unsafe for several reasons.
First, contamination
can be very variable in space,
if you collect your sample
at the wrong place,
you could miss the problem.
Second, contamination
can be very variable in time.
Maybe on the day
that you do your quality testing
there is no contamination,
but the day before
or even hour before there was,
and you were not testing then.
Finally, E. coli is not a perfect
faecal indicator
but it is the best one available.
It's possible that treatment
has killed all of the E. coli,
but some of the other pathogens,
for instance, cryptosporidium
or rotavirus are still viable.
So to say "drinking water is safe"
you need both things.
You need to show that the water
is free from contamination,
but also that there is a system in place
to proactively identify and prevent
contamination from occurring.
Water Safety Plans
are fairly new concept,
but they are taking off rapidly.
There are currently over 20 countries
that require water safety plans
and the regulations,
and many other countries
are in the process
of including them in future regulations.
Water safety plans are typically applied
for conventional treatment
and pipe supplies
at the level of the water supply scheme.
There are examples
of rural Water safety Plans,
including for point sources,
such as boreholes or protected springs.
But most of the experience today has been
with larger, professionally
managed pipe systems.
An important concept
from the system assessment step
of water safety planning
is that of multiple barriers.
Remember, the main source of pathogens
is faecal matter.
So multiple barriers can be put in place
to prevent faecal material
from entering the drinking water supply
and to remove the pathogens
that do make it in
using a variety
of different treatment processes.
Different pathogens
have different levels of resistance
to different kinds of treatment.
Also any single control measure
can fail at some point.
So by including multiple barriers
to remove pathogens
the risk of providing unsafe
drinking water can be minimized.
Conventional treatment of surface water
typically follows this
multiple barrier approach.
Before reaching the treatment plant
the water resource itself
can be protected.
For example, the use of fertilizers,
pesticides or other chemicals
may be restricted
within the catchment area of a river
or an aqua-fer
used for drinking water supply.
Within the treatment plant itself
a series of processes
are normally followed.
Some kind of pretreatment step
may be necessary
to reduce high levels of suspended solids
which could cause problems
for subsequent treatment steps.
Storage reservoirs allow
some sedimentation to take place
and roughing filters or bank infiltration
can remove many particles,
as well as improving
of the microbiological quality
to some degree.
Coagulation and flocculation
remove turbidity for suspended solids.
By addition of a coagulant salt,
typically aluminium sulphide
or ferric chloride,
which forms flocks that grow
removing suspended solids,
as well as some dissolved compounds.
These flocks can settle out of solution
in clarification tanks
or in some cases can float
to the top of the tank,
where they can be removed.
Filtration can then remove
any remaining flocks
or may be apply directly
without a coagulation step.
Depending on the filter material
filtration can be
an effective control measure
for some pathogens,
especially larger ones
like cryptosporidium.
Primary disinfection is an essential step
in most treatment systems.
To achieve the necessary levels
of pathogen reduction
and to provide a safety net
in case previous steps failed.
Chlorine is the most widely
applied disinfectant,
but chlorine dioxide,
ozone and ultraviolet light
are used in some cases.
Finally, after leaving
the treatment plant
water suppliers can prevent contamination
in the distribution system
by ensuring continuous pressure
so that contamination
can't enter the pipes
and by maintaining
a residual disinfectant,
if chlorine is used.
The same processes
that are applied
at conventional treatment plants
can also be adapted and
applied at the household level.
In fact, all of the household
water treatment systems
use some combination of sedimentation,
filtration and disinfection.
And they should be followed
by safe storage
to prevent the contamination.
In the next several videos we'll look
at examples of these processes
that are used in the main
household water treatment systems.
The main difference
between conventional treatment and HWTS
is not in the processes,
but in the point
where the processes are applied.
HWTS requires households
to take charge of their own water safety
by treating the water
at the household level
and preventing the contamination.
Τhis is quite a challenge
since most households residents
are not trained engineers
and don't necessarily even
have a modern concept of germ theory.
The concepts
of the water safety framework
can be applied for HWTS.
But implementing something
like a water safety plan
for household water treatment and storage
requires fundamental changes in behavior.
HWTS should not be seen
as an alternative or competitor
to conventional water supply.
And the long-term goal should be
to extend access
to safe drinking water supplies
at the household level
to everyone, everywhere.
HWTS can represent a short-term strategy
to approved drinking water quality
until that long-term goal can be reached.
So, in summary, we've heard today
about the Water Safety Framework
described in the WHO Guidelines
for Drinking Water Quality.
The Framework consists
of three main components:
Health-based targets,
Water Safety Plans
and Verification monitoring --
independent verification.
There are a lot of resources available
that describe water safety plans
in much more detail,
if you're interested in learning more.
We also learned about
one kind of health-based target --
Log Reduction Values, or LRV.
We'll come back to those
as we look at the different treatments
and processes used in HWTS.
And we learned
that the treatment processes
used in household water treatment
are the same that are applied
in conventional water treatment plans.
The key differences are
in the location of the treatment...