Welcome to the second week of this course.
Today we will talk about drinking water
safety.
Well first, what does water safety mean?
In fact, what does safety mean at all?
Is it safe to swim in a lake?
To walk from your home to school?
Is it safe to eat a plate of chicken
curry?
Is it safe to fly in an airplane?
Well none of these things actually.
In fact, nothing in life at all is
completely safe.
There's always some risk, however small,
that something can go wrong and
that while doing any of these activities
your health can be harmed.
However, once we acknowledge that all
activity has some risk,
the critical question becomes what level
of risk is acceptable,
and how can problems be identified and
controlled before they
occur to manage risks and keep them at an
acceptable level.
If you go on an airplane flight, you are
assuming
that the plane won't crash, and why do you
think that?
Because there are guidelines and
regulations in
place to keep risks to acceptable levels.
The airplane pilots have to go through a
rigorous
training program, long before they could
fly a real plane.
The aircraft itself has to be regularly
inspected,
and preventive maintenance checks must be
performed routinely.
There are auditing systems and inspections
to make
sure that these safety measures are
applied correctly.
And when the safety measures are all in
place, traveling by plane is very safe.
It's not ever 100% safe.
But, on a major airline today, the risk of
being involved in a fatal accident is
much, much
less than one in a million, and most
people
would consider that to be a safe level of
risk.
Well, the same concept applies to drinking
water.
The World Health Organization has a
definition of safe drinking water.
Safe drinking water is that which does not
represent any significant risk to health
over a lifetime of consumption, including
different
sensitivities that may occur between life
stages.
Now notice the definition doesn't say,
does not represent any risk to health.
It says doesn't represent any significant
risk to health.
The WHO guidelines for drinking water
quality include recommended
maximum levels or guideline values for 90
different chemicals.
And these guideline values are normally
set to represent a tolerable level of
risk, which in the guidelines, is taken as
one DALY per million-person years.
Remember DALYs?
Disability Adjusted Life Years.
Well, this risk level means that if a
million
people drink water for a year with the
chemical at
the guideline value, then the chemical
will cause health effects
with a disease burden of one DALY over
that population.
And chemicals that cause cancer are
treated in a similar way.
A lifetime of drinking water at the
guideline value should
cause no more than one excess cancer case
per 100,000 people.
Now this is not zero risk, but it is
considered a tolerable level.
Put another way, risks smaller than this
are considered not to be significant.
WHO guideline values of course, are not
national standards and it is
up to each state to determine its own
acceptable level of risk.
Now health outcomes or water quality
guidelines linked to health outcomes are
two examples of health-based targets,
which define an acceptable level of risk.
There are other kinds of health-based
targets such as performance targets
which specify a certain level of removal
for contaminant or a pathogen.
Or specified technologies.
For example saying that, surface water
must always be filtered before further
treatment.
Let's look a bit more at performance
targets, since those
will be important in the context of
household water treatment.
The main example of a performance target
is the Log Reduction Value or LRV.
This is the number of log units by which
a chemical or other containment is reduced
through treatment.
Now you can easily calculate the LRV by
taking the ratio of
the containment before and after treatment
and then taking the base ten logarithm.
Now, if the concentration is unchanged by
the treatment,
that means there's no removal and the LRV
is zero.
It's also possible for a contaminant to
increase
during treatment, in which case the LRV is
negative.
Hopefully that doesn't happen too much.
Now if a hypothetical contaminant was
reduced from a million to half a million
counts, and here it doesn't matter what
units are used as long as they're
consistent.
That would be an LRV of 0.3, since 0.3 is
the logarithm of two, roughly.
And if it were reduced to 100,000, that is
a
90 percent reduction, that would be a log,
one log reduction.
So you can see that if we talk about
reducing something
a hundred fold by 99%, that would be a two
log reduction.
And to go from one million of something to
a single unit would be a six log
reduction.
So, performance targets can specify the
amount of log reduction
values that should be achieved for a
certain class of pathogens.
For example, a three log removal of
bacteria would mean removing 99.9% of
bacteria.
And a target of five log removal would be
a hundred times more strict.
So that's a quick introduction to
health-based targets.
Health-based targets are one part of the
water safety
framework described in the WHO Guidelines
for drinking water quality.
In brief, the other main components
are system assessment, operational
monitoring, management
and communication and these are then
confirmed by water quality testing for
verification.
Ideally the verification step is done by
an
independent authority and not by the
service provider.
Information from the verification step,
and then feedback into
setting of health-based targets and
acceptable levels of risks.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
The three steps in the middle are the
actions
that can be done by the water service
provider.
And taken together, they can constitute a
water
safety plan for a particular water supply
system.
First, in order to prevent risks, we have
to understand all
the components of a water supply system,
from catchment to consumer.
By examining each step in the water supply
chain, potential hazards can be
identified as places where something could
go
wrong, or where microbial contamination
could occur.
For each hazard, a control measure can
then
be put in place, which defines acceptable
performance.
Once control measures are established,
system operators should
routinely monitor that the control
measures are being applied.
And if anything goes wrong it is noticed
quickly.
This might include testing for e-coli, but
it's more
likely to include very simple actions,
like keeping pumping
logs up to date, checking turbidity levels
after filtration
or measuring residual chlorine as finished
water leaves the plant.
Think of the airplane example.
You don't want your measure of air flight
safety to
be, hey the plain didn't crash, it must
have been safe.
You want the airline to be routinely
monitoring all
of those safety measures that they have
put in place.
Management plans mainly describe the
routine
operations that are done under normal
conditions.
But it's also important to know what to do
when a problem or incident occurs.
Incidence response plans should be
developed
and should be well known by operators
so that if something bad happens the
operators know exactly what to do.
And unsafe water is not delivered to
consumers.
Good records should be kept of both
routine operations and any instance that
occur.
And such information should be shared with
consumers and there should
be channels for consumers to give feedback
to the system operators.
There's a lot more to be said about water
safety plans.
In fact it would be a good topic for a
full MOOC.
But for our purposes, water safety plans
are important
as an example of how water safety can be
conceptualized.
At a very simple level, the water safety
framework consists
of health-based targets to define an
acceptable level of risk.
Some system for identifying and managing
risks, that's the water safety plan part,
and independent verification that the risk
management system is, in fact, working.
In this framework, there is a need for
measuring water quality, but mainly as a
verification measure.
Most of the work to ensure water safety,
is in the system assessment in
the developing of control measures, and
the
operational monitoring to make sure
they're being applied.
If you only do water quality measurements,
you can't be sure that
the drinking water is safe, even if you
don't find any E.coli.
People often make the mistake that if
they've checked drinking water for
E.coli, and didn't find any, they assume
that the water must be safe.
In fact, water without E.coli could be
unsafe for several reasons.
First, contamination can be very variable
in space.
If you collect your sample at the wrong
place, you could miss the problem.
Second, contamination can be very variable
in time.
Maybe on the day that you do
your water quality testing, there is no
contamination,
but the day before, or even the hour
before, there was, and you weren't testing
them.
Finally, E.coli is not a perfect fecal
indicator, though it is the best one
available.
It is possible that treatment has killed
all of the E.coli,
but some other pathogens, for instance
cryptosporidium or rotavirus, are still
viable.
So to say drinking water is safe, you need
both things.
You need to show that the water is free
from contamination, but also that
there is a system in place to
proactively identify and prevent
contamination from occurring.
Water safety plans are a fairly new
concept, but they're taking off rapidly.
There are currently over 20 countries that
require water safety plans in their
regulations.
And many other countries are in the
process of including them in future
regulations.
Water safety plans are typically applied
for conventional treatment and
pipe supplies at the level of the water
supply scheme.
There are examples of rural water safety
plans, including
for point sources, such as bore holes or
protected springs.
But most of the experience to date
has been with larger, professionally
managed pipe systems.
An important concept from the system
assessment step
of water safety planning is that of
multiple barriers.
Remember, the main source of pathogens is
fecal matter.
So multiple barriers can be put in place
to prevent fecal material from entering
the drinking water
supply, and to remove the pathogens that
do make
it in, using a variety of different
treatment processes.
Different pathogens have different levels
of
resistance, to different kinds of
treatment.
Also any single control measure can fail
at some point.
So by including multiple barriers to
remove pathogens, the
risk of providing unsafe drinking water
can be minimized.
Conventional treatment of surface water
typically follows this multiple barrier
approach.
Before reaching the treatment plant, the
water resource itself can be protected.
For example the use of fertilizers,
pesticides,
or other chemicals may be restricted
within
the catchment area of a river or an
aquifer used for drinking water supply.
Within the treatment plant itself, a
series of processes are normally followed.
Some kind of pre-treatment step may be
necessary to reduce high
levels of suspended solids, which could
cause problems for subsequent treatment
steps.
Storage reservoirs allow some
sedimentation to take place.
And roughing filters or bank infiltration
can remove many particles
as well as improving the microbiological
quality to some degree.
Coagulation and flocculation remove
turbidity,
or suspended solids.
By addition of a coagulant salt, typically
aluminum sulfate or ferric chloride, which
forms flocs that grow, removing suspended
solids as well as some dissolved
compounds.
These flocs then settle out of solution
in clarification tanks or, in some
cases, can float to the top of the tank
where they can be removed.
Filtration can then remove any remaining
flocs or
may be applied directly without a
coagulation step.
Depending on the filter material,
filtration can be an effective
control measure for some pathogens,
especially larger ones like
cryptosporidium.
Primary disinfection is an essential step
in
most treatment systems to achieve the
necessary
levels of pathogen reduction and to
provide
a safety net in case previous steps fail.
Chlorine is the most widely applied
disinfectant, but chlorine
dioxide, ozone, and ultraviolet light are
used in some cases.
Finally, after leaving the treatment
plant, water suppliers can
prevent contamination in the distribution
system by ensuring continuous
pressure so that contamination can't enter
the pipes and
by maintaining a residual disinfectant if
chlorine is used.
The same processes that are applied at
conventional treatment plants
can also be adapted and applied at the
household level.
In fact, all of the household water
treatment
systems use some combination
of sedimentation, filtration and
disinfection.
And they should all be followed by safe
storage to prevent re-contamination.
In the next several videos, we will look
at examples of
these processes that are used in the main
household water treatment systems.
The main difference between conventional
treatment and HWTS is not in
the processes, but in the point where the
processes are applied.
HWTS requires households to take charge of
their own water safety
by treating the water at the household
level, and preventing re-contamination.
This is quite a challenge, since most
household residents are not trained
engineers, and don't necessarily even have
a modern concept of germ theory.
The concepts of the water safety framework
can be applied for HWTS.
But implementing something like a water
safety plan for
household water treatment and storage
requires fundamental changes in behavior.
HWTS should not be seen as an
alternative or competitor to conventional
water supply.
And the long term goal should be to extend
access to
safe drinking water supplies at the
household level to everyone, everywhere.
HWTS can represent a short term strategy
to improve drinking
water quality until that long term goal
can be reached.
So in summary, we've heard today about the
water safety
framework, described in the WHO Guidelines
for drinking water quality.
The framework consists of three main
components: health-based
targets, water safety plans,
and verification monitoring, independent
verification.
There are a lot of resources available
that describe water safety
plans in much more detail, if you're
interested in learning more.
We also learned about one kind
of health-based target, log reduction
values, or
LRV We'll come back to those as we look at
the different treatment
processes used in HWTS, and we learned
that the treatment processes used in
household water treatment are the same
that
are applied in conventional water
treatment plants.
The key differences are in the location of
the treatment and
in the motivation and skills of the person
applying the treatment.