Membrane Filtration, passing water through
synthetic membranes to purify
it, is a rapidly growing field in drinking
water treatment.
The vast majority of experiences in high
income countries but increasingly membrane
filtration is being
adapted and applied in low and middle
income countries, and even at the
household scale.
In this module, we will discuss different
types of membranes and how they are
configured,
how they improve water quality and how
they can be applied for household water
treatment.
There are several different kinds of
processes involved in membrane filtration
which all have impacts on the quality of
the filtered water.
Perhaps the most obvious is a size
exclusion phenomenon
where particles are strained out through
either small pores in
the membrane itself, or they're collected
at a surface layer,
a cake that forms on the surface of the
membrane.
A second kind of process though is, an
electrostatic process.
Where particles that have a positive or
negative charge interact with the
membrane's surface.
If the charge is the same, they will repel
each other and if the charge is,
opposite the particles can be attracted to
and absorbed on the membrane surface.
Finally, membranes are biologically
active.
And that can have large impacts on
the removal both of pathogens and
dissolved compounds.
Different type of membrane filtration can
be defined on the basis of the pore size.
Or the size of materials that can pass
through the membrane.
Membranes with smaller pores will exclude
more particles, and even dissolved
substances, but will require more pressure
to force water through the membrane.
First, you can think about simple cloth
filtration.
Most cloths have an effective pore size of
around a 100
to 150 microns, about the diameter of a
strand of hair.
Remember our cartoon of the sizes of
different pathogens?
Certainly viruses and bacteria can easily
pass
through cloth, and most protozoa as well.
However, some pathogens are attached to
larger particles,
which could be removed by cloth, including
insect hosts.
The guinea worm larvae, which is
transmitted by copepods, little water
insects
around one millimeter in size, can be
effectively removed with cloth filtration.
Studies in Bangladesh have also shown that
cloth folded over four
to eight times has an effective pore size
of about 20 microns.
And cholera is also transmitted at least
partially through copepods.
So studies have shown that the use of
cloth
filtration can reduce cholera by about
half in Bangladesh.
Sand, silt, and clay are inorganic
particles that are defined by their size.
Particles smaller than two to four microns
are called clay.
Particles up to about 63 microns are
called silt.
And particles up to two millimeters are
called sand.
After that you get into gravel and
boulders.
Cloth filtration then can remove most
coarse and medium
sand, but doesn't do much for silt and
clay.
So, turbidity may not be very much reduced
by simple cloth filtration.
But most membrane filtration uses
synthetic
membranes made of different, plastic-like
materials.
There are four general types of synthetic
membranes which
have different pore sizes and therefore
operate at different pressures.
Micro-filtration membranes have pore sizes
of about 0.1 to five
microns and require little pressure to
force water through the membrane.
By the way, let's talk briefly about units
of pressure.
The atmospheric pressure at sea level is
100 kilopascals,
which is commonly called one bar, or a
thousand millibars.
Now one millibar is roughly equal to
the pressure caused by one centimeter of
water.
So one bar, a thousand millibars equates
to about ten vertical meters of water.
One bar is also equivalent to 15 pounds
per square inch, roughly, if you prefer
PSI units.
Now micro filtration typically requires
less than one bar of pressure.
Since the pores are large it's easy to
filter water quickly and you
can typically get several hundred liters
per hour from a square meter of membrane.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Micro filtration will usually remove
protozoa, like cryptosporidium and giardia
and depending on the membrane may also
remove bacteria like e coli and Shigella.
Viruses and chemicals would not be removed
except the fraction retained
on larger particles or absorbed onto the
membrane's surface.
Ultra filtration membranes have pore sizes
roughly from ten to
a hundred nanometers, where a thousand
nanometers equals one micron.
So these will completely exclude bacteria
and larger particles.
And may also remove viruses and larger
molecules like proteins.
Ultra filtration membranes require more
pressure, typically
around one bar but up to several bar.
Flux is depended on the operating pressure
but can typically
be around a hundred liters per hour, per
square meter.
Nano-filtration membranes go from about
one to ten
nanometers, so they should completely
exclude all pathogens, including viruses,
as well as larger molecules, having
molecular
masses from about 200 to a thousand
daltons.
Divalent metal cations, like magnesium,
which cause hardness in water,
can also be excluded by nano filtration
due to electrostatic effects.
So these membranes are often used for
water softening.
Operating pressures can go up to about ten
or 15 bar.
Finally, the tightest membranes are called
reverse osmosis, or
RO which can remove pretty much any kind
of ion.
RO is used for desalination, but requires
very high pressure, up to 80 bar.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Membranes come in several different
configurations.
The first main configuration is flat
sheets, like sheets of paper, which can be
mounted on racks or can be wrapped around
a spacer in a spiral roll.
The second main class is hollow fibers, or
tubes, where water is passed either
through the inside
of the tube and collected on the outside,
or
from the outside and then collected on the
inside.
In both cases, one of the objectives is to
maximize
the surface area of membranes that can be
packed into a
treatment module, so you'll also maximize
the amount of water
that can be treated for a given size of
filter module.
Membranes can also be operated in a
dead-end
or cross-flow configuration, where dead
end means that
all of the water is put on top of the
membrane and pushed through the membrane.
In contrast, cross-flow, the water, passes
laterally
across the surface of the membrane, with
some of the water permeating through the
membrane to the clean side where it's
collected.
Perhaps the greatest challenge of membrane
filtration is that of membrane fouling.
A clean, new membrane will process a lot
of water with relatively little pressure.
But with time, particles build up on the
surface.
A layer forms, a cake layer, especially if
the membrane's operated in a dead end
mode.
And internal to the membrane, particles
can lodge in
pores or dissolved compounds can absorb
and restrict pore size.
So over time, flux decreases and you need
more pressure
to get the same amount of water through
the system.
The response to this is to do regular
backwashing, reversing the flow
of water to remove some of those
particles, especially from the surface.
Or to pass water across the surface in a
cross flow at a high velocity to scour it.
And that can remove what's called the
reversible fraction of
fouling, but typically there's still, some
irreversible fouling that remains.
That can be removed in part but not wholly
by cleaning the membrane with solvents
or with acids or bases, depending on the
compounds causing the fouling.
There are many examples of household
application of
membrane filtration, in high income and
middle income countries.
Typically, reverse osmosis, or nano
filtration
systems could be installed in the kitchen.
They would require electricity and,
usually an additional pump
to generate the pressure to pass water
through the membranes.
However, there's increasing development
of, applications using ultra-filtration
or micro-filtration membranes, that use
less pressure to treat
the water, and can even be applied in some
cases without electricity in low and
middle income settings.
One of the best known examples of these
schemes or these
technologies is the Lifestraw family,
which is produced by Vestergaard Frandsen.
The Lifestraw family, here you see their
Lifestraw family 1.0 model.
It uses an ultra-filtration membrane with
a 20 nanometer pore size,
which is small enough to exclude protozoa,
bacteria and also viruses.
It's operated in a, a dead end mode, using
hollow fiber membranes.
The membranes are found in the blue
cartridge here.
And you simply fill the, the blue
reservoir with raw water to be filtered.
There's a hose that connects the reservoir
to the filter, and it's about a
meter long so that provides the pressure
necessary to pass the water through the
membrane.
The system includes a, a red bulb for
manual backwash and it can produce
about nine liters of water per hour with a
lifetime of about 18,000 liters.
The system also includes a, a halogen
compartment where a chlorine tablet can be
put.
And this isn't for, for removal of
pathogens as much as
for preventing of membrane fouling and
minimizing the need for backwashing.
Vestergaard has been producing Lifestraw
filters since 2005.
First, in emergencies such as earthquakes
in Haiti and Pakistan.
But increasingly has been targeting
household routine
use and one of their largest experiences
to
date has been in western Kenya, where
880,000
of these Lifestraw 1.0 family filters were
distributed.
In subsequent models, we'll look more at
their
business model, but here we're focusing on
the technologies.
Vestergaard has recently developed a
second
generation Lifestraw family filter, the
Lifestraw 2.0.
Which has a similar membrane to the 1.0,
though it does include an 80 micron
pre-filter.
One of the big differences, though, is
that the 2.0
includes reservoirs, both a five liter raw
water vessel, dirty water
tank and a five liter reservoir for
filtered water which can
minimize the potential for
re-contamination
after passing it through the membrane.
It's a bit larger as well, so it has a,
a 30,000 liter lifetime compared to 18,000
for the 1.0.
One large application of the Lifestraw
Family Filter, is as
part of the Del Agua Health Program
being implemented in Rwanda.
And this is a combination of the Lifestraw
2.0
along with improved cook stoves to reduce
indoor air pollution.
They are targeting 600,000 poor households
throughout the country.
The Lifestraw family is a well known
application of ultra-filtration
modules at the household level in low and
middle income countries.
But it's not the only one.
Here you can see some other examples of
microfiltration products Katadyn,
primarily targeting, backpackers and
sports enthusiasts.
Nerox, produces a microfilter that's used
in emergencies, as does Sawyer.
Then there are a number of ultra
filtration products out there.
One which my institution, EAWAG, has been
developing, is a gravity driven ultra
filtration
membrane which is a slightly different
approach
in that we allow a biological layer to
develop on the surface of the membrane, so
there's no need to do back washing
or cleaning and if you would like to hear
more about that, visit our website.
Then Lifesaver Systems has a bottle and a
jerrycan
version, Polymem and you've seen the
Vestergaard Franzen system.
Membrane filtration, like all treatment
process, has advantages and challenges.
One of the main advantages is that the
membrane provides an
absolute barrier to particles, as long as
system integrity is ensured.
Most of the membranes can exclude protozoa
and bacteria
easily, and the tighter membranes can also
exclude viruses.
However, the looser membranes, such as
microfiltration
and ultrafiltration have little effect on
chemicals directly.
Though some chemicals may be removed,
along with the
particles or it can absorb on to the
membrane's surface.
Membrane filtration can be very simple to
operate
though there is a need for backwashing and
cleaning.
One advantage is that membrane filtration
doesn't change the taste of
the water, though it does reduce turbidity
which, consumers often appreciate.
However, membrane filtration doesn't
provide
any residual, protection against
recontamination.
So especially if there's not a
safe storage container, they're vulnerable
to recontamination.
Some of the membrane filtration models
require electricity or high pressure.
And for all of them, supply chains are
necessary for
the initial purchase, but also for
replacement parts and services.
So in summary, we've looked at membrane
filtration as one type of the second
class of treatments of filtration, which
could
be followed by disinfection and then safe
storage.
We discussed cloth filtration, and how the
pores in cloths are quite large, so
the cloth is useful for removing large
particles, including copepods, but not
smaller ones
such as bacteria or viruses, and spent
more time looking at synthetic membranes,
especially
these four types of membranes, micro
filtration,
ultra filtration, nanofiltration and
reverse osmosis defined
on the basis of their pore sizes and
operating pressures.
And we saw which membranes could exclude
which kinds of particles and dissolve
compounds.
Finally, we concluded with a brief summary
of the advantages and challenges of
membrane filtration.