In this last lesson,
we will learn how to attack
a project more ambitious
than those we considered
up until now.
That is, how to decompose this project
into easily-solved sub-problems
until we know how to write
the final program.
To illustrate this, we have chosen
a game of connect 4.
You no doubt know the rules
of connect 4.
It is a two-player game with
a grid of seven columns
and 6 rows.
The players drop a chip of their
own color one after another
in the column they choose, until
one player manages to line up
four chips of his color or until the
grid is completely filled.
First, please note that we are not
going to develop
a pretty graphical interface. What
we are interested in here
is having a program which can
follow the mechanics of the game,
and we will make do with a
text-based display of the grid
and chips, that is, something that
would look like this.
Generally, how should
you approach such
large problem as this one?
You should definitely not try to
write the program all at once,
you won't manage that.
You should know how to break down the
problem into sub-problems
to write the program step-by-step.
And at each step,
you must test the code that you
have written in order
to continue on solid bases.
First of all, we must identify
what types
our program needs to work,
what data our program needs.
In our example, it essentially
needs to
be able to represent the grid.
Then, we will have to identify the methods
that will work on these types and test
them as we code them.
Then, when a method is hard
to write,
we can introduce an extra
method
for each of the difficult steps.
I said that we should start by
identifying the types.
What does this mean?
We will start by identifying the data
which our program needs
and finding how to represent these data.
In this case, for our game of connect 4,
the main data are the grid
and the chips it contains
or more precisely, we
want to know, for each cell,
what the cell contains.
Is it a red chip, a yellow chip, or
nothing at all?
The simplest and surely
the most practical way
of representing the grid in
our Java program
is to use a two-dimensional
array
where each element of the
two-dimensional array
corresponds to a cell of the grid.
We shall decree that the
first index of the array
corresponds to the line number,
where line 0
corresponds to the line
at the top of the grid
and that the second index
corresponds to the column number.
And here again, we must decide
on a convention
and we shall say that the left-most
column will be column 0.
We still have to choose the
type of the array's elements,
which corresponds to cells in the grid.
We will choose an int type here,
and define constants of type int.
The three constants will be named
VIDE, JAUNE and ROUGE
(TN: EMPTY, YELLOW and RED).
All three will be initialized with
different values
which will allow us to use these
three constants
to gives values to the chips or
cells of our grid.
There are other ways of doing this,
using for example enumerated
types,
but we will not talk about these
in this video.
Updating the grid will then be
done in the following way:
for example, this instruction will
give the value VIDE (TN: EMPTY), that is, 0,
in the element of the grid array which
is on line 0 and column 0,
which corresponds, if we respect
the conventions we described
a few slides earlier, to this
cell right here,
in which we will put the value
VIDE (= 0).
With this instruction, we will
assign to cell 2,
since we start with the top-most
cell which has the index 0.
We change the element of this line 2
which has an index of 3.
So, 0, 1, 2, 3. This one.
We assign the value JAUNE (TN: "YELLOW")
which equals 1.  But I could easily
have represented this assignment
in this way to show that it corresponds
to a cell of my grid that should be
marked as yellow.
In the next video,
we will learn how to write the
functions which will allow us
to initialize and display the grid.