Coding of an application,
whatever its nature may be,
requires thinking both about
the involved data and their types,
and about the fundamental
functionalities
allowing the implementation
of the desired processes.
We started this work during the
previous episode
for the implementation of
the Connect Four game.
Today, we will push this further
and start to focus on the first
functionalities
needed for the implementation of
this game.
As a reminder, during the
previous episode,
we had started by working on the
representation of the game's grid.
Our choice was, naturally,
to represent it
in the form of a two-dimensional
array.
We had also worked on the
representation of the
content of each of the cells
of this grid.
There are of course many different
possible choices
to represent this content.
We kept one for its simplicity:
representing the type of each cell
as an integer
with a certain convention which
consists in saying
that 0 represents an empty cell, 1 a yellow
cell and 2 a red cell.
To be able to manipulate the
contents of these cells
explicitly and clearly in the
program,
we had defined constants
to represent these different values and
to manipulate them explicitly.
Let's now focus on the first
functionalities
useful for the implementation
of a Connect Four game.
When, in my program, I will
have declared the grid
in the form of a two-dimensional
array,
it is likely that the first thing
I will think about is
to initialize this grid correctly.
Indeed, at the beginning of the game
for example,
it would be best for
each of these cells to be empty.
And so, we must carry
out this initialization.
Another natural function to
anticipate is the display of the grid.
Indeed, for the player to be
able to know
the evolution of the game with time,
it must be possible to display the
different cell colors in the game's grid,
and at that moment, a display function
becomes absolutely necessary.
In this episode,
we will focus on the actual
implementation
of these two basic functionalities.
Let's start by the initialization
function
which we will implement here
via a method called "initialise".
One of the first things to do
when we start to think about
implementing a method
is to try to imagine how we will
actually use it.
So here, if I have first declared my
grid in this form,
it is natural to imagine the
initialization of this grid
through a call to an "initialise" method
which would take the grid as a parameter,
like so.
Such a call to the "initialise" method
would result
in the initialization of each of the cells of
my game grid with
the value "VIDE" [TN: means "EMPTY"].
Let's now think about the header for
the "initialise" method. We have learned
that, at this stage of the course,
the "static" keyword is associated
to every method
for reasons which will be
explained
in the other course on object-oriented
Java.
How about the rest of the elements of hte
header of the "initialise" method?
So, to define this header precisely,
we have to specify the name of the
method -- we chose it here --
the set of arguments that the
method will have to receive
for it to work,
and what we call the return type
of the method.
How do we choose the return type here?
Here, I called my initialization
method
by passing it the grid as parameter
and I do not expect anything in return
from this call.
I do not expect to make this call
in such a way that,
after my grid is initialized, I would
receive a value
in return.
The "initialise" method
returns nothing,
so it is natural to give it a "void"
return type.
It is quite easy to describe the
other elements of the header.
So, we have started writing the code
"initialise"
and the set of arguments is a two-
dimensional array
which represents the grid.
So at this stage, I will have
completely defined
what we refer to as the header of the method.
It is now time to think about
its body,
that is, the set of instructions
which will carry out the
desired behavior,
which is to fill the grid
with the "VIDE" (empty) value.
Small aside before continuing,
you should note that this specific
way of designing the "initialise" method
is of course not the only one possible.
We could easily have imagined
alternative designs,
for example the one that consists
in making the "initialise"
method return a grid,
without taking the grid to fill
in as an argument,
and so to replace these two lines
by something
like this.
And in this case, the initialise method
would not take any arguments,
as it would completely build and
initialize a grid
and then return it.
Its return type would not be
"void" anymore,
but a grid, so a two-dimensional
array.
In the version that we chose, this works
thanks to the fact
that arrays are manipulated via
references
and that we can modify a
referenced object
through the reference passed as argument.
This means that the grid that we
passed to the "initialise" method
will indeed be modified
once the method is done executing.
The algorithm for the initialization
of the grid is easy to imagine here.
For each of the lines of the grid,
we will go through each cell,
each column,
to fill these cells with
the empty value, "VIDE".
Let's start by writing the
lines of code
that will allow us to initialize a single
line of our grid;
for example, the first line.
So here, we need to iterate over all
the cells of this line,
which can be done naturally with an
iteration, a  for-loop,
that we can write like this.
So, for each column of the first line,
which we can write in the form
"grille[0]",
we will put the  "VIDE" value into the
current column.
We know that in Java,
a two-dimensional array is simply
an array of arrays,
so here our grid would have the
following form,
and the first line of the grid is
what is accessible
under the name "grille[0]".
So here, simply, for each of the
columns of the first line,
we populate their content using
the value "VIDE".
"grille[0].length", by the way,
gives us the number of cells
in the first line of my grid,
in this case, 7.
We know that, in a Java array,
the elements are indexed from
0 to size-1
which explains why we stop strictly
before the value 7
and why we start iterating from 0.
Since the code that
we have written here
only allows us to initialize one
line of our grid,
we have to repeat it for each of the
other lines.
So, this routine must be repeated
for each line
and so it is natural to nest this
in another for-loop
which will iterate over the number of lines.
This can be written like so:
for each line numbered from 0 to "grille.length",
we repeat the instructions
that we wrote for the first line.
So here, a few modifications
should be made,
such as replacing 0 by the i-th line
since we are repeating this for each line,
and there we have it.
There, once a game has
been declared in a program,
in the form of a two-dimensional
integer array,
we now know how to initialize it
using the "initialise" method.
Let's now focus on the second
base functionality,
which is a method allowing us to
display the grid,
the "affiche" method.
(TN: "affiche" means "display")
As we did earlier for the
"initialise" method,
let's try to imagine
how we would naturally call the "affiche"
method.
So, we can imagine that,
after having made a certain number
of operations on the grid,
we wish to display its content.
It's quite natural to anticipate
this call being of this form.
So, we pass as a parameter to
the "affiche" method
the grid to display
and we do not expect
any return value.
So, just like for the "initialise" method,
we obtain a method header
quite analogous to that of the
"initialise" method,
in the sense that we do not expect the
"affiche" method to return any value,
so we define its return type
as "void".
As always at this stage of the course, we
use the "static" keyword.
As parameters for the "affiche" method,
we will pass the grid to display.
Let's now proceed to the coding of the body
of the "affiche" method.
The algorithm is very close
to the one we wrote for the "initialise" method,
since we have to iterate over
each line of the grid
and for each of these lines,
iterate on each column
to display their content in a
particular format.
Here, of course, we will not make
any graphical display,
but we will make a textual printing in the
terminal
by adopting a certain number
of display conventions.
For example, we will display an empty
cell with a space
and red or yellow cells using arbitrary
characters
such as 'X' or 'O'.
So we would have a display that would
look like this
for each line of our grid.
In Java, these instructions
can be written like this:
so here I am iterating again
but I will switch it up a little
compared to my earlier
solution
by iterating over the whole set of values.
Here, for each line of my grid,
which is written like this,
for each cell of this line, I will
display its content
and for this I will have to stick
to my conventions
and so write a certain number of tests.
If the cell is empty, I will display
it using a space,
which is written like this.
So here, I don't jump any line,
I just want to display the space.
Then I continue with another test, "else if".
If my cell's value is the red
constant,
then I display it according to another
convention, like so,
and finally, I know that I am
in the situation where my cell is yellow
and so I can display it using
another character, 'X' here.
And here we are!
Here, for each of the
lines of the grid
to be displayed separately from the
others,
I must insert a line break after displaying
each line.
An alternative way of coding this
would have been to replace the
iterations over the whole set of values
by conventional "for" iterations,
which could be written like so.
So here, we have chosen
to iterate over a set of values
which is a little more
elegant and explicit.
So why did we not use this
option earlier
when we coded the "initialise" method?
Why did we choose to use
"conventional" "for" iterations?
Would you know how to
answer this question?
The answer is simply that in Java,
an iteration on a set of values
cannot modify the set of values
that it iterates over.
Whereas for the "initialise" method,
this is an absolute must,
the "initialise" method has to
modify the set of cells of the grid.
There, now our display method
is essentially written
and we will, as good programmers,
comment this method
Here, the comment is
particularly important
because the display conventions
that we chose
are completely arbitrary,
and anyone who reads our code
should be able to know these conventions
without having to read through and
understand the whole of the method's body.
This is why here, we must
absolutely comment our choices
and indicate that, for us, a big 'O'
indicates a red cell
and a big 'X' a yellow one.
Systematic testing of the different
features of an application
during coding
is absolutely essential to produce
robust, high-quality code.
This is a recommendation that
we made
right at the beginning of our case
study on the Connect Four game.
We will now stick to these
principles
and start to test our
first features,
that is, initialization and
display of the grid.
To test the "initialise" and
"affiche" methods,
we will have to write a small
program which calls them,
so a "main" method.
So this "main" method here
will of course declare a grid
in the form of a two-dimensional
integer array
and construct it as a matrix of 6 lines
and 7 columns.
Here, we suppose that before this,
we have declared the constants for empty ("VIDE"),
yellow ("JAUNE") and red ("ROUGE"),
and we will thus proceed to
the different calls
which will allow us to
test the methods,
in other words the initialization of
the grid and its display.
So, if we displayed the grid
immediately after its initialization,
we would not be able to test all
the cases
since the grid would be
completely empty;
and we could not know
if yellow and red cells are
displayed correctly.
For this reason, it
is advisable to modify
the contents of some
cells of the grid,
in order to be able to see how
the program behaves
when it has a yellow cell or a red
cell at a given place.
If our initialization and
display methods
were correctly written
we should obtain an output which
looks like this:
this will allow us to verify that
all the cells of the grid
which were not explicitly modified
are indeed empty cells,
following our convention that we
display a space for these
and that those that were
explicitly modified
are displayed according to the
conventions that we defined.
So, basically, here,
we should be able to verify
that the cell which is at line 2
(remember that we start numbering from 0)
and column 3 does indeed correspond
to a yellow cell,
which we chose to represent
with a big 'X'.
The same goes for the second
explicitly modified cell,
which corresponds here to the cell
on line 2
and column 4, this time
So, the output of the program
will allow us to verify
most of the functions that we
implemented
through "initialise" and "affiche".
The "initialise" and "affiche" methods,
as we have coded them,
carry out most of the functions
that these two methods must implement.
It is now time to wonder about
more cosmetic aspects, about finishing.
Let's go back to the "affiche" method
to see how we could improve
its code.
The "affiche" method, as we
have coded it,
would allow, for a game grid
looking like this,
to produce a text display such as
the one you see here.
As you can see, this display is
rather basic,
and makes it quite hard
to distinguish between
different columns.
And so we could imagine
improving the display
by having something that
would look like this.
So, by explicitly separating the different
columns
and by numbering these columns
to have a much clearer view
of the contents of the grid.
The modifications we must
make to obtain this sort of output
are visible here and I will
now comment on them.
So here, first modification: we
took the precaution,
before displaying each line,
to display a space and a bar, which
corresponds to this output here,
for each of the lines.
Then, once we have displayed
all of the cells,
we should close the cell with
a bar,
like so.
When we have finished
displaying the grid,
we want to add this line,
which will allow us to number
the different columns.
We start by displaying a first '=' symbol
below the space preceding the first
column,
then a for-loop will repeat
as many times as the number of
columns we have in the grid
to display the number of
each column
So, at each iteration here, for each
possible column number,
given that we are numbering, to be more
clear, from 1 to "grille.length",
we will display, for each of the possible
columns,
an '=' symbol followed by the column
number.
So, this for-loop will allow us to display
these different elements:
"=1", "=2", "=3", "=4", ...
and so on.
When we are done with this for-loop,
we find ourselves in the situation
where we have displayed
'=' followed by the last column
number possible.
What remains is to display
these two '=' symbols
for a little more harmony
in the display.
This is what we are doing here.
This illustrates an essential
point in coding practices:
one should always start by working o
essential and fundamental
functionalities
before dealing with
little things, before adding cosmetic or finishing
touches to our application
as we have just done here in this
example.
So we can see that at this stage,
our "affiche" method is starting
to get big,
so we can legitimately ask
ourselves the question:
should we modularize more?
And here, this is absolutely feasible.
We can imagine introducing
two new methods
which would help the "affiche"
method in its job
and render it somewhat
more concise.
We could for example have a method
"afficheLigne" (TN: means "displayRow")
whose job would be to display
one entire row of this grid
and another method, for example "afficheBas"
(TN: means "displayFooter")
which would display the bottom
of our grid.
We are now at the end of
this step.
You now know how to model a
Connect Four grid.
You also know how to initialize it and
display its contents.
We can now move on to the
heart of the matter,
coding the functionalities which will
allow us to play,
as we will see in the following
episodes.