In the previous video,
we learned one way of programming
the joue method,
whose job is to check whether a column
indicated by the player is a legal play
and if so, to put the chip into
the grid.
In this video, I suggest 2 ways
of programming this joue method.
Let's start with the header of
the joue method.
Clearly, if we want to
change the algorithm,
the body of the method,
the header will remain the same.
And so I will remind you
that we take a grid,
an array of integers, which is the
game in which we want to play.
Then an integer which indicates
in which column the player wants to play.
And finally a third integer argument,
which indicates the color of the chip
played in the column.
The joue method returns a boolean,
which returns true if the
play is legal,
and false if the play
is illegal.
Let's change the algorithm from the
last version of the joue method
and let's start by testing the
legality of the play.
The play is only legal if the
cell at position 0, at the row 0,
is not occupied.
Indeed, if the cell located at
position 0 in the column
in which we want to play
is not empty,
this means that there were chips
below and that the column is full.
So, as usual, we will start
by writing the comment
which explains what we will do.
If the column is full,
then the play is illegal.
And now, let's write it in Java.
If the column is full, that is,
if the grid,
at position 0 and in the column
we were given is not empty,
in other words, is not equal to the
predefined value for vide (TN: empty),
then the play is illegal
and we simply have to leave
the method by returning false.
This simplifies exploration of
the grid greatly
to place the chip,
since at this point,
either we left with false,
or we know that the column
is not full
and so we will necessarily
find an empty cell
which we can now start
to look for.
As usual, we put this
into a comment,
we will search the column from
bottom to top to find the first empty cell.
This is written in Java thus:
we start by naming a variable here,
ligne (TN: row) to search
the different rows.
We initialize this line to
the last line of the array,
which is size of grid -1 .
I remind you that arrays
have indices that go
from 0 to size-1.
So, we initialize ligne
to size of grid - 1
and then we will search
this array upwards.
So, while the cell
at the position of the
current line
and the indicated column
is not empty,
we decrement the line number,
so --ligne.
Now, we have found an empty cell
and we simply have to play there.
As always, we write the comment, so we
write that grille (TN : grid),
at position row, column
receives the color which we wish to play.
So the first parameter we received, couleur.
And we can end by returning the
information that we were able to play,
by returning true.
This is our new version of the
joue method.
and I will let you appreciate
the difference in size of these
two methods, disregarding the size
of the comments.
Let's end with yet another version of the
joue method
which, this time, builds upon the
method from the previous video
and improves it.
So, here is the version from
the previous video
and the idea is to use this pleine
(TN: occupied) boolean
and to try to do things differently.
So we will delete it, but with what
will we replace it?
Let's go back to the initial problem,
and I will remind you that we had
introduced this pleine boolean
because we decremented the row
in the first version, until it reached
the position 0.
So when ligne was null,
we continued, in the first version, to
decrement and thus to
exceed the bounds of the array.
All we have to do now is to
write this
and to say that we want to stop
when ligne equals 0.
We want to continue as long as ligne
is bigger than or equals 0.
As soon as the row reaches 0,
we want to loop to stop.
So we write this, while ligne
>= 0.
0, of course,  must be considered,
as long as ligne is bigger
than or equals to 0.
So we can continue removing
all instances of pleine.
There, this simplifies our
loop considerably.
And we will do the same thing in the
last part, at the bottom, were we play,
and we will put the test here too,
the same one.
Namely "if ligne >= 0",
indeed, at this point, the row is
bigger than or equals 0,
it means that we are still within the grid
and that we can play.
Otherwise, we are outside of
the grid.
Here is then the final version,
with comments of course,
which we do not hesitate to add to
make our code more legible.
This ends our third version of the
joue method.
That said, there is still
a potential error
in all our versions of the
joue method.
Do you see what it might be?
I will let you implement this
correction as an exercise
in the version of joue which you
choose to code.
At this stage, you should have a
decent Java program
where you can represent a game,
that is, a grid,
and the colors of the two players' chips.
You can thus initialize this
game and display it.
And you can play with chips and
test the legality of plays in the grid.
To have a complete game,
we still have to ask
a player where he wishes to play
and to be able to alternate
between players: ask red to play,
then yellow.
And finally to check whether the game
has ended,
that is, if one of the players has one or
if the grid is full.
This will be discussed in the next
videos.