Let's continue coding our
Connect Four game
In the previous episodes,
we covered the data structures that we
recommend
you use to represent this game;
how to represent the players' colors;
and 2 basic features which are
the initialization of the grid
and its display.
Now, let's look at the actual play.
What do we need?
For that, we must be able to ask
the user where he wants to play,
as well as verify his play,
validate both the answer
and the data structures.
That is, if the play is legal, make
sure that the structures are valid
and put the disk into the grid.
Then, we must ask the other player
to play, and come back,
and alternate between the two players.
And we must decide if the game
has ended,
either when one of the two players
has won, or when the grid is full.
In this episode
we will focus on the second point,
that is, ask a user for a column
and check if it is valid
and then update the game
according to the play that was made.
Now that we know what we want to do
with the method that we will implement,
let's give it a name. We will call
the method "joue" (TN: means "play").
Now, let's look at how to program it.
Let's start with its header.
To have an idea of what to put in the
header, we should ask ourselves
how the joue would be called
in the program.
For example, when we want
to play in a certain
column of the grid, for example number 3.
Here, we are in the program,
so the positions will correspond
to the positions in Java,
where numbering begins with zero,
and column number 3 would be...here.
Then, we have to specify
the color of the player:
is it a red player, or a yellow player?
Here is a typical call that we could
make,
which would give the following situation:
in column 3, the player inserts a disk
we would have a red disk which
would place itself here.
After that, we would have
calls where, typically,
we would have a disk, for example yellow,
that would be placed in column
number 2,
that is, the third column,
and then the red player would play
again in the same column number 3,
so the fourth column,
which would result in this situation.
There, now it is quite clear to us
how to write the header of our
joue method.
So joue will take as first
parameter the grid,
which is, as we said, a two-dimensional
array of integers,
then it will take a position which will
indicate the column,
so another integer here,
and finally we decided to represent
the player colors as integers,
so the third argument here will
be the color.
That's it for the header of the joue method.
Now, concerning its return value,
we will start with the keyword static
But what is its return type?
To answer this,
note that we did not write "z = joue (...)"
we simply made calls to joue
directly
This means that joue returns nothing
and its return type will thus be void.
Now we have written its header,
we can continue with the definition,
with the body of the method.
For that, let's start by asking ourselves
what we really want to do
if, for example, we have a valid play,
where the player chooses column 3.
Let's imagine the general case,
where we already had disks
in column 3
and the player plays in column 3 again.
What should we do?
The disk should stop at the
first empty cell
in that column.
But, first from where? The first
from the bottom.
The algorithm will thus search from the
bottom for the first empty spot.
Lines are numbered from zero
up until (size of the grid) - 1:
remember that an array is indexed
from zero
to size-1.
Let's start by declaring a variable
which we will call, very creatively,
"ligne" (TN: means "line"),
which will start at size of grid minus 1,
and increment it one by one
until we find an empty spot.
All we need to do now is write this.
We start by writing a comment
which explains what we want to do:
we iterate over the column from the bottom,
until we find an empty cell.
For that, we will declare a counter variable,
let's call it "ligne" (TN: means "row" or "line").
We will initialize it to the last position
of the row array
that is, "grille.length - 1".
So it starts here,
then we will go up as long as we
haven't found an empty cell,
as long as the grid, at the position
of the row
and column we selected, is not empty.
For this purpose, we had defined
VIDE, a value defining an empty cell,
which we can reuse here;
as long as this column is not empty,
we will go up one by one, which we
write as " -- ligne ".
There, at this stage we have found an empty
cell,
and we can fill it with the color we
received.
For that, as usual, we start by writing
the comment,
then, in Java, we simply write
" grille[ligne][colonne] = couleur; ",
where couleur is the color we received.
This ends our first version of the joue
method,
and, as good programmers, we will
now test it.
To do that, we write a main method
which will test its workings.
In the main method,
we will declare a grid,
a grid of 6 by 7.
As you saw in a previous episode, we will
initialize the grid. We can start
by diplaying it.
Then, we directly test a play
in the third column with the
color red,
then we display the grid, which
should give us
an output reflecting the fact that we
have a red disk here,
since, remember, the index we
receive here
corresponds to Java numbering, which
begins with zero
So, the output will be like this,
then we continue by placing a
yellow disk
in column number 2, that is, the
third column
Then we continue to test
by playing another red disk
and displaying the grid,
by playing a red disk in the
fourth column,
column number 3, which will result
in an output
that will look like the grid here.
Now, what happens if we continue
to play
like this in column 3, if we add
disks,
for example red disks, each time
in column 3,
what will our joue method
do in this case?
What happens when we play
in a column that is already full?
What will happen is that
we initialize
our ligne variable as usual to the last
row of our array,
then, while the row, at
the corresponding column,
is not empty, i.e here, while
the row is not equal to zero,
this condition will be true, and
we will continue doing "-- ligne",
and we will continue going up
to position zero.
When ligne equals zero,
what happens?
At that moment, this condition
will still be true,
position zero is not empty,
and we will do "-- ligne" again.
This will make us go out of the
bounds
of our array, outside of our game,
which is at least a conception
error,
since we have a loop which takes
us out of our array.
So, we will have to correct this,
and stop this while loop,
as soon as we reach the end of
the array,
that is, as soon as we reach index 0.
Now we just need to write it.
To do so, we will declare a boolean
which will test whether we
have completely filled a column.
We will call it "pleine" (TN: means "full").
In the beginning, the column is
not supposed to be full,
so we will declare this variable
as false.
Then, in the loop which travels upwards
to find an empty position,
we will change the value of the
pleine boolean
and switch it to true,
as soon as we reach position 0.
This is because if we reach position
zero in this loop,
it means that position zero
was not empty,
so position zero is not empty
only if the rest of the column is also full
So, let's continue writing this.
If the line reaches position zero,
then we can say that the column
is full,
so "pleine = true".
In this case, we must stop
decrementing,
we must not subtract 1 from the row,
so we protect our "-- ligne"
instruction
when the row is zero
So we add an else
which protects this decrementation,
this "-- ligne"
from the condition, from the fact that
the row is empty.
And now we'll correct our loop,
by saying that we continue the loop
as before, that is, we continue to
look for an empty cell,
but only while the column is not full.
This symbol, remember, means not,
so while the column is not full,
and we haven't found an empty cell,
we continue as long as the
2 conditions are true.
If it is not full
and we haven't found an empty
cell, we go up.
If one of the two conditions, either if
it is full,
or we have found an empty cell,
are true,
then the loop will stop.
We can end by adding a pair of
parentheses here
to make our code more legible.
Finally, since we didn't do that
in the beginning, as we should have done,
we will comment what we have just
coded.
The idea is to iterate over the column from
the bottom
until we find an empty cell, or until
we reach the top.
Finally, we must not forget to correct the
end which is not valid anymore,
since we cannot guarantee that it is
possible to play every time,
since the disk will not be placed if
the column is full
So we protect this with the
condition:
if the column is not full, so,
"if (!pleine)".
now, we can play,
and we can also give an indication:
we can add an instruction to our
joue method
so that it can indicate its status
to the outside, for example by returning
true to say "I was able to
play,
the joue method was able to
do what we want".
And conversely, it can return
false, to say:
"no, the column was full, the play
was not valid,
I was not able to place this disk at
the right position".
Finally, as usual, we comment
our code to explain,
either to us, later, when we
go over the code again
or to anyone else who would read it,
what our code does.
Here, if we haven't reached the top,
"if (!pleine)",
if we haven't reached the top
of the column, if it isn't full,
then, we can play.
Let's not forget, finally, to correct
our return type
since we have now decide to return
a boolean to indicate whether
the play was valid or not
So we change the return type from
void to boolean
There, now we are pretty sure
that we have corrected our first version of
the joue method
to have a robust version which accounts
for the case where the column is full,
and now we must test this method
and for that,
we will write a new main method,
where we will specifically test
the case where we always play
in the same column.
As usual, we declare the grid,
we initialize it, we display it,
and then here, we will write a loop
which will play
10 times in the same column,
in the fourth column here, i.e column
number 3.
We write a loop that
repeats 10 times,
playing in column 3.
Note that now, since the joue function
returns a boolean
indicating whether the play was
valide,
we now call joue on the
right-hand side of an expression.
So we fetch the return value by
writing "valide = joue(...)",
and to see what is going on and
to test our program,
in case the play was not valid,
we will display
a message telling us that it
was not possible to play.
In either case, we display the grid
to see what is happening.
What will this give us?
I copied the main here in the bottom,
and all of our joue method.
Let's run the main. We start at
"i = 0" -- we don't use the i,
it just serves to say that we are
executing the loop 10 times.
So here we start at "i = 0",
and we always play
in column 3 with red disks.
This will start by placing a disk here,
then another, and so on.
All of these cases aren't
especially interesting,
but what will happen when we
play the seventh disk?
Once i has a value of 6, here,
we want to play a seventh time
in the same column, which is
already full,
and so when i has a value
of 6, we will end up here again,
with a value of 3 for the column and
the color red,
and here, we will initialize the
row to
the size of the grid minus 1.
We will initialize the boolean to false,
so of course, pleine is true, meaning
that the grid, at the position [ligne][colonne],
is not empty,
the row is not equal to zero,
so here we jump into the else and
we decrement ligne,
which will thus end up here (second row).
Here, both conditions are verified,
so pleine is still true,
and we still have a grid here
which is not empty, and so
we will go up until we reach the
position ligne==0.
So when ligne == 0,
what will happen?
We always arrive here with
a true condition,
and the grid at [0][column]
is not empty,
we go in here, but this time
the if is true,
the row is zero, and at that
moment we change
the value of pleine to true.
We are here, we are at the end of
the if bloc,
we come back into our loop,
but this time, the condition,
"!pleine",
is false and so the
while loop ends,
and we exit the loop.
Then we continue,
here, we reach this if,
again, our pleine is not true,
so this condition here is false.
We jump into the else
and we return false.
Which means that when we arrive
here, when we have a value of 6,
valide will be false and so,
we will display the error message
and this message will be displayed
for i equals 6, 7, 8 and 9,
so the error message
indicating it is impossible to play
will be displayed 4 times.
That was the test which confirms
that we cannot add disks to a column
that was already full,
which is exactly what we wanted.
There, I propose to end this episode here,
and to discuss alternative ways of implementing
the joue method
in the next episodes.