Let's continue programming our
famous Connect Four game.
At this point, we know how
to represent the game,
we know how to represent the colors,
we know how to initialize the game,
how to display it,
and then we saw how to make
the core of the program,
the joue method,
which allows us to get a column
number from a user,
verify if we can actually play in that
column,
and if possible, make that play.
But at this point, we still don't
really know how to play the game.
So let's try to write a main
method
that will handle the actual
gameplay.
For this, what we will need to do
is of course ask a user
for a move,
make this move,
display the game, then
alternate,
change the player's color.
Of course, we want to repeat this,
to play one turn after another
until the game is over.
So, now, we are clear with what the
method has to do, with the "what".
As always, when we write
a method,
we should first think about what it
has to do, the "what"
Now that this is clear, we can
start to write
and of course, we start
with the classic header
then the body of the main method.
Before entering this game loop which
we have just described,
we must of course declare a game.
So here, this is a two-dimensional
integer array,
which we call "grille" (TN: means "grid").
And we know that a Connect Four grid
has six rows and seven columns.
Then we will of course initialize it.
So we call our initialise method.
And it is nice to display it to show that
we are starting with an empty grid.
Now, we will define the color
of the first player.
In Connect Four, we start with the
yellow player.
So we initialize a variable defining the
color of the current player to yellow
There, now we are ready to begin
our game loop,
as we discussed earlier.
The question we should ask
ourselves at this point is:
should we use a while or
do while loop?
Do we begin by testing something?
Or do we begin by executing
something
before testing a condition
and looping?
Here, I can't really imagine what we
might want to test.
We are in the initial situation,
we control everything.
So we will start by running
through our game sequence,
then we will test whether
we should continue or not,
if the game has ended,
and if that is not the case then we
will of course loop
So, this is a do while loop.
We start by writing do.
And what we want to do first
in our loop
is to ask the player for a move.
We could do this with a function,
but here, I will write everything
in the main
and we will come back to it
a little later on.
That being said, even if we
don't make this into a function,
we can adopt the same
methodology
and decompose it into sub-tasks:
to ask for a move, what
should we do?
We must ask the question and
retrieve the answer.
So we start by asking
the question
To do so, we will display
a message to the user
and we will display a different
message
if the player is red or if
he is yellow
since we will also use this
message to indicate their color.
So if the players color is yellow,
we will display the following message:
Of course, system.out.println.
Here, we display "joueur" (TN: means "player")
and their color
here we will display an X for the
color yellow,
player X, and we will ask him
to enter a move.
Otherwise, we display a message
for the red player.
We use a capital O
to display the color red, just like
for the disks.
And we end here with
the same message
Then, we want to input the reply.
To do this, we introduce a new
colonne variable (TN: "colonne" means "column")
which will be the column in which
the player wants to play.
And we read with nextInt.
Of course, we mustn't forget to
declare something to be able to read this,
so we declare a Scanner
as usual.
And, following the suggestions we gave you
in the previous episodes,
we declare this variable outside of
the main here
to be able to access it in
the entire program.
There, let's shift all of this
up a little
to continue with our main.
By the way, don't forget that the indices
we use for the grid in Java
are shifted by one compared to the indices
that we humans use.
Humans would count from
one to six,
whereas we will begin
at zero.
So we must shift by one
with "--colonne".
Then we will be able to
actually make this move.
Remember that the joue
method,
as we wrote it in the
previous episode,
returns a boolean that is true if
the move is valid
and false if it is not valid.
So we get this return value and
store it in a boolean,
in a valide variable which
we declared and initialized here,
with a call to our joue method
which takes the grid,
the column number we just received
from the player
and the color of the current player
which we declared here.
If the play is invalid, it is important
to let the player know
and so if it is invalid,
we display a message indicating that
the play was invalid:
so, println the message.
Now, third step in our loop:
displaying the game.
And now, fourth step...
... let's shift this all to have
a clearer picture...
... fourth step of our loop: alternating
the colors,
i.e changing the color of
the current player.
As usual, we write comments to be
as clear as possible.
So, we change the color
very easily.
We could also write a method to do this,
actually this would be a good place to do so,
but the method is simply: if the current
color is yellow,
then we change it to red.
Otherwise, we set it to yellow.
So, if the current player's color
is yellow,
we set it to red.
So if the color of the player is
yellow, I set it to red.
Otherwise, I set it to yellow.
couleur_joueur, remember,
is the variable representing
the color of the current player.
There, we have finished our loop
and all we need to add
is the condition.
What condition?
The game continuation condition.
We continue playing while...
Well, I will leave this to the next
episode,
and leave this blank.
This concludes our main method
that allows us to play.
I encourage you to compile
and test it.
Of course, you have to write
something here in the blank space.
At first, you can write while true
to have an infinite loop,
and you can stop the program
with the environment.
I encourage you to systematically
make tests like this
when you are at such a step.
Personally, I would prefer to review this
code right now with you
to organize it better, to modularize it,
that is, to create methods to handle
the most important parts.
We have already said that we
could write a display method here
and we will come back to this
later on.
We could write a method to alternate
between the players.
And, on a larger scale,
we could make a method of
all of this,
since it is essentially the core
of the game.
The main is way too large
here. As you can see,
it doesn't fit on one slide
which is a sign that it is not well written.
A main must be very concise, very clear.
So we will modularize it, we
will chop it up into methods.
The easiest is to directly cut out the part
we want to make into a method,
as we explained to you in the episode on
methodology for
function and method development.
Then we start to write the
method call as we envision it,
so for example, let's say that this part
corresponds to asking and playing,
so we will call it demandeEtJoue
(TN: means "askAndPlay").
This will be the name of our method,
demandeEtJoue.
And what does this method
need to receive?
It needs the current game of
course, so the grid
and the color of the current player.
Those are the two arguments
we pass it.
And now we can proceed to
writing this method.
As a reminder, here is the call
in comment.
So we pass the grid and the player's
color to demandeEtJoue
This gives the following header:
void demandeEtJoue
taking a grid
and a color.
Then, in the body of the method,
we will simply
copy everything we had cut
out of the main
to make it into a method.
At this stage, one should be very careful
not to make any mistakes in the names.
For example, here we used
couleurJoueur again
and I strongly encourage you to
save, compile and verify
that the code is correct
and that we haven't made any mistake.
Of course, you should
proofread it,
and possibly test it too
with a small test method.
In the spirit of modularizing,
let's try to avoid copy-pasting
as much as possible.
I see several copies of the
same thing here.
I see that "Joueur" was repeated here.
I see that here, we repeated the message
asking the user for a column number.
This all is not right and we will
have to make it modular.
To do so, we will find the
common parts
and remove them from the
condition on the color.
Because, which part of this depends
on the color?
The only part that does is this
output here
of the X and O.
So we will put the common parts
preceding the display of the X
before the if,
and we will put the common parts
following the display of the X and O
after the if.
This gives the following code:
We start by displaying the common
message "Joueur "..
and careful here, we are using print
and not println
since the line is not finished and we
do not want to display a newline.
Then we make our test on the
color and in this case,
if the color is yellow, we display the X
otherwise, we display the O.
Then we have another common part which
is displayed using println
thus displaying the end of the message.
And now, we see again
that we could modularize
a little bit more.
And this little bit of code here,
these few lines,
could be a color output
which would be useful both in
displaying the game
and displaying the player like we did here.
Let's make the most of already being
in this demandeEtJoue method
to improve the algorithm
part of it.
What happens the player enters
a move that is invalid?
In the previous version, we simply
passed to the other player,
which is certainly not correct
Here, we will have to ask again
while the move is invalid
Asking again means having a loop.
Once again, we ask ourselves the question:
should this be a while loop,
or a do while loop?
In other words, do we start by asking the
question, then checking the condition?
Or do we start by verifying the condition,
then execute code?
So here of course, we start
by executing,
we start by asking for the move before
checking whether it is valid.
So it is a do while loop.
Let's write it.
do the whole bloc of our method
here, then  while.
while what?
Remember, what we want to do if the
move is not valid,
is to display the message, and we want
to repeat this entire interaction
here while the move is not valid.
So this is written while not valide.
There, we're pretty sure we have
finished. We save, we compile
and what happens?
The code doesn't compile because
of the scope of the valide variable here.
It is declared in this bloc here.
And so the valide variable
is not defined here.
So we must move the valide variable
which is declared in the loop,
and put it before the loop to
be able to use it
in the condition of the while.
Of course, if we do this, we must
be careful to note
that we now have two declarations of
valide.
One here, and one here.
So obviously, we should
correct this one and delete it.
Now, we just have one single assignment
in the loop.
There, our demandeEtJoue
method is now finished,
it compiles and should execute
correctly.
Let's end this episode with a last look
at the joue method.
To answer a quiz that was asked in a
previous episode
let's look at what we have to do to
correct this joue method.
The problem here is that we access
a row and column in an array
without actually checking that the column
we received is correct.
We could imagine that this test would
be done before the joue method.
We could for example have done it
right after asking the player
to enter a column number.
If he enters a number that is
too large, such as 100,
we could tell him that the move
is not valid.
But it is best to put this
sort of test
as close as possible to the danger
it protects against.
Which would mean putting it
in the joue method here,
as it receives a column number
as parameter.
Checking here would guarantee
that this column is compatible
with its use here as an
index in the grid.
So we will simply start
as usual, by writing the comment
and saying that if the column number
is larger than the size of the array,
then it means that the move
is invalid.
In Java, this is written like so:
If colonne (TN: means "column") that
we received as parameter
is larger than the size
of the grid,
so for example
grille[0].length,
then at that moment, we simply
return false
since the move is not valid.
There, this concludes this
episode.
All that is still needed,
to have a complete game,
is to implement the stopping
test
in the game's loop.
This will be the subject of
the next episode.