In the previous video, you saw
how to write
the main loop that allows the players
to play in turn.
All that was missing was the
break condition,
that is, what must be written here
so that the loop stops when one of
the players has won,
or when the grid is full.
So for the moment, we'll concentrate
on the case
where one of the two players
has won.
I'll therefore introduce a new
method
that I'll name 'estCeGagne' and
that I'll call like this:
I'll put the return value of my
'estCeGagne' method
in a variable
that I'll name 'gagne', of
boolean type.
To function, my 'estCeGagne' method needs
the grid
and the color of the player that
has just played.
I need to declare my 'gagne'
variable,
and I need to declare it before
the loop,
as I'm going to use it within the
loop's break condition.
It's of boolean type
and I can now use it to define
the break condition,
and we'll repeat the loop until
the player hasn't won.
We have to write this 'estCeGagne'
method,
which is probably the most
difficult part of our program.
There are many ways of writing
this 'estCeGagne' method,
and we propose the following
one.
We'll navigate through the grid
line by line and column by column
until we find a chip of the color
of the player that has just played.
Let's say for example that the red
player has just played,
and that we find this chip.
We'll start from this chip and navigate through the grid
in several directions,
horizontally, vertically, and
diagonally,
to count how many chips of the
same color
there are starting from this chip.
For example, if we consider
this direction,
we can count one, two, three,
four red chips,
we therefore know that the
player has won.
Instead, if we navigated through
the whole grid
and we've always counted less
than four chips,
we know that the player hasn't
won.
We can note that we
don't need
to consider all the directions
and in fact we'll content ourselves
to count the chips
in four directions only,
and we'll choose for example
upwards to the right,
to the right, downwards to the right,
and straigth downwards.
So why is it sufficient to consider
these four directions?
I said that we'll browse the
grid
line by line and column by
column.
Let's suppose once again
that the red player has
just played.
The first chip we'll find is
this one.
We'll first of all count the chips in
this directions,
we'll count a single chip,
this one.
The same goes for this direction,
and this direction,
there's only one chip in these
three directions.
In this direction, there are
two chips.
This isn't sufficient to
win,
so we'll continue navigating
the grid.
The next red chip that we'll find
is this one.
In this direction and this
direction
we'll count only two chips,
which isn't enough to win.
In this direction and this
direction,
we'll count only one chip,
which still isn't enough
to win.
We'll continue navigating the gris
until we reach this chip;
we'll continue counting the chips
in this direction
and this time we'll count one,
two,three, four chips
and we know that the player
has won.
To prove that the red player has just
aligned these four chips,
we can either start from this chip here
and go in this direction,
or start from this chip here and
go in this direction.
Therefore, we aren't obliged to
consider these two directions,
we can content ourselves of
only one,
and the same goes for the six
other directions.
We'll only look at this
direction
and not this direction.
In this direction and not this one,
in this direction and not this one.
We are left with four directions
to consider.
We now have to code this
strategy
by writing the 'estCeGagne' method.
Let me remind you that we call
the 'estCeGagne' method
by the following way,
for example.
We put the return value of the
'estCeGagne' method
in a variable of boolean
type.
And the method awaits a grid
and the color of the player that has
just played as parameters.
The method's header will simply
be the following.
Other strategies consist of navigating
through the grid,
which we'll do with the help
of these two for-loops.
And as we need the chip's
coordinates,
we'll use two standard for-loops
like this.
The ligne (= line) and colonne (= column)
variables will contain the disc's coordinates
from which we'll count the number
of aligned discs.
To simplify a bit the code,
I'll introduce a local variable that
I'll name 'couleurCase'
to contain this chip's color, which
is grille[ligne] [colonne].
If the cell's color is the same as
the player that has just played,
then I must count the chips
in the four directions in which
we are interested.
So, as it's a bit difficult to count
the chips,
well I'll introduce a method that
I'll simply name 'compte' (= count)
and that will do this task.
What arguments does the 'compte'
method need?
Well first of all, of course, of the chip,
the coordinates of the disc
from which we want to count the
aligned chips.
These coordinates are contained in the
'ligne' and colonne' variables.
And we need the direction in which
we want to count the aligned chips.
So how can we define this
direction?
Let's suppose for example that I want
to count the chips
diagonally to the
top-right.
In this case, to go from one
cell to another,
we'll have to subtract one from the
line and add one to the column.
Therefore, I'll use these two
values,
this minus one and this
plus one,
as the arguments for my
'compte' method,
to say that I want to go
to the top-right.
I'll send to my 'compte' method
the number of aligned chips
and if this number of chips is greater
than or equal to four,
then I know that the player
has won.
So why greater than or equal to four,
and not simply equal to four?
Well, that's simply because one can
win by aligning more than four discs.
So of course, I need to consider
the three other directions
and that will be written like this.
To count the chips horizontally, I won't
change the line,
and that's why I use zero as
argument here.
But the column will change, and I'll
go to the next column,
that's why I'll use the value plus
one as last argument.
Then, to count the discs diagonally
to the bottom-right,
to go from one cell to the other,
I'll add one to the line,
that's why I use the value
plus one here,
and I also add one to the column,
and that's why I use the
value plus one here.
Finally, there remains a
last direction.
To count the chips vertically
downwards,
I'll go from one cell to the other,
By adding one to the line, that's
why I have the value plus one here,
But the column won't change and I
use the value zero here.
If one of these four conditions is true,
then I know that the player has won.
It is sufficient that one of these
four conditions is true,
that's why I use an 'or' here.
And in this case,
I'll return everything to my method,
I'll close the curly braces I had
previously opened,
and if I get to this point of my
method,
it's because I've never passed
by here,
that is, I never found at least
four aligned chips,
and I know that in this case, the
player hasn't won yet.
So I'll return 'false' from my
method,
and as a good programmer, I'll
add comments
to explain the difficult points
of my method.
Of course, we still need to
write the 'compte' method.
Let me remind you that we'll call
the 'compte' method
like this, for example.
That is, the method will return
a number of discs,
that's why I'll use the 'int' type
to define the type of the result
value of the method.
The first parameter is the grid,
the two next parameters are the line
and the column
of the disc from which we'll count.
They are both of 'int' type,
and the two last parameters are the
direction for the line and the column
that I'll call 'dirLigne' and 'dirColonne',
as they are of the same nature,
and one refers to the line and
the other to the column.
I'll declare a 'compteur' variable
initialized with zero
to count the number of aligned
discs.
What must the 'compte' method
do exactly?
Well, it must start from the line
'ligneDepart colonneDepart',
and must browse the grid in the
given direction
starting from 'ligneDepart' 'colonneDepart'
while we find chips of the same
color as
the chip at 'ligneDepart'
'colonneDepart'.
So how will we achieve this?
Well, we'll use two variables that
I'll name 'ligne' and 'colonne',
that we'll respectively initialize with
'ligneDepart' and 'colonneDepart'.
And to go from one cell to the other,
at each loop cycle,
we'll add the value of 'dirLigne'
to 'ligne',
and the value of 'dirColonne'
to 'colonne'.
As we'll browse the grid
while we find discs of the
same color as the disc
that is at 'ligneDepart colonneDepart',
we'll use a while-loop.
During each cycle of the
while-loop,
we'll have found a new chip of
the same color
and we'll increment the 'compteur'
variable.
How will we write all this?
Well, we'll begin by declaring the
'ligne' and 'colonne' variables,
initialized with 'ligneDepart' and
'colonneDepart',
we'll therefore use a while-loop
with a break condition that depends on the
color of the disc at position 'ligne colonne',
and we'll continue while the color
of this disc
is the same as the color of the disc at
the position 'ligneDepart colonneDepart'.
During each loop cycle,we'll increment
the 'compteur' variable,
as we've found a new disc of the
same color as the first,
and we'll add 'dirLigne' and 'dirColonne'
to 'ligne' and 'colonne'.
By the way, note that I added
spaces here and here
to align the equal and plus
characters on these two lines,
that makes the code more
readable,
it highlights the fact that the variables 'ligne'
and 'colonne' are of the same nature.
When we exit the loop, it means
that we've found a disc
that wasn't of the same
color,
and we can return the value contained
in the 'compteur' variable.
Except that our method isn't
totally correct,
and maybe you see why.
As with the 'joue' method,
we could leave the grid,
that is, the 'ligne' or 'colonne'
variables
can take illicit values.
So, to correct this, I'll add
a few tests
to the while-loop condition.
I'll verify that the line is indeed
greater than or equal to zero,
and that it is less than the
number of lines,
and I'll add the same tests for
the column.
Finally, I'll add a comment
to describe what the loop does.
To conclude, I'll come back to my
'estCeGagne' method to note that
if the starting cell's line has the
value zero, one, or two,
it isn't necessary to look in this
direction, for example,
as we already know
that the player can't align
at least four discs.
If we start from the line two,
we know
that the player can align a
maximum of three discs.
The same goes when we start from
the right-side of the grid.
It isn't necessary to look in
this direction,
and the same goes when we start form
the bottom of the grid,
it isn't necessary to look
to the bottom.
Our 'estCeGagne' method does
more than necessary,
so I'll modify the code to avoid
counting the number of discs
when we are sure that there won't
be at least four aligned discs.
So, that will be written like this.
When we consider the direction
diagonally to the top-right,
to be able to align at least four
discs,
the line must be greater than or
equal to three.
And the column mustn't be
too big,
and, I'll let you verify when
you do it,
the column must be less than the
number of columns minus four.
When we look to the right
horizontally,
it is sufficient that the column
isn't great enough
and that it is, similarly, less than
the number of columns minus four.
When we look diagonally to
the bottom-right,
the line mustn't be too big, and as
with the column,
the line must be less than the
number of lines minus four,
and the column mustn't be too big.
And when we count the number of
discs downwards,
it is sufficient that the line is less
than the number of lines minus four.
Now, you can observe that I've
introduced a few repetitions,
as this expression appears
here and here,
and this expression also
appears twice.
I'll therefore introduce constants to
replace these repetitions,
constants that I'll logically name
'ligneMax' and 'colonneMax',
and which will avoid the repetitions.
Voilà, this time was really
the final version
of the 'estCeGagne' and 'compte'
methods.
We still have to handle the case
where the grid is full
without any of the players having
won,
and that's what we'll see in
the last video.