We have almost finished our case study
of our Connect Four game.
We now have 2 players
playing alternately
and we can determine if
one of them has won.
We just need to refine
the main program
so that it indicates which
of the 2 players has won
and to take into account a
tie between the players.
So this will be the topic of
this episode.
As a reminder, our Connect 4 game
at this stage
enables 2 players to play
alternately by placing disks:
player 'X' places a yellow disk
while player 'O' places
a red piece
during one round or loop.
This means that at the end
of each iteration of the loop
we can guaranty that the player's
colors alternates between yellow and red.
This continues until one of the two
players wins.
This program nevertheless
needs to be improved.
The first thing to do is that
when we exit the loop
which means that one of the players
has won,
to display which of the 2 is actually
the winner.
The second thing to do
is to consider the situation
where the 2 players continue placing
their disks without anyone winning
until the grid is filled
and then no one will
have won.
It is a tie.
This scenario is not anticipated
in the present program
which is not very good.
Let's start modifying our program
so that it displays
the winner.
So naturally, we have to add
to the code after the loop,
a certain number of instructions,
which will determine
the color of the player whose turn it is
when the loop is exited.
So if the color is yellow
this means that the winner
is the red player.
Why the red player and
not the yellow?
Well, if we examine
the last instructions that
we execute when we leave the loop
we see that they alternate the color
of the player.
If the color is alternated so that
the color at the end of the loop
is yellow,
which is our case,
this means that effectively, the
player who won is
the other color: red.
This explains why
we exit the loop with the color
yellow
and indicates that
it is indeed the
red player who has won.
So here to cover each possibility
in the other alternative case
we simply need
to display the fact
the winner is this time
the yellow player
which is player 'X' in our
modification.
So, now we have covered
each case.
Here we take care to comment
this test that is rather counter-intuitive
by indicating that beforehand we had
already changed the color of the player
which explains the reason
for this test here.
As we said in the beginnning
of this video,
we can also encounter situations
in which neither player wins
because the players have
filled the grid
without anyone getting 4 in a row.
Therefore we will have to
complete our code
so as to take into consideration
this situation as well.
That is to say, we will have to
leave the loop
not only when one party has
won (this is already done),
but also when the grid
is entirely filled,
which is not coded and which
corresponds to a tie.
What would happen
if we do not consider
the possibility of the gird to be full?
Well, what could occur is
that once the grid is filled
we ask a player to place
a token on a valid box of the grid,
which would be impossible,
and so we would enter an
infinite loop
without any likelihood
of anyone winning.
We wouldn't stop asking a player
to introduce a disk
which would be impossible
as the grid is all full
and so we could never
get out of the cycle.
This is obviously faulty for
a program like this
and we have to resolve this
error so that the program
runs smoothly in any situation.
The modifications to do to
our program
to test if the grid is filled
are quite intuitive:
we have to repeat this part
allowing the 2 players
to play alternately,
as long as neither has won,
which is already implemented,
but also as long as the grid is not filled.
This can be written easily
like this
by anticipating a method
"plein" (TN: means "filled")
which will let us test
if the grid is filled or not.
This modification will change how
the rest of the program runs.
Indeed, we will not be in
a one-track mode
where there has to be a winner,
but we also have a situation where
we exit the loop
without there being a winner, which
we will indicate accordingly.
Here, we will have to modify
our program
so as to include this scenario,
so then we test:
"Did we exit the loop because
a player won?"
and signal this duly,
as we did before
if the answer is "yes".
If the answer is "no", then
we have a tie
and we have to let the user know
with a relevant message.
So, now we have covered all the
possible situations.
Here is the code for the
method "plein",
so we will ask alternately the
red player and the yellow player
into which colomn he wants
to place his piece.
Suppose that it's yellow's turn,
if he decides to play in
the first column
then since it is filled
automatically
from the bottom up,
then this means we will
fill in this case
the very first position
of the grid.
This effects how the grid
is tested to see if it is full:
indeed, it is not necessary to test
each box of the grid
to see if they contain a color
or are empty
but we can simply test the last
line of the grid (at the top).
Indeed, if this row is filled,
this means that each box of the grid
is also already allotted a color
because the grid is filled
from the bottom up.
Therefore the grid is filled.
Let's examine how to
code this method "plein".
We saw from a methodological
point of view
that we we consider
coding a method,
we have to always ask
ourselves the question "what?"
"what does the method do?", "what
information does it need to work?"
"what does it return?".
These are elements that we have considered
quickly here
because the function is so simple
through how we anticipated
its utilization
in the principal program.
So we have anticipated that we will
invoke this method "plein" on the grid
and that it returns obviously
a boolean variable, no doubt.
This boolean
indicates whether the grid
is full or not.
This corresponds naturally to
this header of the method "plein".
Now that the "what" is clear,
we can now examine the question "how?".
"How to program the body
of the method 'plein'?"
We can use the algorithm that we
sketched earlier
that is that if we find
in the first line,
that is to say in the last line
according to how  the grid is filled,
an empty slot,
this means that the grid is not
full.
It's this procedure we
will implement.
First we will use a for-loop
iterating on the values
of the slots of the first line.
which is written "grille[0]",
and test if the cell considered
is empty
which would mean that
the grid is not full
and so we would exit the method "plein"
by indicating that the grid is not full with "false".
If we have to go through
all the cells of the first line
without finding any empty slot
then we leave the loop
which means in this case that the
grid is full
and "plein" has to return
the boolean "true".
Note that a frequent error for beginners
in this kind of situation
is to implement the algorithm
but in a wrong manner
by returning "false" if the cell is empty,
which is correct,
but then to return "true"
right afterwards,
which is obviously not the
correct procedure
that we want to implement.
Why?
Because we have to have
tested all the cells
of the first line of the grid
before determining that the
grid is indeed full.
And this cannot be known inside the
body of the loop
so we have to finish the whole loop
before returning "true".
We pay attention to these little details
that beginners tend to forget
but that are important in the end.
So, now we've finished programming
our application for "Connect 4",
of course, there are many ways of
programming this game
and we have only presented one
of them.
The goal of this case study was
to essentially show
how to take on programming
such an application
when you do it for the
first time.
Several key ideas:
first, always proceed from bottom up
start by identifying the essential types
of data needed,
and the main functions
before going into small details.
Each of the functionalities
and fundamental methods
can in turn be modularized
that is, can invoke other
more detailed methods
that will help it
do the tasks needed.
We saw that in coding
each method
it is preferable to have a certain
methodology,
and always ask the question
"what does the method do?",
"what information does it require?",
"what information does it return?".
An only then ask the question
"how?"
and think of the algorithms that
will allow you to do the wanted manipulations.
Finally we saw that it was fundamental
to work on the essential aspects
before working
on the aesthetics.
And an important point
is to systematically test as
you write your code and not
only at the end.
So, that concludes what we wanted
to teach you
in this case study
and we hope it will be useful
farther along when you will take on
similar programming challenges.