♪ (music) ♪
How are your infrastructures
functioning in the city?
How is your transportation system doing?
Is it working?
Is water running from your taps?
Is waste collected?
Is electricity produced
by renewable resources?
Do you have access to greens, and parks?
We are here at Geneva Railway Station.
Geneva is a minor city,
but it is a global hub,
important for corporations,
international organizations.
It is, therefore, crucial
that infrastructure operations
function perfectly,
especially transportation.
This creates the attractiveness,
the competitiveness,
and the quality of life
that the citizens deserve.
But providing excellent
infrastructure services is challenging.
Three big challenges can be identified:
money, time, and system.
Money is important
because it takes a lot of money
to develop the infrastructures,
it takes a lot of money
to maintain the infrastructures--
this money has to be found.
Time is important because infrastructures
take a long time to be built,
and they will be there for a long time.
This requires careful planning.
And system is important
because infrastructures
depend upon each other.
Housing depends on roads,
roads depend on energy,
and so we need a systemic approach
to deal with urban infrastructures
and urban infrastructure services.
State-of-the-art management
of urban infrastructure services is key,
but this management is challenging,
for a series of reasons.
The first reason is because operations
are often regulated.
The second reason is because there is
a lot of private-sector participation,
which requires coordination
between the public and the private.
The third reason is
the jurisdictional challenge,
because the city does not correspond
to the agglomeration,
and therefore public authorities
need to be coordinated.
And the fourth reason is
the systemic nature
of the infrastructures.
There's often an infrastructure provider
and a service provider
that has to be coordinated.
This is a self-paced course,
so you can enjoy your learning journey
about management
of urban infrastructures
at your own pace.
This edition of the MOOC will be open
from February 15, 2016 onwards.
In order to obtain
a certificate of this course,
the participants have to pass
four graded quizzes,
and complete four mandatory assignments,
plus a final exam.
In addition to the graded assignments,
students have the option
to write a 7 to 10 page case study
about management of energy,
or management
of urban transportation systems
in the city of their choice.
This optional case study will be graded
by way of a peer-reviewed
evaluation process.
If you decide to take up
this optional challenge,
you will be asked to review
the works of two of your peers,
in addition to writing the case study.
The best case studies will be evaluated
by our jury at IGLUS,
and the authors of the three best cases
will receive a tuition waiver to enroll
in our IGLUS Professional
Executive Program
as of Fall 2016.
Our course builds on a global action
research project called IGLUS.
IGLUS stands for Innovative Governance
of Large Urban Systems.
In this project, as in this course,
we work with a series of partner firms
and partner universities.
We are the Chair,
Management of Network Industries
at École Polytechnique Fédérale
in Lausanne, Switzerland.
We think that managing
urban infrastructures
is the challenge of the 21st century,
and we hope
that you will join this course,
and by doing so become part
of addressing this challenge.
♪ (music) ♪