Congratulations, you made
it through week 5.
In this last week, we learned
about assessment and planning
methods for municipal
solid waste management.
Let's briefly summarize the
main contents of the week.
We started the week by introducing
a planning strategy to integrate
biowaste management in the general
solid waste management strategy
of a municipality. Having a good
segregation of biowaste
is of utmost importance
for this integration.
This strategy consists of several
steps, such as framing
the problem, deciding objectives and
eliciting their weights, assessing
the performance of the selected
alternatives, and finally scoring them.
We then introduced the wasteaware
indicator set, as a comprehensive
and structured approach, which serves
to compare cities'performance
on solid waste management.
Here we see all the indicators
for the physical components and
governance aspects listed on the
left, and the score of 4 different
cities for each of these indicators.
Climate: such an important topic.
And of course the solid waste management
also has an impact on it, as we saw.
Waste management practices
generate greenhouse gases.
Nevertheless, we saw that there is
reduction potential, depending
on the management chosen.
In the past, several economic
mechanisms were established,
in order to trade emissions, such as
the Clean Development Mechanism.
And now, with new mechanisms
such as the Nationally Adapted
Mitigation Actions, or
NAMAs, this will continue.
And finally, our last module,
which you will probably still
have fresh in mind, gave us an
indication of the future role
of waste management. Linear
management of both biological and
technical materials should have
an end, and a shift towards
more circular patterns
should be achieved.
This is the last course module.
Chris, why don't you join
me for a last goodbye.
Thanks Imanol.
First of all, congratulations
and well done!
But now for a personal request.
We need your help.
During the entire course, you've
been listening to us from
behind the screen, and we
know a little about you.
We need your help with a last
important contribution.
Please tell us how you can,
and how you will be able
to make use of this gained
knowledge: in your job, or in the
development of your
professional career.
Thank you so much.
Use this knowledge.
Everybody can make a difference.
Goodbye.