going to run if it's eco mosca in this
lecture we will see how radiation
interacts with the interstellar and
intergalactic matter interactions occur
at all spatial scales and are analyzed
thanks to images in spectra giving
constraints on the physical conditions
of the gas and dust and cosmic clouds
the interstellar gas apart from the
primordial hydrogen and helium formed a
few moments after the Big Bang is
created by successive generations of
stars and is ejected into the
interstellar medium after the death of
high or low mass stars for low-mass
stars ie less massive than eight solar
masses planetary nebulae are formed
while for the stars with masses
exceeding eight solar masses a supernova
explosion occurs leaving spectacular
filaments as shown in the figure this
image shows the Crab Nebula Messier one
that is a result of a supernova
explosion visible even to the naked eye
in 1054 then the gas is recycled into an
interstellar medium in the galaxy like
this one Messi or 51 where the hydrogen
emission is well visible in the red in
the spiral arms of the galaxy the
hydrogen emission is created by the
ionized gas excited by the swarm of
young massive stars visible in the blue
in the arms of the galaxies apart from
gas and galaxies there is also dust that
absorbs background radiation this effect
can be seen here in the form of dark
trails through the arms of the galaxy
the background light is absorbed by dust
from this pics of gas and dust new
generations of stars possibly associated
planetary systems are formed let's see
in details what is happening in a nebula
the Carina Nebula shown here at optical
wavelengths some sources of ionization
can easily be identified like in this
place a small stellar cluster certainly
composed of young hot stars another
stellar cluster can be seen here
those stars ionize the surrounding gas
sit amet the gas divides and the protons
and the electrons possibly they will
recombine electrons fall back into the
lower energy level while at the same
time emitting photons with a range of
wavelengths each color indicates a
different emission line as it was shown
in previous chapters the density of the
gas is very low roughly one gas particle
per centimeter to the third power which
gives p equals 10-21 kilograms divided
by m to the third power there can be
great differences in the densities from
one nebula to another from one galaxy to
another this density corresponds to the
ionized gas that often produces emission
lines we find also dusty regions similar
to those shown before in a spiral galaxy
dust absorbs radiation in fact this
whole region is affected by dust
absorption mass densities in this kind
of region are even lower about ten to
thirteen particles per centimeter to the
third power which is 10 to 13 times
smaller than the gas density on the
other hand dust particles are much
heavier because the dust is composed of
atoms and molecules the mass density is
one of the order of ten to twenty three
kilograms divided by M to the third
power this means that there is 13 orders
of magnitude less dust particles than in
the gas but in mass density thus there's
only 100 times less massive per unit
volume than gas all we said previously
was about gas and dust in nebula let's
have a closer look at the milky way so
objects with much larger spatial scales
from this place to this other one in the
slide the distance is about 5
kiloparsecs and the previous slide the
scale was about tens of parsec here the
scale corresponds to the kiloparsecs
scale the nebula that was shown just
before as roughly this size quite small
comparing to the Milky Way on the other
hand thus extends over a large region
those areas correspond to dusty spots
that absorb the light coming from the
stars situated behind here are the other
dust regions appreciated in conclusion
that does in a gas intervene at all
scales let's take a look at what is
happening with the ionized gas that
recombines and emits radiation creating
something we can observe nebulizers here
we will assume a gaseous nebula composed
of hydrogen so as the simplify the
calculations of course a composition
could well be different in this kind of
clouds then here is a ionizing source
stars this ionizing source splits the
atoms of hydrogen in this case into
protons and electrons they do not stay
in this state they will tend to
recombine and emit light now we will try
to estimate the typical radius of a
nebula that isn't a strong run radius
enter the astronomer who calculated it
for the first time what we will try to
characterize is this limiting radius of
the nebula stromgren radius as always in
science there is an equilibrium there
are ionizing protons coming from the
source from the center of the nebula
then there are electrons that recombine
with the protons that were ionized by
the radiation field the flux of ionizing
photons is equal to the recombination
ratio of the proton electron pairs the
number of free combinations is equal to
the volume of the nebula 4/3 pi times R
3 times the number of available proton
electron pairs that is ne4 electrons and
NH 4 protons in this equation there was
also a constant that comes from quantum
mechanics and the origins of which is
not needed to be known here it is just a
physical constant that is equal to about
three times 10-13
centimeters three times s minus one for
a gas with a temperature around eight
thousand Kelvin which is a typical
temperature for diffuse Ned like we have
calculated the recombination ratio as
the function of radius the parameter
that we are interested in an electron
and proton density in the nebula now
let's calculate the number of ionizing
photons for the calculations we take a
hot start as an ionizing source with the
temperature of about forty-five thousand
Kelvin this star has a black body
spectrum with its luminosity peak in the
ultraviolet according to the wine law
lambda max is equal to 640 angstrom
which is in the ultraviolet part of the
spectrum where the photons carry a lot
of energy and so they can easily ionize
matter here we have a nebula composed of
ionized hydrogen before the calculations
let's recall a bit of nomenclature we
have talked a lot about hydrogen so
let's now present some notations it may
be that you are familiar with it so
treat it as a reminder if you have such
a notation 1h it stands for a hydrogen
nucleus a notation to H stands for a
deuterium nucleus in this case there is
one extra Neutron in the nucleus let's
move on to the atoms so we have now an
electron that we will note as h1 this is
an atom of neutral hydrogen the electron
in this atom is in its lowest possible
energy state with 13.6 EV it means that
in order to ionize a hydrogen atom 13.6
EV must be delivered in this case one
notes hii for the ionized hydrogen
earlier a notation H alpha H beta H
gamma etc was shown paying attention not
to confuse it with the notation that was
shown before those are the hydrogen
emission lines we can also write h2
which indicates the two hydrogen atoms
now form a molecule so beware of all the
different notations that is all for the
hydrogen nebula now let's recall that we
consider a single star with 45,000
Kelvin in the center of the nebula the
radiation peak is at 640 angstrom and
assuming that most photons belong to
that peak each photon has about the
energy E gamma equals hv then let us
imagine that all photons are indeed
emitted at the peak thus all photons
have precisely that energy the total
amounts to 1.5 for 10-5 j which
corresponds to 19 EV obviously those are
photons with an energy higher than the
ionization energy 13 point 6 eb it means
that if a star surrounded by hydrogen is
considered then with a good
approximation all the hydrogen and the
nebula is ionized because of the photon
flux carrying an energy higher than the
hydrogen ionized energy now we assume
that all the hydrogen is ionized and so
e equals NH and there is the same number
of electrons and protons this implies
that the equation for the recombination
ratio can be rewritten as a function of
the hydrogen atom density and it is
equal to the photon flux carrying an
energy at least sufficient to ionize the
atoms inverting this equation we find
the radius that is the limiting radius
in the equilibrium
the stronger and radius it will be equal
to three times the number of ionizing
photons over 4 PI alpha x + H square to
the power 1 / 3 this is the equation for
the stromgren radius it is given as a
function of the following values a
physical constant the density of the
nebula and the number of ionizing
photons the number of the ionizing
photons can be estimated in the easiest
way it is the stellar luminosity in the
center of the nebula physical / the
photon energy for a star with the
surface temperature t 45 thousand Kelvin
the luminosity is equal to one point
three times ten five solar luminosity
this implies that the number of ionizing
photons is equal to 12 6 10 49 photons /
s this gives an estimate of the number
of ionizing photons let's now estimate
NH 4 NH equals five thousand / cm3 the
nebula is relatively dense and the
stronger in radius is roughly equal to 0
point three parsecs this radius depends
on the number of stars in the nebula but
typically the stromgren radius is about
point 1 to 100 parsec for a typical
nebula in the Milky Way ionized by a
small stellar cluster this is the
order of magnitude of the signs of
ionized nebulae that can be found in the
Milky Way or in galaxies in general this
is a wonderful example of a nebula
illustrating the stromgren spear NGC 602
in a small magellanic cloud which is a
satellite galaxy of our galaxy here one
can see a group of blue stars in the
center of the nebula that ionizes the
gas as far as 50 parsec from the center
this is not implied that the nebula has
its limit at 50 parsec and that there is
no gas further away what it means is
that the photon flux produced by the
stars in the center of the nebula it's
not able to ionize the gas further away
than the stronger run radius now we will
look closer at the dust absorption here
you can see schematically represented
some dust grains which size is much
larger than the atoms or molecules it
could be compared to the dust that is on
a table when when does not clean at its
place or to the chalk left on the
blackboard for example let's take a
volume element that is characterized by
the length input and output surfaces in
the density taken in a following way
this is the numerical density not the
mass density so it gives the number of
dust grains per unit volume one can see
clearly that each dust grain obscures
the light that enters the volume element
each dust grain as a cross-section and
obscures a surface da this allows the
determination of the extinction
coefficient that is simply equal to if R
is the grain radius the cross-section of
the dust grains now it is possible to
estimate the fraction of the surface da
screened by all the dust grains this
would be simply DT the number of the
particles in the Box times the
cross-section
which we have called the extinction
coefficient so dt is equal to n times da
times d1 where one is the cylinder
volume times the cross section over the
total surface if this expression is
simplified one has the extinction
coefficient times the density times the
elements d1 this will be called the
optical depth tea this is a
dimensionless quantity that depends on
distances one can already see that team
x equals 1 corresponds to full
extinction because the obscured surface
is equal to da and so all the radiation
is absorbed this is the definition of
the optical depth let's see how to use
it in order to estimate the fraction of
flux that is lost if we have the
incident flux here in a given volume f
is the outgoing flux that is equal to F
plus DF f can be negative and will be in
this case as there is absorption D F
equals F times DT DT is the optical
depth or as it was called earlier the
fraction of the flux that is lost there
was a minus sign because of the losses
and so DF divided by F equals minus DT
this is a simple equation for which the
solution can be written as an
exponential with boundary condition that
is simply the incident flux the outgoing
flux varies with respect to the incident
flux t is the integral from 0 to the
distance of the observer
so it can't be integrated along the line
of sight up to the star at some distance
D here we have n times the extinction
coefficient times d1 if we assume that
there is on average n particles along
the line of sight we can simplify this
expression he would be and means times
the extinction coefficient times the
distance this is the result of the
integral with the assumption that the
number of particles can be approximated
by some mean value from the distant 02
the observed object at some distance D
so the integration is made from one
volume element to another the
integration of the flux that is lost by
a volume element because of the dust
grains between the source and the
observer the fraction of the flux that
is lost expense is called the extinction
rewriting the resulting formula f
depends on the distance of the observed
object so that FD equals f 0 times e TD
let's try to illustrate that on a graph
it is simply an exponential curve the y
axis represents the flux and the x-axis
the distance at distance 0 the flux is
equal to f0 this is the condition given
in the formula when T equals 0 the
exponent is equal to 1 so f equals F 0
then the flux is exponentially
decreasing at some distance D we have t
e when T equals 1 the flux is equal to
f0 divided by E which means that 1
divided by e times the flux f0 is lost
up to the optical path equal to 1
astrophysicists prefer to use magnitudes
let's take its definition observe
magnitude minus the intrinsic magnitude
before the absorption caused by the dust
along the line of sight from zero to the
distance D this is a situation in which
along the line of sight between the
observer and a star there is dust and
cylinders and nebula etc one has to
integrate the absorption along the line
of sight up to some distance D thus m- m
0 equals 2.5 times 10 g ft / f 0 using
the equation formulated before this is
equal to 2.5 times d but one has to pay
attention to 10 g e this is a decimal
logarithm and not a natural logarithm
one can see that m- m0 is positive what
implies that m is greater than m0
remember that the magnitude scale is
logarithmic there is a minus sign here
meaning that the observed source is seen
with apparent magnitude greater than M 0
which is the intrinsic magnitude before
the absorption this signifies that the
source has been absorbed and so fainter
than the original we've just talked
about absorption but this is not the
only effect present in a volume element
some photons that will be absorbed some
can be reflected back to the source some
reflected in an arbitrary direction it's
extremely important effect is called
scattering this
effect will not be described herein
detailed it will be qualitatively shown
else can during depends on the particles
radiation there are two types of
scattering when photons propagate
through dust they are scattered and the
same way fog would do the first type of
scattering is the my scattering it takes
place when the radius of the Grange is
much larger than the photons wavelength
in this case the extinction coefficient
is equal to the one given by the my
scattering which is proportional to
lambda minus 1 another property that is
this type of scattering is directional
it is not isotropic it means that whole
time do not scatter in a random
direction they'd rather scatter in a
direction that lies closer to the
incidence direction this is the my
scattering another type of scattering is
the Rayleigh scattering it takes place
when the medium consists of small
particles smaller than the wavelength
for this type of scattering the
extinction coefficient depends even
stronger on the wavelength as lambda
minus four real a scattering is
isotropic in conclusion if light is
scattered by large grains the scattering
is directional and is more efficient for
shorter wavelengths the dependence law
is lambda minus one the Rayleigh
scattering arises for small particles it
is isotropic it also depends on the
wavelength it is more effective for the
blue light than for the red light
because of the dependence of the
extinction coefficient as lambda minus
for both types of scattering are more
effective for shorter wavelengths the
consequence of the scattering can be
observed on earth both types of
scattering can be noticed on this slide
firstly the scattering that makes this
guy blue
you this is the scattering by Adams so
all the particles whose radius is very
small compared to the wave light the
wavelength is of the order of hundreds
or thousands of angstroms obviously it
is the case of the Rayleigh scattering
that is isotropic it was said that the
scattering is more effective for the
bluer light this is the reason why the
sky is blue and why there are no visible
structures the uniform blue color is
caused by the isotropic property now
what happens in the cloud the cloud is
composed of water drops so here we can
find rap lots of water with radii much
larger than the wavelength in this case
the leading process is the my scattering
that is directional this is the reason
why one can see obvious structures in
the cloud if the scattering was I so
traffic the structures would not be
visible in the clouds it works in the
same way for nebula that are also cloud
air is a reflection nebula m78 in the
constellation of Orion reflection or
diffusion nebula it is basically the
same in the center of the nebula there
are stars one can find some dusty
regions that absorb light there will be
an extinction coefficient is related to
these areas there are also some areas
where the light is scattered now to see
this in practice the spectrum of the
star is a blackbody spectrum the
spectrum of a nebula should be composed
of emission lines because of atoms that
can be ionized by stars entity
ionization they recombine and generate
emission lines but this is not the case
here those stars are not able to ionize
the surrounding matter instead the light
is scattered if the spectrum was taken
in this area it would be a blackbody
spectrum
the same spectrum at the one of the
stars eliminating the matter around them
that is why obtaining spectra of
astronomical objects is so important if
one has a spectrum that shows lines the
effects present in the nebula are not
the same as for the nebula that has a
black body spectrum in the latter case
there is light scattering while in the
former case atoms are ionized and then
they recombine what is the final balance
between the different processes in the
nebula there was light scattering and
the absorption that both are more
effective for shorter wavelengths and
implies two things the first one the
absorption is responsible for the fact
that the observer sees a source weaker
as if it was emitting less light also if
the light is absorbed or scattered more
effectively for shorter wavelengths and
implied that sources observed through
dust are reddened this is the
interstellar and intergalactic rending
this was the first conclusion now if one
wants to observe sources whose light is
strongly absorbed the observations must
be done in the infrared light with
longer wavelengths propagates through
matter more easily the observations are
not so simple because it may happen that
the source does not emit light at longer
wavelengths one has to adapt a means to
the goal of the observations at least as
far as observations through dust is
concerned they see let's look at the
quantitative description of renting and
its influence magnitude it was said that
the color of objects is measured using
the color index the intrinsic index it
will be called B minus v-0 and is equal
to b0 minus B 0 B is linked to be 0
through absorption which can be in turn
expressed as an optical depth this is
for the blue filter now for the V filter
which is rather than be one has two
magnitudes
both are affected by absorption
subtracting one equation from the other
Gibbs b minus V equals V minus v-0 minus
av- a be with a be greater than a V
because the blue light is absorbed
stronger as it was seen before this
equation can be rewritten as B minus v-0
minus a new term e be minus V that is
used to characterize the reddening of
stars e be minus V is the color excess
be minus V greater than B minus V 0
because a be greater than a B it was
shown that larger color indices
correspond to red stars smaller color
indices correspond to bloor stars
provided that the bluer filter is placed
on the left side of the index the
observed index is greater than the
intrinsic index what implies that the
observed source is reddened thanks to
the color indices and to the color
excess it is possible to quantify the
way in which the stellar objects are
written by dust in the interstellar and
intergalactic medium a direct
illustration of this effect a nebula in
fact a cloud composed of dust seen at
different wavelengths this image
corresponds to the optical wavelength
the limit in the blue light this image
was taken in near-infrared the
wavelength increases in this way across
the slide this is the infrared image one
can easily see that in the image with
the dust all the radiation from the
background is blocked and scattered by
the dust it is lost it does not reach
the observer when going further in the
near-infrared one can see more and more
stars near the edge of the nebula one
can see more
stars one can see more and more stars
when going to the center even more at
longer wavelengths in this image almost
all the stars can be seen through the
dust this is a cloud of dust in the
Milky Way or nard 68 that could be
delimited in this way this is an image
in false color with the visible light in
the blue channel the near-infrared and
the green channel and the infrared in
the red channel looking at this image
one can at once see a large cloud of
dust located along the line of sight to
the observer white constantly interacts
would matter thanks to these
interactions the analysis of the light
gives us valuable information the last
two lectures showed that this analysis
is quite delicate all the physical
processes at play must be taken to
account simultaneously continuous
absorption or absorption lines
continuous emission or emission lines
chromatic absorption reflection
scattering which in fact is also a
chromatic phenomenon also one needs to
consider chromatic effects caused by the
Doppler effect rotation thermal
agitation of molecules that sometimes
broaden the emission in absorption lines
only phenomena play a role at some point
an important role in our understanding
of astronomical objects