Tidal forces play a role in the formation
and destruction of stars.
They are present in all spatial scales:
in planets, comets,
stars and stellar clusters.
It is known that tidal forces can deform objects
as large
as galaxies.
We are familiar with the tidal forces on the
Earth
through the periodic motion of the oceans:
the tides, which gave their name to this force.
There are some dramatic manifestations of
the forces
in places such as the Breton site Mont Saint-Michel,
or when they cause the tidal bore
to the delight of surfers.
In this lecture, the origins of the tidal
forces will be described
along with some illustrations of their manifestation
on Earth,
but also elsewhere in the Solar System and
in the Universe.
How do the tidal forces work?
It is a differential acceleration at ground
level.
A differential acceleration due to the Moon
experienced at ground level.
We will seek how the Moon's gravitational
force
varies at the ground level with respect to
another point,
this reference point being the centre of the
Earth.
In order to illustrate the situation,
let's consider the Earth, and the Moon with
a mass m.
The moon is at the distance d from the Earth,
r is the radius of the Earth.
Let's calculate the tidal forces
at two different points on the Earth.
The observer is placed on the Moon's orbital
plane.
The arrow points in the direction
of the Moon
that has a gravitational influence on the
Earth.
The closer the Moon,
the stronger the gravitational field.
If the Moon is in this direction, it attracts
this side of the Earth
with some force, and the other side of the
Earth
with a force that is much smaller.
The centre of The Earth is attracted with
a force
that has an intermediate norm.
Three points are taken: A, B and C for the
centre of the Earth.
Now, we look for the Moon's differential gravitational
field
at a given point with regard to the same gravitational
at a different point.
It means that we look for the gravitational
field g
caused by the Moon at the point A minus g
caused by the Moon at C, for example.
gA - gC can be represented using vectors.
This is gA,
minus gC, that can be placed at this point
with the same norm as at point C.
Minus gC is also here,
and one can see that gC - gC is equal to zero.
It can also be represented at this point.
Now one can calculate
gA - gC and gB - gC
which is the tidal force,
the differential force that describes the
acceleration experienced at this point
with respect to the centre of Earth, or at
this point also with respect to the centre
of Earth.
Rewriting the equation using m - mass of the
Moon
gA = Gm/ (d + r)² , A is at distance d
(Moon - Earth distance) plus r - Earth's radius,
minus gC = Gm/d².
Earth - Moon distance is much larger than
the Earth's radius
so this expression can be developed into a
Taylor series
factorising the Gm/d² term.
With some further calculations
one soon finds - (2Gm/d³) * r.
The expression for the tidal force at A is
negative,
so the vector of this force is directed outwards,
it can be marked in this way.
This is the tidal force at A.
The same calculations can be done for B.
It can be noticed that for gB - gC, the force
will be directed toward the Moon.
Its norm can be calculated in the same way
as before,
hence, gB - gC = Gm / (d - r)²
Before, there was a plus in this place, now
the other side of the Earth is considered.
so it is -GC / d², it stays the same.
Computing the Tylor series
gives (2Gm/d³) * r with the plus sign.
Plus means the direction toward the Moon,
minus - the opposite direction.
There are two differential forces
that pull each side of the Earth.
Obviously, the differential force with regard
to C
is equal to zero.
To a first approximation, as the expansion
was limited to the first order,
those two forces
have the same norm but opposite directions.
The intensity of the tidal forces in the Moon's
orbital plane was shown.
Here we represent in black the Moon's orbital
plane.
This is the direction of the Moon.
Now, let's represent the Moon's gravitational
force
at different points of the globe.
One force is exerted here, a force at the
centre is weaker
because of the greater distance to the Moon,
another one is even smaller.
Obviously, the vectors are drawn larger in
order to
illustrate better the differences.
Then, we are interested in the points lying
on a line perpendicular
to the Moon's orbital plane,
a line like this.
One can draw the gravitational forces at those
points,
the vectors are tilted in this way.
Each arrow has several components.
If the difference between each vector at the
border of the Earth
and the vector at the centre is taken
one can find the differential forces that
were shown in the previous slide:
both directed outward with equal norm
but with opposite directions.
Those are the tidal forces in the Moon's orbital
plane.
Now, let's consider those three points.
This vector at the centre has a single component
along the Earth - Moon direction.
Those two vectors have two components.
Each of those three vectors is at the same
distance to the Moon.
Placing the x axis here and y axis there,
one can see that their x components are the
same,
meaning that this red vector
has the same norm as those two.
If one takes the difference between those
two vectors,
let's say that here we have the points D and
E,
point C at the centre,
the gravitational field of the Moon at point
D minus the same at C,
as it was shown on the previous slide,
the resulting vector has only the y component
of the gravitational force of the Moon at
point D.
The resulting vectors
can be represented like this.
The Moon influences the Earth in such a way
that the Earth
is stretched in the Moon's orbital plane and
then "crushed"
in the direction perpendicular to the Moon's
orbital plane.
The Earth is flattened,
the tidal forces have an influence on the
Earth's crust,
especially on the fluids on its surface - the
sea.
The Moon is placed in this plane,
and so the oceans are stretched on both sides
of the Earth,
they undergo the force toward the centre of
the Earth
in the direction perpendicular to the Moon's
orbital plane.
This has a direct influence on the motions
of the oceans
around the Earth.
If the Earth-Moon system was isolated,
the tidal forces would have the directions
as indicated,
and obviously, the oceans would follow this
motion -
there would be two liquid lobes on the Earth's
surface.
The description was for the tidal forces due
to the Moon
but, obviously, the same effect is present
due to the Sun.
The intensity of the tidal forces caused by
the Sun
is weaker.
Clearly, depending on
the position of the Moon with respect to the
Earth and the Sun,
the intensity of the tides changes.
In this situation, one has what is called
neap tide
caused by the combination of the tidal forces
originating
from the Moon and the Sun, both effects being
perpendicular.
Moon rotates around the Earth in 28 days,
Earth around the Sun in 365 days.
It means that
the changes in the tidal forces caused by
the Moon are much faster
than the changes of the tidal forces caused
by the Sun.
In this situation, the combined effect of
the tidal forces caused by the Moon and the
Sun
creates spring tide.
Both lobes created by the tidal forces of
the Moon and the Sun overlap.
Once more the neap tide, and then the situation
with the full moon,
as only this side of the Moon is illuminated,
we have a spring tide once again.
For the full moon and new moon we have spring
tides.
For the waxing and waning quarter moon
there is a neap tide.
The tidal forces influence the motions of
the oceans
which in turn influence the Earth's rotation.
Indeed, when the Moon rotates around the Earth
the oceans tend to "follow" it.
Due to the tidal forces the oceans take an
ellipsoidal shape
that follow the Moon's trajectory.
In this motion, the oceans
rub the earth's crust,
causing the release
of energy
in the form of heat.
The Earth looses rotational energy, and so
angular momentum.
This implies that the Earth
slows down its rotation.
This is not the only consequence;
while the Earth is slowing down, the Earth
- Moon distance increases.
This effect is shown on the next slide.
Considering the Earth - Moon system as isolated,
the Earth at this place, and the Moon here.
Let r be the Earth - Moon distance,
m the mass of the Moon and ω its angular
velocity
around the Earth.
This system is isolated
meaning that its total angular momentum is
constant.
Due to the friction of the oceans upon the
terrestrial crust,
the Earth looses angular momentum
increasing at the same time the angular momentum
of the Moon,
as the total angular momentum is conserved.
The Moon's angular momentum
is equal to L= mωr².
As it was said before, the angular momentum
of the Moon increases
so L dot is positive.
Now, it will be shown how the fact that L
dot is positive implies
that r dot is positive, meaning that the Moon
increases its distance from the Earth.
Let's write the angular momentum of the Moon,
its mass,
angular velocity, the square of its orbital
radius.
It was said that L dot is positive.
Let's take the time derivative of L.
Now, using Kepler's laws,
particularly the third law,
one can write that ω²r³ is equal to a constant.
Computing the time derivative
which is zero, and factorizing this expression
leads to an ωr term here
and finally one gets 2ω dot r² + 3ωṙr
=0.
Obviously, neither ωr nor r is equal to zero,
it is the whole expression that equals zero,
implying ω dot r² = -3/2ωṙr.
This equation will be used to replace ω dot
r²
in this formula.
This leads to L dot equals m times
-3/2ωṙr + 2ωṙr. Finally, L dot = 1/2mωrṙ.
It was said that L dot is positive, so looking
at this expression
one sees that if m, w and r are positive
ṙ also has to be positive.
If ṙ is positive it implies that r increases
and so the Moon moves away from The Earth.
This distance increase can be measured
thanks to the retroreflectors placed on the
Moon
by the astronauts during the Apollo 11 mission
in 1969.
The property of those retroreflectors is that
they reflect the light
exactly in the incidence direction. If one
aims at them
with the beam of a laser from the Earth it
is possible to measure the Earth - Moon distance
very precisely by simply measuring
the time it takes for photons to make their
return journey.
In practice, the beam of the laser light is
sent from a telescope,
photons are reflected and then collected by
the same telescope
after around two seconds.
Thanks to this measurement it is possible
to deduce that the change
of the Earth - Moon distace is equal to about
3,8 cm per year.
In the Solar System, Io, one of the four satellites
of Jupiter,
show an exuberant volcanic activity
due to the tidal forces of Jupiter.
Its surface is strewn with volcanoes.
Of the four galilean satellites, Io is the
closest moon to Jupiter
and also the one that has the most eccentric
orbit.
The tidal forces regularly compress
and dilate the rocky mantle, causing it to
melt.
The result is a collection of volcanoes on
the satellite's surface,
and some of them, like the volcano Pele shown
here,
eject matter fast enough
that it overcomes the satellite's gravitational
field and escape.
In the next lecture, we will have the opportunity
to see
that the tidal forces can not only cause the
rocky mantle to melt,
but may also cause the dislocation of the
satellite,
or even dislocate a celestial body in general.