Let's revise what we
learned this week.
On this third week, we focused on
the treatment of organic waste.
We learned the basics of two very
common organic waste treatment
technologies, namely composting
and anaerobic digestion.
Remember, composting is a controlled
decomposition of raw organic
material into compost, which is
carried out by microorganisms
in the presence of oxygen.
We distinguished the active phase,
when temperatures can reach
up to 70 degrees and thermophilic
bacteria are active, and the
curing phase, when both temperature
and oxygen consumption drop
and mesophilic bacteria are active.
In a different module, we covered
the main important operational
parameters that need to be considered
when composting is carried out.
These are: Carbon/nitrogen ratio,
particle size and porosity,
moisture content, pH, and
temperature and climate.
We then introduced different
composting technologies which are
commonly used in low- and
middle-income countries.
Do you remember their names?
For instance, which one is the
one on the bottom right, or the
one on the top left?
I hope you remember!
We compared these 5 technologies
regarding 5 different criteria:
Investment and maintenance cost,
space and time required,
as well as labour needed. In order
to provide you with a more hands-on
feeling of composting, we introduced
2 very interesting study cases.
One from Dhaka in Bangladesh,
shown on the picture on the left,
and one from Temesi, Indonesia,
shown on the picture on the right.
We then moved to learn about
anaerobic digestion, as a treatment
technology for biomass.
Anaerobic digestion is a collection
of processes, where, similar
to what happens during the
composting, microorganisms break
down biodegradable material. However,
in this case, this happens
in the absence of oxygen.
Anaerobic decomposition happens in
a 4-step biochemical process,
which happen partly simultaneously.
These are: hydrolysis, acidogenesis,
acetogenesis, and methanogenesis.
This is an interesting technology,
because it generates methane,
which is flammable and can be
used as source of energy.
Similar to composting, the anaerobic
digestion also has important
operational parameters that
need to be considered.
In this case we have: feedstock
characteristics, such as total
solids or volatile matter content,
organic loading rate, pH,
temperature, hydraulic retention
time, carbon/nitrogen ratio,
and particle size. We then saw
different anaerobic digestion
technologies, which are suitable
for a low- and middle-income
country context; all of them wet,
continuous feeding, and mesophilic.
What about their names?
Do you remember them?
We then proceeded to learn some
hints on how to operate and
maintain anaerobic digestion plants.
We looked at how to dewater, store,
and make use of the produced biogas.
And we also discussed important
criteria, favouring the choice
of anaerobic digestion as
a treatment technology.
And finally we learned how to
calculate the volume of a fixed-dome
reactor for the example of a
school with 250 students.
In the coming modules, we will
introduce some more innovative
technologies to treat organic waste.
See you then!