Hi.
Welcome to this module where
I'll present a composting case
study from Bali, Indonesia.
Welcome to this module where
I'll present a composting case
study from Bali, Indonesia.
As you can see, I even put on my batik
shirt for this special occasion.
First of all, I would like
to thank David Cooper.
He is the initiator of the Temesi
recycling center that we'll
be talking about, and he provided us with
most of the background information.
In Indonesia, the island of Bali
is most famous for its beautiful
nature, landscape and beaches.
Given this situation, Bali is also
Indonesia's primary travel destination.
But tourism, littering, lack of
appropriate waste management
service are jeopardizing
this pristine situation.
Waste is often burned at the
roadside, disposed indiscriminately
in the countryside,
rivers, and canals.
Thus polluting beaches
and even coral reefs.
The Rotary Club of Bali in Ubud
started addressing this problem
of waste, and sponsored a waste
recovering facility in Temesi,
which is in the regency of Gianyar,
where also the city of Ubud is located.
In 2004, a pilot facility for
waste recovery with a capacity
of about 4 tons per day was
built in the village of Temesi,
on the old landfill site.
At this pilot facility, the composting
procedures were learned and optimized.
A state of the art research station
and a fully equipped laboratory
were also established at that pilot
site, and they also received
international academic support
by visiting researchers.
This pilot facility operated
until June 2007, and had already
gained wide local and international
attention, and thus of course
raised high expectations for a
future large scale facility.
By 2007, they then felt that all
required knowledge and experience
had been established to be able
to expand the capacity from
4 tons to 60 tons per day.
But they did this stepwise.
In 2008 the first phase of such
a large facility with a waste
processing capacity of 30
tons per day was completed.
Then, in the second half of 2009,
an expansion to a final 60
tons of waste per day began, and it
was operational in January 2010.
The old pilot plant area was
converted into an environmental
park and an environmental
education center.
This is the layout of the recycling
center: a roofed area covers
a large part; the waste separation
area; the shredding area;
the composting area;
and the sieving
and bagging area.
The roof is to avoid heavy
rainfalls in the rainy season and
keep the rain out of
the composting heaps.
Here you can see this large roofed
area, and also the delivery
of waste at the bottom
left in this red truck.
Temesi's focus lies on organic waste.
Given the waste characteristics
in Bali, 85% of this waste is
organic and biodegradable.
This organic fraction is
processed into compost.
After arrival of the waste at
the site, the waste is sorted
by a cooperative of recyclers.
The recyclers separate 85% of the
organics and 7% of other recyclables
from the waste.
The recyclables are sold to
nearby agents and middlemen.
And the organics are sold to
the Temesi facility, at 45,000
Indonesian rupiah per ton.
That's around 3. 3 US dollars.
About 8% are residues, not organic,
and of no recycling value.
These are disposed of at
the landfill close by.
If the biodegradable waste has large
components in it, these are shredded.
Then the biowaste is piled to
large heaps called tables.
The tables are turned with a
front loader every two weeks.
The compost tables are actively aerated
by radial centrifugal air blowers.
It showed that axial propeller fans
did not give the expected results.
During this whole active composting
period, which lasts around
3 months, the composting parameters,
temperature, oxygen and
moisture, are always measured.
The compost is left for
another 1 month to mature.
So finally after a total period
of 3 to 4 months, the compost
is sieved and bagged for sale.
Main customers are the tourism
industry, hotels for their gardens
and parks, but also landscapers
and home gardeners.
This scheme summarizes the
treatment steps: starting off with
waste separation, receiving the
biodegradable fraction, shredding
if the components in the waste
are too large, piling the waste
onto heaps, here called tables,
active aeriation of these tables,
and turning every 2 weeks and 1
additional month for maturation,
then sieving and bagging with
quality control also at the end.
One important factor is also
the education center.
It often receives schools and other
visitors, to create awareness
of the waste issue and
educate on recycling.
So much for the technical details.
But there are also other factors
that make this case so successful.
A major milestone of the project
was to transfer the ownership
and management of the facility
to a new foundation.
This was in December 2008.
What was created is a private
public partnership: the Yayasan
Pemilahan Sampah Temesi.
That stands for Temesi Waste
Separation Foundation.
It is firmly anchored in the village
and the village administration.
Also, vulnerable women have an
equal opportunity to participate
in the project.
It is a declared employment policy
of the project to give priority
to the needy.
Then, since August 2009, Temesi operates
with a quality control system.
It ensures product quality, work
discipline, and consideration
of consumer satisfaction.
It has a quality manual, operating
procedure, and work instruction manual.
From an economic perspective, Temesi is
a registered CO2 mitigation project.
It obtains carbon credits,
which have a certain price.
It has a partnership with a large
international travel agency,
where the customers of the travel
agency can compensate their
CO2 emissions through a voluntary
compensation fee, buying these
carbon credits for Temesi.
For the compost sales, main
customers are the tourism industry,
the hotels for their gardens and
parks, but also landscapers
and home gardeners.
Temesi is reported to be
economically sustainable.
If the compost can be sold at
410,000 Indonesian rupiahs per
ton, that's around 30
US dollar per ton.
All in all, the Temesi site
recycles 92% of the waste, which
extends the lifespan of the landfill
by more than a factor of 10.
Developing this recycling center
and compost facility had a
large impact not only on the
environment, by transforming the
old disposal site into a nice
recycling center, into a well-managed
and attractive recycling facility.
This activity also shows that you can
create employment opportunities,
and it shows that improvements are
possible and waste management
is not a dirty and polluting activity.
In fact, due to its success, the
facility received various awards
and recognitions nationally and
internationally, for its performance
and its sustainability.
Well, that was the composting case
of Temesi, in Bali, Indonesia.
Let's summarize a few
important aspects.
First of all, aspects of
technical sustainability.
Simple, functional, technical
approaches were used.
They started small and learned
on the way to larger scale.
They also put a strong focus on
always ensuring quality of the
process and quality of the product.
They also had the aspect of social
and organizational sustainability,
by integrating it into the village
setting and creating employment
opportunities for the vulnerable, the
aspect of economic sustainability
by ensuring a market demand for
the compost, and the element
of obtaining additional revenues
through the carbon credit scheme.
In the next module, we'll look at
other biowaste treatment approaches,
besides composting, so stay with us.