Welcome.
I'm Linda Strande.
I'll be your host for
this introduction
to Fecal Sludge
Management.
I am an environmental
engineering scientist
at Sandec at Eawag.
My focus is on the
management of excreta,
waste water and sludge
in low and middle
income countries.
This course is part of a
4 part series by Sandec:
Sanitation, Water and
Solid Waste for Development.
In this course we will
teach you about how to
apply concepts of
sustainable fecal sludge managment
as a component
of achieving city-wide sanitation.
The target audience
for this course is you
because by being here you've already
shown interest in the subject
and by doing so I'm going to assume
that you're already aware
of the global relevance
and need for
sustainable sanitation
solutions.
A general background
in environmental engineering
urban planning
or natural science
might help to fully
benefit from this course
but to accomodate a wide
audience including anyone
having enthusiasm for
the topic,
we have provided additional
resources throughout the course.
If you would like to learn more,
learn more indepth
or get more up to
speed on a topic,
the possibilities
are endless.
Our mutual goal
is achieving
global access
to sanitation.
As one part of achieving
city-wide sanitation
this course focuses
specifically on
fecal sludge management
in urban areas
of low and middle
income countries.
Specifically what happens
from the time that onsite systems
like pit latrines or
septic tanks become full.
How are they emptied?
How is that sludge transported
away from the community?
How is it treated
and then safely used for
resource recovery or disposal?
We will address immediate solutions
for getting excreta
safely out of communities
but with a long-term vision
of developing new
and innovative solutions
that have
global relevance.
Before telling you
more about this course,
let me tell you
a bit more about myself.
My profession was previously called
Sanitary Engineering
or Public Health
Engineering.
The goal of Sanitary Engineering
is the safe removal of human waste
from communities while
Public Health is by definition
a mulit-disciplinary science
with the goal of disease prevention
achieved through engagement
and education of society;
both communities and individuals
and organizations;
both public and private.
Hence in my profession
we need to engage technology but as
Sanitary and Public Health Engineers
we have to think beyond technology
in a multi-faceted approach
to develop long-term
sustainable solutions
that include community health,
environmental health,
behavior change,
economics and public policy.
This is my motivation for
the approach in this course
which stresses that technology
on it's own is not a solution
and acknowledges the importance
of an integrated approach
which also builds on
the approach of the book
Fecal Sludge Managment;
Systems Approach for
Implementation and Operation
of which I am an editor and author.
The need for Fecal Sludge
Management is not new.
The focus on developing
solutions that work is what is new
and this is an exciting
time in the field.
It is rapidly growing
hence we engaged with
practitioners and scientists
around the world
to provide updated information
examples and case studies
in addition to the
basis provided by the book.
There is still a lot of work
to be done but
research and implementation
are filling knowledge gaps.
This course provides
an introduction to the topic
with the goal of
providing you with the framework
so you can dive in
further on your own.
Although it's an introduction
at the same time it is quite dense.
To keep your learning
as active as possible
we will provide weekly wrap up
to summarize important points
and introduce the coming topics
in video questions
and opportunities for feedback,
a discussion forum,
additional resources
for self-guided learning,
3 quizzes
and a final exam.
This course is taught by me
together with Moritz Gold
an engineer who has worked with me
on the research and development
of solutions for
fecal sludge management.
We will also have guest lectures
from 2 of our colleagues.
Charles Niwagaba from
Makerere University
in Kampala, Uganda
and Philippe Reymond
from the Strategic
Environmental Sanitation
Planning Group
at Sandec.
To assist in your learning,
learning objectives are provided
for  each module
together with
these overall learning
objectives for the course.
Following this course,
you will have an understanding
of the importance of
fecal sludge managment
and what is currently lacking;
know fundamentals of
an integrated approach to
fecal sludge management
that includes technology,
management and planning;
be able to identify required
information for the
design and selection
of technologies;
understand managment and
planning approaches that help ensure
sustainable solutions;
be able to explain current research
and innovations in
fecal sludge management;
and discuss how to approach the
implementation of solutions.
This is how the
5 week course is structured:
Before you can do problem solving
you have to do problem finding
so we will start out
the course in week 1
by showing you the problem
and then in subsequent weeks
buildup knowledge to be
able to work on it
and make sound decisions
in deriving solutions.
We will start out with an
introduction to fecal sludge
and fecal sludge management
including the importance of
an integrated approach,
what is currently lacking,
what weak links
in the service chain are
and some examples of what
are and are not working.
How do you build something
when you don't know what to build?
In week 2 we will introduce
fundamental knowledge
for understanding the treatment
of fecal sludge
and that is necessary for
the design and selection
of treatment technologies based on
an engineering design approach
including treatment objectives,
mechanisms, resource recovery
and quantification
and characterization.
In week 3 we will introduce examples
of established technologies
for the treatment of fecal sludge
including the treatment processes
operation and maintenance requirements
and engineering design parameters.
Sanitation solutions in
low income countries
do not rely on
technology alone
and are prone to failure if an
integrated approach
that includes technology,
management and planning
in parallel
is not implemented.
So in week 4
we present the full picture;
in addition to technology,
aspects that need to be considered
to help ensure
sustainable solutions.
Week 5 will then provide examples of
current research
and innovations in technology to
provide you with a solid understanding
of the most up to date options
and what needs to be considered
for further development
and implementation;
including with a case study of
how all of these principles
have been applied
in one city.
Maybe you will find it frustrating
that we're not here
to tell you the answers but
there is not a right answer
other than public health.
You need to be an innovator.
We want to challenge you in this
course to have a curious mindset
and be open to
the unknown.
Our goal is to inspire you
to understand the problem
and then think about
ways to address it.
Up to this point there's been
a relatively small group
of people working on the topic
and now we want to engage
all of you collectively.
What solutions can you come up with?
We will ask you to think about what
can you do in your city
and contribute to an ongoing
discussion in the forum.
So please commit to participating
in the entire series
Each week presents a different theme
all of which is equally important
in understanding the topic
and the way forward.
So thanks for joining and
looking forward to seeing you in class.