Is city wide faecal sludge
management
just a pipe dream?
Like anything that is accomplished
at a city wide scale,
faecal sludge management requires
planning and management
for a sustainable implementation.
But at the same time, we need to
think of steps to start taking now.
We can't wait for years until
a city wide sanitation plan
has been developed and implemented,
and find a way to fully fund it,
then wait to get buyin
from all the stake holders...
We can't wait for all that before
we start to take the first step.
So in this module, I'm going
to share with you
now what's currently working
in 3 different cities.
Following this model, you'll be able
to distinguish differences
in faecal sludge management among
the 3 presented cities
and identify examples of what is
and is not working
in the service chain of each city.
In faecal sludge management,
we are coming up with solutions
for existing cities
and for the current situation.
So we need to be able to adapt
to the specific local situation
and most likely
no 2 solutions will look the same.
We need to distinguish between solutions
we can start to implement now
to manage the current sludge crises
And the most optimal and
sustainable solutions
that we can continue to strive
towards in the future.
In this model, I'm going
to focus on Hanoi, Vietnam,
Kampala, Uganda, and
Toyokawa, Japan.
I will introduce you to
the current reality
of how faecal sludge management
is evolving in different regions.
And what is working
in these cities
that is better than many
other cities.
But what are still some of
the remaining challenges?
Vietnam, is a unique situation.
Since 1996, the building code
has stipulated
that any new construction
includes septic tanks.
In Hanoi, the access
to improved sanitation
is greater than 95%.
So the building code requires
septic tanks
but, it does not account for
the emptying of faecal sludge
which is also the reason,
public entities
do not have strategies in place
to manage it.
In fact, septic tanks are typically
constructed under the house
without access.
And so a hole needs to be made
in the floor of the kitchen
to access the tank if sludge
is going to be removed.
This is what it looks like.
After several years
of operation,
sludge accumulates
in septic tanks.
If it is not removed, it results
in emergency situations
such as toilets backing up
into houses.
This demand has resulted in private
emptying transportation companies
springing up to meet
this need.
In Hanoi, there are now
over 40 private companies
with over 100 trucks.
So far, it sounds reasonably
efficient and effective
for faecal sludge management,
right?
Everyone has septic tanks, there's
tons of companies and trucks
running around to empty them.
The law originally didn't
plan for that.
The private industry stepped
in and filled the role.
But unfortunately, that's not
exactly the whole picture.
What happens to the faecal sludge
after it's emptied?
Collection and transport
companies are official
and legally registered
companies.
And they have the right
to empty septic tanks
but they do not actually have
the right to discharge that sludge.
In fact, that's because there's
no designated place
within the city, for these private
companies to discharge.
So the service chain just
stops there
and the trucks just dump the sludge
wherever they can find a place.
So virtually all
the faecal sludge
ends up directly
in the environment.
This is illustrated in the shift
flow diagram of Hanoi
prepared by SANDEC.
It shows in green, what
percentage of excreta in the city
is safely managed.
And in red, what percentage
is unsafely managed.
However, as of last year,
there is a new decree in place
for the regulation of sludge.
And faecal sludge,
is specifically mentioned
as one type of sludge
in this decree.
Changes are not yet apparent
but this obviously takes some
time to figure out
after instituting the legal
framework.
It is very positive, that
the Vietnamese government
has officially recognised
the need
to manage faecal sludge.
And now, people understand
the importance at a political level.
Certainly, with such a strong
government structure,
changes will start to happen.
Okay. And now, moving
to Uganda.
Most people in Kampala also
have access to a toilet.
However, that may mean
30 people are sharing it
and it's not actually clean
enough to be used.
Around 80% of the population
are served by on site systems.
Of these, 70% are
pit latrines.
About half lined,
and half unlined.
And the other 30%
are septic tanks.
To collect and transport all
this faecal sludge
there are around 70 privately
owned trucks operating
that belong to 2 well organised
pit emptyers associations.
There are also 6 manual
emptying businesses
using the gulper, working together
with Water For People.
KCCA, the Kampala Capital
City Authority
wants to formalise the faecal sludge
collection and transport sector
and this is high
on their agenda.
And there is also an operational
treatment plant
to deliver all that
faecal sludge to,
which is operated by NWSC,
the National Water and
Sewage Corporation.
2 years ago, the Lubigi Faecal
Sludge Plant opened up
with a designed capacity of 400
cubic metres per day.
NWSC is also forward in
thinking of solutions.
For example, they had this tender
out for private companies
interested in the design, build,
and operation
of waste energy business models
at their treatment facility.
There's also lots of applied
research being conducted
by the Universities, research
institutes including SANDEC,
NGOs, and NWSC.
Here you see research on
increasing rates of drain
generating fuel from faecal
sludge for use in the kiln.
An optimisation of
collection logistics.
These are pictures of the pit
emptyers association.
Another thing NWSC has done
is set the fee for discharge that
collection and transport companies
have to pay, low enough
and is much cheaper than what
they charge households.
So the incentive of trucks
for illegal dumping
is quite low.
In addition, NWSC
provides space at their
treatment plants
to locate their associations
and park their trucks.
So what are the challenges still
being faced in Kampala?
This is the SFT for Kampala
also prepared by SANDEC.
We see safely managed
excreta at 48%.
And unsafely managed
at 52%.
There's not enough treatment
capacity.
The Lubigi Treatment Plant was
already operating at capacity
within the first month
it was built.
To address this,
NWSC reopened the Bugoloobi
Waste Water Treatment Plant
for discharge of
faecal sludge
which is not ideal as it's now
over capacitated,
but much better than the
alternative of illegal dumping.
In good news, Bugoloobi
is under renovation
and there are 2 more faecal
sludge treatment plants called for
in the sanitation master plan.
One of which, is in
the planning phase
but not yet in the
construction phase.
Japan is a country
where on site
and centralised sewer based
solutions  have evolved in parallel.
Japan can be held up
as an example
of how faecal sludge
management can work
as a long term solution.
There is an effective system of
collection and transport in place
with discharge to treatment
plants subsidised.
There are well organised and
functioning treatment plants.
30% of Toyokawa is served
by on site systems.
And 100% of excreta is
safely managed
as shown in this SFT, prepared
by Professor Hidenori Harada
of Kyoto University.
So why does faecal sludge management
works so well in Japan?
Due to the enabling environment.
There's a system of laws
and enforcement in place
to ensure that every year,
on site systems are inspected
and maintained by a licensed
service provider.
Collection and transport companies
are licensed and regulated.
Legal discharge of faecal
sludge is subsidised.
The installation and manufacture
of on site systems
is regulated and as our on site
discharge standards.
So what has generated the successes
in all 3 of these cities?
We see that there is support
and acceptance
of the importance of sanitation
and now faecal sludge management
at the governmental level.
In Hanoi and Kampala,
the municipalities are willing
to look for new
and alternative solutions,
which is critical.
They have to be leaders to implement
successful solutions
as there are not a lot of
models of success to follow.
This is in combination
with strong participation
by the private sector
which is now being acknowledged
by the government.
So even though these governments
are having to retrofit solutions
to their existing situations,
they are managing to piece together
city wide approaches
which can be implemented
and then improved upon.
For more information on SFTs,
please visit the SFT promotion
initiative project
posted on the susana website.
And also watch the model
shift flow diagrams
in our MOOC on planning and
design of sanitation systems
and technologies.
In this module, you learned
about differences
in faecal sludge management in
Hanoi, Kampala and Toyokawa.
Examples of what is,
and is not working
in each of the cities,
and we're introduced to
the shift flow diagrams
illustrating safely and unsafely
managed excreta
for each of the cities.
Thanks for joining,
see you next time.