This is an F diagram.
It is called that
because there 6 important
"F" words covered in the diagram.
They are feces, fingers,
flies, fields, food and fluids.
Do you know what these 6 F words
have to do with treatment objectives?
You'll learn about that
in this module.
Following this module
you'll be able to name
different treatment objectives,
relate health and environmental
impacts to these
treatment objectives
and understand that there are different
levels of appropriate treatment
depending on end-use
of treatment products.
The F diagram depicts fecal oral
routes of contamination
which is what we need to prevent
to ensure public health.
Fluids, if excreta contaminates
drinking water,
fields, if excreta contaminates
food crops,
flies, as flies are vector.
They are attracted to both
feces and food resulting
in cross contamination
and fingers; not adequately
washing your hands
before touching food
or eating.
Our number 1 goal in
Sanitary Engineering
and Fecal Sludge Management is always
the protection of public health.
Protection of environmental health
is also very important
and as shown in the
F diagram, these first 2 goals are
often very closely
linked together.
If excreta is contaminating
the urban environment,
then it is a
public health risk.
A third goal that is important to
meet whenever possible
is resource recovery
from treatment products
which is also tied closely
to the first 2 objectives.
Resource recovery is covered in more
detail in other modules.
If it's not possible, then safe
disposal is a requirement
to ensure
the first 2 goals.
To achieve these goals
during treatment processes
we focus on 4
main treatment objectives:
The first one is
de-watering.
Fecal sludge is typically
over 90% water
so de-watering to seperate
the liquid and solids
is very important.
De-watering is the removal
of more easily
separated water
like wringing out
this dripping wet towel
whereas drying is the further
removal of water that is bound
with the solids; like then
hanging the towel on a laundry line.
De-watering is important
because water is heavy
and expensive to transport.
Prior to effluent discharge
into the environment, solids
and liquids need to be seperated
to ensure adequate treatment
can take place
for public and
environmental health
and de-watering is typically
required for resource recovery.
Also important
is stabilization.
Stabalization is the process
of readily degradable
organic matter being coverted
as a result of biodegradation
to more stable
complex molecules.
Here we see that happening
in composting
with heat being released during
the active decomposition phase.
This is important for treatment as
readily degradable organic matter
consumes significant amounts
of oxygen during degradation.
For example, the classic
Streeter-Phelps equation
illustrates what happens if
waste water is discharged to a river
with high concentrations
of BOD
resulting in the dissolved oxygen
in the river being consumed
which can gradually be recovered
with time or distance travelled
in the river until readily
degradable organic matter
has been consumed and there
was no longer an oxygen demand.
Why do we care
about oxygen demand?
Because aquatic organisms
need dissolved oxygen to live.
Stabalization also results in
nutrient stabalization
and odor
reduction.
Also important
is nutrient management.
Fecal sludge contains nutrients
which can be beneficial
if harnessed
for resource recovery
but if not managed properly, result
in environmental contamination.
Environmental impacts from nutrients
include nitrification
and alga blooms in surface waters
and contamination of drinking water.
In pathogen reduction, to revisit
what we learned from the F diagram
fecal sludge contains large amounts
of micro-organisms
mainly resulting
from feces.
These micro-organisms can
be pathogenic
and exposure to untreated
fecal sludge constitutes
a significant health risk
to humans either through
direct contact or
indirect exposure.
The transmission cycle of pathogens
can be interrupted
by putting barriers in place
to block transmission pathways
and prevent
cycle completion.
The appropriate level of treatment
will depend on the resource recovery
or disposal option.
For example,
drying fecal sludge to use it
as a fuel in combustion,
our number 1 objective is to
de-water to increase fuel potential
and in this case pathogen reduction
is not so important
as the sludge
will be incinerated.
Whereas on the other hand
if treatment products
are to be used as soil
conditioners in agriculture
then pathogen reduction is an
extremely important
treatment objective.
The first barrier for
beneficial use is provided
by the level of
pathogen reduction
achieved through the treatment
of fecal sludge.
A selection of further
post-treatment barriers may include
restriction of use on crops
that are eaten raw,
withholding periods between
application and harvest
to allow pathogen die off,
drip or sub-surface
irrigation methods,
restricting worker and public access
during application and
use of personal protective equipment
and safe food preparation methods
such as thorough cooking,
washing or peeling.
When considering risk of infection,
all potential exposure groups
should be accounted for which can
be broadly categorized
as workers and their families,
surrounding communities
and product consumers.
For more information on a
multi-barrier risk based approach
to ensure adequate protection
of public health
I recommend the WHO guidelines
for safe use of waste-water,
excreta and grey-water in
agriculture and aquaculture.
The Sanitation Safety
Planning Manual
and the Sanitation Safety
Planning Module
in Sandec's Mooc
on sanitation systems.
Monitoring to ensure treatment
objectives have been met
is an important part of ongoing
operations and maintenance.
In summary,
in this module you learned about
treatment objectives
of de-watering,
stabalization,
nutrient managment
and pathogen reduction.
Why they are all important
for the protection of
human and environmental health
and that appropriate levels of
treatment will depend
on the intended
end-use.
Thanks for joining.
See you next time.