What type of financial
considerations do you need to make
if you want to buy something
expensive, like a car?
How much money do you have?
How much money can you borrow?
The cost of borrowing money,
like time and interest
on a loan.
What model? Number of seats?
Fuel mileage?
Do you buy used or new?
What are the maintenance costs?
What's the useful lifetime
of the car?
How long will you own it? And
do you plan to sell it afterwards?
These are the same types
of considerations
you need to apply in
engineering economics
when deciding between
different treatment technologies.
Following this module, you'll
be able to understand
the difference between capital
and operating cost.
Be able to calculate costs of
2 equivalent technologies
with annualised capital and
operating costs,
and explain how to include resource
recovery into engineering economics.
Capital costs are fixed
one time expenses
incurred on the purchase of land,
buildings, construction, equipment used.
So for example, if you wanted to
build a treatment plant,
it would include the cost
of the property,
and the construction of
the entire facility.
But with sanitation,
it also includes infrastructure
to get waste water or faecal sludge
to the treatment plant
because there's no point
in having a treatment plant
without a way to get
the waste water there.
Operating costs are the expenses
which are related
to the operation of a business
or equipment
or treatment facility.
With faecal sludge management,
this could be collection in
transport businesses,
vacuum trucks, treatment facilities,
or the operations budget of the utility.
It is the cost of resources just
to maintain their existence.
Net operating costs, can
be offset by revenues
such as the sale of
treatment and products.
If we think about the wide range of
faecal sludge treatment technologies
that are available and covered
in other models,
it is already apparent
that they will all have very
different costs of construction,
capital costs. But also different
operating costs
based on the complexity
of operation.
In addition, they're going to
have very different lifetimes.
For example, comparing
infrastructure costs,
for how many years will
a vacuum truck work?
Compare that to say, what is the
operational lifetime of a sewer?
For example, the Cloaca Maxima
drainage system in Rome
is still operating
after 2500 years.
It's like comparing
apples and oranges.
When costs and benefits differ over
time, between different options,
we need to apply equivalent
equations
for the comparison of the relative
economic value.
To achieve this, we can apply
concepts like annualised costs.
If we know the capital costs,
operating costs, service lifetime,
and real interest rate,
we can use this equation to compare
the relative equivalent costs
of 2 different technologies.
As an example, I will walk
you through the case study
presented in this paper.
Comparing existing side
by side sewer
and faecal sludge management
systems in Dakar, Senegal.
First, let's compare both
of the process flows.
For the sewer based system,
there are sewer lines and
pumping stations,
followed by a waste water
treatment plant.
The process flow has screening
and grit removal,
primary settling,
activated sludge,
clarifiers, with the effluent
going to tertiary treatment
with some water reclamation
at a neighbouring golf course,
and the remainder discharged
to ocean.
The solids, go to anaerobic
digestion
with some of the remaining solids
sold to public works
for use in green ways.
The faecal sludge
management chain
has septic tanks, with vacuum
trucks  for collection and transport,
with settling tanks, followed
by drying beds.
The effluent from both
the settling and drying beds
goes to the activated
sludge treatment
in the waste water
treatment chain.
And the solids from the drying
beds are also used in green ways.
These are the stake holders
and financial flows
that we considered in
the evaluation.
With the sewer based system, we
start at the household level user
who pays a sanitation
tax to ONAS.
ONAS is the national
sanitation utility.
The sanitation tax, is included
as a drinking water tariff
to fund the sewer based waste
water treatment infrastructure.
The end user of
the reclaimed water
and the treated sludge,
also pays a fee to ONAS
for those products.
With the faecal sludge
management chain,
again starting with
the household level user,
they have to pay for construction
of their septic tank.
They still pay
the sanitation tax
because it's incorporated
in the drinking water tariff
even though they are not
using the sewer.
They also then pay
emptying services
from a collection and
transport company.
The collection and transport company
then pays an unloading fee
to ONAS, when they discharge
the faecal sludge
at the treatment plant.
Then again,
the end users are paying ONAS for
the resource recovery product.
All of the calculations, data
and assumptions we used
are included in the supplemental
information
of the paper from the spreadsheet.
For all calculations, the real
interest rate of 5%
is assumed for the lending
interest rate
adjusted for inflation
based on values used
by the World Bank.
To estimate annualised capital
cost for the sewer based system,
we first had to assume lifetimes.
For the household connections,
we selected 20 years.
For the sewer, we used the
relatively conservative estimate
based on PBC construction
of 30 years.
Also 30 years for the pumping
station and treatment plant.
Then we needed to determine
the total capital cost.
This information was obtained
from ONAS directly
from their operating information.
And we had to derive a number
for the number of household
sewer connections.
This was based on the original number,
the number of people per household,
the growth rate to determine
a per capita value.
We then use annualised cost
equation
to determine annualised
capital value.
In addition, we have
itemisation
of annual operating costs
which are also provided
in a supplemental information.
We then did similar calculations for
the faecal sludge management system.
Well first, we had
to assume lifetimes
here, 50 years for a septic tank,
15 years for an emptying truck,
and 30 years for
the treatment plant.
Then we have total
capital cost
for septic tanks, vacuum trucks,
and for the treatment plant.
Again, then we have
the number of per capita
people that are served
by the system.
We then annualised
these capital values
and itemised annual
operating costs,
also presented in
the supplemental information.
This table from the paper
summarises the results.
What we see is with
the capital costs,
the sewer based system,
compared to the faecal
sludge management system
is ten times more expensive.
And with operating costs,
evaluated annually,
1.5 times more expensive.
So the overall sewer
based system
for both capital and annual
operating costs
was 5 times more expensive.
What else we see from the results
is that with the sewer based system,
the costs are mainly borne
by ONAS.
Whereas in the faecal service
management chain
the costs are much more
spread out among the stakeholders.
It is also important
to note
that this is not equitable
as poor households
in the faecal sludge
management system
are having to pay
twice for sanitation.
Once with the sewer tariff,
included in their drinking water,
and 2nd, when they are paying for
faecal sludge management services.
This is where it is
also interesting
to think about how resource
recovery options
could offset costs.
In this model,
resource recovery
is generating
almost no income.
What if we could find
an option
to get 10 dollars for a truck load
of 5 cubic metres of faecal sludge?
And in the car,
they have 2.2 million cubic metres
of faecal sludge produced per year.
That would work out as
an annualised cost
of 8.8 per capita
net operating gain
because it is something that
could be brought in each year
to offset operating costs.
This could have a significant effect
on the financial balance
of the faecal sludge
management system,
making it close to a net
zero total cost.
Could this be used to reduce
the financial burden
to poor households?
This is where we organising
financial flows
and thinking about business
models comes into play.
When applying this type
of analyses,
you also need to consider
other complexities.
Like inflation, taxes,
depreciation, economy of scale,
and salvage value.
And also, conduct
a sensitivity analysis
to evaluate the effect of
any assumptions you make.
In addition, this example
was based on the assumption
that both systems are providing
the same level
of public and environmental
health protection.
This model provided in
introduction
of one type of equivalent
equation method
that can be used
to compare costs.
There are also many others, like
net present value.
These type of calculations are
also further complicated
with faecal sludge management
because many technologies
that we want to compare
have not yet been implemented,
so we don't have experience
on which to base estimated
capital and operating cost,
and so we need to make
a series of assumptions.
These estimates will
continue to improve
with increased implementations.
So, like making a decision
about which car to buy,
it's not purely about the cost.
You also have to include
economic analysis
with other variables
in the design approach.
Like environmental
and social impacts,
local laws and regulations, and
regional economic development.
In conclusion, in this model
you learn the difference
between capital
and operating costs,
how to calculate the equivalent
costs of 2 different types of systems
and consider how to
include resource recovery
into the analyses.
Thanks for joining,
see you next time.