This is a schematic of a Japanese
sludge vacuum truck that
includes de-watering.
My colleague,
professor Hidanori Hirada
from Kyoto university
shared it with me.
Nihongo ga wakarimasen.
Unfortunately, that means my
Japanese is not good enough to
translate this slide for you.,
but in this module I will tell you
a bit about de-watering trucks,
and we will also learn about other
innovations that are being made
in transportation of fecal sludge.
Following this module you
will be able to list alternatives
for optimizing the transport
of fecal sludge that
are ready for scaling up,
provide examples of potential ways
to improve collection of fecal sludge
and understand considerations
for implementation.
I will cover the following four
ideas to optimize surface provision
of collection and transport.
A call center, GIS tools, transfer
stations and de-watering trucks.
All of these concepts have to do
with reducing distances that
water has to be trucked
or moved around the city
because water is heavy
and expensive to transport.
These concepts can also help
increase service provision
at the house hold level
and reduce illegal dumping.
ONAS - the National
Sanitation Utility of Senegal
with support from Bill
and Melinda Gates foundation
is piloting a call center for
emptying services in Dakar, Senegal.
The concept is that instead of
individually calling truck or
service providers, when customers
want their on-site containment
emptied, they can directly
phone the call center.
The operator knows the location
of the house and then gets bids
from three different truck drivers
for the cost of emptying.
The one with the lowest
bid gets the job.
Over three years they've
had over five thousand calls
as shown in blue, many of which
end up in emptying being performed.
It is thought that the calls that
do not end up in emptying
might be used to get a competitive
bid for another empty-er.
The average price for emptying with
an eight cubic meter truck before
the call center was $49 and after
three years had gone down to $42.
The call center is relatively
straight forward to run
with only one supervisor and
two people to answer the phones.
A business model was developed and
first piloted prior to the current
scaling up phase.
Other critical aspects of
the project, including organised
group of formerly
recognized empty-ers
committed on improving the sector
and training, certification, and
supervision of empty-ers to ensure
that they are doing their
work in a hygienic fashion.
It is also being evaluated whether
the trucks would be willing to
install GPS trackers, so the call
center could select the drivers
closest to the customers, reducing
transport distances.
Also important is adequate
communication, and promotion
to customers.
This is a commercial that was used
in the promotion campaign in Dakar.
This is a study we conducted in
Kampala, Uganda, where
thirty four trucks voluntarily
let us outfit them with GPS trackers
and we checked 5653 emptying
operations over three months.
The GIS analysis of all these
emptying events provided
a powerful tool to understand
emptying service
provision in Kampala.
The results together with
demographic data were used
to identify service provision
by density, income level in
non-residential areas.
GIS data could also be used
as a powerful planning tool
for example, optimal
locations for transfer stations.
Key, again to this study, was
a strong empty-ers association
with a desire to improve the sector,
and voluntary commitment to
participate by the empty-ers.
The publication in this report with
all the maps can be downloaded
on our website.
Another innovation that is
frequently discussed
but in reality rarely implemented
is transfer stations.
The goal of transfer stations is
to reduce the transport distances
and make transport more efficient
thereby also reducing
illegal dumping.
Transfer stations could be mobile
or fixed like the tank shown on
the cover of this report, which
can be downloaded on the internet.
More information can also be found
in chapter four, of the fecal
sludge management book.
Transfer stations could
be especially valuable
for areas that are not accessible by
trucks and are served by
manual empty-ers who can
only transport sludge
very short distances.
The transfer station could then be
emptied by a truck and driver to
a treatment plant, however, units
trialed in Ghana failed due to
the secondary collection which
was not frequent enough
so sludge settled too
much or over-flowed
and garbage was also
the problem for the vacuum trucks.
If de-watering could be incorporated
into transfer stations, then they
could even be located
near existing sewer networks.
Once solids are removed,
it could be discharged to the sewer
and only de-watered solids
would have to be transported
greatly reducing transport
volumes and cost.
For example, here in Kampala, where
only about 20% of the poplulation
is served by sewers, our GIS
analysis shows there are lots of
emptying events located near
the existing sewer network.
Of course, the impact to
down-stream treatment plants
would have to be
carefully evaluated.
Other difficulties with transfer
stations are that it is always
difficult to find available
space in urban areas.
They can be expensive and nimby,
convincing people to accept fecal
sludge handling in their back yard.
This brings us to the truck that
we saw in the introduction
which is a de-watering vacuum
truck for fecal sludge in Japan.
Trucks like this were first
in use there from 1980.
In the 90's the technology was
improved and in 2006
the ministry of environment
started promoting their use.
There are now several
hundred in operation.
There is a submerged pump and
a drum screen for solid-liquid
separation, this portal is
the inspection window where
the empty-er observes the sludge
and manually adjusts doses of
coagulants for de-watering
and aeration for mixing.
The affluent goes directly
back into the on-site system
as treatment relies on
the bacterial community.
This example is from Brasil used
for de-sludging of septic tanks.
This, on the other hand, is a mobile
de-watering unit for waste-water
treatment plants.
In smaller towns, where it
is too expensive to build
the water treatment plants,
this unit can travel around
and de-water sludge for
multiple treatment plants.
You can see how the concept of
the de-watering trucks could be
developed into mobile or fixed
de-watering transfer stations.
To further this concept,
the Bill and Melinda Gates foundation
has been working on
the Omni-ingester.
The goal of this project is to
develop a de-watering truck
that can also fully treat
the affluent so it can be directly
discharged to the environment.
Empty-ers would be able to empty
a lot more system in fewer trips
by safely eliminating
the liquid on site.
The goal is also that it would be
able to empty any type of on-site
system in contrast to
the previous examples
which are for more specific
applications, like septic tank
sludge, or waste water sludge.
Therefore it would need to be
two types of units, one for more
wet systems and another for dryer.
It would have a pit-side unit
allowing access to sites
not accessible by truck, and be
able to empty all material within
including rubbish.
The truck has not
been actualized yet
but research has included
investigating mobile pumps
ways to separate
and clean debris
an electro-chlorinator
for affluent treatment
and of course, mechanisms for
de-watering the sludge.
This is a rotary drum thickener,
the biggest challenge of these
trucks so far is developing online
real-time dosing of coagulants
to be able to deal with such a wide
range of sludge characteristics.
This is a research question
for more development.
In this module you
learned about innovations
that are ready to be
scaled up for fecal sludge
in addition to the ones that
are still being developed.
All of the examples could improve
the collection of fecal sludge
but all have different difficulties
in terms of what to manage
for scaling up.
Thanks for joining and
see you next time.