In this introduction to faecal
sludge management, you've
learned a lot about different
elements that need to be considered
and integrated into one system.
Including treatment objectives,
multiple technologies, operations
and maintenance, resource recovery,
qualification and characterization,
financial considerations, legal
frameworks and planning.
In this module I'm gonna provide
you with an example of a city
where these aspects have all been
applied in a systems level approach.
for an innovative adaptive and
integrated approach
to faecal sludge management.
Following this module, you will be
able to distinguish different
approached to faecal sludge
management taken in Durban.
Identify examples of what has worked
in the service chain in Durban
and consider how management examples
could be applied in other locations.
Now I will take you to the city of
Durban, South Africa with Ethekwini
municipality that employs an approach
to faecal sludge management
that is innovative, adaptive, and
integrated.
We'll start the story in August 2000
when a cholera outbreak started
in the KwaZulu-Natal province where
Durban is located.
During one year there were over
100 000 cases with 260 deaths.
A positive outcome of this
unfortunate crisis was that
it brought funding and recognition
to sanitation and lead to a policy
review and propagation of a national
sanitation policy in 2001.
Also in 2001, the current Ethekwini
municipality was formed
when the boundaries of the previous
Durban, what is now Central Durban
were greatly expanded.
With this change the city went from
400 sq. km to 2600 sq. km.
The new boundaries were very
complex.
Demographically, geographically, and
in terms of existing infrastructure.
They include urban, peri urban,
and rural areas.
Of 3 million residents in 2001
it was estimated that 1 million
did not have water or sanitation
services.
Another million was supplied with
severely rundown services,
and 1 million had a high level of
service with flush toilets
and tap water.
In addition, HIV/AIDS and
tuberculosis are rive.
Poverty is high. And it is a
water scarce region.
In South Africa national policy
states that all people have a right
to basic and free sanitation and
water.
eThekwini Water and Sanitation
or EWS was now faced with
fulfilling the right of basic
sanitation to everyone within
new boundaries.
In addition, the new Durban
metropolitan area is undergoing
rapid growth. The goal of eThekwini
was to find solutions that would
satisfy everyone, but they had
to act immediately
and could not wait for perfect
solutions before doing anything.
Solutions needed to be developed
and perfected over time.
EWS set the following wash guiding
principles:
working within the boundaries of a
water-scarce environment by
linking sanitation systems to water
supply; following the law of ecosan
by investigating ways in which
nutrients can be recovered for use
in agriculture. Ensuring that
implementation is backed by sound
scientific research through creating
partnerships with local
and international organisations.
Regularly interacting with the
people they serve to ensure
two-way communication and
awareness through an extensive
educational outreach program. And
sharing of expertise with other
municipalities through the
MILE initiative.
EWS also instituted a business
approach to management.
First built on the basis of their
own human resources to ensure
adequate capacity.
Then building on that foundation
with a key focus on customer service.
If customers are happy, they will
pay for their services, so you can
generate adequate revenue to run
your business.
Revenue then needs to be spent on
asset management and network
expansion.
EWS came up with a multi-faceted
approach that included waterborn
sanitation in a dense urban center
where a sewer was possible,
shown by the blue lines in this
figure. Dry toilets outside of this
area where sewers would never be
accessible due to the terrain and
population density.
Septic tanks were home owners
wanting to take responsibility to
install them. An ablution blocks
for informal settlements.
An integrated approach does not
only mean multidisciplinary,
it means employing different
solutions throughout an area
that are appropriate for our context
into one integrated overall
management solution.
With the increased boundaries,
EWS also inherited responsibility
for 35 000 pit latrines that became
a management problem as they became
full. And most of the areas are
difficult to access with trucks.
An emptying model was piloted
and then scaled up.
And currently the existing pit
latrines are emptied by EWS
on a five years cycle.
Starting in 2002 for sanitation
provision outside the area that could
be served by the sewer, EWS
implemented an innovative solution
with urine diversion toilets.
These were two chamber systems
with alternate usage and storage
with a urine going to a soakaway.
This technology was selected as it
was expected that during
containment sludge would degrade,
become dry and spadable
and have reduced pathogens, so
people could manage faecal sludge
themselves instead of relying on
emptying services.
Most of these areas are very
difficult to access by truck.
There was a massive rollout at these
innovative new toilets with 1000
installations per month. And 75 000
built by 2011.
As shown in this figure, this
included an intensive monitoring
and evaluation program. That
included effectiveness of the
community education program.
Community acceptance,
maintenance by households, and
quality and durability of
construction and hygiene.
Reported problems included
dissatisfaction with odors,
doors, vault covers, vent pipes and
poor construction.
Problems that were all addressed
by EWS.
However, following implementation
85% of respondents reported using
the urine diverting dry toilets, but
only 34% reported satisfaction
with using them. One of the main
reasons was that they had to empty
and manage faecal sludge themselves.
And 80% of respondents were found
not to be maintaining them properly.
In addition, researchers found that
viable pathogens remained in the
sludge even after the two years
of storage.
It wasn't acceptable that the health
risk was transferred to the homes
instead or professional collection
services.
To address these realities of
customers wanting the same level
of services pit latrines, pathogen
destruction not as effective as
thought. Households that didn't
empty overflowing chambers,
in densifying areas where it was no
longer possible to burry the sludge.
As of 2017, EWS has started a pilot
project to provide collection,
transport and off-site treatment
services for the urine diverting
dry toilet faecal sludge. With
service provided to households,
every two years.
Researchers are also evaluating
the possibility of incorporating
pour-flush toilets.
In areas that still have older pit
latrines EWS continues  to provide
emptying services on a 5 year
cycle
and has registered all of the
locations on a municipal GIS system.
To meet sanitation needs in informal
settlements within the water born
area, community ablution blocks
with male and female facilities
including toilets, urinals, washing
basins and showers they all
drained to the sewer have been
installed to serve people within
a maximum walking distance of
100 meters.
The ablution blocks also initially
encountered problems due to theft
and vandalism.
But to solve this the blocks were
remanufactured with robust and
non-valuable materials.
Each block is also now allocated
with the care taker to manage
the facility.
EWS provides consumables such as
toilet paper and cleaning materials
and responds to water leaks, toilet
blockages and vandalism.
Outside the water born urban edge,
ABR is followed by wet lands are
being investigated.
For treatment of faecal sludge
the LaDePa Pelletizer was developed
for pit latrine sludge after
discharging of waste water treatment
facilities with causing them
to fail.
Deep row entranchment has been
studied and currently black soldier
fly larvae are being evaluated
for the urine diverting sludge.
At the same time in parallel, EWS
maintains the sewer network
and 43 waste water treatment plans.
The result over a relatively short
period of time has been an enourmous
improvement in sanitation.
With 74% of excreting now considered
safely managed
and 26% not safely managed.
But with 16% of that due to sludge
that is considered unsafely
contained in informal pit latrines.
So, what are the corner stones of
this case study that could replicated
in other cities?
That produce these successes and
what could have been seen as
insurmountable management
challenges.
EWS has practiced solution-based
thinking.
They thought outside the box,
selected and implemented solutions
and then continued to learn from
them and adapt.
They recognized the importance of
progressive realization
building on what is in place.
There's a strong, but also dynamic
regulatory framework in place to
allow for this and manage risk.
New solutions are first trialed at a
pilot scale
which is in official status
recognized by the municipal council
during which projects are closely
monitored and include intensive
public participation.
Only after this phase can they be
rolled out on a larger scale.
In this way, policy makers and
sector leaders encourage calculated
risk to continue improving service
delivery.
There is acknowledgement,
involvement, and commitment
from the public sector, from the
national and local levels
with a commitment to the need for
safe management of excreta
throughout the entire service chain.
Research is a foundation of this
innovative approach.
In technology, but also in
understanding of community needs
and underlying factors.
EWS has a very strong collaboration
and participatory process with the
universities in applied research to
address solutions.
With the strong commitment to open
communication and sharing of
information.
The focus is not just on building
toilets or implementing technologies
operation and maintenance budgets
receive equal importance.
The whole program is built on
customer care.
The national principle with people
as the customers first.
A switch from an infrastructural
approach to a service delivery
approach with a commitment to
comprehensive long-term community
engagement and education for mutual
trust and understanding.
Monitoring to ensure compliance
for public environmental health
but also success of the whole
program.
The solutions are context specific.
But can also be time specific.
What is right now will not
necessarily be right tomorrow.
For example, in rural areas
satisfaction with the urine
diverting toilets was higher.
Whereas close to the water born
infrastructure there was much less
satisfaction.
Engagement of the private sector
throughout the service chain
including construction of toilets,
collection and transport of
faecal sludge, operation of treatment
facilities and, importantly,
recognition of the innovation
they bring.
And finally, there is no "one size
fits all" approach.
EWS has a culture which encourages
innovation and allows mistakes.
As long as they are learned from and
not repeated.
For more information about
the approaching eThekwini
I recommend these additional
sources.
In summary, in this module we
learned about different approaches
to faecal sludge management
taken in Durban.
Examples of what has worked in
the service chain.
And factors for success that
could be applied in other locations.
Thanks for joining!
See you next time.