Having considered the notions
encapsulation and abstraction,
we will consider
in the following episodes
a third fundamental notion
in OOP:
inheritance.
Let's start with an example,
and forget, for once, rectangles
and other geometric shapes
to concentrate on
players of a game.
Imagine that we would like
to play a game that involves
warriors, magicians, rogues,
and the like.
How would we represent this?
We could imagine
that we have a class for warriors,
a class for rogues, a class for
magicians, and so on.
For a warrior we could imagine
that we could have data members
such as a name,
an energy level, a certain lifespan,
and certainly a weapon.
As for methods, we
could imagine
that a warrior can meet
other people.
For a rogue, he would also have
a name, an energy level, a lifespan,
and he can also meet other
people, and even steal from them.
As for the magician, he would also
have a name, energy level, lifespan
he could also meet others
and he would maybe
also have a wand instead
of a weapon.
We could also have witches kind
of like magicians
but who would have a
staff as well as a wand.
All these classes would have much
duplicated code,
and it would be a waste of time to write
all that,
and most importantly, would be
problematic for maintenance.
Imagine that we do want a
property lifespan anymore,
and instead have life points,
or that the energy level is
not an "int" but a "double".
Then we would have to
revise all the classes that we made.
There is definitely
a better way than this!
This is where the notion of inheritance comes
in: inheritance solves this type of problem
by grouping together data
members and methods
that are common to each class
into what we will call a superclass.
This class regroups characteristics
that are enriched or specialized
in its derived classes that are more
specific.
In our class, the superclass would be
a class "Personnage" (TN: means "Character")
a generic character which
would by the way
solve one of the problems we had:
the fact that we did not
have a class Personnage.
Anticipating a little,
here is what we could
do using inheritance,
by grouping in the class
Personnage
the properties shared by
the classes:
name, energy, lifespan,
as well as methods,
for example "recontrer"
(TN: means "meet").
So this superclass groups
together the common characteristics
of these characters
which would be inherited
by the rogue, the magician, etc.
with each character having
his own particularities, like
a weapon for the warrior, a wand for the
magician, a method to steal for the rogue, ...
From the class magician, we could
even have a supplementary extension,
an extra level of inheritance,
so as to have a witch that is a
magician but with a staff as well
as a wand.
So this is the purpose of
inheritance in OOP.
It represents an "is-a" relationship,
and avoids that common code be
duplicated.
Inheritance also enables
specialized classes
enriched with members to be created.
So a superclass is a class
from which subclasses
are derived.
We also say that subclasses inherit
and we indicate this with an arrow
in this direction.
Subclasses inherit from superclasses,
and so are as a result extensions,
either by adding data members
or methods,
or by specializing the inherited methods,
making them extensions of the superclass.
Before detailing these
in an concrete example,
let's investigate what an inheritance
relationship implicates.
If a subclass C1 is derived from
a class C
or "inherits" from the class C,
we will say that C1 "is a" C.
that is to say, that the type
is inherited.
So for example, if I
have a variable x, of type C,
and a variable y of type C1,
I can in fact put y in x, because
a C1 y "is a" C as well.
However, here it is copied
as being a "C",
and loses its specificity as a "C1",
because it is copied in a "C",
so here it is copied as a "C",
only the part of "C"
of y that is copied in x.
Moreover, the class C1 inherits
from the set of data members
and methods of C.
When we say the set of
data members and members,
except for the constructors
and for the destructor,
-- although since C++ 2011
we can even inherit constructors --
We will talk more about that later,
in the next episodes.
The data members and methods
of C are available in C1
without having to
redefine them explicitly
and finally,
the supplementary data members
and methods can be added to C1
-- this is called enrichment.
But the methods inherited from
C in C1 can also be redefined
-- this is called specialization.
Let's review this in a
detailed example:
imagine that we want to create
a superclass "Personnage"
with 2 subclasses Guerrier and Voleur
(TN: guerrier means warrior, and voleur, rogue).
So we said that when a subclass "C1"
for example here a "Guerrier"
is created from a superclass "C",
so for example here a "Personnage",
the type is inherited.
Actually a "Guerrier" is a "Personnage" as well,
[TN: a Warrior is a Character]
which allows us to write the
following code.
Suppose that we have declared
a variable p of type "Personnage" and
a variable g of type "Guerrier"
that we manipulate and for example
we say that the character p is the warrior g.
So we put the warrior g
in the character p,
which we are allowed to do
because a warrior is a character.
But be careful, we only
put the "Personnage" part of g in p
and this assignment is done
seen as a "Personnage"
and only the part of g
is copied in p.
For example, only "Guerrier" but not all
"Personnages" have an weapon
so "arme" is not copied.
(TN: "arme" mean "weapon")
Of course, we can't do
the contrary
and write "g = p;"
A generic character is
not a warrior in general,
because characters can also
be rogues or magicians,
and we cannot put
a rogue in a warrior,
which would not have any meaning.
So here, the relationship has a certain
direction, it's the warrior who is a character.
We can also imagine a function
that displays a character,
and we could display g,
which is a warrior passed as argument
to the function "afficher" as a character,
(TN: "afficher" means "print" or "display")
(the function "afficher" sees
g as a "Personnage"),
but we can only do this
because a warrior is a character.
A 2nd aspect of inheritance:
Guerrier will inherit, that is to
say, receive, contain
the set of data members
and methods of Personnage.
So for example, if Personnage
had a name, an energy, a lifespan
and say a method "rencontrer",
and Guerrier inherits
from the class Personnage,
then in Guerrier we would also have
an energy, a lifespan,
without needing to
redefine them,
and also a "rencontrer" method, so
we could do something like this.
Suppose that here, with a Guerrier g
and Voleur v, which are characters,
g , of type Guerrier, will inherit
the method rencontrer,
which we could invoke,
if this method is
included in the public
interface of Personnage,
using a syntax "g.rencontrer(v);",
here we pass the rogue v as
argument to the method rencontrer,
but what is important here is to
see that this method rencontrer
is visible to g and
can be called by g because
Guerrier has inherited this
method from Personnage.
Likewise, if we had some
method in Guerrier,
we can directly use the data
member energie like this
in a method of Guerrier,
supposing that energie is not private.
So energie is inherited from
Personnage in the class Guerrier
without having to add
any code.
It's done automatically thanks
to inheritance.
The third and last aspect
that we want to focus on
is that even if the members
of a class are inherited,
and are accessible in the
subclasses,
we can always add
data members and
methods which is called
enrichment,
e.g. adding a data member "arme"
(TN: means "weapon") to the class Guerrier,
and we can redefine methods
called specialization,
so for instance, we could redefine
the method rencontrer of the class
Voleur by saying that when a rogue
meets another person,
he also steals, for example.
Inheritance is a paramount
notion in POO,
because it enables the code to
be organized
to make it more comprehensible
by elucidating structural and
semantical relationships
that exist among the classes,
for example, that a warrior is a character,
or that a witch is a type of magician.
Inheritance also avoids duplicating
large sections of code,
called "code redundancy".
Be careful in how you use inheritance:
use it
only for "is-a" relationships,
e.g. a warrior is a character,
but a warrior is not a weapon,
we say a warrior "has a" weapon,
and to represent a
relationship of possession,
we will use a notion from
before: encapsulation.
Therefore, to summarize, a warrior
inherits from the class Personnage
but will also have as encapsulated
data member a weapon.
We saw that a subclass
can "inherit" from a superclass,
"inherit" means
receive and possess
the data members and member functions of this
superclass, except for constructors
and destructor.
This aspect is transitive,
that is to say if we have
a super-super-class from which
a superclass is derived,
then in the subclass, we
will find all the members of these 2 classes.
More concretely,
if I have a super-super-class A,
from which a superclass B is derived,
from which a class C is derived,
we will find in C the members
found in B,
but also those in A, because
B inherits them from A,
and so they are
accessible in B.
So in B, I have the data
members and methods of A,
and by transitivity,
I also have in
C, these same data members
and methods of A.
So in a concrete example, if we
have for instance a class Personnage,
from which a class Magicien
is derived,
and if we say a witch
is a kind of magician,
then the class Sorcier inherits from the class Magicien.
(TN "Sorcier" means "Witch" or "Sorcerer")
At this point, in the class Sorcier,
we will also have the
data members for the
name, energy, lifespan
that were inherited along with
the method rencontrer that were
inherited in the magician class
and inherited again in the
class Sorcier
and of course, Sorcier will also have the
member baguette,inherited from Magicien.
Thus we have something like
this for inheritance,
a progressive enrichment
of each class,
finally resulting in,
if we draw all the relationships
between the classes,
an arborescent graph,
a treelike organization,
where we see the dependencies
between classes,
the "is-a" relationships, and
the relationships of inheritance,
of data members, methods,
and also types,
which we call as whole,
a class hierarchy,
with the most general class,
Personnnage, at the top,
and the most specialized classes
on the bottom.
To summarize, the inheritance
relationship avoids duplicating code
by implementing in our programs
"is-a" relationships,
creating superclasses that
are more general
which are called "parent classes"
which group the general properties
from which inherit subclasses
also called "child classes"
that receive the set
of data members and methods,
as well as the type of the superclass
that they depend on.
For now, the subclasses inherit
from one sole superclass
but in a few weeks we will have
them inherit from
several superclasses.
That is called "mutiple inheritance".
Up to now, this notion of
inheritance has been
presented very conceptually
and theoretically,
but how do we implement it
in a real program,
and make a subclass inherit
from a superclass?
Let's start with a concrete example.
Suppose, that we want to define
a class "Rectangle"
with a width "largeur" and
a height "hauteur",
and which is also a "FigureGeometrique"
(TN: means "GeometricShape")
And this class of geometric
shapes also has a position.
So we would have the
following inheritance diagram,
a superclass "FigureGeometrique",
with a data member "position",
and a subclass "Rectangle",
derived from "FigureGeometrique".
A rectangle
is a geometric shape,
and so will have supplementary
data members,
besides the inherited
data member position,
such as largeur
and hauteur that
are defined in Rectangle.
But how do I code all this in C++?
The normal syntax to declare a subclass
to inherit from a superclass
is to simply add colon (':'), "public",
followed by the name of the super-class
behind the class declaration,
that is behind the class header,
behind the first line
"class", name of the subclass.
So for example,
if I have a class "Rectangle",
that inherits from the
class "FigureGeometrique",
we add behind the normal declaration
"class Rectangle", ": public FigureGeometrique".
This makes the class Rectangle
an extension of the class FigureGeometrique
and makes a "Rectangle"
to be a "FigureGeometric" (is-a relation)
by receiving the set of data
members and member functions
(apart from the constructors
and destructor).
The only thing to add is
the usual definition of
our class Rectangle,
so that is inherits from
FigureGeometrique
is simply this portion of the code.
In the same way, if I come back to our
example of warriors
with a warrior being a character
so we have a class Personnage
that is defined
that contains all the
data members already mentioned
and we say a warrior is a character
by writing like this
the declaration of Guerrier:
"class Guerrier: public Personnage"
a "Guerrier" inherits from "Personnage",
a "Guerrier" is a "Personnage"
and next we would have
the usual definition of "Guerrier"
with as supplementary member
his weapon ("arme").
So this concludes this
general introduction
to the important concept
in OOP
of inheritance,
The next episodes continue
to detail this concept
from a more practical
point of view
by considering the details
of its implication.