In this episode,
we will continue examining the topic
of inheritance
and will consider in this
context 2 concepts that are related:
the notion of masking and the notion of
protected access rights.
You have seen that the accessibility
of a class's member
--a data member or a member function (method)--
can either be "public"
which means
that is visible from anywhere in the code,
and is acesssible inside the class
it is defined in as well as
outside of it.
If it is "private", its visibility
is restrained
exclusively to inside the class
in which it is defined.
Now we can wonder:
"What happens to access rights within
an inheritance relationship?"
Suppose that we have a superclass A
from which inherits a subclass B,
Suppose that inside the superclass A,
we have declared a private attribute,
just as we have always done
for all data members up to now.
Now, we wonder if
in a method
of the subclass B
for example, a method like this,
we have the right to use this
data member directly.
We saw that because of inheritance,
the class B disposes indeed
of a data member inherited from A.
But can B access 'a' directly?
Can B do something like this
for example?
And directly access the inherited
data member?
Actually, because "private" insures
that the member 'a' is accessible only from inside
its class, this data member is only
accessible in the class A.
We can access this data member
directly
only in the methods of the class A
and nowhere else.
The answer to our question
is thus: "No".
No, we don't have direct access to 'a'
from any method
of the class B
as this data member is defined as "private"
in the superclass.
This puts us in a delicate situation.
An object of type B inherits
a data member 'a' through inheritance,
yet it cannot access this data member
directly!
Since a method of the class B
should logically be able
to manipulate any data
member of the class B,
there exists in fact a third access right:
the "protected" access right.
The "protected" access right allows
a subclass
to directly access the data members
it inherits,
by insuring that the
data member of a class
is visible to all the descendants of the class.
This is specified with the keyword "protected".
So, by replacing "private" with "protected" here
enables that the
subclasses can access
all the protected members,
whether they are data members
or member functions,
inherited from their parent classes.
Another example: a subclass "Guerrier" (TN: means "Warrior")
inherits from a superclass Personnage (TN: means "Character").
It thus inherits of a data member
that represents
its energy level.
If in the class "Guerrier", we want to write
a method "frapper" (TN: means "to hit"),
allowing a Guerrier to hit
another character
and if we decide that the warrior
can only hit another character
when he has enough energy,
then, we are obliged
to use the "energy" data member,
like this for example.
The direct access in a
method of the "Guerrier" class
to a data member inherited from
its parent class, is only possible
because the data member
was declared as "protected".
Again, if it had been declared "private",
this direct access
would not have been possible.
What could then
be done for "Guerrier"
to access its energy level?
What is important to grasp is
that the access right "protected"
simply extends the "private" access right
by granting special access rights
to all the subclasses,
but nowhere else.
Outside these privileged (sub)classes however,
the "protected" member is seen as "private".
For example, if
in the main() function,
I declare an object of type "Guerrier",
and if I try to access
its energy level through
an access like this,
well, this is impossible, as outside the
methods of subclasses
the data member is seen
as private.
More specifically, a protected data
member, will be directly accessible
from within subclasses, but only in their own scope.
Let's start by briefly recalling
what the "scope" of a class represents
with a simple example,
independently of inheritance.
Suppose that we have
a class B
where we have defined a private
data member, such as  b.
We know that the data member b
is accessible in the scope of B,
that is, in every method
of the class B.
More specifically, C++ implements
what is called "class scope"
which means concretely that
this member b will be accessible
from anywhere within the scope of B,
through any object of type B,
be it an object pointed by "this"
or any other instance of B.
This means that in a method
of the class B,
we are allowed to access b,
when writing something like this,
implicitly we are working
with the data variable b
of the considered object.
It's just like writing
something like this.
We are also allowed to access
the member b, via any other instance
of the class B.
That is, for example, if the method "m"
took as parameter
another object of type B,
we would also have the right
to access the data member
b through this other object of type B.
So, in the class B, we have the right to
access this data member
through any object of type B,
whether it is "this" or any other B.
Here, when I say that a data member b
is "of B scope",
I mean that it is only accessible
inside the class B
and through any object
of type B.
Let's see in a more complicated
example
what it means for an access right
that is this time 'protected'
to only be accessible to
subclasses "in their own scope".
Here we have a subclass B
that inherits from a superclass A
which has a protected data member 'a'
and a private data member.
The protected 'a' is accessible
in the subclass B
but only in its own scope,
that is, inside the class B
via any object of type B,
be it "this" or any other b.
On the other hand, the private data
member is only accessible in the scope of A,
and not inside B.
Let's examine this with
a method 'f'
of the class B that takes as parameters
an object of type B, an object of type A,
and an "int".
When we write this
we are accessing a protected
data member 'a' in the scope of B
because we are inside B and are
accessing 'a'
of the current instance.
We are of course
in the scope of B,
which makes this possible.
Here, since it is not possible
in the subclass to access
a private member of
its superclass,
this line would lead
to an error.
The access here
to a private data member of
the superclass via any object of type B
is only possible in B,
via 'this' as in the case here,
or another B.
Again, attempting access to a
private member will result in an error here.
As we saw that protected members
are only accessible
in the scope of B,
that is to say, inside B
and via any object of type B,
then this access is possible
just like this one.
All objects through
which we access A
are in the scope of B.
This access is therefore possible.
Finally, in a last example, we
try to access the protected members of A
but we aren't in the
scope of B.
How is this possible? We are
indeed inside B
and in a method of B, but we
are attempting access to this data member
via an object that is not of type B,
but of type A.
Thus, we are outside
the scope of B, which
prevents this action.
To take a more concrete
example,
imagine that we have a class "Personnage"
instead of our class A,
and which has a protected data member
defining the energy level of the character.
The role of the class B would
be played by a subclass "Guerrier"
who would be a subclass of "Personnage"
and would have a method
equivalent to the method "f":
a method "frapper"
(TN: "frapper" means "to hit")
that enables the warrior
to hit another character.
If we would like this method
to take into account that the
energy level of a character diminishes
when a warrior strikes him,
we could imagine for example
to write something like this.
However, this would not work;
accessing it this way is impossible
because of the same rule
as that which is applied here,
the object "p" which has the same
role as "autreA" in the other example,
is outside the scope,
and is not in the same scope
as the object 'this'.
So now you know the
access rights in C++,
public members are accessible to
all the programmers-users of a given class,
contrarily, private members
are accessible exclusively
to the programmer of the class.
They represent the internal structure
of the class and are
modifiable without
repercussions on the
class users.
Finally, protected members are accessible
to all programmers of extensions
that extend the class in question,
by adding subclasses.
Inside these subclasses
it is possible to access these
protected members.
This concludes this episode
about access rights
in the context of
a hierarchy of classes.