In certain cases, members
defined in a superclass
do not satisfy the needs of
a subclass sufficiently.
Redefinition and shadowing
are 2 concepts that
can be useful in such situations.
In the last episode we
took the example
of a hierarchy of characters in a game
based on the hypothesis
that all characters had the
same way of meeting another person.
Each character, when meeting another
would, for example, greet him.
Suppose now that this way
of implementing the method 'rencontrer' (= 'meet')
works for most classes,
but not all.
We could imagine for example
a warrior as being a bit more belligerent
as others, and when he comes across
another character, well,
instead of greeting the other cordially,
he attacks him.
Thus we are in a situation where
we could consider implementing
the method 'rencontrer' in two different
manners, one for peaceful characters,
who would greet other characters,
and another
for warlike characters,
that would greet people
with a blow of their weapon.
What would be
of our initial class hierarchy?
Would we have to
redesign the whole structure?
Happily the answer is no.
You just need to modify
the method 'rencontrer'
in the subclass 'guerrier'.
We will change the
class hierarchy
in the following manner: we will
keep the general method 'rencontrer'
which is satisfactory for most of the
classes in the superclass 'Personnage'
but in the class 'Guerrier' we will
specialize the method
by redefining it in a more satisfactory
manner
for the subclass in question.
In the case of our example, let's imagine
that the class 'Guerrier' had a method
here by a method 'frapper' (='hit')
[Silence]
that would be called
by the method 'rencontrer'.
The method 'rencontrer' will then
be defined at 2 levels of the hierarchy
Once in the superclass 'Personnage',
and once in the subclass
'Guerrier'.
We call it 'shadowing', because
henceforth, for an object of type 'Guerrier'
the specialized method
has priority.
We say that it 'shadows' or hides the
more general method
called by default if there
are no specialized methods.
For example, if in a program, I
work with an object of type 'Magicien'
[Silence]
and that I apply the
method 'rencontrer',
[Silence]
because the method 'rencontrer'
wasn't redefined in 'Magicien',
the inherited method, the 'rencontrer'
from 'Personnage' will be used.
So here, this method
will be the general, default
method.
However, if now I want
to apply the method 'rencontrer'
to an object of type
'Guerrier',
[Silence]
well, since a specialized method
was redefined in this class,
this method will impose itself
in this case.
So we say that this method will hide
the general, inherited method.
In programming, in general,
'shadowing' occurs when
an identifier hides another.
In the case of class hierarchy,
we speak of 'shadowing' when the same
attribute or method name is used
at several hierarchy levels.
For our example,
the same method header is found
at several hierarchy levels.
Shadowing is little-used and not
recommended for attributes.
It causes confusion,
which means concretely this:
with a superclass A, for example,
from which inherits a subclass b,
a shadowing of attributes
simply means that
in the class A, there is an attribute
named 'a' but that in the class B,
an attribute 'a' is also declared.
If we use an attribute 'a'
inside a method of the class B,
than it is this attribute
that we'll use.
And we say that this attribute,
has shadowed the attribute higher up in A.
So, an object B disposes of
2 attributes:
one that is specific,
called 'a',
and one inherited from
A, also called 'a'
hence the confusion.
So, the fact that we have the same type
here, doesn't change anything,
it suffices to have a same attribute
name for masking to take place.
Evidently this situation for attributes
should be avoided.
However, as we saw in the previous
example where
the method 'rencontrer' was
redefined in the subclass 'Guerrier'
well, the redefinition of methods,
is quite common and quite practical:
it allows classes to adapt to specific
situations according to their hierarchy.
To summarize, in a class hierarchy,
masking a method
consists of defining in a subclass a
method of the same name
as one already defined in
a superclass.
In jargon, we say that
the inherited method
is the the general method,
which is available to
by default all subclasses
that do not mask it.
The method that hides the
inherited one is the specialized method
that caters to the specific needs
of the subclass
in which it is defined.
As previously evoked,
for an object of type 'Guerrier',
it is always the specialized
method that is called here.
So, if we define an object
of type 'Guerrier',
and we invoke the method
'rencontrer' on this object,
and it is not the the method 'rencontrer'
of 'Personnage' that is called,
but the specialized method.
We only apply the normal
scope resolution rules,
for a scope that is closest.
An object of type 'Guerrier' disposes
of 2 of these methods:
the specialized method and the
general method.
It can be useful in certain circumstances
to invoke this general method,
the one that was inherited, even if
we have redefined it
lower down in the hierarchy.
So how do we deal with this?
For example, imagine that we want
to give our warrior a few good manners,
and that he greets someone he meets
before attacking him, or inversely.
This means that the warrior starts by
meeting the character
just as any other person in the hierarchy,
by greeting him, before applying
more specific actions.
The code that allows a character
to greet another
is already incorporated in the general method
'rencontrer' (TN: 'rencontrer' = to meet),
that is to say, the 'rencontrer'
from 'Personnage'.
It is unnecessary to duplicate this
code in the specific 'rencontrer'
of 'Guerrier'.
What is to be done then,
is that in the specialized method,
it is possible to call a general method
higher up,
and then to apply specific actions.
To access the shadowed member
of a given object, we use
a special syntax with a scope
resolution operator (::).
For example, if in the
specialized method 'rencontrer'
of the subclass 'Guerrier',
I want to call 'rencontrer'
as defined in the superclass
'Personnage',
well, in the method I will say:
"I call the method 'rencontrer'
of the class Personnage."
And I make the link between the name
of the method and the name of the class
to which the method belongs
with the scope resolution
operator.
So here, the specialized method
rencontrer calls the hidden, general method
with this special notation.
Then, it follows up with
a certain number of specific actions.
This is very useful, because it
avoids duplicating
the code for all the actions
undertaken in the general method.
We have here, in this example,
thanks to a masked method,
made our warrior a bit
more polite by greeting
his victims before attacking
them, without having to write
the code.
That is all for this episode.
In the next video, we will
look at construction
and destruction in
inheritance.