In this episode, we will consider
the effects of inheritance
on constructors (initialization),
and destructors.
We saw in a previous episode on constructors
that when a subclass is instantiated,
attributes need to be initialized.
This is what we do for example,
when we declare an instance 'r'
of a class Rectangle
by giving its width and height.
This is done with
a constructor
whose job it is to
initialize the attributes.
But if the class Rectangle inherits
from a class FigureGeometrique,
then the class Rectangle inherits
a set of attributes
from the class FigureGeometrique.
So, the constructors of the
class Rectangle
are responsible for initializing
the class Rectangle's attributes,
which comprise those inherited
from the superclass FigureGeometrique.
However, it shouldn't be
the programmer of this subclass
who initializes the attributes
from the superclass FigureGeometrique.
He might even be incapable
of doing this himself
if the superclass had
private data members,
because he couldn't access them.
So, how will the programmer
of Rectangle
accomplish this task?
He will invoke in the constructor
of Rectangle
the constructor of the class
FigureGeometrique.
The initialization of the inherited
data members has to be done
by calling the constructors of the
superclass in the constructor of the subclass.
Let's see how this is written in C++,
first from a general point of view
and then with an example.
Calling a constructor of the superclass
from the constructor of a subclass
is done in the section
"initialization list".
This section,
which begins with a colon,
is positioned between the header
of the subclass and its definition.
So, right after the header of the
constructor of the child class,
in the initialization list, you start
by invoking the parent class in question
so you add the arguments
that you need,
and naturally, the constructor of
the superclass
carries the same name as the superclass.
Then with a comma,
just like we initialize the different
data members,
you would have the rest of
this initialization list
that initializes the data members.
Let's consider the example,
with the class Rectangle, here, that is the child
of the class FigureGeometrique.
We defined a class FigureGeometrique that,
let me remind you,
has a data member 'position'
that is protected
and has a constructor that receives
2 coordinates: x and y
in order to initialize the field 'position'.
So here, in the initialization list of
the constructor FigureGeometrique
we have the initialization
of its field position.
Now, look at the constructor
of the subclass Rectangle,
the constructor of Rectangle will
take as usual
2 parameters l and h to initialize
its width and height,
as before, without inheritance,
but it will also take the 2 parameters
x and y,
we decided here to put them first
but this is not necessary,
to be able to initialize the position
of the FigureGeometrique
through the constructor of FigureGeometrique
that takes 2 parameters.
So, the constructor of Rectangle will
have its 4 parameters
then in the initialization list,
we call the constructor of
FigureGeometrique,
here we chose to call 2 parameters,
followed by a comma,
then the initialization list
of its own data members.
Here we invoked the superclass
constructor
explicitly.
Of course, if the class
has a default constructor,
this explicit invocation
of the constructor
is redundant.
A default constructor,
I recall,
is a constructor that
doesn't take any arguments,
and doesn't need any arguments.
And in this case, it is
not at all necessary to
explicitly call this constructor,
because the compiler will
automatically
call the default constructor.
But we will have in any case
an invocation of the constructor.
However, if the class does not
have a default constructor,
then of course an explicit call
of one of these constructors
needs to be made,
without which, the compiler
would not know what to do.
So, calling a parent class constructor
is mandatory.
If the superclass doesn't have
a default constructor,
then a an explicit constructor needs
to be used
to make an explicit call in the
initialization list of the
subclass's constructor.
Hence, the subclass has to have
an explicit constructor,
to make an explicit call to
the superclass constructor.
Now if our FigureGeometrique
had a default constructor,
it would not have been necessary to make this
explicit call to a constructor,
and we could have omitted it.
Here is a different example,
where the class FigureGeometrique has
a defaulted default constructor.
Let's see what happens in this case.
Here we have the constructor of
the subclass Rectangle that,
in its initialization list, does not
explicitly call
its superclass
FigureGeometrique's constructors,
this is possible because the class
FigureGeometrique
has a default constructor.
We suppose that we didn't write
the constructor
and therefore it has the default constructor
provided by default by the compiler.
So, we have here,
in the beginning of the constructor
of the subclass Rectangle,
a call to the default constructor
of the superclass FigureGeometrique.
Note that here, a default constructor
is called twice,
because here, the class FigureGeometrique,
has as data member, Position,
and because we didn't explicitly
call the constructor,
it it the default constructor,
that is provided by default,
by the compiler,
which will call the default
constructors of each of the data members.
So here, the defaulted
default constructor
calls the constructor
by default of 'Position'.
To summarize, the call
of the constructor of Rectangle,
for example,
if I wrote something like this,
'Rectangle r(3.0, 4.0);
would call the constructor of Rectangle
here by passing 3.0 and 4.0 as parameters,
and would start by calling the
default constructor provided by default,
by the compiler of the
class FigureGeometrique,
which would the constructor
by default of 'Position',
(here I assume that Position
is a class),
and that therefore there is
a defaulted default constructor,
or a default constructor
explicitly written.
We would then first have a construction
by default of the position
that ends the default construction
of FigureGeometrique,
and would then allow
the constructor of Rectangle
to continue initializing its other
data members.
We will come back in an instant
to the order constructors are
called in a hierarchy.
But first of all, I would like
to insist on something.
It is not necessary
to have supplementary fields
in the subclass.
For example, if we have a square,
which is a certain sort of rectangle,
a square is a rectangle where the
width is equal to its height,
then we will not introduce into the
subclass Carre (TN: = "square"),
extra data members.
But we could anyway, in the constructor
of Carre,
and we would have
to do it here,
in this constructor that doesn't
add any fields,
call the
constructor of the superclass.
Look at this example in detail.
We say that a square is a rectangle,
in the class Rectangle, we have as usual,
data members for width and height,
which we inherited from the class Carre
and we would simply say
a square is a rectangle
whose width equals its height.
And we would not add or change
anything else in Carre.
So, we would simply declare the class Carre
as a subclass of Rectangle,
and not add anything in particular.
I will come back with a final remark
in an instant.
Simply,
we will force the constructor here
to take one unique dimension,
the length of the side
of a square,
and to call the constructor of
the superclass
by asking the constructor of
to have the same height and
length,
and we wouldn't add anything
else to the body
of the subclass Carre.
So, and it's simply
these 3 lines here,
and we don't need to add anything.
They suffice to define a square
that is a rectangle
whose constructor is forced
to give it sides of equal length.
Then, when we say that
there is nothing to add,
of course, if in Rectangle,
we had a method
for example the method
SetHauteur
or the method SetLargeur,
then these 2 methods
inherited from Carre
would have to be redefined
so that
the sides of the square
would always be equal.
So we could try to do something
like this,
in the class Carre,
by specializing the method SetHauteur,
which will shadow the method
from Rectangle,
and would, of course set the
height
to the value received,
but would also --and this
is new in Carre--
set the width to equal
the new value too.
Therefore this supplementary
line will be added
in the specialization of Carre,
and we would do the same
for setLargeur.
To summarize, at this stage, each
constructor of a subclass
has to call a superclass
constructor
and this call comes
first on the initialization list.
What happens if we forget to
explicitly call
one of the constructors of the superclass?
Then, a constructor of the
subclass automatically calls
the default constructor
of the superclass
and, as expected, if the superclass
doesn't have a default constructor,
an error occurs in
the compiler.
I will take advantage to remind
you that the default constructor,
that is to say, the constructor
that doesn't take any arguments,
is a bit particular if
we do not write it out.
We have then by default a version
provided by the compiler
of this default constructor.
As soon as we write another
constructor,
this defaulted default constructor
is not available anymore,
and if we want a default constructor,
then we have to rewrite it.
So, to avoid problems
with inheritance,
first of all,
I encourage you to always
declare at least one constructor
and to explicitly invoke a
superclass constructor
in the subclass.
Even though you might
want to call the default constructor,
It is better to write it explicitly
as it makes the code more clear.
So this concludes this first part
of the consequences of inheritance
on constructors.
In the 2nd part,
we will come back to the order
in which constructors are called
in a class hierarchy,
to finish with a few complements.