Let's examine in detail
the order constructors
are called in a class hierarchy.
Suppose for example
that we have defined a class C,
with certain fields
and methods,
and which inherits from a class B,
which has its own data members
and its own methods;
and which itself inherits from
a class A,
with its own data members
and methods.
And so we declare here an instance,
'mon_c' of the class C,
by calling a constructor of a class C.
What happens then, when we
declare an instance, like this for example,
by calling this constructor?
This constructor here,
in its initialization list,
calls a constructor of B,
whether this is written explicitly
or by calling the default
constructor.
Then of course, comes the initialization of
data members.
So when we call the
constructor here,
we start by calling
the class constructor of the class B.
The constructor of the class B
has in its initialization list,
a call to a constructor
of its superclass in turn.
So by calling the
constructor of the class B
in the constructor of the class C,
we first called
the constructor of the
super-super-class A.
So the first thing that will
be done
when a C constructor is called,
is the execution of the constructor
of the highest class in the hierarchy,
the super-super-class here.
And so this constructor
will initialize the data members
'a1' and 'a2'.
And so in the construction of a C,
we start the construction of a B,
which itself launched the
construction of an object A.
The first thing that occurs in
the construction of a C,
is the construction of its inherited
part A,
because of the parental
relationship with A.
C inherits all the data members from B,
B inherits all the data members from A,
so in C we find in fact
the attributes a1 and a2.
So, in the construction of C,
that not yet completed,
we started by constructing
the part from A.
That's the first thing that occurs.
Once we've finished executing
the A constructor,
we come back to the initialization
list in the B constructor,
to initialize the parts that are specific
to the class B,
and so we initialize the attribute
'b1' from the class B.
And after finishing the
execution of the B constructor,
we continue the execution of
the C constructor,
and we end with the initialization
list of the C constructor,
which builds the C part, with
its own attributes.
So after initializing these 3 sections,
we've accomplished the construction of C!
So, in the construction
of a sub-sub-class,
we start by calling the constructor
of the highest class from which
the the constructors of the
intermediate super classes.
We end with part built
by the constructor
of the class that we want
to instansiate.
For destructors,
not much is to be said,
apart from that they are called
in the inverse order.
Destructors are always called inversely
to the order of the constructors.
In the last example,
we first call the C destructor,
because it was the
C constructor
that was last called.
So the first destructor called
in the C destructor,
which calls the B destructor,
which calls in turn the
A destructor.
There are two small details
that we think are worth
the effort to examine
before concluding this part on
constructors and destructors in inheritance.
The first is the
copy constructor.
If you have to redefine
a copy constructor,
which is not necessary
in most cases,
but if you have to do this operation,
then be careful!
In the copy constructor
of a subclass, always remember
to explicitly call the
superclass copy constructor.
For example, suppose that
we have a class Rectangle
that inherits from a class
FigureGeometrique (= 'GeometricShape'),
and this class has an attribute of type 'Position',
that has 2 coordinates
x and y.
and also has for example
2 constructors,
a default constructor,
that initializes the position
at the origin (0,0),
and a constructor
that enables you to initialize
the coordinates (x,y) of the position.
Suppose that we create
an instance r1 of the class Rectangle,
that we initialize with a position,
let's say at (1, 2),
and a width of 3.5
and a height 4.6.
Now we make a copy 'r2' of
'r1'.
We hope that r2, the copy
of r1
has the same position, height,
and width as r1.
But if we write a copy constructor
like this,
without explicitly calling
the superclass copy constructor.
What happens now, when we
try to make a copy of r1 with r2?
We will call the copy constructor
of the class Rectangle.
This copy constructor
of the class Rectangle,
doesn't explicitly call
in its initialization list
a superclass constructor
and therefore calls the default
constructor of the superclass!
Thus, what we start
by doing in the copy of r1,
is initializing the position
of r2 at (0, 0).
So the rectangle r2 will have a position
at the origin, by default
automatically
because of the default
superclass constructor.
Then we copy the width
of r1 in the width of r2,
and the height of r1 in the height of r2.
So, by omitting this line,
we find r2 with a position at (0, 0).
What is to be done,
is to explicitly call
the superclass copy constructor.
This time, what happens is this:
the copy constructor will
explicitly call
the superclass copy constructor.
Without writing this explicitly
we call the default
copy constructor,
which then copies r1 as a
FigureGeometrique.
I remind you that the copy constructor
of FigureGeometrique
has the following prototype
and therefore passes a FigureGeometrique
by constant reference.
Here 'autre' (= 'other') which is a Rectangle
is passed as a FigureGeometrique,
which is absolutely okay,
because a Rectangle is a FigureGeometric.
And so this copy constructor
copies the FigureGeometrique part
of the Rectangle r1, that is to say, copies
the data member of type Position
into the postion of r2.
So we will have here a copy of
the FigureGeometrique part of r1,
which is its postion (1, 2)
in the FigueGeometrique part of r2
that is to say, in the inherited
FigureGeometrique part, Position, of r2.
Thanks to this explicit call
to the copy constructor
of the superclass,
we have r2 that has
the same position as r1.
And then the copy constructor
continues executing as before,
by copying the width and height.
So it is essential to write
the explicit call of the
FigureGeometrique copy constructor,
because otherwise,
the default copy constructor will
intervene, which will
cause problems.
To illustrate this error,
I'll tell an anecdote from
the projects that I give to
my students.
They had to write classes
for vectors,
mathematical vectors,
algebraic vectors,
and they made a subclass
for unit vectors.
Some of them thought they were
shrewd to redefine a copy constructor
for the unit vectors that
inherited from the class Vecteur.
The only thing was, they had forgotten
in the copy constructor
to call the superclass
copy constructor.
But, in fact the superclass
Vecteur had a default constructor,
that constructed a
null vector.
And so they found that
each time they made copies
of unit vectors,
these vectors were null,
which is quite a paradox
for a unit vector.
So, avoid making this
error if you redefine
a copy constructor in a subclass,
and don't forget to call the
superclass copy constructor.
To finish, I would like to
come back to an aspect
that was changed with C++ 2011.
I said that constructors
were not inherited through
an inheritance relationship,
and that a subclass inherited
the set of data members and
methods from its parent class,
but not its constructors
and its destructors.
In C++ 2011, they introduced
what we call
"constructor inheritance".
It is henceforth possible
to ask for constructor inheritance.
By default, we don't have
constructor inheritance,
but if we add a syntax like this,
with the keyword "using", we can add
all the constructors of the superclass.
And then, we can construct
the subclass with all the constructors
and with all the same arguments
as the superclass constructors.
But be very careful,
this is a bit risky.
I therefore advise you
to avoid using
the constructor inheritance,
because the superclass
constructors don't, of course,
initialize the data members
of the subclass,
and so, if we call
a superclass constructor
in the subclass, which is possible
with this new syntax,
then we wouldn't have any
initialization
of the subclass's own data members.
So therefore I advise
you against something like this,
and advise you to do this
only when you don't have
many subclass data members,
and when it's appropriate.
For example, suppose
that we have a super class A,
that has two  constructors,
one that takes a whole number,
and one that takes two doubles.
We also have a subclass B
that inherits from A.
We can therefore, if we want,
inherit the constructors of A in B
by writing this: "using A : : A",
that is to say
by using to the constructors
called A from the class A.
This syntax is a bit redundant,
but that's how it's done:
"using A : : A".
Thus, we have available in B
2 constructors:
one constructor with
an int parameter
and a constructor with 2 parameters
of type double.
But in B, we introduced
supplementary data members,
so be careful, the constructors
in question
will not initialize the other
data members of B
because they are the
constructors of A.
For this reason I recommend
to rarely (or even never) use this function.
But we wanted to mention it
because it was something
that was introduced in C++ 2011,
and which you could encounter.
This concludes this series of videos
on inheritance.