When we introduced the constructors topic,
we saw that these methods
were so important
that C++ provided
a default version.
This is the case notably
with the copy constructor.
We also saw that the
default copy constructor
made what is called
a shallow copy,
which is sufficient in
most cases,
but not all.
In other cases
we have to do what
is called a "deep copy".
This is the topic of this video.
Let me remind you that in C++ there
are special methods
that enable an object to be initialized
at the start of its life: "constructors",
that copy an object into another:
"copy constructors",
or that free up resources associated
with an object: "destructors".
We will only look at
the bare-bone default versions
of these methods, in particular
for the copy constructors.
We saw in a previous episode on the
"counting instances example"
that the minimal default versions
of the constructor and destructor methods
were not always adapted to the situation.
We also saw that
when it was necessary to
define one explicitly,
well, we had to consider
the explicit definition of all the others
as well.
We will now study another example
connected to a default copy constructor
that makes a shallow copy
and we will see this
shallow copy
can cause a certain number of problems
in particular when we have
data members that are " pointers".
Let's start by defining
what a shallow copy does:
in essence, it copies member to member
each data member.
Suppose we have our favorite
class: Rectangle,
and that in a code, we declare
2 objects of type Rectangle.
A Rectangle r1 has its width and
height initialized by
constructors in the class Rectangle
and a 2nd object r2,
of the same type,
which we created and initialized
by copying the Rectangle r1.
Suppose that in the constructor used,
the first argument corresponds
to the height and the second to the width.
Hence r1 is an object
in the memory
that has 2 data members,
width and height, initialized like this.
Suppose that in this class Rectangle,
no copy constructor is
explicitly defined,
which means that the
moment we execute this line,
it's the default copy constructor
that is called.
If we assume that this is the
data member height of r1
and this is its width,
the execution of the
default copy constructor
will result in the creation of
the rectangle r2
whose data members would have been
shallow copied from those of r1.
This means concretely
that the value of the data member
height of r2 will be copied
from the value of the data member
of the same name in r1,
and likewise for the height.
The default copy constructor
therefore copies superficially,
that is to say, makes a
shallow copy of the data members.
When the data members
are "pointers",
contrarily to the example
in front of us,
well, shallow copy,
can then become the root of several problems,
which we will now review.
Let's take another example,
that of a class Rectangle in which
we have chosen to have width and height
implemented with pointers that
point to the values
stored as doubles
instead of just having doubles.
Of course this implementation
is not very smart, does not really make sense,
but let's examine this simple example
for the sake of illustrating our point
The constructor of the class Rectangle
is in charge of dynamically allocating
memory in order to store
the width and height of
an instance of Rectangle.
To recall, this expression allows
memory to be allocated dynamically
for a double, while the code
is being executed,
and to store the value "l".
What is returned by this instruction
is the address of the allocateddouble,
which is stored in
the "largeur" data member,
which is effectively a pointer,
an address.
So by using this definition of
the class Rectangle, it is possible
in another part of the code to
declare an initialization of a rectangle
by using the provided constructor
like here,
the result of which
corresponds to the construction
of an object in the memory
whose 2 data-members "largeur" and "hauteur"
are addresses of doubles
that point to the actuall width
and height of the rectangle.
In C++, he who allocates
is responsible for deallocating.
Here, the class Rectangle
is in charge of allocating
memory space
when a rectangle is created.
This class therefore,
when an object ceases to exist,
deallocate this space,
and this is done of course
by the destructors
of Rectangle.
You will also note that in this
definition of the class Rectangle,
the constructor is explicitly
defined
and the destructor is also
explicitly defined
but the copy constructor
is not explicitly defined,
which means that the default
version would be used implicitly.
Suppose now that a programmer
wants to use the class Rectangle
and so he defines a member function
"afficher_largeur" (TN: means "print_width")
that takes as parameter a rectangle
and the goal of which it is to print the width.
So the programmer could decide
in one section of the program
to declare an object of type
Rectangle
that would be created with
a constructor
that we presented
in the last slide
and then invoke the function
"afficher_largeur" on this Rectangle
to print its width.
To recall, as we have seen, the
object "r" appears like this.
Its members "largeur" and "hauteur" are
addresses that point to
2 memory locations
that contain the values
for the width and the height.
This is what is constructed
when this line is executed.
We would then also like to display
the width of the new rectangle
and to take this risk of
getting a bad surprise.
We might risk making the discovery
that the object "r"
was manipulated
in this display.
But what happened here,
when this function "afficher_largeur",
which is supposed to simply display
the width of our rectangle, was run?
If we scrutinize the header
of this function,
we see that the parameter, the
rectangle whose value we want to display,
is in fact passed "by value".
This means concretely that
when this line of code is run,
the value of "r" will be copied into "tmp"
because we are passing by value,
and the code of this function is
run on this copy "tmp".
Who is in charge of carrying out the
copy of Rectangle "r" into Rectangle "tmp"?
Well, its indeed the copy constructor
of the Rectangle class
which is responsible for the copy.
This constructor however
is not defined explicitly,
which means the default
copy constructor is called.
And it's this default constructor
that makes a shallow copy.
So, at the execution of this line
of code,
an object "tmp" will be
created from the object "r"
by copying it with
the default copy constructor.
This means that "tmp"
will appear like this.
The default constructor
copies member to member
the values of the
different data members.
Suppose that the 1st attribute
contains the value "addresse1",
and the 2nd "addresse2".
If they are copied shallow,
which means concretely that
the 2 fields of the object "tmp"
point to the same memory location
as those of the object "r".
The body of the function "afficher_largeur"
can be executed of course,
because in the object "tmp"
we can access through the
pointer to the width field "largeur"
which is the same as that of "r"
and in this case it displays
the desired values.
However, farther along,
things don't go as well.
Indeed, the parameter "tmp"
in the function "afficher_largeur"
is a local object in the function
and which cannot be used
outside of the function.
This means that when we finish executing
the function "afficher_largeur",
this object "tmp" is not
needed anymore,
and so the destructor will
automatically be invoked on "tmp".
To recall, the destructor of the class
Rectangle was responsible for
deallocating the memory space
associated with the object's data members.
So in our example,
this means that
the moment the function "afficher_largeur"
has finished executing,
the destructor is invoked
on the object "tmp"
which will deallocate memory
associated with its data members.
Unfortunately however, the
memory deallocated
in the destruction of "tmp"
is the same as
that pointed to by
the object "r", which
still exists even after
"afficher_largeur" has finished running!
In reality,
there is no reason why
printing the width of a rectangle
should cause the destruction of the memory
associated with that rectangle!
However, this is nevertheless
what happens here,
and this means very concretely,
that we we are using the rectangle here
to carry out its manipulation,
which in principle,
should not have been obstructed by the
getting its width before.
Well, we are actually working with
a corrupted object
because the memory associated
with it was deallocated.
To summarize our example,
calling the function "afficher_largeur"
by passing as parameter a rectangle "r"
results in "r" being copied "tmp"
with passing by value.
When the function "afficher_largeur"
finishes executing,
"tmp", being used locally,
is destroyed automatically
by a destructor of the class Rectangle.
This destructor will free
the memory pointed to
by the fields width and height of "tmp"
which is the same memory,
as that pointed to
by the width and height of "r".
In this way, using "r" after having invoked
the function "afficher_largeur"
exposes us to several
dangers.
We can see the contents
of "r" eradically change,
we can risk exposing ourselves
to a "segmentation fault",
for instance if the object "r" is destructed afterwards.
The corruption of "r"
following the destruction of the
object "tmp" is closely related to the fact
that these 2 objects refer
to the same memory location,
though this shouldn't be the case.
"r" and "tmp" point to the same
memory because
as we have seen before,
"tmp" was the result of a "shallow copy".
To avoid this problem, the copy
should do what we call
a "deep copy", which doesn't
simply copy the addresses,
but rather copies what
the addresses point to.
This means that we don't want
there to be a link
between "tmp" and the memory
pointed to by "r".
We want to instead create from "r"
an object "tmp" that points
to a separate memory location,
and that would have the same
values as the original object, "r".
In this way,
the destruction off "tmp",
at the end of the execution
of the function "afficher_largeur",
would only affect the
fields pointed to by "tmp"
and therefore would not
modify those pointed to by "r",
which could safely continue to be
used .
The default copy constructor,
that only makes a memberwise
copy, is not adapted.
We therefore need to redefine
the copy constructor by ourselves
so that it makes a deep copy
that copies the memory pointed to.
So we want the constructor to duplicate
the memory pointed to
by a rectangle "r" whose
data members point to doubles.
We want the copied object "tmp"
to be completely independent
whose data member values
are new addresses pointing to doubles
of the same value as those
of the original object "r".
Thus the copy being completely
independent of the original object,
its destruction would have no incidence
on the original object.
The copy constructor
should therefore be written
as to duplicate the locations
pointed to.
Creating a copy "tmp" of the object "r"
by using this copy constructor
is equivalent to the following
situation the memory:
the object "tmp" would have a field width,
"largeur",
whose value would be a new
address,
the address of
a newly allocated object.
Thus the contents referenced to
would be obtained by copying
what the original object pointed to
and likewise for the height
"hauteur".
So if we want
to analyse this more closely,
"obj" is the object we wish to
make a copy of,
this expression "obj.largeur" will give
us the value of the address,
the value pointed to by the address,
which corresponds to the value pointed
to by the original object.
The instruction "new double"
allocates a new memory location
for the field "largeur"
whose value is that of the
original object.
So here is how we
should rewrite this class Rectangle
so as to avoid problems associated
with shallow copying
when data-members are pointers.
We have seen
that a constructor that takes care
of allocating memory
and a destructor that deallocates
are not enough,
but but that we have to also define a
copy constructor that makes a deep copy,
one that doesn't simply copy addresses,
but duplicates the memory pointed to.
Strictly speaking, we
should also redefine
the assignment operator, "operator=",
which, as we have seen in previous episodes,
is closely related to the copy constructor.
The default version of the "operator="
in effect also
makes a shallow copy.
Thus, if we do not define it correctly,
we expose ourselves to the same
problems as forgetting
to correctly redefine the copy constructor.
So, here is the approach
to a class that has data members
that are pointers.
Remember the deep copy
and at least ask yourself:
"Do I have to redefine
the copy constructor
in order that it makes a copy
of the memory space pointed to, or not?"
If we redefine the copy constructor,
also think about the overload
of the assignement operator, "operator=",
that also has to be defined appropriately.
And when we make a deep copy,
we frequently have to use
new memory space
and in this case, also think about modifiying
the destructor.
Finally, a small reminder when we redefine
the copy constructor
in the context of a inheritance relationship,
that is, in a subclass.
Make sure that
the subclass copy constructor
invokes
the superclass copy constructor,
otherwise it's the default constructor
of the superclass that is called,
which can cause the program
to act strangely.