If the history of humanity
could be attempting
to be summed up in one sentence,
it could be said that to begin
with the 190,000 year era
during which resources
were mostly withdrawn
from the natural environment,
that is Palaeolithic.
Then, an 11,000 year period,
during which there was a mix
of predation and production.
During this period, it was possible
to dramatically increase production,
especially, once fossil fuel
sources were mobilized.
‘Ecological awareness’
could now be called the cultural event
leading to the conclusion
among a significant number
of experts and the public opinion
that the Neolithic age
will not be endless.
The argument is quite plausible.
If the predation/production period
continues to demonstrate growth,
someday, the natural inputs withdrawn
from the natural environment
will inevitably be exhausted.
As we'll be seeing later in this session,
this option collides with the image
of traditional agricultural industry,
which perceives the mix
of predation/production
to be a normal, unquestionable
way of life for societies.
It will also be seen
that within the discourses
pertaining to the ecological
awareness corpus,
there are two opposite
families of approaches.
On the whole, there is a set
of three models of nature
which are in competition.
As can be seen on the table,
these models of nature
are also models of society.
As a matter of fact, statements
on natural environments are so pervasive
that they have major consequences
on the way societies are organized.
This is particularly true about space.
Conceptions of inhabited space
clearly differ from one model to another.
If we now more specifically focus
on models compatible
with ecological awareness,
it can be noticed
that they stand in
profound opposition.
Here can be found
two irreconcilable approaches
to the organization of social life.
‘The Limits to Growth’, that is
the Meadows’ report published in 1972,
is a good example
of neo-naturalist interpretation.
It appeared in the wake
of a long intellectual tradition
beginning with Thomas Malthus,
the famous 19th Century
demographer and theologian.
The basic idea is that when
natural resources are limited,
population cannot increase
without provoking massive starvation
and other disasters.
According to a neo-naturalist
point of view,
there is also a moral dimension
as the graph shows.
The neo-naturalist paradigm
always assumes
that intrinsic moral values
are conveyed by natural beings,
be they animals, plants or minerals.
The implementation of these values
contributes to creating
a natural order which man has disrupted.
In this regard, the issue
of biodiversity clearly is critical.
Some biologists warn
of an anthropic seventh extinction,
which might affect from 15% to 50%
of existing species.
It is also true that
back in the Palaeolithic era,
humans, in fact,
destroyed many species.
For instance, scientists have good reasons
to believe that forests were destroyed
thousands of years ago
by the first Palaeolithic societies
living in Central Australia.
And who transformed
a vast area into desert.
However, the four last extinctions
annihilated more than 50%
of previously existing species,
with the Permian extinction --the fifth--
eliminating 70% of terrestrial species
and 95% of marine life
250 million years ago.
The difference this time
does not originate
in the quantity of species
projected to be lost,
nor in the pace of extinction.
Most extinctions,
such as the disappearance
of the dinosaurs
during the Cretaceous,
occurred as a result
of a sudden catastrophic event
such as a volcanic eruption
or a meteorite.
The difference this time
comes from man's supposed guilt.
Keeping the same perspective,
the very notion
of ‘climatic disturbance’ is disputable.
It's supposed that before
human intervention,
the climate was both stable
and consistent, obeying rules,
the antonym of disturbance
being organization or order.
Debates on climate are clearly
marked by the weight of neo-naturalism.
Roger Pielke Jr.
assumed that once
controversial scientific research
meets controversial political issues,
the schola’s role tends to switch
to the stance of an activist.
He detected this tendency
in many documents
overestimating our level of knowledge,
and not only trying to blame
human impact for climatic warming,
but also any orientation
towards development.
The idea of sustainable development
progressively appeared
in the 1970’’s and 1980’s.
Gro Harlem Brundtland's text
‘Our Common Future’ released in 1987
by a UN agency devoted
to the natural environment,
was the first official
political expression
of the sustainable
development orientation.
The term ‘sustainable development’
is not the title
of a complete political agenda,
but rather a general
framework for public debate.
The main idea is that, if we want
to make development sustainable,
and maintain it as efficient
for future generations,
three pillars should be
simultaneously strengthened:
economic growth, social cohesion,
and the preservation
of natural environments.
For promoters of sustainable development,
there’s no antimony
between these three objectives.
Quite to the contrary.
As the graph demonstrates, they are all
the more compatible among themselves,
since each component includes
a substantial intersection
with the others.
Said differently, it could be argued
that each of the three pillars
is a particular way of saying
the same thing, that is:
the crucial necessity
of considering societies’ futures
as long-term processes
supposes encompassing nature
as a dimension
of socio-economic development.
The sustainable development framework
has also clearly identified
the global scale
as the one most relevant
for addressing developmental
and environmental issues.
One of the key issues
in these models of nature
is humanit’s ability to arrange
development programs
which can be efficient
with a decreasing withdrawal
of non-reproducible natural resources.
The graph demonstrates
that bet about decoupling.
The decoupling process shows
that despite the high level of unevenness
persisting inside and amongst societies,
there are significant tendencies
in the World
in favour of overcoming Neolithic logics.
An important and probably dominant part
of human production and activities
has already been the result
of immaterial processes.
The economy of knowledge
is growing daily,
and it is easy to imagine
a production system
in which all natural inputs
are reduced to recyclable sources,
such as water, metals, soil,
or non-limited sources,
such as, wind, sun,
or some day nuclear fusion.
However, it’s true that decoupling
is just the first step.
In a post-Neolithic world,
fossil energy will disappear,
and the destruction of useful
and limited resources
will tend towards zero.
This era has clearly not yet arrived
and the positive impact
of some technological processes,
such as cleaner cars,
has been weakened by the simple
increase in quantities produced.
Much remains to be done
for the construction
of a ‘post-lithic’ production system.