One more concrete example of
the issues raised by
the Sustainable Development
paradigm is space.
Are there certain spatial configurations
more favorable
to the three pillars
of sustainable development?
The following documents show that
the city – that's to say
the urban configuration maximizing
density and diversity –
at its best, clearly satisfies
the requirements
of sustainable development’s
three pillars.
First of all, the compact city is
the best solution for developing
a post-predatory approach to
natural resources.
At this point it can clearly be seen
how the spatial logics
of farming and industry
are the problems.
These two sectors,
are in contradiction
with urban rationales,
as the city is the solution.
As can be seen in Session 5,
however, urban sprawl,
or the ‘Johannesburg’ model,
is not a good answer.
The more an urban area is scattered
and fragmented,
the more negatively it will impact
upon natural environments.
The pillar of economic growth
was analyzed in Session 5.
The map is a reminder
of the strong correlation
between the relative
and absolute urbanity,
and productive efficiency.
Finally, social cohesion turns out
to be to the advantage of the city.
These maps representing
two different cartographic languages
– a cartogram based on population
and a classic Euclidean map –
the degree of income diversity
in each small statistical area
of 2,000 residents
of the Parisian built-up area.
As the maps demonstrate,
the maximum social mix
is attained in city centers,
that’s to say
where density is higher,
city centers are places
where exposure to otherness
is the most accepted,
and even expected by the people,
rich or poor,
who have chosen to live in it.
The misguiding notion of
gentrification,
which is actually,
a way of promoting ghettoes
as a relevant orientation
for urbanism,
appears to be particularly
counter-productive in this case.
Logically, urban issues and
political scenes
are good expressions of
the debates about nature.
To take the example of mobility,
it can be seen that
each of the three
nature-society models
lends its own point of view
to this topic,
which is consistent
to its general rationale.
The second graph shows that
compromises are possible
between these pure orientations.
Anti-urban mobility,
self-mobility,
or the right to mobility are
possible hybridizations
of two of these orientations.
Of course, these compromises
do not eliminate contradictions.
Does self-mobility, for instance,
include high-speed trains?
The neo-naturalist activists
would answer ‘no’,
just as, in the ‘post-lithic’ approach,
a ‘yes’ would be perfectly consistent.
In short, the pivotal role
of nature is confirmed every day
in political controversies,
especially when space is at stake.
The spatiality of nature is,
above all, political.