We will now address space through two
transversal approaches: nature and time.
In the first case, we often mentally
superpose an environment
that has inhabited spaces above,
and another environment beneath: nature.
What if nature was nothing but
a component of society?
Furthermore, many people, including
scholars, have believed, or still do,
that pre-human realities like atoms,
cells, planets or living species
could be sufficient cognitive resources
to explain human behavior.
It can be first argued, conversely,
that human history has its own rationales.
It can be contended, too, that there are
different natures, that none of them
is reducible to the logics of physical
and biological worlds.
Warning: nature is not the opposite
of culture, but a part of it.
Let's try to go beyond this paradox.
The relationships between societies
and natural environments have long been
a substantial component of geography,
to the point that geographical determinism
meant natural determinism
throughout the 20th century
and in many different languages.
Today, things have changed and nature
has become just one particular topic
among others for geographical research,
as it is in the other social sciences,
such as the economy of natural
resources in economics,
or the politics of nature
in political science.
This new situation gives the social
sciences of space the freedom,
and responsibility, to propose fresh
insights into relationships between
inhabited spaces and natural environments.
In this session, the general societal
issues of these relationships
will be examined, in addition to their
spatial dimensions.
What is nature? And how far
can nature be a part
of the exploration of inhabited space?
This is the question we
will be examining in the course.
Let's try to get a simple and clear view
of this subject.
First of all, there is a reality,
the physical universe,
which is studied by the science
of matter, or physics.
Because of the emergence of living
organisms and their logics on planet Earth
there has been a distinct
field of research
to explore the sciences of life,
or biology.
The objects of these studies are,
through their construction,
independent of social life.
They existed before humans appeared
and would continue to exist
even if every human disappeared.
These realities are called
bio-physical worlds.
Now, if we look at societies, we see that
they had high mountains,
which, during millennia, were strongly
repulsive realities, even if they are
now very attractive, as well as
being economically significant
for skiing, trekking, and climbing.
The soil of the western United States
has long been unsuitable
for agriculture until knowledge
of dry-farming was developed.
This was also true for part of the arid
Champagne region of France,
which was incapable of producing high
yields and was called ‘hampagne pouilleuse’
or ‘seedy Champagne’, until new farming
techniques made of it one of the most
efficient cereal crop-producing
zones in Western Europe.
Biophysical worlds have
their own chronology,
and nature has a history,
which is human history.
Nature can then be defined
as biophysical realities,
insofar as they concern societies.
In other words, it could be said that
nature is a social dimension
of biophysical realities.
Therefore, nature should not
be opposed to culture.
Nature is a part of human culture.
Here, the notion of a three-fold
system, including
actors, objects, and environments,
could be useful.
Nature can be considered as an environment
but not the environment.
There are unnatural environments,
like social milieus.
Inhabited spaces are environments.
As for nature, it shouldn't be forgotten
that there are two major natural
environments; the body, and
the external natural environment.
These two envelopes are certainly
environments, and pre-figure
the actors they encompass, but can be
modified by the actors' intentionality.
This is obviously true for the body.
Our body kills us, at the end of the day,
that is our lifetime,
but the psychosomatic impact of our mind
over our body is massive and indisputable.
Volcanic eruptions,
earthquakes, and tsunamis
can kill hundreds of thousands of people.
What has been called the ‘Anthropocene’
is a geological era defined by
the significant impact of human agency
upon Earth's biophysical worlds.
The recent and progressive accumulation
of power by societies gives human actions
the same level of influence
as physical or biological forces,
imposing on humanity a brand new
series of responsibilities.