Hello and welcome to this fourth module of
this MOOC
on protected areas management in Africa.
This module focuses on protected areas management
effectiveness.
In short, how to obtain the best results for
conservation.
So this week, the module will be structured
in the following way.
In the first lesson, we will look at this
notion of management effectiveness
and the different tools we have to evaluate
it in protected areas.
The second lesson concerns
a particular aspect of the work in protected
areas,
namely surveillance of the territory and law
enforcement.
Ecological monitoring, the cornerstone to
impact assessment
will be the subject of the third lesson.
In the fourth lesson we will discuss education
on conservation,
an essential subject for the future
and that we could do an entire MOOC about.
The fifth lesson tackles an approach, which
is just developing,
to know and recognize the best protected areas
in terms of management and governance,
which we call the Green List.
The last lesson concerns our weekly convention
and we will talk about world heritage this
time.
Finally, we will have a quick recap
of the important points discussed this week
in the form of an animation
and your assignment, which relates to that,
will be given out.
So here we go.
Have an excellent fourth week with us.