Welcome to today's lesson
about Management Effectiveness of Protected
Areas.
The reference book that complements this lesson
is the IUCN guidelines on evaluating effectiveness,
edited by the World Commission on Protected
Areas.
The link can be found here.
In addition, on the papaco.org website,
you will find a lot of the evaluation results
from various African countries,
as well as the tools
that we will be talking about in this lesson.
So, let's first of all ask ourselves
why management effectiveness is important.
Let's use the example of lions in Western
Africa.
On the map that we see here,
the historic lion distribution is in grey,
and it is, let's say, a century old.
Except in the forest, on the coast there,
lions were present everywhere in Western Africa.
In dark grey
- all of these spots -
we can see the lion distribution
based on the estimation of a cat specialists
groups,
four IUCN specialists, in 2006.
The estimation shows that-- this is the good
news--
that most of the lions were within or in close
proximity
to protected areas that we can see here limited
by the black lines.
Let's now look at this map that was done in
after a new study was carried out on the area
to control the presence of lions in all of
these sites.
The black is where the lion has been confirmed
present,
and so in all of the other places, the lion
seems to be absent.
They are therefore present in four sites in
Western Africa: Niokolo,
the WAP area - W, Arli, Pendjari -
that we talked about in the lesson on transboundary
areas,
and then, two little parks in Nigeria, Kendji,
and Yankari,
and then, that's it.
Everywhere else, including in protected areas,
the lion has disappeared or it is so rare
that clues of its presence weren't detected.
We can therefore see it in this example of
lions:
even though protected areas have existed for
decades,
they haven't prevented a species from pretty
much becoming extinct,
despite it being an emblematic species.
Unfortunately, many species have experienced
this trend
like the black rhinoceros
which became extinct at the beginning of the
2000s
in the north of Cameroon, in parks in Faro,
in Bouba Ndjida, in Bénoué.
There are many other ungulates that are now
very rare, or extinct,
like we saw in the first lessons, the Oryx
dammah in Western Africa.
Protected areas are therefore, not enough
to preserve ecosystems
if they are not well managed
with the aim of fulfilling their primary objective,
which, to remind you, is the conservation
of nature.
This graph, that we have already seen, shows
the decline of fauna in Africa
in the last 30 years.
I think it is explicit enough,
especially the curve for Western Africa.
Just to remind you, that's a loss of 85% in
35 years for the major park species.
This notion of management effectiveness covers,
very generally, two aspects.
First of all, it refers to our ability to
do our work well,
so, overall, to do it in accordance to what
is expected of us.
Generally, that is what is written in the
management plan.
Effectiveness is therefore our ability to
do our work well.
But that is not enough,
and the other concept that this term of effectiveness
covers
is the impact of our actions.
Is what we do useful for conservation?
The usefulness of our work.
Let's look at the following examples.
A park ranger patrols the park regularly in
accordance with the established plan.
He stops poachers, and so he does his job
well.
However, the poachers are quickly back in
the park
because the judge is corrupt.
The ranger did a good job, but it was pointless.
Another example is an officer who carries
out ecological monitoring
in the park throughout the year.
However, the data he sends off is not dealt
with
or integrated into the decision-making system.
He did his work well, but it was pointless,
and so, in the end, it was not effective.
It is therefore essential
for protected areas management to make progress.
A global analysis of the situation, at the
global level,
shows that, in fact, less than 25% of the
evaluated protected areas
are managed in a way
that can be described as correct:
24% in the world.
In 36% of the cases, it's basic,
et so, more than 40% are under the minimum
requirement.
So to respond to all of this,
the World Commission on Protected Areas has
created an evaluation framework
that allows for methods to be developed that
will be based on the same approach.
This means that we can cater to the diversity
of expectations,
of methods, of competencies, and of contexts
in quite a homogenous way
and by having quite a sound basis for joint
discussions.
Let's have a look at the stages in this framework
one after another.
The stages are very logical and simple.
First of all, there's the context.
Where are we?
Working on management effectiveness
is first of all about identifying the initial
situation,
i.e., the framework
within which we will carry out our activities.
For example, it is in this stage
that we will identify the values of the protected
area.
These are the values that will direct our
work
since we want to preserve them.
It's also at this point
that we will pay attention to the current
threats,
to what could happen,
to the land.
Next is the planning stage.
Where do we want to go?
This stage enables us to pay attention to
the management plans
but also to questions the protected area's
design,
its shape, its structure, its legitimacy,
its location,
its role in the global system of protected
areas in that country.
The next stage in evaluating effectiveness,
considers the methods that will be required.
What do we need?
Here, we estimate the budget,
the human and technical methods that are available,
and the way that we will allocate them.
Naturally, comparatively, stage four looks
into describing
the work done or the work that needs to be
done.
How will we proceed?
We analyze what we are doing,
and, if possible, we compare it with the recognized
standards,
for example, the number of officials per hectare,
the sampling rate required for good ecological
monitoring etc.
That's exactly what we will talk about at
the end of this course
along with the Green List.
Then there's the crucial stage of evaluating
the results we obtained.
What have we achieved?
Here, we identify if the work was carried
out well,
in accordance with the announced plan,
and if it answers our question: did we do
the job well?
It's also here that we make an inventory of
all the products obtained,
for example, the number of patrols done,
the number of educational sessions in schools,
the number of tourists who visited,
and finally, everything related to indicators
that show we did a good job.
Even more important is the sixth and final
stage
in the evaluation framework
which focuses on the impact of our actions.
It is the stage where we evaluate what has
changed in the area,
and that's where we ask if our work is useful.
In particular, it is in this stage that we
need to determine
if the values were well and truly preserved.
For example, it could be
an emblematic animal species like this cheetah.
Of course, it is the hardest stage to complete
and many evaluation tools don't cater for
it.
There we go, we have seen the framework
for the evaluation of management effectiveness.
It is a simple tool made to help us think
about our work
and that will allow us to organize our own
thoughts
in order to progress.
It is a cycle,
and so it's a thought process that needs to
become permanent
and that must influence our work throughout
the whole year.
As soon as the area is affected, that's the
sixth stage,
the context changes and so we need to start
analyzing again.
It isn't very complicated though.
It just needs to become a reflex for the organization
whether that be during the self-evaluations
that we carry out
or if our activities are audited.
Based on the framework, various tools have
been formalized
to allow for the principles to be quickly
applied to the area.
Some tools focus on the protected area networks
like RAPPAM, which is a quick evaluation tool
and it prioritises stages in protected area
management.
RAPPAM enables comparisons between sites
within a coherent whole,
for example, a national protected areas network,
or a system within ecosystems.
Let's take the example of the network of marine
protected areas in West Africa,
RAMPAO, that Charlotte has already talked
to us about,
and let's see with her how it is evaluated.
We evaluate the performance of the Regional
Network
of Marine Protected Areas in West Africa
on several levels.
It is a protected areas network, a network
of sites, of course,
and so the evaluation of the performances
of the sites
is already a very important aspect, and in
fact, most of the RAMPAO sites
do or have done regular evaluations of management
effectiveness,
especially by using known tools such as METT.
Global evaluations of the network's performance
or of its performances as a whole
are mainly carried out by using the RAPPAM
tool.
A first exercise was done in 2010, and, in
fact, it was backed by IUCN.
So, it is an exercise that gathers all of
the members of the network,
the managers, who carry out this evaluation
together,
who identify the progress, the challenges,
and who also recommend network management
improvements.
A second exercise was carried out in 2013
and a larger number of requests was involved
because the number of members had grown within
that period.
It also tried to analyze the current challenges
and recommendations to try and improve the
network.
Other tools focus on evaluating one site in
particular.
A frequently used tool is the METT,
the Management Effectiveness Tracking Tool.
It is a self-evaluation tool made to be used
on one single site.
It allows us to follow the progress of one
site over time,
but, once again, it should not be used to
compare one site with another,
that is what the RAPPAM is for.
Some tools, like the EoH, Enhancing Our Heritage,
a tool created for world heritage, also focuses
on one single site,
but they are complex management analysis tools,
that are to be used when we want to go into
a lot of detail.
Take some time to look at the case studies
introduced in the guidelines on management
effectiveness.
Have a look also at our numerous site or network
evaluations in Africa,
on the papaco.org website.
Finally, have a look at a blank METT questionnaire
to understand the architecture and the principles.
Try and recognize the process from the World
Commission's framework
through this simple exercise.
That's the end of the lesson.
The next episode will be
on putting into practice some of these principles,
particularly that are related to monitoring
protected areas.
Have a great day.