Hello.
In this lesson we will discuss surveillance,
which is a key feature in managing a protected
area.
Protected areas require surveillance,
firstly to ensure compliance with laws and
regulations.
Of course, if all concerned parties have been
involved
in drafting the management plan,
it will be more likely that these laws will
be well-understood and followed.
However, this is not always the case.
Things change, communities move,
the context will evolve,
and so, well-organised surveillance is vital.
In this lesson, we're going to look
at the different elements involved in a surveillance
system.
(man) I've been around since 1999.
Initially, it was more about larger vessels,
because industrial fishing, was what was dangerous.
Since then, we almost have industrial fishing
under control.
No vessel today would consider entering the
PNBA.
We have to board fewer ships
as fines have increased.
Before, people paid 4,800 per person,
and they would be immobilized for 15 days.
Now however, since it's 100,000 ouguiyas per
dugout,
people are thinking twice.
We are talking about a system, or surveillance
setup.
This cannot be improvised,
or if it is, it has to be done in a planned
way.
For it to be effective, surveillance needs
to take a number
of means and requirements into account.
We're going to look at all of these characteristics.
Firstly, the means and equipment required,
then the training of the teams,
the organisation of patrols,
the different levels of surveillance
which must be complementary and organized.
We'll touch on the requirement of financing.
And lastly, we'll discuss data submission
and how to capitalize on surveillance.
Firstly, means and equipment.
Surveillance is generally done in a vehicle
or a boat
for maritime surveillance, as you can see
in this example,
but also on foot.
This is often an area of high expenditure.
For maritime surveillance, we're talking
about the purchase of speedboats and land
vehicles.
All this is very costly.
Maintenance is expensive too.
So it's important to secure sufficient funding
to invest in and to run this surveillance.
In this case, please note that poachers are
well-equipped.
Secondly, teams need to be trained.
You will have noticed
that the evolution of poaching means that
staff training in parks is vital
for their mission of protection to succeed.
Surveillance cannot simply consist
in stopping poachers.
The mission requires tight relationships with
the communities,
and so, an important part of surveillance
consists in explaining, clarifying,
alerting ,and raising awareness among communities
and visitors.
Things don't end when an act of poaching is
found.
It is up to guards to board and detain offenders,
and this is a tricky step
which requires method and experience.
So, in terms of training, please note these
points:
1) Teams must be fully aware of the rules
and regulations
of the site in question.
This seems obvious, but needs to be said.
2) It's vital to acquire the methods and tools
for negotiation.
3) They must have certain communication skills
so as to inform communities and to talk.
Please note that in certain countries in Africa,
the management of protected areas is undertaken
by civilians,
whereas in many other countries, such as the
Ivory Coast,
or the Democratic Republic of Congo,
managment and surveillance is carried out
by military bodies.
The organisation of patrols.
The organisation of patrols and surveillance
must be dissuasive,
and based on a strong presence on the ground.
There is a high chance for poachers and offenders
to be caught.
So teams on the ground must be optimally distributed
according to available resources,
and given the means
to be able to get around quickly based on
information,
to conduct both planned and random patrols,
for instance at night,
based on information received,
or even to improvise a response to new information.
The work of surveillance teams must be monitored
so as to be able to assess their activity
on the ground
and the areas covered by patrols.
The use of GPS now enables coverage to be
mapped
and to see which areas are monitored per day,
per patrol
or over longer periods.
Now let's look at this example
of maritime surveillance patrols
in the PNBA.
There are several levels of surveillance
and I'd like to insist on the complementarity
of these different levels.
Surveillance patrols must be on the field,
in speedboats or cars or on foot.
They must be able to get to locations
and also to be able to communicate with the
populations,
so as to intervene directly.
But there is also a extra level which is much
wider.
Today, with the help of GPS and aerial techniques,
surveillance can be carried out more remotely.
Then, groups on the field can intervene.
Let's look at the example of the PNBA, which
has
both surveillance on the field with surveillance
speedboats
as well as a radar station
which enables flying over and seeing the whole
maritime area.
There are also guards on the field.
It's very important
that these two complement each other.
I would like to draw your attention to the
fact that well-organized
and well-understood surveillance
will be able to include community participation
on top of that of the guards
and professional surveillance
and that of military bodies.
Let's look together at the example of the
PNBA,
for which tripartite surveillance has delivered
results.
Data submission is very important.
After a patrol, guards will submit
a certain amount of information
to their surveillance team.
Here again, you can see the example of the
PNBA.
All instances of boarding
which took place in the maritime territory
have been geo-logged.
And you can see over a 10-month period in
2009,
the map for boardings of "lanches" (non-motored
boats) and dugouts,
either from inside or the outside.
It's this type of tool that enables analyses,
and to determine where surveillance needs
to be increased,
and where its best understood,
or at which places changes and threats are
occurring.
By now you'll know that surveillance is a
key factor
in the effective running of a protected area.
Today's poachers are using more and more sophisticated
methods.
Surveillance teams and guards
must be able to compete with them
in a complementary way,
listening to the populations.
Frequently, tripartite teams have proven their
worth
and have communicated their results in a way
that enables communities
to better understand the role of surveillance.
Thank you.
That's this section over.
Good day.