Welcome to today's course, focused on ecological
monitoring of protected areas,
what it is, what it is for, how to do it.
There are, unfortunately for us, as many materials
to look up,
as there are monitoring processes,
and you can find some models in this PAPACO
study.
Of course, it's far from complete,
so once again I asked Béatrice Chataigner,
from IUCN PAPACO in Nairobi,
to help us go through it.
I don't know what the zebra just told her,
but it seems like she's having fun.
Let's see with her what ecological monitoring
actually is.
Ecological monitoring is a set of data collecting
and analysis methods
that will enable to measure the status and
evolution of protected areas' values,
and that will monitor the threats that these
values might suffer.
If you can recall what was said during the
planning course,
the values, in fact, are the principal reason
why a protected area is created,
and these values can be, for instance, the
population of a given animal species,
for which the ecological monitoring will enable
us to know if this species
continues to survive, if it can survive,
and to understand whether its population can
increase,
and improve over time, and within a given
territory.
Keep in mind that each protected area has
its own values.
These values aren't the same from one area
to another
because stakeholders' interests when they
set up the values are very different
depending on the protected areas' context,
culture, history, its ecology.
For instance, a community can give a lot of
importance
to a particular species, like the hippopotamus,
here on the screen,
so they might consider that the protected
area's goal
is to ensure the species preservation.
In that case, the ecological monitoring will
be centred on the river
where the hippos live.
Whereas elsewhere,
the hippo might not be a species people want
to preserve,
especially if residents have problems with
them.
Another example could be where a community,
considers that the value of a protected area
is the water spring
at the centre of it, because this spring turns
into rivers
that communities use everyday for they daily
activities.
If that spring is a value,
that spring exists thanks to a river basin
existing nearby,
which captures the water and then pours into
the spring,
so monitoring the state of health of this
spring,
,since it is the value of the protected area,
is in fact monitoring the state of health
of the river basin.
A neighboring protected area can have different
values,
so its ecological monitoring will be totally
different
because it will monitor different values.
There is no unique recipe for ecological monitoring,
it is specific to each protected area.
This is logical.
Planning is of course specific to each protected
area
and planning heads towards the conservation
of these values.
Ecological monitoring should be, likewise,
adapted to each site,
and intrinsically bound to the values it preserves.
Ecological monitoring is therefore a method
of assessing
a value's health, seeing how it evolves,
and also taking into account the evolution
of the threats it faces,
to see how they were reduced, or not.
So thanks to this ecological monitoring we
mesure the value's health
to see if the actions carried out
to protect these values succeeded or not.
And these managing actions stem from the managing
scheme.
In other words, the ecological monitoring
enables us to mesure the impacts
of managing actions on the values,
which makes it an essential method to assess
the effectiveness
of the managing scheme in general.
In some ways, it's a barometer
of the effectiveness of the management of
the protected area.
To get there, it is necessary for ecological
monitoring to provide
accurate and relevant data on the state and
the evolution of the protected area.
In some cases, time and resources can be lost
collecting useless data.
We can sometimes realise that none of the
real values of the protected area
are truly measured by direct or indirect data
collected
during the ecological monitoring,
which will obviously restrict the opportunities
to make informed decisions for the preservation
of these values.
Results of ecological monitorings are also
means of communication.
Firstly, with stakeholders committed to the
protected area's management
as it enables us to show them how far we've
come,
what planned actions have taken place, what
impact they've had,
and it's also a simple and efficient tool
to inform other contributors and lessors
on the advancement state of the activities
for the values' conservation.
For that communication to be efficient, you
need the results
of the ecological monitoring to be presented
as a map,
simple, readable, intelligible, understandable
by everybody.
You need to avoid by all means complex unreadable
charts
that nobody can understand.
It is important to use a geographical information
system
that produces complete and readable maps
that everybody will easily read and understand.
But, careful.
Data can be sensitive.
For instance, the exact breakdown of a particularly
poached species
should not be communicated with a large audience.
It's logical.
The rhinoceros, white or black, is a good
example of that.
So, in practice,
how do we build and develop the ecological
monitoring of a protected area?
Once we decided to monitor the state of health
of our values,
firstly we need quite a few indicators to
properly mesure the state of health,
and then, there is an important choice to
make about the relevant metrics.
Let's take the example of a protected area
where there are many ecosystems
and the savanna ecosystem is considered to
be the value of the protected area.
So in that case, we'll consider which indicator
we need
to monitor the state of health of this savanna.
In general, what happens is that we monitor
the key ecological attributes,
and that will constitute indicators.
So, what are they?
It can be for example some features
of the vegetal and animal populations forming
this savanna,
and the indicators that we will monitor
could be the size of the population of a particular
vegetal species,
that could be a very fragile one, or a fragile
animal species,
and this will ascertain the threshold of the
savanna ecosystem's health.
It can also be the geographical breakdown
of the vegetal and animal species,
or its intra-population composition.
When selecting these indicators, we have to
choose the most relevant
amongst a large set of indicators we could
monitor.
Once we made that choice, it is important
to ensure
that the metrics will inform us on the state
of health,
whether it improves or not,
to make sure that we will have data, whatever
scenario happens.
Let's take a simple example to illustrate
this idea.
We know that the elephants have a visible
effect on the forest cover,
because as they move and feed themselves
they break trees, eat the barks, etc.
So we have a direct effect,
a direct link between elephant density
and the quantity of broken trees in the area
where they move and live.
We could use as an indicator, for instance,
the health of the forest cover.
If we have many broken trees,
we can assume that the elephant density is
quite high in the area.
But then imagine, that, for example,
the elephant population has been suddenly
eradicated by poachers
so elephants would all have disappeared,
but not the broken trees, still standing there,
which means that this indicator we chose would
still be there,
accounting for a large elephant population,
while in fact they would all have been killed
overnight by poachers.
For each type of indicator to monitor,
there are in fact many data collection protocols
that we can use,
there is really quite a large number of them.
We can either take a census over the whole
territory, exhaustively,
or we can proceed to sampling.
This can be done by foot, by car, by plane,
depending on the environment and the conditions.
But each method has its own protocol
that has to be followed in a very strict manner.
Sometimes, we will count a species, sometimes,
we will count individuals.
Sometimes, we will only count tracks, indirect
evidence.
But anyway, we always choose the monitoring
method
that will end up being the most profitable
on a price-efficiency ratio.
What does this mean?
It means that we will choose a method that
will give the best possible quality
both in terms of quantity of data, and frequency
collection,
and to make sure that it will be done at a
lesser cost.
There are many methods, that we can't all
list here,
some are more frequently used than others,
though.
For instance, those that you will find in
the appendix of the study
carried out by PAPACO on ecological monitoring.
A commonly used method is photo trapping,
sometimes video trapping,
which enables us to observe what happens in
the ecosystem
without disturbing wildlife.
On the screen you can see some results of
the ecological monitoring
in the National Park of Lopé, Gabon,
that's the park where our university diploma
is run.
There.
Some interesting images, quite gratifying
to see.
Be careful next time that you go for a walk
in the forest.
Obviously, Big Brother is everywhere.
But do not mix up ecological monitoring and
research.
Research aims to answer a scientific question
to explain an event or a situation.
It is an important element in the protected
area management,
but rarely a daily tool in territory management.
Of course, those two are complementary and
can information can be shared.
In practice, it is true that data from ecological
monitoring
is useful to trigger research work,
because thanks to the collected data, coming
from ecological monitoring,
we can see evolutions appear, and then, we
can ask questions,
scientific questions that research will aim
to answer.
It helps to formulate research questions,
but keep in mind that it isn't the main goal
of ecological monitoring.
To sum up, ecological monitoring is a central
element
of the protected area management,
because it is a way to mesure the management
impacts on values
and consequently, to redirect management if
needed.
So, it is essential to have it set up
and run by the protected area managers themselves,
and not to leave that to external contractors,
who have no responsibility in the territory
management.
Take time to think about a protected area
you know
and try to define elements that the ecological
monitoring should mesure
according to the values of the territory and
the threats it faces.
Then try the opposite exercice,
read about already set up ecological monitorings
to see if they monitor the values of the protected
area or not.
You could be very surprised with the results.
Here we are, it is the end of this class.
In the next episode, we'll talk about raising
awareness for conservation.
Have an excellent day!
A partnership between André Hoffmann, Ecole
Polythechnique Fédérale de Lausanne,
and IUCN.
This MOOC results from the academic collaboration
amongst the following institutions: