Today we will look at raising awareness
for the conservation of protected areas.
The document you should look at to complement
this lesson,
is the toolkit on Communication Education
and Public Awareness,
edited this time by the IUCN Commission on
Education and Communication.
Their website can be seen here.
So, to convince you that this aspect of protected
area management is important,
I am giving you here a reminder of the Aichi
Target that includes
the individual's awareness of conservation.
As you can see, it is the first target, and
that is not a coincidence.
So for this lesson, once again,
Béatrice Chataignier from IUCN PAPACO in
Nairobi
will help me along with her zebra, who looks
like he's in great shape,
and who we will call Nestor.
Like we have seen in the previous classes
on governance and planning,
active participation by all stakeholders
in decision-making
and just as much, in managing activities themselves
is essential,
so that they know and recognize and therefore
retain
the protected area's values
and also so that they feel responsible for
these resources.
These stakeholders could be close to the protected
area,
like for example, from the local community
or the local politicians,
or even from private neighbouring companies
etc.
But these stakeholders could also be far away,
like at the central services of protected
areas management,
users of bush meat, coal, or wood
that may be living in far away towns
or even farmers who pump river water
down stream from a protected area.
Either way,
as users,
they need to understand the importance of
protected areas
to safeguard their future and the products
that they depend on.
If the parties who intervene in and around
protected areas
do not become aware that the resources they
use daily
are limited and need to be used on a reasonable
basis,
and even, that some need to be preserved,
then these users will continue to increase
the threats
weighing on the protected area,
and thereby damage the ecosystems
and all of the services they provide them
with
and that these protected areas help to preserve.
And so if all these stakeholders that we have
just listed,
who intervene,
who actually impact these protected areas,
whether that be from far away or from close
by,
if these parties don't become aware that,
in fact, one way or another,
they are affecting these protected areas,
and subsequently, the ecosystems' services
and the natural resources they protect,
then they will continue to use them in an
irrational way.
There will therefore be no hope for the future,
for the sustainable use of these resources.
That is why it is vital to make them aware
of the role
that they have to play in the conservation
of natural resources.
In Kenya, for example, the lion plays a crucial
role
in balancing out ecosystems of course,
or even in photo tourism.
And yet, the local breeders see lions
mainly as a problem,
and of course, they act accordingly,
which is why they need to be informed and
made aware.
In practice, what should we do to reach these
actors
and to make them interested
in the conservation of nature, in general,
and particularly in protected areas?
Paradoxically, while the research, which is
very extensive, shows
that the situation is critical for the survival
of certain species,
well, that isn't enough to convince all of
these actors.
Why?
Because very few of them have access to the
results from the research,
starting with political decision-makers.
And so, in the end, these people don't use
the data,
even though they are extremely relevant,
because they are either rarely communicated
or badly communicated;
either way, they are misunderstood and eventually
not used.
And that's the aim of raising awareness,
it's making the data, which is so vital, available
and accessible
to this large panel
of stakeholders.
In
many Central African countries,
the drop in the elephant population due to
poaching for ivory
is alarming,
and yet if we look closely,
a small percentage of poachers or traffickers,
who are arrested, are eventually sanctioned
by the court.
It is therefore urgent to intervene at the
magistrate's level
to make them aware and to educate them to
treat these cases
with the same severity as the stakes at play.
And these stakes impact more than just biodiversity.
For example, trafficking impacts the country's
tourist economy.
Of course, we also need to intervene with
ivory consumers,
which are mainly Asian countries,
and China in particular.
I'm sure you can imagine how hard that is.
All of this isn't easy
and it is not just because something is communicated
that we will see some action follow on the
field.
There are many obstacles to overcome
so that the information is first heard by
the target audience,
and of course understood,
accepted,
incorporated,
and then implemented,
and even repeated,
if that is necessary.
Therefore, saying it or communicating it,
does not necessarily mean doing
or making them do something.
So, what do we do?
And for that, we need to first identify the
emotional reasons
or the customs that drive these stakeholders
to act like they do.
That means we need to be able to identify
their personal concerns,
what they are interested in,
what interests them in their daily life.
We need to make the link between natural resources
that we want to protect
and show them that what's best for them is
to change their behaviour
to preserve this resource that they are in
fact using.
So this message needs to be well and truly
clear,
directly linked to their concerns,
and so strike a chord emotionally with these
parties.
It also needs to be explicit enough for them
to understand exactly
what they need to change
and the alternative action they must perform.
That is extremely important,
it is about grasping the message.
For that reason, we need to not forget that
it is when we dialogue with them
that adults learn best,
because it is in that situation that they
will be acknowledged the most
and they will considered responsible learners
and the experiences and the knowledge they
have gained
will be shared and better recognized.
For them, it is the best way to be taken into
consideration
and so to change how they do things.
Thus, the methods we use to raise awareness
must be specifically adapted to each audience.
There are many examples of campaigns,
mainly through social media nowadays.
What
is
therefore the actual impact of all these efforts
for these awareness initiatives in terms of
conservation?
At what point can we hope to see a change
in behaviour?
These are very difficult questions.
How much time would we need
to measure the impact of growing public awareness
once it has started?
Changes brought in amongst young people, the
new generation,
are usually faster and easier.
It is an absolute priority to educate and
to raise awareness among all these young people,
all these children,
because it is them who will change our society.
Have a look on the internet at some public
awareness campaigns
led by the big conservation NGOs.
Some of the websites are suggested here.
See if the target audiences of these campaigns
have been well understood,
if the messages that have been distributed
give the target audience
an opportunity to act at their level.
There we go, that's the end of this lesson.
The next episode will be on the Green List
of protected areas.
Have a great day.