Hello, today we are going to look at a tool,
recently developed by the World Commission
on Protected Areas and IUCN,
which is called the Green List of Protected
Areas.
Why a Green List, what is it and what is it
for?
You can find out more on the Green List website.
The address appears here.
Once again, to help me in this lesson,
I think you will recognize the team:
Nestor and his friend Béatrice.
The first question that we will ask
is about the reasons
behind the development of the Green List.
The IUCN Red List,
that we will talk about later in this MOOC,
focuses on species that are at risk of extinction,
so species that are in danger.
It provides an evaluation of the major threats
which put a strain on the planet's species.
We understand that identifying the threats
that are urgent to counteract,
to ensure preservation of biodiversity is
essential.
But it is also extremely important
to share the success, to show what works,
wherever in the world we are.
This is exactly the purpose of the Green List,
to show the protected areas that work,
that have succeeded in reaching their goal
of conservation,
whatever their system of governance,
however they are managed,
no matter where in the world they are, there
are successes
that we must be able to share with other areas
that find themselves in similar situations,
that need to make progress
and in order to do that, they need to be inspired
by other's conservation success stories.
In short, this Green List is above all, a
new label.
Do we need a new label when there are already
so many?
There are in fact already many labels associated
with protected areas.
But in general, they only concentrate on a
few specific aspects
of these protected areas.
For example, UNESCO's MAB, Man and the Biosphere
designates biosphere reserves,
or WWF's PAN Parks,
which aim at certifying the quality
of the tourism services of a site
in terms of conservation.
Or another label such as Ramsar,
which recognizes the importance of wetlands.
As for World Heritage,
it identifies an element of the protected
area
as having an extraordinary universal value.
Contrary to World Heritage,
which recognizes an extraordinary value within
a protected area,
,a value that existed before,
the Green List will be concerned with the
way in which the managers
will manage and govern this protected area
to preserve its values in general.
So the Green List has the advantage
of recognizing a job that is well done by
management
and then being able to share that to other
sites
or managers who wish to learn.
It's an important detail: contrary to World
Heritage
the Green List doesn't look at the intrinsic
value of the site,
it is about measuring, qualifying
the governance and the management of the site,
in order to recognize the quality of the manager's
work.
Youssouf, who is going to talk to us
in the next lesson on World Heritage,
will tell us a little about it now.
Although the World Heritage sites
are supposedly well run,
it's not the case for all of them,
to the extent that they lose partially
the value or values that warranted their inclusion,
either due to an ineffective management system
or governance.
These World Heritage Sites cannot
therefore be included to the Green List,
because their management system or governance
does not allow
the long term conservation of their outstanding
universal value.
Conversely, a lot of protected areas that
are eligible for the Green List,
will never be able to make it onto the World
Heritage List
as they do not have an outstanding universal
value.
Thus the Green List is a powerful process
for recognizing the efforts of managers
to govern and manage their protected area
well.
What these managers can expect in return,
as benefits
of the Green List,
is firstly a greater visibility for marketing,
for example,
because this is a label with worldwide recognition,
that can also reinforce a plea on a national
level,
for the recognition of protected areas
within the national system of protected areas,
for example.
It is also a way of lobbying to anticipate
the unsustainable use
of certain resources around the protected
areas,
and sometimes in the protected areas.
It is also helpful when it comes to fundraising,
for example,
it can be motivating for staff
as they are seen as having done a good job.
It's a way of improving the working standards
and staff competency.
Another of the major advantages that the Green
List brings,
is that the protected areas that take part
in this process
will directly benefit from the experience
and successes
of the protected areas that already appear
on the Green List.
So it is a way of constantly being required
to progress
and to improve practices on a daily basis.
So more specifically, how does the Green List
work,
how do you get on this list?
This is a totally voluntary procedure
for areas that decide to participate
this means that candidate PAs must put together
their own application themselves.
This application is made up of two things.
It's easy.
One part is a questionnaire, made up of a
list of indicators
which give information about the requirements
of the Green List.
So this is a whole list of questions to which
the manager will respond.
And then,
the second part of the application, is all
the evidence
proving that the responses on the questionnaire
are true.
This can be maps, documents, reports, photos,
a whole pile of evidence, proof
that backs the responses on the questionnaire.
The application is then examined by a reference
group,
a group of experts, on a national scale
which will analyse and assess
the appropriateness of the supplied information
in meeting the requirements of the Green List.
If this reference group is satisfied,
it transfers the application to an external
certifier or auditor,
who will again analyse the application
and check that the information is provided
and with enough detail,
and check that the group of experts' working
method was suitable.
If the auditor is satisfied,
he finally transfers the application
to the global committee of the Green List,
which is at IUCN's head office,
and who is the independent authority
that makes the final decision
whether or not to include the site on the
Green List.
So how is the development of the Green List
going
on a worldwide level or in Africa in particular?
The pilot phase lasted two years and ended
at the end of 2014.
It enabled eight countries to test the process
in their countries.
Those countries are:
Korea, France, Spain, Italy,
Kenya, China, Australia and Colombia.
At the end of this pilot phase,
24 protected areas were included on the world
level list.
Two of them are in Africa,
in Kenya as it was the pilot country for Africa.
In Kenya, there are two private conservancies
who have been added do the Green List,
Lewa and Ol Pejeta Conservancy,
recognized for the excellence of their management
and governance.
And now the process is up and running
and it allows the inclusion of new countries
and new protected areas on the Green List.
The objective is to achieve in two years a
mechanism
that is well-oiled and tested on the ground
so that it is long lasting in Africa.
The Green List of Protected Areas is therefore,
above all,
a tool to stimulate learning by example
by identifying and explaining best practice.
We can expect that it will progressively become
a new source of motivation
for all managers of protected areas around
the world.
On the Green list website, the address appears
here,
take the time to look at the requirements
and indicators
and how they are outlined.
It should serve as a guide to our future activities
in and around protected areas.
It is the end of this lesson.
The next episode will be about World Heritage
with Youssouf, as I said earlier.
Have an excellent day.