Hi, and welcome to the class.
Today, we'll talk about
the World Heritage Convention.
The reference reading as a complement of this
class
is of course, the convention itself and its
operations guidelines
if you would like get into more details.
A quick look at this document will help you
know more
quite rapidly and, of course, you can also
check out UNESCO's website -
The link is right here.
You will also find on papaco.org
many evaluation results of World Heritage
sites
conducted in Africa these last few years.
For this class, as I said in the last class,
an IUCN papaco's colleague, Youssouph Diedhiou,
based in Dakar, Senegal, is going to help
me out.
He is specifically in charge of world heritage
conservation.
So, let's see with Youssouph where this convention
comes from,
and what its exact purpose is.
World Heritage is the legacy of the past
that we enjoy today and that we're passing
on
to the next generations.
World Heritage Convention looks at the sites
that have an outstanding universal value
that we'll define later on.
What triggered its creation
was building the Assouan dam, in Egypt,
that was going to flood Abou Simbel's and
Philae's temple.
Facing this threat, UNESCO started
an international cooperation in 1959 in order
to protect
these major architectural sites.
Then started long discussions
on how to set up a mecanism
to protect these exceptional sites.
These discussions ended upon elaboration of
a text called
the Convention concerning the protection of
Cultural and Natural Heritage,
that was adopted in 1972 in Paris,
during the UNESCO general assembly.
This convention's objectives are to identify
and protect these exceptional sites, but also
to introduce them
to the international community.
The convention helps States parties
by reinforcing their sites management capacity.
It also helps the States parties
to safeguard their sites,
by reinforcing their technical capacity
but also by bringing them
professional assistance.
At site scale, it supports
the local communities' participation
to cultural and natural heritage protection.
Finally, the convention brings an international
support
to immediate danger
exposed sites.
Youssouph told us, this convention
looks at sites that have
an outstanding universal value.
What does it mean, specifically?
The outstanding universal value
means a cultural or natural importance that
is so exceptional,
that it transcend borders
and that its invaluable characters stay the
same
for present and future generations.
This outstanding universal value has three
components.
The first one affects criteria that
are numbered from one to ten.
The first six criteria involve cultural sites
and the last four criteria,
meaning seven, eight, nine and ten,
involve natural sites.
The second component is integrity.
Integrity describes the untouched values
that we want to see
appear on the World Heritage List.
The third and last component
is the management system that must be effective
in order to allow this universal value transmission
to next generations.
All of this is only theorical of course,
but it's the spirit of the convention.
Okay, all of this isn't necessarily
very easy to understand the first time,
so let's have a few examples
to better understand.
For the seventh criterion, let's have a look
at
the Mount Kenya National Park, with its spectacular
landscapes,
its peaks and its cliffs.
The seventh criterion is simply relating to
the beauty,
the exceptional aesthetic of a territory.
For the eighth criterion, let's look at
the National Park of Virunga, in Democratic
Republic of Congo.
It consists of seven volcanoes two of them
being
the most active in Africa right now.
The eighth criterion relates to Earth geological
evolution
and to what helps us understand it, or see
it today.
Regarding the ninth criterion, let's look
at National Park of Nakuru,
that is part of a lakes network;
in between which the lesser flamingos
of the Rift Valley travels.
The ninth criterion shows the natural evolution
of ecosystems on earth,
as shown by the functioning
of this migration.
Finally, the tenth criterion relates to biological
diversity.
The National Park of Niokolo Koba in Senegal
is a good example.
It's a very rich ecosystem, in flora and fauna,
at least, at the time of its enlisting.
What is the situation of World’s Heritage
sites
in Africa, nowadays?
The state of conservation of African World
Heritage sites
is very concerning,
With 35% of the sites registered on the in
danger list
some of which for over 20 years.
A site is registered on the in danger list
if it's threatened by a proved, precise and
upcoming danger.
For example, poaching of its biodiversity,
or when it's facing serious threats,
such as an upcoming conflict outburst
or heavy programmed infrastructures,
such as the mine on Mount Nimba in Guinea.
This deterioration of African goods
is linked to several factors,
and the most important are
anthropic pressure
such as poaching, agriculture,
the development of mining.
This is conveyed by an unsuitable budget,
insufficient staff,
and deteriorating infrastructures.
All of this does not allow to sustainably
preserve
the universal outstanding value of those sites.
Since 2008, the IUCN made several assessments
on management effectiveness of those sites
and the overall outcomes
of these assessments confirm this state of
deterioration
of these African world heritage sites.
A big thank you to Youssouph.
Now, we know the essential points.
Take the time to check out the UNESCO website
about World Heritage.
Look at what the criteria for registration
of these sites are,
the ones that you know,
and analyse which are the threats that they
face,
and why they are, or are not, at risk.
That's the end of this class.
Next episode will be the conclusion
and then the homework for this week.
Have a great day!