Working on management effectiveness is about
assessing
the ability of a protected area to preserve
its values.
This allows to identify the quality daily
work:
Am I working well?
But especially to measure its usefulness:
does what I do serve a purpose?
This is the notion of responsibility tied
to governance.
When done regularly, an assessment of effectiveness
allows to
redirect management actions to respond to
identified problems.
There are numerous tools that have been developed
based on the evaluation framework
prepared by the World Commission of Protected
Areas.
This tool is made up of six simple and logical
steps.
Where am I?
Where am I going?
What do I need?
How do I do it?
What is the result?
What has changed?
Some tools assess networks, such as RAPPAM,
others focus on one site, like METT.
In all cases, the evaluation should be a voluntary
process
conducted by, or with, the managers,
and bringing together all parties
involved in the management of protected areas.
Monitoring a protected area is essential for
effectiveness
because it allows for threats,
faced by the values, to be controlled.
Good monitoring is the result of a meaningful
analysis
and of prioritizing threats.
The monitoring strategy should be flexible
and adjustable
according to the evolution of these threats
and the values concerned.
Ecological monitoring is another aspect of
effectiveness
and it consolidates methods of collecting
and analyzing data
which will measure the evolution of protected
area values.
There are many direct or indirect methods.
The choice of method will depend on its effectiveness.
Ecological monitoring must be carried out
by, or at least, with the managers
and not simply entrusted to an external contractor
who has no responsibility for the management
of the area.
Effective management is also about managing
together
and this is widely dependent on the support
and collaboration of all,
when it comes to conservation.
Therefore, we have to ensure
that everyone understands the priorities of
protected areas.
Education and awareness enable citizens' perceptions
to evolve
towards a more realistic understanding
of the importance of protected areas in their
everyday life.
It is an essential strategy to anchor conservation
as a common cause.
It is certainly difficult to measure the impact
of this awareness on behavior,
and yet this has to be an absolute priority.
Finally, in this module we have seen how the
Green List will enable us
to recognize, at a global level, the quality
of the managers' work,
not only in terms of their management effectiveness,
but also for the quality of their governance,
which finally allows us to fully measure
the responsibility of each person.
The Green List will be a powerful way
to encourage protected areas to follow the
best examples,
by transmitting useful tools to all sites
on their journey to be added to this unique
list.
Now, let's start this module's test.