Welcome back to part 3 of this chapter 5.
I have somewhat rearranged
the figures that Peter Hore has chosen
to illustrate this chapter
by starting with an example
taken from proteins.
Indeed, the determination
of the structure of proteins
is one of the principal applications
of the Overhauser effect today.
Recall that proteins are large molecules
and therefore tumble slowly
and therefore the Overhauser Effect
is dominated
by the zero-quantum transition probability
between near-degenerate spin states,
that is to say, the flip-flop rate,
so that the Overhauser Effect
leads to a loss in signal.
Proteins, as you should know,
are basically polymers of amino acids.
Each amino acid contains
a number of protons
and these protons can be assigned
by methods that we
shall discuss in Chapter 6.
Since the Overhauser Effect
is predominantly driven
by flip-flop terms,
it tends to attenuate signals.
So, the question really is,
if we irradiate selectively
a proton that is attached
to amino acid number a,
could it be that a proton attached
to amino acid number d
is partly attenuated
because of the Overhauser Effect.
If that occurs, we must come
to the conclusion that amino acid a
must be close in space to amino acid d,
because the vehicle that allows
the Overhauser effect to occur is
the dipole-dipole interaction,
which, as we have seen, decreases
as the sixth power of the distance.
So, we come to the conclusion
that the protein cannot be a linear chain
but that amino acids a and d
must be close in space.
Likewise, we can do an experiment
where we irradiate a proton
belonging to amino acid b, and we find
that there is an attenuation of the signal
of a proton of amino acid f,
and we come to the conclusion
that b and f must be close
in space, and likewise c and d, etc.
In fact, one can typically determine
hundreds or even thousands
of so-called “distance restraints”
and conclude that certain pairs
of amino acids must be
close together in space.
It is one of the merits of Kurt Wüthrich
at ETH in Zürich to have shown
that if you have a sufficient number
of such restraints, you can determine
a unique structure--
not just a structure
that satisfies all restraints,
but that there is only one structure
that fullfills all of them
at the same time.
This is one of the reasons
why Kurt Wüthrich
got a Nobel Prize in 2002.
Although applications to proteins
are very important nowadays,
we should not forget that we can also use
Overhauser effects very fruitfully for
stereo chemistry in simple molecules.
This is a case where a simple molecule
here has been substituted
by introducing
trimethylsilane groups.
A question that one may ask
is whether the silane group
is attached here at the top
or here at the bottom.
It's not so easy to distinguish between these two.
Of course, the molecular mass
is exactly the same
and many features are very similar
between these two isomers.
But, if we decide to irradiate
the resonances of the methyl groups
of the silane, then we see
in this case an enhancement
of this aromatic proton here
and an enhancement
of that aromatic proton there,
whereas, if we do the same experiment--
if we saturate the transitions
of the methyl group attached to the silane
in this isomer, then we would only enhance
one aromatic proton.
So, the answer is very simply:
if two protons are enhanced,
we have this isomer, but if there is only
one enhanced proton, we have the other isomer.
We can confirm this by irradiating
this proton here,
which stands out in the spectrum.
Again, for the isomer
on the left-hand side, we would expect
an amplification of two aromatic protons,
whereas, in the isomer
on the right-hand side,
we would expect an amplification
of only one of the aromatic protons.
So, this is a very convenient way
of deciding where the new group
has been attached.
Overhauser effects are not the only useful
methods to determine structures
and assign resonances.
Sometimes it can be useful
simply to measure
the T1 of carbon-13.
This adamantane is
a famous molecule,
which has two different carbon-13 sites—
in this position
and in that position.
The obvious difference is
that this carbon has only one proton
attached to it, whereas this
carbon carries two protons.
Consequently, this carbon-13 is exposed
to fluctuating fields
due to the dipolar interaction
between itself and its unique attached proton,
whereas this carbon-13 is exposed
to more intense fluctuating fields
that stem from two neighbouring protons.
Consequently, the relaxation
of this carbon is almost twice as fast
as the relaxation
of that carbon, or if you prefer,
the T1 of this carbon is
almost twice as short
as the T1 of that carbon.
This is an elegant example
of how you can use T1 of carbon-13
to determine the assignment.
Sometimes it is useful to measure
both the spin-lattice
or T1 relaxation times
and the Overhauser enhancements
on carbon-13.
Take this molecule here,
where we see that the methine,
that is to say, the CH carbons,
all have T1’s
of about two seconds,
whereas the quaternary carbons
have far longer T1’s.
The obvious reason is that the protons
that are responsible
for fluctuating fields
at the sites of these carbons, f to i,
are further away.
The reason is obvious,
namely that the protons
that are responsible for relaxation
of these carbons here
are further away, since the carbons
are quaternary, whereas these have
protons that are
directly attached to the carbons.
We can also see that
the Overhauser effects,
which, as you will recall,
should have at best eta = 2,
but eta varies from one situation
to another depending on the complexity
of the relaxation pathways.
For quaternary carbons,
the Overhauser effects are very weak.
In some cases, T1 relaxation allows us
to gain subtle insight
into molecular behaviour.
This example refers to measurements
of longitudinal
spin-lattice relaxation of carbon-13
in methyl-substituted benzenes.
If the methyl groups
are not crowded,
they do not interfere with each other,
and the T1 relaxation times
of the carbons are rather long.
In this case, however, there is
a steric hindrance
between the two methyl groups.
I wouldn't say that they touch
each other, but they interfere.
This is sometimes known
as a cog-wheel interaction.
The idea is that the protons
on these two groups
almost touch each other, although that's
perhaps more a view of the mind.
Whatever the mechanism is,
it is striking that the relaxation
becomes much faster.
Clearly, if we plot relaxation times
as a function of correlation time--
you will recall that there is a curve
that goes through a minimum--
we have faster T1 relaxation
because the correlation time
of the cogwheel motion
is slowed down compared
to the correlation times
of the unhindered freely rotating methyl groups.
There are some more exotic effects
which are worth understanding
to prevent misinterpretation
of observations.
This example is concerned
with T1 relaxation of carbon-13
in this rather strange
cigar-shaped molecule.
If you have a molecule like that,
then of course it's much easier
to have it rotate around its long axis--
or the rotational diffusion coefficient
around that axis will be much faster
than the rotational diffusion coefficient
around a perpendicular axis.
Thus there is an anisotropy
of the rotational diffusion tensor.
In this case, the authors
have determined large differences
in T1 relaxation times, about 1
and 5 s,
depending if we are in the para-,
ortho- or meta-positions.
We can explain that if we consider
the relevant correlation time,
not of the overall tumbling
of the molecule, but the correlation time
that is relevant for the reorientation
of the carbon-proton vectors
that are either in the para-position,
or in the meta- and ortho-positions.
If we recall this curve, it turns out
that for the para-position,
we have a rather long correlation time--
remember that it takes
slow tumbling
to move this carbon--
whereas for the ortho- and meta-positions
we have a shorter correlation time,
and therefore a longer T1.
It is interesting that T1 relaxation
of carbon-13 gives us insight
not only of molecular motions
but also of the viscosity of the environment.
Particularly when the molecules
are capable of forming
intermolecular hydrogen bonds.
Take the simple case of decane.
In fact, there are only five
distinguishable carbons
because of the symmetry,
and they turn out to have
roughly equal T1’s, so that is
not very interesting.
But if we go to decanol,
where the first carbon
carries an OH group, then we see
a vast range of T1 relaxation times.
The C1 carbon, which is weakly bound
to a neighbouring molecule
through hydrogen bonds, has
a very short relaxation time.
As we go down the chain,
the relaxation times
of the carbons increase.
If we consider C20, it has
a smaller range of relaxation times.
Although there are no hydrogen bonds in the case,
the bulk of the molecule
is partly immobilized because of its inertia.
Relaxation is not limited to liquids.
It can also be studied in solids.
Indeed, Raymond Andrew
and his coworkers have done this
in the '50s--
Raymond Andrew also invented
magic angle spinning,
which is a remarkable invention.
He studied relaxation
and line widths in solids
at low temperatures.
He found that if you freeze benzene,
it looks like a crystal or a glass,
but if you're in a temperature range
between 200 and 130 K (Kelvin),
the lines are fairly narrow
because there is residual motion in the solid,
a rotation around the six-fold axis.
But if the temperature
goes below 100 K,
you can freeze this rotation
and you have a true rigid solid,
so that the line width
becomes much broader--
speaking of the proton line width.
Likewise, if you look at T1 relaxation
of protons in benzene,
there is a minimum that corresponds to a situation
where the rotational motion
has about the same frequency
as the Larmor frequency.
These minima depend on the spectrometer
that you use for their observation.
So far, we have talked
about “longitudinal”
or “spin-lattice” relaxation.
We now briefly mention
“transverse” relaxation,
also known as “spin-spin” relaxation.
The main manifestation
of transverse relaxation
is that it leads to line broadening.
If relaxation is responsible for the line width,
it is sufficient to measure this line width
at half height.
The T2 relaxation time
is inversely proportional
through a simple relationship.
It turns out that
the transverse relaxation rate,
called R2, which is the inverse
of T2, is made up
of two important contributions.
This first contribution we have seen
before, because that is also responsible
for longitudinal relaxation,
and it depends on the spectral density
at the Larmor frequency.
But for T2 relaxation, there is
also a term that corresponds
to the spectral density
at the origin, at zero frequency,
that corresponds to a lack of motion.
You will note that these two terms
both have coefficients of 1/2,
so, if the two spectral densities are
equal, then you can lump them together,
but that is only the case
in extreme narrowing,
when the correlation time is much shorter
than the inverse of the Larmor frequency.
In general, when you move
from fast-tumbling molecules--
remember that 10^-12 s or
a picosecond is characteristic
for water-- then T1 and T2 are equal,
and as we have seen before,
there is a minimum for T1.
T1 increases again
as we go to larger molecules.
That is not so for T2.
As you can see from this graph,
T2 inexorably decreases,
becomes shorter and shorter.
That means that the line widths
become larger and larger,
and that means that, unfortunately,
it is impossible to observe
proton or carbon-13 signals
of very large molecules
without doing some smart things.
So, to summarize Chapter 5,
we shall look at the bullets
that Peter Hore has given
at the end of his chapter.
Nuclear spins attain
thermal equilibrium--
that is to say, the Boltzmann equilibrium--
by a process known as
spin-lattice relaxation, also known
as longitudinal relaxation,
that drives the populations
of the energy levels
back towards equilibrium.
Spin-spin relaxation, also known
as transverse relaxation,
results in NMR line broadening.
Spin-lattice and spin-spin
relaxation times
are known as T1 and T2.
Spin relaxation is caused
by modulations of interactions
between spins that are due to molecular motions.
Dipolar interactions are made
time-dependent by molecular tumbling,
and they are a common source
of spin relaxation.
Dipolar couplings also cause
cross-relaxation, which leads
to the Nuclear Overhauser Effect.
T1s and T2s and NOEs give information
both on molecular structure and on motion.
Thank you for your attention.