This is Sami Jannin from the EPFL.
Welcome to our MOOC
on basic steps in magnetic resonance.
Today we shall be talking
about dynamic nuclear polarization.
This is going to be
the first part of this chapter.
This picture shows you
one of the most famous DNP experiments.
On the upper side here,
you can see a spectrum
measure on a urea sample
with a single scan with DNP.
On the lower side here,
you can see the same spectrum
measured without DNP
with 200,000 scans in 65 hours.
According to the authors
of this paper published in 2003,
the enhancement provided by DNP
exceeded 10,000 folds.
So the first question
that is important to ask in this MOOC
is "how insensitive is NMR?"
You probably know that if you have,
let's say, milligrams of sample,
sensitivity is usually not a problem,
but if you decrease the amount of sample
to, say, for example, 70 micrograms,
you might run into trouble.
So in this MOOC, we're going to take
as an example sodium pyruvate,
labeled on the carbon-1 position,
and we're going to assume,
just for the example,
that we only have 70 micrograms of sample.
Now if you measure this sample overnight
in a 300 megaherz spectrometer,
this is the kind of spectrum
you're going to get
in 128 scans at an interval
of 350 seconds,
and measured during 12 hours.
Now what if you want to look
at the other carbons,
those who are not labeled,
so in natural abundance,
with about 1% C13?
This is the kind of spectrum you get.
You see absolutely no signal
because the signal-to-noise ratio
only grows with the square root of time.
So if you want to measure
the same signal amplitude
that you had measured
on the labeled carbon,
You're going to need 12 hours
multiplied by a hundred
multiplied by a hundred,
which amounts to 5,000 days,
equal to 13.7 years.
So who is responsible
for such a low sensitivity?
On the picture here you can see Boltzmann,
and we're going to explain now
why the low sensitivity of NMR
is mainly due to the Boltzmann Law.
You may have been told
in some NMR courses or books
that the thermal equilibrium
density operator of a spin one half
can be described by Iz plus the identity.
But in reality there is a prefactor
that describes the polarization
in front of Iz.
In the picture here you see
the two-energy level of a spin one half.
The balls describe the amount
of populations of spins up and spins down.
As you can see on this picture,
there are almost as many spins up
as spins down, described
by these big balls.
Still, there is a very little amount
of spins in excess
on the energy level up
with respect to the energy level down.
This is precisely what
the polarization factor describes.
The important thing here
is that this polarization factor
is usually much smaller than one.
So what happens when you do
your NMR experiment?
You're going to drive transitions
between those energy levels
but since you have
as many spin up as spin down,
it is just going to yield
destructive interference,
leading to absolutely no signal.
The only signal that you're going to get
will arise from this very small amount
of population in excess
on one level with respect to the other,
proportional to the polarization factor.
Now what you would like
in your NMR experiment
is to have all the population
sitting on the same energy level
so as to have a very high polarization
in such a way that when you drive
your transition, you end up
with a very large signal.
Fortunately, the distribution
of population at thermal equilibrium
is described by the Boltzmann law.
This Boltzmann law tells you
that the ratio between the population
and the two energy levels
is described by an exponential law,
exponential -ћω,
which is transition energy,
divided by kT, which is
the thermal energy.
From this law now, if you calculate
the difference in population
divided by the sum here, which is
by definition the polarization,
you end up with this formula,
the tangent hyperbolic
of ћω over 2kT.
Now if you take your NMR sample
and put it in a field of seven tesla,
you realize that this polarization
is very low at room temperature.
At around 300 kelvin, the polarization
of your carbon-13 spins
is only about 6 ppm.
That means if you have a million spins
in your sample, only six spins
will actually participate
in the creation of a real NMR signal.
All the other spins
will yield destructive interference
that will not be observable.
There are two ways,
according to Boltzmann,
to increase the polarization.
Either you increase the magnetic field
or you decrease the temperature.
In order to achieve
a polarization close to unity,
you will need something like a mega-tesla,
which is not practical,
or you will need something
like a milli-kelvin,
which is also very difficult to achieve.
So another idea
that was introduced by Overhauser
is to rely on the electron gamma.
The gamma of the electron
is about 660 times bigger than for protons
and about 2,600 bigger than for carbon-13.
That means that
the frequency is much higher,
and that means finally that
the polarization is also much higher.
So what we're going to do
is we're going to bring an electron
and a nuclear spin together
and try to transfer polarization
from one to the other.
If you take your electron spin molecule,
in this case a nitroxide molecule
with an unpaired electron
sitting on the [N-O] bond,
and on the other side you take
your pyruvate molecule
and you look, for example,
at your protons,
and you put this molecule
in your field at room temperature,
the polarization is still fairly low.
Of course, the energy
of the transition is quite different
and if, now, you bring
the temperature down,
you might end up in a situation
where the electron polarization
is high, for example more than 90%,
while your proton polarization
is still very low.
Now how are we going to transfer
polarization from the electron
to the nucelar spin?
The first thing to do is
to bring them together.
You have to bring them into contact,
such as you have, for example,
a dipolar coupling, a hyperfine coupling
that will allow transition
between those energy levels.
How are we going to do that?
How are we going to, for example,
transfer the population here
to this energy level so as to create
a large nuclear polarization
along this transition?
This is going to be done
by applying microwaves
at the suitable frequency
and this is what DNP is about.
In summary, we have illustrated
how insensitive NMR is.
We have described the spin polarization
and explained why the sensitivity
was directly related to this polarization,
and we have shown
that this polarization was very low
in conventional NMR conditions.
Finally, we have introduced
dynamic nuclear polarization
as a technique to enhance
the nuclear polarization
by transferring
the high electron polarization
to the nuclear spins
by applying microwaves,
the ultimate goal being
to increase the nuclear polarization
to, for example, a value close to unity
by having most of the nuclear spins
sitting on the same energy level.
Thank you for listening
to our MOOC on basic steps
in magnetic resonance
and thank you for listening
to this chapter dedicated
to dynamic nuclear polarization.