Okay. In this week,
we're going to talk about
some features that are important
for understanding
the contrast mechanisms
in magnetic resonance imaging.
Now, there is an issue here that is,
we have spent not much time
on each of the imaging techniques,
x-ray-based techniques.
And there is something
that is different with magnetic resonance
and that is that the interactions
between what we can manipulate
on the scanner
and how the image looks like,
these interactions are far more diverse--
the mechanisms are far more diverse.
And so, the point
I want to make here is that,
the contrast strongly
depends on experimental parameters.
So if we look at an image measured
25 milliseconds after the excitation,
this is what it looks like.
This is a sagittal cut through the head.
We have, the nose is roughly here.
The back of the head is here,
so the head is a bit tilted.
This is what the image looks like.
If we look at it after 50 milliseconds,
we have the appearance
of the head like this.
After 75 milliseconds
and 100 milliseconds.
Notice here how the appearance of the head
considerably changes
as we increase the time after excitation
in intervals of 25 milliseconds.
So this is one parameter
that we can change.
Here is another example of images
as this parameter,
time after excitation, is increased--
here very short, two very long.
Here we can only see
the fluid-filled spaces in the brain.
The next parameters, actually,
two parameters I want to look at
is the flip angle alpha--
we've dealt with that last week,
what this is.
This is by how much
we tilt the magnetization away from z.
So we've taken equilibrium magnetization
and we've tilted it away from the z-axis
by this angle alpha, and now it precesses.
And the other parameter
is the time between excitations TR.
We have, on the vertical access,
the TR in milliseconds
so this increases
from 17 milliseconds to 1.25 seconds,
and the flip angle
increases from 10 to 90 degrees.
What do we notice here?
Well, we do notice that the image,
as we increase the flip angle here,
it becomes progressively darker.
And as we increase the TR,
the image becomes progressively brighter,
there's more intensity.
Here it's a very grayish image.
Here it's essentially a black image.
As a side note, the bright dots
that we see here,
these are actually blood vessels
where magnetization
is flowing into the image plane,
but that's a side note.
So here, in this matrix,
we can see that the flip angle
and the time between excitations TR,
these two parameters have an interplay
between each other
and they manipulate the contrast also,
quite substantially.
So we're already at three parameters:
time after excitation,
time between excitations,
and the flip angle.
These three parameters, they're all
under the control of the operator--
of the experimenter that we can change--
which can fundamentally
alter the image contrast.
So let's recap what we know
about magnetic resonance so far.
What we have seen is:
We need a nucleus with non-zero spin
so we have a magnetic moment,
and we need an external magnetic field
that's generated by our magnet.
If we have these two ingredients,
we put our subject into the magnet,
then we get a nuclear
equilibrium magnetization
that builds up after a certain time.
We can always picture you
going to the magnet,
and after a while, your body builds up
this nuclear equilibrium magnetization.
Its magnitude is dictated
by the Boltzmann distribution.
This equilibrium magnetization--
the thermodynamic nuclear
equilibrium magnetization--
increases with the number
of the spins in the voxel,
the magnetic field B-zero,
and the gyromagnetic ratio gamma.
So these are three key elements:
Number of spins in a voxel,
gyromagnetic ratio gamma--
those are two parameters
that we have limited control over.
Gyromagnetic ratio
we have no control over.
Number of spins in a voxel,
we can change the size of the voxel--
that can be changed.
And the magnetic field is something
we can experimentally alter.
Now if we take
all of these elements together...
then our conclusion is that:
Imaging of the proton--
that is, the hydrogen nucleus in water--
is the most sensitive.
Our body is filled with water
so we have a high number of spins.
Water is present in concentrations
of around 40, 50 molar in the body,
so it's about 80 molar protons
in our body.
It has the highest gyromagnetic ratio,
so imaging of the proton in water
is the most sensitive way to do imaging.
And that's for most
practical purposes, but not all.
We will essentially consider
imaging of water in this course.
We have seen last week
that the thermodynamic
equilibrium magnetization M-zero
is proportional to B-zero.
So if we look at the equation of motion,
then the derivative of this equilibrium
magnetization with time
is equal to M-zero cross gamma B-zero.
And, frustratingly, this term is zero
so the consequence is
that the equilibrium magnetization
is along z and stays along z--
nothing happens.
And if nothing happens,
we cannot measure anything,
so we need to induce some changes
since all this
that we have told you so far--
this does not generate
a measurable signal,
so we need to do something
to be able to detect a signal
from our nuclear magnetization.
So we need to do something
to the magnetization
to generate a measurable signal
because just leaving
our subject in the magnet
will not produce
something that we can measure.
So first, I want to talk about
how the MR signal is being detected.
What can we detect?
And the essential principle
that lies behind this is shown here.
We have a magnetic dipole
whose position varies in time
and in that surrounding
conducting structure
there is an electric field
being induced--
a voltage being induced.
And all of this is simply
Faraday's Law of Induction.
Faraday's Law of Induction states
that we get a induced voltage,
it is given by the time derivative
of the magnetic flux.
The magnetic flux is given
by the surface integral of magnetic field
with the surface vector.
So if we look at what this means:
We have the surface vector dA here,
it's perpendicular to the surface,
and what we have in magnetic resonance,
the surface is constant;
we don't change the orientation,
so this is a constant.
And so, basically, the induced
voltage in the coil that we have here
is proportional to the change
in magnetic field with time.
We have Lenz's Law to consider
that the voltage is induced voltage
that produces the current--
This produces a magnetic field
that opposes the change in magnetic flux.
And this all is completely
analogous to power generation
whether we do this motion,
or here in the bicycle...
power generation
for the light of the bicycle.
And we'll demonstrate this
in the following experiment.
We'll take two situations
to illustrate the generation of voltage
with the change in magnetic flux.
So in this coil I'll turn on the current
and we'll see
the induced voltage in this coil
as we change the magnetic flux.
I'll turn it on.
We saw a little blip
that's here on this side.
And then if I move closer,
the movement creates a change
in magnetic flux on this coil over here.
Likewise, I can take a bar magnet...
and if I move that bar magnet here,
I'll see, already,
an induced voltage at this distance.
If I'm further away,
we don't see anything.
And it gets really big
if we're very close.
And, of course, if I change the polarity,
I'll change the polarity
of the induced voltage here,
so it goes from both sides
as I turn around.
We have similarly here
with a magnet in here,
I can demonstrate this
in the following fashion:
So if I move the magnet in here,
depending on the motion,
direction of the motion,
the flux sine will have the LEDs
that indicate the flow change.
If I'm further out, nothing happens
because now we're further away
and with the Biot–Savart Law,
this induces a lower voltage.
So that's a demonstration
of the distance effect
of the change in magnetic flux
on the induced voltage.
Okay, now we also have to consider
the law of Biot-Savart
which basically says
that the magnetic field
produced by a current
falls off with the distance squared,
so it's one over R squared.
There is the law of Biot-Savart.
So these are the laws of electromagnetism
that we're basing our observations on.
And so, if we take the situation here,
we'll take a microscopic bar magnet,
we have the coil that picks up
the change in magnetic flux,
that converts it to a emf.
And now we will look at
what is the induced voltage in this coil.
So the induced voltage is illustrated here
with this bar, the magnitude.
And now as I rotate this magnet,
the voltage changes...
periodically.
Now, if I increase the distance
of the magnet from the coil,
what happens now?
We have still the induced voltage,
but due to Biot-Savart's Law here,
we are getting a reduced induced voltage.
And we will illustrate this interaction--
the distance dependence--
in a small experiment
that we have prepared for you.
Okay, so what we have here is,
we have coils,
we have the magnet here in blue.
The coil, as I turn it...
as I turn it sufficiently large,
it is moving the magnetic field.
Therefore, the flux changes
and that produces the current
that lights the light bulb.
This is one situation
that does not correspond
to what we have in magnetic resonance.
The situation that we have
in magnetic resonance
is more like this one.
Here we have the magnet, in green,
and the coils that pick up
the change in magnetic flux are around it.
As I turn this, we will see
the induced voltage
by the light bulbs up here.
So as I turn it, this is like
the magnetization in magnetic resonance--
we have a change in magnetic field flux.
This magnetic field flux
is picked up by the coils
and this produces induced voltage,
and here, in this case, produces light,
which, of course, we can't do with MRI.
Okay, so we have seen
with a physical bar magnet
that when we change its orientation
in a conducting structure,
we induce a voltage,
and as we move this away,
we reduce the voltage.
Now the link between a physical
bar magnet and nuclear magnetization
is that it is the same effect;
it is still Faraday's Law.
So we have a magnetization,
so the role of the rotating bar magnet
is taken by the magnetization.
We have, again, our coil here
and the induced voltage--
As the magnetization rotates,
it creates a change in magnetic flux.
The magnetic field
becomes time-dependent here.
This term is time-dependent,
this term is constant,
so we have a magnetic flux
that changes with time,
and this induces a voltage in the coil.
And similarly to the bar magnet,
the analogy here holds very well--
If the magnetization is further away
from our conducting structure,
then the induced voltage
is substantially reduced.
So if we take this together,
then as we increase the dipole distance
away from our conducting
structure from this wire,
then the induced voltage decreases.
In other words, dA emf,
the electromotive force,
the induced voltage,
decreases with distance
from the rotating magnetization.
Now, on a side note,
how do we generate the RF field B
that we've discussed
at the end of last week?
And this works
with the following principle:
We have a coil here--
it's very often the same coil
as we have here for detection--
we run a current through it
and this current is applied on the coil.
Now, this will just generate
the linear polarized B1 field,
but we can always consider
any B1 field that's linear
to be a superposition of counter-rotating
circle of polarized B1 fields,
and one of them is going to precess
in the right frequency.
So if we have this--
We have the current running in the coil,
then, at this point, we will generate
a B1 that is indicated here.
If we are further away from the coil--
remember Biot-Savart--
then, in this case,
the current, being still the same,
but now the B1 field is reduced.
So consequence is: The B1 field
is strongest closest to the coil
and decreases with coil distance.
So the degeneration of the RF field
is the inverse process of detecting
the precession of the magnetization.
Here, we run a current through the coil,
this produces a B1 field that rotates,
and this B1 field is the one
that we have discussed
at the end of last week.
Okay, so much for the theory.
What are the consequences now
for the fact that:
As we are further away
from the magnetization,
or further away
from our object of interest,
either B1 or the induced voltage decrease.
In other words, what does
an MR detector look like?
Well, since distance is so important,
it implies that we have to optimize
the coil geometry, the detector,
so ideally--
and this is the physicist's
view of things--
we'd like to put our object
into our detector,
and this detector should be
as tight as possible.
Clearly, the hippo here is not happy,
it's not comfortable,
this is not a situation
that is ideal for comfort.
So what this means--
It also means that our detector
is not going to be a detector
built for the human body
and detect everything from the human body,
but it means that we are going to have
a detector for every organ of interest.
Here's an example
of detectors for the brain.
They look like bird cages, and indeed,
they are also called bird cage.
Here's to give you an idea
how the subject is placed.
Here's a mirror for comfort,
here's the subject's head,
and here is the structure that detects
and excites the magnetization.
Here are three examples put together--
We have the head coil, again,
we have a breast coil for breast MRI,
and for a pelvic phased-array,
it's a coil that's made
for the lower abdomen.
Here, we have an endorectal coil--
it's a small coil--
and we have a prostate coil.
A prostate is an important disease,
so we want to be as close as possible
with detecting our signal to the organ.
You can imagine--
I'll leave that to your imagination
to figure out where this coil is placed
to be as close as possible to the organ.
And here's an example with a rat.
So for the rat brain--
Here's the rat, here's the brain,
and here's the detector that's the coil
that was placed on its brain
for optimal sensitivity.
Clearly, taking such a small subject
into the detection
of a brain coil or a head coil
does not make sense
at all because there,
the conducting structures
are too far away.