So now I want to review
the rotating frame description
of the magnetization
because this is really important
that we have a good grasp
of this description.
So, the equation of motion
for the magnetization
has to be valid in any reference frame
in the presence of a magnetic field
is given by the Larmor equation
which states that
the magnetization precesses
around delta B effective
with the frequency
gamma delta B effective.
If the B effective is
along z, then this means
that the magnetization will precess
in the xy plane with a frequency
that's given
by gamma delta B effective over 2 pi.
Now, let's re-look
at the rotating reference frame.
So we have a reference frame
that rotates around z, about z,
with a frame frequency omega RF.
Let's take the first case:
The rotating reference frame
does not rotate.
That's the lab frame; that's what--
our reference frame.
So, omega RF is zero.
In this case, the magnetization precesses
in the xy plane with a frequency
gamma B 0 over 2 pi.
So, if you take the reference frame here,
we have the B-zero here;
we have our magnetization here.
We're just putting the magnetization
at a certain angle,
so we're just looking
at the component that's transverse.
That's effect -- this component here,
the component that's perpendicular
to B-zero does not precess.
So this magnetization here,
the transverse magnetization will precess
with a angular velocity omega-l.
So it will -- this angle will increase
with omega-l-t,
it goes around B-zero,
encircles the transverse component.
So if we take the transverse component,
then the transverse component
will simply do this motion.
That's the Larmor equation
in the non-rotating reference frame.
Now we'll take the second case,
and that is the rotating reference frame.
And now we'll place ourselves
into the rotating reference frame
that rotates exactly
with the Larmor frequency.
In this rotating frame,
as we are rotating exactly
with the magnetization,
this magnetization is,
by definition, stationary.
It does not move, or in other words,
it precesses in xy with zero frequency.
Now, the equation of motion
that we have up here
still has to be valid
in this reference frame.
So, the precession frequency is equal
to gamma-delta-B effective over 2-pi,
or in this case,
the delta-B-effective will be zero.
And our magnetization will do this motion,
namely, none,
because we are in the reference frame
where it doesn't move.
Now, the Larmor frequency in [inaudible],
in the rotating reference frame is given
by gamma-delta-B-effective,
and this gamma-delta-B --
this delta-B-effective
is given by B-zero
minus omega-R-F over gamma.
So what this means
is we are to get from here
to the lab frame,
to the rotating reference frame
that rotates with a Larmor frequency,
what we have had to do
to still have the equation work,
we have to subtract
a fictitious magnetic field
which in this case equals
to omega-L over gamma
and omega-L is gamma-B-zero,
so the delta-B-effective
was B-zero minus B-zero equals zero.
But this holds true for any omega-R-F
for any angular velocity
of a rotating reference frame,
and we can calculate a delta-B-effective.
Now here, I want to make
a short digression into quantum mechanics.
Not what we strictly need
quantum mechanics for understanding
most of the MRI principles.
We can actually work very much
with a classical principle.
But we want to remind ourselves
that magnetic resonance
is a quantum mechanical manifestation.
It is a property, comes
out of quantum mechanics.
Quantum mechanics is the proper way
of describing things,
and what I want to do here
is build a bridge between
our description, classical description,
and the quantum mechanical theory
that's behind this.
So let's look at
the Schrödinger representation.
We have the derivative of the cat
is equals to the Hamiltonians
times the cat,
and if the Hamiltonian is constant
in time, then we can write the solution
very simply.
The expectation value
of a operator I-z
is given by this term here
in the Schrödinger representation.
So this is all standard theory
from quantum mechanics.
Now, we have some equivalencies here,
and that is the magnetization
along z is the expectation value
of the operator I-z,
magnetization along x, that of i-x,
and the magnetization along y,
the expectation value of I-y.
So in other words,
our macroscopic quantities
that we observe the magnetization
are the expectation values
of the quantum mechanical
operators associated.
So, this is very nice.
So, for a spin one-half
that's a hydrogen nucleus
at the proton,
we have two energy levels,
so we have -- this is the operator
for I-z, I-x, and I-y.
These are the Pauli spin matrices
that describe the system.
Now, how do we determine
the time dependence of I-x,
that is of the m-x magnetization?
And the way this is done here
is we split the Hamiltonian
into time-invariant
and time-dependent terms.
So we can write
our Schrödinger equation here.
We'll split the Hamiltonian,
this term here,
into time-invariant term here
and a time-dependent term.
And then we impose
that the time-invariant term
is much bigger.
Its eigenvalues are much bigger
than those of the time-dependent term
and we'll use here now
the interaction representation,
which comes from
higher order perturbation theory.
And if we do that,
the transformation that is being done
that comes out of this theory
is that we have now the cat
in the interaction representation
and we will now enter this condition
the representation equation of motion
for the wave function
becomes this term here.
And we have now the V of t
is transferred to the V
in the interaction representation.
This is the transformation given here.
Now for spin, for a nuclear spin,
this is all general theory,
now, for a nuclear spin,
the static Hamiltonian
is the one associated
to the magnetic field.
That's the one that generates
the two energy levels.
Hence, we have I-z here as the operator,
and we can take
the time-variant Hamiltonian
given by this term here.
Now what is this --
How does this transform if you do
this transformation here
if we use an omega-R-F here
in this term here
that is equal to gamma-B-zero?
And actually, if we do this transformation
we'll find that
in the interaction representation,
this time-variant term here,
which we have in this term here,
becomes time-independent.
So, the beauty here is
that we have used classically
the description
in the rotating reference frame
to make things stationary.
If we do this
in the interaction representation,
and we make our Hamiltonian
in this representation stationary,
we're essentially doing the same thing
but in quantum mechanics,
and we obtain our stationary Hamiltonian,
this is equivalent to putting ourselves
into the rotating reference frame.
So we have an additional
quantum mechanical equivalent
that is the B-zero is along I-z
is proportional to the operator I-z
at the B-one, and x or y
is given by the operator I-x-I-y.
That's what this term here is.
This is the description of the R-F field.
So, this is a short digression
into quantum mechanics
to remind ourselves
that what is behind magnetic resonance
is truly a quantum mechanical event.