What happens with the motion
of the magnetization
when we apply such an RF field
and it induces a flip angle?
Let's look at the laboratory
frame of reference.
Then we have the Larmor equation,
which says, derivative
of the magnetization with time
is equal to "γ" times the magnetic field,
and the magnetic field
I have conveniently split
into the B_1, which is time-dependent
and B_0, which is constant.
Now, what happens is,
actually in the motion:
As we apply the B_1, it rotates with ω_RF.
As the B_1 is in the transverse plane
and it rotates, the B_0,
the magnetization will start
to deviate from being along z.
The minute it starts to deviate
from being along z,
it will start to precess.
It will precess
with the Larmor frequency,
which is on the order of 100 megahertz.
We have seen with the examples
for the B_1,
this is on the order of kilohertz.
So this will go 100,000 times
around in circles
for every rotation that it makes
around the field B_1.
So, what happens in the motion is
that we have the B_1 field here
that rotates.
And now what I will describe here
is the motion
of the transverse magnetization
and the longitudinal magnetization,
as we turn on
this rotating reference frame.
So, we have the B_1
applied that Larmor frequency
in the transverse plane for a time τ,
and this will create a nutation
of the magnetization in a spiral motion,
as it tips away from the z-axis.
So, let's look at this in the animation:
the B_1, the magnetization, rotates
so the transverse component increases,
the longitudinal component decreases,
until we are done,
and we have done a 90-degree excitation.
Now, remember, the rotation
is happening 100,000 times
for each rotation
that we flip the magnetization.
So it's difficult to visualize,
but we will illustrate this effect of B_1
in the experiment that we have done,
again, with a simulation
of the magnetic resonance effect
with this experiment
with a yellow magnet that is rotating,
and we will look at this experiment now.
So, in this experiment
we have the same setup
as in the experiment I showed last week,
but we have an additional magnet here,
which produces a magnetic field
that's perpendicular
to the main magnetic field
which is this way,
and this magnet
produces a magnetic field this way.
And so, as we have seen
with the equations in the course,
having this magnetic field rotate
at Larmor frequency
will induce the change in the orientation
of the magnetization vector,
and that's what we should be seeing here.
So, I will bring it into rotation
and then, as I turn it around,
you can see how it goes down
and then tips at the end.
So, this is the same rotation motion,
if I take--this is my B_1 field here,
magnetic field, this way,
I take this out
and just give it a spin here
for the ball without this B_1 field,
then it will precess
in the external magnetic field,
like we have seen last week.
OK, so, we have seen,
we can visualize that,
if things are going slow.
Now in reality, things move around
at the Larmor frequency
in 100 megahertz range
and rotate into the transverse plane
in the kilohertz range.
So, putting ourselves
into the rotating frame of reference,
where we no longer
consider the motion due to the B_0,
so this term is canceled by the ω_RF / γ .
Τhen in rotating reference frame
we have this equation
of motion to consider.
So, in this rotating reference frame,
which rotates exactly
at the Larmor frequency,
we have a B_1, that is stationary,
we will look now here
at the z-magnetization,
and we will look
at the transverse magnetization.
And the B_1 field now will rotate
the magnetization towards the x-y plane.
The way this works is,
the x-component increases,
the z-component decreases,
this is a simple--
in this reference frame
is a simple rotation
because in this reference frame
the B_1 is stationary.
The amplitude of B_1 determines
how fast we get
towards the transverse plane,
that is, how fast it is rotated,
and we can calculate the flip angle,
if we know the gyromagnetic ratio, the B_1
and the duration
of the application of this B_1,
which is also called the RF pulse.
So, that's the flip angle given.
After the application of this RF field
the z-magnetization
equals to M_0 cos α --
we have rotated by angle α,
and the transverse magnetization
increases with sin α --
so it's given by M_0 sin α.
This is when we start out
with the equilibrium magnetization.
To give us an idea in MRI
what is the γ B_1,
so we'll look here at frequency,
so γ B_1 / (2 π)
is typically from anywhere
from 0.1 to 1 kilohertz.
This means that the duration
of this RF pulse,
where the RF is turned on,
is typically on the order of milliseconds.
For all practical purposes,
this is all that we need to know here.
So now, we have talked
about nuclear magnetic resonance.
So, we have had the term nuclear--
we had a nucleus involved,
we have a magnetic field,
so we have the magnetic in there,
but we haven't really talked
about what "resonance" means.
Let's look at the excitation
with the B_1 field,
and the question we are asking here is
how does applying such an RF pulse,
so an RF field B_1 that we apply
for a certain time τ,
how much can we get excitation,
that is, up to what range,
how close do we need to be
to the Larmor frequency
so that we can generate an excitation
that is a rotation
into the transverse plane?
So, now, if we are
in our radio frequency field
or rotating frame,
frequency ω_RF,
which we will choose always
such that the B_1 becomes stationary.
This is the simplest way to describe it,
and here ω, the angular frequency
of the rotating frame,
becomes the angular frequency
of the radio frequency,
so ω_RF.
So we are now away
from the Larmor frequency,
so we have a Δ ω that's non-zero.
And in this case our magnetization
will experience an effective field
that is given by γ B_eff,
just given by γ B_1 square + (Δ ω) square
and that the square root.
How does this come about?
Well, we have seen, if we are
in a rotating reference frame
that does not exactly match
the Larmor condition,
then we have a residual
z magnetic field, along z,
and that's given here by Δ ω.
We are by definition
in a rotating reference frame,
where γ B_1 is stationary, that is--
so γ B_1 is stationary,
and our magnetic field
along z is given by Δ ω,
which is given by γ B_0 - ω_RF.
And so we have a z-component
of the magnetization;
it's stationary, we have
a transverse component
of the magnetization
in our reference frame--
that's stationary as well.
So this is the vector addition,
this gives us an effective
magnetic field, B_eff
that's tilted by the angle θ.
So, what does it mean now,
we have the Larmor equation,
and Larmor equation is always true,
so we have now the rotation axis--
it's dictated by the direction of B_eff--
so it is tilted by an angle θ
compared to the transverse plane.
If we were exactly
on the Larmor frequency,
Δ ω would be zero, θ would be zero,
and we have the case
that we have discussed
last week and just before.
So, here is now, what I am going to plot,
is to illustrate this.
We have the z-axis on the vertical,
we have the equilibrium magnetization
that we started out with,
and this little sphere here indicates
the tip of the magnetization vector.
So, that's the magnetization tip.
It's easier to describe this
with animation.
Now we'll apply,
in our rotating reference frame,
a B_1 that is constant.
But we are not exactly
at the Larmor frequency,
so we have a Δ ω / γ
that's the Δ B that is left.
So we have also the z-component.
So, this corresponds to this,
and this corresponds to this,
so we get a B_eff
that's in this direction.
Now, the Larmor equation says,
our magnetization
which is initially here, it will...
only its component
perpendicular to B_eff will change,
the one that's parallel will not change,
so we will get a circular motion
around B_eff,
and here is our circular motion.
So our magnetization vector here
will rotate on a circular motion
around B_eff.
Now, here the particular choice of Δ B
is such that B_1 = Δ ω / γ,
so we have a 45-degree angle,
and in this case, we are still able
to get the magnetization
from being along z
to being in the transverse plane.
Βut remember, when we had
the B_1 only here,
we were on resonance, this term is zero,
so the B_eff is along B_1,
then we can easily rotate it also
into the - z-orientation,
the magnetization here,
with this particular condition
we are no longer able to do that.
Now, let's take the same situation.
We'll start out with the magnetization--
it shall be the same.
Here is the magnetization vector tip.
I'll apply the same B_1--
this shall be the same B_1 as here.
But now, let's say,
we are applying this B_1 field
further away from the Larmor condition,
so we are further away
from the precession frequency
of the magnetization
in the absence of a B_1 field.
So, now our B_eff is given again by B_1,
and the z-component--
that's the mismatch between the frequency
at which B_1 rotates
and the Larmor frequency.
And now we have the motion,
again, by the Larmor equation
given by precession around B_eff,
and now it precesses
on this conical motion
on this circular motion around B_eff.
Notice here that the magnetization
is now no longer able
to reach the transverse plane,
so we are no longer able
to excite the magnetization fully.
I'll take a third example,
we will start out again
with the same magnetization.
Here is the vector tip,
the tip of the magnetization vector.
We will use the same γ B_1,
so the same B_1,
and now we are even further away
from the Larmor condition
with the frequency of our B_1.
So we are rotating--
The B_1 is now applied at a frequency
that's far away from the Larmor frequency.
Our rotating frame
is far away from the γ B_0.
In this case, we have
a residual z-component, Δ B,
which is Δ ω / γ,
so that's B_0 - ω_RF / γ
and the B_1 has stayed constant,
so our B_eff is now tilted more
towards the vertical axis,
the motion is again
by the Larmor equation
given by this circular motion
perpendicular to B_eff.
Now, you can imagine,
as you go further and further away
from the Larmor condition,
the z-component
of the effective field will increase,
the frequency
by which the magnetization precesses
progressively increases,
while the flip angle, maximum flip angle
which is this point here
that we can obtain
decreases and decreases,
and at some point we won't be able
to produce any motion
of the magnetization that is discernible,
and nothing happens.
So, clearly if the RF,
the frequency of the RF field
is too far away from the Larmor condition,
we are no longer able
to produce excitation
and have the magnetization
in the transverse plane.
So, this condition here,
where we have considerable alignment
of the effective field with z,
where essentially
nothing interesting happens,
is called the "off resonance",
the B_1 is much smaller than the Δ B,
and essentially the effective field
is more or less parallel to z.
Whereas, if we have "on resonance",
then "on resonance",
it suffices to say
that the γ B_1, so this vector,
is much larger than the Δ ω--
that's this component here.
And in this case essentially
the effective field is parallel to B_1,
and we have the situation
of the stationary B_1 field,
"on resonance".
So this is the situation
of "on resonance".
We are close to the Larmor frequency,
and "close" here means
that γ B_1 has to be big
compared to the mismatch
between a radio frequency
pulse frequency
and the Larmor frequency.
This is a reason why one in MRI
applies radio frequency pulses
for short duration of periods;
one wants to have
a sufficiently large γ B_1
and, as an idea here, the RF field--
the B_1 field,
is typically applied for periods
of around one millisecond.
As a rule of thumb, the RF field
with an amplitude of B_1
can excite a range of frequencies
on the order of + - γ B_1 .
We can see here, here it is, γ B_1
the Δ ω is γ B_1 here,
and here we still can excite,
so in this case that's the plus and minus,
because we can do this
also on the other side.
Now, there is
a quantum mechanical equivalent--
we remind ourselves,
we're talking quantum mechanics here,
and this basically means we have--
as we change the orientation
of the magnetization,
we also change the population
in the energy levels,
and the transition probability
is highest if the photons--
we speak of photons here--
the energy of the photons matches
the difference of the energy levels
in our nucleus.
That's how we can induce transitions
in the population of the energy levels.
And this is illustrated here
with people jumping on the bridge.
If you do this with the correct frequency,
then you get the maximum
amplitude, classically.
That is what we've seen
with resonance when we discuss,
in classical mechanics,
the harmonic oscillator.
And on the right you'll see the picture
of the Tacoma Bay Bridge--
famous example of illustrating resonance
that's used in the classroom context.