So far we have dealt with the fact
that when we go into a magnet
there's an equilibrium
nuclear magnetization that develops.
We have discussed
on how we can get this magnetization
into the transverse plane.
Now, we know Boltzmann rules,
Boltzmann is always right.
So we know after we have a applied
our B_1 field,
we tipped the magnetization
transverse plane.
It's not going to stay there forever.
It will eventually at some point
return to the equilibrium magnetization.
This return to equilibrium magnetization
is what I will discuss in this section.
Let’s talk about --
we have thermodynamic equilibrium.
We have a magnetization,
equilibrium magnetization along that.
We’ll apply now a B_1 field
on this magnetization.
This is done by RF pulses or pulse,
or multiple RF pulses
mediated by the RF field B_1.
Now, we look at the situation.
What happens after excitation?
Here’s the B_1.
After excitation, our magnetization
is in the transverse plane.
This is for excitation
in 90-degree pulse.
Now, in this situation,
as you’ve noticed here,
we have no longer
a z magnetization.
Magnetization is no longer present.
We have a transverse magnetization.
Now, what happens after this excitation?
We know that the transverse component
has to disappear
and a longitudinal component
has to build up.
This is described by a process
that’s called relaxation.
There are two time constants
that are affiliated with it
that we will discuss shortly.
The transverse component decays,
and the longitudinal component
builds up again along z,
that [inaudible]
the equilibrium magnetization.
This process of relaxation,
the reestablishment of thermodynamic
equilibrium magnetization
has a phenomenological description.
For the transverse magnetization,
we’ll consider here x and y axis,
and we’ll now look at,
on the resonance that is,
we are rotating with a Larmor frequency
of the magnetization.
We have the change in magnetization
is proportional to the magnetization itself,
same for the y magnetization.
These two expressions are actually
fairly similar to what we’ve had
for the linear attenuation coefficient.
So we have the same
mathematical solution here
as we have dealt there,
and we are getting an exponential decay
of the transverse magnetization.
Our transverse magnetization –
this is a solution of this equation,
it's now right here x y
instead of each individual component,
which just means
any transverse component
is given by the transverse
magnetization at zero times e ^(- t / T_2).
This is phenomenological T_2.
There are a lot of calculations
in trying to tease out
from the theory how this T_2
is being calculated.
For us, it suffices to accept this
as a phenomenological constant.
I will in the following
give you a rationale
what influences this decay time T_2.
What are the mechanisms of relaxation?
Essentially, what we’re dealing with here
is the fact that our molecules
are not static, that they move.
We have, for example, Brownian motion.
Now, if you have a molecule that moves,
the motion in the magnetic field
will create local oscillating
or fluctuating magnetic fields.
They are small. You can easily picture this.
Here’s a molecule
that kind of tumbles here.
We have a magnetic field,
and we can certainly envisage
that this molecule on a local level,
on atomic level, or molecular level
has a non-constant magnetic field.
There are some perturbations
to the main magnetic field
that are time-dependent.
In addition to the B_0,
which is on the order of Teslas,
one gets a small fluctuating
magnetic field.
It is small, but it’s randomly fluctuating
that is acting on the nucleus.
This field depends on the orientation
of the molecule,
and also, how it behaves
is described by the correlation time, τ_C.
The correlation time is defined
as the time for a molecule to rotate
by about 1 radian.
It essentially is a way also to say
it is a measure of how long the motion
between two molecules, for example,
is correlated.
Now, what are some sources
of this fluctuating field?
We have coupling between dipoles
of the nucleus of interest
and the solvent.
So if we take, for example,
glucose in water
and the glucose molecule will interact
with the water.
Here’s our nucleus of interest
and in blue is the solvent,
or we have interactions between
nuclear magnetic dipoles.
That’s another source
of this local fluctuating magnetic field.
If you have a water molecule
and another water molecule,
then the two dipoles
which are not perfectly aligned,
and they will interact and create
this local magnetic field.
It is useful here to consider
the correlation function,
which is given by this correlation time.
The correlation function is e ^ (- t / τ_C).
This function essentially describes
the correlation of motion
that is t seconds apart.
It’s dependent on this correlation time.
What I’m getting at here is the parameter
is the correlation time
because that correlation time depends
on a number of things that we know.
One of them, viscosity.
This is easily envisageable.
If you take the sugar molecule
in our blood,
this sugar molecule
will come more fairly fast.
So the correlation time is short.
If you take the same sugar molecule
in honey--honey has a very high viscosity
so there that sugar molecule
will move less,
so the correlation time will be longer.
Then it makes also sense
that, as temperature decreases,
the correlation time increases
because essentially at 0 Kelvin,
we froze and we don’t move at all.
Finally, that it is somehow dependent
on the radius of the molecule
makes also sense.
It takes just much more thermal energy
to rotate the big macromolecule
as compared to a small glucose molecule.
This correlation time
has some molecular effects in there,
some properties of the molecule itself.
Relaxation has in large part to do
with microscopic motion, random motion
that generates a randomly varying
magnetic field,
and this has a lot to do
with molecular properties
of the molecules.
Now, how does a locally varying
magnetic field that fluctuates
cause a loss
of transverse magnetization?
We will deal with T_2 largely
as a phenomenological time constant.
But in this little example
I want to give you some rationalization
on how this T_2, this decay time
for the transverse magnetization
and how that is influenced
by molecular events.
First, to give us an idea
what we’re talking about,
the T_2 ranges from typically
on the order of microseconds,
10 microseconds in bone
to several seconds in water.
T_2 is also called
the transverse relaxation, T_2 relaxation.
The underlying cause
is molecular dynamics
and spin-spin interactions.
If you have nearby spins
and depending on how the molecule moves,
this will influence the magnitude
of this relaxation constant.
It has also been called historically
"spin-spin relaxation"
because it is based, to a large extent,
on interactions between spins.
This leads to a loss of signal
in the x y plane.
It’s also called "memory relaxation."
How does this lead to this loss
in magnetization
that we phenomenologically described
by the exponential decay?
Let’s look at a situation after excitation.
We have a transverse magnetization,
we have now [afflicted] around x
with the B_1 field.
We’ve tipped it to magnetization along y.
If now you can see that your voxel
as composed of little sub-voxels
and in each of the sub-voxels,
your magnetic field
that the nucleus spins experience
is identical for all in nuclear sub-voxels.
Nothing of interest will happen.
They will all precess
with the same Larmor frequency,
and this magnetization vector
is preserved.
But now, we have random local
magnetic field.
Imitate your voxel in image.
Imagine that you've cut it into
tens of thousands sub-voxels,
tiny little pockets
where in each of the pockets
you have a magnitization.
A tiny magnetization associated with it,
so sub-voxels, if you will.
Now in your mind
assigned to each of these sub-voxels
a slightly different
external magnetic field B_0.
Now, what you will get is that
in your voxel,
these magnetization will now precess
at slightly different Larmor frequencies.
If they have slightly different
Larmor frequencies
even if you put ourselves
into the rotating reference frame
of the main Larmor frequency,
some of them will precess faster,
and some of them will precess slower
in that rotating reference frame.
If they don’t precess exactly
at the same frequency,
that means between these magnetizations,
an angle will build up.
And this is in this looping animation here
that we have this build-up of the angle
between the magnetizations
that produces...
...the dephasing of the spins
and therefore, a reduction
as they lose the same orientation.
The effective transverse magnetization
that we measure is reduced.
We have a rule of thumb for water.
That means the less the water
is in contact with tissue,
be it bone, be it membranes,
be it proteins, et cetera,
the longer is the bulk water T_2.
The purer the water,
the longer is the T_2.
The longest T_2
that you can have for water
is degassed, demineralized water.
How does this T2 relate
to the correlation time?
Any of these things increases
a correlation time of water.
If you look over a voxel,
we have the density of our spins
times the local fluctuation
in the magnetic field with time
times the correlation time.
If our correlation time increases,
then this term here increases over τ_C,
and so we get a faster
differential precession
along with differential precession
until the molecules reorient
and this goes to zero faster.
And here's another major conclusion.
If your object of interest,
your molecule of interest
has a long correlation time,
it accrues a lot of phase difference
over this correlation time.
This results in a short T_2.
That is important and the conclusion is
this one, this is
the take-home message here.
Bone, membranes, proteins,
for intents and purpose
of biomedical imaging, they are invisible.
That means, although they carry
magnetization, it decays so fast
that we cannot practically measure it.
Here’s an example.
We have a transverse magnetization
in cerebrospinal fluid of the brain.
There is hardly any proteins.
This decays the slowest.
The T_2 is 1.4 seconds.
We have grey matter.
It’s 100 milliseconds, 90 milliseconds
is white matter
and that, for other reasons,
has an even shorter T_2.
These are some examples here
for the relaxation that they are,
because of the differential environment
and the interactions
at the water molecule has
on a molecular level,
these interactions are different
for different tissues.
And that is a source for changes in T_2
between different tissues.
Now, we have said,
for relaxation to occur
and for the thermodynamic equilibrium
magnetization to be re-established,
we have to re-establish
the magnetization along z
to get to the equilibrium magnetization.
And so, there is also something happening
with the longitudinal magnetization,
the magnetization along z.
So, we consider that we have excited
our magnitization
to the transverse plane.
The transverse magnetization, M_ x_y
has decayed by T2,
and now our z magnetization,
which is zero , has to be reconsittuted
and approach
the equilibrium magnetization.
And this is described
by the longitudinal relaxation
which happens along the z axis,
and this is governed
by this differential equation here.
So we have the time derivative
of the z magnetization component
is given by something
minus the z magnetization
times the constant.
So, if we have the derivative of something
equals to something of that derivative
and a constant, it makes sense to consider
an exponential solution here as well.
Let’s first, however, look at
what happens after T_2 relaxation.
We have no z magnetization,
so it is zero.
The solution to this equation here
is given by this solution here.
You can verify by plotting this term
in here, doing the derivation
that this is indeed the solution.
If we said, t = 0,
then we have M_z (0) = M_z (0),
so that works.
If we set t to infinity, t / T_1,
this goes to zero, this goes to zero,
then we have M_0,
so it’s the right behavior.
What this means is that
after we have had T_2 relaxation,
we have no nuclear magnetization
in our sample.
And as T_1 relaxation, this equation here
on the left works,
the z magnetization is reconstituted
until the equilibrium z magnetization.
Now, what are the mechanisms
for T_1 relaxation?
They again have a lot to do
with molecular motion,
its incoherent fluctuations,
and it has to do a lot with
how these fluctuations, the motion,
the molecular fluctuations are close
to the Larmor frequency.
Remember, a change
in thermodynamic equilibrium magnetization
is associated with the change
in energy transfer
between the energy levels
in the higher and lower energy diagram.
It has therefore been also
historically called spin-lattice relaxation
because one can consider the spin pool
as a thermally isolated pool
and the heat is lost to the surroundings.
Remember, if we have a 90-degree pulse,
we have equal distribution of the spins
in upper and lower energy level.
This corresponds technically
to a temperature of infinity,
so the spin system has to cool down.
Incidentally, this by the way
has been used,
manipulation of nuclear magnetization
has been used at a very low temperature
to further cool a sample
by working with heat and exchange
between the lattice and the spin system.
To give an idea what the T_1 is,
it’s typically between 0.5 and 5 seconds.
The longest is for water,
5 seconds value that’s pure,
degassed, demineralized water.
We have at the time,
after 90-degree magnetization,
we have no z magnetization.
So the population distribution
is equal in the two energy levels.
This corresponds
to a temperature of infinity.
We draw the two energy levels here,
lower and higher energy level,
here’s our energy difference
governed here,
and this would be at 0 Kelvin,
we have a mole in the lower energy state.
And we’ll take here an extreme drawing
that is our equilibrium magnetization
that we have at the beginning.
We start out
with equilibrium magnetization,
and when we do a 90-degree flip,
we have equal population
in the higher and lower energy level,
which corresponds to infinite temperature.
Now, we wait, T_1 relaxation is happening,
and the spins that are in excess
in the higher energy level
eventually return back
to the lower energy level
until the Boltzmann distribution
is re-established.
Then we have thermodynamic
equilibrium magnetization,
which is dictated
by the Boltzmann distribution here.
And 1 / 82 = e ^ (-Δ E / k T).
Now, this change in energy level,
the spins that are in the higher level
that are in excess,
they have to go to the lower energy level.
In doing so, they have to give off energy.
This is essentially done
by transfer of energy
from the spins to the system,
and the system here is the lattice.
It is done by photon transfer,
but it is done thermally.
This energy transfer is most efficient
if the motion of the system,
that is, frequency
with which the system fluctuates,
the energy fluctuates,
matches the energy difference here
between the energy levels.
We want to give off the quantum of photon.
We can only give it off the energy
in form of exactly,
this energy difference.
This happens most effectively
if the motion has that frequency
in it as well.
If the motion of the molecule
largely does not correspond
to the frequency
of energy difference here,
this Δ E here,
then where do the photons go?
They cannot be easily given off.
That’s the intuitive description here.
This basically means
that the Larmor frequency
times the correlation time
should be roughly 1.
Then we have the most efficient transfer.
The most efficient transfer means
that we have a minimal
T_1 relaxation time.
Now, if we have solid state like bone
or plastics, or cement,
or anything, or teeth,
then the correlation time is very long.
The ω τ_C is much larger than 1.
Then we have a T_1
on the order of seconds to minutes.
You take water and you freeze it down
to a few Kelvin of temperature.
You measure the T_1.
In that situation,
that T_1 is in the order
of tens of thousands of seconds.
It’s very long because there is no motion
close to the Larmor frequency
of our magnetization.
To sum up here the relaxation of T_1,
there’s also a rule of thumb
that is useful for us to know.
It is very similar to what we had for T_2.
Basically means the purer the T_2 ,
the purer the water is,
so there’s less other molecules
at the water interact,
the longer is the T_1.
The more there are like membranes,
proteins, et cetera
with which the bulk water
can come in contact,
the shorter is the T_1.
That’s the rule of thumb for tissue
that is useful to remember.