So now we will look at a description
of the changes in magnetization.
And this will bring us
to a full description of the changes
in the longitudinal
and transverse components.
What we have to do, we've already seen
in the previous lectures--
in the previous weeks--
we have seen the Larmor equation,
which describes
the precession of magnetization
around either a static magnetic field
or a rotating magnetic field like the B_1.
Now what we have to do here
is we just have to add the terms
in the differential equations
for relaxation--
that is T1 and T2.
So for the z magnetization
we will have this term
that's along z.
For the x magnetization we have this term.
And for the y magnetization
we have this term.
Now this is a fairly complicated
set of equations here.
As you can see, there are couple
of differential equations
but if we look at this as a whole--
this expression here--
this is nothing but the vector product
of gamma B with M.
So this describes the precession
of the magnetization
around the magnetic field B,
and here B is a general vector.
Now we have the relaxation along z
that we have introduced this week.
So we have the change
in magnetization along z,
change in magnetization along x and y.
So these are the relaxation terms.
And this gives us the full set
of differential equations--
the behavior--
so we have, on one hand,
we have precession around B--
that's these terms here--
and we have relaxation now incorporated.
And these three equations here
are the Bloch equations.
They're named after a Swiss physicist,
Felix Bloch,
who was awarded the Nobel Prize
for his discovery of the nuclear
magnetic resonance effect.
He was awarded
Nobel Prize in Physics in 1952.
If we substitute the term
for the rotating reference frame,
so we'll substitute the big omega,
which is given by minus gamma B_0
plus omega RF,
then we obtain
these equations for the term
that's substituting
these three equations with this term
and this is the rotating reference frame,
or in other words,
it's gamma B_1 plus omega
in the rotating reference frame
that rotates with the B_1 cross M.
So that would be in the description
in the rotating reference frame.
Now what characterizes
the basic MR signal?
We'll start out with
the transverse magnetization
and here I'll describe it
as a complex function.
So the transverse magnetization
in complex terms
is given by the transverse
magnetization times zero,
times e to the minus i-omega-t,
times e to the minus t/T2.
This is relaxation, this is precession.
Here we're using the complex notation--
we're using the real part, for example,
to represent the x axis
and the imaginary part
to represent the y axis.
And what does this signal look like?
This expression--
this is the x component.
The envelope,
that is the amplitude,
decays with T2,
that means the envelope decays with T2
and we see oscillations here
in the real part,
that's the cosine omega t term.
Likewise, for the y term--
that would be the imaginary part
of this equation--
has a similar function
except it's sine omega t in this case,
but it has also the T2
as the decaying amplitude--
the T2 effect.
For longitudinal magnetization,
and here I'll just stick to the case
where we have
a 90 degree full excitation,
so the magnetization has been flipped
into the transverse plane,
then the z magnetization--
the longitudinal magnetization--
is equal to M_0 times 1
minus e to the minus t/T1.
So in the end, what we have
is a complex description of the motion.
We have the z component
which recovers towards M_0.,
we have the x and the y component,
which basically together
means that the transverse component
rotates in the transverse plane--
according to the Larmor equation--
and also decays exponentially.
So this could be described
by a behavior like this
and this is fairly complicated.
So if you look at the z magnetization,
it builds up in an exponential function.
So it goes from zero to M_0.
This-- how fast it recovers to M_0
is described by T1.
So we have the equilibrium
z magnetization like this.
We'll start out essentially
at zero magnetization
and then what happens with time
is that the z magnetization
recovers with e to the minus t/T1
towards M_0,
that's what the magnetization vector
will do over time.
Now if we look at
the transverse component Mxy--
I'll here not distinguish between x and y,
I'll just take this
as the transverse component--
then this component decays
while the z component increases.
Of course, Mxy precesses
depending on the choice
of our rotating reference frame.
So we have also a condition here
that we can never exceed
the equilibrium magnetization M_0
and this is a constraint that if we look
at the norm of the vector--
the total magnetization vector--
it cannot be bigger than M_0
and this typically implies that T2
is not bigger than T1.
It is typically much smaller,
but certainly it does not exceed T1.
Now, I want to give you an example.
This is a preparatory example
for what is to come next week,
and this is how can
we be sensitive to T1 changes?
Or how can we measure
T1 changes precisely?
And here we'll consider
a so-called multipulse experiment.
So the experiment
is fairly simple, an RF pulse
that is a B_1 field
is applied every TR seconds.
So here is our scheme,
we apply this every TR seconds.
So here's the time TR.
Then we have a flip angle alpha
applied here
and we'll set this to 90 degrees.
And what this pulse does,
it converts the z magnetization
to transverse magnetization
and then the signal is measured.
So at the beginning, the signal
is proportional to the z magnetization
and therefore it is sensitive
to T1 effects.
So now we'll take the basic
differential equation
that describes the behavior
of the z magnetization.
We have the recovery to M_0
and we have
the starting magnetization M_0,
that M of time zero that decays with T1.
At time zero, we can say
that the magnetization,
the z magnetization,
is M_0 cosine alpha
and then we can write this in this form
that is basically we are using the fact
that we have used a 90 degree pulse here.
So M_0 cosine alpha,
since cosine of 90 degrees is zero,
then we have this term is zero,
so our z magnetization
is just this term here,
which is written here again.
So, if I express this now as a function
of the repetition time,
so we'll repeat our 90 degree pulse
every TR seconds,
then our z magnetization
as a function of TR
is given by the equilibrium magnetization
times 1 minus e to the minus TR/T1.
Now here what is crucial
is we have an effect of T1
as well as an effect of--
the same holds true for T2
but the effect of T1 on the signal
depends strongly on how it is measured.
So let me give you the example here.
If we take a short T1 component
and we measure every 500 milliseconds,
we get the signal intensity
that is like this.
If we have a long T1 component,
but we measure with 1.5 seconds TR,
we get the same pixel intensity.
So unlike the CT units--
the Hounsfield units in an MRI--
we cannot attribute a signal intensity
in a pixel to a specific value of T1
or a specific biophysical mechanism
because we need to know
how this has been measured.
So in this particular example,
if we had measured at 1.5 seconds,
this component
will give the same intensity
as if we had measured at 500 milliseconds
for a short T1 component.
So this is essential here
that the pixel intensity, as such,
doesn't have a direct
biophysical interpretation.
Now if we are doing
this multipulse experiment,
so we apply a 90 degree pulse
every TR second,
at what point would be
the most sensitive to changes in T1?
And for imaging that's important,
that would give us the maximum contrast.
To approach this, we will use
the error propagation calculation
that I introduced in lesson one
of part one of this course.
The same procedure here applies.
So first we calculate the derivative
of the z magnetization with respect to T1.
This just tells us how strong
does the z magnetization vary
if one were to vary T1.
So where is the z magnetization?
How much does it vary
in response to variations to T1?
So that's just the derivative
of this term with respect to T1
and this is the expression that we obtain.
And we'll call this function big F.
Of course we know, if we measure with TR
it essentially equals zero.
The magnetization cannot recover
so it will be essentially zero.
So we are not sensitive to changes in T1.
And if we write 5 times the biggest T1
that is present in our tissue
then everything has recovered to M_0
and we're again, not sensitive
to changes in T1.
So somewhere between zero and infinity--
for the time T--
we have a maximum of this function.
And to find the maximum
of this function F,
we'll take the derivative of F
with respect to the time T,
which is here the TR.
We'll set the F to dt equals zero,
we want to find the maximum,
we do the chain rule for derivation,
so that's what we're interested in
and then we obtain this expression here.
If we simplify what we've obtained here,
this is not zero, this is not zero
so only what is in brackets can be zero.
And t equals the optimal TR,
if the optimal TR is equal to T1.
So this is a not surprising result,
we have seen similar things.
We're always dealing
with exponential functions
and typically the change
in the decay constant
or, here, the T1 is optimally detected
if we measure at an exponential parameter
that corresponds to this decay time,
or the T1 here.
So in other words, if we have
a rough idea what the T1 is,
we should be setting
for a series of 90 degree pulses
that we apply every TR seconds.
We should be setting this TR to roughly T1
to be most sensitive to changes in T1.
And here is a message that is dear to me
that I want to stress.
The intensity in our images--
the MRI images that are being measured--
depend strongly
on the relaxation, but in a way,
that depends strongly
on how this signal intensity
is being measured.
So let's look at the transverse component.
We have transverse magnetization.
This is cerebrospinal fluid,
we have gray matter, white matter and fat.
And we can see for CSF--
cerebrospinal fluid
which contains very little cell membranes,
very little proteins--
the T2 is very long,
it's about 1.4 seconds in this example.
Gray matter is at 100 milliseconds
and white matter is at 90 milliseconds.
And then we have fat here,
so 37% of the decay signal
gives us the T2 here.
If we look now at the recovery--
here's the 90 degree pulse
and the recovery,
then fat goes the fastest,
white matter goes second fastest
then gray matter then CSF.
And CSF here in this example
has a T1 of 2.5 seconds.
So what we see here is now typically
we would do a T2-weighted image
if we want to see changes in T2.
We would wait a certain time
after the excitation pulse
and detect the signal.
Now CSF will be the brightest
because it has the longest T2,
it has very little protein in it
so it has long T2.
Conversely, CSF has long T1
but here we're deducing the waiting
by waiting not the full time,
we're waiting a shorter time
than full relaxation.
So actually, the signal
from the cerebrospinal fluid
will be lower compared to the signal
from gray matter and white matter.
So even though it has long T1
and a long T2 in T1-weighted images
the CSF will be dark
and in T2-weighted images
it will appear bright
compared to the other tissues.
So let's look at an example here.
We have on the vertical axis
we are plotting the time after excitation
and the TR on the horizontal axis.
And so we have a very long TR here,
we go from 30 to 160 milliseconds.
Look at the eye bulbs
which are primarily just water,
how bright they get
with a longer time after excitation.
As we start reducing the TR,
we're starting to have
increasing effects of T1
and we're starting also to see
that the images are getting darker.
That is a consequence
of not being over here
but being more and more closer
to this situation.
We're here at 800 milliseconds
and here is 200 milliseconds.
We can clearly see the fat here
becoming bright at short echo time
and short TR.
The fat is becoming bright,
the CSF here is dark,
the eyes are dark--
that is consistent with these values here.
And what is also important here
is a good choice of parameters
allows to depict
certain pathological conditions.
A bad choice of parameters is detrimental
to detection of any signal.
So if one is to choose a long echo T--
time after excitation--
and a long TR,
then we are basically seeing no signal
and that is not a good choice.
So in order to interpret MRI signals,
one has to know
the experimental conditions
that are being done
and this is one of the reasons
why MRI is such a complex technique
to use in clinical practice
but it is also an advantage
because we have a lot of mechanisms
and means to manipulate image contrast.
Now I want to conclude this week's lecture
with a summary on magnetic resonance.
What do we know so far?
So we have established last week
that we need a magnetic field B_0.
This establishes
an equilibrium magnetization M_0
that is parallel to the z axis.
And this equilibrium magnetization
increases with the number
of spins in the voxel,
it increases
with the static magnetic field B_0
and it increases
with the gyromagnetic ratio gamma.
So that's one thing that we need.
We need to be in a strong magnetic field
to have an equilibrium magnetization.
Then we need a RF field--B_1--
which is typically applied
on the resonance
that is close to
that Larmor frequency, omega L.
And this B_1 field allows us
to tilt the magnetization
into the transverse plane,
so we're tilting the z magnetization
into the transverse plane.
Here the plane is in xy.
The signal detection process
of magnetic resonance imaging
is done by precession.
We're looking at the transverse component
of the magnetization
that precesses
around the magnetic field B_0.
That is the detection process.
Then we have established this week
that we have relaxation for T2
that decays and for T1 which builds up.
So we have an exponential decay
of the transverse magnetization
and exponential return of Mz to M_0
that's described by T1 and T2 relaxation.
These time constants T1 and T2
reflect the molecular environment
in which the molecule finds itself
and they are a major source
of contrast in MRI.
So now some take home messages.
In MRI, we can only detect mobile spins.
So typically of major interest
here is water.
Immobile nuclei--
nuclei that are part of a molecule
that's immobile--
are not detected.
The equilibrium magnetization
reflects the number of nuclei
and thus the water content in tissue.
Now, water content typically varies
between 70 and 100%
or 70 milliliters per 100 gram
to 100 milliliters per 100 gram
in our bodies.
And so it is actually
not a good source of contrast.
To detect tissue contrast,
we rely on differences between T1 and T2.
Those T1 and T2 differences,
how they manifest themselves
on the image contrast
depends strongly on
the experimental parameters.
Examples that we have seen,
are RF pulse timing
or generally pulse timing,
and another example here
is the flip angle alpha
by which the magnetization is tilted
into the transverse plane.
So these are the key messages.
This is what we have so far dealt with:
magnetic resonance.
Next week we will talk about spectroscopy
and this makes a link between MRI
and the chemical applications
of magnetic resonance.