After nature,
let's have a look on time.
Space and time are often associated,
at least because we massively use
spatial metaphors to address
the complexity of time.
This second transversal approach
will lead us towards
a fundamental principle :
geography is not the opposite of history.
Both geographicity and historicity
are dimensions of the thick bundle
of logics that make us, society, exist
as a complex yet consistent reality.
When we cross-cut space with time,
we discover that time is at any
of its scale
a major spatial substance
as well as power or money.
To explore this dimension,
we welcome Hélène Noizet,
a remarkable historian of space,
that is to say, a time geographer.
She prepared this session
with a contribution of
Groupe Du Lac,
a group of historians, archeologists,
and geographers
focused on space-time relationships.
Hello, we’re only going to talk here
about historical time
and Western Europe in general.
In this session,
we’re going to address the temporal dimension of social facts,
which are also fundamentally spatial, as we’ve seen before.
First of all,
we’ll see that space has a history
Certain social forms are located in space and in time
having a beginning and an end.
Conceptual tools from metric geography
such as the territory-network pair
help us to better define ancient social structures
for example those from the Middle Ages.
Later,
we’ll demonstrate the discontinuity of spatio-temporal processes
in the construction of the social.
The goal is not to juxtapose the dimension of time with that of space,
but to intersect them
by analysing social processes
as specific spatio-temporalities.
Space has a history.
Certain contemporary social arrangements
seem structural to us,
and it’s difficult to imagine things working differently
since we’re so much a part of them.
And yet neither the State, nor the city,
nor even the fact of gathering together into communities
are a given;
they are not inherent necessities for the human condition.
Only biological needs such
as eating and sleeping
are invariables for the human race.
Beyond that, everything is a a matter of space and time.
This means that spatial forms of the social can be historicised.
For example, the idea of a national State
is a relatively recent form of organisation in Western Europe.
It began to be set up at the end of the Middle Ages, in the 14th to 15th centuries,
developed during the Modern Era
and has seriously been brought into question since the end of the 20th century.
Globalisation, supranational constructions,
and regionalisation undermine the national scale.
Whether we accept it or not,
the national State is no longer destined to be the principle operator
of supra-local spatiality.
If this social form now seems to be heading towards its end,
it also once had a beginning.
At the end of the Middle Ages, lasting administrations emerged
which were at the service of a single power,
and national sentiments
were more and more exclusive
for example in France and England
following the Hundred-Year War.
It must be noted that at that time
the properly territorial dimension
of this political construction, the State,
was not at all a given
contrary to what is often said.
Too often, what is understood today by “State”
is projected backwards onto previous ways of working.
By doing this,
we inject modern attributes into the past,
such as that of territoriality,
which weren’t there from the beginning
of the state-making process.
For example,
the most classical maps on the construction of the Royal Capetian domain,
considered as the foundation of the French national State,
were mostly choropleth maps,
such as those by Auguste Longnon in 1884,
Fernand Braudel in 1986,
or Georges Duby's one,
which was republished in 2008.
And yet even at the end of the Middle Ages,
written documents identifying the rights and revenues of the king
clearly carry a fundamentally reticular dimension of royal power.
The king , and it is the same for all feudal lords ,
never held power over all of a region
in a continuous manner
but only over precisely located points,
such as this map of points
by Olivier Guyotjeannin in 2005 shows.
This map is more respectful
of Medieval reality than previous maps were.
If this map refers to a 12th-century reality,
during the reign of Louis the VIIth,
it is difficult to apply it to later realities.
It was still clear in the 14th century
that royal power wasn’t territorial
as demonstrates the cartography
done by Marie-Pierre Buscail in 2014
on the prisée, the price evaluation of 1332.
The prisée was a document
listing revenues located in the Gâtinais,
a little region to the south of Paris,
destined for the queen in case of the king’s death.
By looking at the local scale,
like here in the provostship of Janville,
we can well see how the powers exercised in different places were entangled.
Here’s the king in black
as well as the Lord of Puiset in red
but also the Lord Bishop of Bonneval Abbey in purple.
Given the reticular form of royal rights,
it is impossible to assign
a territorial dimension to kings during this era,
an era which however saw the introduction
of other fundamental characteristics of the national State.
Finally, it wasn’t before the French Revolution
and Napoleonic Empire
that the definition of the areas covered
by departments and communes
created truly local territories.
The continuous juxtaposition of all of these spaces,
with a perfect joining between each sector,
ensured that there were no empty spaces
and that any point in space
fell within the scope of only one public authority.
This contributed to territorialising the State.
This reasoning, that historicises the nation State, can be can be applied
at a more local scale,
to the city, which deserves to be conceptually distinguished from the urban.
The urban,
is one of three ways of managing distance
through co-presence in addition to two other ways,
transportation and telecommunication.
Just like the other two ways,
the urban has always existed
and has been translated into variable spatial arrangements.
The city is one of them.
The city can be defined
as a temporary and particular configuration of urban space,
erected as a powerful ideal model,
yet still capable of legitimising action.
However, the development of the city
still remains a historical sequence,
and is therefore temporally situated,
generally from 1350 to 1950.
From the middle of the 14th century,
every urban form has been thought of as a city.
The city at that time was thought of as a symbiotic unity AND a territory.
The symbiotic unity was the civitas,
which was a city made up of a political community
endowed with its own personality,
and formalised through an institutionalised municipal government.
The territory was the urbs,
whose material unification
through a barrier encircling it
helped to give it both
the singularity of a place,
and a territorial envelope
with a distinction between inside and outside.
Therefore, it could be said that the city
is the urban conceived of as a territorial place.
Frescos painted by the Lorenzetti brothers in the Sienna city hall,
from 1337 to 1339,
show for the first time
a territorialising bi-partition of humanised space.
All of human beings’ spatial devices
can thus be summed up into an alternative pair,
that of city and country,
the separation being realised by an urban fences.
However, this modern and territorialised conception of the city,
which existed materially until the 20th century,
and still exists today from an ideal point-of-view,
did not exist between the 8th and 14th centuries.
At least during this phase, which lasted for a long time,
whether it’s based on textual documentation or images,
everything shows that the urban
was fundamentally segmented and polynuclear.
Obviously, there existed urban settlements characterised by co-presence,
implying socio-spatial density and diversity.
For example, this archeological site in the South-West of France,
dating back to the 8th to 10th centuries,
shows a very high density of silos arranged in a series,
destined for grain storage.
However, these populations didn’t have any residential structures
on the site where the silos were found ;
So we found silos but no living areas.
It was a bit like our modern-day supermarkets in commercial areas,
where nobody lives but where everyone goes to do their shopping.
Finally the contemporary urban form,
often qualified as broken, distended, diffuse, and geographically spread-out
has some points in common
with the first medieval urban,
so mainly from 8th to 13-14th centuries.
Thirdly, after having visited the cases of the State and the City,
we could also talk about
communities of inhabitants at the local level.
They also corresponded
to a special organization of the social sphere,
which appeared in Western Europe between the 10th and 12th centuries,
so in the Middle-Age,
and lasted until the end of the 18th century.
Inhabiting is not to be considered
only in its material dimension,
but as a set of social relationships of power.
Hence, communities of inhabitants allowed lords
to dominate people who were dependent on them in other ways than directly
and coercively, like it was the case in the high Middle Ages.
From then on, the community of inhabitants will be divided in "feux"
that is to say in households, as we woud say today.
Especially from the High Middle Age
this community of inhabitants is to constitute
a moral person
whose legal existence was recognized by lords
in charters of liberties.
These "feux" were relatively autonomous in their daily lives,
even materially,
as suggested by this bird’s eye view of Rohrdorf in 1575-76,
a Swabian village in Germany.
This community of inhabitants is represented
as a block of autonomous "feux",
with each house having its own enclosed garden.
These households were gathered around the church,
which was more-or-less located at the village centre,
Having the church in the village centre
dates from the High Middle Ages, that is to say very recently.
was not at all an immemorial, eternal form of the rural landscape.
Like the State or the City,
the community of inhabitants as a concept
developed relatively later on, in the second half of the Middle Ages.
If the church was an element of the homogenization of these many households,
the properly seigniorial factor also unified the agglomeration
into a community of inhabitants.
In face of the lords
the community’s many households only constituted one being,
one body,
which is also suggested by this picture.
This view was created within the context of a trial between several lords
to know exactly in which part of this village
the baron of Zimmern could exercise his justice.
The unity of this community of inhabitants is suggested by the village fence,
called an etter,
the alignment about which these lords disagreed.
The black line defined the jurisdiction of baron of Zimmern
according to his opponent, the Counts of Zollern,
whereas the red line defined this same jurisdiction according to the barons of Zimmern.
These demarcations were identified by a certain number of places,
such as trees, doors, fences, and so forth,
numbered starting from one..
The other unifying elements of these households, which were otherwise autonomous,
correspond to particular points in space,
all of which were meeting points:
that is to say points of polarization in social life,
under the auspices of ecclesiastical and seigniorial powers.
The church, the pendulum wells, or yet the village square
which served as a place for the proclamation of seigniorial decisions,
and where seigniorial justice was administrated.
These various hand-drawn objects
were either places of polarized movements,
such as the church, well, and meeting place,
or places preventing crosspassing, such as the etter gates:
all of them refer thus to constrained movements.
What such a figurative representation
of a community of inhabitants hardly shows
are the dependents’ movements within this particular space,
which were linked to the seigniorial domination.
In fact, one of the core interests of the community of inhabitants
was that it assumed, at least partially,
the distribution and collection of seigniorial dues,
and that, through physical and ritualized movements of goods and people,
this collection objectified and made the holders of seigniorial authority
visible to everybody.
The community of inhabitants
was a structure for the seigniorial appropriation
of rights over a space:
but this appropriation was achieved by the dependents themselves,
at once spatially, via perambulation through the territory,
and temporally according to a specific calendar.
On this actual photograph of signposts
from a French commune in Ambourville, Normandy,
the arrows symbolize the spatio-temporal movement
structuring a community of inhabitants.
First, we can see the present direction of City Hall
which is the same direction as the church, and opposite that of the castle.
This makes manifest the “historical victory” of the clergy
over the secular lords
from the point-of-view of the structural development of the community of inhabitants:
the church more than the castle
was therefore the principal pole for community densification since the end of the Middle Ages.
Moreover, the diverging arrows correspond to specific movements in space.
It suggests that medieval mastery over space firstly worked
through a regulation of movement
that is to say through imposed rhythms of spatial usage:
when, how often and how you had go to a given spot.
Social domination and internal promotions were achieved
through the frequency imposed upon movements,
going, for example, from a pure and simple prohibition
all the way up to a coerced daily frequency;
through the scope of movements,
from a purely domestic stay to a faraway pilgrimage;
through the ritualization and social values and so on.
with which these were achieved, and so on.
The internal structure of the mighty group
resulted from the establishment of priorities between lords in this regulation of mobility:
the more one could spatio-temporally regulate the movement of others,
(including other lords) to their own profit, and the less their own movements
were regulated from outside, the more dominant position one could have.
These arrows not only represent a spatial phenomenon,
for example a direction to take or a distance to cross,
but also a temporal phenomenon,
such as the length of the journey,
which is today only indicated
for marginal social activities
such as hiking trails.
However, the movement is as much about time as it is about space
in the same way as co-presence is as much a spatial phenomenon
as it is a temporal one.
Overall, the social interpretation
of the emergence of these communities of inhabitants
is completely different from that which is normally drawn.
There was no local proto-democracy
bringing seigniorial authority into question;
it was not a liberation,
but to the contrary,
a system of collective self-disciplining,
allowing for the maintenance of seigniorial domination over dependents
through specific spatio-temporal regulations.
These regulations were interiorized and effectively achieved by the dependents themselves,
which has been shown to be a much more effective method of control
than merely coercion by the mighty. Social organisation historicised in this way
encourages us to more broadly intersect
the spatial and temporal dimensions of social facts,
not only within a given time, as we saw for the Middle Ages,
but also within the longer temporality of transmission,
or yet between different times.
First of all,
we’ll see how in a certain way
the past doesn’t exist,
and that over the long term
the heritage of past societies
cannot be preserved as such
but must be re-actualised,
so as to both be transmitted and transformed.
Then, we’ll see how space can produce the social,
or in other words be an operator for spatialities,
through spatio-temporal connections and recurrences.