This photo shows the ruins of the burned-out village of Oradour-sur-Glane,
in Limousin, France, whose entire population of men, women, and children
were atrociously massacred on June 10th, 1944 by SS troops.
There rapidly developed both a local and national movement to preserve these ruins
in their original state in order to give witness to the horror of Nazi barbarity.
It shows how,
in Oradour, life brutally came to a halt that day.
It seemed essential
then to show a place frozen in time, as if suddenly fossilised
by the historical cataclysm which had seized it. Yet, no one had imagined at the time the
effects that the site’s own inertia would have, a site which itself had not died in 1944.
People still continued to pass by along the road to Oradour;
peasants still owned barns where they stored their agricultural machinery;
families still had gardens where they grew vegetables…
In short, the ordinary material things of life
continued in Orador despite the traumatic event.
So, one of the principle measures to accompany the ruins’ recognition
as a national historical monument in 1946
was enclosing it within a barrier
and completely forbidding access and thoroughfare.
To preserve Oradour as a historical monument,
Oradour had to cease being a place of human occupation.
Those responsible for the administration of historical monuments
to whom the project had been entrusted had not anticipated
the growing importance that the maintenance work would take
in order to preserve the site, as soon as Oradour was completed.
At first, only minor maintenance work had been planned,
such as weed removal, or small repairs in the stonework,
to be carried out by communal employees.
Yet from 1946 on,
a real building programme had to be launched,
with more and more work needed every year:
walls which were falling down and exposed to storms had to be fixed,
and rotting wood over door lintels had to be replaced by pieces of concrete…
In the same way, as soon as the gardens were gone,
which had nonetheless contributed to the site’s upkeep,
there was no other solution than to create large, grassy spaces
in order to control the rampant growth of bushes and trees.
Over time, and year by year, Oradour took on the surrealist physiognomy
of a fabricated, contemporary park of ruins,
in which restorative work progressively was substituted for the original elements.
The preservation of Doctor Descourteaux’s car
is without doubt the most striking example
of the impossibility of fixing archeological constructions in the past.
This car was at first supposed to recall the circumstances
in which Doctor Descourteaux had to abandon his car on the spot,
upon arriving in Oradour and immediately being carried away by SS troops to be killed.
The car has remained there ever since,
but what is striking today is that
it resembles less and less
what would be expected of a real car:
since 1944, all of the paint has disappeared, leaving the oxidised metal visible,
which had to be stabilised and protected using an anti-corrosion polish.
Small elements such as window-wipers and rear-view mirrors
are no longer there, as well as some of the windows and the seat lining.
The tires have literally disintegrated;
the car’s carcass now sits on the ground directly on its chassis
a bit awry, while the base of the doors has fallen onto the pavement.
What is visible today is no longer a car from the 1940s;
it’s an archeological vestige of a car from the 1940s,
such as can be presented in the 2000s,
that is to say that it has changed from 1944 to 2014.
Therefore, whatever we may do, the past continues to exist
and to be transformed in the present.
It is because we believe in a unilinear and sequential historical time,
in which every temporality follows that which precedes it,
that we are persuaded that Oradour must be preserved in its original state.
But we don’t see that this historical time, which we want to remain fixed,
is not the archeological time of the vestiges themselves.
In fact, to preserve the remains of the past “in their original state”,
it takes a whole lot of additions foreign to them,
that is to say it takes reinventing them.
Thus, vestiges from the past can travel through time
and arrive at our knowledge of them only by being transformed.
Exactly the same observation could be made about another object, more ancient yet,
that of Roman centuriation.
In Antiquity, centuriation was a surveying technique used to create
a subdivision of land for colonists,
most often veteran soldiers,
in a land conquered by the Roman army.
They were created by regular squared grids,
formed of squares about 700 metres to a side,
and which depended on a main axis indicating the general orientation,
which was called the cardo maximus.
These grids exist in present landscapes
and can stretch on for several hundreds of square kilometres,
such as in Italy, as these satellite photos of Venezia show,
which is a landscape presently known under the name of graticolato romano,
or in Romagna, Cesena.
A simple first question is, from when does this centuriated landscape date?
Classically, the founding moment is given,
that of centuriation’s implementation,
principally dating from the era of the Roman Republic
from 509 BC to 27 BC,
saying that centuriation has been more-or-less well “preserved”
or “fossilised” from Antiquity to the present day.
But in the constitutive elements of the squared grids visible from these aerial photos
from the beginning of the 21st century, not everything dates from Antiquity, far from it.
Even better, certain sections of centuriation which are several hundreds of metres long,
have been excavated by archaeologists.
However, either they don’t reveal any antique vestiges but only a ditch from modern times,
as in the case of centuriation B Orange, Bartras site,
or there is a present materialisation along the ancient axis,
such as a road, while the Roman ground is buried
under 3 to 5 metres of sediment,
as in the case of Lugo, Romagna
Therefore in certain places, the axes of centuriation awaited the Modern
or even Contemporary era to be materialised, that is to say, to be imprinted onto the soil,
in the form of a ditch or a road.
In Antiquity these axes only existed as survey lines,
without a material basis, so they were merely sight-lines.
They only became material limits,
such as drainage ditches or roads,
at a much later date, without relationship, then,
to the ancient structure to which it referred.
Therefore we have the choice of understanding this question in two different ways.
One, the classic understanding, says that what we see on the present map is Roman,
and that it is inertia that explains its survival,
which is the fixed notion of linear continuity and durability.
Another way of understanding it, a new one,
says that the perfect planimetry which can be seen on the maps of Padua or Cesena
are creations over time
and that they probably didn’t exist in those forms in Antiquity,
that they are as much Medieval, Modern, and Contemporary than Roman.
So we have to replace the idea of survival
by that of construction over time.
The explanation that this is the form’s fossilisation or an inertia
doesn’t work anymore because these spaces have not been unused since Ancient times
quite on the contrary. We must therefore consider
a diachronic reading of centuriation, highlighting Medieval and Modern interventions
which have reactualised the system’s overall form, or have even extended it.
In both cases, in Oradour as with the centuriations, if the form inherited
from a previous social configuration is still present,
it’s not only because previous societies have agreed to produce such or such configuration,
such as destroying a village or assigning conquered land to colonists.
It is also subsequently because the following societies have,
whether consciously or not, replayed the inherited spatial device
through other social configurations.
These new configurations re-actualised the inherited forms.
To do this, they transmitted the previous form while giving it a new meaning,
for example by turning it into a heritage site in Oradour,
or into a drainage operation during the Medieval or Modern eras, as with the centuriations.
This is where the idea comes from that the past as such doesn’t exist,
but that it has been transmitted to us all the way through to the present by way of
a series of intermediary moments which are just as necessary as the initial moment was.
Therefore, we suggest formalising this idea by the concept of “transformission”,
meaning that every configuration inherited from the past can only be transmitted
if it is reused,to different ends, and thus necessarily
more-or-less reorganised, transformed.
With the examples of Oradour and the centuriations,
we’ve seen that the relationship to time is not more linear
than the relationship to space is isotropic.
To this must be added the fact that
history can be consciously mobilised
as an efficient spatial resource.
Therefore, we’re now going to see
how spatio-temporal connections produce the social.
In spatial planning projects today, there’s sometimes
an explicit desire to bring the present closer to a time
very far removed in the past or even in space.
Different temporal states, as well as discontinuous states for the same space,
can thus be directly connected.
These connections, as artificial as they may be
since they neglect all of the effective intermediate phases of transmission, are themselves
powerful operators of spatiality. They justify the decisions made at the present moment
and thus participate in the production of a new, socio-spatial configuration.
During the Fascist era in Italy,
urban planning projects for the city of Rome offer
good examples of this time-compression,
which put Mussolini’s Rome into direct relationship with Roman antiquity.
Great clearances aimed at putting the capital on stage,
and mass pro-regime demonstrations are organised.
In particular, the creation of the Via dell’Impero
between 1930 and 1933, which is now the Via dei Fori Imperiali, built right through
the middle of the vestiges of the Forum, allowed the regime to link the Piazza Venezia
to the Coliseum.- Palazzo Venezia was the epicentre for the new seat of power :
it was transformed into Mussolini’s residence, while the Monument to Vittorio Emmanuelle II
became in 1926 the Altar of the Fatherland. This project carried out to the detriment of
archeological preservation presents the Fascist regime as the heir of Roman Emperors.
This production of centrality and urban space
is based on the compression method.
It is a discursive urban planning procedure that legitimates the present power
by bringing the contemporary stratum closer to the glorious strata of the past,
in this case an ancient stratum,
and by erasing any intermediate transmission.
On another note, heritage making also creates
a connection between temporalities, which are often discontinuous,
and we can perceive the desire to remove a section of space out of its
« normal » evolution so as to enable it to be transmitted.
Beyond spatio-temporal connections, which are conscientious reconstructions,
the ability space has to produce the social
and thus to indirectly be a social operator, is also related to certain
recurrent spatio-temporalities, which for example can be observed at the global scale.
Progressions of spatial modifications which can be generalised
starting from a precise historical case do in fact exist.
Regular successions of synchronic configurations
can thus be identified and found again in very different contexts.
For example, the evolution of the Mediterranean basin
from early to late Roman Empire, along with the shift
in its centre of gravity from Rome to Constantinople,
can be resumed in the following manner:
At the age of early Empire, Rome was in the centre of its space.
In fact, this central position was the inheritance of two successively dominant spaces,
Greece and then Rome.
Then there were asymmetric external pressures
from the so-called barbarian invasions starting in the mid-3rd century.
Faced with this threat, people returned to their old home
and the capital was displaced to Constantinople in 330.
This caused a decentring and stretching of maximal distances.
From then on, ruptures were created along the offset boundary,
with a new wave of barbarian invasions starting in the 5th century.
This finally produced two types of inherited spaces, one which was fragmented,
in Western Europe where a mosaic of Romano-German kingdoms were created,
and the other a hardened space, in the Byzantine Empire in the East.
This progression, which can be called the Constantinople principle,
can thus be generalised in the following form: “central position,
decentring based on a threat, fragmentation or hardening”
which recalls the general outline decontextualising the principle.
However, it is interesting to see that this principle also works for another case,
completely different in space and in time : Ancient Egypt during the three millennia
before our era. This case even allows us to consider complex spatio-temporal dynamics.
Traditionally, Upper and Lower Egypt were contrasted
each having  its own capital location: number two at North being Tanis, or Avaris;
and number three in the south being Thebes.
When Egypt was united, the capital became the pivot
between Upper and Lower Egypt: this is number one, Memphis, or Licht.
That is moreover, Cairo’s location today.
The recurrent evolution of Egyptian space can be schematised in four steps:
A = Egypt was united and governed from the pivot between Upper and Lower Egypt
B = This unification allowed the Egyptian Empire to become powerful,
and thus conquer lands towards the south, in Nubia,
or towards the north-east, for example in the 15th century BC.
C = The North became distant and ran the risk of gaining independence,
which caused a power vacuum. If this internal depression in Egyptian space
had come at the same time as an external pressure, there would have been a risk of invasion.
Faced with the threat, the seat of power was displaced towards the North according
to the Constantinople principle. D = In turn, the southern part of Egypt became independent.
If the disunited empire  hadn’t resisted, Egypt would have been conquered.
In the North, a decentered capital represented the invading power, with the conquest
starting in the south. et la conquête se fait à partir du sud.
The Egyptian spatial configurations can thus be resumed in four simple types:
A = A united Egypt, a strong and conquering State
B = A divided Egypt, but only divided into two States, capable of resisting
external pressures for at least a certain time
C = A reunited Egypt, but weakened and submitted to external pressures
D = A politically fragmented Egypt dominated from outside.
However over time, these configurations could be observed
to progress several times in this order: D => B => A => B, or C => D
This progression corresponded to what we call, in Egyptian history,
an “empire” (B=>A=>C), framed by intermediate periods (D).
We could thus summarise this into a model of Egyptian history,
which progressed in a complex but recurrent manner,
according to the Constantinople principle:
The first rectangle represents the Ancient Egyptian Empire 2700-2200 BC.
The second represents the Middle Egyptian Empire 2033-1786 (2000-1800)
The third represents the New Egyptian Empire 1500-1000
Et entre chacun des ces trois moments,
on a une phase D.
These repeatable progressions can thus create spatio-temporal scenarios,
or in other words geo-historical evolutions.
Their recurrence in different circumstances shows that
space is an essential actor in history.
Clearly this must not be viewed as deterministic,
but only as a way of showing that spatial configuration is one of the elements
which comes into play when some decision is made,
for example in the choice of a capital.
It is this sometimes important role of spatial positioning which explains
the regularity in certain spatio-temporal combinations over history’s long duration.
In conclusion, let us summarise several lessons:
1. Certain spatial configurations, such as the city and the State,
can be historicised.
They are not unsurpassable and invariable frameworks of humanity,
but spatial sequences, in these cases territorialised,
limited in time, generally since the end of the Middle Ages up
until the 20th century.
Such an intellectual deconstruction should allow us to accept the changes
in these Modern but inherited political frameworks,
and to accept them not as a tragedy,
but as an inherent consequence of the human condition.
2. The past does not exist as such,
but is always made known to the present through a process of transmission
which necessarily causes its transformation, re-actualisation, and reinvention.
For example, it would be better to think of development projects,
not as lasting but as transformable.
Whatever money, energy, and power
is put into a development project, it will only be temporary
since the social forces which created it won’t exist eternally,
and the project will last only if it is re-appropriated and transformed.
It would thus be better to assume the obsolescence of spatial amenities
and encourage their capacity for re-appropriation rather than to seek
to lengthen their lifespan.
3. Modes of articulation between space-times
allow for a better understanding of social dynamics
than when only one spatial or temporal dimension of society is considered.
This can occur either by synchrony,
that is a social community conceived of as a special structure
for the appropriation of a space-time, or by diachrony,
in spatio-temporal recurrences and connections.