The Virial theorem is to random motion
what Kepler's laws are to planar motion.
It relates the kinetic energy
to the potential energy of « self-gravitating»
systems,
that is systems under the influence of their
own gravitational field
and isolated from any external gravitational
field.
Such systems include globular clusters
or more generally stellar clusters, such as
Omega Centauri, shown here.
Its mass, 1.5 million solar masses,
can be measured by applying the Virial theorem.
Lets demonstrate the Virial theorem in the
following
which says that the time average of twice
the kinetic energy
is equal to the time average of the potential
energy.
Let us consider
a quantity S equals to the sum over all particles
k
of the momenta times the radius vectors.
This is the projection of all the momenta
vectors
along the radius vectors of all particles.
As both the radius vectors and the velocities
are distributed randomly
around a centre of gravity common to all particles,
the time variation of S oscillates around
a mean value of zero.
Therefore the derivative also oscillates around
The time average of dS/dt must then be zero.
Let us compute this derivative.
We have the sum of two mean values.
One of them is the average of the potential
energy and
the other is twice the average of the kinetic
energy
as we are going to show.
Let us rewrite the equation seen previously.
Here we have simply separated the two terms
of the equation.
We immediately recognize the velocity vector.
P can be expressed as a function of the velocity.
We have thus m v_k times v_k.
The vector v_k is obviously collinear with
v_k
and we recognize immediately
minus two times the average of the kinetic
energy of the particles.
We now have to show that the other side of
the equation
is the time average of the potential energy.
This is what we are going to see now.
Let us rewrite this side.
We recognize here the force
which must be the gravitational force since
we have a central force.
The gravitational force.
If we can show
that this term is minus the potential energy
then we will have proven the Virial theorem.
This is the same term as before.
We know know that we have a gravitational
force
which is a force that can be derived from
a potential.
We can therefore choose a potential.
Let us call it ϕ (r).
It is proportional to the radius raised to
a certain power.
For gravity, n = -2 so the potential depends
on -1/r
Let us rewrite the force in this way here.
What we have really written
is the derivative of the potential
with respect to the radius
with the potential that we chose here.
We can now rewrite the sum over k of all vectors
F_k r_k
We now have n+1 at the exponent since we multiplied
by the radius.
We can therefore immediately identify the
potential
since we have here the same term as in the
and r^(n+1) here.
We can then rewrite this term as a function
of the potential.
We immediately recognise the potential energy.
For easier notation, we previously removed
the bracket
representing the time average.
We didn't make any calculation that would
make this average disappear
so we put the brackets back at the end here.
We have thus proven the Virial theorem.
The Virial theorem is extremely useful in
astrophysics
because we have on one side
the mass of the bodies through their potential
energy (U)
and on the other side we can generally express
the kinetic energy in two different ways.
A first way is as a function of the body's
temperature.
If we consider for example a gas cloud at
a given temperature
then we have 1/2 n k T with k the Boltzmann
constant
and T the temperature per degree of freedom.
K is then equal to 1/2 k T per degree of freedom.
For example if we have three dimensions and
n particles,
then K = 3/2 n k T
with K the Boltzmann constant and T the temperature.
If we consider a gas cloud
at a given temperature T with n particles,
then we can express its kinetic energy in
this way.
We can also express it in the more usual way
of being the sum of the kinetic energies
of all particles, that is 1/2 m_k (v_k)².
For example, if we have a cloud of particles
and we know all the velocities or the velocity
distribution
then we can express the kinetic energy in
this way.
We just saw how to express the kinetic energy.
Now let us have a look at how to express the
potential energy.
To this end, we greatly simplify the body
of interest.
Lets take a spherical approximation.
This spherical body has a given density ϱ
which does not depend on the radius. In other
words, ϱ is constant.
We now stack spherical shells of density ϱ
from the infinity to a given radius r to form
a body with
a total mass (M) and a final radius (R)
once we stacked all the spherical shells.
The variation of the potential energy due
to the stacking of all the spherical shells
is equal to the work of the gravitational
force
to bring a shell from infinity to the radius
r.
We will first compute this work to bring the
shell from here to there
before integrating, that is summing over the
works
of the gravitational forces to bring all the
spherical shells
from infinity to r.
Let us have a first look on how to integrate
the gravitational force
from infinity to a given radius r.
The force is the gravitational force
between the mass m(r) and the spherical shell
with mass dm
located at a distance s from the sphere of
radius r.
We integrate this with respect to the bound
variable s.
The result of this integral is completely
obvious.
This term evaluated between infinity and r
gives a variation of the potential energy.
We have thus computed the variation of the
potential energy
when the gravitational force works
to go from infinity to a radius r.
In order to get the total potential energy,
we have to sum over all the elementary potential
energies
that we computed previously from 0 to the
final radius R of the body
we are interested in getting the potential
energy.
This is the variation of the potential energy
that we just computed.
Let us rewrite it.
We can give an explicit form to this term
"dm"
by assuming as said earlier
that the mass density in the spherical shell
and in the sphere here is constant.
We have G m(r) / r.
The term dm is the surface of the sphere times
its density and thickness.
We now have an integral that only depends
on r
and that we can thus compute.
We still have to make a last assumption.
Since we assumed
the density of the body we are interested
in
to be constant,
we can assume its mass to be 4/3 π R³ ϱ.
In the same way, the the m(r) here can be
expressed as 4/3 π r³ ϱ
We have here a lower case r for the small
sphere
and an upper case R as the final radius
of the star or body we are interested in.
If we use this to end the calculation
we get that
the potential energy of a sphere is -3/5 G
M²/R
where M is the total mass of the body and
R the final radius.
Just like Kepler's laws,
the Virial theorem will appear many times
during the course.
It is essential in order to link the masses
of the studied bodies
to velocities or velocity distributions.
It is useful in the case of stellar clusters
where the velocities of the stars can be measured,
such as here with Omega Centauri cluster.
It is also the case for stars in galaxies
or even for galaxies in galaxy clusters
such as the one here.
All these astronomical bodies can be weighed
in order to determine their mass
through the measurement of velocities or velocity
distributions
by using the Virial theorem.