Now that you've had a chance
to go through all the tools
we've discussed in the course,
we wanted to come back
and try to tie things together.
I'll start by reminding you briefly
about the overall
technology innovation process.
Basically, the technology
innovation process
comprises three broad phases: the concept,
feasibility, and the implementation phases.
Phase one is the concept development
phase, which involves
a variety of issues, such as:
defining your mission,
choosing your pilot country origin,
engaging local stakeholders,
taking stock of alternative products,
and then defining your product specs.
Phase two is
the feasibility phase
where you attempt to test
and demonstrate
the feasibility of your product
concept and business model.
This may end up requiring you
to readjust your product concepts
and business strategy.
And phase three
is about implementation
that is actually bringing
the products to the market,
where you will aim to reach
your break even stage,
and then scaling up to other region.
This is also the phase where
you will need to diligently
carry out impact monitoring
activities, in order to ensure
that you advance towards
your original mission.
For each of the phases there
is one key message:
For the concept phase
the main message is to LEARN,
for the feasibility phase the main
message is to COLLABORATE
while for implementation
we say "BE AGILE".
For the rest of this lecture we'll
only focus on the Concept phase.
The concept phase can
be broadly divided into the following parts
which are:
1) Define your mission,
2)Define and engage your stakeholders,
3) Assess existing alternatives
and competition and understand
why they are falling short,
4) Define the specification or specs of
the solution you have identified.
Naturally, the first task for you
is to define your mission,
in other words: What problem
are you trying to solve,
and what change do
you want to achieve?
After you have done that,
then you need to go back
and do some background research,
in order the verify
that what you wish to solve
is indeed a real problem.
So, after you are satisfied
with the validity of the problem
then you must decide what is
the technology innovation solution
you wish to propose
to address the problem,
with a view to achieving your
desired change in the long term.
Then, after that, you need
to understand and define
who your stakeholders are exactly,
in other words, who are the direct and
indirect contributors or beneficiaries,
or said differently, who will
affect and/or be affected
by the activities of your organization
when implementing your solution?
Afterwards, create a Stakeholders'
Rating Table and identify
the ones who are absolutely key,
for example,
those scoring high on interest
and power to affect your solution.
But also identify those capable
of influencing perceptions
and opinion on your solution,
that is the Key Opinion Leaders.
Engage them as extensively
as feasible, in order to understand
what type of solution they
really wish to see for this problem.
Now, discuss your proposed solution
and find out what their opinion is
and what feedback
they can give you on it.
Once you have satisfactorily defined and verified the problem
and the change you ultimately aim
to achieve using your
proposed technology solution, then
you need to define the activities
required to get
to the required change.
This pathway of activities must
include deliverables
and milestones along the way,
as well as the metrics and methods
to measure and monitor them.
Now, if you think back to
the first tool we introduced,
namely the Impact Canvas,
you will see right away that
it is the ideal tool to enable you
to carry out
the process we mentioned above.
As you can see, the process of
defining your mission is very akin
to the theory of change methodology
in the impact plan development.
Therefore, the first key deliverable
for you
during the concept development phase
is the Impact Plan
or the Impact Framework.
Note that in order to help you
map out your stakeholders
a high level non-detailed analysis
of the product value chain
is the tool we recommend.
Now that you have defined
your technology solution concept,
the key question you have to address
is where you intend
to launch your product first,
in other words,
what will be your pilot market?
Even though our intention in this
course is to develop products
that eventually have as global a
reach as possible,
you must first learn to walk
before you can run.
Therefore, it is advisable to pinpoint
a pilot market prior to scaling up.
So, here we encourage you to think
global but at local, initially!
And we constantly remind you of this
philosophy throughout
the innovation process.
There are various factors to take
into consideration
when making this decision,
and here the PESTLE analysis
in the market part of the product
value chain tool
will be particularly useful
in helping you map out
key original parameters that may
have an impact
on your product's success
or lack thereof.
It is also important to start off with
a country you know reasonably well
and where you have good and reliable
contacts.
And for this reason, many tend
to choose their home
or domicile market initially,
after all, charity begins at home,
as they say in English.
But this need not
necessarily be the case,
choosing a pilot market is important,
because it will allow you
to go deeper and more specific in
your assessment
and understanding of customer needs
and get more concrete data
about your technology solution.
However, you must also guard against
over-tailoring your solution
to that specific region
to the extent that
it becomes irrelevant
outside that territory.
So try and select a country
or region that is as representative
as possible of the global community
you wish to address
with your solution.
In the case of the digital X-Ray
project that we discussed, for example,
Cameroon was chosen because
it was deemed to be sufficiently
representative of the challenges
we wished to address that are faced
by low and middle income countries
with respect to radiology
access and infrastructure.
You need to have a good
understanding of the status quo,
in other words, how are
the intended beneficiaries
currently obtaining the
benefit you wish to provide?
In most cases there is generally
an existing mechanism that
people try and obtain
an essential service or benefit from,
even if it's not
to their satisfaction.
Make a maximum effort to discuss
with and understand what
the clients do appreciate about it
and what they genuinely miss.
Be sure that whatever is missing
is what one might term
"A must-have" rather than
a "Nice-to-have" service or benefit.
In order to help you
with this particular process
we recommend using
the Porter 5 forces analysis
in conjunction
with desktop research.
As we said before, this will help
you understand where power lies
in the market place, as well as
understand your potential strength
in the market you will be
considering moving into.
Before you move to the next step,
for technology innovation
it is generally very important to understand
the intellectual property landscape
surrounding your solution.
Even if you do not wish to file
a patent, you still need to be sure
that you have what
is termed "Freedom to operate".
However, there are still many
regions in the developing world
who have weak intellectual property
laws, which may render even
a valid patent ineffective.
ineffective.
Consequently, many players simply do
not designate these regions when
filing patents.
However, the PESTLE analysis
should, in principle, provide
you the the relevant intellectual
laws for your pilot region,
you can then make the call
on the intellectual property issue.
After carrying out
the detailed process above,
you are now ready to start drafting
your initial product
specifications or specs.
This exercise is best done as a group
with your colleagues, for example.
If you have the opportunity,
make sure to also include
some key opinion leaders
and other relevant stakeholders
as this might also generate a sense
of ownership for the eventual product.
Getting such an early buy-in from
key opinion leaders and stakeholders
could pay off handsome dividends
for you, as they are likely
to be comfortable and
willing to advocate for the product.
Once you're satisfied with this version,
we recommend that you put it through
the low and middle income country
context assessment tool
that we discussed earlier,
in order to determine
how adapted your solution
will potentially be
in their anticipated contexts.
And if required, revise and alter the specs,
in order to comply with this context.
Finally, you should carry out
a SWOT Analysis,
in order to have a global overview
of products position. In addition,
do also carry out a SWOT Analysis
on the current team
to assess what strengths
are already available
and which vital competences
are missing
to successfully develop
the product concept.
Now based on your product's specs,
try and identify the
top two or three potential markets
opportunities
that could be addressed
with your product's specs.
And then, with the help of
the information you have collected
from the impact plan
and product value chain analysis
carry out the exercise of filling out
the sustainable business model canvas
for each of the product options
separately.
This will allow you to construct
various business models scenarios
that could result from your product.
And for each business opportunity
you should develop
a corresponding value proposition.
Ideally, you should carry out
this exercise as a group, involving
your colleagues
and any other relevant players
or stakeholders
that you may have access to.
Just remember that, the more diverse
the participants the better the outcome.
The process of carrying out
the activities we discussed
in the previous slides requires that
you spend an excessive amount of time
if you wish to do it well.
Therefore, in most cases it can be
very difficult to do it
as a part-time activity
and requires full-time commitment.
But depending on your personal
situation many people require
income for a living, and so,
the question begs as to
how do you finance yourself
during this phase?
I will say upfront that there is
no easy answer, unfortunately,
to this question, especially
at this early stage.
At this stage, traditional sources of finance
such as the banks, businesses angels
and venture capital are not likely
to take any interest
as it is too early-stage for them.
So, the number one source is you,
that is, your personal investments.
This includes not only any financial
expenditures you can make,
but the time, resources and
the sacrifices you need to make.
This also includes all days and
nights you may spend in your garage
testing out numerous technical
concepts.
Your number two source is likely
to be the so called the "Three F's":
Friends, Family and Fools.
They may be able to lend you money,
for example, to carry out the trips
and visits to meet the important
stakeholders,
or also by just allowing you
to continue to stay with them
without paying boarding
and lodging costs,
or simply giving you a downright
lump sum of money,
in return for equity
or a convertible loan.
And depending on where you are
there may be a variety of grants
for supporting early stage
startup companies.
But, generally speaking, cash grants
for the concept development phase
are rare.
However, there are several kinds
of support instruments,
such as Business Plan competition,
incubator and/or enterprise accelerators.
These instruments typically provide
in kind support of by way of giving you
access to expertise to help you
develop your product concept
as well as infrastructure such as
physical space
and IT.
So, to summarize what outputs
or deliverables should you plan
to have from the concept phase?
The first tool you used is
the Impact Framework tool,
which then provides you with
your Impact Plan as a deliverable.
And then you applied
the Product Value Chain analysis,
to give you a more comprehensive list
of stakeholders and key opinion leaders.
And finally, your product specs
or product concept.
And then the sustainable business
model canvas enabled you
to develop suitable business models
for each of the identified product
options from your product specs.
So, in general you will have noticed
how many times we encouraged
the interaction with/and
participation of stakeholders
in the various processes we have
discussed in this lecture.
That is because this is really
the phase when
it's vitally important that you put
together as accurate a concept
as possible before you go further
with the arduous process of
product development.
So again, we cannot over-emphasize
the need to involve
them in this phase.
Goodbye.