Hello. In this video we will
recapitulate the methodology
applicable to what we called
the feasibility phase.
The objective of this phase is to
demonstrate the feasibility of our
concept. This involves a technology
side and a business side as we
have seen. This phase is where we
need to remove all the unknowns
and risks we can. Because the next
step is when our concept will be
deployed. And, hopefully, scaled-up.
The best way to do that is to
test our concept and hypothesis
with stakeholders. In the previous
phase we have identified the
stakeholders and we have brought
together a project team which
includes diverse competences such as
engineers, marketers, specialists
and key opinion leaders.
Very importantly we have also
involved local people
from the pilot country which we have
selected in the previous phase.
We also need to keep in mind that
we will want to deploy our
technology not only in the pilot
country, but also in other regions
where there is the same unmet need.
Let us now look into this phase
in more details.
In the first phase we have developed
specifications that describe our
technology. We now need to verify
that this technology is really
feasible within those specifications.
Demonstrating technological
feasibility will generally require
that we develop and test some
prototypes.
When develop those prototypes, we
must constantly verify that our
choices are compliant with our
specifications. This technology
development task will need to be
properly documented.
It is important to write down all
the choices we make and why we make
those choices. There are chances
that we will need to refer to these
documents at a later stage. In
particular, when we need to make
changes. It is also very important
that we comply with industrial norms
applicable to our technology as
we have said multiple times
in this MOOC.
Technology development is not
something that can be done alone.
We need to constantly interact with
our stakeholders,
and especially with the users and
key opinion leaders.
We can easily see why this is
important.
There will always have to be
tradeoffs and these tradeoffs
need to be validated with the key
stakeholders.
There is a simple memory trick to
remember the most frequent
tradeoffs we will have to make.
We call it the CPD triangle.
For every choice we need to make
we will need to balance essentially
three things: the functionality or
performance of our technology,
the cost and the durability.
It is generally impossible to
maximize all three of these criteria
at the same time. So that we will
need to find an acceptable
compromise. Prototypes are immensely
useful in these regards,
as they can be used to assure that
we have properly understood
user needs. Let's look into these
with some examples taken from our
X-ray project.
During the feasibility phase of the
X-ray project it was determined that
the user interface needed to be
tested in details.
This user interface involved a touch
screen and a software allowing to
operate the X-ray system as well
as to acquire, store and review the
images. The team developed a
suitcase-like design which involved
the command touchscreen and the
diagnostics screen.
A first version of the software was
developed and integrated into the
prototype. The goal was only to
test how the user would respond to
the architecture of the
menus and buttons.
In the second picture you can see
the prototype being tested in Cameroon
by a local radiographer on the right,
under the supervision of the joint
project manager Dr. Moulion Tapouh
on the left, who is a Cameroonian
radiologist. The radiographer is
given a classic type of task
such as taking a radiography of
a limb, and every click is recorded
as well as the sequence in which
he operates the software.
At the end of the test he's
questioned for his impressions
and comments.
In this particular case the team
came to realize that the software
had many flaws and needed a quite
important redesign in order to be
more user friendly. This was an
important learning for the team.
In our second example the question
was to determine the best mechanical
configuration allowing to position
the detector on the X-ray tube
with respect to the patient.
A swivel arm solution had been
chosen by the engineering team.
However, it was crucial to determine
which were the patient positions
that were possible and those
that were not with this solution.
The problem was solved using
a wooden prototype which was
presented to Professor NKO'O,
who is a widely recognized opinion
leader in radiology, and a partner in
the project from the beginning.
Several additional workshops were
realized which allowed to accurately
determine the mechanical functions
and necessary degrees of freedom for
the design. As demonstrated in this
example it is not necessary to build
sophisticated prototypes to verify
specific feasibility aspects.
We can use any kind of simple
material such as wood or cardboard
to assess even complex questions.
A second important point I would
like to emphasize is that it is
generally not advisable to wait
until we have a complete prototype
before showing it to our
stakeholders.
Building rough-and-ready prototypes
in order to test only the specific
aspects for which we have doubts
is a great way to remove unknowns.
Yet another nice way to test our
ideas is to make drawings.
Here the team wanted to explore
ideas related to the configuration
of the whole X-ray system including
the patient bed, and the lead screen
behind which the radiographer
will be operating the device.
These drawings brought about many
discussions with many stakeholders.
Here's finally a more advanced
prototype of the X-ray system.
Note that the industrial design
aspects have not been integrated yet
and that this is not a final product
for which much more work needs to
be done. However, this prototype has
allowed to conduct many tests
including realizing real X-ray
images of a human hand.
Of course, the human hand was a
skeleton hand incapsulated in resin,
which allows to mimic a real hand.
It would not have been ethically or
legally acceptable to make tests on
real humans before all the regulatory
approvals are obtained. In these
slides we have only discussed
technical feasibility. And yet we
know that the business model is also
extremely important. Let us look
into this.
The fundamental question we need
to answer at this stage is
the following. Is our value
proposition attractive to potential
buyers? As we have seen, the buyers
and the beneficiaries may be two
different groups.
We need to make sure that our value
proposition is both attractive
and that it allows to fulfill the
unmet need.
We need to go out and test our value
proposition with the very people
who will pay for it and those who
will benefit from it.
This process is extremely important.
And will more often than not lead
to adjustments and modification
to our value proposition.
In practice, this may involve
presenting a prototype to a group of
potential buyers. And carefully
recording their reactions.
In marketing this is called a
focus group.
Selecting the right sample of
participants can be quite difficult
as one has to be careful not to
introduce biases such as involving
someone from the design team who
would skew the discussions.
Focus groups can be very useful.
For example, to test pricing
hypotheses. One can even evaluate
the price sensitivity of the buyer
which is very important for our
economic viability.
Of course, there are many other ways
to collect quantitative and
qualitative user feedbacks.
Such as using well-designed surveys.
Whatever the method, what counts is
to carefully plan how the value
proposition will be tested and later
to honestly analyze the results.
The trap here is not to fall in love
with your solution, but to really
listen to what people say even
if that means making important
changes.
Finally, depending on the technology
it would be absolutely great to
have written preorders. Not only
does this prove that the technology
is attractive and that the pricing
is right, but it will also allow you
to demonstrate that you have
identified a potentially highly
interesting business opportunity.
This is absolutely invaluable when
you will want to convince investors
to finance your project at a later
stage.
If you're a really good sales person
you may even try to obtain a
downpayment which may help you
finance your development and
deployment. This is typically what
you're trying to achieve with
crowdsourcing websites.
Another subject that must be
carefully tested during the
feasibility phase is our product
value chain.
In particular, we need to test what
are the conditions under which our
partners will supply a component
or provide a service.
Typically this is done by requesting
written offers from our partners.
These offers will allow us to
decide if it is more favorable to
purchase the component or service,
or if it is better to provide it
ourselves. This is very important
as we need to consolidate our cost
targets and to estimate the
profitability of the company.
Finally, once we have confirmed our
strategy, we need to go back to the
sustainable business model canvas.
And balance our triple bottom line.
Remember as a principle, all 3
bottom lines should be neutral
at the very least. Our initiative is
ethically questionable if the social
benefit is lower than the social
cost. Or if to get a social impact
you're destroying the environment.
It is assuredly bound to fail if the
revenue streams do not allow you to
cover the costs. At this stage it is
also very important that we think
global. This is, of course,
not simple.
Indeed, as we get better and better
at understanding our pilot context,
there is a risk that our product and
strategy won't be applicable
elsewhere. As we have said in the
past videos, we should think about
how our technology could be made
available wherever it is needed,
which could be all of low and
middle-income countries.
In the feasibility phase it is thus
very important that we benchmark
against other contexts.
For example, how attractive would
our concept of X-ray machine be
in Asia or South America?
In order to do that, we can contact
local NGOs or local universities
and engineering schools to help us.
It would be a pity if failing to
introduce a small change at this
stage would hinder a large fraction
of the world's poor from getting
access to our technology.
Our three tools, the impact canvas,
the product value chain, and
the sustainable business model
canvas can be a convenient way
to communicate our strategy to
stakeholders in other contexts.
At this stage we also need to update
our impact metrics based on the
impact canvas.
An important aspect that we did not
discuss up to now is the
communication strategy.
By the time we have a reasonably
clear concept and strategy, it will
become very important to spread the
word.
Here you can see the two project
managers presenting the X-ray
prototype in a public show.
There are many channels you can use.
Such as the internet, social media,
radio, TV, etc.
Short video pictures are great
communication tools which can
basically be made with very little
resources.
Be careful though, that this won't
interfere with your patent strategy
as we have explained in a previous
video.
Raising public awareness of the
problem you are trying to solve
can allow you to attract crucial
partners and potentially also
investors or other organizations
who could be ready to support you
financially. The issue of raising
adequate funding for your project
is always a problem.
However, multiple funding sources
exist.
Ranging from crowdsourcing to
international organizations, or
foundations. If universities or
engineering schools are involved
you may be able to convince them
to apply for a research grant
in collaboration with you.
Fundraising can be really
frustrating at times.
But that is also where you can
demonstrate how strongly you believe
in your idea. You need to hang-in
there and find creative ways to
convince funders to support you.
Having a good communication
strategy will almost always turn out
to be helpful in these regards.
As a summary, here are the main
deliverables which must be available
at the end of the feasibility phase.
First, a detailed and validated
product specification.
Then data demonstrating that
the technology is feasible
according to the specifications.
A finalized prototype which
incorporates all potential changes
made in this phase.
And a receipt of your patent
application if that is applicable.
Finally, a complete business plan
describing your project and
business model. This document
doesn't need to be many pages.
It should be quite easy to write
based on your reflections in this
phase. Simply start by summarizing
the content of your 3 tools.
The impact canvas, the product
value chain canvas, and the
sustainable business model canvas.
However, our advice is: don't lose
too much time on this document.
Make it crisp and attractive.
It will be useful for
the next phase.
Goodbye.