Now you've reached the point where
you've completed your developments
and must now launch a product.
You must now find a mechanism
to deploy your innovation
which is effective
as much as possible.
How do you go about that?
Well that's
the million dollar question.
Or rather shall I say,
the billion dollar question.
Remember, poverty affects well
over 2 billion people.
Therefore, you have to keep in mind
that whatever innovation you develop
has to have the ambition
and capacity
to reach millions
of the affected people,
if you wish to achieve any
appreciable impact.
Now this lecture is not intended
to be a comprehensive tutorial
on how to carry out this process;
That's beyond our scope
with the timeframe we have.
What we wish to do, instead,
is to orient you and equip you
with the right mindset
on what to consider when planning
for this stage.
Let's first look at the notion
of life-cycle
of technology adoption.
Rogers attempted to describe this
via a theory termed,
"The Diffusion of Innovations."
Diffusion of Innovations is a theory
that seeks to explain how,
why and at what rate new ideas
and technology spread?
This theory was popularized
by Prof. Everett Rogers in his book
that was first published in 1962,
and is now in its fifth edition
and beyond.
The process of adoption over time
is typically illustrated
as a classical,
normal distribution
or "bell curve".
The model indicates that
the first group of people to use
a new product are called Innovators,
which you see on the left.
Followed by Early Adopters.
Next come the Early Majority,
and Late Majority,
and the last group to eventually
adopt a product are called Laggards.
Unfortunately, in reality,
the majority of innovations
never make it past
the early adopters stage!
So what can you possibly do
to enhance the chances of success
beyond this stage
for your innovation?
There are various strategies
and concepts being proposed,
but we will discuss two main
compelling and enduring
schools of thought.
As we said before,
at this stage,
you have developed the proof
of concept for your innovation.
And you now wish to deploy
a product in the market.
This is generally a very tricky step
for technologists and scientists,
because typically
technology innovations
can seemingly have endless
interesting features
or applications in principle.
But in reality, probably only 20%
of those features
or potential applications
really matter in the market.
So what that means
is that rather than
spending your time and resources
over-engineering your product
with unnecessary features,
you should rather focus
on the features that really matter.
That is the philosophy underlining
the increasingly popular approach
in technology innovations,
especially.
This is the Principle
of Lean Innovation.
Lean innovation embraces
a philosophy of not letting
perfection get
in the way of progress,
as Tom Agan puts it.
Lean innovation contrasts
conventional approaches
to product development,
where R&D teams
expend enormous effort
trying to create a perfected
multi-featured product
over an extended period,
without any sufficient actual
market customer or feedback.
The resulting products are often
too expensive, too complicated,
too different
from what customers want,
and worst of all,
too late to market.
When thinking about lean innovation,
it is perhaps useful
to take into consideration
something I just alluded to.
The Pareto principle.
Which states that,
20% of the invested inputs
are responsible for 80%
of the results obtained.
This is also referred to
as the 80:20 rule.
What does that mean
for your product?
It means that potentially
20% of the product's features
may most likely deliver 80%
of the benefits sought by customers.
So your first crucial challenge
is to spend time identifying
which 20% of your product's features
can fulfill this criterion?
Once you have done that
you will have defined
what could be termed
the Minimum Viable Product,
and we'll call it MVP, for short.
We now look at the concept
of the Minimum Viable Product
in a more holistic perspective.
Essentially, what you have
had until now
is rather an idea or hypothesis.
Which is in fact based
on the analysis you carried out
with the Product Value Chain
and Sustainable Business
Model Canvas early on.
So a minimum viable product
is actually that version
of your new product that you utilize
in the process of collecting
a maximum of information
about your hypothesis,
but using a minimum of resources.
The process itself is actually
a build, measure and learn,
feedback loop.
The build part of the feedback loop,
involves a process
of building a product
with only the core features
or minimum feature set.
For example, you can do this
by first listing and ranking
all the features that you really
believe your product should have.
And then simply apply
the Pareto rule,
and select the top 20 percentile
of that list,
to become the minimum feature set
of your minimum viable product.
You then have to identify
a sub-segment of your market,
the visionaries or early adopters,
that you will sell
your minimum viable products to.
And that information
may or should be obtainable
from the analysis
that you carried out
with your sustainable business
model canvas tool before.
And this sub-segment could include
some of the stakeholders
and key opinion leaders
who actually helped you define
your product, for example.
And when selling
the product to them,
you may still want
to make them aware
of all the other features
your product may have later on.
Therefore, you'd be doing
what one of the well-known
proponents of lean innovations,
Steve Blank, calls
"Perfection by Subtraction".
You'd be selling the vision
and delivering
the minimum feature set
to visionaries and not everyone.
An important point
to remember in our case
is that we are also after impact.
So you also need to ask yourself,
are the features
of your minimum viable product
also relevant and core to your
impact objectives?
However, based on the manner
you defined your Product Specs
when applying the sustainable
business model canvas tool,
there is a high likelihood that your
minimum viable product
will also match your impact
objectives anyway.
The next phase is the Measure phase,
whose aim is to validate
that our product development
activities thus far
are indeed inline
with our hypothesis
of what we believe
the target customer group wants.
And the other task you have,
includes measuring your indicators
from your impact framework,
in order to verify
if, indeed,
you're obtaining the results
you hypothesized.
And here,
there are various feedback points
we can receive or learn from.
Which brings us to the important
or critical phase of Learning.
Remember,
bringing in a new innovation
to the market
is actually an experiment.
Albeit a marketplace experiment,
rather than a laboratory one.
So, learning from the first phase
of your experiments
provides you the necessary knowledge
that brings you closer
to your ultimate hypothesis.
Or in this case, the final product.
So one of the key questions here,
is to really determine
even with this subset
customer segment
that somebody actually wants
what we are building.
As well as what other features
should be added.
How product development
should continue?
And if it turns out
that no one wants this,
then no amount of continued
and over-engineering down this path
will help.
And this is a very important
point to learn.
And in that case, we should pivot.
In other words, abandon this path,
and take a different direction.
Without expending
generally scarce resources.
And as was mentioned earlier on,
rather fail them early,
and fail them cheap!
Therefore,
by applying the necessary iterations
of the build, measure & learn feedback loop
on your minimum viable product,
you should eventually
optimize and refine
your final product offering,
as well as fine-tune
your impact framework
or impact value chain,
if necessary.
Now you have finally defined
your best products.
And you have actually managed
to get some sales traction
with a handful, or even hundreds
of customers.
So, if we look
at the technology adoption curve,
you have what we call,
early adopters,
which are indicated in red
on the curve on the screen.
But remember, as we said earlier,
most innovation products
never make it past this stage
of early adopters.
Why?
Well, it turns out that in practice
it is so much harder penetrating
the next market segment
of the early majority.
Primarily because early adopters
and early majority
have two vastly different
commercial mindsets.
It is not a smooth
and seamless transition.
as the technology adoption curve
I showed you earlier
from Rogers' theory might suggest.
Instead, there is what
Jeffrey Moore has famously coined,
as a "Chasm".
A chasm between early adopters
and the early majority.
In his book, "Crossing the Chasm",
Moore says that,
the early majority are pragmatists,
share some of the early adopters'
ability to relate to technology,
but they are driven
by a strong sense of practicality.
They want to see
well-established references
before investing substantially.
But because there are so many people
in this segment,
roughly one third
of the whole adoption life-cycle,
winning their business is key
to any substantial growth, though.
So this is because
this early majority of pragmatists
care about the company
they are buying from,
the quality of the product
they are buying,
the infrastructure
of supporting products
and system interfaces,
and the reliability of the service
they are going to get.
So the sales-pitch that made you
successful with the innovators,
and early adopters,
will not necessarily work
with the pragmatists
or early majority.
Now to cross this chasm,
Moore proposes a whole methodology.
But we will not cover it
in detail here,
but rather encourage you
to read the book,
which is referenced at the end.
The message I essentially
wanted to convey
is that there are two
very distinct phases
in launching and adoption
of a technology innovation.
And that the methods needed
to succeed in the second phase
tend to be considerably different
from the ones required
in the first adoption phase.
So in other words,
the fact that you succeeded
in the first phase
with the so-called early adopters,
does not necessarily guarantee
you success in the mass market
of early majority.
Now to summarize,
you might ask yourself the question,
Why these two concepts specifically,
namely, lean innovation
and crossing the chasm?
In fact, you will see that,
if you have noticed already
that these two concepts
are actually complimentary.
In lean innovation,
you identify and build
your minimum viable product.
And then learn intuitively
from its deployment in the market,
on how to make the best product.
One of the key secrets of success
of lean innovation
is actually embracing learning.
As it has been shown
that learning has, by far,
the single greatest impact
on revenue from new products.
Its focus is in the most
important product attributes.
And the rapid cycling,
via trial and error,
helps to accumulate
critical knowledge quickly,
and ideally, in the real life,
competitive environment.
In other words,
lean innovation is not necessarily
a better innovation process,
rather it is a more efficient
learning process.
Whereas in crossing the chasm,
once you have defined and validated
your best product,
you assemble a strategy
for its full rollout,
which should see it reach
hundreds of thousands,
and millions of clients.
If you think of this
as a game of darts
you can think of lean innovation
as enabling
the efficient implementation
of the early adoption phase.
Or having to point
the small missile correctly.
While crossing the chasm methods
enables success
with the early majority.
Or give inertia and direction
to your small missile,
to get to the Bull's Eye!
Goodbye.