Welcome to the course on Principles of
Reactive Programming.
One year ago, when I finished the course
on function programming,
many people asked me for a second course
on more advanced material.
At the time I was too flat out exhausted
to consider anything of the kind.
But now, one year later, there is a second
course.
But the topic is reactive programming.
So, why this topic?
Three reasons really.
The first is that
reactive programming is becoming
ubiquitous.
Nowadays if you write any web service or
mobile app, or really any
large system with a real-time component,
then
knowing the reactive programming
techniques is essential.
The second reason is that reactive
programming really builds on functional
programming.
In fact we will spend the first two weeks
of this course with some of the more
advanced concepts
of functional programming, which then will
lead naturally
into the reactive programming content of
the course.
Third, I'm really happy that I could draw
on the help and
expertise of two of the masters of the
field, namely Eric Meyer,
who's the inventor of RX, the reactive
extensions framework, and Roland Kuhn
who's the lead of the Akka library for
actors concurrency, who will both
teach the, co-teach the course with me.
So, let's get started.
Reactive programming describes a set of
programming patterns and
techniques that have become increasingly
important over the last years.
And the reason for that is mostly driven
by change in requirements.
Ten years ago, a typical large
installations would have tens of servers.
[INAUDIBLE]
response times would be measured in
seconds.
There would be maintenance downtimes, a
couple hours per month, say.
And data volume would be measured in
gigabites.
Nowadays, a large server installation or
cloud installation would have thousands of
nodes.
Users expect sub-second response times,
response times in milliseconds.
There should be no maintenance down time,
system should be available 24 seven and
our data volume
has easily reached a terabyte and is going
into the petabytes.
So these new requirements also need new
architectures.
The classical architectures is optimized
by
something like the Java Enterprise
architecture.
It consists of managed servers and
application containers.
What you see now is more and more a shift
towards so called reactive applications
that are event driven, and that makes them
also scalable, resilient, and responsive.
The Merriam Webster diction defines
reactive as being readily
responsive to a stimulus.
What we mean by that in the world of
software systems is a system that can
react to events, so it's event-driven.
And the system should also be able to
react
to changing amounts of loads, system load,
that means
it should be scalable.
Furthermore, such a system should be able
to
react to failures and we call that
resilient.
And finally, and probably most
importantly,
the system should react to its users.
It should be responsive.
Now, being event driven is a technical
property that enables the properties of
being scalable, and being resilient.
And all three properties
together enable systems that are
responsive to the users.
So let's start with event-driven.
Traditionally, concurrent software systems
were composed of multiple threads,
communicating with shared and synchronized
state.
That let to a very high degree of
coupling, and also such systems were hard
to compose.
Event-driven systems, by contrast, are
composed from loosely coupled event
handlers.
Events in such a system can be handled
asynchronously.
They do not incur any blocking.
And because there's no blocking, that
means that typically resources
can be utilized much more efficiently.
The next property of a reactive system is
being scalable.
An application is scalable if it's able to
be expanded according to it's usage.
And typically we distinguish two
directions of scaling.
They scale up which means they make use of
parallelism
in multi-core systems, which become more
and more common in computers
today, and then their scaling out, which
means we make use of multiple server nodes
of an, in a data center, or in the cloud.
Important for
scalability here is always to minimize
shared multiple state.
Because we will see that that actually has
implications
on the ease and the, the efficiency of
scaling.
Important furthermore for scaling out, is
the property
of location transparency.
What that means is that it shouldn't
matter where a location is located.
It could be at the same computer as a
client, or, at some other computer across
the internet.
The functionality should always stay the
same.
The other important property for scaling
out is resilience, because
once you have multiple nodes, some of
these can fail.
And the system has to cope with that.
The third property of reactive system is
resiliency, an
application is resilient if it can recover
quickly from failures.
Such failures could be software failures
such as throwing an exception, or hardware
failures, a computer going down, or maybe
connection failures, an internet
connection going down.
Typically, resilience cannot be added as
an afterthought, it needs to
be a part of the system design from the
beginning.
Important techniques for constructing
resilient systems
are, keeping your components loosely
coupled.
Having a strong encapsulation of mutable
state.
And having pervasive supervisor
hierarchies.
Finally, an application is responsive if
it provides a rich,
real time interaction with its users even
under load, and
in the presence of failures.
Response of applications can be built on
an event driven, scalable, and resilient
architecture.
That doesn't automatically lead to a
responsive application.
You still need to pay careful attention to
algorithms,
system designs, including back pressure,
and many other details.
But being event-driven, scalable, and
resilient are important
some would argue, even necessary building
blocks to
arrive at a responsive application.
Now let's take a closer look at events and
event handling.
Of course event handling is not new.
It's traditionally being done using
call-backs.
A common form of call-backs is found in
Java.
In the subject observer pattern.
So you see an example here.
we can define a class counter that extends
a class called action
listener, which is part of the Java screen
framework, and then what the
counter would do, it would register itself
with an event source.
In this case, the event source is
a button, so we would set, say
addActionListener(this).
That would register the counter, itself,
at the event source.
Then the event source would call, whenever
there's a new event, this method action
performed.
So that's a callback.
You register yourself to be called back
here.
And when the callback
comes, there's an event that, gets
triggered
which gives you details about the event.
And then, every time that gets triggered.
You perform an action like increment the
counter by one.
Now, this is the common model that I guess
most of you have already seen today.
But it's also a model that has quite a few
problems.
So the first problem is already apparent
in the type of this actionPerformed
method,
its return type is Unit.
So that means to have any effect at all,
the actionPerformed method has to
have a side effect, in this case the side
effect is on the variable count.
So a design using listeners and callbacks
naturally leads to shared mutable state.
The second problem is that it's very hard
to construct higher abstractions out of
simple listeners.
So event handlers have a hard time being
composed.
And, in summary, all this leads quickly to
what has been called call back hell.
So that means applications that
essentially consist
of a big web of call backs that are very,
very hard to track and understand.
So how can we do better?
So the idea that is promoted in this
course is to use fundamental
constructions from functional programming
to get composable event abstractions.
In particular, some of the core principles
of
this course is that events should be first
class.
They are often represented as messages.
Handlers of events should also be first
class so that
complex handlers can be composed from
primitive ones.
So here are the topics that we are going
to cover in the next seven weeks of this
course.
We're going to start this week with a
review of functional programming, about to
the degree that
you have already seen it in the first
course
of prin-, on principles of functional
programming in scalar.
But we are also going to introduce some
new topics.
In particular, we are going to cover
an important class of functional patterns
called monads.
However, reactive systems are not
typically described
as pure functional programs, so next week
we are going to open up the paradigm of
pure functional programming and combine it
with the more typical world where we have
mutable states and non-deterministic
computations, including events After these
two more
preparatory sessions, we apply what we
know to reactive abstractions.
We first cover how to abstract over events
that will lead us to futures.
Then, how to abstract over event streams
that will lead us to so-called
observables.
We will then look at message passing
architectures, where the nodes are actors.
We will look at how to handle failures.
Including the concept of supervisors, and
finally we
will look at scaling out, to distributed
systems
looking at distributed actors.
The course is given by three lecturers, I
will cover the first two weeks.
Eric Meier will will cover futures and
observeables.
That's week three and four.
And finally Roland Call will cover actors,
supervisors and distributed actors
[SOUND].
As prerequisites, you should have a solid
grounding in functional programming.
Ideally, you've followed the principles of
functional programming in Scala class on
Coursera.
But if you know some other functional
language, the switch should be rather
easy.