In this unit we are going to do a quick
recap on functions and pattern matching.
Most of this you've already seen if you
followed the course on functional
programming in Scala.
But there are also some new additions,
in particular, the notion of partial
functions.
So to get started lets look at a possible
domain that we
can express with functions and pattern
matching and that domain is JSON, the
Java Script Object Notation.
So if you don't know what JSON is then I
guess it's best
understood by looking at this example
which
I have lifted straight out of Wikipedia.
a JSON structure is a recursive data
structure consisting of fields of
primitive types.
For instance, here, we have a field named
John, the type is string.
Here, you have another string called
Smith.
values can also be structured objects.
For instance, the address object consists
of three fields called streetAddress,
state, postalCode which are two strings
here, and the number there.
And they can also be sequences, sequences
are written in brackets.
So here you would have a sequence of two
phone numbers, whereas objects are written
in curly brackets.
So this object here has three
bindings, three fields, and the outer
objects that you see
here then would have, four
fields, firstName, lastName, address, and
phoneNumbers.
So that, in a Nutshell, is what JSON is,
and it's
a fairly popular interchange format,
between JavaScript and also other
technologies.
How would we represent JSON data in Scala?
The most straightforward way, I guess, is
to just have
a sequence of case classes that capture
the different cases of a JSON object.
So we would start with an abstract class
JSON, you could also use a trait for that.
And then there would be cases, one case
for each kind
of data in JSON, which will give you six
cases total.
The first case here is JSeq, representing
sequences of JSON objects.
The sequence is captured in
this list of JSON elements here called
elems.
The second case would be a J object, a
JSON object that would contain the
bindings which are a map from strings,
those are the field names, to JSON
objects.
finally there would be the primitive types
JNum which
captures a number, which is a double in
Scala.
Jstring, which captures a string.
JBoolean, which captures a Boolean.
And finally, JNull, which represents the
null value.
So these sequence of case classes would
represent JSON data completely.
Now here's an example how you can
construct
the JSON object that you've seen before,
in Scala.
It's exactly the same object that you've
seen on the first slide, here.
But now using Scala's internal
representation, using case classes,
rather than the external one using this,
this text representation.
So the JSON data would be a Jobject, which
has, is a map containing the
bindings for firstName, lastName, address,
and phoneNumbers.
FirstName, lastNames are strings, so
Jstring John, Jstring Smith.
The address is again a Jobject with
another map.
the postal code here would be a JNum, a
number.
The state and street address would again,
be strings.
Phone number is a sequence that contains
as elements in a list.
A object which maps type to home, a number
to this string.
And the second object put map type to the
string fax and number to that string here.
So that's how you could represent JSON
objects.
To be sure they're tricks how one could
dress
this up further and make the construction
of JSON
objects even shorter in Scala, but this is
what you get for a
completely straightforward representation
in case classes, and
overall it's quite legible, I would argue.
So let's now do something with this data
structure.
The most obvious way is to print the data
or rather to represent
them as a string, in more or less the way
you have seen before.
So what I want to do now, is I want to go
from this object here
and get the string representation for this
object that you've seen here.
Without the new lines, so without any
formatting I would just write the things
with comas one after the other ,but
otherwise I
want to see elements just as they are
given here.
How would we do that?
Well here's the method that does that.
It's as you would guess a recursive
function, call
it show, which takes the JSON object,
gives you
back a String, and it would work by
pattern
matching over the kind of JSON objects,
pretty obvious.
So you would start with JSON match.
Your pattern matching functions in Scala,
then you would just go case by case.
The first case you would say, well, if
it's the sequence of elements or the
pattern would say, well the elements in
the sequence are now in this variable
elements.
Then what do you do?
You print a open bracket, then you show
recursively
all the elements and you concatenate in a
string
using the make String function with commas
between
them, and you close with a closing
bracket.
I skip object for the time being because
it's that's, it's the most complicated.
So the other four cases are all rather
simple.
JNum, if you have a number then, well you
just turn
the number into a string using Java and
Scala's toString function.
If it's a string, JString string, then you
print the string
between quotes, If it's a boolean, you
turn the boolean to a string.
And if it's a null, you return the string
null.
So the last case we have to look at is the
case of, JSON objects.
So if you have a JSON object with some
bindings, which are a map in Scala.
Then what do you do?
Well you have to traverse the map.
That's done here, we define a value called
assocs, for
associations.
And you define it like this.
You go through the map bindings, so for
each
binding that you find, what does the
binding look like?
Well, it will be a pair from a key to a
value.
And you can do that by just having another
pattern match here directly on the map
function that says well, apply this
function that
takes a key and a value and returns
the key in quotes, a colon, and the value
subjected
to the show function.
So that would give you a list of strings
that each contain the key, a colon, and
the string of a value.
And then finally you take that list, you
concatenate all the
elements using commas, and you put it
inside braces, and you're done.
So this was just an example to get warm.
Again, with function programming in Scala,
you've
seen the basics of pattern matching,
recursive
functions, and some of the combinators
that
are very important in Scala are just map.
What I want to do now is look at some
aspects of this code in more detail.
The first thing I want to look at is this
function here.
So you have a case
expression in curly braces.
And that's a function that gets passed
directly to this map combinator.
So the question then is what is the type
of this function?
So simplifying slightly, what is the type
of this expression where we have a pattern
match on key and value and return the
concatenation of key, a colon, and value.
If you would try that out you would find
that this Scala compiler flags this as an
error.
It would say that an anonymous function
lacks an expected type for the parameters.
So to correct that you would have to give
this function a type from the outside.
So if we plug this function into the
function
map that you've seen before here, that's
where it appears,
then you will find that map expects a type
like this.
What it wants is a function type from or I
call JBinding to string
and the JBinding type I've abbreviated it
here just to make
it cleaner is an alias for pair of string
in JSON.
So those are the bindings in a JSON map
for an object.
The keys are strings,
the values are JSON objects and the whole
function here would
then need to have a type that takes one of
these bindings and returns a string.
So as you know in Scala every concrete
type is a type of some class or trait.
And the function type is no exception
there.
A type like JBinding arrow string is in
fact
just a shorthand for Scala Function1 of
JBinding and String.
So if we look at that then we see that
Scala Function1 is a
trait defined in the standard library, and
JBinding and String are its type
arguments.
So we write type arguments with brackets
here rather than angular brackets that you
would see in Java or C# or C++.
So let's look at the Function1 trait
in more detail.
Here's what you would see in the standard
library.
Function1 is a trait with two type
parameters, call
them A and R, and a function which is
abstract here called apply, which takes an
argument of
type A and gives you a result of type R.
The function type parameters have these
minus and plus in front of them.
They indicate
the variance of a type parameter, so they
tell you how
the type is a whole behaves with
sub-typing when you'll change the
type argument of the re-, result, let's
say you make it
a super type, and the whole function type
becomes a super type.
Whereas for the type argument, it goes in
the other way.
That has been
[INAUDIBLE]
explained in detail in week 4 of the
functional programming course.
It's not essential to get an understanding
of the following,
so, and we gloss over that a little bit
here.
Now, let's look at the pattern matching
block that we've seen before.
what would that expand to?
So if the type is Function1, what would
the actual value be?
Well the actual value would be a
new instance of Function1 with the type
parameter
[INAUDIBLE]
that we have seen before, and what we need
to do is
we need to give a definition of the
abstract apply function here.
So here it is.
So our apply function would take a
JBinding parameter and it would do the
pattern match that we've seen here in the
block, on the argument here.
So we would write x match and then comes
the pattern matching block.
So that completes the
function definition and now you've seen
how case blocks
as a whole can expand two functions, one
instances.
Now one nice aspect of functions being
traits in
Scala is that we can sub-class the
function type.
A good instance for that is lets say the
trait Map which
is have you, you have seen before, it
takes keys to values.
You can see that actually as an
extention, as a specialization of
functions from keys to values.
Scala maps are functions, so you can apply
them to a key and get the value directly.
So another example are sequences, which
are treated
as functions from indices of type Int to
values.
So sequences would be described by a trait
in this color standard library called Seq,
parameterised
with an element, type Elem, and that trait
would extend to function type Int arrow
Elem.
Well actually you would need a pair
of parentheses to make this syntactically
correct.
That's also why we can write elems of i,
so the index in parentheses
to refer to the ith element of the
sequences elems.
So, sequence indexing is written the same
way as function application because
sequences are functions.
And because arrays in Scala are treated as
sequences
by means of an implicit wrapper, the same
syntax
would work for array indexing.
Compare to Java, where you would have
written elems of i in brackets.
For array indexing in Java, you would do
that because, of course, arrays are
not functions whereas in Scala, through
the implicit sequence wrapper, they are.
So we have seen that a pattern matching
block like this one here case ping to pong
can be given type String to String.
Let's try this out directly in practice.
So what I do is I go in the Eclipse
[INAUDIBLE]
Scala IDE.
I create a new worksheet.
Call it test.
[UNKNOWN]
I want to play with that.
So we have, say, first, the pattern
matching expression, case ping to pong.
Would that type check?
No, it wouldn't.
The compiler would say there's a missing
parameter for an expanded function.
so you need to give it a type from the
outside, let's do that.
Let's say val f
[NOISE].
I guess you would agree that a good type
is String to String, equals case ping to
pong.
Yeah, that worked fine.
And now we can write something like f of
ping, and we would get pong as expected,
but what would happen if we apply this
function to another string, call it abc?
Well we would get a match error that
indicates that the pattern match that we
have done here, lacks the case abc, so we
haven't defined a case
for that and the resultant in Scala is an
exception called match error.
Now it would be nice to find out
beforehand given a
function f whether the function is
applicable to a certain argument.
And unfortunately with the function type
itself we can't do that.
But it turns out that there's another way
in Scala to achieve
that which we are going to see next.
So here it is.
we can give the expression ping to
pong, then type PartialFunction from
String to String.
So PartialFunction is another sub-type of
function it's a special type.
What it does, is like function, you can
apply
it to an argument, but you can also query
whether
the function is defined for a given
argument.
And this is done with the isDefinedAt
method.
So you can write, f is defined at ping,
and that would give you true,
or f is defined at another string like
pong, and that would give you false.
Let's test that in the worksheet.
So what I do now is that instead
of string, I write PartialFunction of
String and String
[NOISE].
And then instead of this thing here, I
write f is the find at.
And what it would give me that now f is
not
defined at a, abc, but would f be defined
at things a?
Yes, here the answer is true.
So let's have a look at the
definition of PartialFunction in the
standard Scala library.
So it's an extension of Function1 with the
same type arguments.
Like Function1, it has an apply method.
the, in fact, the apply method is
inherited from the Function1 trait.
The fact that we have written here, it is
redundant, it's just there for clarity.
And it has an additional method called
isDefinedAt, which maps an argument
x of type A to Boolean.
So if the expected type of a pattern
matching block is PartialFunction then the
Scala compiler will expand it differently.
It will create a PartialFunction object
now obviously, and it
now has to fill in two abstract methods,
apply and isDefineAt.
Apply gets translated just in the case of
a normal function,
the ping gets mapped to pong.
Whereas for isDefinedAt, the pattern
matching block would be like this.
If the argument is ping, then the result
is true.
For all other cases, the result is false.
So the Scala compiler would do that
systematically for
any pattern matching block if the result
type is PartialFunction.
So let's finish with an exercise.
Given this
function here, a PartialFunctions from
list of Ints to
Strings that is implemented by this
pattern matching block here.
So in the case of Nil I return one, in the
case of a list consisting of
x followed by y, followed some other
elements rest, I give back two.
What do you expect as the result of f dot
isDefinedAt list of 1, 2, 3?
True or false?
I guess the answer to that one is pretty
straightforward.
the second pattern here definitely does
match lists of three elements.
The first one will be x.
The second will be y, the rest of
the elements will be captured in this
variable, rest.
So the function definitely is defined on
the input data, and the result is true.
So let's look at a slight variation of
this exercise, and
now I have a function g which looks like
f, except that the second
pattern matches elements consisting of a
head and some arbitrary tail.
And then I have a nested pattern match
which
works for the rest being Nil, and no other
case.
So now what would you think?
Is g defined at the list 1, 2, 3?
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Actually, it turns out the answer is true,
g is defined on the list, because after
all, the second case of g, x rest matches
a list of three elements.
The first one is x, rest would be bound to
the list 2, 3 then.
Even though when you run this function g,
then of course, you would get a
match error, because what would happen
when
the function g is applied to this argument
that the second case here would apply,
then in the nested pattern match, the list
2, 3 would be matched against the single
case Nil, and that of course can't work.
That would give you a match error.
So what you see in this example is
that the isDefinedAt guarantee that
PartialFunction gives you.
Only applies to the outer most pattern
matching block.
It does, is not a guarantee that if
a function is defined at an argument that
this function definitely will not throw a
match
error when it is run, because the match
error could be thrown by, as you see here.
Nested pattern matches or it could of
course also be thrown by a
completely different function that gets
called from
this function in a chain of calls.