In this unit, we are going to do a recap
of Scala's collections.
You've already seen them at length if
you followed the previous course on
functional programming.
So, what we do now is just review some of
the core principles and highlights.
If you have seen the material before, then
you might
want to fast forward to parts of this
course now.
First, Scala has a, quite a rich hierarchy
of collection classes.
The base class is one of the base classes
is called iterable, and it gives
you collections you can iterate through.
And then there would be sub-categories.
there would be the sequences, the sets,
and the maps.
if you look at sequences, in turn, they
could
be indexed, which means you have fast
random access.
Or they could be linear, which means they
are optimized for sequential scan.
And then you would have concrete
implementations, a
standard one for indexed sequence would be
vector.
A standard one for linear sequence would
be
list; that's a list, you have already
seen.
And then there are also types that, in
a sense get imported into this hierarchy
from Java.
So there would be the Java arrays, which
are a kind of index sequence.
And the Scala strings, sorry, the Java
strings,
which are also a kind of indexed sequence.
I've drawn the line here dotted because
these
cannot be by their nature subtypes of
indexed sequence.
We can't really add new super types to a
Java class.
What we do instead is make them behave
like indexed sequences through the use of
implicit wrappers.
Similar to sequences, sets and maps would
also have several sub-categories and
several implementations.
Having so many collection types could be
confusing, except for the
fact that they all share a common set of
general methods.
So it's very easy to apply a usage
profile that you know from one collection
to another.
The methods that the collections share are
things
like picking the first element picking
some arbitrary element.
But in our case, more importantly, core
methods such
as map, flatMap, and filter, are shared by
all collections.
Other important methods would be the fold
operations,
foldLeft and foldRight, that map a binary
operations to,
on a collection and reduce it to a single
value.
Let's have a look at map, flatMap, and
filter in more detail.
What we are going to do is study how
they're implemented on the List class that
you've already seen.
Let's do map first.
So, idealized, map takes a function from
the
list element type T, to some arbitrary
type U.
So U is a type parameter of map.
And it would give you back a list of U.
And what it would do is it would do a
pattern match over the list itself.
If this list
is a cons cell consisting of a head
element x and a tail xs, then we would
apply f to the head, map f over the tail,
and compose the results with a cons.
If the li-, current list is Nil, then the
result list is also Nil.
So that was map.
If you want to learn about flatMap, the
easiest
way to do that is to study the differences
with respect to map.
So the first difference you see here, the
function we pass to flatMap now doesn't
return a single element, but a list
of elements of an arbitrary type U.
But it, again, returns a list of Us.
So its implementation is, again, a pattern
match.
the function f gets applied to the first
element head.
But since it's a list, now it gets
concatenated
with a recursive call to flatMap, rather
than just prepended with a, with a cons.
So instead of a cons here, a double colon,
you have the concatenation operation,
which is written plus plus.
And again for Nil, flatMap gives you back,
a Nil.
The last operation we're going to look at
is filter.
So filter takes a predicate that's a
function from the List element
type T to Boolean and gives you back a
list of T.
It keeps all the elements of the list that
satisfy the predicate.
The way it does that is again with a
pattern match.
If the list is not empty with a head x,
then if the predicate holds for x.
Then you get back x followed by filter on
the tail with a predicate.
Otherwise, you just filter on the tail,
and you drop the first element.
And in the case of Nil,
you get back Nil, as before.
In practice, the types and implementations
of these
methods are quite different in the Scala
collection library.
And that's for two reasons.
The first one is that in the
Scala collection library, map, filter and
flatMap
are not just defined for lists that
are defined for arbitrary collections and
iterables.
and that means that their types need to be
more general
than what you see here.
The second difference is that in the
implementations of map, flatMap
and filter for lists, we want these
methods to be tail-recursive.
If they weren't tail-recursive, then
applying them to lists over a certain
length, probably over a couple thousand
elements, would give you a stack overflow.
So to make map, flatMap, and filter work
even
for very, very long lists, we need a
tail-recursive implementation.
This one is not because you see for
instance here, the
call to filter is actually nested inside
the call to cons.
So we need to refactor this implementation
to give,
give us something that works in constant
stack space.
The second thing I want to cover which is
related to collections is for-expressions.
For-expressions are useful because they
give you a simpler notation for
something that comes down to combinations
of
these core methods; map, flatMap, and
filter.
Here's an example that you've seen already
in the first course on functional
programming.
It's a combination of flatMap, filter, and
map.
If you look at it for a sufficiently
long time, you probably figure out what it
does.
But why go through all the trouble if
there's a simpler notation like this one
here?
So this
one here, I would argue it's immediately
clear what it does.
You let i step to the integers between 1
and 10, j between 1 and i.
You ask whether the sum of i plus j
isPrime
and then you yield the pairs of i and j.
So you yield the pairs of all
those integers in these ranges whose sum
isPrime.
And it actually turns out that if you have
these for-expressions, then what the
compiler of Scala would do is give
you something that's equivalent to
precisely
this combination of map, filter, and
flatMap.
So the way this is done, we are going to
show next.
Here's how the Scala compiler translates
for-expressions in terms
of map, flatMap and a lazy variant of
filter.
There are three rules that apply
to the different shapes of the
for-expressions.
The first one applies to for-expressions
that consist of
a simple generator, written with a left
arrow here.
So, you have for x taken from some
expression e1, yield some expression e2.
And that's translated into a simple call
of map.
So it would be translated to e1.map, and
then you
have the closure that takes x as an
argument and
gives you back the expression e2.
The second rule applies to for-expressions
that follow the
initial generator with a filter, here
written if f.
And there could be also other fields that
I expressed as s that follow this in turn.
Such a for-expression is translated to
this one that you see here.
The idea is that the filter f would appear
as an argument x
arrow f of an anonymous function that
gets passed to withFilter of the first
expression.
So essentially what you do is, you take
the generator expression e1, and you
immediately prune down all the elements to
those that satisfy the filter f.
And then you continue with the rest of the
for-expressions.
You can think of withFilter as a lazy
variant of filter that does
not, allocate a, a new list consisting of
the elements that are kept by the filter.
But instead, passes on only those elements
to
any following cause to map, flatMap or
withFilter.
The third rule applies to for-expressions
that start with two generators in
sequence.
These for-expressions are translated to a
call of flatMap.
So the flatMap would apply to the first
generator here.
And it would contain in its result a
for-expression that
is essentially the all the rest of the
original for-expressions.
So it starts with the second generator,
then keeps the, any other elements
s and the result expression e3.
So you've seen that each of these rules
translates a for-expression
to a for-expression that has one fewer
elements between the parentheses.
First for-expression eliminates the single
generator, the
second one eliminates a filter element
here.
And the third one eliminates the leading
generator in the for-expression that is
nested here.
So if we apply these rules repeatedly, at
some point we
will be left without any generators or
filters in the list.
And that is then the final result of the
translation.
So one thing that we haven't seen yet is
that the left-hand side of
a generator in a for-expression can also
be a pattern, not just the simple
variable.
An example of that you see here, so it's a
query over JSON data.
we are given a list of JSON objects in
this data value.
And what we do now then is we step through
the data we match
on all JObjects that contain some
bindings.
So we would in that case, discard any
other JSON
values like sequences or strings that
appear on top level here.
We then look at the phone numbers
binding in bindings, that's a simple map
application.
We pattern match to say, well that should
be a JSequence of phones.
We go-, step through all the phones,
each one gives, gives us a phone.
the phone is itself an object.
We pick its number field, that should give
us a JString of digits.
And we demand whether the digits start
with the number 212.
And if that's the case, then we yield
bindings of first name and bindings of
last name.
So what this would do, in a nutshell,
would
give us the first and last names of all
persons
that have a telephone number that starts
with the area code 212.
Patterns in generators act as implicit
filters.
Essentially, what happens here when you
have a generator like this is then that
the match with JObject bindings gets added
as an implicit filter to these data.
We'll see how in the translation scheme.
So, we look
at a generator pat left arrow expression,
where pat is a pattern.
For simplicity's sake, we assume it has
only a single variable x in the pattern.
And that then would be translated to this
expression, here.
So, we take the generator expression,
expression run it through withFilter.
Here we say, keep only those elements that
match the pattern.
Otherwise return false and
so the elements would be dropped.
And then that result, in turn, gets mapped
with the function that
takes a pattern and returns x, the
variable that is in the pattern.
Here's an exercise.
According to the rules that you've seen
for
the translation for-expressions, what
would this expression translate to?
This one, or this one.
I guess the answer is quite easy to come
by.
one indication already is that, that
for-expression starts with two generators.
We have seen that, that should map into
something that starts with a flatMap.
So, that would rule out the second one.
And also, if we check all the other
details, then we see
that indeed this for-expression maps into
this combination of map, flatMap, and
withFilter.