In the last unit you've seen the concept
of a for expression.
What we are going to do now is use for
expressions
in another and interesting application,
namely, the generation of random values.
So far we have seen four expressions
operating on lists, on sets.
in the previous course we have also seen
them on databases and options.
All these things are collections of data
items in some sense.
So the question is are for expressions
good
only for collections and interestingly the
answer is no.
All that is required is some
interpretation of the map, flat map, and
with filter
functions that make sense for the type in
question.
There are many domains outside collections
that have such an interpretation, and an
example that we are going to see the now
are random value generators.
So what are random value generators?
You know about random numbers from a
language
like java, here you would in port java
util,
to random.
Create a new, random number generator,
take
the next random number of the nextInt.
My question now is, is there a systematic
way to get random values for other
domains?
For instance, we want random booleans,
random
strings, random pairs, lists, sets, or
trees.
So here's a way to do that.
We define a trait generator,
with some element type T, and that would
generate random values of type T.
Here's the outline of the trait, so it's
Generator here's the type
of values that get generated, and here's
the function; generate, that does that.
Let's look at some instances of this type.
The first instance generates random
integers.
So that will now be packaged as follows.
the integers generated
as a new random generator, of type int.
It defers to the Java integer, gen-,
generator, and its generator method just
picks off the next random number from
rand, the Java generate random number
generator.
What about Booleans?
Well, once we have a generator for
integers, Booleans is easy.
We create a new generator Boolean.
Its generator method just generates a
random number using the integers
generator and asks whether that random
number is greater than 0.
If it is, we return true.
If not, we return false.
What about pairs?
Well, here's a generator that gives you
pairs of integers.
Its generate method calls generate twice
on
the integers generator, and packs the
results
in a pair.
Now all this works, but it's also a bit
cumbersome.
Each time we have to setup a new anonymous
class
of type generator to find a generate
method and so on.
Question is, can we do it without all that
boilerplate?
Ideally what we would like to write is
something like this.
To get booleans which are, say for x taken
from the integers then generator,
yield x greater than zero.
Well for pairs we would like to say that,
let's have two generators of two arbitrary
types t and u, call them
lower case t and u, let x be taken from t,
y be taken from u.
Return the pair of x and y.
As you want to do that, then a good
question is, what does the compiler expand
this to?
Here's what it would do.
Booleans would be expanded to a call to
map, and
pairs would be expanded to a call to flat
map
followed by a call to map according to the
expansions
of for expressions that we have seen in
the last unit.
So you see that as long as we have map and
flat map defined
on the generator class we can actually
use the convenient syntax with four
expressions.
So let's see how we would define map and
flat map on the generator class.
Let's start with map.
So here's the type of map.
It takes a function from the random value
type T to a new random value type S.
Gives you a generator of S, and the way it
would do that,
it would generate random numbers of type T
using its own generate method.
Then apply
f to those random numbers and those give
you the random numbers on the S type.
There's a twist here in the call to
self.generate.
If we had written just generate,
that would be according to th Expansion
rules and scholar, this.generate.
But this is this new anonymous class would
refer to current method that we define
here.
So it would be a recursive call
to the generate method, which would not
terminate.
What we need instead is we want to call
the generate method of the object one
further out.
That's this generate method here.
And the way that we can achieve that is
that we define an alias for this
value of this object out here using the
syntax self error.
So that would define an alias name for
what,
for the this term of the class over here.
So writing then self generate would defer
to this method over here.
Another way that could be
achieved in both Java and also Scala would
be to
prefix the this with the name of the
class, so we could have written
generator.this.generate, and that would
have done the same thing.
So the second thing we have to do is
define flatmap on generators.
Here it is.
again it's useful to compare
with map, so flatmap would give us back
now a generator of S from the function F.
So it takes a random value to a whole
sequence of random values to a generator.
And its result type is, again, generator
of S.
Its generate method is implemented, as you
see here.
So, what we would do is: first, generate
a random vary of type T using self
generators
as before.
Apply the function F to it, so that it now
gives us a complete generator on the new
domains S.
And to pick a random value in that domain,
we invoke generate here again.
Now that we have defined the general
machinery that we needed
on class generator, we can look at some
specific generators again.
So booleans, here is our syntax list for.
what does that expand to?
Well, the compiler would expand it to our
map, and if you look
at the map operation and generator then
that's what it comes down to.
It would say while the function f, that's
this close
right here and you see it here gets
applied to
the generate method from the random number
generator on the
left-hand side of the map, the receiver of
the map.
And that of course can be simplified by
just doing the so-called beta reduction.
So we apply the function to the argument,
and we'd
use it in one step, to what you see here.
So that's exactly the Boolean, generator
for Booleans that we started with.
Let's try the same thing with pairs.
So here's the, already the expanded syntax
of the for expression for pairs.
if we expand the map then that's what we
get here.
If we expand the flat map we get this
expression
here so lets look at this in a bit more
detail.
We get a generator for pairs from t of t
and u.
Its generator method gives you the
generator here that does generation
of the pairs like that and then we call
generator again
on this method generator.
If we simplify that expression then we
get, again,
the expression we started with, a pair
where we
generate on the t and generate a value on
the u generator and collect the two in a
pair.
Let's have a look at some of the building
blocks for generators.
A useful, even though very simple building
block is the single generator
That is in the sense a borderline case, in
that
it always gives you back the same random
value T.
So the value is not that random after all.
So you get the value that you want
to return and generate each time returns
that value.
Another building block is that chose
generator that would give
you an integer in the interval between low
and high.
The way it would do that, it would take an
arbitrary
random value from the integers and would
normalize it to be in the
interval between low and high using this
modular expression here.
The last generator one of can pick an
arbitrary value from a list a choices.
So you can call it for instance like this,
one of three colors red blue you know,
would give you a random color that can be
red, blue or yellow.
OneOf takes a VARARG argument, T star,
which means that
you can give it as many choices as you
want.
And would, what it would do then is it
would choose an integer between zero and a
number
of choices that we have passed, and it
would,
you pick the choice, which is at this
index
in the list of choices that are passed by
t star.
So with these building blocks we can now
set out
to write random value generators for some
more structured types.
Let's start with lists.
How would you generate a random list?
Well one way to do it, is first to flip
a coin where the list should be empty or
not empty.
That's done with this generator here,
because with
the Booleans we record the result and it's
empty.
Then, if the coin gave us that the
list should be empty, we always return
the emptyList, otherwise we return a
nonEmptyList.
So how would we return always the
emptyList?
Well, that's just the generator single
that always returns a Nil.
How would we get a generator that
generates a nonEmptyList?
Well that's another for where we say now
for, getting a non-empty list of integers,
we have to pick a random integer, here
in the head and left arrow integers
generator.
And then, we have to follow that with a
random list.
So we have here a call, a recursive call
to the list generator.
The random value that comes out of that is
called tail.
And we, all that is left is that we need
to compose the head random integer with
the tail random list.
So, here's an exercise for you.
Can you implement a generator that creates
random Tree objects?
Such objects would be type, Tree.
and the Tree trait would have two case
classes, to cases.
a Tree could either be an Inner node
consisting of two sub-trees or it could be
a Leaf consisting of an integer.
So let's open a worksheet
to see how we would do this.
I've opened the worksheet generators which
contains the base,
some basic generators that need, the
integers and the booleans.
what we will do now is go bottom up, so
how to do a generator for leafs.
Well that's, that one is simple.
We just say, well, we need a random
number.
And for each random number that we get, we
produce a leaf with
that random number.
So that covered leafs.
How about inner nodes?
Here's a generator for an inner node.
What we do is we generate a random tree,
call it l.
Generate a random tree, call it r.
And produce a new inner node, call it l,
inner of l and r.
Now finally the trees generator.
This, you see here.
So, as in the
case of lists, we flip a coin whether we
want
a leaf or an in and out, that's done here.
If we want a leaf then we turn to the
leafs generator
to produce a random value, otherwise we
return to the inners generator.
Let's see how this would work in action.
So we take the trees generator and
generate a random value.
So what did we get here?
Well, we got a tree that
consists of two leaves, and an inner node,
and then they themselves are
the left tree of another, other inner node
with a leaf on the right.
That's just one possible random trees.
The next time I run this operation then of
course I would get a different node.
So this time the tree I got was, was much
smaller.
Let's try a third time.
Now, it was much bigger.
So you see, what you get is
really real random values in the tree
domain.
An important application of random value
generators is random testing.
So you know about tests, in particular,
unit tests.
They're the ideas.
You come up with inputs to a program
function, or a set of program functions.
And then you have an assertion or a post
condition
that should hold when these functions are
on, on the input.
So the post condition is a property of the
expected result.
And then you run the tests to verify that
the program satisfies the post condition.
But the point is, after all the tests
pass, hopefully, and you
only know that the program satisfies the
post-conditions on these test inputs.
There might be others where the program
still could fail.
So typically, you would need to be smart
about finding
a lot of good test inputs that exercise
the program in
all possible program paths.
So the question is can we do it without
all the hassle of finding all these test
inputs.
Can we do completely without the test
samples.
And the answer is yes in some cases at
least.
If we can simply generate random test
inputs.
So all the hard work of coming up with the
input
values we leave to the random number, to
the random value generator.
So here's an example of how we can do
that with the generators that we have
defined so far.
Here is a test function, it takes a
generator,
that it gives us input values in some
domain
T, and it takes the number of times we
want to run the test on different randomly
generated values.
And then it takes a test function that
returns
true, or false, or the idea is returns
true
if the test pass and false when it fails.
And would it would do then, is it would
for
I from zero to number of times, generate a
random
value and then assert that the test
function returns true,
and if not, we will give you this
assertion error.
If everything goes well, then it would
print
that we have passed the number of times
test.
So here's an use case of this test
function so we would apply it to
the generator that gives us pairs of
lists, and then the function would say,
well, given two randoms lists, xs, ys, two
arbitrary lists, xs and ys, is the length
of the concordination, always longer than
the length of the list xs itself.
Question to you, does that
property always hold?
Well, one way to answer this question is
to simply try it out.
We have all the random number generators.
We have the test function.
I have assembled them in another worksheet
where you see all the generators here,
and finally we have the test function that
you see here at the end.
let me just, run this test on pairs of
lists.
And the function would be that, given two
arbitrary lists,
xs and ys.
We want to postulate that the length of
the concatenation is greater than the
length of just xs.
[SOUND]
And what do we get?
Well, we get a counter example and
insertion error which says
the test failed for and here you have to
count example.
The first is a list consisting of a single
element, It's,
you see that's a random value that we have
on here.
the second list is empty and in that case,
of course, the length of these two
lists is one, and where it's the length of
xs is also one, so the two lengths
are equal and the assertion fails.
So the answer to this question here
is obviously, the property does not always
hold.
We have just found a counter-example.
Now the idea of these random tests and
random value generators is embodied
in a very useful tool that we can use for
your Scala programs.
The tool is called ScalaCheck, and it is
modeled to
a latch degree after a tool called
QuickCheck, which exists in the, for Haska
programs and variance of quick check have
been developed for quite a few other
languages.
Alan is one example and in the formal
scholar check.
Also for scala.
So the idea is just as you've seen quick
check would come up with random.
Value generators.
It's a bit smarter than what you have seen
in that it
can actually generate, sometimes the
random values if you just give it a type.
So it knows how to generate random values
for types that have a certain form
and then you would run tests similarly to
what you have seen with the test function.
Only in scholar check its called for all
so
you would just write for all and then you
would have the predicate that says well on
which
domains do you wish to run your test in
this
case two lists of ints.
And what property should hold, so that's a
property that you want to test here.
And the test works similarly to what
you've seen,
run a prescribed number of times, which
you can configure.
Scholar check is quite a bit smarter then
what we've seen also, in
the sense that if a test fails, it can
minimize the counter example.
We can take sample you saw was a
list with a rather large random number
that was
the first one it found that falsified the
the test.
Whereas what QuickCheck and ScalaCheck
would do in
this case is they would then try
repeatedly to
find smaller and smaller examples I'm told
the
example is something that is essentially a
local optimum.
So, it would, typically, such a small
example would be easier to understand as
a counterexample than just an arbitrary
random value.
If you want to find out more about
ScalaCheck, then there's a tutorial on the
course page.
And ScalaCheck will also be used in the
first
assignment that you are going to do in
this course.