In the final unit of this week, we'll
cover some of the general theory that
underlies
[INAUDIBLE]
what we have seen before.
We're going to study a very general class
of
design patterns that come up almost
everywhere in functional programming.
And also in reactive programming.
The theoretical foundation of this class
of design
patterns is important in the concept of a
Monad.
As we've seen data structures with map and
flatMap are quite common.
And in fact there's a name that describes
this class of
data structure together with some
algebraic laws that they should have.
These data structures are called monads.
A monad is a parametric type M with a
tight parameter T that has two operations,
flatMap and Unit.
And these operations
also need to satisfy some laws.
So you could, can see it in Scholar as a
trait, M.
Where M is the monad, T is the type
parameter.
It would have a flatMap method of the type
that you see here.
So, it takes an arbitrary type U as a
parameter, and a function that.
Maps at T to a monad of U and it gives it
back the same monad applied
to U.
And besides flatMap that would also be the
unit method.
That unit method takes an element of type
T
and gives you an instance of the monad of
T.
In the literature, flatMap is more
commonly called bind.
But in scholar, we have flatMap already as
the established name.
So I will continue to use that.
Here are some examples of monad.
List is a monad where unit is just the
single element constructor.
So, given an x, I return the list that
consists of just x.
Similarly, set is a monad where unit of x
is set of x.
Option is a monad where unit is some, so
unit of x would
be I have an element, and here it is.
And the random
value generators that we've seen in the
last unit, they're also a
monad where unit of x is the single
generator single of x.
As you've seen, flatMap was available as
an operation on each of
these types, where as the unit in scala is
different for each monad.
Quite often, it's just a name of the monad
type applied to an argument, but sometimes
it's different.
For instance, for generator,
we use single, for option, we use some.
So we've seen monads have the flatMap
operation.
What about map?
Well, in fact map can be defined for every
monad as a combination of
flatMap and unit.
So, the map applied to a monad with a
function f would be flatMap of.
First apply f to the argument x and then
reinject into the monad using unit.
Another way to write this expression would
be to use the m then combinator in scala
that you have for function composition.
So you could write m, m map f is m flatMap
of f andThen unit.
So you first apply the f function and then
you apply the unit function.
To the result of that.
Now in scalar we do not have a unit that
we can call
here because every monad has a different
expression that gives the unit value.
Therefore map is in scalar a primitive
function that is also defined on every
monad.
To qualify as a monad, a type has to
satisfy three laws that connect
flatMap and unit.
Associativity is, as usual, a law about
placing parentheses.
Here, the parentheses would be placed on
the left hand side.
And here, you see them placed on the right
hand side here.
So we can alternatively.
Either do the flatMap here first, or
combine the
two functions in the flatMap, and apply to
the monad.
Domain where associativity is a bit easier
to
express as if we go from monads to
monoides.
Monoids is a simpler
form of monads, it doesn't bind anything.
So for instance, integers
are a monoide, and they are associative
because x plus y plus z.
It's the same thing as x plus y plus z in
parenthesis.
So I can, I can put the parenthesis either
to the left or to the right.
The second law that needs to hold for
monad
is called left unit.
It says that if I inject into the monad
using unit, and then flatMap with f.
Then the result is the same as simply
applying f to the value x.
The last law is right unit.
It says that if I flatMap with the unit
constructor,
I end up with the same monad value as
before.
Let's check the monad laws for an example
type,
I pick Option for that.
First thing we have to do is look at
flatMap for Option.
So what flatMap should do is, it should
take an optional value.
If that optional value is None, so, we
have nothing, then we keep None.
If the optional value is something with a
value x, we apply a
given function to that value and that will
give us another optional value.
Let's start
to prove the Left Unit Law.
What we need to show here is that, unit of
x for option that was some of x as you
know.
flatMap f is the same thing as f of x.
So let's start with that expression, some
of
x flatMap f, and expand what flatMap
means.
So flatMap is this pattern match which
says, well, if it's some of x,
then apply f to it.
If it's none, keep on having none.
Now that we can simplify obviously,
because we have a
some of x here, so it clearly matches the
first pattern.
And that would give us f(x) as the result.
So the first monad law holds.
Let's look at the right unit law now.
So the right unit law says that some
optional value flatMap, with some which
is the unit constructor.
Is the same thing as that optional value.
So we start with the left hand side.
Optional value, flatMap some.
We expand what flatMap means, so we again
have this pattern match which says well,
match if it's some of x then return now
function f is some.
So the function f here gets inserted here.
So we return some of x, and if it's none,
then we return none.
And that again simplifies to just opt,
because we see that in each of the
two branches of the pattern match, we
return exactly this thing that we started
with.
So the right unit law holds also.
Finally we have to check the Associative
Law.
So here it is.
We need to show that the sequence of the
two flatMaps
with the parenthesis to the left, is the
same thing as
a flatMap of a flatMap with the
parenthesis to the right.
So let's start with the left again.
Here we have the sequence of the two
flatMaps.
Here's what it expands to.
So that line is the first flatMap with the
two pattern matches now on one line.
And the parenthesis will go to this.
That's its expansion.
So that result has to be subjected to the
second flatMap.
So here we immediately follow the first
pattern match with the second one, which
now implements the flatMap called, it's g
instead of f before.
So that's the expansion of this
expression.
Now what I do is, I take the second
pattern match, this one here.
And I move it inside.
The two branches of the first one.
So I know that the result of the first
pattern match will be the selector of the
second one.
All I did here was to say, well let's take
each branch of the first pattern match.
And make it the selector of the second
one.
So I pulled the second selector in here.
And in here.
That gives me this expression here, and
that expression now in turn, we can
simplify.
So let's look at the case, none here
first.
So in, if the optional value is none, then
we have the
match none match case some y g of y case
none none.
So obviously it would be the second
pattern match that applies.
And the whole expression simplifies to
this one that you see here.
So the
second case is just, if you get a none, we
keep a none.
Let's turn to the first case.
So in the first case we say well, if we
got
a some of x then we match f of x in turn.
If we, again, get a some of y we give you
g of y and we keep a none.
So what that is, if we look at things in
reverse, it's just f of x flatMap g.
Because if we expand flatMap g, then that
expansion
in turn gives us exactly that pattern
match here.
And if we look at that expression in turn,
then we see that it's
just another instance of a flatMap, this
time the flatMap is with this function
here.
So we say well it's the function that
says,
given an x, it will return this expression
here.
So we get opt flatMap x arrow f of x
flatMap
g and that's exactly the right hand side
of our original equation
that we wanted to prove.
So option is a monad because those three
laws hold as we have just shown.
You might ask well why should I care about
the Monads Laws?
What significance do they have for
programming practice.
Well, one answer to that is that they give
a
justification for certain refactorings of,
for expressions that are quite intuitive.
The Associative Law
says essentially that one can inline
nested for expressions.
So if I have a for expression like that,
where the first generator is in turn a for
expression.
What I can do is I can essentially inline
the two generators here.
In one large for expression, and the
result would always be the
same, provided that the type in question
satisfies the Monad Associativity Law.
The right unit law also has a significance
for, for expressions.
It essentially says that the trivial for
expression here where I generate x and
immediately return it, is the same as the
original value that you see here.
For the left unit law, though, I haven't
found an analogue like that for, for
expressions.
So it seems that as what concerns behavior
for,
for expressions, only associativity and
right unit is important.
So here's another type that might or might
not be a monad.
We'll find out.
And that type will be important in the
later parts of this course.
The type is named Try, and it resembles
option.
Except that instead of some and none,
there
are two cases which are named success and
failure.
The success case returns a value, just
like some
does, but the failure case returns
something, namely an exception.
So the idea is that try will be used in
cases where we want to.
Propagate exceptions not at the call
stack, but say between
different threads of different processes,
or even between different computers.
So in, in a sense we want to bottle up an
exception in a value that we can then
freely pass around.
Here's a definition of the Try class.
It's an abstract class Try with a T
parameter, just like Option.
The Success case extends Try and gives you
simply a value of type T.
The second case, failure, contains an
exception and extends Try of Nothing.
As you've seen in the functional
programming
course, nothing is the Bottom type in
scala.
Know where nothing doesn't have any value,
and it
typically refers to something that is
either a missing
value in the exception or a computation
that does not return normally.
Because maybe the computation throws an
exception or it loops infinitely.
So a typical way to create try values is
using.
Try of expressions, so you can wrap an
arbitrary expression in a try.
And that is achieved by making try an
object in the standard library that has
an apply method.
So, you've seen that anything that has an
apply method can be applied just like a
function.
The same holds for objects such as try.
So what is the definition of the supply
method?
Well, it would take an expression, a
computation, and return a try of the
type of that computation, and what it
would do is it would use a Java try.
So a try that
you know from the jvn that's written, in
lowercase try.
So we try to compute the value of
expression and rapid inner success.
If the computation here throws an
exception
that will be caught here in the block
and the exception will then be wrapped in
a failure value and returned as a result.
That happens for any exception that is non
fatal.
Non fatal
is a fairly technical thing essentially
and exception is fatal if
it doesn't make sense to export this
beyond a single thread there.
Couple of exceptions that are.
But the vast majority of all exceptions,
both
run time exceptions, and normal
exceptions, are non fatal.
What's important here is that the
expression is passed as a by
name parameter because otherwise, of
course,
we would already have our value here.
So there wouldn't be a computation that
could throw an exception.
So that's why you have the type arrow t
indicating call by name parameters here.
Just like with option, try value
computation can be composed in for
expressions.
So, for instance, you could write for x
taken from some computation compute
x, y taken from some computation compute
y, yield the result
f applied to x and y wherever f is some
function that takes an x and a y value.
So, what that means is that, if compute x
and compute y both succeed.
So, they give you result, success x and
success y, respectively.
That would return a success value with the
value f of xy.
But if either computation fails with an
exception, this will return failure with
the first
exception that got drawn.
So to support this kind of notation
all we need to do is define map and
flatMap the right way on the Try type.
Here the definitions of flatMap and map on
the Try type.
Let's look at flatMap first.
So flatMap takes a function from the
domain T, gives us a try of U.
And what it would do is, it would say if
we start out with a success, so we have a
value x, then let's apply f to x.
That would give us the result value.
But on the other hand if the function f
itself throws an exception
which is not fatal, then let's package
this up in a failure value.
Because there is a principle that we will
never leak non-fatal exception from a
trial computation.
On the
other hand, if we started out with already
a failure, and
an exception, then that gets propagated
into the result and returned here.
What about map?
So map just takes a simple function from T
to U and we have to wrap it up in a try.
The way this is done is again, pattern
match on success and failure.
If we have a success x, then let's apply f
to x and submit it to the try constructor
so that again, would if f throws an
exception, give us a failure,
if f returns a value, then we will drop
that in a success.
And, as before, failures get propagated in
the result.
So if we look at the relationship between
flatMap and map, then that's what we have
here.
A try value of mapped with a function f.
It's the same thing as a flatMap
where the function f gets applied to x,
and then the
result gets trapped in a try because
that's how map was defined.
And if I rewrite that expression here, I
get t flatMap f and then try.
So t map f is the same thing as flatMap f
and then try.
So having map and flatMap defined like
this, some try values suggest that try
might be a monad where the unit is the try
constructor itself.
Is it?
Possible answers would be yes, it is, or
it isn't.
And in that case I would also like to know
why
it isn't, so it couldn't, it might not be
a monad
because the Associative Law fails, or the
left unit or the
right unit law fail, or maybe two or more
Monad Laws fail.
What do you think?
Well, if you check the laws, then you find
out that, in fact, the left unit law
fails.
Let's see why.
So, what's the left unit law for Tries?
It says that the unit, so that would
be Try, applied to an expression, flatMap,
a function
f, would have to be the same as f apply
directly to the expression on the left.
But it isn't.
We have a non equality here.
And why is that?
Well, the left hand side, here as we've
seen, will never raise a non fatal
exception.
Neither try nor flatMap would.
Where as, of course the right hand side
will raise
any exception that's thrown by the either
f or expression.
So that means that the left unit law
cannot possibly hold
for a good implementation of Try and,
otherwise put the Try,
in a sense, trades one monad law for
another law.
Which in this context is more useful.
That other law, I call it the bullet-proof
principle, would be that an expression
composed from Try, map, and flatMap will
never throw a non-fatal exception.
So to conclude, we've seen that for
expressions are useful not only for
collections.
Many other types also define map, flatMap,
and
withFilter, and that enables with them
for, for expressions.
For expressions can be written over these
types then.
The examples we've seen are where
generator.
Option and try.
We've seen that many of the types that
have a flatMap and map functions
are in fact monads.
That means that we can also give a unit a
constructor, and we can verify that they
satisfy the monad laws.
You might ask what about filter?
We haven't seen filter so far.
Well, it turns out that if these
monad's define also with filter and
satisfy certain
additional laws, they are called monads
with
zero which is somewhat richer category
than monads.
The three monad laws that we have seen
give useful guidance in the design of
library APIs, but as always of every law,
you also have to know when to break it.
We've seen that the laws do apply to
option and
are very useful there, but they don't all
apply to try.
the left unit law fails.
on the other hand, we've also seen that
the
left unit law itself doesn't really have a
good explanation
in terms of for-expressions.
So that would mean that while try is not a
monad, it is
still a type that can be used in a
perfectly safe and reasonable way.
As they carry a type of a for-expression.