So far, we have concentrated in this
course on pure functional programming,
that is we have always worked just with
functions and immutable data.
However in a reactive system of any size,
there's sooner or later some state that
needs
to be changed and maintained, or some
states
changes that need to be signaled and
propagated.
To express this we are going to broaden
now our notion
of functions to work together with mutable
state.
We will see that this combinations has
quite a few repercussions.
On the one hand, it gives us powerful new
ways to express ourselves in certain
categories of systems.
On the other hand it poses considerable
challenges how to reason about the
resulting systems.
So until now, our programs have been side
effect free, and one important
consequence of this is that we will see
that the concept of time wasn't important.
How do I mean that?
Well, for all programs that terminate, any
sequence
of action would have given the same
result.
And that was also reflected in the
substitution model of computation.
So let's quickly remember what that model
was.
In the substitution model, programs can be
evaluated simply by rewriting the program
text.
There are a number of rules.
The most important rewrite rule covers
function applications.
So here you see the rule.
It says that if you have a function
definition, say
a function f with parameters x1 to xn and
body b.
And then later on, you have a call of the
same function
f, with actual values, v1 to vn.
Then, the program
can be rewritten by keeping the
application and all the other program
elements, but replacing the call by the
body of the function, b.
Where all the former parameters, x1 to xn
are at the same time
replaced by the actual values, v1 to vn.
So that
was the central rule that we had for the
substitution model.
Now, let's see that in an action, and in
an example.
Say you have two functions, iterate and
square.
Iterate would apply the given function, f.
N times on the given argument x.
And here you see it's right inside.
Square is just the squaring function that
takes an argument and multiplies it by
itself.
Let's now look at the call iterate of one
square and three.
That call can be rewritten as follows.
The first thing you do is you take the
right hand side of iterate,
and you replace the actual arguments for
the former parameters n, f, and x.
So that would give you this line here.
The next thing that happens is
that you do two auxiliary reductions.
The first one would simplify the
arithmetic expression one equals zero to
false.
And then this next reduction would
immediately simplify the if then else
by saying, well if false something of
something takes the else part.
So, that's the part that you see here.
In the next step then, we would have to
rewrite the call square
of three of the iterator application, so
that would give you, obviously,
three times three by simply expanding the
right hand side of square.
And arithmetic simplification gives you
this line here, where
the three times three has been reduced to
nine.
Now you would have another expansion of
iterate, so the right hand
side of iterate would again show up here,
with the actual arguments
replacing the formal parameters.
And some subse, subsequent reductions on
the
if would finally give you, if zero equals
zero, that's true, so you would return the
then part, and that would be nine.
One interesting observation here is that
rewriting can be done anywhere
in that term, and all rewritings that
terminate would lead to the same solution.
In fact, that's an important result of
lambda
calculus, which is the theory behind
functional programming.
So let's see that in an example.
The first reduction, result of reduction
in our iterate example was this line here.
If one equals zero three else iterate one
minus one square, square of three.
And we rewrote it to this expression here.
But that's not the only thing we could do
with this expression.
Alternatively, we could also have
concentrated on
the nested call here and rewritten that
one.
And if we had done that we would have
gotten this expression here.
So now we have two different terms that
same, same term up here can rewrite too.
And the important result here is that it
doesn't matter which of the two we pick
because in the end, both of these terms
actually will give the same answer, nine.
And that idea that I can rewrite anywhere
in a term but finally all, all results
yield
the same result, is sometimes called
confluence because
these arrows, they flow together in the
final result.
And this confluence result has been
discovered by Church and Rosser, so
sometimes it's also called The
Church-Rosser Theorem of lambda calculus.
Now all of these observations hold in the
world of pure functional programming.
What I want us to do now is take
a step outside that world and introduce
state and objects.
So, why would one want to do that.
Well, normally, one describes the world as
a set of objects.
And some of these objects would have state
that can change over the course of time.
So what would, does that mean?
An object has stated changes over the
course of time?
It turns out that a very abstract but
accurate definition is that,
an object has state if its behavior is
influenced by its history.
So for instance, if I take a bank account
as an object, a bank account has state.
Because the answer to the question, can I
withdraw 100 Francs would depend on
the previous history of the account.
It would say true if I had deposited
earlier enough money so
that I could withdraw 100 Francs, and it
would say false otherwise.
So that was the abstract definition of
state full objects.
In practice, every form of mutable state
is constructed from some variables.
A variable definition in scala is written
like a value
definition, but with the key word var in
place of val.
So we, so you would write var x: String
equals " abc".
And that would give you a variable, x of
type string, with initial
value abc.
So just like a value definition, a
variable definition, associates a value
with a name.
But if you wrote var, so if you have a
variable definition, that association can
be changed later through an assignment.
So, you could afterwards write x equals i,
and give the new value
to the variable x, or you could define a
count to be 111.
And then add one to the count as you used,
in to do in imperative programming.
So in practice objects with state are
usually represented
by objects that have some members that are
variables.
So for instance, here is a class that
models a bank account.
You have a class bank account, and here
you
see a variable balance initialized to
zero, and the keyword
private in front says that that balance
variable can
be accessed only from the methods within
class bank account,
but not from clients of that class.
What methods are there in class bank
account?
Well, there's the deposit method, which
allows one to deposit
a given amount of currencies units, that
amount must be positive.
If it is, then it gets added to the
accounts balance.
And conversely, there's the withdrawment
method that allows
one to withdraw an amount that also must
be positive, and furthermore, must be less
than or equal to the current account
balance.
If that's not the case, if the, for
instance the amount is bigger than the
current balance, then the withdrawal
method would
throw an exception with the error,
insufficient funds.
So in summary, class bank account defines
one private variable balance,
and two methods that can be used to change
that variable.
To create bank accounts, we use the usual
notation for object creation.
So, you would write val account equals new
BankAccount and that would give you a new
account.
So let's try out some of these concepts
using a worksheet in the Scala IDE.
What I've done is I've defined a project,
Reactive2 for the second week of the
reactive course.
And in there I have defined the class
BankAccount like you saw it on the slide.
One thing you notice is in the
syntax coloring, variables actually appear
in red.
Which is a good sign that means pay
attention.
Here's a feature that is, at the same
time, very powerful, but also dangerous.
So pay attention to that.
So what we're going to do now is interact
with bank accounts using a worksheet and
this scala IDE.
To do that I create a new worksheet, call
it Account.
And the first thing to do is create some
account.
And deposit some initial money, let's say
50 currency units.
And that now would respond that an account
was created.
And what I can do now is withdraw funds.
Let's withdraw 20 currency units.
So what I see here is the 30 that remain.
Let's do that again.
So now it's just ten that remain, and
let's try
to overdraw, and we get an error which
says insufficient funds.
So clearly, accounts are stateful objects,
because when
we perform the same operation, like
withdraw here twice, the results differ.
The first time we cut back 30, the second
time we cut back ten.
And of
course that is because the effect of the
withdraw method depends
on the history of the object, what, what
operations have been performed.
Before on that object.
So we've seen that statefulness is often
connected to having variables.
Let's see how strong or not strong this
connection is in a couple of examples.
The first example is an implementation of
streams, that means lazy sequences
that you have already seen in the previous
course in week seven.
We have a slight variation here that
instead of using
a lazy val, we implement non-empty streams
using a mutable variable.
Here you see how.
So the idea is that we have a function
cons, which, which will create a stream
consisting of
a head T, and a computation tail that
gives
you the rest of the stream when it's
demanded.
And the way it's done is that the cons
function
creates a new anonymous class of type
stream of T.
And it has in that object a variable tail
opt and
mutable variable of type option of stream
of T, which is pre-initialized to none.
Now, the tile operation on cons would
query the variable tail opt,
if it is has already some value x that
value is tail.
If it is still set to none, then the tail
opt will be computed by
calling tail, so this reference to tail
will actually invoke this operation and
wrapping it in a some and returning the
result.
So the question now is, is the result of
cons a stateful object?
If you hesitated in your answer, I don't
blame you.
Because in fact, in a sense, both the yes
and the no are
valid responses, depending on what
assumptions you
make on the rest of your system.
One common assumption is that streams
should only be
defined over purely functional
computations.
So, the tail operation here should not
have a side effect.
In that case, the optimization to cache
the first value
of tlOPt and reuse it on all previous
calls to
tail is purely a optimization that avoids
computations, but that
does not have an observable effect outside
the class of streams.
So the answer would be that, no streams
are not stateful objects.
On the other hand, if you allow side
effect in computations for tail, let's say
tail could
have a printing statement, then you would
see that
the second time tail is caught in this
string.
It would come straight out of the cache,
so there would be no side effect
performed.
Whereas, the first time,
it would be called the operation
would be performed, including the printing
statement.
So that means clearly the operation tail
depends on the previous history of the
object.
It would be different depending on whether
a previous tail was performed or not.
So in that sense, the answer would be cons
is a stateful object, provided
that you also allow imperative side effect
in computations for tail.
Here the second example to have you think
about it.
So here we have a class BankAccountProxy,
and it does not contain any variable.
Instead it takes a constructor argument a
bank account, and
its deposit and withdrawal operations
would simply forward to that account.
Question, are instances of
BankAccountProxy stateful objects?
So here the answer is actually more clear
cut,
even though BankAccountProxy doesn't
contain any variable, its behavior
is clearly stateful because it depends on
the history.
all that it does is it forwards to this
other mutable bank account.
So for instance, calling withdraw twice
would give you
different results just as the original
withdraw would have done.
So clearly the bank account proxies are
stateful objects.