It turns out that the introduction of
mutable
state and changing objects has
repercussions on object identity.
That means the question, when are 2
objects the same, or when are they
different?
You're going to look at this question in
detail in this unit.
So previously, we questioned whether two
objects were
the same, had often a rather easy answer.
Let's say we have two value
definitions, x equals E and y equals E
where E is an arbitrary expression, and we
don't consider any assignment, then it's
reasonable to
assume that x and y are the same.
By that, we mean that we could also have
written x equals E, and
y equals x, and the two forms of
definitions would mean the same thing.
That property is usually called
referential transparency.
In fact, if we use the substitution model,
then having
written that, we would reduce in one step
to a program
like this because the rule for value
references means that
we replace a value reference, x, by it's
right-hand side, E.
So we arrive from here to here in one
step.
But it turns out that once we introduce
assignments, the waters
are considerably muddied, and we will see
how in the next slide.
So once we allow for assignments, the two
formulations
above, here and here, don't mean the same
thing anymore.
For instance, if we define two bank
accounts in x and
y, can we reasonably assume that x and y
are the same?
What do you think?
So if you're like me, then I believe the
answer to that would be
clearly no because creating two bank
accounts
should give you two things that are
different.
But on what grounds, precisely, do you
base it on?
So, is there something that tells you
clearly
that now the answer if you create two
definitions
of the same right-hand sides that give you
back
something different, whereas before it was
always the same?
When do you make that decision in what
direction?
If I were to respond to that question more
precisely, we
need a theory of what it means to be the
same.
And the precise meaning of being the same,
is defined by a property called
operational equivalence.
In a somewhat informal way, this property
can be stated as follows.
Let's say you have two
definitions for x and y, and they are
operationally
equivalent if no possible test can
distinguish between them.
So let's see what mean by that, clarify
that, we
have to look at what can be a possible
test.
So to test if x and y are the same, what
we can do is essentially put them in a
black box
that consists of the definition x and y.
And then an arbitrary sequence
of instructions that pokes into these two
definitions in any way possible.
So let's call this sequence of
instructions, f and it, we say f
of x and y because it can access both x
and the y.
So that was one part of the experiment.
We create two bank accounts.
We do some
things with it.
What we do is arbitrary, which we have the
full
choice of operations that we can use in
the experiment.
So then the second half of the experiment
is to run
the same sequence of operations on our two
banks account definitions.
But now we are only allowed to access the
x.
So where previously you would have a
sequence
that may be interleafed called x and y,
now every access to y will
be replaced by exactly the same access,
but to the object x.
If you can observe a difference from that
sequence to that sequence,
then the expressions x and y are clearly
different because, what?
It makes a difference whether you access
one or the other.
That's the meaning of being different.
On the other hand, if every possible
experiment,
every possible pair of sequences, produces
the same result,
then we say that x and y are the
same because there's no way you could
distinguish them.
They can't, they're not different because
there is no test that can
give a different outcome on the x and y or
the x and
x on the right-hand side.
So that, in a nutshell, is the definition
and the theory of operational equivalence.
Let's put it to a test in our bank
accounts example.
So, we start with the expressions, lets x
be a bank account and y
be a bank account, and let's see whether
they define values that are the same.
Here's our test sequence.
We deposit 30
units into x and withdraw 20 units into y.
What do we get?
Well according to our definition of bank
accounts,
we get 30 currency units in the first
line.
Actually, there wouldn't be anything
printed, it's just 30 currency units.
And we get insufficient funds when we
withdraw 20 currency units from y.
Why?
Because, well, the initial balance of y
was zero, and x and y are different,
so you can't withdraw 20 from an account
with a balance of zero.
So that was the first half of the
experiment.
In the second half, we rename every
occurrence of
y in in the sequence of operations to x.
So now we have x deposit thirty, and x
withdraw twenty.
And yes, indeed, now, the second line
would give
us a result of 10, rather than an
insufficient
fund ex, exception.
So the final results of both half of the
experiment are different, and that means
we can conclude that x and y are not the
same, that they define different objects.
On the other hand, if we now defined x
equals new bank account, and y equals x,
then it turns out that no sequence of
operations can distinguish between the x
and the y.
So they are the same in this case.
Now to prove that two objects are the
same,
and this theory is considerably harder
than to prove
that they are different because you have
to show
that no possible sequence of operations
can distinguish between them.
So, you have to argue about a possibly
infinite number of possible experiments.
Whereas to prove that 2 definitions are
different, a single counter example is
enough.
Now, one thing the discussion so far shows
is that our model of computation
by substitution has become problematic, in
fact that it cannot be used.
Indeed, if we apply the Substitution Model
to our bank account example, then we
can always replace the name of a value by
the expression that defines it.
So for instance, if we have the,
these two definitions, then by the
Substitution Model,
as we have seen, that rewrites in one step
to the definitions on the right.
So, instead of the reference to x here,
I take the right-hand side, new bank
account.
But we have seen that, the, this change,
this step
from here to here, in fact leads to a
different program.
So, clearly going from here to here is not
a valid step, and that means that the
Substitution Model,
as a whole, stops being valid once we add
assignment to a language.
It is possible to adapt the substitution
model, for instance,
by introducing a store that keeps track of
all the references.
But unfortunately, this becomes
considerably more complicated.
So, in the future, we will say with some
regret, goodbye to
the Substitution Model for all code that
is not purely functional, and
we will fall back on a more operational
and sometimes intuitive reasoning instead.