In the first two units of this week we
have moved
from pure functional programming to a
combination of functional and imperative
programming.
Another feature often associated with
imperative programming are
loops, and these will be studied in this
unit.
In fact, it turns out that loops,
as a feature, are nonessential for
comparative languages.
With just variables we can already model
all imperative programs.
So if an imperative program contains a
loop, how do you emulate that?
Well, you can emulate the loop itself by
using a function.
Let's see an example.
Here's a Scala program that uses the
familiar while loop.
It's an example that raises x to the power
of a exponent,
and it uses the usual loop that works with
successive multiplications.
It's not the best way to express power in
Scala.
It serves just to as an example to
introduce a loop.
So in Scala, the while loop is actually a
language construct, and while
is a keyword, but it turns out that it
wouldn't have been necessary.
We could have defined while just using a
function.
To show the difference between the
built-in while and the function,
we name the function with all capitals,
WHILE.
So that function WHILE can be defined as
you see here.
It would be a function that takes a
condition
and a command, and its result type would
be Unit.
And what it would do is it would execute
the command, as long as the condition was
true.
So, it would say, if condition holds, then
execute
command, and do a recursive call to WHILE,
with the same condition at the same
command.
If condition is false, simply return with
the unit value.
So, one thing to notice that both the
condition and the command must
be passed by name, so that they can be
re-evaluated in each iteration.
Otherwise, if the condition was by value
and maybe initially true,
the while loop would loop forever because
the
condition would never be re-evaluated to
be false.
The other observation is that the while
loop is
tail recursive, so the recursive call
happens as the
last action in this branch of the if, and
that means it can be implemented in
constant stack space.
Implementing the recursive call back just
to jump back to the beginning of
the code here, in a way which is just as
efficient as a native while.
Now, you've seen how to emulate while
loops
with just a function definition in the
call.
What about repeat?
Let's write a function that implements a
repeat loop to be used as
follows, REPEAT, command, and then it
should
stop once the condition here is true.
How would you do that?
If we look at the usage of the
repeat function, then it's clear that the
definition will,
should look like this.
REPEAT takes a by name parameter command
of type arrow Unit and a by named
condition of type arrow Boolean, so it's
also a by name parameter.
And its body would be like this.
So repeat, we said, should always execute
command first.
And then if the condition is true,
it should stop.
And otherwise it should do a recursive
call
with the same command and the same
condition.
Now, here's a variation of the previous
exercise.
Let's say I'm not happy with the previous
syntax of repeat, and
I want to write something like
this instead, REPEAT, command, UNTIL,
condition.
Can you devise a definition of a
repeat function that would support that
call syntax?
That's actually feasible, even though it's
quite a bit harder
than what we've shown in the previous
example, so it's
left as an optional exercise for you.
It's not essential to follow any of the
rest of the course, but if you want
to have some fun playing with the
capabilities
of Scala syntax, then it should be quite
instructive.
Now, we've seen two variants of a
hypothetical repeat loop.
what I haven't told you yet is what syntax
Scala actually uses.
Turns out neither of the two.
What Scala actually
uses is the same, again, as in C or in
Java.
You write do and then some command.
And then you'd write while and then a
condition.
So we've seen while loops and repeat loops
and do loops,
the last category of loops that we should
cover is for loops.
Here it turns out that the classical for
loop that you'll find in
C or C++ or Java, cannot be modeled simply
by a higher order function.
So if you look at such a for loop, you see
the example
here, you see that there's actually a
definition here, that i equals one,
that introduces a variable that is used
later
on in the other parts of the for loop.
And that's something that cannot be
straightforwardly
achieved by using just higher order
function applications.
And, as a matter of fact, Scala does not
have this kind of for loop.
What it has is a kind of for loop that is
similar to Java's extended for loop, so
you would write something that's
equivalent to the example up here like
this, for i ranging over one until three,
system out.print i plus space.
And that would display one and two.
Now, this looks pretty much like a for
expression, like the ones you've seen in
the functional
programming course and also in the first
week
of this course, and in fact that's no
accident.
For loops translate quite similarly
to for expressions, but where for
expressions translate into combinations of
functions
map and flatMaps, for loops translate into
combinations of the function foreach.
So, foreach is a function that's defined
on all collections with elements of type
T.
It would take an argument which is a
function
from T to Unit, give you back a Unit.
And its effect
would be to apply the given function
argument f to each element of the
collection.
So, here's an example where you use two
nested generators.
You let i range from one until three, j
range over the
elements of the string abc, and you print
i plus space plus j.
So in this case, that should print
1a, 1b, 1c, 2a, 2b, 2c.
That expression gets expanded into two
nested calls of foreach.
You start with the first range, one one
until three.
You apply the closure, i arrow something,
to that range.
That closure takes each element i, taken
from one until three, and there's
a nested call of foreach, where the base
collection is the string abc.
The loop variable is the j, and the final
result is the println.
So to summarize, we have seen the
different forms
of loops that you would expect in
imperative languages.
And have shown how each of these can, at
least in principle, be translated
into more basic units in the Scala
language.
While and repeat can be translated into
simpler
cause of higher functions, and the
extended for
loop gets translated into
inter-combinations of the foreach
method, which is defined on every Scala
collection.