In the second example of the Discrete
Event
Simulation case study, we will look at the
APIs.
The programming interfaces of the core
libraries and how they are used.
So we've seen in the last unit that the
class wire and the functions inverter,
AND gate, and OR gate, represent a small
description language for digital circuits.
What we need to do now
is we need to give an implementation of
the class
wire and these functions which allow us to
simulate circuits.
And those implementations in turn are
based on a simple API
for discrete event simulation which we are
going to study first.
So what is discrete emu, event simulation?
A discrete event simulator performs
actions which are specified by the user to
take place at a given moment.
An action is simply a function that
doesn't take any parameters, and which
returns unit.
So everything in action do, it does by its
side side effect.
And the time when an action is takes place
is simulated.
It has nothing to do with the actual wall
clock time.
It is the simulated time.
So, concretely, we are going to write
simulations
inside objects that inherit from a trait
called simulation.
And that trait has the following
signature.
There's a function currentTime, which
returns the current
simulated time in the form of an integer.
Then there's a function afterDelay, where
the user gives can
install a block of statements to be
performed as an action.
At a time that is delay time units after
the current time.
And finally, there's the function run,
which lets the user start
the simulation and execute all installed
actions until no further actions remain.
So let's take a look at the structure of a
typical simulation application.
It would be composed of several classes
that are shown in this Class Diagram.
At the top of the diagram you have the
trait simulation,
which we have just seen in its API.
that trait would give, give you the
necessary
tools to do any kind of discrete event
simulation.
that trait would be inherited by something
that is a little bit more
special, namely that gives you the tools
to the, do basic circuit simulation.
In particular, it would contain the class
wire, and the gates for
AND, OR, and inverter.
They would be defined on this level here.
one level further down you would have a
trait
that gives you more complex circuits, call
it circuits.
And here, you would find things like the
half adder and b adder.
And, then finally you would have the
concrete objects that the user wants to
simulate.
Call this maybe my simulation, so that
would typically be an object that
can obtain all of the functionality and
discrete event simulation.
The gates and the circuits, by inheriting
from these traits.
So that's a structure of a typical
application.
We have already seen simulation.
Let's look at the interface of this gates
layer next.
So indicates layer.
You have first have the class of wires.
To be simulated a wire should support
three basic operations.
The first operation is get signal.
That should return the current value of
the signal that's transported
by the w, wire.
Current means, at the current simulated
time.
Then there should be a way to change the
signal
of a wire, that's done by the method set
signal.
And that modifies the va, value of the
signal that's transported by the wire.
And finally there's a third method called
add action, which let's us add an action.
To be performed every time the signal
of a wire changes.
Here the idea would be when the signal
of a wire changes, then certain things
should happen.
The things that should happen can be
installed
so to speak with a call to add action.
So, here's an implementation of these
ideas for wires.
So, a wire then would have a private
variable,
sigVal which is the value of the current
signal from
the wire, and it would have also private
variable actions which are the actions
to be performed when that signal changes.
GetSignal simply returns sigVal.
The set signal method would take a new
signal value.
If it's different from the old one, the
old, the current signal value is updated.
And all actions are executed.
So that's done by calling the foreach
method on each action.
And what, what is being done
is that the action is simply run by
applying it to the unit parameter.
If we use a for loop for the same
signification we would write it like this.
So that would expand into exactly this
code over here.
For a taken from action run a.
The last method is called addAction, and
what it simply does is it prefixes
the current action to all of actions that
are all ready stored in the wire.
And what it also does it turns out to
be technically necessary to get the
simulation off the
ground is.
Once we add an action we immediately
perform it a first time because otherwise
it turns out that the simulation would
essentially rest in an inert state
forever.
So we have to perform the action the first
time to get things off the ground.
So to summarize, the state of a wire
is modeled by two variables, sigVal which
represents the
current value of the signal and actions
that represents
the actions that are currently attached to
the wire.
So, once we have wires we can look at
gates.
Let's look at the inverter first.
So, the inverter is implemented by
installing an action on its input wire.
That way, that action would be performed
each time the input write changes.
And what would the action do?
Well, it would produce the inverse of the
input
signal, but not immediately but only after
a certain delay.
Call that InverterDelay, units of
simulated time.
So that's the idea, let's see how that
would be put in code.
Here's the inverter method.
It takes an input wire and an output wire.
And here's the inversion action.
So, what to invert, the input wire, what
we would
do is we would take the signal of the
input wire.
And then we would set the output to the
negation of the
input signal, but we would do that only
after a certain delay.
So we'll use this method from the
simulation API.
After delay it says, perform this block
here,
invert the delay time units after the
current time.
So that's the invert action, and this
action
should be performed every time the input
wire
changes it's signal.
So we achieve that by adding this invert
action to the input wire, so that way the
wire itself would perform this action
every time it's signal changes.
The AND gate is implemented in a similar
way.
The action of the AND gate then would
produce the
AND, the conjunction of the input signals
of the output wire.
And it would happen after a certain
delay, call it AndGateDelay, units of
simulated time.
So that gives us the following
implementation here,
AND gate takes two inputs and one output.
The AND action we take
the values of the two input signal, after
AND gate delay.
We set the output to the logical AND of
the two values of the input signals.
And when should this action be performed?
Well, it should be performed anytime the
signal
of one of the two input wires changes.
So we add that AND action to both input
one and input two.
That way we're sure
that whenever one of the two input
changes, the output signal would be
recomputed.
As to the OR gate, that's implemented
quite analogously to
the AND gate, so here you still see the
AND gate.
To go to the OR gate we simply change the
action in
orAction from the logical conjunction to
logical disjunction.
The order of the two input signals, and
otherwise everything is exactly as in the
AND Gate.
So to test the understanding, let's have a
look at the way the signals are computed.
So we take the getSignal for, for input
one and input two
before we run the code in afterDelay in a
separate val definition.
So the question to you is what happens if
we compute the two signals in1Sig and
in2Sig inline, that means inside the
afterDelay call,
instead of before writing them in value
definitions.
Would the new definition of OR gate, call
it orGate2, have the same
behavior as the previous one, or would
orGate2 not model OR gates faithfully.
So, let's analyze what would happen.
In the new program, once an input signal
changes, we would wait OR gate delay time
units, and then set the output to the,
this junction of the sampled two signals.
But, the sampling would take place at the
time after OR gate delay,
and the output change in the sampling
would appear at exactly the same time.
In the original orGate
of course we would sample first, then wait
orGateDelay time units and then set the
output afterwards.
So you have seen that it does make a big
difference whether the signals are
computed outside after delay, or inside
and
consequently orGate2 does not model OR
Gates faithfully.
[BLANK_AUDIO]