In the third and final part of the
discrete event simulation.
We will look at the implementation of the
call libraries, and then we will put
everything together.
And draw on a concrete simulation to
demonstrate and test how everything works.
All we have left to do now is to implement
the simulation trait.
The principle idea is to keep in every
instance
of the trait an agenda of actions to
perform.
The agenda would be a list of simulated
events, and each event would
consist of an action and the time when
that action should be produced.
We sort the agenda list in such a way that
the actions to be performed first are in
the beginning, that way we can simply pick
them
off the front of the list to execute them.
That leads to the following start of the
implementation
of the trade simulation.
There's the type action that takes an
anti-parameter list to unit.
Then we would have a class of events.
For convenience we make into a case class,
that way
it's easy to pad a match on that an event
would have a time when it should be
executed and
an action which gives us the function that
should be executed.
There's the agenda
which is just a list of events, and
there's the private
variable agenda of type agenda, which is
initially the empty list.
To handle time, we do that with another
private variable, call it curtime.
That contains the current simulation time.
And that one can be then be accessed with
the getter function current time.
So, the implementation of the method after
delay, with a given
delay and of given block, would then
insert the task event at current time plus
delay to the action that when invoked will
perform the operations in the block.
And, it would put that event into the
agenda list at the right position.
Here's the implementation of after delay,
as we have
seen it creates the event at the given
time.
With the given actions to perform, and it
inserts it into the agenda.
The implementation of the insert function
is straightforward, remember what it needs
to
do is insert an event at the right place
into, in the list.
That it appears at the right position
given its time, so
we do that by doing a parent match on the
agenda.
If the agenda has a first
element, that has a time, that is less or
equal to the current items time.
Then we insert the item in the rest of the
list.
Because we should still keep first as the
first element.
If that's not the case, that means the
list is either empty, or the
first element of the list should appear at
a later time than the current item.
In both of these cases we take the item as
first
element of the list and follow with the
agenda.
The last part of the simulation
implementation
has to do with actually running the
event loop, so that event handling loop
would remove successive elements from the
agenda.
That would be correct because we know that
the
agenda is already time sorted, and perform
the associated actions.
Here's the implementation of the event
handling
loop, it performs a para-match on agenda.
If agenda is not empty, then it will strip
off the first item from agenda, set the
current time
to the indicated time of that item,
perform the
item's action, and continue with the
recursive call to loop.
If the agenda is empty, then the
simulation has ended and the function
connects it.
So to run the simulation we simply call
loop, but before
we do that we install our first action to
be performed.
And that action actually tells us that the
simulation has started, and what the
current time is.
Before we can launch the simulation, we
still need to
wait to exam the changes of the signals on
the wires.
So far, the simulation doesn't give us any
output.
So we would be flying blind.
To change that, we define a function,
probe.
So probe is something that you can attach
to a wire
Sort of like an oscillator that tracks a
digital signal.
Something like that.
And the form it takes here is just like a
gate or another component.
So probe takes the form of a component,
much like
an AND gate or all the other components in
the system.
here's the function probe.
You attach it to a wire.
It has a name that is typically the name
of the wire.
It is an action.
The action consists in printing the
name of the wire, the current time, and
the new signal on that wire.
And what it would do on installation is,
it would add this action to the wire.
So, as always the action gets executed
each time, the signal on the wire changes.
What the example also shows is a neat
feature of scala
in string formatting, so you can write a
string like this.
You prefix it
with an s, which means it's the standard
string
interpolator, and then you can write
anything you want
to embed in the string with a dollar and
the name of the thing that you want to
embed.
Or if the thing that you want to embed is
more than
a single identifier, you can put it in
braces and write that here.
So the string that you see here, you
could have done also by concatenating
strings with plus.
It would
look something like this.
Name, plus space,
plus current time, plus value
equals plus wire.getsignal.
The
tool would print to the same string, but
of course the first one is far easier
to understand what actually gets embedded
where in the string, than the
second version, that relies on the string
concatenation.
The last thing we have to do before we can
start the simulation is define all the
technology dependent parameters.
Remember that our gates use constants in
InverterDelay, AndGateDelay and
OrGateDelay, which were abstract on the
level of basic circuit simulations.
we need to define
them to fit the technology that we use in
the simulation.
A convenient way to do that is to pack
them all in a
separate trait, that can then be mixed in
in the actual simulation object.
So you could define trade parameters with
the delays, and then the actual
simulation object would extend the
circuits class with parameters.
If we look at the class diagrams, then
there
would be another trade called parameters
that gets inherited
from the concrete simulation objects.
Let's try out a concrete simulation,
before we do that in a work sheet.
Let's take a tour of the classes that
we've seen so far.
So there's first the simulation class that
you have seen here.
With its Action type, its Event type, and
the Simulation API.
Which consists of the method after
Delay run and Current time.
You then have the label of Gates.
Where we have the three delays as abstract
methods.
So these need to be filled in later on.
And we have the definition of the wire
class that you have seen.
Of, and then of the gates, inverter gate,
AND gate, and OR gate.
And we also put for pro,
convenience the probe method on that
layer.
Finally we have the layer of circuits
which contains things
like the half Adder that you've seen and
the full Adder.
And the last part is parameters, which is
the trait that
fixes the technology specific constants.
So here we have taken two for inverted
delay, three for the AND gate delay, and
five for the OR Gate delay.
With all that in place, let's launch
a work sheet that does a concrete
simulation.
So I create a new scala work sheet, call
it test.
What I need to do is first create an
object for the actual simulation, so that
would extend the circuits that I have
defined
so far, and would mix in the parameters.
I import everything in that object from,
for convenience.
Then I can get started by creating some
wires for a half adder.
Let's, call them in1.
>> In2, and the output wires would be
Sum, and Carry.
So that would give us four wires that we
see here.
We next connect these wires, with a half
adder.
So we write half adder, in1, in2, sum and
carry.
And to see something, we put probes on the
two output wires.
So we would have a probe, sum, on the sum
wire.
And a probe carry
on the carry wire.
So, that already gives us immediately the
values of the wires.
Sum and carry would both be false.
That's a side effect of immediately
executing an action, once we install it.
And, the action of the probe is simply to
print the current value of the wire.
To run a simulation, let's change a signal
of one of the wires.
So let's say, let's put a one on in
one and run the simulation.
What we see is the welcome message,
simulation has started.
The time 0 and at the time eight, the
new-value of the sum would be true.
The value of the carry has not changed, so
we don't see anything there.
We can continue by placing an input signal
on in two, and running s, the simulation
again.
What you will see now is that the
simulation has restarted at the
time eight, the last time that we saw a
signal change earlier.
And now we see at time 11 the carry signal
would get a new value,
true, and sometimes later, at time 16, the
sum would be false.
We can now retract the signal on in1, and
run the simulation a third time.
And that would give us a time 19, that
the new carry value is false and the sum
value is again true at some later time.
So I hope that gave you a little taste,
what you can do with simulations.
Of course, you could also, in the same
way, simulate
other circuits, and also create your own
circuits to simulate them.
Let's finish the simulation by studying a
variant
of the gates that we have seen so far.
We have seen so far the OR gate
in a manner completely analogous to the
AND gate.
it defines
an action that gets installed from its
input wires.
But in fact another, an alternative way
would be to construct
an OR gate out of the AND gate and in the
inverter.
Because after all we can use, make use of
the
formula that a or b is the same as not not
a and not b.
So to implement that formula, inverters,
and AND gates are enough.
we can have a circuit like this one here.
If the a and the b,
then we invert both inputs.
We make an AND gate and we invert the
output.
So, that leads to this circuit here where
we have
three internal wires, notIn1, notIn2, and
notOut,
replace the inverters and the AND gate as
you see here.
My question to you is if you replaced our
implementation of OR
gate by the alternative OR gate that
you've just seen, what would happen.
Would you compare to the earlier
simulation would you see a change?
Possible answers are no, nothing would
happen, the two simulations behave the
same.
Or maybe the two simulations would produce
the same events,
but the indicated times are different.
Or maybe the times are different, and also
the alternative application of OR
gate could produce additional events that
you don't see in the original simulation.
Or, as a fourth choice, the two
simulations would produce completely
different events all together.
What do you think?
Let's try this out.
I have changed the alternative version of
the OR gate to the standard one.
And I renamed the first standard
one to out.
So let's launch
the simulation again with this alternative
version of the OR gate.
And what we see is that initially we get
some glitches on the sum value.
So it changes value before we can
stabilize.
We see a, at the time five, it has a value
of true, at ten it is false,
and again at ten it is true, so there is
some different behavior here.
Let's see whether we can explain that.
So what I've done here is I've placed the
new version of the OR
Gate into the half adder circuit, and
let's see what happens.
So initially, the value of this wire here
would be zero.
After two, time units the inverter would
make
that wire to be one, after again two time
units,
that inverter would make that wire to be
one.
So, after five time units, the AND gate
here would return a true value, a one
value.
After ten current time units similarly the
initial signal here, the zero here
would propagate to be a one here a one
here and everything would flip around.
And again at the same time
after ten time units, the final set value
of the signal a would take place, and
the propagation would chase each other and
would
produce the final value true for the sum
signal.
So the moral of this is that in these
circuit simulations you
have to give it some time to let the
circuit stabilize itself.
That's also true for the actual
simulations
so the initial results here can sometimes
be misleading.
So the answer which maybe was surprising
to you would be the times are different.
And the added version of OR gate can also
produce additional events.
Why?
Because it's built from more components
that take more time to stabilize
themselves.
So, to summarize, we've seen that adding
state and
assignments makes our mental model of
computation more complicated.
In particular, we lose the property
of referential transparency which says
that it
doesn't matter whether we use a named or
the thing it refers to.
We've seen with the bank account example
that it matters quite
a lot whether we refer to it an existing
bank account,
or we create a new one.
The other thing that we lose is the
substitution model so we
do not have anymore an easy way to trace
computations by rewriting.
On the other hand, assignments allow us to
formulate some programs in an elegant and
concise way.
We've seen that with the example of
discrete events simulation
where a system was represented by a list
of action.
And that list was a mutable variable.
It changed during the time of simulations.
The effect of the actions when they're
called would in turn change the state of
objects, and they could also install other
actions to be executed in the future.
You've seen that in this way combining
higher
functions and assignments in state led to
some very,
very powerful techniques that let you
express fundamentally complex computations
in a concise and understandable way.
So in the end it's a trade off.
You get more expressiveness that helps you
tackle
certain problems in a simpler way, but on
the other hand you loose tools for
reasoning
about your program, referential
transparency, and the substitution model.
So
I guess the moral would be that you should
stick to the purely
functional model whenever you can, and you
should use state responsibly when you
must.