Hi, this is Eric Meijer from Mello Park,
California.
Welcome to week three and four
of the introduction to reactive
programming course.
I hope you had a lot of fun with Martin's
first two weeks.
And in the next two weeks we will
talk a lot about futures, promises,
observables, and observers.
In these lessons, we will mention the word
monad quite a lot.
Just like we did in the first two weeks.
When I use the word monads, it will always
be in the informal sense.
That is, I mean, with the monad, a type
that has map flat map unit.
And it's really used to make the return
type of a function more expressive.
In fact, I will never worry about a monad
loss.
If you have followed week one,
you know that Try of T has the shape of a
monad, but that it satisfies only two of
the three monad laws.
Regardless of that, I will still speak of
Try of T as a monad.
I hope that you all have as much fun
following these lessons as I have making
and recording them.
Enough talking, let's have some fun
learning.
When we look at programming.
I consider the following four essential
effects.
And these will be the four effects that we
will discuss in the two lectures on
futures and observables.
But before we can talk about futures and
observables.
Which are about asynchronous computation.
I want to first revisit, try and iterables
which are about synchronous computations.
And since this is the first lecture of our
series,
we're going to start by looking at try and
T.
So we're going to first look at
synchronous computations.
That return a single value.
These are the computations that we are
used
to, that most of our programs deal with.
The code that we're going to use to
illustrate
our first effect is a very super simple
adventure game.
Here's the trait that defines such a game.
We have two methods.
Collect coins, which returns a list of
coins.
And once we have a list of coins, we can
buy treasure.
And, given these two methods and this
trait, we can write our game as follows.
We create a new instance of adventure by
calling the factory method.
And then we collect our coins.
Once we've got our coins,
we can start to buy treasure with the
coins.
This looks all really, really simple.
But, it's really not as simple as you
would think at first sight.
Because things can fail.
How can things fail, well, you, if you
played any video
games, you'd know that the action hero can
die and game over.
Right.
So let's look at a little bit more detail,
how collect coins and buy treasure
are implemented.
Here's a very simple implementation,
possible implementation of collect coins.
If we get eaten by a monster, then we
throw a new game over exception,
and otherwise we have got a list of coins,
so say that we
return gold, gold and silver.
As you see here, that the
code in that we write doesn't know
anything about the fact
that an exception can be thrown.
It just sees that it returns a list of
coins.
And here you, when you call the method,
there's
no indication at all that say collect
coins may fail.
Let's now drill into, buy treasure a
little bit.
So, here's
[INAUDIBLE]
possible implementation of buy treasure
that will fail.
And when will it fail?
Well, let's see.
If we have our coins.
We sum the value of the coins and if
that's less than the cost of treasure.
Well, then game over.
Nice try.
So, now we have two implementations of the
methods.
Collect coins and buy treasure that can
both, both fail.
And even though the code
looks really, really clean.
Something magic is happening in between
these goals.
Let's make that explicit.
If we really look what's going on, then we
will see that after we call
adventure collect coins, we are blocking,
at this point, until
we have collected all the coins and we
only continue if there was no exception.
Similarly, after we have called buy
Treasure, we block
until the treasure is bought, and we only
continue if
there's no exception.
So this code only shows the happy path,
but it doesn't show at all the unhappy
path.
It doesn't show at all what happens when
there are exceptions.
So let's make that explicit.
Because this is not really fair.
We, we're writing code here that meets
your exceptions, but
it doesn't show up in the structure of our
code.
And that's never a good thing.
So instead of having a function from T to
S.
That may throw.
What we want is, we want to make the
fact that this function can throw explicit
in its type.
And the way we do that is by using the
standard Scala
type Try of T, and in this case, we
instantiate it with S.
So we say one thing, but we really mean
this thing.
And we're going to make
this explicit now and what we're going to
do next
is we're going to look at how Try is
defined.
To make the Try type available in our
codes we import it and here's the
definition.
Try is defined as a
[UNKNOWN]
type, with one case here that is Success.
And in case we have Success, we just have
the element of type T.
And the other possibility is that we have
a Failure, in which case we have a
Throwable.
If we use the Try type to make the chance
of exceptions explicit, the signature
of collectCoins changes as follows.
Instead of just returning a List of Coins,
we now return a Try of List of Coins.
What does that mean?
Well, it means that we can either return
failure which was an exception,
game over or we return Success of T which
is just the List.
Similarly buyTreasure.
Takes just a regular list still.
But now it returns a Try of Treasure.
Again, meaning that either
it fails, giving an exception, or it has
success and then we just return the
treasure.
As we would love to get as the result of
this game.
When we're dealing with failure explicitly
in our
code, our code gets a little bit more
ugly.
Because we have to be explicit about it.
So, let's look at the code, how our code
looks like.
The, again, we create the adventure.
We collect our coins, and the type of that
is now Try of List of Coins.
But now, we can not just call buy treasure
anymore.
Because buy
treasure expects a list of coins, but what
we got
here from collect coins is a try of list
of coins.
So what do we have to do.
Well, we have to pattern match now on
coins.
And if it was a success we can grab the
value and pass that into buy treasure.
But if we failed we will fail again.
Now let's further type check this because
the type of this guy, as I say here,
should be try of treasure.
Is that correct?
Well, that is correct because this buy
treasure here
will return a try of treasure or it will
fail.
So this is all still type correct.
But you see here.
It looks kind of ugly because we have to
be explicit about the errors.
To make our code look nicer we're going to
use some
of the higher order functions that are
defined on the try type.
And here's a list, a partial list of the
functions that are defined on try.
Let's look at this one here filter, map,
flatten and of course, our friend flat
map.
What flat map does, is it takes a try of t
and a function
that takes a t and a try of s and returns
a try of s.
And this is exactly the function that we
wanted in our previous code.
Remember.
When we collected the coins that returned
a try of list of coins so with flatMap we
can get directly at the list of coins
and flatMap will then take care of
propagating all the errors for us.
As you probably already have noticed.
The fact that try of t has a flatMap
operator means that try of t is a monad.
And it's a monad that handles exceptions.
And what is really a monad?
You can, you know, pontificate about what
monads are but really
monads are types with operators that guide
you through the happy path.
Okay.
And so in this case, flatMap will guide us
through
the happy path, and deal with handling the
exceptions for us.
But the nice thing about Try, the nice
thing about
a monad, is that the effects are visible
in the type.
Because before.
When we just had a return type of type T,
we were hiding the fact that our
computations could fail.
By using try of T as our return type,
it's now clear that things can fail, but
we
don't want to deal with failure all the
time.
We want to see that things can fail, but
we want
to automate handling of that and that's
what monads give you.
And in this case again, Try is a monad
that handles exceptions.
It leads us through the happy path, when
the exceptions don't happen.
And it will take care of all the
propagation
of the errors.
So what flatMap does is, it, it's kind of
a Dolby for our code.
It gives us noise reduction.
Remember that ugly code that we have to,
had to write with all the pattern
matching?
Look how beautiful it looks now with
flatMap.
What we do is, we create our adventure,
then we collect our coins.
This is of type try of list
of coins but with flatMap we get here
access to the
list of coins that we can then use to buy
treasure.
And any exceptions are automatically
propagated
by the implementation for flatMap for us.
flatMap is the plumber for the happy path.
Of
course, you remember from earlier lectures
that if
you have a monad, you can use
comprehension syntax.
So we can write the same example here.
Using the four comprehensions as follows.
We get a we collect our coins and then we
can
get the coins, with using the coins we can
buy treasure.
We get the treasure and then we yield our
treasure.
One way to
remember how these four comprehensions
work, is that on the right hand
side of the arrow you have something of
type try of T.
And then on the left of the arrow, you
have something of type T.
So the arrow takes the value of type T out
of the monad.
And that's why there's an arrow there.
So it reduces the type, it takes the value
out of the monad.
That's a little thing that you can use to
remember how this thing works.
Let's look at how some of the operators on
Try of T are defined.
In particular, we want to look how map is
defined.
And in order to use, to do that, we first,
of course, have to look at the companion
object for Try.
And in particular the constructor
functions.
So here's the constructor function.
And what it does, it takes a block that
returns
a T and it turns that into a try of T.
Now this is very subtle, because when you
want to do a try of T, you, you.
you know, you want to have a computation
that you can pass in.
In order to, you know, do here the try
catch on that.
So it's essential that you have this call
by name parameter here.
So what you do, is you take the block and
you try
to execute it and if it succeeds then you
just wrap it into
the success constructor and in case it
fails.
And that is done by the try catch
construct.
In case it fails, in case it draws an
exception, you wrap the exception in the
failure construction.
Once we have the factory method, we can
define map as follows.
What we do is, we match on this, which is
of type Try of T.
If this is of type Success of value, then
we
were in a successful, we were in the happy
path.
So then we can try to call f with the
value.
But we have to now use the constructor
here.
To make sure that when f of value throws,
that we wrap it into failure.
And when f of value succeeds without any
exceptions we wrap it into the success
constructor.
And if we
failed, we just propagate the failure.
So here you see what I mean when the happy
part is
taken care for us and the exceptions are
propagated under the covers.
One way to look at Try is that it
materializes exceptions.
The exceptions here are implicit.
This type doesn't say anything about
exceptions, but on
this side here, all the exceptions are
made explicit.
The exceptions are turned.
From something that happens in the control
flow of your program
into an actual data value that you can
patch a match on.
So a more kind of official word for that
is materialize.
And we will see this notion of
materialize appear, reappear later on in
these lectures.
Let's finish off with a quiz and where we
implement flatMap.
So, what we are going to try is to define
flatMap for try of t.
So, the signature of flatMap is flatMap
takes a function from t to try of s.
And remember the this is of type try of t
and what we need to return is a try of s.
So, take a few seconds to think about
which answer a, b or c is the right one.
Good.
Let's see which answer was the correct
one.
And we are going to do that as usual by
inspecting all the choices one by one.
Let's look at the first one.
And the trick, this is the beauty of
functional programming, that often by
looking at the types, you can already see
when something is correct or not.
Let's look at this guy here.
this looks kind of type correct, because
if I call f with value.
well the value is of type t, f was of type
t to try of s.
So this is indeed of type try
of s.
However, what we don't do here is we
don't catch any exceptions so if f of
value throws an exception.
It's not materialized.
And so it doesn't appear as a value in the
output.
So this one is wrong.
Now let's look at the second solution.
What this does, is this
tries now to wrap the result of f of value
in a try.
But remember what the, the type of try
was.
Try, and I'm going to remind you.
Try took something of type T or, well, is
like, a,
a call by name parameter of type T but
for,
for here we can be a little bit more
simple.
So it's f of values of type T, and it
returned something of type try of T.
Okay?
But f of value is of type try of S, so if
I wrap that in another try, the result
type will be.
Try of try of S,
which is one try too much.
So this one is not the expected type, so
this one is wrong.
So hopefully the third answer is right but
who knows maybe you know, I
made a mistake, I am just a human so I can
throw exceptions as well.
Let's look at this guy.
So, what are we going to do?
Well, we're going to do the pattern match,
just like all the other ones.
If the, this is success,
well what we're going to do, we're going
to call f of value.
And but we're going to wrap that in a try
catch.
So in case f of value throws, then we know
that we have to materialize the exception.
And if it doesn't throw, this returns a
value of Try of S and we're good.
And if this was failure then we
immediately propagate to failure.
So the last answer c.
Is the correct answer.