In the previous lesson, we looked at
exceptions as an effect.
In this lesson, we'll look at latency as
an effect.
This week and next week, we were going
to talk about the four essential effects
in programming.
In the previous lesson, we talked about
Try of T.
The effect of exceptions.
In this lesson we will look at
asynchronous computations and the effect
of latency.
And, what we will do is we're, we'll
move here from synchronous computations to
asynchronous computations.
And then in the next week we will look at
computations that return multiple values.
But before that let's quickly revisit what
we discussed in the previous lesson.
In the previous lesson
we defined this super simple adventure
game.
Remember that?
We had two methods; collectCoins that
returned a
list of coins, and buyTreasure that
returned a treasure.
And then we wrote our simple adventure
game.
And then what we did is we said, well,
this was not really
precise, so we turned the return type into
try of list of coins.
And try of treasure
respectively to make clear in the types
that the computations could throw an
exception.
And that was the monad of exceptions, try
of T.
Now let's take this very same adventure
game, and let's massage it.
Let's turn that, let's apply a
homomorphism to this code.
And let's create some networking code.
Look, we just renamed the method.
We renamed adventure to socket.
And, we renamed collect coins to read from
memory.
We renamed by treasure to send to Europe
and we get a simple networking stack.
Isn't that amazing?
But, just like before, things are not as
rosy as it looks.
So if we write the code here that
we create the socket, we read from memory
and then we get
the packet that we got from memory, we
send that to Europe.
When we look at this code in more detail,
there is again much more going than the
code shows.
There are all kinds of, of effects
happening that are not apparent in the
types.
And what we'll do.
Just like we did last time.
We will make this, the types more precise
to expose the
fact that there are side effects happening
when we run this code.
And as I said, the effects that we are
interested in this week is the effect of
latency.
And Peter Norvig has collected a nice
table
here of timings for various operations
that you know,
that things take on a typical PC.
And in this case we were reading stuff
from memory and we're sending
a packet back and forth to Europe and if
you look at the table
you see that reading a you know, I mega
byte for memory takes 250
nanoseconds and sending a packet from the
US to Europe and back, takes.
Wow.
150 million nanoseconds.
So, let's look at our code again.
Here's our code.
Within comments the effects that are
really happening.
So when we read from memory we are
blocked here at this point for 50,000
nanoseconds and
we only continue after, you know, we have
blocked for that time and there is no
exception.
And then when we send the packet to Europe
and
back, we are blocked for 150 million
nanoseconds.
And again only after this thing terminates
successfully
we will move on to the next line.
And this is a very, very heavy effect.
And to make that even more clear, is what
we are going to do.
We are going to translate these
nanoseconds, which really don't
say very much.
At least for me, I don't know what 50,000
nanoseconds is.
We're going to translate nanoseconds into
more human terms, into time units
that we can understand as humans, and then
we can see how bad this really is.
What we're going to do is we're going to
translate one nanosecond into
one second and then we convert everything
to hours, days, and months or years.
Okay.
Let's have a look at Peter Norvig's table.
How that looks like when we do this
translation.
This is quite extreme.
Look at this.
Reading one megabyte from memory, in human
terms, takes three days.
Okay.
What was that,
150,000 nanoseconds?
Well, in human terms that is three days.
And sending a packet from the US to
Europe and back, in human terms, takes
five years.
So if we look at our code again, and we
update the comments.
Instead of nanoseconds, with human terms.
What we will see is that when we read
from memory, it will take us three days.
That's a long time.
So you see, our little hero here starting
to grow a little beard.
And then when you send the packet to
Europe and back, that takes five years.
By that time he, this is an old man.
Okay, so this is an effect that we should
not let, unaccounted for.
We really should make this effect the
effect of latency and explicit in our
types.
Here's another illustration.
How slow computers actually are.
If we would take the same distance that
this
packet takes from the US to Europe and
back.
If we do, would do that ourselves as
humans.
Well, if you search on Wikipedia for
people that have done this,
it will take say, 12 months to walk, walk
from coast to coast.
apparently people have swam across the
Atlantic in three months.
So, we can swim from here to Europe in
three months.
We take three months to go back.
And then 12 months to walk back from the
East Coast to the West Coast.
So, in total, that is two and a half years
that it takes
us to, kind of, you know, take a packet
from here to Europe and back.
Remember that a computer
would take five years and three days.
So humans are twice as fast as computers.
That's good to know.
So what we have seen is that there's this
very,
very expensive effect of actions that take
time and may fail.
The obvious question is, isn't there a
monad for that?
And of course, there's a monad for that.
Which monad?
The Future monad.
Future of T is a monad that handles
exceptions and latencies.
So if you have a computation of type
Future of T It's something that takes care
of the happy path with respect to latency
and of exceptions.
Let's look at how future's defined in the
standard scala library.
Futures are defined in scala.concurrent
And here is the trait for future.
Futures, we will look at the other methods
in a minute.
But this is the main method that's defined
on futures.
Futures are computations that will
complete in the future.
Because again, they are
intended to model computations that have
high latency.
And the way we deal with that is we give
it a
callback that will be called as soon as
the value is available.
So that is what asynchronous programming
typically does.
You work with callbacks.
So I register a callback on the Future
that will be
called as soon as the value of the Future
is available.
And remember that I said, that futures
model
computations that have latency and
exceptions and that becomes
visible here in the fact that in our
callback we get a value of type try of T.
If the computation has failed, this will
be a failure,
if the computation has succeeded it will
be the sub-type success.
Now there's
one thing here that we will be a little
bit implicit about
and this is also defined in scala as an
implicit parameter because futures
run typically on background threads on a
thread pool or something because if
something takes a long time you don't want
to block any main threads.
So you run them on a separate background
thread.
And in order to route the thread pull
through your computation, Scala uses
this implicit parameter that takes an
ExecutionContext.
We will leave this implicit, because to
understand Futures, you
really don't have to worry too much about
the ExecutionContext.
When necessary we will always import the
global execution context to make things
run.
Here are two possible design alternatives,
how futures could have been designed.
So, what we have seen in the previous
slide was that,
the onComplete took a function from Try of
t to unit.
Well, the first thing you are going to do
on a Try
of t is to do a switch statement, to do a
case, right?
You are going to say, if its success, do
this.
If its failed, do that.
So, what you have define is two functions.
So, instead of passing Try of t to unit.
What we can also do is we can pass in two
functions.
The one for success and the one for
failed.
So, this would be totally isomorphic with
the previous design.
And the second alternative would be to
take these two callback functions.
The one for success and
the one for failed and wrap them in their
own trait.
So let's call this trait Observer and an
observer is just something that pairs
these two callbacks.
And I think it's clear that this is
exactly the same.
So you can always take a value that has,
you know, like
a sum type, and replace it by the
functions that you would use
to pattern match on that value.
Now that we know what Futures are, again,
just
for a reference, I repeat the definition
of Future here.
Let's now rewrite our socket trait using
futures.
So instead of returning a regular byte
array we now return a future of byte array
to indicate that reading from memory will
take a long time and may fail.
And then also, send to Europe here now
takes, returns a future of array of byte.
Again, this now in the type shows that
sending
a packet to Europe takes a long, long
time.
Okay?
So whenever you have a computation that
takes a
long time, you should always make it
return a future.
Such that a consumer of your values can
see
in the type that this thing will take a
long time and that they won't block on it.
However, once we rewrite our signatures to
return
futures we also have to adopt our code.
To you know, pass around futures and grab
the values out of the futures.
So, how does our coat look like.
Let's try here to use onComplete directly.
So, we have our socket.
We read from memory and now we get back a
future of an array of byte.
We want to send that array of bytes to
Europe and back.
But, it's wrapped in a Future.
How do we get it out?
Well, what we have is, we have our
onComplete function
so we give it two call backs when it's
success.
In that case, we can send the packet to
Europe and back
and if it fails, well, whatever we do
there we probably propagate the
failure directly.
But, you see here the red
squigglies, and now they're green
squigglies this
is not type correct because on complete
took a function
here, the success function, took a, was a
function here from success to unit.
And the whole onComplete.
The, the whole result
of this is of type unit.
Whereas what we want, is we want it to
be of type future of array of byte.
So that is the result type of this.
But unfortunately, the signature of on
complete doesn't allow
us to return the future as such.
What can we do about that?
Well one thing that we can do is that we
push the rest of the
computation inside the success case here.
So again we read our socket from memory.
And now inside the success branch, we can
continue writing regular code.
So we can now say here's our confirmation,
which of type future of array
of byte, which is the result of sending
the packet to Europe and back.
But this is not really helping us because
now we have to move
all the rest of the computation in here
and you can already see
if there's failures and success this will
become like a very, and I'm
waving my hands on purpose here, this will
be a very spaghetti like code.
And spaghetti
is great as food but not good as code.
We're going to punt on how to write better
code using Futures
for a little bit, because first I want to
show you how you can create Futures, okay?
And how do we create futures?
Well, like with all threads, we look at
the companion object.
And here's the companion object for
futures and there is the apply method.
And the apply method takes a body and
an implicit execution context and returns
a Future.
And this is the context in which the
Future is run.
'Kay?
So, you see that here in the comments.
When you create the future using the
constructor method
here, it creates an asynchronous
computation to which you can
give a call back on which you will be
notified
when the value here is ready, when this
computation terminates.
Just like we drilled down into our little
adventure
game, let's look at a possible
implementation of readFromMemory.
And to readFromMemory, and then send
something
to Europe, well, what should we do?
Well, let's read email messages from
memory.
So what we will do is we'll define a
queue, and in
the queue we will have a list of messages
from the various
instructors of this course to each other
and then we read a message from memory.
We have to serialize it because we needed
a byte array to send the packet.
And, so we then serialize.
We, we grab a serializer and we serialize
the email.
And now we get a byte array.
But we have to turn this into a future so
that, here we recall,
the future constructor.
So now, even though this will take a long
time, what was it again, three days.
Because we call the future.
Factory method here.
This will run on the background thread and
when
you call read from memory, you want block
on that.
You can pass a function to onComplete that
will be called when the value is
actually read from memory.
Well, let's do a little
quiz.
Here is a, our packet.
We use our newly defined function,
readfFromMemory.
So now, instead of just an array of byte,
it returns a future of an array of byte.
And now let's call onSuccess twice
on this packet.
And here, we import the execution context.
So what will happen is this execution
context will be used to run this callback
and this callback but the question is
after this code here.
Say that both on success callbacks have
been called.
How many messages are left in
the email queue?
Take a few minutes to think about that.
What do you think would be the most
natural answer?
All right.
So, I was a little bit mean to you,
because I didn't explain how
this work, but I asked you what do you
think is the most natural answer.
Well, what you expect is that once the
future completes,
every time you call onSuccess, you will
get the same answer so that the future
caches the result, right?
You, the future meant that it's the result
of the computation that may happen later
in time and so what you, what you want is
that this thing really represents this
single value of type array of bytes, okay?
So, if you call onSuccess here, you get
the array of bytes that is read from
memory, and this value of packet and when
you call onSuccess again, you get the same
value.
It's the same with a regular
variable, if you read From a variable
twice you get the
same value if it hasn't been assigned to
in the meantime.
Okay?
So the right answer, how many messages are
left in the e-mail queue, is b.
There were three messages in there.
I've taken one out, even though I call
onSuccess twice,
only one message is taken out, so b is the
correct answer.