In the last lesson, we introduced Futures
as the effect for computations
that have latency and may fail.
Remember that?
Okay.
Now, what we're going to do in this
lesson.
We're going to look at the various
combinators that can be defined on
Futures.
And in particular, we want to know whether
futures are
really a monad, which means that we have
to check if
it has a flatMap.
Let's look at the standard library of
Scala and, you know, grab the trait
definitions.
And guess what.
There is our friend flatMap.
So we are happy, we now know that futures
are monads because there is a flat map.
And there's some other operators here, we
will look
at them in a minute and then there's
another
super type here.
So future of t actually extends Awaitable.
We will talk about a way to also later and
just to remind
you again, this is the companion object
for Futures that would take a
block and return a Future and remember
from the previous
lesson that all this takes an implicit
execution context because we want
to run the Future here in its own separate
thread.
Such that it doesn't block the main
threat.
What we're going to do next is we're going
to
look in a little bit more detail at the
various operators.
This is the code that we were left with
when we introduced futures.
Remember the mess that we arrived at.
Because we were using,
we were trying to use onComplete to chain
together the readFromMemory method call
with the sendToEurope call.
So readFromMemory returned a future of a
byte array
and then we register the onComplete
callback with that future.
If that was successful, we can grab the
packet here.
Send it to Europe, and
then we have the future of byte array for
the confirmation.
But we were stuck inside the success case
here.
And we would end up with our spaghetti
code.
Yep, you remember the mess, I'm pretty
sure about that.
Now, just like with Try of t, flatMap will
lead us through the happy part.
So,
let's rewrite this code using flatMap and
look how beautiful
we get our packets from memory, returns a
future of t and then
we can just flatMap that which gives us
the packet and send it to Europe.
This is of type a future of array of
bytes which exactly is the right type for
flatMap,
so now we get our confirmation which is a
future of array of bytes.
Okay, so here you see again, flatMap is
really the hero of every monad.
flatMap allows us to chain together
computations inside the monad, and it
will allow us to focus on the happy path
flatMap will take care of all the noise.
flatMap is the Dolby for programmers.
Let's drill down into a possible
implementation
of send packet to Europe and back.
Assume that we have an imaginary HTTP
library.
you can pick your owned favorite HTTP
There's many HTTP libraries for Scala
available and
for Java but that's not relevant for this
lesson.
The only thing that we want from our HTTP
library
is that there is a factory method that
takes a URL, that takes a
request, and then asynchronously runs this
HTTP request,
sends it over the network and at some
point gives us back a response.
So we want an asynchronous computation
that given
a request delivers us a response at some
time.
Of course this might fail because we all
know that a network is unreliable and may
fail.
Here's the code that uses this eh, trait
here, this object.
It sends packet to Europe, it returns a
future of array of bytes.
And let's say we send it to a mail server
in Europe with our packet.
We wrap that into a request.
Then we only want to see the requests that
are okay.
And then since we get back a response,
here, but we needed a byte array
we assume that we have some way to turn
the response into a byte array.
Now this code is still not completely
correct
because Too many things can still go
wrong.
This code can
still throw and what we want to do is we
want to turn this code into a robust mail
send program.
So we want to send mail to Europe but we
make sure that it happens.
Let's look at a few possibilities how we
can do that.
Here was our code.
That was not very reliable.
So let's try this attempt here.
What we're going to do, is we're going to
send
our mail both to Europe and to the USA,
okay?
So that's what we want to do.
And that also shows a weakness of our
original implementation because we hard
wired the mail.server in Europe in our
method.
So, in this case here we have abstracted
that out.
So we are now taking the the URL as a
parameter such that we can send mail to
two different mail servers using the same
call without having to repeat the code.
Well you can think, this is great.
I'm sending it to Europe, I'm sending it
to USA.
And then, I zip them together.
And remember the type of zip.
Zip takes two futures and returns a future
of pairs.
So that's what you see here.
Now, we get two confirmations.
We get a future.
That hopefully contains two confirmations.
Is that really safe.
Is this really robust.
Well, unfortunately not.
Because if either one of them fails, the
future here will fail.
So, we have absolutely no guarantee that
sending both
to Europe, and sending to the US will give
us the success that we're after.
Because if either one fails, then the
whole Future will fail.
So actually, this is a worse
implementation, because now
the chance that something goes wrong is
here doubled.
So yeah, I, I, I wouldn't recommend doing
this one.
Fortunately, the Scala designers have
already kind
of, you know, thought about this problem.
And in the library for Futures there are
these two functions here.
Very helpful functions.
The first one is called recover.
And what it takes, it takes a partial
function.
It takes a throwable and returns a t.
And that's one you can use in case your
future has failed.
Yeah, you, you can check the throwable and
then you can deliver a value that is
returned when the computation failed.
And so the result type here is future of
t.
So, recover takes a future of t if
that future failed, you call the partial
function, you
check the exception and then you return
the
value that you want to return as a
recovery.
And the other one, recover with,
is very similar, except, instead of a
future instead
of a t, it returns a future of t.
So what that means is that you can do
another asynchronous computation in case
the first one failed.
You can try another thing that takes a
long
time and then you, both of them return a
future.
We will not look at the definition of
these functions in this lecture.
But you can go and
look at the standard library and their
implementations are fairly simple.
Basically they just use the on complete
and in the error case.
They call the PartialFunction here, okay?
There's our function sent to a URL, and
now let's look at
the first attempt to make this safe.
So, sendToSafe takes a packet and
returns a future of array of bytes, just
like here.
And what we're going to do, is we're first
going to try to send the packets to
Europe.
And if that fails, we use recoverWith to
send the mail to the US.
And again, we use recoverWith because this
one was
future of t and this one is future of t.
So, we have to use recoverWith and not
recover.
But if sending the mail to the US fails.
Well we run out of possibilities and then
we just use the error
message that we got when we failed to send
the message to the USA.
Unfortunately, this method here does not
really do what
we want because our goal was to send the
package
to Europe and really sending it to the US
was a backup strategy.
But what this thing returns, when both
sending to Europe
fails and to the USA fails, is the error
message
that we got from sending the pack, trying
to send
a packet to the USA, which is not what we
want.
What we really want is the error message
when we send it to Europe.
So let's see
if we can make this code even better.
What
we're going to try to do, is we're going
to make this code better in multiple ways.
So, first of all, what we want to do is we
want to get the right error message
so we don't want the message for the USA
error but we want a message from the
Europe error.
But the other thing is that this code also
looks
kind of ugly.
I'm not a big fan of all this case
matching and so on.
I don't like that.
So, I want to write code that looks
better and does better recovery and does
less matching.
We're going to define a new method
fallback on future of t.
That takes a, a call by name other future,
so we don't want to evaluate this thing
eagerly.
We only want to evaluate this thing if our
first future fails and
and if that's that future succeeds, we
want to have its result
but if that future fails, we want to have
the failure of our original future, okay?
Because we were looking here for the
message for Europe.
Now assume that we have this fallback
function.
How would
send to safe look like.
This how it would looks like, and you see
there's
one less case match there, so that's
already an improvement.
So what we're going to do, is we're going
to send the mail to Europe.
If that fails we're going to send that to
the US.
If this fails and that failed, well we get
the error message,
the error for send to Europe.
So then we just use the normal recovery.
But in this case we get the Europe error,
not the
U.S. error, and then we convert that to
the byte array.
So this goes, this exactly what we want
to.
Of course, we're still cheating because we
have not yet defined fallbackTo.
So that will be our next exercise.
Here's the definition of fallbackTo.
It looks beautifully concise.
So let's drill down how it works.
Remember, fallbackTo
was defined on future of t.
And it takes a second future
here, a.
Call by name future called that.
And what we wanted to return is a new
future
but we want to only call that when this
would fail.
Well, we already have part of that because
we have recover with.
So, if this succeeds, recoverWith will do
nothing.
So that's good, so that's
exactly what we want.
Now if this returns failure, in that case,
we
run that.
So only at this point, we will execute
this Future.
And if that fails, well we still, we want
it to return this.
Which was failed, so we get exactly what
we want.
And look it's, it's like a little bit like
poetry, right.
This recover with, that recover with this.
I think this is super beautiful.
You agree?
One of the constructor functions that's
sorely missing
from the Scala standard library is the
following.
What we want to do with Try, is we want it
to
take a block that returned a t, into a Try
of t.
That was a regular definition of Try.
But now that we have Futures, we want to
have something very similar.
What we want to do is we want to take a
Future of T and materialize
all the exceptions that can happen when we
execute the Future of T.
And we want to return a Future of Try of
T.
In this quiz, we're going to look at the
implementation of this factory method.
And here are four possibilities and I'll
give you a few
seconds to look at all of them and pick
the right one.
Let's look at all the possible answers
one-by-one.
Let's look at the first one here.
The first one is starts out quite clever.
It says, let's do f and then register a
callback that
will be called when f completes.
And since the callback takes of, an
argument of try of t.
Now that's what we want to have here as
well why don't we just return the x
immediately?
Unfortunately this was exactly the same
thing that brought us this mess in
the beginning, why we needed flatMap is
because onComplete returns unit.
Okay?
So, returning the Try of t here doesn't
help
us at all because onComplete will just
return unit.
And not Try of
t as we want.
Now let's look at the second case.
Second case says let's do a recover with
where in this
case, we return a Try of t here when it
failed.
Unfortunately, when f succeeded, it won't
return a Try of t.
Because it will just return the normal
Future of t.
So this one is also wrong.
Option c, we map f, with, by wrapping x
into Try of t.
Well this one doesn't work for exactly the
opposite reason.
If f succeeds we happily wrap it into a
Try of t, which is great.
But if it fails we don't wrap it into a
failed.
And therefore, we need to have the last
one, d is the correct answer.
Let me kind of make
sure that we don't see all the wrong
answers.
Here d, what we do, is when f succeeds,
you
know that it's succeeded, so we wrap it
into Success.
And when it fails, we recover by returning
a failed Future.
And this is the right answer.
We're going to end this lesson by looking
at this mysterious trait here
that was the super type of future of t and
this trait
awaitable has two methods, ready and
result that
take a duration.
Now, this trait here,
should be used very carefully because this
trait here.
The awaitable trait allows you to block on
the result of a future.
So, instead of calling complete or you
know, using the methods
on future.
Sometimes, you want to go from future of t
to t.
And this is what awaitable allows
you to do.
So, in particular, result here goes from a
future of t via its super type Awaitable
into a t.
So it allows you to go out of the monad.
And going out of a monad is always
dangerous.
Because if you look at monads there's a
way to go into monads with flat map and
all the operators you see that they always
return the, the, the monad value but
there's usually
no way to go out and if you go out you're
doing something dangerous.
And that's exactly what this trait
Awaitable gives us.
Now some things, sometimes we wan't to be
dangerous, we want to be asynchronous
where possible.
But sometimes we just need to block and so
it's great to have the possibility to
do so if we really need to.
But I really want to emphasize, you should
really never block if it's not necessary.
So use this one with care.
and, you know, maybe this should have had
like a
better name, but it's really dangerous to
call the result here.
But, you know, that's something that you
should
then, whenever you see result, think in
your mind.
Let's see how we can use result to block
on
a Future.
Say that we have read our packet from
memory.
Send it, safely, to Europe and back and
we've gotten the confirmation.
And now we want to print the text of the
confirmation on the standard output.
But, we have to wait until the Future has
terminated.
But we don't
know how to print a Future.
Do you know how to print a string?
So in that case, what we can do is we can
call Await result.
But in order to not block forever.
There's a timeout here,
so what this will do is it will wait for
at most two seconds.
If the future has not terminated within
two seconds, this will throw.
If it terminates within two seconds, it
will give you the value here.
Instead of a future of byte array, it will
be a byte array.
Then we can
turn that to text, and print it on the
standard output.
Now one thing that you may have noticed is
that we've write here two seconds.
Which is quite elegant.
And what is the magic that allows you to
do that.
Well, let's briefly look into that.
If you import scala.language.postfixOps
and you have the duration object in scope.
The duration
object has a constructor method that takes
a length and
a time unit and thanks to the post fix
operators.
You are able to write the constructor
function here
in post fix notation.
So, you can just write you know, if you
want to define five years which is 1826
minutes.
You can write this beautifully here using
postfix notation.