We've seen quite a few examples of using
futures but what we want to do in this
lesson is to write code that uses futures
in slightly more interesting ways.
So not just using flat map.
But, using more interesting ways.
We want to write real programs on
computations that return Futures.
Here's our familiar example of using
Futures to read
from memory and send a packet to Europe
and back.
And, in this case, we're using flatMap to
compose
the readFromMemory call with the send to
Europe call.
Of course we know that we can write this
using for-comprehensions as follows.
So we read from memory and we send the
packet.
But now imagine that we want to do
something slightly more complicated.
that we want to do something that involves
control flow.
In that case.
Loads, flatmap and comprehensions are not
the most convenient tools.
And since we want to be real functional
programmers, we're going to look
at some more power tools that we can use
to write codes involving futures.
The challenge that we're giving ourselves
is to implement the call on method.
This method takes a, an integer and a,
call
by name future, a lazy, a block, a lazy
future and returns a future.
And what we want to do is we want to retry
this computation at most m times.
So, as soon as it succeeds, we want to
return it.
But otherwise we want to keep trying, keep
trying, up to n times.
And since we want to rerun the future
every time.
Because of course, if we would not do
that, remember the
future, once it's has completed it will
always return the same result.
We have to pass it here.
As a call by name parameter.
So this
is super important.
If you would not do this then the future
would
be eagerly evaluated and you would always
get the same result.
So, what we want to do is to run this
computation at most n times.
How do we do that?
Well, here's a way to use recursion.
What we do is, we just recurse over the
number of times.
If we have zero times left, well, then we
obviously have failed.
So we return a Future that is failed, with
an exception.
Sorry we couldn't you know, make this
thing succeed.
Otherwise, we use our friend, fallbackTo.
We execute
the Future, and only if it fails, we call
retry recursively.
And notice that.
Because of the laziness here, because of
the call by name, everything works out.
Fallback took also a call by name
parameter so it only evaluates its
argument if
this one failed, and now we call retry
again with a call by name parameter.
So all the laziness exactly works out.
Now, some guy called Erik Meijer once said
that recursion
is the GOTO of Functional Programming.
And, guess what we are doing here?
We are using recursion.
And that guy Erik Meijer happens to be me.
So I really am not allowed
to write recursion programs, because
otherwise I would contradict myself.
So,
let's see if we can write this without
recursion.
As true functional programmers, we all
know that instead of recursion, we
should use fold.
Fold right, fold left or any of the
variations of fold.
I found it, I had a tip from Richard Bird.
This is the real hero of list programming.
And he has a nice tip to remember what
fold left and fold right means.
If you look at the wind, if you say, today
there's
a northern wind, it means that the wind
comes from the north.
And this is the same with fold left and
fold right.
The fold right comes from the right.
So here you see the arrow.
Fold right comes from the right.
And conversely, fold left comes from the
left.
So if we have a list a, b, c.
And we
fold right with a seat value and a
function.
We come from the right.
So we start the seat value.
Then we take the last value of the list,
we apply the function.
Then we take b, apply the function and
finally we apply a.
So here you see fold right comes from
right to left.
Starting with the seat, applying f.
To each element in the list.
And here you see fold left coming from the
other side.
Starting with the seat and applying the
function to each subsequent element.
Alright, so what we're going to do, is
we're going to now
try to write our retry function using fold
left and fold right.
This is what we're going to do.
So let's look at here, this is the trick
that we're going
to do.
Say that we want to do retry three of our
future block.
What we want to do is we want to unfold
that into the following quote.
So we want to do failed recoverWith.
The first copy of the block.
Recover with second.
Recover with third.
And as you see.
This is a fold
left because we are starting on the left
and you see that the brackets are like
this.
So how do we write this as a fold left?
Well first of all, we need to create a
list with three copies of the block
and we need to make sure that those
futures here are not evaluated.
So we, we create a list of, alright well
we shouldn't a create of three copies.
We,
as we should create a list of.
Number of times.
So we create a list of number of times,
and
then we map that, the block over that, so
now
we have a nice list with copies of the
block,
and then we do our foldLeft here with the
recoverWith.
to run over that, and you will see when
you
execute this, when you unfold this, it
will actually unfold
exactly into this.
Now, let's try to do that with the
foldRight, what we
want to do here, is we want to achieve the
full
[INAUDIBLE].
In this case, we want to start on the
right.
And then, build up our code like this.
We want to have failed, or but, we want to
build
it from the right to the left as you see
the braces.
But really we're reading the code from
left to right so.
We want to have block one and then if that
fails, we want to fall back to the second
try.
If that fails, we want to fall back to the
third try, et cetera.
And then, of course, in general, number of
times.
So here we do the same thing, we create
the list, we map the block over it.
Being careful that the block get not
executed.
And then we do the fold right over here.
Now notice that in this case, we start
with a seat that is a function,
okay?
And whenever we now
Combine the two, so this is our
accumulator and this the block.
The accumulator is a function.
It's a function from unit to future.
And what do we do?
Well we do the fallback and in this case
since the fallback here is in, inside A, a
block.
We have to reduce the type here
from a unit to future to a future but that
gets
captured in the fall back block so that's
all lazy just lazy enough.
So this code is quite subtle and I advice
you to kind of go grab a cup
of coffee or a pot of tea or you know a
few snacks.
And study this code at your own time and
really
convince yourself that when you execute
this, that the result is this.
The previous two attempts to use fold left
and fold right were not.
I think, our best examples of writing
code.
If you're a real great programmer, you
should write baby code.
You should never write code
to where you have to think very, very long
To do something simple.
And writing this retry with fold left or,
or fold right.
I mean, it required us to think about that
for a long time where it should be really
simple.
You intuitively feel that you should be
very simple.
But instead we came up with this.
You know, really complicated solution.
And that's not good.
So remember, great programmers write baby
code.
And what we try to do there was definitely
not baby code.
So we were really not good programmers.
And one way to write good code, or baby
code, is to go in the opposite direction.
So.
Instead of making effects, explicit.
We want to make effects, implicit.
Because sometimes that makes life more
makes
life easier.
And, so what we are trying to do is we are
going to see if we can make this effect of
latency our future.
If we can make that implicit, okay?
So, we want to take
the function of type T to future of S, and
we really
want to treat that as if we had a function
from T to try of S.
Or, even better, we want to turn that into
function of
type T to S.
So, I should be careful there what I say.
We're not going to turn that into a
function from T to S.
But we want to hide the effects.
We want to say, yeah we know that we are
in the context where the
effect is future.
So I don't want to deal with it, I want to
have that implicit.
So again.
We say one thing but we really want
another thing.
Is this possible?
It turns out that this is in-fact
possible.
And to do this, you have to import some
scala magics.
So you import the scala.async.Async.
type,
and what you get in that case, is two
functions.
One is here, the async, which takes a
body, a call by name block.
And an implicit ExecutionContext, and it
returns a Future of T.
So think of this as just another.
Factory methods for future.
Remember we had the factory method future
that also
took a called by name body and then
execution context and returned a future.
So, this is very similar.
The big difference is that for async is
that if you are inside an async block.
You can use this function here await, that
turns a future into a t.
And we saw before, when you do that, you
were blocking.
But in this case, it does that without
blocking.
And that's the magic of the async await.
So what this does is there's a, is a
magic compiler transformation that allows
you to wait, without blocking.
So, it allows you to kind of treat a
future as a regular value without
blocking, but the
great thing is that you can now write
regular control flow.
Inside this async block and now you can
write super, super natural code.
And lets have a look how are retry
function will look using this async await
feature.
There's a little bit of small print
because as
I said, it relies on some, on compiler
magic.
And the main.
restriction is that you cannot use await
inside a try/catch block.
Which means that if a, if a future can
fail, we have to use our
try constructor that takes a future of t
into a future of try of t.
To make sure that there's no exceptions,
but that the exceptions are materialized.
And that's also the reason that I gave you
this exercise a
few lessons ago.
Okay, that was exactly such that we could
then use async await and use that
constructor function for try.
Here's how we can write our retry function
using the magic of async
await.
What we do, here is our signature,
we get the number of times that we want to
retry, and our block of futures.
And, we want to return a future.
How do we do that?
Well, we enter the async block, and inside
here we can now write
regular control flow.
And the way we do it is like any normal
programmer would do it.
We declare a variable, we start with the
result to be failure because we might not
be
able to you know, execute the block
without
failing, and then we do a simple loop
here.
As long as we have not gotten success, and
we still have tries left, we await.
The result of the block.
And we increase
the counter and we loop here.
But remember the small print, that you
could not await in, with a Try Catch.
So what we have to do here is we have to
materialize the exceptions in our Future,
by using the constructor function that we
did a few lessons ago.
So the constructor function that took a
Future of
T and returned a Future of Try of T.
This is what I would call baby code,
right?
Everybody can understand this code and
it's obviously correct.
And the nice thing is that even though it
uses mutable state inside, on the outside.
It's purely functional, right?
It gives you a number of times.
It gives you a called by name future.
And it will retry this at most number of
times.
But thanks to the magic of
async, you can write the code in the
most natural way and sometime writing
imperative control flow.
Is the most natural way.
Let's right.
Some other examples using await.
Here's how you would write filter using
await.
So, filter as the return of future.
So, whenever you have a function that
needs to return a future.
Think
about.
If you can use async, okay?
Because async is an extremely powerful way
to create futures.
Here is how we do filter.
Filter is defined on future of t and we
need to apply a
predicate from t to Boolean.
So we need to go from future of t to t.
How can
we do that?
Well using await.
So we just await ourselves, future of T.
Now this guy's of type T.
Then we check the predicate.
If the predicate halts we return, the
value.
And if the predicate does not halt we, we
throw an exception.
Because there is no value and the future.
Well, the way we represent the empty
future is by exception.
Okay?
So this I believe is the most natural way
you can write filter.
As a quiz, we will write flatMap using
async await.
So, just remind us again, what is the type
of flatMap?
Well, flatMap was defined on type Future
of T.
It takes a function from T to Future of S.
And it has to return a Future of S.
Here are four possibilities.
Take your time, pick the right one, and
then we will discuss this after a few
seconds.
Okay.
Maybe your, the impression that you get is
that this looks a little bit like
[UNKNOWN].
Async, await, curlies.
So let's use our power tool of checking
the types.
If the types don't work, the function is
definitely wrong.
So let's go and look at the types for each
of those.
First of all, the this, is of type future
of t.
And f takes a t.
So here this can
never be right because there, it's a type
error here.
F expects a t, we give it a future of t
so, that's wrong.
Same here.
We cannot call f on this even though we do
it inside an async so this guy goes away
as well.
This one looks a little bit better.
So what we do here
is we await this so now the result of that
expression is of type T.
Remember, await strips off a level of
future we call f, which is great so now we
get the future of S.
But, now if we do this in an async, the
result type of this thing will be future
of future
of t.
Because, if we remember correctly, the
async takes a value of type t.
And returns that into a type of future of
t.
so, this run is also not correct.
So now that means,
hopefully that the last option here d is
correct.
It looks very elegant so let's check if
it's
type checks and let's convince ourselves
that it actually works.
This is of type future of t, when we await
this, we get a value of type t.
We call f.
Which gives us something of type
future of s, which we await, which gives
us something of type s, and the async
turns that into a future of s.
So it's type correct, but it's also
exactly.
What flatMap needs to do, right?
Because the async awaits, will propagate
all the exceptions for us.
So, we only have to concentrate on the
happy part.
But unlike flatMap.
Here, we can just write regular control
flow because we have eliminated the
effect.
You know, temporarily by entering this
async block and then using await.
So this is the power of async await, that
we can write just regular code where we
use
the await to kind of, you know, get the f,
the, the T out of the future like this.
How would filter look like, without using
await?
If you go to the scala implement the, the
implementation of future on github.
Then you will see this code, or if you
download
the jar with the source code, you will see
this code.
So, and this code doesn't look too
complicated but
not nearly as elegant as the
implementation using await.
And one thing that this code uses is this
type future.
future, this type Promise here.
And that will be the topic of our next
lesson.