We ended the last lesson with a promise
that we would talk about promises.
So, here we're going to going to fulfill
that promise.
Let's remind ourselves of the
implementation of filter without await.
And that was the implementation where we
first discovered.
This new type Promise that we're going to
talk about in this lesson.
Let's leave this code for now, because the
first thing before we
can understand this code, we first have to
understand what Promise really is.
Here's the definition
of the Promise trait.
The promise trait has a couple of methods
but the three most important ones are the
ones that are here on the slide.
First of all a promise contains a future,
and then a promise has two methods,
complete, two variations of complete.
That take a try, and
then the only difference here is that one
returns a unit and then one returns a
Boolean.
Now when you have a promise, when you
create a promise.
You can take a future out of the promise.
So, if I take the future out of the
promise, I get a future.
And this future will be notified.
It's call back will be called whenever you
call complete
on the promise.
So think of a promise as a mailbox.
So the mail man comes in, puts a value in
the mailbox, turns up the flag, which is
now calling
the call back and then, you know, you get
your
mail delivered here in the uncompleted
call backs of the future.
So a Promise, again, is very much like a
mail box.
You can take a future out
of the Promise, then you know that
you will be called whenever the future
completes.
So that value that you pass into the
complete will
be the value that will be passed into the
callback.
Now, you may ask yourself, why are there
two methods here?
Complete and tryComplete.
Remember, a few lessons ago,
when we called on completed twice on the
same future.
we said that you would always get the same
value.
So once a future is completed.
It contains a single value and whenever
you call
the call back that's the value that you
get.
And that is here kind of, you know, shown
in this type when
you complete and you try to complete again
and the future is already completed,
this one will throw.
Or otherwise you can do tryComplete.
And if it's already completed, this one
returns false.
So the fact that a future's item potent is
also reflected in the fact that
really, you can only call complete once.
You can only complete a promise once.
Or you can try to complete it, but if it's
already
is completed, you're returned false.
In this case.
Here's an example of trying to complete a
single Promise twice.
And, in this case, we're going to use
concurrency.
And I'm going to import here the standard
ExecutionContext.
And I'm going to let two threads race.
To complete
the Promise.
So I define, we define a Promise here.
And then we have two Futures, Future left
and Future right.
And what we're going to do is we're going
to
say, if left completes, we're going to
complete the promise.
And if right completes, we're going to try
to complete the Promise.
And since the onComplete runs on the
context here.
The two tracks here will compete and the
first one that is able to complete a
promise will set the value of the future
that is returned from this promise here.
Okay, so this was a simple race between
two futures.
The first future that completes will win.
Now in the exercises for this lecture, you
will have to write
a couple of other operators on futures
just like this race one.
You may ask yourself, is this race
combinator here useful at all?
Well it actually is because suppose that
one of the futures is
a computation that you want to do but you
don't want to wait
for that computation all the time, so what
you can do is you
can have a second computation that is like
a time out that will.
First complete or maybe you know, complete
ahead of the other one.
And so that you're not waiting forever on
this computation.
Another example of using race is when we
want to do send email.
Remember that we tried to use zip.
But zip would fail if you know, either of
them would fail.
Well in this case we can use race to try
to do sent email to Europe and to the US.
And then the one that fails or completes
fastest will win.
In the rest of the slides, we'll use two
simple helper functions that are defined
in the promise trait.
and that those are just simple wrappers on
the success and the fail constructors for
try.
So we can just call success with a value
and failure with
a throwable so we don't have to kind of
call the constructor explicitly.
Very simple methods but we will use them
as we're going forward.
Let's look if we can understand now how
filter is defined using promises.
Remember that filter was defined on a
future of t, it takes a
predicate from t to bool, and it has to
return another future of t.
The way we do it, is we first allocate a
promise.
That's the promise whose future we're
going to return here.
And that we're going to complete, once the
future here completes.
So, what we're going to do, is we're going
to install a callback on this when.
That fails.
Well, in this case, our predicate, our
filter will
fail, so we just complete the promise with
a failure.
In case
the future this will succeed with some
value x.
We have to check whether the predicate
holds.
If the predicate holds, we will complete
the promise with success.
So, now that value will be propagated to
the future.
So, whoever is listening to the future
will receive the value.
That's as intended.
When the predicate does not hold, we will
complete the promise
with a failure, namely that there is no
such exception.
So anybody waiting on the future will be
notified that the filter returned an empty
future.
When we try to make our send a package
to Europe robust, we, our first attempt
used zip.
And remember that I said, that zip would
not
work because if either of the futures
would fail.
The whole result of zip would fail.
And, now we can look, if that was
actually true, by looking at the
implementation of zip.
Just for fun, I'm using
a slightly different signature than the
zip
as it's defined in the standard library.
To zip in the standard library returns a
future of a pair of t and s.
But what I'm going to do instead, I'm
going to pass in a function here that
takes the results of the, this, and the
future debt.
In case both of them have succeeded.
And then it computes
the R.
And it returns a future of R.
And you can easily define the regular zip
function.
By just passing here the constructor for
[UNKNOWN],
okay?
But this is a slightly more general
signature.
The pattern for zip is very similar to the
pattern for filter.
We allocate a promise and we hand out the
future corresponding to that promise.
And then the rest of the implementation is
also pretty straightforward.
We install a call back on this, in case
this
completes with failure.
Well, we complete the promise with
failure.
So, we already see that this happened in
the email.
If one of the sending messages failed, the
whole thing fails.
If, onComplete succeeds with a value x, in
that case, we install a handler on that.
And when that succeeds, with y.
Then we call our function f, and send that
on the Promise.
But, if that failed, then we fail the
Promise, okay?
So really, this code is pretty
straightforward.
But what I don't like about it, is that
there's all this case distinctions here.
Let's see if we can remove
that using async await.
Here is zip defined using async await.
And you see that it looks beautifully
short.
So, what we do is again, we define an
async block.
And then we really do what we were
kind of encoding in the previous
implementation of zip.
Because what we said is we have to await
this, and we
have to await that.
And if both of them succeeded, if both of
them returned
a value, a value of type t, a value of
type s.
We.
Called a function f and re-, return this,
that as a future.
So, here you see that, really the code
that we write here
captures the essence and all this pattern
matching and all that noise
is taken care of by the compiler.
And that's what a high-level language
should do.
As programmers, we should be able to focus
on the essence.
This is the essence of the algorithm.
And then all the rest is take care by the
infrastructure of the language.
And I think the async await is a extremely
powerful addition to the Scala language.
We are going to end this sequence of
lessons by
implementing a slightly more complicated
operation on
future of t.
And in particular we are going to
implement the function sequence that takes
a list of futures.
Into a future of lists.
And this function,
you will see this for many, many monads,
so you can do this the same
thing if you have a list of tries, you
turn that into a try of lists.
And for many, many monads, this function
can be defined.
And in this case, we will do it for our
future time.
And the simplest implementation, really is
with async
here, we again, we learned async block and
now we can write a regular control fill.
So what we do is we, copy our list.
Into a mutable variable.
We create a list buffer, that holds the
result values because
we have to return a future that has a
list, since
we are in an async block, really what we
have to
return is a list because the async will
turn that into
a future.
So, we can already see that this will be
our return value.
And what we'll do is we will just walk
through the input list.
And await all the values in the input
list.
Add them to the result list.
And then, at the end, return the result.
So again, this is baby code,
right?
This is how anybody can imagine that this
works.
I get a list of futures.
I have to produce a list of results.
What do I do?
I allocate a new list.
I walk to the import list.
Awaiting every future in it and then
return the result.
And I do that inside an async block which
allowed me to forget about the fact that
I was actually in the future monad.
It made the future monad implicit.
Just to compare and contrast this.
Let's look at the implementation that uses
promises explicitly.
Let's compare and contrast our
implementation of sequence
using async await, with the old-fashioned
implementation using promises.
And as real functional programmers, since
we have a list of.
Futures here, as our input.
We will, we are going to use a foldRight.
But the algorithm will be very similar to
what we did with the async await.
And again, what you, what, if you think
about this a little more.
You will see that the async await allows
us to focus on the essence whereas here
we have encode things with you know
promises and
folds and, and so on and even here, four
comprehensions.
So this, this is quite hairy code.
So let's focus, and drill down into this.
So, the first thing we do.
We are going to do a, a fold right and we
are going to fold right with a future.
Okay?
So we are going to start with a future
that contains the empty list.
So the way we do that is we have our, we
start here with a promise and then we
succeeds the promise with the empty list.
And that's the seat.
The future of that is the seat that we're
going to use in our foldRight.
And, as we're folding, from the right, our
accumulator is a future, okay?
And it's a future of lists.
So this guy here is of type Future.
Of
list, of t.
And the values in our list were of type,
future of t.
So now we have in our hand a.
Oh, well I should've called that future.
But you know, you can get that as f,
future.
Future of list of T and a future of T.
So, I have both the future with the list
that comes from the right.
And what we're going to do, is we're
using a four comprehension here to first
get the.
Value out
of the future here so we say x from f.
And then the accumulator was a future of
list so we
get, you know, use the four comprehensions
to get the list
out of that so now if you look at the
types
this has type t and this has type list of
t.
And then we yield a new value of type list
of t by counting the value on top of this
thing.
And then we see that the result of this
guy should be of type, future of list of
t.
For the fold right to be right.
So lets check if that's the case.
That's correct, right?
Because this a list of t and the result of
a for comprehension
is a future, of list, of t.
Okay?
So, as you can see.
This is quite, quite hairy code but on the
other hand.
It is doing essentially the same as our
previous solution.
So, we are working to the list and we are
going to be awaiting all the futures in,
in, in this list and the only trick is
that in this
case, we had to do this kind of double
waiting because our accumulator.
We have to make this everything
asynchronous, here.
This ends our first lecture.
What we have seen in this first lecture
is synchronous and asynchronous
computations that return one
result.
We have looked in depth at the try monad,
the monad of computations that can fail.
And we
looked in depth at the future monad, the
monad
of computations that have latency, that
take a long time and that can fail.
And we also have seen that, computations
that's returned a try or t are blocking.
So, they blocked the main threat where the
computations that return a future t were
asynchronous, okay?
And they were based on the call backs.
In the next, lecture we will switch
attention to computations that return many
values.
And just like with one values we have
synchronous and asynchronous computations.
When we have computations that return
multiple values, we have the same.
We will first look at iterables, which
are computations that return many values
synchronously
by blocking.
And then we will generalize that
to asynchronous computations that return
multiple values.
And for that, we will introduce a new
type, called Observable.
So see you next time.