In the previous lectures, we talked about
how futures help us
to write code that is asynchronous, and
that deals with latency.
Futures however, return only a single
result.
What we're going to do now, is we're going
to turn futures into observables.
Which are asynchronous streams of data,
so collections that asynchronously produce
their values.
Do you remember our little diagram of the
four essential effects in programming?
What we've done in the previous lectures
is focus on this side.
We looked at computations that returned
one value.
Both synchronously and asynchronously.
What we're going to do in these lectures,
in
the coming lectures, is we're going to
look at
computations that return multiple values.
Either synchronously or asynchronously.
And if it's synchronously, it's iterable.
And our new type that we'll introduce is
observable.
But before we go there, let's first look a
little bit more in depth at futures and
tries.
Because there's some interesting things
that we have to discover there still.
In particular what we're going to show is
that future of t and try of t are dual.
Oh, that sounds really, really difficult
and complicated.
But actually it's a lot of fun.
But first, let's look again at the
definition of our future of t trait.
Future of t had one method, onComplete,
which takes a function from try of t to u.
And implicit execution context, on which
the work is run, and it returns unit.
And this function here, this callback
function,
receives this single value when the future
completes.
Now this is all in your traits, and
definitions, and whatever.
So if you really simplify this type, what
we get is a function that takes a function
from try of t for u, and returns unit.
And for simplicity, we will substitute
unit for u there.
So, a future is really nothing more
than a function, that takes a callback
from try of t to unit, and returns unit.
So that's really the essence of a future,
is this simple type.
Now, let's do some massaging on this type.
We're going
to kind of, you know, squeeze it and turn
it into something different.
The first thing we're going to do is we're
going to flip the arrows.
So here's the function that we created,
that captured the essence of all the
futures.
What we're going to do now is we're going
to turn the arrows around.
What will happen now, is that this unit
here that's
the result, becomes the argument, and that
try becomes the result.
And the same here, we take this
unit and instead of being the result of
this function, it becomes the argument of
the function.
So, you see this here?
This goes there, and that goes there.
Good, so we have just dropped the arrows,
and now this signature looks a little bit
unusual.
Because typically instead of taking unit,
which is a type that
has a single value, as a parameter, we do
use a function
that takes no parameters.
And that's how we write that.
Okay, so we just rewrite this a little
bit, and now we get the fault line
function.
We can even simplify this further, by
noticing
that the future only returned a single
value.
Remember, when we call onComplete multiple
times on the future,
we know that the future always returns the
same value.
Saying that, future is item potent.
And the, in this case we can use that to
simplify this expression even further.
Because the arrow here, is only there to
allow side effects and the same for here.
But if the try here is always the same
value, then we don't
need these extra tongues here in front, so
we can represent it immediately
by this try.
What did we arrive at?
Well, here we have our asynchronous
function, that returns a future.
And how do we communicate by that?
By passing a callback, from try to t to
unit, to this future.
Or we can do a synchronous method.
Which returns a try of t, and blocks until
the result has been returned.
So we see here the difference between an
asynchronous call that returns a future.
Where we get the result by passing a
callback.
Or we do a synchronous goal where we have
to block until we get the value.
But they are very, very closely related.
Because what we did is we reversed the
arrows, and then we simplified a little
bit.
And what that means is that future of t
and try of t are dual.
Now, if you want to know more about
duality and so
on, you have to learn a little bit of
category theory.
If you go to Wikipedia, for example, and
you look
up duality, you can find a lot of
information there.
but this course is about programming, not
about category theory.
So, we'll leave it by this statement.
What we have seen, is that try of t, and
future of t, are each other duals.
And that one is used for an asynchronous
computation,
and the other one is used for a
synchronous computation.
What we're going to try now is to see
whether we
can play the same trick, for computations
that return multiple results.
But before we do that, let's revisit our
old friend iterable again.
Here is the trait definition for iterable.
Iterable consists of two types.
There's iterable, that has the single
method iterator.
And the Iterator is the one that has the
next method that gives the next value in
the stream.
And the Boolean has next, that tells you
when the stream still has more elements or
not.
Here's our little action hero again.
The action hero wants to get coins.
And in this case the coins are in an
Iterable collection.
So, how does our little friend here get
the coins out of the collection?
Well, the first thing he does, is he calls
iterator.
If you call iterator on an Iterable of
coins, you get an Iterator of coins.
And then he does
while has next, he calls the next coins.
Notice he's pulling the values out of this
iterator.
Every time you call next, you have your
block in, until the next coin comes out.
If we look further in the search codes of
iterable, we
see that it has a lot of interesting
methods defined on it.
Our good friend filter, map, take, et
cetera.
But the most important one is flat map.
Flat map takes an Iterable,
and a function that, for each element in
the Iterable, returns another iterable.
And then flattens all these streams into a
result stream of type iterable of b.
Another way of saying this is that
iterable is a monad.
But we all know that that was true
already, so that's nothing new.
Nothing new.
In order to talk nicely about collections,
we're going to use so called marble
diagrams.
Marble diagrams show the values of a
collection like this on an arrow.
So in this case, we have a collection of
coins.
And we have a function that turns coins
into diamonds.
And when we map that function over the
input
collection of coins, we get an output
collection of diamonds.
And in the rest
of the lectures, we will dr, keep drawing
these kind of marble
diagrams, because they give a very concise
way of how these operators work.
You can see, you know, this is like a
sample input, and you can see the sample
output.
So they are very, very beautiful to look
at.
Since we were interested in asynchronous
computations,
it's good to remind us of the times,
you know, things take on a typical PC,
that we converted on a human scale.
These were the times that Peter Norvig
collected.
And what we're gong to do is, we're going
to
write some code using Iterables to read
values from a disk.
And what we will see then, is that it's
really not such a good
idea to use iterables to do, kind of a,
computations that take a long time.
Here's the sample code.
If we look in the standard library, the
standard scala library.
There's a trait source that has a method
from file, that takes a path.
And on that you can call get lines, and
which returns an iterator of strengths.
Say that we read all the lines from our
attempt directory, attempt file.
And now we for looping over this
number of lines.
But notice that we're reading the lines
from disk.
And, you know, say that each line is, you
know, a few hundred k.
Which typically means you know, in with
these numbers, that it would
take two weeks in human time to get a line
from disk.
So this is really not a very smart way to
read stuff from disk.
Instead what we need to do.
Just like we did
with futures, we have to start doing
asynchronous io.
In order to get to this, we will do
the same dualization trick that we used
for futures.
Now let's look at our iterable and
iterator traits.
And let's convert them into their duals.
And we are going to take exactly the same
steps as we did with futures.
So the first thing we're going to do to
turn this
pull model into a push model, is to boil
Iterable and Iterator
down to their essence.
So, instead of having threads, we will
just describe them using functions.
In order to boil down iterable and
iterator
to their essence we look at the signature.
So the iterator method takes no arguments,
and returns an iterator.
So what we do is we write here a function
that
takes no arguments, and returns the boiled
down version of iterator.
So what is an iterator?
Well, it something that either has a
Boolean or a t.
Which we really can model with an option
of t.
Okay, so if you, you know, instead of
having these two functions, what you
can do is you can just have a function
that returns an option of t.
And now, we have to even be a little bit
more careful.
Because next can also throw an exception,
if has next returns false.
So, really what we should do is that an
iterator corresponds to a function
and has no arguments.
And returns a try of an option of t.
Okay, and that corresponds to the fact
that these methods can
either throw, or return a t, or return
nothing.
So, you see that the three choices here
are exactly corresponding
with the values that these two functions
here can produce.
This type here is quite complicated,
right?
This is like a composition of two types
that already are some types of two things.
So this is not as simple as I want it to
be.
So let's make this even simpler.
And the way we're going to do that, is
instead
of having a value of try of option of t.
We're going to represent this value, by
the callback functions that you would give
when you better match on a value of this
type.
Before however we're going to simplify the
type, we still have to flip the arrows.
Remember that?
We were going to play the magic
dualization trick.
So here's our type that we boil down for
iterable iterator.
The first thing we're going to do is we're
going to flip the arrows.
And as we flip the arrows, a function that
takes no argument becomes a function that
returns unit.
But you see here, we just reversed the
arrows,
just like we did when we were massaging
future.
Now if we look at this type here, that
doesn't really look simple enough to me.
Because this try of option of t, it's a
composition of two types that are already
pretty complicated themselves.
So what I'm going to do, is I'm going to
replace this type by the
set of functions that I need to pass, when
I'm pattern matching on that type.
And what do I need to do, when I pattern
matching on that type?
Well, there's three possibilities.
The first thing is that the inner value is
an exception.
So I have to pass in a function from
throwable to unit.
If it was not an exception,
then the result I get, is the success of
an option of t.
Which means that I have to pass two
functions.
One in case there is a value, and one in
case there was not a value.
So what we ended up with after simplifying
iterable and iterator,
reversing the arrows, and then simplifying
this, is the following type.
It's a type that takes three callbacks and
returns unit.
Now the next step that we're going to do,
is we're going to unsimplify this.
We're going to complexify this.
And instead of you know, all these
functions, we're going
to define a few traits that capture the
essence of this.
So we're going to unboil these functions.
And here on the right, you see the result
of you know,
complexifying these types.
The first thing that we have is we have a
new trait observable.
The observable is the thing that
corresponds to a trait
that takes these three as an argument, and
these guys here become the observer.
And you see that subscribe takes an
observer and returns unit.
Well, instead of unit, we are making it
slightly more complicated, and
we return a subscription.
What is the subscription?
Well, unlike futures where we didn't have
a notion of cancellation.
What we want to do when we have a stream,
the stream can be infinite, it can return
many, many results.
And what we want to do is if we pass a
call, a set of callbacks
to the stream to receive the values.
At some point we may want to signal to the
producer, that we're not interested in
receiving any more values.
And so, when you pass your observer to an
observable, you get back a subscription.
And when you go unsubscribe on the
subscription, you tell
the producer that you're not interested in
receiving any more values.
But don't worry.
We will have a whole lesson
to talk about subscriptions.
Let's put iterable, iterator,
and observable, observer, next to each
other.
And you see that they really look very,
very similar, except that things are
swapped around.
Alright.
I think this is quite remarkable.
What we did is we showed that try and
future, are duals.
And the one is synchronous, and the one is
asynchronous.
And then what we did is we did
exactly the same exercise, this
dualization scheme, on iterables.
And then we came up with this notion of
observables.
That's quite nice.
Now, what we want to do is let's put
futures and
observables side by side, and see how they
are related.
Because here it says that this one
is a asynchronous computation that returns
one result.
And observables are asynchronous
computations that return multiple results.
But that must mean that, in the types,
when
we boil the, the types back down to their
essence.
We must be able to see where the
difference between and, one
and many lies.
Okay.
Here are our two types, observable.
We have, you know,
moved back to the try of option of t, and
returns unit.
And let's ignore for now the subscription.
And if we look at future,
future was a try of t to unit to unit.
And the reason
I don't want to kind of, you know, look at
the
subscription here, is because I'm not
interested in the cancellation part.
I'm really interested in the one and many
part.
And that's exactly what you see in the
difference of the type.
When you have a future, it returns only a
single value and that
single value, well it's either a value or
ec, there can an exception.
But in an observable you can have multiple
values.
Or you can have an exception.
So the exception part is still the same,
but to be able to receive multiple values,
you have to have a way to also indicate
that there will be no more values.
And that's where the option of t comes in.
So here you see that, because there's no
option, the only
thing really that you can do, is to
produce a single value.
But, once you have a try of an option of
t, then you have the ability to have
multiple values.
Because I can signal whether there's an
error, or whether this stream
has terminated, or whether there's a
regular value that is produced next.
Now, there was one thing that we also
haven't talked about yet, is that in
futures,
we had this notion of execution context.
So, whenever we had a body of a future, it
would run in a certain execution context.
How does this, you know, work with
observables?
Because observables are asynchronous, so
there must be
some way of doing things concurrently
there as well.
And that's exactly true.
Except that in observables, just because
there's also many results,
we cannot have simple execution context.
But we need something slightly more
complicated, and that's a scheduler.
And we will have a whole lesson, or two
lessons actually, devoted to schedulers.
but for now, in the next few lessons,
we will really not talk much about
schedulers.
We don't need to.
Well, that was more than enough theory and
category theory and so on.
Let's look at some real code here.
Let's look at some simple examples of
observables.
The easiest way to think about an
asynchronous stream, is a clock or time.
Or, you know, it's a timer.
In, in this case, we have the interval
function,
onobservable, that takes a duration.
Look how beautiful this is in Scala with
postfix notation.
So this guy says, create an observable
stream, that
turns a long every single second.
And since observables
have the same operators as any other
collection, we can then take that
stream of ticks.
And we can filter it and only keep the
even ones.
And then we can do even fancy things, like
buffering the things by
chopping up that stream in slices of two,
where we shift by one.
So this is like slices of two, shifted by
one.
And then, in the end, we subscribe to this
stream and we print them out.
Let's see how this works.
And here you see I can, you should never
believe me when I
say that this is runnable code because
there's a kind of a typo here.
But believe me, this is actually runnable
code.
Let's see what it does.
And as I promised, we're going to use
marble diagrams to visualize how
our streams look like.
Our tick stream is type observable of long
will tick, it will tick one second before
It produces the first tick.
And then another second to produce the
second tick, and another second.
So this is every time there's one second
in between.
When we filter
all the ones that are even, well, all the
ticks that are even will fall through.
But, all the ones that are alt will be
filtered out.
So what we end up with, is a stream of
numbers that are two seconds apart.
Right?
There's two seconds now between every
tick.
And then the last one here, this buffer.
What buffer does, it takes segments of
length two,
shifted by one.
What does that mean?
Well, it takes segments of two shifted
one, so there's the first segment of two.
Now it shifts one, and then it creates
this second segment of two.
And then it will shift one, and create
this second, the,
the third segment of two there, so there
will be six there.
Et cetera, et cetera.
So what you will see is that you now get
the two values here,
with two seconds in between.
When are these values actually produced?
That's an interesting question, because
what buffer does, is
it only produces the, the pair, at this
point.
Because it doesn't know yet, here, that
there's a value here.
So, it needs to kind of, get two values
before it can send them out too.
This pair, actually, is produced, at this
point.
But, you know, the pic,
for the picture sake, we left it like this
here.
Let's do a little quiz.
Here's a function, observable.range.
This is a function that we will develop
later in this course.
but what observable.range does, it just
returns the numbers,
starting at one, and then the next ten
numbers.
So if I do observable.range, one through
ten, it
produces an asynchronous stream of the
values one through ten.
Now let's map x plus one over this stream.
What is the answer?
Well, let's look at all the possibilities.
Let's look at number a.
Well, if you map over sequence the number
of elements never changes.
So here if this stream stops at ten.
And you know, here there's suddenly,
there's, you
know, like 42, there's many more values
here.
This cannot be the right answer.
Because
this cannot be the right answer, because
there's too many values.
Moreover, the values here are flipped, so
this is completely wrong.
Now let's look at the second one.
This one here is the correct answer.
It, exactly the same values as the input
stream, except that this
function here that you're passing to map,
is applied to each element.
And for the same reason that the first
one was wrong, these other two are wrong
as well.
But what this shows you, is that even
though this is
an asynchronous string; where the values
are pushed at the consumer.
You can still do map filter, and all
the collection operations on these
asynchronous data streams.