Now that we know how we can
derive observable collections by dualizing
iterable collections,
let's look at some combinators and some
operations that we can do on observable
collections.
Here's the list of functions that operate
over observable collections, and it should
come
as absolutely no surprise that we see here
all the kind of, you know,
our well-known friends, filter, map,
takeWhile, and of course, flatMap.
Now, the thing is that because
we're living in an asynchronous world
Especially,
we'll be a little bit different, than what
we are used to in iterable collections.
So, let's look at that in a little bit
more detail.
Here's map, as a marble diagram.
Nothing is different here compared to the
regular map.
We get our input stream of observable
values and we
have our function in this case, again, the
function that turns
coins into diamonds, and out comes an
observable collection of diamonds.
But this run works exactly as you expect.
The only difference with iterable is that
instead of pulling the
values from the input collection, the
input collection values get pushed at you.
And then we apply the transformation and
push the values in the output collection.
Now let's look at flatMap.
FlatMap is quite different than map.
Because the problem is this.
Here the first value is pushed in the
input, and
flatMap transforms that into another
stream and start pushing them out.
But as flatMap is pushing out the values
on the
output stream, the next value comes in on
the input stream.
Remember, this is asynchronous.
So flatMap has no control over when the
values appear on this input stream.
So, when the second value appears, it
applies the
function, and it starts to produce them on
the output.
But as it's doing that, the third value
might appear on the input stream.
And again, flatMap will apply its
generator function
here, and it starts to output all the
values.
So, what you see is that even though all
the outputs of the red input value here
are in the same order, all the values
corresponding
to the green input are in the same order.
They are all merged together in here.
So, to look at this is we can say that
flatMap is defined
as usual, as map followed by flatten.
But in this case,
flatten really means nondeterministic
merge.
So we have a stream of observables that we
nondeterministically merge.
Here's a simple example that shows the
merging behavior of
flatMap when flatMap is defined using map
followed by flatten.
Let's look at what this example does.
The first thing we do, is we create
an observable stream that quickly fires
off three, two, and one.
You see this stream right here, and you
see it fires of three, two, and one.
On that stream, we call that stream
excess.
We map observable.interval for x seconds,
so what that will do is it
will generate for each input value, it
will generate a stream that will
take at three seconds, respectively two
seconds, respectively
one second.
So the first stream, that's a three, will
wait for three seconds, take, and wait for
another three seconds, and take again.
Same thing for the second stream.
It takes at two, waits for two seconds,
takes, waits for two seconds, and takes.
And remember we did a
take two here.
So, this stream only produces two values.
And the last one for one.
When we merge those what we get is that
the
first value here is the first value from
the third stream.
And what we do is we map that back to the
original value such that we can see where
the values come from.
So the output when we merge it is first
this guy comes in, then after two seconds
these two come in in rapid succession.
Then we have the first value for three,
the second
value for two and lastly the second value
for three.
Okay.
What is this flatten, how is that defined?
Well, flatten takes an observable of
observables and it flattens them.
But how does it do that?
Well it does that by flattening them
stream by stream, so pair wise.
So we only have to look at merging two
streams and
then we know how we can merge a stream of
streams.
Right?
If we know how to merge two streams we can
just apply
that recursively and flatten a stream of
streams by applying this simple merge.
Here's the Marble diagram for merge.
You see, there's two streams.
And the outputs are merged together.
One thing to notice is that we have to
be careful what we do with the terminating
conditions.
In this case, the first stream arrows out.
The second stream keeps on going.
But what you see is that the merge stream
stops
as soon as one of its input streams has an
error.
And this is behavior that we typically
have in RX
is that whenever we do some kind of
combination of streams,
as soon as any of them has an exception,
we
immediately fill fast and propagate the
exception to the output stream.
And only if all the streams have
terminated then the outward stream will
terminate successfully.
The next example we look at is when we
don't want to merge the output
streams, but we want to get them in the
same order as the original input stream.
And here the colors come in handy.
In this case, we start with red three,
green two, and yellow one.
And what we want is we want the values in
the output stream to be in the same order.
So we first want to see all the red ones,
then we want to see all the green ones.
And finally, at last, we want to see the
blue ones.
As you can see here, this goal is exactly
the same as before.
We start with our observable three, two,
one.
We map interval of x seconds.
We then map it to the value itself.
And, we only take the first
two elements.
But, the interesting part happens here
with the concat.
So the concat,
what that will do is it will buffer all
the
input values until the right moment when
you can output them.
So, in this case, it will wait until
outputting the green and
blue values, until it has seen all the red
values, and it will wait
to output the blue values until it has
output all the green values.
Now, in general, this concat is a little
bit dangerous because, you know, it
can require arbitrary buffering, because
you don't know how long it will take.
You know, maybe this stream is even
infinite, so you
have to kind of keep them buffered for way
too long.
But as we will see, when the observable
streams are generated from a future,
that's one case
where you sometimes want to do concat in
order to
make sure that the values remain in the
right order.
Here's the marble diagram for concat.
And in this case, what we do is
we show the concat when there's two
successful terminations.
And what we see is that concat only
terminates successfully when both input
streams terminate successfully.
And here we will see that it holds onto
this
yellow value until the first string has
terminated, and then only
then outputs the yellow value.
And again, you have to be super careful
with concat, especially because of this
buffering behavior.
Our previous examples, were a little bit
artificial so, right
now, we're going to look at a more
realistic example.
And, in the exercises, you will write a
code
for this, so I can just leave this here
unimplemented.
The first function that we have, returns
and observable of EarthQuake.
And it does
that by calling into the US Geological
Service web
service that gives us a real-time stream
of earthquakes.
Earthquakes, in fact, are a really good
example of a
push-based stream, we are not pulling the
earth for earthquakes.
No, earthquakes happen and they get picked
up by sensors
and then, you know, we, we get them in
real time.
We, we get notified when an earthquake
happens in real time.
And the class for earthquakes has a
bunch of information about each
earthquake, including
where the earthquake happened and the
magnitude
of the earthquake, how big the earthquake
was.
And, since the earthquakes, the date that
comes in as a double for
the magnitude, which is not very useful,
because it's on the Richter scale.
That's it's a logarithmic scale.
So what we want is we want to make this a
little bit more readable by mapping the
values into a little bit more readable
notation.
So, if you go to Wikipedia and you search
for earthquake magnitudes.
You see that they have this categorization
that goes from micro to great.
And what we are going to do now is we
are going to take our stream of
earthquakes and replace
the magnitude as a double.
By this enumeration that gives us the more
readable form of the magnitudes.
We start with our sequence of earthquakes,
and what we're going to
do is we're going to project out the
locations for each earthquake.
And then we're going to project out the
magnitude which was a double.
And we're going to replace that by this
enum such that we get this more readable
form.
And then what we're going to do is we're
going
to filter out all the earthquakes that
are, at least, major.
Since we now get back a tuple of a
location and a magnitude.
We have to do a pattern match here to see
that we get the pair, and
then we project out the magnitude.
And so we can filter out all the
earthquakes that are not very interesting.
And then finally we subscribe to the
earthquakes.
We again have to do a pattern match to
get the location and the magnitude and we
can now
print out our real time stream of
earthquakes where
we only see the earthquakes that are at
least major.
Let's try to improve our code even more.
One of the things that is not so nice
about the previous earthquakes is that the
locations are given in geo-coordinates.
So that's lat, long, and altitude.
But that, for most people if your not a
real geek, you know, it doesn't say much.
So let's use a Reverse GeoCode service
that will take a
GeoCoordinate and retunrs a Future.
With the country information that
corresponds to that geocode.
And here, we're using futures, because
when we do the reverse
geocode, we give it one geocoordinate, and
we get back one country.
So, that's a very, very natural use of a
future.
But what we want to show here, is how you
can mix futures and observables.
So, let's start with this function that
will return an
observable of observables of pairs of
earthquakes with the
country in which that earthquake happened.
Okay?
So what we're going to do is we're going
to project for each earthquake in our
original stream.
We're going to take the GeoCoordinates and
then look
up the country.
And somehow, we want to kind of,
you know, create this double-nested
observable stream.
Yeah, I think about that for a second.
Here is how we do that.
This is our original stream.
Now we map over that.
Our original stream was a stream of
earthquakes.
So this is of type earthquake.
Now what we do, is given the earthquake,
we can
get this location.
Look-up its reverse geocode.
Which gives us a future.
Remember future is also a monad, so we can
map over a future.
So we, countries of type future country,
so we map over country, given
the country, and then we pair that up with
the original earthquake data.
So, that one is still here in scope, so we
pair up the earthquake with its
country, okay.
This guy here is of type future
of pair of quake and country and we turn
that into an observable.
So the end result is that we now have an
observable of observables that pairs each
earthquake with its country.
Yeah?
And this is quite nice that we're using
Map both on
futures and Map on observables in one
single piece of code.
Now just like with our previous artificial
example We
have two possibilities to merge this
observable of observable list
into a single observable stream.
So, one way to do it is to flatten it.
And the second way to do that is to
concatenate it.
Now in this case we probably want to use
concat and the reason
is that the earthquakes come in a certain
order.
Right?
Earthquakes happen at a certain time but
what can happen is that
the geocoordinate lookup for one
earthquake
can take longer than for another.
And if we Flatten them with merge, then
the earthquakes can come out of order.
Let's see how that works using some
pictures.
Here's an example of merging
the Geo, Reverse Geocode look-up for each
earthquake.
So, there's the first earthquake that
appears.
And suppose that looking up the country
for that one takes a long time.
Maybe there's a load balancer in the data
center that does the
reverse geocode look-up, and that one is
sent to a slow machine.
The second earthquake, the reverse geocode
goes really quick.
So that terminates, this is the future of
country, and
so we pair them up here.
And then the third earthquake is also
relatively fast.
And now only then, the first earthquake
appears.
So what we see is that the earthquakes
really happened in the order red, green,
blue.
But after geocode, reverse geocoding, they
come out in the order green, blue, red.
And maybe this is acceptable,
but sometimes it's not.
And in that case, we want to concatenate
the results.
If we concatenate the result.
What we do is we buffer the values of
every previous earthquake until the
earlier earthquakes have been geocoded.
So in this case, we have to wait until the
red earthquake returns the geocode
for the red earthquake's returns and then
we can output the green and the blue one.
And again, since we know that there's only
one value
here, we can, you know, it doesn't really
matter that we are
waiting for an infinite amount of time,
because this thing always terminates.
Of course, we might need to do something
with
error conditions, but for now, we'll just
gloss over that.
The last operator we're going to look at
is a very
interesting one, namely, groupBy.
What groupBy does, as you see in the
signature below there, it takes an
observable of T and then
it has a key selector that it will use to,
to select a key,
a common key for each value in the stream.
And what it will return is
an observable stream of pairs of the key
and
a nested stream that contains all the
values T from the original
input stream for which the key selector
maps to this key.
Perhaps, that's better explained in the
picture.
So in this case, we're grouping by shape.
So what we will get is
we start with this sequence here, with
different shapes, circles and triangles.
We're grouping by shape.
So, we get, in this case, two streams.
One stream that consists of circles.
Another stream that consists of triangles.
And then this collection here is actually
paired with its key.
That in this case is circle and in that
case is a triangle.
All
right.
Now lets now use this group by function to
group our earthquakes.
Let's use groupBy to group by our stream
of earthquakes
with reversed geocode information by
country.
So, what we will do is we will take the
stream where we have paired of each
earthquake with the country.
And we will for simplicity just flatten
it.
So, this merged stream has type observable
of pairs of earthquake, and country.
And what we're going to do is we're going
to use the country as the key for grouping
by.
So in this case we will say, we will
take this merged stream here and group it
by country.
'Kay?
So we have a little better match where we
project out the country.
And the result of this groupBy will be
this following
rather large type.
So what we get back is an observable.
An observable of pairs of country, which
is the key.
And an observable where we get all the
pairs of the earthquakes with the country.
So concretly imagine that we have a stream
of
earthquakes and there's earthquakes in the
Netherlands and in Switzerland.
And we're grouping by country so the
first earthquake here happens in the
Netherlands.
So we upgrade the new group with the key
Netherlands and we will fire off the first
value here.
Netherlands two, into that stream.
Now the second earthquake happens here in
Switzerland.
We didn't have a group for Switzerland
yet.
So we create a new group with key
Switzerland.
And we fire off the pair of the country
and the earthquake into that stream.
And now, the third earthquake comes in
here for the Netherlands.
Since we already had a stream for the
Netherlands, we will fire this pair
up here in the stream for the Netherlands
and so on and so on.
Say, that there's now, an earthquake in
Belgium.
In that case we'll create a new stream and
fire
it in there and as, as new countries come
in they will get their own stream.
We're going to finish off this lesson by
doing a little bit of analysis of
our earthquake stream.
In particular what we want to do is, we
want to compute the running average of the
magnitudes of the earthquakes per country.
How are we going to do that?
Well, we have our stream here of
earthquakes.
So that's the stream of earthquakes
grouped by Country.
So, it's an Observable of pairs of
Countries, with
an observable stream of the EarthQuakes,
with each country.
Now imagine that we have another function
here runningAverage, which takes a stream
of doubles
and outputs another stream of doubles that
is the running average of the input
stream.
So whenever new input value appears, it
will update the running average and send
that to the output stream.
And the goal of this exercise is to define
this function here, or this, this stream
here that returns an observable of
running average of the magnitudes grouped
by country.
Okay?
Let's take a few seconds to think which of
these values is the right one.
Okay.
You had a few seconds to think about it.
Let's check them one by one.
One of the biggest powerful analysis
techniques when you look at code like
this is to do some kind of type checking.
And of course in this case, the
[UNKNOWN]
checker would have already found the ones.
But what we're going to do is we're going
to do this type checking by hand.
So let's look at the first case.
We start with byCountry, which is an
observable stream, so we can map over
that.
So far so good.
This observable stream is a type, has
pairs.
So, oh, this looks good because we're
doing
a pattern match on a pair Where the first
one is a country.
Okay, so far so good.
Now, we have to return an an observable of
pairs of countries and something else.
Okay, that looks still good because we
return a country.
But now here there's something suspicious
right?
Because we're taking the running average
of quakes but quakes to
take the running average we have to have a
double, but quakes
here is of type observable of EarthQuake
and Country, so this is completely wrong.
Because the type, the expected type, here
is a double.
And what we give it is EarthQuake and
Country.
So this one is clearly, clearly wrong.
Now let's look at the second one.
Again, it starts the same.
But now it takes the running average.
By mapping the magnitude over the quakes.
So this is a good attempt, because we're
looking the
magnitude to get a double, but
unfortunately, quakes, those were pairs.
So we cannot take the, the, the, the
magnitude of these
earthquakes, because we first need to kind
of project out the earthquake.
So, we cannot
take the magnitude of this pair.
So, the last one here is the correct one.
We get a country and a list of pairs of
countries and earthquakes.
And what we return is the country and the
running average, where we
map the first element here and take the
magnitude of that.
So this
one is the correct one.