Now that we've seen how observables are
the dual
of iterables, how futures are the duals of
tries, it's
and we've seen plenty of examples of
observables, let's
look a little bit deeper in the mechanisms
underneath observable.
Here's a fragment from one of our earlier
examples where we had our stream of
earthquakes.
And that wasn't observable of earthquakes
and
we subscribe to the stream and that mean,
means that we kind of receive all
the notifications whenever there is a new
earthquake.
The observer and the subscriptions will be
notified.
And we said that if you're not interested
in receiving
anymore updates, you unsubscribe from the
subscription.
And what that means, when you unsubscribe,
you retract your observer from the
earthquate stream, and you will not be
notified anymore, of any future updates.
Now, it's important to distinguish between
two kinds of observables.
The first kind are called hot observables.
A hot observable is
an observable where all subscribers, in
this case
we have four subscribers, all share the
same source.
And this source will produce values
independent of how many subscribers
there are and independently of whether the
subscribers come and go.
For example, UIEvents are, are hot
observables.
Your mouse moves happen independently
of how many Event handlers you have
subscribed to them.
The other kind of observables are called
cold observables.
A cold observable has its own private
source for each subscriber.
For example, the observable stream of
earthquakes, is a Cold Observable.
Nothing happens until you subscribe to it,
in
which case it may, will make a network
call
to the web servers and start producing all
the values.
The difference between cold and hot
observers is
important when we talk about
unsubscription versus cancellation.
In general unsubscribing just means that
the
observer that unsubscribes does not get
any further notifications.
For example, if this observer here
unsubscribes, it will just not receive any
notifications from this observable of T.
But notice, there may be other active
observers, so, when this
one unsubscribes, it doesn't mean that you
can cancel the computation here.
Because yeah, there might be another one
listening.
But we will be quite sloppy, and we will
say, cancel and unsubscribing
interchagably, but typically when you
unsubscribe, it doesn't mean that the
underlying computation gets cancelled.
What most APIs do, is they try to do a
best effort that
in case there's no subscribers left, they
will try to cancel the underlying
computation.
Here's the trait that defines
subscriptions.
Subscription is only a single method
called unsubscribe that returns unit.
And the companion object has an apply
method, a factory
method that takes a block of work, and
returns a subscription.
Now there's many, many kinds of
subscriptions, and
we will look at the whole family right
now.
The first type of subscription
is the Boolean subscription.
A Boolean subscription has an additional
method, it's unsubscribed, that you
can use to check whether the subscription
has been unsubscribed or not.
The next sub-type of subscription is
CompositeSubscription.
A composite subscription is like a
collection of
subscriptions where you can add and remove
subscriptions.
And when you unsubscribe on
the CompositeSubscription, all inner
subscriptions get unsubscribed.
And the third sub-type of a subscription
is a MultipleAssignmentSubscription.
A multiple assignment subscription is like
a proxy for an inner
subscription that you can set and replace
but there
is always one inner subscription active.
Here's some
sample code that uses the simplest form,
the basic supscription.
It creates a new subscription with, as the
work printing you know, bye, bye, I'm out
fishing.
When you go and subscribe twice, you have
to be, make sure that this is idempotent.
So typically what happens, the
implementation of subscription will call
unsubscribe
here, so it will print bye, bye I'm out
fishing once.
And then when you call it a second time,
it remembers that
it has been unsubscribed and it will not
print a second time.
But if you implement your own
subscriptions, make sure that it's
idempotent.
That you can call unsubscribe any times
because
it could be that you hand out a
subscription
to multiple threads, and each of these
threads,
independently of each other, might want to
call unsubscribed.
Our next sample shows the
BooleanSubsciption.
This BooleanSbuscription has the same
trivial body
as the previous example gone out fishing.
But the special thing about a
BooleanSubsciption
was that it had this method isUnsubsribed.
So after we have created the
BooleanSubsciption, when we ask
isUnsubscribed, this will return false
because we have not yet unsubscribed.
As soon as we unsubscribe and
we ask is unsubscribed again then it will
return true.
When we draw pictures of subscriptions
we'll use a
solid circle to indicate the subscription
that has not
yet been unsubscribed, and we will use a
dashed
circle to indicate an subscription that
has been unsubscribed.
Let's look at Composite Subscriptions now.
First of all, we define a Boolean
subscription that prints A.
A normal subscription that prints B.
And then we will add these
two subscriptions to the composite
subscription.
So, what we get now is one composite
Look at, it's as a solid circle because it
has not yet been unsubscribed.
And it contains two sub-subscriptions that
also have not yet been unsubscribed.
So if we ask,
is the composite unsubscribed?
This will return false.
Right?
Because the line is still solid.
If we now unsubscribe from the composite
subscription, and we ask whether it's
subscribed.
We will see it's now unsubscribed.
And if we ask whether A is unsubscribed, A
was a boolean subscription, it will also
say true.
And you see that here in the picture,
that both A and B, once we unsubscribe
from the composite subscription.
Both the inner subscriptions will also be
unsubscribed, so this behaves like a unit
of, like a, a, a set of subscriptions that
all get unsubscribed together.
Now you can ask yourself, what happens
here if
we have another subscription, C, that we
add to
the composite subscription, after we have
already unsubscribed it?
What do you think would be the answer?
Well, there's two possibilities, if our
composite subscription has not
yet been unsubscribed, adding C to it will
do nothing.
It will just add C to it and it won't
touch C.
However, if we try to add C to an already
unsubscribed composite subscription,
we will eagerly unsubscribe from C, so C
will also be, become dashed.
Multi-assignments are our last example of
complex subscriptions.
Again, we define subscription A and B, in
this case, just simple subscriptions.
And we grade a new multiassignment
subscription, and ask whether it is
unsubscribed.
Well, it is unsubscribed and it contains
A.
Now, when we
change the subscription from A to B.
A just gets removed and nothing happens
with A, and now the
MultiAssignmentSubscription contains B.
And as soon as we unsubscribe from
the MultiAssignmentSubscription, then also
B will be unsubscribed.
The difference between a multi-assignment
subscription and
a composite subscription is that a
multi-assignment
subscription always has a single
subscription that gets replaced.
Where as a composite subscription has a
whole sets of subscriptions.
But we have to ask the same question that
we asked before.
What happens when we change the
subscription of
a multi assignment subscription, once it's
already been unsubscribed?
The answer is unsurprising, and very
natural.
When we try to set the subscription of a,
a MultiAssignmentSubscription
that is not yet unsubscribed, we will just
replace the inner subscription.
However, if the
MultiAssignmentSubscription
has already been unsubscribed, setting
the subscription will eagerly unsubscribe
from that new subscription.
And, that's what you see here in the
picture.
Once you've set this guy in there, it will
become unsubscribed.
The last question we have to ask ourselves
is, what happens if we have
an composite or multiassignment
subscription, where the
inner subscription gets unsubscribed from
the outside.
So here you see I'm going to sub,
unsubscribe from the inner subscription.
Since the outer
subscription has no way to get notified of
any changes in the
inner subscription, the only reasonable
thing that we can do is that is that the
outer subscription still has a solid arrow
that, you know, you still have
to unsubscribe from it, because it has no
way to see what happened inside.
Here's a little quiz with subscriptions.
We declare four subscriptions, a Boolean
subscription
that prints A, a regular subscription that
prints B, and we creates, as before,
a composite subscription that contains A
and B.
What we're going to do now, however, is
we're
going to create a multi-assignment
subscription, and add the
composite subscription as the inner
subscription of that multi-assignment
subscription.
And then, we unsubscribe from C, we
unsubscribe from the composite
subscription, which of the following
statements, A, B, C or D is true?
Okay, let's look at the answers one by
one.
First line b isUnsubscribed.
Well lets look at B.
B is not a boolean subscription so this is
a type error.
So this is invalid.
So that answer is not correct.
Now look at A.
A is unsubscribed it's false.
However, A was part of the composite
subscription that we unsubscribed, so
after this statement here,
c.unsubscribed, a.isUnsubscribed would be
true.
So this
one is false, as well.
Now let's look at the answer c here,
m.isUnsubscribed equals true.
Let's have a look.
Well we never unsubscribe from m.
So m is still, you know, unsubscribed.
So, this is also false.
And let's see if the last answer is
correct.
C is unsubscribed,
that is right because we have our
composite subscription here and we
unsubscribe from it.
So, this is the correct answer.