Now that we know everything about
subscriptions, boolean
subscriptions, multi assignment
subscriptions,
composite subscriptions and we have
seen lots of examples of RX operators,
let's look
at how we could implement some of them
ourselves.
And the main work horse that we're going
to
use, is this overload in the observable
companion object that
we call Observable.create.
Here's the picture, the marble diagram for
Observable.create.
Observable.create takes a function from
Observer to Subscription.
And in that function the Observer can call
onNext
on the Observer, and then finally
onCompleted or onError.
And the result of this application here
will return us an Observable
of T, we call this the mother of all
factory methods.
And we will see that most of the
Rx operators can be implemented using this
particular overload.
The first Observable collection that we're
going to implement is a very, very,
very simple one, namely Observable never.
This is an observable stream
that will never give any notifications.
No uncompleted, no OnError, no OnNext,
nothing.
It's completely silent.
The second Observable collection that
we're
going to implement is Observable error.
This is slightly less trivial, because the
only thing that
this one does is, it will call OnError on
the observer.
As we promised, we're going to implement
never with observable.create.
And in order to implement never,
what we have to do is we have to come up
with a function that takes an observer
and returns a subscription, and then when
we pass
that to observable.create, we will get
back the observable.
Never is really, really as simple as I
promised you.
Because what never does, it takes an
observer and it
does nothing with it, and it immediately
returns a subscription.
So you can
reason that, you know, the observer,
nothing will be called on the observer,
so there will be no notifications when you
subscribe to never.
The observable error is implemented as
another factory function.
So we define another apply function, that
takes as the argument a throwable.
And again, we call observable.create, by
passing it a function
that takes an observer.
And what this one does, is it immediately
calls observer.onError, with the argument,
and then returns the empty subscription.
Because, after you have seen the error,
you
don't have to do anything with that
subscription anymore.
The third observable collection that we're
going to implement is startWith.
StartWith takes an observable collection,
and prepends some extra elements in front.
To implement startWith,
we will be using observable.create
yet again.
Here's the definition of startWith.
It takes a varargs in scala, we indicate
that by putting a star after the argument
type, and it returns an observable of T.
And what do we do?
Well, the first thing that we do is we
take the observer and we
push out all the values from the argument
list, onto the observer.
And, once that's done, we just subscribe
that same observer to our original stream.
The source stream.
And, that will then, push out all the
other values on it.
So, the picture looks, as follows.
The first,
if this is our argument list.
We will first call OnNext to push out each
of
these, and then we just subscribe to the
original source stream.
Which will just copy all the values into
the next output stream.
Alright, we've now seen a few simple
examples.
Let's look at some more realistic
operators on observable collections.
The first one we're going to do is filter.
Just as a reminder, filter takes a
predicate.
In this case, is it a circle.
And then throws away all other values that
don't satisfy that predicate.
To implement filter, we're going to use
our observable.create yet again.
And what we're going to do is we just have
to copy all
the values from the input stream to the
output stream if the predicate holds.
And if the predicate is not true for a
particular element, we just drop it on the
floor.
How do we do that with observable.create?
Well, simply like this.
We call observable.create, passing at this
function
that given observer will return a
subscription.
Well, how do we get the subscription?
By subscribing to our source stream, and
then we pass
in here the three functions for OnNext,
OnError, and OnCompleted.
When we get an OnCompleted, the source
stream is completed and
then the output stream is also completed.
When we get an OnError, well that means
there was an error on
the source stream, so we just propagate
the error on the target stream.
And now the interesting case is when we
get a regular OnNext.
In that case, we get a value of T of type
T.
We check whether the predicate holds or
not.
And if the predicate is true, we propagate
the value
to the output stream.
So here you see that this implementation
of
filter really, really is very close to our
intuition.
We just listen to all of, all the
notification on the input stream.
And only if the predicate holds.
We propagate it and we also propagate
errors and completions.
Of course we cannot implement any
operators without having implemented map.
Just to remind ourselves what map does,
map takes a collection as its input,
in this case an observable collection, it
produces an observable collection as its
output.
And it has a function.
And what it does is it simply copies all
the values from the input stream to the
output stream.
But, while, when doing that,
it quickly applies that function.
So in this case, it turns all the circles
into diamonds.
Map is actually simpler than filter.
The, the two last cases are the same.
When we have an OnCompleted, we just
propagate the OnCompleted.
When we have an OnError, we just propagate
the OnError.
And now when we get a regular OnNext, all
we do, is we call the function
F on the value that we got on OnNext, and
propagate that to the observer.
So again, you see
that the implementation of map very
closely
reflects our intuition of how it should
work.
What is fun is to look at the
implementation of map on
iterables and compare how it relates to
the implementation of map on observables.
And what we will see is they are very very
similar, and
that's unsurprising because as we know,
iterable and observables were each other's
duals.
Here's the definition of a map for
iterables.
Again, it takes a function from T to S.
And in this case, instead of an
observable, it returns an iterable.
And the source collection is also an
iterable.
What do we do?
Well, in this case, we use immediately
the constructor calls, we, there's no
factory methods
for iterables, so we just call new
iterable and we define the methods in
there.
So what we have to do, the iterable has to
define a method iterator,
that returns an iterator.
But before we return that iterator, what
we do
is we take the iterator from the source
collection.
And then, what we do is we do exactly the
same as what
we did with the, map for observables, if
we get a regular value.
So if hasNext is true, we call next.
And, you know?
We pass the value
to the output.
And you know, we also just propagate the
hasNext of the source to the output.
So, again, you see here that this
implementation follows
the intuition that you have of map, very
closely.
It just copies the stream and while it's
copying, it is applying f to every
element.
Okay.
We have now seen a couple of examples.
And we learned that implementing filter a
map wasn't too hard.
Time for a bigger challenge.
Let's try to implement a conversion from
observables to futures.
So, what we want is we want to take a
future.
And turn that into an observable that
just contains one value, and then
immediately doesn't
uncomplete it.
Now, in order to define future, we
have to make a little excursion and come
up with subject.
What are subjects?
Well, subjects are to observables as
promises are to futures.
Just to remind ourselves what futures are.
If we look at the implementation of map in
the future class,
we saw that it looked as follows.
We created a new promise.
Then we waited for the completion of our
future, and we applied
the function, and then pass that to the
promise by calling complete.
And then we returned the future part of
the promise.
In the picture, the promise we can
visualize
a promise as follows.
A promise has two operations.
We can complete a promise by sending it a
result of type Try of t.
And from a promise we can grab a future.
And then on that future we can call
onComplete by passing it this callback.
So whenever we pass in the complete here,
the result for complete.
The callback of this future will be
called.
For observables, we have something that is
very,
very similar, and that type is called
subject.
A subject is, it has the same idea
as a promise, but the implementation is
slightly different.
Instead of, you know, taking a promise
from the future, a subject is both
an observer and an observable.
But it works the same.
What you can do is you can put a
value into a subject by calling onNext,
onCompleted, or onError.
That's the observer part of a subject.
And then the other thing that you can do
is you
can subscribe to a subject, written
observer or again with three callbacks.
And then whenever you call onNext here, it
will be propagated to the callback
function there.
And whenever you call onCompleted,
it will be propagated to the observer on
the
other side, exactly how a promised worked
for futures.
Now, maybe you remember the lecture about
cold versus hot
observables, and what, what we said there
is that a
cold observable is one where you get a
private, source
for each subscription, and a hot
observable was one where
the source was shared.
Well, here you see that the subject makes
a cold observable hot.
Once you subscribe to a subject here, it
has kind of only one side here.
So, it's a sharing point where you can
have multiple subscribers that listen to
one source.
To drill down a little bit into that
aspect of subjects,
let's look at the following code.
And this code shows that a subject behaves
like a channel, like a fan-out point.
And the first subject that we're going to
use here is called a publish subject.
And we're creating a publish subject of
integers, and let's call that one channel.
And we're going to subscribe to that
channel
with two subscribers, a and b, and they
just print whatever value comes out of
them.
Now, on the channel, we're going to push a
sequence
of values, and we're going to subscribe
and unsubscribe as well.
The first thing we're going to do is to
push 42 onto the channel.
So that's what happens here.
Since both a and b here are at
this point subscribed to our channel.
What we will see is that a will receive
42.
And b will also receive 42 because both
are subscribed.
Now, the next thing is that a will
unsubscribe.
In which case, it will not receive any
further notifications.
Remember, that's what, is what
unsubscription means.
Once you unsubscribe, you will not be
notified
of any other notifications.
So, if we call onNext
4711, then b who is still subscribed will
receive that.
But a as you see here, will not receive
this 4711.
Now let's call uncompleted on the channel.
We indicate that with this
little exclamation mark.
And after that, we're going to subscribe
another subscriber here called c, that,
that we show over there on the right.
And last thing that we do, is we're
sending 13 on the channel.
Now the channel is such that, after you've
called onCompleted on it,
it will ignore all subsequent values.
So, this value, 13, as you see, is not
propagated.
Because, as soon as you call onCompleted
on
the channel, all the subscribers will
receive an onCompleted.
And anything you send on the channel after
you've sent an onCompleted will just be
ignored.
So c will only see uncompleted, and b will
see 42, 4711, and then uncompleted.
But the Rx contract we will talk about
that in a future lesson, will guarantee
that after you've seen uncompleted on, or
onError, you never see any more values.
One interesting thing to notice is that
subscriber c here that subscribes
to the channel after it was completed,
still receives the onCompleted.
And in that way
c knows that it is going to subscribe to
an already completed channel, so you see
here it's, happens afterwards, but it
still got the onCompleted here.
The second subject that we're going to
investigate is the so called replay
subject.
A replay subject is something that buffers
all
the values that it has seen in the past.
So, let's create a ReplaySubject, let's
create two subscriptions
to it, a and b.
Again, we see them here in this picture.
And let's send again 42 onto the channel.
Since both a and b
were subscribed to it, we see that a gets
42, and b also gets 42.
Now a unsubscribes from the channel, which
means it will not receive any future
notifications.
So, a only ever will see 42.
We're going to send 4711 on the channel
which will be received by b.
And then we will call onCompleted here,
Now after
the channel has been completed, we
subscribe subscriber c to the channel.
And guess what, since the channel has a
history
cached, whenever you subscribe with c, it
will replay the whole sequence
so c will receive 42, 4711, and
onCompleted.
And again, if we push anything on the
channel
after it has been completed, this value
will
just be ignored and dropped on the floor.
There are four different kinds of subjects
in Rx that are most commonly used.
And they are the publish subject that we
already saw.
The replay subject that we already saw,
and then there's
two new ones, the async subject and the
behavior subject.
Let's revisit the publish subject for a
second.
The publish subject always sends out the
current value.
What does that mean?
Say that, you know, the subscription here
below
subscribes at the point where the arrow
is.
What it will see, it will only see
onCompleted.
And, the, the top subscriber here always
was subscribing
from the beginning, so it has seen the
whole sequence.
So, this is what we saw in the previous
example.
The replay subject, we've seen that as
well.
In this case, it caches all the
values so if the bottom one here
subscribes at this point,
it will get all the values and then
finally, the onCompleted.
Now there, the two other ones.
let's do the behavior subject first.
A behavior subject always caches the
latest value.
So in this case when the bottom line here,
when the bottom subscriber here subscribes
at this point.
The latest value was 4711.
So at the moment you subscribe here, you
get the latest value 4711 plus
all future values, and then in this case,
onCompleted.
The last subject here is an async subject,
and
an async subject caches the final value of
a stream.
So it caches the last
onNext before an onCompleted.
And in this case, you see that both
subscribers here get the same value.
And the async subject is a little bit like
a replay subject, even though
you subscribe to it after it has
completed, it will send out the cached
value.
To close off the subject of subjects, pun
intended, let's do a little quiz.
Let's define a channel that is an
AsyncSubject of integers.
And, again, we have our two subscribers, a
and b.
That just print the values again in our
picture there's a and b here,
and we're going to send the same values
over to channel 42, then a
unsubscribes, then we send 4711,
then we call onCompleted.
Our next subscriber enters, and
finally we called 13, and after we've
already closed the channel.
The question is, which of these sequences
here, a, b or c, is correct?
Let's look at a.
According to this,
a receives the sequence 4711 and
onCompleted.
However, a already unsubscribed, before
the channel completed.
So a will never get the onCompleted
because it has unsubscribed.
So this is wrong.
Let's look at c here.
C joined after the channel was completed.
But since this is an async subject,
it should only see the last value, and so
this 42 should not be in there.
So, this one is also wrong.
And the last one here, this is the correct
answer.
Because we're sending 42, 4711, and then
onCompleted, and
then AsyncSubject caches the last onNext
before an onCompleted.
And then that's in this case 4711.
That's here.
And then it immediately sends out
onCompleted.
Alright.
Now that we know about subjects, let's
revisit how
we're going to create an observable from a
future.
To convert the future to an observable,
we're going to
define a new constructor function in the
observable companion class.
So we, we're going to define apply here
that takes a future and returns an
observable.
And what we're going to do is we're going
to use
the fact that an AsyncSubject behaves very
much like a promise.
Remember a promise was something where I
can
put in a value and then whenever I wanted
to listen to that value, whenever I can,
I,
that onComplete on the promise, I got that
value.
Well the same thing, we're going to do
here.
So we're creating async subject, and then
what we're going to do is we're
going to take the future and give as it
onComplete the following functions.
When the future completes with a failure,
well, we just send onError to the subject.
However, when the future terminates
successfully with
some value c, what we do is we send that
value c onto the subject.
And we complete the subject.
And now, we return the subject and all is
great and fine.
Because when we subscribe to this subject,
to the observer part of
the subject that comes out of here, it
will give us always this value.
Which is exactly the value
that comes out of the future.
As we've seen in a previous example,
futures use this try class, so their
callbacks take a value of type Try of T,
which has two
subtypes, namely success with a proper
value of type T, or a failure.
On the other hand, in observables.
What we do is we typically take three call
backs.
One for OnNext,
one for OnError, OnCompleted.
But in Rx, there's also a type that
corresponds very closely to the tri-type.
And this is the type notification of T.
A notification of T has instead of two
cases, it has three cases.
It has an OnNext, which directly
corresponds to the success case here.
It has an OnError, that directly
corresponds
to the failure case in a Try.
But it also needs the third case, to
indicate successful termination,
and that is the third case of the sum
here, OnCompleted.
And there is a method on Observable called
materialize that turns an Observable of T
into
an Observable of notifications of T, and
in that case, you can do a pattern match.
On the notification of the very similar to
how you do a
pattern match on the Try of T in the
OnComplete of a future.
Here's the marble diagram for materialize.
We see here our regular
stream where there's onNext, onNext,
onCompleted and when we materialize what
we do is we inject that into the
notification type.
So now we get a value onNext that has the
value that was passed here in the onNext.
We have a value onNext here for the second
one, and
then onCompleted.
And then, the underlying stream has it's
own completed as well.
Remember when we were.
Discussing futures that we said that
sometimes you need
to do blocking, even though that's a bad
practice,
but you know, say that you want to debug
things, or you, sometimes you just need to
block.
And to make this really, really apparent
in futures, we use this
await thing here the await class, where
you, where you did .result.
And then you know, you would wait at most
ten seconds in this case.
But the blocking was made very, very, very
explicit by using this await.
The same is true for observables.
Sometimes you just want to block on an
observable.
for example, if you're de-bugging.
Or, maybe, you know, you want to, you have
to move back to a blocking,
situation.
It's not recommended, but just in case,
you can do the same with observables.
And the operator that we use for that is
called two blocking observable.
So when you have an observable and you do
two
blocking observable, you get a few extra
methods that are blocking.
But all the other regular methods in Rx
are all non-blocking.
One interesting aspect of Rx, as I said,
is that all operators are non-blocking.
Let's look at this following example.
We creating an observable stream, using
Observable.interval, so this
is the observable creation method that
will create the
stream that will tick every second, and we
will
take the first five values of that using
take(5).
If we want to turn that into a list, we
first
have to call this dangerous method
and it's long on purpose,
toBlockingObservable,
and then we can call toList.
So what you see here is that we go from an
observable[Long],
to an list of long, and we do that by
calling this toBlockingObservable.
So, when we print ys, we get the list zero
to five.
Now, say that we call the sum operator.
On the original, sequence axis here.
So we have an observable of long, and we
call sum.
So that sums up all the values.
Well since all the operators, the regular
operators are non-blocking, the
result of summing the numbers is still an
observable of longs.
However it's an observable
that has only a single value.
So when we want to get that value out of
this observable, what we do is we again,
we can call toBlockingObservable and then
we can call the function single.
To get from an observable of long to an
observable.
And notice that single will throw if the
argument, if the source stream does
not contain exactly one element.
As you may remember from the lectures on,
on lists, before.
A lot of the aggregate operators like sum
and average
and so on, can be defined in terms of
reduce.
Reduce is a function that has the
following signature.
It takes a binary operator, T and T, and
it returns a T.
And what it does, it just collapses all
the values
in the input stream.
Into a single value by applying this
operator.
So the marble diagram shows that very
nicely.
We have our source stream here, and the
reduction collapses all the values by
combining them.
And you see here they kind of are nicely
stacked on top of each other.
The thing in Rx is that reduce
still returns an observable.
So, as you can see here it returns
an observable collection that has a single
value.
Which is very much like a future.
So, another possibility would have been
that reduce would have returned a future.
But since we can turn a future, an
observable,
into a future, you can always do that by
hand.
And we have just shown you how you
can do that yourself.
What is interesting with blocking is that
we are removing concurrency.
So if we start with an observable
collection and we want to go to a
list, we have to block, which means that
we have to remove concurrency.
In the next lecture, we will show how to
go from an iterable collection,
to an observable collection.
And in this case, we have to add
concurrency.
And that reminds us of another duality.
Namely, De Morgan's duality.
And this is a duality that every
programmer knows
and that all of us use everyday when we're
programming.
And De Morgan's law says the following,
that not a and b is the same as not a or
not b.
And conversely, not a or b is the same as
not a and not b.
What this says is that and and or are
dual.
And the energy between this, that drives
this duality is negation.
Interestingly we have seen that iterable
and observable are each others dual.
And there, it's not negation that is the
energy between them but it's concurrency.
And that's what we will see in the next
lesson.
In the next lesson, we are going to tackle
this challenge.
Given an iterable collection.
We want to create an observable
collection.
And the challenge is that we want to make
this work even if this iterable collection
is infinite.
And in particular what we want to do is
that at any time as we're iterating
over the source collection, we want to be
able to unsubscribe from the resulting
observable collection.
As a cliff hanger, I'll give you the wrong
implementation.
So, let's try to define this naively,
using our big friend, observable, create.
Here's our function from takes an iterable
and it returns an observable.
And what are we going to do?
Well, let's do this.
Now if we would just go to foreach over
the search collection, and then bump out
the values on the observer.
Then we complete and then ret, return a
subscription.
If you think about this a little bit, you
will see that this doesn't really work.
If the sequence is infinite, it will never
reach the onCompleted.
If the sequence fails, it doesn't call
OnError.
And even, since the subscription here is
trivial, it doesn't allow
us to unsubscribe as we're iterating over
the foreach loop.
So this implementation is completely
wrong.
Completely wrong.
We should really, really kind of forget
this.
Remove it from our brains.
The question, however, is how can we make
this work?
And for that, we need schedulers.