Alright, so last lesson we looked at
creating observables, and in
particular we were left with the exercise
to create an observable from an iterable.
And we're going to tackle that problem
right now.
So here's a picture of what we want to do.
We want to define a function from.
That takes an iterable,
here, collection of values, and returns it
into an observable.
And the way we want to do that is by
pulling each
value out of the iterable and then pushing
it into the observable.
Now the real challenge is that we don't
want to do this only for a finite
sequence like we see here, but we also
want this to work for an infinite
sequence.
Okay.
Here's our signature of the function that
we are going to define.
Function from takes an iterable of t and
returns
an observable of t, and this is our test
case.
We want to define an infinite sequence of
numbers, nats.
Then we want to turn that infinite
sequence into an observable sequence.
We want to subscribe to it.
But then we want to unsubscribe to it, and
terminate
the subscription.
Can we make this work?
First of all, let's define this infinite
sequence of numbers as an iterable.
To do that, we just use anonymous classes,
so we define a new iterable.
How do we do that?
Well, in order to define a new iterable,
we need to define and iterator.
And in order to define an iterator, we
need to define has next and next.
And in this case,
what we will do is just before we create
the iterator, we will allocate
a mutable variable, and then our iterator
will always say that it has
a next value, and when you ask for the
next value, it increments.
And the counter and returns the value, so
when you iterate over this collection of
natural numbers, you get 0, 1, 2, et
cetera.
To create our observable, we're going to
use, of course, our factory method create.
The signature of the method is here just
for reminder.
Observable apply it has a subscribe that
takes an observer and returns a
subscription.
And as the picture shows in that function
you can use the observer to go onNext
if you want to produce a value on the
output observable.
And you call onComplete or onError when
you're done.
And the subscription that you return here
is the subscription
that you get back when you subscribe to
this observable.
And we have seen this method before, but
we
will see much more of it in this lecture.
Here's our first attempt to define from.
What we do is, we call our constructor
function,
pass it in observer, and what do we do?
Well, the only thing we can really do is
to, foreach over the
sequence, and whenever we get the next
value, push it into the observer.
And when we're done, we call onCompleted.
Of course, this function here must return
Subscription.
But what can we do?
Well, I think the only thing that we can
do at this point is return an empty
Subscription.
Now let's see if our test works.
So what we do, is we call our natural
numbers, infinite stream of numbers.
We subscribe to it, with print line.
And guess what?
We will never reach the unsubscribe.
And why is that?
Well, if this stream is infinite,
this will not terminate.
So, we will never reach this point, which
means that we
will never reach this point because the
subscription is never returned.
Oops, Houston, we have a problem.
So to recapitulate, here is our code
again.
The problem was that we never got there,
we never
got past the onCompleted, and hence, we
never got here,
on the consumer side, past the
subscription.
So, what should we do?
Well, the solution is that we should
introduce
schedulers, we should introduce
concurrency and what we're going
to do is, we're going to do the
iteration over the source interval on a
separate thread.
That calls on next on the observer, such
that
the consumer here can unsubscribe on its
own thread,
and then we will not be stuck at this
point.
Let's look back in the past at future.
When we talked about futures we saw that
every future took a execution context on
which the work of that future was run.
So, the constructor function for future
takes.
A block for the body.
An execution context and returns a future.
In,
for observables, we have a similar
concept.
Except, that instead of an execution
context, we have a scheduler.
And, what we'll do know is we'll look at
the differences between the execution
context and the scheduler.
Because, there's a difference between
observables and futures, remember.
That futures are things that return one
result,
and observables are things that return
multiple results, and
that will have an influence on the way
that we define scheduling.
The execution context for futures is
defined as follows.
It has a single method, execute, that
takes a runnable and returns unit.
The reason that it takes a runnable is for
legacy reasons.
So a runnable is an existing java type
that
really corresponds to a, a block that
returns unit.
So in our x we can do the more modern
thing,
the more scholar thing.
So instead of runnable.
We take work of type you know, arrow unit.
Now the other difference is that in
the future, it's impossible to cancel the
work.
So once you execute a runnable, there's no
way to cancel it, it will start running.
But for our x, as we have seen, we want to
unsubscribe.
So, instead of returning unit,
we return our subscriptions.
And we have seen, a lot of things about
subscriptions in the
previous lesson and we will use some of
them here as well.
Okay, here's a very small example of using
a scheduler.
one of the, schedulers that we will use a
lot is the NewThreadScheduler.
And what that will do, is, when you
schedule work on the NewThreadScheduler,
it will take that
block, schedule it on another thread, and
it will run there.
And in this case, it will just print line
from a different thread.
Very simple.
Okay then.
Let's try to define our function from
using schedulers.
Here is the signature from takes an
iterable, now it takes also an implicit
scheduler.
Returns an observable, all clear.
So what can we do?
Well, we call again our observable create,
taking an observer, and what
we do this time is we schedule the foreach
on a new thread.
And when the
foreach terminates we call onCompleted.
Does this work?
Well, unfortunately, it doesn't work yet.
Because when you schedule work on the
scheduler, it can
only be unsubscribed, when the work has
not yet started.
So once this work has been scheduled,
once you start foreach-ing over your
collection,
there's typically no way you can cancel
that work anymore.
So you only have a very brief moment in
time where you can cancel
this, but you can only do that when onNext
has not been called yet.
So this is not a very useful
implementation.
In order to do, do a second attempt to
write a front function,
we will look at some of the other methods
in the scheduler trait.
We have already seen the first one, takes
a unit of work and reduces subscription.
What we'll use next is the second
signature here.
Which is more interesting and more
powerful.
Because, what it does is, it takes a
function that gets a Scheduler
as an argument.
And this function can then use that
Scheduler to schedule multiple steps.
It also returns the subscription that is
then returned to
the caller, that the caller can use to
cancel these steps.
And then, what we will do is we will take
that function
and implement the third overload here with
that, with the second one.
And the third
overload has this rather bizarre looking
type here.
Takes an arrow unit to unit.
And it returns a subscription.
Let's look at that guy.
Here's our second attempt to define from.
Again, should be no surprise, we use
our create function, taking of the server.
But, what we will do now is, we will
unfold the loop that was done by the
foreach and do it ourselves.
So, the first thing we do, is we take the
iterator from the iterable, and then we
schedule the following work.
We first look if there's still a value.
In which case we call onNext.
And then we have rescheduled our self
recursively.
And if there is no more work, we stay, we
are completed.
Here's how this looks in a picture.
Here we see our condition if there's still
a next value, what do we do?
We call on next with the next value, and
then what we do
is we recursively schedule ourselves in
the future, and what will happen there?
Well this will call the same condition
again.
So we will go on and on and on, until at
some point our source
is exhausted, and then we call on
completed.
Does this work?
Let's run our test.
Again, there's our infinite stream, we
turn it into
an observable and subscribe to it with
print line.
And guess what, when we now unsubscribe
from it we will
terminate the stream, because this guy
will schedule itself
recursively and at each schedule there's a
chance for it to unsubscribe.
Of course, we're all curious how this
recursive scheduler works.
So let's drill down into the
implementation.
The recursive scheduler, schedule, takes
work, that takes
the continuation and returns unit, and it
returns as always a subscription.
Now how are we going to make this work?
Well of course if we are going
to take multiple steps, what we need to do
is we need
at every step we need to be able to
unsubscribe from this step.
So what we will do is we
will use our good friend
MultipleAssignmentSubscription to create
a subscription that we pass to the
outside,
that the outside can use to unsubscribe
for.
And what we will now do is we
will schedule work and then update the
MultipleAssignmentSubscription every
time we reschedule work.
So every time we reschedule work, we will
update
the subscription with the current batch
that's in the scheduler.
Sounds simple?
It is simple.
Let's look at it.
What we do is we schedule.
We get a scheduler.
What we do is do is we schedule some work.
And we return the subscription.
And what work did we schedule?
Well, as soon as we get
run, we update a subscription with
scheduling ourselves, doing
the work, and passing the continuation
which will call itself.
Here's a picture that explains this in a
more visual way.
So here we see a scheduler.
That's the red bubble here.
And this is our work.
So, every time the work gets scheduled to
run, it does some work, and then
reschedules itself.
And when it reschedules itself, it updates
the
multiple assignment subscription to point
to the current work.
So when you sub,
unsubscribe here, it will always cancel
this work.
If you don't get cancelled, you get run
again.
You do it again, and then you reschedule
yourself on and on and
on, until you either don't reschedule
yourself, or when you get here canceled.
Now, anyone that has seen this
implementation
of schedule here, would ask why did
you do this kind of, you know, really
weird function here with three parameters?
Because as real scholar programmers, we
all know
that we can define a local definition
right
up there such that we can capture the
parameters in the closure instead of
passing them explicitly.
So let's simply
find this code a little bit.
To make it look more like, you know, that
we're functional programming ninjas.
Hear this, what we do is we have a local
definition now for loop.
It still returns Unit, but now you see
that it can close over the schedule.
It can close over work, and of course it
still calls itself recursively.
As an argument to work.
This is all nice and well to do this
crazy thing with recursive scheduling, but
as functional programmers
we also know that we always want to
capture
patterns that we often use as a high order
function.
And that's what we're going to do now.
What we want to do is, we want to use this
weird recursive scheduler to define
a new constructor function for observable,
that will just return
an infinite stream of units by recursively
scheduling itself.
So here's a picture of that stream, so
what we
want to do is you want to have a stream of
ticks, and each of these ticks is
scheduled recursively, such
that we can cancel the subscription in
between all these steps.
In order to write this code, of course I
could do it
right here, but I think its more
interesting if you try it yourself.
lets see what it does.
Well first of all, it of course calls our
friend observable create, and then it
uses the recursive scheduler to schedule
itself but what should it do in the body?
You pick a, b, c or d.
you guessed the right answer.
What you have to do is you have to first
call OnNext and then re-schedule yourself.
So, operationally again what happens is
you schedule, you call OnNext,
you call yourself, which schedules itself,
calls OnNext, et cetera, et cetera.
So if we get our friend, the
NewThreadScheduler here in scope, then we
can define
the infinite stream of ticks just by
calling this new default constructor for
observable.
And let's see how this really works,
because I can tell you, you know that
this thing goes on recursively, but we
really, really want to see how that works.
To understand how ticks work, we first
come to revisit observable create.
And we're going
to get a little bit of a algebraic law
that we can use to reason about it.
So, here's the signature again, observable
has an apply method that takes
this function from observer to
subscription
and it returns a new observable.
And, what this does is conceptually it
just defines the
subscribe method, by calling the function
that you passed in,
which as you can see has exactly the same
argument as the subscribe function.
Takes an observer to a subscription.
So, what it does, it calls your function
here with the observer here.
And so, now you get here Subscription, and
that's exactly what's your return.
But that's not all.
And that's why I say this is just
conceptually,
because what it does is that it also some
magic going on.
Now we will talk about this magic later.
But given this conceptual definition, we
get the following rewrite rule.
If you have an observable that you create
using this function, so you
do that by passing, you know, our usual
function from observer to subscription.
When you subscribe to that with an
observer,
that is really the same as calling the
function directly with the observer.
Put some magic around it.
And that's the subscription that you'll
return.
So this is the model that we will use to
understand our ticks function.
One of the magic things that observable
create does for us is how to unsubscribe.
What does that mean?
Well it means that when you create an
observable using observer.create by
passing this function F.
When that function F calls uncompleted or
on error on the observer, the magic will
automatically call unsubscribe on
the subscription.
And that guarantees that onCompleted and
onError are only called once.
And then, any subsequent onNext calls on
the observer will do nothing.
The main reason that we have all this
magic.
In the observable create, is to enforce
the Rx contract.
And the Rx contract says that a stream in
Rx always has the following shape.
It consists of zero or more onNext
calls, followed by exactly one onCompleted
onError.
But that can be optional because we have
already
seen that we can have an infinite stream
that never
calls onCompleted onError.
So here you see two correct Rx sequences.
This one here terminates nicely with an
onCompleted.
This one terminates nicely with an
onError,
but the third one here is completely
wrong.
First of all, it has both in onCompleted.
And then, afterwards, it calls an onNext
and even an onError.
And the other thing that Rx also
guarantees
is that all the onNext calls are, happen
sequentially.
So, they never happen concurrently.
So you can always be sure that your onNext
call is called.
By itself without having to care about any
race conditions.
What do we learn from this?
Well, that you never, ever have to
implement Observable or Observer yourself,
but always
should use the factory methods Observable
create
and we have also similar methods for
Observer.