Alright.
Schedulers Part Two.
But before we go there, let's do a little
quiz to see if we still
remember the Rx contract.
So, here is a very simple example.
We create an observable using observable
create.
We call onNext.
We call onCompleted.
We call onNext again, and we return
the empty subscription, and then we
subscribe to
this with println.
What is the output of this code?
A, B, C, D, or E?
Well, the answer is obviously D.
And why is that?
Well, we call onNext.
But once we've called onCompleted, the
magic in observable create will make
sure that nothing else here is going on.
So this is what the output is.
Our goal, in this lecture, is to
really understand how the recursive
scheduler works.
So, we're going to blow our mantle stack
by going deep recursive.
Just to remind ourselves, here was the
definition of ticks.
What we were doing is, we had our
observer.
We were calling OnNext and recurse to
ourselves.
And, we created this infinite stream here.
What we're going
to do now is we're going to go step by
step.
Unfolding the code, to make sure that we
really understand that this thing actually
recursively schedules itself, and that we
understand
at what point we can cancel this.
In the next step, we're going to use our
rule for observable
don't create by substituting the observer
here in the body of the function.
So everywhere where o appears in the body,
we will replace it by observer.
So that's this place.
So what we see here is that everything is
the same
here except where the observer was, we now
substitute the observer.
What we don't show here is the magic,
because we now all understand the magic,
and that would only clutter our
development here.
The first thing that we are going to do
now
is to make this code look a little bit
better.
It's, like, all kind of, you know, messed
up here.
So let's put it all on one line, that we
can see what's going on.
After we've done the create step, what we
end
up with is a call to schedule, with some
work.
Now, remember what our definition of
schedule was.
It's just here.
So what we're going to do now is we're
going
to substitute this definition of schedule
in our previous example.
This following step looks a little bit
complicated, but it's really not that
hard.
What we are going to do is we're going to
take this part here, the work that's here
in bold.
And we're going to substitute that in the
definition
of schedule that we saw in the previous
slide.
So when we do that, well, the definition
of schedule is pretty large.
But where we, what we end up with here is
that the work is right here.
And it's applied to loop as we have seen.
And in the next step what we will do is
we'll
[INAUDIBLE]
this application and substitute loop in
here, because now we see our function
applied to an argument and we know that we
can evaluate that, right there.
Remember when we talk about continuations,
well the continuation here is the self.
So this is the argument that we pass to
this work, where here you see it goes to
continuation.
And what we see is that the continuation
is this loop, and
in the next step we will substitute loop
for the continuation In the body of this
long
[UNKNOWN]
here.
When we do that, we end up with this nice
and simple expression here.
Okay, let's rearrange the code here.
Now it looks all beautiful.
The next thing that we're going to do is
to take this definition and move that out.
Because, you know, once all the variables
are bound we don't want to have
this in our codes all the time because it
just clutters up the go to.
What we're going to do is we're going to
lift that out.
So, when we lift that out it looks as
follows.
We have the loop outside this, and we're
left with this
simple code, here, and the definition of
loop is nicely lifted out.
All the variables are bound, so we don't
have to worry about that.
We can now concentrate just on unfolding
our simple code, down here.
If we rearrange again a little bit, put
everything on a single line, we see
that we end up with a call to schedule of
the second overload of schedule.
That takes the scheduler and then you
know, calls loop, and returns to
subscription.
When we call this schedule function, what
will happen is that it will at some point
run the work inside that body, which wants
loop followed by subscription.
Well, let's unfold loop, because we have
the definition right there.
If we unfold the definition of loop, we
see that we
have this call, and then we still need to
return to subscription.
The first thing that this thing does it is
will assign
a subscription of the scheduling of the
loop into the
scheduler to our subscription that we pass
to the outside.
So, when we do that, we will see that we
overwrite
the subscription now with the work that
we're scheduling in the scheduler.
And this is exactly the situation that we
wanted to end
up with, because what we're doing now is
we're handing off
this subscription to the caller of our
text function,
and it points to the work that's scheduled
in the scheduler, and guess what
the first thing is that it's going to do?
It's going to call OnNext.
Let's run the computation, and let's see
what it produces.
So, here's the output of the observer that
we're going to see.
And the first thing as we see here is
going to call OnNext.
So this is the first value that we see on
the output Once we do that we have sent
the tick
to the observer, this thing disappears and
we end up with loop.
Guess what?
We're going to substitute now loop for its
definition, and see what happens next.
When we unfold loop, we end up with a
subscription.
That has scheduled work, which will update
the subscription
with a schedule of observer OnNext with a
loop.
Well, that looks familiar.
So now, we are back again at where we
were.
We have already send out one thing.
This guy will send out next thing, and
we'll loop again et cetera, et cetera, et
cetera, until we call unsubscribe on this
guy,
in which case, this thing will not be
rescheduled.
Great.
Now that we know how our new observable
create
works, let's create just an infinite
stream of text.
We can start to write more interesting
applications of this.
First of all, let's define a new function,
range.
Range takes two values, a start value and
a count.
And what it's going to do, it's going to
create an observable
stream that starts at start and contains
count values.
So, for example, if I say range (1,5),
what
will that produce?
Well, it will produce the
values 1, 2, 3, 4, 5.
Right, there's 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 values.
How does this work?
Well, we call as always observable create.
We allocate a little bit of mutable state.
And now on
our recursive scheduler, which we get from
the implicit context.
We subscribe to that, and then if the
count is still greater than,
you know, the number of values that we
have already sent out.
We send out start plus i, we update our
mutable state, and, if we're done, we
call onCompleted, and the magic in
Observable create
will make sure that our subscription is
unsubscribed.
And no more values will appear on the
output string.
Here's how we use range,
let's go range from 1 to 10.
Subscribe to it with print line, and guess
what?
It nicely prints the values of 1 up to 10.
And then terminates, as we expect.