Welcome to the Actor part of the Reactive
Programming course.
This week we will learn about the Actor
model.
That means what Actors are, how they
interact, what they can
do, and in general, how you can structure
your computations using Actors.
Last week, we saw what reactive streams
can do for us.
How data flow in them from producers to
consumers.
How they are transformed, filtered, how
streams
can be merged.
But it all goes more or less in one
direction.
Actors give you more freedom than that.
Because they can collaborate and
communicate just like we humans do.
In particular we will talk about how
actors can create other actors.
How they change their behavior over on
time, how they exchange messages.
And in the end, we will conclude with a
lesson about how to test
Actor systems.
So that you are well equipped to solve the
exercises.
Before we dive into what Actors are, let
us first take a
look at why we want to investigate them,
and where they came from.
The Actor formalism was first published by
Hewitt, Bishop, and Steiger in 1973.
And what they wanted to achieve is to
create a model
in which they can formulate the
programs for their artificial intelligence
research.
One of Hewitt's students published his
Ph.D thesis in 1986.
Gul Agha formulated Actor languages, so
how to write down Actor
programs, how to reason about them.
He described communication patterns
between Actors, and
how to use them to solve real problems.
In the same year, Ericsson started
developing a programming language named
Erlang.
This is a purely functional programming
language,
whose concurrency model is based on
Actors.
And which was then subsequently used in
commercial products.
In 1995, Ericsson presented their new
telecommunications platform.
Which was highly successful.
It quoted a reliability of 9 9ths, which
means that
there was only about 30 miliseconds of
downtime per year.
This robustness and resilience was made
possible by the Actor model.
Inspired by the success of Ericsson's
Erlang, Philipp Haller
added Actors to the Scala standard library
in 2006.
Jonas Bonér was then influenced by Erlang,
as well
as the Scala Actors to create Akka in
2009.
Akka is a active framework on the JVM with
Java and Scala
APIs making the Actor model available to a
wide range of developers.
Actors are applicable in a wide range of
problems.
And we will see that in the following
sessions.
But we, before we go there, let me first
show
you a few problems which motivate our use
of Actors.
In the past, programs just got faster by
using the next generation of CPUs.
This was due to an ever increasing core
frequency.
But this came to a halt around the year
2005.
Since then, CPUs are not getting faster,
they're getting wider.
This means that instead of making one
execution core more
powerful, multiple such cores are
incorporated
within one chip, accessing shared memory.
And in some of these, the cores are even
virtualized such
that one physical execution core can host
multiple logical execution threads.
There are different ways to benefit from
these wider CPUs.
The first one is that you can run multiple
programs
in parallel on the same computer.
This is called multi-tasking, and has been
done since the first versions of Unix.
But
if you have a single program which you
need to execute faster, and
you have no choice but to run parts of the
same program in parallel.
And this is called multi-threading.
In order to achieve multithreading, your
program must be
written in a different way than the
traditional sequential form.
The difference between running separate
programs in parallel, and using threads
of the same program in parallel, is
that these threads collaborate on a common
task.
And if you think about a group of people
doing something together, they will need
to synchronize their actions.
Otherwise they step on each others toes.
The same can happen in a multi-threaded
program.
There are a new class of bugs and problems
which await you there.
And this
is the reason why programs need to be
formulated differently in order to be
ready for multi-threading.
In order to understand what that means,
let us take a look at
the good old bank account which was
introduced by Martin a few weeks back.
This is the class.
I just copied it.
It contains a field for the balance, and
it has two methods to deposit some amount,
and to withdraw some amount.
Now let us look at the withdraw method in
detail.
I have marked out here, specifically the
places where
the balance is read, and where it is
written to.
So let us take a look at what happens,
if two threads run this code at the same
time.
I am making little table here.
Let's say this is thread 1, and this is
thread 2.
They are executed by different CPUs, so
can run really and parallel.
They enter the method with an amount.
Let us say that thread 1 wants to withdraw
50 Swiss francs for example.
And thread 2 wants to withdraw 40.
The first thing they will both do is read
the current balance.
In both cases, let us say the balance is
right now 80, so they will both see 80.
Then both will enter the if statement, the
check.
Is the amount positive?
Yes it is.
And are there actually sufficient funds in
the account?
Yes there are.
So both will continue.
They will calculate the new balance.
The new balance in the first thread will
be 30, and in the second will be
40.
The next thing the threads will do is they
will write back the new balance, into the
balance field of the bank account, object.
The first thread will write 30, and the
second will write 40.
This is clearly in conflict, because only
one of the writes can win in the end.
The one which comes last, will overwrite
the one which came earlier.
This is the first problem which we see
here.
It is that one of the updates to the
balance is actually lost.
The other problem is that the invariant of
the bank account is violated.
In that we have withdrawn 50 and 40 Swiss
francs which is 90
in sum, and the balance was only 80, which
should not have been possible.
One of the threads should have failed.
And that, that did not happen is the other
problem with this code.
Now what can we do to fix this problem?
We need to add synchronization.
When multiple threads
are working with the same data, they need
to synchronize their actions.
Because otherwise they would be prone to
step on each other's toes.
What we need to do is to make sure that
when
one thread is working with the data, the
others keep out.
Like you put a don't disturb sign on your
hotel door.
So let's say in this example we're looking
at the balance,
as the data to be protected.
And what we need to do
[SOUND]
is to put a fence around it, so that when
one thread is working with the data, say
thread 1.
That this one has exclusive access to it.
Which means threat 2 here, if it tries to
access the data, it will
actually be denied access at this time.
And it has to wait
until threat 1 is finished with it.
This way, the balance will be protected.
And all modifications done on it are done
in a consistent fashion, one after the
other.
We also say serialized.
The primary tools for achieving this kind
of synchronization are lock or mutex.
Which is basically the same concept as
shown just previously.
Or a semaphore where the difference is
that multiple but
only a defined number of threads can enter
this region.
In Scala, every object has an associated
lock.
Which you can access by calling the
synchronized method on it.
And it accepts a code lock which will be
executed in this protected region.
How do we apply this to the bank account
to make it synchronized?
Well, we have the withdraw method here.
And if we put all of it inside
of a synchronized block, then reading the
balance here.
Performing the check and writing it back,
will all be done as one atomic action.
Which cannot be disturbed by another
thread executing withdraw,
at the same time.
That other thread will have to wait.
But why do we have synchronized also here
on the deposit method?
The deposit method also modifies the
balance.
And if it was not synchronized, then it
could modify it without protection.
And once the withdrawal writes the balance
back here, it would
override the override the update performed
by deposit at the same time.
This is to illustrate that
all accesses to balance need to be
synchronized, and not
just the one which we have proven to be
problematic.
Now, let us try to transfer some money
from one bank account to another.
What we need to do is to synchronize
both objects, such that they're in a
consistent state.
Because otherwise, someone reading the
balance of
the accounts could find the money in
flight.
We withdraw from one account.
We deposit later into another one.
During this time, the money is basically
nowhere.
And if the invariant which needs to be
enforced, is that the sum
of from and to needs to be the same, this
will be violated.
Hence, we need to synchronize.
So first we take the lock on the from
account.
Then we take the lock on
the to account.
Now we are safe that no other thread can
modify these two accounts, but we can.
One property of locks in Scala is that
they are reentrant, meaning
that the same thread can take it twice or
any number of times.
it's just a protection against other
threads.
There is a problem with this code, in
that it introduces the possibility of a
deadlock.
Let us say that one thread wants to
transfer
from account A to account B in one thread.
And another thread tries to transfer in
the opposite direction.
If both start at the same time, they take
the first
lock, this one on account A, this one on
account B.
Then they go on to take the other lock.
This one will not succeed in taking the
lock, because
it was already taken by the other thread
for account B.
The same is true for account A in the
other thread.
This means that none of the threads can
make progress, they will both be stuck
forever.
Because there is no chance that either of
them will yield the lock they already
have.
This is called a deadlock.
There are solutions for this deadlock.
For example, to always take the locks in
the same order.
You need to define an ordering for
accounts and so on.
and then you could potentially solve this.
You will find that there are most of the
time solutions of that kind,
but they will aggregate and make your code
much more complicated over time.
And in this
case, it is simple, because both are bank
accounts.
But what if you want objects to
collaborate which do not come
from the same code base, for example, in
which you cannot modify?
In that sense, it would be much better
if our objects would not require blocking
synchronization.
Because blocking is what really makes the
deadlock happen.
Because one thread gets blocked on the
lock.
The other problem with blocking, is that
it is bad for CPU utilization.
If there are other threads to run, then
the operating system will run them.
But otherwise, the CPU will be idle.
And, waking it up, or getting a thread
back to run
when some other thread has interrupted it,
takes a lot of time.
So your program will run slower if you use
blocking.
Another problem with blocking objects
is that synchronous communication couples
sender and receiver, quite strongly.
Because the sender needs to wait until the
receiver is ready.
So if I call a bank account which is
synchronized,
that bank account will block me until it
is ready.
Non-blocking objects are exactly what
Actors are.
And we will see that in the next lecture.