Now it is high time that we go in media
space and look at what actors really are.
Actors represent objects and the actor
model
describes how these objects interact, and
this is
all inspired by how we humans organize
and it especially respects the laws of
physics.
What do I mean by this?
Let us say that we have a person here
without a watch who wants to know the
current time.
Over here, is another person.
With a watch.
Now the first person will ask the
question, what is the time?
.
And the second person might just answer,
it's 12:43.
This is a simple exchange between two
humans and we all have done
something like that before so I hope
everybody can relate to this example.
But there's more than is visible at the
surface.
First of all we take note that, we
transmit information by speaking and
hearing the words.
That means the first person sends a
message to the second person.
The second person then thinks a little
bit,
looks at the watch and replies with
another message,
traveling back, on waves of sound.
The two fundamental qualities here are,
first of all, it is based purely on
messages, and second, messages take time
to travel from one object to the other.
It is helpful to think of actors not
as these abstract objects on which you
call methods.
But instead to visualize them just like
persons
who talk with each other.
One thing also to note is that when we
humans talk, we
do not reach into each other's brains, for
example, by mind reading.
we rely only on messages, and that is a
very fundamental part of actors.
More formally, an actor as defined by
Hewitt,
Bishop, and Steiger is an object with an
identity.
We know that from the second week of this
course.
And it has also a behavior, which we also
already have encountered, and it only
interacts using message passing.
Which is still compatible with the normal
object definition, what is special about
actors is
that their message passing is always
asynchronous.
Let me illustrate what that means using
another small drawing.
We have an actor here, let's call it Actor
A.
And this wants to send a message to actor
B.
Actor A will send the message and then it
can
just continue doing whatever it wants to
do after that, without
having to wait for the message to travel
to B And
it will be processed by B, especially the
processing happens in
a different context, at a different, later
time as
determined by the system where the actors
run in.
This is the most important property of
actors.
For this, we use the actor traits in Akka.
The actor type, defines one abstract
method which is called receive and this
receive returns something of type receive.
Receive is a partial function from Any to
Unit and
it describes the response of the actor to
a message.
Any message could come in, hence Any, and
the actor
can do a lot of things, but in the end,
it does not return anything to its caller,
because the
caller is long gone due to the
asynchronous message passing.
We implement the Actor trait here in a
simple class called Counter.
This one has one Field count and it has a
behavior.
It must implement the receive method in
the
Actor trait and that must return a partial
function.
That's the partial function literal here
with one
case statement and it matches the incoming
message.
So if we get a message with
a string incr then we want to increment
the counter.
Which we do here, on the right.
This object is a pretty boring actor,
actually, because we can only send it the
string and we never get any answer back.
And we cannot determine what the counter
actually is.
Therefore this object does not exhibit
stateful behavior.
If we want to make it stateful we want to
enable other
actors to find out about what the value of
the counter is.
And therefore actors can send messages to
addresses they know.
Addresses in Akka are modeled by the
ActorRef Type.
So, the addition here is, we add another
case, and if we get a tuple
with the string get, and something with
type ActorRef, which we call
customer, then we can send to the
customer, the count
as a message.
This is the exclamation mark operator
which is used
to send messages and it is pronounced tell
in Akka.
So customer tell count.
In order to understand what is really
happening behind the
scenes let me show you more parts of the
actor trait.
Each actor knows its own address.
It's an ActorRef called self.
And it is implicitly available.
ActorRef is an abstract clause which has a
method called tell or exclamation mark.
And if you use the exclamation mark that
is
the nice Scala syntax, tell is more for
Java.
This takes an implicit argument.
The implicit argument of of type ActorRef
is picked up from the surroundings.
So if you use the tell operator within an
Actor it will implicitly
pick up the sender as being the self
reference of that actor.
Within the receiving Actor, this value is
available as sender, which gives back
the actor ref, which has sent the message
which is currently being processed.
Passing the sender reference along with
the message to the receiving
actor needs to be done explicitly in other
actor implementations like erlang.
But since it is such a common pattern, we
devoted this
one name in the actor to this purpose and
do it automatically.
Using this new power we can make the
counter actor look a bit nicer so we just
use the messages here and the sender is
automatically picked up to which the reply
is sent.
An actor can do more things than just send
messages.
It can create other actors, and it can
change its behavior.
To access these functions, we need to know
about the actor's context.
The actor type itself only has the receive
method,
so it only describes the behavior of the
actor.
The execution machinery is provided by the
actor context.
Here you see
an excerpt of the methods available on the
actor context.
These two are called become and unbecome.
Each actor has a stack of behaviors and
the top most one is always the acted one.
The default mode of become is to replace
the top of the stack with a new behavior
but you can also use it to push an
un-become to pop the top behavior.
You have access
to the context within the actor by just
saying context.
Now let's see this in action.
We can reformulate our counter actor into
one which does not have a bar.
It will be a stateful object without a,
explicit variable.
First, we need to define a method, which
gives us a behavior.
This method takes an argument, what the
state of the counter currently is.
We start out with the counter at zero, the
behavior counter of zero.
If we get an incr message here, we change
our behavior
to be that of a counter of n plus 1.
N first is 0 so it will be a counter 1.
Within this counter behavior, at anytime
we can get a
get request, where we just reply with the
current counters value.
You can see here that this looks a bit
like a tail-recursive function, because we
call it inside
itself, but it is asynchronous, because
context.become evaluates what
is given here only when the next message
is processed.
This is functionally equivalent to the
previous version
of the counter, but it has some
advantages.
First of all, there is only one place
where the state is
changed, and that is the call to become,
and this is very explicit.
The other is that the state is scoped to
the current behavior, so
there is no variable which we can leave
somewhere in an unknown state.
We always have the current state here.
The last thing, one can fundamentally do
with actors, is to create and stop them.
The actor context has methods for that.
First, actor of, which takes props, that
is a description on how
to create an actor, and a name, and it
returns an ActorRef.
Also, each actor can stop other actors.
One thing to note here is that actors are
always created by actors.
This means that they naturally form a
hierarchy because
an actor is created by exactly one other
actor.
We will see that hierarchy and another one
in the following weeks.
And another thing to note is that stop
here is often applied to
the self reference, which means that the
actor decides that it wants to terminate.
Let us try this all out in a runnable
application.
Of course an application is also modeled
as an actor in this model.
So we call it main.
This is an actor, and it uses context
actorOf to
create a counter.
We can say, Props Counter to create
an actor which does not take constructor
arguments.
And as all good things.
It needs a name, we name it counter in
this case.
Then we send messages to this counter, in
this case we
send it incr three times and then we send
it get.
Remember that sending
with the tel operator within an actor will
pick up the self reference as the sender.
And since the counter will reply, we will
receive it in this actor.
Here in our behavior, we receive the
count, which is of type int.
We will print it out and then stop
ourselves.
I have loaded the counter actor code into
Eclipse.
Adding the appropriate input of the actor
trait
and with the implementation that you have
already seen.
The same for the main class which needs
the props in addition.
In order to run this we need to tell
Eclipse how to
run actor applications because it
currently does not know about that yet.
So we create a run configuration.
I have one prepared here.
It uses the main class akka.Main which
expects as its first argument, the class
name,
the full class name of the actor class
which is to be instantitated.
Then, if we run this.
We will see that the count was three.
This printout was done by this
line, so we, we received the count from
the counter
actor, and we received three because we
incremented the counter three times.
We could, for example, delete one of those
lines.
And run the program again.
And then the count is two.
Now we have seen all the basic things that
actors can do.
When they receive a message, they can send
messages, create actors.
And they can change their behavior for the
next message,
and this all, this is the actor model of
computation.