Actors live and breathe in messages.
So now we will take a look at how exactly
messages are exchanged between them.
The most important property of actors is,
that access
to their state is only possible by
exchanging messages.
There's no way to directly access the
current behavior of an actor.
Messages can be sent to known addresses,
and in Akka those are typed as ActorRef.
Every actor knows its own address, which
is
very useful when sending messages to other
actors and telling them where to
reply to, but it can also be useful to
send a message to self.
The second possibility is creating an
actor, which
will return the address of the new actor.
Most notably it will only return the
address,
so the ActorRef, and not the actor
instance.
It is not possible to call methods
on this newly created actor, besides
sending messages.
The third way is that addresses can be
sent between actors within messages.
The most prominent example of this is the
automatic capturing of the sender in Akka.
The other important part of how actors
work is that they are completely,
independently executed.
Every actor performs its calculations
completely locally,
they are not shared directly with other
actors.
The only way to share them is by sending
messages.
There is no notion of a global
synchronization between
the steps actors do because they all run
fully concurrently.
And message parsing is the only way in
which they
interact and the way messages are sent is
completely one way.
When an actor sends a message to another
it continues on its way and
is completely oblivious to whether the
other
actor will receive or process the message.
It does not wait for its completion.
This means that actors are completely
incapsulated and
isolated from each other.
One could also say that actors are
the most encapsulated form of object
orientation.
We have seen how actors interact, as seen
from the outside.
On the inside, an actor is effectively
single-threaded.
It will receive its messages, one after
the other.
And, for each, it will invoke its
behavior, possibly
change the behavior for the next message
and move on.
But, it is important to note that
processing one message is the
atomic unit of execution.
Everything an actor does while processing
a message cannot be interrupted
or interleaved with processing another
message; they are strictly sequential.
This, has the same benefits of making all
methods synchronized, as
shown in the first part of this lecture,
but without the
disadvantage of blocking.
Blocking is replaced by simply enqueueing
messages, for later execution.
Now let us apply these principles to the,
our well-known bank account example.
This bank account will, of course, be an
actor and it will receive messages.
It is good practice to declare all the
possible message types expected
by the actor, and also returned and reply,
in its companion object.
We have therefore here, the object bank
account, and in that, we have case
classes.
One for depositing some amount, I'm using
big integer here,
to avoid problems with overflow, just
because someone might
have more than two billion Swiss Francs in
one account.
And of course we need the amount to
deposit to be positive.
Require is a library function which will
simply
throw an exception if the condition does
not hold.
This means that a deposit object which
has been instantiated will always have a
positive
amount in it.
The same for withdrawals we have another
case class, which gives the amount.
And then, our actor will have to respond
to requests so
that we can detect that it actually has
performed the work.
And for that we have the positive, Done,
and negative Failed reply.
Now let us look at the actor itself.
First, of course, we extend the Actor
traits.
Then we import all these message types,
which we have defined.
And the actor starts out with a balance of
zero.
Then it will handle messages as they are
received.
We can receive a deposit, in this case, we
increase the balance by the amount.
And reply with a positive acknowledgement.
If a withdraw message arrives, we need to
check
that there is actually sufficient funds in
the account.
If that is the case, then we deduct the
amount from the balance, and send
back a positive reply, in all other cases
we reply with a failure.
This actor is equivalent to the bank
account object defined earlier,
but including synchronization, because the
code
in here will be completely serialized.
One message entering this behavior cannot
interfere with another
one because the other one will be forced
to wait its turn in the processing.
That is the very convenient,
the most convenient feature of actors when
working with them.
In order to transfer money between these
accounts we need several actors to
collaborate.
And actors collaborate basically in the
same way that humans do.
Let me first make a small detour here,
let us say we have an account Which we
call Alice, here.
And we'll have another account, which we
call Bob.
Now we want to transfer money.
We could include the code to perform the
transfer in
the bank account itself, but that would
mix up the logic.
The bank account should not have to know
how exactly a transfer is done.
This is why we introduce another actor,
let's call him Tom.
Who will be our model of the activity to
transfer some money.
Tom will first send a message to Alice to
withdraw the money from Alice and Alice
will eventually reply, hopefully with a
success.
In case of failure, Tom will just abort
the transaction.
Then Tom will send to Bob,
a deposit.
And eventually Bob will reply, yes all is
done.
And at that point the transfer has
completed, the transaction has been done
and Tom can shut itself down, possibly
informing whoever wanted to know about it.
How does this look like in code?
Well, we need another actor, we call it
WireTransfer, and
this one will also accept some messages,
again, in the companion object we have the
Transfer case class, from is a bank
account, but we only know the address.
To is an address to another bank account
and
amount is the amount of money which shall
be transferred.
This actor also can signal success and
failure and it is good to keep the message
set used by one actor local to it
and to keep different actors separate from
each other.
Transferring money proceeds in several
steps as we have seen in the picture.
First of all, when we create a
WireTransfer
actor it will start out with an initial
behavior.
It accepts only message type Transfer.
And this Transfer
tells it from whom, to whom, how much
shall be transferred.
So the from actor gets a message to
withdraw amount and
then this actor changes its behavior to
await the
result of this withdraw activity and as
you suspend its execution.
It will not consume any CPU resources it
will
not run unless a message is actually sent
to it.
The behavior which we install for the
second step, awaitWithdraw, needs to know
the account to which the money shall be
transfered, which amount that was.
And also who sent the transfer command to
send back the acknowledgement at the end.
The behavior in the second step is defined
here.
We await the result of the withdraw
operation and the, a bank account
might reply with a done, in which we, in
which case we proceed.
We send a deposit to the recipient
account, and then we change behavior
to await the result of that operation.
If the withdrawal from
the originating account actually failed,
which means that there were insufficient
funds, then we need to tell the client
which requested the transfer.
And we need to stop this transaction.
In the last step, if the withdrawal was
successful, we await
the BankAccount.Done, from the account
which was supposed to receive the deposit.
Once we get it, we confirm that the
transaction has been successful.
To the or, original client.
And stop this transaction.
Perhaps it is instructive to see this all
in action.
I have again, put the code which was
presented so far into an Eclipse project.
Here we see the bank account with
well-known messages.
And here we have the actor itself, and
I've added a debugging feature here.
I've said LoggingReceive around the
behavior.
We will see what that
means shortly, it is imported here from
the Akka event package.
Similarly, we have the wire transfer actor
which has also been treated in the
same way with logging receives in all
behaviors.
The last part is an actual main program
which runs all of this.
Again, this is an actor like in the last
example.
And we create two accounts, account A and
account B, both bank accounts with
different names.
Then we send to account A a deposit of 100
Swiss Francs, for example, and
in the initial behavior, we await
confirmation
from this bank account that the deposit
has
been received.
Then we start a transfer of 50 Swiss
Francs.
Transfer is a method which first creates a
transaction actor, this WireTransfer
called transfer, then it
sends to this transaction the command to
Transfer from account A
to account B, the given amount.
And then it changes the behavior of this
actor to wait for the confirmation.
Once it is received, we declare success
and stop the program.
Again, I have prepared a run configuration
for this
with the akka Main class.
And as argument, the main class the, the
actor class to be run.
I have set here a debug option,
Dakka actor debug receive equals on, this
activates
all the logging receive blocks, so that
they
tell us when which message is being
processed.
It is done so at log level debug.
Now running it,
produces a lot of output.
Here we can follow the progress of the
program.
First, the account receives the deposit of
100, then the application receives the
confirmation.
Next we instantiate the transfer and tell
it to transfer from account A
to account B, amount 50.
Account A will then receive the withdraw
message and
reply to the transfer with the successful
acknowledgement.
Then Account B will receive the deposit,
and again, reply successfully.
At the end, we receive a Done message.
At which point the application terminates.
If we now try to transfer more than that's
in the account
and run again,
we will see less output.
First, again, we deposit 100, and that was
successful, then the transfer starts,
withdraw 150, which fails.
Then we see received unhandled message
failed, and nothing more happens.
This is because in this behavior here, we
do not handle this case, and we do not
stop the application.
So I will quickly insert
this case and when re-running it we
see again that it, now it receives the
handled message failed and it terminates
the application.
To recap what we have done, we have
modeled accounts as actors
which were Alice and Bob, account A and B,
in our sample.
We have modeled the activity of
transferring money
from one account to the other as an actor.
Which was named Tom here, and then we saw
how the messages flow, to complete the
task which are supposed to be done.
Actors interact only using messages,
as we have seen.
But messages can also be viewed like
letters.
We have seen that actors interact only by
sending messages.
But sending messages is something which
requires one more thought.
Whenever you send it, you can never be
completely sure that
it will be received as all communication
is always a little
bit unreliable.
The same is true for synchronous method
calls.
Which are also messages in a sense,
because for example,
the computer might crash while trying to
invoke a method.
You could say then that the message was
not delivered.
if you invoke network transfers for
example, send messages across
a TCP/IP connection, then obviously, the
chances
of messages being lost is higher, but
nevertheless, you need to always deal with
the fact that communication is inherently
unreliable.
This is something we know from daily life,
so we can also employ the protocols.
Which we have developed.
Say we have a person here, and this person
wants this other person over here,
to perform a certain task.
Let's just say it says,
something like please do.
Whatever it is that shall be done.
What we typically do is, we do not race
past the other person's office and shout
in, please do.
Because then we don't know whether the
command was actually heard.
What we typically do is we wait for a
confirmation.
Now the other person, which was listening,
was hearing that this person said, please
do, might respond okay.
This gives confirmation that the message
was actually
delivered and then both can happily go
away.
But what happens if, for example, a big
noise occurs.
That shadows this okay phrase, so this
person doesn't hear it.
Well, we humans are pretty adaptive, so
this one will ask
have you heard?
And this can go on until the process is
complete.
We can take this as inspiration for how to
construct actor systems, which perform
tasks reliably, although the communication
they employ is unreliable to begin with.
Successful delivery of messages requires
that eventually, we will succeed.
In the example with the two persons it
requires that both are perseverent enough
to come back to the process and
keep talking until the confirmation is
conveyed.
In more formal terms.
Delivery of a message requires the
eventual
availability of a communication channel
and of the recipient.
We can classify the kind of effort we go
to and the resulting delivery guarantees
in three ways.
The first one is if you just send a
message once, then it will either arrive
or not.
Hence, it will be delivered zero or one
times.
This is called at-most-once delivery.
If we keep resending a message until we
receive an acknowledgement.
That means, we will resend it until it has
been processed, so it will be received at
least once.
But up to an infinite number of times.
Because the acknowledgement itself might
be lost.
And we will keep resending
it until that is also successful.
If we keep state at the
receiver, to make sure that only the first
received message is
processed, then you can ensure that the
message is processed exactly once.
This is the most costly of the three
options.
The first option can be done without
keeping any state in sender or receiver.
The second choice requires that the sender
needs to keep the
message to buffer it, in order to be able
to resend.
And the third choice, additionally
requires the receiver to
keep track of which messages have already
been processed.
The good thing about messages is that
making them explicitly,
supports reliability quite well.
First of all, messages can be persistent.
You can take a copy of a message and store
it in some persistent storage.
You can not do the same thing with a local
method
invocation for example because that is an
ephemeral act you have one
object invoking a method and the context
in which this happens might go away.
A message on the other hand from one
sender
to one receiver is something which you can
persist.
If you include a unique relation ID in the
message, you can enable the exactly
once semantics by allowing the recipient
to
find out whether it has already received
this,
this unique message.
And finally, delivery can be retried until
successful.
If the messages were persisted then
retries
can even be restarted after a catastrophic
failure.
For example, if all the computers were
down due to a power outage.
Then once the power comes back up,
delivery can restart.
But one thing to note, it is not
enough to deliver a message to a
recipient.
If you do not get a reply from that
recipient,
you can never be sure whether it has
processed it.
That means, that all of these semantics
discussed
only work if you include a business level
acknowledgement.
That means that the actor which shall
process the message
actually needs to say, I have gone this
specific task.
It is not enough for the framer to say,
I have put this task into the recipient's
mailbox.
How do we apply these principles in our
bank account transfer example?
We can make the wire transfer reliable by
logging all
its activities to persistant storage so
that it has a memory.
Then each transfer needs to have a unique
ID by which it can be
identified in the Withdraw message and in
the Deposit message so that
the bank account actors do not perform
Withdraw or
Deposit more than once if resends should
be necessary.
And for that, they need to store these IDs
with their state.
The details of how to do this, I leave as
an exercise for the viewer.
The last topic in this section, is about
message ordering.
When you send multiple messages in your
system.
In which order do the actors process them?
An example.
Let us say,
we have an actor Alice and as usual,
accompanied by Bob
and Charlie.
As, Alice sends a message to Charlie.
So far so good.
But if in the same, at the same message
processing turn,
Alice also sends a message to Bob, which
one gets processed first?
You don't know.
Conceptually they are processed completely
concurrently.
You cannot tell in which order they are
processed.
Now, if this message to Bob would contain
a reference to Charlie,
so an actor refer it, then Bob, might, in
response to this message, also send a
message to Charlie, but since we do not
know in which order they are processed,
this message from Bob to Charlie might
actually arrive before the one from Alice.
In the original actor
model, those were all the rules.
Message ordering is not prescribed by the
model.
In Akka, there is one addition.
If Alice sends another message to Charlie,
then the message
of, the order of these two messages, will
be the same at the
receiving side as on the sending side.
Either of these messages
could be lost, of course.
But they will not be delivered out of
order.
There are other, more sophisticated
systems.
for example, the e programming language.
Where causality goes a bit further.
So if Alice sends a message to Charlie.
Then in Alice's view, Charlie has already
processed the message for all intents and
purposes.
So if it sends Charlie's reference to Bob,
then if Bob subsequently
sends to Charlie, this should not be able
to arrive before the message from Alice.
This guarantee is rather expensive to
realize but
E has also a different focus than Akka.
The philosophy of Akka is to provide the
minimum level of guarantee which make
the programmer's life easy but still allow
our implementation to be very fast and
efficient.
Therefore we chose not to implement the
full causality,
just the ordering between a single sender
and receiver pair.
In summary, actors are fully encapsulated,
independent agents
of computation, which run fully isolated
from each other.
And the only way they interact is by
passing messages.
Making message parsing explicit also
exposes the possibility of message loss.
But it also allows you to explicitly treat
reliability in your programming model.
Lastly, the order in which messages are
processed is mostly undefined,
but we have seen how to deal with that in
our wire transfer actor, if you have one
actor which coordinates a certain session
between other actors.
Then this one dictates the order
in which
things happen.