We have seen what actors are.
And how messages are passed between them?
But, how does one go about actually
writing actor systems?
This is what we will look at in the
following.
Encounter a few other useful things to use
in the Akka toolbox.
When starting to design an actor
application, it is
helpful to visualize first a room full of
people.
And you have all these people at your
disposal.
you have your task, which you need to
solve?
And, what you need to figure out in the
process
is, how to divide the task into sub-tasks,
and sub-sub-tasks?
So that every person knows what to do.
And there is not too much to do for any
one of them.
Since actors have fairly low overhead, you
can create many of them.
So, consider this group of people to be
of very large size, for all practical
purposes.
And you know from organizing, like party,
or anything where people collaborate on.
It is important to keep an eye on who will
have to
talk to whom and how much they will have
to talk, in order
to fulfil their tasks?
It is important to optimize their
communication paths in actor system.
Just as it is in a human organization.
There is one aspect of this comparison
between, actors and people.
which does not quite hold.
And that is, that actors in contrast of
people are easily spawned and terminated.
You can create as many
of them as you want in the process of
solving your problem.
And they can be short lived, just unlike
people.
As you go about, defining the tasks of
certain actors in your
system and their role they play and the
other actors they collaborate with.
Draw a diagram and mark down their
communication lines
between the actors and how they relate to
each other.
I will demonstrate this process now on a
simple project.
The problem which we want to solve, is to
write an application.
Which, given a URL.
It will go to the web, retrieve the
document, check for
links in it, and follow the links and
repeat the process.
After a certain maximum depth of course,
otherwise it would be boundless.
And all links encountered
in the process, shall eventually be
returned
to the one requesting, that this be done.
How would you solve this with a bunch of
people?
There will be one actor.
Which we call receptionist.
And this one, is responsible.
For accepting incoming requests.
These will come from, some external
client.
This receptionist is a person who will
just have the responsibility of accepting
your request.
noting down that it shall be done.
Noting who was the client?
And then, telling someone else to do the
real job.
When traversing the web,
we will encounter many links.
And there might even be cycles.
So, when we see a link which we have
already visited, we
need to stop there, because otherwise we
run in an endless loop.
It is best that we assign one person to
the task of one such traversal.
Because that person will remember, what
has already been visited and what not?
Translating that into an actor.
Let's call it controller.
This controller will need help.
Because it's main job is to remember what
was visited and what still needs visiting.
But, it would be better if we had someone
else to do the actual visiting of the
link.
And to extract the information which we
want.
So, let's put in another actor, which we
call getter.
Getter is a rather simple one.
It will just go look at one URL, retrieve
the document, extract the
links which are in there, and then tell
the controller what it found.
The controller can then spawn other
getters to visit the new links and so on.
To recap, let us now put in the messages
which will be exchanged to achieve this.
The client
sends a get request for a URL.
The
receptionist will create a controller.
And send it a,
check, for a given URL with
a certain depth.
Because we do not want
to do this in a boundless fashion.
The controller
will then, will then tell the getter.
To
retrieve, what is at
that URL.
And the getter,
will then reply.
With possibly
multiple links.
And then finally,
a done message.
So that the controller knows that this
getter
has exhausted all which was found at that
URL.
All links which are found in the process,
should be treated
as quickly as possible and they can also
be retrieved in parallel.
So there will be multiple getters.
Which perform the subsequent
checking of the links in parallel.
The controller will have to
keep track of which URL was encountered at
which search depth.
So let us say this comes down at depth one
and the links come back at depth one.
But when they are checked by the next
getter they will be at depth two.
And so on.
It is best to keep this state travelling
with the message.
So that this request contains the depth
and the responses contain the depth.
Freeing the controller from having to
remember all of this.
Once the depth is exhausted, and all
getters have sent their done messages.
The final result is communicated to the
receptionist.
The receptionist was the one who kept
track of which client
requested which URL, and it will send back
the appropriate response.
To the client.
This is the whole process, which we will
implement in the following?
What we will do, requires the use of some
web client.
I will be using the async-http-client
library.
As given in this artifact here.
Then, we need to write a getter for
processing the body which was retrieved.
Then we step up and able to write the
controller,
which takes care of the getters and all
links encountered.
And finally, we will think about the
receptionist and how that manages the
controller?
Let us start with the most simple example,
which is
also given at the top of the documentation
for AsyncHTTPClient.
First, we create an instance of this
class, and store it away.
This client is able to perform multiple
requests and it will catch connections to
servers being quite efficient.
The client will be used by the get method.
We give a URL as a string, and we expect
back, the body again as a string.
So, we call client, prepare get for the
URL.
Execute, this gives us back a future, but
not a scalar future.
When which we call get.
And this will wait until the response is
there.
So we have the response here to deal with.
Then we check the restart,
return status code.
If it is not an error code, then we look
at the first 128 kilobytes of the body.
And give that back.
Otherwise, we reply with a bad status.
And they reply in a synchronous method
like this one.
of a bad result is done by throwing an
exeception as we know.
This looks very simple,
but it is also problematic.
The problem is precisely here.
Here we block until the web server has
replied, and given
us the whole body and we have stored it in
memory.
If we, for example, use this method, from
an actor, then this actor will be blocked.
It will not be able to execute anything
else, until this finishes.
Which means that during this time the
actor is
deaf to other requests.
For example, we will not be able to send
it's a request to cancel the operation.
The other problem is that blocking in this
fashion wastes one thread.
On our machine, and in the virtual machine
you can have a
few thousand threads, but for sure you
cannot have millions of them.
And you can have millions of actors.
So there is a mismatch, and we should
always think
that we should not waste threads, because
they are a finite resource.
How do we fix this?
Well, we still use the same client.
And, as the name implies, it is an
AsyncHttpClient, so
it is capable of performing the operations
in a non-blocking fashion.
First, we do the same thing, but we stop
at the execute.
This gives us back a future.
We want to adapt this into a scalar
feature, so
we construct a promise as you have seen
two weeks ago.
The feature returned by acing HTTP client
is not a Java YouTube concurrent feature.
It has some added functionality, namely
that you can add a listener.
When this future is completed, this
listener, which we register runnable on,
will be run.
So, this gets executed.
So, when we call f.get in this code, it
will
not block, because we know that it has
been completed.
Running this runnable will need an
executer.
Because it is a task which is to be run
asynchronously.
And that is a common theme, that, theme
that you will need,
a thread pull in the end on which to
execute these tasks.
In the
end, we need to return a future.
And you get the future from the promise
by saying p.future.
AsyncHttpClient is
a java library, using java and its own
futures.
So what we have done here, is an essence.
A mapping, from, the listenable future of
AsyncHttpClient to scalar futures.
I have included this here to demonstrate a
common pattern.
If you have an event based source for
something.
And you want to wait for a single-shot
event like in this case.
It is best to wrap things in a future, and
expose that as an API.
Then if someone needs a synchronous
version, they
can still await if they really need to.
But, being asynchronous as the default is
good for reactive applications.
That was the main lesson to be learned
here.
The reactive application needs to be
non-blocking and event-driven from top to
bottom.
If there is one blocking piece in it, it
will infect all other code which tries to
call it.
Therefore, watch out, and try to use
asynchronous libraries where possible.
Now that we have the ability to read
documents from the
web, the next step is to extract the links
from it.
To illustrate the process, I've sketched a
small HTML document here.
With head and body sketched out.
And yet, we have one link in here.
Finding the link targets in this document
proceeds in two steps.
The first one is to find all the anchor
tags in it.
Which is done by the regular expression
given up here.
We use it to find all matches in the body.
And we iterate over all of the ones we
find.
The anchor corresponds to what we have
found here.
The regular expression has a capturing
group here.
Which matches the attributes of the anchor
tag.
And we can get them in here, by using the
subgroups method.
which will give us a list of all captured
groups, there will be exactly one in this
case.
And we match it with the second regular
expression.
The goal of this one is
to extract precisely, this part of the
string which we are interested in.
It could be either with double quotes or
with, surround
with single quotes, or it could be a bare
string.
Since the findAllMatchIn method here
returns an iterator, and we transform the
contents of it into steps, to a string.
We will return an iterator
of strings from the Find Links method.
After these preparations we can get ready
to write our first Actor.
The getter will receive a URL string, and
a depth, which is an integer.
And in this case we pass them with a
constructor.
Because the getter will be a single shop
actor and terminate after it has done its
job.
Within it, we first
need to ask the web client to get the URL
for us.
This will return a future, as we have
programmed.
What we then want to do, when this future
completes?
We want to tell the actor about it, so
that it can act on this new information.
In case we get a success, which contains
the
body stream, we send that body to the
actor.
If it is a failure,
we send the failure also but wrapped is a
status failure.
This operation is so common that Akka
contains a
pattern for it, which you can import as
Akka.pattern.pipe.
And then, it simplifies to this.
As you have also seen with the combinators
on collections, for example, we
can get rid of the points and the
parenthesis in this expression as well,
to make it look like this.
This reads quite naturally, WebClient get
url pipeTo self.
We have seen that the actors context is
the machine which makes it run.
And in particular, there is a dispatcher
in it, which
is capable of executing the mailbox when
it is not empty.
We can get this by saying
context.dispatcher.
And make it implicitly available here.
Since both
get, and pipe to, need a way to run their
tasks.
Get needs an executor, and pipe to needs
an execution context.
The actors dispatcher implements both
interfaces.
But due to a design deficiency in Akka,
which will
be fixed in the future release this class
is currently necessary.
Now that we have arranged for the data to
arrive at the actor.
We need to write down it's behaviour,
which will happen in this case.
If we get a string, which is the body,
then we use our find links method.
To get an iterator of all the links.
And for each of those links.
We send them in a message.
Context has another nice method,
which is called parent.
Remember, that every actor was created by
exactly
one other actor, and that is its parent.
We can access it like so, which gives us
an actor ref.
Then we send the message, to check the new
link
we've found at the depth, which we have
been told.
Once we have communicated all the links
back to our parent, we stop.
Which means sending the parent a done
message, and stopping ourselves.
In case of a failure, we just send the
done right away and stop.
What we have learned here, is that actors
are run
by a dispatcher, which is potentially
shared among multiple actors.
And this dispatcher is also capable of
running futures.
The next actor which will, we'll be
writing, is the controller.
And in that one, we would like to log the
progress which is made.
Logging is also something which is handled
by Akka.
There are many flavors to solve this
particular problem.
And many frameworks out there.
The, the solution which we chose.
is specific to actors in the sense that
it is focusing on not blocking the entity
which wants to do the logging.
The obvious way to achieve this is not to
perform any
I/O like writing to the disk or to the
network directly.
But to pass that off as a task to a
dedicated actor.
Because we know that sending to an actor
is a non-blocking operation.
You can set the overall log level with
the setting akka.loglevel.
I put it to debug in this example.
You can conveniently use the logging, by
extending the actor
trait with actor logging, which will give
a log method.
that returns the logger for this actor.
The source information provided by this
logger will contain the actors name.
So there you have a case, why it
is very important that you properly name
your actors?
Here we simply log a debug statement that
we recieved a certian message given here.
There is a very simple syntax using this
pair of
braces to denote something which needs to
be put in.
Without further adieu, we will look at
what the controller now does.
Remember, the job of it was to accept the
check messages, for certain URL's.
And, once everything is done, to send back
the overall result.
The result needs to be collected
somewhere.
And this is the cache here, which is a set
of
strings and the strings will be the links
which were visited.
Whenever a check request arrives, we log
it at debug level to see the progress.
Then, if the cache already contains the
URL we don't need to do anything about it.
Or if the maximum depth is zero, we don't
need to do anything about it.
But otherwise, we need to create a new
getter, tell it
about the URL to fetch, and decreasing the
depth by one.
This is created using actorOf, which gives
back the ActorRef.
And we need to keep track of all the
children we have created.
This is kept in the second set named
children up here, which is a set of
ActorRef's.
Finally this URL will have been visited,
so we add it to the cache.
The getter which we have just created
will go to the web client, ask it,
retrieve the document, get back the links.
And will send other check requests at
depth minus
one because that's what we told it to do?
And at some point it will be finished and
then it will send a Getter.Done.
At this point, we remove it from the
children set.
And once no getter is running anymore, we
know that
the whole process is finished.
So we tell our parent the result.
The result is just the set of links which
we have encountered here.
At this point, it is important to note
that we are sharing the cache here.
If we would have used a var cache with a
mutable set instead,
then sending that to the parent, could
have disastrous effects.
For example, this controller might be used
to process another query, keeping the
cache.
Would be a valid use case, but then the
result which had been sent back
to the parent, points to the same set,
which is mutated by this actor.
And then the other actor will be confused,
as to
what the contents of the set are.
It is much better to prefer using
variables here, which point to immutable
data structures.
This way they can safely be shared as is
done here.
And that is the third point, which we have
encountered on our journey, the third
lesson we learned.
The controller and getter which we have
written so far, play
well together as long as the web client
always yields a result.
But what if for example, a web server
takes
really long to respond or does not respond
ever?
For this we need to forsee a time out.
A simple possibility is to use another
function of the actors context, the
capability to
set or receive time out.
This receive time out is a timer which
is reset, restarted after the processing
of each message.
So whether we get a check Or a
Getter.Done, or even this receive timeout,
once we have processed it, the receive
timeout will be reset again to ten
seconds.
When it expires, we get,
namely, this ReceiveTimeout object here,
and in this
case We tell our our children to abort.
Of course we need to code this
functionality in the Getter as well.
That we can see here.
We add a new case, case abort in which we
just stop.
In order to support services like the
ReceiveTimeout, Akka includes
a basic scheduler.
The focus of this scheduler implementation
is on supporting a very high frequency
of scheduled tasks, but also very frequent
cancellation of these.
The flip side of this is that it is not
terribly precise.
It's main use is to schedule the sending
of a
message to an actor at a future point in
time which
is the first variant given here.
The object which is returned from
scheduleOnce is a cancellable,
which can, which you can use to cancel the
task.
But be aware that there might be a
race condition between the task firing and
you cancelling.
So it is possible to receive the message
in the target actor after cancel has been
called.
This is usually not very problematic
because often it is the Akka itself which
schedules the message it wants to receive
later,
and then the Akka can just store away the
knowledge that it has canceled the task.
And can then ignore the message should it
arrive nonetheless.
There are 2 other variants, this one more
for Scala and this one
more for Java, for running an arbitrary
block of code after the delay.
But these 2 methods should be used with
care.
We could have implemented a timeout in a
different fashion,
for example, if we wanted to have a
timeout which fires
ten seconds after the controller starts,
and not ten seconds after
the last message was processed, then we
might use the scheduler.
The context gives you access also to the
whole system.
The system is the container in which all
actors run, and it contains many services
among others also the scheduler, and you
can ask it to
schedule once, in ten seconds, that this
block of code runs.
Now we say, that after these ten seconds,
we
want to tell all children that they shall
abort.
What is the problem you see with this
code?
Is it that it does not compile, or is it
not thread-safe, or will
the scheduled code simply not run?
Concurrently with the actor processing the
next message, and both of these codes
then, the actor, and this lock, access the
shared variable children,
and they try to modify it, or try to read
from it,
and that could have unpredictable results
if there is no proper synchronization.
And the trick was that actors encapsulate
their
states such that no synchronization is
needed.
This is a plain bar and we don't take any
locks.
It would be nice if the compiler could
tell us about this
problem and give us an error that we did
something wrong here.
That is unfortunately not yet available.
Or it would be nice if the actor could
somehow magically know
that this code shall not be executed by
the scheduler and refuse
to run it, but that also is impossible to
realize.
So, this is why you need to manually make
sure that
this problem is not one which you invite
into your code.
So how do we do this properly?
This is why I emphasize most the first
variant of the schedule
once method, which takes, besides the
delay, an actor ref and the message.
And the scheduler then makes sure that the
message is delivered, after the delay
has elapsed to the actor ref, and we get
it here in the behavior.
Here we can safely access the actor's
state,
and in this case, tell all children to
abort.
Similar issues can occur if you mix
futures and actors.
As an example we have here a simple cache
actor, which when it gets a
request to get a URL, you can look into
its cache, which is a variable here.
And if it finds something, it will reply
with the element in there.
Otherwise, it will have to go to the Web
and actually cache the document.
As we remember,
WebClient get url returns a future which
we can
use for each one to act when the body
has been received, and in this, that case
we
just update the cache and reply to the
sender.
The first problem is exactly like in the
scheduler case, this access.
to the cache, which happens from outside
of the actor's
scope, namely in the scope of the callback
on the future.
And if the actor runs at the same time,
then
both may access the cache variable, and
there might be clashes.
And once we get it here, we can safely
update the cache and reply to the client.
But this actor contains another problem.
The transformation described by the map
operation on the future,
runs the code which you give it, in the
future.
And that means that, the sender will be
accessed.
In the future.
This is problematic, because sender is
giving
you the actor
[UNKNOWN]
which corresponds to the actor, which has
sent the message, which is currently
being processed, but when that future runs
the actor might do something completely
different.
Therefore, we must cache the sender in a
local value, and when
you reference this local value in here,
then the closure which is formed
by this function literal will contain the
value itself and not the recipe
of how to obtain it, so it will not call a
sender method.
So the fourth thing we learned is that we
should
make sure that we do not refer to actors
state from
code which is running asynchronously.
For example using the scheduler or in
future combinators.
The last actor that we need to create is
the receptionist.
In this implementation the receptionist
always will accept requests but
it will make sure that only one web
traversal is running at any given time.
Thus, the receptions can be in two states.
It can either be idle waiting for the next
command.
Or a command can also already be running.
When waiting, when we get a request, we
need
to start the traversal, and switch to the
running state.
In the running state, when we get a
request, we cannot execute
it immediately, so we append it to some
queue And keep running.
When we get back a result from the
controller,
we need to shift that back to the client.
And then run the next job if there is one.
If there is none, then we go back to the
waiting state.
In our formulation of the two behaviors,
we will need helper methods.
And the first one is, run next, whose job
it is to pick the next job and run it.
Here a job is a
[UNKNOWN]
of a client, ActorRef which has sent the
request, and the url which shall be
visited.
When the job queue is empty then there is
nothing for
us to do and we go back to the waiting
state.
Otherwise we need to instantiate a new
controller, send it the work
which is to check this given url at the
head of the queue.
And here I hard-coded the depth of the
search to two.
And here we are in the running state with
this queue.
As always, it is a good idea to name
actors,
and these are controllers, so we name them
C something, but
there is one condition you may remember
that actor names need
to be unique, so we cannot call them all
just controllers.
To facilitate that, there is a variable
request number, which gets
implemented every time we execute runnext.
That means that during each run of this
method, this nuimber will be unique.
This number could also be used for example
for statistics purposes so
that you can ask the receptionist how many
requests it has already processed.
The second helper method is used to
enqueue a job.
Given a queue which is
a vector of jobs and a new job, we simply
check if the queue has a certain size.
We limit it to 3 here then we immediately
reply with a failure and stay in the
current state.
Otherwise we append it.
Now we can plug all things together, to
show the 2 behaviors in their full
glory.
First waiting, once we get a URL to check
will become runNext, off a queue with this
one job in it.
Eventually, the controller which was
spawned in here will send back a result
of links.
We look at the queue.head to find the job,
extract the client, and send the result
with the links and the job.url back to it.
Then we stop the controller because we
will want
to use a new one for the next request.
The next request
is obtained by using runNext with the tail
of the queue.
This might be empty, then we would go back
to the waiting
state, or there might be something left,
and then we stay here.
If in the running state, a Get request is
received, then
we simply enqueue the Job and stay running
as we said.
During our journey of designing an act,
actor system we have
learned how to do that but we have also
encountered the following.
Valuable lessons.
First of all, a reactive application needs
to
be non-blocking and event driven from top
to bottom.
Meaning that you should strive for the
use of only asynchronous libraries where
possible.
The simplest
libraries often have use for an executor
or thread pull, and we have seen
that the dispatcher, which runs actors, is
very useful also in that regard.
The third point was to always prefer
immutable
data structures because they can be safely
shared.
And there is no problem sending them
across thread boundaries.
The fourth point was
to always prefer context.become to model
different states of actors, and
to keep the data local to the behavior
where that makes sense.
I have shown you some examples of where a
deviation might be useful.
If in doubt always code both ways and
compare them, and choose the one which is
more readable, more clear or more concise.
And also consult with your colleagues
who will have to maintain that code.
And the fifth and very important lesson is
To not leak the actor's internal state,
to code which runs asynchronously, because
that breaks the actor moral encapsulation.
We have assembled all the pieces for our
program.
Now, we also want to see it in action.
For that, I have created a main actor.
As you have seen before, which will run
it.
The first thing we'll do is to create a
receptionist.
And then it will send a request to
this receptionist to check a well-known
website for leaks.
The reply will be received here.
It can either be a positive, in which case
we take
the set of links, convert it to a linear
structure from a
setm Sort that one, and convert it to a
string by saying
results for this URL and then on each line
is one link.
If we get the failed result, we print
failed
to fetch.
Finally, we want the application to
terminate if
no more messages are received after 10
seconds.
In that case, we get ReceiveTimeout and
stop the program.
It should be noted that the async http
client in here Has some
resources which it needs to shut down for
the JVM to properly terminate.
I have created a RAM configuration
as before using the main class aka domain
and if we run it,
we will see the output.
Results for http://www.google.com We see a
number of links were found.
The search depth was two, if you remember
correctly.
So first, it was going to that, I can tell
you, I tried it.
This gives you a redirect to google.com/
and then some very complicated cookies.
And if you follow that one, you get the
actual search page, which you
see in your browser when you open it, and
that contains all of links,
some international links I have a German
set browser, and I'm currently
in Switzerland, so you see here all of
what is on, on the front page of Google.
Now let us try to give the receptionist a
bit more work.
You may recall that we limited the queue
it
keeps to the depth of three, meaning it
will
start processing the first request and it
will queue
these three and it should fail on the
fourth one.
Running it again, we see the first
failure, here, fourth request
was rejected, then we see the result for
the first one, which we already know,
and after that We have the results for
slash one, two and three.
These are URLs on which there is nothing
to find on Google
so they turn up just link which we gave
initially as visited.
This program is of course no proper link
checker, you
would have to augment the functionality
especially in the getter.
to make it right, but I'm sure this
conserve is a
good starting point if you would ever
choose to implement one.