You have seen now all that you need to
know in order to
write actors, and have them interact with
each other, but one thing is missing.
Testing actors is integral to developing
them as we will see.
You will notice, when testing them, when
you have,
for example, chosen a messaging pattern
which does not
lend itself well to testing, and that
might be
a hint that the design is also not so
well-suited for production.
For example, if you couple components too
tightly, you will notice during testing.
Therefore, we will look now at the tools
available in the Akka toolbelt for this
purpose.
The first thing to note about actors,
remember,
is that they only interact using message
passing.
There is no way to reach into them and
to check their current behavior without
sending a message.
And all you can ever get is a message
back.
This is what I mean when I say
that tests can only verify externally
observable effects.
An example, this actor called Toggle has
two states, happy and sad.
You can ask this actor how it feels right
now, and
it will reply with either happy or sad.
And on each reply it will switch its
behavior.
How do you test this actor?
Well, there is only one way to do it.
We must send it, how are you messages, and
then we must observe
which replies we get back, and they should
alternate between happy and sad.
Akka comes with a test kit, which makes
this
task quite easy.
The central piece in it is called Test
Probe.
A Test Probe is like a little remote
controlled actor.
It's only purpose is to buffer incoming
messages in an internal
queue so that they can be inspected from
the test procedure.
When we write a test, we need to start the
whole system, and we cannot use the
Akka.main class for
this purpose, which we have used so far.
Here you can see how to explicitly create
an Actor System.
Like actors, Actor Systems also have
names.
We call this TestSys.
Then we make this system implicitly
available.
The second step is to create our actor on
the test.
We create a Toggle, and then we create a
Test Probe.
Creating a test probe also creates this
little actor inside for which it
needs the system, and the system is picked
up implicitly in this case.
Now we have two actors, the actor on the
test,
and the probe, and they can have a little
chat.
The probe sends to the toggle, how are
you, and
then the probe expects the reply back,
happy.
When we do the same thing again, the
expected reply will be sad.
When we try to send something which the
actor does not handle we did
not foresee a case for that, so the actor
will not react to this.
So we do not expect a message.
And we wait for one second, that should be
enough to verify
that no response is received.
Since we created the Actor System in this
test, we
also need to make sure to properly shut it
down.
Because otherwise the threads, which it
creates, will keep running.
You might have wondered about
system.actorOf because so far
we have only seen context of actorOf, and
the
context was that one of an actor meaning
that only an actor can create another
actor.
System.actorOf does the same thing behind
the scenes.
The Actor System comes with a so-called
guardian actor and system actorOf
sends a request to that guardian actor to
create this actor for us.
The Test Probe is a little actor which is
driven from the
outside but we can also use the test probe
from the inside.
We can run a test in the context of a
probe.
This is done by using the test kit class,
which is initialized with an Actor System.
Inside of this class the system is
available with the name system.
The trait with implicit sender makes the
internal Small actor
available implicitly, so that it will be
picked up here, where we sent messages.
The sender, which is picked up
automatically here, is named
testActor, and is an actor ref, which you
can also use in this test if you need to
send it explicitly.
The second thing to notice as, is that
we use expect message without a leading
probe dot.
This is because expect message is a method
on TestKit.
So it is directly available here.
But then the test runs in exactly the same
fashion, and at the end we
still need to shut down the system.
Some of the actors which you want to test
will have external dependencies.
For example, they need to talk to a
database or a web service of
some sort, and you do not want to use
those real ones for testing.
The traditional solution to this problem
is
to use dependency injection, to use
different,
for example, database handles during
tests,
during staging and then in production.
You can use the same approach with actors.
You could use, for example, Akka together
with Spring.
If you Google it you will find how to do
that.
We will look at a very simple solution
here which is to simply add overridable
factory methods.
For example let's
look at the Receptionist.
The Receptionist needs to create a
controller in,
under certain circumstances, and if we
hard wire
the props controller in the actor of call,
we cannot stub it out in a test.
What we can simply do is to add a
method, controllerProps, which gives these
props with the known behavior.
And this allows us to override
this method in a test to create a
different actor which, for
example, does not really go to the Web to
retrieve the links.
Or, talking about that, if we look at the
Getter, the Getter used WebClient get URL,
if we want to switch out the WebClient
from the real one which I've renamed
AsyncWebClient here.
To a fake one, we can just insert this
method as shown, and
then the test can override it.
Let us look at this in practice.
I have renamed the web client object to
AsyncWebClient, and
factored out the interface WebClient here
with the get method.
Within the getter, this def gives the
AsyncWebClient which is used here.
Next, I have prepared some code to fake a
web client.
First, we start out at a certain link and
we take the
actual html document, which shall live at
this link, from this body's map here.
And there is a links map, which for this
link also has the desired output
of the getter, the sequence of links
encountered.
Then, we create a FakeWebClient which
implements the WebClient interface.
When we get a URL we look simply in the
bodies
map and if there is none, we give a
BadStatus(404), not found.
If there is one we give it a successful
future with the body.
We can inject this into a getter as shown
here in the fakeGetter method.
This returns props describing how to
create a getter which uses the
FakeWebClient.
We say props, new getter, and then we
override in an anonymous class definition
what client
means, and we say this shall be the fake
web client, instead of the real one.
Before we can test the getter, we need one
more thing.
The getter actor sends to its parent.
And that is what we want to verify, but
the parent
is something, if we have the system create
a getter for us,
then that would be the guardian, and that
would not be
very useful because we cannot monitor what
gets sent to the guardian.
Therefore, we need to create a StepParent
for
the getter.
The StepParent is an actor which takes a
description of how to
create a child and the probe to which all
messages shall be forwarded.
It then creates the child, and whenever it
receives a message, it sends to the probe
with
the tell method, to send the message, and
to keep the original sender so that what
arrives
at the probe seems to come from the
original sender.
So it's, will seem to come from the
getter, in that case.
Before using that on the real getter, let
me show you a slight variation of this
pattern.
If we want to inspect all the messages
which are exchanged between a child and a
parent,
in both ways, then we could create a
FosterParent,
which mediates between the child and its
real parent.
The FosterParent again gets the
description of
how to create the child and the probe.
Now it
needs to remember the child actor ref
because whenever the
context.parent sends a message, then in
addition
to forwarding the message to the probe, we
also forward the message to the child.
This forward here is the same as shown
previously, so it
will use tell with the current sender as
the sender argument.
If we receive a message from another
actor, presumably from the child, then we
send it to the probe as well, but we
forward it also to the parent.
This way, this FosterParent is nearly
completely transparent
for all messages sent between parent and
child.
The only thing which does not quite work
is if one of those two would expose
the ref of this foster parent to external
actors, because for that we do
not have the necessary logic to find out
where the message should have gone.
Now we are ready to write the Getter
specification.
Class GetterSpec extends TestKit with an
ActorSystem with an appropriate
name, and I am using Scala Test with the
WordSpecLike.
BeforeAndAfterAll is needed so that after
the tests
have run we can shut down the system.
An ImplicitSender is needed, as you have
seen so that messages sent will have
the right sender.
Here we have the specification of the
Getter and it has two
test cases, and the first one we create a
StepParent for a fakeGetter.
Which starts at the first link of depth
two.
And we want to verify that we get the
right response.
The name we give to this test case, main
actor, is rightBody.
So we can see if something goes wrong.
We look into the links map.
Which we have in the test case for the
first link.
And for all links we expect, we
say, expect message, controller.Check,
link at depth two.
And finally, the getter must terminate the
exchange by saying, getter.done.
In the second test case, we try to
retrieve a URL which does not exist, and
we only expect Getter.Done.
If you installed the Scala test plugin for
the
Scala IDE, then with a right click in the
Context
menu under Run As there is Scala test
file,
if you click on it the test will be run.
And we see the bar is green, everything
has worked.
Another example we can look at is how to
test the Receptionist in isolation.
For that, we need to create a
FakeController.
The FakeController here will be an actor,
which
when it receives a check, will just sleep
for one second, simulating that something
takes, takes
time, and then it will send back the
result.
But wait a second, did I just say sleep?
Actors shall not sleep, so let's fix this.
We
can replace this by the scheduler.
Much better.
This is just test code, you might say.
But remember you need to think that actors
should never block
and not practicing it anywhere is a good
way to achieve that.
We wired this FakeController into a
FakeReceptionist.
Again by saying Props new Receptionist,
and then in an anonymous class, we
override the controller props to be
pointing to this Fake Controller instead.
The Receptionist Spec works in the same
way as
the Getter spec by using a TestKit with an
ActorSystem.
This time, with a different name, to make
it clear which
test is currently running, WordSpecLike,
BeforeAndAfterAll,
with the shutdown, and the ImplicitSender.
And here, we have the test cases.
In the first test case, we verify that the
result is returned as specified.
We create a receptionist, using the fake
one, and we send it a get for my URL.
This is tested completely in isolation, it
will
not call any getter, so any string will
do.
We expect back the message that the result
for this myURL
is exactly the set with just myURL in it.
The other thing we are going to test
is that the Receptionist properly queues
and rejects requests as we have designed.
So again we create one with the name
rejectFlood and we send it
five requests, each with a different
string so that we can disambiguate them.
First, we expect
the failed for the last one, where the
queue should be full and then
we expect the other ones exactly in the
order in which we sent them.
Running this test
will take a little longer because we built
in the
one second delay but the bar is green,
everything worked.
When testing Actor Hierarchies.
So you have collaborating actors which
work
together and some are parents of others,
you will of course want to test each actor
in isolation as much as possible.
But what you should also do is to work
your way up the hierarchy by starting out
from the leaves and then spawning the
supervisor which will create the children
actors in the test, testing them all
together.
This is more integration testing of your
actors,
and since you go from the leaves outwards,
you're adding shells on top of what you
currently have, I call this Reverse Onion
Testing.
It's like not peeling back the onion
layers, it's like putting them onto the
onion.
With the techniques
shown in this lecture, you should be all
set to begin the exercises, and
successfully complete them.
I wish you the best of luck.