This week, we will turn our view to the
last crucial missing piece.
And that is how to handle failure in actor
systems.
This model was inspired by Erlang, and
it is centered around the concept of
supervision.
So when you have a failure, it is
contained and
delegated to a supervisor who is then
supposed to handle it.
This gives rise to the question of how
an actor's state is supposed to be
handled,
which will lead us to the error kernel
pattern,
and we'll also talk about how to persist
and actor such that its state survives a
failure.
So far we have looked at actors which
do exactly as they are told, and nothing
unforeseen
happens, but we need to concern ourselves
also with
handling the cases which we did not
foresee, and
that is what we will do in the following.
In an asynchronous system which is
completely based on asynchronous
message passing, there is the problem
where failure should go.
Normally, when you call a method, an
exception is thrown, and the
caller gets this exception and then also
is obliged to handle it.
When you send a message to an actor, that
actor
processes the message long after the call
in context is gone.
The sender has gone onto something else.
So where should failure go?
In the actor model, there's just one way
to communicate, and that is by
way of messages which means that failure
also needs to be sent as a message.
We take the exception which was thrown
inside the actor.
We reify it as a message.
And we send it, well, to whom?
One possibility would be to send it back
to that actor
which had sent the message during whose
processing we just failed.
Let's step back a bit and try to visualize
what that means.
Let's say you're standing in front of a
vending machine
and you put in the coins and you select
your product.
Which means you make a request to the
machine.
And then something goes wrong, the ma, the
machine is not
in a state where it can sell you things,
and then you
get to handle the exception.
That basically means that the customer of
the
vending machine, you, is responsible for
fixing it.
With actors we can do much better than
this.
The inspiration for how actors collaborate
is taken from how we humans work together.
Just like we form teams, actors work in
systems.
And the failure of an individual
is handled by the team leader or, in that
case, by another actor.
In our society, we apply this pattern in a
hierarchical fashion.
Let's look at, for example, a big
corporation.
This
big corporation might be divided into
different divisions.
For example, marketing, sales,
and engineering.
And engineering, for example,
might have different product teams.
And
within the storage group, for example, we
might have the file systems and
the database.
All of these teams on all levels have
multiple members and one leader.
The leader of the whole corporation is for
example the CEO.
And in the database team it might be the
project leader for the database.
Let's say that in this team someone falls
sick.
Now the leader has to either redistribute
the work
among the remaining members of the team or
ask
for help and as additional resources.
If he cannot fix the problem himself he
will therefore have to escalate it to his
boss.
The boss of the storage coop might then
decide either to pull in resources from
file systems
or if they're underwater as well She might
just
escalate it to the leader of the
engineering department.
And this goes on,
onto the top, making sure that every
failure is eventually handled.
This is precisely how actor systems do it
as well.
Resilience means recovering from a
deformation.
So to get back to the proper shape and
form
and function that it used to have before
something went wrong.
In order to achieve this we need two
things.
First of all containment which means that
a failure is
isolated such that it does, cannot spread
to other components.
The actor
model naturally takes care of this because
we
have seen that actors are fully
encapsulated objects.
The second is, that failure cannot be
handled by the failed component, because
it is presumably compromised, so the
handling
of failure must be delegated to another.
For actors, this means that one other
actor needs
to decide what to do with a failed actor,
whether it shall be terminated or
restarted.
Of course, it would be confusing if this
decision would somehow be
taken by more than one actor, because they
would have to collaborate.
So in practice, it needs to be done by
exactly one.
And this means that if you look at
supervision, there is a hierarchy which is
formed.
So if you have one actor here, let's call
it top, which supervises three other
actors,
A, B and C.
It will handle all their failures, and in
order to do that it must also be able to
restart them, or when it terminates them
to recreate
them to get the service up and running
again.
This means that top is not only the
supervisor
of A B and C but also its parent.
The two hierarchies which are formed, the
supervision hierarchy and
the creation hierarchy are the same.
In Akka, we call this mandatory parental
supervision.
How does this supervision hierarchy
reflect in code?
Let us look at one example.
This class called manager is an actor
which supervises two children.
It creates a DBActor and it creates and
ImportantServiceActor.
Let's call them
db and service.
This miniature much declare what shall
happen in case of failure.
We say override val supervisorStrategy to
override the default
.The default would restart all children
when they fail.
We want to do something else here.
So we say we have a OneForOneStrategy.
I'll cover variance in a second.
And then we give it what we call a
decider.
This is a partial function here with three
cases.
In case, we have a DBException from the
DBActor.
Then we restart it.
This will probably tell the DBActor to
reestablish the connection to the database
in hope that the failure was transient.
And will be fixed by reconnecting.
The second case describes what shall
happen
when the actor receives a kill message.
You can write, actor, bang, kill, which is
a case object.
And this is handled automatically by the
actor context.
And, which will make the actor
throw an exception, namely this
ActorKilledException.
And then the supervisor gets to decide
what to do, and usually the intention was
to
stop the actor, so that's what we do here.
But what if this very important service
actor fails?
This manager depends on it.
It cannot function without it.
So it cannot fix the problem itself,
hence it escalates this exception to its
own supervisor.
We have started from the premise that
failure is communicated as a message, just
as anything else between actors, hence it
also acts like a message.
It is sent and processed like a message.
This means that the supervisor strategy
declared inside the actor has full
access to the actor's state, just as any
message processing would have.
Processing failure messages
is sequentially serialized with all other
messages as well.
They go through the same mailbox.
Which means that no normal message can be
processed while a failure is currently
being handled.
In this example, we use this power to
implement a bit more refined scheme.
First we create a map restarts from
ActorRef to integers.
Which defaults to zero for the values.
Then when we get a DBException,
we actually look in the restarts map for
the sender of this failure.
And check, if it has failed too many
times,
then we remove this actor from the map and
stop it.
Otherwise, we update the map, increasing
the failure
count for this actor and issue a restart.
This is just a very simple example to make
it fit on one slide.
You can do any kind of processing you
would like.
It is important to note that this should
be a value and
not a death.
It would also work if you write overwrite
death but then
this strategy would be re-instantiated
during the handling of each failure.
And that is usually not what you want and
it is not particularly efficient.
There are variations on what you can
apply.
For example, the one for one strategy
always deals with each child actor in
isolation.
If a decision shall apply to all children,
then there is also the all for one
strategy.
Which means that the supervisor is
supervising a group
of actors which need to live and die
together.
Let me show you an example of this.
We have a supervisor here,
who's just super.
With three
children,
A, B and C.
Now if A fails.
So I go, send the failure.
The supervisor gets to decide what to do.
And if
it will restart A, then all of them will
restart.
If A would have been stopped, all three
would have been stopped together.
Both the one for one strategy and the all
for
one strategy can be configured to include
a simple rate trigger.
This means you can tell it to only allow a
finite number of restarts.
Here's an example, one for one
strategy allows the specification of more
arguments.
This max number of restarts, ten, means
that after
ten restarts a restart would turn into a
stop.
The other feature which is demonstrated
here as well
is that this can be applied within a time
window.
So if there come ten restarts within one
minute it's still fine.
The eleventh in the same minute will be
turned into a stop.
An actor is restarted in order to recover
from failure.
The benefit of this is that other actors
can
continue communicating with the service
provided by this actor.
Before and after the restart without
having to fix the problem.
That was the initial goal.
But this requires that the identifier by
which other actors
refer to this actor must be stable across
a restart.
In Akka, the ActorRef stays valid during a
restart.
It is just the actor object behind it
which is
swapped out during the restart as we will
soon see.
There are other ways to implement that.
For example, in Erlang, actors which fail
always terminate.
And they are replaced by new ones.
In order to give them a stable identity,
there is
a name registry into which the so called
PID is registered.
One issue with this approach is that
clients of this registry must be
able to cope with the fact that a name
might be registered at one time.
Then when the actor fails there is no name
registered.
And then once it is restarted the name
refers to a different actor.
An actor in Akka has a richer life cycle
than a
PID in Erlang, which is a trade-off
between this additional
complexity and avoiding the race
conditions during restart.
So far we have talked about restarts in an
abstract vision, saying that it fixes
the problem.
But what does that really mean?
Expected error conditions within an actor
are typically handled explicitly.
The sender will get a failure response as
we have seen in the bank account example.
It is the unexpected errors which we
are concerned with here and anything
unexpected.
So an exception which is thrown which we
did not foresee, for example,
indicates that some part of the actor
state has become invalid.
The decision whether a possible failure is
treated as an expected or
an unexpected error Is one which needs to
be taken on a case-by-case basis.
But the goal of the actor model is to keep
each actor as clean
as possible, concerned only with its own
business, and have the
supervisor handle the rest.
As a consequence, the supervisor's
action will be course-grained.
It can only stop, restart or escalate.
In this sense the only safe action a
supervisor can take upon a restart is
to cause the actor to install its initial
behavior to return to the initial state.
Because that supposedly is a valid one.
Now how does an actor's lifecycle look
like?
At first, it will be started.
This happens when the parent calls context
dot actor of and giving it the props.
When the call return this start action
will be scheduled to run asynchronously.
The first thing which happens
is that the actor context, the actual
machinery, creates a new actor instance.
This will run the constructor of the actor
clause.
The second is to run a method, a call back
called preStart.
This is executed before the first message
is processed.
Until this point, messages may have
already been buffered in the actor's
mailbox.
The actor
then begins processing messages and maybe
it
fails here.
The failure reaches the
machinery, the actor context, which
will then consult the supervisor what to
do.
Once the verdict comes back, let us say
it was a restart.
What then happens is
that, on this actor instance, another hook
is called, namely
preRestart.
Then this instance is terminated.
The object is not referenced any longer.
It will collect it by the virtual
machine's garbage collector.
The next is that a new instance of the
actor will be created.
Again, a hook is run, this time
postRestart.
No messages will be processed between the
failure and here.
The message which caused the failure will
not be processed again,
because presumably it could also have been
the cause of the failure.
Then after postRestart, the actor resumes
its actions.
After a while, let us say the actor wants
to stop.
It signals this to the actor context,
which will initiate
the stop procedure.
As part of this,
the last hook will be run
called postStop.
And then, the actor instance will be
terminated.
Restarts, so all of this, can happen zero,
one or any number of times.
But an actor will always have one start
event and one stop.
And after the stop, it is
completely terminated and cannot be
restarted anymore.
And it should be noted that at this place,
this is where the actor's state is cleared
out, because
it was supposedly invalid and replaced by
a new one.
No internal actor state can cross this red
line.
The actor lifecycle is reflected in source
code by the actor lifestyle hooks.
Here we have the preStart method, which
does not get an argument.
preRestart, we know the reasons by which
the
restart was caused, and we may know the
message.
Which was processed while the actor
failed.
The default behavior is to stop all
children at this point.
Because child actors are considered part
of an actor's state.
Then by default the postStop hook is
invoked.
After a restart, postRestart again is
invoked with the reason.
And this defaults to preStart.
And the postStop hook is the one which
will
be called after the instance is no longer
running anymore.
Let me illustrate two different ways to
use these hooks on to examples.
The first one is an actor representing a
database connection.
This DBActor, in its constructor calls
DB.openConnection
to return a handle to a database.
When the actor is stopped, it needs to
close this connection.
By default, during a restart of course the
constructor will rerun, after
the restart and before the restart the
handle will have been closed.
This means that the actor is fully
reinitialized during a restart.
Another possibility is an actor which has
external state.
This listener will register with a source
to receive events.
In preStart it sends to the source a
message, RegisterListener
self, which means it registers its
ActorRef to receive the
notifications which it desires.
As we have seen the
ActorRef stays valid over restart, so
preRestart,
we do nothing.
And postRestart, there is no reason
to re-register, because we did not
unregister.
Only in postStop do we send to the source
the unregistration command.
It is important to note that actor-local
state cannot be kept across the restarts.
Remember the red line.
Only external state like this registration
can be managed in this fashion.
You will also have noticed that by
overriding preRestart to do
nothing, we also do not stop child actors
upon a restart.
In this case, the actor context will
recursively restart the child actors,
which were not stopped.