The error kernel pattern allows us to keep
important actors relatively safe.
But there are cases where we need to not
lose state at all.
We need to persist it.
In this lecture we look at how actors can
do that.
The first observation is, that losing
state future
restart is not the only thing which can
happen.
Not only our software can be buggy, our
hardware can make mistakes too.
For example the computer's power supply
might fail or there might be
a power outage in the whole region and the
beta center goes down.
In that case, the running state of actors
will
be lost, because it is only kept in
memory.
If we need to keep that state across, for
example the power outage, then we
need to make sure that is stored on a hard
drive, for example.
When the power comes back on, we can then
read the last persistent state and start
from there.
The same principle applies when it comes
to a softer source of the restart.
The reason why we did it might be
different,
but what needs to be done is exactly the
same.
We need to store the result of successful
processing.
And once a failure has happened, when we
recover from it we need to recreate
the current running state so that we can
keep running from where we left off.
There are two main ways in which state can
be persisted.
The first is to have the actor mirror a
persistent storage location and
do in-place updates of both.
So when the actor's state changes, the
persistent location is also updated.
This persistent location could be files,
in the file system.
Or it could also be a record in a
relational database.
The other way is to not persist the state
itself, and update it.
But to persist the changes which are
applied to state.
And this is done in an append-only
fashion,
meaning that these change records will
never be deleted.
They will only be added to.
The current state can then be derived by
reapplying all changes from the beginning.
There are obvious benefits to persisting
the state.
And doing in-place updates.
The first is that recovery of the latest
state can be done in constant time
because you just need to go to that one
memory location and read it back.
The other advantage is that the data of
all you needed for storage
depends only on the number of records and
not on their rate of change.
It is easy to see that if you persist the
changes you will always persist at least
as much and most of the time much more
data than if you would just persist the
records themselves.
But there are also benefits to persisting
the changes.
For example if you do that you can go back
to any point in time and replay history.
Audit what happened in which order or
restore a certain state.
Say from last Thursday,
because you need to either rerun what has
happened or you
need to discard all the changes which have
been done since then.
During a replay, the code which handles
the processing could also
have, for example, been fixed, because it
had a bug previously.
And that means that errors which crept
into the current state can be corrected
retroactively.
This is not possible if you only store the
current state, because it will have the
bug in it.
You all have seen the third advantage at
work.
For example, if you were shopping at a
large shopping site on the Internet
which we all well know, if you look at the
shopping cart and you put an item in.
It is in the shopping cart.
You might
continue shopping, take it out, replace it
by another one, and finally, once you go
to the checkout, the current contents of
the shopping cart is what you actually
buy.
If you only persist that, then the whole
history is lost.
But it might be very interesting to keep
statistics.
For example, this refrigerator has been
replaced in
50% of the cases by that other one,
and people can then learn from other
people's decisions.
Of course, these insights can also be used
inside the company itself to organize
their logistics processes.
Storing all these events takes a lot
of space, but space is comparatively cheap
nowadays.
And therefore, if profit can be made from
analyzing these data, then it's well worth
it.
The fourth advantage has to do with
hardware and how that works.
If you write to an append-only stream, you
can write a much higher
bandwidth to IO, to network devices and
also to hard disks.
The reason is, that in-place updates need
to at least appear
to occur in exactly the order in which
they were given.
Which limits
the possibilities for optimization.
Finally, persisting immutable data
has the advantage we have seen throughout
the functional programming course.
Anything which cannot possibly change can
be freely shared and replicated.
There is no need to synchronize access.
And whether you store an event stream to
one, two, or three
locations does not make a difference.
This
point allows the benefits of both
approaches to be combined.
Consider an actor which wants to persist
its state.
It writes, events describing all the
changes, into a event log.
Since this log is immutable, another
process could take these data,
and feed them into a database offline.
From which the actor could then
retrieve the latest persistent state in
constant time.
Doing that for all changes can be the
right answer in certain situations.
For example, if there are multiple readers
for that state, and not only this actor.
But if you only want to persist the state
of an actor and
put an upper bound on the time a recovery
may take.
Then you can also use snapshots.
So we have again our actor, producing the
stream of changes.
And then to the side, there are snapshots.
Which it
tags at this state when I persist that
event that was my state.
And it can do so periodically to keep the
time short between these.
And if a recovery's needed then only the
na-, latest
snapshot will be taken and all events
which came after that.
Snapshots again have the property that
they are immutable so they can
be written append-only in an efficient
fashion and they can be freely shared.
With this
background we can look at how actors
actually persist to changes.
There are two ways to do this,
Command-Sourcing and Event-Sourcing.
Command-Sourcing means that we make sure
that the actor does not lose any commands.
Since it persists them before they arrive.
So in front of the actor, or in front and
to the side we place a log.
And a command which comes in is diverted
via the log.
And goes then to the actor.
That means that all messages which are
received by the actor have already been
persisted.
The actor can then reply normally
to all requests it gets.
But how does recovery work?
Again, we have the actor.
We have the log.
During recovery, all messages which have
been logged are sent to the actor.
The actor will process them again.
It will go through the same state changes
again and arrive at
the same state that it was in before the
failure or crash.
But an actor does not only change its
own behavior it also sends messages to
other actors.
During a replay all of those messages
would of course be sent again.
As we discussed last week, sending
messages
again is a common pattern.
It is retrying in case we did not get a
reply, and the only
thing we need to do is to make sure that
the receiver can disambiguate.
Is this something I have seen already or
is it not?
For this purpose, the message types which
are handled by the log are
specially coded and they contain serial
numbers for example and identifiers
of which actor it was that possessed them.
The actor then does not send directly to
its targets.
For example, when it replies, it uses a
so-called, channel.
And the messages which arrive at this
channel will be checked.
Have they been delivered already or not?
Because the channel is also persistent.
A command-sourced actor persists all the
commands it gets before processing them.
And while recovery, it will go through all
the same actions it did while first
processing them.
But since the side effects which we are
looking at are only sending messages to
other actors The channel abstraction can
make sure
that during a replay all effects stay
local
within here.
We will see how to deal with external
effects in the next section.
The
other way of persisting an actor state is
called Event-Sourcing.
The focus here does not lie on replaying
the commands which generated this state.
Instead while processing commands, events
are emitted
which describe the state changes which are
supposed to happen.
Let's look at, at a little diagram.
We have the, commands coming in, and our
actor here.
And the actor processes the commands.
But instead of updating
its own state directly, it generates
events.
The fundamental difference between these
two is
that a command describes something which
shall hap-,
happen in the future whereas an event
describes something which has happened in
the past.
This means that for commands you do not
know yet what their outcome will be,
but for events you know what for sure
what has happened, and that cannot change
afterwards.
The events are what gets stored in
Event-Sourcing inside our log.
During a replay, the actor does not need
to see the commands again.
It will just receive the events which it
has generated from them.
And once it has reached its last known
state, it will continue processing
commands as usual.
The mechanism which is used during replay
is
that events are applied to the current
state to
produce the changed state, and that is
exactly the
same mechanism which is also used during
normal operation.
Meaning that there is no code duplication
necessary to support both use cases.
Obviously this round trip through the log
will take some time.
The log, of course, will typically be an
actor, so the events will be sent.
And then messages will be sent back.
To the actor before they can be applied.
Let us look at what that
means in an example.
Suppose we want to write an actor which
processes blog posts.
A user can send in new blog posts, but
there is also a limit beyond which posts
are accepted.
The state transitions of this actor can be
modeled by having two events.
Post Created contains the new text of the
post.
And Quota Reached signals that this user
has reached his or her
limit for example for today to post new
entries.
In order to conveniently pattern match
against all events, we
use a sealed trait from which these two
events extend.
The state of the actor is encapsulated in
this case class here,
which holds the post and the current,
status
with the new posts are allowed or not.
And the state knows how to update itself
so how
to produce the next state when an event
comes in.
If a Post Created Event is applied then we
copy
the state by appending the text to the
previous list.
If a Quota Reached event comes in, then we
switch the disabled flag to true.
It is good to keep these operations
separate, because
semantically, they don't have anything to
do with each other.
Creating posts is just about creating
posts.
And whether or not the quota was reached
at the same time is unrelated.
Therefore we have defined two distinct
event types for that.
Our User Processor Actor which uses these
types could look like this.
It starts out with an empty state which is
not yet disabled.
And then when a new post is submitted
It checks is submitting new posts
currently disabled.
If not, that's okay.
So, I iterate an event
post created with the text, but then let's
say the quota was one, so it's immediately
reached.
The emit method which I stopped out here
is supposed to send these events to the
log which will send them back eventually.
So we will see them in the behavior again.
And for each event which is received, we
update the state.
There is one obvious issue here.
If between sending the events and
receiving them back, a new post comes in.
It will perform the step, the, the check
here with the old state.
This means that we will potentially create
two or
even more posts even though only one
should've been allowed.
There are two basic choices when it comes
to when to apply the changes which were
persisted.
The first one we have just
seen applying them only when they come
back from the log.
In this case they leave the actor in a
stale state.
In the meantime the alternative would be
to apply
the, the changes immediately before they
have been persisted.
We can compare what this means in two
little flow diagrams.
We have the processor here.
And the log here.
When a new post comes in, the processor
will perform
check and then send the events to the log.
The log will write them to disk, and that
takes some time.
After a while, the events come back to the
processor
at which point they are applied.
And finally, the result is sent back.
This was emitted from the code for brevity
reasons.
Now the question is, what shall happen
with
another post which comes in at this time.
At this point, the actor's state has not
yet been updated to, to reflect the
previous post effects.
It might just be that we admit more
posts than we wanted to.
The alternative
would be to not leave the processor in a
stale state.
So, when a new post comes in, we perform
the check.
We generate the events and send them to
the log.
But we immediately apply them.
All of this happens during the same
message processing,
so it cannot be interrupted by a new post.
Eventually, the events will come back.
But we don't need to apply them.
We just need
the signal to generate
the final response.
Now if a new post comes in at this point,
the check which is performed will be done
with the newest data.
And in this case it will correctly be
rejected.
The disadvantage of the approach shown on
the right hand side is
that in case of a crash of the whole
system, the processor might not reach the
last known state.
Because the states reached here are not
guaranteed to be persisted.
In the left case, all states which
the processor was in have already been
persisted.
So it can be a recreated just as it was at
that time.
So it seems like you need to
choose between correct persistence and
correct behavior.
But in this case, there is a third way.
When a new command comes in while
outstanding events have not yet been
persisted, then the actor must simply not
respond to it right away.
It must keep it buffered until
the events come back from the persistent
store.
This will give lower performance [UNKNOWN]
lower
throughput, but it will be more
consistent.
The ability to postpone messages which can
currently not be
handled is provided by the stash trait in
our code.
.
This actor does the same thing as the last
example shown, but
when it gets a new post and was not
disabled and it has emitted the events,
it changes its behavior.
It becomes waiting for
the two events to be persisted.
This uses the stacking feature
of the behavior stack of Akka actors by
discarding equals false.
When waiting for in events to be
persisted, we treat only events.
In which case, we update the state.
And if this was the last
one we were waiting for, we pop the
behavior off the stack and
allow all messages which came in in the
meantime to be reprocessed.
They were stored in an internal stash, and
the
way they get in there is in this default
case.
Anything which is not an event is stashed
away.
When messages come back from the stash,
they need to
be pre-pended to the mailbox instead of
the usual appending.
And it is done so that the order is
retained in which they originally arrived.
This actor has the desired behavior of
persisting the events
and only then applying them, but not to
respond to new posts in the meantime.
Dealing with consistent application of
changes within an
actor is relatively easy as we have seen.
But it gets messy once we leave the actor
world.
Consider for example an addition to our
block post service
where it would cost some money to post an
entry.
This could be paid by credit card for
example.
And the actor would have to perform a
credit
card transaction every time a blog post is
accepted.
In this case, the external entity which
processes the request,
the credit card company, does not offer
any way to interact with them
in, in this actor kind of fashion where
you can apply Command or Event-Sourcing.
It is just something where you either make
a request, and then
the credit card will be charged, or you
don't, and then it won't.
What the actor needs to do in order not to
charge multiple times is to persist that
this has been done.
But unfortunately, persisting that
I have charged the credit card or even
that I will charge the credit card.
Cannot be made consistent or atomic with
actually charging the credit card.
It will always be two lines in your
program, and one will go before the other.
You need to order them in some fashion.
In this case, there is no smart way out.
There are just two choices.
If you perform the actions, so you charge
the credit card before the events
have been persisted then you achieve that
you charged the credit card at least once.
You need to do that if you need to ensure
that the credit card is charged.
If you do it the other way around.
Then the event might be persistent, but
the system might crash
right after that, so charging the credit
card might not actually happen.
In this case, the action is performed at
most once.
Which of these two you choose
depends entirely on your underlying
business model.
In summary, actors can persist their state
by persisting either incoming messages or
generated events.
Events are immutable and can be therefore
be replicated, read many times and
analyzed.
They can also be used to inform other
components as we have seen.
To recover an actor's state at any given
point in time, commands
or events need to be replayed since the
last snapshot was performed.
And while investigating how to update an
actor's state
consistently with its persistence
mechanism, we encountered
a useful utility from the Akka toolbox.
The Stash trait allows us to defer
messages which shall not currently be
handled.