In this last week of the reactive
programming course, we
will focus first on something which was
implicitly there already.
Namely, that actors as independent agents
of computation are by default distributed.
Normally you run them just on different
CPU's in the same system.
But, there is nothing stopping you from
running them on
different network hosts, and we will do
this in practice.
This means,
if you picture for example, people who are
living on different continents that
it takes some effort for them to agree on
a common truth or a common decision.
The same thing is true for actors and we
call this eventual consistency.
After that, we will talk about scalability
and responsiveness
and how you achieve these in an
actor-based system.
Rounding up all the four tenets of
reactive
programming, which were event-driven
Scalable, resilient, and responsive.
>> Actors are designed to be
distributed, and in this
lecture, we will see an example of that
using the Acacluster.
In order to fully appreciate how far
actors take us, when it comes to
distribution,
let us look at.
What the impact of network communication
is to a distributive program.
compared to communication within the same
process, by calling methods for example.
We will experience several differences
when doing that over the network.
First of all, the memory is not shared
anymore.
Data can
only be shared by value because a copy
will be made.
The object will be serialized, sent over
the network
connection, de-serialized, therefore, the
object will not be the same.
We have seen that a stateful object is one
whose behavior depends on its history.
But the history of the copy of the other
side of the network will not be the same
after a while than the history of the
object on the
originating node.
This has the consequence
that only immutable objects can be
sensibily shared.
Other differences include that the
bandwidth available for communication is
a lot lower when you traverse the network.
And the latency for all communication is
quite a bit higher.
You cannot transfer a network packet in a
nanosecond
but you can call a method in a nanosecond.
Together with a need to serialize and
de-serialize
objects instead of just passing along
their reference.
This makes the difference even more
severe.
But in addition to these quantitative
effects,
there are also new things which can
happen.
When you send a message over the network
It might just not
arrive, or it might arrive, and the reply
might not come back.
Thus, there is the possibility of partial
failure,
or part of your messages might not arrive,
for example, and you cannot know which
ones
that were until you get the reply back.
Another kind of failure is that data
corruption can also happen.
I know from personal experience that when
you
send data down a TCP connection for
example.
You will see about one corruption event
per terabyte data sent.
Running multiple processes on the same
computer
and having them communicate for example
Over the
localhost interface, makes some of these
differences
less severe, in number, but the
qualitative issues
stay the same.
The overarching description of the problem
is that distributed computing
breaks the core assumptions made by a
synchronous programming model.
We have talked about actors for quite
awhile now, so you know that
all of their communication is asynchronous
one way, and not guaranteed to arrive.
Hence,
they model precisely what the network
gives us.
You could say that, instead of taking the
local model and
trying to extend it to the network, actors
took the inverse approach.
Looking at the network model and using
that on the local machine.
The next feature of actors is that they
run so fully isolated from each other that
from
the outside they all look the same.
They all just, ActorRefs.
Regardless where they live it will be the
same sending a message to them.
This is what we call location
transparency.
The current semantics in feature set
offered by [UNKNOWN] actors have
been reached by rigorously treating
everything as if it were remote.
And all features
which cannot be modeled in this world were
removed.
As a result, the effort of writing
a distributed program Using actors is
basically
the same as the effort of writing a local
variant of the same program.
The code itself will not look much
different, as we will soon see.
Before we can witness actors
talking to each other over the network, we
need
to look at how that is done under the
hood.
We know that actors are hierarchical and
every actor
has a name in the name space of its
parent.
They form a tree just like a file system.
Let's say we have an actor here, named
user.
This is [UNKNOWN]
Guardian actor for all actors you create.
With system actor of.
And this one creates a greeter.
This is the same as
a file system having a folder called user
and in it a folder called greeter.
All actors can have children so they are
all like folders and not like files.
When you run this program and print the
path
of this actorOf that you will show you
this.
All paths conform to the URI format.
The
uniform resource identifier.
This one has an, a
so-called authority
part, [SOUND]
and a path.
In Akka, the authority part is used to
display the address of the actor system.
In this case, we created an actor system
called HelloWorld in the Akka scheme,
so the Akka protocol designates that this
is a local Actor path.
Then with slashes, we separate the path
element.
So user is this actor
greeter is this actor.
We want to talk about actors
which use the network, so we should look
at a remote address example.
Here we have an akka system using the TCP
protocol.
Also named hello world at some IP address
or
hostname, colon and then the port at which
it listens.
This description is enough for any other
actor system
to send a message to any actor within this
one.
It will just open a TCP connection to this
IP address, and port
and try to connect to this actor system
should it have responded to that.
We have seen here two examples, a local
address for the greeter,
and a remote address.
Which for the greeter, would look like
this, this
means, that every actor is identified by
at least one
URI, it could have multiple, if for
example, the actor
system is reachable by multiple protocols
or multiple IP addresses.
Up to know we have nasty work with
ActorRef.
And the newly found ActorPath has some
relationship
to it ActorRef, which needs to be properly
explained.
Actor names are unique within a parent,
but once the terminated message has
been delivered for a child, the parent
knows that the name can be reused.
It could create an actor which has exactly
the
same name but it will not be the same
actor.
The ActorRef will be a different one.
Therefore, keep in mind that ActorPath is
just the full name of
the actor and the ActorPath exists whether
the actor exists or not.
An ActorRef on the other hand points
exactly to one actor.
Which was started at some point.
It points to one incarnation we say, of
the
actor path.
An actor path also has a tell method, we
will see that later, so you can send it
messages.
The difference is, since you don't know
that behind
this ActorPath actually an actor exists,
it cannot be watched.
You need an ActorRef if you want to use
life cycle monitoring.
In the end the difference between an
ActorRef and
an ActorPath is just one number.
We call it the UID of the
actor incarnation.
If you print an ActorRef, it looks just
like the actor path, but with a fragment
part added, which is this UID.
When communicating with remote systems, it
is necessary to talk to actors
Which you have not created and for which
you have no means to acquire an ActorRef.
You just know at which host and port the
Actor lives.
What the system's name is and where the
Actor is in the hierarchy over there.
To support this, the Actor context has
another method.
Called actor selection.
It can pass in any actor path, and it will
construct something which you can send to.
It's the only operation it supports.
And, there is one message that every actor
automatically handles.
And that is akka.actor.identify, imported
here,
which takes one piece of data, a
correlation identifier, you
can use anything you want.
This little actor here,
the resolver will perform the job of
resolving an actor path, if possible.
To the actor ref of the actor, which is
currently living under that name.
So sending
the Identify message with the pair of path
and current
sender will result in us getting back an
ActorIdentity.
In the positive case, where the actor is
currently alive, we get this one.
With some reference.
So we can tell our client that we resolved
the path, and this is the actor
ref of the actor currently.
Otherwise, the actor identity message will
contain none.
This procedure reflects that communication
is necessary.
In order to determine whether an actor
exists or does not exist.
This is why no actor refs can just be
fabricated from thin air.
They must be obtained by using identify
from
paths, if there is no other way to obtain
them.
Actor Paths do not have to be absolute.
They do not need to contain all the Actor
systems address information.
They can also be relative to the current
Actor.
When we see context.actorSelection, and
give
a relative URI without a leading slash.
Then it will be interpreted to the current
actors position in the hierarchy.
In this case,
if the current actor has a child actor
named child.
That one had a child actor named
grandchild.
And this actor selection will select it.
Just as in file system, you can use dot
dot
to signify the parent at any point in the
selection.
If the selection starts with a slash, its
anchor
will be the system's root guardian.
So you can resolve actors which live
somewhere near the top Of
the hierarchy, and where you know the
exact name of all parents.
Finally, actor selection also supports
wild cards.
So, you can, for example, send a message
to this actor selection.
/users/controllers/* to send to all
children of the controllers actor.
The ability to send to a name instead of
to an actor ref is
exploited by the akka cluster module which
we will look at next.
First, what is a cluster?
A cluster is foremost
a set of nodes, of actor systems in this
case, and
this set is defined such that all members
of
this set, so all nodes of the same
cluster, have the
same idea about who is in the cluster and
who is not.
It is like a group of people where
everybody
knows everybody else and foreigners are
known to be foreign.
This group of people can then collaborate
on a common task.
And the same can be done between actor
systems.
Let's say,
we have some.
Actor systems, some nodes, A, B,
C and D.
And these four,
all have the same idea that they four form
a cluster.
Now if we have another node here.
Called e and this node thinks it forms a
cluster
with the other four.
Then the set of a, b, c, d, and e is not a
cluster because not everyone in this set
agrees upon who is in the cluster.
Cluster membership can change over time,
of course.
And A, B, C, and D might learn of
Es existence, and finally accept E into
the same cluster.
And then the cluster would have size five.
We'll see how that works in a minute.
Clusters are formed in a form of inductive
reasoning.
It starts with one node which basically
joins itself, it declares
itself to be a cluster of size one, and
then any given node can join a given
cluster.
To enlarge that cluster by 1.
This is achieved by
sending a request to any current member of
the cluster and
then the information is spread within the
cluster than this new
one wants to join and once all the current
members have
learned of this, they agree okay it is a
good idea.
Let's accept it in.
One important property of the akka cluster
is that it does not contain any
central leader or coordinator which would
be a single point of failure.
Information is disseminated in an epidemic
fashion.
This gossip protocol is resilient to
failure because...
Every node will gossip to a few of
its peers, every second, regardless of
whether that was successful or
not, so eventually, all information will
be spread throughout the cluster.
Let's see how this works in practice.
For that, we need one more dependency,
which is the akka cluster module.
And in the configuration we need to enable
the cluster module by saying
that the akka.actor.provider must be
akka.cluster.ClusterActorRefProvider.
This configures the actor system to use a
different mechanism when creating actors
All calls to context actor of are in the
end handled by the actor ref provider,
and the cluster one supports a few
operations
that the local one cannot, as we will see.
There are several ways to apply this
configuration,
for example, you could add a file named
application.conf.
To the class path which contains this
snippet.
Or you can use Java system properties like
that on the command line.
Next, we need to write a new main program.
This actor, when it starts up, obtains the
cluster extension of the system.
Subscribes to some events.
This in, in the end works the
same way as the event stream.
And finally, it joins its own address.
If remember, the first step in forming a
cluster is that one node must
start it off, it must join itself.
Then, in the behavior of this
actor, we wait for MemberUp events, for
which we registered.
And if the member which just joined is not
the current one,
then someone else joined and then we can
do some interesting stuff.
The default configuration of the remote
communication module is
that it will start listening on port 2552
using TCP.
To make this exercise interesting, we need
of course a second node.
Since all actor systems will need to
listen on a TCP port But only 1 of
them can have the port 2552.
We need to configure a different port
for the ClusterWorker.
Setting the port is done like
this with the property
akka.remote.netty.tcp.port.
And setting it to 0 means to pick a random
one.
We don't need to know at which port the
cluster
worker lives because it will just join the
main one.
The address of the cluster main can be
derived from this worker's self address by
replacing the port with the number 2552.
And then, the worker joins
the main In this case, we registered for
receiving
not member up, but member removed events.
And
whenever the address of the removed member
is the main one.
So when the main program shuts down, this
also stops.
With these 2 main programs, we can
if we run them observe that they will
join.
But nothing much will happen.
We need to define some actor which makes
use of the cluster.
For this, we are going to modify the well
known receptionist.
To spawn the controller actors not
locally.
Using context actor of simply as local
children.
But to run them instead on
cluster nodes which are not the current
node.
How does that work?
First of all, the receptionist needs to
know who is in the cluster and who is not.
Therefore, it subscribes to member up and
member removed events.
And when it stops, it unsubscribes itself.
In response to cluster.subscribe.
The actor will always receive first the
current cluster state.
And this current cluster state has a
members list.
I convert these members to a linear
sequence from a set and
a map _.address over it to extract all the
addresses of
the cluster nodes.
Then from these addresses I filter out
the self address.
So whatever remains is not myself.
And if there is another node, so not
myself
is not empty, then I change to the active
node.
But typically, when the receptionist is
started, that happens quite
early in the program, the cluster has not
yet been formed.
So typically, the current cluster state
will contain
no members.
Therefore there is the second case that
upon member up.
If that members address is not my own
address.
I change to the active state with the
vector of size one getting just that
member.
While of 18 members we have no computing
resources In order to perform the task of
getting
url for example.
So during that time we reply through the
sender
that it failed because we have no nodes
available.
The active behavior will also have to
monitor the cluster.
Because after all, members can be added or
removed at any point in time.
When more members are added, again which
is not the self address, then we just
change to the active state with the
addition of the newly known address.
And when members are removed from this
set, we filter it out from the addresses.
And, if that was the last one, then we go
back to the awaiting members state.
Otherwise we
continue with the reduced list.
Now we get closer to the interesting part,
using the information we just obtained.
In the active state, when a get request
comes in.
We look whether the currently running
requests that is context.
children.size is less than the addresses
we know about.
Otherwise, we have one request running per
cluster node.
Lets say that is the limit and then we
reject it.
But If it is the first request which comes
in, that will always work.
So we copy the client, that's the sender
of this get request.
Then we pick an address randomly from the
list and extract it here.
And then we create a new actor A
customer which I'll show the in the next
slide, which gets the client, URL, which
is
supposed to be retrieved, and a cluster
address,
where the work is supposed to be
performed.
Please note that these two lines are
necessary because
The actor creation described in here runs
asynchronously.
Props describe how to create an actor
later.
Therefore, it is subject to the, the
same restrictions as with future
call-backs within actors.
Or scheduled actions within actors as we
have seen last week.
Finally, the customer actor.
This one is reponsible
for making sure that the given URL is
retrieved but the work
is supposed to be performed at a remote
node whose address is given here.
For that we need to create a controller.
We have props, controller here.
Props, as I said, is a recipe for how to
create an actor, and what
we have used so far is the default
behavior of creating an actor locally.
But it also supports giving other
arguments.
Here we say, with deploy and then a deploy
that is a description of how to deploy the
actor.
You can modify several things.
One of them is the scope in which it shall
be deployed.
In this case it is a Remote Scope.
We do not want to create the actor on the
local node,
we want to create it on the given node,
whose address is here.
This is the only change which is necessary
To perform the work on a remote node.
The call to context actorOf then looks
just the same, gives back an actorOf.
Sending to this actorOf looks just the
same,
but this will go over the network now.
Context.watch controller will watch this
actor
also over the network.
But the call we make here looks exactly
the same as in the local case.
There is one more detail in this actor
which needs special explanation.
It's this line here.
Whenever a message is sent for example,
here
to another actor we know that the self
reference of the enclosing actor is
automatically picked
up and passed along as the sender
reference.
This customer actor here is an [UNKNOWN]
one, it is one which is not supposed to be
seen from the outside.
What this line does, is it changes the
meaning of
who the sender of messages of this actor
shall be.
This implicit value is also of type actor
ref.
And it is available in the current scope,
which
takes precedence over implicit values
found in the actor trait.
Therefore, all messages sent by this
customer, will
appear to have been sent by its parent
instead.
Since
the consequences of this remote deployment
are not visible in code.
Let me draw a diagram to show what
happens.
The whole program starts, because we
instantiate the cluster main application
actor.
We need to mark out in which actor system
that happens.
This is.
Cluster main.
And it's guardian actor.
The app then goes on to create the
receptionist,
And when a request comes in this one will
create a Customer.
Up to this point everything has been
local.
But the customer deploys the
controller into the cluster workers
system, so we need to draw that as well.
This system also has a, user guardian.
And application.
But this application does not do anything
besides waiting for the termination of the
program.
This system has another thing which is
interesting here.
It has a remote guardian, and when the
customer deploys the controller.
What it really does is it sends a message
to this one to create the controller for
it.
This one will first create a folder so
that it can keep actors deployed from
different other systems.
And within it, it will create a marker
for, that it was
user, app, receptionist, customer, and so
forth.
And then it will finally create
The controller actor.
These here are
not really actors.
They are just names inserted such that,
the controller can be found for remote
communication.
But the controller will be the child actor
of the customer
logically.
So when in the controller we say,
contexts.parent, the message will go here.
Then as in
this link checker example, it will spawn
getters as needed during the retrieval of
the URL.
Now that we have successfully remote
deployed
the controller, we just need to supervise
it.
As usual, there was the receive timeout,
in which case We unwatch the controller
and say, the retrieval has failed, because
we didn't get anything in time.
Note that deathwatch works exactly the
same even though the controller
is remote deployed.
So in that case, we also give a failure
message.
If we get back a successful result.
Again we unwatch and send back the
successful result.
And then whatever happens after any of
these three has occurred, we need to stop.
And this stop is recursive, so once this
parent actor is stopped the
controller is stopped with it.
We need to explicitly annotate the type of
this
partial function literal here because
galas type inference would
not be able to figure that out without
help
a when it comes to the and then
commonator.
I have loaded these actors as well into
the
Eclipse project so that we can try it out.
First here you see the cluster worker with
the code that you already know.
Note that the web client will now be
called in the cluster worker so
this is where we need to clean up the
resources of the async web client.
The ClusterMain is like the
original main program, but it has been
adapted as shown to
watch for cluster events and to join
itself in the beginning.
And in the behavior, when we're, when we
receive the MemberUp event and
the member's address is not our own Then
we know that there is a cluster worker.
So I have written a small function get
later to use this system scheduler
to send a get request to the receptionist
after a certain delay which is given here.
So after 1
second we retrieve google.com.
After 2 seconds, we try two parallel
queries.
One of them should fail because there's
just one cluster worker.
And then we try two more.
In the run configuration for the cluster
main, I have
set the necessary option to switch on the
clustering support.
And here is another option, which can be
set We say
the cluster shall not start unless there
are at least two members.
For the cluster worker, as mentioned, we
need to configure the remote port
to be automatic.
And then there is one more option which
I've set, which is called auto down.
Which I will explain in the following.
So, we run the cluster main.
It starts up.
Informs us that the node akka tcp main on
port two, five, five, two.
Is in the joining phase but nothing has
happened yet.
When we start up, the cluster worker, the
program will start to run, and
now it has finished, so we can look at the
logs.
This was the line which we had already
seen.
Then, the cluster worker running on the
[UNKNOWN] port is also seen as joining.
Then That, this here, it says the leader
is moving
node 2552 to up and the other one also to
up.
I told you there is no single point of
bottleneck in akka cluster.
Although it does have a leader.
Now this seems to be contradictory but it
is not so.
The leader is not elected.
It is one special node.
Any node can be the leader.
And it is just statically determined
by this set of node addresses.
They are sorted in a certain format
and then always the first address which is
in the membership list will be
the leader.
And since everybody agrees on who is in
the list and on the sort order.
Everybody will see the same as the leader
without the need for communication.
Once the nodes are up, the program goes on
to retrieve the page from
Google.com.
Then we launched two queries in parallel.
One of them gets rejected by too many
queries.
The other are successful.
Finally, we had modified the main program
such that it
will shut down after the retrievals have
all been performed.
So the leader is moving itself first to
leaving and then to exiting states.
And then the whole program shuts down.
There is some communication afterwards
between nodes in the end.
First this one shuts down and the other
one has
also automatically shut down.
This one has gone by a different route
which I will explain in the following.