In the previous part of this lecture, we
have extended the
link check example to run on a cluster of
nodes, and we
have seen that cluster start up and shut
down, but how
did that actually work, what were these
states that we have seen?
When a cluster node wants to join, it
enters the joining state.
That was the first one we have seen.
We've also seen that in the example,
nothing happened until the second node
joined, because we had defined that the
cluster needs at least size two to work.
But what happened then is that the node
became up.
This transition was made by the leader,
when the leader determined that
all members of the cluster had seen all
new nodes joining.
When the program was done, the cluster
main shut itself down, and
it did so by declaring that it wants to
leave the cluster.
This intention is expressed by going to
the leaving state.
This transition can be done by any node,
without the leader having anything to do
with it.
The information that the node wants to
leave needs to be disseminated to
all others, so that they are prepared to
remove it from the membership list.
Because otherwise, not all would have the
same
picture, and it would not be a cluster.
In order to do that in an orderly fashion,
the leader
determines when all have seen.
And moves
the node to the exiting
state.
And this is the
signal for all the other nodes to
remove this entry from their membership
list, at their next convenience.
This was the sequence of states which the
cluster main went through.
From joining to up, then performing what
it was
supposed to do, and then leaving via this
path,
until it shut itself down.
The ClusterWorker lift the
cluster afterwards by is, a little bit
different route which was
via a state called unreachable.
And, we'll talk about that next.
In order to form a cluster, everyone
within it
needs to be in consensus about who is in
it.
That was the definition of it.
Therefore, only if the members of the
cluster
can communicate with each other, can the
cluster function.
This means that the reachability of all
cluster members
must be closely monitored, and once one
becomes unreachable,
special action needs to be taken.
In order to check the ability to
communicate, every node in
a cluster is monitored by several others
using so called heartbeats.
That means that periodic messages are
sent.
And once they are not received anymore
there is presumably a problem.
Now if you have a very large cluster it is
impractical to have everybody
monitor everybody else, because then the
number
of connections needed for that, the number
of communication pairs, would be roughly
one half n squared which can be a lot.
Therefore, we apply a technique of that
the neighbors monitor each other.
How do we define neighbors?
Let's say we have a cluster with seven
nodes.
One, two, three, four,
five, six, and seven.
Since these nodes all agree that they are
the seven which are in the
cluster and you can apply a sort order on
their addresses,
every of these seven nodes can draw the
same kind of ring with
the same order of the nodes in it.
And then we could
say that one monitors two and three, two
monitors three and four, and so on.
This would be a picture if every node
would monitor two others.
For a more tight mesh, we could also make
it
three, for example, then it would look
like this.
Let us say that node five
fails.
It was monitored by
two, three, and four.
Eventually,
these three nodes will not receive a
heartbeats from five anymore.
But, heartbeats cannot be sent at a one
millisecond interval.
That would just be too much.
So, let's say you send a heartbeat every
five seconds.
Then, within five seconds, the three will
notice
that the first heartbeat was not received.
But, that might just have been a fluke.
The next one might still arrive.
So triggering when one is absent is
usually too finicky.
So what you need to wait for is that two
or three fail and then it takes maybe 15
seconds.
And the more monitors you have, the higher
the chance is that you get
the signal a bit earlier.
So let us say, node 4 was the first to
detect that 5 is down.
Then this information will be included in
the gossip messages.
And four talks randomly to all the other
nodes in the ring and spreads the
information.
So, it might be communicated to six, and
then
to two, but six also keeps talking to one,
and so on.
And eventually, all of them will know that
node number four has seen that five is
down.
For a cluster to be hampered in its
function, it
is enough that one of the communication
links does not work.
Unless messages can be routed
by other nodes.
So if 4 and 5 cannot talk anymore,
and if, for example, the routing protocol
does not messages to
go via one, for example, then the cluster
cannot function.
And that is the case in Akka that supports
only direct messages at this point.
This means that as soon as one node sees
another
node as unreachable, that node has to
be considered unreachable for the whole
cluster.
And that means that the cluster currently
is inconsistent.
Because these six nodes think, that that
one is not part of the cluster.
But this node, well it might not have
crashed.
Someone might have pulled the, the network
cable out from it, so it
cannot communicate anymore.
And the last state that it has is that
everybody is part of the cluster.
But as this node is also monitoring other
nodes - namely six,
seven, and one - it will conclude after
some period of time that they are down.
It will start monitoring these instead to
see if they are still up.
So in the end, the clusters will split.
Five would be in a cluster on its own,
and these nodes would also be in a cluster
on its own.
But in order to form these clusters, nodes
need to be removed properly,
so that these six nodes can declare that
five is no longer in it.
Going to back to this state diagram,
unreachability is not really a state.
It is a flag, because I know it can become
reachable after a period of time.
For example, someone plugs in that network
cable again, and everything happily starts
over.
But unreachability is important enough to
be part of this diagram.
And nodes can become unreachable at all
times, at any time.
And if the did not really crash as I said,
they can become reachable again.
In order to form a new cluster, without
the unreachable node, that node needs to
be communicated that it is leaving.
But it is not the same kind of leaving
as we've seen over here.
Because, the node went down.
This transition here is a policy decision,
because you cannot in all cases say
whether
the node is really down or whether it
is transiently unreachable, whether it
will come back.
So in the end, there will be some either a
program or
an operator monitoring the system, and
deciding after which
an unreachability period to move a node to
down.
Once that has happened, and once that has
properly been disseminated
among all of the remaining cluster nodes,
the leader removes the node.
Now we can recapitulate the whole history
as seen by the ClusterWorker.
It's, it was joining it saw the main
joining and then up, and once the
main program stopped, the ClusterWorker
detected it as being unreachable.
Then I have shown you that I set an option
called autodown in the worker.
Which means that as soon as a
node becomes unreachable, this transition
happens automatically.
So as soon as that failure detector
flagged that the
main is unreachable, it went from up via
unreachable to down.
And that means that there was just one
node in that cluster left.
The cluster worker was the only node, and
therefore also its leader,
and it removed the main, and that
triggered the ClusterWorker's main actor
to shut down the program.
In the program code, we registered
for certain events to be received.
The first one was MemberUp.
And that is published exactly with this
transition here.
And in response to it, we started the
program running.
The cluster main reacted to this MemberUp
event in order to start the calculation.
The cluster worker was more interested in
when the main exited.
And that is published as MemberRmoved upon
this transition here, as well as this one.
There are other transitions which you can
listen to, for example
MemberLeaving, and MemberUnreachable,
which were not shown in code so far.
Whenever a node is removed from the
cluster, all the actors which are on it
might still be alive, if it's just
a network partition, but that does not
matter.
As far as the cluster is concerned, this
node is
removed and does not exist anymore.
That also means that all actor refs which
are still held within
the cluster to actors on that removed node
need to be considered terminated.
If, for example, DeathWatch was registered
on these
actor refs, then the terminated messages
must be delivered.
Even though the actors possibly have not
really stopped
yet, but they are considered to be dead
after the node has been removed.
This is important to allow consistent
cleanup of resources.
One actor, monitoring the lifecycle of
another was interested in when that other
actor cannot perform its duties anymore,
and that is clearly the case here.
Another reason why this needs to be done
consistently is
that for remote-deployed actors, for
example, if a child actor was
on the remove node, the parent needs to be
told that child is no longer there.
The name is free again, for example.
Or, if that node had remote deployed
children
to nodes which are still on the cluster.
Then these are currently without a parent.
And that cannot be because then there is
no one who will handle
their failures.
This means that they also need to be
stopped.
The most important part of the semantics
of DeathWatch are, that once the
terminated message has been delivered, no
further
communication will be received from that
actor.
This has consequences on the cluster as
well.
Once a node has been removed, and
DeathWatch has fired on all the actors
within it, this node cannot join the
cluster again.
It cannot come back, because that would
mean that the actors could also
start sending messages again, and that
would
violate the contract of the terminated
message.
Therefore, a node which was removed from
the cluster needs to be
restarted completely before it can join
again, and there cannot be any
of the old actors still on it.
If you have paid close attention, you will
have noticed a small inconsistency here.
In Akka message delivery is not
guaranteed, but
still we do guarantee that the terminated
message arrives.
The need for this guarantee should have
become clear, and
the reason why we can afford to implement
this guarantee is
that terminated can just be synthesized.
It can be put together even though the
sender is currently not able to do that
anymore.
Therefore the terminated message enjoys
this special status.
To try this out, we will modify the
ClusterWorker, not to rely on the
MemberRemoved event, but instead to use
DeathWatch so that it terminates once the
cluster main stops.
First of all the worker needs to subscribe
to the MemberUp event.
And after joining the main, it waits
for this event to arrive, signaling that
the cluster main has been started.
Then we need an actor to which we can
apply DeathWatch,
we know one which will exist, that is the
receptionist.
We can construct the receptionist's actor
path because we have the
main address, and we can form a root actor
path from it.
And then these paths have a little DSL
built in where you can separate
by slashes, the path components.
So, this is the
address of the cluster main / user / app /
receptionist.
We can resolve this actor path using
actorSelection and sending it an Identify
message with some random tag here,
and If we cannot find, if we cannot
resolve the receptionist, something must
be wrong.
We stop the program.
Otherwise, this is normal case.
We just watch the receptionist, and once
we get the terminated, we stop the
program.
YOu can see here this modified
ClusterWorker.
I've inserted one log line, when we
successfully
watched the receptionist, to print out who
that was.
Now running the program.
We see that the main program performs its
duty.
It did the retrevials and then it shut
down.
But we're more interested in the worker.
We see here that the worker was welcomed
into the cluster by the cluster main.
And then we resolved the receptionist to
be this actor ref here, with the UID.
This was at 11:09:21, and then eight
seconds later when the work
was done, the application was shutting
down because it received the terminated
message.
As you have seen, using the cluster is
really not complicated,
it just means subscribing to some events
and then reacting to MemberUp.
And for example, using DeathWatch just as
normal.
I invite you to play around with this
program a little bit, maybe
add more cluster nodes and see how you can
make this program scale.