In the previous lecture, we have seen how
the Akka cluster works.
And what was evident there is that
everything takes time.
It takes time for a node joining
to disseminate the information among the
rest of
the cluster, and then it takes time until
the welcome message arrives, and so on.
And the decisions are taken in some
consistent fashion, but they are not taken
immediately.
The cluster is one example of a system
which is eventually
consistent, and in this lecture we will
look at what that means.
When we made our bank account thread-safe
by introducing synchronization, we made it
strongly consistent.
That means that after an update to the
field all subsequent reads will see the
new,
the updated value.
You can see here a minimal example of such
a system.
We have a private field, accesses to which
are protected by a synchronization.
And the update method accepts a function
which transforms from the current
field value to the new one.
And in the synchronized region we read
the field, apply the function, write the
new
value back, and then return the written
value.
Any excess reading this field will also
synchronize on the same object.
That means that all reads and all updates
are serialized.
They are executed in one specific order.
And every read observes the value which
was put in by
the most previous update.
This is called strong consistency, and
it can be easily achieved here, because we
are doing it in a fully local system.
The locks offered by Scala's objects only
work because we are
executing all code here in the same Java
Virtual Machine, on the same computer.
But even so we have already
discussed that this can be problematic
because synchronization blocks the thread
which wants to execute it potentially.
And that is not good for CPU utilization.
We can remove the need to block the
calling
thread by moving the synchronization into
another execution context.
Here, this synchronized block is
executed in a Future.
That means that the update method, which
takes this function,
does not return the new value itself, it
returns a
Future of that new value and the thread
can continue
normally without having to wait for the
update to occur.
In order to properly publish the new value
of the field, we write it here back.
And if
we mark the variable as volatile, that
makes sure that other
threads see the updated value when they do
their next read.
Therefore, no synchronization is necessary
for the read message here.
By removing the blocking nature of the
update method, we have also removed
strong consistency, because calling update
and then immediately calling
read will probably not give us back the
new value.
It will take some time until the new value
is visible.
This is called weak consistency and that
means that after an
update, certain conditions need to met
until the new value is visible.
And this is called the inconsistency
window.
Eventual consistency is a special kind of
weak consistency.
First of all, it takes awhile until all
reads return a consistent
value, and second, this only really works
once the system becomes quiescent.
So once the updates stop, and then, after
awhile, once everyone has communicated the
new value
then everyone is on the same page and
consistency will be achieved.
Let us try this out with a simple actor.
This actor, also, the main purpose is to
hold this field an integer.
But the goal is to have different actors
collaborate and share the
value of this field, such that updates can
be performed on any
of these.
And eventually, the update will be seen on
all other copies.
For the outside protocol, we need an
update command, which gives a new value.
Then we need a get request, and a result.
Reply type.
The actors, which are part of this
distributed store network, will
communicate additionally using
synchronization
messages and they will learn of their
existence using Hello.
Now, how can we serialize the updates to
this field?
Because there are multiple copies of this
field, one in every actor.
And once two writes happen on different
actors, these
two actors need to agree upon which value
to keep.
Say, we have an actor D1 here, for
distributed
store one, and
D2.
And this one
get's a command, Update
42.
And this one gets
another update, 43.
They will both locally
process these messages, and afterwards,
they will talk and sync up.
And they need to keep either the 42 or the
43.
In order to serialize these updates, we
use here the current time in milliseconds.
Whenever an update is made, we capture a
timestamp
and associate it with this value of the
field.
And then when D1 tells D2, I have a new
value for you, then
D2 can check, is this actually a new
value, or do I have something better?
This is a simplified implementation of
this protocol.
Every time an update comes in,
we write to the field, and we take a
current timestamp.
When a get request comes in we reply with
the current field value.
So far, so simple.
Now when a synchronization message comes
in with a potentially new
value we check that this timestamp is
newer than what we know.
And if that is the case we apply it and
keep track of the new timestamp.
In order to set up this system, a Hello
message must be sent from D1 to D2, for
example.
And then D2 knows this a new one, which I
need to keep updated.
So, in reply to the hello, we sent the
first sync, and whenever we get a new
update, an original one, we took everyone
who wanted to know about it.
We can try this out in the Scala Ripple.
First, we import all important Akka
things.
Then, of course we need an actor system to
run things in.
And I made this implicit to use something
called the Actor DSL.
This is a small toolbox if you want to
create actors on the fly in the Ripple.
It can be done like this.
What this does is, it creates a new actor.
I didn't give it a name, hence it got the
name $A.
And the function of this actor is to just
print out any message that it gets.
This is made available as an implicit
ActorRef so that it will
be picked up when we send a message here
from the prompt.
I have loaded the code, in a package,
which
I'm importing real quick.
And now let us instantiate two such
actors.
Called
a, and b.
If we send a get request
to a, it will reply with a result of zero
to this anonymous
actor we had up here, which will print it
out.
The same result for b right now.
If we now update a,
we see that is was updated.
But b does not know anything about it.
Now we can introduce these two actors.
So, effectively, b sent a hello
to a, a should have replied with the
value, and we see that has worked.
Now, if we update
b, that is reflected here.
But
now, a was not updated because the, the
introduction needs to be done
both ways.
Now, the update has propagated back to a.
And now we could update on any of the
two, and the other one will eventually
learn of it.
After playing with actors in the Ripple,
we need to shut down the system, otherwise
the Ripple will not properly terminate.
Actors and eventual consistency are deeply
related concepts.
We have seen that within an actor, we have
an, so to speak,
an island of consistency in an ocean
of nondeterminism, which is the messaging
outside.
So everything you do within an actor is
sequentially consistent.
Everything happens like it was on a single
thread.
But as soon as you have actors
which collaborate, they can never be
strongly consistent.
They can never agree on a shared thing.
Because they always need to exchange
messages,
and a message takes time to travel.
So by the time it arrives this date
which should be agreed upon might already
have changed.
Therefore, collaborating actors can at
most be eventually consistent.
But that is not automatically the case.
You need to work to make the behavior
eventually consistent.
Looking back at the distributed store
which we
have just seen that had a few flaws.
For example, if updates come within the
same
millisecond then the merge was not
properly resolved.
Another problem is that message delivery
is not
guaranteed, but there was no resend
mechanism.
And this would also be problematic because
eventual consistency requires
that eventually all updates are
disseminated to all interested parties.
And this usually implies that there needs
to be a resend mechanism.
Another way to do it has been shown in the
cluster which does not resend
because of failures.
It just resends pessimistically so to
speak.
The gossip messages are always sent no
matter whether we know that the
other party, for example, needs the update
or it might all be old news.
And the last observation is that in order
to achieve eventual consistency,
the data structures which I shared need to
be suitable for that.
There is a class of such
data structures which are called
commutative or
convergent replicated data types described
in this paper.
If you have watched the second part of the
Actors Are Distributed lecture then
you have seen another example of this one,
which is the cluster membership state.
In the following I explain how that data
type works.
But this is optional as was the part of
the distributive lecture.
As a reminder, we had six
states.
It began with joining.
And then we had up,
leaving.
Exiting
removed, and we had down.
The
property which makes this data type
manageable as a convergent
data type, is that all transitions form
a directed and acyclic
graph.
So the normal way the nodes takes
through this is from joining via up,
leaving, exiting, to removed.
But there are other ways.
For example, from these
states, you can always become down, and
then removed.
When cluster nodes exchange gossip
messages, these messages contain
the state of all nodes currently known to
the cluster.
So for each of the members, there will be
one of these values.
For example, we had a cluster here with a
few nodes.
And this one, learns something about say,
node four.
And this one learns something else about
node four,
then the information might spread.
And let's say,
node two learned the green thing first and
then the red thing.
These are two new informations about node
four which need to be merged.
It'll say that the red information was,
that it was down, and the
green one was, that it was leaving.
Because this is such a nice graph, we can
give an order to all the
possible pairs of states, saying that down
takes precedence
over leaving, because you can go from
leaving to down, but not the other way.
This gives us the property that a
conflict,
for example, as here, can be resolved
locally, first.
And the second one is that conflict
resolution is commutative.
So it does not matter whether you learn
this first, or that.
The merge result will always be down in
this case.
And this is the property which makes the
cluster communication eventually converge,
even if conflicting information was
injected at several different points
in the cluster.