In the past lectures, we have seen
how actors collaborate to achieve a common
task,
but now we will look a bit more in detail
on how to compose them.
The type of an object describes how that
object looks
like from the outside, what you can do
with it.
When looking at an actor, the role of the
type is played by the set of messages it
accepts.
The set of messages is not bound to the
name of the actor, and hence the
type described by it is not nominal, and
actor's type is structural.
Since an actor can change its behavior
over time the structure can
also change, and that means that the type
of the actor could change.
In terms of a protocol which exchange with
it.
If you look at the types appearing in
actor implementations, we have seen two
main methods.
First is sending a message, that's the
tail.
And it has signature any to unit.
And the second is the behavior inside the
actor, which is a partial function.
Again from any to unit.
These types do not restrict what you can
send.
In a sense, you could say that actors
are not usefully typed.
As represented for example in Scala and
Akka.
But it should be noted that this
limitation is not fundamental.
While it is true that an actor can change
its behavior
arbitrarily in principle, most Actors you
write will not do that.
They will either always accept the same
set of
messages, at least the types or it might
change.
But then the total sets of all messages
ever accepted will be bounded.
In all actors we have seen so far, we
defined the
complete set of messages they accept in
their companion object for example.
This makes it possible to statically
verify that when you send a message to
an actor, it could in principal at some
point, have a chance to handle it.
Means you could reject a large number of
errors.
This is tried out.
There is an experimental implementation of
typed channels.
In Haskell there's cloud Haskell with
typed channels between actors as well.
I think we will see some development in
that area.
However, the type system will never allow
us
to express which state an actor currently
is in.
So we can deal with the complete set of
messages, but we
cannot statically determine whether an
actor
will process a given message for example.
There are many reasons for that.
One of them is that delivery is not
guaranteed, for example.
Another one is that actors may interact
with several different parties
and if we have here, for example, Alice
and Bob both talking to Charlie.
Then Bob may send a message changing the
state, so that when Alice sends a message,
that might find Charlie in a state which
is not suitable for that message anymore.
And since this can happen concurrently, it
is not known statically at compile time.
So the compiler will not be able to catch
those kinds of mistakes.
However, having fully typed Actors is
something which we do not
have yet, so let us use what we have right
now.
Given that sending a message to an Actor
does not
return anything and the types currently
are not really restricted.
It is obvious that Actors cannot be
composed like functions.
Instead we have seen that actors
collaborate like human organizations.
You can split down a task into sub tasks
and have each actor
perform its own part, and then the results
are taken together, they are composed,
and reply to the client which asks for the
operation to be performed.
This means that actors are not composed
like functions,
they're composed at the protocol level.
This gives the actor the possibility
to do everything you can think of
conceptually using function composition.
So you can translate the values passed
into a function.
You can translate its return value.
And the same thing you can do with
messages flying back and forth.
You can also call multiple actors and
then aggregate the results.
But what protocol composition can do
which,
function composition cannot do, is, for
example, to
alter the frequency with which an actor is
called, or the precise timing of the
calls.
Or perhaps dropping messages, injecting
new messages.
There is a lot more freedom here but this
freedom is
bought by list type safety.
Let us now look at a few patterns of what
you can do.
The most fundamental pattern is one which
we have seen since
two weeks ago, reappearing everywhere, and
that is the request-reply pattern.
It is so common that in Akka the
sender reference is kept exactly for that
purpose.
Because you
so often need to reply.
And for that you need to know to whom to
reply.
Let us say that Alice wants to know
something
of Bob, and sends a message.
Together
with the sender information, this enables
Bob to reply.
But we have seen other uses, for example
Bob could forward the message to
Charlie for example.
So it's basically this.
And forwarding means that the sender
reference stays the same.
So the sender of that message here, will
not be Bob, it will be Alice.
And then the reply from Charlie, goes
directly back to Alice.
This means the fact that simply putting
the sender reference in the
message and letting it travel with it
allows dynamic composition of actors.
Bob can decide
dynamically whom shall handle the request.
Then the reply will go back to the one
requesting it.
We could also take an ActorRef and wrap it
inside another actor, say here, this
AuditTrail, which does nothing but forward
all messages to the target, like so.
But it's, logs every message which it has
forwarded,
to leave this audit trail.
These interceptors are trivial to make
precisely because messages are not typed
specifically.
We can just pass along anything that might
be sent.
Another useful pattern is the one where
you expect exactly one reply.
We call this, the ask pattern.
You ask a question, you get one reply.
This is also pretty common, which is why
it is implemented as a pattern within
akka.
Importing this gives you an implicit
conversion
on ActorRefs, which gives it this question
mark operator here.
We pronounce this, user service ask
FindByEmail in this case.
The actor which we are looking at here
might be a part of
a blog management system and it has a
reference to the user service.
And you can ask this PostsByEmail actor to
find
all the posts which have been posted from
a certain
email address.
Unfortunately, the user service does not
offer this kind of information directly.
So we write a little actor, which
transforms what the user service can give
us.
So when we get a request with an email in
it we ask FindByEmail everything you know
about that user.
And this returns a future.
Since
Actors are not usefully typed as we've
seen.
This is a future of any.
But we expect back actually a user info.
There is an operation map to, which takes
a type, and
that will, under the hood, transform the
future, doing a checked cost.
So after this, we have a future of
UserInfo.
Then we can map
that and take this info.
And look at it, for example might have a
list of posts, which we
filter, whether the email matches, and
this
filter list then goes into the result.
So this has been transformed into a future
of result, now.
And then at the end we pipe it back to the
sender.
We have seen that before.
The line here,
takes all errors which might occur, and
takes them, this is, this
is throwable, this is an exception, and
wraps them in a failure message.
Let's say failure was also a message,
defined by PostsByEmail.
And this is done such that pipeTo always
sends a normal message, so, either
a result or a failure, back to the sender.
Which are the pieces that can
go wrong here?
We have this ask operation.
We have seen that actors only can send
messages to ActorRef.
And there is not really an explicit
ActorRef to reply to in this case.
What the ask operator does is, it creates
a little, very small tiny light weight
pseudo actor,
which just is an actor if linked to a
promise.
This actor of course has a name and
everything, it needs to be registered.
So it also needs to be garbage collected
when it is no longer needed.
Unfortunately, that is not very easy to
determine, because actors are also
location transparent.
So for example, user service might be on a
remote system, and we do not know
when or if it will reply.
For this reason, the ask operation takes
an implicit
time out, which we have set to three
seconds here.
After these three seconds, the future will
be completed with an ask timeout
exception.
And this little pseudo actor will be
stopped.
So this is the first thing which could go
wrong.
We could see an ask timeout exception
here.
Map to does a checked cast.
So if the reply was not of type UserInfo,
then we will find a class
cast exception in this future, so it will
propagated here.
And then finally, within the map, whatever
goes wrong
here, would also end up in the recover
case.
You will find this sequence of steps quite
common when transforming another
Actor in this kind of façade fashion.
An alternative to this pattern would be to
spawn an Actor, of course.
So when we get an email, we could create a
little customer Actor
which uses tell to communicate with the
user service, and then the user service
sends back.
And this Actor would then reply to the
original sender.
The ask operation here is just an
optimized form of this.
The actor which is created in this case,
consumes less resources than a real actor
would.
Even though a real actor is really cheap,
but if
you do this million times per second, then
the difference matters.
Another consideration
is that this code is fairly clear.
We
ask this of some other actor then we make
sure it has the right type.
We transform it catch errors, and pipe it
back.
So if it is this kind of easy
transformation then ask is fine.
If you find yourself writing very
complicated expressions in here,
or multiple steps with different futures
and the error recovery paths
get ever more convoluted, then it is for
sure time to switch to a customer actor.
The third possibility, is to keep track of
who the original sender was, but including
this information in the message which
travels to the user service and back.
If you are designing your
own system from scratch, that might be the
most efficient way to do it.
But, if you need to work with a user
service, in this case, which
you cannot modify, then you need to use
ask or or a customer actor.
Another use case where the ask pattern
comes in handy
is if you need to aggregate results from
multiple other actors.
So let's say this is a blog PostSummary
actor, and when
it gets a request for a certain postID
with user and password, then we
generate three requests.
First we ask for the status of the post.
Our sub publisher actor.
This result will be some kind of post
status.
Then we're we retrieve the text from the
post store by issuing a get request.
But then we also ask the authentication
service
whether this user and password is a valid
combination and
whether that user is authorized to see
this kind of information.
We use a for comprehension to tie these
three futures together.
And when all of them are successful this
code will run.
So we check whether the authentication was
successful.
In that case we send back the result.
Otherwise it gives
a failure, saying, not authorized.
This is a transformed future.
We started out with a future here, and
then the, this is
translated to flat map and map of futures,
and this yields a future.
We have a response here which is a future
of result or failure.
And this response is then piped back to
the sender eventually.
This
is an extremely common pattern if you are
running, like, a web store or some big
website, and the user requests, for
example, his
own home page on some social network, for
example.
There will be possibly hundreds of such
requests involved in
answering this one Get operation from the
client's web browser.
But an actor is not limited to
transforming the values which travel.
It also can transform, for example, the
lifecycle monitoring, or the semantics
of how an actor works.
For example, let's say we have, a
FileWorker
here, which is an actor
which can write things to files.
And let's say we have a request here.
To write something.
The File Worker will try to do that but
we know that during IO many things can go
wrong.
So this write just might fail.
Then of course there will be an exception
and the supervisor will handle it.
But even though the file worker might be
restarted, for example
there would be no reply to this request,
because the processing failed.
And the
only way for the client to determine that
it was not successful, is to
wait for a timeout to happen.
That can take a lot of time, because you
need to foresee; IO operations could take
some seconds, and then a reasonable
timeout window would be impractically
long.
What we can do is to wrap this
FileWorker's function in another actor.
Let's call it FileWriter.
And then the write does not go here
anymore.
It is sent here.
The FileWriter will create a worker and
supervise it
and monitor it.
And then, well, successful results could
come back, or it might fail, or terminate
before sending a successful result.
No matter what, the FileWriter itself did
not perform the
risky part, so it is a lot less likely to
fail.
Therefore the writer, very likely can
respond,
done or failed,
making the interaction with this
FileWorker more safe.
Here I have sketched this out a bit in
code.
We have the FileWriter, and when it gets
it a write command, it will
create a new FileWorker for the file, and
tell it to respond.
To self, so, to the FileWriter.
Then we watch it, and we also need to keep
track
of for whom this particular worker is
performing the work.
So we can send back the done or failed
messages.
Then, if anything goes wrong, we have a
stopping strategy.
That means that the worker will not be
restarted.
And in the end we either get a done
message, or the actor terminates.
Whichever happens first
will be successful, because we look into
the map
for the sender, this is now the worker
actor
and if there is still contents in the map,
then we send the done message and remove
this one.
This means that when it terminates later
this one won't find anything anymore.
But if it terminates without having sent a
done message, we send a failed to the
client.
Using ephemeral actors which are created
per request is a quite
common pattern, especially if the work to
be performed is risky.
We have seen a few patterns of how you can
compose
actors, to translate values going in and
out, or to validate requests.
But it is easy to imagine many more of
these.
For example, rate limitations, or also
access control.
These are things which with normal method
calls are hard to implement.
Or for example, access control needs to
use
aspect oriented programming, for example,
to insert it around method calls.
Since actors are purely based on
asynchronous message
passing we have many more possibilities on
how
to compose them on protocol level to
achieve
these things, for example, without using
aspect-oriented programming.
On the other hand this great flexibility
is part of the reason
why actors are not as usefully typed or as
strictly typed as method calls.