An important aspect of the reactive
programming is
the scalability, specifically that we
favors scalability over performance.
The distinction I am making here is that
performance focuses
on when the system is used by a single
client.
Making the system faster in this case will
usually involve optimizing it for running
on one CPU,
for example, which is as fast as possible.
But when multiple clients use the system,
these optimizations mean that there is a
ceiling
which will be reached, and beyond a
certain point the system will not scale
anymore.
It will not be able to process
the inputs received from these multiple
clients anymore.
Sketching this graphically, I have here
the
number of clients, and here the request
per second.
And optimally this would be what clients
want,
because every new clients adds just to the
request
per second that the system can handle,
which
means that the responds time will stay
roughly constant.
In this case, let us say it looks like
this.
Of course, a real system will have a
maximum, say, here.
And that means that the real performance
curve will look somewhat like this.
And what that translates to, in terms of
response time,
is something like that.
So when I say, focus on scalability
instead of performance, that
means moving this red line as far up as it
is practical.
And this will make your system withstand a
higher number of clients, without
compromising the service quality, as would
happen in this case here.
You want to move the point,
where the response time explodes as far to
the right as possible.
What does that mean in terms of
implementing an actor system?
We learned that one actor can process only
exactly one message at any given time.
It cannot do more work, just because there
are more messages coming in.
You need to have multiple actors working
on the incoming requests, in
parallel, in order to make the system with
more requests per second.
One pattern
we have already seen in the link checker
example, is to start new actors for every
request.
Another one is that you can have replicas
of actors, which perform a certain
task, and if these actors are stateless,
then these replicas can run concurrently.
Let's say you have an actor here, for
example, calculating
mortgages.
And when a client requests, it sends a
message, and then the mortgage service
will calculate the conditions, and reply
back with an interest rate, for example.
Now if this calculation is moderately
complex, then it will take some time, and
we could, for example, scale it out by
having multiple workers
to perform the task.
It is not necessary to have one per
request.
It could be a pool of, say five or ten,
and then they can use at most five or ten
CPUs completely for this purpose.
By not having one actor per request, it
is easy to limit the parallelism, which is
allowed.
Since actor communication is,
conveniently, asynchronous message
passing, the client here
does know whether the Mortgage Service
does
the calculation itself, or whether it has
farmed it out to any of the workers.
This means that asynchronous message
passing gives us the possibility for
vertical scalability, which means using
more CPUs in the same node.
The purpose of this mortgage service, in
the last example, was
just to route the incoming requests to the
pool of workers.
There are different schemes for doing
that,
which we shall look at in the following.
These schemes can be grouped into stateful
or stateless routing.
Stateful means that the routing algorithm
itself needs to keep some state.
For example
round robin needs to keep a count.
We will see what that means in detail.
And in general, stateless routing might be
preferable, because that can even
happen, in parallel, by multiple routers,
because they don't need to share anything.
The most easily understood routing scheme
is the round robin one.
You have the router here, incoming
messages,
and let's say we have three targets.
One, two, and three here.
Then the first request will go here.
The second will go here.
Third will go here, then it starts over.
Always one, two, three, one, two, three,
one, two, three.
This means
that the distribution of messages to these
routees here will
be quite close to equal at any given point
in time.
But that also means that if, for example,
actor one here experiences failure and the
restart takes a bit, then it will
still receive the same incoming rate of
messages.
So, the mailbox of this one will get more
full
than the other two.
And that means that messages which go to
number one, which
is 1/3rd the incoming messages here will
experience a higher processing
latency, because there is a mailbox in
here, which the actor
needs to work off, in order to get to the
current message.
This can be fixed, of course, by looking
at
the mailbox size, and routing only to
those which
have the lowest number of messages,
currently.
This requires all the routees to be local
so the message queue can be inspected.
It obviously does not work over the
network.
And also, the cost of looking into the
mailbox
and counting the messages in there, is
rather high.
These data structures are concurrent and
need to be properly synchronized.
And they're not as cheap to traverse as a
normal collection is.
This means that this routing cost is
rather high, and only worth
it if the job to be performed takes more
time than that.
But in that case, the imbalances
introduced between different processing
speeds of the actors are evened out by the
algorithm, and the latency
which is experienced by clients, is more
consistent.
Taking this model to the extreme means
sharing a work queue between different
actors.
So, what we have here is just
a queue for the messages, and then we have
our routees here.
And they always process the oldest message
in the queue.
And effectively everyone pulls
from there.
Messages go in on top.
The most efficient implementation of this
scheme is
that they really do share the same work
queue.
There is an aka the balancing dispatcher
for achieving
that, but that requires the routees to be
local, again.
Of course this will give the most
homogeneous latency which you can achieve.
So far, evening out imbalances
came with a rather high cost of routing
itself, and, or the need for the routees
to be local.
If we sample the imbalances, for example,
over time, it can be rather coarse.
It doesn't need to happen per message.
It could be once per second, for example,
or even less frequently.
Then we can gather this data and use them
to steer
the routing weights.
So if we have here, the incoming
message stream, and here this adaptive
router and the routees.
The routees will periodically send back,
the feedback of, for example, how full
their queue was at this second,
or what the CPU load is on that node.
Because they could run on different nodes.
And then this one has an algorithm inside,
which uses this information
to change the relative weights of where
messages shall go.
For example, more frequently here, less
frequently
here, if this node is currently under more
load.
This can be a good compromise, but it
requires the steering of
these weights to be done carefully,
because other wise you can introduce
oscillations.
Or over-dampening, so that the reaction
times
are longer than necessary.
And for that you need to look into
feedback control theory.
The routing algorithms we looked at so far
have all been state four.
The router itself needed to keep
information.
For example, the round ro, robin needed a
counter where the last message was sent.
This can lead to some routing overhead
because the decision depends on something
which
is shared.
If you use random routing, for example,
then, in principle, no router is
necessary.
We have the incoming message stream.
And we have, our routees.
And
each sender of a message to this set of
actors, randomizes, on its own,
where the actual message goes.
That means that there doesn't need to
be an intermediate actor here, which does
anything.
This offers the lowest possible routing
overhead.
The problem with it is that well the
process is random.
So, there are also, there is the prob,
probability that for
example, number one, might for a certain
time window, get more messages
than two and three.
Asymptotically, these will even out.
But in the real running program, it might
be observable.
Another stateless routing scheme, is that
of splitting up
the incoming message stream, consistently,
according to some criteria.
So we have our routees again.
And
then, let's say,
we have the black part,
the red part,
and the green part of the message stream.
And all messages which match
this green color, always go to routee
number 3.
This means that there also does not mean
to be a central authority here during the
routing.
But it also means that the sub stream need
to
be chosen, such they are, that they are of
equal weight.
Otherwise, it will lead to systematic
inbalances
between the processing times for the three
routees.
This scheme has another advantage.
Up to now, it was not really deterministic
which message comes to which node, or
which routee.
So, one, two, and three, needed to be
identical actors.
And if another
request comes in later, it will have no
correlation, or it cannot have any cannot
require
any correlation with a, an earlier
request, because
the state of these reactors is not shared.
Splitting up the message screen, according
to some criterion allows us, to, for
example, have all requests pertaining to a
certain user Go to this actor.
And if the user is the important state to
be kept, then well, everything
perti, pertaining to my user, for example,
always goes to routee number one.
And then, subsequent messages could have
a,
common interest correlation because they
all go
to the same target, always.
And updates to my user for, example,
at number one, would be safe because later
messages will see the updated state.
This means that consistent hashing routing
can be used to replicate
stateful actors.
This requires that the input stream
of messages can be split, in such a
fashion,
that the state affected by these
substreams is independent.
If a certain part of the state is shared
between several actors,
we have seen that in a previous lecture,
with this distributed store.
You have two actors here, A and B.
And if they share something, which shall
be the
same, then they need to communicate, we
have seen
that, and they need to exchange data in
appropriate
data structures, so that they can achieve
eventual consistency.
Here, replication is not used for
scalability
so much, but it can also be used for fault
tolerance.
And
while we are at that topic, it is quite
easy to see that persistent
actors persistent stateful actors, can be
replicated as well.
When something goes wrong, we just need to
recover the
actor, and that could well happen at the
different location.
For example, if the node where the actor
was living.
Let's say
node A, we have our actor here.
If that node crashes and is not
recoverable,
then on node B, we can just replay the
state of actor A
and resurrect it.
This will also require a certain
message router, which first sends messages
here, and then after the crash, switches
to the new instance.
And if we are using event sourcing, we can
even optimize this process.
This second
copy of A could be started right away, but
it could be inactive and only,
replay the event stream which generate,
which is generated by Ą.
So, the event store, and then recovery of
A
in the event of failure takes very little
time.
All the features seen so far, have been
made possible by the design of the actor
model.
Asynchronous message passing gives us
vertical scalability, so the
ability to run a process in parallel on
the same node on multiple CPUs.
And location transparency, which means
hiding everything behind actoreth
and remoting does not look different,
enables horizontal scalability.
That means running the computation not on
one node, but on a cluster
of potentially hundreds of nodes.