Concerning actors, we have talked
about their message-driven or event-driven
nature.
We have talked about that supervision
makes them resilient against failure.
And we've seen how routing of messages can
achieve scalability.
As a conclusion to this part we need to
talk
about the fourth tenet of reactive
programming, which is responsiveness.
And we will see that this trait ties all
of the four of them together into a
cohesive whole.
The first we note is that responsiveness
means that a system can respond to input
within a given time limit.
If it is unable to respond and there is
just a certain waiting
time which you give it that is equivalent
to the system not being available.
This means that resilience is not achieved
if the system cannot respond.
No matter how you restart your parts of
your actor hierarchy, for example, if that
does not lead to the system generating
responses
in time, then it is all for nothing.
One regime in which this is particularly
hard
to achieve is when the system is
overloaded.
But even there it holds that
if the system does not respond in
an overload scenario, then it is not
resilient.
In the following, we will talk about
patterns, how to achieve
responsiveness in both the normal and the
failure cases and underload.
Let us first look at the nominal case and
see what we, what we can do there.
We had this example in the aggregation
patterns where this PostSummary actor
fires
off requests to different backend
services, and
aggregates them and then responds to the
sender when everything has been received.
But what we do here is, we ask one actor
and when we get the reply, we ask another
one.
When we get the reply, we ask the third
And once we have all three of them, we
construct the response
which can be result of failure.
And then pipe it back to the sender.
This adds the call latencies to all these
three
actors together before the final result
can be dispatched.
This PostSummary actor will respond quite
a lot sooner if
we were intead to fire off the requests in
parallel.
So, we ask in parallel, and then we tie
the resulting futures
together in one full comprehension, to
compute
the result, and this will reduce the
latency.
Obviously, the slowest of these three
actors to respond will
define how long it takes the PostSummary
actor to respond in turn.
Once all opportunity for parallelism has
been exploited,
the next step is to look at the
responsiveness of each single component,
and try to reduce the latency time there.
One thing which should be avoided is that
the processing cost
depends on how loaded your system is,
because that will amplify
problems when users start to hit your
business for example, and
you become successful, and then suddenly
the site doesn't work anymore.
Because you built in something which is
for example
order of n squared in the number of
current users in your system.
This mean choosing data structures and
algorithms
which preferably exhibit linear or
algorithmic complexity.
Once you have reduced the time it takes to
process a single request as far as is
practical or desirable, then you need to
add parallelism when needed.
For example
using the scalability patterns where we
talked about
different routing strategies and pools
which you can use.
But inevitably, every system has a certain
limit, and once
the system's capacity is reached, requests
will start piling up.
This means that the processing get
backlogged, queues fill,
and the latency rises for everyone using
the system.
Eventually the clients themselves will
time out.
You have seen that on web pages for
example, where
the browser tells you that the site did
not respond.
What do you do in that case?
Well you go to different site if you have
a choice, so this needs to be avoided.
In order to achieve this, you can use the
circuit breaker pattern and implementation
of which comes with Akka.
Let's use an example here, where we want
to contact
the user service and ask it about a
certain user.
We want to make this resilient against the
user service being overloaded or just
constantly failing.
So this ask returns a future and
the circuit breaker wraps this future and
looks
at whether it succeeds and when it
succeeds.
The configuration of it is given here.
The call timeout is one second.
So it checks for every future put in
here, whether it was completed within one
second.
And if it was not, it increases a failure
counter.
And when that reaches three, then the
circuit breaker will open.
And all subsequent requests will fail
immediately wthout contacting the user
service.
This takes the pressure off the user
service
and makes the system respond a lot faster.
Then, as requests keep coming in, every 30
seconds the circuit
breaker will allow one request through, to
see if it succeeds.
And if that is the case, then the circuit
breaker closes again, and things
will proceed normally.
But if that also fails, then it will open
again for another 30 seconds.
You'll notice here that the timeout for
the ask operation is two
seconds, while the call timeout for the
circuit breaker was one second.
And that can come in handy, that you say a
single request may take two or
even 5five seconds, but if three in a row
are slower than one second, I want the
circuit breaker to trip.
This pattern is a good way to separate two
components
such that failures in one do not influence
the other.
But it does not completely isolate actors
if
they happen to run on the same dispatcher.
Therefore, the last thing we need to
consider is to segregate the resources
available to different parts of your
system
to make them independent from each other.
For example, you have that part of the
system
which is responsible for sending a
response to the client.
And that part needs to function as long as
possible, even if all the back ends
services are down.
This can be achieved by configuring these
actors
to run on different nodes for example, or
on the same host to run on different
dispatchers.
You can configure this if you create the
props of your actors
and say, with dispatcher, saying for
example compute jobs in this case.
And that will make this actor run on
a different thread pool than its parent
for example.
If you do not specify this,
actors run on the so-called default
dispatcher.
This is the configuration section which is
the current default in
Akka, and it says that the executors is a
so-called fork-join-executor.
And it uses minimum eight threads, maximum
64 threads.
And in that it defaults to three times the
number of your CPU cores that you have
available.
You configure
another dispatcher just by putting another
config section in your
file with the name you gave in the with
dispatcher method.
And then you can just say, compute jobs
and configure it.
For example, fork-join-executor and this
locks it down to exactly
four threads, which you reserve for this
kind of compute job.
While doing this, you should keep in mind
that configuring many more threads
than you have CPUs in your system can
defeat the purpose of this bulk heading.
Because then these threads will compete
for the available CPU cores.
Detecting failure in distributed systems
takes time because the only
thing you can observe is that you do not
observe anything.
And, you need to give yourself a timeout
for that.
There are systems where you can afford to
wait and you have for
example a back up system which you need to
switch to immediately.
But obviously, this is limited in latency
to how
frequently you check that the prime system
is up.
Where there is not enough you can do
nothing but immediately
always send to all, so you have for
example three systems.
And you have the requests coming in.
Nominally you would use A and then you
would want to switch to B or C as needed.
But if that needs to happen within a
millisecond for example, there is no
choice, you always need to send to all of
them to keep them in sync.
Because within a millisecond, you cannot
transfer all state between A and B.
And then what you can do is,
like for example, in highly redundant
satellite systems,
get the responses from all three, and as
soon as you
have two responses and they match you can,
send the reply.
And if you notice that one of the nodes
does not send within the time
allotted, then you can shut it down and
request a new one to be added.
Such a scheme would allow you to be always
responsive, even if one node fails.
We have seen how event-driven
systems can scale vertically, because you
can dispatch the processing
of events to any number of CPU cores in
your system.
And if you add the ability to send events
over the network, so you make your system
location transparent, that adds horizontal
scalability, because you
can run your computation on whole cluster
of nodes.
But the quality which we want
to achieve in the end is that the system
which we construct responds to inputs,
giving the correct outputs.
And this demands not only scalability,
which
we get by being event-driven and location
transparent, but also resilient, which
means that
failure is contained and fixed by
delegation.
Therefore, we can see
how responsiveness ties together all the
principles
of reactive programming including,
resilience,
scalability, and its event-driven nature.