[BLANK_AUDIO]
So, welcome.
I'm Maggie Montgomery, from the World
Health Organization.
And, here today to talk about the
evaluation
and the validation of household water
treatment technology.
So, I want to thank, Dr. Johnston for
inviting me.
And let's get started.
So there's going to be three main things
I'd like to talk to you about today.
The first is why is it important
to assess the performance of household
water treatment.
And I'll talk just briefly about the fact
that household water treatment, the main
benefit is health.
And so it's important that we know how
well.
Household water treatment technologies
remove pathogens so we
have some indication of the protection of
health.
And second is, I'll talk about the WHO
global standards on the performance of
household water treatment.
And give a bit of background about how
they were developed.
And lastly, I'll talk about what WHO is
doing to implement these standards.
Specifically.
Discuss the WHO International Scheme
to evaluate household water treatment
technologies.
There's two main reasons why it's
important to
assess the performance of household water
treatments technology.
The first is to understand if these
technologies are achieving.
The objectives of improving health, which
requires, first of all that they
remove the pathogens that are causing
the diarrhoeal disease in a specific
population.
And in some cases, we know specially which
pathogens are causing that disease.
For example, in a cholera outbreak, it's
very well known that
is the bacterium vibrio cholerae that is
causing the diarrhoeal disease.
But in other cases, for example, people
living with HIV AIDS, who are more
susceptible to diarrhoeal disease, it
could be
a suite pathogens that are causing this
disease.
And in all cases, it's important that the
devices that are being used with these
specific populations.
Are removing the pathogens we are most
concerned about.
And if we don't know exactly which
pathogens those are, it is
prudent to make sure that these devices
remove a suite of pathogens.
The second reason why assessing household
water treatment performance is
important is that government especially as
well as implementers and funders.
Need to know that the, the devices that
they are investing
in are achieving the aims that they set
out to achieve.
And this requires a rigorous evaluation of
household water treatment.
Now, in many countries where household
water treatment is most needed, i.e.
Where the water quality is poor and the
diarrhoeal disease burden is
high, governments don't have the
resources,
nor the capacity to do such evaluations.
And lastly, I just wanted to emphasize
that while today's talk
is going to be focused on the performance,
realizing the health
benefits from household water treatment
also requires that users correctly and
consistently use household water treatment
when their water quality is compromised.
So in order to facilitate the evaluation
of household water treatment
WHO come out with global recommendations
on how to assess performance.
Now, these global recommendations, the
goal is to protect
the health of the users and also to ensure
that.
More household water treatments products
that achieve minimum performance standards
are
being distributed and used to those that
most need safe water.
Now specifically the recommendations look
at three main classes of pathogens.
And these three classes of pathogens, I
know you've already talked
about with Dr. Johnston and hopefully you
understand well at this point.
But these are the three main classes that
cause diarrhoeal
disease in humans and they are viruses
bacteria and protozoa.
From these three classes of pathogens we
derived
targets and what I mean by targets we
derived, what are the minimum amounts of
removal
that need to be achieved in order to.
Achieve a certain minimum amount of risk
in a population.
Now these targets were derived based on
what has already been done in the WHO
guidelines for drinking water quality and
these guidelines
use what is called quantitative microbial
risk assessment.
So quantitative microbial risk assessment
are basically models that allow
us to predict what will be the health
consequences in a population if they
ingest a certain concentration of
pathogens with a certain frequency.
So for these models we obviously had to
pick specific pathogens within each of
these, classes of viruses, bacteria and
protozoa to come up with an estimate.
Now from that estimate we also decided.
What was the minimum amount of risk we're
willing to accept and I'll talk
about that in the next slide, that allowed
us to then develop our removal target.
We also used a tiered approach.
So rather than setting one very high bar
for household water treatment, we
recognized that even
devices that maybe are not the best but
do provide some protection and even
limited protection.
Can have a very significant impact in
populations where the concentrations
of pathogens are very high and the disease
burden is very high.
So this tiered approach was, was done to
acknowledge the fact
that even lesser performing devices can
still have an health impact.
It was also created because we recognized
in some situations it's just simply not
economically feasible to have the very top
device, and cheaper
and perhaps less protective devices can
still have an important impact.
lastly, the recommendations provide some
information on the laboratory
protocols, or how you would actually go
about doing experiments.
To test the performance of these household
water treatment devices.
Before I present the performance
standards,
I want just to briefly highlight what
log-removal is and what it actually means
when we're talking about concentrations of
pathogens.
So let's say, for example, we start with
cryptosporidium before we put the water
through a filter.
We put the water trough the filter and
filtering we have 10 cryptosporidium.
So that means we've removed 90
cyrptosporidium pretty
simple math, we can equate that to a
percentage and we say we have 90% removal
and that is equivalent to 1 log removal.
Now let's say with that same source water
we still have a 100 cryptosporidium.
But after filtering we use a better
filter, a more highly performing filter.
We only have one cryptosporidium remaining
in the water after it's been filtered.
This means we, we've removed 99
cryptosporidium.
Or achieved a two-log removal.
Assessing performance.
So based on the quantitative microbial
risk models I spoke of earlier, we were
able to develop specific reduction targets
for
each of the three classes of pathogens.
Based on allowable risk.
Now the most stringent requirement were
the category where
we're allowing the least amount of risk in
a
population, specifically ten to the
negative six DALYs per
person per year, it is a highly protective
category.
Now in this category.
Devices must achieve at least four log
removal of bacteria, at least
five log removal of viruses and at least
four log removal protozoa.
Now you'll notice, that for the viruses,
the
log reduction is even greater because we
know viruses.
Are more likely to cause infection and
disease with
just a single virus, compared to the other
pathogens.
Now for the protective category, we're
allowing
a slightly less conservative risk in the
population.
It's 10 to the negative fourth DALYs.
And consequently, the log removal doesn't
have to be quite as high.
Two, at least two for bacteria, at least
three for viruses and at least two for
protozoa.
The final category, Limited Protection,
are actually technologies
that achieve at least two of the targets
for.
The classes of pathogens and protective.
Now, these may be technologies that do
really well for
two of the classes, but not on the third,
and
in populations where we are very sure of
the main
pathogen that's causing disease, they
could be a very effective option.
Now, for each of these classes of
bacteria, viruses, and protozoa.
We had to chose one specific organism to
represent the class as a
whole, in order to develop the models and
come up with the specific log-reductions.
So we choose pathogens that we know in
human
populations do account for a significant
proportion of diarrhoeal disease.
And bacteria specifically it's
campylobacter, virus
is rotavirus, and protozoa was
cryptosporidium.
Now what are some
examples of technologies that are already
being used in the
field and have been tested quite
rigorously in the lab.
That meet these performance standards.
Well for highly protective, the number one
technology or actually it's a method, is
boiling.
This is by far the oldest method we have
and it's very efficacious in the removal.
But the problem with boiling is re
contamination, so that's an important
issue to consider.
Ultra fi, filters, I know you've just
learned about filtration, are
also very efficacious as well as a comb,
combination of approaches.
So you may do filtering followed by
chlorination
in order to achieve a higher level of
protection.
In the middle category we have
membrane filters as well as many
flocculant-disinfectant.
And lastly in limited production category
some examples include chlorine which we
know is very effective against bacteria
especially cholera, but fairly ineffective
against protozoa.
Especially cryptosporidium.
Ceramic filters and some bio-sand filters
also fall into this limited protection
category.
Now you may wonder why did we have three
levels of performance.
Well there's two main reasons.
First of all, we know in populations where
there is a high burden of diarrhoeal
disease and
a high load of, of fecal contamination in
the environment and, and therefore in the
drinking water.
Even devices that achieved the protective
or limited
protection level could have a significant
impact on health.
We also know that in many of these areas,
economics and cost are huge barrier.
And, sometimes The highly protective
devices may also be cost-prohibitive.
So we don't want to prevent other, maybe
lesser-performing but still having
some protection devices, such as
protective
and limited protection from reaching those
populations.
Nuts and bolts of testing.
So how do we actually.
Test these devices and what kind of water
do we use,
to see that we're actually achieving a
certain level of performance.
Well we want to really mimic the types of
waters that
we find in the environments and
communities that would use these devices.
So, in order to do this.
We've developed two types of waters.
The first is a general test water.
Now this is water that represents high
quality groundwater or rainwater.
It will have a very low turbidity, so
there's not
a lot of particulates, in the water, and a
fairly, a
temperature that is fairly consistent with
the ambient temperature It
is the non-stressed phase of testing so
it's not technology specific.
We also though, want to see how these
devices will perform when we have
really turbid or contaminated water like
this river that you see here in Lao.
Many people are still using surface water
and this challenge water is supposed to
represent.
Such surface waters like rivers or ponds
so the
turbidity is very high as well as the TOC.
Now this is the stressed phase challenge
phase of testing and depending on
the different product, we may vary
the conditions, as different products will
fail.
Under different con, conditions.
Depending on whether or not it's a filter
or a chemical additive or some combination
of approaches.
We've talked about why it's important to
assess the performance of household water
treatment.
And we've also talked about the global
recommendations on performance of
household water treatment.
The third thing I want to talked about.
Is the WHO scheme to evaluate household
water treatment technologies with, which
is specifically how WHO and government
are working to implement these
recommendations.
There's two main objectives to this
scheme.
The first is to promote and coordinate the
independent testing and
evaluation of household water treatment
products Based on the WHO criteria.
I would like to stress the word
independent because often we find that
laboratories,
especially in particular countries, do not
have
the ability to provide independence and
objectives.
Evaluations.
The second, is to support national
governments
in building the technical capacity of
research institutions.
So, improve the ability for governments to
assess local products, to
do complimentary testing, in the field of
household water treatment products.
Especially after they've been in use for
some time.
And this is all linked to WHO's greater
work in water quality.
On applying the WHO guidelines on drinking
water quality.
I'd like to explain a bit about how the
scheme works and
in order to do that, highlight the scheme
actors and the components.
First of all, just wanted to mention that
WHO is hosting the
scheme secretariat and managing all the
different pieces and actors within the
scheme.
Providing advice to WHO is the Independent
Advisory Committee, so
this a group of experts who are reviewing
the test
protocols and the test results and
providing recommendations on how
products should be tested and what level
of performance they've reached.
There's also, of course, the
manufacturers.
And the manufacturers are submitting their
products for testing.
The designated testing laboratories,
currently we
have two, one in the United States
and one in the Netherlands, are doing the
actual testing of the products.
Now, at the same time, this scheme is very
interested in building up
a whole group of laboratories that
can do complementary testing especially in
countries.
Where household water treatment is most
often used.
Lastly, we have government, UN agencies,
donors, all those groups of entities that
are procuring, regulating and distributing
household water treatment devices.
And, finally, and perhaps most
importantly, we have the users.
And the, the scheme also aims to help
users make informed
choices about the products they're using
and the protection they're receiving.
There's three main steps to the scheme.
It's fairly simple.
The first are the submissions, and those
are received by WHO from the
manufacturers.
The second is the testing.
And as I mentioned the testing will
occur initially in these two designated
testing laboratories.
And lastly, we have the results and the
dissemination of those testings.
The overall aim of the scheme is to reduce
diarrhoeal
disease through safe or effective
microbially effective household treatment
technologies.
Now there's three main outcomes related to
this.
The first is to provide a publicly
available list of products tested.
And those summary results whether or not
the product passes or fails
to meet one of our three level performance
standards on the WHO website.
The second is to work with governments and
specifically the member states of the
World Health Organization.
To ensure that their national regulations
start to reflect some of
the recommendations the WHO has made in
regards to health risks.
And achieving specific levels of
performance.
And, lastly is to strengthen the national
capacity of research institutions, of
laboratories, in
order to enable them to test local
products as well as products in the field.
A number of capacity-building activities
are associated with this scheme.
The first is to train officials in
risk-based assessments.
So this could be related to house water
treatment, but it could be related.
To community water supplies as well and
for them to understand how they
can address these risks and manage these
risks to provide better protection for
health.
The second is I already mentioned is to
strengthen
the national laboratory capacity in terms
of skills and equipment.
The third is to align where possible, with
water quality surveillance efforts.
So we find more and more, there's work
going on to assess
water quality not only at the source, but
also in the household.
Lastly I just wanted to mention that
Ethiopia as
an example of a country that has already
begun.
Applying the WHO recommendations on
household water treatment
and recently they were able to use these
recommendations
to prevent a particular product from being
distributed
because it didn't meet the minimum
standards for WHO.
So we plan to work with more countries
like Ethiopia that are very interested in
improving the way that they assess these
products
and ensuring that those products that are
distributed.
Meet the minimum standards.
In summary, I'd like to stress two main
points.
First hopefully by now you've understood
that the assessment
of household water treatment performance
is important for protecting health.
Now, I spoke only about the
microbiological performance of house water
treatment.
The chemical performance of house water
treatment also
is important and is something that WHO
recognizes.
Needs to be addresses, but hasn't been
developed
yet in terms of a set of global
guidelines.
I also want to make sure you leave
by remembering that is equally important
that these
products are used correctly and
consistently by the
groups that are most at risk for
diarrhoeal disease.
So young children, people with HIV/AIDS,
those in emergencies
or in cholera outbreaks are just a few
examples.
Secondly, the WHO International Scheme to
Evaluate
household water treatment aims first of
all to
inform and to provide objective
information about
performance but it also hopes to spark
innovation.
And already we're seeing that
manufacturers are trying to develop
technologies
that not only are highly protective but
also are low cost.
Easy to use and can be easily distributed
in places where water quality is its
poorest.
And lastly, the scheme aims to build
capacity
so someday in, in the future, we can work
ourselves out of, out of a job, and
governments
themselves can evaluate and regulate
household water treatment technologies.
So would like to thank you for your
attention.
I'd like to point you to some additional
resources and information.
First of all, if you want to read the
performance recommendations
I spoke about, you can find them online at
this web address.
These are the recommendations.
Also if you want to learn more about the
scheme, you can go to
the website that presents all the
information
about the scheme, their related protocols,
the laboratories.
And lastly, if you're just interested in
household water treatment more generally,
I refer you.
To the WHO/UNICEF international Network on
Household water treatment and safe
storage.
Which is working on a variety of issues,
to try to make sure household
water treatment, gets to where it's
needed, and used by those most in need.
So thank you.