So, welcome!
I'm Maggie Montgomery
from the World Health Organization
and here today to talk about
the evaluation and validation
of household water treatment technologies.
So I want to thank Dr. Johnston
for inviting me,
and let's get started.
So there are going to be
three main things
I would like to talk to you about today.
The first is why is it important
to assess the performance
of household water treatment.
And I will talk just briefly about the fact
that for household water treatment
the main benefit is health,
so it's important that we know
how well household water treatment
technologies remove pathogens,
so we have some indication
of the protection of health.
And secondly, I will talk
about the WHO global standards
on the performance
of household water treatment
and give a bit of background about
how they were developed,
and lastly, I will talk about
what WHO is doing
to implement these standards,
specifically discuss
the WHO international scheme
to evaluate household
water treatment technologies.
There are two main reasons
why it's important
to assess the performance
of household water treatment technologies.
The first is to understand
if these technologies are achieving
the objective of improving health,
which requires, first of all,
that they remove the pathogens
that are causing the diarrheal disease
in a specific population.
In some cases we know specifically
which pathogens are causing the disease,
for example, in a cholera outbreak
it's very well known
that it's the bacterium Vibrio cholerae
that is causing the diarrheal disease.
But in other cases, for example,
people living with HIV/AIDS
who are much more susceptible
to diarrheal disease,
it could be a suite of pathogens
that are causing this disease,
and in all cases it's important
that the devices that are being used
with these specific populations
are removing the pathogens
we are most concerned about,
and if we don't know exactly
which pathogens those are,
it's prudent to make sure
that these devices
remove a suite of pathogens.
The second reason why assessing
household water treatment
performance is important,
is that governments, especially,
as well as the implementers
and funders need to know
that the devices
that they are investing in
are achieving the aims
that they are set out to achieve,
and this requires a rigorous evaluation
of household water treatment.
In many countries where
household water treatment is most needed,
i. e., where the water quality is poor
and the diarrheal disease burden is high,
governments don't have
the resources nor the capacity
to do such evaluations.
And lastly, I just wanted to emphasize
that while today's talk is going to be
focused on the performance
realizing health benefits
from household water treatment
also requires that users
correctly and consistently
use household water treatment
when their water quality is compromised.
So, in order to facilitate the evaluation
of household water treatment
WHO came out with global recommendations
on how to assess performance.
Now these global recommendations,
the goal is to protect
the health of the users
and also to ensure that more
household water treatment products
that achieve a minimum
performance standards
are being distributed and used
to those who most need safe water.
Specifically the recommendations
look at three main classes of pathogens
and used three classes of pathogens --
I know you've already talked about
with Dr. Johnston,
and hopefully
you understand well at this point,
but these are the three main classes
that cause diarrheal disease in humans,
and they are viruses,
bacteria and protozoa.
From these three classes of pathogens
we derive targets,
and what I mean by targets we derived,
what are the minimum amounts of removal
that need to be achieved
in order to achieve a certain
minimum amount of risk in a population.
Now, these targets were derived
based on what has already been done
in the WHO guidelines
for drinking water quality
And these guidelines used,
what is called,
quantitative microbial risk assessment.
So quantitative microbial risk assessment
are basically models
that allow us to predict
what will be the health consequences
in a population
if they ingest a certain concentration
of pathogens with a certain frequency.
So for these models
we had to pick specific pathogens
within each of these classes
of viruses, bacteria and protozoa
to come up with an estimate.
From that estimate we also decided
what was the minimum amount of risk
we were willing to accept,
and I'll talk about that
in the next slide
that allowed us to then
develop our removal targets.
We also use a tiered approach,
so rather than studying one very high bar
for household water treatment
we recognized that even devices
that maybe are not the best,
but do provide some protection,
and even limited protection
can have a very significant
impact in populations
where the concentrations
of pathogens are very high
and the disease burden is very high.
So this tiered approach was done
to acknowledge the fact
that even lesser performing devices
can still have a health impact.
It was also created because we recognize,
in some situations
it's just simply not economically feasible
to have the very top device, and cheaper,
and perhaps less protective devices
can still have an important impact.
Lastly, the recommendations
provide some information
on laboratory protocols
or how you would actually
go about doing experiments
to test the performance
of these household
water treatment devices.
Before I present the performance standards
I want just briefly highlight
what log removal is
and what it actually means
when we're talking
about concentrations of pathogens.
So let's say, for example,
we start with 100 cryptosporidium
before we put the water
through a filter.
We put the water through the filter,
and after filtering
we have 10 cryptosporidium.
That means we removed 90 cryptosporidium.
Pretty simple math.
We can equate that to a percentage,
and we say we have 90% removal,
and that is equivalent to 1-log removal.
Let's say with that same source water,
we still have 100 cryptosporidium,
but after filtering --
we use a better filter,
more highly performing filter --
we only have 1 cryptosporidium
remaining in the water
after it has been filtered.
This means we've removed
99 cryptosporidium,
or achieved a 2-log removal.
Assessing performance:
based on the quantitative
microbial risk models
I spoke of earlier
we were able to develop
specific reduction targets
for each of the three classes of pathogens
based on allowable risk.
Now the most stringent requirements
were the category
where we're allowing least
amount of risk in a population,
specifically 10 to the negative 6
DALYs per person per year
is the highly protective category.
Now, in this category
devices must achieve
at least 4-log removal of bacteria,
at least 5-log removal of viruses
and at least 4-log removal of protozoa.
Now, you noticed that for the viruses
the log reduction is even greater,
because we know viruses are more likely
to cause infection and disease
with is a single virus,
compared to the other pathogens.
Now, for the protective category
we are allowing
a slightly less conservative risk
in the population,
it's 10 th the negative 4
DALYs and consequently the log removal
does not have to be quite as high,
at least 2 for bacteria,
at least 3 for viruses
and at least 2 for protozoa.
The final category, limited protection,
are actually technologies
that achieve at least 2 of the targets
for the classes
of pathogens in protective.
Now these may be technologies
that do really well
for two of the classes,
but not on the third.
And in populations where we are
very sure of the main pathogen
that's causing disease
they could be a very effective option.
Now, for each of these classes
of bacteria, viruses and protozoa
we had to choose one specific organism
to represent the class as a whole
in order to develop the models
and come up
with the specific log reductions,
so we chose pathogens that we know
in human populations
do account for a significant proportion
of diarrheal disease.
And bacteria, specifically,
it's campylobacter, viruses rotavirus,
and protozoa was cryptosporidium.
Now, what are examples of technologies
that are already been used in the field
and have been tested
quite rigorously in the lab
that meet these performance standards?
For highly protective,
the number one technology,
or actually its' a method, is boiling.
This is by far the oldest method we have,
and it's very efficacious in the removal,
but the problem with boiling
is recontamination
so that's an important issue to consider.
Ultra filters, I know,
you've just learned about filtration,
are also very efficacious,
as well as a combination of approaches,
so you may do filtering
followed by chlorination
in order to achieve
a higher level of protection.
In the middle category
we have membrane filters,
as well as many flocculant disinfectants.
And lastly, in the limited
protection category,
some examples include chlorine,
which, we know, is very effective
against bacteria, especially cholera,
but fairly ineffective against protozoa,
especially cryptosporidium.
Ceramic filters and some biosand filters
also fall into this
limited protection category.
Now, you may wonder why did we have
three levels of performance.
Well, there are two main reasons.
First of all, we know, in populations
where there is a high burden
of diarrheal disease
and a high load of fecal contamination
in the environment
and therefore in the drinking water,
even devices that achieve the protective
or limited protection level
could have a significant impact on health.
We also know that in many of these areas
economics and costs are huge barrier,
and sometimes
the highly protective devices
may also be cost prohibitive.
So we don't want to prevent other,
maybe lesser performing,
but still having some protection devices,
such as protective and limited protection
from reaching those populations.
Nuts and Bolts of Testing.
So how how do we actually
test these devices
or what kind of water do we use
to see that we are actually achieving
a certain level of performance?
Well, we want to really mimic
the types of waters
that we find in environments
and communities
that would uses these devices.
So, in order to do this
we've developed two types of waters.
The first is a general test water.
Now, this is water that represents
high quality groundwater
or rainwater and will have
a very low turbidity
so there's not a lot
of particulates in the water,
and a temperature
that is fairly consistent
with the ambient temperature.
It is the non-stressed phase of testing,
so it's not technology specific.
We also, though, want to see
how these devices will perform
when we have really turbid
or contaminated water,
like this river you see here in Lao.
Many people are still using surface water
and this challenge water
is supposed to represent
such surface waters
like rivers or ponds
so that turbidity is very high,
as well as the TOC.
Now, this is a stressed phase
or challenge phase of testing
and depending on the different product
we may vary the conditions,
as different products
will fail under different conditions
depending on whether or not
it's a filter or a chemical additive,
or some combination of approaches.
We've talked about
why it's important to assess
the performance
of household water treatment,
and we also talked
about recommendations
on performance
of household water treatment.
The third thing I want to talk about
is the WHO scheme
to evaluate household
water treatment technologies,
which is specifically how WHO
and governments are working
to implement these recommendations.
There are two main objectives
to this scheme.
The first is to promote and coordinate
the independent testing and evaluation
of household water treatment products
based on the WHO criteria.
Now, I would like to stress
the word "independent"
because often we find that laboratories,
especially in particular countries
do not have the ability
to provide independent
and objective evaluations.
The second is to support
of national governments
in building the technical capacity
of research institutions.
So improve the ability for governments
to assess local products,
to do complementary testing
in the field of household
water treatment products,
especially after they've been in use
for some time.
And this is all linked
to WHO's greater work
in water quality on applying
the WHO guidelines
on drinking water quality.
In summary, I would like
to stress two main points.
First, hopefully by now
you've understood that the assessment
of household water treatment performance
is important for protecting health.
Now, I spoke only about
the microbiological performance
of household water treatment.
The chemical performance
of household water treatment
also is important and is something
that WHO recognizes needs to be addressed
but has not been developed yet
in terms of a set of global guidelines.
I also want to make sure
you leave by remembering
that it's equally important
that these products are used
correctly and consistently
by the groups that are most
at risk for diarrheal disease,
so young children, people with HIV/AIDS,
those in emergencies
or in cholera outbreaks
are just a few examples.
Secondly, the WHO international scheme
to evaluate household water treatment
aims, first of all, to inform
and to provide objective information
about performance.
But it also hopes to spark innovation,
and already we're seeing
that manufacturers are trying
to develop technologies
that not only are highly protective,
but also are low cost, easy to use
and can be easily distributed in places
where water quality is at its poorest.
And lastly, the scheme aims
to build capacity,
so some day in the future
we can work ourselves out of the job,
and governments themselves
can evaluate and regulate
household water treatment technologies.
So I would like to thank you
for your attention.
I would like to point you to some
additional resources and information.
First of all, if you want to read
the performance recommendations
I spoke about,
you can find them online
at this web address.
These are the recommendations.
Also if you want to learn more
about the scheme
you can go to the website that presents
all the information about the scheme,
the related protocols, the laboratories.
And lastly, if you are just interested
in household water treatment
more generally,
I refer you to the WHO UNICEF
International Network
on Household Water Treatment
and Safe Storage,
which is working on a variety of issues
to try to make sure household
water treatment gets to where it's needed
and used by those most in need.
So, thank you.