This week we've explored monitoring
and evaluation of HWTS
from a variety of angles,
from the validation
of specific technologies
to understanding why effective
and consistent use of HWTS
is important for achieving
health improvements.
We've also examined how to choose
among the many treatment
and storage approaches,
especially in terms of cost-effectiveness.
During this module we'll look
at how some of these important issues
are being confronted within
a rural water supply program in Nepal.
In this case study you'll see how
drinking water quality goals were defined,
how water quality data was collected
in remote communities
with very limited resources, and finally,
how this information is being used
to choose an effective and viable
water treatment and storage strategy.
The Water Supply Treatment group
here in Sandek aims
to merge research
with development cooperation
to improve the lives of people
in the global South
so our objectives are really twofold:
we plan and implement
water supply projects
in cooperation
with our partner organizations,
and we also conduct systematic research
and share our study results
at conferences and also
in peer-reviewed publications.
(water splashing)
We learned about
the Helvetas Swiss intercooperation
Water Resource Management project,
or WARM, in Nepal.
For many years now, Helvetas
has been working throughout Nepal
to identify water resources
and foster effective, equitable
and efficient use at the local level.
This is mainly done
through a participatory process
which leads to a Master plan
and this plan is then adopted and owned
by the community members themselves.
In the WARM project
there's a specific goal
to integrate household water treatment
and safe storage, or HWTS
to improve the health and hygiene
of people living within the program area.
To ensure sustainability of the project,
promotion and implementation
of HWTS will harness local markets,
and also focus on meeting
household demand for these products.
So now, Helvetas
and Sandek are working together
to conduct a study across the program area
to better understand
what sort of treatment strategy
can work well in this setting.
Overall, the main objective of the study
is to devise one or more
effective water treatment
and safe storage solutions
for the WARM project area.
This includes assessing
drinking water quality at taps
and in storage containers within homes.
Often, in communities
where households are extremely remote
and where data on water quality
is quite lacking.
Water quality information was needed
to understand the extent
to which treatment was required,
and also to assess the impact
of possible water treatment intervention.
We also needed to understand
behavioral aspects
of household water management,
such as individuals' perceptions
about the quality
of their drinking water source
and also whether households are currently
using any treatment
or safe storage practices.
Finally, since Helvetas is focused
on a market-driven approach
to implementing HWTS,
we undertook a survey
of local market conditions
as well as customers' priorities
for future investments,
and their willingness to pay
for water treatment technologies.
A researcher is not
a businessperson, indeed.
We also have to keep in mind
that at certain times
and in certain contexts,
there could be alternatives
that are more suitable
than market-based interventions.
Let us recall that our ultimate objective
is the general health of the population.
Are we replacing the role of government
by placing priority on what sells?
In which context should one leave
the provision of safe water
to the government, with water quality
as a subject of consumer protection?
So what does this study
look like on the ground?
Mostly it's a lot of time spent
collecting and processing water samples,
sometimes under very
challenging conditions.
We aim that a testing procedure
that meets the WHO guidelines,
suits the field conditions,
and keeps costs for consumables
at a reasonable level.
The membrane filtration method
performed best,
but other quantitative methods
like the Multi-Tube
or Most Probable Number method
are still several times more expensive.
I think we have two challenges
here in the Chinese domain
From my side, first is the electricity
because in the case of remote Nepal
you don't have sufficient electricity.
If you conduct this kind of analysis,
you have to make sure you have
24 hour electricity for your incubator.
The second one is the study area,
because in the case of Nepal,
you have hilly mountains, or sometimes
you have to walk maybe two, three hours
to reach the area, so that one is
the most challenging for me.
It was necessary to build an incubator
for the compact dry plates
using a solar voltaic array, and also
using special lightweight materials
so that the incubator
could be carried to communities
across this mountainous terrain.
For the behavior study,
we held in-person interviews
with hundreds of people
to understand more about their daily life
and their needs regarding water.
We asked questions about
their main priorities and concerns,
because sometimes,
as water researchers, it's easy to forget
that there's more to worry about
than a clean drinking water supply.
There's also employment, access
to health care, electricity, food security
and the list goes on.
So the survey also looked closely
at how people perceive
the quality of their own water,
whether they believed it presented
a health risk to them
and to their families,
and also how they treated
their water supply currently, if at all.
All of this information is important
for planning a viable HWTS strategy
because if demand
for a treatment product is very low,
it can't really be expected
that people will be willing
to change their behavior
and treat their own
drinking water consistently.
We can learn from people's demand
for similar products, services or proxies;
their consumer preferences,
and their general approach
to health issues and other risks.
Why don't they currently
treat their water?
We tried to find out
whether they simply dislike the products
currently available on the market,
or they just do not perceive
their water as risky.
How many times does one
have to suffer from diarrhea
before he or she starts boiling
or filtering their water
several times a day?
To investigate the contextual factors,
we interviewed doctors,
pharmacists, merchants,
NGO and government representatives,
and also consumers,
like patients and households.
We combined these interviews
with structured observations
and data from health institutions
and markets to understand the low priority
that most households currently place
on preventing diarrhea.
Pharmaceuticals are often
available at no cost.
People seem to prefer using them
for severe sicknesses
while overlooking
minor digestive disorders
and preventative options.
Yet, exposure to pathogens also has
long term effects like stunting,
and can generally impair
the immune system.
This is a connection
that most households do not seem to make,
and we can observe a similar attitude
among Western city dwellers
suffering from smoke, but choosing
not to wear protective masks
despite the known health hazards.
The results from our study
are still coming out,
but already we're seeing
a very interesting story.
We know that in many cases,
the water at the point of collection
is relatively free of fecal contamination
but on the other hand, some taps have
very high concentrations of E. coli
and this presents a real
health risk to the local community.
This heterogeneity in quality is important
because nearly all
of the water points visited
are classified as an improved water source
according to the definition used
by the Millenium Development goals.
Yet, we see that this categorization is
not enough to reliably ensure
a safe drinking water
source in this setting.
We're also learning that households
generally do not practice water treatment
or safe storage consistently.
Most households perceive
their water source to be relatively clean
and the risk to health
to be relatively low,
so really, it makes sense
that they're not motivated
to treat their own water.
The market study has also revealed
that despite the availability
of many HWTS products locally,
they are not actually
prioritized by households
when they consider the many other things
that they could spend their money on
such as food, housing, soap and toilets.
All of these items were typically
a higher priority investment
among survey respondents.
In the next phase of this study
we'll work closely with Helvetas
to develop a strategy for improving
household water quality
based on the results
from this baseline evaluation.
It's clear that a market-driven approach
will need to confront many issues,
including highly variable water quality
at the point of collection,
also relatively low demand
for HWTS products among water users.
So, possible strategies could include
an information campaign
to raise awareness among water users,
or maybe testing innovative technologies
like passive chlorination at the tap,
possibly even promotion
of a really aspirational product
of some kind, which households
might value more.
Finding a sustainable solution
really requires constant dialogue
with our partners, and especially,
the potential customers
who will be using these products.
Our team is really excited to see
how this project will unfold
going forward.