Hello.
Welcome to this module
on Local Treatment Solutions.
My name is Juliette Ndounla.
I'm a post-doctoral researcher at Sandec,
the Department of Water and Sanitation
in Developing Countries,
at the Swiss Federal Institute
for Aquatic Science and Technology.
Today I will present a case study
of water quantity and water quality issues
from Dschang,
a small town in Cameroon,
here in the west region
and from some villages
of the Yitenga province
in Burkina Faso, around here.
As we can notice,
in several rural
and pre-rural areas in Africa,
as well as in many developing countries,
people face the challenge
of unsafe drinking water
for their daily activities.
This water could be collected
from wells, rivers, lakes,
and directly from rainwater.
River and well water
may be readily available,
but polluted with biological
and chemical contaminants,
especially during the rainy season,
due to runoff water and floods.
Considering the water quantity issue,
it can be noticed that water supply
is not equally distributed
within these countries.
In the south,
water is usually available
in enough quantity,
particularly in Cameroon,
which is situated
near the Equatorial line.
However, this water is subject
to high contamination levels,
especially during the rainy season,
while the north of both countries
is subject to serious water shortages
during the drought,
the [inaudible] of the dry season.
The water quality issue--
We noticed the presence
of total coliforms,
E. coli, coliforms,
and salmonella bacteria
in several drinking water sources
from these countries.
The consequence of these is
the serious outbreak
of water-related diseases,
such as typhoid, cholera, and dysentery.
These were noticed, recorded
in both of these countries,
as a consequence
of unsafe drinking water supply.
As presented in the previous slide,
Dschang is situated in
the western region of Cameroon.
In Dschang, water is available
all year long.
However, as the water table
is near the surface
in [inaudible], in Dschang,
the people from such places use,
regularly, unimproved wells,
as the one present here,
using a car wheel
for the well superstructure.
These traditional, unprotected wells
are regularly contaminated
with air and surface pollution,
and runoff water.
The presence of shoes and leaves
could be noticed in such water,
also heavy contamination of bacteria
such as salmonella typhi,
entamoeba histolytica,
[inaudible],
lead to water-related diseases
such as typhoid or dysentery.
These water-related diseases
and several other gastroenteritis
are regularly experienced
by well-users in Dschang.
The turbidity of this water is regularly
more than 100 NTU,
[inaudible] here.
To reduce the health vulnerability
when using water
from your unimproved well,
the owner uses traditional filters
made with locally available materials
such as sheet metal,
old nylon sacks,
old mattresses under
the old nylon sacks, and stones.
This homemade filter shown here
reduced the water turbidity
to less than 13 NTU,
as it can be observed here.
However, this filter process
cannot make this water
completely safe for drinking purposes.
To be safe for drinking,
this water will require
additional disinfecting steps,
such as solar disinfection
or chlorination.
In Burkina Faso, Moringa Oleifera
is used as the local solution
for water purification in some villages.
Moringa Oleifera is a tropical tree
from which seed can be ground
to a powder and used
as a natural coagulant.
People from the villages situated
around the Yitenga-Pouytenga dam
often use Moringa seed powder
for their drinking water purification,
especially to reduce turbidity.
The Moringa seed powder process
and efficiencies in water purification
has been scientifically
evaluated and recommended.
This method is more efficient
than using a homemade filter,
shown in the previous slide,
and the steps are simple
and easy to practice.
The purifying principle of clarification
not only diminishes
chemical contamination
but also harmful bacteria.
Remaining on local solutions
used by village people,
we find also in the Yitenga region
that some people
were using aluminum sulfate
for their water purification.
However, aluminum is expensive,
and if improperly used
may be linked to health problems
or environmental pollution.
Using Moringa Oleifera instead
to purify water
efficiently replaces
such chemical products.
The Moringa process
for water purification--
First they begin with the grinding
of dry seed into powder.
The powder should be put after
in a small quantity of water,
approximately 250 ml,
and shaken for approximately
five minutes.
Then after, this small quantity
of water is put
in the water to be treated,
here it's 20 liters,
and rapidly stirred for two minutes,
and after slowly stirred
for 10-15 minutes,
before leaving the water undisturbed
for approximately one hour,
or until the water is clear,
depending on the initial turbidity
of the water.
When all the impurities are settled down
the water should now be filtered,
and put in a safe container
before being drunk
by the family members.
The main recommendation
for the Moringa seed dosage
is to consider the water source,
as water from marine sources will need
a different amount of Moringa powder
because the impurities present
will not be the same.
It's also recommended
to make a jar test
to help in evaluating the correct amount
of the powder needed.
However, this table provides
the general guidelines for the dosage.
In the presence of low turbidity,
less than 50 NTU,
the recommendation is to use
one seed per four liters,
and in the presence of extreme turbidity,
more than 250 NTU,
you would need two seeds
per liter of water.
Like many other water treatment processes,
the use of Moringa Oleifera seed powder
in water treatment
also has some limitations.
It could lead to secondary infection
if the process of shaking or stirring
is not well handled.
This process of shaking and handling
should be followed closely
to activate the coagulant properties,
because if the flocculation process
takes too long
there is a risk
of secondary bacteria growth
during the flocculation.
The treated water
could also face recontamination
if the settling process
is not well handled.
It should be noticed that the sediment
at the bottom of the water,
after settling,
contains some impurities.
so care must be taken to use
only the clear water on the top,
and not allow the sediment
to recontaminate the clear water
after the treatment.
We should also consider that Moringa
does not provide residual disinfection,
so there is a possibility
of recontaminating the water
through contact with hands
during the transfer
of the treated water in a safe container.
Care should be taken during this transfer.
Finally, we should notice that
the Moringa treatment
[cannot be] 100% effective in removing
of pathogens in the water
during its treatment.
It's important to consider combining
this natural coagulant process
with additional steps
of water disinfection.
In conclusion,
recall that local populations
in developing countries struggle
to handle their safe water production.
They may even need to use
local available materials for filtering,
as we've seen in Cameroon,
or use Moringa seed powder
in water purification,
as we saw in Burkina Faso.
However, they still need training
and recommendation,
in both cases, for safe and sustainable
household water treatment.
This water, treated at the household level
for drinking purposes,
still needs additional disinfecting
treatment, as we saw previously.
Some of those steps will be
solar disinfection or chlorination.
Additional information
on Moringa process details
for water purification can be found
at the links below.
However, if there are still
some questions and queries
about one of the case studies
presented here,
[inaudible],
just let us know
through a question in the course's forum,
and it will be a pleasure for us
to answer it.
Thank you for following us.