In this lecture,
I'm going to cover locality.
Locality is the notion that
you would probably intuitively assume
is about things being
close to each other or not.
A little focus to some extent
on date locality,
versus locality of computation.
Nowadays, in more and more
scenarios in computer science,
we realize that data governs computation
and if we remove computation
to better data rather than vice versa.
Of course, there will be concerns
about parallelization,
concurrency and networking
but we have to worry about computations
happening in different places
but usually, everything
is centered around data.
Locality in a sense is the aspect
of system that most closely relates
software systems with the physical world.
With the world of atoms and matter, etc.
We can fundamentally only pack
so much memory and computing power
into a limited space.
If we build a CPU, there will be
gates, transistors inside the CPU
and the amount of integration
we can do will be limited
by physical concerns of the real world.
As data and computation needs grow,
we'll get into locality problems.
Data, just like computation,
takes space inside chips
or other devices.
In a sense we can reduce pretty much
any concern about the performance
in the systems to locality considerations.
In computing, essentially all time
and energy costs is due to moving
data over a distance.
That's relatively clear if you think about
the data transfer, let's say from RAM
to a CPU cache.
Obviously the time this takes is governed
by the speed of light
and the time it takes
to move to see the message
from the RAM to the CPU.
It is in the more abstract sense
also truthful computing in general.
If you figure the gates
and the connections in between them
inside the CPU,
we can think of a computation
being governed by the way it travels
by some bits that is involved
in the computation.
So even if you got a loop, that means that
the bits flow in some sense
several ways in circles so to say
from the same gates in general
we can still think of this as
overall time travels governing
the time it takes to do the computation.
Now, there's fundamental limits
to shrinking the distances
these electrons have to travel.
There is quantum effect to soon take over
as we integrate our chips further,
make them smaller.
So automatically it will not be able
to work with messages that are constituted
by less than one electron.
And there's of course, noise,
on these very small scales
that will require to have
more than one electron.
There is this fundamental
failure of Dennard Scaling,
that we observe in computer
architecture, which is in a sense,
more fundamental, less contested
and more important than what we
sometimes consider the feel of,
the upcoming feel of Moore's law.
So, in Dennard scaling, Dennard's law,
refers to the empirical effect over
many decades now.
We've been able to reduce
the voltages needed
to run our computations
with the size integrations
that means we double the number
of gates, we half the size
of each gate needed so overall the space
didn't grow and we also halved'
the voltages needed
so we didn't need more energy.
Now this Dennard Law is now failing
and it's really failing permanently.
Which means, we still might be able to
integrate and decrease sizes
for some more time, energies
and energy densities increase
which means our chips get hotter,
and it gets harder to keep them cool.
That also relates to the fact
that only have two or if you like to see
at most three dimensions to pack stuff
and that means gates in a CPU into space.
People right now are working
on three dimensional chips
but already for two dimensional chips,
right now with this high integrations
cooling is very hard
and for three dimensional chips,
it gets even harder.
So cooling becomes
a really important challenge
apart from the fact that if
you are using a lot of energy,
that also has a cost.
Computation links need space.
Buses and networks increasingly become
bottlenecks as we
integrate and grow our data
and our computation capacities further.
That means, as we have computers
with more and more data at the disposal
or storage capacities at their disposal,
the relative bandwidths for transferring
this data decreases.
In many, if not in most
modern applications we care about.
Including big data analytics,
video streaming, things like this.
CPUs are now mainly waiting
for data to arrive,
and one could argue that this should
inform and guide us in our design
of new hardware.
But this is not just for two
or three dimensional
applications of course.
The solution to this, of course is cache
hierarchies, prefetching, etc.
Now, there's an important notion
of memory hierarchies and we should
talk about this a little.
If you think of a computer system,
it will have multiple CPUs.
maybe with multiple cores.
Here on this right side we have
an example picture where we've got
single core CPUs and these CPUs
have caches.
Then there's the anagram that connects
to these caches and connects
at the same time also
to the storage devices.
They might be storage devices like
hard drives, flash drives, etc.
And they themselves have (inaudible)
several layers of (inaudible)
including the physical storage device
and then a number of caches, potentially.
It is important to understand and remember
that there's vastly different
transfer rates and speeds at which
these different devices can be accessed
for read and write.
On this slide I've got
a number of examples
for a specific model
and chip and you can see that
in all the times it takes
to do certain tasks even inside the CPU
for different caches really differs
by two orders of magnitude basically.
So if I take the fastest cache
and I hit something it means
it is in the cache and I don't
have to go further to find
my data, it takes about
four cycles on this chip
while having to access
the level three cache
off that CPU and let's say
even on a different CPU
on that same main board
might take hundreds of cycles.
Now if we assume that this chip
has a (inaudible) frequency of
three gHz, then accessing
local TRAM which takes,
let's say six nanoseconds,
takes 180 cycles.
Accessing or seeking on a hard drive
10 milliseconds, takes about
40 million cycles, so we see
a vast difference on the magnitude
and speed, about seven orders
of magnitude between fast caches
and hard drives. Of course there's devices
that are even slower.
So there are a number of basic principles
to optimize locality that we are going
to talk about in this series of videos.
I have a group of three major ideas here.
The first is caching, which is about
keeping some kind of work inside
of data that's frequently used
close to where the computation happens.
Another one is to prefer sequential
over random access.
Physics governs that some data
is better read or written sequential
than by random access, that's true
for many kinds of devices.
It's very obvious for hard drives or tapes
but it's also true for even an ananogram
for example.
In a sense, prefetching connects caching
and this notion of sequential
over random access in a sense that
when you do things like branch prediction.
If you try to predict what to prefetch
into a cache, often enough you try to get
more of the same. We try to continue
sequential that we have been reading.
And another, in a sense the final major
class of things that you can do
for locality is partitioning
and dealing with data
in a data parallel way.
Not necessarily using parallelization
but basically splitting up the parts
and doing divide and conquer.
We're going to talk in future videos
about use cases
like out of core algorithms,
things like joints and sorting.
Let's closer into these three strategies
and start with caching.
Caching is really everywhere in systems
there's many examples and just some
of them are of course, the CPU caches.
In address translation,memory management,
as the translation look at side buffers.
In networks there's many examples,
one is edge caches which are really
fundamental to be able to do for example
streaming video on the internet
in reasonable times.
Another example are buffers
in operating systems, data base management
systems, storage device controllers, etc.
Another example is materialized use
in database systems.
There you can basically take a query and
store the query result for future use.
Caching is actually frequently equated
with localities so if you look
at our textbook, Salzer and Kaashoek,
there's a performance chapter
and in there they talk about locality
and for them it's just caching
and I think there's more to it.
We mentioned prefetching
as one way to do speculative filling
of a cache, to have stuff in there
that you might use next
so that you don't have to wait for it
How can you do it?
There's of course different techniques
and many of them are trade secrets
but often enough
there's nothing better
that you can do than to assume
that some loop is going to continue
and you're going to eat more of the stuff
that you've been just reading on
sequentially from wherever
on the next lower level no matter where
or how the data is coming from.
That connects us to sequential access.
Sequential access is fast
than random access
in many different kinds
of storage devices
in the memory technology.
What does this mean?
So there is some notion
of locality of storage
for example in a hard drive,
things can be stored sequentially
in tracks on disks, on RAM there are
gates close to each other
that have addresses similar to each other
and we're going to talk about
sequential access via reading
things that are close to each other
in physical storage versus random access
we have to jump around and go from one
(inaudible) to the other
that are completely unrelated
to each other.
Now in hard drives, it's perfectly clear
why sequential access is faster than
random access.
There, we've got a physical read/write head
and we've got a rotating disk
so that the read/write test has to place
itself on the right track on our disks
and the disks have to rotate to the right
place to be able to start reading
a particular address.
That takes time because we've got
mechanical pieces rotating, moving around
and that's of course, extremely slow
on the time scales that they talk about
in the context of computing.
Now, your seek times in modern
disks are on the level of let's say
ten milliseconds each time.
Once you're at the right place,
transferring lots and lots
of pages of data, very quickly,
that's kind of fast.
We might be reading tens of mega bytes
per second, so if we have to randomly
jump around for each byte and incur
ten milliseconds of sync time, every time,
we're going to have
horrible access times.
While, if we get to go to a place
and then sequential read basically
off the hard drive, that's going to be
quite good.
It is also true for devices
that are not like this,
that are not physically a rotating
disk for example.
Let's take for example
flash and solid state devices.
They designed model solid state devices
in a way that you can only write
certain sized blocks.
This is actually also true for hard drives
but you can write only to places
that are empty in a sense,
and if something is not empty
you have to erase it first.
While you cannot just write
individual bytes, let's say,
or words to locations but you have to
write in blocks.
Erasure applies to even larger blocks.
So, we mean if you've got a fragmented
solid state drive you must first
defragment it, erasing large regions
to be able to do this.
You might have to move useless stuff
that you still need around
and solid state devices controls have
garbage collectors and corresponding
caching strategies, etc.
Counterintuitively it's actually
also true for dynamic RAM.
That means sequential access is preferred
over random access
for random access memory.
That's counterintuitive but why
is that true? Well, one is
if you want to address
a consecutive block of memory
in random access memory,
there are techniques for optimizing
this information transfer
on the bus this requests
to actually use little space
you might see "I want to read this range",
or "I want to transfer this entire block
in random access memory".
That can be done more efficiently
than having to address each individual
position.
Also, if you do random access to DRAM
you will have lots of misses in the
translation local side buffer
while you could do prefetching
properly to sequential access.
Finally, there's partitioning,
so we've got a problem that consists
of larger pieces of data
having to be processed
and we can decompose this data
into pieces, process each of these
pieces independently, without having
to look at the other pieces
having two local result and then combining
these results, that's what they call
embarrassingly parallel.
This means, no communication
needed between these pieces
of locally (inaudible) these different
pieces and process them.
A more classic example is map/reduce
which really relies on the ability
to assign map tasks to different pieces
and combine their results.
Of course, that's not
applicable everywhere.
So it's actually a non phenomenon
that frequently, when we look at the graph
the data gets processed in and by that
I mean, not simply that our data
is graph shaped but there are
certain dependencies on aligning
our data, relationships between
pieces of data that can be resent
in different ways.
For example, as relations, but also
as graphs, for example.
The ace, in this graph is a relatively small
diameter, so these are
the so called "small world phenomenon"
"small world graphs" and these graphs
have no small cuts that means
such problems, and they
are very ubiquitous and you'll see this
in the next video, they cannot
be processed in an embarrassingly
parallel fashion.
And that's very frequent actually.
To summarize, we've been talking
about data locality, its fundamental
nature that connects the physical world
with software systems, its impact
on performance, and arguably,
its (inaudible) to care about
when you think about performance.
You can always connect performance
with a data locality problem,
fundamentally.
We've talked about three broad strategies
for dealing with locality
and making things more local.
These were caching,
sequential access preferred
and partitioning.