Well next we're going
to talk about locality
in the context of data structure
and data structures.
We will not be very concrete
about data structures
talking about specific
tree data structures for example.
We will talk in general about arrays,
about trees and about graphs
and what implications these kinds
of data, have on locality.
We're going to assume
that there is basically
a single linearly local memory.
That means, there's only, you know,
in a single dimension,
there are ediation data elements.
Now let's look at an array;
any dimensional array.
Let's say a two dimensional array.
A matrix, for example.
If we have such a matrix we stored
in a linear memory,
then we would actually have
to shred up this two dimensional array
into a sequence of several linear pieces.
So for example, in the matrix
on the right here, we can shred it up
column by column
and concatanate the columns
and store it so that it enters
a matrix as a linear array.
Or you could do it,
row by row, for example.
If we do computations on this array,
we will have to worry about
whether my looping order
matches my representation order.
So for example, if I have stored
my array, one column after the other,
I could do two ways to loop
all the elements of this array.
The first would be, that a loop,
let's say of an index "I" first
and then of an index "J" or "Aij"
that means for each column
I loop over each row,
over each element.
The second choice would be
to do the other way around.
For each row, I iterate
over all the columns.
And given that we've decided to store
column by column,
the first way to do this is vastly
more efficient then the second.
Because the first basically does overall
a single linear scan over
the entire linearist version of the array
while the second choice makes
a huge number of random accesses, right?
One random access basically for
every element in the array.
So we would have to get performance
well done here.
We would have to align our storage
layout with the use cases, or visa versa.
That means if I have the ability
to reorder my loops, I could do this
automatically to adapt myself
to the storage layout.
That's something that is actually
happening in compilers
that use loop reordering
to get good performance.
Visa versa, if I know a workload,
a set of use cases,
a set of different kinds of algorithms
that I want to run,
I could potentially optimize
my storage structures for these.
And that's something that is
important in databases.
So, concerns about sorting, nesting,
and grouping as we're doing it here,
co-clustering. All these concern database
systems that relate to such data stuctures
and their arrays and relations.
One thing that is particularly important
in this context is this consideration
of row versus column-stores
and columnar representations.
We've basically just discussed this
but there is more to say about it.
In the context of databases
specifically in data warehousing
and analytical databases
there is now a big battle
that basically has been won by the column-
stores, between row and column-stores.
And it can be argued that column-stores,
those that actually take relations
and shred them up column by column
and store the columns individually.
they are better suited for many
analytical tasks than classical row stores
where either relations
are stored in pages,
and each page consists of
a sequence of tuples.
And why is that?
Because many analytical queries
use relations that have many columns
and many such queries use only
some of the relations.
That means I've got a choice
to use row-store,
and I would have to fetch
all of the tuples in entirety.
And then always throw away stuff
that I don't need in each of these tuples.
Or I could store them column by column.
Then I would only fetch those columns
that I care about and combine those
into those projected relations,
hese partial relations that are
necessary to actually add to the query.
Also if I store column by column,
I can use compression
on this more effectively.
That means if for example,
I have a column that stores
telephone numbers then
if I compress only these columns,
all the telephone numbers together,
I will be able to reach much better
compression rates then if I store
and compress an entire address table
with street addresses, personal names
and identifiers, but also phone numbers,
for example together, tuple by tuple.
Because then the phone
numbers are not local
next to each other
and I need a much smarter,
more intelligent compressions
algorithm or I will need something
much more general.
If I have only phone numbers
I will have only ten digits maybe,
right, that I have to compress
and I can use better compression schemes
that are more succinct.
That means there will be less to read
and write from and to disk
and I will be faster overall
because the disks are slow.
But this is a concern that is not just
true and relevant in databases,
even for example look at option on
the programming language
specifically about the Java
virtual machine then the same applies.
Actually column representations
are much more efficient
row representations
of (inaudible) relations.
So take an example of
a row representation
where you've got an array of structures
and each struct
has two integers inside.
So it's basically two tuples, right?
So you can think of this as an option
on the representation
of a relational database table.
Now I could do this or I could use
a pivoted column representation
where I've got a struct,
a pair of two integers arrays.
And I can store the same data in there
and I can relink this data
by the array index.
Now these relations are equivalent
but actually the second,
the column representation
is vastly more efficient.
So why is that?
Well if you think of what happens inside
Java you'll see that in the first case
you're producing linearly many objects,
while in the second you only
produce constantly many.
Simply because each of the structs
in the first case is going to be an object.
And this means that in practice
at runtime we will create and destroy
vast amounts of objects
and of course this pollutes
the entire memory hierarchy.
You're going to see this in the caches
as well and if you make a deep analysis
of what your program does you will see
a surprising number of object creations
and destructions that you wouldn't
potentially expect, just temporarily.
Actually a column representation
can be much more efficient
in this context then a row representation
even in the context
of let's say the Java virtual machine.
Now let's look at trees.
Let's take an example of a binary tree,
but a Belan's binary tree.
So such a tree on each level
has twice as many nodes
as on the level above.
So in a sense, as you go downwards
the tree grows exponentially fast.
And there is no way to store
the data of this tree in a linear memory
or even a finite dimensional memory.
So that the parent-child relation
remains close and preserved.
That means parents are stored
close to their children.
No matter how you present the tree
you're going to have to tear this apart
and there will be non local child-parent pairs.
That means going from parent to child
would be a big jump.
That means we are basically, so to say,
hopelessly lost in the context of trees.
What we can do, however, is we can
keep siblings local
by let's say a breadth-first enumeration.
And even if you take
a depth-first enumeration
to store your data, you know, linearly.
It remains essentially local
because the lowest level
dominates the overall size,
the lowest level is as big as the rest.
So if you care about the lowest level
you can read it sequentially,
you have just
an overhead of effectors too.
And that ultimately is the
basis of tree indexing.
Let's say in databases
but in general in data structures.
So let's look at these tree indexes
a bit more in detail.
So the leaf level of a balanced tree
is essentially local
in reasonable representations
we've already said that.
And that's the idea of a primary,
let's say B tree index
in a database management system.
We can align the leaf level
with the sort order the data files.
So we assume the index is separate
from the actual stored data.
Of course we could store the data
in the B tree index itself
but let's assume we don't do this
because we want to have
many indexes on the same data.
So we store the actual data
in a Heap file, in some sort order.
And if we have just one index
and that index gives us sorted access,
you can efficiently find data elements
and then let's say we can scan
from an item we found from there
to the right sequentially
and find elements that are next large
in the sort order of that tree index.
And that way we can officially
do range indexes--range lookups.
If I want to do a search
for a range of values,
for which I've got an index structure,
I don't have to find each value
in that range individually
I go to the first value
and then I read to the write
until I find a value
that is out of the range.
Now the problem is, that's well known
in the context of databases,
I can have at most one such index
that is aligned with the sorting order
of the data structure in general,
of the actual data file.
If I have a second that uses
a different sorting criterium
they cannot be both aligned
if they're sorted.
That means one of those different
data structures will require completely
random access to the data
which will be very inefficient.
Now in general if you go down
from the root to find our elements,
always compare. Do we take the left
or the right side
of the children, of each node?
We're going to do random access.
Overall as we down we will do
logarithmicly many steps of random access
to get to our data.
And then if we want to fetch
many items in the primary index
that is aligned in sort order
with the data file, we can then scan on
and get all the items out until
there is an item
that we don't want anymore.
But if it's the secondary index,
the one that is not aligned,
it's not like this.
So here's an example
on the right hand side.
So you see that we've got a data file
with binary tuples
and the tree above the data file
as shown is indexing the first column
of this relation and the data file
is ordered by that first column.
That means if for example,
I want to find all my values
from five to 14, I use the B tree index
to find value five and then I scan
on the data file until I find
the value 14 or above, and then I stop.
On the other hand I've got
a second B tree index
shown below the data file in this example.
And that index on the second value
as you see at the bottom level,
these pointers that connect
the leaves of the B tree
with the actual data file.
It's completely out of order,
lots of crossing, it's random access.
That means of course that if I want
to do a range lookup
it will be very inefficient.
I will have to find each value
individually and have to jump around
and jump around.
And that's going to be terrible.
So in that case it's probably better
to just scan the entire data file
and just take the values that actually
match the selection condition.
But even the primary index
is not that greatly useful
because if you think about this
you could just as well
do a binary search on the actual data file
to get the same effect
as looking it up in the binary tree.
Now let's look into graphs.
So we have to distinguish
a number of types of graphs,
graphs that have different properties.
Well first there are the graphs
whose edge relations
are really having a local representation.
And there is really not
some interesting graphs here.
We've got chains, right?
Or even trees and we've
discussed this before,
they're not interesting in general.
And then there are the graphs
that have relatively small cuts.
What does this mean?
I mean by that,
I've got the representation of the graph
and I can cut the representation
into pieces so that in each piece
there are some nodes and lots of edges
and there's only very few edges
that cross in the pieces
between two nodes and different pieces.
Those edges I also have to record
because in general, they matter.
These graphs with small cuts
they can be essentially processed,
more or less by
embarrassing parallelism,
piece by piece and then I have to worry
about edges that connect them.
It depends, of course, on the algorithmic
problem that I'm trying to solve,
whether that's that simple but in general
small cuts are good.
And these small cuts exist in certain
resource-constrained graphs.
Let's, for example, talk about planar
or almost planars embeddings
into a 2D surface.
What do we mean by this?
Just imagine a map of the world,
for example.
And I've got a graph and I can project
the nodes of that graph to positions
in the map so that
no edges cross each other.
So that would be a planar embedding.
And almost planar is if there are
only a few edges crossing each other.
Now a road network, where I think of
roads never tunneling under each other,
there are no bridges.
I always think of roads being connected
where there is a bridge,
they would be planar graphs.
So from a certain view point on a high
level, if you look at maps of a country,
road maps of a country,
these are planar graphs.
So these are not trees but they have
a relatively low degree of cyclicity.
They have few redundant, non-local links.
So for example, in a road network,
roads take space. I cannot look
at any particular line on that map
and say an arbitrary number of roads
could cross this line of a certain length.
Because roads have a certain
width. It doesn't make sense
to put roads higher
than a certain density
into the map because
people couldn't use them,
it would be expensive,
there would be no space
in the country left for
other things than roads.
If you look at physical internetworks,
there you have to deal with
line costs and routing complexity, etc.
It doesn't make sense or it would
just be extremely expensive
if we have linearly many in
the number of nodes
in the internetwork, deep sea lines
between Europe and US.
There are relatively few
and they hopefully
have good enough bandwidth.
But if you make cuts, there are small cuts
between these areas.
Although the graph is not a tree,
it has relatively few cycles
actually compared to its size.
And if you think about it
the human brain
connecting neurons, in a sense
it's such a graph in practice
because there are physical constrains.
We cannot have infinitely many
connections between neurons
in a finite amount of area or space.
But then there are all other graphs
and they are locality a nightmare.
And there are many many
interesting examples,
Internet communication patterns.
Differently from the
Internet networking infrastructure
there are the communication patterns.
Who connects to whom.
And these graphs don't have
these small cuts
or social networks in general.
Of course Internet communication
patterns you can think of social networks.
Or the brain in practice.
And there are many other examples.
To talk about these other graphs,
the bad graphs,
let's talk a bit about random graphs.
So what is a random graph?
We've got a set of nodes, initially
without any edges and then I randomly,
I toss some coins and choose
some pair of node
and make an edge between them.
So if a randomly add edges,
completely randomly
until I get more and more edges,
there are some predictable
structs to these graphs.
The first thing that is
worth mentioning is
as I reach a certain edge to node ratio,
which is about one,
essentially, all the graph gets connected.
It becomes very unlike these big
disconnected components because there are
so many nodes in each of these components
that probably at least two of them
are connected somewhere.
So we get these monster components,
that's well understood.
Such graphs always tend to have
a low degree of separation.
That's the small world phenomenon.
And they have no small cuts.
That means as we said before,
if you try to take the graph,
the set of nodes and partition into two
equal sized sets of nodes
there is no way to do this.
Such that, there are very few,
let's say, constantly
or sup-linearly many edges
between these two sets of nodes.
And the interesting thing is that's
already true when the graph is sparse.
Which means that the
edge to node ratio is just linear.
Of course the edge to node ratio
could be up to quadratic
but already for linear edge to node
ratios for random graphs
we have to since there are no small cuts.
And that's of course bad because
embarrassing parallelism
is not possible in general anymore.
So if we talk about real-world graphs
and networks and we're excluding
those resource constraint graphs
that we've talked about before,
road-networks, the physically
internetwork, etc.
Then arguably we could say
essentially all the other graphs
and networks are of that kind,
they behave like random graphs
and they have these nasty properties.
So one thing that is known to say
a bit more about random--
about graphs as they happen
in reality that are actually random-like,
there are alternative characterizations,
that are actually very robust
and interchangeable for here, for this.
So take for example a random graph
in which you add neighbors
such that there is a power law,
in the sense shift distribution.
There are logarithmically few nodes
which have exponentially many links.
And then there's degrees,
more and more nodes
that have fewer and fewer links.
That's called a power law graph.
Another thing is typical social networks,
where they've got this "rich get richer"
phenomenon.
Popular people get even more friends.
In a sense you could say
it's a random graph again
where you enter edges and node
is more likely to get another edge,
yet another edge, even though
it already has many edges
connecting it to other nodes.
So that's the "rich get richer"
phenomenon.
And you see this very often
in social networks of all kinds.
Or these so called small world graphs
which have only these
"k degrees of separation" famously
has been observed that
probably there is about
six degrees of separation in the world.
So that over a sequence of six people,
I know any person in the world.
So I've got a friend, who has a friend,
who has a friend, etc. six times
I connect to anybody in
the world about like this.
So this has studied in more detail,
for example in Facebook where you
can formally study this
with a real graph, people have observed
that degree of separation
is about five point something.
And probably decreases with time.
Now the important thing is to say there
are three different characterizations
that are actually equivalent.
An important thing again is you have
this property, no small cuts
and that's really true for
all sparse graphs.
All these graphs have this
problem that essentially--
if you do have this random component,
there's a lot of noise of natural,
real world phenomenon here.
They behave like random graphs
and there is a way of deterministically
constructing such graphs.
Graphs that have no small cuts
and they are sparse, there are only
linearly many edges and number of nodes.
And this construction is actually
surprisingly difficult given that
if you do it randomly you'll also get this graph.
But it's possible. And these are
called expanding graphs,
they play an important role
in theoretical computer science,
for the derandomization of randomized
algorithms for example.
Now as we said non-resource
bounded real graphs have no small cuts.
I've told you what that is.
That means they cannot be
partitioned effectively
to handle regions independently
without requiring lots of
communication between regions.
So it's essentially impossible
to paralyze graph analytics
effectively on such real graphs
that we see everywhere.
In those contexts in particular
where you want to do graph analytics
like let's say in large social networks,
Facebook, Google, etc.
Well it's impossible in a sense
to do it practically well
but everybody still does it
because we need it.
And there are these system like
[Pragle] and Giraffe and so on,
that do that and they have
horrible performance
if you think about it.
It's really the worst case scenario
from the viewpoint of locality.
Every node has to talk to every node
in every computation step, more or less.
People do it because they have to.
And in a sense, in the worst case
there's nothing you can do about it.
Of course you can assume
that certain algorithmic problems
have a deep-seated property
that you could exploit
if you find it, to make things better.
But in general, that's the situation.
On the other hand, if you talk about
a small world phenomenon
that we have mentioned.
It says something about
locality in a sense.
It says that there are short paths
within any two nodes,
which is of course relevant for routing.
It does not mean that communication
is spatially local.
In the internetwork there are long paths,
there's right area for connections, etc.
But it's local if you only count
the hops, not the time it takes
to move between hops.
And that's also relevant.
If for example, time cost of communication
is somewhat dominated
by the routing for example.
Which we hope is not so often the case.
Well then that's what matters to you.
What we're saying here is still
that there is this notion of
the small world phenomenon
that has been studied
in many different contexts
and it can explored
in many different ways.
For example, in sociology there is
the famous theory of "weak ties"
by Granovetter, which is one of
the most cited papers in sociology,
if not the most cited actually.
And it basically says that if you've got
such a graph,
a social network,
and you've got close neighbors
and more distant neighbors.
For example, you're best friends,
you're drinking buddies
that you see every evening
and you compare those
to those kind of long
distance connections.
For example, your lawyer
that you don't see very often,
who has very different friends, etc.
Then for learning something new,
for getting new connections
over a great distance these weak ties,
these infrequent connections,
the lawyer for example,
is much more useful
than your best friends.
In the sense, you cannot learn
anything from your best friends
because your best friends
they behave equally to you.
They have the same taste,
they have the same favorite movies, etc.
But if you want to, for example,
quickly get to somebody
you don't know via a short chain
to someone in China let's say,
then this distant connection
is much more useful
than the close connection.
That's ultimately also
interestingly used in routing.
If you want to move somewhere
far away you will try to use
the right, hopefully, long distance
connection rather than
move around locally in your network.
That's ineffective.
So to summarize we've talked
about data structures.
We've talked about arrays,
relations, graphs, and trees.
And we have sturdied how locality
effects them and what we can say
about optimizing locality
in all kinds of algorithmic techniques.
This of course, underlies
programming in general.
It underlies databases.
It underlies networks
and there's a lot more to be said.
This was a high level overview.
And there is much more that you can see
in concrete examples.