In this video, we are going
to discuss a concrete example
of an out-of-core algorithm.
That means an algorithm that is going
to work with large amounts of data
and where concerns about memory locality
are highly relevant.
We're going to talk
about join processing.
In general by a join of two relations,
let's say R and S,
we think of trying to consider
all pairs of tuples
from the first relation, R
and the second relation, S
that match a join condition.
And those pairs,
for which this join condition is true,
we output.
So, you see this in tuple quote
in a couple of the slides.
So, we loop away each tuple in R
and each tuple in S,
and we test the join condition.
And if the join condition is true,
in this case some particular field
in tuple of R and another field
in tuple of S match,
then we add the result.
Now, conceptually here for each tuple
in the outer relation,
we scan the the entire inner relation.
The outer relation being the outer loop
of these nested loops.
Now, let's assume an example,
where we've got, let's say,
1,000 pages of R tuples
and 500 pages of S tuples.
And in each page,
let's say we've got 100 R tuples.
So, why this page-based abstraction?
Well, we think of data coming
from our hard drive,
it's too large to make memory a priority,
let's say,
and this example is, of course, small
and there would be enough memory
but with transferring the data
from main memory to RAM,
the process concepts the data there
we will not think in more detail
about caches, etc.
So, essentially it's the cost
of transferring the data
from this into random access memory.
And we're going to see that in this case,
the cost of this overall joint processing
is dominated by the cost of transfers
from the disk and to the disk.
The cost of these seeks and transfers,
it dominates what the CPU does,
because the CPU has to do
relatively easy things here.
So, in this example, conceptually
we're going to read all the data of R ones
that means we're going to read
1,000 pages.
And we're going to read,
for each tuple in R
that is 100 times,
because there are 100 tuples
in each page times 1,000
there's 1,000 pages of R.
For each of those tuples in R,
we have to make a complete loop of S,
S is 500 pages.
That means for each of these loops
we'll read 500 pages.
So, overall the cost is about
50 million IOs.
That of course is quite huge
given these small relations.
Now, one immediate improvement you can do
is to make this page-oriented.
That means we are going to still have
the same looping structure.
We read over each tuple of R,
by reading R page by page,
that means we read a page from R,
we loophole every tuple of R in there,
and then we go to the next page of R.
And in the inner loop we're going to,
again, read S page by page
and in each page read the tuples
and compare them.
We're not going to do this
for each entire page of R,
we're going to make a single scan of S
and compare all the tuples
in that page of R
with the tuples
in that scan of S.
So, on a high level,
R is still the outer relation,
S is the inner relation,
but the looping structure
has changed a bit.
That means S a scan of R over S,
we're not just comparing a single R tuple
to all of these S tuples,
but we're comparing all of the R tuples
in the page that we have not buffered
in main memory to S.
How much main memory does this need?
Conceptually it needs space
for one page of R and one page of S.
The page for S is raised very quickly,
very frequently,
and only after we've done
a complete scan of S
you're going to read a new page of R.
The cost of that is, of course,
greatly reduced,
it's going to be the cost of reading R
completely once,
1,000 pages plus 1,000 times 500 pages,
the number of pages in R
times the number of pages in S,
which is, of course, 100 times faster
than the first solution.
Well, even with such a nested loops join,
we can do better.
And a famous technique here
is the so-called block nested loops join.
And that's a technique that's actually
implemented
in real relation database systems,
and in some cases,
actually the best technique to use.
Beating other things
that might sound more sophisticated
like, let's say for example,
hash joins, or sort-merge joins.
Now, how does that block nested
loop join work?
So, the idea is as follows:
We've got main memory
at the granularity of a number
of certain pages, right?
And let's say we've got P number of pages
of main memory available
to process this join.
So, we're going to partition this
into a certain amount of pages for R
and a certain number of pages for S.
And then we're going in each step
read as many pages, new pages,
into this R buffer or S buffer,
whenever something's exhausted.
How are we going to do this?
Let's assume R is still
the outer relation.
We're going to assign a number of pages
to R, as we said,
we're going to enter it or R by reading
many page of R at once together.
And then we're going to make a scan of S,
by reading as many pages
with results for S
at once into S,
compare them to all the R tuples
occuring in this big, big R buffer
that consists of several pages now.
And then you're going to take
the next chunk of S,
put into the buffer.
Compare to all the R tuples
in that big R buffer
until we've done the complete scan of S
and then we take a new
complete chunk of R tuples
and put into the R buffer,
replacing all the old R tuples.
And then again make a complete scan of S.
Now, how do we decide how
to split the main memory buffers?
We will assign, assuming that you want
to have out buffer,
one page is out-buffer,
and of the remaining pages,
one is the import buffer of S
and all the rest,
for the import buffer of R.
The reason for this will become clear
a bit later.
So, how do we calculate the cost
of this join operation in numbers of IOs?
It means in number of pages read
from this.
Conceptually, we need to make a single
complete scan of the outer relation, R.
And for each of these big chunks
of outer relation tuples.
That means, every time
we fill a block of R,
and then make a complete scan
of the inner relation,
we have to calculate
these correspondingly.
That means the number of outer blocks
times the number of pages
in the inner relation,
because we make a complete scan
of this inner relation.
Then for other blocks
it's the number of pages
of the outer relation,
divided by the block size available for R.
So, for example,
if you assign 100 pages to R
in main memory,
and the page number of R
is over 1,000
we will need 10 iterations of S.
That means, the number of the blocks
will be ten,
the size of the other blocks
will be 100,
that multiplies up to 1,000 pages an hour.
And for these ten times,
we fill some part,
100 pages actually into
the main memory block.
We will have to make a complete scan
of the inner relation.
That means we have to count
that many pages there are
in the inner relation.
Now, that's the number of IOs.
We have, of course, abstracted away
from real costs.
Real costs also involve CPU costs,
but that might be completely dominated
by hard drive costs,
particular you mightn't believe this,
that you actually do the CPU computations
while data is being fetched from the disk,
but the other big important thing
you have to keep in mind
is the number of seeks involved.
The number of times you have to place
or read/write it in the hard drive
to a different position,
just be able to again
to do a sequential scan.
So, how many sequential scans
do we have there?
Conceptually, we have about two--
Actually we've got exactly
two times the number of scans
we do of the inner relation.
That means two times the number
of all the blocks.
Why is that?
Well, every time you have
to read an outer block
you have to move
to the right position in R,
read that piece of R into main memory
and then move to the beginning of S
and make a sequential scan
of all of S.
And again,
we jump to the next position in R
to read one big outer block,
then we jump again to the beginning of S
and read S entirely.
That means, two times
the number of outer blocks
that's the number of seeks.
So, we could calculate the overall cost
of accessing the hard drive,
which might be quite accurate
as an estimation of the overall cost
of the join, as the cost of the seeks
plus the cost for the transfers.
The cost of the transfers, IOs,
is the cost that is given
by the formula here on this slide.
Now, how do you minimize that cost?
You do this by assigning as many
main memory pages
as possible to the outer relation,
all but one of those input pages.
That way, you minimize
the number of iterations
you have to do over S.
You minimize the number of outer blocks
needed scanned.
And that way you minimize the number
of iterations of S.
It's worth noting
that this analysis changes
if, you have to assume that S
in a join edition
is expensive enough that the CPU
cannot always keep up
with the sequential reads in that case.
You might actually partition
the data differently
for example, assigning equally
many memory buffers to R and S.
One further comment also
is that you would like to make
the outer relation the smaller relation.
That yet is another strategy to minimize
the number of iterations used overall.
That means R would by a smaller relation.
Now let's look at another
important join operation,
in database systems,
the so-called grace hash-join.
This is actually a sophisticated technique
that is more complicated
than what you might assume.
It's not simply a join operation
that consists of looping our old tuples
of one relation and then making a lookup
in a hash index for the other relation.
It works as follows:
It consists conceptually
of three phases.
In the first phase, we take one
of the relations,
let's call it R,
and scan it completely.
And as we make the scan,
we create an in-memory hash table
of that relation on the join condition,
or on the columns that we will join on.
As we fill up the buffers
for the packets of the hash table,
we will have to write it out to disk.
And you create as many partitions
as there are buffer pages available
for hash buckets in the hash structure.
So, I'll make a complete scan
of the first relation,
and build a hash table on disk
for that relation.
Then I'll do the same thing independently
for the second relation,
using the same hash function
on the join column of the other relation.
This, of course, assumes that you
actually do an equal join,
that means we compare by equality
of two columns of the two relations.
It would not work, for example,
for an unequal join,
where we test, for example,
for less than.
For such a join condition,
we would really have to resort
to the block-nested loop join.
But for an equal join,
this works.
So, we use one hash function
to hash the two relations
into two hash tables
that we then write out to disk.
So, we will have, let's say,
B main memory buffers,
we will assign one page for reading
in the input, step by step,
we will have B minus 1,
all the other pages available
for hash buckets.
So, we'll have a hash function that hashes
the tuples into B minus 1 buckets.
Whenever one of these
bucket pages fills up,
we write it out and you produce
B minus 1 partitions on disk.
So, we're reading the relations
and we're writing them out
again back to disk.
That's the first two phases,
so to say,
it's used for both relations.
And then we're going to start
reading in again the two relations,
partition by partition,
it means we read in the first partition
of the first relation
and the second relation,
then the second partition
of the first relation
and the second relation etc.
And as we do this,
so to say, in parallel
read the corresponding partitions
of the two relations
we take one relation's partition,
and we hash it into main memory
using a different hash function.
Of course, if you use
the same hash functions,
we would map that partition
all to the same bucket,
which is, of course, useless.
But now we're going to use
so to say, a different hash function
to create a higher resolution hash table
in memory.
How do we do this?
Well, we're going to use essentially
all the available main memory
for this hash table.
Let's say, all but one page.
And that remaining page
we will then use
to make a scan of the second relation's
partition, the corresponding partition.
And as we scan over the second relation
for the corresponding partition,
we compare the tuples we see
with the hash table.
That means we do an in-memory hash lookup
to find the matching tuples.
That way we actually pass
the join condition.
Once we have completely done this
and have produced the tuples
we wanted to produce,
we're going to take the second partition.
That means, for the first relation,
we make a scan of the second partition,
we build an in-memory hash table
using B minus 1 buckets
for that first relation
and then we make a scan
of the second partition
of the second relation
and compare the tuples
with the corresponding hash table
that has been produced
for the first relation.
And we do the same thing
for the third partition
and the fourth partition etc.
until you've exhausted the relations.
So that's how we do this.
So, there are actually several phases
and there's two different ways
we use hashing to produce
our join results.
The analysis of the hash-join
is a bit more complicated
but one important thing has to be seen.
We will use essentially B,
B minus 1, to be exact.
Different main memory buffers
are for pages for creating a hash table.
That means, that way we can
split up the relations
into B minus 1 parts,
hopefully of equal size
if the hash function is good.
Let's assume that.
And then the second phase,
you're going to have
to fit the smaller relations,
let's assume you do this
for the smaller relations.
Partition entirely into main memory.
That means we have
to have enough main memory
then you can do the hash table for
that partition of the smaller relation.
And then you scan
the corresponding partition
of the other relation to compare.
But this means that the size
of the smaller relation
has to be upper-bounded
by, essentially, B squared.
We take the relation,
we split it into about B
equally-sized parts,
and each of these parts has to fit
down to the hash table
into main memory.
Again, into these B pages.
Let's assume that the hash table
doesn't take more space
than actually, just simply
the relation partition here.
It means that the relations
are bounded by B squared,
or in other words,
that B has to be at least the square root
of the smaller relation's size.
So, if that is not true,
that means we have
less main memory than that,
we, in practice, cannot use
the hash-join.
There are some refinements
that work different
and again allows to work
with larger data.
There's all kinds of tricks
and refinements,
but ultimately this is
not a big constraint,
because given the gigabytes of RAM
that we now have,
squaring that is actually
quite large data.
So, if you think about the cost of this,
the cost is basically
in this partitioning phase
two times complete scans
of both relations,
and in this matching phase,
we are reading the partitions in,
and that's again just the cost
of reading both partitions in.
That means, overall, the cost
in terms of IOs, pages read and written,
is just three times the size
of the two relations.
If you think about the seeks,
it's more difficult to analyze,
because it depends on how
we write out the buckets.
The seeks can be considerable.
But, overall, this cost is really linear
in terms of transfers.
That's at least true if you don't have
large sets of tuples
that all agree on this jointly.
Because then, of course,
in the worst case,
we have to produce
a contracting-sized output.
And, of course,
that's not being dominated
by this linearly sized upper bound
on the transfers.
In summary, we've talked about two joins.
There's others like the sort-merge join
that I don't want to talk about now,
but talk about the block-nested loop join
and the hash-join,
they're both quite nice examples
of outer-core algorithms
where locality concerns
come into play.
In both cases, there is a lot
to be thought about
in terms of how to optimize
sequential access.
Both algorithms do a lot about this.
You probably don't want to call
the kind of buffering to caching,
because in a sense
they have complete control
over what data is put into main memory,
and it's not just opportunistically reused
as you would do in caching usually.
However, the second algorithm,
the hash-join,
also makes important use
of partitioning strategies
to kind of divide and conquer
to make the problems simpler.
You can do the hash-join,
partition by partition,
the final phase,
completely without having to look
at the other partitions.
So, really have achieved these kind of
embarrassing data parallelism
that we have mentioned.