In this lecture, I will show you how
we can form
a high quality thin film
on a substrate.
You may remember the case study of
the bimorph thermal actuator beam
where we deposited a 500 Nanometer
thick layer of chromium
on a SiO2 silicon wafer.
Such thin films in metals
are deposited by so-called
physical vapor deposition
or PVD.
In this lecture, you will learn
the basics of vacuum evaporation.
I will start by showing
the physical principle,
then show how the equipment
looks like, and finally
present some examples.
Don't confuse thermal evaporation
with spattering,
which is anther PVD method
and that will be shown
in the subsequent lessons
part two.
So in this first part,
let's have a look
at thermal evaporation,
also called vacuum evaporation.
I will introduce the topic
and show how the vapor is created.
So how do we get from the source
of metal to a well controlled
thin film on the wafer
like shown here in grey.
This is done by so called
evaporation.
Let's take gold as an example.
Evaporation occurs when the atoms
of the evaporant
achieves sufficient energy
to overcome the solid
and liquid binding forces
and enter the gas phase.
By drawing here.
This is physically achieved
by heating the material,
but just heating is not enough
for our purpose
even at very high
as you will see.
In this process, we have to consider
three distinct phases as follows.
First of all, how is the vapor
created?
Second, how the vapor flux
is directed towards the substrate?
And third, how the material
condensates on the substrate
to form a thin film.
So let's look at these steps
one by one in detail now.
As said, we will set gold
as an example material
but everything applies
to other materials as well,
just with different parameters
and specificities.
The transformation of a material
from condensed phase,
either solid or liquid into vapor
is described
by the Hertz-Knudsen equation.
In fact, it was found
experimentally that the vapor flux e
is proportional to difference
between Pv and P.
Where Pv is still at equilibrium,
vapor pressure of the evaporant
at temperature t,
and P is the reactor pressure.
It further depends on a series
of parameters
that are all listed here below.
Another convenient way to quantify
the deposition parameters
is to use the evaporation mass flux
in gamma,
which is the vapor flux
multiplied by the molar mass
divided by the Avogadro number.
It was found that the evaporation
rate does not increase further
by supplying more heat unless
the equilibrium vapor pressure
is also increased by this action.
Thus, there is a maximum
evaporation rate set by Pv
and can only be achieved in a vacuum
where P approaches 0.
For highest vapor's flux,
one therefore operates
the evaporation in a vacuum chamber
and by heating up
the material in the Crucible.
Another advantage to operate
in a vacuum is to avoid
any contamination of the evaporant
with residual gases.
Please note that according
to the formula,
heating up should actually
decrease the flux
because T is in the denominator
but this is compensated
by the fact that Pv
also increases with T.
There are various ways to hit up
the materials to evaporate.
One simple way to wrap
some evaporant material
around a tungsten wire
like shown here
but which has a limited source
lifetime.
Therefore, one typically places
the evaporant material
in a so-called crucible or boat,
which is made of  a robust material
that resist very high temperature,
meaning that
it is not evaporating itself.
Heating can be achieved
by passing a current
either around the bolt
or by directly passing a current
through the crucible that warms up
and evaporates anti-metal.
This technique is simple,
but has the drawback
that there's a possible risk of
alloy formation and contamination
if we heat the entire container.
Therefore another way
has  been developed which is based
on the use of an electron beam
to create the current
that heats up the evaporant.
So assuming here is
an electron emitter,
with a corresponding anode
that accelerates the electrons,
now the electrons are...
have a trajectory
that can be controlled
by a magnetic field so that the heat
the metallic target
enclose the current look.
So this induces the heat that melts
the metal in the crucible.
By changing magnetic field,
one can scan the electron beam
to uniformize the heat generation
on this molten metal.
On the photograph you see nicely,
and the  electron beam
coming from the left and heating
the molten metal here,
in this, the crucible.
The size of this crucible
is in the order of four centimeters.
The library of materials that can
be evaporated
is quite extensive and includes
not only refectory metals
but also dielectric
and organic material.
See the accompanying documents
for an overview
of operation material and their
corresponding specific parameters.
On the left, you can see a crucible
with the electron's source.
If we use it in our
cleaning room operator,
the typical size of the crucible
here, shown here
is about 40 millimeter and may
depend on the equipment parameters.
In the center you can see
three optical images
showing different materials
being heated with the electron beam.
This images has been taken
from outside the vacuum chambers
through a glass window.
It is worthwhile mentioning that
each material
has a very different structure
in the crucible.
For instance, SiO2 is forms
of beads shown here
with gold and silver,
are completely molten
under the e-beam current.
This photo shows for instance
how gold looks like
as evaporant material when it
is placed in the crucible
before it is heated and molten.
Atoms leaving the evaporant's source
into the vacuum
follow straight line paths
until  they collide
with other guards molecules
or strike the substrate
or the wall of chamber,
condense there,
and form a solid thin film.
In Kinetic theory, one can define
a distance that an object travels
between collisions with other
moving objects.
This leads a mean free path,
expression of lambda
that is shown here, which primarily
depends on the gas viscosity
to molar mass,
and last but not least,
on the reactor pressure.
So if we have less collisions,
that means the deposit
is more directional.
This is one of the primarily
characteristic
of the vacuum evaporation
and has some consequences
for a particular case
as you will see.
One of them is that there's
a certain risk of shadow formation.
This table will give an overview
of various mean free path values
as a function of chamber pressure.
At atmospheric pressure, we have
very short mean free path,
and so the molecules
are bouncing into each other
and the average, every
65 Nanometer of travel
if you go to low vacuum,
or medium vacuum and high vacuum
for example, we can already gain
mean free path of several meters.
So our chamber that we built
is typically a half meter,
one meter, in size.
So an atom or molecule
leaving the evaporant's source,
will not have any collision before
it hits the substrate surface.
That means this is very directional
flux from the source
to the substrate.
In contrast as you will see later,
spattering is performed
at higher pressure and involves
more collisions  of target molecules
and ions before deposition.
This leads a very different
film morphology.
For instance,
much less shadowing,
which favors smooth film formation.
Let's now consider how we can derive
the thickness of the film,
deposited from an evaporation
source.
Consider a small sphere dS1
that evaporates material
in all direction at the given rate
as shown here.
You call such an evaporation source,
a point source.
In this case, the material
passing through a solid angle
the omega, in any direction
per unit time is given by
this equation.
In reality, the evaporation comes
from a plane source
with the area dS1, and the material
is evaporated from one side
with a certain rate.
In this case, dm can be written as
the following.
In the case, the material flux
arrives at a small tS2 on a surface
that is inclined by an angle theta
with respect to the normal
to the direction of the vector
stream as shown here,
we can write the equations
as follows.
And we can rewrite the two equations
for the point source
and the planar source
as follows.
So how can we now get
to the thickness of the film,
let's assume that the material
has a density row D,
in grams per cubic centimeter
and the film thickness per unit time
is T in centimeter per second.
Then the volume of the deposit
on these two
must be T times TS2,
and we can rewrite dm as follows.
Then our two formula for the
planar source and the point source
can be rewritten finally
as shown here in green.
For high throughput integrated
circuit and MEMS processing,
we need to be able to code
large numbers of wafers,
each requiring a uniform
film thickness.
In this case, we use
a planetary system  that consists
of rotating spherical sections.
The principle behind
is shown here.
The receiving service is spherical,
having a radius r0
that includes also
the planar source.
We can already state that
the angle T
equals, T angle theta
and we can write
cosine C equals cosine theta
is given by r over 2r0.
Taking what we did use
in the previous slide,
we can rewrite now the thickness
like follows.
So the thickness is independent
from the radius r.
That means that deposition rate
is the same for each point
on the spherical surface.
Thereby, a uniform film thickness
can be obtained also
for a large number of wafers.
In a real evaporator system,
the wafers are arranged therefore
in a spherical holder
called planetary,
as you will see in the next section
of this chapter in more details.