Evaporation is performed in the
vacuum chamber.
The evaporant is heated in a
crucible at the bottom of the
chamber and the vapour flux
condensates on the wafer surface
placed in the upper part of
the chamber.
A large source substrate distance
of roughly 1 meter, enables
directional deposition that is
important for lift-off precesses.
Different standard evaporants are
permanently loaded in various
crucibles inside the evaporation
chamber.
The material to evaporate is
selected by rotating the crucibles
at the bottom of the chamber.
If an additional material is
required, a crucible filled with the
material to be evaporated can be
placed in an empty pocket.
In this specific case we
used chromium.
A shutter is used to control the
deposition. When the shutter is
covering the evaporation source
wafer flux can reach the substrate.
To start the deposition the shutter
is moved on the side and the flux
can reach the substrate.
Such a mechanical shutter is much
better to control the on off state
of deposition, compared to switching
on or off the evaporation itself.
This sequence shows some typical
substrate before evaporation.
For standard micro nano
fabrication, we typically use
silicon or glass substrates.
Here are shown a couple of silicon
wafers that are either bare silicon
in grey, or silicon with dielectric
coating, silicon nitride in this
specific case, which gives the
nice blue colour.
The wafers are first loaded upside
down into the sample holder
which has an opening at the bottom
which itself is then loaded into
the evaporator chamber.
The chamber is closed and pumped
down to reach a vacuum of about
10 to the minus 7 torr.
The pumping is the longest step
in the evaporation process.
It takes a few minutes to several
tens of minutes depending on the
required level of vacuum.
This leaves some time for the
scientists to discuss with students
and technicians.
The evaporant is then heated
in this case with an electron beam.
Depending on the material
the electron beam movement varies.
For chromium for example
which is not a very good
thermal conductor
the beam sweep is rather large.
Here the sweep speed is reduced
compared to the one used in
a real process
for the purpose of this video.
When using gold on the other hand
the sweep area is smaller as it is
an excellent thermal conductor.
Finally this last example shows
titanium in the crucible under the
bombardment of the electron beam.
The deposition time depends on the
rate and required thickness
Typical time for 30 nano meter gold
is on the order of 1 to 1.5 minutes.
Once the desired film thickness
is reached, the shutter is closed
and the e-beam power is ramped down.
After a cooling period of about 20
minutes, the chamber is vented
opened and the wafers are unloaded.
Note that here we see the back side
of the wafers and not the
coated sides.
After removing the wafers from the
holder and turning them around
we can see here the wafers
after deposition.
Gold in yellow and chromium in grey.
The blue ring of the underlying
silicon nitride layer at the wafer
edge stems from the shadow of the
wafer holder.