Now let's have a look in detail
how the film forms on the surface.
As mentioned before, the long
mean free path
allows for very directional flux
of evaporant.
This has an effect for surfaces
that are not perfectly flat
as often encountered in MEMS
and microfabrication
with 3D surface features.
The left image shows a situation
for a type of surface structures
in grey ,
that has to be coated
by the thin film in green
with the source coming from
the bottom.
Now, by simple geometrical
consideration,
one can already see that
on the flat part,
that is facing the source, we
obtain the target of thickness t1,
whereas on the sloped part
of the structure,
we have a thickness of only about
one third of the target thickness
in the case of an angle
of 70 degrees like shown here.
This can be calculated simply by
a geometrical considerations.
Another important cases of x,
position of the wafer
which we always have in this sought
of arrangement,
is that if we have surface features
we can create
a shadow effect because
of the directionality of the beam.
which can not deposit
on the lee side of this structure.
Consequently, there is a much
thicker film deposited
on the slope, facing the source,
than on the slopes
that are under an angle
to the source
or actually invisible
to the source.
To overcome this important drawback,
modern evaporator tools
are equipped with rotating
planetary systems as shown here
which repositions the wafers
during the evaporation
and to cancel the four
mentioned effects.
Thus, every wafer
in the planetary system
receives the exact same amount
of material under various angles
which yields a well controlled
film thickness
across a wafer's surface,
and from wafer to wafer in a batch.
In addition to the basic
configuration
of a thermal evaporator,
there are some other features
that have been incorporated
for better control and monitoring.
One of them is the
mechanical shutter shown here
that blocks the flux between
the crucible
and the wafers and allows
for very precise timing
of the deposition.
It's much more precise than
switching on and off the heat source
Another important feature
is the thin film monitor,
typically a quartz crystal
microbalance that measures
the added mass which can then
be used to reduce
the thickness that has been added on
each of the wafer.
We can furthermore control
the temperature of the substrate
either by cooling or heating
which has an important influence
on the film morphology
as the thin film gross.
Further, we can always control
the pressure in the chamber
and also inlet some specific gases
for reactive evaporation.
All these features have an influence
on the stress of the thin-film
as it grows on the surface
and can be optimized
if one knows how they influence
the growth mechanism.
Here on this photograph,
you can see the inside
of one of our clean room
thermal evaporators.
On the bottom you can see
the crucible
with the mechanic shutter,
and on top,
you can see the wafer holder system
that holds a couple of wafers
for thin film coating.
And here you can see a close up
photograph the crucible area
with the mechanical shutters.
More details of these
equipment aspects
will be shown later
in a dedicated video
taken in our clean room.
So now that we have seen
the basic principles
and equipment aspects
of thermal evaporation,
let's have a look at
some characteristics examples.
I want to show you in particular
the so called lift off technique
and then stencil lithography.
They both rely and benefit
from the long mean free path
and shadowing effect
that we can obtain in thermal PVD.
Let's have a look at the lift off
which is a particular example
where thermal of evaporation PVD
is very useful.
Lift off is done typically
on a substrate like shown here,
like a silicon wafer
that has been coated
with a layer of photoresist
and pattern by lithography,
it is that photoresist layer
that has an opening
by lithography and development
and now we come
with the source that is far a way,
that emits chromium
as material in a vacuum chamber,
which deposits now
all over the surface
and forms a film which has more
or less this shape
But this is chrome.
You notice now that the photoresist
was designed to have
a certain sloped angle
which prevents
that the direction of flux
of materials creates a breech
from the part of the film
that is on the photoresist
and part that is directly
on the substrate.
Now the extra lift of this then,
the stripping of the photoresist,
which is a liquid, a solvent,
that can penetrate
through the openings and start
to remove the photoresist
from this part and removes
everything
that is also on top of it.
And the same on this side.
Which leaves us at the end...
the chrome pattern that we want
and this chrome pattern
now has been made
simply by one lithography
and deposition
without the need for etching.
Some materials are indeed
very difficult to etch
so the lift off is a very
convenient way
to create micro and nano patterns
by this technique.
Here you can a live demonstration of
a lift-off step in our clean room.
A glass wafer has previously
been patterned with a photoresist
and then coated by PVD evaporation
with a thin film of chrome.
When placing wafer in a solvent,
for example, Acetone,
that photoresist dissolves
after some time
and also removes the metal layer
on top of it.
This lift off process takes
a few seconds
depending on the materials involved
and the dimensions.
It helps to mechanically
move the wafer in the bath.
Also ultrasound can be applied
in some cases .
In this step, the appearance
of  the pattern metal structures
become visible.
At the end, the glass substrate
is rinsed with the solvent
to remove remaining residues
on the surface,
then rinsed in the high water
and finally dry it for further use.
The second example that benefits
from the long mean free path
and the shadow effect
in PVD in Stencil Lithography
which is shown here
where a very thin membrane
with apertures is approached
close to then surface to be coated
and then when we get
material evaporated
with a very directional flux,
there is the deposition
of the material on the stencil
but also through the apertures
on the substrate
like shown here.
The third step would then be
remove the stencils
simply mechanically
and the surface features
are create without any further heat
or chemical processes
which makes this technique
very suitable for partnering
fragile  substrate.
In the animation, you can see now
how the, material is deposited
through the stencil
on the surface
leaving their features
and the second step here
also shows that this stencil
technique can be used
for local etching.
Here you see photos
of our clean room equipment
from thermal evaporation.
One the left side is shown
the front panel with a loading port
and the control panel.
On the right photo you see
how the equipment looks
from the back side
with all the connections
for pumps, heat sources,
monitors, et cetera.
A sophisticated equipment like this
has many features
as yo can see here, an e-beam source
with the pockets
for various materials,
resistive heating,
then here is your list
of possible materials
that can be evaporated
in faction equipment, it can hold
the four and six inch wafers.
It has a very large distance between
the source and the substrate,
more than one meter
and you remember this is important
for the directionality and shadow,
and which is therefore
very good for lift off,
it can deposit from
room temperatures to 200 degrees,
and it has a very strong pump
to reach a vacuum
in the order 10 to -6,
10 to -7 Torr.
And it has  the before
mentioned quartz,
crystal deposition rate monitor.
This concludes this part of the PVD
lesson on thermal evaporation.
You have seen that it is the first
and simple technique
to call the wafer with
a thin material film.
There is no surface damage,
it is done in a vacuum
which yields higher purity films.
No atoms from the atmosphere
are integrated into the film.
Limitations come from the shadowing
poor step coverage
of high aspect ratio status,
non uniformity over large areas
and a difficult to evaporate
compounds
because of their decomposition
or face change at high temperature.
So let's now have a look
in the clean room
how such an equipment
is operated in details.
In the next lesson, I will explain
to you how spattering can be used
to form a thin-material frames.