In this lesson I will introduce
the second PVD technique
that is called sputtering,
and which allows for a whole
variety of thin film
materials to be deposited.
In fact many more than
thermal evaporation.
I will first show some basic
principal how plasma is created
for our purposes show
the different plasma zones
in the sputter chamber, and how to
optimize it for efficient sputtering
and also introduce the Paschen law.
The goal of the sputter process
is to remove physical material
from the target and deliver
it to the substrate a wafer.
This is done by ion
bombardment in the plasma.
Ions that hit the target
with sufficient energy
eject atoms from the target.
These atoms are then deposited
as a thin film on the wafer
placed adjacent to the target.
So how is this done exactly?
Let's have a look.
First the air is pumped out of
the chamber to create a vacuum.
Shown here, this is the chamber
with the vacuum pump
that evacuates this are from air.
That chamber is then filled with Argon,
an inert gas until the pressure reaches
values in the order of a couple
of hundreds of milliliter.
A plasma is then created
by applying the high voltage
of about 1500V between
two electrodes, shown here.
The positive Argon ions in blue
are accelerated towards the cathode
which is the negatively
charged electrode
and hits the target here,
so the target, in this case
we choose Gold as a material
and here's the wafer on which
we want to deposit the gold.
The target is in fact made
of the material that we want
to deposit, and it's mounted
directly onto the cathode.
With the impact energy, atoms are
ejected from the target,
here in yellow
travel through the plasma,
and finally deposit on the wafer
as a thin film.
Sputtering allows all kinds of
materials including metals, compounds
as well as refractory materials.
The deposited thin film has
a generally good adhesion
and excellent step coverage.
We will come to these
details later in this lecture.
Let's have a short look what
plasma is and how it
works for out purpose here.
Plasma is defined as
partially ionized gas
that is neutral,
and thus has the same
number of ions and electrons.
It is commonly also referred to
as the fourth state of matter.
By the way, plasma is also
used for dry etching processes
that my colleague Martin Gijs will
cover in detail in his
corresponding lesson.
The simplest form of plasma
for out purposes, the DC plasma
it is created as follows.
First, the chamber is pumped down
and filled with Argon gas to reach
at the position, pressure in
the order of 10 to 100 mTorr.
Shown here, some Argon
atoms in the chamber.
Second, a DC voltage can be
applied between these two electrodes
shown here.
With the terminal resistance,
and here the potential that
can be applied to
the cathode and the anode.
At low voltages, the only measurable
current comes from so called
"background ionization".
Which is always present,
but often negligible.
The region of this background
ionization comes, for example
from a photon that hits
one of the Argon atoms
and ionizes it.
The result of this ionization
is that we get an electron
and an Argon ion.
This current is very low, and
the voltage on the electrodes
is about the same as
the voltage of the source
as there's nearly no
voltage drop over Rs.
If you increase the voltage,
the current first remains constant
since the voltage does not effect
the background ionization.
We can draw here a typical curve
how this current increases if you
increase the potential
between the electrodes.
The slight increase,
but not very drastic
because it's only based
on the available ions
due to the background ionization.
When the voltage is further
increased over 600V
approaching 1kV, depending
on the gas and the pressure
electrons and ions resulting
from the background ionization
gain enough energy
to ionize other atoms.
So this electron, for instance,
can ionize  this Argon atom
which would release another atom,
and be able to release another
Argon ion.
As a result the current increases
exponentially with the voltage.
So, now we're increasing
the current drastically
for the given voltage.
The regime described here is called
"Dark discharge" as
no light is generated.
It is not used for micro
fabrication applications
as plasma in this regime
is not energetic nor stable.
When the electric field
between the two electrodes
is further increased,
breakdown of the gas occurs.
The medium becomes ionized,
and an avalanche of inelastic
collisions between
electrons and ions appear.
So now, even argon atoms
that have not been ionized
by the background radiation,
can be ionized by the strong
electric field between the two,
cathode and anode.
So, one can create here electrons,
and here Argon ions
with all available Argon
atoms in the chamber.
And this is creating an avalanche
effect, because they can then
ionize other Argon
atoms that are available.
That means we suddenly
have a very strong current
that can be installed between
the cathode and the anode.
So, this is also shown here
in the curve, where we now
get a very strong current, up to
a couple of hundred milliamperes
but with the drop in the voltage.
Indeed, as the current increases
the voltage drop in the source
resistance becomes very important.
When Argon ions
collide on the cathode
secondary electrons
are ejected and sustain the plasma.
Without these electrons,
the plasma would rapidly vanish.
Finally, the plasma
reaches a steady state
and the loss and gain
of electrons is equal.
In this regime electrons have
enough energy to excite atoms
to an energy level where they emit
light when they are relaxed to
a lower energy level.
The plasma is luminous, and this
regime is called "Glow discharge".
This regime plasma is
stable and energetic enough
to be used in micro
fabrication technology
ideal for sputtering or for etching.
Typically to achieve this regime,
a voltage of about 1.5kV
is applied between
electrodes separated by 15cm
which results in the electric
field in the order of 100V/cm.
In this photograph we can see
the glow of plasma in one
of out sputter equipment.
We will see more of this later
when we go and see how
the equipment looks like.
Electrons and ions
don't have the same mass.
Electrons are lighter and
thus have a higher mobility
than an accelerated field gradient.
As a result, in a plasma
ions and electrons
don't move at the same
speed which creates
positively and negatively
charged areas.
Consequently,  electric field is
not constant along the plasma
and the electron energy varies
and creates the bright
and dark areas, as shown here
this light on the upper right side.
And we have the plasma chamber with
the cathode and the anode
in different zones in the plasma
due to the different mobility
of ions and electrons.
For more details about plasma
zones please have a look
at the accompanying documents.
Bright areas are called glow, and
dark areas are called dark space.
In the practical setup
for sputtering or etching
the distance between the two
electrodes is rather small.
In the order of 15cm,
as we have seen before.
This is the showing of the chamber,
the cathode and the anode
and the plasma in between.
As a result, the anode, which is
the positive electrode
is placed in the negative glow.
Therefore, the plasma column
can be simplified from here to here
and only the cathode dark
space the negative glow
and the anode dark space subsists.
Negative glow, cathode dark space,
and the anode dark space.
The potential changes very
abruptly close to the electrodes
in the plasma sheets and it's constant
in the glow region of the plasma.
As shown here.
There is a very steep slope
of the potential difference
of the cathode into
the plasma vacuum
then the plateau
where's the glow area
and here again a steep slope,
and the approach to the anode.
And these are the two plasma sheets.
The origin of this plasma sheet
has realized the computation
of the potential, along the plasma
is studied in more details in
the chapter about dry etching.
The required voltage to initiate
the break down of the gas
and create the plasma,
depends on three main parameters.
Which are the pressure,
the inter-electrode distance
and some gas properties.
This was firs observed by
Paschen who found out that
the breakdown voltage could be
plotted as a function of the product
between the pressure and
the inter-electrode distance.
It results in an asymmetric
parabola with a minimum
at a specific Pd product,
like shown here.
Here we have a typical curve,
for an example gas like Argon
every plot, the breakdown voltage,
and the plasma is breaking down
as the function of the product of
the pressure and the distance.
Paschen has found that this
curve in fact can be expressed
by an equation that is shown here
which gives the breakdown voltage
as a function of parameters like
for example, the pressure
and the electrode distance
as we already know, times
an empirical constant which is
observed experiment, and then
as a function of the secondary
electron emission
coefficient at the cathode
which plays an important role.
Here, three example gases
with the breakdown voltage
for a given value of
pressure and distance.
On the left side of the curve minimum,
one needs a higher voltage to reach
breakdown because there are less
molecules between the electrodes
available for the reaction.
As a result, when the gas, atom,
or a gas molecule is ionized
free electrons reach
the anode without colliding
with other gas molecules,
and they are lost.
For the breakdown of the gas
to occur, higher voltages
have to be applied in order
to increase the number
of free electrons and thus
the probability of collisions
with other molecules.
However, on the right side
of the minimum of this curve
we have another exact for
the breakdown voltage
to increase again.
Now, due to the large
number of gas molecules
between the electrodes, electron
molecule collisions become
more frequent and electrons
mean free path becomes shorter.
As a result, electrons don't
gain enough kinetic energy
to ionize other gas molecules
when colliding with them, unless
the higher potential is applied.
For reach gas, the minimum breakdown
voltage and the corresponding Pd
product is different.
These values depend on
the gas molecules, mean free path
the ionization potential and the speed
that the gas molecules can recapture
electrons after they
have been ionized.
Numerical values for the most
common gases are given
in the table here at the bottom,
right of the slide
but values for many other gases
can be found in the reference book.
For sputtering, it's not always
favorable to work at the minimum
breakdown voltage. Indeed,
it is more important
to work with lower pressures
and thus with a higher
breakdown voltage
in order to have energetic ions
striking the cathode and removing
atoms that can be deposited
as a thin film on the wafer.
For now we have seen some
basic physical principles
behind sputtering,
about how to create a plasma
and the Paschen's law.
For now, let's have a look
at the three main implementations
of sputter technique that is the DC,
RF, and Magnetron sputtering.