Now, we'll have a closer look how
in a clean room the various
sputter equipment are working.
I will show DC, RF,
and Magnetron sputtering.
DC sputtering is one configuration
of a sputtering system
shown here on
the right of the slide.
As an average sputtering system
the material target
is placed on the cathode
while substrate
is placed on the anode.
To create a plasma,
a high DC voltage
in the order of 1kV or more,
is applied between the electrodes.
This is why we call the system
"DC sputtering".
Usually the anode is grounded
and the negative voltage
is applied to the cathode.
Atoms that are ejected
from the target
under the bombardment of positive
ions condense on the wafer
there by forming the desired
thin film, like shown here.
The main advantage of this
system is it's relative simplicity.
However, it suffers from
two main limitations.
Firstly, the plasma is present in
the entire area between
the electrodes
which has the consequence that
this space is filled with electrons
which are repulsed by
the negative cathode
and collide on the substrate.
As a result, the substrate
substantially heats up
and efficient substrate
cooling is required.
Secondly, it is possible to deposit
only electrically conductive
materials with DC sputtering.
Indeed, even if electrically
insulating target is used
it will charge within
a few milliseconds
due to the accumulation of
positive Argon ions on the target.
As a result, the plasma would stop.
RF sputtering main difference from
DC sputtering is the way
how the plasma is created.
As in the case of DC sputtering,
the target is placed on the cathode
to attract the positive ions
and the substrate is
placed on the anode.
The difference is that, here
the plasma is created applying
a high frequency RF voltage
between the electrodes.
As you will see in details, using
AC voltage instead of DC voltage
has the main advantage
to avoid target charging
and that allows the position of
electrically insulating materials
such a dielectrics.
The key element to it, to this
system using an AC voltage
is a self-bias capacitor,
shown here.
To enable RF sputtering, the following
three conditions are required.
First, avoid target charging
as the cathode where
the target is placed
will alternate between
positive and negative voltages.
Both ions and electrons will
accumulate on the target
resulting in a null of
all charge of the target.
However, if the frequency is too low
accumulation of ions during
one single negative period
of the signal can be
sufficient to charge the target
if it's electrically insulating,
and to terminate the plasma.
Using frequencies higher than 50kHz
allows overcoming this throwback
as charging time becomes shorter
than a millisecond, which is
too short to charge the target.
Second, it is required to have
energetic ions
colliding on the target.
If you simply use the AC
voltage to accelerate ions
the energy they will gain
during on cycle is too low
to eject atoms from the target.
A solution to overcome this effect
is to use frequencies
larger than 5MHz
typically, 5.6MHz, and the capacitor
at the cathode for DC self-bias.
At such high frequencies,
ions cannot follow
the RF field anymore,
due to their mass.
On the other hand, electrons are
lighter and can follow the RF field.
They will then alternatively
strike the cathode and the anode.
However, because of
the capacitor at the cathode
they will accumulate there,
and the cathode will progressively
be negatively biased.
This negative DC voltage will
then accelerate positive ions
from the plasma, and enable
the sputtering process.
The third condition is to avoid
sputtering of other
surfaces than the target.
For example, avoid having ions
colliding somewhere else
than on the target.
To do so, the anode must be
larger than the cathode.
This result is studied in more
details in the chapter about
dry etching given by my colleague,
professor Martin Heiss.
The reason behind is that
having smaller cathode
allows having a larger
potential drop
and thus more bombardment,
because of current conservation.
In a typical RF sputter system,
the anode and the entire chamber
are therefor grounded
to satisfy this condition.
The main advantage of
RF sputtering over DC sputtering
is it's ability to overcome
charging problems
and thus to deposit electrically
insulating materials, such as
dielectrics.
In addition, electrons oscillating
in the RF field couple the energy
more efficiently to the plasma,
as a result, compered to
DC sputtering, higher
deposition rates are achieved
and lower power consumption
is required in the RF sputtering.
However, there's one main drawback
leading to the deposition of
the electrically
insulating materials.
These materials are
often poor heat conductors
which requires very efficient cooling
of the target during the sputtering.
In addition, as for the DC sputtering,
the plasma is not localized
and many electrons hit
the substrate and heat it up
thus substrate cooling
is also required.
To even further increase
the plasma efficiency
and thus the deposition rate
magnetron sputtering
systems are introduced.
The added feature
compared to the RF system
is the magnet plate behind
the cathode, shown here
which creates a magnetic field,
who's goal is to confide electrons
so they stay close to the cathode,
and induce a lot of collisions
with argon atoms to ionize them
and contribute to
the spotter process.
Let's have a closer
look how this works
and what it brings.
So, let's assume that we
have our target here
material that we want to sputter
any metal or dielectric
so we mount our target
on a setup that includes
a magnet
so, here we have a magnet,
which has magnetic
field lines showing like this
and that means we have to
close the magnetic field here
here, magnetic field, that are
going into the plasma
and here we have an electron
in this area it will swirl
and follow the field line
as schematically show here.
So why is that?
You all know that we have here
the south and north
pole of the magnet
and we have here, an electron
that has a certain velocity V
and within the magnetic field B,
that we have then a force
that is orthogonal
to the two vectors
of the velocity and
the magnetic field
so that, this electron has
no other choice than spiraling
around the magnetic field line,
and follow it, basically.
Due to Lawrence forces,
electrons follow a helical trajectory
while ion trajectory is not influenced
because of the higher mass.
So, having a magnet behind
the target allows to confide
electrons close to the target.
This improves ionization efficiency,
because of the larger amount
of collisions between
Argon atoms and electrons.
As a result, it is possible
to use lower voltages
and lower pressure, which allows
deposition of film
with higher purity.
In addition,
the plasma is localized.
This enables higher deposition rates
because of the larger amount of ions
impacting the target,
and also
decreases substrate heating,
as less electrons collide
on the wafer.
On the other hand, the system
becomes more complex
and the ware of the target
is non-uniformed.
Here on these two photographs
you can see two targets of
a magnetron sputtering tool.
The left image shows the target
after some short term usage
where we can start seeing how
the material is being eroded.
On the right photo,
we see a similar target
after extensive use where
a lot of the material
has actually been removed.
The pattern shows here
that the ion distribution
has the function of
the magnetic field
provided in the magnetron
sputtering tool.
For now we have seen how DC, RF
and magnetron
sputtering are working.
Let's have a closer look
how actually the ions
are interacting with
the target material
to be able to remove material
and deposit it on the substrate.