So in this lesson, we will now
have a closer look
at how ions interacting with
the target material
in order to remove the material
from the target,
and to sputter it on the substrate.
When a so called primary ion
collides with a target,
made of the material to deposit.
Several interactions may occur,
as illustrated in the figure on
the right side of the slide.
The interaction depends primarily on
the ion kinetic energy,
the type of ion,
and the target material.
Negatively charged electrons
in the cathode
will then neutralize the positive
ion, Argon in most cases.
When the energy is low, smaller
than 10 electron volt.
Ions hitting the cathode
may be reflected,
absorbed, or may migrate
on the surface.
During the inpinching, it can
induce some surface damage
such as point defect,
or topographical changes.
It may also induce some chemical
reactions on the surface.
Ions with high energy,
10 kilo-electron volts or more,
will penetrate deeply into
the target material
and form an implant or compound
electron here.
When ions are in the energy range
between 10eV and 10 keV,
they will eject atoms
from the target
like the ones shown here.
This is the action that
we want for sputtering.
By doing so, they will simultaneously
create secondary electrons,
and secondary ions.
Finding the ions interacting
with the target
can also result in the emission
of photons and x-rays.
95% of colliding ions transmit
energy as heat to the target,
therefore cooling is required.
And it is worth noting
that in sputtering,
the deposition of compounds
such as carbide, nitrite, and oxide
is indeed possible,
because mechanical energy is used
to eject atoms from the target.
This differs significantly from
the case of the thermal
or electron beam evaporation
where thermal energy is used to
vaporize the solid target material.
So once again, on the drawing
so you see here.
The target material in orange,
which is biased negatively.
And the wafer in grey,
that is biased,
positively on ground.
And now, a primary ion,
with a correct energy
will hit the target material,
will remove atoms from the target,
which then fly through the vacuum
and will land on the wafer and form
the thin film of
the target material.
Unlike for evaporation,
the amount of material ejected from
the target does not depend on
the vapor pressure,
but is given by the so called
ejection rate, W.
The ejection rate W depends on
parameters such as the sputtering yield,
the voltage between the electrodes,
the discharge current,
as well as the pressure
and the inter electrode distance.
From the equation on the left hand
here on the slide,
we see that the target  ejection rate
increases with the voltage,
but is inversely proportional
to the pressure
and the inter electrode distance d.
This can be explained as follows.
When increasing the voltage,
argon ions are accelerated
more rapidly
and strike the cathode with
more kinetic energy.
On the other hand,
when decreasing the pressure,
argon mean free path is increased.
And when decreasing
the inter electrode distance,
argon ions will collide
with less argon,
before striking the cathode.
As a consequent, argon ions
impact the cathode with
more kinetic energy.
Finally, the target ejection rate
also depends on
the sputtering yield, S.
Which is the ability of one ion
of a specific gas
to eject an atom from the target made
of the specific material.
Obviously, the sputtering yield
depends on the ion energy
which itself depends on
voltage, the pressure,
and the distance.
But it's also related to the type
of gas in the reactor,
and to the target material.
In general, heavier ions
usually have larger
sputtering yields
and harder target materials result
in lower sputtering yields.
A few typical sputtering yield
values for common materials
are shown in the table on
the right side here.
The different metals, with their
corresponding sputtering yield.
So here, the target is bombarded with
500 eV argon ions.
You can see for instance
that titanium sputtering yield
is significantly lower
than that of for example, gold.
Because titanium is much harder
than gold.
As explained previously,
only the target should be bombarded
by energetic ions.
To avoid sputtering off other
surfaces than the cathode,
the anode as well as
the entire chamber,
is grounded to increase, in fact,
the anode area.
Still, this would not be enough
to prevent sputtering
on the backside of the cathode.
Indeed,
when all the walls
of the chamber are grounded,
a plasma will still install between
the 2 electrodes as wanted.
But also between the walls and
the backside of the cathode
as shown here,
on the top left image.
In this case, energetic argon
plus ions,
shown here in blue,
will also sputter the backside
of the cathode
and deteriorate it.
To prevent sputtering of
the structural elements
of the cathode,
a grounded shield,
is placed at the distance
less than that of the plasma shield
as shown here on the lower
right illustration.
In this way, the space between
the shield
and the cathode is too small
to allow plasma formation
and the plasma is contained in front
of the target.
In order to create a plasma,
a certain amount of gas molecules
is required
between their electrodes.
Consequently,
The pressure at which the deposition
in a sputtering system occurs,
is higher than that used for thermal
or electron beam evaporation.
We use typically
10 to the minus one,
to 10 to the minus 3 tau
for sputtering, instead of 10
to the minus 6
to 10 to the minus 7 tau
for evaporation.
As a result, the mean free path
in sputtering
is only a few millimeters
compared to meters in evaporation.
Atoms ejected from the target will
therefore collide
with many gas particles, and ions,
before reaching the substrate.
You do the multiple collisions.
The atoms inpinch on the surface
with random incident angles.
Shown here,
with the yellow arrows
on this cartoon.
Thus the way atoms deposit
onto the substrate
and the film grow is different
from evaporation.
For instance, having random incident
angle allows
having better step coverage.
Compared to evaporation,
where a long
mean free path
produces a line of sight deposition
with a possible shadowing effect,
as you may remember from
the evaporation lesson.
Adding a reactive gas
in the chamber,
reactive sputtering is possible.
Atoms ejected from the target
react with the gas,
for instance oxygen, and forms
compounds such as oxides.
Another deposition technique
to deposit compounds
is called co-sputtering.
Finally, if needed,
the direction in a sputtering
deposition is possible
by using a collimated sputtering.
It's done by placing a grid
in between the electrodes
and thus filtering atoms with
high angles of incidence.
So on this micro graph,
taken by an electron microscope.
You can see an example
showing the
capability of sputtering
aluminum
on a double layer lift-off resist.
So you see here, 2 layers
of photo-resist
with an over hanging geometry
like a small mushroom
that has been coated by
sputtering aluminum.
And since the aluminum came
under various angles,
it was able to deposit also
underneath the mushroom.
If I'm drawing here again,
where we see the aluminum
on the mushroom structure.
The top, then also here,
we have again
aluminum that has been deposited.
Only just underneath
the over hanging structure,
there have been no, or non visible
deposition of aluminum because
the incoming angles
were for the aluminum.
Atoms could not reach
this shadow part.
So let's have a look at how
various parameters
influence the sputter film quality.
Increasing the voltage results
in more energetic ions
striking the cathode.
Consequently, more atoms and
more energetic atoms
are ejected from the target
which leads to higher
deposition rate,
and better film adhesion.
Indeed, more energetic atoms
have a longer penetrating depth
at the wafer surface, and also
allow cleaning the wafer surface
from remaining contaminants.
Adjusting the pressure,
and the inter electrode distance
is a question of trade off.
As explained previously,
Paschen's law
gives the breakdown voltage as
a function of the product
between the pressure and
inter electrode distance.
Thus, for a fixed voltage
changing either the pressure,
or the inter electrode distance
will alter the plasma stability.
In addition,
increasing the pressure or
the inter electrode distance
leads to more collisions
of the atoms on their travel
between the target
and the substrate.
As a result,
less atoms and less energetic atoms
will deposit on the substrate
which will lower the deposition rate
and also the film adhesion.
There's also risk
for contamination
of the deposited hin film
by argon atoms from the plasma
if the pressure is too high.
Too high pressure and large
inter electrode distance,
should thus be avoided.
Finally, the pressure also impacts
the morphology
of the deposited thin film.
If it is an amorphous, or
forms crystal.
This point will be traded in more details
in the lesson about film growth.
The substrate temperature is another
controlled parameter.
Increasing the substrate
temperature,
increases atom energy
on the surface
and thus improves the diffusion.
This leads to better
film uniformity
and adhesion, and lower
internal stresses.
The temperature also impacts
the crystal structure
as it will be explained in
the film growth chapter.
One of the main advantages
of sputtering
over thermal evaporation
is stability
to deposit almost any kind
of material
including metallic, and
non metallic elements,
alloys, ceramics, and polymers.
In addition,
Reactive and co-sputtering enables
the deposition of oxides
and chemical compounds
such as nitrites, and carbides,
among others as depicted in
this table here on the right side.
In addition to the wide choice
of material to deposit,
sputtering ensures a good adhesion
of the deposited thin film
because of the relatively high
kinetic energy
of the atoms when they inpinch
on the substrate.
Due to the non directional
nature of sputtering,
which means atoms arrive on
the substrate
with random (INAUDIBLE)
of the incident.
This deposition technique
enables good step coverage,
good uniformity over large areas,
and suppresses shadowing problems
typically of thermal evaporation.
Sputtering targets can be
relatively large
and thick, which allows
to deposit
more material than with evaporation.
Sputtering systems are compatible
with production processes
as large amount of material can be
uniformly deposited
over large areas.
In addition,
sputtering systems can be adapted
to (INAUDIBLE)
deposition to it.
Finally, surface cleaning and
activation is possible
with the process called
sputter etching.
Reversing the electrode's polarity
and creating a low energetic plasma
sill result in ions colliding on
the substrate.
As a result, these ions will remove
contamination layers
or particles on the surface,
break oxide and surface bonds
to activate the surface.
Dry cleaning process using a plasma
is less efficient than wet cleaning
but has no surface tension effects,
doesn't require any drying step,
and is performed directly
in the chamber
where the deposition
will take place.
In practice, a cleaning step
is very common before starting
the sputtering process.
Sputtering can be done
at room temperature,
but unless used with magnetron,
substrate heating is substantial
because of the atom's kinetic energy
and bombardment by secondary
electrons.
Chemical reaction between
the substrate
and the deposited layer can start.
In addition, surface damage
can also occur
because of the substrate
cooling system
the setup and material change
is more complex
than the thermal evaporation system.
And thus the sputtering equipment
is more expensive.
Finally, due to the high
deposition pressure,
it is difficult to have high
purity films.