After having seen
the basic principles
of sputtering and details
on the film growth,
let's now present a couple
of relevant examples
where sputtered films
are used in MEMs.
At the end of this lesson
I will also show some details
of the sputtering setup
and take you into the clean room
to see the real tools at work.
At first, application where
sputtering is advantageous
is the fabrication
of transparent
conductive oxide films
for photovoltaic solar cells (PV).
A photovoltaic solar cell
is a device which transforms light
into an electrical current.
In most common solar cells,
the absorbing material
is made of crystalline silicon
contacted with metallic electrodes.
Incoming photons are absorbed
in the crystalline silicon layer
and generate electron hold pairs.
These electron hold pairs
are then extracted
through the electrodes.
Although a simple cell
made of silicon directly contacted
with metallic electrodes could work,
its efficiency would be very low
because of ohmic losses
in the silicon metal junction
and because of
the surface recombination
of electron holds pair.
To improve the efficiency
of crystalline silicon solar cells,
amorphous silicon
or alpha silicon
and transparent conductive oxide
so-called TCO
are added in between
the active crystalline
silicon area
and the metallic electrodes,
in silver.
As shown here
in the right side of the slide.
In this specific example,
two different TCO are considered.
First,
the indium tin oxide
or ITO
is added
at the front side of the device
where the light comes in.
And the second
a zinc oxide aluminum
silicon dioxide alloy,
shown here,
is added at the rear
of the device.
The first call of the TCO
in the photovoltaic solar cells
is to decrease ohmic losses
between the electrode
and the absorbing medium.
However,
TCO also functions
as anti-reflection coatings
at the front of the solar cell,
as well as for infrared light
absorption management
at the rear of the cells.
In order to fabricate cells
with the highest
efficiency as possible,
TCO layers must have
low resistivity,
high transparency,
and a low refractive index.
To satisfy all these
three requirements
at the same time
it is not that straightforward
by using standard
thin film materials.
One way to succeed
to match all of these properties
is, for instance, to add SiO2
to zinc oxide aluminum TCO layer
On the right side of the slide,
we can see a TCO layer
made of zinc oxide aluminum SiO2
in between the silicon
absorbing medium
and the silver rear electrode.
Like shown here.
Silicon, the TCO
and the silver layer
This sputtered composite layer
allowed for tuning
the optoelectronic properties
and for improving the PV efficiency.
Let's see in the next slide
how this film is actually made.
To deposit a zinc oxide
aluminum SiO2 layer
cool sputtering
of zinc oxide aluminum
and SiO2
is performed.
As shown here,
two targets
are used within the same
vacuum deposition chamber.
Tuning the voltage
on each target
enables to change
the zinc oxide aluminum SiO2 ratio
into film.
Formed here on the substrate.
And thereby to adjust
the film microstructure
and refractive index.
The more SiO2 we add,
the less crystalline
becomes the material
and the lower
is the refractive index.
In this concrete example,
sputtering enables
the deposition of two compounds
at the same time
and thereby tuning
the final stoichiometry
of the deposited film.
Such a performance
is impossible to achieve
with thermal evaporation.
The fabricated films
exhibit high transparency
and low refractive index.
Three different coatings
are shown here.
First, on the left,
the zinc oxide aluminum film
without addition of SiO2.
And then with increasing
SiO2 concentration.
It shows that
the texture is changing
towards less grainy morphology.
The same time,
the solar cell efficiency
increases by 20%
in the infrared
when using
the zinc oxide aluminum SiO2
TCO layer
at the rear of the device.
Instead of a standard
zinc oxide aluminum layer.
For further details
let's have a look
at this cited paper.
Our second thin film
example of interest
is based on piezoelectric materials,
that are often deposited
by reactive sputtering.
Piezoelectric materials
are very important
and used in many MEMs devices
such as ultrasound transducers,
that means the devices
that converts a pressure wave
into an electrical signal.
Or mass sensors,
where the mass change induces
a resonance frequency shift.
And bulk acoustic wave filters.
For this latter application,
suspended
piezoelectric microstructures
are sandwiched between electrodes.
When an incoming electrical signal
which matches the mechanical
resonance frequency
of one of the microstructures
is applied to the input electrodes,
the device enters into
a mechanical resonance
and an electrical
signal is transmitted
to the output electrode.
Typically,
bulk acoustic wave filters
are made of aluminum nitrate;
because of the excellent
electroacoustic properties
of this material
and its chemical compatibility
with micro-fabrication processes.
The quality of the filter
is determined by
the piezoelectric
film crystal structure.
Reactive sputtering
with an aluminum target
in a nitrogen atmosphere
is used to deposit
the aluminum nitrate film.
As it is the only deposition method
which allows
for high film quality
below 500° C.
However,
the film crystal structure
is highly dependent
on the underlying seed layer.
Film growth structure and stresses
are explained in details
in the film growth lesson.
In the case of bulk
acoustic by-filters
this underlying seed layer
consists either of
the platinum bottom electrode.
Shown here.
Or of a silicon dioxide layer.
Indeed,
the platinum electrode is
patent and away for surface,
prior to the aluminum
nitrate deposition,
is thus made
of two different materials,
platinum and SiO2.
As you can see
here on the right,
the aluminum nitrate
deposited on top of platinum,
has very defined
crystalline structure,
compared to the aluminum nitrate
that grows on top of the SiO2
which is less uniform.
In addition,
the residual stress
of aluminum nitrate
grown on platinum seed layer
is also lower
in the order of 200 MPa,
tensile stress,
versus minus 700 MPa,
compressive stress,
respectively on the SiO2.
For the challenge here
is to optimize crystallinity
of the overall film
in order to acquire
the best piezoelectric
properties as possible.
Here is one further example
which illustrates how sputtering
enables the manufacturing of MEMs.
In this case,
we are depositing
a silicon thin film
by sputtering
and followed by
lithography and etching.
Many suspended
microstructures are made
of low-pressure chemical
vapor deposition (LPCVD)
polysilicon.
Because of the
well-characterized
mechanical properties of polysilicon
and because of the residual stress
in thin films deposited by LPCVD
can be tuned.
However,
the LPCVD process
requires temperatures
higher than 600° C.
And is thus not the most compatible.
Building the MEMs device
directly on top of a CMOS circuitry
to control a MEMs device, however,
would increase a device performance
as well as its functionality.
Indeed,
having signal amplification
close to the signal source
allows decrease in the noise,
and on-chip multiplexes
enables the dense integration
of a large number of devices.
We thus look for a low temperature,
silicon deposition technique,
and use sputtering
instead of CVD.
Tuning the pressure
and power of the sputtering process,
and performing a post-annealing
at 350° C,
allows depositing up to 2 μm thick
silicon films
with residual stresses
lower than 100 MPa.
In addition to be
the most compatible,
such a process can also be performed
on a polymeric
or organic sacrificial layer.
As a result,
suspended silicon structures
can be fabricated
on top of CMOS circuitry
using a dry relief process
in oxygen plasma
to remove the sacrificial layer.
This process is much simpler
than the usual SiO2
sacrificial layer using HF,
wet release,
and critical point drying process.
An example of a sputtered
silicon microstructure
suspended with 4 springs
next to its CMOS circuitry
is shown here.
The silicon plates,
shown here in the magnification,
is electrostatically actuated
and its deflection is quantified
measuring the change of capacitance
with a dedicated
on-chip CMOS amplifier.
Like, shown here.
And like it is nowadays integrated
in many state of the art
commercial MEMs.
Here is an example
of a cluster sputtering tool
from our green room.
A load-lock system.
Here.
Enables to load the way
first into the tool,
without venting
the deposition chambers themselves.
This way
pumping time is shorter
and there is
less contamination
of the deposition chambers
with gaseous atmospheric components.
A robotic arm,
located in the central chamber,
automatically moves
the way for the load-lock,
here,
into one
of the 4 deposition chambers.
Shown here.
Each chamber has
a different target of material,
which enables serial
deposition of multiple materials
without venting the sample
in between each deposition.
This is an advantage
when the deposited material
are very sensitive to native oxides,
for instance.
To conclude this chapter
about sputtering,
let's now have a look
how such a system
really works in reality.
So let's come together
in the clean room.