The sputtering system that
you see here is called
a cluster sputtering tool.
In this case with 4  of the
precision chambers
allowing you to pass wafers to
various sputtering chambers without
breaking the vacuum.
Per sputter process step, only one
wafer is used per chamber in this
particular equipment.
Wafers are loaded in the load lock
chamber of the system from behind
the wall on the right side
of the image.
Then a robotic arm located in the
centre of the tool transfers the
wafers from the load lock into one
of the 4 sputtering chambers.
The robotic arm enters into the
load lock, moves up to lift the
wafer from the chuck,  leaves the
load lock and distributes the wafer
in the desired sputtering chamber.
Let's now have a further look at the
inside of the tool and see how
the clean room engineer changes the
sputter target.
Remember the target is a plate
made of the material that we want to
sputter deposit on our substrate.
In that specific case, the target
which is changed, is used for
RF magnetron sputtering.
You can see the RF generator
the grey metallic box
and the magnet, the black cylinders.
The other 3 chambers are DC
magneton sputtering with only the
magnet and no RF generator.
The first step when changing the
target is to remove
the target shield.
This shield is used to avoid
sputtering of the structural elements
of the cathode and to improve
gas diffusion.
Then the target itself can be
removed.
The home made tool is used to remove
the target in order to allow
a single person to perform
this manipulation.
In this specific case, the target
is made of titania.
It is changed not because it is worn
out,  but because we need to  sput
another material in this
particular chamber.
We can also see that a copper grid
is used at the back of the target
to ensure a good electrical contact.
When a sputter target is worn out
it also needs to be changed.
This operation is shown here
which also shows nicely how a
sputter target in magnetron
sputtering looks after some use.
The wear, clearly is not uniform,
because of the magnetic field
which concentrates ions along
magnetic field lines so that they
optimise the sputter yield.
In comparison, here are shown new
sputter targets where the surface
is still uniform.
The two examples shown in the video
are aluminum oxide and silicon
dioxide new targets.
To mount a target in the tool
the operation steps shown in this video
sequence are performed in the exact
reverse order.