Welcome to this lesson
on other PVD techniques
that are of interest
for micro/nanofabrication.
I will first show the so-called
ion assisted methods,
which are combination of evaporation
and ion induced surface preparation.
Second,
I will introduce MBE
which is an important technique
to create crystalline thin films.
Third,
I will present PLD,
which is a favorite method
to deposit composite material
with complex stoichiometry
at high quality.
These methods are more complex
and expensive than previously shown
evaporation and sputtering
but they are very important
for advanced film
control and formation.
This lesson will conclude
with some supplementary methods
and the comparison
of the various PVD methods shown.
Ion assisted deposition
(IAD),
and ion beam assisted deposition
(IBAD),
are 2 techniques
combining material evaporation
and substrate sputtering with ions.
The differ in how the ions
are created.
In the case of IBAD,
ions are generated
using an ion source
or ion gun
as shown in the schematics
on the right side of the slide
So here you can see
the setup that we already introduced
in the evaporation.
Now, in addition
to the crucible
and the electron source
that evaporates the material
that is going to be deposited
on the substrate in the chamber.
We have, in addition, an ion source
or ion gun,
which emits ions
into the vacuum chamber
that heats the substrate
before or during the deposition.
In such we can clean the surface,
and add additional energy,
to enhance the control
of the film growth
on the wafer
during the deposition.
In the case of IAD,
a plasma is created
in the evaporation chamber
and ions are accelerated
by applying a negative bias voltage
on the substrate.
In both cases,
the high energy ion bombardment
of the substrate is used to clean
and activate the surface
prior to the deposition
and to improve the film quality
during the deposition.
By doing so,
thickness uniformity, as well as
film adhesion can be improved.
In fact,
energetic ions enable atoms
to diffuse on the surface
and also enables atoms to penetrate
into the surface.
By this mechanism,
film density and hardness
can be increased,
which is particularly useful
when depositing dielectric films.
As we know,
denser films have lower etch-rates
and higher dielectric constant.
Let's now have a look
to how a typical ion source
for IBAD works.
You can see on the right side
of the slide a schematic
of a source
used in one of the evaporator
in the EBF clean room.
The substrate is not shown,
it will be somewhere
on the top of the slide.
The source consists of two parts,
the hollow cathode
electrode source,
and the ion source itself.
Firstly,
argon gas enters the hollow cathode
and a high voltage is applied
between the keeper
and the hollow cathode,
creating a plasma
within the hollow cathode.
Shown here.
Once the plasma is stable
in the hollow cathode,
a bias voltage is applied
with a bias controller
to emit electrons
out of the hollow cathode.
Emitted electrons are deflected
towards the ion source
using a magnetic field.
Shown here.
In the ion source
electrons collide with gas atoms,
here we use argon or oxygen,
and ionize them.
Resulting ions are then repulsed
by the positive anode
and bombard the substrate.
Upwards. Which is not shown here.
Electrons emitted
from the hollow cathode
are also used to neutralize
the substrate,
which charges positively
with ion bombardment.
Ion beam assisted deposition
has 2 main advantages over
non-beam ion assisted deposition.
Both come from the fact
that no plasma is used
in the actual deposition process
in contrast to sputtering.
Firstly,
better film purity is achieved
as a higher vacuum can be used.
Thin films,
with improved internal stress
and microstructure control,
can be deposited
as substrate temperature
can be better controlled.
As there is no plasma
close to the substrate.
On the other hand,
non-ion beam deposition
also have some advantages
over the beam assisted deposition.
As evaporated atoms
travel through the plasma,
they will be scattered
and some of them will ionize.
As a result,
conformal coatings
and compound deposition
can be achieved.
For compound deposition,
an additional gas
is added to the chamber
and it will react with
evaporated atoms
that will have been ionized
in the plasma.
For instance,
dense and very hard
titanium nitrate coatings
are thereby possible.
Finally,
IAD and IBAD
can be combined
with sputtering deposition
as well as chemical
vapor deposition.
Let's have now a look at epitaxy
which is a method to create
crystalline material frames that
are not possible with evaporation
and sputtering processes.
Indeed,
evaporation and sputtering PVD
the deposited layers
either amorphous
or sometimes polycrystalline,
but never monocrystalline.
The crystal structure
of deposited thin films
will be studied in more detail
in the chapter about film growth.
Epitaxial deposition consists
in growing a single crystal film
on the crystalline substrate,
as shown in the top schematic
on the right side of the slide.
If the film is of the same material
as the substrate,
the process is called "homoepitaxy".
It is called "heteroepitaxy"
if the materials differ.
In order to have a successful growth
of the epitaxial layer,
several conditions
have to be satisfied.
In a thermal way,
the epitaxial layer
crystal structure is the same
as the substrate crystal structure.
In the case of homoepitaxy,
this is rather straightforward.
On the other hand,
in the case of heteroepitaxy,
things are more complex.
Indeed,
if there is a lattice mismatch
between the material
to grow and the substrate,
the single-crystal film thickness
will be limited or even zero.
In addition to
the crystal structure condition,
there is also a condition
on the energy
and diffusion time
atoms have when they
arrive on the substrate.
If they are too low
or too short, respectively
atoms will not be able
to go to the right location
in order to grow a single crystal.
There are several main applications
of epitaxy, such as the fabrication
of silicon membranes
on silicon substrate
with predetermined thicknesses
and doping levels.
And stacks of silicon layers
with sharp and large
doping level changes.
Such stacks can be used
in microprocessors,
high-performance logic circuits,
and as electrochemical [INAUDIBLE]
for MEMs fabrication.
More details are given`
about this last application
in the chapter
about wet-etching.
Another widely used application
of epitaxy is
silicon-on-insulator wafers
or SOI.
SOI wafers consist
of a thin surface
or device layer of silicon
an underlying layer
of insulating material
typically SiO2 or aluminum oxide
and a support silicon wafer
as shown in the bottom schematic
on the right side of the slide.
Such wafers can be used to fabricate
faster and more compact
transistor chips
in the thin epitaxial
device layer.
It can also be used
to fabricate mechanically
and electrically insulated layers
in MEMs devices
Two main types of epitaxy exists:
Chemical vapor deposition
and physical vapor deposition
In this chapter we will
focus on the latter one,
also called
"Molecular Beam Epitaxy",
or MBE.
Molecular beam epitaxy, or MBE,
is a PVD technique
very similar to resistive
heating evaporation,
but with significantly
technical differences.
Firstly, the crucible containing
the evaporant is placed in a cavity
with a very small aperture
in the millimeter-side range
called Knudsen cell
as you can see on the figure
on the right side of the slide.
Typically, graphite crucible
with tantalum foil,
resistive heatings are used here.
The use of Knudsen cell allows
to better control both
the temperature of the evaporant
and the flow of atoms
exiting the cell.
The flow of atoms is correctorized
by the Knudsen number,
which is defined
as the ratio of the atoms
mean free path
over the Knudsen cell
orifice diameter.
Shown here.
If the Knudsen number
is smaller than 0.01
the mean free path is comparable
to the orifice diameter.
This means that atom bounces against
the orifice sidewalls.
In such a case,
atoms exit the cell
in a continuous whisk of flow.
In the case of MBE,
the mean free path is
is in the range of
ten-to-the-sixth meters,
and the orifice diameter
in the range of 10 to the -3 meter.
As a result,
the Knudsen number
is much greater than 1
and atoms are passing through
the orifice one by one
in a single, straight track.
Secondly,
MBE requires an ultrahigh vacuum
of about 10 to the -11 Torr.
in contrast to a vacuum
of 10 to the -6, 10 to the -7
used in standard evaporation.
As a result,
atomic stream evaporated
from Knudsen cells
in MBE,
impinged to substrate surface
in a line of side manner,
and then diffused
to that thermodynamically
minimal crystallographic location.
Finally,
as shown in the schematic
on the right side of the slide
multiple Knudsen cells can be used
with the same MBE chamber,
which allows depositing compounds,
alloys, and even multiple
types of dopings.
In addition to the main shutter,
that covers all the cells,
each cell has its own shutter.
This way, stacks
of different material
with various different
doping levels can be deposited.
In order a single crystal film,
having molecular flow of atoms
impinging the substrate
is not sufficient.
As mentioned
in the introduction slide
about epitaxy,
once the atoms land on the surface
they need to move around
until they find an atomic side
to chemically bound to it.
To do so, atoms on the surface
must have enough energy and time
to reach the right
crystallographic location.
Several conditions have
then to be satisfied.
Firstly,
the substrate
has to be absolutely clean.
Secondly, the substrate is heated
from 400° C up to 800° C,
to increase the atoms energy.
And thirdly,
giving atoms enough time
to travel to their
energy minimum location
leads to very low deposition rates
in the range
of 0.1 to 2 ångström (Å) per second.
Which results in very long
deposition times.
Finally,
in the case of heteroepitaxy,
if the lattice from
the material to grow
is different from
that of the substrate
epitaxy might still be possible,
but the thickness of the thin
crystal film will be limited.
Indeed,
the film will strain
in order to match
the substrate lattice
and at some point
internal stresses will
become too important
and dislocations will appear.
Such a slow deposition rate
and fast acting shutters
to control the atomic stream
allows very precise
and accurate thickness control
for each material.
Ultra-sharp doping profiles
and layers
with a thickness precision
of +/- 2Å can be achieved routinely
So in comparison
to other PVD techniques
epitaxy allows for better
thickness control
and enables the deposition
of single crystal layers.
And in addition,
in comparison to chemical
vapor deposition epitaxy
molecular beam epitaxy
requires lower temperature
400° to 800° C
versus 1200° C.
And allows better thickness control.
Working at lower temperatures
enables to work
with doped substrates
and to deposite doped films
without auto-doping
and diffusion problems.
Better thickness control
allows for fabricating quantum wells
where layer control
of +/- 40 Å is required.
Finally,
both low temperature
and precise thickness control
are required to fabricate
semi-conductor lasers,
such as laser diodes.
They are made of a stack
of different materials
with very specific doping levels
and they are widely used
for CD, DVD, BluRay Discs,
reading and recording,
as well as pen-sized laser pointers.
On the other hand,
MBE is more expensive
than other PVD systems
because of the required
ultrahigh vacuum
and because the deposition rate
is very slow
It is used only for applications
where no other technique can be used
Pulse laser deposition (PLD)
consists in using a
high-energy UV excimer laser
to ablate material from a target.
The physical ablation forms
a high-temperature vapor plume
that reaches the sample surface.
We will see that the main advantage
of such a system is its ability
to deposit compounds
for very complex stoichiometry.
The working
principle of PLD is as follows:
First,
a high-energy UV excimer laser pulse
is focused on a target
made of the material, to deposit.
Shown here.
As the laser focusing on the target
in green.
Typically, a krypton fluoride laser,
at 2.48 nanometer is used
and pulses of 10 to 30 nanoseconds
with an energy in the focus
of 2 Joules per centimeter square.
Pulse repetition is
in the order of 15 per second.
The energy of the pulse is absorbed
by the target
a plasma plume is created
at the surface of the target
and it interacts with ablated pieces
and the target itself.
Finally, the vaporized
material rapidly expands
and condenses on the substrate.
In between pulses,
the target cools down
and solidifies.
For metal, the absorption depth
is about 10 nanometer.
The energy is further relaxed
through electron phonon interactions
in a phenomena which
takes 1 to 10 picoseconds time.
Concretly, the electrons
are removed from the atoms
and oscillate in
the strong magnetic field,
created by the laser.
The generated heat diffuses around
due to collisions of these
free electrons with other atoms.
In the first time,
this melts the material.
And finally,
a small amount of material
is evaporated and ionized
PLD deposition at room temperature
usually results
in amorphous thin films.
However,
heating the substrate
to 700° to 900° C,
allows to get
crystalline thin films.
Substrate heating can be achieved
in two ways.
One conventional way is to use
a substrate holder
with an integrated heater.
Another way is to use a CO2 laser
which is focused on the substrate.
Pulse laser deposition
has several advantages
that make it into an attractive
PVD technique.
Firstly, the deposition
pressure range varies
from atmospheric
pressure to high vacuum.
Secondly,
it is almost possible to deposit
any material on any substrate
and there is no X-ray [generation]
as it is the case with sputtering.
Finally,
the most important strength of PLD
is that the target material
is deposited onto the substrate
with almost no decomposition.
A stoichiometry is conserved
complex compounds
and alloys can be deposited.
This makes PLD a unique
technique to deposit,
for instance, functional oxides,
such as super conducting materials
or bio-compatible based ceramics
to protect sensors from body fluid.
On the other hand,
PLD also has some
severe limitations.
Firstly,
there is a risk of splashing,
because of surface boiling
or shockwaves
due to the plasma plume expansion.
Boiling occurs when the layer
below the surface of the target
reaches its evaporation point
before the surface
of the target itself.
As a result, micrometer particles
are injected and impinged
to substrate surface.
This problem can be partially solved
using ultra-short laser pulses
of less than 1 picosecond.
A such pulse with a shorter
than the electron lattice
relaxation time,
the heat diffusion and melting
is reduced
and the material is forced
directly into plasma state
without going into
liquid phase first.
This leads to cleaner,
smoother and higher quality films.
Secondly,
PLD is a line of side technique,
and results in poor step coverage
which means
on the positive side
that it can be used
for lift off and
shadowmask techniques.
Finally, because of
the small source size
this technique is not suited
for large scale deposition
Call for new equipment is being
developed for this purpose.
To conclude this chapter,
I briefly want to introduce
one important and recently
very prevailing coating
material for MEMs,
which is parylene.
It is widely used
in microfabrication
as structural material,
thick protective coating
and thermal insulator.
Deposition process consists
of 3 subsequent steps.
During the first step,
a solid parylene
diamond is evaporated
in a chamber at 150° C.
In a second chamber,
the temperature is further
increased up to 670° C,
in order to separate
the diamonds in monomers.
And finally, in the third chamber,
the monomer gas is cooled
at room temperature
so that it condenses
on the substrate and polymerizes.
Layer thicknesses ranging
from 50 [nm] to 10 µm
double side coating,
as well as conformal
and stress-free layer are possible.
In addition,
parylene shows excellent
thickness and uniformity
below 1%.
Is thermally stable.
Has a good resistance to solvents,
acids, and bases.
Last but not least,
it is biocompatible,
which makes is an ideal candidate
for packaging application
for bioMEMs.
This table summarizes
the key features
of the main PVD techniques
introduced so far.
It allows to compare
the various parameters
and to select the proper method
for one's own use.
Please have a look at the variations
in parameters and try
to get an overview
of the pros and cons
of each of the methods.
We have looked at the wide range
of different PVD methods,
such as thermal evaporation
sputtering, ion plating,
molecular beam epitaxy
and pulse laser deposition.
The underlying physical
principles have been explained.
So you should now be able
to distinguish the various methods
and to eventually choose
the proper one for your purpose.
In an upcoming video lecture,
we will analyze more in details
how PVD films grown
unto to substrate.