This lesson on the growth
of thin films in physical
vapor deposition
presents the basic parameter
that influence the morphology
of the added material
on the substrate.
I will start by describing
what happens when the atoms
arrive on the surface
An important factor here
is the interface property
which determines
the adhesion of the added film
as well as the way
the film actually grows.
I will then show
the various growth modes
influence, on their turn,
the crystal structure of the film,
and will conclude
with some remarks on
the mechanical stresses
in the thin films.
Thin film deposition
and film growth
depend on the materials
involved
as well as on several
process parameters.
These include
the energy of the impinging atoms
their arrival rate
and the substrate temperature.
When atoms condensate
on the substrate
they are adsorbed
and attached to the surface
either by chemisorption
or by physisorption.
In the first case,
atoms create chemical bonds
to the surface
with the bonding energy
in the order of 1 electronvolt (eV).
The available energy depends
on impinging atoms energy
as well as on substrate temperature.
On the other hand,
physisorption occurs
when there is a chemistry mismatch
or when the energy is too low
to create chemical bonds
and which leaves
the chemical species
of the adsorbate
and the surface in tact.
In other words,
there is no chemical
reaction occurring.
Physisorbed atoms are weakly attached
to the surface by
van der Waals forces,
with the bonding energy
in the order of 0.3 to 0.5 eV.
As a result,
physisorbed atoms can diffuse
on the surface.
And diffusion of physisorbed atoms,
increases with the available energy
but is inversely proportional
to the atom's arrival rate.
Why is that so?
The explanation is as follows:
If the arrival rate is high,
atoms on the surface
will rapidly collide
with new arriving atoms.
And this limits the diffusion
and strongly influences
the growth mode.
Growth modes are detailed
later in this chapter.
Here on the figure you can see
various events that can occur
after the arrival
of the atoms on the surface.
As a result of this
surface diffusion
physisorbed atoms will
either bind at the kink
- shown here, a small step -
or at the defect.
Shown here.
Or nucleate with other atoms
and form clusters.
Nucleation is increased with
available surface energy.
Finally,
if the atom's energy is high enough,
they can also desorb
again from the surface.
The likelihood of desorption
is lower
for clustered atoms
in comparison to single atoms.
Once there are enough atoms
on the substrate surface
the film starts growing.
A very important parameter here
is the interface stability.
Or in other words, the question
whether the layer will adhere
to the substrate or not.
Thermodynamics allows determining
if the atoms will be chemisorbed
on the surface or not.
So if the change in Gibbs energy
which is given by the
Gibbs energy of the product
minus the Gibbs energy
of the reactants
is smaller than zero
then the reaction is possible.
Let us take the example of titania
on SiO2.
So the Gibbs free energy
is the product Gibbs free energy
of TiO2
minus Gibbs of SiO2
which is, in numerical values
known to be
160 minus 165 Kcal,
which is minus 5 Kcal
which is smaller than zero,
for this reaction can happen.
It means we can deposit
titania on SiO2.
Another material of interest
may be cobalt.
Depositing cobalt on silicon
is also possible.
As a corresponding
Gibbs free energy calculation
would show.
But the deposition
of cobalt on SiO2 is not possible
as the ∆ G is larger than zero.
Thus the cobalt deposition
on silicon is very sensitive
to the presence of native oxides.
Besides the initial
interface stability criteria
different types of interfaces exist.
An abrupt interface,
shown here,
is encountered in most
PVD and CVD depositions.
And which produces
an almost-ideally sharp
material transmission.
However,
if the goal is to grow a thin film
directly on silicon,
this is not as straightforward
as it sounds;
because without special precaution,
silicon is often covered
by a few nanometer-thick
native SiO2 layer.
In this case,
an interfacial layer
exists between the substrate
and the added film.
Shown here.
To remove
the interfacial SiO2 layer
typically a special surface etching
and cleaning has to be done
priorly, to the deposition.
So in some other cases,
for instance,
during the deposition of copper
on silicon dioxide,
the added copper atoms
diffuse into the substrate.
Chemical reactions
between the thin film
and the wafer
may also occur.
This is the case of nickel,
cobalt and titanium deposition
on silicon
which forms a so-called
"Silly Side"
at 400°, 500° and 600° C,
respectively.
There is a reaction going on
at the interface.
In some cases,
an annealing step is sufficient
to ensure a good
electrical conductivity
between the added thin film
and the silicon.
See the case
of the pitted interface,
for example.
This is the case
of silicon in aluminum
when heated over 425° C.
The spikes of the film
into the wafer
can be several micrometers deep.
On the positive side,
they allow for better
electrical contact
between aluminum and silicon
and is even able to break
through this thin native
silicon dioxide interface
that we have presented here before.
The adhesion of the added thin film
to the substrate
is a very important issue
in microfabrication
and special attention
is therefore required.
Particularly,
substrate cleanliness
is of a major significance
as residues from the environment
or from previous process steps
will almost inevitably lead
to poor adhesion.
The thin film
deposition process itself
also plays a role
if there is a strong
or weak adhesion.
For instance,
in sputtering,
highly energetic ions and atoms
knock out surface contamination
and loosely bound atoms.
This enhances the adhesion a lot.
Thus,
sputtered films tend to have
a better adhesion
compared to films formed
by evaporation.
However, as explained
in the previous slide
sometimes it is not possible
to grow a thin film
of a desired material
directly on the given substrate
because of thermodynamics.
Examples are the cases
of noble metals,
which are inert and do not react
by nature.
As a result,
they do not adhere well
to silicon or SiO2.
So, what to do?
To deposit noble metals,
adhesion layers
are therefore required.
These adhesion layers,
which are chosen according
to their ability
to make chemical bonds,
consist of few
nanometers-thick films
deposited just
before the noble metal,
in the same vacuum chamber.
This ensures
that we have
a clean interface
and substrate.
Two common pairs
of adhesion noble materials
in micro and nano fabrication
are titania and platinum
as well as
chrome and gold.
Here is the example
that shows the silicon substrate
with the chrome
adhesion layer,
and then the deposited gold,
that is now well-adhering
to the substrate.
This photo here,
on the right side,
actually shows
a failure process.
A 500 nm thick
chrome layer
aimed as electrical conductor
to drive current
with bimorph actuator
has poor adhesion to the substrate,
and is detached,
or delaminated, how we call it,
from the substrate.
You can see this
in this optical microscope
This is either due to poor adhesion,
and/or to high intrinsic stress,
both.
This will eventually lead
to the complete failure
of the device
and needs to be overcome.
To test thin film adhesion
a first, straightforward test
called the "tape-pull test",
can be performed.
A standard office tape
is attached to the wafer
and then pulled off.
If the film peels off
with the tape,
then adhesion is not good enough,
and process or adhesion layer
should be modified.
In the second example,
we added 10 nm chrome,
between the silicone nitrate
and the added 100 nm of gold film,
and as you can see,
now the gold film adheres very well,
under the tape-pull test.
There are, of course,
more sophisticated equipment
that measure the adhesion
of thin films.
But for first order information,
this tape-test is very convenient.
Now let us have a closer look
how the thin film grow
classify the modes,
and identify
the important parameters
on which this depends.
The 2D,
or layer-by-layer mode,
also called
Frank - van der Merwe mode,
occurs when the adatoms,
here in orange,
bond more strongly
with the substrate
than with other atoms
and
when they have
enough energy and time
to diffuse around to the energetic
minimum location.
This is the case
in ALD,
MBE,
and also PLD.
Here,
we have a relatively slow
growth rate,
so that the atoms have time
to rearrange themselves
before the atoms
for the second layer are coming.
The second growth mode is the 3D,
or island mode.
Also called,
Volmer - Weber Mode.
It typically occurs
during the deposition
of metal atoms
onto an insulator,
since bonds between
metal atoms are stronger
than bonds between
insulator and metal atoms.
In the island mode,
surface atoms have enough
energy and time to diffuse around
but not as much as in the 2D mode;
because the growth rate
is higher than the previous case.
As a result,
a few surface atoms nuclei together
and form clusters,
or islands.
At some point,
islands merge together,
and a uniform film.
For films formed
by sputtering and evaporation,
a continuous thin film forms
at around 10 to 20 nm thickness.
Before this threshold value
the film does yet not cover
the entire surface.
Island more typically occurs
with sputtering deposition
or with evaporation
when the substrate is heated.
A mixed mode,
combining 2D and 3D mode
also exists.
It is then called
the Stranski - Krastanov mode.
Finally,
when the surface atoms' energy
and mobility is low,
atoms stick where they land,
and islands are not able
to merge together.
In this last mode,
which is called the columnar mode,
grains grow upwards
and voids between the grains
can remain.
Columnar mode typically takes place
when the deposition is performed
at room temperature.
The growth mode determines
the way in which the film forms.
For us as users,
what is more important
is actually
the resulting film
intrinsic structure.
It plays a key role
for many physical properties
of the thin film.
Such as electrical band structure,
conductivity,
hardness,
transparency,
and piezoelectric properties.
The first important
question to ask is,
if the film is amorphous
polycrystalline or monocrystalline?
As a rule of thumb,
thin films made of silicon
covalently bonding materials,
compounds and alloys
are often amorphous
If no special precaution
is taken during the deposition.
Metals, on the other side,
are often polycrystalline.
In order to grow
monocrystalline films
very special deposition techniques,
such as MBE or PLD,
are required.
However, it is sometimes difficult
to predict the exact structure
of the thin film,
as it depends on
so many several parameters.
Such as the material itself,
the deposition method,
and the process.
In case of sputtering of metals,
for instance,
a well-known model,
called the Thornton's Zone model
shown here,
can be used.
It shows in empirical diagrams
the morphology of thin films
as a function of
the chamber pressure,
shown here on this axis,
and the substrate temperature (T).
Normalized by the melting
temperature of the thin film (Tm),
shown here.
Sputtered metal thin films
have a poorly crystalline structure.
At high pressure,
or low temperature,
(zone one),
atoms do not have much
energy to diffuse around.
Which results in columnar grains.
We see them here.
Usually this leads to porous films
with tensile stress
unless oxygen is present
in the chamber,
which leads to compressed stress
in the film.
At lower pressure
and higher temperature
impinging atoms are more energetic
and can knock out
loosely attached atoms,
and diffuse on the surface.
This results in denser films
with compressive stress.
Simultaneously,
the film grain structure moves
from zone 1 to the zone T,
for transition,
and zone 2,
where the grains are larger.
At some point,
if the temperature
is further increased
the film's crystal structure
reaches zone 3,
where annealing occurs,
and the film loses memory
of the deposition process,
as it is called in technical terms,
In the case of sputtered aluminum,
typical grain size
can go up to 0.5 µm
and can be in the order
of the film thickness.
Processes which depend
on grain boundaries
such as diffusion
and electromigration,
are strongly affected by the ratio
between grain size
and the characteristic dimensions
of the thin film in the microdevice.
For some materials,
the film crystal structure
does not change continuously
as described
in Thornton's zone model.
Instead, it changes abruptly
due to a phased change
occurring at specific temperatures.
An example of such a material
is tantalum.
Finally,
it is relevant to note
that the texture
of the added thin film
is inherited
from the underlying film.
Seed layers are, therefore,
often used to obtain
a validifying crystal orientation
on the subsequent deposition
of a thicker film.
You will remember
the case study
of the bimorph actuated
that we saw in one
of the introduction lessons
of this book.
After the (INAUDIBLE)
release of the beams
the cantilevers did not remain flat,
but were bent upwards.
This is due to residual stress
in the thin films
resulting from
the different process steps.
Let's now have a more extensive look
at the different kinds of stress
that exist in the thin films,
and to their origin.
As mentioned in the previous slide,
the deposition method
and the process parameters
influence the crystal structure
of the thin film.
In addition,
they also influence
the residual stress
in the thin films.
Stress in thin films
can be divided in two categories:
Extrinsic stress
and Intrinsic stress.
Extrinsic stress results
from a mismatch between the film
and the substrate's
coefficient of thermal expansion,
CTE.
If both the film and the substrate
undergo the same
temperature difference
a simple formula, shown here,
describes the stress
which is directly proportional
to the difference between
the two expansion coefficients
and to the change in temperature.
Such a situation occurs,
for instance,
during cooling after a CVD process.
Indeed, during CVD,
the film and the substrate
are at the same
elevated temperature.
By convention,
a negative stress is compressive
and generally
extrinsic stresses are uniform
over the film thickness.
Finally, it is worth mentioning
that most materials
used in microfabrication
have a higher CTE value than silicon
except SiO2, silicon nitrate,
and diamond.
On the other hand,
intrinsic stress is less understood.
There is no simple theory
that allows computing them.
The understanding relies
on empirical results.
Intrinsic stress is closely related
to the film material,
and microstructure,
as well as to the deposition method
and parameters.
For instance,
a lattice mismatch between the film
and the substrate,
or the incorporation of voids
and foreign atoms
generate intrinsic stress.
On the contrary,
bombarding the substrate
during the deposition
pinches of loosely attached atoms
which can reduce stress.
And intrinsic stress is not uniform
over the film thickness.
Which creates stress gradience.
These gradients are inducing
the banding of cantilevers.
Even if they are made
of a single layer material.
Intrinsic stress
can be partially removed
by means of an annealing step.
The total stress in a thin film
is equal to the sum of the extrinsic
and the intrinsic stress.
Usually films deposited
by evaporation
result in tensile stress.
Stress in sputtered films
depend on many parameters,
such as bias power,
or argon pressure,
sputtering gas masks,
substrate temperature
and deposition rate.
As a guideline,
sputtering at low pressure
at about 1 millitorr
usually results
in compressive stress.
While sputtering at higher pressure,
10 millitorr,
usually results in tensile stress.
Depositing sequential layers
with tensile and compressive stress
enables to perform
stress compensation.
Residual stress in thin films
leads to substrate
or device curvature.
To qualitatively understand why,
let's consider the schematics
on the top left corner
of this slide.
This is the case corresponding
to an extrinsic tensile stress.
If a thin film,
here in yellow,
is deposited by operation
on a substrate, here in grey,
at room temperature, for instance,
the film, which is initially hot
shrinks more relatively
to the substrate,
which is cold.
However, the lateral dimension
of the substrate
and of the thin film
have to be the same.
Therefore,
film is under tensile stress
while the substrate
is under compressor stress.
Shown here,
in this second line of the drawing.
To satisfy the sum
of the force's equilibrium,
the tensile force in the film
is equal to the compressive force
in the substrate.
However,
the mechanical equilibrium
is not satisfied yet;
because the sum of the moment.
Thus, the wafer and the film bend
in a concave way,
for the case of tensile thin films.
Indeed,
the film tends to retrieve
its shorter, unstressed state.
In the case
of compressive thin films,
in the top right corner,
the same reasoning leads
to convex bending
of the film.
It is worth to notice that
if a wafer with a thin film
were manually bent,
a tensile stress in the thin film
would occur in the case
of a convex shape.
It is the opposite, then,
for residual stresses.
Tensile stress
in thin films leads to cracks
while compressive stress
leads to buckling.
The well-known Stoney equation
quantitatively relates
the way a curvature
to the residual stress is
in the thin film.`
By measuring the radius
of curvature of the wafer
before and after the film deposition
and knowing the substrate
and film thicknesses,
it is possible to compute
the average stress in the thin film.
Here we see 2 SEM images
showing 2 different
cantilever arrays.
In both cases,
we have free-standing SiO2 films,
1.1 µm thick
grown by thermal oxidation
at 1050° C.
They are between 40 and 200 µm long.
The bilayer microcantilevers
were obtained
after an additional Ti (left)
and Al (right)
that was deposited
onto the SiO2 cantilevers.
The Al films with thicknesses
ranging from 0.3 to 1.7 µm
were deposited using
thermal evaporation.
In addition, the titanium films
were with thickness
ranging from 0.1 to 0.3 µm
were deposited using
electron beam evaporation.
The SEM images here show
the bilayer microcantilever array
and their respective bending
due to  intrinsic stress.
In the case of titanium,
it bends upwards,
and in the case of aluminum
it bends downwards.
In both cases,
we have SiO2,
S material plus titanium.
And here we have the SiO2
plus the aluminum.
So we can obtain
different types of stresses
in free-standing cantilevers,
by playing with different
material compositions.
In this chapter we first saw
that depending on the chemistry,
that the deposition method
and the process parameters,
atoms can either be chemisorbed
or physisorbed at the wafer surface.
Once arrived on the surface
the atoms stay, move or desorb.
Once the film starts to grow,
an important parameter
is to film substrate interface.
Will the film adhere or not?
To answer this question,
thermodynamics allows
computing interface stability
and several types
of different interfaces
were shown in this lesson.
We have seen that
all following factors
influence the thin film adhesion:
Interface compatibility,
substrate cleanness
and deposition method,
as well as adhesion layers.
Film growth can be categorized
into different modes,
which are 2D, 3D
and columnar modes.
These modes,
as well as the resulting
film crystal structure
are strongly dependent
on the deposited material,
the deposition method,
as well as
on the process parameters.
There is no general theory
that allows determining
the final crystal structure
of a thin film.
Some empirical data
can sometimes be used,
but most of the time,
trial and error method is required.
Finally,
as a signature
of the deposition method
and process parameters,
residual stress in thin film
was also studied.
Extrinsic stress
is differentiated
from intrinsic stress,
and the final total average stress
in a thin film
can be related to
the ranges of curvature
of the wafer using
the Stoney equation.
With this lesson,
we close the chapter on
physical vapor deposition.