Hello, and welcome to the
fourth and last unit of our MOOK
on ecological monitoring.
In this unit, we will give
several examples
of ecological monitoring
directly taken from the field.
Again, Inza Kone, social professor
at the Houphouët-Boigny University
of Côte d'Ivoire
and Emmanuel Iman, social professor
at the Ki-Zerbo University
in Burkina le Faso
will be helping us out.
Let us follow some elephants
to see what will be presented
in this unit.
First off, we will consider
the different levels
at which ecological monitoring
can be done
from a global to a local level.
Then, with Beatrice,
we will be looking at a group
of particular areas
in Kenya working together
to monitor the animals.
After this, along with Emmanuel,
we will be looking at the Nazinga Park
a terrestrial particular area
in Burkina le Faso.
We will, of course, not forget
about the marine environment
the (INAUDIBLE) seashells
will be
a particularly interesting example.
At the scale of the park,
we will make the difference
between monitoring forest,
with the example
of Tai National Park
in Ivory Coast
and monitoring the savannah
which Inza will be explaining.
In this case, we will be traveling
to Comoé National Park,
The next section will be wetlands
and we will try to monitor the birds
populating these areas.
Then we will focus on monitoring
a specific species and we will take
the example of the elephant.
Finally, we will briefly present
twenty golden rules of monitoring
that we think may be useful
to keep in mind
and could probably help you
with your work.
That's it.
Now don't forget about the quizzes
between the sequences.
They will help you
better understand the examples
and take (INAUDIBLE) from them.
Have an excellent fourth unit.