Ecological monitoring in this MOOC
mainly deals with monitoring
at the level of a protected area.
But there are plenty of other levels
where monitoring can be implemented.
Sometimes, it doesn't involve
the entire protected area.
It can be a specific system
or targeted species
that will lead
to only monitoring the area
in which these species exist.
For example, chimps
of the Niokolo Koba National Park
in Senegal
have undergone specific monitoring
for a long time
that usually only involved
the forest blocks they are present in.
In other words, less than ten percent
or fifteen percent
of the parks' surface.
If the indicators are well-chosen,
localized monitoring can, however,
adequately inform on the state
of the entire park
because generally
the conservation conditions
are inherently linked and
local success depends
on overall protection.
Here is another example:
monitoring the large carnivore
is sometimes taken as an indicator
of the overall state
of the protected area's conservation
as you mean that they are
the highest level of the food chain.
This, however, is not always relevant.
Their number can decrease due
to targeted persecution from the (INAUDIBLE)
while the rest of the protected area
is being preserved
or they can prosper
by feeding themselves
on the periphery of the area
while the antelopes of the park
become scarcer.
So, in the long run,
managing the ecosystem
by focusing on only one species
is not the most suitable solution.
By the way, managing a site,
regardless to others
in the same network can give way
to some shortcuts.
Indeed.
It is useful, if not essential,
to share the methods and results
with the other parks
in the same network,
like a national network
for protected areas, for instance.
Or between protected area
covering the same kind of ecosystem
like marine areas or mountain areas.
Otherwise, within a site,
you risk missing a trend
visible at the level
of the entire network.
For instance, marine protected areas
should make sure the information obtained
from monitoring is communicated
from one area to the other.
This makes sense when you look
at fish species or turtles
that will move from one area
to the other, obviously.
The specific case of transmonitoring
protected areas is indicated.
Of course, these sites share
the same natural resources
and ecological monitoring
should involve the entire ecosystem.
It is, however, rarely the case
because of logistical, administrative,
and even legal difficulties.
Thus, monitoring elephants
in Pendjari National Park
shows strong variation from one year
to the other.
This doesn't mean an increase
or decrease of the population,
but simply the fact
that according to the state
of the environment, elephants
may still or already
be in neighboring areas
of the W National Park,
the other national park, and so on.
So the only way, then,
to get a proper idea
of the population's number would be
by monitoring the entire territory
shared by Burkina, Benin and Niger.
So, the question of monitoring
beyond the borders
of the protected area is,
of course, relevant.
Many species are a value
for a protected area
but their distribution in space
or in time extends far beyond
the limits or the time
when the monitoring takes place.
Adapting monitoring to the situation
seems to be a necessity.
Monitoring the species can be done
only when it is found
within the protected area.
The risk is then that
the conservation measures we will take
will be disconnected
from real challenges,
challenges faced by the species
when it is located somewhere else.
For instance, the elephant population
in N'Gouma in Mali
moves in a very vast area
between several different waterholes.
Only counting animals that are
around one pond or waterhole
doesn't provide a genuine idea
of the threats
faced by these elephants,
nor does it give an idea
of possible solutions
regarding their conservation.
You can extend monitoring
to all the areas
visited by the species.
In other words, adapting it
to specific moments in time
when the species goes
to every site.
This requires a strong collaboration
between sites, countries or regions.
A good example of this
is the water bird survey
that takes place every year
around mid-January
in Europe, but also in Africa,
to have a better idea
of the species' population.
You can also choose to focus
on the species, rather than the place,
wherever it may be, which requires
even better coordination.
Thus, many migrating bird species
are monitored mainly
thanks to colors or microchips
because they move a lot
and inconsistently from one year
to another.
Localized monitoring wouldn't
have any sense other than to provide
local information to the manager.
You can also use tools
that allow monitoring
ecosystems as a whole
on a very big scale.
It is a case of satellite images
that give information
on the health state of entire sections
of the planet
and to hope, to better understand
what is happening locally
by contextualizing the situation.
A good example would be the impact
of climate change that can be hard
to detect locally
over a short period of time
while there would be appearance
on the long period of time
or on a big surface.
For instance, the shrinking surface
of the wetland
or the coastline changes.
Finally, it is required to adapt
ecological monitoring
to the characteristic of the species
or environments that you want
to monitor, and
to the challenges they face.
It is, therefore, not certain
that all the answers
regarding the management
of the protected area
can be found at the level
of this protected area.
It will always be useful, anyway,
to see what is done, as well,
at other levels in order to know
if the question
you are asking yourself
for your protected area
wouldn't be better treated
this way in other places?