In Kenya, the protected area network
is made out of parks
and national reserves
but also of many conservancies
that are, in fact,
either committee-based or
private protected areas.
The Northern Rangelands Trust - NRT -
is an organization that provides
technical support
to committee-based conservancies
to help them to set up
a sustainable network
of conservancies
throughout the country.
To this end, NRT helps
committee-based conservancies
to design their own
ecological monitoring program
according to their own needs
and to what is technically
and financially feasible.
For this, they will use a range
of tools called wild-life comms
for conservancy management
monitoring systems
which is a template
of monitoring forms, of databases,
and data analysis tests
that can be adjusted
according to the needs
of each of the conservancies.
Within a conservancy,
when they develop
the ecological monitoring program,
on the basis of comms, too,
managers, rangers and stakeholders
like the traditional chiefs,
will first gather together
and define a shared vision
for their conservancy in terms
of conservation of the nature.
Then, they determine
what are the species
that could provide useful information
to reflect the health
of this ecosystem,
and among these species
that they identify
they eventually choose the one
that can be easily observable,
that are well-known,
and often encountered
in order to guarantee that the rangers
will gather, afterwards,
enough information and
reliable information
in order to feed the future
statistical analysis.
For instance,
in the Westgate conservancy,
the values that have been chosen
are the buffaloes, the elephants,
zebras, predators like hyenas,
cheetahs and lions,
as well as ostriches, warthog
and several species
of antelopes.
In this case, the ecological
attributes to assess
in to monitor these values,
these species,
are the evolution
of the species' density over time
and their distribution.
This is very useful information
that helps detecting animal enemies
such as new threats
that will need to be controlled.
On this graph, you see that over
the last three years,
population of cheetahs, eland
and elephants have been coming
more and more to Westgate Conservancy,
in spite of buffalo populations.
Now that's a good question
to be analyzed
by the conservancy's managers.
The indicators to measure
these ecological attributes
are the number of living individuals,
of course, that are encountered
by the rangers, but also
the carcasses they may see
and the indicators aiming
at monitoring illegal activities
and human wildlife conflict
in and around the conservancy.
As means in these conservancies
are limited,
it's not possible to hire staff
specifically dedicated
to ecological monitoring,
so the rangers are the ones
in charge of collecting information
for ecological monitoring
during their patrols.
The counting will, therefore, be done
on foot and by blocks.
The tool used to record the data
are paper forms,
which is a simple method and,
therefore, very sustainable
and affordable.
The data from the monitoring form
fed in by the rangers
are then recorded in the database
and the person within the conservancy
in charge of the database
can extract from it all the reports
showing the evolution
of the population
of monitored species
and their distribution
among the different blocks
in the protected area.
And here is an example
of the kind of report
you can extract from the database.
And this is the map that shows
the distribution of elephants
throughout one year
in Westgate Conservancy.
Then the analysis
of monthly ecological monitoring reports
allows to rethink which areas
should be better controlled
by future patrols to guarantee
all blocks have been covered
in an equitable way or to choose
an intervention to reduce
human-elephant conflicts
in the high-risk zone,
if there are any.
So these two kinds of decisions are
good examples of adaptive management
based on
ecological monitoring results.
Thus, the comm's tools
in the Kenyan conservancies
shows that it's possible to implement
simple and cheap
ecological monitoring systems
adapted to the needs
of each particular conservancy
and that provide relevant information
for management decision making.
As the managers themselves decide
what value they want to monitor
and they are the ones responsible
for the storage and analysis
of the data throughout the year,
they are taking ownership
of the ecological monitoring
which guarantees its sustainability
over time.