The Nazinga Game Range is located
in the south of Burkina Faso
two hundred kilometers
from the capital city
which is Ouagodougou.
The Nazinga covers
around nine hundred square kilometers
and these entirely are made
of savanna.
The range's main management targets
are the conservation of biodiversity
and the valorisation
of natural resources
through hunting and tourism.
I mean, vision tourism.
Because of this, the park falls
under the protected area
of category six.
Population growth
in the many surrounding villages
is one of the greatest threats
faced by the range.
This causes poaching, and creates
the need for agricultural space
which greatly impacts fauna
and flora.
Despite this contraint,
and with the aim
of reaching all its targets in mind,
the range has implemented
a continuous ecological
monitoring system
of some values
of the ecosystem.
So, in Nazinga, the climate is monitored
to know the state of the environment
and the factors that can affect it.
To give an example, making
the right decision
regarding bush fires ignition,
including preferred date
or time of fire to set,
which are key elements
in this savanna's ecosystem
as it will help management
to have knowledge on the influence
of the quality of pasture available
for the park herbivores
who are also monitored
and valued in the range.
Climatic factors are monitored
through the weather station located
in the range, as well as
another station located
in Po City, near
the protected area.
And more recently, via
another station set up
by some program, research program,
called WASCAL,
which is studying climate changes
in the area.
Monitoring water points
is also considered
when monitoring certain habitats.
This type of monitoring aims
at controlling the presence
of surface water over time
to know its availability
for the park's animal species,
especially elephants,
which are also one
of the range's values
To do this, the water level progression
of the main dams
and water courses is assessed
every season
through direct observations.
If water runs out, the decision
may be made to fill it up
artificially to avoid animals
dispersing outside the park.
The fauna dynamics
are also monitored
to set collection limits, especially
when it comes to huntable species
like roan antelopes, warthogs,
waterbucks, etcetera.
After several tests, the line
transects by walking on foot.
This is foot samplings
on line-transect systems or method
that was chosen for the site.
To get even more information
on the diversity of species
in the park, scientific results
are also used,
as well as data that is collected
by tourists.
It is by this way that the range was able
to complete the list of bird species
that is already 290 as known,
for example for the park.
Hunting enables the collection
of species biometric data
from killed animals, including
weight, height, horn size, etcetera.
This gives information on the health
conditions of the species,
such as waterbuck or roan antelope,
and indirectly,
on the food availability
inside the park over years.
In monitoring the anthropic pressures
on different animal and plant values,
listed until now,
is essentially conducted
through surveillance;
I mean, law enforcement.
This gives the possibility
of specifically recording
any form of harms done
to the targeted species
namely, signs of poaching,
or wood cuttings
and other types of collections.
Monitoring habitat and flora
is enhanced by research activities
that are focused
on specific themes identified
during the ecological
monitoring processes.
They are mostly carried out
by students or researchers
in direct link with the park's staff
and are coordinated
by the park's manager.
One of Nazinga's main problems
is related to elephants
which are one of the monitored values
of the protected area
as they create conflict in the villages
surrounding the park.
This threat is monitored
by collecting information
on the damages around the range
which are systematically recorded
and allow to understand
elephant's population dynamics,
as well as their moment
and damage frequencies.
This will naturally help
the management
to implement suitable
preventive measures.
In all ecological monitoring systems
implemented in Nazinga
enables the range managers to obtain
both the qualitative and quantitative
information that they need
to carry out interannual comparison
and to evaluate the shifting trends
of the protected area values
in terms of animals' numbers
or habitat quality
or even to understand
anthropic pressures that face the range.
This is also always to evaluate
and adjust management
and valorisation decisions
of natural resources
inside the range, especially
when it comes to hunting game.
This reaches a key value
for the parks.