Marine protected areas
are specific ecosystems
involving both land and sea.
And their ecological monitoring
is a reflection of this specificity.
We will use the example
of Aldabra island,
in the Indian Ocean.
Aldabra is an atoll
in the Seychelles,
located north of Madagascar,
in the middle of the Indian Ocean.
It covers around
350 square kilometers,
but it is mainly
comprised of a lagoon,
of which two-thirds
are emerged during low tide.
The island is managed
by the Seychelles Island Foundation,
and does not have any inhabitants
except for some researchers
in the research station,
that is shown on the screen.
Aldabra has incredible
biological diversity.
Over 100 thousand giant tortoises
stay there.
You see one here.
It is one of the biggest
egg-laying sites
for Indian Ocean's turtles.
It is also a home
to many seabirds colonies
and animal species,
such as Aldbra rail.
But also,
to the region's vast population
of manatee.
The coral reef
attracts exceptional
underwater fauna.
All these elements
have led the island
to becoming
a UNESCO World Heritage Site,
in 1982.
Though the ecological monitoring
focuses on
the atoll's different values,
of course,
and there are many of them.
It requires expert knowledge
in different fields.
Monitoring tortoises
focuses on different
aspects of the population.
The number of individuals
is determined by
traveling over
12 permanent transects
at regular intervals.
The population is today
considered stable.
The ecology of these tortoises,
is assessed by
specifically monitoring hundreds
of identified individuals,
by marking their shells
which also allows determining
their lifespan.
Their movements
are monitored thanks
to GPS microchips,
placed on some tortoises.
And their impact on the environment
is assessed by the protection
of certain plots,
where you can measure
the growth of vegetation
in absence of tortoises.
Turtles are subject
to a similar approach.
Egg-layings are recorded
at night on clearly defined
beach areas,
which allows for evaluating
their evolution over time.
Over 500%
in the past 40 years.
Some turtles are also collared
or monitored
by satellite microchips,
which gives information
about their overall dispersion
in the Indian Ocean
when they move away from the atoll.
And about their survival rate also.
Seabirds colonies
their nests, the number of chicks,
are surveyed each year
which gives us
the number of seabirds,
the condition of the population,
the fluctuations linked
to food availability,
et cetera.
Aldabra has become
the second largest colony on earth
for frigate birds.
And this statement can be made
thanks to precise knowledge
obtained by monitoring the colonies.
Seabirds are also monitored
when moving.
For example,
microchips arrose
for monitoring
the red-tailed trumpet birds,
that reproduce in Aldabra
and will wander off
several thousand kilometers away
before coming back
to the original site.
Some (INAUDIBLE) species,
like the Aldabra rail
can be subject
to targeted monitoring
through regular
surveys and collaring
to assess movements
or survival rates.
Eliminating cats,
previously introduced
onto the island,
has allowed to restore
the rail population,
and monitoring showed
the progression rate
in numbers and distribution.
Monitoring invasive species
is an essential part
of the atoll management.
This has allowed taking
the suitable measures
to get rid of cats and goats
introduced almost a century ago.
And more recently,
to deal with the rats
brought in by visiting navigators.
Monitoring invaders
is, today, above all, preventive
and consists in detecting
new species that can present
a local risk.
And in this case,
suspicions will immediately
be eliminated.
This requires a permanent watch
ensured by civilian staff
during patrols conducted
for this purpose
in a systematic way.
For example,
Malagasy sparrows,
arrived from the neighboring island
of Assomption in 2012,
during a storm.
They were detected then eradicated
because they were
presenting a threat
to the survival,
or the purity,
of the endemic Aldabra sparrow,
the one we see here.
This ecological watch,
carefully organized and conducted,
has other virtues.
It has namely allowed to rediscover
a snail species
that was thought to be extinct
since 2007.
Therefore,
carefully monitoring an environment
can give information
on the ecosystem
far beyond the goals initially set.
When, for example,
it allows discovering
or rediscovering
an unknown species.
The maritime environment
is of course also
subject to monitoring.
The entire coral reef of the island
has been mapped to enable
detailed monitoring.
Monitoring the underwater fauna
is done during
regular diving sessions,
but also via immersed cameras
that allow for the distance
surveillance of 12 control sites.
Surveying fish species
(INAUDIBLE) is done to detect
evolving tendencies
of the ecosystem.
All this
gives information
on the condition of the reef,
and allows for further monitoring
of evolutions linked to the increase
of the ocean temperature,
for instance.
The large sea mammals
are also spotted from the coast
and the frequency
of their visits is monitored.
Ecological monitoring of Aldabra
combines the classic
monitoring approach
that is regular, organized,
and so and so,
to research that will help answer
the questions raised by monitoring.
This leads to the exceptional
management of the atoll,
and confirms the utility
of adaptive management
based on good knowledge
of the environment.
This knowledge is possible
thanks to the structured
ecological monitoring plan.
A big part of monitoring
is purely forward looking
and aims at keeping any form
of invasive species
or other problems from appearing.
In this respect,
Aldabra is absolutely remarkable.