The Taï National Park, or TNP,
is located in the southwest
of Côte d'Ivoire.
With each extension of
the zoo fauna reserve in the north,
the TNP covers a surface area
of around 536 thousand hectares.
Or of a 1.3 million acres.
It is the largest protected
primary rain forest in West Africa.
The park has been listed
to the international network
of Biosphere Reserves
in 1978,
and World Heritage site in 1982,
in the framework of the MAB
UNESCO program
shows how important it is.
For this case study,
we'll be looking at the 10 phase
ecological monitoring program,
implemented in the Taï National Park
between 2005 and 2015,
to monitor all
of the animal populations.
This case is based on the result
of data collected during phase 4,
which took place between August 2008
and February 2009,
as well as those
from phases 2 and 3.
We will specifically look
at the duikers value.
Ecological monitoring
in the TaÏ National Park
aims at assessing the following
ecological attributes:
What is the duiker population
size within the park?
What types of threats
do they face in the park?
How are these threats
and duiker populations
distributed inside the park?
The ecological monitoring method
used to inform on these
3 ecological attributes
is based on a total
sweep of the park,
following transects.
The aim was
to look both for direct
and indirect indicators
of duiker populations
and other animal populations.
Related pressures were also noted.
This illustration shows
the layout of different transect
groups throughout the park.
So, 368 kilometers of transects
divided into 5 zones
were roamed by sampling teams
working simultaneously.
Each transect measures 2 kilometers.
They are led out regularly
throughout the park
in groups of 4,
separated by 8 kilometers.
And within a group, transects
are separated by 1 kilometer.
The data analysis
mainly consisted in calculating
encounter rates and proportions
from the raw data,
in order to estimate the population
size of duikers in the park.
The Maxwell's duiker
remains the most prevalent species
with 0.52 individual per kilometer.
The bay duiker
is the second
most encountered species.
And the scarcest ones
are the yellow-backed duikers
and the zebra duikers.
To get an idea of a distribution
of species in the park,
simple distribution maps
were drawn up
from ArcGis 9.2 software,
by combining
geographical coordinates
with the observations
made by transects
Just as in phases 2 and 3,
indicators of duiker presence
were found throughout
the Taï National Park.
Areas with higher concentration,
meaning more than
10 indicators per kilometer,
were mainly in the east,
as opposed to phase 2
where there were almost no zone
with high concentration
of indicators.
This situation could be a sign
of progressive recolonization
of duikers in the entire
Taï National Park.
The total number of observations
made on these transects
is important,
and reaches over 11 thousand,
all species included.
Most were bovines
with 39% of observations.
By the way,
during this phase,
the number of direct observations
has practically doubled,
going from 282 during
the previous phase, to 484.
Human activities,
essentially illegal activities,
like hunting, mining and so on,
represented only 4%
of recorded observations.
But the most encountered
indicators of human activities
were trucks with 300 observations,
traps with 171 observations,
and (INAUDIBLE)
with 131 observations.
Even though
there were more indicators
of fauna attacks during phase 4,
319 of total observations,
the critical encounter rate
of one indicator rate per kilometer,
was not reached.
Furthermore,
the encounter rate
of poaching trails
was reduced by more than half.
And in phase 4,
went from 1.01 per kilometer,
to 0.42 per kilometer.
As for traps,
their encounter rate
did not change much,
but was slowly decreasing.
Going from 0.55 in phase 3,
to 0.47 per kilometer in phase 4.
The analysis of hunting
indicator distribution, however,
shows that
in all phases
there are areas
with higher rates of attacks.
In phase 4,
these areas
are mainly located
at the periphery of the park.
In all 3 phases,
the research area shows
a very low rate
of hunting indicators,
probably thanks to
regular presence of humans
and to man-made actions
implemented in the park.
Other animals, such as apes,
24% of observations,
and birds, 18% of observations,
were also observed a lot.
But this is not true for elephants,
with only 1% of observations.
Either because
there are very few individuals
of this species in the park,
or because the monitoring methods
is not useful to assess
its ecological attributes.
To finish off,
we can see that
over the course
of a couple of years,
the encounter rate of duikers
has been increasing
in the TaÏ National Park
while indicators of attacks
have stabilized or fallen.
These results are undoubtfully
a result of management decisions
that were implemented
to protect the duiker value,
used here
as an example
of all animal populations,
and to reduce the threats
weighing against it.
This would hence
be a demonstration
of the park's success.