The Comoé National Park,
or CNP,
is located in the northeast
of Cote d'Ivoire,
and covers 1'149'000 hectares
or over 2.8 million acres.
It is the largest protected area
in west end Sub-Saharan Africa.
This park is representative
of Cote d'Ivoire's savannah biomes.
It was classified
Biosphere Reserve in 1982,
and World Heritage Site in 1983.
At the Comoé National Park
pressures have increased
during the long
political and military crisis
the country went through
between 2002 and 2011.
These threats
have caused resurges in gold mining,
illegal transhumance and poaching,
which led to the depletion
of some animal species,
such as chimpanzees,
elephants and lions.
In 2010 and 2014,
the return of social
and political stability
has allowed for 2 aerial sampling
to take place
in the Comoé National Park,
with the technical support
of Wild Chimpanzee Foundation (WCF),
and the GTZ.
This study unit
is based on the result
of these 2 surveys,
which were a form of surveys
aiming at rediscovering the state
of the park and its values,
and to reorganize management
based on the identified priorities.
Let's remember that surveillance
is not the same thing as monitoring,
and that it is based on a series
of samplings repeated over time,
providing baseline data
for the later implementation
of ecological monitoring.
The study area
covers 16'703 km².
It is made
of the Comoé National Park,
and 2 biodiversity hotspots:
Warigué in the north
and Mount Tingui in the south.
In 2010 and 2014,
the data collection methodology
consisted in systematically
[flying over] the study zones
by sampling [transects lines]
of different lanes.
The sampling system
included 45 transects
tilted at 20° to the north,
and led out regularly
and systematically 6 km
apart from each other.
In total, 2955 km of transects
were overflown
among which, 70% were located
in the Comoé National Park.
The sampling rate
of the surveyed zone was 6.21%.
In 2010,
a total of 8477 direct mammal
observations were made.
Among these
with 90% of all individual scenes
domestic animals,
especially oxen,
were the most encountered animals.
With 756 individuals,
representing 8.92%
of all observations,
the second most prevalent
species encountered
were the wild bovine species,
including hartebeests, buffalos,
defasa waterbucks, kobs, bushbucks
[INAUDIBLE] antelopes
and some duikers.
As for primates,
two chimpanzees and 30 monkeys,
among which were live baboons,
patas and green monkeys
were observed.
Two footprints of elephants
and 36 individuals
of other mammal species
were also observed.
Also
these special distribution maps
show that the fauna was distributed
unevenly throughout the park,
and indicators
of entropic activities
were found in the park
as well as on the outskirts.
With more than 6000 domestic animals
observed in the Comoé National Park,
during the 2010 survey
was reduced 100 times in 2014
to around 60.
While the number of wild animals
has increased 2 times,
going from 752
to 1047 individuals.
Furthermore,
86.99% of domestic animals
observed in the surveyed
in the area, in 2010,
were found within
the Comoé National Park.
While in 2014,
that number went down to 4.58%.
In both 2010 and 2014,
the special distribution
of bovine species
covered almost
the entire surveyed area.
But in 2014, the distribution
of bovine observations
over the entire park was less even.
However, that same year
the maximal encounter rate,
8 individuals per kilometer,
exceeded that of 2010,
7 individuals per kilometer,
where areas of high-encounter rates
of bovine species
were more isolated.
First,
the chances of finding wild animals
are higher in the central parts
of Comoé National Park.
In 2010,
rates of human activity encounters
higher than 1 indicator
per kilometer,
were essentially found
around the park,
where more than 3 indicators
per kilometer were observed
in the entire area.
This is proof of a great
entropic pressure.
In 2014,
the encounter rate
of these indicators
decreased
in the Comoé National Park
going from 5 indicators
per kilometer,
to 2 indicators per kilometer.
Between 2010 and 2014,
in the Comoé National Park,
there was indeed
a significant difference
between the encounter rates
of entropic activity indicators.
These aerial surveys
give fundamental results
on the state of the main
species still present,
which are potential
protected area values,
and of some of their attributes:
Where number, distribution,
group composition,
and threats they are facing.
Carrying out surveys
on the same zones
and in similar conditions,
shows the shifting trends
of the attributes
at times where it is key
to be able to closely monitor
park management decisions
in the context
of the park's recovery.
Great conservation efforts
are first being made by managers
and the data collected
shows the results thereof.
But monitoring and actions
must continue;
because entropic pressures
on the Comoé National Park
are still present.
Namely,
in east peripheral zones.
This could have negative
impacts on the balance
of the Comoé National Park
ecosystem.