Wetlands are ecotones,
areas of transition
between water and land,
which diverse function give them
remarkable biological, ideological,
economical and sociological values.
In the MOOC
on protected areas management,
we have seen that wetlands
face many threats:
drainage, industrialisation,
pollution, urbanization and so on,
which keep reducing their size.
According to the Ramsar Convention,
waterbirds are species of birds
that are ecologically dependent
upon wetlands.
Here we consider waterbird species
as a value of wetlands.
And we will see how their attributes
ought to be monitored,
especially the diversity of species,
and their number
of individual per species.
Waterbirds are monitored
because they are indicators
of the quality of wetlands.
First, according
to the Ramsar Convention
a wetland is considered
globally important
when it includes at least
1% of waterbirds populations.
1% can be a very big
number of birds.
They can also be monitored
because of their sustainable use
for vision, tourism,
or hunting, for instance.
Monitoring namely
has to draw up or update
wetland management plans.
Or to design sampling plans
correlated with
the available resources.
In this unit, we will talk about
direct monitoring methods.
These methods depend
on many factors, such as:
The monitored species,
the size of the site,
coastal accessibility,
observation points given
another view,
the time available
to carry out the count,
the number of people to include,
and the equipment available.
In all cases,
monitoring requires
experienced staff,
and meticulous preparation
as always in monitoring.
If possible,
apply the same monitoring protocol
during each site visit.
It can, however, be difficult
to standardize counting protocols
on sites undergoing
important changes over time.
And that is particularly
true for wetlands.
Frost, draught, or floods,
can greatly influence
the counting conditions
from a year to the next.
And these factors
should be considered
when drawing up protocols
and of course when you
proceed to data analysis.
Waterbirds can be monitored directly
in 3 different ways.
One, ground counts,
usually done on foot,
sometimes by bicycle or by car.
Two, monitoring from a boat.
And three,
aerial monitoring from a plane
or a helicopter.
Of course, ground counts
are the easiest
and most commonly used protocol.
And also the cheapest.
You can also take
photographs or films,
and use these to individually
count birds
after you've done those pictures.
Or simply verify
the observer's estimates.
During each visit,
the site should systematically
be covered on foot
following an identical,
predetermined route
following the transect model,
used by (INAUDIBLE)
to identify the birds.
Identify the species,
count individual
of each species,
determine the gender ratio for some
of them when it is feasible,
observe interspecific combinations,
note feeding behaviors
and habits, and so on.
As there can be many individuals
at the same place,
bird counts are often
done per block.
Experienced observers can count
blocks of 10, 20, 50, 100 birds
or more.
Birds on the first block
are generally counted one by one.
Then the mental image
of the first block
is carried forwards
to the entire group
to estimate the total number.
Most observers
use blocks of 10 birds.
It can be complicated
to go above that number.
A tally counter
reckoning number
of birds or blocks,
can improve precision and avoid
forgetting an individual or block,
of course.
You can also use a voice recorder,
or ask help from a colleague.
Blocks of 100 birds or more
are generally only
applied to birds flying.
Or when the time at hand
to count is very limited.
In this case
it is usually easier to proceed
from the back of a fleet
by examining the group
in its flying direction
using binoculars or a telescope.
Not easy, but feasible.
Of course, on small sites,
it is better to count birds
one by one.
It is usually easier to count birds
that are resting or feeding,
standing on the ground,
or on the water.
If you wish to monitor
a colony of breeding birds,
it is crucial to minimize the risk
of disturbing them,
and the observer should
avoid getting too close
whether on foot, by car
boat or on plane.
Just to avoid disturbance.
Just like it is
for all types of monitoring,
aiming at detecting
(INAUDIBLE) variations,
the same site should be counted
season after season
following the same
standardized protocol.
The different methods
can go from a rough estimate
of a total number
of breeding birds present
to a total count of occupied nests.
If the colony is counted
only once during breeding season,
all the nests occupied
by eggs or chicks
should be counted.
If the count takes place monthly,
only nests occupied by eggs
should be counted.
As for larger colonies,
proceed once more
to estimates by counting in blocks.
For birds breeding
on large surfaces,
the total number of birds
can also be estimated
through quadrat sampling,
for instance,
and extrapolations.
In the end,
good monitoring is, above all,
based on the observer's
quality and precision.
But of course, this is true for all
types of monitoring.