The elephant is one of the most
studied species on the planet,
and there are many
techniques to monitor it.
But let's have a look
at some of them
that are useful to guide
management decisions.
The first question the manager
can ask himself
is to know how
the elephant are distributed
in and around the protected area,
so that he can detect
abnormal movements
caused by entropic pressures.
A common technique to determine
the distribution of elephants
consists in studying their tracks,
either droppings or footprints,
in transects spread
over the entire protected area.
Alternatively,
sampling implications
in space and time
of these transects
allow to get more reliable results
of the real distribution
of the elephants.
As for the methods using
telemetry or satellite monitoring,
which consists in placing
a tracking collar
on certain key individuals
to monitor their journeys
the signals emitted by the collar
are then received by an antenna
or a satellite,
that gives the animal's positioning.
So this system
enables direct monitoring
that can be useful
when a quick management decision
needs to be made,
when elephants get closer
to populated areas, for instance.
Especially if those elephants
know how to cross
electrified fences,
which draw the limit
between the protected area
and the neighboring communities.
They can then be spotted
early enough to intervene on time,
and prevent
human-elephant conflicts.
On the other hand,
knowing the damage rates
done by elephants on certain
(INAUDIBLE) forests
of the protected area,
where they are present
in high densities,
will allow to intervene
if this sensitive habitat
needs to be protected.
Even if the cause-effect
relationship between elephants
and their habitat
is often hard to establish,
there are simple models though
to predict them
and that allow the manager
to simulate the consequences
of interventions,
in order to assess the level of risk
before implementing them.
Such models
have been developed, for example,
for Tsavo, Serengeti,
and  Manyara ecosystems,
in east Africa.
Thereby, to better manage
these habitats and their threats,
beyond knowing the distribution,
the manager will also need to know
the number of elephants present
in the protected area
and their density.
And even the possible evolution
of the resident population
over the years.
If the protected area
is in the savannah
you could,
for example,
proceed to aerial
or ground based censuses,
by counting the elephants
on transects.
On this map
we see that the aerial count,
done in 2008,
over the Laikipia
and some rural areas in Kenya,
have allowed to identify the zone
with the different
densities of elephants.
In the protected areas
located in the dense forests
in Central Africa,
we stick to ground-based censuses.
Or we use capture-recapture method,
by phototraps,
or DNA sampling on feces,
and statistical models
then allow to deduce the abundance
and the density of elephants
in the studied zones based
on these data.
So knowing the distribution
and the abundance of elephants
is a good start.
But some managers
can be willing to go further
and look to detect abnormalities
in the social structures.
Because this can also reveal
management problems to curb.
The size of elephant groups,
or families,
can be modified;
because of the suppression
of certain age groups
for instance,
because of intensive poaching
targeting old individuals
with large tusks.
And of course,
you shouldn't forget to monitor
the threat to elephants
and their habitat,
to make sure that management actions
to counter them are effective.
This will be done by assisting
the patrolling efforts
the arrest rates,
and following up on prosecutions.
So as we can see
there are multiple methods
to resolve these different
management questions
and they are more or less elaborate
or reliable.
But it is useless to choose the ones
that we know we won't
have the means to implement.
In the case where
the resources are limited,
you may only want to focus
your ecological monitoring
on the distribution of elephants
and the threats they face,
because this already gives
a lot of key information
to protect the elephants.