We've seen in this MOOC
what ecological monitoring
of protected area means.
It is the assessment
of a peer value conditions.
This value is characterized
by its ecological attributes,
described by indicators.
All this follows a protocol
that determines the sampling plan,
the method that will be used,
dependent on the context,
on the competencies,
and the means at hand.
So as a conclusion,
let's keep some
simple rules in mind.
Ecological monitoring
must have a purpose.
And is thereby not a simple
collection of information,
that nobody needs,
and that will pile up for nothing
in the manager's office.
The purpose for the monitoring
needs to be clearly defined,
to be understood by the managers,
executants and those to whom
the results will be sent to.
Monitoring is part
of the protected area's management.
Particularly during the preparation
of the management plan,
during the assessment
of its effectiveness,
and in daily staff activities.
Monitoring identifies
what is being monitored,
and it is based on the protected
area's values
it describes
the ecological attributes,
and the indicators
that will be chosen in priority.
Monitoring needs
qualitative criteria,
and is therefore assessed
for the results it provides,
but also for the way
it is carried out.
It is based on the strong knowledge
of the ecology of the values
that are to be monitored.
Monitoring is adapted
to the monitored values,
its responsiveness, in particular,
allows to detect variations
of the ecological attributes
in a good and workable way.
Sampling must be
precise and relevant.
The chosen method
must be representative
and explainable to all.
And it must give way
to the least bias possible.
Monitoring means effort.
So sampling needs
to be random, if possible,
and not centered
on the accessible areas
or the ones where we know
species are plentiful.
The chosen method needs
to be sustainable,
therefore needs to remain
unchanged over time.
Or the possible changes
need to be justified, at least.
Honesty is key.
Meaning, tampering with protocol
or results, to make them
more impactful or meaningful,
is useless,
and will sooner or later
be noticed.
You need to keep the original
hypotheses in mind,
because the conditions,
the choice of methods,
can influence the way
we interpret the data.
The surveying method
needs to be replicable
by each operator.
Because individuals
don't make the results.
The monitoring results
have to be used for what they are.
If the bias are too important,
you need to have the wisdom
and the courage to speak up.
You also need to be smart
when extrapolating the data.
Because you can have statistics
to say what you want them to say.
So common sense
need to prevail.
If you want monitoring
to be realistic and sustainable,
it needs to be adapted to skills,
to the needs and the site of course.
Monitoring needs to be enhanced.
In other words,
the cost,
the working time needed,
the means to mobilize,
and the skills to acquire,
need to be extremely well-managed.
All the relevant data need
to be accessible and stored.
This will guarantee transparency,
sustainability and credibility
of the monitoring.
The results need
to be communicated simply.
Meaning that monitoring is useful
only if the results are shared.
Finally, monitoring is carried out
by the stakeholders of the protected
area's management itself,
and shouldn't be outsourced.
The first call of monitoring
is indeed to improve
the site's management itself.
There you go.
Some simple rules
that we hope will be useful daily
in the execution
of your ecological monitoring plan.