We have reached the end of this MOOC
on ecological monitoring.
I hope you that have enjoyed
participating in it
as much as we have enjoyed
preparing the course.
And of course I do hope it helped
you better understand
how important
ecological monitoring is
for the health of protected areas
and for the entire
decision making process.
I would like to thank
a couple of people.
First, all the speakers
involved in this MOOC.
Béatrice Chataigner, (INAUDIBLE)
Inza Kone, (INAUDIBLE)
Thanks to you all.
Then,
thanks to (INAUDIBLE)
who manages the MOOC daily,
and Madeline (INAUDIBLE),
who translated it
into English and prepared
the book that comes with it.
I also want to thank
the staff from EPFL,
especially Tibo (INAUDIBLE)
who edited all the videos.
Thank you to all of those involved
in the EPFL Center
for digital education.
And of course, our friends
from the MOOCs for Africa Unit,
who allowed for this program
to even exist.
Please let us know what you thought.
Any suggestions to improve
this MOOC are welcome.
We need your input
to keep moving forward.
And of course,
you can follow us
via our other MOOCs
but also on papaco.org,
on Facebook.
Also if you would like
to stay in touch,
don't forget to sign up
to the monthly NAPA newsletter.
Finally, I would like
to thank the organization
that financed this MOOC,
École Polytechnique
Fédérale de Lausanne,
and the France-IUCN Partnership
particularly
the French Development Agency.
Here we are.
I truly hope you will join us
in our other MOOCs.
Have a good day.