This is the last series of episodes
of this MOOC, introducing
object-oriented programming (OOP)
in Java.
In this last series of episodes,
we wanted to present to you
an entire problem,
a very general problem,
a case study
which will consist in representing
different watches.
There will be analog watches,
digital watches,
watches that will be both;
watches will have accessories such
as bracelets, bodies,...
So a rather general frame
which could serve for example
as management software for a jeweler's
or as sales software
or even for printing catalogs.
Through this, we will illustrate
different concepts
that were presented all along
this course.
The themes we have chosen to
present to you
in these summary episodes
include first of all
the notion of conception, the
modelling of a problem
from an OOP point of view :
which classes have to
inherit from which other ones,
whether abstract classes are
needed,
how to make the calculation of watches'
prices polymorphic,
or how to make the output polymorphic.
Output will be treated in a
very specific way,
with an override of the toString method
inherited from Object,
and an adaptation of the output
for each class, to have a polymorphic
output.
We will also go over interfaces,
with the different mechanisms,
digital or analog watch mechanisms,
and even double mechanisms, which
will be both analog and digital,
then we will end with a last
episode
presenting a problem
we have not yet seen
in this course, which is the notion
of polymorphic copy,
how to copy heterogeneous
collections;
how to copy watches which can
contain different components,
each behaving in different ways,
on the point of view of either
price or display.
This is the menu for this final week.
But let's start by presenting
the problem in more detail.
We want to model watches,
let's say that watches are products,
in the sense that a product is something
that we can sell, that has a price.
Watches will have basic mechanisms,
typically hands, to display the time,
and will be made of different
accessories
such as a body, a bracelet,
the glass, the clasp.
The products we will discuss later
on will have a price,
and the calculation of this
price can vary.
So this aspect is interesting for
conception,
as it varies depending on a base
price that is fixed at the level of the product.
All products can be displayed,
and the output can vary,
as each product must be
displayed in its own way.
Of course, what is behind these notions
of "can vary" and "displayed in
its own way",
is the concept of polymorphism.
Then, the mechanisms we have
discussed just above,
and the accessories that
make up the watches,
these mechanisms and accessories
are also products.
We have used the
verb "to be" several times,
which refers to inheritance
relationships.
We could for example buy accessories
or mechanisms separately,
so each of these could behave
like a product,
and have its own price,
and its own way of calculating its price.
Fundamentally, there are
three sorts of mechanisms:
mechanisms we will
refer to as analog,
to represent watches with hands,
whereas digital watches will be
represented by a digital mechanism,
and we will have watches
that are both
analog and digital.
For mechanisms that we call double
mechanisms,
we will suppose that they
display only one time,
so we will say that there is
a time associated to a watch here,
and that it will have two
ways of being represented.
This is a point of view
chosen as an exercise
we could of course have chosen
a different point of view
which would consist in associating a time
to each of the representation mechanisms,
either analog or digital,
but it is not the point of view
that we took here,
in order to introduce an interesting
problem
on coding these classes.
To sum up, regarding classes,
that is, regarding the types of objects
that we will have in our program,
we will have watches, we will have
products,
we will have mechanisms and
accessories,
where accessories can be
bodies, bracelets
-- all of these will be classes --
regarding mechanisms, we can have
analog mechanisms,
digital mechanisms, or
double mechanisms.
That is the whole set of classes.
Regarding inheritance relationships,
we have seen that watches
are products,
so they will inherit from Produit
(TN: means "products"),
we have seen that analog, digital and
double mechanisms
are sorts of mechanisms,
so these three classes will naturally
inherit from the Mecanisme class
We have also seen that
mechanisms and accessories
are also products.
So all of this will lead to the following
hierarchic model:
Right at the top, we have the concept
of a product,
accessories, mechanisms and watches
are products (TN: "montre" means "watch")
however, a watch will have a mechanism
and accessories,
so it will encapsulate those classes.
Among the accessories, we will find bodies,
bracelets (TN: "boitier" means "body"),
clasps, glasses (TN: "fermoir" and "vitre",
resp.), all of these are accessories.
Mechanisms can be analog
or digital, these are both
mechanisms.
Finally, the double mechanism.
Originally, it is a mechanism,
but we have decided, according
to the last remark,
that it indicated only one time,
which we will certainly represent
at the level of the notion of mechanism,
and that it behaves both
as analog mechanism
and digital mechanism, which will
certainly require an interface,
but we will see later on how to model
this exactly.
Let's see how all of this can be
translated into code
By the way, we suggest that while
you watch these videos,
you take breaks from time to time
to write the code yourselves
in your favorite development
environment.
First point, watches
are products,
this is represented with a Montre class,
which is a, which inherits from Produit,
and so of course we introduce
a Produit class,
of which Montre inherits.
And for now,
we simply have an empty main.
Second point,
watches have a mechanism,
so they will encapsulate a mechanism,
watches have a mechanism and
are made of,
they have, different accessories.
So how do we translate
different accessories?
It is simply a collection
of accessories,
a dynamic array of accessories.
And so this introduces
two new classes.
A Mecanisme (TN: "mechanism") class and
an Accessoire (TN: "accessory") class.
Next aspect: products
have a price
So we could simply encapsulate
a price,
naturally represented as a double,
but we have a constraint saying
that the price can vary,
which shows that we will have
to calculate the price.
For example, later on, we will
decide that the price of a watch
is the price of its mechanism and
the sum of the prices of its accessories,
and so a price is no longer a datum
but becomes a process,
which we will represent
with a method here.
This method returns a price,
naturally a double,
then we want to say that
the price can vary,
so this means that we may have
a polymorphic behavior
Let's say that, by default,
we will return the base price,
the base value,
and so what we called a
price, earlier,
will become a base value,
to be the price of the product
by default,
but maybe later,
in other subclasses of the
Produit class,
it will simply be used
in different calculations
for the price of other products,
subclasses derived from the Produit class.
Moreover, all products
can be displayed,
which means concretely that we will
add a polymorphic toString method,
that will be capable of giving us
a character string
corresponding to displaying a product.
Products can be displayed
but each in their own way
which means that we will have
a polymorphic output.
We will leave this for the
next episode,
we will come back to it in that episode
For now, we will simply
write a header
to remember that we want to
override the toString method for products.
Regarding mechanisms and accessories,
we said that mechanisms and
accessories are products.
So here too, we have an
inheritance relationship,
where the Accessoire class
inherits from the Produit class
which was defined earlier,
and the Mecanisme class also inherits
from the Produit class.
About mechanisms: there are three
kinds of mechanisms
so these three classes, of course,
extend Mecanisme.
We have MecanismeAnalogique (TN: means
"analog mechanism") which is a Mecanisme,
which inherits from Mecanisme,
we have MecanismeDigital
and MecanismeDouble which
also inherits from Mecanisme.
And final point, about double
mechanisms,
we will suppose that there exists only
one time within the double mechanism,
but that double mechanisms behave
as analog mechanisms and as
digital mechanisms,
which is something we haven't
translated here,
and which will affect this inheritance
relationship,
but we will come back to that
in an episode specifically
dedicated to that aspect.
There, this concludes this
first episode
on the presentation and object-oriented
modelling of the problem.
The next episode will focus on
polymorphic display
and on filling the Produit class.