In this episode, we will continue
our case study on watches,
Swiss or not, by the way, and we will
attack the polymorphic display
of the different products
in our hierarchy
As a reminder, at the previous step,
we made a draft of the hierarchy
of products and we know want to
make sure that
these different products can be
displayed in a polymorphic fashion.
Basically, a product like a watch, a mechanism
or an accessory will have
its own way of being displayed
and we want this display
to be polymorphic, that is that,
if we put an object of type
Montre (TN: "watch")  in a variable
of type Produit (TN: "Product") and we invoke
the display method on that variable,
then we want the output
to automatically adapt to the actual
type of the instance stored in the variable.
So each product has its own way of
being displayed and we are wondering
how to proceed to make a
polymorphic display.
So, the idea would be for example that
I declare a variable of type Produit,
I assign to it the reference of an object
of type Montre, which is a subclass
of Produit, and that I then
proceed to display
this object "p". And I would like
to have all the characteristics of
the object, and I want them to
be automatically adapted to the fact
that the object is actually a watch,
i.e that what I stored
in the variable "p" is an object
of type Montre.
The most natural way is of course to
use the toString method,
which is automatically invoked
by system.out.println,
and if we want each product to be
displayed in its own way, we simply
need to override this toString method
accordingly in
each subclass where it seems useful
to do so.
Suppose that we wish to make sure
that the default way to display
a product is to display its price
Remember that in the previous episode,
we described a product
as being characterized by an attribute
of type double
corresponding to its base value,
and the class also contained a
public method
which calculated the
price of the product
and which, in the Produit class, simply
returned the base value.
In the Produit class, to make sure
that the toString method
displays a representation in the form
of a character string of the price of the product,
and we could thus be tempted
to display the price
by directly using the value of the
attribute, since we reason that
anyway, the price is just the base
value of the product.
This way of doing it, however,
is not the correct one.
Do you know why?
We want the toString method
as defined
in the Produit class to determine
the default behavior,
that is, it must be capable of
displaying the price,
the correct price of the product,
even if it isn't overridden
in the subclasses.
Yet the price of an object
corresponds to its base value
for a basic product, but this
is not necessarily
the calculation we would make for
sub-types of products.
For example, the price of a bracelet
could correspond
to a base value; however, the price
of a watch could be calculated
as being the sum of the price of
all its components.
And in that case, if we applied
the toString method to an object
of type Montre, we would want
the price of the watch to be displayed
correctly, and not some base value.
The correct way to proceed here
is thus to use, instead of valeur,
the prix method, which can of course
have a polymorphic
behaviour itself.
Finally, you will have noted that
here, we had to
convert the double returned by
prix to a string
using this syntax.
Now, let's finalize
our Produit class.
One of the first things that come
to mind naturally
is that a product does not exist as such
It is an abstract entity in
our implementation.
We can make this clear, at the
design level,
by labeling the Produit class
as being abstract.
Suppose that now, we wish to force the
fact that the value of a product,
once initialized, can not be changed
during the lifetime of a product.
So, the idea would be to give a
first value to this attribute
but not to allow it to be modified.
This is possible by
labeling the attribute
as being final.
If valeur had been an attribute
of type object, so
something else than a primitive data type,
would the act of labeling it as final
prevent any and all modification
of this attribute?
Suppose lastly that we wish to impose
that a product should have, by default,
a null base value: this can be done
by adding to the Produit class
a default constructor which
would take care of
initializing valeur to a null value.
Overloading, and specifically here
overloading constructors
is a rather common way of giving
default values
to certain parameters in Java.
So, this is what our Produit
class looks like in the end.
We have declared it as abstract
because we do not want
products to be instantiated as such,
they do not exist in that form:
a bracelet can be instantiated,
and so can a watch,
but not a product itself.
An instance of Produit is defined
by its base value.
We have labeled this attribute
as final, which means
that once it has been initialized
by one of the constructors,
we will not be able to
change its value.
So a product has a constant base
value during all its lifetime.
A product can thus be initialized
in two ways:
either using a constructor that takes
a base value as argument
that will be given to the attribute,
or using the default constructor,
in which case the base value
is set to zero.
Since we have these constructors,
would it be possible to write something
like this: declaring a variable of
type Produit,
and initializing it like this, for example?
The answer is of course no, since
this class is abstract
and thus cannot be instantiated.
These constructors will only
be used by constructors
of subclasses of Produit that can actually
be instantiated.
The Produit class contains an override
of the toString method inherited from Object,
and the goal of this is to be able
to use this toString method
in a polymorphic way, that is, to
be able to override it
in subclasses of Produit.
That said, it offers a default, basic
definition which consists in
displaying the price, converted
to a character string.
The price is calculated using another
polymorphic method,
that is, a method that we will
be able to redefine
in subclasses of Produit to
adapt to the actual nature
of the instance to which it belongs.
That way, when we call the
toString method on a Montre
stored in a variable of type Produit,
then the prix method of the Montre
object will be called
and the display of the
price will be correct.
This concludes our episode
on the definition of products
and their polymorphic display.