In the previous episodes,
the general case study problem
we are interested in
has been presented. It's about
modeling watches
with different mechanisms,
different accesssories.
Then we covered the more
specific problem
of polymorphic display.
We also completed the Produit class
(TN : means "Product").
In this episode, we will build
a first operational version
of our code,
by adding accessories to watches
and defining several of these
accessories.
Let's start with adding accessories
to the Montre class (TN: means "Watch" class)
which, remember,
inherits from Produit and
has a "Mécanisme" (= "Mechanism")
and especially, something that is
of interest to us now,
a dynamic array of accessories which
we called "Accessoire" (TN : means "Accessory")
The idea is that we want to be able to
add elements to this
dynamic array
by calling for example, on a watch,
instance of the Montre class,
Montre.ajouter, for example, a "new Bracelet"
(TN: "ajouter" means "add" and "Bracelet", "WatchStrap")
where, remember, "Bracelet" is
a subclass of Accessoire
And we want this to add a new
watchstrap
to the collection of accessories;
a "Bracelet" being an "Accessoire",
it can be added to a collection
of accessories.
Now, let's see how this "ajouter"
method can be defined.
Here, we will implement a
very very simple solution
which we will revise later on,
in the last episode in this series,
covering the concept of deep copies.
But for now, we simply make
a shallow copy here
by just adding a reference
to an accessory
that we received, to the dynamic
array of accessories
which is called "accessoires".
Now, let's try to make
a first operational version of the program.
So let's try to finalize what we
have written up until now.
And for now, let's not add
any mechanism
nor copy any watch; we will leave
these two points
for the next two episodes.
So, to be able to finalize the program
that we have written until now,
we will need a few more concrete
accessories.
We will have to finish the Montre class
which is not quite operational yet
and, of course, use all of this in
a typical "main" method.
We will take each of these points
one after the other
starting with a few accessories.
Remember that we have an "Accessoire"
class which is a "Produit"
And let's decide, say,
that at the accessory level,
we have a name to refer to them.
For this, we will say that
we have a name
which will not change once
it has been fixed
by the constructor.
And so we will add a constructor
to the Accessoire class
that will take a name, to name
this accessory.
Then, we mustn't forget that
any product can be sold
and will thus have a price. So
it will take a second parameter here
to initialize the base value for the
price of the product.
Accessoire's constructor will
start by calling
the constructor of the superclass, Produit,
passing it
the parameter valeurDeBase which we received.
(TN: "valeurDeBase" means "basisValue")
Then, we will initialize
the "nom" attribute with the name received.
(TN: "nom" means "name")
So, that's it for the constructor
that we decided to give to
all the accessories.
Now, let's decide on a way to display
the accessories because,
as we have seen
all products can be
displayed in a polymorphic way.
So we will override the
toString method here,
inherited from Produit.
As we have seen, we override it by adding
the "override" annotation here.
Let's say that, for example, it is
displayed with an indication
of its name and cost.
So we will simply display
the name
then indicate what it costs
-- and we already know how to
display the price --
by simply calling the method from
the Produit superclass.
So here, we use the "super" keyword
to call the method inherited
from the Produit superclass.
Because, of course, if we
only write toString
with no unmasking here,
it is the toString method
from the current class, and
we would have infinite recursion:
toString would call itself
and so, to call, within the toString
method of the Accessoire class,
the toString method
inherited from the Produit superclass,
we need to unmask this
toString method.
Finally, let's say that the
price of accessories
is the same as the price
of a normal product,
that is, a product
as we designed right at the
top of the hierarchy
and so now,
we don't have to do anything
since the prix method
that we inherited from
the Produit class
is enough here, and we don't
need to override
it in the Accessoire class.
So now, we have a completely
functional Accessoire class
that corresponds to what
we wanted.
So let's now define a few accessories
for example, a Bracelet (= "watchstrap")
A "Bracelet" is an "Accessoire"
so we have an inheritance relation here.
Regarding accessories,
let's say that we want
their name -- remember that
accessories have a name,
so every accessory will
inherit this name --
let's say that we want
each of the accessories to
have a name
that marks what it is, for example,
the name of a watchstrap will
start with "bracelet",
the name of a "Fermoir" will, for example,
start with "fermoir" (TN: means "clasp").
And so we will force this at
the constructor level
so for example, for the Bracelet
subclass
of the Accessory class, we will
receive the name
which will be a complement that
we will add here,
behind the word "bracelet".
So for example, "en cuir"
(TN: means "of leather")
for the complete name to be "bracelet en cuir"
(TN: means "leather watchstrap")
and as a second parameter the price,
which we also pass to the constructor
of the superclass.
So, in the same way, we could define
a Fermoir inheriting from Accessory
in which we would define a constructor
taking a complement to the Fermoir name
and a price to be able to call
the constructor
of the Accessoire superclass
where the full name will thus be
"fermoir" with this complement we
received as the first parameter
and as second parameter, the
price that we received,
and as always, the virtual destructor.
There, we have now finished
with accessories
Let's try to make the Montre
class usable,
without mechanisms and without
copy, still,
as we will treat those later.
At this stage, we have simply defined
the contents of the Montre class
in which we thus have this "ajouter" method,
which allows us to add accessories
to our watches.
Let's start by giving our Montre
class a constructor.
For now, let's settle for a
default constructor
that we will still override
since the "default default constructor"
would make this reference null,
where we would rather have an
empty dynamic array, here,
that we could then fill up with
our ajouter method
This is how Montre objects are constructed.
Now, let's decide how we want
to compute the price of watches
and let's say that it is the sum of the
prices of its accessories.
For this, we will override the
"prix" method:
We override this "prix" method inherited
from the Produit superclass.
So we will decide that, at first,
the price of a watch is the base price
that we get through the original
"prix" method
inherited from the Produit superclass.
Then, from this base price,
we will add
the sum of prices of the various
accessories.
For this, we go through the list
of accessories
and add their price to the
price that we had initialized,
by calling the "prix" method each time.
Finally, we return the price that
we have just computed.
Now, let's define how to
display watches.
For example, let's say that we
want a message
to say that a watch is composed of,
followed by a list of its various
accessories, etc.
Then, at the end, we display
the total price of the watch.
To do so, we will for example add an
"afficher" method (TN: "afficher" means "display")
in which we will start by displaying
"une montre composée de"
(TN: means "a watch composed of").
Then, we go through all of the
accessories of the watch.
For each of these accessories,
we display an asterisk
and then we display the
current accessory.
Finally, we end the display with the message
"prix total" (means "total price")
and a call to the "prix" method of the watch
to compute its total cost, as we
have just seen.
Next, to have an executable program,
we need a "main" function that we will
use here
to test the implementations of the
objects we have created.
And to do so, we will declare a watch
like this, in the main.
We can do this
because now, we have a default constructor.
Then, in the watch, we add different
accessories, like so.
Each of the accessories has
its own constructor,
with the name or the complement to the
name, then its price
This way, we add four accessories
for example
and finally, we display a message
to display the watch here.
And so executing this program will
yield the following result:
we will first display the message
"Montre m"
then, we will enter the afficher
method of Montre
which will display
"Une montre composée de: "
and then a loop over its
different accessories,
and then the display of its
total price,
which is the sum of prices of
its accessories.
For those who would like it,
the entire code is available
on the course's website
There, this ends the presentation
of this first operational
version of our code.
There are still two chapters to cover
in the next two episodes.
First, all of these mechanisms and their
dependencies, and the concept
of interfaces,
and finally the concept of
copying a watch,
how to make a deep copy of all the
different accessories of a watch.