Let's continue our case study
on watches.
The idea is to refine the model of
the different types of mechanisms used
in particular by including
the concept of interfaces.
As a reminder, in the
previous episodes,
the heart of a watch was
modeled as being a mechanism,
a mechanism that could take
on different forms;
we could have either
an analog mechanism,
a digital mechanism, or
a double mechanism
These three types of mechanism
all inherited from Mecanisme.
This first hierarchy, however, does not quite
correspond to our wishes
concerning modeling of
double mechanisms.
Indeed, we would like a double
mechanism
to be able to have
characteristics
from both analog mechanisms
and digital mechanisms.
Ideally, a double mechanism
should be able to inherit
from the MecanismeDigital class
as well as from the
MecanismeAnalogique class.
Unfortunately, multiple inheritance
does not exist in Java.
Suppose for example that
in the analog class
we have a attribute that is specific
to analog mechanisms
which would be the date
displayed by the mechanism
and that in the case of the digital
mechanism,
we have another attribute
which would be an alarm
linked to the digital mechanism.
Then, maintaining this inheritance link
would result in a duplication
of both attributes into
the double mechanism class
since we would effectively want
a double mechanism to have
the characteristics
of both of these classes
that is, having both an alarm
and a date.
We would end up in this situation
as would be the case
for all the methods
specific to analog mechanisms
and to digital mechanisms
which we would have to
review entirely
in double mechanisms.
Thus, we could decide that,
for example,
a double mechanism is an
analog mechanism
to which some characteristics
of digital mechanisms
would be added.
If we take this point of view,
we can prevent
duplication incurred by the
original conception of inheritance.
In this case, we would end up with
a hierarchy that would look
like this:
double mechanisms inherit
from analog mechanisms,
and for now there is no
direct link between
double mechanisms and
digital mechanisms.
We will correct this a little later on.
All the attributes specific
to analog mechanisms
and all the methods are thus
inherited by the MecanismeDouble class
which doesn't need to duplicate them.
However, since we cannot inherit fro
the MecanismeDigital class,
the characteristics of digital mechanisms
that we would like to see
in double mechanisms
must be duplicated.
The Java code that corresponds
to this first revision of the hierarchy
is as follows.
We have a Mecanisme superclass
which is derived from Produit and which
has two direct subclasses:
the MecanismeAnalogique class and
the MecanismeDigital class;
so we suppose, here, that our classes
for analog mechanisms
and digital mechanisms have
specific attributes:
a date, for analog mechanisms
and an alarm for digital mechanisms.
And we choose to consider
that a double mechanism
is first and foremost an analog mechanism
to which we add some characteristics
of digital mechanisms.
So here, the inheritance link between
double mechanisms
and analog mechanisms is established,
and we graft onto the MecanismeDouble
class some elements
that are characteristic of
digital mechanisms.
So here we are forced to duplicate
the reveil attribute (TN: "reveil" means "alarm").
Now, let's focus on construction
of the mechanisms:
programming constructors in a
class hierarchy
follows certain rules that we
will review now.
Let's start by defining how
we will construct mechanisms
-- up until now we only had a
default constructor --
and let's refine the description
of this constructor.
Given that a mechanism is a product,
meaning it inherits from the Produit class,
it must initialize the base value
of the product inherited from Produit
and it must initialize its own attribute,
that is, heure (TN: means "time").
So naturally, we could think
of a constructor for the Mecanisme
class that would look like this.
It would take as parameter a
value allowing
to initialize the attribute inherited
from Produit
and as second parameter,
a value
allowing to initialize its
own attribute.
The constructor of the Mecanisme class
must absolutely invoke
the constructor of the Produit
superclass
via this syntax.
If, during construction, we want to
assign a default value
to the heure attribute,
then we will do this
in the same way as we did
for the Produit class
by overloading the constructor.
That is, we define a second constructor
that would take no parameter
for the mechanism's time, but
that would initialize this attribute
with a specific value.
Now, let's work on the
constructors of the subclasses.
First, the constructor of the
MecanismeAnalogique subclass
for example, which inherits directly
from the Mecanisme class.
This constructor will take, as
parameters, values
allowing it to initialize
all of its attributes; those
inherited from higher up
and its own ones.
The constructor of the
MecanismeAnalogique subclass
must therefore also invoke
the constructor of the
Mecanisme superclass
always in the same way.
And the constructor of the
MecanismeDigital class
will be written in a very
analogous way.
One possible constructor for
the MecanismeDouble class
is a constructor allowing
the initialization of all
of its attributes,
those that are specific to it
such as the alarm here,
and those that are inherited from above.
We will inherit several attributes
from higher up:
the date, from MecanismeAnalogique,
the time from Mecanisme and
the base value from Produit.
This constructor for MecanismeDouble
will thus call the superclass's
constructor to initialize
the inherited attributes
and it will initialize its own attribute.
Now, let's focus on how the constructors
will handle default values.
Remember that when we
defined
the constructors of the
Mecanisme class,
we had provided the possibility of
constructing a mechanism
without supplying a time,
in which case the time
would have a certain default value.
And now, we want to know how
the constructors of the subclasses
can preserve this default value.
For example, we would like
to be able to
define a double mechanism without
giving it a time
and in that case, we would like
its heure attribute to have
the same default value
as the one that is intended
for simple mechanisms
and of course, we still want to have
the ability to initialize its own value
The solution, once again, relies
on overloading.
The overload would define
the constructor of the MecanismeDouble
class in a way that would allow it to
work without a value
for its heure attribute
It would then call the constructor
of the superclass
that is based on the same principle,
that is, a constructor that would not
require the time as a parameter.
This means that in the
MecanismeAnalogique
superclass,
there is a constructor that does not
require a parameter for the time.
and do you know what the first instruction
of this constructor will be?
The constructor of MecanismeAnalogique
will indeed invoke this constructor
of the Mecanisme superclass
which will initialize the default
time correctly
To conclude our discussion on
construction at this step,
remember that the Montre class has a
core attribute of type Mecanisme.
The constructor that we used up til now
was a default constructor
which simply initialized the
set of accessories
as an empty array
Now, we can provide a somewhat
more complete constructor
which would take as parameter a Mecanisme
that would be used to initialize
the core attribute
This way of initializing the core
using a reference to an object passed
as parameter to the constructor
is not very satisfactory.
We will come back to this
in the next episode
when we will cover deep copy.
Now we have finished with the
constructors for mechanism,
let's focus on displaying them.
Suppose that to do these displays,
we wish for all mechanisms
to be displayed following
the same model:
a model that is imposed and
cannot be modified.
This model would for example be
to systematically
display the mechanism's type
followed by displaying the dial
which would contain the time
and, when applicable,
the date, the time of the alarm,
all of this followed
by the price, for example
But we would also like
each of these parts,
each of the parts of this model to
be adaptable.
What we mean by part
would be for example the part that
displays the mechanism's type
the part that displays the dial.
This conception implies
that there is a general display method
for all mechanisms that follows
a precise model
but that this method calls other
methods
which could have a
dynamic behavior,
in a polymorphic way.
Therefore, the idea is to allow
these methods to have
a specific behavior
depending on the subclass, meaning
that, for example,
we would have a display method
for mechanisms that would be
specific to each subclass.
Similarly, we would have a method
for displaying the dial
that would be specific to each subclass
and, thanks to polymorphism,
it would be able to adapt automatically
to the real nature of the objects
for which it is called.
The fact that the same basic schema
is imposed for all mechanisms
implies that once these methods are
made to follow this fixed outline,
they must not be modified anymore.
This should make us think of
final methods.
We also want to make sure that
there exists a usable version
of the dial display
in the subclasses.
So this method should have
a default definition,
typically right at the top of the hierarchy,
in the Mecanisme class.
This default version could for
example simply
display the time and be used
in the subclasses
to display the time but also possibly
more information
So here, we are going towards
a method that would be
polymorphic for the display of the dial
but that would have a default
definition in the superclass.
However, to display the type
of mechanism,
we absolutely want
to force an override in subclasses,
which should make us think
of abstract methods here.
Here is how we can translate these
constraints into Java code
Our Mecanisme superclass provides a
polymorphic display method
which overrides the one inherited
from Product that displayed the price
our Mecanisme superclass therefore
provides a display method
that follows a precise schema
including displaying the type,
the dial and the price via
the method inherited from Produit
To make sure that this schema is
fixed once and for all
and cannot be overridden in a subclass
of the hierarchy,
we mark this method as "final".
Subclasses of Mecanisme will no
longer be able
to redefine the toString method. It is
declared as final.
However, they will be able to
redefine parts
of this schema, such as the display
of the dial for example,
or the display of the type,
which are polymorphic methods
which will be able to adapt
to the type of mechanism on which
they are called.
The method that displays the dial
according to what we
specified earlier has a
default definition
in the Mecanisme class.
There, it simply allows one
to display the time
We have decided to declare
it as protected
to allow subclasses to use this method
of their superclass.
There is no risk concerning
encapsulation here
since the toStringCadran method, which
allows us to generate a representation
of the dial,
does not modify internal details of
the mechanism.
However, we can consider
that the method
that displays the type of the mechanism
cannot really be defined at this
stage of the hierarchy.
This method will therefore
be defined as abstract.
The fact that we declare this method
as abstract
forces its redefinition in all of the
subclasses of Mecanisme
that we want to instantiate later on.
Any subclass of the Mecanisme class
that we want to be able to instantiate,
such as the MecanismeDigital class
for example,
will absolutely have to provide
an actual definition
for the method that displays
the type, as is the case here.
The MecanismeDigital sublcass
can of course also
override the method that handles
the dial's display.
And it can override this method
by using the method
inherited from above,
that is, the one that allows us
to display the time.
So here, displaying the dial of a digital
mechanism will display the time
as well as the alarm.
Displaying the alarm is also
handled through a method
but in this case, the method is specific
to the MecanismeDigital class.
It simply displays "réveil" followed
by the time of the alarm.
The MecanismeDouble class,
if it is do be instantiated,
which is the case,
must also imperatively
override the method handling
multiple display.
Since it has an alarm, whose value
we probably also
want to be able to display, we
must also define
the method that will allow us
to display the time of the alarm
in the same way as we did for
digital mechanisms.
And we can consider redefining
the method that handles the
display of the dial,
that is, the one that can display
information on the dial
inherited from MecanismeAnalogique,
specifically the time and the
date here.
And we would then display the
information pertaining to the alarm
through this specific method.
So as you can see, both the
MecanismeDouble class
and the MecanismeDigital class
contain methods that are used
to display information about the alarm
and do so in a completely analogous way.
However, there is no link
between the two.
It would be nice to clarify the link
between mechanisms
that have a digital behavior,
that is, MecanismeDouble and
MecanismeDigital in our case,
and to force mechanisms that
have this digital behavior
to implement these common methods
such as
the toStringReveil method that
handles the display
of information relating to the alarm.
And this leads us to a new revision of
our class hierarchy.
We can establish the link between
digital mechanisms
and double mechanisms via an interface,
which would force
subclasses that implement it
to implement the method that
handles the display
of information about the alarm.
So we can introduce the ReveilDigital
(TN: means "digital alarm") interface
and force all classes that would implement
digital characteristics
to provide a method allowing the display
of information concerning the alarm.
Our MecanismeDigital class
would implement this interface.
The same would go for the MecanismeDouble
class. And if we want to be able to
instantiate these two classes, they
must imperatively provide
an implementation of the
same method,
the method allowing the display of
information about the alarm.
In this model, the MecanismeDouble class
is mostly an analog mechanism
that would contain a certain number of aspects
of digital mechanisms,
that we can also find in the
MecanismeDigital class.
But it is forced to implement these
elements that are characteristic
of digital mechanisms due to the fact that
it implements the ReveilDigital interface.
Note that thanks to the introduction
of the interface,
the model is now clearer, more
understandable,
but we have not avoided code
duplication
that results from the lack of real
multiple inheritance in Java.
If these code duplications become
too common,
then this model that we based on
inheritance
would have to be reviewed, and
probably changed to have
a model using encapsulation.
For example, we could imagine
introducing a "DigitalFunctions" class
grouping all the common elements
from digital mechanisms,
and so each of the MecanismeDigital
and MecanismeDouble classes
would have an instance of this as
an attribute, for example.
If you paid attention to the
evolution of the code
in the previous slides,
you may have noticed that we modified
the access rights
of the toStringReveil method.
Do you know why?
There, this concludes the modelling
of our class hierarchy.
As usual now,
here is a small main program
allowing us to test the latest
additions.
These lines of code will allow us to
test the different constructors
of our subclasses, including
those that manage
unprovided, default values.
This constructor builds an analog
mechanism that has a base
value of 312,
a time that will take on
the default value,
that is, 12.0, and with this date.
And this call builds a double mechanism with
a base value of 543,
with an explicit initialization time of
8:20,
a date -- since it is a MecanismeDouble, it
inherits from MecanismeAnalogique
and thus has a date -- and an
alarm time.
The following lines will test
that the toString methods coded in
the different levels
were coded correctly.
We can now declare a watch with
a core
that corresponds to a specific mechanism
and we can, as we could earlier,
add accessories to this watch.
We can finalize the display method
by having it display its core too,
since we now have display methods
for our mechanisms
and this will allow us to display
an entire watch.
The code for this part can be downloaded
on the course website.
And this concludes this episode
on the modeling of mechanisms.