To conclude this case study
on watches,
we will focus on a particular
problem, namely
how to copy watches.
We are not talking about counterfeiting,
but introducing
a new theme, interesting in programming,
which is "deep copying".
Let's define the problem concretely.
You have a watch, and your
friend wants the same one.
We have learned all along this course
that assignment in Java
does not actually make a copy as such.
If I write "montreToto = maMontre"
(TN: could be translated: "totosWatch = myWatch")
I am simply assigning the reference to
"maMontre"
to the "montreToto" variable.
So basically,
"maMontre" and "montreToto"
point to the same object in memory.
This means that if a watch provides
a method
for setting the time, for example,
then whenever I set a time on my watch,
I will also modify Toto's time;
a rather unexpected behavior, indeed!
Therefore, we need a mechanism
that will allow us
to truly copy a watch.
Let's try to see how we can
implement this
using a copy constructor.
A watch is a relatively complex
object
that includes a core attribute
of type Mecanisme
and a list of accessories.
So, when I declare an object
of type "Montre",
initialize it and add, for example,
accessories like this,
I end up with a memory situation
which looks like this,
where my variable 'm', of type "Montre",
is a reference
to an object of type "Montre",
that has a "coeur" attribute (TN: means "core"),
which is a reference to an object,
for example of type "MecanismeDouble",
and whose second attribute is a
reference to a dynamic array
containing references to accessories.
When I build a watch by copying 'm',
what situation do I want to
end up in?
If I simply copy "m" into "m2"
by copying the different attributes
one by one,
then the "coeur" of "m2" will have the
same value as the "coeur" of "m",
which means that it will point to the
same object in memory,
and for the accessories of "m2",
I will have
a reference to the same array
Here, we end up with a problem similar
to the previous one,
since the "m" and "m2" objects share the
same array of accessories in memory:
if we add an accessory to m's array,
we will add it to m2's array as well.
Similarly, setting the time on m's mechanism
will set the time on m2's mechanism.
To have two objects of type Montre that
have the same values
but that are totally independant,
we must implement what is called
a "deep copy".
The situation in which we want to end up
is rather the following:
we want m2 to have
its own "coeur"
which would be identical...
to that of m,
but in a separate memory area,
and a set of accessories which would
also be its own
and whose values would point
towards identical objects
that are nonetheless in their own
memory area.
This is what we call "deep copying".
If we write a copy constructor
for Montre
that would simply assign to the core
of the current instance
the core of the copied object,
and if we do the same thing for
the accessories,
we do what is called a "shallow copy"
which, as we learned earlier
will, as opposed to deep copy,
simply allow both watches to share
the same core
and to share the same list of
accessories;
this way of doing things is not satisfactory
[for our current situation].
Here, we should really make
a deep copy
of each of the entities we mentioned
earlier,
meaning that we should assign to
the core of the current instance
a new mechanism built based on
the copied core
and we should build a new
list of accessories
where each accessory, added to the list,
would be a copy of the corresponding
accessory in the copied object.
Here, we would iterate over the list of
accessories of the copied object
and we would create a copy of each of
these accessories
to be put into the new list.
However, we have a problem here.
Indeed, to get a copy of the core,
since [the attribute] "coeur" is of type "Mecanisme",
we used the copy constructor of the
"Mecanisme" class.
Actually,  "autre.coeur"
(TN: means "other.core")
might very well be
a "MecanismeDouble".
In such a case, it's indeed
a "MecanismeDouble"
that we want to obtain for "coeur".
Can the copy constructor of "Mecanisme"
produce a "MecanismeDouble"?
The answer is no!
Because, as we discussed
in the corresponding lectures,
constructors are inherently
non-polymorphic.
The copy constructor of the "Mecanisme"
class will thus not be able to adapt
to the actual type of the instance
that it is trying to copy
Thus it will only see the object to copy
as a Mecanisme,
and will only copy the part of it that
is a Mecanisme
So anything that is specific to
MecanismeDouble will disappear.
There will be no date and no alarm clock then.
So, the question that arises is:
how do we copy each element,
be it an accessory or a mechanism,
as such?
Meaning that, if it is a
MecanismeDouble,
it will be copied as a MecanismeDouble.
If it is a "Bracelet" (TN: means "Watchstrap"),
it will be copied as a "Bracelet".
So, how do we implement this
polymorphic copy?
To carry out a polymorphic copy,
we cannot resort to
copy constructors,
as we have just seen,
but we simply need to use a method that
can, itself, be polymorphic.
The idea would thus be to define
a polymorphic copy method that would
allow us to copy mechanisms
and a polymorphic copy method
allowing us to copy accessories.
Let's see exactly how  we can write
a polymorphic copy method,
for accessories for example,
and we will be able to apply the same
thing to mechanisms,
and this procedure will allow
us to really implement
deep copy,
in a way that will allow us to obtain
a copy of the object to be copied
that is completely independant
from this object.
Finally, an aspect that I did not mention
up til now but that is important
is that when we write a copy constructor,
it is crucial not to forget to call
the copy constructor of the superclass
Otherwise, if we forget this call,
what will happen?
Then, the default constructor for
Montre's superclass,
that is, for the "Produit" class,
will be invoked
This constructor will initialize the
base value of the object to 0;
which means that any watch that is
made with a copy
would have a base value of zero,
which is not necessarily what we want.
Now, let's see how we can code
a polymorphic copy method
for accessories
An accessory as such is
an abstract entity,
we will not define a copy for
accessories themselves,
so we will simply define the
copy method
as an abstract method in the
"Accessoire" class.
In each concrete subclass of
"Accessoire",
we will have to define
the copy concretely
and the trick here
is that the polymorphic copy method,
in the subclass, can use
the subclass's copy constructor to carry
out the copy
Suppose, here, that an object of
type "Accessoire"
is copied using the copy method,
and that it happens that in reality,
this object corresponds to a "Bracelet".
The memory situation would
be as follows:
we have the object that we
want to copy,
which is a reference to an object
of type "Bracelet"...
which would have, for example,
a base value,
as well as a name...
so when we call the copy method
the current object is this object;
since it is an object of type "Bracelet",
we will look for the copy method in the
"Bracelet" class,
which will invoke the copy constructor
of the "Bracelet" class.
Here we copy a "Bracelet", so there
is no problem
in using the copy constructor to
copy a "Bracelet".
And this constructor will simply call
the superclasses' constructors
to initialize the name inherited
from "Accessoire"
and to initialize the value inherited
from "Produit".
This supposes that there is
a copy constructor
in the "Accessoire" class,
which could be written like this
for example:
the copy constructor for the
"Accessoire" class
would take as argument...
another accessory, of course!
It would call the copy constructor
of the superclass,
which would be the copy constructor
for the "Produit" class
and it would copy the values
that are specific to it...
given that an accessory has an
attribute that is the name.
This supposes that in the superclass
of "Accessoire",
that is, in the "Produit" class,
there is also a copy constructor.
This one will simply copy
the base value
We would proceed in a similar fashion
to define the polymorphic copy
of "Mecanisme".
Finally, a point that might have
caught your attention
is that if we examine the header of the
copy method in the "Bracelet" subclass
and its header in the "Accessoire"
superclass,
we realize that the return types are
not exactly the same.
That said, this is still
an override of the copy method inherited
from the superclass
Why?
Because the return types are
compatible;
"Bracelet" is a subclass of "Accessoire".
Technically, this is known as a
"covariant return type".
To finish with this part on copying,
let's go back to the constructor
of the "Montre" class.
We had originally programmed it to
take a "Mecanisme" as a parameter
and to assign this "Mecanisme"
directly to the "coeur" of the "Montre".
If the "Mecanisme" object can
be modified,
this can cause what is called
an "encapsulation leakage".
Imagine for example that we have
an object of type "Mecanisme"
that is properly initialized
such as this for example.
If we use this "Mecanisme"
to create a "Montre"
like so,
then the "meca" variable
and the "coeur" of the "Montre"
reference the same object in memory.
If the "meca" object can be modified,
meaning that if there is a method
that we can call on this object to
modify it,
imagine for example we have
a method
for setting the mechanism's time,
then when I set the mechanism's
time, I will also set
the time for the core of the watch.
Indeed,
the "meca" variable has a reference
to an object in memory
that would be a "MecanismeDouble".
'm', which is a watch,
which is a reference to an object
of type "Montre",
and whose core would be the reference
to the same object
as the one pointed to by "meca".
Suppose that at the moment the "Montre"
object was created,
the "meca" object had a time which
was the following,
and suppose that "Mecanisme" provide
a setting method,
meaning that it would be possible
for example
to set the time of the mechanism
by using
this sort of syntax, for example.
Then this would mean that the
time of the mechanism is modified,
and this would mean that the
watch's time would also be modified.
It is important to always be
mindful of this aspect
when writing constructors that
take objects as parameters,
if these objects can be modified, unless
we really want to share them,
meaning that the sharing behavior
is actually intended.
We must think of assigning a copy
of the object passed as a parameter
to avoid undesirable side effects
such as the fact that we can set the
watch's time
through an outside object here,
which is indeed an encapsulation leakage.
So here, typically, we would
use the polymorphic copy of "Mecanisme"
to get a "coeur" that is independent
from the initial mechanism
and to avoid this sort of side effect.
Note that a similar problem arises with
the "ajouter()" method
which provides a way to add
accessories to a watch.
Indeed, if the "ajouter()" method receives
a reference to an accessory
as a parameter,
here, accessories can be modified,
for example, there would be a method
for repairing accessories
that would allow us to modify some
of their values,
then in this case, the same problem
would arise
and we would want to add to our
set of accessories...
a copy of the accessory that
was passed as a parameter
to make sure that our watch's
accessories
do not depend on an accessory provided
from the outside and that can be modified.
Finally, and you might have been
wondering about that for a while,
what about the "clone()" method
inherited from the "Object" class
that is supposed to copy objects?
Actually, we could have called our
polymorphic copy method
"clone" instead of "copie".
If we had called it "clone",
we simply would have had to follow
a few conventions
such as the fact that classes
that define or override the
"clone()" method
should implement a specific interface
which is the "Cloneable" interface.
There are a number of other
technical details
associated to the use of "clones"
according to Java conventions.
We deliberately ignored these aspects
partly because "clone" is far from being
widely-accepted among developers,
-- it is a controversial subject --
but mostly because we want to
focus the discussion
on the theme of deep copy itself,
as you might see it
in other programming languages.
This concludes this case study,
and thus this course.