Hi, in this module I'd like to talk about
the link between waste management and
climate change. I'm quite sure that
you're familiar with the climate change
challenge, but here just a reminder as a
small repetition. Global warming and
climate change
refers to an increase in average global
temperatures with various human activity
as the main cause for this.The increase
in average global temperature is caused
primarily by increases in greenhouse
gases, as shown here on the right.
Predominantly carbon dioxide but also
other gases, such as methane, nitrous
oxide and other fluorinated industrial
gases, which are however less relevant in the
waste management discussion. What you see
in this list, is also this number, showing
how much more this gas would warm the
earth over a hundred year period as
compared to carbon dioxide. So, methane
is 25 times as potent as CO2 and nitrous
oxide even 298 times more potent.
What is done in this
whole greenhouse gas discussion, is to
relate these different gases to CO2,
using this number. And the unit is then
tons of CO2 equivalents. Besides the gases
research has also identified another
substance that can have a large impact
on climate and its relevance to the
waste management sector. This is called
black carbon, which are small black
particles in the atmosphere, resulting
from incomplete combustion of biomass.
Black carbon has been recognized as an
important short lived
climate pollutant. Black carbon is not
yet included in the whole emission
quantification as there is yet no good
or agreed metric to compare black
carbon with other greenhouse gases. As
mentioned, black carbon is a typical
result of burning waste. This whole issue
of black carbon is clearly a topic of
growing interest, which in future will
need much more attention and research.
Now, let us have a look, how different
countries and how the waste sector
contributes to global greenhouse gas
emissions. This infograph of the World
Resources Institute allows you to look
at different countries and sectors
contributing to greenhouse gas emissions.
The inner circle differentiates between
the top 10 countries and the others.
The countries are then shown in the middle
section with the top 10 shown in colors.
Finally, the outer circle shows the
emission contributions by sector. First,
we shall click on Indonesia, shown here
in bright red. The total CO2 equivalent
emissions are 760 tons,
as shown in the grey bar above.
While the waste emissions are 69 tons, so
the contribution of the waste sector is
8%. Why don't you google this infograph
and search for your own country in the
list and the emissions contribution of
the waste sector. Compare this with other
countries and share your views on this in our forum.
In the global average, the
waste sector including wastewater
contributes only 3-5%
of the global greenhouse gas emissions.
This is mainly through methane emissions
from landfills, methane and nitrous
oxide from wastewater and some minor CO2
and nitrous oxide from burning of fossil
carbon. However, experts agree that this
contribution is severely underestimated
because certain
aspects of waste management are not
considered. For instance, the contribution
of recycling or of reducing transport of
waste through recycling. It has been
estimated at around ten to twenty
percent of global greenhouse gas
emissions could be reduced by the waste
management sector. This can be by
projects that recover landfill gas to
either flare it or convert it to
electricity or by methods adapting the
landfill management. For instance,
landfill aeriation to avoid methane
generation or also by utilizing cover
soil as a way to reduce methane
emissions from landfills through the
methane
oxidizing effect of soil bacteria. Here
is an example of landfill gas recovery
and electricity production from South
Africa. On the left, you can see the
landfill in its early stages being filled,
and on the right, the infrastructure
where the collected landfill gas is
transformed to electricity.
In the background of the picture on the right
you can see the final landfill cells
with soil and grass cover. Other
greenhouse gas mitigation measures are
avoiding disposal in landfills either by
composting anaerobic digestion or
thermal processes. Here is not only the
effect of meeting avoidance that play a
role but also the substitution of other
resources. For composting, this is
substitution of chemical fertilizer
which are energy intense in their
production. Or for anaerobic digestion
and combustion it may be the
substitution of fossil fuel energy
resources.
Finally, in addition also waste
minimization recycling and reuse
represent an important and increasing
potential for indirect reduction of
greenhouse gas emissions through the
conservation of
raw materials and fossil fuel avoidance.
Any government or individual company is
free to choose how they will reduce
emissions. One mechanism is that they
purchase emission reduction credits or
allowances from other sources, for
instance from waste management project
in low and middle income countries, which
have mitigated emissions of CO2
equivalents. They're different schemes
that help regulate and control these
emission reduction units. The clean
Development Mechanism CDM is a
market-based mechanism under the Kyoto
Protocol where projects in developing
countries can earn carbon credits
equivalent to the amount of CO2 they
have reduced or avoided. These credits
can then be used by industrialized
countries to meet a part of their
emission reduction targets. This is what is
called the compliance market based on
the Kyoto Protocol agreements of each
country. CDM has registered methodologies
on how emission reductions are calculated,
but also standardized and monitored and
also verified as these for their registered
projects before issuing the certified
emission reduction units. Similarly the
carbon finance unit of the World Bank
uses money by governments and companies
in OECD countries to purchase carbon
credits, generated by projects in low- and
middle-income countries. Finally, there is
also a voluntary market, which uses other
certification measures and standards to
issue voluntary emission reduction units.
Waste related projects account for
approximately 18% of all CDM projects.
Since the beginning of CDM, around 200
municipal solid waste project have been
registered worldwide. However, nearly 90%
of registered solid waste
projects involve landfill gas flaring
and recovering.
And most of these projects have been
submitted by middle-income countries.
the lowest income countries have generally
not yet
benefitted from this mechanism. Here is an
example from the Doña Juana
landfill in Bogota Colombia. It is one of
the largest Clean Development Mechanism
projects in Latin America. The project
started in 2009 and was 100% operational by
the end of 2010. For the period of
January to June 2015, the emission
reduction amounted to 340000 tons
of CO2 equivalent.
Total greenhouse gas emission reduction
is estimated to be 14.8
million tonnes of CO2 equivalent over
the entire 22 year life of the
project. After the climate conference in
Bali in 2007, a new concept was
introduced: the nationally appropriate
mitigation action NAMA. This refers to a
set of policies and actions that
country's undertake as a voluntary
commitment to reduce greenhouse gas
emissions. It recognizes that different
countries may take different actions
depending on their respective
capabilities. It also emphasizes the need
of financial assistance from developed
countries to developing countries, to
reduce emissions. It can include a wide
range of actions: policies, strategies,
research or development, even training
and capacity development, and of course
projects. So, let me summarize what we
have covered in this module. We have
talked about greenhouse gas emissions, in
general but specifically also from waste
management. We've talked about how
greenhouse gas emissions can be reduced,
either by landfill gas recovery or
diversions from landfills or waste
minimization recycling
and reuse. We looked at different carbon
trading measures, specifically at the
clean development mechanisms, with one
example from Bogota, Colombia and we looked
towards the future with the new
mechanisms such as NAMA. Thank you for
listening.