Hello Jorge!
Hello professor Maria do
Rosario, it is a great pleasure to be
here to talk about the study
that was conducted in Mozambique.
Very well. Let us now
start by describing
precisely the context
in which this study was carried out.
We will talk a little about the
characteristics of the
region where the study was conducted.
Well, the study was done
in Mozambique, so
in the Central region of the country.
It is therefore a region which has a
high prevalence of
malaria, and the study  was conducted
in two
provinces, that beyond
the high prevalence of
malaria, also are characterized by being located in
rural settings where
the sanitation system
is not very good.
So access to a
health facility is
relatively low,
in other words, people,
the population, have travelled
huge distances to
have access to
basic health services.
Very well. So let's now
move to the next phase.
I imagine that before
these new  startegies
were implemented,  a situation anlysis was conducted
with various actors,
and that it reached some conclusions.
So tell us a bit about
how this was done
and what were the
main problems that were
raised in this analysis?
Well, a situational analysis
was conducted involving
various stakeholders,
including the health ministry
and its offices
at the local and
district level, so in addition to
these actors, there were also
health partners involved,
as well as non-governmental
organisations (including one to which
I belong, which is called World
Vision), and there was also the
involvement of
community leaders,
and community structures,
such as actors
actively involved
in the process
of distribution of mosquito nets.
Okay, so what were the
main conclusions reached?
Well, during this
situational analysis,
three main conclusions
stood out. The first is
related to the actual
process of
household registration, so
one of the key steps is to
register all families
that exist in that
area, and it was noted that
this process was highly
complex, with the registration forms
for registration of households
requiring various details
related to the
household, such as
for example, the name of each
household member,
age, gender ... This
made things a little difficult,
making the registration process very complex.
The other issue related
to the registration itself had
to do with the fact that there is
the possibility of duplicate
household registrations
because the houses were not
identified, and/or conversely,
it was also possible
that a particular household was not registered
And the second important
aspect of the
situation analysis
relates to the process of
allocating mosquito nets
for each family,
which was complex. It required a
rather complex manner of
distribution of the net
per household, and finally
there was also the need to
evaluate the distribution process itself,
reaching the conclusion that
people were spending
a long, long time
queuing to get
their mosquito nets.
So the issue of
registration of these households,
the long queues,
and the
criteria for allocation of
number of mosquito nets per household were
the three key aspects that
stood out in this situation analysis.
I therefore imagine that for this
process to be implemented,
several stages are needed.
I would like you to tell us a little
about all these stages
that took place, that have thus been
developed so that
the new strategies
could finally be implemented.
Well, the very
process of distribution of
mosquito nets has several
stages and in the first stage
it was necessary to build the
capacity of health authorities,
so that
district staff are
trained. They, in turn,
after this training
would replicate the
training itself to others
at the district level,
in order to strengthen
the district team.
Community leaders were also involved,
they were selected
for a particular locality place
in the  region or  neighbourhood,
and the volunteers for
the registration process
of household were selected in the same way.
It was important to mobilize people from the
community, because they are
better  accepted  and the
households open up
their doors easily
to them,
trust them more.
And these registrars -
they are called registrars - are
trained too,
they provide
coupons and a
sticker to identify
the homes that have been registered,
and coupons ensure that
at the end, the families go
to a certain distribution point
and receive a
number of nets
and all this information is then
compiled and the date of
distribution is registered
at the closest distribution point
for that community, and
families go there with
coupons and take the mosquito nets
and these are
generally the
stages of the
distribution process
with the new model.
From what I understood, this new
model has three innovative aspects, is that right?
On the one hand,  the
mechanisms for assigning the number of
nets per family is simplified, while
on the other hand, a coupon is introduced in the
process  that ensures
a more accurate identification of the
families when they
get their nets, so
the long queues are no more present.
And on the other hand,
also the fact of having a
sticker meant that
there were no such
over-registrations or
under-registrations of households, is that it?
It was, it was
All right, you already told us
about these three innovative aspects,
but I am sure people  who are listening to us
are curious,
about the way it works and
this new distribution .
Can you explain in more
detail then the format
of the coupon and the information
that was in this coupon and also what
is the main  difference that
exists between the
old method that was more
complex,  namely because
of distribution of nets to families
was  based on a complex, formula
and now this new method
that is much simpler?
Can you explain then
why it is so important to provide guidance,
why these are the
most important strategies of your study?
Exactly. So the coupon
has the two parts,
the part  on
the left side of the coupon, which
stays with the registrars
and the team involved in
the process of distribution, and
on the aprt on the right side
given to the family, it has
basic information about the
address of the household,
so basically the
residence, residential area
the number of household
members, this is very
important because the
first changes were made
in order to allow a
net to be assigned for each
household and
basically the formula was the number of
household members
divided by two and
rounded up
to a integer number.
This is the new method, isn't it?
And what was the previous method like, can you explain?
The old formula would,
after harvesting data about
the age, gender, and
number of members
of the household,
try to find out the sleep patterns
so that
a family, for example,that
is composed of
three household members
may receive
one net, two nets,
or three nets. For
example, with the old model of
distribution, a
family with a father,
a mother and a two-year-old child
would receive one net because
it was assumed that
they all slept together.
However, if in this
family the child was ten
years old, they would receive
two nets because the father and
mother would sleep together and
the son would sleep separately.
However if this family
had a father,
a grandfather,
and another child who is twenty years old,
it would not be possible for the father
to sleep in the same space,
in the same bed, as, say, the
grandfather and also the son
who is twenty years old, they would have
had to receive three mosquito nets.
So there were three
situations for the same situation, three
possibilities for the allocation of
mosquito nets for the
same
household composition.
This is changing with the new
approach so it is
simply the number of
households divided
by two, with the
aim of having a mosquito net
for every two persons.
The innovation was alos in the coupons and the stickers , the stickers
had basic information
so in terms of
location of the
neighbourhood, of the community and
informing that the
house was already registered.
And it was attached to the main door
of the house, the hut,
I think the best example
is the hut, which is
the rural context of the
communities where we worked and
tested the new model.
So when the
supervisors of the registration
process came to a
particular community and saw that
there were houses that did not
have the sticker already, we could
assume in principle that in fact
these homes were not registered.
So it was already
easier to deploy a specific team
to that community for
the registration of those families.
Thank you very much. So
now that we have spoken, no?
about this new strategy
that was used, let's talk a
little bit about the study design. OKt?
So we have talked about
the research question and now
we know that for the  specific research
question  there is a research design
more suitable, no?
We therefore need to talk a little bit
about the research design.
Okay. For this study you
use a resaerch design with a qualitative
component and
a quantitative component.
A qualitative
study was conducted at each
phases of the project, therefore
for the process of
delivery of mosquito nets
we conducted focus groups
with key actors.
And the goal was to try
to reap as much information
about how it had happened,
in that particular
phase, or all phases,
the pros and cons of
each stage,
in order to be more adequate the
interventions. In the quantitative component,
the study was
a
quasi experimental  study
in where we had a district that was
an intervention district
in which the new model
for distribution was followed,
so a net for every two
persons, use of
coupons, use of stickers
for the identification
of the houses, while
having a control group.
So the district with the
control rules, that had
the previous intervention techniques,
so those complex
registration criteria, and rules for allocation
of mosquito nets
per household.
We tried as much as possible to have
something comparable from one district
to the other, so
in terms of rural
characteristics and even
in terms of the people
who are benefiting or
would benefit from mosquito nets.
Okay, one question
I wanted to ask is that
in this qualitative study, or rather,
in the qualitative part of the study,
focus groups with key actors were conducted and
then came to a conclusion.
You then change the
process according to
what people had stated?
Can you give an example?
It was noted that the
characteristics of the coupons
that had been made
were not most appropriate and
resistant, taking into account
where the family
would store the coupons.
Consequently in the next district where
the pilot study was  going to be conducted,
we improved
the quality of the coupons,
a bit more.
And this was, for example,
one of the lessons
that we could quickly
recognize as positive factor
for the successful implementation and applied it
in another intervention district.
Very well. We're almost
coming to an end, no?
And now  that we have defined
the strategies?
that we have  already  presented  the
research design,
It is time to test the new model and as we will see
we already have some results.
Can you tell us a little about
just what has been
done on this pilot study,
and what were the
main conclusions
reached in this study?
First in terms of
outcomes used to measure
the results of this
study.
First
the percentage of mosquito nets
distributed  when compared
to what was planned. And  also
to the coverage of nets
in the households,
in families.
And what we observed,  the result
of the implementation , was that after five
days, so
in the first calculation, the first
result, the
percentage of mosquito nets
distributed using the new
distribution model
was higher compared to
the previous model.
With the new approach it was 88%
against 77% in the control model.
And this difference was
statistically significant, no?
This difference was
statistically significant, yes.
Regarding the coverage of
households in terms of
mosquito nets in households,
at the end
of the five days,
which is the period of
implementation of distribution of
mosquito nets, there was a
difference between the
group, the district where
the new model was implemented,
and the district
with the previous mode.
so in the new model with innovative strategies,
the coverage was
greater, about 81% in relation to
the coverage in the district with the
previous model, which was 73%.
And this difference was also
statistically significant.
Yes, there is just one more thing I want to say,
to ask: when
did this study  took place.
It is important to have the
time-frame in which this study was conducted?
So the study
took off last year,
so in 2015.
In 2015 in the period from October to
December 2015,
and results  already available in
in
January for detailed analysis
And now we need to follow the next steps.
True. What are the
next steps?
These results  were presented to the
Ministry of Health and to various
sectors  involved in
the distribution process in the
provinces and districts concerned.
And the  Ministry of Health
has adopted this new
strategy for a
massive distribution process
of nets at national level.
Which in the first phase will be
an implementation on a
wide scale so
northern provinces of
Mozambique, in particular
the Nampula province which will
be held  in 2016.
Okay. So thank you
all for being here
today, to close this  part of module 3.
I hope you
enjoyed it and see you soon!