Spaces, from local to global
and specialities produced
by both small and big actors
combining in creating a powerful
component of social words
we can call geographicity.
As this dimension
and efficience specificity
to justify the use of a special
language different from the others
Of course, social sciences
of space commonly use
verbal and mathematical languages
or all the classical
communication tools.
However, geography as a special
language talking about space
occupies a unique position
in the cluster of these courses
be them scientific or not that deal
with the inhabited space.
That is why we logically decided
to devote an entire session to maps.
For this exploration, that will also be
an initiation to cartographic practice
we have invited Dr. Patrick Pense
with both brilliant theoretician and
active practitioner in cartography
to bring us his ideas.
we will speak about maps.
which cannot be understood
in a simple and unequivocal manner.
what cartography
has to do with geography.
Besides, geography and
cartography are often confused,
that is to say the scientific expert
with the technical artist.
between the two professions,
between science and technology,
a relationship which seems obvious,
does not fit well with the
diversity of representations
which can be designed under
the generic term of “map”.
This session could doubtlessly shed light
upon the logics of these intricacies,
perhaps better than a definition of
the map which may be hasty and simplistic.35
and without excessively normative ambitions,
that we can content ourselves to start off
with a simple definition of the map:
A graphical representation of space
which does not play upon
effects of perspective,
thus which has no foreground
nor background.
may be surprising.
It combines a great
functional openness
and a single condition
concerning its style,
that is, no depth, which most often
leads to a zenithal viewpoint,
that is to say, from above.
and creative practice
but which can also mobilise
specific and codifiable techniques.
In brief, it is an art
more than a mechanical action.49
should be nevertheless added
to this first definition,
for the issue of cartography
is the production of stable,
transmittable images which escape their creators’
influence to sometimes be interpreted
contrarily to their original meaning.
a singular geographical thought,
just like any text, table, graphic
or other basis of linguistic expression.
the fact that it renders a thought
tangible and real,
has otherwise a feedback effect
ultimately giving it its true importance.
It fixes an image of space and,
from this fact, it conditions
geographical thought and spatial action,
which end up by conforming to it.63
within the confines of this session,
it is however possible,
and perhaps even useful
to present the major issues
and great principles
of cartography in
an organised manner.
geography from cartography,
identifying their respective scientific
and technological logics,
in view of improving
your geographical thinking
and your spatial intelligence.
So that you do not take the maps
and theoretical relationships
uniting and distinguishing
geography from cartography.
If they share the concept of
distance as a common point,
they each give it
a slightly different,
although compatible, content.
how to move from a geographical idea
to a cartographic project.
more concretely approach
the steps of making a map:
on the primary matter of
the map and its treatment.
four simple and general principles
for making maps.
from the point-of-view of a creation
inserted into a rich and
complex communication system.88
and differs from a text
in that verbal expression
is often secondary,
is not immediately obvious.
To the contrary, it constitutes the central
issue and object of cartographic work.
It is this issue which defines the cartographic genre,
which is very specific,
despite its variations.97
is the absence of perspective.
It is by this detail that the map
can be distinguished from landscapes,
which are the other great tradition in spatial representation.
On a map, all of the visual
objects are deemed to be
at the same distance
from the observer.
Their size or shape do not depend upon
the point-of-view or the position
in the geographical scene represented.
Two places with the same spatial
importance are represented in the same way.
allows for a very great variety of forms,
and only serves to specify
the genre “map”.
a normative approach must not mask
the fundamentally practical
character of cartography.
A character common to technologies,
in contrast to sciences.
that which is most important is communicational efficiency.
on a terrestrial globe
is affected by
a perspective effect.
for a globe do not play upon this effect.
The cartographic work of making globes
is above all a cartographic task.116
in reality be distinguished the three “Occupations”
corresponding to the
three principle types of maps.
Every real map principally pertain to
one of these three types,
but can borrow some
distinctive secondary
traits from the two other types. 121
or for example a topographical map
are instrumental maps.
or in preparation for this use,
in a sort of simulation.
the “traditional” map,
which requires great technical
skill in its preparation.
It is work for professional cartographers,
who manipulate and localisedata.
These maps are decoded more than read,
the decoding being permitted by the legend,
which is an essential component of these maps.
denotation is more important than connotation. 132
which we may call “mapdesign”.
it produces “cartographies”.
By balancing connotation and
denotation in its expression,
MapDesign seems more like
a tongue than a code.
It multiplies the internal references
in the universe of the map,
as well as external references,
with other graphical universes.
MapDesign is the
cartographic domain of spaces
more than that of data.
That is to say the domain of spatial objects
that it has complex and complete objects.
acquire the status of objects,
including in the concrete and
material sense of the term.
They are largely autonomous objects,
which are the work of true authors.  144
is that practiced by anyone,
when a quick and practical
drawing of a space
is worth more than
an involved explanation.
It is the cartography of non-cartographers.
we speak of a “photo” to distinguish
popular art from professional
and artistic “photography”.
Neither instruments, nor even objects,
these cartos are media.
In reality they express spatialities
rather than spaces,
that is to say actions and capacities
of a project inscribed into a space.
For this, they have recourse to what may be called a language
- such as a computer language -
that is to say a simplified
and purified language,
which is minimally structured, often created
on the go, borrowing from a number of
existing or implicit
conventions between speakers,
and a minimalist denotation.
That is to say that it has very little
for a legend, or simply explained orally,
and economical graphical means.161
a total mastery
over the three forms of cartographic expression which we have just presented.
However it must be recognised that cartographic production
can give results only within one or another
of these three communicational “poles”.
about communication.
Even if it is only a dialogue with oneself,
it is still about communicating. 167
cartography leaves lots of room
for creativity, and the message
must be sensitive to the context.
That which is technique
in cartography is thus not
an ensemble of automatic rules,
but rather means at one’s disposal
to concretise the image of a space,
or the principles for its construction,which one has in mind into a geographical form.
in the sense that it cannot be resumed
to techniques or recipes,
but is first of all based on an intention,
and it develops an assumed statement
more-or-less effectively according to the
mastery over the technique at its disposal.178
the business of cartographers.
It can be practiced with
as much effectiveness, or even more,
by someone who has put in the effort of thinking
carefully about the means at their disposal
or that he can create
to express a spatial idea.
of the application
of automatic treatment
to geographic information,
but only the result of good suitability,
and often good compromises
and the means of its expression.
It is the logic of the image
which is important.
it is a good map.
to cartography has two goals.
from dependency on ready-made maps,
and at least be able
to criticise their implicit logics.
This simple criticism of maps
has already and often
served as a means for
entering into a spatial reflection.
the fact that the person
who thinks about space
he uses to make it.
Mistaking the map used can lead to mistaking ourselves about the space used.
In brief it runs the risk of mistaking
the geography and in short
making mistakes in
the spatial action taken.
It could lead to mistaking the path to take,
as well as mistaking the urban development plan
or the commercial conquest of the world.200
uniting cartography and geography
is an incitation to deepen
that which composes it.
if the expression of geographical ideas requires a certain cartographic mastery,
upon what is this relationship founded,
and until what point does it go ? 205
and geographic space alike?
Can maps really be counted upon
to think about space? If yes,
until what point are they useful?