a hypothesis
could be made about
the manner of reading it.
Let us grant that
a map’s reading proceeds
through a series of eye motions
where it zooms in and out.7
could be conceived as that
of conditioning the back-and-forth
motions of the eye by the image itself,
and this in a manner so that the eye successively identifies
visual objects which it will
associate with places.
These places will create the backbone
of the geographic statement,
and the examination of their relationships on the map
will allow for the development of this statement.
with sorts of visual “stops”
upon which the eye can rest.
In addition, every visual element
which could interfere with the image must be eliminated as much as possible.
Visual noise must be eliminated
to only keep the music of the map.
a model of reading
which plays upon objects’ scales through the zooming of sight is preferred.
For contrarily to seeing
a figurative image such as a photo
or a painting, objects which
must be shown,
thus the geographic places displayed on the map,
are often of novel and unknown forms,
and of a very diverse size.
It is less often about
recognising a form,
such as a face, a tree, or a person,
as discovering and memorising
abstract elements.26
the cartographic theory presented here
means to be simple,
global, and open.
It is based on a play of
four “components”:
shape, size, colour,
and visual effects.
validity of the cartographic options.
In general, this has as an effect
greatly limiting imaginable solutions.
To the contrary, it encourages creativity,
innovation, and even unorthodox solutions
from the point-of-view of more
traditional cartographic theories.
considers that the map’s validity
can in any case only be judged at the end,
based on its efficiency
in regards to its communicational project, and not in respect
to abstract recipes applied in
a scholarly fashion
during the entire process of its creation.40
to that of information.
That which has a specific shape vehicles information,
to the contrary of
that which has none.
a collection of angles.
Let us take for example
two triangles.
the angles composing them are different.
If not, they cannot be distinguished
one from the other apart from their size.
can serve to differentiate
geographic objects, at least
for certain spatial configurations.
However, it is firstly and above all
a means of defining an arbitration
between the geonic component and
the geotype component of a space.
cities of a country
by similar disks is a way of cancelling
their geographic singularity
in large part
to keep only the relative location
is identifiable to the others.
Each constitutes an instance of a geotype which
can be called
“a city” in this country.59
using geometric symbols,
parallel lines,
or other simple
and repetitive shapes rather than the exact
geographic contours of spatial objects
allows not only for a unification of them
in terms of meaning, but also
allows the map to simultaneously be more effective in visual terms.
It thus better transmits its message.
of a rapid transit link
between an airport and a downtown, it would be better
to draw a “dynamic” and straight arrow
proposed at the airport
linking the two places, rather than
a line which exactly respects
the planned path, but which may be confused
with the ordinary road
network with which
this transit in fact wants to compete.
that the play on shape concerns
not only a contrast between graphical objects,
but also affect the composition,
that is to say the overall form of the map.
Yet the composition of a map
gradually guides its reading.
Like a painting, a map must present
a composition
which is at the service of
its statement.
once the shape has been decided upon,
the other parameter of given geometric object is size.
is relatively simple,
that of size is distinctly less so.
mean height, depth,
area, or even the
overall impression.
be strongly affected
by the optical effects of the rest,
as we shall see.86
size is often used
to indicate the quantitative
attribute of a place.
The general principle is that
the importance of a phenomenon
in a place - let us say population
for example - may be analysed
using the size of the figurative image representing this place on a map.
this is not really possible
if the shape of the figurative image does vary from one place to another,
for comparing the size of two
different shapes is difficult.
be more generally useful to differentiate
object categories if their scale is manifestly
a means of distinguishing them,
without nevertheless having to respect
the actual geographic sizes of the objects.
Here can be found the idea,
which is already advanced,
of scalar spectrum.
that the size of objects on the map
and the importance given to them
is also partly dependent
on the size of the map itself.
This is what causes an object of a size
nearly as big as the map
to go unnoticed…
Said otherwise, it is not true that
the bigger it is, the more visible it is.
rule of proportionality
when it comes to proportioning symbols with the local values
of a variable. It has become
a habit that the area of a symbol
be made proportional to the
characteristic value of a place.
Essentially to make
mutually comparable.
However, it is often to the detriment of realism in regards to the values considered.
For in this case
their distribution is
de facto crushed
and their important
values weakened.
the great cities of a country,
when their importance for a whole
series of social phenomena
is in proportion to the number of relationships among their inhabitants
rather than the number
of inhabitants themselves.
psycho-physics has demonstrated
in the 1920s that the eye’s
relative perception of size itself
follows a specific rule,
which varies according to
if length, area,
or volumes are compared.
are thus possible
as soon as the final image creates
the nuances of the geographic idea
which one wishes to convey
in a satisfying manner.
Moreover, it is always useful to think about
the exact and singular nature
of the geographic objects represented and the manner
in which the map’s geometry
can take account of this.129
which can be coded and quantified
through different models, including the HSL model,
combining an indication of hue
- the colour - , an indication of
saturation - the colour’s intensity - ,
and an indication of lightness
- the amount of black in a colour,
giving it its dark or pale character.
to construct a greyscale,
from black to white.
making objects visible.
It more generally serves in modulating their visibility relative
to objects among themselves. This can be done
by a simple play upon contrast,
between dark and
light colours for example,
whether it depends upon differentiating
objects among themselves or objects
from the basemap.
played down and attention drawn
to the important objects.However, care must be given to the fact that
certain colours are pale
and others dark,
A map coloured in red and green
will come out uniformly grey
once photocopied
in black and white!
Using blue and yellow would solve this problem.149
in graduating a phenomenon in cartography,
or yet to distinguish phenomena
amongst themselves.
colours succeed each other
around the colour wheel can be played upon,
as well as that they can be discoloured
or darkened to create shades
or colour scales.
The rules for creating colour
scales can be technical,
but they are also fairly intuitive.
Everyone has in fact learned,
when they were little,
to put away their felt pens in
a harmonious order of colour.
Also, each of us has doubtless
found a solution
to overcome the difficulty
of categorising browns and greys.
intermediate colours is not permitted
and one is limited to using a number of
hues widely-distributed across the spectrum,
such as the colours of
the rainbow for example,
colour can become a tool
for cartographic
place differentiation.
However, be careful!
Colours also tend to be associated
together in different ways:
dark and pale, primary,
complementary, etc.
However rest assured that studying
general colour theory is very easy
and will allow success to be found
in using colours in cartography.171
This may seem superfluous,
but optical illusions are not a marginal phenomenon in cartography,
since the images created are abstract.
in the same way as an object, a tree,
can serve as a guide to interpreting
and avoiding ambiguities.
What is more, the coding and decoding logic via the legend
makes the message conveyed by
the map very directly dependent
upon the quality of the coding
and its own graphic modalities.
Such a shade of red represents such a rock, and mixing it up
with such a shade of red-orange
may lead to mistaking shale for gneiss,
or worse, a conglomerate for marble.
and the best would be to learn from then,
to know how to best use them.
somewhat impressive examples.
It should be noted that a colour changes slightly in relation to the size of the area
across which it is spread, as well as
to the neighbouring colours.
shape of visual objects.
As can be seen in the illustration,
the central circle appears to be
a different size in each picture,
whereas it is the same size
in each of them.
The circles around it change
its apparent size.
visual effects that
can be played upon by a cartographer concerns the clipping of the map into layers.
To do this different shading
or perforation techniques must be used,
allowing a dissociation from thematic layers.
It may also limit visual interference
and encourage the map’s reading
through a layering effect.
effects in cartography,
especially those allowing relief to be created, and the only limit
is the cartographer’s imagination combined
to the techniques at his service.
especially its framing,
the orientation of its segments, tearing, anamorphosis,
or yet its regularisation through
simple geometric shapes,
squares or hexagons for example.
consist in multiplying
the superimposed figures,
which combined with layering effects,
allow volume to be created and display quantities
through an overall reading when even
the concerned places pattern
is very constricted.215
typography and symbolisation,
which can be very elaborate
and very effectively enrich
a map’s message, with the advantage of introducing
specific information at least cost.
cinematic effects.
By creating cartographic movies,
of spatial dynamics
to be displayed
by using rhythmic effects
or simple visual changes.