The fundamental link between
geography and cartography
is none other than  distance.
Geography thinks about distance,
cartography gives it a face.
Cartography, as a general rule
practiced on planar
or assimilated surfaces,
a sheet of paper,
χάρτης, kartès, in Greek,
or a screen,
thus represents distances
through drawings.
Let us take a simple example :
a circle drawn on a page.
It is made up of all of the points equidistant from the centre.
It is thus well-defined by a distance,
its radius in this case.
The centre is located somewhere
on the map,
perhaps at a certain distance from other points,
or even from other circles
or geometric shapes.
In any case, it is located at a certain
distance from the edges of the page.
The principle of cartography
is to consider
that such a circle could be
an adequate representation
of a real or imagined
geographical space.
A space defined by a centre
and a distance to this centre,
the circle possibly portraying
a border, a city limit,
the interior disc its extent, etc.
It is in this way that
a geographic place
can be represented by a
cartographic circle, for example.
This simple analogy is
unfortunately not completely suited
to the representation of geographical space.
For, to the contrary of
cartographic space,
that is to say to that of a sheet of paper,
a geographical space is not
entirely “Euclidean”.
It may happen that the shortest
route from one place to another
is not a straight line,
or that the travel time of a trip may differ
according to its shape or its direction.
Cartographic metrics, that is to say
the way of measuring distance
on a map is thus a poor, unequivocal metric,
compared to the richness of metrics
structuring a real geographical space.
Cartographical work is thus partly
made up of finding a compromise
between the Euclidean positions of
the places represented,
in brief their location in relation
to the map’s framework,
and their location in
relationship to one another,
taking account of every distance involved
and which no drawing can render.43
expression of geographic reality
touches upon scale.
whereas every space is characterised
by what I will call a scalar spectrum.
ensemble of distance values
which are more represented there than others.
This constitutes in some measure
its spatial signature.51
cartographical principle
is that of a unequivocal rule of correspondance valid in any point,
between a distance on the ground
and its representation on the map.
respected in many maps,
first because of the
cartographic projection,
it remains that the cartography
considerably impoverishes
the representation of a space
as soon as he has to sooner or later
choose a certain size for geographical objects
within the spaces which have geographical
objects of different sizes.
the circumscriptions of urban and
rural voting offices
cannot both be represented together,
for the scalar spectrum of
the voting office’s space
one which is urban
and the other rural,
small for the former,
and large for the latter.68
cartography in many cases
leads to making a radical choice by transforming metrics,
by losing the ability to measure
kilometric distances
between cartographical objects
to the contrary trying to produce
shape-types and simple images
or hamlets, for example.
it thus means weakening
the singular component of maps,
and weakening the representation
of the geon
in order to arrive at a figuration
preferring geotypes,
that is to say visual forms of
the organisation of cartographic space,
and similar to standard shapes
or models of organisation
of geographical space,
such as the centre-periphery model,
for example.82
geon and geotype
is at the heart of cartographic work.
or a satellite image,
any more than a painting is
similar to a photograph.
It is not a work capturing reality,
but rather progressively
constructing an image,
element by element, layer by layer,
“touch”after“touch”.
of reality.
It is to the contrary the result
of a progressive accumulation
of graphical elements
leading to a more-or-less
complex image.
However, more often,
these graphical elements
proceed from an initial simplification of principles,
so that their combination does not too
rapidly result in an unreadable image.
to express geotypical part
of geographical space.
It is their combination which results
in the expression of a geon,
the singularity of space.
of geographical spaces,
two manners each of representing them
in an archetypical manner
could be proposed.
A primary form and a secondary
form could be proposed.
An envelope and a framed content
could be proposed
for the « territory »,
a punctual level and an areal
gradient for the « horizon »,
for the « rhizome »,
and connections and nodes
for the « network ».
a certain number of elementary
geographical concepts – the geotypes -
which can be expressed with the help of signs
which are, themselves, relatively simple.
we may mention
the Egyptian hieroglyph for “city”.
It is a cross within a circle.
The underlying spatial
concepts are obvious.
symbolises a road-crossing.
and not merely commercial,
and a meeting-point.
within space by a boundary,
which may be fortified,
or it may more simply form a territory,
which is signified by the circle.
how these few lines can establish
a fairly solid link between
the spatial idea and a graphic.
to study the visual symbolism of space
through systems of expression which are
real sign-languages,
with their own cultures,
such as the national
sign-languages
used by the deaf and
hearing-impaired.
the notion of territory, network,
cities, or even rhizome 132
visual expressions
for a spatial idea to be understood,
as can be seen.
However, they also allow
this variety to be understood
as a cultural difference
and to foresee connotation processes
which must be taken into
account in cartography.138
geographic thought
is distinguishing spaces
and spatialities.
Spaces are complex realities,
aggregates, the study of which could be called synthetic geography,
and which are the objects which
cartography best knows how to represent.
the contrary aptitudes, skills,
and capacities, relationships with space,
and localised actions.
They are the subjects
of analytical geography.
These are the things which cartography
has much difficulty in representing,
for it is necessarily synthetic and direct
from the fact of
its graphical nature.150
represents spatialities
through the intermediary
of correspondences with spaces.
This system of correspondences
has been theorised
by spatial intelligence in the “spatial balance” model.
It identifies spaces to spatial assets
and spatialities
to liabilities.156
balance sheet,
spatial assets are organised
by increasing liquidity:
rhizomes and networks.
Spatialities: city-ness, mobility,
and connectivity, for example,
are organised by increasing
degree of social intermediation.
and structural order
which allows a space and its
dominant spatialities
to be simultaneously
shown cartographically.
leeways can also be freed
by “vertically” shifting the correspondence
between spaces and spatialities,
that is to say between liquidity
and intermediation.
to map a network,
it is enough to preferably
retain its territorial component,
as this map of the rail transportation
network for Ile-de-France shows.
It displays a network
accessibility indicator
at every point of the territory.
the rail network then allows
another network to be shown
under the classical
form of a trellis,
and to thus compare the two spaces,
whereas the superpositioning
of two irregular “grids”
would have rendered
the map unreadable,
being salient to the other.179
to greatly affect cartography,
which is the representation
of urban spaces.
geometric nature
encourages the representation
of spreading,
unvarying, flat spaces.
This is generally the contrary of urban space,
which is dense,
diverse, mixed,
and presents some variability,
which is moreover arbitrary.
to represent the geography
of the city ?189
in subway maps,
especially when they
are very effective.
In practice, subway maps
condition the reality,
the functioning,
the subdivision into neighbourhoods,
and the names (after the station names)
of urban space in its entirety
in an important way.
What is more, in a city endowed
with a very good subway network,
the metric of space
is certainly patchy,
but Euclidean overall, with
a scalar spectrum with two levels:
that of a network in its ensemble,
where speeds are constant,
and that of neighbourhoods with
foot traffic, also at a constant speed.200
as if the city had been produced
as a territory by its map.
Instead of being the map
which attempts
to reproduce the reticular
spatialities of mobility
at the heart of the metropolitan network,
sometimes well and sometimes badly.
fundamentally non-Euclidean city
thus loses its interest
if we change perspectives
by considering that the correspondence
between the map and geography,
between representation
and reality
is in fact the same as
an active reality of society.210
truly appears as it is:
the expression of
an intention about space.
Far from a simple recording,
cartographic work
must begin firstly by
a sketch.
That is to say by a
rough drawing of the space
such as it is thought that
it could be represented,
with the help of some
simple elements calling upon
identifiable geographical concepts.
of collecting
geographical information
allowing to
“flesh out” a map
illustrating the related idea
and based on proven facts.