this last part will address the
question of cartographic “design”.
expressing a simple idea:
The map proposes a singular combination
of a message and an ergonomics.
The object design proceeds
in a similar manner,
through the association of
an identity and a functionality.
A chair’s design, for example,
requires an originality of creative
form or an innovative material
and the presentation of a comfortable seat.
A good map is a comfortable device
to gain access to an idea concerning space.
in cartography also resides
in the fact that itoften requires
making geographic thoughts clearer.
The act of mapping often
acts in practice
in a spatial problem.
for an equilibrium.
It does not exclude beauty, nor the search of aesthetics more generally,
a search which must guide the cartographer.
It demands of itself a finished
geographical thought
and the search for the right picture,
even before the technical and graphical mastery,
which can also be confided to specialists.
an affair of intuition and creation.28
sketched the broad outlines here,
clashes with a cartographic tradition
which tends to impose norms
whose justification is not
always evident,
especially concerning what is
traditionally called
the « dressing » of maps.
doubtlessly essential.
always necessary,
for certain simple maps can use
the title in place of a legend.
useful in the measure
that the instrumental component of the map is sufficiently important,
if distances must be measured for example.
Be careful about the projection,
which will often change the scales
from one end of the map to another!
the most worthy of criticism
is probably that of mentioning
an orientation, a compass,
or a North arrow.45
and useful to a map whose
statement is sun exposure,
for the most part useless.
this question introduces another:
that of cartographcal
implicit understanding.
cartography is also a tongue,
with its culture, conventions, and grammar.
Conventionally, North is at
the top of a page.
It is only indicated if this is not the case,
and not placing it at the
top can effectively be
part of the cartographic message.
cartography can count on them.
It can partly be constructed upon implicit understanding,
and not over-emphasise
recourse to coding,
which is characteristic of very technical
and specialised instrumental maps,
and sometimes even rather esoteric maps.63
comfort and cartographic ergonomics
concerns the basemap.
a layer for propping.
It is a common world
for several spaces,
a common metric and scale.
a secondary map,
a map which is slipped under the principle map
and aiding its interpretation.
perhaps a bit too simplistic,
for it could be remarked that it is highly probably
that this underlying map could
also considerably modify
the sense of the “principle” map.
disassociated from the map itself.
It is an essential component.
It is not simply a neutral and arbitrary surface
on which geographic data are projected.
a fully-fledged map,
as well as being a means
of expression in itself.
It is for example a good means for
identifying a collection of maps,
giving them a style (vintage),
even breaking with usual codes
by using unconventional colours
(the sea in black or red…).85
There exist auto-extensive maps,
which form of themselves their own base.
Only the locations of places in
relationship to one another count.
This kind of map can be read in terms of shapes.
They can be compared according
to their general look
and their similarities.
to induce visual groupings
through graphical objects the places
of which they represent are not thought
to have a geographical function
in the spatial issue represented.
the world without a basemap of continents
can allow, for example, to better discern
the great masses of planetary settlement,
and this without being influenced
by continental groupings
or oceanic discontinuities.101
essential point in the act of mapping:
Every map is inserted within a world
of signs which pre-exist it,
and to be effective, every map must take this into account.
graphical world of the map
can firstly be found within itself.
It is marked by the style of the map.
Whether it is desired or not, whether it be
the result of a voluntary and creative act
or the application of predefined
oftware automatisms,
a certain graphical style.
a cartographic charter,
even to a graphical charter.
does not thus stop
simply at colouring polygons on a sheet of paper.
It also consists in mastering
the style of the product,
even in developing one’s own style,
a cartographic signature,
in a way in which a person’s maps can
all be recognisable as that person’s.
the professional cartographer’s skill
to conform oneself as little as necessary
to the graphical charter which is imposed
by the publication environment for the maps.
Even if, otherwise, the cartographic
charter he gives himself
can sensibly differ
in order not to restrain
his creative capacity.
However, this liberty is all
the easier to conquer
if the cartographer who
proves to be original
can claim the status of the author
of a cartographic work.
inserting a map into its environment
concerns its relationships
with its immediate vicinity.
presented on its own,
alone, without complement, without an editorial environment,
without accompanying text, nor table,
nor even that it accompany something,
and be sufficient on its own.
level thus consists firstly
in fixing a principle for the demarcation of cartographic space.
It can be contained within a frame,
in a once again very traditional
and expected manner
according to scholarly cartography.
It could to the contrary be conquering
and interfere in the interstices
of its environment.
This is essentially an affairfor negotiation,
but definitively marks the
place given to cartography
in a statement about space.
thus also consists in giving
an opinion on the repartitioning of roles
amongst different “media”.
The best principle consists
in letting the map say
what it says best, better than
a text or paintings could,
and to the contrary it must renounce mapping
that which the properties of other media
could treat with more finesse or dexterity.
level of integrating a map
into its environment,
within a communicational system,
at once both symbolic and material.
the cartographer also consists
in knowing the different physical bases for the map.
Of course, this includes screens and
their optical characteristics,
but also papers and inks
as well as their ability to render
such-and-such a colour nuance.
A map projected onto
a screen is not under
the same demands as that printed in a book.
also partly a “communicator”.
That is to say someone who not only knows how to say things
but knows to whom to say them, when,
how, in which exact manner,
and especially what not to say,
what may cause a problem.
A cartographer also
understands the orders
given to emphasise
such-or-such a space 167
obviously stated.168
communications counsellor,
even if it means advising not making a map.
This is the case when he thinks
that cartographic media
is inappropriate to the role
which it is to be made to play,
and ultimately the message
to be conveyed.
than might be realised,
for the effect of a truth produced
by the geographic image
associated with the necessity
of locating things
sometimes obliges the client
to clarify the positions
which she would have preferred to
leave aside to verbal imprecision.
which is presently ending,
I would like to insist upon a point which has guided us
all throughout this introduction
to “mapdesign”:
The cartography of human spaces
is a human activity.
seems important to me,
for it is a necessary condition for the opening up of cartography
well beyond the world of
cartographers and specialists,
and all the way to geographers.
education as in their practices,
geographers are not always either very interested nor very involved
in this technological discipline.
Its richness is however amusing,
and training in it offers
both an exciting study
of the statistical processing
and of the history of Art.
is also a free cartography.
Free to try new images,
free to make mistakes, and to lack effectiveness.
However, it is also free in an
essential thing for geography itself:
Free to outline new spaces.
For - and this is also one of
the essential points of our statement - ,
for many, the map is  to be found in
the definition of spaces in particular,
and space in general.
Its renewal is one of the certain means
of making progress in geography.