Most objects which are the matter
for geographic reflection
are only summarily situated,
or in an implicit manner,
often leaving the concrete modalities
of this location unresolved.
it gives itself the right
to decide upon a location,
or more precisely a mode of location
within the Euclidean space of the map.
More plainly, on the map.
a limiting idea for geography,
and which it has taken
much time to undo.
space must have coordinates.
be decided upon, but also their shapes,
more-or-less complex shapes,
but planar: polygonal,
in a network,
simple points, and lines.17
thus always the result
of an initial arbitration
as to its graphical form,
and we have seen that
this form could be defined
by a type of reference space
and its properties.
error to location in cartography.
When a city is
resumed to a point,
a county to its geometric centroid,
or to the contrary, that which is less
often perceived as an error in location
but which remains an
important approximation,
when a punctual measurement
is attributed
to a polygonal space.
a cartographic reading,
one single rule applies:
every piece of information related
to a point is supposed to be “local”,
that is to say valid for this point
and its immediate neighbourhood,
and loses its relevancy the
farther away one distances oneself.
such as administrative borders can be
used to define this neighbourhood.
However it is often an artifice
which complicates the map’s reading,
even to the point of
being parasitical.
of a spatial reality on
a terrestrial globe,
and the distances separating it
from another reality
can be very different once
the terrestrial surface is flattened
by the operation called
projection.
Projection allows
a map to be drawn
over a planar base, when the geographic
reference space is not planar,
since it is the surface of a globe.
of the instrument at your disposal,
these projections are innumerable.
By transforming coordinates originally
given in longitude and latitude,
according to meridians and parallels,
and into rectangular coordinates,
that is to say relative
to the edges of a map,
the neighbourhood can be recomposed
in a very unexpected manner.
a source of creativity.
Used wisely,
they can reinforce a geographic
idea by a simple image,
made of alignments for example.56
is an integral part of the work
of cartographic conception.
It is not only concerned with the choice
of the geometric shapes of places,
respect areas,
and then it is called
an equal-area projection.
It can also respect local shapes,
but not over a long distance,
and that is called
a conformal projection.
However the two are not
possible at the same time.
Projections which do not respect anything,
called aphylactic projections,
can provide very appropriate
location bases
for the geographic
messages of the map.
This is the case for
Buckminster Fuller’s projection,
which displays
the world as an island,
that of a unified
human species.72
into the configuration
of cartographic reference.
It is more and more
common today
to have recourse
to anamorphosis.
They allow the map
to be deformed
in a way to give
more visibility
to spaces which are the most
important to the map’s theme,
the most populated
areas for example.
bases are called cartograms.
By increasing or decreasing
the size of territorial units
in proportion to the
population of voting age,
to population” for example
allow a weight to be given equivalent
to the inhabitants of a county
in electoral cartography.
A person equals one vote equals
a fixed area on the cartogram.
By default, on a traditional map,
the votes in rural places
and places lacking density
seem to dominate the map.90
process yet further,
we could construct
inverted cartograms,
which could be called
“anti-cartograms”,
for example by using
an anamorphosis
inversely proportional
to the population.
The resulting map displays
a filamented structure,
of settlement pattern,
the opposite of
a classical cartogram,
bubbles at the spot where cities are,
but almost makes
intermediate spaces
and the inter-urban relationships
which they compete to disseminate.
to a traditional Euclidean map,
the latter could be equated
to cartogram according to area.
The ensemble forms a triptych
in fact enlightening what
I call the three phases of space:
the co-presence phase
for the cartogram,
focusing on urban spatialities ;
the circulatory phase
for the anti-cartogram, 108
of mobility;
and logically the
tele-communicational phase
since for this kind of map
no deformation seeks to reduce the connective spatialities
normally being substituted
for co-presence
or circulation.115
by cartographers,
very simple maps
such as tourist maps
or subway maps are however examples
of cartographic effectiveness.
Cartographic places are fabricated
by the means of a figurative image
or a symbol perhaps indicating
their distinctive qualities,
such as the activities are proposed,
their function or the weather.
to be studied as a whole,
to analyse the overall structure
of space for example.
However they remain efficient
for comparing places one to another,
measuring their remotness,
or even planning an itinerary.
is available, which is often digital,
it is however possible to draw maps
according to statistical bases.
For example, the size of a figurative image
representing a place in relation
to its population could be varied.
allow maps with continuous colour
nuances to be created,
often revealing the deep
structures of a territory
in a very efficient or
even attractive way.
Its demographic dynamic
regarding fertility for example.
has focused on statistical concepts
to develop techniques
allowing graphical contrasts
within a map to be better controlled
in a way as to make them clearer,
and to produce sharper maps.
This can be done for example by contrasting
two or three place categories
based on their characteristics
which are however much more varied.
discretisation,
answer to two distinct
and sometimes contradictory logics.
The first one consists in distinguishing
the statistical values characteristic
of places according to thresholds
which are significant
according to the map’s theme.
Places on the map can thus be ordered
into classes defined
by these thresholds,
for example the threshold would be
the majority in an election
or zero degrees Celsius
for frozen areas.
the cut-off thresholds
based on the statistical data
themselves for all places,
allowing either a maximal
differentiation of space
- the median is thus used -,
and making maps on different
themes easily comparable,
or a location of each place
into a scale of existing values
- thus the average and
standard deviation are used.
requiring specific skills
and a sensitivity to biases
statistical manipulations.
However once mastered, it can be understood
that the real issues in cartography
are not about these techniques.
to test different discretisations
for the cartography of two indicators
whose geography is very different.172
I have just addressed
are widely practiced today
with the help of software.
There certainly exists software
specific to cartography.
However, until now the trend has rather
been for an increasing disassociation
between pre-treatment,
carried out by what is called
geographic information systems
- GIS, SIG in French - ,
raw cartographic layers,
and vectorial drawing software used downstream,
carried out by specialised
cartographers and graphic artists
to end up with editorial-quality maps.
of maps which are relatively
less elaborate graphically.
However, cartography practiced
beyond a certain level
and beyond the exploratory stage
cannot do without real
work on the image,
requiring appropriate instruments,
but also and especially
specific skills, close to design work
and fairlyd istant from
computer programming.192
none other than
information systems devoted
to spatial information.
They are thus based
on a database system,
in general made to store
elaborate geographic information
allowing for a description
of complex spaces.
For example spaces with
holes or discontinuities,
territories with lakes,
or networks where the direction of traffic
must be recorded could be evoked.
GIS add calculation modules
which are made to treat
geographic information.
For example, they allow distances
and areas to be calculated,
using a network, etc.
for cartography is to unify
geographic information into
a normal framework
at the heart of which
can be developed standards
facilitating a sharing
of information.
and freely-available GIS
are now being developed.
It is only to be expected
that cartographic modules of an
increasing quality will improve them,
further with only these instruments,
which at the beginning were
very much for programmers only.
of these software platforms
designate them as choice
instruments for the research
and development of
spatial intelligence
or in applied geography.
They in fact allow
the practical validity
of new theoretical concepts
to be tested,
such as that of scalar spectrum
for example.222
does not stop at the creation
of thematic layers such as
administrative boundaries,
built space, roads, demographic
or economic data,
be superimposed
to create a finished
and effective map.227
of the relationship between
cartography and geography consists
in the art of this combination.
the ensemble of graphic techniques
specific to the objects which are maps,
techniques which allow a maximisation
of the range of expression
for spatial ideas through design.
superpositioning
of crude spatialised
information layers,
it means making a patchwork
or a juxtaposition of plates.
Each will then correspond to a geographical place
and return the image’s content
into the register of geography and its concepts.