In this episode, we will present
the notion of multiple inheritance
in C++.
Before we dive into this matter,
we will start by reviewing
all the knowledge aquired up to now.
Now, you are familiar with the three
central concepts of the object oriented programming:
encapsulation/abstraction,
inheritance and polymorphism.
You know that encapsulating and
abstracting means to regrouping
data and processing into
one same entity.
It also revolves around separating the
user interface from the implementation details.
Also, you know that the inheritance lets
us set up a "is a" relationship
between different classes of a program.
You also know that this tool
lets us use polymorphic
solutions
in the sense of "inclusion polymorphism".
Finally, you have learnt that the
polymorphisms is a very powerful tool
making it possible for the
execution of a same code
to automatically adapt to
the different types of data.
In C++, you know that we are
able to set up a polymorphic
solution using two mandatory ingredients:
we must use virtual methods through
references or pointers.
To conclude this brief review
of your knowledge,
let us mention the notions
of "abstract classes*
and "pure virtual methods".
These let us improve
the object-ortiented models
dramatically.
Let us move on to the thema
of this episode: "multiple inheritance*.
It actually follows an already mastered
thema, the simple inheritance.
Until now, the inheritance relationships
we have studied
were simple inheritance relationships.
This means that each sub-class only
had one direct parent.
Multiple inheritance simply revolves
around one sub-class having
several direct parent classes.
Multiple inheritance is allowed in C++.
In other words, we may
have one sub class inherit directly
from several parent classes.
However, this notion is not
provided by all
object-oritented programming languages.
Basic notions regarding multiple
inheritance are mostly
the same as the ones regarding
simple inheritance.
Consequently, one sub-class will inherit
from these base classes, all their attributes
and methods (except constructors and destructor),
as well as their type.
Let us dive into a concrete example;
we shall see how
multiple inheritance will deem useful.
For old time's sake, let us choose
a game-related example.
Now, several entities will play a part
in the game. For example,
a ball, rackets, a net, a player.
On each entity, we will bestow a method
called "evolue" (TN: means "evolve")
making it possible to track the
position of the entity during the game.
In our first draft conception,
we could imagine
a super-class "Entite" (TN: means "Entity")
whose main method
will be called "evolue". This method will
probably be polymorphic and
redefined in the sub-classes. However,
this is not our point here. Then, we will have
sub-classes representing the different
concrete entities in the game
such as the classes "Balle", "Raquette", "Filet" and "Joueur"
(TN: means "Ball", "Racket", "Net", and "Player")
Now, after further analysis, we might
realise that, due to game requirements,
all these entities do not, in fact,
behave exactly
the same. They might not
have the same needs.
For example, we may need to print
or draw certain entities.
The ball, the net or the racket may require
a graphical representation aswell.
Others may not require it. For example,
we may not need to
see the player in the game.
Moreover, certain entities may need
to be interactive,
that is, controllable with mouse and
keyboard (maybe the ball and the racket).
Others may not need to be controllable :
for example, maybe we need not
control the player nor the net.
We are now wondering how to
set up all this.
The class hierarchy (which you can now see)
answers precisely
to the just-now-mentioned needs.
Here, we have introduced
a super-class "Interactive", thanks to
which we will take care
of the different entities requiring
to be interactive,
such as the ball and the racket.
This super-class will provide the methods
regarding
this very interaction.
Similarly, the super-class "Graphique"
lets us define
all entities we wish to see drawable
in the game
(that is, the racket, ball and the net).
this super-class will provide the
necessary material
to the graphical representation
of these entities.
These two super-classes let us
see some entities
- albeit not all - as
interactive objects
and/or as graphical objects.
Please note that it would not have
been correct to place the drawing and
interaction methods in the
super-class "Entity".
Why, do you think, is it the case?
Indeed, placing these methods in
the super-class "Entity" would force certain
classes to have a drawing method while
we want them to be undrawable.
It would also force certain classes
to be interactive
while we do not wish it.
Thanks to multiple inheritance,
we now have a better model
of what we wish to realise.
C++ grants us this option.
We can imagine many another
situation requiring
the use of multiple inheritance.
Here comes a zoological example.
Assume that you are tasked to model
the animals in a zoo.
As it happens, some animals
are ovoviviparous and this inherit
from the oviparous
and from the viviparous.
Multiple inheritance lets us model
clearly
the different lodgers of the zoo.
Oviparous animals lay eggs and
the egg "develops" the embryo
until birth. Viviparous animals
give birth to live babies.
Ovoviviparous animals (such as the seahorse)
indeed inherit
the characteristics of
oviparous and viviparous both:
their embryo is "developed" by the egg
(just like oviaprous),
but they are born live (just like
viviparous).
Finally, a more informatic example.
You may not know that the different
C++ classes regarding
inputs and outputs,
(these ones should ring a bell),
are organized thanks
to multiple inheritance.
This organisation in particular,
presents the famous,
"diamond architecture" on which we
will expand
later on.
Let us now move on to the concrete
use of multiple inheritance in C++.
In C++, if we wish to declare that a
sub-class inherits from several
parent classes, we simply need,
during the class declaration,
to indicate all the super-classes,
separated by commas.
Thus, here, for each super-class from which
the sub-class inherits
we will indicate
"public nameOfTheSuperClass",
and separate the different parent classes
with commas.
Concretely, this here means that
the class "Ovovivipare" inherits
from the super-class "Ovipare",
and the super-class "Vivipare".
Then, the class's content is not very
different from what we have seen
in the classes written or read until now.
Finally, please note that, the
order of the declaration
of the inheritance links is
relevant. Indeed, it impacts
how we will build and destroy
an instance
created through multiplte inheritance.
This is the next point we
will focus on.
How do construction and destruction
work in the frame
of multiple inheritance.
Let us discuss what mutiple inheritance
implies on constructors.
There is in fact not much new;
although there is one point
you must pay attention to.
So, like with simple inheritance,
the initialization of the attributes  inherited
from the super-classes is done
through the initialization list
of the sub-class constructor
by calling all the constructors
of the parent classes we inherit from.
Thus, the general syntax is the same
as for simple inheritance.
In the "initialization list" section
of the sub-class constructor,
we call, like this, the different constructors
of the super-classes
we inherit from, separated by commas.
And, obviously,
if one of the super-classes has
a default constructor,
it is not necessary to explicitly call it.
As always,
while you are still unfamiliar with
the constructor concepts,
we recommand you explicitly call
the default constructors aswell
so that you do not forget that there is
a call to the default constructor,
even though this is not necessary.
However, be careful: there is a little
peculiarity with multiple inheritance.
The call order of the constructors
is not the order
of the written constructors in the
initialization list of the sub-class
constructors. The constructors are called
following the order
of the inheritance declaration.
As always, the destructors are called
in the order reverse to that
of the constructors.
Let us illustrate all this
with a concrete example.
We will go back to the example regarding
ovoviviparous who inherit
from both oviparous and viviparous.
Let us assume that
oviparous' constructor typically require
a number of eggs, and that
the viviparous' constructor
requires a gestation period.
For ovoviviparous, we will add
an attribute here: it is a boolean
indicating
if the species is rare or not.
Thus, we pass here as the third parameter
an argument "rareté" (TN: means "rarity").
This lets us initialize wether
the species is rare or not.
Therefore, the prototype of the
ovoviviparous' constructor will typically
have one parameter for the oviparous' constructor,
one parameter for the viviparous' constructor,
and one parameter
to initialize its own attribute.
To this parameter, we give a default
value, which is "false".
The constructor for ovoviviparous is thus
tasked with calling the constructors
of the classes it inherits from.
First of all, it will call,
in its initialization list,
the constructors of the classes
it inhertis from. For example, it will
called the viviparous' constructor
by passing the expected parameter.
It will also call the oviparous' constructor
by passing the corresponding parameter.
These calls are, as usual, separated
by commas. Then, we will initialize
its own attribute with the parameter
received here as argument.
Pay attention though, here, even if
we may think that, as it is, the constructor
of ovoviviparous will
first call the viviparous' constructor,
then the oviparous' constructor,
actually, this is not the case.
The first called constructor will actually
be the one of oviparous.
What matters regarding the call order
of the super-classes
in case of multiple inhertiance
is indeed the inheritance declaration
and not the order of declaration
in the constuctor's
initialization list in the sub-class.
This means that here, whatever we write,
the oviparous' constructor
will always be called first.
Then, the viviparous' constructor
will be called.
To make things easier, most modern
compilers will now indicate
with a warning if the call order
of the constructors does not match
the one you think you have
written here.
Voilà, this was all we had to say
on multiple inheritance
and the order of the constructors' call.
We remind you that the destructors are
always called
in the reverse order
of the constructors'.