In this episode,
we will discuss the most subtle
point
of multiple inheritance. This is the
reason
why some languages refuse to include
multiple inheritance.
This is what we call
virtual classes.
Let us begin by illustrating the problem,
to which this new concept pertains.
Let us go back to our infamous example
regarding ovoviviparous - they are
oviparous
and viviparous. This is a case
of multiple inheritance since the class
"Ovovivipare" inherits from the classes
"Vivipare" and "Ovipare".
Now, let us imagine that Ovipare
inherit from the class "Animal"
(indeed, an oviparous is an animal),
Similarly, a viviparous is also an animal.
Therefore, in a certain way, an ovoviviparous
is two times an animal.
Here is a more technical example
from the system library of C++.
Of couse, you do not have to comprehend
every single detail;
we merely wish to make it obvious
that the problems we are talking about
occur in daily life.
So, regarding the "iostream" class
(we have talked about it along
with "cout"),
it so happens that this "iostream" class
is both an "ostream" and an "istream".
Then, the conceptors of these classes
have decided that
both "istream" and "ostream" were
also "ios" (no matter what it actually is).
Consequently, "iostream" is
apparently two times an "ios".
By the way, this how, in reality,
we represent multiple inheritance
diagrams. We never draw
the same class multiple times on
an inheritance diagram.
However, we draw it once only with
both inheritances going back
to the same class.
The reason why we have drawn
our diagram this way is so that you
understand
what the problem is.
What does it mean that an ovoviviparous
is an oviparous (which is an animal)
and also a viviparous
(which is an animal too) ?
Does it mean that an
ovoviviparous is two times an animal?
For example, if an animal has a head,
does an ovoviviparous have two?
Does it have an oviparous head
and a viviparous head?
Or does it only have one head?
Is it the very same animal?
This here is the core problem.
Due to this conundrum,
certain languages refuse to
provide multiple inheritance.
In C++, if we do not take precautions
(this is why we drew our diagram in
such an unusual way),
our ovoviviparous will
indeed inherit twice from the
class "Animal".
Each instance of Ovovivipare will
have two times the attributes
from the class "Animal".
Let us see this in an concrete example.
Let us imagine the following example.
Here, we have written it in a condensed way
so that it can fit in a single slide.
We thus have the class "Animal".
It has a constructor which initializes
its attribute.
This attribute is a character string
indicating what kind of head the animal has.
We receive a character string and
we initialize the head attribute
with the received paramater.
Then, we have an "Ovipare" class,
which inherits from the class "Animal".
This "Ovipare" class redefines
a default constructor here - we kept
things really simple here.
This default constructor calls the
constructor of "Animal"
passing a character string : "à cornes"
(TN: means "horny").
This means that an instance of  Ovipare have
a horny head.
Then, we have the class "Vivipare"
which also inherits from "Animal".
It also has a default constructor
which says that the animal has,
for example, a fish head.
Finally, the class "Ovovivipare"
inherits from "Ovipare"
and from "Vivipare".
We thus get the very diagram
that we have presented previously.
Then, we have a public method
called "affiche" (TN : means "print") which
prints the head
inherited from "Animal" through
"Ovipare". Here, we can see
the scope resolution operator.
We do have an ambiguity since
Ovovivipare
inherits two heads;
one from "Ovipare", the other
from "Vivipare".
In order to solve the ambiguity,
we use, as always,
the scope resolution operator.
Thus we say "j'ai une tête" (TN: means "I have a head"),
print the head of Ovipare,
"et une tête" (TN: means "and a head"),
and print the head of Vivipare.
Now if, for example,
in the main function
or elsewhere,
we declare an Ovovivipare "x"
- it is absolutely possible
since "Ovovivipare" has a default
constructor.
Now, " x " will be constructed through
the default constructor.
It will call the two default constructors
of the super-classes
in the inheritance declaration oder,
here at the class level.
Here, we will thus call the constructors
of "Ovipare" and of "Vivipare".
We can very well do this
default construction here.
Then, if we print " x ",
we will have the following
printing for this ovoviviparous :
"j'ai une tête à corne"
(TN: means "I have a horny head"),
which is the result of the initialization
through the default constructor
of "Ovipare", and
"et une tête de poisson"
(TN: means "and a fish head"),
which is the result of the printing
of "Vivipare::tete"
initialized through the
default constructor
of the class "Vivipare".
Thus, the class "Ovovivipare" has indeed
inherited two heads.
There are two animals in the class
"Ovoviviparous".
Here, of course,
it is rather unwanted for an
ovoviviparous to retrieve two heads
through this multiple inheritance.
Same for the fact that there are two copies of "Animal".
Please note that, in certain cases,
we may to effectively inherit
the attributes twice.
For example, let us imagine that
we have a hierarchy of vehicles.
We have petrol engine vehicles,
and electric vehicles.
Now, we imagine that we have
hybrid vehicles:
they are petrol engine vehicles
and electric vehicles.
The question is :
Is a hybrid vehicle a single vehicle,
just as was the case for ovoviviparous?
Or are they indeed two vehicles?
This depends on what we mean
by "vehicle"?
If, by vehicle, we mean four
tires, a steering wheel...
then, naturally, a hybrid vehicle
has only one time
four tires and a steering wheel and
surely not eight tires and two steering wheels.
If, on the other hand, we mean
that a vehicle has an engine, it is different.
Indeed, we have an electric engine
and a petrol engine.
In this case, we will wish
to have two engines in "hybride".
Now, you can see that this is
a subtle problem
which is very conception-dependant.
We need to understand
what the inheritance relationship
truly means in the case at hand.
If we do not wish to receive
several times the attributes
of the super-super-class,
we will need to do something
particular
in order to prevent it :
we will declare the inheritance link
as a virtual link.
We are once again using the keyword
"virtual" here, but for another reason.
Here, the inheritance link
is virtual.
Thus, if a super-class has
its inheritance links
towards its sub-classes declared
as virtual,
the super-class will be called
a virtual super-class.
Be careful, this has nothing to
do with an abstract class!
In an abstract class, we have
virtual methods,
and, in a virtual class,
we can whatever method
we desire.
It is the sub-classes' inheritance
link that is special,
that is virtual.
Do not confuse one concept with
the other.
The general syntax is as follows :
for the sub-classes we will say
that we inherit virtually.
Personally, we say that it is
a virtual inheritance
rather than a virtual class.
Thus, we say that inherit virtually
from the super-class.
Concretely, in our ovoviviparous
example,
we will change things at the level
of Ovipare and Vivipare.
This way, Ovipare inherits virtually
from the class "Animal" :
consequently, "Animal" is
a virtual class.
Similarly, we will write that
"Vivipare" inherits virtually
from the class "Animal".
Please note that it is the class
we inherit from several times
that is called virtual.
Here, this means that it is
the class "Animal"
that will be a virtual class.
We have to modify the inheritance
links from Ovipare towards "Animal"
and from "Vivipare" towards "Animal"
even though it is the class "Ovovivipare"
that introduces the problem.
You can see that there is
a problem
with the general conception.
The designers of the classes
"Ovipare" and "Vivipare"
must declare a virtual inheritance
towards the class "Animal" because,
possibly,
someone, someday, will imagine
a sub-class "Ovovivipare",
which inherits from "Ovipare",
and from "Vivipare".
This is a severe flaw of
virtial inheritance
and virtual classes.
It creates a dependency of
higher-level inheritances
towards possible lower-level
inheritances.
This is another reason why certain
programming languages
want nothing to do with
virtual inheritance.
However, since the possibility
exists in C++, we should use it
carefully, and parcimoniously.
Now let us go back to our
multiple inheritance diagrams.
In order to signify that the
inhertiance links
are virtual, we will use dash lines
instead of the full ones.
Now, let us see concretely
what happens with virtual
inheritances.
What happens in our example
if we render these two inheritances
virtual?
The "Ovovivipare" class will
only have one single head.
What will happen is that we will
only create one "Animal"
in "Ovovivipare".
We will no longer create two
animals inside "Ovovivipare".
This solves the aforementioned
problem.
Now let us see how
virtual classes,
virtual inheritances,
impact the constructors.
It generates a strong restraint
for the programmer.
But first, a remainder.
Remember that, in a
usual inheritance,
the constructor of the sub-class
calls the constructor
(or the constructors in the case
of multiple inheritance)
of the direct super-classes.
Direct meaning that they inherit
directly from these super-classes.
So, in the case of multiple inheritance
with a virtual super-super-super class,
the responsability to initialize,
to call the constructors
of this virtual super-super-class belongs
to all the sub-classes
we want to create an instance of.
Thus, all these sub-classes,
sub-sub-classes...
which inherit indirectly from a
virtual super-super-super-class,
and are not abstract
(which means we can create
instances of them),
will have to explicitly call
the constructor of the virtual
super-super-super-class.
As you can plainly see, this is
a strong constraint
in the declaration of the constructor
of the sub-classes.
Let us see this concretely
on the Ovovivipare example.
In this case, we have the
sub-sub-class "Ovovivipare",
which inherits from the sub-classes
"Ovipare" and "Vivipare".
These two classes inherit virtually
from the class "Animal".
We thus have a virtual class "Animal".
Consequently, the sub-class
"Ovovipare" must,
in its constructors, directly call
the constructor of "Animal".
We will thus have to write the following
instruction in the constructor of Ovovivipare :
an explicit call to the
constructor of "Animal"
is mandatory here.
Let us suppose this constructor
takes three parameters
before we write the call
to the usual constructor
of Ovovivipare's direct
super-classes.
As we have said, this is a strong constraint
regarding virtual classes.
Now, let us see what concretely
happens when we declare an instance.
Let us declare an instance " o "
of Ovovivipare.
Thus we are calling Ovovivipare's
constructor.
First of all, we will trigger
the constructor of an "Animal".
Thus, when we are building a sub-sub-class,
which inherits from a virtual class,
the first thing we do
is to create the virtual class.
There is only one virtual class.
Indeed, the goal of multiple inheritance
and of virtual classes is
to have only one
virtual classes and not several along
with all the inheritance paths.
Since we have only one virtual class,
we must build it first and foremost.
Consequently, we will build
this "Animal" first.
The first constructor to be
called
is the constructor of "Animal".
Then, we will go back to the
normal calls of the constructors.
Thus, the constructor of
Ovovivipare
will then call the constructor
of Ovipare.
This constructor of "Ovipare"
should normally call the constructor
of the super-class.
But here, since we have
already initialized the super-class,
this call to the constructor of "Animal"
found in the constructor of "Ovipare",
will be ignored.
Similarly, we will then call
the constructor of "Vivipare",
which will ignore the call to
the constructor of "Animal"
since it has already been done.
Let us now sum up the
construction of an Ovovivipare.
First of all, we call the constructor
of "Animal".
Secondly, we call the constructor
of "Ovipare",
in which we ignore the supplementary
call to the constructor of "Animal".
Thirdly, we call the constructor
of "Vivipare",
in which we ignore the supplementary
call to the constructor of "Animal".
Finally, we conclude by
the usual
initialization of its own attributes.
Let us sum one final time.
During the creation of an object
of the most derived class,
the sub-sub-sub-class of
a virtual class,
it is the constructor of this
sub-sub-sub-class
that is tasked with the direct
call to the constructor
of the virtual super-class.
Also, the calls to the constructor
of the virtual super-class
in the intermediate classes
are simply ignored.
Naturally, if the virtual super-class
has a default constructor,
it is not mandatory
to explicitly call its constructor.
But, one way or the other,
there will be a call to this
default constructor :
it will be called during the
creation of the most derived instance.
As usual,
if we omit the call to the constructor
of the virtual super-super-class
in the sub-sub-classes and that this
virtual super-super-class
has not default constructor,
the compiler will naturally
report an error.
Indeed, it will try to call a
non-existing constructor.
So, in a class hieararchy, where
there are virtual super-classes,
the initialization of the
virtual super-classes
must be done by all the sub-classes
we wish to create.
The constructor of the
virtual super-classes
will be called first and foremost.
Then, the calls to the virtual
super-classes
in the intermediate classes
will be ignored.
Regarding non-virtual
super-classes,
they are then initialized in the
order of the inheritance declaration,
as usual.
The call order of the copy
constructors
follows this rule aswell.
As always, the call order
of the destructors
is the reverse order to
the constructors'.
Thus concludes this
sequences on this
slightly delicate subject
of virtual classes,
and virtual inheritance.