Welcome to module 4.2,
our second case study
on urban sanitation.
This time we move to China
and explore an urban eco-san pilot project
implemented between 2004 and 2009
in inner Mongolia, in China.
We chose this case study
because it is one
of the best-documented cases
of a failed attempt to introduce
innovative ecological sanitation solutions
to a new housing estate.
We'd like to thank
the Stokholm Environmental Institute,
and especially Jennifer [McConnville]
for providing us
with the information shown here.
Erdos was a Chinese/Swedish
eco-town project
that aimed to test new frontiers
of waste management.
It involved 832 apartments
and housed around 3,000 people.
When the project was initiated in 2003,
Erdos was just beginning
its rapid expansion
and much of the existing
sanitation provision
was still very poor.
Only one third
of urban hoseholds in Erdos
used modern flush toilets,
and the city periphery
was not connected to any sewers
and mostly relied on on-site solutions.
This slide shows the location
of the Erdos project area,
in inner Mongolia, Northern China.
It is one of the fast-growing areas
of inland China
thanks to exploration
of gas and oil fields.
Some of the features of Dongsheng District
The population was about 250,000
back in 2003.
The area is between 1,400
and 1,600 meters high
with a wide range of temperatures
from -30º in winter to +30º in summer.
However, by 2007, already 75%
of the urban area was sewered.
In line with many Chinese cities.
It should be noted that Erdos
lies in a water-stressed region
with low rainwater fall,
and that historically,
the use of waste as a fertilizer
was quite common.
The project developers decided
that this was an enabling base
for testing newly proclaimed
Chinese recycling economy.
This slide shows the project rationale.
On the right side you can see
a promotional flyer
that was shown and distributed
to attract buyers
for the residential property in Erdos.
The modern apartments
tried to sell the eco-features:
energy saving,
innovation in sanitations systems,
and water savings.
It thus formed a keystone
of the recycling economy
that became the national policy of China.
The housing estate was developed
by a private-public partnership
with a private developer,
the Daxing Estate Co.
as the main investor.
This slide shows the project timeline.
The project was initiated in 2003
by the Dongxing District government
and the Stokholm Environmental Institute.
In 2004 and 5, the housing estate
was constructed.
One of the buildings is shown
in the middle on the bottom.
In 2006, 832 apartments were completed
and the households started moving in.
The photo on the right shows
the source separating toilet,
dry toilet used
for all apartment buildings.
In 2008 two of the buildings
were retrofitted with improved dry toilets
and in 2009, due to high dissatisfaction
with the sanitation system,
all households decided to change
the entire sanitation system
and to revert back
to conventional flush toilet systems.
In 2011 SEI conducted
a project evaluation
and published a book
about its findings in 2012.
Some of the design considerations
of the Erdos project:
It featured a sustainable
environmental sanitation system
with closed loop separated waste streams.
This included separation of feces,
urine, greywater and solid waste,
and the recycling use
of human waste for fertilizer.
This slide shows an overview
of the sanitation system.
Firstly, feces and urine
being separated in the dry toilet,
shown here in the user interface.
The feces and sawdust were collected
in the cellar in plastic bins,
collected and transported and brought
to a thermal composting plant,
and finally after treatment,
brought to a demonstration garden.
The urine was collected
in an underground urine tank,
pumped out at regular intervals,
and also brought
to the demonstration garden.
This slide shows the system design
in a section of one
of the apartment buildings.
It shows the different
urine-diverting dry toilets,
shown here in green
which are connected
to dry collection systems or chutes
which were used as pipes
with 280 mm dimensions.
Additionally, there were vent pipes
connected to each toilet
that ventilated the toilet systems.
These pipes were 110 mm.
Finally the bottom of the system
in the cellar, the feces bins
that were connected
to each of the toilets.
The system as it is shown here
is the first attempt
at introducing
urine diverting dry toilets
in multi-story apartment buildings.
Let's look at the system design.
The picture on the left
shows the dry chute
that are connected
to the collection bins in blue.
Additionally, there were 22
underground urine tanks
that collected the urine
from the different toilets,
and there was also a ventilation system
connected to each toilet
that led to the roof.
The image on the bottom left
shows the onsite treatment station.
Thermal composting of feces
that could treat
1.5 tons of feces per day.
Additionally, there was
a greywater treatment system
that consisted of anaerobic tanks
and sedimentation tanks
that could treat
up to 250 cubic meters per day.
The compost and urine could both be used
in the adjacent demonstration garden
next to the housing estate.
This slide shows the user interface.
The heart piece
of the eco-sanitation system.
It featured an innovative
dry separating toilet
with a teflon coated turning bowl
that separated the users from the waste.
It also featured sawdust
instead of water.
The sawdust was added
to minimize the odor problems,
but also to speed up
the drying process of the feces.
The separated urine was collected
in an underground tank,
shown here in this section,
and was initially used in agriculture.
Later on in the project
it was also dumped
at municipal landfill sites,
or even at clandestine locations
by the emptying company.
The project also included
user sensitization.
This was conducted
through initial training events
after the households moved in.
They also distributed
flyers and reminders
about the correct use of the facilities
and introduced a telephone hotline
where people could complain
about malfunction of their system.
The Stokholm Environmental Institute
also conducted regular
user satisfaction surveys
and this user survey from 2007 and 2008
shows two of the main problems
that arose quite early in the project.
In blue, the odor problem,
which was most pronounced
during the cold months,
especially in December and January,
and the toilet mechanism,
especially the turning bowl parts
and the ventilation,
which are featured in red.
In the next model we'll be looking
at some of the reasons
for the system failure
of the Erdos project,
and why the dissatisfaction
with the toilets
and the sanitation system
eventually led to the dismantling
of the existing system
and replacement with conventional
sanitation flush toilets.