Good morning, good afternoon,
or good evening everybody,
depending where you are.
My name is Isabel Blackett.
I'm the senior sanitation specalist
working for the World Bank [Worsham?]
sanitation program based in the
East Asian regional office in Jakarta.
Today I'm going to present an overview
of some work I did a few years ago
when I first arrived in Indonesia.
It was a very exciting, it was a huge
and very challenging project
in a very complex and diverse country.
For me, it was a fantastic experience
and the teamwork that resulted
in a very good outcome, so something
I will always remember.
I hope you find it useful and inspiring,
and if you ever want to get
in contact with me for more information,
please do so.
But, in the meanwhile, I'll say there's
several publications which I'm sure
[Sendac]? will let you know about.
Thank you.
Hello everybody. Today we're going
to talk about the Indonesia Sanitation
Development Program.
This is going to be a case study
in which we're going to look at
how a national program was started up
and has gone to scale.
We will do a quick overview of how
that happened and the purpose and
output of the project, the program
design, and the inputs and resources.
First of all, if you look at slide 3,
this is a cartoon that I think illustrates
really how sanitation is perceived
in many countries.
I've heard the story
in Africa and in East Asia,
which is mainly where I've worked.
No one wants responsibility.
Sanitation is a dirty,
unpleasant, smelly little child
that no one
really wants responsibility for.
The situation in Indonesia was just
the same as that in 2005.
But four and a half years later
we found the situation
had changed quite dramatically.
This is a situation where people had
begun to accept their responsibility,
but it was seen very much
in terms of self interest.
They would be involved in sanitation
because it was good
for what their ministry would do,
and they would do it together, not --
with no one ministry taking responsibility
but everyone playing their part,
doing that formally.
The question for this session today,
and for part 1 and part 2,
is why did the decision-makers change
their mind and what led them
to changing their minds?
Let me give a bit of background on
the situation of sanitation in Indonesia
prior to starting this program.
The country is a very large one,
240 million people,
and it's almost 50% urbanized.
Sanitation has historically,
and to this current day,
very much seen as a private matter.
And, this is something that
is the perception of the household
but also of local government
and national government.
It wasn't clear to government
what they're supposed to do.
There was no history
in which the government expected
to have to undertake
public health interventions.
This had evolved partly through a rural
situation where people looked after
their own waste, and then
the country had become urbanized,
and then that attitude
had never really changed.
This is illustrated very well by under
2% of the urban areas have actually
access to sewer systems, and in global
terms, especially for a country that's
middle-income or lower-middle income,
it's very exceptionally low.
In fact, in this stage the only country
that has lower sewage access is Laos
and their capitol of Vientiane, which has
about half a million people has actually
got no sewage system at all.
Of the perception -- the country is quite
wet, quite high rainfall,
and there are lots of rivers,
channels and drains, and the perception
is that you don't need a system because
the waste just goes into these drains,
and into these rivers,
and it gets washed away.
Out of sight, out of mind.
But at the same time there is quite
high coverage of household toilets.
I won't call it sanitation, we'll just say
people have access to toilets,
typically 80-90% in urban areas.
People use very simple pour flush pans
connected either to a soakpit
or to a drain or a river.
The confusing thing about soakpits is
they call them "tanky septics,"
which, they certainly aren't septic tanks.
And there's still a really quite high,
again for a middle-income country,
quite high open defecation around
18%, and if you look in the picture,
you see there actually a toilet, a
overhung toilet directly into the river,
and the woman there
is waiting to use it,
and she's queuing because she's
certainly not the only one who uses it.
Very often you see large queues there.
So moving on to slide 6.
This program came in 2006,
the Indonesian Sanitation
Sector Development Program,
and the purpose of the program
was not to build anything at all.
It was to establish a sector, a
sanitation sector,
which had been completely absent.
It was seen that this would happen
through development
and operationalizing policies,
through institutional and regulatory
reforms,
through introduction
of sanitation strategic planning,
and through a great deal
of advocacy and awareness building,
and capacity building.
The program had
four main areas of outputs.
First of all,
the intention was to establish
an enabling environment for sanitation,
which really covers a lot of the things
mentioned in the previous slide.
An environment in which sanitation
could be developed at the local level
and at the national level.
A coordination
and investment framework was needed,
and next to that you'll see a
question mark in the tick.
I think the coordination framework
has been very successfully established.
It started off partly by all the donors
getting together and working together
and after a couple of years of that,
in a sense, the government said,
"well, what are you guys up to?"
and they joined in and we now have a
meeting every one or two months,
could be called in by donors or by
government on particular subjects,
it could be urban, it could be rural,
it could be policy, it could be a review
that's come out...a particular subject
and that's a good dialogue between
all the donors and the government.
Works very well.
Investment framework perhaps
has been a little less successful.
The government didn't seem to see
the need for an investment framework
and they have increased their budgets
as you will learn about in part 2,
but a strategic investment framework
was something that didn't appeal
to the way they do the national budgeting.
The third item was the sanitation
awareness and hygiene campaigns.
These would be designed,
they would be tested, implemented
and they would have
a particular focus on the urban poor.
Again, this has
a question mark and a tick.
At one level this has been
very successfully achieved.
At the other level it was
a fairly painful learning process
in which we realized you
couldn't design these campaigns,
and raise awareness,
when you had no delivery mechanism
and you didn't even know what type
of sanitation you were promoting.
So the local governments
were very reluctant to do
any public awareness work,
because they hadn't got
anything to offer the public
and they didn't have answers
for many tricky questions.
So that became much more
an advocacy program,
and at that level
it was very successful.
Advocacy to get national government
and local governments more involved.
And, as they became more involved, they
had some very specific programs.
They became more confident about doing
sanitation awareness and hygiene work
within communities.
And the third component which I think--
the fourth component was probably
the main hub of this program was
to develop local capacity
and citywide sanitation strategies.
This is where a lot of the initial
focus was built, and we would say
that the national change of attitude
came from the local governments,
not the other way around, and I'll talk a
little more about that later.
We move on to slide 8.
This is a diagram that describes
a very comprehensive program design.
It was designed strategically
to impact at the national level.
But the actual operational focus
of what we were doing on the ground
was happening in specific cities.
This started with six cities, it seemed
to be going very well and we expanded
this to twelve cities. And here we
modeled what we thought could
become a national approach to
dealing with sanitation.
I will talk more about that in part 2.
And then our very specific clients
were poor urban dwellers,
and so we had
some pilots happening at that level
but the community focus
was in poor urban areas,
rather than more generally, and we
call this a poorer inclusive approach.
So what did it take to achieve this?
Very broadly, a great deal of time and
effort, blood, sweat and tears would
be one way of putting it, but we had very
strong buy-in from the government
of Indonesia, initially from the planning
department and the health department
and the ministry of works. Public works
came on board perhaps a little later.
But very strong commitment. They had a
budget and they had staffing
into this program,
so it wasn't a donor-driven program.
We contributed, we contracted
a multi-disciplinary
technical assistance package.
It cost around
$10 million over four years,
but that was done in two sections.
First of all we did two years
to see how that was going
and it was going well,
and then it was extended
for another four years.
So we tested things out and halfway
through we make quite a lot of changes.
There was a government working group
and government staff working alongside
the TA hand-in-hand and they worked
together in a shared office.
This had a lot of benefits.
And the TA was sitting near government,
not near WSP or the World Bank.
At the same time WSP
had a number of other activities
that it was running in parallel,
in very close coordination.
These were the ones
that you may have heard of;
the economics, the sanitation
initiative, a big hand-washing program.
And finally, the point of flexibility.
You cannot design a program like this
up front, five years in advance.
There has to be a continual reflection:
Is this working? Is it not working?
and how do we adjust it?
So that was
the sort of broad framework
of what we set out to do
and what we used.
In part 2, I'm going to talk a bit
more about how it actually happened
and what was achieved.