Hello and welcome to this
second lesson of Electrotechnics 1
in this lesson we will
after the introduction
see how to, together, agree with
a notation for all the MOOC
Electrotechnics 1 and 2 course
we shall also see the way
to do graphical notations
that will enable a universal language
or at least a common one
for all the different lessons
of this MOOC course
The utility of a clear and universal
terminology
,of a normalization of
the reference systems,
of mathematical symbolism,
of graphics,
is evident in all domains of
technical sciences.
The necessity of such an effort
of normalization has been recognized
very, very early in electrical engineering.
In order to present a coherent concept,
the authors of this MOOC course have
decided to follow as much as possible
the recommendations developed
by the international electrotechnical
commission, IEC,
regarding the terminology,
the graphical and literary symbols ;
the system that will be used is the
International System SI,
adopted by the General Conference
on Weights and Measures in 1960.
The mathematical symbols
are those recommended
the International Organization
for Standardization ISO.
Here is the convention on
the direction of current
and on the reference direction of the
voltage that will be used in this course ;
we know that physically,
the electric current corresponds
to a movement of electric charges,
we have here a noted electric current,
we arbitrarily admit that
the direction of the current
is the direction of movement
of the positive charges
and thus the reverse of the
movement of negative charges,
electrons, for example ;
in the establishing of an
electric circuit calculation
this physical direction of the current
is generally unknown at first
and very often we have, for example, an
alternating current, that periodically reverses itself,
thus, the electrical engineer must
attribute to every current
of interest a conventional direction,
mathematical and completely arbitrary.
In direct current, if the calculations lead
to a positive numerical value
the conventional direction coincides
with the physical direction
and in the case of a negative value
the conventional and physical direction
of current are in opposition ;
It is almost of universal use
to indicate in a diagram the mathematical
direction of a current with an arrow
generally positioned on the line connecting
different elements, as indicated here.
Thus, the most positive
point of the voltage
appearing at the terminals of a resistor
crossed by a positive current
is located at the current entrance terminal ;
so we have, like in the diagram
mentionned here
a voltage that is in the same
direction as the current
and then the current comes out
from the resistor, from this side.
Similar to electric currents, voltages
between terminal pairs in a circuit
are not known at first,
thus they must receive an
arbitrary mathematical direction ;
the manner in which the positive
voltage direction is graphically indicated
is unfortunately not yet unanimous
amongst electricians
despite the efforts of the International
Electrotechnical Commission,
this positive direction is generally
indicated on a circuit diagram
either with a pointing arrow,
placed along the element,
as you can see in this drawing,
under " International "
or, by using + and - signs
like in the central diagram here.
The three most frequently encountered
ways in technical litterature
are represented in these three figures
on this diagram,
solutions 1 and 2, I will call
International or Belgium/USA
are recommended by the International
Electrotechnical Commission,
the International solution in which
the direction of reference of the voltage
is indicated by a pointing arrow
from the point of highest potential
towards the lowest potential
is of customary usage in Switzerland
and will be adopted for the entirety
of this Electrotechnics 1 and 2 MOOC
It presents the advantage of guiding
the current and voltage arrows
in the same direction when these values
are of the same sign ;
The middle solution is currently
recommended by the Americans,
and also used in Belgium,
and the solution on the right,
essentially used in France,
in which the lowest potential points
towards the highest potential
is still frequently used in France,
as I've mentioned,
or in all the countries born from
French tradition
in education.
The authors that use this
kind of reference
must explicitly specify it.
In our case, we shall focus
on the first way of writing
by always writing the current,
as you can see here,
from the highest point
to the lowest point
with the voltage in the same element
following the same direction.
The manner of writing is fundamental
to the electric engineer
or electrician,
indeed, the manner of writing
conveys information
it is thus a certain form of language.
I will give you an example here
especially with the currents,
the symbol of the current is i,
We shall also see it later on,
but this letter i can be written
in quite a few ways.
I shall show you several of them here,
first of all, a lower-case i such as here
an underlined lower-case i,
an upper-case I,
an upper-case I with a hat,
an upper-case I with a line,
or also an underlined upper-case I,
we can add one more
another i with a 1.
You can see all these ways of writing
an i that, in the end, indicate a current,
will have very different meanings ;
let's take the first :
if we write an i like this,
lower-case,
well, it will mean that the
value is instantaneous,
so, an instantaneous current.
an underlined current means that
we are using complex number notations,
so we have here,
an instantaneous complex current ;
an upper-case I will mean
an R.M.S. (Root-Mean-Square) current
or a continuous current ;
an i with a hat on top will mean
a peak current or a peak value
so, the maximum value,
we will see all of this when we study
single phase AC systems
an upper-case I with a line on top
will indicated an average value ;
an underlined upper-case I will tell us
that it's an effective value phaser
and finally
the last symbol that I've written here
an i with a small 1,
means that we have here the the first
harmonic of the current.
As you can see, all these conventions
these different ways of writing, convey
a different meaning,
it is thus very important,
fundamental even,
that the engineer who is writing,
who's writing the analytical
calculations absolutely follows
a way of writing, a convention
allowing others
who will continue his work to be able to
follow and understand the steps of the first
and understand the writings of the first.
Graphical representation is
also very important
since it will also convey
a certain form of meaning,
through the notations.
The first graphical representation
that I would like to show you
is a simple conductor that will
like the elements,
we will thus draw here a line,
this is a perfect conductor.
Why is it perfect ?
because we will decide
that if we draw a line, like here,
the resistance of this line is null.
Thus we make the hypothesis that
it is a null resistance,
we make the hypothesis
that every time we've drawn
a line to link the components
these lines are all perfect
or convey a current or voltage
in a perfect manner.
Through this perfect conductor, a current I,
for example will be able to flow
that I'm drawing here ;
another possibility : we have the
possibility of having switchs,
so for example here,
an open switch
the open switch will mean that
current is no longer flowing,
thus in this open switch
we are telling the person looking,
interpreting the diagram,
that the resistances is infinite,
no current can flow through.
Similarly
the closed switch,
that will be drawn
in the following manner
and will mean that our resistance
is once again null
and that all the current is
flowing through the switch
without any problem ;
finally, we will be able to draw the elements
we will detail them later
these elements that, for example
are formed by drawing a small
box, a small rectangle,
or two parallel plates,
and so on,
we will have here some elements
and these elements,
in the end, also represent
but we shall see later on that the
empty square represents a resistor,
that the two vertical plates
represent a capacitor,
and thus convey, behind, the entire physical
aspects linked to these different elements
and finally we shall see a way
of having a certain power
it's what we will call a supply,
we will define theses supplies
together, later on,
but I will already give here the two
fundamental elements of this supply,
supplies are symbolised by a
line with a circle
and we will have here a voltage, for example
for the voltage supply
or a circle with a
horizontal line
for the current supply.
I arrive now at the convention for
supplies that I just told you about
and I've been very careful not
to talk about, at that time
at the time when I've defined the voltage,
the voltage supply and the current supply,
not to tell you in which
direction the current flows
of course we have the choice
as mentioned earlier,
these are only conventions,
we can decide on either one or the other,
what is very important
it's to be constant in the manner of
solving a problem from start to finish
and to use the same convention
from start to finish.
We've seen it previously
for an element such as the resistor,
the flowing current will be
written in the following way
it enters the resistor R
and the voltage at the terminals
follows the same way direction
as the current in this element.
We can see it here in the
diagram drawn on your left,
we have a voltage supply
connected to a resistor,
but in this case, in the voltage supply,
the current is flowing in the opposite
way, in the direction of the voltage
and this way of doing
and in general,
it is recommended to choose a convention
for the direction known as motor type.
systematically
as shown in this diagram ;
the motor convention implies
automatically a positive power
when it is consumed,
negative when it is supplied,
It's a random choice
of the direction for the voltage and current
but we will settle it
once and for all for this course
because if we change
while solving a problem,
this does not allow a proper
interpretation of the powers.
In this case,
we will have in the resistor a voltage
in the same direction as the current
but in the supply, the current is
flowing in the opposite direction ;
thus we write P of R
the power in the resistance,
is equal to u0,
in other words, the voltage between the terminals
of R, multiplied by the current I
which will be equal to R times I squared ;
for the supply, we will write
P of the supply is u0
and here we will have a current
flowing in the opposite direction
or, minus u0 times I
we can see that Ps is equal to minus PR
and as we can see here,
the motor convention implies
a positive power
when it is consumed,
it is what we want
in the resistor,
negative when it is supplied,
it's what we want in the supply ;
thus, from now on and for the entire
Electrotechnics 1 and 2 course
we will use this motor convention
for the supplies
and the international convention for
all passive elements
that we will discover.
In conclusion, we've discovered the
importance of the units of notations
to be absolutely clear from the
beginning to the end of a problem
and this international manner
of agreeing on a language,
a language in its own right,
a universal language,
but to be universal,
it implies being based on a certain
form of international agreement
and we will thus follow the
international conventions of the IEC
for all the conventions of this course.