Hello and welcome to this lesson
dedicated to the main elements of a circuit
and in particular, dedicated to
voltage and current supplies
which will be the primordial
elements to supply energy
to our different
circuit elements.
We will, after the introduction,
see the notations of circuit models,
see how these voltage and current
supplies can be defined.
We will then study the different
basic components and, finally,
in this lesson, how we can
model a complete circuit.
First of all, we will define a
relatively simple notion :
the "dipole" ;
respectively "tripole"
and "quadripole".
What is a dipole ?
It's a component
which will have two terminals.
Hence, we can model
or draw it easily.
It's a "bloc", like this,
on which there are two terminals.
This can be an element
such as a resistor,
a capacitance, an inductance...
It can also be a supply.
The tripole, by evidence related
to the definition of the dipole,
is an element which
will have 3 terminals.
We can mainly find it
in three-phase circuits
when the components linked
to the three-phase system
will include three impedances.
So, for example, a circuit
which we will observe
in the later lessons,
with three terminals.
So here, for example, is a tripole.
And finally, a quadrupole, which will have
- this is a little more complicated -
four terminals that enter
the quadrupole,
rarer, but also possible
with a "two entrances/
two exits" circuit
or vice versa,
that we will write or
define as a quadrupole.
The first element
that we will define,
fundamental when defining
an equivalent model
of an electric circuit :
the voltage supply.
The voltage supply is,
by convention,
drawn in the following
way, in other words a circle
crossed by two vertical lines
and two terminals.
So we typically have here a dipole,
drawn with an arrow from
up to down : the voltage.
We then have, here at this terminal,
the ground or neutral
or the lowest part in the
difference of potential.
We will then write :
the lowest end.
And on the other hand, at the top,
the part with the highest potential,
and by definition, in the supply,
with the conventions that we've seen
during the first lessons of this MOOC,
when the voltages goes from
the highest to lowest point,
the current flows from bottom
to top as shown in this diagram.
We then have here
a load circuit,
in other words, we connect
to this voltage course a resistor,
capacitor, or any other element,
or a combination
of these different elements,
and on your right,
you have a graph
which allows you
to notice the current
that this supply is outputting
as a function of the voltage.
We discover then a phenomenon,
or, let us say, the strange
characteristics of this supply,
which is that this supply
produces the same voltage
- it is constant - no matter the
amount of current it outputs.
It is obvious that such a thing
does not exist in nature.
It is impossible, no matter the
current outputted by this supply,
to, in the end, be able to have
a strictly constant voltage.
Hence, this is a supply
which we will call ideal.
It does not exist, we could say,
quote, "in real life".
Thus, it does not represent a
proper model of the voltage supply
that we can find in the art,
like a battery, battery cells,
or a normal power supply.
This supply will, in
fact, have its voltage
change with the
outputted current.
So we will define this
ideal voltage supply,
in the following way,
We have a voltage
with two terminals.
We know that this supply is ideal.
[dictates] "It does not exist
in real life"
But it will be
immensely helpful
for the modelling
of the real one,
or we shall call it
real voltage supply,
when we will talk about it soon.
An important element is,
in fact, the short-circuit.
A special, or
particular, case :
[dictates] the short-circuit
What is a short-circuit ?
Well, let us take a supply,
a voltage, U, an outputted current as such
and we will connect this supply to a wire
and thus, we short-circuit
our supply.
Well in this case, the current
- since I'm using the previous graph -
I have a nondescript voltage
no matter the current,
and this current is supposedly
always identical to U.
But, this is impossible since,
if I make a short-circuit
the voltage that I have here is zero volts.
And we can already see
here a first problem
and thus we see the impossibility
of having this type
of supply in real life.
We can do the same
with the current supply.
It's even more difficult to imagine
since the current supply is not
a usual element in practice,
in the usage of electricity,
we often mention voltage supplies
but rarely current supplies.
We shall see later on, while studying
the theorems of Thevenin and of Norton
that, in the end, it's two way
to model the same thing.
But the idea of the current supply
is to have an object defined as
once again, as a circle,
but this time not with a vertical
line but with a horizontal one
and a current flow,
defined by the supply itself
and at the terminals, then,
will appear a voltage.
To this current supply we
will also be able to
define - or connect, sorry -
a load circuit.
and you have here, once
again on your right,
a voltage - current graph.
The current is defined by the supply
and we can see that no matter
the current drawn from the load,
once again, the voltage
will adapt here.
It's once again,
like previously,
an element impossible
to have in real life.
So we shall call this
current supply
an ideal supply :
that does not
exist in real life.
So, to redo the
same diagram,
we have here a current supply
with a current i,
I have this dipole
and let's imagine
that I connect...
Better, I do not connect this
supply to anything at all.
By definition, it not possible
to have any current flowing.
However, we just saw in
the previous diagram
that the current is
drawn, no matter what
I connect here to the terminals of the supply.
Thus, an open circuit,
or in other words, we don't connect anything :
[dictates] The current should be null.
But it is impossible, here,
using our definition of
this current supply.
Thus, we once again have,
here this impossibility
and we will need to model
differently the real current supply
that we will encounter.
So, in the end, how to change
this ideal voltage supply
into a real voltage supply
that corresponds to what
we have in the art ?
Well, easily,
by adding a resistor following
the ideal voltage supply.
I will show you
the result.
So we have, first of all,
our supply of voltage U
followed by a resistor
that we will call Ri.
Why Ri ?
Because it's the internal Resistance  of the supply.
Here is our new dipole
which characterizes here,
in all,
this will be
my real supply.
So we will try to convince
ourselves of it
to be sure that we've
made the right choice.
So first of all we will write,
here, a Uo at the supply
to properly say that this supply Uo
is the ideal voltage supply.
While using this supply,
we will never have
this Uo voltage at
the terminals of the U circuit,
and this U supply
which will be the real voltage that
the user we will see from the supply.
So we define :
first of all Uo will be
[dictates] the value of the ideal supply
Ri will be, as we've mentioned
previously, by definition
[dictates] the internal resistance
of the ideal supply.
And finally, U will be
[dictates] the value
of the voltage of the real supply.
Thus, if we apply Kirchhoff to this
small simple element by using U,
Uo and the voltage drop
at the terminals of the resistor Ri,
we can write, knowing that the
sum of voltages will be null,
by going around clockwise,
we have -Uo + Ri x I.
I will write I upper-case by using
the convention that, here,
we have a continuous, or direct, current
and with an I that is like this.
Thus - Uo + Ri x I + U = O.
If we put all of this back together,
we have that the real voltage supply U
is equal to Uo - Ri x I
This, by definition, is
the real voltage supply.
So I mentioned earlier that
there was an impossibility in
the ideal voltage supply.
Let's try to see, now, if we
managed to properly model it,
we should no longer
find any impossibility.
So we will make a small graph
of this voltage supply
with here, again, U and I.
First of all, we can notice that
when I is null, U equals Uo.
So at first, we will find
ourselves, for example, here.
At the end, in other words when U
equals zero in a short circuit
we have that U equals zero.
Thus, we have Uo - Ri x I
equal to zero.
and thus Uo = Ri x I
and finally, this short-circuit current,
I will add CC in subscript,
is equal to Uo / Ri.
This Uo / Ri can be,
for example here,
Uo / Ri is my particular
short-circuit current
and between the two
I have a line
which allows me
to define the characteristics
of the ideal voltage supply.
And you can see that it corresponds,
relatively differently, since
instead of having a horizontal line
with a permanent voltage
no matter the current,
I have a voltage that diminishes
as a function of the current rise
until, finally, a value,
where this voltage at the terminals
of the real voltage is equal to zero.
In this case, the supply is
completely short circuited.
and the short-circuit current,
in other words, the maximum current
that this supply can output
is Uo / Ri.
Thus we've defined here
a model that corresponds
rather correctly and faithfully
to what we can
find in reality.
This real voltage supply
that we have just defined,
we can do the same thing
with the current supply
which will then become
a real current supply
and by definition
this real current supply,
will be, similarly, a current I,
transformed by the addition
in parallel of an internal resistance.
Here again, this element, or this bloc,
becomes a real current supply.
Here also, the impossibility that was there,
earlier, in open circuit,
allows us to perfectly, correctly
model this phenomenon
since by not having anything
connected here to this supply
the current outputted
by the supply I
will simply flow through
the internal resistor.
It's the way to properly model
this real current supply.
We will also see in
in the later chapters,
that this real voltage supply
and this real current supply
have an equivalence,
can be equal,
and this equivalence,
we will discover
that it is present
if this internal resistor is
the same for the voltage supply
and the current supply.
Thus, this model describes reality.
This brings me to
the last element
that I wanted to talk
to you about in this lesson,
it's how to model a complete circuit,
with the elements of this circuit
and with a voltage
supply like Uo here.
Once again, I will remind you of
the notations and definitions
linked to what we have agreed
upon as a convention of signs.
We've agreed that with the supply
that goes from the highest
to lowest potential,
the current flows
in the opposite direction.
And in the elements, the voltage for example,
at the terminals of this resistor
is in the same direction as the current.
Similarly here, the voltage at
the terminals of the inductor.
We have here the current, so the voltage
at the terminals of this inductor
will, again -we will write
in subscript L1, L2 -
here we have again Ur,
but we will write " 2 ".
We have here the U of a capacitor.
And finally, the voltage here
for the third inductor, L3.
This finally allows us,
with the help of simple conventions
and with proper writing,
to apply Kirchhoff's equations.
But it is fundamental for that
to have a unified convention
which allows us to not reverse
things from one mesh to another,
which would absolutely falsify
the resulting equations, when we are
using Kirchhoff's equations.
To finish and to conclude,
I would like to remind you
that the models for the ideal
voltage and current supplies
must, in the end, be
completed, as we've seen,
with an internal resistance
to render it real.
So either by putting a serial
resistor for the voltage supply
or by placing a parallel one
for current supplies.
Then, the direction of currents
and voltages in a complete diagram
as we've seen just here, at the end,
must follow a predefined direction.
You can also define this direction yourself.
There isn't a right or wrong
direction, what is needed is to
have a single way of doing things from
start to finish when analysing your circuit.
Thank you.