Hello, welcome to this new lesson of the
Electrotechnique 1 course.
In the framework of electrical circuits,
it is rarely needed to know the evolution
of the currents and voltages,
in every location of the circuit.
It is then possible to find a basic
equivalent circuit
which is simpler but which
accurately translates
the behaviour of the original circuit.
We call equivalent bipoles or dipoles
two dipoles that have the same current
at all times
when they are under the same voltage,
or vice versa.
A dipole can be reduced to
another, more simple,
dipole by way of different reductions,
provided that they keep the
same characteristics.
We have seen different possible reductions,
such as the Series or Parallel
reductions,
that apply to resistors, current sources,
and voltage sources.
We have seen the voltage divider,
or the current divider,
we will see even other transformations,
like the Y-Δ transformation or
other methods.
In most cases,
these reductions and transformations
are easily applicable,
but of, in particular, complex circuits,
we will mostly apply the
principle of Thevenin
or the theorem of Norton.
These two theorems and also valid
for more simple circuits.
We will now develop these two theorems.
Lets consider a dipole that is characterised
by a certain number of resistors,
a certain number of sources,
whether these are voltage sources
or current sources, for which we
have two terminals, two poles.
The respective expression of the Thevenin
or Norton theorems
say that it is always possible to
reduce such a dipole,
containing any combination of independent
sources and resistor
to a dipole that finally contains only
one ideal voltage source, U0,
with, in series, an internal resistor Ri.
So, this dipole - we put the terminals
a and b-
presents a voltage Uab,
and the extreme simplification of
this original circuit,
is the theorem of Thevenin.
The theorem of Norton says that this dipole
can be reduced to a current source,
equal to icc, in parallel with
an internal resistor,
the same internal resistor,
put in parallel.
Once again, the terminals a and b
and the voltage at the side of these terminals,
is the expression of the Norton theorem.
The equivalence of these dipoles is fulfilled
if they have the same no-load voltage,
and the same short-circuit current,
and so fatally, the same internal resistor,
is the equivalence between the real voltage
source and the real current source,
that we saw in the previous lesson.
It is now a question of determining
these three parameters,
the no-load voltage, the short-circuit
current and the internal resistor,
that, in fact, represent this source,
this more complex dipole.
So, let's take these diagrams back,
it is now a question of determining the
no-load voltage U0,
which is, in fact, the voltage Uab,
from the original voltage,
when the current is equal to zero.
It is now still a question of representing
or determining the current icc,
which is the current between the
terminals a and b,
when the dipole is short-circuited,
namely when the voltage Uab
is equal to zero.
The internal resistor is the resistance
seen from outside the dipole,
when all the sources are cancelled.
I represent the dipole here,
the terminals a and b,
the internal resistor seen from
outside the dipole, Ri,
it is the resistance between the terminals ab,
when all the sources are cancelled out,
namely all the uj are equal to zero,
and all the ij are also equal to zero,
and we have seen that this internal resistor
is the ratio of U0 over icc.
By knowing these three parameters
between U0, icc, Ri,
we completely determine the source,
knowing that Ri is equal to
the ratio of u0 over icc.
Lets now pass to a concrete
example.
We consider this circuit, which is
composed of a source and a load,
we define the dipole ab between
these two terminals a and b.
This is then the source,
this is the charge,
and this dipole here can be simplified
into the following dipole,
by the Thevenin theorem,
a no-load voltage in series with an internal resistor.
It now a question of calculating this
no-load voltage Uab,
and to calculate the short-circuit current.
For the no-load voltage...
the no-load voltage is the dipole voltage
when the resistor R3 doesn't exist,
the circuit is open.
We can then write the following equation,
firstly,
the current i1 is equal to the current i2,
so there is only one loop in the circuit,
and so i1 or i2 is
equal to the source U1,
divided by the sum of these
two resistors R1 and R2,
since they are in series.
Finally, the voltage that appears between the
points a and b in no-load,
also correspond to the voltage drop at
the terminals of the resistor,
namely that U3 is equal
to R2 times i2
and this is equal to R2 divided by
R1 plus R2, multiplied by U1,
and this is the no-load voltage.
Lets calculate now the short-circuit current.
It is the current passing through
the terminals a and b,
when we short-circuit them,
namely when we replace the resistor
R3 by a null resistor.
We simply find that icc is equal to
U1 over R1,
since the short-circuit cancels out, here,
the effect of the resistor R2.
We have then determined the no-load voltage
and the short-circuit current,
we can now determine the internal resistor
of the circuit, the dipole,
the internal resistor is the ratio
of U0 over icc,
and it is equal to, U0 is R2
over the sum of these two resistors,
multiplied by R1, and
multiplied by 1 over icc,
namely R1 over U1, which finally
gives for the internal resistor,
the product of R1 times R2
over the sum of R1 plus R2.
Here is our original dipole which is here,
replaced by the simplified dipole,
found with Thevenin's theorem.
We can assure ourselves that the internal
resistor seen from outside,
Ri which is the resistance seen when
all the sources are cancelled out,
well, R1 in parallel with R2
is equal to the product of R1.R2
over the sum of R1 plus R2.
Now that we have completely
determined
the three parameters U0, icc and Ri,
we can express the current i3
and the voltage U3, or Uab,
in function of the resistor R3,
we know that the current i3 is equal to U0
over the sum of Ri plus R3,
and the output voltage Uab or U3,
is equal to the product of R3 times i3,
which is equal to R3 over Ri
plus R3, multiplied by U0.
We recognise here the expression
of the voltage divider.
There, the simple simplifications
are often applicable,
but for complex circuits or sub-circuits,
we can usefully apply the theorems
of Thevenin and Norton:
they guarantee the dipole equivalences.
Later, we will see more methods for
circuit transformations.