Hello! Today we will talk about the impedance
of a dipole
and its inverse the admittance, and also
the way which can be carried
to combine them when
they are in a network.
We will first remind the
definition of the impedance
and see its representation
in the complex plane.
We will then see how we will combine
these impedances,
We will finally see the equivalent
tripoles in AC steady state
also the voltage divider and
the current divider,
as we saw in DC steady state
but this time in AC steady state.
So either a dipole characterized by
a complex impedance,
its the real part of the
complex impedance,
called the resistance R of the dipole.
The resistance R is therefore
the real part of Z.
I remind you that Z, is the ratio of
the voltage over the current,
and this is equal to U over I,
multiplied by cos phi,
it's the resistance.
The imaginary part of the complex
impedance is called the reactance,
of the dipole written X.
Therefore X is the imaginary part of Z,
and it's equal to U over I times sin phi.
Now lets considerate the inverse of the
impedance, that is to say the admittance.
The real part of the admittance
is called the conductance.
G is therefore the real part
of the inverse of the impedance,
therefore the admittance that we write Y,
and is equal to I over U,
multiplied by cos phi,
it's the conductance.
Finally the imaginary part of the
complex admittance
is called susceptance, and
is written B,
it is the imaginary part of Y, that
is equal to I times U time sin phi,
with the minus sign here
because phi is negative.
And this is the susceptance.
In the complex plane, we can represent
the impedance and the admittance.
The impedance Z is represented here.
These transformation equations
allow to transit
from a polar representation
to a Cartesian representation or
rectangular.
Knowing that R, the real part is the projection
of the vector Z on the real axis,
the imaginary part is the projection
of this vector on the imaginary axis,
and for the transit in the other way,
the norm of the vector Z can be found
by Pythagorean by calculating the square
of each side of the right-angled triangle.
And the angle is determinate by
the tangent arc
of the imaginary part over
the real part.
For the admittance, which is
the inverse of the impedance,
again, we have the polar representation
with a norm and an argument,
or the Cartesian representation,
With the real coordinate
and the imaginary coordinate.
As the admittance Y is the inverse
of the impedance Z,
at the norm, the length of the vector,
it will be the inverse, namely if
Z has a norm of 1.25,
Y will have a norm of 1 over 1.25,
namely 0.8.
For the argument, it will be the opposite,
that is to say that if phi is positive for Z
it will be negative for Y,
we can easily see it here.
We will now combine the impedances
in series or in parallel.
In the first case, the serial case,
we want to know the equivalent
serial impedance Z,
that is the sum of the impedances Z1,
Z2, till Zn,
we find that Zs is equal to
the sum of k, d Zk.
By against for the total equivalent admittance
Ys, is the inverse of Zs,
and this inverse of the sum
of the impedances,
or the inverse of the sum
of the inverses,
namely 1 divided by the sum
over K of the inverses.
As regards the admittances, when
they are in parallel,
they add themselves, that is to say that
the equivalent admittance in parallel,
is the sum over K of all the
admittances K.
Therefore we here see the advantage
to use the admittances,
because in parallel it's easy, we
add them.
By against, for the equivalent parallel
impedance,
again, by analogy,
one is the inverse.
Namely Yp is the inverse of Zp,
and is also the inverse of
the sum of the admittances,
or the inverse of the sum of the inverses.
On the following board, we have a few
examples of usual circuits,
for which we have calculated the
impedance and the admittance.
We see that for two impedances in series,
here a resistance that is
purely resistive,
we can add the impedance of the
inductance, that is omega L,
to get the equivalent total of
this dipole,
that is R + JωL,
ωL being the part, the reactance
of the inductance.
We can calculate the inverse, namely
the admittance of this circuit, of this dipole,
and we find after a few calculations,
this result here with a real part
that is R divided by the denominator,
that is a scalar,
and the imaginary part omega L divided
by this same denominator.
We have here other examples.
Here, few examples
of circuits in parallel,
we see the whole interest to work
with admittances
because the admittances in parallel add
themselves
and we find the admittance of R,
it's 1/R,
the admittance of the inductance,
is 1/ωL,
and we can do minus 1/ωL, and we then
can do the sum very easily,
and then return, at the impedance,
with a notation of that form there.
Here, a few other examples.
In DC steady state, we saw the
transformation πT.
This is a circuit in π,
and this one is a circuit in T,
and we have calculated a relation
to determinate,
to make the transit from one another,
namely to determinate the impedances,
or the resistances in this case here,
of Z12, Z31 and Z23,
knowing Z1, Z2, Z3.
These two circuits are perfectly
identical,
they behave in the same way.
To make the transit between one another,
by considering the impedances,
we can do the same reasoning that we
did with the resistances,
but we will do it this time with
the impedances,
we directly give the result,
for example,
if we want to determinate the value of Z1
as function of the elements of the circuit in π,
Z1 is equal to Z12 times Z31, namely
the impedance from point 2
is from point 3, divided by the sum
of three impedances of the circuit in π.
Z23 + Z31.
We write here that the additions and
these multiplications, divisions,
must be done with
complex numbers.
The transit of the circuit T into a circuit π
is done by applying the following relation:
we have that Z12, namely the impedance
between point 1 and point 2,
is equal to the sum of duplicates,
Z1 times Z2, plus Z2 times Z3,
plus Z3 times Z1
divided by the impedance
of the opposite knot, namely Z23.
We give all these relations to calculate all
the impedances,
either the circuit in T,
or either the circuit in π.
As regards the voltage divider or
the current divider,
that are represented here,
voltage divider, current divider,
we found a result
with resistances,
one can extrapolate the impedances,
by knowing we must use
complex numbers to treat
these impedances,
for example U1 which is the voltage
drop at the terminals of this impedance Z1,
is equal to Z1 divided by the sum
of the two impedances, multiplied by U.
For the current, we have found
the result that was the following type.
The current I1 that flows through a branch,
is the Z2 impedance's quotient,
opposed to the branch over the sum
of the impedances Z1 + Z2,
multiplied by the total current.
It also gives the relationship for U2 and I2.
Again, I remind you that these variables
are complex numbers,
and must be treated with
the rules of the complex calculation.
We define the dipole's impedance
and its inverse the admittance,
and also their graphical representation
in the complex plane.
We saw the combination rules
of these elements in a network,
and we also saw that it was sometimes
useful to work with admittances
to simplify the calculations.
We saw a board of usual circuits,
this board is not exhaustive.
As in the DC steady state,
we saw the equivalent tripoles,
and the voltage dividers,
current dividers.
Always remember to work
with complex variables.
Thank you for your attention.