Hello, welcome to this new lesson
of the Electrotechnics Course.
Today, we will discuss
about two methods
that we have developed
in the DC steady state and we will adopt
for the AC steady state.
First of all,
we will initially see
the Thevenin and
Norton theorems
applied to a circuit
under the AC steady state.
Secondly,
we will see under which conditions
we can apply
the superposition principle
in the AC steady state
and we will then see a small example.
To recall, the Thevenin theorem
says that any dipole,
here we have an example of dipole
with elements inside
and we have here the two dipoles.
Therefore,  any dipole could be replaced
by a real voltage supply, then an ideal voltage supply,
in series with an internal impedance.
A real voltage supply
when the voltage U0, here,
is the no-load voltage of the dipole
and that the internal impedance Zi correspond
to the ratio of the open-circuit voltage
and short-circuit current.
Therefore Z, here, is equal to U0
the non-load voltage divided by
the short-circuit current
when we short the dipole.
Same, the Norton theorem
says that any dipole
can be replaced by
a real current supply,
then, here, by an ideal current supply,
in parallel with
an internal impedance.
Therefore, a real current supply
with the current Icc, here, is the short-circuit
current of the dipole
and with an internal impedance
equal to the one of the real
voltage supply U0
which is equal to Zi*Icc
The condition so that the
Thevenin theorem
and Norton theorem
are applicable
is that all the supplies
in the dipole
should have the same frequency.
If the dipole is equivalent to
a real voltage supply
or an ideal voltage supply,
then, there is also an equivalence
between a real voltage supply
and a real current supply.
If we replace the dipole, or the circuit,
by this real voltage supply,
or only part of the circuit
we obtain the equivalence
applying this relation,
namely, the ideal
voltage supply is equal to the ratio
of the no-load voltage U0 divided by
the internal impedance
and the internal impedance, which is
in series with the voltage supply,
is here in parallel
with the current supply.
The inverse operation,
that is to say if we isolate
in the circuit
or if replace the circuit, this dipole,
we find out the equivalence
of the real current supply
with the real voltage supply
replacing the tension U0 by
the product Zi*Icc.
And we replace the internal impedance in parallel
by an internal impedance in series.
As we've already seen in the DC steady state,
we can also determine
the internal impedance
removing all voltage
supplies and computing
the impedance seen from outside,
the dipole impedance,
and we therefore obtain the internal impedance.
We will now see a small example.
If the voltage supply is equal to U0
that we write under
the exponential complex form,
then a norm times an
exponent exp(j alpha)
and that the internal impedance Zi is equal
to an internal resistance plus
an internal reactance Xi,
the current for the transformation,
the short-circuit current will be given
under Icc=U0/Zi
which is equal to the norm times exp(j alpha)
divided by the internal
resistance plus the internal j X.
We can see at that stage of development
that it is not easy to solve
this kind of fraction.
We will then use the
exponential properties,
we will transform this part,
which is in cartesian form,
to an expression in polar form.
Then we can rewrite
the identical numerator exp(j alpha)
and then the denominator
that we will write as a
norm times exp(j phi),
an argument, knowing that Zi,
using Pythagoras,
is equal to square root of Ri² + Xi²
and that the argument phi is given by
tangent arc of the imaginary part,
the reactance Xi,
divided by the internal resistance.
Written like that,
we can simply rewrite the equation
as U0/Zi*exp(j(alpha-phi))
and this is the current expression,
namely, Icc*exp(j beta)
and, by analogy, we see that
the norm of Icc is U0/Zi
and the argument beta is equal to alpha minus phi.
Then, the mathematical operations
must be carried out using
the rules of Complex calculation.
In this second part of the lecture,
we will see how
could we apply
The superposition principle
in the AC steady state.
As a reminder, the superposition principle
says that the response of a circuit,
namely a current somewhere
in the circuit
or a voltage across
an element of the circuit,
the circuit response to a sum of
excitations is equal to
the sum of the responses
of each excitation.
taken individually.
As in the DC steady state, the superposition
principle is applicable
but as long as,
the steady state is linear.
As a reminder, the linear term
means that the value R of a resistor
doesn't vary with the current
flowing through it.
Therefore, the relation U = R*I
is still valid.
Same for an inductance,
its value L will not vary
with the current flowing through it,
so it does not saturate.
And, finally, the value C
of a capacitor
doesn't vary with the voltage
which is present at its terminals.
We will then threat these two cases:
The first case for which
all the supplies
of voltage and current
have the same frequency.
We  successively consider
each individual supply
to know its response
for the requested variable.
The final variable is
the vector sum
of individual contributions
of each supply.
So for a variable
that we call here X,
The variable Xtot is the contribution,
the vector sum
of each contribution
of each supply.
The variable X in this equation
can be either a voltage
or a current
but not a power.
Why? Because the power
is a quadratic function
and then not linear, so the superposition
principle is not applicable
in the case of powers.
We can demonstrate,
namely, if we write
the power P1
that will be dissipated  in the resistor
R due to the supply 1,
this power would be equal to R*I1².
The power P2 that would
be the dissipated power
in the resistor due to supply 2,
would be equal to R*I².
But the total power is not equal
to this, why?
Because Ptot, which is
the sum of two powers,
is not equal to R times
the total current I1 + I2 squared.
Why? Because the last expression
can be developed as follows...
where you can see this double product,
here, showing that for the powers
the superposition principle
is not applicable.
We threat now a second case.
It is the case for which
all the supplies
of voltage and current
don't have the same frequency
and the method is:
We will first regroup
the supplies based on their frequencies,
that is to say we take all
the supplies that have the same frequency
and we will put them together
and for each group of frequency,
we will apply the method seen in case A.
Therefore, we will have a vector sum
of contributions for each frequency,
it is expressed here.
For the first frequency
we have a first contribution
of the supplies at that frequency
and for this frequency,
we have again a sum
of contributions,
and so forth for all the frequencies.
Finally, the addition of
the vector sums,
of the sums here, of the contributions
has to be done, finally,
in the temporal domain.
This transformation in
the temporal domain
we will do it now,
we will threat only a simpler case,
a general case where we will
have only two frequencies.
For the first frequency f1,
we will have a sum of all
the contributions that we call Xtot1,
that i can write under
the exponential form
with a norm:
Xtot*exp(j alpha1)
and I will transform
this effective complex phasor
in an instantaneous complex value,
in the temporal complex domain.
The norm which is here under effective form,
I will take its peak value,
namely a square root of 2 times Xtot,
times exp(j),
we reintroduce the omega1 pulsation,
omega1 times t plus alpha1,
and this is equal to small x, lower case x,
because it depends on the time, xtot1.
Same for the second frequency
we've identified
where we have the sum of the contributions Xtot2
under exponential complex form
we can write as Xtot2
-- sorry I've forgotten here the 1 --
times exp(j alpha2),
that we transform in
a instantaneous complex value
namely a square root of 2 times Xtot2,
-- sorry I've forgotten again the 1 here --
then the peak value times
exp(j oméga2*t + alpha2)
and this is equal to xtot2.
Now, to have the final result,
we will add these two
partial results,
we have that xfinal, the instantaneous
complex value
in the temporal domain,
is equal to xtot1 + xtot2.
If we develop, we have xfinal,
as function of time,
equals to square root of 2 times
xtot1 times the exponential.
And the second term
for the second frequency,
square root of 2 times
xtot2 times the exponential.
The exponential sum
is not well suited
for the additions so we will transform
these instantaneous complex values
in instantaneous values
in the temporal domain
and then the final value ....
will be equal to square root of 2 times
xtot1 times
the sin (oméga1 t + alpha1),
plus the second contribution,
square root of 2 times xtot2 times
sin (oméga2 t + alpha2).
Let's consider now this small example
where an RL circuit is supplied,
the circuit will be excited using two supplies:
a first supply U0
which has a certain frequency,
here a frequency null,
it is a continuous supply,
and a second excitation,
it is the voltage U1
which has a second frequency equal to 50Hz.
Therefore, the excitation is caused
by these two supplies in this circuit
and we are looking for the response,
here in this case the total current.
We can then decompose this circuit
into two sub-circuits,
the first one where we consider only
the voltage supply U0
and we will have the following result:
the voltage supply U0, the resistor R,
the inductance L and the contribution of Itot,
the contribution of U0
that we call here I0.
We will add the contribution
of the second excitation,
of the second supply
which lead us to the following circuit:
a voltage U1 which feeds the circuit RL
and whose answer is  the current I1.
The total current will be the sum
of these two contributions I0 and I1.
So let's develop now
the equations.
the impedance Z of this circuit is given by
the real term R plus
the imaginary term j omega0 times L,
and omega0 is the frequency
of the supply U0
which is equal to zero so
this term here is null,
it remains only R.
The current I0 resulting therefrom
is given by:
I0 equals to U divided by
the total impedance, then R.
It is our first result.
Concerning the second excitation,
once again we have the impedance Z
which is equal to R, the real part,
plus the imaginary part here
that is equal to j omega1 times L,
this time omega1 is not
equal  to zero,
we will have to take this into account
in the calculations.
and we can write by Kirchhoff that
this voltage is equal to the voltage
drop across the two elements,
we have then U1 equals
to the impedance Z,
which are in series,
times I1.
And then, I1 is
the ratio of U1 over Z.
We develop this term
and we obtain that I1 is equal to U1,
we divide the normes,
divided by the norm of Z,
here using Pythagoras, we find
that it is equal to square root of R² + X²,
i directly replace X,
with omega square L
X2 times the exponentials.
We assumed that U1
is equal to U1*exp(j0),
no phase shift with respect
to time gives 0,
and then we have here the exponential
of -jφ1,
φ1 being the arguent here
of the impedance Z.
φ1 is equal to the arc tangente
of the imaginary part ω1L/R.
In instantaneous value, we obtain that
the instantaneous complex current is equal to
the peak value,  that is
to say the square root of 2 times the effective value I1
times exp(jω1t - φ1),
that I express in the time domain,
we have then I1 equals to
the peak value Î1, this term,
times sin (ω1t - φ1).
The contribution current of the other supply
is equal to I0
and we recall here that it is U0/R.
The total current is therefore
the sum of the two contributions ...
and it is equal to U0 over R plus
square root of 2 times U1
divided by the norm of Z,
this is the current,
times sin (ω1t - φ1).
This being the final result.
That's it, we have shown that the theorems
of Thevenin and Norton
are valid in the AC steady state
but with the additional condition
compared to the DC steady state,
is that all supplies
must have the same frequency.
Concerning the principle
of superposition,
it is also valid
under the AC steady state
but we should distinguish two cases:
The first case where all
the supplies have the same frequency,
and we can in that case make the addition
in the complex domain
with phasors,
The second case where all
the supplies don't have the same frequency,
we should regroup in this case
the supplies according to their frequency
and then, in the end, go through
the temporal domain to make the addition.
Thank you for your attention.