Madam, Sir, good morning and welcome
to this new lecture about powers.
We will discover during this lecture
that it exist not only one power
with only one name, but several
types of powers,
starting with the instantaneous power
then we will discover
what are the active, reactive,
apparent,
and also the complex apparent powers.
First of all, the instantaneous power.
We can right what we already know from
a long time ago
about the power.
The power being defined by the product
of the instantaneous values
of the voltage and the current.
We can then write
that this instantaneous power
product of the current and the voltage,
but in instantaneous values, gives that.
After small development,
we will end up with an equation
or a clearer result
in order to understand what means
this instantaneous power.
First of all, a linked part here
not to the time but rather to an angle
and then a cosine
whose frequency is twice
which gives, for the effective values here
and not anymore peak values
in order to simplify the writing ...
So, to simplify here,
I note that phi, as we've
already seen previously,
it is the difference of angle between
the voltage's angle
and the current's angle.
This instantaneous power function
has a constant component
UIcos و,
as you see, it doesn't depend on time,
and a sinusoidal component
of amplitude  UI and of a double frequency.
What's interesting to do now,
it is to draw the graph
of this function
in order to better understand
what's happening in terms of exchange.
First of all, we've represented here,
high above,
the graph of the voltage U(t),
instantaneous voltage,
then, the current graph
as a function of time I(t).
And finally, that instantaneous power
we've just computed.
We remark here, the dotted line
that corresponds to UIcos و,
it's that constant
that we've talked about before,
that we've found in the equation
of the instantaneous power.
And around this constant,
an added a cosine
at the double frequency.
We therefore see that, from time to time,
we have a exchange of positive power
even, here in this graph,
an exchange of negative power,
but, in average,
we have this exchange here: UIcos و.
It is now interesting,
to develop what w
have previously written
to write it a bit differently.
We will bring out
two fundamental components
of the instantaneous power
under sinusoidal steady state.
First, we put:
the angle beta which is equal
to alpha minus phi
and we also put
the following trigonometric identity:
cos (2ِt + 2ل - و)
It is equal to :
cos و cos (2ِt + 2ل)
+ sin و sin (2ِt + 2ل).
It looks more complicated,
it even complicates the equation
that we have seen before,
but if we replace this identity
in the pulsating part
of the instantaneous power
that we have previously written,
we end up with the following result:
this instantaneous power that will be equal to
to UIcos و that multiplies
[1 + cos (2ِt + 2ل)]
+ UIsin و sin (2ِt + 2ل).
So, here we will see something very
interesting in these two components,
the first one, that corresponds
to the first term of the second member,
is a component
pulsed always positive,
it's:
cos (2ِt + 2ل)
always positive,
hovering around the
average value  و UIcos.
It translates an exchange
of a unidirectional energy
between a supply and a load.
Then, the second part corresponds
to the second term of the second member,
and it is an alternative component
that varies sinusoidaly
with the amplitude UIsin و
and then, the average value
is always equal to zero.
It is then alternatively
positive and negative,
and it shows here,
an oscillatory and reversible energy exchange
between the supply and the load.
So, we can already observe something,
when phi is equal to zero,
namely, a load purely resistive,
the cosine of phi here will be equal to 1,
the sine of phi here will be equal to 0,
the average value UIcos و
is therefore maximal and is equal to U time I
whereas the second part,
as we've already said before, will be null.
On the contrary, there is another extreme,
when phi is equal to ً/2 or -ً/2,
then the load is purely reactive,
an inductance or a capacitance,
so in this case, it is this power
which will be maximum because
sin و will be equal to 1 or -1
whereas the  UIcos و will be equal to 0
and this part becomes zero.
We will then define here
this first part
as being an active power
and this second part.
reactive power.
This active power indicates
an energy transformation.
This energy will be transformed,
will be used,
whereas the reactive power
is an energy exchange
between the supply and the load
but without transformation.
It is the fundamental
part of our course
that we will see
during all that lecture
and we start
by defining now
one after the other,
that active power
and that reactive power.
But before that, and to
better understand,
I would like to show you now
a movie that will allow you
to visualize that exchange of energy
either active or reactive
or both at the same time
when in the presence
a load of both resistive
and reactive
As you may seen in this graph
we have drawing here the total power,
with the reactive and active terms
and you see actually in the top middle,
in the imaginary plane,
the vector of the impedance Z.
We see that impedance Z that changes.
Now, that impedance
is purely reactive.
We then see that the reactive term
in dotted purple lines, is maximum
whereas the active term is null.
We will see when that impedance
varies again
the change of this power,
with once again a passage
with an impedance purely reactive,
at that moment, the active term is complete
and the total power is equal to the active term.
And here again a change arriving
to a capacitance, because Z has now
an angle of -ً/2 (capacitor)
and you have again
the reactive power
that completely dominates
and the active term which is null.
Here again a change,
in other to well understand
that energy exchange
between the supply and the load.
And as I mentioned previously,
either that exchange is purely alternative
in supply and load,
or we have then
an energy transformation.
We define now
the active power.
As we have seen before,
this active power is the mean
value of the instantaneous power,
this is the definition
of the active power,
the mean of the instantaneous
power p(t).
We can then write that
this average of p(t),
which is written as p(t) with a bar,
which is equal to capital P,
we will define this as a variable now,
P will mean the active power,
or the mean value
of the instantaneous power,
and by definition, the mean value
is the integral from 0 to T
of the function p(t)dt
and this mean value
if we reconsider the equations
previously written,
it is only the part
that does not vary with time
that to say UIcos و.
So, to be very clear,
we can maybe already
do three small cases.
If we take the case of the resistor.
A resistor has an angle
of the impedance which is null
and that will make this active power equals,
for only a single resistor,
to U times I.
For the case of the impedance.
The inductance has an angle
equals to ً/2,
which leads us
to an active power = 0.
The cosine of ً/2 will be equal to 0,
So here we have an active power which is null.
And for the capacitance, the angle is equal to -ً/2
and the active power
is still equal to 0.
The active power, measurable
by a power meter,
corresponds to a real supply
of convertible work
or heat energy.
And, we can see it here,
this is possible only
with a resistor.
The two other elements,
inductance and capacitance,
can't transform that energy,
convert it
to work or heat
and, as mentioned before,
the active power is maximum
in case of load purely resistive,
this is what we see
in this small table.
We can then define now
a reactie power.
Definition:
This reactive power,
you have seen it before,
there is an exchange
of energy.
With the active power we notice that,
when we try to compute
the active power of an inductance
or a capacitance,
we end up with a result null
and yet we know that
there is an exchange of energy.
We have seen it in the equation,
where we clearly see these two different terms.
this exchange is described being
oscillating around a value UIsin و.
We will define
this reactive power.
We will choose the symbol or the letter Q
as UIsin و
that corresponds to this alternative
exchange of energy.
So, so that there is
no confusion,
we will give to it an other variable
than the active power,
written in Watt,
and this reactive power
will be written as var
for Volt Ampere Reactive.
Therefore, the reactive power P,
which is equal to UIcos و, is measured in Watts
and the reactive power defined here,
is measured in Volt Ampere Reactive
in order to avoid any confusion.
It's actually here,
for the reactive power,
a fictive power.
It doesn't respond to a
real physical definition
but it allows us to characterise
that nonconvertible exchange of energy
that appears in the case
of a reactive load:
Inductance or capacitance.
Although this exchange corresponds
to a zero balance
after an integer number of periods,
it must nevertheless take account
the circulation of this energy
in particular on
a distribution network.
If you have here a pylon with wires
from one load to another,
the energy that flows here,
we have a current i,
a voltage between the wires,
even though this current is going back and forth
as function of time,
fifty times per second,
and even if finally this balance is zero,
we will have losses on the line
and these losses have an
overall impact on the network.
So it is necessary to
characterize this exchange
by this so-called reactive power.
We will again define
a third power.
If we consider the two first
were reactive and active,
the third one is called apparent power.
It corresponds to
the product of the effective values
of the voltage and the current.
It is expressed conventionally,
to distinguish it,
in yet another unit
as we saw earlier
which are the Volt Ampere.
This product has the dimension of a power
but it does not necessarily
provide a work
hence the name of apparent power .
By definition, this power
which will take the S symbol,
is the product of U times I.
As now said,
we will note it in Volt Ampere.
Is the amplitude of the fluctuations
of the instantaneous power
compared to its average value
so called apparent power.
This variable is finally linked
to the two powers that
we have seen before:
the reactive and the active power,
because if I remind you that
P is equal to UIcos و,
that Q is equal to UIsin و
then it seems almost obvious here,
when we know
the trigonometry calculations,
that S is equal to P‚ + Q‚.
Then the apparent powers,
corresponding to a module,
can not be
added algebraically
because of this.
Contrariwise, one of the properties
is that if one is looking
at the total power in a circuit,
the total power in a circuit
is the sum of individual P
and the individual is from 0 to k, the number of
items that we have in the circuit.
We can do the same
for the total reactive power,
it is the sum of i from 0 to k
of individual Q.
This is a very good way,
that will be seen in another lesson,
we can use this property
to solve the problems.
On the other side, beware the total S
is not equal to the algebraic
sum from 0 to k of Si.
We can only do that
on the active and reactive power
but not on the apparent power
because of this relation
that you have here
and making things non-linear
and therefore impossible to solve.
To finally allow the possibility
of having the sum of these powers
corresponds to the sum
of the different elements,
a new power is invented,
another new power
called complex
apparent power.
It is a pure conceptual product
to mathematically finally allow
to do the sum,
this time a vector sum,
of the different apparent
powers of the elements
correspond to the total complex apparent
power of the circuit.
We will therefore define
this complex apparent power
as being always S,
but now it is vectorial,
it is underlined,
P + jQ or Se(jو)
Once again,
it is purely conceptual.
Here you have in the imaginary plane
written the vector S with
its purely real component P,
its purely complex component Q.
It brings together
the various powers
previously defined
by making its real part the active power
and its imaginary part the reactive power.
Here, the property is that
this total underlined S, but this is vectorial,
this time is equal to the sum,
but this time vector sum,
of the different apparent powers.
It is interesting to see again
some properties of
the complex apparent power.
In fact, if we define
the complex conjugate of the current
as being this current
with a negative angle relative
to the normal current,
we can say that
the complex apparent power it is
U times I complex conjugate.
We will demonstrate here.
We take an impedance Z
which is equal to R + jX.
We will replace in this expression,
the expression written here:
U times I conjugate complex,
replacing U with the equation
of the law of Ohm Z times I.
This becomes S underlined,
we replace U with Z.I
that further multiplies the
complex conjugate I.
One of the well-known relations
is that a vector multiplied by
its complex conjugate
becomes purely real,
we have then here Z underlined that multiplies I‚
but which is not a vector anymore,
it is just I‚.
And if we write it  ZI‚ and we develop it
it becomes obvious that we have RI‚ + jXI‚
What have we just discovered?
We've just discovered here
the active power,
that corresponds to the Joule losses,
and here the reactive power,
that corresponds to the exchange of energy
related to the reactance X
which may be here a capacitance
or an inductance.
We can then write and summarize that P,
which is equal to UIcos و,
is also equal to RI‚
and that the reactive Q,
which is equal to UIsin و,
is also equal to XI‚,
another way to compute
the active power
or the reactive power
if we know for instance
the impedance value and,
even better, the current value.
I come to the synthesis of our lesson
where I summarized here,
on this graphic or rather on this table,
the active power, the reactive
power and the apparent power
for a purely inductive,
capacitive or resistive load.
We summarize and we note that,
for a single resistor,
the active power,
as it is equal to UIcos و,
will be equal to UI.
On the other side, as we have already seen,
the reactive power UIsin و,
if sin و is equal to 0, this is null
and the apparent power
is always equal to UI.
Then, the inductance.
The inductance, as we have seen
for the active power,
the angle of this impedance is equal to ً/2,
we have here an active power null
whereas the reactive power
is equal to UI,
and the apparent power
doesn't depend on the angle
so it is always UI.
And finally for the capacitance where
the angle is equal to -ً/2,
the active power is alway null,
the reactive power is negative -UI,
and finally the apparent power is equal to UI.
We first remark here
for those who discover
the active and reactive powers,
and especially those who are used to
the active power
which is always strictly positive,
they are Watts,
we can only see 10, 100, 100 Watts
but not negative.
The reactive power,
cant be negative.
It will characterize the load
and its reactive value,
either inductance or capacitive
depending on the plus or the minus.
the apparent power is
always positive.
We notice then
that we have two elements:
the inductance and  the capacitance,
whose power is not convertible,
or the energy is not convertible.
As we see,
the active power being null,
this inductance
and this capacitance can only create
energy exchanges
of power exchanges
in the circuit.
Only the resistance allows
this energy transformation
into work or heat.
That's it, as you have discovered
during this lesson,
we have seen a multitude
of different powers:
the instantaneous power
which then is characterized
by active, reactive, apparent
and complex apparent powers.
Only the active power represent
a power or a convertible energy
and the reactive power,
corresponds to an energy exchange
between the supply and the load.