Good morning, welcome to this new
lecture of the Electrotechnics course.
Today, we will talk
about a last point of theory
that we have developed in the context of
the supplied circuits under a DC steady state,
and we will deal with it for the AC steady state.
It comes to the power adjustment.
We will first start
by a recall of the results
that we have found
for the DC steady state.
We will then develop
the same theory,
but adjusted to the AC steady state.
We will see the case of
a real voltage supply
that feeds a load impedance,
namely, with a reactive part.
Finally, we will see the case
of an adaptation
with a reactance in series
and a case with a reactance in parallel.
So, here we recall the circuit
we have used for the DC steady state.
It is a real voltage supply
which is composed
of an ideal voltage supply
and of an internal resistor.
This real voltage supply supplies
a resistive load.
Therefore, a current flows
in the circuit.
This current is here.
What interested us was to
calculate the power
which was dissipated in the load
resistance.
To do so, we calculate this value of
power load
which is, in fact, the resistance
multiplied by the current squared.
We represent it here in this equation,
the resistor is here,
and the current squared,
it is the voltage divided by the sum of
the resistors, they are in series here.
Then I², is equal to u over total R
squared.
We can see in this equation
we have two extreme cases.
A power which is null when
the load resistance is null.
So if Rch is null, the power
is also null.
An extreme case: f the load resistance
is infinite,
then the current is null.
There is no current flowing in
the circuit, the power is also null.
Between these two points,
there is a maximum,
and to find that maximum,
what do we do?
We take this function,
a load power,
and we will derive it in relation to
the variable, that is to say  Rch .
And we look for what values
of  Rch  this derivative is zero,
and it will allow us to
find the value  Rch
for which the power is maximum.
We have found that in order that the power
is maximal,
we also speak of power matching,
the condition was that the value
of the internal resistance of the supply
and the value of the load resistances
must be equal.
And the power matching condition
is therefore realized when
the value of the load resistance
and of the internal resistance are equal.
As part of a circuit under an AC steady state,
we perform the same approach,
considering, to stay in a general case,
a real voltage supply
with a load with a
resistive part,
the internal resistance, here,
of the supply,
and the resistance of the load,
first thing.
And a reactive part, it is an
internal reactance of the supply
and the reactance of the load.
We write now the expression of the
active power in the load, here, Pch,
it is the variable which one wishes
to find the maximum value.
This value is given by Rch times I²,
namely:
Rch multiplied by I²,
and therefore the modulus of I²,
and the modulus of I is given by:
the voltage U0 divided by
the norm of the total impedance of the circuit,
namely, U0², divided by  (Ri + Rch),
the resistive part, squared,
then the reactive part of the supply,
plus the reactive part of the load,
squared.
So this is  Z² , the norm
of the square of the impedance vector.
We rewrite here the equation
a little bit cleaner,
and we derive this
expression of power load
that we would like to maximize,
with respect to two variables of the
load, that is to say  Rch  and  XCH ,
we will have to make a partial derivative.
First,  relative
to the load resistance  Rch
the result is the same
as in DC steady state,
we won't do it again here.
And second, a partial derivative
with respect to another variable,
which is the load reactance.
So, we will write the partial derivative
of the power load,
with respect to the variable  Xch,
which must be zero.
So, we won't do again the same calculation,
because it is exactly the same
as the one for the derivative with respect to Rch,
but we obtain a result
as follows,
which says that the derivative is zero for
the value of  X  is equal to minus Xch.
That is to say that the derivative is zero,
so the power is maximum,
when the internal reactance is equal
to the opposite of the load reactance.
That's it, based on
this final result, here,
one can draw the conclusion,
is that under the AC steady state,
the power matching condition is
realized when
the load impedance value, here, the load impedance,
this elements here,
and the value of the internal impedance
of the supply, this part here,
this part here,
are complex conjugates.
Namely, the
real part is the same
and the imaginary part is opposed.
The reactive power, since both
reactances are cancelled,
is therefore also cancelled.
The adaptation of the impedance
tends to make it minimal,
so its norm, by
adding a reactance in series or in parallel.
The purpose is therefore to cancel
the reactive part
to make the resulting impedance
purely resistive.
By canceling the total reactance,
the current is then maximum
because the norm of
the impedance is minimal,
and therefore, the active power
will be maximal.
Adding here a reactance in series
the solution is easily found.
We only need to write Xs, the reactance
in series must be equal to -X.
We therefore have these two terms which cancel,
it only remains the resistance R.
Adding a reactance
in parallel, here,
we can advantageously
work with the powers.
For the dipole considered, which is the
same as the one earlier,
we will add the reactance in parallel,
and we wish to cancel the total
reactive power of the dipole.
In the base branch, this one,
we can write the two powers,
the active power which is equal to  R times I²,
of the current flowing through this branch,
therefore we have R times I², and the value
of I, is U over the norm of Z,
namely, U² divided by R² + X².
For the reactive power, once again,
in this branch,
we can write that Q is equal to X times I²
then the resistance multiplied
by I² which has the same value,
it's U² divided by the norm of Z².
So what interests us
is mainly this point.
This is valid for this branch.
At the reactance here
in parallel,
we can write that the power Qp which
passes in the parallel reactance
and it is simply U²/Xp.
And what we want is that these
two reactive powers cancel out
so that the sum is equal to zero.
We can then write that
the total reactive power
which is equal to Q + Qp,
is equal to zero.
If we rewrite this, it is simplified by U²,
we obtain that  X/(R² + X²),
must be equal to -1/Xp.
And it follows that the value
of the parallel reactance
we should add
to cancel the reactive part,
the reactive power, must be
equal to -R² + X² divided by X.
So for this parallel reactance
that we add in order to adjust the supply,
we have the final result
in this window Xp.
That's it, in conclusion, we can say
that in the AC steady state,
to adapt a load to a supply
and therefore maximize
the output active power,
we need two conditions:
as in DC steady state, it is necessary
that the values of internal resistance
and of load resistance are equal,
it's this point here.
Also, we must delete
the total reagent,
The reactance of the supply and
of the load should then be opposite,
it is this equation here.
In the end, it is necessary
that the internal impedances,
of the supply and the load,
are complex conjugates.
Therefore, adjust the load to a
supply or vice versa,
also means removing the
reactive power, here,
we have seen it in the example treated.
Thank you for your attention.