Hello. Welcome to this new lecture of the
Electrotechnics course.
So far, we have studied
many aspects of an electrical circuit
but always with a power supply
either in DC steady state,
or at a certain frequency,
eventually at multiple frequencies
but simultaneous, it was the case
of the principle of superposition.
We will see
how a circuit behaves
over a big range of frequencies.
Today we will start by defining
what a geometric locus is,
then we will see
the behaviour of an impedance
while varying one of its parameters,
in this instance, the frequency,
we will see an example,
and finally we will look at
the current in the circuit,
because if we change the impedance
the current will also change,
we will then compute the current
as a function of the frequency.
We start then by a definition,
the definition of the complex domain.
We call complex domain relative
to any complex variable,
here it would be the impedance Z,
thus any complex variable,
the location, or the curve, the path,
described by the extremity
of the vector representing this variable
when we vary a parameter
of the network, usually
it is the pulsation, the frequency,
but it could be
the resistor, the inductance
or the capacitor
And today, we will only look at
the pulsation.
For a given circuit,
for example this RLC circuit in series,
we can write
the expression of its total impedance
that has a real part
and an imaginary part.
We can represent it
on the complex plane.
We have here Z.
Z of omega.
And we would like to know how varies
this extremity of the vector Z
when we move, modify
the frequency.
For a given circuit,
powered by an AC supply,
the goal is to compute the curve
covered here by the total impedance
when we vary the frequency.
So in the given example,
the RLC circuit in series,
we are facing three components,
because there are three elements.
We have the impedance ZR which is equal to R,
which doesn't depend on the frequency.
We have the component ZL here.
ZL which is equal to jωL.
And the last component ZC.
ZC is equal to -j(1/ωC).
The two impedances ZL and ZC
are not dependent on the frequency ZC,
the inverse of the frequency,
and ZL is proportional to the frequency.
To get the total impedance of the circuit
we will conduct a sum,
since they are in series,
these three impedances.
Therefore, the sum of these three impedances,
using the property of
the vector addition,
we have this first impedance ZR
to which we will add ZL,
which is represented here,
We add and we add again
ZC which is negative
in order to get the total impedance.
This total impedance has a norm
and an angle, a phase shift,
with respect to the real axis
and the end of this vector is
given here for a frequency of,
for example here,
omega equal 200 radians per second.
If now we change this
frequency value and raise it,
that's it, we are here at omega equals
314 radians per second.
We see that ZL increased slightly,
and linearly with Omega
because ZL is ωL.
ZC, has decreased because
its expression is  1 / ωC ,
and then the final result,
the sum of these three vectors,
give a new point here for
omega equals 314 radians per second,
a new point that corresponds
to the new norm
and a new phase shift of the impedance
with respect to the real axis.
If we increase again the frequency,
we have increased once again
the frequency or the pulsation, this
time we are at 550 radians per second.
We see that ZL has again increased
and ZC decreased
in order to end up with a value so
that both offset each other
and we end up here with
a total impedance,
this point here,
at 550 radians per second,
a total impedance
purely resistive.
We will threat this particular case
in the next lecture.
Increasing again the frequency,
this time we have omega
which is at 720 radians
per second for example,
so ZL becomes bigger than ZC.
Thus the nature of the impedance has
become inductive,
with a positive reactive part,
whereas until now
it was capacitive.
And increasing again the frequency
we finally get a total impedance, ZT
which this time even more
inductive than before
and see our spot,
namely the curve described
by the end of the vector Z
as a function of the frequency,
that is taking shape.
I represent it but for
more values of omega
and we see that the spot of our impedance
which is a RLC circuit in series
is finally a straight line.
This straight line goes from minus infinity to
plus infinity on the imaginary axis,
when the pulsation is null
we have in fact the term 1/ωC
which goes to infinity
and when the frequency is infinite
we have the term ZL that is worth ωL
and tends to infinity.
That's it, we will work on a concrete case.
We will take this circuit example
where we see we have a resistor
in series with an inductance,
and all in series with a resistor
in parallel with a capacitor.
So we will define this first part
as Z1
and this second part
as Z2.
These two impedances, Z1 and Z2,
are in series.
That's it, we can write the equivalent
impedance of all this circuit,
of all these impedances in series.
We see that we have a term
that corresponds to Z1 with its part, here,
resistive, R1, and
the reactive part,  jωL1 .
Then for the Z2 part,
you can refer to the table
that we've given you
in the previous lectures,
but we can rewrite the real part,
here, of this impedance
as being this plus the reactive part
which is equal to jω times this term here.
Now, we would like to compute
or determine the place of the impedance Z
when we vary the pulse,
the frequency, omega.
The result, we give it to you
in the following slide.
We have here this result
that i will comment.
So we represent here the impedance Z1
and the impedance Z2.
The first impedance here, Z1,
is given by, here,
this Z1 which has a real part
and an imaginary part,
it is this term R1 plus jωL1.
A small remark because of the software
i use that is not able to
underline, we have actually
to write correctly this equation,
we have to underline here the Y2, the Z2
times all the impedances,
even these ones to be correct.
Thus I said that the first part
here of the impedance Z1,
which corresponds to this term R1
and this term jωL1,
indeed, we find it here
if we vary the frequency
from zero to infinite.
This term does not vary,
we still have R1 which is this point here,
and the impedance will increase gradually
with the increase of the frequency,
it's the term jωL1,
of a resistor and
an inductance in series,
it is a straight line
that tends from zero to j infinity.
Now for the second part of
the circuit, the impedance Z2 here,
we can advantageously use
the admittances,
because we known that the parallel
admittances can be added,
and it allows us to
describe the location of Y2,
that is to say that Y2 is the sum
of these two admittances,
the admittance of R2 is here,
it is 1/R2, it is the inverse,
and the admittance of C2 it is jωC2
and we see that this term here,
these terms,
are very similar
to these two terms here,
something constant
for the real case,
we have this term here, 1/R2,
and we add an imaginary term
which is proportional to the frequency.
It also gives us a place, here,
which is half-right
that goes from j null to j infinite.
So we can do the mathematical
demonstration
but we will not do it here.
Making the mathematical demonstration
that the inverse of a line
in the complex plane,
so that goes from j0 to j infinity,
from the zero imaginary part
to an infinite imaginary part,
is a semicircle.
So the image or the inverse
of a straight line is a semicircle
that starts from this value here
for omega equals to zero
and tends to this value here.
To get the final result,
one must add the impedance Z1,
is this place here,
and this impedance Z2
we found in doing
the opposite of this straight line here,
it's this semicircle here,
the sum of the two, is this impedance
plus this one, which is here,
which gives this result: Z1 plus Z2.
The sun of these two impedances
for omega equals zero,
we go from this point here
where we have the sun of R1 plus R2.
And increasing the frequency,
first we will be negative,
which means capacitive,
because at low frequency
the impedance Z2 is very high,
it is capacitive.
So we will first be capacitive,
we arrive at a particular value
where we are purely resistive
and when the frequency increases further,
we will become very inductive
to follow this curve here.
So, we start with a total impedance value
for a frequency,
a pulsation, null
from this point here.
We have actually
the sum of the two resistors R1 and R2.
Why?
Because jωL1 is null
and 1/ωC is infinite,
So we have an open circuit here.
Instead of C2
we have only R1 plus R2,
it is this starting point.
That's it, i launch the video and we see
that the impedance is first capacitive,
resistive, and she becomes
more and more inductive
progressively as the
frequency increases.
We have seen what happens at
the impedance, at its norm,
at its phase in the complex plan
when we increase the frequency
of the circuit.
We will now, for this example
given here, get interested in the current,
namely, its norm and its phase,
once again depending on the frequency.
So we try to compute I of omega
and beta, the current argument.
So to know the current
which passes through the circuit, we need,
knowing here
the supply voltage U0,
we need to know the impedance here
of the RC circuit in series.
So we can write that Z = R - j(1/ωC)
and then that its norm is equal to,
by Pythagoras, to the real part squared
plus the imaginary part squared.
So we have that the norm of Z
it is √R² + (1/ω²C²).
This is the norm.
Now the phase shift.
The phase shift of the impedance,
it is given by the arc tangent
of the imaginary part
over the real part,
namely the imaginary part 1/ωC
divided by the real part R.
That's it, we have completely defined
here the impedance Z, and now
to compute the current.
The current is given by the ratio
of u0 to Z.
So, if I express u0
in function of the argument,
we have u0 times  e^jα,
usually we put α equal to zero,
and the impedance Z which is given
by the norm we have just computed
multiplied by e^jφ.
From this equation
we can write the norm of the current,
which is u0 over Z,
multiplied by e^j(α - φ).
With identification, we have that this term here
is the norm of I
and this term here, is the argument of I,
it is beta.
We can express the norm of I,
we develop.
We have that I it's u0, the supply
voltage, divided by the norm of Z,
namely R² + (1/ω²C²),
and the angle beta,
the argument of the current,
it is given by -φ,
namely  tangent arc of 1/ωRC.
We will analyse now
these two functions,
the norm of I and the argument of I
in function of omega
and we will represent them in a plan
omega is the variable
we would like to represent.
We will first represent
the norm of I in function of omega.
And the argument of I in function of omega.
For a pulsation omega equals zero,
we have that I is equal to zero.
why?
Because this term becomes very
big and then
the ratio of u over something
very big is equal to zero.
So for a null pulsation,
we have a norm of the current
that goes from this point here.
Concerning the phase,
we have that beta is equal to pi over 2.
Why?
Because the vector ZC is infinite
as long as omega is equal to zero,
therefore the norm of C is infinite
and we have an angle of minus pi over 2.
and since beta is equal to minus phi,
we go from this value
that worth pi over two
for a null frequency.
In contrast, when
the pulsation is infinite,
the current tends to a value
that is u0/R.
We see that in this equation.
The pulsation being infinite,
this term is equal to zero
and we have then u0/√R², is u0/R.
The current, when omega equals
infinite, tends to u0/R.
In between, we will increase
that way.
For the argument of the current,
beta at infinite equals zero.
Why?
Because for an infinite value,
the capacitor behaves
as a Short Circuit
and this term here tends to zero.
The curve of the argument goes from
phi over two and tends to zero
for omega equals infinite.
We have completely defined
the behavior of the current
which passes through the circuit
as a function of the frequency
in terms of the norm
and the argument.
Thus a steady-state capacitor
acts as an impedance
infinite, then no current.
We are at this point here.
And a capacitor at an infinite frequency
behaves as a short-circuit
and then we only
have the resistive part
We have defined and built
the geometric locus of an impedance,
here in function of the frequency,
but we could also have done it
in function of R, L or C for example
if we wanted to take into account
the aging of the components
where R, L or C may change,
or in function of the load
that would be put in this circuit.
We have seen that a circuit could change
in nature depending on the frequency
to which it is supplied,
so either capacitive, purely resistive
or inductive, and there is a particular
value for which
it is purely resistive,
that is what we will see
in the next lecture.
We have seen that it is possible to delete
the reactive part of an impedance
but this is only
possible at one given frequency.
Consequently,
one can also remove
the reactive power in a circuit
combining the element L and the element C.
Finally, we have seen that if the impedance Z
changes with the frequency,
the current also changes
with the frequency,
we have shown how it evolves
in terms of its norm and its phase shift
as a function of the frequency.
Thank you for your attention.