Hello.
As we have seen in a previous video,
we now have a tool and approach
to define our theory of change
and how our project will lead to
impact on a specific issue.
Now we need to look into the
technological product that we want
to develop and how this product will
be made available to the user.
There are several questions that
we will need to answer.
How can we capture the key
activities and steps needed for
our product to be available to our
user in a sustainable way?
How can we identify all
the stakeholders whose
intervention is crucial?
How can we make sure that we have
captured most of the technological
and business constraints?
In this chapter we will introduce
a new tool to you, which we have
developed to help envision the chain
of activities that are required
in order to achieve our goal.
We call it The Product Value Chain
analysis tool.
The concept of Value Chain was
developed by Michael Porter
back in 1985.
As he had defined it, the Value Chain
referred to the organisation of a
company or a business
unit as a whole.
The idea was that each group of
activity in the company, such as
operations, logistics or marketing,
are a segment of the chain.
Each segment consumes resources
and adds value to the final
output of the company.
This definition is not the one
that we will use here.
Our concept of Value Chain, which we
explain in the this chapter, focuses
on the product itself and not on the
internal organisation of a company.
In fact, making the product
available to the user may
involve a whole series of companies
and other organisations.
Again, remember that each segment of
the chain is an activity that adds
value to the customer and for the
various stakeholders involved.
As we will see later, this is related
to the value proposition that will
be created and provided to the
people who need it.
Analysing the chain is vital and
there is a tight relation between
each segment and the final product,
as well as between one segment
and another.
What you see here is a generic and
basic form, which can be used as a
starting point.
However, you will have to
expand it and tailor it to
your specific technology.
Each activity should be further
subdivided into smaller segments,
which will help you to identify
key suppliers, partners
and other stakeholders.
So let's now have a quick overview
of this Product Value Chain before
we take a deeper dive
into each segment.
Any technology or product
will first need to be
imagined, designed and developed.
We thus naturally start
the Value Chain analysis
with this segment.
This early stage involves
creative thinking,
but then concepts must be refined
and adjusted to the industrial
constraints, the needs of the
customer, the legislations and
many other factors that must
be accounted for.
The aim of the Produce step is to
manufacture the product with
a constant quality and at the cost
target that has been defined.
Production methods need to be
tailored to the volumes
that will be needed,
as our technology deployment
grows and scales up.
This step does not only include own
manufacturing but also takes into
consideration all kinds of
subcontracting types that you
may put in place with partners to
reach the best price-quality ratio.
It also encompasses the supply chain
management required to manage
the flow of raw material,
components and semi-finished goods
all along the production flow until
the product is finalised and tested.
The next one is the Market step.
The aim is to sell the product at
the right price, which means that
it has to be competitive on the
market while still offering a
sustainable profitability to
your organisation.
We know that affordability is
a crucial concern as we think about
solutions for low and middle
income countries.
However, this step involves looking
at the complete value proposition
for customer, not just the product.
For example, alongside the product,
there may be a need for training
which is part of the value
proposition.
This step will also involve
market analysis,
business model definition, branding,
publicity and so forth.
In a later chapter of this MOOC,
we will introduce a very effective
tool to develop and analyse
innovative business models
in detail, which is called the
Sustainable Business Model Canvas.
A very important segment is related
to all the activities needed to
bring the finished product from the
producer facility to the user.
This is our Distribute segment.
Distributing the product includes
topics such as packaging, logistics,
customs clearance or insurances.
This segment of the Value Chain
often represents a major roadblock/hurdle
in the countries we are considering,
for all sorts of reasons, such as
geography, climate or governance.
Our final step is one that is,
unfortunately, often overlooked,
especially when considering
deployment in low and middle
income countries.
As we have seen, the level of
failure of products is huge when
they have originally been designed
for industrialised settings and
they are delivered to customers
in  developing countries without
any second thoughts.
This is largely a consequence of
neglecting to investigate the context
and behaviour of users.
The Support Use segment of the chain
is a vast subject starting from when
a product is received by the
user all the way to when it is
decommissioned and recycled.
Note that the process is circular.
This is because one day the product
will become obsolete and the
whole cycle starts all over again.
I would like to make a few
additional general remarks
on this Product Value Chain.
First, although it is shown as a
process with arrows linking the
different segments in a
chronological way,
it is essential to understand that
all the steps are interconnected.
They must all be taken into
consideration early on,
even as we are just starting
to work on the concept.
For instance, when designing the
product, you will need to have
information about what options
are available for manufacturing,
about market requirements,
distribution constraints and
about how it will be used,
maintained and recycled.
Second, what we have represented
here is a  Generic Value Chain,
which should be used mainly
as a starting point.
Your project could be to develop
any kind of technological products,
such as a new type of housing
technology, a machine, a drug
or an IT application.
The Product Value Chain needs to
be tailored to this product and
expanded in much more detail.
However, a fundamental rule is to
keep it as simple as possible
but not simpler, as
Einstein once said.
In some cases, not all steps will be
applicable, but it always makes sense
to go through the Value Chain and
ask yourself if a specific step is
relevant to your product or not.
Third, when beginning your
project, you will not have all the
information at hand.
You will need to make assumptions.
As your product gets more
mature, you will be able to confirm
or refute these assumptions.
You will also identify new,
relevant parameters that
you did not consider at first.
The Product Value Chain analysis,
like all of the tools proposed
in this course, is intuitive and
must be reviewed regularly
all along your project.
Fourth,  to successfully use this
tool, you need to use it as a team.
It is crucial to involve people
who have the knowledge
that you may be missing.
For example, if you are a marketer,
you may want to at least involve
an engineer and so on.
If you are someone from an
industrialised country,
make sure to involve someone who
has a deep understanding of the
country or region you are targeting.
In the next videos, we will move to
a more detailed discussion of the
different segments.
For each one, we will discuss some
key strategic topics to be aware of
and which are especially relevant
to low and middle income countries.
Goodbye.