Hello!
The first activity in
the product value chain
is to imagine and
develop the product.
As discussed in the overview, our
purpose is not to give you a course
on R&D project management, but rather to
bring up a few key strategic topics
that are especially relevant in
the context of this MOOC.
These topics are:
The needs assessment
by which we strive to
clearly understand
what is the current situation of
our technology in the context
we are considering.
This will allow us to determine if
we need a complete redesign of
the technology, or a mere evolution
of something existing.
Then the definition of the product
specifications is absolutely crucial
and we will explain what kind
of topics should be included.
Once we have our basic
specifications, we need to
think in terms of partnerships,
who do we need to partner with
in order to develop our solutions,
can we bring in some strategic
partners who could help
us accelerate our process.
Another key subject is the one
related to industry standards and
regulations applicable
to our product.
They will need to be
clearly identified early on.
Then we have to consider
the angle of intellectual property,
such as patents
trademarks and copyrights.
And finally there is the user
experience of the product.
Design is important in all markets
and this should not be neglected
here either.
Let us look into these
different topics.
The first step is to analyze
the need for the product.
What are the current technologies
that are being used, if there is no
technology solution available at
all, what are the alternatives or
substitutes that people have
found in our target context?
We need to honestly define
what are the pros and cons of
existing solutions.
This requires a close collaboration
with the people who
we are trying to help
as well as other stakeholders.
After having analyzed the market
situation, we will be able to
come up with innovative solutions
that may, or may not involve
a complete redesign
of the technology.
The solution may simply consist
of a smart and different use
of some existing technology,
or it may involve a profoundly
disruptive innovation.
This is a strategic decision, because
if you have to completely redesign
the technology, both the risks
and the efforts will be much higher.
On the other hand, the impact may
also be much more important.
It is important to capture
the results of the needs
assessment in the form
of written specifications.
What is important is that
these specifications need
to be quantitative
and measurable.
For example, saying that
a water treatment system
must have the highest possible
output is not good enough.
We must be able to describe
the output in quantitative terms,
for example, the pump must be
able to deliver 100L per hour.
Specifications don't just capture
technical characteristics, but
many other aspects that will depend also on the other
segments of the product value chain.
Specifications will typically
include the following rubrics,
but there might be many others,
depending on the industry:
Technical characteristic which
capture key technical elements
of your product,
Performance characteristics, which are
closely related to the customer needs.
Applicable standards and regulatory
requirements and we will come back
to this particular topic.
Product risks, very often
safety of persons may depend
on the product, which means that
we will have to conduct a product
risk evaluation.
Quality level, obviously, we would
like to provide solutions that are
ultra durable, however this comes
with a cost and there has to be
a trade off.
Assessing customer's expectation
or comparing existing solutions
might provide useful information
about the quality level
to be achieved.
Production means, prior to any
development it is important that we
think about how and where
to manufacture the product.
We will review that in more
detail in a later video.
Target price.
Target price must be coherent
with the market expectations,
while still allowing your
company to be sustainable.
We will see how to
achieve this balance
in a later video.
Packaging and distribution.
We must specify how we will
package and ship the product.
This is linked to the distribute
segment that we will see
in a later video as well.
Support use and
especially maintenance.
It is important to know how
we will support the use of our
product, for example, by defining
which maintenance
activities are necessary.
As the goal is to maximize impact,
it would be great to be able
to minimize the need for
maintenance and spare parts.
We will see that in detail in
the last segment of the value chain.
Product evolution.
Most of the products will evolve
in the course of time because of
changes in the technology
and in the market.
Some of these changes can
be anticipated in the design
so that a product will be
easily up-gradable if need be.
We should make sure to think about
about our product as a platform for
future evolution.
Discontinuations and recycling.
Sooner or later our product
will be worn out or obsolete
and it will need to be phased out.
The question of how our product
will be recycled is very crucial
because we don't want to create harm
to humans or to the environment.
And finally we have verification.
We must think of how we will make
sure that our product complies
with what has been specified
in the previous points.
If a specification is not very
viable it is not adequate.
There are many rubrics in this list
but it is still not exhaustive, but our
hope is that it helps you ask
yourself the right questions.
Our next strategic
topic is partnerships.
This is of course a very valid
question in all of the product
value chains segments.
But we decided to insist on it,
especially in this one, as it is
where it is often overlooked.
Inventors like to do things
themselves, and this is fine
as long as we are not missing an
opportunity to be more efficient.
Projects could often be accelerated
if we were able to overcome
the infamous "not invented here"
syndrome.
Procter & Gamble has famously tried
to correct this very human behavior
by promoting the motto:
"Proudly found elsewhere".
We should never refrain from
partnering in the interest of our
objective, because an efficient product
development partnership
can make you avoid years
of painstaking work.
We have also repeatedly insisted
on the importance of collaborating
with local partners and
across disciplines.
There is hardly any moment
when it is more important than
in the early phases
of a project.
We need to ask ourselves
who could be a good partner?
It could be an institution,
a company, an NGO
or simply an individual.
Another important topic is related
to standards and regulations.
Getting into details would
take another MOOC.
Broadly speaking, a standard is
a set of rules which define
a preconceived way to design
or test some product.
Standards are generally developed
by organizations such as
the International Standards
Organization or the ISO, or
the International Electrical
Commission or IEC.
The application of standards is
generally voluntary, but can
become mandatory if adopted by
a government through legislation.
In Europe and some other places,
products are required to beat
the CE mark, formally this indicates
that the product complies with
the European legislation
for that category of products.
This does not necessarily mean
that the product complies to all
technical standards existing
for that product category,
but certainly to some of them.
We will need to check for
our target country or region
what the legal requirements are
for our product.
This can sometimes be time
consuming and expensive, especially
when the countries define
their own rules to protect
their local industries.
Another challenge is that the standards
have evolved with the progress made
in industrialized countries and may
not be well adapted to the situation
in low and middle income countries.
Now we would like to discuss
a crucial ethical issue.
It is not because some low income
countries have loopholes
in their legislation that we should
neglect the compliance
with key standards
for our product.
We don't want to develop poor
technologies for poor countries.
In spite of the challenge,
we strongly believe that
every human being deserves
the same level of product quality
safety and effectiveness.
We need to resist the temptation of
making short-cuts and neglecting
relevant standards, even if it makes
the project much more difficult.
We give you a simple rule
to know if you have achieved
a sufficient level of
safety and effectiveness.
Would you be allowed to
sell your technology in
an industrialized country?
If the answer is yes,
then you're fine.
Our best advice is to have a good
discussion with people who
know this subject early
on in your project.
Also, a lot of relevant information
can be found on the internet.
For example, on
the website of the IEC.
Another important topic is
intellectual property protection.
Here as well the subject
would require another MOOC.
I will not discuss trademarks
or copyrights but concentrate
on patents.
Patents are intended
as incentive to invent.
A patent is a means by which
the authorities grant the inventor
a time limited exclusivity for
the commercial exploitation
of his or her invention.
the process of filing and
managing a patent is complex
and support from a specialist
is generally required.
However, we have to carefully
think about our strategy
regarding patents before hand,
because they are very expensive.
Not only are the filing costs high,
but there also many additional fees
that will have to be paid all
along the patents lifetime,
which is limited to twenty years.
Over it's lifetime a patent
filed in a dozen countries
can easily cost up to several
hundred thousand dollars in total
and this does not even
include potential litigation.
The costs must really be offset by
the benefits obtained from
the patents exclusivity rights.
It is, thus, fundamental to ask
yourself if a protection offered
by a patent is worthwhile.
Also, you will have to designate
the countries in which you want to
request protection
for your invention.
Every additional country
or region will increase costs.
On the contrary, you may decide
not to pursue any patent protection
at all, and leave the invention
open for everyone to use.
There is a downside to
this strategy, however.
At a later stage you will perhaps
want to involve investors and they
usually like to see patents, because
they are barriers to entry for your
competitors, it is a way to keep
your company competitive and
sustainable, so there is
a balance to be found.
On the other hand, in case
of infringement of your patent
defending it against an
an unfair competitor
could cost you years of litigation,
which could lead to bankruptcy.
There is one additional important
thing we need to keep in mind.
Any public disclosure of
an invention before it has been
filed will prevent you from
seeking patent protection.
This public disclosure could be
in the form of publication in
a news paper, on the internet,
or simply a poster placed in
a public location.
We have to be especially careful
with our partners as they sometimes
disclose things inadvertently.
Conversely, if you do not want
to patent your invention
you should disclose it publicly,
as otherwise someone could
come along and file a patent on your
invention, which he could then use
against you.
This tactic is called
defensive publishing.
As you may find out,
your idea may have already
been patented before.
This could entitle someone
else to prevent you from
using your innovation
or to claim payments
or royalties.
To anticipate this problem you need
to assess your freedom to operate.
An easy way to check if
a patent is still enforced
is to look at the so
called priority date.
If the date is over twenty years ago
you're most probably fine.
It could also be that the inventor
has stopped paying the fees and
the patent is no longer valid, even
if it is less than twenty years old.
It is also important to check if
the filing was done in your target
country or region.
It could be that a specific patent
has been filed in a high income
country only because
the patent owner
did not consider the others as
potentially interesting markets.
There are searchable databases
on the patents on the internet,
which allow you to see if
a specific patent is still active.
Finally, we would like to insist
on the value of a patent as
a bargaining tool.
If you own a patent it could be
used to negotiate a partnership
with an established company.
In exchange for the right to use
your invention that company
could, for example, manufacture
some products for you
at a favorable price, or help
you distribute you technology.
There are many more possibilities
of win-win partnerships which
can be negotiated if you own
the rights to a valuable invention.
Finally there is
the user experience.
Design is much more
than the look of a product
it is really about optimizing
the interaction between the product
and the user.
It is not because a customer
lives in a developing country
that he or she is not sensitive to
the look and feel of the product,
quite the opposite, in fact.
As we have already said in the past,
we should put our future product
in contact with our
potential customers
as soon as possible.
As we are working with
the product value chain tool,
for instance, we should
provide them with mock-ups
or rough-and-ready prototypes
and pay attention to their comments.
Here, again, the aim is to
identify potential miss-matches
with our assumptions and adapt
our product as early as possible.
Remember,
it is better to fail early
to fail often, and to fail cheap,
as failures at a later stage will
have much more severe consequences.
Goodbye.