So the ambition to
develop an African technology
demands a wealth of strong
contributions.
Firstly intellectual contributions
even psychological contributions,
to claim:
"We are able to
trust ourselves,
we are capable of
developing our environment,
we can be inspired by
what others have already done
to better adapt it to our
own context."
But nowadays I think
all my energy goes to
telling Africans
it's still possible to do something,
it is possible to bring
something to mankind,
but we need a positive view,
more self confidence
we need more trust,
more respect about the fact that
we are an elite in this environment
that needs us,
that needs solutions,
that needs innovations,
but firstly African innovations,
we shouldn't think
straight away
about innovating at an
American scale,
at a Japanese scale,
at a Swiss scale.
We should start with small
steps, like we say:
"The longest trip
starts with the first step".
Let's do the first step,
but in our own environment.
As soon as we have competent
personnel
to ensure the use
of health technology in Africa,
we can improve the
situation, that gives me hope
because the raw material is here
and if we also have the know-how
in human resources
using this raw material is possible,
so I have hope that the African
technology will evolve.
You see, there are 5 stages in
this process.
The first one is drawing
what you see!
If you have seen something,
you should be able to draw it,
how does it work?
You have understood!
But now, do a
drawing of it,
then being able, truly from
this drawing
to bring an innovation,
improve something
rather that it happening like that,
it will happen like this.
and be able to test it,
IT tools exist for that.
Then be able to reproduce
what you have thoroughly tested.
You see! Be able to
reproduce and test it
then put it into production.
There is a scheme here,
sometimes I feel like
we want to progress too quickly.
But no! The world has existed
for billions of years
and it is only as we see it today,
so it should go slowly,
level by level,
learn something
the methodical way
at that moment,
it is said somewhere
we will spend 6 days
creating the world.