Hello.
You have now reached a stage
where you need to create
a product from your
innovation concept or idea.
As we said all along,
we don't intend to give you
a course on how
to manufacture products
but rather discuss what
we consider to be crucial points
for consideration
for products conceived
or destined for
developing countries.
Manufacturing can be defined
as a value added production
of merchandise for use
or sale using labour, machines
tools, chemical
and biological processes.
Or in very simplified terms,
manufacturing
is the process that turns
your idea into a product.
Now, before you begin putting
together your manufacturing strategy
you need to remind yourself
of who your target market is
and what price point
you wish or need to reach.
After that, one of the first things
you need to think about is
which elements or components
of your idea or innovation
really need to be manufactured
from scratch, because in most cases
the product can be realized
using existing or available
components, for example,
and bearing in mind that
when you manufacture any product
you will almost always have
various options on which materials
to use and which process
you select to make it.
And the target market
and the price points
you are trying to reach
will play a decisive role
on what choices you make.
Now the next major
question to confront is
do you manufacture at home,
or do you outsource this abroad,
that is offshore?
because today the Contract Manufacturing
industry is highly developed
and now extends far beyond China.
And most of them offer
a turn-key solution,
that is a one-stop shop
that includes packaging
and direct delivery
to your client's doorstep.
For technology based products,
especially, it is highly advisable
to well understand if
and how this industry can
add value to your strategic objective.
However, you should bear in mind,
though, that the manufacturing sector
is often highly coveted by policy
makers in developing countries.
It is viewed as an instrument
and catalyst of modernization
and skilled job creation,
as well as a source
of various collateral industries.
Governments also promote
local manufacture
with special tax concessions
and reduced tarif rates
for importers of manufacturing
machines and equipment,
as well as giving preferential status
for government tenders
to locally manufactured products.
Now, a very important issue
to look into also during
the process of selecting
the operational location
is that of supply
chain management,
which is essentially
the management of the flow
of goods and services
into the company
as manufacturing inputs,
or out of the company as products.
You will need to be
fully comfortable
on how you will manage this
critical process before you begin.
Now, once you have dealt
with the issues above
you will need to commence planning
of your operation in more detail.
And one of the top priorities
will be to devise and implement
a suitable quality assurance system.
For technology based
products, especially,
which can be relatively complex,
it is very important
to have this in place even before
you start your operations.
When it comes to choosing
a location for production
there are a number of practical
and key considerations
that can help you make
an informed decision.
First of all,
evaluate your game plan,
which means start by clarifying
the organization strategic goals
and objectives.
Do you intend to reduce cost,
for example?
Or serve a new market?
Or expedite response time
or diversify risk?
The consideration of
broad organizational goals
into the decision will help
to support
the long-term sustainability
of your manufacturing investment.
As we mentioned before,
one of the main challenges
faced in the regions
of relevance to this course
is the lack of
the skilled workforce.
Be sure to do your homework
diligently and meticulously
and verify that you will
indeed be able to find
the key required skills for the job.
It maybe necessary to import
certain of these skills from abroad,
especially senior personnel who may
come for a certain limited period
to effect a skills transfer.
So it will be helpful
to also select a location
that may have some appeal
to foreign citizens.
And one of the best sources
for this option is actually
the foreign embassies
of the countries of your interest.
Look beyond labour costs,
apply a Total-Cost decision model.
The location with the lowest
labour costs may not necessarily be
the preferred one or even the most
cost effective place to do business.
To make the right choice,
consider a wide range of factors,
including everything from cost
of transportation and electricity,
to supply chain risk
and tax incentives.
Identify and prioritize
all the needs of your business
and see how each location
compares against
your specific requirements.
Now let's discuss supply chains.
The supply chain management
is defined as the management
of the flow of goods and services.
It involves the movement
and storage of raw materials,
inventory and finished goods
from the point of origin
to the point of consumption.
Establishing a viable
and sustainable market
in a region requires, first
and foremost, that customers
have reliable access
to your products.
Therefore, before
you begin manufacturing
pay careful attention
to supply chain details
in the area where your
manufacturing operations
will be carried out.
This point should be also
be factored in during
the selection process of
the manufacturing location.
You should consider
the entire supply chain
because many modern factories
are really just assembly operations
with much of
the actual manufacturing
done by upstream suppliers.
So when deciding where
to locate eventually
proximity to your customers
should be an important
factor in fact.
Now for example,
if we look at sub-Saharan Africa
there are significant variations
in the logistics costs
and lead times required
to access different African markets.
Today, for example, the air freight
hubs of Nairobi in Kenya,
Addis Ababa in Ethiopia,
and Johannesburg in South Africa
provide sufficient capacity
to meet current needs
in those regions,
while air cargo capacity
in West Africa is still limited.
Same with ports,
important automotive parts
through Port Apapa in Nigeria
will take over three months,
while importing the same parts
through Durban in South Africa
takes only one month.
And these delays and lead times can
be detrimental to the enterprise.
Now to avoid these delays, the
enterprise may elect to hold
an inventory of big size
and high variety,
but for small markets holding such
a big inventory may not be justified,
because there may not be
sufficient demand
to off-take it all.
This means that they
have to order according
to the needs, and with
the longer lead times
compared to their counterparts
with the better supply
chain ressources,
they may suffer reduced
responsiveness, flexibility
and overall competitiveness.
We'll now discuss quality assurance,
which is essentially
the way industries prevent
mistakes or defects
in manufacturing products
and avoid problems
when delivering solutions
or services to the customers.
Quality assurance
and quality control
are two very closely
related concepts
and because
of that close relationship
they are often confused
and one is inappropriately
used as a substitute
for the other.
Quality assurance
is essentially a system
that is put in place before
operations begin ideally.
In order to ensure
that the steps of the various processes
will be done in the correct way,
including mechanisms
to prevent mistakes and defects.
If the system is designed properly
or correctly, then there is
a high level of assurance
that the desired results
will turn out as expected.
Whereas quality control is
a series of tests at various stages
during the manufacturing process
that verify that the expected
outcome at each stage, as specified
in the quality assurance system,
has been obtained
for each resulting product.
If the correct controls are in place
then you have high certainty
that all the final products are good,
because they have each passed
all the quality control tests.
One of the most well known
quality assurance standards
is the ISO 9000
that was first published in 1987.
and has since then been
widely adopted world over.
Apart from this general standard
most industries have
their specific standards
that in many sectors
will be mandatory
for your product to be allowed
and sold on the market.
For example,
the quality assurance system
appropriate to the manufacturer
of pharmaceutical products
would involve guidelines such
as good manufacturing practice
or GMP, and other associated codes,
such as good laboratory practice
and good clinical practice,
or GCP.
As a final word it is important
to think about some of the issues
discussed in this lecture
as early as you can
for example, if you can
figure out very early on
that to obtain your product
you need to only manufacture
one component in the end
and the rest you can obtain
in the market,
then you can simply
focus your R&D on the most
crucial part instead of trying
to build the whole system.
This would save you
precious time and resources.
Goodbye.