Now you have managed to deal with
manufacturing issues and must now
think about convincing your customers
to buy the products
you intend to manufacture.
In other words, you now need
to establish or refine and finalize
your marketing strategy.
The main objective of a marketing
strategy is to define
the target customers and how
to effectively reach them.
Segmenting the market is especially
important for small businesses,
because they cannot go after every
segment and need to allocate
their limited resources selectively.
In the following minutes,
we will discuss various widely used
approaches for defining or
optimizing a market strategy.
This includes methods such as
Pestle, which stands for political,
economic, social, technological,
legal and environmental issues
around your business.
The Porter's 5 Forces
The SWOT, which stands for
Strengths, Weaknesses, Opportunities
and Threats to your company
and its products.
Value Proposition,
Unique Selling Point and positioning
As well as typical or common
Market Demographics
found in developing countries.
Now, your PESTLE analysis will
help you to have a holistic view
of the position of your product
within its external environment.
The analysis will help your
enterprise understand
the following factors:
Political, this looks at
the political trends.
For instance, are these trends more
or less in favor of your industry?
Can you expect some incentives
from the government?
Could some laws change and
impact your business?
Economic, is the economy growing
or rather in recession?
How is the exchange or
the interest rates evolving?
And what about
inflation and taxes?
Social, how is the demography,
the age pyramid,
the average mortality?
What is the average
level of education?
What are the lifestyle trends?
Technological, are you in line with
technological trends to come?
Are there some technological
or technologies that might
make your product obsolete?
Legal, how is the legal system
in the region?
And what about Intellectual
Property and enforcement?
Environmental, what sort of
waste regulations
exist for instance?
What is the position on energy,
savings and green technologies
transportation issues, etc.
Overall, the information derived
from the PESTLE analysis also
serves as useful input to
the external factors
In the SWOT analysis,
which we discuss later.
The Porter's 5 Forces tool is
a simple but powerful tool
that is often used to identify
whether new products,
services or businesses have
the potential to be successful.
It achieves this by helping you
understand where power lies
in the marketplace.
This helps you understand
both the strengths of your
current competitive position
and the strength of the position
you are considering moving into.
Five forces analysis assumes that
there are five important forces
that determine competitive power
in a business situation.
And, these are
Supplier Power
Here you try and assess how easy it
is for suppliers to drive up prices.
Here in general the few other
supplier choices you have
and the more dependent
you are on them
the more powerful your suppliers are
on your business.
Buyer Power
Here you look at how easy it is
for buyers to drive down prices.
Again, this is driven by
the number of buyers,
because if you only have a
few powerful buyers
then they are in a dominant
position to dictate terms to you.
Competitive Rivalry
Again, if you have many competitors
and they offer equally attractive
products and services, then you'll
most likely have little power
in this situation, because clients
will go elsewhere
if they don't like your offer.
However, if no one else can do
what you do, then you'll hold
a dominant position.
Threat of Substitution
This is affected by the ability
of your customers to find
different ways of doing what you do.
If substitution can be achieved
easily, and it is viable
then your position is weak.
Threat of New Entry
Power is also affected by
the ability of new players to enter
your market.
If you have strong and durable
barriers to entry then you are
likely to have a favourable position.
Such as a patent, for example.
Now, the information from
the Porter's 5 Forces analysis
can thus also flag areas that
may need attention
before hitting the market.
SWOT
SWOT which stands for
Strengths, Weaknesses,
Opportunities and Threats
is an analytical framework
but is often used during
strategic planning.
Its primary objective is
to help organizations
develop a full awareness of all
the factors involved in a decision
by identifying both internal
and external influences.
It serves as a precursor to any sort
of company actions,
such as exploring new initiatives,
making decisions about new policies
identifying possible areas for change
or refining and redirecting
efforts midway through.
The SWOT analysis requires
the participation of at least
the entire management team,
for it to provide
maximum benefits
to your organization.
Now, when drafting a SWOT analysis
you typically create a table
comprising of four quadrants,
where you list
each impacting element
side by side for comparison.
Do not necessarily expect strengths
and weaknesses to match with
the identified
opportunities and threats.
However, pairing external threats
with internal weaknesses
can help you identify
the most critical issues
faced by your organization.
Internal Factors
the first two letters in the acronym
S for strengths
and W for weaknesses, refer to
internal factors
which means, the resources and
experience readily available to you.
Examples of areas typically
considered include
financial resources,
core competences
and intellectual property.
Now, one word of caution when
evaluating your core competences.
You need to actually determine what
you are uniquely good at and
better than others, but which
customers value.
This could even be a core process,
which is a key activity that turns
inputs into outputs.
Because, being exceptionally good
at something is not necessarily
a strategic advantage.
Instead, you must be exceptionally
good at something
valued by customers.
In fact, some of the information
from your Porter's 5 Forces analysis
could provide useful input here.
It is recommended, though, to start
by analyzing your strengths
and weaknesses first,
as these are factors you
generally have control of,
as opposed to external factors.
External Factors
the last two letters
O for opportunities and
T for threats
refer to external factors,
which are often things
your organization does not
have control of.
In fact, many of these factors
are the ones you assessed
in your PESTLE analysis
such as political, economic,
social trends, etc.
So, all in all, the SWOT tool serves
as an aggregate or dashboard view
that embeds the results from
the other more detailed analyses
we discussed before and
provides an overview
of both harmful and helpful issues
to the enterprise.
In the simplest terms,
a value proposition
is a positioning statement that
explains what benefit you provide
for who and how you do it,
uniquely well.
It describes your target buyer,
the problem you solve
and why you are distinctly better
than the alternatives.
As you set out to create your
compelling value proposition
consider the following four steps:
Define, Evaluate,
Measure and Build.
Number one, Define the problem
and verify whether it's really
a problem worth solving.
There is a saying
in entrepreneurship.
A problem well stated
is a problem half solved.
And unfortunately, many
entrepreneurs still make the mistake
of diving deep into the solution,
before fully understanding
what problem they are really
seeking to solve.
Evaluate.
That means evaluate whether your
innovation is unique and compelling.
After you've determined and
defined the problem you're solving
and validated its criticality,
ask yourself
what is unique and compelling about
your proposed solution.
Measure or estimate the potential
gain for the customer
in adopting your product.
Simply saying that you have
a product or service
that is faster, cheaper and better
is not good enough.
Everybody says so.
So, show me the money.
It is said that, to be successful,
a new venture or product
must deliver an order of
magnitude improvement
over the status quo.
So, if you can't deliver
a ten times gain promise,
you may face the risk that
customers will typically
default to doing nothing,
rather than take the risk
with a new and unknown product.
As a famous saying goes:
Better the devil you know....
Build the value proposition.
Once you've gone
through the steps
of defining, evaluating
and quantifying your value,
you are now in a position
to build your value proposition.
And here is an example
of a framework
that you can use to construct
your value proposition.
For these (target customers);
who are dissatisfied
with (the current alternative
or status quo);
our product is
(a new product);
that provides
(these key problem solving
capabilities);
unlike (the product alternative).
This subject will be revisited
in more detail when you
carry out the business model
canvas to later on.
There is often confusion between
value proposition
and unique selling proposition
or USP.
So, who is the chicken
and who is the egg?
Now, as we heard before
a value proposition is
a description or a clear statement
of the tangible results
a customer gets from using
your products or services.
While a unique selling proposition,
or USP
is only that aspect
that differentiates
a product or service from all
other similar products or services.
So, if you want a successful product
it is not enough to
only consider to provide
value, but it must be
possible to set
that value apart from other similar
value bearing products
currently available.
So, both the USP and
value proposition
need to exist,
but it must be pointed out that
the USP is inherently
part of the value proposition.
So fortunately, here we have
a clear answer of who is the chicken
and who is the egg.
In one of our earlier videos
on essential technologies
and construction,
we talked about the rising and
rapid rate of urbanization
in developing countries.
An issue, which has caught many
of these cities off guard
in these regions,
and unprepared for these mass
migrations, which
resulted in the emergence of slums,
as we discussed.
So, estimating market demand and
developing a market
in developing countries poses
a significant challenge.
This challenge arises
from the coexistence
of three distinct kinds of markets
in a single country.
The rural or agricultural sector.
The modern urban
or high income sector.
And the very large
transitional sector
usually represented by low income
urban slums.
The modern sector comprises
the rapidly expanding
middle class that is typically
located in the plush effluent
areas of the city
and may have easier access to
all sorts of infrastructure
and amenities.
The traditional rural sector
tends to work in the countryside
as it has for decades.
Now, production and consumption
patterns vary across
these three different sectors.
Therefore, when you establish
a market strategy, one must take
into consideration that
developing countries
will have these three different
market segments.
Each can prove profitable,
but each requires its own
marketing program
and products and services
that are appropriate
for its market characteristics.
For example, you may need to employ
a two tier pricing plan,
where you charge
a slightly higher price
for the effluent clientele,
while offering
a lower, affordable price to
the public sector
and rural districts.
Now, when pricing for
the less affording segments
for certain products,
it may be a good strategy
to think about applying
a price that considers
not just the acquisition price,
but rather the total cost
of ownership during the lifetime
of the product,
such as routine servicing
and the repair
of certain parts, etc.
Somewhat similar to the
automotive industries
that offer, say, a ten year
warranty on a new
car purchase price.
This could be an important
differentiating point
from competition,
as the clients in these markets
tend not to have
steady and reliable
revenue streams,
including governments.
Which, in fact, is also
one of the reasons
that many enterprises
in these markets
employ a pay as you go
or pay for use
business model.
Now, branding
is a very important
and tricky subject,
because even the customers
at the bottom of the pyramid
are highly sensitive to the
prestigious and powerful brands.
However, bear in mind that a lot
of these products from powerful
brands were designed for the needs
of industrialized countries
and tend to not fit well
with the needs of the markets
in developing countries.
Therefore, you may have a great
opportunity if you can
better focus and tailor your
value proposition
and USP with this in mind.
In general, it is highly recommended
to launch your product
in your domicile market,
which may or may not
be sufficiently large for your
product to be sustainable.
Whatever the case,
it is strategically important
to evaluate and export
an expansion opportunities
beyond your domestic market
as early as possible.
Today, virtually
all developing countries
tend to be part of regional
trade corridors
and economic agreements.
As a first step towards achieving
economies scale and being
able to reach several countries
in your region,
adopt a regional approach.
If we look at Africa as an example.
Many organizations have tended
to divide it into four zones.
With roughly comparable GDP's.
These zones are Southern Africa,
Eastern Africa, Western Africa
and Maghreb.
Picking the correct
regional breakdowns
and developing sustainable
partnerships with those regions
can be highly beneficial on
aspects such as
supply chain networks, for example.
As mentioned before
you may also benefit from
preferential bidding opportunities
for large government tenders,
even from other countries
in the whole sub-region,
in cases where trade corridors
and agreements have
or are being established.
Such as is the case in
Southern Africa
and East Africa, for example.
Now lets try and put some
of the things we discussed today
in perspective.
Let me start by asking you
a simple question.
Which region in the world will have
the largest working age population
in the world by 2035?
We'll come back to that question
in a moment.
Now, you might be asking yourself
should I really bother about
this PESTLE stuff or not?
In our earlier lesson,
we saw a bleak picture about
the extent of poverty and
all other doom and gloom
in Sub-Saharan Africa, especially.
In fact, it turns out that some
of the fastest growing economies
in the world are,
in fact, in this region.
It also turns out that
Africa will have the largest
working age population in the world
of 1.1 billion by 2034.
This is a highly valuable asset
in this rapidly aging world today.
And Africa will continue to have
the highest urbanisation trends,
which implies that there will be
continued strong growth
in the urban, low income
market segments,
but as well as the affluent segments,
if taking into account the expected
strong economic growth.
Now, having all this knowledge
could assist you
in planning and making
decisions timely
to invest in tailored products
and assuring proper
supply chains for
each of these segments.
And how would you timely
obtain all of this information?
By doing your PESTLE analysis,
for example.
And also the Porter's 5 Forces
and SWOT analysis.
And having your value proposition
and USP will enable you
to pinpoint your real,
addressable market
as opposed to trying to infer
that from market reports
which tend to be rather general and
unaffordable to most entrepreneurs.
So, in conclusion
To PESTLE or not to PESTLE?
That's the million dollar question.
Goodbye.