You must know that we
are in a rural zone.
It's true,
we are not very far from Yaoundé.
Between 55 and 65 miles,
less than 65 miles.
But it is actually
mainly a rural zone
where people mainly live off
subsistence crops
so they mainly live off agriculture.
There are subsistence crops,
cash crop cultivation,
mostly cacao.
Which means for cacao
the harvest is one
period of the year
a certain period,
from let's say September,
till march of the next year.
So at that moment,
visitor levels are at their highest,
meaning people come
more often to the hospital,
because at the
moment with the cash crops
it means they have more money,
they'll come more
willingly to the hospital
it's easier for them
because now
they can really
pay for their treatments
and this period
we could say,
we could consider it also
in health terms,
as the high hospital attendance period,
from November to December
November to December roughly,
then, it goes down bit by bit,
until March,
after March,
the attendance falls.
In our countries
it is hard to use
modern medecine
because it is expensive
and we don't have a
social security system
the patient pays for everything
and sometimes,
there are a lot of exams
that a patient would need
but because of their small income
they cannot do them.
So we try
to use our intelligence
to make an early diagnosis
and not always a clinical diagnosis
because the living standard
the buying power,
doesn't allow it.
Ad Lucem was created
for the poorer population
but between you and me,
you cannot
give good quality care
and even medication for free
so there is a small fee
that the patient must pay
for it to work.
So the poverty problem
means we often treat ill people
that don't have money
and that causes problems
for our financial management
because the hospital
finds it difficult to
get the money elsewhere
for the debt created by
these ill people
so sometimes,
we have to play a social role,
if you owe us 100,000
and you come in for
an emergency cesarian
we will operate on you,
and after the operation
when it amounts to 100'000
but you can't even pay 50'000
and you stay 1 month
sometimes two months,
even three in the hospital
stuck because of this 50'000 debt
and we have to help these people
sometimes we treat people
and just let them go.
So that creates a hole
in our budget
and there, without
the public grants
given by the government,
a lot is given by
the general direction
for our service mode,
we couldn't even function.
You would have to understand
that we must manage
the patients wallet,
what I mean by that is
his financial capacity,
you need to be able to control that.
You can't prescribe and exam
and send him or
her straight to Yaoundé
because they feel like
we are trying to get rid of them
and that, at least they know
that at Yaoundé
the cost will be huge.
When I try to
look at the anatomy
of the human body,
the way,
Lorie, she has slightly
dislocated her knee
the knee goes inward,
so when she walks
the foot is deformed
it is deformed
and you can see the deformity
when she walks.
That's it.
And it from a lack of means,
I could not possibly
take her to Yaoundé
to do the x-ray.
The other challenge,
is everything that has to do with
the financial side of healthcare
because unfortunately in Cameroon,
households still suffer
from the cost of healthcare
and that really is something of
an important challenge
for the government,
to be able to put into place
a solidary system
and insurance system
to finally allow
that all
can have access to health treatments
without paying a lot.
In Cameroon,
the price of health services
is in fact lower than the actual cost
which would be needed for the equipment,
that is the first fact.
The second fact,
when you buy a scanner,
well,
the scanners are very
high tech pieces of equipment
that need to work optimally,
meaning they must do exams
every single day
constantly,
you must do 20,30,40 scans a day
to hope to be able to
make it cost-effective
after five years in use
and that is not the case
in our countries
because the access to
these treatments
is still too expensive
for the population
to be able to afford these exams
you have to have your family contribute,
save up,
look for money here and there,
so the exam you must do within a day,
will be done a week later,
so when you multiply the exams,
the machines are under-used,
and the rate of use
doesn't follow the life expectancy
in order to make the
machine cost effective
and that,
is how they break down so often
when you haven't even started
to amortize the cost.
The problem is the durability
of this equipment.
And in the current context,
the hospital must ensure
a follow up
from the income generated
by the services
done within these health facilities