Hello.
In this video, we will continue
our journey through
the product value chain tool.
As for the other segments
of the chain, we will raise
some strategically important topics,
which are especially relevant
to low and middle-income countries.
We have already discussed issues
related to developing the product,
to manufacturing and marketing it.
Now we will look into
the distribution of our product.
You may have heard
about the term "logistics".
In industry,
logistics includes two main parts.
One is the upstream supply
of components and raw materials
to the manufacturer,
and the second is
the downstream transfer
of finished goods
from the manufacturer
to the customer.
In this video,
we will look especially
at the second part,
which is called distribution.
Distribution is the management
of the flow of goods
between the manufacturer
and the point of consumptions or use
by the customer.
The product must be delivered
according to contract specifications
in a perfect state, in due time,
and at a cost
which has been optimized.
In this chapter we will discuss
the following topics:
Distributions channels.
Shipping.
Packaging, which depends on
which shipping mode
has been selected.
Third party logistics.
Customs, taxes and regulations.
And finally, insurances
and Incoterms.
The distribution of our technology
can be realized
in many different ways.
We will spend quite some time
in this video discussing
practical aspects related to
transporting the product,
and yet there are
some fundamental options
we need to think about first.
Think for example how you acquire
consumer goods,
such as a tool for gardening.
Such a tool would most probably
be manufactured somewhere
and then shipped in large quantities
to a wholesaler.
The wholesaler would then
sell a batch to a retail shop
located near your home,
where you will finally buy it.
As we can see there are
two intermediaries
between the manufacturer
and the final customer.
For your technology as well,
we will need to decide
if you want to sell it
directly to your customer
or if you prefer to involve
some reseller.
There are many different options,
which all have
their own advantages
and disadvantages.
This is a complex subject.
But I would like to give you
a general sense of the trade-offs.
In our first option we decide
to find a partner
who will purchase from our company
and then resell
to the final customer.
This partner could be
a local company,
which already has
a large customer base.
We can just benefit
from an existing access
to the customers,
which will expedite
the deployment of our technology.
In that way, we would reach
large-scale much quicker.
The downside is,
that the reseller will, of course,
take a margin
from the sales revenues.
A second problem is that
there is a risk that we won't have
any direct contact
with the customer.
This can prevent us
from being aware of issues
with customer satisfaction
and from reacting
before it is too late,
if there is a problem.
Also, we need to conduct
a very detailed analysis
of our partner's reputation
and capabilities,
since this will be critical
for our success.
In the second option
we decide to create
our own distribution channel.
This will generally mean
that we can expect higher margins
as we don't have to pay
any intermediaries.
We will also have the advantage
of a close proximity
between our company
and the customers.
One downside,
which can be quite serious,
is that creating our own channels
is costly.
Creating a subsidiary can also mean
lots of lengthy legal
and administrative hassles
in certain countries.
Remember our
ease of doing business index.
Also, it can be very complex
to manage from abroad.
In general, companies opt for a mix
of owned and partnered channels,
depending on the customer segments
and product sold.
Getting this distribution mix right
is of crucial strategic importance.
There is space for innovation here.
For example, you may want to think
about direct sales
through the internet,
or even mobile systems.
Whichever way your customer
acquires your product
and unless your product is software,
the next issue you will then
have to solve is
how your product will be
physically shipped to the customer.
Fundamentally, the first question
we need to ask ourselves is
how we will transport our products
from the site of manufacturing
to the customer.
This mainly depends
on three key questions.
The first is, what is the product
that we want to ship?
It is important to know
the product well, obviously.
Since this will determine
the conditions
for the shipping and handling.
For example,
if the product is a vaccine
it requires a "cold chain".
We need to know
the components of the product,
as some of them may have to comply
with specific regulations.
For example,
if a lithium battery is involved,
which can catch fire.
Depending on the product
and specific market
this will also determine
the lead time
and the costs involved.
These elements are, of course,
very dependent
on the transport mode.
For example, if we decide
to ship our product by air,
which is very costly,
it may take two or three days,
as compared to weeks
if we use the cheaper option
of maritime transport.
The second questions is
what is the point of origin
of the product?
Sometimes the product
is completely manufactured
in some specific location
and shipped to the customer.
But more often the cost
can be optimized
if the final product is assembled
close to the customer.
For example,
when the product involves heavy
or cumbersome components
which can be locally manufactured.
It is also important to consider
that there may be instances
where we need to keep some inventory
of semi-finished or finished goods,
as this can counterbalance
fluctuations in demand
or geopolitical instabilities.
The third questions is,
who is the recipient?
This question goes back
to the sales strategy.
It could be that we try
to sell directly to individuals,
or we might sell to intermediaries,
who will then
further deploy the product
to the final customer.
Here as well there are
quite a few possibilities
to optimize our shipping strategy
for cost, quality and lead time.
In general, shipping involves
lots of aspects,
which will ideally be handled
by someone who has the experience
in the specific country.
It is always interesting
to work close
to an internationally recognized
hub, where lots of goods are
in transit as a start.
This will tend to reduce unknowns
in terms of paperwork
and regulation.
As we consider the global
shipping strategy for our product,
we also need to hedge
for some specific risks,
such as fluctuations
in freight costs,
geopolitical problems or variations
in currency exchange rates,
which can be a game-stopper.
We need to think about alternatives
and create back-plans
right from the start.
As we want to ship our product
we will obviously need
to protect it during the transfers.
The first role of packaging is
to provide sufficient protection
for the goods during
transportation and handling.
As we usually do not know
the shipping mode in advance
there are several layers
of packaging involved.
The primary packaging,
which directly contains the products,
will provide an individual
general protection.
Then, the separate
primary unit packs
will often be grouped together
in secondary packages
for transport.
These secondary packages
might then be placed on a pallet
for easy handling
prior to being put into a container,
which would be our tertiary package.
These second and third levels
of packaging will strongly depend
on the shipping mode.
For fragile products
we may need to define
maximum acceptable temperature,
humidity, vibration and shock loads.
These transport specifications
will help us design
adequate packaging,
which will be adapted
to the corresponding
optimized shipping mode.
We need to take
these parameters into account
as early as when we are
designing product,
because the overall cost
of the product
may be largely influenced
by transport costs.
It may also happen that even
a slight modification to the product
and to its packaging can have
a great influence on these costs.
As said before,
we also need to be aware
that some products
like chemicals, liquids, explosives,
biohazardous goods,
need to comply with special
standards and regulations.
They may require specific packaging
and handling processes,
which depend on the shipping mode
and the country.
The packaging will also need
to carry mandatory information,
including labeling,
regulatory compliance markings
such as de CE mark in Europe,
as well as
the traceability references.
Traceability means that we need
to be able to know exactly how,
when and by whom
the product was transported
and finally received.
This is mandatory for many goods
such as medical devices,
pharmaceuticals, food and so forth.
International shipping is
such a highly specialized activity
that most suppliers
and even large companies
prefer to subcontract
these activities
to third-party experts.
The third-party shipping companies
are generally divided
into two types.
First, those specialized
in single pack shipments.
These well-known global companies,
such as UPS, FedEx or DHL,
are specialized in shipping single
and low-weight boxes
or envelopes to private consumers
and businesses.
They are efficient and provide
simple, all-inclusive,
quick and reliable
point-to-point logistics.
These companies also operate
their own means of transportation
like aircraft and trucks.
However, their price
per unit of weight and volume
is high.
Second, there are those specialized
in freight forwarding.
The freight forwarding companies
are  less known
to the general public,
as they work mainly
in the business to business markets.
Usually, freight forwarders
do not move the goods themselves,
but they work with carriers
for the transportations
and customs brokers
for the customs clearances.
They usually handle larger
and heavier loads.
For instance, they can handle
a whole container
from the factory to the customer.
The price per unit of weight
can be surprisingly low.
They are one of the pillars
of the global world economy,
as they move goods
around the world at a low cost.
The differentiation
between those two types
of third-party companies
tends to dissapear nowadays
as the single-pack
shipping companies have entered
the freight forwarding business
and freight forwarders
are also getting more diversified.
Logistics companies
in developing countries
are not very different from
their industrialized counterparts
with regards to performance.
However, they tend to be
more fragmented
in developing countries.
Some companies may specialize
in  a particular region
or transport mode,
some others will specialize
in customs clearance
in a specific country,
while others won't.
In difficult regions of the world,
a third-party shipping partner is
absolutely crucial
for a successful distribution,
and this needs to be carefully chosen.
Customs remain a major burden
in many parts of the world,
as they will increase costs
and lead times.
International tariff headings
have been defined
to differentiate all kinds of goods
that can be traded.
Specific products might be subject
to very different customs duties
depending on its tariff heading
and country of origin.
This is a tricky and complex topic
and customs regulations are
specific to each country
and might be subject to exceptions,
special cases and modifications.
For example, some countries
have decided not to tax
import of medical goods
in an effort to facilitating access.
As we think about
which country to work with,
customs duties and regulations
may have a great influence
on our industrial strategy.
For instance, many countries
would not tax half-finished products
as much as finished goods.
Therefore, a good strategy might be
to consider importing
semi-finished goods,
which will then be assembled
in the country to avoid high taxes.
In addition to taxation issues,
customs are also responsible
to check that the product complies
with the local legislation
and require certifications.
This can become very troublesome
as customs officers are not
specialists in all local regulations
for all types of products.
So, we might get our product
stuck at the customs
because of a missing document,
whether it is
really mandatory to have it or not.
Unfortunately, we might say,
customs officers can have
significant power,
as they can decide
to block goods of high value
at customs.
In some countries
corrupt customs officers
will use this opportunity
to request bribes.
On top of the customs duties,
the customer will have to pay
the value-added tax or VAT
to the local tax authorities.
Most of the countries in the world
apply this consumption tax
on products and services regardless
of the product's origin.
As you certainly know
there are all sorts
of economic agreements
between countries
and entire regions or continents,
which define the rules that apply
to the trade of goods.
Amongst the most important ones,
we will find free-trade areas,
customs unions, common markets
and economic unions, etcetera.
These different forms of cooperation
tend to define the level
of the trade barriers
that exist between
concerned countries,
Trade barriers can come
in multiple forms.
which can be based on tariffs,
which are import or export taxes,
or non-tariffs.
Non-tariff trade barriers can be,
for example,
import quotas, subsidies,
customs delays,
technical barriers or other systems
preventing or impeding trade.
In Central Africa, for example,
there is the Economic and Monetary
Community of Central Africa
or CEMAC, which is the customs
and monetary union.
In Southern Africa there is
the Southern African Development
Community or SADC,
which is a free-trade area.
The trade of goods within
a free-trade agreement region
will be subject to limited,
and sometimes,
even zero customs duties.
It is certainly wise to carefully
look into those issues,
as we develop our technology
and business model.
This is yet another reason
why we need to consider
involving some expert,
who is used to handling
customs issues in the country
we are considering.
Let us now listen
to a customs officer
in Douala, Cameroon,
who discusses these questions
from his perspective.
An extended delay to process goods
at the customs
can be due to several issues.
Let's not forget that,
at the port area level,
several parties take part
in the process.
There is, indeed, the customs bureau,
the consignee,
the stevedore,
the port authority...
There are also other units,
such a the health department,
in the case of medical equipment,
There are plenty of services involved.
And sometimes,
the service that matters is not well informed
of the procedures.
It could be preliminary procedures,
for example,
at the Ministry of Health,
where it might be required
to ask for an authorization,
or it could be afterwards,
dealing with port area parties,
because sometimes procedures
must be anticipated before shipping.
Sometimes, people are not aware
of the procedures
and if you'd like the procedures to last
as little as possible,
you should start the procedure
before the ship arrival,
with the assistance of a professional,
and starting at the right time,
issuing all necessary documents
beforehand,
and that these documents
are very well prepared.
If you go
through all these steps,
you'll ensure that customs procedures
will be done within deadlines.
It is easy to imagine that goods
might suffer from damages or lost
along the whole logistics process.
Although it is not compulsory,
it is highly recommended
to look into ensuring the goods
during distribution paths.
Since casualties are relatively low
in comparison to the huge amount
of goods transported,
the cost of insurance is
relatively low as well.
Most of the time it is much less
than one percent of the goods value
but the premium will depend
on the level of risk estimated
by the insurance company.
International commercial terms
or Incoterms
are a series of predefined
commercial terms
that clearly define the obligations,
costs and risks involved
in the delivery of goods
from the seller to the buyer.
For instance, Ex Works,
which is abbreviated EXW
with the name
of the place of delivery attached
means that the seller
will make the goods available
in his own premises.
It is up to the customer
to pick them up there
and to take care of the whole
transportation process,
including insurance,
taxes, customs, etcetera.
At the other end of the spectrum,
we have so the called
Delivery Duty Paid
or DDP,
which means that it is the seller
who will organize and pay
for the delivery of the goods
to the customer.
There are many variants
in-between those two cases,
which places more or less obligation
on either the buyer's
or the seller's side.
It is highly advisable
to be aware of these aspects,
as they may have
important consequences
on risk, cost and lead times.
Finally, if you have
a software product
things will look quite different
since your product
does not have to be
physically packaged
and shipped in a container.
However, asking yourself,
how the software will be made
available to the customer
remains a central question.
It will probably involve
regulatory aspects,
which are specific to each domain.
For example,
patient data privacy protection
is a very important topic
in the field of medical software.
Of course,
there is much more to be said
on the topic of distribution.
However, we believe
that we have touched on
the most important aspects.
I think we have convinced you
that it is highly advisable
to start discussion on the subject
with knowledgeable people
early on in the process.
Goodbye.