Hello.
We have now reached the final
stage of the product value chain,
that is use and support.
Since your goal is to achieve
sustainable impact,
this phase is particularly crucial
to your overall mission,
as we will discuss.
There is often a tendency
to think that once the product
has been successfully
realized and delivered,
the job is done and dusted.
However, we must remember that
the key objective for your product
is to obtain sustainable impact,
which implies providing
a continued and reliable supply
of intended benefits
with your products.
Therefore, this requires such
a product that is always functional,
and for as long of
a period as possible.
This section discusses elements
related to putting your new product
into use and providing it
with proper support,
in order to ensure it's
long term viability
and ultimately impact.
And in this session we will discuss
commissioning, training
maintenance, decommissioning,
and recycling.
The main objective of commissioning
is to finally put
a new product into use.
Depending on the type of product,
commissioning may also involve
establishing and verifying
safety objectives, connecting it
to the requisite utilities,
as well as the procurement
of sufficient stocks
of material required
to put the product in full use.
It is very important though
that the documents relating
to the commissioning
process be kept well.
Another important issue
is the establishment
of a user feedback mechanism.
Presumably, you have done
as much as you can
to make sure that your product
is as user friendly as possible
so it is important to verify
for every client, if possible,
if they are indeed happy
or not with the "usability"
,
ergonomic features
and other aspects related
to using the product properly.
This could be achieved by
a simple questionnaire, for example
but it would provide you invaluable
feedback of what is working well
and what needs improvement.
Commissioning is also the period
for finalizing how technical support
will be provided
and who will carry it out and when.
And we'll discuss this some more
in the coming slides.
So overall, commissioning
requires appreciable planning
and adequate resources
must be budgeted for.
Many problems are known to occur
during commissioning, in fact
if it is not planned properly.
And these problems
can seriously hamper
the product from ever obtaining
proper functional levels
and frequently leads
to premature breakdown
and use discontinuation.
An extremely important point
is that the commissioning process
must be accompanied
by a suitable training program
for potential operators and users.
If you are based in regions that
tend do have high
or frequent personnel turnover
it would be prudent to train
your needed critical personnel
in duplicate, for example.
Because the availability
of the suitable, qualified personnel
at all times is fundamental
to the long-term longevity
of the product
and it maybe necessary to recruit
new staff beforehand, if insufficient
on none available in-house.
It is also likely that you
will not be in a position
to set up your own after sales
infrastructure everywhere
you'll be selling the product.
The common strategy used
by many businesses
is to find already
existing local distributors,
who may also have the technicians
to support local needs
for repair and maintenance.
In that case,
you also have to design
a suitable training program
for such strategic partners,
in order to make sure they are
suitably equipped and must be
regularly updated with
new developments.
Training can involve various formats,
depending on the complexity
of the product.
For example, it could be in the form
of a tutorial that is embedded
in the equipment itself,
which could be regularly updated
via internet links when new
product developments or revision occur.
Or it could be accompanied by actual workshops
at the client's premises,
especially if your product
contains complex procedures.
Providing a workshop
also allows you to include
all the background
or the theoretical information
that maybe necessary to understand
and optimally operate
the equipment.
In our previous slide,
we emphasized the importance
of properly commissioning
your new product
in order to assure
it is put into full optimal use.
Unfortunately in many cases,
for as long as the product seems
to be running smoothly,
little or no care is given
to routine and preventive
maintenance issues.
How ever rugged and hardy you
may try and engineer your product,
it is a fact of life that
certain parts will
experience wear and tear and
will need replacement eventually.
If you are dealing with
complex instrumentation,
it may also require occasional
routine maintenance
such as re-calibration.
Maintenance is crucial
to ensuring that your product
continues to deliver
optimum performance,
which is a key enabler towards
your desired impact.
With devices, it will also ensure
continued safety
of the product, for example.
Now, despite
it's obvious significance
it is often neglected
in many developing countries
for reasons that have partially
been discussed in other lectures,
such as the lack
of suitably skilled staff,
cost of maintenance contracts, etc.
It's no always that we think of
or can afford
to negotiate a a maintenance contract
as soon as we get the device.
It can be delivered
with a minimal warranty
that rarely goes
beyond the first year.
After the first year, we become
dependent from the dealer
that didn't leave a
technical documentation
and holds us in case
of a breakdown
because we can only call him.
And as we're not under warranty
he can apply his own conditions
before coming.
Those are elements
that are troublesome
in the devices commissioning chain.
Those devices are handled
by private softwares
So
if you're not
from Siemens,
if you're not from Philips,
if you're not
from General Electrics
you can't access the equipment.
Even in case of breakdown.
So you have to ask the salesman,
the service provider.
You have to sign
a maintenance contract
but for this contract to work out
the service provider
will need
several reparation contracts
so it's interesting for him when
he has several equipments on one territory.
And not one or two.
And in this context
we can imagine some sort of contract
or deal
would be signed between
the service provider
and the Ministry of Health
to resolve a certain number
of very simple breakdowns.
It's obvious that
for a certain level of breakdown
you'll have to ask
for the expertise of the North.
The training of a local engineer,
when there is one
which is sometimes present
in the contract
is not made...
because normally the service provider
when the contract was well negotiated
has to deliver the equipment
and train somebody to its' maintenance.
Sometimes this is not done.
It should be, I think, the supplier
who installs the equipment
who should train him
to recognize early signs
of frequent breakdowns.
It isn't a very long
or complex training.
It's just teaching us
to read code
and when you see
this or that come up
understand this or that problem
is going to happen.
And call us,
it's that simple.
Now all of this discussion
highlights the important issue
I wish to re-emphasize
that is, when you are designing
your product do not think
only about fulfilling
the intended function
as the only criteria for success,
but also pay very close attention
and consideration
about how this product
will maintained and repaired
and how you can make this process
as simple and cost effective
as possible.
For example, if it's
a device or equipment
you may consider incorporating
remote monitoring features
via mobile telephony, for example,
that would collect pertinent data
routinely from each and every one
of your devices out there,
which could potentially
be used to detect problems
before they occur and eventually
pre-empt and prevent total machine
breakdown and failure.
And even when the machine
requires to be repaired,
think hard and carefully
about how to make this process
as simple as possible,
so that anyone can virtually do it,
such as using plug-and-play
strategies where you only need
a minimum of tools,
such as a screwdriver.
Also, if possible, try and make sure
that most of the repairs
that would be required
could be based
on universally available parts.
In fact, we can go as far
as saying that the issue
of simplifying maintenance
and repair can, in by itself,
be a fertile hunting ground for new
innovations for developing markets.
In other words,
for many existing products
you may not need to develop
them from scratch,
but can simply engineer features
that made them easier to maintain
and repair, even
in remote rural areas.
Sooner or later your product
will reach the end of its life cycle
and will need to be rid off
or decommissioned.
The term decommissioning
is generally used
for major equipment.
Manufacturing plants,
production lines
or hazardous products.
Decommissioning is an important
part of the life cycle
of an equipment or installation,
but often receives insufficient
attention during
the planning, budgeting
and operational phases
of the equipment.
This has lead to many unforeseen
issues and challenges
when the products reaches
the end their economic life,
because decommissioning can be
a complex multi-disciplinary process
and it may require the management
of diverse issues
and the involvement
of international
and government agencies
local communities and NGOs.
So make it a point to understand
the sectorial laws, regulations
and guidelines applicable
to decommissioning your products
including any tax issues.
In general, decommissioning is
the task of the client who owns
their equipment,
but in many developing countries
waste management
and recycling is often a challenge
and not carried out appropriately.
So you may wish to consider
developing a suitable plan
for the recovery or the recycling
of product material, and perhaps
include it as the last step
of your after sales services.
And the cost of this activity
could be integrated in your
initial sales price in fact.
This way you would be sure
that your products
does not end up contravening
some of the sustainable
development goals,
which you sought to promote
with your innovation to begin with.
So overall, it is important
to design a product
that simplifies this phase
as much as possible,
such as avoiding
the use of toxic components
or difficult to recycle materials.
We hope that you have understood
the importance of this final step
of use and support
and it's crucial contribution
towards attaining your sustainable
development objectives
with your innovation.
Furthermore, we hope you
have appreciated the significance
of taking a holistic approach
and looking at the total cost
of ownership to your customer
when thinking about your product.
Because the purchase
is only the first step,
but if the other costs
are not factored in or considered
your product may quickly become
a white elephant and be unable
to achieve it's intended impact.
This now brings us to
the end of the discussion
of the product value
chain analysis tool.
I hope that you have appreciated
how important it is to consider
all the steps, and the various steps
within each of the steps, in fact.
And also the fact that innovation
may not only be needed
only at the R&D phase,
but there may be other innovation
opportunities right through
the other sections
of the product value chain.
Goodbye.