If you want to buy an x-ray machine,
if you want to buy a dialysis machine,
the first question you ask is
in what conditions does it work?
Because before ordering
the equipment,
you need to be sure
that we have the
right environment to use it,
to be adequate
and it is not possible
to arrive in this kind of hospital,
this envrionment,
you see a lot of cars parked
because the x-ray machine is here,
but it hasn't been
working for a month.
Because sometimes
even the planning
for acquiring the equipment
doesn't take into account
these aspects,
especially for big equipment.
For example,
now we have
built the
imaging centre,
we have built the
hemodialysis centre
we have a lot of
other equipment
for example
for radiology,
they are quite
heavy equipments
that you really
need to plan
before you order them
and for the functionality
and to put the
budget into place
obtain for the
health facility
a competent
technicien
to train us how
to use this equipment
but, there's so many things
that aren't taken into account
from the start.
Where we were trained,
we usually have seen
installed equipment,
before it arrives,
we had meetings
on what the machine does,
the expected innovations
compared to the old machine,
and very often,
a service technician would go get training
somewhere where they
already had this machine,
so that when the equipment
does arrive
there is at least one person
who is familiar with it.
Well.
On top of that,
those who install, the technicians,
whether it be in house
engineers,
of the company
producing the machine
or the application engineers,
they come first,
and have a meeting
with the maintenance team
and at the delivery,
the two parties sign the document
and the service that
must use the machine
sign to say they have
understood how to use it
and understood the
necessary precautions
for the optimal
functioning of the machine.
And only then
the machine is considered
as commissionned.
Unfortunately here,
what I have seen
is, well I don't want
to say the opposite
to not be too
extreme,
but was practically
very rarely applied in this way.
Even when the
equipment is bought,
for it's commissionning,
which usually
means the supplier
has been contacted
whether it be a dealer
or private operator,
whatever, he
comes to the hospital,
he just needs the
administrative authorisation
and he comes and
installs the equipment.
What some of these
dealers or suppliers
have done in the past,
and that some still do,
is that the installation is
managed like a state secret.
During the installation,
the room is closed,
none or very few precautions
are taken to involve the personnel
in the service, which would be essential
in order to understand the
entire process of the installation
not on a technical level,
but at least the details we
will need in the future
to use the equipment
or just to know when to call
in case of a preventive
maintenance alert.
Sometimes the technical
manuals of the equipment
aren't even left with us
to be given to the bio-medical
engineers in case of a problem.
And sometimes,
the training of the local
engineer
when there is one,
which is stated in to the contract,
is not done
because in principle
the dealer,
when the contract
was properly negotiated,
must leave the equipment
and also train someone
for maintenance,
and sometimes that is not done,
so those are the elements
that are a problem
with the commissioning.