In the second part of chapter two,
I tried to summarize
the mechanics, the mathematics
that underlies the description
of the so-called
McConnell-Bloch equations,
which allow one to derive
such things as line broadening
line narrowing, coalescence
and all these things
on a more serious basis, rather than
that of pure empirical discussions.
Now, Peter Hore has collected,
a remarkably well-selected,
set of examples
of chemical exchange.
I would like to start with
the example that Peter mentions
as one of the last
of his illustrations because I think
it's one of the
most important ones.
Also, it happens to be
discovered in Switzerland
at ETH Zurich by Kurt Wuthrich
whose name I wrote out here.
And Kurt Wuthrich got a
Nobel Prize for NMR of biomolecules.
This was in 2002, if I remember correctly.
And he once said, in an
informal lecture, that the effect
that I'm going to explain
to you now, was one of his
most important discoveries.
And I would tend to agree
with that judgement.
He has done many, many things,
but this is very intriguing.
So, what we're talking about
is tyrosine, the motion of tyrosine
which occurs in proteins.
And in fact, the side chain of a tyrosine,
you have the backbone here.
Then you have the CH2, and you
have a phenyl ring,
which is para hydroxy
group, so that's tyrosine.
And of course, there are four protons
in positions two, three, five and six.
If the tyrosine is rotating freely,
as it would be in solution,
then you would expect
protons five and three,
which are in the ortho- position,
to have the same chemical shift.
And likewise, you would expect six
and two to have the same chemical shifts.
Now, Wuthrich did not record
these spectra in free solution,
but he considered tyrosine,
actually number 35, which is
in this protein, which is called
basic pancreatic trypsin inhibitor,
which has about 70 or so
amino acids and number 35
happens to be a tyrosine.
There are other tyrosines,
but this one is particularly interesting.
As you can see, you can
record spectra BPTI
from very low temperatures,
just above freezing,
to very high temperatures.
In this case, without significant
denaturation of the protein,
which is not obvious,
many proteins would decompose.
But this one is quite happy.
And you see that at high temperature,
you see the effect that
I sort of hinted at, that protons
two and six occur at
a given chemical shift,
about 7.2 or so ppm.
Whereas, protons three and five
give rise to a single chemical shift
which is actually split into
a doublet.
And a doublet actually comes
from the coupling between
the ortho and the meta positions.
But that's not relevant
to today's discussion.
As you lower the temperature,
which is easy to do,
you find that that spectrum
gets more complicated.
And the first thing that happens,
going from fast flipping to slow flipping
is that this broadens out,
and then it splits up into
two distinct resonances.
One corresponds to the ortho position,
sorry, the meta position two.
And the other corresponds
to the meta position six.
So these two protons now have
vastly different chemical shifts.
That comes not from
the tyrosine itself,
but from the environment.
It turns out that the protein
environment here is distinct
from the protein environment
on the other side.
And therefore, these two protons
are exposed to different local fields,
and have different chemical shifts.
Something similar happens
if we look at protons three and five.
So those are the two in ortho position,
which I now put in a square box.
So at high temperature,
they are simply degenerate.
The doublet structure
as I said is irrelevant now.
And when you go to lower
and lower temperature,
they broaden and they split up
into two distinct resonances,
five and three here,
two distinct doublets.
Now the remarkable thing is
that this happens,
although the temperature scale
is the same, you see that
the coalescence for the two
protons that are close together
at low temperature, occurs
at about 40 degrees or so.
Whereas the coalescence
for the two protons
that are far away from each other
occurs at about 60 degrees or so.
That is simply in fact,
a verification of the laws
established by Bloch and McConnell
and can be calculated
with the type of theory
that I explained in the previous part.
Actually, beyond a simple illustration,
this picture has dramatic implications
for protein and the understanding
of protein dynamics
because this interconversion
really supposes that
the protein flips as it is
drawn by this line here--
that the aromatic ring of the
tyrosine actually flips over.
Now that means that
it must be standing upright
perpendicular to the plane
of the paper,
maybe for a very short interval.
But it has to be able
to flip over from
the flat position one way
to the flat position the other way.
so that the positions
of two and six can interchange.
And three and five
likewise, interchange.
Now that implies that
the protein must be dynamic,
that it must be able
to breathe, as it were,
in order to leave sufficient room
for such an exchange process.
Indeed, a quite remarkable observation.
Now there are more basis examples,
and this one was probably already
discovered in the '50s,
possibly at CERN
by the very early investigations
of Dharmatti and others.
Now we're talking about ethanol.
It turns out that if we take
the multiplets of ethanol at neutral pH.
So this is at pH 7 here.
Then, we cannot not only see
the conventional triplet
for the methyl group
that is due to the neighboring CH2,
but the CH2 is not simply
split into a quartet
because of the neighboring CH3,
but it's in addition, split into a doublet
because of the neighboring OH.
Likewise, we can actually see
this OH proton here.
And it is split into a triplet
because it is coupled, scalar coupled,
with a neighboring CH2 row.
Now it turns out that
you only have to do it
at a very minute amount,
a trace amount of acid
for this effect to go away.
And then we observe
a singlet here.
And the multiplet of the CH2 group
collapses to a simple binomial quartet.
So the question is, why do we
observe such a collapse in the spectrum?
The answer is, if we consider
a simple molecule,
a monomeric form of ethanol,
we may have a proton
called "A" attached to it,
which may well have a polarization
which is parallel to the magnetic field
which we could call alpha.
And the external proton, the one that
comes from the water or from the acid,
would be called proton B.
And that, in this hypothesis has
the opposite polarization, namely beta.
If these two exchange,
and that is exactly
what chemical exchange is all about,
then, of course, the B proton
will become part of the ethanol molecule.
But it will retain its beta polarization.
Whereas the A proton will go out
into the medium
while retaining its alpha polarization.
From the point of view
of the CH2 protons here,
that's these ones here,
which that we find here again,
it looks as if the neighboring
proton in the hydroxy position
has flipped from alpha to beta.
And this flip can occur
at a phenomenal rate
because acid base reactions
are extremely fast and therefore,
they can be--they lead to a collapse
of the multiplicity of the CH2 group.
And that is exactly what we see here.
You will recall that this line here
can also be broadened
because of exchange between
OH and the environment,
so it's not easy to observe
such a sharp line.
But normally, we just see this part here.
We should indeed see a quartet here,
and a triplet here.
One of the best examples
that Peter Hore has cited in his book,
actually due to David Grant
and others in Salt Lake City,
is the example of cis-decalin.
Cis-decalin can be drawn
as a flat molecule.
So this is not aromatic,
but it still can be drawn like this.
And if we do it that way,
we can number the postions.
So we talk about
the carbons or the protons,
in this case, the carbons.
This is the conventional
numbering of this molecule.
And if we draw it like this, it is not
surprising that the symmetry makes
that the chemical shifts
of these two sides are identical.
And you can go further,
and you see that
the chemical shifts of this side should
be the same as this side.
And this side should be
the same as this side.
And then of course, the other
sides are distinct,
so we find that these sides
are all distinct from the previous ones.
And then that effect is that
at 46 degrees Celsius,
when the molecule can be
essentially considered
as interconverting so fast
that we allow to draw it on a flat plane.
Well, at that temperature,
we only have one peak
that corresponds to these two
bridging carbons.
We have one peak that
corresponds to the four carbons
that I have circled here.
And there's one peak for the four carbons
that I have put in square boxes.
So far, so good.
Now it turns out that if
we go to lower temperature,
from 46 to 16 to -12 to -29,
then the situation becomes
more complicated.
And a little bit like, in the case of
Wuthrich's tyrosine, we see
that these lines split up.
And the reason is that at
lower temperature, we now have
to consider these molecules as
separate rotamers, or separate confomers.
And that the symmetry is lifted.
So we still have a symmetry
between these two,
and likewise between these two,
that has been preserved.
And indeed that line doesn't move
at all as a function of temperature.
But we see now,
that for example, this line,
although it's the same as this line,
it is no longer the same as this line.
And no longer the same
from that line.
So we see one and five,
which still pile up together,
and we have four and eight,
which are still degenerate.
But they are no longer equal.
However, if we warm them up,
so you see that one and five,
and four and eight are here,
and they will tend to coalesce
and end up with the positions
that I've indicated previously.
Now we see that this,
there's here a two-fold coalescence.
We notice, by the way
that in this case, the coalescence occurs
at about the same temperature.
And that the splitting between
these two and these two, by accident,
happen to be about the same.
This is a very good example.
In fact, at the beginning
of this chapter, I spoke about
the interconversion of cyclohexane,
which as I mentioned,
is too fast where you see
when you mix cis-decaline
it becomes slow enough so that you
can observe it at room temperature
or in the vicinity of room temperature.
The next example is much
more sophisticated.
This is known as bullvalene.
It's one of these molecules
that was probably designed
in order to get into the
Guinness Book of Records
for maximum complexity.
And in fact, all we have to remember
is that we have a cyclopropene unit
where we have three positions,
Carbon 13 positions, which appear here.
And we have a bridging position
which is a long position here.
We have all sorts of rearrangements,
so-called Cope rearrangements
where the double bonds travel
and the cyclopropene ring opens up.
I will not give you a lecture
on organic chemistry,
but you see that this cycle here,
it turns up here and so on and so forth.
And in doing so, for example,
this site here, which was the isolated D,
now becomes a site A, which is typical
of the environment of cyclopropene.
And so indeed, there's an
interconversion between A and D.
And in fact, the entire process
can be summed up
in this sort of topological graph,
showing that D goes to A.
A goes to C, C to B, and B remains
in part, equal to itself
in the course of this rearrangement,
this Cope rearrangement.
Now we see again that at high
temperature, there's only one position.
But as we lower the temperature
it splits up into many lines.
And we can, of course, precisely
determine the exchange rates
of these processes by doing
an analysis of these line shapes.
So, the next example in Peter Hore's book
should be more to the liking
of people who are interested
in organometallic chemistry.
He is interested, so it explains
and cites an example
of the ruthenium complex
where you have the tri-carbon ruthenium
which is sort of hovering
over this cyclooctatetraene ring.
And in doing so, can find itself
attached to different positions.
So we have two ordinary double bonds,
in this delocalized affair
which is the location where
the ruthenium is most strongly attached.
And it turns out that the ruthenium
is not very tightly bound to this
and can move a little bit like the hands
of a clock around a circle.
And in doing so, at high temperature,
we have a single line in Carbon 13,
but as the temperature is decreased,
it splits up into a manifold.
And you can see that again,
we can draw topological diagrams
which show the exchange rates between
these two different, four different forms.
It turns out that the question here
is whether we have a 1-2 shift,
or a 1-3 shift, or a 1-4 shift,
or a 1-5 shift?
And the spectra allow you
to rule out some of these mechanisms
and decide, choose one of the
ones that is correct.
So the next example in this chapter
has already been discussed
in an earlier chapter about
scalar couplings between
spin 1/2, such as Carbon 13,
and quadrapolar spins
such as Lithium 6, in this case.
So Lithium 6, to remind you,
has a spin of I equal one.
And therefore, has three possible states,
M equal plus one, zero or minus one.
And consequently, the neighboring
Carbon 13 here, if there were only
one lithium, would be split into
a triplet, with three equal intensities.
So this is known
as a non-binomial triplet.
But as we have discussed before,
it turns out that lithium can build
a tetrahedral structure.
And that we have these
tertiary butane molecules,
butanol molecule groups
which can attach
not to the corners of this
tetrahedron, but to these faces
in the middle of each
of the triangular faces.
And when that occurs at low temperature,
each Carbon 13 will be coupled
to three Lithium 6.
And it results in a rather peculiar
non-binomial multiplet like this
at low temperature.
But the situation gets even
more complex if we heat it up.
So if we go from low
to high temperature
because then it turns out
that these groups here
can move about from
one surface to another.
In fact, they can hop from
one triangular surface to another.
Or if you prefer, they stay
where they are.
But it's the lithium cluster
that rotates within the cloud
of the carbon substituents.
Whatever this case may be,
it turns out that at 26 degrees Celsius,
we find that each Carbon 13 is coupled
not to three lithiums, but four lithiums,
because all four lithiums, even this
remote one, will at one point
be close to the Carbon 13,
and have a stronger coupling.
We see two interesting things.
First of all, the multiplet
becomes more complex.
And also, the effector scalar coupling,
there is a splitting here
between this and this, is larger
than it is here.
It is actually reduced
because of the average.
So I'd like to summarize
chapter four.
The chapter that Peter Hore
dedicated to chemical exchange
which seems to be one
of his favorite subjects.
And is indeed, one of the key aspects
of modern magnetic resonance.
So chemical exchange effects in NMR
can arise either
from chemical or from
conformational equilibria.
In the slow exchange regime,
NMR lines are simply broadened,
and we can measure
that exchange rates by
looking at the line widths.
Now, the difference in NMR
frequencies between exchanging spins
can be averaged by fast exchange.
It is the magnitude of delta nu,
that is to say the difference
in the chemical shifts between
the nuclei that are involved
in exchange processes,
relative to the exchange rate constants
that determines whether
the exchange process is
in the slow or in the fast regime.
Chemical exchange effects give
information on the rates and mechanisms
of chemical reactions, molecular
rearrangements and internal motions.
Now most comments in Peter Hore's book
refer to chemical exchange
between sites that are distinct
because of their chemical shifts.
But there are other ways
of distinguishing sites.
And one of them, for example,
is quadrapole interactions in solids.
Here, at the Ecole Polytechnique
in Lausanne, we have spent years
determining the spectra
of Nitrogen 14 which
is a quadrupolar nucleus
with a spin one,
and has a quadrupole interaction
that ranges from one
to about five megahertz.
Now in that case, we have observed
exchange broadening effects
between different sites that
are interchanging at very high rates.
So when the exchange rate
is say one megahertz,
that means the lifetime is
on the order of 10 to the -9.
That is to say seconds,
that is to say nanoseconds.
And consequently, the n-14 spectra
are sensitive to processes
that occur on that timescale
of about a nanosecond.
And it all depends on which
nuclei you look at
and in which environment.
Chemical exchanges are probably
one of the subjects that will live
for many years to come.
There is currently much attention
paid to chemical exchange in proteins
and also in DNA, for it has been found
that the well-known double helix
is not as static as it appears
and that in fact,
there are many exchange processes
that are worth studying
in large biomolecules.
Thank you for your attention.