Welcome to our MOOC, or Massively
Online Open Course
on basic steps in magnetic resonance.
Today, we shall be talking about
chemical exchange.
That is the subject of chapter 4
of Peter Hore's book.
The author has chosen an example
of chemical exchange
for the title page of his book
so it is safe to assume that he found
this subject particularly interesting.
Like many other basic aspects of
magnetic resonance,
the effects of chemical exchange
were discovered in the 1950s.
The name of Herb Gutowsky is often
associated with discovery.
The theory was initially developed by
Felix Bloch and Harden McConnell.
As we shall see, chemical reactions
that occur during the observation
of NMR spectra lead to
characteristic effects:
line broadening, coalescence,
and line narrowing,
all of which allow us to determine
the rates of reactions.
Typically, one can study rates that
aren't comparable with differences
in chemical shifts.
The range of applications is
truly staggering.
From simple confirmation
of equilibria,
to internal mobility of biomolecules,
such as proteins.
So, the word chemical exchange has
a particular meaning for
NMR spectroscopists which is perhaps
not shared by the entire
community of chemists.
To explain this point, let's consider
some simple examples.
All of us, in first year chemistry,
must have learned that cyclohexane
normally looks like this, if it is
drawn as a static molecule,
and that we have protons, or generally
speaking, substituents
sticking out from this ring in axial
position and other ones
that are in, sort of,
equatorial positions.
Now, we also know that this can
interchange to give another
check on formation which we can
draw like this which again
has an axial and an equatorial position.
Now, what is curious is that,
in the static molecule,
if we could stop it from exchanging,
we would expect a different chemical
shift for this axial position here
and this equatorial position.
One would expect them to have
different chemical shifts.
Let's not talk about the fact that
they are also coupled,
that is not currently of interest.
Now it turns out that this position
of the actual proton
will be transformed, a chemical shift
rather of the actual proton
will be transformed into the chemical
shift of an equatorial proton.
Whereas this equatorial proton will
find itself in a position
of an axial proton and consequently
there is an interchange
between their chemical shifts.
It turns out that this process is
extremely fast and therefore
difficult to measure with NMR,
unless we find some way
of slowing it down, which is actually
rather still a topic of interest.
I can take another example, this is
more of a chemical reaction.
Let's consider some carboxylic acid,
which looks like this
in the acid form.
And we have all learned that this
can be transformed into the
conjugate base by losing a proton,
or giving a proton to the environment.
Now if we think of the carbon 13 in
this side, which we find on this
side as well, we can expect the
chemical shift of this carbon
to be different from the chemical
shift in the conjugate base.
And indeed it is.
Again, such a process tends to be
very fast, and therefore not easy
to measure and appreciate with NMR.
But it turns out that similar processes
can be slowed down considerably.
For example, if this carboxylic acid
is hidden in the heart of a protein,
belongs to the site chain of a protein,
of one of the amino acids
in the protein, in such circumstances
the exchange can be slowed down
and can actually become measurable,
of great interest to NMR spectroscopy.
Now, in order to support this whole
discussion of chemical exchange,
I invite you to look at chapter four of
Peter Hore's book on
Nuclear Magnetic Resonance.
You will see that he distinguishes
symmetrical two-sided exchange
and unsymmetrical two-sided
exchange.
We shall see in a few minutes
what the difference is.
And in this chapter, there is a great
wealth of very interesting examples
that I will take some
time to discuss with you.
Let's first talk about symmetrical
exchange which I wrote here
as exchange with equal populations.
Equal populations you will have if
the two forms in equilibrium
have the same energy.
So, if the energy is a function
of the degree of freedom,
turns out you have the same energy
in the A and B forms.
If that is so, then the populations
will be equal, according to
Boltzmann's Law, and also the
interconversion from A into B
will be precisely matched by the
reverse interconversion
from B into A.
Such systems are very numerous,
but we have an example here
of dimethylnitrosamine where we have
two distinct groups here,
a methyl group here, which is in the
same side as the oxygen
or cis, if you prefer, and another
methyl group here, which is
on the opposite side or trans,
with respect to the oxygen.
And as you can see, there is a
pseudo-rotation around this bond,
this single bond, or partly single
bond, then the oxygen will swap
and go to the other side, and what
was here, the methyl that was
in the cis position now ends up
in the trans position
and therefore can be
labelled like this.
So, the point is that while this
pseudo-rotation is going on,
the methyl groups change their
environments and in doing so
change their chemical shifts
because the energies
of these two conformers or rotomers
are exactly the same, the populations
are the same and therefore we have
a symmetrical situation where the
forward and backward exchange rates
are exactly the same, or we could
write this as k+ is equal to k-, or
we could also write the
equilibrium constant in this case
is equal to one.
Now, in this particular case, where
we have equal populations,
we can distinguish different regimes.
And this picture you can also find
on the title page of Peter Hore's book.
First of all, it shows the spectra
that we see for such cases,
as a function of the exchange rate.
You will note that this is a
logarithmic scale,
for example, this corresponds to one
jump per second,
and this corresponds to a thousand
jumps per second,
and of course we go all the way
to 100,000.
This corresponds to generally speaking
to an increasing temperature.
There are other ways, of course,
of changing or affecting
the speed of a chemical reaction but
temperature is certainly
one way of doing that.
And so at low temperatures we have
slow rates, and at slow rates we can
actually distinguish the chemical
shifts of site A and site B
as we have in the previous examples.
In this case, at least in these
simulations, they happen to be
separated by a difference in chemical
shifts which the author tells us is
50 hertz and which elsewhere he calls
delta nu, written like this with a
lower case delta.
So that's the abstract notation for
the difference in chemical shifts
or if you prefer, we could say delta nu
is equal to nu zero of side B
minus nu zero of side A.
Now, what is interesting is that
if we increase the temperature
or increase the interchange rate,
then we see that the lines
begin to broaden, and more surprisingly
they tend to move closer together.
It turns out that the distance between
this and this broad hump is smaller
than the distance between the two
narrow peaks at low temperature.
You see they get broadened to the
point we see at most no signal
and then they turn up as a single
hump, the two lines are merged
together into a single hump, a
phenomenon that we call
coalescence in our trade.
And then, more remarkably, the single
line which is initially rather broad,
will become narrower and narrower as
the exchange rate increases,
while at the same time, we end up
with an average chemical shift
which is simply halfway between the
two chemical shifts of the separate sides.
So, at the low temperature end of
our picture, we see line-broadening
effects which are due to slow exchange.
Before we speak of line-broadening,
we have to define what exactly we
mean by the width of a line.
There are actually several definitions
in the literature but this is the one
that we shall use.
First of all, we can see that the height
of the line, just the peak height,
and we call that H, and we divide
that in two and we measure the width
in hertz at the half the height
of the line.
Now this quantity we call delta nu,
nu is our Greek letter that we use
for frequencies, and it can be shown
that the line width is simply
proportional to the exchange rate, k
divided by the factor pi.
Since the exchange rate k is nothing
else but the inverse of the lifetime
of a particular conformer, or molecular
form, we can substitute that into
this equation, and come to the
conclusion that the line width
delta nu is equal to one over pi times
tau, tau being the lifetime.
Now, the width can be rationalized in
terms of the lifetime of the states.
Remember that a transition in NMR
is always between a ground state
and an excited state, but we have at
the beginning of our book discussed
these as stationary states that have
an infinite lifetime.
In fact, if the molecule doesn't exist
for very long, the states don't exist
very long either, and they get blurred.
The shorter the lifetime,
or the faster the exchange,
the more severe the blurring.
And you can see on the left hand side
they are only slightly blurred and
therefore the line is fairly narrow,
but in this case the blurring is
quite severe and of course the
differences in energy is also blurred
and therefore the line becomes
very broad.
So, this is a hand-waving way of
explaining line-broadening.
There are, of course, more satisfactory
ways of explaining the same thing.
So, for a two site problem with equal
populations and equal forward and
backward reaction rates, we have the
following three distinct regimes.
In the slow exchange regime, we
simply have line-broadening
which is the same for both A and B
resonances, and in both cases
is simply proportional to the exchange
rate k, or if you prefer, inversely
proportional to the lifetime of either
of these molecules, or conformers.
In the fast exchange rate, we have
an entirely different situation.
In this case, the line width here is
inversely proportional
to the exchange rate.
That means that the faster the
exchange rate, the narrower the line.
Furthermore, there is a very important
parameter here.
This delta nu is the difference in
chemical shifts, so we wrote that
as before, zero a minus nu zero b, that's
the difference in chemical shifts.
And as you can see,
it comes here as the square.
Now that's very important because
that means that the residual
line width here will be proportional
to the square of the difference
in chemical shifts.
And this difference in chemical shifts
is, among other things, proportional
to the magnetic field into which we
immerse our sample, or molecule
and consequently if we go from say
a 400 megahertz spectrometer
to an 800 megahertz spectrometer,
that is to say, if we double the field,
then we also double the difference in
chemical shifts, and we therefore
quadruple the square, that is to say
the line width becomes four times broader.
This is one reason why chemists and
physical chemists like to have
spectrometers of different fields
in the laboratory.
You can also convert this equation by
saying that the line width here,
apart from the square of the
difference in chemical shifts
is directly proportional to the
lifetime of the states.
And then we mentioned that halfway
between the two there is a critical
condition called coalescence.
In fact, that's the precise point
where the three extrema of these
funny curves merge into a single
extremum, a single maximum,
and it turns out that that occurs
when the exchange rate is precisely
2.2 times the difference in
chemical shifts.
Now this equation is of limited use
to us because in that vicinity
of coalescence the lines are often
so broad that you can barely see them,
let alone decide whether they
have been merged or not quite yet.
We have just discussed chemical
exchange between two sides that have
equal populations because
they have equal energies.
But the discussion can be broadened
to encompass the more general case
where the populations are unequal.
So here we have a case where we have
on the one hand the same, an O residue.
We have the same methyl group, but
here we have replaced one of the
methyl groups by a benzyl group which
is CH2 attached to a phenyl ring.
And so these are clearly unequal and
therefore you would expect the molecule
to have different energies depending
on whether the oxygen is pointing
on the same side as the methyl or
on the opposite side.
And indeed, the energies are quite
different between these two forms
and therefore the populations are
going to be different so there will
be more molecules in this lower
energy state than in the
upper energy state.
We can also say that the likelihood
that we move from left to right
is faster, the exchange rate is higher
than the other way around.
So this situation now means that k AB
is different from kB.
This will have some consequences on
the spectra.
So, when the populations are unequal,
this has, as you might expect, dramatic
consequences on the exchanging spectra.
So here we have a case where the minor
isomer A has about half the concentration
of the major isomer B, but they still
have distinct chemical shifts.
In this case, the simulations refer
to a difference of 50 hertz
so this is again the delta delta,
which is nu zero A minus nu zero B
and as you can see, when the exchange
process begins to be felt, then the
minor isomer broadens actually more
or faster than the major isomer.
Furthermore, they tend to coalesce
and then narrow as in the case before,
but the narrowed line is not positioned
halfway between the two chemical shifts,
but displaced towards the
major isomer.
In fact, the rule is very simple, the
average chemical shift is a weighted
linear combination, or a weighted
average between the two
chemical shifts with a population of
the minor isomer and the population
of the major isomer which are applied
as weights to these two chemical shifts.
Remember that the sum of the two
populations is defined to be one,
because these are
probabilities of occupation.
As you can also imagine, if the major
isomer becomes very dominant,
the minor isomer becomes negligible
and the average line will be essentially
indistinguishable with the position
of the major isomer and that becomes
therefore difficult to determine
the exchange effects.
It turns out that this picture is
quite a modern picture.
I guess it was first drawn in the '50s
but there has been recent work
going on in proteins where one can
now distinguish the dominant major
conformation of a protein, and a
minor conformation which might
be activated perhaps the conformation
that allows the protein to work
as an enzyme or having fruitful
interaction with its substrate.
This kind of argument is now used,
not only for protons but also for
nitrogen-15 and carbon-13 and proteins.
And turns out to be a very powerful way
to identify mobility of macromolecules.
Now, if the populations are unequal,
unequal as opposed to the equal case
we treated before, then as I said,
there are two different
line-broadening effects.
The line width of side A becomes
inversely proportional to the
lifetime of A and the lifetime of
side B is inversely proportional
to the lifetime of side B.
If side B is dominant, then its lifetime
will be longer and therefore
it's narrower, its line width smaller.
If this is a minor conformer, then
tau A will be short and therefore
its width larger.
Furthermore, we have this average
population which as I said, is weighted
by the populations and this is a
somewhat more scary equation
where we have the residual line width
in the high temperature limit
in the fast exchange limit.
And here we see that, much like in
the case of a symmetrical exchange
it is still proportional to the square
of the difference in chemical shifts
and therefore, if we double the field,
this delta nu parameter will be
multiplied by a factor of four,
like before.
Furthermore, we see that we have pA
and pB, these are the populations
and the sum of the
two exchange rates,
the forward and the
backward exchange rate.
Of course, this should converge with
a simple equation if we take pA
and pB to be one half each.
To summarize the first part of
chapter 4, we have discussed
the pictures that serve as front
cover for Peter Hore's book,
and we have discussed the fact that
if there are two isomers
with two molecular forms, or two
partners in a chemical reaction that have
different chemical shifts, then these
lines will be broadened by the
chemical exchange and the broadening
can go as far as coalescence and beyond
into a line narrowing at an average
position and in line widths of these
different spectra can be used to
extract the chemical exchange rates,
which are, of course, of great interest
to chemists and physical chemists alike.