So far we have simply explained
in an empirical fashion
how chemical exchange affects
NMR spectra.
And we have shown you
some computer simulations
without telling you
how these effects can be calculated.
Let me try to explain the basics now.
First of all, we spoke of spectra,
which in the low exchange regime,
comprise at least two lines,
with frequencies
nu zero B and nu zero A,
so these were two chemical shifts.
It turns out that such a spectrum,
which typically is drawn
from right to left, by convention,
is obtained by an operation
called the Fourier transformation,
which I just write as a black box
with this italic F,
and we'll talk more
about that in Chapter 6.
So, the time domain signal,
which Felix Bloch called
the Free Induction Decay,
we shall see in Chapter 6
how you can record that.
This time domain signal is in fact,
in this simple case,
composed of a super position
of two different cosine waves
which have two different arguments.
There's a phase for site A which:
is equal to two pi
times nu zero A times Time
And there is a phase for
Site B which is:
two pi nu zero B
also proportional to time.
And so we have
two cosine waves,
Simply cos phi A plus cos phi B
So both of these phases
are linearly proportional to time
and if you draw them
then we have a slow beat here,
dotted lines that corresponds
to the lowest frequency
and dotted lines as slow cosine wave.
And on top of that,
a faster cosine wave.
Now we can plot the difference
in phase, so this is: Delta phi,
and Delta phi is the difference
between the fast and the slow.
So Delta phi is
equal to phi A minus phi B.
And if these equations hold,
that is to say,
if there is no chemical exchange,
then you expect
the difference in phase to be simply
proportional to time,
since both of these factors
are proportional to time,
then consequently
we have a simple line
with a slope that is determined
by the difference in chemical shifts.
So the slope would actually be;
two pi times delta nu
which is the difference
in chemical shifts.
This is applicable if
there is no exchange,
but if there is hopping
of the molecules
from one site to the other,
so A becomes B
and B becomes A,
then these different signals here
cannot build up a phase difference,
because we effectively hop
from one curve to another
in a stochastic fashion.
And this haphazard hopping,
from one site to the other means that
chemical shift differences are
averaged to zero
that means that there can be
no build up of a difference in phase
and in fact, if the exchange
is reasonably fast
without being infinitely fast,
then we get this rather noisy line
in which where the phase difference
is close to zero degree.
If we have a very fast exchange,
infinitely fast exchange,
then it will be a sharp horizontal line,
without any stochastic excursions.
So far, we have discussed
the consequences of chemical exchaange
on the line width and line positions
of NMR spectra
in a sort of empirical fashion,
supporting our discussion
by numerical simulation,
but without telling you,
really, how these
numerical simulations were made.
So to understand that
we have to go one step beyond
and I would like
to discuss with you what happens
with the magnetization
in a frame
that we shall discuss
in Chapter Six,
which is known as the rotating frame.
It turns out that the magnetization
can be drawn as a vector,
and this vector has an X component
and has a Y component,
and in the course of
the magnetic resonance experiment,
it will undergo both a precession
and a decay of its magnitude.
And the precession angle, here,
from its initial position
to its position at Time T
can be called Phase as a function of T.
Now it turns out to be very convenient
to define a complex number,
which I call M plus of T,
and which is defined as
M-X of T plus I of M-Y of T.
So this is a simple complex notation.
Incidentally, it's modeled after
a so called raising operator
in Quantum Mechanics.
Which is defined as
I plus equal I -X plus i- I- Y.
So this is the model,
so to speak,
Bowery's model for our nu definition.
Now if you want to describe procession
then we can write
M plus of T is equal to
M plus of T times Zero,
incidentally this notation encompasses
both the amplitude
and the phase of Time Zero,
and the precession
can be written like this:
two pi nu Zero,
that's the chemical shift
at which these things precess,
and Time.
If we want can embellish this notation
by taking in to account
the decrease of the amplitude
and that can be done
by multiplying this
with a decaying function T2.
Now from this equation
which describes both the precession
and the transverse relaxation
of the magnetization.
We can obtain the Time derivative,
which we can write:
D over D-T
of the same complex objects,
which can be written in
shorthand notation;
M plus of T with a dot over it,
and this turns out to be the same as
M-X of T times-- a minus in front--
and then we have I-2-Pi nu zero
and we have plus 1 over T2.
Now, if we wish to consider
similar things
for two different
magnetization vectors,
we would have them
in different speeds
we can change color,
if you will,
so we can have
another magnetization vector,
which would be in green,
and that would have
a different phase angle,
maybe a faster recession,
maybe a phase here,
would be moving faster,
so this would be phase of site B,
Where of this of T,
and then we can rewrite these equations,
both for A and for B.
So vector A can be written like this:
A and T2 of A
and this is the
Time derivative of A, of A, of A and A
but I can also do
the same thing for vector B,
and of course then,
I have to replace A by B,
replace all of these As by B,
and in this fashion can cook up
an equation that describes
the magnetization of the other site,
without actually rewriting everything.
So far so good, we will see
in a minute
why this is convenient
to describe chemical exchange.
So in the previous picture
you have seen
how the precession
can be described
in terms of a
complex magnetization vector
with phase and amplitude
and now we shall discuss
how chemical kinetics
can affect this precession.
And to prepare the ground,
lets first start with a simple equation--
chemical transformation of A to B:
which is accompanied
by the reverse reaction, like this.
And we know that that means
that if we take the Time derivative
of the concentration of A,
it will be decreased
with a factor proportional
going from forward proportional
to the initial concentration of A,
but it will be replenished, as it were,
by the reverse reaction
from B to A.
So now in this notation we have,
K forward and K backward
So likewise, the time dependence
of the concentration of the other form B,
will be proportional
to the concentration of A,
and this is--as it were--
fueled by the forward reaction,
at the same time
the concentration of B
is depleted by the backward reaction,
so it looks like this.
Now, this is a set
of two differential equations
and it turns out to be convenient
to write them in the form
of a matrix and a vector,
so we can say the same thing
that we have the Time derivative
of a vector consisting of
the concentration of A
and the concentration of B,
both time dependent quantities,
of course, and we have a matrix
which is made up of the coefficients
that we see here;
minus K forward plus K backward
plus K forward minus K backward
and this multiplies
another vector,
comprising the same concentrations
of A and B.
So this is a-- I would say--
a rather conventional description
of first order chemical kinetics.
Now it turns out that
we can combine the interplay,
we can express the interplay
of these things,
by describing the interconversion
of the magnetization vectors.
And to do that
we have to take
the Time derivatives
of the magnetization vector,
complex magnetization vector site A
and the complex
magnetization vector of site B,
and we make a vector of these two
and then we make a matrix
and in this matrix we have;
minus K forward
that we know from the
chemical exchange effect,
but we also have;
minus I-2-Pi nu zero A
for the chemical shift.
Then here we have;
plus K backward
and here we have;
plus K forward
minus K backward
but we shall add to this;
minus I-2-Pi Nu zero B,
and this will then multiply
and effect the M complex vector,
complex number that was describes
the magnetization of site A
and the complex number that describes
the magnetization of site B.
So this equation describes
both the chemical exchange
which is in the numbers K--
the symbols K and the precession
due to the chemical shift
of sites A and B.
We can, in fact,
embellish this by putting:
1 over T-2 of site A
in this diagonal element,
and also by;
subtracting 1 over t-2 of site B
on the last diagonal element.
But the basic idea is that we have a;
2 by 2 matrix that describes this.
And such a matrix
can be resolved,
such a differential equation
essentially by diagonalizing this matrix.
Its not a completely trivial matrix
to diagonalize
because it is not necessarily symmetric,
and also it has imaginary components
in the diagonal elements,
but it can be done-- and moreover--
this can be generalized
for assisting with N larger than 2 sites.
So it is quite remarkable
that you can handle,
in fact, an arbitrary number of sites--
A,B,C,D-- and still set up a matrix
and diagonalize that matrix.
And this kind of calculation
forms the foundation of the simulations
that you have seen
in the first part of this chapter.
This concludes Part 2 of this Chapter.
Thank you for your attention.