Hi.
My name is Félix Schmidt.
I am a lecturer here in the EPFL
in Sanitary Engineering, but
most of my professional
activities are in my company
C.S.D Engineers.
Today we will speak about waste
collection and transport.
I would like you to remember
two important points.
Firstly, collection and transport
are usually the major part
of waste management costs, much
more than landfill costs.
Second point I want you to remember,
is that the cost of collection
and transport is varying a lot from
one city to another, according
to local characteristics, urban
situation and the level of services.
Frequencies, collection rules,
equipment, bags or containers
and trucks, have a big
influence on the cost.
What is the main problem
of waste management?
Money!
We have not enough money to do
the waste management as well
as we think to do it.
Thus, we have two solutions:
either we bring the cost down,
or we adapt revenues and taxes
to reach a sufficient level.
Generally we have to do both.
Today we will see how to bring
the cost down and improve
the service to the population.
What are in waste collection
the most expensive elements?
First there are trucks, the trucks are
very expensive, and also the workers.
The workers are also a
big part of the cost.
Thus, if we want to reduce the
cost, we have to develop solutions
in order to use better
these important elements.
We have to work on time reduction,
in order to load as much
waste as possible in a reduced time.
For that, we have to work on the
organization and on the equipment.
We need to choose good trucks in
order to minimize as much as
possible the time we need to load, to
transport and then to unload the waste.
For that we have to choose trucks
allowing to load the waste
in the shortest time possible.
An important point is to have a
compaction system, which allows
to take more waste.
But a second point, very important,
is to consider the height
of loading the waste.
Here we have some one meter height.
Here in this example in São
Tomé we have 2 meters height.
It's much more work, much more time.
Here in Peru we are using
trucks with 4 meters height.
This needs much more work, much
more time, and lots of people,
for doing the same job.
If we consider the cost of
operation of such a choice,
here in Peru we have some estimation
of some 60 soles/ton.
With this kind of trucks we
are on about 350 soles/ton.
This is 5 time more!
And if we consider this kind of
open trucks we are at about
650 soles/ton, because we need
a lot of time to load and to
unload such trucks.
And if we consider these little
vehicles here, which could be
very useful to go in narrow streets,
the cost is 1,900 soles/ton.
Which is much, much higher
than our 60 soles/ton.
So the choice of good trucks is
very important in order to reduce
the cost of the collection
and transport.
The volume of the trucks is also a
very important point of efficiency.
If we consider such trucks,
we have approximately 0.8 tons
per cubic meter; because
we have a compaction system,
we have more or less 7 cubic meters,
which makes more or less 5.
6 tons.
In such an open truck, we have only
0.3 tons per cubic meter.
Also about 8 cubic
meters, we have only
2.4 tons.
This is just half.
In this bad system, we have also
0.3 tons per cubic meter and 1
cubic meter, which means only
0.3 or 0. 5 tons.
So the transportation between
these different types of trucks
is very different, and we have
to choose also a good volume
for efficient transportation.
This has influence on time
and on fuel consumption.
Other element, very simple, is to
choose trucks having an unloading
time as short as possible.
In this kind of trucks we see
that we can unload it in more
or less 2 minutes with one driver.
If you have to do it manually,
like in this situation, we need
3 or 4 hours with 3 or 4 workers.
These are not good solutions.
For reducing the time the trucks
are stopped for loading
the waste, we also need to choose
a good container strategy.
Bulk waste in the ground
is the worst case.
Here in Albania, or in São Tomé,
we see how many times it's
necessary to load the
waste to the truck.
The utilization of plastic bags
allows a faster loading time.
The best is the utilization of
containers, and if possible standardized
containers.
Ideal solution for reducing the
loading time is to provide containers
with large or very large capacity.
A truck takes more or less the same time
to load 100 liters or 3 cubic meters.
There are some other conditions
to reduce the loading time.
First, is that the containers must
be accessible for the trucks,
and not blocked like here
in Albania by the cars.
For having the containers in good
condition, it needs to organize
maintenance and repairing
the containers.
This means to respond
to some questions:
Who is the owner of the container?
Who is responsible?
Who is in charge of the maintenance?
Who would react if there are not
enough containers, or if the
containers are not in good condition?
A good routing design is another
important point for efficient
collection of the waste.
In this example, we see the door-to-door
collection of every container.
The collection time and
distances are quite high.
It could be also possible to reduce
the number of loading points,
and to reduce the
distance of the work.
It will take less time, less effort
for the same number of containers.
It will require that the population
has to go 100 or 200 meters
to the containers.
But this happens in a lot of cities.
Finally, transports are an
important point of the cost
as we saw at the beginning.
Transport costs are depending on
local conditions, quantities
and distances, and materials.
If you use a big truck or a small
one, the time and fuel consumption
are more or less the same, so it's
very important to use trucks
as big as possible.
To reduce the cost it is also
important that the trucks are
in average near 100% full.
If they are not full enough, the cost
per ton will increase rapidly.
But, in general, collection trucks
are not optimal for transport.
If the distance to the landfill is
more than some 20 kilometers,
and if the volume is big enough,
it is interesting to study
the possibility of the implementation
of transfer stations.
In this case, transport is done by
big trucks, having a capacity
of 3 to 5 collection trucks.
Collection trucks and teams keep
working in the city, and transport
trucks ensure the transport
to the landfill.
Such transport stations can
contribute significantly to
the efficiency and to the cost
reduction of the transport.
The sustainability of the waste
management service is strongly
depending from the cost.
The experience shows that there
is usually a big potential of
cost reduction in
collection and transport.
Working for cost reduction means
to choose good trucks and good
bins in order to reduce the times,
but also to choose a reduced
number of collection points,
to make a good routing, and
to create a good organization and
maintenance system of trucks and bins.
Next time we will see in more detail
how to proceed on an analysis
of the present situation in
order to reduce these costs.