Management of Protected Areas
6.2 Finance
In this first episode,
we are going to look together
at the basic concept
of financial planning.
This is about assessing several things.
On the one hand,
the needs of a protected area,
identifying possible revenue,
funding deficiencies.
Then studying preconditions
for the creation
of any financial mechanism.
Is this possible? Feasible?
Do institutional, legislative conditions,
the capacity of a protected area
lead it to the establishment
of a certain mechanism?
And finally to consolidate everything,
it is recommended
to develop a business plan;
we will look at that
together in part three.
First and foremost,
let's look at financial requirements.
When identifying requirements,
note that it is important
on the one hand, to make the link
between the management plan's goals,
in terms of activity,
required investment,
and this, based on needs
and priorities at the time,
and I will come back to this soon.
Secondly, to study opportunities
to reduce costs, optimization.
Also to take into account the utility
of the financial management system
of a protected area,
that is the accounts,
the classification of expenditure,
good financial management,
transparency of financial data
and the requirements of audits.
I cannot emphasize enough,
the need for good skills
when it comes to the financial management
for a protected area.
Also to analyse carefully
the actual financial situation
of previous years.
But keep in mind
that budgets for protected areas
are generally determined,
depending on available funds
and not on the actual needs
of a protected area.
This management by default is
of course a pragmatic one,
but it does not always allow us
to see good results on the ground,
hence the need to set up a business plan.
And finally, extrapolating future needs.
As I have mentioned,
the financial needs of a protected area
are to be evaluated
depending on the management plan's
goals and activities.
But you will have noted
that a protected area's financial needs
are also dependent on its life cycle.
Financial needs
and priorities are not the same
throughout the life of a protected area.
Let's look at a fictional example
of a protected area's budget
over 20 years.
At the very beginning of the life cycle
of the protected area
in the identification phase,
we note the great financial needs
in the follow-up,
in terms of scientific expertise,
to determine reference points.
Fairly important requirements
also in consultation with the communities,
with all interested parties.
Then, in the creation phase,
often supported by donors,
by projects.
It is at this time that the infrastructure
of the protected area is built,
that personnel is recruited,
which are important needs.
Then throughout the operations,
of the protected area
in an operational phase,
budgets are more or less balanced.
However, you will note the differences.
For example, here,
with a tourism project,
a donor project of course.
A little further on, we have
a community development project.
Still a little further on,
a conservation project
or a restoration project.
You can see that these different projects
involve jumps
in the budget of a protected area.
You will have understood
that on the basis of identifying
the protected area's needs,
the identification
of plausible sources of finance,
we remove the shortfall, the funding gap.
Before searching for potential funding,
it is important to look at preconditions,
on the one hand, in society,
in that country,
and also the protected area's
own capacities.
Firstly we will look at the preconditions
on a macro level.
Are the roles and the values of the sites
and ecosystems included and shared by all?
Do general policies fully recognise
the roles and values of the MPA?
And have laws been adopted
that implemented these general policies?
Are there technical capacities, abilities,
able to capitalize on financing options?
And finally, is there a system
of governance that provides
and emphasizes
the values of transparency,
responsibility and confidence?
The key questions to ask.
Firstly a practical question.
Which mechanism can be set up
the most efficiently?
Then, we look at the current legal
and administrative provisions
of the country
which can allow for the creation
of the new mechanism.
Are difficulties envisaged
in administrating,
implementing, in raising finance
or distributing finance?
Look to see if this new mechanism
will be seen as equitable and legitimate.
And I emphasize this point:
the financial collection mechanism
must be seen
to be equitable and legitimate
by all the interested parties
We look at the support
by the interested parties and govenment
for implementation of this new mechanism.
And finally, we remain vigilant
to the environmental impact
of this mechanism on the protected area's
goods and services.
To consolidate all this information,
we will prepare
what we call a business plan.
The business plan is used in all sectors
of the economy.
It serves to compare different options
and to study the financial viability
of a certain initiative.
Adapted to protected areas,
the business plan allows us
to maximize environmental results
with an often limited
financial contribution.
It allows the comparison
between different options in the long term
and future planning,
to better plan entries
and financial needs of a protected area.
The business plan must allow
to put into perspective
over five to ten years,
on the one hand, expenditure
expected,
investments, personnel,
operations, activities,
and on the other hand, expected revenue,
self-financing, national budget, donors
and projects and other mechanisms.
Note that is a tool of internal management
which allows us a technical
and financial long term vision.
You will have noted
that protected area budgets
are generally determined
based on available funds.
A business plan allows us to implement
and identify the actual needs
of a protected area.
It allows us to determine
priority investments.
Also, don't forget, the management plan--
the business plan, sorry,
allows us to communicate
and present a clear and concise view
of the activity of a protected area
in the long term
and to show financial needs.
Here you can see a fictional example,
once again, of a business plan.
Don't be concerned about all the numbers,
it's just to give you an idea.
This table has been adapted
from the business plan
of the Iwokrama protected area in Guyana.
You will note
that expenditure is organized
based on activity programs.
Expenditure, conservation expenses,
administration, it's a good thing.
This allows us to make the connection
with the management plan.
You will note that revenue
is defined as best possible
according to information, and outlook,
and total revenue,
whether from sales, tourism revenue,
merchandise, and handicrafts,
is recorded and extrapolated
over the coming years.
Finally, you'll note
that we can identify...
the gap, the shortcomings,
throughout the five years
of the business plan.
It's about, for protected areas,
defining actions
seeking funds, marketing
and external relations to bridge this gap.
The procedure to manage the business plan
is well defined in this guide
which I suggest you take a look at.
It is guide on how to formulate
a simplified business plan
for protected areas
written by Benjamin Landreau for the FIBA.
Note particularly the different stages.
Firstly, define the process
of the business plan.
Who is in charge?
What consultations are necessary?
Then, analyze past financial execution.
Then, determine the medium
and long term needs,
investments, operating expenses,
salaries, staffing requirements.
Then, indicate the existing
sources of finance
and extrapolate potential revenue.
Finally, analyze the funding gap
and different possible scenarios
and evaluate other sources of finance.
This episode has given you
the basics on financial planning.
Note that searching
for financial sustainability
is essential for a protected area.
It is about identifying
financial requirements in the long term,
studying and evaluating
the preconditions of the country, the site
and the protected area itself
and to define financing options.
And all this generally
within the framework of a business plan.
Several reference manuals are available.
I have suggested one of them.
I also suggest you look
at the UNDP's BIOFIN website,
the work of the TEEB initiative,
mine is blue, this is green, but...
The Economy of Ecosystems
and Biodiversity,
a guide which will be available very soon,
Financial Planning for National Systems
of Protected Areas,
and finally, the reference guide,
Sustainable Financing of Protected Areas,
A Global Review of Challenges and Options.
We have reached the end of this episode.
I suggest you have a look
at the reference materials
and I wish you a good day.