Hello, welcome to chapter 1 interpolation,
the problem to be solved
is the following : given n a nonnegative integer
supposed to be large, and n+1 values, denoted
t0,t1,t2 up to tn.
Is is important for these values to be
pairwise distinct, so t0
different from t1, different from t2,
and so on... we take now n+1 values
that we note p0,p1,p2 up to pn.
These values can all be equal.
We are looking for a polynomial p
of degree n that goes through the points (t0,p0),
(t1,p1) ... up to (tn,pn).
So I am looking for p in Pn.
Here Pn is the set of polynomials
of degee less or equal to n
such that p evaluated at tj gives pj
for the subscripts j from 0 to n.
Then I can draw the situation with n=1,
In this case I have 2 points,
the corresponding value, and I look for the unique
degree 1 polynomial that goes through
those two points, I write it a0+a1*t.
Now if n=2 I have three points so here are t0,
the point (t0,p0), the points (t1,p1), and (t2,p2)
and I look for the unique degree 2 polynomial
going through those three points.
I can write it p2(t) = a0+a1*t+a2*t^2.
There is a java applet that
allows us to continue with n=3,4,5.
I can use this java applet to
do a few experiences.
I place 2 points here, and
here is the unique
degree 1 polynomial going through
those 2 points.
I add a third point, here we get the
unique degree 2 polynomial going through
those three points. I add a 4th point
and see that
the concavity of the function changes once.
And so on I can keep
adding as many points as I want and get
here for instance 6 interpolation points
and the unique degree 5 polynomial
going through those points
I can add even more points if I wish so.
Now we wonder
what would happen if I put a point
right below an existing one ?
Well, what will happen is that we
indeed get
the polynomial, of degree 8 here,
going through those 9 points.
But the price to pay is that this polynomial
oscillates a lot more.
we try now a new experiment,
take the function exp(-x^2).
Now when I put a point, it
belongs to the graph of
this function, so I try to approach this
function exp(-x^2)
by a polynomial. So here I have
3 points here
now 4,5 points. And the question
I ask is : if
I add a lot of points, will
my polynomial approach correctly
the function ? The answer depends on
the placement of these points..
For example, here I have a few points.
Observe that if I put one
here, then things go well
in the center, but quite
bad on the edge of our interval.
So I add some points
on the side of the interval, and now
I get a polynomial of high degree
since I have 15 interpolation points.
My polynomial has degree 14
that approaches reasonably well
this function
exp(-x^2)