The bad way of dealing with the problem is the following :
I am looking for p, a polynomial
of degree n that I write
p(t)+a0+a1*t+a2*t^2+...+an*t^n.
So I have n+1 unknown quantities,
which are the coefficients a0, a1, a2
up to an, the coefficiants
of the polynomial in the canonical basis
1,t,t^2 up to t^n. I get n+1 equations
that correspond to p(t0)=p0 for the first
equation, so
a0+a1*t0+a2+t0^2+...+an*t0^n=p0
likewise for p at t1, that
should give us p1, which gives
a0+a1*t1+a2*t1^2+...+an*t1^n=p1.
and so on until p(tn)=pn.
I can write those n+1 equations
as a linear system
since a0,a1,a2...,are linear factors
of our canonical basis
The unknown quantinies are
a0,a1,...,an
We can see the ai's as coordinates
of the vector a.
On the right handside of the equality
we get the given values p0,p1,...pn
as entries of the vector p
Now I have to write down the entries
if the matrix T such that Ta=p.
The first line is
a0+t0*a1+t0^2*a2+...+t0^n*an = p0.
So
on the second line we have 1,t1,t1^2,... until t1^n
And finally on the last line
we have 1 tn tn^2 ... tn^n
We're now down to solving
a linear system. This method is
bad because the number
of operations to solve a linear system is
high. We'll see in the chapter 4
that this number has the size of
n cubed, n^3.
On the other hand we have another method
that will give us an explicit formula
for the polynomial p(t). Here the
formula isn't explicit because I have
to solve a linear system to get the coefficients.
We'll see later an explicit formula for the
polynomial, we're now going to
talk about Lagrange interpolation.