Now we'll solve the
problem with n=2.
We have three pairwise distinct values
t0, t1, t2 from which
we'll construct φ0, φ1, φ2
the Lagrange basis
for degree 2 polynomials,
associated with t0, t1, t2.
Those three functions
φ0, φ1 and φ2
Are 3 polynomials of degree 2
built as follows :
Here are our points
t0,  t1, t2
the first polynomial φ0 is a
degree 2 polynomial such that
φ0(t0) = 1, φ0(t1) = 0 and φ0(t2)=0
We can draw this φ0 and we can even
write a formula for φ0 since
it is zero at t1 and t2, so
we can write it as
(t-t1)*(t-t2) and I want it
to be equal to 1 at t0
so I divide it by (t0-t1)*(t0-t2).
So we get the formula for φ0
Likewise I can build the polynomial
φ1, degree 2 polynomial such that
φ1(t0)=0 φ1(t1)=1 φ1(t2)=0
So here is the polynomial φ1
and again we have a formula for
φ1 which is
(t-t0)*(t-t2) to get 0 at t0 and t2
and I want it to equal 1 at t1
so I divide it by
(t1-t0)*(t1-t2).
Finally we can build
φ2 of degree 2 such that
φ2(t0)=0 φ2(t1)=0 φ2(t2)=1
and we get an analogue formula.
I now claim that those 3 functions
φ0, φ1, φ2 are a basis for the
set of polynomials of degree
2 or less. Indeed we
have three functions in
P2 the set of degree 2 polynomials.
The dimension of the space of
degree 2 polynomials is 3.
Why 3 ?
Because if p is a degree 2
polynomial, write it a0+a1*t+a2*t^2.
So  is the canonical
basis for the degree 2 polynomials.
There are 3 elements in this basis
so the dimension of P2 is 3
Hence the only thing to check to
get that φ0, φ1, φ2 are a basis is that
those three functions are
linearly independent, so
I take 3 coefficients α0, α1, α2
and I write the linear combination
α0*φ0+α1*φ1+α2*φ2
and suppose
this equals 0.
I have to show that this implies
that all coefficients
α0, α1, α2 are 0.
To show this, it suffices to take
t=t0 to get α0=0
t=t1 to get α1=0 and
t=t2 to get α2=0.
so those 3 functions are
linearly independent which means
that if p is a degree 2 polynomial,
we can write p(t) as
a linear combination if those
3 functions
α0φ0(t) +α1φ1(t) +α2φ2(t)
Now I will give the solution of
the problem.
Recall I am looking for
a degree 2 polynomial that
goes through the points
(t0,p0), (t1,p1), (t2,p2). The solution
is just a linear combination of
φ0, φ1 and φ2, and the
coefficients of this linear combination
are p0, p1 and p2. So
p(t)=p0*φ(t)+p1*φ(t)+p2*φ(t).
We can easily check that
this is the solution to our problem.
p is a degree 2 polynomial, because
it is a linear combination of those 3
functions, φ0, φ1 and φ2.
And one can check that for example
p(t0)=p0. Why ?
Because φ0(t0)=1 and
then p1*φ1(t0)=0.
and p2*φ2(t0)=0.
so we indeed have p(t0)=p0.
Likewise p(t1)=p1 and p(t2)=p2.