We'll now solve the problem
for any n.
We define φ0, φ1, ..., φn
the Lagrange basis for polynomials
of degree n, Pn, which
depends on the points t0, t1, t2,..., tn.
Take an integer k, between 0 and n
k is fixed. Then φk
is a degree n polynomial
defined as follows :
we want
φk(tk)=1 and φk(tj)=0
for all tj
with the subscript j different
from k, and between 0 and n.
The formula for φk is the following
φk(t) is the product on
j from 0 to n, j different from k,
the numerator is of the type (t-tj)
such that φk(tj)=0
and on the denominator we have
tk-tj, so that φk(tk)=1.
I claim now that φ0, φ1, φ2, ..., φn
is a basis
for polynomials of degree n.
The dimension of the space
of degree n polynomials
is n+1 because any
polynomial of degree n is a linear
combination of the functions
1, t, t^2, ..., t^n
so there are n+1
functions in the basis, so the
dimension of Pn is n+1
So we just need to check that
φ0, φ1, φ2, ..., φn are linearly independant
Take any coefficients α0, α1, ..., αn
and a linear combination
α0*φ0 +α1*φ1 +...+αn*φn
Suppose this linear combination is 0
That is to say 0 for all t in R.
We must show that this implies that
all the coefficients α0, α1, ..., αn
are 0. I choose for example
t=t0 and I get φ0(t0)=1,
φ1(t0)=0, ... φn(tn)=0 so
α0*φ0(t0)+α1*φ(t1)+...+αn*φ(tn)
= a0*1+α1*0+...+αn*0=α0
So I get α0=0.
Likewise if I choose
t=t1 I get α1=0 and so on.
So I indeed showed that those
functions are linearly independant.
Recall that I am looking
for a polynomial
of degree n going through
(t0,p0), (t1,p1), .... (tn,pn)
and I claim the solution of the problem
is given by p(t).
p(t) is a degree n polynomial so we can
write it as a linear combination
of the basis functions φ0, φ1, ..., φn
and the coefficients of the linear combinations
are the values p0, p1, ..., pn
so p(t) = p0*φ0(t)+p1*φ1(t)+ ... +pn*φn(t).
We can indeed check that it is
the solution to our problem.
Firsly, this polynomial is a linear
combination of the functions
φ0, φ1, ..., φn the Lagrange
basis, so it is a polynomial
of degree n. And I must check that
p(tj)=pj.  For instance, let us show that p(t0)=p0
p(t0)=p0*φ0(t0)+p1*φ1(t0)+...+pn*φn(tn)
but φ0(t0)=1, φ1(t0)=0, ..., φn(t0)=0
so we have p(t0)=p0.
and we continue likewise until
we get p(tn)=pn