Now I will talk to you about polynomial interpolation
of continuous functions.
This topic is covered in the
book by chapter 1.4
Given a continuous function f defined on
the interval [a,b] in R (real numbers).
I choose regularly spaced interpolation points,
such that  t_j = a + (b-a)*j/n for all j in 0,1,...,n.
Here is the interval [a,b],
I choose five equidistant points, t0,t1,t2,t3,t4.
cinq points équidistants. Je vais prendre
ici le graphe de la fonction f et je
and search for the polynomial p_n of degree n
which matches the function f in the equidistant
points t_j; thus
p_n equals the function f in t_j for all j in 0,1,...n.
Here are the values f(t0), f(t1),f(t2),f(t3) and f(t4)
and I can draw the polynomial p_4 of
degree 4 through these five points.
Given the polynomial p_4 of degree 4
passing through
the equidistant points t0,t1,t2,t3,t4 which
coincides with f in these points.
The question we are looking to answer is the following:
when I increase the number of points n,
say n goes to infinity, does the
polynomial get closer and closer
to the function f ? I suggest a short numerical
experiment with a java applet.
In this java app you see the graph
of the function f in red;
this function is the following
f(t) = 1/(1+25*t^2) in the interval [-1,1].
In blue you can observe the
polynomial of degree 4
through the five equidistant points.
You can see that
the polynomial and the function coincide.
So the question to answer is:
when we increase the number of points
does the blue curve
get closer to the red one ?
Let's try !
This time I set eleven points. We can observe
that the blue curve gets closer to the red one
in the center, but moves further away in the edges.
So we can carry on and
instead of taking eleven points I take
21 points and build the polynomial
of degree 20 through these 21 points;
same remark, in the center
the blue and red curves are nearly overlaid,
but on the edges of the interval [-1,1] the blue curve
is further and further away
from the red one, hence p_n moves away from f.
If I do the same thing except with 41 points,
I build the polynomial of degree 40
through the 41 points I observe that
the trend is even more pronounced.
The polynomial p_40 and the function f
are close to each other in the vicinity of 0.
Unlike close to -1  and 1 where they
are far away from each other.
Let's do the same experiment
with the sinus function
on the interval [-1,1], in red the sinus
function and in blue the polynomial
of degree 2 through three equidistant
points. You can see that
there is a little difference between the
polynomial and the sinus function.
Using 5 equidistant points,
the red and blue curves
are now overlaping. With 11 points
no difference can be seen.
Again with 21 points the difference
can't be seen with one's nacked eye.
So the question: can a polynomial p_n converge
to f when n approaches infinity ?
i.e. when I take more and more equidistant points ?
The answer from numerical observtion is:
it depends !
It depends mainly on the function f.
So I suggets to you
a theorem to allow us to conclude
in a certain number of cases.
nombre de cas.