Now I will present theorem 1.1 from the book,
which allows us
to explain the results in some cases.
I remind you that
the problem is the following:
let us consider a function f defined
on an interval [a,b] in R. We considered t_j
equidistant interpolation points,
t_j = a + (b-a)*j/n for j=0,1,...,n.
These t_j points are equidistant.
Let p_n a polynomial of degree n which
coincides with
the function f in the points t_j.
So p_n is equal to f in t_j, for j = 0,1,..,n.
p_n is a linear combination of the
functions phi_0, phi_1, ... phi_n
which are the Lagrange basis polynomials
of degree n associated
to the points t0,t1,...,tn. So p_n of t is
f of t0 times phi_0 of t plus
f of t_1 times phi_1 of t plus...
f of t_n times phi_n of t.
Again, phi_0, phi_1, ... phi_n are the
Lagrange basis polynomials of degree n
associated to the points t0, t1, ... tn.
The hypothesis is that f is
(n+1) times continuously differentiable
on the interval [a,b] and the
conclusion of the theorem is the following:
I am interested in the error, i.e. the difference
between the function f and the
polynomial p_n of degree n
also known as the interpolant of f
associated to the points t0,t1,t2, ... tn.
I track this error at all points t,
and consider the maximum of the
error on the interval [a,b]. I then claim that
such this error is upper bounded by 1/(2*(n+1)).
times (b-a)/n
elevated to the power (n+1).
times a term which
brings in the (n+1) derivative
of the function f on the interval [a,b],
in absolute value
and consider the maximum of this quantity
on the interval [a,b]. Hence the error between
the function f and the polynomial is upper
bounded by a term which approaches zero
as n approaches infinity and another term
which uses the derivatives of increasing order.
Let's consider two cases
which correspond to both examples
done in the java apps.
In the case where f(t)= sin(t)
I know that all derivatives of sin(t)
are upper bounded by 1 ,
this for all t in [a,b] or even R.
This quantity is bounded by 1,
this one approaches 0 as n approaches infinity.
So we must have
the limit of the maximum of the
error between the function f
and the polynomial p_n goes to
zero as n goes to infinity.
In the case when f(t)=1/(1+25*t^2),
an explicit formula of the derivative can not be given.
Neverthless I can observe that
the (n+1) derivative of f goes to
infinity as n goes to infinity.
Hence there is one term which
goes to infinity
as n goes to infinity, and a second
one which goes to zero
so no conclusion can be made.
Nevertheless the numerical examples
show that the polynomial moves further away
from the function f.
At least the maximum of the error
goes to infinity when
n goes to infinity. The conclusion is the
following: choosing equidistant interpolation
points is not a recommended when the
number of points goes to infinity
i.e. when the degree of the polynomial gets
higher and higher.
One method to resolve this issue is by
choosing points with adequate spacing
on the interval [a,b].
By experimenting with the java app,
you can see that by placing more points
towards the edges of the interval, things get
better. The other solution
which I will do next in the course, is
interpolation by intervals.
This is what is done in
finite element softwares.