In this video I will talk to you about interpolation
of degree 1 by interval.
I will consider a function f
defined in the interval [a,b].
Let x_i be equidistant points in the interval [a,b]
such that x_i = a+((b-a)/N)*i for i=0,1, ... N.
Here the interval [a,b], the variable x.
The function f defined on the
interval [a,b]. I choose
a certain number of equidistant points on
this interval [a,b] called x0, x1, x2, x3 and x4.
So here is the function f(x) on
the interval [a,b]
and I will build the function f_h
the following way
This function f_h will be the interpolant by
intervals of degree 1 of the function f.
This function is continuous on the interval
[a,b] and should coincide with the function
f at points x_i for all i = 0,1, ... N.
In this notation
we used the letter h, but what is it ?
It is the following: h = (b-a)/N, the distance
between two consecutive points.
This h approaches 0, or equivalently
N approaches infinity.
So the functions f and f_h must
be equal at nodes x_i.
Furthermore f_h restrained such that
on every sub-interval x_i to x_(i+1)
f_h is a polynomial of degree 1
for i = 0,1, ... N-1.
So f_h on the interval x0 to x1 is a
polynomial of degree 1
passing through (x0,f(x0)) and (x1,f(x1))
and so on for the sub-intervals x1 to x2,
x2 to x3 and x3 to x4. Each time it is a
different polynomial of degree 1.
Here is the function f_h of x; the question
I want to answer is:
does f_h converge, somehow, to the function
f as h approaches 0, or
as N approaches +infinity.
The error is here. I will consider the maximum
of this error on the interval [a,b].
The theoretical result is the following:
theorem 1.2 in the book:
a positive C exists such that
the function f is twice differentiable
on the interval [a,b].
This is the case for my drawing.
For all h positive we have the error
(f_h(x)-f(x)), by taking the absolute value
of this error and considering the maximum
on the interval [a,b]; we get the error
visible here.
This error is smaller then C*(h^2) times
the maximum of the
second derivative of f on the interval [a,b].
According to this theorem, C does not
depend on neither h nor f,
hence there exists for all h and all f
a value C depending on neither h nor f.
The meaning of this theorem is the following
in practice:
we choose a function twice differentiable
on the interval [a,b]. For a given h
we measure the error and must
observe that this error
is at least divide by 2^2, so 4, each time
h is divide by 2.