This time we will consider the
interpolation by interval of degree 2.
As previously, we take the function f
defined on the interval [a,b] in R
and consider the equidistant points x_i
on the interval  [a,b] such that
x_i = a + (b-a)/N * i for i = 0, 1, ... , N.
The parameter h is still the (b-a)/N.
Again the graph of the function f
on the interval [a,b].
I take five equidistant points x0,
x1, x2, x3 and x4. The graph of
the function f. I will build the function f_h
which is continuous on the interval [a,b].
We must impose that this
function f_h coincides with
the function f at the points xi:
f_h(x_i) = f(x_i) for i = 0,1, ... , N.
I will add one extra constraint,
I will impose that
the function f_h coincides with the
function f in the middle of the
sub-intervals: x_(i+1/2) for i = 0, 1, ... N-1.
These x_(i+1/2) points are the middle points
of the sub-intervals x_i to x_(i+1).
So x_(1/2) is the middle point
of the interval x_0 to x_1.
So the functions f_h and f must
be equal on these intermediate points.
Finally,  I impose that the function f_h
is a polynomial of degree 2 on each
sub-interval x_i to x_(i+1)
passing through the three points of
each sub-interval. Previously we
imposed that the function f_h was a
polynomial of degree 1.
Here is the interpolant of degree 2,
this for all intervals for i = 0, 1, ... ,N-1.
Now I can draw this interpolant.
On the first interval x1 to x2,
we have three points.
This is the unique polynomial of degree 2
through these three points.
On the interval x1 to x2 there are also
three points. Again this is the only
polynomial of degree 2 through these points.
You can observe that the left derivative
isn't equal to the derivative to the right
at point x1.
So the function is continuous, but not
once differentiable. By moving on
to the next interval x2 to x3, we get the
unique polynomial of degree 2.
Finally, on the interval x3 to x4 we also
have the unique polynomial of degree 2
passing through these three points.
I have now built my interpolating function
of degree 2 by intervals. Again I
must evaluate the error.
Here is the maximum of the error.
Will this error approach 0
as the parameter h, still the distance between
two points, approaches 0 ?
So does f_h converge, somehow, towards
f as h approaches 0,
equivalent to, as N approach +infinity.
The answer is yes, given by theorem
1.2 of the book.
Let C be a positive constant such that
for all f three times differentiable
on the interval [a,b]. I must here assume f
three times differentiable.
Previously for the interpolating function
of degree 1, f needed to be twice
differentiable. So there exists C such that
for all h positive, again h
does not depend on f nor h,
the maximum of the error on the
interval [a,b], f_h(x)-f(x) taken in
absolute value. I consider the maximum
of this error on the interval [a,b].
Well this error is upper bounded by C * h^3
times the maximum of the third derivative,
taken in absolute value.
Again the signification, or the numerical
experiment which can be done,
is the following. We choose a function
three times diferentiable,
we then calculate the error between f
and f_h. We can observe that this
quantity, the maximum of the error on
the interval [a,b] is divided by
2^3 = 8 each time h is divide by 2.
chaque fois que H est divisé par deux.