A short summary of this first
chapter on interpolation.
The problem we tried to solve was the following:
we search for a polynomial of degree n
such that p( tj )= pj. The values tj and pj
are given for all
indexes j = 0, 1, ..., n. The solution to
the problem can be written
as a linear combination of the
functions phi_0, phi_1, ..., phi_n
which form the Lagrange basis of polynomials
of degree n and depend on the choice of
points t_0, t_1, ... , t_n. Hence the solution
is a linear combination of these functions
phi_0, phi_1, ... phi_n, and the coefficients
of the linear combination are the values
given by the p_j. So we have p(t) equal
to the sum over j = 0, ... n of the product
of p_j times phi_j(t). The k-th basis function
of the Lagrange basis is a polynomial
of degree n which must cancel out for
all points, except for j equal to k.
The numerator is monomials of the form
(t - t_j), and the denominator is
composed of monomials (t_k - t_j) such
that phi_k(t_k) is equal to 1.
That must be understood for the exam.
Next we considered a function f
defined on a continuous interval [a,b].
We built the polynomial of degree n which
coincides with the function f in a given
number of points t_j equidistant on the
interval [a,b]. Again, we have p_n a
linear combination of these fixed functions,
the functions forming the Lagrange basis.
The coefficients of the
linear combination
are the values of the function f evaluated
at points t_j. As n approaches infinty,
we want to know if the
polynomial p_n approaches
the function f ? The answer is given
by a theorem which depends on the
derivative of order n+1
of the function f.
We have considered another problem :
interpolation by intervals.
We built f_h, the interpolant by interval
of the function f, with equidistant points.
h is the distance between two
consecutive points
which will approach zero. So f_h is a
function which is continuous, but not
differentiable. This function coincides
with the function f at
these equidistant points and the function
f_h is a polynomial of degree 1 on each
subinterval. In this case the error
between f and f_h is an error
which follows h^2, this is true only if f is
twice differentiable.
Now if you consider an interpolant f_h
of degree 2 on each subinterval, well
you get that the distance between f and f_h
is of order h^3,
so the error is divided by 2^3 = 8 every
time h is divided by two.