In this episode, we will go over
the details of
one of the important applications of
polymorphism, known as
"heterogeneous containers"
Up to now, we have seen that
inheritance and virtual methods allow us
to define generic functions accessible to
all instances of a class hierarchy
This is polymorphism.
We learned that if we want to
use functions or methods
in a polymorphic way,
that is, apply these functions to objects
then these objects must be
passed by reference.
What if we have a set of objects,
a collection of objects (a.k.a. an "container")
belonging to a hierarchy which we
wish to be able to manipulate
in a polymorphic way?
This is known as a "heterogeneous
container".
Meaning that each object stored in the
container, in the set
can have slightly different,
specific behavior.
Let's illustrate this with the example
of our game with the characters.
We had a Personnage class with a certain
number of members
and specific methods, and different
subclasses:
thieves, magicians, warriors etc,
who were all characters.
We wanted to put them in a game that
would contain several characters.
So we would have a collection of
characters, but we want each
character to behave according to
their real nature.
A warrior will behave as a warrior,
a thief as a thief, etc.
So this collection will be "heterogeneous".
How do we define the game
in this case?
We could define the game
like this, of course:
having a specific container for each
of the subclasses, that is,
having a container for all
of the warriors
one for the magicians, etc.
Then we could display all of the
warriors through a method
allowing to display the warriors,
display all the magicians through another
specific method, etc.
We could add a warrior to the game,
or add a magician, a thief, etc.
This solution is possible
and in some cases,
it will be necessary to differentiate
between the subclasses
and to have specific containers
for each of the subclasses.
They will not be heterogeneous containers.
There would be as many specific containers
as subclasses.
That solution is quite possible, but we
could imagine
a different solution.
It depends on the context, on
the needs of the program,
where we could imagine managing all
the characters in a global way,
to manage them generically in a
container of characters.
These characters would have their
own specificities,
so we would have a heterogeneous
container.
In that case, we would define
the "Jeu" class like this
We would have a collection of characters,
in the form of a vector
which would group all our characters.
We would only have one
"afficher" method
that would display all of
the characters.
And we would have a generic method here,
"ajouter_personnage" which would allow us
to add a generic character to
the collection.
In this context, we would want each
of the characters to have
their own behavior and so if
"personnage[i]" is a warrior,
then the method "personnage[i].afficher"
would call the afficher method of the
warrior subclass.
We would want to have
a polymorphic behavior
for the characters stored in the game.
Unfortunately, the code we have
present up til now does not allow
polymorphic behavior. Indeed,
here we have
a vector of characters and
we access the characters
directly without passing through a reference
or a pointer.
However, remember that
polymorphic behavior is only possible
with virtual methods, as well as
either pointers or references.
Which one should we use here?
I'll remind you of a general piece of advice
concerning pointers and references:
Use references whenever you can,
and pointers when you must.
Here, the idea would be to
use a set of references.
Unfortunately, we cannot put references
in a vector
nor in any standard C++ container.
The technical reasons for this are beyond
the scope of this course.
We are forced to use pointers here.
So we will change the implementation
of our Jeu class to have
a vector of pointers to characters.
To have polymorphic behavior for our characters,
we will have
an vector of pointers-to-Personnage.
The question we could ask ourselves
here is, do we want to use
"C-style" pointers or "smart pointers",
C++11 pointers?
So here is an alternative,
a C++11 version.
We recommend you use
this second approach.
We will detail the reasons for this choice
in a extra, optional episode
which will follow this episode.
If you follow our su"ggestion and
use "smart pointers
in the C++11 style, you will define a vector
of unique pointers to Personnage.
To use unique pointers, remember
to include
the memory library.
For those who would like reminders
on pointers, we have uploaded
all of the courses that we gave on pointers
from our previous MOOC, Introduction
to Programming.
I encourage you to
review these courses if necessary.
So here, we could use either solution.
In any case, note that it is
pointers that
will be stored in this container.
The "personnage" vector here is a
vector of pointers, and no longer
of instances directly.
This will have some influence
on the design and execution of
the game, since the instances
are now outside of the Jeu instance.
In Jeu, we only have pointers
to the instances.
How do we continue developing our Jeu
class and adding
these methods for displaying or adding
characters, for example?
The easiest is to first look at how
we will use this game, this instance of Jeu.
So, we would declare a game, an instance
of Jeu, and imagine that
we want to add a character.
But we have to add a pointer.
The easiest is to add a pointer
allocated dynamically with a "new".
For example here, we create a new warrior,
"new Guerrier", which will return a new
pointer to a warrior.
So in memory, we would have
the following situation:
a Jeu which has a
set of pointers.
At first, it is completely empty.
Then, we create a warrior in
memory
and the "new" would return a pointer
to this warrior that we would store
in our container.
So the prototypes for our methods
would be:
here, a "ajouter_personnage" (TN: means
"add_character") method that would
take a pointer to Personnage.
This is what it receives, as new returns
a C-style pointer to a Personnage.
Then the afficher method which
doesn't pose any problems,
which displays all the characters.
So we would have the usual prototype
for this display method.
Now, let's see how we can define
these methods.
Let's start with the method that
adds a character.
Its prototype takes a C-style pointer
to a character
to allow a call as we have just seen.
We start, to be safe, by checking that
we have indeed received, through
the "nouveau" (TN: means "new") pointer here
a pointer to a real Personnage instance.
So we check that the pointer is
not null.
Then we add it to the character
container.
Remember that we decided to
implement the character container
as a vector of
unique_ptr's to Personnage.
So we simply add it with
a "push_back"
The C-style pointer, "nouveau", returned
by the call to "new"
will be transformed to a unique_ptr.
Because new returns a C-style pointer
and we have decided to
implement our pointers as
C++11-style "smart pointers",
we will transform this C-style pointer
here into a unique_ptr.
Let's go over the previous call
in detail,
" jeu.ajouter_personnage (new Guerrier) ".
(TN: means "game.add_character(new Warrior);")
We call the constructor with parameters
for Guerrier's constructor. It will do
the following:
first, it will execute new Guerrier,
which will create a new warrior
in memory.
New will return a pointer to this
allocated memory area.
This pointer will be passed to the
ajouter_personnage method
and be called "nouveau".
This pointer is not null.
So we arrive here
in the Jeu class and do
a push_back.
Suppose that this vector
was initially empty.
So we execute this push_back which
will add an element to our vector
in which we will add the result of the
transformation of this C-style pointer
to a unique_ptr pointing to the memory
area allocated by the new statement.
Now, let's talk about the "afficher" method.
Suppose that each character has its
own afficher method
which is polymorphic.
So we simply need to do this,
to loop over all of the characters stored
in the vector of pointers
to characters,
and to call the afficher method
through this pointer. This is exactly why
we have pointers,
to have a polymorphic behavior.
However, this code does not compile.
Indeed, our "Personnages" collection is
a vector of
unique_ptrs, of unique pointers.
There cannot be more than one
pointer to a given memory area.
In memory, we have something
like this:
a vector of unique_ptrs
pointing to characters.
When we write the for loop,
when we write the for loop like this,
it happens the the "quidam" variable
is another variable that will
take the value of each of the elements
of the personnages vector, one after the other.
So quidam is a pointer that will
point to the same area
as the various pointers to our characters,
one after the other,
as they are stored in the vector.
So for example, the first step, which is
to say that quidam equals this pointer,
means that two pointers are equal, they
point to the same area.
This is impossible, due to the fact
that we have unique_ptrs here.
We can only have one pointer per
memory area.
So this solution is unacceptable.
To do this, we need a reference
to the stored objects,
a reference to the unique pointers.
That is quite possible.
So the correct for loop is
written like this:
"for auto reference", of course here
we will not modify anything,
as the display method is const, so we
can use a "const reference".
So "for auto const reference"; quidam is now
a constant reference to the elements
of the personnages vector.
That is, a constant reference to
unique_ptrs.
This is a subtlety of unique pointers.
Now, let's see how we can use our
Jeu class.
Here, we would declare a game and
add characters to it
by calling the ajouter_personnage method
and creating them dynamically with new.
We have a new warrior here, with parameters
for its constructor.
Then we add a new magician,
a new thief,
perhaps another new warrior, etc.
When we want to display the game,
we simply call jeu.afficher.
But this innocent Jeu class nevertheless
hides a potential danger.
What happens if one of the objects
we added to the collection,
-- or rather, whose address we added to the
collection -- what if one of these objects
were to disappear?
In that case, we would still have a
pointer to that object in the vector
despite this object being destroyed,
and this could cause big problems.
For everything to work correctly,
it is absolutely necessary
for all of the elements that are pointed to
to last at least as long as their pointers.
So in this example, all of the characters
in the game must exist
at least as long as the game.
And it is up to the programmer to
ensure that with good design.
So, it is up to the programmer not to
make this kind of mistakes.
For example, imagine a slightly naive programmer
who wants to create a function
to create and add a magician
into the game
This function would modify the game,
and take a reference to the game
and it would create a magician here,
passing parameters to its constructor
and then,
it would call the ajouter_personnage.
And since we must pass pointers
to add characters,
it passes the address of
this magician here
And so in the main,
we would have the game.
We call this "creer_magician" function.
We pass the game by reference
to add a magician to it.
Then we display the game
The problem is that this
creer_magicien function adds
a new magician which is a local
variable.
It is important never to do
this sort of thing,
never to add local variables.
This local variable will cease to exit:
"mago" here will cease to exist as soon as
we exit the function.
So here, we will have added a pointer
to a magician via
a reference, but this magician
will no longer exist
as soon as we exit the
function that created it.
So, from this semicolon here,
we should never try to access
this magician.
We should not try to display it anymore.
So here, we know what will happen,
we will display a magician
that potentially does not exist anymore.
I say potentially because on some
machines,
as this code is relatively short,
nothing bad may actually happen.
But if you imagine several lines of
code with several manipulations
between this function call and
this display here,
then it is virtually certain that you will
get a nonsense result.
So, never do such a thing!
Never take the address
of a local variable,
never use the address of a local
variable like this
The correct way to do this, to solve
this sort of problem is to use
what is called dynamic allocation and to
guarantee that the allocated memory area
will be preserved for at least as long as
its container.
So for example, here, the creer_magicien
method which takes a game by
reference, would add to this game
a dynamically-allocated magician
as we have done up til now.
This new will trigger a dynamic allocation
and the memory area will exist as
long as we don't call delete.
In the case of a container where we manage
pointers through unique_ptrs,
we don't even need to call delete.
The memory will be freed automatically
by the unique_ptr as soon as it is
no longer used.
This is one of the advantages of
unique pointers.
This is why we recommend you use
these "smart pointers", these unique
pointers at first.
You will not need to bother about
freeing memory, so you will not risk
accidentally freeing memory while
it is being used.
However, the pointer
will automatically be freed as soon as
we no longer use this memory area.
Now, the second aspect, the unique
aspect.
The smart aspect of the pointer
handles deallocation,
and the unique aspect prevents having
multiple references to the same area.
As we saw in the example of the for loop, this
introduces a few constraints.
But it is a big advantage to have
only one pointer to a certain
object. That way, the object
truly belongs
to the container to which it is
supposed to belong.
There are no other places in the program
pointing to this object
and that could modify it.
These are the reasons why we recommend
you use, at first,
unique_ptrs
Now, we could also use
C-style pointers.
If you wish to learn about this, we have
produced another episode,
an optional one, which will detail
this solution
and should thus shed more light on
the advantages of unique_ptrs.