We have seen that if we want
a heterogeneous container,
that is, a set of polymorphic
objects
grouped in a same container,
for example in a vector
then, it was necessary,
in order to have polymorphism,
to have a set,
a collection of pointers to
these objects.
And we recommended, up until now,
that you use a vector of
C++11 style smart pointers,
an vector of unique pointers.
In this episode, we'll take a look
at how we could do this
with C-style pointers and
what it would imply.
Remember, we had used the
Jeu class in our example,
containing a collection of characters
that could be polymorphic.
They could be warriors, thieves,
magicians, etc.
And so for this, we used a
vector here,
with pointers to our characters.
In the previous version, we had
used unique pointers;
now, let's see what happens if we
use C-style pointers
since after all, the interface to
add a character
uses a C-style pointer.
As a reminder, the usage was to have an
instance of Jeu,
and to call "jeu.ajouter_personnage"
(TN: means "game.add_character"),
with dynamic allocation of a warrior
here, through "new Guerrier".
This returns, of course, a pointer
to a warrior,
and this pointer to a Guerrier
is compatible with a pointer
to a Personnage,
since a Guerrier is a Personnage;
a pointer to a warrior is also a pointer
to a character.
So in this case, how can we
write the two methods of
the Jeu class with C-style pointers?
Let's start with adding a character;
the prototype hasn't changed.
We take a parameter, "nouveau"
which is a C-style pointer to a
character,
since this is the result of a call
to new.
And since we have decided to have
a vector
of C-style pointers to characters,
there is nothing complicated here.
We simply need to add
"push_back" at the end of the vector
of characters
with the "nouveau" parameter that
we received.
As in the previous version, we can
start by
verifying that the pointer we have
received is not null,
that is, that it is a pointer to
a real object.
This version is a little simpler than the
one with the unique pointers.
Similarly, for the display,
we can simply use a classical
"for auto" loop
since there is no issue, no problem
with having several pointers to the
same memory area
as is the case with unique pointers.
So here, there is nothing special to
be done compared to unique pointers.
I will let you compare both
codes to
see where the differences lie.
We can see that in the unique
pointer version,
we had to add "unique_ptr"
here
instead of simply having a star.
On the unique pointer side,
we also had to add
a "const" here to avoid having
several pointers to the same area,
unlike in the C-style pointer version.
And finally, we had to add the conversion
from a C-style pointer
to a unique_ptr,
which isn't necessary either in the
C-style pointer version.
Thus it seems that the C-style pointer
version is simpler
that the unique pointer version.
So why did we recommend you
use unique pointers?
The problem with C-style pointers is that
the programmer
has to take steps to prevent various
potential problems
with their class.
The first thing to think about
when using pointers in a class
-- such as here,
when we add pointers to our
heterogeneous container,
in our game --
the first thing to think about is:
when we have pointers in a class,
we must think about the copy constructor
and the destructor, as well as the
assignment operator.
Indeed, if we have pointers
in a container,
such as in our game here, where
we have an vector
of pointers to characters.
The question to ask is:
what does it mean to copy a game?
Do we want to make a surface copy?
If I have a game j2 here,
which is a copy of j1,
it will have a copy of the vector
of characters,
but if we only make a surface copy,
if we only use the default
copy constructor,
then we will copy pointers.
We will simply copy the various
elements one after the other,
copying only the pointers.
This means that the game j2 will point to
the same characters as the game j1.
And this is usually undesirable,
since we generally want
both collections to have
independent elements.
Here in the example of the games,
we would like to be able to play
the first and second games separately,
without the characters from one game
influencing the characters from the other.
This problem does not occur with
unique pointers
since with unique pointers,
it is impossible to have multiple
pointers
to the same characters,
and we would not be allowed
to copy them.
So copying is inherently forbidden
with a game containing
unique pointers.
The compiler would indeed have
forbidden this call to the copy constructor,
which tries to makes copies of the
unique pointers.
So the program would have realized
that there was a problem here.
Moreover, with C-style pointers, it is
important not to forget deallocation
and especially the golden rule,
that whoever allocates the memory,
whoever calls "new",
must also free the memory,
that is, call "delete".
Here is a reminder of how this worked;
to add a character to the game, the
character was created
with a call to "new", so for
example "new Magicien",
with parameters for its constructor.
So it is this one who makes this
call here, who will have to handle destruction.
In this case, there is no way of getting
the pointer that was allocated,
since this value wasn't saved,
and we must provide a means to
destroy the characters
we have put into our collection.
For example, with a "detruire_personnage"
method (TN: means "destroy_character")
where we would indicate the
address of the character we wish to
destroy; but this would suppose of
course that the one making the allocation
keeps a trace of their pointers
to be able to use them here.
We could also destroy a character by
indicating which number,
which index that character has,
supposing that we had numbered, that
we had access to the characters' numbers,
we could destroy character number 2,
etc.
Or, we could provide a method that
would destroy all the characters.
That is up to you, depending
on your design, depending
on the heterogeneous container
that you want to use.
But in any case, you will have
to think about
providing methods allowing deallocation
of allocated memory,
to be able to free the pointers that
are in your container.
For example, if we had decided to
provide a method to destroy
all pointed-to objects stored
in the collection,
that would destroy all the characters
pointed to in the game,
then we would iterate like so,
with a "for" loop,
over all the characters, all the pointers
in this "personnages" vector,
and we would "delete" each of
these pointers.
Of course, in the end,
we mustn't forget to empty
the vector of its pointers
to avoid keeping in memory
the pointers to memory areas that
have been freed.
Here is another solution, if
we wish to provide the method
allowing the destruction of a character
specified by their position,
for example to destroy the
second character,
we would have the following
situation:
We have a game
containing its vector of characters
which are pointers to characters,
warriors, thieves, magicians,...
And suppose that we pass
the parameter 1 here
to this method,
meaning that we want to delete
the second character,
-- character 0, character 1 : we want to
destroy the second character --
so the first thing we would do
if, of course, we are sure that this
parameter here, "lequel",
is smaller than " personnages.size() ".
This could have been tested on the
outside, before the call to "detruire_personnage",
of course, if we cannot guarantee it, if
it is not the case,
we could always add a test here.
And so if such a condition
is guaranteed,
the first thing we would do would
be to "delete" this memory area,
so " delete personnages [lequel]; " here,
so "personnage[1]".
We will call "delete" here
on this memory area
but of course, once we have
done this,
we will have to avoid
keeping this address
of an invalid memory area,
so we will have to delete this pointer.
So there, you have 3 solutions
depending on what you want to do.
All three solutions are quite
applicable.
It depends on how you want to
manage your heterogeneous container:
if we want to keep the same order
and the same number of elements
in our vector of characters,
the same number of possible characters,
but simply indicate that this
character is dead,
then at that point, what we could do is
simply to say
that we replace the invalid pointer
by a null pointer,
saying that this character was destroyed,
represented by a null pointer,
"nullptr".
This would yield the following
memory situation
and so here we would indeed
have an vector that continues to
have 4 possible characters
with a null pointer here to indicate
that the character at position 1, the
second character, no longer exists.
This is a possible situation,
but that implies that the one using this
vector will make sure to
test if the object does indeed exist
before calling a method on it,
for example.
Another solution, when we
destroy a character,
is to say that at that moment,
the number of characters in the
game is decremented by 1,
the size of the vector is reduced by 1,
and so to actually delete this element.
In that case, there are 2 possible
solutions,
an efficient solution which
does not preserve order,
but that is very efficient, that only
deletes a single element,
and a solution that preserves the order
but that will be very expensive,
since it will require copying all
the elements
following the element that
we are destroying.
Let's look at the first solution.
The first solution simply consists
in exchanging,
with "utility"'s "swap" function,
to exchange the pointer on which
we have just called "delete"
with the last pointer of the vector,
" personnages.back ", remember, is the
last element of
the "personnages" vector,
and so we will exchange these 2 elements,
which will result in this.
If we exchange both pointers,
this element will now
point here,
and this element
will point over there.
We have exchanged these two pointers.
Once this exchange has been done,
then at that point,
we can delete the last element
of the vector
since we now know that this
last element
is the pointer that we want
to destroy.
So with this "pop back",
we will delete this last element.
This means that after that
we will only have 3 characters left
and no trace of the address of
this memory area
that we have just freed.
A third solution, depending
on our needs,
would be to delete this pointer,
but to preserve the order,
that is, to keep this pointer
at the beginning,
this one in second place,
this one in third,
and not by exchanging them like
we did here,
as we did earlier.
By using "vector"'s "erase"
method,
we will delete -- I show you this
with no further details --
the element at the position "lequel".
And the reason this is so expensive
is that this method
will indeed delete this element, but it
will copy all the following elements
to move them, one after the other,
in order to ensure that the vector
stays contiguous in memory,
with 3 elements.
So this is how we could do it,
one way or another,
to make it possible to remove elements
from the container.
To summarize, C-style pointers
in a heterogeneous container
pose a problem for data integrity.
In fact, there are 3 sides to this problem:
the first, is to guarantee the lifetime
of the data pointed to,
the lifetime of our characters
in the game,
for at least as long as the
game exists.
We already spoke of this in the
unique_ptr case.
We talked about it in the
previous episode.
This is a point we find
both with unique pointers
and with C-style pointers.
The second problem is the
deallocation problem:
we must guarantee that we will
free the memory that we allocated,
and with unique pointers,
since they are smart pointers, there
is nothing to do.
So here, everything is alright.
However, with C-style pointers, this is
of course not automatic.
So we must, as we have just
discussed,
provide a means to do so cleanly.
Then, third problem, is sharing
data
between different collections.
We already briefly discussed
this earlier with copying,
and I will come back to this in a moment.
This is not a problem with
unique_ptrs,
as it is this unique aspect
which prevents any sharing
of data
between different containers
But this is not at all guaranteed by
C-style pointers,
and so we will have to handle this.
Finally, let's take a closer look
at this last point.
To do so, I have chosen an example
that seems a little
more illustrative.
Imagine that we have drawings
(TN: "dessins")
that would be our heterogeneous containers.
Drawings are sets of geometric figures.
So we would have 2 classes,
the "Figure" class which
is an abstract class,
and we can imagine having
different figures
such as rectangles, circles, etc.,
inheriting from it.
So we would have a heterogeneous
container of figures,
which would be our drawing and
would contain different figures,
that would be polymorphic:
rectangles, circles, etc.
The question now is to know whether
the contents of a drawing
are personal or shared.
So for example, if I imagine that I
have several drawings,
for example, drawing "d18",
containing a set of pointers,
of course,
since we want figures to behave in a
polymorphic way,
pointers to figures,
and so imagine that I have another
drawing
also with its collectio
of pointers to figures.
Suppose for example
that one of these objects is a circle
and that we decide to modify
a property of this circle,
for example to color this
circle red.
The question is,
if I color this circle red,
will it just be the circle of this
drawing "d18"
that will be colored in red,
or will it also be circles for other
drawings?
For example, is this circle
shared
between drawings "d18" and "d4",
in which case, if I modify it through
one drawing, it will be modified for all.
The answer to this sort of question
depends of course
on the context in which you are designing
your heterogeneous containers
It depends on the design of
but I really think that in the
case of drawings,
we don't want figures to be shared
by several drawings
but we want each drawing to
have its own figures.
A drawing has its circle, another
drawing has another circle,
which are different.
In the case of the games we had taken
as the first example,
I also think that contents should
not be shared.
With whom would they be shared?
I think that in that case, we
only have a single game
and we will avoid copying games.
So if you want an example
where we could imagine having collections
that share their contents,
it could also be a game, but
a little more complex,
where we would have different cameras
that could each see the players of the
game under different angles,
and we could imagine that each
camera has
a collection of characters that
it can see,
like so.
So for example, camera 1 could see
monster 1 and player 2,
and camera 2 could see
both players.
And this would give us
the elements of the game
that are shared by
different collections.
But this kind of design is
much more advanced,
and possibly more rare.
In the examples we have given you,
we certainly did not want to share
the contents of the collections
between different collections.
We would want each collection to have
its own characters, in the case
of the game;
its own figures, in the case
of the drawings.
So, we would have to guarantee,
at the level of the program,
using methods and functions,
to guarantee that this is the case.
Or, use unique_ptrs
which prevent having several pointers
to the same object.
To conclude,
we have recommended using
unique pointers
to make it easier to guarantee
data integrity.
In any case, be it with unique pointers
or C-style pointers,
you must think about the problem
of the lifetime of the data
pointed to by these collections,
of the objects contained in
these collections.
But in the case of unique pointers,
you don't have to worry about
deallocation,
thanks to the smart pointer aspect
of C++11 pointers,
or about sharing data between
collections,
thanks to the unique aspect
of unique pointers.
If you go for a C-style pointer
implementation,
then you will need to thing about
these problems,
and also solve them.