During our learning,
we encountered three
different concepts
Function or method overloading;
shadowing;
qu'on appelle en anglais shadowing
and overriding
of virtual methods.
The latter applies only to virtual
methods.
So for virtual methods, we could
in principle have all three:
overloading, shadowing
and substitution.
What are these exactly?
To avoid confusion for some programmers,
since C++2011,
we have two new keywords which I will
talk about at the end of this episode,
namely override and final which
allow the programmer to specify his intention.
Let's go over these three concepts
in detail to clear up
what they do.
Before illustrating these concepts
with an example, let's review their definitions.
Function or method overloading happens
when a function or method
has the same name as another, but
has different parameters,
and has the same scope.
Careful, in C++, overloading is only
possible within the same scope.
We will come back to this later.
Shadowing, or hiding, occurs when
entities, variables, functions
or in the case of object-oriented programming,
members and methods,
have the same name but different
scopes.
Thus, following scoping rules,
C++ resolves to the nearest scope,
that is, the closest scope hides
the entity with a further scope.
Note that a single method with the same
name is enough to shadow all other methods
of further scope, independently
of their parameters
since with regards to parameters,
we would be in the case of an overload,
and overloading only happens
within one scope.
So if we are in another scope, we
simply need to have the same name
to mask all other methods.
We will come back to this with an example.
Finally, overriding is valid only
for virtual methods, and the idea is to
redefine, in a subclass,
a virtual method inherited from
a superclass
allowing what is known as
dynaming binding, and
polymorphism.
The method of the actual instance will
be invoked if it is called
via a pointer or a reference and, similarly
to shadowing,
if we redefine only one virtual
method,
it will override all the others,
even if they don't have the
same parameters.
Only one will be defined, but it will
simply hide the others.
The rules of shadowing also apply to
overridden functions.
Let's review this in detail
in an example:
Imagine that we have three classes
A, B and C
such that B and C both inherit
from A.
These three classes will have a method
m1 which
we will overload, override and shadow.
To make the example a bit more
concrete,
in the main function, we have an
instance b of class B
and an instance c of class C.
We will go over the different ways
of calling these m1 methods.
In class A, we have a first m1 method which
takes an integer.
Each of these methods will simply
display
a message indicating which method
was called.
Moreover, in A, we also have an m1 method
which has a different list of parameters
than the first method.
Here, it takes a string instead of an integer.
These two m1 methods have the same scope,
the scope of class A.
They have different lists of parameters,
but the same name.
This is therefore a simple case
of overloading.
In class B, we have an override
of one of the two methods.
We override the method which takes
a string
as argument.
This m1 method overridden here in
the B subclass of A
thus hides A's m1 method in B.
Since it is the only method of the two
which was overridden in B,
based on rules of scope and
shadowing,
this method also masks the other method
since in class B,
we will only have one accessible
m1 method.
Class B will effectively have three m1 methods.
Its own m1 method and the two m1 methods
inherited from the superclass, A.
But because of scope resolution rules,
when we are in B, we resolve to
the closest scope,
and the only one directly accessible
is the one that was
defined in B, which thus
hides both of A's methods.
Let's look at this in the main.
Here, we have our instance b.
We cannot make a call like this.
This is why we commented the m1 method
that takes an integer
since the m1 method taking an
integer, inherited from A,
is hidden by the method in B
which takes a string.
We can indeed call the m1 method
which takes a string. This
poses no problem at all.
But we cannot call the method from m1
taking an integer.
We get a message saying that
this function cannot be called.
However, it does exist;
if we want to call it, we will have to use
the scope resolution operator
saying "the method m1 of scope of
class A which belongs
to the instance b of subclass B".
which does indeed inherit this method from
class A since B is an A.
This method can thus be called here
but it will need to be "unhidden"
using the scope resolution operator.
In class C, we have introduced a
third method
a new method, since we have a third
type of parameter
with a double. This will define a new,
third m1 method
which will, once again, following scoping
rules,
hide both of the methods inherited from A.
With the instance c of class C,
we can call neither
the method with the string
nor the method with the integer.
Careful, this is a trap. This
call here, c.m1(2) does not invoke
the method taking an integer
since it is hidden.
If you execute this code,
you will get a message
saying "C::m1(double)" as it is
indeed the only method
which can be called directly without
unhiding in C's scope.
And an integer can be
converted to a double,
so here, there is a conversion from an
integer to a double to call
the only method which is in C.
Of course, as before, we can
unhide
the methods taking a string or an integer.
By using the scope resolution operator,
c.A::m1 with a string,
we will of course call A's method, which
takes a string.
This call here, with an integer, will
now unhide A's m1 method
inherited by the subclass C;
we will call this method here.
That's it for the aspects of
overloading and shadowing,
let's now discuss the overriding aspect.
In fact, all of these methods were
declared as virtual.
We simply need to declare, here,
these methods as virtual
to make them virtual automatically
in the subclasses.
Here, since we have exactly the same method,
the virtual is transitive.
It doesn't have to be repeated.
However here, we have a new method.
So we can define it as virtual or not.
All of these methods are declared
as virtual,
so we will have an override.
Overriding follows the same rules
as shadowing.
Essentially, dynamic binding will be used
if we have pointers or references,
which was not the case here.
Here, we simply had instances.
To observe the effects of overriding
and dynamic binding,
we will need to use pointers.
This is what we do in this new
example.
We still have the instances
b and c of classes
B and C, respectively,
but we now have a pointer-to-A
that we name pa.
First, pa will point to b
and then it will point to c.
Here, we make pa point to b.
The memory situation is as follows.
pa points to b and we call
the m1 method
through this pa pointer.
Note that m1 is a virtual method
which is overridden in class B.
So polymorphism is taken into
account here.
The m1 method from class B
will indeed be called
and will output the message
"B::m1(string)".
However, even though pa points to a B,
it is still a pointer-to-A.
And remember that in C++,
it is the type that
is determining when there is no
polymorphism;
static binding is used.
We resolve according to the type.
So here, pa is a pointer-to-A and
as such,
can access A's methods.
These method calls are in class A.
In other words, these calls are
in the scope of A and so
we can absolutely call the m1
method with an integer,
even though pa points to a B.
We are in A's scope.
So here, it is A's method which will be
called: "A::m1(int)".
Similarly, even if pa points to c,
even though we point to a C,
we are still in the scope of A
since we are working with a
pointer-to-A.
Here, we will call the method.
Careful, even if we pass a double,
we are still in A's scope
and so we will call the method that
takes an integer here.
This double will be converted to
an integer to call, within the scope of A,
the only method that can be called
with a double.
It is this one, where we convert
the double to an integer.
This is quite possible in C++ and
it is indeed
this method which will be called.
The method that is in C is not accessible
in the scope of A.
Though a C is an A, an A is
definitely not a C.
Here, since we are in A's scope,
it is in this scope that
we will resolve the name "m1".
So it is indeed m1 with an int
which will be called and
we will get the output for A::m1
with an int.
For the same reasons, we
absolutely cannot try
to unhide the method taking a double
by trying to use
the scope resolution operator on C.
This is completely illegal since we
are passing through a pointer-to-A
and an A is not a C.
C is an A but A is not a C.
A is at the top of the hierarchy.
C is an A, but A is
definitely not a C.
So this would not compile.
It is forbidden by the compiler.
It is not A which inherits from C,
but C which inherits from A.
There! All of this is certainly
rather technical
and at first may be a little difficult.
You should come back to this episode
later, once you have
had some practice with polymorphism
and its different aspects:
shadowing, overriding, and
especially overloading
the latter of which should not pose
any more problems.
Actually, since these concepts are
quite complicated,
C++ 2011 introduced two
new keywords
to allow the programmer, if he
so wishes,
to clarify his intentions.
These keywords are override which
indicates that we want
to override a virtual method inherited
from a superclass;
and final which prevents any
future override
of the associated method in potential
future subclasses.
Let's look at this in detail in an example.
Suppose that here, we have a class A which
contains four methods:
a method f1 that is simply defined
as virtual;
a method f2 which is also virtual and
has the const qualifier,
which cannot modify the instance;
a method f3, which is not virtual;
and an f4 method on which we
add the final qualifier.
Then we have a class B which
inherits from A and will, of course,
override and shadow these
various methods.
So we have an override of method
f1 in class B.
The prototypes are identical.
So the override keyword
is used correctly.
Indeed, f1 is an override of this
method.
Here, we have another method.
I will let you guess what it is.
Here, you can see that we have
a typo.
The developer wrote f-lowercase L
instead of "f1".
This, I guarantee, is a rather difficult error
to find while debugging.
Such a small difference between a lowercase
L and a 1
is often hard to spot.
So here, if we had forgotten the override
keyword...
-- of course without this line here --
what the person who wrote this in class B wanted
would have been to override the method f1
But instead of overriding the f1 method,
because of this typo,
they would have introduced a new virtual
method in B.
What the override keyword
allows
is to have the compiler check
for this.
As the developer of this class B
has specified,
they want an override of one
of A's methods.
In this case, since there is no fl
method in A,
the compiler will indicate
that there is an error.
This fl method does not override
any method from A.
This protects class B's developer
against potential mistakes.
Another type of mistake can be seen
on the f2 method.
Class B's developer wants to override
the f2 method.
However here, we will get
a compilation error.
Can you see why?
The error here is that the f2 method
is not const
whereas it was defined as const
in class A.
So the f2 method here is a
different f2 method
Be careful! const is completely
part of the specificity
of the method header.
The full prototype of the method
contains const and so here,
this is a different f2 method.
So the compiler doesn't accept this.
This is not an override of the f2 method
but a new f2 method.
So this is another example of a protection
against developers' mistakes.
Forgetting the const keyword,
or making a typo.
Regarding the f3 method, this
could be a conception mistake
at A's level.
Maybe f3 should have been virtual
and we thought that
we could override this
f3 method.
Remember that it is unnecessary to
repeat the virtual keyword.
We could easily, even for a virtual
method, write this.
The developer of class B wants
to override a virtual method,
so they add the override keyword.
Here again, they get an error message
from the compiler saying:
"No, careful, you are not doing what you
think you are doing".
This f3 method cannot be overridden
because
it is not a virtual method.
So here we have pure shadowing
without an override.
Here is a third case that can
protect the developer
of class B against potential
errors.
Here, the error would come either from
his interpretation of what class A is
or even from the developer of class A who
may have forgotten the virtual keyword.
Finally, the last situation with
the final keyword.
Here, class A's programmer
prevents any future override
of this f4 method.
So the developer of class B, a subclass
of A, cannot
override the f4 method.
It is final here, meaning
that we cannot override
this f4 method in subclasses.
So the compiler would refuse
to compile this line.
That's it for this example.
We recommend that you use the
override keyword.
Even if it a little cumbersome to write.
Use it to protect, at first,
against potential errors such as the
ones we have just discussed.
Concerning the final keyword, I don't think
it is essential at this course's level,
you can forget about it. In my opinion,
it is completely useless.
Why would we want to prevent anyone
from overriding these methods?
Finally, to be exhaustive, I would
like to mention
that the final keyword can also be used
to prevent deriving subclasses.
That is, to prevent inheriting
from a class.
For example, we could define a Sterile
class here
which cannot have any subclass.
By adding the final keyword here.
So we would not be able to
inherit from this Sterile class here.
This keyword makes the compiler
signal an error
whenever a subclass tries to inherit
from this superclass.
Here again, I don't think this is very interesting
at this course's level.
For this course, you can
forget about final
But do make sure to write
override each time
that you want to override a virtual method
inherited from a superclass.