In this episode, we will
discuss how
polymorphism can be a very good
complement to abstraction,
allowing us to better
specify classes
at the most abstract level.
We will introduce the notion
of "abstract classes"
and "pure virtual methods".
But let's start by presenting
the problem
that these pure virtual methods
address.
At the highest level in a hierarchy,
we don't necessarily know
how to define a method,
even though we know it will exist
in all the subclasses.
For example, if I imagine a very
general class
representing any closed
geometric shape,
then at that point, in this class,
it will be quite hard to define how
to calculate the surface area
of a closed, nondescript geometric shape.
This is certainly something that
is hard to define,
we wouldn't really know how
to do it.
However, we know that
for all closed figures,
for example circles, which
are closed figures,
we know that for each specific
closed figure
we should be able to define a
"surface area" method.
So, we can imagine that
all closed figures
will have a surface method,
even if we don't know how to define it
at the most abstract level.
Yet, to push it further,
we can even imagine that
this surface method
will be used at the highest level,
for example to calculate the volume
occupied over a certain height
by this surface
In this case, the volume occupied
by this geometric figure,
-- depending on this height --
would be defined as the product
of the height multiplied by
the surface area of the closed figure
So we could even call this method
even if we don't quite know
how to define it.
At the highest level, it would be defined
for all the actual examples of
closed figures.
The correct way to do this,
to introduce a method that
we know must exist,
but that we don't necessarily
know how to define
at the level of a superclass,
is to introduce the method as
a "pure virtual method".
Let's illustrate this concept of
pure virtual methods
with another example and return
to our game
with characters,
where we had warriors, who are
characters,
magicians, who are characters,
robbers,...
The class "Jeu" (TN: means "Game") would
of course contain several characters:
we decided to put them here
in a vector of characters.
And to have polymorphism,
we have an vector of pointers-to-characters
(TN: "Personnage" means "Character"),
this specific aspect of arrays
of pointers to a class
will be detailed in a future episode
on heterogeneous collections.
Here, we simply have our
vector of characters,
and imagine that in the game,
we wish to display
the whole set of characters.
So we would write a loop which iterates
over the set of characters,
which iterates over this "persos" vector,
and for each of these characters,
we would display that character.
In this syntax here, "un_perso"
(TN: means "a_character")
is the variable that iterates
over our vector of characters,
so it a pointer-to-Personnage.
And since we have a pointer, we
use this syntax here
to call the afficher method of
the object pointed to by un_perso.
So here, we would indeed
display each of the characters,
one character in the set of
stored characters,
here in the "persos" data-member
of the game.
The problem is how to display
a generic character.
We don't know how to display
We certainly know how to display a warrior,
a magician or a thief,
so each of the specific subclasses knows
how to be displayed;
however, at the general level of
a character,
we don't necessarily know how to
display it.
But we know that we need to do so,
here at the very general level of the game,
we know we will have to display
the characters.
So, how do we do so?
Of course, if we do nothing
in the "Personnage" class,
if we do not define any "afficher"
method in "Personnage",
then the "afficher" method in Jeu
would not compile
since here, we call the "afficher"
method of a character
and the compiler would not
know what to do,
it would give us an error.
So we should be able to write this
at the global level of the game,
we must introduce an "afficher" method
in the "Personnage" class.
Moreover, we would like to impose
to each of the subclasses,
warriors, magicians, to be displayed with
their own "afficher" method,
to have a specific method, and that it is
this specific method
which should be called in the general call
here at the level of the game.
Essentially, we want to force
the presence of a specific
method at the class level, and we want
this method to be polymorphic.
So this method has to be "virtual"
and exist at the character level.
But how do we do this if we don't know
-- suppose that we don't know how
to display a generic character.
What's more, how do we force
subclasses to override this
"afficher" method?
First solution for the first problem:
how to define the display for a
generic character.
We could have some arbitrarily-defined
method,
for example, suppose that here,
we arbitrarily define
that the display for a generic character
is no display at all.
This solution is a very bad idea,
because, first, it is a bad model
of reality
as characters do not appear as nothing,
so it doesn't correspond to anything,
the display is incorrect.
And what's more, the display would
be incorrect
if a subclass forgot to override
this method;
in that case, we would have characters
that would not be displayed,
phantom characters, which could be
a problem for the game.
Moreover, this solution does not address
the second problem,
it does not force the subclasses to
define their own "afficher" method.
The only good solution is to indicate
that the "afficher" method
must exist and must be defined
in each of the subclasses.
This is known as a "pure virtual method".
I hope this second example has
allowed you to understand
the need for these pure virtual
methods
in defining general, abstract superclasses.
Now, let's see how all of this is
actually written in C++.
A pure virtual method, also known as
an "abstract method",
is used to force subclasses
to override the inherited
virtual method.
To define a pure virtual method,
an abstract method,
we simply add "= 0" at the end
of its prototype.
For example, if in the "Personnage" class
we had written the virtual method
"afficher"
-- the "afficher" method does not
modify a character --
and at the end of its prototype,
instead of just having a semicolon,
we also added "= 0".
Then this would define a pure virtual
method, an abstract method.
Generally, a pure virtual method
is only partly specified,
meaning that there is usually
no definition
but only a prototype in the class
in which it was introduced.
This is not a strict requirement, but
it is often the case.
Here for example, we would not
define the "afficher" method
for a generic character;
we expect that each subclass will
define its own "afficher" method
specific to warriors, magicians,
thieves,...
If I go back to the other example,
the one with the closed figures,
we would have a "surface" method,
which would be a pure virtual method,
so here we would add "= 0"
to the end of its prototype,
that we could still use,
We are allowed to call
pure virtual methods.
we can for instace define
a "volume" method
which we have not defined as virtual
as there is no reason for a subclass to
override this volume method,
which takes a height and
calculates the volume occupied
as the product of the height and
the result of the call to the surface method,
where the surface method will be the
one belonging to the instance on which it is called.
Because as we will see,
a class containing a pure virtual
method,
such as FigureFermee,
cannot be instantiated
and so we will never call the
surface method
directly on a FigureFermee object.
However we can imagine subclasses
such as rectangles or circles
who know how to calculate
their surface area.
So we will call the circle's method
if it is a circle,
or the rectangle's method if it is
a rectangle --
that is the polymorphic aspect,
enabled by this "virtual" keyword.
Here, we call the surface method
through a pointer,
indeed, remember that this is
exactly the same as writing
"this -> surface", as we
might easily forget,
and so here, polymorphism is used
since we make the call through
a pointer,
even if it is not explicitly written, and
the method is virtual.
Another pure virtual method that
we could define
at the level of the FigureFermee class
is the concept of the perimeter.
The method would return the
perimeter of a closed figure,
and we don't necessarily know how to
define this generally either
at the level of the very generic, abstract
class describing closed figures.
But we could imagine being able to define
this properly in subclasses.
We will return to this example shortly.
A class containing a pure virtual
method such as this one
is known as an abstract class.
It is indeed an abstract class because
if a class contains a pure
virtual method,
then it cannot be instantiated.
We cannot create instances
of this class.
For example, we cannot declare a
variable of type "Personne",
and of course any subclass that inherits
from an abstract superclass
remains abstract as long as it
doesn't provide definitions
for the pure virtual functions
they inherited.
In other words, as long as they
haven't removed the "= 0"
from the prototypes of their override
of the pure virtual method
inherited from the superclass.
Let's take a look at this through
an example,
our example of a game with characters,
where a warrior is a character,
and has inherited a pure virtual method,
an "afficher" method defined as
pure virtual in the "Personnage" class.
If we do not redefine this "afficher" method
in the "Guerrier" class,
then this "Guerrier" subclass
is thus also an abstract class
since it has inherited a pure
virtual method
that it did not override, and that
hence remains pure virtual.
So if we try to add a warrior like this,
to add an instance of the Guerrier class
to the game
the we will get a compilation error
saying that I cannot create objects,
instances of the abstract class Guerrier,
since the virtual method "afficher"
in "Guerrier" is a pure
virtual method.
Let's complete our second example on
geometric shapes.
We have these closed figures
which have two pure virtual methods:
one for the perimeter and
one for the surface.
Let's imagine that we have
a Cercle class
which inherits from FigureFermee
as well as a Polygone subclass
which also inherits from FigureFermee.
In the Cercle subclass, we override
the surface method.
The surface of a circle is pi times
the radius squared.
The Cercle class would have a
member variable for the radius.
And we also override the perimeter, defining
it as 2 times pi times the radius.
So the Cercle class defines the surface and
perimeter properly.
The Cercle class has thus overridden both
pure virtual methods
without keeping them pure virtual, without
adding the "= 0" here,
so the Cercle class no longer has
any abstract methods
and we can now create instances
of this class.
There is no problem in defining
an instance of "Cercle".
On the other hand, we have the
Polygone class. Let's say that
a polygon is defined as a vector of sides.
This polygon class would override
the perimeter method,
without making it abstract,
removing the abstract aspect of
perimetre.
It overrides this perimetre method,
but the Polygone class does not
override the surface method.
We think it is too complicated
to have a formula here
to define the surface area of a polygon
in a general way
and so we do not define the surface
method in the Polygone class.
So Polygone remains an
abstract class:
we cannot declare instances
of Polygone.
It is impossible because in the
Polygone class,
there is a pure virtual method left
which is the surface method
inherited from FigureFermee
And since the Polygone class still
has a pure virtual method,
it is an abstract class and we cannot
create instances of it.
There, this example concludes this episode
on pure virtual methods and
abstract classes.
The next episode will focus
on heterogeneous containers,
vectors in which we put
the pointers to characters for example,
in our game.
We will go over all of this in detail
in the next episode.
And then we will discuss
additional aspects related to that topic
in a final, optional episode.