You now know about the fundamental
object-oriented concepts of
encapsulation, abstraction
and inheritance.
It is time to focus on an equally
important concept,
polymorphism.
Generally,
polymorphism allows one piece
of code to adapt
automatically to the different types of data
it might encounter.
It is an important concept, since
it makes it possible to move
towards generic code; code that
is written in unified way
for different types of data.
To introduce the concept of polymorphism
more concretely,
let's start with an example.
Suppose that we wish to program
a game that features the
characters from the hierarchy
we have already used in the previous
episodes.
Suppose that our game features
a main character
which would be the player.
And that in one turn in the
game,
this character faces
encounters,
that is, it will meet with a whole
set of other characters.
The set of characters could be represented
in the following way
in C++: a vector of Personnage
(TN: "personnage" means "character"),
which would be the autres
(TN: means "others"). And to write the code
that would make the others meet the
player, a for loop
like this, for example,
where each of the other characters meet
our player in turn.
So that our game doesn't become
too monotonous,
we would of course like to have,
in the collection of
other characters, characters of
various natures,
of various types.
meaning that here, in this
perso variable,
we would have, alternately, a warrior,
a thief, or a wizard.
We also know, from a previous episode,
that a subclass
can have its own, more specific
definition
of a method already defined higher up.
For example, we could imagine that
when the thief meets the character,
he steals from him.
Polymorphism consists in applying
the same code to objects
taking different forms
and having the execution adapt
automatically
to the form of the object.
This means, concretely,
that if at a certain moment our character is
of type Voleur (TN: means "Thief"),
the rencontrer (TN: means "to meet") method
will be chosen to be the thief's one,
who will thus rob our character without
further ado.
The idea is that thanks to inheritance,
the same code can apply
to any type of character possible.
All these forms of characters have a
rencontrer method
allowing the way that a character
meets another to take on
different forms,
meaning, effectively, that a magician can
greet a character,
a warrior can hit him, a thief
can rob him and so on.
And thanks to polymorphism,
the same code,
when applied to different characters,
will be able to have a different behavior
specific to each of them.
In other words, if I put a Voleur (= 'Thief') in a Personnage (='Character'),
in a polymorphic context,
the rencontrer method would
adapt automatically
to the real nature of the object contained
in the Personnage-type variable
and so here, we would use the rencontrer
method of the thief.
The point of manipulating a thief
as a generic character
and not directly in the form of a thief is
to be able to make
unified manipulations on all sorts
of objects.
You have an example of this here
where a whole set of characters of
different natures are manipulated
in the same way by being placed
in an array of characters (Personnage).
This supposes that at one point,
I added to my collection of characters
different characters of various natures,
i.e that I carried out
manipulations such as these
For example, if I have an object
of type Guerrier (TN: means "warrior")
and an object of type Sorcier
(TN: means "sorceror")
then I will have filled my array
of characters
by doing something like
this, for example.
That is, since the cells of my array
are of type Personnage,
we have put an object of type Guerrier
in a Personnage variable.
Small reminder on inheritance:
assigning a Guerrier to a Personnage
is completely valid.
In a class hierarchy,
the subclass inherits from the superclass
not only the member variables and methods
but also the type.
Guerrier is also a Personnage
and so, this assignment is
completely valid.
Remember also that inheritance
in transitive,
meaning that I can also assign
a Sorcier to a Personnage.
Why? Because since inheritance
is transitive, a Sorcier is also a Magicien
which is a Personnage itself.
The Sorcier is also a Personnage.
We can thus assign to an object of
the superclass type
an object of subclass type.
We see an example of this here
in this assignment.
This possibility also applies
when passing parameters, as we will
see in an example
on the next slide.
Here, we suppose that there exists
a class hierarchy
as described in the
previous example.
A programmer who uses this class
hierarchy
has defined a faire_rencontrer
function (TN: means "make meet")
which allows a character to meet another.
This faire_rencontrer function is used
in this main program
and it is passed, as arguments, a first
character who is a warrior
and a second character who is a thief.
This is to show that we can indeed
put a Guerrier
in a Personnage or a Voleur in
a Personnage
when passing parameters.
Putting an object of the subclass type
in a variable of the superclass type
is allowed both
in the context of assignment and in
the context of passing parameters.
This is due to the fact that
in an inheritance relationship,
a Guerrier is a Personnage.
Somewhat more formally then,
polymorphism allows
instances of a subclass
to substitute for instances
of their parent classes,
of their superclasses,
whether they are arguments of
a method or during assignment
-- as we have just seen in the
previous slides --
while keeping their own properties.
In this example, the idea would thus
be to put a Voleur
in a Personnage while guaranteeing that
the execution of the rencontrer method
will adapt automatically to the real
nature of the instance contained
in the Personnage variable,
meaning that we would apply
the rencontrer method of Voleur.
The fact that we can assign a thief
to a character variable
is a direct consequence of inheritance.
However, the fact that the
method to invoke
is chosen at execution time
depending on the real nature of
the instances
depends on what is known as
dynamic binding.
Let's see what this really is.
To do so, let's return to our previous
example where we substituted
an object of the subclass type
for an instance of the superclass type.
We put a Guerrier in a
Personnage
which is the parameter of the
faire_rencontrer method
and we call the rencontrer method
on the Personnage concerned.
Here, we are in the context
where our class hierarchy
would have two rencontrer methods.
One defined in the superclass
which is the default method,
the general method,
and one that is specific to warriors,
in the Guerrier subclass.
Which of these two rencontrer methods
will be called here?
Looking closer, we can see that
there are two possible points of view.
The first consists in saying that
the parameter is of type Personnage, so we will fetch the
rencontrer method
in the Personnage class. The second
consists in saying that
we put a Guerrier in Personnage, and so it
is the Guerrier class
that we will go and fetch the
rencontrer method.
There is thus a point of view which
says
that it is the type of the variable
that determines the choice of methods,
and a second point of view
that says
that it is the actual type of the object
contained in the variable
that determines the choice of methods.
In C++, if we do nothing special,
it is the type of the variable that will
determine which method to execute.
We use what is known as
static binding
meaning that here, it is Personnage's
rencontrer method
that will be called.
We speak of static binding
because the choice of methods can
be made statically, before the program
is even executed, during compilation.
At that stage, we can already know which
type a variable has
and based on this type, choose
which method to apply.
In some cases however, it can
be more natural to resort
to another type of binding,
known as
dynamic binding.
With this, the method will be chosen
during execution, dynamically,
based on the type of the object actually
contained in the variable,
meaning that here, we could make
sure that the rencontrer
method is the one belonging to the
object that is actually stored
in the Personnage-type variable.
Static binding is what is used
by default in C++ if we do nothing special.
However, it is possible to use
dynamic binding
but for that, we need to use two
specific ingredients.
The first is that methods for which we want
to use dynamic binding
must be declared with a specific label,
they must be virtual methods
and they must be able to apply
to the real instances of the objects via
references or pointers.
Our small initial example thus uses
static binding here.
In order to use dynamic binding, the
rencontrer method
has to be virtual, and should apply
not to an object
but to a reference of this object, or to
a pointer to this object.
This is not the case here; we do
indeed have static binding.
Virtual methods and their use via
references and pointers
will be the subject of the next
episode.