In the previous video, we learned
that polymorphism is a central concept
in object-oriented programming.
We learned that to implement a
polymorphic solution,
we need to make use of what is known
as dynamic binding.
The goal of this episode is to show you
how to implement dynamic binding
in C++ using virtual methods.
More specifically, we concluded the last
episode
by stating that for dynamic binding
to take place in C++,
two ingredients must be present.
First, the use of virtual methods
on references and pointers.
This episode will explain this concept.
Remember that we started with an example
where we had a hierarchy
of classes in which a subclass, the
Guerrier subclass,
overrides a method already defined
in the superclass.
An object of the subclass type was assigned,
via passing arguments,
to a variable of the superclass
type.
We had then asked ourselves
which rencontrer method
would be called here.
The rencontrer method of the superclass,
or the one of the subclass?
And we had seen that in C++,
static binding was used,
meaning that the type of the variable
on which we call the method
determines which method will be called.
In C++, if we want dynamic binding
to be used, that is, if we want the
contents of the variable
rather than its type determine which
method to call,
then we must explicitly declare
in the program that the method
must be dynamically bound.
And this is done by declaring
this method
as virtual.
For dynamic binding to take place,
we thus have to declare this method
as virtual, but it must also
work via a reference or a pointer.
This is the case here, un is a
reference to the object passed as a parameter.
In C++, we must indicate explicitly to the compiler
that a method
can use dynamic binding.
And this is done by declaring it
as virtual.
This declaration must be made in
the most general class
defining this method, that is, at
the highest
in the hierarchy, in the original prototype.
So in the case of our example,
in the Personnage class.
And to make a method virtual in C++,
one simply prepends
the prototype of the method with
the virtual keyword.
Note that any override in subclasses
of a method
that was declared as virtual in the superclass
will also be considered as being
virtual even if we don't add the virtual
keyword
before its prototype.
So basically, if I have a superclass,
A, containing a particular method
m, and if I have a subclass B which
overrides this method.
If in the A superclass
the method m was declared as virtual,
then it will also be virtual
in the subclass
even if the keyword isn't
explicitly included.
If we go back to our first example,
if we want our method to
benefit from dynamic binding,
then we should declare the method
as virtual
in the superclass.
But is this really our original example?
If you have been attentive,
you may have noticed
that the example that you
see now
is a variation on the example
presented initially.
A variation in which the arguments
of the faire_rencontrer function
are passed by value.
We deliberately made this change
to show you the effect
of not using a reference or a pointer
on dynamic binding.
The problem is that when we
pass by value
the Guerrier object will be copied
into a variable of type Personnage.
The rencontrer method will thus not
apply to the original instance,
but to a copy of the instance in a
variable of type Personnage.
Essentially, if we had an object of
type Guerrier in the variable g,
once it is copied into the variable un,
which is of type Personnage,
it will then be considered only
as a Personnage.
Personnage doesn't have a member
variable for a weapon, for example.
The object contained in the
variable un
is indeed of type Personnage.
Therefore, even if the rencontrer method
is virtual,
and can thus benefit from dynamic
binding,
since the object contained in the
variable is of type Personnage,
then the rencontrer method of
Personnage will always be
called here.
As we mentioned in the previous episode,
for dynamic binding to be able to
take place,
two conditions must be verified.
The first is that the methods must be
virtual, as we have just discussed,
and the second is that these
virtual methods
must apply to real instances
via references or pointers.
If we choose to pass by
reference,
then when we pass the arguments,
we will not copy them
into objects of type Personnage;
we will simply indicate that un
is another name for the variable g.
This way, we allow the virtual method
to work on the actual instance.
By allowing a virtual method to
work on the real instance,
we obtain the behavior we want,
namely, dynamic binding.
As we said earlier, it is the combination
of using references
and making the methods virtual
that we obtained the desired result.
Here of course, we could make do with
a constant reference as parameter
since the faire_rencontrer function
does not modify its parameter un.
This is how we should write the code
in order to obtain
dynamic binding in the context
of this example.
So, to allow a virtual method to
operate on
the real instance, it is possible to use
references.
We can also use pointers
as the following example will show.
And this time, to switch things up,
here is a zoological example where
we have a subclass Dauphin (TN: means
"Dolphin") inheriting from
a Mammifere superclass (TN: means
"Mammal"). Each of these classes
has a default, explicit constructor and
a destructor.
Mammals, in general, have a default method
for eating (TN: "manger").
Dolphins have a specific method
for this action.
And the same goes for the methods
allowing the mammals or dolphins
to move (TN: "avancer").
Here is a small main program which
uses the class
hierarchy  that you have just seen.
Let's study its execution step-by-step
to see what output it will produce.
The first line of the program declares a
variable named lui (TN: "lui" means "him"),
which is a pointer to a Mammifere.
This variable takes the address of an
object of type Dauphin allocated dynamically.
The object of type Dauphin, allocated
dynamically, is constructed using
the default constructor of the
Dauphin class.
The lui variable thus contains the
address of an object of type Dauphin.
The default constructor of the Dauphin
class was used here
to construct this object.
This is the default constructor,
as defined in the Dauphin subclass.
Note that the constructor of a subclass
always invokes
the constructor of the superclass.
If it doesn't do so explicitly, then
it is the default constructor
of the superclass that is called.
This means that, before the "Coui, Couic !"
message is displayed,
the message "Un nouveau mammifère est
né!" is displayed (TN: means "new mammal born").
The execution of this line of code will
therefore output the following:
A new mammal is born! Why?
Because the default constructor
of the Dauphin class
implicitly called the default constructor
of the Mammifere class.
The constructor of the Mammifere
superclass was invoked
by Dauphin's one.
When its execution is done,
the body of Dauphin's constructor will
be executed,
producing the following output.
Second line.
We apply to the object pointed
to by the lui pointer,
that is, this object here,
the avancer method.
Note that here, since we use pointers,
we allow the method to be applied
to the actual instance pointed to
by the object,
and thus to have polymorphism.
Remember that the notation
"lui->avancer()"
is equivalent to writing
"(*lui).avancer()"
We access the contents of
the object pointed to by lui,
and call the avancer method on
this object.
The avancer method is defined
as virtual in the superclass
and overridden in the
Dauphin subclass.
Since we allow this virtual method
to act directly on the actual instance
via the pointer,
dynamic binding is used and it
is Dauphin's avancer method
which is called.
Therefore, the message "Je nage" (TN: means
"I am swimming") will be displayed here,
and at this stage, we have
the following output.
Let's move on to the next line, where
the manger method is called
on the object pointed to by lui.
The manger method is indeed
overridden in the Dauphin class but careful,
unlike the previous case, the
manger method
was not declared as virtual in the
superclass.
The manger method is indeed
called via a pointer
but this is only one of the
two ingredients
necessary for dynamic binding.
The pointer is there,
but the method is not virtual,
which means that we cannot have
dynamic binding.
In this case, it is the type of
the variable which wins.
lui is a pointer to Mammifere,
so the object it points to is perceived
as an object of type Mammifere.
Static binding thus occurs in this case
and it is the manger method of Mammifere
which will be called here.
The output after execution
of this statement will thus be:
"Miam... croumf !", which is the message
displayed by Mammifere's manger method.
Let's go to the next line.
"delete lui" means that we free the
memory area allocated
dynamically at this stage of the program.
This means, basically, that we recover
the memory area associated
with the object of type Dauphin
previously allocated.
"delete lui" causes this object's life to end
and since its lifetime is up,
the destructor is called.
But which destructor exactly
is called?
If we examine the code of the
Mammifere class,
we can see that the destructor was
declared as virtual.
This means that this method, if called
via a pointer
for example, will benefit from
dynamic binding.
The destructor is indeed called via a pointer,
which means that
dynamic binding will take place for
destruction as well.
The object will be perceived according
to its real nature,
that is, as a Dauphin,
and it is Dauphin's destructor
which will be called,
causing the following output.
We learned in a previous episode that the
order in which destructors are called
is the inverse of the orders
for constructors.
So to create an object of type Dauphin,
the constructor of the Mammifere supercalss
was called, then Dauphin's constructor.
For destruction, it is the opposite,
we will first call Dauphin's
constructor,
then Mammifere's destructor.
Now, let's imagine that the destructor
of the Mammifere class
was not declared as virtual.
Since the destructor was not declared
as virtual in the Mammifere class,
the call that is made here cannot be
dynamically bound.
This means that the type of the variable
will win
for the choice of the destructor method,
and it is this destructor here that
will be called rather than this one.
So essentially, if the destructor
for Mammifere
had not been declared as virtual
in our example,
then only Mammifere's destructor
would have been invoked
and Dauphin's one would not have been.
Meaning that the object that was
allocated dynamically in our program
with a type of Dauphin would be
only partially destroyed.
Only the part of the Dauphin which is
a Mammifere would have been destroyed here.
If the object of type Dauphin
dynamically allocated here
had required a certain amount of
resources,
then these resources would not have
been freed correctly.
To summarize, when a virtual
method is called via a reference
or a pointer, that is, when both of these
ingredients are present,
then the choice of the method will be made
based on the actual type of the instance.
This is known as dynamic binding.
But watch out, here are a few important
points to consider regarding virtuality
in the context of construction
and destruction.
As we discussed in the example of
Mammifere and Dauphin,
to avoid having a partial destruction only,
it is recommended to always declare
destructors as virtual.
However, since a constructor is always
designed to
initialize the current instance,
it cannot be virtual.
If it calls virtual methods,
then the virtual aspect of these
methods will simply be ignored.
This is an advanced concept -- let's see
what it means in a concrete example.
Here is an somewhat academic example
that will explain
what happens in this case
where we have a superclass A of which
the B subclass inherits.
Both classes have a method m which
happens to be virtual
and is hence overridden
in the B subclass.
When we execute this line of code,
the default constructor for
the A class is called, and calls in turn
the method f.
The method f is called on the this object,
which is of type A,
and so we will of course invoke the f
method of the A class,
which will display the following.
On the second line, we create
an object of type B.
There is no explicit constructor in the
B class,
and so the default constructor
will be invoked,
and it will invoke the default constructor
of the superclass.
The f method therefore now applies to
a "this" object of type B.
However, the virtual aspect of the method
is completely ignored
in a constructor.
So this aspect is not taken into account,
and it is still the current class's
method which is called.
Therefore, when this second line
is executed,
we will also have the following output.
The next line of code declared a
variable pa of type pointer-to-A,
and initializes is with the address
of the object b.
The f method is then called on the object
pointed to by the pa pointer,
which is an object of type B.
Here, both ingredients necessary
to dynamic binding are present.
We have a virtual method f which
is invoked via a pointer.
The f method will thus be chosen
depending on the real nature of
the instance pointed to,
and it is the method of the B class
which will be invoked.
So we will have a different message here,
when this last line of code is executed.
Here, we do indeed have polymorphic
behavior on the part of the f method
since we invoked it outside of
a constructor.
However here, the polymorphic aspect
was completely ignored.
And this concludes our episode on
virtual methods which are, in C++,
the basic building blocks for
polymorphism.