Welcome to this lesson on MEMS
success stories.
Before we go into detail of the
various micro nanofabrication
methods, let's have a quick look
what MEMS are and how we are
actually using them day by day.
We have invited for this lesson
a guest lecturer who is a real
expert in the field so let
me introduce Dr. Julien Arcamone.
He is responsible for the industrial
partnerships and business
development in MEMS within
the Silicon Components Division
of CEA-LETI in Grenoble, France
one of the largest MEMS R&D
centres and foundries.
Julien will show you some selected
MEMS examples, he will in particular
highlight how micro fabrication has
enabled such systems to become so
performing and cost efficient
to manufacture.
So Julien, the floor is yours.
Thank you Jurgen for the introduction.
Hello, it's my honor and pleasure
to give this lesson on successful
MEMS products.
Let's start right away.
So maybe not everyone has noticed
yet, but MEMS have become ubiquitous
in our daily life.
One example is a multiplicity of
MEMS devices inside smartphones.
This scheme depicts a tear down view
of the iPhone 6 and the various MEMS
devices present inside it.
In this lesson, I'd like to focus on
3 applications.
First accelerometers, so
acceleration sensors.
Second, microphones
Third, BAW resonators and filters
BAW stands for Bulk Acoustic
Wave Resonators.
Let's start with the accelerometers.
Technically speaking, the most
classical device is a capacitive
comb-drive accelerometer
with electrostatic actuation
and capacitive detection by means of
a set of lateral combs.
The physical principle
is rather simple.
This sensor detects a capacitance
variation induced by an acceleration.
Let's illustrate how this
device works.
This scheme depicts a top view of a
proof mass, which is sensitive to
accelerations around the X axis.
This proof mass acts as an inertial
mass. It can move laterally and is
anchored in 4 points.
In this picture, the movable
suspended parts are in grey
the anchored or fixed
ones are in black.
Typically a proof mass is between
100 and 200 microns wide and long.
This proof mass is equipped with a
set of lateral comb fingers.
They all have an opposite and
mechanically fixed comb finger.
The fact of using combs provides
a larger capacitive area which turns
into an enhanced capacitive readout.
Let's zoom in on a few fingers
In this example, 4 capacitors
are depicted.
Always a capacitance C, and a gap G.
The 2 ones on the left are polarized
at plus V IN.
The 2 others at minus V IN.
Let's suppose for example an
acceleration towards the right side.
It induces a counter force
towards the left
which makes the proof mass and it's
combs move towards the left too.
So let's show it again.
Consequently as the gap narrows
the capacitance of the 2 left
capacitors becomes C plus Delta C
The capacitance of the 2 right ones
becomes C minus Delta C
as the gap widens.
Overall this provides a differential
readout and the output voltage
is approximately equal to
Delta C over C.
The key parameter in terms of
sensitivity and resolution  also
name d limit of detection is a gap G
which must be minimized as
much as possible.
It is generally in the
range of 1 micron.
This video is recorded inside a
scanning electron microscope.
So the images here are recorded with
an increasing zoom.
Here you can see the  polysilicon
structures, with the moving parts
in particular the combs moving in
front of the reference electrodes.
So the motion is the combination
of the electrostatic attraction and
the restoring force of the springs.
Basically here the motion is in the
range of a few microns naturally.
This is just an example of layout
but of course many designs are
possible to make the same function.
Let's take an example of fabrication
process of such capacitive
accelerometers.
This scheme depicts a cross
sectional view at the
end of the process.
The MEMS layer can be either a
monocrystalline silicon layer
if an SOI substrate is used
or a polycrystalline silicon layer
also named polysilicon.
The routing of the mechanical
structures is made with partially
suspended polysilicon interconnects.
the mechanical structures are
released by removing the underlying
silicon oxide sacrificial layer
by wet or vapor HF etching.
HF stands for hydrofluoric acid.
The MEMS active parts are
encapsulated by a polysilicon
thin-film packaging which provides
an hermetic cavity at ambient
pressure protecting the MEMS from
moisture, humidity and dust.
The input and output signals
are brought and picked up through
metal pads, here for example.
Or here.
Let's also mention that some silicon
structures are on top of
silicon nitride pillars in order to
electrically isolate them
from the substrate.
One of the key steps
is the Deep Reactive ION Etching
abbreviated as DRIE
of the silicon MEMS layer.
This etching has to provide vertical
and smooth side walls
with a high aspect ratio
of at least 20.
The thicker a silicon MEMS layer
the wider is the gap due to the
maximum affordable aspect ratio,
Typically the silicon MEMS layer is
around 20 microns thick
and the gap is around 1 micron wide.
Let's zoom on a particular area.
This scanning electron microscope
abbreviated as SEM
image depicts a set of movable
and fixed comb fingers.
They feature all the necessary
characteristics I mention.
They have vertical and smooth
side walls and small gaps.
So let's talk about application now.
First, which MEMS companies sell
these kinds of devices?
Let's site Bosch, STMicro Electronics
InvenSense, Analog Devices, etc.
As I mentioned before accelerometers
are present inside smartphones
in particular for screen rotation
and for gaming.
I like to mention another use case
inertial MEMS are also widely used
in automotive for various purposes.
Let's take the example of NXP's
HARMEMS technology
Such accelerometers are implemented
to detect front or side crash
in order to trigger airbags
In the left picture the car contains
5 so called accelerometer satellites
or modules.
At the center of the car an airbag
electronic control unit, ECU
also senses crashes and
triggers airbags.
Let's move to example 2
microphones in smartphones.
Generally what is called a
MEMS microphone
is a dual-die component.
The MEMS microphone itself
most of them are based on
capacitive  detection
and its ASIC readout circuit.
ASIC as you may know stands for
Application Specific
Integrated Circuit.
They are connected one to another
by wire bonding.
MEMS and ASIC dies are both housed
inside a package which has
a sound port, either on the top side
or at the bottom of the package.
This scheme depicts a bottom port
component.
The package has multiple functions
of course as in all MEMS. it
protects the device and provides
a crucial electromagnetic shielding.
In addition to that the back chamber
plays a very important role on the
acoustic performance.
The larger it is, the higher the
signal to noise ratio,
abbreviated as SNR.
Although piezoelectric microphones
are emerging, capacitive ones are by
far the most widely used.
How do they work?
Basically there are 2 suspended parts
a moveable membrane, here in red
and a fixed back plate
here in purple.
Both form a variable capacitor which
senses the motion of a moveable
membrane caused by any incoming
sound wave.
In this example the sound comes
from the bottom and the package is
not depicted.
To repeat again, the sound wave
generates a pressure differential
between the front and back chamber
consequently the membrane is deformed
and this results in a
capacitance variation.
The membrane contains ventilation
holes, not depicted here, to allow
the compressed air of the back
chamber to flow out.
The back plate contains perforation
holes basically to transmit the
sound to the back chamber.
The membrane diameter is typically
in the order of 1 millimeter.
Regarding the microphone bandwidth
it has to cover the human ear
bandwidth, so from 20Hz up to 20KHz.
Let's turn to the fabrication
process of such sensors.
This example is quite representative
of all capacitive MEMS microphones.
Generally the process is a mix of
surface and bulk micromachining,
The first critical process module
is a deposition of the low-stress
polysilicon membrane on top of
a SiO2 layer.
The second critical process module
is a successive deposition of a
thick polysilicon layer
and of a highly tensile
silicon nitrate layer.
These 2 layers form the back plate
which must be rigid enough
to constitute a fixed
reference electrode.
Finally, metal interconnects are
deposited in pattern.
Another important step consists
in realizing a deep cavity
from the back side.
It's obtained either by wet etch
for instance with KOH
or DRIE.
The first option is cheaper
but side walls are inclined.
The second one, with deep reactive
ion etching, represented here
is more expensive, but side walls
are vertical, which provides
a larger cavity.
The final critical step
is a membrane release by removal
of sacrificial SiO2 layer by
wet or vapor etch.
Anti stiction control is crucial
during this step.
So let's talk about application now.
First, which MEMS companies sell
these kinds of devices?
Let's site Knowles, Infineon, OMRON,
STMicro, InvenSense, etc..
As I mentioned before microphones
are present inside smartphones.
The image below illustrates the
number of MEMS microphones inside
the iPhone as a function of
its generation.
Nowadays, the iPhone 6 contains
4 microphones.
Some are used to pick up the voice
others for the cancellation of
surrounding parasitic noise
and the least main function
is for the hands free kit.
Let's move to example 3.
BAW resonators in smartphones.
As I said, BAW stands for Bulk
Acoustic Wave resonators.
The resonance frequency generally
in the range of the gigahertz.
In terms of structure, BAW uses a
piezoelectric layer made of
aluminium nitride most of the time
sandwiched between a bottom and
a top electrode.
usually made of molybdenum.
In terms of resonance mode
a thickness mode, either with
longitudinal or shared vibration
is operated.
In the longitudinal mode, the
resonator expands and contracts
all the time in the direction
of its thickness.
Its resonance frequency is half the
velocity of sound
divided by the resonator thickness.
The velocity of sound is the square
root of the young modulus
divided by the density.
With a thickness of 1 micron
approximately the resonance is
around 5 gigahertz.
BAW resonators are used to implement
band-pass filters, I'll get back to
this in the next slide.
In this sense the so called
KT square coupling coefficient
is critical in terms of filter
bandwidth and insertion loss.
The KT square is given by the ratio
between the difference between the
resonance frequency and the
antiresonance frequency
divided by the resonance frequency.
In fact, the KT square depends on
piezoelectric material properties
therefore the deposition and further
process of the piezoelectric layer
is crucial.
How can we build a filter using
BAW resonators?
Basically by implementing a
ladder filter architecture.
It's unit cell that can be
replicated n times
contains 2 BAW resonators
a series one and a shunt
connected to ground.
Let's explain how it works by
observing the filter response.
At the center of the slide
the frequency response of the shunt
resonator is depicted at the top.
The one of the series resonator
is depicted here
And this is the response
on the whole filter.
Please note that the shunt resonator
response is shifting down to lower
frequencies, such that the shunt
antiresonance coincides with
the series resonance.
In state A, both resonators are
far from the resonance frequency.
Therefore, they both behave
as capacitors.
In state B, the series resonator
is still far from resonance.
And it behaves as a capacitor.
While the shunt one is at resonance
in other words its impedance
is minimum.
In fact, in this state, its
impedance is equal to its
so called motional resistance
which is less than 1 ohm.
As a consequence the output node
is almost grounded and there
is no signal transmission.
In state C the series resonator
is at resonance. In other words
its impedance is minimum and
of less than 1 ohm.
In the meantime the shunt one is at
its antiresonance.
In other words its at its maximum
impedance and it behaves as an
open circuit.
As a consequence the impedance
between input and output nodes
is minimum and a signal transmission
is maximum.
In state D the series resonator
is at its antiresonance, in other
words, at its maximum impedance.
And it behaves as an open circuit.
The shunt one is far from resonance
and behaves as a capacitor.
As a consequence, the impedance
between input and output nodes
is maximum and signal transmission
is minimum.
In state E, the situation is very
similar to state A.
Both resonators behave as capacitors.
So this is basically a summary
of how a ladder filter using
BAW resonators works.
Let's turn to the fabrication
process of BAW.
Let's first mention that there are 2
types of BAW due to the fact that
there are 2 main approaches  of
acoustic wave confinement.
So called FBAR, thin-Film Back
Acoustic wave Resonators
are suspended resonators
over an air gap.
So called SMR, Solidly Mounted
Resonators, consist of unreleased
resonators, so I mean not suspended
located over a Bragg mirror that
reflects back the waves.
We will focus on this type.
This is a cross sectional view
of an SMR, processed on a
high resistivity silicon substrate
You can see the Bragg mirrors here
which are made of tungsten plates
surrounded by SiO2
The first critical process module
consists in depositing an aluminium
nitride layer by physical vapor
deposition on top of a properly
oriented molybdenum bottom electrode.
This sputtering technique allows
obtaining first, a precise and
uniform thickness, have in mind
that the resonance frequency is
inversely proportional to the
thickness, and second
good piezoelectric properties which
result in high KT square.
The top electrode is also made of
molybdenum.
Another important step is the mass
loading of shunt resonators.
In fact, shunt and series resonators
are identical by design.
Then this mass deposition on top of
the shunt resonators allows for
quickly decreasing the resonance
frequency so that the antiresonance
coincides with the series resonator
resonance as I explained in the
previous slide.
The second critical process step
is wafer-scale ion beam trimming.
By locally moving some material
the ion beam allows precisely
adjusting the resonance frequencies
of each series and shunt resonators
It's very important that each filter
has the same bandwidth and center
frequency.
The resonators have a silicon
nitride passivation, in green
and are capped with a thin-film
packaging, in pink
to provide them with an hermetic and
clean cavity at ambient pressure.
This optical microscope image shows
the top view of a filter chip at the
end of the fabrication process.
Basically the white squares
and rectangles
are metallic contact pads.
And the coloured squares are BAW
resonators which have a typical
150 by 150 square micron area.
Depending on whether they are mass
loaded or not, I mean series or
shunt, the resonators colour
is different.
So let's talk about application now.
First, which MEMS companies sell
these kinds of devices?
Let's site Avaga that produces FBARs
and Qorvo and TDK-EPCOS that
produce SMR's.
BAW band-pass filters have become
a key element of RF front-end
modules of smartphones.
Such modules are essentially the
RF stage located between the antenna
and the analog digital convertor.
In this context BAW filters are used
to select a given telecom band.
In green you can see all the filters
present in this example of
front end module.
And for example the iPhone 6S
contains more than 20 BAW filters
dies either for 4G or LTE connection
or for Wi-Fi connection.
I'd like to wrap up this lesson.
We've analysed 3 examples of
commercially successful MEMS devices
All these devices have been sold in
the hundreds of millions of units
and all of them rely on advanced
micro and nano fabrication techniques
that you will see in the upcoming
lessons of this MOOC.
Thanks for your attention.