Welcome to this lesson in micro
and nano fabrication.
The picture behind me shows
a colorful SEM image
of a bi-morph MEMS activator.
And in the next few minutes,
I will show how it was fabricated
in our clean room at EPFL.
Although it does not involve all
possible fabrication steps
that are nowadays available
in advanced MEMS processes.
It initiates you the students
to the basics of a process flow.
As you will see, the fabrication
is a well defined sequence
of lithography, thin film deposition,
as well as wet and dry etching.
In my left hand,
I'm holding a silicon wafer
before the fabrication.
And in my right hand, you see
a similar wafer containing
hundreds, if not thousands, of MEMS
devices like in the background.
But before diving into
microfab aspects,
let's briefly recall how a thermal
mechanical device, or bi-morph,
actually works.
A bi-morph is a device that can take
two or more shapes.
'Bi' means 2 in Latin, and 'morph'
means shape in Greek.
On the right side you see a typical
example of a bi-morph
made by 2 thin films.
In our case,
SiO2 in green,
and Chromium in blue.
Since both materials
have very different
thermal expansion coefficients α,
they induce a bending when
the temperature changes.
When you apply a voltage
to the Chrome layer...
you induce a current
that will heat up, this...
cantilever, and by the temperature
change will induce bending.
The curvature radius of the bending
can be expressed as
by a formula shown here.
Where the radius of curvature
is described by β
times the difference in thermal
expansion coefficients
of the 2 materials, Chrome and
Silicon dioxide
and the temperature change.
β is a constant, as a function of
the thickness of the device
and its Young's modulus.
Other formula
to describe the system are
the spring constant
of the cantilever, and
the resonance frequency.
And here's a list of all
important parameters
that can be used to describe
the system.
In the accompanying documents
you can see how this formula
can be derived from basic physics.
The process flow is typically shown
schematically by a sequence
of cross section figures.
In the case of the bi-morph
cantilevers,
there are 7 major process steps.
The representation is
in principle sufficient
to show the effect of added
thin films,
and the effect of wet and dry
etching on each layer.
Such a document will accompany
the wafer during the process.
You know always exactly at which
step of the process the wafer is.
And what process parameters
have been applied to each wafer.
Now let's have a look at each
of the 7 steps
in detail, 1 by 1.
The first step is to grow
a Silicon dioxide layer,
which will be one of the 2
bi-morph materials.
Before the actual oxidation,
the wafer is thoroughly cleaned.
This process is called RCA cleaning,
which is an industry standard
since the 1960s,
and consists of a couple of steps.
Wet oxidation is then carried out
in the furnace
with oxygen rich atmosphere.
Silicon on the surface is thereby
transformed
into a Silicon dioxide layer
that grows with time,
while consuming
the underlying silicon.
To form a 1.5 micrometre
thick SiO2 layer,
we typically oxidise the silicon
wafer during 6 hours
at 1100 degrees C.
Here you see a couple of
silicon wafers,
100 millimetre in diameter
or 4 inch.
The centre is a silicon wafer
without any silicon dioxide,
looks grey, and here is
a couple of
silicon wafers with different
silicon dioxide thicknesses
ranging from 100 nanometre,
up to 10 micrometre.
We can see clearly the difference
in colour,
which is due to the interference
of the dielectric thin film on
the silicon wafer.
With experience, one can actually
indicate already what thickness
the wafer is.
However, to measure precisely, one
will then rely on an ellipsometer.
Step 2 is the physical vapor
deposition
of the chromium layer.
Which is the second material in
the bi-morph cantilever.
This layer serves 2 purposes.
First, as a thin conductor, it will
allow driving a current to heat up
the surface that will result in
the bi-morph activation.
Second, chromium is chosen before
other metals
because it has very different
thermal expansion coefficient
than silicon dioxide.
This mismatch will induce a very
pronounced bi-morph effect when heated.
In this particular case,
we deposit
a 500 nanometre thick chromium layer
using an electron beam evaporator
equipment.
And here on the right side,
you see 2 photos.
The left one shows a silicon wafer
with the 1.5 micrometer
silicon dioxide
appearing again, colorful.
And the right photo shows the same
wafer,
after having been coated with
500 nanometer chromium.
Now the wafer looks again like
a reflecting mirror.
This photo shows the PVD thermal
evaporator equipment
in our clean room.
With the scientist loading evaporating
material at the lower part.
The substrate wafers will be mounted
on the upper part,
which gives a long source substrate
distance for optimal film uniformity.
Once the substrates are loaded,
the door will be closed, and the air
will be pumped out
to install the high vacuum.
Step 3 shows the first
photo-lithography step
that has to go to pattern the chrome
layer into micro heaters
that are subsequently used
to heat up the cantilever
and to induce its bending.
Photo-lithography is the process
step that creates
the pattern in the photoresist
by local elimination through
an exposure mask.
The exposed resist is developed
and remaining resist pattern
protects the underlying material
from being etched.
So on these 2 photos,
you see on the left side,
a computer drawing of
the design layout,
where we see 4 heater loops
in chrome.
On the mask, and on the right side,
we see the fabricated results.
So what you see here in brownish,
is the pattern photo-resist
on top of the chrome layer.
This is the step after
the lithography
before actually
the chrome etching.
In this video sequence,
you see how the photo-resist is
spin coated
on the wafer substrate.
To this end,
the wafer is spun at high speed
and the resist is dispensed
in the center.
This forms a uniformed resist layer
over the entire wafer surface.
We will see details, how thick?
And how uniformed
the resist film is?
In the dedicated lesson
on lithography.
Once the photo-resist is patterned,
we can now proceed
to etch the chrome.
To this end, we use a dedicated
chromate solution as shown
on the upper right corner.
The wafer with the photo-resist
pattern is placed
into the chromate solution
after the chrome has completely
etched through,
a strong color contrast appears
on the wafer.
At this point, the photo-resist
can be removed
by a so called stripping process
followed by thorough rinsing
and cleaning.
Here you can see 2 photographs.
On the left side you see
the situation,
after the lithography, with the
photo-resist
on the chrome.
And on the right side,
you see the situation
after the chrome etching,
and the photo-resist stripping.
(INAUDIBLE) nicely,
the well defined chrome pattern
that will define the micro heaters
on top of the SiO2 layer.
Now that the chrome is patterned,
we can structure the underlying
SiO2 layer to carve out
the cantilever shape.
This step also defines the shape
of the anisotropic silicon etch
to release the beam
from the substrate.
Before UV exposure, the photo mask
is aligned to the first one
by means of a so called
mask aligner.
The left image shows the cut
mask lay out,
where as the right image, shows
the optical photo
of the 4 cantilevers.
One can actually see clearly
the 2 layers now.
The shape, of the cantilever in
transparent photo-resist
defined in the second
lithography.
And the chromium, that was defined
in the first lithography step.
This allows checking that
the alignment
of the mask is within
the tolerant specifications.
The photo-resist that we patterned
in the previous steps
serves now to protect the silicon
dioxide during the etching
in buffered hydrochloric acid,
BHF.
This etchant has SiO2 etch rate
of about 80 nanometer per minute.
And the etch selectivity to silicon
is almost infinite.
Thus for etching the 1.5 micrometer
thick silicon dioxide,
we typically need about
20 minutes etch time
which stops naturally at
the silicon surface.
Be very cautious.
BHF is dangerous
and strict safety measures
have to be applied.
After the SiO2 etch,
the photo-resist can be stripped,
exposing again the chrome layer.
This video sequence shows
a clean room scientist,
who puts a batch of wafers into
the BHF etch pod,
to etch the silicon dioxide.
Please notice the serious protection
that is needed.
On this right photo,
you can see now the result
after the fabrication, where we can
see in dark grey
the contours of the silicon
dioxide cantilevers
still on the silicon.
And in light grey, the chromium
heater pattern
that runs on top of the 4
cantilever shapes.
The final step releases
the cantilever beam
from the underlying silicon by
anisotropic under etching.
While there are several options
that can be used to etch silicon,
such as dry plasma silicon
etching.
We use here the anisotropic wet
etching of silicon
done in Potassium hydroxide,
also called KOH.
This method is very versatile,
and widely used for
these type of structures.
The silicon 1,0,0 plane has an etch
rate of about 20 micrometers per hour
in KOH.
Whereas the 1,1,1 silicon planes
are hardly etched at all
which allows creating the
well defined (INAUDIBLE) etch structure
in the shape of a truncated
inverted pyramid.
The SiO2 thereby serves as
an etch mask to define the borders
of the etch structure.
With the largest cantilever beam
80 micrometers wide,
we need about 2 hours to under etch
for the micrometers from each side.
When the under etching is completed,
and the cantilever released
from the silicon,
the intrinsic stress in the SiO2
chromium sandwich layer
induces an out of plane bending
of the cantilever.
On the right side,
we see 2 photographs.
showing the fabricated bi-morph
cantilevers.
On the left, an optical microscope
image taken from above.
Where we see nicely
the square etch,
that has been etched by the KOH
into the silicon.
And the 4 cantilevers in the corner
that have been under etched.
Cantilevers themselves are not
easily visible
because they are pre-stressed,
and pre-bent largely, so they're
out of focus of the microscope.
To see them better,
we're going to the scanning electron
microscope.
Where we see now nicely
the cantilevers in all details.
We also see nicely,
the square that has been etched
by the KOH into the silicon.
The cantilevers are largely bent
due to the stress
between the SiO2,
and the chromium.
Please note that at this point
of time,
there's no heating applied. So this
stress, is the intrinsic stress
due to fabrication, and not an
actuated bending.
The bi-morph thermo-mechanical
micro actuators are now ready
for characterization.
For this, we use a probe station
that can align micro needles to
the contact pads
to apply electrical signals
to various devices
on the chip or wafer,
and to measure (INAUDIBLE).
In our case, we have measured
the resistance
of our chrome heaters, and they
are (INAUDIBLE)
in the order of about 50 ohm.
These 4 optical images,
show bi-morph device under various
DC currents.
Please remember, that the initial
bending
of the cantilever is due to
the intrinsic stress
and occurs already
at room temperature.
It is not due to heating.
Heating in fact will bend
the lever downwards.
From left to right,
the voltage is increased from
0 to about 6 volts,
which gives us an increasing current
as shown here.
The current heats up
the chrome layer
by Joule heating.
Already in photo 2,
We can see that the bi-morph
has moved downwards
a bit.
This actuation effect
is more pronounced
in this photo,
where we also start seeing
a color change.
This color change is due to
the heat
generated in the chrome
resistor,
which emits radiation.
Increasing the current further,
we can see that the bi-morph
starts to glow.
Running this experiment for a very
long time will damage the device
like a fuse.
Here you can see a movie
that shows
the actuation of the bi-morph
cantilever
driven by DC voltage.
Using the same voltage range
as shown in the slide before,
from 0 to 6 volt.
You can see in real time
when ramping up the voltage
and current,
that the cantilever
starts bending down.
And at very high current levels,
the cantilever starts to glow,
and ultimately might burn
like a fuse
if the experiment is run too long.
And here you can see, the actuation
of the bi-morph and the voltages
changed manually.
Details of the frequency response
is provided by
the accompanying documents.
Please have a look, as they provide
useful information on the bandwidth
in which such a device can operate.
As you can guess, this is not
only a function
of the mechanical resonance
frequency of the cantilever,
but also of the heat dissipation
away from the cantilever.
This concludes this chapter on
the fabrication
of the bi-morph cantilever.
I hope you learned how one can get
from a blank silicon wafer,
hundreds and thousandths of micro
devices,
by series of micro fabrication
steps.
In the next chapters,
my colleague and I will present
technical details
on the different fabrication
steps.