We have seen that many
identical microelectronic devices
can be realized on
a single wafer
which is a technology that is
at the basis of many
high performance applications
in nearly every domain
of our daily life.
The reproducibility
of microfabrication indeed
is a key factor
for economic realization
of any consumer product.
Therefore, these devices
are most of the time realized
in a clean room environment
where experimental
and manufacturing conditions
are reproducible
and very strictly controlled.
In this lesson, we will introduce
a few of the basic aspects
of the design of
and work in a clean room.
We will start by discussing
different contamination problems
that may arise when one
wants to develop
a microfabrication process.
We will the different sources
that are at the basis
of contamination and that can result
in failure of devices.
We will introduce different options
for creating an environment
with clean air
and for clean room construction.
Finally, we will give an example
of a clean room
by introducing the center of micro
and nano technology at EPFL.
Different types of contamination
exist which all can compromise
successful realization
of a microfabricated device.
The first problem is posed
by the presence particles in the air
which, when they have the size
of the features
of the microfabricated structure,
can result in failure
of the device.
This drawing shows as an example
two micron wide metal lines
which can be realized using
a thin film deposition technique.
When during deposition,
micro particles are situated
on the substrate and when
they have this size,
they can give rise
to these connected metal structure
like shown here.
Another contamination problem
is that of iron impurities.
If one works with semiconductor
circuits,
the operation of device can be
severely disturbed
when unknown metal impurities
are present in the semi conductor.
Especially so-called Mobile
Ion Contaminants
or MICs,  most problems.
These contaminants are present
in most of the chemicals
that are used for microfabrication
of a device.
And when incorporated
in the silicon,
they can migrate to a sensitive area
where they can cause devise failure
even a long time after fabrication.
This implies that chemicals
should be as pure as possible.
The table here shows
metal impurities
that are present in a typical
wet chemical
that is used in the clean room.
More generally, the presence
of trace chemicals,
unwanted chemicals and process water
of insufficient purity,
can result in unwanted
surface etching effects
or deposition effects
which are at origin
of non-uniformities
in microfabrication processes.
If these contamination sources
are present,
they affect the devices
in different ways.
First of all, there is the devise
processing yield.
Like shown in the drawing
on the left,
a change in dimension
or an interruption of device parts
results in non-functional device.
Such failure can be measured
immediately
after microfabrication step
by optical or microscopic inspection
or microscopic inspection.
Some defects are not directly
visible but can be measured
by evaluation
of the devise performance
after completion of
the full microfabrication process.
Usually, electrical testing allows
eliminating devices from the wafers
or chips from the wafer
that are not functional.
Contamination also affects
device reliability
and can cause failure of device
a long time
after it's microfabrication.
An example of such failure can be
the diffusion
of a mobile ion contaminant
in an electronic circuit.
The impurity can migrate
to a sensitive region
on the wafer, a long time
after microfabrication
leading to disfunctioning
of a microelectronic circuit.
An important source
of possible contamination
in a clean room is the air.
Small particles can float in the air
and remain there for a long time.
They're called also aerosols.
The fewer and the smaller particles
are in the air,
the better is the quality
of the clean room.
The quality of a clean room
is therefore characterized
by the clean room
class number
which is the number of particles
above a specified diameter
in a cubic foot of air.
For example in this graph,
we see that the class
thousand clean room
has not more than
thousand particles of half
a micron in size per cubic foot.
A class 10 clean room
has not more than 10
of these particles
in a cubic foot of air.
The lower the class number,
the better the quality
of the clean room is.
As a rule of thumb, particles
that are present in the air
should not exceed half
of the feature size
of the microstructure
to be fabricated.
As examples of air quality,
a normal house room
has a class of 100,000, while
a very large scale integration area
in a cleaning room
should have class 10
for particles of 0.3 micrometer.
A person can produce
in between 100,000
and 1 million particles per minute
which are flakes
of dead hair and skin,
while normal clothing
adds more millions of particles.
It is clear that the person
has to be completely covered
when he is in the clean room.
And he needs to be covered
with a special clean
and dust free tissue.
The photograph on the left
shows the person
wearing special overshoes
which are above
the normal shoes.
The person has gloves, and he wears
an integral clean room suit,
a mask of the mouth
and the nose
and gloves, and glasses
to protect the eyes.
A particular dressing protocol
has to be followed
when someone enters the clean room
to minimize particle contamination.
Such protocol is shown
in the following video.
A person who in a clean room, first,
takes care of not entering dust
or contamination via shoes.
There's a particular way
of entering.
Before the barrier, the environment
is not clean
and going in by this type of motion
during which the shoes are covered
with a clean protective coating,
ensures that no contamination
is released from the shoes
into the clean room.
Next, follows putting on a coat
where by one,
assures that the sleeves
do not touch the ground.
Then follows putting on this type
of overshoes to further
protect the clean room
from contamination
originating from the feet.
Then follows putting on a mask
for covering the heads and the hair
and a mask that covers
nose and mouth.
Glasses are put on
for eye protection and security.
The last stage is that the operator
puts on gloves
for protection of the hands.
Now finally, he's ready to enter
into the clean room.
A second source of contamination
in a clean room is the water used
for processing the wafers.
All water that is used
has to be treated,
as normal city water contains
dissolved minerals,
particles and bacteria,
which can introduce impurities
or non-uniformities
during microfabrication.
Dissolved ions like sodium
and chlorine ions
can compromise quality
of microfabricated circuits
and can originate from salts
dissolved in the water.
Therefore, the water has
to be deionized
and the degree of ion concentration
in the water
can be measured by measuring
the resistivity of the water.
Indeed, if there are very few
dissolved impurities,
the resistivity of the water
is very large.
Eighty million Ohm centimeters.
If there are more impurities,
resistivity is much lower.
For water used in a very large scale
integration area in a clean room,
the resistivity of minimum
18 M Ohm cm is required.
Deionisation is a chemical process
that uses ion exchange resins
that exchange protons
and hydroxyl ions for dissolved ions
in the water.
After which, protons
and hydroxyl ions recombine
to form a water molecule.
Besides process water,
all process chemicals and gases
that are used in a clean room
should be of high purity.
The most serious impurities
are the metallic
mobile ion contaminants
in chemicals.
And in a chemical concentration
smaller than
one part per million
are desired.
Also common gases that are used
in a clean room such as oxygen,
nitrogen and hydrogen,
and special gases like arsine
and carbon tetrafluoride,
should be very pure.
The gas quality can be classified
according to four criteria.
The percentage of purity
of the gas.
It's water vapor content.
The number of particulates
in the gas,
and the number of metallic ions
in the gas.
The photographs on the left
show the typical infrastructure
for water and gas handling
which is present in proximity
of the clean room.
How does one obtain clean air
with a minimum number of particles?
The first possibility is to do
the processing of the wafers
in individual work stations
with filtered air.
These work stations or hoods
are arranged in rows
and are provided with
high efficiency
particulate arrest
or HEPA filters.
which contains small holes
and a large surface.
Air is blown through such a filter
and a vertical laminar flow
exposes the wafers
that are manipulated here
in the hood.
So the wafers are only exposed
to highly purified air
with the minimum number
of particles.
If chemicals are operated
in the hood,
this is not the right construction
as the toxic fumes of the chemical
would go the operator.
If one needs to manipulate
chemicals,
the hood is of this type.
Part of laminar flow is evacuated
via this line
so that there is no risk
for the operator who is working here
to be in contact with these
chemical vapors
because basically, he's doing
his manipulation here
in this area.
The picture on the left
shows a hood
for manipulation of chemicals.
A drawback of such laminar flow hood
is that the environmental conditions
can change due to the people
that are present in the room
and who can be the origin
of particles underneath the hood.
Therefore, a better but also
a more costly solution,
is to build this HEPA filters
in the ceiling of the room
and provide everywhere
in the room clean conditions.
That is when one makes
really clean room.
This brings us to concept
of the total clean room
where the complete clean room
has purified air
due to the presence
of a continuous laminar flow
from the ceiling to the floor.
Also, through table tops
with perforations, and so on.
Purified air will expose the wafers
and the people,
and any generated particles
will be transported away
through the floor and be purified
before being re-injected
to HEPA filters in a clean room.
The clean room not only
has good purity of the air,
but there is also a tight control
of the temperature
which is essential for operate
and comfort
and for reproducibility
of chemical processes.
Also the humidity
has to be controlled
as the presence of moisture
on wafers
can influence many processes
like at adherence of a photoresist
for example.
Also, smoke needs to be avoided.
As a reactive gas, it's like ozone,
it can interfere with many
chemical processes
that are running in the clean room.
These two photographs show part
of the air-handling infrastructure
of a clean room that is present
above and below the clean room area.
A high quality clean room is
essential for high quality research
in microfabrication related areas.
At EPFL, we have such a clean room
which really is a corner stone
of many of our research
and educational activities.
The following video provides
a glimpse
of the EPFL center
of micro and nano technology.
In this lesson I explained
that the clean room
is  a necessary infrastructure for
the reproducible microfabrication
of miniaturized devices.
Air, process chemicals,
water and gases
should all be of high purity.
We have discussed two approaches
of creating
a clean room environment.
First there was the laminar
flow hood for creating
locally clean air conditions
and next, there was a total
clean room strategy
Finally, I introduce to you
the center of micro
and nano technology at EPFL.