Pedestrians/cars.
So we've just had the choice
of interior/exterior.
And also that of favoring
the pedestrian or the car.
We will see that in the United Arab Emirates
they favor the car, while in Southeast Asia,
in Singapore and Kuala Lumpur,
we find more and more--
and this is new-- that it is the
pedestrian who is favored.
There is also one with city models,
political choices.
What flow of people
should I bring to my global city?
Should I make sure that
they can take a walk in fresh air?
We have just seen interior/exterior.
Will they go out as pedestrians,
or will there be more
drivers in city streets? For example
in Abu Dhabi, as you can see,
very little space, one can
nonetheless find
two people who try, under
umbrellas since it's so hot,
to take a stroll, but one can see that,
while not all paths are bad,
it will be difficult to go from one point
to the next because sidewalks
simply do not exist,
and that one can only cross
vast parking lots where the cars
are taking up all the space.
Ditto, and even more striking,
we can imagine a bad pedestrian.
There too, passing under a walkway
which one can climb to cross the street,
but there is a barrier which
completely blocks it from the road,
so to go from one point to the next
you must go back up,
cross and go down on the other side.
A striking example in Dubai,
where we have a pedestrian crosswalk
which ends, and even if it
were to continue there is no sidewalk,
and even if there were,
one would end up against a wall,
so one can basically do nothing;
one cannot take a walk
in this universe, unless it is
to walk on the road or ground,
and try however one might
to find a place to cross.
On the contrary, Malaysia offers
signs for tourists, of course,
to the important city landmarks,
and directions to them,
even indicating the time
it will take to get there.
So there is a signage put in place
for the pedestrian.
But, not everything is resolved in
Kuala Lumpur, where there are
path markings for the blind,
so sidewalks exist.
One can walk, but there is
still a slight problem,
shall we say, of parking,
which is done precisely
in the same spot where
the pedestrian should walk.
Singapore, old-style Singapore,
rather like Abu Dhabi, where one
had to walk on the road in order to
cross, and now, little by little,
all the overpasses
have been upgraded,
which means that
in the Southeast Asian
model they realize that
there will be pedestrians
who encounter scooters,
who encounter cars, all this
happening with relative ease.
On the contrary, in Dubai, in Abu Dhabi,
all the different flows are separated,
making it extremely difficult for the
pedestrian to get from one point
to another, as the flow is granted
above all to the car.
Another element of our model,
after interior/exterior,
after car/pedestrian, is the question
of homogeneity, or heterogeneity.
In European cities there
is research on homogeneity.
Buildings, and large groupings
of them should be similar.
Such is the rue de Rivoli in Paris,
the hundreds of arcades,
kilometers of the same type of
buildings, always the same type.
The other way is to
assume this heterogeneity.
We will see that, in Dubai
as well as Abu Dhabi,
via their skylines they
seek a homogeneity
of the image they offer to the city.
Not on the level of buildings,
all very different,
but on a global level,
on a general level of city skyline
where one finds
a situation which
seeks homogeneity.
On the contrary, in
Southeast Asia, in Singapore,
Kuala Lumpur, one clearly and
simply assumes this heterogeneity.
Here is an example of homogeneity.
We see more and more
a skyline whose buildings
have the same template, more or less,
the same implementation,
and one tries to be homogeneous,
throughout the region.
This is where it's even more striking,
even if the buildings
are very different, it is the
skyline which emerges.
We can remove the image and see how
what emerges is that of a
relatively homogeneous city.
Again, this time in Dubai,
this research method of
placing one line like this,
across the buildings.
There are two layers of buildings,
shall we say, lined up on the street,
which gives them a homogeneity
which can be perceived
at any given moment. On the contrary,
Singapore or Kuala Lumpur.
We will see the complete homogeneity
of building methods.
We can have, as we have here,
very small buildings.
We can have enormous buildings.
We can have the old, the
contemporary, it matters little.
One assumes this heterogeneity,
and one builds accordingly,
level by level, without seeking
to homogenize the area.
So here we have a vision
which some might find
a bit apocalyptic, with so many
different and disparate elements.
But, it is a heterogeneity
which is totally assumed.
Whereas in other areas,
particularly in Europe, one seeks,
historically, a homogeneity
across the whole of the city area.
There you have it.
Once again we have questions about models
homogenous vs. heterogenous.
The last example, the question
of flux vs. fluidity.
In the model of the U.A.E.,
what is sought is above all flux.
They seek the quantity of people,
the quantity of maximum flow.
Whereas in regions of Southeast Asia,
in Singapore or Kuala Lumpur,
it is exactly the opposite.
It is not the flux which is
of interest, but the fluidity.
Everything should be linked,
it should be possible to arrive
very quickly, to get off
the plane, hop in a cab,
arrive at one's hotel,
and quickly be in one's room,
all the sequences--
for the tourist, of course,
because the goal is to attract
people from outside,
they try to reduce as much as possible
these sequences for the tourist.
Here we have an example,
in Abu Dhabi, where we are not
certain of fluidity but yes of flow.
There are cars everywhere, an enormous
mass of cars, absolutely everywhere.
And the opposite example,
here in Kuala Lumpur,
where we have an aerial monorail
which picks up passengers here,
who get on the monorail.
The cars pass here.
We have crossing flows but it is
very easy, from one's hotel,
to get on the monorail,
travel two stops, get off, take a bus,
hop in a cab and off you go.
So each transfer, each change
of means of transport
is facilitated and is extremely fluid.
And this is political volition,
there in the background,
which ensures that it is
the quickest possible.
So now we will leave Southeast Asia,
and leave the Arab world.
These few elements,
to help us to reflect once again,
on the African city, so let's now
think about Johannesburg,
Dakar, Kinshasa.
Let's think of all these cities
and imagine how they are constructed,
how they are arranged.
Are we in the interior?
The exterior?
The fluidity or flux?
A pedestrian, or a car?
The answer to the question of
the car is relatively simple.
We do not yet have the
example of an African city
specifically set up
around the pedestrian.
Which is no doubt wrong, as the great
majority of people are pedestrians.
We can offer as example
Switzerland: 500 vehicles
per thousand inhabitants,
while Dakar must be
at fewer than 30 vehicles
per thousand inhabitants.
So the great majority
of people get around on foot.
And it is perhaps with these
people that we should begin to reflect,
which is what Singapore did,
and Kuala Lumpur, which is
besides attracting more and more
this flow of tourists, of
international business travelers,
this also allows those
who live there
to be able to get from one place
to another with relative ease.
Some examples now, of models,
of the American model, as we see here,
You know the huge grid
found in the U.S.
This is a one-mile grid,
but all the land is squared off like this.
One by one, and then as
each square is added,
urbanized little by little,
until all the squares which
remain are urbanized.
But the pattern is exactly
the same everywhere.
It is a model, as you can see.
Another model, taking an example
from Dakar, with its turnpike.
"A Large State Venture",
"The Future of Amina," "Being Built Today"
They place on these great
works and on the turnpikes
to be constructed a future
for future inhabitants.
This is not to judge the value behind it;
it is simply another model,
which is already in use,
particularly in Dakar.
Another model, this one historic,
is the plan of Nouakchott.
Nouakchott does not yet exist
in its modern state,
the model kept is one of segregation,
between a residential North here,
and a much denser, more popular South.
So in 1957, three years before
independence, we still have,
for a new city which will be Nouakchott,
laying the first stone in 1958,
for this new city for which
was chosen a segregative plan,
between a European city,
as one once called it,
residential zones for the rich,
for the elite, and then a Southern
zone more popular, indigenous.
This is a city model.
One was not obligated to separate
the population in two.
One might have imagined that,
at the same time those
of the popular neighborhoods might be
instead spread uniformly around the area.
Once again, not a value judgement,
one does not say if this is good or bad,
one simply can say that,
these are choices made,
and different models.
Finally, an interesting model which
I'd like to leave with you to reflect on.
Is it better to live in this first part
of the screen, on the bottom,
in the market-- animated, informal,
popular, or in a version
of modern Africa, in a building,
where one sees no one outdoors?
I leave this question hanging,
we'll have the opportunity to return to it
but the idea to reflect on is
which model would you prefer,
for which city.
We'll stop there,
on the question of model.