Just for once, in our discussion of models
of today's modern cities, let's go to Asia,
with the analysis of several cities:
Kuala Lumpur and Singapore
in Southeast Asia and, in the Arab world,
Abu Dhabi and Dubai.
We'll explain why we've chosen
these cities in particular,
and what our reasoning is
for choosing to analyze these four cities.
What we'll try to show is
that there are choices,
political choices, societal choices,
which are made as one plans a city,
and that these diverse choices,
the panoply of choices which one makes,
is what, in the end, we call a model.
There are great models one can follow,
we have city models which are,
in the end, economic ones,
but not solely, for within these same
economic models in Southeast Asia
or in the Arab world,
we can see that the choices made
are extremely different,
with very diverse results.
So we'll begin with
what we call "global cities."
Why global cities?
Because a number of cities,
whether African, Asian,
European or American, today form part of
this worldwide competition,
where the goal is to attract
the largest flow possible,
whether this is one of
people or finances,
based at once on
business and tourism.
Therefore the state of the global city
is to a great extent linked
to these flows, which may be
of money, of airport rankings,
the number of mentions in the press.
This is where it all begins,
with the number of
international visitors.
But a city cannot declare itself
a global city.
On the contrary, these are
key means to achieve this,
via the number of international
conferences, studies, important indicators
which give or deny a city its
status as a global city.
We will also see that
in certain global cities,
whether in Africa or Asia,
the strategies are precisely the same.
The goal is to attract
the largest number of people and
the flow of finance and commerce.
So to speak of "global cities," let's use
the ranking which is practically
the rule of law:
the MasterCard ranking,
whose #1 in 2008,
---since we don't have the latest
figures, this will work--
was London, a prime example
of a global city, followed by
New York, Tokyo, and
with Singapore in fourth.
I'll go down the list quickly,
for as you'll see
it is made up of mostly American
and European cities; we have to
go much, much lower in order
to reach African cities,
or Asian cities. Yet these are the
ones which interest us today:
Singapore, as we've mentioned,
Dubai in the U.A.E., and Kuala Lumpur,
which we find in here in 38th position,
Dubai in 37th in 2007,
moving down a bit in 2008, and Kuala Lumpur
with a steep drop in 2008.
Abu Dhabi... the fourth city,
is not on this list of global cities.
Four cities, four countries: Malaysia,
Singapore, the U.A.E,
Kuala Lumpur 1,500,000,
Singapore 4,700,000,
Abu Dhabi, a very small city
with fewer than 700,000
and a city such as Dubai which is on par
with Kuala Lumpur, with 1,500,000.
The goal is not to calculate
demographics based on this data
which are certainly of interest,
but rather to quickly dive into
these other cases, and see how they
have treated urban space in a different way.
Abu Dhabi.
In a few words, Abu Dhabi was
a bit wary of opening itself up to
foreign investment until 2004,
when upon the death of the Sheikh,
Abu Dhabi found itself
as a regional center while Dubai
saw itself as an international hub.
1962, a very important date.
The first commercial effort
to exploit oil and,
since 2004, another important phenomenon,
the increase in oil prices,
which transformed Abu Dhabi
into an extremely rich
country and, conclusively,
allowed an influx of capital,
thanks to the security measures,
notably in the U.S.
after the terrorist attacks.
Abu Dhabi sees itself equally
as a cultural city.
While it may not currently be,
it will become one,
little by little, investing in
museums, such as
the Louvre and the Guggenheim, both
of which can be found in Abu Dhabi.
Dubai has far less oil than Abu Dhabi,
yet during the crisis of 1973
quadrupled its price,
so that finally the royalties from oil
would become so significant that Dubai
would achieve autonomy,
but very quickly exploring
other options, outside of oil,
for development, notably thanks
to their deep water port.
So Dubai sees itself as a solid base
for the development
of enterprise and commerce and,
while Abu Dhabi is a cultural city,
Dubai is one of commerce.
Singapore, developed since 1980,
with a huge recession,
and therefore other avenues
have been pursued, notably
the question of its patrimony
during the 1980's, one will invent,
the invention of the patrimony,
one will invent the patrimony.
They will take all that is more or less
their colonial patrimony
and blow it up
to make of it a selling point.
So they will rely at once on
commerce and on tourism.
Our last city: Kuala Lumpur,
Kuala Lumpur arrives much
later, its delays in development,
blamed on the "Tigers," on the
large Séhoui-style cities
which had been developed
well before in Asia,
and takes back the domains
that the others no longer wanted.
Singapore wants no more of
heavy industry, neither does Séhoul,
and it is Kuala Lumpur who will
take back part of this development.
Kuala Lumpur will develop
industry, for it is a city
of commerce and industry
which profiles itself
equally on information technology.
Why do I say this?
Simply because we can see how
the paths are different,
the choices are different, one can at the
same time base one's commerce on
development, on tourism, on industry,
yet in the end it is the same,
which is to say it must attract
the greatest possible flow.
We'll now see, in detail,
several flashes like this one,
where the great differences
which one finds between cities which are,
after all, which at the end of the day
have extremely similar strategies.
But the answer we'll find
behind these strategies
is extremely diverse.
It is what we'll see, within this
first theme which explores the question
of interior vs. exterior.
The Dubai Airport. Interior.
A shopping mall, where one
sees only retailers,
stores, the ebb and flow of people,
all night long, who arrive at 2 a.m.
and leave at 6 a.m. for another place,
and who in the meantime consume.
We are in an air-conditioned space,
a closed space, one that is protected,
100% controlled.
The Dubai airport, where the only
hard thing is to find the boarding gate,
sandwiched in between two large signs
of world distribution.
Another example.
Dubai once again. A commercial mall where
they have recreated an Italian piazza
with relative success, but where all
the symbols of the Italian square
are recreated in the interior.
It's 40 degrees centigrade outside,
in the shade, 18 degrees inside.
It is full of people, who spend their day
in these commercial malls,
in these artificially created universes,
an exterior universe
recreated in the interior.
Another example, again in Dubai.
Inside a commercial mall: a ski slope.
A ski slope that would
normally be outdoors,
in countries where it is extremely hot,
like the U.A.E., can only
be achieved if it is indoors.
One leaves this commercial mall,
leaves the ski slope,
and finds oneself, still in Dubai,
with housing developments and banks,
yet no one is outdoors.
One sees only a flow of cars,
yet not one person strolling,
not one pedestrian, for the conditions
are such that it is extremely hot.
There is no shade. We can see
how difficult it would be to
imagine sitting oneself down, calmly,
on a bench, under this glaring sun.
On the other hand, we have Singapore.
The same temperature.
Slightly higher humidity.
In other words, a heat
which is difficult to bear,
yet a place where
large shaded coverings
permit a natural ventilation
and allow people to walk around outside.
Kuala Lumpur, at night.
Restaurants line the streets.
We see that there is truly life
in the exterior.
We find that, in both Dubai and Abu Dhabi,
one recreates in the interior,
in a confined space,
in a completely temperate climate,
one that is completely controlled,
a universe which should be exterior,
while in the cities of Southeast Asia,
one relies on the exterior,
knowing that the people will go, despite
the heat, to these exterior spaces.
Another example, again in Singapore.
People wait calmly
to cross the street.
while in Dubai or Abu Dhabi,
this would be practially impossible.
To finish up on these questions of
interior/exterior, we should say that
when we speak of models,
here are some choices.
Does one develop a city for pedestrians,
who can walk outside?
Or does one develop a city for drivers
who park their car,
or take a taxi, who park their car,
and find themselves in an aseptic,
totally air-conditioned climate?
We can see here that, between
the countries of Southeast Asia
and those of the U.A.E.,
the situations are extremely different.
Okay, let's stop here,
at the end of this first part.
I'll see you for the next one.