We have previously seen
various types of cities.
We will now see what forms
these types of cities generate.
These different forms of urbanization,
these urban forms
are a total of five, these
are the main ones.
While there are of course subgroups,
these are the five
main ones that we are going to find
in all of the cities in the world.
First there are slums and
working-class neighborhoods,
there are gated neighborhoods,
the gentrified centers
most of the time,
the large residential suburbs and
business and/or commercial areas.
We are going to quickly review these
different forms of urbanization.
Here, we clearly recognize the slum
or the working-class neighborhood.
We are now in Haiti, we have
crossed the Atlantic
to find other forms of
urbanization
that are exactly and totally
the same as those that can be
found on the African continent.
If I continue, we are now in Riyadh.
in Saudi Arabia in what we call
the large gated neighborhoods,
that is the "gated" communities that are
protected from the outside
by walls and we can see
that there are relatively
few entrances in the neighborhood
so the resident movement can
be controlled by two entrances,
three entrances with guards and
we can clearly see that in this
situation the whole of the space here
is without a doubt private.
Next.
The large gentrified centers.
Here we recognize the cathedral.
We are in the center of Dakar.
The process of gentrification is
relatively slow in Africa,
but little by little, these centers
are redeemed, whether the old houses
are once again purchased and destroyed
to make places for buildings,
for populations that are much more well
off than those who lived there previously.
The large residential centers.
Here is a little atypical
of an example, since we are
in Kinshasa.
It's clear that we are not observing
the formal but rather
the informal but that these large
suburbs disperse and
the housing disperses over
extremely important areas,
which we call a diffuse city, we could
have very well used as
an example a residential neighborhood
in the United States since
in principle, these are images
that we know best.
The last form of urbanization,
last type of urban form,
is the commercial center or the business
center, we have combined
commercial and business, it is here that
jobs are found in general,
and here we are typically
in an industrial zone.
We see very clearly
by the form of the parcels,
by the size of the parcels and
the size of the buildings.
As an example here, we have
without a doubt neighborhoods,
islands in residential neighboorhoods,
we see the size of
the highway and then we see that
the industrial parcels
here have been subsequently subdivided
in large parcels, so we see these
are no longer the same proportions here,
without a doubt, of kerosene or
of great buildings and hangars here,
so without knowing exactly which
are the industries in these areas,
we see by the form of the area,
the size of the buildings that we are in
a form of business center.
Here are a few large forms of
urbanization quickly described.
So there are subcategories,
we can find forms that
are a little different,
but really they can be found
in every city on the planet
to which the African cities are
not really an exception,
it's what we find in terms of
forms of urbanization.
The only drawback of being on the topic
of gentrified centers
since Europe is notably in a much
more advanced process
but we see that the process
is exactly the same in
the large African cities and that
little by little these large cities
are gentrified, that is a much richer
population tries to settle
and finally change the form
and the face of the neighborhoods.