After very optimistic and uplifting vision of Thomas Vizel,
let's return to the historical evolution of mobility to find
that transport policy is like clothing.
It constantly changes according to fashion
and that we love one day can be thrown the next day.
A vivid example of this versatility, Geneva, from which for at least a century
has exchange transport policy like one exchange a shirt.
♪ (jazz 50s) ♪
(narrator) The tram.
152 years that it resonates in the streets of Geneva
♪ (jazz 50s) ♪
That's a model of the 50's that the tram lovers Association
pampers to keep it in working order.
For them, the tram is at least one big advantage
(Tram running)
(man) The undeniable advantage is the capacity.
In a tram you put 300 people.
With the usual load of cars at Geneva
1.1 persons per vehicle, it takes almost 300 cars
to replace a tram.
So the content of a tram is enough alone
to a traffic jam of cars.
♪ (classical music playful) ♪
(narrator) The Voyage of the Geneva tram
began in 1862 with horse-drawn cars, cars drawn by horses.
In 1878 we go to the steam and then to electricity from 1894.
♪ (classical music playful) ♪
Over the years,
Geneva built one of Europe's largest tram networks.
♪ (classical music playful) ♪
In the early 20th century,
there are over 125km of rail throughout the canton
and several lines go to near France.
♪ (classical music playful) ♪
But this golden age will not last.
In 1925,
the lines begin to disappear, replaced by buses.
And at first it is the small campaign lines
that are dismantled.
(Cedric Black) These long campaign lines bring back few money,
as there are relatively few travelers.
The rehabilitation infrastructure level is too expensive
so we begin to remove them.
This is the line of Versoix,
that duplicates the railway line,
which disappears first.
After, in the 30s, this is the line of Chancy, Douvaine.
(narrator) During the war, the dismantling stops.
The traminaux still look great, they even have their mobile canteen.
And that's by tram that sometimes we carry mailbags,
as here in Grand Lancy in the 40's.
But since the post-war
the removal of tram lines starts over again.
The rails disappear facing the influx
of a formidable competitor on the road, his majesty the car,
whose numbers in Geneva as everywhere, explodes.
(Tram bell)
In the 50s, take the tram, it's a little corny.
(man) Who takes public transportation?
(Cedric Black) This is called the captives.
People who do not have the means to travel by car.
Older women, older men also finally ...
The elderly, children and people who do not have the means
to have a car.
As anyway, in the idea,
the public transport is doomed to disappear,
we put a bus for a few years, it is quite enough
until everyone has a car.
♪ (classical music playful) ♪
(narrator) To measure the absolute triumph of the private car,
let's transport ourselves in the 50s, and let's stop a moment
on original documents.
(Book that flips)
Take for example,
this imposing general traffic study in Geneva in two volumes.
It dates from 1955.
The engineer was asked to imagine and predict
what would flow in Geneva 25 years later, ie in 1980.
Seen today, the result is quite astonishing.
First example, the Quai des Bergues.
We had imagined that in 1980,
it is an expressway of 4 lanes that pass under the crossroads here
and that would lead to the dock.
If the project had been done,
there would be here five lanes in total,
the road would 17m wide and 42,000 cars per day
would allegedly dumped along the Rhone and the surrounding bridges.
(road traffic)
(Flowing water)
(Malik Melihi) We are on the Longemalle square
a quiet, semi-pedestrian square today.
If the project of 1955 was realized, we would end up here
with a flood of traffic rather consistent.
Nearly 30 000 vehicles per day.
(rattle)
The latest example, the Rue des Deux Ponts.
Here it is on an expressway of 6 lanes were allegedly would have circulated cars.
Width of the road: 36 meters
Consequently also expected and assumed by the study of 1955,
the plot involves the demolition of the buildings on the right side of the road
(Collapse of buildings)
♪ (jazz) ♪
1964 ultimate symbol of the automotive kingdom, the opening of the first Swiss motorway
Geneva-Lausanne, with wise advice to the driver.
(vintage video narrator) Dangerous faults,
serious offenses may be understandable at first,
are still common, but inexcusable today.
So what of the practice of leaving the motorway
against the grain when, thoughtlessness or by speeding,
we missed the track release.
Sometimes a motorist takes the wrong path
and heads in the opposite direction which he intended to follow.
No way then to cross the central mast,
guardrails will completely prohibit it soon.
♪ (jazz) ♪
(Journalist) Do you think the car is essential in modern life?
Absolutely.
Essential.
The car, it's part of a man as a jacket,
as a pair of shoes.
♪ (jazz) ♪
(narrator) The fascination of males for beautiful bodies
even intrigued psychoanalysts.
The drive of the automobile has a sexual investment.
This is a way to extend the power of man.
But you know very well that the powerful man
is powerful because he is sexually powerful.
If he is not sexually powerful he will compensate for impotence
or that insufficient sexual power
precisely by the power of his car.
(narrator) Faced with such power of seduction, how the tram
clumsy and noisy, could resist it?
Between 1946 and 1968 the lines disappear at the speed of light.
Result, in 1969 the canton of Geneva now has only one tram line.
This is the tram 12.
(Tram bell)
(narrator) 9 unfortunate kilometers of a network that has counted up to 125.
But over the years, the wind will turn.
For the explosion of traffic will eventually cause problems.
Too many cars, too many caps, too much pollution.
(Generic to the wise)
In 1977, even the show  wise  is concerned.
(vintage video narrator) Each morning, everyone takes his car
to go alone in the same place as these neighbors.
In each car, one person.
The consequence is that we consume 4 times more energy than 25 years ago.
(vintage video narrator) Every morning thousands of workers
arrive simultaneously at work. These are commuters.
And that's as many cars that often stay parked all day.
(Journalist) Do you come to Geneva every morning?
Yes
(journalist) Do you have traffic jams every morning?
Oh yes, then ... (laughs)
(journalist) - Is it bearable  - No.
Oh my God it's a disaster!
(journalist) - How do you bear ?  - Badlyl. I get very nervous at night.
(narrator) Faced with this onslaught of cars,
the city is on the verge of suffocation.
And one begins to regret the virtues of good old tram.
♪  The tram 12 arrived  ...  ♪
After being deleted, Geneva begins in the late 80s
to recreat tram lines.
(narrator) And yes! In 1987 the rails reappear.
And often on the same routes as the old lines.
We put the rails where they had been removed some years before.
So the error that was of tajing them off, putting them is repairing the error.
(narrator) Between 1995 and today, eleven new lines
emerged in the township, and there are projects until 2020.
Attitudes have so changed, the population of the city as well.
In the district of St. John, we are in the Gonzenbach family.
(Sound of cutlery)
Every morning, Lila, 10, goes alone to school,
as a big girl, by foot. The building is two steps away.
As for Victor, his little brother 7 years old, his mom accompanies him,
before going herself to work by bike or bus.
(man) It really is a choice of lifestyle.
We chose to live in the city to not be dependent
of a single car,
contrary to the possibility of living in the countryside away from it all
where we would have needed to have, if not one car, maybe two
or a motorcycle or scooter, a dependency we did not want.
(narrator) Martin works in Lausanne.
he has his little folding bike to go down to the station.
A bike he will take with him on the train.
Because obviously, Martin has the General rail pass.
(Martin) We never owned our own car,
we are members of a cooperative of carsharing, Mobility,
allowing us to have a car when we need it, where we need it,
with the choice of vehicle if required too.
(narrator) Fleet car sharing as Mobility, carpooling,
trips from booking via mobile phone,
all these systems have the wind in their sails.
Not really need to have one's own car.
(Martin) We are in a trend where the dream of the car
as social prestige object is history.
Somewhere it is a freedom not to have one.
To not have worries, the financial burden, the moral burden
and bulk to be oneself a car owner.
To me it was obvious that in the city center
everyone comes here, we are no longer pioneers.
(narrator) Admittedly, at first glance, traffic seems chaotic in Geneva.
Still, a small silent revolution is on.
Today, over 40% of the inhabitants of downtown Geneva
simply have no more individual car.
Half of young people between 18 and 25 years do not have a driver license,
and even if it is not seen with the naked eye, in the city center,
the number of cars fell by nearly 20% since 2000.