Welcome to the 3rd week of
our Smart City MOOC.
In it, we will talk about
smart urban transportation systems
and the block is structured as follows.
First, we will conceptualize these
smart urban transportation systems
lay out the key elements of it.
Then, Maxime will talk about what we
call the "improve" pathway
that namely the role that ICTs,
that digitalization plays
in improving the current
transportation systems.
This will be followed by an
interview with Siemens.
After that, Maxime will talk about
what we call the shift pathway
That is the use of the ICTs,
the role that digitalization plays
in making the transition to
smart urban transportation systems
and this will be followed by an
interview with the RATP Group
Finally to conclude, we will lay out
the necessary conditions.
That is, what it takes at the
managerial and the policy level
in order to move towards
smart urban transportation systems.