Hello and welcome back.
In this session, we will
conceptualize the transition
into smart urban transportation
system and we do this in 3 steps.
We will firstly identify the main 3
drivers towards such systems
and then we will conceptualize the
evolution of these systems
and finally we will lay out the 2
main steps that it takes in order
to make this transition
Now the main drivers.
There are 3 main drivers, we think,
that push towards smarter
urban transportation systems.
The first one is one is,
of course, urbanization.
More people living in cities.
Transport becomes more
and more congested
and the users have an
increasingly poor experience,
be it the users of the car
or the bicycle or the buses
and that is certainly one of the
main drivers that pushes for
smarter systems
and the second driver is the
main topic that we have
always dealt with in this MOOC.
That is the digitalization that
actually makes a whole series of
changes that makes smarter urban
transportation systems possible.
And the third driver here is climate
change or resource efficiency.
Approximately 15 - 20% of
global CO2 emissions actually
come from urban transportation
and so there is a strong push
to make these systems more
efficient and make them smarter.
These 3 drivers together push towards
smarter urban transportation systems.
Now how to think about
this evolution and
how to conceptualize this evolution?
There was transport in
the cities before the car.
There were actually trams
in the cities or carriages
and when the car appeared,
the efficiency of urban
transportation initially increased
but then as more and more
cars entered the city,
as there were more and more
people using the cars,
at some point the car led to some
sort of counter-productivity
where by more cars in the
city actually led to a poorer
user experience
and the efficiency of urban
transportation systems
rapidly declined to the point
where we think we are today.
So here we are at a point where
digitalization and the other drivers
together will lead to a
paradigm shift.
We don't know yet where
exactly this will lead to after
but we can clearly identify the 2
elements of that paradigm shift.
The first element being the fact
that people want to own
less and less things,
including cars
and they want to use the vehicles
they want to use the
transportation modes.
So, ownership to usership
and the second element of that
paradigm shift is the fact that
we move away from separate
transportation systems
to mobility systems in the sense
that when you become a user
you actually care much less
about which kind of transportation
mode you use and so ultimately
this leads to some sort of
mobility services.
Let's now talk about the
steps towards transition
and we think there are 2 main steps.
So traditionally there is already
quite a lot of improvement of
existing transportation systems,
infrastructures and service
but with the new data layer,
with the digitization,
there are more improvements.
The existing improvements
can be significantly enhanced
and that will be the first step
towards the transition.
The second step will be the, so called,
shift pathway whereby things
are done in terms of the paradigm
shift I mentioned before in terms of
ownership to usership and in
terms of transportation mode
to mobility services
and the next 2 sessions will
talk about these 2 steps
which are conditions for making smart
urban mobility systems a reality.