Hello, and welcome back
to the course.
My name is Maxime Audouin, and I am
a researcher here at EPFL.
In this session, we will focus
on how the ICTs
can help to improve urban
transportation systems,
in terms of user experience
and safety.
We will focus on 2 directions.
Namely, the use of the information
and communication technologies
to monitor urban transportation
infrastructure
and automated driving
vehicles.
We will see that these 2 directions
have implications for
both public and private
transportation.
The first area where
digitalisation can help
is in the monitoring of urban
transportation systems.
Indeed, by making the transportation
infrastructure
equipped with data gathering
devices
such as video camera, speed cameras,
sensors for traffic detection.
Such as infrared, laser, RFID,
as well as wired, and wireless
communication devices,
we can now have
a better understanding
of the behavior of urban
transportation systems.
And thus, decide to optimize them
accordingly.
The use of the ICTs to monitor
transportation infrastructure
has direct implication, to begin in
the Infrastructure Layer.
Indeed, transportation and
infrastructure managers
now have to pay attention to
the integration of the legacy
transportation infrastructure,
with this new data infrastructure.
There are also implications
in the Data layer.
Transportation infrastructure
managers
must pay attention to
the reliability of the data.
And whether they are complete
and holistic or not.
Data coming from different channels
should also be easy
to standardize.
Last but not least, one must be sure
that the data
is secure. That is to say that
the data
doesn't end up in the wrong hands
as they might be confidential data,
and should not be misused.
To finish, there are implications
in the Services Layer.
Thanks to the data gathered,
transportation providers
can make their transportation services
more accessible, performing,
and respond eventually
more adequately
to the demand.
Where as private car users can
benefit from new services
such as ways
allowing them to adapt their routes
when driving.
For example, thanks to dynamic
route planners
that are using real time data.
The other direction that
is contributing to improve
the experience of private and public
transportation users
as well as the safety of urban
transportation systems
can be observed in the development
of self driving vehicles,
also known as
Automated Vehicles.
Most of the road accidents
nowadays
are caused because of human errors.
And having machines
complete the driving task
instead of humans,
should it be for personal cars,
or public transport vehicles,
could ultimately reduce the number
of accidents on the road,
increase the safety of
transportation systems,
and ultimately make our urban
transportation systems
more efficient.
Another argument in favour of
automated vehicles
is that it would allow people
to complete other tasks
than the driving task
when using a vehicle to go
from one location to another.
That is to say, help them stop
wasting their time
when commuting.
Traditional vehicles, should they be
cars, shuttles, buses,
are already producing important
amounts of data
that you do not even think of.
Think about the speed of a vehicle,
the direction it's headed,
its location, its directions and
stability control,
the brake status, the hours of
operation,
the mileage.
Thanks to the ICTs,
these data can now be used to make
our vehicles more automated
to go progressively towards
what is known as
Self Driving Vehicles.
As agreed by The United States
Department of Transportation,
car automation can be divided
into 5 steps.
Level 0, which is not
a step
is known as the
No Automation Level.
Level 1, which is the first step
is when the driver
benefits from one driving
assistance system
such as braking systems
for example.
Level 2, is where the river
benefits from
at least 2 driving assistance
systems.
Fr example, cruise control, and
braking assistance at the same time.
Whereas these 3 first levels are
enabled by automation mechanisms,
the next 3 steps are enabled
by a combination of automation and
ICT facilitated processing.
Level 3 is defined as
the conditional automation
where the driving task is completed
by an automated driving system.
But it is expected that the driver
responds appropriately if needed.
Such systems are currently being
used on highways
with for example, what Tesla
is proposing in California
in the United States,
but not yet in urban systems
due to the high complexity
of traffic in town.
Level 4 is defined as
the High Automation,
which is the evolution of
Level 3 into a stage
where the human driver does not
even need to respond
appropriately if needed.
This is being developed, and
according to Tesla
still such functionalities
should be available
in 2018.
The last level of this
automation ladder,
is the level 5, known as
The Full Automation
where all aspects of driving
will be completed by driving
assistance systems
including activities such
as parking.
Automated vehicles of Level 5
will not have any options for
human driving
meaning they won't even be equipped
with steering wheel
or controls.
As we will see now,
self driving vehicles
have implications on
the infrastructure, the data,
and the service layer.
In order to reach these levels
of automation,
the transportation infrastructure
needs to be updated.
First, vehicles need to be equipped
with data processing
and communication technologies
so they can communicate
with each other.
This is also known as the
vehicle to vehicle communication.
The infrastructure itself
needs to be able to
be able to communicate with
the vehicle as well.
For example, speed limitations,
road signs,
traffic lights, need to be equipped
in order to be able to send signals
to vehicles about the road conditions.
Should we one day have automated
bus rapid transit systems,
bus stations will need to
be equipped with data receiving
and emitting devices
to be able to communicate with
the driver-less buses fleet.
Implications in the data layer
are also very important.
The data need to be standardized
between the different vehicles.
For example between the bus
and cars,
and between vehicles from
different manufacturers
So they are still able to
communicate with one another.
Then comes the question of
who owns the data?
Is it the consumer?
Is it the vehicle manufacturer?
Is it the public authority?
Who are those owning the data?
We must ask the question of
the pricing of the data.
And to what extent the data can
be sold to 3rd party companies?
Last but not least, the data
need to be secured.
As you can imagine, misuse of
self driving vehicle data
could be highly dangerous.
At the services layer,
implications also exist.
Indeed, in case of a road accident,
the question of who is
held accountable
must be taken into account.
Is it the car user
that is responsible?
Or the transportation provider?
The vehicle manufacturing
company?
The insurance company?
And we also need to care about
the social acceptance
of driver-less vehicle technologies.
That will not be the same among
different social classes
or age groups.
You might think about the social
acceptance of driver-less cars,
but the social acceptance of
automated public transport
should be considered with
the same importance.
Last but not least, driver-less
vehicles
will have institutional implications.
For example,
public authorities
might need to make the driving
code evolve.
Or one can wonder if people will
even need to own a kind of
driving license...
anymore to be able to use
a driver-less vehicle?
In this session, we have seen
two main directions
enabled by the ICTs
to address the safety
and user experience challenge
in private and public transport.
And the implications these 2
directions have in the infrastructure,
the data, and the services layer.
We will now hear from
our expert Steffen Schaefer
from Siemens,
who will explain to us what
the main drivers
behind the emergence of smart
urban mobility systems are.
Stay tuned.