Welcome back to the course.
It is my pleasure to discuss today
with Steffen Schaeffer.
He is a senior principal
of mobility management
at Siemens in Munich.
And maybe, Steffen,
you can give us a little bit
of your background.
Thank you, Matthias,
for inviting me.
I'm glad to be here.
I have been working
for 15 years now
on mobile internet
and sensor network solution,
what today is called
the internet of things.
I've been at IBM for many years,
and have been starting with
the smart city solutions in 2010,
when IBM launched
the Smarter City campaign.
Three years ago I joined Siemens,
and I'm now responsible
for innovative digital
mobility solutions.
Okay.
So you have a lot of experience
and if you look 10 years
ahead from now
in which direction
are the smart urban
mobility systems going?
Even in 10 years from now,
satisfying mobility needs
for rapidly growing
population in cities
will remain one of the key issues
in urban infrastructure management.
Of course,
the privately owned cars we know it
will still be around in 10 years.
But to a much lesser extent.
With the rise
of self-driving vehicles,
new mobility services,
and the sharing economy,
there will be significant change
in urban mobility.
Modern information technologies,
or what is called digitalization,
are already enabling
new transport modes,
and are changing existing ones
very rapidly.
We see examples in this
in for example, free floating cars
that are paid by the minute,
and can be dropped anywhere.
The have become very popular
in Germany and some US cities.
Bike sharing are normally used
through apps
and with information technologies.
Taxi apps or limo services
have caused a lot of discussion
and are challenging
the existing taxi landscape.
As a last example,
Demand Responsive Transport (DRT),
is now an interesting new mode
that replaces the traditional
shared hail service
by leveraging today's technologies.
All of them are complementing
existing public transport
at least in the midterm.
With all these
new transport modes, though,
it will be important
to make intermodal journeys
seamless to the traveller,
in the sense that
it is easy to transition
from one transport mode
to the other.
For example,
schedules are synchronized,
or the information
about when people arrive.
Ticketing schemes
and payments are integrated.
And so forth.
Okay. Thank you.
Now how does automatization
play into the evolution
of smart urban mobility?
This is a great question.
Automation in mobility
will certainly become a reality
also in cities.
I personally can see
two potential scenarios,
and reality might
well lie in between the two.
First scenario, public transport
such as urban rail,
underground or light rail trains,
will remain the key transport mode
in cities.
Basically forming
transportation backbone.
Where such public
transport infrastructure
has been implemented
it will stay and remain
very efficient means of transport.
In complementing this first scenario
there can be self-driving vehicles
that will offer
first and last mile transport
in intermodal trips.
And thus complement and strengthen
rail bound public transport.
In the second scenario
self-driving vehicles
may offer door to door services,
at least within a city.
They could basically
compete against mass-transit.
Due to self-driving capabilities,
they wrote as
a relatively inexpensive
infrastructure,
can be used intelligently,
so that traffic jams are avoided.
Either way,
self-driving vehicles
will be more intensely used
than today's cars.
They will be
almost constantly on the roads
for transporting
passengers and goods,
and if they need to park
they will park themselves.
So as another effect
less parking infrastructure
will be needed.
So what are the main drivers
toward smart urban mobility systems?
I see
primarily technical
and institutional drivers.
Let's start with the technical side.
Let's look at
what is behind digitalization?
What does it mean
for mobility in cities?
Let's look at
the internet of things,
for example.
In mobility, it means
connected vehicles.
Maybe even, of course,
cars and buses and so.
Maybe even bikes.
It could mean traffic lights
that signal to cars
the remaining red and green faces
Mobile internet and smartphones
are another technology
that are key drivers.
For example,
people are able to locate themselves
on the map and find
mobility services around them,
and purchase, for example,
public transport tickets
on the spot.
Thirdly,
cloud plays an important role
because now computing resources
can be provided
in a very flexible way.
For example, you can adapt
the size of the computing resources
to the traffic pattern.
That there will be more
computing resources needed
in morning and evening peak hours
than during the night
And fourthly,
artificial intelligence
is a really important technology.
Because it is essential
for self-driving cars.
And it can also help offer
improving coordination
of complex transportation networks.
And besides these
information technologies,
there are also technologies,
other technologies that are changing
better and cheaper batteries,
for example.
And how about
the institutional drivers?
Oh that is a really
important point.
A suitable framework
needs to be brought in place
to make this all work.
And to fully utilize
these new technologies
by also keeping or creating
a level plane field.
I can see more
private mobility providers
emerging beside
the public transport operators,
to a degree that citizens
are offering rides,
sharing their cars,
similar to a public service.
And when Uber entered the market.
It gained a certain attraction
and popularity
amongst the citizens.
But the city governments
and taxi companies
first didn't know
what to do with it.
But in the mean time now,
national and city governments
are bringing the right
regulations in place
so the new transport modes
and these new services can be used.
Car sharing is another example.
Think how,
and under what circumstances
should car sharing provider
be allowed to park their fleet,
which can be a few
hundred cars in a city.
And what circumstances
are they allowed to park their cars
on public roads.
That is the framework
that needs to be set up
by the governments.
As another example in the US,
we see an interesting trend
that companies
are trying to impact
the mobility behavior
of their employees.
They are charging parking fees,
fees for parking the car
at the corporate sites
and take this money to subsidize
alternative modes of transport
for coming with your private car.
So there,
you can see that
in the absence
of a good institutional
framework of regulations,
even private companies
are going in this way.
And lastly,
look at the two scenarios
I have painted before
on the self-driving vehicles.
What is, ah, which scenarios
will emerge in your city?
It's not a technical question.
And maybe also not a commercial one.
It strongly depends on
the regulations you're setting.
Ya, I think that's a really
clear conclusion.
The role of regulations
in all of this.
Thank you so much, Steffen,
for your insights
on smart urban mobility systems.
It's been a real pleasure, Matthias,
thanks for inviting me.