Hello, and welcome back
to the course.
In this session,
we will see how the information
and communication technologies
are enabling the development
of new mobility modes
that are disrupting
the traditional urban
transportation landscape.
And more generally, we will see
how the ICTs are enabling
the paradigm shift
from traditional urban transportation
to smart urban mobility.
We will do this along
the three following steps.
In the first time, we will discuss
the different mobility services
that are emerging
thanks to digitalization.
Then we will talk about
the potential of the ICTs
to go towards more integration
in urban transportation systems.
Finally, we will see what this implies
for  our infrastructure,
data, and services layer.
Thanks to
the development of the ICTs,
and especially to
geo- localization technologies,
new mobility services,
partly relying on mechanisms
borrowed from the sharing economy
have emerged in the last 10 years.
For example, the information
and communication technologies
have supported the development
of car sharing schemes.
Indeed, you can now for example,
use your cellphone
to know where
a car sharing station is located,
book a car,  pay for it online,
use it, and drop it
at the next car sharing station.
car2go, DriveNow,
for example, are among
the most well known
car sharing company.
Should you be using
your own vehicle for a defined trip,
you can now decide
to enter your trip origin
and destination,
so people that are planning to do
a similar trip
than the one you're doing,
can decide to join your ride.
This is called car pooling,
and one of the most famous platform
to do it, is provided by
the French company BlaBlaCar.
Still thanks to geo-localization,
you can now use your smartphone
to hail a ride anytime, anywhere.
This is call E-hailing
that allows you to have access
to mobility solutions
in many different countries.
Uber or Lift are, for example,
providing such services.
One must also acknowledge
the fact that some of these
new hybrid mobility modes,
as we call them,
might also become driverless
at one point.
As we have already seen
with Uber rolling out
driverless Uber services
in Pittsburgh, United States.
We are at the edge
of a real paradigm shift
in urban transportation system
that is facilitated
by information
and communication technology.
These new ICT facilitated services
are impacting
public and private transport.
They affect the need
for urban dwellers to own their own car,
as they make
mobility solutions more accessible.
And they also impact
public transportation providers
that have, for example,
in some case started to provide
on-demand shuttles
for the customers,
such as the Kutsuplus services
that was provided
in Helsinki last year.
There is
a real paradigm shift happening
from transportation to mobility,
and from car ownership
to mobility usership.
However, many of these
new mobility modes are redundant.
And are complexifying
the mobility offers in urban systems,
calling for more integration
within mobility modes,
and across mobility mode.
All mobility modes
are now producing data.
So, it has now
become possible to integrate
these data under different schemes.
The first scheme is known as
Integrated Ticketing Systems
that you might also know
as smart card.
There, the users use only
one single ticketing system
to access and pay
for different mobility solutions.
For example, in Seoul, South Korea,
the T-money card
is accepted on all buses, metros,
and suburban trains
of the transportation network.
But, it can also be accepted to pay
in all taxis operating in Seoul.
Thus integrating public
and semi-private transport solutions.
Integrated Mobility Platforms
correspond to
more advanced form
of transport integration
facilitated by information
and communication technologies.
With Integrated Mobility Platforms,
users have access
within one smartphone app
to information
from
various transportation providers
about the trip
they are planning to do.
Thus, they are able to know
from different transportation providers
proposing the trip they want to do,
how long the trip will take,
how expensive it will be,
and much carbon they will make.
They are not just able
to have the information,
but also are able to book and pay
for the chosen trip on the app,
independently of
the mobility provider chosen.
And to receive their tickets
on their smartphones electronically,
as well as their invoice.
Such solutions tend to integrate
public transport solutions
with more hybrid solutions
such as E-hailing or car pooling,
or even human powered solution,
such as bike sharing.
The ultimate
integrated mobility solution
is known as
the Mobility-as-a-Service,
which is
a mobility distribution model
in which a customer's
major transportation needs
are made over one single interface.
And these
interface mobility services
are bundled into monthly packages,
similar to mobile phone priced
on package that you probably have.
An easy way to understand
Mobility-as-a-Service
is to think about it as the Netflix
or the Spotify of transportation.
It's a platform.
You pay a monthly fee and have access
to solutions and mobility services,
depending on the package
you have selected and paid for.
Even if not proved yet,
it's more and more agreed
going towards integration
should improve the user experience.
As it will make public transport
and hybrid transportation solutions
more attractive and more serious
alternative to private car users.
By promoting more
shared mobility solutions,
integrated mobility solutions
have the potential
to reduce congestion,
and make our transportation systems
more efficient,
and ultimately more sustainable.
Integrated mobility solutions
contribute to the shift
from legacy transportation system
to smart urban mobility systems.
However, reaching such levels
of integration
will have implications
in our infrastructure,
data, and services layer.
In the infrastructure layer,
financing is the big deal.
New business model
have to be developed
to warranty the quality
of transportation services
which translates in investments
in the infrastructure layer.
Nowadays, many different
mobility services
are using transportation infra,
but these transportation infrastructures
are still being financed in most
of the cases by public authority.
So new mechanisms on how to finance
transportation infrastructure
must be developed
to cope with the digitalization
of urban transportation systems.
In the data layer,
one must also make sure
that all the data are integrable.
Among different
transportation providers,
one must be sure  that the data
is inter operable and exchangeable.
Data from different
mobility providers should reach
the same level of quality
and reliability
and of course, be protected
to warranty the security
of the customers.
At the service layer, coordination
between mobility services providers
must be achieved
to avoid redundancy.
To ensure complementarity
of the different transportation modes,
public authority must
put regulations in place
as newcomers that
are coming from digitalization
and traditional
transportation providers,
are now sharing
the exact same playground.
Last but not least,
new business models
have to be developed
between platform operators
and mobility service providers
to go towards
the subscription formula,
as it is more and more proposed
in the Mobility-as-a-Service model.
In this session we have seen
how the ICTs are enabling
the development of new
mobility modes that are disrupting
the traditional mobility landscape.
And how the ICTs
can enable the paradigm shift
from legacy urban
transportation system
to smart urban mobility system.
In the next session,
you will hear from Natalie Leboucher,
Vice President at RATP Group,
who will explain how
legacy transport operators are adapting
to the digitalization
of urban transportation systems.
Stay tuned.