Welcome back to the course.
I have the pleasure of receiving
Nathalie Leboucher,
Executive Vice President Innovation Strategy
and Business Development
from the RATP Group in France,
a public transport operator.
Before, she was a head of Smart City at Orange,
the French telecom operator.
Thank you, Nathalie, for being here.
Hello. This is a real pleasure
to be here at EPFL.
Thank you. So the 1st question
I would like to ask you is
what are the main trends you see
in urban mobility?
Today, we can see that 3 major trends
are reshaping urban mobility
and accelerating the emergence
of smart mobility solutions.
First, there is increasing pressure
on urban mobility systems.
By 2030, more than 60% of the world's
population will live in urban areas.
This will lead to a massive increase
in daily individual journeys,
representing a new challenge
for urban mobility systems.
Other factors put urban mobility
systems under pressure,
such as financial sustainability,
environmental challenges,
and infrastructure capacity.
Second, we observe major shifts
in city dwellers' habits and needs.
Here are a few examples:
Consumers want on demand,
customized solutions to their daily needs.
They look for the best value
for the money.
More and more customers prefer
a pay as you use system.
They expect to have access
to additional services.
And last, but not least,
they want to be able to choose within
their large range of transport solutions
and get recommendations at each step
of their user experience.
And, finally, we are in the middle
of a major digital revolution.
There are some recent digital technologies
that offer a huge field of possibilities
for the future of urban mobility:
big data, machine learning,
the Internet of Things,
the user experience
and user interface design,
open data and blockchain technologies,
just to name a few.
Good. Now 2nd question.
What are the main models emerging
in urban public transport?
Well, Matthias,
we foresee 6 main categories of emerging
business models in public transport.
Thanks to the internet revolution,
intermediation platforms allow direct transactions
between service providers and users.
The revenue model is a commission
on each transaction,
and we all know Uber, BlaBlaCar,
and Booking.com.
Pay as you use models are defining
a new a paradigm.
There is a shift from owning
a product or an asset
to using a service.
For the transport sector,
we are seeing newcomers in car-sharing,
bike, and scooter services.
Consumers pay for monthly fees
and according to usage.
Device Centric models
are based on consumers
devoted to a top-of-the-line
innovative brand,
such as Apple or Tesla.
The primary revenue source
is the device itself.
Additional revenues comes from paying for services
within the core system.
Low Cost models focus on the key expectations
of clients for the best price.
In this case, revenues come
from core service prices
and extra charges for additional services.
Data Centric models, now, are based
on process data.
They generally provide customers
with free high-quality services
and, in exchange, gather all data
produced by their use.
If it's free, then you know that
you are the product.
Most developed centric models,
for example Google,
which is probably the best example with free
services along the whole mobility value chain,
with maps, live transit, Waze, Google Wallet,
Google Flight, and so on.
The latest, and most revolutionary
business model to emerge
is decentralized services on platforms
using blockchain technologies.
Decentralized services are emerging models
with no proven pattern of success at this stage,
but if they do succeed, they could be
a major revolution in the transport sector.
Imagine this as Uberization of Uber,
with companies such as Arcade City
or LaZooz.
These emerging business models
are disrupting the urban mobility ecosystem
as we know it.
They challenge the whole
public transport value chain.
They are inventing smarter ways
to meet urban mobility infrastructure challenges.
Provide city dwellers with customized,
on demand mobility solutions.
And develop green mobility solutions.
New players enter the transport
value chain
through customer-related activities,
information, and sales.
They invest, massively, in customer acquisition,
where traditional players,
such as RATP Group,
invest heavily in infrastructure.
And now to the 3rd question:
So what main strategies do you see
of legacy operators
to adapt to this new environment?
The emergence of innovative,
smart mobility solutions
represents both a huge opportunity
and a huge challenge
for legacy transport actors.
Legacy transport operators,
such as RATP Group,
are facing stiff competition
from 4 different directions:
market deregulation on core networks,
urban mobility solutions now being
offered by car makers,
smart mobility and disruptive solutions
now being offered by digital actors,
both major internet players and start-ups.
To adapt to this new environment,
legacy transport actors have to strive
for excellence in their core business.
Improve and deepen knowledge
of their customers
to enhance user experience.
And develop a full mobility ecosystem
based on 2 elements:
expand the range of mobility solutions
and offer additional services.
Three levels are vital to success.
The 1st is to implement a digital
transformation plan.
At RATP, our plan is based on 4 pillars:
customer experience,
employee experience,
operational performance,
thanks to big data and IoT,
and environmental performance.
The 2nd level is to accelerate innovation.
In the past, legacy transport operators
have mainly focused on incremental
and technical innovation.
Their aim was to improve their
existing network
and operational performance.
Today, they need to add market innovation
and disruptive innovation
to the equation.
Let me give you a few examples
of what I mean.
We need to develop innovation capacity
through specialized experts and labs
and launch major innovation programs,
such as 3-D printing, robots,
energy storage, drones,
Silver Economy, and so forth.
We need to increase agility
and speed of execution.
Focus on business driven innovation,
and promote a culture of innovation
throughout the company.
New business models and partnerships
are the 3rd, and final, level to success.
Legacy operators must enhance visibility
in the urban mobility ecosystem
by participating in major tech
entrance port events.
They need to build partnerships
with both large groups and startups.
They need to develop M&A investment
capacity
for early stage, or development stage,
companies.
From all that you said, what would be
the main message to our participants?
Well, from what I've just shown you,
it is clear that we live in a radically changing
urban mobility context.
Thanks to the digitalization,
we have exciting opportunities
to better serve our clients.
Thank you very much, Nathalie.
Thank you.