Welcome back.
In this last session
of the third block
we will now talk about
the necessary conditions
towards smart urban mobility systems.
Highlighting in particular
that main challenges for managers
and policy-makers.
So let's first look
at the challenges for managers.
I mean typically
those are challenges
for urban transportation managers.
And we have distinguished this
along as a series of categories
but the most important one
a sort of the challenges in the area
of the infrastructure layer,
the services layer
and the data layer.
Now, the most important challenges
at the infrastructure layer level
are the questions of interconnection
of transportation modes.
The different transportation modes
in light of mobility
as being the new kind of approach,
the new kind of services.
Managers need to pay
much more attention
into the interconnection
of the different transportation modes.
And also they need to pay attention
to upgrading the infrastructures
with the necessary ICT devices,
sensors, tools, so that
they can be made digital compatible.
So that the services
can actually be offered.
On the services layers,
I think managers
are particularly challenged
to come up with new business models.
On the basis of this data
that are generated
it is important
to find the business models
that are sustainable
and that will work.
And also on the services layer
it is of course important
that the users accept a new services
and that has very much to do
with the digital divide.
Not all types of user
are equally adapt to dealing
with a new digital mobility services.
On the data layer
the typical challenge
pertains for managers,
for urban transportation managers
pertains to data standards,
and protocols.
So that the data that are generated
can actually be exchange
and used later to meet
make the services.
Another big challenge of course
at the data layer
is the security challenge,
to make sure that this data
are not hacked
and that there are no security breaches.
Now, let's look at the challenges
for policy-makers,
for urban policy-makers
Again, the same distinctions
but the focus is of course different
and the infrastructure layer.
I think policy-makers
are very much challenged
to find the necessary finances
for this infrastructures.
This is not necessarily a question
that is new but of course
in the context
of the new mobility services
it's very important to look
at what needs to be finance
and which infrastructures
need to be finance.
Then other policy-makers challenges here
are the infrastructure development
which infrastructures to develop,
what kind of infrastructures to develop
and that always in relationship
to land use planning,
where to develop.
And if one looks at
the metropolitan level
it's the same kind of thing
except that there are
multiple political authorities
that need to plan and develop
the infrastructures together
and plan the land use together.
On the services layer,
the challenge here for policy-makers
is the coordination
of the different actors involved.
If we go to mobility services
There're many more actors
to coordinate and that is often
a political challenged
and then it's also of course
the question of the regulation
because the different actors
operate under different
kind of roles.
And there is no level playing field
and therefore there is a big challenge
for policy-makers to come up
with regulations that actually allow
for mobility services.
The same actually is true
at the metropolitan level
except that most typically regulation
will not happen there
but it's also a challenge
of coordinating the different actors.
And on the data layer the challenge,
the main challenge for policy-makers
pertains first to the whole financing
of the data infrastructure.
There are all kind of investments
that are necessary
to make this data platforms,
to make them available,
make them usable
and put them at the disposal
of the different operators.
Another political challenge
is the privacy challenge.
How much privacy is necessary?
And how much privacy
do actually the citizens want?
Then a further challenge
pertains to political challenge,
pertains to data policy,
is data an infrastructure,
is a data just a service,
is data a product
and how to regulate
these different data?
How to regulate access to this data?
How to regulate ownership
to this data?
The same questions arise
of course also
at the metropolitan level.
To conclude,
in this block we have conceptualized
smart urban transportation systems.
And we have showed
how the ICTs, how digitalization
can improve and can enable the shift
towards such systems.
We highlighted in particular
at the end
the challenges for managers,
urban transportation managers
and policy-makers.
Now, in the next two blocks
we will have take a much more
in-depth look into the transition
towards smart cities.
Stay tuned.