We've understood,
it is a secret to no one,
that rapid population increases put cities
in increasingly delicate situations.
So at the city government level,
we call this the local government,
this might be an "urban government,"
or even in a small village,
we must deal with the arrival
of these new residents,
but also the deficit in infrastructure
the deficit in city services.
In order to pay for the infrastructure,
to pay for the cities,
we need financial resources.
We are to going to see
how to obtain these resources.
And what interests us also,
is to see which are the mechanisms
to obtain financing,
how to go about it so that the cities
have sufficient resources in order to
be able to finance the infrastructure.
So we'll see what mechanisms
are behind the investment.
The city has to invest.
There are two ways to do it,
we can either answer the demand
or create the supply.
We can plan and program based on
the supply or the demand.
We'll use the classic example
of the railway, for example,
We'll use the example of the railway.
We have a demand,
to take from point A to point B
a certain number of people
But we can also program, plan,
based on supply.
Say I'm providing service
from point A to point B
every 30 minutes
for a certain number of people.
And then see if there is a link
to the demand.
We can start with supply
or demand, for investment,
it's the same thing.
I offer and provide a service,
or I respond to a demand.
Most of the time we're dealing
with responding to demand
and we are well below
what would be needed.
Before providing for the newly arrived,
we should note that,
Most cities, a huge majority of cities,
are underfunded
in infrastructure and facilities.
So they don't have the means to provide
a number of services which
are the basic services.
In order to finance the investment
we have our own resources,
we will see what they are.
We have loans.
We have land.
Public-Private partnerships,
and grants.
These are the five ways
to finance investment in cities.
Community resources.
Broadly, there are four categories
of resources.
Here are the four types of resources.
Transfers, which are issued
by the State.
Taxes which are handled locally,
property taxes, professional taxes.
Subsidies, which can be given by donors,
and loans, which we'll see in a moment,
issued by banks or also by donors.
There you have it.
This is the classic pattern,
these are community resources.
These are the resources
of the local community.
The second type of financing is loans.
Loans, whether from the bank,
from a donor,
or a specialized organization.
So the loan is used to borrow money
to create an infrastructure.
There are infrastructures
which are profitable,
and others which are not directly profitable
but are necessary to the city,
yet others which are not at all profitable,
"not necessary,"
and we can question the relevance
of building this type infrastructure.
These are the infrastructures
or facilities of prestige,
but in the typical case, at the start,
we borrow money to pay for
the infrastructure that we'll put in place,
so this infrastructure has to be profitable
in order to provide a return,
to pay the interest and finally
so that the loan that we took out
can be repaid.
So there is a whole series of mechanisms,
a whole series of conditions
or conditionalities if it's a city
who is borrowing or if it's a State,
but it's important to know
that it's something used
relatively little by cities, why?
Because they have relatively restricted
financial capacities.
States borrow, for the most part,
massively.
The cities in the North are
constantly borrowing.
In the South of Africa it's something
much more rare, why?
Because they don't necessarily
have the potential to then
repay their loan.
So in order to borrow,
we must prove the ability
to repay what has been borrowed.
The valuation of land is a way
to obtain money, for a local community,
in the form of taxes,
in the form of taxes on capital gains.
We will come back later
to these questions,
but we have two possibilities,
either on the lands not yet urbanized--
We saw in a previous video
how the pressure
will be on the non-urbanized
peripheral areas for now.
We can say that we will urbanize
these areas, and we can,
particularly through taxation,
capture a part of the land value.
In the centers where we continue
to build infrastructure,
or where public transportation
is being developed,
we are creating a land value appreciation
due to the centrality and the density
and this increase in value
should be captured,
at least partially,
to help pay for facilities.
We will come back to this a little later.
There is also the possibility
of public-private partnership,
where the investment is made jointly
by private and public sources,
and then often the management
is handled by the private sources,
who pay the dividends,
or who pay a return to the public
and after a given number of years,
the investment, the infrastructure
returns directly to the public sector.
So there exist as many types
of partnerships possible,
as there are types of contracts possible,
we won't go into detail,
but it's something very common
in today's cities,
That is, one makes
these joint investments.
If the municipality doesn't have
the possibility to invest,
it will be the private sector who
will invest, and will pay,
in the form of a fee, each year,
a certain sum to the municipality.
Finally there are grants,
let's not forget that in certain contexts,
the donor is extremely present,
and not only in borrowing
but lending, with interest.
There is also a certain sum available
and often for studies,
planning studies in particular.
It's in the form of grants,
and it's a country,
via the World Bank, via a donor
who gives, without consideration,
a sum for studies.
We are rarely dealing
with large infrastructures
but there are bilateral co-operations
which make grants without consideration,
even for large infrastructures.
Bilaterally, it is possible.
Multilaterally, often grants are given
for investment in studies
more than in infrastructure.
There you have very quickly
the few types of financing possible,
locally, for a city.
In a very concise manner
we have been able to see
which are the first mechanisms
for the financing of cities.