Planning & Financial Resources
African cities: Intro. to Urban Planning
Cities have financing needs.
They have infrastructure
and facilities needs.
They need to pay for the infrastructure
and finance this infrastructure,
but they rarely have the means to do so.
Earlier we saw the possible mechanisms
between loans and taxation,
and we'll see more specifically
which may be the levers,
particularly when it comes to real estate,
which allow for an increase in local revenues.
It is possible to look for them elsewhere,
but there are also local possibilities
to increase some of these revenues,
and we'll see that
this is directly linked,
directly connected, to the urban plan.
The problems are numerous,
because the available resources
do not meet the need,
but one of the main problems today
lies in decentralization.
Now decentralization itself
is not a problem.
We've delegated
a certain number of powers
from the central government
to local organizations,
but we've delegated these powers
and these responsibilities
to these organizations
without necessarily budgeting for them.
So we find ourselves in a situation
where the local organizations
have more work to do
without having more money budgeted
to accomplish it.
That is the heart of the problem,
that we are in a situations where
municipalities are in dire need of means
with which they might accomplish
all that they are tasked with.
Revenue sources are two-fold.
There are property taxes
and activity taxes.
For this, as we'll see, the property
clearly needs an address or a cadastre
in order to collect these taxes.
But we have within this plan
taxes on property and activity.
There are three challenges.
The informal, how I can capture
part of this informal activity.
The question of property,
and the question of economic activity.
These are the challenges to secure
resources for a local government,
is to work on these three possible levers.
The question of informality
is relatively simple.
How do we handle an activity
that is by definition informal?
How can we succeed in capturing
part of its resources?
Because it does have resources,
because the economic activity,
while poorly paid, is paid.
So we can come up with mechanisms
to capture a small portion
of this activity.
To do this we can, for example,
impose a tax on street vendors.
Now these street vendors
are accounted for and must pay,
each day, each week,
a tax to the municipality.
These are relatively low taxes,
the costs to collect them is significant
in relation to the low taxation,
but in the whole scheme
of informal activity
this reaches amounts
which can be significant.
It requires a systematic approach
so that this revenue source
becomes a real source of revenue.
When it costs more to collect the taxes
than those collected,
we must ask ourselves if it is not
a problem in the system.
But even with the informal,
there is no problem
when it comes to collecting taxes,
we must just know how and
on which types of activities.
When it comes to transportation,
it's the same thing.
We can collect taxes on private buses,
which are by definition informal,
at least organized
in a totally informal way.
Real estate value.
I'll return to our city plan,
with the city center, here.
There are two types of real estate values.
For this entire urban extension here
I can tax the price of my parcel,
I can collect tax upon its purchase
but also an annual tax.
This tax must then be applied
to the costs of roadways, electricity.
I'm oversimplifying,
but this is exactly what it's about.
We take it once, at the time
of the transaction, or annually.
Here too, the more roadways I build,
the more I densify key zones,
the more my value will increase,
and thus the land value will increase,
and the greater the appreciation
on my real estate.
We can imagine a mechanism
which would allow us to capture
this appreciation, at least partially,
and this will then allow for
the financing of our infrastructure.
The case study, my subway route,
which we saw in Rabat,
in a previous video,
allows for the creation
of a real estate appreciation.
We must find the mechanisms
which allow us,
in the case of the sale or rent
of an apartment,
to capture part of this appreciation,
which will in return pay for
the infrastructure
which I put in place
to create this appreciation.
Thus it's a cycle, a virtuous cycle,
the only problem being that as soon as
we say we'll capture this appreciation,
there is a whole series
of possible circumventions
which will allow us
to keep these official values,
and then to leave the informal
to avoid paying,
or being able to pay these taxes.
But we must keep in mind that,
in the case of our urban plan,
of our urban planning,
whether in the outskirts or in the center,
all the infrastructure that I plan
is directly interconnected
with local finances.
This is to say that there is
an enormous influence
of my urban plan, of my master plan,
and of the way in which I plan
on these local finances.
Urban planning has an enormous influence
on infrastructure costs.
We've seen this
in housing developments,
but there is also an influence
on the appreciation which
one may or may not create.
So we must play both sides
when planning,
on the one hand to limit investment costs,
and at the same time allow for
an appreciation on these investments
so that we can, in turn, tax them.
In sum, there is an economic activity,
we can be taxed.
The more it prospers,
the more taxes we'll collect,
which is to say that the city plan,
the master plan,
should enable us to provide
a certain amount of land,
or through its infrastructure,
the necessary conditions
for the development of economic activity.
It is always these sweeping ideas,
this wishful thinking,
the infrastructures needed for
the development of an economic activity.
But this is what it's about.
At the same time,
it is about land offers,
and about offering
accessibility to them.
Accessibility, not only to the land,
not only to the city.
If I apply a global view,
the fact that, for example,
When some countries allow
easy entry without a visa,
and as such allow the stream
in and out of people,
this allows for
the development of activity.
If while seeking to develop this activity
you are subject to constraints
significant enough that you are
no longer interested in its development,
then finally you will go and develop
somewhere else.
There are some who are captive,
because they are in the city,
and won't leave it to go to another city
to develop their activity,
but for economic activity
coming from the outside,
to position oneself
at an international level
requires total accessibility,
and this accessibility passes through
the airport system, the visa system,
and all the other things
which make it so that,
yes, it is fluid and easy to come and go,
or no, it is extremely difficult to come
and work or invest in this or that city.
Here I am truly taking the perspective
of a foreign investor
who comes to invest in this or that city.
Now, here too,
what I wished to show quickly is
that there is a direct link between
urban planning and finances.
The cost, the cost of urbanization,
and, on the other side,
the possibility of capturing,
via taxation,
the resources which can then
be invested elsewhere.