Land registry
African cities: Intro to urban planning
Land registry is different
than addressing, why?
Because it allows to see
all the properties.
On the address, the whole
property is indicated,
in square meters
and with the owner's name.
In legal terms, the cadastre
allows greater security.
In contrast, it allows
to know the entire land,
and it enables the taxation
of a certain number of owners.
Land registry is not a new concept,
it's been used for a long time.
Since land property exists,
it has always been made in a plan.
When we talk about Land Registry,
we mean land ownership.
And possession of lands.
Land Registry is a sort of ID
for land ownership.
There is a plot, its owner
and some features.
There are three land registry missions:
technical, property and tax.
The cadastre is
a two dimensional representation,
a mapping of the city.
There is a number of plots with a database
attached to the representation.
So we have both alphanumerical data
and geographical data.
The tax cadastre allows the listing
of all personal and real properties,
and consequently the taxation.
The land registry is not created
only to know who the people are
and where they live, but also
for taxation and levy purposes.
The legal land registry
is a security of land ownership.
The plot of these many square meters
located at such place
is registered somewhere
as Mr John Doe's property.
Then, the technical land registry,
allows a sort of city plan
to help making decisions
for all networks and infrastructures.
It becomes a tool for daily
urban management.
We realize that when making urban plans,
specific background maps are necessary.
The technical cadastre can play this role.
But for the land registry
to be used as such,
just like tax or legal land registry,
it must be updated on a regular basis.
Each move, each change and each new owner
must be registered in the cadastre.
Each new plot must be identified
and put in the database.
It's major work with high resource costs.
Most cities do not have the resources
to update the land registry.
They often have the resources
to create it and its layers,
but it remains untouched for years.
Yet the land registry is only interesting
if regularly updated.
Consequently, even if it demands
a lot of resources,
once in place and updated
it enables better returns
for the local economy.
So a part of the collected taxes
should be reinvested
to update the cadastre.
It's a whole system
that needs rethinking.
In some countries,
there is the land registry,
in others, the law on taxation,
on land ownership,
but no one pays it because
no one asks for it.
There is still a long way to go.
This is to say that land registry
or addressing should have
their biggest impact on local finances.
The idea is not to have populations
paying, no matter what,
but that today, in our cities,
creating equipment and infrastructures,
or providing services, etc., has a cost.
And we must find mechanisms
to be able to cover the costs.
For example, having people
paying for these costs,
the wealthiest people of course,
we can't ask people squatting the land
to pay a tax, even if it were possible.
Tax is not individual, it serves
a collective effort
which enables, not to replenish
the government budget,
but to create a daily management
of lands where we are.
This is extremely important, because
it is not in the spirit of the age today,
but we have to realize that the lack
of infrastructures and facilities
in the African cities
comes also from the fact that
people do not see why
they should pay taxes and levies.
Yet it's exactly to make up
for this deficit that taxes must be paid.