Hi! I'm Nettra Pan.
And I'm Shirah Foy.
You'll be seeing the both of us
throughout this MOOC
with tips and information
on how to make the most of this course.
We're both based at EPFL,
the Swiss Federal Institute of Technology
in Lausanne, Switzerland.
EPFL has established
amazing long term partnerships
with outstanding academic institutions
across the African continent.
In this video, we're going
to be introducing to you 5 entrepreneurs
who are facing issues similar to the ones
you're going to be learning about
in this course.
In the next few months, we're planning
to add more interviews
to our archives from West Africa,
South Africa, and around the world.
(Nettra) We caught up
with the entrepreneurs
that you'll be meeting this week
in Ethiopia, Kenya, Rwanda, and Uganda.
They work in a range of industries
from medical technologies to agriculture
to mobile technologies and finance.
But the one thing
that they all had in common
was the entrepreneurial mindset.
They brought resources together
to create value where before,
there were little or none.
The other thing that they had in common
was that they all shared
a defining entrepreneurial moment,
decision, or event.
Finally, they all engaged
in the long process
of developing their venture.
As they introduce themselves,
really try to put yourself
in their situation
and think about how you would've
brought together resources
in similar conditions
with the same constraints.
Because resource constraints are
a challenge faced by every entrepreneur
in every country and in every industry.
OK. Let's meet some entrepreneurs.
Our first featured entrepreneur,
Joel Macharia,
adopted the entrepreneurial mindset
at a very young age.
This led him to start
a financial news company
and a financial consulting business
among others.
I like how Joel talked about
the mental strength required
to be a successful entrepreneur.
This is especially important
for high growth tech entrepreneurs
who are often working in fast paced
and high stress environments.
In a way, you're going to be seeing
how Joel talks about
this process of entrepreneurship
as going from a no to a yes.
He says that for every one year,
you can expect to hear
the word no about 100 times.
Along his entrepreneurial process,
he also talks about
how important it was for him
to have the support
of his friends and family.
With the support
and his mental determination,
he managed to perfect his offer
for investors and clients,
transforming all
of those noes to a big yes.
(chattering children)
My name is Joel Macharia.
I'm 28 years old.
I'll be 28 in August.
I'm the founder of Capital Associates,
which I started in August of 2007
when I was 21.
Capital Associates is currently
a financial consulting business
focused on small businesses
and helping them figure out
how to manage their money,
how to access capital,
and just kept to be proper businesses
when it comes to running
and handling their finances.
On top of that,
we're building an online platform
that will allow
retail investors, individuals
to invest in the Nairobi Stock Exchange
providing them the tools, tips, tutorials
on how to get started and how to invest.
That platform is called Abacus
from the old calculator.
I started my interest
in the financial markets
in the Nairobi Securities Exchange
or the Stock Exchange as it was known.
I started back when I was in high school.
When in my last year and my fourth form,
we had a trip to the NSE.
I couldn't understand how people
seem to make money out of nothing,
pieces of paper that were selling
for some reason
or the other at higher and higher prices.
I wasn't used to not understanding
concepts so it became an obsession.
I guess I liked math.
This was something mathematical,
or it felt very mathematical.
In 2004 when I graduated
from high school--
actually after my KCSO, I went
into the Nairobi Stock Exchange,
and I asked them
to give [an introduction].
I got a job doing data entry
somewhere in the filing rooms
and full records
that were being digitized.
But I felt like
I wasn't learning anything.
They didn't give me
an opportunity to learn
about how the market actually worked.
So I left and started to do
my own research.
I spent all day in a cybercafe cafe
because back then 3G
hadn't picked up.
It was really expensive
to get online on your phone.
We didn't have WiMax connections.
We didn't have free Wi-Fi.
We didn't have cable connections
into the homes.
So you know, for 500 shillings,
a shilling a minute,
I'll have a whole day's worth of surfing.
I'm going and go to Investopedia.
I still remember this.
I loved Investopedia.
I'd copy a lot of
their tutorials, explanations,
and how the market worked
and what was what.
I'd paste that to a one document,
and then save that, and then go home
and use that and read that all day.
I'd read it and then
go to the Stock Market.
I'll call my stockbroker
and ask several questions.
I borrowed money from my dad
to invest in the stock market
when there's an IPO coming up.
The IPO did very well.
I turned that into other investments
because it went up.
I sold my share.
Instead of taking the money out,
I decided to buy other shares.
My dad also got interested.
He asked me to take him through
while I was doing to teach him.
That's how I got started
teaching people around
how to invest in the stock exchange.
Between 2004 when I graduated
from high school and 2007,
the market was on a tear.
It was bull market and it hit
It's highest peak in 2006.
It was a success investment.
That's where everybody wanted
to put their money into.
It was very easy for me--
(door bell rang)
- Sorry.
- It's okay.
I was very easy for me
to get more and more people
be interested in learning.
What happened is they'd learned
how the market worked.
The next thing they want is--
they'd be like, "Here,"
They'll give me a sum,
"Here are 100,000 shillings.
Why don't you pick the shares?
You know I'm a doctor,
I have patients to deal with.
300,000 shillings. Invest this for us."
That's why I started Capital Associates.
It was ideally you're partnering
in capital.
(children chattering)
My first entrepreneurial experience,
I think what I do remember
was actually trading food.
I think it must've been, what,
nine years old, where my mom paid.
We had an account to a small eatery
very close to the school where I was at.
We'd go over, eat I think up to
30 shillings, and then go back to school.
My mom would pay this,
either at the end of the day--
This was within our office complex.
I remember going in and taking chapatis,
which is some flat kind of bread.
We marketed it to school
and exchanging that.
I'd have five chapatis
and I'd sell those in school.
I trade one chapati
with somebody who had rice,
another one for somebody
who had beans so I had my meal.
Then I'd sell that at three
and buy sweets.
I think that's [las de alias]
I can remember.
I do remember selling bread
in high school.
Airtime, I mean cell phones
had just become the thing.
I was a prefect in high school
so I can get away with a lot of things
so people brought me
their cell phones to keep for them
and charge, and just make sure
they didn't get confiscated
by the rest of the prefects.
Selling Airtime,
selling bread in the school,
writing letters, poetry.
Poetry was actually
one of the things I did a lot of.
I remember my trademark.
Poem would be the first letter of--
so it spelled the name going down
and then using each letter
[at the beginning] of the sentence.
Then of course, after high school,
it's been pretty much
different experiences,
experimenting with exporting handicrafts.
under the African Growth
and Opportunity Act
which went into the US tax-free,
sold cars, imported.
My business partner had a cousin
who would send
the cars over from the UK.
Then we would sell them here.
Then we put money together,
bought accident vehicles, write-offs
and fix them up and put them
back on the road and sold them.
I mean it's been a varied
set of experiences.
The [alias] I can remember
it's actually the chapatis back in--
must've been eight or nine years old.
(chattering children)
One my favorite quotes
says that entrepreneurship
is living a few years of your life
in a way most people won't,
to live the rest of it
in a way most people can't.
It's actually a difficult thing.
You have to be ready for it
and never give up because that's where--
Get your resources in place
in terms of personal support.
Spouse, make sure they know what it is.
Parents, family, get those
because those are the things
that will matter the most.
(chattering children)
An entrepreneur will get
that [person] eight hours a day
that they can sell.
Find 5 of them, the funding
to build an office
and then go out and get the business.
Make sure that all five have--
by pulling all this
and paying all these costs,
then it's left with something
on top of it, which is the profit.
That role is a very solitary role.
It's a very difficult role.
I mean noes exceed yeses
by a factor of 1 to 100.
So for every one year,
you probably need
to go through 100 noes.
The thing you can do
is to prepare yourself mentally
to realize that you need
to keep your perspective.
You need to always remember
what you're looking for.
(chattering children)
If I was to offer advice
to an entrepreneur
who's thinking of going
into entrepreneurship
or somebody who's thinking
of going into entrepreneurship,
invest in yourself.
That would be what I tell them.
Ideally, what happens is that,
for very, very long time--
I mean, by the classical definition
of what an entrepreneur is,
it's somebody who puts
resources together.
I know guys who have been
in business seven years.
They have been researching seven years,
and they still haven't figured out
how to get started.
There will never be
a right time for anything.
You always get started now.
Make the decisions.
Be decisive. Move forward.
Then pick the results as they're coming.
Then make the next decision.
(interviewer) Thank you very much.
Many of you may be familiar
with the serial entrepreneur,
Richard Branson.
When asked by a journalist,
"Why did you go into business?"
Richard Branson says that he realized
that he never actually wanted
to go into business.
He says he was just interested
in creating things.
Well, our next entrepreneur
sounds a lot like Richard Branson.
His name is Yohans Wodaje.
Like Branson, Yohans, wasn't fixated
on the idea of going into business.
He says he didn't even know
what the word "entrepreneur" meant
until very recently.
Yohans simply brought resources together.
This was medical information
with the web platform
and then became medical services
with mobile technology.
Slowly but surely, Yohans brought
resources together to create value.
When he was feeling stretched,
that's when he sought business partners
and staff to help him sustain his venture.
Another thing to listen for Yohans's story
is how he de-risked
his venture along the way.
At the beginning
of an entrepreneurial process,
the chance that a venture
will fail is very high
compared to the chances
that it will succeed.
Yohans says that in a developing country,
the risks are even higher.
That's why it's so important
to develop your venture
in a way that reduces risks.
Let's switch over it to Yohans.
(chattering children)
I was born and raised
in Ethiopia here in Addis.
I went to medicine school here.
I'm a medical doctor by profession.
That's how I'm related to medicine.
I worked in the rural parts of Ethiopia
right after medicine school.
During that time,
I was thinking about what I could do
because I wanted to do
something on my own.
Also, it was very visible to me
the scale of limitations
in infrastructure we have in this country.
So I got interested in systems,
the health systems.
Then when I came back to the city
after working
in the rural parts of Ethiopia,
I had the opportunity to work
with friends from other walks of life
who are in technology and engineering.
We just set up websites
in the hopes of creating a platform
for people to get access
to health information
in their local language, into Amharic,
and also thinking of expanding it
to other local languages.
With that endeavor,
we set up this website.
Eventually, I got introduced
to another company
that was working on increasing access,
ability of services to people
by creating a platform
that allows people
to access different services
on their mobile phones.
Then it became a nice marriage
within these two companies,
rises up my company,
Telemed Medical Services
and partner up
with BelCash Technology Solutions,
which is a company,
that the mobile enabler company.
We set up product for Hello Doctor
that allows people to access
health advisory services
using their mobile phones
or any phone actually
and be able to talk
or consult with a doctor.
(chattering children)
I actually learned
that word very recently.
(interviewer giggles)
If you're asking me, I think it was
when I was in high school.
I saw people that I looked up to
that were doing things,
that started things.
I kind of had the desire
to also do something
or to start something.
(chattering children)
I cannot quite put a finger
on what's really attracted me
to starting something on my own
and becoming an entrepreneur.
But I've always been passionate
when I get interested
in a certain thing, whatever it is.
It could be music.
It could be whatever thing
I start thinking about,
I tend to be passionate about it
to continue to dwell on it,
and have the urge to take it
sort of in my own way.
I can't quite see that as the thing
that attracted me about it.
Also, there's a lot of things
that I feel about
doing something on your own,
or starting something on your own.
You cannot do anything on your own.
You basically start something on your own
and eventually built the team
that helps you do it.
The beautiful thing about that,,
I think the most fulfilling feeling
is that the sense of creating
something or starting something.
That's a very fulfilling feeling.
(chattering children)
I did feel I had the skills
to be able to do what I had in mind,
which was create a platform
to be able to teach people
or to help people access information.
That's why we were doing it
when we started the website with friends.
We didn't have a company then.
The need to create a company
came later on as things progressed.
I really didn't have time
to stop and reflect
on whether I can set up a company
and run a company or anything like that.
It just sort of happened.
Eventually,
once it actually started to grow
--grow in a sense
like very [small], yeah?--
It stopped becoming just me,
and I started hiring people.
When those things came,
I actually got the sense of what it means.
This is really a company.
People are relying on us
so we're hiring people.
We have to make paycheck.
We have to make payroll every month
and all those questions.
Then we start asking those questions.
Am I really going to push through?
Are we going to be able to do this?
You've already done something
that you feel like you could.
(children chattering)
I guess from my experience, the advice
I can give to aspiring entrepreneurs
is to think of two things.
One, that you may not be able
to do it all on your own.
That may mean that you have
to give a share of your bread.
But if you want to make things happen
and get things moving,
I think it's really smart to
look into partnerships.
It really helps not just in terms
of getting things to roll out fast,
not just in terms of
lowering your initial costs.
It's also very helpful
in terms of having a party.
When you're doing good,
your partner may be not doing well
and use the one that's giving the push
and then vice versa.
In your [...], you have a partner
that's saying like,
"It has worked out well for us, so come."
It sort of pushes each other.
Find the right marriage
and always do things, make things easier.
Whatever you can do by partnering
and giving it to the right people
to do themselves and sharing
I think is a good strategy.
That has helped us.
In any developing country,
--I don't think it's very unique
to Addis Abbaba or Ethiopia--
there's a lot of things
that could test your patience.
Most developing countries
are just starting
to really make robust infrastructure
when it comes to--
especially if you work in the IT sector.
Telecom services can be
not so reliable at times and tricky.
But it's important to understand
that in mostly like that,
it's important to strategize for it
to sort of mitigate that risk
from the outset.
That's one thing that's unique
to functioning in an emerging market,
I think, that we have had to deal with.
As we're growing,
so is our telco industry.
We're sort of learning at the same time.
It's important like I say,
to be patient and understand,
and actually develop the relationship
and that forces
investing in the relationship.
- Okay. Thank you very much.
- You're welcome.
Up next is an inspiring young woman
named Clarisse Iribagiza,
who started her company
while still in university
in the year 2010.
This was a time when access to information
was a big problem in Rwanda.
On the other hand,
high levels of mobile penetration
with over 90 % of the population
having access to mobile phones
presented a huge opportunity.
With HeHe Labs, Ltd, Clarisse created
a content and feedback
management application,
first via SMS and now
via smartphone applications.
The system leveraged
existing infrastructure
by letting people receive new information
on devices they already owned.
Clarisse doesn't mention that here,
but they actually lost
one of HeHe Labs' early clients
when the client themselves
lost their license to operate.
This was a huge blow to her team's morale
as that particular client
had brought a lot of optimism
and income to the venture.
Needless to say, HeHe Labs
recovered and has moved on.
Clarisse's story shows
just how unpredictable and exciting
the entrepreneurial journey can be.
(chattering children)
(sound of a passing car)
Well, my name is Clarisse Iribagiza.
I'm 26 years old. I'm a computer engineer.
(interviewer) Okay.
Please tell us about your venture.
HeHe Labs is a mobile
technologies company.
We're almost five years old now.
We've been building
mobile information systems
across East Africa,
in the sectors of agriculture, healthcare,
transportation, and education.
(interviewer) Beautiful!
What attracted you
to starting your own business?
When we founded HeHe Labs,
I was part of a college group
that was working on a project.
We were just really inspired
by the ability to impact change
with the skill set that we had.
Given the environment that we were in
that really encouraged entrepreneurship,
it was quite easy for us to get started.
(chattering children)
I never quite imagine myself
becoming an entrepreneur
in the context of founding a company.
But as a child, I always worked on
different projects
to sort of solve whatever problem
I saw around myself.
Maybe it was a class project or something
with my friends, with my family.
I was always around
just building solutions.
That's what I define as entrepreneurship.
(noise of cars passing)
I would say that we're
in the mobile technology space
because when it comes to
information technologies,
we believe that it's a great opportunity
to connect people to information.
We know that information is empowering.
When it comes to leveraging
the mobile phone as a platform
for delivering our services,
I would say that it's as basic
as the fact that a lot of Rwandans
have access to a mobile device
close to 70%.
It's pretty much the easiest way
to get to the last man
and to get to the last mile
when delivering the information
that we need for people to access.
(cars honking, children chattering)
I think the one skill that's needed really
is just the willingness to learn.
A lot of what we do even as a business is
we're always trying out new things
so we need to learn every single day.
I think that the ability to learn
new things was what stood out for me
as an ability to help me become
an entrepreneur.
(interviewer)
Did you develop other skills
as you were building the business?
I did develop a lot of other skills,
skills around leadership, collaboration,
business development
as well as technical skills
that include finance
and other things around product design,
which I've come to pick up along the way.
(sound of passing cars)
(interviewer) Did you face any challenges?
Yes. I have faced a couple of challenges
mostly because we've pretty much
been doing new things
every single day here at HeHe Labs.
Most of our challenges include
just figuring out what's next –
that's always difficult –
finding the resources to make it happen,
working in an environment
where some of the ideas
that we have are relatively new
so just getting people to believe
in our products and use them.
Those are some
of the challenges that we face.
Let's go back to the idea
of the entrepreneurial mindset,
which is the willingness
to see opportunity
in uncertain and rapidly
changing conditions.
Stone Atwine, our next entrepreneur,
will tell you about
how he saw opportunity
in a problem faced by his grandmother;
the difficulty of receiving money.
While others may have looked at
the situation and seen bank fees,
complex regulations as chaos,
Stone and his team saw this area
as representing a problem
that needed to be solved
and a problem that had
a lot of value behind it.
The interesting thing about
the entrepreneurial mindset
that Stone and his team exemplifies
is that it's something
that doesn't just happen
at the beginning
of the entrepreneurial process.
It's something that you'll need
throughout the experience.
As Stone and his team
developed the idea behind remit.ug,
there were moments when he thought
they should close shop.
He says, "OK, guys, can we wrap this up?"
Luckily, Stone and his team
still saw value in what they were doing.
They persevered
and they're still doing this today.
An inspiration.
(chattering children)
My name is Stone Atwine.
I'm 32 years old from Uganda.
I started computer science at school.
I'm an entrepreneur.
(interviewer) Fantastic!
Tell us about your venture.
What we've done is we've built
a web-based platform, remit.ug,
which helps people in the diaspora
or people all over the world
to send money from their cards,
that's Visa and MasterCard,
to mobile money in Africa.
We've started with Uganda,
delivery into Uganda.
Initially, I had this idea
to transfer money back home
from the diaspora,
from all over the world.
I noticed that there was--
their current system was broken
in terms of it's very inconvenient,
and it's expensive.
I had this idea and I knew
I couldn't do it alone,
so initially, I shared it
with a friend of mine,
Teddy Ruge.
At that point, I was living in Nairobi.
I was working in Nairobi,
and Teddy was living in Texas.
Because he had all these connections
with the diaspora and was working,
doing work along those lines,
I chose to tell him.
What was interesting is
when I told Teddy about my idea,
he told me that he also had
the same idea
and was actually facing the same problem,
that same challenge
of sending money home from the US.
He actually sent me his notes
that he had drawn up from before.
Basically, we were both
trying to do the same thing.
We said, "OK, we're going to try
and find some money and do this,"
but we share little bit.
Then at the beginning of 2013,
I came back home from Nairobi to stay.
At that point, Teddy was
also actually in Uganda.
One evening, I was hanging out
talking to a guy.
We're just talking about
the local tech ecosystem,
another friend called Collin.
I told him that we want
to do this, me and Teddy,
we want to do something
along money transfer.
Collin goes like, "Hey,
we've actually been talking about this."
Collin has had
this other gentleman, David.
They had also been planning
on building something like this.
Actually, they already had a prototype.
These are four people.
All of us just by coincidence,
we talked about doing the same thing.
Each of us has done a lot about it.
Essentially, I called up Teddy
that evening. We sat down.
One hour later, we had agreed
to act together.
Within the next week,
we had just set the company
and gotten everything done.
We continued and built
a minimum viable product.
We've been testing, and now
we are ready for the big turn.
(sound of passing cars)
We saw the need to do this,
to start this company
because one,
is we were actually facing
this problem ourselves.
Then you sit down and think and say...
in my case, I'm like,
"Why is it so hard to send
money to my grandmother?
I mean it shouldn't be this hard."
Because I was in Nairobi, there was M-Pesa.
There was mobile money in Uganda.
The first thing was, "How come
these two networks can't talk
so I can't send this money as easy
as when I'm in Uganda?"
Actually, initially,
what I used to do is I would ask,
I'd do a bank transfer
to a friend of mine in Uganda.
My friend would pull out the money
and put it in my Ugandan mobile money.
Then I would send it
to my grandmother, so it was hectic
because my grandmother
is not interested in the banks,
and all that stuff.
She didn't even have access to the banks.
It was mostly because of the struggle.
Then seeing the solution and saying,
"Oh, we could actually use
mobile to pull this off."
Starting this was essentially
because we were suffering
from this problem of transferring money.
Then you sit down and say,
"Ah, it's out of necessity."
Then we were like, "We can actually
make money out of this.
We'd actually start a business
and in the process help people."
I remember in the beginning
when we were starting,
we were looking for a lot
of information about remittances
and this business of money transfer.
We read reports from the World Bank,
from the African Development Bank,
from various NGOs.
They were all pointing to the fact
that the current money
transfer system is very expensive.
It's very inconvenient.
It was almost a dual point
like two big guys who do this.
They're charging you.
I mean moving money
from Johannesburg to Kampala
could cost up to 20%
of the money you're trying to move.
If you're trying to move $200,
you could end up paying $40, $34.
If you're moving $100, you could pay $18.
That's how we started.
We sat down. We looked at
the costs of sending money.
We said we could actually put
only one fee.
Our fee is just one 5.4% and charge that.
It will be much, much easier.
We bring down the cost
on the persons we're helping--
we're helping both
the senders and the recipients
because they get more money
in their pockets.
(interviewer) It's 1.5% that you take?
- Us?
- Yeah.
- 5.4%.
-Oh 5.4.
5.4%. We really want to bring this down.
The reason we charge 5.4%--
we think it's high still,
but we have challenges
with like card transfer.
(man chattering)
I'm not sure.
I guess it was the need
to solve problems
that people I see every day face.
Beyond that, right from
when I was a young guy,
I was like building things.
I like building things.
Building things, I'm solving problems.
I guess it's something
that I was meant to do.
And the need to help people.
(chattering children)
The skills that make
a successful entrepreneur,
I think you really have to have
a lot of endurance.
You have to have grit, not give up.
You have to understand
what you're doing.
You have to manage to people.
That's very critical.
But I guess the most important thing
is the need to build things
and the capacity to stay that course
and make sure you follow through
all the time, every time.
(truck breaks screeching)
The advice is to really start.
You have to go out there.
You have to start.
I mean you could have
all these plans and dreams.
But if you don't take
the first step of starting,
then you're not going to go anywhere.
It is go out there, start, try, and see.
You're going to fail,
maybe you're going to do it,
but you have to start.
The biggest challenge that entrepreneurs,
potential entrepreneurs face,
I think in Africa
is not being able to find money.
But you could start.
I mean when we started,
we also didn't have all this money.
We didn't have money at all.
But we said, "We're going to do it.
We're going to do it."
We started it.
The next thing is that you must speak.
I mean the challenges
we faced with remit...
Sometimes, you're like,
"OK, guys, can we wrap this up?"
Then you say,
"But we've done so much work.
Let's try. Let's try.
Let's push. Let's move forward."
You go here. You borrow
money to bring it in.
You borrow from family, from friends.
Really, it is sticking to the business
until you reach a point
where you realize that
you're going to make it.
You make a decision and you say,
"We're not going to make it,
let's close shop."
But really, the biggest piece of advice
is to start and to stick to the business,
and work extremely hard
because you're going to work.
You're not going to get paid
for a very long time.
Up to today, we don't get paid.
So it's a huge, huge challenge.
The money issue is a problem.
It's a big problem
because you have a team of guys
who have been working now
for almost a year.
If we were sitting down
and working on this every single day,
we would be much farther.
We have to go and find money,
which we can actually bring in
to help the company.
We don't take a salary
because we don't have money.
Every little money we make,
we put back into the company.
Because of that, we also have
to actually work on the side
to get some money.
It's a challenge,
but you just have to push
and push and push and push.
You don't give up.
Our final entrepreneur for this week
helps us better understand
the idea of the entrepreneurial event.
One of the challenges
of studying entrepreneurship
is the difference in every one's journey.
Some people quit their job
and immediately register a new venture,
which creates a public record
of the founding of the company.
Others work for years,
on nights and weekends
until they are confident enough
about their venture
before deciding to quit their job
and register the company.
Samir's decision to jump into
the entrepreneurial lifestyle
seems a very clear cut.
It might not be the same for you.
The second thing to observe
about Samir's story
is how he transferred knowledge
from Kenya to the US and back to Kenya
and is constantly trying to absorb
new information like a sponge.
When you're offering
a specific product, in a specific place,
but with different cultures and habits,
making false assumptions
could kill your venture.
Let's hear more on this from Samir.
(chattering children)
My name is Samir Ibrahim. I'm 26.
My background is in finance
and international business.
(interviewer) Perfect.
Tell us about your venture.
Our company is called SunCulture.
We design and sell solar-powered
irrigation systems
that make it cheaper and easier
for farmers to grow food.
We got here in May, 2013.
Actually, we got here in October, 2012.
Since then, we have helped
hundreds of farmers across Kenya,
improved their lives by growing
high value fresh fruits and vegetables.
(chattering children)
Yes. Since I was a little kid,
I've always wanted to be an entrepreneur.
It's always been in my family.
I always said I'm going to actually
come back to the region and do something.
I'd always sold books on the side.
Little ventures on the side
while you're young is always fun,
sort of like the stereotypical
lemonade stand.
It's exciting to have made
that move. It's very fulfilling.
(children chattering)
My family has always been
small business owners and entrepreneurs.
When my co-founder and friend,
Charlie, approached me with this idea,
we decided it was the right time
to make the jump.
Charlie had started
a few companies before.
I was looking for a way to escape
the corporate America life
that I was living.
It made sense at the time
and very happy we did it.
(interviewer) What elements
of entrepreneurship
really sort of stood out to you
to be attractive in that way?
The way we look at it
is that everything great
that's ever happened in the world
started from someone starting something.
We figure if we wanted to make
some impact somehow, somewhere,
we had to start something ourselves.
That's the most attractive thing for us
is we can shape the way our company works.
We can actually live our dream
and live our vision the way we want to.
(children chattering)
I don't think anybody knows
if they have the right skills
to become an entrepreneur.
I don't know if there's a skill set
that makes a good entrepreneur,
makes a bad entrepreneur.
I think having a mindset
where no matter what,
you're not going to give up.
That resilience is something
that everyone one should have.
I'm not really sure if that's something
that you're born with.
It can be developed. I'm not sure.
But it's something that's really important.
I think anybody
that wants to be an entrepreneur
should try and should keep pushing.
Because if they really believe
in something
and if you really want to do something
for yourself, it's possible.
It's always possible.
You just have to keep crawling
through all the obstacles.
And It'll be OK.
(interviewer) I feel like
you're playing down a little bit
the kind of skills you do need
to have an entrepreneur.
At least we'd like characteristics.
If you were to sort of say like
what are the things you need
to be cognizant of,
in terms of business and apply it?
Sure. That's a good question.
The money, you need money skills
to be an entrepreneur.
If you don't have money skills,
find someone who can help you
with money skills.
You or your co-founder
or somebody in your team
has to be able to manage people.
Then you or your co-founder
or somebody in your team
needs to be able to handle the
technical side of whatever you're doing.
Taking a step back,
the reason why I think we're so lucky
is that Charlie and I come
from two separate backgrounds.
We have two very complementary skill sets.
I come from a very finance
and international business side of things
and Charlie comes from very technical...
- he's a mechanical engineer by training -
large scale solar installations.
We have two very defined hard skills
that when put together,
we can kind of handle everything.
I think that's something really important,
and not a lot of entrepreneurs realizes
you need people in your team
to cover everything.
You don't need to do it yourself,
but you need to have people in your team
who have the skills necessary
to execute what you're trying to do.
When you start a business,
you're never prepared
for the skills you'll need.
We don't come from
agriculture backgrounds.
We know everything
about agriculture right now.
It's those things where you have
to pick up hard skills along the way.
I think the most important skill
that we had to learn along the way
is to manage the emotional rollercoaster
that we go through on a daily basis.
I think that's something
that if I can go back a few years
and tell a younger Samir,
"This is something you need
to know before you start this
is that you're going to have
ups and downs on a daily basis.
You need to be able to manage that.
Otherwise, it'll eat you up."
That's actually the most difficult thing.
(chattering children)
There have been a lot of challenges
we've had to face.
Like I said, the number one challenge
in one that you're not always prepared for
is how to manage your own
psychological state.
Being an entrepreneur
is difficult. It's also very fulfilling.
Every decision you make directly impacts
the success of your company.
Every decision you make directly affects
a lot of other people as well.
There's a lot of stress.
But if you can manage the stress
and come to an understanding
you're doing this because you love it
and remind yourself that sometimes,
then it's extremely fulfilling.
That's the most difficult thing.
Learning to manage it better
is very helpful.
Yeah.
(interviewer) No other challenges?
There a lot of other challenges.
Starting a company with a new technology
in a fairly nascent agricultural market,
in a new country for us,
comes with lots of challenges.
Dealing with the operation nuances
of bringing goods into the port,
or understanding tax law,
understanding what drives people
in different part of the world,
understanding how to sell to people
in different parts of the world;
it's tough.
You can't come to a new country
and launch a business
with the same mentality
that you had when you were back
where you were before,
we were in New York.
People are different.
What drives people is different.
The way business is done,
the formalities, all different.
You have to be very flexible,
and very open,
and not have too big of a head
where you come to a place
and think you know everything;
because you don't.
You have to be able and willing
to learn the new things that come
with starting a company in a new country.
That's something that's challenging.
If you allow yourself
to sort of you sponge
and absorb a lot of information,
then you'll be fine.
- Okay, just be a sponge.
- Just be a sponge.
- Easy. You make it sound so easy.
- That will be the tagline.
Nairobi is such a concentrated pool
of awesome people.
Working in an environment
where there are so many people
who are shooting for such amazing goals,
it gives us an opportunity to
bounce ideas off to people very closely.
The sort of starting community
here is very tight.
It makes working here much easier
because you can speak to people
about the problems you're going through
and the challenges that you have.
You always have peers
to bounce things off a bit.
It really helps you
when you're starting a company.
I hope you found those interviews
insightful and inspiring.
In the next few weeks,
we'll be talking with more entrepreneurs
about their experiences
with opportunity identification,
understanding their customer,
marketing, fundraising,
and growing their venture.
Be sure to submit all
of your questions to us on Coursera,
in the quiz that is provided
because we're going to be hosting
live Google Hangout panels.
We really want to make sure
that your questions get answered
with our great panelists.
Thanks very much.
All the information is on the slide.