In this module, we will ask what is the relevance
of smart specialization strategy
In the age of global value chains or GVCs.
We show that this relevance is not challenged.
Building local capacities and the development
of transformation activities
are a key asset for the management of the
future, particularly in front of hazards
and risks caused by certain forms of governance
of global value chains.
Let's allow the economists of international
trade,
who question the need to train local industries
in the second age of globalization, speak
first.
Keith Maskus, which incidentally is also
an excellent economist of innovation
tells us: "It is not clear whether in today's
economy increasingly
dominated by global production chains,
it makes any sense to even try to encourage
the establishment of local industries
in particular areas."
A stone in our garden!
The most extreme version of this contestation
is provided
by Charles Baldwin.
Baldwin theorizes the coming of a new phase
of globalization
which he calls the "second unbundling".
Thanks to new information and communication
technology,
production stages, once assembled on the same
site,
can be decoupled within regional areas.
The competition now takes place at the production
stage
rather than at the sector.
What matters to a region is not to create
a complete industry,
but that companies take position at a particular
stage of production
and thanks to this positioning, progress,
learn and acquire
new skills fast.
Baldwin concludes that there is no reason
to spend 30 years of effort
on the establishment of a new industry, like
South Korea did
with the automotive industry.
"Joining a global value chain could create
advanced manufacturing activity
in a developing nation in a matter of months.
"he wrote.
But what Baldwin said is easily digestible
by the theory of smart specialisation.
The industrialization or economic diversification,
is probably less "lumpy".
That is to say: it is less compact and less
indivisible than yesterday,
and therefore, industrial policy or “smart
specialization”
should not necessarily aim to create a complete
industry.
That is why - you recognize this diagram that
we saw during the first week -
smart specialization is not aimed at sectoral
specialization,
a sector that we would take 20 years to build.
But the goal is the development of new activities,
or specialties, located at a finer level of
aggregation.
Ultimately, no one discusses the value of
forming local capacity,
not to cover an entire industry, but to be
in a better position
in front of global value chains at a particular
stage of production.
We see it very well by comparing what happened
in two regions specialized in the production
of shoes.
Let's start with the Sinos Valley, in Brazil.
In this region lived a set of small shoes
companies
for the domestic market.
These companies will transform when US buyers
push for high-volume production,
leading to business growth and stimulates
their evolution
in terms of quality standards and process
innovation.
However, these companies will never go very
high in the value chain,
the logistics and the design remaining the
privilege of US buyers.
And the danger of this situation is evident
when Chinese producers barge in and offer
products
that are cheaper than Brazilian products on
the US market.
The Brazilian cluster is swept aside.
This means that the positioning in a global
value chain
is in no way a guarantee to evolve and transform.
There are of course more positive cases
but the main lesson is that the ability to
learn and develop new skills
thanks to the membership of a global value
chain
depends on how the latter is governed by the
final purchaser.
It can also depend on strategic actions,
on an innovation policy conducted to ensure
the development of capacities.
And it is Baldwin himself who wonders
if the Brazilian Government should not have
encouraged and helped shoe production
businesses to diversify, to go up market.
We find here the idea of ​​smart specialization.
The smart specialization which, in the same
industry, gave much more positive results,
is the case of Portugal.
From the 2000s, the Portuguese shoe industry
is strongly affected by competition
from low-cost countries like China.
I owe this story to Jose Caldeira, an expert
on innovation
in the manufacturing industry in Portugal.
In Portugal, there are resources to be mobilized
to launch a collective action
in the field of modernization of the sector.
The technological University of Porto,
companies specializing in production technologies,
and software development companies.
Finally, some major shoe industry brands,
well positioned in terms of design and marketing.
In this context, a vast operation of entrepreneurial
discovery is coordinated
and supported by the public agency for innovation.
This is to develop advanced production technologies,
to establish flexible production
which will effectively produce small series
of differentiated products
and of high intensity design.
The promises of this new field are very big,
so much so that we quickly tip over to the
growth of a new speciality,
at the intersection of the shoe industry and
advanced
production technologies, which will lead to
a major structural transformation.
Undoubtedly, the process of entrepreneurial
discovery,
you recognize that diagram that we saw during
the 1st week,
this process was not carried out to the letter,
but the spirit is there:
a strategic area is identified,
coordinated projects are stimulated,
so that a transformative new activity emerges
and grows.
This is an almost ideal case as we discern
well the process by which
the Government led to the opening and exploring
of a new area,
by supporting the development and integration
of local capacities,
to facilitate the transition to a new specialty.
We also see how smart specialization is a
response
to a potential crisis caused by unbridled
competition on costs.
Thanks to this smart specialization, part
of the shoe industry
in northern Portugal generated new competitive
advantages
based on design and flexible production
which ranks it today in the 1st rank in Europe.
So there is nothing embarrassing in Baldwin's
words,
and other economists of international trade.
From the moment we also recognize the end
of sectoral strategies,
based on this notion of lesser compactness
or lesser indivisibility
of industrialization and diversification process,
and the need to build local capacities at
a finer level of aggregation,
to develop transformative activities that
will,
ultimately, allow companies to be better positioned.
The smart specialization strategy is a way
to regain control,
against the global value chains.