We've just said that, in the second age of
globalization,
it still seemed relevant to build local capacities
for the development of new transformative
activities.
Let's now spend five minutes on this notion
of "local".
We talked of scale,
critical mass, innovation system, agglomeration.
We have not yet said that these structures
also have to be
physically located on a certain territory.
There are a lot of agglomeration phenomena
on the net.
And it is even fairly easy to build. But this
is not enough.
A critical mass can be virtual
and many relationships between agents can
be remotely established indeed.
Why is it then recommended to have localized
capabilities
on a territory
and linked by some
physical proximity?
The general idea is that the co-location of
firms,
research partners, skilled workers
and other resources, constitute
an important engine for innovation.
So there is
an economic gain to encourage the formation
of local innovation capacities.
We can, following the economist Marianne Feldmann,
give a critical explanation.
Spatial proximity
enhances the flow of knowledge,
information, new ideas and facilitates
cognitive interactions.
The key explanation is that the knowledge
needed for innovation,
as well as for relationships between partners,
have an important tacit dimension.
We cannot write everything
and codify everything,
so that everything could be done remotely.
We must meet and talk to understand each other
and for knowledge to combine and integrate.
Physical proximity allows all of this
much better than the virtual worlds. It facilitates
communication,
increases unforeseen and surprising encounters
probabilities
that can lead to new ideas
and also the opportunity to build social relationships,
themselves conducive to the circulation of
ideas.
Let's also observe the nature of the connections
between a company
and additional capacities, research,
services, training or users
which are needed to innovate.
The company can obviously establish distance
relationships
but physical proximity
offers opportunities for observation,
interaction and mutual learning.
From this explanation,
it appears that the innovative performances
not only result of the individual effort
but also the quality of the immediate environment,
characterized by a certain density of relationships
and physical proximity
to certain key institutions.
We also observe that this effect of physical
proximity
on the quality of interactions between agents
is even stronger when companies belong to
the same industry
or related industries.
Finally, it should be noted that the co-location
of capabilities
and people has dynamic virtues,
which allow the growth and enrichment of the
agglomeration
of resources.
A territory can evolve, grow, diversify
thanks to different types of virtuous circles
arising from this physical proximity.
For example, it is more interesting to settle
somewhere
when the density of connections increases.
This produces a classic phenomenon
of self-reinforcing and tipping point.
The more firms there are,
the more possibilities of connections,
of recombinations and surprising encounters.
In addition, the increasing number of firms
on a site
strengthens factor markets - skilled workers,
specialized services -
as well as research infrastructures.
In other words, the fact that businesses are
located somewhere
will increase the attraction of this "somewhere"
and the likelihood
that others come too.
The works of Brian Arthur
that analyze the effects of positive feedback
on location
were pioneers in this field by highlighting
the strength
and the persisting influence of small events
or historical accidents
that arise very early in history
and influence the final result in terms of
agglomeration
and relational density.
But if a simple increase of the number of
firms has virtuous properties
of self-reinforcing, other factors are also
important
to magnify the effects of physical proximity.
Some economists - Agrawal and Cockburn
in particular -
identify empirically dynamic elements
creating virtuous circles
within the local innovation system.
These are important results that we should
know before designing
a smart specialization strategy
and initiate policies
to promote the growth of a new business
in a certain area of ​​specialization.
We can first mention the virtuous role of
large enterprises
who do R & D
in a particular area of ​​specialization
and create many positive externalities
in favour of the other actors operating in
the same field.
They strengthen for example the research of
local Universities,
facilitate the growth of factor markets
and improvemarkets for technologies,
thanks to the relationships they have with
small businesses.
This is the theory of Anchor Tenant.
A powerful research university in certain
areas
is also a key factor in the agglomeration
dynamic
and spatial concentration.
It enables the advancement of knowledge in
these fields,
the training of the people
who will then be innovators in the private
sector,
the undertaking of problem-solving activities
in collaboration with the industry
and finally, the creation of new firms.
Firms of different sizes are also an important
asset
for the dynamic agglomeration.
Large firms, we have just said it,
produce externalities that benefit the immediate
environment.
They also create spin-offs
which, as a rule, are installed nearby.
Symmetrically, small firms produce external
effects,
by attracting specialized services
that they cannot internalize.
Both externalities, spin-offs of large firms
and third party services attracted by small
ones,
complement each other and create a virtuous
spiral of agglomeration
and strengthening of the relational density.
The agglomeration of diverse institutions
(enterprises, research, finance, services)
can create forms of learning,
Based on synergy and hybridization
thanks to institutional mobility of people,
Which is made easy by physical proximity.
Finally,
a site, a territory
has memory.
The mobility of economic agents, the fact
that they leave a territory
does not necessarily mean a net loss of knowledge.
Those who are going keep their social relationships
with those who remain and therefore continue
to collaborate.
They leave but are not forgotten.
We thus reach
the idea of rich and dynamic innovation local
system.
A system characterized by significant agglomeration
effects,
capable to provide all the additional resources
and likely to grow
by attracting new resources
thanks to the increase of the value to be
localized there.
A system we can leave
but that has memory.
The ultimate project of a smart specialization
strategy
is to generate this dynamic,
in a small number of strategic areas.
The idea of smart specialization, which highlights
the importance of building local capacities,
recognizes this economic value of physical
proximity
and territorial roots.
But beware!
This does not mean that the process must be
closed
and that the ambition of the strategy
is autarky. In fact, it is just the opposite
for it is by having strong local capabilities
that we will be able to take advantage of
external resources
which are still essential. In other words,
the problem is not so much for a peripheral
region to choose
between a strategy
of building local critical mass and local
interactions
and a connection strategy to the outside because
the two go together.
We must constitute
strong local capabilities
through smart specialization strategy
to be able to benefit more from global interactions.
It is therefore clear that the smart specialization
strategy,
the goal of building local capacities in some
areas,
should not be an excuse to ignore or snub
the global value chains,
the international investments realized on
its territory
and the external resources to the region.
The way a strategy must be lean on these elements
of globalization
is part of the operationalization of the concept.
Again, the aim is not autarky or isolation
towards the outside
nor towards international assets placed in
its territory.
On the contrary.
only a rich and strong local system
will benefit from these external elements.
Thank you!