In this module,
we wish to challenge a misconception,
which is quite persistent.
This idea would be that smart specialization
strategy,
is good for the richest and strongest regions.
Not at all.
Although these regions, will use it profitably,
especially to correct their weaknesses,
the logic of the smart specialization strategy
is also required in the case of least developed
regions
or transition regions.
We know where this error comes from.
The neoclassical microeconomics of knowledge
of Ken Arrow until Partha Dasgupta,
an elegant and even fascinating theory
which explains that
knowledge does not need to be produced more
than once
since this piece of knowledge can be reused
indefinitely
and never be degraded by this use.
Unlike a physical good.
By going a little fast, we can then say that
some large research and innovation centres
will suffice
to produce the most sophisticated knowledge
which would then be used everywhere.
It is more reasonable
for regions non-selected as hyper centres
to abandon the economy of knowledge and innovation
to indulge in other activities of production
and services.
In this perspective,
why would Galicia do biotechnologies?
And why do we develop research
in Information Technology in Crete
while global hubs, Silicon Valley or Zürich
or a few others exist to do so
probably more effectively?
In these conditions,
no need for smart specialization
for most areas.
But if this theory is based on a relevant
argument-
"Knowledge is not destroyed by use"-
it leads to false prescriptions.
Certainly a piece of knowledge
does not need to be produced more than once.
The problem is that there is
An infinite number of knowledge pieces to
produce
which will have a particular value in socio-economic,
sectoral, geographical, climatic contexts,
which are specific.
It is in front of this huge number
of potentially achievable knowledge
and that will never be produced by Silicon
Valley
that the smart specialization strategy of
a region
makes sense because this region is probably
well placed
to produce some of this knowledge.
The essential point is that,
as Manuel Trajtenberg says regarding innovation:
"There is not only one game in town".
There are different orders in innovation.
We can radically invent at the technological
frontier
and commercialize radically new technologies,
methods and products.
But we can also innovate in other ways.
Generate “innovational complementarities”
to transform traditional sectors,
Diversify and conquer a new market,
and by adapting and transforming capabilities,
innovate in this way.
These types of innovation are less bright
than breakthrough innovation
but they will be the key mechanism
of economic growth in many regions.
It is still Trajtenberg who writes:
"Innovation should be widely distributed
over the whole spectrum of economic activities,
that is across sectors
(not just high tech)
and types of innovations
(not just formal
research and development)."
The theory behind this idea:
"There is not only one game in town"
is closely associated with the concept of
general purpose technology
that economists like Bresnahan and Trajtenberg
developed.
General purpose technologies, such as steam
engine,
the dynamo and the computer, today the information
technology
or biotechnologies give a role to play
to all regions, not just to the leader.
Indeed, a specificity of general purpose technologies
is horizontal and intersectoral diffusion
thanks to the development of applications
specific to different sectors
and the complementarity between fundamental
invention
of these technologies and application development
in user sectors.
The characteristic of a general objective
technology
is to be relevant for the whole economy
thanks to the multiple applications that are
developed.
We will say that it generates externalities
or spillovers
in the form of multiple applications
that enable innovation in many sectors.
In economics, we will say that the fundamental
inventions
of a general purpose technology
extend the frontiers of invention possibilities
for the whole economy
whereas the development of applications
changes the production function of particular
sectors .
Trajtenberg, again, writes:
"Although mostly dealing with local industries,
these innovations based on the co-invention
of applications of a general purpose technology
will ultimately impact the productivity
of a wide range of sectors in the local economy."
And when things evolve favorably,
there is therefore a general dynamics of the
general purpose technology
which can be spatially distributed
between regions specialized in fundamental
inventions
and regions specialized in the development
of applications.
Here is an example of spatial distribution
of the dynamic of a general purpose technology.
It is limited to one country only, but of
course, in reality,
this spatial distribution will usually be
global.
On the map, whilst radical inventions are
made,
for example in Helsinki, in the field
of information and communication technologies
the co-invention of applications will happen
:
in Oulu, in the field
of green information technology applied to
the mining sector,
in northern Finland,
For the forest and pulp and paper industry,
and on the coast, finally,
For what concerns the management of marine
resources.
And so Finland
is full with high-tech
but high-tech connected to local industries.
This framework suggests that every region
has a role to play
in the knowledge economy, the leaders and
the followers.
A critic of the smart specialization strategy
can then be formulated.
But you lock the followers
in a position that they can never leave.
They will forever remain followers
waiting for fundamental inventions from outside
to develop their own applications.
The answer is that
thanks to the smart specialization strategy,
we go at least from a position of "bad follower"
to a position of "good follower."
A region capable of co-inventing applications
to transform its structures.
That is to say capable of absorbing
the externalities produced by fundamental
inventions.
For this, we must form local capacities
and these clusters of competences.
We have already seen many examples in this
course.
Biotechnologies for marine resources,
the information technologies for tourism and
cultural heritage conservation,
nanotechnologies for the food industry.
Admittedly, smart specialization doesn't have
any magical properties
that would transform Galicia or Crete
into a new Silicon Valley or a new Zürich!
But the smart specialization strategy
allows at least a less advanced region
to position itself as a "good follower"
that is to say a region capable of allocating
resources
for research and innovation,
to realize at hom,
the potential for innovation offered
by radical inventions produced elsewhere.
A "good follower" and the firms that make
up
the considered innovation system
are capable to define a competition area
in which participants, some other regions,
are relatively equals in terms of capacity
and resources,
and are capable to create a viable market
niche
that will not be rapidly destroyed by the
entry of external competitors.
The regions concerned by this market niche
will compete of course
but they should also exploit the potential
of cooperation
and circulation of skills and knowledge.
Can a good follower become a leader?
Certainly yes.
But not a leader in the invention of a general
purpose technology,
rather in an application associated to a particular
sector.
Finally, a "good follower" creates "co-specialized"
assets
that is to say that the regions
with a smart specialization strategy
and the human capabilities that are formed
on site
mutually need each other.
This reduces, remember,
the famous "Midwest syndrome" risk -
young graduates who leave the region,
as we saw during the first week.
Here's a final example of a set of regions
characterized by an important fishing and
exploitation of marine resources sector.
There is a potential for innovation to achieve
for each of them
and a transformative activity to develop
on the basis of information and communication
technologies
to modernize their industry.
These areas are certainly in competition
in some markets,
but the similarity and specificity of their
strategic area
also draws a space for cooperation and circulation
of knowledge and skills,
a space that can allow each of these regions
to progress faster towards the desired structural
change.
So there is an important relation
between smart specialization strategy
as a dynamic that aims to build innovation
capacities
to change the structures and the opportunities
offered by general purpose technologies
in every region.
Other dynamics of innovation are possible
to guide smart specialization
but the dynamics of the general purpose technology
is certainly central
because it provides opportunities to all.