In this module, we talk about entrepreneurial
discovery
and show that it is an essential principle
that will help us change paradigm
in terms of innovation policy.
This is what allows a region and its government
to identify and initiate large strategic actions
without falling into a mode of central planning.
We'll talk about the theoretical basis of
this concept,
on one side Hayek and Sabel
on the fact that the State cannot know everything
and that the discovery process is an essential
aspect;
on the other hand, Hirshleifer and Kirzner,
for who discovery
has a fundamental informational dimension,
unlike innovation;
and also Haussmann and Rodrik who helped popularize
the theme
in their work in development economics.
A smart specialization strategy
seeks to identify strategic areas
in which capacities are built
for the development of new transformative
activities.
So there is a problem of information and knowledge.
How to identify these areas
and learn about the probability of success
within each of them?
There are two solutions:
the omniscient State,
the big planner who believes he has the ability
to accumulate enough information
and "ex ante" knowledge
to determine strategic priorities,
to develop a plan and then create incentives
for companies to execute the plan.
This is what Sabel calls "the principal-agent
governance."
The alternative works on the assumption that
the state does not know,
or not enough.
The knowledge about future activities
which are susceptible of transforming a sector,
of modernizing, diversifying it,
is not obvious, not trivial.
It is only very partially in books
or in consulting firms.
It is dispersed and divided, it can be hidden,
it often results from the combination and
integration
of dispersed and fragmented knowledge.
And above all, it cannot be fully produced
and known "ex ante".
A large fraction of this knowledge is unknown
and will gradually be discovered
according to the actual process of exploration
of selected areas.
It was Charles Sabel who wrote it.
"What happens when we assume that there are
no principals,
no omniscient State,
with robust and panoramic knowledge needed
for a directive role?"
Any systematic information produced "ex ante"
is obviously useful, we will see it in the
3rd week,
but will still be insufficient.
There is a discovery process to carry out
and
who can do it if not the innovation actors
themselves
the entrepreneurs, the researchers, the leading
users
perhaps even citizens?
The main difference between the two solutions
opposes an information research mechanism
based on the assumption that we can know everything
before,
and that our decisions will therefore be fully
informed;
and a discovery mechanism,
according to which we do not know a lot before,
at least not enough
and that a fundamental element of surprise
accompanies the discovery mechanism.
We could retake and detail many methods
which aimed to identify strategic industries,
key sectors, technological complexity levels
that industries should get over.
All these methods, particularly popular in
the 60-80-90's,
are more sophisticated than each other
and are alike in that they leave no room
to entrepreneurial discovery and to that element
of surprise.
These methods basically rest on a form of
illusion.
The illusion that it is possible to know everything
in order to plan everything
in a centralized and scientifical way.
The production of "ex ante" information is
obviously useful but
we must make the difference between an approach
aimed at a supposedly complete "ex ante" information
to achieve a central plan, which does not
seem relevant to us,
and an "ex ante" information of a stylised
facts type,
like those written here,
or knowledge of the existing structures and
resources,
what we will see in the third week,
of which we recognize the incompleteness and
which we will use
as a guide for entrepreneurial discovery.
This fundamental principle of
incompleteness of "ex ante" information to
decide priorities,
logically and inevitably, leads
into the principle of entrepreneurial discovery
or "self-discovery".
We can ask ourselves: what are we trying to
discover?
The information that has to be discovered
in order to create a smart specialization
strategy,
is structured by the objective of the considered
policy.
In our case, it is a compound element
which answers two questions.
Is this area strategic?
The answer is given by the probability Pa.
Can this strategic area be successfully exploited?
The answer is given by the Pap probability.
The Pap discovery is on the early phases
of development of the new activity,
on the ability of actors to coordinate
and to form a critical mass for the development
of this activity.
We must understand that the answer to the
second question,
on ?ap involves concrete investments
in exploratory projects, platforms, networks.
This is to explore the strategic area
and learn about the possibilities of development
in this area,
the formation of a critical mass and the potentials
for structural transformations.
And it is probably at this level
that the discovery of new knowledge,
along the process,
and the surprise element that accompanies
it will be the most marked.
The social value of the entrepreneurial discovery
process
is this informational value that allows the
State
to answer the two questions listed
and therefore to make decisions at both levels.
What strategic area?
What chances of success in each area?
The entrepreneurial discovery process
also informs companies
on opportunities in such and such field.
Entrepreneurial discovery
is basically the mechanism
which enables to solve the information problems
in away that avoids falling into a central
planning mode
or a "principal-agent" mode of governance.
The companies, rather large, can internalize
the entrepreneurial discovery process.
They seek new strategic areas,
then explore them concretely.
Let's give two examples, taken at random.
Toshiba
identifies a new strategic area
and develops exploratory research projects.
This is the conversion of some of these establishments
to develop "clean factory farms"
in order to produce vegetables and fruits
in perfectly free of germs environments.
Schindler, a leading company in the field
of elevators
and other escalators
explores a new strategic area,
that of the "transit management".
This is not about further improving the lift
but to develop the concept of integrated and
intelligent mobility
that combines access, support, communication,
transport and security.
Although it is more difficult, a group of
SMEs,
can also internalize
a process of entrepreneurial discovery,
especially if the collective action which
is engaged
is coordinated and supported by an industrial
association
or a technology centre.
The difference between an entrepreneurial
discovery process
internalized by a firm
and an entrepreneurial discovery process
as a basis for a public policy
is that in the first case,
the social value of the process will be lower.
Typically, the company will disclose
information on Pa, probably not on Pap.
.
Toshiba, Schindler announce in the press
their new strategic area
but these announcements are logically rather
superficial
in terms of information on the content of
projects.
When the entrepreneurial discovery process
is supported by an innovation policy,
it is critical that the informational value
is the strongest possible.
And so,
subsidized companies under this policy
must agree to comply
to these information disclosure rules.
What are the obstacles and barriers
that can hinder a policy aiming to stimulate
the entrepreneurial discovery process?
Specifically, the potentially high informational
value of the process
poses complicated problems that are well known.
The social return,
because of a so high informational value,
is higher than the private return.
Because of such information externalities,
companies will tend to invest too little in
this process
since it is supposed to inform others.
This externality must therefore be corrected
without reducing the informational value of
the process
since that is its "raison d'être".
Only a subsidy mechanism, unlike a patent,
can solve this problem.
On the other hand, the production of information
on PAP
involves solving coordination problems
when the area to explore
requires assembling varied skills and knowledge
that are not all available in the region
and that may be held by very different organizations.
Here, as we have already seen in the first
week,
having identified rather narrow strategic
areas
and stimulated a coordinated project portfolio
can help solve these problems of coordination.
Regions must take this principle of entrepreneurial
discovery as an opportunity,
not as a constraint.
John Enos, a distinguished Oxford economist,
did not say something else when he wrote
already in the 80s : "countries and regions
should put more efforts into choosing,
in detail and for the future,
the direction of research and development
- on what products,
what processes, into what markets".
He added that an essential reason for this
is that, by doing so, we gain knowledge
and accumulate experience
which will be of great value for the following
stages of innovation.
But what Enos said is only true
if there is indeed discovery, learning, surprise.
It would be less true in the case of omniscient
planner
which precisely seeks to avoid any surprises.
That is what is meant.
In our view, the principle of entrepreneurial
discovery
is fundamental.
It enables to change of policy paradigm
and not fall into a centralized planning mode
based on the belief
of a possibility of complete "ex ante" information
to decide.
During the third week,
we will look at the operational content of
this process.