For a long time, there is a debate
to know whether the regions have an interest
to specialize
or rather to diversify.
There are positive arguments on both sides
and the empirical literature
could never produce a final findings on this
issue.
The reason is probably
that both logics are important
and must be reconciled.
This reconciliation is at the heart of the
concept
of smart specialization strategy.
We can see in fact
that a smart specialization strategy
does not really push
to specialization in the classical sense.
When we see this pattern
we realize that the objective
is the generation of new options
and new opportunities
to diversify and transform structures.
However we also know
that for these options to be viable and effective
we must concentrate resources,
form capacities.
In short, one must "specialize"
in new activities that have been selected.
Thus, the smart specialization strategy
reconciles diversification and specialization.
We specialize in activities
that diversify structures.
This is a first proposition,
the diversification is favorable to innovation
and to structural change
when it is accompanied by the formation
of new critical masses
and is therefore not synonymous with scattering
and dispersion of projects and capacities.
A close proposition
is that variety is especially favorable
for innovation and development
when that variety is technologically connected
to existing structures.
Looking back at all the cases
of spontaneous dynamic of entrepreneurial
discovery
and structural changes
that we had seen during the first week,
most have basically the same structure
which is the development of a new activity
connected to an industry or two existing industries.
Thus the Lyon technical fabrics
come from the silk manufacturers and chemists.
The plastic molds of Marinia Grande,
come from glass molding factories.
The development of nanotechnologies
is associated with the paper & pulp industry
in Finland.
And even the eyewear cluster of Morez
comes from a nail factory.
Diversification refers here
to economies of scope,
that is to say the possibility of redeploying
production tools
to target a new market.
Whilst transition and modernization
rather refer to spillovers,
that is to say to the integration of new technologies
in a traditional sector
which allows to develop a new activity.
All these cases illustrate
that the entrepreneurial discovery
and the process of structural change
often follow a logic of related varieties.
This concept was formulated by Koen Frenken
and his co-authors to attempt to gather
the arguments in favor of specialization
and the arguments in favor of diversity.
The process of structural change,
the most logical, the most common
is that of related diversification
and regions diversify
by plugging in to new industries
which are connected to local industries.
We go in the Lyon region,
from the silk and chemistry sectors to polymers
and technical fabrics, pharmacy,
equipment for extreme sports etc.
Of course, there are very important external
inputs
but this branching process
from local industries is central.
This logic is more likely to happen
than that of an unrelated diversification.
The smart specialization strategy
is essentially governed
by this principle of related varieties
this exploration of possibles adjacents
as Ricardo Hausmann says.
It's time to finish now
by situating our interpretation
of the concept of "specialization"
compared to more standard interpretations.
Specialization?
What does that mean
in the term "smart specialization"?
Most of the time
specialization refers to a relative measure:
if the share of this industry in the regional
economy
is stronger than the share of the same industry
in the national economy,
then the region is qualified a "specialized"
in this industry.
In some areas of economic life
relative measures can constitute
a good point of comparison.
For example in the health sector
or education.
But in the field of R & D and innovation,
what matters the most
are absolute values.
That's critical mass,
agglomeration of resources and
the assembling of capacities
that make the difference.
Relative performances
are not necessarily the panacea
because as already said
there are indivisibilities,
agglomeration and
critical mass effects.
Take the example of Upper Austria,
the region of Linz.
A region of strong industrial tradition
in the fields of mechanics and machines
and that happens to be in a strong relationship
with much larger neighbours
as Bavaria or Baden-Würtemberg.
One of my students, Monica Coffano,
calculated the relative ​​and absolute
values of the specialization of Upper Austria
in electro-mechanics and optical fields
on the base of patent data.
From a "relative specialisation" point of
view
we see that Upper Austria
is highly specialized
in electro-mechanics and optical.
These are all the small yellow bars
which extend to the right
and show that this region
is specialized in these areas
relatively to other Austrian regions.
And besides, the fact that the yellow bars
are larger
than the other coloured bars
shows that this relative specialization
is often higher
than the other regions taken as a comparison
like Baden-Würtemberg
Bavaria, Flanders, Piedmont.
So a large specialization
in some electro-technical fields
which would place it at first European rank
ahead of Bavaria or Baden-Würtemberg.
But when we go to absolute measures
still on patent data,
this region, without wanting to offend it,
becomes a dwarf against giants
such as Bavaria.
And from R&D efficiency,
and innovation point of view,
from creativity point of view
it is this second measure that counts
because it captures critical mass
and agglomeration effects.
Thus, the fact that a region
has a smart specialization strategy
should not be understood
as an indication that this region
is specialized in the considered field,
in a passive sense
relative to other regions.
But we must understand that it involves
building capacities,
skills and other factors
to develop a transformative activity.
This does not mean
that there will be no effect
of this strategy on relative specializations.
There will probably be some without doubt,
logically,
but only in the long term
and this is not the most important.
This module has proposed an overview
of the relationships between diversification
and specialization
and has positioned the concept
of smart specialization strategy within this
framework.
We made 3 propositions.
First, the diversification is favorable to
innovation
and structural change,
when accompanied by the formation of new critical
masses
and is not synonymous with scattering
and dispersion of projects and capacities.
Secondly,
the variety is especially favorable to innovation
and development,
when that variety is connected
to existing structures.
Finally, the measures of specialization in
relative terms
will not allow to capture
a smart specialization dynamics.
We will offer other methods of measurement
during the next week.