When we have to make strategic choices
aimed at the preferential development of new
activities
and that therefore involve targeted interventions
towards certain areas or certain firms,
we risk making mistakes.
Some choices may seem irrelevant afterwards
whilst decisions not to engage in such area
could later appear as erroneous.
And that's one of the advantages of a horizontal
policy
to avoid these mistakes since the programs
and instruments
are available for all.
In this second part, we recall the five types
of errors
commonly made
and we identify
the design elements that help to minimize
these errors
or to reduce their costs.
First is the error of the omniscient planner.
We've already talked about it.
This error is based on the belief that we
can accumulate
in advance,
all the knowledge and information that will
allow
to design a complete plan
and then stimulate
enterprises to execute it.
But, we have said it,
the knowledge that the Government can hold
in advance
is very limited,
even after ordering sophisticated statistics,
simply
because the most important knowledge will
be discovered
as the process goes.
The only medicine against this error,
is the application of a principle of
entrepreneurial discovery.
We do not know ex ante what to do.
We must find out.
This was module 3 of this week and we will
come back to it
in the weeks devoted to the operationalization
of the strategy.
The second error
is the choice made at the sectoral level.
(Tourism, textile, food, pharmacy).
Conducting a sectoral prioritization
within an innovation policy
does not make any sense.
The problem is not to help all the firms
simply because they belong to such sector
but to help those who are engaged in a project,
in the development of a new activity.
The sectoral level
is also not adapted, as was already said,
to the new phase of globalization called the
"second unbundling".
The level of prioritization
must be located at a finer granularity,
the activity or specialty.
We do not help the fisheries sector
but the biotechnology development activity
for the management of marine resources.
We do not help the wood and forest industry
but the development of a bio-economy
applied to wood and forest.
Thus, the distortions are reduced
because public action is located in the area
of an ​​innovation policy
and not in the area of a sectoral sector.
In addition,
this level of activity,
is the right level
at which a region can discern opportunities
for itself,
that it could not see at sectoral level.
Finally, it allows to have an inclusive strategy,
as we will see later.
At this finer level,
priorities can be distributed through a relatively
large number
of sectors or cross-cutting areas.
Third mistake: the choices made for ever.
On the basis of comparative advantages, as
with Ricardo,
Portugal produces wine and Great Britain,
the textile.
And everyone sinks in,
we could even say mires in its specialization
because the comparative advantages and disadvantages
at the origin of the initial specializations
are self-perpetuating.
This error is serious enough and there are
many reasons
for this problem.
Some priorities may become irrelevant.
So we must stop them.
Any activity without exception
after a certain time is no longer new.
An activity that has become mature
no longer needs to be supported preferentially
because other funding mechanisms are better
suited
to an activity that has reached maturity.
Parallel to this process of maturation of
some areas
new opportunities can appear
and thus new priorities must be established.
Finally, some projects in each priority area
can fail.
They must be stopped.
The main lesson of this set of observations
is that
the smart specialization strategy is a living
document.
It would be absurd
and not "smart" to have priorities established
for ever
and to declare that the strategy is definitely
completed
by refusing for example to incorporate new
options
and opportunities later.
The principle of flexibility is essential
but who says flexibility also says monitoring
and evaluation.
The implementation of these principles will
be addressed
during the fourth week.
The fourth error, like the following one actually,
is not specific to a non-neutral policy aimed
at preferential actions.
It is also made within
horizontal policies.
Indeed, it is not enough to provide generous
fundings
to R & D projects or platforms
in each priority area,
because what needs to be increased concerns
all the factors
that enter a process of research and innovation.
But, the supply of human capital (R & D engineers)
is fixed, at least in the short term.
It cannot instantly adjust
to an increase in demand for human capital
that would be consecutive
to the aditional funding.
Let's look at this diagram.
With a supply of human capital that takes
time to adapt,
the increase of the demand in human capital
will translate into higher wages
without significant increase in R & D volumes.
The demand curve
moves upwards
thanks to R & D grants.
But the supply of scientists and engineers
is fixed.
From then on, subsidies are dissipated
in a rise of wages
without resulting in an increase in volume
of R&D and innovation activities.
Of course, the problem of supply adjustment
can be solved in part by immigration
and the call for engineers and scientists
from other regions.
But when a new priority area has been identified,
it is also coherent to anticipate
the development of appropriate training
in the region itself.
The last error, finally, concerns the fact
of financing projects,
activities that would have existed anyway,
that is to say, even in the absence of public
funding.
If public funding is given for a project that
would
have been executed by the firm anyway,
there will be no aditionality effect.
It is a simple transfer of resources from
public
to private.
It is inefficient for this reason,
even if the project is successful.
It is often a difficult thing to understand.
How to fix this error? What project to finance?
The theoretical answer, e.g. Trajtenberg
or Wallsten and Stiglitz,
tells us that only the projects or activities
that are characterized
by a negative correlation between private
profitability
and social profitability
should be financed.
This logic is illustrated in this figure by
Stiglitz
and Wallsten.
The vertical axis
is the social return of the projects;
what it brings back to society as a whole.
And the horizontal axis
is the private return;
what this brings back to those who undertake
this project.
The projects in zone C
are projects whose private profitability
is important. They therefore do not need public
funding
to be undertaken.
Public funding of C
would therefore consist of a simple transfer
of resources
from the private to the public without allocative
effect.
Bad decision!
It is therefore better to fund type B projects.
However, there is a public funding opportunity
cost
and we cannot fund everything simply because
these type B projects
have a low private profitability.
Projects in zone A
have a low level of private profitability
and their anticipated social return
is inferior to the cost of public funding.
So, indeed,
without public funding, they will not be undertaken
but would that penalize society? Probably
not.
Finally, public funding will
be efficient in the case of projects
in zone B since they are low private return
projects
but which expected social return
exceeds the cost of public funding.
In practice, of course,
it is difficult to identify projects of zone
B.
But we can nevertheless believe that entrepreneurial
discovery projects,
that combine and integrate fragmented knowledge
to explore a new field
and that will ensure a wide and fast distribution
of information on these findings,
these projects belong to zone B
and must be financed by the Government.
These are the five elements of a good design
for a non-neutral policy that involves making
choices
and allocate resources preferentially.
This good design
obviously requires a skillful and competent
Government.
We can ask ourselves if,
in many areas, this requirement is realistic.
We will discuss
during the fourth week by inviting a specialist
in this matter
our colleague and friend, Kevin Morgan,
from the University of Cardiff.
I hope you enjoyed this module
on the place of smart specialization strategies
in the space of innovation policies.
A place that smart specialization strategy
does not occupy alone. Other policies are
like it.
In terms of a logic of non-neutral resource
allocation,
enabling strategic choices
through preferential actions.
But this place also implies fundamentally
taking care
of the design of the policy,
to minimize possible errors.
After a week full of theories and concepts
of all kinds,
let's now see the practice
and operationalization of our approach,
which will be developed next week.
Thank you!