In this module
it is about highlighting
what distinguishes
a smart specialization strategy
as an innovation policy
compared to more traditional policies,
the so-called horizontal or sector-neutral
policies.
What distinguishes a smart specialization
policy
is its complexity
and the fact that it can't offer
a single, standard solution
because it must take into account the specificities
of the priority areas which are selected.
I like to say it is "haute couture"
rather than "ready-to-wear".
So it is expensive
and difficult to implement.
This complexity and specificity
involve a number of constraints and challenges
in terms of policy design
which I'll talk about now.
For decades
we've been searching for good policies
to stimulate structural change
that is to say, the transformation of structures
of an economy in a positive direction ;
diversification, modernization
emergence of new industries.
Until recently
preferred policies, particularly in Europe
were called horizontal policies
that is to say policies
which focus on general conditions
and generic factors of innovation.
For instance:
public research infrastructure
or the financing of start-ups.
Problems that affect all businesses
like R & D costs
or intellectual property.
It is also about indirect policies
as those about training or immigration
The instruments of such policy are classical
:
R & D grant, tax credit,
refundable loan
but also organizations and platforms
that address generic problems.
All companies are involved
whatever their sector of activity.
These policies thus avoid
preferential interventions,
the targeting of such and such technology
area.
This is why they are called
sector-neutral policies
There certainly were exceptions :
cluster policies
in favor of the new Länder
just after the reunification of Germany
or competitiveness poles in France.
But horizontal policies
dominate the landscape in Europe
and beyond for decades.
This is a commendable policy,
it helps improve key elements
of the innovation system
and minimizes the risks of distortion
inherants to any policy
which selects projects
by sectors or technologies.
And such a policy can lead
to structural change
through well known mechanisms,
spotted for example by my colleagues
Ron Boschma and Koen Frenken.
The ability of companies to diversify,
the dynamics leading
to the creation of new companies,
networking and mobility of people,
particularly from the outside of a region.
These horizontal policies
have worked rather well
particularly in the case of the most advanced
regional or national economies.
In these ones
the positive structural change
can be stimulated through the only virtues
of horizontal policies
and companies respond positively
to the incentives produced
by the proper functioning of the framework
conditions.
However, these policies have not allowed
the least developed regions and countries
to progress much.
Why did this not work too well
in a number of regions
whereas important resources
were allocated in
the framework of the cohesion policies
dedicated to R & D and innovation?
That is the question that must be asked.
Innovation in most cases
not only requires
that the general conditions of the economy
work well.
To get the basic right .
Innovation not only requires
that public research infrastructures
be funded and developed.
But it also requires specific capacities
and resources:
research, services, skills
platforms, suppliers.
It therefore demands a critical size
so that these different resources
can be mobilized.
It demands scale and
agglomeration effects, relational density.
Innovation is therefore based
on rich and sufficient in size
local innovation systems.
And these systems are specific
to each sector or each technology.
In the more developed regions,
these specific capabilities
are provided thanks to the wealth
of ecosystem of innovation.
Large companies, top universities,
other public or private actors
provide these capacities
in the form of spillovers
of their own research activities,
training, technological diffusion.
These spillovers represent
these complementary capacities
of which SMEs can benefit
even if they have not contributed to their
production.
In other regions
as Suzan Berger explains
in her beautiful book "Making in America",
the sources of these capabilities have dried
or have never existed.
Gaping holes exist in ecosystems
"SMEs are home alone," she says
speaking of many
regions of her country.
They are isolated and without
these complementary capacities
so important for innovation.
Even startups with generous fundings
and an excellent innovative idea
cannot do everything at home
and require these additional capacities.
Suppliers, skilled workers
engineers, expertise:
the ecosystem is too poor
to provide all that.
Some local ecosystems have degraded
because those providing complementary capacities
no longer do.
A consequence of offshoring
and of the new governance logics
of large companies.
Other ecosystems have not degraded
but have remained very poor.
This poverty of the ecosystems
is a problem for the less developed regions
that can't solve a policy
limited to horizontal measures.
But it is also a problem
in the case of advanced regions
where very often there is only a small number
of ecosystems capable of functioning properly.
In the greater part of an economy
of an advanced region,
firms are also "home alone".
This analysis suggests
that in many areas
policies must break
the dogma of neutrality
and horizontality
because structural changes
will not emerge spontaneously
from a "simple" improvement
of framework conditions.
The government must do more
that is to say support
the formation of local innovation systems
which are specific for each field
or each sector
and which is not only reduced
to public research
but include all additional capacities.
But we are left now
in another part of the policies space.
We left the sector-neutral
policies part
to join the part of the policies
that attach to provide specific capacities
to serve specific activities.
As Haussman
and Rodrik say,
this move is inevitable. They write:
"It is an illusion to believe
that the Government could disengage
from specific policies
and limit itself to neutral policies;
an illusion which is produced
by the misunderstanding of the specificity
and the complexity of input factors
and required capacities for innovation ".
The problem is the difficulty of this policy.
Each sector, each domain is specific
and it is therefore about very expensive policies
in terms of implementation, coordination
provision of specific capabilities.
Support the development
of biotech applications
applied to fisheries and marine resource management
involves providing different capacities
from those required
for the development of advanced
manufacturing technologies
in the case of the food industry.
Very different from those that allow
the development of energetic efficiency solutions
in the automotive field.
We could of course use
the same instruments
as the horizontal policy
while targeting beneficiaries.
Research tax credit
only for green technologies
and R & D grants
only for food companies
which adopt information technologies.
However, this type of targeting
is practically very difficult
and poses almost insoluble problems
of definition of industries borders.
Who is in? Who's out?
Who does what ? It's very complicated.
So a non-neutral policy
will rather seek to provide
specific complementary capabilities
that only interest companies
that are really engaged in a certain area.
Such policy oriented
towards the formation of complementary capabilities
and the concentration of resources
in specific areas
must take into account this specificity
and this complexity.
And this has a cost
This is the cost of "haute couture"
compared to the "ready-to-wear".
R&D tax credit
is a "ready-to-wear" instrument.
Of course it is expensive
in terms of tax loss
but the implementation is relatively easy.
On the other side,
providing specific capacities
in such and such technological area
is much more expensive and difficult:
"haute couture"!
Numerous economists are skeptical
about the ability of a government
to master such complexity
which requires a detailed understanding
of needs in such areas
and complementarities
between different types of investment.
A famous development economist
Matsuyama said for example
that one thing is to develop a theory
of economic coordination mechanisms,
another is to develop useful tools
to build a policy
aiming to address these problems effectively.
This skepticism is justified.
A minimalist solution
is to recognize that the Government
cannot do everything
and meet all the specific needs
and attempt to solve
all the coordination problems
in all the parts of its economy.
It must make choices.
It is not that choices are desirable,
they are simply unavoidable
as Haussman and Rodrik say.
And we have already said it,
we join the first argument
in favor of a certain specialization:
"a region should not be doing a little bit
of everything".
This was an argument
of scale, of critical mass.
The argument of political feasibility
related to the limited capacity of the Government
is added.
However,
choosing between different areas
to conduct preferential actions
faces a second wave of skepticism.
Well formulated for example
by Anne Krueger.
it's a long quote
that concludes with "allocating resources
preferentially
so that some kinds of activities
will benefit from excellent infrastructures
and others won't;
this appears as a distortion. "
These different types of skepticism
are certainly justified
and we can share the opinion of those economists.
But where most economists
decide to give up
and return to the space
of neutral policies
where there is no choice to make
between areas, sectors,
the approach of smart specialization
does not give up the non-neutral policies
but open a new perspective.
Certainly there are potential risks
but the question is not to know whether
we will do this policy
but rather how to do it
to minimize the risks.
Skepticism must be our motivation
to be closely interested
in the design of the policy
that is to say to the operating modes
that will help minimize
the issues raised
by a non-neutral policy
aiming to identify strategic areas
to carry on preferential actions.
In the policy space -
we are therefore in the part
of non-neutral policies -
and we can identify different logics
on the basis of "how to choose".
Who's deciding ? What level of aggregation?
In the previous module
we show
that the principle of self discovery is crucial
to avoid falling into the trap of the Government
who knows everything
and thus protects itself from unexpected
learning and the potential of surprise
that conceals entrepreneurial discovery.
We are not coming back to it
only to say that this opposition
between two ways of solving
the information problem
structures the space of non-neutral policies.
There is a long history of policies
establishing priorities in a top down way
by an omniscient government
which asks a bureaucratic committee to decide.
The methods of choice
can be very sophisticated.
However, they remain marked
by the technocratic illusion
that we can know everything ex ante.
The alternative
is therefore the principle of self discovery.
This subspace
is not only occupied
by the smart specialization strategy
but other approaches
claim such logic.
They also recognize the importance
of strategic choices
but these must be informed
by the entrepreneurial discovery process.
This is the case of development policies
by Haussman and Rodrik.
We can thus discern
a familiarity of goals
and approaches between these approaches
which certainly have different objectives
but try to reconcile the fact
of being forced to choose, to specialize,
and the fact of promoting
an entrepreneurial dynamic.
As such, the smart specialization strategy
finds its place in what is called
new industrial policies :
non-neutral policies
where the design of the policy is central
to minimize the risks
linked to any policy action
aiming for preferential interventions
in areas defined as strategic.