You're in charge
of improving the sanitation
situation in your city,
with low income neighbohoods,
such as this one in Nairobi.
And you ask yourself
"Where do I even start?"
You're not the only one.
Urban sanitation is complex.
Different urban contexts
mean different sanitation challenges.
These challenges
often need to be addressed
with different sanitation systems
or management skills.
How do we tackle this complexity
and enable city-wide
inclusive sanitation solutions?
This is what this MOOC is all about.
This course is produced in collaboration
with the World Bank
and the World Health Organization.
Cities are not homogenous,
especially in low
and middle-income countries.
We can differentiate
between three different contexts:
the middle and high-income settlements,
the informal settlements,
and the peri-urban interface.
How to provide sanitation services
to each of these contexts?
In this course, you will learn
about state of the art sanitation
planning approaches,
like Sanitation 21.
Dealing with city-wide planning.
Clues.
Focusing on informal settlements
and communities.
And the World Bank City Service
Delivery Assessment tools,
and WHO's Sanitation Safety Plans.
Plus, we will also feature
some best-practice case studies
from Africa, Asia, and Latin America.
Stakeholders
and institutions
are key to urban sanitation.
You will learn how to bring them
on board in a participatory process,
in order to achieve
city-wide inclusive sanitation.
But how do we actually choose
proper sanitation systems?
Building on the Compendium
of Sanitation Systems and Technologies,
we'll get an overview
of the different technologies
adapted to these contexts
and how to systematically combine them
into a proper sanitation system.
We will cover the entire sanitation chain,
from the user interface;
for example, using this squat plate;
Collection and storage, conveyance,
transport, treatment,
and finally, disposal and use.
For example,
using this urine-based fertilizer.
Or, this dried sludge pellets
made out of faecal sludge.
Interested in learning
all about urban sanitation
theory and practice?
Then this course is for you.
EAWAG SANDEC is partnering with EPFL
to bring you a full series
of online courses.
This is the EAWAG web page
where you can get links
to our whole MOOC series
on Sanitation, Water,
and Solid Waste for Development.
All courses are offered
with French and Spanish subtitles.
Other subtitles are available
for this course,
such as Hindu.
Check out for more.
(Speaking French)
Please join us.
You're only one click away from registering.