Welcome to the first week
of our online course entitled
Planning and Design
of Sanitation Systems and Technologies.
My name is Christoph Lüthi from Eawag.
In the next five weeks,
we will be exploring some of the issues
and challenges in urban sanitation.
What makes urban sanitation so different
and more complex than rural contexts?
Let's take a look at our learning goals.
Firstly, we'd like you to get familiar
with urban sanitation assessment
and planning tools.
Secondly, different options
of sanitation systems and technologies.
And lastly, understand
which systems and technologies
are most appropriate
to different contexts.
We'll be looking
at different systems and technologies,
the institutions and stakeholders
that need to be involved,
and we'll be presenting best practice
from around the world
featuring innovative and robust solutions
to inclusive urban sanitation.
And finally, we're also
going to be taking a closer look
at different planning
and assessment frameworks,
and the design
of different sanitation systems.
What makes urban sanitation so different
and more complex than rural contexts?
Firstly, the different urban contexts
or domains that need to be considered:
from the modern inner-city planned areas,
to the dense and unplanned
informal settlements or slums
found in most cities of Africa,
Asia, and Latin America.
And finally,
the fast-growing city periphery,
also called the peri-urban interface.
These different contexts
and urban realities
call for specific solutions
when seeking appropriate and sustainable
urban sanitation services.
Let's take a look at a typical
low-income area in an African city.
Some of the challenges
found in these neighborhoods
include unsanitary environments,
lack of space for sanitation facilities,
like the pit latrine shown here,
and informal, unhygienic toilet emptying
or open defecation, as shown here.
So what can be done about this situation?
In this course, we will focus
on a key concept of urban sanitation,
the sanitation value chain.
We will highlight the different components
and functional groups,
as in the example shown here.
First, the user interface,
or pour-flush toilet shown here in red,
the safe storage of the human waste,
followed by the mechanical emptying
of the sludge
by the exhauster trucks in yellow.
The safely-collected fecal sludge
is then brought
to a treatment site in green,
in this case, a sludge-drying bed,
and finally, the safe reuse
in urban agriculture, shown in blue.
The value chain allows
for a realistic assessment
of a range of sanitation
options and solutions,
and its technical
and managerial implications.
Our five-week course
will be examining the issues
around the planning, design,
and implementation of inclusive,
city-wide sanitation systems
and technologies.
The sanitation value chain
will be our guiding concept.
Let's take a closer look at the syllabus.
In week one, we're going to give you
an overview of city sanitation,
planning and programming,
the political economy,
and provide you
with some assessment frameworks
on how to better understand
the urban sanitation framework.
In week two, we're going to introduce you
to different sanitation products,
and the five functional groups
starting off with user interface,
the collection and transport.
And in week three,
the sanitation systems and technologies,
especially for treatment,
and use or disposal.
In week four, we're going
to look at different case studies
that feature best practice
from Africa, Asia, and Latin America.
And finally, in week five,
we're going to be taking a look
at urban sanitation planning
and assessment tools
featuring some
of the state-of-the-art tools
of the World Bank and WHO.
And finally, the final exam,
where you will be able to evaluate
what you have learned
in the past five weeks.
Here we list some
of the recommended references
that you may want to download
from our course site.
These documents were produced
by the institutions involved
in putting together this course:
Eawag, the International
Water Association,
the World Bank,
and the World Health Organization.
On behalf of my team and fellow lecturers,
I'm looking forward to working with you
and hearing your contributions
on the Coursera Forum.
Let's start the course now,
with the first input
by Jonathan Parkinson,
on Sanitation Planning.
Enjoy.