City-wide sanitation diagnostic tools
and planning frameworks – Part 1
Welcome to the first of two modules
on City-wide Sanitation Services:
an Introduction to Diagnostic
Tools and Frameworks.
My name is Sanyu Lutalo,
and I'm a Senior Water
and Sanitation Specialist
with the World Bank Group
based in Washington D.C.
In this module and the following module,
we will introduce some
systematic ways to understand
and analyze the complex
urban environments
we often face
when planning improvements
in sanitation services.
These two modules will
introduce a number of issues
related to sanitation planning,
which we will explore more
deeply later in the course.
For sanitation services
to be appropriate,
affordable, and sustainable,
we need to consider more
than just the type
of technology to be selected.
In this module, we will explore
some of these aspects,
and we'll do so based
on the principles
of the sustainable
development goals,
or SDGs framework while
looking at two broad aspects:
urban sanitation services
and public health
and the need to consider
integrated urban services.
You may already be familiar
with the sanitation services chain
comprising waste containment,
emptying, conveyance, treatment,
and end-use or disposal.
In practice, there are two
major types of chain,
which we can refer
to as: networked,
basically comprising sewerage systems
with treatment plants,
and non-networked, comprising
on-site sanitation options
with fecal sludge management.
The millennium
development goals, or MDGs,
included targets to reduce
the proportion of people
without access
to an adequate toilet.
In other words, they focused
on the containment part
of the sanitation
service chain.
The sustainable
development goals,
or SDGs, however,
set targets for universal access
and monitor
the whole sanitation chain
including conveyance, treatment,
and reuse or disposal.
We will now look at how
the sanitation service chain,
when it is not working effectively,
can contaminate the household toilet
and the residential
and/or urban environment,
including local groundwater,
posing a range of public health hazards.
The sanitation chain
is represented
vertically on the left,
and the hazard pathways
can be summarized
as follows.
A dirty toilet is a threat
to its users.
A leaking tank,
or pit, or a drain,
or a sewer can pollute ground water.
Unsafe emptying of a tank or a pit
is a risk to the emptiers,
to the household,
and to the neighborhood.
Contaminated drainage structures
and leaking sewers
add to the hazard
of fecal contamination.
And non-existent
or poor treatment
and/or inappropriate end-use
and disposal of sewage, septage,
and sludge results
in a contaminated environment,
in contaminated produce,
and in contaminated water bodies.
In such a contaminated
environment,
hazard becomes risk
when people do not practice
good hygiene, for example,
by washing their hands with soap.
This is all exacerbated
by poor solid
waste management,
which allows garbage
to further interfere
with the proper functioning
of sanitation services,
and by uncontrolled land use,
which makes planning
and enforcement
of the sanitation service chain
even more challenging.
And finally, when it rains,
blocked drains, pits,
and sewers overflow,
and the wider environment
is fecally contaminated.
By analyzing
the contamination routes
in this way,
we see where
and why sanitation
interventions are needed.
For example,
continuous monitoring
and maintenance of the sewerage system,
behavior change communication,
and improved fecal sludge management
may all be essential elements
in a particular city.
In the last slide,
we saw the challenges
that need to be addressed,
whereas now we will
look at the services
which can address
these challenges.
There are five components
to urban sanitation services.
As you can see in the slide,
latrines, septic tanks,
and sewers are accompanied
by solid waste
and storm water management,
as the latter two services
are inseparable from the proper
functioning of the fecal waste chain
in a given town or city.
Both sides of this diagram,
the upstream services on the left,
which typically interface
with the households
and other customer groups,
and the downstream services,
including treatment, disposal,
and reuse on the right
are impacted by the quality
and enforcement of physical planning
and of land use control.
At the household level,
housing tenure,
and urban upgrading programs
can also play an important part
in advancing
urban sanitation services.
Likewise, treatment
and appropriate reuse
and disposal also contribute
to reducing
the public health risk
and to improving
the ecological environmental
endowment of a city
while increasing
quality of life
and city attractiveness
and competitiveness.
But poor management
of these interrelated
components often leads
to the creation of a highly contaminated
mixed waste stream
in the drainage system.
And when it rains,
it just gets worse
as flooding spreads
this contamination far
and wide across the city.
To summarize,
in this module,
we have seen that sanitation
is about a chain of services
which will protect public health
and the environment
from fecal contamination
and that there needs
to be integration
between the management
of solid waste, drainage,
onsite and network
sanitation services.
In the next module,
you will learn about tools
that can help us
analyze the multiple complex
technical and nontechnical factors
involved in urban sanitation
and how to prioritize them,
and how urban sanitation
is about services
which are developed
and implemented by both public
and private sector entities.