Welcome to the second of
the two modules
on Citywide Sanitation Services
and Introduction to Diagnostic
Tools and Frameworks.
This module will
continue the introduction
to some systematic ways
to understand
and analyze
the complex urban environments we face
when planning improvements
in sanitation services.
In this module, we'll look
at how tools such
as the Fecal Waste Flow Diagram
and the City Service
Delivery Assessment
can help us to analyze
and understand technical
and non-technical challenges
related to sanitation service delivery,
and we will look
at urban sanitation
as a service
and the roles of government
and the private sector
in delivering it.
When looking at
the sanitation challenges
of a specific city,
the Fecal Waste Flow Diagram
or "SFD"
as it is commonly
referred to,
is an effective way to illustrate
the fecal flows in the city
and to highlight areas
of the sanitation service chain
which need attention.
You will be learning
more about the development
and use of SFDs in later modules.
Here is the SFD
for a typical
low-income city in Africa
and it highlights
the need to improve
the operational effectiveness
of the sewerage system,
to improve the fecal
sludge management services,
and provide household
sanitation options
for rental housing and marginal
challenging environments.
To achieve the SDGs,
sanitation services
need to include everyone.
Data disaggregated by wealth
quintiles shows that
it's the poorest households
which have the worst access
to sanitation services.
Global analysis has
identified four key
aspects of sanitation services
which need much more attention
if sanitation services
are to reach everyone.
One, making better
use of existing
and future investments in sewerage.
This includes ensuring connections
to existing sewers,
making sewerage accessible in difficult
to reach and poor communities,
and having approaches
for facilitating
the connection of poor
customers to sewers.
Two, fecal sludge management
to make on-site
sanitation hygienic
and viable.
Three, services
for rental housing
and informal settlements,
including the use of shared toilets
and the challenges of limited space
of multi-story residences
and of illegal or informal settlements
and the implications of situations
where households don't have tenure
on where they rent.
And four, marginal areas
and challenging environments.
Sanitation is further complicated
where communities are located
in difficult terrain
such as where there are swamps,
high groundwater,
housing over water bodies
such as rivers, lakes,
or the sea, rocky terrain,
steep hillsides,
cold climates, etc.
New tools are available
which enable a systematic assessment
of the non-technical
aspects required
in an urban sanitation
service chain.
The city service
delivery assessment
allows the visual presentation
to decision makers
of a scorecard
that encapsulates
the underlying policy,
planning,
and budget context,
how expenditure, equity,
and outputs are monitored,
and the quality of operation
and maintenance, etc.
This analysis enables
decision makers
to prioritize
which institutional
and service delivery issues
need immediate attention.
The prognosis for change tool
enables a more detailed
analysis of incentives
and influences
and enables decision makers
to seek win-win outcomes
on specific issues.
The tool seeks to assess three things:
How key formal and informal
institutions function,
what incentives those institutions
provide to stakeholders,
and the formal
or informal power
those stakeholders
have to exert influence.
It also considers
the implications
of the findings
for effective engagement
with the problem
by those wanting to improve
the situation
and aims to make interventions
more likely to succeed by
ensuring they are taking the underlying
political economy
of the city into account.
Here we list some examples
of the type of non-technical issues
that typically need
to be tackled in developing
an effective
inclusive sanitation program
at scale in a city.
Different services need to be
provided along
the sanitation chain
and these vary in nature and in scale,
from material supply
to small-scale construction
and operating public toilets
at the household end
of the spectrum
through desludging,
fecal waste transportation and sewage
and sludge treatment
and disposal to maintenance
and management of drainage
and solid waste services
at the other end of the spectrum.
These services can be
grouped as customer services,
directly interfacing
with households or customers,
public services,
and infrastructure development
which is a necessary,
but not a sufficient
enabling input
for the service providers
who operate and maintain
the infrastructure.
And these services
can be broadly seen
as being private goods
benefitting individual households
or groups of households,
although they mostly also
have a public benefit,
and public goods
which do not benefit
only a single household
or individual,
but rather benefit the public
or the city at large.
These distinctions
have important implications
for how financing, subsidies,
and regulation are
organized and practiced.
Users have traditionally
been left to pay
for private goods themselves,
but because of their
public good element it
may be appropriate
to provide partial
or in specific circumstances
even total public funding
for these services
where users are unable
to pay the full cost.
Similarly, public goods
may be provided
by the private sector
if costs can be recovered,
for example,
from land developers
or from the sale
of treated wastes
or under an agreement
with a public sector institution.
But in all cases, the full
sanitation services chain
needs to be regulated
by the public sector
so as to safeguard standards.
We will now consider the roles
for the public and private sector.
As we saw in the last slide,
there are three main categories
of goods and services:
Customer services,
public services,
and infrastructure developments.
Customer services
are often best provided
by the private sector
as this usually creates
stronger accountability
but may also be provided
by the public sector.
At the other end
of the spectrum,
finance for major public
sanitation infrastructure
will usually be cheaper
from public sector sources,
but the involvement
of private sector partners
is gaining popularity
as it may accelerate improvements
and promote cost effectiveness.
In between these
extremes, the provision
of public services
offers wide scope
for public-private partnerships
of various types.
For these services to provide
sustainable sanitation
for everyone, local government
typically plays a key role
in providing planning
and coordination,
local regulation
and bylaws, appropriate
tariff structures,
local standards,
enforcement of land use,
support to get
the local service providers up
and running which may not otherwise
happen by itself,
housing, tenure,
and land use policy,
and the promotion of services,
behavior change programs,
and monitoring.
The role of national government
is to provide a conducive
and supportive environment
which includes appropriate
policy frameworks with laws,
national standards and regulation
to support them, planning structures
and monitoring systems,
finance windows and mechanisms
for infrastructure developments,
and national capacity
building initiatives.
To summarize,
in this module
we have seen that tools
such as the Fecal
Waste Flow Diagram
and the City Service
Delivery Assessment
can help us analyze
the multiple complex technical
and non-technical factors
involved in urban sanitation
and how to prioritize them,
and urban sanitation
is about services
which are developed
and implemented by both public
and private sector entities.
Later in the course
we will return to look again
at aspects of the urban
sanitation service chain
from both the municipal
and the national perspective.