Welcome back.
In the last presentation
by Jonathan Parkinson,
we explored some of the issues involved
in city-wide sanitation planning
and planning for
urban sanitation at scale.
In this module, we are going to dig
a bit deeper and explore the local level.
With local level, we mean the thousands
of urban neighborhoods and communities
in Africa, Asia and Latin America that are
currently unserved or underserved
with environmental sanitation services.
We are specifically going
to look at the household domain,
and the community domain, the areas
and settings where most people
lead their daily lives in the urban areas
of the developing world.
The local level means areas
like this here, in Kibera, Nairobi,
one of the most notorious
informal settlements in Africa,
with high densities of over
1000 inhabitants per hectare.
On the image here, shown in the middle,
a first attempt at providing
public sanitation services,
a public toilet built together
with the Wassa Program
water and sanitation for the urban poor.
What are the learning goals of this module?
We want you to get to know
the CLUES planning approach
for environmental sanitation
in urban low-income areas
and we will also explore some
of the linkages between city-wide
and community level interventions.
The most difficult spacial contexts
to deal with are undoubtedly
the rapidly expanding para-urban areas
surrounding most cities
and the informal settlements found in much
of Africa, Asia and Latin America.
These unplanned areas not only have
poor access to developed services,
they also exhibit
dysfunctional institutions
where government services hardly reach.
Each spatial setting requires
its planning approach.
For rural areas, widely known today
is the CLTS approach,
Community Led Total Sanitation.
For urban areas,
we will be presenting CLUES,
the Community Led Urban Environmental
Sanitation planning approach,
and finally, at city-wide level,
the Sanitation 21 approach
which Doctor Parkinson has explained
in the modules before
covering the entire urban sphere.
Some few words about the Community Led
Total Sanitation for rural sanitation.
CLTS helps rural communities
to collectively find solutions
to their inadequate sanitation situation.
In most cases, this means overcoming
open defecation in the villages.
Its focus is on igniting a change
in sanitation behavior
rather than constructing toilets.
The approach is very much
a community-driven one.
It doesn't only focus on individual behaviors
and the first significant step of CLTS
is to put an end to open defecation.
It starts by enabling people to do
their own sanitation profile through
appraisal, the observation,
and the analysis of their practices
of open defecation
and the effects that these
have on their lives.
There are many existing planning frameworks,
but we're highlighting only two
state-of-the-art planning frameworks
that are specific for urban settings.
Sanitation 21, which was just presented
by Jonathan Parkinson,
and the CLUES approach
which I will now present.
CLUES has some common characteristics
with CLTS, especially during
the initial stages of the process.
Both approaches seek to initiate
stakeholder involvement
by triggering collective action
at the community level.
However, the post-triggering process
is quite different for both.
For CLTS, it's all about sustaining
behavior change
and ending open defecation.
For CLUES, this entails
a structured planning approach
that addresses
the entire sanitation chain.
Why is CLTS not the answer
to urban sanitation?
Firstly, urban complexity.
There is often not the community cohesion
found in rural settings.
Secondly open defecation and toilet access
is often not the main issue.
Rather, it's a safe handling
of human wastes.
Thirdly, land tenure is a major issue
in the urban sphere.
Tenants cannot just build
their own toilets where they like.
Fourthly, unlike rural investments,
urban environment sanitation
is hugely expensive
and must take an integrated approach,
including issues like
storm water drainage, greywater,
or solid waste management to be effective.
And lastly, neighborhood solutions
need to be synchronized
with the city-wide efforts
and cannot be planned in isolation.
Also, urban poverty
has specific characteristics.
First of all the level of commoditization.
The poor living in urban slums
have to pay rent.
They must pay for basic services,
for transportation getting into town
to their place of work and for their food.
Secondly, the environmental hazards.
Most dense settlements suffer
from inadequate water supply,
environmental sanitation deficiencies,
and high levels of environmental pollution.
And lastly, the deprivation
of urban poverty marked
by urban and domestic violence,
often accompanied by drug and alcohol abuse
and insecure employment.
These three levels of urban poverty
make for quite a different set
compared to rural contexts.
Also, urban sanitation is a bit
more complex than rural sanitation.
We need to think about
wastewater treatment,
solid waste management,
fecal sludge disposal,
what happens with the greywater,
what about the water supply
in these dense urban areas,
storm water drainage and the decision
between on-site or off-site sanitation.
These make for higher level of complexity
of urban sanitation when compared
to rural sanitation.
In this slide, I present
the four key CLUES principles.
Firstly, CLUES places the neighborhood
and community at the core
of the planning process
and, with this, it complements
city-wide strategic planning.
Secondly, it employs both expert
and community knowledge.
Thirdly, it encourages
resource conservation
and reuse, recycling, when and if possible.
And fourthly, it is based on the concept
of domains and tries to solve problems
within the domain nearest
to where the problems arise.
To sum up, it is people centered,
it involves a multi-stakeholder approach,
it tries to come up
with local solutions wherever possible,
and lastly, it tries to promote
environmental, sustainable solutions.