Welcome back.
Last week, we learned a lot
about urban sanitation
both at the city-wide
and at the community level.
This week, we'll provide a
systematic overview
of the sanitation value chain
and the relevant technologies
that are applicable to urban settings.
At the start of our second week,
we would like to highlight
a useful document that we will be using
during the next weeks:
The Compendium of Sanitation
Systems and Technologies.
This book was first published in 2008
and has just now been republished
in an updated second version.
It has gained popularity among
engineers and planners
because it structures the whole range
of urban, peri-urban and rural
sanitation technologies in low and
middle income countries
in one single document.
The Compendium is available
both as hard copy,
and in an interactive, online version
called the eCompendium.
The Compendium has since been
translated into several languages
shown here and can also be downloaded
from the website given here.
The Compendium is divided into two parts,
and is color-coded for easy reference.
The first part provides an overview
of nine basic sanitation systems,
ranging from the most simple,
the single pit system,
to the complex, sewerage system
with urine diversion.
The second part,
shown here on the right,
consists of 57 technology
information sheets
which describe tried and tested
sanitation technologies.
Each of these fact sheets explains
how a technology functions
and for which system it can be used.
Now there is also an online version of
The Compendium of Sanitation Systems.
It's called the eCompendium.
Compared to the print version,
it offers the user easy navigation
within the Compendium. For example,
on the system templates,
you can choose the different technologies
that you'd like to look at.
Given here by a gas reactor,
you simply click on that
and it takes you directly
to the technology.
There is also a filter function,
which facilitates the combination
of suitable technologies and
links to the SSWM tool box.
The eCompendium also allows you to study
the different technologies in detail
and is linked to the SSWM tool box
with a lot of additional information,
case studies, further reading,
training material and videos
on the different technologies presented.
And finally, the eCompendium also offers
a complete glossary
of environmental sanitation terminology
that provide a short and precise
definition of all terms
covered in the Compendium.