Hi!
My name is Lukas Ulrich
and I am an Environmental Engineer.
I work at the Department Sandec
at Eawag
in the research group on Strategic
Environmental Sanitation Planning.
In this module we will start looking
at the different technologies
which can be used to design
a sanitation system.
We will go through the technologies,
functional group by functional group,
from the user interface
to final disposal or end use.
In this course we cannot cover
all technologies in detail,
but we will give a brief introduction
to most of them.
If you would like to learn more
about a specific technology,
I recommend you to read
the corresponding section
in the Compendium of Sanitation
Systems and Technologies.
The Compendium provides
a double-page description
with further explanations
for 54 different technologies.
So, let's get started with the first
functional group: the User Interface.
The User Interface describes
the type of toilet, pedestal, pan,
or urinal with which the user interacts.
It is the way by which the user
accesses the sanitation system.
The user interface must guarantee
that human excreta is hygienically
separated from human contact
to prevent exposure
to fecal contamination
In this module, you will get to know
which different user interface
technologies there are,
and how they function.
You will learn which input products
they can deal with,
and which output products they generate.
You will also find out
what needs to be considered
to choose and design a user interface
for a specific context.
So, let's take a look
where our friends Pee and Poo can go.
The oldest and most widespread
user interface option is the dry toilet.
In its simplest form,
it consists of a slab with a drop hole
and possibly footrests
to provide some user guidance.
This design is suitable
for those who prefer to squat.
For users who prefer sitting on a toilet,
a pedestal can be installed.
Let's take a look at the products
which can go into a dry toilet,
and what comes out of it.
Obviously, feces and urine
go into the toilet.
Anal cleansing water
and dry cleansing materials
can also possibly be input products;
however, they do not always occur,
and for some subsequent technologies,
it is not recommended
to put them into the toilet.
This is indicated by the grey font
and the dashed lines.
Whether anal cleansing water
or dry cleansing materials occur or not,
of course, depends
on the user preferences.
As you can see on this diagram,
flush water is not listed
among the inputs.
That is why we call it "the dry toilet".
When urine and feces are mixed,
they are called excreta.
This is the principal output product
of a dry toilet.
Depending on the local context,
anal cleansing water
and dry cleansing materials
may be mixed into it, indicated by the "+".
This way of structuring the input
and output products of a user interface
may seem unnecessarily complex,
but when we design a sanitation system
it allows us to select
a compatible technology which can follow.
In this case, the subsequent technology
should be able to deal with excreta
as an input product.
In these photos, a few different
dry toilet designs are shown.
You can see
that different materials can be used,
from wood, which may be
a bit difficult to clean,
to concrete, and prefabricated plastic.
Also, the drop hole
can take different shapes.
The keyhole design, for example,
is a very common one.
A round slab has the advantage
that it can be rolled.
For example, to move it to a new pit
when the old one is full.
A lid may provide a certain barrier
against odors and flies,
but is not always recommended, especially
for subsequent collection technologies
which need to be ventilated.
Now, let's look
at another type of dry toilet,
the Urine-Diverting Dry Toilet or UDDT.
This option allows
to separately collect urine and feces.
The one I have here
is a plastic model from China.
It has a lid which a user can open
with one foot, and close again.
The special thing
about this user interface technology
is that it has
kind of a funnel in the front
where our friend Pee can go.
For our other friend, Poo,
there is the drop hole at the back,
where he just can jump in.
This technology option
is of particular interest
for those who want to use
the normally sterile
and nutrient rich urine
as a fertilizer in agriculture.
A Urine-Diverting Dry Toilet
can be designed in various ways
to suit the preferences
of almost all users.
It can be a squat model,
as the one from China I showed,
or it can be a pedestal to sit on.
For those who use water to cleanse
rather than dry cleansing materials,
designs exist which have a separate bowl
for the collection
of anal cleansing water.
The input products of a urine-diverting
dry toilet are exactly the same
as for the regular dry toilets.
The difference can be seen
in the output product,
where pee and poo stay separate
and do not form excreta together.
Depending on the dry
cleansing materials used
and the subsequent collection technology,
dry cleansing materials may go
into the drop hole with the feces.
Anal cleansing water
is never mixed with feces,
because they should always stay dry.
Where anal cleansing water is used,
it should always be collected
in a separate compartment of the toilet
and disposed of separately.
These pictures show a wide range
of different urine-diverting dry toilets
with squatting models above,
and sitting models below.
Urine-diverting dry toilets can be made
of ceramics, concrete, or plastics.
They can even be self-made
using a funnel and a bucket
as shown in this image here.
Where men prefer to stand for urination
rather than sitting or squatting,
it can be a good idea to install a urinal
to collect their urine.
Urinals also exist in different designs,
and they can be
water-flushed or waterless.
Inputs include urine, and in case
of flush models, also flushwater.
Depending on the design, urine emanates
in undiluted form,
or diluted with flushwater.
Especially where the urine
is collected in a tank
and where it is supposed
to be used as a fertilizer,
it is recommended to collect it
without dilution, to reduce the volume.
Urinals can take a variety of shapes,
and are usually made of materials
like plastics or ceramics.
All the urinals shown here
are waterless ones,
except this one here, which has later on
been retrofitted to be waterless
by closing all the holes
in the drain except one
to limit the odor emissions.
Waterless urinals should always
be fitted with an odor seal,
such as the rubber one
shown in this picture.
There are also designs for women,
but they are not widely available
and implemented.
Those two here on the right side
are female designs.
The next technology
is the Pour Flush Toilet.
It has its name from the bucket
that is used to pour water
into the bowl to flush it.
Pour flush toilets
should be equipped with a U-bend,
also called S-trap or gooseneck,
which acts as a water seal.
This seal effectively prevents
odors or insects
from returning to the user interface.
In addition to the input products
that we already had
for the dry toilet options,
the pour flush toilet depends
on a source of flush water to function.
The product that comes out
of the user interface
is the mix of excreta, flushwater,
and possibly anal cleansing water
or dry cleansing materials,
called blackwater.
Pour flush toilets
are mostly made of ceramics
and typically in the squatting design.
Pour flush sitting toilets
have also been developed,
but they are not
widely available and implemented.
The Cistern Flush Toilet or water closet
is another very widespread and well-known
water-based user interface.
It also has a water seal, and is equipped
with a water-filled cistern.
When the user operates the flush mechanism
the water from the system
is released into the toilet bowl
to carry away the excreta
to the next functional group.
Both sitting and squatting models exist.
The input and output products
of a cistern flush toilet
are exactly the same
as those previously shown
for the pour flush technology.
Blackwater is also generated as an output
but normally in larger quantities
than in the pour flush toilet,
due to the higher water use.
Cistern flush toilets exist
since more than two centuries,
but only became
a popular industrial product
in the late 19th Century,
with its worldwide spread
starting from Europe.
As you can see on the right-hand side,
flush toilets looked
quite different in the beginning
from how we know them today.
The urine-diversion principle
has also been applied
to the cistern flush toilet
as urine-diverting flush toilets
were developed in more recent years.
This user interface technology is equipped
with a bowl for the collection of urine
and with a water seal through which
the feces are carried away.
There are designs with valves
which close during the flush
to collect undiluted urine.
Other designs do not prevent
a small quantity of flush water
from entering the urine pipe.
The urine-diverting flush toilet has,
again, the same inputs
as a pour flush system
or a cistern flush toilet:
Feces, urine, flush water,
anal cleansing water
and dry cleansing materials;
however, the urine is not mixed
with the other products,
but separately collected.
The resulting urine-free product
which is flushed away
is therefore called brownwater.
This technology also exists
in different shapes and colors,
and as sit and squat models.
This design here is also installed
at the Eawag offices.
It collects urine,
which we use for our research,
mainly to study ways
how to recover nutrients
for the production of fertilizers.
The blue diversion toilet,
which was developed by Eawag
in collaboration with industrial designers
from EOOS in Austria
is a special variant
of the urine-diverting flush toilet.
It also has a flush, but only to clean
the urine collection bowl
as you can see here in the image.
The water is then treated and recycled.
Feces and urine, they are not
mixed with flush water.
Therefore, this design does not generate
brownwater as an output.
Urine-diverting flush toilets
are not very widespread yet
because of some design challenges,
high cost, and limited demand.
We now have seen six different options
for the user interface,
but how can we choose the right one
for a given context?
There are a number of factors
on which the technology choice depends.
The availability of water is crucial
for all technologies which depend
on flush water
to carry away the excreta.
The user interface should, of course,
also take into account
the preferences and habits
of the people who use it.
Are they sitters or squatters?
Washers of wipers?
Another important factor
is the local availability.
Can I find the technology
on the local market,
or can I build it myself?
As we have seen,
the different technologies
generate different output products
with very different characteristics.
This influences the technology
which can come next,
be it a collection and storage technology
or a conveyance technology.
Last but not least, special needs
of user groups should also be considered,
such as the needs of children,
elderly, or disabled.
People's needs change
based on age, location,
health, physical ability,
mental state, etc.
The concept of inclusive design
takes this into consideration.
Inclusive design aims to remove
barriers that exclude people
from being able to use facilities
as a result of their evolving needs.
It ensures equitable access for all,
including marginalized user groups
which may, in some cases,
also face some barriers
and exclusion from sanitation
and hygiene facilities.
An example of inclusive design
is the provision of ramps
or the installation
of handrails in toilets
to ensure easy access.
Inclusive design considerations
are of particular importance
for facilities at schools
or health centers and for public toilets.
In the last few minutes
we have gone through
a variety of designs through which
people access a sanitation system.
To sum it all up,
I would like to highlight four key points.
Different designs have been developed
for different user preferences and habits,
such as squatting and sitting toilets
as well as options which allow the use
of different materials for cleansing,
such as water for washing,
or dry materials for cleansing.
Second, there are two
main types of interfaces:
dry technologies
that operate without water,
and water-based technologies
that need a regular supply of water
to properly function.
Third,
different user interface technologies
generate different output products.
This, of course, influences
the subsequent type
of collection and storage technology
or conveyance that is possible.
FInally, the design
should not only consider
technical aspects
and user preferences,
but also the barrier-free access
for all users.
In the next modules, we will be looking
at the following functional group:
Collection and Storage,
and on-site treatment.
The following modules will also answer
the question of this fellow here:
Where do the products generated
at the user interface go?
See you later.