In the last module
we looked at the different
user interface technologies
and how they function.
Now we will move on
to the second functional group,
and see how the output products
of a user interface
can be collected, stored,
and/or treated on-site.
The functional group
Collection and Storage/Treatment
describes the ways of collecting,
storing, and sometimes treating
the products generated
at the user interface.
The treatment provided
by these technologies
is often the function of storage,
and is usually passive,
without requiring energy input.
Products that emanate
from these technologies
often require subsequent treatment
before use or disposal.
There's quite a wide range of technologies
which belong to this functional group.
In order to present them
in manageable packages,
I split them up into three modules.
In this module I will talk
about technologies in which
a single pit is used.
Then I will present the options which rely
on two alternating pits to function,
and third, we will look
at anaerobic technologies
which are not based on pits.
So let's start with the first module.
I will first present the difference
between a single pit
and a single Ventilated Improved Pit.
Then I am going to explain
how the ventilation functions
and why it can be an advantage to install
a ventilation pipe with the pit.
In the end, I will show
some key considerations
for a good pit design.
The single pit is one of the most widely
used sanitation technologies.
It consists of a hole in the ground
which is usually
three or more meters deep.
It normally has a lining
to stabilize the walls of the pit.
At least the top 20 to 40 centimeters
should be lined
with a support ring
made of bricks or blocks.
The user interface
can then be placed on top of it.
I will give you some more details
about pit lining a little bit later.
The single pit is a simple technology
which is most suited to rural areas
and can be at very low cost,
depending on the materials used
and the depth of excavation;
however, emptying costs may be quite high
and the sludge
needs to be further treated.
This has to be considered
when choosing this option.
A major disadvantage of single pits
is that the emptied sludge
is still very pathogenic
and leakage can contaminate
groundwater resources.
Also, odors are normally noticeable
and flies hatching in the pit
can be a vector for disease transmission.
As we have seen for the user interface,
the different technologies have
different input and output products.
This also applies to each technology
from the other functional groups
including collection and storage.
If we take the example of the single pit,
the input products can be
excreta, blackwater, or feces,
usually mixed either
with anal cleansing water
or dry cleansing materials.
Remember that those
are the output products
of the different user interface options.
Obviously, several
user interface technologies
are compatible
with this technology here,
because several different input products
are possible here.
On the output side we have fecal sludge,
which needs to be transported
for further treatment.
For the following technologies,
I won't give such a detailed presentation
of the inputs and outputs anymore,
because the principle remains the same,
but if you are interested
about possible inputs or outputs
of a specific technology,
you may look it up
on the corresponding page
in the Compendium.
When designing a sanitation system,
it can be very helpful to look
at the input and output products
of a technology
to see which options
can be linked to it
before or after.
Single pits can be improved
by installing a ventilation pipe
with a diameter
of at least 11 centimeters.
They are then called
Ventilated Improved Pits, or VIP.
But why is the ventilation
an improvement?
Of course it can eliminate odors,
but it also has another important function.
But let's first look
at how the ventilation works.
The main driver that helps
to ventilate the pit is actually the wind.
Wind passing over the top
of our ventilation pipe
creates a suction pressure
within the pipe
and induces an air circulation.
If the vent pipe is well fitted
and the edges of the pit are airtight,
the air is drawn through
the user interface into the pit,
moves up inside the vent pipe,
and escapes into the atmosphere.
For an effective ventilation,
the top of the pipe should extend
at least 30 centimeters
over the roof of the superstructure.
The vent works best in windy areas
but where there is little wind,
it's effectiveness can be improved
by painting the pipe black
and exposing it to the sun.
The heat difference between
the cool pit and the warm vent
creates an updraft that pulls the air
up and out of the pit.
Besides removing odors,
another beneficial effect
is that flies that hatch in the pit
are attracted to the light
at the top of the ventilation pipe.
With a semi-dark superstructure,
flies fly toward the light in the pipe.
A fly screen or mesh
at the top of the pipe
traps them and prevents them
from escaping.
The attraction for flies from the outside
is also minimized,
because odors are allowed to escape.
Good ventilation
effectively prevents odors
and is able to reduce the fly problem
and the spread of diseases they may carry.
The ventilation is not that easy
to construct properly;
however, a design like the one here
is probably a bit exaggerated.
Something like the one over here
with a good fly screen
is normally sufficient.
The VIP is a low cost option,
although slightly more expensive
than a simple pit.
Other advantages and disadvantages
are the same as for the simple pit.
Now, let's look at some general design
considerations for single pits.
Pits may be circular
or rectangular in plan,
as shown in this image.
Round pits are more suitable
because the earth pressure
is evenly distributed,
creating a natural arching effect.
Rectangular pits
have a tendency to collapse.
Typically, a pit is at least
three meters deep
and one meter in diameter.
Especially if the pit is to be reused,
its walls should be lined.
This prevents the pit from collapsing
during emptying.
Pit lining materials can include brick,
rot-resistant timber, concrete, or stones.
The lining of the upper edge of the pit
can be built in the so-called
"corbelled brickwork" technique
as shown here.
This design allows us to use
a smaller diameter slab
and can save some costs.
The bottom of the pit
should remain unlined
to allow for the infiltration
of liquids out of the pit.
Permeable side walls
can accelerate the leeching.
To protect the groundwater,
sometimes watertight
or sealed pits are built,
but this can be very expensive.
To prevent groundwater contamination,
the bottom of the pit should be at least
two meters above the groundwater level.
A minimum horizontal distance
of 30 meters between the pit
and the water source
is normally recommended to limit
exposure to microbial contamination,
but these values depend on the soil type,
moisture, and other environmental factors.
The pit volume should be designed
based on the number of users,
the design life or desired filling time,
and the local sludge accumulation rate.
The sludge accumulation rate
depends on several factors
including the infiltration
capacity of the soil,
the biodegradability
of dry cleansing materials,
and the water use.
It is typically in the order of magnitude
of 40 to 90 liters per capita per year.
SIngle pits are a simple technology
which can be very appropriate,
particularly in rural areas
with a low risk of groundwater pollution.
Single pits should not be used
where the groundwater table is high,
or in areas that are frequently flooded
or have rocky soils.
They are not suitable
for dense urban areas,
particularly because emptying can pose
serious problems and health risks.
The use of a vent pipe in a VIP
adds comfort and reduces flies,
but needs to be carefully designed
to function properly.
In the next module we are going to look
at the technologies that use two pits.