In the second module,
Collection and Storage
we will look at four
different technologies
which are based on
double pits or double vaults.
I will explain why it can make sense
to install two pits
and use them alternatingly
and in which situations
those four technologies
are most appropriate.
Like everything in life
these technologies also have
their advantages and disadvantages.
You will learn about them
in the next few minutes.
Let's start with something
that we are familiar with already:
the ventilated improved pit or VIP.
What you can see here
is basically the same
as the single VIP we already know,
just with the second pit
added next to it.
That's why we call this
technology the double VIP.
It's use is very similar
to the single VIP
but when one pit is full,
it is not immediately emptied.
Rather, the full pit is closed
and the superstructure
moved to the other one.
While the second pit fills
the content of the first one
is allowed to rest, drain
and naturally decompose
until both pits are full.
Only then, the first pit is
emptied and used again.
This cycle can go on indefinitely.
Each pit should be designed
to accommodate the excreta
of one to two years.
During that time, the material
in the resting pit
becomes partially sanitized
and humus like.
We therefore call it pit humus.
The humus is a solid product
which cannot be pumped
and needs to be excavated
manually using a shovel.
The side walls of the pits
can have openings
for better infiltration.
But the middle separating wall
should be waterproofed
to avoid re-wetting
of the resting material.
Instead of being moved
from one pit to the other
the superstucture may also
extend over both pits
as the one shown in this photo.
In this example from Mauritania
the superstructure is relatively big
because there is also
a bathing place in the middle
which is connected to a separate
soak pit for the greywater.
The picture below shows two
access covers for emptying.
An advantage of the double VIP
is that the pits are permanent
and designed for constant operation.
With proper maintenance
double pits can have
an indefinite service life.
Emptying is easier and safer
than fecal sludge
because the resulting pit humus is solid
much less offensive
and has a significantly
reduced pathogen content.
The product may even be used to improve
the water and nutrient retaining
properties of agricultural soils.
As in VIPs, the contamination
of groundwater resources
is still possible with this technology,
and double VIPS are not suitable
for rocky ground or areas
that are prone to flooding.
Because of the product being solid
manual emptying is required.
This can be done by the users themselves
which reduces the operating costs
and does not require accessibility
by vacuum trucks.
However, the upfront investment
costs for double pits
are obviously higher
than for single pits.
The so called Fossa Alterna
is very similar to the double VIP.
Compared to the double VIP, however,
which is basically just designed
to collect, store
and partially treat excreta
the Fossa Alterna is actually designed
to make higher quality earth-like product
that can be used as a
valuable soil conditioner.
This is achieved by adding
soil, ash, or leaves
as cover material after each defecation
which absorbs the liquids inside the pit
and increases the pore space
allowing for aerobic conditions.
The cover material also reduces smells
and introduces a variety
of microoganisms
which help in the degradation process.
The pits are dug to a maximum
depth of 1.5 meters,
and therefore, often do not require
a lining on the entire side walls
allowing for soil organisms
to enter and do their job.
Like in the double VIP,
the full pit degrades
while the second pit is filling
which ideally should take one year.
Because of the added carbon-rich
bulking material,
the degradation process is accelerated
and the content is ready for excavation
and use
much faster than in a double VIP.
Greywater should not be added
because it fills the pore spaces
and deprives the aerobic bacteria
of the oxygen that is required
for degradation.
The advantages and disadvantages
of the Fossa Alterna
are slightly different to
the ones of the double VIP.
Emptying is still done
manually using a shovel
but may be even easier
because of the cover material
which give the humus a less
compact, more aerated form.
Important to note
is that soil, ash or leaves
should be constantly available
to generate the desired
nutrient-rich, compost like product.
Separate solid waste
and greywater management
are crucial to enjoy
a high quality product.
Twin pits for pour flush,
sometimes called double leach pits
are designed to receive
blackwater as input
and possibly also greywater.
As you can see on the drawing,
the pour flush toilet
is used as user interface
and connected to one
of the pits by a pipe.
The other pit is properly sealed
for example, using cement and bricks.
Alternatively, it is also possible
to use a single straight pipe
fixed with light mortar
and covered with earth.
The blackwater is collected in the pit
and allowed to slowly
infiltrate into the surrounding soil.
As liquid leaches from the pit
and migrates through
the unsaturated soil matrix
pathogenic germs are absorbed
onto the soil surface.
In this way, pathogens can be removed
prior to contact with groundwater.
Like in the previous technologies,
when the pit becomes full, it is closed,
and allowed to rest before being emptied.
As this is a water-based wet technology
the full pits require
a longer retention time
of two years to degrade the material.
Over time, the content is sufficiently
dewatered
and can be safely excavated
in the form of pit humus,
again, manually, with a shovel.
It is recommended that
the twin pits be constructed
one meter apart from each other
to minimize cross-contamination
between the material pit
and the one in use.
Water within a pit
can impact its stability.
Therefore, the full depth of the pit walls
should be lined to prevent collapse.
As you can see
in the drawining on the right
numerous openings in the pit lining
facilitate the leaching.
Twin pits also have a few specific
advantages and disadvantages.
Compared to the previous options
flies and odors are further reduced
due to the use of the pour flush latrine.
Because this is a water-based technology
the soil must have
a good infiltration capacity.
Clay, tightly packed, or
rocky soils are not appropriate.
This technology is not suitable
for areas with a high groundwater table
or where there is frequent flooding.
There is a risk of groundwater pollution
when pits are located in areas
with a high or variable water table.
As a rule of thumb, it can be recommended
to have a minimum horizontal distance
of 30 meters between
the pits and the water source
to limit exposing the water source
to microbial contamination.
Dehydration vaults are watertight
alternating chambers
that are usually built above the ground
to collect, store and dry feces.
One chamber is in use while
the other one dehydrates.
When feces are not mixed with urine
and other liquids, they dry quickly.
In the absence of moisture
organisms cannot grow
pathogens are destroyed
and smells minimized.
This technology requires the use
of the UDDT as a user interface.
Urine is diverted,
flows through a hose or pipe,
and is collected in a storage tank.
What enters the dehydration
vaults is only feces
and possibly dry cleansing materials.
To prevent flies, minimize odors
and encourage a drying
a small amount of ash, lime, dry soil
or sawdust should be used
to cover feces after each use.
Ash and lime additionally raise the pH
which causes pathogens to die off.
A vent pipe is required to
remove humidity from the walls
and control flies and odors.
The World Health Organization recommends
a minimum storage
time of six months
if ash or lime are used
as cover material.
Otherwise, the storage
should be one to two years
depending on the climate.
Each vault is therefore sized
to accommodate at least
six months of feces accumulation.
After the recommended storage time
the pathogens are significantly reduced
and it is easy and safe
to remove the dried material
from the chamber using a shovel.
The dehydrated feces
can then be used as soil conditioner
and the vault put back into service.
As long as no liquids entered the chambers
this technology should be
a confortable and odor-free solution.
It is therefore possible to build
dehydration vaults attached to the house
as it can be seen in this photo
or even integrated into the house
as shown in this drawing.
Dehydration vaults
are especially appropriate
for water scarce and rocky areas
or where the ground water table is high.
They are also suitable in areas
that are frequently flooded
because they are built to be watertight.
Dehydration vaults can be
a clean and easy to use technology.
It is crucial however,
that the users are well trained
to understand how the technology works
and appreciate its benefits.
In this module, we looked
at four technologies
which all have in common
that they use storage
and naturally occurring dewatering
and degradation processes
to produce a material that is safer
and more easy to handle than fecal sludge.
The products from these technologies
can even be used as soil conditioners.
Due to the material being solid
it is not possible to mechanically
empty it using a pump.
It needs to be dug out manually.
This may be seen as a disadvantage
but also as an advantage
especially in areas where
mechanical emptying is expensive
or impossible due to difficult access.
All the double pit technologies shown
are permanent and can be
constantly used if well maintained.
Therefore, they are particularly suited
to peri-urban or urban areas
where it is not possible to dig
a new pit when the old one is full.
On the other hand, the potential risk
to groundwater sources due to leaching
limits the applicability of these
double pit technologies in urban areas.
In the next module
we are going to look
at anaerobic technologies
for collection and storage.