Hello, and welcome to this module
on conveyance technologies.
My name is Philippe Raymond.
I'm an environmental engineer
working at Eawag SANDEC
on sanitation planning
in international
development projects.
I will be presenting
the different conveyance
and treatment technologies.
In the last modules, Lukas Ulrich
introduced you to the user interface
and collection and
storage technologies.
Now the question is: what
happens when the pit is full?
How do we transport waste water
or sludge out of a neighborhood?
Well, there are two
categories of conveyance,
or transport systems.
On the one side,
the sewered systems,
relying on pipe networks,
and on the other side,
the non-sewered systems,
relying on different kinds
of container-based solutions,
upon which we are focused
in this module.
The different sewer systems will
be presented in the next module.
We have three learning goals
for this module.
First, to get to know the
different ways to transport
sanitation products.
Secondly, to get
an integrated view
of manual and motorized emptying.
And finally, to understand
the pros and cons of the
different technologies.
Let's start.
We will take a look
at different ways
to transport sanitation products,
focusing first on manual ways,
and then on motorized ways.
Many development projects focus
only on drinking water supply
or the provision of latrines.
However, in both cases,
building new infrastructure
also implies new sanitation products,
which need to be transported
and properly treated.
These products, which we call here
"output products," can be,
for example, blackwater
and greywater, sludge,
urine, dried feces,
or pit humus,
according to the technologies
that are implemented.
We will focus now
on the transport
of products from on-site
sanitation systems,
and more specifically,
the conveyance of sludge,
or, if you prefer,
fecal sludge, or septage.
When a pit is full, people have
the choice between two options:
either they let the pit overflow,
which is both a nuisance
and a health hazard
for the neighborhood,
or they call manual or motorized
service providers to empty their pit.
The most efficient
and hygienic way
in such a case is the use
of pumping trucks.
However, in low-income
contexts, the use of trucks
is often not possible.
The main reasons are either
that there is no access for trucks,
that the sludge
is too thick to be pumped,
or that the household cannot
afford the often costly service.
Thus, people often resort
to manual emptyings.
Unfortunately, most of the time,
manual emptying looks like this.
Hard work in very unhygienic conditions,
provoking hostility from neighbors.
Manual emptiers face
very harsh conditions
and, at the same time, lack
recognition for their work.
The situation can be improved
with proper equipment
and technologies.
Human-powered emptying
of pits, vaults, and tanks
can be done in two ways: either
with buckets and shovels
or using a portable,
manually operated pump
specially designed for sludge,
such as the Gulper,
the Rummer, or the MAPET.
Manual sludge pumps
are relatively new inventions
and are still being optimized.
Sludge hand pumps --
here, the Gulper --
work on the same concept
as water hand pumps.
Here's the operator, who
pushes and pulls the handle.
The sludge is pumped up and
discharged through the spout.
It can then be collected
in barrels, bags, or carts,
and removed in a quiet,
hygienic way.
Next to that, it is important
also to ensure
that workers are adequately
protected with gloves, boots,
face mask, and overall.
It is important to mention
that proper equipment
and organization help
the manual emptiers
to gain recognition
and acceptance.
Sanitation programs should
strive to legitimize
the work of the laborers
and create the right
enabling environment by
providing permits and licenses,
as well as helping
to legalize the practice.
Let's now look at
motorized emptying.
Motorized emptying refers
to vehicles equipped
with a motorized pump
and a storage tank.
Namely, pumping trucks,
or vacuum trucks.
Generally, the storage capacity
of a vacuum truck
is between 3
and 12 cubic meters.
Pumping trucks come
in all size and shapes,
as shown here in
these four pictures.
They can be locally manufactured,
which ensures that maintenance skills
and spare parts are available.
A drawback, however,
may be limited efficiency.
Smaller vehicles have also been
developed to access areas
with narrow pathways, where
normal trucks cannot access.
Let's look now at
the pros and the cons
of motorized and manual emptying.
The main advantages
of motorized emptying
are that it is fast and efficient,
and it minimizes health risks.
However, it has high capital costs,
as well as operation
and maintenance costs.
These costs are often
passed on to the customer,
who sometimes cannot
afford them.
Besides, the trucks cannot
pump thick sludge,
garbage in pits may block the hose,
and the pumps really only suck
to a depth of 2 to 3 metres.
Trucks may also have difficulties
with spatial access, and spare parts
may not always be available.
The main advantages
of manual emptying
are low operation
maintenance costs,
the possibility
to access every pit,
and the availability
of maintenance skills
and spare parts.
However, it has
a limited efficiency
and is a time-consuming activity.
And it implies health hazards
when not done properly.
As said before,
it is tough work.
Besides, it requires a disposal
pump nearby, within 500 meters.
In both cases, proper disposal
of the sludge is a challenge.
Distance has a cost,
but not only.
Traffic jams, police checkpoints,
bad state of the roads
may add to the costs
and turn into hindrances
for such conveyance
to treatment plants.
Emptying service providers
aim to reduce distance and time
for each trip, save fuel,
protect their truck,
and minimize the problems
with the population.
All these aspects need to be
taken into account
when selecting options
and designing
a fecal sludge management scheme.
Distance is a critical issue.
If the distance from the collection
points to the treatment plant
is too long, there is a possibility
of building transfer stations.
Transfer stations can be
underground holding tanks
where manual emptiers or small
scale motorized service providers
bring their sludge.
The sludge is then further
conveyed by vacuum trucks.
Another option is a sewer
discharge station,
where sludge is directly discharged
into an existing main sewer line.
In that case, it is important
to manage discharges
with care in order not
to overload an existing
waste water treatment plant.
Transfer stations can be
a useful interface
between informal settlements
where vacuum trucks cannot access,
and formal settlements,
where municipal
or private motorized service
providers are active.
They have to be carefully
located and well maintained
to minimize odors and problems
to nearby residents.
To sum up, we saw that container
based conveyance is much more
a management and institutional
issue than a technical problem.
It needs to be addressed when
building any type of latrines
and collection
and storage system.
Most cities in low-income
countries rely mainly
on on-site sanitation systems.
Container-based conveyance
is not an exception.
It is rather a norm.
So far, it remains mainly
a private sector business,
in which, unfortunately,
most sludge ends up
untreated in the environment.
Proper management schemes
and sustainable financial arrangements
need to be put in place
for the sludge to be treated,
for the service providers
to be recognized and legalized,
and to reduce the health hazards
both for the workers and for
the neighboring population.
Above all, we have to
remember that conveyance
to proper disposal
points has a cost.
The critical aspect
is to estimate this cost
and see how it can be shared
between the different
sanitation stakeholders.
To learn more about
fecal sludge management,
about manual and
motorized emptying,
and how to plan a sustainable
fecal sludge management scheme,
we strongly recommend
the recently published
Eawag Sandec FSM book that
you can download for free
at the link shown below.
In the next section,
I will be presenting
the sewer based
conveyance technologies.
See you then.