Condominial Sewerage Systems
Planning & Design of Sanitation Systems
and Technologies Klaus Neder, CAESB
Welcome to this module
of the MOOC on condominial sewers
and the approach employed in their
design and implementation.
My name is Klaus Neder.
I am an engineer
at CAESB,
the Water and Sanitation Utility
of the Federal District
in Brasília, Brazil,
where I have led CAESB’s efforts
to roll out condominial sewers
and appropriate wastewater treatment
to the whole of
the Federal District
region over the past
twenty years.
Nowadays serving
about 1.5 million people,
the metropolitan area of Brasilia
is one of the most
extensive examples
of the use of the condominial sewers
in the world.
In this module,
you will learn,
what are condominial sewers
and how do they differ
from conventional sewer systems.
What are the advantages
of condominial sewers
over conventional sewers
and in which circumstances
are they particularly beneficial.
What are the implications
of condominial sewers
for a utility company?
Prior to adopting the condominal
sewerage approach in Brasilia,
CAESB found that conventional sewers
were being built but,
households would not
connect to them.
It was quite common that less
than 50 percent of the neighborhood
was effectively connecting
to the new sewer systems.
Consequently,
the large amounts of funds
invested in the trunk
sewer infrastructure
and in the wastewater
treatment plants
would not realize
their expected public health
and environmental benefits.
Some of the major factors
for this failure were,
a lack of dialogue
between the utility
and the households regarding
the sewerage solutions
to be designed
and installed.
The high capital costs
of conventional sewers
that utilities,
and by extension
their customers,
had to cover.
We found that the major reason
that caused users not to connect
to sewers included,
a lack of funds
in the household to allow them
to make the piped
connection to the sewers.
No adequate
internal toilet/plumbing
installations in the household.
The local topography,
including situations
where internal installations
are located lower
than the sewer lines.
An existing solution,
such as septic tanks,
already in use.
Where connecting would require
the breaking of floors and walls
or where the wastewater
was already connected
to some kind of drainage
requiring its separation.
Soon we realized
that conventional approaches
to implement sewers
are generally rigid
and not flexible
or adaptable enough
to take into account
the specific requirements
of the target population
and of the local situation,
such as those mentioned.
As a result, it is often difficult
to roll out
conventional sewerage systems
to which households
actually connect,
especially in informal,
densely populated,
unplanned settlements.
When CAESB first introduced
condominial sewers in Brasilia,
we adopted an approach
in which we did not
expect the client
to come after the sewerage project
but, instead,
through which we would
actively pursue the client.
In fact, following
the condominial philosophy,
we start our work
and our analysis
from the upstream source of the sewage,
this means at the household,
with a focus on each
individual household connection,
and then follow a downstream path
through the trunk sewers
to the wastewater treatment plant.
Such an approach is
in the marked contrast
to conventional
sewerage projects
in which the household connection
is the last concern
or sometimes
is not a concern at all.
Providing adequate, effective,
and affordable connection
to the sewer network
is thus a main objective
of condominial sewer.
The following slide will show
the key characteristics
of the condominial model,
which has been developed
and refined in Brazil, generally,
and in Brasília with CAESB,
in particular,
over a number of decades.
The Condominial approach features
several key characteristics
that distinguishes it
from the implementation
of conventional sewerage interventions.
One key difference
is the participatory approach adopted
during the design and implementation
of condominial sewers
and, sometimes,
during their operation
and maintenance as well.
Households are mobilized
even before engineering designs
are commenced
and are fully encouraged
to engage in the design
and the works phases
of the implementation
of the local sewers.
The community is a major decision
maker regarding the design
and implementation
of the sewer system,
and becomes the owner
of the ‘condominial branch’,
which will be described
more fully later.
An important factor
of condominial sewers
is the reduction in capital costs
that can be achieved
when compared to conventional sewers
through the optimization
of the condominal network
in regards to branch routing,
pipe extension,
pipe depths, pipe diameter,
and the optimized use
of inspection boxes.
One outcome of this optimization
is that condominial sewerage
networks can typically be
50 percent of the length
of conventional ones.
The condominial approach
to implementing sewers provides us
with the tools to depart
from conventional thinking
on the design
principles of sewers.
It thus allows us
to design sewer system
that can be successfully
implemented in densely
populated, unplanned,
informal areas, such as in slums.
One of the guiding principles
of the condominial approach
is to achieve 100 percent
connection rate of households,
whether they are located
in rapidly expanding poor
informal settlements
or in middle class
or rich areas of the city.
Technical details
for the implementation
and maintenance agreement
of the condominial branch
are the result of a discussion
and a joint decision
of the utility
and the targeted community,
and result after consideration
of all viable solutions.
Households are not forced
into certain solutions,
but the technical
and other alternatives
are discussed with them
so that an agreed
optimal position is reached.
In many cases, however,
the local topography
and the elevation of existing household
sanitary installations
are the determining factors
for locating the household
connection and for routing
the condominial branch.
The sequence of development
and execution of condominial works
is different from that
of the traditional sewerage system.
After the utility
has concluded a survey,
a preliminary sewer design is used
to define the ‘condominiums’.
These are the units of service
which will be each having a single,
shared condominial branch sewer.
Both the social
and the technical teams
of the utility will work
with the Condominium members
to define the type
and routing of the condominial branch
that will serve them
as well as the terms
that will be applied
to the construction
and subsequent operation
of the sewer branch.
An essential part
of the implementation
of a condominial program
is the dialogue
and collaboration of the utility
with the Condominium members.
A close relationship
between the two parties
is required
to successfully design,
construct and operate
the condominial sewerage system.
Since such participatory
approaches are relatively new
to traditional sanitation,
CAESB deploys “social teams”
together with their “technical teams”
to facilitate the approach
and to thus help
successfully arrive
at the necessary joint agreements
between the utility
and the community.
The final engineering design
related to the collector networks
are only undertaken
after agreement has first been reached
between the utility
and the condominiums
on the lay out
of the condominial branch.
This process of finalizing
the design of the collector networks
is carried out during the execution
of the corresponding sewer
civil works themselves,
we call it in the field
"final design".
Let us take a closer
look at the possible
layout of a condominial sewerage network
and the different elements
made up by it.
As we just heard,
a condominium
is a newly formed service unit
with a single,
collective connection point.
All households
in one condomium
will connect to
a shared branch
that discharges into a
secondary sewer network.
Instead of service laterals
directly connecting households
to a sewer main
under the street,
the condominial system
uses one single pipe
that connects to each household
in the block.
This is called
the “condominial branch”.
There are different
types of branches,
depending on their location.
However, irrespectively
of whether the branches
are internal
or are at the sidewalk,
they are considered
the responsibility
of the household,
as a sewer connection would be
under traditional sewerage projects.
The illustration shows
how the extension of the pipe network
can be reduced through
optimized routing
of the condominial branch.
Together with the shallower
depth of the branches,
smaller pipe diameters,
and the use of simple inspection boxes
instead of manholes,
capital costs
can be consequently
reduced.
Besides the optimized
network layout introduced
when using the
condominial approach,
there are other design
aspects of condominial sewerage
that help optimize
the costs of installation.
Pipe diameters in condominial branches
are generally minimized.
Hydraulic conditions permit
a diameter of 100 milimeters.
Shallower depths of pipes can be used
when sewers are laid in front or
in the backyard or under the sidewalks,
thus avoiding traffic-bearing sites
so to get as little as 60 cm,
reducing the amount
of excavation required.
In condominial sewerage system,
the number of costly
manholes is reduced
and they are replaced
by simplified forms
called inspection chambers.
These factors not only reduce
the cost of the sewers,
but can also prove beneficial
during maintenance and repairs.
When condominial branches
are located in household yards
and in sidewalks,
access for repair
and maintenance is possible
without the need for the utility
to break up roads
and interrupt traffic.
The condominium members
jointly agree on the location
of the condominial branch.
If the utility is
to maintain the branch,
the sidewalk is
the preferred branch location.
However, in informal, densely populated,
unplanned settlements,
or in other circumstances
such as where the sanitary
facilities are located
at the back
of the house,
the back-of-the-lot branch
is sometimes
the only feasible option.
It is in these circumstances
where the condominial approach
is especially beneficial,
as it can provide
solutions in situations
where conventional sewers
would not be feasible.
Costs savings
of condominial sewerage systems
usually range between 30
and 40 percent of those
of conventional systems.
Furthermore, given that
construction costs
of the condominial branches,
which are considered the private part
of the sewerage network
and are generally
covered by the household,
this arrangement represents
a significant reduction
in the financial burden
assumed by the utility.
Even though the households
are responsible
for the cost of construction
of the condominial branch,
in most cases it is executed
by the utility.
These construction
costs are covered
by the condominium members
in the form of a connection fee,
and are in accordance
with the agreement
signed by each household
and the utility.
A service fee for operation
of the condominial sewer
is usually based on the household’s
monthly water consumption.
In situations where users
opt to maintain
their branch themselves,
they qualify for
a reduced service fee.
The condominial approach involves
the targeted households
and their community
as a fundamental part
of the sewerage solution
and thus creates
ownership among the users,
which is an important factor
in the sustainable
operation of the sewers.
The condominial approach
is based upon the full participation
of the community
in the engineering design
and construction
of the local sewerage system.
This requires
that the utility
employs social outreach specialists
as well as technical/engineering
specialists to work in conjunction
on the design
and implementation phases.
This participation throughout
the project cycle leads
to high levels of
connection by households
to the sewer network,
often reaching 100 percent.
Given the optimization
of the local sewer layout,
the smaller sewer diameters,
the shallower depths
and the greater distances
between the inspection chambers,
the costs of the condominial sewer
civil works can be reduced
by some 30 to 40 percent of the costs
of a corresponding
conventional sewerage solution.
The adaptability
of the condominial approach
to local conditions
enables the provision
of sewerage service
where conventional solutions
would not be possible,
for example
in informal,
densely populated, unplanned,
peri-urban settlements.
However, the condominial approach
can be equally applied
to formally urbanized areas.
In the district of Brazil
where CAESB works,
condominial sewers have been
successfully implemented
in all types
of urban settings,
poor and rich alike.