Welcome back to this final section
on sanitation systems.
The next few templates
that we'll discuss
are all based on transporting
blackwater off site,
so away from the point
where it's generated
to a more centralized point
where it can be treated
along with the blackwater
generated by other households.
This system of blackwater treatment
with effluent transport
is a little more complicated than
a traditional sewer-based system
that would exist in a large
European city
because only the effluent
from the storage technology
is transported.
Each toilet or group of toilets
is connected to some type
of collection and storage technology.
This produces sludge
which must be periodically removed
and treated
as in the previous systems.
But now, the solids-free effluent
can be transported easily
through small diameter sewers
without the risk of clogging.
The effluent can then be treated
in a centralized treatment technology
like a constructed wetland.
The previous systems that we looked at
that relied on infiltration
were not appropriate for dense areas
because of the holding capacity
of the soil.
That is not the problem for this system
because the effluent is transported
in impermeable pipes away
from the community.
Here you can see the construction
of a community scale ABR
and the solids-free sewer
that connects the houses to it.
This system would be suitable
for a very dense urban context
irrespective of the groundwater
or soil conditions.
The solids-free sewers are being laid
underneath these paving stones.
This system, "blackwater transport
to semi-centralized treatment"
is the typical system for most European
and North American cities.
A flush toilet generates blackwater
which is transported through a sewer
to some sort of treatment.
Notice here also that the blackwater
will require some sort of pre-treatment
to prevent the solids from clogging
some of the more treatment systems.
Even robust systems like those
based on activated sludge
should still include some sort
of pre-treatment
just to ensure that no rubbish
enters the treatment technology.
Effluent that is destined for discharge
into the environment
could require some sort of post treatment.
This would ensure that the levels
of pathogens, nutrients
or other constituents do not exceed
environmental limits for the discharge.
The final slide is basically
the water-based version
of the urine diversion system
that we saw in the beginning.
Certainly, it's not a very common
or popular system yet
but it's becoming more commonplace
and it is the system that operates
in the Eawag building in Zurich.
Here you can see what the urine storage
tanks in our buildings look like.
But before we can harvest the urine
we need to start at the beginning
with the user interface.
The system requires
a urine-diverting flush toilet.
This allows for the separation
of urine and brown water
which, you remember, is the combination
of feces and flush water.
The brown water is then transported
through an existing sewer network
to a centralized treatment facility.
Urine does not provide a lot of volume
to the overall waste water mix
but without it the nutrient quality
in the brown water is much lower
and may require less treatment
to meet discharge standards.
The sludge must be treated,
as in the previous systems,
but because there is less liquid
remember that there will also be
less flush water
if urine is not flushed,
the sludge may be thicker
and easier to dry.
The urine, of course, can be used directly
after a sufficient storage period.
However, because this system is best
suited to dense areas or buildings
the large volume of urine may be
difficult to use locally
or alternatively, transported
to where it's needed.
We covered a lot of material
in this module on sanitation systems.
But the key points are simple:
We can use system templates to help
design complete, logical systems
that do not skip
any products or processing.
A system template is essentially
a matrix of products and functional groups
with specific technologies
at the intersection point.
There are nine different system templates
that can be used to generate
hundreds of possible systems,
and realistically, there could be
other system templates
but these are the ones
that we work with at Sandec.
Although the system templates can
help in the initial phases,
they must be used in conjunction
with good engineering
and local understanding.
In Module 4 you will see and examine
some different case studies
in which sanitation systems either
worked out fairly well
or, sometimes...not so well.
Looking forward to seeing you then.