We are now going to look
at technologies
for using or disposing
of treated effluent.
I will also briefly talk
about surface disposal
and storage of sludge
and other solid products
that cannot be utilized.
Biogas is another sanitation product
that can be used beneficially.
We will shortly see how.
Let's start
with the utilization of effluent.
Remember that effluent
is the general term
for a liquid that leaves the technology,
typically after blackwater or sludge
has undergone solid-liquid separation
or some other type of treatment.
Depending on the level of treatment,
the effluent may be completely sanitized
or may still require further treatment
before it can be used or disposed of.
In general, only water that has had
secondary treatment, for example,
in a physical and then a biological
treatment step, should be used,
to limit the risk of crop contamination
and health risks to workers.
To reduce dependence on fresh water
and increase crop yields by supplying
increased water and nutrients to plants,
properly treated wastewater
can be used for irrigation in agriculture.
There are two kinds
of irrigation technologies.
First, "drip irrigation", where the water
is slowly dripped on or near the root area
as shown in this drawing here,
and second, surface irrigation
where water is routed over land
in a series of dug channels or furrows,
as you can see on this photo.
Of course, it is also possible
to manually apply water to plants
using watering cans.
To minimize evaporation
and contact with pathogens, however,
spray irrigation should be avoided.
WHO published a volume of guidelines
specifically on wastewater
use in agriculture.
These should be consulted
for detailed information
and specific guidance.
You can find this document
for download on the course webpage.
Another way of generating benefits
from treated effluent
is the use in aquaculture.
Aquaculture refers
to the controlled cultivation
of aquatic plants and animals.
Two examples are fish ponds
and floating plant ponds.
Fish and plants growing in such ponds
remove the nutrients from the wastewater
and are eventually harvested.
Fish are typically used for consumption
or as a source of protein
for other animals,
and plants like duckweed can be used
to feed animals, for instance.
Plant ponds can even achieve
additional reduction of organic matter
and suspended solids.
It is possible to combine fish
and floating plants in one single pond.
There are also WHO guidelines
on wastewater and excreta use
in aquaculture
containing detailed information
about health aspects
and specific guidance for risk reduction.
You can also download them
from the course page if you're interested.
In case there is no use for the effluent,
it can be discharged to a "soak pit",
also known as a "soakaway" or "leach pit".
A "soak pit" is a covered,
porous walled chamber
that allows water to slowly infiltrate
into the ground.
It can be left empty and lined
with a porous material
to provide support and prevent collapse,
or left unlined and filled
with coarse rocks and gravel
as shown in the photo.
Primary treatment of the wastewater
is required in both cases,
In order to prevent clogging.
As the effluent percolates
through the filter material,
into the surrounding soil,
small particles are filtered out
by the soil matrix
and organics are digested
by microorganisms.
This relatively simple technology
is best suited for soils
with good absorptive properties.
A "leach field" or "drainage field"
is also designed to infiltrate
pre-settled effluent.
It is a network of perforated pipes
that are laid in underground,
gravel-filled trenches,
to dissipate the effluent, typically
from a water-based collection
and storage technology,
like a septic tank.
The piping system
distributes the effluent
into the subsurface soil
for absorption and further treatment.
The treatment takes place
by soil microorganisms.
To prevent contamination,
a leach field should be located
sufficiently away
from a drinking water source.
This technology
is particularly appropriate
for rural areas, where the risk
of over-saturating the soil is low,
and where there is sufficient space.
Like for the soak pit,
primary treatment of the effluent
is crucial to prevent clogging.
Treated effluent or stormwater
can also be directly discharged
into receiving water bodies
such as rivers or lakes,
or into the ground to recharge aquifers.
The use of the surface
water body, for example,
as a resource for drinking water,
influences the quality and quantity
of treated wastewater
that can be introduced
without negative effects.
Parameters such as turbidity,
temperature and nutrients, among others,
should be closely monitored
when releasing effluent
into a natural water body.
Groundwater recharge
is most appropriate
for areas where groundwater
resources deplete,
and in coastal communities
where saltwater intrusion from the sea
becomes a threat.
In the previous module, we already
looked at agricultural application
of treated feces, compost, or sludge.
In case there is no demand for,
or acceptance
of the beneficial use of these products,
surface disposal of the generated solids
may be the only option.
"Surface disposal" refers to the stockpiling
of sludge, feces, or other materials
that cannot be used elsewhere.
Once the material has been taken
to such a disposal site,
it is not used later.
Storage refers to temporary stockpiling.
It can be done
when a future need is anticipated
or when further
pathogen reduction or drying
is desired before application.
Surface disposal
is primarily used for sludge
although it is applicable
for any type of dry, unusable material.
Landfilling sludge along with municipal
solid waste is not advisable,
since it reduces the life of a landfill
which has been specifically designed
for the containment
of more noxious materials.
Surface disposal sites
should ideally be located
close to where the sludge is treated
to minimize transport distances.
Attention must be paid
to groundwater contamination and leaching.
Sites for temporary storage of a product
should be covered to avoid
rewetting by rainwater.
"Biogas" is another quite different type
of product from sanitation systems.
It contains energy and can basically
be used like any fuel gas.
As you can see from these pictures here,
biogas can be easily used
at household level
for cooking and for lighting.
but it is even possible to operate
refrigerators or vehicles with biogas.
Another use of biogas
is in engines to generate electricity,
like the small one shown here.
At household level, cooking
is the most suitable use,
because the calorific efficiency
of 55% is quite high for that application.
With only 3%, biogas lamps
are far less efficient.
We have seen
that properly treated effluent
can also be beneficially used
in agriculture or aquaculture.
Its constant availability
throughout the year
may reduce farmers' dependence
on fresh water
and the valuable nutrient contents
can help to improve crop yields.
If utilization is not possible or desired,
ways to safely dispose
of the generated effluent
or solid materials have to be found.
In order not to pollute the environment,
it is of particular importance
to identify appropriate sites
to dispose of those products.
Sanitation systems can be designed
not only to recover water and nutrients,
but also energy.
Biogas is a valuable
source of renewable energy
which can be easily generated and used.
The following module is about
innovative emerging technologies
and ongoing developments
in the sanitation sector.