Welcome to the final module
on sanitation technologies.
It is about emerging technologies
and new ongoing developments
in the sector.
In the last few lectures
we tried to give you an overview
of the entire spectrum
of sanitation technologies.
We could not present
all technologies that exist,
but our focus was on those
that are fully developed
and that have been proven
and tested in field applications.
However, in addition
to those established technologies,
there are several innovations
that have moved beyond laboratory phase
and are currently being implemented
in the context of low
and middle income countries
at a scale that shows
great promise for the future.
In recent years many organizations
around the world
started to work on technology
and business model innovations
in the entire chain
between user interface designs
and end use technologies.
Other research focuses
on further developing
the already well-known
and widespread technologies
to improve their performance.
There are so many exciting
and promising initiatives and projects
that there is no way for me
to list them all here,
I just want you to be aware
that the list of technologies
that we presented in this course
is not the end of the story.
It may just be the beginning.
If you are interested to learn more
about what's going on
in this dynamic sector,
I can highly recommend you
to check out the online forum
of the Sustainable Sanitation Alliance,
SuSanA,
and in particular the section
on innovative sanitation science
and technology.
The SuSanA is a great platform
for learning and sharing,
and by signing up on the forum
you can continue the discussion
beyond this course
and exchange your
knowledge and experience
with more than 4,000
sanitation enthusiasts
from all over the world.
Some further reading
on the emerging sanitation technologies
is provided on pages
166 to 169 of the compendium
and in the chapter The Way Forward
of the FSM book.
As described also in that book chapter,
a lot of research and development work
still needs to be done
in order to achieve
adequate sanitation for all,
and it will take time to overcome
the bottlenecks that still exist.
One major challenge is that innovation
and transformation processes
in this sector are quite slow,
because, among other reasons,
centralized network infrastructure
typically stays in the ground
for several decades,
and alternatives are still
too little known.
This prevents innovative
sanitation technologies
from being taken up at scale.
I am convinced that through
our joint collaborative efforts
we can overcome the knowledge gap
and bring sanitation innovations
a step further.
In the following modules
Elizabeth Tilly will show you
how the technologies
of different functional groups
can be combined into logical systems.