Welcome to week four of our course
on sanitation planning and implementation.
This week, we will be taking a look
at three case studies
from around the world
that have successfully
or unsuccessfully implemented
different sanitation solutions
for urban areas,
and tried to improve
environmental conditions.
In this first case study, we will analyze
an example of a small town in Nepal.
The Nala case from Nepal is an example
of the CLUES planning approach
and subsequent implementation
conducted between 2009 and 2012.
We'll look at the sequence
of planning steps,
the main outcomes, and the costs involved
in turning the plan into reality.
The Nala case study
highlights the great advantages
of involving communities
from the start,
and the cost savings that can be achieved
through community engagement.
The case study of Nala in Nepal
is a typical case study
for a small town in Asia.
Nala is a small town near Katmandu
with a population
of about 2,300 inhabitants,
390 households, with an average
household size of 5.8 persons.
Why was Nala chosen?
Because of the strong demand
from the community
to improve sanitation conditions
in the area, and secondly,
because of the high
settlement density in Nala
that allowed to test
urban service provision
that goes beyond
individual onsite solutions
and to test sewered, connected
sanitation solutions like this one here,
with a simplified sewer
under construction.
Some of the socioeconomic data about Nala:
Nala is not very poor, but there is
a considerable minority Dalit population
of about 10% of the population
that lives just under
or about at the poverty level.
Health and hygiene
is also partly very poor,
with 66 households within Nala
that did not have access to toilets,
and that relied on open defecation
on the outskirts of the small town.
The main economic activities
in Nala is agriculture.
A lot of potato seedlings
for the entire country are grown here,
and Nala is also positioned
well near Katmandu Valley
with less than one hour drive
to Katmandu, the nation's capital.
The infrastructure conditions
were quite poor.
The majority of population
had pour flush toilets
that were connected to cesspits,
but because of the poor condition,
needed frequent emptying.
The storm water and gray water
in town was also poor,
emptying into temporary drains
and frequent flooding events.
Water supply in Nala
came from public tap stands
like the one shown here on the left,
or from private taps within households.
Common to all public and private taps
is the high microbial contamination
of all sources
due to the poor sanitation
found in Nala.
Solid waste: you could find
traditional composting practices
which combined kitchen waste
and animal waste at household level.
We'll now look at the planning steps
that were undertaken,
in CLUES planning in Nala
and how the six planning steps
led to the implementation
that was then chosen.
It all started with step one,
process ignition and demand creation,
in April 2009.
A series of workshops,
people were brought together
from the community
to inform them about
the CLUES planning approach
and the proposed project
to improve sanitation,
environmental sanitation services
for the Nala community.
Closely linked to the ignition
was user empowerment
and the holding of several
key promotional events
like the sanitation bazaar
shown here,
where people were informed
about solutions,
about different technologies,
and about how at the individual levels
households could also improve
their individual sanitation
and water supply systems.
The sanitation exhibition shown here
was held on one day in November, 2009,
and brought together NGOs
from all over Nepal
who showcased some of their solutions
that they had come up with
in other parts of the country.
Step two was the launch
of the planning process.
This included household mapping,
a socioeconomic survey,
and a stakeholder assessment
of all the key actors in Nala.
In step three, a detailed assessment
of the current situation was carried out.
This included expert workshop
and the assessment of user preferences
that was conducted
in focus group discussions.
Important was that the detailed assessment
and the information that was found
during the assessment period
was also shared with the community.
An example is shown to the right:
the water quality for the different
public taps found in Nala
that were shared
with the population at large.
In addition, exposure visits
were carried out by the Nala committee.
Here was all about learning from others,
how had others solved some
of their environmental sanitation problems
but also exposing
the users committee from Nala
to management options
and other technology choices
that were made
in similar settings in Nepal.
Step four included the prioritization
of the community problems,
and the validation.
The factors considered here
were technical feasibility of solutions
and the socio-cultural acceptance,
making sure that the solutions
to be proposed in step five
really meet people's
and users' expectations.
During step five, the identification
of service options was done.
This included drawing up an action plan
for offsite sewered sanitation,
shown in brown on the map to the right,
or onsite sanitation for VIP latrines.
The two areas were selected
due to physical conditions.
The green areas are areas that cannot
be easily connected
to the sewered network.
The following, the three options
that were discussed,
both with experts and with the community,
are quickly shown.
The first option was a fully onsite,
double VIP latrine option,
which included pour flush toilets
that are connected
to a double pit solution
and further transport and treatment
that are offsite.
The second solution included
urine diverting dry toilets.
The UDD toilets
are quite well know in Nepal
and have been tested
in other locations,
and of course, include an onsite treatment
to separate urine from feces.
Both of them which could then be used
in agricultural areas outside of town.
The third option and most complex option
is the simplified sewerage
connected to a DEWATS, Decentralized
Waste Water Treatment System.
This actually was the option
that was chosen by the community,
connecting existing pour flush toilets
connected to a collection,
then to transport
through simplified sewers,
treatment through DEWATS, and then
final reuse or disposal of the influent
to natural water bodies.
All three of these options were discussed
in the Environmental Sanitation
Improvement Plan for Nala,
which is shown here,
and the action plan was drawn up
and written by a local NGO, CIUD,
which also prioritized black water
and health and hygiene promotions
as the first step for improvement
of the urban environment in Nala.
Let's look at some of the CLUES outcomes
that have been implemented since.
Nala has built a new
offsite infrastructure system.
It is the first sewered
small town in Nepal
that features a simplified
sewerage network for the entire town,
except for the few households
we had mentioned before.
352 households
are connected to the system,
and each household pays a user fee,
which amounts to $1,300
that are collected annually in fees.
Out of this money, a caretaker
has been employed,
and he ensures a daily maintenance
of the entire system plus treatment plant.
The cost sharing arrangements
for the capital expenditures
was met by the local authority,
the UN-Habitat, Water Aid, and Eawag.
Most of the capital costs
were paid by external donors
such as UN-Habitat or Water Aid.
There was, however, a significant
contribution by the Nala community,
contributing an estimated 37%
of the overall CAPEX
for sewers and the DEWATS plant.
All households connected
to the sewer system
were expected to pay
a connection fee of USD$80
and could apply for a micro-finance loan
with 6% interest yearly.
By 2014, all of the loans
have been repaid.
Great attention was also paid
to operation and maintenance,
and during the construction period,
an O&M workshop was conducted with the
Nala Water and Sanitation Users Committee.
Since 2013, a full time caretaker
has been employed
who ensures smooth running
of the sanitation services
and can troubleshoot
any problems in daily operations
of both the simplified sewer
and the plant.
After over one year of operation,
the simplified sewers
have only been blocked once
due to construction activities
whilst connecting a new household.
The infrastructure
that was put in place in Nala
includes a state-of-the-art
DEWATS treatment plant,
including 36 cubic meter settling tanks,
two ABReactors
with 105 cubic meter volume,
and shown in the left in the background,
two horizontal subsurface flow
constructed wetlands
with a surface area of 210 square meters.
This is during construction phase.
That is why the constructed wetlands
have not yet been planted.
The entire spatial footprint
of the plant is 350 square meters.
The overall treatment capacity
is designed for 32 meter cube per day.
The management arrangements were also
a key to the success of the Nala planning.
It involved three key actors:
most importantly
the WatSan Users Committee,
which is legally registered entity
that acts as the local operator
and ensures the long term
O&M of the system.
The Users Committee also collects
the annual maintenance fee
from each household.
Second, the formal LA, local authority,
called Village Development Committee,
or VDC in Nepal.
They were instrumental in ensuring
the land acquisition for the DEWATS plant.
Lastly, the supporting NGO, CIUD
which provided expertise
and coordination on the ground,
ensuring smooth planning
and implementation.
Let's take a look
at the capital expenditure
and operational expenditure
of the Nala case.
On the CAPEX side, we have costs
for the planning, the DEWATS plant,
the simplified sewerage,
and quite a hefty cost,
the land acquisition, at USD$31,000.
Together, these costs add up
to a per capita capital expenditure
of USD$75 per capita
for both sewers and DEWATS plant,
and that is quite a good price ratio
for a complete system for a small town.
Important to note is also
the high cost contribution by the users,
which adds up to an estimated 37%
of all the costs mentioned above.
This was brought by in-kind
contributions in cash,
or through labor contributions.
The estimated operational costs
are given at around USD$1,000 per year,
although this number is only
after one year of operation.
The timeline, the planning took
14 months in 2009 and 2010,
and the implementation,
12 months between 2011 and 2012.
Some of the conclusions and lessons
learned from the CLUES case study in Nala.
It pays to have a strong,
community based leadership
that is well rooted in the community
and can drive forward the process.
Secondly, the labor and cash
contributions by the community
contributed considerably
to lowering the costs
of the overall infrastructure and services
that were put in place.
Thirdly, the incremental improvements
that were brought to the system,
starting out with the black water system
put into place for Nala,
combined together
with hygiene promotion efforts.
Then fourthly, the informed choice
by key stakeholders in Nala,
ensuring that empowerment and ownership
of the new services and infrastructures
are guaranteed in the long run.
This was the first case study
presented in week four
on different case studies of urban
sanitation planning and implementation,
and gave an overview of the CLUES approach
between 2009 and 2012
in Nala, Nepal.