Welcome back to our second module
on the Erdos, China case study.
In the last module we presented the case
of the Erdos eco-san pilot project
and highlighted
some of its unique features:
the first multi-story source-separating
dry toilet project in China,
and the closed loop
nutrient recovery processes
that were implemented.
In this module, we are going
to analyze some of the problems
and challenges that cropped up very early
after the residents had moved in,
and eventually led
to the low levels of user satisfaction
shown in the graph here,
and finally led to the total dismantling
of the dry sanitation system in 2010.
This graph highlights the four
main grievances and issues at play
that explain the high rate
of dissatisfaction.
The institutional, financial,
and socio-cultural aspects.
By far, the most important
are the technical aspects.
The main issue here
was new toilet technology
that was not yet robust and mature enough
to stand the wear and tear
of everyday use.
This was due to mechanical parts
that malfunctioned,
and the incorrectly installed
ventilation system
that was compounded by broken fans.
This led to major odor problems
and huge complaints by the residents.
Also, the fans were perceived
as being too loud
when they were in operation.
A further problem common
to urine separating dry toilets
was the crystallization of urine
in the odor locks.
Some of these failures can be explained
by the installation
of a totally new system
and the lack of experience
by the local builders
in installing them.
Secondly, the socio-cultural aspects.
The Erdos apartments
were bought by aspiring,
upwardly mobile apartment owners
who never really accepted the toilets
and perceived them
as being inferior technology.
This non-acceptance
led to the incorrect use,
for example, using water to flush
as shown here,
or throwing solid waste
into the toilet bowl.
These problems were highlighted
by an evaluation conducted by SEI.
The two graphs on the bottom left
show that a majority
of interviewed households
were ashamed of using their toilets,
and thought they lowered
the value of their apartment.
Thirdly, the financial aspects
certainly also played a role.
The entire capital and maintenance costs
proved to be more than twice as high
as a conventional
water-flushed sanitation system,
and especially the maintenance cost
with mechanical emptying
of waste bins and urine
were seen as costly.
The ecological benefits
like the water savings
were not perceived as a great benefit
by the homeowners.
And finally, the institutional aspects
that led to some
of the abovementioned problems.
During the project implementation,
there was not a clearly
developed understanding
of the responsibilities and duties
between local government
and the main developer.
The diverse interests
of the three main stakeholders
were also a major issue.
The Stokholm Environmental Institute
was mainly interested
in promoting ecological sanitation
in a multi-story building.
The Dongxeng District government
was interested in having
a solution for water shortages
and also promoting an image
as a modern city.
And lastly, the Doxing Estate
development company
was of course,
interested in making a profit.
In hindsight, the incorporation
of a single management entity
would probably have led
to less building mistakes
and less technical failures
when implementing something totally new.
In the end, three and a half years
after moving in,
and despite attempts at installing
a newer generation of dry toilet
called the Separette,
and improving and widening
the ventilation pipes
and replacing the fans,
the homeowners collectively decided
to replace the entire dry toilet system
and replace them with low flush,
water-based cistern toilets.
The only remaining part
of the project today
is the onsite treatment plant
which acts as a decentralized
wastewater treatment plant.
This module provided only a short insight
into some of the challenges of trying,
ultimately without success,
to introduce novel closed-loop
sanitation systems
in a multi-story context.
It does not mean that dry sanitation
systems cannot work per se,
but that mature and robust
technology solutions
need to be aligned with user
expectations and aspirations.
If you want to learn more
about this interesting project
and details about how
the whole story played out,
you can order this book
from Practical Action Publishers,
which we've included
in this week's list of further reading.
In our last and final case study
we will move to Indonesia
and present
one of the great success stories
of bringing urban sanitation to scale.
This module will be presented
by Isabel Blackett
from the Water and Sanitation
program in Jakarta.
Thanks, and see you next week.