So in part two we're gong to look
at a little bit more
about the content of the program
or what was actually done,
and in particular focusing
on our systematic sanitation cycle
that was developed for the cities.
Developed within the program
and has since been scaled up nationally.
Also about the importance and how
high-level national support was secured,
and the importance
and the role that played
in moving the program forward.
And a bit about budgets
and mainstreaming them
and how that has worked out since then.
Let's have a look at slide number three.
The sanitation city cycle.
This cycle was very fundamental
to developing a model
that could be scaled up,
so we started in the six cities
and then went to twelve,
and as we did the twelve,
we had to simplify it a great deal.
The vision became that this would be
rolled out nationally.
There were at the time
around 100 cities in the country.
Although the vision has been
that
the approach is applied
in a similar way in districts as well,
- there are around 300 of them altogether - ,
so we're looking at very large scaling up.
The cycle incorporated,
first of all, advocacy.
Now, the advocacy depended
on which stage the city was at.
Initially the program was looking
for cities which were willing
to throw their hat
in the ring and have a go,
and to become those first six cities.
Those cities then became
advocates for the next cycle
and gradually, the cities began
to advocate to the national level
and then the national level became
the main hub of the advocacy
to the cities that were
a little further behind.
So having the city
committed itself come onboard,
it was very much a voluntary,
demand-driven program.
No one had to do anything.
Cities volunteered, put their hands up
and became part of it.
They then established a working group
and some institutional structures
through which they would work.
The first activity
that the working group undertook
was to establish
what was called a white book,
and it was really a sanitation
situation assessment
and sanitation mapping.
It involved quite a bit of survey work
and bringing together existing data,
local knowledge
and some primary research,
looking at what the situation
was in the city.
And from that white book,
which was quite transformational
because the working groups
were working together for the first time,
they began to see things
that their departmental silos
had not seen before.
They developed a sanitation strategy.
And from that strategy
would become what was called
"a program memorandum" which is really
a project shopping list, or a plan,
and applications to put in
for particular projects
to national level or to donors.
So this was it,
the name "project memorandum",
was how it was coined.
Then, finally, there would be
a process of monitoring
and evaluation during implementation,
and that would be an ongoing cycle.
So, this cycle
was perceived at the city level
and what we tried out.
If we can move on to slide four now,
we find is that the center of this program,
as I mentioned in part one, was the city.
And the cities had an impact
at the national level.
At the national level we had the buy-in
of the planning department,
and to some extent,
the health department.
The other departments
that should have been involved,
the ministry of public works
and local government
were a little bit
more ambivalent about it.
So we went down to the cities
that were interested,
where there was commitment
and where there was very strong ownership,
they established their groups,
they did their assessments,
and then they started holding.
This idea came from one particular city:
a sanitation summit, in which
the project cities would get together
and they would, to some extent,
show off, share what they'd done,
and try and hold each other
accountable for what they were doing.
We call this friendly peer review,
and a bit of competition.
But this process evolved
over a couple of years.
The national government
was invited and the very first time,
they were called to come and join
one of these sanitation summits.
We managed to secure a director general
from the ministry of public works to come,
and I remember the look on his face
when he heard the man talking
about his sanitation budget
and his sanitation strategy.
He looked shocked, and he said,
"I never expected to hear this
coming from a city.
"I had no idea cities
were taking this so seriously.
"I need to go back now to Jakarta,
and I need to look at what
our national department is doing"
I can say this was in April 2009, I think.
Everything changed from then on.
He went back to Jakarta.
He talked to the minister,
and a national program began to formulate
quite soon after that.
But someone articulated this as,
"the cities produced the wake-up call
to the national government."
The national government responded.
They increased their attention,
they got a national program in place
called "the national acceleration
of sanitation development
in settlements program"
commonly called PPSP,
and they used that sanitation cycle
and what the cities had done
during this ISSTP program
as the basis for rolling out
a national program.
So moving on to slide five,
we call this one, the high-level support
for the unmentionable.
If you get your, in this case
it's the vice-president,
you get them talking about sanitation
at the national level,
this is something
that had been unthinkable
even two years earlier. And it had been very much triggered
by vocal articulate mayors
at the national level
showing that they had done something,
and if we can do it, why can't you?
The national government got on board
when there was something there
that they could copy,
they could scale up.
I think it's quite
an important lesson for this,
that if you want to motivate
at the national level,
they need to have
something to roll out.
The peer pressure
and competition among cities
had been very instrumental.
It increased the motivation,
mayors increasingly, the city
became embarrassed
to come to the summit
without their mayor,
so more mayors started attending.
Sanitation was seen
as a good public interest platform.
It became mentioned in elections,
one mayor actually said to us
"I was reelected through
my sanitation mandate."
Very satisfying to hear that.
The mayors have a lot of clout
at the national level.
The cities' strategies became
a very tangible outcome
for local government planning,
and it fitted into the government's cycle.
We had worked entirely
within the government
planning and budgeting cycle,
which had a lot of limitations,
quite a few frustrations,
but that was the way
to institutionalize what was happening.
I'll show you later
a picture of some products.
We used a lot of very high quality
media communications.
A very inspired local company
who had wonderful, wacky ideas
to appeal to people,
and there was a lot of video images,
a lot of posters, and visual images
that the media could pick up,
that people could catch on to.
By 2009, this became
quite a big national issue.
And the program, which was due
to finish in early 2010,
then helped the government to develop
their national acceleration
of sanitation program
and this is slide six, sort of a summary
of what they intended to do
from 2010 to 2014.
So they have almost come to the end
of this first five-year plan
and they are now developing
their second five-year plan.
What you'll see here
is that this is an integrated
wastewater, solid waste,
and drainage plan.
That was very much the demand
of the cities and what was required,
and it has very specific targets
for each of those subsectors.
I forgot to mention in part one
that actually the city focus
had all three of these areas
because this was what
the government wanted to do.
We went with what they wanted.
We ended up getting two sets of funding
to enable us to do that.
We'd initially gone in only on wastewater,
but when it became clear that wastewater
probably wouldn't fly on its own,
we managed to get co-funding to add
the solid waste and drainage sectors.
There was a great deal of government
support for an integrated approach.
If you look at the five year
acceleration program on slide seven,
you will see some very large numbers.
The government was very ambitious,
and again on the left hand side,
you see that cycle.
They want you to work
through that cycle systematically
in the number of cities
that they were working in,
so even to go from the twelve cities
to 41 cities in 2009
was already very ambitious.
The roles and responsibilities
for who would be implementing
these different parts of the cycle varied
depending on what needed to be done,
so you can see that
on the right hand side of the slide.
So if we look now at slide eight,
what actually has happened,
what is very clear, investment
has gone up enormously.
Slide nine will give you a graph
of what this looks like in practice,
but we've gone from a miniscule
national proportion of the national budget
to a third of one percent.
In a country the size of Indonesia,
a third of one percent
of the national budget
is a lot of money.
A 1000% increase from $50 million a year
to $540 million a year
over the seven years
in terms of the national budget.
This has included
not only national commitment,
but an even greater increase
in the spending
of local governments on sanitation
so it's very much a co-funded initiative
between central government
and local government.
The PPSP program which was to scale up
those figures you saw
in the previous slide
was not fully funded,
but it went a very long way
and given how ambitious
the targets were,
there's a big question
about whether the capacity
to spend all that money was there.
Slide nine, you just
briefly see that scale.
I would like to point out again
that the program finished in early 2010,
so if you can look at the escalation
in funding since the program finished,
you can see how much funds
were leveraged by that $10,000 investment
over five years.
Finally, I just want to focus
on a few lessons learned
along the way.
There are many, but here are a few.
First of all, to get
the national government
or to get the high level leaders,
whether it's the mayor of the city
or the vice president or the ministers
prioritizing sanitation,
is an essential step to going to scale.
It is not enough, but it is necessary,
but not sufficient.
Talking about money to decision makers
is more effective than talking
about infant mortality
or health or anything else, really.
We had done this economics
of sanitation work.
The first results
had come out in Indonesia
about 2008, so we could use those figures
as part of the advocacy campaign,
and there's no question that they were
the most effective element
of that campaign
and we built that in at that time.
Local government capacity
varied a great deal,
so although we had this sanitation cycle,
this city sanitation cycle,
the way it worked in different cities
varied a great deal.
Some cities could almost run
on their own quite early,
others needed a great deal
more technical support,
hand-holding and capacity building.
We had to find a balance
between technical facilitation
without compromising ownership.
Now, this is a really tricky one.
Do you get the consultants to go in
and do a very high quality
city sanitation strategy,
or do you let the city do it on its own,
and it's perhaps
a little bit lower quality.
Do you take over, and this is a balance
that all the time we had to work out,
and I think to some extent
that balance is going on.
The city needs support
from a technical assistance team
or from local consultants,
but how do they do it?
Keep the decision making
at the local government level,
don't let any project or program
take over that decision making.
And a real lesson learned,
we had worked with local government
and at national level,
and we'd kind of forgotten
about the provincial government,
and that was a role
that we began to see was very important
and towards the end of the program
we began to realize
that we needed to strengthen that program
and use the national government
more significantly
and at that stage, they began
to see what was happening
and they were interested,
began to work out quite well.
So this is a very brief overview.
There's a couple of publications available
that Sandec will let you know about
and you'll be able to read
a bit more about this.
Well, I've very much enjoyed
sharing this program.
It was five years of my life,
and I hope you found it inspiring.
And thank you for listening.