Welcome to the
Lusaka Sanitation Case Study.
Today, we will travel to Lusaka,
the capital of Zambia in Southern Africa,
where we will have a closer look
at a sanitation service
delivery model for urban areas.
We chose this case study
because it shows how service,
adapted to the local conditions,
can deliver sanitation services,
and to illustrate how many different
details other than the technical system
contribute to the success
of a service delivery model.
Please pay special attention
to the delegated management
used to deliver the service,
the financial revenue model,
and the sanitation technologies,
and give special focus
to the faecal sludge management.
Furthermore, we want you to understand
how a formerly illegal business
was formalized.
In this video, people often talk about
"peri-urban areas",
which in Zambia is used ambiguously
for the settlements outside
the city center.
This case study is presented to you
in partnership with
Water and Sanitation
for the Urban Poor (WSUP).
We would like to thank WSUP,
The Lusaka Water and Sewage Company,
The Kanyama Water Trust,
and the people of Kanyama
for allowing us to give this insight
into their work and daily life.
Lusaka is the capital city of Zambia,
and it has a population of
about 2.3 million people.
And out of that 2.3 million people,
you have about 60-70% of that population
living in the peri-urban areas of Lusaka.
And out of that 70% I've referred to,
we have about 90% of them
using on-site sanitation.
The high-income areas are well-planned.
And so, those that could be only on-site
sanitation using their septic tanks,
we easily acquire services of
their tank operators.
And their costs, of course,
they can be able to afford
the cost of having
such a level of service.
But if you go to a low-income area
where there's no planning,
the access to the properties
is quite a challenge.
It becomes difficult for the tanker
or service operators
to provide this level of service.
But also, the fact that you are talking
about the high cost of this service,
as the affordability capacity,
on the part of people
in the low-income areas,
it can't allow them to be able to
pay for such a high-level of service.
Kanyama settlement, or peri-urban,
is one of the most-populated,
in fact, it's the most-populated
settlement in Lusaka.
You are talking over a population
of not less than 250,000 people.
And if you look at
the challenges of sanitation
in Kanyama itself, it's huge.
The water pit is,
we dig a shallow, a shallow pit,
and it gets full quickly,
and in the past we would cover it up
and dig another one,
it would get full really quickly,
and that would be the trend.
Another problem that we face
is when the rainy season comes,
the pits easily fill up
and that are flowing,
and flows to the street,
and that increases the chances
of disease such as cholera.
Lusaka Water and Sewage Company
was formed in 1988.
One of the departments which is
of interest to everyone
is the peri-urban department.
It is the department which is
in charge of coordinating
water and sanitation service provision
in all the peri-urban areas in Lusaka.
The Kanyama Water Trust is a
community-based service provider,
which provides services
on behalf of the mandated organization,
which is Lusaka Water and Sewage Company.
We are actively involved in the services
of supplying water to the community.
Secondly, we are also
involved in sanitation.
The Faecal Sludge
Management Service,
of course, was an initiative of
Lusaka Water and Sewage,
in partnership with Water and Sanitation
for the Urban Poor
and the community,
who are represented by Water Trust.
One thing to note is that
we are still grappling with the challenge
of dealing with faecal sludge
in all these peri-urban areas.
We designed the business model
of the Faecal Sludge Management Service.
We looked at a number of factors.
And as much as this was a service
that we would provide,
we also wanted to look at it
from the business side.
So we looked to see how much revenue
we would generate
from the provision of this service.
And also we looked at the operation's
cost to be made,
'cause we wanted this to be sustainable
for it to generate its own funds,
and also be able to continue.
The way the Faecal
Sludge Management System
works is that the customer
would request for the service.
So, they will try to find out
how the service...
they can access the service.
So what happens is that once
a customer expresses interest,
The Water Trust sends the pit diggers
to go and make an assessment.
So once they assess,
then they advise the householder
of what level of service
they can pay for.
Because we have three
levels of service that are designed.
So we looked at for 12 barrels,
for the smallest toilets.
This would cost 250.
Then for 24 barrels,
the customer would be required
to pay 380.
And for 32 barrels,
the customer would be required
to pay 450 kwacha.
And this is how the entire structure is.
So, it's up to the customer to tell us
which amount they can afford,
and also looking at
the size of their toilets.
I came to know about the
pit emptying service
through door-to-door marketing services.
Since the first time we
registered for this service,
up until now,
we are the only people who are
using it to empty our pit.
This is a service where
pits are emptied,
and the sludge from the pits
is safely transported
to the treatment facilities,
where again it is treated
and safely disposed of
or resold as, either as bio-fertilizer
or gas that is used for energy purposes.
We started the first of its kind
in terms of service provisioners
of faecal sludge management.
We started this service
in February of 2013,
and from February 2013,
for the three years of operation,
900 pits were emptied,
benefiting close to 25,000 people
in the low-income area of Kanyama.
So you can see how this
model of service delivery
is responding to the sanitation needs
of people in the low-income
areas of Zambia,
and in particular, in Kanyama.
There's a big difference between
when I was emptying illegally
and now that I'm with the company.
Because when I was emptying illegally,
I never had tools to use,
and now with the company,
I'm able to empty using the right tools.
With our methods, it's far different.
It's professional.
There's care.
Because when we go there,
to empty toilets,
we open up,
we service it off,
and we are able to empty it
up to the bottom.
Thereafter, we make sure that actually
the site is disinfected,
as we leave the site.
So it's more professional,
it's really covering good hygiene
in our communities.
I was very happy with the service
because my pit was emptied
to a considerable amount,
and the service is worth the money
that we pay for it.
If I want a load of sludge
to be removed from anything,
I'll pay more.
And if I want less,
I will pay less.
We know that things, for instance,
that are making the model to be
not fully financially viable.
So, our priorities as of now, as WSUP,
is to see how this current model
can be improved so that it can become
more financially viable.
Because when it does so,
then we can be able to,
together with Lusaka Water,
be able to recommend it for a scale-up
to other low-income communities.
This has really made our lives easy,
because we had a really big problem
and now, with the pit empty,
we have the services which are available.
This module provided
some insight into the daily life
of sanitation service delivery
in peri-urban areas in Lusaka, Zambia.
There are a number of key takeaways
from this case study.
Firstly, delegated management can help
to bring adapted services,
even to unplanned peri-urban areas.
Secondly, an underlying business model
to assure financial sustainability
is key for any successful
sanitation system.
Revenue streams can come from customers,
taxes, or other forms of subsidies.
And service has to be adapted
to the local conditions to be successful.
Thirdly, the complete sanitation chain
has to be considered,
from improving the toilets
for easier emptying,
to transport, treatment,
and safe reuse and disposal.
There are many elements to this case study
that could not be portrayed
in full length due to time constraints.
If you would like to learn more,
we recommend that you go
to the WSUP homepage,
where you'll find many resources
about this project.
Thanks for your attention.