Results-based financing
to deliver urban sanitation services
Planning & Design
of Sanitation Systems and Technologies
Inga Afanasieva, World Bank –
Global Partnership for Output-Based Aid
Welcome. This module
introduces the role
that results-based financing
approaches can play
in meeting growing infrastructure
and service challenges
in the provision
of urban sanitation.
My name is Inga Afanasieva
and I am an Infrastructure Specialist
with the Global Partnership
for Output-Based Aid of the World Bank,
a partnership of donors working together
to support communities
to access basic services
using results-based financing
and output-based aid approaches.
In this module,
we will introduce the role
that results-based financing
and output-based aid
can have to improve
the delivery of urban
sanitation services
to the poor
and explain
how these innovative
financing approaches
can deliver
verified results.
Results-based financing (RBF)
is a term for a range
of financing mechanisms
that provide payments
after verified results
have been delivered.
It is becoming
increasingly important,
as delivering public services
and basic services
requires policymakers
to consider innovative
financing methods
to improve service
delivery and outcomes
and increase cost
recovery levels.
Results-based financing
has emerged as an important,
innovative tool for
financing basic services
because it switches
the emphasis from inputs
- funding given in advance
for expected results
(such as planning
and buying construction materials)
- to outputs, such as
electricity connections,
or new or improved latrines.
Payments from funders
or government
to service providers
happen only when the agreed results
have been achieved.
The service provider
takes the risk
that if the results
aren’t achieved,
they are not paid.
By moving the focus
from activities and plans,
to the monitoring of results,
governments and donors
can ensure money is spent
on the intended purpose.
They can also give service
providers the latitude
to focus on the activities and methods
that they think are best
to achieve the desired outcomes,
and can be used to leverage
private sector financing.
This approach thus enhances
the focus on learning
about what actually works,
and creates scope for
ownership and innovation.
Results-based financing
approaches can be applied
in various sectors and contexts
with a variety
of partners and purposes.
Different instruments
can be used to incentivize the demand
or the supply side
of the service.
On the demand-side,
instruments such as
conditional cash transfers offer rewards
for consuming a service
that can improve their health
or well-being and benefit society
as a whole.
For example,
families can receive
a cash transfer
as long as their
children attend school
or if they go to clinics regularly
for medical check-ups.
On the supply-side,
service providers
can be incentivized
to deliver the desired
services or results
by output-based aid,
where service providers are rewarded
for the improved performance
or for extending
quality services,
such as certified
sanitation facilities,
to target poor consumers.
Other results-based financing
instruments link disbursements
to the achievement of specific
government program results
or measurable progress
in a country.
Which type of approach,
or combination of approaches
to use in a given situation,
is highly dependent on context.
For the remainder of this module
we will focus on output-based
aid approaches,
which have been used
in every region of the world
and in numerous sectors.
For more information
about other types
of results-based financing,
please refer to the recommended
reading for this module.
Output-based aid is designed
to increase access
to basic services
for the poor.
It is used in situations
where poor people are excluded
from receiving basic services,
such as urban sanitation,
because they cannot afford
to pay the connection fee.
In the example
shown on the screen,
the cost of a connection
to a sewerage network
is $100.
However, the household can
only afford to pay $15.
A service provider
or third party financier,
like a commercial bank
may invest additional capital
into the connection
cost—in this example,
$25,
which can be recovered
though a user tariff
or a government subsidy.
That means that the gap
for the poor household
that prevents them from receiving
the service is $60.
The output-based aid subsidy
for the poor household
– which is paid only after
measurable results
have been verified
- fills the $60 gap
between the affordable level
that the households can pay
and the real cost
of extending the service
to these households.
By definition,
the output-based
aid subsidy is disbursed
after the connection is made,
so it is important
that the service provider
is able to pre-finance the cost
until the output-based
aid payment is received.
Results-based financing
and output-based
aid can be designed
to deliver innovative solutions
in different environments,
working with both public
and private operators.
They provide incentives
for innovation and efficiency
through competition
or benchmarking,
and by leaving the
technological solutions largely
to the service provider
who gets paid
the agreed amount
if the outputs meet
the quality standards.
In Nairobi, for example,
dense populations
in informal settlements
and water rationing posed a challenge
to the original project design
of household sewerage connections.
Under the output-based scheme,
the service provider
was given the flexibility
to implement multi-faceted
technical solution more appropriate
to the context.
This involved both
individual household water
connections for the flushing
of the toilets
and compound solutions,
with water storage tanks
for toilet flushing
which also included
an option to use greywater
from handwashing for flushing.
Another example
where output-based aid
is used is the greater
metropolitan Accra area in Ghana.
There are 4 million people
living in the area
and the population is expected
to reach 5 million by 2020.
Half of the households
reside in single rooms
of compound houses
and only 1 in 5 households say
that they used their
own household toilets.
Public funding in
the sanitation sector
cannot keep up
with the demand
and there is considerable room
for the private sector to play a role
in the provision of sanitation.
The poorest suffer the most
because of the high cost of
building their own facilities,
and the high cost
of borrowing to do so.
To address this challenge,
the Government of Ghana chose
output-based aid
with the following
project design:
Households finance 50%
of the cost of the facility
either though a microfinancing loan
or their own savings,
after that service providers
are contracted to build the toilets
to required standards.
Once the construction is complete,
the service provider receives
the remaining 50%
- the output-based aid subsidy
- in two installments:
2/3 upon verification
of the physical construction,
and 1/3 after 3 months
of successful use.
The project was designed
to target low-income communities
and to fund an awareness campaign
through the metropolitan assemblies
and the Environment
and Health Offices.
The project was
designed to develop
the full cycle
of sanitation services
by also subsidizing
the desludging of toilet facilities.
The purpose of the desludging subsidy
was to incentivize the service delivery
and to ensure that
households understand
how to properly dispose
of fecal matter.
The subsidy was designed
to cover half the cost
of the desludging service
and to be payable to the provider
upon verification
of successful service
delivery and proper
disposal of the fecal
sludge.
The total cost of the program
was $5million , which
was expected to incentivize
the construction of over
7,000 household facilities
and 200 desludging operations.
Results-based financing
plays an important role
in meeting the world’s
development challenges.
Output-based aid is a form
of results-based
financing that can provide
service providers the incentives
to extend inclusive
urban sanitation services
to poor and marginalized beneficiaries
that would otherwise
not be reached.
Output-based aid can
be effectively designed
into an urban sanitation
investment program
only after considering
multiple variables,
such as the need for the subsidy,
which needs to be assessed
on the basis of the demand,
the costs and the social benefits.