Hello, and welcome to the MOOC module
Shit Flow Diagrams:
A tool to illustrate and communicate
sanitation service delivery.
My name is Lars, I'm an environmental
engineer and I'm working
in the department of sanitation, water
and solid waste flow development.
Shit flow diagrams
are often referred to as SFDs,
and in 2015 a team of organizations
came together
to develop a consistent approach
for the production of SDFs,
and the description
of sanitation service delivery.
I hope you are excited to learn
about the SFD, excreta management,
and the overall link
to sanitation systems
and fecal sludge management.
At the end of this module, you'll be able
to describe what an SFD could be used for,
explain the different pathways
excreta can take in the environment,
and provide examples of safely managed
and unsafely managed excreta.
To start, let's answer the question
of what the SFD can be used for.
The SFD is an assessment
of sanitation service delivery,
which is helpful for understanding
the current situation.
The SFD is a communication tool,
which presents complex information
in a simple illustration.
And the SFD is an advocacy tool.
It can be used to demonstrate the need
for improved sanitation service delivery.
Now, let's discuss
what the SFD can convey.
The SFD conveys percentages of excreta
transported through sewers
or emptied from containment,
but it's not a detailed planning tool.
It also shows how much
is delivered to treatment,
but it's not a quantification tool
with accurate volumes.
Lastly, it shows percentages of excreta
treated or not treated,
but doesn't assess treatment performance.
Let me just briefly introduce you
to the research behind the SFD.
Discussions about SFDs are only possible
if results are based
on a consistent approach.
On this slide, you can see an example.
This SFD is based
on the methodology and tools
which are available on the website.
Green and red arrows illustrate
safely and unsafely managed excreta
along the sanitation service chain.
The SFD method provides guidance
to derive these percentages,
but also defines terminology.
During the following minutes,
I'll guide you through a city
to explain this terminology
in more detail.
Here you can see an example city.
Excreta is managed
with off-site and on-site sanitation.
The SFD starts out by separating
those two sanitation options.
This pictures shows
a typical wastewater treatment plant.
Ideally, wastewater
is delivered to treatment.
If not delivered, or not treated,
we refer to it
as "excreta unsafely managed,"
as shown here in red.
But if the wastewater is treated,
then we refer to it
as "excreta safely managed,"
as shown here in green.
Here you can see a pit latrine,
which is an on-site sanitation technology
used by the majority of the population
in low-income countries.
Fecal sludge accumulates
in these technologies,
and once the containment fills up,
the sludge needs to be removed.
In this example,
a manual emptying-service provider
collects fecal sludge in barrels,
which are then transferred
to a pickup truck.
On the SFD, this is described
as "fecal sludge emptied."
The terms "fecal sludge contained"
and "fecal sludge not contained"
will be explained in a later scene.
Ideally, fecal sludge
is then delivered to treatment,
the next step
of the sanitation service chain.
If delivered,
the arrow on the SFD is green.
In this example,
you can see a septic tank,
another common
on-site sanitation technology,
which is connected
to flush or pour-flush toilets.
If the groundwater
and soil conditions allow,
the effluent infiltrates
through a soak pit
into the ground for natural treatment.
Solids settle at the bottom of the tank,
and fecal sludge has to be removed
on a regular basis.
If not removed, tanks can overflow,
and this can result
in groundwater pollution.
Instead of using barrels, septic tanks
are usually emptied by vacuum trucks.
If delivered to treatment,
the arrow on the SFD is green.
Here you can see
a typical fecal sludge treatment plant.
Liquids and solids
are separated in settling tanks.
The solids are then transferred
to drying beds,
while the liquid part
is often treated in ponds.
If treatment is effective, fecal sludge
is described as "treated" on the SFD,
and therefore safely managed.
The next scenes will provide you
with more examples
of unsafely managed excreta,
which is a common situation
in many places.
Where sanitation facilities don't exist,
open defecation is practiced,
which directly contaminates
the environment,
and is considered unsafely managed.
The next examples show situations
where fecal sludge is emptied,
but then not delivered to treatment,
as described on the SFD.
Where sanitation facilities exist,
but vacuum trucks
cannot access the facility,
dumping of fecal sludge
directly into the environment is common.
Fecal sludge is directly flushed out
into nearby drains
by removing bricks from the containment,
or by installing pumps.
Informal emptying practices
also often lead
to dumping of fecal sludge
into the nearby environment.
On the SFD,
both scenarios are referred to
as "fecal sludge emptied,
but then not delivered to treatment,"
and therefore unsafely managed.
Let us now look in more detail
into the definition
of "fecal sludge contained"
and "not contained."
To do this, we need to look
at the water table and soil conditions.
The animation provides you
with an example
of a septic tank and a pit latrine
that infiltrate into the ground.
In this first scenario,
the water table is low,
and therefore the risk
of groundwater pollution.
The result is fecal sludge contained,
as you can see on the SFD as green.
Another scenario
is that the water table is high,
and in this case, infiltrate
from the septic tank and pit latrine
drains into the groundwater.
This situation causes a significant
risk of groundwater pollution.
The result is
"fecal sludge not contained,"
which you can see on the SFD as red.
In places where there's enough space,
a common practice
is to cover a full pit with soil,
and then build a new one.
If groundwater pollution is not an issue
because of good soil conditions,
and low water table, this practice
could be considered as safely managed.
While it can provide a solution
in rural settings,
this should not be promoted
in urban settings.
You have now learned about scenarios
where fecal sludge is not safely managed
due to a number of reasons.
But I hope you're not surprised
if I tell you
that even fecal sludge emptied
and collected by vacuum trucks
often is not delivered to treatment.
There are many possible reasons for this.
Firstly, treatment plants
for fecal sludge
may simply not yet exist.
Fecal sludge is dumped
into the environment,
and on the SFD considered
as "not delivered to treatment,"
and therefore unsafely managed.
Another common scenario
is that treatment may exist,
but is located far outside of the city.
In overcrowded cities
where traffic jams are the reality,
fecal sludge gets dumped
into the environment,
which again is referred to
as "unsafely managed" on the SFDs.
But even where treatment exists
and is reachable,
high fees for discharge
may discourage service providers
to actually deliver sludge to treatment.
The last situation shows trucks
that deliver fecal sludge
to a wastewater treatment plant.
This typically results
in failure of treatment processes.
The SFD illustrates this as "fecal sludge
or wastewater not treated,"
and therefore unsafely managed.
Let's zoom out of our city again.
You have now learned
about the SFD terminology,
and what unsafely
and safely managed excreta means.
I hope you enjoyed this animation.
So now, before we finish this module,
I would like to show you
one more example of a real SFD.
Here you can see the SFD
for Dar es Salaam in Tanzania.
On the left-hand side, you can see
that 9% of the population
uses off-site sanitation.
90% of the population
use on-site sanitation,
and 1% practices open defecation.
In total, we found that 43% of excreta
are safely managed,
and 57% are unsafely managed.
Of the 57% that is unsafely managed,
the majority results from fecal sludge
that is not contained and not emptied.
This is the scenario we have shown you
in the animation,
where the water table is high
and excreta infiltrates
into the groundwater.
Additionally, more than half
of the emptied fecal sludge
is actually not delivered to treatment,
and directly dumped
into the environment.
This contributes another 18%
to unsafely managed excreta.
Of the 43% safely managed excreta,
a major contribution is fecal sludge
contained and not emptied.
SFDs represent the current situation.
At the time this one was made,
many pit latrines
were built quite recently,
and simply not yet full.
Once these pit latrines
need to get emptied,
treatment infrastructure
needs to be available
so that emptying service providers
have an appropriate location
for discharge.
If not, the percentage
of unsafely managed excreta
would increase significantly.
The SFD promotion initiative
has developed a methodology,
tools, and templates
for worldwide production of SFDs,
using the terminology presented here.
To learn more about SFDs,
please visit the project website,
where all those materials
can be downloaded.
Is there an SFD for your city?
If not, maybe you can start producing one,
and use it to raise awareness
about the gaps
in sanitation service delivery.
Thanks for listening to me today.
We really hope you enjoyed this module.