Hello.
I'm Kate Medlicott,
technical officer
for sanitation and Wastewater
at the World Health Organization.
In this video I will give you an overview
of sanitation safety planning,
and we'll look at an example.
Sanitation safety planning,
or SSP for short,
is a risk-based management tool
for sanitation systems.
A safely managed sanitation system
prevents exposure
to disease-causing excreta,
at all steps of the sanitation chain
from containment through emptying,
transport, treatment,
and to disposal or reuse.
It can be used to get out
with excreta flow diagrams or SFDs,
shown in the previous module,
to make sure that excreta reaches
safe rather than unsafe endpoints.
SSP reduces health impacts
while increasing the benefits of reuse.
SSP can be used
for all kinds of sanitation systems,
both in formal and in informal settings.
The approach is best used
for improving existing systems.
In communities with no sanitation,
demand creation should be prioritized.
So, how do SSPs work?
First, we need to understand
the system we plan to manage.
This is referred to
as a system assessment phase,
where the sanitation chain and exposure
groups and pathways are identified
and expressed as hazards.
Risks are assessed,
and when they're unacceptable,
improvements are designed to reduce them.
This approach ensures action
is prioritized according to risk.
Monitoring and management
using multiple barriers along the chain
ensure that the whole system
is operating as intended.
SSP can be applied in many settings.
Today I'll be illustrating the approach
in an informal urban setting
typical of growing cities
in many countries.
We'll follow the chains showing
examples of exposure groups,
hazards, controls
and monitoring at each step
to build up a safely managed sanitation
system that protects public health.
Notice as we go that not all improvements
involve expensive capital investment.
Changes in management and behavior
can also significantly reduce risks.
Also notice that different stakeholders
bear responsibility for controls
and monitoring at each step.
Here is a simple pit latrine
with manual emptying.
Although excreta
are contained in the latrine,
this unimproved system poses
a number of health risks.
Exposure groups include the users,
the workers who empty the containers,
and the surrounding community.
Children and the elderly
are especially vulnerable
from contact with soiled surfaces
in an unhygienic latrine.
These groups may be exposed
by a direct excreta contact
through the feet and hands,
and when excreta is inadvertently
transferred to the mouth
via dirty hands or flies.
The risks here are medium to high,
depending on the exposure group.
While the goal is a more hygienic
improved sanitation technology,
we can still reduce risks.
For example, controls
such as wearing shoes,
better cleaning of the latrine,
personal protective equipment for workers,
and using an emptying system
that reduces direct contact
will all incrementally improve the system.
Visual monitoring of these measures
by a community health worker
is a simple way to check and respond
if these controls are not in place.
This latrine with septic tank
is an improved technology
that poses less risk to users
than the previous situation.
Let's look at the emptying process.
Motorized emptying and transport
is much safer than manual emptying,
but there are still risks
that need to be managed.
A key exposure group is the workers.
Hazardous events are mostly related
to blockages and malfunctions
of the equipment.
For example, the operators
may be sprayed with sludge
and also contaminate the surrounding area.
These risks are typically high.
Here are some controls to protect workers:
providing appropriate equipment, working
according to standard operating procedures
and ensuring workers wear
personal protective equipment.
The organization responsible
for overseeing collection and transport
can set minimum standards like these
and make spot checks
to monitor if they are followed.
In this example, all of the fecal sludge
is delivered to the treatment plant,
but in poorly managed systems,
some may be diverted to dumping sites.
This can have serious health
and environmental impacts.
SSP should also identify dumping
as a hazardous event
and include controls and monitoring
to manage these risks
posed to the wider community.
At the treatment step it is vital
that the treatment process operates well
so that effluent and bio-solids
meet agreed standards.
If not, users on farms
and consumers of the farm produce
will be exposed to an unacceptable risk.
The hazardous events may include
overloading of the plant, breakdowns,
the processing temperature and time,
and the presence of flies or mosquitoes,
or seasonal factors such as high rainfall
that may affect performance.
The risks and consequences
of these are high.
Example controls include
proper design and construction,
trained operators,
and a preventive maintenance program.
Monitoring may include periodic testing of effluent
and checks on delivery volumes.
But even the best treatment processes
will occasionally not meet standards.
In some cases, lower levels of treatment
may be unavoidable
with the existing technology,
or desired by farmers
who wish to access nutrients for reuse.
That's why barriers at the next reuse step
are particularly important.
During reuse, there are risks
to farmers using the bio-solids,
especially where intestinal
worm infections are prevalent.
Risks will depend on the performance
of the treatment plant
in the previous step,
and the way the bio-solids
are applied in the farm.
For example, manual
or mechanical application.
When produce is sold
to the general population for consumption,
many people are potentially at risk.
Pathogens can be recycled
back to the community at large
and lead to a disease outbreak.
This is costly in terms of public health.
It can also ruin the reputation
and operation of businesses
that reuse wastewater and sludge.
The type of crop grown
and the application method
affects the risk for consumers.
For example, crops eaten raw
have a much higher risk
compared with crops which are cooked
or processed before eating.
These risks are potentially high.
Controls that can be used include:
selection of crops not eaten raw,
setting a time between
the last application and harvesting
to allow pathogens to die off naturally,
and washing of produce
in clean water before sale.
Monitoring may include
checking crop types,
application and harvesting practice,
as well as hygiene
during the packing and sale.
We have just followed
the modules in the SSP manual.
First, describing the sanitation system,
identifying hazardous events
and exposure risks,
developing and implementing
improvement plans,
monitoring controls
and verifying performance.
Coordination amongst stakeholders
is needed to implement all controls
and monitoring in a safely managed system.
That's why establishing
a team at the outset
with members representing
each step of the chain
is vital to prepare for SSP.
Coordination can be challenging,
but evidence shows
that safely managed systems
lead to far higher health gains
than improved sanitation alone.
Further, using
the multiple barrier approach
reduces dependence on capital
intensive treatment technologies
as the main barrier.
Controls can be included at any step
and incrementally improved over time
as resources permit.
In summary, SSP is a risk-based tool
for safely managing
existing sanitation systems.
SSP coordinates improvements in monitoring
by actors along the sanitation chain.
SSP does not rely on treatment only.
It uses multiple barriers, including
behaviors, management and technology
to prevent exposure.
The SSP manual that includes
more guidance and tips
is available in several languages
on the WHO website
along with other resources
to help users get started
and implement SSP.