Hello, everybody.
My name is Petra Kohler,
I'm a social anthropologist
working at Sandec.
My focus is on the persons
using certain technologies.
This module's topic is
Sanitation from a Gender Perspective.
A gender approach will address the needs
of greater spectrum of users,
not just women,
and make interventions more acceptable
to the community as a whole.
I will introduce you
to the lines of thinking,
the arguments
for gender considerate sanitation
and shortly present
an ongoing research project on WASH
in hospitals in India and Uganda
with a strong gender focus.
Now please read the definition of gender.
But what does that mean?
It is about the different roles, tasks
and responsibilities of men and women
in a given context, in a given society.
Gender is something that we do,
but gender is something
that is also dumped to us.
What this means in practice
for sanitation planning
and implementation
will be addressed in the following slides.
Sanitation from a gender perspective
is pervaded by many interrelating aspects.
In this gender flower,
you can see the Seven Key Aspects,
like policy, rights and justice,
education, health and safety aspects,
culture, technology and economic aspects.
We will have a closer look
on some of them.
Some of the gender-related challenges
are illustrated in this picture.
Inequalities in access,
especially in public spaces.
Particular groups, such as women,
elderly, children and handicapped people
are more strongly affected
by the absence of adequate sanitation.
Health and safety aspects,
especially women and girls
can encounter various problems
in connection
with non-appropriate sanitation,
like violence, occuring as a result
of walking to a public toilet,
or infections
from waiting too long to urinate.
Girls' school performance
is influenced by sanitation.
Many girls do not attend school
because of lack of proper sanitation,
especially in secondary education
where menstrual hygiene becomes a matter.
School absenteeism and dropout of girls
lead to gaps in education
between girls and boys.
The most sophisticated technology
does not solve any problem
if it is not adopted by the users,
one of the lessons
sometimes painfully learned
in the past decades.
Focusing on biological aspects,
it is obvious that men and women
follow different practices,
encounter various challenges,
and have different needs and priorities
when it comes to sanitation.
As an example,
men urinate in a different way
than women.
Women spend around
six years menstruating in their lives.
On average, each woman
will dispose off 125 to 150 kilograms
of sanitary material in her lifetime.
In the developing world
many end up in waterways, open dumps
or are littering communities.
We all want to have toilets
which are clean,
safe and healthy to use,
accessible, comfortable
and assure for privacy.
In order to plan for appropriate
gender-friendly sanitation facilities,
or to improve conditions
of existing toilets
which are far away from acceptable
like shown in those pictures,
the following aspects
must also be understood.
Intimate needs, personal hygiene -
like are you a washer or a wiper -
the social construction of dignity,
like the perceptions of purity
and impureness.
Now, I will present you a case study
which takes into account
all the mentioned before
on gender and sanitation.
It is a interdisciplinary
two-year research project called WASH
in the context of maternal health
and menstrual hygiene,
how Indian and Ugandan health centrum
managed the sanitation needs
of special user groups.
It is combining social anthropology
and gender studies
with sanitary engineering.
It is researching the different users needs
of outpatients, inpatients,
attendants, staff members,
and wash infrastructure
in health care facilities,
particularly on how they deal
with the special needs of women
during menstruation,
child birth and the childbed.
The full range of dimensions
like health, safety issues,
accessibility, etc. was covered
applying different assessment tools.
First, an infrastructure assessment
was undertaken
which discovered the following
lacking topics.
A place to take a bath after giving birth;
washing and drying place
for usable menstrual hygiene products
and a disposal bin for used
for menstrual hygiene products.
Secondly, semi-structured interviews
where gender-specific question guides
were applied;
and a gender-sensitive
focus group discussion tool
which will be explained in more detail
in the next slide.
The Gender Action Learning System, GALS,
is a technique from the Participatory
Rural Appraisal repertoire.
GALS is basically
a focus group discussion tool
and has been adapted and tested
to the context of gender and sanitation.
The ideal group size of a GALS
is around 30 to 40 participants,
with 50% males and 50% females.
Reality sometimes shows a bit
a different picture,
like experienced in India.
Instead of the planned 20 women
and 20 men from different villages,
80 women appeared and only 15 men.
This means also that the facilitators
need to be very flexible
and act and adapt
on the existing situation.
GALS spaces upon sex separated
group discussions,
complemented by writing or drawing,
and sex mixed presentations,
and plenary discussions.
The two core elements from GALS are
the Gender Diamond.
The purpose of this first step
of the exercise,
is to identify the challenges faced
by the participants
in connection with their experiences
on a certain given topic,
like sanitation issues
in the presented case.
The second element is called
Action Trees.
The goal of this exercise
with the action trees
is to identify the causes
of the named problems
from the Gender Diamond,
and to find possible solutions
to address and solve them.
The process is similar to the one before.
Now, some explanations.
The roots of the trees
are the "causes" of the challenges,
stemming from the Gender Diamond.
The branches are the possible solutions
to address the problems identified before.
And potential personal commitments
to solving the problems,
those are the fruits.
GALS has a lot of strength.
It is a striking method when it comes
to the identification of topics
which are unusual, sensitive or taboo,
and it fosters the inclusions of positions
of women and men alike.
The overall data stemming
from the three assessment tools
provides evidence for interventions
that are not only gender considerate
but also neat spaced,
technically appropriate,
and socially acceptable.
After this excursion
into a concrete example
of a gender-sensitive plan
and executed project,
I would like to come to the summary
of this module.
You heard about the main
sanitation challenges,
learned by including a gender perspective
into sanitation planning
is of essential importance
and how it could be done
from an example in the field.
Maybe you want to include
a gender perspective
into your upcoming project?
Then ensure for following good practices.
First, integrate gender systematically
to your project from the very beginning
and try also to involve gender experts.
Collect sex-disaggregated data
of the beneficiary population
and send mixed teams to the fields.
Ensure for participation of men and women
in the needs analysis, planning
and in decision-making.
Thank you for watching and goodbye.