Decision Making Support
for Urban Sanitation
Planning & Design
of Sanitation Systems and Technologies
Peter Hawkins, World Bank – Water
and Sanitation Program
Sanitation is often low on
the agenda of mayors,
utilities and other
related urban managers.
By gathering credible information
and presenting it
in an easy-to-understand format,
it’s often possible
to demonstrate
to decision-makers the importance
of improving sanitation,
and to guide them
in defining priorities.
In this module,
we’ll look briefly
at some useful ways
of presenting information
and how they have been
successfully applied in practice.
The fecal waste flow diagram,
or SFD, is a way of visualizing
how well, or how badly,
the various sanitation service chains
in a city are working.
The width of the arrows
represents the population
contributing to each waste flow,
and is thus a proxy
for the potential hazard
to public health
and environmental quality.
The green arrows represent safe
excreta management,
whilst the dark arrows
represent unsafe flows.
This type of diagram
has proven very successful
in communicating sanitation problems
to decision-makers,
including those who don’t have
a technical background.
This one was used in the context
of a major multi-donor
funded project to improve
sanitation in Lusaka,
the capital city of Zambia.
The project is based on a recently
produced sanitation master plan,
focused mainly on sewerage.
The SFD was used as a tool
in the dialogue
between the utility and the donors
to define the content
of the project.
It clearly shows that two thirds
of the unmanaged fecal
waste originates from unsafe
manual pit emptying.
On the basis of the diagram
it was agreed
that the project should address
the upgrading of the latrines
which make up the great majority
of sanitation facilities
in the city,
to make them easier
to empty hygienically;
and the development
of effective and affordable
emptying services
to substitute widely-used,
unhygienic manual emptying.
Another example
of using the SFD
comes from Balikpapan in Indonesia.
This one was used
in a city-level sanitation planning
exercise led by the municipal
planning bureau.
It was projected
onto the wall in a meeting
with all the relevant
municipal departments
and used as a point of reference
to identify issues,
define actions and attribute
responsibilities
for resolving them.
The SFD shows that almost
half of the city’s toilets
do not contain fecal
material effectively,
and so it ends up
in the environment,
particularly in groundwater
and surface water.
Of the remaining amount
of fecal waste
that IS collected,
less than half arrives
at the treatment plant,
where treatment is
seriously inadequate.
On this basis,
the planning team
identified that the main priorities
were to upgrade
inadequate toilets,
to improve emptying services,
and to improve fecal
sludge treatment.
Aggregating the data
to city level
can hide important differences.
In this example from Lima, Peru,
the water and sanitation
utility, SEDAPAL,
has a political mandate
to service informal settlements
not served by the water
or sewerage networks.
The city-level SFD shows
the vast majority served by sewerage,
and the main problems
are a degraded network
and poorly functioning
sewage treatment,
which result in significant
environmental pollution.
However, if we look
only at the 8%
of the population who live
in informal settlements,
a completely different
picture emerges.
As Lima is a huge city,
this 8% comprises
about a million people,
nearly all from the poorest
strata of society.
In these areas we see the need
for a major improvement
in the quality of the latrines
and other on-site facilities
used by these populations,
and for the introduction
of emptying services
for these improved latrines.
SEDAPAL is now working out
how it will deal
with these issues,
which were previously left
entirely to the informal sector
and funded by the meager
incomes of slum dwellers.
This underlines
the importance
of making sure we understand
the specific problems
of the poor and other marginalized
urban residents.
Returning to Lusaka,
we can see how the collection
and analysis of data disaggregated
to neighborhood or ward
level can help in prioritizing
sanitation interventions.
This was done on the basis
of an Urban Sanitation Status Index.
In the case of Lusaka
it was calculated
that a survey
of 1,500 households,
stratified by neighborhood,
provides statistically
significant results
on a neighborhood
by neighborhood level.
The index rates
the performance of each step
in the sanitation service chain
in each neighborhood.
In addition it includes
complementary services
such as drainage
and solid waste management,
which are intimately linked
with sanitation outcomes.
These subsets are aggregated
using an algorithm
based on expert opinions
of the relative importance
of pairs of factors
or indicators,
to calculate an overall
sanitation status index
by neighborhood,
ranging from zero
for very poor sanitation,
to one for very
good sanitation.
In this case, an extra
layer of information
on groundwater vulnerability
was added, as about half
of the city’s water
is abstracted from aquifers
beneath the city.
The overall results clearly
illustrate the high priority
for improving sanitation
in the south-west
quadrant of the city,
where the sanitation
index is lowest
and the groundwater
vulnerability highest.
The index also indicates
slightly lower priority areas
for intervention in
the north-east of the city.
This Urban Sanitation Status Index
has been used in defining
and sequencing areas for sanitation
improvements under the project.
Economic factors are of course
critical in decision-making
on sanitation services.
This example is taken
from the municipality
of eThekwini in South Africa,
which is made up of Durban
and its surrounding area.
It has a rapidly
growing population
of about 3½ million people,
distributed fairly evenly
between high income
and low income urbanized areas,
and a large rural fringe.
The municipal utility
was obliged
to meet the challenge
of the constitutionally-defined
right to a free minimum
basic level of water
and sanitation services.
Sewerage is the most
cost-effective solution
in higher density areas,
and is provided where
there is formal land tenure,
and therefore
a stable urban layout.
This corresponds
to the “waterborne edge” in the map,
and covers the main
built-up area
and a few satellite settlements.
In dense, unplanned areas
with informal housing,
temporary facilities in the form
of communal toilet blocks,
maintained by the utility,
are provided until such time
as the areas are upgraded.
In low-income,
low density areas
without on-plot water supplies,
the utility provides
on-site facilities
which it empties every
five years free of charge.
Customers requiring
any extra emptying pay
for it at a commercial rate.
VIP latrines were initially
provided in these areas,
but due to high solid
waste inputs it
was found that manual emptying
was the only feasible method.
The utility has therefore
switched to using urine
diverting dry toilets,
which, although they are
more expensive to build,
produce almost pathogen-free compost,
which can be emptied
by the utility more cheaply
than the sludge from VIP latrines,
which has a higher volume
and always contains
fresh fecal material.
Political buy-in
from decision-makers
is critical for sanitation planning,
implementation and service provision,
and the preceding examples
show some of the ways
they can be influenced.
However, it is very
important to ensure
that there are proven
and scalable sanitation
intervention mechanisms in place,
to spend the funds
that are released
when sanitation is prioritized
by decision-makers.
If such mechanisms are lacking,
funds may be spent
on ineffective interventions,
results will be poor,
and it will become harder
to mobilize support
for improving sanitation.
This was an explicit consideration
in the sanitation sector
development program in Indonesia
led by mid-level officials
from the National Planning Bureau
and supported by WSP,
which we looked at earlier
in this course.
Initial work focused on
developing a data collection
and planning system
in selected cities
that was effectively aligned
with institutional mandates
and government budgeting
and planning procedures.
As a viable city-level planning
and implementation model emerged,
advocacy
with higher level
decision-makers was ramped up.
As a result, new funding
windows were created,
and the Public Works Ministry
realigned itself around
an inclusive city-level
sanitation agenda,
which the upstream work
had made feasible.
This has created
a virtuous cycle
whereby local and national government
investment in sanitation
has risen over a decade
from almost zero to the order
of billions of dollars.
To sum up then:
We need local data
and we have good tools available
to collect and present this;
we also need to look a bit
behind those tools
and to consider
the economic aspects;
and last but not least
we need to address
the needs of politicians
who make the decisions.