Welcome to the module on
Behavior Change in Urban Sanitation.
The focus of this MOOC
is on how to deliver
and sustain quality sanitation
services city-wide,
and to achieve that
it’s important to remember
that a vital link
in the value chain
is the customers.
They create the pull that
makes the value chain work;
if they don’t create this pull,
then the system doesn’t
work efficiently.
So how do we make sure
that demand is created
for the sanitation services
that we implement
or strengthen;
that the sanitation products
we develop
are purchased and used;
and that the sanitation hygiene
and behaviors we are promoting
are adopted and maintained?
In this module, we will
explore some principles
and steps to make
our demand creation
and behavior change
programs more effective.
Before starting
any behavior change program,
we need to be clear
on the behaviors
at the household or citizen level
that will affect
the outcomes of our program
and ultimately its success.
Here are some examples
of urban sanitation behaviors
which we might want to achieve:
Households connect to a sewer;
utility customers
pay their bills on time;
households empty
their septic tank
on a regular basis
using an accredited supplier;
citizens use public toilets
and stop using flying toilets,
or users upgrade existing
on-site sanitation facilities.
Once you’ve identified
the desired behavior,
the next step is to
understand the barriers
to and drivers of the behaviors
from a customer perspective.
We often assume that
the target population
is not aware of the service
or its benefits.
But more often than not,
there are other factors at play.
Here is a framework that's
commonly used to organize questions
related to the barriers
and drivers:
Does our target population
have the opportunity,
the ability and the motivation
to practice
the desired behavior?
Some typical questions
asked under this framework might be:
How easy or difficult is it
to access the service?
How affordable is the service
to the household?
Are there drivers,
such as increased social status,
that can create
the pull we want?
In its 2015 World
Development Report,
the World Bank proposes
a simple way
of understanding behaviors:
Humans think socially,
in other words,
what other people do,
or what we think
they are doing,
will influence our own behavior.
We think with mental models;
our beliefs about the services,
their providers,
and those who use them,
shape our behaviors.
We think automatically;
many of our behaviors
don’t involve conscious thinking
or planning at all.
The more we know
about the particular behavior
or biases involved,
the more effective our behavior
change programs will be.
So, how you diagnose
the situation?
At the minimum, a desk review
of previous studies
or a literature review
will help you better
understand the context.
If you have time
and resources available,
you can commission
a diagnostic study.
Depending on the objectives,
this can be a market
or consumer research study
including surveys,
focus group discussions
and other techniques.
For example,
a research technique
called “mystery clients”
can be used.
Mystery clients
are trained individuals
who visit service providers
in the assumed
role of clients,
and then report back
on their experience.
Some organizations use
an approach called
a “deep dive”
where researchers
and stakeholders
immerse themselves
in the community.
Once you have
identified the factors
preventing or facilitating
the desired behavior,
then the next step
is to develop
a program or intervention
that will address them.
There are many courses
on marketing
and behavior change communication
so this is really
just an introduction.
Here are some principles to remember:
Use the lens of
your target population
to analyze the situation.
This means for example,
not thinking in terms
of the technology ladder,
but thinking in terms
of the incremental benefits
to the customer.
Be holistic and use
multiple approaches.
When it comes to
behavior change,
there is no silver bullet;
there's not always
a single trigger
to achieve the desired
behavior change.
Get the expertise you need.
You wouldn't get
an advertising agency
to build a wastewater
treatment plant.
Conversely you do not
want an engineering firm
to design your behavior
change campaign.
The Behavioral Insights
Team in the U.K.
uses a framework
called EAST
which stands
for make it Easy, Attractive,
Social and Timely.
Easy: reduce
the "hassle factor"
of taking up a service;
prioritize and simplify messages;
harness the power of default options
whenever possible.
Attractive:
Use human-centered design
or other techniques
to ensure the service
and product features meet customer
needs, desires and aspirations.
Social:
If most people are already
paying their bills on time,
make that information known;
leverage the power
of social networks
and peer-pressure;
encourage people
to make public commitments.
Timely: Promote
products or services
when the cash
constraints are lower
and mental bandwidth greater;
foster new habits
during major life changes
like marriage or a new baby;
let households know when it’s time
to empty their septic tanks.
To illustrate the EAST
framework further,
let’s take the example
of wanting households
to use improved pit
emptying services.
You could make it:
Easy by enabling households
to order by mobile phone;
attractive by stressing
that there will be no digging up
of the backyard
to bury the sludge;
social by not discharging
sludge into open drains,
by appealing to neighborly
and civic pride,
and timely by promoting
the services prior
to the rainy season,
when pits can otherwise overflow.
Another framework
is the “4ps”
used in commercial
and social marketing.
The 4ps are Product, Price,
Place and Promotion.
The more you get the 4ps right,
the greater the likelihood of getting
the behavior change you
are interested in.
If you want households
with a septic tank
to connect to a sewer,
for example,
you can think through
the 4ps as follows:
Product:
Based on the research
insights,
what additional benefits
or advantages
are they getting
from connecting?
What do they value
most: Modernity?
Peace of mind?
Freedom from overflows?
Remember that most households
don’t care what happens
to their effluent
and may be satisfied
with their current system.
Consider bundling services or solutions
that can reduce the hassle
or can add value
while construction is going on.
Place:
Make sure the customer contact
points are easy to access,
efficient and service-oriented,
from order-taking, installation,
post-installation service,
and paying a monthly tariff.
Price:
Offer installment payments
to ease cash constraints
or enable payment
through mobile money.
Promotion: Tell
potential customers why,
where and how
to get the service,
but go beyond Information,
Education and Communication
or IEC as is it called.
Frame your messages based
on the diagnostic study.
Consider developing
a strong brand
through which you can
also connect emotionally.
If you’re targeting
the poorest customers,
face-to-face communication,
product demonstrations
and community-based
events are likely to be
more effective than mass media.
To summarize what we have
covered in this module
about behavior change
in urban sanitation:
Define what behavior
and whose behavior
are important to
the success of your program.
Understand what factors
are influencing these behaviors.
Design a comprehensive intervention
that will aim
to remove barriers
and activate drivers.
Remember two frameworks
that can be used:
EAST and the 4 Ps.
And finally, get the type
of expertise you need
for your program
to be most effective.