In this module
we continue examine ways
to ensure the sanitation infrastructure
investments are used
to deliver actual services
and are sustainable.
In it we look at tools
for assessing the strengths
and weaknesses
in the institutional,
regulatory,
budget and monitoring
sanitation service situation
at the city level.
This information
can be used to identify
and prioritize what exists
and can be improved,
and what needs to be
newly developed.
Political economy analysis can help
in this process
by explaining why the situation
is as it is,
what drives or impedes progress
and how to find
win-win solutions.
To deliver quality
sanitation services city-wide,
finance is used to provide
sanitation services for people.
Along the whole
sanitation service chain
this will include:
first of all, the development
of an enabling environment
at the city level,
and this is need to develop
the sanitation services,
and to sustain
the services over time
and throughout the city.
Each of these three pillars
has a number of building blocks,
and these include policy,
planning and budgets
for the enabling environment;
expenditure monitoring,
ensuring equity,
and monitoring outputs
for the developing services pillar;
and maintenance,
expansion of services
and ensuring actual user
outcomes are needed
for sustaining the services.
These pillars apply
across each part
of the sanitation service chain.
A policy, institutional
and regulatory situation
assessment can be undertaken
in many different ways.
One way is to use
a City Service
Delivery Assessment tool.
This is a participatory tool
that enables multiple stakeholders
to work together to identify
and build consensus
on where the major institutional
constraints are
for improved urban sanitation.
By answering together
a number of preset key questions
about each of the building blocks
and based on solid evidence,
a traffic light score can be assigned
across the whole sanitation chain
and for all aspects
of sanitation service delivery.
Such a graphic provides
a useful focal point
for multi stakeholder discussion
and consensus building
and it immediately
shows up strengths and weakness,
which can be used to develop
a priority intervention plan
that can then be implemented
alongside the development
of the sanitation
infrastructure itself.
But such an assessment
does not explain
why the current situation exists
or how to change it.
For that, we will look
in a moment,
to political economy analysis.
But before we do that,
here is an example
of a City Sanitation
Delivery Assessment
from Balikpapan in Indonesia,
which was conducted in 2014.
In the diagram we can see
that there was
no effective planning
of sanitation services
and consequently no budgets
were allocated.
And the reason for this was because
no institution had responsibility
for the entire
sanitation service chain,
although there was responsibility
for a sludge treatment works.
There were no government
sludge emptying services;
there was no regulation
of the private sector
and there was no output monitoring
of what existed.
Three private sector
vacuum truck operators
provided a reasonable
emptying service to the households
they could reach and those
who could afford to pay.
Given the density of housing
in the poorer areas,
and the consequent
difficulty of access,
often the tankers could not reach
the poorest households.
The private operators often dumped
the sludge indiscriminately or,
in one case,
dispose of it
on the operator’s private land,
much to the annoyance
of his neighbors.
Some of the results achieved
appear to be quite good,
but this was attributed
partly to the rather low demand
for sludge emptying services
and to the private sector’s ability
to meet most of the low demand.
However, around 25%
of the latrines
in the city
were found to overflow
directly into drains
and waterways,
and the sludge that
was collected by the trucks
was rarely taken
to the sludge treatment plant.
The postscript to this is
that since the Service
Delivery Assessment
was carried out in 2014,
the sanitation institutional roles
have been clarified
and regulations
have been developed;
the treatment plant
is now used by
all three private sector
emptying services;
and the local government
is piloting
a scheduled emptying service,
and the quality of the city’s
onsite sanitation services
are in the process
of being improved.
Political Economy
Analysis enable us
to look at the key interests
that may provide support to,
or be obstacles for,
certain choices and developments
in sustainable
sanitation service delivery.
Political Economy Analysis or PEA
can be used to enable
a city’s stakeholders
to identify the obstacles
and opportunities to providing
improved sanitation services
and to develop ways to overcome
the identified hurdles
and leverage opportunities.
Political Economy
Analysis first maps out
the institutions involved,
not only the formal sector,
which is government
or the larger private sector,
but also the informal institutions
such as manual pit
emptiers and artisans.
Following the mapping,
the Political Economy
Analysis looks at
how these institutions
and systems provide incentives.
Such as, influence, political power,
connections,
networks, money,
personal or family opportunities
to the different
stakeholders.
Which are the identified
individuals,
groups and organizations
involved in sanitation
service provision.
In turn, these incentives
exert influence
throughout the sanitation service chain
in both formal
and informal ways.
Formally though government
action and behavior.
And informally through contacts,
personal networks
and vested interests.
This Political Economy
Analysis structure
enables us
to answer questions
related to the existing
sanitation service chain in a city.
Questions such as:
Who decides?
Who benefits?
Can things change?
And by understanding
these questions,
stakeholders can begin to look
for commonalities
between interests,
and how the involved groups
and individuals could be mobilized
around these commonalities to improve
the sanitation services delivery.
Often you, and many
of the city stakeholders
will know how the formal
and informal systems
and institutions work,
or at least they will know
a good part of them.
By carrying out
a political economy
analysis around the agreed
priority issues,
those are the issues identified
previously in the city service
delivery assessment
or another approach,
the important tacit
knowledge of many
of these different
local stakeholders
can be captured and put
into a systematic form.
For example it can surface
and answer questions
such as who is
really responsible
for which aspects
of sanitation?
What is actually happening along
the sanitation service chain?
Are there gaps and are there
overlapping responsibilities?
All of this will help form
the basis of a dialogue
between the different stakeholders
to identify win-win
solutions and scenarios.
For example,
the need to negotiate
much clearer formal roles
and responsibilities,
or the identification
of a role for manual pit emptiers
once more hygienic
emptying services are put in place.
But this discussion
will only happen
if the Political Economy
Analysis is carefully researched
and articulated in a frank,
but appropriately sensitive, way.
Invariably Political Economy
Analysis reveals vested interests
and informal power structures
which can raise
very sensitive issues.
The term Prognosis for Change
may be a term that is useful
and is less controversial.
So, the Political Economy
Analysis or Prognosis for Change
should be an iterative process
which allows participants
to return to the issue
and discuss more options.
And when win-win solutions
are found these can be used for advocacy
with the key stakeholders.
So, to sum up:
Effective policy,
institutional,
budget and monitoring systems
are needed for improved
urban sanitation services.
An initial assessment
can be undertaken
in many different ways,
but participatory
tools can enable
multiple stakeholders
to work together
and build consensus
on priority actions.
Political Economy
Analysis helps us understand
why the situation
is the way it is,
and what interests are driving
and impeding progress,
and how to work with stakeholders
in order to identify
win-win outcomes.
Finally a key takeaway
from this module
is that all stakeholders
need to be part of
building consensus
about the policy,
institutional,
and regulatory arrangements
for poor inclusive city
wide sanitation services.
Including both formal
and informal aspects.
These will be the basis
of the accountability structure,
which is needed to ensure
sustainable sanitation services.