Welcome to the Module
on Integrated
Urban Water Management:
Sustainably Managing
the Urban Water Cycle.
My name is Lizmara Kirchner,
and I am a Senior Water
and Sanitation Specialist
with the World Bank Group,
based in Washington, DC.
In this module,
we will introduce
some systematic ways to understand
and analyze complex water issues
in urban areas
through integrated
urban water management,
a holistic approach to managing
the urban water cycle,
which brings diverse actors,
services and sectors together
around common goals
for sustainable outcomes.
Integrated Urban Water Management
is an integral component
of sustainable cities
and metropolitan areas.
In this module we
explore the challenges
in urban water management
and how Integrated
Urban Water Management
can contribute with
sustainable solutions.
We cover basic concepts,
key principles, common drivers,
and building blocks
that can be used to apply
an integrated urban water
management approach in a city.
The world is currently
facing an urban water crisis.
54% of the world’s population
resides in urban areas,
and by 2050 two thirds
of the population in the world
will be living in urban settings,
adding 2.5 billion people to cities,
90% of whom will be
in Asia and Africa.
Economic development
and rapid urbanization
dramatically increase the demand
for water
for municipal,
domestic, industrial,
agricultural,
energy, environment
& recreational uses.
Water pollution
is increasing
in developing country cities
due to rapid changes
in land-use patterns,
inadequate wastewater collection
and treatment,
poor solid waste
and storm water management
and aging infrastructure.
Climate change imposes
additional stress
on urban water sources
due to increased variability
and uncertainty of both
floods and droughts.
Traditional approaches
to urban water
investments are often fragmented
and frequently unsustainable
since they generally
do not take into consideration
the multiple dimensions
and cross cutting issues
of urban water management.
Integrated
Urban Water Management,
or IUWM, is a flexible,
participatory
and iterative process,
which integrates the elements
of the urban water cycle,
such as water supply, sanitation,
storm water management,
and solid waste management,
within the context
of a city’s land use,
urban development and river
basin management,
in order to maximize economic,
social and environmental benefits.
IUWM offers a holistic way
of undertaking strategic planning
by considering the management
of competing water uses
at the level of the watershed,
while recognizing the needs of the city
as well as those upstream
and downstream users.
IUWM takes into account
the needs of all users
within the basin
while working across vertical
and horizontal administrative boundaries
in order to overcome
the traditional fragmentation
of the Urban Water
Cycle as well as to allow
the consideration
and integration
of interdependent sectors
both urban and related sectors,
shown in green,
and the different
water subsectors,
shown in blue.
International experience shows
that the transition
to an integrated urban
water management approach
is an incremental process
triggered by one
or several drivers
that could be:
social, such as population growth
and rapid urbanization;
economic, for instance
when there is an urgent need
for livable space;
or environmental,
such as water
quality issues,
water scarcity
or extreme climate events.
Cities in developed countries
have transitioned through
these phases,
motivated by socio-political drivers.
Fast-growing cities
in developing economies
could ‘leap-frog’ some
or all of these earlier phases
so that they can become
water-sensitive cities more quickly,
thus avoiding the mistakes
that developed cities made while
following this path.
We will now present
practical guidance on building blocks
and potential activities
that may be considered
when engaging with a city
under an Integrated Urban Water
Management approach.
The activities listed
are to be taken
as general guidance,
as their application in each case
will vary depending
on local conditions and drivers,
as well as on
the city’s experience
in applying an integrated approach,
the level of interest
of its key stakeholders,
and their capacity.
Assessments
undertaken using
an integrated urban water
management framework
should include the evaluation
of urban and water
investments over a longer-term period
of 20 to 50 years.
In line with this long-term
strategic planning,
specific investment projects
and programs can be
designed and implemented
that may deal
with a smaller
number of complementary urban
and water interventions.
The main objectives
of the engagement
phase are to determine whether:
an Integrated Urban Water
Management Approach
is appropriate to deal
with the city's challenges
and development goals,
and to determine whether there
are appropriate drivers
and a suitable
enabling environment
for embarking upon an Integrated
Urban Water Management
planning process.
Activities to be undertaken
in this phase can include:
Conducting a data review
of the urban and water sectors
in the city
covering
the aspects listed
on the screen in order
to gain a better understanding
of the city profile
and of the water
and urban issues it faces;
identifying and mapping stakeholder
and analyzing the related institutional
and regulatory framework
as well as the political
economy in the city
and whether these are favorable
to an IUWM approach;
making the case for integrated
urban water management
with the identified
stakeholders,
and undertaking a rapid field
assessment of the urban
and water challenges
in the city
in order to refine the desk review
analysis with the stakeholders
to gain a better understanding
of the water challenges
the city faces
and the processes and systems
in place to deal with them.
Based on the data gathered
and the stakeholder consultation
carried out
during the previous phase,
the main objectives
of the diagnostic phase
are to determine
which challenges urban
and water sectors are facing,
or will face;
analyze the links between
water use in the watershed
and other sectors,
including those listed here
; consider existing
integrated practices
or lack thereof;
assess the resilience
of the urban water sector
to future demographic change,
water resource constraints
and climate change impacts.
It is important
to look not only at data
but also at the modus operandi
of the involved institutions.
Technical studies
should be carried out next
with the objective of:
Determining whether the proposed
IUWM measures make economic
and financial sense;
assessing the financial feasibility
of solutions identified
as suitable
during the diagnostic phase;
identifying the resulting structural
and non-structural IUWM
measures to be implemented,
where structural measures are
the infrastructure interventions
and non-structural
measures cover
the regulations,
legal frameworks,
tariffs, and education
and capacity building.
A number of technical studies
will be required to inform
the next phase
of strategic planning,
including those listed
on the screen.
The objectives of the strategic
planning phase are to:
Validate with stakeholders
the proposed IUWM framework
and options considered;
clarify institutional responsibilities
for implementing
the proposed solutions;
put mechanisms in place to manage
and share data across sectors
and institutions;
develop and apply
an appropriate monitoring
and evaluation framework
for the strategic plan.
Once stakeholders have
decided to move forward
with an IUWM approach,
a vision can be developed
for the long-term integration
of urban water management in the city
to include
the following elements:
Agreement on a set of proposed
outcomes for the city,
on institutional responsibilities
and cost sharing
arrangements;
milestones and a monitoring
framework for the tracking
of the implementation of activities
to reach the proposed outcomes;
mechanisms for review, feedback,
knowledge management
and course correction.
To summarize, in this module
we have seen
that integrated urban water management
is about improving
the way water resources
and related services
are managed across
the urban water cycle by:
promoting resource diversification,
system efficiency
and conservation,
while taking into consideration
all water users
in the city
and in the wider catchment
through broad
stakeholder participation.
IUWM offers a holistic approach
to strategic planning
and implementation which
considers the management
of competing water uses
and urban service provision
in the city,
in the context of the watershed,
while recognizing the water
needs of the city
as well as those of upstream
and downstream users.
An approach to integrated
urban water management encompasses:
initial engagement
and mapping of stakeholders;
the undertaking of diagnoses
to analyze the city’s urban
and water challenges;
strategic planning
to identify objectives and outcomes,
priorities and costs,
institutional responsibilities,
monitoring
and evaluation frameworks,
and feedback mechanisms.