Hello! Welcome to the module
on institutional
and financial options
for sanitation service delivery.
My name is Sophie Trémolet
and I am a Senior Economist
in the World
Bank Global Water Practice.
In this module, we will discuss
how sanitation services are provided
and how they can
be financed.
There is no “one-size”
fits all in this area.
Understanding who is in charge,
where they get funding from
and how they could mobilize
additional financing
is essential
to start
identifying solutions
for improving services.
The public sector
is usually responsible
for ensuring that sanitation
services are provided.
With this comes related
responsibilities
for making policy:
to define what services
need to be delivered,
and for regulation:
to ensure that those services
which need to be delivered,
do indeed get delivered,
and are delivered
at a fair price.
Policy functions entail
preparing policy documents,
norms and standards
and establishing service
delivery targets,
which reflect how much funding
is going to be allocated
to sanitation services overall,
and by the public sector
in particular.
For example,
policies need to state
where funding for sanitation
is going to come from
and what service levels
need to be provided.
Economic regulation
entails ensuring
that tariffs are set at a level
that allows service providers
to be financially viable,
whilst incentivizing them
to deliver better services
at a fair cost,
including to the poor.
Environmental and public
health regulation
is also needed to ensure
compliance with standards.
The public sector
may also be in charge
of providing the services themselves,
but this will vary
depending on the nature
of the urban sanitation services
along the sanitation value chain
and on whether the public sector
has the capacity
to deliver such services.
A common recommendation
is to keep policy
and regulatory
functions separate,
so as to maintain
“checks and balances”
in the system and avoid
conflicts of interest.
For example,
if a municipal utility
is providing sanitation services,
it would be preferable
for this utility
to be corporatized
and to operate under
a clear service
delivery contract
with the municipality,
so that it is not
the same department
that sets service
delivery objectives
that is also in charge of delivering
on these objectives
and/or in charge
of verifying
that these objectives
have been met.
Sanitation services
can be provided
either by public
or private service providers.
In developing countries
where sewerage coverage is limited,
which is the case in most
of Sub-Saharan Africa
and in much of Asia,
the private sector has stepped
in to provide services.
This private sector includes
small artisans building latrines
or small latrine
emptying operators,
who either provide manual services
or operate one or two emptying trucks.
Many of these private
service providers
operate in a regulatory
vacuum, however.
To maximize the efficiency
from private sector participation
and ensure that services
are delivered in line
with public policies,
structuring these markets
will call for more regulation.
This could entail
issuing them with licenses
for example
to ensure that
emptying trucks conform with standards
or do not apply
extortionate charges,
or entering into public-private
partnership contractual arrangements,
also referred to as PPPs.
The latter are
particularly applicable
when the private operator
is requested to manage
a public sector asset,
as this would be the case
for utilities managing
a sewerage network
or a wastewater treatment plant,
or even for a small operator
in charge of managing
public toilets, for example.
For such cases,
different PPP contracts
can be applied,
ranging from a service contract
which only entails minimum
delegation of responsibilities
to the private operator
to a concession contract,
where the private operator
is in charge of investing
in new assets,
as well as operating
and maintaining them
during a contractual
period of time,
before transferring them back
to the public sector.
Sanitation services,
as is the case
for water supply services,
generate a number of costs
that need to be recovered.
These include:
the costs of operating
and maintaining the services,
what we refer to
as O&M costs;
the costs of capital maintenance,
for large repairs
and for asset rehabilitation;
the costs of investing
in new assets;
the financial costs
associated with borrowing
for such investments,
and any taxes associated
with the provision
of such services.
To cover these costs,
funding for sanitation
can only ultimately come
from three main sources,
which are commonly referred
to as “the 3 Ts”.
These are: tariffs:
that’s a short-hand
for referring to funds
that are directly
generated by households.
This could take
the form of payments
to a service provider
for a service rendered,
for example a sewerage tariff,
or direct payments
by households themselves,
for example to build
an on-site sanitation facility
on their premises;
taxes is a short-hand
to refer to the funds
provided by tax-payers
via the government system.
These can include capital
investment subsidies,
the provision of free-land
to site, an asset,
or grants used
for demand-creation,
as we will discuss
in more detail later.
Transfers is a short-hand
to refer to voluntary contributions
and grants,
which may come
from foreign governments
in the form of Official
Development Assistance or ODA,
or local and international NGOs
and philanthropic foundations,
or even from migrant workers
via remittances.
These are three sources
of what we call
“funding for the sector”,
meaning the money that is allocated
to cover the costs
of service provision.
But sanitation sector
investments are very lumpy;
that means,
quite significant in size.
For example, when
a household builds a latrine,
the cost of this investment
can be equivalent
to their annual income,
or even double that.
Most utilities
in developing countries
would not generate
enough cash surplus
to pay for investments
in sewerage networks up-front.
As a result, borrowing
for sanitation, i.e.
mobilizing what we call
repayable finance,
is essential to
enable these lumpy
investments to take place.
Such repayable financing can come
from product suppliers,
microfinance institutions,
commercial banks
that lend at market rates,
or the so-called
development banks
that lend on
concessional terms, i.e.
conditions that are
more advantageous
than market conditions
for the borrowers.
How these sources of funding
and financing are combined to pay
for sanitation depends
on government policy
and on the ability
of regulatory institutions
to enforce those policies,
by setting fair tariffs,
for example.
Some investments generate
public good benefits:
this is commonly cited
as a reason
to use public funding
for sewerage networks
and wastewater treatment.
By contrast,
most countries consider
investments in on-site
sanitation systems
to be private investments,
which should be made by those
who directly benefit,
the households themselves.
Such commonly encountered policy
principles can lead
to misallocations, however.
In Dar es Salaam,
back in 2012,
it was found that 99%
of public sector financing
was used to pay
for sewerage systems
and associated wastewater
treatment which,
at the time, served only 10%
of the city’s population.
The remaining 90%
of the population,
including of course the poorest,
had to rely on
their own resources
to build latrines,
at a cost that vastly
exceeded the charge
for getting a sewerage connection.
However, sewerage connections
were only accessible
for richer people
living in areas
already covered
by the sewerage network.
The Sustainable
Development Goals aim
to achieve access to adequate
and equitable sanitation and hygiene
for all and end open defecation,
paying special attention
to the needs of women and girls
and those in vulnerable situations.
As network-based solutions
are expensive,
many cities will need
to deploy alternative
technical solutions
to sewerage,
such as on-site
sanitation systems
with provisions
for the adequate management
of the entire sanitation chain,
as discussed in more detail
in other modules
of this course.
Given these challenges,
public funds, taxes and transfers,
will need to be used
in a smarter
and more catalytic
manner going forward.
There are lots of reasons
why using public funds
to support sanitation adoption
can be fully justified.
The overarching reason
is that there are
significant public benefits
in universal
sanitation coverage.
If a household builds
and uses a latrine,
it won’t stand to benefit
fully from its investment
unless everybody else around
that household also uses one.
So how can public funds
be used better
for urban sanitation?
They can be used:
to create demand for the service
by investing
in demand-creation activities
and behavior
change campaigns;
to provide partial subsidies
towards the costs of investment,
such as for household investments
in on-site sanitation,
to support the connection
of poor households
to existing sewers,
and/or for investments
in the downstream systems
that are needed to collect
and treat the faecal sludge
or the wastewater.
To be more efficient
and better targeted,
these subsidies would
ideally be provided
based on verified
actual results.
Public funds can also be
used to facilitate access
to finance for households,
small businesses
or even utilities
that need to borrow
in order to invest
but are unable to do
so for a variety of reasons.
For example,
grants can be provided
to help educate lenders and borrowers
on what it means
to borrow for sanitation.
Concessional financing can be blended
with commercial financing,
to extend tenures
(the length of time
one borrows for),
or to provide credit enhancement
in the form of guarantees.
If one wants to improve
how financing for sanitation
is allocated,
it is essential to start
by understanding
how much is spent
on sanitation services,
and by whom.
This is not straightforward, however,
as funding and financing
for sanitation
are channeled in many
different ways to the sector.
In most cases,
there is not
a single budget line
dedicated to sanitation.
Building a graphical
representation of the sector
such as this example
can help with visualizing
not only who is
in charge of what,
but also how funding flows
between these different actors.
This can then provide a basis
for estimating the volumes
of funding that are currently
going into sanitation
and identifying ways to mobilize
funding for the sector.
In this module,
we have talked about
how sanitation services are organized
and how they
can be financed.
Key take-away messages
are as follows:
One size does not fit all;
there are many different ways
to organize the delivery
of sanitation services.
A key principle
would be to maintain
a separation
between policy,
regulation and service
provision functions,
so as to ensure
checks and balances.
Sanitation services
can be provided
by public or private
service providers.
Bringing in the private sector requires
clear regulatory arrangements,
via licenses or contracts
for service provision.
Sanitation services
can be funded
from a variety of sources.
However, public funds
need to be spent
in a smarter
and more catalytic manner,
to ensure that
the Sustainable
Development Goal
of universal access
to sanitation becomes a reality.