Working within the project cycle
Planning & Design of Sanitation Systems
and Technologies
Sanyu Lutalo, Isabel Blackett
and Peter Hawkins, World Bank
– Water and Sanitation Program
In this module we will look
at how some of the ideas
outlined earlier
can be applied in the context
of an urban sanitation project
or a broader urban
development project.
It must be stated at the outset
that no two projects follow
the same trajectory,
and there may be other
independently managed activities
and documents
that can be brought into
the project process,
as well as the project
team’s accumulated knowledge
and that of their
country counterparts.
This also means
that not all the tools
will be needed in any given situation.
They should be seen
simply as resources
that may be useful
to decision-makers
and to those who prepare
and implement projects.
This slide shows the steps
in a typical project cycle,
starting with identification
and the development
of a project concept,
through planning
and design,
to implementation and,
finally, evaluation.
The lessons learned
from the evaluation
should then feed into the design
of a subsequent project.
Some of the details addressed
in these different phases
are shown on the slide.
Here is the table
of how the tools
discussed in previous
modules might be applied
in a generic project.
As you can see,
the various tools can be
used at different stages
of the project cycle.
In the case of a project
prepared in Lusaka,
for example,
the starting point
was the preparation
of a Sanitation
Master Plan for the city.
Such plans, however, often focus
on infrastructure development,
and normally propose the expansion
of sewerage at great
cost to the city.
Even though areas
that are earmarked
for on-site sanitation
may be identified
under a master plan,
little consideration
is usually given
to prioritizing
between them,
to identifying how on-site systems
will be designed
and constructed, etc.
Moreover, the issues
involved in creating
a fecal sludge
management service chain
are also usually not addressed.
At an early stage
in project development,
a fecal waste flow diagram,
or SFD, was prepared for Lusaka,
which highlighted that
the biggest sanitation issue
in the city is, in fact,
fecal sludge management or FSM.
This is very important information
to present to decision-makers
and service providers
in a city,
as they may be reluctant
to engage with FSM
if it is a service that they have
not formally provided before,
or if there are concerns about
how to implement FSM solutions,
how to cover its costs, etc.
There may also be prejudice
against pit latrines,
which are sometimes
seen as a dirty,
polluting or inappropriate
sanitation solution.
Latrines are often poorly
constructed in rapidly
urbanizing neighborhoods,
but the extent to which
they pollute the groundwater,
as compared to septic tanks
and sewers which exert
a much higher hydraulic
load of polluted water,
should be analyzed
in the city in question.
Groundwater
pollution from sanitation systems
can be an important
consideration in a city:
by way of example,
Lusaka draws almost
half of its water supply
from karstic aquifers
beneath the city,
and so a groundwater
vulnerability map
was prepared in order
to understand this issue better.
The preceding information
can then be combined
with the findings
of the Urban Sanitation
Status Index which,
in the case of Lusaka,
was based on a geographically
stratified survey
of about 1,500 households
across the city,
in order to prioritize
project interventions.
For Lusaka, the combined information
clearly shows that the largest
concentration of poor sanitation
is in unplanned
peri-urban settlements
which sit almost entirely over
the area of maximum
groundwater vulnerability.
This information provided a clear basis
for prioritizing non-networked
sanitation interventions.
The City Service
Delivery Assessment
and the Prognosis
for Change tools
can then be used to draw
out the key institutional constraints
and to develop
a politically feasible roadmap
for providing sustainable
sanitation service provision
under the project.
A City Service
Delivery Assessment
was prepared
in Balikpapan, Indonesia,
for example,
and highlighted a need
for better management
of the downstream end
of the FSM service chain,
and a more systematic approach
to the full service
delivery chain
by the local authority.
Although the service outcomes
were rated as quite good,
this was mainly due to services
provided autonomously by
the private sector.
As a result of this information,
the city moved to develop
sludge treatment capacity
and to oblige service
providers to use it,
as well as to
improve containment
and emptying in poor
unplanned neighborhoods.
In the Indonesian city case,
these were issues
which the SFD had identified
and the Service Delivery
Assessment further highlighted
as not being addressed
by the authorities.
The project design stage
takes the project components identified
and outlined in the initial
conceptual description
and translates them into plans
for infrastructure
and for developing
the enabling environment
and the institutions
which will provide and oversee
the sanitation services.
At this stage,
it is also useful
to identify early interventions
that can achieve
short term results,
as a means to further
consolidate support
from the key stakeholders
and to thus gain
further traction
for the project.
Insights into the political economy
and the potential for change
can be very useful to inform
which early interventions
should be prioritized.
The Service Delivery
Action Framework builds
on the results of the Service
Delivery Assessment
and the political
economy analysis.
It is designed to indicate
the next steps
in building up sustainable service
delivery arrangements,
starting from the
current situation.
These steps can then be translated
into technical assistance
and other supplementary
inputs to be provided
under the project.
In the cities of Maputo
and Beira in Mozambique,
for example,
technical assistance
was provided
for a revision
of the sanitation bylaws in order
to recognize and allow
for the regulation
of FSM services
provided by both the public
and private sectors;
in Balikpapan,
the authorities built
on the Service
Delivery Action Framework
to move towards
scheduled emptying.
The Intervention
Options Assessment process
is an engineering process
of comparing solutions,
and cannot be substituted
by the use of tools.
However, by adopting
a systematic approach
that takes into account
the whole sanitation service chain,
technology choices can be matched
to the specific challenges
previously identified,
drawing on technical expertise
and up-to-date
reference material,
and validated with
the responsible authorities,
service providers and users.
A key external resource
for this design stage
is the material produced
by EAWAG/SANDEC,
which clearly lays out in one place
much of the technical
knowledge around sanitation
and fecal sludge
management technologies.
As a result of having undertaken
such preparatory design work,
project interventions
are identified.
In the case of Lusaka,
these include interventions
to upgrade latrines
to make them easier to empty as shown
in the pictures on the right;
to develop small-scale
service providers
to empty latrines
in unplanned areas,
and to install transfer
and treatment facilities
to deal with the fecal
sludge collected.
The tools I have described
in this module
are focused on diagnostics
and project preparation and design,
and are not intended
to add substantially
to the implementation stage
of the project cycle.
However, impact monitoring
and the learning
of lessons at project
closure bring
the cycle full circle,
and the basic diagnostic tools ,SFD,
USSI and CSDA,
can then be re-run
to assess progress made
under the project,
how sustainable it is,
and what lessons
can be taken forward
for the design of subsequent projects.
In summary,
the material we covered
in this module looked
at the following aspects
of the project cycle
in its different stages:
Identifying problems
and risks,
identifying and prioritizing
interventions,
identifying management
and institutional issues,
designing institutional improvements,
designing the physical interventions,
monitoring outcomes,
and evaluating the lessons
learned to feed
into future project designs.