The first lesson about
operational amplifiers
consists in describing
the circuit itself.
Then, we'll talk about
the negative reaction
followed much later on by
what is called the positive reaction.
We will start with
a short introduction
and we'll go over
all of the symbols,
look at voltage and
the flow of electric current,
and how to power
an operational amplifier (op-amp).
And straight after this, we'll go on
to examine this type of amplifier
in a range of circuitries.
These circuitries will exemplify
what we call
a frequency-independent amplifier,
which means that
once this op-amp
has been connected
to an electronic circuit,
the input and output are
independent from frequency variations.
This is an example of  linear function.
This will bring us to consider
the topic of filters.
Inside the filters,
we've got an op-amp
which will be connected
and which would allow us
to vary the amplifier gain
in line with frequency variations.
Here's an example
of an op-amp
or rather what we find
inside the amp.
You can see there are
a lot of transistors.
All of these transistors will
perform a different function
to allow this op-amp
to display the characteristics
which we'll examine
as we go through this chapter.
So, as you can see,
this is a very complex process.
These transistors, which
inside here are of MOS type
display quite a few functionalities
This type of circuit
would be integrated to a chip
or to a silicon base .
In the end, we do not show
anything about what's inside.
We'll have to limit our observation to
the input of this op-amp which is here,
a second input, to be found is there,
two supply voltages which
bring power to the circuit,
and an output.
So, in the end, there will be
five tracks to the circuit
and this circuit will be later
represented by a triangle
with two inputs, one output
in addition to two voltage supplies.
What we will mainly look at
is this symbol.
Once all of the transistors
are marked in this triangle,
this triangle comes to
represent the op-amp
which  has one positive imput,
one negative input,
and an ouput.
In addition to one positive
and one negative voltage supply,
and this is very, very important.
These two voltage supplies are going to
bring power to the electrical circuit
with a positive current
going one way,
and a negative current
going the other,
and all of this will work
in relation to a reference point
between input and output,
called the ground.
Here we have:
a positive voltage supply,
a negative voltage supply,
and a common point between the input
and the output which we call the ground,
and this type of  diagram outlines
everything included in the integrated circuit
what is required to power it up
and to give it a reference point.
However, once we've begun
to use this op-amp
we'll stop drawing
the +Vcc and the -Vcc signs.
What remains is the mass potential
which is essential.
Today, we're simply going
to look at this slide,
and as soon as we've moved on
to the circuits based on the op-amp,
you'll see that the +Vcc and the -Vcc
will disappear.
The perfect op-amp has certain characteristics
which allow it to
on one hand, amplify to a gain A = ∞;
and on the other hand, there is
an input resistance which is also infinite.
This means that when you look at the current
that will be absorbed by the op-amp,
it will be summarised as a I=0 current.
We've said that
there are two inputs.
In either of these inputs,
no current feeds
into the amp.
Therefore, this amp merely receives
two voltage supplies, V(+) and V(-),
and both these voltage supplies
will be infinitely multiplied
and sent back
towards the output.
Now, when we look at the output,
the output resistance of this
op-amp is equal to zero.
This means that the resistance
which should have been there,
in series with this source of controlled
voltage supply that you see at the output,
this resistance
that should be here,
just does not exist.
So, we've got absolutely
no series resistance
with a controlled voltage source
that picks up a difference in the voltage
V(+) - V(-) which is called ΔV
and which will be multiplied by a A= V gain.
These three characteristics
show a typical op-amp with:
an infinite gain,
an infinite input resistance,
and an output resistance
that equals zero,
This will the type of op-amp
that we'll be using
throughout this introduction
before starting to look at
what we refer to as
the imperfections the op-amp,
when we will see that there are
certain characteristics
which aren't as ideal as
those we see on an ideal op-amp.
Let's look a bit closer at
how this amp works.
Unluckily, or rather luckily,
the voltage output is saturated
The voltage ouput V(out)
can't in anyway
exceed the positive voltage supply
and the negative voltage supply.
This means that V(out) is limited by
what we call Vsat(+) and Vsat(-)
which are nothing more
than voltage saturation values,
which in the first case,
have been equalised
by the voltage supply.
It goes without saying that
we find op-amps on the market
that have a positive and
negative voltage saturation
that are not at the same levels
as the voltage supply.
Here is the characteristic which
connects the input voltage V(+) - V(-)
to the voltage output V(out).
We can distinguish two zones.
One positive saturation zone,
and a negative one,
we call it saturation, we've just had
a look at it just now,
and a very interesting feature
of this op-amp
which will constitute the topic of
how to use this op-amp in linear circuits,
which is referred to
as the linear amplification zone.
If you look now at how
an op-amp reacts to a signal.
We just said that there are
two voltage saturations,
Vsat(+) and Vsat(-),
and here, it's about non-linearity
because we can't go
any further than that.
We lose the linearity.
and, between these two voltage saturations,
we have a straight line.
And this straight line here,
we call it the linear zone,
and it's this linear zone
that creates the amplification function
of this op-amp.
Let's see how
all this interacts  into a circuit.
Let’s just summarise
what we've just said.
We've just said that
the voltage an op-amp
cannot go over
the two voltage supplies,
that we represent by +Vcc et -Vcc.
We've also said that
the linear zone is a zone where
the voltage output is linked
to the difference
between V(+) - V(-)
that we call ΔV and which is
multiplied by a gain.
We've also said that
the gain is infinite.
We've said that this part here,
is the part that interests us the  most
when we want to create linear circuits.
It is inside this linear zone
that the op-amp should create,
within a given circuit,
a connection between V(out)
and a input voltage V(in)
which we're going to  look at next.
If we don't have this linear zone,
the op-amp is basically non-linear,
il will be torn between two voltage levels
that will cause it to block.
So, these are power supply tracks.
So within the linear zone that we've just seen,
we can formulate it
like this in English:
if the op-amp output is
neither Vsat(+) nor Vsat(-)
and the output voltage
is strictly below Vsat(+)
and strictly more than Vsat(-),
then yes, we can say that our op-amp
is fixed in this relation here,
it is in the linear zone.
And here we can draw
an interesting conclusion,
that when the op-amp,
which has infinite gain,
because this A here is equal to infinity,
when this gain is equal to infinity,
independently from the output voltage
knowing that the voltage can't ever
go over Vsat(+) et Vsat(-),
Of course, the difference
in voltage is zero.
So, if this difference equals zero,
the potential in this node here is equal
to the potential in that node there.
And it's this characteristic
that will allow us to
achieve a wide variety of
functions in electronics,
and we're going to use the op-amp
in a purely linear function,
and a direct relation y = x will
connect V(out) to V(in).
We're going to see
how this will be confirmed
within the context of a
negative feedback circuit,
caused by a negative reaction.
Let's see
if I can use my op-amp
within the positive or
negative saturation zones,
therefore in a non-linear function.
For any input value V(+) - V(-),
independent of this value,
we have a unique output value,
which can be either
here  or there,
independent of this value,
we have a unique output value,
which can be either
here  or there,
it's a detector signal from the op-amp
that is called the comparator.
So, if V(+) - V(-) is positive,
in other words, if V(+) > V(-),
or, if V(+) < V(-),
we'll find ourselves
with a saturated output,
either a positive saturation,
or a negative saturation,
which will lead us to use the op-amp
in a non-linear function.
Here's an example that
demonstrates this characteristic.
Take a completely variable signal,
that varies over time,
and watch how the op-amp
reacts at the ouput
to detect whether
the signal is positive,
so all of this part here
will allow us to
source a voltage at the output
that is always equal to Vsat(+).
And all of this part here
will lead us to find a voltage
that is always negative.
So with a binary voltage,
if it's Vsat(+), we can say that
the voltage is positive,
and if it's Vsat(-), we can say that
the voltage is negative.
So, with this, we have a
detection signal at the input
which will tell us if V+ > V-
or if V+ < V-.
Of course, there are
many ways of applying this.
We can see here that we're analysing
the op-amp in open-loop
with the op-amp applications,
or when we use the op-amp
in positive reaction.
And this brings us on to look at
some of these applications:
There's a technique called
Pulse-width modulation,
that uses an op-amp open-loop.
Here's the diagram
of an op-amp loop
where we are interested
in the voltage output.
When we compare the
continuous input voltage, U(0),
that is connected to the
negative charge in purple,
and on the positive charge, voltage U(1)
I'm going to connect a triangular voltage.
We're going to look at
what happens at the output,
and here, in blue, we've got
the output voltage V(out).
What I would ask you to do,
is to go and connect this in a laboratory
I've prepared this for you, so just here,
you will notice,
or carry out an experiment, just to see what happens.
I've prepared this for you, so just here,
you will notice,
or carry out an experiment, just to see what happens.
What I would ask you to do, is to go and connect
this in a laboratory
that when we compare a continuous
voltage with a triangular voltage
What I would ask you to do, is to go and connect
this in a laboratory
that when we compare a continuous
voltage with a triangular voltage
and look at the pulse-width at
the output of an op-amp
which will become
increasingly wide or narrow
depending on the
comparison value
to apply a well-known
modulation technique
that's called the PWM, or
"Pulse-width modulation".
And so, we have here
now in purple, the DC voltage,
which is compared to the
triangular voltage, that is in yellow,
and you'll notice that
at the output we find
the voltage in blue,
that corresponds to V(out).
So, we can clearly see
that if the triangular voltage is
greater than the DC,
the output is Vsat(+) ou à Vsat(-).
We are moving the input voltage,
and we see the pulse-width
V(out) reacting
exactly in comparison
to the triangular voltage
and the DC voltage
that is at the input.
Therefore, the pulse-width
becomes increasingly narrow,
And, when we lower the DC voltage,
you'll notice straight away
that the pulse-width
modulates in comparison,
and this can be easily observed
on the screen of an oscilloscope.