In a previous episode, we saw that to
program consists of describing a
task for the computer to execute.
This task being decomposed on
one hand in
a number of data, that is, physical
quantities of the real
world which we want to represent in
the program; and
a number of
computations, that is, operations and
manipulations
of these data.
We have already seen how to manipulate
the data with operators.
But in order to truly have a program,
the data should
be able to influence on the computations
to be done.
This is what we are going to study
in this episode.
It's what are called "control structures".
Indeed, until now, the programs
we executed
were simply sequences of
instructions
one behind the other.
Theses computations weren't conditioned
by the values of the variables.
Control structures precisely allow
to
choose, for example, if we want
a certain
sequence of instructions or another,
depending for example on the value
of a variable.
That is what we call a "conditional branch"
(or "conditional statement").
There exists in fact three control
structures : the conditional branches,
which allow to choose between the execution
of a piece of code or the execution
of another piece of code, depending on
certain conditions on the data.
There exists the iterations, which
are simply loops on
a set of code snippets to be repeated
a number
of times; and finally the conditional
loops, which also
repeat instructions a number of times,
but depending on
a condition which is evaluated every
time.
In this episode, we are going to
have a look at
the conditional branches, which allow
to
skip certain parts or to choose
certain parts if various conditions
are fulfilled.
Now let's have a better look at
all this.
Let's suppose, for example, that we want
to do this or
that, depending on the value
of an integer
that was entered on a keyboard, here
by using the "scanner".
We are going to use what we call a
conditional branch, which
I will detail in a moment, but for example
if the value
is less than five, we are going to do
a certain thing, and
if the value is greater than five, we
are going to do another thing.
That's the idea of a conditional branch,
in which we choose, depending on
the fact that n is greater than or less
than five,
this or that piece of code to execute.
The lines in question are these
three lines here, which are organized
according to the general following syntax.
We begin with the keyword "if". Then in
parentheses we here have a condition.
Then we
have here in curly braces a block
of instructions
which will be executed when the
condition is true.
We'll then have, optionally, another
keyword,
"else", which will itself monitor another
block of instructions, which will be
executed if the condition we tested at
the beginning is false.
Here we see that depending on
the condition, we are  going to execute
either a block of instructions,
or another.
This is what we call a "conditional branch"
depending on the condition.
The general structure of a conditional
statement is
the following: we begin with the
keyword "if".
Then, we put a condition in parentheses.
We'll return later in the next episode on what
the conditions are and how to
write them.
We then have a block of instructions
which executes when the condition is true.
Then, we optionally have the reserved
word "else", followed by
another block of instructions, which will
be executed when the condition is false.
Let's have a look, on a concrete step-by-step
example, how this works.
Let's suppose we have the following
code,
with the conditional statement situated
here.
But first, we begin by asking
the user a question, to input
an integer.
So let's suppose for example that
the user inputs the integer 3.
A this point, we'll get to this
conditional statement and
ask ourselves:
is 3 less than 5?
3 is indeed less than 5, so the
condition
here is true and therefore the block
of instructions which will be
executed, is the block that immediately
follows the condition, which
means that in the program, in this case,
in which the user has entered
3, is going to print the message : "votre nombre
est plus petit que cinq." (= "your number is less than 5")
Then, the program will continue after
the conditional
statement here; it will continue
the normal progress and print
here: "fin du programme."
(= "end of program")
Now what happens in the case where
the user enters a number
greater than 5?
For example, if he enters the value 7,
we'll get to the condition
in the conditional statement, and
evaluate the
condition, is 7 less than 5?
The condition is of course false,
which means that
the branch will be made here on the
block monitored
by the keyword "else", which is the
block used when the condition
is false.
We'll therefore print here : "votre nombre
est plus grand ou égal à cinq".
We'll then continue the execution
after the conditional statement block,
so here we'll once again end by
printing "fin du programme".
The curly braces
are used to control a set of
instructions, whether
it's the block of instructions executed
when the
condition is true, or whether it's
the
block of instructions executed when the
condition is false.
These curly braces are used to regroup
the instructions that we
want to put together to execute in this
or that condition.
We can of course add as much
instructions as we want in
a block of instructions.
Let's suppose for example that we want
to print a message which
indicates the value of the number, when
the number is less than 5.
So, what we are going to do, is,
in the block conditioned by the
condition
"n less than 5", add here a line
which will let us print an additional
message.
By the way, when a block
contains a single instruction, it
isn't
strictly necessary to use the curly
braces.
However, I recommend you to always
use a
block structure, that is, to always
use curly braces.
This makes the code not only
more readable,
but also more maintainable; it
facilitates
adding instructions later on: if we
want to
add an instruction here, we can do it
without any other hassle, as the block
is already there.
However, you could encounter here and
there, in
external code, this kind of syntax without
curly braces.
This is why it is useful to know it,
even if I don't encourage you to
use it.
I rather recommend you to
systematically use the
block syntax, that is, with curly
braces.
Furthermore, you must know that the
else-block is totally optional.
We can absolutely write a block
of conditional statement, here,
without any "else".
Simply, what happens is that when the
condition is false, nothing
in particular happens, and
we continue to execute the program
normally.
In such a case, something in particular
will be executed
only when the condition is true.
Let's have a look at an example.
Let me come back to the previous example
with the value input.
Let's assume that the user has entered
the value 3.
We arrive here at the conditional
statement.
We test the condition:
is 3 less than 5?
This condition is, of course, true,
which means
that we execute the block
here monitored by the conditional
branch, and therefore
we print here the message : "votre
nombre
est plus petit que cinq."
(= "Your number is less than five")
And then, we continue the execution
of the program
as usual and we print the ending
message here.
What if the user had entered
a value
that is strictly greater than or
equal to 5,
for example 7. It is greater than
or equal to 5,
so the condition is false this time.
In this case, nothing special
happens.
We ignore the conditional statement
block and
continue the execution after the
conditional statement block,
which means that in this case, we only execute
the ending line, the ending message.
In Java, conditional statements
follow the following
general structure: we start by the
reserved word "if";
then in parentheses, here, we write
the condition
which we want to evaluate.
Then we put here a block of instructions
which will be executed
if the condition is evaluated to true.
Then
we could put here an
optional else-block with a block
of instructions which will be executed if
the condition is evaluated to false.
These blocks of instructions
can contain any part of a Java
program,
and can, in particular, also contain other
if instructions.
In this case, there are what are called
nested choices.
Let's have a look at an example.
Let's suppose that we have three variables
x, y, and
z, of which we want to test the
equality. For example, is
x equal to y, is y equal to z, or are
they the three equal to each other?
What we
can do here, is to begin by a block
of instructions which will test if x is
equal to y.
This block extends right to here, with its
associated else and the else-block,
and in the block, for example, monitored
by
the first test, when the first test
is true,
we see here likewise a second if, which
is perfectly possible,
with its own block for
true conditions and its block for
false conditions.
In the same way, in the first else,
we see here
again an if with its block for true
conditions and its
block for false conditions; and we see
that in the
last block of conditions, we can even have
a last if.
You know understand why you should not
abuse of this kind of construction.
It quickly becomes a little difficult to
understand, difficult to read.
Above three levels,
I think that it becomes
difficult to understand, if not even totally
unreadable.
Now let's have a detailed step by step
look at the example.
Let's suppose we have here three
variables, x, y,
and z which each contain the value 1.
We begin with the first if statement,
here, which will test : "is...
...x equal to y?". We effectively have, here,
a 1 that is equal to a 1.
The condition
is true, which means that we arrive
at this second if statement, here,
which will evaluate whether the value of y
is equal to the value of z.
We therefore ask ourselves again:
"is 1...
equal to 1?", which is indeed true,
which
means that we enter the block here
and
we print the message : "les trois valeurs
sont égales." (= *the three values are equal")
Then, we continue the execution at the
end of the block considered.
Here, there isn't anything in
particular to do.
Then, we also continue the execution
after this block here.
That is, we arrive here at the end
of the program.
Now, let's look at what happens when
we have, for example, the values y and
z which each have the value 2, and
which are different from x.
The program begins, like before,
by evaluating: "is the value of x...
...equal to the value of y?",
And in this case, of course, the answer
is no and therefore the
condition here is false, so we execute
the corresponding else-block.
We therefore enter here the
else-block at
the bottom of the program, which means
that we enter
here in the test of this second
condition: "is...
...the value of x (1) equal to the
value...
of z (2)?".
Of course, this condition is false and
therefore this "if" will branch to
its else-block, and we will find
ourselves evaluating this third
condition: "does y have a value equal
to z?".
2 is equal to 2: here, we have
of course a
condition that is true, which means
that this condition, this if
block, this conditional branch will
execute the
block here conditioned
by the fact
that the condition is true, and will
therefore
print: "seules les deux dernières valeurs
sont égales" (= "only the last two values are equal").
We will then continue the execution
from there, we
will continue after this block here, that we
are executing.
There isn't anything special.
We then continue the execution after
this conditional branch.
There isn't
anything special.
We then continue the execution after
this branch
and we arrive at the end of this
example.