In a previous episode, we
introduced the conditional branch
instruction if, and
we saw that in order to work,
such an instruction needs to express
conditions.
The condition examples which we
saw until now were relatively simple,
they
consisted for example in comparing
the
value of a variable with another
value.
We are now going to examine
the notion of condition in a
more detailed way and see that, in Java,
it is possible
to express relatively complex
conditions.
So, you here have an example of
a conditional
branching instruction, like we have already
seen
previously, and we see that in order to
write this conditional statement,
we need to express a condition, as we
can see here.
Here the condition is a simple condition, which
consists in comparing
the value of a variable n with a constant,
the constant 5.
Small syntactic note :
the conditions in a conditional
statement are, in Java, always
enclosed
in parentheses, which we concretely
see here, in this small example.
Let's begin by examining in a more
exhaustive
way how we can, in Java, express simple
conditions,
The objective of simple conditions is
to compare two expressions,
and for this effect we will use
comparison operators.
We have already had the opportunity
to come upon them several
times in examples, like less than
or greater than.
Java, in fact, offers a whole
collection of predefined
comparison operators, for example
the less than operator lets us
compare if the value of an entity is
less than the value of another entity.
Let's suppose for example that I have two
variables x and y, and that I want to
know if the value of x is less than
the value of y, I would use the comparison
operator less than
to perform this test, to express this
condition.
In a similar way, I can use the operator ==
to verify if two entities have the
same value.
For example, if I have once again two
variables x
and y, if I want to test if the value of
x is the same as the value of y,
I would use == and would
express my condition this way.
In a similar way, we also have the
operators greater than or equal to, less
than or equal to, and different than.
What you must know is that the
evaluation of such an expression
returns a boolean result, that is, the
value "true"
for true, and the value "false"
for false. A small
warning : the comparison operator
to test if
two values are equal is defined by two
equal symbols.
Do not confuse it with the
unique = symbol, which represents
assignment.
Here in this example, I test if the value
of n is 5.
This isn't what I'm doing when I write
n
= 5; n = 5 means that I assign
the value
5 to the variable n.
It should be noted that this kind of
way of writing isn't tolerated
by the compiler, in
Java, therefore here you'll have
a compilation
failure, if you write this kind of
instruction.
Now let's illustrate, with small concrete
examples, the use of simple conditions
in Java.
Here we have the case of a small
program which
begins by declaring two variables a and
b, by
assigning to them initial values,
respectively 1 and 2.
We now want to compare the values
of a
and b, to check if they're equal,
and for this effect we have used
a simple
condition which uses the comparison
operator ==.
Here, the values of a and b are
different, which
will has as a consequence that
the evaluation of this expression
will return "false".
We will therefore branch on the else
part of the conditional statement, and
execute this
instruction, which will have as a
consequence to print the
message "Cas 2", as we see here.
Then let's continue the step by
step execution,
and we now want to compare
the value of two times a with the value
of b.
It should be noted that with simple
conditions, we can compare not only
the value of two variables, as it is
the case
here, but also the values of two expressions,
in a more general sense.
If I evaluate two times a, I obviously
get the value
2, the value 2 which is of course equal
to
the value of b, so the evaluation of
this
expression will return "true", this
instruction,
the following instruction, will
therefore
be executed, and "b est égal au
double de a" will be printed. Note here
that we are dealing with an expression
that is relatively simple, when the
expressions get more
complex, to formulate conditions, it
is recommended to use parentheses
on the terms
of the expressions to make them
more readable.
Here for example, we could have begun
to do it
by adding a pair of parentheses
around this term.
In another situation,
we now want to compare the values
of a and
b to know if a is different from b.
As it is the case, the evaluation
of this
expression will return "true", we
will therefore
branch on the positive part of the if,
the true part, and print "Cas 2".
If we continue in sequence, we now
want to compare the value
of two times a with the value of b,
to test if two
times a is different from b.
It isn't the case, so the evaluation of
this expression will return "false",
therefore we will
branch the execution after the if
instruction, as there isn't
any else block, so nothing gets
printed.
We have just seen how it is
possible to express
simple conditions in Java by using
comparison operators.
In practice,
it is often necessary to formulate
more complex
conditions, and therefore to combine
simple conditions.
This is done with the help of
logical operators.
For example, the AND logical operator,
which in Java is defined
by the double symbol &&, lets us
verify if two conditions are
simultaneously verified. We note that
the logical operator
requires two operands. The
evaluation
of the expression with the AND
will return
"true" if and only if the evaluation
of each operand also returns
"true".
Note that if suffices that one
of the two operands returns "false",
for example this one,
and a fortiori the two, of course,
for the entire expression to also
return "false".
Second concrete example on the
use of the logical operand AND.
Here we have the case of
a small program, which asks the user
to input
a number, and we want this number
to be between 1 and 10.
The number is read from the standard
input, and stored in a variable n.
We want to verify that the number
that the user
inputs is indeed in line with our
expectations,
that is, that the number is between
1 and
10, we will consequently express a
condition by
imposing to the user that the entered
number is greater than
or equal to 1, and less than or equal
to 10.
As each of these conditions
must be verified, we will use the
AND logical operator.
Let's suppose initially that the user
inputs a zero.
In this case,
the evaluation of the first operand
will return "false".
We have seen previously that it suffices that
one of the operands is "false"
for the entire expression with the AND
logical operator to be "false",
we will therefore branch on the
else block of the conditional
statement and
print "incorrect", to show the
user
that the entered number doesn't
fullfill
the requirement.
Now let's suppose that the user
inputs the value
5, in this case the evaluation of this
first
operand will return "true", as 5 is indeed
greater than or equal to 1, the
evaluation
of this second operand will also return
"true",
as 5 is indeed less than or
equal to 10, consequently, as the two
operands return "true", the entire
expression will also
return "true", and in this case we
branch on
the positive block, the true block
of the conditional statement, and
print the message "correct", to
tell the user that the
entered number fulfills our
requirements indeed.
Other usual logical operator, the OR,
which is defined in Java
by a double vertical bar.
In the same way as the AND
logical operator,
the OR operator awaits two operands,
which are
two logical expressions returning "true"
or "false".
For the entire expression to return "true",
one or
the other operand must return "true",
a fortiori the two.
We see that in this case, if we want the
logical expression
to return "false", the two operands
must return "false".
In all the other cases, the expression
will return "true".
Now, here's a small concrete illustration of
the use of the OR logical operator,
let's suppose here that we have a small
program which
asks the user to enter two values, and
we want
one or the other of these values, at least,
to be positive.
The two values are read on the standard
input and
are stored in two variables n and m.
We want one or the other of the
entered values
to be greater than zero, we shall
therefore express a condition,
it is sufficient that either m is greater than
or equal
to zero, or n is greater than or equal
to zero.
As it is sufficient that one or the other
of these conditions
is verified, we will naturally use
the OR logical operator.
Let's suppose that the user
inputs the values -1 and 1,
the evaluation
of this first operand will return "true",
as
the value 1 is indeed greater than or equal
to zero, and we have ween that it is
sufficient that one or the other of the
operands is
"true" for the entire expression to
also be "true",
therefore, we branch here on
the positive block of the if
instruction, and tell
the user with a message, that indeed,
at least one of the entered values
is positive.
Now let's suppose that the user has
entered the values -1
and -1, that is, two negative
values, in this case the evaluation
of this operand will obviously return
"false", the evaluation of this second
operand also returns "false", and in this
case, we're in the
situation when the evaluation of the
global expression
returns "false", as the two operands
are "false".
In this particular case, we will
therefore
branch on the else block of the
conditional statement,
and tell the user with a message
that none of the two entered values
are positive.
Last usual logical operator, the
logical NOT, the negation,
which in Java is defined by an
exclamation mark.
Unlike the two other operators we have
just seen, the NOT operator,
the negation, is a unary operator,
that is, it awaits only one operand.
It's purpose is to return the negation of
the value of this operand.
For example, let's suppose that the evaluation
of this operand returns "false", which
concretely means that a would be greater
than or equal to b, the negation
of the value "false" will be "true".
Now let's suppose that the evaluation of
this operand returns on the contrary
"true", in this case, the negation of "true"
will be "false".
We'll have the opportunity
to examine many examples
of the use of the negation operator
in the
next lessons.