Now let's have a look at a few mistakes
often made by
beginner programmers when it comes to
writing conditional branches.
The first trap that awaits you is that the
equality test is written with two
equal symbols, like here, and not a unique
equal symbol, which is used for assignment.
This code
is therefore incorrect, as there's only
one
equal symbol, the correct version is
of course : if (a
== 1), and this code which is incorrect
is simply not allowed by the Java compiler.
Here's a second mistake example,
do you see the problem ?
In fact, there shouldn't be any
semicolon here and if we execute this
code, it will
be accepted by the compiler and the
message "a vaut 1" will
get printed whatever the value of a is,
so it's a little
mysterious, but to understand why
you must know that the
semicolon is considered as an
instruction,
an instruction that does nothing.
I could have written this code in
this way, which is easier to
interpret,
because the semicolon, this
emtpy
instruction, is considered inside the
conditional branch, but this instruction
is
considered outside the conditional
branch.
If a has the value 1, we enter the
conditional branch, execute the empty
instruction, that is, do
nothing, and whatever the value of
a is, skip to this instruction and
print the
message "a vaut 11".
Note that if we had used
curly braces when there's only
one instruction
in the conditional branch, the mistake
that we have just
seen would have had less chance of
happening.
It is therefore a good practice to
systematically use curly braces, even
when there's only one instruction in
the block.
A third mistake is, precisely,
forgetting the curly braces when they are
necessary, like in this code.
Having these lines indented,
that is, having
them shifted a but to the right,
isn't sufficient for them to be
inside the conditional branch, unlike
other languages.
In your opinion, what happens when I
try to compile this code ?
Well, the compiler will print this
error message which tells me
that there's an else without the
key-word if. So why ?
Because in fact, I could have written
this code this way,
the first instruction, which is the
print instruction is indeed inside
the conditional branch, but this second
instruction isn't, it is
after the conditional branch and when the
compiler comes upon this else, it is
already outside the conditional branch
which is
here and this else is therefore not
attached to an if instruction.
That's why it generates this
error message.
Now let's take three quizzes.
First of all, what does this code print
when it is
executed and when the user inputs the
value 1 for the variable
n and 2 for the variable p.
So in your opinion, what's the
correct answer ?
The correct answer is the answer C and
we are going to see why.
If you think you've understood, you can
go directly to the next quiz.
Let me remind you that in order for a
condition which uses the AND logical
operator, written like this, to be true, the
two conditions must be true.
In order for a condition which uses
the OR logical operator, written like
this, to be true, it is sufficient for one
of the two conditions to be true.
The user inputs the values 1 for the
variable n and 2 for the variable p.
This condition "n strictly less than p" is
true,
as n is equal to 1 and p is equal
to 2 and that 1 is strictly less than 2.
This expression has the value two
times n, that is,
two times 1, which is two, p has
the value
2, therefore this entire condition is true,
as 2 is indeed greater than or equal to 2.
This condition is therefore true, so we
enter the conditional
branch and execute this instruction
which
simply prints 1, 1.
We then move on to this
conditional branch.
This condition is still true, it's the
same
as the one we had previously, as it's
an OR here, I don't have to
consider the value of this condition,
because I
already know that this entire condition
is true.
We therefore print 2 here.
We then move on to this conditional
branch.
This condition, which is the same as
above, is still true, so
we enter this conditional branch
and test this new condition.
This expression
has the value two times n, that is, 2.
p has the value 2, so this condition is
true, as 2 is greater than or equal to 2,
we execute this part of
the conditional branch, so we print 3,
skip this
part, we arrive at the end of the
conditional
branch here, we move on and simply
print a
newline,
Second exercise, same code, but this
time the user inputs the values
1 for the variable n and 3 for the variable
p.
So, in your opinion, what is the
correct answer ?
The correct answer is the answer B,
let's see why.
This time n has the value 1,
p has the value 3, this condition is true
as 1 is strictly less than 3.
This expression has the value 2 times 1,
that is 2, p has the value 3, so this
condition is false, as 2 isn't greater than
or equal to 3.
As it's an AND here, this condition
is false and we go directly
to the next instruction which is also a
conditional branch. This condition
is the same as before,
it is still true. As it's an OR here, I
know that
this entire condition is true. We
therefore enter the conditional
branch, print a 2, and move on to
this conditional branch.
This condition is the same as before,
it is
always true, so we enter the
conditional branch.
This condition is false, like before, it's
the same as this one.
We execute the second part of the
conditional branch,
that is, be print 4, move on to this
instruction which
simply prints a newline. This time,
the values
entered by the user are 2 for n and 1 for p.
In your opinion, what is the correct answer ?
The correct answer
is the answer A. For this last
exercise, n has the value 2 and p
has the
value 1. This time, this condition
is therefore
false, as 2 isn't strictly less than 1.
As it is an AND here, I don't have to
evaluate this condition, I already
know that this entire
condition is necessarily false.
I therefore move on to this
conditional branch.
This condition is, well, the same as
before, I had said it was false,
but here it's an OR, so I have to
evaluate this expression,
this condition, 2 times n is 4, p
has the value 1,
and because 4 is greater than or equal
to 1, this condition
is true. As it's an OR, this
condition is true, so we
execute this instruction, that is,
print a 2.
We then move on to here. This
condition is false,
it's once again the same as before, so
we skip this conditional branch
to reach this stage of the program
which simply prints a newline.
Now let's turn to the boolean type,
which is the type of the conditions.
This type will let us declare
variables which will contain the condition's
value.
A variable of type boolean is often simply
called a
a boolean and can only contain two
possible
value, either true, or false, or more
exactly in
Java, we'll use the literal values
true and false, as expressed in English.
In this example, I begin by declaring
two variables
a and b of type int, a is initialized
to 1, b is initialized to 2.
This instruction
is a boolean variable declaration,
this variable is called test1, which will be,
indeed, of type
boolean. Like with any variable,
I can
represent it with a box. This variable
is initialized
to the value of the condition a equal b,
a has the value 1,
b has the value 2, so this condition is false
and test1 will
be initialized to false.
This following
instruction declares a second variable
of type
boolean, this time called test2, which
will be initialized to the value of the
condition a strictly less than b.
As a has the value 1 and b has the value 2,
this condition is true.
Therefore, test2 will be initialized
to true.
Some students don't have any problems
with
booleans, others sometimes have a
mental block.
So, remember that a variable of
type boolean is a variable like
another, that is, you can represent it
as a box.
It turns out this box can only
contain two possible values,
either true or false.
It also turns out that we can use
logical operators
between variables of type bool and that
we can use these
variables like conditions, for example
inside a conditional
branch, and that's what we're going
to see in this example.
As in the previous example, I begin
by
declaring a variable a of type int
initialized
to 1, a variable b also of type int,
initialized to 2. In the following
instruction, I this time
declare a variable of type boolean
which is called c and which is
initialized to the value true. In the
following instruction
I declare a boolean which is called d,
and which is initialized to the value of
the condition
a equal b. a has the value 1, b has
the value 2, the condition is
false, it therefore has the value false.
Thus d is
initialized to false. In
the following instruction, I declare a
variable of
type boolean which is called e and
which is initialized to
the value of the condition. d has
the value false.
This condition, a less than
b, is true, it therefore has the value true.
As the logical
operator here is an OR, this entire
condition is true and
it has the value true. So e is
initialized to true.
We now move on to this conditional
branch
which has as condition the value of
the boolean variable called e,
which is true, so this condition is true,
and we
enter the
conditional branch to execute this
instruction
and print the message "e vaut true" (TN which
means "e has the value true").
Voilà ! That's all for the moment concerning
booleans, but be aware that they are
helpful in many situations and
we'll encounter them in many examples.