Hello, and welcome this third unit
of our MOOC on ecological monitoring.
In this unit, we will introduce
different ecological
monitoring techniques.
This will help us better grasp
what ecological monitoring
practically looks like on the field.
Inza Kone, social professor at the
Félix Houphouët-Boigny University
of Côte d'Ivoire.
and Emmanuel Ima, social professor
at the Ki-Zerbo University in Burkina le Faso
will be helping us out.
Let's follow the impalas to see
what the techniques mentioned
in this unit will be.
First, we will examine
what key ecological attributes
should be monitored
and how to identify them.
Then, we will talk about the choices
of method and sampling most adapted
to the attributes.
After this, we will look at ways
of following the ecosystems
abiotic component, the ones
supporting life.
We will also specifically focus
on monitoring plants.
Big mammals will then be
our point of interest,
either by direct counting
or by indirect counting.
Both are obviously
very different techniques.
Next up, we will talk
about the specific case
of large carnivore monitoring,
with some lions, for example.
Then, our friend Inza will share
about his specialty,
the very specific monitoring
of primates.
As we zoom out a little bit,
we will talk about aerial counting
which can be useful
in certain circumstances.
And we will finish the unit
with Emmanuel
by looking at animals
that move around a lot
and the specific tools needed
to monitor them.
There you go.
Remember, the quizzes between the sequences
that will help you better understand
all these techniques
and have an excellent third unit.