The ecological characteristics
of animal species to monitor
influence the ecological monitoring.
In particular,
regarding the choice
of key ecological attributes,
the surveying methods,
or monitoring plans
to implement.
As we have already seen,
monitoring key ecological attributes
show the conditions
of the monitored species.
There are 3 types of attributes.
The size and distribution
of the species.
Its composition
and population dynamics.
And the quality of its habitat.
Obviously,
it is not about monitoring
all of these parameters,
but to choose the ones
that will give the best information
on the species' condition
and at the lowest cost.
The choice depends essentially
on the ecology of the species.
The chosen ecological attributes
should also reflect
the abnormal modification
of the population,
so that quick reaction
can be put in place if needed.
The ecological attributes'
size of the population
can vary abnormally.
For instance,
for example, it can decrease
due to poaching,
which would require an intervention.
But it can also vary
due to some natural phenomenon.
Elephants, for instance,
tend to travel seasonally
far beyond the limits
of the protected area to find food.
During the dry season
you will find them around the pond
looking for water.
And during
the rainy season,
where there
is plenty of water,
they can spread
over vast areas.
For this reason
the number of elephants
in the protected area can fluctuate,
but it doesn't necessarily mean
the population is in bad condition.
The distribution of the species
on the other hand,
depends on the quality
of the suitable habitat
within the protected area.
But also on the species' tolerance
of other species
or potential risks.
For instance,
if the distribution map of a park
shows that
concentration of a species
is in areas that are far
from the park's boundaries,
once grazing is possible everywhere,
it could show that
there is a poaching threat
coming from the surrounding areas.
The  distribution
of the animal species
is therefore is a good indicator
for the condition
of the species in the park
and of the location
of possible threats.
The second type
of ecological attribute
is a structure of animal population.
It is characterized normally
by the size of the groups,
or the numbers
of families it consists of.
The size depends
on the social system
of the species in question.
For example,
zebra herds gather several families.
The size of the group
depends on the difficulty
to find water and food
in the considered area.
The more food there is,
the larger the group will be.
And if the conditions
of the habitat gets bad
the group splits up
to form smaller units.
Thus, monitoring looks
at the size of groups
and detects
if the population suffers,
let's say,
and has to adapt
to difficult conditions.
Some species form large flocks,
like the buffalos,
while others stick to family units
with few individuals
like the [INAUDIBLE], for instance.
So you need to have
a rather good knowledge
of the normal social structure
of the different species
to detect any form of anomaly
during the monitoring.
Finally,
the third type
of ecological attribute
to take into account
is the species' habitat.
Indeed,
to survive,
animals need the suitable habitat
one in which they can get
food and water, obviously,
and also find the right conditions
for their reproduction.
Species can be dependent
on a particular habitat,
like some water birds,
for instance,
are dependent on permanent wetlands
within the park.
So monitoring
the quality of this habitat,
the wetlands in this case,
and especially the evolution
of invasive plants
that may invade those ponds
is key to the monitoring
of the survival of those species
within the protected area.
You need to know
the ecological characteristics
of the monitored species
to be able to identify
what key ecological attribute
would be the most
relevant to monitor
in order to differentiate
natural variation
of its population's condition
from abnormal ones
within the territory.