We've seen that ecological
characteristics of animal species
influence the choice
of key ecological attributes
that will define
the species' condition.
But ecological specificity
also play a part in choosing
the surveying method
and the sampling plan to implement.
The type of habitat is key
in choosing
the surveying method
to apply to the field.
If the species are difficult
to spot
because they live in an area
with dense vegetation,
indirect methods proving
the presence of the species
and giving an idea of the number,
by following
the droppings, nests,
the tracks, etc., should be used.
For instance, small antelopes
lives in forests and the (INAUDIBLE).
It is therefore, quite difficult
to spot them.
But they are territorial,
and mark their territory
by visible droppings.
In this case, these elements are
the ones that should be monitored.
On the other hand, larger species
living in open spaces
can be subject to direct ground-based
or aerial surveying.
So now, what about sampling
and the ecological factors
that may or will
guide it?
In this case, the area over which
a species is distributed
or it's daily and seasonal
travel region
influence the method to use
and the way it should be implemented.
Thereby, species distributed over
smaller area
will undergo closer monitoring
of it's overall population
compared to species covering
more ground.
In this case, the species
will be monitored by
a random sampling process in
the entire park.
Obviously, if you want to assess
a change of population
a smaller bit maybe, more
samples need to be collected
in order to be able to detect
this change.
Also if a species move over
different habitats,
it's not a bad idea to consider
the proceeding
to stratified sampling
where each stratum is represented
by one of the possible habitats
used by the species.
Ecological factors also influence
the time
when surveying should take place.
To maximize the possibilities
to observe
the monitored species, the surveying,
the monitoring
needs to take place at
a time of year or of the day
when it is most active and easiest
to observe, of course.
For instance, wild beasts leave
Serengeti in Tanzania
to enjoy the greener pastures
of the Maasai Mara in Kenya.
when it already raining there.
So, the managers of the Serengeti
National Park
and the Maasai Mara Reserve,
will proceed to do monitoring
of these wild beasts at different
times in the year,
according to this animal rhythm.
Yes.
So finally, there are also
ecological factors that influence
the frequency of data collection.
The more the considered species
is likely to adapt rapidly
to new constraints,
like changing territory
to escape threat, for instance,
the more you will need
to increase
the frequency of surveying
in order to be able to detect
this change on time,
and take then the right
management actions.
Conversely, for instance,
to monitor a normal increase
of the elephant population,
it is useless to proceed
to early counts as natural growth
is around 5 to 6 percent.
In this case it is better to go
4 or 5, or 10 years
surveying frequency,
which will allow
to follow the population
at lowest cost.
In short, the concept of ecology
to master
in order to design an ecological
monitoring plan
of a given species that will make
surveying easier,
are to know, first, the suitable
habitat of the species.
It's social system, to determine
the composition of the groups,
and their seasonal variations.
The frequency and the way
daily and seasonal travels occurs.
The normal growth rate
of it's population.
It's tolerance to the threats,
such as poaching,
competition with other species,
either world or domestic.
Also human presence,
change of habitat
and other kind of threats.
And the type of visible markers
that indicate
it's presence, like nests,
we saw that for chimps.
droppings, tracks, broken trees,
if we are talking of elephants.