Abiotic factors are lifeless
elements of an environment.
They include physio-chemical factors
and in this case they are climatic
including rainfall,
temperature, humidity,
winds, light,
or edaphic which is size,
texture, structure, or PH
and also hydrological
which includes water
physio-chemical properties.
Flows, siltations, levels,
et cetera.
Elements that impact
the environment's living being.
Abiotic factors are therefore,
potentially
key ecological attributes
accessing the health condition
of certain habitats.
For instance,
general climatic factors
especially those related
to rainfall, to winds,
to temperature
and to relative humidity
highly influenced plants
phenology
which is for instance period
of flowering,
or period of fruiting, and  also
leaves renewal.
They also influence fruiting
and seedling germinations.
Monitoring these factors
consists in implementing
an observation system
on the field
that involves  a synchronic
observation approach,
as well as diachronic
observation approach.
The synchronic observation approach
means comparing state
of the environment to a defined,
at a defined moment,
within and between territories.
Meanwhile diachronic
observation approach
means a comparison
of environments overtime.
In practice, the heterogeneity
of the ecosystem
usually requires a representative
sampling approach
thus, one should start
by considering
some of the following questions:
what does, are variables
and indicators
for change that I should monitor?
Another question to ask is
what is the minimum amount
of data needed to detect
such a change,
or how to account
for data collection process.
You may ask more
or many other questions.
Then, depending of the factors,
three line of approach
in monitoring abiotic factors
can be identified.
For case one, consist in
whether monitoring
that account for climatic factors.
For case two, accounts
for hydrological monitoring
that accounts
for  hydrological factors.
And for case three,
consist in pedological monitoring
that accounts for edaphic factors.
Whether the monitoring focuses
on measurements
of some variables,
including rainfall,
daily temperature,
and for measurement
of daily temperature,
one will need to measure
the maximum temperature
and the minimum temperature.
You will also need to measure
air humidity,
which is the hygrometric contents
of the air,
and also, the wind strength
and the light.
In fact, indices of rainfall,
temperature,
winds strength
and light intensity
are monitoring indicators
that ought to be tested
and validated.
Climatic data measurements
should be carried out daily
and always take place
at the same time
of the day or night.
In general, meteorologists
have chosen midnight,
six am, noon and 6 pm GMT.
Within  a protected area,
hydrological monitoring
essentially targets surface water.
This focus of ecological monitoring
is particularly useful
when it comes
to managing place
in arid and semi arid regions
where water is a limiting factor.
The most important viable
in hydrological monitoring
are the quantity of water
in stock.
You will measuring floods,
base floor, evaporations
infiltrations, et cetera,
of water bodies.
You also have to measure
water quality
which is physio-chemical
component of water.
You have to measure water floors
and water bodies siltations.
Water levels,
temperature, PH, oxygen,
conductivity,
turbidity, height of solid deposits,
and flow velocity,
which is rate of flows entering
and leaving the pounds
are protected areas
water body indicators
that  have to be tested
and approved
for comparison sync later on.
The periodicity of hydrological
measurements
is usually seasonal,
but monthly controls
of water levels
should be considered in dry
and semi-arid zones
which are example,
Savannahs
especially in dry seasons.
The data collected helps
to elaborate
weekly hydrological reports
in periods of flooding
and monthly ones,
in low water periods.
Under natural conditions,
the soil which
is edaphic components
does not vary significantly
in one place from one season
to another.
Soil monitoring especially
will target typological variables
which is type of soils
and the degradation of
the other soils
by factors including
desertification,
erosion, pollutions, et cetera.
In practice, pedological monitoring
also consider
the land use systems
of your sites.
Above all, indicators consider
the ratio
of lands affected by
a phenomenon
including desertification,
pollution, soil salinity, et cetera.
The data are collected
through pedological studies
including observation
of the field,
physio-chemical analysis,
description of soil profiles,
et cetera,
and also, through
socio-economic studies
and remote detections
including cartographies,
et cetera.
The periodicity of data collection
for pedological data monitoring
by process depends
on the problematic
synchronic and diachronic
data collected
or all these series of data
should at the end
help validating indicators
of change.
The idea is to proceed
to comparative analysis
between indicators to understand
the shifting trends
that would be observed
especially related to living beings
in the ecosystems.