Monitoring plants
that are considered
as protected area values
if often key
to understanding the ecosystem
and making the right decision
especially when it comes to ensuring
a sustainable development
of certain woody plants.
If the goal is to monitor
long-term changes
of plants biodiversity
in different ecosystem,
it is key to use samples
in permanently marked-off areas.
The intensity ecological factors
can change
based on geological
or topographic gradients
which then causes changes
in the structure
and in the floristic composition
along these gradients.
Regarding the monitoring
of plants communities
that do not have strong gradients,
it is recommended
to use permanent plots,
but when the gradients are strong,
it is better to use
permanent transects.
We won't be developing
these specifications here
as this unit focuses on monitoring
trees of a forest canopy
in stands where there are
no strong gradients.
Monitoring trees of a permanent
forest plots in the long run,
provides important information
on the forest structure
and composition,
on it's condition,
the growth pace and longevity
of trees species
inside the forest,
on the progressive variation
of a species' composition
and the size of the population,
on the impacts
environmental changes
have on the mature trees,
et cetera.
This continuous form of monitoring,
help to assess the impacts
of the decisions
affecting forest vegetation.
In this case, permanent plots
can ground-truth
the measurements obtained
via satellite images.
Square shaped plots
are generally the norm.
In the case of forest ecosystems,
two sizes of square-shaped plots
are recommended,
100 by 100 meters,
one hectare or 2.5 acres
and 20 by 20 meter plots.
These two formats
are interchangeable
or can be used together.
Ideally, you should be able to use
at least two plots of 2.5 acres
per selected type of forest
or stand
and whatever the stand,
use at least 5 independent quadrants
of 20 by 20 meters.
Plotting the species
accumulation curve determines
if this number is sufficient
for the given forest stand.
To avoid bias, the plots should be
scattered randomly
throughout the chosen stands.
Likewise, the location of the plot
in each settlement
should be set at random.
Some basic principles
ought to be followed.
A, the equivalent 3 times edge
of the forest covers
should separate the plot
from the edge of a non-forest stand
to prevent an edge effect.
B, plots of 2.5 acres
should be separated
by at least 250 meters
and 20 by 20 meter quadrats
by at least 50 meters.
See, in small or un-even
forest stands
where the previously stated
conditions can not be respected,
only independent
20 by  20 meter quadrats
and not 1 hector plots
should be established.
D, avoid establishing plots
where there are strong
and an unusual plant variations
or in the presence
of important ecological disruptions
such as a small lake,
a field or a river,
and E, avoid places where
roads or paths
run for the plots
unless the study is about
the impact the use
of such paths.
In this case, the decisions
should be justified.
It is vital to collect and take note
on the following data.
The tag number and species
of all standing trees
with a diameter at breast height,
DBH, equal to
or higher than 10 centimeters,
4 centimeter, or higher,
when forest growth
is poor.
Two, the location all numbered trees
of course, located on a map.
The DBH of all numbered trees,
the DBH measurements
following strict rules
as just showed on this diagram.
The general state
of all numbered trees.
The following data should also be
collected and recorded.
The height of all numbered trees,
the height of the lowest
leaving branch
of all numbered trees.
The canopy age, photos taken
from given places
at set times and dates.
The degree of canopy closure
per quadrat.
The forest stand should be assessed
every five years
or whenever needed.
If the quadrats suffer
from terrible weather conditions,
fires or other catastrophic events,
the quadrats should be
measured again,
and the new information
should recorded as soon as possible
after the catastrophe
when the conditions  have improved.
To analyze the data, draw up list
of standing species
found for all selected trees,
take notes of all
the species found in the plots
or in the permanent quadrats.
For each species
of living trees only,
calculate separately
the abundance,
the basal area,
the density and the dominance,
the frequency,
the relative density,
the relative dominance,
the relative frequency
and the value of importance.
Calculate the total basal surface
of all standing dead trees
and the ones leaning.
If carried out well
on the representative samples
of a studied stand,
monitoring plants will help,
making the right
management decisions
be there in terms
of forest conversation
or of it's sustainable use
when compatible
with the protected area's
conservation targets.