Direct mammal monitoring
relies on the study
of the state and the evolution
of animal populations,
as well as
the influence of pressures
on said population
through direct
observation of individuals
or group of animals.
In practice,
it consists in monitoring the trends
of certain key
ecological attributes
of this population.
The most common ones are density,
distribution,
or shifting trends
of this population,
as well as in direction
it can have with its habitat.
The choice of the assessment methods
of these parameters
is key to direct animal
population monitoring.
The type of method chosen
depends on simple questions.
Such as,
"Which ecological attribute
should I monitor?"
"Which indicators should I follow
for each of these
ecological attributes?"
Et cetera.
We can take the example
of ecological attributes
related to the population size,
average density,
group sizes,
distribution per habitat.
We can also at
attributes describing the structure
and the population dynamics,
gender, or age ratio,
data related to health conditions,
for instance.
But it is also important to see
what the minimum data needed
to monitor the population is.
This will help define
the collection cycle,
or periodicity,
as well as its duration.
Many inventory techniques
can be used, of course.
Among them, as we saw in Unit 2,
total count methods
can be carried out,
as well as methods
based on sample.
In the case of total count,
the entire study zone is inspected.
And statistical calculation,
if any,
only concerns
the estimation of bias.
Total counting on food,
for example,
is based
on the individual inclination
of all animals seen by the observer.
This technique can be applied
to a great number of species,
such as elephants, giraffes, rhinos,
most predators,
and some antelopes
that are easy to spot.
Most of the time, big species
that you can see
easily on the field.
As said earlier,
sampling should be
carried out at random,
for the number
to be representative
of the entire animal population.
In practice, the sample units
can take on multiple forms.
The most commonly used
are quadrats and transects.
Quadrats are based on the idea
of visually counting
the number of individuals
inside a predefined plot
set at random
in the studied zone.
All individuals observed
outside this plot
are not counted.
The estimation of the population
consists in calculating
the density of the sample
which is the ratio
between number
of counted individuals,
counted animals
in the quadrat,
and its surface area,
and to extend this number
to the total surface of the zone,
to obtain, of course, an estimate
of the global population
of the monitored species.
And for inventories by line transect
the method consists
in searching animals
along a line of undetermined width.
The animal's perpendicular distance
to this transect line is noted.
And in practice,
three measurements are taken
per observation.
These are the radial distance,
the viewing angle,
and the perpendicular distance.
The transect line
can be traveled on foot,
on horseback,
by car, or by whatever mean
you may have.
You could use a bike, of course.
Density estimate is then obtained
by a formula that considers
the number of observations,
the total transect length,
the width of the line
of the observation strip
which is determined, once again,
by the distance
at which animals are seen,
and the detection
probability function.
And there are several estimators
of this function
that are widely documented
in the literature.
Distance is a specialized software
that can help you to
estimate the functions.
Another technique,
the capture-recapture technique,
is a method often used
when data on mobile species
need to be collected.
It is a special technique,
where a known number
of animals of a species
is marked and released.
And based on the hypothesis
that the population
of marked individuals
compared to non-marked individuals
is the same in the sample
as in the entire population.
The share of marked
and non-marked animals
that will be captured next,
will be used
to estimate the total number
of animals within the population.
There are different
capture and recapture methods.
The choice depends
on whether you work
on closed population,
in other words,
one that is not in contact
with population outside
the protected area.
Or you work on open population
when protected area individuals
migrate outside the protected area.
Quite often,
another method is also
used very frequently.
The kilometric (abundance) index.
It is based on observations
made during walking surveillance,
patrols, for instance,
corrected depending on [INAUDIBLE].
For instance,
the walking time.
The more you walk, the more you see.
This essentially helps
to detect population variations
over time.
One technique especially
consists in looking
for noncturnal animals
with rump.
But this method is not suited
to sensing species
with low or very low density.
The punctual abundance index
is a technique consisting
in counting animals
at a certain fixed point.
Like waterholes, for example.
And to monitor population
fluctuation over time.
This technique
is usually carried out
from a hideout
at a set time and duration.
And the measurement
should be repeated
to have enough data.
Measuring the group size
is also a technique
that is used sometimes.
And for some herbivores,
the group size depends
on abundance of species
in the environment.
[INAUDIBLE] monitoring of this indicator
helped detect fluctuations
in species density.
For example,
group size of mountain goat
tend to increase
when the density increases.
Monitoring a sample
would then allow
to estimate abundance variation,
without having to count
the entire population
Which indeed is a much simpler way.
In all cases,
monitoring techniques
require a good capacity
to identify species,
and to be able to estimate numbers
upon very brief, sometimes,
visual contacts.
Biological knowledge of the species
is also key
to predict their behavior
in the presence of observers.
Finally,
observation conditions
should be good.
One should avoid windy,
dusty, too hot or rainy conditions.
Observers should move quietly,
that's the very least,
and consider animal reactivity,
especially in areas
prone to poaching.
Direct monitoring has the perk
of giving information
on the conditions
of pack animals.
But is not applicable
to hard-to-spot
or secretive species.