Hello.
Indirect mammal monitoring methods
are used when the animals
themselves are difficult to observe.
When vegetation is dense, as it is
the case in forests, for example.
When animals are present
in low density,
or when a species tends to appear
scarcely in the open.
Indirect counting approaches
are usually based on
sampling techniques we already
talked about
in the indirect monitoring.
And so (INAUDIBLE) use sampling units,
such as the quadrats
you are familiar with now.
Of course, line transects
can also be used.
They are axis of progression
along which
the indicators are counted.
Belt transects can also be used.
They are based on
the same principle,
but the counting is done
over determined surface
on both sides
of the progression axis.
There are several indirect
inventory methods
depending on the species
that is being studied,
on the environment's physical
characteristics,
on indicators that
are being measured,
and the resources at hand.
What we are looking for
in that case, remember,
are signs or indicators
of the animal's presence.
And to measure,
to monitor large African mammals,
the most commonly used methods
are as follows.
These are monitoring footprints,
monitoring tracks,
monitoring dens and burrows,
and nests,
monitoring faeces,
and monitoring family
noises or calls,
especially when monitoring lions.
Okay, let's see that in detail.
The footprint counting methods
can be used when the substrate
allows it, and it is a case
in sandy regions, for example.
Monitoring footprints can
be done daily, at any time you want,
but at each passage, do not forget
to cover
the signs that have already
been recorded, of course.
And the analysis of footprints,
helps to estimate
the walking direction,
and the use of the habitat,
as well as the size, the gender,
and even at times,
the age of the individuals.
An estimation of
the population density
can then be done by
a simple formula,
combining the density of
the tracks recorded
and the average size
of the considered species' habitat.
The tracks recognition methods
helps in some cases
to recognize an animal,
and to monitor it.
Recognition can be done
by sampling scars,
sizes, missing claws, etc.
For example, this technique
has been used
to monitor leopards
in the Namibian desert.
It can also be used
for the individual
monitoring of elephants.
Yeah, it's often
used for elephants.
The footprints of a species
can vary
depending on if they are front
or back paws, for example.
Depending on the age,
the gender of the animal.
It is therefore advised to combine
direct observation
of the animal and it's tracks.
Ideally, in each region,
it is recommended to set
a baseline collection using
plaster moulds,
or 3D photographs.
Yes, and counting burrows and dens,
consist in monitoring
animal resting
or reproductive sites.
It isn't always easy,
because the number of
individuals in the burrows
may vary.
They maybe abandoned
or occupied by another species.
For example,  aardvark burrows
can be occupied
by wart hogs, hyenas,
mongooses, etc.
Lots of species.
On the field this method
consists in distinguishing
the number of
abandoned burrows occupied by
the studied species,
occupied by other species,
as well as the number
of individuals per
occupied burrows.
To clarify this question,
it is advised
to combine this technique
with the identification
of tracks at the burrow entrance.
As the faeces monitoring method
is commonly used
when monitoring elephants,
it consists
in counting all the dung heaps
or dung piles
in the sampling area where
units are often made
or quadrats or again,
transects we have talked about.
Yeah.
Each elephant dung
is classified in one of
the five age categories
defined by specialists
going from very fresh
to almost completely decomposed.
And only relatively fresh
dung piles
are to be considered in
the mathematical estimate
of dung densities.
Thereby, droppings that are
too decomposed
are considered to have disappeared.
There is a relatively simple
relation between
the elephant density, E,
the number of dungs
produced by elephant per day,
Y, the dung decomposition rate,
or (INAUDIBLE) the dung density, D.
This gives an estimation
of the number
of elephants present
in the zone.
And the nest counting method
is very much used
when monitoring certain primates.
(INAUDIBLE) will share more about that
.with you
It consists in counting the nest
in the sampling area
where the units again, are often
quadrats or transects.
There is a relation between
the nest density
and the average size
of the nest groups.
The nest degradation speed, v,
and the density
or (INAUDIBLE) if you work on (INAUDIBLE), C.
The method using sounds or calls
is essentially used
when monitoring lions.
It consists in recording
the sound at set point
separated by a minimal interval of
13 kilometers,
in order not to recount
the same animals.
In this way you obtain
an estimate of the minimal
number of lions on
the survey sites.
Finally, you can also use
sensors and captors
to detect indirectly the animals.
It could be acoustic sensor
or camera trap
that takes pictures of or make
movies as we have already seen.
That way you can follow the animals
species of your path
without having to be on the ground,
especially when
your cameras are connected
so that you can
download the data from your office.
And then you enter
the Internet of Things.