Let's have a look into
a special case of carnivores
by starting with census for
direct observation on
linear transects.
Two or three observers run the
entire length of the transects
day or night. In a closed environment
like the forest, these prospections
would rather be carried out on foot.
In an open environment they are
usually done from a vehicle.
When an animal is spotted
It's perpendicular distance from the
transect line is recorded as well as
other relevant observations
regarding the number of individuals,
their gender, their age group,
what they are doing,
their behaviour, etc.
Well, if the sample size does not
give an estimation of the population
density, you don't have enough data.
The number of animals identified per
kilometre covered at least gives you
an ID of the relative abundance
And when the sample size does give
an estimation. The density of
populations can be estimated thanks
to the DISTANCE software, which
Emanuel taught us about earlier.
Of course, you can also carry out
a dropping count
along the line of progression
this is indirect monitoring.
In this case an observer examines
the ground looking for droppings.
While the others they focus on the
route thanks to a compass,
for instance. They'll measure the
traveled distance and clear the way.
However, for many carnivore species
in the forest, this approach won't
give any information
and it is better to sense droppings
along trails and roads where
they are more visible.
When a heap of droppings is found
measure the width of the strip
containing it so that you will be
able to use the Distance software.
Also look at its level of
decomposition and the type of
vegetation around it.
There is a relation between
the density of carnivores,
especially the big cats,
the number of droppings produced
per cat and per day,
the dropping decomposition rate and
the density of these droppings.
Counting the footprints along
the transects is also a good idea.
This method simply consists in
counting the tracks left by great
carnivores along the progression
lines. The number of tracks per
kilometre covered gives you, once
again a kilometric abundance index.
With all species of large carnivores
the density of tracks is greatly
related to the population density
and there are simple calculation
methods. Let's take the example
of the lion in this formula.
Xi is the population density
expressed in number of individuals
per 100 square km. And Ti is the
track density expressed in number of
tracks per 100 kilometre covered.
Quite simple, for each track,
record the GPS point, the distance
from the starting position,
the number of individuals, the age
of the track, when it is possible to
record. Whether this track belongs
to an individual from previously
recorded tracks, the type of
substrate where the track is spotted
and so on.
Some precautions need to be taken to
avoid counting individuals twice.
For example, respect a distance of
at least 500 metres before tracks
of an individual of the same species
can be recorded again.
Eliminate the second observation and
the next if identical individual
travel over 500 metres
in the same direction.
Also, eliminate tracks of the same
age and size moving about in
opposite directions over
short distances.
Photographic recording channels will
be done using, for instance,
photo traps. In this case the camera
should face a trail often used by
carnivores. To find the right place
look for crossing trails, droppings
signs of food, etc. The location
should be narrow enough for animals
to be obliged to come near the
camera.
A network of cameras can be set up
through the surveyed zone or at the
centre of some sampling you need,
in that case, most of the time,
a quadrant.
You can also put bait in such a way
as to photograph any animal
approaching the bait. This is a
good solution when the trails are
often used by humans or to sample
carnivores rarely using
the roads and the trails.
Hereby you obtain important
information on the presence of
species in the zone and this
information may be very important
in itself and sometimes on the
structure of the populations.
For species that can be identified
from the specific trait, such as
the shapes on their coats, directly
count individuals, describe their
traveling patterns and calculate
population density from the photos
taken by cameras set up in the
sampling blocks.
This is, in particular, useful for
leopards, for instance.
A special technique is also used
to count and monitor lions from,
what we call, calling stations
This simply consists in playing
the sound of a species in distress,
like a young buffalo, to attract
lions in the surrounding areas and
to count them simply.
Usually you would photograph them,
photograph the lion, which come,
to compare individuals between them
and to be able to
differentiate the lions.
Of course, you need to move the
calling station to try to cover
different territories and this
is usually done by night.
And, as far as possible,
just try to pay attention to the
lion you attract.
Absolutely.