Just like with other species,
start by choosing
the ecological attributes
to monitor.
Then, based on these attributes,
select the methods among the ones
we will be presenting shortly
that will provide information
on the indicators to assess.
The direct line-transect method
is recommended.
In this case, detect the animals
as follows:
Early in the morning
or in the late afternoon,
observers slowly, at an average speed
of one kilometer per hour,
and quietly work along
the transect line.
The weather can influence
primate detection.
Some species cry less
in windy conditions
and they are all more difficult
to see when it's raining.
Therefore, avoid counting
during a shower or right after.
As soon as a primate is spotted,
take note of the following information:
the name or transect number,
the distance traveled
along the transect - measured,
thanks to a (INAUDIBLE),
the date, the time,
the detection method - seen, heard,
branch movement, falling fruit,
animals running away, and so on.
The species, the distance
between the observer and the animal,
the angle of observation,
the perpendicular distance
between the animal
and the transect line.
This is measured
with a tape measure,
a non-elastic rope, or optical
or a laser range-finder.
Also, write down the information
concerning the group of primates:
the number of individuals
in the group by gender,
age group, and species,
the surface area covered
by the animals
and their main activity: eating,
traveling, social interaction, rest.
To analyse the data,
two or three data sets are needed.
One: the distance traveled
along the transect line,
which is determined by multiplying
the lines' total length
by the number of times it was traveled.
Two, the number of groups encountered,
specifically, groups having
both male and female individuals.
Three, the forest surface
on which
a given number of primates
were recorded.
This is obtained by multiplying
the transect (INAUDIBLE)
by the distance covered.
The relative abundance
of a species
or the number of groups
per kilometer  traveled
can be calculated using
the first two sets of data.
With all three data sets,
the population density
can be calculated, expressed
in groups per square kilometers
using the DISTANCE software.
which, as Emmanuel explained, considers
detectability variations
of animals in different zones.
Another approach,
indirect this time, is nest counts.
When a nest is spotted,
the process is just similar
to when a primate is detected.
Some information is vital
to capitalizing
the nest counts per square kilometer:
namely, the nest construction rate
per individual
given the age differences
and the time it takes
for nests to decay to a point
that can no longer
be identified as such.
This time depends on factors such as
seasons, altitudes, species, etcetera.
Once you have information
concerning nest-making
and their decay rates per site
and per season,
it is possible to calculate
reasonable estimates
of the decline rate of gorilla
or chimpanzee populations.
This often varies.
Finally, let's talk about call mapping.
Because of their powerful shouts,
or calls,
some animals can be detected
from a greater distance
than in observations.
This method is especially useful
to indirect monitoring
in places where monkeys
or apes chatter loudly.
In the case of diurnal species,
the observer should start working
early in the morning,
in many cases right before dawn.
Walk slowly at an average pace
of one kilometer per hour
and stop at certain marked locations
to listen to the shouts or calls.
As soon as he hears the calls,
he should be waiting
between fifteen and thirty minutes
when the interaction
between the two groups is over.
In the case of nocturnal species,
the detection work depends
on the species.
Generally, bush babies squeal
at nightfall
and for around an hour at dawn.
The task should be repeated
over several days
depending on the species, the site,
the season, and the weather conditions.
For particularly loud species,
like the red colobus,
three days can be enough to record
all the groups present
in the survey zone.
But more time is needed
when shouts are scarce and quieter.
Generally speaking, the census
should carry on
until quality sets are obtained.
To record data, proceed as follows:
when the observer hears shouts,
he should take note
of the following information.
The date, the time, the species,
the type of call,
the position of a call to
where the observer is,
the estimated distance
between the observer and the animal,
the observer's geographical coordinates
at that moment.
If the same group can be heard
after the observer
has moved away,
a new survey should be carried out
so that the group position
can be calculated more precisely
by means of triangulation.
Finally, the information
should be processed as follows:
draw up a precise map
of a surveyed area on graph paper
and note the main topographic elements
such as waterways, wetland, etcetera,
Copy this map as many times as needed,
so that the data on different species
can be noted separately.
On the map, write down
the date and time
on a pencil-drawn line
where the shouts were recorded
and where the observer
was positioned.
The distance between the observer
and the animal is estimated
and also noted on the map.
Make sure to triangulate the shouts
of a group heard at different moments.
Make sure not to count species
that cover great distances quickly
and that can be heard
at different places,
like mangabeys, twice.
To reduce this type of mistake,
it is important to know the size
of a surveyed zone, potential overlap
between feeds,
and traveling and feeding patterns,
which you can obtain
through long time service.
Note on the animals observed
and not heard can also be
written on the map.
This will enable you to draw up
a complete table
of all the present groups.