Aerial monitoring is an ecological
monitoring technique
commonly used in protected areas,
particularly in Africa
where protected areas
can be quite vast.
It essentially relies on the use
of an aircraft
but other instruments
can also be used
like ULMs, drones, kites.
Some conditions determine
this choice of method.
First, the protected area
should be sizeable.
This means that for a best
cost effective
or cost benefit ratio,
monitoring a park
of less than 1000 square kilometers,
100,000 hectares,
should be ground-based.
The environment needs
to be open, in deed,
aerial monitoring is not adopted
to closed area like forest
or un-even terrain where the ground
cannot be seen.
Finally, the species we look for
need be visible from air, of course.
They would usually be
the bigger mammals
or species living in large herds
like impalas
or buffaloes in this case.
You can also choose
to monitor the floral distribution.
So the main objective
of aerial monitoring is to be able
to estimate the numbers
and monitor the evolution of one
or more spaces in time
and in space
by connecting periodic surveys.
The aerial monitoring also gives
a different perspective
of the territory.
A border and more
comprehensive view
compared to the traditional
ground based monitoring,
it is a good tool
to better understand
how the ecosystem works.
It allows to confirmed
the existence of certain species
when they are hard
to detect by other means.
It provides an estimation
of the numbers
within the detected species
as well as an estimation
of the size or the structure
of the groups.
Obviously, it allows to understand
the special distribution
of the species in the park,
and shows the evolutionary number
and distribution when the counting
is repeated overtime.
When you have a map
of the protected area's vegetation,
aerial monitoring allows to connect
the distribution of species
and of different habitats.
It also gives important additional
information for management
like signs of poaching, carcasses,
the presence of cattle
or human activities
like gold mining, encroachment
of the park boundaries
and nogging for instance.
There are many advantages
to aerial flying.
It is a reliable method
that can be implemented rapidly.
It  mobilizes few staff members
and allows to cover large surfaces.
Thanks to aerial flying,
you can access
usually, non-paroled territories
and easily get a lot
of geo-specific information.
This method is limited
by the state of the area
that shouldn't be too close,
and also by some spaces
that are being looked for.
Some of them are difficult
to detect
because they live in the forest,
so we cannot see them,
or form uncountable herds
like the baboons for instance
or because they don't run away
as the aircraft gets closer,
so it's difficult to see them
and they're difficult to spot,
like the eland for instance.
The one we see there.
Aerials have an income also,
of course,
be costly, even though, this fact
needs to be put  into perspective
compared to other method
and quality of obtaining results.
Aerials surveying is done
by transects,
usually parallel lines fall
by the aircraft.
Most of the times several transects
are covered during  flights
and they are  oriented in a way
to avoid having to face the same.
Generally speaking, the overflight
takes place early in the morning
or in the late afternoon,
to avoid the hot hours
of the day.
Animals are counted (INAUDIBLE)
on the ground
that were calibrated on the plane
during the preparation phase
of the protocol.
Aerial counts are made
thanks to high-wind aircraft
for better visibility on the ground.
The surveying team usually
gathers four people
including the pilot
who follows the flight plan,
the navigator will record
the information given
by the observers and controls
the flight parameters
and, two observers
at the back,
in charge of detecting the follow.
The pilot, as this one,
and the navigator,
can also contribute to the survey
by supporting the main observer,
and the GPS will be programmed
with all the transects
before off.
Sampling is the best way
to proceed
to aerial survey, because
if you do the total count,
there is a high risk of recounting
moving animals especially
when using several aircraft
launched at the same time.
The first step consist in defining
a path on each side of the plane,
generally between 100
and 250 meters large
according to visibility
you will have.
You then calibrate the plane
thanks to the banner
that are attached to the the spars
to define the path on the ground.
The interval between transects
then depends
on the desired sampling rate
you will wish to obtain.
During the overflights,
only the animals within the path
are to go into account which allows
to calculate a theoretical density
along with a standard deviation
that is of greater magnitude
when there are fewer contact points
an when the counting effort
is reduced.
The sampling method requires
simple statistical processing
of data, following the Jolly method
most of the time,
this is explained in the
second module
about statistics in this MOOC.
The count usually covers
10 to 20 % of the territory
and the results can greatly vary
from one season to another.
In order not to disrupt the flight,
big herds are usually photographed
for subsequent counting.
Finally, using a geographical
information system,
allows to determine
the distribution of animals
within the protected area
if the GPS positions of the
observations are properly recorded.
Sources of aerial are due
to the sampling rate.
The more transects there are,
and the wider paths are,
the more ground is covered
and therefore,
the position of the survey improves.
Some species will systematically
be underestimated
because  they're hardly visible
from the plane
like this lion for example.
For bigger herds, you need
you need to force yourself
to count only the animals
present inside counting path.
The meteorological conditions
and visibility
can also greatly affect
the counting performance.
The experience of a people
is essential to avoid
identification.mistakes
and to quickly being able
to estimate the number
of animal present.
You also need
to take into account that
tiredness greatly affects attention
after a while.
Of course, you would need test
of the ability of the observers
to fly  without getting sick
in often harsh conditions.
Finally, since it's a low
level flight
in a quite hostile environment,
you need to have a prepared team
to the possibility
of an engine failure,
that will lead into
an emergency landing.
Good luck.