So monitoring mobile species
requires the implementation
of suitable monitoring systems.
In Ecology,
there are several ways
of observing mobile animals
and this can be done broadly
or not depending
on animals traveling distance.
When animals travel
of a shorter distances
big mammal ecologist
often use what is called
radio tracking.
This is a monitoring
or detection system
for animals previously fitted
with a radio transmitter.
The animals confirmations,
their environment
and ways of moving about
are considered
when fitting the transmitter.
In the case of large animals,
harnesses and collars are used
and whenever the harness is too big
adhesive tapes or subcutaneous
or even surgical implants
are preferred.
You must remember
not to either equip a small animal
with transmitters that will exceed
6% of their weight.
Another technique
for animals traveling
over short distances
provided they are easy to find again
with the bit to use bands
or colored marks.
This is obviously more convenient
than radio transmitters.
The animal is equipped
with a non-bird ring
and a bright colored tag
or plate to facilitate
each identification
from a short distance.
This will help clearly
to recognize it
and in a group settings
to monitor each movement
and behavior individually.
Parts of their coat
can also be blench
to monitor individual animals
of a species on a territory.
This is by the way
of them carried out on animals
such as large birds
of prey or wading birds.
And for animals traveling
of a long distances
ecologist essentially use
GPS tags or ARGOS tags
which shows the animals location
from a distance.
The GPS,
this is global positioning systems.
The GPS then has the benefit
of recording location
with great precision
of not having a range limit
and also it gives the possibility
of choosing the time
and the frequency of data receptions.
In the special case
of migratory birds,
it isn't uncommon
to band the animal
to monitor movement
but these requires
using the capture.
This is to put the band
and recapture again the individual
to (INAUDIBLE) results.
The only exception
is when monitoring large species
where it is possible
to read the larger range
from a distance.
All the techniques
that uses tags and transmitters
help finding living animals
but also the carcasses
which is a very useful
when studying the causes
of animal’s death.
This is also a techniques
that gives the possibility
to obtain important information
on territorial limits
and also interaction
with different population.
Also, it gives information
on breeding areas
and rate and food intake
breeding areas, rate, food intake
and any other behavior.
They are therefore
excellent techniques
that will complete
which is complementing
other direct monitoring techniques
that we have talked about earlier.
Even though they resemble a research
more than strictly
speaking monitoring.
This is due to their cost.
The indicator collection time
and thereby information
to be processed by management
to make them much more
costly for management.