Transaction and abstraction for dealing
with concurrency and systems.
They're actually very simple and elegant
and intuitive abstraction
because they correspond to the notion
of transactions as we're used to
from the real world,
from business transactions.
So, if you go to a bookstore
to buy a book, you will think
of a transaction as: to choose your books,
take the book and give money to the store.
It means that there are at least
two actions that happen:
the moving of the book
into your ownership, into your possession,
and the movement of money
into the possession of the store.
And you want to handle
these two actions atomically.
That means, you would like to have
both of them or none of them.
Of course, as the buyer,
if you give money; you want the book.
And as a store, you want to get
the money if you give the book.
And not just one of the two.
Also, if at the same time maybe,
in the bookstore, there's another buyer
who also wants to buy a book,
maybe at a different checkout,
I would think of that
as a different transaction.
We wouldn't want
to have to confuse the two.
We don't want to put them together;
we can treat them separately,
from the viewpoint of the buyers
and to some extent,
from the viewpoint of the book store.
Transactions are actually a notion
that came out of database research,
and they play a very important
role in delivery systems.
But they also play an important role
in other context of systems,
application service transaction
processing systems of all kinds,
and also in the context
of transaction memory.
Which is an important notion
in the context of programming languages
and computer architecture.
Transactions allow us to support
the concurrent execution of user programs
and they are essential
for good database performance.
Why is that the case?
Well, one thing is that transactions
might be quite long-running.
For example there might
be humans involved
and the two steps of the transaction
that I talked about in the bookstore;
they might take some time to happen
because humans take their time
and they are much slower
than computers, right?
So if such transaction takes a minute
for example, you don't want to enter
the system to be locked down,
and only be able to deal
with this one transaction, and not be able
to serve any other transactions
at the same time.
Our computers are very fast,
and we want to use that performance.
So as I said, transactions
are an abstraction....
and they allow us to separate
things that are relevant to the database
system, for executing the transaction.
For making this set of concurrent changes
possible, while keeping other things
separate that are not important.
For example, an application program
a frontant, a browser frontant for example,
for a webstore, will be worrying about
displaying things in all kinds of colors
and putting text in all kinds of places,
and that might not be important
for getting the transaction right.
But the delivery system has to know which
book I want to buy, and how much money
I am going to give for it, from which
account, what my identity is etc.
So, users submit transactions and can
think of each transaction
executing by itself,
independent of any others.
We don't have to know
about other transactions.
We can think of as a user,
for the purpose of abstraction,
that there is nothing else happening
in the system at this point in time.
We call this thing Isolation.
Concurrency is then achieved
by the database system,
which has to interleave these actions,
has to worry about how to make things work
how to make this transaction
become... get executed.
And how to put as much work into
as little time as possible, ideally.
Each transaction
must be completed
and leaves the database
in a consistent state.
Which means that if there
was a notion of consistency,
at the beginning of the transaction,
before the transaction started,
the database was in a state where
were everything was correct
nothing is wrong; nothing that
I expect violates it.
Then I want this property of everything
being consistent and fine also to hold
after the transaction has finished.
In the consistent database system,
we talk in particular
about integrity constraints here.
That means, constraints like--
there mustn't be two users
with the same social security number.
Things like that, right?
These integrity constraints;
they must at all points in time,
conceptually hold true.
Sometimes, there might be dependencies
between different items that we change,
so they have to change together
to achieve consistency.
For example, it might be that I have
two different records in a delivery system
that belong together and it's only
possible if the other one exists as well.
For example, I could create a new user
only if there's at least one business
[inaudible] that just bought something
in my bookstore and at the same time,
a business transaction is not possible
without the user record.
That means at a point in time when
the user for the first time buys a book,
we have to enter two records
and the integrity constraints
and the mutual dependency between
the two records right--
If one is there, the other one is almost
always there and visa versa.
It cannot be guaranteed
at all points in time
if you really enter record by record.
But if I create a transaction that
atomically creates both records together,
then all I have to require
is that the integrity constraints
holds before the transaction starts
and after it finishes.
You know the constraint,
well that always disappears off records.
So this notion of satisfying
all integrity constraints,
posted on the system,
formalized in the system
corresponds to some of the consistency
in database systems.
In more generally more challenging module,
we will think of consistency
as a broader notion.
But for the purpose
of this transaction video today,
we will restrict consistency
to satisfying the integrity constraints.
But beyond satisfying the integrity
constraints post by some programmer
to the database system,
the database system doesn't have
to understand the semantics
of the data; it cannot really.
And consistency doesn't concern itself
with intuitive notions of what is right,
that are not specified to the system.
I've already mentioned the notion
of atomicity in transactions.
So, a transaction consists of a bag
or actually a sequence of actions,
operations that may change
the state of the database.
And in the end, I would like to execute
all of the transactions or none of it.
If it's for some reason, not possible
to complete the transaction,
or if a user chooses
to cancel the transaction,
there is this notion
of aborting a transaction,
and then the database has to get back
into the state it was in at the beginning
of the transaction, before any changes
were made by this transaction.
In general, you can imagine
that this is not super easy to achieve,
if there are many transactions working
concurrently that might depend
in some way, on each
other, conceptually.
So the notion of atomicity connects
to the notion of committing
or aborting a transaction.
Committing means,
in the end of all my actions
I say, "Now indeed, I would like to make
all of these changes persistent
and I would like to enter
the transaction that way."
The alternative is to abort it
and then all has to be undone.
This notion of aborting
can be implemented in different ways.
One way is to have a, kind of, log
that records all the actions
so that we can undo them in someway.
Maybe the pre and after
images of the database.
Another notion would be to work
with a snapshot that copies the database;
that can be thrown away if you choose
not to commit to transaction.
A very famous notion
is that of ACID transactions.
You may have heard this already,
it's actually very important
in computer science.
And ACID is an acronym standing for:
atomicity, consistency, isolation
and durability.
So we have just discussed atomicity
and we've discussed consistency;
that was the notion of satisfying
all the integrity constraints
posed to the system.
Isolation refers to, and I think
I mentioned this before as well...
The idea that transactions
were completely independent;
they don't interfere with each other.
Each transaction can be executed
using a conception model--
that nothing else happens
at the same time in the system.
And finally, durability refers
to the notion that things
that we commit become
durable and don't get lost.
That means conceptually,
if I commit a transaction,
and I say "Finish it; store it."
Then it mustn't go away;
the data must remain stored.
It mustn't, for example, crash
suddenly and then the data is lost.
Something that is committed, must be
recorded so it'll stay for eternity.
Keep in mind though,
that another transaction
may intentionally change
things back to an old state.
If it's a different transaction,
then that's OK.
This doesn't conflict with durability.
If I've got a first transaction
that increases my bank account
by 100 Swiss Francs and the second
that decreases it by 100 Swiss Francs,
this is not in violation of durability.
It would be a violation of durability,
if after the first transaction
which increased my bank
account by 100, something bad happens
and this change is lost and goes away.
But if you intentionally change it
in a separate transaction
then that's not
in violation of durability.
Here's an example of a transaction
or actually a sketch of two transactions.
So, we will use the notion of sketch rule
or history to refer to a recording
of multiple transactions possible
that occur over a time frame.
And usually, we'll write
these transactions
along a timeline from left to right.
Transaction begins and then there might
be sequence of actions that happen
one after the other.
And in the end, they end.
In example that you see actually,
I just say 'BEGIN and END'.
If I don't say anything else, I assume
by end that the transaction is committed.
[Inauduable]
Sometimes, it will say
explicitly: commit or abort.
So, here we see two transactions,
the first one says well,
take two bank balances
for example, two account balances,
and I increase and commence one,
the first bank balance A by 100
and I decrease the second B by 100.
So the idea is, I actually
make a bank transaction
moving 100 of a currency from B to A.
I've got a separate transaction
that actually increases all the balances,
that means, both A and B's balance by 6%.
That means we multiply
the current balance by 1.06,
and assign that new value
to the bank balances.
So I can imagine this as two transactions
in a bank, in a banking system.
The first one is a wire transfer,
the second one is and interest payment
on all the accounts.
So, what could I mean by this?
In a sense, these things
happen concurrently.
If transaction T1 happens completely
before T2, everything is probably clear.
And if T2 happens completely
before T1, everything is clear.
Actually, it makes a difference though.
Because if the bank balance
of A initially is zero
and we first increase by 100
and then pay interest, A will own 106.
While, if we first pay interest
and then get our increase,
A will own 100 only.
So the order of the transactions matters.
And that order is going to be determined
by the order in which transactions
physically arrive in some sense.
We're going to only require the semantics
to be such that, we can think
of transactions that have
happened in some order
not in the living.
That's consistent with this notion
of isolation and expectations
that we have about
transactions discussed so far.
Let's consider some possible
interleavings of these two
transactions we've just seen.
At the top of the slide,
you see an interleaving
were the first action of the first
transaction, is followed
by the first operation of second
transaction, followed by the second
operation to the first transaction
and finally, the second operation
of the second transaction.
If you look at the first two
actions in this schedule;
they're both on object A
on the first user's bank balance.
And then the third and the fourth
actions are only involving B.
So in a sense, the first two actions
don't interleave with this second set;
the actions 3 and 4.
And conceptually, I could reorder
the second and the third actions
in this schedule, to get
a completely serial schedule,
namely T1 completed before T2.
That means, I could move the B=B-100
before the A=1.06 x A and it would have
exactly the same meaning,
the same semantics to the schedule.
So this schedule is actually equivalent
to a serial execution of T1 before T2.
And that is what we think
of as an acceptable execution
of these set of transactions.
And if you look at the second schedule
that you see on this slide,
were we first have A=A+100, A=1.06 x A
and then B=1.06 x B and then B=B-100.
The interleaving of T2 nested into T1,
is such that there is actually
no execution that is
serial and equivalent.
So if you execute a T1
completely before T2,
we would have a different semantics
because then B would have had its money
deducted before the interest
was paid, which is different
from what we see right now, were interest
is paid before money is entirely deducted.
So current schedule, as you see it here,
is advantageous to be compared to one
were T1 is executed before T2.
And visa versa.
If you would execute T2
entirely before T1,
it would be unfair, so to say,
in the other sense,
compared to the schedule.
So what we're saying is that,
this schedule, the second schedule
actually does not correspond
to any serial execution of--
It's not equivalent to any serial
execution of these two transactions
and we want to exclude
such an interleaving.
Because it doesn't correspond
to our notion of isolation.
This does not make sense
if we think of this system
executing everything
one after the other,
elimination the need for us
to understand concurrency.
Just for completeness right now,
from the viewpoint of the database
system, analyzing such schedules,
we can actually extract away
from the application code that
[inaudiable] does certain things with A,
and changes A in certain ways
and changes B in certain ways,
reading off values of B, etc.
And we could only talk
with reads and writes.
So, we could say that this very first
action: A=A+100 is actually a read of A
followed by a write of A.
What is written depends
on the reading of A,
so we cannot ignore
what has been read.
But how exactly it's written;
that effect is that we actually
increment it by 100.
We don't need to know or worry
about these ordering constraints.
So in fact now, each of these four
operations is or corresponds
to a read of the old value
and a write of the new value.
And you can think of this schedule
on the level of abstraction
that we will really have to study later;
its just a sequence of reads and writes
in each transaction.
So I've already kind of said
this in this example,
so we think of a serial schedule
as a schedule that doesn't have
any interleavings.
Each transaction is executed--
the transactions are executed
one after the other.
For example, T1 completely before T2
or T2 completely before T1.
That's serial.
Any interleaving were things
are overlapping, is not a serial schedule.
And if you go for two schedules
as equivalent, if they lead to the same
result no matter what
the initial database state is,
that means no matter what,
they are all [inaudible] A and B,
the result must be the same,
and then the schedules are equivalent.
And a serializable schedule
is a schedule that is equivalent
to a serial execution
of the transactions.
That means, it's equivalent
to a serial schedule.
It's a serializable schedule.
And this is a very important notion
because that is what we think of
as an acceptable execution
of transactions in concurrent systems.
That means serializability allowing
only serializable schedules
is exactly what we want to, kind of,
guarantee this notion of consistency
of actually ACID's
in a consistent databases.
What can go wrong
in non-serializable schedules?
There's actually three major notions
of things going wrong;
anomalies, that we should talk about.
The first is what you call: Reading
Uncommitted Data or 'dirty reads'.
We can also call them,
Write-Read Conflicts.
So look at this example schedule here.
We've got T1 writing A,
followed by T2 reading A.
Then T2 is committing and finally,
T1, let's say, is aborting.
That means that T1 made
a change to the database,
a temporary change
to the database that it later undid.
And T2 read this change and made
decisions based on that change,
wrote to the database
state and committed this.
That means, this commit depends
on data that actually was not final,
and thus, this read of A
in T2 is a 'dirty read'.
It's a read that shouldn't have happened
in this way and thus the database
is not in a consistent form
anymore and it's corrupted.
So this must not happen.
The second form Read-Writes conflicts,
unrepeatable reads.
So, look at this example, so we have T1
reading A, T2 reading A then writing it
then committing.
And then we have T1 reading A again.
So, T1 reads A twice, and it will
in general read two different values,
because in the meantime, between
the first and the second read of T1,
T2 has changed the value of A.
And isolation basically governs
that this must not happen.
We should think of T1 happening
in complete isolation.
We don't need to store the value
of A locally for consistency.
We can rely on
the database to store it for us.
And the semantics of A's transactions,
requires that this is safe to do,
that reading two values twice,
if I have not written them in between
in my transaction,
has to lead to the same value.
So these unrepeatable reads
are of course bad
and they won't be possible
in serializable transactions.
The third case is: Write-Write Conflicts,
where we overwrite uncommitted data.
So for example here, T1 writes A,
then T2 write A and then writes B, commits
and then T1 writes B and commits.
So, in a sense, what T2 has done
specifically, what it has done to B
has been lost, it has been overwritten
and durability in a sense,
has been violated.
At the same time, I cannot
just say, "Well, this is OK,"
because I could have executed T2
completely before T1
leading to a serializable schedule
because I'm actually writing
A and T2 after I am writing A and T1.
So this interleaving, nesting T2 intoT1,
leads to a Write-Write Conflict
and that's again, bad.
And it would not happen
in a serializable schedule.
So finally, let's think again about
what it means to abort a transaction.
There's a few issues here.
First of all, again if a transaction
is aborted then all its actions
have to be undone.
That's required by atomicity.
But not only that.
If some other transaction reads
what a transaction has written,
then this transaction is getting aborted.
That means, a transaction
depends on values that are now
getting undone by the abort.
Then this other transaction that depends
on those values, has to also be aborted.
So this can lead to a cascade of aborts.
A single abort can force other
transactions to be aborted as well.
And we have to be careful because
we mustn't allow these other transactions
get committed before the first
transaction gets committed.
Because if the first transaction
gets aborted then you've got
this dependencies which
cannot be recovered from.
And the database is permanently,
so to say, corrupted.
That mustn't happen.
So we have to actually worry about
in our concurrency control
algorithms and protocols,
not just about serializability
but also about correctly
dealing with aborts.
In summary, transactions
are a very nice and clean abstraction
for dealing with concurrency.
We've talked about the ACID
properties of transactions:
atomicity, consistency,
isolation and durability.
All of those, are important
and there's good reason for them.
Atomicity really makes
the transaction work.
It's not a single individual update
but a sequence of things
that belong together.
Consistency means that you can have
constraints on the validity of the data,
integrity constraints, and they must be
satisfied before and after transactions.
Isolation means, you can really think
of, as a program of database application
for example, that there's nothing else
happening, you don't have
to worry about consistency.
So you don't really have to be
an expert systems engineer, for example,
to be able to deal
with a database system.
You can program your application
programs as if nothing else happens.
And the database system is entirely
responsible for ensuring
that concurrency is dealt with properly.
And transactions
are the vehicle for doing this.
And finally, durability is the,
kind of, obvious thing that,
things that you store and mean to store
and say, "I really mean to store this,
I commit," they mustn't get lost.