We've defined the gold standard
for the semantics of transactions
to be serializability.
That means given
a schedule of transactions,
if you can say, and show,
and understand
that this schedule is equivalent
to a serial execution of the transactions,
where transactions
don't execute concurrently,
but one after the other, completely,
then such transactions are called
serializable--that's what we desire.
Now, in this video, we're going to talk
about one family of techniques,
based on locking,
for achieving serializability.
Specifically, we're going to now introduce
the notion of conflict serializability.
That's a special case of serializability.
Whenever a schedule
is conflict serializable,
it's also serializable,
but not necessarily vice versa.
So two schedules are conflict equivalent
if they invoke the same actions
of the same transactions,
and every pair of conflicting actions
is ordered in the same way.
We're going to see by example
what that means, exactly.
We can actually formalize this via
the notion of the dependency graphs.
In any case, conflict equivalence
implies equivalence.
It's a special case, I would say
a stronger condition.
And if a schedule is conflict equivalent
to a serial schedule,
then we call it conflict serializable.
So just like serializability
means that a schedule
is equivalent to a serial schedule,
conflict serializability means
it's conflict equivalent
to a serial schedule.
Now, how do we decide when
a schedule is conflict equivalent?
Let's look at this example.
There's two transactions, again,
shown by this timeline.
And we can build a dependency graph
where each node, or each transaction
has a node for itself,
and the enter edge from
one transaction to another transaction.
If there is a dependency
in the schedule of the following form
that either one transaction
writes one particular object
that another transaction afterwards reads,
that means a write-read
conflict so to say,
that would mean for that object
you might get an error
from the writing transaction
to the reading transaction.
Also, if one transaction first reads,
and the other one afterwards writes,
we've got a read-write conflict,
and you would make a dependency edge
in the dependency graph.
And similarly, if you've got
a write-write conflict.
There are three kinds of anomalies.
If one transaction first writes,
and the other one afterwards
reads the same object again,
then we will enter an edge
from the first to the second transaction.
We will also usually label these edges
with the kind of object
that was the culprit, so to say,
which was responsible
for the dependency.
Remember, there is no read-read conflicts.
If all transactions only read, there's
no change to the database, in a sense,
then we don't have to worry about
concurrency and about changes,
because there are no changes,
and nothing bad can happen.
Everybody will read
the same version of the database,
and nothing's getting changed,
and everything is safe.
So we have write-read, read-write,
and write-write conflicts.
Now, we built this
dependency graph that way.
In this example we've got an edge
from T1 to T2 labeled A,
because T1 first writes A,
and T2 afterwards reads A.
And we've got an edge
from T2 to T1 labeled B,
because T2 first writes B,
and then T1 reads B.
You can see that there's
a cycle in this dependency graph,
and that cycle evidences the problem.
The edge from T1 to T2, labeled A,
shows that there is a write-read
conflict between T1 and T2,
and to make this serializable
you would really need a serialization
where T1 is actually going to be for T2,
and vice versa: the edge from T2 to T1
says that basically,
to make this serializable,
we would have to show that
it's equivalent to serial schedule
where T2 is completely executed before T1.
So there is this kind of mutual conflict:
T1 has to be before T2,
and T2 has to be before T1,
and that's of course not both possible.
That means whenever we've got
a cycle in this dependency graph
then it is not conflict serializable,
and thus also not,
in general, not serializable.
So let me repeat:
we can construct
a dependency graph as follows.
There is one node for each transaction,
and there is an edge from the first
to the second transaction,
but the second transaction never depends
on the first by a particular object--
and depends means there's either
write-read, a read-write,
or a write-write conflict.
And this dependency graph
completely determines, via cyclicity,
whether a schedule
is conflict serializable.
That means a schedule
is conflict serializable
if an only if its dependency
graph is acyclic.
Now there is a nice general technique
for determining conflict serializability,
or to actually guaranteeing
serializable schedules
that are also conflict serializable,
using locking.
For that I'll introduce you to
the Two-Phase Locking Protocol.
It works as follows--
Each transaction must obtain a read lock,
or so-called shared lock
on an object before it can read,
and then an exclusive, or write lock
on an object before it can write.
So the read lock is called shared lock
because if one transaction
has a read lock,
then a second transaction
can also get a read lock,
but if anybody has a read lock,
then nobody can get a write lock.
And if somebody gets a write lock
on something that is purposely unlocked,
an exclusive lock, it's exclusive,
and nobody else can read or write.
So these kinds of locks
basically will guarantee us
to avoid these write-write, read-write,
and write-read conflicts.
And the notion of shared lock
basically enables us
to have concurrent reads,
which are by themselves innocuous.
A transaction will have
a certain kind of lock grow phase,
where initially it can get
more and more locks,
up to a point where it decides
to do some more work,
and then maybe starts releasing locks,
but once it has released a single lock
it cannot get another lock.
For that reason you've got
so-called two-phases,
a first growth phase, where we only
monotonously add more locks,
but not remove any,
and later a release phase,
where we can only release locks,
but cannot get any further locks.
The Two-Phase Locking Protocol
is also abbreviated by 2PL,
we sometimes call it just 2PL.
There's an important modified version
of the Two-Phase Locking Protocol
called a Strict Two-Phase
Locking Protocol,
that works like 2PL, but in addition,
there's an additional constraint
that says that all locks
held by a transaction
are released all together at the time
the transaction completes.
That means the second phase,
of the release phase of
the Two-Phase Locking Protocol,
happens all of a sudden, at once.
So in a sense you don't need
a specific free-lock command,
but you can allocate more locks,
more locks, more locks,
you can do work, and at the point
you commit or abort,
all locks are automatically released.
And you don't do this by hand,
all of them are released
at the same point in time.
Now already the first protocol,
the 2PL protocol,
allows only schedules whose
precedence graph,
the dependency graph, is acyclic.
That means they're conflict
serializable and thus serializable.
So this locking protocol
guarantees serializability,
which is what we want, after all.
There is a reason for having
the strict two-phase locking protocol,
and that's it simplifies
transaction aborts.
So remember this notion
of cascading aborts.
If I have just two-phase locking,
not strict two-phase locking,
I might start releasing some locks
before I'm committing,
maybe long before I'm committing,
and during this time--
from the time I release my first lock
to the time I commit,
another transaction might
obtain that lock on this object,
and it might start, for example,
reading a value that I've already written.
So if I'm late to abort,
I would cause and force
the second transaction--
it hasn't read my value,
because I released the lock--
also to abort, so I can cause
cascading aborts.
On the other hand,
in strict two-phase locking,
there is no need for cascading aborts,
so handling aborts is much easier.
There is one thing to mention, though,
that in both cases,
even for strict two-phase locking,
but also for classical two-phase locking,
bad locks are possible,
because the growth phase,
where we allocate locks,
is not happening atomically,
at one point in time
like the release phase is
in strict two-phase locking.
That means, for example,
I might have two transactions,
where both try to allocate
two resources, A and B,
but the first transaction
allocates A first,
and then tries to allocate B,
and the second tries to allocate B first,
and then tries to allocate A.
So it could happen that both transactions
each have one object,
and try to wait for the other object,
which cannot be released
because these two transactions
wait individually for each other.
That means I've got kind of
the dining philosopher's problem here,
and I get a deadlock.
So we have to deal
with deadlocks separately,
and neither of these
two protocols avoids them.
There is basically two
important ways of doing this.
One is deadline detection,
the other one is deadlock prevention.
Deadlock detection, I can basically obtain
by yet another dependency graph.
So what I'm going to do is basically
I'm going to have, again,
a dependency graph with
the nodes and transactions,
and I'm going to have an edge
whenever one transaction
waits for an object that another
transaction already has allocated.
That means I'm going to draw an edge
from transaction T1 to transaction T2,
if T2 owns an object,
has a lock-in object,
that T1 also wants.
So I can put again a label on it,
for this object,
and that means basically
T1 will be blocked
until T2 releases this lock.
And of course, if I get a cycling,
only if I get a cycling in this graph,
I've got a deadlock.
So I can easily, while I lock,
create this dependency graph,
and then I get a cycle, I know
I have to do something about this.
What can I do?
Well, I could kill a transaction.
The idea is simple,
but let's look at an example.
This actually is slightly a big example,
illustrates maybe some other ideas,
as well, that we've discussed so far.
So we've got four transactions here,
and what you see is, again,
the read and write commands,
but now we've also explicitly
denoted locking commands.
There is the S of A, for example, in T1,
that actually creates a shared lock on A.
And the X of B in T2 creates
an exclusive lock on B.
Of course we have to assume
that these are possible,
otherwise they would not be executed,
or the transaction would have to fail.
So we see that we are creating
a shared lock for A, reading A in T1,
then we create an exclusive lock
for B to write,
and write, actually, in T2, for B.
Then we are going to shared lock
for C, in T3, and read C,
and next I will need to try to get
an exclusive lock on C in T2,
that means we plan to write.
Then we're going to try to get
an exclusive lock for B in T4,
and, finally, an exclusive
lock for A in T3.
So the dependency graph,
I'll show it to you first,
before we do this final operation
of getting exclusivity lock on A.
And what you see
is we'll have three edges.
There is an edge from T1 to T2,
because at the time we created
a shared lock for B in T1,
there was already an exclusive lock for B.
That means T1 would have to wait for T2.
So we make an arrow from T1 to T2,
because T1 has to wait for T2,
because of B,
it wants a lock at B,
but it cannot get it,
because right now T2 has a lock on B.
So T1 is right now blocked, basically,
until T2 releases the lock.
Now we also have an edge from T2 to T3,
because T2 tries to get
an exclusive lock on C
while T3 already has a shared lock on C.
That means T2 now gets blocked
until T3 releases the lock on C.
And then, in transaction T4
we tried to get an exclusive lock on B,
but T2 already has a lock on B,
actually an exclusive lock,
that means T4 is not blocked,
and waits for T2.
We have not reached a deadlock yet,
because T3 can still execute.
But now let's execute
this final operation,
trying to obtain
an exclusive lock on A in T3.
This will now make T3 wait for T1,
because T1 has a lock on A,
which means now that we've got
a cycle in the dependency graph:
T3 waits for T1, T1 waits for T2,
and T2 waits for T3,
and that's a deadlock,
so we have to do something.
We'll have to kill a transaction
to be able to continue.
There is also the possibility of avoiding
deadlocks, preventing deadlocks,
by using timestamps on transactions.
That means we could create,
at a time any transaction starts,
a timestamp, a start timestamp
for the transaction,
recording when it starts,
how old the transaction is,
and then essentially using this timestamp
to bring a greater notion
of fairness to transactions,
to avoid starvation.
A transaction that is older
might have higher priority than others,
and a transaction that is older
might get priority
to continue and finish
over other transactions.
There might be several strategies
that we could now enforce
to deal with this.
So let's assume that we've got
timestamps for each transaction,
noting down essentially the time,
logical or physical,
when the transaction started.
And this totally old transactions,
let's assume that.
First priority will be that
if Ti, transaction Ti,
has a higher priority, is maybe older,
then Ti will wait for Tj,
if Tj has a lock.
Otherwise, Ti would abort.
That means a high priority,
an older transaction,
will wait to get a lock,
while if a new transaction
tries to obtain a lock
that an older transaction already has,
it will get killed, so there will be
no blocking for that reason.
So that way, at some point
old transactions get really executed,
and don't get killed all the time
that a new transaction comes
and wants something from them.
The alternative would be
the second strategy,
where if Ti has a higher priority,
then Tj aborts,
and otherwise Ti waits.
So that means sometimes
we start transactions, they have to--
again, from scratch--
continue doing everything
as they did before,
in the same order, basically,
as they've executed so far,
and just the order in which
locks are trying
to be obtained is different,
and ultimately,
everybody gets their turn,
and the highest priority
transactions, so to say,
are sure to ultimately finish and succeed.
Now here's a problem.
If we relax the assumption
that the database is just static,
and a fixed collection of objects
that never change,
then two-phase locking,
even strict two-phase locking
do not ensure serializability.
So if you allow to insert new items,
or delete items,
then we are getting into trouble.
And to illustrate this,
here's an example.
Let's look at the schedule
at the bottom of this slide.
First, let's ignore
these little stars and primes.
So in that sense
it's a classical schedule.
Think of this I of A and D of B, which
are going to be insertions and deletions,
just as writes, for now.
So what happens?
We are trying to get a shared read lock
and read A, in transaction T1,
then I'm trying to write A and write B.
And then, again, we want to read B in T1,
and, finally, write C in T1.
We have a read-write
dependency from T1 to T2,
and a write-read dependency
from T2 to T1.
And I just added this write C in T1
to make it not a completely
read-only transaction.
Well, obviously that's one of these
classical and nested scenarios,
where there is no serial schedule
that's equivalent.
We cannot move T2 first, because of
that read-write dependency on A,
and we cannot move T1 first, because of
that write-read dependency on B.
So this is obviously not conflict
serializable, and thus not serializable.
We will detect this using locking.
But now what happens if we are not
doing any more writes in T2,
but we're actually doing
insertions and deletions?
Now here's the example.
In this example I use a database schema
where we've got the database
of a sailing club,
and in this database we have
records for each sailor in the club,
and each sailor has an age,
among the things that are stored of him,
and the rating--how good a sailor he is,
or something like that.
So now let's try to do
the following thing.
T1 tries to lock all the pages
containing sailor records
with a shared lock, a read lock,
just to find the oldest
sailor of rating = 1.
So what I'm doing is basically with
this A* in my schedule below
is I'm trying to lock all the A records,
the A records being
the sailors with rating = 1.
I do this just to be able
to read them, to find out
who's the oldest sailor
among those with rating = 1.
Next, we're going to insert
a new sailor of rating = 1,
an even older one, in T2.
So this sailor should have been the winner
if T2 had happened before T1.
But since T1 happens before T2, initially,
we'll not find this oldest sailor,
we find only the second-oldest sailor,
the oldest sailor that was already
in the database before this new insert.
The next step is that T2 also tries
to delete the oldest sailor of rating = 2,
and we call this oldest sailor
of rating = 2 "B".
After that T1 tries to lock
all the pages, all the B pages,
all the pages that are rating = 2,
and find the oldest sailor.
Well, you'll find only
the second-oldest sailor,
because the oldest sailor of rating = 2
has just been deleted.
So we have these dependencies,
just like we have classical
read-write conflicts,
although there are no objects
appearing/disappearing.
So that's a problem, because we cannot
easily modify our technique
so far to deal with this.
There are a number of techniques
to deal with this in database systems,
and I'll just mention them briefly,
the two main techniques.
The first one is index locking.
Just imagine you've got
an index structure over these items,
particularly an index structure
that finds the sailors by rating,
and maybe even sorted
by age within the rating.
And it's a dense index, like a B-tree,
such that it covers
all the values in our database.
So I can, for example,
then lock a node in that tree index,
and if I force my database system
to always access the data
through this index,
and no other way,
that means if anybody
wants to see the data
they have to search the values
through that index--
locking a node that basically
locks an entire range of values,
maybe all the values that correspond
to that particular rating,
guarantees us
that entire range of ratings,
also future values of that rating,
which would have to be inserted
in this B-tree at this point,
if we would insert them, are locked.
So using an index structure I can
lock a particular predicate, so to say,
and all future tuples
that are not in there yet either.
So that's one way of doing this,
but it of course requires that
there is a suitable index structure,
and that it's used as
the only way to access the data
so that you don't do anything wrong,
because then you're going
to lock the index structure,
or part of the index structure,
right in the data itself.
The alternative would be
predicate locking.
That means basically we're going
to have some kind of store
that remembers which kind
of conditions are on the data
we have used to search for,
for example--
For example, if we remember
that somebody looked
for all of the people of rating = 1,
and if I now want to insert
somebody of rating = 1
I will be locked until
that first transaction is finished.
This of course is complicated,
because it means--
it requires every time
a static analysis of the queries.
And that has a certain kind
of complexity, of course,
and challenges associated with it.
To finalize this video,
just to make you remember
that conflict serializability
is not the same as serializability.
Whenever a schedule
is conflict serializable,
it is also serializable,
so we are safe.
But there are serializable schedules
that we don't find conflict serializable.
That means there are schedules
that we might lock up,
and say they are bad,
but they're actually okay.
Nothing bad can happen.
Why is that?
Well, in general, serializability
is an undecidable condition
of sets of transactional programs,
and we have no chance of doing this
automatically, finding it out.
And conflict serializability
is a very easy syntactic condition,
so there is no chance,
there is no hope
that conflict serializability guarantees
or covers all of serializability.
That said, here's a notion of
a special class of serializable schedules
that is more general
than conflict serializability,
but it's actually still not
all of serializability.
This condition, it's a semantic condition,
it's more complicated,
more difficult to check,
more computationally expensive
to check than conflict serializability,
but it is actually still decidable,
I think it is NP-complete.
So this is not covering serializability,
it's a class strictly in between.
Everything that is view serializable
is also serializable,
and everything that
is conflict serializable
is also view serializable.
But there are view serializable problems
which are not conflict serializable,
and there are serializable problems
which are not view serializable.
So how does it work?
Well, I can talk about two schedules
being view equivalent,
which implies equivalence,
but not conflict equivalence.
If whenever some transaction Ti
reads the initial value of A in S1,
then Ti also reads the initial value of A,
some object A, in S2.
That means the initial values
of each object
are read by the same guys,
in both schedules.
What does initial value mean?
Well we imagine that there is
some consistent database,
there are no transactions running yet,
and now the schedule starts,
and several transactions
start in some order,
and initial value means
the state of the database
just before any
of these transactions started.
Now the second condition
is one of something classical--
if Ti reads the value of some object A
written by Tj before, in S1,
then Ti also reads the value
written by Tj in S2.
And finally, the corresponding
condition for final values,
final values being the values
that you will have in the database
after all these transactions commit,
so if Ti writes--transaction Ti writes
the final value of A in S1,
then it also writes
the final value of A in S2,
and not somebody else,
not another transaction.
So let's understand this...
Here are two examples, below.
The left schedule has three transactions,
T1 reading A,
T2 writing A,
and then T1 reading A again.
And, finally, T3 writing A.
Now, if we look at this,
this schedule is not
conflict serializable,
because obviously,
if I just look at T1 and T2,
there is a read-write conflict
from T1 to T2,
and a write-write conflict from T2 to T1.
So there's a cycle of dependency graph,
so this one is not conflict serializable.
Now if we look at this
entire schedule, though,
it is equivalent to the schedule
on the right side.
Look at the schedule on
the right, it's the same,
just that these two writes,
of A in T1 and T2
have been reordered,
and now it's actually
a completely serial schedule.
T1, as given, finishes before T2 starts,
T2 finishes before T3 starts.
So this right schedule is serial,
and that's also serializable.
The left schedule
is equivalent to it...why?
Well, yes, if I would look
only into section T1-T2
it wouldn't be equivalent,
but we are reordering
this write of A of T1 and T2,
but what we write is anyway unimportant,
because T3 will overwrite it, in the end.
In both schedules, the final write
of object A is done by T3,
and that means whoever
wrote, in which order
before this particular value,
it doesn't matter.
So that connects basically
the second and the third condition
of this definition.
That means if the schedule consisted only
of the first and the second transactions,
but not of the third,
then we would indeed
have a non-serializable schedule,
but adding another transaction,
that basically makes certain
write orders unimportant,
enables us to see
that this particular
schedule on the left-hand side
is equivalent to a serial schedule,
the one given on the right-hand side.
And we can find this using this view
equivalent definitions in this case.
So this is indeed a more general
condition, a conflict serializable.
Serializability needs and it still
guaranteed serializability.
But remember, there are
yet other serializable transactions
that are not covered
by view serializability.
That concludes this video,
and what we've done, in summary,
is we have talked about locking techniques
for ensuring serializability.
So locking is a very natural way
to do this in systems, obviously,
and we're familiar with locking from
basic systems programming courses,
and there's no magic to it.
But one thing to keep in mind
is there are also other techniques
that are not based on locking.
Actually nowadays, in current, modern
database management systems,
locking is not the default technique
for achieving what people usually
use in concurrency control,
and I'll go over this
in more detail in a different video.
But locking, in a strong sense,
connects to conflict serializability,
which is an important definition,
purely syntactically enforceable
by a dependency graph.
And you've also seen that
it is not all of serializability,
there is more to it.