Optimistic concurrency control
is a technique for ensuring
the serializability of
concurrent transactions.
In that sense, it's an alternative
to lock-based concurrency control.
Optimistic concurrency control
basically assumes that you can be lucky,
and nothing is to be done to make sure
that consistency is maintained
in the face of concurrency.
That usually works well,
when there's relatively little overlap
between the object request
that's used and changed
by different transactions.
It also tends to work better
if there is relatively little work
to be done in transactions.
In that sense, it is
more popular, and useful
in the context of, for example,
transaction memory,
than it is in scenarios where
major, large, bulk changes
are to be made,
on large amounts of data,
as is often the case in database systems.
Locking, as we've discussed,
is a conservative approach
to ensuring serializability in which
conflicts are prevented a priori.
They cannot arise because
locking ensures they don't arise.
The disadvantages of this are that,
a) There isn't a overhead lock management.
We need data structures,
we need machinery,
inside our system.
There are potentially deadlocks,
which we have to deal with,
or we have to avoid them,
which needs more infrastructure.
And, lock contention
can become a big issue
if there are some objects
which are heavily under demand,
and each transaction
wants them, so to say,
and then concurrency
really deteriorates greatly.
However, if conflicts are rare,
then we could basically, by default,
assume that no conflict arises.
We act as if no conflict arises,
complete our transactions,
and then, just at the end,
check that everything goes fine,
when we commit.
That's the basic idea
of optimistic concurrency control.
We act as if no conflicts can arise,
we do our work,
we record it in, so to say,
a temporary copy of the database,
then we check,
when we want to commit,
and only if you want to commit.
If you decide to abort, you can just
throw away the copy of the database,
and don't even have to think about
whether there was any
concurrent control issue.
If you want to commit, we have
to check that everything went fine,
and then we can commit.
Of course, in practice we have to avoid
naively copying a big piece
of the database, and doing it smarter,
but conceptually the idea is
that optimistic concurrency control
works on a copy of the database.
So the basic classical paper
on optimistic concurrency control
was by Kung and Robinson,
and thus this model is called that way.
So the idea there is that each transaction
is executed in three phases.
The first phase is
the so-called Read phase.
This phase actually performs the reads
and the writes of the transaction,
but it works on a copy of the database.
That means when you start transaction
we create a snapshot,
we work, reading and writing
on that database,
and only then, when somebody
says, "and now, please commit,"
we start validating our changes,
which validating this transaction
can indeed commit
with respect to other
transactions in the schedule.
And only then,
if we decide everything is fine,
nothing bad had happened,
we can actually do a write
of all the changes
we've done to the database,
to the global copy of the database.
Of course other snapshots
that have been great
optimistic concurrency control
for other transactions,
they would still start from
that old version of the database,
so we have to make sure,
in our protocol,
in validation, in particular,
that nothing bad arises from this fact.
So, how do we perform validation?
We are going to do this
by making three tests,
and these tests are going to be sufficient
to ensure that no conflict occurred,
and that serializability is guaranteed.
To do this, we assign
each transaction a numerical ID,
a timestamp,
meaning a logical timestamp,
the order in which
the transaction was started
in the whole history
of transactions in this system.
The transaction ID's are assigned
at the end of the read phase, actually,
just before the validation begins.
We're going to talk about the notion
of ReadSet and WriteSet
of a transaction,
which is just the objects that are read
or written by the transaction.
So the first of these
three tests is as follows--
it's the most conservative test,
and it's also easy to check, basically.
So here you see
two transactions, Ti and Tj.
Transaction Ti started before Tj.
In this case it has a lower timestamp.
Each of those two transactions
have three phases:
the Read, the Validation,
and the Write phase.
Now let's assume that Ti
completely finishes before Tj begins.
Well, in a sense, we don't really
actually have to refer to this transaction
in validation if it has completely
finalized before Tj begins,
because in a sense the start state
of Tj is the final state of Ti,
and there's no overlap.
The second test is--well, we can
actually deal with some overlap--
so Tj starts before Ti
completely finishes,
but we know that Ti has completed
before the Write phase of Tj begins.
In that case what we have to do
is we have to ensure
that the WriteSet of the first transaction
does not intersect
with the ReadSet of the second.
That means what Tj does
does not overlap,
does not depend on what Ti did.
That means you're going to write,
and you're going to potentially overwrite
values that have been written by Ti,
but it doesn't hurt,
because how we overwrite them
does not depend on what Ti did,
and since the end of Write phase of Tj
is completely after Ti,
we are ensured that we're not going
to have any overlaps between writes.
So the last write,
the winner so to say,
is going to be the second transaction,
it's going to get to overwrite everything.
And conceptually this means that we have
serialized Ti completely before Tj.
And the first check,
is the most powerful check, so to say,
the least conservative.
We're allowed to do this even if
the only condition that must hold
is that Ti completes
its Read phase before Tj does,
that basically is some protection of two
always completes this phase
before the other.
So let's just assume Ti is this one.
So Ti completes
its Read phase before Tj does,
and now they have
overlapping validation phases.
And what we're going to require
is that the second transaction,
the one with the younger timestamp,
which is assigned at the end
of the Read phase, if you remember, Tj.
It will have to check that
the WriteSet of Ti
does not intersect with its ReadSet,
and the two WriteSets of Ti
actually don't intersect.
In that case, well, nothing
that Tj does depends on Ti,
and again, we allow to commit Ti.
There are no dirty reads,
and Ti cannot overwrite
any things that Tj does,
because there's no overlap
of writes in the WriteSets.
So because there is
no overlap in the WriteSets,
we are guaranteed
that we don't have to require
that the Write phase
is a distinct [inaudible],
as was the case in the second test.
Now let's do an example.
We have seen this example before.
The overlap looked different,
because right now, conceptually,
we cannot talk about schedules anymore,
that strictly one happens
before the other,
but in a sense, a priori,
things start at the same time,
there is real overlap and true concurrency
of individual atomic actions
inside two transactions as well.
So we have got Ti, and T1 and T2,
and T1 starts before T2.
T1 reads and writes A and B,
and T1 reads and writes A and B.
Of course this is not going
to work out if there is overlap.
We're not going to be able
to conceptually serialize
the two transactions completely,
if the reads and writes of B of T1
happen after the reads and writes
that happen in T2.
I've not shown it like this
in this example,
because conceptually T1
is not getting blocked
as things happen in T2,
in the optimistic concurrency
control model,
but what I've written down is
there is this true overlap,
that T1 tries to write something
while T2 already does something.
So what happens in this case?
What happens in this case is that--
Let's assume the Read phase of T1
is completed before the Read phase of T2.
So we can say that T1's timestamp is 1,
and T2's timestamp is 2.
So we're going to have
to worry about the validation
of the second transaction, T2,
what's going to happen.
Well, the first test fails,
because these are overlapping.
The second transaction has started
before the first has completed.
The second test fails
because the WriteSet of T1,
and the ReadSet of T2 overlap,
and the third test fails
for the same reason, among others.
That means that T2 has to get restarted
once T1 has completely finished.
But observe here that...
I've been a bit strange here,
in my schedule.
I've really now had like R of B,
read of R at B, and read of A
completely overlap,
happen at the same point in time,
something that we didn't look at before.
Conceptually, I could argue that this
is actually a serializable schedule,
because I could actually
serialize T1 completely before T2,
if things are really like this.
If, on the other hand,
the write of B of T1
is really slightly after
the read of B of T2, for example,
then the situation
is not like this anymore,
then it's truly not serializable.
But what you're seeing is that
if the optimistic concurrency
control algorithm is succeeding,
and we indeed
have ensured serializability,
but vice versa, again,
there might be serializable schedules,
like this one, where optimistic
concurrency control fails.
So, again, it's not a complete mechanism,
just like conflict serializability,
what the notion of serializability,
that optimistic concurrency
control covers,
is not all of serializability.
A few words on validation.
It's important that the Write phase
happens in a critical section,
that means it happens atomically.
Well, what have you achieved this way?
I'm talking about atomicity
on a lower level of abstraction,
it's not on the level of transactions
anymore, it's inside the system,
the system has to commit
all of these changes
that a single transaction makes,
together, atomically,
before anything else can happen again.
You might say, well, one of the main goals
of optimistic concurrency control
is ensuring atomicity,
and now we are requiring atomicity
to make the protocol work.
Well, I would argue,
at least in a non-distributive scenario,
we have achieved something,
because all we have to do now
is use the operating system's machinery
for ensuring a critical section here.
But we have a clean semantics
for concurrent transactions,
which [allow us to] execute
the concurrency concurrently,
I'm assuming now a single threaded
model, maybe, a single core machine.
We have gotten the semantics
of the transactions right,
but we need some low-level machinery
to ensure atomicity of multiple steps.
So, now the Write phase
has to happen in a critical section.
This is not to be
underestimated in its cost,
because, on one hand,
we have split the work
done by a transaction into three phases:
The Read phase, where the program runs,
the application program runs,
maybe [user interaction is done],
humans are involved,
things are very slow,
and this is not our problem anymore,
we're not waiting for this
in our transaction management system.
We can do a lot of work
with other transactions
while, maybe, the application [inaudible]
waits for the user input.
The validation can also be done
with some [overlapping other] parts
of the transaction workload.
Any Write section has to happen alone;
nothing else must happen
in the system during this.
Otherwise, we can corrupt,
so to say, our database.
For certain kinds of transactions,
this is not a good solution.
Just imagine a small transaction
that does a massive bulk update
that says, you know,
update as select, in SQL.
That means we're going to change
many, many objects
by a transaction workload
that is going to be
very little work from the front,
it means the Read phase
is going to be very fast,
the Validation phase may be fast,
but in the Write phase
touches many, many objects.
Most of the work is actually done in a way
that there's no concurrency possible.
That is the main disadvantage
of optimistic concurrency
control, potentially.
Of course, if you've got
a read-only transaction,
then you don't need
a critical section for this one,
and in some contexts,
some workloads,
many transactions are actually read-only.