In this video, we discuss
timestamp concurrency control,
which is yet another technique
for achieving serializability
in transactions.
The basic idea is that we assign each
object in the database, conceptually,
a read timestamp which indicates
when it was last read,
and a write timestamp which
indicates when it was last written.
Furthermore, each
transaction has a timestamp
which indicates when it was started.
We can then use these
transaction and object timestamps,
compare those, to detect
any problem that has been arising.
So in particular,
if two actions of two
transactions are conflicts,
and one transaction--
the first transaction has
a smaller timestamp the second,
then we could say that we
restart the second transaction
to avoid the conflict.
And we can use the read
and write timestamps
to detect these conflicts sufficiently.
That means, for the purpose
of detecting conflicts,
we can do this in constant time
by just comparing read
and write timestamps,
and we don't have to look at
the history of the transactions so far,
to detect that a conflict arose.
The protocol, or the algorithm,
is actually somewhat complicated.
So we will go with this first,
basically just saying what happens,
and later we will execute an example,
seeing and understanding better
why everything is the way it is.
So let's first look at the case
that a transaction wants
to read an object O.
The case is as follows.
If timestamp of the transaction
is less than the write
timestamp of that object,
that means conceptually,
the object has been
written by a transaction
that is coming later--
is to be serialized later
than our transaction T,
then we cannot read
the appropriate value.
We can only read a new value
that is too new, so to say.
So this violates the timestamp order of T,
and we have to basically
restart this transaction anew.
That means we are always
going to try to basically,
serialize the transactions
in the order of the timestamp order--
in the order in which they began.
And when we have only
an object at our disposal
that has been written
by a new transaction,
and want to read it, we can't.
However, if the timestamp
of our transaction
is greater or equal to the write
timestamp of that object,
we can read it.
In that case, we update the read
timestamp of that object
to the maximum, so to say,
of the timestamp of this transaction,
and the old read timestamp.
These timestamps have to also
be recorded on disks appropriately,
to deal with crashes
and be able to recover.
Of course this,
and the fact that we have to
restart transactions from time to time,
kind of puts the cost of transaction
management in this protocol.
Now when transaction T
wants to write an object O,
then we do the following comparison.
If the timestamp of that transaction
is less than the read
timestamp of the object,
that means that
the transaction is older
than the transaction that has
read this object already.
Then this violates timestamp order.
So to say, we cannot write
this object in this older transaction,
because a newer transaction
has already read that value.
So if you changed it,
this new transaction should have
read another value, and it didn't.
So we are not allowed to do this.
So in this case, we have to abort T.
Otherwise, if the transaction timestamp
is less than the write timestamp of O,
that means we have--
we are trying to write now,
before another transaction--
a later transaction overwrites it.
But we have already decided
what to do in this later transaction.
We have already written this new value.
Then this conceptually,
violates the timestamp order,
but it doesn't matter, because
the value of T1 to insert now,
is going to be overwritten later anyway.
It has been overwritten already,
so what we can just do is,
ignore this write.
We just drop the write,
and everything is going to be correct,
because that later transaction
has written a value
that would overwrite our value
if we have done it in proper order.
So if you don't write it now,
we are doing the right thing.
That's actually called
a Thomas Write Rule.
When otherwise, we are allowed
to write this object and of course,
have to update the write
timestamp properly,
to this new transaction.
Now let's look at an example.
In this example,
we've got two transactions,
T1 and T2.
And T1 consists of the operations:
read A, write A.
Read A in transaction T2,
writes A after the first operation of T1.
We think of the database
to be in intial state,
timestamp zero,
and the read and write
timestamps of object A
have been set up accordingly.
They have initially, state zero.
Now let's execute this protocol.
The first operation is R(A)
in transaction T1.
The read timestamp of A is zero.
Since one is greater than zero,
we are in the second case of read.
The read protocol is here.
And that means we are allowed to read O,
and we have to set the
read timestamp to one.
Now we get to the second operation.
The write of A in transaction T2.
So TS(T) is 2.
The read timestamp is one.
We are not having to abort.
And the write timestamp is still zero,
so with this case, we also go over.
So we're allowed
to write O in transaction T,
and we also have to write
the write timestamp
so it becomes two.
That means the read
timestamp is still one.
Next, we are going to try
to write A in transaction T1.
In this case, the read
timestamp will still be one,
so we are not going to the first case.
However, we have to go
into the second case.
The transaction's timestamp is one,
and the write timestamp is two.
So this violates the timestamp order,
but we can apply the Thomas Write Rule
and just basically drop this operation.
We don't execute it,
because there is a newer transaction T2,
that written the value that
conceptually, will be written later.
It would overwrite this value.
So we don't write this value
in T1 in the first case.
So in this case we don't do anything,
we also don't update the timestamps.
Finally, we read A in transaction T1--
or try to do this.
So the timestamp
of this transaction is one,
and the write timestamp
of the object is two.
So we are in the first case,
and this violates
the timestamp order of T.
So we have to abort the transaction
and restart it anew,
with a larger timestamp.
That means we abort transaction T1,
and we restart is as transaction T3.
That means we are going
to basically start T3 as
R(A), W(A), and R(B).
Let's assume that the
transaction variable of T2
was really just his write.
So we could for example, now commit.
And conceptually, everything
that happens in transaction T3,
is serially after everything
that happened before,
and ultimately T3 will also succeed,
unless something happened
with later coming transactions
that for example, transaction T4.
So that's the basic idea of this protocol.
So that's it for timestamp
concurrency control.
It's a clever protocol.
It uses various kinds
of timestamps to do its job,
compared to lock-based
concurrency control.
We have no deadlocks.
On the other hand, there's a drawback.
We might sometimes abort transactions,
which doesn't happen
in lock-based protocols,
unless there is deadlocks.
Compared to optimistic
concurrency control,
we have a clever way
of making, so to say,
dealing with versions more cheaply,
rather than having to deal
with copies of the data,
that we try our protocol
optimistically on,
we can work with a single
version of that data,
and just mantain consistency,
so to say, via these timestamps.