In this video, we discuss
multiversion concurrency control
which is yet another concurrency control
for achieving serializability.
So the basic idea is that you can have
multiple versions of objects
that means we create copies
when we need them
to be able to make sure that
there is an appropriate copy version
for each relevant transaction
still alive in the system,
so that transactions
can find the object it needs.
So in this way, we can basically
create something
like efficient snapshots of the databases
as it’s also needed, necessary,
inside the optimistic
concurrency control.
So we will have in channel a version pool
and the versions are chained
so that the new versions chain
backwards to the older versions
and we can find which older
versions exist.
And there is a main segment
that tells me about
what the current versions
of DB objects is for new transactions.
Each version of an object
has again a timestamp,
a write timestamp and a read timestamp
just as in timestamp concurrency control.
Transactions are classified
either as readers or writers.
The readers can only read.
The writers can read and write.
And the transaction
has to be declaring its start time
whether is a reader or a writer.
The fact is just simply that if you know
that a transaction will never write,
we can deliver it more efficiently.
And in particular, readers are always
allowed to proceed, while in general,
sometimes we might have to terminate
and restart writers or block them.
The protocol again
is somewhat complicated
and we’re going to discuss the cases
of readers and writers individually.
A reader transaction works as follows.
For each object to be read,
it finds the newest version
in the version pool with the write
timestamp of that object
being less than our timestamp.
That means, assuming that
we want to read this object,
we’re not going to update
its write timestamp
and we’re going to find the newest
write timestamp of any transaction
that is older than my transaction.
Again, as in timestamp
concurrency of control protocols,
we’re going to try to serialize
the transactions by transaction timestamp.
That means we want to serialize them
in such a way that an older transaction
is serialized before a new transaction.
And of course in a serial
orders transaction,
my transaction can only read
older transaction’s output.
I will never have to read my own
transaction’s output
because I’m not a writer.
So I’m reading the most recent
all the transactions write.
And you have to have such an object
in the database.
For a writer transaction, reading works
just as for reader transactions.
And to write we find the newest
version of the object
such that its write timestamp is less than
timestamp of the transaction.
And if the read timestamp of the object
is less than the timestamp’s transaction,
we make a copy of that object
with the write timestamp of this copy
being the timestamps of the transaction.
That means you create a new version
especially for that transaction
and potentially later transactions,
newer transactions
that might also want to read it.
The read timestamp is also going to be
the timestamp of the transaction.
And otherwise, if the condition
read timestamp of the object
is not less than the timestamp
of the transaction,
we have to reject the write.
Now let’s go over an example.
We’ve got two transactions here,
T1 and T2.
T1 starts by reading A.
Then T2 reads B.
Then T1 writes B.
And finally T2 writes A.
The two objects A and B have initial
read and write timestamps zero.
That’s my initial version of the database.
And the version zero of the database
has two values for A and B,
15 and six let's say.
So we start by reading A.
What does this involve?
We are going to look up
the newest value for A
who’s timestamp is older than
transaction T1.
That’s of course value 15 in V0.
We’re going to update
the read timestamp to one.
Next we’re going to try to read B.
For that we look for the newest
version of the database
for this object that is older than
the two which is also V0.
So we get value six.
And we have to update the read
timestamp to two.
Next we’re trying to write B.
So there we make a comparison
between the transaction’s timestamp one
and the read timestamp of B which is two.
According to the rules
we had on the previous slide,
we’re not allowed to do this write because
we’re going to try backdate this write.
We are trying to write to an object
while we already have read from an object
that should have been newer.
And this object didn’t exist.
That means the read of B in the two
should have read this value
that we’re now going to write.
We didn’t do this,
so we’re not allowed to do this.
That means we’re not allowed
to perform this operation
and we will exit this transaction.
Now let’s look at the second example.
This is the same example again.
Let’s modify this by say, writing B here
and reading B here instead.
So we’ve reordered
the second and third operation
giving them to the different transactions.
Now let’s start again.
We’re going to first read A
and we’re allowed to do this.
We’re reading the initial value, 15.
And we’re going to update
the read timestamp of A to one.
Next we’re going to try to write B.
So what this take?
We’r going to check and realize
that B is still virgin.
There is nothing done to this yet.
We are going to be allowed to write B.
For that, we have to create a new version.
An object V2.
And this value will be for B,
whatever we write here.
Let’s say we write seven.
Now we also have to update
the read timestamp
and the write timestamp to two.
Next we’re going to try to read B.
Well, to read B, we have to find
the oldest version of B
that is newer than transaction T1.
And that’s actually fifteen again.
That means we read 15 again
despite the fact
that B has been updated,
however, in a new version.
So that’s the true value of multiversion
concurrency control.
We can deal with different versions.
We can serialize T1 before T2.
That was a decision we made
at transaction start time
by giving timestamps to the transactions.
We can do this using versions.
And we’re allowed to continue here.
So finally,
we’re going to try to write A.
And for this we have to compare
the read timestamp of A
which is one with the timestamp
that was action two
and since two is greater than one,
we’re allowed to write this value here.
We’re going to write some value,
let’s say 16 in version two.
And now we can actually
commit T1 before T2.
Multiversion concurrency control
in summary,
is a clever way of dealing with
multiple versions.
So we can for example
deal with the snapshots if you like
that we also used optimistic
concurrency control.
It’s efficient. We don’t copy
the emptied out database,
we only copy stuff
that we really need to copy.
And we have a way of keeping track
of all the different versions
of the objects.