In this video, we discuss
snapshot isolation
which is yet another formalism
for achieving a notion
of concurrency control.
Before we go there, however,
let's look at transaction support
in standard SQL-92.
Inside there, we actually
have four different,
so-called, isolation levels.
Which you can actually
pick and choose
when you start a transaction.
And they have names,
they are called:
read uncommitted, read committed,
repeatable reads, and serializable.
And they are subsequently
stronger and stronger,
up to serializable,
which is meant to
guarantee serializability
in the way that we have defined it.
They can be characterized,
or classified
by which anomalies they avoid,
and you can see that the weakest,
the uncommitted,
avoids none of these
three classic anomalies,
dirty reads, unrepeatable reads,
and phantom problem,
while serializability,
it does all of them.
There is however a problem,
in a sense that is,
the classical standard defines,
essentially, serializability
via an implementation.
Which is based on locking.
That means if you choose
to try to achieve
another implementation
using different techniques,
you might be wrong.
And this has actually happened
in real, popular database systems.
Particularly, snapshot
isolation is a technique
that is meant to achieve
serializability,
but actually does not.
This was not always clear.
However, it is actually used
and implemented in
major database systems like Oracle,
Microsoft SQL Server, and Postgres.
So if you studied transaction
in Oracle for example,
and you set isolation level
to serializable,
you do no guarantee serializability.
And there anomalies that can still happen.
However, that is called
serializable in these systems.
There is actually a patch that somewhat
gracefully allows us to modify
snapshot isolation into something
that actually guarantees serializability.
And that has recently
been implemented in Postgres.
So nowadays,
different from earlier versions,
when you use Postgres,
and you use serializable isolation level,
you really guarantee serializability.
By default.
You can still turn it off, and get
the old notion of serializability.
So how does snapshot isolation work?
Conceptually, a transaction
works on a copy
made by the transaction at start time.
So in that sense, it is like
multi-level concurrency control,
conceptually,
and it's like optimistic
concurrency control.
Of course, in practice,
you don't want to implement
copying of the entire database,
by really copying it,
but what you want to do is,
you want to have a multi-version
concurrency control style scheme
where you only copy objects
that are getting modified.
And this method, of course,
guarantees that reads in a transaction
see a consistent version of the database.
Namely, the consistent
version of the database
at the time the transaction started.
By "consistency," I'm a bit sloppy,
because, as I said,
conceptually, we think of consistency
only being guaranteed by serializability
which is not guaranteed
by snapshot isolation.
So of course, in a sense,
snapshot isolation
can corrupt our database,
and then we don't see, after,
all the transactions
that have been committed,
and we start a new one,
a consistent version of the database.
But let's ignore this.
Let's assume there are
no transactions yet.
The database is consistent by
the field,
And now we populate the database,
and we only, in that transaction,
see the database as copied,
or as modified by us.
Other modifications
work on different copies,
and don't affect what we see
in our transaction.
Now, committing is only allowed
if there is no updates of this transaction
that conflict with updates made
since the start of the snapshot.
That means by other transactions.
And that can, of course, be verified
by something like write sets,
as in optimistic concurrency control.
Now, unfortunately, this does not
guarantee serializability,
and here's a COUNT example.
And this kind of COUNT example
is called a write skew anomaly.
So here we've got two transactions:
T1 and T2.
And T1 reads A, and T2 reads B.
Then T1 writes B, and T2 writes A.
These two transactions
have no overlap in their write sets.
That means the condition
that is required
by snapshot isolation
is actually ensured,
and these two transactions
are allowed to commit.
However, there is no
equivalency of the schedule.
That's a problem, of course.
In a sense,
snapshot isolation is related
to optimistic concurrency control,
in that, conceptually, snapshots
are created at transaction start time,
and there is an analysis phase.
Which, a bit like in
optimistic concurrency control,
looks at what has happened,
and then decides whether the transaction
can actually commit or not.
And if it commits,
it conceptually writes,
at the time of the commit,
the data back into the database.
From its copy.
In a different way,
different sense,
it's also similar to
multi-version concurrency control.
And you can think of multi-version
concurrency control
as a way of implementing
snapshot isolation.
Or a weakened version of
multi-version concurrency control
where write-read conflicts
are not properly caught,
is someway that corresponds
to snapshot isolation.
But, of course, in snapshot isolation,
we don't have to maintain
a read and write time stamp,
which is basically the reason, arguably,
why one might say,
you could use snapshot isolation.
Another argument would be
that people were not aware
that snapshot isolation
doesn't guarantee serializability,
when they chose to implement it.
So it's important to understand
that snapshot isolation
does not use locks a priori.
So you mustn't equate concurrency
control with locking in databases.
There is techniques,
and they absolutely don't use locking.
However, that said,
there is systems that use
snapshot isolation,
nevertheless, have locks
for other reasons.
For example, for supporting
distributed database transactions.
So it's important to understand
snapshot isolation,
because it has its pitfalls.
It doesn't guarantee serializability,
and it's actually,
essentially, the dominating method
in real-world database systems.