Let's now look at the case
of distributed transactions.
Our model is as follows:
We assume there is multiple database
servers that can talk to each other.
In a network.
There is no replication.
That means each database object
is on one server only.
And transactions access objects
on multiple servers, in general.
That means a transaction will
probably originate from one client,
that communicates via some middleware,
with, by default, maybe one machine,
but potentially several of these
database servers.
A transaction can involve several objects
that are read or written,
and the database servers
have to figure out among themselves
how to properly execute
these transactions.
There is a number of issues
that we have to look at.
The first one is, how to achieve,
so to say, serializability.
One way to do this is by locking.
That's probably the simplest form.
And what one could do is to use
a global version of two-phase locking.
What would that mean?
That would mean that there is
maybe a single dedicated server
that globally maintains locks
for all the objects of all the machines,
and executes a classical
two-phase locking protocol.
Alternatively, one could have
some clever scheme
of not leaving this
to a single node,
but achieving the same
performance behavior.
Alternatively, we could simply use
local, strict two-phase locking
on each side.
That means strict, rather than classical
two-phase locking, where all the locks
have to be released together
at commit time, and not before.
If you do that, actually it's sufficient
to do locking on each node,
on each so, individually,
and overall, serializability
will be maintained.
Let's first see why,
if you would locally use
two-phase locking,
rather than strict two-phase locking,
that would not be enough.
So here's an example.
I have shown you two transactions.
T1, and T2.
And there is two database objects
that you care about.
Well actually database object A
is stored at the first machine,
which is machine number 1,
and object B is stored
and maintained by machine 2.
So, transaction T1 first greets object A,
then transaction T2 writes object A,
then transaction T2 reads object B,
and finally, transaction T2,
writes object B.
If you now ignore this allocation,
that A is at node 1,
and B is at node 2,
we can really see that classical example
of a non-serializable transaction.
We've got a read-write
conflict from T1 to T2,
and a read-write
conflict from T2 to T1.
So there's a cycle,
this transaction schedule
is not conflict serializable,
and it's actually also not serializable.
However, if we look at individual nodes,
maintaining ANP respectively,
we could do an extreme thing
and could locally, at each node,
think of each of these individual
operations as the transaction.
That means, from the viewpoint of node 1,
it sees an operation that T1 executes,
that asks for a reading of A.
And later it sees
transaction T2 writing A.
But then there's nothing else left,
there's no more work to be done
for either transaction.
So we could actually think of,
locally, if locking and unlocking
are completely maintained
by the database system,
that since there is no more
work to be done,
this transaction, T1 for example,
is finished after the first operation,
and we can start unlocking this object A.
Which would then immediately allow us
to get a write-lock on object A
for transaction T2.
And the same thing on the second node.
And of course, overall,
this leads to something that looks like
four different transactions,
T1 on the first node,
T1 on the second node,
T2 on the first node,
and T2 on the second node.
Of course, the semantic is not the same,
and this is not correct.
So this is a consequence of basically,
unlocking as soon as,
from the viewpoint of a node,
nothing more needs to be done
in this transaction.
This is allowed, so to say,
under two-phase locking.
However, if you use strict two-phase
locking in each case, on both local nodes,
then this scenario would be avoided
because the locks would be maintained
until globally, on all the nodes,
we do a commit.
And this would,
in the case of this example,
lock transaction T2
as soon as it tries to write to A.
So clearly, using classical
two-phase locking,
non-strict two-phase locking,
is not sufficient if you do it locally
in each machine.
But we have said that strict two-phase
locking, doing it locally, is sufficient.
So why is this?
Well if you think about it,
it's not that surprising
because all we need to do when locking
is avoid conflicts between accesses,
by two different transactions,
on the same resource.
And right now, each resource
is one node only.
That means we can locally deal with
every conflict that arises,
some node maintains the object
on which the conflict arises,
and then we realize that
one transaction has to be
ordered before the other,
by blocking one transaction,
because another transaction has to lock.
Now, if we then not unlock
until a commit happens,
then things will be maintained properly,
and serializability will be assured.
So now we have a way of maintaining
serializability using locking.
One thing that can arise in lock-based
concurrency control is deadlocks.
And we have dealt with this by either
avoiding deadlocks, or by detecting them.
How do we detect deadlocks
at this particular scenario?
So what we can do is have each side,
each different individual database server,
maintain a local waits-for graph
that basically has a node switch
transaction, and and edge.
When one transaction is blocked,
it waits for a lock
held by another transaction.
Now it can absolutely arise,
and we've got an example here,
that there is, let's say,
two database servers,
Site A, and and Site B,
and they individually have
an acyclic waits-for graph,
but if you combine those
by combining the edges,
adding them up,
we get a cyclic waits-for graph,
which means there is a deadlock.
That means, maintaining waits-for
graphs locally is not enough.
What we can do, of course, is
have a single centralized database server
responsible for maintaining the edges
of waits-for graphs of all the nodes.
That means, a machine
that collects all these edges,
and then maintains, globally,
the waits-for graph for all the machines,
and does detect cycles and deadlocks.
And then can let machines know
that they have to deal with deadlocks
by killing transactions.
Alternatively, you can optimize this a bit
by having some hierarchical scheme
of propagating edges towards
something like a central node,
and there are certain optimizations
that can be done using this idea.
The alternative would be, of course,
having a time-out to detect deadlocks.
If nothing progresses
in the system anymore,
we can start killing transactions.
In that case, we don't need
such a waits-for graph.
One thing that we have not discussed yet,
is performing commits.
So far we didn't have much
to say about this.
In a single-node scenario, once we decide,
in a single-fronted scenario,
once we decided that we want to commit,
it was relatively clear
what has to be done.
In certain schemes, locking-based schemes,
data was already in place,
and all we had to do is not roll back.
Not undo changes.
In other scenarios, lets say,
the scenarios that use multiple versions,
or snapshots, these snapshots
would be just deleted,
and not propagated back to the database.
Now in this one scenario,
the committing problem is harder,
because we really have make sure
that whenever we decide to commit,
we commit on all nodes.
And not just on some.
If we did the latter,
if we commit only on some,
we could get into serious
consistency issues.
A very famous technique here,
a very famous algorithm,
is so-called, "two-phase commit".
Which is a committing algorithm
in this particular scenario.
And it shouldn't be confused, of course,
with two-phase locking,
which is something completely different.
Although, there is again, two phases.
Now, in the two-phase commit scenario,
there is one coordinator
among all these database servers,
which initiates the commit,
and then is responsible for collecting
certain votes and answers
to make sure that everything
works properly.
Well, if for example,
our client has been most recently
in contact with a single machine to say,
"Now I want to commit my transaction,"
then, this could be, for example,
the coordinator.
Or we could have some
lead election scheme
to decide which machine
to coordinate this.
This is not a very heavy-load job,
so we don't have to worry very much
about paralyzing this.
Now, when the message from the client
lets say, arrives,
that we want to commit,
we do the following:
the coordinator receives this message,
and decides to send a prepare signal
to all the machines
involved in the transaction.
If the coordinator itself
is one of those machines,
it also has to act as a subordinate.
Now, the subordinates
receive this prepare signal,
and have to force-write
a prepare record to the log.
Then they decide,
based on their own constraints,
whether their part in satisfying
the integrated constraints
that have to be maintained,
can be satisfied.
That means they will check
locally at the objects
whether all the potential integrated
constraints can be maintained.
And if there is any reason to believe
that this is not going to be possible,
then that subordinate has to say "no"
as an answer to the coordinator.
If however, the subordinate can say,
"Locally aside, my part
in the committing can be satisfied,"
then it will send a "yes".
The coordinator has to wait
for all the responses
from all the subordinates.
And then decides, based on these votes,
whether every of the subordinates --
each of the subordinates can commit.
Only then, it decides to commit.
Otherwise, if there's at least
one machine that says,
"I cannot commit,"
then all of them have to abort.
So, it collects the votes.
When it has received only yes's,
and everybody has answered,
then it will send a commit signal
to all the subordinates again.
That's the second phase.
Otherwise, it tells all the subordinates
that they have to abort.
The subordinates, again,
have to force-write this decision
to abort a commit to the log,
and then they send
an acknowledgement.
And of course they do the action.
That means they either abort, locally,
or they commit their part locally.
Finally, the coordinator waits for
all these acknowledgments to arrive,
and then writes an end record to its log.
We haven't talked about logs before,
in the previous lectures,
but the log is actually important
to be able to deal with failures
during to the commit.
So, assume a protocol where data is,
change data of a transactions
in a local copy,
lets say, multi-versional
concurrency control,
or optimistic concurrency control,
then dealing with aborts is very easy.
Just, we want to make sure,
when they commit,
that they write everything correctly.
And of course,
the two-phase commit protocol
is not bound in any way
to lock-based concurrency controls,
it can be used with any distributed
concurrency control protocol,
be it multi-version based,
snapshot isolation based, or whatever.
So the challenge is,
what happens if at least one machine
breaks while the commit is executed?
In that case, we must be sure
that we proceed as planned,
and don't forget what we've decided.
So for that reason,
when the core data makes a decision,
and it communicates to the other machines,
it has to make sure that this decision
is logged and written,
so it will save to the log,
so that when it crashes, it can recover
and is still in the same state,
and similarly, the subordinates
will have to make the same decision.
Now there are many details
about this protocol.
There is many corner cases
that have to be dealt with,
and they're really beyond
the scope of this lecture.
For that one, we'll have to read
the specific literature
to implement two-phase commit correctly.
There's many potential pitfalls,
including all these fine-grain details
about how to deal with
failures during commit.
In general, there may be
many database machines involved,
and the more machines that are involved,
the more likely that
at least one of them fails.
So this has to be handled properly.
But, again, just to say
the high-level things,
two-phase commit is called
two-phase commit,
because there is these two phases.
The first, the voting phase,
where together,
the distributed fashion will decide
whether we can actually commit.
There's the coordinator
which collects these votes,
and then, based on the votes,
counts them, so to say,
and makes a decision.
And then all of these guys
who have to commit themselves,
have to follow this decision.
So it's not possible
that a machine says "commit",
and later, after it has been confirmed
that it should commit,
by the coordinator, it decides,
"Actually, I cannot commit."
I have to abort."
This is not possible.
And in this first phase,
the subordinates make sure
that if it says,
"Yes, I can commit,"
it can really commit.
So, in summary,
distributed transaction management,
at least on this high-level
that we have now discussed,
is not that hard.
We have talked about two-phase commit,
which is an important protocol,
not to be confused with two-phase locking.
We've talked about lock-based
concurrency control,
and why local, strict two-phase
locking does the job.
We've talked about deadlock
protection avoidance,
and that said, of course,
we have only scratched the surface.
There is much more
to be said about this topic.
And there could be special-purpose
lectures on this, and courses for this.