In previous videos,
we have discussed
the notion of consistency
that is used in ACID transaction
processing systems.
That means we've got transactions
that are conceptually executed atomically,
and the executions of many,
potentially, interleaving,
overlapping concurrent transactions,
is equivalent to a serial execution
where there is no overlap.
That means, the [inaudible] first
transaction is going to read the output,
the written values,
of the cave transaction.
It makes sense, in general,
to also consider weaker
notions of consistency.
These are potentially useful
to have more scalability in systems,
but they come with their own
disadvantages and problems.
So before we are able to talk about
weak consistency in general,
we have to make a few assumptions.
A priori, we will have to now assume
that we don't talk about general,
concurrent applications
that work with data,
but we have to think about,
specifically, key-value stores.
But the only semantics we have
is that we can read and write values.
Key-value pairs, potentially.
In general, we'll have
a distributed key-value storage,
that means, the storage is
distributed on multiple machines.
There might be replication,
but certainly, not all data will,
in general, be stored at all machines.
So if we don't have a sufficiently
strong notion of consistency,
it might well happen that a certain client
writes a new value,
and after that, another
client reads that object,
but sees an old value.
That is excluded by what you
would call strong consistency.
It would be excluded,
conceptually,
by ACID transactions.
So we assume a distributed
key-value store model,
and a client-server model here.
Let's next discuss some
special cases of weak consistency.
The first is what is called
causal consistency.
So here, you have processes
communicating with each other,
changing values,
and if a process A changes a value,
and tells process B about it, so to say,
then subsequently--
or communicates with process B,
and might have said something
that relates to this value,
subsequently, process B
must read this value,
this written value by process A.
So the kind of causal relationship--
I've told you about it,
so you know about it--
has to be preserved.
Read-your-writes consistency
is something closely related,
or in a sense, a special case,
where a process that
has written something,
has to subsequently, read its own value.
Session consistency says that, basically,
inside a predefined session,
it's a bit like a transaction,
a bag of subsequent changes,
you will see consistently
what you've changed, so to say.
In monotonic read consistency,
you will--
once you have started
reading an object,
you will, in subsequent reads,
see the same version.
And not an older version.
The monotonic write consistency property
means that if you write
a new value for an object,
and subsequently you overwrite this,
then you will not end up
with the older version of the write.
But the writes are ordered correctly,
so to say, within your own process.
Now, eventual consistency,
basically means that,
a number of changes can be made,
a number of reads are made,
and after a certain point in time,
if no further writes appear,
no further changes happen, so to say,
we wait a bit, and at some point,
all reads will return the same--
the last updated value for each object.
That means, we might be at--
while the system is
not in a stable state,
while changes happen,
or briefly, thereafter,
have processes that read values,
and they are outdated values.
Because, potentially,
there might be multiple servers
in these distributed key-value stores,
and the data has not been
propagated correctly yet.
But with time, as data get
more and more propagated,
we have reached a stable state,
and after that, every read,
no matter which server we reach,
sees the same value.
So, a system that has reached
this notion of consistency
is said to have converged.
This was, in a sense,
the client-side viewpoint.
So, from the viewpoint of the client,
it might connect to any server
in this distributed key-value store,
and does reads and writes,
and might observe certain inconsistencies.
Of course, some of these inconsistencies
are easier to resolve that others.
For example, if already,
by ensuring that a client
always accesses the same server,
which is a way of
still achieving scalability
by having many servers,
serve many clients.
Unless the server is implemented
in a very strange way,
certain notions of consistency
are very easy to kind of ensure.
For example, the notion of making sure
that writes by the same process
are not stored out of order,
but are durable.
Now let's look at the server-side.
Let's assume there is N machines,
in this distributed key-value store,
that can store replicas of data.
Let's assume that whenever we write,
we write at least two W many replicas.
And these have to, together,
acknowledge receipt of the update
before the update completes.
So in a sense, the client,
or the middleware that supports it,
or a client library,
will have to wait for all
the acknowledgements
of the machines that were asked
to write down this value.
When we read, we could say
that we always read R replicas.
From all different machines,
we read the value.
So what does this mean?
We assume now that each machine
might hold a replica of each object.
And if the number of writes,
W is equal to N,
then is means that every time we write,
we update all the replicas
on all machines.
That means if you read
from any single machine,
you will see the new value.
And by requiring this receipt
and acknowledgement,
you basically do these writes
atomically, so to say,
from the viewpoint of the client
who requests the write.
But not necessarily from the viewpoint
of the client who requests some reads.
Now reads can also happen,
in terms of multiple reads.
And this might allow us
to identify some inconsistency.
For example, if writing has
only happened to some of the replicas,
and now we read several replicas,
and they are not in the same version,
we know that there is some inconsistency.
And this gives us the basis,
for basically, for example,
collecting a quorum.
So, if you for example,
make three reads,
and two of them are equal,
and the third is different,
you might for example, choose
that the majority, so to say,
the value that is represented
by two machines, wins.
This might not be the right thing
to do in general, though.
Now, however, suppose that this
W plus R is greater than N.
Then strong consistency is ensured.
So for example, if we have three machines
that each can store replicas of objects,
and R is two, and W is two,
that means whenever we write,
we write it to two machines, together.
And then when we read,
we read from two machines.
We can basically identify inconsistencies.
And then we just wait,
or decide to read more copies--
more replicas,
to decide which is
the winner, so to say,
which is the right value.
So, by having W plus R
to be greater than N,
we can ensure strong consistency.
And if, in general, W is not N,
but is less than that,
then this is usually called
the quorum consensus method.
So we will basically collect a quorum.
If we have read enough values
to be able to decide the right outcome,
we are good.
In general, if we want to optimize
for read performance,
we might, for example,
take large W and R equals one.
That means, we are not making our reads
inefficient by having to read
many, many machines,
but by writing to many machines,
making the value highly available,
we can really paralyze the reads.
Of course, that works best
if the writes are relatively uncommon,
compared to the reads.
And of course, by having
W more than one,
we have better availability,
we can deal with failures of machines.
Now if W plus R
is less than or equal to N,
then we've got a notion
of weak consistency only.
And then probably, it makes most sense,
or maybe only sense to assume
that R equals one.
If we anyway cannot say anything
about the correctness of the value,
it doesn't make sense to read
multiple values, potentially.
We have talked about
ACID transactions before,
and now let's think about weak
consistencies for comparison.
So, clearly,
what counts against ACID transactions
and in database management systems,
is that strong consistency
implemented in distributed scenario
by two-phase commit, or Paxos,
or strong consistency
protocols like this,
does not scale.
This is well-known.
You may have heard about the CAP theorem
that essentially asserts
a related statement.
It has been discussed
earlier by people,
and observed earlier
by people like Jim Gray,
that actually, beyond a certain
number of nodes
in a distributed database management
system that uses strong consistency,
two-phase commit for example,
adding more nodes makes the system
actually not get fast.
That means the transaction
throughput doesn't increase anymore.
So it doesn't make sense
to add more machines.
And whilst it's the
communication overhead,
ensuring strong consistency.
If you think about two-phase
commit for example,
we need four times N
many messages, essentially,
to finalize the protocol
where N is number of machines,
overall, in the system.
And of course, that's very costly.
In a very large system
with very many machines,
there might be stragglers,
there might be failures,
and overall, the latencies
of finalizing a transaction
gets very high, and in general,
that means, overall,
that there's dependencies
between transactions,
and all these transactions
of concurrency protocols,
are disconnected--
just completely ruined throughput.
So this is well-known.
And this has lead to the rise
of the so-called NoSQL
movement in recent years,
started by lots of web
application companies like:
Google, Ebay, Facebook, Yahoo, etc,
that were unhappy with the scalability
of database management systems,
and built their own systems that use
weaker notions of consistency
to deal with the scalability issue.
Of course, if you think about it,
weak consistency might be
cheaper to ensure,
because in general,
we will not need to do these
strong consistency protocols
that have these high latencies, obviously.
The disadvantage of these
weaker consistent systems,
is that programming them
is very hard and error-prone.
In a sense, you will have to,
in your applications--
every time you write an application--
deal with what happens
when something went wrong,
and you haven't reached
strong consistency,
you have the right/wrong values etc.
So you might end up,
in most sophisticated applications,
basically re-implementing
strong consistency protocols
in the applications, which is,
ultimately, not what you want.
So, compared to that,
programming ACID transaction
programs is really foolproof,
because you need know
and understand very little
about concurrency and the deeper
side of distributed algorithms.
You can just think as if there was
no concurrency at all in the system,
and you're working with single-node,
single-threaded system
that does your data reads and writes.
This is actually a reason
that few new systems nowadays
use weak or eventual consistency.
There is a few kind of bases and centers
of using eventual consistency,
specifically Amazon,
that uses it for example,
even nowadays,
for managing shopping carts.
Also also in some other
places in its overall infrastructure.
So it can actually happen that if you,
on your machine,
start two different browsers,
and connect to Amazon,
and start putting products
into your shopping cart,
then you will see, although
you have the same user,
and you have logged in
as the same user,
you might see two different states
of your shopping carts,
even after several updating runs.
So what Amazon has to do, basically,
it will propagate data,
and ultimately at some point,
will have to deal with
conflict resolution
if you have done inconsistent things
in the two different browsers.
It will have to some application-
specific custom code
that will have to decide
what to do about this,
and how to make the shopping
carts consistent again.
So also, Google,
which initially was really,
a very militant partisan
of the NoSQL movement,
and strongly opposed
to classical strong consistency,
is actually now building ACID systems.
And if you look at the development
of the whole sequence
of major database management
systems that they have built,
you can see this development.
So for example, in Bigtable in 2006,
we had atomic tuple updates.
So you could actually write tuples
that consisted of several fields,
atomically, but nothing else.
So you could not build transactions
in the classical sense.
In 2011, they built MegaStore,
or published a paper on MegaStore,
where they supported
the notion of entity groups,
that means you could have
atomicity across multiple tuples
with certain constraints.
Then in 2012, they presented Spanner,
which is yet another such
database system.
And it's really not a database system.
It is called a globally
distributed database system.
It does it on a quite large scale,
but it really implements
ACID transactions.
So how is this possible?
Because they achieve
classical strong consistency
and it is still kind of claim to scale.
Well the answer is probably that--
well the answer is not just probably,
but certainly that they don't truly scale.
The just achieve a certain
high degree of size.
And how do they do this?
They actually implement a lot
of specific machinery
for ensuring strong
consistency in hardware.
So when Jim Gray wrote his paper,
that I mentioned above,
he actually measured this threshold
above which it doesn't
make sense to add more nodes
to still be able to support
something like two-phase commit,
at about 70 nodes.
But he also remarked
that this number
depends on hardware
technology ultimately,
and on lower level,
software technology.
For example, on how long it takes
to transfer messages between machines,
so they're lower bound on latencies.
So if you can improve on these things,
you can ultimately push this constant--
puts the constant
number of nodes higher.
And it might be just large enough
that you can potentially at one day
even support the largest applications.
And that's basically what Spanner does.
But it doesn't truly support scalability,
and it needs a strong
consistency mechanism.
Another thing that I want to
remark upon again,
is the CAP theorem.
So this is something
that was essentially celebrated.
Many people use it in all kinds
of appropriate context, ultimately.
And what it says, is basically,
that in ultimately,
a key-value store--
in a distributed
key-value store if you like,
you can only have at most,
two of the following three properties.
Which are: consistency, availability,
and partition-tolerance.
So, consistency, strong consistency
is what you by now know.
Availability is what you also know now.
And partition-tolerance means,
basically, that if you have
this distributed system,
consisting of many nodes in a network,
and you partition the network,
that means you cannot reach,
from the viewpoint of a client let's say,
or of certain servers,
the remaining nodes,
the system degrades gracefully.
And it can still continue.
It might not be fully available anymore,
because certain data
is not in that part of the system,
but it's still continuous,
and can do a gracefully
degraded partial service.
Now, weakly consistent systems,
basically choose the two properties:
availability and partition-tolerance,
at the cost of not supporting
consistency anymore.
What's the alternative, really?
Conceptually, the paper about
the CAP theorem, originally that
conjecture leads also to the proof
doesn't exclude that you can take
any pair of two properties,
and build a system around it.
So what about database
management systems?
There are two argumentations.
Let's assume I've got a distributed
database management system,
and we are just not very fast.
We basically don't keep up
with our workload.
Then we're getting, maybe, blocked,
waiting for my two-phase commit to finish.
In that case, we are not availability,
or have bad availability,
and basically what we are supporting
is consistency partition-tolerance.
Alternatively, you might
say that basically,
if you would reduce those overheads
of communication, so to say,
and of the protocols,
and basically,
the cost of computation
to just execute
the concurrency control protocols
almost to zero, basically.
Or make it infinitely small.
Then you have consistency
and availability.
Of course.
But of course it requires some kind of
unrealistic, infinitely fast system
that violates all of what
we said about locality.
But just by increasing the cost
of communication between nodes a little,
this is not true anymore.
So in that sense,
it is not partitioning-tolerant,
because just this little latency
for communicating,
you could think of something
like a network partition.
Of course to some extent,
all these comparisons,
and all these considerations
are somewhat limited in usefulness,
simply because, in a sense,
the CAP theorem is really not meant
for this kind of consideration
or for entire applications, in a sense.
It is however, important to say
that really, key-value stores--
this weakest notion of semantics--
just as reads and writes are independent
and they don't care about anything else,
they are no applications.
And the CAP theorem
really says only something
about these key-value stores.
So consistency refers to dealing with,
basically, consistency of replicas.
Even if you cannot
deal with any atomicity
across several different updates,
as transactions would do.
So in a sense, I would argue that
if you look at real applications,
that as we see nowadays,
at Google and other places,
really require something
like transactions,
then, something like a CS theorem,
where S stands for scalability,
and C of course, for consistency,
would be more reasonable
than the CAP theorem.
Why is this?
Well, if you want to think about
scalability and performance
in the context of real applications--
complex applications,
where the workloads involve,
potentially transactions,
or something like this.
Then it's not helpful to model
scalability and performance
using availability and
partition-tolerance.
That's why we had this
strange argumentation
about DMS's trading off
for consistency and availability,
or of consistency and
partition-tolerance.
So we could however say,
because ultimately,
given this argumentation,
we can model, or translate
the CAP theorem
to a consistency or a scalability
theorem where we can say,
"you can have only one of these two."
And in my opinion,
that is more meaningful.
And of course then,
ACID systems would make the choice
of taking consistency,
while weaker consistent systems,
of course, take the choice of scalability.