Let's look a bit more
into eventual consistency.
Specifically, in this lecture
I will talk about causal consistency,
and their realization using vector clocks.
So there is an important system
that you should know about,
called Dynamo, which was
implemented by Amazon,
which is also the foundation
and the driving force
behind this shopping cart example
that I talked about
in the previous lecture.
Conceptually, causal consistency
is the following:
A system provides causal consistency
if the memory operations
that potentially are causally related
are seen by every node
of the system in the same order.
So that means if I've got
a process A that makes a change,
and communicates with a process B,
then process B has to start from there,
and basically start from the values
written by this previous process.
And this propagates,
transitively, so to say.
And you can implement causality,
causal consistency,
using vector clocks.
Let me say that this is not enough
to ensure eventual consistency,
because all that it ensures
is that certain things
are not really inconsistent,
but it doesn't guarantee that ultimately
everything is propagated everywhere,
but that's only a small step
from causal consistency.
Also, in general, causal consistency,
mechanisms using vector clocks,
might lead to conflicts
that then have to be resolved
using application-specific semantics.
For example, the shopping cart example,
these vector clocks will tell us
that there is a conflict,
but then we have to decide, and
that's going to be application-specific,
how to resolve them,
and that's separate from
the vector clocks themselves.
So how do vector clocks work, in general?
In general, we will have
a vector of, basically, pairs,
and each pair has the information of,
identity of a server,
and a logical timestamp.
So a vector consists
of several such pairs,
and such a vector is basically
associated with a data value,
but it's not global to a data value,
so if we've got multiple replicas
of that data value, at different machines,
then at any point in time
there might be different vectors
associated with each of those.
So now let's assume
that we are at timepoint zero,
nothing interesting has happened yet,
of course our data values
have some value,
and now data value D1
is actually written to by server X.
So, initially,
this is the first timestamp,
the entry to this ,
so to say, entry vector,
this pair Sx,
and logical complement
we want is the initial value.
So this means Sx has written.
Now let's assume that
Sx makes a second write,
still in the same process,
to D1 and it changes this value,
copies this value to D2,
in general writes to D2.
Now, we will create
this vector clock and tree for D2,
which is Sx, so the x is written,
and the increment--
whenever we make a local write
the local server's vector clock by one,
so we now have the timestamp 2.
Now assume that we're now
communicating this value
to server Y, and server Y
is going to, itself, write the value.
So we're going to extend
this vector clock for this value,
let's say we write to D3,
by adding for Sy a logical timestamp 1.
So we'll now have the vector
Sx with timestamp 2,
and Sy with timestamp 1.
These could be the same value D2,
but that server is different,
that doesn't matter,
but D2 has communicated
some information to D3,
potentially the value of D2.
Based on this, the decision
was made to write particularity D3,
so we have to basically infect
the vector of D3 with the information
that what happens here happens
after logical timestamp 2 at server X.
So we have to record that the relevant
last-seen timestamp of server X was 2,
and the last-seen timestamp
of server Y is 1.
Now let's assume that independently,
after Sx has written
its second logical timestamp to D2,
some data is communicated
to a new server, Sz,
and a value is written to D4,
then we also have to expand
the logical vector clock for D4 there,
and we get Sx 2 and Sz 1, assuming
that's the first logical timestamp for Sz.
Now, let's assume now we want
to reconcile this information,
that means we send
to some server two values,
or we communicate from both Sy
and from Sz to a single server.
Let's assume that server is Sx again.
Some information sent from both,
the vector clocks have communicated,
and they're basically now
aggregate these vector clocks,
we have to combine them.
So Sx writes a new value.
It sees Xx 2 and Sx 2 from the different
vector clocks of Sy and Sz,
and itself, it's going to increment it
to the next vector clock time,
which is free.
And it has to combine Sy 1 and Sz 1.
This is a conflict,
because it cannot order,
relative to each other,
the changes made by Sy and Sz,
they are independent
from each other, so to say.
So we need to invoke
a conflict resolution mechanism
that decides what to do
with this value now.
Now, what does conflict resolution mean
in the context of this example
that we discussed before,
of the shopping cart at Amazon?
We could think of, and model this
as the shopping cart,
consisting of a number of products,
these are the different objects,
and values being either serial 1-bits
that say whether it's
in the shopping cart or not.
Let's assume that for now.
Well, then, an inconsistency could arise
if a particular product
is in the shopping cart in one browser
but is not in the other,
so we have, for example,
in Sy, set the bit to 1,
and in Sz we have set the bit to 0.
And then we would need
a conflict resolution mechanism
to make a decision about this,
and in the case of shopping carts,
it may be not so critical.
We could either ask the user,
or we could, for example,
use a physical timestamp,
an actual timestamp,
to decide what is newer,
that might be acceptable,
but not in practice,
given that users are very slow,
and might not be able to click
at the same point in time,
into two different browsers.
But overall things are quite clear.
On the other hand, it might also be
that both Sy and Sz
have both set to speak to the same value.
It's still a conflict in the viewpoint
of the vector clock,
because the vector clock doesn't know.
But a conflict resolution mechanism,
given the application semantics,
might easily be able to tell
no, that's not a problem,
there's no conflict,
resolution's very easy,
the biggest one in both cases
the new bit is 1.
Now, how do we achieve
eventual consistency,
given this protocol?
Well all that is left to be done
is that servers that hold replicas
of the same object
talk to each other from time to time,
so that their vector clocks are merged
and, if there's a conflict,
it gets resolved.
So, ultimately, after some time,
all machines will have
the same values for each object.