Using stochastic interest rate
models
we can now price all interest rate
derivatives.
In the sequel, we will focus on the
standard derivatives,
interest rate futures, caps and
floors, and swaptions.
In this first part, we will recap
the definition of an interest
rate futures contract.
We will then derive a formula
for the futures rates.
As we have seen earlier
futures rates typically differ from
forward rates.
The difference being called
the convexity adjustment.
We will now calculate these
convexity adjustments
for Gaussian Heath-Jarrow-Morton
models.
We will illustrate our results in
the Vasiček model.
Let us recap what we have learned
about interest rate futures.
Similar to a forward rate
agreement
an interest rate futures allows one
to manage the exposure
to the simple spot rate prevailing
over a future period (T-0, T-1)
with lengths that we denote by
δ in the following.
Recall that in contrast to forward
rate agreements
interest rate futures are daily
marked to market.
The marking to market works
as follows.
At any date t the futures
price is quoted.
It is given in terms of the futures
rate
as shown here.
If the futures price changes from
time t to time  t + Δt
the holder of the contract receives
a cash flow
which is given by the difference of
the futures price.
At time t+Δt minus the
futures price from day t
we denote this cash flow
by Δ x futures price P at
t + Δt.
This cash flow can be positive
or negative.
The futures rate determining
the futures price
is chosen according to the following
rules.
At the delivery date T-0
the futures rate is equal to the
underlying
which in this case is the simple
spot rate.
At any earlier date t
the present value of the cash flow
from holding the futures contract
has to be 0.
This is the present value
of the cash flow
and has to be 0.
We then approximate the discount
factor
for small Δt
by e ^ - r(t)Δt.
Because this is measurable with
respect to the information
available at t,
we can pull this out
from the expectation, and will be
left with the conditional expectation
of the cash flow itself.
We infer that the conditional
expectation has to be 0.
But this just means that the futures
price process
is a martingale under Q.
Because the futures rate is linear
in the futures price,
we conclude that the futures rate
process itself is a martingale under Q.
Hence the futures rate
at any time t
is given by the conditional
expectation under Q
of its terminal value
which is the future simple
spot rate.
Now let us contrast this with what we
know for the simple forward rates.
We recall that the forward rate
process
is a martingale under the T-1
forward measure.
Hence at any date t
the simple forward rate is given
by the conditional expectation
of the future simple spot rate but
under the T-1 forward measure.
The difference between the futures
rate and the forward rate
is called the convexity adjustment.
We denote it by the letter γ.
This value depends on the
underlying interest rate model.
We now calculate the convexity
adjustment
in a Gaussian Heath-Jarrow-Morton
model.
Consider a Gaussian HJM model
with the deterministic forward rate
volatility σ.
As usual, we denote the T-bond
return volatility
by the letter v which is
minus the integral of σ.
Some stochastic calculus then shows
that we can express
the T-0 bond price divided
by the T-1 bond price
as shown here.
This is the product of a Q-martingale
times a deterministic function
of time.
From this we easily infer
that the conditional expectation
of the terminal value of this
ration process
shown here, is given by
the ratio process itself
at time t times
this deterministic correction
factor.
Notice that this identity
holds because
v is a deterministic
function.
Using this identity, we can now
calculate the convexity adjustment
as shown on the next slide.
The convexity adjustment γ
is the difference between the
futures rate
minus the forward rate.
Using the identity from the previous
slide
we can calculate this conditional
expectation.
Plugging that in and re arranging
terms
we arrive at this expression for
the convexity adjustment
in a Gaussian Heath-Jarrow-Morton
model.
Notice that the convexity adjustment
γ is non negative
if the exponent
is non negative.
And this holds in particular if
the cross products
of the σ are non negative.
This is clearly the case
in a 1 factor Vasiček short
rate model.
Recall that the Vasiček short
rate model is
a Gaussian HJM model with
this volatility function.
We now compute the convexity
adjustment
for the parameters as shown here
for the futures and forward rates
written
on a 3 month simple
spot rate.
The plot on the left hand side
shows the convexity adjustment
as a function of time to maturity.
We see in this example that
the convexity adjustment is
smaller than a basis point
for times to maturity up to
5 years.
In the right figure we see the
convexity adjustment as a function
of varying volatility parameters σ.
Here we fix the time to
maturity to be 6 months
and we vary the volatility σ
from 0 to 2%.
As we can see, the convexity
adjustment is increasing in σ
and the order of magnitude is
again somewhere between 0 and
1 basis point.