If you have issued the floating rate
note and have to pay floating rates
you'll want to protect yourself
against too high rates.
In this case, you would buy
a so called cap.
On the other hand, if you invested
in a floating rate note
and receive floating rates,
you'll want to protect yourself
against too low rates.
In this case, you'll want to buy
a so called floor.
Caps and floors are like
calls and puts
and they are related through a
parity relation
which relates them to the value
of a corresponding swap.
We will price caps and floors using
the forward measures
developed in the previous part.
We will learn about the so called
Black's and Bachelier's price formulas.
Both formula's express caps and
floor prices
in terms of a single volatility
parameter
which is in 1-1 relation
to these prices.
It is market practice to quote
caps and floors
in terms of their implied
volatilities.
A caplet with reset date T-0
and settlement date T-1
pays the holder the difference
between the simple spot rate
and the strike rate κ.
Specifically, the cash flow at
time T-1
is δ times the positive part
of the difference between the
simple spot rate
and the strike rate κ.
Formally, this is as shown here.
We denote by δ, the length of the
time interval (T-0, T-1).
It is clear that the caplet protects
the holder against too high rates.
What is the price of this caplet at
some spot date t.
Let us do it in 2 steps.
We first observe that the pay off
of the caplet at time T-1
is known at time T-0.
We can thus infer the time T-0
value of the caplet
by simply multiplying the cash flow
by the T-1 bond price.
We can express the simple
spot rate
in terms of the T-1
bond price
and rearranging terms
brings us to this identity as shown
here.
Notice that this is factor
1 + δκ
times the pay off of a put
option
on the T-1 bond with expiry
date T-0
and strike price over 1 + δκ.
This is the value at time T-0.
The time t price of the
caplet therefore is
the price of this put times the
factor 1 + δκ.
We denote the price of the caplet
like this.
A cap is a strip of caplets.
It is specified by a sequence of
reset and settlement dates
T-0 up to T-n.
Here T-0 is the first reset date
and T-n is called the maturity
of the cap.
It is further specified by a cap
rate κ
and for simplicity of notation
we assume that the length of these
intervals is equal to δ.
At the first reset date T-0, we
reset the first caplet
which yields a cash flow at
time T-1.
Same then at T-1, we reset the
cash flow of a caplet
that pays at T-2, and so on
and so forth.
These payments are random and
can sometimes be 0.
By linearity of prices
the cap price at the spot date t
is given by the sum of the prices
of the corresponding caplets.
A floor is the converse to a cap.
It protects the holder against
low interest rates.
It is defined as a strip of
floorlets
with cash flows at time T-i
given by the positive part
of the difference of
the strike rate κ
minus the prevailing simple spot
rate.
Again at the first reset date T-0,
there we set the first floorlet
which yields a cash flow
at time T-1
and so on and so forth.
Again these cash flows can be
positive or 0
depending on whether the prevailing
simple spot rate
lies above or below
the strike rate κ.
By the linearity of prices,
the price of the floor
at the spot date t  is given
by the sum of the
Let us observe the following parity
relation
which holds for the difference for
the caplet
minus the floorlet pay off.
It is simply equal to the cash flow
of a prayer swap.
This proves the following parity
relation
Here is the cap, floor,
parity relation.
The price of the cap minus the price
of the floor
is equal to the value of
a payer swap
with fixed rate, notional 1 and the
same
reset and settlement date
as the cap an the floor.
We then say that the cap and
the floor
are at the money if their
values are the same.
This happens exactly when the strike
rate κ
is equal to the prevailing swap rate
which renders the value of the
payer swap equal to 0.
The cap is then said to be in the
money
if the strike rate is smaller than
the swap rate
and out of the money if the strike
rate is larger than the swap rate.
For the floor, it's just
the converse.
We now derive 2 price formulas
for caps and floors.
We start with Black's formula.
Let us first look at these
generic price formulas.
We know that the present value
of a cash flow that takes
place at time T-i
is computed by taking the
expectation
of the pay off under the T-i
forward measure
and multiplied by the prevailing
T-i bond price.
So in order to compute caplet
and floorlet prices
we need to know the distribution
of this future
simple spot rate under the T-i
forward measure.
Black's formula assumes that this
distribution is log-normal.
More specifically
it is assumed that the forward
rate process
follows these dynamics with the
constant σ.
Recall that we know that the forward
rate process
is a martingale under the T-i
forward measure.
So Black's formula simply assumes
that this martingale
has very specific dynamics.
This one.
Under this log-normality assumptions
we know how to compute these
expectations.
This is bringing us to the
following theorem.
Black's formula for the ith
caplet and floorlet price
is as shown here.
Where the ingredients are Φ
which stands for the standard normal
cumulative distributive function
and the parameters d-1
and d-2
which are expressed in terms
of σ.
This is the single volatility
parameter
in Black's formula
and hence is called, the
Black volatility.
it is also called the
relative volatility alternatively.
Recall that the cap is a strip of
caplets
and the price of the cap is the
sum of the caplet prices.
So it is important to know that
the Black volatility for the cap
price
has to be one and the same for all
the caplets that belong to the cap.
The same holds for the floor.
Bachelier's formula assumes that the
future simple spot rate
is normally distributed under the
T-i forward measure.
More specifically
it is assumed that the forward rate
process
follows a Gaussian process with a
constant volatility σ
under the T-i forward
measure.
This brings us to the next theorem.
Bachelier's formula for the ith
caplet and floorlet price
is as shown here.
Where the ingredients are Φ
the standard cumulative normal
distribution function,
φ is the density,
and D is the parameter
shown here.
Again this is expressed in terms of
the single volatility parameter σ
which is called the normal
volatility.
Alternatively it is also called the
basis point volatility
or the absolute volatility.
Again as it was the case for the
Black's formula,
the normal volatility is going to be
the same for all caplets
belonging to a cap and similarly
for the floor.
With this convention, there is a 1-1
relation
between the Black and the normal
volatilities
and the cap and floor prices.
It is market practice to quote cap
and floor prices
in terms of their implied Black or
normal volatilities.
Caps and floors are typically traded
on 3 months
simple spot rates in the US market
and on 6 months simple spot rates
in the Euro market.
Here is an example.
These are at the money cap
prices
in the Euro-zone from August 2013.
We see that maturities range
up to 30 years.
The first column gives us the cap
prices in percentage points.
The second column shows the Black
implied volatilities
and the third column shows us the
normal implied volatilities.
Notice that the normal implied
volatilities
are of an order 100th factor
100 smaller than
the Black implied volatilities.
The plot on the right hand side
shows
the implied volatilities as functions
of the maturity of the underlying cap.
It is a challenge for any interest
rate model
to match these given volatility
curves.