In this part
we introduce options on swaps,
so called swaptions.
We study the notion of moneyness.
We see when there's a swaption
at money, out of the money,
and in the money.
We will also see how swaptions
can be used
to synthetically create
callable bonds.
We will review Black's and
Bachelier's price formulas
and finally see how swaptions
are quoted in terms
of their Black and Bachelier
implied volatilities.
A payer swaption with strike
rate K
gives the holder the right to enter
a payer swap with fixed rate K
at the swaption expiry date.
Usually the swaption expiry date equals
the first reset date
T-0 of the underlying swap.
Well let us assume that
T-0 is here
and the swap has a length of
T-n - T-0.
It pays a fixed rate K.
at cash flow dates, and it receives
floating at the same dates.
This leads to a value of this swap
at time T-0
that can be positive or negative.
You will exercise the swaption at
expiry date T-0
only if this value is positive.
So let us have a closer look
at the payer swaption
pay off at expiry date T-0.
The value of the payer swap is
shown here
without the plus sign.
The holder of the swaption
will only exercise
the option to enter the payer swap
if this value is positive,
hence
the payer swaption pay off is the
positive part of this value.
Now notice that this pay off
cannot be decomposed
into more elementary pay offs.
As was the case for caps
and floors.
This is because the positive part
of the sum
is not the same as the sum of
the positive parts.
From this we saw that the dependence
between
the different forward rates
will enter
the valuation procedure
of a swaption.
Now recall that an equivalent
expression
for the value of the payer swap
is given in terms of the swap rate
which is shown here without
a plus sign.
Hence an equivalent expression for
the payer swaption pay off
at expiry date T-0
is what is shown here with
the plus sign.
This leads us to the following
convention.
We say a payer swaption is
at the money
if the strike rate is equal to the
prevailing forward swap rate.
The payer swaption is said to be
in the money
if the strike rate is smaller than
this forward swap rate
and out of the money if the strike
rate is larger than the forward swap rate.
For the receiver swaption it is
the converse.
There is also the convention
to call the swaption that has expiry
in X years
and an underlying swap length
of Y years
the X year into Y year
swaption.
Here is an application.
Swaptions can be used to synthetically
create callable bonds.
Let's illustrate that with
an example.
Suppose a company has issued a 10
year bond with a 4% annual coupon
on the principal of n.
Now suppose that the company
wants to add the right
to prepay or call the bond at par
after 5 years
but the company cannot change
the original bond.
Let's look at the situation the
company faces after 5 years
sitting at this time point.
The company is facing cash
flows,
4% annual coupons
on the notional of N.
The company wants to add
the option
to get rid of these payments
of these 4% annual coupons
and instead pay the notional
N at date 5.
Now notice that the value of the
bond at time 5
is given by the expression here.
Formally speaking
this is the same as the notional
N
plus the value at time 5
of a receiver swap
of length 5 years.
Now the company will only
call the bond at par
that means at value N
if the value of the receiver swap
is positive.
Now here is the solution.
The company can buy a 5 year into
5 year receiver swaption
with a strike rate of 4%.
The pay off of this swaption at
expiry date 5
is just the positive part of the
value of the receiver swap
that was seen
on the previous slide.
From a cash flow point of view
this is also clear.
Suppose the company exercises
the swaption,
enters the receiver swap,
then the company will receive
the 4% coupons
on these 5 years.
And it will pay floating instead.
At the fixed leg payments cancels
with the 4%
coupon payments on the bond
and we know from the
previous part that
paying the notional N
at time 5
is equivalent to paying the notional
N at time 10
and floating in between.
Here is Black's formula for payer
and receiver swaptions
where Φ denotes the standard
normal cumulative distribution function
and the parameters d-1
and d-2 are given here.
Again this formula has one
volatility parameter.
It's σ and is called Black volatility
or relative volatility.
The underlying modeling assumptions
for Black's formula
which was log normality under the
forward measure for caplets and floorlets
is now different.
Here, it is log normality of the
swap rate
but under a different measure
then the forward measure.
So we refrain from deriving it
here.
Bachelier's formula for payer and
swaption prices
is shown here
where Φ is the standard normal
cumulative distribution function,
φ is the normal density
and the parameter D
is given here.
Again there is a single volatility
parameter σ
called the normal volatility.
Swaption prices are quoted in terms
the Black or normal implied volatilities.
The accrued period δ for the
underlying swap can differ from
prevailing 'δ's for caps
within the same region.
For example, in the Eurozone
caps are typically written on semi
annual LIBOR
where δ is equal to 6 months
while swaps pay annual coupons such
that the δ is 1.
Here is an example
of swaption quotes
in terms of Black's implied
volatilities
of at the money swaptions
in the Eurozone in August 2013.
Maturities range from
1 to 10 years,
and the swap length from
1 to 10 years.
So the first row gives us the 1 year
into 1 year
2 years, 3 years, and so on to
10 years swaption quotes
in percentage points in terms
Black's implied volatilities.
The matrix of values is illustrated
in the figure on
the right hand side.
An interest rate model for swaptions
valuation must fit
such a given volatility surface.
Here are the normal implied
volatilities
of the same at the money
swaptions
in the Euro-zone in August 2013.