We now have all the ingredients
to calibrate an interest rate model
to market data.
More specifically, we calibrate
a two factor
Gaussian Heath–Jarrow–Morton model
to market data consisting
of swamp rates
and at-the-money cap quotes.
For that, we first derive
pricing formulas for caps
in Gaussian HJM models.
And for the calibration,
we need the appropriate function
to be minimized, and we will see
that a good choice
for weights of pricing errors
are the the vegas,
the derivatives of the Black
and Bachelier prices
with respect to their volatility.
Let us review the pricing of caps.
We consider a spot date t note
that we set to 0 for simplicity.
We then consider a sequence
of reset and settlement dates
T note, T1, up to Tn, and assume
that they're all equidistant
with difference given by delta.
We're also given a cap rate kappa.
Recall that the ith caplet
that resets the time Ti-1
and settles the time Ti
is equivalent
to 1 plus delta k kappa
times put option
on the Ti bond that expires
at time Ti-1
The price of the ith caplet
therefore, is given by
by the Q expectation
of the discounted payoff
of these put options on the Ti bond.
Now suppose the underline model
is a Gaussian HJM Model,
and recall the bond put option
price formula in such models.
That gives us the prize
of the ith caplet as shown here
where caplet Fi is to stand
normal cumulative
distribution function.
and the parameters d1 and d2
are given  as shown here
in terms of the integrated
T-bond return volatility, v.
Now consider more specifically
the following
two-factor Gaussian HJM model
with the volatility specification
as shown here
where v1, v2
beta 1 and beta 2
are real parameters to be calibrated
to cap market data.
Elementary integration shows us
that in this case,
we obtain the following expression
for the integrated volatility terms
in the option price formula.
We now want to calibrate these
two factor Gaussian HJM model
to swap and cap data
given at the spot date, t note.
More specifically, the given data
consists of spot swap rates
with swaps that pay
annual fixed coupons
and at-the-money cap quotes
where the caps
have semi-annual cash flows.
The procedure is the following,
we first estimate the discount curve
from the swap data.
Second, we then calculate
the forward swap rates
with semi-annual fixed payments.
These correspond
to at-the-money cap rates.
And then third, we minimize
the weighted square cap prize errors
for calibrating
the volatility parameters,
v1, v2, Beta 1, Beta 2.
Here is the swap data.
We have swaps paying
fixed annual coupons
with length ranging from 1 year
to 30 years.
Swap rates are given in this column.
The first quote is
the 6th month simple spot rate.
For the valuation of the caps
in the model,
we need the discount curve
at the semi-annual frequency.
We use the exact methods
based on the pseudoinverse
to estimate the weighted increments
of the discount curve.
Delta, as shown here,
the estimated discount rates
are given in this table.
We then compute
from this distant curve
the 6th month forward swap rates
whose first reset date
is T note equal to one-half
and that have semi-annual
fixed payments
we derive these swap rates
from these well known formulas.
The figure on the right hand side
shows these forward swap rates
as function of their maturity
which ranges from 1 year
to 30 years.
These forward swap rates
dive us the at-the-money strikes
of the corresponding caps
with maturities
ranging from 1 to 30 years.
The corresponding prizes of the caps
are given as nominal prices
and equivalently, in terms
of their black implied volatilities
and in terms of their
normal implied volatilities.
Recall that these caps
have semi-annual cash flows.
The calibration problem now consists
in finding the remaining parameters
v1, v2, Beta 1, Beta 2
that we summarize by theta
such that the model cap prizes,
let me denote by C hat theta,
n for the nth cap,
are as close as possible
to the market cap prices Cn
shown on the previous slide.
We minimize the mean squared error
of the implied volatilities,
rather than of the nominal prices.
The reason is that the black
and normal implied volatilities,
they standardize option prizes,
they're more robust overtime,
and better comparable
across maturities and strikes.
The problem is that
computing implied volatilities
involves numerical inversion
of the Black or Bachelier formula
at each minimization step
and that is computationally costly.
Fortunately there is an easy way out
as shown on the following slide.
We make use of the vega,
the derivative  of the Black
or Bachelier cap price,
with respect to the volatility.
A first-order Taylor expansion
of the black price function Cn
then, gives us this relation
where sigma, hat, theta n
denotes the model implied volatility
and sigma n
is the market implied volatility.
We can then express the squared
implied volatility error
as a weighted squared cap error
as shown here.
Now the good news is that
there exists a close form expression
for the vega in the Black
and the Bachelier model.
Recall that the black price
of the ith caplet
is given as shown here
where caplet Fi
denotes the standard normal
cumulative distribution function
and the parameters d1 and d2
are given as shown here
and we write Fi,
short for the forward rate
as shown there.
Elementary calculus
using this identity
then, gives us
the following expression
for the derivative
of the caplet price
with respect to the volatility
parameter sigma,
the Black caplet vega.
By linearity,
the Black cap vega is then simply
the sum of the Black caplet vegas
as shown here.
Similarly, we recall
the Bachelier price formula
for the ith caplet shown here
where caplet Fi is again,
the standard normal cumulative
distribution function
and small fi is the density.
The parameter Di stands for this,
where Fi is shorthand
for the forward rate.
Elementary calculus, again,
using these identities
give us the following expression
for the derivative
of the Bachelier caplet price
with respect to the volatility,
the Bachelier caplet vega.
Linearity gives us
the Bachelier cap vega
as the sum
of the Bachelier caplet vegas.
Using the Bachelier vegas,
the calibration problem
now boils down to the weighted
least squared problem shown here.
Using standard optimization
libraries
such as the Matlab built
in fminsearch,
we find the following values
for the parameters.
We obtain similar results
using Black vegas
in stead of Bachelier vegas.
On this slide we see
the fitted normal
and Black implied volatility curves.
In black, we have the market quotes
and in red,
the model implied volatilities.