In the previous episodes,
we saw that
the attributes defined inside
a class represent
information that is specific too
each instance of the class.
If we take our favorite example
with the rectangle again,
each instance of "Rectangle",
each Rectangle-type object
will have its own width, its own
height,
information that is specific to it and
which caracterizes it.
However, what happens if many
instances of a same class
need to access the same
information,
a common information?
That's the topic of this episode.
Until now, we have used different types
of variables in our programs.
We've used instance variables,
which are commonly called "attributes".
We've used local variables,
which are variables declared inside
a method's body.
We've also used parameters,
which we can assimilate
to local variables in the methods,
and which are used to provide
data to methods
so that they can work with.
In this episode, you'll discover
the notion of "static variables",
which are also called "class variables",
as opposed to instance variables.
They are in fact particular attributes,
the declaration of which is preceded
by the reserved word "static".
They look like the standard attributes,
the instance variables.
They are declared the same way,
except for the "static" modifier
that is added before.
They are declared as instance
attributes,
as instance variables, outside
of the methods.
As the instance variables, they are
visible everywhere in the class,
and are inherited by the
subclasses.
In this episode, we'll mainly
focus
on static variables,
but it must be noted that there also
exist static methods,
which will see later on.
In Java, the static modifier
is used
for both variables and
methods.
In the two cases, a static member
can be used
without having constructed
the object beforehand.
Note that in Java, the static
modifier
doesn't apply to local
variables,
that is, to variables declared
inside a method's body.
But what does it actually mean that a static
member can be
accessed without constructing
any object?
If we take the example
of the rectangle again,
what we've used until now
were attributes
declared inside classes,
a.k.a. instance variables.
And we have methods,
and in this context it is
strictly impossible
to use a member of the
rectangle class
without constructing an instance
of rectangle beforehand.
So here for example, if I want
to use the surface method,
I have to construct an object
of rectangle type.
And through this object, I can
call the
method that computes the surface.
A static member, whether it's a
variable or a method,
is invokable without having created
an instance beforehand,
by using only the class name
according to terms that we'll
examine later.
One of the facets is that we
can use
a static member without
constructing any objects.
The other facet, relatively to
static variables,
is that they are shared between
each instance of the class.
Until now you've learnt that
each instance has
its own memory area for
each of its attributes.
Each instantiated rectangle in
a program will have
its own memory areas for
the width and the height.
So here for example, for
the rectangle 'r1',
we'll have memory areas storing
the value of its own width and height.
For another rectangle, there'll be
other memory areas
that will store the width and the
height of that second rectangle.
That's why we say "instance variables":
because each instance owns its own variables.
On the other hand, a static variable
would be an unique memory area
associated with the class rather
than the instances,
but accessible from each
instance.
To sum up, for instance
variables, the attributes,
we reserve a memory area
for each object that we instantiate,
that we create with "new".
So each object has its own
memory area, its own value
for the corresponding instance variable.
For a class variable, that is,
a class-attribute,
declared as static,
there's a single allocation of an
unique memory area.
This reservation is done as soon
as we load the class,
that is, to simplify, as soon as the class
is mentioned in the program,
No memory area will be
allocated for that attribute
when we create a new instance
with "new".
However, that attribute remains accessible
like instance attributes used up to now,
via all the objects of the class,
which will refer to the same
memory area,
the unique memory area allocated
for that static attribute.
Let's see this with a
concrete example.
We have the case of a class A
that contains an instance variable,
an attribute as we have always
used them until now,
and a class variable, that is,
an attribute
whose declaration is preceded
of the reserved word 'static'.
The class A also contains a
modified method,
which can access all the
attributes of the class,
whether they're static or not.
Now let's examine step by step
what happens
when we execute the following
code.
In fact, before the execution,
as soon as the class A is used
in a program,
as it contains a static
variable "c",
there'll be an allocation of a memory
space for this static variable "c",
which will be initialized with the
value 10 because of this line.
If we examine this first
line of code,
the first thing that we see is that
the class variable
is accessible independently of the
creation of any instance.
We can access the 'c' attribute through
the name of the class only,
without creating any instance.
When we execute this line
of code,
we increment the class variable 'c',
which is a class variable of the class A,
which has already been initialized.
We'll have this situation,
the value of 'c' will go
from 10 to 11.
The two following lines declare
an instance of A,
and initialize it using the
default constructor.
Each instance of A has its
own instance variables,
here, in this case, the variable
instance 'b',
which means that when this instruction
line's execution has finished,
the memory situation will be
the following:
we'll have a variable "v1"
containing a reference to an object
of type A
which has an attribute 'b',
initialized to 1 with the
help of this line.
The modified method is then
called on the instance "v1".
This method increments the value
of the instance variable 'b',
we'll therefore be in this
situation
at the end of the instruction
line's execution.
The modified method then increments
the class variable 'c'.
You'll note by the way that the
methods of the class A
can access the static
attributes
in the same way they access
the non-static attributes,
the instance variables.
The execution of the second line
of this modified method
will therefore result in an
additional incrementation
of the class variable 'c', which
will be 12.
So we were able to modify the
value of the class variable
of the static attribute both by
passing by the name
of the class uniquely, and by
using an instance.
So here through the "v1" instance,
we were able to modify the
class-variable 'c'.
The modified variable, whether its
through the name of the class,
or through an instance, is an
unique memory area.
With this example
we saw
that when we modify an
instance variable,
the value changes only for
the current object.
But when we modify a
class variable,
the value changes for all the
objects of the class.
Indeed, the class variable is unique
and accessible to all the objects.
As we have just seen in the
previous example,
a static variable can be used
through the name of the class
without passing by the creation
of any object.
We can therefore use static
members
and do completely without
objects,
which goes against the
"object-oriented" approach.
Using static members to avoid
the "object-oriented" approach
is of course a bad reason to use
static variables.
A good reason is to represent
a value
common to all the objects
of a class.
Let's have a look at this with
a concrete example.
Let's imagine that in a program, we have an
"Employe" (= employee) class.
We want to represent the fact
that 65 years old
is the official retirement age for
all the employees.
Let's consider two possible
versions to implement this.
So a version where we use
an instance variable
to represent the retirement
age,
and another version where we use
a class variable,
a static variable.
First version, an "Employe"
class
that represents the retirement
age as an instance variable.
The constructor of the class
"Employe1" would be in charge
of initializing each attribute with
values passed as parameters.
Now let's suppose that an
"Entreprise" class
uses this "Employe1" type, in
particular to create an array
containing a number of employees.
Each element of the array
would be filled by creating
an instance of Employe.
As the official retirement age
is represented
with an instance variable,
each Employe will store a memory
area that contains this official age,
which happens to be the same
for everybody.
Therefore, we reserve a memory
area for each Employe,
to contain the exact same
information.
So if we have thousands of
employees,
we'll end up with thousands of
times the value 65 stored,
which of course is an
unncessary duplication.
Moreover, this duplication causes major
maintenance problems.
Let's suppose for example that the
law changes,
and that the official retirement age
is now 67 years old.
We would have to iterate over all
the possible instances
to modify this age in
a proper way.
If the instances were stored in an
array, it's still feasible,
but imagine if the instance were
created independently.
This would create a major update issue.
In the second version, where we now
use a static variable
for the official retirement age,
so where we precede the declaration of the
attribute with the reserved word "static",
we don't have this problem
anymore.
Indeed, there would be an
unique memory area
accessible by each
instance,
which would contain the official
retirement age,
which is the same for everybody.
This retirement age can be
accessed from each instance,
or from the class name.
There isn't information
duplication anymore,
and it's easy to do
modifications.
Here we don't have to look for each
instance of every employee anymore,
just to modify the retirement age
and change it to 67 years old.
Voilà! I hope that this small
example will have convinced you
of the benefits of using
static variable well.
Also note that for
constants
that are common to every
instance of a class,
it is unnecessary to store the value
for each object of the class.
You must in fact declare them
as "final static".
For example, for a "Planete"
(= Planet) class,
we need to use G, the
gravitational constant.
This constant is the same for each
planet,
and in this case, it is better
to declare
the constant in question as
"final static",
whether than only "final",
to avoid duplicating this constant
for each instance of Planete.
To conclude on this chapter
of static variables,
let's come back to an often-used
instruction line.
We are now in position to
understand
what this instruction line
does,
which we had used up till now as
a magical incantation.
What can we use directly through
a class name,
well that's nothing else than
a static variable.
So 'out' is a static variable,
it must therefore most likely
contain a reference to an object,
as we apply a method on
this 'out' variable,
obviously the 'println' method.
'out' is indeed a static variable of the
'System' class,
a variable of type 'PrintStream',
so it's an instance of the
'PrintStream' class,
and this 'PrintStream' class contains
a 'println' method,
which is invoked like this.
This concludes our episode
on static variables.
In a following episode,
you'll have the opportunity of
learning about static methods.