After the static attributes, we'll learn
about static methods,
class methods, in this video
episode.
Like with the attributes,
if we add the keyword "static" in
front of a method,
then that method becomes a
class method;
that is, a method that we can call
without any object,
without any concrete instance of the class.
So let's see an example:
here we have a class A in which
a method is defined.
"methode1", which is a class method,
a static method.
We also have a usual method,
an instance method, here, named
"methode2".
In the use example of this
class method,
we see here that we can absolutely
call
"methode1", a class method,
without any instance of the
class A.
The syntax is simply: "name of the
class, dot ('.'), name of the static method,
name of the class method".
This is entirely possible, it
will call "methode1"
and print the message
« Méthode 1 ».
Of course, for a standard method,
an instance method
that isn't declared with the
"static" keyword,
we aren't allowed to use this
syntax, it doesn't make any sense.
"methode2" must be related to
some instance.
So here, to continue the example, we
create an instance 'v' of the class A.
Of course, we cal call the
class method
with the syntax "v.methode1". That's
exactly the same
that writing "A.methode1". It's
only an alternative form.
I recommend you to
rather use
"the name of the class"."the name of the
method", for class methods,
to show your intention and remind
that it's a class method,
even if the instance method
notation is possible.
It is in my opinion a bit
more ambiguous,
and I find this one to be
more clear.
And of course, as usual, we
can call "methode2",
which is an instance method
on the 'v' instance.
As a static method can be called without
any instance, without any object,
such a method can't rely on
the existence of such
an object,
and can therefore not use any instance
variable nor call any instance method.
The "this" reference doesn't exist
in such a method,
as we can't guarantee the
existence of an object.
So such a method, a
static method,
can only call other
static methods,
and can only access class members,
static attributes.
Let's illustrate this with an example.
Here we have a class A
that contains a usual non-
static attribute 'i',
and a class attribute, a
static attribute 'j',
a usual non-static instance
method "methode1",
and a static method, "methode2",
which is a class method.
In the usual method, "methode1",
we try to access the 'i' attribute,
which isn't problematic.
A method linked here to
an instance can access
both the instance
attributes
and the 'j' class-attribute.
We can access the two.
Of course, we're allowed to call
"methode2",
which is a class method,
in "methode1".
So everything is permitted
in an instance method.
But in a class method,
we can only access the attributes
and the class methods.
If we try doing the same thing
than in "methode1",
and accessing the instance
attribute 'i',
then we'll get a compilation
error.
We aren't allowed to do this because
we are in a class method.
We can't guarantee the existence
of an attribute,
of an object, of the
A class.
But we can access the static
attribute 'j',
'j' is a class attribute, a
static attribute.
We are allowed to do this.
We aren't allowed either in
"methode2", static method,
to call a non-static method,
"methode1",
so this would also generate
a compilor error.
On the other hand, we can
absolutely call static methods,
including themselves.
This call is syntactically correct,
there's no problem with it.
So of course, here, as we've
called the same method,
we should be careful and
take precautions
so that it doesn't end up
with an infinite recursion,
and protect this call with a
break condition.
But that is bringing us a bit to far,
we only wanted to show, here,
that we can call another
static method
in a static method.
Of course, if we create an instance
like this in a static method,
we can absolutely create an instance
so of course we can here call
"methode1" on the 'v' instance
of the A class.
Therefore, what are the uses of these
static methods, these class methods?
Well precisely, to write methods
that aren't attached
to particular instances
of a class,
very general methods, typically
tool methods.
We'll do toolbox classes
like this,
which we won't create any
instance of,
but of which we'll simply use
the class methods.
For example, a mathematical
toolbox
like this class, 'MathUtils',
in which we've defined a
class constant,
in which we can also define
a class method,
that is, typically, a tool function
'auCube',
which would compute the
cube of its parameter.
Of course, the creation of an
object of 'MathUtils' type
is totally artifical.
We don't need any object of
'MathUtils' type,
and we could directly call the PI
constant of the 'MathUtils' class,
as, let me repeat it, PI is
indeed a class-variable.
We could therefore also call, like this,
'MathUtils.auCube(3.4)',
as here again, 'auCube' is an
instance-method.
We can therefore call it without the
creation of any 'MathUtils' object,
directly with the name of the
class.the name of the method
to compute the cube of 3.4.
This 'MathUtils' class is only
used to
store utility methods and
constants.
It isn't used to create any
concrete objects.
In fact, that's exactly the case
of the Math class.
And if you had to use the
PI constant,
you'd use the one of the API, and in standard
Java that is written Math.PI,
the Math class of the API,
exactly like
our small pedagogic example
with MathUtils.
Of course, you never do this
yourself,
but you use the constants
defined in the API.
So that's typically what static methods,
class methods, can
be used for.
That being said, avoid abusing
of the "static" keyword,
avoid proliferating this
"static" keyword,
and keep it for very
particular cases.
Typically, the three following
cases.
We can use static with 'final'
for an attribute,
that is, here, a class variable,
to define constants.
That was the example with
the Math.PI variable.
The second situation is to
use static without 'final',
for an attribute. That's
more rare,
and it's for sharing a common
value at the class level,
value common to the class, but
that could change.
This situation is more rare and
you won't come upon it
in the context of this course.
Concerning the methods,
finally,
we can define class methods,
static methods,
when, as we've seen before,
we have utility methods,
for which it is artificial to
link to a particular object,
and which are therefore invokable
without any object.
It's generally also very rare that
you write them yourself,
but you'll typically use the ones
provided by the API,
like for example the sqrt,
square-root, method
of the Math class, provided by
the Java API.
Another example of static method,
that you've already practiced,
is the main method.
And we now understand why the
auxiliary methods,
which we call functions in general
procedural programmation,
so the auxiliary methods of main
are static methods.
As main has indeed a
fixed header,
it must be a method that is
static in a class.
As it's a static method,
it can only access other
static methods,
and therefore the auxiliary
methods of main
have to be static
methods.
Likewise, the main method,
because it is static,
can't access any object of the class
in which it was defined.
So it can't access
variables
and instance methods of the class
in which it has been defined.
Note that apart from that,
the class in which the main
method is defined
is like any other class, it
can have attributes,
methods, constructors, etc.
Voilà! This concludes our episode
about static methods,
class methods.