In this episode and the
following one,
we'll see a new concept:
Java interfaces.
But first, let's begin with an example,
with another game
that would for example
need balls,
rackets, nets, and players.
And let's suppose that each
of these entities
needs an 'evolue' (= "evolves") method,
to make them evolve during the game.
Naturally, the way of
conceiving this
in object-oriented
programming
would be to create an abstract
class 'Entite' (= "Entity")
which would have the abstract
method 'evolue',
and to make the ball, the rackets, the
net, the player
inherit from the abstract class
'Entite'.
But let's suppose that we
go a bit further
in the game's analysis,
and that we realize that
some of these entities,
for example the balls, the
rackets, the nets,
should have a graphical
representation such
that we effectively do see them
on the game's screen,
and that, for example, we
don't see the player.
So at that moment we would
have to dissociate
the players from the balls, the
rackets, and the nets,
as having or not  a graphical
representation.
We could also imagine that
some entities
should be interactive,
for example to be able
to control them
with the keyboard or
with the mouse,
like a ball or a racket.
And others that we
couldn't move,
so for example the net
and the player.
So how would we organize
all this
in the context of our object-
oriented conception?
Ideally we would do all
this through classes
with, for example, an
interactive class
which would allow us to manage
the ball and the racket
in an interactive way.
A class that would allow us
to have a method
to graphically draw the
graphical objects
of which would inherit
net, racket and ball.
But this would make what is
called multiple inheritance.
The ball would inherit in
multiple ways
from an interactive and graphical
entity.
But we can't have multiple
inheritance in Java;
there's only single inheritance
in Java.
So how do we do?
Before answering that question,
let's simply note
that some other programming
languages
have chosen multiple
inheritance,
so why isn't there multiple
inheritance in Java?
Simply because multiple inheritance
may induce confusion,
and make some situations difficult to understand.
For example if we had a class
that multiply inherits of an animal,
is it an animal? The same
animal?
Or is it two animals?
And these situations are also
difficult for the compiler,
which has decisions
to take.
Those that would want to convince
themselves could go and see
the episode on virtual
classes in C++,
on our other MOOC that is taking
place in parallel
on the C++ language, and you'll
most certainly be convinced.
Another reason is that there
can be ambiguity
when a method or a variable
is declared
in many super-classes.
Which one to use? How to
access it?
So, for good reasons, Java
decided
not to have multiple
inheritance.
So, how can we well
design the game
that we've imagined until now
in Java?
For that, let's go back to the
reason that pushed
us to introducing multiple
inheritance.
Why did we want multiple inheritance
in our video game?
To impose the use of common
methods to
some classes.
So for example, we wanted
'ball' and 'racket'
to have methods that allow you to
manage a mouse click, for example.
But the 'gestionClic' (= "clickManager")
method
can't be a method for their
super-class,
common to all for the 'Entite'
class,
because a 'gestionClic' method makes no sense for the player
for example.
What we want to do is to impose a common
content to some sub-classes,
without any inheritance
relation,
and differentiate them from
other sub-classes.
That's the notion of
interface in Java.
The interface notion
in Java,
which is different from the
notion of class,
will allow us to impose to
some classes
to have a particular
content,
without them being part of
a class, properly speaking.
So for example, here, the sub-classes
'Raquette' and 'Balle',
sub-classes of the 'Entite'
class,
will additionally have, for
example,
the 'Interaction' or
'Interactive' interface,
which gives the ability to manage, for
example, mouse interactions.
Of course, it wouldn't have
been correct
to have this 'gestionClic' method in
the 'Entite' class,
because in that case, the net
and the player
would also have had a
'gestionClic' method,
of which they doesn't have any use.
The 'balle', 'raquette' and 'filet' (= "net")
sub-classes of the 'Entite' class
will also have an interface
that oblige them to make a choice, from
a graphical point of view.
So that's it concerning the
interface concept.
Now that you have an idea of the
utility of interfaces,
let's see what they concretely
look like in Java.
Before going on about interfaces,
we shall add an important remark.
Interfaces up to Java 7,
as you'll see it in the coming slide,
can contain only constant variables,
and abstract methods.
However, many new features have
been added in Java 8.
In the following slides, we will
mainly present interfaces
as they were till Java 7.
The new Java 8 features will be
presented in another video.
In Java, an interface is declared
a bit like a class,
with the difference that we'll
replace
reserved word 'class' with the
reserved word 'interface'
followed by the interface's name,
freely chosen,
then a pair of opening and
closing curly braces,
like the body of a class.
Unlike a class, an interface can
only contain
abstract methods, which is the
most common case,
or also constants.
This is how the code of interfaces from
the small introductory example
could look like.
Here you'll wonder why
the methods defined inside
the interfaces
are defined without the reserved
word 'abstract',
when we've just seen that
an interface
can only contain abstract methods.
We'll come back to this
later.
As a reminder, the idea was
that these interfaces
impose a certain content
to the classes
to which they are
related to.
And here the imposed content
was typically
a number of methods.
An interface, that can only contain
abstract methods,
can't contain any constructors.
It is therefore impossible to create
an interface instance.
So for example here, I can't
write something like
this in a program, which
is to declare a graphical
object
and try to instantiate it
this way.
This is obviously impossible.
But let's go back to the question in which
we were concerned before:
why are we here exempt
from
explicitly putting the reserved word
'abstract', for example?
As the methods of an interface are
necessarily abstract,
java exempts you from explicitly
mentioning it.
What you must know
is that any method declared in
an interface
is necessarily abstract and
necessarily public.
If you try declaring an interface
method
with another modifier than
'public',
you'll get a compiler error
message.
It is also possible to put
constants in an
interface, even if that's
less common
than abstract methods.
For example, I could define
an interface like this
that contains constants.
And in this case, I need to give values
to the constants,
as there's no eventual
constructor
that could give initial values
to these constants.
I must do it at this stage,
and like the methods,
there are also implicit modifiers
for the constants.
Every constant that you put in
an interface
is necessarily public, final,
and static.
We now know what we can put
inside an interface.
Let's look at how to
establish the link
between the interface and
the class.
This link is established with a particular
reserved word:
the reserved word 'implements'.
When we declare the class,
we'll indicate that this class implements
a number of interfaces.
There can be many, separated
by commas.
For example, to indicate that our
net class
extends the class Entite,
but implements the Graphique
interface,
which will let us see this net as
a draw-able object,
we'll write, in Java, the class 'Filet' (= net)
extends the class 'Entite' (= entity),
and implements the 'Graphique'
(= Graphical) interface.
When a class implements a number of
interfaces,
It is imperative, if we want it
to be instanciable,
that is redefines all the
methods
declared in the
interfaces.
All the abstract methods
must be concretely redefined in
the class that implements them,
so that these are
instanciable.
This is the way that an interface
imposes a content
to a class that implements it.
The moment we establish the link
between the class and the interface,
so the class, if we want to
instantiate it,
must redefine all the methods
specified in the interface.
So as we've seen,
a class can perfectly
implement
many interfaces, for
example,
the ball is a clickable object and
is a draw-able object,
so it implements two
interfaces.
The Interactive interface and
the Graphique interface.
If we want to create basic
instances,
which is probably the case,
then the Balle class must
imperatively
give a concrete definition of
the 'gestionClic'
and 'dessiner' (= draw) methods.
Note that in Java, it is
totally possible
to declare a hierarchy of
interfaces.
We'll say that an interface
extends another
and this is expressed with the
reserved word 'extends',
like with the classes.
For example, here we have
two interfaces
GerableParSouris (= manageable with the mouse) and
GerableParClavier (= manageable with the keyboard),
which both extend an Interactive
super-interface.
Here we indeed have a hierarchy
of interfaces
and two interactive
super-interfaces,
and two sub-interfaces
GerableParSouris
and by keyboard.
Before continuing,
let's go back to our first example of
a class implementing an interface,
to mention a point that can have
its importance.
We previously saw that, in
an interface,
the methods are de
facto public.
What happens if a class that
implements an interface
defines the method present
in the interface
but with rights different
that the public right?
So imagine for example
that here
I put the access right
'protected'.
Well this will simply be refused
by the compiler
because in Java, when you
redefine an existing method,
you are allowed to enlarge
the rights,
but never restrict them.
Note that this is
also valid
for the redefinition in the
context of inheritance.
For example, if I have a
super-class  A
of which inherits a
sub-class 'B',
if  A defines a method
m as 'public',
then the method's redefinition
can't restrict the
rights.
This will be refused.
By declaring an interface
in a Java program,
you in fact declare a
new type,
as it is the case when you
declare a new class.
It is therefore possible
to declare
a variable of 'interface'
type
like this, for example,
and to affect an object to it. But
be careful, not any object:
the object of a class that
implements this interface.
This is the case here,
so we affect to a variable of type Graphique,
an object
initially instantiated as a Balle.
So that it is possible, the 'Balle'
class must
obviously implement
the 'Graphique' interface.
In some situations, it can be
interesting
to manipulate the objects
through their interface
rather than through their initial type.
For example here, rather
manipulate a ball
as a graphical object, and
in this case,
it justifies this kind of
assignment.
Last small note:
knowing that we can perfectly assign
an object of a sub-class type to
a variable of super-class type,
this variable containing an object
of 'Balle' type,
which implements the 'Graphique'
interface.
Is it possible to assign this
variable
to an object of 'Graphique'
type?
So, this is possible, but
with a condition.
You must here reassure
your compiler
on the fact of what is contained
in the variable
is indeed an object that implements
the interface
in question, the 'Graphique'
interface.
To do so, we use type
conversion,
casting, here.
To summarize, the essential
function of an interface
is to attribute common
components
to classes that aren't linked with
an inheritance relation.
In our example, the 'Interactif'
interface
allowed us here to impose
a common content, a
'gestionClic' method,
to two classes, Balle and
Raquette for example,
which aren't related by an
inheritance relation.
We don't have 'Balle' inheriting
from 'Raquette' or vice versa.
An interface can have
constants,
that is, final, static, public
variables.
That's quite rare and requires
some discipline.
Why? Because there can be
a possible ambiguity, if, for
example, a class
implements two interfaces that each
contain the same constant.
Suppose for example that
in a program,
we have a first interface 'l1'
that contains the definition
of a constant,
and a second interface 'l2'
that would contain a constant
of the same name.
With possibly another value,
but not necessarily.
Now, if we want to declare
a class C
that implements the two
interfaces,
then there is clearly a problem,
an ambiguity:
which of the two constants
do we want to use?
This will be refused by
the compiler.
Another possible component
of an interface,
and the most common one:
the abstract methods.
And here we saw that
every class
that implements the interface, if
it wants to be instantiated,
must provide a concrete
definition of the method,
otherwise it can't be instantiated.
The interface therefore
allow to
impose to some classes to provide
a certain content without necessarily
using the notion of class and
abstract method.
Contrary to the case of
variables,
as the abstract methods don't
have any instruction lines,
there isn't any possible
ambiguity, for example,
if in the 'l1' interface
there's an abstract method m, and
in another
interface 'l2' there's also
an abstract method 'm', then a
class 'C'
can perfectly implement the
two interfaces
without making the compiler
react.
If it wants to be instantiated,
the 'C' class must, indeed, provide
a definition of the 'm' method,
no matter what imposes
its presence.
Note that the Java API
provides many predefined
interfaces, for example,
the 'comparable' interface
imposes to the classes that implement it
to provide a 'compareTo' method,
that takes an object of Object
type as an argument.
To conclude, let's look at what
relation types
set up an interface.
Typically, we saw that
inheritance allows us to use an
"is-a" relation type.
A ball "is an" entity of the game.
We also saw that when
a class
has as an object of another
class as an attribute,
then a "has-a" relation type
is established
between the two classes:
a warrior has a weapon.
Finally, an interface lets us
be reassured
that a class conforms to a
certain protocol,
and we'll say that the relation
that is set up
is a relation of type:
"behaves-as": a ball 'is-a'
game entity,
but it behaves like
a graphical object and an
interactive object.
And this concludes our episode
about Java interfaces.