As outlined in a previous video,
the concept of interfaces has received
important additions since Java 8.
The point of this video is to show
you these new concepts and particularly
the notion of interface default methods.
We have seen that, up until Java 7 included,
an interface could contain
constants as well as
abstract method signature.
This is of course still
possible for interfaces in
Java 8, but it is now also possible
to give these methods a body.
We can give a default definition
to an interface's methods,
this is a noteworthy addition.
It is also possible to give, to define
inside an interface a
number of static methods, in the
same way we define
static methods in a class.
In this video, we will
mostly show this part,
that is, default methods
in an interface.
The second part is the subject of a
PDF supplement that you can find
on the class' website.
To illustrate the notion of default
methods in an interface,
let us start with an example.
We will of course use our famous
example of game characters.
Suppose we now wish to model
the fact that certain
characters are able to ride mounts.
This means that these characters
would not be able to
have features relative to the
fact that they are riding a mount.
For example, is a character that is
riding a mount allowed to
dismount during gameplay?
How will they move around
while on this mount?
And so on.
Where to put these features
in our design ?
Suppose now that in our game,
only rogues and warriors are
able to ride mounts.
It does not make sense, in this case,
to put features related
to riding in the Personnage (="Character") class.
Here, it would not make sense to put
a 'seDeplace' (="moves") method indicating
how a character moves with a mount
in the Personnage class,
and neither would putting a 'peutDescendre'
(="can dismount") method in Personnage
indicating if a character is allowed
to get off his mount or not.
Why?
Well, simply
because the wizard is not able
to ride a mount, and so it does not
make sense to make him inherit
methods 'seDeplace' and 'peutDescendre'.
Hence it is normal, here, to rather put
these methods in an
interface, here the interface
'Chevauchant' (="Riding").
We would put in that interface
methods typically relative to
moving around with a mount,
or to check how we can
use this mount, for example
if we can dismount or not.
Here is what the 'Chevauchant'
interface could look like.
This interface could contain
the signature of a 'seDeplace' method,
which would be used
to indicate how moving
while riding would work, as well as
a method 'peutDescendre' returning a boolean
and indicating whether
or not one can dismount.
You can see that this is
the same as what was shown for
interfaces in Java versions
before Java 8.
We have here two abstract method statements:
each class that we would
like to be instantiable and which would
implement the Chevauchant interface
will necessarily
provide a concrete
implementation of these two methods
just to be instantiable.
Let's see what it is possible
to do from Java 8,
and let us suppose that in most cases
a character riding a mount
cannot dismount.
Well since Java 8,
it is possible to specify this
behaviour inside the interface.
This is done by giving a default
definition to the 'peutDescendre' method.
In practice, this means that this
method can now have a body.
This body simply consists
of returning false,
which indicates that
one cannot dismount.
Every interface method
which contains a body,
that is, a concrete definition such
as this example, must be
prefixed with "default", without it
the compiler will call you out
by telling you that an abstract
method cannot have a body.
Remember, every method
header is automatically
abstract inside an interface,
even if this modifier,
the 'abstract' modifier,
is not explicitely written.
The formal syntax for the declaration
of a method with a default definition
in an interface is simply as follows:
you have the reserved keyword
'default' followed by the concrete
definition of the method,
thsi definition is done in exactly
the same way as what you do
inside a class, you put a header
followed by a body inside braces.
Of course, this addition raises
new problems.
We will see in the next part what
the usage rules for methods with a
default definition are.
Are we allowed to redefine them?
How do classes which implement
interfaces with default methods
use said methods?
But above all we will see how to
solve any ambiguities
that can result from using
these default definitions.
For example,
suppose we have an interface I
with a default definition
for a given method,
and suppose that a class C
which implements
interface I also contains
a method with the same signature
but potentially another definition.
Thus, we potentially have
a conflict.
Another example: suppose we have this time
two interfaces,
with each one containing a
default definition
for a same signature method.
Here, interface I1 has the method M
with a default definition,
similarly, interface I2
contains a default definition for
method M, too.
What happens if a
class implements both interfaces?
Here, again, we have a
potential conflict.
Four fundamental rules
govern the use
of default methods
in interfaces.
We will now show them to you.
The first rule is that default
method definitions are inherited.
Recall that we defined the 'Chevauchant'
interface as follows :
this interface had an abstract
method 'seDeplace'
as well as a default definition of a
'peutDescendre' method, returning false
to indicate that
the default behaviour of
a mounted character was
never dismounting.
It is entirely possible to
define a sub-interface,
here sub-interface 'Cavalier' (="Rider"),
of the 'Chevauchant' interface,
which does not explicitely redefine
the 'peutDescendre' method.
If a rider has as default behaviour
never dismounting,
then the definition inherited
from super-interface 'Chevauchant'
is enough,
and in that case,
we do not redefine that method
and keep the inherited one.
You will have realised that it is
possible to implement in a
sub-interface, here 'Cavalier',
a default definition for
an abstract method, which was abstract
in 'Chevauchant', from which it inherits.
This is the case here with method 'seDeplace';
a rider has a concrete definition of
the 'seDeplace' method,
which was not the case in
super-interface 'Chevauchant'.
A rider goes at a trot.
Here, a class implementing the 'Cavalier'
class would have a 'peutDescendre'
method whose default definition
returns false, and a 'seDeplace'
method which has the default behaviour,
that is, going at a trot.
We have said it wasn't necessary
to redefine a 'peutDescendre'
method in 'Cavalier' if we are
satisfait with the default definition
inherit from above, but, of course, if we
are not satisfied with it,
nothing is stopping us from redefining
what was inherited,
just like we did for classes,
so here, for example, we can imagine
an alternative design of the 'Cavalier'
interface, which would have not only
a default definition of 'seDeplace',
but also a redefinition of the
'peutDescendre' method which would this time,
for example, return true, indicating
that a rider has as default behaviour
the ability to dismount.
Rule number two: a class which
implements an interface
is not required to give
concrete definitions
for methods having default
definitions in the interface.
For example, suppose the 'Guerrier' (="Warrior")
class implements the 'Cavalier' interface,
this interface had two methods,
'seDeplace' and 'peutDescendre', which
had both default definitions;
in this case
the 'Guerrier' class can
be instantiated as is,
it does not have to redefine
these two methods.
This is the main reason
for the existence of
default methods in interfaces.
Indeed, Java's API contains
numerous predefined interfaces
implemented by a number of classes.
Before Java 8, it wasn't possible,
without default methods,
to edit an external interface
by adding a method,
without having to change all classes
implementing this interface.
In concrete terms,
suppose we have
in the API an interface I,
with a number of methods.
Keeping it simple, here,
two methods, m1 and m2;
suppose that a lot of classes
implement this interface.
We take two here, as an example.
So, classes C1 and C2, both
implementing interface I.
Both class here are not abstract,
which means that we want them
to be instantiable; for them
to be instantiable,
they must necessarily give a concrete
definition of methods m1
and m2; so if these classes exist
and are compilable,
it is because they have
a concrete definition
of the methods given by
the implemented interface.
So, same here for m2.
And we would need to do the same in the
interface, in the class, sorry, C2.
Now, suppose that,
our needs evolving with time,
we realize interface I
also needs a method m3.
What happens to existing code?
Well, simply,
if we write it like this, the existing
code does not compile any more.
Classes C1 and C2 are not abstract,
and so,
like what we did for m1 and m2,
we would need to edit
these classes to give a concrete
definition to m3.
Being able to give a
default definition
for method m3,
lets us work around this problem.
According to this rule,
a class implementing an interface
is not obligated to redefine
a method which has a default definition,
and in this case there is no need to define m3
inside the classes
so that these classes stay
compilable and instantiable.
The two rules we just examined
determine how we can
write and use interface methods,
with default definitions.
Let us now look at the two rules
relative to potntial conflicts,
as shown before.
To begin with, what happens if a
class implementing an interface
defines a methods which already had
a default definition in the interface?
For example, suppose the 'Guerrier' class
implements the 'Cavalier' interface,
which contains a default definition
of the 'seDeplace' method.
Suppose that same class, 'Guerrier',
already has an alternative definition
of the 'seDeplace' method, here by
inheritance from the 'Personnage' class.
Here, we are in a slightly different context
than that of our introductory example,
we have a design in which a
general method, 'seDeplace',
is present from the start
in the superclass 'Personnage'.
The question is: how to solve the
ambiguity between this general
'seDeplace' method, and the one with
the same name in interface 'Chevauchant'?
Will the warrior move by running,
or at a trot?
Well, the rule chosen
by Java, is that methods from
classes have priority,
have precedence, over any default
definitions in an interface.
Here, if I declare an instance of the
'Guerrier' type, and invoke the 'seDeplace'
methoed, in this instance, the definition
from the class
will be chosen, and so the warrior will
move by running.
Of course, if we rather want the
interface's method to be used,
it is completely possible
to specify that.
To do that, the 'seDeplace'
method must be redefined
in the 'Guerrier' class,
and it must specify that the method
from the interface is to be used.
So, here, the method 'seDeplace' is
is redefined in the 'Guerrier' class,
it is redefined such as to invoke the
method, the default definition of the
'seDeplace' method, as it was
defined in the 'Cavalier' interface.
To invoke a method with a default
definition in an interface,
we put the name of the interface,
then a dot, then the reserved keyword
'super', another dot, and the name of
the method with the default definition.
Note here the usage of reserved
keyword 'super'.
This keyword is used to differenciate
between invoking a
method with a default definition
and invoking a static method from
the interface.
For example, it is possible to declare
an interface like this,
putting in it methods with default
definitions, which we now know
how to do, but also to put in
static methods,
in the same way we can put
static methods in a class.
Suppose a class C
implements interface I,
if we want to invoke a method
from the interface
inside one of C's methods,
we proceed as follows.
So, to invoke the static method,
we put the name of the interface,
then a dot,
then the name of the static method.
To invoke the method with default
definition, we use the name of the
interface, followed by 'super', then the
name of the method with default definition.
Note the distinction, here:
to invoke a static method of an interface,
we put the name of the interface,
then the name of the method;
it is exactly the same
syntax as the one used to invoke
a static member from a class.
However, to invoke a method with
a default definition,
we insert the reserved keyword 'super'.
Remember that static interface
are the subject of a PDF
complement on the course website.
Small remark, here, before continuing,
these two interface methods
cannot have the same name.
The compiler does not accept an interface
method with the same signature
to be at the same time static
and also have a
default definition.
What happens, now, if a class
implements two interfaces, with
both containing a default definition
for the same method?
Here, for example,
we have two interfaces:
'Dragonnier' (="Dragon Rider"), and
'se téléporte' (="teleports").
Both of these interfaces have a
default definition for a 'seDeplace'
method, with exactly the same
signature in both cases.
We have here a class, 'Mage Ultime'
(="Ultimate Mage"), which implements
both interfaces; when we invoke
the 'seDeplace' method
on an instance of 'Mage ultime', which
one of the two methods is invoked?
We have here a conflict.
The rule adopted by Java to solve
such situations is that
classes which implement conflicting interfaces
are required to remove the
ambiguity themselves.
For example, the 'Ultimate Mage'
class, which implements both
conflicting interfaces, must redefine
the 'seDeplace' method, to specify
which of the two it wants to use,
Which of the two default definitions,
from the interfaces, it will use.
Here the choice is made,
towards the default definition contained
in the 'Dragonnier' interface.
The 'seDeplace' method from 'Mage Ultime'
is redefined such as to invoke the
'seDeplace' method as it was default
defined in the 'Dragonnier' interface.
Nothing prevents us, of course, from
choosing instead the 'seDeplace' method
from the 'se téléporte' interface.
In this case, the 'seDeplace'
method is redefined in
'Mage ultime' such as to
choose the 'seDeplace' method
as it is defined in the
'se téléporte' interface.
A lot of other implementations are,
of course, possible; and nothing prevents
the 'Mage ultime' class from
redefining the 'seDeplace' method
such as to use the default definitions
from both interfaces.
Here you have an example of a
definition of 'seDeplace' which calls,
in certain conditions, 'seDeplace' from
the 'se téléporte';
and in other conditions the 'seDeplace'
method from 'Dragonnier'.
If the ultimate mage can dismount, then
they move by teleporting, otherwise,
well, they move like a dragon rider.
With the introduction of default
definitions in interfaces, their content
is now very close to that of
abstract classes.
We can now indeed put inside an interface
not only abstract methods,
which was already the case before
Java 8, and we can also add
methods which now have a concrete
definition by default.
That puts them very close to
the concept of abstract class.
We can thus ask ourselves when to
choose on option
over another.
Well, one of the biggest differences
is that an interface cannot
specify a state,
it cannot contains attributes.
For example,
it is not possible to define
what the rider's mount is in
the 'Cavalier' interface.
Here, I cannot put an attribute like
'Monture' (="Mount") in 'Cavalier'.
Being able to specify an attribute
would let us specify a state
for the rider: depending on
which mount they are riding,
they would be in such or such state; this
is not possible in an interface.
The other difference,
which is inherent to the notion of state,
is the lack of constructor;
it is inherent to the notion
of state, since the
constructor is used to initialise
attributes, but there are none.
To sum up, though, no state,
no constructor.
The general rule one should follow is that if
what we want to modelise is a
behavioural, functional aspect,
like moving around, independent of state,
of an object, then we will favour
using interfaces.
The implements relation
is much more flexible,
less restricting than that of
inheritance while designing.
Remember finally that the main point
of default definitions
for methods in interfaces,
is not to copy multiple
inheritance, or to bring an alternative
to abstract classes,
but it is to allow
adding new methods
to existing interfaces,
without penalising existing code,
that is, without having to edit
a class implementing those interfaces.
And this concludes this video on
post Java 7 interface specificities.