Hello and welcome to this fifth MOOC module
on the management of protected areas in Africa.
This week we will look at some specific aspects
of the management of protected areas.
This module is structured as follows:
The first class will be about culture
and how it can, not only
be part of the values of a protected area
but also how it can enhance conservation.
The second class will focus on the training
of staff
and partners of protected areas.
You can imagine that this is a vital point
for us.
In the third class, we will dive into marine
protected areas.
The fourth class will be about the conservation
of species
of fauna and flora through protected areas
with a particular focus on the red list.
The fifth class will focus on an important
tool for promoting
and valuing protected areas: tourism.
The last focus for the week,
and this has become a habit, will be about
a convention, this time
about CITES.
This deals with the international trade
of endangered species.
And finally, we will have a brief recap
of the main points covered in this module
and then the homework.
Here we go!
Enjoy an excellent fifth week with us!