- Hello Geoffroy.
- Hello Paul.
Hello everyone.
Today's lesson is dedicated to culture
or, more precisely, to the benefits of taking
culture in account
in approaches that relate to protected areas.
You can refer to the guidelines
of the World Commission on Protected Areas
for sacred sites, in addition to this lesson.
Of course, it's important to keep in mind
that the religious side you're talking about,
like all these sacred sites, that the guidelines
are refering to,
this religious dimension is just a part of
culture.
Culture is a bit complicated, it's a human
institution
based on customs, traditions and conventions.
On the contrary, nature has been for a long
time perceived as a solid reality
on which mankind didn't have any control,
or little.
Obviously today, we see that the action of
man
is changing the world,
this is what we call anthropocene.
So culture, that seemed to derive from nature
is about to become
on the contrary, one of the elements that
determine its evolution.
Yes, now we do not perceive nature
in opposition to culture
but as two elements that are closely related.
For a few decades in Africa,
and as we saw in the class on governance,
decentralization policies encouraged
some local communities to dedicate themselves
to conservation
of the areas they control
by building on their cultural framework.
Exactly, sometimes sacred territories
got the status of protected area,
which sort of legalized their role in conservation
that was initiated by the religious approach,
local sanctuaries thereby became respected
protected areas.
They have the double advantage of combining
cultural and natural
dimensions, that African communities refer
to a lot
even today.
When it happens,
the creation of such protected areas gives
the possiblity
to collect knowledge and traditional wisdom
that reinforce the viability of the conservation
network.
Indeed, the existence of terrestrial sites
usually relies on
the practice of initiation, which uses forest
areas
that have usually maintained a great diversity
of flora,
and occasionally fauna,
because of prescriptions, like prohibitions
and taboos
that are sometimes advocated, reinforcing
the interest for conservation.
Yes, absolutely.
Some swamps or river sites exist as well.
Their identification is sometimes harder
because marking the area is more difficult
or it is temporary and evolves with time.
The example of Bijagos in Guinea-Bisseau is
interesting
because lots of small islands are accessible
only at certain times, and only for certain
initiated people.
So this tendency to use culture
in order to preserve the environnement,
is global,
widely supported by international commitments,
like the Aichi targets for instance, that
you talked about earlier and
that we see here.
We listen to Paul Ndiaye talking about Agenda
21.
Agenda 21 mentions that indigenous populations
and communities
and other local authorities have a vital role
to play
in the management of environnement and developement
because of their knowledge of the area and
their traditional practices.
States should recognize their identity, their
culture
and their interests, providing every necessary
support.
Here we have another justification for taking
in account
cultural realities
in order to reinforce the conservation system,
especially in Africa.
The Convention on Biological Diversity also
recognizes
the importance of culture in conservation
and the necessity of promoting the traditional
knowledge
that supports it,
especially the article 8 (j) and the Nagoya
protocol.
Let's see how it works in the field.
A play is being performed
about the settling in of new users
that kill lamantins
which is forbidden by the rules
of the commnunity protected area.
It's very important because culture
is one of the pillars of marine protected
areas,
here we can organize cultural groups,
start an animation process
and encourage cultural updates by young people.
It's important to be careful.
Even if nature and culture are frequently
associated in Africa,
they have characterics
that make it sometimes difficult for their
effective integration
within a conservation approach.
Here's an example to understand the problem.
Here we see the map of Niokolo-Koba in Senegal,
it's a pretty homogeneous natural space,
surrounded by different cultures.
It can be pretty complicated to harmonize
the rules,
between, on one hand the north,
essentially mobile muslim shepherds ,
and on the other hand, in the south,
sedentary Bassari hunters gatherers, mostly
animists
who developped all sort of practices
to catch animals.
They all speak with the manager of the park
but the way he is going to approach them depends
on
their cultural differences
and the manager will have to take their cultural
identities
into account to manage his park.
Many areas that became protected
are the results of a reconversion of sacred
territories,
such as sacred wood, places for libation,
totemic elements, or various sanctuaries for
spirits:
for instance the national Park of Orango
in Bijagos islands of Guinea Bissau
or National Park of the Madeleine islands
not far from Dakar, Senegal, that we see on
this picture.
The cultural dimension becomes more significant
when it is the origin of the guarantee
of respect of integrity for the protected
area.
Then, it's not surprising that pilgrimages,
mystic rituals
and all kind of ceremonies take place there.
Apart from sacred sites,
obviously, for culture and nature to go together,
requires a good amount of communication
between different stakeholders.
Some studies actually show that
biological diversity often goes
with cultural diversity,
because different cultural frameworks
can help preserve different values.
Therefore, knowledge, customs, traditional
practices
can be the basis of the persistence
of a protected area, and even of its resilience.
We think, for instance, about the use of fire
for maintaining savanna landscapes,
in particular in sites of category four or
five
where the influence of humans is major.
Protected areas, made from cultural values
present specific requirements.
They can belong to almost every IUCN category,
especially categories number two,
four, five,
or just to a small number of them, depending
of the diversity,
of the conditions of their creation.
Most protected areas
that result from this process
have small territories,
sometimes only a few acres,
like the Madeleine islands.
Unless a decision from the State gives them
a more bigger
territory extension,
for example in the case of Orango, here on
this picture.
I agree with you.
But their is still a doubt about the sustainability
of these protected areas
because they are threatened by the erosion
of values
that were the reason for their creation.
They depend of the survival of practices
that are, themselves, sensitive to the decrease
of traditional values,
especially in the cities.
Plus, people who hold
knowledge and traditional power are almost
always old,
in small numbers and often poorly known
and less and less recognized.
This raises the problem of knowledge transmission
useful to preserve this kind of protected
areas.
So, using the strengths of local cultures
to stimulate the conservation of natural heritage
is a challenge
and at the same time, I want to say,
almost a duty,
because it's now admitted
that the values of protected area, which we
talked about a lot,
combine culture and nature
in an intangible whole
which is greater than the sum of its parts.
One of our goals must be to use every opportunity
to enlarge the network of conservation
and spaces traditionaly preserved
for cultural reasons
represent an interesting potential use of
territory.
Indeed.
Here we are.
Already at the end of the lesson.
The next episode will be on capacity building
for protected areas.
- Bye Geoffroy.
- See you soon
Have a great day.