Hello and welcome to today's course
which is about protected areas staff training.
For more information, you can check
the guidelines of the 17th volume
of the World Commission on Protected Areas
on the subject.
Also, take a look at this practical guide
developed by FIBA.
It is short, specific, and informative.
This is our colleague Elise Mazeyrac from
WCS in Gabon
who will be helping me today.
She heads the CEDAMM training center in Lopé
National Park
and trains many field practitioners.
Elise, why is training for Protected Areas
so important?
Training is more than just learning,
it is a tool to respond to changes
and to respond accordingly in managing protected
areas,
so it is a strategic investment.
In Africa, the establishment of protected
areas
has unfortunately not always led
to needed policy changes or much-needed training,
and not often enough
to good training of people recruited to implement
these measures.
Furthermore, we too often see continued education
as harm reduction,
whereas the lack of initial training
is the result of a lack of available courses
tailored to the management of Protected Areas
in Africa.
Training enables us to meet
both qualitative and quantitative staffing
requirements
for the management of Protected Areas and
their changing needs over time.
For the individual, learning these skills
can strengthen personal motivation.
For a service provider, a Protected Area,
or an institution
in charge of the management of Protected Areas,
training enables to face issues of staff turnover
for some jobs or a lack of required skills.
Or it can motivate well-performing staff
by opening up new career opportunities for
them.
As the context of conservation evolves
so do the skills expected from managers.
We understand that we need to think and plan
ahead
if we want to align training with needs,
without forgetting the different categories
of Protected Areas.
As we have seen in a previous module,
training is more than teaching.
Prior to conducting training there needs to
be the identification,
analysis, and understanding of the context
and needs,
and the development of training activities
according to a plan or a strategy
which will specifically address these needs.
It is only then that the completion of the
training itself can take place.
Finally, of course, the training must be assessed.
Actually, here we find the steps
of the management-cycle of a Protected Area
as we encountered them in our lesson on planning.
So now let's see if Africa has any specific
needs
for the people involved
in terms of managing Protected Areas.
The needs of Protected Areas can differ wildly,
but have common aspects,
especially for countries in French-speaking
Africa
where there are some specificities related
to regional contexts.
Numerous studies have shown
that needs can be classified into two broad
categories.
First, the specific needs
for the management of Protected Areas, for
instance ecological monitoring,
a knowledge of biodiversity, ecology, and
planning,
for management, anti-poaching, the rights
of Protected Areas,
of the environment, etc.
And then on the other hand,
there are the so-called cross skills that
are not specific
to the management of Protected Areas, but
which have a major impact on it.
For example, the management of human resources,
the planning and financial management, logistics,
mechanics, IT.
So in each of these categories, the tools
and the level of skills expected
will vary according to the position and context.
So, there many needs, which isn't really surprising.
But how can we respond effectively?
Training can be done in a room with a trainer,
but can include many other aspects depending
on the context
such as the objectives and expected skills,
or available means.
The first step is to plan training, by analyzing
the context,
the current situation, and the expected situation.
From there, it's possible to develop a training
program
which is as suitable as possible.
There are several methods for training.
There is obviously face-to-face training in
a room with a trainer
and a variety of teaching tools.
But there are also other ways such as distance
learning
be it with a tutor or in self-study like this
MOOC
you are currently taking.
There's also training at the workplace, apprenticeships
where the learner shares his or her time between
periods of theory and practice.
Some courses confer diplomas or certificates
whereas others only attest to training having
been followed.
They can be done on site, in the Protected
Area,
or in another place by relocating people.
They may be in a school, a university, a training
center,
and also in any place suited to the required
needs.
Let's see what types of courses are offered
to the managers of Protected Areas and their
partners, e.g. at CEDAMM.
In CEDAMM with PAPACO and at Senghor University,
we have developed a college degree
on the management of Protected Areas.
In two months, this course covers eight modules
of one-week each,
many required priority skills which are specific
to the planning,
monitoring, and evaluation of the management,
the rights of the environment.
It also includes techniques of inventory,
practices, and concepts of ecology, etc.
There are also short courses, ad hoc training
which last from several days to weeks,
e.g., training in GPS navigation to the use
of software such as SMART
for monitoring the application of the law
or the collection and analysis
of data on large mammals in the forest.
It also serves to collect socio-economic data
with tools like MARP, and BNS,
or the use of picture traps for ecological
monitoring.
We are always looking to develop flexible
training
which is reactive and based on tools and practical
skills
by involving more and more partners in conservation
but not only that,
also to meet the skill needs in Protected
Areas.
Finally, there is the difficult but essential
question:
How do we measure the impact of such training
in the field?
Measuring the impact of training on the field
is essential.
This will assess and develop our training
activities.
It is also a necessary step
to measure whether or not the training has
impacted the field,
changed practices, or improved the ability
to manage Protected Areas.
But it is often difficult to be sure that
improvements in practices
can be attributed to training.
And often the positive impacts are multifactorial:
the availability of resources, internal recognition
policy,
team motivation etc.
But thanks to recent studies, with former
graduates of our University Diploma,
for instance, we can see there is a change
in professional attitudes
and in improvement in knowledge, and its practical
implementation.
For example, the training in monitoring large
mammals:
more than half of those trained in this method
in 2012
conducted ecological monitoring in the year
following their training.
The courses also allow for personal development.
This is supported by a study
conducted with graduates from our DU in Central
Africa,
where 30% of graduates got a promotion
within the 18 months following their training.
In the same way, every graduate said they
feel more comfortable
in their professional activities,
and almost 3/4 have more responsibilities.
Finally, one of the effects of training which
is too often underestimated
is the fact that they lead to the networking
of practitioners.
This networking continues beyond the time
of training
and leads to the sharing of practices and
experiences.
It allows the creation and consolidation of
a network of practitioners.
Well, that's the end of the class.
The next episode will focus on the specific
management
of marine Protected Areas.
Have a great day!