This sequence will focus on marine protected
areas.
We will look at the definition of a marine
protected area,
its key-features,
why marine protected areas are created, their
purpose,
and lastly, the main challenges in the management
and the creation of marine protected areas.
Let's look at the definition.
What is a marine protected area?
The first definitions were written
at the Fourth World Parks congress
in Caracas in 1992.
In 1999, IUCN adopted the following definition:
"Any area of intertidal or subtidal terrain,
together with its overlying water and associated
flora and fauna,
historical and cultural features,
which has been reserved by law or other effective
means
to protect part or all of the enclosed environment."
This is the definition that is commonly adopted
and is found in most manuals and reference
guides.
Note however, that in 2008,
the IUCN congress adopted a new definition
of protected areas.
This definition, to my mind,
hightlights marine protected areas.
they are a clearly-defined geographical space,
recognized, dedicated, and managed
through legal or other effective means to
achieve
the long-term conservation of nature with
associated
ecosystem services and cultural values.
I want to emphasize three points:
First, it is a defined space,
so delimitation is required.
This is a challenge for marine protected areas.
Note the strong emphasis on conservation.
Conservation is the primary objective of the
protected area.
This implies a clear demarcation, in my opinion
between sites that have as their main objective
conservation,
and sites for which the primary purpose
may be sustainability or extraction of resources,
such as fishing.
Note also that this space must be managed.
This involves management actions of the protected
area.
There are now some 12,000 marine protected
areas.
Coverage of 2.8% is the official figure given
at the IMPAC Conference 3
in October 2013, held in Marseille.
I would emphasize
that recent studies suggest even higher figures.
The Protected Planet Report 2014 mentions
3.4%.
Please note that until recently, we were talking
of only 0.65% coverage
of the oceans and seas as marine protected
areas.
The number of MPAs therefore jumped
from about 200 in the 1970s to over 12,000
today.
We've done well.
However, please note:
1) We're still well below the Aichi target
of 10% by 2020
and 2) It remains to be seen that management
is effective
in all these protected areas.
Note also, on this map,
that their distribution is very uneven.
Some regions have high coverage,
such as Oceania, in particular.
Africa, on the other hand has less than 3%
coverage
in most countries.
There's a lot of work to to do, especially
in Africa.
Let's see the characteristics of an MPA.
First of all I would like to emphasize that
a marine protected area,
is firstly a protected area.
The IUCN guidelines state
that the same management principles apply,
the same modes of governance can be applied
to an MPA,
for instance, a Community MPA.
So, all you have studied so far
will apply to the marine protected area.
But let's have a look at some of its special
features.
First, it is a fluid environment,
which is open in three dimensions.
A marine protected area incorporates,
in general, multiple ecosystems
such as marine, terrestrial, and wetlands.
This makes things a little more complicated.
The value of a marine protected area is less
visible,
and is more difficult to quantify.
It is under water, hidden, and inaccessible.
The applicability of the principles of management
frameworks
is not always clear-cut,
and these are often difficult, if not impossible,
in the case of monitoring, for instance.
Also, note that the guides and manuals
were often written for terrestrial protected
areas
with few references to marine specifics.
It is particularly difficult to control inputs
and activities, to delineate areas
and the installation of demarcation buoys
in the marine environment
is a special challenge and often impossible.
The level of scientific knowledge
is considered less advanced than on terrestrial
ecosystems
as there's less education, less funding, and
consequently, less knowledge.
Let's see now why we would create an MPA.
You will have noted that the first reason
to create a marine protected area
is the conservation of its resources,
ecosystems, habitats, and species.
I know you're going to say
that a marine protected area is pretty, and
this is true,
beauty and wellness is important for communities
and for visitors
and should not be overlooked.
But let's look at all the other reasons
to create a marine protected area.
Among the many motivations alongside the goal
of conservation,
MPAs have an important role to play
in protecting marine and coastal biodiversity.
Known as "The blue planet",
more than 70% of the surface of earth is covered
by water
and is the host to remarkable marine and coastal
biodiversity
and an important gene pool.
I would also point out
that MPAs are one of the tools of coastal
management.
As part of an integrated policy on the management
of coastal areas,
MPAs play a fundamental role in managing and
minimizing the pressures
on the environment and resources
so as to mitigate and reduce the impact of
global change.
Look at this map:
over 60% of the population lives in coastal
areas.
This creates pressures,
both in terms of urban planning and in terms
of pollution and waste.
Here we have the global map of human impacts
on marine ecosystems.
You can see that certain areas of the globe
are particularly impacted.
Finally, here's a world map on climate risk.
Take a look at this map which highlights the
pressures
and the multiple effects of global change
and climate change.
So you will understand
that the coastal zone is subject to strong
pressures,
and it plays a vital part in fighting these.
I'll refer here to the role of mangroves
in mitigating the impacts of natural disasters,
such as tsunamis or cyclones.
In terms of motivation, I would stress the
importance
of marine and coastal natural resources
for the food and economic security of local
populations.
The MPAs, through their fishery resources,
also contribute
to the economic development of countries.
Note that many MPAs were created with that
goal in mind,
such as preserving the breeding grounds and
nurseries,
thus being one of tools of fishery management.
However, this graph makes it quite clear
that fish stocks decline sharply,
and that they are either fully exploited,
as seen in the yellow column,
or overexploited, as seen in the the orange
column,
and the brown band represents those for which
the stocks have collapsed.
None of the commercially exploited species
are seeing their stocks grow at present.
Let's look now at the main challenges
in the creation and management of a marine
protected area.
Firstly, these aim to strengthen
the management capabilities of marine protected
areas.
Training, awareness, and exchanges on the
ground are important.
This is so as to better define the values
and the effects of an MPA.
I invite you, if you have time to read over
these references.
One of the challenges too
is to establish coherent and representative
networks of MPAs.
Here, the example of the network of marine
protected areas
in West Africa called RAMPAO.
Note also the Mediterranean network, MedPAN,
applies.
These networks have a charter and governance,
and they implement capacity-building activities,
grants, exchanges and sharing.
They have a strong role to play,
both representing MPAs with policies and with
international donors.
Finally, in terms of challenges,
one of the main challenges right now
is to create marine protected areas on the
high seas
in areas which are very little protected.
The other challenge of course is funding,
finding how to finance
the creation of marine protected areas and
their management.
That's it, this sequence is completed, and
there's a lot in it.
I invite you to read the background documents.
For more, go and visit a marine protected
area,
and go and talk to their managers to find
out more.
Good day.