Hello.
In this sequence, we are going to study
the different aspects of tourism inside protected
areas.
Tourism can have a positive impact on protected
It can provide funding for the protected area
and its communities,
help to raise awareness among visitors and
communities alike,
and maintain the landscapes.
It can also have a negative impact:
pollution, degradation,
it usually requires a lot of resources,
water, food, and space.
It can also have a significant cultural and
social impact
with the population and with the communities.
Note that tourism differs a lot
across the protected areas.
In some countries, particularly in East Africa,
there are more than 100,000 visitors per year,
who want to see the wildlife, the megafauna,
present in these PAs.
Other protected areas only have a few.
Now, let's take a look at those differences.
For this sequence, I encourage you to refer
to three manuals and guides.
The first one is in French : Le tourisme dans
les aires protégées d'Afrique de l'Ouest.
I also invite you to read the analytical report
of the evaluation on Marine Protected Areas
by the FFEM,
and in particular the sixth section, on tourism
management in MPA.
Lastly, read the IUCN guidelines
Sustainable Tourism and Protected Areas,
It has stayed a reference guide and it is
in English.
The experiences accumulated in the different
protected areas,
as you will see it in your reference documents,
can lead us to distinguish different kinds
of tourism
in terms of their impact, the income
that these activities can provide,
on a local, national, or even international
level.
We can divide these touristic activities into
five groups.
On one hand, high-end tourism.
It is sought after to generate funds.
The drawbacks: generally not a very good impact
on the environment,
and most of the time, profits leaving the
country.
Medium to low-end tourism, can be a good source
of revenue
for the protected area,
most of it will be produced by concessions
entrance fees.
But it also has a lot of impact on the environment.
Sustainable and/or responsible tourism
can create a variety of jobs, easily accessible
for the communities.
There is little impact on the environment,
and profit that goes directly or indirectly
to the communities.
Be wary, this kind of tourism can be quite
volatile,
and you need a solid partnership to make it
work.
The community tourism is often the one preferred
by the communities.
Here again, direct jobs, although few in numbers
small impact, and direct and immediate profits
for the population.
Only, it's often on a very small scale,
and needs a lot of supervisory work.
Lastly, scientific tourism, present only scarcely,
in protected areas,
but which can prove very profitable.
It requires significant investments.
Let's look together at ecotourism,
or community tourism in protected areas,
with an excerpt of a video shot in Senegal,
in Casamance, and in the Bamboung park.
The modern tourist wants
to go to villages inside marine protected
areas.
Because when you go there, you can see everything.
They come here, to la Pointe Saint-Georges,
to see manatees, because it's quite rare,
nowadays.
The customers who come here are interested
in ecotourism,
in the environment, and in what we are doing.
Also, the campsite is on a island,
where it's calmer, more quiet and relaxing,
with an important diversity.
I think that's why our clientele
comes here in Bamboung instead of going to
expensive hotels.
The campsite was built
in order to secure the future of the MPA,
the Marine Protected Area of Bamboung.
The main goal is to be able
to pay the ecoguards,
pay for the oil so that they can
patrol the protected area.
Then, it's also contributing to the local
economy.
Every month, there is a part of the profit
that goes to the marine protected area, and
to the rural community of Toubacouta.
One of the assets of the campsite
is that we put forward the discovery of the
area,
the visitors find themselves in the heart
of the mangrove,
so it's both beautiful, pleasing, but also
very enlightening
because they can be in contact
with the wildlife,
with the ecosystem of the mangrove.
Now, let's take a look at the role of the
Protected Area's manager
with regard to tourism.
First, he will have to promote
the development of sustainable tourism.
We are looking for community or ecological
tourism
to develop as an alternative or additional
activity
for the communities and local population.
The manager will also have a preventive and
accompanying role
for the touristic development.
The goal is to anticipate and reduce the risks
and impacts.
We will then conduct impact studies, a survey
to establish
if the protected area can sustain a large
enough number of people.
We will conduct a business plan in order to
anticipate risks,
and manage conflicts between the parties involved.
For example, between the fishermen and tourism,
we will study in particular, the social aspects.
Lastly, we will make informative content available,
for both the visitors and the population.
The other role of the manager is to keep some
of the income
from the tourism activities for the protected
area,
to fund part of its operations,
for example, the surveillance in some protected
areas.
All of this requires an active and attentive
role from the manager.
Now let's look at the benefits that the PA
can gain from this.
All the parties expect to get some profit
from tourism.
But the time scales to get these benefits
can vary.
Communities hope for quick earnings.
Private operators can't expect to obtain financial
equilibrium
before three to five years,
depending on the countries and the types of
hotel industry involved.
On an other hand, the autonomy of the protected
area,
thanks to the revenue of tourism,
cannot be achieved before many years, if it
ever comes,
even though substantial revenues can be earned
earlier.
The income from tourism falls into four categories:
The entrance fee to the protected areas, the
price of which can vary a lot.
It will be free in some areas
while it will cost 20 to 60 dollars in Tanzania,
or 9 to 20 dollars in South Africa, for example.
The license-fee on activities, in marine environment,
for example mooring sites, diving sites or
yachting.
License-fees on hotel concessions,
and other activities and sources of income
for the communities:
craft, local products, tourists guiding, etc.
Now let's insist on some key notions regarding
tourism in PAs.
Coming first, is the redistribution method
of the profits made.
It should be studied on a case by case basis.
The creation of a community fund is an interesting
solution.
It allows for the communities to claim a part
of the park's revenue
and to manage it directly.
In any case, it is important to evaluate
the potential benefits generated by tourism,
and to clarify in advance
the part going to the local population,
and the part going towards the operating of
the protected area.
We talked briefly about the manager's role
earlier.
We have to think about the role of the manager
in regards to tourism.
Sometimes, the protected area can be fully
involved
into managing and developing touristic activities.
Yet we can ask ourselves if the manager's
role
is really this one,
or if he should rather focus on making sure
that the touristic activities present in the
PA
do not impact it in any negative way,
like we saw earlier.
Note that tourism is also a business:
it is therefore recommended to establish partnerships
with tourism professionals
and to develop efficient tools with them:
a business plan, like we saw, is important,
so are load capacity studies,
and fair partnerships between the tour operator
and the park.
Lastly, good practices regarding tourism must
be developed at all levels.
In the relations with the communities, and
the choice of tourism sites,
in the adjustments needed
when construction or exploitation projects
are ongoing
where priority will be given to local materials,
workforce, etc.,
and in the field of touristic activities.
To develop a hotel industry that respects
the environment
is often a priority.
Take a look at some examples of labels like
Green Globe or others.
That's it, our sequence is over:
needless to say, tourism in protected area
also needs management.
It's not the jackpot,
even if income from tourism can bring substantial
revenues
and help to obtain financial stability for
the protected area.
I suggest that you read the reference manuals
for more information.
Have a nice day.