Hello and welcome to today's lesson
which is about the Convention on International
Trade
in endangered species of wild fauna and flora.
For more information, you can check out
the Convention's website, the address of which
is here:
For this course, I asked our WWF colleague,
Lamine Sebogo,
to help us this week.
He is based in Nairobi, Kenya.
He is specifically in charge of elephant conservation.
So, what is this agreement, and what is its
purpose?
This is CITES; CITES is The Convention
on International Trade in Endangered Species
of Wild Fauna and Flora.
We also call it the Washington Convention
because it was adopted in Washington in 1973.
This agreement is supposed to regulate international
trade
in species of wild fauna and flora
to ensure that trade does not lead to the
overexploitation of species
which may lead to their extinction.
But does the international trade
in endangered species or products derived
from them
really threaten the survival of these species?
This trade is a real threat to fauna and flora.
Let me make two points.
The first point is
that the trade is becoming increasingly important
because the demand for these products
is growing exponentially.
At some point,
nature itself may not be able
to supply the products that the market demands,
so that's a threat.
There will come a time when there will be
over-exploitation
which could compromise a species' survival.
The second remark is that CITES
specifically targets the trade in specimens
of certain endangered species threatened with
extinction.
Take the example elephants which are decimated
because of ivory,
and rhinos, because of their horns.
Even plant species such as rosewood from Madagascar
are affected.
There are many examples, but I will mention
only a few.
So when the trade
in these species is not regulated,
these species reach the threshold of extinction.
Let's see how the convention works in practice.
As we'll see, it's not so simple.
Under this agreement, species are grouped
into annexes.
There are a total of three annexes,
and species are combined according to their
degree of protection
which is their degree of threat.
You have for example, Annex 1,
which regroups really endangered species threatened
with extinction,
and these are species for which trade is prohibited.
The export, re-export of any specimen of these
species is prohibited
except under certain conditions including
research.
Species that are regrouped under Appendix
include species of fauna and flora.
Regarding fauna, we must mention mammals,
reptiles, and birds.
The African Elephant, for instance, is listed
under Appendix 1,
as are the great apes, including gorillas
and chimpanzees.
All are in Appendix 1 of CITES.
So the trade and international trade of all
of these species is banned.
The second category covers the species listed
in Appendix 2.
Appendix 2 includes species
for which the international trade in specimens
is allowed but regulated.
The trade in specimens of these species
requires an export certificate
or re-export certificate
to be issued by the exporting countries.
All this is to ensure that there is no over-exploitation
of these species.
There is control and regulation
so that the resulting use of these species
is sustainable.
The Guinea baboon, the white-bellied bustard,
and among other birds, the Madagascar sparrow
hawk,
and even the Royal Cobra are among these.
There is also the wild cat found in sub-Saharan
Africa.
All these species are part of Appendix 2.
Appendix 3 contains the list of species
proposed by member states.
Proposing a species for inclusion in Appendix
assumes it’s overexploitated at a national
level,
and that steps have already been taken at
a national level
to protect the species,
and that the co-operation of other states
is required.
I will cite the Dorcas gazelle as an example
of a species nominated for inclusion in Appendix
3.
The proposers were Tunisia and Algeria.
Regarding the species in Appendix 3,
the export document is the certificate of
origin
issued by the CITES bodies.
It must be said that both the export certificate
or re-export certificates
or other permits are issued by the country
of origin
under very strict conditions.
The elephant is a symbolic species for the
convention
as its possible trade for ivory causes many
problems.
What is the situation now?
The situation of the African elephant is as
follows:
the African elephant has a lot of problems.
The situation is not good!
The situation is not good,
and that is why all elephant populations in
Africa
were transferred to Appendix 1 of CITES.
Since 1989, if memory serves me correctly.
Meanwhile, there are other populations,
including elephant populations for four southern
African countries
which were transferred back to Appendix 2
of CITES.
The underlying reason for this reclassification
is that these populations are relatively well-managed.
There are four countries:
South Africa, Namibia,
Botswana, and Zimbabwe,
which benefited from a transfer to Appendix
2.
This allowed them
to legally trade their stocks,
twice, I think, under certain conditions.
Of course, this sparked much controversy.
There are people who think
that legal trade cannot coexist with illegal
trade,
believing that it is the legal trade which
itself contributes
to the exacerbation
of the illegal trade in ivory,
and therefore, increases poaching,
whereas others think that no, regulated legal
trade,
where it occurs,
does not lead to increased poaching.
Poaching however is not the only pressure
at work.
The loss and degradation of remaining habitats
and their fragmentation
poses a problem for the elephant's survival.
The elephants in West Africa are suffering
most
from the destruction and fragmentation of
their habitat.
There are also conflicts between them and
populations.
Many people have problems because they lose
their crops
and infrastructure is often destroyed.
But there are what we call indirect threats
which cause direct threats and demographic
pressure.
There are more and more people and more and
more mouths to feed,
and people need a lot of space
for human settlement and for their activities.
Added to this are major infrastructures
which are sometimes implemented
without their impact on conservation being
studied.
We now know the basics.
Please take the time to study the website
and browse CITES' Appendices to find out
what species you know or which live in your
Protected Areas
that are affected by this agreement.
This is the end of this lesson.
The next episode will focus
on concluding and setting your assignments
for next time.
Have a great day.