In this module,
we have seen how important it is to consider
culture
when looking into the conservation of protected
areas.
Sometimes, this can oppose conservation objectives,
but it is most often the case
that it is a quality that can help in the
protection of parks and reserves
when it is well understood and respected,
and enables the association of population
and local knowledge
to conservation efforts.
By the way, Ssome protected areas, make it
one of the values to be conserved
for the same reasons as the flora or fauna,
and some parks are directly born out of sacred
territories for example.
Education is another aspect in the development
of protected areas.
The management of these territories and their
partners need specific skills,
and these must be passed onto them
by programs which are adapted to the specificities
of Africa.
This training is also a crucial factor
when addressing necessary changes for protected
areas,
in terms of management and governance.
There are already many training courses available,
but there is a tremendous need,
whether in the classroom or online,
and this MOOC, we hope, will meet this need
on a modest scale.
The management of marine protected areas meets
the same requirements
as that of the protected areas in general.
However, specialized knowledge, methods, and
equipment are necessary,
as they are natural environments with different
balances and issues.
The areas are fluid and open,
resources are less visible and often not well
known,
even if they are especially coveted,
as much for food safety of the local populations,
as for the economies that depend on fishing.
Marine protected areas must also be considered
as one of the tools in coastal management,
more generally.
We can also approach management of protected
areas
via the species that inhabit them.
These are often good indicators
of the stakes and the pressures of the area.
These are also significant resources,
no matter how they are used, consumed or not.
They are unfortunately sometimes a source
of conflict
with neighboring populations,
and this requires the development of strategies
to control these nuisances.
A specific tool can help us to understand
and protect these species: the Red List
which defines their status and the urgency
of their conservation.
Tourism in protected areas can itself be linked
to these species in territories
which are still rich in emblematic animals
and flora.
It can be a source of revenue, for a good
number of sites,
providing advantages
both to the communities and to the protected
area itself.
It is also an important vehicle in raising
public awareness
of the importance of protecting these zones.
The manager's role is
partly one of support for tourism development,
in order to reduce the risks and the negative
impact, if there are any,
and partly a role of encouraging the development
of sustainable ecotourism,
producing, most often,
direct benefits for neighboring communities.
And finally, relating to plant and animal
species,
a specific agreement concerns the trade in
endangered animals and plants
to fittingly prevent their disappearance.
It is the CITES, which prohibits, or at least
regulates,
trade in these resources according to its
three appendices.
It is here particularly, that the major question
of the ivory and the rhinoceros horn trades
are discussed.
Let's now start the tests relating to this
module.