We now consider
Stochastic interest rate models.
In the first part,
I'll provide the basics
in Stochastic calculus,
that is needed for developing
Stochastic interest rate models.
We will then look at
short-rate models,
where the dynamics of the short-rate
is specified;
and in a second step
we'll look at so-called
Heath-Jarrow-Morton models, where,
the evolution of the entire
forward curve is specified,
as a Stochastic process.
Eventually, we will see
how these models can be used
to price options on bonds.
In this first part,
I recap the basic notions of
Stochastic calculus.
That is: Brownian motion,
the Stochastic integral
Ito formula,
the Girsanov theorem.
Obviously we cannot go into
the mathematical details.
But the good news is,
once you acquire the rules
of Stochastic calculus,
you can engineer any of
the following interest rate models.
I will also, in this part,
give you the basics for
pricing options,
namely,
the Arbitrage pricing theorem
We always fix a Stochastic basis.
Random variables are modeled on
a probability space.
This is a triple consisting of
the set of samples Omega;
and on this set of samples Omega
we have a structure
which is called a sigma algebra,
which is denoted by a caligraphic F.
This is the collection of
the so-called measurable events.
The probability measure P,
acts on the sigma algebra,
caligraphic F
and it assigns a probability to
any measuble event, A.
The flow of information
is modeled by a filtration.
This is an increasing family of
sigma algebras
indexed by time, t.
And F,t
represents the information
available by time, t.
Let's look at following example
which consists of a sample set
consisting of four samples.p
Suppose the probability assigns
the same weight
to each sample.
We have two time periods.
At t2,
the true state of
the nature is fully revealed
However at t1,
we can only tell whether
we are in the set,
cosisting of Omega 1 and Omega 2
or in the set consisting of
Omega 3 and Omega 4.
So the signma algebra F1
consists of the two sets:
Omega 1, Omega 2
and Omega 3, Omega 4.
At t0, the sigma algebra is trivial.
We cannot distinguish
any of the samples at time 0.
A stochastic proces
is a family of random variables
indexed by time t.
We usually suppress
the argument omega.
We call the stochastic process
adapted
if for any fixed time, t,
the random variable Xt
is Ft measurable.
We call Xt a martingale
if it is adapted
and such that,
at any time t.
The conditional expectation of
the future values
at some time point, T,
is just equal to the currently
prevailing value.
A martingale
is a model for fair game.
In the sense that on average,
you cannot gain more than
what you have today.
As an example,
consider again the Stochastic basis
from the previous slide;
and let's assume that Xt models
the price of a financial asset
at state T
and assume that Xt is adapted.
In the two period context
it means at t2,
we know the terminal price,
which is a function of
the state of the world.
At t1, we cannot anticipate
the future.
So, the asked price
must be the same
in the state Omega 1, Omega 2.
and also it must be the same
in the two states Omega 3, Omega 4.
At t0 we have no information yet,
and the asked prices is a constant.
The prototype of a martingale
in continuous time,
is a Brownian motion.
A standard Brownian motion, W,
is characterized by
the following four properties:
it is continuous and adapted process,
it starts at t0,
and its increments w(t2)-w(t1)
are independent of the past
and normally distributed
with mean 0 and variants proportional
to the time increment.
As I already said,
the Brownian motion is
a continuous martingale.
The figure on the right
shows four trajectories simulated
from a Brownian motion.
All trajectories start at 0.
As you can see,
Brownian motion has rough paths.
They are not smooth.
They are not differentiable.
And at any given point in time,
the expectation of
the Brownian motion is equal to 0.
A Brownian motion is
a Gaussian process
in the following sets:
We define a Stochastic process Z(t)
to be a Gaussian process
if its final dimensional distributions
are multivariate Gaussian
or normal distributed
for any finite selection
of time points t1 up to tn.
Since the multivariate normal distribution
is determined by its mean vector
and the covariance matrix,
it follows that the distribution
of a Gaussian process Z(t)
is determined by its mean function,
that we call m(t),
and the covariance function,
which gives the pair of covariances
of Zt1 and Zt2.
For any adapted process sigma(t),
whose trajectories are
square integrable in time,
we can define the Stochastic integral
with respect to a Brownian motion.
This is how we denote
the stochastic integral.
Even though the rigourous definition
of the stochastic integral
is a bit more involved,
we can think of it as being
the limit of remaining sums
as shown here.
Where we go over partitions of time
and let the mesh tend to 0.
It can be proved that
the stochastic integral
is a continuous martingale,
if the integral satisfies a somewhat
strong integrability condition.
The stochastic integral
will be the model for the risky part
of the return of an asset.
An ito process X(t)
is an adapted process
of the following form.
It can be decomposed
into an initial value,
plus a drift term,
plus a martingale term,
which is a stochastic integral.
Remember that the Brownian motion,
and therefore
the stochastic integral,
has rough trajectories.
The drift in contrast
has smooth trajectories
and models trends
in the evolution of X.
An ito process is thus
the ideal model for the price process
of a financial asset.
We often use
differential notation for X
where we omit the initial value
and write as shown here.
Keep in mind,
whenever we specify an ito process X
in differential notation,
there is always an initial value
to be specified with it.
Sigma is also called
the volatility of the process X.
It can be proved that
if the initial value, the drift,
and the volatility of X,
are deterministic functions,
then, the procss X(t)
is a Gaussian process
with the following mean and
covariance functions, as shown here.
It is easy to understand why
the mean function is as shown here,
because the martingale
has zero expectations.
We take for granted that
the second moment of the martingale
is given by
the integal of sigma² ds.
The core of stochastic calculus
is the ito formula.
It states that for
a C²-function f(x),
meaning, the function x
is twice continuously differentiable,
and for an ito process X(t)
which is given in
differential notation here,
the composiition f applied to X,
is again an ito process
with the composition given by that.
It is important to see
that real calculus
would give us a total derivative
that is underlined.
But this would only hold if X(t)
would have differentiable trajectories.
Recall that the stochastic integral
has rough trajectories
which are not differentiable,
which is inherited by X(t);
and that causes the appearance of
a second order correction term.
It also explains why this formula only
works for C²-functions f.
We need f to be twice
continuously differential.
There is also a multivariate version
of ito's formula
but I'll refrain from showing it here,
with the following exception:
The integration by parts formula.
It states that for
two ito processes X1 and X2,
both indifferential,
notation as shown here
the product X1 times X2
is again an ito process,
with the composition as shown here.
Again we realize that
this is the product rule
that we are knowing from real calculus;
but that holds only if X1 and X2
had differentiable trajectories.
Since they do not, due to
the stochastic integral,
we have the second order correction term.
As an example of ito's formula,
let's look at the exponential function
applied to an ito process X,
which is given in
differential notation here.
The decomposition of e to the X
is given by the sum of the derivative
of e to the X,
which is e to the x itself,
dX, plus
the second order correction term;
which involves the second order derivative
of the exponential function,
which is again
the exponential function itself.
Again, we see here
the fundamental differential equation
that Y would satisfy if X(t) would have
differential trajectories.
There is a counter-part to the classical
exponential function in stochastic calculus.
It's called the stochastic exponential
and it's denoted by a calligraphic E.
It is defined as shown here.
It is now an exercise
for you applying ito formula.
to show that the stochastic exponential
actually satisfies the fundamental stochastic
differential equation,
which corresponds to the fundamental equation
that would hold in real calculus
if X would have differentiable trajectories.
This property of the stochastic exponential
is very useful for two reasons
First of all,
the stochastic exponential is
positive by definition.
This is useful because
most price processes of financial assets
are positive.
And second, due to this fundamental
stochastic differential equation,
the stochastic exponential
preserves the martingale property.
That means if X is a martingale,
Then the stochastic exponential
of X is also a martingale.
In sum, the stochastic exponential
is the prototype
of  a positive martingale
in stochastic calculus.
In financial modeling, we often
change the probability measure.
This is why it is useful
to review base rules.
Let Q and P be
equivalent probability measures
with Radon-Nikodym density,
denoted by dQ over dP.
Base rule relates conditional
expectations on the P and Q.
For any bounded random variable X,
the conditional expectation
of X on the Q
can be expressed
as conditional expectation on the P,
if we multiply the argument X
by the Radon-Nikodym density of Q
with respect to P;
and normalize by the conditional expectation
of the Radon-Nikodym density.
If we vary little t,
then this becomes a martingale.
It's called
a Radon-Nikodym density process.
It is a positive martingale.
The Girsanov theorem describes
what happens to a Brownian motion on the P
when we change to an equivalent
probability measure Q.
The statement is as follows:
For an adapted process lambda,
satifying some more
technical conditions,
the ito process called W* given by
the expression as shown here
becomes a Brownian motion under
the equivalent probability measure, Q,
which is determined by the Radon-Nikodym
density process as shown here.
This means if we are given
a Brownian motion
with a drift lambda dt
under the measure P
we can de-trend
by changing the probability measure
to an equivalent measure, Q,
exactly when the Radon-Nikodym density
of Q with respect to P
is given in terms of the drift lambda
in this way.
Here is a very important application
of the Girsanov theorem
in financial modeling.
It's the arbitrage pricing theorem.
It states that any traded asset
with a positive price process
denoted by S
must have a return as shown here.
That means the return is decomposed
into a drift component
and a martingale component.
The drift component models
the expected return
Its rate is the sum
of the short rate r(t)
plus a risk premium which is
of the form sigma times lambda.
Sigma is the volatility of the return.
the larger sigma,
the more risky the return is
and lambda is the so-called
market price of risk.
In consequence,
the more risky the asset is
ie, the larger sigma is,
the larger is going to be
the excess expected rate of retun
over the risk-free short rate
Recall that the short rate
is called the risk-free rate of return
because this is what
the investor would earn
if he would simply invest
in the savings account.
We now see how
the Girsanov theorem comes into the play.
We can rearrange the terms,
the excess expected rate of return,
and denote its part, as show here,
what we see here is
the Brownian motion plus drift
we use the equivalent
probability measure, Q,
as shown on the previous slide
in Girsanov theorem
where we learnt that
this is a Brownian motion W*
under the equivalent measure, Q.
We can re-express
the asset price return as follows.
In terms of W*
We now see that under
the equivalent measure, Q,
the expected rate of return
is the risk-free rate, r
while the volatility remains the same.
We can thus re-state
the arbitrage pricing theorem
by saying that there must exist
an equivalent measure, Q.
which is called risk neutral-measure,
under which the return
of any traded asset
has an expected rate,
given by the risk-free short rate.
Using the integration by parts
and ito formula
we can show that
this differential notation
is equivalent to what is shown here.
It states two things.
First, the discounted
asset price process
discounted by
the risk-free numeraire
the risk-free asset,
the savings account
is a martingale
under the risk neutral-measure Q.
And second, this martingale is given
as stochastic exponential
of the martingale part
of the return of the price process.