We will now see
how the Arbitrage Pricing Theorem
yields a bond pricing formula
in terms of the short rates.
Indeed, the earliest
interest rate models
which date back to 1980s
were short rate models.
The most prominent among
the two are the Vasicek model
and the Cox–Ingersoll–Ross model.
You know both are still
very much in use.
They both come with their strengths
and their limitations.
Limitations are that these models
produce forward curves
which are low parametric,
and we have seen
that this posses problems when
fitting to a given term structure.
We remedy this by adding
a time-inhomogeneous term
and that leads us
to the hull-white extensions.
We now focus on the risk neutral
measure Q
and assume,
given an adapted short rate r.
The Arbitrage Pricing Theorem
implies that
the discounted bond prices follow
martingales and Q.
And that has to hold
for any maturity, capital T.
Using the fact that the terminal
value of the T bond is 1,
and using the defining properties
of a martingale
being the conditional expectation
of its terminal value,
this leads us to this
bond pricing formula.
So that the T bond price
is the conditional expectation
under the risk neutral measure
of the exponential
of the time integrated
short rate process.
This is not very explicit and we ask
what are the dynamics
of the T bonds price processes
that we get?
While this will depend on the model
for the short rate process,
under the risk neutral measure Q
and if on top of it we're interested
in the dynamics of P,
and the real world measure P,
we also would need to specify
the mark price of risk lambda,
which brings us back from Q to P.
The first model we consider
is the Vasitek Model.
The Q dynamics of the short rate
is as shown here.
This model has four parameters.
Kappa is the mean reversion speed,
theta is the mean reversion level
and sigma is the volatility.
The forth parameter, don't forget,
is the initial value
of the short rate which is not shown
in the differention notation.
As we will see
on the following slides,
this is a Gaussian process that
mean reverse to the level theta.
The figure on the right hand side
shows a simulated trajectory
for these parameters as shown here.
The means reversion level
is 8 %.
The process starts at the value 6 %
and we see that the mean reversion
forces it to tend
to the mean reversion level of 8%.
This trend is super posed
by the martingale part
that is larger,
the larger the sigma parameters is.
We can solve
the Vasicek differential equation
shown on the previous slide
for the short rate process r(t)
using the variation
of constants formula.
It shows that the solution
can be written explicitly
in integral form as shown here .
Again you may be familiar
with this  fact from real calculus
for this part of it.
Overall, you can verify the validity
of this expression
by just applying Ito formula.
This expression also shows
that r(t) is a Gaussian process
with mean function equal to
the deterministic part of it
and the covariance function
as shown here.
When t tends to infinity,
we see that the mean
tends to theta and the variance
when t1 is equal t2, is equal to t,
tends to sigma square the value
by 2 kappa.
In deed, the limiting distribution
of the short rates is normal
with mean theta
and variance sigma squared
divided by two kappa.
Now what about bond prices
in the Vasicek Model?
We proceed to calculating
bond prices in two steps.
The first step is to show
that the time-integrated
short rate process
is a normal random variable
and we determine
its characteristics.
We proceed by plugging in
the solution for r(s)
that we saw on the previous slide.
And it gives us the expression here
on the left hand side in black.
We next manipulate these expressions
in two step.
First is, we change
the order of integration
as shown here.
we apply that to both the drift term
and the stochastic integral term.
We then do for both parts
as shown here in the first part
multiply with e to the minus kappa t
and multiply with e
to the kappa t again.
We then realize that this integral
is equal to B cap T minus t
where the function B
is defined as integral of e
to the minus kappa s.
We further realize that
e to the minus kappa t, r(0)
is the first part of the expression
for the short rate r(t)
as shown on the previous slide.
We get the other two parts
from the drift integral
and from the stochastic integral
so that we can summarize
and get this first to mend
on the right hand side here.
We also get these two terms
as shown here.
Using the dependence
of the increments
of the Brownian motion,
we realize that
the stochastic integral
is independent of f(t)
and it is normal with mean 0
and variance given by
the integral of the square
of the integrant
with respect to d(u).
The first 2 terms are measurable
with respect to f(t)
because the short rate process
is adopted.
These observations imply
that the time-integrated
short rate process,
conditional on F(t)
is normal distributed
with mean given here
and variance
given here.
The bond prize, remember,
is the conditional expectation
of the exponential of the time
integrated short rate process
with a minus sign
We have just seen that this exponent
is normal distributed.
We know it's mean function
and we know it's variance,
so we can use
the moment-generating function
for the normal distribution
plugging the ingredients
and arrive
at the expression as shown
on the right hand side here
where the function A
is defined, here.
Summarizing the Vasicek
short rate model
yields exponential
afﬁne bond prices in the prevailing
short rate r(t) as shown here.
The functions A and B
can be shown
to solve the two coupled
ordinary differential equations
which are quadratic.
This is why they are called
Riccati equations
along with initial conditions
0 and 0,
for A and B.
The next short rate model
we consider
is the Cox-Ingersell- Ross Model.
In short, CIR Model.
The Q dynamics of the short rate
look similar to the dynamics
that we have for the Vasicek model
except that here,
the volatility of
the short rate process
depends on the square root
of the short rate itself.
Again we have the parameters,
theta, the mean diversion level,
kappa, the mean diversion speed
and sigma, the volatility.
For technical reasons,
we have to assume
that kappa times theta
is non-negative.
In contrast to the Vasicek model,
we can not write down
the solution to this stochastic
differentiation equation.
but it is a mathematical fact
that there exists
a unique no negative solution
for any no negative initial values.
We illustrate a similarity
trajectory
of the CIR short rate process
for the same parameter theta,
kappa and sigma
as for the Vasicek model.
Again we start at the level of 6%
Again we have mean reversion
but this time,
the volatility is smaller
because we use the same sigma
which has to be multiplied
with the square root
of the short rate to give
the total volatility contribution.
These parameters of course,
have only illustrative character.
They would have to be calibrated
to specific given
market data conditions.
But we cannot show it
from first principles
as we did in the Vasicek model,
we claim that
the CIR short rate model
also yields exponential afﬁne
bond prices
in the prevailing short rate
as shown here.
The function A and B solve again,
a (inaudible) system
of differential equations
which are quadratic.
So Riccati equations, along with
initial conditions 0 and 0
as was the case for the Vasicek
short rate model,
the solutions A and B
for this Riccati equations
are given in close form.
They are shown on the slide here.
We now prove the claim
that the CIR model
yields exponential afﬁne bond price
and we use stochastic calculus.
The claim is written here in black.
We multiply both sides
of this claimed equation
by the red factor.
This way, we get rid
of the small t dependence
of the argument in the conditional
expectation on the left hand side.
We call this argument M(T).
Just looking at the left hand side,
we realize we have a martingale.
We label the expression
on the right hand side
by M(t).
By Ito's formula, this can be seen
to be an Ito process.
We also see because of the initial
conditions A and B being 0,
that M(T), in deed coincides
with the argument
on the left hand side.
Hence, in order to prove equality
between these two sides,
it is now enough to prove
that M(t) is a martingale.
We do this by applying integration
by parts, and Ito formula, to M.
A few lines of stochastic calculus
shows us that the drift
of the M which we already
divided by M
because it factors out,
equals the expression
that is given here.
Now both components of this sum
are zero,
and this is due to the fact
that A and B
satisfy the Riccati equation
shown in the claim.
This proves indeed that M
has zero drift,
in other words,
M is a martingale.
Both models, the Vasicek
and the CIR models
yield closed-form expressions
for the bond prices.
It can also be shown
that they yield analytic expressions
for auction prices and bonds.
This explains why they
are very popular.
This models also have a weakness.
In both models
the forward curve
is given in closed form
in terms of the functions A and B.
Now the functions A and B
are determined by the parameters
kappa, theta, and sigma.
If we count the initial values
of the short rate
as a fourth parameter,
it shows us that
the initial forward curve
produced by either model,
the Vasicek and the CIR
is for parametric.
The problem that comes with it
is that these models
do not fit the data in general.
It is illustrated here
for the CIR model
with these parameters,
the red is the implied
initial forward curve
which cannot match
the observed data points in general
because of its low degree of freedom
Fortunately, there's
an easy solution to it.
The idea is to add
a time-inhomogeneous
and its component to it
with infinity degree of freedom
in such a way that you preserve
the analytic tractability
of the model on the other hand.
Here is how the idea works.
It is illustrated
for the Vasicek model
but it will equally-well work
for the CIR model,
and in fact, for any
diffusion short rate models.
We need 2 ingredients.
The first is an auxiliary simple
Vasicek model as show here.
We assume that initial short rate
matches the data.
In blue we indicate a given
initial forward curve.
As we well know, the Vasicek model
yields closed-form exponential
afﬁne bond prices.
For functions A tilde  and B tilde,
given in terms
of solutions of Riccatic equations.
The second ingredient
is a deterministic function Phi T
with 0 initial value.
We then get a time-inhomogenous
short rate model r(t),
as the sum of r(t) plus the auxiliary
simple Vaiscek model r tilde.
Notice already that
these short rate models
matches the initial short rates
by construction
because Phi 0 is 0,
and r tilde 0,
is the desired initial value.
The bond prices are still given
in closed form.
This is a simple consequence
of this observation done here.
From this, we easily infer
that the model implied
initial forward curve
is given a shown here.
And now, it is evident that we will
obtain a perfect fit
of the given initial forward curve
whenever we choose
the right function Phi
as the difference of the given
initial forward curve
minus model implied forward curve
from the auxiliary Vasicek model.
What can we say about the dynamics
of the time-inhomogeneous
short rate process r(t).
Let's illustrate these
for the Vasicek short rate model.
So assume r tilde is the auxiliary
Vasicek short rate model
as seen on the previous slides.
We then simply differentiate
the sum of Phi(t) plus r tilde(t),
to get the differential of r
in this form.
We then r tilde
by r minus Phi,
and it follows that r(t)
has a decomposition as shown here
where now the theta
is a t-dependent function
given in terms of Phi, this way.
It becomes evident that we
just obtained
an extension of the Vasicek model
by making this constant theta
a time-dependence theta.
This extension is also called
the Hull-White Model.
In sum, the Hull-White Model,
yields closed-form exponential
afﬁne bond prices
and at the same time matches
any given initial forward curve.