In short rate models, we specify
the dynamics of the short rates.
In the Heath-Jarrow-Morton framework
we take a different approach.
We specify evolution of the entire
forward curve directly.
As a consequence,
the initial forward curve
enters as an exogenous parameter.
So there are no tiers with fitting
the initial forward curve
as we had then
with the short rate models.
We will see that the drift
of the forward rate dynamics
is going to be fully determined
by the volatility
of the forward rate dynamics.
This is the famous
HJM drift condition.
The HJM framework is very broad
and it contains
all interest rates models
which are driven by a finite number
of Brownian motions.
Formally as ingredients, again,
we fix filtered probability space
which is now carrying
a d dimensional Brownian motion.
A d dimension Brownian motion
is simply composed
of independent standard scale
of Brownian motions W1 to Wd.
In turn, we need the market prizes
of risks that we stack
into the d dimensional market price
of risk, back to the Lambda
and the Girsanov theorem
still applies
under the risk neutral measure Q
which is equivalent to P
with the Radom-Nikodym density
process as given here.
Under this measure, the pros is W*
which is the Brownian motion
and the P plus the market price
of risk drift
is a Brownian motion under Q.
The Heath-Jarrow-Morton framework
or HJM framework
is very broad and contains
all interest rate models
driven by a finite number
of Brownian motions.
We specify directly the evolution on
the Q of the entire forward curve.
Formally this means,
|for every maturity capital T,
we the forward rate process
as a process in small T
follow an Ito process
with drift alpha.
Hence, volatility sigma
which are both indexed
by the maturity capital T
but otherwise
are processes in small t
as we're used to
in the case
of generic Ito processes.
We will see later on
that the drift process, alpha
is going to be fully determined
by sigma.
That is going to be a consequence
of the Arbitrage pricing theory.
keep in mind that Sigma is now
a vector valued process.
We stack the d component sigma 1
up to sigma d
into this row vector
that we call sigma.
We're also given
as an exogenous parameter
and initial forward curve
f(0), capital T.
Bond prices are explicit in terms
of the forward curve.
This is in contrast
to the short rate models
where bond prices
were  given implicit
in terms of
the integrated short rates
via the conditional expectation
under the risk neutral measure.
Hence in contrast
to short rate models,
here, we can directly infer
the dynamics of the bond prices
in terms of dynamics
of the forward rates
by using Ito's formula.
Let's do this in several steps.
We first start with the process
that is in the exponent
of the right hand side.
We see that the running time small T
showing up at two places,
as an integration boundary
and the time argument
of the forward rate process.
Formally differentiating
under the integral sign
gives us the integrant
at the lower integration boundary,
f, small t, small t
which by the way just
to short rate, r(t)
as we're going to, right here,
minus the integral of
the differential of the integrant.
We then plug in the differential
of the forward rates
and change the order
of integration dt, du
and the same with dW*(t), du
and we arrive
at the second line here
where we use short hand notation
and define v(t, T)
as minus the integrated
forward rate volatility.
Summarizing this first step,
we shown that the T bond price
is given by the exponential
of an Ito process
whose the composition
is given here.
We can now apply the Ito formula.
The Ito formula applied
to the exponential function
gives us what we see here
on the first slide.
Notice that I have divided
on both sides by T bond price.
Plugging in the expression
for the Ito composition
of this process here
from the previous slide,
we arrive at what is shown here.
This is the T bond return
decomposition into drift component
and martingale component.
From the Arbitrage Pricing Theorem,
we know that
the expected rate of return
to drift of
the T bond
under the measure Q
has to be equal
to the short rate.
But this implies
that minus the integral of alpha du
plus one half square of normal v
has to be 0.
This must true
for all maturities capital T.
So if we differentiate this equality
in capital T,
we arrive at this
HJM drift condition.
The drift of the forward rates
dynamics alpha
is fully determined in terms of
the forward rate volatility signal.
Summarizing, we arrive
at this HJM theory.
The Q dynamics of the forward rates
is fully determined
by the forward rate
volatility sigma
because the drift
that we use to label alpha
is given in terms of sigma
as shown here.
The corresponding risk neutral
bond price return dynamics
is of this form.
it has a risk free
expected rate of return
and a volatility v which again,
is defined as minus the integrated
forward rate volatility.
The minus sign
comes from the fact
that an upward shock in
the Brownian motion W*
drives forward rates up.
Rates going up means
bond prices go down.
The HJM framework contains
all the short rates models
we have seen so far.
So which HJM model,
sigma (t, T)
corresponds to the Vasicek
short rate model.
To answer this question,
we recap the Vasicek
short rate model dynamics
and we recall that
the Vasicek short rate model
implies forward rates
which are f Phi functions
in the prevailing short rates.
The functions A and B
are given in closed form.
They solve a system
of Riccatic equations,
the first order derivative of B
is e to the minus kappa,
cap T minus small t.
This is enough applying
integration by parts
to determine
the martingale component
of the forward rate dynamics
which is as shown here.
We could as well
by integrating by parts
we apply stochastic calculus,
derive the drift
of this implied
forward rate dynamics.
But we don't need to go
through these calculations
because the HJM theorem
already tells us
what the HJM drift here
has to to look like.
It is given explicitly in terms
of the volatility,
the volatility of the forward rates.