We have seen that
by the Arbitrage pricing theory
the bond price processes
discounted by the savings account
are martingales
under the risk neutral measure.
In this part
we will now learn that
if we discount bond price processes
by a specific T bond,
then this will give us
martingales again
but under some equivalent measure,
that is called
the T-forward measure.
This change of numeraire technique
proves most useful
for option pricing
with stochastic interest rates.
As an application, we will derive
closed form formulas
for options on bonds in the Gaussian
HJM model and framework.
As a setup we consider
a filtered probability space
with risk neutral measure Q
which is equivalent
to the real world measure P.
On this stochastic basis
we're given a short rate process
and the T-bond price processes
which are given by the arbitrage
pricing theory in this form.
such that the T-bond price process
discounted by the savings account
is a martingale under
the risk neutral measure Q
as becomes evident here.
Moreover this martingale
is strictly positive
so that after normalizing it
we can use it as a candidate
for a Radon Nikodyn density process
for an equivalent measure.
We call this measure
the T-forward measure
denoted by Q index T.
It is equivalent to Q
with a Radon-Nikodyn density process
given by the normalised
T-bond price process
discounted by the savings account.
Normalising means that
this martingale in expectation
is equal to 1.
The T-forward measure is defined
on a time horizon T.
At this terminal time,
the density is simply given
by the reciprocal
of the savings account
time the normalising factor.
Here is an important application
in derivatives pricing.
Consider a claim that is due
at time capital T
but suppose the pay off
is given by X.
The price at time small t
is given by discounting the payoff X
with the savings account
and take the conditional expectation
under the risk neutral measure Q.
The difficulty for computing
this expectation
comes from the fact
that the argument
is product of the discount factor
times X
Using the T-forward measure
we can re-express this expectation
of the product
of the discount factor times X
as expectation of X only
The expectation is taken
under the T-forward measure
and the expectation
has to be normalised
by the prevailing price
of the T-bond.
To equate these two sides
the Q conditional expectation
and the QT conditional
expectation of X
we use base rule as shown here.
Here is a fundamental property
of the forward measures.
For any time points T nought and T1,
the T nought bond price process
discounted by the T1 bond
is a martingale
under the T1 forward measure.
Strictly speaking this martingale
is only defined
up to the time which this is given
by the minimum of T nought and T1.
Again, this claim can be proved
using Bayes' rule
as shown on this line here.
As a consequence
the simple forward rate
for the  future interval T-nought T1
follows a martingale
under the T1 forward measure.
This follows from the relation
between this forward rate
and the ratio
of the T nought bond price
divided by the T1 bond price.
Because it is a martingale,
it can be written
as a conditional expectation
of it's terminal value
at time T nought
which is simply
the future simple spot rate.
We can say more in a specific model.
So let us consider
the HJM model framework
where the T-forward rate dynamics
under the risk neutral measure Q
is given as shown here.
This is simply rewriting
the HJM model drift
as we have seen it previously.
Using the bond return volatility V
which is defined as
as minus the integral of
the forward rate volatility Sigma.
In such a Heath-Jarrow Morton model,
we have also seen
that the discounted
bond price process
can be written as stochastic
exponential as shown here.
So we're given
an explicit expression
for the Radon Nikodyn density
process of the T-forward measure
in terms of the Brownian motion W*
under the risk neutral measure Q.
We can then apply Girsanov theorem
that implies
that under the T-forward measure
the process that we call
W upper index capital T
which is defined as shown here
is a Brownian motion.
It then follows immediately
from this representation
of the T-forward dynamics
that the T-forward rate process
is a martingale
under the T-forward measure
and there's a consequence.
It can be written
as conditional expectation
of it's terminal value
which is just the future short rate
at time capital T.
Now let us look at the most basic
option in the bond market.
It is a European call option
on the T1 bond
with expiry date T nought
and strike price K.
This option gives the holder
the right
to buy a T1 bond
at the expiry date T nought
for the price K.
The holder of the option
will exercise the option
only if the T1 bond price
at expiry date T nought
is not greater than K.
As a consequence
the  payoff to the holder
of the European call option
is given by the positive part
of the difference
of the T1 bond price
We obtain the price
of this call option at the time 0
by discounting the payoff
with the savings account
and take the expectation
under the risk neutral measure.
We could compute this price for
any time small t prior to T nought
but for simplicity of notation
we concentrate here
on the spot date 0.
We see again that the difficulty
for computing this option price,
comes from the fact that the
argument in the expression operator
is the product of
the discount factor times the payoff
which is a random variable
which is measurable
with respect to FT nought.
We could have seen
on the previous slide
get rate of the discount factor
by rewriting this expectation
as an expectation under
the T nought forward measure
but we will do something
smarter here.
We denote in blue here the
exercise event of the call option
that is the centrefold states
where the holder of the call option
will exercise the option.
This is exactly when
the T1 bond price
is greater than the strike price K.
We can then decompose
the payoff of the call option
into the difference
of the T1 bond price
times the indicator function
of the exercise event
minus the strike price times
the indicator function
of the exercise event.
We then use the linearity
of the expectation operator
and can write the call price
as the difference
of the expectations
of the respective components.
We then change to
the T nought forward measure
for the second expectation
to get rid of the discount factor
as shown here
and we end up with the expectation
of the indicator function
of the exercise event
under the T nought forward measure
which is  simply the same as the
probability of the exercise event
under the T nought forward measure.
In the first expectation,
we observe that
this factor that I underline here,
after normalisation
with the initial T1 bond price,
is the same as the Radon Nikodyn
density of the T1 forward measure
conditional on T nought.
This is just what we need
to apply base rule again
and re-express
this first expectation now
as expectation of the indicator
function of the exercise event
under the T1 forward measure
which is nothing else
than the probability
of the exercise event
under the T1 forward measure.
As a result we summarise
that the call option price
of a T1 bond at expiry date
T nought, can be expressed
in terms of the probability
of the exercise event
under the T1 forward measure
and the T nought forward measure.
So in order to find
a closed form formula,
we have to formulate the model
for which we can compute
these two probabilities
in closed form.
And this will be the case
in particular for
Gaussian Heath-Jarrow-Morton models.
As an intermediary step,
we observe
that the probability
of the exercise event
under the T1 forward measure,
can be rewritten as probability
of an event
that is expressed in terms
of the T nought bond price
discounted by the T1 bond price.
Similarly, the probability
of the exercise event
under the T nought forward measure
can be rewritten as probability
of an event
expressed in terms of
the T1 bond price
divided by the T nought bond.
This is a useful observation
because we know that
bond price processes discounted
by the T1 bond
are martingales under
the T1 forward measure
and similarly for T nought,
bond price processes
discounted by the T nought bond
are martingales under
the T nought forward measure.
That means in both cases
we have here
the terminal value of a martingale
under the respective
forward measures.
In the Heath-Jarrow-Morton framework
we can even  write down
how these martingale look like.
The T nought bond price process
discounted by the T1 bond
can be written explicitly
as a stochastic exponential
of a stochastic integral
with respect to the  Brownian motion
under the T1 forward measure.
And this holds interchangeably
for T nought and T1.
Now in view  of these
two identities,
it should be clear that
when the volatility
is a deterministic function
the stochastic exponential
is a log normal, random variable.
We can compute it's mean
and it's variance
and so we  will be able
to compute this probability
in closed form.
And similarly interchangeably
T nought T1
we will be able
to compute this probability
and here are the details.
Assume that the volatility Sigma
is a deterministic function
and so consequently
the bond return volatility
is also a deterministic function,
we can go back
to the stochastic exponential
shown on the previous slide
and take the logarithm
which gives us this identity
as shown here.
Because V
is a deterministic function,
we know that
what we have on the right hand side
is a Gaussian process.
The mean function is given
as shown here
and the variance function
is given as shown here.
Setting small t equal to T nought
and combining this insight
with the previous slide,
we arrive at the following theory.
In a Gaussian Heath-Jarrow-Morton
model,
that is a Heath-Jarrow-Morton
model
with deterministic
volatility function Sigma
the time 0 price on
a European call option
on a T1 bond with expiry date
T nought and strike price K
is given by the difference
of the T1 bond price
times the probability
of the exercise event
under T1 forward measure
minus strike K
times the T nought bond price
times the probability
of the exercise event
under the T nought forward measure.
These two probabilities
can be written
as standard cumulative
distribution function Phi
evaluated at D1 and D2 respectively
where these numbers are given
by the expression shown here.
This is a closed form formula
for the price
of a European call option on a bond.
From it we can easily now infer
a price formula
for a European put option on a bond
as shown in the following.
The put call parity
relates call prices to put prices
in a one to one relation.
It derives from this
elementary identity.
Here is the payoff
of a call option
and that is the payoff of
a put option with the same strike K.
By linearity of the prices,
we infer that the difference
of the call price
minus the put option price
is given by the present value
of what we have here
on the right hand side
which is simply the T1 bond price
at time 0
minus K times the T nought
bond price at time 0.
We can solve the put call parity
for the put option price
and plug in the call option price
from the previous slide
to derive that the put option price
in the above
Gaussian Heath-Jarrow-Morton model
is given by the expression here.
From the put call parity we also see
that the put option price
is equal to the call option price
for a specific strike price K
given by the T1 bond price
divided by the T nought bond
the strike price is called
the at the money strike price.
As an example
let's look at a specific
Gaussian Heath-Jarrow-Morton model
the Vasicek short rate model.
We already know that the
forward rate volatility function
is given as shown here.
We can then explicitly compute
the difference between
the volatility fn the return
on the T nought bond
minus the volatility of the return
on the T1 bond as shown here
such that the integrated square
difference of these volatilities
is given as shown here.
This is one ingredient
of the Gaussian HJM model
call option price formula
The other ingredient
is the initial discount curve.
We thus obtain an explicit
closed form
bond option price formula
in the Vasicek short rate model.
For an illustration we choose
the parameters as shown here
For these parameters we compute
the put option prices
on the Ti bond with expiry date
Ti minus 1
and the at the money strike price Ki
which is given
by the ratio of the Ti bond price
divided by the Ti bond price.
We do this for a sequence
of expiry dates and bond maturities
going from one quarter of a year
up to 10 years.
We obtain a term structure
of put option prices
as shown in this graph here.
The scale on the Y-axis
is in basis points.
This means the price
of a put option
on the one half year bond
with the expiry date in 3 months,
is slightly less
than 4 bases points.