Hello, my name is Rich Johnston,
and I started this course
when I was working
in the Sandec Department at the Eawag.
Now I work for the
World Health Organization
in the WHO Unisef Joint Monitoring Programme
for Water Supply and Sanitation.
And I am Sara Marks,
research scientist at Eawag
and a group leader of the Water Supply
and Treatment group.
My team works in countries in Africa and Asia
to improve drinking water quality
through developing
innovative treatment solutions.
And one way that people can improve
drinking water quality themselves
is to treat it at the household level.
And that's the topic of this course,
an Introduction to Household
Water Treatment and Safe Storage.
(Sara) This course is the first
and a serious e-learning initiative
jointly developed by Sandec and EPFL,
which will cover the full range
of Sandec research activities,
Household Water Treatment,
Sanitation Planning
Solid Waste Management
and Faecal Sludge Management.
This course will run for five weeks.
At the beginning of each week
We'll release approximately
one hour of video lectures
divided into short modules.
(Rich) The first week, of course,
is an Introduction.
We'll start by exploring
why it could be useful
to treat drinking water
at the household level.
We'll talk about
the global burden of disease,
discuss how drinking water
can be contaminated
and get a brief introduction
to the technologies
used in household water treatment.
In the second and third week
we'll go through these technologies
in more detail
with examples of actual applications
from around the world.
But the course
is not only about technologies.
We'll also look
at Implementation Strategies,
which are successful or not,
we'll consider
how household water treatment
can be targeted
to particular vulnerable groups,
such as in emergencies
or through schools.
And in the final week we'll look
at monitoring and evaluation
both of the technologies
and their implementation in the field.
You can find all relevant information
about the course on the course website.
There is also an online discussion forum,
where you can add your comments
about the course and the lectures,
form study groups,
even share your experiences
about household water treatment.
On Sandec Youtube webpage
you'll also find the lectures
for each course
and our WASH in
Developing Countries online series.
We're looking forward to the course
and hearing your contributions
on the online forum.
So let's get started now
with the module about the diseases
caused by unsafe water.