[BLANK_AUDIO]
Hello and welcome to the course about
Household
Water Treatment and Safe Storage An
Introduction to HWTS.
Make yourself comfortable.
Would you like something to drink?
Glass of water?
I don't know where you are but I'm sure
you have
access to drinking water otherwise you
wouldn't be taking this course.
But is that water really safe to drink?
Is it safe when it comes out of the tap?
Or out of the well or the stream?
Is it safe after you've collected it and
stored it in your house for a while?
Well, unfortunately for many people around
the world
the water they drink is not always safe.
And this is true in poor countries like
Ethiopia and Nepal but also in transition
countries
like Uzbekistan or Bolivia and even in
parts
of rich countries like England or the USA.
My name is Rick Johnston and I study
drinking water in developing countries.
How safe it is what makes it unsafe and
how it can be protected and improved.
One way that people can improve their
drinking water
quality is to treat it themselves at the
household level.
And that's the subject of this online
course.
An Introduction to Household Water
Treatment and Safe Storage.
I started this course while I worked
at eawag the Swiss Federal Institute for
Aquatic
Science and Technology which is the WHO
collaborating
center for sanitation and water in
developing countries.
Within eawag I worked at Sandec The
Department of Water and Sanitation in
Developing Countries.
And the aim of Sandec is to develop or
adapt concepts and technologies for
application in developing countries
with a range of research and
implementation partners to
improve sustainable access to good quality
water and sanitation services.
During the preparation of this course I
moved
from Sandec to the World Health
Organization in Geneva.
But this MOOC remains a product of Sandec
along
with EPFL the Swiss Institute of
Technology in Lausanne.
This course is the first in a series of
eLearning initiatives jointly developed by
Sandec and EPFL, which will cover the full
range of Sandec research activities.
This course will run for five weeks.
And at the beginning of each week we'll
release approximately one hour of
video lectures divided into short modules
usually around 10 or 15 minutes long.
The videos contain quizzes where you can
test
your knowledge about the materials being
presented and you'll
also be able to get PDF copies of
the presentations and English
transcription and a French translation.
Each module will start with an
introduction slide like this one.
Here you can see that today I will show
you the course outline.
We'll talk about quizzes and homework and
the course forum.
Let's start with a look at the course
outline.
The first week of course is an
introduction.
We'll start by exploring why it could be
useful to treat drinking water at the
household level.
We'll talk about the global burden of
disease discuss how drinking water can
become
contaminated and get a brief introduction
to
the technologies used in household water
treatment.
In the second and third weeks we'll go
through these technologies
in more detail with examples of actual
applications from around the world.
But the course isn't only about
technologies.
We'll also look at implementation
strategies which are successful or not.
We'll consider how a household water
treatment can be targeted to
particular vulnerable groups such as in
the emergencies or through schools.
And in the final week we'll look at
monitoring and
evaluation both of technologies and their
implementation in the field.
Especially in this week we will draw on
some useful documents and programs
produced by the WHO.
Most of these lectures will be delivered
by me but we will have a few
special guests from experts in the United
Nations or leading research institutions.
This course is an introduction we won't
get
into much detail about these topics but we
will always try to point you towards
websites
or documents where you can get more
information.
Quizzes and homework.
Many of the modules will include short
in-video quizzes which are not graded.
But at the end of each week there will
be an assignment which counts toward the
course grade.
At the ends of weeks one two and four
this will be a quiz which will be
automatically graded.
After week three you'll have a
peer-reviewed assignment in which you will
need
to apply the knowledge that you've learned
so far towards a realistic scenario.
And after week five you will take a final
exam.
I will even tell you one of the questions
right now.
I'm a nice guy.
You will have to tell me what this thing
is and how it is used in household water
treatment.
If you complete the assignments and the
final exam successfully
by the deadline you will receive a
Statement of Accomplishment.
Let's first take our first in-video quiz
right now.
You can find all relevant information
about the course such as
grading policies and information about the
peer-review assignments on the course
site.
We've also developed a forum section where
you can comment and discuss about the
course.
There's a General Discussion Forum and
three further forums with content specific
purposes.
In the General Discussion Forum you can
share
your reactions to the course material as
it's presented
and if you have your own experiences about
household
water treatment this is the place to share
them.
Study Groups Forum is a platform where you
can find friends and arrange meet-ups and
please invite your friends to the course
to create learning groups and discuss the
topics.
The Lectures Forum is for specific
questions about the lectures.
And Exercise Forum is for specific
questions and clarifications
about the quizzes the peer-graded
assignments and the final exam.
Finally there are two course specific
forums where you
can communicate any course material errors
and technical issues.
At the end of each module there's a
summary slide like this one.
And at the end of each week there is also
a
short summary module to give a recap of
the week's modules.
I'm looking forward to the course and to
hearing your contributions in the forums.
Let's start the course now with a module
about
the diseases that are caused by unsafe
drinking water.