[BLANK_AUDIO]
In this module, we'll talk about diseases
caused by unsafe water,
sanitation, and hygiene, and how they can
be classified, as well
as the burden of disease due to unsafe
water, sanitation, and
hygiene, both in terms of deaths or
mortality and disease or morbidity.
They say that three things in life are
certain, birth, taxes
and death, and somehow some people have
managed to avoid taxes.
But deaths are inevitable.
There are about 55 million people who die
every year.
But there are even more people who have
babies every
year, about a 135 million new babies are
born each year.
So that means that overall there's about a
1.1% increase in the global
population each year and the population
will
double every 60 years at current rates.
One useful way to classify diseases was
proposed by
the authors of the 1972 classic book
"Drawers of Water".
according to environmental transmission
pathways.
This so called Bradley Classification
includes four
types, water-borne, water-washed,
water-based, and water-related diseases.
Now, some of those 55 million deaths per
year are
caused, at least in part, by unsafe water,
sanitation, and hygiene.
And we can think about different ways to
classify those diseases.
First we can talk about the water-borne
diseases, which are diseases
caused by actually drinking, ingesting
water that has some pathogens in it.
These include the diarrheal diseases
caused by
different pathogens: rotavirus, cholera,
shigella or cryptosporidium.
but also Hepatitis A and E, and even Polio
can be transmitted through drinking water.
For any of these water-borne diseases, an
intervention to
reduce the disease then, could involve
improving the water quality.
Next we have the water-washed diseases,
which are caused by poor hygiene due to
lack of water, rather than by direct
ingestion.
Most water-borne diseases are also water
washed, because they
can be transmitted through hands and
contact with other surfaces.
Trachoma is the leading cause of
preventable
blindness globally, and is transmitted by
flies,
which land on people's faces.
And acute respiratory infections are also
transmitted through
contact with pathogens on hands and other
surfaces.
Water-washed diseases can be reduced by
increasing the
amount of water that's available to
improve hygiene.
Water-based diseases are those caused by
parasites
which live part of their lifecycle in
water.
The most serious of these is
schistosomiasis or bilharzia
which affects 160 million people globally,
mostly in Sub-Saharan Africa.
Another serious water based disease is
guinea worm or
dracunculiasis, which is a horrible
disease, which used to
affect many people, 3.5 million people in
1986, but
cases are now down to only 542 in 2012.
And those are confined to about four
countries.
Mainly in South Sudan.
For water-based diseases, control
mechanisms involved targeting the aquatic
organism host and protecting surface water
bodies from contamination.
Finally, there are water related disease,
which are
caused by insects which breed in water,
especially mosquitoes.
The most important of these is malaria
which affects
about 250 million people each year,
causing about 589,000 deaths.
The great majority of those are in
sub-Saharan
Africa and affect children under the age
of five.
Another important mosquito disease is
Dengue fever which is growing
in numbers and can cause explosive
outbreaks especially in urban areas.
In both cases the mosquitoes breed in
certain types of
water and a control mechanism is to remove
their habitat.
So in summary,
there are many diseases which are caused,
at
least partially, by unsafe water,
sanitation and hygiene.
Water-borne diseases are those that are
caused
by directly drinking, or ingesting
contaminated water.
And those diseases can be controlled, at
least
partially, by treating the water at the
household.
Household water treatment though shouldn't
be expected to have an impact
on other diseases that are water washed,
water based, or water related.
Now let's take a little break.
You see on your screen five different
infectious diseases and I'd like you to
think for a minute about which of them
cause more or less deaths each year.
Arrange them in the order of numbers of
deaths per year and then click the next
slide.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
The most recent global mortality figures
were released by the WHO in 2013
and estimate deaths over the years 2000 to
2011.
You can see that lower respiratory
infections such as pneumonia were
by far the largest cause of death among
these diseases in 2011.
Diarrheal disease caused about 1.9 million
deaths,
followed by tuberculosis, malaria, and
measles.
Now take a moment to click on the link
to the WHO website where these data are
available.
Download the Excel file called "Global
Summary"
Estimates, and look at the summary tab.
How have the numbers in this table changed
since 2000?
If you compare the numbers you will see
that measles, for
example, has declined tremendously to
about a quarter the level of 2000.
Since diarrhea causes 1.9 million deaths
per year,
it is the most important of the
water sanitation and hygiene related
diseases.
It's also a water-borne disease, so water
quality is important in its transmission.
The burden disease from diarrhea is large.
It causes about 3.5% of
all deaths globally, and
if you look at children under age five,
the number rises to 9.3%.
Diarrheal disease is second only to acute
respiratory infections in terms of disease
burden.
There are important non-infectious
diseases; such as heart disease,
stroke and lung problems, which effect
many people also.
Now the 2011 figures have just been
released by
WHO and are not yet desegregated by risk
cause.
So we can't say how many of those 1.9
million deaths are due to unsafe water
sanitation and hygiene.
But in the previous round of estimates
from 2004, this analysis was made.
And WHO estimated that about 88% of the
then 2.2 million deaths
per year were attributable to poor water,
sanitation and hygiene.
So it's clear then that poor water,
sanitation and hygiene have a
major impact on the global burden
of disease, especially through diarrheal
disease.
So far we've been talking about burden of
disease in terms of deaths or mortality.
But it's also important to consider
sicknesses which
can greatly reduce the quality of life, or
morbidity.
We can do this through a metric
that's called disability adjusted life
years, or DALYs.
What DALYs do is combine two aspects,
first, the years
of life lost in comparison to a standard
life expectancy
and second the years lost to disability
which are number of years you live
with a disability times a weight for how
serious that disability is.
Well, lets consider this with some
examples.
First consider a person who has a normal
life
expectancy of 80 years and has no
particular disabilities
and this person lives a fully healthy life
for 80 years
and has zero years of life lost, or years
lost to disability.
So they have no DALYs.
Second, let's consider an example, where
someone
also lives, has a life expectancy of 80
and lives a very normal life to begin
with, but then
has some kind of sudden accident at age
70, and dies prematurely.
Then they have years of life lost.
How many?
10 years of life lost.
There's no disability here, so then the
number DALYs is10.
Okay.
This time, let's consider a person who has
a normal healthy life until age 50 when
they have some kind of accident which
leads
to loss of a foot, amputation of the foot.
Now the disability weight for a foot
amputation is 0.3.
So it goes up to there but then that
person lives to the expected life
expectancy of 80.
So here we have years of life lost to
disability.
How many?
30 years from age 50 times a weight of 0.3
for foot amputation.
There's a total of 9.
So that's nine DALYs.
Finally, a more complicated example, is a
person who lives
a normal life until age 36, when they
contract HIV/AIDS.
Full blown AIDS without any medicine,
without
antiretroviral therapy, has a weight of
0.5.
But after four years that person then is
able to get medication and
have a much better quality of life with a
weight of 0.167.
Then that person lives until age 70, dying
prematurely.
46, 36, then 40.
So here we have years lost to disability
and here we have years of life lost.
How many?
Ten years of life lost.
How many years lived with disability.
We have four at that high rate.
That's a total of two, plus 30 at a lower
rate.
That's five.
For a total of seven.
So then the DALYs, plus ten plus seven,
for 17.
So you can imagine the diarrheal disease
then,
which impacts, very young children in many
cases will
also have a high contribution to DALYs
because
of the large number of years of life lost.
Now that we have a metric for morbidity,
the DALYs
we can examine the overall burden of
disease posed
by diarrhea, and compare it to other
diseases globally.
Now, that 2013 WHO report about deaths,
globally, hasn't yet been analyzed to
develop DALY
estimates, so we have to look at an older
WHO report from 2008 shown up here.
Where they reported that diarrheal disease
caused over 52 million DALYs per year,
which again the distribution was very
similar to
the mortality numbers we've seen, with a
little bit
more than 3% of the global total, and
about 9% of the burden of disease for
children.
This report also listed, country-wise,
DALYs.
And you could see that India was by far
the, the
largest country in terms of DALYs, in
terms of disease burden,
followed by other large countries, China,
Nigeria,
Pakistan, and the Democratic Republic of
Congo,
which all had more than 3 million DALYs.
In fact, in DRC the contribution of diarrheal
disease to the
overall disease burden was more than 10%
of all DALYs.
So
far we've been talking about numbers
generated by the WHO, either their
2000 report on mortality or earlier
reports for morbidity or risk factors.
But there is another large, important and
recent data set out there.
It's called the Global Burden of Disease
2010 Study and it was done
by the Institute for Health Metrics and
Evaluation, or IHME, based in Seattle,
Washington.
The GBD 2010 Study was a massive
undertaking involving hundreds
of scientists from all around the world
including many WHO researchers.
However even though it uses a similar
approach
to the WHO models, WHO hasn't endorsed the
findings,
in part because of some methodological
differences
and in part because they weren't given
access to
the data and the findings to validate them
before publication.
Some of the main differences between the two
studies are
that first IHME calculated new disability
weights for various health conditions.
This was done through a participatory
online process, as
well as through field surveys in a number
of countries.
Second, while WHO considered hygiene,
water and sanitation risks
IHME found that the data available
for, hygiene practices, nationally
representative data
sets, were too weak, so they decided not
to include this risk factor.
And then finally, in the IHME model,
people accessing
a basic level of water and sanitation,
such as
improved sources of water like a bore hole
or
protected spring, or improved sanitation,
the basic pit latrine.
They were considered to suffer no burden
of disease due to their water and
sanitation.
This was not the approach followed in the
WHO models.
Nonetheless, this was a massive and
important undertaking,
and we can learn a lot through its
findings.
Let's take a look at them.
Let's take a look at the GBD 2010 data
from the IHME website.
You can find it just by searching for
IHME.
And
then let's go straight to their data
visualization.
[SOUND]
They have many different visualization
tools, we'll look at GDB Compare.
Now in GBD Compare this is what's called a
Tree Map and if you hover
over different diseases you can see the
percent
of their contribution to the burden of
disease.
Here let's put a focus on diarrheal
Now that box will always have a square
around it
and we can change between DALYs and
deaths.
We can look at global or specific
countries or regions.
We can change years.
We can see that if we look at under
five children, the contribution of
diarrheal disease is much larger.
So you can you can find out a lot of
things from this kind of map.
Down below, we have different options for
secondary visualizations.
We could look at a time plot for instance
and see the number of deaths decreasing
over time.
Here is shown as rates or as numbers
decreasing from 1.7 million under five
deaths in 1990, to about 666,000 in 2010.
We can also look at a map and see
which countries have greater or lesser
burdens of disease.
Here we can see that India, with 150,000
child deaths,
is by far the largest contributor to the disease.
But, if we looked at rates, then we
would see higher rates in
Sub-Saharan Africa
and the same if we look at proportion of
DALYs.
If we compare the GBD 2010 numbers to the
WHO estimates,
there is some similarities and some
differences.
IHME predicts 1.5 million diarrheal deaths
per year which
is a little bit lower than WHO's 1.9
million.
However they predict a higher number of
DALY's.
WHO was at 52 million, though that was an
older figure.
The highest ranking countries remain
India, DRC, Nigeria, Pakistan, countries
with large populations and moderate or
poor water sanitation and hygiene.
China in this model though has a
relatively lower
burden of disease compared to the earlier
WHO estimates.
One of the biggest differences, though, is
that in the IHME model,
only 25% of the diarrheal deaths are
caused by poor water and sanitation.
So, water and sanitation, as a risk
factor, accounts
for less than 1% of the burden of disease.
And this is, in large part, because
hygiene wasn't included in the IHME
models
and we'll see when the recent WHO figures
are updated
to include DALYs and risk factors, how
those numbers compare.
So in summary, we have a couple
different data sets for burden of disease.
From WHO, we have the recent numbers about
mortality, which include data and maps
and you have earlier reports with
mortality,
as well as morbidity and risk factors.
From IHME, you have data and maps
and risk factors and really nice
visualization tools.
What both of these data sets tell us is
that the
burden of disease from unsafe water
sanitation and hygiene is high
and that diarrheal disease is the leading
contributor to
that disease burden both in terms of
morbidity and mortality.
You can now access these reports or
websites
to get more detailed information if you
need.
In our next module we'll be looking at
some of the specific pathogens that cause
diarrheal diseases
in drinking water.
[BLANK_AUDIO]