In this module we'll talk about the
Millennium Development Goals.
What they are?
Where safe water fits into them?
And how household water treatment and safe
storage is related to the MDGs.
The Millennium Development Goals, or MDGs.
Our set of eight, well goals, that were
established by
United Nations member states in the year
2000, the millenium.
And set a development agenda for the next
15 years.
In most cases they tried to set specific
targets for each of the goals.
Which could be measured, and would be
ambitious, but still could be achieved.
Within the time frame.
Now these goals are, are very broad they
cover
poverty and hunger, primary education,
gender equality and women's empowerment.
Child mortality, maternal health, severe
diseases, environmental
sustainability and a global partnership
for development.
Now you might think, well what about water
and sanitation?
Where to they fit into the MDGs?
Well, where would you put safe water and
sanitation?
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Well, water and sanitation are found
under goal seven, ensure environmental
sustainability.
There's a target there.
7C.
Which is to have, by 2015, the proportion
of people
without sustainable access to safe
drinking water and basic sanitation.
Obviously, the main goal of HWTS is to
improve drinking water quality at the
household level.
This is most important when there are many
risks of fecal contamination along the
drinking water chain.
Many of those threats lie outside the
household, and in the long run
should be best addressed through source
protection
and development of high quality water
supply.
HWTS doesn't replace the obligation of
service providers
to provide sustainable access to safe
drinking water.
It's more of a stop gap measure for people
who don't
yet have access to high quality drinking
water in the home.
For people who need to collect water from
public points.
Or who accessed piped water, which is not
fully reliable, for
example, due to intermittent operation and
contamination in the distribution system.
So HWTS can contribute to the safety of
drinking water but it
doesn't improve access, the quantities
available
or the sustainability of the water supply.
So if people who rely on unimproved water
sources such as rivers or ponds are
able to use HWTS sustainably and
effectively to improve water quality
at home, it may be safe, but it still
wouldn't be the same
as sustainable access to safe drinking
water as in MDG target seven C.
This would in fact, transfer
responsibility
from the service providers to the
consumers.
Which wouldn't be fair.
So, HWTS can contribute towards MDG 7, but
also towards the other MDGs.
Especially the health related ones.
Unsafe drinking water is a major risk
factor for under five mortality, MDG 4.
As well as people living with HIV/AIDS,
MDG 6.
Contaminated water is also linked with
malnutrition, so
HWTS can have an indirect impact on MDG 1.
And since children often miss school when
they're suffering from
diarrheal disease, HWTS can have an
indirect contribution towards MDG 2.
So in conclusion, HWTS contributes to the
MDG target on safe
drinking water, but also toward other
MDG targets, especially the health-related
ones.
However, HWTS alone doesn't guarantee
sustainable access to safe drinking water
and so it shouldn't be considered as an
indicator for target 7C.