Hello, today we will talk
about global monitoring
of water supplies and sanitation
and how these monitoring efforts relate
to household water treatment
and safe storage.
Maybe you've been wondering,
what is meant by global monitoring
and why monitor access
to basic services anyway.
To answer this let's take a look
at two policy frameworks,
which shaped the priorities and actions
of the international
development community,
including the water
and sanitation sectors.
Many of you will be familiar
with the Millennium
Development Goals, or MDGs
and eight international development goals.
Annual MDGs, which were established
following the 2000 Millennium Summit
and adopted by all UN member states.
But perhaps fewer of you are aware
that in the coming decades,
what is called
the post-2015 monitoring period,
a new development agenda
is about to be launched,
called the Sustainable
Development Goals, or SDGs.
First of all let's look at the MDGs
Under this framework there
are 8 Goals with 21 associated targets
ranging from ending
extreme poverty and hunger
to achieving universal primary education,
to improving maternal health.
The aim of Target 7C under Goal 7
for environmental sustainability
is to halve the proportion
of the global population
without sustainable access
to safe drinking water
and basic sanitation.
The latest round of reporting
by the WHO Joint Monitoring Program, or JMP,
shows that on a global level
the target for expanding access
to improve water supplies
has been met several years ahead
of the 2015 deadline.
This is really an incredible
accomplishment for the water sector.
Unfortunately the news for sanitation
is not as positive.
We see that delivery
of improved sanitation services
has not kept pace with population growth,
and thus we will miss the global target
for sanitation in the year 2015
by nearly 700 million people.
It's important to know
that for both water
and sanitation targets of MDG
data are reported at the national level,
so there is not a specific objective
to encourage equitable distribution
of services within each country.
This is one critique of the MDGs,
and we will revisit this later.
But first let's define a few terms
that you will hear throughout this module.
First, a goal is an ambitious commitment
to address a single challenge,
typically global in scope.
Each goal can be broken down
in two specific targets.
A target is defined as a specific
measurable and time-bound outcome
that directly contributes
to the achievement
of the stated goal.
And finally targets are monitored
by periodically collecting data
on various indicators,
which are clearly defined,
metrics using,
used to measure
progress towards targets,
generally based on available data.
To use the earlier example,
Goal 7 of the MDGs,
which relates generally
to environmental sustainability,
includes Target 7C,
which states that by 2015
we shall halve
the share of people globally
without sustainable access
to safe drinking water
and basic sanitation,
as compared to 1990 levels.
So you can see that the target is
an action-oriented objective
to be achieved
over a specific time period.
But how can we monitor progress
towards this target?
For water supply the JMP
has defined an indicator
of use of an improved
drinking water source
which is one that is protected
from outside contamination,
especially faecal contamination.
When a household reports
using a protected water point,
such as a household or yard tile,
public standpipe, borehole or tube well,
protected dug well, protected spring
and rainwater harvesting system,
that household is counted
as progress toward the MDG target.
So far we've discussed
the Millennium Development Goals
and how progress
on this development agenda is monitored
using specific targets and indicators.
Let's examine now
how global monitoring will look
in a decade following
the conclusion of the MDGs
and a new policy framework
called the Sustainable
Development Goals, or SDGs.
The concept of SDGs
was formally proposed
on the 2012 UN conference
on sustainable development
with UN member states agreeing to goals
which are action-oriented, concise,
easy to communicate,
limited in number, aspirational,
global in nature
and universally applicable
to all countries,
while taking into account
different national realities, capacities
and levels of development.
As of March 2015 there were
17 proposed goals shown here
and 169 targets and hundreds
of proposed indicators
to monitor compliance.
You can see here
that there is a standalone goal
for water and sanitation, Goal 6,
which proposes to ensure availability
and sustainable management
of water and sanitation for all.
This goal is underpinned
by targets and indicators
that center around three key concepts.
First, safely manage
drinking water services,
second, safely manage
sanitation services
and, third, hand washing at home.
Let's take a closer look at Target 6.1,
the water related target.
This proposed target is to achieve
by 2030 universal and equitable access
to safe and affordable
drinking water for all.
The proposed indicators
and definitions are shown here,
organized around
the drinking water service ladder.
You can see, the indicator
for safely managed water
is the percentage of the population
using safely managed
drinking water services
and defined more specifically
as the population
using a basic drinking water source
which is located on premises
and available when needed
free of faecal contamination,
as well as priority chemicals
and/or regulated by a competent authority.
In this case
a basic drinking water source
is similar to the MDG definition
of an improved water source.
But now within a 30 minute round ship
from household including queuing time.
This information is already
routinely collected in household surveyes.
The information on faecal
or chemical contamination
can come directly
from water quality testing
and also from administrative offices
which have data on regulation
and management practices.
In addition to prioritizing
the elimination of inequalities
SDGs will also try
to improve an MDG framework
by monitoring access to WASH
in schools and health care facilities
ending open defecation
and achieving universal basic access.
The SDG dialog is evolving as we speak,
and you can keep up with the conversation
by checking out the reports
and links listed here.
Take a minute to explore these resources
and let us know what you think
about the SDG agenda
on the discussion forum.
So, in summary, this module examined
global monitoring of water supply access
to the use of goals,
targets and indicators.
We also looked at how access to water
is defined and monitored through
the Millennium Development Goals
and learned that MDG Target 7C
to halve the share
of the global population
without access
to improved water supplies,
but fortunately achieved
well ahead of schedule.
Next, we explored the upcoming
sustainable development goals
and a new set of targets
which aim to improve upon MDGs
through eliminating access inequalities,
monitoring WASH access
in schools and health care facilities
and eliminating open defecation worldwide.
There are several challenges
and opportunities
that the new SDG framework presents.
One major challenge
includes striking the right balance
between granularity and simplicity
such that the indicators
are both true to the ground reality,
but also universally relevant.
Opportunities include
the chance to expand
the monitoring capacity
of the national institutions
beyond household survey data collection
and also the chance to harmonize efforts
and institutions around a new set
of development priorities.
And what about HWTS?
SDGs did not specifically prioritized use
of household water treatment
and safe storage,
but since drinking water quality is now
a specific indicator on the Target 6.1,
there may be opportunities
for water treatment and safe storage
to play a role,
especially at the community level.
In any case, we are about to enter
a new and exciting period
of global monitoring
and we look forward
to hearing more on the forum
about how the SDGs might affect you.