Hello.
Welcome to the module on the international
network on household water treatment and
safe storage.
I am Michael Forson the co-host to the network.
And I work with UNICEF.
In this module we are going to look at the
issue, what triggered the network?
Actually, the question is why the network?
Then, we will look at the network
strategy, the
core elements of the strategy, its
mission, objectives, targets.
We will look at the hosting and then the
implementation arrangement.
And the membership, what are the benefits
when you
join the network and also some of the
achievements.
Then the challenges.
You know as every institution or every
organization have some challenges, what is
working, what worked and what didn't work,
and some of the relevant information.
Okay, the question is, the issue, a large
part
of the world population is without access
to drinking water.
You know, in 2010, when the joint
management program
for UNICEF and WHO announced that the
world has
met the target on drinking water, for the
millennium development goals
specifically target three of the MDG goal
seven.
It was a big joy, but however, looking at
it critically you
will see that there are still people
without access to safe drinking water.
Again, by definition of the MDG targets, I
mean the definition,
it indicates that it actually looks at the
type of water source by its construction.
So, that means we're not very much sure,
about the quality of the water as they
drink.
And I must emphasize here that clean water
or clear water is always not safe water.
We s, we can say that as of 2011, there
were still 768 million people without
access to safef drinking water.
And then more billions also are not having
access to the safe drinking water itself.
Again, millions are served by unreliable
pipe systems and are forced to store water
in drinking in certain continents, which
really
puts a risk to contaminate the water.
Millions are also affected by emergency
situations, which in directly
affect the water and sanitation systems,
broken down water systems.
Therefore a potential risk to the safety
of the drinking water.
Then we realize that diarrhea being the
major cause
of child mortality it's also dependent on
drinking water.
If we look at the equation for the
diarrhoea reduction,
safe drinking water actually takes about
30% of the variables.
So the question is why a network?
In February 2003, WHO convened a
multi-stakeholder meeting,
to really think through, what is the best
platform that stakeholders should
come together, to address the issues that
I mentioned in the previous slide.
And after deliberations, they agreed that
a network
would be the best forum to be used.
The advantages of a network is that a
network is a forum.
It's an information clearing house and
vehicle to move, to
promote collective, bilateral and
individual
action as part of the stakeholders.
That means, it's more like an
all-inclusive
clearing house so everybody have a say.
Again it co, it encourages communication
and cooperation.
So whenever you want to see South-South
corporation,
South-North cooperation, the network can
really do that.
And again as a network, we can really
monitor and
map the global efforts, to inform
advocacy, implementation and investment.
Then, we can also raise awareness about,
HWTS,
its rule and make the understanding how
one should
understand it, and the supports to
government in
making decisions regarding, household
water treatment and safe storage.
Then again, we are to, as, as a network,
we can conduct agreed targeted researches
which are coordinated
to really give us, I mean, evidence as to
how best we can win the health impact on
HWTS.
On this slide, we see
I wanted to portray the timeline how the
network has really fed.
In Phase one, which was actually from 2003
to 2008, we saw
the time of planning, more of a thinking
through and so forth.
During that time, WHO was the sole host of
the network.
After 2008.
UNICEF and WHO released their
seven
point strategy for comprehensive diarrrhea
control and management.
And then the network adapted this as the
key or the basis to really move the
agenda.
There was a strategic meeting or
consultation
during the f the, the, the interface.
And it was a [INAUDIBLE] strategic
meeting.
Now it was agreed that UNICEF and WHO
would co-host it.
So, that gave birth to the second phase in
2011 where WHO and UNICEF co-hosted
a platform and we've had a couple or a
number of original meetings.
So, we can now see, in 2014, where we are
now.
Now, that network every organization or
every, institutions, you have a vision.
So, to the network, our mission is to
contribute
to a significant reduction in water-borne
and related vector-borne
diseases, especially among vulnerable
populations, by promoting HWTS as
a key component of community targeted
environmental health programs.
Our focus is on vulnerable population,
people
affected by HIVs, people who are
disenfranchised.
People who are malnourished, people who
are, I mean, but,
but, just, I mean, in, inequality, being
affected by inequality.
And again, we are trying to, our mission
is also
to look at, trying to, eh, make an
integrated effort.
To leverage other more environmental
health programs because we
talking about what, the equation of the
diarrhea reduction.
It's not only safe water, but then there
are other elements in that.
The objectives of the network, the HWTS
network
has the following four objectives and
three targets.
The objectives and targets are shaped
around the
three core areas that the network derives
its strength.
Advocacy, communication, research and
implementation and scaling up.
The objectives is actually to HWTS, will
be
used as an evidence base of public health.
The evidence base of HWTS as a public
health intervention.
Will really be strengthened.
And it is our objective also that there
will be tangible reasons.
For scaling up HWTS activities globally.
Then, we looking at national policies and
institutional frameworks
to be developed as part of the
environmental health interventions.
Then also to disseminate best practices in
HWTS across the group.
We have three key targets.
The first target is that by 2015
thirty countries should have established policies
on
household water treatment and safe
storage.
By 2015 we are expected that they will
strengthened, we
are expecting that they will be
strengthened evidence to guide effective
and replicable HWTS activities and
approaches which will give, which
will influence Long-term widespread and
use and its public health impact.
And also, by 2020, we are hoping that 50
countries
should have achieved a country-wide scale
up of project-based HWTS.
In terms of participation, we currently
have over 160 membership drawn from
various organizations, the academia, The
United
Nations agencies, governments and so
forth.
There are a number of benefits if you join
the network.
One is it connects you to a global network
of HWTS.
That's what we are, you meet with experts,
senior officials,
program implementers, researchers, and on
the ground implementers.
And again you will receive the
latest
news on the HWTS project as it evolve.
There are meetings and events through
which the Network really share
information.
We have a Network listserv and a
newsletter that really give you up-to-date
information.
Then again, you'll be able to know who is
active where, and
how to engage with other partners
if you're are planning for HWTS
interventions.
Then, you also benefit from having
your
work disseminated and highlighted in the
network communication material.
You will have also a voice in the annual
network
meeting and therefore have an input into
the annual work plan.
Then you have access to an online,
interactive webspace to
share files and discuss matters of
interest with Network participants.
We have this arrangement with the Network.
The secretariat is made up of WHO and
UNICEF with, the University of North
Carolina, the Water Institute at the
University
of North Carolina playing the
communications role.
Within the secretariat, we have an
advisory group.
Which is pulled from the various members
of the high ranking proven practitioners
and researchers.
The catch here is that if you are with a
UN
organization, you are excluded from being
on, on, on the advisory group.
Then we have a public private partnership
group.
This group also works hand in hand with
the
advisory group and the secretariat because
the network prove, is
trying to provide a level platform for
their private
sector to really invest into what move on
the HWTS.
We have the participating organizations
and members around the Secretariat then,
in the strategy we had working groups but
then it didn't really work well.
So, in terms of implementation the
WHO
and UNICEF both designated focal points as
co-hosts, and the membership of the
Advisory
group were selected based on an agreed
criteria.
And the Secretariat organize and convene
network
and annual, and the Advisory group
meetings.
Again we develop and implement the
communication plan.
UNC performs the communication function
for the network.
Now, within the network, here are the
responsibilities.
There are four core areas.
WHO take care of two, knowledge
advancement and policy and
advocacy.
In terms of knowledge advancement, WHO
look at research, knowledge management,
technology assessment.
For the policy and advocacy, they look at
the global and national
level poli advocacy, and the policy
formulation and review of strategic
document.
UNICEF leads on the capacity development,
training
workshop, dissemination of best practices,
et cetera.
And also take care of monitoring, where we
talk about the global process, progress,
on HWTS, and then the mapping at, of
implementation at the country level.
UNC maintains regular and constant
communication
within the secretariat and outside the
secretariat.
Out, here are some of the key achievements
but not all.
We've hosted over a dozen, over half a
dozen regional workshops
leading to the formation of over 20
national HWTS action plans.
A tool kit of harmonized indicators to
strengthen
monitoring and implementation of HWTS has
also been developed.
And awareness have been raised on
integration.
The need for integration among key public
health efforts.
Such as HV, HIV AIDS, maternal and child
health, nutrition, et cetera.
And we rarely emphasize on the role of
HWTS.
Out of these abrife notes that we can lay
hands on.
Again, we are supporting a quality
assurance
of HWTS products through the HWTS
evaluations scheme.
Then there is a global capacity building
through strategic webinars.
What worked and what is or what is
working?
The co-hosting arrangement actually
harnessed the
strength of both UNICEF and WHO.
The original workshops has really been
great.
It's focus is controlled and it's really I
mean selected based
on the countries and this one really have
very strong output.
Integration is also great.
It has worked very well with other
environmental health
such as the indoor air
pollution et cetera.
We are however have a bit of challenges.
The first is the working groups.
It started well but then it died off.
I can li, link it like a community of
practice.
So what we intend doing is now when an
issue is hot,
then you will form a community of practice
to deal with that issue.
Again, the network has a very ambitious
target.
And as we go down implementation during
the review,
we will look at what needs to be done.
There need to be a clear alignment
and harmonization between water safety
plans and HWTS.
There's been a bit of confusion whether
HWTS is under the water safety
plans or not, but we realize that HWTS is
unique on it's own, but at the same time,
it's also one of the vital
or the vital
actions that will help water safety plans
at the community level.
The advisory group was also working great
but
however we are faced with challenges of
membership.
Here on this slide, we have the
information, the network home
page is hosted by WHO and the other one
hosted by UNC.
Then, if you want to subscribe to the
newsletter, you
can contact Ryan, the
communication at the email below.
And Ryan will comfortably and add you to
the network
and you will receive all the information
that is needed.
Thank you very much for participation.
Again, I'm Michael Forson, the co-host to the
network.
Thank you.
[SOUND]