Hello I'm Aurelier Favier, project manager of this course
and I would like to welcome you to cement chemistry
and sustainable cementitious materials.
This course will introduce you the basic of cement integration
and out to develop
and characterize low carbon cement.
It is divided in two main parts.
The first part will enter do sustainability
and the chemistry of cementitious materials during four weeks.
The last two weeks will focus on the use of X.Ray diffraction
For the analysis of carbon cements.
During the first week, Professor Scrivener
introduce you to the challenge facing research
and development of cement. It will detail of a viable
solution to meet the ecological challenges
and growing demand for building materials. In week two,
we will begin the courses on the duration of cement. you will
learn of also those microstructure and the
consequence of the property is medium and long term.
To complete the course on the duration, a week free
will be devoted for tutorial for the use of scanning electron
microscopy on put a phase to
characterize a cement during the duration.
First video will explain how
to stop the duration proper
and pretty simple for microscopy
Then the second tutorial will show you
SEM-DX to identify these phases and quantify them.
The last week of the first part will
detail a different kinetics of cemented ration
and will be restricted with a tutorial on as a
general calorimetry to monitor the progressive reaction.
Finally the two last week will focus
on the use of X.Ray diffraction
to characterize cement, hydrated phases
suplementary cementitious materials.
You will find different demonstration videos to
illustrate the data acquisition phases it into vacations
and quantification by rietveld method.
For our discourse you will find quizzes,
exercises documents
and complimentary links,
as well as videos on the development of limestone crafts
and Clay cements else if it were.
The whole team thanks you for your participation and wish you a good time with us.