In 2012
four billion tons of cement were produced worldwide.
This makes concrete the product most consumed by humans.
Compared to many other materials,
producing cement is very ecological
But with several billion often produced each year, the cement
industry become a major contributor to global CO2 emissions.
To reduce its impact we constituted a part
of cement by supplementary cementitious materials.
Our new course, cement chemistry and sustainable construction materials,
will introduce you using lecture
and tutorials about the cement hydration
and how to develop and
characterized the carbon cement.
This course will be divided into two major phases.
The cement chemistry during the first four weeks.
Then the last two weeks will focus on the use of
X. Ray diffraction for the analysis of the carbon cements.
Professor Scrivener and her team;
and Dr Snellings, researcher at VITO, hope to find all you there.