OK! So welcome back.
In this second unit of this introductory module
I've called it why Portland cement.
And what we're going to look at in this module is why
the composition of cement is as it is.
Why Portland Cement? 99.99% of cement made today
is based on what we call Portland cement
or more precisely Portland Cement clinker.
So clinker is these nodules you see in the picture here
and that's the material that
comes out of the cement kiln.
And the name Portland this is purely a marketing name
this was chosen by Joseph Aspin who was the person who patented
the term Portland Cement in 1824
and what he wanted to do, he wanted to highlight the
appearance of his new material to Portland stone which was then
regarded as the best building material in England. So
don't worry about this word Portland it's purely a marketing term
So the dominance of this type of cement is really not by chance.
It's a direct consequence of the raw materials
which we have available on Earth.
So here on the left we see the composition of the earth's crust
and it's remarkable to see that we have just eight
elements that's to say oxygen, Silicon, Aluminium
iron, calcium, sodium, potassium, magnesium. These together
make up more of than 98% of the earth crust.
This is quite remarkable
but for those of you who may have done some astronomy
will realize that it's a direct consequence of the formation of
elements in stars.
And it also means that this is not just the composition of the earth
but we're really a similar composition for all
the rocky planets we can imagine in the universe.
What this means is that even elements we regard
as quite common like for example copper,
are very much less abundant than these eight
rock forming elements like for example silica.
And this relative abundance of one to a thousand
will translate in terms of the availability
and the cost of these materials.
So having seen in the last marginal how
very large amount of the cement that's
produced, clearly we can't think about making cement
out of the all the other elements that is in that remaining 2%
So now we can understand that the composition
of the earth which limits the practical chemistries
we can have the cementitious materials.
But looking on the bright side, it also means that
we can explore all possible options, it means that there's no kind of
breakthrough out there that
we haven't discovered there yet.
And what we need to really know in a bit more detail is how cement
works to understand how these different elements can be used.
So this is what I've illustrated in the next few slides.
So this schematic here really tries to explain this.
When you mix grey cement powder with water,
what you have is grains just floating about
and that is very convenient because it means you have a
florable material, you can cast into molds you can make into
different shapes. And then we have a chemical process
whereby these gray cement grains are dissolving
and then the ions are reacting with the water to give us
this new solid wood shop called the hydrates. So in this image
here, the red areas are the cement hydrates.
And these have a higher volume of solid
and therefore it holds the cement grains together.
Are creating a rigid solid.
So let's go back
and look at this composition of the earth.
Most of those elements are associated with oxygen as oxides
and look at whether these different oxides can react
to give us a cemetery material.
Now if we take the two
alkali oxide sodium and potassium,
the problem here is these produce very soluble salts.
So maybe in your chemistry lessons you've used
Now if we take the two
alkali oxide sodium and potassium,
the problem here is these produce very soluble salts.
So maybe in your chemistry lessons you've used
sodium hydroxide
and you'll know that you can have very strong sodium hydroxide
because a very high amount can go into solution without
precipitating. So clearly this is no good for producing solid
hydrates which hold the structure together.
On the other hand, if we look and iron oxide and magnesium oxide,
the problem here is that these oxide have fairly
low mobility in alkaline solutions which is the
solutions we have in cementitious materials.
So what we can see in this image
here this is just a piece of concrete taken
from a normal concrete wall and in this
image we have some very bright areas
and these very bright areas are
where all the site is located.
And in fact those bright areas are exactly the same as in the
original cement grains. During that whole thirty years
that in the cement grains has just stayed
in the same place. so it's not doing any harm
but basically it means it's not going out
into solution it's not precipitating new solids
and therefore making very little contribution
to the bonding and the development of strength.
It's a similar story for magnesium here in this picture
now we see a blended cement, we're going to talk about that in a
few modules time and in
this blended cement.
The darker grains such as in the center of the picture here
you see are now surrounded by a region of dark products
and these darker project products are because all the
magnesium that was in that slag grain is concentrated there in
that area.
And same situation this Magnesium has not moved into
the space between the grains it's not really contributed to
bridging the space between them.
So this means we end up with just three
oxides which are really the most useful
bridging the space between them.
So this means we end up with just three
oxides which are really the most useful
and of the essential component for the Portland cement
we have today. So this is really in no way a coincidence that
we've ended up with this composition because if we now
look at that Turnery system between calcium oxide silicon
dioxide and alumina, we see the
composition of Portland cement.
And in fact portland cement as we see it here this is
composed of calcium silicates there's really only one are the region
in this diagram where we have minerals that
will react with water in the way we previously saw
and give us cementitious materials
and that's this region here which is the
reason where we find calcium Aluminite cements
and calcium aluminate cements. Small amount of sulfur
is the sort of extra dimension which is not shown in this
diagram here.
So these other compositions calcium aluminum calcium sulfur
Aluminite, have a lot of advantage because they have less
calcium and you see their further away from that county oxide
corner, means they have less calcium oxide
and therefore there's less CO2 produced
chemically during the production of these phases.
so there are some. It's very good
but the problem is that it's not so easy to make
these because the raw materials we need a not so widely available.
And we have to ask the question, what sources are minerals
are there which contain much higher amounts of alumina to silica.
Most minerals have about the same ratio of silicon to
aluminum, as in Portland Cement about two to one to get a
composition down here in this alumina rich part of the
diagram we have to go to materials like bauxite.
Now bauxite is much more localized than
the materials used for making Portland cement.
It's estimated that only ten countries contain
about ninety percent of the reserves of bauxite
And of course book site is the
first real material for aluminium production
So the consequence of all this
means that it's rather expensive
and it means that you cannot produce
calcium aluminate cement
or calcium so for eliminate cement for the same cost
as producing Portland cement.
we can look at this
effect of chemical CO2
and how it's related to composition
in more detail on this slide here.
So the top we see the two
calcium silicate which
are present in Portland cement.
tricalciumsilicate C3S,
Dicalcium silicate or C2S.
And many people have proposed that what we should be
doing is making Portland cement with more C2S
As opposed to C3S
But the problem here is that the reduction in chemical CO2
is really very marginal. it's only around ten percent
and that's more than offset by the much slower
kinetics of C2S so the.
Strength development is much slower
and because the strength developed is much slower
This would mean that him practical situations where people need a
given strength at a given time
then they will use more cement
and that use the more cement will completely cancel out
this ten percent. so be like Rich thinkers really don't
contribute a tall to lowering CO2 emissions.
Down here we can see the figures for yellow might that's this complex
phase called C4s3s Bar
And as I said on the previous slide this has a good
reduction potential in terms of lowest chemical Co2.
But we have the problem of
the cost of the raw materials
and finally on this slide I want to point out this line here
because many people nowadays are proposing that we should
use magnesium based cements, there can be
context in which this might be possible not now
but if somebody can invent
a way of producing.
Magnesium based cements from magnesium
silicate rocks it might be interesting
but what's happening at the minute
Most people are using magnesium carbonate
and what you can see here very clearly is that the
chemical CO2 emissions from breakdown of magnesium carbonate all
way higher than they are from the calcium silicate phases
we have important cement. So here we come back to that
composition of the earth
we've discussed in detail
and we compare it with the composition
of a typical Portland cement.
And you can see the elements present are similar.
The big difference between the Portland cement
and the composition of the earth is the dominance
of this sector for cousine. And this is as we explained
In the last lecture where the
chemical CO2 is coming from
but from a practical point of view it's very easy to make
things with this composition because limestone which is
usually very pure Calcium carbonate is very
widely distributed across the globe
and it could mean that you can make these poor has cement
out of limestone the other elements are generally coming from
something like clay, but you can make
this almost everywhere in the world
and therefore transportation of the final product is minimise.
So the other important aspect is the passage of reaction
of the Portland cement
and this is shown in this diagram here which puts
the heat evolution, which is a signature of the rate of reaction.
And what we can see is if the beginning of the
reaction we have we have a burst of reaction
and then we have this period here where the reaction remains
slow for several hours. For a practical point of view this
is extremely important as it gives us time to
mix the cement and transported to the building site.
And then after about three hours the reaction takes off again.
Now this pattern of reaction means that it's very
very simple to use cementitious materials. Here we see
a picture from India where people are making concrete under
really quite rustic conditions.
But nevertheless because it's such a robust chemical reaction
it still works is still gives very good quality building materials.
Really well we're going to see that for all these
reasons I have explained to you here cement space on
Portland clinker will be the most important materials
for the forseeable future. They can be made from widely available
road materials. There's an incredible economy of
scale leading to very low cost and they're very.
Easy to use even by unskilled workers.
Given the composition of the earth, this composition
Portland Cement clinker really is the best option
but in the next lecture, What are we going to see
how by replacing part of this Portland cement we can lower
environmental impact.
So thank you very much.