So hello and welcome to this series on cement
chemistry for sustainable cementitious materials
In this series of Modules, we're
going to look at the cement chemistry
and how this helps us to understand the
sustainability of these very important to materials.
Most of the modules should be really understandable to
anybody with a fairly basic knowledge of high school chemistry.
In the first module, we're going
o look at the overall context.
We're going to look at the role of cementitious material
in the world today and what are the origins of their CO2 footprint.
Now in this first slide,
we can see the overwhelming dominance of cementitious materials
They make up between thirty to fifty
percent of everything we produce. Probably about fifty percent
of solid materials and thirty percent
if we include things like fossil fuels.
And in the light of that the fact that they're responsible
for CO2 emissions of around five to ten percent is a
very good
Ratio.
But more importantly, we can really see that this just
would no way be possible to replace cementitious materials
with alternatives at any meaningful level.
For example, if we look at the amount of wood produced worldwide, this is
between ten and fifteen percent the
amount of cementitious materials
and already it's estimated that this amount of wood is beyond
the limits of sustainability that's to say we're cutting
down more trees than we're planting.
So while this may be a nice option in Europe
or North America, it's really not practical for the
many people who need to be housed in countries like China, India,
Africa and South America.
This slide here really shows how the
environmental footprint of concrete is very low
and we should talk about concrete because concrete
is the final material we really use. Cement is the precursor
and that's roughly about
ten percent of cement in concrete.
On the right here I've
normalised these figures compared to
the highest which is Alluminium. You can
see very vividly just how much energy
and CO2 you can save
by recycling alluminium
and I hope after seeing this you don't
throw your coke can in the bin anymore.
But concrete is really extremely low,
lower than almost all other materials.
Of course this is
just on a weight
basis. When you put this into a structure, it becomes
more complicated. We're not going to go into that here.
But generally, even in that situation concrete still
comes out very strongly as an environmentally friendly material.
The amount of cement we're using has increased
very very dramatically in the past few decades.
since 1950, the population has increased about three fold
and at the same period the amount of cement we use has
increased by about thirty four times.
In recent decades this is really being
driven by the development in China
and we should not view this negatively because, this development
has lifted a lot of people out of poverty. It's provided
them with decent homes, with roads, railways
to get around and everything like that.
But we certainly cannot imagine that this growth in
demand for cement is going to slow down because there are many many
other parts of the world where people still haven't have decent housing
or transportation systems.
Finally where we do with our lives and the CO2 produced
is a question of choices.
And here again if we decide to build a house,
we make maybe a house for a family of three people,
This will typically take about
ten to twenty tons of cement
and last for about fifty years. So we can calculate
from that that the CO2 to do with your materials in your house
is about twelve kilograms a month.
Now if you're driving a car which you
almost certainly are that same family of three
will probably drive at least
ten thousand kilometers a year
and then they'll be consuming fossil fuels which will
be producing about ninety kilograms of CO2 per year.
Seven or eight times more than
the materials in their house.
But we should also reflect on our other choices
in life for example the food we eat.
Here you can see for a very meat
intensive diet the associated CO2 production would
be around five to seven kilograms of CO2 per day.
Whereas a vegetarian diet is much lower at around
three to four kilograms the CO2 it per day
And so if we calculate for the same imaginary
family of three that they went from eating meat to being vegetarian,
maybe for just two
or three days a month, this would be equivalent to saving
all the CO2 that they need to build their house.
So rather than just blaming the producers of these materials,
we have to think about what we're doing in our lives
and what we choose
to do that produces CO2.
OK there's no reason for complacency
because if we did nothing about the
CO2 footprint of cementitious materials,
we could end up in a situation like this.
here we see the blue line is the
trajectory that has been estimated we
should try to meet if we're to restrict global warming to.
There's two degrees temperature rise.
Whether we're going to do that or not is another question,
but that the trajectory of overall global
emissions if we're going to do that.
If we achieve that blue line and we did nothing about cement,
then the emissions from the production of cement
and some tissues materials
will form of the red line.
And we see the by 2050 we would end up in a situation
where cementitious materials would be responsible for
something like thirty percent of world C O two emissions,
which is clearly unacceptable.
So where is the consumption
of cement taking place?
What we see here is the distribution
of cement we use around the world.
And only about ten percent of cement
used is taking place in O.E.C.D.
Countries
And in these countries, it's forecast that demand will
really stay pretty much constant. More than ninety percent of
consumption is taking part in the developing world, particularly
in China which has been very dominant over the past two
decades. It's been estimated in the last three
years China produced more concrete than was produced in the whole of
North America in the twentieth century.
And many other countries like India in particular,
are looking to follow this development path to provide decent houses
for their people, decent rail systems
and decent road systems.
And this will inevitably mean that the growth in use of
cement is going to increase. So if we're going to meet this
challenge of the growing demand for cement, we need
solutions where first of all practical they can be used by
unskilled workers
and this shows you the kind of typical situation
you can have for mixing concrete examples from India
and also economically.
Now you know cement is an incredibly cheap
in most of Europe, you can buy a ton of
cement for less than one hundred euros for a whole ton.
In many developing countries though the prices are
actually higher even though the incomes are lower so it's a very
important that we have solutions which are really economically
viable for these countries where there's this huge need
for building infrastructure and housing etc.
So let's look at where the CO2 emissions are coming from.
Unlike most other industrial processes,
only a minority of the C O two emissions are coming
from the energy consumption. Producing cement is the high
temperature process, going up to temperatures of
fourty or fifty and this does take energy
but it's still the minor amount.
A cement kiln as we see here looks like a
fairly unsophisticated type of instrument.
But this is in fact not true because in the past few
decades there's been very dramatic improvement in the amount of
energy needed to produce cement
And it really state of the art equipment now, the
production process is highly optimized to nearly eighty percent of the
thermodynamic limit, which is those
of you who will study thermodynamics
will know is very close to the maximum you can achieve.
Another factor which is important is that rather
than using fossil fuels which used to be the dominant
means in the past, nowadays we can use a wide variety of waste
fuels.
So for example of cuts from producing furniture,
Old car tires, many many different kind
of ways can be burnt in a cement kiln
and in many parts of Europe, plants are
using more than eighty percent of waste fuels.
So this is a very efficient
tool for valorising waste materials.
So if we're going to make improvements we need to
turn to the other side to this sixty percent of the equation
and this sixty percent This comes from the
breakdown of calcium carbonate into calcium oxide and co2.
Calcium carbonate, this is in fact limestone which is
eighty percent of the raw material used to make cement.
Now the fact we have this chemical CO2 means that if we're
going to reduce this, then we're going to have this has
implications for the chemistry of the cement
and that means it has implications for the whole way it
behaves in use etc which of course is a bit challenging.
So what are we seeing in this lecture? Well we've
seen how important cementitious materials are, how they make up
by far the overwhelming majority of all the materials we used
and therefore cannot be replaced by other materials.
We've seen that in fact the environmental footprint from these
materials is in fact quite low and we've looked
at where the CO2 emissions come from
and we've seen that most of the C O two emissions
come from the chemical breakdown of limestone that's calcium
carbonate
and therefore we can't really imagine to do much about
CO2 emissions by for example looking at alternative energies
So in the next lecture we're going to go into more
detail about why the chemistry of cement is as it is,
So I look forward to
seeing you next time
and I hope you've enjoyed this first module. If
you want to find out more, then this publication Eco-efficient cements
which we published in November 2016, gives
you a very good background to all the aspects I will tackle
in this first module.