So welcome to the third video in this introductory module series.
In this module, we're going to talk about how we
can know the environmental impact of cemetitious materials by
replacing part of the Portland cement clinker with other cementitious materials.
So classically, cement has been clinke
which is ground with a small addition of calcium sulphate
normally referred to as gypsum to produce cement.
And this is what we call only Portland Cement O.P.C.
or Plain portland cement.
If the Years ago this made up
practically all the cement produced
but nowadays the vast majority of cement produced also contain
what are known as supplementary cementitious materials or SCMs
Now what are these SCMs?
Some examples are limestone which comes from the quarry.
Fly ash which comes from burning coal to produce electricity
slag which comes from blast furnaces where iron ore is
is reduced iron and natural porcelains which
are found in nature and finally calcine clays.
Now these are often bright
products a waste from other industry
and their availability well vary considerably from place to place.
If we look at the overall level of substitution of
S.C.M.
Since immense around the world, we can see in this graph
here that just three materials make up the overwhelming
majority of the substitutes.
Namely; limestone slag and fly ash
Secondly we can see that while a few years ago
the level of substitution was increasing, for the last five
or six years it's remained almost static.
Now before we look at the reasons for this let's
look at these different S.E.'s in a bit more detail.
So first we have limestone. This comes through from the
same quarry where limestone is excavated for produce in the clinker,
but the important thing here is passage doesn't pass through
the kiln it doesn't lose it CO2. It's typically into ground
where the cement during milling
and we find that if we have small levels of addition up
to about five percent it actually enhances the properties
and this is due to the fact that a small amount
of the limestone does react with the illuminated feigns
and also because the fine lines the particles, enhances
the nucleation of the C.S.H. and Give a denser microstructure.
Now we don't actually need to use high quality
limestone, although this is often required in standards.
The second material is blasphemy slag.
Schematic here shows that we have iron
which comes from the iron ore
and slag is the material which is used to help
the separation of the iron from the impurities in the iron ore.
This material is liquid during in
the blast furnace and then is poured off.
And depending on the cooling, we can either have
crystalline material which really can only be used as aggregate.
Which is actual slag we can also make expand
this flag which can be used as lightweight aggregate
but what we're really interested in is when we
quench this slag which one is what is known as granulation,
and by this very fast cooling with water,
then we produce amorphous phases
and these amorphous phases can then
dissolve in water and react like the cement grains.
And here we see a picture of the slag, we can see these
angular grains. They're made up about 90% percent or more of them
or amorphous material.
And then this is ground
And the break up of this glass gives these sharp irregular
glassy materials. It has a very high calcium oxide
content
and produces what is called a latent hydraulic material.
Because of the high couse in content then we can replace very
high amounts of clinker in cement chipper called
replacement levels are in the range from 30-70% percent.
The problem with slag is that the growth in availability of
Slag has been not as fast as the growth in availability of cement.
So at present the annual production of Slag is only
around eight percent of the production of clinker
and this proportion is unlikely to increase
because we're producing more or more iron
and steel from recycled materials
and this means there's less
slag available from blast furnace.
Next we move to fly ash
and as I've said, this is the installable incombustible
material which is in the coal. What happens is during the
burning of the coal little droplets of water form,
these droplets then are carried in the flue gas
and subsequently recovered by electrostatic precipitation
to avoid their dispersion into the atmosphere.
Now because they are very small,
they cooled quite quickly
and this quick cooling again leads
to the formation of amorphous glassy material
So we have much lower proportion of amorphous
material. We typically find the that the core of these
grains is crystalline, because of this reason and the
chemical composition where it contains less cow C.M.
This is less reactive and slag
and the typical levels of addition we
can make up to around thirty percent.
Now the other problem with fly ash is that
it's a very heterogeneous material. In this micrographs
here we can see the different grade levels indicate the
different chemical composition and on the right
here we've made a chemical mapping of that fly ash
and the different colors indicate different chemical
compositions. So what you can really see is that the chemical
composition varies considerably from place to place and
this makes it quite tricky to determine how fly ash is react
and means of one fly ash can behave quite differently from another fly ash.
So in this series of slides, we can look at
the availability of these SCMs compared to Portland Cement.
So this red bar shows the amount of Portland cement produced
in the world today, just over four billion tonnes.
And if we look at these common replacement materials; slag
and fly ash, we see that there are the amounts available much
lower than the amount of Portland cement.
So we have about eight percent
compared to portland cement.
and the vast majority of this is already used either
blended with cement or idea of the concrete stage.
When we come to fly ash overall we have a somewhat higher
amount. Because of that variability, the amount that can be
used with cement
is quite a bit lower
and these two materials together make up only around fifteen
percent of the amount of Portland cement produced today.
Now people have looked for other materials
that can be blended in. The other material we have is.
Limestone we've talked about earlier and
there's effectively a limited amount of this material available.
But the problem is that we can't have very high
amounts without diluting the properties of the cement.
And generally if we have additions above
about ten percent or so then the strength
and other properties of the cement tends to decrease.
Now people have looked at other materials to uses S C M's which we
see now here on the top.
We see natural pozzolan land.
The amount used today are really quite small.
This could perhaps be increased,
but nevertheless geographically the
distribution of natural pozzolan is very uneven.
People have considered vegetable ashes, so notably,
the ash produced by burning ash husks can be an active
addition cementitious materials.
But the amounts of available
are really quite small
and there are a lot of other problems with these vegetable
ashes such that they're only produced seasonally, they are
produced tend to be produced in rural areas where
the big demand for cement is in urban areas
and currently many of these.
Agricultural waste are used as fertilizers So if they're
taken off the land, they may lead to a problem of soil
fertility.
People have talked about waste glass, but really we see
that the amounts of this a very very small
and of course it's much much better to
recycle waste class into new bottles.
And finally of course silica few which is a very high
performance additive widely used to produce high performance
concrete but the amount available
are really very very small.
So what else can we have?
Now what we really.
The see is this is only one material that's
available in the kind of quantities we really need
and this is calcine clay. And the amounts of
calcine clay really are virtually unlimited.
So to summarize that, what we see is that there's
no magic solution. Blended cements with S C M's will be the best
solution for sustainable for cement for the forseeable future. The traditional S.C.M.S.
We have are only about fifteen percent
compared to the amount of cement we produce
and the only material available in viable
quantities apart from these is calcine clay.
And even more interesting, is the use of combination of calcine
clay with limestone which will talk about in another
video of this module.
So this material, this material with the combination of
calcine clay and limestone is what we call limestone calcine clay cement
or L C three.
So before summarizing this, I just want to say a short
word about Alkali activated materials or Geopolymers
The low availability of slag is the main reason
why alkaline activated materials will not contribute
significantly to lowering global CO2 emissions.
All the formulations of alkali activated materials
contained to today, contain mainly slag
And as we've seen the availability of slag is really very low.
So I slag is diverted from used in cement plants
and concrete and.
To be used in alkali activated materials, but we may be able
to say that these that these alkali activated materials have a
lower CO2 emissions, but globally the
emissions of other concrete will increase
and in fact what we need to consider is
also the CO2 emissions of the alkali activator.
And for these two reasons, the CO2
emissions may be increased at a global level.
And in fact there are very few countries which have
really abundant supplies a slag which would favor the use of alkali
activated materials, so one exception in this case is Japan.
OK So let's summarize what we've seen in this lecture.
In this lecture we've seen that supplementary seven
tissues materials are an effective way to reduce the amount of
clinker in cement or in concrete
and hence to reduce CO2 emissions. Over the past few
decades, the average level of substitution has increased to
around twenty percent and this is made
up mainly of slag, fly ash and limestone.
Further progress in this respect is mainly
limited by the availability of these SCMs
and this limited availability is also the main reason that
alkali activated materials cannot have really significant
impact on lowering overall emissions
from cementitious materials.
What we have seen is only other material
available in the kind of quantities we need
is clay which is active when Calcined
and this is particularly interesting
when used in combination of limestone. So in the next lecture
we're going to look in detail at the use of calcine clays for
cement and concrete.
So thank you for listening and hope to see you next time.