So welcome to video number four in this introductory module.
And in this video we're going to talk about LC3
or limestone calcine clay cement.
So what is limestone calcine cement?
This is a family of cements and often we talk of LC-350 or LC-365.
The figure in this case refers to the clinker content.
So here we see on the left, we see the composition of
ordinary portland cement where we have about 95% clinker,
or 5% of calcium suphate or gypsum.
When we have typical portland pozzolanic cements as shown here,
we will have about 70% clinker and about 30% pozzolan,
which can be typically something like
fly ash but can also be calcine clay.
And usually because of the reactivity of these pozzolanic additions,
30% is the highest level of addition we find in practice.
However, what is very special about the LC3 family,
is now instead of adding calcine clay on it's own,
we add calcine clay
together with limestone.
And what we find is that we can add an extra 15% of limestone,
we can remove 15% more of the clinker,
and we can get the same performance
as in the pozzolanic case here.
So on the right here we see some strengthened results for LC350. You see that
one day the strenght is somewhat lower and it was for the ordinary portland cement,
But already by only 7 days, the strenght of the LC-350
system has surpassed that of the ordinary portland cement
and it is still higher at 28 days.
So this quite remarkable because it means that
for only 50% of the clinker, we have the same performance.
This also means we have about 30% less CO2.
We get just as I said similar strenght.
And in some respect, we have quite a big improvement in the properties,
particularly in respect to chloride penetration and Alkali siica reaction.
So in this module, what we are going to
talk about is what types of clays can be used
how they can be calcined
and where we can find the kind of
suitable clays in the world today.
So what we see in this slide here are
the crystal structure of the basic clay types.
They are all clays' layer structures so here we see
the layers and these layers are alluminosilicate layers.
So we see the orange dots represent the silicon
atoms which are found in little tetrahedra.
So in a little cage of oxygens. And the green atoms
represent aluminium, which are found in octahedral cages of oxygen.
Now two materials on the left here, the
Illites and the montmorillonite are called 2-1 clays.
What these means is that we have two silicate layers here,
and here we have sandwiched the aliminium layer in the middle.
And the diference between Illites and the montmorillonite,
is in terms of the irons that are found between the layers
and the montmorillonite usually has
alkali ions and more water between the layers.
And finally on the right here, we have the kaolinite structure,
and the kaolinitic clays are what is called 1:1 clays
And this means in the layers we have on
layer of silicate and one layer of aluminate.
In this slide here, what we see is the thermal
decomposition of the different clay types.
And that these have a thermal
decomposition in different ranges.
And what these peaks represent? They represent the amount of
heat that is absorbed by the material as it is heated up
And this heat is absorbed due to the loss of hydroxide
from the structure which is called dehydroxilation.
And we can see that these different clay types
have dehydroxilation in different temperature range.
The clearest dehydroxilation is this one here for the
kaolinite which occurs between about 450 and 650 degrees.
And this signature provides a very good way of determining
how many kaolinite we have in any clay we have to investigate.
All you do is to make this
kind of thermal decomposition
You can simply quite do it by heating
your material in two different ovens
one of the ovens is
400 and the other 700
looking at the weight loss
between these two temperatures.
Of course as you can see there will be a small
interference if you also have some highlight in the example.
But these kinds of effects can be determined
by looking at something like a Xray difraction diagram.
If we look at the electromicrograph,
we can see this layered clay structure,
we can see that the clay are made up of little platelets.
Here we see the raw clay before dehydroxilation,
here we see the clay after dehydroxilation, basically this level in the SCM
you dont see any change in the morphology, it appears to be very similar.
We have to use other techniques to really see
what's happening within the crystal structure.
and particularly useful in
this regard is solid state NMR
when we study 27 aluminium ion.
So nuclear magnetic resonance or N.M.R.
Is a technique that can be used to look at the
local environment of a particular species.
So we see for the two two to one clays, Illite to
montmorillonite that as we heat these materials, we get a
transition of the aluminium from the octahedral coordination
in the wall clay. Octahedron has six a pair apexes
So this is also called a six coordination to a
tetrahedral coordination or a four fold coordination.
What is quite clearly different in the Kaolinitic Clays
is that as well as the shift from octahedral coordination to
tetrahedral coordination, we see quite clearly the emergence
of this five fold coordinated site. and this five fold
coordinated site is the
indicative of a disordered
or semi amorphous sight, which is what
means that it's easier for it for react.
so this is a very important difference between
that happens in thermal decomposition between the two to one clays
and the one to one kaolinitic clays.
The one to one
kaolinitic Clays had this disordered
Aluminium which is then the
atoms that can go on and react without cementitious materials.
Here we see the appearance of these
calcined clays depending on the other materials
that are present in the clay, the color of the clay can change over the whole
spectrum from white to reddish
If there's a lot of iron oxides present.
You can actually control the color of
that comes out in the end by the
conditions of oxidation reduction in the kiln.
OK in this slide here, what we see is the pozzolanic reaction all of
these different clay types in cement. So the
pozzolanic reaction basically involves the reaction of the pozzolan
and the calcine clay in this case with
calcium hydroxide that comes from the cement.
And these different this code here,
K stands for Kaolinitic, I stands for Illitic,
M for montmorillonite clays. And as references
we've got the plain O.P.C. and The plain O.P.C.
With us than in the filler
which in this case was course.
So we can see how the different clays react by looking at
their consumption of calcium hydroxide relative to the amount.
of the cement, the
clinker based cement O.P.C.So we can see how the different clays
react by looking at their consumption of calcium hydroxide relative to the amount.
And in most cases, we see that the amount of calcined
hydroxide produced is actually somewhat higher than the reference
which is this curve in black,
which is the plain importance cement.
And the amount of calcium hydroxide is somewhat higher
purely due to a filler effect as in this gray curve here, where
the fact that you have a dilution of the cement by
the clay gives a bit more room for the cement to react so it
produces a bit more calcium hydroxide.
In sharp contrast, we see the kaolinitic clays here
we have much lower cousine hydroxide contents this cast some
hydroxide content becomes lower
with time and this is a typical
signature of the pozzolanic
reaction of the calcined clay.
Even in very early ages we can see the calcium hydroxide
content is very much reduced compared to the Portland cement reference.
Finally we perhaps want to look at this montmorillonite
clay here wish does seem to show some reaction at later ages.
What should be the optimum temperature for the calcination.
In this graph, here we see for a particular clay
that has been calcined at different temperatures
how the strength there is over time. So the different temperatures
we've used are the plain raw Clay with
no calcination at all. 600,700,750,800
And the raw clay, it's just reacting as a filler
So you see the strength development is really quite poor. The calcined
clays even from three days are giving a very significant
increase which is indicative of their reaction.
And we see by seven days that for this particular clay
which contained about forty percent kaolinite
If for the optimum calcination temperatures,
this strength is supporting that of the Portland cement. We see the
strength is increasing from six hundred to seven
hundred to seven fifty. Eight hundred is about the same
and by the time we get to eight fifty then we see in
this particular case the strength is going down.
And this is what we have observed in most cases that
the optimum calcination temperature is in this range seven fifty
to eight hundred. It may be somewhat lower
if you have small content of calcite in the Clay.
Instead of having to do
this series of strength tests,
What we see on the right is the results of a
reactivity test which we'll talk about later in the
series and here we can use much smaller amounts of
clay and study the heat evolution in what's called a calorimeter
but we can see the same trend, we can see the raw
material has no reactivity, at six hundred we get modest reaction
this increases through
Seven hundred, seven fifty, eight hundred
and then by eight fifty there's a clear decrease in reactivity.
Now why do we have this decrease in reactivity? we can
see that in this series here, this is the clay calcined to
six hundred. We can see these are grown roots of these tiny
clay platelets.
Again we can see these are
glommerates at eight hundred and now
when we go to higher temperatures in this case
we've gone right up to 925, we now can see that we
no longer see the individual
platelets but we see these kind of.
glassy looking glass grains
and what's happened is we've had a small amount of liquid phase
forming which actually syntax these clay particles together
And if we have this happening, then we'll
get a very strong decrease in reactivity.
So the critical question now is what grade of clay do
we need to be able to make these L.C. Three materials?
So at EPFL here, we've started a wide range of clays from
around the world. These clays had different origins, some came from
Latin America some from India or other parts of
Asia except for even from Europe and the finest of this clay
by the production method of the clay the different the
minor phases that were present in addition to clay, all of these
very quite widely between the different materials.
But we have calcined all of these
if they weren't calcined, we'll calcine these clays
and then we use them in the LC350 system and
measure their strength in the European mortar walk test.
And what we see quite clearly here is that we get a very
clear correlation between the calcined kaolinite content that's
the amount of Kaoline which was in the original clay
that had been broken down during the calcination, between the
calcined kaolinite content.
And the compressive strength development, so we have different
curves here for the different ages for one day for seven
days three days, for seven days
twenty eight days, ninety days.
And in addition to this strong correlation with the
calcined kaolinite content, we've indicated here by this dotted line,
we've indicated the reference strength of the prime
Portland cement. So you can see the three days if you have a
kaolinite content of over eighty percent, you can meet the
same strength as your ordinary portland cement. Whereas if you're prepared
to wait a bit longer to about seven days then if
you have a kaolinite content of between forty
and fifty percent, you will get a similar
strength to your ordinary Portland cement.
So this is very important
because it means for this LC3
system, we don't need to use very high purity clays.
High purity clays notably used to produce Mehtakaoline have to
have very strong requirements for
color for purity except.
Which makes them very expensive where is these kind of clays
which contain much lower amounts of kaolinite only
say forty fifty percent are generally waste
materials which are consequently much cheaper.
So the kind of clays we want to use are very
widely distributed around the Earth.
And this is a Soil Map which gives an indication of
what kind of clays you're likely to find below the surface
and it's a rather simplistic.
Representation
but we can be quite sure that in all the regions where
we have this yellow color or this pink color there we will
certainly have abundance in clays
and we see that this is really very very widely available
in the central equitorial subtropical region going through
China Southeast Asia, India, Africa and Latin America
And in fact we've seen in India where we've might made
much more detailed studies that suitable clays are not confined
only to these yellow and pink regions
but we actually have very large amounts of suitable
clays for example in this region of India in Gujarat chain
registers on which on this soil map will appear
or not to be so suitable. So What's the main message
here, they say kind of clays we need are incredibly abundant
throughout the world the reserves are virtually unlimited.
These are just the countries in the equitorial subtropical
regions where the growth and
demand for cement is strongest.
And in many of these countries, what we can find is that
the suitable clothes are currently stockpiled as waste.
So this picture comes from a quarry in India.
This is a quarry where there extracting high purity clay for
producing Metakaoline which is then used
for ceramics or in the paper industry
and this huge mountain here is just waste. This is material
which has too low quality for exploitation at the present
time, but this waste here is a very suitable quality for blending with cement.
And we've taken those kind of waste materials,
we've made full scale trial productions. This just shows a couple of
houses produced from these productions. This one in Cuba
here. This one in India all the materials the
Concrete blocks, the render here the roof tiles etc,
These are all produced with LC3 material
and they were actually produced they could be produced by
totally unskilled workers in the same factories with those
special training, just purely with a
one to one replacement, taking one back of the
Cement that was used before either O.P.C.
or Pozzolanic cement with fly ash
and replacing that with LC3.
And in this case in India we made a more
detailed calculation of the CO2 savings
and we could calculate that about seven tons of CO2
were saved just in this one single house by using LC3
materials compared to the existing materials.
So let's look at what we've seen in this module.
What we've seen is how we can use a combination of
calcined clay with limestones to go to much higher levels of
substitution than is typical iin pozzolanic cements.
We've seen that it's really the kaolinitic which have
the potential to give these high pozzolanic
activity after calcination.
And this high positronic activity results from their
one to one structure which means we get poorly
Organized alumina after calcination.
The optimum temperature for calculation is in this range
seven fifty eight fifty. If we go to higher temperatures then
we may get centering a loss of surface and reactivity.
If we look at the performance in
Mortars
and concretes we see that if we've got more than about
forty percent Kaoline this can be very suitable for use in LC3
blends, even in our mix system you can
get a similar strength after about seven days
and we're sure you could get even better
earlier strength by optimizing the grinding parameters.
These kind of clays with forty percent
or more kaolinite are very widely available around the
world particularly in the regions where the growth in the
demand cement is highest.
And we've made trial productions of L.C.
Three in both Cuba and India.
So that this short video completes the introductory model.
I hope that you will be interested to come back
and listen to the module on hydration which follows this.