Welcome to POCS again.
This week we'll talk about
redundancy and fault tolerance.
Now redundancy is one of the most
important principles of computer systems.
It actually has roots
in digital systems design.
And fault tolerance is one of
the most important attributes
that we could associate with
any of the systems
we've built through careful design.
So this is a broad topic and as usual
break it into different components.
First we'll talk about redundancy itself
and the techniques by which
we can achieve it.
Then we'll talk about the fundamentals
of the fault tolerance design process.
Then in the third module we'll shift
and start talking briefly about
the metrics and a little bit word
of caution about some of the most
commonly used metrics in the field.
In the fourth module we'll talk about
high-availability.
And high-availability is an approach
in which we apply
a sweeping simplification
and the separation of state in order
to create simple systems
that can achieve a
high degree of availability.
In the fifth module, George Candea
will actually talk to us
about consensus in the presence of
fully distributed systems
including systems that have
various types of faults
including Byzantine Fault and talk about
some of the complications
associated with achieving consensus
in these fully distributed systems.
And then I'll come back
in the final module
and we'll put it all together
by comparing two case studies.
Two very very different ways
of achieving the same degree
of fault-tolerance in modern systems.
So let's talk about redundancy.
And first redundancy is
an overloaded term
and if you look it up
and thank you Wikipedia
you'll see different definitions for it.
First, it actually has a precise
definition in the context
of information theory.
There redundancy equates
the wasted space used
to carry certain data.
Now outside of our scientific field
it has a meaning as well.
For example, in certain countries
that speak a dialect of American,
a redundancy is a synonym
for a layoff or termination.
It also has a precise meaning
in product design,
where a feature is considered redundant
if the same task could be achieved
through multiple different ways.
And the people who are responsible
for product design often refer
to this situation as a belt and suspenders
approach to the system.
That is because you have
two possible ways
of achieving the same function.
Now this brings up, of course,
to the case of redundancy
in fashion with belts and suspenders
as a fashion statement
that you may not want to try this at home.
But redundancy in
computer systems is very different.
It is aptly fundamental,
it has a positive connotation,
it is the foundation for digital design
and computer system.
Now in digital design,
redundancy is defined
as the ability to automatically
detect and correct
deviations for normal behavior.
And you can do that
both in space or in time.
And here's an example of
space-space redundancy,
it's the classic three way
modular redundancy
that is fundamental to digital design.
You replicate the circuit three times
and you have a discrete fourth circuit
which is the majority gate
that is the responsible
to determine the correct output.
Now redundancy also applies
to computer systems
as we'll see the different ways
in which this can be done.
You can achieve this through coding,
through data replication,
through N-way modular redundancy
this time applied to other aspects
not just digital designs
but computer systems.
And by replication of
the entire software stack.
But let's first talk about redundancy
in the context of coding.
Coding is a way to achieve redundancy
in an incremental and efficient way.
This is a principle technique used
to detect, contain, and mask faults
that occur in memory subsystems
and in communication subsystems.
Now coding is cheap since it only requires
an incremental amount of redundancy.
Just add a few bits and you increase
the resiliency of the overall systems.
So for memories,
error correcting codes, or ECC,
have been a saving grace in improving
the availability of computer systems.
And this is an instance of
space redundancy.
Now because they repair single bit errors
which eliminate many forms of failures,
ECCs improve availability of the systems.
In addition, they can detect
double bit errors
which allow the computer systems
to take appropriate action.
And in many cases the action
is either to stop execution
or to take down a particular process.
Now similarly for disk, various forms
of RAID use coding
to recover data efficiently
in the presence of
sector failures or drive failures.
RAID5 for example uses
a simple parity encoding using XOR
which is then symmetrically
distributed across sectors
and that helps you deal with
signal drive failures.
RAID6 extends the concept by using
much more advanced mathematics,
Galois fields to be precise,
and that provides you
the ability to tolerate two independent
drive failures within a RAID group
without losing any data.
Now coding is also present
in all communication layers.
And here this is an instance
of time redundancy.
At the network link layer, layer one,
forward-error-correction
is used to correct transmission
errors as they occur.
And at layer two, CRC are used
to detect transmission errors
on the link itself
and that is a link local check.
And then finally, checksums are
often present at the end layer,
at layer four, and that is the well known
TCP checksum for example.
You can actually take
the approach even further
and apply the end-to-end principle
of applying incremental redundancy
for end-to-end checks
in communication or in storage.
For example, the data integrity field
or DIF part of the SCSI standard
is a way to ensure the end-to-end integrity
of sectors written on disk.
Now coding applies best
to well defined structures
such as cache lines, disk sectors,
and network packets.
Obviously its main virtue
is that it is very efficient
because it is incremental, the overheads
are measured in percentages
of the underlying resource.
Now when that does not work,
replication is the
big hammer of redundancy.
And that is either where
we double or triple the resources
required to ensure availability
or durability of information.
So RAID1 is a classic example.
Rather than having the content on
a single disk you mirror it on two disks.
Works great, works fast.
So if performance is more
important than capacity,
use the big hammer of redundancy
which is simply replication
and, in this case, RAID1 mirroring.
Now replication is also commonly used
for scale out data storage access systems
such as Amazon S3 or Hadoop.
And this time by replicating the data
not twice but three times,
now why three times and not two?
Well there are a few good reasons
that have to do with ensuring
both the durability and the
availability of data
in the presence of disk failures,
server failures
and even possibly rack failures.
And in particular considering
the repair time
that could grow very large given
the size of disks and the bandwidth
available across networks these days.
Okay, so we've talked about redundancy
and the main message
is that redundancy is a good thing.
And then we talked a little bit
about two ways
in which we can achieve redundancy.
Coding, which is a form of
incremental redundancy
and then replication, the big hammer
of redundancy when it applies to data.
Next we'll talk about how we can apply
the same concept to systems.