So now that we've talked about redundancy,
let's talk about one of
the most important applications
of the redundancy principle,
and that is the ability to create
fault-tolerant systems.
And first, let's get
one thing off the table.
The alternative to fault tolerance,
which would be
the ability to avoid faults,
is simply a symptom of denial.
It might be one thing
to reason about your own code,
and to convince yourself
that there are no bugs,
and with the appropriate level
of verification and checks,
convince yourself
that this is actually running
free of any particular bug,
but this code depends on other code.
That code actually runs
on top of an operating system.
The operating system runs
on top of hardware,
which consists of multiple
independent components,
which may all fail.
And then the system itself
depends on environmental assumptions--
that there is enough power, for example,
or that you have an Internet connection,
in order to properly behave.
So it's impossible to think about
any computer systems
without thinking about the possible faults
that the system may encounter.
And in order to reason about this
it's first important
to get a couple definitions off the table.
And these two definitions
are important to use consistently.
They're the definitions of faults,
and the definition of failure.
So fault is an underlying defect.
Now, because denial is not a strategy,
we have to assume that we have
potential faults, everywhere.
The most obvious types of faults
include bugs in our own code,
bugs in somebody else's code,
hardware components that go bad,
memory that gets corrupted,
mechanical parts that fail,
power supplies that fail.
When you look at this globally,
there are other critically
important types of faults--
a design fault, for example,
or a sizing limitation.
An operational fault,
a canonical user error
is also a fault, for the purpose
of this conversation.
Information-critical application,
the scope of faults,
extends well beyond the IT space,
into considerations such as
the failure of the power grids.
Okay, so that's for the fault itself,
now the fault does not mean
the failure of the system.
First, some faults
may actually be latent--
in that they have no visible side effects,
and other faults may be active.
But beyond that, the ability
to contain the impact of faults
is the whole point of this conversation.
So let's define a failure as when
a module's not producing
the desired result.
A failure occurs only when
an underlying fault
is neither detected
nor masked by the module.
And this leads up to the concept
of fault tolerance
and fault-tolerance design.
Fault tolerance is the systematic approach
that allows us to build reliable systems
out of unreliable components.
This goal is achieved by applying
two fundamental principles:
redundancy, and modularity.
Now here we apply the modularity
principle in a precise way,
so that errors can be handled internally,
within a module,
and without propagating
to any other part of the system.
So at its core,
the fault-tolerance process
is pretty much always about
applying a three-step process,
within each module.
In the first step, you need to provide
a mechanism to detect errors and faults.
How we detect errors
is a function of the module itself,
but in general this assumes
some redundancy within the module.
If there is some memory module,
for example,
redundancy or coding can detect errors.
If this is a hardware component,
the component must have
enough instrumentation capabilities
to determine whether
it is operating correctly, or not.
In the second step,
you have to design the system
to ensure that any error
is contained within the module.
Again, ideally the modularity
principle applies
not only during the normal
operation of the module,
but also during error conditions.
Take for example, the example of a library
that has a corrupted data structure.
Ideally, the effects of that corruption
would be contained to that library.
Client server designs,
that rely on isolated processes
ensure this guarantee,
but single-address based designs do not.
So discretionary modularity,
which is what a library provides
in its relationship with applications,
is not sufficient
to fault-containment purposes.
Instead, we need to have a way
to enforce the modularity
at the boundaries of each module,
during normal and abnormal operation.
And third, and critically,
the fault-tolerance design process
is about having a remedy to errors,
so that the overall system
can continue to operate
after the error itself,
and this is done by masking
the error and correcting it.
And here again we rely on redundancy
to ensure that we can mask the problem.
So redundancy applies not only to data,
it actually applies to all aspects
of computer systems.
The incarnation takes a different form.
At a system level,
in particular in digital design,
you can apply redundancy to logic,
and what is known as
the N-WAY modular redundancy system.
And in this picture, again, you have
the three-way modular redundant circuit.
Each circuit is totally independent,
but its output feeds into a gate,
and the gates themselves
feed into a voter,
which is also known as the majority gate.
And in an NMR system,
the majority rules.
So if this if this a boolean circuit,
there's always a majority,
since each gate can
only have one of two states.
Now with a bit of luck,
the vote is unanimous,
but there could be
a distending opinion,
which is the minority report.
By definition, this indicates
a fault of the component.
That fault must be signaled
to an outside entity,
for example to signal a repair.
And in those systems,
as the majority rules,
the fault is presumed to be
in the minority gate,
and it's masked for further operation
until the failed component
can be replaced.
Now the approach applies
not only to digital design,
but also to commercial systems.
For example, the same algorithm
of N-WAY modular redundancy
could be performed by
N totally independent modules
on different machines who run N software
which then vote on the winning result.
This is used in avionics, for example,
where by design, different
approaches and algorithms are used
to ensure the overall
resiliency of the process.
Now if the implementation
of the modules is different,
i.e., the software running
on them is different,
this approach is called N-WAY programming.
And this makes sense
for safety-critical applications,
for example to fly airplanes,
but these examples are rare
and few and far between.
And instead the field of computer systems
has developed some systematic approaches
that can build fault-tolerance
into systems
without going through
the extremes of implementing
N-WAY module redundancy
or N-WAY programming.
And the general principle is always
around finding a way to respond
to active fault within
the systems, to contain them,
and then to repair the system itself.
So let's first talk
about error containment.
It is a key benefit
of the enforced modularity principle.
In a system, for example a layered system
as shown on screen right now,
the enforced modularity
of each of the layers
ensures the fault can be contained.
Let me rephrase that sentence.
Containment is possible
because of enforced modularity,
but although necessary,
this is not a sufficient condition.
As a matter of fact,
we have different design options,
and let's think a little bit about
what the various design options
in our system might be
in the presence of a fault.
Well first, if there's enough
redundancy in the system,
within the layer you can
repair it transparently,
mask the error, and keep operation.
That's how ECC operates,
for example,
when it automatically
repairs its own faults.
Now if that's not possible,
another solution is to explicitly
report the error to the layer above.
This is called fail-fast,
and this is a case of the
end-to-end principle being applied.
Assume that the layer above
will know best how to recover
from the failure of the underlying module.
Well alternatively, you can operate
in fail-safe mode,
that is ensure that the module
will keep operating,
and produce acceptable values.
By acceptable, we mean
values that are consistent
with the theory of operation
of the module itself.
Now fail-stop might seem pretty harsh,
but it's actually a pretty good choice.
By fail-stop we just
stop operating the module
as soon as we detect a fault.
Kernel panic is an example
of fail-stop operation
if some invariant
in the operating system fails.
Also you can operate
with degraded specification,
also known as fail-soft.
And in some situations the fault has
a performance implication
without impacting the function,
and thus is the case of fail-soft.
RAID is actually
an example of fail-soft,
and particularly when
the fault is permanent,
that is you've lost a sector
on a permanent basis,
or a disk on a permanent basis.
Until a replacement disk
has been brought up online,
and the RAID-5 parity
has been fully reconstructed,
the layer is operating
with degraded specification,
and possibly with degraded performance.
That's because
the RAID control in practice
is competing for bandwidth
with the application.
And so in a fail-soft mode
you're operating
with degraded specification
while the error is present.
And then of course there's everyone's
design favorite: do nothing,
let the upper layer deal with
a completely arbitrary specification
that has not been determined.
Now this classification
may seem a little abstract,
but it all boils down
to how you respond to faults.
And so let's walk through an example,
and see what that means.
So specifically let's look
at what that means
when there's an active fault
in the system.
Now this flowchart,
which comes from the textbook,
discusses the process to classify
faults into two categories--
the ones that you can tolerate,
and the ones that you cannot.
Now the bad news here seems to be
that most paths lead
to the untolerated error and state.
In reality, they're actually
at different end states, as we will see.
This flowchart is a useful guide.
So let's actually walk through
our concrete examples
with memory errors.
In this diagram there are only
two layers that are shown,
the memory subsystem and the operating
system controlling applications
as the second layer,
and you'll see why in a second.
Now by now, hopefully,
you know about ECC's.
Let's first study single-bit errors.
As we all know these faults
are both detected and masked
within the DIMM itself,
and therefore these are tolerated errors,
as far as this flowchart is concerned.
But let's now study double-bit errors.
They can be detected,
but they cannot be masked.
So the flowchart goes
from the detected error
to the unmaskable error state.
So that's the bad news.
Now the good news is that
modern computer systems
have a fail-fast mechanism,
and that fail-fast mechanism is called
a Machine Check Exception, or an MCE.
Think of an MCE as a signal raised
by the DIMM that interrupts the CPU.
As a matter of fact,
that is pretty much what it does.
And this brings up
the second layer of this system,
which is the operating system itself.
Now because of MCE
the OS has a way to detect faults.
These are memory faults,
where the memory has gone bad
because of a double-bit error.
Now the first thing that the OS does
is to determine who uses
that particular faulty page in memory.
If the page is unused,
either because it's free
or because it's part
of the file-system buffer cache,
then it's actually sufficient
for the operating system
to mark it as invalid,
never reuse it again,
and keep operation.
But if the page is used
by one application,
then the appropriate
behavior is actually
to propagate the fault-tolerance
design one level up,
and kill the application.
And this provides the application
fail-stop semantics
in the case of double-bit errors.
If the page is used
by the operating system itself
then obviously it's harder to resolve,
and typically the operating system
will actually issue a kernel panic,
and trigger a fail-stop operation
for the entire computer system itself.
Now so far we've talked about trying
to reduce the impact of failures,
but this is actually
not an acceptable situation
for many applications that require
a higher degree of availability.
And for that people have developed
and engineering discipline
that eliminates systematically
all possible single points of failure,
either in hardware or in software
in the system.
And we're actually going to study
one very classic example of such systems
that has systematically eliminated
all single points of failures,
and that is the Tandem NonStop
operating system and hardware platform
that was developed during the 1980's.
Now the computer scientists
at Tandem get credit
for having written the most
seminal papers in this field,
and I've found this
technical report on the web
that dates back to 1986,
and actually very succinctly describes,
on a single page,
the design principles
of fault-tolerant systems.
And you'll notice that the second author
for this technical report is Jim Gray,
and Jim Gray has arguably been
one of the most influential persons
in the combined field of computer
systems and databases.
And this paper lists the key
design principles on a single page.
Now we've talked about modularity
many times already,
the first design principle.
We've talked about fail-fast
as a design option.
Now in this context this is defined
through the combination of self-checking,
in other words redundancy,
and fail-stop operations.
The paper then defines
single-fault tolerance, as follows:
"When a hardware or software faults,
its function is immediately taken over
by another module--
given a mean time to repair
measured in milliseconds.
For processors or processes this means
a second processor or process exists.
For storage, it means the storage
and paths to the storage are duplexed."
In other words, there are
no single points of failure.
A definition does not
get better than this.
It then discusses the need
for online maintenance.
And this is actually part and parcel
of the single-fault tolerance model,
because after failure it is okay
to operate in a degraded state for awhile,
but you actually need to be able
to go back to the fully protected state
without requiring a service interruption,
therefore the need
to do online maintenance
and perform online maintenance
and repair of a running system.
And then it actually talks about the need,
even going back to the 1980's,
for having a simple user interface
that guides these operations,
make it accessible to people
who are responsible,
in particular for the repair
of these operations.
So think about it--this is a technical
report from nearly 30 years ago
that describes the principles
of fault-tolerant systems.
So let's actually see what that means,
and how those systems were built.
Well, first it means redundant hardware
with no single point of failure.
This means redundant CPU's,
redundant storage,
redundant connections
between the CPU and storage,
and some redundant connection
between the two CPU's
so that they can know about
each other's health.
But this is actually not sufficient
to achieve low recur time,
in the presence of failures.
For that you actually
need to create a process pair,
and in this model each process
has a backup process,
on the other processor,
and the pair stays in sync
through a special API
that they need to follow.
And that API ensures that the state
is appropriately synchronized at all times
between these two processes.
So first the system calls
themselves are mirrored,
but the application level state
is also mirrored as well through this API.
So that if the primary fails,
the secondary processor,
or the operating system,
can detect the failure,
and it immediately signals the process
to take over without losing transactions,
and without having to repair
the state of the transaction system
from stable storage of the database,
and that is because the two processes
and their address space
are kept logically in sync.
Now think about this for a minute
from a layering and
a fault-tolerance perspective.
Of course the hardware layers
are self-checking, fail-fast,
and redundantly deployed,
but the process pair itself
is also a distinct layer
that is also self-checking,
and can repair its own errors.
So I actually find this pretty neat.
With the mean time to repair
measured in milliseconds
for errors that could be masked,
and an actual mean time
between total system failures
that was measured in years, at the time.
And this is extremely impressive
given that the individual components
used to fail much more frequently.
So let's just summarize this module.
We saw redundancy and enforced modularity
as the two foundations for
the fault-tolerant design process.
We saw that there is
a systematic design process
that helps you reason about errors,
classify errors,
and associate a particular
failure semantic
to any particular module in the system.
Then we saw a glimpse about how
to achieve fault tolerance in hardware,
and the need to have redundant paths
and duplicated resources,
and we also saw a way of achieving
the same goal in software
through process pairs
that depend on a special API.