Still talking about redundancy
and fault tolerance,
but this time moving away from the
principle discussion to that of metrics.
It's important to first have a
good handle on the principles
so that you have a mental map
of the concepts that are in play,
but then you need to have an equally
strong handle on the metrics
in order to quantitatively
evaluate the system at hand.
And in the case of redundancy
and fault tolerance,
the principle metric that we talk about
is availability.
Now since fault tolerance is about
building reliable systems
from unreliable components,
we need to have those
metrics of unreliability.
And those metrics
apply at all layers,
the components or the faults
may be frequent and the availability poor,
and the fault tolerance systems
themselves
which hopefully show better metric.
Now this is important first a metric
is availability itself.
The second key concept is that
of availabilities complement,
and that is called the downtime.
Now the downtime is the ratio between
two other metrics of a system.
The denominator is the mean time
in between failures
and for the purpose of the fault time
and design methodology,
you first want to improve the mean time
between failures.
For example,
redundant power supplies
allow you to take the MTBF
of the power supply module
from being a significant source
of faults in a computer system,
to a completely insignificant
source of faults in a computer system.
But improving the MTBF alone
is not sufficient to ensure availability.
Rather, one must also
consider the time it takes
to recover from an unrecoverable fault.
And that is where the
mean time to repair or MTTR
comes in as the nominator
in this equation.
Now the MTTR varies widely
and is generally not only
a function of technology.
If your cellphone goes under a truck,
the MTTR is the time it takes you
to go to Swisscom or Orange at the
store and get another cellphone.
Now if your cellphone unfortunately
goes under a truck on a Saturday night,
your MTTR is 36 hours, since the stores
are closed on Sundays in Switzerland.
Now if your SIM card somehow
survives the catastrophe,
and you have an older phone at home,
then your MTTR might be shorter.
And here in this case,
by now the old phone
plays the role of the spare,
and as we'll see in systems
a notion of having a spare
and even a hot spare is critical
to reducing the MTTR.
Now of course when you're talking about
metrics of availability,
you have to talk about the nines.
3 nines, 4 nines,
5 nines, 6 nines,
I'm sure you've heard about the nines.
So let's first define what this means
and later what this implies.
Take 5 nines, often desired as the
target operation level
for critical services.
Now what 5 nines of availability means,
it means that on average,
you can allow for either
five minutes of downtime a year
or one hour of downtime per decade.
Well, that's not a lot of room when you
put all the assumptions on the table,
and of course all assumptions
must be put on the table,
dealing with the failures in
hardware and software,
but also failures in the environment,
even things such as software upgrades
that are expected
during the lifetime of the product.
So as a matter of fact,
for server applications,
5 nines of availability generally
requires that you have a solution
that straddles multiple,
physical data centers
separated by substantial distance.
On top of that, you need to monitor
the per of those systems
through strict procedures
and human processes.
And the traditional assumption,
was that such a solution
had to to be built exclusively
out of enterprise grade components,
although this assumption
is being revisited
with the advent of cloud based
application paradigms.
It's also important to think about
the time dimension here.
A decade is a reasonable length of time
to bound the useful life
of a mission critical application.
And so it makes sense to think about
the overall downtime budget
at the timescale of a decade,
and many, many, many things will occur
to the service during
that time period,
including many component failures
and many software upgrades, like...
Now let's expand on the
metric just a bit.
We've already introduced a
notion of the MTTR,
that is the mean time to repair.
Now this is something that is also known
as the recovery time objective,
when applied to data protection.
Now depending on the type of
fault in the type of module,
the MTTR can actually be quite long.
Now the MTBF is actually the
sum of the time to repair
and the time between failures.
So in other words, the time to repair
actually shows up both in the nominator
and the denominator
of the downtime equation.
I can't stress enough how
important this ends up being,
having an impact on
systems design in the end.
Unfortunately, it's often overlooked.
Now the MTBF itself is a funny metric.
First, it's the mean of the
median of a distribution
that is nearly always non-uniform,
and that is when you're lucky,
and sometimes correlated with other
failures when you're an unlucky person.
Now the best example for this are
hard disk drives.
High quality disk drives are sometime
quoted with MTTF of 200 years.
Wow, that's impressive, none of us
would live long enough to deal with that.
Now although this sounds impressive,
it's a lot less impressive
when you have 10,000 disk drives
in your data centers
and one fails, on average,
every week.
Now in addition to the failure rates
of many components,
disk drives, flash drives,
power supplies, batteries,
are subject to what is known as
the bathtub curve.
Now there are three critical portions
in the bathtub curve.
First, on the length, there's a period
in time that has a significant amount
of what is called infant mortality,
and that is the early phase of the
system being in operation.
It is often indicated by having a
higher than usual failure rate.
After that, there is a somewhat
constant failure rate
during the normal life of the component.
And at the other end of the bathtub,
there is often the observation
of having an increased failure rate
towards the end of the useful life
of the component, and by useful life,
this is something that is
measured in years,
rarely in decades and
absolutely never in centuries,
even for systems that have an
MTBF quoted as being 200 years.
And to build available systems,
you have to take into account
the fact that at some point,
the system will fail.
Well how important is the bathtub curve
in practice in systems design?
Well the answer is it's fundamental
and I want to share with you
a real world data point from a
company called Backblaze
that offers backup as a
service to consumers.
Now the data comes from 2012,
but I doubt it's changed since.
And they had, at the time, a pretty large
installation with roughly 40PB
of capacity under management,
and that translates to
about 20,000 drives which are all
packed in these custom built,
red storage boxes you see on the picture.
And you can put about
45 such drives per box.
Now the system is obviously
designed to handle faults,
as matter of fact, durability of the data
is fundamental
since this is a backup service,
and to ensure that,
they're leveraging the coding algorithms
of RAID 6 to deal with failures.
And specifically it's organized as
RAID 6 sets of 15 drives each
so that you can lose two drives out of 15
and still have the ability
to recover data.
So I want to talk about two examples
from this data point.
First is the MTTR and then
the bathtub curve itself.
Now this may come out as a shock,
but the MTTR,
which is measured as the
time it takes to recreate
the redundancy of RAID 6,
so full protection,
is about three days.
Now during that time,
the service is available,
the data is available, but the durability
is no longer as guaranteed.
It's not three seconds,
it's not three hours,
but three days.
Why? Well RAID 6 does coding
over the entire disk set.
So 15 x 3 TB, which is 45 TB of I/Os
required to recreate the redundancy.
And when you do the math,
three days works out to about 200 MB
of sustained sequential I/O per second.
Now onto the bathtub curve.
Not only do the engineers at Backblaze
notice the bathtub curve,
but they spontaneously use the term
when discussing failure rates,
even though I'm not sure whether
they read about it
during they're academic training.
Now the good news in their case,
is that infant mortality is short.
It's just a few days.
And after a few days of
sustained I/O burn-in tasks,
you can effectively eliminate
all of the disk drives
out the of system that are
a subject to infant mortality.
Well then comes the bad news.
The bad news is that
the best drives fail
at 2% per anumm.
So forget that 200 year MTTF.
A 50 year MTTF is what
you can actually expect
in practice for sustained operation.
The worst is about 7% by the way,
so there's a big difference
between manufacturers.
With that failure rate,
the operational team must replace
about two drives a day,
and since the MTTR is about three days,
that's why you understand why
RAID 6 is necessary
and RAID 5 would not be adequate.
And then the last data point to
the bathtub curve
is that the company started in 2008,
so it got to be about four years old,
and they start to see an increase in the
failure rate of the older drives
which are nearing the end
of their useful life.
So even though you may have an
MTTF measured in decades,
four years might be all that you can
actually expect out of the useful life
of the components such as a
mechanical drive
that is being used on a sustained basis.
So here you have it.
Our real world data point
on the bathtub curve,
and the moral of the story
is to make sure
that you regularly backup your own data.
Time to wrap up this
quick module on metrics,
and to be fair,
we didn't really go in-depth
at all, into metrics.
I only brought them up in the context
of redundancy and fault tolerance
so that you have a basic sense
of what they mean
while evaluating the principles.
Now what did we cover?
Well metrics are important,
the mean is even--
is both the central data point
that you use to compare, quantitatively,
components, as well as
the most meaningless metric
when you're actually studying
the components in detail.
And then the last point to keep in mind,
is the importance of repair
in availability and in
fault tolerance systems.