Welcome back!
In this module, we'll talk
about a class of systems
that apply redundancy in order to achieve
"good enough" levels of availability,
without necessarily being viewed
as fault tolerant.
So, if you remember our discussion
of tandem in the nonstop operating system
and the use of process pairs,
we saw a systematic discipline,
in which we applied redundancy
both in hardware
and between applications
in order to create a fault tolerant system
Now that level of availability is required
for a certain class of application,
but it's not necessarily necessary
for all possible class of applications.
As a matter of fact, you can actually
create a spectrum
and define the operating point
of various systems based on their use.
And this is sort of an illustrated view
of that spectrum
from the lowest levels
of required availability
to the highest possible levels
of fault tolerance.
And the tandem example
actually falls most closely
into the category that today
we would call carrier-grade,
or at least that the networking industry
would call carrier-grade today.
And that is a term that describes systems
that have no single point of failure
and upgrade themselves
without service interruption
and can recover from failures quickly,
including software failures.
Now the tandem servers
were often used
to create fault tolerant transaction
processing systems
and used process pairs.
And today's carrier-grade routers
have very similar design patterns
to ensure that they never fail
and they never lose a networking state
in the case of component failures.
But there are actually
very different design points.
Now, first there are systems
that are not just fault tolerant,
but additionally what we call
dependable.
And these are the systems
that our lives depend on.
Not our digital lives,
but our actual lives.
And that actually suit
different sets of assumptions,
unlike the Telecon model,
which must live on forever,
dependable systems often have a built-in
concept of a maintenance window,
rather than the concept
of in-server serviceability.
So, for example, after the airplane lands,
you have a convenient time
in which you can upgrade systems.
You don't have to worry about doing
a software upgrade
while the airplane is actually flying.
However, obviously none
of the control systems on the airplane
should ever fail, under normal
circumstance during the flight,
and the process pair methodology
or the end way
modular programming
is often necessary in order to capture
all the possible failure models
of that particular system.
Now at the other extreme
of the spectrum
is what we would call
a customer-grade design.
There the availability is often determined
and dominated by external factors.
Take a cellphone, for example,
I used before.
The operational assumption is that it
will be subject to temperature variations,
humidity, bacteria,
downloads of dubious applications,
frequent synchronization over USB ports,
a high probability of theft or loss,
and the possibility that it gets run over
by a truck.
And you think about it,
cellphone designs have worked out
many of these assumptions
into their model,
but when it comes to faults and repair,
the customer-grade design point
makes absolutely no amends.
It should work, and if it does not,
just get another one.
Now, of course this is not acceptable
for enterprise-grade designs,
products that are sold to companies.
And here, the computer hardware
is designed around the notion
of components that are, whenever possible,
field replaceable units.
Now this means that the customer
can directly exchange
a faulty hardware component
such as a disc drive, a fan,
or a power supply.
And this approach dramatically reduces
the mean time
to repair of the computer system,
and therefore improves the availability.
Now, generally these field-replaceable
units are deployed themselves
in a redundant fashion.
Disc drives already together,
fans and power supplies
have enough spare capacity to deal
with the failure
of at least one of their components.
And again, this improves
the MTTF of the system.
Now this module focuses
on the main design principles
to ensure enterprise-grade availability.
And particularly with a focus
on the software layer
that can be deployed on the hardware
of enterprise-grade servers.
Now, to put this further into perspective,
let's compare the MTTR
of different design points.
In previous modules, we actually looked
at two extremes of the spectrum
end way module redundancy,
as used in digital design
can repair itself extremely fast.
Sometimes nanosecond fast.
At the other extreme of the spectrum,
we saw that RAID 6 can take multiple days
when using SATA drives.
And then in discussing tandem,
we saw that process pairs
can recover from software failures
and hardware failures in milliseconds.
Now, the high availability design point,
which is the focus of this module
is another systematic way
to achieve fault tolerance.
It has a much higher MTTR
than fault tolerance.
Often measured in minutes,
sometimes hours,
but it can actually be deployed
in a very simple,
and much simpler matter,
than the full fault-tolerance discipline,
which makes it interesting.
Now, the basic idea is pretty simple.
To create a high-availability cluster,
you need two independent systems
with a logically-shared storage subsystem.
Now, between the two servers,
you have a heartbeat mechanism,
and the heartbeat mechanism is used
to detect whether the other server
is up or down and to communicate.
And the logically-shared disc
is where the shared state that is used
by the application is actually stored.
So, so far this is actually
nearly identical
from the fault tolerance
transaction processing system,
the way the tandem engineers
designed it.
The difference is in a sweeping
simplification of the design,
which is to separate all durable state,
which is presumed to be consistently
written on disc,
from the transient state
of the application.
So, the durable state is on disc,
and the transient state is only
within the application
very specifically only within
the active application of the pair.
So, whereas the fault tolerant design
aims to keep a transient state
of the two processes
in correspondence at all time,
the high-availability design only monitors
the pair for help.
And when a fault is detected,
whether hardware fault
or software fault,
the hot spare takes over and reinitializes
the transaction system,
or the application,
from the durable state,
that is, from disc.
So, in practice that means
that the hot spare must recover
the state stored on disc
as if the system simply had crashed
and was rebooting on the same machine.
In this case, the MTTR is dominated
by the application recovery time.
For example, in the case
of a database management system,
this is the time to apply
the redo log and the undo log
onto the database file.
Now, in the previous example, we used
two servers and two software stocks
to create a high-availability cluster.
Now it turns out that the same methodology
can also be applied to a single stack
without having to configure
a separate operating system image,
an application image,
as the backup.
And this is possible
when you use virtual machines
to create the cluster.
Now, in this model, a pool of servers
are running virtual machines.
And when one server fails,
all of its virtual machines
automatically restart elsewhere
on the cluster.
This clustering algorithm involves
the various hypervisor instances,
but each of the virtual machines
simply restarts on a different node
without knowing that anything changed.
Now, of course, this works
because the virtual machines
are stored on a shared storage device
and the state of the virtual machine
is fully-encapsulated and portable.
And again, as in the previous example,
we're making the simplifying assumption
that the disc subsystem itself
is always up.
And that it is a logically-shared,
accessible component.
In other words,
so far we've been concentrating
on server failures.
Now, of course, we know
that this can be a problem too.
That's actually not a limitation.
Simply because you can easily
combine clustering,
which guarantees
the availability of servers,
with replication of the storage
subsystem itself.
And here's actually an example
of how you would deploy financial
trading systems today in real life.
This is actually a very hard
and constrained problem
since the system must ensure
high availability,
must be resilient to any possible
component failure, software failure,
and, in addition, must deal with the case
where the entire system fails,
including the case
where the entire building fails.
And, of course, this issue became a front
and center problem
on September 11th in 2001.
And since then the financial industry
has more or less figured out
a standard way to answer this problem,
in part through regulation.
It's no longer sufficient to keep
the database in one storage array,
but instead you need to have two
identical copies
that must be, at all times, kept in sync
on two different storage arrays.
And this is called the synchronous
storage replication model
between two storage arrays.
It's actually a very stringent requirement
since it requires the copy
of each disc write
must be written to both locations
before the disc write is returned
to the server with a successful
completion message.
In that model, by the way,
the primary and the backup servers
are also in the two locations,
so the high-availability cluster
actually stretches the two buildings
in the same way that the storage cluster
stretches two buildings.
And while I go into details,
distance matters a great deal here.
It's not--
It has to be sufficiently distant
that a major disaster will not affect
both locations.
It has to also be sufficiently close
to each other
not to impact the latency
of disc transactions.
And then there's a bigger issue
associated with partitioning,
which is why these deployments
are usually done
on dedicated fiber-optic connections
that are redundantly deployed
between the two data centers.
And in this picture, by the way,
which I found on some
commercial presentation,
even shows a third copy of the data.
This time only with asynchronous
replication requirement.
This is typically used for analytics
as well as archiving purposes.
Let's actually go back
to our MTTR spectrum.
We've just spent this module so far
covering the high-availability
point of the spectrum.
And if you recall the sweeping
simplification,
of the basis of high-availability
clustering
is the separation between durable
and transient state.
This principle is that the system
can recover from durable state alone
and therefore, let's not keep
any additional state
to make recovery faster.
Now, unfortunately this has
a very significant implication
on the MTTR.
There's actually another point
in the timeline spectrum,
which is called
Recovery-Oriented Computing.
And the ground-breaking research
result in Recovery-Oriented Computing
are due to our own George Candea,
and you'll actually read about this
in the paper this week.
So, the key observation behind
Recovery-Oriented Computing
is that MTTF is due to many things,
hardware, software, environment,
of which we can actually address many
by simply throwing money at the problem.
But software reliability remains a problem
in particular it impacts the recovery time
especially if you use the classic
high-availability cluster methodology
with its sweeping simplification.
So, Recovery-Oriented Computing
and the use of micro-reboots
addresses this very specific topic
and I hope you enjoy
the paper this week.
So, it's time to summarize.
In this short module,
we've covered the concept of building
a high-availability cluster
for solutions that need
to be "good enough"
for enterprise grade level availability.
And that can be done with the hot spare,
and a sweeping simplification
to only focus on durable state.
There's another sweeping
simplification in this design,
which I hope you appreciate,
is that we have access to a shared
logical disc between multiple points
and that disc actually serves
as the arbiter
for the ownership of the disc,
and to determine which
the primary application actually is.
We covered how different ways in which
we can apply the cluster methodology,
either by having two software stacks
on two physical servers,
or one software stack
and a virtual machine
running on a cluster of hypervisors.
And then lastly, we've put this
all in perspective
on the MTTR time spectrum,
introducing the concept
of Recovery-Oriented Computing,
which lands between fault tolerance
and high-availability clusters.