We've already seen the idea of using
voting as a way to deal with failure.
And voting is really
a fundamental concept.
We see it everywhere; its the foundation
of democratic societies.
It embodies the belief that
multiple opinions are better that one.
And when a majority of potentially
faulty people agree on something,
then they're probably right.
So we use this a a building block
to develop much more sophisticated forms
of dealing with failures,
especially in distributed systems,
which are systems that consist
of nodes that can only communicate
by exchanging messages.
So what are some
examples of such systems?
Well one of the simplest situations
is agreeing on time.
Protocols like NTP
are used by computers connected
by package switch variable
latency networks
to agree on what the current time is.
It's one of the oldest
internet protocols,
precisely because agreeing on time
is such a fundamental need
in a distribute environment.
Another example, involves the delivery
of messages to nodes
in a distribute system.
And often, it is important that all nodes
process these messages in the same order.
And the nodes must collectively
agree on that order.
Sometimes we want to take a checkpoint
or snapshot of the state
of a distributed system
while it keeps running.
So we need to collect a set
of node level checkpoints
that are consistent with each other.
And this requires some way of voting
or reaching consensus
on which those checkpoints should be.
But consider, for instance,
a distributed database
where the different participants
need to agree unequivocally
on whether a transaction
can commit or must abort.
Its obviously crucial
that all involved nodes,
agree on the outcome of the transaction.
And for a final example,
there are process controlled systems
in automated assembly plans
were some action needs to be taken
when a component fails.
But what they should hear is that all
parties involved need to agree
on the nature of that failure.
So if you think of the much simpler case
of a cluster based web service,
one of these nodes might fail,
but then some other nodes need to agree
that the node is failed
and should be removed from the cluster.
If they don't agree, the web server
can become terribly inconsistent.
Let's look at how an air
traffic control system might work.
It's basically a bunch of ground base
controllers with each controller
being in charge of some
portion the air space.
And these controllers are responsible
for directing the aircraft,
providing them adviser services,
preventing collisions,
organizing the flow of traffic
and so on and so forth.
And for all this to run smoothly,
the system has to maintain, first of all,
information on the position of the planes
and this state is, of course,
replicated for felpars.
The information obtained
from radar stations, has to obtained
and distributed
to all nodes in the system
to the place, to the controllers, etc.
And then the operators, are in charge,
of managing, controlling
and administering
the air traffic control system.
And all these entities need
to agree on what needs to happen next.
And they need to be able to agree
even when parts of the system fail.
And they need to agree
in a timely fashion.
And this is what we call
the consensus problem.
Now in order to come up with
principal solutions to this problem,
we often start by opening
on an abstraction
of the real distributed system.
And this is often represented as a graph,
in which the vertices correspond to nodes
and the edges represent,
communication lengths.
Now the agreement problem says,
we need all these nodes
to pick the same value "V".
Now in the case of our 'ATC' system:
the air traffic control system,
we have controllers talking
to pretty much everyone.
The databases also talk to each other.
The radar stations also talk to planes,
and planes even talk to each other.
In fact, airplanes beyond a certain size,
are equipped with special transponders
for collision avoidance,
which is known as TCAS.
When planes come too close to each other,
these transponders talk to each other
and notify the pilots
of a potential collision.
And the automated TCAS systems,
actually negotiates among the planes
and quickly decides which plane
should take which maneuver.
And then the plane changes altitude
or it can modify their climb
or sync rates, to avoid this collision.
And of course, goes without saying,
it is always preferable for the planes
involved to agree
on who does what maneuver,
less they all do the same thing
and therefore collide.
Now in such a setting, we say that,
for consensus to be achieved,
we must have four key properties.
Now the theory people
like to think of consensus
as starting with a proposed value,
and then the nodes through the process
of achieving consensus,
decide a value.
So the result of consensus is a decision.
Now in terms of properties,
of course there is agreement.
And what this means is that,
if a correct node decides value "V",
then every correct node in the system,
decides the same value "V".
In other words, if a correct node
believes that value "V"
was chosen by mutual agreement,
then it must be the case
that all the other correct
nodes believe the same.
And notice, we say nothing
about what the faulty nodes do.
So we only care here
about the correct nodes.
But agreement is not enough,
we also need termination,
which basically means that within
some finite amount of time,
every correct node decides some value.
A third property of consensus is validity.
Which says that, if it just so happens
that all correct nodes have consensus
from the very start, meaning they all
proposed the same value "V",
then it must be the case
that every correct node
decides that particular value
and not another.
And finally we have integrity.
This says that a correct node can
decide at most one's,
basically implying that,
once you've made a decision,
a correct node cannot change its mind.
And additionally, whatever value
a correct node decides,
must have been proposed by some node.
In other words, an agreed upon value
cannot be something
made up out of thin air.
It must be a value that was actually
proposed by one of the nodes.
You might look at this and think,
"Hey, integrity implies validity."
But actually, this isn't the case,
because integrity says the decided value
must have been proposed by some node.
So it could be a faulty node
that proposed the value.
Whereas, validity refers exclusively
to what happens with correct nodes.
Alright so, if an algorithm
provides these four properties,
then we say, it solves consensus.
Now you can see why all these four
properties are useful for the case
of our air traffic control system
that we were talking about earlier.
So let's see a simple way to accomplish
this with a consensus for the case
when everything works okay.
Nothing fails; neither nodes
nor communication lengths.
So say the nodes in the system
are labelled 'Ni'.
Each node can then choose
its favorite value 'Vi',
and broadcast this to everyone else.
Then it waits to hear all the values
proposed by the other nodes.
And after some time,
every node in the system,
will have received the values
chosen by everyone else.
So they have a common
set of values: V1 through Vn.
Now at this point, each node applies
a deterministic function,
to choose a value from the set.
For instance, everyone chooses
the min or the max or whatever.
When you have nodes with ID's
like with IP addresses,
you can also just pick the values
proposed by the node with the smallest
or with the largest IP address.
It really doesn't matter
what the function is
as long as every node
uses the same function,
and the function is deterministic.
Now given that all the nodes see
the same set of values
and apply the same
deterministic function,
this guarantees that they end
up choosing the same value.
Now does this solve consensus?
Well yeah.
And life's really easy
when there are no failures.
This algorithm achieves agreement;
it does so within a finite amount of time,
and it guarantees
both validity and integrity.
But what happens
when there are failures?
Well there are a couple
of ways to reason about this.
One model is what we call:
the synchronous model
of distributive systems.
Even-though failures can occur,
there's a really nice property
which is that:
nothing can take forever.
So first, any message can take at most
delta time, to reach its destination.
So it cannot dilly dally
forever in the network.
And in the Internet, we use TTL's:
the Time To Live field in my P pack;
it is to provide this property.
Second, a node cannot take forever
to do it's computation.
It must respond within
a maximum theta amount of time.
And of course, this model
accepts failures
of both the communication
lengths and the nodes.
And the lengths can both drop
and reorder messages as they wish.
And the nodes can either
exhibit crash failures,
Also known as stopping failures,
in which they halt
and never speak again.
Or they simply lie.
Which is what we call
a Byzantine failure.
So the synchronous model
is a pretty reasonable model
if you think about the real world.
Of course some of its assumptions
cannot always hold, you know like,
putting bounds on communication
and computation time.
Because we may, for instance, hit a bug
and get into some infinite loophole
of the nodes without wanting to.
And then they'll say
that computation takes forever.
But now then let's--
so this Byzantine failure model
is something actually I'd like us
to talk about in a bit more depth.
This type of failure
was introduced in a classic paper
by Pease, Shostak and Lamport.
And the actual term was coined
by Lamport a bit later.
Before this paper appeared,
it was generally assumed
that a three node system
can tolerate one faulty node.
And this paper shows
that Byzantine faults,
the so-called Byzantine faults
in which a faulty node sends
inconsistent information
to the other nodes,
can defeat any traditional
three node algorithm.
So Lamport actually says that he figured
that for a problem to be well known,
you know, like Dijkstra's
Dining Philosophers Problem,
it has got to have a story behind it.
So the story here is a group of generals
have to come to a common agreement
on whether to attack
an enemy army or retreat.
But they can communicate
only by sending messengers
who might be captured
or die on their way.
Furthermore some of the generals
may be traitors so they would try
to deceive the others.
Yet the challenge is to still
have the good generals
reach a common decision.
And it seems that the Byzantine empire
was full of treachery so Lamport
in the end, gave the generals
the Byzantine nationality.
And since then, we know failures that
manifest as lies, as Byzantine Failures.
Now a Byzantine Failure
is meant to model arbitrary behavior.
So it can therefore model pretty much
any type of misbehavior.
It includes both omission failures
such as crash failures
or failing to receive a request,
or completing ignoring or non-responding.
As well as commission failures
such as giving the wrong answer
or corrupting state
or being inconsistent.
So we can model with
Byzantine failures,
any form of bugs; any form
of non-determinism in execution
like race conditions that can
lead to data corruption.
Even deliberately malicious activity,
whether it might result, say from a node
being broken into by a hacker.
So one of the key results in that paper,
is an impossibility result.
It says that if you want
to solve consensus in a system
that has "F" faulty nodes,
then you must have at least
3f+1 nodes in total.
Otherwise it's impossible
to achieve consensus.
So clearly, if you have
a three node system,
this paper says you cannot
tolerate any of those nodes failing.
And Lamport's contribution to this
landmark paper, was to to show that
if digital signatures are used,
then 2f+1 nodes are enough
to tolerate "F" Byzantine failures.
Now in this context, digital
signatures as used here,
are sort of a metaphor
since the signatures needs to be secure
only against random failure;
not against intelligent adversaries.
They're easier to implement
than true digital signatures
like fancier crypto-base stuff.
Now subsequent work has shown
that another way of getting around
the 3f+1 limitation is to use
randomized protocols.
In which case, one can obtain
a probabilistic guarantee of agreement.
And in practice, this may
actually be good enough.
By the way, according to Lamport,
the people at Boeing came across his work
in 1986, and that as a result,
the people who built
the passenger planes at Boeing,
became aware of the problems
and started designing
their systems accordingly.
But in the late 80's and early 90's,
the people at Boeing working
on military aircraft and on the space
station as well as the people
at McDonnell Douglas, allegedly still
did not understand the problem
and why it's not possible to achieve
consensus unless you have
at least 3f+1 nodes.
So this impossibility result is really
crucial to anyone who builds systems
that are meant to tolerate
failures of this nature.
Now Paxos is a family of
algorithms or protocols;
we can call them either way,
for solving consensus.
The Paxos includes a spectrum
of trade offs between a number of nodes,
a number of message delays before
learning the agreed value,
the activity level of individual
participants as the number
of messages send, types
of a lot of different things.
That's why we have a family
of algorithms not a single one.
It's a relatively complex
family of algorithms,
so I'll not describe it here.
But it's an extremely
important one to know about.
For example, Goggle uses
the Paxos algorithm
in their Chubby Distributed
Lock Service in order to keep replicas
consistent in case of failure.
And Chubby is used by Big Table
which is in production
in Google Analytics and other products.
Google Spanner and Mega-store use
the Paxos algorithm internally as well.
Microsoft uses Paxos in the autopilot
cluster management service,
which is used at least at Bing,
if not in other places.
XTREEMFS also uses a Paxos based
least negotiable algorithm
for fault permanent and consistent
replication of file data and meta data.
And a bunch of other not including--
like Heroku uses Doozer which intern
implements Paxos for its consistent
distributive data store.
So not surprisingly, Lamport's paper
describing Paxos received
the ACMC-SIGOPS Hall
of Fame Award in 2012.
As a side note, Apache ZooKeeper,
which is a centralized service
for maintaining configuration
information, naming,
providing distribute synchronization,
providing group services.
So this service, the ZooKeeper
is sort of like Chubby
but it does not use standard Paxos.
And Yahoo research guys who built
ZooKeeper, devised a protocol called Zab,
which is a totally ordered
broadcast protocol
and it's very close to Paxos
in spirit, but not exactly it.
Can you remember, we talked about
the synchronous model in which
we always have upper bounds
on the time it takes a message to travel
and on the time it takes a node
to finish its computation.
There also exists what we call
the asynchronous model
of a distributed system
in which there are no bounds
on communication delays
and no bounds on processing speed.
Now the reason this model is interesting
is that it is fully general.
Basically, an open distributed system
that covers a wide geographic area
or one that has unpredictable work loads,
is in essence asynchronous.
Because we cannot predict what
the bounds, delta and theta ought to be.
So if we have an algorithm or protocol
that works in the asynchronous model,
then it will definitely work
in the real world.
But when it comes to consensus,
there's a fundamental impossibility result
proven by Fischer, Lynch and Paterson
in 1985 and this something
we definitely need to know about.
This result states that "It is impossible
to design a deterministic consensus
algorithm that works in an
asynchronous distributed system,
even if the only type
of failure you can get,
is a single Crash
failure of a node."
This is the simplest type of failure
in which the node just crashes
and stays crashed; it doesn't lie,
it doesn't do anything.
And so this result says, we cannot have
a consensus algorithm for that situation,
if the system is asynchronous.
And this result is super important
because it tells system designers
what the boundaries are of what
they can expect to accomplish
in a fully asynchronous setting.
Now the intuition behind the proof
is that, it is impossible to safely
distinguish between a Crash node,
a very slow node, and a node
with which communications
are just very slow.
So as you might expect, the consensus
property that ends up being violated
is typically termination.
Now researchers have found various sets
of minimal assumptions,
that were satisfied by an asynchronous
distributed system,
make the consensus problem solvable.
And some of these are things
like partial synchrony.
There also exists, randomized algorithms
that give us a probabilistic guarantee
of consensus; one can use,
for instance, failure detectors.
Then there are key agreement algorithms
were the nodes need not agree
on a single value but can
agree on a set of key values.
And this actually works as long as
"F", the number of faulty nodes
is less than "K".
And so on, there are a number
of ways to do this.
So now you may ask,
"Oh what about Paxos?"
Well, although no deterministic consensus
protocol can guarantee termination
in an asynchronous system,
Paxos can still guarantee
the safety properties namely:
agreement, validity and integrity.
And the conditions that could prevent
Paxos from terminating, turned out
to be somewhat hard to make
happen in a real system.
Hence the relative success
that Paxos has had in practice.
So to conclude, let's recap
what we've learned about consensus.
First, it's a way to get multiple nodes
in a distributed system to correctly
agree on the same value and to do so
in a bounded amount of time.
Second, for this to work, we need at least
3f+1 nodes in the system to participate
in this algorithm where "F" is the
number of potentially faulty nodes.
And finally, the FLP
impossibility result tells us
that in a fully asynchronous setting,
if you have even as little
as one crash failure, it is impossible
to achieve consensus
which means that one cannot design
an algorithm that guarantees consensus
in such a situation.