Welcome back.
By now you have an appreciation
on the importance and the ubiquity
of the redundancy principle
in computer system.
By now hopefully you also have
an appreciation
there are different ways in which
redundancy could be applied
in order to achieve different
levels of fault tolerance
or high availability.
Now in this module we're actually
going to look at two different systems
that both try to achieve
roughly speaking
the same degrees of availability
but have a very different
set of operating and design
principles and how to achieve that.
The first case study is
an extension of the enterprise grade
clustering design
presented in the prior module.
And the second case study is an in-depth
discussion on how Microsoft Azure
uses distributed systems
and commodity components
in order to achieve a highly available
storage and service stack.
So let's get started.
Let's first talk about our first
case study which is
the enterprise data base clustering model.
If you remember
there are two sweeping simplifications
that were made in this design.
The first one is the separation
between transient state and durable state.
Now I'm not going to revisit
this sweeping simplification again.
I'm actually going to go in depth
into the second sweeping simplification
which is that the two servers,
the active server and the backup server
both had access to a logically-shared disc
that can serve as an arbiter.
Now this is actually a very,
very important point.
The disc has to be logically shared.
So it has to be logically
accessible by both sides
and it also has to serve as an arbiter.
And the reason why having an arbiter
is fundamental is that the arbiter
is what guarantees that the system
will operate correctly at all times
and in particular will never suffer
from a split brain syndrome.
And the split brain syndrome would occur
if both the active and the passive server
were to concurrently conclude
that they were actually
the primary server and would
start to modify the database.
Corruption would immediately ensure
and that needs to be avoided.
Now in this case
there is a hardware mechanism
that is used as the foundation
of the clustering model
that guarantees the absence of split brain
and that mechanism is called
SCSI reservations.
So deep into the hardware
of the logically-shared disc,
we have an abstraction which is called
SCSI reservations,
in which basically the primary server
or every server that believes
to be the primary server
must with every disc transaction
guarantee the fact that it can prove
that it is the primary server
by passing a key.
And that key can change
and it's the change of the key
that actually ensures that
a takeover is explicit
and that two servers can never
concurrently access the same
storage device.
Now there's a lot of implementation
issues associated with creating
this abstraction of a logically-shared
arbiter, one of which
and a non-trivial one is that
the disc itself obviously
cannot be a single point of failure.
So if we actually drill into the next
level of detail,
the disc is never a traditional disc.
And you remember that
from our layering discussion.
As a matter of fact, the disc
is typically a very complex
computer system of it's own.
So think about the logically-shared disc
as being a rack-size computer system
with lots of rotating media inside it.
Now those systems themselves
are designed with a very high degree
of availability, durability, they're also
designed explicitly for servicability.
So they actually meet many of these
exact same design principles
that we saw in the context
of the tandem computer system design
but this time applied
to the storage subsystem.
Now let's double click on what we mean
and what is inside those systems.
So the first requirement is to ensure
that the logically-shared disc
could be made available at all times
including in the presence of
component failures
within the disc subsystem
or within the ways in which we connect
the servers to the disc subsystem.
If you remember our conversation
in the context of the tandem
nonstop system, there was
a key hardware design principle
which stated that all paths to storage
had to be fully duplexed.
Now that principle still holds
20 or 30 years later.
And what you see on screen
is the canonical design
on how you connect servers
to enterprise-grade storage subsystems.
You have a fully redundant fabric design
with redundant adapters
connecting the servers to the fabric,
redundant switches connecting the switches
to the storage arrays ensuring
that the storage subsystem
will be available and
reachable at all times
including in the presence
of path failures.
Now the second requirement
of course is to ensure
that the storage subsystem
itself never fails.
And here also the tandem design
principle is the primary guide
for the design of an enterprise-grade
storage subsystem.
Now the components of
the storage subsystem
are not particularly important here.
I'm not going to go through
them in detail.
What's important is to realize that
we applied those exact same principles
of redundancy and fault tolerance
within the inside of a storage subsystem.
For example, a storage subsystem
has redundant front-end controllers.
Those are both the recipients of
connectivity from the servers
but they actually need to work in pairs
in order to ensure
that the logically-shared arbiter
can actually be implemented.
And so the abstraction of that
logically-shared arbiter
is actually implemented
by having a collection of front-end
controllers coordinate their state
using a process-pair model
or something very similar
to the tandem process-pair model
for their own implementation.
At other aspects of the system,
storage subsystems also use
the fundamental redundancy principles
to ensure durability and availability.
The cache memory uses
error-correcting code.
That was one of the primary applications
of error-correcting codes
when they were introduced.
The backing storage controls are also
replicated and redundant.
The connectivity between the backing
controllers and the rotating discs
is also duplexed to ensure that
you can always reach a disc
at any particular point in time.
And then obviously we use raiding coding
and various forms of RAIDs
in order to ensure the data
will be durable including in the presence
of rotating media failure.
So there you have it.
All the details and the
implementation principles
of modern storage arrays
are actually very much inspired
by the original tandem
system of the 1980s.
So to summarize, to create
an enterprise-grade
high availability system you need
to have redundancy between components.
You need to have redundancy of data
through replication in coding
and you need to have redundancy
of the paths connecting
the components together.
And the key insight here is that
there's a magic number of two,
which means that by having two sets
of components at all levels
and duplex paths between the layers,
you can actually achieve
an enterprise-grade high availability
with no single point of failure.
And that is because some of these
abstractions even though
they're replicated in pairs of two
actually create arbiters
that appear as a hardware
abstraction to the layer above.
Now let's keep this number of two in mind
especially as we look at our second
case study which is from Calder et al.
This is based on an SOSP paper
describing the design
and implementation of the
Windows Azure Storage System.
Now one of the important aspects
of the paper is the consistency
semantics of Azure Storage.
We're not going to talk about that at all.
We're actually going to talk about
some of the high availability,
characteristics of this design.
So Azure Storage is premised around
the notion of a system.
A system is called a stamp.
A stamp is quite large.
It can actually be deployed on multiple
racks, ten to 20 racks.
It could hold 30 petabytes of data
but it is a single system
running a single software stack
and all the components are designed
to work with each other
in order to create an abstraction
delivered by this single system
at a large scale.
Now the components
that are within the rack
are all commodity based.
You have commodity-based
Ethernet switches,
commodity-based servers
and lots of obviously rotating media
within each server instance.
And we'll focus on how
Azure designed its system to ensure
the highest degree of availability.
So this is achieved through layering
and replication.
So layering is used first
as a design principle to provide
various abstractions, modularity
in how these abstractions are implemented
and the management
of different namespaces
at each layer within the stack.
Now the stamp again is the system
and the stamp ensures
the durability and
the availability of data.
And for this it actually uses replication
synchronously within the stamp.
So we're applying redundancy by using
three-way replication within the stamp
in a synchronous manner.
It also provides a greater degree
of availability and durability
through a geo-replication mechanism
which this time is
asynchronous across stamps.
So within the stamp,
you replicate synchronously
and across stamps you replicate
asynchronously.
And again we have to think of a stamp
as a single system
and in particular as from a fault and
availability perspective
as one domain that will ensure
the availability of the service
even in the presence
of component failures.
And so you have to assume
that there are other elements
within the stamp such as
power distribution units,
power supplies, air-conditioning units,
network switches.
All of which also have to be redundantly
deployed in order to ensure
the availability of the system as a whole.
One of the key observations is that
different stamps will ideally share
as few of these global infrastructure
components as possible.
And this simplifies
the monitoring of the stamp
and the availability of the data
that is replicated across stamps.
Now let's double-click
on the different aspects.
And first a stream layer
managers the data.
And specifically it exposed
the abstraction of a highly-available
stream to the partition
layer of the stamp.
Now each stamp has a logically-centralized
stream manager,
it's written SM in the figure,
which manages the stream name space
for the entire stamp.
Now of course having a single instance
of a stream manager would create
a massive single point of failure
and therefore the stream manager's
database is replicated on the
multiple independent servers.
Now because there's no shared hardware
state, the authors chose to use PAXOS
which is the de facto standard
mechanist to replicate state machines
across fully distributed systems.
Now once the stream has been created,
the partition layer which is the client
to the stream layer can directly
connect to the extent nodes.
And the extent nodes
are responsible to hold storage.
They're equivalent to the chunk nodes
or the chunk servers
in Hadoop-based systems.
And by doing that you ensure that
the stream manager is off
the critical path for data access.
It is only there to provide metadata
capabilities to look up
where the data should actually be stored.
And then at the layer below each
extent node manages its local discs.
And on any write which is
actually the pen within the stream.
The first extent node
that replicates the request,
to the two secondary extent nodes
before acknowledging the request.
This is how you implement synchronous
three-way replication within the stamp.
If you're interested
in learning more about
the Azure system,
I refer you to the paper.
But now let's see if we can
compare these two case studies.
As a matter of fact,
it's even interesting to question
whether these two systems are comparable.
They're radically different on nearly
every point in this spectrum.
They scale very differently.
They provide different abstractions which
has implications for the applications.
These abstractions are presented using
very different networking technologies.
They also use different mechanisms
to ensure the atomicity of transitions.
In one case, we use a hardware mechanism
which is SCSI reservations
and in the other we use the
PAXOS consensus algorithm.
They offer different
quality of service characteristics.
They have different deployment models
but they're both designed to never fail
or more accurately said,
they're both designed to ensure
maximum availability.
This wraps it up for this week.
Thank you! Enjoy the papers.