Congratulations,
you've completed week 4!
Let us quickly look what we
have covered in this week.
We looked at biological
biowaste treatment options,
we looked at vermicomposting and
processing with black soldier flies,
we looked at thermochemical
conversion of organic waste,
but then we also looked at
hazardous and healthcare waste,
and concluded with E-waste.
In vermicomposting, we looked
at the worm cycle as a start.
Here shown in this
picture, Eisenia fetida.
And then we looked at the environmental
conditions suitable for vermicomposting,
such as aeration, moisture,
also the need to be shaded
and the daily feed rates of
about 50% of worm rate per day.
We also looked at case studies,
and looked how this
technology is constructed.
Such as the example
here from the Philippines.
And then we looked at the
products of vermicomposting:
the vermicompost, the worm
tea, and the worms themselves.
Then we looked at another
approach of biowaste processing
using black soldier fly larvae.
First we looked again at
the life cycle of the insect.
Then on how to manage the colony,
and how to operate
the treatment process.
And then we looked
at the BSF products:
the residue, which is similar
to vermicompost and the larvae,
which have a high protein
content of 40% and fat content of 30%,
and are a high value product
especially for animal feed.
In the module on
healthcare waste management,
we started off by
looking at the waste amounts.
Remember, only 15 to
20% is actually hazardous.
The rest is typical
municipal waste,
so segregation is
a main priority.
And then we looked at how to
enhance this source segregation
by color coding,
and the provision of
containers, for instance for sharps.
Then, we looked at healthcare
waste treatment options,
mostly referring to this book:
"The Compendium of
Technologies for Treatment
and Destruction of
Healthcare Waste".
We looked at different systems;
autoclaves, but also incineration,
and finally ending with the
special pits of landfilling.
In the module on
thermochemical processes,
we looked at the different
options and their different parameters:
temperature, air, and retention time,
but we also looked at the products from
these processes and their quality.
After looking at the
processes and their parameters,
we also looked at the value chain,
starting off with primary products, through
to conversion, to finally the market;
looking at different products of value,
which we can sell in the market.
And then the module on E-waste,
where we looked at the
relevance of E-waste on a global scale,
but also the risks of E-waste
recycling and how this can be improved.
Stay with us for an
exciting fifth week,
where we will be talking
about strategic planning,
benchmarking city performances,
looking at waste and climate change,
and also the issue
of circular economy.