I'm Cécile Hébert, professor
in physics at the EPFL
and leading the center
for Elec-microscopy here.
And I'm Duncan Alexander,
a scientific professional at EPFL
specialized in transmission
electron-microscopy
and welcome to CIME's course on
transmission electron microscopy
for materials sciences.
Since it's invention, transmission
electron microscopy has become
a key tool in analysis of
many types of materials.
It has the ability to generate
an image with nano-metric or even
atomic resolution and can give,
for example information on
the crystallinity of materials,
but also on the defect structure
the characteristics of interfaces
and grain boundaries, etc.
Nowadays, state of the art
transmissionary microscopy
is both a mainstay of much
advanced materials and technological
research, but also for industries,
such as semi-conductor fabrication
or catalyst production.
When using this microscopy, often
called TEM, or Tem for short
The electron beam of the microscope
has strong interactions
with the sample of interest.
We use these different interactions
to characterize and to understand
many different properties
of this sample.
To take such useful data
or to interpret TEM results,
it is important to have
a thorough understanding
of the basics of TEM.
Starting from the microscope
and it's optics through
electron matter interactions,
and on to how to use these to record
imaging data.
Teaching these basic is
the aim of this course.
Starting with an introduction to the TEM,
on through electron diffraction and
diffraction contrast imaging,
and finally to phase contrast imaging
used for high resolution TEM.
This course is clearly designed for
people working with solid specimen
I mean, non-biological specimen
where the crystallinity
dominates the contrast.
So, if you are to take a practical
training on a TEM, this course
provides a first theoretical
grounding for your training.
However, it will also be useful
to understand any TEM image
you might encounter, or it can
provide the basic building blocks
you need before studying or applying
one of the many more advanced
TEM based techniques.
And as TEM is an imaging technique,
and operating the instrument
a dynamic process, in our course
we embedded many examples
filmed on real TEM, making
it more visual than a book.
We hope you enjoy it.
In the coming weeks you will see
both of us for different modules
in the course.
Now for the introduction, Cécile
will begin, so over to you Cécile.
Thank you Duncan!