So, welcome to CIME's lecture on
Transmission Microscopy for material
science. In this video we will have
a brief historical introduction
about the Transmission microscope
and then review all the building parts
of the instrument with which we will
work during this lecture.
The Transmission Electron Microscope
was first built by Knoll&Ruska
in 1931. When they have built the
first prototype.
Actually, when they started working
on this device, the idea was to prove
the theoretical demonstration that
thin electromagnetic coil would have
exactly the same effect on electrons
than a thin glass lens has on light.
So, if you want to prove this, the
idea was to say: "OK, let's prove
that this lens, electromagnetic lens
can focus electron and make an image"
And very soon they realized that
it's possible to get images with
better resolution than the light
microscope. Only two years later
the TEM is surpassing the light
microscope in terms of resolution
And then only 6 years later there're
the first commercial instruments
which is quite fast if you look at
the time and history in Germany
at that time. And then time passes
and it's only 1986 that E.Ruska's
is awarded the Nobel Price. About
the Nobel lecture I really recommend
that you have a read at a Nobel
lector E.Ruska because it's both
very entertaining and very
instructive on how this instrument
was imagined, developed, built
and all the interaction between
engineering technique and
science at that time.
I said 1933 the TEM surpasses the
light microscope in resolution.
Why is it so? How can we explain
this? For the light microscope you
all know the Abbe diffraction limit
based on the Rayleigh Criterion
It gives you the smallest detail
that you can resolve in a microscope
as a function of the wavelength
lambda and the numerical aperture
n sinus theta. A similar formula
holds for the electron microscope
where lambda is the wavelength
of the electrons and theta -
the maximum angle at which
electrons are collected.
Let's try to plug in some numbers
in there. Lambda for typical
transmission elec. microscope at
200 kilovolt is about 2.5 picometer.
so  10 to the -12 meter at 200
kV. Theta is the angle at which
electrons are collected, and it's
typically around 10 milliradians.
Say 10 to 20. So, 10 to the
-2 radians. You will come back later
to this during the lecture. OK,
putting this into the formula, we
get "d" approximatively 1.2 times
2.5 10 to the -12 over 10 to the -2
which is around 3 10 to the -10
it's 3 Angstrom. We are around the
atomic distances in material. Atomic
resolution is possible and that was
already recognized as early as in
the 30s. Let's imagine now if we
improve things a little bit with
lambda, or with theta, then we can
get maybe less than 3 Angstrem.
If we have 10 to 20 millirads then
20 millirads gives us 1.5 Angstrom,
that's really around the interatomic
distance in crystals. It's far above
the resolution of a light microscope.
And indeed if we watch the evolution of
resolution of microscope,
you see that the resolution of light
microscopes was improving at the
beginning and then is hitting some
maximum just limited by the
Abbe diffraction limit and
wavelength of light and you reach
something around 100-200 nanometers
and as soon as it started being
commercialized the EM
surpasses the resolution of LM.
And the resolution increase as
progress is made to be able to
work with larger theta, or smaller
lambda. But then, it reaches also
a maximum which is just below 1
Angstrom. Why is it so? Can't we
improve things by having a very
large theta? Well, actually not
because we have problems with
aberrations. So, for these microscopes
the resolution is limited by the
aberrations and not as for LM
by the wavelength. Later on
aberration corrected microscope
were developed and with aberration
corrected transmission microscope
you can reach even better resolutions.
So, I think that's sufficient to be
convinced that this is a fantastic
instrument that will open
an incredible amount of
possibilities. But before learning
how to work with it and how it works
we need to look at its difference
building blocks. So, we need to look
at all of the constituent of the TM.
Let's start with this microscope:
it's a Jeol 200cx an old generation
microscope that has been cut open,
so you can see all the internal part
because normally they have to be
under vacuum. The electrons are
generated on the top and come down
the electron column they hit the
specimen at the height of the
specimen holder and they're focused
by all these electromagnetic lenses.
So, let's start from the top.
We have the electron gun at the top
The electron gun will be the part
that generates and accelerates
the electrons. The first part, where
the electrons are generated is
hidden behind this plastic part
and then all these ceramics are
separating of different parts of
the accelerator. The emitter emits
the electrons. And the accelerator
stage accelerates them to the
desired energy. There are 4 types
of emitter listed in the next table.
W and LaB6 are so-called
thermionic emitters. For those 2
types, the emitter is heated and
electrons are emitted
because of this heating.
The Cold Field Emission Gun is
a real field emission emitter
The electrons are emitted thanks
to a high electric field applied to
the emitter. And in the middle we
have the so-called Shotkey FEG
which is a compromise between
thermionic emitter and Cold FEG
where the electrons are emitted by field
emmission assisted by a heating of the
filament. A key quantity to
characterize the emitter is the
brightness. The brightness gives
the intensity emitted per sq.m
and steradian. So, if you take an
area of your emitter and you look
at the current, the number of
electrons by unit of time
emitted for this given area, and
in a solid angle omega, you get the
brightness. There's a huge difference
in brightness between the different
type of emitters. And the high
brightness is linked to a high coherency
because the electrons come from
a small part of the emitter
This is important for phase contrast.
A second characteristic is the size
of the cross over after the emitter.
It is much larger for W, than for
the Cold FEG. With a small size of
the cross over after the gun
you will be able to focus your
beam more precisely on the specimen
which will be good for chemical
analysis, for example, or for
working in scanning transmission
electron microscopy.
The third characteristic is the
energy spread. How well are
the electrons defined in energy.
Field emission gun have a much
narrower energy spread. This is both
important for chemical analysis,
but also a smaller energy spread
gives a better temporal coherency
important for phase contrast as well.
But those better characteristic
come at a price. We need a higher
vacuum or those emitters, which
means that they are much more
expensive in operation,
but fortunately they also have
a longer lifetime.
Let's continue down the column
to the next part.
One of the most important one:
It's the electron lens.
The electron lenses, you see some
there, but also some down the column
They are electromagnetic coils.
If you look at an enlarged picture
you can clearly see how the wires
so it just a copper wires winded
around the optical axes of the micr.
You see all is wires there.
So, with this geometry, they will
definitively generate a field with
cylindrical symmetry. Also, with
this type of lenses, there's a big
difference compared to light
microscopy. Here we can easily
change continuously the focal
length of the lens by just changing
the current in the coil and that is what
we do all the time when we operate
the microscope. For example, when
we change magnification, the focus
of the image, change from imaging
to diffraction, etc.
This is much more versatile than
for a light microscope.
We had a little talk about this.
They are "bad" lenses.
They have a lot of aberrations,
and that will be the limiting
factor to the resolution of
microscope. So the TEM is
limited by the aberration of
this kind of lenses. That is why
we will review the aberrations in
the next lesson as they are very
important to understand the
imaging properties of the microscope.
Also, if you stick to lenses with
cylindrical symmetry, as is usually
the case in the TEM, then you only
get convergent lenses.
And last. Because the electron lens
has the same focusing property
on electrons,  than a glass lens has on light, you can make use of
ray diagrams to understand your
microscope as you do in light
microscopy. So, basically, I have two
news there. One bad news-
the electron microscope is limited
by the resolution of those lenses.
One good news - you will be able
to use ray diagrams and you will
make use of them all the time
during this lecture. They are very
important to understand the
working property of the TEM.
OK. It's a good news provided
you remember how to use them.
So, do you remember how to draw
the image produced by the thin
convergent lens? If not, it will be
explained in the next video.
But let's continue on the building
parts of the microscope now.
The next one, that we will look at
are the Apertures. The Apertures
are holes of defined size placed
on the path of the beam.
They are supported by a thin plate
mounted on a rod.
You can see here some apertures
in the lower part of the image also.
These holes are small 10-200
micrometers and they will limit the
extension of the beam. Generally,
you have something like 4-8 sizes
you can chose from, like here,
for example you recognize
maybe 3-4 sizes, and they are at
strategic places in the microscope.
They will define some properties of
the beam, like the one which is just
after the beam-forming coils that
we will review next time or the one
which are at strategic places in the
imaging parts of the microscope.
And, finally, we need to look at
something, right? We want a specimen
we want the specimen  hold at  some place. It's hold in the
Goniometer and in a  thing called
the Specimen holder. The specimen
we look at TEM is small and you will
see that is the specimen holder that
enters the beam, the optical axis
is down there and at that point you
have the place for the specimen.
So, the specimen holder will hold
the investigated specimen.
Very commonly it's a 3mm disc
and you need an area that will be
transparent to your electrons an
magnitude should be around 100nm
or less. If it's thinner, it's much
better for some imaging.
Natively, you will be able to tilt
your specimen along the axis of
the specimen holder. That's what
we call the alpha-tilt.
Some holders will also allow you to
tilt the specimen along a second axis
which is perpendicular to it. And
then some holders will allow
incredible things. Like, you will
be able to heat your specimen or cool your specimen
to liquid Nitrogen temperature or
even to liquid Helium temperature.
Might be able to have electrical
fields, or electrical currents
You might be able to have some
straining experiment or some
indentation experiment, well
there's no limit to the imagination.
That will not be too much part of
the lecture that if you look in to
what's done in transmission
electromicroscopy, there's a huge
variety of in situ experiments
allowed by these specimen holders.
And, finally, to be a little bit
back to the real world, well
I've brought you a specimen holder.
It's there in its protective cover
and if I remove it, you see this
very thin long rod. That's an O ring
that will allow to keep the vacuum
in the microscope and there you have
the place where to put the specimen.
So, it's a small thin disc and some
specimen can be, for example,
nanoparticles or whatever
that are deposited on a copper grid
covered with a thin carbon film.
How does the copper grid looks like?
Well, it's this very thin tiny 3 mm
disc that you have here. So,
manipulating them you need
a lot of care.
So, in this module you have seen
the main constituents of the TM.
One of them is the lens. In the
next module we will review all
the aberrations that are relevant to
electron lenses.