Do you remember how to
draw the image produced by
a thin convergent lens?
Try to reproduce this figure on
a piece of paper and to draw
the image of this object,
so this green thing there would
be your object, you have your lens,
the focal points of the lens
F and F prime, and I want to obtain
the image of this object called
AB by the lens.
Okay, it's a very simple rule that
you will have to use all the time
and we will use it a lot when
we interpret images and diffraction
pattern in the microscope.
There are two rules.
The first one is, if I take a ray of
light that is coming out of
my object, if this ray passes
through the central part
of the lens, then it will
be undeflected, so if it goes
there it will be deflected, but not
if it goes through the center of
the lens, so I can draw a first ray
this one that comes from the B point
of the object and obviously my image
will have to be
somewhere on that line.
But with only one line I don't
have the place where to find B.
I can do a second ray,
by taking a ray
that is now entering the lens
parallel to the optical axis.
If I do so, the ray will be
deflected exactly through
the focal point, I can then
continue it, and at one point
it will cross the first ray, so now
I do have a place where I know
I have my B point.
I know that the image of A
will be on the same height
but on the optical axis, so I know
exactly how to draw my image.
It's like this, there, I have
A prime and B prime.
Okay, for your assignment you
will have to do a few more of
this drawing and this is a language
that you really need to be fluent in
to follow the lecture.