Welcome to CIME's lecture
on Transmission Electron Microscopy
for Material Science.
In this video, we will review the main
aberrations that are relevant
to understand the imaging properties
of a transmission electron microscope.
You remember, from the last lecture,
we had this graph that shows you
and tells you that the microscope
has its resolution limited
by aberrations.
Actually, the most important one
is the spherical aberration,
and we will start with it.
So, spherical aberration, you probably
remember it from your lecture in optics.
First of all, it is characterized
by its coefficient, Cs,
given in millimeter.
Then, it tells us that rays that enter
a lens away from the optical axis
are more focused.
That's the case for positive Cs.
How does it look if we try to draw
this information?
We have, here, a lens,
and we will take some rays
that will enter the lens
all parallel to the optical axis.
There we have it.
Normally, such rays should be focused
to the focal point of the objective lens.
So, something like this,
and all rays  coming through
the same point
But now, we say that rays that enter
the lens away from the optical axis
are more focused.
So this one is further away.
So the lens will be stronger,
and the ray will be more deviated.
That continues holding
for the next rays,
which will be even more deviated.
Then, we should draw this
in a symmetrical manner,
and finishing the drawing,
obtain something like this.
That's what you're used to in optics.
But now, generally, in a transmission
microscope,
we are working with very small
specimen parts.
So you can consider that everything
comes from the same place on the specimen.
What is the effect, now, if we take
a point object?
Let's take the same setup,
but our object is now a point.
I first need to find a place
where the image will be formed.
For this, I need to imagin
an extended object
and draw its image by the lens.
This gives me the position
of the image
at that point on the optical axis.
That's where the image of this point
object should be.
Now, a point object will emit rays
in different directions that will hit
the lens.
Those rays will be focused by the lens
to the object point.
The problem is that rays that are
further away from the optical axis
will see a stronger lens
and be focused closer to the lens.
It is symmetrical and is even
worse for the further rays.
You see that the image of a point
is not a point anymore, but a disk.
Somewhere on the optical axis,
I have the place where my disk
has the smallest possible size.
It's the disk of least confusion.
This will blur the image
and, eventually, make some kind
of strange effect,
like the one we will see
on the next slide,
which shows a real electron
microscopy picture.
Typically, the Cs will make 2 effects.
On one side, it is able to create
ghost images
of strongly defracting specimen.
You see, there, that you have the actual
image of the small crystal
but also like a bright image on each side,
left and right.
That is what we call ghost image,
and this can be obtained due to the Cs.
It will also blur interfaces.
Here we have a defects in a crystal
which should be only extending
over 1 atomic layer
in this high resolution image,
but if you look at it you have the feeling
that it's extending over 4 or more
atomic layers.
These 2 effects are called delocalisation.
You will see this one in the lecture about
imaging with defraction contrast,
and this one will be discussed
in the lecture about phase contrast.
The next aberration I want to discuss
is the so-called chromatic aberration.
Again, probably you know it.
It is characterized by its coefficient, Cc,
given in millimeters.
In that case, it tells us that electrons
at lower energy,
or longer wavelength, will be more
focused by the lens.
Again, let us try to draw this.
I have there my lens,
and I will start this time with a simple
point object
and a the focal points.
Again, I should have the image
of that point
at the same place than I had before.
Now, I will consider electrons which have
the nominal energy of the electron beam,
and I will draw them in blue.
They will enter the lens
all with different angles,
and I will neglect the spherical aberration.
So all those rays will be focused to the same
point, properly, like it should be
by a perfect lens.
Finishing the drawing gives me
the following:
a nice point image of a nice point
object.
Now, I also have electrons
with lower energy.
I will draw them in red.
They will follow the same paths between
the objects and the lens,
but then we say that electrons at lower
energy are more focused.
So those ones will see a stronger lens.
The same for the one which are there,
and the one which is at that point
will also see a stronger lens.
Again, I neglect the spherical aberration,
which means that, still, my point object
gives me a point image.
Altogether,
I will, again, end up with a blurred
image.
This also results in a disk
of least confusion
and, therefore, blurring of the image.
Fortunately, the chromatic aberration
is less important than the spherical
aberration
for several reasons.
First of all,
the small energy spread of the probe,
especially if you use a special
monochromator
that will even reduce the energy spread
of the electrons coming out of the gun,
will reduce the impact.
If you use a thin specimen,
your electron beam will not interact
too much with the specimen.
So the electrons will not have too many
events that will lead to energy loss,
and they will keep the nominal energy
of the beam.
So, a thin specimen will also reduce
the impact.
Like for spherical aberration,
for chromatic aberration, it is in principle
possible to develop correctors,
but they are only developed
in very few labs.
It is still a research area, while
spherical aberration correction
exists nowadays on commercial
instruments.
It is important to consider it
at very low tension
but also if you want to analyze
the energy loss by the electrons.
This will be part of a later module.
A short historical note on these
aberrations,
chromatic aberration and spherical
aberration.
Actually, they were recognized
to be very important
in limiting the resolution of the TEM,
already in the 30's
by Otto Scherzer.
If you look at this paper, published
in 1936,
what Otto Scherzer tells us
is that you cannot avoid spherical
and chromatic aberrations
for lenses with cylindrical symmetry.
They will limit the resolution
of the microscope.
The same Otto Scherzer proposed,
only 11 years later,
some solution for this.
One of them is to break
the cylindrical symmetry.
Building such a piece of equipment
was so challenging and so difficult
that the 1st successful correction
of a TEM came only in 1997.
So now we remain with only 1 aberration,
and this one has a slightly different
position.
It is called astigmatism.
Astigmatism is when the focal length
is not the same for 2 perpendicular
directions of the lens.
Therefore, we need to represent
astigmatism in a 3-D drawing,
which will make the drawing a little
bit more challenging.
Astigmatism affects all electron lenses
because of inhomogeneities
in the material or machining,
but also because of dust particles
that escape the specimen,
contamination on aperture or pole pieces,
or even because of the specimen itself,
if it is magnetic.
But I have very good news.
It's that astigmatism can be corrected.
That is even one of the important steps
that you are doing
when aligning a transmission microscope.
Let us look at it in more detail.
First of all, I have my 3 dimensional
lens
with the vertical direction
and 1 horizontal direction.
So I really have to enter the 3rd
dimension.
This is the optical axis.
I will, again, take a point object,
which has, as an image,
a point image.
Let's start with imaging
that we have there.
The image obtained when I have rays
that enter the lens on the vertical axis.
Now, we say that the focal length
is not the same for 2 perpendicular
directions.
If I take rays that enter the lens
on this perpendicular direction,
they will not focus at the same point.
So maybe after, maybe before,
depending on how the astigmatism
is going,
but not at the position
where it should go.
It will look a little bit like this.
It is more difficult to imagine
what's really going on there
because that means that my image,
if I look at this plane,
is sharp in the vertical direction
but completely unsharp
in a horizontal direction.
So let's try to see what is going on
on a real transmission electron
microscopy image.
I've taken the simplest case
of a hole that is there,
so I have no specimen on the inside,
and which is in a carbon film.
So that's amorphous carbon.
If everything works well,
and if my image is in focus,
you see, very well, the rim of the hole
with no particular contrast.
If I now over focus the lens,
I will see some strange contrast there,
which looks like grains appearing
in the carbon film,
and this dark rim on the side
of the hole.
In this case, the rim is the same
everywhere.
I have no astigmatism in those 2 images.
It is perfectly corrected.
But this one is a bit strange, right?
It looks like it is in focus there
and completely over focused
at that position.
Indeed, this image has a strong
astigmatism.
So this image is in focus,
over focus,
and this has some part over focused
and some part in focus.
If you look carefully, you will
also see that the carbon film
is not homogenous anymore.
It looks like maybe it has been
stretched, or whatever.
You see elongated structures
in this direction,
which correspond to the direction
of the astigmatism.
Again, it is because I'm in focus
in that direction
and not in focus in the other direction.
Okay. With this, we have seen the main
aberrations
that are relevant to understand
a transmission electron microscope.
In the next video, you will see
how we can take groups of lenses,
put them together, and build a complete
transmission microscope.
Before jumping to this, I would like you
to have a look at these links.
They will explain to you and show you
that electrons are also waves.