Welcome to CIME's lecture
on transmission electron microscopy
for material science.
In today's video, we will use
the building blocks
that we have seen before,
the lenses.
And see how we can put them together
to get a working microscope,
with all its parts able
to make the image
of a specimen.
There are many lenses
in a microscope.
They belong to 3 main groups which
have different functionalities.
The first one before
the specimen
is called the Condenser lenses.
These are the lenses used
to form the beam
that is exiting the gun
and project it onto
the specimen.
The second block is the objective
lens and its apertures.
It's where we have
the specimen,
and that is a very important
lens
used to make the first
intermediate image
of the specimen, and also
a diffraction pattern.
And finally, we want to be able
to change the magnification
to look either at the image
of the specimen
or at its diffraction pattern,
and also to change the magnification
of the diffraction pattern.
That is done by the third group
which is made of
the intermediate lens
and projective lenses.
So the first group,
condenser lens,
forms the beam, projected
on the specimen.
The objective lens makes an
image of the specimen,
and the intermediate
and projective lenses
will project this image
on the recording device,
magnify it, or project
a diffraction pattern
eventually magnifying it.
Why is it important to understand
those lenses and how they work?
Let's go to the microscope.
So here we are at the real
transmission electron microscope.
This is a JEOL 200kV
and you can recognize the same
structure as we had before
in the lecture.
On the top, we have the gun.
This is a 200kV field
emission gun.
Then we have the condenser lenses
with condenser aperture.
And below we have the objective lens
with the specimen,
the objective aperture,
and hidden behind, we have
the selected area aperture.
Further down, we have
the intermediate
and projective lenses.
And here on the table, we have
the computer
for controlling the microscope
and the control panel.
There are a lot of knobs on
this control panel,
and each of these knobs will have
some influence
on some of the lenses
of the microscope.
So, for example,
this brightness knob
controls the condenser lenses
and the illumination
on the specimen.
If I change the focus knob,
it will change the current
in the objective lens.
I can change the magnification
which will have an influence
on the projective lens.
I can switch to diffraction
that will change the projective
and intermediate lenses.
And I also can deflect the beam
on after, before the specimen
So it's very important to understand
what you are doing
when you operate the microscope.
And for this you know
to understand the functioning
of all those group
of lenses.
And that's what we ill see now in
the following part of the lecture.
The condenser system forms
the beam after the gun
and projects it on
the specimen.
It is the first set of lens
before the specimen
and after the gun.
And it is made of at least
2 lenses
and 1 aperture.
We will start with
the simplest case
of 2 lenses and 1 aperture.
The first one on the top
is called condenser 1.
The second one just below
is the condenser 2.
And the aperture is
the condenser 2 aperture.
The specimen is further away
and the beam formed by
the set of lenses
will be projected on it.
The gun is producing
a crossover
which is a point where
all the electrons will cross
on the optical axis.
These set of lenses will then
form an image
of this crossover and project it
on the lens.
In that simplest case
which I've taken,
the distance between lens
and focal point
is the same as the distance
between focal point and object.
So I know that in this
schematic
I will have a magnification
of exactly 1,
and the image will form
at the same distance
as the object is. The drawing
is therefore very simple.
Depending on the strength
of the C2 lens,
I can form my last crossover
exactly on the specimen,
before the specimen,
or after the specimen.
I will take the case where I form it
exactly onto the specimen.
You see that the condenser 2
aperture
actually limits the extension
of the beam.
I can redo the drawing in
the reverse direction
and I will know exactly
what is the maximal opening
of my beam.
This part of the beam, is cut
by the aperture
while this one is kept
by the aperture.
I have here, a maximal angle
that will illuminate
the specimen.
It's called the illumination
semi angle alpha.
If I change the excitation of
the C2 lens,
I will change the position
of the focal point.
By doing this, I will
also change
the position at which the crossover
is formed.
For example, if I increase
the strength,
the focal point will move
closer to the lens
and the strength of the lens
will be stronger.
I will have the same ray
path after C1.
But after C2, as I will have
a stronger lens,
my crossover will form earlier.
My lens will be
in over focus.
My crossover,
before the specimen.
The reverse is if I decrease
the strength of C2
I will form my crossover
after the specimen.
If I want to know what will be
the effect of changing the strength
of C1, I have to redo
my drawing.
And this time, I will increase
the strength of C1.
Which means I will have
my focal point
closer to the lens,
and the symmetric focal point
also closer to the lens.
In that case, the image
of my crossover
will not be at the symmetrical
position as before.
I have to do a complete drawing
to know where to find it.
With this drawing, I know
the position
of the image
of my gun crossover
and then I can draw
the ray pass.
I have to take rays with
a slightly lower opening.
I need to know the image
of this crossover done by C2.
I will adjust my C2 lens
in such a way that the image
is forming on the specimen,
and to have a convergent beam
on the specimen.
Adjusting the C2 lens, means
that I am allowed
to change the position of
the focal point.
Now my constraint is that
my object for C2 is there
and my image for C2 is
at that position.
With this drawing,
I have the position
for my new focal point
F2 of the C2 lens.
I also notice something.
Before, I had
a magnification of 1.
Now, I have a magnification
between this as an object
and that point as an image
which is smaller.
I can finalize the drawing
by knowing that the rays
will converge
to the specimen,
and then eventually take
into account the C2 aperture.
Finally, by changing
the strength of C1,
I end up with a beam
on the specimen
with the same alpha as before
when I'm converged
on the specimen,
but with a de-magnified image
of my source.
I am working with a smaller spot
of electrons on the specimen.
And that's finally why we say
that C1 controls the spot size.
And C2 with its aperture,
will control the opening
of the beam,
and the width
of the illumination
on the specimen.
So, that was for a 2 condenser
lens system.
With the help of
the appendix video
you will figure out by yourself
how it works
for a 3 condenser
lens system.
But now let's go
to the microscope.
Okay, here we are again
at the microscope.
And I will show you the effects
of the condenser lens system.
This time, we see the image
of the beam of electrons
that will illuminate the place where
we have the specimen.
If I turn the knob
called brightness,
I can illuminate a larger
or smaller
place on my specimen.
And this is done by changing
the current
in the second condenser lens
which is called CL3 here.
I can also change the spot size.
Now we have spot 1,
to increase it
for example, to spot 3, 4, 5, etc.
This changes massively the current
in the first condenser lens
and with this I'm able to have
a smaller illumination
on my specimen.
But now let's move on to the next
building block of the microscope.
The objective lens makes
the first intermediate image
and diffraction pattern
after the specimen.
It's a very important one.
It has 3 main components.
The lens itself,
and 2 apertures.
At that height, we have
the specimen.
We can generally make
a simple sketch
where we have
the optical axis,
the specimen, and
the objective lens.
We suppose that we know where
we have the focal point
F and F' of
the objective lens.
First of all, we need
to figure out
where the image of the specimen
is forming.
With this, I see that I have
an image
formed below the lens with
a small magnification.
For simplicity,
I will imagine
that my illumination system,
the condenser lenses,
produce a parallel illumination
on the specimen.
Some of the electrons will
interact weakly with the specimen,
and will exit the specimen
parallel to the optical axis.
Those electrons will be focused
to the back focal plane
of the objective lens.
With this drawing,
I know exactly
that this point
of the specimen
corresponds to this point
of the image.
If I imagine that I have
a series of electrons
that are diffracted
in the specimen,
they will exit the specimen
with the beam making an angle
to the optical axis.
But all this part
of the specimen
will diffract the same way
which means that all these rays
will be parallel
to each other.
Still,
rays exiting the specimen
from that point
will correspond to the same
image point
on the specimen.
They will be focused by
the objective lens
to this point. The same
holds for the next one.
And I can continue
my drawing.
Now, what you can observe
is that all those red rays
cross at the same position
in the back focal plane
of the objective lens.
That's something that you might
have seen in your optics lecture.
Rays that enter the lens
parallel to each other
but at an angle
to the optical axis,
will be focused to a point
in the back focal plane
of the objective lens.
Now we can connect
the different parts
of this drawing
with the microscope.
At that position, we have
the specimen holder
with the specimen.
We have a first aperture.
This one is the objective aperture,
and it is exactly situated in
the back focal plane
of the objective lens.
We have a 2nd aperture
further down.
This one is situated
at the height
of the first intermediate
image
of the specimen.
This aperture is called a selected
area aperture.
Actually, if you want to go
a little bit further,
you might have seen in
your optics lecture
that in the back focal plane
of the objective lens,
you have a Fourier transformation
of your object.
The Fourier transformation
of a specimen
if it's a crystalline specimen,
you enter
the reciprocal space.
Which means that
in the back focal plane
of the objective lens,
you have an information on
the reciprocal lattice
of your specimen.
And that's exactly
your diffraction pattern.
We will come closer to this
in the lecture about
diffraction contrast, and
diffraction in the TEM.
But now, let's look
into more detail
at that real transmission
microscope.
If you look carefully,
you will recognize
that the objective aperture
which is in the back focal plane
of the objective lens
is very close to the specimen.
And that in contrast,
the selected area aperture
is very far away.
A second strange thing
is that the objective lens
seems to be
below its back focal plane.
This is absolutely impossible.
In reality, you have soft
magnetic material
which guides
the magnetic field
produced by the coil of
the objective lens,
to be very close
to the specimen.
All these distances are
in the order of magnitude
of a few millimeters.
The focal length of the objective
lens is generally
around 2 millimeters.
The specimen is very close
to the front focal plane
of the objective lens.
What would happen if you
would try to draw this exactly?
Instead of having
the focal point
between lens and specimen,
we should put it close
to the specimen.
In that case, when I try
to draw the image
of my specimen,
I will take a point close
to the optical axis,
passing through the focal point,
and then exiting parallel
to the optical axis...
Oops. I have a problem.
I can't do my drawing.
The image is forming
very far away.
A second thing
that you notice,
is that if this is my object,
the image would have this size
even if it's much further down.
That's exactly what happens
in the microscope.
The magnification by
the objective lens
is around 50 times.
The specimen is very close
to the focal point
and the image is forming
far away
from the lenses.
Since such a real scale drawing
is not practicable,
we will always use a sketch
with small magnification.
We now remain with the last
building block.
To visualize the image
or diffraction pattern formed
by the objective lens,
we use the intermediate
and projective lenses.
This is the group
that is situated after
the objective lens.
Generally you have at least
one intermediate lens
and 2 projective lenses.
Do we really need to draw them
to understand how
they are working?
Actually, we never do it.
We stick to the drawing
of the objective lens,
the one that we have here
which I have put a little bit
further up.
So let's connect all
the things together.
At that position I have
the specimen,
then I have the formation
of the diffraction pattern in
the back focal plane
of the objective lens.
And the selected area aperture
in the first intermediate image.
That's the diffraction pattern,
the image, and that's my specimen.
The current in those intermediate
and projective lenses
is not changed continuously.
It has presets,
and those presets
will help to either
project the image
of my specimen on
the recording device,
and when I do this
I obtain on my camera
something that might
resemble that.
That's a small oxide particle,
and that's the direct image
of this particle.
By just doing one press
on one knob,
I can switch all my lenses
and then move
to the projection
of the diffraction pattern
on the recording camera.
And in that case,
I see directly
the diffraction pattern
of this small oxide particle.
Okay, you will see
this interplay
between the pre-select of this
intermediate and projective lens,
and those planes in
the next part of the lecture
where we will show
the complete microscope
at work.
Together with demonstration
on a real TEM.
So in today's module,
we have seen the
3 main blocks of lenses
that are used first
to produce the image
of the crossover after the gun
to illuminate the specimen.
Then to make your first image
of the specimen,
and finally to take the image
or diffraction pattern
and view it on your recording device.
Next time,
we will have a look at the complete
microscope at work.
Both in diffraction mode,
and in imaging mode
and see how we can control
those lenses
to really obtain images
and diffraction patterns.