In this video, you will figure out
by yourself what's going on
in the Three condenser lens system.
Okay, I told you this two condenser
lens system is the simplest one.
In most of the modern microscopes we
have a three condenser lens system
It's very important, for example
if you want to have
a parallel illumination
on your specimen, that means
if you want to have your beam
of electrons coming altogether
parallel on the specimen.
So, here is your exercise.
You have to redo this
drawing on a piece of paper
and then try to draw the schematic
and explain at which place you have
to put the crossover of
the C2 lens in such a way that
the C3 lens will produce a parallel
illumination on your specimen.
So the constrains are two fold.
First of all we have
the crossover produced by the gun
which is then imaged by C1,
since we are not allowed to
change the strength of C1,
the position of the crossover
after C1 and after C2 is fixed.
The second constraint that we have,
and this is a very important one
is that we want to have a beam
making a parallel illumination on
the specimen, something like this
will happen when you have all your
electrons passing through the front
focal point of the C3 lens.
That means that I have to make
sure that the crossover of C2
exactly matches this
focal point of the C3 lens
and then the rays will exit
the C3 lens parallel to the optical
axis and I will have a parallel
illumination on my specimen.
Okay, so now I have
a second exercise for you.
What happens now to
my parallel illumination
if I first decrease
the strength of C3
so now I have C3 with
a smaller exitation and
I adjust C2 in order to still
have parallel illumination.
Okay, take another color and
draw this on the same drawing.
The constrains that I have
a C3 at a smaller exitation
tells me that the focal
lens of C3 is now larger
therefore the focal point F3 has
moved upwards the optical axis.
I still have to adjust C2 in a way
that the rays pass now to the new F3
which means that I have to increase
the exitation of C2, this adjustment
is an increase of the exitation .
At the end, the rays are passing
through F3, they will exit C3
parallel to the optical axis, and
the final effect is that I have
a parallel beam on the specimen with
a larger diameter than I had before.