Welcome to CIME's lecture
on Transmission Electron Microscopy
for material science.
In this video
I will take you to the microscope
and show you how it can record
images and diffraction patterns.
First of all,
I need to introduce you the
control panel of the microscope.
This is, this panel,
which I have at my disposal,
and where I can change,
for example, the magnification
of the image or
the diffraction pattern,
I can change the intensity,
as we saw on a previous video,
I can also move the specimen
to select different areas,
or I can change the position of
the illumination on the specimen.
I have also a very important knob,
which is called "Diffraction",
and this one will help me to switch
between "Image Mode",
while image the first
intermediate image,
and "Diffraction mode" will image
the back focal plane
of the objective lens.
Then, we have the screen capture
of the software
that controls the microscope
and gives us as an image filmed
of either the specimen
or the diffraction pattern.
This is, this big panel.
In the center you have the image
where you'll see the image displayed by
the intermediate and projective lens
in that case, this is an image
of a specimen.
The ring that you see corresponds
to the illumination on the specimen.
At that position, you see
the magnification that is chosen,
and on the left panel, I have
the possibility to choose aperture,
either the selected area aperture
or the objective aperture.
To help you understand
how it's working on the micoscope,
you will also have a sketch of the
Transmission Microscope.
This is, this small drawing,
which we had before
with the specimen, illuminated
by a parallel beam of electrons,
and we imagine that the specimen
is crystalline,
so we have undiffracted electrons
and some electrons which are
diffracted by the specimen.
That is the objective lens, in the
bifocal plane of the objective lens
we have the diffraction pattern,
and, later on,
we have
the first intermediate image.
Those black drawing are the aperture,
this is the objective aperture
and this is the selected area aperture.
And with the orange arrow
I will symbolize which plane
I'm currently imaging.
When I move to the microscope
I see it in that state,
I have the image,  I'm imaging
the first intermediate image
and I have no aperture.
First I adjust the focus,
with the focus knob,
which changes the current in the
objective lens,
to obtain the minimum contrast.
Then, I will insert
the selected area aperture,
which comes in
the first intermediate image
given by the objective lens.
This aperture cuts the image
and is now visible.
Now, on the panel, I will
hit the diffraction knob,
with this I changed the current
in the intermediate and projective lens,
and have a diffraction pattern.
On this diffraction pattern you see
several diffraction spots
and the pattern is not very regular,
it looks like
we are selecting several grains
with different orientations.
In the next step, I will insert
the objective aperture,
which will come
in the diffraction pattern,
and select only the central beam.
I can choose the size
of the aperture
and, eventually,
center it around the beam.
Now you see that we have only
direct beam
and none of the diffracted one.
Then, back to the panel,
I hit, again, the diffraction knob,
I am back to "Image Mode",
I see again
the first intermediate image
but this time
with a stronger contrast
and still with
the selected area aperture inserted.
I will take it out, so we have
the whole image of the specimen.
What you see now
is an image of the specimen
but with much higher contrast
than we had before.
The place where we have a hole
is bright,
that's why the image is called
"Bright Field".
You recognize several dark parts
on the specimen,
the contrast has two origins:
First of all, parts of the specimen,
which are thicker,
specially on
the bottom left part of the image,
will appear much darker because
they are scattering more electrons,
so more electrons are cut
by the objective aperture,
which is still inserted.
But also on the rim of the specimen,
close to the hole,
you see a lot of bright
and dark contrast,
these are diffraction contrasts.
If you look carefully,
some grain appear dark
while other appear much brighter,
it depends on the orientation
of this particular grain,
some will diffract strongly
and be dark,
and some will not be in
good diffraction condition
and they will appear brighter.
Back to the control panel,
I can change the magnification
and also adjust the brightness,
so that I keep the illumination
on the area which I see
on the screen.
So I zoom in my specimen
and I can also move it.
I'm still keeping
this interesting contrast
due to the objective aperture.
Now you see
in the center of the screen,
there is a grain which appear
very dark.,
it might be interesting
to have a diffraction pattern
originating only for this,
from this grain.
What I will do is, I will insert
a smaller selected area aperture,
which will cut the image
and select only part of the image
that I'm interested in.
Now we'll go back to "Diffraction"
I see not much, because the contrast
aperture, or objective aperture,
is still inserted,
so I have to remove it
to see the diffraction pattern,
and know you see
the clear diffraction pattern
of, nearlly,
a single Crystalline grain
close to zone-axis orientation.
And now inserting, again,
an objective aperture,
but this time I will not
center it around the central beam,
but I will choose one of these
bright diffraction spot
that I had in my diffraction pattern.
If I hit back "Diffraction",
I'm back to image mode,
imaging the first intermediate image,
I need to remove
the selected area aperture
and what you see now
is the same specimen
with a different contrast,
the hole is dark
because in the hole I have no
diffraction or diffusion of electrons
so they are all cut by the aperture.
The specimen itself
has brighter parts
And the very bright part are the one
which diffract strongly
in the direction which I have
selected with the objective aperture.
This is called a "dark field" image.
Again, I can play around, change
magnification, adjust intensity,
to zoom in and out of my specimen,
but still keep the same dark field contrast.
I might want to have a closer look
at my specimen
and go to higher resolution.
For this, I insert, again,
the selected area aperture,
adjust it properly
to select the same small area
of my specimen as before.
I switch back to "Diffraction"
and I will select
a much larger objective aperture,
which will take
several diffraction spot,
and I center it around
the center beam.
Back to "Image",
by hitting the diffraction knob
and removing the selected
area aperture,
We have, again,
a bright field image
with less contrast then
in the first one,
it's clear,
we have a larger objective aperture,
so we have selected, also,
some diffracted beam.
And now
I'm increasing magnification
and adjusting the intensity
to keep it on the specimen.
You see the magnification on
the bottom of the panel.
Once I've reached
a very high magnification
in that time,
more than one million times,
I start to see on my screen
what is called "lattice fringes".
Actually, with the resolution
of the video capture of the screen
you can not really recognize them
on this video.
So, we will switch back
to the presentation
and I will show you the
capture images that have been taken
on the CCD camera.
To have you better understand
what I mean with "high resolution",
I now have inserted this image,
which was acquired on
a good CCD camera on the microscope,
you see clearly the lattice fringes
and you will understand
how they are formed in the module
about high resolution
and face contrast.
Now we are finished
with the introduction,
you've had the building parts
of the TEM,
as well
as it's main operating modes.
In the following,
we will start considering
electron scattering by the sample
in more depth,
and for this
I will pass over to Duncan.
Thank you,  (INAUDIBLE)
When imaging any crystalline sample
in TEM
elastic scattering from
the crystal lattice, that is diffraction,
will dominate the image contrast.
Therefore, understanding
electron diffraction is vital to TEM analysis.
Here, starting from an assumed
understanding
of the basics of crystallography
and diffraction,
in the coming lectures
we will consider both
the theory of electron diffraction
and its influence in TEM image contrast.