Welcome to CIME's lecture
on transmission electron microscopy
for material science.
In this video we will see
Bragg's law, which is
a simple way to understand
the formation of diffraction pattern
in a transmission
electron microscope.
In a crystalline specimen
we can draw lattice planes
hkl with inter-lattice
distance d_hkl.
An electron wave will come and impact
on the specimen with an angle θ.
It will be reflected with
the same angle θ.
If I draw the wave on
the second plane
it will arrive also with
the same angle θ
and have the same
reflection angle.
The second ray has a path difference
with the first one, if I want to see
something in that direction, I need
to have constructive interferences
between those two waves.
That will only happen if the path
difference is a multiple of
the wave length.
The path difference can be found
on the graph and that position
it is the sum of those two paths and
since I have the angle θ again here
the lengths of those two
segments is 2*d_hkl sin θ.
Thus the condition for constructive
interference is nλ=2* d_hkl sinθ.
This angle θ in the case where I
do have diffraction is called θb
for θ Bragg.
and in the transmission microscope
we only have the first order so n=1.
Looking at some orders of magnitude
λ at 200kV is equal
to 2.5 pico-meters.
Ten to the minus twelve meters.
In a typical crystal we can imagine
that we have
the inter-lattice distances
in the order of magnitude
of 2.5 angstrom.
Let's take
d_hkl=2.5x(10^(-10)) meters
that gives me
sinθb≃5x(10^(-3))
it is small, it means that
θb is close to sinθb
θb≃5mrad
Usually, the microscope is vertical.
In that case the electron wave
is arriving close to the horizontal.
It's not realistic, so if we want to
draw it like it is in the microscope
it's more something like this.
I have the incoming election wave,
and the planes of my crystal.
But actually I don't
have such a large crystal
I have a thin specimen
in the microscope
which means that I have a drawing
looking like this, with the specimen
the objective lens and the place
that will be in the right position
for  Bragg diffraction.
If I illuminate this specimen with
parallel beam of electrons
so, parallel to the optical axis,
I will have some rays that will pass
through the specimen and
some rays that will be diffracted.
They will be imaged by the objective
lens, and as we've seen before
in the back focal plane,
I will have the formation
of the diffraction pattern and
in the first intermediate image
of the specimen,
I will have my image.
This can be connected
to the microscope
that we have seen before
in the following way.
The specimen  is in the specimen
holder at that position.
The diffraction pattern is in
the back focal plane of
the objective lens, where
I have the contrast aperture
or objective aperture.
And the first intermediate image is
where we have selected are aperture.
Again, we have to be careful,
that was the incidence angle
that we had before, and that's
the θb after the specimen.
The inter-lattice distance is
d_hkl and Braggs law tells us
λ=2d_hkl sinθb
but in the transmission microscope
we look at the angle between
the incoming electrons
and the outgoing electrons
and actually, if we look carefully
the incoming electrons are
continuing like this, this angle is
2xθb, so the angle that we find
there is 2θb.
With this you have a sufficient
understanding of diffraction
in the TEM to understand the main
operating modes of the transmission
electron microscope that
we will see in the next video.