Welcome to CIME's lectures on Transmission Electron Microscopy for materials science.
Continuing on the theme of the basics of electron diffraction,
in this lecture I will introduce the reciprocal lattice,
which together with the Ewald sphere,
will form our framework for understanding
and interpreting electron diffraction in the lectures to come.
To consider the reciprocal lattice,
I'm going to begin by considering the geometry of the diffraction vector,
that was introduced in last time.
From there, I'm going to go on and look at reciprocal lattice vectors,
and then the basis vectors of the reciprocal lattice a*, b*, and c*.
These form the reciprocal lattice unit cell,
and have certain properties which will be discussed briefly.
Then finally, I'm going to go from there,
to looking at an illustrated schematic of a reciprocal lattice,
which will then take further in the next lecture on the Ewald sphere.
As a way towards understanding the reciprocal lattice,
I'm first going to look at the wave vector diagram for 2-beam Bragg diffraction,
that I discussed in the last lecture.
If you remember, in this diagram we have an incident wave vector k_I,
where the modulus of a general wave vector k equals 1/λ.
As we saw last time,
this incident wave vector k is scattered at an angle theta,
by the Bragg diffracting plane.
Such that in the diffraction pattern,
we would see two spots:
one for the direct beam,
corresponding to the incident wave vector k_I,
and another spot for the diffracted beam,
corresponding to the diffraction wave vector k_D.
And then, joining these two,
I introduced the diffraction vector g,
where I use g as a shorthand for g_hkl.
Now if we look at this diffraction vector_g,
we can notice two things:
The first thing, if we just consider that Bragg diffracting plane,
it is evident that the direction of the diffraction vector_g
is perpendicular to the Bragg diffracting plane.
Further we saw how the modulus of g is one divided by the plane spacing.
While, in this case, g corresponds to a particular diffraction vector,
I'm now going to introduce a general vector
– called the reciprocal lattice vector –
which will correspond to any possible diffraction vector.
So, each plane (hkl) will have its own reciprocal lattice vector.
Evidently, this reciprocal lattice vector
must have the same properties as g.
In other words,
the reciprocal lattice vector will be perpendicular to
its plane (hkl),
and will have a length
which is inversely proportional, or the reciprocal, of the plane spacing.
To understand reciprocal lattice vectors, I'm going to draw in
some reciprocal lattice vectors for hypothetical planes in real space,
such as we have in this diagram here;
where we have plane d₁ in red and plane d₂ in blue, with an origin here.
We're going to define a reciprocal lattice vector for a plane d as d*.
Now, first considering the plane d₁,
we know that the reciprocal lattice vector will be perpendicular to the plane d₁
and so, for instance, starting at the origin will look like this.
Now, instead considering the reciprocal lattice vector for the plane d₂, firstly
this is going to be perpendicular to that plane d₂,
so in a different direction to d₁*,
but also we can see that the plane spacing for d₂
is smaller than the plane spacing for d₁.
So for d₂* we will obtain a longer reciprocal lattice vector, like this.
Just for clarity, I will now redraw these two reciprocal lattice vectors over here,
so we have d₂*
perpendicular to the plane d₂, and d₁* perpendicular to the plane d₁.
These are just the reciprocal lattice vectors for two planes,
but we can continue on considering other planes.
So we shall do that here.
Here I have again marked on the planes d₁ and
d₂, and their reciprocal lattice vectors d₁* and d₂*,
but now I'm going to add another plane, d₃.
Now if the plane d₁ has an (hkl) of (h₁ k₁ l₁),
and the plane d₂ has an (hkl) of (h₂ k₂ l₂),
the fact that the plane d₃ intersects these two planes
at one plane spacing from the origin,
means that d₃ will have an (hkl)
of (h₁+h₂ k₁+k₂ l₁+l₂).
I'm now going to mark in the reciprocal lattice vector for this plane d₃.
So once again, of course, this reciprocal vector will be perpendicular to
the plane d₃, and have a length which is inversely proportion its plane spacing.
Its plane spacing is even smaller than that of d₁ or d₂,
so its reciprocal lattice vector is even longer.
Now, this vector can be marked in on this cleaner diagram over here, and there,
once we have done that, we can notice something:
that the reciprocal lattice vector d₃* equals the reciprocal lattice vector
d₁* plus the reciprocal lattice vector d₂*.
Therefore, for this relationship of the planes' Miller indices, we have
a vectorial addition that: d₃* = d₁* + d₂*
Now we have looked at a general vector for a lattice plane (hkl),
we're going to look at the basis vectors that form the reciprocal lattice unit cell.
While the real space lattice has units cell basis vectors: a, b,
and c.
In the reciprocal lattice we will also have a unit cell,
and this will be defined by its own basis vectors, a*,
b*, and c*, defined as follows: that a* = d*₁₀₀.
Clearly, a* will therefore be perpendicular to the (100) plane.
It will also have a length of 1 divided by the plane spacing of the (100) plane.
Similarly, b* = d*₀₁₀, and will have
a modulus equal to 1 divided by the (010) plane spacing.
And we have c* = d*₀₀₁, where again,
the length of c* equals 1 divided by the spacing of the (001) plane.
These reciprocal lattice basis vectors can then be used
to define the reciprocal lattice vector for a general plane with Miller indices (hkl).
To understand why, we can consider the following. First of all,
we will consider a plane with Miller indices (hkl) equal to (200).
Now, this (200) plane is going to be parallel to the (100) plane.
However, if we instead think about plane spacings,
we know that the (200) plane will have
a plane spacing which is half that of the (100) plane.
So, d₂₀₀= d₁₀₀/2.
Now considering reciprocal lattice vectors,
since the planes are parallel,
the reciprocal lattice vector for the (200) plane will be parallel to that of
the (100) plane, but it will have two times the length.
So we will have a reciprocal lattice vector
d*_200 = 2 x d*_100
Now, as we saw previously,
d*_100 is defined as the reciprocal lattice basis vector a*.
So, d*_200
simply equals 2 x a*.
Generalizing this finding a bit further,
we go to planes with Miller indices of (h00),
or alternatively (0k0).
Starting with the (h00) plane,
taking this derivation a bit further,
it can be seen that it has
a reciprocal lattice vector d*_h00 = h x a*,
(the first of the reciprocal lattice basis vectors).
Going on now to the (0k0) plane, similarly,
that has a reciprocal lattice vector d*_0k0 = k x b*,
(the second of the reciprocal lattice basis vectors).
Finally, we could also consider the (00l) plane.
And that in turn, will have a reciprocal lattice vector
d*_00l = l x c*.
Now taking these findings,
together with the vectorial addition for
the reciprocal lattice vectors that we saw earlier,
for a general plane with Miller indices (hkl),
we obtain a reciprocal lattice vector d*_hkl equals to
d*_h00 + d*_0k0
+ d*_00l, so equal to
h x a* + k x b* + l x c*.
Thereby relating this plane's reciprocal lattice vector to
the Miller indices (hkl) and the reciprocal lattice basis factors a*, b* and c*.
On this slide we will now look in a bit more detail
at these properties of the reciprocal lattice basis vectors.
Already, we have established that d*_hkl = h.a* + k.b* + l.c*.
We also know that a* is the normal to the plane,
which contains the real lattice axes b and c. Hence
will obtain the scalar products a*.b = 0 and a*.c = 0.
Equally b*.a = 0, b*.c = 0,
and c*.a = 0 and c*.b = 0.
It can also be easily obtained that a.a* = 1, b.b* = 1,
and c.c* = 1.
Finally, because a* is perpendicular to b and c,
it's clear that a* is going to be parallel to
b cross c. And with a bit more derivation,
it can be shown that a* equals b cross c divided by V_c,
where V_c is the volume of the unit cell.
And similarly for b* and c*.
The previous slides have introduced the logic
behind the reciprocal lattice vector, and discussed
the derivation of the reciprocal lattice basis vectors a*, b* and c*.
However, what's more important in the lectures to come, is to understand
the reciprocal lattice as something visualized by a series of reciprocal lattice nodes,
where each node represents the reciprocal lattice vector for
a plane (hkl) in what we will call reciprocal space.
To illustrate this idea,
I'm going to show a section of a reciprocal lattice for a BCC metal.
In the middle we have the origin 000.
I'm now going to say that the basis vector b* lies along here, and has this length.
And the basis vector c* is here.
Because it's cubic, the lengths of b* and
c* are identical to each other, and they have a 90 degree angle between them.
Now considering the systematic absences for BCC,
if we go along the vector b*,
then the first diffracting plane we can have with a normal parallel to
this vector will be the (020) plane.
And we know that the (020) plane will have a diffraction vector
which will be two times the length of b*,
since b* star corresponds to d*_010.
Therefore, we represent the reciprocal lattice vector for that (020) plane as a node here.
Note that rather than drawing a vector to that node,
we just represent it as a spot,
which corresponds to a possible diffraction event.
If that is the node for the (020) plane, on this axis,
parallel to c*,
we will have the (002) node here.
Between them, we will have another node, for the (011) plane.
We can carry on identifying these different nodes.
By symmetry, here we will have the (00–2) and here the (0–20).
Here, the (01–1), and so on.
Now for simplicity, this is
just a two dimensional section of what would be a three dimensional lattice.
And we'll see next time how, by interacting
this three dimensional lattice with the Ewald sphere,
we can identify which planes
are going to diffract under certain conditions of, for instance,
sample orientation with respect to the electron beam.
To summarize, I have introduced the concept of
the reciprocal lattice vector for a plane (hkl).
And further seen how this reciprocal lattice vector d*_hkl can be described in terms
of the reciprocal lattice unit cell basis vectors a*, b* and c*.
Further to that, by assigning the reciprocal lattice vector for each plane a node,
we can consider schematically
a three dimensional reciprocal lattice made up of a framework of nodes,
where each of these nodes represents a possible diffracting plane.
Finally, as a last note I'll point out that
the reciprocal lattice is in fact the Fourier transform of the real lattice.
And this is something that will become important for
understanding the nature of electron diffraction in a few lectures time.