Welcome to CIME's lectures on transmission
electron microscopy for materials science.
In the last lecture,
we saw how the size and
shape of the sample,
in particular the fact that is very thin
leads to the reciprocal lattice
nodes having an elongated form.
The so called reciprocal lattice rod or
rail rod form.
And it is this elongation that gives the
relaxation of the Bragg condition, which
in turn allows us to start understanding
why in a zone access condition,
we have such strong scattering from many
different crystal planes at the same time.
In this lecture,
we're going to consider in more detail
the intensity along one of
these reciprocal lattice rods.
But I'm looking not at
the zone access condition,
but instead at the two beam
electron diffraction condition.
And further, considering what happens
to the intensity in a diffracted beam
when we deviate slightly from this
perfect Bragg scattering condition.
Here, we have a schematic diagram of our
sample with strong scattering from this
Bragg plane into this diffracted beam kD,
and the sample having a thickness of t.
To calculate the intensity
along a railroad,
we need to determine the free
transform of this sample thickness.
Effectively, the sample is like a top
hat function along this Zed access.
We have a function which is either
at maximum within the sample,
or along the rest of Zed
has a value of zero.
We need to calculate the Fourier
transform of this function.
Once we have identified that,
by taking its modulus squared,
we can obtain the intensity
distribution along this axis.
This, we will plot in reciprocal
space along the axis of the rail rod.
And for reasons that will become clear,
we will call the distance along
this rail rod, s, with a center of
the railroad corresponding to s = 0.
The amplitude and intensity distributions
of that top hat function are equivalent
to those from the scattering of plane
wave by a single slit with width W.
Here, we look at such a plane
wave with a wavelength
of lambda incident on the slit
which has this width W.
When the wave scatters from the slit,
we will obtain some
interference pattern that
the waves spreading out
with a central maximum and
then other narrow maxima
Looking at the far field,
the aptitude we're scattering for
a scattering
angle of phi is given by
the formula A = A0 sine of
pi W phi over lambda divided
by pi W phi over lambda.
In other words, we have a sync function
of sine x over x multiplied by A0,
where A0 is the maximum amplitude observed
at scattering angle phi equal to 0.
To translate this formula to the TEM case,
we know that W,
the width of our slit,
is equivalent to the sample thickness t.
And further, it can be easily showing
that in reciprocal space, phi over lambda
equals s, the distance along
our reciprocal lattice rod.
Taking these together,
when you see that A = A0
sine of pi ts over pi ds.
Plotting out this aptitude function along
the length of our reciprocal lattice rod,
s, we obtain an aptitude
distribution that looks like this.
With these modulations which are strong
in the center, where s = 0 and
the k out either side.
Further, considering s away from 0,
it is clear that when pi ts = n pi.
Where n is an integer that A = 0,
therefore, we see that s = n divided by t.
We have zeros along this modulation.
The first at 1 divided by thickness.
The second at 2 divided by thickness t and
so on.
Additionally, we see that
these sine type modulations
sit within a 1 over s envelope.
This is the amplitude function, but
in diffraction, we measure intensity.
To calculate the intensity distribution,
we simply need to take
the square of this function
corresponding to this Fourier transform
multiplied by its complex conjugate.
Looking at this intensity function,
we now have an intensity proportioned to
sine-squared of pi t s divided by pi
ts squared, or sine squared pi ts.
Along the railroad axis, We, again,
have a central maximum at s = 0.
And again, has 0 in the modulation at
s = 1 over t, 2 over t, and so on.
However, these time, these modulations
sit within our 1 over s squared envelope.
Here, we make that intensity expression
yet more specific to the TM case,
by considering that we have an incident
intensity on the sample, include a 1.
And now, calculating directly
the intensity in a diffracted beam, Ig.
Where Ig is, again, given by the sine
square root of pi ts on the top.
However, on the bottom, we have a new term
sIG is known as the extinction distance.
And while not proved here
is given by the expression
sIG = pi times the volume
of the unit cell times
cosine theta b,
where theta b is the Bragg angle,
divided by lambda,
the wavelength, times Fg,
where Fg is the structure factor for
that particular reflection.
Further, it can be straightforwardly
shown that the intensity at
the tip of the central maximum, at s = 0,
is given by the expression Ig = 0
= pi t divided by phi g squared.
One thing that is very important
to mention at this point is that
this expressions only apply in the case
of what we call kinematical scattering.
Kinematical scattering means
single elastic scattering.
In other words, the beam will
be diffracted at most one time
on its transmission or
trajectory through the sample.
While such kinematical scattering is
not an accurate assumption during real
electron diffraction where the probability
of scattering is very high.
Nevertheless, this expression and this
intensity distribution with this 1 over s
squared envelope will still give useful
insights in the remaining slides, where
we will interact this rail rod intensity
distribution where the Ewald sphere.
On this slide,
we're gong to make this interaction
looking at the perfect
Bragg scattering condition.
So we imagine we have a sample
of thickness t, with a plane
scattering at a perfect Bragg angle t to
b, giving a diffracted beam as follows.
Given that we're at the perfect Bragg
condition, the center of the reciprocal
lattice node is intersected
exactly by the Ewald sphere.
Thus, we will have a diffraction vector,
g, coming here
which is of course perpendicular
to our Bragg scattering plane.
We know that this reciprocal
lattice node is at the center
of some reciprocal lattice rod.
And now, we're going to plot
the intensity distribution
along this reciprocal lattice rod.
As we saw before, it will have some
modulations with a central intense peak.
Given that the eval sphere intersects
in the center of this peak,
the diffracted beam will have a strong
intensity given by that maximum.
Thus, if we took a diffraction pattern,
we will have one bright spot for the 000,
the direct beam, and another very bright
spot for the diffracted beam hkl.
On the next slide,
we will look at what happens to the
intensity in this diffracted beam when we
now tilt this diffracting plane slightly
away from that perfect Bragg condition.
On this slide, if that diffracting plane
was previously at this angle, there's now
been tilted slightly by an angle down to
theta towards the incident electron beam.
Since the reciprocal lattice vector
is perpendicular to this plane,
it also is rotated by an angle,
delta theta, compared to previously.
The reciprocal lattice rod is going to be
centered on this vector, g, as follows.
With the Ewald sphere
intersecting this real rod here,
the diffraction vector
kD drops as follows.
Sketching in the intensity modulations
along the reciprocal lattice rod,
we say that unlike the perfect
Bragg condition, where
the intensity in the diffraction beam was
given by the maximum in this central peak.
The intensity in that diffracted beam
is now given by this locus here.
Thus, clearly,
if we now sketch a refraction pattern,
While the direct beam will be strong,
the intensity in that refracted beam
will be much smaller than before.
Thus, this deviation away from
the perfect Bragg condition
has led to a dramatic weakening of
intensity in the diffracted beam.
In addition, the vectorial expression we
had before for perfect Bragg diffraction,
where kD = kI,
the incident wave vector, + g.
The diffraction vector no longer applies.
To solve this, we now introduce
another vector which we'll call sg.
By closing the loop,
we obtained kD = kI + g + sg.
Where essentially,
sg describes the deviation from
the perfect Bragg condition.
Cleaning these two diagrams up, here,
we have the schematic illustration for
scattering at the perfect Bragg condition,
where the Ewald sphere intersects
the center of the rail rod.
Thus, giving an intensity
in the diffracted beam,
which corresponds to the maximum
in this sync squared function as
demonstrated by this real experimental
diffraction pattern here.
Now turning away from that perfect Bragg
condition by a small amount delta theta,
the Ewald sphere wave from
the center of that peak,
resulting in a significant decrease in
the intensity of that defected beam.
Given the 1 over s squared envelope for
this intensity distribution,
for example, with a typical
thickness of 50 of 100 nanometers,
delta theta just needs to be
a fraction of a degree for
us to observe a significant reduction in
the intensity of this diffracted beam.
Finally, to describe this deviation
away from the perfect Bragg condition,
we introduce this new vector sg.
Where in this case, I define sg as being
parallel to the incident wave vector ki.
Further, sg is known under two
expressions, either the excitation or
deviation vector.
Having defined sg,
I now introduce a scalar quantity s.
So s equals the scalar quantity of sg.
This s is, again,
known under two different expressions.
One of them being the excitation error.
In other words, how much we are in error
of exciting a perfect Bragg condition or
alternatively, as the deviation parameter.
In other words, how far we are in
deviation of the perfect Bragg condition?
However, it should be known that while
some people refer to s has being
the deviation parameter.
In other works,
the deviation parameter can refer to
a quantity of s times phi g,
the extinction distance.
Being in reciprocal space, this excitation
error, s, is typically measured or
specified in inverse nanometers.
Obviously, for
the perfect Bragg condition, s = 0.
Away from the Bragg condition,
if s is within the Ewald sphere,
that is corresponding to a tilt of
the diffracting plane this way, and
then s is greater than 0.
And if s is outside the Ewald sphere,
then it's negative.
This time, instead corresponding to
a tilt of the diffracting plane,
this way relative to
the perfect Bragg condition.
Looking a bit more at the s
equals negative scenario, here,
I have a rather symmetrical illustration
where this would be the g vector for
the perfect Bragg condition.
Given that the diffracting plane has
been tilted away from the perfect Bragg
condition by an angle delta theta,
which gives an equivalent
total angle of this reciprocal
lattice vector ghkl.
It is clear from this that the small
angle of approximation, delta theta
= s divided by the modulus of ghkl.
Given that the modulus of ghkl simply
= 1 over the plane spacing dhkl.
We can see that the excitation error, s,
is given by delta theta divided by dhkl.
We know that in this s = negative case,
the diffracting plane was tilted this way
away from the perfect Bragg condition.
Therefore, for signs to correspond, in
this case, delta-theta must be negative.
Alternatively, tilting
the other way from the perfect
Bragg condition,
would give a positive delta-theta.
To summarize, in this lecture, we have
seen that the intensity distribution
along a reciprocal lattice rod modulates
within a 1 over s squared envelope.
The s is the excitation error or deviation
parameter when we're at the exact
Bragg condition, s = 0, and
we will have an intense diffracted beam.
However, when s is away from a 0,
the intensity in that diffracted
beam can decrease dramatically.
Further, we define that s is greater
than 0, when the vector sg lies
within the Ewald sphere, and it's less
than 0, when it's outside the eval sphere.
While all this may seem a bit abstract,
knowledge of the excitation error
is critical to certain kinds of
diffraction contrast imaging.
For instance, for imaging dislocations
in weak beam or strong beam conditions.
Finally, all this was studied in
what's called the kinematical regime,
meaning single electron scattering.
In reality, in a two beam condition,
we typically have what is called dynamical
scattering, this is multiple
elastic scattering.
In the dynamical case,
the more duration along the reciprocal
lattice rod will be the more different.
Indeed, you may not even have a maximum
intensity at s = 0, but at s away from 0.
However, the general principle that
the intensity in the diffracted beam
is directly related to the intersection
of the Ewald sphere with this intensity
distribution remains the same.
Thus, this kinematical
condition provides a useful
introduction to a concept needed for
understanding dynamical diffraction.