Welcome to CIME’s lecture on Transmission Electron Microscopy for Materials Science.
In the last few lectures on the basics of electron diffraction,
I have looked at the theoretical case
of two beam electron diffraction. As we saw, in this case,
we have one plane (hkl) which is inclined relative to
the incident electron beam, at the exact Bragg angle theta_B.
We have strong scattering from that plane, giving a diffraction pattern
which has two strong spots: one for the direct beam, the
000, and another for the diffracted beam, hkl.
However, if we look back at the video of electron diffraction
I showed in my first lecture, you will see in that video that there is
another case of diffraction where we have many different
diffraction spots – so scattering from many different beams –
also showing a high degree of symmetry. This is a so-called zone axis
diffraction pattern, and this is the case that I'm going to look at in this lecture.
As an example, we can look at two experimental diffraction patterns taken from
a single crystal of silicon. In this pattern,
I once again show the case of 2-beam electron diffraction,
here with the plane with Miller indices (hkl) of (220)
at the exact Bragg condition. So, we have strong
scattering into this diffraction spot, such that we have strongly
excited the diffraction vector g_220.
In this case, I have instead aligned the crystal such that its
[001] axis – that is its z axis – is aligned
exactly parallel to the incident electron beam. This
gives a so-called [001] zone access diffraction pattern.
We will now look at this case a bit more closely. So if we look at this pattern,
we can see that we have many different diffracted beams; so-called
multiple beam scattering. The crystal has been aligned on what
we call a low index lattice vector; effectively an important crystallographic direction.
For instance, if you have a cubic crystal, such as silicon, this could be
a direction such as [001], [110],
or [111]. This lattice vector will have these indices
[UVW], and we will call this the zone axis. So the
zone axis corresponds to the direction in the crystal which is aligned
parallel to the incident electron beam. In this case, we have
diffraction from planes in the crystal which are parallel to that incident
electron beam. So to the electron beam these planes look like they are end on,
with each plane giving a corresponding diffraction spot.
Multiple beams are excited at the same time. In this condition we obtain a diffraction
pattern which has lots of symmetry. So if we look at this pattern in particular, we can see
that we have a mirror plane here, a mirror plane here, another mirror plane
here, and a fourth mirror plane here. Instead looking at rotational
symmetry, we can see that there is 90 degree rotational symmetry
through the diffracted beams. So, we have fourfold
rotational symmetry: a tetrad. And we can observe that this mirror and rotational
symmetry corresponds to the rotational symmetry for the [001]
direction in the crystal. In other words, we have a diffraction pattern which has
the rotational and mirror symmetry of its corresponding lattice
vector in the real space crystal lattice. So why does such a
diffraction pattern form in this zone axis condition? To gain some
insight into the formation of this zone axis diffraction pattern, I'm going to
make a simple analogy, and say that in this zone axis condition our TEM optics
and sample are similar to the condition for a diffraction grating in
Fraunhofer far-field geometry. Here I have a representation
– an illustration – of this diffraction grating;
and we can see that we have an incident plane wave, with a wavelength Lambda,
being scattered by a regular array of slits, with each slit
having the spacing d. When this incident plane wave is
scattered by the grating, each slit acts as the source of a spherical wavelet
spreading out. We can represent that wavelet a ray scattered at different
angles, which here are called phi. Now what we can see is that, at certain angles
phi, parallel rays have a path difference which will correspond
to that for constructive interference. In other
words, this path difference here – which equals
d.sin(phi) – by corresponds to one, or multiples of,
a wavelength. In other words we have constructive interference when
d.sin(phi) equals n x lambda, where lambda is
the wavelength and n is an integer. If we now put a screen
sufficiently far from this diffraction grating, then we will be in
a far-field geometry where parallel rays come to a point, and
we will obtain a diffraction pattern. Where first of all we'll have a spot in the
center corresponding to beams that are scattered straight on:
the direct beam. But then, for sin(phi) =
lambda/d, we will obtain another diffraction spot; here. So with an angle of
scattering given by sin(phi) = lambda/d.
Then we'll have another spot here, for 2.lambda/d,
3.lambda/d, and so on; and their inverses the other
side. So you can see that this grating has given a diffraction
pattern of regularly spaced spots. As an exercise, you can
prove to yourself that, in the small angle approximation for this far-field geometry,
the angle of scattering between the diffraction spots is exactly the
same as you would obtain for Bragg diffraction in an electron diffraction pattern.
We should also note that this Fraunhofer far-field case is equivalent to the
back focal plane of the objective lens in TEM because, in both cases,
parallel rays come to a point. We shall now use this diffraction grating
approximation to help construct a zone axis diffraction pattern. For this
example, I'm going to take a very simple case of a primitive tetragonal
unit cell, such that there are no systematic absences in the reciprocal of
lattice.
And, we're going to take an alignment of this tetragonal unit cell of the electron beam
parallel to the lattice vector [001]. In other words,
parallel to the z axis of the unit cell. So here
I show an illustration of a 2 x 2 block of unit cells
in this orientation. Being tetragonal, we have a equals b.
So, we just have a simple square form. And now we're going
to look at the planes which are parallel to the incident electron beam – in other
words the electron beam will view them as end on planes – and take each plane in
turn, and say "that is like a diffraction grating" and we'll see which
diffraction spot it will make in our diffraction pattern.
So if we start off even without any object, of course we will always
have a central direct beam in the diffraction pattern;
the so-called 000. Now we consider diffraction from planes.
First of all I take this plane here. We can see that this plane is parallel to the y axis
and intersects the x axis at one unit cell parameter. So this is
clearly the (100) plane. Like a diffraction grating, it will make a
diffraction spot in our diffraction pattern perpendicular to that
plane; and with a spacing which will be the reciprocal
of the plane spacing d. So we get a
diffraction spot looking like this. Now we move on;
consider another plane. We can see that this plane is instead parallel to the x axis,
and intersects the y axis at one unit cell spacing. So this is clearly the
(010) plane. This plane has exactly the
same spacing as the (100), but it's perpendicular to it. So it will give a
diffraction spot over here, with the same spacing as the (100), but at an angle
of 90 degrees. Now we move on, and consider this plane. We can see that this plane
intersects the x and y axes at 1 unit cell spacing. So this is going to be
the (110) plane. Its spacing is 1/SQRT(2)
of the spacing of the (100) plane, or the (010) plane.
So it's going to give a reciprocal lattice spacing which is SQRT(2) x larger than this spacing here.
Also it's at this angle here;
it's going to give a spot, then, in this direction. So it's going to give a spot
over here: the spot for (110) plane. Moving on, I
consider this plane. We can see that this plane is parallel to the (100), but
it intersects the x axis at half a unit cell spacing. So it's going to
be the (200) plane. Being parallel to the (100), it's going to
give a spot in this direction. But, having half the plane spacing of the (100),
the scattering angle will be two times that of the (100), so it gives us here
– the (200). Moving on, I put on this plane here.
It intersects at half a on the x and y axes, so is clearly the (220) plane.
Being the 2 2 0, it's going to give a spot parallel to the (110).
But having half the plane spacing, is going to have double the scattering angle,
so it will give a spot over here. And we can keep on going. Here I put on the
(300) plane, which of course is parallel to the (100),
so will give a spot in the same direction, but with three times the scattering angle,
so giving a spot here. And we can keep on going, and as we
do this, we build up this diffraction pattern which, by symmetry,
includes inverse planes such as the (–100) and
(0–10). And we can notice a number of things about this. One thing: we can see
that it looks like a section through our reciprocal lattice, which
indeed it is. Secondly, we have associated each diffraction spot
with the Miller indices (hkl) of the plane that's created it.
This is called "indexing the diffraction pattern". The third thing I will
point out is that here we have our electron beam parallel to [001];
so [001] is our so-called "zone axis". And we can note that all
these planes – being parallel to the zone axis – obey
the Weiss zone law:
hU + kV + lW = 0
- the rule which applies for plane (hkl) being parallel to a lattice
vector [UVW]. Now we have looked at the formation of the zone axis
diffraction pattern by the simple analogy of the crystal as a diffraction grating,
we should instead look at the diffraction pattern formation by the Ewald
sphere/reciprocal lattice representation. So that's what I have done here.
Here we have the Ewald sphere, and the vector for the incident
beam k_I. And, when we have this geometry, what
we see is that one layer of this reciprocal
lattice is now tangential to the Ewald sphere.
And what's more is that, when we have this geometry, we see
that the Ewald sphere actually does not intersect any of the reciprocal lattice
nodes in this layer directly around the 000 beam.
In other words, the Bragg condition is not met. Now this is the exaggerated
Ewald sphere representation that I showed before. We can make it a realistic
representation; as follows. So here, now the
curvature of the Ewald sphere corresponds to what we would see for a 200 kV
beam, and a reciprocal lattice for body centred cubic iron. But
even in this case we can see that, even with this very flat Ewald sphere,
the surface of that sphere does not intersect most of these reciprocal
lattice nodes. In other words, the Bragg condition of scattering
for these reciprocal lattice nodes is not met. And if the Bragg condition is
not met, theoretically there should be no scattering from these planes,
and we should not have all these diffracted beams that we in fact see. Because
experimentally, we know we have strong scattering from many planes in this zone
axis condition. So, we have some problem in our
representation using the Ewald sphere and reciprocal lattice, for the
zone axis condition. To summarize,
when the electron beam is parallel to some important crystallographic direction,
or so-called low index zone axis [UVW], we obtain a zone axis
diffraction pattern which has multiple scattering in many different beams.
This pattern can display high symmetry, with mirror and rotational symmetries
which correspond to that of the real crystal lattice.
Further, in this condition, we had diffraction from planes
which are parallel to the incident beam, and so parallel to the zone axis
[UVW}. And because of this, the Weiss zone law is met. So
all of the planes directly around the direct beam obey the Weiss zone law,
where for the plane (hkl): hU + kV + lW = 0
On the other hand, when we represent this condition using our
Ewald sphere/reciprocal lattice representation, we find that the Bragg
scattering condition is not met.
Clearly there is a problem in our representation. The problem in our representation is
because, while the recipient lattice nodes so far have been represented as
infinitely small points, in fact they have a size and a shape – and the size and
shape leads to a relaxation of the bragg scattering condition, and
we obtain multiple beam scattering in our schematic diagram.
And this is what we will look at in the next lecture.