If you look in their literature on dynamical scattering,
you are likely to meet a variety of notations that are used to express
scattering intensities and their equations.
In this addendum, I described some of these notations.
In order to clarify and strengthen the connection of these lectures
to references that you may read or study.
Looking at it further at this expression for the intensity
in the diffracted beam, always bearing in mind that the intensity
in the direct beam equals one minus the intensity in the diffracted beam.
In different references, you’ll see that this expression is rearranged
in different ways depending on the needs or purposes of the authors.
For instance in some works, a parameter is introduced
corresponding to Psy G times S
Since psy G has units in real space and S had units in reciprocal space
This parameter is dimensionless and is often called
W as for instance by Hawaiian wheelin.
Note that when it’s introduced some authors call this the
deviation parameter while other authors actually use this
same expression deviation parameter for S
which I've been calling the excitation error.
Having introduced W, this equation can be expressed as follows
IG the intensity in the diffracted beam
equals one over one plus W squared times sine squared
of PI T over psy G times root of one plus W squared.
Sometimes, an additional dimensionless parameter called beta is introduced
where beta is defined as follows cot beta
that is cos beta divided by sine beta equals W.
once this is done you can show that
one over one plus W squared equals sine squared of beta.
Thus this expression now becomes
IG equals sine squared beta times sine squared of PI T
over psy G  times the square root of one plus W squared
In other works, yet another parameter is introduced
which we call the effective excitation error or S prime
where S prime equals the square root of the sum of 1/psy G squared
plus s squared. Once this effect of excitation error is introduced
this equation can now be expressed as follows;
IG equals PI T divided by psy G squared
times sine squared of PI T S prime divided by the square of PI T s prime
Expressing it this way emphasizes the sine X over X all squared
type of function now related to thickness and S Prime
in other words sinh squared PI T S prime
Finally we can substitute S prime into the last expression
from the previous slide giving the overall compact expression
IG equals sine squared of beta times sine squared of PI T S prime.
Well we have all these different ways of expressing diffracted beam intensity
In these lectures I’m going to mainly stick to this expression here
because it shows in a rather clear way the effects of thickness
and S on the intensity of the diffracted beam