Welcome CIME's lectures on Transmission Electron Microscopy for Material Science
in the last lecture I introduced a dynamical scattering. That is the
multiple elastic scattering that can occur as a beam propagates across the thickness
of a 10 sample. I further showed how this effect
leads to a strong interaction between the direct beam and different diffracted beams.
That in the two case can be conceived of as the diffraction and re
diffraction of a propagating beam. In this lecture I'm going to
demonstrate one of the most evident effects of dynamical scattering in tame
imaging namely the formation of thickness fringes that is
patterns of bright and dark fringes that can be seen in images
of crystalline objects of varying thickness. We're going to consider the
formation of these thickness fringes in the case of a two beam scattering condition
as shown in the last lecture. The intensity in the defective beam IG
is given by this expression here in the tubing case where S is
the excitation area that is the deviation from the perfect bragg condition
t is the sample thickness and size G is the
extinction distance given by this formula here where V0
is the volume of the NASL feet b is the bragg angle for scattering
lambda is the wavelength and F G is the structure factor for the
diffracted beam of interest further. Sometimes this part of
the expression the root of one over size G squared plus S squared is referred to as s
prime. The effective excitation error this expression refers to an
incident intensity of 1. So since we're in a TVM condition and all the
intensity must either be in the direct beam I0 or the diffracted beam
IG clearly the intensity in the direct beam is given by one minus
IG. Now if we consider the case where we're at the exact bragg
condition then the excitation error s equals zero for this
Ezekial zero case. You can easily see that IGY simplifies to sign
squared of PI T divided by size
G.
Further since the intensity in the direct beam equals one minus IGY
then that intensity is given by zero equals cause squared of PI
T divided by side G If we plot these two
intensities against Thickness. It is clear that both of them would relate sinusoidal  with
thickness as shown on these curves. Here where the black curve refers to
the intensity in the direct beam and the blue curve. The intensity in the diffracted beam
further we can see that their modulations are an anti phase with each other.
Looking further the black curve is zero. The intensity in the direct beam we can see that
when the something has no thickness obviously this intensity is at a maximum because they can be no
scattering. However as sample thickness increases this intensity
decreases until when the sample thickness equal size G divided by 2.
The intensity goes to zero equally at that thickness.
The intensity in the diffracted beam is at a maximum
looking now. This blue curve for the intensity and the diffracted beam. This in
turn decreases to zero where the thickness equals one size
G and then to side G and so on. Thus when thicknes
T equals an integer number of extinction distances
then the intensity in the diffracted beam equal zero. For this exact
bragg condition situation and that's why g is called the extinction distance
because when T equals size G the intensity in this reflection G is
extinguished.
What would be nice is if we could measure these intensity more dilations experimentally
and in the next light hour show how that can be done with simple bright field and dark field imaging
to demonstrate these intensity modulations with thickness. I use a sample of
silicon with a basic zone axis of 0 0 1
here's the diffraction pattern on that zone access which can be indexed as follows
in the center.
The Direct being 0 0 0 surrounded by some 2 2 0
toper reflections is further out 4 0 0 type reflections
the sample is a so-called cleaved wedge. That is it has been made by
cleaving the silicon on one or one type planes. Thus
if we look in cross-section the sample has a form like this. Here we have the
0 0 1 axis and this is solid material bound
by these one or one type planes. We look at the sample in projection with the
electron beam traversing it as follows. Clearly
as we move away from the vacuum edge of the sample the thickness and
projection increases
further if we go the distance from the edge X
then with this geometry the thickness is given by the simple
formula T equals 2 times x. I have
tilted the sample such that this two to zero reflection is that the exact bracket
condition giving this to diffraction pattern. Here where here is the direct beam.
And this is G220.
Tilting in this way is known as exciting the reflection
I have then inserted an object of aperture in order to select just the
direct beam and cut out the diffracted beam here. When we do
this effectively we specially map the intensity in this direct
beam making this bright  field image here.
In this image here is the vacuum. And then here is the edge of the sample. So
X measures this way here. And as we've seen as
x increases so does the thickness of the sample and clearly
with increasing thickness we see a pattern of bright and dark fringes
as predicted by the formula for the intensity in the direct beam.
I have then displaced the object of aperture in order to select the diffracted beam.
So now we make a dark food image where we spatially map the intensity
IG in that diffracted beam
similarly to the bright field image. We again see a pattern of bright and dark fringes
but as predicted these fringes are an anti phase with those
in the bright field image. So this is the edge of the sample is X
and we can see that in the vacuum of course it's dark because there is no diffraction.
And then at a certain thickness when the bright field image is dark
dark the image is bright on this light. I take this Bright field and
Dark field image pair and pull out the intensity profiles with respect
to thickness. So looking at the bright image we can see that the intensity profile is bright
he descends to being dark and then it's bright and dark. And
so I've taken this profile and plotted it against
thicknesse T where I've simply said that T equals to X as
previously discussed with X being that distance from the edge of the sample
I have done the same thing for the dark field image taking its intensity profile
and plotted these two profiles on this curve here where on
the gray curve I showed the intensity and the direct beam and then the red
curve I show you the intensity in the diffracted being the intensity
of both these curves has been normalized to the intensity in the vacuum in the
bright field image. As predicted these curves are shown
sinusoidal modulations in anti-faith with each other. And if we look we can
see that the extinction distance size G is
approximately to 80 nanometers. We now take
this plot and compare it to the theoretical model from before.
That's what we do on this slide where here I show you that experimental data put intensity in the direct
beam and the intensity in the diffract beam in gray and red
respectively compared to that simple model for the intensities
discussed earlier where in the black we have the intensity on in the direct beam and
the blue curve the intensity and the diffracted being as predicted by the models
we have those sinusoidal modulations and anti-faith with each other. However in the
experimental data the maximum intensity DKs
with thickness further the minimum intensity increases a bit with thickness.
The reason this is not seen in the model is because this simple model did not account for
absorption effects.
However as sample thickness increases as well as there being more dynamical scattering
There is also absorption of the transmitted electrons and it is
because of this we see these changes in maximum and minimum intensity as thickness
increases. To demonstrate that here
I have changed the model to account for absorption in a rather simple
way. Specifically I have introduced imaginary parts of the
extinction coefficient both for the direct beam and the defective
beam where for the direct beam I have introduced an
imaginary part of extinction distance size zero prime equal to
ten times Size G and I have given the diffracted
beam an imaginary coefficient size G prime equal to
15 times size G. Once I have accounted for absorption
in this rather simple way we can see that the model is strikingly
similar to the real experimental data.
These bright and dark fringes are typically known as thickness fringes though they're
also sometimes called extinction controls so far. We
have looked at the case of the exact bragg condition when s equals zero.
And the diffracted beam is strongly excited. However we can ask what
happens when we change the value of s. In this case where we
make s greater than zero. Looking at the diffraction pattern from the
general region of interest we can see the intensity in that defective beam has
decreased compared to the Ezekial zero case
because we are no longer at the exact bracket condition.
If we consider this quantity here sometimes known as S prime or the effective
excitation era and clearly when S is greater than zero
this quantity is larger than when s equals zero. Thus
the intensity in the defective beam will be extinguished and smaller thickness variations
than the equal zero case and that's exactly what we see here. And this dark food
image made from g with s greater than zero.
Compared to the Ezekial zero case it is clear that the
separation between these thickness fringes has decreased
indeed. Whereas before we had extinction of the defective beam
for a thickness of about 80 nanometers. Now we have extinction
for a thickness of just 45 nanometers. In this case I have increased the
excitation area S such that S Square it is about the same order of magnitude
as one of her side G squared. But we can ask what happens if I
make S squared much larger than size G squared. That's what we discuss on the
next slide we can see that if we can deviate
sufficiently from the perfect bragg condition we can make S squared
much larger than one over side squared.
In this case. One of us IDs square plus Esquire it is simply
approximately equal to s squared. Thus the intensity in the defective
beam becomes proportional to sin squared of Pie
TS
this condition is known as a weak beam imaging condition
one that is often used for analysis of defects such as dislocations
on this slide. I have set up such a weak beam imaging condition. Indeed in this case
what's known as a GI 3-G condition on the diffraction
pattern here is my reflection G. However what I have done
is instead of putting G at exact bragg condition, I have put
3G here at the exact bragg condition. If we consider the
ewald sphere construction with the reciprocal lattice is a direct beam
is 3G the ewald sphere in the sense that 3-G.
Exactly. Now if our mark in the G and also the 2G
we can see that reflection G has a large and positive excitation era
s here. Making this week being conditioned we're S squired
is much larger than one over side G squired.
experimental case s is approximately equal to
0.075 nanometers to the minus one. Now looking
at the dark food image made from that reflection G
we can see that compared to before. There is an extremely dense frequency
of bright and dark thickness fringes pulling out an intensely profile
with respect to the thickness we can see that here we have
very frequent dark fringes that spacing of about one every
13 nanometers where that distance corresponds
to one divided by S. This intentionally large excitation
error as well as being a function of the excitation error S, If we consider the
formula for the extinction distance here we can see that thickness fringe frequency
will also be a function of FG the structure factor for the reflection
such that side G will be proportional to one over FG.
This is a case that I illustrate on this light using a sample of a cleaved wedge
not now Silicon but of aluminum gallium arsenide or gas
as it is sometimes known where the aluminum and gallium irons can substitute for
each other on the same atomic sites. The sample
again has a basic zone axis of 0 0 1
and I have excited this two to zero reflection here.
Given this tubing pattern here and then
made a dot for the image from that excited reflection.
On the left of this dark food image we have thicknesse fringes in the
substrate where the substrate has a composition of about
25 percent aluminum and 75 percent gallium on these
shared atomic sites. On this
substrate quantum wells have been deposited which are perfectly
hypotassium. However they have a different composition in
these quantum wells. We instead have a composition of about 80 percent
aluminum and 20 percent gallium on the shared
sites. If we look closely at the thickness fringes in the quantum
worlds we can see the fringe separation as larger than the
fringe separation in the substrate. In other words the quantum
worlds have a larger extinction distance than the substrate.
This is reasonable because aluminum scatters less than gallium. So it
has a small atomic scattering factor than gallium does as the percentage of aluminum
increases the atomic structure factor from this shed's site
decreases decreasing the structure factor for that reflection and
increasing the extinction distance. Another thing you might notice is
that the onset for the thickness fringes is further away from the edge of the
sample and the quantum wells than in the substrate that's due to another
effect. These quantum Wells oxidized badly. Thus the
first part of the thickness is amorphous oxidized material
and doesn't count to the crystalline dynamical diffraction scattering
effect needed to make the thickness fringes. This cleat which sample geometry which
I've used to illustrate thickness fringes is little use in regular tame
analyses. Thus in a way these illustrations have been rather academic.
However thickness fringes will regularly be observed in regular tame
imaging here I sure bright field image of barium
Titanite nanocrystals the crystals are randomly orientated with
respect to the electron beam. We can see that some of the crystals have rather low
contrast these crystals must be in a weak
scattering condition far away from a low index zone axis. However we
have other particles which are darker showing a strong diffraction contrast.
The particles have varying thickness and being in a strong diffraction condition
they have increased dynamical scattering and we can see that as the thickness
changes away from the edge we see thickness fringes here
and this particle here on this edge here on this edge here
this illustrates how you may well see thickness fringes from dynamical
scattering and regular teme data of for
instance such randomly oriented nanoparticles or maybe narrow roads or
other crystalline objects of strongly varying thickness
to sunrise in a tubing condition. I have measured the intensity and the direct
beam zero and intensity in the defective beam I G using
Bright field and dark field imaging are the perfect bragg condition
with Ezekial zero. We see that zero G
model 8 sinusoidal G and are in anti-faith with each other with increasing
thickness giving bright field and dark food images such as
these where these patterns are bright and dark fringes are known as thickness fringes
or extinction contours we further see that when
we pull out the intensity profiles of zero and IG on these wedge
shaped samples and the profile matches very nicely a model which accounts for some
absorption effects. I have gone on to show that if we increase
S then the frequency of these thickness fringes increases
in keeping with theory. Finally with an example of barium Titanite nanocrystals
I have shown how such thickness fringes are often observed in regular term data.
When your image samples of strongly varying thickness in the next
lecture I'm going to continue on this theme of dynamic and effects and time imaging this
time looking at what happens when our crystalline sample is deformed or
bent giving rise to the appearance of bend controls and
bright field and dark field images.