Welcome to CIME’s lectures on Transmission Electron Microscopy for Materials Science and the
first of my lectures on dynamical scattering so far in this course
we have considered electron refraction through the framework of the ewald sphere interacting
with the reciprocal lattice. This framework is very successful for identifying which
planes to diffract under certain conditions of the orientation of the
incident electron beam relative to that of the crystal lattice. It is further
very successful for identifying the position of each diffraction spot
in a diffraction pattern. If electron scattering was
kinematical In other words if we had a single scattering such
that a beam was diffracted at most one time as it transmits through the sample.
Additionally the intensity of diffract a beam would be proportional to
FHKL square, that is proportional to the square of the structure
factor of the corresponding deflecting plane.
Indeed an x ray diffraction. This is typically the case
this is because in x ray diffraction the interaction of an x ray with the crystal lattice is rather
weak therefore the probability of having two consecutive scattering events is very
small. In contrast in electron diffraction the interaction
of the electron beam with the sample is very strong. This is because the transmitting
electrons are charged particles and they are scattered by the Coolum field of the atoms
in the crystal lattice because of this strong interaction. Typically we have what
is called dynamical scattering. This means a strong
multiple elastic scattering of the electron beam as it transmits through
the sample. Essentially the electron beam is re-diffracted
in a multi beam ozone access diffraction pattern. This has an important consequence
because a refracted beam can be read refracted into other beam.
As a result the different diffracted beams interact with each other and so
their intensities are interdependent and we lose the kinematical
relationship of diffracted intensity to the structure factor.
Therefore unlike for X-ray diffraction the intensities in the election
diffraction pattern are typically not readily interpretable in
this lecture. We're going to look at this dynamical scattering to simplify
matters. We will study it with the idealized case of to be an electron diffraction and
look at the consequences of dynamical scattering on the intensities of both the diffracted beam
and the direct beam. We're first going to look at this dynamical scattering where the
simplified radiogram are being, being scattered by a plane diffracted at the
bragg angle as this beam transmits across the sample.
Now we know for this to be diffraction geometry and the diffraction pattern
we should see two spots one for the direct beam the 0 0 0 and
for G would diffracting beam, if we
put in an incident rate here which was scatter from this black plane. So this
ray is at the bragg angle 0B
relative to that plane. It is clear if we're high up
in the sample. So we had a very very thin sample then the
amount of scattering would be very small. Thus if we looked at the
diffraction pattern the 0 0 0 spot would
be very intense. And in contrast the spot for the
diffracted beam would be very weak in intensity as the sovereign
becomes thicker. There will be more and more scattering into the refracting beam
in the diffraction pattern. This leads to a redistribution of intensity
from the direct beam spot to the diffracted beams spot which in turn now
becomes much more intense. However if we look at ray diagram
we can see that this ray for the defective beam is at the perfect bragg angle
to be scattered from this plane here. When it does this
it will be scattered at the bragg angle and will end up in a re
parallel to that of the incident beam. Now as the sample
gets thicker the probability of this double scattering event will increase. Thus if we looked at
this thickness we would again see a redistribution of intensity.
Now from the Beam G back end to the direct beam
Zero and so the direct beam
becomes very strong and the refracting beam becomes very weak.
As the beams continue to propagate across the sample we can see that this
beam is again the perfect bragg angle and so can be
redirected yet another time. Giving another way which is
parallel to the ray for the distracting beam G. Thus
as the sample becomes thicker yet again we can have a redistribution of
intensity from that direct beam back into the
refracting beam and this scenario can
continue as the electron beam propagates across the sampled
following the simple schematic for the fraction followed by re-diffraction fraction.
We can imagine that there will be a certain thickness at which the diffraction
beam here will have zero intensity and all of the intensity will be back in the direct
beam. Indeed we will see that this thickness corresponds to
sage G
When I sage G is the extinction distance for this particular defecting plane
considering an amplitude of the incident electron beam on the sample equal to
1 in this case of two beams scattering
under dynamical conditions that has been the rise that the
amplitudes of the resulting direct beam and refracting beam leaving
the sample are given by these expressions here.
Well first we have the amplitude of the direct beam
and then we have the amplitude of the deflected beam
in these expressions.
I is simply the imaginary number T is the
specimen thickness and S is the excitation error that was
introduced in the last lecture on deviation from the bragge condition.
Finally we have this parameter sage G. Where sage G is the extinction distance for the
reflection where V0 is the volume of
the unit so 0 B is the bragg angle
lambda is the wavelength of the electron and
FG is the structure factor for the defrocking plane. I know that in the
idealized case where there is no absorption of the electron beam in the sample
then F G is a real number.
However if you want to treat absorption this can be modeled by introducing an
imaginary component into F G and also into f 0. The
structure factor for the 0 0 0. These expressions given here have been derived by a
number of different ways. In the literature perhaps the most popular of those ways
is the block wave theory as first proposed by beater
this block wave approach involves finding the solution of the Schrödinger equation for
an electron wave moving in the periodic potential of the crystal lattice.
The solution results in wave functions known as block waves.
These block waves or plane waves which propagate across the sample
parallel to the diffraction Crystal plane and they have amplitudes which are motivated
by the periodic lattice potential unlike the so-called Howi wheel and
equations the block wave approach is fully scaleable to many beams.
So for M defecting beams there are M block waves.
Each of these block waves has m components one for each of the resulting deflecting
beam. Thus in the two in case there are two block waves.
Now if we consider an incident electron beam at the
bragg angle relative to this crystal plane so far we have only considered
one diffraction wave vector. However in the block wave approach we now
consider that there are two block waves which propagate across the sample and each
block wave has a way vector component corresponding to the direct beam.
And that affected beam this here for instance we have the wave vector
components from block wave one.
So here's the component from Brockway one for the direct beam
and here the defrocking bean.
And then we also draw on corresponding wave vectors for the second block wave.
Which again have components for the direct beam
and for the distracting beam so after the block waves
have propagated across the sample the components for the direct beam would add up to give
the direct beam amplitude and the components for that refracting being would add up to give the amplitude of
the distracting beam following Hashimoto.
These block waves can be schematically illustrated as follows. So here is block wave 1
and here is block wave 2. In this
illustration we're looking at a simple cubic lattice with these being the bragge
reflecting planes.
As explained in the last slide each of these block waves has components
corresponding to the direct and diffracted beams
with this curve representing the amplitude of block wave one we can see that this
amplitude is centered in between the atomic planes.
In contrast the amplitude of block wave 2 is centered on the atomic
planes as a result of being centered on the atomic
nuclei. This block wave 2 experience has a stronger negative
potential as it propagates through the crystal lattice the stronger
potential accelerates as block wave to more. Compared to block wave 1
decreasing its wavelength or equally increasing its wave
vector relative to block wave 1 as a result of phase difference
develops between block wave 1 and block wave 2 as they propagate across the crystal
lattice a result of this phase difference is that there is a beating between the two block waves
as they propagate across the crystal lattice. And it is this beating that gives result to the
thickness dependence in the signed term of the amplitude of the resulting
deflecting beam in the case where we assume that there is no
absorption when the excitation area s equals zero. In other words we're in the
exact Bragg condition than the amplitudes of the two block waves are identical.
However if we leave this perfect Bragg condition by tilting slightly away from it
creating either a positive or negative excitation error then the amplitude of the
two block waves cease to be equal. And this gives rise to the averages of the
resulting direct and interacting beams being also in function of the excitation area
S finally considering absorption
the block wave to being centered on the atomic nuclei is
absorbed more strongly than the block wave one. And this gives rise to so-called
anomalous absorption effects in the intensities of the diffracted and direct
beam. It also connects to channeling effects which you might come
across in chemical analysis returning to these
expressions for the amplitudes of the direct beam and the diffracted beam.
We can easily determine the intensity of the diffracted beam by calculating the
square of the modalists of sage G. Since
this term here is a phase term.
It just contributes a factor of 1 to the intensity and then the intensity of the refracted
beam is simply going to be
1/1 + G2S2 X  sin2? T v(1/(G )  )2  + S2
So we have some science squared modulation in function or both thickness and the
excitation error s. If you also calculate the intensity
of the direct beam which can simply be
done by multiplying this term here by complex conjugate
you find that this intensity equals 1 minus
IG. In other words we have conservation of intensity with the incident
amplitude of one the incidence intensity is one and this intensity is
conserved into the two beams such that they are complementary to each
other having in the last lecture looked at the kinematical case
or the intensity of a defective beam as a function of the
excitation era as we're now going to use this expression to look at that
intensity in the dynamical case. So here this intensity has been
modeled using an extinction distance of 100 nanometers for
various specimen thicknesses. T looking first of this curve
for fatigue was 150 nanometers. We can see that there are oscillations in
intensity inside an envelope where now this envelope
corresponds to 1 over 1 plus sage
G squared X squired, and otherwise this envelope does not
depend on thickness it only depends on the excitation era and the
extinction distance what does depend on thickness is the
frequency of these modulations. We can see as we go through a thicker sample
the moderations go to smaller excitation areas. S
similarly to the kinematical case when as equals zero we
can see that the intensity and the defective beam is simply given by IGY equals
sin squared of Pi t over
sage G. And these posts here I have specifically chosen
thicknesses are the thickness T equals
Sage G times 2 and plus 1 divided by 2 n where n is an
integer. Because in this case when s equals zero the intensity in the
diffract beam equals 1 that we see here and here.
However we can ask ourselves what happens when we deviate from this nice condition.
That's what I've done on this slide here I've kept the T 150 nanometers curve.
Whereas here I plotted the curve with for T equals 220 nanometers.
Now we can see there's a marked effect on the intensity as equal zero
intensity is no longer a maximum. Indeed there is a dip in intensity
as equals zero. Now what will happen if we reduce
T further to 200 nanometers when T will become an integer
multiple of the extinction distance. We look at that on this light. Now we
have T equals n times sage G where n is an integer. In this
case when s equals zero here we now take the sign square of pi
times n which will be 0.
Therefore the intensity in the deflecting beam is zero. Indeed looking at this
T because 200 nanometers curve we can see that that S equals
zero. There is no intensity in the diffracted beam. So all the
intensity would now be in the direct beam with zero in the diffracted beam. For
this thickness at the exact bragg condition. To summarize on this
lecture I have introduced dynamical scattering as being the multiple elastic scattering of
the electron beam as it transmits through the sample in transmission
electron microscopy. This is the typical case because the interactions of the electron beam with
the sample are very strong. In the tubing condition this
can be interpreted in a rather simple way as a diffraction and then read or fraction
of an electron beam as it propagates across the sample. And depending on the number of
diffraction events there is a moderation in the intensity of the diffracted and
direct beams as a result of this further we have looked at the full expressions for the
intensity of the direct and diffracted beings which are a simple function of the
specimen thickness t the excitation area s and the extinction distance
sage G. And then we have looked to the consequence of these expressions
on these curves of intensity versus excitation
era. I know that in the literature these curves are often referred to as
rooking curves. This expression comes from a
technique known as rooking electron diffraction where the incident electron
beam is tilted or rocked from side to side.
And as it changes an angle relative to the sample you're able to measure the
intensity of a beam at different excitation areas as having
introduced dynamical scattering in this lecture. And the next lecture we're going to look at another
dynamical effect in imaging mode in the formation of thickness fringes and
Bright field and dark field images.