Welcome to Seemings lectures on transmission electron microscopy for material science.
In the last two lectures,
we have looked at two effects of dynamical scattering on
the contrast scene and Bright-field and Dark-field imaging of crystalline samples,
what might be known as diffraction contrast imaging effects.
In this lecture, we're instead going to look at an effect of
dynamical scattering on diffraction pattern formation,
with a particular case known as double diffraction,
where the multiple elastic scattering of
the beam as it propagates across the sample leads to
the formation of diffraction spots for crystal planes which are kinematically forbidden.
We should look at double diffraction in what is probably
the most common and hence best known case,
that are silicon aligned on a one one zero zone axis.
Silicon has the diamond structure and for this structure,
if you consider the family of zero zero two planes,
they have a structure factor say F zero zero two, which equals zero.
In other words, if scattering was kinematical,
such planes would not be visible at diffraction spots in a diffraction pattern.
They are also known as forbidden planes
whose diffraction spots are systematic absences.
So, if we made a kinematic simulation of
diffraction pattern of silicon on this one one zero zone axis,
it would look like this;
where by applying the vice zonal HU plus KV plus LW equals zero,
we could index the diffraction pattern as follows.
In the center, we of course have the direct beam
zero zero zero and it's surrounded by four one one one type planes,
which we could for instance index as one bar one one here.
One bar one bar one here.
Bar one one bar one here.
And finally, bar one one one here.
Looking at this plane here,
we can see that by adding these two diffraction vectors,
it corresponds to an index of two bar two zero.
And therefore this one here is,
bar two two zero.
And then looking along this axis we see a spot
here which corresponds to the zero zero four plane.
And then the zero zero bar four here.
What's noticeable is that there's no diffraction spot here for the zero zero two,
or here for the zero zero bar two,
because they are systematic absences,
they are kinematically forbidden.
Whereas this simulation is kinematical,
we know that experimentally,
when on a zone axis we have
strong dynamical scattering as the case for this real diffraction pattern here.
Comparing this experimental case to the simulation,
one thing stands out,
that in the experimental case we see intensity for these two forbidden planes.
So we have a diffraction spot for the zero zero three and the zero zero bar two.
We will now look at why that is.
We know that dynamical scattering
can lead to diffraction followed by re-diffraction of a beam.
This can lead to addition of diffraction vectors,
G vectors, as one beam scatters into another beam.
We can see that as follows,
if we look at our simulation we have a diffraction vector G one bar one one
here and here we have G bar one one.
Dynamically, we can have
scattering on this G vector followed by scattering on this G vector.
In other words, the diffracted beam for this G vector acts as
the direct beam for a subsequent scattering event.
When this happens, we can add this diffraction vector to this diffraction vector,
giving a diffraction spot here in the zero zero two plain location.
Equally, we could have scattering to this reflection here,
followed by scattering to that reflection there,
giving a spot in a zero zero bar two location.
This is known as double diffraction and can be
interpreted in terms of the addition of diffraction vectors.
In this case, we have G bar one one one,
plus G one bar one one,
which equals zero zero two.
This dynamical scattering effect is so strong,
that for a typical high tension of two or three hundred kilovolts,
you would need a sample just a few nanometers thick to avoid having
intensity at these systematic absences.
We're now going to consider in more detail,
the formation mechanism for this double diffraction effect
by looking at it within the Ewald sphere reciprocal lattice framework.
Here we have a schematic illustration of the reciprocal lattice of
silicon on this one one zero zone axis looking in a pseudo three dimensional projection.
These lines represent the elongated form of the reciprocal lattice rods.
Because we are aligned on the zone axis,
this zero order Laue zone,
is perpendicular to the incident electron beam.
Therefore, we can draw the wave vector for that incident beam like this.
Associated with this incident beam is of course the Ewald sphere,
which will intersect these different reciprocal lattice rods.
To represent this intersection,
I will draw arcs which correspond to different circumferences on the Ewald sphere,
intersecting different pairs of reflections.
So one here, here, and here.
So giving a diagram that looks like this.
Because these planes are parallel to the incident electron beam,
the Ewald sphere does not intersect at the center of the reciprocal lattice rods
but instead at a negative excitation error.
Therefore, if we consider this one bar one one plane here,
the Ewald sphere intersects somewhere there.
Thus considering that for this illustration,
the center of the Ewald sphere is somewhere above the slide;
the diffracted beam wave vector for this plane,
and coming down as follows,
giving a figure like this.
In double diffraction, this diffracted beam wave vector KD,
now acts as the direct beam for subsequent scattering events.
To represent this, we first center
a new reciprocal lattice at the end of this wave vector here.
So it's zero zero zero here.
Over here, we will have a reciprocal lattice node
for a zero zero four plane and the zero zero bar four here,
and then the one one one plane's here,
in line with the original zero zero zero;
somewhere here,
here, and here,
giving an illustration that looks like this.
As well as marking in a new reciprocal lattice,
we also have to mark in a new Ewald sphere,
associated with this wave vector here.
Because this wave vector is inclined related to the incident electron beam,
this Ewald sphere will be tilted compared to the original Ewald sphere.
I now draw in arcs for the intersection of
this new Ewald sphere with its reciprocal lattice,
giving a final diagram which looks like this.
We can see that in the projected electron diffraction pattern,
the intersection of this new Ewald sphere with this reciprocal lattice road here,
will give a diffraction spot in the zero zero two plane location.
Equally, if we consider re-diffraction from this bar one bar one plane here,
we would end up with a reciprocal lattice road here,
corresponding to the zero zero bar two plane location
in the electron diffraction pattern.
We can think of this as a convolution of the reciprocal lattice with itself.
So here, this new reciprocal lattice was convoluted with
a reciprocal lattice node of the original reciprocal lattice.
However, it must be noted,
that in reciprocal space,
this new reciprocal lattice is at
a negative excitation error compared to the original reciprocal lattice.
In other words, it's higher up.
We're now going to look at a way that we can experimentally
prove that the diffraction spots for
these forbidden planes are the result of dynamical scattering.
If you look at the diffraction pattern,
we know that each spot is associated with a plane which
is perpendicular to its diffraction vector.
So for this spot here,
we could mark in a plane like this,
and for this one here, a plane here,
and then planes for this spot here.
And then this one here, and
this plane here, and another here.
And you could continue for all the different spots in the diffraction pattern.
Now we know in the zone access geometry in the zero or the Laue zone,
all these planes are parallel to the incident electron beam.
Then what we're going to do is tilt the sample on
this axis here as follows.
If we look down that tilt axis at the zero,
the Laue zone, we will see something like this.
Where this is looking down the tilt axis where we would
see reciprocal latticed rods both for the 000,
but also these other planes here.
And these are reciprocal lattice rods for planes out here or out here.
Being in zone access orientation,
the ethosphere is tangential with the zero or the Laue zone,
so when intersect, the reciprocal lattice rods as follows.
When we now tilt around this axis,
we even tilt this zero or the Laue zone around this point here as follows.
We can see that if we tilt far enough,
the ethosphere no longer intersects the reciprocal lattice rods of these planes.
However, the ethosphere does still intersect the planes on the axis of rotation.
That's because these planes remain parallel to the incident electron beam.
Doing this is called exciting a systematic row.
That's because in the diffraction pattern,
we will obtain something like this.
The direct beam in the center,
then a spot for a plain that we will call G,
then another spot the 2G,
the plane which is parallel to the plane for G but has half its spacing,
and then 3G and so on,
and their negative counterparts.
However, there should be very little intensity in
the other diffraction spots because it is only these planes
which are parallel to the incident electron beam.
Now, in this case if we say G equals 002,
then by exciting this systematic row,
we will cut out
the 111 planes which are responsible for its formation by double diffraction.
Therefore, as we tilt to excite the systematic row,
we should see G and minus G disappear.
And also if we included them on the diffraction pattern,
then 3G and minus 3G.
We should be left only with 2G and minus 2G
corresponding to the 004 and 00 bar 4 planes respectively.
To show you this, we look at a video of tilting in this way.
At the beginning, we were aligned precisely on
the 110 zone axis with the 002 and 00 bar 2 planes strongly excited.
Now, we start tilting around this axis.
And as we do this,
we will see intensities changes the ethosphere cast planes at different excitation areas.
And then gradually, we will see these 002 planes
disappear when the 111 reflections are completely de-excited.
So then if they've already disappeared, they come back again.
And then now as we tilt even further to excite the systematic row very precisely,
the 002 planes have completely
disappeared thus proving that they were a consequence of double diffraction.
To summarize, in this lecture we have looked at
double diffraction which is a particular case of
dynamical scattering that can give rise to the appearance
of diffraction spots for kinematically forbidden crystal planes.
To look at this,
I have used the case of silicon aligned on a 110 type of zone axis.
Where in the experimental diffraction pattern,
we see intensity for forbidden planes 002 and 00 bar 2.
We have interpreted this in terms of a diffracted beam from
first scattering event that acts as the direct beam for new scattering events.
For instance in the case of silicon,
we can look at scattering on this G vector to this 111 type plane,
combined with scattering on this G vector adding
together to give scattering to this 002 diffraction spot location.
Looking at this in more detail,
we can conceive it as an additional reciprocal lattice and
ethosphere centered at the end of a way vector for an initial diffracted beam.
Well, here I have demonstrated
double diffraction for the case of scattering across a single crystal.
Double diffraction can also occur when there is scattering from
one crystal lattice into and across another crystal lattice.
In the second case,
it can lead to the formation of what are known as satellites spots which
surround the diffraction spots from the initial crystal lattice.
It can further be interpreted via the same ethosphere reciprocal lattice construction,
where the second reciprocal lattice would instead correspond to
the reciprocal lattice of the second phase in the sample.
This brings me to the end of my basic discussion of
dynamical scattering effects for a parallel incident illumination.
If we instead focus the beam to a spot on the sample,
the illumination is convergent.
If you then look at the diffraction pattern,
you'll see what's called a convergent beam electron diffraction pattern or CBED pattern.
These patterns can show very strong contrasts from dynamical scattering.
And one we've covered so far,
this contrast can be highly interpretable to obtain useful information about your sample.
Returning to the case of a parallel incident illumination,
there again there can be another kind of multiple scattering,
this time where the coherent elastic scattering that we have considered so
far is preceded by an incoherent scattering event.
The combination of this incoherent scattering followed by coherent elastic scattering,
can produce bright and dark lines in a selected area diffraction pattern.
These Kikuchi lines can be very useful for precisely
aligning a sample to a specific diffraction condition.
However, these two are a subject for another time.
Now that we have created the basics for the theory of electron diffraction,
and also seeing some examples of the effects of diffraction on time image contrast,
we will now go into another important category of imaging contrast in TEM,
namely face contrast imaging.
And for this I hand over to Cecil.
Thank you Duncan. Face contrast that is
from the interference of different elastically scattered beams,
and it's the basis for high resolution TEM also called atomic resolution imaging.
We will go through the theory of face contrast in the coming lectures.