Welcome to CIME's lecture on
transmission electron microscopy
for materials science.
In the previous module you have
learned a lot about diffraction
and diffraction contrast.
In this module I want to take
to the world of phase contrast
for which it's important to
know that electrons are waves.
But before starting this,
let's go to the microscope.
My sample is made of
Indium-Arsenic-Tin nano-wires.
You have them at low magnification
here on the carbon film.
Now I have only one of them in,
so called high resolution mode.
This nano-wire is well crystallized
and has an hexagonal cross section
and it is lying on the carbon film.
So if I make a sketch
of the specimen
I will have my
amorphous carbon film
and the nano-wire with
the hexagonal cross section
lying on it, which means that
from the side of the nano-wire
towards the center I have
an increasing thickness.
That's why you recognize the bright,
dark, bright, dark, bright, etc.
bands which are
thickness fringes
you have seen them with Duncan.
But on top of this, because
the nano-wire is very well oriented
in zone axis, you also recognize
especially at this position
the periodic contrast of white dots.
It's very tempting to call this
atomic column, or atomic contrast
and to think what we have there
is just a projection of the well
ordered atomic column
seen from the top.
But on the other hand,
while the contrast is very clear
in that region, you see that it's
getting messy in this intermediate
part and then I have an inversion
of contrast before I start again
with something looking like
white atoms in the next band.
And then again, inversion of
contrast and later on white atoms.
Actually, things will get
even more complicated
if I start changing the focus.
Now I'll start changing
the focus of the objective lens.
Concentrate on the band close to
the edge of the specimen.
You see, I'v reached a focus where
the contrast has completely changed.
I continue changing the focus now
and I'm back to
the original contrast.
And then, again changing...
back to the original contrasts
well actually I'm only changing
the focus in the same direction.
Now I continue changing the focus
changing the direction
of focus change
and you see, again, how
these contrasts are moving.
So, clearly there's an interplay
between the focus of the objective
lens, the thickness and
the crystallinity of
the specimen and
the kind of image that I get.
To understand phase contrast we
need to take everything into account
what the electron wave's
has interacted with.
If we take the optical axis as
the vertical axis, we have
the electron waves
that can be considered
as plane waves.
Those electrons will first
interact with the specimen.
After the specimen, the electron
wave will be completely changed.
It will have changed phase
and amplitude.
We draw it as a distorted wave.
This is the incoming plane wave and
this wave is called the exit wave.
It carries everything we would like
to know about the specimen.
It is a complex quantity which
has phase and amplitude
and it's actually the quantity
that we would like to access to.
But in order to access it,
we then have the objective lens
bellow the specimen.
Unfortunately, the objective lens
is not a perfect lens, so instead of
transmitting the exit wave perfectly
it will transmit it mixed up with
some properties that are due to
the lens, like aberrations
or cut off by the aperture.
After the objective lens,
we have the electron wave
that carries information about both
specimen plus the electron lens.
And then we need to measure it.
Usually we have a recording device,
like a CCD camera with pixels
on which we will project
our electron wave
but this recording device we
can only measure the amplitude
so we have the projected
amplitude of the electron wave.
it's very different
from the exit wave.
In order to understand phase
contrast, we need to understand
this whole chain of
information transfer.
And to make it a little bit more
simple, we will start in the first
part by describing the interaction
of the electron wave with
the objective lens.
In the second part, we will see
how the specimen will affect
the plane wave.
And then finally we will combine
those two approaches to get
the complete information
transfer by the system
and then understand what we
obtain from the projection
on the recording device.
Basically, this will be the subject
of this module about phase contrast.
So, let's start with the next video
to see how the objective lens
affects the electron wave.