Welcome to CIME's lectures on transmission
electron microscopy for materials science.
In this video, we will see
the effect of a thin specimen which
only affects the phase,
the weak phase object approximation.
And what's the influence when we
consider the contrast transfer function.
So now I am back with my specimen,
the electron wave that comes on
the specimen and is a plain wave.
And I have the electron wave after
the specimen called f(r).
This is affected both in amplitude and
phase.
At that position I have the phase shift,
which depends on the thickness
of the specimen t.
Here is the amplitude and the phase.
If I have a thin specimen, only the
projected potential will affect the phase.
I can write the phase shift as
pi / (lambda.E) V_t(r).
Since I have a thin specimen,
the phase shift is small.
Lambda is the wavelength of
the electrons and E the electron energy.
So if I have a very thin specimen,
the amplitude is not affected,
so A(r)=1.
And the phase shift is extremely small,
so pi/ (lambda.E) V_t(r)
is much smaller than 1.
With this I can rewrite f(r).
This called
the Weak Phase Object Approximation.
We will now look at what is the influence
of the objective lens on this object wave.
So we keep the specimen object wave in
the Weak Phase Object Approximation.
And we know at the objective lens.
The objective length is described
by the point spread function.
And it's Fourier transform,
the contrast transfer function.
Which is the Fourier transform
of the point spread function.
After the objective lens,
we have the electron
wave formed as an image,
which is the convolution
of the exit wave and
the point spread function.
But what we measure is then the intensity
projected on a recording device.
So the measured quantity I(r)
has the following expression
g times its complex conjugate.
I will calculate this using
the point spread function and
the approximation for the exit wave.
I now insert this expression for f, but
I'll keep the point spread function.
I have a real part, an imaginary part.
So now I will consider
the two parts real and
imaginary part of
the point spread function.
So I will first expand
the convolution product, and
see what the first term is doing.
And then for the second part,
I will need to consider separately
real and imaginary part of h.
I will first take care of this first
quantity, one convoluted with h.
If I want to get this,
I can consider it's Fourier transform.
So this is the inverse Fourier
transform of its Fourier
transform which will transform this
into a multiplicative product.
The Fourier transform of
1 is a Delta function,
I'm now entering reciprocal space.
So I have u times the Fourier
transform of the point
spread function is the contrast
transfer function.
This is A and A is equal to that.
Okay, this just picks the value of H for
u equals 0, which is 1, so
it's also a delta function.
The inverse Fourier transform
of a delta function is unity.
So A is equal 1.
So we're plotting now this
equation on the next slide.
I will continue by expanding this term
to separate real and imaginary parts.
The real part will come from
the multiplication of this imaginary
part with this one, and
the imaginary part from the last term.
It's time now to calculate
the modulus to get y.
So the real part squared plus
the imaginary part squared.
Let us now come back to the weak
phase object approximation.
We build it by saying that this
quantity is small with respect to 1.
Now I will have this quantity,
small with respect to 1 as well.
And if you look well,
this will be of order 2.
And this can be simplified by
keeping only the first order.
The two last term,
Are negligible.
So the projected intensity only depends
on the imaginary part of
the point spread function.
Since now the only important quantity Is
the imaginary part of
the point spread function,
that also means that for
the contrast transfer function,
I will only need to consider
its imaginary part.
The CTF was A times the envelope times B,
which is exponential y times chi.
If I take the imaginary part of the CTF,
I end up with A times E, both are real,
times sinus of chi(u).
Now I also have this factor
of two which arise due
to the approximation we made before.
So I can define the phase
contrast transfer function
T(u) as being A(u),
E(u) times 2 sinus chi(u).
So this phase contrast transfer function
is a characteristic of the microscope.
It includes the effect of apertures,
the envelopes, and
the aberrations of the objective lens.
It will act as a filter
in reciprocal space and
govern on the transfer of information
as a function of spatial frequencies.
So we have to remember now, this very
important quantity called the phase
contrast transfer function.
If we only have defocus and
spherical aberration,
we had an expression for chi(u)
This is this expression depending on the defocus
delta f and
the spherical aberration coefficient Cs.
So now, we have the fast growing
function as a function of u,
and we take the sinus of this.
You can imagine that we
have chi(u),
which will grow for
increasing u very fast.
If you take the sine of this,
you can expect the transfer
function T(u) to
have a very complicated
form with something I
don't know how it will look
like at the beginning.
But for sure when I increase,
go to increasing u,
I will get faster and faster oscillations.
What does it mean to have
such a strange function?
If it crosses the horizontal axis,
I have to transfer function equal to 0.
That means,
I will not transfer any information.
If I have a positive or negative,
I will have inversion of contrast.
This is the spatial frequency u.
So that as a function of u,
I will have very
complicated different
transfer of information.
So now, you have seen how we come to
the phase contrast transfer function,
which is very important to
explain the transfer of
information in the case of the weak
phase object approximation.
In the next video,
we will look in more details at the phase
contrast transfer function as a function
of the microscope capabilities, C_s and
defocus, and see how it affects
the image that we can record.