Welcome to CIME’s lectures on Transmission Electron Microscopy
for Materials Science
in this video, we will have a closer look
at the phase contrast transfer
function and  first look at it
with a simulation
software and then see its effects
in a real transmission electron microscope
on amorphous carbon.
So from the last video you
remember that we arrived to the phase
contrasts transfer function.
When we are imaging at week phase object with
the objective lens this function is made
of two parts, an envelope part.
And a second part which corresponds to a phase shift
applied by the objective lens which depends on the
scattering vector reciprocal  Space Vector u, even
if we only have defocus and spherical aberration this
phase shift is already a complicated function of u
including the defocus the spherical aberration coefficient
and the wavelengths of the electrons.
Now in reality we have other aberrations like astigmatism to
each of them corresponds in an analytical formula
that can be included in the phase
contrast transfer function.
So getting an intuitive interpretation of that function is not
easy. We will use the simulation software called
JEMS to plot this function as a function
of u and also the phase contrasts transfer function including
the envelopes. You have all the instruction to download and
install JEMS student edition on the Moocs.
And I strongly suggest that you do so to practice and follow
what we will see now. after starting JEMS student edition,
you go to the tab called drawing and you
choose transfer function. You have a new screen
appearing. And the first thing we will do will be to select the kind of
microscope we will be working with, for the
beginning we take a generic microscope. Let's take the HF2000
This is a Hitachi model but it has 200
kilovolts 1.6 millimeter for the
chromatic aberration coefficient 1.2 millimeter for the
spherical aberration coefficient and here an energy
spread of 0.6 we will put it to 0.8
with this we have a standard field emission
gun transmission electron microscope for materials science
without CS correction. of course
if you know the microscope you're working with. You're free to change those
parameters to adapt them to your exact situation.
In the tab CTF profile we see
a plot of the phase contrast transfer function as a
function of reciprocal unit length. So
nanometer minus one it's in reciprocal space. And
of course this is only at trace in
one particular direction in the reciprocal space which has
normally two dimensions.
It includes all the terms at the beginning but
we would start by removing the influence of the envelopes. So we
go to the tab call envelope, and to remove all
those envelopes also, there's a remaining
influence from the tab  drift and noise which
we put to zero as well. with this the phase
contrast transfer function is as we expect
oscillating strongly and between one
and minus one, it is because it's the same function
of this complicated function of u including C_s
defocus and wavelengths of the electrons
in the tab called CTF, besides the CTF profile you
can have a look at the 2D drawing of the contrast transfer
function also in reciprocal space. But here we have
the view of the reciprocal vector and not just the trace
in one direction. The CTF profile will be sufficient for
now as we're working with aberration which have a cylindrical symmetry.
So the CTF are circular and we have all the
information in a clear way from the profile.
On the right part of the screen in the tab "order two", I have access to the
defocus of the microscope. Let's do it with  "fine" so we
don't change it too much and see what happens if we change the
defocus with this slider. You see how the
oscillations change as we change delta f which
will influence the phase contrast transfer function but whatever we
do at high spatial frequency we have this strong
oscillations. Let's put back
the envelopes, spatial and temporal and go to option
and plot's them. So no we see not only the effects on the envelope but the
trace of those
you can change the parameters that influence the envelopes in the tab
called coherence especially the energy spread of the microscope.
OK. No we can come back to this tab "order two" and change the
defocus while we have the effect on the envelopes.
Still we see strong changes in the phase contrasts transfer
function and we see that we're able for example to put it in a way where we
have a relatively wide band where the phase contrasts transfer function
is close to minus one at more or less constant while in other
range of the defocus we have a crossing of the zero axis
in the middle of the accessible spatial frequencies.
As zero crossing means that we have no phase contrast transfer at
this particular spatial frequencies. In other words we
have no information transferred. So we will be
missing part of the information in the image
Also, around the crossing, we have an inversion of the sign of the phase
contrast transfer function. This means that we will have an inversion
of contrast for the different spatial frequencies.
Before and after the crossing. Obviously an
image acquired under those condition will not be very easy to
interpret. Playing around with the defocus we find only
one value of delta F which gives us this wide band
of transferred frequencies. Now in the tab called diffractogram
I have the possibility to simulate the image of an amorphous
specimen for example carbon or it's diffractogram
which is the fast Fourier transform of the image. This diffractogram
is closely related to the phase contrast transfer function. Dark rings
corresponds to regions where no infon is transferred hence crossing of the
Zero axis in the phase contrasts transfer function. The dark
circles that you see appearing at some defocus and
some value of u means that at those particular
frequencies I have no information transfer
using an amorphous specimen to look at the contrast transfer
function. It's a good idea because an amorphous specimen
will have a wide band of spatial frequencies over the whole
specimen region. Now we will go to the real transmission of electron
microscope to see how things look like with an amorphous
Carbon film when we take an image and build the fast Fourrier transform
transfer of this image. Here my
specimen is an amorphous Carbon film with a few very
small particles.
And on the right part of the image there's a hole, so no specimen
in the right pannel you see the fast Fourier transform, also called
diffractogram, of the left image. Now
I will start to change the focus going to under
focus and then back to over focus
you see two things on the right part in the diffractogram,
you see this ring pattern like we had in the
contrasts transfer function. On the left
part on the image you see clearly the defocused carbon
film. Now I'm back towards focus,
when I'm in focus, I have the minimum contrast and now my
contrast is increasing again. I see again the rings.
It's important to keep in mind that those black rings are
spatial frequencies which are not transmitted by the optical
system so in that region I have
no transfer of information.
So back to the simulation software  we will now have a
closer look at the particular defocus for which
I had a good transfer of information. We come back to
the CTF profile and we play around
with the focus to see if we can find
an optimal value of Delta F
Clearly I have a tradeoff between the width of this
band and the small indentation in the middle of
it. If we look at the tab Defocus, we
have preselected value of the defocus, and
actually, the first one gives me a good compromise.
No surprise. This is Scherzer's defocus. And we will now
try to see close up what it really means in the transmission
electron microscope. Let us have a closer look at the
situation. When I choose this value for the
defocus I have then the first crossing
of the phase contrasts transfer function with the zero axis
at this frequency, I have no contrast transferred. And after this
frequency the first contrast transfer function is oscillating.
This means that we will have several crossing with zero axis where
no contrast is transferred as well as part where the contrast is
positive and part where it is negative. This will produce
images which are difficult to interpret. We referre to this crossing
as being the point resolution of the microscope.
I can obtain it for the particular value of defocus
called Scherzer's defocus which
depends on the wave length and the spherical aberration
coefficient and which will give a good
compromise in terms of width and value of the
phase contrast transfer function in this first band.
But even after this first crossing you'll see that I am able to
transfer some frequency and by tweaking the
defocus I could be able to map all this
frequency domain up to a certain point when
the envelopes are cuting completely the phase contrast transfer
function, then I cannot get anything more out of my
microscope. This is called the "Information limit". But
what's happening if I have a C_s corrected microscope? for a C_s
corrected microscope. The spherical aberration coefficient can be
corrected and be equal to zero. Would that mean that the Sherzer's
defocus would also be zero? Let's have a look at what the
simulation software tells us.
So now I come back to the same situation and microscope as before, but
I will change it to have a corrected C_s.
So a spherical aberration which is put to zero. I find
this in the tab "order 4", and I can take the slider and
put the C_s, actually to the value I want but
I will be choosing exactly zero.
Whoops. What happens there? I don't see my phase contrasts
transfer function anymore. The Sherzer's defocus
is zero, and I am now at Scherzer,
zero defocus, but what happend? Let's look at
the tab where I have the defocus and play a bit with the defocus.
Indeed, if I add some defocus I see my phase contrasts
transfer function coming back.
That's a well known effect. If you have a perfect correction of the spherical aberration,
No defocus at a weak phase object, we will
have zero contrast. Very good resolution but no
contrast so no image of the specimen.
Of course if you have a specimen that goes beyond the weak phase object
approximation you will probably see some thing but
it will not be easy to interpret, the work around is to
put a little bit of C_S but much smaller
than what you usually have in a microscope. So, in some
micrometer range and then playing around
with the defocus, I can again find
condition where I have this Scherzer's defocus or
white band and the good thing is then the point
resolution is very close to the information limit of the
microscope. But what I can do too is put a negative
C_S because that's allowed by the C_S corrector. And then
you see an inversion of the contrast and especially
if you adjust the defocus to have the proper wide
band of phase contrast transfer function then
you have a positive contrast and this will give
you very nice images especially if you are imaging
small particles or very thin layers.
Now we have a quick look at how thin amorphous carbon film
looks like in a C_ss corrected microscope. At the beginning,
I have a defocus of zero and actually  so few contrast that
you probably cannot recognize where the film is and where the hole is
on the right part. You see the FFT of the left image
increasing the defocus you see progressively the contrast appearing
and exactly the same ring path as before on the non C_S corrected
microscope. Here we are not so much limited by the
envelope but more made available spatial
frequencies given by the carbon film
and now I will come back to zero defocus
and see how the ring pattern and the image are
changing. After that. The next step would be to look at the effect
of astigmatism. So now we are back to the simulation software to look at the effect of
astigmatism. First of all I want to take the same microscope as
before and we'll put the spherical aberration back to
1.2 millimeter. With this the CTF has the usual
circular symmetry back to the tab which contains the
defocus but also twofold asstigmatism we can for
example change the twofold astigmatism or first put the
defocused to a value which is close to the Scherzer's defocus we've seen before.
If I now play around with the twofold astigmatism actually I
don't see much difference with what happend before.
We should not forget that we are looking at an aberration
which has different effect in two perpendicular directions. So we
really need to look at the CTF and not at the profile to
understand what's going on. Here you see the
strong assymmetry in the
CTF in two dimension and with this
slider we are able to turn it on the screen. Once I
put a lot of astigmatism I can play around with the
defocus and see how the pattern changes in a
relatively complicated way also including
crosses and oval patterns and ring patterns and so on.
I suggests that you play around yourself with the JEMS software to see
a little bit what effect you can get.
Watching the shape of the CTF which you can see in the
FFT of the image of an amorphous sample will
obviously be a big help to correct the astigmatism of your
microscope. Looking at
the diffractogram. We recognize a similar shape than the one we had
in the CTF and indeed that would be
easy to recognize on your microscope.
So now we will jump to the real microscope and see if
we can see exactly the same shape as we head here.
Back to the same specimen as before just having a slight
defocused to see one black ring.
My microscope was correctly adjusted, and I will start
to mess up with the astigmatism correction. You see
how the diffractoram lose its symmetry its
becoming aval. Now I change the focus and you
see the same changes in the diffractogram as we had in
the CTF using JEMS
back to the same under-focus as before, now I will
increase the astigmatism even further.
So that will make the diffractogram more oval.
And if you look on the
left image you start to see an elongated structure in
the carbon film.
And when you go through the focus and then to
over-focus, you see how the direction of the
structure change in the film. This is a
typical effect of astigmatism in a carbon film.
And clearly the diffractogram will be a big help to correct
astigmatism and have a well aligned microscope
OK.
with this video you have seen the effect of the phase contrast transfer
function on a thin amorphous specimen, and how  it is
possible to draw it with a simulation software and to image
it with a carbon film in the transmission electron microscope.