So
This brings us to the end of CIME's lecture on
Transmission Electron Microscopy for Material Science.
In this course
We have described the principles of how
a transmission electron microscope works
And the theory behind the image contrast
and data that you record at the microscope
You now have the basics for taking
a practical training at the microscope
Or for moving under study one of the many advanced
analytical techniques that TEM offers
Congratulations on finishing the course
We hope that you have enjoyed learning about
this powerful and fascinating type of microscopy
We wish you luck for any plans
you have to progress with TEM
Either on the theoretical or learning
how to use the microscope yourself
So
It's goodbye from CIME's lecture on
Transmission Electron Microscopy for Material Science