Welcome to the course
on Space mission design and operations.
This is the introduction to the course,
and we'll tell you about the style
of the course, the spirit of the course,
and I'll be using this set of pictures
that you see here,
which was in fact the logo
of the course over the past few years,
in order to illustrate
the various sections of the course.
First of all, this is going to be
a concept course.
The idea is really
to understand concepts.
There will be little deep calculation.
You can forget about Matlab,
you can just use your head,
your brain, and maybe a calculator.
There will be only
relatively simple calculations,
but I would like you
to understand concepts
of space exploration
and utilization of space.
So, let's look at these pictures.
Here we have the Space Shuttle
on low Earth orbit.
This picture was taken
in the summer of 2005,
on Space Shuttle Mission STS-114,
which, by the way,
was commanded by a woman.
Eileen Collins was the commander
of that mission.
A picture taken
from the International Space Station
shortly before the docking
of the Shuttle to ISS.
This is just to...
in fact, the Shuttle, at this time,
is flying over Zurich, Switzerland.
So, this picture is very dear to my heart,
it's over my home country.
This is just to illustrate the fact
that we'll talk a lot
about trajectories and orbits,
and orbital changes, maneuvers,
changes of inclination,
changes of attitude of the orbit.
And, a picture taken from ISS,
so obviously there was a rendezvous
of the Space Shuttle with ISS.
There will be one pretty big section
in the course
about rendezvous in low Earth orbit.
And this was valid for the Space Shuttle,
and the Hubble Space Telescope,
for instance,
the International Space Station,
for many, many missions,
until the Shuttle was retired in 2011,
and, of course, it still is the case
for Soyuz rendezvous
with the International Space Station,
to bring personnel there,
or resupply spacecraft
from the various nations
that also have to perform automatic
rendezvous with the Space Shuttle.
So, low Earth orbit, orbital changes,
maneuvers and rendezvous.
Now, in the lower right and lower left,
you have illustrations of exploration
of the solar system, using either probes,
on the lower right, here,
you have the Cassini spacecraft
on orbit around Saturn,
since many years
a very successful mission,
and on the lower left here,
you have a robot on the surface of Mars.
There has been a whole series
of robots on Mars.
Presently we have Curiosity still active
on the surface of the Red Planet.
So this is going to be a pretty important
section of the course also,
the missions to other targets
in the solar system,
whether it's planets or satellites,
and we'll look at strategies
to leave the Earth's vicinity
and go towards Mars, or Venus,
or Jupiter, or Saturn,
on a heliocentric trajectory for a while,
but when we are
in the vicinity of the Earth,
we have to handle it differently,
and when we are close
to the destination planet,
we also have to make
a special treatment.
We'll cover all of that.
Now, in the upper left,
you have a rocket going into space.
There will be a chapter on propulsion,
and the rocket equation.
We'll talk about
the ascent into space,
we'll cover the case
of the multistage rocket,
in order to reach the orbit
in a more efficient manner
than if you had only one rocket.
We'll talk about attitude control
of spacecraft
we will not cover in detail
spacecraft systems,
this is a course on mission design
and not so much on spacecraft design.
Spacecraft design is covered
in other courses.
And, last but not least,
in the middle we have a spacewalker.
It happens to be me,
on 23rd of December, 1999,
when I was on my last mission, STS-103,
a Shuttle mission
to the Hubble Space Telescope.
We did some repair work on Hubble.
At the end fo the course, I'll cover
specifically human spaceflight,
the conditions of life
on board a spaceship,
whether it's a Shuttle
or the International Space Station,
and there will be sections also
on robotics used on the Shuttle,
and on ISS, and also on spacewalking.
Anyway, have fun on this course.