At the urban scale, spatial agency is a major issue too.
Action on the city has long been described by the term ‘urban planning’.
At the beginning, experts, mainly architects and engineers,
were commissioned by the public authority
to conceive, design and build material infrastructures and buildings
that would shape the future urban spaces
and condition their inhabitants’ lives.
But this is changing now,
and the term ‘urbanism’, that was used to mean
‘urban way of life’ in 20th century English,
has turned to be a synonym of the reinvention of urban planning.
The table shows the shifts that have taken place
from traditional urban planning to the emerging urbanism.
As we can see, the experts are becoming actors among other actors,
and the empowerment of ordinary citizens is fundamental.
Although their opinion is not properly taken seriously,
they have conquered powerful means to hinder or cancel projects:
Law suits, single-issue street or media activism,
direct democracy or even individual moving from a house to another.
Switching from urban design to urban becoming
is all the more important that simultaneously
the process of urbanization as we've seen in Session 5
has shifted from absolute to relative.
With the end of the absolute urbanization,
the issue at stake will less and less be the making of containers
for urbanized, fixed or mobile life,
but more and more the shaping of urban life itself.
In a society of urban individuals,
the inhabitants’ choices
become the major strategic parameter of urban dynamics.
These choices are subject to change
but much easily in a dense, and open participatory process
in which experts and politicians
turn out to be actors amongst other actors.
Much has been done in theoretical research,
namely by authors such as John Rawls, or Amartya Sen,
to explore the concept of justice as a crucial issue
in contemporary societies.
Now the attention of the adjective ‘spatial’ to a
supposed-to-be-non-spatial justice,
raises a number of epistemological and theoretical problems
that geographers are just beginning to tackle.
The risk here is to oversimplify the answer
to one or more of these questions.
Who defines what is just and how?
To what extent could space be something else
than a neutral container of unjust or just items?
Could geographers’ work
bring a specific contribution to the public debate on justice?
The example of debates about gentrification
shows that this ‘programme’ for spatial justice
is highly controversial.
In the Anglophone geographical literature,
scholars such as David Ley, Chris Hamnett or Richard Florida,
can be opposed to David Harvey, Neil Smith or Edward Soja.
The key issue is, first of all, vocabulary.
Gentrification is commonly used
as a virtual synonym of the French ‘embourgeoisement’.
Should we name the middle class individuals
that move to poorer neighborhoods, ‘gentrifiers’ or, instead, ‘ghetto-killers’,
or ‘mix-makers’?
Although it has rapidly been used in a derogatory way,
the term ‘bobo’ coined by David Brooks in 2000
is more relevant than ‘gentrifier’
precisely because ‘bourgeois-boheme’ people
have the choice to dwell in different kinds of real-estate-price locations,
and it's easy to prove that if this group did not exist,
a geography solely made of land-value-generated, homogenous districts
would spontaneously emerge.
This is exactly what happened between the 1950s and 1980s
in most North American cities
when the ‘urban flight’ involved the huge majority of the middle class.
We can see the difference with Europe during this period.
In Western European cities,
people with high cultural capital remained in the cities historical centres
even when their incomes were low.
They arbitrated in favor of smaller or less comfortable flats,
while the social atmosphere was favorable
to various kinds of de-densifying urbanization processes.
The word ‘gentrification’ embeds the idea
that deprived persons or already segregated groups
should be left in a homogeneous environment
and that this would be a better situation than social mix,
which is praised in general but denied in practice
as either impossible or dangerous by many authors.
In short, it is not because gentrification is a danger for social mix
that it should be condemned, they say,
but right on the contrary
because it enlarges districts’ sociological spectrum,
and weakens ghettos.
If we connect the history of debates on urban topics
to the history of urban realities,
we are inevitably struck by their growing diverging course.
On the one hand, after decades of urban flight and its consequences,
pervasive violence in the streets,
the emergence of urban renaissance does not appear as a pretentious model
but as an effective bifurcation.
It suddenly makes sense
that David Ley explicitly used
the ‘Vancouver Experience’ of urban regeneration
as a primary study case
to develop his critical statements on gentrification.
In this city,
the urban re-encounter with urbanity began in the late 1970s
and the Expo 86 represents a first milestone
in the process of urban regeneration.
All the intellectual construction of contemporary urbanism,
I mean urban agency here in the European meaning,
is underpinned by the idea that through public space
sociological and functional diversity is at stake as an issue and a goal
in every single action, at any scale of the city.
On the other hand, the neo-structuralist approach rejects
the very idea of social mix
as the revenge of the bourgeoisie over the proletariat,
and understands the right to public space as a synonym of a right to the ghetto.
Between both sides, discussion is not easy.
These oppositions are part of a larger paradigm divergence
and are not a problem in itself.
Pluralism in debates should be the correct response
to plurality of ideas.
Trouble begins when the hegemony of one approach
practically discards all others.
There is clearly a problem here in Anglophone literature.
One single point of view appears overwhelming and omnipresent
while the others are censored, or self-censored.