From Session One we have proposed
to you a rapid journey
across theories and languages
of space, and spatiality.
Two major issues:
the World and the individual.
Two essential processes:
urbanity and telecommunication
and two major topics: nature and time.
At the end of this itinerary,
the question we'd like to pose is:
How do spaces as environments
and spatialities,
as sets of actions, interact and combine?
More specifically, how can human agency
modify spaces that prefigure agency,
but however, are clearly exposed to it?
The examples of war, Europe,
and urbanism will help us
to comprehend two critical notions:
spatial justice and inhabiting.
In this session,
we will go back to the questions
addressed during
the previous eight sessions.
We will explore the same realities
and tackle the same issues,
but with a particular angle,
that of agency.
The starting point is that geographicity
is submitted to actors’ moves.
These actors being individual, collective
or organizational components of a society,
or the society as a whole.
We will begin with a global scale
and continue to downscale,
by next, focusing on a continent, Europe,
and finally the city.
As a conclusion of this course,
we will introduce two transversal issues:
spatial justice and inhabiting.
One of the major reasons why human agency
has become more possible,
is that the huge constraints that weighed
on individual and collective leeway,
have been progressively eased.
Spatial freedoms
have correlatively increased.
The issue of war and peace is a good case
for us to analyze this change.
Let's take an example
to make this hypothesis
slightly more intelligible.
What can we say about wars?
On this controversial topic,
several theories can be considered.
Some simply contend
that war is not a historical object
and consider war is in man,
as an expression of
man's natural propensity to violence.
For others, geopolitical logics
have always existed and will do forever.
However, we know today
that pre-paleolithic wars
were short-friction, violent episodes,
whose nature changed when the control
of surpluses became a major issue.
About 5,000 years ago,
within the neolithic era,
the birth of the geopolitical state,
endowed with a permanent army
and fortified places,
is a logical defensive,
as well as an offensive response
to the fragility
of the emerging productive systems.
What is called geopolitical wars,
interstate wars or classical wars,
begins then and continues for centuries,
until the paroxysm of WWII.
Now, some converging observations show
the decline of classical
geopolitical wars,
namely because
the most developed countries
do not make war to each other anymore.
Most current wars
are intrastate, that is to say
they are conflicts that occur
inside a particular state,
such as civil wars,
like Syria, since 2011.
Secession wars like South Sudan,
between 1983 to 2005,
or inter-communal wars
(many conflicts in Sub-Saharan Africa).
This is what the surveys
of the ‘Human Security Report’ show.
Regarding state based wars,
there are fewer wars and less casualties
on the battle fields.
Moreover, wars are increasingly
intrastate conflicts,
which make them go beyond
classical geopolitical wars.
Today, the most developed countries
don't always have
friendly relationships with each other,
but they endeavour
not to make war to each other,
because they have painfully learned
that the cost of wars
and management of empires,
which can be imaginable
in economies of stock,
has lost its sense
in economies of flows.
Conquering territories by force,
generates the risk of elimination
from the international scene,
with few advantages.
It is this unhappy end
that Europe experienced in 1945,
after centuries of bloody wars.
Even when pursuing the traditional goal
of gaining more influence,
a state is more efficient
in ‘soft’, than ‘hard’ power,
as Joseph Nye wrote.
Geopolitics is setting back
as this fear of politics is enlarging.
Hybrid situations appear.
This table shows
the possible intersections
between two rationales;
that of intersociety relationships;
realism versus idealism,
and that of intrasocietal
political stances
(conservatism versus progressivism).
The upper left and the bottom right boxes
are easy to put into perspective.
We can understand
that a certain kind of conservatism
refuses the trend
toward the universalizing of values
and, as a result, believes that we'll live
more comfortably in a segmented World.
Contrarily, it is consistent
with the idea
of self perfectibility of society
that, sooner or later,
the World will become a new,
fully-fledged tier of citizenship
with a democratic government
and a rule-of-the-law justice.
Immanuel Kant versus Carl Schmitt:
this is a fair, bright fight.
More mysterious, and yet, present
on the scene, are the two other boxes.
We recently had the opportunity
to observe the historical experiment
of idealistic conservatism
epitomized by the neoconservatives
under the George W. Bush administration.
In Europe, a significant part
of the parties
belonging to the traditional left,
support the ideology
of realistic progressivism,
characterized by a rejection
of any intervention
based on human rights, aiming at a state.
In the American case,
the post 9/11 defensive nationalism,
is a resource
for aggressive interventions
all over the World.
In the European case,
the tetanized clutching
to the welfare state,
protecting against any change,
hampers the emergence
of a post-national vision
of World affairs.
Anti-Americanism,
although it is wrapped up
in an anti-imperialistic ethical speech,
often resembles a nostalgic revival
of inter-imperial rivalries,
especially in France.
In both situations,
the state functions like a screen,
which hinders the capacity
of addressing the issues at stake
at a global scale.
For example,
unilateralism and multilateralism
take place under the same
geopolitical and antipolitical paradigm.
In a political society
there is pluralism in opinion,
but only one scene, one parliament,
or one government.
Moreover, in a federal political society,
a government accepts
the existence of other governments,
on upper or lower tiers.
This table can help us understand
that the invention of politics
is a major, non-trivial issue
that global civil society
has on its control panel,
with states being
alternatively friends and foes
of this perspective.
A war-less World, is a World
where social construction
loses its tragic character
and becomes pragmatic,
that is, a complex resultant
of actors' intentionalities.