This is precisely the case for Europe,
a continent that has been,
for a long time,
devastated by the wargame
of its numerous and brutal nation-states.
A five-century geopolitical system
has operated between an Eastern area
threatened by
Central Asian nomad empires,
and the Atlantic Rim,
soon protected from invasions
able to construct endured states
and to project itself
into overseas empires.
Europe was, simultaneously,
the place that brutalized
the rest of the World,
and a place from where
universalist inventions emerged,
like the rule of law, civil liberties,
democracy, social security,
contemporary individuality,
and public space.
During centuries, states have tried
to reinforce themselves
at the expense of civil society,
by conquering or annexing territories,
creating monopolies, levying taxes,
imposing constraints on commerce,
mobility, and urbanization,
but, on the other side,
the cities, merchant guilds,
local societies,
have tried to develop
alternative scales and metrics.
The Hanseatic League
is a good example
of this type of network
during the late medieval era.
The long dispute
between territories and networks
progressively turned to the advantage
of the states and territories.
As soon as 1648,
the reinforcement of the states’ power
had led to the Treaty of Westphalia,
to which the states self-identified
as the exclusive players
of European history.
This was not only
a matter of political regime.
After absolute monarchy,
the modern states continued the search
for a centralized,
unrivaled architecture of power
that could help them channel resources
towards their geopolitical projects.
After the first massive mobilizations
during the French Revolution,
the number of potential drafted soldiers
became a key criterion
for the handling
of ever more bloody conflicts.
The states then decided
to exchange democracy and welfare,
again, the possibility of sending
millions of young citizens
to dreadful battlefields.
World War II appeared, then,
as a paroxysm of a process
that had begun much earlier.
Killing not only soldiers
from the other party,
but its own population,
was the final stage
of the European nation states’ supremacy
in the age of totalitarianism,
with their Communist-Stalinist
and Fascist-Nazi branches.
The 1918-1945 period
has been called,
not without justification,
the ‘suicide of Europe’.
Since the Renaissance,
many thinkers and statesmen
had proposed a European Union,
but few paid attention to their voice.
The European Construction
really only began
when, after 1945,
almost all the continent
was controlled by non-European,
Soviet and American troops.
This was the beginning of what is called
the ‘European Construction’.
The Treaty of Rome, signed in 1957,
was the founding act of birth
of what is currently the European Union,
its 28-member countries,
and its 500 million inhabitants.
The main idea was, and still is,
to propose a voluntary unification
that deliberately puts aside
the use of force,
and announces some principles
for the incremental setting up
of a peaceful post-geopolitical
transnational political power.
The European Construction
has long been a process
that was ignored by the public opinion
because it seemed
both opaque and of little importance
for the average European state of life.
The era of powerful,
but neglected technocracy,
probably began to decline
as early as 1992,
when the Treaty of Maastricht
paved the way
for a single continental currency.
The euro, and other aspects
of the instauration
of a European supranational power,
met a strong resistance
in the less urbanized areas.
This period clearly ended in 2005,
when the referendums
on the constitutional treaty
gave a negative result
in France and the Netherlands.
After the 2008 crisis,
many European citizens
welcomed the idea
of a strong commitment
from the European institutions
to save the financial system,
but blamed the sacrifices
that were demanded
from the workers, taxpayers,
and consumers.
In Greece, since 2010,
a significant part of the public opinion
sees its country
as an undesired protectorate
of the European Union.
As a matter of fact, every day,
European citizens can observe
the loss of momentum
of economic growth on the continent,
in spite of the incremental,
but substantial, elements of construction
of continental institutions.
The maps show that,
after the first stage of the 2008 crisis,
Europe was the last part
of the World to recover.
Europe is still one of the major,
if not the biggest,
node in the global economic network,
but it's relative decline is obvious.
This point wouldn't be so negative
if it only meant
that other regions of the World
were doing better
than they used to do before.
In fact, Europe's problem
has to do with the image of future,
its horizon of expectations.
The conservation of
a supposedly threatened heritage,
and the fear
that the European social model
would be under the assaults
of an unleashed globalization,
largely occupy European citizens’ minds.
Will the Europeans be able to invent
a renewed concept of future,
a new narrative for a shared progress?
This question remains unanswered so far.
The Europeans
will certainly be those required
to propose and discuss
fresh ideas on this issue.
If they gave up,
the risk of a defensive closing
must not be excluded,
as we can observe
the growing electoral success
of far-right, anti-EU,
anti-globalization,
and xenophobic parties.
European citizens
will also have to decide
where the border of their society
must be located.
Until now, the process of enlargement
has been based on voluntary adhesion
under the control of some key economic
and political parameters
imposed by the pre-existing members.
Within this process,
and although present-day Europe
is a ‘variable-geography’ space,
the European Union could include
about 50 states in the next decades,
with the entire Balkan region,
Turkey, Ukraine,
and why not trans-Caucasian states?
The following map
shows the current situation
of core and peripheries in Europe,
which suggests that inclusion
and integration should continue.
However,
there is a strong tendency to stop
or, at least, break,
the enlargement course
by using the argument
that the member states
have too many internal difficulties
to be able to welcome new beneficiaries
of a generous welfare state
as it exists in Europe.
This issue raises
a stimulating geographical problem.
When geopolitics is not the rationale
of intersociety relationships any more,
which spatial logics will prevail
in the construction
of a new kind of political construction,
such as the EU?
Another correlative question
concerns the interscale relation
between the EU and the World.
If globalization continues,
including its political dimension,
and tends to create a fully-fledged
society at level One,
what would be the specific role
of a continental,
that is, level Two, entity?
Here, again, the citizens,
inhabitants will have to decide.
An interesting study case
is given by Ukraine.
As Turkey,
the Western part of the former USSR,
has been a twilight zone.
Will it join Europe?
Would it stay back inside new Eurasian
or near Eastern influence areas,
or would it remain
in its historical hesitation stance?
Since its independence,
Ukraine has not only been crossed
by linguistic, cultural,
and political boundaries,
it has been, as a whole,
a border country,
a buffer zone
between Russia and Europe.
Since the victory
of the pro-European side
at the end of 2013,
after months of turmoil and violence,
a new phase has begun.
The Russian President, Vladimir Putin,
has decided to support separatists
in Crimea,
and annexed this formerly Russian region
to Russia again.
Armed separatists
and Russia-supported uprisings,
burst out in the southeastern part
of the country.
The Russian government
activated the weapon of gas prices
to impose a change
on Ukrainian leadership.
Doing this, however,
Putin, probably,
has lost a long-term capability
of influencing
the Western fringe of Russia.
The question whether the border
between Ukraine and Russia
puts Crimea and Donbas
in either of these countries,
is not so crucial.
The pivotal point is that a borderland
has been turned into a borderline.
After the Baltic countries,
Russian geopoliticians
have had to admit
that the traditional objective
of the Russian Empire,
that is, to play its moves in Europe,
which was made explicit
by Peter the Great,
at the beginning of the 18th Century,
is fading away.
The myth of the dual nature of Russia,
and of a continental borderline,
the Urals,
located in the very middle
of the Russian society,
probably ceased to exist in April 2014,
when Putin suggested to the Duma
to ratify the annexation of Crimea.
West of Russia,
Belarus remains
the only trophy territory
Putin could show
as evidence of a reconquest,
and this has been possible
only because of the fierce
dictatorial grip
his friend, Alexander Lukashenko,
has been imposing on the small country
for two decades.