From the very beginning of this course,
we have seen how important
the ‘spatial me’ is,
and, more generally, spatial agency,
or spatiality,
is as a power in contemporary societies.
We have equally observed how space can be
a powerful and shaping environment
and how it can be seen as a public good.
Inhabiting can be identified
as a meeting point
between spatiality and space.
Let's explain. Even when
they seem immobile,
the constitutive elements of a society
function as a dynamic configuration,
at least in reproducing
what which already exists,
but more often as a process of change.
And space is not an exception.
It is composed of actions--
those of the actors themselves,
which actors have injected
into objects that become active,
and, finally, those which have ended up
by crafting environments,
that is to say establishing
frameworks for action,
which may be modifiable by new actions.
The relation between spatiality and space
opens up the possibility
for multiple actions and futures,
shaped by the history of relationships
between societies and their parts -
individuals, collectives,
organizations, institutions –,
the emergence of the individual actor
being a major historical bifurcation.
The distinction between
‘Gemeinschaft’ and ‘Gesellschaft’
has been largely documented
by social sciences,
since it was first outlined
by Ferdinand Tönnies in 1887.
Max Weber, Émile Durkheim, Norbert Elias,
and many contemporary scholars,
converge in describing
the contemporary social world
in developed countries
as a society of individuals.
This implies that old
communal allegiances,
based on biological, religious,
economic or national principles,
are challenged by other forms
of social organization,
in which traditional structures
may not have vanished,
but enable a direct dialog between
individuals and society as a whole.
This is made possible
by new social apparatuses:
a powerful welfare state,
which provides to everyone
minimal ‘primary goods’,
a rule of the law state,
that transcends communal rules,
and forms of democratic governance,
which, at the least, prevent
the exclusion of ordinary citizens
from public deliberation.
A society of individuals is therefore
by no means less societal
than the former communal society.
On the contrary, it is characterized by
both more individuality and more society.
In any case, it is clear enough
that a society of individuals
gives a new consistency
to a specific relationship
between actors and spatial environments.
Finally, spatialities and spaces
generated by the humans
do not possess by themselves
any tragic characteristic.
Their destiny is not predetermined
and the Earth does not call out.
As a literary genre, space emerges
rather as a ‘drama’:
a tension which results from
the capacity of each individual
to affect the space of all the others,
as well as their own,
and this constitutes
a remarkably dramatic lever.
However, the play is written
at the same time as it is being acted out.
This is another confirmation
that spatialities as actors’ agency,
and space as societal environment,
are not dissociable.
In Session 2 we analyzed the limits
of Heidigger's conception of inhabiting,
a conception that privileges
rootedness, nearness, and fixity,
and proposed another approach
to inhabiting
that encompasses mobility,
otherness, and historicity.
Once reconciled with history,
the notion of inhabiting can become
both a fully spatial,
and fully social concept.
It offers a useful abstract
of an interactive, but balanced, relation,
that spatialities and spaces,
geographical actors
and geographical environments
can entertain.
But, the very interest of this concept
lies in the fragility
of its pragmatic implementation.
Building a single house
in a natural landscape
has the effect of modifying this landscape
in a significant manner.
Geographicity presents at once
an individual (spatiality)
and a societal (space) characters.
This creates a very sensitive tension,
and sometimes a very visible one.
Space is that environment which,
in a more explicit way than others,
inhabits us at the same time
as we inhabit it.
This is probably why the geographical
approach of social worlds
has a special power
to make visible simultaneously,
what, separately or together,
humans hold,
and of what holds humans together.
Said differently, how can I
make the world inhabitable
without making it uninhabitable
for others, and for me, among them?
That is the fundamental question
citizens ask
the social scientists of space.
Thus, space seems to be
a particularly vulnerable
environment par excellence.
Since modifications
made by a small number of actors
can have consequences
on all of the other actors,
it appears also
as a par-excellence expression
of the possible co-operative
dimension of social life.
Inhabiting is what happens
when environments enhance
the actors’ spatial freedoms
and when actors develop
the environment's capability
to make a living-together
possible and worthwhile.
This course is now ending.
Let's sum it up in one statement.
Spaces are made up by spatial agency
and spatial agency
is about spatial actors,
that is to say, everybody, each of us.
Hence, the last question
I would like to ask you:
what spatial actor would you like to be?