Ecological monitoring is a key tool
in protected areas management.
It provides information both
on the conservation state
of the values protected by the area,
but also, on the threats
these vales are facing.
Thanks to monitoring, the impacts
of our decisions can be assessed,
operations can be re-oriented
if needed,
and results can then be measured.
Monitoring also helps
to better understand ecosystem,
thereby equipping managers
for the benefits of conservation.
It involves many stakeholders
of the protected area,
and improves team cohesion.
Thanks to ecological monitoring,
operations can reported on
and decision makers
gain responsibility.
Finally, it is an excellent tool
to justify the financial support
for particular areas,
and to communicate on successes.
This is what this MOOC
is all about.
It is divided in four units.
Understanding what
ecological monitoring is,
how it is planned, implemented,
assessed and so on.
Knowing the most treatable
principles and statistical methods.
Discovering what techniques
to apply
depending  on the values
that are being monitored.
Finally, learning from
several examples directly
to confirm the field that will
illustrate everything we see.
Beatrice Chataigner from UICN,
Emmanuel Hema from the Ouagadougou
University in Burkina Faso
Inza Kore from the
Félix Houphouët-Boigny
University of Cote d'Ivoire
and Victor Panaretos from EPFL
will be helping me
during the course.
As usual, online material
is available to help you
making progress at your on speed.
Videos, quizzes,
additional readings or forum,
our Facebook page,
online descriptions to share
from your own experience.
There is no prerequisite to sign up
and of course, it's free.
If everything goes well,
you'll be able to sit in the exams
and receive the certificate.
There you go, now join this
and together,
let's make ecological monitoring
your success factor
for our particular areas.
See you very soon.