Hello and welcome to this
MOOC on ecological monitoring.
This MOOC is about a fundamental
tool for protected areas management.
It will help us understand
what ecological monitoring is,
what it's benefits
and limitations are
and how to implement it.
How to use the results
to improve our impacts on
conservation and so on.
In the first unit we will
introduce the concept of
ecological monitoring.
This will help us better understand
the conditions of such monitoring;
why you would do it?
What is it for? How are the values,
attributes and indicators defined?
What methods should be used?
At what cost?
What kind of sample should we
target and so and so.
The second unit will look into the
useful statistical methods
to carry out
ecological monitoring.
We will talk about the
general statistical concepts
and also about uses
applied to monitoring.
The third unit will
introduce different
monitoring techniques
used on the field.
How to monitor the
ecosystems or the vegetation,
mammals, birds,
directly or indirectly.
We will also present
some specific methods
that can be applied to
carnivores, primates,
migratory species,
et cetera.
Finally in the fourth unit
we will give practical examples
to illustrate the concept;
ecological monitoring applied to
peer networks, marine,
terrestrial sites, forest,
savanna, wetlands,
targeted species.
In other words a representative
sample of real-life possibilities.
There, now it's your turn.
Don't forget about the quizzes
and of course
the exams after each unit.
They will certainly help you
making good progress.
Have a
great MOOC.