Hello and welcome
to the first unit
of our MOOC on
ecological monitoring.
This unit introduces the concept
of ecological monitoring.
It will help us better understand
how this monitoring is operated.
No panic. We will go into further
details in the next unit.
Let's follow the line
to identify the questions
we need to
ask ourselves.
Why proceed to
ecological monitoring?
We will see why
it is important.
What it's connection
with planning is.
We will see
how it contributes
to the effectiveness
of our actions and so on.
What is ecological monitoring
and definitely what is it not?
How to differentiate it from
inventories or research for instance.
What is it for? How does it feed
the decision making process
or does it give
accounts on the state of
the protected area values;
on the pressures,
on the threats,
on the impact of our work?
How to define it's objectives.
More specifically we need to look at
what values to monitor.
What ecological attributes
characterize them; what indicators
are more important et cetera.
How to choose the monitoring method
depending on the
ecological attributes
we target, of course
but also the
context in which we work.
What is sampling and how
to organize our work
for a better
effort : result ratio.
At what cost because
this will determine our choices
in method, equipment,
staffing and so on.
What type of
analysis should be chosen?
This will prepare us for
the second unit
where will go into
more detail regarding
the statistics applied
to ecological monitoring.
Finally the unit will
end with a short summary
of everything
we've seen thus far.
There. Don't forget about the
quizzes between the sequences.
They can help you
make better progress.
Have an
excellent first unit.