Protected areas preserve values.
These values can be animal
and plant species
as well as ecosystems.
These are the values that need to be maintained
in a sustainable way.
It is, therefore, important to be able
to measure the current state
and the evolution of these values,
as well as to detect the threats
they are facing.
In Burundi, for instance,
an invasive plant species, the Lantana
has taken over the Rusizi National Park, completely.
To avoid this situation,
the problem should have been identified
upon finding the plant in the park,
but it is now probably too late.
The park has lost an important part
of it's ecological value now.
Ecological monitoring is a key step
in adaptive management,
but it is not the only tool that can get
information from the field.
Indeed.
Other means such as anti-poaching surveillance,
research, and tourism
can also provide a lot of information,
actually.
Okay. This is agreed, but ecological monitoring
remains the main source
to guide decisions, and actions,
for site management.
Yeah, sure.
In the early 2000s,
when the population of Black Rhinoceros
in the North Cameroon disappeared,
strict ecological monitoring,
like collecting droppings for instance,
would have allowed us to identify
the imminent threat of these extinction,
or at least to stop the useless surveillance
once the species disappeared.
We know that a protected area
is a special kind of territory
with several characteristics:
it is defined, recognized, dedicated, and so on,
and it is managed for the conservation
of nature.
Keep in mind, as this is its primary goal,
as we explained in the MOOC
on Protected Area Management
in the 4th sequence of the 1st module.
Ecological monitoring can be applied to many
territories and species
outside of protected areas as well.
For example, swallow populations
are being monitored in Europe
in order to measure the impact
of pesticides.
In the case of a protected area,
ecological monitoring intends to show
that the goal of the protected area
its conservation, is being achieved.
So monitoring is, hence, intentional
and targeted.
Indeed, and this is especially interesting
to have ecological monitoring
in a protected area
since it is, let's say usually, a significant
ecosystem on the national or regional level.
It contains complete, or at least sufficiently
representative,
ecological processes
for successful research.
Since the protected area is being managed,
it offers a good working base,
with means and infrastructures,
and, sometimes, available
and qualified staff.
A protected area allows
for long term monitoring,
and can provide historic data,
which increases knowledge.
It is a good place to experiment,
and it allows for  a wide distribution
of information,
to other protected areas of the same category,
for instance.
It can also be a good medium for sharing
results with different targets,
in schools or  universities,
but also with the general public.
Therefore, protected areas play an important
part in raising awareness for conservation.
As we saw in the MOOC on Protected
Area Management,
the management of protected areas is organized
according to a management plan,
defined in a participatory way
with clear goals
concrete activities, and assigned
responsibilities.
Ecological monitoring has to be integrated
to the preparation of this plan
to ensure it will give relevant indicators,
but also that it will be effectively
implemented.
It is useless to plan actions
that cannot be assessed
or to associate them with indicators
that cannot be measured.
Ecological monitoring must be discussed,
shared, and understood
by everybody involved in its implementation,
and the park's manager needs to take ownership
of the plan from the very start.
Ecological monitoring is obviously part
of the protected area management,
but it is also one of the tools used
to measure
the effectiveness of said management.
As we saw in the MOOC on the Protected
Area Management,
monitoring needs to be subject
to protocols
as well as to reliable methods
to be implemented.
It is important to note that it is one of the rare
possible sources of information
regarding the impact of our management
actions, or decisions.
For example, by showing the evolution
of the environment over time,
according to what we do,
or what we did,
Therefore, regular monitoring of the state
of plants
can show that repetitive bush fires
in grasslands
lead to the disappearance of some useful
grass species.
This finding will allow to choose
a better adapted season
and a better periodicity for the ignition
of those fires.
Ecological monitoring accounts
for the state of the protected area
and identifies the pressures and threats
it is facing.
It is important to base this ecological
monitoring
on matters that will allow making the best
decisions in controlling those risks.
Since means will necessarily be limited,
monitoring needs to be prioritized.
This is very important.
This should not compete with more
urgent actions in the protected area.
This reinforces the necessity
for good coordination
with all those involved in the management,
in and around the protected area,
from the implementation
of the monitoring protocol onwards.
To make it simple,
a useless ecological monitoring program
is worse than none at all.
Ecological monitoring is also
and important tool
in training and motivating staff.
It empowers rangers, eco-guides,
volunteers,
and includes them in the management
process in whole,
not as mere implementers,
but as the providers of information
that is at the very heart
of the decision-making process.
By giving access to new tools,
such as cyber-trackers, GPS,
or camera, like here on the screen,
ecological monitoring broadens
agents' skills,
and since they are in touch
with researchers,
their personal knowledge
is being developed.
Monitoring is also a powerful tool for collecting
funds for a protected area.
By providing reliable and transparent
information
regarding the state of the conservation
and the progress that has been made,
it makes is possible to justify the use
of the funds that they have received.
Yes, in a documented way for once.
By proposing new targets or activities,
it justifies access to additional
funding.
It serves as a tool for accountability.
We know that. We understand that.
But also for prospection.
Ecological monitoring is also a vector
for internal organization.
It strengthens the collaboration between different
departments of the protected area,
like the admin, the research, the surveillance,
communication, training departments, and so on,
because it is multidisciplinary and needs
everybody's input to be successful.
For example, storing collected data
is key to monitoring sustainability.
To process this information within
the protected area,
and store all the data,
the entire organization is engaged.
Beyond the management aspects,
ecological monitoring, of course,
has its own distinctive role,
which is to inform on species
and ecosystems.
Now, we know that.
You get to know what species inhabit
a protected area,
in what numbers, during which seasons,
at what places, and so on.
On this basis,
ecological monitoring with measure
the variations in space and time,
short, medium, long term.
You can then understand the interactions,
measure the impacts of the pressures,
and better estimate samples
to be taken.
For example, monitoring elephant populations
within the Kruger National Park,
and monitoring their impacts on plants,
has allowed determining the threshold at which
said population needs to be maintained at
in order to prevent damages on the ecosystem
that will also be detrimental
to other species.
The next step is to figure out how to do it,
but that's another story.
Ecological monitoring is crucial
in the PA management process.
It is quite surprising to find
that many parks
don't have a monitoring protocol
in place at all.
Others have one,
but it doesn't give any information
on the state of the values
or it is based on outdated techniques,
or the produced results are not understood
or shared or used.
And this is not the case in a minority
of sites, unfortunately.
it's the situation of a vast majority
of protected areas,
where management has turned into a plain
and systematic repetition of actions
with no effort put into assisting
the impacts, actually.
Sadly.
So sad.