In a protected area, the idea of
environmental monitoring
can take on different meanings,
and it is important to
clearly define the terms.
Let's start with inventory.
To make it simple,
the inventory is a census.
It can be qualitative, as in,
what species are present in my
protected area?
It can also be quantitative,
how many individuals of this
species exist?
The inventory needs to be made
by using standardized methods,
and is generally set
in a limited time frame.
It is essentially a data provider,
and is not meant
to answer a specific question.
It is simply there to give
information regarding the condition
of the ecosystem at
a certain point in time.
The basic information gathered
from the inventory
is of the presence/absence kind,
like for example the existence
of a given species
at a specific place,
at a specific time.
Now let's talk about
ecological monitoring.
Monitoring in itself is based
on a series of data collections
repeated over time.
It consists in systematically gathering
useful pieces of information over time.
Monitoring has a specific goal
and answers the following
kind of question,
what is the condition of the park
through the seasons?
But it can also be introduced
to compare the data we collect
with a known standard.
It can be a baseline condition
for example like,
the number of animals of a certain
species per unit area,
or in reference to
a desired state,
what would be the number
of animals of this species
if there was no hunting?
Here is another example,
to measure the impact of fire,
isolate a plot where the vegetation
will be preserved
and will serve as a reference
that will allow to understand
the evolution of several
elements like the environment,
the species, depending
on the fire.
And this information will help
to take relevant decisions
for the management.
We can then quickly classify
ecological monitoring
in 3 categories.
The monitoring based on, say
curiosity, referring to a type of
essentially leaning to a better
knowledge of the environment,
without necessarily having
a problem to solve.
Mandatory monitoring,
in other words, the regular
follow up of indicators
that are essential for management,
like, for example measuring
the burnt surfaces
in a park every year.
And then action oriented monitoring
whose aim is to solve
a precise problem
and is therefore developed specifically
in relation to this problem,
which is by the way not necessarily
linked to a matter of daily management
in the protected area.
Okay, let's move on to
a different word
and approach the surveillance.
So surveillance in this context
covers two dimensions.
The park surveillance can be
an inventory program
systematically repeated in order
to provide time series of measures.
Surveillance consists in repeating
the collection of data over time,
with no preconceived idea of
the evolution of those parameters
that are being measured.
Therefore, surveillance
is essentially  descriptive.
You can, for example
focus on
gathering meteorological data
in a park,
and file them, keep them
in the event
of having to use them later
on for research.
Surveillance also refers to
the control of activities
taking place in the park,
like the fight against poaching.
If this this type of surveillance
is not directly linked
to an environmental monitoring,
very often, the rangers also
carry out ecological surveys
during their patrols.
There is a small frontier
between monitoring and surveillance,
but the difference is real,
monitoring has a specific goal,
it answers a management problem.
Surveillance may only be a process
of collecting information
that may or may not
be used subsequently.
For example, the surveillance
of a river
can help to detect a variation in
quantities of fish present over time.
But if you are not looking
at a particular species,
you won't be able to link these
variations to the diet
of the white cheeked otter living
in the same river for instance.
Last but not least, let's
look at research.
A research program is based
on a starting assumption
and aims at validating it
after having processed data
and analysed the results.
Part of it can be experimental
and take a step back from
data collected in the field.
Research is the main component
of the management scheme
but goes beyond the sole needs in
management of the protected area.
It encompasses
not only monitoring,
but also allows
a better understanding
of the way the site is run.
For instance, the drop
in fertility of the swallows
can be observed in the course
of a multi-year
environmental monitoring program,
but it is by specifically studying
the diet of these birds
that we are able to see that
the problem can be pin pointed
to the use of certain pesticides,
and that is provided by research.
In brief, the ecological monitoring
of a protected area
consists in following the values
of the territory
in a methodical way, over time
and with a specific goal.
It gives information about
the condition of the protected area
in the course of time,
and is hence
in a position to guide
the site management.