Ecological monitoring has several
key functions in a protected area.
As we have already seen,
it is not just a photo
at a given moment,
but it is conducted
for a specific purpose.
Thanks to ecological monitoring,
you get to know the species of fauna
and flora populating the protected area.
Their abundance, their significance,
and the relationships between them.
You also get to measure the temporal
and geographical distribution
and observe potential changes
in all these parameters
in the short, medium, and long haul,
as well as the biotic and abiotic
factors influencing the species
such as the soil condition, the fires,
climate variations and so on.
Knowing the original state
of the environment
in itself is a fundamental step
to being able
to determine the changes induced
by management,
or by events that escape
from manager's control.
But this baseline condition
is of little relevance
if you don't link it to
the optimal condition
in which the protected area
should be.
Too many conservation projects
still set as baseline condition
the state in which they found the
protected area at the beginning.
Because of this, the goals set
to improve the protected area
can lead to a state that is
actually quite average
compared to that in which
the site should be
if work would have been done
correctly and continuously.
It would in fact be wiser
to estimate the protected area's
ideal condition,
and then to set a rate
of the progress
that is intended to be made
to achieve this goal.
This would make the project's
impact more understandable
and make analysis of the cost
benefit ratio more consistent.
On the basis of this
acute knowledge of the site,
monitoring allows you to determine
the heritage values
of the protected area, those that are
targeted by management actions.
It also helps to identify
the pressures, and the threats,
the values are facing,
their scope, importance,
and evolution.
Monitoring gives information
regarding the interactions
between all the identified factors,
be they biotic or abiotic,
in space and in time.
But also on the evolution
of these indicators
that will allow measuring
the protection
of the threatened values.
Climate change is a good
example of alteration
suffered by an environment that can
only be detected in the long haul,
through strict monitoring that
requires special targeting
to detect the threat
and assess it.
Yes, absolutely, this work
on values
will enable prioritizing actions,
both according to what
we expect,
key values to preserve, and to
what is indeed feasible,
depending on the means
we have.
The understanding of the way
the protected area works
is key to avoid seeking
to follow indicators
that are too complicated
when more accessible and
cheaper ones exist.
For instance, monitoring populations
of hoofed mammals in the forest
is usually simply done
by measuring the damages
caused to trees in
benchmarked areas.
If the amount of damage increases,
more animals are collected,
and conversely,
if the damages decrease too much,
we limit the number of animals
being collected in order to let
the populations recover.
The management plan includes
a part where
the ecological monitoring
is described.
It is crucial to think through
this part according to the staff's
practical needs, theoretical
and in skills,
as well as the actual means
at hand.
Let's not forget that the analysis
of results provided by monitoring
will allow to determine
new management actions
and thereby new
monitoring procedures.
Thus, ecological monitoring truly
is a major component
of adaptive management.
As such, management decisions
will evolve over time
thanks to ecological monitoring
and vice versa.
This monitoring will
specifically determine
if the species of special interest, that
are the values of the protected area
remain within acceptable limits,
so the standards
for their conservation.
It will help understand
if the pressures
and the threats are being controlled
and redirect management according
to the changes that were detected.
It enables to prioritize the means
allocated to the conservation
according to the effectiveness
and to the pressures
that arise but also to
communicate the successes
that have been achieved and
to learn from past mistakes.
As we already mentioned earlier,
the management plan defines
its goals at different levels,
and the collected information
during the ecological monitoring
will allow to measure the degree
to which the program's objectives
are met.
Monitoring will then directly
measure the manger's ability
to execute the plan and achieve
the projected results,
and to give an unbiased assessment
of his work quality.
Ecological monitoring also
shows the necessity
to have managers and scientists
working together
if you want to achieve the best
adaptive management possible.
For instance, a recent study carried
out on 200 protected areas
in 34 countries showed
the positive correlation
between the good results obtained
regarding conservation
and the existence of adapted
ecological monitoring.
The protected areas
where monitoring
is not or just partially implemented
show the lowest success rate.
However, ecological monitoring
is sometimes perceived
as too expensive and offers
too little economic return.
Of course, monitoring an ecosystem
is a long term investment
because change occurs slowly.
But too many decisions
are made
'out of habit' or by people
thinking in the short term
without even trying
to identify
if better actions could be carried
out for the protected area.
A good example is the early detection
of the emergence of invading species
that requires strict
ecological monitoring.
The potential risk needs
to have been identified,
and thereby it is
important to know
the potentially
dangerous species,
to have well-trained staff
to setup a permanent monitoring
protocol, etc.
Generally speaking,
since we are talking
about a potential risk
and not a reality,
all these things aren't done because
they are viewed of little importance
by managers actually.
When a species, here
we can see (INAUDIBLE),
is eventually detected,
it is generally too late for a small
intervention to suffice,
and costs related to the
rehabilitation of
the environment exceeds by far
that of ecological monitoring
that should have taken place.
So think twice
before putting off a much needed
ecological monitoring program
because of your budget.