We already saw the role
of ecological monitoring
in a particular area  is to get
information on its value condition
and thereby to asses the impact
of management actions
of these values over time.
For instance, in Ol Kinyei,
a conservancy in Kenya
one of the values is the migration
of wildebeest from the mountain
to the nearby Mara ecosystem.
This is a value that matches
a single species:
the wildebeest.
In the same conservancy,
another value is the Acacia forest
that we can see here
and this time, the value matches
a habitat as a whole.
It is clear that monitoring
these two values
calls on different criteria.
This is why we will look at
which criteria
can characterize the values.
This is what we call
key ecological attributes.
A key ecological attribute
is shaped
by the vital characteristics
of a value's ecology.
. By identifying these attributes
you can describe the value
and measure its viability.
Ecological attributes are based
on some fundamental
ecological concepts.
To make it simple,
we can say that there are 3
main categories
of ecological attributes
which characterize species
and their habitat.
The first one is the size
of the natural habitat
or the abundance of the
considered value  under territory.
For instance, the number
of elephants present
In the Maasai Mara Reserve.
The condition of the value,
the structure of the population
and the interactions
that exist between individuals
such as the compatibility between
the number of predators
and the density of preys
within a park.
Finally, the context in which
the value involves.
This includes
the ecological processes
that can contribute to maintaining
the presence of this value
such as the flood, the pond,
the fire regime, or the connectivity
for species moving
from one habitat to another.
After having identified
the ecological attributes,
for each value, you simply need
to determine
which ones are key for its survival
in the long run
and consequently important
to include
in the ecological monitoring
process.
Taking the example of a tree,
the best way to check its health
will be by assessing the numbers
of flowers produced per year
rather than looking at its size
because it can grow slowly actually.
But even if these attributes
are describing the values
they are often too vague
to be assessed
effectively and at low cost.
Hence the necessity
to define indicators
that will give us information
regarding the state
of the attributes over time.
So roughly,
an indicator can be a measurable
characteristic
of the ecological attribute,
for example,
the total number of adults
of a population of impalas.
This indicator can also
be an aggregation
of several characteristics
of an attribute
combined n only one index.
For example, the evolution
of a forest's canopy,
the top of the trees
can be measured
by the number of species
encountered.
So, choosing a good indicator
to characterize
the ecological attributes
is key to the success
of the monitoring,
this isn't an easy task though.
So let's list some elements
to defining a good indicator:
They need to be measurable,
in a quantitative or qualitative way
by procedures giving reliable,
repeatable and precise information.
They need to be predictable
over time, meaning
the indicator should have the same
meaning for everybody at all times.
They should be specific,
so the indicator is always
associated with said
ecological attribute
in a non-ambiguous way,
and is not affected
by other factors.
The indicator has to be noticeable
should vary significantly
in response to the variations
of the threats or actions we engage.
to conserve it.
It has to be swift
and able to rapidly detect
the changes
of the ecological attribute
so that taking the appropriate
management measures
on time is possible.
It needs to be easy to collect
and not require several operators
or pricey materials, in the best
cost-effective way of course.
Finally, it should facilitate
the communication of results,
and therefore be easy to understand
in order to allow the public
to better get the situation
of the protected area
through its attributes.
Once the indicator is identified,
the first step will be to determine
its current state which will serve
as baseline condition.
Then, define the desired state
you want to achieve
for this indicator.
This will enable the analysis
of results
of the ecological monitoring
in view of the baseline condition
of the values,
and the conservation goals
or for each of them.
Obviously, there will be
a certain fluctuation
of the indicators
within an acceptable area.
This is what we call the acceptable
level of variation of indicators.
Thanks to these variation
thresholds,
we can determine what managers
deem to be the normal level
of change of the considered value,
and thereby to define what level
of alteration
of the ecological attribute
will be deemed too severe
and need an action plan then.
The acceptable level of variation
also defines the level
of restoration
of the ecological attribute
when needed.
As you can see, it's rather simple.
The steps to follow are first
to identify
the key ecological attributes
of each value.
Then, to select
the relevant indicators
for each attribute
and to characterize
the baseline condition
of the attribute by indicators.
Finally, you need to determine
the acceptable levels
of variation of the indicators
that will obviously contain
the desired state of conservation
for the considered attribute.
Nothing really complicated,
just a little bit of methodology.