We've seen which indicators
to assess over time
to determine the
health of the values
by following the key
ecological attributes.
In practice how can these
assessments be made in the field?
Actually choosing an assessment
approach will depend
on the ecological
attribute to assess
and therefore on its
ecological characteristics.
For instance, a species
that is abundant enough
to be detected from
afar in the savannah
could be subject to
an aerial count.
One this approach wouldn't
work for: a nocturnal species
or one living
in a dense forest.
You also need to make sure
that the chosen approach is
precise enough to carefully
detect all the variation
of the ecological attributes
so the approach needs to have
broader detection limits
than the range
of variation
of the attributes itself.
For instance, if you want to
assess the evolution of plants
on a small area,
remote sensing from
a satellite image
wont be the best solution
because of it's
low resolution.
The approaches to measure
the variation of
ecological attributes can be
direct, meaning the focus
on the attribute itself
like the number of individuals
of a species
for example
or they can also be indirect
and in this case
focus on the variable connected
to the attribute
like the number of tracks
on the ground or the nest
or the damages on the tree
or the droppings, et cetera.
Imagine you want to measure the
concentration of chimpanzees
in a park. Are they living
in dense forest
where it is difficult to see
them through the leaves?
It is better to count their nests
which are much easier to detect.
So the nests are in this case
an indirect indicator
of the presence and the
number of chimpanzees.
We see here that the choice of
a suitable approach
requires good knowledge of the
ecological attributes in question.
It is thus not relevant
to choose an approach only
because the managers are used
to using it if it does not
allow to properly measure
the variations of the attribute.
The monitoring results would be
unusual and the time span
to set it up will be
most certainly wasted.
Whatever the approach, the
collected data can be qualitative
meaning they are of
presence/absence kind
or classified in categories
like rare, occasional,
frequent, abundant,
et cetera.
They can also be quantitative.
For example, the number
of individuals or tracks
in a specific area.
Quantitative data are precise
but generally require
creative thought
to collect.
And that's not all.
The method used for counting
should be the most reliable
in measuring what we want
in view of the context of
the protected area itself.
So it's important to choose the
method involving the least bias.
For example, if you are looking
to estimate the density of
antelope in a park, you could
count from the ground by foot,
by car or by overflying
the zone in low altitude.
If you are in a park where
poaching is a problem,
an animal runs away
as you get closer
counting directly from the ground
may be difficult since
the animals will run away
before you have time to see them.
Aerial counting would be, in this
case, the most suitable
because it allows for the detection
of animals at a greater distance.
Bias can occur at different levels.
It can be linked to the observer
who makes mistakes when
identifying a species
or estimating the size
of a group of the species
for instance and it can also be
linked to the monitoring conditions
like bad weather that can affect
the quality of observation
during the collection of
data in the field.
Bias can also be connected to
the type of habitat.
In zones with dense vegetation
identifying certain species
will be more difficult.
We saw that for the chimps.
It can be connected to the
time of the day or year
because some species are active
or not and therefore visible
or not only at certain times.
This needs to be taken
into account
in the protocol.
Finally, you also need to understand
that some biases are inevitable
and it's important to estimate
whether or not they are likely
to have fact effects
the validity of the final results
of ecological monitoring.
So beforehand you need to
identify all the possible sources
of bias in order to attempt
to control or reduce them
if possible.