We have already seen
what attributes offer a given value
to manage of,
and how to do so.
But, all the aspects still need
to be clarified.
Yes, for example, do we need
to assess the entire population
of the monitored species,
or rather it's entire habitat,
or will assessing only
a part of it be enough?
How many assessments need to be made
to get a result accurate enough
for good management
decision making?
When, how often and where
do these assessments
of the chosen ecological attribute
needs to be made?
Well, this is precisely
the sampling plan
that will allow us to answer
these practical questions.
Sampling is particularly useful,
when a monitored value covers
a large area.
Indeed monitoring everything
will not only be expensive
but also unsuitable because
it gives way to bias
that will skew the final results.
Particularly if the monitor species
is mobile
or if the targeted eco-systems
spread over
too many inaccessible areas.
The total count of the vast
protected area
of a very mobile species
creates a high risk
of unknowingly counting
the same animal several times
leading to false results.
There are cases, however,
in which sampling is not required.
For instance, when a considered
values spread over a small surface
which can be entirely covered
proceeding to counting the values,
entire population
would be in that case very easy.
So same to sampling,
you only need to asses a portion
of the value.
And then to extrapolate the result
to the entire population.
Like, to the surface area
of the forest for instance
or to the entire population
of the animal specie
and this portion of the value
that is being assessed
is what is call the sample.
That is it.
Now, what steps need to be
followed to draw a sampling plan?
First, you need to decide
where in the particular area
you need to collect this information
In other words, what will
be the sample size?
Be careful, in order to get
an adequate picture,
it is essential
for the sampling size
to reflect the entire value.
This is what we call
the representativeness
of the sample against the species'
global population
within a particular area.
To guarantee this, its better
to proceed to random sampling.
This way you are making sure
each sample unit of the population
has an equal chance
of being selected.
And since we are looking
to asses specific parameters
of a species in a given habitat,
it may be relevant
to proceed to a random, stratified,
or clustered sampling.
There are indeed quite offensive
substantial variations
within the protected area
for the ecological attribute
that is being assessed,
and this can be caused
by environmental guidance
or by difference in management
between different areas
of the protected area.
In this type of situation,
it can be useful to divide a site
into sub-units let's say, or strata,
that refer to different
characteristics
of the considered
ecological attributes.
Like the different densities
of a single species
according to it's location
for instance.
This way, you can sample
each stratum separately.
Estimation-based strata
are then combined
to give an estimation
of the whole protected area
for this attributes.
Stratified sampling is therefore,
generally used
to make estimations more accurate.
The second step of designing
the sampling plan
consists in choosing the size and
the  number of samples to collect.
The step is very important.
It essentially depends
on the degree of precision
and at which we want to assess
the considered attribute.
Because the more precision
you want,
the more samples you will
need to collect, but obviously,
the more there is to sample,
the more expensive it will be.
The third step consist in deciding
on the sample collection
calendar
in the identified sampling area,
At what time of the year,
and of day, will they take place?
And also, how often?
These choices, essentially depend
on the biological cycles
of the monitored values.
For instance, it's best to choose
the time of year or day
when animals are more active
to be sure the observers
will be able to spot them.
Yes, monitoring populations
of winter migratory bird population
should be done in the middle
of the winter
when the expected population
of birds have arrived
and are not ready to leave yet.
Like these bee eaters for instance.
Plants are better monitored
after flouring period.
Otherwise, you risk counting
only the foreign plants
and forget to detect the stems
that don't floral discharge.
Deciding on the frequency
of assessments,
depends essentially on the speed
at which changes occur
within the considered attribute.
For instance, endangered
animal species can decline rapidly
due to bad management.
and you will then need to increase
the frequency of assessment
of relevant indicators.
Like we see with this
black rhino for instance.
Hopefully, this will allow
to react on time
if it's not too late.