A complete ecological
monitoring protocol implies
value, ecological attributes,
indicators to assess the attributes
but also a data collection method
and a sampling plan
that are effective, precise, realistic,
feasible, unrepeatable over time
whoever the people involved in
it's implementation may be.
Now the question is
can all this be done in view of
the available resources
within a protected area?
So let's see what
resources are need to
implement such
a protocol.
A data collection method comes
with specific equipment
for the collection process,
storage and data analysis.
Sometimes staff needs to be
trained specifically
to be able to use
this equipment properly.
The monitoring process
will consequently
have a cost in purchasing
and maintaining the equipment
but also in the time spent
training the staff
in charge of collecting
and analyzing the data.
For instance, buying your GPS
or camera trap
generates an expense of
a couple of hundred euros per device
to which the battery, the transfer
and data processing software
need to
be added.
This can seem a detail for certain
parks but it can also be
too expensive orders
where simple maps are still used
for localizing the
area of observation.
It's not very precise, indeed
but of course it's also,
it cost's
almost nothing.
Training the staff can be
a rewarding role
but it can sometimes
be useless.
It is a case when trained
agents are transferred
before having the
opportunity or the time
to particularly apply
their knowledge.
Finally, and this is important.
You need to check if the staff
have the ability to fill in
the sheet properly or to
implement other way
of reporting that
are adapted to
the observer's level.
As for the chosen sampling plan,
it will determine
the number of data
collecting campaigns
to do in different places
as well as their frequency
during the year,
for instance.
This will have a cost
in working time, travelling,
mobilizing vehicles,
logistics, et cetera.
For instance, the table shown here
compares the sampling plan of
3 different approaches to monitor
the birds during breeding season.
The contact point approach is
the least time consuming
over the year. It's about 8 hours
of work but also
the one giving the least
detailed results.
This approach will be most adapted
in places with few staff at hand
to collect data or if the dense
vegetation prevents access
to certain key sampling sites
that would be required
when using the tools or approaches,
the grid plan and the transect plan.
The cost of an ecological
monitoring protocol
as a time factor and can have an
outsourced expertise cost
if there is a need to implement
some specific monitoring steps that
the protected area staff itself
wont be able to do alone.
To guarantee it's
long-term sustainability,
it is however better for
the ecological monitoring
to be done
by the manager himself
along with his properly
trained staff.
If the ecological monitoring
protocol is clear and unique
the manager will be able
to do all the sampling,
data collection, data analysis
procedures himself
and this contributes to
the global strengthening
of the park's
capabilities.
In short, you need to choose
a protocol that matches
the available human and
financial resources
in a protected area
in the medium haul
while making sure this
protocol is effective enough
to detect indicators to assess
with as little bias as possible.
Estimating the monitoring cost
should be done while planning
and implementing
the ecological monitoring process.