For each value of
the protected area,
ecological monitoring protocols
are drawn up and together
they form the global
monitoring program of the territory.
The only thing left to do
is to implement them.
The staff in charge will collect,
store and analyze the data
throughout the year following
this established scheduled.
You need to make sure though
that the psychological monitoring
remains consistent overtime,
meaning that the collected data
will be comparable
from one collection campaign
to another over several years.
This quality control is facilitated
by the creation of a clear
technical manual that guarantees
the compatibility of data
and the repeat-ability
of the used approaches overtime.
This technical manual should
describe in detail
all the protocols.
In other words, it tracks the data
from when they are collected
up to the analysis.
It guides the ecological monitoring.
Thus, any kind of variation
from this manual,
be it connected to observers
or to the method used,
is to be recorded overtime
in this manual and then
incorporated to the results
of statistic test.
The manual should first describe
how the data
will be recorded in the field.
There are several option available
on the paper form,
through a recording tool as
symbol through that
we can see it there,
or a smart phone application.
The choice depends on the quality
of information together,
on the means at hand,
and what would be
the most practical tool
for staff in the field.
This is why it is very important
for the users to test
the chosen tool first.
For instance in conservancy
around Maasai Mara in Kenya,
several connection tool
have been tested;
phone like a smartphone app
as well as a smart tool
and the rangers after having
tested all these tools
have finally chosen
the smart phone app
as being the easiest one to use
in the field to collect
and store all the data.
Then the manual should state
how the data needs to be stored.
There are two important criteria
to consider here.
The first, you need an easy to use
database that allow
to easily extract the data
to analyze.
Microsoft Access for instance
is a good example
of a simple database that enables
the heavy handling
of data for different types
of analysis.
And then excel sheets
are even easier to use
and offer better options
to process the digital data
and they are also easy
to transport to statistical software
or GIA software for special data.
I know the key element is that,
the data, need to persist
over several years.
It is therefore crucial
to do backups
on the next day on our drive
for instance,
and to secure the database
to avoid losing the information.
And a good solution for this
is to appoint one person
responsible for the database
to make sure it is updated
and that everything works,
and the other users
will be able to access
the database of course,
but only to conceal the data
and not to edit it.
Obviously, creating
and maintaining a database
is not an earning itself,
we have the data
but who will analyze them
and when?
To often the data piles up
and nobody uses it,
so the manual also need to say
who will do what and when.
Let's remember that
analyzing the data
for ecological monitoring
needs to enable comparing the data
of a sample at a predefined
thresholds
like the threshold of viability
of a species for instance.
Also to compare the data
of a collected sample
at different point in time,
to see if there are
any notable variation over time
in this same sample.
The analysis usually implies
using hypothesis test
and confidence intervals
which are detailed in this module
in the session on statistics.
Hypothesis test will allow
for instance
to show that they're may or may not
have been some sort of variation
in partly the entire population.
However, this information is often
of limited interest
because we know
that there will be variations
due to the dynamic nature of the
animal population and habitats.
What is more interesting
is finding out how important
this variation is, and if it is,
let's say, ecologically significant.
This is where confidence intervals
are useful to describe the normal
or abnormal variation range.
Let's keep in mind that the use
of inadequate statistic test
or neglecting some biases
in the analysis
can lead to serious mistakes
and interpretation.
The person in-charge of
analyzing the data  should therefore
have good knowledge on statistics.
He needs, he or she,
needs to be around to measure
the possible biases
particularly well.
Finally, once the data has been
described and analyzed,
the results have to be interpreted
and presented clearly.
Strangely enough, this step
is often the longest
and the most complicated.
Because, let's not forget
that the results
need to meet the objectives
for which the monitoring
has been set up.
Namely, informing
the decision makers on the state
of the protected area's values.
Thus, the quality
of ecological monitoring
is also measured by it's capacity
to be understood
by the decision makers and thereby,
to guide the management
of the protected area
to changing the management practices
where it's needed.
An interesting example
are the maps
from the geographic
information system that easily
convey the evolution and the
distribution of certain species
present in the protected area
overtime,
allowing thereby,
pragmatic decision making.
And we can see on this one,
the distribution of some wild life
in a park in Cameroon,
of the Cameroon.