In this module, we've seen
what ecological monitoring
a protected area means
and that it intends
to asses the state
of the territory's values.
These values are characterized
by ecological attributes
which are described by indicators.
Ecological monitoring
follows a protocol
that specifies assembly plan
and approach to use.
So, let's summarize the steps
to follow to implement
ecological monitoring.
First off, you need to identify
the values to monitor,
the ones that matter to the
management  of the protected area
and that could be part of a
sensible ecological monitoring plan.
It can be an animal species
or an ecosystem
within the protected area,
for instance.
You then determine
the key ecological attributes.
The one that will characterize
the value and help understand
the state of the protected area,
the density of the species
that is being monitored for instance
or it's population dynamics
or even original floral composition
of the chosen ecosystem.
It is generally useful
to specify some indicators
easily measurable to express
these ecological attributes.
In other words, the number
of individuals
of the targeted species,
the age distribution,
or even the presence or absence
of invasive species
within the ecosystem.
The next step consist of identifying
the acceptable limits
within which the
ecological attributes may vary.
The limit between
a healthy attribute and one
that requires intervention.
An example is to set the minimal
number of individuals
that indicates the endangerment
of the species or on the other hand,
a maximum number that implies
an excessive number of individuals
that puts the ecosystem at risk.
Then come the choice in method
to measure these indicators
which would of course
take into account
the monetary values
but also the capabilities
of the protected area itself
in terms of means and skills.
You can either choose to directly
count the animals
or indirectly by monitoring tracks
for example,
these decisions should be based
on the context
in which you work and the results
you hope to obtain.
Well, the approach as in, you need
to draw up the sampling plan
that will ensure obtained results
will be as usable, precise,
and correct as possible.
You can then proceed to counting
all the individuals
near water point
if the species is localized
or on the other hand, assembling
10% or 20% of the park
if the species
is spread out equally.
For instance, monitoring invasive
plant species is done
by counting the new stems
in random transects.
And then collect the data
according to the chosen method
and sampling plan.
What maters in this step
is to follow drawer pools
and to do the work
with precision.
If you don't, you give way
to an acceptable bias
for the data processing.
And the data collected
should be stored
and remain available for future use
because they guarantee
the truthfulness and the reliability
of the monitoring.
They especially ensure
that another user
will obtain the same result
later on with the same data.
Exactly, and this data
will then be analyzed
and the obtained result will be
transformed into information.
Thereby, the animal account
is rendered into a density
in the park, which can then
be compared to a non-standard
for this kind of ecosystem
and the species.
At this point, and according
to the  determined monitoring goals,
you should get an idea of the
monitoring values condition now.
For instance, the questions around
invasive plant species,
we started a discussion, should now
be answered;
what species are present,
how many, where,
offers do they present, et cetera.
And depending these health condition
and the predefined limits
for the attributes
we have defined before,
the decision will be made
and actions put into place
to maintain protected area
in a good condition
or on the other hand,
restore an attribute
that may have been damaged.
If animals become too scarce,
we would, for example,
need to change the strategy
and the fights against poaching,
if we have one.
If the environment is invaded
by an invasive plant species,
you change the rate
of fire ignition or you proceed
to manual extraction.
And all these needs to be repeated
as often as needed,
to feed the decision making process
of adoptive management,
because the monitoring is in fact
just the part of a larger cycle
that it tends to manage
the territory
in the best way as possible.