Welcome back to part three
of this chapter.
So, it's also interesting to look at
two-bond coupling constants,
so, what we're talking about
typically, here, is the coupling
between a proton
and another proton,
mediated by two bonds attached,
for example, to a common carbon.
And in the case here,
if we look at the proton-proton coupling
between these two protons
attached to the same carbon,
because these protons are not equivalent,
it turns out that we can measure
the coupling between them,
and these couplings, as you see,
are in the vicinity of a few hertz,
and they are critically dependent
on the question of
if the substituent X here
is an electron-donating
or -withdrawing group.
In this case, the dependence
is even more pronounced.
We see here, this is a coupling
between two of the protons
attached to the same carbon.
This is X, and now we're talking
about this coupling here,
and it turns out that these couplings
are generally negative,
and they are in the vicinity
of -10 to -17 hertz.
Incidentally, you may not have heard
of negative couplings before;
very often, in the literature,
NMR literature,
nobody mentions the sign of the coupling,
and what people actually report is simply
the absolute value of the coupling.
Of course, if you do it that way,
you cannot see the sign.
The fact is that it is rather tricky
to determine the sign,
and it takes a bit
of understanding of NMR,
and particuarly
of two-dimensional spectroscopy,
of multiple-resonance,
in order to detect the sign.
But, signs have been measured,
and can certainly be calculated.
Now, some people have been looking
for very exotic couplings,
so that they have a chance
to get a record in the Guinness Book,
and here, for example,
we have a very long-range coupling
between two protons separated
by one, two, three, four, five bonds.
Because of the delocalized structure
of the electrons,
this is about 2.2 hertz--
mind you, all units in this chapter
are given in hertz.
And we can even go to seven bonds,
and it turns out that we then have
a negative coupling. Rather strangely.
You may wonder how one can measure this,
because these two protons
are magnetically equivalent.
Well, there is no multiplet structure,
but what you do is,
you replace one of them with deuterium,
and then it becomes inequivalent,
and you have a long-range J-coupling,
and in this case, you can see that JHH
is proportional to JHD,
provided we multiply
by the ratio of γH over γD.
So, we measure H-D
in an asymmetric molecule,
and then apply this rule in order to draw
a conclusion about the H-H coupling.
More straightforward is benzene groups.
It turns out that ortho couplings
between neighboring protons--
so this is an ortho coupling, of course--
is somewhere betwen seven and ten hertz,
depending on the substituents.
Meta couplings are smaller,
and para couplings
are typically on the order
of less than one hertz.
So, this is smaller,
and this is almost negligible,
although, of course, they can be detected.
Likewise, if we have molecules
that are rigid--
this doesn't work if they are floppy,
but if they are rigid, then we can have
long-range couplings,
provided the arrangement of the bonds
is in a so-called W structure,
that allows one to convey the information
through the electrons.
There are some interesting properties
of J-coupling constants
that are worth knowing.
Some people have an encyclopedic
knowledge about these things.
First of all, one can distinguish between
proton-proton couplings that are
on the cis-- on the same side
of the double bond-- or trans.
So, cis and trans, and these couplings,
as you can see,
the cis are in the vicinity of 10,
and the trans in the vicinity of 15 to 19.
It critically depends on the question,
whether there is a substituent
here in the third position.
So, many people, good chemists,
can know these things by heart,
and just from the knowledge
of the coupling constant,
they can tell you what
the substituent X really is.
There are other examples here.
So, this is now the proton-proton
coupling between these protons here--
that is to say, between vicinal protons--
and they are contained in a smaller range,
but also depend on the substituent X.
This kind of observation
is very important
in chemistry of cyclohexanes
and their derivatives,
and in particular of sugars,
because many sugar molecules
are built on six-membered rings,
with an oxygen,
and, of course, hydroxy groups,
but the basic pattern
is a six-membered ring.
It turns out that, here,
we can distinguish axial coupling--
so if there's a proton up here
and a proton down here,
then this is an axial-axial coupling,
and that turns out to have
a dihedral angle,
if you look at the Newman diagram,
of 180 degrees,
and the scalar coupling is quite large,
in the vicinity of 12 hertz.
But, if we now consider, for example,
between this equatorial proton here
and this axial here--
so, now, there is
a 60 degree dihedral angle,
and the coupling drops
to about four hertz.
Likewise, between the two equatorials--
so, we compare this and this,
there is also coupling between these two,
and again, the dihedral angle,
although it's not obvious
from this diagram,
is only 60 degrees,
and the coupling is 3.9.
So, there are important
lessons to be gained
from looking at three-bond
coupling constants.
Now, of course, this hasn't escaped
the attention of some theoreticians,
and there is a famous relation
that was invented many years ago
by Martin Karplus.
He got a Nobel prize a few years ago,
but that was not for this equation.
His equation explains a relationship--
it's actually a partly empirical,
partly theoretical relationship--
of which Karplus himself said
that if you use it, it's at your own risk.
But, anyway,
I won't give the equation here,
but the point is that the J-coupling
between two protons in vicinal positions
is dependent on the intermediate
dihedral angle.
In fact, this J-coupling is largest
if the angle is 180 degrees--
that is to say, if one proton is sitting
here and the other is sitting there.
They are somewhat smaller,
but not dramatically smaller
if the angle is 0-- that is to say,
if the two protons are eclipsed,
if the back proton is hidden behind
the front proton, so to speak.
And, they drop to something like
two hertz or so
if the angle is 90 degrees,
which it frequently is.
Such relationships can, again,
be calculated,
using quantum chemistry,
but they can also
be observed in molecules,
provided that you fix the angle.
You contrive the molecule
with suitable substituents and rings
and what have you,
in order to prevent it from rotating.
Karplus postulated a famous equation
which bears his name,
and it says that a three-bond coupling
is proportional to a constant,
plus a factor B times cos(θ),
which is the dihedral angle,
plus a factor C times cos^2 (θ).
So, you see
that if the limit
that θ is equal to 90 degrees,
then, of course, cos and cos^2 disappear,
so 3J becomes equal to A.
In the limit that θ
is equal to 180 degrees,
then the cosine is -1
and the cosine squared is +1,
so 3J is A-B+C.
And, of course, the limit
when the angle tends to zero
is 3J = A+B+C.
So, basically, this Karplus equation
is a nice way of empirically catching
that complexity.
We see such things
if we look at amino acids.
An amino acid can be represented
in a Newman projection.
So, in front here, we have
what's known as the α carbon,
which sustains, or is attached to,
the carboxyl group
and the ammonium group
of the amino acid, and then behind it--
behind the disk of Mr. Newman--
is the β carbon,
and on the β carbon we find
the "residue," the rest of the chain,
plus a β2 and a β1 proton.
And on the α carbon, of course,
we have the α proton,
and so the question is, what is
the coupling between these two,
and what is the coupling
between these two?
It turns out that,
depending on the angle θ,
which is the angle through which
these two planes are rotated,
that these couplings vary dramatically.
For example, in this configuration,
between α and β1,
we have about 60 degrees,
and between α and β2, we have 180.
In this configuration, this is about 60
and this is about 180.
So, you see that the coupling will vary,
depending on the angle θ.
On average, we shall be observing
the weighted average
of the three couplings,
and therefore we can draw conclusions
as to the average value of this angle θ.
In fact, this is a rather modern subject.
We find similar things
in polypeptide chains--
that is to say, chains of amino acids--
but in a slightly different disguise.
Here, we see there are couplings
between the proton attached to the α,
and the proton attached to the nitrogen,
which is part of the amide bond.
And here, there is a coupling,
so this is a 3J,
H attached to proton, and H alpha,
will tell you about
the dihedral angle here,
which in the language of peptides
is known as the angle φ,
the other one being ψ and χ.
The knowledge of these couplings,
which can be determined
even in fairly large molecules,
allows you to determine that angle,
and if you know such angles
from one peptide bond to the next,
ultimately you can define
the entire three-dimensional
structure of the peptide,
and that is a very flashy thing to do.
Now, in this chapter three
of Peter Hore's book,
there is also a brief discussion
of dipolar couplings.
Dipolar couplings do not occur in liquids,
as we shall see,
but they occur in solids,
and are very important as such.
They can be seen in solids
in the form of splittings,
but they also influence
spectra in liquids,
because they are essential
to drive relaxation.
Relaxation, as we shall see, is a process
through which the magnetization
returns to its thermal equilibrium,
and as such it's very important,
both to be able to record NMR spectra,
but also to determine
certain molecular properties,
such as internal motion,
or diffusion coefficients--
rotational and translational diffusion.
So, dipolar couplings
are a different type of thing.
What you see here is doublets
of a spin A, coupled to a spin X,
in a solid, as a function
of the orientation.
The reason for these splittings
is that we have a spin A--
so, somewhere here,
let's call this spin A--
and then somewhere else in space
there's another spin, call it spin X,
and the direction, the distance,
is described by a vector.
This molecule will be placed
in an external magnetic field,
which we call B0, as usual,
and if we extend this internuclear vector,
we find an angle here.
This is the angle called θ.
And it turns out
that the energy level diagram
is affected by the dipole-dipole coupling.
This has nothing to do
with the J-coupling,
it is nothing to do with electrons,
it is purely mediated through space.
So, you see here, that there is
an angular dependence.
In fact, this thing is called
the Legendre polynomial of rank two,
sometimes just called P2.
The peculiar property is that it depends
on the orientation of this vector
with respect to the magnetic field.
And so, you give an example here,
of the doublet of this--
this is split into a doublet,
it's a large doublet, if θ is zero--
that is to say, if this vector is aligned
with the magnetic field.
Then, there comes a point where
it goes through zero,
the doublet collapses to a singlet.
That turns out to be the case
when θ is equal to about 54 degrees,
which is the so-called "magic angle."
And, if that is the case,
we only have a singlet,
and then the splitting reappears,
and as we go to 90 degrees--
that is to say, if this vector
is perpendicular to the external field,
we have a splitting where the magnitude
is one-half the splitting
that we have if it's parallel.
It turns out that this splitting,
which the authors call R--
rather un-typically,
most other books call it D--
but it's proportional to the product
of the gyromagnetic ratios
of spin A and of spin X,
and most importantly,
it's inversely proportional to the third
power of the distance between them.
So, R, in this case, is simply the length,
the modulus of the vector
that we have drawn here.
And that vector R, that distance R,
of course, is interesting to chemists,
because it allows you to measure
the size of the molecule
and the length, the distance,
between two spins.
It turns out that if we consider powder,
then there is no single orientation
of this vector R.
So, let me draw the field again,
and remember that we have
an internuclear vector like this,
which subtends an angle θ.
If we have a powder, that means
that we have all sorts of particles,
a bit like in sugar or in salt,
that have different angles,
and consequently, θ is distributed
over a full range of angles.
It turns out that we then
get a powder spectrum--
also invented by George Pake,
by the way, in the '50s--
discovered for the first time,
and explained, more importantly.
And it turns out
that the small splitting here, RAX,
which was on the previous transparency,
corresponds to the case
where θ is exactly equal to 90 degrees,
and those crystallites are fairly common,
because it's quite likely
that the vector be perpendicular
to the external field.
But this larger splitting, here,
corresponds to θ equal to 180 degrees,
and the signals are weaker here,
in amplitude,
because the likelihood
that they should be precisely parallel
to the magnetic field is much smaller.
In fact, you can see that this Pake
pattern is made up of two halves.
It's actually a superposition
of two paths, like this,
and these are the two transitions
of the doublets that we talked about.
Now, let's recapitulate,
together with Peter Hore,
what is to be said about J-couplings
and dipolar couplings.
First of all, J-couplings require bonds.
They are mediated by electrons.
If there are no bonds,
then there are no J-couplings.
Whereas, dipolar couplings
go directly through space,
and therefore can be intermolecular,
whereas these can only be intramolecular.
J-couplings are weak,
typically on the order
of 100 hertz or something like that--
of course there are some exceptions,
but that's an order of magnitude.
And, dipolar couplings
tend to be much larger.
It depends on the γ of the nuclei,
but 100 kilohertz is a good number.
J-couplings are isotropic.
That is what scalar coupling means.
Isotropic, in the sense
that their magnitude is independent
of the orientation of the molecule
with respect to the magnetic field.
Dipolar couplings vary
with the orientation,
according to the Legendre polynomial
which is 3cos^2 (θ) - 1,
where θ is the angle subtended between
the magnetic field, on the one hand,
and the internuclear vector on the other.
Then, J-couplings tend to drop
to small numbers
if there are more than three bonds
that separate the nuclei,
whereas dipolar couplings
always are proportional
to the inverse of the third power,
and therefore, insensitive.
J-couplings cause splittings
in spectra in solution.
They also can be seen in solids,
but it's more difficult
because they're so small.
Whereas, dipolar couplings lead
to splittings,
large splittings, in solids,
and also in more exotic things--
like liquid crystals--
such as partially-aligned molecules.
J-couplings do not contribute
significantly to relaxation--
that is, the return of the magnetization
to its equilibrium,
but dipolar couplings
are causing relaxation;
in fact, they are driving relaxation,
particularly in the presence of motion,
and therefore, they give a way
of determining this motion.
There are some comments here.
The strength of the interactions--
both this and this--
depend on the magnetogyric ratios--
I call them gyromagnetic,
but that's the same thing--
and on the molecular structure.
The numbers are very approximate,
so this is just to guide the eye.
They can be more complicated
if there is chemical exchange going on,
and one has to worry
about internal motion.
So, in summary, spin-spin interactions--
they can be either J-couplings in liquids,
or dipolar couplings in solids--
give rise to multiplets.
So, in liquid-state spectra,
it's only J-couplings,
and in solid-state spectra
it's mostly dipolar couplings.
J-couplings usaully occur
via chemical bonds,
because they're mediated by electrons,
and are generally small
when the nuclei are more than
three bonds apart.
J-couplings give information
on bonding networks in molecules.
J-couplings within a group
of magnetically equivalent spins
do not produce any multiplet splittings.
So, as soon as you have identified
an ensemble of spins
that are magnetically equivalent,
there is no evidence that there
are couplings between these spins.
Strongly-coupled spins have more
complex spectra than weakly-coupled spins.
Particularly, when we have
a two-spin system,
the inner lines tend to grow
at the expense of the outer lines,
and this is known as a "roof effect,"
and in larger spin systems
they can be very, very complicated.
Dipolar couplings occur through space,
and normally do not lead to multiplets
in liquid-state NMR spectra,
unless we happen to be in materials
or in molecules like liquid crystals,
that are partly aligned
with respect to the magnetic field,
but this is clearly a very exotic subject.
Thank you for your attention.