Welcome to our MOOC,
massively online open course
on basic steps on magnetic resonance.
Today, we shall be talking
about spin-spin couplings
that are the subject of chapter three
of Peter Hore's book.
The appearance of multiplets
in NMR spectra is familiar
to all practitioners of analytical NMR,
quite familiar to virtually all chemists,
to many biologists,
and even to a few physicists.
However, not all of these
are aware of the subtle aspects
of muliplet structures.
Spin-spin couplings were
originally discovered
by a serendipity in the 1950s
by Erwin Hahn, in Berkeley.
Erwin Hahn noticed that
spin echoes were modulated.
This observation came shortly
after Hahn's invention,
or perhaps one should say discovery,
of spin echoes.
More about this in chapter six.
Such echo modulations
can be observed,
even when the homogeneity
of the static field is too poor
to resolve the multiplet structures.
As indeed, was usually the case
in the 1950s.
Scalar couplings have a few
important properties.
First of all, there are isotropic.
That means they do not
depend on the orientation
of the molecule, with respect
to the external field.
And they are also field independent.
That is to say, they have the same
magnitude at say 400 or 800 megahertz.
They are mediated by electrons
via the so-called Fermi interaction,
and are set to be through-bond
as opposed to through-space.
It is still a challenge today
to calculate scalar couplings constants
with reasonable accuracy.
If the coupling constants are known,
the mutiplets, due to scalar couplings,
can be predicted
with remarkable accuracy
by simple diagonalization
of the matrix representation
of the Hamiltonian in the product base.
The agreement between theory
and experiment is viewed by some
as a nice confirmation that
quantum mechanics actually works.
Works perfectly in this case.
This perfection is due to the fact
that Hilbert space,
the space that contains
all the states, is a finite dimension.
Multiplets due to scalar couplings
give crucial information
about molecular symmetry.
They often great opportunity
to practice group theory.
Multiplets, due to scalar couplings,
give unique insight into
populations of rotamers, and into
their inter-conversion.
Another fascinating aspect,
where anomer allows the chemists
to grasp the mobile, flexible,
and generally speaking,
dynamic nature of most molecules.
Chapter three, of Peter Hore's
little book on nuclear magnetic resonance,
is dedicated to spin-spin couplings.
In a characteristic fashion,
Peter Hore speaks first about
the manifestations of these effects
in a sort of empirical fashion.
And then, proceeds to explain
where they really come from.
So, you will see these chapters,
one right after the other as usual.
So multiplets, particularly
in proton NMR spectra,
are quite familiar
to the practicing chemist.
Particularly to organic chemists
because they allow them
to identify the fragments of the
molecules that they are trying to analyze,
or that they have synthesized
or hope to synthesize.
Now, we shall start with the very
important example of ethenol again,
but now observed in a magnetic field.
A modern magnet that has
a sufficient homogeneity
so that we can not only
resolve the three chemical shifts
of the OH methylene and methyl protons,
but also the fine structure.
The fine structure which is due
to the scalar couplings.
And as most chemists
will know, the CH2 group
is split into, a quartet
because the CH2 group
has as neighbor the CH3 group.
While the CH3 group
is split into a triplet,
because its neighbor
is a CH2.
This kind of logic is kind of
instinctive for many chemists,
but in fact, it's not so easy to explain.
And one of our objectives
is to go into some detail
in the course of this chapter.
Multiplets are perhaps best explained
in so-called heteronuclear systems
where we have for example,
one proton, which has a spin 1/2
with two states, alpha and beta.
And one carbon-13, also
Now we can take a molecule,
which only contains two such spins.
For example, the conjugate base
of formic acid, or formate, if you will,
which abut from this proton here,
has a single carbon-13.
About 1% in natural abundance,
or up to 100% if we enrich
the material in the upper isotope.
Now, there will be two spectra.
There is, if we take a field
of 9.4 tesla,
then there will be a chemical shift
here in the vicinity of 400 megahertz
And another chemical shift
of the carbon-13
in the vicinity of 100 megaghertz.
In both cases, however,
we do not see singlets,
but we see doublets.
So the proton signal
is split into a doublet
and so is the carbon signal.
And it turns out that
the splitting exactly
is exactly the same.
If we wonder where this comes from,
we have to look
at the energy level diagram.
And remember that spectral transitions,
or lines in the spectrum
always correspond
to differences in energies.
If we consider a single isolated proton,
than it can be either parallel,
its polarization can be parallel
with the magnetic field.
We sometimes call this the alpha state.
Or it can be anti-parallel, in which
case, we call it the beta state.
Of course, between the two energies,
there is only one transition
which is near 400 megahertz.
And consequently, we observe
a singlet, like here.
But if we now have a carbon-13
in the vicinity, it turns out that
that carbon-13 itself
can be alpha or beta.
And in this case, we assume
that the carbon is in the beta,
that is to say
the anti-parallel configuration.
And remains in the beta
anti-parallel configuration
while the proton is
undergoing its transition.
It turns out, and this is the
manifestation of the scalar coupling,
that the splitting between
these two states is larger than
the splitting between the two states
in the absence of a carbon.
Conversely, if we consider
a carbon which is polarized
parallel to the magnetic field,
in the alpha configuration like here,
then it turns out that the splitting
between the two levels, where the proton
goes from parallel
to anti-parallel is reduced.
And if we think of the spectrum,
in this case, the splitting is enhanced
from here to here.
And consequently, the line moves from
central frequency to higher frequencies.
Remember that high frequencies
in spectra run from right to left,
in anomer anyway.
Whereas, the other line here
has a reduced energy splitting
and therefore, a lower frequency.
So this line turns out
on the right-hand side.
So the effect of the scalar coupling,
we could call it one-bond scalar coupling,
because there's only one bond
between these two nuclei.
In formate, is to split the line
of the proton into a doublet.
And likewise, weakens difference argument,
split the carbon-13 into this doublet
with this same spacing.
Now, we can try to do this argument,
in its likely more general way,
and it's more fundamental
so that we can include
arbitrary energies and arbitrary
numbers of spins.
For example, if we consider
the energy of a state.
So we have now many states
and these states are
specified by magnetic quantum numbers,
m, lowercase m, which could be
either mA, can be either
plus 1/2, or minus 1/2.
And so each energy level diagram
is specified by two quantum numbers
and each of them can be
either plus or minus 1/2.
And having said that,
the energy level diagram
is primarily determined by
this expression, h times Nu.
That's the Larmor frequency
of spin A.
And then h times NuX, that's
the Larmor frequency of spin X.
Each in this case is
Planck's constant, Planck,
because the energy here
is expressed in joule, as it should be
in the international system.
Though, in practice, NMR spectroscopists
often express their frequencies in hertz,
which you can achieve by dividing
the energies by Planck's constant.
So we often write things is hertz,
which amounts to energy divided by Planck.
Now anyway, in this equation, it is
written correctly in terms of joules.
And you see that the main effect
comes from the offset,
from the chemical shifts, excuse me.
But there is this perturbing
term here, which is due to
the scalar coupling between A and X.
And it turns out if mA and mX
have the same sign,
then we have a positive contribution
of 1/4 times h times A.
If they have opposite sign,
then we have a negative contribution.
So we see this
very nicely on this diagram.
First of all, we start with a
molecule in the absence
of a magnetic field.
Then we switch on the field
for the A nucleus, we see a splitting.
So this is the Zeeman splitting
across spin A, which could be the proton.
And then we have another
Zeeman splitting for spin X,
typically the carbon-13
by the way of
this ratio splitting to this splitting
should be equal to the ratio
of the gamma carbon divided
by gamma protons.
And then we see the effect
of the coupling is
to increase this somewhat, because
the two magnetic quantum numbers
are minus 1/2 times minus 1/2
is of course, plus 1/4.
So we have an increase here.
And here, because we have
a product of minus 1/2 and plus 1/2,
the product will be minus 1/4.
And indeed, the energy
decreases like this.
Here, it's again minus 1/4
because the off that product goes down.
And here, it's plus 1/4,
and indeed, the energy goes up.
So this is clearly a manifestation
of this equation.
So, in practice, if we look
at the transitions, we see that
the A transitions in the absence
of splitting of a J-coupling,
we have just one line for the A,
that would be in this case, the proton.
And one other line for the carbon.
But as soon as we introduce
this interaction, the J then the A
splits up into doublet,
and the X spectrum splits up
in a doublet with equal spacing.
And in this diagram, you can see
that they have aligned, or Peter Hore
has aligned these arrows here
with the line in the spectrum.
And this logic has been
used throughout.
It is interesting to notice that
Peter Hore likes to draw
energy level diagrams
in this vertical fashion.
Many NMR spectroscopists are tempted
to draw a diagram more in this fashion,
in the fashion of a lozenge
where these would be
the transitions of one spin.
And this would be the transitions
of another spin.
And somehow, some of us
think it's easier to remember this.
So this would be for
a homonuclear system.
Or for this heteronuclear system,
you would have large transitions
for spin A and smaller transitions,
smaller energy differences, for transition
So this would be the A transitions,
and this would be the X transitions.
Some people prefer this
kind of drawing over this sort of
vertical, ladder representation.
It turns out that in larger spin systems,
with three or more spins,
we have more complicated multiplets.
And that these multiplet patterns
can be built up, as it were,
from different splittings that are
invoked one after the other
in a sort of cascade of splittings,
or sometimes called a 'tree'.
And we can see here, that if we
have a given spin that
resonates at a chemical shift A,
it will be split into a doublet
if we have a neighboring spin M
with a coupling JAM.
And this doublet will again
be separated, split into a sub-doublet
by spin X with a coupling AX.
And so, if we assign different,
spins different polarizations,
it turns out that the left-most
line in the multiplet,
if all the couplings are positive,
corresponds to a situation
where both M and X are negative.
Or they could both be
in the beta position.
Whereas, in the second line from left,
the spin M is still in the beta position,
but alpha has flipped over
from beta to alpha.
And so, this can be assigned like this.
And so this is a very elaborate
way of interpreting
the different components
of a multiplet in terms of states.
I should say at this level,
that one cannot circumstrict
energy level diagrams like this.
And for example, for a two-spin system,
it would be like this.
And if we have a third system,
then it would be like this.
So we have two lozenges,
and we connect them like this.
And it turns out that the parallel
transitions of this cube correspond
to transitions of spin A
and other parallel transitions.
For example, these could be
the transitions of spin A
and other transitions would be
those of spin M and spin X.
But one of the purposes
of this particular picture
is to show under certain circumstances,
the coupling between AM and AX
may become equivalent.
And then we speak of a situation
where spin A is coupled to a spin X,
and another spin X, and in such a way
that the scalar coupling constants
are accidentally, or by symmetry, equal.
In that case, we have only one J,
and it's called JAX.
And you can see
what happens in this diagram,
the central legs of these
two doublets here become
shifted on top of each other
and become degenerate.
And this degeneracy means
that the central line is
twice as intense as the
individual lines on the left-hand side.
And we can take this
one step further.
We can consider the case
where A is coupled
to three different nuclei,
all with the same coupling constant.
And so this is known as
an AX3 system.
And in that case, we have
a quadruplet with the so-called
binomial intensity distribution.
And each line can be assigned to the
polarization of the neighboring X nuclei.
Now it turns out that these
multiplet patterns can be
generalized in terms of so-called
Pascal's triangle.
Or this is just a way of rationalizing
in a simple way, a binomial distribution.
You probably know how
the Pascal triangle is built up.
For example, there's three,
number three here
is just the sum of numbers
one and two on the line above.
And you can use that rule
systematically all the way down.
And what you see here
are the distributions.
So there are line distributions
of different spin systems.
This is the isolated A spin,
a two-spin system in AX2, AX3, etc., AX6.
Now you may think this is
purely formal.
Well in fact, it is not.
And it goes a long way further.
You could for example,
consider a situation where
we have silicon-29,
which has a spin 1/2.
And which is surrounded by
four methyl groups.
This substance is called TMS,
tetramethylsilane.
And in fact, it turns out
that there are three times four,
12 equivalent protons.
So the system is actually
an AX12 system, and you
can imagine that you have
to expand the Pascal triangle
a very long way to go that far.
By the way, these intensity rules
are not always easy
to identify on the spectrum
because it turns out
that the outer lines here
are very weak compared
to the central lines.
And sometimes you just
don't see the outer lines.
And one way of not being fooled
by the fact that the outer lines
may be drowned in noise,
is to compare these inner lines
of the central components.
In this case, we have 15:20:15,
which is of course, distinct from 1:2:1.
And therefore, we can identify on which
level of the Pascal triangle we are,
without actually measuring,
numbering out the full list of lines.
So, there are many cases
where couplings involve nuclei,
so-called quadrupolar nuclei,
which have spin quantum number I,
larger than 1/2.
The simplest example being
the deuterium nucleus, which is a spin one
But there's also the nitrogen-14
nucleus with a spin one.
Or the lithium-6 nucleus
with a spin one and many others.
Not to mention all the higher spins.
Now let's take a simple example
where we consider a carbon.
In this case, a carbon-13
attached to a deuterium nucleus.
It turns out that, and we shall
call this carbon nucleus, spin X,
and the deuterium nucleus
will be called spin A.
Now it turns out that
the energy level diagram
is composed of the following,
for the deuteron, which has I equal one.
And therefore, magnetic quantum
numbers of spin A can be either
minus one or zero, or plus one.
While we find these three
levels corresponding
to the minus one, the zero
and the plus one,
quantum numbers of the deuteron.
And it split be this transition
which actually is
degenerate to this transition
which is just the same
interaction for the deuteron.
If we're in isotropic phase,
these are always deuterons,
so there's actually no evidence
that this is a quadrupolar nucleus.
But if we look at the carbon-13
next door, then we have
to take into account that there's also
a splitting for the carbon-13.
And we see here that
this one here, has let's call
the quantum number S
to avoid confusion.
And in this case, MX can be
minus 1/2, or plus 1/2.
This is what we call a
beta or alpha state.
And you see that now we have
six energy levels, and we have
a certain amount of transitions here.
We see on the carbon side,
let's just say on the X side,
we see these three transitions,
so as before, this is nicely aligned
with this peak and this is
aligned with this peak.
And so you see there's
a relationship between
the energy level diagram
and the spectrum.
Some people say that
a spectrum is nothing else
but a peculiar projection
of the energy level diagram.
On the other hand, if we
look at the A side,
it turns out that this line and this line
are still rigorously degenerate,
have exactly the same frequency.
So they end up with a doubly
degenerate line on this side here.
And likewise, these two transitions
here are exactly degenerate
and pile up on top of each other
and give this doubly degenerate line.
The remarkable thing now
is therefore, that on the X side,
it's the carbon-13, we don't
have a binomial triplet,
but we have a triplet with
equal intensities, 1:1:1.
Now, it turns out that there are more
sophisticated quadrupolar nuclei.
And we have an example here
of boron-11, which has
spin quantum number I equals 3/2
And therefore, the m of the boron
can go from minus 3/2
to minus 1/2, to plus 1/2,
to plus 3/2.
So there are four distinct
quantum states for each boron.
If we take this peculiar molecule,
known as diborane,
which comes from the condensation
of two BH3 molecules.
So we have 2H3, two times,
give a B2H6.
And it turns out that
the structure of this B2H6
is a rather peculiar assembly
that you see here,
where we have so-called
terminal protons, there are four of those.
And each of these terminal protons
only sees one boron-11.
Incidentally, we assume that
boron-10 has been eliminated
by proper synthesis,
synthetic preparation.
Now each proton sees
just one boron,
and consequently the terminal
protons are split up into
a quartet of four equal lines.
So we call this a non-binomial
1:1:1 quartet.
And that's characteristic of
any spin 1/2 nucleus coupled
to a spin 3/2 nucleus.
But more peculiar is what happens
if we look at the bridge protons.
So these protons actually
have equal bonds to two borons,
and also equal scalar couplings.
In fact, the whole molecule,
as we shall see,
is completely symmetrical.
And these protons and these
borons are magnetically equivalent.
But if we want to understand
the fine structure of the peak,
or the multiplet of that proton,
the bridge proton,
then we have to do a division
into four peaks like this.
And each of them has to be
subdivided again into four equal peaks.
But because the two couplings
are equivalent, like we have seen
in AX2 and AX3 systems, you see
that there are now, for example,
at this line here, there are two
ways of getting there.
Either from here, or from here.
And therefore, the intensity of that line
is twice as high as the first line.
So we get rather peculiar multiplets.
1:2:3:4:3:2:1,
which is
not a binomial multiplet.
This does not fit into
the logic of Pascal's triangle.
But you see where it comes from.
And by way of an exercise,
I would like to encourage you
to think of the next level.
What happens if the proton
were coupled to three boron nuclei?
Then of course, we have
even more complex multiplet,
and the challenge would be
to determine its multiplicity.
This is not an academic question,
since there are actual molecules
that have that pattern.
So this concludes part one
of this chapter.
Thank you for you attention.