So welcome to our MOOC
on magnetic resonance.
This is now the second half
of chapter three
where we shall be speaking more
about spin-spin couplings.
We should now address a tricky
issue of equivalent nuclei.
It turns out-- and this is very nicely
described in Peter Hore's book.
I think it's one of the best
books on this subject.
There are two forms of equivalence.
There is a chemical equivalent
that's fairly easy to understand.
That means that you have two nuclei
that cannot be distinguished
in chemical terms.
One cannot substitute one
without substituting the other.
One cannot replace one.
One cannot conceive of a reaction
that would affect one
without affecting the other.
That's one thing.
And then there is the concept
of magnetic equivalence
which is much more subtle
and more difficult to define.
Let us start with a simple application.
First of all, we have this
magnetic equivalent pair here
where these two protons
have the same coupling
with the two fluorine.
So if we take this coupling here
or this coupling here,
it turns out that by symmetry
of this molecule,
these two couplings are the same.
Likewise if we started
with the two fluorines,
they also have the same
couplings to the two protons.
But this is not so, so these
two here are the same.
But if we look at this coupling here,
which is a cis coupling, it's different.
Different magnitude
perhaps even a different sign
from this long-range coupling here,
the trans coupling.
So this is distinct from this
and therefore, there are
two different cases.
Well, it turns out that Peter Hore
has a wonderful way
of explaining how you
can check for the existence
of magnetic equivalent nuclei.
First of all, you define an ensemble
of nuclei A, B, C, etcetra
of nuclei of which you want to decide
whether they are magnetically
equivalent or not,
such as in this case
Proton A and Proton B.
And then you define external nuclei,
if they exist, like in this case.
This fluorine which we call Z,
or rather Peter Hore
uses that nomenclature.
And then he says,
"If the J coupling between A and Z
is equal to the J coupling
between B and Z,
between C and Z,
and all similar things,
in that case, we have
magnetic equivalence."
And if that is not the case
as in this molecule here,
then we have only chemical equivalence.
We shall see in spectra
that has dramatic consequences.
Now this test here, where we compare
the scalar couplings
between A, B, C and an
external nucleus Z,
in principle has to be repeated
for different external nuclei.
For example we once do it for Z
and then we have to do it
all over again
for the nucleus Z prime.
In practice it turns out that once
you have a negative
answer for one of them
you don't need to check the others.
Magnetic equivalence
needs to be reflected about,
thought about carefully.
Now. there are cases
which are not obvious.
For example this is dodecahedron--
has the molecule or formula C20 H20.
If all carbon are C12,
which is not obvious
but if it's depleted in carbon 13,
then we have no other nuclei
than the 20 chemically equivalent protons.
And so there is no Z.
There is no external nucleus Z,
and consequently we can't conduct the test
and it turns out that all 20 protons
are magnetically equivalent
and not only chemically equivalent.
The same is true on a much more
mundane molecule
which is that of benzine.
There we have six benzene protons,
as you all know,
and in this case they're all equivalent
because there is no proton Z
or no carbon Z
and that could prove that
they are inequivalent.
Now, multiplet patterns can be used
to check for molecular symmetry
or to confirm or reject a hypothesis
about the symmetry of the molecule.
And Peter Hore has collected
some wonderful examples
for phosphorus 31 NMR spectra
in these compounds which contain
only phosphorus and sulphur.
So the large spheres represent
the phosphor atoms
and the small spheres the sulphur atoms,
And you can see they can be
different arrangements.
And it turns out that sulphur has no spin
at least the dominant isotope
has 99% but it has no spin.
And therefore, we can ignore it
and we we only have to worry
about the chemical shifts
and about the equivalence,
chemical or magnetic equivalence,
of the phosphorus nuclei.
So it turns out that
in a configuration like this,
again there is no atom Z.
There's no nucleus Z
that could conceivably have different
couplings with the different A nuclei
and the four phosphorus nuclei
and therefore it turns out
that these four As
are on the same environment.
They're chemically indistiguishable
and furthermore they are
magnetically equivalent.
And therefore we call them A4.
This system has a different symmetry.
You immediately see
that these two nuclei are--
these phosphorus are sitting
between three sulphurs,
whereas, these phosphorus nuclei
have another phosphorus
for a neighbor and then only
two sulphurs as a neighbor.
So chemically, they're quite different.
In fact, they also have different
chemical shifts
but when it comes to the symmetry,
it turns out that the coupling
between one of these As
and the two Xs is equal
and so we have an A2X2 system.
And the result of that is that
on the A side we have a triplet
and on the X side we also have a triplet.
This is a more complicated case
where this phosphorus on top here
has three sulphurs.
A bit like what we had before
but at the bottom here,
we have a phosphorus which is squeezed
between two other phosphorus,
whereas the other phosphorus
are squeezed between
a phosphorus and two sulphurs.
So clearly we have three
different chemical environments
and it turns out that
we have an AMX2 system
because the only equivalence,
the only magnetic equivalence,
is between these two X nuclei
and the consequences are as you can see.
Example here in the A multiplet,
we have a large triplet
due to the coupling between A and X.
The X are the neighboring
phosphorus nuclei
and a smaller coupling JAM between the A
and the distant M nucleus.
So this is a wonderful example on how
we can look at the spectra
and draw conclusions as to
the symmetry of the molecule.
Now there are also amusing cases
when we look at lithium 7
or lithium 6 is also an interesting case.
But lithium 7 has a spin 3 halves.
This is a little bit like boron 11
that we have discussed before.
In this case we consider
a strange molecule
which is actually a cluster
comprising four lithium atoms
arranged according to a tetrahedron.
And it turns out that you can attach
these tertial butyl group,
and that they are not attached
to one of the lithium atoms
but they tend to attach themselves
to the middle of the triangular surface
of one of these sides of the cluster.
Very mysterious chemistry
but the NMR is without any doubt
proving that this structure
is the true structure
and not the one that
you might intuitively draw.
Well it turns out that
because of this structure
if we look at the lithium spectrum,
lithium 7 spectrum,
which as I said has a spin three-halves,
we shall see an ordinary binomial quartet
because of the splitting
to three equivalent
carbon 13 which are--
so each lithium in effect
sees three carbons.
For example, if you take this lithium
at the top here,
it sees this carbon 13 and this carbon 13
and this carbon 13 as equivalent.
And therefore, we have
this wonderful quartet.
On the other hand,
we could also decide to enrich
this cluster with lithium 6.
Lithium 6 has spin one,
so it will split its neighboring
carbon into three equivalent lines
with amplitude one to one to one
but then it turns out
that each carbon is coupled
to three lithium nuclei
and therefore gives ride to this
very strange non-biominal multiplet
which is comprised of three
interleaved triplets.
So I vividly recommend
you to look at this.
This is in fact similar to what
you have seen in diborane
except that now it's a coupling
to three neighboring nuclei.
In four-spin systems we have
more complicated structures
as you might expect
but they're fairly easy to rationalize.
In fact, we can simply take
the proton NMR spectrum
of dibromonitrobenzene.
This is of course a very simple molecule.
And we can see that
we have here a proton A
which is squeezed between a proton P
and a proton M.
The couplings here, the ortho-couplings
are not exactly equal
but they are similar.
And then we have this X here
which is across the ring,
so to speak, and that
will have a long range
para coupling to the A
and medium range to the
meta positions P and M.
And as a result, the A multiplet
will be split into what is sometimes
called the pseudo triplet.
In fact it's just a doublet of doublets
with very closely related couplings.
And there's a fine structure
which is a doublet
which is due to the para position X.
The M on the other hand is split
into a large coupling
because of the J A M.
And then each line is split into a doublet
and again into a doublet
first because of P
and then because of X.
Likewise, the same logic applies
to spin P which is very similar
to spin M as far as the structure
of the multiplet is concerned.
And finally spin X is a pseudo triplet
because they're almost equivalent
couplings to P and to M.
Each component is split
into a small doublet
because of the para coupling
between X and M.
This kind of spectrum can
allow you to determine
this molecular structure almost
without any other help.
There is an interesting phenomenon
in scalar coupled multiplets
and this is known as strong coupling
or sometimes known
as second order coupling.
And you can see that we have a system
that evolves from a case
where the splitting here, the J splitting,
is much smaller than the
difference in chemical shifts.
In this case we speak of an AX system
but when the chemical shifts come closer,
then we notice that the multiplets
not only become closer
as you might expect but also they change
the amplitude ratios here.
The inner lines become stronger
and the outer lines become weaker.
And in a case like that, we use
two letters in the alphabet
which are closer together
and we speak of an AB system.
And ultimately, if the two chemical shifts
become degenerate,
if fact we have only one line over,
left over, and then
we speak of an A2 system.
So to understand strong coupling
we have to use a little bit
of quantum mechanics.
This is not treated in any detail
in the first volume of Peter Hore
that I recommended to you
but there is a second book
that you may wish to read
in a year from now maybe
that is written by Steve Wimperis
and Jeremy Jones
and the same Peter Hore
in the same series,
the Oxford Primer series
and that speaks about such
quantum mechanic effects.
Well in this case you should know
that we have to explain
the case where we have the AX system
where we have just two doublets
we have the AB system where
the two doublets move
close together so that the inner lines
become more intense
and the case of the A2 system.
It turns out that all three
can be explained in one equation
by saying that the bottom state,
that's this one here,
where the two spins are parallel
with the magnetic field
is not affected by this phenomenon
so they're always the same.
It's always a simple state
with alpha alpha.
Likewise, the upper state here
where the two spins
are anti-parallel is unaffected.
It doesn't matter whether the system
is strongly or weakly coupled
but the intermediate states
called psi2 and psi3
they are mixed.
In fact, they are neither alpha beta
nor beta alpha
but there is a wonderful admixture
between these two
and the coefficience are
cosine of an angle chi
and sine of an angle chi.
Now this angle actually
is determined by the ratio
of the J coupling and the difference
in chemical shifts.
So to draw this in, sort of,
simple trigonometry,
if we draw the chemical shift
horizontally like this,
so this would be a number in hertz,
and if we draw the scalar coupling
vertically, also a number in hertz,
then we can make a little diagram
like this and we can have this
line here and this angle here is 2 xi.
So you can immediately see
when the J coupling goes to zero
or becomes much smaller
than the difference in chemical shifts
then xi goes to zero.
So the limit of xi going to zero
means that if we take state xi 2
the cosine goes to one
and the sine goes to zero
and this is a pure alpha beta.
Alpha for spin A and beta for spin B.
And likewise if we take the limit
of xi going to zero
for xi 3, then only the cosine
term survives
so this would be a pure state
where spin A
is in beta polarization
and spin B is in the alpha polarization.
So you can see from this
diagram that the large J
compared to the difference
in chemical shifts,
the steeper the slope,
the closer this angle to xi
approaches 90 degree
and therefore the angle xi
turns to 45 degree.
It's therefore interesting
to see the limit.
One xi goes to 45 degree.
We see from this equation that the cosine
and the sine become equal.
and so if we take that function
then it's just one over
square root of two,
alpha beta plus beta alpha.
Likewise, the limit for xi
going to 45 degrees,
so this is still the case where
this J coupling is much larger
than the difference in chemical shift
of the other function
goes to one over square root of two
and here we have minus alpha beta
plus beta alpha.
Now you notice that the case of the A2,
you see there is this symmetrical
linear combination
which is what we have here.
This is symmetrical in the sense
that if you do a permutation
of spins A and B, this
wave function doesn't change.
It is invariant to the permutation
and is known as totally symmetric.
Whereas the other wave function,
this one here,
that's the one that I just
concocted up here,
is anti-symmetric with respect to
permutation of the spins.
It turns out that this first state
together with the top state
and the bottom state,
that these three together
form what is known as a triplet.
That is to say three states
of the same symmetry.
Whereas this guy here
is known as a singlet.
And the remarkable thing is that
now the intensity that we see here
in the spectrum is made up of two lines,
only two lines, that are degenerate
and occur on top of each other.
One corresponds to this
transition to the middle
component, the triplet,
and the other line
corresponds to the top transition
within the triplet.
Whereas the transitions from
the bottom line to the singlet
are forbidden so that's represented
by this dotted line and
I cross it out to show
that these two transitions
are completely forbidden.
In fact, they are here
virtually, so to speak.
If you look at their frequencies,
they are a plus and minus J
away from the central component
but their intensity are vanishingly weak
and that is why we cannot see them.
This kind of quantum mechanics
has been known for decades
but it has gained some renewed
interest very recently
because it turns out that the populations
here flow quite freely
within this triplet manifold
as a result of what we shall call
longitudinal or spin lattice relaxation.
Whereas the populations
are locked in the singlet state
and cannot flow from the singlet
to the triplet state.
So if one can contrive some way
of populating the singlet state,
then the populations
would be locked in there
and one can have
so called long-lived states.
This is the speciality of Malcolm Levitt
in Southampton
and we have done a lot of work in Lausanne
to try to improve techniques
to populate the singlet states.
This concludes part two of this chapter.
Thank you for your attention.