Now, let's speak about
landfill construction.
We will see some important elements
to be considered for building
a new landfill.
It is usually very difficult to find
a new landfill site, especially
near the big cities, for different
technical and political reasons.
It is often impossible to find a site
which meets all the environmental
and economic criteria.
For that reason, a lot of cities
have transformed progressively
their dumpsite in controlled landfill.
This is the case of Rio de Janeiro,
but also of Geneva, for example.
Along all the criteria required
for a new landfill, I will focus
on a limited number of unusual ones.
First, geological quality and natural
protection of the underground
water resources is certainly the main
environmental and known criteria.
Another criteria is the site
position in the service region.
In terms of traffic, as we
mentioned before, the best place
for a landfill is the center
of gravity of the region.
Each kilometer away from this
center represents, in average,
two more kilometers for each
truck all along the year.
This has an impact on the
environment and on the cost.
An important criteria is to have
a big surface and a long-term
available volume.
It is important to build a
landfill for 30 or 50 years.
For that, it is necessary to build
the first steps and to have
another possibility to create
future cells for the next years.
Other point is to have a local
availability of earthen material
for covering the works or for covering
the different steps of the landfill.
Landfills need a very big volume of
such material to cover the waste.
For that, it is eventually partially
possible to use inert construction
materials but also local quarries are
necessary to have the required material.
These local quarries can be the
next cells of the landfill.
Otherwise, the transport cost will
be too high to make a good job.
Impermeable base layer is important
to reduce the infiltration
of wastewater in the ground.
Many European norms are proposing
plastic impermeable layers.
These plastic solutions are
expensive, extremely fragile in
the construction and
the operation phases.
Here, in an example in Albania, we
can see holes made by machines
during the construction or the
first months of operation.
To make such plastic layer needs a high
technical experience and control.
But why to spend so much money
for this plastic technology if
then the plastic layer
is full of holes?
I'm largely in favor of using mineral
layers using local materials
available locally.
This needs some geotechnical
knowledge in order to find in the
region a good material that can be
compacted, with a high density
and a low permeability.
Normally, we need to mix different
proportions of sandy material
with clay and to strongly compact
it in two or three layers
of twenty or thirty centimeters.
Here, in this example, we can see
a mineral layer made by natural
local material mixed
with clay material.
These technologies are not very
far from the road construction
techniques and you definitely need
a good geotechnical engineer
to conduct the operation.
But, mineral layers will give
you a very long term, good and
stable impermeable system.
And remember: if we have petrol
today, it's due to the impermeable
quality of clay.
The rainwater flowing through the
waste becomes highly polluted.
We call that substance the leachate.
It is very important to have a
very good drainage system of
this leachate on the
bottom of the waste.
Here, we have the bottom of the
waste with the impervious system
and here the drainage system.
This drainage system is
important for two reasons.
First, the leachate quantity then
can flow through in the nature
through the impervious layer is
directly proportional of the
height of the water on the top
of the bottom of the landfill.
If we have a good drainage, we
reduce this height to a very
limited level and then reduce
infiltration in the nature.
Second reason, as we mentioned
before, the accumulation of water
on the bottom of the landfill will
increase the risk of instability
and, for this reason, it is very
important to take this water
out of the waste.
The leachate has generally a high
potential of clogging the drainage.
To avoid that, the leachate drainage
is realized through a continuous
drainage layer of twenty or thirty
centimeters of pervious material.
It is possible to use inner-construction
waste for that – like
bricks or concrete waste.
The best is to add drainage tubes
with a design allowing a future
access from outside for possible control
and cleaning of the main tubes.
A slope of a minimum 3 percent,
2-3 percent, must be considered.
All around the landfill, a big
drainage system must be constructed
in order to avoid that the
water enters the waste.
Additionally, it is also important
to capture and evacuate the
rainwater coming in the top of the
landfill and to avoid a possible
erosion effect of the covered top.
The degradation of the organic
matter without oxygen produces
methane as well as little proportion
of other gases producing
very bad odors for the human nose.
Methane production has, moreover,
a very high contribution to
the greenhouse effect on climate.
Then, the gas drainage and burning
has two important functions:
reduce the bad odors for the population;
reduce the greenhouse effects.
These are different techniques
for gas drainage.
As we saw, the most common are
to realize stone stack during
the development of the landfill.
This can be done through a simple
accumulation of stones or
inner-materials – inner-metallic tube
– which is elevated layer by layer.
The accumulation of stones creates
a continuous vertical drainage
stack and the metallic tubes
can be used very easily
to fire the gas coming from the waste.
This gas represent a huge
energetic potential.
In the second step, the gas can
be collected through a pumping
system to a motor-generator that will
produce a continuous production
of electricity.
These technologies exist
and are very efficient.
The economic interest of this
electricity production is strongly
dependent of the price of the
electricity but, important to
mention, is that such system
requires a high technology as well
for the gas drainage system as for the
preventive maintenance of the motor.
The design of the tube collecting
the gas to the pumping station
should be done considering a high
settlement of the waste during
the life of the landfill.
This will create some technical
problems but can be solved.
Honestly, the landfill leachates
are very difficult to be treated.
Usual biological process for urban
wastewater have a very limited
efficiency on that kind of water.
On another hand, it makes no sense
to build and pay an expensive
impermeable layer in plastic or
mineral at the base of the landfill
if the leachates are just collected
and then discharged in the
environment downstream the
landfill and without treatment.
Depending on the climate, the
best solution is often to store
the drained leachate in big basin
and then to pump it and to
recycle it in the waste system.
This needs to have a pumping system
and an infiltration system
with drains that allow the leachate
to enter again in the waste.
This storage and recirculation
have many beneficial effects.
First, it will treat and partially
evaporate the leachate water.
Secondly, it will increase the gas
production and then the electric
production in cases of a
gas-to-energy system is in place.
It will generate an important
volume reduction of the waste;
the production of gas will reduce
organic composition of the
waste and this gain in volume will
give an interesting economic
value and increase the landfill life.
The volume of the leachate basin
has to be defined according
to local climate conditions
along the years.
Main points of landfill construction
are to use local material,
implicate geotechnical engineer,
control the water, capture and burn gas.