Congratulations and well done!
You have made it through
the first week.
I hope this week has been
inspiring and exciting for you.
In this first week, we started
by giving an overview of the
course content, before diving
straight into the specific issues
and the current waste situation
in developing countries,
and by this, explaining the relevance
and the importance of proper
and sustainable solid
waste management.
We looked at population growth
and urbanisation trends,
and explained how growth influences
waste generation and how this
growth is particularly pronounced
in Asia and Africa,
where in fact, many low-income
countries are.
More people typically
means more waste.
And the problems augment in large
cities or regions with high
population density.
Besides generation of waste, we
also looked at composition of
municipal waste, looking at
average percentages of different
waste fractions, grouped by
country income levels.
In general, the trend is obvious:
the lower the income,
the higher the organic fraction.
We however also highlighted
the large variability depending on the
specific local city or country
context, and the specific
waste practices.
There is no way around it: you
need to assess this for your
specific local situation. A key
message is that knowing
the properties of your urban waste is
very important, as these properties
influence appropriate solutions,
be that in the collection,
transport or treatment.
We also pointed out that not only
spatial but also variations
in time need to be considered when
designing a waste generation
or composition sampling plan.
Then, we moved to collection,
highlighting this key function
in municipal solid waste management,
crucial for the protection
of human and environmental health.
We showed how municipalities in
developing countries often spend
a large share of the available
municipal budget on solid waste
management - collection, but
unfortunately often only managed
to serve less than half of the urban
population with collection services.
And it is the poorest that suffer
most from this lack of service.
We showed that improvements in
collection can be achieved on
different levels, and there is
a large scope in optimisation
and improving cost efficiency.
We also presented the potential
for cost reduction in collection,
while keeping workers'safety in mind.
We also discussed a common
feature in developing countries,
which is the split between primary
collection service
and the secondary collection scheme.
The primary collection which allows
the service for neighbourhoods,
which are else impossible to service
with a typical waste collection
truck, and we pointed out the
complementary distinctive advantages
of each, also indicating that
cooperation and coordination between
both collection schemes
is very important.
After presenting some main facts
on recycling of paper, glass,
plastic and metal, we then
covered three highly complex
and high-cost options, typically in
operation in high income countries:
incineration, mechanical biological
treatment and refuse-derived fuel.
We looked at the underlying objective
of implementing such technologies,
but also discussed their drawbacks,
especially in the low-income
context, and highlighted the need for
waste separation before treatment.
We then ended the week by
looking at landfill disposal.
Unfortunately, the way this is
practised in low-income countries
is typically unsustainable,
and often severely polluting.
We looked at key issues that help
in moving from a dump towards
a sanitary and well-engineered
landfill, where negative impacts
can be reduced to a minimum.
We highlighted the importance of
good site selection, and some
key operational principles and tasks.
And we ended by showing that also
easy step-wise improvements
can help us upgrade existing dumps.
Well, and that was all for this week.
I invite you to use the forum and
paste your views and personal
experiences, or even to discuss
certain points we have raised
during this first week with
your fellow students.
It would be great if you would
stay with us and join us for
the next week modules, where we
shall be covering various groups
of stakeholders and their roles,
as well as issues regarding
legislation, public awareness and
financing of waste management.
Stay connected!