Hi! Welcome to this module on the waste
generation and characterization.
This is the outline of the module on the
things I would like to share with you.
First of all we'll discuss
why do we need this data
and what do we do with it?
Then we'll look at a waste generation
in different countries across the globe.
Then we'll also look at key properties
of waste, especially composition,
then we'll look at moisture,
density and also calorific value.
Finally we'll conclude by thinking about
how can we measure these parameters
and what are the important
things to consider.
So first, we need to ask the question:
what do we want to
know about waste and why?
You might remember this
graph from previous modules.
That shows the different physical elements
of the waste management stream.
Now, if our question is:
what measures do we want to introduce
for waste prevention and reduction?
It is, of course, important to know
what's is generated in the household,
and what can be achieved
with such measures.
If it's important to
know what the capacity
and the number of collection
vehicles that are necessary,
then it's also important to know
what waste is generated in the household
which needs to be removed
and collected by vehicles.
However, we want to
assess feasibility,
and the scale of a treatment option.
Then it's rather important to know
what's entering the
treatment station at this point
in the waste management stream,
and what needs to be processed.
If our interest is in
identifying recycling opportunities,
then of course we need
to know the composition
and the value of the waste generated.
Finally, if we want to estimate
the life span of the landfill,
then it's important to
measure waste amounts
that are reaching the landfill.
On waste generation,
let's look at this graph from the
global waste management outlook.
What we see here is waste
generation per capita, per year,
and on the x axis we see gross
national income per capita.
What is clearly visible is
that, with increasing income,
we have increasing
waste generation rates.
Poor countries generate less waste,
rich countries generate more waste.
Another way of showing
this is on the global map,
shown with different colors,
low waste generation and high
waste generation in a darker blue.
What you clearly see is
the African sub-continent,
which generally has low waste
generation rates per person.
Also, South Asia has quite
low generation rates per person.
So what influences generation rates?
The evidence is not so clear, but what
is certain is that it's lifestyle,
degree of urbanization, and what we have
just seen previously, income level.
Let me give you an
example of lifestyle.
People that tend to not eat at home,
and eat outside of their home,
they tend to generate
less waste at their house.
That's a typical
phenomenon of lifestyle.
More information on city generation
rates is available in this document:
"What a waste a global
review of solid waste management",
which can be found on the internet
and can be downloaded free of charge.
What's exciting in this
graph is a projection for 2025
in categories of low
income, middle income,
and higher income countries.
What you can see clearly
here is that the increase
will be mostly pronounced in
the lower middle income countries.
This is mainly due to a
large population increase
projected for 2025
in these countries.
Now, let's look at
municipal solid waste composition.
These pie charts show the different
fractions in municipal solid waste.
What we are showing are
4 different pie charts,
for 4 different income groups:
low income countries,
lower middle income countries,
upper middle income
countries, and high income countries.
What we need to highlight is
that in low income countries,
the organic fraction,
is significantly higher
than the organic fraction
in high income countries.
On the other hand,
packaging waste, paper and
plastic in high income countries
is much higher than it is
in low income countries.
Remember that waste
composition may vary quite significantly,
depending on the location.
You see here the same pie chart from
the lower and middle income countries,
and on the right hand side,
you see the composition from
Nouakchott, the capital of Mauritania.
What is astonishing
is that in Nouakchott,
only 5% of waste is organic.
And typically in the lower middle
income countries, it's 53%.
So, why is this?
In Nouakchott in Mauritania,
many households have goats
or they have friends that have goats.
And most of the organic material,
kitchen scraps from the households
are fed to these goats.
That's why the organic fraction in the
residue waste for collection is only 5%.
On the other hand, there is a
significant amount of "others",
which is mostly sand and stones given
the desert area of Mauritania.
Another example is
this one from China,
where we differentiate
between households using gas,
and households using coal.
And you see, the difference is
predominantly in the fraction of "others",
which is mainly ash from using coal,
which then, ends up
in the waste stream.
This example shows how waste
composition affects collection.
This is an example from
Indonesia where waste at the household
has quite a large
fraction of sand and stones.
Here the waste collection vehicle was
adapted by applying these mesh walls,
which act as a sieve during transport,
to let the sand fall out of
the waste collection cart.
Now, let's look at other properties
of municipal waste, again,
by low, middle, and
high income country.
What you see clearly
is the moisture content,
so the amount of water in waste
which is significantly
higher in low income countries
than in high income countries.
Also, the density of waste
which is due to the moisture
is significantly higher in low income
countries than in high income countries.
Finally the lower calorific value
is lower in low income countries,
and much higher in
high income countries.
So why is this important?
Let's focus on density.
If we use such compactor
trucks as is shown here,
these compactor
trucks compact the waste
up to a specification of
500 kilograms per cubic meter.
Now using such a truck,
under such conditions,
does not really fulfill any purpose.
Because the waste is already so dense.
This truck however is very useful
in high income country conditions,
where the waste is very
bulky and needs to be compacted
to efficiently transport the waste.
Finally let's look at another
property of municipal solid waste,
the lower calorific value.
This is a very rough formula
to estimate the lower
calorific value of your waste
based on the
composition of your waste.
What's important is that the
result gives us an indication
if the waste will burn or not.
So for incineration
without adding fuel,
we require a lower calorific value of at
least 1000 kilocalories per kilogram.
If we want to incinerate
and recover energy,
then we will require a
lower calorific value
of at least 1500
kilocalories per kilogram.
In this formula, you see how the
different composition of wastes equate.
Plastic equates quite strongly
in raising the calorific value,
while the moisture
content, the water content,
of course will negatively
influence the calorific value.
As an example, now let's plug in the
numbers for a low income country.
We have 6% paper,
2% textiles,
and 53% biowaste,
which would be the sum of
wooden leaves and food waste.
Then we compute 90 times the 7% of
plastic minus 46 times 60% moisture,
which is a typical
moisture content of such waste.
If you calculate this, the result
is a 310 kilocalories per kilogram.
This tells us that this kind
of waste here would not burn,
and we would have to
add additional fuel
if we would want
to incinerate it.
Or, another option would
be to significantly dry it
and lower the moisture
content in the waste.
Before concluding, now let's
think of where and how to measure.
In this module I won't give
you the necessary information
for a measurement campaign.
However I do want to
highlight a few main issues.
First of all, you need to think.
If you want to divide into sub-areas,
that's important if
you want to understand
how the different income
groups affect waste generation.
What you will also need
to decide is on properties
that you want to measure.
What is always important,
is to ensure random sampling.
To get the variation
of waste generation,
we need to sample
over at least a week,
and if possible, we should also
ensure multi seasonal sampling,
to capture the seasonal variation.
So let's summarize what
we've heard about in this module.
We discussed the importance of
understanding what your questions are,
before developing a
measurement campaign.
Then we looked at waste generation,
and showed how it
varies by country, by city,
and how it correlates
to income and lifestyle.
We also looked at composition.
And the general rule is that low
income will have high organics,
high moisture, and high
density, and low calorific value.
And finally, we looked at
some key issues
in the measurement of waste
characterization and generation,
which is capturing the variation
in the week and in the season,
and ensuring random sampling.
So thanks for listening.