Hi.
Today we will talk about the most
frequent solution of waste
treatment which are
dumpsites and landfills.
Landfill is not a
sustainable solution.
We don't really treat the waste but we
just store it in safe conditions.
Landfill will create long
term effects on the water.
So the surface water or the groundwater,
we transfer to our children
the responsibility and cost to
manage our present waste
and to manage this water in the long term.
But the reality is that in most
cases there are no other solutions
and landfill is the only affordable
solution for the next years
and we have to build and operate
good landfill in order to protect
human health and environment
as much as possible.
In most cases after treatment
and even after incineration,
we still need landfill to store
the residues of the treatments
in every countries.
These are not landfills but just
dumpsites; here in Albania,
in Peru, in Sao Tome, in
Morocco or in India.
We have the same problems everywhere:
we have fire, water contamination,
noxious smokes, strong odors, health
danger for humans and animals.
Stability hazards and
environment destruction.
Such open dumpsites are still the
world's most common disposal method.
This has to be stopped
and can be stopped.
The first measure to take for a
good operation is to close the
sites and limit access.
It is important that nobody can come
and the animals can't enter the sites.
Recycling should be made and
organized upstreams in the town
and not in the dumpsites for
health and security reasons.
Another point is to reduce the
surface of dumping of the waste.
Every area which is not use has
to be covered and we have
to limit the working area to
a very limited zone.
This will avoid the presence of
animals, reduce their water
infiltration and reduce the
production of leachate.
Cover of non-active zone is
important, can be done with inert
material or earthen material.
In any case a water evacuation
system should be realized
in order to reduce as much as possible
the infiltration of rainwater.
Compaction is a key element
for economy and the ecology.
Compaction allows to gain in
volume in the landfill and this
is also a cost reduction.
But compaction also allows to stop
the presence of oxygen in the waste.
This is the best solution to avoid
fire and limit the presence
of animals like rats or
insects in the waste.
No fire, no smoke, no air, no animals.
Compaction will also reduce
the flight of the waste.
The best for this is to use
specialized trucks like this one
but the type of each is strongly
depending on the waste composition
and climate.
Compaction can also be done with
a choice of the trucks path
in the surface of the landfill.
For the environment dumping in
high elevation will reduce
the quantity of waste water or leachate.
The quantity of water going
through the waste is depending on
the surface but not on the height
of the waste so if we are
higher we will produce proportionately
less lixiviate waste.
For that, we have to ensure a
slope stability with a slope of
one vertical to three horizontal
like this: one to three,
for having a good stability in
the outer flank of the landfill.
It is also preferable to begin each
floor by building an external
dyke and it is cover like this.
First we will build this dyke,
we can cover it and then we begin
to dump the waste without to be seen from outside.
This will also limit a little
bit the flight of the waste.
Another important point is to reduce
the flight of plastic and light waste.
This is possible by stretching
high vertical nets around the
dumpsite like here.
Or like here.
For dumpsites as well as for landfill
it is possible and necessary
to build gas vertical
drainage, gas flue.
This allowed to burn the gas at
the surface of the landfill.
This can be done very simply
using stones and metallic tubes
which can be elevated step
by step with a waste.
Gas drainage system allowed to catch
the methane gas and to burn it.
By burning the gas you also
eliminate the very bad smell and
reduce the greenhouse effect
of CH4, the methane.
It's not perfect but very efficient
to reduce odors and air impact.
Drainage of the water is an important
point as well as for landfills
and for dumpsites.
There are two very simple and
important drainage systems to
be build, even if not perfect.
Why is drainage so important
in dumpsites and landfills?
The reason is simple and geomechanic.
If water accumulates into the
body of the waste it creates
a danger of landslides or wasteslides.
This with terrible possible
downstream dangers.
The first drainage is for catching
the rainwater runoff upstream
of the landfill all around in order
to avoid that a big quantity
of water enter the waste.
The second drainage is on
the bottom of the landfill.
The simple horizontal drainage
in the waste every three
or four meters of elevation in
order to avoid the accumulation
of water and risks of landslides.
These drainage can be made easily
with stones or construction waste.
It's also possible to combine the
water drainage with a gas drainage.
Realizing such dumpsite operations
will largely reduce the impacts
but requires two conditions.
Firstly you need a certain amount
of money for that operation,
machines and manpower and you need
to define an engineer responsible
of the site operation.
In a summary, we can say that the
first priority is to organize
and improve the operation of the
landfill or the dumpsite in
order to close the site and stop fire.
This needs to name and train a
head of site operator and
to decide a certain budget for
dumpsite or landfill operations.