Welcome!
In many cities of the
developing countries,
the informal sector
plays a crucial role
in managing municipal solid waste.
In this module, we should look at
that more into depth on this role,
and also, see how a city can
make use of this opportunity
to integrate the informal sector
into the municipal
waste management sector.
I was helped a lot in this
module by Dr Sunjai Gupta.
Informal sector waste
workers are defined as individuals,
or small enterprises, that
intervene in waste management.
They are not formally registered,
and are not formally mandated
with providing waste
management services.
Their predominant activity
is in recycling materials
from the waste stream.
In the recovery recycables,
they are active throughout
the waste management chain.
Starting at the household
as well as scavenging
through garbage bins,
collection points, or disposal sites.
They extract, process
and sell those materials
that have a high intrinsic value,
on which they can make some profit.
But sometimes, they also
provide collection services.
The informal recycling sector
is structured like a pyramid.
At the bottom of the waste
trade pyramid are the waste pickers
who engage in the
free collection of waste
from municipal garbage bins,
streets, and disposal site.
They're often subject to
high occupational risk,
but also socially stigmatized.
Above them are the scrap buyers,
who purchase or
collect small quantities
of recyclable waste
materials from households.
Or small shops that buy
materials from waste pickers.
A new trend for
instance are waste banks,
where residents can
bring their recyclables
for a price or a voucher.
Above this level are then
different levels of traders,
including retailers,
stockists and wholesalers.
Many of whom are also informal
and not registered as businesses.
The materials recovered by
this informal valorization sector
are sold into the larger
industrial value chain.
A smaller amount may be
processed directly by smaller businesses
or cottage industry, to new products.
The trade gets more
specialized as it moves up the pyramid.
At every successive level,
waste is sorted more specifically,
and further processed,
here by adding more value.
Here are some examples of these
different types of informal waste workers,
starting with the waste pickers.
Scavenging materials at the roadside,
or from the trucks
delivering to the disposal site.
It becomes obvious from these pictures
that this is a quite a high
risk and hazardous activity.
On the other hand, they are also the
collectors of recyclables at the household,
often they are equipped
with their own vehicle.
Such is this example from Thailand
that collects recyclables
at household level.
And finally, the junk shop, a
trading station for these recyclers,
but also the location where
recyclables are sorted further,
stored, and then sold to
the next level of trader
in larger bulk amounts.
What is actually quite typical,
besides the collection of
recycled at the household level,
are also formal employees of
the waste collection service,
that informally practice the
recovery of recycled materials
during their collection duties.
As shown here, where you can see
the baskets attached to the trucks,
where materials are collected.
The collectors remove items of value,
from the mixed waste stream,
and store them in these baskets.
A study by the collaborative
working group on solid waste management,
in collaboration
with the German Society
for International Corporation GIZ,
conducted a detailed study,
in different cities worldwide,
to assess the importance and
contribution of the informal sector.
Here is a graph, on the average
cost savings for each municipality,
showing 6 major cities.
You can see that
depending on the city,
the cost savings for the municipality
range between 1 and 16
million euro per year.
Major savings relate to the
effect of recycling before collection.
The savings by
recycling at the landfill
are mostly related to space saving,
and extending the life
span of the landfill.
Then there are also
other cost savings,
which are a bit more
difficult to monitorize,
such as the savings due to
substitution of raw materials.
Estimates of these
savings in externalities
are shown here for 3 cities
ranging from 2,4 million
in Quezon city Philippines,
up to 7,2 million for Lima, Peru.
And lastly, it's important to state
that outsourcing to waste pickers cooperatives,
wherever they exist,
is often cheaper than involving
formal private public partnerships,
or private sector involvement.
Study from Mumbai showed
that the informal sector
is 20% cheaper than
the municipal services,
while the private
sector is only 6% cheaper.
Besides the cost savings for
the municipality, of course,
the informal sector is an
important source of livelihood
for millions of people.
It is estimated that worldwide,
nearly 15 million people work in
the informal waste management sector.
This graph shows the number
of informal waste workers,
as compared to those
employed in the formal sector
for some selected cities.
Of course, variations can be
quite large depending on the city,
and on the context.
But just look at Cairo, as an example,
where 33000 people are
working in the informal sector,
as compared to 8800
in the formal sector.
This is a factor of 3,7.
This informal sector recovers
significant amounts of the waste stream.
Earnings of this informal
sector can vary significantly,
depending on the type of
activity, the people engaged in.
Typically though, waste picking is the
lowest paid part of the recycling chain.
But even here, like in
this example from Brazil,
a study showed that 1/3 of the waste pickers earn the minimum wage,
or slightly above, while more than half
earn up to 4 times the minimum wage.
Attitudes of municipal authorities
towards the informal sector
differ from place to place.
In some places there is hostility, in
others indifference, and in some places,
they are regarded as a useful
part of the waste management system,
and are given the opportunity
to enhance their livelihoods.
The role of the
municipality is critical,
to mobilizing the informal sector,
and organizing the recycling sector.
The first way to
upgrade the informal sector
would be to integrate them
into the city's masterplan.
But also integrate them into
collecting waste at source,
with the right over recyclables,
and a guarantee of
regular access to waste.
In a recent development,
waste picker cooperatives
had been formed by the informal
sector, workers, in many countries,
with the help of
non-governmental organization,
municipalities, and donor agencies.
These workers undertake
some formal work under contract
to municipal authorities, while also
being involved in informal recycling.
Thus in this respect
making their roles semi-formal.
Now let's look at some examples how
the informal sector was integrated.
Brazil is one of the
world's most progressive countries
in integrating waste pickers in
solid waste management system.
And Belo Horizonte has
led the way in this effort.
Already back in 1993,
the city put a focus
on promoting
segregation at the source,
and started integrating
the informal sector,
by helping to develop cooperatives,
and guide them throughout,
towards material recovery
close to the household,
instead of waste
scavenging at the landfill.
In Belo Horizonte, there are an estimated
2700 informal waste workers in the city.
With the assistance
of the municipality,
8 different cooperatives were created.
For these cooperatives, warehouses
are provided by the municipality.
Here, the materials are processed,
before moving up the recycling chain.
All cooperatives were
provided with scales,
personal protection equipment,
and big bags for storage.
Since 2001 Brazil has even included
"catador de material reciclado".
Sorry for that terrible
Portuguese pronunciation,
which stands for
collector of recyclables,
as a formal profession in the
Brazilian occupation classification.
Another example of a successful
integration of the informal sector
is the SWACH cooperative in Pune, India.
SWACH is a wholly owned
cooporative of waste pickers.
It started off as a 2 year
pilot project from 2005 to 2007
that carefully tested and
established the workability of this model.
Then, in 2008 SWACH then entered
into a memorandum of understanding,
with the Pune municipal corporation,
to collect waste, door to door,
and this was an important
milestone for the waste pickers.
The scope of SWACH
includes collection,
resource recovery,
trade and waste processing.
And it is conceived as an
autonomous social enterprise.
It is in close contact with the clients
and residents by providing this service,
and it also operates a
helpline for feedback and complaints.
Currently, through its 1867 members,
with 80% of the members being women,
it provides service to the
1,5 million people of Pune.
The cooperative is overseen
by a governing board
that has 14 waste picker
members on the board,
2 representatives of the
Pune municipal corporation,
and 2 members of the
trade union of waste pickers.
Data has shown that
waste reaching the landfill
has been reduced by more
than 55%, or 320 tons per day.
So let me summarize what we
have covered in this module.
We have looked at the
significant role of the informal sector
recovering up to 30%
of the waste stream.
We also looked at the cost
savings for the municipality,
up to 16 million euro per year
for the example of Lima, Peru.
Waste recycling provides up
to 2% source of livelihood
for the urban poor.
And recycling happens
all along the waste chain.
One can estimate one job
for each ton recovered.
What's also important is
that work conditions and income
improve when recycling is closer
to the source of waste generation
or formalized, for instance,
through cooperatives.
Thank you for listening.