Hi. This module and the next one will deal about
money. Did you ever ask yourself which
money flows in solid waste management
systems exist? In this first module we
will learn and we will discuss the main
costs of solid waste management services
and various methods to finance
investment costs. Whereas in the next
module we will mainly talk about
operation and maintenance costs. The very
first thing, the main responsible for the
solid waste management service of the
city needs to know in order to take cost
effective decisions, are the total costs
of providing a good service,
considering all the physical elements.
Based on this, we can assess how to
improve the cost efficiency and what it
might cost to improve the service.
Unfortunately very rarely are the costs fully known.
Often the costs are shared by multiple actors
or there is not a separate municipal
budget for solid waste management costs
and money comes from different sources.
Or part of the allotted budget is used
for other expenses. In any case, in solid
waste management we distinguish two
types of costs: investment costs also
called capital costs and operation and
maintenance costs also called recurrent
costs. There are however externalities
which are often not quantified in
economic terms that are also considered
hidden costs. What are these
externalities? If there is inadequate or
no solid waste management, there are also
costs and these are called externalities.
For instance, the death of animals eating
waste or grazing on contaminated land.
Public health impacts: The externalities can be
associated to the cost of
buying medicine or visiting the doctor
or even the loss of revenues by not
being able to work,
water contamination and the costs of
having to clean that water or the costs
of finding another more expensive clean
water source, impact on tourism and
economy in general.
According to the recently published
"Global Waste Management Outlook Report",
the cost of these externalities can
represent 20 to 50$ per capita
per year or even more. Expanding waste
collection coverage or upgrading
disposal facilities costs are a fraction of
that. It is cheaper for the society
to manage its waste now in an
environmentally sound manner than to carry on
polluting the environment and then trying to
clean it up later. If that is even
possible.
Ok. But now back to the costs in terms of
expenditures by the municipality or the
organization providing the service of
solid waste management, which are
investment costs and operation and
maintenance costs. These costs are paid
from different money sources. Let's have
a look to each of them separately. What
do we mean by investment costs?
Investment costs, also called capital
costs, are all those related to
developing and constructing
infrastructure or large equipment. There
are five main financial sources for this
costs. These are national government,
local government, local or international
financial institutions, which are most of
the times
banks or the private sector, donors, or a
combination of this. The money received
can either be a grant, which are non-repairable
funds or loans, which need to
be paid back. Let's briefly describe each
of these options.
National government funding is a very
important source of investment finances.
For example, for the People's Republic of
China, municipal solid waste management
infrastructure has been a priority since
2000. Or in India the Jawaharlal
National Urban Renewal Mission launched
by the central government and envisages
an investment of 20 billion US$.
Local governments can also invest in
solid wastes management services, after
raising funds from
local sources of income. These could be
taxes such as the property tax fees such
as parking fees or reserves for
instance. Reserves are portions of
current revenues, which were saved for
financing future investment. Ideally,
most investment costs should be financed
through this use of reserves. However,
this is not the case, as it requires good
planning. Another way to obtain finances
for capital investments is to raise
funds through the issuance of bonds.
Often local and national governments
have other priorities than providing
waste services for the limited budgets.
So municipalities often need borrowings,
also called loans, which are lend by
local banks or international financial
institutions. Some of the most active
international financial institutions in
solid waste management investments are
the World Bank, the Asian Development Bank and
the Inter American Development Bank which
many of you might have heard of. For you
to have an idea of the amounts that are
being invested here, it may be helpful to
know that 4 billion US$ were
invested in solid waste management
services between 2003 and 2012 globally.
This might sound like a lot. However it
represents approximately 0.3% of
the overall development finance. It's a
tiny portion. In terms of the population
of the countries receiving Solid Waste
Management Development Finance in 2012,
this equates 0.09$ per
capita. Much less than per capita levels
of 2.43$ in the water and
sanitation sector and 31$ of
development finance overall. Not every
municipality is eligible for these loans.
The World Bank for instance estimates
that of the 500 largest cities in the
developing world, only 4% are credit worthy.
in international capital markets.
Grant-funded support is the other key
element of Development Cooperation
amounting to an estimated 1.2 billion
dollars between 2003
and 2012. These funds are free of interest
costs. However, the donor financing often
comes with requirements such as
achieving full cost recovery or using
public-private partnerships or other
private financing schemes. Experience
also shows that free money also has
risks that cities need to be aware of.
When money comes easily, facilities are
often oversized, affecting considerably
the operation and maintenance costs. Or
investments are made into technologies
which do not fit with the local climate
condition or waste characteristics. For
instance, building an incineration plant
where municipal solid waste management
is predominantly wet and has low calorific
value or obtaining compactor trucks for
a city with unpaved and narrow streets
with high waste density. The cost of
operating and maintaining these three
vehicles is often several
times higher than operating a more
appropriate but maybe not sophisticated vehicle,
such as the one shown on the right.
When will the private sector be involved in
investing? They will only do this if they
can recover their investments and earn
profit or if they can use the secondary
products and/or energy obtained from
waste. Let me give you two examples: in
2008, the industry group called the
Indian Tobacco Company based in
Coimbatore invested in waste collection
in order to secure reliable supplies for
paper. Or the second example is based in
Cape Town, where due to the demand for
compost from source separated green
waste on behalf of the farms, a farmer runs
still the biggest existing composting installation.
In this module we learned about the total
cost ofproviding solid waste management services.
Knowing this cost is really important.
These are investment costs, operation and
maintenance costs, which will be covered
in the next module, and externalities.
Furthermore, we also saw the most common
sources that exist to cover investment
costs, which are coming from national
government, local governments, local and
international financing institutions,
donors and the private sector.
For those interested in deepening
the topic, we recommend
these two key readings, which are
downloadable for free from the internet.