Hi.
This week, we'll talk about
anaerobic digestion technologies
and their practical operation.
Remember, you can download the book
for free, from our webpage,
if you want more detailed information
on anaerobic digestion.
This diagram looks really scary,
but don't worry, it isn’t.
It's a classification of different types
of AD technologies.
We can differentiate
between dry and wet systems,
between batch and continuous systems,
between thermophilic
and mesophilic operating systems
and between one-stage
and multi-stage technologies.
What I would like to go through
together with you in this module,
is I would like to look
at wet, continuous,
mesophilic, and one-stage reactors.
The examples that we will be discussing
are floating-drum, fixed-dome,
and balloon-type digestors.
Continuous actually means
that we are feeding
at a regular interval, at the same time,
an equivalent volume that enters,
an equivalent volume
will also leave the digestor.
Wet means that we'll be operating
with the total solid content
of 16% or less,
so low TS.
So, now, let's look at these digestors,
Let me start by showing you
the wet, continuous, mesophilic
fixed-dome reactor.
This is a brick-built
and gas-tight plastered structure,
which is often put underground.
It has an inlet pipe,
where the waste material is fed
into the digestor.
It has a digestor,
with a volume of slurry,
and then, it has
the gas-holder storage space.
What it further has is an outlet,
or what we also call
compensation chamber,
and the overflow.
You might also see here
that the gas pipe is at the highest point,
with a valve to open
or close the gas flow.
There are different designs
of fixed-dome digestors,
and sizes can vary.
This is the most common
reactor-type in developing countries.
When starting the reactor
for the first time,
it is important to inoculate the reactor
with methanogenic bacteria.
The easiest way to do this
is by adding cow manure,
and water, with the ratio of 1:1,
or, even easier, use digestate
from another reactor.
A rule of thumb is
that it needs about 10%
of the reactor volume as cow manure
to start the process.
But more is also fine, or even better.
In this animation, we can see
how this works.
The waste material is mixed with water
and enters the reactor,
and mixes with the material
already in the reactor
undergoing degradation.
Bio-gas is generated in the slurry
through anaerobic digestion.
The gas bubbles then move
to the top part of the reactor
where gas accumulates
and starts to build up pressure
if the valve is closed.
When the valve is closed,
the gas pressure will increase,
and push down the slurry
in the reactor,
and up into the overflow chamber.
When then the gas is used,
the gas pressure drops,
and the slurry level balances out
to a new equilibrium.
Here, you see a sequence of pictures
of the construction
of a fixed-dome reactor in Lesotho
during the building
of the structure and the dome.
Here, the dome is just about finished.
And here, it's being plastered.
This is another example from Indonesia.
What you see here is that the bottom part
is built with concrete,
and the dome part
is just starting to be built with bricks.
Here is a summary of some advantages
and some disadvantages.
For the advantages,
let me highlight three:
long life span,
absence of moving parts,
and the underground construction
which saves space.
There are also disadvantages.
I'll also highlight a few:
one is that it needs
specific technical skills,
it also needs a special sealant
to make sure that's gas-tight,
and another disadvantage
is the fluctuating gas pressure
depending on the volume
of the stored gas,
and its use.
A second type
is the floating-drum digestor.
You see this in this picture.
It has similar features:
the inlet, the digestor for the slurry,
the outlet, and the overflow.
But here now, the gas holder
is not a fixed unit
but is a moving unit.
Here it's floating on a water jacket,
in some cases, it could also be floating
directly on the slurry.
With increasing gas pressure,
this floating gas holder moves upwards,
and when gas is used,
the weight of the drum
pushes it back down.
The gas drum is typically made of metal,
painted to protect it from corrosion.
It can also be made out of
fiber glass reinforced plastic,
or galvanized sheet metal.
In this design,
there is also a guiding pole
to make sure to stabilize it
while it's going up and down.
There is also a divider wall
which helps to avoid
short circuiting of the slurry
from the inlet to the outlet.
You see it here.
The digestor is often placed
below the ground
while the gas holder drum is above ground.
Here is an example
of such floating drum digestors
from India
with the metal floating gas holders.
Or here, another; also, from India.
Here are examples of small household units
made out of fiber glass
reinforced plastic.
The brown part on the top
is the floating drum.
Or here, another example from Tanzania
made by using
the typical water tanks out of plastic
and some plastic piping.
Here are some advantages and disadvantages
of the floating-drum reactors.
Advantages are: that it's simple
and easy to operate;
one big advantage is that the volume
of gas is directly visible
and that means we know
if the system is working or not;
we also have constant gas pressure,
or we can increase this pressure
by adding some weight
on the gas holder tank.
Some disadvantages are
the high material costs
for the steel drum,
and that these steel parts
are susceptible to corrosion.
There are also regular
maintenance costs that arise,
from keeping this corrosion at bay.
The third digestor type
I would like to show you
is the tubular digestor,
like this one in Costa Rica.
These are quite common
in the Latin American region.
These are long horizontal line
tubes or balloons,
made out of plastic and rubber.
The inlet and outlet are attached
directly to the skin of the balloon.
You see this here in this schematic:
the balloon, the inlet, and the outlet,
and the gas pipe on the top.
These balloons usually need
some protection
from the top, as well as from the bottom,
what we usually have
as a compacted backfill.
Some advantages are:
low construction costs,
very simple to install,
easy to construct,
but some disadvantages are:
a relative short life span,
and susceptible to mechanical damage.
So, those were the three types
of technologies
that I wanted to share with you.
There are a lot of variations in design.
For instance, this combination
of a fixed structure for the digestate,
and then a balloon for the gas storage.
This is an example from Germany.
Why don't you share with us
what kind of systems
you might have encountered
in your region or during your travels?
Submit them into our forum.
So let me summarize
what we covered in this module:
we looked at three different types
of digestors,
we looked at their design features
and some examples.
For each, we listed some advantages
and disadvantages.
In the next module, we'll focus
on maintaining the digestor in operation
and at the product chain,
the gas, and the digestate.
Thanks very much.