Hi again! In this last module on anaerobic
digestion, we'll talk about using the
product of AD. The gas and the
digestate. I will try to explain what needs
to be considered so that a biogas
facility can be sustained and maintained.
Before we do this however, let me quickly
sum up what we have heard about AD until
now. So, we have looked at some issues of
the substrate chain, we have talked about
particle size, we had talked about
volatile solids of different waste
materials I also described the
biochemical process stages and the main
parameters, which are contained in here
and some typical digester technologies.
So, what now is left to do, is to cover
the product chain. The gas and the
digestate. We will also discuss the
issues around sustaining the whole
system and answering the question, when
can anaerobic digestion be an
appropriate treatment option for waste
management. And when not. So, now with an
appropriate digester and in good
operating conditions the reactor will
produce biogas. This biogas is
saturated with water vapor and in the
first instance the water vapor moving
through the pipes will condensate and
moisture will collect as water in the
pipes. We will need to remove this
moisture. We call this dewatering. We can
remove the water at the lowest point in
the pipes. If this water is not removed,
it can block the pipes, hindering flow of
gas. That is why you will need to install
a water trap at the lowest point in the
gas lines. There are different types of
water traps you can install. Here are two
examples: an automatic one and a manual one.
Both have T-joints at the lowest
point in the gas pipes and  a water storage
unit below the T-joint, where the
condensate can flow into. The automatic
trap
empties itself, when full, by using a
U-bend overflow, whereas the manual water trap
is emptied by opening a valve. The biogas
produced in the reactor will vary during
the day according to feeding patterns
and also ambient temperature changes.
Biogas production also continues during
night time when less gas is used and
therefore there are periods when the gas
has to be stored. This can either be in
the digester itself as in the top part
of the fixed dome digesters, as we had seen
before, or in bags or balloons like in
this unit in Indonesia. Gas can also be
stored with medium or high pressure in
gas tanks.This can be done with
compressors, but of course this requires
energy. The Indian Institute of
Technology in Delhi is engaged in
research on bottling of biogas. For use
as fuel in three wheeled vehicles. They
combine conditioning and cleaning of biogas
and compression. In an uncompressed form,
the energy content of one cubic meter of
biogas corresponds to around a half a
litre of diesel. As a rough rule of thumb,
about 10 kilograms of biowaste are needed
to produce this one cubic meter of
biogas. For all use in machines, engines
or generators, biogas needs to be
conditioned. We could also call this
cleaned. The goal is to remove water
vapor, which we've already talked about, but more
importantly also hydrogen sulfide, which
is very corrosive and CO2, which has no
energy value. Removing hydrogen sulfide
is what we call desulphurisation.
We can do this with ferrous oxide, which
then transform the hydrogen sulfide
into iron sulfide. We can also do this
with water scrubbers which at the same
time also can remove CO2.
If we think about biogas application
and appliances, actually the most simple
way is to use the biogas close to the
anaerobic digestion facility for direct
combustion. For this purpose,
conditioning of biogas is not necessary.
A household cooking stove only needs
20 to around 450 litres per hour.
Frequently, when no direct use of gas is
obvious, methane is fed into gas
generators to produce electricity.
However, with the conversion losses we
can only retain about 30 percent of the
energy as electricity, the remaining is
lost as heat. Besides the gas, another
product from anaerobic digestion is the
digestate. In wet digestion systems,
this is a nutritious slurry with
nitrogen, phosphorus, potassium, as well as
trace elements. 50% of this nitrogen is
available as ammonium nitrogen that can be
directly assimilated by plants. So, all in
all, it's a good fertilizer, that can be
used in agriculture. But remember if it's
in the mesophilic range, we're not having
high temperatures, so if we have
pathogenic substances these are not
hygienisized. If it is not possible to use
this digestate in agriculture, then
the digestate has to be treated before
disposal, as it still has a high organic
load and based on regulations would not
be allowed for discharge into surface
waters. Remember no system works without
maintenance and care. What does that mean
for biogas systems? We need to regularly
check for leaks.
We can do this with a pressure test,
looking if the gas pipes are ok. We also
need to check and unblock pipes if
required. We don't need to forget, to
empty water traps and we need to
regularly observe the slurry level in
the outlet chamber.
It gives us a lot of information on the
processes. Remember to not overload the
digester, otherwise we will have
acidification. And now and then we need to
desludge the digester. Typically
recommended is every 5 to 10 years
and this will be mostly sand and grit
which accumulates at the bottom of the
digester. So, now we've heard a lot about
anaerobic digestion as an option for
waste management. But when should we
actually choose this option?
Well, one aspect is that we need access
to a well-sorted organic waste source.
What we also need to think about is that
we need local skills and experience in
construction and operation. Then need and
demand for gas is a requirement. Or we
need to have a small power grid which we
can feed into. We also need a competitive
chance to compete with other energy
sources. And this is an economic issue.
Finally, we need an institutional
environment allowing feeding into the
grid, especially for converting gas to
electricity. And ideally we need a demand
for the digestate for reuse in
agriculture. So let me summarize what we
covered in this module. We looked at
biogas dewatering and conditioning. We
looked at biogas storage options, we
looked at gas use and energy content, we
discussed what issues are necessary to
maintain the system. And finally, we also
looked at criteria favoring the choice
of using anaerobic digestion for organic
solid waste treatment. Thanks for
listening