Hi. Welcome back. In this module,
we'll try to give you a glimpse
of a quite innovative biological
treatment process which
is feeding biowaste to insect larvae
and then harvesting the larvae as
protein source. For this, let me
introduce you to Stefan Diener.
Stefan has been researching this
process for a number of years
and he's really the ideal
person to give this overview.
Stefan, welcome, and
the floor is yours.
Thank you, Chris, and thank you
very much for giving me
the chance to help you with this
module, but, first of all,
let me also introduced the main actors of
this module: the black soldier flies.
Are you already excited about
them or still grossed out?
Here is the outline of this module.
First of all, I'll tell you something
about the life cycle because
we need to know the biology before
we can go into the treatment.
Then, we'll look at the rearing and
then the treatment technology itself.
And at the end, we will take a
look at the conversion products,
which are key for this technology.
To put it in a nutshell, fly larvae
composting converts different
organic sources into valuable
end-products which come as nutrient
rich larvae which can be used as animal
feed or nutrient rich soil amendments.
In this process, we make use of
the black soldier fly larvae's
voracious appetite. They not only
process with large amounts of
organic material, they do that very
fast as well, watch closely.
In this clip, you see them
feeding on to rainbow trout.
One on the right is cooked and
the one on the left is raw and,
as you can see, in a period of about
7 hours, both fish are devoured.
Once the larvae have processed
the material and gained a lot
of weight, they can be
harvested as you can see here.
Thereafter, they can be fed to
animals, here we fed them
to piglets and you see here
how they love the larvae.
Now, let us take a closer look at the
life cycle of the black soldier fly.
This will help us to understand why
this particular fly is suitable
for organic waste management.
The organism of our interest is the black
soldier fly, Hermetia illucens.
It has its origin in the Americas
but has been spread over the
world by the transport of goods
and can, nowadays, be found
in the temperate and tropical areas.
It's quite a big fly compared to the
house fly, it's about 10 times heavier.
And its adult lives only
for about a week.
During this time, it doesn't take
up food, that means, it does
not hop from one food source to
the other and therefore cannot
spread diseases. Its main activity, during
the adult stage, is pretty simple.
It just has to find a
mate and reproduce.
Now, this is how it works: an
adult fly lives for about a week
and during this time it mates and
the female lays about a 1,000
eggs close to a suitable feed source.
This can be a wide variety of
organic material, such as food,
market waste, animal manure, slaughterhouse
waste, or even human excreta.
The eggs take about 3 days to
hatch and small larvae emerge.
At this moment, they're only
about one millimeter in size.
These tiny larvae search now for
food and feed on it for over
a period of 14 days. During this
time, they grow from 1 millimeter
to around 2. 5 centimeters length and
finally weigh about 200 milligrams.
They go through 5 larval stages
before they molt a last time
and become the so-called prepupa.
These prepupae search for a dry,
dark location to pupate,
and thus usually crawl out
of the waste source.
Pupation takes about 3 weeks and
results in the emergent fly.
Now this was the natural life cycle.
We want to use this knowledge now
to design a treatment facility.
First, we want to manage a breeding
and rearing facility which
guarantees us a constant supply of fresh
young larvae to add to the waste.
To reach this, you need to provide
the flies with an environment
which makes them happy and
stimulates them to mate.
This means enough light, space and
humidity or even a water source.
In this picture, you see a couple of
cages which meet these conditions.
We call them love cages.
Within the love cage, we
provide the female with a medium
into which they like to lay eggs, like
this sheet of corrugated cardboard.
It's placed above a substrate
which gives off a strong smell
or, you can also say, it stinks.
Females are attracted by the smell
and fill the holes with eggs.
Here you see a few females which
are just about to place their
eggs into the openings. On the
right picture, we see the egg
packages that fill the holes,
for example here and here.
Each package contains
800 to 1,000 eggs.
Once the larvae have hatched, we
keep them in the nursery for
5 days before adding
them to the biowaste.
Ideally, you prepare the waste by
grinding it up so that
the larvae can feed easier on it.
Typically, we add a defined amount of
larvae to a given amount of biowaste.
The ratio however varies
depending on the substrate.
For food waste, for example, we
need about 8,000 larvae to treat
1 kilogram per day. After they
have fed for about 2 weeks,
the larvae are ready to be harvested.
By the time we harvest, the wet
waste has been reduced by 80% to 90%.
Although this approach can be
considered quite new, if you search
the Internet you will find a lot
of videos, pictures and small
scale systems that people have
experimented with or are even for sale.
Most of them make use of the
prepupae's habit to crawl out of
the material and offered therefore
some sort of ramp to harvest
the protein rich prepupae.
In most of these systems, you do
not maintain a separate colony
or nursery like I described
before, but you rely on natural
reproduction and assume that
females are attracted by the smell
of the waste and lay enough eggs
to keep the process running.
On the other end of the spectrum,
there are a few large facilities
operating in different
parts of the world.
They are all designed to process more
than 60 tons of waste per day.
For some of them, revenue comes not
only from selling the harvested
larvae but also from the treatment
feed, meaning that they are
paid for taking the waste from
the one who generates it.
But you may ask, why are people
so eager to use this fly?
Of course, the waste reduction is
impressive. The process in general
is fascinating but honestly, it's
all about the products:
the residue and the larvae. The residue
is similar to vermicompost,
you get about the 100 to 200
kilograms per ton input, but
you have to keep in mind that the
BSF process does not kill all
the pathogens that are
present in the waste.
That means, if we have an input
source which is contaminated,
we need a sanitizing post-treatment
step for the residue.
This also applies for the
larvae, our second product.
Depending on the input source, you can
harvest 100 to 200 kilograms per ton.
The larvae, they consist of
40% protein and 30% fat.
This makes them an attractive
feed source for animal and
they can replace the fish meal
nowadays used in animal feed.
In the chart, you see the
development of the prize for fish
meal over the past 15 years.
As you can see, it tripled
in the past 10 years.
The reason is: the demand has
increased because there is much
more aquaculture today than ever
before, and the wild fish population
on the other hand is depleting.
With increasing fish meal prizes,
the larvae become an interesting
option for both, the animal feed
producer on one hand, but also
for the waste manager because
selling the larvae at a good price
helps covering to treatment costs.
Let me summarize what we just learned.
Just like it's the case with worms
in vermicomposting or bacteria
in anaerobic digestion, we have
to know the life cycle and
the preferences of our target organism
in order to optimize
the treatment technology. So we learned
about their huge appetite,
which leads to the reduction of
about 80%, but it's not only
about the waste reduction, it's
also about the larvae production.
Meaning that from one ton of
waste we can harvest up to 200
kilograms of larvae. They replace
fish meal in animal feed and
there are existing backyard applications
and some large scale operations.
I hope your disgust has now
transformed into ecstasy.
Thanks for watching and goodbye.