Hi and welcome to this module on
thermochemical conversion of biomass!
In this module we will introduce the most
common thermochemical processes used to
treat biomass. These are pyrolysis, gasification
and combustion. These technologies can be
technically complex and expensive.
However, we will focus only on cases and
examples that are existing in
developing countries. So, what is a
thermochemical conversion. Thermochemical
conversion implies exposing biomass to
high temperatures between 200 and 1500
degrees Celsius. These high temperatures
together with other parameters such as
oxygen supply, use of catalysts, time and
pressure decompose and depolymerize
biomass into either intermediaries, which
are used later to synthesize
more complex products or into its
simplest constituents such as water and
CO2. Let's briefly describe some basics
of each technology. We will start with
drying, although drying is not a
thermochemical processes on its own.
Feedstocks need to be dried before being
processed. This occurs at temperatures
up to 100 degrees. Pyrolysis is not only
an independent process but the core
reaction of all thermal processes. It is
the first step in the gasification and
combustion process. Pyrolysis occures
when biomass is thermally decomposed at
temperatures between 300 and 600 in the
absence of oxygen. The absence of oxygen
can also be explained by lambda which is
the little figure that you see there.
Lambda is the ratio between the oxygen supply
to the thermal process and the oxygen
required for complete
combustion of all organic compounds. In this
case, therefore, lambda is 0. Broadly
speaking, two types of pyrolysis can be
distinguished slow pyrolysis and fast
pyrolysis. These vary on several
process conditions: Retention times for
instance are around one second for fast
pyrolysis and can last several days for
slow pyrolysis.
The process results into solids, namely
char, liquids called bio-oil and a
mixture of gases, some of which are
fuel-gases also called pyrogas and
some of which are combustion gases, such
as CO2 and water vapor. The relative
proportion of the output materials
depends on the process conditions. In
slow pyrolysis approximately 35% of the
input is turned into char. 30%
into bio-oil and 35% into gases.
Whereas fast pyrolysis obtains much
more liquids.
Around 75% of the input, and lower solid
and gases 12 and 30%
respectively.
The reaction after reaching 280 degrees
Celsius becomes exothermic and generates
heat. Torrefaction is a form of mild
pyrolysis, which occures at
290 degrees Celsius and lasts for 10
to 60 minutes. 80% of the
input is turned into a solid product of
higher homogeneity and increased energy
density compared to the input material.
The rest becomes gas. Let's move forward.
Gasification is our next process on the
list. This thermal conversion of organic
material takes place at elevated
temperatures, above 750 degrees Celsius
with a partial supply of oxygen. Lambda
ranging between 0.2 and 0.5. Retention
times are short, ranging between seconds
and minutes. In this process,
85% of the input material is
then converted into a
mixture of permanent gases. Carbon
monoxide, carbon dioxide and hydrogen,
also called syngas or producer gas.
Char would represent only 10% of the
output, whereas liquids would only be
5% consisting mainly of water
and condesables as minor products.
Combustion is our last process.
Combustion occures at higher temperatures
over 700 degrees Celsius in the presence
of oxygen being lambda higher than one.
Burning is how you and me would normally
refer to this process.
Combustion is the oldest way of using
biomass and accounts for over
97% of the world's bioenergy production.
During combustion,
organic matter is decomposed to produce
mainly gases carbon dioxide and water
vapor, as well as ashes. The chemical
energy is released as heat. In the ternary
diagram, we can see how thermochemical
processes shift materials in different
directions based on the relative content
of carbon, hydrogen and oxygen. We see
where biomass is located here in the middle.
Slow pyrolysis for instance
increases the relative carbon content
shifting the biomass towards the black
area. Char is a solid product. On the other
hand, oxidation or combustion mainly yield
gaseous products such as CO2 and water,
which can also be seen here in the diagram.
Time for some clarification: We saw that
char is one of the output products of
these processes. But char, charcoal,
biochar. Did you ever hear these terms?
Do you actually know what they mean? Let's
see what are their differences. The
term char is generally used for the
solid product obtained from the thermal
decomposition of any biomass, which has a
higher heating value of approximately 25
to 28 megajoules per kilogram. When
char is obtained from less bulky
biomass, such as leaves, small branches,
plant seeds, coconut shells, etc.,
the final output might be too dusty to
be burnt directly, as the one seen
in the movie. And therefore it requires
briquetting. Briquettes have a lower calorific
value due to binding materials used. When
the biomass is wood, the material
obtained through the same process, is
called charcoal. Charcoal is mainly used
as fuel for cooking or industrial
processes, as it has a high heating value
of 31 to 33 megajoules per kilogram,
much higher than the others. Most of the times
charcoal does not require any
post-processing. Char can also be used
as soil-amendment, in which case it's called
biochar. This is the core idea of the
Terra Petra Movement.
So, what products can we obtain from
these thermochemical processes? We've
seen that the primary products are
char, bio-oil, fuel, gas and heat.
For char, we talked about 3 market
products that we can obtain: charcoal,
briquettes and biochar. Char can also
be refined into biofuel or other
chemicals. Bio-oil and fuel gases can be
upgraded through refinery in order to
synthesize other chemical compounds, or
to be used as biofuels. They could also
be consumed in turbines engines or
boilers and produce electricity and heat.
The heat obtained from combustion can be
used in boilers to obtain electricity or
directly commercialized. Thermochemical
conversions are therefore promising,
considering the growing challenge of
waste disposal and fossil fuels.
Being aware that biomass represents the
biggest waste fraction in developing
countries, these processes might represent
opportunities to valorize it.
How are these processes currently being used
to treat waste in developing countries?
From the ones explained before, we will
mainly focus on two: slow pyrolysis and
combustion, since they are the ones that
are being used. Let's have a closer look to them.
Did you know that carbonization or char
making is a slow pyrolysis process?
We humans have produced char since the
dawn of civilization. In developing countries
this is still a very extended practice
as it consists the main source for
cooking fuel. 80 to 90% of
urban households in sub-saharan Africa
for instance use charcoal for cooking
and heating. Charcoal production in
Africa was 29 million tons in 2011. This
table here shows some big charcoal
producers in the world. Although urban
biowaste represents a potential feedstock
for charcoal production, the majority of the
charcoal is derived from wood, which
substantially contributes to deforestation.
Let's have a closer look to the
charring process.
This figure here illustrates the changes
in weight, volume and heating value after
slow pyrolysis of wood to charcoal. We see
that the weight is reduced to 20%,
the volume to 50% and heating value is
doubled. During carbonization, materials
are dehydrated and deoxygenated,
resulting in a decrease of the hydrogen
carbon ratio and oxygen carbon ratio.
The Van Krevelen diagram is used to
depict this. On the horizontal axis, we see
the oxygen to carbon ratio and on the
vertical axis the hydrogen carbon ratio.
These areas show where biomass and
other solid fuels are located according
to these ratios. Carbonization will
shift the values of the regional
biomass in this direction. The length
of the arrow between input and output
ratios indicates the intensity of the
process. The bigger the intensity, the
more oxygen and hydrogen that are lost,
lowering the ratios and the better fuel
properties that output material has.
This graph shows the impact of temperature on
a solid yield. The lower the temperature,
the higher the solid yield, which is partly due
to higher volatile matter content.
With higher temperatures more volatile matter
is degraded, reducing the solid yield,
but obtaining a cleaner and preferable
fuel. High content of volatile matter
in char, over 40%, is
undesirable. Volatile matter facilitates
ignition but produces noxious fumes
when burnt. The input requirements depend
on the final use of the product. Either
if it's for domestic use or industrial use.
In any case, having moisture content
lower than 10% is a requirement, which
means that fresh biomass often needs to
be dried beforehand. Feedstocks with high
fixed carbon content are preferred, as
fixed carbon provides an approximation
of the possible char yield that we're going to
get. While feedstocks with a high ash
content like rice husks for example or
contaminated with inert material such as
sand, produce char with very high ash
content.
And this lowers the heating value of the char.
How do we know when the reaction is
finished? Look at the smoke. In
traditional charcoal making, three stages
can be characterized based on the color
of the smoke emitted. Drying white smoke,
pyrolysis yellow smoke, and process
completion of char or combustion blue smoke.
Pyrolysis technology can look very fancy but
actually the vast majority of the
reactors in developing countries are
simple and functional. In this video we
see how cardboard is carbonized in a drum.
The drum is closed after igniting
the material. Part of the material will
be combusted to provide the heat
required to pyrolyze the rest. At the end,
we can appreciate the volume reduction
and the carbonized cardboard at the bottom
of the drum. Ok, so we are finished with
pyrolysis. Let's say now a couple of
words about combustion. Combustion is a
waste management method spread out
all around the world.
Incineration plants for example will
combust waste in order to reduce its
volume and obtain energy from it.
However, open burning of waste is a very
common practice, especially in low and
middle-income countries. Open burning is any
open flame exposed to the environment,
where pollutants produced from the fire
are emitted directly into the
surrounding air. Many people in
developing countries have burned
trash for generations. People often burn
because there is no other way to get rid of their trash.
In this module we learned the
three main thermochemical
processes, which are: pyrolysis,
gasification and combustion. We also had
a closer look, especially on slow
pyrolysis, but also a bit on open burning
as two common waste practices in
developing countries.
For those interested in getting more insights
about carbonization in low- and
middle-income countries, we recommend
this report, which is available for free
on the internet.