E-waste. What is e-waste? Does it ring a
bell? Did you ever hear that term?
E-waste is used to cover all electrical and
electronic equipment and its parts, that
had been discarded by its owner as waste,
without any intent of use. It is also
referred to as WEEE,
from Waste Electrical and Electronic
Equipment or electronic waste or e-scrap,
depending on the region.
Electrical and electronic equipment and
therefore also e-waste, can be classified
into the following six categories.
Temperature exchange equipment, such as
refrigerators or air conditioners,
screens and monitors, lambs, large equipment,
such as washing machines, heating systems,
electric stoves, photovoltaic panels, etc.
Small equipment such as vacuum cleaners,
microwaves, toasters, radios, etc. And small
IT and communication equipment, such as
cellphones.
Considering the numerous applications of all electronic items, it
is not hard to imagine that the
composition of e-waste is very divers. In
general, it is characterized by
containing a combination of metals, such
as steel or aluminum, plastics,
chemicals for example as batteries, glass
or other substances and materials or
even mix of materials, such as this
orange part called flexible PCB or this
green part with many little, small parts
where the green part is called FR4.
And all the little small parts
consist of copper, gold and many other
materials such as silicon, glass, etc.
Among the substances of particular interests
are a very wide range of metals,
including rare earth metals, such as
lanthanum, cerium, praseodymium.
Precious metals such as gold, silver and
platinum or other metals such as copper,
aluminum or iron, which have together
with plastics of the used covers, a high
intrinsic value. In addition, e-waste also
contains many hazardous materials, heavy
metals for example,
such as arsenic, mercury, lead, cadmium, etc.
And chemicals such as
chlorofluorocarbons used in cooling
units, polyvinyl chloride used as cable
insulator or various flame retardants,
such as polybrominated biphenyls.
This table shows the material composition of
four e-waste categories in percentage.
In fact, up to 60 elements from the periodic
table can be found in complex
electronics. In spite of many of them
being scarce and recoverable, recycling
rates are very low,
often due to the current high economic
costs. So, this of course
represents a threat to restore security
over the long term. By now, you might be
wondering how much e-waste is generated in
the world. E-waste is the fastest growing waste
fraction. According to the United Nations
University, the global quantity of e-waste
generation in 2010 was around 33.8 million tonnes.
Only four years later this value had
increased to 41.8 million tonnes,
representing approximately 2% of the total global
waste generation.
That means an increase of 25% only
in four years. So now, I would like to ask
you to match the generated amounts per
year
per e-waste type. Can you guess which of the
e-waste types amounts to 12.8 million
tons per year? Or which one amounts to
one million tonnes per year?
Let me help you a bit on this. 12.8 million
tons of small equipment are generated
per year. Whereas 1 million tonne of
lamps are generated per year. The other
e-waste types correspond to the amounts as
shown with the numbers. From the 41.8
million tonnes generated in 2014, only
6.5 million tonnes were reported as
formerly recycled. That represents 15.5%
of the total generated amount.
The collection and management of e-waste
heavily depends on the legislation of
each country. However, developing nations
often lack the legislation on this type
of waste, infrastructure needed for
handling it properly or treatment standards,
which leads to improper
practices, as we will see later.
An important legislative document that also
affects e-waste is the Basel
Convention effective since 1992. The
Basel Convention was designed to reduce
the movements of hazardous waste between
nations and specially to prevent
developed countries from illegally
dumping waste in developing countries,
where recycling infrastructure is
typically absent. Depending on the
constituents and materials of e-waste,
this can fall under the scope of the
Basel Convention and be categorized as a
type of hazardous waste. Thanks to this
convention, trading of second hand
equipment and e-waste containing
hazardous materials is legal only if it
is allowed by both, sending and receiving
countries. Plenty of information on the
Basel convention is available on the internet.
So, what happens currently with e-waste?
We distinguish these four practices: The first
practice consists of official take back
systems. In this case, e-waste is mostly
collected by municipal collection
services, retailers such as stores or
supermarkets or commercial pick-up
services. The collected waste in this
case goes to state of the art treatment
facilities which recover the valuable
materials in an environmentally sound
way and reduce the negative impacts.
Here, we see the percentages of the total
generated e-waste that is annually handled
like this in several countries. This
picture shows an operator in a
collection point for e-waste in
Switzerland, whereas in this second
picture, we see the operators of an e-waste
recycling company in Bolivia.
The second practice involves disposing of e-waste in
mixed residual waste, such as shown here in this bin
full of paper, plastics and e-waste.
Small equipment, such as lambs, USB sticks,
phones, electronic toothbrushes, etc., are
often thrown into the normal dustbins.
Often this trash is brought to a landfill
or incineration plants leading to a loss
of potential resources and negative
environmental impacts. It is estimated that
0.7 million tonnes of e-waste are
handled like this in the
European Union. The amount of e-waste
that is disposed of in waste bins is
unknown for other regions. The third
practice involves collecting e-waste
outside of official take back systems. In
developed countries e-waste is also
collected by individual waste dealers or
companies and then traded through
various channels. This waste is usually
not reported and it is often not treated
appropriately and possibly it is shipped
off to developing countries.
The export of e-waste is motivated
mainly by two reasons. Often inexpensive
second hand equipment and raw materials
are demanded in less developed regions.
However, as the cost of waste disposal
skyrocketed in developed countries,
shipping e-waste to regions with less
stringent environmental regulations is
cheaper. Many countries in Africa and
China have been common destinations for
such exports. When these trades occur
with material subject to control under
the Basel Convention, this could be
classified as waste trafficking or waste
crime, rather than legitimate trade.
Delivered missclassification of waste
types and false declarations of
waste products as reusable products are
typical fraudulent examples. This map
shows the main intercontinental exports
of e-waste.
If you happen to be living in any of
these countries and you witnessed one of
these e-waste sites next to your homes or in your
neighborhood,
why don't you share it with us? Take some
pictures and post them on the forum.
I'm sure it will be very interesting for all
your colleagues or other colleagues
following the course. Once this exported
e-waste reaches the shore it is
typically dumped indiscriminately,
spilled accidentally or managed
improperly, causing severe health
problems, even death and poisoning the
land, water and air for decades or
centuries. The fourth and last practice
involves informal collection and
recycling of e-waste in developing
countries.
A big portion of this waste that is
imported into developing countries, as
well as the small amounts of e-waste
generated within this countries is
recycled informally through backyard
recycling. Such backyard recycling
techniques include open burning to
extracting metals, acid leaching for
precious metals unprotected melting of
plastics and direct dumping of hazardous
residuals.
These practices expose workers to
dangerous working conditions that pose
great risks to their health and caused
serious environmental pollution. Lacking
legislation, treatment standards,
environmental protection measures and
recycling infrastructure are the main
reasons that e-waste is recycled in a
crude minor. Let's mention a well-known
example: The Agbogbloshie dump
in Accra Ghana is one of the 50 biggest
dumpsites in the world and perhaps the
world's largest e-waste dump. It
receives around 192000 tons of
e-waste annually.
Much of it imported and pollutes soil, air
and water and causes serious health
problems in the lives of 10,000 informal
sector workers, gaining their livelihood
from sorting and recycling. From the
resource perspective. E-waste
is a potential urban mine that could
provide a great amount of secondary
resources for remanufacture,
refurbishment and recycling. For instance
the gold content from e-waste in 2014 is
roughly 300 tons. This represents 11%
of the global gold production
from mines in 2013, which amounted to
2,770 tons. Recovery of such valuable
materials requires both, high collection
rates through formal take back systems
and high recycling efficiency.
In order to exploit the opportunities and
simultaneously mitigate pollution, good
policies are needed. These policies
should facilitate the creation of an
infrastructure, treatment standards and
should also contribute to create green
employment opportunities. In this model
we learned about e-waste, we saw the
different types and compositions of this
type of waste, as well as the current
generated amounts worldwide.
On the second half of the module, we
covered the four existing practices
regarding e-waste management. Finally, we
mentioned the opportunity that e-waste represents as
an urban mine for recovery of secondary
resource. For those interested in deepening
more on the topic, we strongly recommend
the literature shown here, from which
many insights were taken for this module.