In this module I want to share with you
some thoughts about strategic planning
in waste management, and specifically
with regard to integrating biowaste
management into the municipal system. So,
why biowaste management? Let me briefly repeat
what we have learned so far on biowaste
management. Biowaste is the largest
fraction, with over half of all municipal
waste consisting of biowaste.
When collected and disposed of in
neighborhood, biowaste may impact
negatively on the environment, while
degrading. It may generate methane, a potent
greenhouse gas. Biowaste is also an
environmental threat. Leachate from biowaste
pollutes groundwater and surface
water and biowaste may attract or even
promote disease-carrying vectors, like
flies or rodents. It is also an
underutilized resource, whereas
recyclables like glas, metal, paper
and even some fractions of plastic
already have a quite well established
recycling market, biowaste is still
struggling. However, treatment
technologies exist.
You've heard about them in the previous
modules and municipalities are slowly
but surely becoming more and more aware
of the potential to manage biowaste as a
separate fraction and make use of this
resource. But how to go about this in a
well planned and systematic way? What to
choose?
Often decisions are taken like: Oh, what
should we do? Or, what do the donors
suggests? Ok, we'll just do composting at
the landfill and that might work.
Actually and unfortunately it will
probably not work. In this module I
should try to guide you through some
planning steps, to come up with some
informed decision on what to do with biowaste.
The planning steps we shall go
through are those typical of any project
planning cycle as you see in this graph.
Something you might have come across already.
The first step is identifying
problems and needs based on an
assessment of the existing situation.
Then, developing goals, generating, weighting
objectives and elaborating on potential
actions to meet these objectives.
The next step is then preparing
scenarios that address the alternative
futures in biowaste management comparing
each scenarios impact, costs and
constraints and examining stakeholders
willingness to pay for or cooperate. Then
developing and reaching a consensus on
both selection criteria and the choice
among scenarios that best address the
objectives. And then finally, following
through with implementation, operation,
monitoring, evaluation and adaptation,
summarized in these boxes. The first step
involves a preparation and initiation
of the planning process.As well as
framing the problem. You want to make
sure to have support of key stakeholders,
typically the local authorities, but also
ensuring enough human and financial
resources to conduct the process. This
will include a professional facilitator as
well as technical experts for the
appraisal of options later. Then, the next
step is to identify the relevant
stakeholders for this participatory
process. A subsequent task is to then
frame the decision problem. This means
defining the area of concern, assessing
waste types and amounts, as the origins
of the waste and the
accessibility to the waste. What you see
in this table is an example of different
types of biowaste. In the columns you can
then see the descriptor of original
generation
the amounts, the variations over the year,
but what is also essential information, is
to know, how the waste type is currently
being managed, if at all. If a recovery
and recycling pathway is already
established, it makes little sense to
disrupt this. An example is the case of
certain types of vegetable waste, from
the markets that are already sold or
left to farmers for feeding livestock.
The next step in the cycle is defining
the goals and objectives with the
respective sub objectives. An example is
shown here in this objective tree.
This objective tree can be validated or even
adapted in a participatory process.
During this process
different objectives can also be
weighted, depending on the perceived
importance. This example shows some
predefined sub objectives grouped under
different headers which were developed
by expert consultation. There is the
issue of technical reliability, social
acceptance, the aspects of environmental
pollution, of high hygiene and health
protection, and finally the aspect of economic sustainability.
Then, the next step is to select the various
alternatives and assess their performance
with regard to the objectives we want to achieve.
Here is the list of different biowaste
treatment options as we have
heard about them in the previous modules.
We can now assess their suitability
regarding all those performance criteria
we had in the objective hierarchy.
Here are some examples. For instance the waste
type, which is in the technical objective.
Or the availability of skilled people.
Also in the technical objective.
Or the market
of the products, which is one under the
economic objective. So, let me say a few
things more about this economic
objective. Given our experience, we have
noticed that many municipalities feel
that making for instance compost will solve
all their problems and they might even
make a lot of money. Typically this is
not so without a very well-planned
distribution and marketing approach.
Maybe at the end the compost is then used
as cover material at the disposal site
and this would be fine and makes a lot
of sense.
The main point is that it is thought
through at the onset of the planning.
This aspect of economic sustainability
not only necessitates a good
understanding of the costs but also of
the expected revenues. So, the potential
value of the product being made from
biowaste,
be it gas, protein or soil amendment. In
biowaste management, it is in fact this
aspect, which is currently most difficult
to assess, as the databases for making
such estimations is quite weak. We, at Sandec,
are putting a lot of effort in
trying to quantify treatment costs for
the different options or we could also
say production costs for that specific
product that we make from biowaste.
If you have such information from your
specific context, please post it to the
forum and we will compile it and use it
for our reports and even future lessons.
When assessing the alternatives, we come
up with scores on how they perform
towards certain objectives. It is
important to discuss this performance of
alternatives to look at scores and
discuss trade-offs. Then, we might find a
consensus of the best practicable
alternative. This then needs
a detailed feasibility assessment.
Detailed, because we start defining
scale, we start defining location and
even the logistics around it.
All our experience from biowaste management
shows that is best to have a pure
biowaste stream. This ensures high-quality
product and, of course, minimizes costs of
sorting. Sometimes it is best to start
with easy waste. Waste which is not
contaminated by none-degradable
fractions, like waste from
vegetable markets or pre-consumer waste
or waste from food processing
industries or restaurants. If we want to
target household waste, it is crucial that
we first mobilize and incentivize waste
segregation at the household level. So, in
summary, strategic planning of biowaste
management includes the process of
assessing alternatives in biowaste
management, deciding on the objectives
that we want to achieve, assessing the
different waste types and the source and
validating the performance of the
alternatives versus the objectives. And
one key realization is that segregation
is really a key step for all future
biowaste management. Thank you for listening.