Hi and welcome to
this new module on comparing cities
performance in municipal solid waste
management. This topic will be presented
by Dr. Ljiljana Rodic, who is an expert in
this field.
Her most recent work includes the Global
Waste Management Outlook Report, that she
prepared with colleagues for UNEP. In
this course we have taken various
insights from this report.
Welcome Ljiljana, the floor is yours!
Thank you very much Imanol. It is a pleasure to
be here and share my experiences with
you. If we look at the cities around the
world, most have some form of solid waste
management services. In fact, some perform
very well, while others still face
numerous challenges as we have seen
throughout this course. But how do you
know, whether it all works, whether it
achieves its objectives on public health
and environmental protection,
whether it meets the needs of the city's
residence. For example, is this good or
bad? How do we know? And why do we care to
know?
So, in municipal solid waste management
practice, we make decisions how things
will be done either deliberately and
putting them down in strategic planning
documents or we make them as we go along,
as day-to-day operations require, and
then react upon these decisions. But then
it is wise to take some time to observe
or monitor how the system is actually
functioning, whether the plan works in
practice. And then we reflect on these
observations to see whether some changes
would be appropriate. If we identify some
shortcomings and possibilities for
improvements we adapt our plans or make
new ones and another cycle begins.
Well, measuring the performance of our solid
waste management system and even
comparing it with that of our peers can
be very beneficial. Some of the major
benefits are listed here. It is very
important to check our gut feeling
against the facts. It is also very
beneficial to identify the existing
strengths, which are often overlooked.
And such a measurement is very beneficial
for the learning cycle that we have seen
in the previous slide. Traditionally,
performance of urban waste management
systems is measured by means of
numerical quantitative indicators, such
as percentage of households that receive
waste collection services or percentage
of waste that is taken to recycling
facilities. However, it has been said that
"Not everything that counts, can be
counted, and not everything that can be
counted counts". Accordingly, there are
aspects of waste management that do not
lend themselves to quantification, they
simply cannot be expressed by numbers,
but they are very important for a
well-functioning system. Among various sets of
indicators that have been proposed, one
is particularly comprehensive in this sense,
as it includes both,
quantitative and qualitative indicators
to measure, describe and enable
comparison of performance of solid waste
management systems. It is the Wasteaware
indicator set. It consists of two groups
of indicators related to physical
components and governance aspects of a
solid waste management system. As you
know, physical components of the system
describe what happens with waste,
starting from waste generation,
segregation at source, collection and transfer,
sorting, transport, recycling, energy
recovery and disposal. Governance
indicators address how things are done,
considering three essential aspects:
institutions, finances and inclusivity of
important stakeholders. Physical
components are measured by four
quantitative indicators and three
qualitative indicators, whereas governance
aspects are measured by five qualitative
indicators. The Wasteaware indicator
set includes four quantitative indicators
for physical components of the system.
Two of them pertain to waste collection:
One is waste collection coverage, which
is percentage of households that receive
services and waste captured by the
system, which is percentage of the waste
generated. The third quantitative indicator
pertains to control treatment and
disposal, which is percentage of waste
destined for treatment or disposal that
goes to controlled facilities. And
finally, we have a recycling rate and
that is percentage
of waste generated. That is included in
recycling and valorization of organic
waste. Now, I will give you examples of
three of those indicators. For protection
of public health
it is essential, that collection coverage
is complete. In other words, that hundred
percent of people receive waste
collection services. This is indeed the
case in high-income countries, as well as
in many east block countries and in many
cities in People's Republic of China.
Waste collection coverage varies between
60% and 100% in the middle
income countries, as we can see here on
the examples of Buenos Aires and Delhi.
And it varies between 35 and 85% in
low-income countries. For environmental
protection, it is essential that waste
that is collected gets to the facilities
that are controlled. Here we see very
high percentages in high-income
countries and the full range of
variation from O to 100%
in middle-income countries. In low-income
countries this range is also very broad,
from 0 to 85%. As you have seen in
previous modules, resource value is
recovered from waste. Interestingly
unlike the previous two indicators
recycling rates are not really related
to the income level. Some high-income
countries score rather low in this
indicator, while lower-income countries
score high. We do have Adelaide here
with 55%, but some other cities in
Europe, for example, score 20 to 25%.
Middle-income countries recycle in some
cases
up to 50% of their waste and low-income
countries up to 30%. In addition to such
quantitative indicators, Wasteaware set
includes three qualitative indicators
for performance of physical components.
Each of these indicators consists of
five or six criteria. In here, I just give
a few examples of these criteria. For
example, criterion 1C.1 pertaining to
collection, describes appearance of waste
collection points. And you can clearly
see the difference between two collection
points, both in Bolivia. Or for example
criterion 2E.3 that describes the
quality of treatment and disposal. It is
the criterion monitoring and
verification of environmental controls.
On the left, you see an open dump with
open fires and all kinds of emissions
and no controls in this case in one of
the Balkan countries in Europe. And on
the right, you can see an engineered
landfill with all the measures of
environmental controls for leachate and
landfill gas in People's Republic of
China. As an example of a criterion under
the recycling qualitative indicator, you
can see here
occupational health and safety of the
workers who are involved in sorting and
recycling activities. In both pictures we
can see the informal sector, on the left is a
transfer station in Nepal, and on the
right it is plastic recycling in India.
For governance aspects, Wasteaware set
includes five qualitative indicators.
They're listed here. They pertain to
inclusivity of stakeholders. In this
case, service users and service providers,
Then, there is one indicator
on financial sustainability and two
indicators on institutions and policies:
one at national level on solid waste
management framework and one at local level,
which deals with local institutions. Here
are also some examples of the criteria
that comprise the main indicator. One of
the criteria under the indicator user
inclusivity. We have this criterion
which pertains to public awareness and
education. And here you can see a poster
for waste segregation at source in
Bangalore India. Under the indicator
national policy framework, we have a
criterion that pertains to existence of
appropriate implementation documents.
So, once you have strategies and legislation
also documents are needed to help
practitioners to implement indeed such
documents in practice. In here, we have an
example of such a document from Costa
Rica. Under the indicator on local
institutions, there is a criterion, a very
important one, on capacity of local
institutions which as we know from
practice is often a bottleneck in many
countries. And now, we will see some
examples of cities where Wasteaware
indicators have been applied. These
cities are spread across different
levels of income and you can look at the
numbers later. On here you will also find
references to some relevant literature.
Until now Wasteaware indicators
have been applied in around 40 cities on
six continents.
So, here we are at the end of this
presentation. First we saw the benefits
of knowing about the performance of
solid waste management systems.
We distinguished between quantitative
and qualitative indicators and we saw in
what way Wasteaware indicators address
both of this. The experience is in 40 cities
around the world. Why not try it in your
own city? Should you have any questions
or comments, do not hesitate to contact
me at the email address given here.