Hi and welcome again! In this module we
will introduce the hot topic of circular
economy and its relation to solid waste
management. Dr. Ljiljana Rodic is with us again.
She has pioneered university
education on this topic in the
Netherlands.
Ljiljana, welcome again! The floor is yours.
Thank you very much Imanol. It is a
pleasure to be here again.
Nowadays, we often hear or read in the
media about circular economy. In this
lecture I will introduce this term,
explain briefly different meanings in
which it is used and discuss potential
place of solid waste management in
circular economy. How did you hear the
term circular economy? You may have heard
about the circular economy promotion law,
the milestone legislation of the
People's Republic of China adopted in
2008 to promote the circular economy as
a national strategy for sustainable
development. Or you may have come across
reports towards a circular economy
prepared for the Ellen MacArthur
Foundation. But what is it all about?
Since the industrial revolution our
economies have grown following a linear
pattern of use of natural resources
consisting basically of take, make, use,
discard steps. This was based on a
false premise that the resources are
infinitely available and accessible at
an affordable cost, both in terms of
money and in terms of environmental
impacts. However, such a pattern simply
cannot be sustained by the earth system. On the
one hand the sources of materials are
finite and on the other hand, there are
limits to the ability of Earth's
ecosystems to recover from habitat
degradation and pollution by various
hazardous and other chemicals. But if you
look at nature and natural ecosystems,
how they use natural resources around them,
we see that nature functions
in a circular pattern. Starting from
plants as producers, including several
levels of consumers and when they die
decomposers get to work to convert them
into soil nutrients, which in turn serve
as food for the producers again.
Circular economy envisages a similar
system, where after make and use stages,
materials are recovered and processed into
a new cycle of production and use.
For materials to be recovered and returned
to the next cycle of production, they
need to be clearly defined in circular
economy. Materials can be defined either
as biological materials or technical
materials. Biological materials are used
to make the so-called consumption
products, which get consumed during use,
such as a soap or shampoo or wear off
during use, such as clothes or shoes.
These are designed to be safe for human
health and the environment and as such
they can safely return to the natural
biological cycle. Here, we have an example
of biological material: food. Technical
materials are used to make service
products, such as computer, telephone,
washing machine, a car. As they are
non-renewable and often hazardous to
human health and the environment,
these are kept within the industrial
technical cycle, where they will be used
to make new products,
time and again. At that some materials lend
themselves perfectly for cascading use.
This is usually the case with biological
materials, wood and textiles are very
good examples. Biological materials can
be used in defined cascades where the
quality deteriorates from one
application to the next, but both, along
the way and at the end, the material can
be fully returned to the biological
cycle with no harm to human health or
the environment. In the end, they can be
processed,
by for example, aerobic composting or
anaerobic digestion to recover resources
such as organic matter nutrients and
energy. Of course, products user stages can
be extended through reuse and repair.
Also, after this assembly parts can be
used for refurbishment and manufacture
of the products. Here, you see an example
of complete disassembly into the part
and their corresponding materials.
As you know, recycling is usually downcycling,
whereby materials loose their quality in
each cycle. However, it is possible for
recycling to actually be upcycling,
whereby quality improves in each cycle.
Here, we have an example of a packaging
that is made out of 100% PET
bottles, and from the PET material
during recycling antimony is removed,
which was there originally.
So, this material is now better quality than it
used to be.
It often makes sense to explore
possibilities of closing material cycles
together with energy and water cycles.
For example, closing metal cycles saves a
lot of energy, if we close water cycles. It
allows recovery of nutrients.
Also, for renewable energy it is important to
consider materials used for such
technologies, as they often contain rare
and hazardous materials. For a fully
circular economy a lot of innovation
will be needed in various disciplines in
various fields. For example, in material
sciences, well-defined materials are
particularly important. Also, for the
design, end of use stage need to be taken
into consideration: How easy the product
is to be repaired, to be refurbished, to
be disassembled, to be remanufactured.
Also of particular importance are the new
business models, where a lot of
innovation is needed, so that services
are sold and not necessarily the
products. This also includes our
relationship to ownership. Do we actually
need to possess and own a product or are we
perfectly happy with the service it
provides us? This also means that new
relationships or new types of
relationships are needed along the
supply chain, where trust among partners
has a prominent role, because it is about
sharing proprietary information about
materials and parts. This also means that
citizens have a new role and that is
that they have to make sure that these
materials indeed do return into the next
production cycle. And government has also a
role because it can provide supportive
policies, legislation and incentives to
enable support such developments in
society. You may have seen in literature
that the role of the design is very
important for circular economy. It is
indeed, because it is the design stage
when all the decisions are made about
the material, about assembly methods,
about the usage. However, solid waste
management has an equally important role in
circular economy, because it makes the
other half of the cycle complete. It makes
sure that the materials after usage
will indeed return to the next
production cycles. Circular economy is
currently in the focus of political and
public debate and its importance is only
going to increase. While it begins with
the design of products,
everybody has a role to play and
everybody can contribute. Not the least,
us citizens, as consumers to choose
buy and discard the products.However,
solid waste management has a very
prominent role as it makes sure that the
materials actually return into the
next production cycle. Should you have
any questions or comments, do not
hesitate to contact me at the email
address given here.