Hello everyone, today we'll talk
about the slingshot maneuver
or gravity assist maneuver.
The problem is the following.
If you want to go far away
in the solar system,
in the outer regions of the solar system
with a spacecraft or with a robot,
you know you have
a certain ΔV capability
from your spacecraft
which depends
on the mass of the spacecraft,
the mass of the propellant
and the efficiency
of the propulsion system.
But to go far away,
you need a relatively large V_d,
the departure velocity from
the parking orbit around the Earth,
respectively a large V_d ∞,
the hyperbolic excess velocity
at the boundary of the sphere
of influence of the Earth.
But sometimes, you just
don't have that capability.
So you need to use another trick
in order to gain energy
in the medium, low or medium regions
of the solar system
so you can get to the outer region.
The idea is the following.
You come with a certain
heliocentric velocity
into the vicinity of a planet
and you swing around that planet,
the gravity assist planet
or slingshot planet.
Then, when you exit the sphere
of influence of that planet,
you are going to get an increased value
of your heliocentric velocity,
a different direction also which will
give you enough energy
to go further away in the solar system.
Sometimes we can even do
several gravity assist maneuvers.
That was the case
for the Rosetta spacecraft,
the Cassini spacecraft.
Here we have an example of New Horizons
that flew past Pluto recently.
It was in July 2015 and it used
one gravity assist from Jupiter.
Jupiter is a very massive planet
and it gave New Horizons enough energy,
respectively enough velocity, to gain
the outer region of the solar system.
Well, let's look
at the gravity assist process,
or the slingshot, and the illustration
on the left-hand side.
We are leaving the Earth here with
a heliocentric velocity V_1.
By the way, all the velocities
we have here
are heliocentric velocities
so they are capital V's.
V_E is the velocity of the Earth,
the circular velocity of the Earth
on orbit around the Sun.
Then we are on this trajectory
towards the gravity assist planet.
And we penetrate inside
the sphere of influence
of the gravity assist planet
with velocity V_2.
The target is really to get there.
The green dot on the left-hand side
is the target planet
in the outer solar system
and the idea is the following.
We get with a capital V_2
inside the sphere of influence
of the gravity assist planet.
And then we come out
of that sphere of influence,
which of course here is not to scale,
but that's for the clarification
of the drawing.
We have a velocity V_5,
which, as we see here,
is larger in amplitude on the one hand
and in a different direction than V_2,
the penetration velocity heliocentric
into the sphere of influence
of the gravity assist planet.
So we have obviously gained energy,
and the idea is to target
the geometry of the encounter,
respectively the flyby of the red planet,
in order to get to the targets.
Now sometimes we have
only one gravity assist
to go out into the solar system,
sometimes we have several;
we'll see examples later.
Well, let's look now
at the slingshot maneuver profile,
especially what happens
inside the sphere of influence
of the gravity assist planet.
We saw before that we are at this point,
penetrating the sphere of influence
of the gravity assist planet
with a velocity V_2
that's heliocentric.
In order to get the value
of the planetocentric velocity
of penetration inside
the sphere of influence of the planet,
we have to subtract V_p
and then we get the v_3
and this is the v_a ∞
into the sphere of influence
of the gravity assist planet.
Then, as we know, it's exactly like
the arrival at a planet that we looked at
for travel into the solar system
from the Earth to any planet
In the solar system.
Then we know that we have
a hyperbolic trajectory
inside the sphere of influence
of the planet.
And this is the trajectory,
we come at the closest point
to the gravity assist planet here,
and, of course, the distance
to the gravity assist planet
will depend on the vector value of v_3
or the arrival infinity,
but also on the impact parameter,
we'll come back to that later.
Then we come on the outer branch
of the hyperbola and at this point
we are leaving the sphere of influence
of the gravity assist planet.
and the v_4 is really
the v_d ∞ departure infinity,
the velocity at which we leave
the sphere of influence of the planet,
and that's the planetocentric velocity.
We need to add V_p,
the heliocentric velocity of the planet
to find V_5, which is
the heliocentric velocity
of the probe upon leaving
the sphere of influence
of the gravity assist planet.
And, as we can see here,
this is highlighted here,
the V_5, vector V_5, is quite a bit larger
and somewhat different direction than V_2.
That's the advantage that we get
through this process.
Let's look at the geometry
of the slingshot maneuver
around that planet,
which looks like it's the planet Mars,
and we are especially interested
in the determination
of the β angle or δ angle.
So the deviation angle
from the initial direction,
which here is v_a ∞,
pretty much a vertical,
and this is the v departure
from the sphere of influence
with a change in direction.
Again, these are all small v's
so they are planetocentric velocities
with respect to the gravity assist planet.
Now the situation is very similar
to the one we encountered
when we looked at arrival to a planet
for interplanetary trajectories,
with a hyperbolic trajectory inside
the sphere of influence of the planet.
Let's write down a few parameters here.
This here is equal to r_p.
The distance to the center of the
gravity assist planet at the periastris.
And this distance here is equal to a.
Now you remember that we have here
the d ∞, the impact parameter.
We have this triangle here.
And by the way,
we also have the value of a, here.
These are all the properties
of the hyperbola.
So we have this triangle here
that we can solve
in order to find the value of r_p
and then find the value of δ or β,
the deviation angle.
So you remember that we had
the following situation.
We have a equals µ
divided by v_a ∞  square
This is a consequence
of their conservation of energy,
considering that the sphere of influence
is far away from the planet in question,
and it's nearly infinity
so we had to factor 1 / r
in the vis-viva equation
that we equaled to zero.
Now what we know is v_a ∞,
this is the velocity of arrival
in the sphere of influence.
We know this and we choose d ∞,
the impact parameter here.
Now you remember, we saw this previously,
r_p + a equals the square root
of μ squared
divided by (v_a ∞)^4
plus d ∞ squared.
It's just a resolution of this triangle
that we have here.
Now we can determine
the value of r_p is equal to...
I won't write down the whole expression
but we can determine it.
And then we have the cosine of β
is equal to the cosine of half of δ.
It's equal to a divided by a + r_p.
And, of course, we know
the a on the basis of this
as we know v_a ∞,
and the r_p we know from this,
knowing v_a ∞ on one hand
and d ∞ also.
So we have a way to determine
the deviation angle δ on this slingshot.
And this is a major parameter.
We know that the distance
of this point to the planet
or this point to the planet is the same
because that's a symmetric process
on the hyperbolic arc,
and we can so determine
the value of the deviation angle
as well as the r_p, the closest distance
to the deviation planet.
Well, this is quite an interesting example
of several slingshots
that were necessary to bring
the Cassini-Huygens spacecraft
all the way to Saturn, where it still is
and recording very interesting data
on the planet itself
and the system of rings
and the 62+ satellites of Saturn.
We had a launch here in October 1997
and we had a total of four flybys.
We had first a Venus flyby here.
We had a second Venus flyby here,
coming with the red trajectory.
Then we had an Earth flyby at this point
and finally a Jupiter flyby here.
And each of these flybys gave extra energy
to the trajectory of the spacecraft,
allowing it to go to the target
far away in the solar system,
Saturn at this point.
The Rosetta mission,
which is an ESA mission
that has an objective to rendezvous
with comet Churyumov–Gerasimenko,
very far away in the solar system,
and then follow the comet
as it was getting closer to the Sun,
developing a tail,
going through the perihelion of that comet
and then follow it for a while
after passing the perihelion.
The mission departed from Kourou,
French Guiana, with Ariane 5 in 2004,
and the journey
was going to take 10 years.
The rendezvous with the comet
was going to be in 2014, which happened,
but the initial energy of the spacecraft
was by far not enough
to reach that faraway region
of the solar system,
and it was necessary to perform 4 flybys
of Rosetta with different planets,
and we'll see the 4th or last flyby
which is a flyby of the Earth.
And at the conclusion of this flyby,
the energy of Rosetta was enough
to reach the target several years later,
in fact it was 5 years later.
Here we see in green
the trajectory of the Rosetta spacecraft,
and the controllers had planned
a flyby to the Earth, which we see here.
And now we see a view from Rosetta itself
as we are coming
into close proximity to the Earth
to deflect the velocity vector in order
to reach the goal in terms of energy
and go far away in the solar system.
A pretty spectacular path
close to the Earth,
and now we are on the new trajectory
which is again heliocentric, elliptical
but with a much larger value of a,
the semi-major axis
and the proper geometry to
rendezvous with the comet 5 years later.