Today, we're going to talk
about governance,
new forms of governance,
due to the rapid development of poverty
which is a statement to
observation planning failure
as, despite every attempt
we've had at planning,
we find ourselves in a situation
where poverty continues to increase
and therefore, inequalities also
continue to increase.
As a result of this failure,
we asked ourselves
what type of governance
should be implemented
in order for infrastructures,
for amenities,
for everything that
we plan for specifically,
physically, down to the ground,
can be effective one day or another.
We'd like to remind that
planning is only useful
if it is effective, efficient,
if it serves the majority.
If you plan a road
which will never be built,
it is useless to plan it.
So, we began to imagine
new government systems,
new decision-making processes,
which we regroup under
the governance umbrella.
Today, this governance,
this government,
is no longer centralized
but requires a multi-party approach.
We no longer just have
the State level of government,
we now have a larger number of parties
which can be at once public and private,
and together, these parties,
will more or less,
make decisions about the future
and the development of cities.
This is why we are no longer
talking about a government
but a governance system instead.
We are, therefore, going towards
good governance
as there would be a basic scheme.
I say, "there would be",
we have not yet fully tested everything
in order to say, "this is how it works",
but we have a good governance,
an idea of the parties' involvement
needed in order to ensure
that decision-making on urban territory
is carried out properly.
To ensure this, multiple parties
and, mainly, less visible borders
are needed between both
public and private parties.
Which is public, which is private?
Until today there was a clear
delimitation between the two.
Which is formal and which informal?
Things are less obvious here as well,
less clear-cut than they used to be
and the State versus the civil society,
a centralized approach versus
a decentralized approach.
So, today's governance involves
our questioning regarding borders
between these different elements,
public/private, formal/informal,
the State/civil society.
The paradox of globalization
we already mentioned it.
What is it?
It is that on the one hand we'll try
to have a good governance,
a decentralization of powers
and on the other hand,
we realize that in cities,
in today's winning global cities,
there is a re-centralization of power.
Therefore we are in
a paradoxical pendulum
where, on the one hand we adopt
a decentralization approach
and on the other hand
on the contrary, on the world stage,
when one studies global cities,
there should be a tightening
of powers around a small number.
The other paradox is, if you go down
governmental levels,
decentralization, from the State
to the municipality, we find ourselves
in basic administrative units
which are municipalities
which most of the time,
don't correspond to anything.
Why don't they correspond to anything?
Because in the case of agglomerations
we find ourselves
in several municipalities
and it is exceedingly rare
to come across a complete overlap
between functional space
and political space.
The government rules over a space
and it's not necessarily the logical one
for the functions found in that city.
In this case there is no overlap.
There is also the development
of large entities such as
the European Union.
Therefore, on the one hand
we will decentralize municipalities
and on the other hand we have
much more important developments
where large entities are being created.
It is a true paradox, as we have
opposing political movements.
And so decision-making
somehow becomes extremely blurry.
We don't know if we should
continue decentralizing
or, on the contrary, re-centralize
and fight on the world stage.
We have already said,
regarding environmental issues,
the municipality, the local community
is probably not conducive
to making major decisions.
Consequently, there are
a certain number of decisions
which must be made between the State
or between larger entities,
larger than the state, no doubt,
and others can be decentralized
at the municipal level.
Today, this new style of governance
implies, first of all, a decentralization,
which we have already begun to talk about.
Decentralization, in other words
the State will transfer some of its power
to local communities.
Having multiple parties,
is the second element
to these new forms of governance,
we've already talked about it.
Decentralization, multiple parties
which include private ones
but also what's globally referred to
as civil society.
Once we take into account
these new parties
and decentralization,
there are types of partnerships
which can be created.
Two of the main parties,
as well as the State of course,
are, on the one hand,
community organizations,
and on the other hand, the private,
through public/private partnerships.
We have already mentioned
these partnerships
so, in the next video
we'll talk mostly about
community organizations.
Who are they and what can they do
regarding urban decision-making?
Are they parties that we can apply?
You know the answer, it's yes,
it is a new party,
which we are increasingly considering
but we will see that there are also
a number of limitations
to this new multi-party approach.
Involving these new parties, however,
shouldn't be a way for the State
to dissociate from
a number of rights they had.