When we are talking about governance,
we need to talk about decentralization.
We have seen it previously,
new forms of urban governance
presuppose decentralization
and the challenge of new players.
Decentralization.
That's what we are going to look at now.
The few different stages
and limits of the financial capacity.
The three stages according to Gauthier
and Vaillancourt, revisited by Paulet.
We have decongestion.
These are officers that perform
functions in the local communities
but which are attached
to the central government.
Delegation.
So this is a transfer of responsibilities,
often in a particular field to entities
that can be autonomous,
but which must report
to a higher authority.
So we are still not
at the local community level.
And then we have devolution
which is a transfer of skills
to local governments and these governments
have autonomy in the decision process.
So it really is the last stage,
the only one which corresponds
exactly to what we call decentralization.
So decentralization can be,
at the same time, political,
and this fits very clearly
in the notion of devolution,
but decentralization should,
obviously, also be economic,
financial, and not only political.
And it's there, as we'll soon see,
that there is a problem,
since often political decentralization
has taken place,
but in fact, financial decentralization
has never taken place.
The current state
of decentralization in Africa.
You can find very old texts
that are actually 15, even 20-years-old
on the subject of decentralization.
Keep in mind that all the processes
are not taking place
in the same way
in all of the African States.
It's the first thing that must be mentioned.
Secondly, it's that decentralization
has never really functioned very well.
There are few states which have
clearly implemented decentralization,
since financial decentralization
has never taken place or in rare cases.
And it's in seeing the state of finances
of local communities
that we realize that decentralization
has not worked.
So there is always
an extremely weak point,
the weak financial autonomy
of local communities.
And we can say whatever we want.
We can say that the texts are there,
it is undoubtedly the application decrees
that pose problems.
Most of the time, the law is enacted,
but its enforcement decrees are not.
So to summarize all of this,
it's by the financial autonomy
of local communities
that we will be able
to really establish decentralization.
Decentralization can also
have undesirable effects.
Finally, there has been an increase in
the number of municipalities in the area.
So decentralization also means
creation of new entities that want to be
autonomous in an area.
So that is an undesirable effect.
It's that the more you decentralize,
the more you will see areas
which want this degree of autonomy.
So we haven't won anything yet
since we are only fragmenting
the areas further.
And it is well known that especially for
management of large cities, it's really
not fragmentation that is needed
but a joining of these various powers
that would in this way
allow a higher authority
to manage the entire city.
What are the skills?
One could of course give
management of large networks,
management of urban services,
completely to the local communities,
but its weak financial capacity
prevents all transactions of this type.
So it will remain at the regulations level
or at the State level,
since the local communities,
except in some rare cases,
very rare cases compared to
all of the cities, agreed,
but the communities do not have the means
to assume these types of tasks
due to a lack of resources.
This won't be comprehensive
however the skills
would be, for example,
the maintenance of the public domain,
lighting, waste management,
basic education,
health, everything that concerns
environmental issues,
so we see that we're mostly dealing with
social as well as environmental issues.
Agreed?
So that's what we have.
So when we talk about education,
it is of course basic education,
since in theory, universities are not
considered in this diagram.
In fact, the universities are managed,
in theory, in every country,
at the State level.
But basic education, elementary school,
high school, are the jurisdiction
of local communities.
We of course have here items
that have a cost
which have few possibilities
of recovering costs, and on top of that
we have the extremely limited resources
of the local communities.
Financial capacity.
We have both what comes from
the community's own capacities
but also from the transfer of State money,
in the form of grants
or in the form of taxes,
on the value added, for example,
where a portion of it should,
in theory come back directly
to the local communities.
But we realize that in practice,
that this transfer of funds
from the higher authority
to the local community is very weak
compared to the needs,
and the State keeps a large portion
of these resources.
There you have it, we have quickly looked
at the issue of decentralization,
by explaining what it is,
showing its limits
precisely because it is not
completely effective,
for reasons such as the fiscal year
and to also show
that with the growing complexity
of relations between areas,
the birth of large cities
which require precisely
a more centralized management
at the community level, certainly,
but a re-centralization of power
to be able to manage these cities,
we realize that we are on
relatively shaky ground.
And in my opinion, it's of no help at all
to be too dogmatic,
because according to the times,
depending on the methods,
we see that the pendulum
swings back and forth.
We must simply understand at which stage
we are in urban history.
In my opinion, we must take care
when trying to apply
these ready-made solutions.
Decentralization can work
in a number of cases.
It also has its limits, and we must find
forms of governance
that are sustainable over time.