Today we'll discuss community-based
organizations and their roles.
Over the past decades we've seen in Africa
the emergence of a new party
in the form of
community-based organizations.
Regrouping populations,
often their poorest members,
who get together to work among
such organizations in order to both,
participate in managing their future,
and to assist the State
or local authorities
with decision-making.
That's the basic plan.
We'll take a look at some of the processes
which involve these
community-based organizations.
One often associates community-based
organizations with civil society.
Civil society is much broader than
our definition of it here.
In Africa It practically doesn't exist
or, on the contrary, it is very active.
Let's put aside for a moment this
question of civil society,
to instead concentrate on
community-based organizations
who form the battalion of the poorest
in African cities.
When we say community-based organization
we mean participation,
we mean participatory decision-making.
There are many forms of participation,
And of course we have, as always,
between a weak and a strong participation
a cursor, which can move,
depending on the country,
depending on the city,
but also depending on the project.
Projects for which there is
very strong demand
and a very strong participation of
community-based organizations.
Why? Because these are decisions
which directly affect the community,
and perhaps because when it comes to
our ability to make decisions,
it is very weak, if not nonexistent,
at higher levels.
There are, then, different
types of participation.
We'll highlight the five main ones.
To begin with, appropriation.
Communities have decision-making power,
and it's the State
who takes the initiative
when the community demands it.
There is cooperation.
It is the State and the communities
who work together with one sole objective.
Often the processes are assisted
by others, especially by NGOs,
but there is a sort of coproduction
on the decision and on the project.
There is consultation.
Thus the communities
won't make the decisions,
but will be consulted on projects
to seek their input,
and then the project
will be modified in a timely manner
based on the results of this consultation.
There is the information level,
which is a summarized
version of the consultation.
Usually the communities
are informed of what will happen.
And subsequently there is manipulation,
where, ultimately,
the communities are used
instead for the wrong reasons.
They are given the impression
that they have a say,
yet the decisions had already been
taken well in advance.
We see that nevertheless
there is a split,
we have manipulation for
all the wrong reasons.
Here we have the four top ones,
for the right reasons,
with, once again, the cursor which
points strongly towards appropriation,
as the communities demand,
and the State acts,
and the lowest level of participation,
which is consultation.
Between the two there is room to move,
and we have varying levels
of participation.
What was just said
is for the participation
of all development projects as a whole.
We can go further in participation,
up to participatory budgeting,
which can be divided into four phases.
The first phase, preparatory,
we'll mobilize citizens.
Second phase, the identification of
problems and needs,
where we define priorities.
A subsequent phase of execution
and provision of services as identified,
and a supervision phase of what has
been done and the audit.
So first, we'll prepare,
then identify and allocate budgets,
do the work, supervise what
has been completed,
to then return to the start,
a chain which allows us
to revisit and modify
based on what has been found
during the supervision of
what was requested.
There is truly a daily control over
the allocation of the different budgets.
This is, I would venture,
an absolute form,
which may possibly be
at the local community level,
but which involves, in any event,
community-based organizations.
These are ordinary people
who have in their hands
this question of participatory budgeting.
There are communities who are given
only a portion of
the participatory budgeting,
but the interest lies in the fact
that they feel a responsibility,
an accountability on the part of
the inhabitants for the budgets.
Together they decide how much
will be allocated, and where,
and then together they control
these allocations.
So this is the participatory budget,
with or without community-based
organizations.
That's all we'll say for now
on participatory budgeting,
because the lecture was only on
community-based organizations.
After we'll return to it, but for now
what are the development projects,
which might be handled at the level
of community-based organizations,
with the State.
We also have the very important
question of housing.
There are large housing programs,
or perhaps housing benefits,
which can be implemented with,
at the same time,
community-based organizations
and the State.
Infrastructure, of course.
Often it is the basic infrastructure
in neighborhoods,
certainly not about building
a large roadway together.
But all that is infrastructure and basic
facilities within the neighborhoods
enters into the transactions which
the communities have with the State.
Urban dynamism.
We can, within these given areas,
reinvigorate, spark urban renewal,
where a certain number of social programs
enable us to live together in harmony.
Thus with the possibility we have to work
on-site on these social programs,
community-based organizations are,
I'd say, the strongest link to them.
And finally, the question
of waste management.
Community-based organizations
can play a very important role here,
because it involves being
actually on the ground.
We quickly realize that what the State
lacks is this anchor to the ground,
and being able to manage it
with local communities.
This allows access to a central authority,
or even to a decentralized power.
It allows access on the ground
with those who face difficult
situations on a daily basis.
In return, of course,
the State must play a role.
It can not simply be demanding
of the community-based organizations,
but should primarily recognize them,
which is no small task,
for within the normal plan of governing,
this civil society, these organizations,
do not exist.
So we're dealing with different stages
or strata of the State,
but the first thing to do
is to recognize these organizations.
Next to offer technical assistance for
the development of their projects,
assist them with the financing
of these projects.
The State finds within these
community-based organizations
a neighborhood base.
But for this to happen the State
must also invest in it,
the two levels of decision-making
must be addressed.
And the State must recognize
their right to have a say,
which is without doubt one of
the most difficult tasks,
because it requires that
a place be made for this
within the plan, within the organization,
within the actual governing of the city.
So limits and conclusions.
Limits, there are two.
It is that participatory decision-making,
as we've already seen
in a certain number of cases,
does not work.
It works as long as it involves
decision-making on facilities, on layout,
within the neighborhoods.
It works a bit less successfully,
or not at all, when it involves
city planning on a macro level.
When we want to install
large networks, roadways,
it becomes difficult to include
the participation of
all the city's inhabitants.
The main result of this participation,
of these participatory processes,
is that in the end, the decision is
that nothing will get done.
So if we want the city
to evolve at some point,
we must also make decisions
on a centralized level.
And rather than having to apply
one plan or another,
we must realize that,
depending on the projects,
depending on the challenges
of these projects,
we must make them
to some degree participatory.
It is perhaps cynical to say
these sorts of things,
but we must recognize
the limits of the system,
and realize that we cannot ask
the whole of a city's population
for their advice on this or that project.
So there we are perhaps at the level
of informing rather than participating.
We must inform and show clearly
what we are in the process of doing;
this is undeniable.
This is, I'd say, the foundation,
but there are certainly times when
one can go even further
in the participatory process,
and others when it must be
placed on the back burner.
The end result is that, now that
we've seen these important trends,
these new methods
of urban governance,
these community-based organizations,
decentralization,
we must know how to utilize them.
There is no out-of-the-box solution,
there is no plan that should be applied
to all African countries.
We must simply recognize the validity
of community-based organizations,
recognize them, and in collaboration
with them see in which measures
they might or might not
take part in the decision-making.