OK, welcome back!
This is segment 5.2 on Capturing Value.
Now, what we've done so far in this module
is we've talked a lot
about intellectual property protection.
And here we're going to take it
one step further
and talk about how companies
can make money from their inventions.
Let's start with some definitions.
First, what is innovation?
Innovation is the use of new knowledge
to provide new products,
services, or processes.
And it involves invention,
commercialization, and appropriation.
Let's talk about those.
If you look at this graphic:
invention is usually thought of as being
the research and development,
the first initial ideas
for a new product, process, or service.
Commercialization is product development
and bringing the product to market.
And, finally, appropriation,
or appropriability,
is about getting money and capturing value
from the invention in the marketplace.
We're going to focus a lot
on appropriation in this segment.
Appropriation, or appropriability
is intimately bound up
with the idea of imitability.
Imitability is the ability of someone else
to copy the invention of the entrepreneur.
And it's related to appropriability
in the following way:
when it's easy to copy something,
therefore imitability is high;
it's much more difficult for the inventor
to make money in general
to capture value.
And when it is difficult to copy
that means imitability is low.
Then it is easier for the entrepreneur
to capture value
from his or her invention.
Most people think
that imitability is driven primarily
by intellectual property protection.
And that may be true.
However, there are many cases
where intellectual property protection
is not the key driver of imitability.
For example, it could be difficult
to copy an invention
even if there's little or no IP protection
on that product or service.
That can be done
through many different ways
including complexity; where is not obvious
how the product is actually put together
or what's happening behind the product.
It could be tacit knowledge,
where the entrepreneur
has specific knowledge
that is difficult to codify and transmit
and can only be learned on the job.
That could be also difficult to copy.
And, finally, if there's a lot
of process innovations
behind the production
of the product or service.
Process innovations are usually
very, very difficult to observe
and, therefore, difficult
to copy the end product.
OK, let's talk about
complementary assets.
The first thing we want to know is:
what is a complementary asset?
A complementary asset is everything
that's required
to commercialize an invention
aside from the technology itself.
So what are examples
of complementary assets?
You could imagine your sales
and distribution,
your manufacturing of a product,
the marketing of a product,
and everything else that you can do
to bring your product to market
aside from developing
a project or a technology itself.
Imagine that you are part
of a supply chain.
You may order raw materials
from some partner.
You may do some operations
on that to produce a product.
You need someone to go off
and sell the product.
And then you may need to distribute
the product to the people who bought it.
All of those points,
aside from the product itself,
you might need access
to some complementary asset.
Now, the question is:
is the the same as a complementary good?
And the answer is: no, this is not
the same as a complementary good.
A complementary good is like a shoe
and shoe lace, you know.
When the price of shoes goes up,
the demand for shoe laces drops.
The two products
are used simultaneously with each other
and they're complements to each other.
So that's a complementary good.
What we're talking about here
is a complementary asset,
which is access
to some source that you need
to commercialize your invention.
The question often arises:
when do I need to think
about complementary assets?
And the way
that we usually think about this
is to treat each complementary asset
one at a time and to examine it and say,
"Is it relevant to me?"
"Do I need to care about this
particular one?"
And to do that, we're going to develop
a little framework
to think about whether you should care
about each complementary asset.
I'm proposing that the way to think about
whether a complementary asset
is relevant to you is to think about it
along two different dimensions.
The first is: is the asset
important or not?
The second one is: if it's important,
who controls the asset?
Is it in competitive supply,
in other words freely available?
Or is it tightly held
by only one or two parties?
So if you look at this graphic,
what you see are four quadrants
that are based on the combinations
of these things.
So the lower-right corner, for example,
is you have an important
complementary asset,
but the complementary asset itself
is freely available.
Let's say you've developed a basic watch.
It's nothing fancy and it builds
on standardized components
that you'd find in other watches.
Now, you may ask yourself
whether you should care
about the manufacturing of that watch.
Is manufacturing an important
complementary asset?
And I think the answer here is yes.
You need access to manufacturers
to be able to commercialize your watch.
However, I would also propose
that it is freely available.
There are many manufacturers out there
who would love to have your business.
And I think with a few phone calls
you could already have several offers
on the table within a few hours.
So, therefore, we see that this is going
to be in the lower right quadrant
where the complementary asset is important
however it is in competitive supply,
or freely available.
Now, imagine instead of a basic watch
that you had invented a software program.
You may ask yourself whether manufacturing
is a key complementary asset
for your software product.
And here I think most people would say
that a manufacturing facility
is probably not too important
for a software program.
So we see ourselves here
in the lower-left corner
which is the complementary asset itself
is unimportant even if it is
freely available in the market.
Now let's consider a different case
where you have developed
a software app for a phone.
And now you're wondering
whether you should care
about the App Store,
which is the distribution network
for your app.
I think here we could agree
the App Store, or a similar store like it
like the Google Play store,
would be critically important
for the distribution of your app.
And, therefore,
to commercialize your product,
you're going to need access
to that App Store.
But, unfortunately for you, the App Store
is held and controlled by one company.
And if you're thinking about other phones,
in general, the distribution
to these phones is held
by a very small number of companies.
So there we find ourselves
in the upper-right quadrant
which is where the complementary asset
is important and it's tightly held.
And that means the owner of the App Store,
in this particular case Apple,
would be controlling a lot
of the negotiation
and controlling the terms of the deal
of your revenue-sharing agreement.
Furthermore, the controller
of the complementary asset can decide
whether or not to even accept you
into the App Store or not.
Now, finally, let's say you've come up
with, instead of an app for a phone,
you've come up with a fancy new case
for a phone, something like this.
Now, this particular case
could be made of a new material
or have some other properties
that are desirable.
So there let's consider
the case for the phone,
and let's consider the App Store
as a distribution channel.
Now, in this particular case, I think
most people would agree
that the App Store is not really
that important as a distribution channel.
Even if it's tightly held by Apple,
it doesn't really affect
the distribution of phone cases.
That would be a completely different
distribution channel.
And so the App Store here is unimportant
to you as the entrepreneur.
So, as you can see, there are
only two categories of outcomes here.
And only one of which
the entrepreneur really cares about.
I've broken that into two colors here:
the red zone and the green zone.
The red zone is the case
where the complementary asset
is both tightly held and important
to the entrepreneur.
And the other three cases,
we put that in the green zone
because that's not very much
of an issue for the entrepreneur.
Either the complementary asset
is unimportant, in which case we're done,
or it's freely available,
in which case it's in competitive supply
and we can negotiate
with lots of suppliers
to give us a good offer.
So we're tending to capture value
from our invention.
Moving along to the next graphic,
what I've done is I've taken the red zone
and put that on the right-hand side.
That's the zone
where the complementary asset
is both important and tightly held.
And on the left-hand side
of this table is the green zone.
The green zone is where it's either
unimportant or it's freely available.
Those are equivalent in the eyes
of the entrepreneur.
And then, on the left-hand side,
what we have is we go back
to the imitability table,
and we can differentiate
between things that are difficult to copy,
that's low imitability,
or things that are very easy
to copy, that's high imitability.
And now what we're going
to look at here is
who captures the value from the invention
in each of these quadrants?
And it's not the same.
Let's look at the upper-left quadrant.
The upper-left quadrant, here, is the case
where the complementary assets
are unimportant or freely available,
and imitibility is low.
So here's the case where the entrepreneur
has a product or service
that's difficult to copy,
and all the complementary assets
are either freely available
or they're unimportant.
In this particular case,
the entrepreneur or the inventor is going
to capture value from the invention.
The opposite case is
the lower-right quadrant.
That's the case
where the complementary asset
is important and tightly held
and, unfortunately for the entrepreneur,
it's easy to copy the product or service.
Now there, as you can see,
the complementary asset holder
is going to be in a very strong
negotiating position.
Why?
Because the complementary asset holder
can simply copy the invention
and commercialize it itself.
Let's look at the lower-left corner.
That's the case where it is easy
to copy the invention
and at the same time,
either the complementary assets are
unimportant or they're freely available.
In this particular case, what
you'd expect to see is lots of entry.
People will copy the invention as soon
as they see it, they'll commercialize it,
and there will be many products
in the market that are highly similar.
In this particular case, you'd expect
to have a price war which means
that none of the companies here
are going to benefit or capture value.
And, instead, it will be the customers,
or the end-users, that will benefit
by having a much lower price
in the market.
And then, finally, let's look
at the upper-right quadrant.
In the upper-right quadrant you have
a tightly held, important
complementary asset,
and you've also got a product
from the entrepreneur
that is difficult to copy.
This puts us into a negotiating,
bargaining game situation
where both parties have some power
and no one can dictate the terms.
And in this particular case
you might ask yourself,
"Well, which party is really going
to capture the most value?"
And it's difficult to state here,
but empirically speaking, most of the time
it's also the complementary asset holder
and not the entrepreneur
that captures the value,
usually because the entrepreneur
is smaller
and wants access
to the network or to the asset
that the complementary asset holder has
and, therefore, has slightly less
bargaining power
even if the complementary asset holder
can't copy the entrepreneur's product.
So what we just said
I've summarized here in this graphic.
And what you might want to know is:
If I can't capture value, am I doomed?
Do I have a bad idea?
And there are several different answers
to this question.
The first is, in terms
of the opportunity recognition,
if you recall from the prior modules:
from the point of view
of opportunity identification
the entrepreneur has some choice
as to which quadrant
he or she is going to end up in.
For example, the entrepreneur
could choose a product or service
where complementary assets
are freely available.
Or it could be that they invented
a new distribution mechanism.
If you think of the case of Dell computer
that went directly to sales
over the phone and finally the internet,
that was an interesting innovation
in the sense that it bypassed
the retail channel completely
which was normal
in the hardware business.
So it's not to say, "If you're in
the hardware business,
you're doomed to go through a retailer
and retailers are powerful, etc."
You may be able to come up
with your own distribution channel
which then bypasses
the complementary asset that you need.
So first of all, in terms
of opportunity assessment
and recognition, exploitation,
the entrepreneur isn't fully constrained
by the different quadrants here.
And second of all,
even if you are in a quadrant
that is not very advantageous,
in other words anything
but the upper-left quadrant here,
you're still not doomed.
It's just that different strategies apply
to these different quadrants.
So for the upper-left quadrant,
that's very clear.
You're very difficult to copy, you've got
strong intellectual property protection,
or maybe you've got complexity
going in your favor,
and therefore, you can expect to release
the product to market, capture value,
and recoup your investment
taking your time to come up with
your next product or service.
However, in the other quadrants
you may be forced
or it may be desirable to come up with
a quicker response into the market,
especially the lower row here
where it's easy to copy.
If it's easy to copy your invention,
then when you get it to market,
you will make money at first,
you will capture some value.
But in the long run, or the medium run,
you won't be able to capture much value
because other people are going
to see you, copy you, and enter.
Therefore, you need to come up with a plan
to make a continuous stream
of new products
once the first one's in the market.
So this is more what you call
the Run strategy
versus the Block strategy.
The Block strategy is: you just release
the product to market,
you capture value
because it's difficult to copy,
and you can, more or less,
milk your products, as we say.
On the other hand, the Run strategy
is where you release the product to market
and then you continue to commercialize
new products in a continuous stream
that enables you to make money
for short periods of time
before you move on to the next thing.
Now, one final note here about alliances
and the role of alliances.
I often hear from entrepreneurs, they say,
"Oh, I've got a great business.
It's built on alliances.
Alliances are so great."
I think if you look
at this framework here,
you can understand why alliances
may or may not be so great, right?
If your alliance is
with your complementary asset holder,
and it's tightly held and important,
then the complementary asset holder,
in other words your alliance partner,
is going to charge you a lot
to gain access to that asset.
Therefore, it's not
necessarily a guarantee
that having a bunch of alliance partners
is going to be either very profitable
or a very good idea.
If the alliance partner is going
to dictate the terms,
then it could end up being
a very expensive proposition.
So, to summarize what we've covered today
in this segment on capturing value:
we started by discussing appropriability,
or the ability for the entrepreneur
to capture value.
We then moved on
to a discussion of imitaility,
or how difficult or easy is it to copy
the entrepreneur's invention.
Then we talked about complementary assets
and we drew a distinction between
the cases where the complementary asset
was important and tightly held
versus freely available or unimportant.
Then we looked
at these different combinations
of these factors
to determine that one of the nicest places
for the entrepreneur to be
is the case where it's difficult to copy
and complementary assets are
either freely available or unimportant.
And probably
the most difficult place to be
is the case where it is easy to copy
and the complementary asset holder
is tightly holding on to access
to an important complementary asset.
And there are different strategies
for dealing with the situation
that you're in;
how quickly you should commercialize
and release new products.
And we also talked
about the opportunity assessment
and exploitation plan that might lead you
to one quadrant or another
so that you can have
a more successful venture
that captures a lot of value.
Thanks a lot, we'll see you next time.