Welcome back to 5.3.
Today we're going to discuss
legal aspects of entrepreneurship
and just to give you a quick overview
of kind of top level issues
that you should be thinking about
right now, while you are considering
starting a company,
and my disclaimer, again, is
this should not be construed
as legal advice! (laughs)
So I can't give you any legal advice,
I'm just throwing some information
out at you here
that you might find interesting,
and you should definitely talk to a lawyer
if you have any of these issues.
We are going to discuss what is liability,
we'll talk a bit about incorporation,
vesting shares, what does it mean.
We'll talk about
intellectual property filings
outside of your country,
what is a non-compete
clause or contract,
how do you deal
with product liability, what is it,
then, we'll also give you some suggestions
on how to find a lawyer.
So let's move right along
right now, with liability.
What is liability?
Liability is when you are held responsible
for something that you did.
It sounds bad usually,
because it is bad.
There's usually something bad
happening and therefore,
people are trying to, as we say,
"search for the guilty",
try to find the person who is responsible
from a legal point of view.
So, liability is
when you are held responsible
for something bad that's happened.
As an entrepreneur,
there are many reasons
why you might be held responsible;
we're going to try to talk about
some of these major ones today.
In the course of running your business
you may have made
a bad business decision
which injured somebody,
monetarily or otherwise.
It could be that you are acting
in a fraudulent fashion;
that you're hiding information,
or you are lying, etc.
Negligence, which is when you are
neglecting something
that you know to be wrong or harmful.
There could also be employment
or HR problems
in which you are held liable,
and it could be, finally,
that your products
cause damage to somebody,
--could be physical damage
or could be monetary damage--
and you might be considered
liable for those as well.
So let's walk through this bad list here,
and try and understand the issues
for each of these things.
We already touched
on incorporation in Module 4,
but I wanted to give
a little more detail this time around.
When you talk about liability,
you have your own personal liability.
And then, depending
on how you incorporated your company,
you may have liability
for the whole company.
So it depends on the country,
but most countries do make a distinction
between something
that has unlimited liability
and other forms that have
limited liability.
So, usually, when you are
the only owner of the company
--we'll call that sole proprietorship--
and that is an extension of you;
you are basically
making money on the side,
and you have your own little operation.
And there you, unfortunately,
have unlimited liability.
So, when something happens to that company
something goes wrong with that company,
then you may be on the hook
to cover any damages
that you've caused,
any monetary damages
or physical damages,
based on your own assets.
Usually, sole proprietorships
are done at the very beginning,
or for very low impact-type businesses.
You have your own consulting company,
you don't have very many clients,
but it's fine, you do your own thing
and it's very unlikely
that you are going to injure somebody
and therefore, you are not that worried
about your assets.
A partnership is similar, in many cases;
now different countries have
different rules about partnerships,
but the most basic form of partnership is
that you go into business with a partner,
and depending on
the kind of partnership it is,
and the country,
but in many cases,
both partners are liable for everything
that happens with that business.
Or if there are multiple partners,
they are all liable,
and there are
certain kinds of partnerships
where some partners are not liable,
passive partners, limited partners, etc.
But in general, when partners are
coming together in a partnership
and they are in fact jointly liable
for anything happening with that company.
So partnership, in general,
does not protect you
from liability problems.
Then you have different kinds
of what people call
limited liability companies,
and those limited liability companies have
different names in different countries,
but the basic principle is
that you either have
a private corporation,
which means you have
a very limited number of shareholders
--we talked about that a little bit,
when we talked about crowdfunding--
or you have a public corporation,
which is when you have
many, many shareholders,
and when you make
some statements and disclosures
about how your company is run,
and you have it open
to the general public
to buy shares in that company.
What do these forms have to do
with each other?
They trade off ease and low cost
against protection from liability.
So, sole proprietorship is very easy,
you can do it immediately pretty much,
in most countries.
On the other hand, it does not
protect you at all from liability.
Then, the more you move
toward a limited liability company,
then, it's difficult,
because you have to go
through lots of steps
to register the company, etc.,
but on the other hand,
that does protect you
from the liability point of view.
So, it's something to think about,
how you want to plan that progression
as you move toward producing
and commercializing your product.
It does not protect you;
none of these legal forms protect you
from fraud and negligence.
Not that you are planning
on being fraudulent or negligent.
We'll talk about this one
in few minutes,
but if you know about something
that's happening,
then you should react quickly.
You should not try to cover things up,
or hide problems, etc,
especially problems that can cause
damage to your customers, etc.
In such cases in most countries
you can be found liable
for problems that were caused
by your fraudulent activities
even if you have some kind
of limited liability company.
So, be careful here,
and what this does protect you for
is bad business decisions.
In general, in most countries,
you cannot be held liable
because you've made
a bad business decision.
OK, let's talk about
employment issues now.
Employment issues are dealing
with the agreements that you make
with your co-founders
and with your employees.
So, what I'm recommending here
is that, in the very early stages,
I mean, once you think
you might start a company
and that you might want to work
together with some people,
you should draw up
a kind of a preliminary agreement.
You should involve everybody
who's involved with the business idea
at the beginning,
and you should figure out a way
to compensate them or to reward them,
and they should accept it,
to prevent disagreements later.
So you kind of laying up
the story of the company,
who is participating, who contributed,
and what are they going to get from it.
What does this avoid?
This avoids missing founders
type of situations,
where somebody contributed
at the beginning,
then they disappeared,
and then, if the company
is very successful,
they reappear and say, "I am the one
who thought about all these ideas,
it was my idea in the first place,
I want you to pay me...", etc., etc.
So there you've got problems
with people showing up
after your company is already successful.
These kinds of agreements early on
are also better for tax planning
in case, at some point,
this thing takes off
then you will have thought through
perhaps some of the tax issues,
because there are tax implications
of when you can count as income
certain compensations that you received.
Let's talk about vesting for a minute.
Founder shares, and early employees too,
they should always vest over time.
So what you don't want to do
is make an agreement at the beginning
where everyone owns a lot,
and then, one of the people leave
and this person leaves,
and then they've got all these shares
that you gave them at the beginning.
Should be a reward
for staying in the company
is that you should get
more and more shares.
What usually happens
is there's some shares
allocated to the different founders,
and then, those shares do not take effect
until certain milestones have passed,
either business milestones,
or time milestones,
so that it rewards people
who stay longer and do more work.
They end up having more ownership
and control of the company.
And all of these apply
to early employees as well,
so you want to spell out
what they are doing,
spell out their compensation,
whether it be for money
or for shares, equity of the company,
and then, all early employees
should also have shares that vest
so that makes them feel
committed to the company,
and they are actually rewarded
for the amount of the time
that they spend in the company.
Speaking of employment issues,
let's also discuss non-compete clauses
or non-compete contracts.
They are very tricky.
It's something that you need
to think about for yourself
--we'll talk about that in a minute--
and for your co-founders
and for your employees.
What is a non-compete clause?
A non-compete clause
is a kind of a contract
that's drawn up between
an employer and an employee,
and it prevents the employee
from competing with the employer
in the future.
So I might sign a contract,
I might go to a company,
I want a job and they say, "Fine,"
or "Sign here."
And it says, "you cannot compete
in this industry again,
and you have to work for me forever,
(laughing)
and if you leave, you can't do anything,
for any amount of time in the future,
that has anything to do
with this business.
That's a very broad definition.
It can also say, you are not allowed
to contact any of our current customers,
and you are not allowed to hire
away any of our current employees.
That's a very broad non-compete contract.
Most countries don't allow such...
that's called, in general, slavery,
so, "you can never work anywhere
in the world, you can't do anything
except for work for me."
That's not very good,
most countries disallow
those super broad contracts,
and what they are looking for
to be enforced
is something that's got
a very limited duration,
a very narrow scope,
both geographically
and technologically,
or product-scope,
so it could be, you cannot compete
in this particular region,
two years after you leave this company,
and it can only have to do
with products in this certain area.
So that would be a more enforceable
non-compete clause.
So, why do we care about
non-compete clauses?
Because you may have one now
if you are working for a company,
and you have to be careful
how this is handled.
If you are going to quit the company
and start a competing company,
then you might start
with a legal problem right off the bat.
On the other hand,
if it's a big boiler plate,
with lots of generic terms,
you're probably OK,
although, again,
I can't give you any legal advice,
because you have to check
with your own country,
and your own rules,
in your own region, etc.
If you are trying to hire some employees,
if they've signed one
with the current employer,
you have to be careful about that
and see how that works,
make sure that they are not violating it,
or if they are, if they are violating it
because is so general.
And then, finally,
once you hire people,
you might want to think about
how you want them to behave
as non-competing employees,
so once they leave,
what compensation
you are going to give to them,
what kinds of restrictions.
So again, I would advice
against this very generic, very broad,
and try to make a narrow contract
with your own employees
when you are hiring them,
and the best time to do that
is before you actually offer them the job,
or during the negotiation to hire them
so that you can resolve
all these problems before.
Bad time to do it
is after the person already left.
Right before they're about to leave,
you might have another opportunity,
but then you are talking about
compensating them,
and you have to have them sign something.
By the way, the more
the employee negotiates,
the more enforceable
the contract is, in general.
Boiler plates stuff is
not so enforceable in general.
Things that people negotiate
where they cross off a line here
and say they want to do
this and that other thing,
once you start negotiating
then it's considered
to be a valid agreement
that you have some power over
when you signed it.
Be careful with non-compete clauses
both for yourself, when you are leaving
another company,
and the ones that you are setting up
with your own employees.
OK.Let's talk a little bit about
intellectual property strategy.
Here, we've already discussed
this week, IP in general,
and now what we want to think about
is what do you do when you want
to move outside of your own borders,
of your own country.
If you don't think about this early on,
sometimes you can get stuck in a situation
where someone else owns
an invention that you made.
So that's why is important
to think this through.
Some intellectual property filings
can only be done early on.
Some countries have these rules,
"first inventor to file" rule,
so if you are multiple inventors,
the first one to actually put the forms in
is the one that has the right
to the intellectual property.
Worst one is even "first to file".
Not many countries do this anymore,
but still, that means that anybody
who hears about anything,
who brings the forms in to the IP office,
then they are the ones
to have the patent on it,
regardless of whether someone
invented before them or not.
When you have an international filing,
this could be a little tricky,
because you are working
in your own country,
which makes sense,
but then, when you want
to go to another country
you find out that someone else
already has intellectual property
based on your invention.
So you need to think about this
on the early side.
Try and get the websites, trademarks,
even in other jurisdictions,
other countries,
you might want to try and get websites
and trademarks in other countries,
patent filings if you can.
Patent filings are expensive
to undertake in multiple jurisdictions,
so it's a little bit tricky,
and we understand that it costs a lot,
so you might not be able to do
all these things.
One thing you might consider
is a patent-cooperation treaty application
which is PCT,
which is valid and recognized
in multiple jurisdictions,
or, if you think that it's too expensive
to do any of these things
it might be advisable
to think about a disclosure,
especially if you have IP
in your own country,
to think about how
you might disclose it and publish it.
That prevents other people
from getting patents on it.
When you want to go to their country,
then, at least, you have what people call
freedom to operate
in the sense that you don't have to worry
about violating or infringing
on someone else's patent,
when you move to a new jurisdiction.
Now let's talk about product liability.
What if your product
or service has the possibility
of doing damage to users?
And again, this could be
actual physical damage.
Someone could cut themselves
on your product,
or it could be monetary damage
where you advised to do something
and they follow your advices
or they use your service,
and they lose a lot of money.
These are what you generally call
product liability problems.
You need to think this through
a little bit, make sure
if you are designing something,
that they don't have problematic features.
The classic example here is
children's clothing
that doesn't have a draw string
around the neck,
so kids don't chock themselves on it.
Make sure you want to avoid
sharp edges on the edge
of a product like a phone,
you don't want to cut yourself on it.
And then, once you've made sure
that the designers know
how to avoid these features,
then, what you want to do is make sure
that the manufacturing process
also doesn't introduce defects.
And that means iterating
with the design group
if it ever gets to that point.
to make sure
that when building these things
that they don't have defects in them
that can cause damage;
you know, you don't want to blow up,
you don't want them to cut people, etc.
Clarify the intended use of the product.
What does that mean?
That means in certain countries
you could actually be held liable
for something
that your product caused damage on,
even if it wasn't used in the way
that you intended.
So, if you could imagine
someone trying to shave with a cell phone,
and poking themselves in the eye,
and saying, "A-ha!
Your product hurt my eye."
"Well, my product is not intended
to be used as a razor.
My product is intended
to be used as a phone.
So you have to think these
so called intended uses through,
and make sure that people
who buy your product or service
know what the intended use is.
You want to get insurance,
there's all kinds of product
liability type insurance in the market,
and you should probably think about that,
especially if you have
a lot of customers at some point
and you think that the product
might be possibly misused,
you can try,
it can't hurt,
although it's unlikely.
You can also get
some of your supply chain partners
sometimes you can get the retailers
to indemnify you if there is a problem,
so try and negotiate
with your supply chain partners
to share in the risk.
Recall the product if it's necessary.
If you find that there is
something wrong with the product,
then recalls are very expensive,
we know they are,
but they are less expensive
than you being held liable
for fraud or negligence,
because you know about something
and you didn't do anything
I hear about these stories,
all the time in the news,
and it just doesn't make sense.
Do not ignore problems
when they are brought to your attention.
Because as soon as you ignore something,
and someone can say: "A-ha!
You were negligent
in dealing with this problem.
You knew about this problem
and yet, you told no one about it
and 10 more people die
because blah, blah, blah.
So, don't ignore problems
when they are brought to your attention.
Use the recall, obviously,
the cheapest solution
is to fix things in the design phase.
And then, it's a little more expensive
to fix them in the manufacturing,
and then it's released to market
and of course,
depending on the industry,
you've got beta test,
you've got updates, etc.
Once it's out there and commercialized
then recalls are
the most expensive options.
Beyond that, the worst option is
being sued, held liable
for fraud, negligence,
because you knew about a problem early on
and you decided you didn't want to fix it
because it was going to be
too expensive to fix.
Be careful there,
and make sure that you understand
these kinds of issues.
OK, hopefully, I have not scared you away
from actually... (laughs)
...working on your startup!
Because working on your startup
is really the most important and fun part
about this whole thing,
and it's true that there are
a lot of legal issues here
that may make it a little less fun.
So, usually, the best thing to do
is to actually talk to an attorney.
And you have to to find one.
What I've done here is
I've given a little list
of things you can think about
when you are looking for an attorney.
The first thing, does this person
have experience with startup companies?
This is super important.
You don't want to get anybody,
this friend of a friend;
"Oh, yeah, I've done some wills,
I can incorporate your company for you."
So there it's tricky
because you really, really, really
want to work with someone
who has experience
with small companies.
Preferably, someone with experience
in the specific sector
in which you are operating.
So, if you are doing a software product,
and you find an attorney
who's an expert in biotech companies,
you know...yes, the person's had
some experience with startups,
but maybe not in your sector,
and it can also be
some very sector-specific things
that you need to know about.
So it's preferable if you can find
someone with experience
in the sector in which
you are operating.
Has this person defended startups?
They had problems in the past.
Has this person stood by
startup companies in the past,
or did they just run away?
So you want to make sure
that the startup lawyer,
has had some experience,
working with and dealing with,
and sticking with startup companies,
all the way through different processes.
Has this person worked
on financing negotiation?
Because it really is nice
if your lawyer understands
the kinds of financing
you are going to get,
that you expect to get,
and can help you with negotiations
because there are a bunch
of tricky legal issues,
There's tax complications,
tax consequences on a lot
of decisions that you make early on,
and so, it's good if this person
has also worked
on some kind of financing negotiations,
similar to the kind that you think
you are going to need.
And of course, the last two
are more personal things,
but do you have a referral
from a trusted colleague?
Given the choice between two lawyers,
one of whom was
recommended by a friend of yours,
or by someone who was
in the same industry as you,
that you know personally,
and someone else you don't know
anything about,
then, even if that person
is a little more expensive,
it might make sense
to go with the referral.
And finally, do you have
a personal rapport with the person?
In other words, do you get along
with the person, can you trust the person,
can you reveal things to the attorney,
and can you get an honest opinion,
and give your honest opinion as well.
So that's a very,
very important part of this.
So, that's it for legal issues,
as again, I hope I haven't been
too scary trying to lay out
all the potential problems that you have;
But I think, in general,
for startup companies,
it's good to understand
the potential problems early on,
and try to figure out a way
to mitigate them,
rather than being surprised
by problems later on in the process.
So I hope you find this useful,
and stay tuned,
we're going to come back next
and talk about growth.