This week we are going to discuss
an application of magnetic resonance
that is dear to chemists
and biochemists alike,
but also has some applications
in biomedical imaging.
And I want first to start out
with some of examples
on the distinction of the
magnetic resonance signal
based on its chemical environment.
And the prominent example
of magnetic resonance imaging
here is fat and water.
So, if we take an image of the brain--
here are the eyeballs,
this is a transversal cut,
here is the midline--
this is a typical T_1 waited image here.
And then here the same image
has been repeated,
but through some manipulations
the signal that arises from the fat
has been eliminated,
and we will discuss
how this is being done.
So we see the subcutaneous fat is gone.
We also see that the signal
behind the eyeballs here is eliminated.
And this is due to the fact
that behind our eyeballs
we have the so called retrobulbar fat.
So, in this image one has been able
to eliminate the source of signal
due to fat taking particular property.
And so this bright region here,
which could potentially be a tumor,
is established here
as containing a lot of fat
and is most likely a lipoma.
So, if you look at the body,
then we have the original image,
which is everything included,
then one can generate an image
that has only the the fat signal--
we see the fat signal here on the surface,
this fat here or just
the water-only signal.
Or here, another example--
somebody who carries more fat.
There is more fat here in this image,
as illustrated here in the fat-only image
and in the water-only image.
The area which is rich in fat
is not so intense.
Here is another example--
this is MRI of the breast.
We have a normal MRI of the breast here--
very bright images
and then to distinguish
between potential cancer tissue
and fat signal
which both would give up
in this type of images bright signal--
the signal here was acquired
with suppressing the signal from the fat.
One sees a bright signal here,
which is a potential cancerous lesion.
Here is important to know
that cancer typically
does not contain a lot of fat signal.
Here is an example from fatty liver.
This is an area taken here from the liver,
and one looks now at signal--
the water in these different cases
of fatty liver is constant,
and here on the side this extra peak here
goes from mild to moderate
to severe fatty liver.
So this is an example
of the way the data is analyzed
to obtain biochemical information in vivo.
So, why is NMR spectroscopy
so important
for chemists and biochemists alike?
It is actually so important
that essentially any department
of biochemistry or chemistry
does have its NMR equipment.
And the reason here is,
it is a routine tool.
It allows non-destructive
analysis of samples.
A more amusing example is
to analyze the quality of wine in bottles.
If you have an expensive wine,
but you want to have quality assurance
that this wine really is
what it pretends to be,
this can be done--you don't want
to open the bottle of wine.
Another example is,
if you have spent several years
in synthesizing in your compound,
and you want to verify
that the synthesis process
has properly worked
and your volume of your milligrams
of the compound that has been synthesized
you don't want to subject it
to an analysis
that's destructive,
that destroys the molecules.
Other examples include
structure determination solution,
so, since we are limited
to soluble molecules,
this allows to study
the molecule structure in solution,
molecule dynamics are accessible,
since we have T_1, T_2
and similar effects
and also chemical reactions
can be followed in situ.
So, how is it done?
Well, typically the solution
with a compound
is put into an Eppendorf--
one needs some strong magnetic field,
just like with by medical applications--
here the z axis is vertical
that is a vertical bore NMR instrument,
the sample is inserted,
data is obtained, the data is analyzed,
and here is an example
of this complex molecule,
and one now looks at different signals
from this molecule,
each corresponding
to a different proton in the molecule.
Or more complex here
is the signal of protons,
this is a 2D plot [inaudible]
what signals are linked
to other signals here.
I will come to that later.
This typical data can be analyzed,
and from that the structure
can be determined.
So here is the structure of a protein.
One can see the core
and four alpha helices here.
Here is another example of a structure
that's been determined with NMR.
This work was pioneered by Kurt Wüthrich,
a biophysisist from Zurich,
who for his work received the Nobel Prize
in Chemistry in 2002.
So, first, before I come
to the chemical effects
of how we can measure chemistry
with nuclear phenomena--
that is nuclear magnetic resonance
I want to dwell a bit
into the effect of the relaxation
on the magnetization.
So, let's look at the effect
of T_1 and T_2 on the signal.
We have here time,
we apply an RF pulse with flip angle α.
The flip angle for such an RF pulse
is given by γ B_1 times its duration τ,
and so the magnetization M_z
after this RF pulse is given
by the z magnetization
before the RF pulse times cos α.
The transversal magnetization
after the RF pulse--
that would be here--
is given by the z magnetization
before the RF pulse times sin α.
So here this is
the transversal magnetization
at this time point,
which we call M_x_y (0).
So, these are the effects
of T_1 and T_2 on the signal,
are given
by the transversal magnetization,
evolves now by this initial
transversal magnetization
with its exponential decay--
that's what we see here.
And so, after the RF pulse
the signal decays
under the influence of T_2 relaxation.
Now, we call this,
this z magnetization at time zero,
then this period before the RF pulse,
which we typically call
the repetition time T R or T I,
the time of inversion--
we will see shortly
why this is called this way--
giving this time, we have
the influence of T_1 relaxation.
So. the effect of T_1 is given
by this differential equation,
the solution of which is given
by this general equation here,
and we call this equation
also longitudinal coherence--
and we will see shortly why.
So, if we're setting,
M_z(0) is equal to this term here,
then we substitute here the solution,
we substitute this term here,
and we obtain this solution here.
We call this longitudinal coherence ,
because the effect of T_1 on the signal,
because we ultimately obtain the M_z (t).
The M_z (t) by the RF pulse is converted
to transversal magnetization,
which is being detected.
So, the influence of T_1 depends
on prior RF manipulations.
And this comes in the solution
to our differential equation
from this term here,
which includes prior manipulations,
that is, prior applications
of RF pulses, that is, B_1 fields,
that have been done to the magnetization.
So, this is important here that
what we do to the magnetization
in terms of RF pulses,
that influences on how T_1
manifests itself on the signal.
So, now I want to address the question
under what optimal conditions
are we most sensitive to changes in T_1?
This is also a flip side of that is
under what optimal conditions
can one measure the influence of T_1.
And here the term to introduce
is inversion-recovery,
and you will see shortly
why it is called inversion-recovery.
Essentially we are looking at this, say,
application of two RF pulses--
it is the multipulse experiment--
and it is a traditional experiment
which is used to measure
the influence of T_1.
So, we consider here
an RF pulse of flip angle α,
a certain time delay τ
and then a 90 degree pulse.
This time here we will call T I,
or time after inversion.
This 90 degree pulse, π / 2 pulse,
it's sole function
in this particular multipulse experiment
is to convert the z magnetization,
which is present right here,
into transversal magnetization,
because we want to measure
the z magnetization,
and z magnetization
cannot be directly measured,
so one has to go through the detour
of converting it
into transversal magnetization.
So, that is the multipulse experiment
we are going to consider.
So, the measured signal
is essentially z magnetization
after this time period T I.
This z magnetization is given here
by the solution
of the differential equation,
where [inaudible]
and here we have M_z (0).
M_z (0) = M_0 cos (α),
so we have waited a long time,
we have equilibrium magnetization here,
we apply now RF pulse α,
and so the z magnetization
at this time here is M_0 cos (α).
And we substitute
this term here into this term,
and this gives us this equation here,
where we express the z magnetization
as a function of this time T I here.
Now, two things:
What is the best choice of α,
so what would allow us
to produce the most sensitive experiment
to changes in T_1?
We will use the same approach
that we discussed last week
and we introduced in the first lecture
in the first part of the course.
It's the error propagation calculation.
So, first we are interested
in establishing
how sensitive is our z magnetization,
right here, at this point,
just before the π / 2 pulse,
to changes in T_1.
That is, we calculate the derivative
of z magnetization with respect to T_1.
It gives us this expression here.
Here is the z magnetization,
we will take the derivative
of this with T_1,
and here we have not put T I,
we just put just put a time t,
and we call this function F.
Now we want to know
under what choice of α
is this function maximal.
So, we will take the derivative
of this function with respect to α
and will set that derivative to zero.
This tells us at what point
with respect to α
is this function maximal.
And here is the derivative,
this id non-zero, this is non-zero,
so we are interested
in a solution, where sin α = 0
And here we have two possibilities:
α = 0 or α = π.
Now, α = 0 is a silly experiment,
because then basically
we are not applying this RF pulse,
the flip angle is zero.
We will be just measuring
equilibrium magnetization,
and we are not sensitive to T_1,
so the correct answer here is α = π.
So, α = π , that is a 180 degree pulse
or, as we have introduced
earlier, two weeks ago,
this is an inversion pulse and hence
this experiment is called inversion,
followed by recovery,
and T I is called time of inversion.
So, in this particular case we have now
the z magnetization as function of T I.
It's given by the equilibrium
magnetization times (1 - 2 e ^ T I / T_1).
Next question is: What will be
the proper choice of time T I here
to detect changes in T_1?
So, we want to choose the T I such--
we have established
that α is 180 degrees--
we want to choose T I such that we are
most sensitive to changes in T_1.
So, we will take this function here
and we will calculate now
the derivative of this function
with respect to time.
Here we did it with respect to α
to find the optimal α,
now we will do it
with respect to this time t here,
which is our T I.
This is a chain rule,
we get this expression here,
we simplify the terms--this is non-zero,
this is 2, this is non-zero,
so the term in the bracket
has to be zero,
and we are finding
that the optimal inversion time T I
to be sensitive to changes in T_1 is,
if we choose T I = T_1.
This is again not surprising--
we have an exponential function
and, again, in an exponential function,
as you increase,
you are not sensitive here,
you are not sensitive here
somewhere in the middle, and it turn out
that you are most sensitive exactly
when this time equals to T_1.