Now we have introduced magnetic resonance
as a very insensitive technique.
We are limited by
the equilibrium magnetization,
which is limited by
the Boltzmann distribution,
and we have clearly established
that this technique is not suitable
for detecting the signal
from just a few molecules.
But we have to get a decent signal
to be able to measure it.
And this is typically done
by the approach of averaging.
So multiple acquisitions
are being acquired,
be it for spectroscopy, for NMR,
be it for MRI, this is generally the case.
So what one does is one applies
the same experiment over and over again,
by averaging obtains a sensitivity,
an SNR that is increased.
So we have the situation in this case,
that RF pulse is, or flip angle à,
are applied every TR seconds,
and they're applied this n times.
And now the question is at what point,
under what conditions
is the transverse magnetization,
which is proportional
to the signal, maximal?
So we have two parameters.
We have the flip angle à
and the repetition time TR.
And what one now is interested
is calculating the flip angle à
as a function of TR.
It is clear that if one waits so long
that one has equilibrium magnetization,
so 5 times T1,
e^-5 is equal to 0.01,
5 times T1 gives us
the equilibrium magnetization.
At that point, the optimal
flip angle is 90 degrees.
However, if our TR is very short,
and we always apply
a 90-degree flip angle,
then we will not get any signal,
we've seen already at the beginning.
At the end of last week's course
we have seen an example thereof
where we get no signal.
So this is the strategy here.
We want to figure out
what is the good choice
of the flip angle as a function of TR.
So here is the experiment.
We have an RF pulse flip angle à.
We detect the signal.
We have the RF pulse à applied again.
We detect the signal here again,
and we'll call here this signal
at the beginning of this second RF pulse,
we'll call this M
the transverse magnetization
at time zero, that is our signal
that we wish to optimize.
This time here is equal to TR,
we'll call this TR.
And now we will assume that before
the application of the RF pulse,
any transverse magnetization
has decayed away in the time of TR second.
This is usually a good approximation
and it shall suffice
for the calculation here.
So we'll assume that
we have no transverse magnetization
and we just have magnetization
along z at this time point.
So our z magnetization
has a function of time here,
this is again, the general solution
of the differential equation
for the z component,
is given by this term here,
which describes return
to equilibrium magnetization,
and this term here, which describes
longitudinal coherence.
Now let's assume that we are doing
a number of these à degree pulses.
Can be a thousand, ten thousand,
a few hundred, or so on.
And after these RF pulses and the nth TR,
so let's say, we have done 100 TR periods,
100 RF pulses followed by 100 TR periods,
we have a z magnetization at that point
and we'll call that Mz(n).
So at 100 or 1000,
doesn't matter what the n is,
it has to be sufficiently big.
In practice, it's actually 3 to 5,
is already sufficient,
but we'll see that later.
So we'll call this magnetization here,
just before this RF pulse
after n TR periods,
n applications of à RF pulses
and TR periods, Mz(n).
Now a flip angle à is applied
and so the Mz at time zero,
that is the z magnetization
here at this time,
that would be here,
is given by Mz before the RF pulse
times cosine à.
We've already seen that relationship,
that's the magnetization that's left
after a flip angle of à.
Now during this period,
we'll consider the T1 recovery.
So Mz(n + 1) is equal to this term here.
That's essentially using
this equation here,
by substituting Mz(n) here,
times cosine à, as Mz(0).
So we'll take this term,
substituting this equation,
we have the terms rearranged here
so that the exponential term
is on this side.
And so this Mz(n + 1),
that's the z magnetization
just before the second RF pulse
here in this scheme,
and I've regrouped the terms here
and we have M0, the return to equilibrium,
and here's the longitudinal
coherence term.
Now we're going to apply
a steady-state condition.
We're going to assume
that a sufficient number, small n,
of RF pulses and TR periods,
has been applied
so that the Mz(n + 1)
and the Mz(n), are equal.
We can assume that
this happens at some point.
At some point it will always recover
to the same z magnetization
and then we will call this magnetization
equals Mz(n + 1)
and we'll just call it Mz.
So we have now here Mz(n + 1),
here we have Mz(n).
After n periods we'll now assume
that these two are equal,
so we'll set them equal,
I've done this here,
and we'll put the terms
that contain Mz on the left side,
and we're left with the terms
that contain M0 on the right side.
And so we can now express
the z magnetization
as a function of
the equilibrium magnetization,
as a function of the time
between RF pulses, the repetition time,
and as a function of the flip angle here,
the cosine à term.
Now this is not yet our signal.
This is just the equilibrium
z magnetization that we have
just before this RF pulse here,
so we are now interested in
the equilibrium transverse magnetization
because it gives us
the signal that we obtain.
So the transverse magnetization here,
after this RF pulse
is equal to the z magnetization
before the RF pulse
times sine à.
We'll set this in and now we have
the equilibrium magnetization
equation here.
So that's our transverse magnetization
at equilibrium
is proportional to M0,
is influenced by the flip angle,
and influenced by the TR/T1.
And so we have now TR/T1 on one side,
and the flip angle à
that influences this
equilibrium magnetization.
This is a fairly fundamental equation here
that describes
the influence of the signal
as a function of flip angle
and time between RF pulses.
So now comes the question,
this was a fairly complicated equation,
and the question is,
how does a signal depend on TR,
time between RF pulses,
T1, the T1 relaxation,
and the flip angle à?
So if you plot the signal
versus flip angle à,
and here I'm showing this equation again
that we just derived
on the previous slide.
This is the same expression here,
and now let's look at what we observe.
So if TR/T1 is 10,
e^-10 is essentially zero.
So we have this is M0 sine à
divided by 1.
So we have M0 sine à,
so our signal describes very nicely
a sinusoidal function here.
And the maximum is at 90 degrees,
not surprisingly.
Even for TR/T1 equals 5,
here e^-5 is 0.01,
we get essentially the same behavior.
So this is not surprising.
Then as we see, if we plot this function
here for different TR/T1's,
as TR/T1 gets smaller and smaller,
then we can see that the maximum
shifts further and further
away from 90 degrees.
So here's this function plotted
and I've tried to, with this dashed line,
indicate where the maximum
of the flip angle is.
So at what choice of flip angle do we get
the maximum transverse magnetization?
And here it's expressed normalized to M0.
So if you look now at this flip angle,
so we want to calculate
the transverse magnetization,
which is our signal,
at what flip angle à
is the maximum obtained?
And this is done by taking the derivative
of the transverse magnetization
of this expression,
with respect to the flip angle,
and setting it to zero.
I will spare you the math of doing this.
This is a simple cumbersome exercise
of multiple calculations.
We'll just take the derivative
of this term here,
with respect to à
and I'll give you the solution here,
which is cosine à is equal e^-TR/T1,
where à is called the Ernst Angle.
So if we plot this now, we have the TR/T1,
and notice here the logarithmic scale,
the angle here in degrees.
We have at a very high TR/T1,
we have the not surprising 90 degrees,
and as the TR/T1 gets shorter and shorter,
this asymptotically goes to zero.
Of course, if TR/T1 goes to zero,
then cosine à goes to 1,
that is a zero-degree flip angle.
And this optimal flip angle is called
the Ernst Angle.
It's been named after Richard Ernst,
a physical chemist from Zurich,
who received for his work,
among also this work,
he received the Nobel Prize
in Chemistry in 1991.