Okay, now we're talking about
nuclear magnetic resonance here.
We're talking about a nuclear property,
so how can we from a nuclear property
deduce chemical information?
And the question is,
how does chemical environment
influence the nuclear
magnetic resonance effect?
So let's start out with the nucleus
of the proton of the hydrogen atom H1,
that's the proton.
That's a single lone proton.
This proton typically if you take
a isolated hydrogen atom is
surrounded by an electron,
so there's an electron cloud
surrounding that nucleus here,
and it's nice and symmetric.
For the resonance frequency
of the pure proton,
that is the procession frequency,
we have the Larmor frequency,
which is gamma (ğ›„) B zero
so that is the Larmor frequency
that we have dealt with so far.
Now if we have our hydrogen atom
in a magnetic field B zero
what now happens is a distortion,
a very small distortion
of the electron cloud.
I will not go into the details
of the quantum mechanical explanation
of how this electron cloud is distorted
but you can rationalize this
simply by the fact that the electron
which swirls around the nucleus
around the proton, that electron,
its flight pattern is most likely
influenced by the presence
of an external magnetic field.
Think of it this way, if it happens
to fly parallel to be zero,
there's no influence of the magnetic field
if it flies perpendicular to B zero
there's a maximal influence.
What the consequence of this is
that the electron cloud is deformed,
it changes ever so slightly its shape.
As a result of that,
a small magnetic field
due to the electron is being introduced.
This magnetic field,
we'll call it here delta (Î”) B,
this magnetic field is proportioned
to B zero with proportionality
constant Î” here.
So the presence of the electron
around the nucleus in the magnetic field
leads to an alteration
of the magnetic field at the site
of the nucleus.
So this small change
in the magnetic field B zero
at the position of the proton
leads to a multifield expression
for the procession.
Here's the Larmor equation
and now we don't have ğ›„ B zero
but we have ğ›„ (1 + Î” )
That is the equation of motion
that describes the behavior
of the magnetization and as a consequence,
the Larmor frequency is now
the procession frequency
which is  ğ›„ B zero times this
is now changed and is given
by the Larmor frequency times (1 + Î”).
And this Î” is called the chemical shift,
short for chemical shift
of the Larmor frequency.
The sign here is not important
for the further understanding
whether we put a +Î” or - Î”.
What is important here is
that based on the presence
of the electron, the proton
magnetization will no longer process
exactly at the Larmor frequency.
Now let's think about if we have
this hydrogen atom close to a nearby
electronegative atom
such as oxygen or chloride.
These electronegative atoms attract
the electrons.
They produce therefore a reduced
electron density at the site
of the proton and therefore
a so-called deshielding
of the nearby hydrogen nuclei
of the protons.
That means we have less
of an effect of the electrons
on the resonance frequency.
So I'll illustrate this here
with an example.
First we'll take the normal
hydrogen isolated hydrogen atom.
Here's the hydrogen electron.
Everything is as we have described here.
If we now have nearby an oxygen
so we'll look at a hydrogen nucleus
in a OH, which is part
of an OH bond,
we have the electronegative oxygen
and now for convenience I have drawn
a simplified distribution
of the electron cloud that belongs
to the hydrogen atom.
And essentially because
oxygen's electronegative,
the probability that the electron
is swirling around the hydrogen
is much reduced and most
of the electron is actually at the site
of the oxygen.
So what this means now
is if we put the OH group
into a magnetic field,
there's little shielding from the electron
so there's little modification
of the magnetic field
at the site of the nucleus
of the hydrogen atom here
at the proton.
Consider a third example.
This is a CH bond,
so we have the carbon here.
Carbon is less electronegative
so it starts to pull the electron cloud
off the hydrogen electron
over to it but not as much as the OH,
which is here.
And so as a result,
there's a stronger effect
of the presence of the electron
on the changing magnetic fields.
So there's more shielding
and a stronger shielding
of the magnetic field,
this Î”B, this figure.
So as a consequence,
the resonance frequency
of the nucleus of the hydrogen atom
of the proton is higher in an OH bond
than it is in a CH bond.
So I'll stick
with this qualitative description
because it helps us
qualitatively understand
what's happening,
the strictly quantum mechanical
beneath your calculations
trying to predict based on molecular
[inaudible] of chemical shifts.
They are qualitatively very good
but they are not sufficient
in explaining all the details
that one sees.
So we will stick with this qualitative
argument here
that electronegativity, that is
the distribution of the electron clouds
has an influence on the resonance
frequency, and therefore
through the change in resonance frequency
with this nuclear magnetic
resonancy effect, one is able
to sense the chemical environment.
So how is this chemical shift
of the resonance frequency
or chemical shift Î” linked
to electron negativity.
And I've taken here a table,
we're looking at compounds CH3X
where X is fluoride, oxygen,
chloride, bromide, iodine, hydrogen
or silicone.
In these molecules, one has determined
the electronegativity precisely
and also the chemical shift
of the proton resonance frequency.
Taking this table
and plotting electronegativity
on the x axis versus
the chemical shift on the y axis,
we actually see a fairly nice
at least monotonous relationship
between electronegativity
and chemical shift.
This compound is
a little bit different from the others,
but this is a very nice strong correlation
between chemical shift
and electronegativity.
Now chemical shift is not measured
in Hertz but it's measured
in parts per million.
And parts per million here
is not a measure of the number
of molecules present
and it's not an absolute measure.
It's actually measured with respect
to a reference compound.
For protons, tetramethylsilane
is one compound or TMS,
and here it is the reference compound
so this is set to zero.
So the exact explanation here is
the difference of the resonance frequency
observed, relative to that
of the reference compound,
divided by the frequency
and that typically gives us numbers
that are 10 ^ -6
or it's a parts per million effect,
and someone multiplies
by 10 ^ 6 to obtain
a number which is something
in the order of 1 to 10
or something like that.
it's easier to write
than constantly having to write 10 ^ -6
and that's why
it's parts per million or ppm
because we multiply here by 10 ^ 6
So there is no absolute measure here
that this is zero is a convention
where the zero is placed.
What is important here is
the relative relationship.
And so if one looks at the chemical shift
of protons that's the nuclei of hydrogen
in all sorts of different compounds,
one knows roughly based
on the type of chemical bond
in which range the chemical shifts
to appear.
So we will not see this type OOH
with a chemical shift over here.
This is a high chemical shift here.
This is all with respect to TMS,
tetramethylsilane.
So at what place in the spectrum,
here the proton spectrum,
the resonance frequency is observed
tells us a lot already
about the chemical compound
under investigation.