So how can we-- and this brings us
to the question on how
can we measure chemical shift?
And this is done by looking
at the free induction decay signal.
So we have our signal
as a function of time,
a is the transverse magnetization
times zero times e ^ - i omega (Î©)t
times e ^ -t / T2
We've seen that previously
that expression, that's our time signal.
Now let's say you have a signal
that is separated by 1 ppm.
So that is one millionth change
in the resonance frequency.
Would we be able from such a signal
to be able to see a change
in one millionth
of the resonance frequency?
Even if we place ourselves
into the rotating reference frame
where it might be easier to see that
there are multiple frequencies present,
we're not very good at detecting
in time domain signals
the change in frequency.
And so here we are going to use,
what is used here is
the Fourier transformation,
and I'll show you here
the Fourier transformation
of this function but only
the real part, and we'll not take
the full expression here.
We're just interested in
the fact that the Fourier transformation
is proportional
to the transverse magnetization
of times zero times this function here
which is the Fourier transformation
of this term here,
and x here is given by the frequency--
that's the argument here--
minus the chemical shift.
That's the exact resonance frequency
of our compound times 2ğ›‘ times T2.
So what does this look like?
We'll take this signal here,
Fourier transform it,
and we're getting this line shape here.
This function here is
a Lorentzian function.
It has its maximum when Î© is equal
to delta (Î”), then x gets zero.
This is maximally and the full width
at half maximum here is given
by 1 / ğ›‘ T2
That's the full width of half maximum
of the function of Fourier transformed,
which is also called the peak.
Now the area of the resonance is
proportional to the magnetization
at times zero, this here.
This is proportional to the number
of nuclei and therefore proportional
to the concentration if one can neglect
the effect of relaxation
in particular here T1 relaxation.
So in this case,
we are obtaining a signal,
the area of this resonance here
is proportional to the concentration.
So to verify this, we have the signal
at times zero is equal
to the inverse Fourier transform
of G(Î©) which is e ^ i Î© t (d Î©)
but now we'll evaluate this
at times zero
to obtain the signal at times zero.
So that is the integral
of this function G(Î©).
So that's the integral of this.
That's nothing
but the area of the function,
and we can see that this is now--
the area is proportional to this term here
so it's proportional to M zero
if we neglect the effects of relaxation.
Now let me illustrate this
with a molecule that most of us
have been exposed to in their life
and that's ethanol.
So ethanol's found in,
among others, in nice wines.
Here's its structure.
It's got a CH3 group,
the methylene group and an OH group,
the alcohol here.
Here's the 3D rendering.
Here's the oxygen.
Here are the carbons
and in white are the hydrogens
which we are interested in.
And if you now take a milliliter of wine
or ethanol and you put it
into your NMR spectrometer,
then you observe three peaks,
similar to here.
Three peaks here,
this is the reference peak
of the reference compound TMS,
that sets us the zero ppm scale.
What we are observing is three peaks,
if we know there's only one compound
in there, then we know we have
three different types of protons
in that molecule that are subject
to three different chemical environments.
But we actually know more
because we can also calculate
the area under the curve,
that is this function here.
And we'll see here this is the red curve.
That's just integrating from infinity
to whatever frequency is plotted here.
We'll see an increase here,
that's the area of this peak here.
Then this area here is twice
as high as this one,
and this area is three times as high here.
So if we know that there's
only one compound in our sample,
aside from TMS, and we know
that the ratio is 1: 2: 3,
then we know that there are
three protons that have essentially
the same chemical environment.
They are to the right
so they have a lower ppm
so they are in a less
electronegative environment.
We have two protons
in a more electronegative environment
and one proton
in the most electronegative environment.
This is actually where we expect
the OH groups to be,
and so it's easy to deduce from this data
that this is the most probable molecule
that we are observing.
So we'll stick with the example
of ethanol for what is to come.
There's an additional effect
of chemical proximity
that I want to illustrate,
and we'll stick here with the example
of ethanol.
So we have here, again, here's TMS,
here's the methyl signal, the methylene
and here's the OH signal.
Here's the chemical shift scale
here in ppm.
So on the horizontal axis
and as a a reminder,
here is the molecule
that we are discussing.
Now if you look at the methyl signal,
we actually see this is not one resonance
but there's three signals that we see.
And for methylene, we see four signals.
And what I want to explain here
in the next few minutes is
the origin of these extra resonances
that are observed.
And essentially what they are
dealing with here is a hyperfine splitting
of the resonance frequency.
The main mechanism
that we have to consider here is
that the nucleus which has
a nucleomagnetic moment
produces a very, very small
magnetic field linked to its dipole.
So we have B zero,
we have the electron cloud.
And now if we have the same electron cloud
but we have a nearby nuclear spin,
then this nuclear spin will produce
an extra magentic field,
this magnetic moment that adds
to the magnetic field of B zero,
and therefore, has an effect
on the electron cloud.
So this additional tiny magnetic field
that's linked to the dipole of the nucleus
this additional magnetic field
for a spin one half nucleus like hydrogen,
like the proton is either oriented up
or oriented down.
So this changes polarity,
and this will affect the electron cloud
in the molecule and therefore alter
the magnetic field at a nearby nucleus.
So if I have a nuclear spin here,
this nuclear spin points
either in this direction
or in that direction.
This will create
an additional magnetic field.
This creates an additional reorientation
of the electron cloud
and at the site of the nucleus
that we're measuring,
it will then, depending
on its orientation, create a small change
in the resonance frequency
or the Larmor frequency.
So let's say we have
a nearby spin one half,
and we'll look here
at the proton resonance.
So we are here interested
in this proton here,
and we have now a nearby spin
one half nucleus.
Here it's pointing down,
and here it's pointing up.
And so therefore it produces a--
in our nucleus hydrogen of interest
which is this guy, the electron cloud
will change its configuration
ever so slightly depending
on whether that nearby spin one half
is oriented upwards or downwards with
respect to the external magnetic field,
and this results in a split
of the resonance frequency
and the intensity of the resulting
two peaks is exactly the same.
Now why is it exactly the same?
Now remember we had dealt
with the Boltzmann distribution.
So we had said the probability
whether it's up or down,
that probability is
essentially 50 percent.
Well, one is 50.00001 percent
and the other one is 49.99999 percent
but in terms of intensity
we don't see these small differences,
so it is essentially the 50 percent
up or down and so therefore
the number of protons that see
the spin up or the number of protons
that see a spin one half down
is the same and therefore
we're seeing this signal split
into two peaks of equal magnitude,
and that's called a doublet.
Now for a CH2 group,
so if we're now here on the methyl,
we have nearby the methylene,
that's two protons.
That's these guys,
and these two protons, we'll assume here
that they are
chemically indistinguishable,
and so we have four probabilities:
up up, down down,
up down and down up.
So four probabilities.
They are of equal possibilities,
four configurations of equal probability:
up up, down down.
That's easy.
Up down and down up,
we cannot distinguish them
because the two dipole fields
of the two protons in the CH2 group
cancel each other
so up down or down up
will produce the same change
on the electron cloud.
And so we have a triplet peak
with a relative intensity ratio
of 1: 2: 1.
We're here observing three protons,
but the next molecule
that this interacts with has two protons,
so we have four possibilities:
one, one and two,
that's the up down, down up.
Now at the CH2 position,
if I look at the protons that are here,
they are seeing three protons
from the methyl, three protons.
So three protons, and they are--
because the methyl typically
rotates very fast-- the three protons,
they are having a number
of combinations, and actually we have
eight combinations.
We have up up up, up up down,
up down up, down up up,
down down up, down up down,
up down down
and down down down
so if you count this,
this was eight possibilities,
and so we have a quartet.
Up up down, up down up,
and so on are indistinguishable,
same thing for the other cases.
They cannot be distinguished.
So this gives us a quartet,
a resonance which is split
into 1: 3: 3: 1 intensity structure.
So to conclude here,
in the case of ethanol
we see three peaks,
we have already a good idea
that there most likely are three protons
in the same chemical environment,
but what this kind of splitting tells us
indeed this whatever is in here
is close to a CH2,
and whatever is in here is
close to a CH3,
and from the relative intensity
2: 3 of the entire area,
two to three,
it is easy to deduce that the molecule
that one observes here is
indeed ethanol.
So I want to give here an example
and that is phosphorus spectroscopy.
Well, phosphorus spectroscopy was
actually the first application
of strong magnetic fields
to living humans.
There was an interest in looking
at phosphorus metabolism,
phosphate metabolism in the human brain
as well as in muscle,
so these were the first
in vivo applications,
and I want to illustrate here
the type of information
that one can get.
So this is a phosphorus spectrum,
and this is taken
from the brain region here
indicated in yellow.
One observes the signal
due to phosphocreatine.
We have phosphomonoesters
such as phospho-ethanolamine
and phosphocholine.
These are membrane anabolic
compounds.
Then one has glycerophosphocholine
and glycerophosphoethanolamine,
breakdown products
of lipid metabolism.
And then we have
adenosine triphosphate.
I presume you're all familiar
with ATP, its structure,
so we have adenosine triphosphate,
so we know there's three phosphates in it,
and indeed we have three resonances.
The alpha (ğª) is the one
that is closest to the ribose.
This is the ğª, this is the beta (Î²),
this is the gamma (ğ›„),
and we can observe three peaks
related to ATP.
And what we can also see here
is the splitting here.
This tell us that there's
a nearby phosphorous
relative to this.
Relative to this peak,
there's a nearby phosphorous,
and if we can see here,
there's a 1: 2: 1 structure.
It's not a very good
signal-to-noise ratio here,
but it indicates itself,
and so we see that this must be linked
to two phosphates nearby,
and indeed this is the Î²,
the middle one which sees
this one and this one as well.
We also have inorganic phosphate,
which is resonance 24,
which is this peak here,
and dinucleotides NAD or NADP.
Whether it's with the H
or without the H,
the dinucleotides contribute
to this signal here.
So these are the compounds
that can be observed.
They are linked to a large extent
to cellular energetics.
What is also measured is
intercellular pH from the position
of this peak creating kinase activity
by measuring the conversion
between phosphocreatine and ATP
and ATPAs by measuring
their conversion
of inorganic phosphate and ATP.
These are reactions
that can also be measured.
So this is an example
of what the information
that is obtainable and can be done.
Here's the example of phosphorous.
Like I mentioned, phosphorous,
for historical reasons,
was the first nucleus
to be studied in vivo.