The question now arises,
what can MR spectroscopy measure?
I've just given you an example,
phosphorus, out of historical interest.
Essentially MR spectroscopy
allows to assess
the concentration
of biochemical compounds in vivo.
The signal is typically proportional
to the number of spins present
and in particular to the concentration.
After the Fourier transform,
what one does is measure the area,
so integrate in this case.
This is assuming
that the effect of relaxation,
such as T1,
has been taken into account,
but it's still proportional
to the concentration,
even if there is a flight of T1.
Now what compounds can one detect?
And there are three rules
I want to share with you here.
One is, one needs typically
a concentration
on the order of millimoles, millimolar.
If you translate this
into tissue concentration,
since the density is roughly 1 g/mL
this translates into typically
1 μM/g wet weight
to give you an idea of the concentration
that one needs to be able
to see the signal.
Then what one would need is typically
a water-soluble compound.
It doesn't have to be exactly--
but it is a good guess
that if it is highly water-soluble
then it is sufficiently mobile
to be detected.
Remember, T2 is very short
for immobile signals.
So the main requirement here
is mobile but a good indication here
is water-soluble compounds.
We can, for example,
measure vitamin C in our brains,
we know it is 1.5 μM/g.
The concentration of vitamin E
which intercalates into the membranes
in the lipid bilayers is not detectable.
Third one to remember is the influence
of the gyromagnetic ratio.
So proton, the hydrogen nucleus
of the proton,
is the most sensitive nucleus.
So taken together, if we are now looking
at the spatial resolution
that's achievable,
we have to bear in mind
that the voxel volume that one can,
in a certain amount of time measure,
is inversely proportional to the signal.
The more signal we have,
the smaller the voxel can be.
And here's an example, this is
phosphorus spectroscopy of the heart.
Here's an MRI of the heart
and here this little square is the voxel
from which the phosphorus data
has been taken.
So if you look at this grid here,
which gives you the size
of the voxels in the heart,
this grid has a course resolution
that would not allow us
to detect the individual
anatomic features of the heart,
so it's much bigger.
And why is this so?
Well, let's look at water.
The water protons in the tissue
are at roughly 80M concentration.
Biochemical compounds, on the other hand,
are typically on the order
of millimolar concentration.
So we're looking at something that is
roughly 10^5 times more concentrated
when we image water
compared to when we measure
informational biochemical compounds.
So one gets, as a good ballpark,
a millimeter spatial resolution in humans.
For water MRI
and for biochemical compounds
the spatial resolution is typically
on centimeters in humans.
If one looks at rodents, one can get
50 microns spatial resolution
in rodents for water imaging
and millimeter spatial resolution
in rodents
for the biochemical compounds.
So these are some ideas.
The main point here is, the difference
between what one can see with MRI
this gray-scale image versus
what the biochemical measurements
with spectroscopy,
the main difference here
has to deal with the fact
that the concentration
of most biochemical compounds of interest
is on the order of millimolar.
Now, there's a question:
"Why is spatial resolution
better for the rodent studies?"
Think about it.
Assume you have the same compound,
same concentration
and the same external magnetic field.
Why do we get a better signal,
a better spatial resolution
in rodent studies?
Well, the answer is, as we have seen,
the RF coils which detect our signal
are dictated to a large part by B_0 sub r
which means that we want the coil to be
as close to the organ as possible.
And if you look at a mouse head,
which is roughly the size here
of my small finger,
the entire dimension of the mouse head,
corresponds to skull thickness
and fat on my head, for example.
So a RF coil that's designed to detect
a signal from the mouse brain
would not even see the signal
in the human brain.
And so because the detector,
the RF coil, is further away
from the organ of interest in humans,
the spatial resolution is also lower.
Now we have seen that
there's a huge advantage
in imaging the water.
What if we're interested in measuring
the signal from biochemical compounds
which carry protons?
We have to deal with the fact
that we have a strong signal from water,
which is response to concentration of 80M
in order to be able to detect
a signal of our compounds,
which is on the order of millimolar.
And here's an example.
We have water and phenylalanine.
This is just looking at
the full signal of this mixture
and here if one scales this up,
now the vertical scale has been expanded,
one can see the resonance
is end up due to phenylalanine.
And then here's the same thing shown again
but now there has been something
done to the water magnetization
so the signal from water
is much reduced.
Now how can one suppress the resonance?
How can one suppress the signal
from a particular compound?
And this is done
with resonance suppression
or with reducing the magnetization
that is being detected
relative to that resonance.
And the simplest procedure here
to describe is where one takes
the z magnetization of, let's say, water
and one takes the z magnetization
and applies a so-called
selective 90 degree pulse
on the resonance of the water
or on the signal to be suppressed here,
particularly we'll stick with water.
So the experiment to be done
is a selective 90 degree pulse.
This selectivity, remember,
the selectivity is determined by B_1.
We have said we can roughly excite
a bandwidth that corresponds
to γ B_1/(2π) in frequency
so one uses a weak B_1,
a 90 degree pulse,
so γ B_1 τ has to give us 90 degrees.
If B_1 is weak the pulse has to be long,
so it's a long RF pulse.
After that pulse,
the z magnetization of the water is zero
but that of the other compounds
has not been affected
because the B effect is along z.
And then one applies, for example,
an α degree pulse
for excitation of a detection.
We'll assume here
that something has been done
between the 90 degree pulse on water
and this excitation pulse
such that the transverse magnetization
of the water does not generate
a measurable signal.
You can assume it has been decayed by T2.
We'll discuss, in next week's lecture,
some of the measures
that allow us to destroy
the transverse magnetization
that is by dephasing.
But for now we'll just assume
this has been done.
So our signal here then will contain
only the signals of interest
and the water is no longer there.
So let's take an example from muscle here.
This is the water signal,
here we have the lipid signals,
water and fat.
And now one applies
such a 90 degree selective pulse
on the water signal
and here is the signal
that is being observed.
Not very interesting because at this scale
we can roughly see some bump here,
so one can vertically expand this scale.
And now we can see all
the resonances linked to the fat signal,
monounsaturated fatty acids,
polyunsaturated fatty acids
and all sorts of different
chemical environments of the proton nuclei
and the water signal here
is substantially reduced.
That allows to see those details.
So this technique is being used also
in MRI for producing Fat-Sat scans,
fat suppressed scans.
So we'll first take the technique,
we'll have here the signal from water
and from the lipid or fat
and if one applies now
a selective pulse on the water,
the water signal has been suppressed
and one has only the fat signal
to contend with.
Conversely, if the resonance frequency
of this long, weak RF pulse is adjusted
to be on the resonance with the fat
then the fat signal is being saturated,
that is the z magnetization
of the fat magnetization is set to zero
and one obtains a water-only signal
or more precisely a Fat-Sat scan.
So now I want to give an example
of proton spectroscopy of the brain.
So we'll plot the chemical shift axis,
that's in parts per million,
and this is a proton spectrum
of the brain.
One will notice here,
one of the signals that is negative,
this is actually the incompletely
suppressed water signal
so water suppression, as we have
discussed before, has been applied
and this is the information
that we can obtain.
We have resonances linked
to energy metabolism
such as phosphocreatine and creatine.
They are here.
So phosphocreatine and creatine,
whether phosphate is present or not
does have an influence
on the chemical shift
of the methylene proton in creatine.
One has the signal from glucose,
that's this tiny little guy here,
I have lactate at this position
and alanine which is nearby.
Lactate and alanine
share a metabolic reaction
that's alanine aminotransferase.
Compounds that are linked
to neurotransmission in the brain
are glutamate, which has
multiple resonances,
there's two CH2 groups
and a CH group in it;
glutamine which is
structurally very similar,
so compound number 7 is close
to compound number 6;
gamma-aminobutyric acid,
which has multiple resonances as well;
and N-acetyle-aspartyl-glutamate,
a dipeptide involved in neurotransmission.
We have aspartate that's also been linked
to the processes in neurotransmission,
and glycine as well.
And we have also serine
contributing to the spectrum.
We go on with compounds that are
typically linked to membrane metabolism.
Phosphoethanolamine
and glycerophosphocholine,
they are here, and here, and here.
And N-acetyl-aspartate,
which has the aspartyl group, is here,
and here is the acetyl group,
this prominent signal here.
So these are the compounds linked
to membrane metabolism.
And finally there are some compounds
linked to either antioxidative defenses,
such as glutathione,
vitamin C, ascorbate, taurine,
and myo-inositol linked to taurine
and myo-inositol have mostly
been linked to osmoregulation
but in the case of taurine,
there's most likely
multiple roles in the brain.
And finally we have an isoform
that is scyllo-inositol
that contributes, as well,
to the proton spectrum of the brain.
So it's a wealth of chemical information
on a number of important
biochemical processes
that can be measured in vivo
with proton spectroscopy,
and we'll briefly discuss
on how these measurements are done
and then I will give some examples
and illustrate the measurements
that are possible.
So we have introduced
that the area under a peak
is essentially proportional
to its concentration
and so how can we actually get
biochemical concentrations in vivo?
So we'll look at the proton spectrum
here again, here is a measured example.
And then what is done is a fit
that's been made to that spectrum
and one looks at the residual.
And I just want to illustrate
this principle here
because for most compounds we know
the ionic strength, we know the pH
and we of course know the temperature.
So one knows very precisely
the exact resonance frequency,
that is Larmor frequency,
of the particular compounds
and their groups.
So we have N-acetyl-aspartate.
We have the acetyl group here
and the aspartyl group, which is here.
Here's the chemical structure
that we're looking at
and these are the peaks
that are recognizable here.
We have glutamine, here's its structure
and here are the peaks
that are linked to the glutamine,
two CH2 groups and one CH group.
And finally we have glutamate.
Here's its structure and glutamate
has these resonances.
Note this, the difference
between glutamate and glutamine
is this NH2 group that changes
this group here to an NH2 group.
So for the resonances,
the further away that we are from here,
the more similar they are.
So we have glutamine,
glutamate here, fairly similar.
Here it's almost the same chemical shift
but in this group which is the closest
to the carboxyl-terminal here
is the biggest chemical shift
at this position.
That has to do with chemical proximity
and the change in
the electron cloud configuration.
Last example here is lactate.
We have the methyl peak here,
and the CH group is here.
Here's the molecule methyl peak here,
And we see, very nicely, the doublet here
that tells us that
there's a CH group nearby.
For measuring these concentrations,
one measures an in vivo spectrum
fixed with the model spectra
obtained under in vivo conditions
and this way allows us to deconvolute
the number of concentrations
and measure, therefore, up to 20 different
neurochemical compounds in vivo.
So here I want to give an example
of metabolic phenotyping
of transgenic animals.
This is a historical study here.
What one was looking at
is wild-type animals
and transgenic animals
for Huntington's disease,
it's a Huntingtin gene knock-in,
the so-called R6/2 mouse
and in that particular study,
over seven mice,
what one saw is a difference
in glutamine levels.
Now the difference
in absolute terms is not very big
but the measurement with these types
of analysis can be very precise
so these error bars
indicate standard deviation
and it was, hence,
already in the data, clear
which animal had an abnormally high
glutamine concentration
compared to the others.
Now here I want to show some examples
from the human side.
This is a patient with a brain tumor.
We have some changes
in the MRI signal here.
And now these squares here indicate
where the signal has been taken.
Here, this signal
corresponds to this side,
where the image intensity is abnormal.
And here on the normal side,
one sees a normal pattern
for human patients.
Now the knowledge
of the biochemical composition
of an area in the brain
is illustrated here, it's advantage.
The changes like these observed in vivo,
they could mean that one has
necrosis of the tissue,
they could mean neoplastic tissue,
they could also be consistent with edema.
So there are a lot of cellular processes
that influence the relaxation
of water in the tissue.
However, the biochemical information here
which tells us that N-acetyl-aspartate
is essentially not present in this area
and there's a lot of
choline-containing compounds,
implies that this is indeed,
to a large extent, tumorous tissue.
In the muscle physiology, which has been
an interesting area of application--
this is a muscle here.
The proton spectroscopy is taken here
and here's the phosphorus spectroscopy,
a lot of phosphocreatine relative to ATP,
characteristic of skeletal muscle.
Now what is interesting here
is for the proton spectra
the fat signal is split into a signal
that is attributed
to intramyocellular lipid
and extramyocellular lipid.
The intramyocellular lipid
is fat that's contained in vesicles
that are bound to the mitochondria.
This fat is what is being used
for a marathon run.
The extramyocellular fat,
this signal here,
is attributed to the white inclusion,
so when you eat a steak
you see the white stuff,
that's the EMCL: extramyocellular lipid.
The reason those two are distinguishable,
research at the University of Bern
have very nicely demonstrated
it has to do with
the magnetic field susceptibility,
the magnetic field is slightly different
between these two environments.
I'll show one last example.
This is proton spectroscopy
of the mouse brain.
This is a tumor in a mouse.
Here is the normal appearing spectrum
and here is the side of the tumor.
Now there are a lot of specific
and detailed changes going on
but in terms of seeing that
there's something major going on
with the biochemistry,
we don't have to be magicians,
this is fairly obvious
that this is clearly different
from what we see in the normal case.
And here's an example
of a mouse model of stroke.
We have the normal proton spectrum here
of a region that has not been
subjected to stroke
or before they've been
subjected to stroke.
And then three hours after the stroke
one observes an increase
in the glutamine signal
and a decrease in the glutamate signal.
Now, again, this is of course subjected
to the type of analysis
that I've illustrated before.
But visually we can clearly see
that this peak here has gone up
and this one has gone down
in relative terms
so there is something going on
in this area here.
And glutamine and glutamate share
an important metabolic relationship
in mediating neurotransmission.
So this concludes the examples
of NMR spectroscopy for this week.
And next week we will discuss
how in MRI one can reconstruct an image.