Programming means
writing programs.
A program is a sequence of instructions which
will be executed by the computer.
For a given task, the programmer will
thus have to design a program
well suited to accomplish this task.
The first step is to develop an algorithm,
that is, to find the sequence of instructions
constiuting the program.
However, it is the computer's
microprocessor which will finally
execute the instructions
constituting the program.
Unfortunately, the microprocessor can
only execute very simple
instructions. Those are too basic
to be efficently used by a human being.
Fortunatley, the programmer can write his
program in a programming language,
C++ being one of them, more accessible
to a human being.
The programming language will be
translated in instructions
understandable and executable
by the microprocessor.
Thus, do not ever forget that your
(high-level) program must be written for humans
and not for a computer.
More precisely, a program is one
or more text files,
which can be automatically translated [into
machine instructions] by another program.
This other program is either an
interpreter or a compiler.
In the case of C++, a compiler is
used.
The C++ compiler generates an
executable file from the
the text file(s) containing the
source code,
that is, the C++ program.
This executable file contains
the instructions
executable by the
microprocessor.
In this course, you will learn to
analyze a problem so as to write
a program in a high-level language.
The language here will be C++. However, we
will attempt to keep a broad view
and to teach you principles
valid
in most programming languages.
For a given problem, you will first have to
conceive the sequence of instructions,
which the program will go through.
Then, you will write the C++ program
corresponding to this sequence of instructions.
Then, you will compile your program,
thus generating an executable program.
In practice, it is possible for the compiling
to fail because your program
does not abide by the C++ rules.
Therefore, the compiler has not
been able to translate it.
In such a case, you will have to correct
your C++ program so that it
indeed abides by C++ rules.
Often, the compiler will produce error
messages, which will
guide you in the correction
of your program.
Once your program has
been compiled,
you will be able to execute it and
test its results.
At this point, it is possible that your
program
will not result in what
you expected
because you erred during the conception
of the original sequence of instructions.
Do not forget that the microprocessor
will blindly execute your program.
You thus have to be cautious
during the conception.
In case of unexpected results, you will have to rethink
your sequence of instructions,
modify your program accordingly,
and resume the development cycle.
Let's now write our first
C++ program.
We will start by opening a development
environment.
The easiest solution is
probably to use Geany;
you will find the instruction procedure
on this course's website.
The beginning of our program is
a little mysterious
and is read : hash, include, iostream.
using, namespace, std, semicolon.
You do not need to understand these
lines right now,
just be aware that they are required so
that your program may function.
The following of the program is :
int, main, opening parenthese,
closing parenthese,
opening brace.
This part will be thourougly
explained in the lesson related to functions.
The tradition, when learning
a new programming language,
is to start with a program printing
the message "Hello world".
We will respect this tradition.
In C++, it will be done as follows :
cout, less-than sign, less-than sign,
quotation mark,
Helllo world, quotation mark,
less-than sign, less-than sign, endl,
semicolon.
Our program ends with the line :
return, 0, semicolon
and a closing brace.
From now on, always try to present
your programs clearly.
Albeit not required for
your programs to compile and run,
it is good practice so that
your programs remain readable.
For example, all lines should
begin on the first column,
except the lines between braces, which should
be indented to the right,
for example by adding 2 blank spaces,
as we did.
There are no strict rules. For
example, some programmers would
put the opening brace here.
Simply endeavor to be readable
and coherent, in other words,
follow always the same
rules.
Before we call the compiler, we should
first save our program.
We will save it in a directorly on
the desktop,
which we called "programme CPP".
Of course, you are free to save
your programs wherever you wish,
though it is recommanded to be
in a directory containing
but C++ programs.
We will call our fille
helloworld.cc
The extension ".cc" serves to indicate
that your file is a C++ file;
we can also use the extension ".cpp".
Now, you can see that the development
environment
has colorized our program.
Indeed, Geany is now aware that our
text is a C++ file,
thanks to the ".cc" exension.
With a bit of practice, you will soon
realize that the colors make
your programs all the more readable.
Now, let us compile our program.
With Geany, we simply have
to click the "build" button.
This will not only launch the compiling
but also generate an executable program.
Be careful, the "compile" button
only triggers the compiling
and does not create an executable program.
So, if we click this "build" button,
a message will appear here, informing us
that the compiling has ended successfully.
Since everything went good,
we can now execute our program.
To that end, we simply have to click
the "execute" button.
A window opens and
prints our message.
Voilà ! We have created and
executed our first C++ program.
In the directory where we saved the
C++ program,
there is now a new file called
"hellowolrd" without exention
or with the extension ".exe",
if you are using Windows.
This is the executable file we have
just created.
We can now launch this file
without passing by Geany.
As by clicking the "execute"
button on Geany,
a window opens and our
message appears.
It is probable that, while
typing this first program,
you have made a typo.
What happens then?
And what should we do in such a case?
For example, let us suppose that
you have omitted the semicolon after the "endl".
The compiler will display
an error message,
indicating that it was expecting
a semicolon before the "return".
It also indicates the line number where
the error occured.
Be careful though, this
line number is only indicative;
it is possible for the error to have
occured in the previous line,
as is the case here.
By the way, if we click on the
error message,
Geany will send us to the corresponding line.
Now, if we put back the semicolon,
the compiling will, again,
be successfull.
Now, if, instead of "std" you had
typed, for example, "sdt",
the compiler would generate many mistakes.
No need to panic; one always has
to start by correcting the first mistake
and then compile again.
Very often, a mistake is caused
by another mistake occurring
before in the program.
If we correct the "sdt" to "std",
all the mistakes will disappear.
To sum up : be thourough
while typing your programs,
mind the presentation and,
in case of mistake, always correct
the first mistake and compile again.
Very often, this will correct, at least,
some of the following mistakes.
In order to find this mistake,
start by checking the line number
indicated by the compiler (do not
forget that the error
may have occurred on the previous line).
Then, interpret the error message
displayed by the compiler
in order to understand the problem.
If you have not done so already, we invite
you to open your development
environment and create your own
helloworld program.