In our introduction, we have
discussed the different steps
leading to the creation
of a program.
We know that we should start
by thinking, conceptualizing,
and planning the sequence of instructions
we aim to realize.
Then, we will translate this conception
into a known programming language,
such as C++.
Then we will go through several steps,
such as compiling and testing,
before we finally end up
with an executable program.
Now, we will enter the heart of the matter
and acquire the tools necessary
to translate a program conception
into a C++ program.
A program is nothing but a
sequence of instructions,
working with data.
Actually, the sequence of instructions
are closely related to
the notion of processing.
These processing operate on data
while the data also operate on
processing.
Depending on the nature
of the data, different types
of processing will be performed.
Let us imagine that we wish to
write a brief program
tasked with resolving a
quadratic equation
of this kind.
We can picture rather easily the
different steps
leading to the solving of such
an equation.
First of all, we should figure out
the involved coefficients,
the b, the c in order to know concretely
what equation we are working
with.
Then, we will calculate the
discriminant (delta).
According to the value of this delta,
there will be different possible situations.
Thus, different processing
will be held.
For example, if the delta is negative,
we will simply print
that there is no solution.
If delta is zero, we will calculate
the unique solution
and print it.
Otherwise, there is the case where we
have two solutions.
We will not treat this last case
explicitly now.
We can see that there are
several processing.
Here, at the step two,
we have a processing calculating
the delta.
These processing operate on data;
indeed we see that
calculating delta
means working with the data
b and c,
which are provided at the beginning.
We also see that data influence
processing,
for example, here,
the newly-calculated data delta
will impact the performed
processing.
Here, depending on the value of delta,
we will either print that
there is no solution
or calculate the unique solution
and so on.
We clearly see that there is a
codependency between data and processing.
Processing operate on data,
which then impact the performed
processing.
We can draw two conclusions here.
The first is that one of the
fundamental component
to express processing is
the notion of expression.
Here, we need to evaluate
a short arithmetic expression
in order to calculate our delta.
The second is related to the
notion of data.
For exemple, here, we see that a data
like delta is associated with a value.
At different stages of the program,
we need to find the value associated
with this data.
Having a name,
such as "delta" gives
access to the value of this data,
at different stages of the program
and to reference this value
using a name.
This brings us to a fundamental notion
called the notion of variable.
The objective of this introductory
programming course
is to present the necessary
components
in order to perform processing
and manipulate data in
a suitable way.
As processing, we have declared
that the notion of expression
was fundamental and will examine
it thouroughly later,
along with the notion of operators.
Regarding data, we have just
demonstrated, through
our little example, the fact that
memorizing data
through variables is primordial.
This is the subject
of today's episode.
In programming, a variable
is a way to store a data,
to associate a name with it.
Concretely, in a program
executed on a machine,
a variable corresponds to an area
named in the memory,
a named area.
We usually call this name
an identifier,
the identifier of the variable.
This memory area will contain a value,
as we can see here,
will store a value associated
with the name "n".
An important fact is that C++
deems mandatory to clearly
define the genre associated
with every data we wish to manipulate.
We call this, the type
of the variable.
For example, we may want
to manipulate integer-type,
decimal-type or character string-type data.
We need to clearly specify it when,
in our program,
I indicate that I want to use a variable.
In our example,
we would thus have a variable called n,
storing the value 123.
Its type is the integer type, which is written
"int" in C++.
But what should we do
concretely in a C++ program,
when we wish to declare a variable ?
You have here the little shell
of a C++ program,
ready to receive your instructions.
We will now declare an integer-type
data,
storing the value 4.
To this end, we type the name of the data.
We specify its type : integer.
And we associate it with a value,
here, the value 4.
We have here the aforementioned
components :
we declare a variable n,
containing the value 4,
with the int type.
When we write such a line
in a program,
as we just did in an
editor,
we are actually
declaring a variable.
We declare, in our program,
that we wish to use a variable
called n.
Referring to our former
terminology,
the identifier of the variable here, is "n".
Through this identifier, we will
be able to access
the value stored in
this variable.
Associated to this data, is a type,
the integer type,
which is written "int" in C++.
In C++, we do not absolutely
need to
give an initial value to our
variable when we declare it.
We can declare a variable
leaving it empty,
which we did here.
Here, we have an identifier "n_carré"
(TN: n_carré means n_squared)
of the type int, but with no
initial value associated.
These two lines are both
valid variable
declarations in C++.
To initialize a variable is to
give it an initial value.
This usually done along with
the declaration
Here, we declare an int-type
variable n
and  initialize it to the value 4.
this translates into
such a memory diagram.
We now have an area,
identified by "n",
containing the initial
value 4.
This is the recommanded way
to proceed.
We have seen previously
that it was possible in C++
to declare a variable
without initializing it.
We find ourselves in such
a situation :
the variable n_carré can contain
absolutely anything.
Therefore, the processing
manipulating this variable n_carré
are utterly unfathomable
and can result in any
type of results.
These results will probably be incorrect.
This is why we need
to initialize a variable
before using the value
it contains.
The type associated with
the variable upon its declaration
is absolutely fundamental.
This type will condition
the type of processing
we may perform with this
variable.
When we realize such a declaration
in our program,
we indicate that n can contain
integers and integers only.
Similarly, if we declare a double-type
variable in our program,
where double means decimal in C++,
we declare that the variable x
will contain decimal numbers
and decimal numbers only.
To sum up, the declaration
of a variable in C++,
follows this layout :
we indicate the variable type,
its identifier
and, in parentheses, its initial value.
Also, we should not forget
the semicolon at the end.
This second way to declare
a variable is valid,
but disadvised, for we do not
give any initial value to the variable.
By the way, please note that
the type of a variable
cannot be changed later on.
When we declare a variable
of a certain type,
this variable will keep its type
for all its existence in the program.
In C++, it is possible to declare
two variables on the same line.
In this case, we indicate the
associated type only once
and separate both declarations
by a comma.
This can lead to ambiguities,
therefore it is recommanded not to
overruse it.
There a few conventions one needs
to respect
when declaring a vairable.
When we give an identifier
to a variable,
this identifier may only be constituted
of letters and digit.
By the way, the underscore character is
considered as a letter.
You have here the example
of a valid identifier.
Accents are not allowed.
You have here the example
of an invalid identifier,
containing an accent.
Also, the first character has
to be a letter.
You have here an example
of an invalid identifier,
the first character being a digit.
Of course, the identifier cannot be
a reserved keyword of the programming language.
There are several reserved keywords
which we cannot use as the
name of a variable.
Upper case and lower case
are authorized
but not equivalent, meaning that,
for example,
the identifiers "ligne" and "Ligne"
are not equivalent.
They do not refer to the same variable.
We have already discussed the notion of type,
essential when declaring
variables.
The two main elementary types,
allowing, in a program,
to manipulate numerical data
or declare numerical-type
variables are int and double.
We have already encountered
them in several examples.
There are, of course, many
more predefined types in C++.
For example, if, in a program, I wish
to manipulate positive integers,
for example, the number of students
attending this course,
we will resort to the "unsigned int"
type.
This type precisely means
positive integer
and lets us characterize our data
in a more precise way
than an int would.
Similarly, if, in a program, we need to
manipulate characters,
namely the usual characters from
a to z, we can use the type "char".
Later in this course,
we will expand further on the predefined
types in the C++ language.
Right now, we know how to
declare and initialize a variable
in order to have it store a data.
Very often, it will be required
to change the value of the variable,
during the execution of the program.
This can be accomplished
through an assignment.
Assignment is performed
through the "equal to" operator,
also called assignment operator.
Such a line is read : we assign
the new value n times n
to the variable n_carré.
This means that we are
changing the value of the variable
in order to store inside it
the new value n times n.
Be very careful not to mistake
this with a mathematical equality.
The executuion of an
assignment operation
actually occurs in two steps.
First of all, the expression on the right
side of the assignment symbol
"equal to" will be evaluated.
Here, in our example, we have
a variable n,
storing the value 4.
Knowing that in C++, the asterisk
represents the multiplication,
the result of the evaluation n times n
will simply return 16.
Then, what we have evaluated during
the first step
will be stored inside the variable
on the left side of the assignment symbol.
Here, the variable n_carré
stores the value 16.
It is important to understand,
that if n_carré formerly
contained something else than 16,
this result would have been
erased and replaced by the new value 16.
In general, the assignment
goes as follows :
You have a variable name, followed by
the assignment symbol "equal to"
followed by an expression, which
will define the new value
the variable will take through
the assignment.
Naturally, we will examine expressions
thouroughly later.
You can see a few of them here :
An expression can be reduced
to an elementary value,
a simple expression like
n squared here.
We will use the usual
arithmetic operators,
which we will discuss later on :
multiplication, soustraction...
Of course, do not forget the famous
semicolon at the end;
it is essential for the well-functioning
the compilation process,
As we stated previously,
one should not mistake the assignment
with the mathematical equality.
Despite the "equal to" symbal being
the same, it does not carry the same meaning
in mathematics and programming !
Let us analyse these two
instructions here :
in mathematics, these two lines
would mean that a and b
have the same values,
in both cases.
In C++ though, this is not exactly
what is going to happen.
Let us pay attention to the first instruction,
supposing that we have
variables a and b,
each storing a different value.
Executing this instruction
will result
in evaluating b, which has
the value 2,
taking the result of
b's evaluation
and storing it inside
a; this will produce this result.
Now, let us do the same with the second instruction,
supposing that we still
have our variables a and b,
with the values 1 and 2.
We will evaluate a, take the
result of the evaluation
and store it inside b.
We take a, and shove it inside b.
Therefore, we end with both a and b,
having the value 1,
We can see that, in programming,
a and b indeed end up with
the same values,
but these values are not the same
in both cases.
Moreover, if, later, one
variable is modified,
the other will not be impacted.
For example, if a is then
modified to 3,
b will keep the value 1.
Similarly in mathematics, if we
were to write something like this,
it would mean that, throughout
all calculations,
a and b will always verify
this property.
In C++, the situation is not quite the same.
Let us imagine a situation where
we assign the value 5 to
the variable a.
Then, we write this line, not unlike
what we previously
expressed in mathematics.
This will result in
storing inside b, the result
of the evaluation "a plus 1",
that is, 6.
Then, we can perfectly, when
we execute the next instruction,
modify the value of a again.
We clearly see that this relation
is not verified anymore here,
which would be the case in mathematics.
Therefore, in C++, it is absolutely
valid to write such an instruction,
meaning to calculate the expression
" a plus 1 "
and store this result inside a.
Here, concretely, if
we have a variable a,
formerly containing, let us say,
the value 3,
we will start by evaluating
the expression on the right side
of the assignment operator.
The result of this evaluation will be
" 3 plus 1 ", that is, 4.
Then only, we will store this
newly-calculated value inside a,
leading to this result.
This here, is an instruction
very frequent
and useful in programming.
You will have the opportunity
to use it intensively
through many an exercise.
We have now seen hwo assignment
permits to modify
the value of a variable
during the course of a program.
However, in certain situations,
once a variable has been granted
an initial value,
we do not wish to see this value
change later;
we wish to ensure it will not change anymore.
In such case, we will precede the
declaration of the variable
with the keyword "const".
The rest of the declarations
remains identical:
a type, an identifier,
an intial value.
We simply added the reserved
keyword "const".
You have here an example of
a constant declaration.
We declare VITESSE_DE_LA_LUMIERE
(TN: vitesse de la lumière means speed of light)
as a double-typed constant
having this for value.
After this declaration, it will
not be possible to modify,
via assignment,
the speed of light.
If I attempted it, it would cause
a compiling error.
Now, you know how to declare
and initialize a variable.
You also know how to change
its value in the course of the execution
thanks to the assignment.
We still need to discuss some
fundamental elements,
such as printing, for example,
the value of a variable,
or such as the different expressions
we can use
to assign a new value to
variable.
This will keep us busy
for the next episodes.