Up until now, we have seed
how to declare, initialize
and assign a value to a variable
Now, we will focus on how
to print the value of a vaiable
and how to read it from
the keyboard.
Let us begin with the printing :
if we glance at this
simple example program,
a printing line is, for example,
such a line.
Let us examine it :
This line begins with
the reserved keyword "cout";
this is a variable representing,
in the program,
the standard output device,
generally, the terminal.
Then, we can see several printing
sections.
We must systematically regroup them like this,
with the " << " sign (double less-than sign).
meaning that we wish to print something.
From a mnemonic point of view,
this represents the flow
through which the information
circulates.
The information will go from what
follows to "cout".
This should make it easier to remember
the direction of these signs.
So, behind this sign, meaning
"print",
we can have different possible
printing values.
Here is a "literal" value,
in these double quotes.
This means that the sentence will be
printed exactly as it is.
Then, we have a variable name, n, written
here,
representing the value of the variable, stored in the memory
under the name n.
Therefore, we will print the value
contained in the variable n.
Be careful not to mistake this with "n".
(double quote, n, double quote).
which means "print the letter 'n', the word 'n'".
Then, we have the period written
as it is,
as a character string.
Finally, we have the reserved
keyword "endl",
meaning "end of line".
This permits to jump to the next line,
to generate a line break.
The printing of the variable n
is actually a specific
case of a more complex expression.
Actually we can use any C++
expression in "cout".
For example, we can print 2*n
(2 times n).
The following line is thus read :
on cout, print the message
"le double de", print the value of n,
print the message "est" (= "is"),
with here, two blank spaces.
Then, print the expression 2*n
(two times n), print a period
and, finally, a line break.
(TN: "le double de" means "twice as many as")
"cout" and "endl" are actually called
std::cout
(S-T-D, colon, colon, "cout")
and std:.endl
(S-T-D, colon, colon, "endl").
We can write them simply
"cout" and "endl"
because, at the beginning of the program,
we added the instruction:
"using namespace std;"
thanks to think, we do not
have to write
"std::" before the reserved
keywords belonging to the
so-called "standard library namespace",
the namespace std.
Without the line
"using namespace std;",
we would need to write
std::cout and std::endl.
We wanted you to know that because,
in code from the outside,
you could encounter this syntax.
Now, to illustrate all this,
let us examine step by step,
the course of our example program.
First of all, we declare an
int-type
variable n
and initialize it to the value 4.
This will create in the memory,
an area
where we will store an integer n,
inside which we put the value 4.
Then, we will declare a int-type
variable n_carre (means "n_square").
Since it is not initialized, we
do not know a priori what value
it initially contains.
Then, we execute the instruction
n*n (n times n) goes into n_carre,
that is, n_carre = n*n.
By the way, remember that writing
the "equal to" sign here
means that we evaluate the expression
on the right
and copy it inside the variable, here, on the left.
Therefore, the variable n_carre,
will receive the value 4*4, that is, 16.
Now, let us move on
to the printing instructions.
First of all, we will print here : "la variable n contient"
(TN: "la variable n contient" means "the variable n contains")
then, we will print the expression
of the variable n, namely its value, 4;
then, we will print a period
and finally, here, we will generate
a line break thanks to this "endl".
Now, we move on to the next printing,
which will print :
"le carré de", n, which is an expression,
corresponding to the value 4 stored in the memory (TN: "le carré de" means "the square of"),
"est", n_carre, which is another expression, the value
of which in the memory is 16 (TN: "est" means "is"),
and finally a line break.
Now we can print the last message.
"le double de n est"
(TN: which means "twice as much as n is")
By the way, here n is a letter
included in the message,
therefore, it will be printed as such.
It is the word, the letter "n" which
will be printed here
and not an expression as it happened
on the previous line,
or as we could have here.
So, "le double de n est",
then the printing instruction 2*n.
Thus, we will search for the value of n, 4,
2*4, which, of course, will be evaluated to 8.
Therefore, 8 wil be printed here.
Then, we print the period
as a character
and finally we generate a line break.
A question now. Please look at
the following code
and tell us what it will print.
Here is the step by step answer.
First of all, we declare an
int-type variable a
initialized to the value 2.
Then, we declare an int-type variable b,
intialized to the value 1.
We then have the assignment here,
starting by evaluating the expression a*(b+2).
That is, two times the value of b (which
is 1) plus 2.
That is, 2 times 3.
This expression is copied
inside b, which is now 6.
Now, we print the value of a, "comma",
the value of b.
Another question :
What will this program print ?
Here is, again, the step by step
answer.
First of all, we declare a variable a
initialized to the value 1.
Then, we declare an int-type variable b
initialized to the value 2.
Then, we copy the value of b, inside a.
Therefore, a will be 2.
Then copy the value of a, which
has just been modified,
inside b. Therefore, b will
still be 2.
Finally, thus "2, 2" wil be printed.
A question we could ask
is how to swap the value
of two variables ?
Let us suppose that we have
a variable a, containing 1, initially
and a variable b, containing
2, initially.
How do we proceed so that,
after the swap,
a will contain 2, and
b will contain 1 ?
Let us suppose that we have
to deal with water glasses.
Let us suppose that we
have a glass a filled with grenadine
and glass b filled with mint.
How would you proceed in order
to transfer the mint into the glass a
and the grenadine into the glass b ?
The solution is, of
course, to resort to a third glass,
which we will call "tmp".
It is not any more
complicated for variables.
One simpy needs to introduce
an intermediate variable.
Let us do this. First of all, we will
create an intermediate variable "temp"
in which we will copy the value of a.
So, we will initialize temp
to the value of a.
Here, temp will thus be 1.
Then, we will copy b into a.
Finally, we will copy the value
of temp into b.
Now, let us move on to reading
of the value of variables
from the keyboard.
Let us go back to our example
program
and suppose that we do not only wish
to calculate the square of 4,
but wish to be able to enter
the value of n
through the keyboard, by asking
it to the user.
How would we do that ?
Why, we will simply add here, in the
program,
something letting the user enter
this value.
First of all, we will start by
printing a message :
"Entrez une valeur pour n : "
(TN: which means "enter a value for n:").
Then, thanks to this instruction
"cin redirected towards n",
we will be able to read the value of n
from the keyboard.
Thus, the reading from the keyboard
requires the instruction "cin".
"cin" representes the standard input device,
"in" as in "input";
this represents the reading
from the keyboard.
After the "cin", we see a sign similar
to the one used for printing;
the direction is reversed, though!
Here, the information goes from the
keyboard to the variable n;
this a good way to remember the
direction of this symbol.
Finally comes the name of the
variable inside which
we will store the value
read from the keyboard.
"cin" thus represents the keyboard
inside the memory, the program, of the computer.
The symbol here represents the fact
that we are going from "cin" to the memory,
then, the reading direction
and, then the name of the variable.
By the way, it is important to understand
that what follows the reading direction here,
is indeed the name of a variable.
It cannot be a message or
anything else.
This is rigorously forbidden.
If you want to print something,
you have to use the "cout" instruction.
You will begin by printing a message,
then a line break -it is optional-
and then, with a second instruction,
we will read from the
keyboard into the variable n.
The message will indeed be printed on
the terminal "cout" and not on the keyboard!
Meanwhile, the reading instruction is
indeed here, and contains the "cin" here.
By the way, it is possible to read
several variables successively,
one behind the others.
We simply need to add the reading
sign every time.
Here, it means :
"from cin, read n1, then read n2, then read n3."
Personally, we advise you to write
it in several clearly separated lines.
Thus writing : reading from "cin" into n1.
Then : reading from "cin" into n2.
Then : reading from "cin" into n3.
Mayhaps it is a little more tedious,
but we do believe that it
is clearer
at the beginning.
Now, let us examine our example
step by step.
We initially declared the variable n.
Then we print the question :
"enter a value for n : ".
This will result in the printing of this message.
Then, we will read from the keyboard.
Let us suppose that the user
types the value 2.
Thanks to this "cin into n" instruction,
the value 2, typed on the keyboard
will be stored inside the variable n, here.
Once this instruction has been
executed, the variable n
will contain the value
read from the keyboard.
From this point, the program will perform
exactly as before.
We declare the variable n_carre.
Then, we calculate n squared, n times n,
and assign it to the variable n_carre.
Then, we will proceed to the
printings, starting with :
"the variable n contains",then printing
the value of n,
which is 2, in our example.
And the program will resume exactly as before.