So far, we saw that every program
manipulates data
and that these data are stored in
so-called variables.
We also saw that in Java, every
variable
must be associated with a type,
which represents the kind of values
that we want to store in the
variable.
So far the types we had a
look at
are simple types, for example integers,
doubles or booleans,
that allow us to model data of
elementary types;
for example, dimensions, logical
expressions,
and similar things.
In many situations, it is
necessary
to represent more sophisticated data,
to manipulate sets of data as a whole.
This is the goal of this episode.
The objective of today's lectures is
to go beyond
simple types
such as integers, double, characters
or booleans
and to learn how to manipulate more
sophisticated data
by combining data of elementary types.
Generally speaking, in computer programming,
a structured, composed
or advanced data type will
essentially allow
to manipulate a set of data as
a whole.
For example, in a program,
if I need to model a set of
ages,
which is a set of homogeneous
data, integers in this case,
it is natural to think of something
that would look like
a table, an array of data that I
can manipulate as a whole.
I can also imagine sophisticated
representations of this nature
wherever the nature of data is heterogeneous,
like here for example,
a sequence of characters, a double
and an integer.
More simply, we can also
consider
that a sequence of characters is a
composed type,
as a sequence of characters is a
set of characters,
letting us manipulate a set of
characters as a whole.
Today, we are going to continue exploring
the building blocks
that allow us to build a program
in terms
of computations and data in Java.
Today we are mostly going to have
a look at
the data component and see how
it is possible to work
with arrays of data,
more precisely,
we'll work with fixed-size arrays
in today's episode.
To illustrate the use of arrays
in computer programming,
here's a small introductory example.
Imagine for example that you want to
write a small program
that manipulates players' scores.
Here, the goal is simply
to print the score of each player,
to compute the mean
of all the scores,
and to print the deviation from the mean
of every score.
We'll initially try to write a
Java program
capable of doing this computing, but
by using only
what we have learned so far,
that is data of elementary types.
To begin with, we won't be too
ambitious.
Let's imagine that we simply have
to represent two players.
So we have to model the scores of
two players,
which can be done by the
existing means
using two integer-type variables:
the variable score1 and the variable
score2.
We consider that in this program,
these values are obtained
through some keyboard interaction,
like here.
Once these values are obtained,
the computation of the mean can
simply be done
by summing the two scores and
dividing the sum by two.
We can then proceed to
printing the score and the deviation
from the mean
for each score. We here print
score1
and the deviation from the mean of
score1, and we do the same with score2.
A question that will naturally arise is
how do we proceed with more
players ?
Obviously, we'll have to add as many
variable as there are players
and typically, in the context of this
example with five players,
we would be obliged to
to declare five variables
"score",
one for every player, which is already
relatively laborious.
The computation of the mean becomes
more complex
as we now have to sum up the values
of five variables,
and also, how do we print the results?
For every score, we must repeat
the instruction line that prints
the score and the deviation from
the mean.
We'd like to get around this rather
laborious task,
repeating every instruction
and naturally we'll think of
using a loop.
How would we proceed if we
wanted to print the different
scores
and the deviations from the mean
using a loop?
A natural solution would be to use
a for-loop,
which would allow us to iterate
over every score
and for every score to print what
is needed.
We can therefore imagine writing
the loop in this spirit.
We'd have a counter which would iterate
from the first score to the last one
and for every score, we would print
what is needed.
However, if we examine this program
in more detail,
the for-loop and even the entire
program,
we realize
that this approach doesn't meet
all the needs we can consider in
this context
in a completely satisfactory way.
Let's imagine fore example that
I want
to have more than 5 players,
like 100 or 1000.
In this case the program would take
unmanageable dimensions,
we'd for example have to introduce
thousands of variables,
complicate the computation of the mean.
Furthermore, if we have a look at the way
we wrote the score here
to access the i-th score of the
sequence:
in fact, this is not a valid Java syntax
to designate the i-th element
of a sequence.
And final point, our approach
doesn't satisfactorily respond to
the situation where the number of
players isn't initially known.
So if we want to write a program
of this nature,
the tools that we have at our disposal
so far
don't satisfactorily respond to our
needs in this context.
"Arrays" are the solution to this.
To give you a concrete idea of what
the notion of array is,
here's how the previous program would
be written using that concept.
So the idea would be to use a new
type of data,
the type "array of integers", of which
we'll see the syntax
more in detail later in this video.
Primarily, when declaring an
array,
we can manipulate a sequence of data
as a whole,
and access the i-th element of the
sequence by using indexation.
So we can see that the previous
program
can be written more concisely,
in particular we can manage the
part that reads the scores
in a unified way with a
for-loop.
Then, whatever the number
of scores,
we'll write the program the
same way,
whether we have 5 or 1000
players
and we can now also manage
the case
when the number of players isn't
initially known
and therefore read the number of scores
before executing the computation
that we want to do on the scores.
In computer programming, an array is
a type of data that allows us
to manipulate a collection of homogeneous
values as a whole.
In an array, values are all of the
same type.
Here you have an example
representing an array of integers.
All the values contained in the
array score are of 'int' type.
Of course, in Java we can define
arrays
of any known type, arrays of integers,
doubles, chars
and any other known type, including
arrays of arrays.
Generally, in computer programming,
we can consider
that there exists four types of arrays,
depending on the answers to the
following questions.
First question: is the array's size
initially known?
That is, when I begin writing my
program
do I know which size the array has,
or don't I (know which size the
array has)?
We can have two possible answers to
that question.
Then, second question: can the size
vary
while using the array?
That is, once I've set a size to
my array,
can I vary that size
while the program runs
or will that size be fixed
once and for all?
The type of array that is the more
flexible, the more general,
and that responds to as many needs as
possible is certainly
the one that has this configuration,
an array whose initial size isn't
known
when I write the program.
We can set that size when
the program executes, but I don't
know it
when I'm writing the program and
this size can also vary
while the program runs.
For example, let's imagine that I
want to write a program
that manages the ages of the people
registered to this course.
That number isn't known when I
write the program
but will be determined when I
start
the execution of the program with the
effective number of registered people
that I get at that moment, and we can
imagine that during the execution,
I have new registrations, so the
array's size will grow.
I can also imagine that people
will
unsubscribe from the course,
in which case
the array's size will decrease.
At the other extreme, there exists
arrays
the size of which is known when I
write the program
and whose size isn't
going to change
during the execution of the program;
so this configuration here.
For example, if I want to write a program
that manipulates
two-dimensional vectors,
so I know that my vector has
2 dimensions;
it has two components and no more.
So, a component for X and
a component for Y
and I know that a two-dimensional vector
will remain a two-dimensional vector
during the whole program's
execution
and therefore it's size won't change
while I run the program.
Intermediate situation: the case where
an array has a size
which isn't known when I write
the program,
but once that size is set, it
doesn't change anymore
during the program's execution, so
this case here.
We can for example imagine that
I'm writing a game
which is played by 2 to 7
players.
When I execute the program, I
don't know
exactly how many players are going to
be in the game.
So when the program starts
it will ask how many players
there are.
For example, there're 5.
Once these 5 players are in
the game,
it must take place with the 5 players
and no more.
The array's size isn't going to
evolve
while the program runs.
Last case finally, maybe more
difficult to illustrate,
a bit less intuitive: the case where
the array's size
is known when I write the
program
and can vary while the program
executes.
For example, I want to represent the number
of "cantons" [= districts, provinces] of a country.
This number of cantons is set, it
is known a priori.
So when I write the program,
I know for example that there are 26 of them.
[TN: this is the case in Switzerland]
We can also imagine that at a
given moment
a new canton is created in the
country
or that two cantons merge
into one.
So the array's size will increase or
decrease
while the program runs.
This last case is probably the
least natural
and the least frequent in practice.
Most programming languages don't
offer any specific tools,
dedicated to the management of each
case presented here.
For example, in Java we mainly dispose
of two tools,
the one that allows us to manage
dynamic size's arrays.
Here for example, with the use of
a predefined type
of Java called "ArrayList",
which responds to the needs of
situations number 1 and 2.
And then arrays of fixed size,
on which we will focus in the context
of today's videos,
and which respond to the needs of
situations number 3 and 4.