We now know how to declare and
initialize a fixed-size array.
We'll have a look at the different
classical manipulations
that we can do on such arrays.
First manipulation: printing an array.
Let's imagine for example that we
have declared and initialized
an array t1 this way.
We'll have the following situation
in memory:
In the variable t1, we have a reference,
an address to the array.
The array is initialized in this manner.
Now let's suppose that I want to print
the array by simply using
an instruction line like this one.
I pass as argument to
System.out.println,
the array t1 that I want to print.
Here, I'm going to print the
content of t1
which is a reference.
This will translate into printing
something a little strange
which will look like this.
Something like fe25235d, which will
correspond to something
that is a reference to an array,
something not very understandable.
In reality, what we want to do is
printing the content of the array.
To achieve this, we have no other choice
than to provide a loop to iterate
over each element of the array, and
print them one by one.
Let's suppose that we want to print
each element of an array.
Let's imagine that this array has initially
been declared this way.
It's an array of integers.
How do we iterate over such an array
to print each cell?
Well, we've got two conventional
solutions.
The first is what is called "iteration over a set of values"
and which will be written like this.
The reserved word for and the array's
values's type in parenthesis,
which obviously has to be of the same
type as what we specified here.
We then have to give a variable
name
that will allow us to designate
an array's cell.
Then, after a colon, we must indicate
the array
over which we want to iterate.
After that, to print the current cell,
we just have to
write this sort of instruction line.
In fact, val will take each element of the
array turn by turn
and we'll print them in sequence
one after the other
with this iteration over the set
of values.
The even more standard solution
is to use a for
as we know it so far.
A for that uses an index, which will
go from 0
to the array's size.
Here, this way of specifying the size
isn't great
because it is uncorrelated to
the array itself.
We have hard coded the value 3.
The question of how to specify this size
in a cleaner way will arise.
We'll see that later.
So we move on with our index to
iterate over every cell of the array.
We access the arrays' cells with
the indexation mechanism.
To sum up, if we wish to iterate over
each value of an array
we dispose of tools such as
the iterations over a set of values.
We have just seen a concrete example
of it.
We can also use a standard for
iteration.
At that moment, the problem of
the computation of
the array's size arises,
which we'll see further.
In reality there exists a third way
of iterating over an array,
the one that uses the notion
of iterator.
But this notion isn't presented in
the context of this course.
Let's come back to the question at hand
concerning standard iterations:
how can we specify the size of
a fixed-size array?
How can we recover this size?
In Java, it is possible to get get
the size of an array
from it's name.
To achieve this it is necessary to
resort to a particular notation.
This notation is the following:
I use the array's name, followed
by a point,
followed by the reserved word
'length'.
Here's a concrete example:
I declare/initialize an array scores
that contains four elements.
If I want to print the array's
size,
I just have to resort to the notation
I've just described.
So the array's name, followed by a
point, followed by 'length'
which will, here, obviously, print 4.
An analogous example here, with an array
of booleans with two entries.
It is important to note here that length
will always give you
the possible number of elements
and that the effective number of
filled cells isn't important.
The fact that you explicitly put values
or not
isn't taken into account.
Here's a concrete example:
Here we declare an array without
initializing it
with concrete, effective values.
Neither with an assignment of
this type,
nor with the assignment of a global
array with a certain number of elements.
I haven't put any explicit values
in my array.
However, if I print the
array's size,
I get 2 indeed. Why?
Because here, when I construct
the array,
I allocate a size of 2 to it.
Which means that I'll have this
situation in memory.
The variable score is a reference to
an array with two entries.
And we know that by default, these
entries are initialzed with 0 for integers.
So we are effectively dealing with a
fixed-size array,
containing two entries.
length will give us this size.
No matter whether we initialized it with
explicit values or not.
We were interested in how to iterate
over the entire set of values of an array.
We saw that it is possible to do it
with a standard for-loop
which lead us to discuss about
the problem
of the computation of the array's
size.
But before concluding the chapter on
iterations
let's come back to the other type
of iteration,
the for-loops allow us to iterate
over a set of values.
We saw that this kind of for-loops
are written like this.
We can easily see that it's
a very simple and elegant
way of iterating.
We don't even have to worry about
the array's size.
However, there exists a certain
number of limitations
to this for-loop that we don't encounter
with the standard iteration
and which are the following.
First limitation:
an iteration on a set of values won't
allow us to modify
the content of the array.
So here, if I have declared/initialized
an array this way
and that I want to iterate over
this array
with an iteration over a set
of values.
The fact of writing something
like this,
won't allow us to modify the content
of the array.
I can't modify the array
by using a notation of
this kind.
Second limitation: I can iterate
over one array at a time.
So I can iterate over only one
array.
Here, a notation of this kind
doesn't exist.
If we want, for example, to
iterate over two arrays at the
same time,
with such a notation.
To compare the values of the
first array
with the values of the second array,
this doesn't exist.
We won't be able, with an iteration
over a set of values
to proceed to the simultaneous
iteration of the two arrays.
Third limitation:
With the variable val, with the iteration
over a set of values, I can
only access one element at a time.
For example, it won't be possible
to compare
an element of the array with the one
following it.
With val, I can access one element
at a time.
Finally, last limitation:
I can iterate one step
at a time only.
For example, if I want to jump
two by two in the array,
this isn't possible with an iteration over
a set of values.
Note that the standard iterations don't
have any of these limitations.
It is possible to do everything with
a standard for iteration.
Manipulating arrays requires taking
a number of precautions.
You should pay attention to a
number of aspects
to not cause any errors.
Errors either during the compilation,
or during the program's execution.
Errors we'll encounter while learning
about arrays,
are errors on indexes or access
errors
before the array's construction.
There exists other types of errors
which are related
to the object-oriented
programming aspect
which will be presented in an upcoming
course on object-oriented Java.
Concerning the index problems, there
are two things to be observed.
The first is that the index of an array
must imperatively be of int type.
That's an integer.
You must absolutely respect the array's
bounds, which are between
0 and T-1, where T is the
array's size.
Here, I declare and construct an array
of size 250.
I commit a first error here, by trying
to use an index
that isn't of int type.
So it's an error on the index type.
Here I commit a second error by
trying to use an index
that is outside the array's bounds.
So it's an error on the bounds.
Likewise, an error on the bounds, here.
We know that an array of 250 element
has indexes going from 0 to 249.
If I use the index 250, I overflow.
I am not in the array's bounds.
In this case, I also have a
error on the bounds.
Note that the first type of error is
an error that will be detectable
by the compiler, so when I compile
the program.
Contrariwise, the other errors
are errors that will only be
detected during the program's
execution.
Of course in practice, we won't
commit
this kind of error in such
explicit ways.
Often, it's if we get the indexes
through a computation,
and that our computation is wrong, that
we'll end up with this kind of error.
In general, we won't commit them
in such explicit ways.
Another classical error: the access
before construction.
In Java, if we want to access an
array's element through indexation,
it is imperative that the array has
been constructed beforehand.
An array's construction can be done,
for example,
by directly indicating the values when
declaring the array.
What can be seen here, with
this instruction line.
When I declare my array, I put a number
of values into it,
explicitly, with an assignment of
this nature.
So obviously, here, the element of index 0
really exists.
It is possible to access it, it is entirely
licit to proceed to this kind of access
with the array's cell of index 0.
Contrariwise, here, I have a
slightly different situation.
I declare the array but I don't
construct the array,
I don't assign initial values with an
assignment of this nature to it,
no more than I construct the array with
this second type of instruction lines,
which allows me to give an initial
size to it and allocate
a number of cells to this array.
As I don't resort to this possibility, nor
this possibility, nor this one,
the access to a cell of the array
is impossible.
So here I would have an error.
So what's missing with this
instruction line
is having built the array beforehand,
which I can do
with a trick of this nature.
At that moment, the problem is
resolved
and I don't have problems of access
before construction anymore.