We'll now see what an assignment
means
when used with arrays.
To achieve this, it is necessary to
come back on our discussion
comparing the basic types and the
advanced types in Java.
Let's assume that we have two
variables a and b, of
sometimes basic types,
for example here a and b are integers,
and sometimes advanced
types; there we'll suppose
that a and b are arrays.
What will writing a = b mean in
both cases?
Here we imagine, for example, that
b initially contains 2,
and that there, b initially contains
a reference to an array.
So if I execute an assignment
in the case of basic types,
I find myself in the situation where a
eventually contains the same value as b.
It's the same in this case there:
if I execute this instruction line,
I'll copy in a the same value as b,
that is a reference to the same array,
in our case.
For a basic type, doing this
assignment
doesn't introduce any particular
relation between "a" and "b".
For example, if I decide afterwards to
modify "a" with an assignment
such as this one, this obviously
doesn't have any incidence on "b".
A different situation arises
for arrays containing the referenced
object.
When I achieve this kind of assignment,
it becomes possible to modify
the array referenced both by
"a" and "b".
Which means that if I write here
a[0] = 300,
b[0] will also have the value 300.
So, in the case of basic types, there's
a true autonomy
between the two objects, the
modification of one of the objects
has absolutely no incidence
on the other one.
On the other side, when I do an
assignment on objects
such as arrays, there'll be
a dependency
relative to the referenced object.
The message here is that, unlike
basic types,
to do an assignment between two
variables of array type creates
a dependancy between these
two objects.
Here, we begin with a situation where
we initially have two completely
distinct arrays, which are autonomous in
memory, so a first variable "a"
that contains a reference to the
10-cell array,
and a second variable "b" that
contains a reference
to a second array with 10 cells,
initially completely autonmous.
So we begin by filling the array "a",
simply
with a for-loop, by putting in each
cell the same values
as the indexes. So we end up with
this situation in memory;
and we execute our much vaunted
assignment of "a" into "b".
So with this assignment, we'll put
in "b" the same address
than the one in "a", which means that
now on "b"
will point to this array.
This relation is broken, these memory
locations aren't accessible anymore.
And here, if I modify the third entry
of the array via "a",
I see that the same array's entry
accessed via "b" is also modified.
We therefore see that the assignment
of two arrays with =
only makes sense if we want
to have
two different names for a
same array,
which is relatevly rare.
In the most general case, with an
assignment we want
to ensure that each cell of the array "b"
is put in corresponding
cells of the array "a", while
ensuring that
both array keeps their autonomy.
For such a situationt, it is better to
proceed with a loop,
which will allow us to copy each
value from the first array's cells
to the corresponding cells of the second
array,
paying attention to stay between the
licit bounds!
So if, for example, we choose as
break condition the size of the
array "a", well, in order for this loop
to not commit any error,
it will be necessary for the size of "b"
to be at least equal to the size of "a";
otherwise we'd have to formulate
the break condition
in a slightly different manner.
You can now easily understand that
the fact that arrays in Java
are manipulated through references
also has
an impact on the semantic of the
'==' comparison operator.
If "a" and "b" are two arrays,
comparing them with ==
will, of course, compare the
references, and not
the content of the arrays.
So here I'm in the situation where
I have "a", which is an array,
so it contains a reference to the
array, and same for "b";
so a == b will return true only if
the same reference is effectively
contained in the two objects "a" and "b";
when they both point to the same
memory address,
which is obviously the case when
I've done an assignment of this
kind beforehand.
So the == operator applied to arrays
doesn't test the equality
of the content of the arrays pointed
by "a" and "b".
If we want to compare the contents,
we must, like before
for the assignment, proceed
with an iteration.
So if we rather want to compare the
content of the two arrays,
we'll have to write a number of
instruction lines to test
if it's the case or not.
We can for example begin by
testing if the arrays
have the same size; if it's not
the case,
we are sure that the content
isn't the same.
We'll usually also take the
precaution
of comparing the arrays with the
special reference,
the reserved word
"null". "null" is a special
value that can be assigned
to an array and that indicates that the
array doesn't reference anything.
We usually take this precaution too.
So if the arrays don't reference anything,
or if they're of different sizes,
then we can immediately say that
their content is different.
Otherwise, we can suppose that their
content is possibly the same,
but we'll have to test it, and we'll have
to iterate over the entire
array and test cell by cell if the
content of the two are identic.
If we exit the loop because of
the first condition,
it means that we've iterated over
the entire array
and that the condition was always
true cell by cell,
so we can assert that the
contents were the same.
Otherwise, well we're in the situation
where the contents are different.
To conclude this presentation about
fixed-size arrays in Java,
here are a few simple examples of
standard routine manipulations,
like for example printing the content
of an array or inputing
the content of an array.
We suppose here that we have initially
declared a variable "table" that can
contain a number of double-type values.
We also suppose that, later, the
program took care of filling
the array with values that we consider
as appropriate, for example
with assignments of this nature, and
we want to print
the content of the array.
To achieve that, it is necessary to
resort to iterations, for-loops,
which will allow us to iterate over the entire
set of values of an array and print them
one by one. The type of for-loop to choose,
we saw that there exists two of them,
will in fact depend of the situation:
will we need to explicit
the indexes or not. In the case where
it is not necessary
to explicit the indexes, we can
use a for-loop
of type "iteration on a set of values".
We saw that for this kind of
for-loop, we must declare
a variable of the same type as
the array's elements.
This variable will alternately take
the different values of the array
and we'll be able to print them
simply like this.
Contrariwise, if we need to explicit
the indexes, then we'll resort to
a standard for-loop, and at that moment
we have to declare an index
that will vary from zero to the
array's size.
We saw that the array's size
is expressed by
this particular notation. Knowing
that the array's indexes
go from zero to size-1, we'll have
to take the precaution
of stopping just before the array's
size, and of course, we'll have
to move the index forward while we
progress in the array.
So at that moment, we can
print both the index,
as it is explicit, and the corresponding
value.
Second example, the input of the
array's elements
with a keyboard interaction. We saw
that the range for-loop (iteration
on a set of values) doesn't allow us
to modify the content of the array.
So for this we don't have a choice,
it is absolutely essential to explicit
the indexes in Java.
Here, we'll therefore resort to a
standard for-loop,
iterating, like before, from zero
to the array's size
and stopping one index before, to
avoid overflow,
and at that moment we can input
each value of the array separately
with a standard keyboard input, as
we have already
done previously.