The fixed-size arrays
we were interested by until now
were uni-dimensional arrays.
They allowed us to store simple
sequences of values.
In some situations,
it is necessary to resort to arrays
that have greater dimensions.
Let's illustrate this with a concrete
example.
Let's assume for example that
I want to store
the different grades obtained at the
different written assignments
in the context of this course for a
single student.
So here, I can use a one-dimensional array that
I would name "notes" [= "grades"] and that would
contain, for each of its entries, a grade
of one written assignment.
So here we would have the grade of the
assignment 0, so the first assignment.
here we would have the grade of the
assignment 1, etc.
So here I manage to count in a
satisfactory way,
the grades of a single student to the different
assignments that he accomplished
in the context of this course.
Now let's assume that I want to
take into account
not only the grades of a single student
but of all the students following
the course.
At that moment, I would need to use a
two-dimensional array here,
where the first dimension, which is the
lines here,
would correspond to a student.
So here I would have the first student
of the course.
And every column would in fact
represent all the grades
obtained for one given assignments by
all the students.
So here for example, I would have
the grades for the first assignment,
and here the grade of the
last assignment.
So here I see that I need to resort to
a more complex
data structure, a two-dimensional
array
where the lines correspond to
the students
and the columns correspond
to the assignments.
Multidimensional arrays
correspond exactly to this need.
In Java, a two-dimensional fixed-size array
is no more than an array of arrays.
In reality, it's a little more complex
than that
because we know that in Java,
arrays are manipulated through
references.
So the more correct diagram
would be something
looking like this: in every cell,
we have a reference to an array.
So the diagram you have here
in front of you
corresponds in fact to a structure that
looks like this in Java.
It's indeed an array of arrays.
Concerning the syntax, adding a
supplenmntary dimension
to an array in Java is simply
equivalent to adding
another level of brackets.
Here you have two concrete
examples.
Now let's have a better look
at one of these examples.
Here, I declare a two-dimensional
array, I have two levels of brackets,
which homogeneously contains integers
and which is named "score".
It's a two-dimensional array,
so I'll initialize it with a construction
that is analogous to
what I know concerning one-
dimensional arrays.
Here I have a number of lines,
which corresponds to a number of players,
say for example
that I have no more than 3 players
by which I am interested.
And regarding columns; a given number
of columns
which correspond to a number
of games played by the players.
So let's say, for example, that I
have no more than 4.
The purpose of the array "score"
is to count
the score obtained at every game
by each player.
So concretely, what structure
am I going to have
after such a declaration?
Well here I declared an array
with 3 entries,
which translates into this,
so every entry is itself an array with 4 entries;
which can schematically translate
into this.
So here, for the entry "i", I have
an array
that can contain at most 4 entries,
and each entry corresponds to
a score.
So this allows me to record the
score obtained at every game
for every player.
So if I want to access the i-th player,
I iterate over the first dimension.
Once I accessed this dimension,
I can access the second dimension
which will give me the different
scores obtained
at the different games.
So schematically, I can represent this
with a two-dimensional array,
So here I'd have an array with 3 lines
and 4 columns.
So every line "i" corresponds to
a player,
and this would be the line of
the player i.
And each column "j" corresponds
in reality
to all the scores for the game j.
So if I want to know the score
obtained by the player i
when he played the game j,
I need to access this cell of
the two-dimensional array.
The score for each game are in
reality integers,
which explains why I declared my
two-dimensional array
as an array of integers.
If I know all the array's values
when I'm declaring it,
it's possible to initialize it
at the time of declaration with a
trick of this nature
that looks a lot like what we did
for unidimensional arrays.
Of course, you need to specify as many
values a there are dimensions,
and that is for each dimension.
What you are looking at corresponds
to an array with 4 lines.
And we can see that every line
corresponds to an array,
and that the number of columns
isn't necessarily the same, in Java,
for each line.
So we can absolutely construct
an array that looks like this,
where we have a different number of
columns for each line.
We see indeed that we are
dealing with
an array of arrays.
Each individual entry of the
first array
corresponds to an array.
The indexation mechanism that
allows me to access
the different values of the array
has the exact same signification as
the uni-dimensional arrays.
Here for example, if I access
"array of [2]",
I'm trying to access the elements of
the first level of this array.
So here, knowing that the elements
are numbered from 0 to "size - 1",
here I have the element of index 0, of
index 1, of index 2,
so when I access the element of
index 2,
I'm precisely getting this array, which I
can find again here.
So knowing that "array[2]" is itself and array,
I can now access its j-th cell with
the second index.
So here, knowing that the indexes
are once again numbered
from 0 to "size - 1", the element
of index 1 will be this one;
which corresponds to this in the
diagram,
and to this element in my
declaration/initialization.
So to sum up the discussion we
have just had,
if we know what elements to put in
the array beforehand,
when we declare it,
it is possible to initialize it
like this.
What we saw in the previous
example,
is that the elements of the first
dimension
are all arrays.
In this instance, they're arrays
of integer values.
So concretely, in the example you
are looking at,
you have an array of 3 arrays:
y[0], y[1], y[2].
The array y[0] is this array.
The array y[2] is this last array.
To access the elements of the
second dimension,
I add a level of brackets,
and obviously, at that moment, the
accessed value
is an integer and not an array
anymore.
For example, if I want to access
this element "y[1][1]",
I first have to get the array y[1],
which is this one,
then I access the element of
index 1, which is this one,
so here I get the value 4.
In the most general case, when we
know the
values to put in the array
beforehand,
we'll simply reserve the necessary
memory locations when initializing,
like in the uni-dimensional array case.
So concretely, here, we'll end up
with the construction of an array
that contains 3 lines and each line
contains 2 elements,
that's the structure we'll end up with
in memoery.
And we saw that there exists
default values
for the initialization of these
values in Java.
So the values are the same as
for the uni-dimensional arrays,
so here I'll have zeroes everywhere,
as they're integers.
Then we need to proceed with an
ad-hoc, manual, filling.
Here I do it very explicitly by
accessing cell by cell
and by putting a value into it,
so here I'll put 1 and I'll put 2
here, and so one.
And we can of course imagine that
it's very fastidious
to proceed like this if we have very
large arrays;
which naturally makes us think
about loops
and the notion of iteration.
How would we proceed if we want to iterate
over a two-dimensional array, or more?
The most natural way to iterate
over a two-dimensional array
is to nest two for-loops.
The first for-loop will allow us
to iterate over
the entire set of lines of the array,
so concretely, here, would allow
us to iterate
over each of these lines, so
to iterate
over each of these lines alterantely.
The second index, the second
loop,
will allow us to iterate over all the
colzumns of each line.
So here, for each line,
we want to iterate over each
column.
That's why the two loops are
in reality nested.
It's because for each "i",
we want to iterate over all
the possible "j"s.
Notice especialy the looping conditions.
So the number of lines
obviously stops
at "array's size - 1", which corresponds
to this notation.
And the second loop condition
corresponds to the size of the entry "i"
of the array, which correponds to
this notation.
You now know the essential
about fixed-size arrays in Java.
We studied the cases of uni-dimensional
arrays, and two-dimenisonal arrays.
It is of course possible to
go beyond
and have arrays of even bigger
dimensions,
even if we rarely go over 4 in practice.
The use stays exactly the same as
for two-dimensional arrays.
To complete our study of arrays, we still have to
see, in a following episode,
the case of dynamic arrays,
which we'll present shortly.