Hello.
We are going to talk about
Land Use Planning Tools, more precisely,
urban development operations.
So before reviewing
the various operations,
they serve above all
to maintain or welcome
new residents and new activities.
So it's the objective of the game of
an urban operation and also,
these urban operations help us to put in
facilities and infrastructure.
Thirdly, it also serves the purpose of
preserving the heritage,
or to showcase it.
So there are different types of
development operations,
urban restructuring, urban renovation,
housing operations,
integrated land use planning operations,
major infrastructure projects, and
finally, large housing programs.
Urban renovation, these are land use
planning actions in sectors
which are unregulated sectors, on sectors
which are extremely deteriorated.
The most concrete example is
the slum, the restructuring of slums.
So in general, the aim is the improvement
of living conditions
and this goes through a number
of things, that may be in particular,
real estate,
water supply, so the infrastructures
and services.
It's generally this we're going to
work on,
real estate, infrastructures and services.
Urban renovation is the action of
land use planning
on a substandard sector,
but it's eventually
its total or partial destruction in any case
and its reconstruction.
So, in the renovation, we were working on
what was existing,
here we destroy it to make something else.
Housing or large framework operations,
next week, we'll see a whole
course series on how to
make a subdivision,
but it's really urban expansion
that we're talking about.
On greenfield land, we are going to create
a number of subdivisions
which are lots where there will be parcels
where people will be able to come settle.
It's without a doubt the urban operation
which is the most current today
in African cities.
It's the least mediatised.
Rather we're going to talk about renovation
or urban restructuring,
but in terms of number of people
who are going to settle,
in terms of surface area, these are
the subdivisions
and the large frameworks which are
the majority in African cities.
The African city today grows
thanks to these subdivisions.
And all of the programs which are
good things,
the restructuring of neighborhoods that
are unstable is only
a small part of the problem.
The big problem, we have had
the statistics,
this volume of urban people that will come
in the next 10 years in the African cities,
they will settle in the outskirts, mostly
in the subdivisions.
So the concern of the subdivision in
the African city today is essential.
There also exist the districts
of special planning.
So generally it's when we have
a property issue.
This is both the State and
the property owner who is a private entity
who play planner.
There is a dialogue between two
to put land on the market.
It's generally when there are lands
which are claimed by the customs who made
this type of planning, where a part
goes back
to customs and another is
placed on the market.
It's a tool that is known in France,
a tool which
is not used in all countries and which
is relatively little used in Africa.
But we need to know that this tool
clearly exists
and that it's one of the possibilities
to do the planning with this strategy.
The big infrastructure projects, therefore
the most classical, are water
electricity, but also
transport networks,
large transport infrastructures: roads,
highways or public transport.
This gives the city a superstructure.
but the effect on the neighborhoods
is quite visible.
When you draw a highway
in a neighborhood
inevitably, we will separate
the neighborhood in two.
But it's generally projects which are
structuring for the city.
So the impact of infrastructure is huge,
both in macro terms
for the whole city, as well as micro terms
in the neighborhood.
So we really must pay attention to
these large infrastructure projects, and
and we must do so very clearly,
in an organized manner to know
how we are going to succeed
in integrating the new infrastructures
in the city.
How we are going to succeed in integrating
them but also
what are we going to get out of it,
because the objective is to be able
to use the structuring effect of
the infrastructure to drive
urban development.
Finally, the large housing projects.
We are straddling urban
development operations
and public policy, urban policy.
In general, the objective is to offer
a roof to the greatest number.
So we are going to make housing programs,
and we can be dealing with
specific parcels, some parcels,
or on the contrary with the whole city.
Here we are dealing more with,
no longer land use planning
but public policy.
The large housing programs,
they have had
hour of glory some decades ago.
Donors, including World Bank
have invested heavily
housing before completely stopping
and doing only the stable parcel.
Today we are slowly coming back
to these large housing programs
because we realize that beyond property,
we must also give a roof to the most
vulnerable populations,
and it's through these large housing
programs that it will happen.
So there is a consequence to all of this.
When there are the big events,
let's say, Brazil, in Rio
in particular, with the World Cup and
the Olympic games that will follow.
But also, when we create
large infrastructures.
When we create these
large infrastructures,
this creates, or we want to
create property appreciation,
or we do urban renovation,
all these phenomenons have a
common point, these are the evictions.
This means that to build a new stadium
in Pekin, thousands of people
had to be displaced.
In order to build a highway in Dhakar,
it wasn't thousands but rather hundreds
of people that had to be displaced,
since they had
their housing exactly on
the highway layout.
This means that when we put in place
an infrastructure, this creates
property appreciation.
The more public transportation
in the center
of cities, the more the property price
will increase
and the more the poorest populations
will no longer have
the means to pay their rent
that will have increased.
So the property appreciation,
the mechanisms that
are behind this eventually
create evictions.
So in the first case mentioned,
it is the State who is going to
displace the people, they're going to
take them and displace them.
In the case of the property appreciation,
it is not necessarily in the same case.
It is the market which, in the end,
will make it so that people
are going to have leave by themselves,
but it's also a case of eviction.
The last case, urban renovaction.
We easily understand that in
urban renovation, there is
a part which is destroyed in order to be
rebuilt, and often,
it is not built by the same standards,
by the same norms,
and the housing size is increased,
the construction standards.
So that they are not the same populations
who used to live there
before and who will be able to live there
after, and this creates evictions.
There you have a quick description of
some of the most classical urban
development operations, with their
consequences always being evictions.
So it's important to question before
creating these large operations,
what this means
in human cost, in evictions, to know if
you are going to displace
many people or not.
Zero eviction is rarely possible,
but we should,
little by little, extend towards
this objective.
There is sometimes the impossibility
of extending towards this objective,
since we have to, for the whole city,
and all of the people, carry out
a number of infrastructures
in particular and we cannot simply
avoid the dwellings.
However between, I'm going to
displace everyone
and no one, there must be
a way which is
the best possible for all of the residents
of the city and above all
for the residents of neighborhoods which
are supposed to be the ones displaced.