Today we'll look at
the question of diagnosis.
Diagnosis is a term borrowed from
the medical profession.
To diagnose is to perform the necessary
analyses to diagnose an illness.
In other words to find out what
problems the patient has,
in order to come up with
the appropriate treatment.
By analogy, it is the same situation
for territorial diagnostics.
What we want to know is
what the problem is,
the state of the patient
for as long as he is ill.
And this is what we'll examine
in the following minutes.
Diagnostics brings up, above all,
two questions.
The first is why of diagnostics.
What are its reasons and what are
the questions it answers?
It is critical to know how to respond
to each question.
We should not perform diagnostics
for the sake of performing diagnostics,
run the numbers for the sake
of running the numbers
or to have an encyclopedic
knowledge of a territory.
We must respond to
the questions which arise.
Next, the important question of how.
What are the means and
the approaches necessary?
These are the two questions
which will guide our diagnosis.
Here's a very classic way to diagnose.
We have our assets,
and we evaluate the present and past
dynamics of the territory.
These can be economic, social,
environmental or architectural.
but we look at the presence or absence
of certain problems or certain resources
which are considered to be
the assets of a territory.
We try to understand the system's
ability to function,
and determine if, in its present state,
it will enable us reach our goals.
By analogy its weaknesses,
which is the opposite.
This is the evaluation of present
and past dynamics, as with assets,
but this time we'll instead focus first
on what's not working in the system.
This time we look at the possible
developments of the territory,
so we're looking ahead.
We are symmetric with its assets,
both present and past.
With opportunities, it's the same idea
of their effect on the system,
but from a perspective and by analogy,
of course, of possible threats.
So we have here the past and
the present, here looking ahead.
Here we are with the positives,
and here, with weaknesses and threats,
in the negative.
So here you have the grid for analysis,
the initial framework.
These are the questions we'll ask
for a holistic diagnosis.
A method of diagnosis
by no means exhaustive.
We have questions of institution,
demographics, urban context,
roadways, water, lighting,
and surely others,
here, without at doubt also
the most important.
Why? Because we will try to offer
a vision of the city,
of its past as well as its present.
We'll highlight some of its weaknesses,
but also some of its strengths.
Because of this we are, at the same time,
on political and institutional levels,
as with questions of resources or other
more complex issues of social context.
Let's look at this example.
The economic zone of a city,
of Nouakchott.
Each zone where there is
economic potential is indexed.
We'll soon see what becomes of it.
It is not simply because
we've identified a zone
that it becomes useful for our planning,
but it gives us an idea of where
economic activity occurs within a city.
Administrative questions,
we're going to divide it up.
We know that the city is divided into
a certain number of municipalities,
and we'll have the statistics
for each municipality.
This is always where the difficulty lies.
If we plan for the whole
of the urban perimeter,
we still have subdivisions, whether by
community or municipality.
as a function of the cities
they form part of.
Another critical element is that of
primary water resources.
Right away we notice a deficit here,
another large deficit in these zones,
where there are few resources,
This x-ray of primary water resources
gives us a quick view
of where the major problems lie
when it comes to water supply.
The stages of expansion.
This helps us to understand
how the city was developed,
with indicators of each stage.
We see that the initial nucleus was here,
and how the city developed from it,
with indications of the time periods
during which this or that policy
was put in place regarding
the use of the territory.
Existing subdivisions.
We discussed earlier land issues,
which are crucial here.
Which is to say that all these
indexed zones are subdivisions
which were offered or sold,
yet were not developed.
In other words, all of these parcels
are occupied.
Which means that the city perimeter
extends more or less to this point,
and if today we want to develop a plan,
all this zone is already occupied,
even if in fact it is not,
so our plan must begin a bit further out.
A map such as this one offers
a quick view of land issues.
Another map, this one
of urban public transport.
This might be independent transport,
or official transport by bus.
Here were are perhaps dealing
more with small-scale transport,
but we see the breakdown
of lines and stations.
Roadways, both existing and also those,
within the diagnosis, already planned,
since we're not just planning, but also
dealing with ongoing projects
which take place over
the next few months or years,
which are already "in the pipeline",
which means they will happen.
We can, then, consider them
as already existing.
Densities. If we have a subsequent
policy for land density,
we need to know how we might apply
this policy, in which neighborhood,
know which neighborhoods are densest.
We can easily see here that the densest
neighborhoods are the poorer districts,
with shantytowns here, and here, so we're
dealing with extremely dense areas,
with between 350-450 inhabitants
per hectare.
We see, when we superimpose
these different maps, different resources,
an idea of where the problems
might occur, and what they might be.
If we look at the map of water supply,
we can see that this zone here
is particularly problematic,
because it is extremely dense
yet has a scant water supply.
Constraints, pressures,
and environmental potential.
In the case of Nouakchott,
we have here these huge dunes,
one of which protects from the ocean,
and these areas of dry salt lakes,
which are below sea level.
This gives us a snapshot of the situation
as it exists today in Nouakchott,
where a breach of the dune ridge
would lead to the flooding of this zone,
and we see that this urban planning is,
ultimately, dependent on
the stability or instability
of these large dunes.
Land use.
A supplemental map showing
habitat zones, green spaces,
the few industrial zones which exist,
and, finally, a summary of the questions,
with a few problems here, others here.
This map tries, although doesn't
necessarily succeed, but at least tries,
to illustrate the issues
behind this diagnosis.
Quickly, another example,
that of N'djamena,
a city, like Nouakchott, of fewer than
one million inhabitants.
We have, of course, on this summary map
all the problems, the potentialities,
of the city of N'djamena.
The most important thing is,
of course, the map,
but let's not forget that we also
need a legend, for without it
we wouldn't know to what the colors
and arrows on the chart refer.
So that was a brief
overview of diagnostics.
Don't forget the assets,
weaknesses, opportunities, threats.
This is the starting point we need
in order to build and imagine a diagnosis.
I've shown you several maps, and
might have shown you others,
or taken others away, but what
you should keep in mind
that a map is only useful if it
assists you in your planning.
If you make maps just for the sake
of making maps, they will be useless.
Each element that you bring
to your diagnosis
must contribute to your city planning.