Hello, today we are going to talk
about basic data.
To make a plan or a diagnostic,
a certain amount of basic data
to work from is necessary.
The basic data can vary,
the most obvious ones being
maps, satellite images, blueprints
historical plans, all graphical things,
the graphical representation
of the city on plans.
Those are the first data
that can be provided.
Then, we have other types of data
called statistics,
there is literature,
there is the official data,
there are field studies.
Next come multiple tools
that can be used for planning.
Maps and images.
A Google image as a first example.
This is Madagascar.
We go on Google Earth or Google Maps
and we find most of the options
that are before us,
since we can quickly get maps
and see the situation.
There are always geo-referencing
and scale issues.
We must be able to measure things,
from here to there
or surface areas,
so it's not always easy,
but we do have a first source here,
with Google images or satellite images
bought by the city council or ministries.
Another example on the coast,
which shows a potential problem
in this area,
and we can start understanding
the different urban fabrics
here and there,
just with an image.
Here is Dakar.
Simply observe this area here
and the development of a new lot
where only the road network
has been built for now.
Maps may also be
historical maps or plan.
Here is an old plan of Nouakchott,
an image of Nouakchott from the 70's,
and other types of documents
which can be used as master plans,
they are old master plans
that we will be working on as well.
So every time, we try to assess
what has been done,
and history is expected to carry on,
something existed before,
even if the plan didn't work.
We will look for previous plans
to assess them and see
what has been established or not,
what has worked or not
and if it didn't work, in what extent
and why it didn't.
Let's see the statistics now.
Let's pick any country and enter
« Institut national de la statistique »
or « Office national de la statistique »
and you will find a website
with the main stats for each country.
Usually, it is national
and regional stats.
It's very difficult to find council stats
and even more so at the urban area level,
which is a gathering
of several municipalities.
So we must refer to national stats
for mortality rate, for example,
which is linked to the global population.
Literature, broadly defined,
includes all reports from experts.
For each city, you will find dozens
or hundreds of reports from experts
on subjects from access to drinking water,
focus groups, to socio-economic studies
or socio-demographic studies in poor areas
or general matters, previous planning,
study reports on previous planning.
You will definitely find
a wealth of information.
Just a downside to be careful about,
usually in these reports,
the figures are used over and over
the previous reports are used
to update the new ones
without questioning the reliability
and validity of the data.
We can often trace,
just like a historian,
the progression of mistakes
about the population
and we find the source
in one report,
and see that the following ones
have just copied it
without checking the information.
Pay special attention to this,
reports are a source of information
but the validity of the information
must be known and understood.
Official data.
Besides stats,
there are different types of data
which may be land titles for example.
Those can be found at the property,
at the Land registry for cadastral plans.
So there is a number of official data
which can be used.
They are often hard to obtain
because generally speaking,
whoever holds the data has the power,
and it is very difficult to obtain
full listings of land titles, for example.
However, in some countries,
the data are increasingly free
and available for all.
So we are going from
a centralized view of the data,
where nothing can go out
and everything is kept very tightly
as there seems to be no reason
to be giving them away,
towards a much broader view,
which represents more the present days,
namely to have basic data
available to everybody.
Finally, field studies.
They can broadly be categorized.
First, household survey
where a questionnaire is made
and it's carried out on the field,
and the questions will be processed
to create statistics.
For everything needed
that is not in the stats,
or can't be found in maps and plans,
reports and literature,
or in official data,
you must go on the field
to lead the necessary surveys
in order to obtain the data.
A field survey may also be
counting cars on streets.
You place people and you count
several hours a day
traffic loads at given crossroads.
They may also be household surveys,
surveys, focus groups in districts
in order to try and understand
people's lives
before starting to plan anything.
It might be the most important part
of our basic data.
It's all the data that we don't have
and that we must find
and field survey is essential
for this matter.
This concludes this overview
of the data issue.
You need data and you can find only a few.
In African cities, data is national,
but not at town or municipality level,
so it can prove difficult to obtain
convincing information.
It doesn't mean it doesn't exist,
it's just harder to get.
Everything you won't find
you will have to go look for
with field surveys,
to set up methods that will allow you
to quickly gather the data you need
for your planning.