Hello.
In this video we will see
today a working method.
We are going to talk at length about
urban planning, the course subject.
We are now going to see an example
of a planning that was done in N'Djamena.
The interest in planning as we are going
to show it, is to put
the focus on a method that we have
developed some years ago.
So in a very synthetic way,
the city of N'Djamena,
the historical and colonial center,
working class neighborhood as we have
often spoken of each time.
A segregated city, a river here,
with bridges over the river to connect
the South Shore to the North Shore.
A border, since this whole area here,
we are in Cameroon, the airport.
And finally we see that the city has
developed like this
with a first beltway, a second,
but when is the third ring?
There you have a very quick base drawing
of the city of N'Djamena.
So let's review some images.
Let's go downtown.
Some atmosphere pictures for those
who do not know,
who have never had the chance
to go to N'Djamena.
These are things that can be found in
most cities of this region.
And the working class
neighborhoods not far
from downtown, we see that just as
in many places in Africa,
we have here a waste water disposal
that happens out in the open.
There are a number of collectors and
of course the streets are not paved.
Let's talk about method now.
Here's a first group of municipality
and department officers.
The idea was to create the planning
and to train people.
It was necessary to answer very quickly
to a demand from authorities
to make an urban plan,
a framework document, the first document,
a planning sketch
and for this we have brought together
twenty participants.
We have brought together participants from
Ministry and participants and City Hall.
We have taken young, young
budding urban planners,
to create this plan together.
Therefore, the application was both a
training and a planning.
Rather than separate the two things,
we have combined the two things,
and we have said, we are going to
plan together, and to train together.
So we bring everyone together in one room,
we discuss, we draw in groups,
each one making its diagnosis.
each image is discussed, each option,
each part of the diagnosis
is put on paper and we draw
once again together.
The idea here being that
we have 20 participants.
We are not going to know
who knows the most
about the city of N'Djamena,
it's not the objective.
The objective is to add up all of
this knowledge and all of the abilities
of the participants.
So there is no right, there is no wrong,
there's no what's true.
There are abilities and knowledge
that people have.
People can talk about
their neighborhoods,
of the road, of the problem
of a certain neighborhood,
of the problem of a certain facility
or a certain infrastructure
and we put this all together on the paper.
And I guarantee you that with 20 people,
we very quickly have a photograph
which is relatively correct of N'Djamena
in very, very little time.
That in two, three days we have
a diagnosis together.
We discuss, we decide,
people don't agree.
We put it on paper and then each group
presents their ideas.
So we make a diagnosis.
Then, this diagnosis, we are going to
extract the main issues put on paper.
Then these issues, we are going to
transform them in political orientations.
Finally, it's not because there's a
problem that we decide to solve it.
So what is interesting for us to know,
is at what moment we have
a problem, what is the exact problem,
and are we going to solve it or not?
And then it will become an orientation
if we decide solve it .
In that regard, we have orientations, then
we're going to spatialize them on a plan.
So, always in groups,
in orientation groups,
we redraw and then
we project these different drawings,
these different handmade sketches.
And directly, all together,
orientation by orientation,
we draw on the board, directly
from the computer.
We do it so that the drawing is done
little by little
with everyone coming to a end result.
So it's really we decide all together,
we draw all together, and in this case,
the expert is here to bring a number of
elements and reflection.
So it's not the expert that
will make the plan,
it's the participants who make the plan.
They are questioned, they are pushed
a little so that they come up with
the best of themselves and we realize
very quickly
that we end up with excellent results.
Here is a quick plan which is
the diagnosis plan.
This was made all together,
we have just redrawn it.
And then, when it comes to the planning,
stage by stage, we have a river
we have an existing city,
we have city limits
urban perimeter limits,
administrative cutbacks,
then a slice, a road network,
a number of green areas and
industrial areas,
water problems in downtown, draining,
large infrastructures, the center
which gets drawn slowly, the projection of
future roads, priority areas to be restructured.
And so, little by little, by phases,
we end up with a master plan,
of course with the final title block
which is very important,
since it doesn't suffice to just make
a drawing, it's also important
to know what the drawing is
that was put in place.
There you have very quickly,
an experience that was done
with the Urbaplan office, a Swiss office.
I myself participated as expert to develop
this method with this office.
It's one way to go about it that
we are proposing to you.
What are the advantages?
The advantages are undeniable.
It is then that people who have
developed the plan,
are the people in administration
who will have to put it in action.
It's people who will finally
have to enforce or not,
and it's easier to enforce regulations,
if it's you who has written it.
It's easier to enforce a plan
if it's you who has created it
and who has integrated all the stages.
It's not something that
comes from the exterior
which is imposed, it's something that
is imposed from the interior.
And finally, at each stage, each decision,
we know why such or such
a decision has been taken.
So it's easier then to justify
to the exterior that this should have been
done like this,
because we know the whole story
of this decision making.
And this is fundamental.
We are not dealing with
a participatory process,
it's not participation with people.
We are dealing with macro planning
of a city, large orientations,
big options.
But we all do it within an administration,
within the municipality, which allows for
the training of young urban planners,
and also at the same time all these people
will be those who in five, ten years,
will still have to enforce this urban plan,
this planning.
And it's for this reason that they must
be quickly, very quickly integrated
in the process, rather working
in workshops,
and above all using all of
the abilities of the people.
Each person, each land planner,
geographer, political,
each citizen even has a number
of competences, knows the land,
knows the problems that occur.
And the idea for us is to put all of this
in common and have a situation,
a diagnosis, a quick basic image which
may be validated by all and amongst all.
There you have it, the end of our case study
of the city of N'Djamena.