Welcome to our last week
of the Planning and Design
for Sanitation course.
Congratulations!
You've made it to the end
of an intensive five weeks
and have hopefully learned
a lot about the challenges
and some possible solutions
to urban sanitation.
Let's do a quick review
of the past few weeks.
In Week 1, we started off with an overview
of the multi-level challenges
of urban sanitation
and presented two planning approaches.
In Week 2, we introduced
some fundamental concepts
of environmental sanitation,
the different waste and resource products,
the sanitation value chain,
the five functional groups
that make up the sanitation system,
and we explained
the sanitation technologies
for the user interface, collection,
and storage and transport.
In Week 3, we introduced
different sanitation systems
from the simple single pit system
to the centralized treatment systems.
We also learned about
the more sophisticated
treatment technologies,
as well as possibilities
for the use of end products.
After these two weeks,
you should have gained
a better understanding
of the different systems
and technologies that are available
and feasable in urban settings.
Week 4 brought you
three different case studies
at different scales,
from the small town Nepali example
to the urban neighborhood example
from Erdos, China.
And finally, the successful sanitation
sector development program
in Indonesia that has managed
to scale up to a nationally anchored
and funded program,
using realistic and funded
city sanitation plans.
We've highlighted
the different urban contexts
from the planned city areas
to the peri-urban interface
and presented two planning frameworks,
which seek to structure
and guide sanitation planning
and programming at city-wide level.
Firstly, Sanitation 21,
dealing with the entire city
and at the neighborhood
and community level through CLUES.
We highlighted the importance
of creating or working
towards an enabling environment
regarding institutions, finance,
and legal issues.
Our focus has been on affordable
and context specific solutions
within the sanitation value chain.
Firstly, the user interface.
The most visible and direct part
of a sanitation facility
that has a lot to do
with the functionality,
attractiveness, and easiness to clean,
be it a dry, a source separating,
pour flush, or system flush toilet.
This is an area that is seeing
a lot of renewed interest
in people-centered design,
new materials, and toilet designs,
like the mobile pedestal toilet
using small container based solution,
shown on the bottom left
from Ghana.
Second, the storage
and containment of human waste,
from single and double pit technologies
to water-based anaerobic technologies,
like the septic tank,
or the biogas reactor.
Issues to be considered
are treatment efficiency,
space needed,
and the reliance on the fragmented
Mason based supply chain,
which is still the expensive main mode
of construction of onsite solutions.
Third, the conveyance
and transport of wastes.
The card game shown here,
shows some of the great variety
of motorized emptying vehicles out there
that safely collect and transport
fecal sludge to a treatment station
for further processing.
For many, if not most,
low-income country cities
this will continue to be
the modus operandi
in the decades to come.
Fourth, the treatment technologies,
which feature a mosaic of options
ranging from anaerobic, aerobic,
for liquid solid separation,
for the removal of grit and grease,
for the stabilization of sludge,
the polishing effluent, etcetera.
This is certainly the biggest gap
in the sanitation supply chain,
as most waste water
and sludge worldwide
still ends up untreated
in the environment.
There's a need to create more capacities
to plan, build, and run treatment plants
in a sustainable manner.
And lastly, the use or disposal
of treated waste.
An area of urban sanitation
that is gaining traction
in the recent past.
We have highlighted some of the examples
for the safe disposal of wastes
without harm for the environment
and value added safe use
of process sanitation products
for irrigation, fertilizer,
soil conditioner, or energy generation.
And finally, we have introduced
the universal theme
and guiding concept
of the enabling environments.
Governments need to create
an enabling environment
for everyone to have access
to improve sanitation.
The enabling environment includes
government support,
the legal framework,
institutional arrangements,
skills and capacities,
financial arrangements,
and, last but not least,
the socio-cultural acceptance.
We have also highlighted
that the absence of skills, capacities,
and the appropriate institutions
can severely hamper the proper
planning and implementation,
particularly in low-income,
urban settings.
At the end of this course,
I would like to thank
our guest lecturers,
Jonathan Parkinson and Isabel Blackett.
And our colleagues at Eawag Sandec
who've been constantly working
behind the scene
to make this course run smoothly.
Thanks to Fabian Suter, Lea Zaretti,
and Daniel Kroiss.
Our thanks also goes to the
EPFL MOOC team,
Gwenael Bocquet, Patrick Jermann,
Nicolas Peslerbe, and Jeremy Riedar
of the Center for Digital Education,
who've provided tremendous support
in putting this course together.
The next course,
in our WASH series in 2015
will be on solid waste management
in developing countries
and this will be directed
by my colleague, Dr. Christian Zurbruegg.
Thanks a lot.
I hope you enjoyed our course
and I look forward
to hearing from you again.
Bye bye.