Welcome back to the course.
So far you have seen three blocks.
In the first block,
we defined smart cities
then in the second block, we talked
about smart urban energy systems
and in the previous block we talked
about smart urban
transportation systems.
In the next two blocks or weeks
we will talk about the transition
to smart cities and the challenges
this transition raises.
In order to do that, let me first,
in one slide, conceptualize
what transition is for us
and what it is
from a system's perspective.
So the way we look at transition is
by defining sort of two dimensions
two boundaries, on the one hand,
technology changes, and on the other
hand institutions change
and institutions are
the rules if the game.
And the city as a socio-technical
system evolves as a result
of interaction of technology
and institutional change
and of course the driver
the ultimate drivers of this
change are the actors.
They take up the technology,
they play under particular rules
and they create the dynamics of
the whole socio-technical system.
Now, this leads to particular
services, the actors produce
services, and these services
determine actually the performance
of an urban infrastructure system.
Now, this MOOC is about smart
cities, and we have already
insisted about the role that
digitalization plays in this.
And digitalization is
extremely pervasive in that
it affects technological change,
it affects the institutional change
and it affects the way
the actors behave.
And so, digitalization becomes a new
driver of the transition of
socio-technical systems.
In the first block, and then applied
to the second, to energy and
transportation systems, we have
come up with this distinction
into three layers.
We have said that the smart city
is about an infrastructure layer
a digital or data layer,
and a services layer.
And again the services affect
the way the city performs
ultimately.
So, the next two weeks
are structured as follows.
First we will talk about transition,
and Muhammad will start out by
talking about the transition
of socio-technical systems
in general, then I will come back
and talk about the transition
of the digital, of the data layer
and this will be illustrated by
a series of interviews
from experts.
In week five, we will talk in
particular about challenges.
First the challenges on the services
layer, then the challenges on
the infrastructure layer, and then
we will bring all this together
an talk about what this
means for managers.
Finally we will conclude and
put all that into a context of
policy recommendations,
so stay tuned.