Hello and welcome
back to the course.
My name is Mohamad Razaghi,
I'm a researcher at EPFL
and in this session I would
like to share our approach
towards transition to
smart cities with you.
My core argument in this session
is that in socio-technical systems
which cities are of course great
examples of such systems,
We are dealing with complexity.
And that, to manage and
govern the transition process
in such complex context, three
key considerations are vital.
First to have a Holistic approach,
second to have a long term
perspective, and third
to be flexible
in managing
the process of transition.
Let me start with the notion
of complexity in socio-technical
systems and what does that mean.
As you know, feedback
loops are essential elements
when we are talking about systems.
In socio-technical systems,
the feedback loops
are present at the technical.
the social. and what we call
the socio-technical levels.
In the technical level,
we have feedback loops
both inside and across
different sub-systems.
Let's for example think of
the transportation or
the energy systems.
As an example of feedback loops
inside these technical systems
you can for example imagine how
changes in the rooting, or
the roots of the bus systems
will have impact on the demand for
the metro or the light rail system
in the city.
As an example of feedback loops
across different technical systems
you can think for an example,
the impact of introducing
electric buses in
the transportation network
and the effects that it would have
on the demand on the electricity
and the energy
infrastructure in the city.
Feedback loops are also exist in
the social level, as we call that.
For example, between the economy
and the social sub-systems
between the economic and
the political sub-systems
and so on and so forth, so you
can think of that between
the economy and
the environment and so on.
But also, the feedback loops exist
in the overall socio-technical
system and this is what is
really important for us
when talking about transition
towards the smart cities.
For example, let me
give you an example
of a new subsidies scheme
on public transportation tariffs.
This new tariff system can
be seen as an economic decision.
But, introducing this change
can have very profound impacts
on all the other sub-systems as well
such as putting more pressure
on the transportation
infrastructure
due to the increasing demand
for public transportation
services by the citizens.
Now the service is cheaper,
so the demand might go higher.
Also, the availability of more
affordable public transportation
in the city, might affect
the citizen's choice
of place for living.
For example, you can imagine
that those groups in the city
that are less advantaged,
compared to the other ones
might decide to move to
the outer side of the city
where the housing is more affordable
while they can still commune to
the city center and access
to their jobs thanks to
the availability of these cheap
public transpiration tariff scheme
that is already introduced
in the system.
This can have the significant
impact on the social dimensions of
life in the city as well, for
example you can imagine
how it can result in
deeper social segregation
between different neighborhood
in the city, because
not anymore, all the groups
of the citizens are living
in one place, someone living in one
neighborhood, the other ones are
living in other neighborhoods,
which are more advantaged
probably, or even on the political
dimension of, you know
governance and management
of the city, for example
you can imagine how this new tariff
system can help the current
administration to win the next
election, probably, because
this new tariff system would be
very visible to the eyes of
the citizens, while benefiting
from that tariff.
This simple example already
shows the three important
characteristics in
socio-technical system
which result in complexity.
Namely, the inter-dependency,
which means that a change
or the ultimate performance of
one sub-system in the broader
socio-technical system will
have impacts on the performance
of other sub-systems as well,
and ultimately this is
the combination of the performance
of all these sub-systems
which will result in the performance
of the overall system and each of
them in isolation.
The second important point
here is the past dependency
which means that every change
or decision in a socio-technical
system is dependent on the changes
that occurred on the system in
the previous stages, which often
take quite some time until their
effects become fully
utilized in this system
and are observable and
become tangible for the citizens
and the decision-makers,
of course.
And last but not least,
we are talking about
irreversibility.
Irreversibility means that
we cannot just undo
the impact of the decisions
that we made and the changes
that we introduced in
the socio-technical systems
because the impacts of
the change in one sub-system
is affecting many other sub-systems
as well, and often over a very
long period of time, which makes
it almost impossible to redo
the effects that one change
or one decision has in
the socio-technical system.
Let us now discuss what
are the implications of
of these important features
of socio-technical systems
for management and
governance of the transition
towards the smart city.
The interdependence here
among different sub-systems
offer socio-technical system call
for adopting a Holistic and
quite often a multidisciplinary
approach, then managing
the transition process
towards the smart cities.
Indeed, because introducing changes
in one infrastructure will influence
on and will be influenced by changes
in other sub-systems of our broader
socio-technical system, we have to
have a Holistic approach
in managing the different elements
of the transition process
towards the smart cities.
By adopting a holistic approach,
I mean that we have to consider
technological, economic, social
political, institutional
and also very importantly
environmental considerations.
In a holistic fashion, and not
just in isolation from each other.
Then, we are trying to
manage the process of transition
towards the smart cities.
Without such a Holistic approach,
new initiatives in complex
socio-technical systems. like
the smart cities
often fail, or even result in
adverse effects that we don't
even foresee them in
advance and will
distort the performance
of the system, potentially.
The past dependency of changes
in socio-technical systems
calls for adopting a long term
perspective in management
and governance of transition
towards the smart cities.
Let me benefit from S curve
innovation to elaborate
on this point.
The S curve innovation, which is
the result of a lot of
empirical research
shows us that the performance
or progress of introducing
an innovation, which can be
technical or institutional
is dependent on time.
But the relationship between
the time and the progress
of an innovation is
not a linear relation.
Indeed as you can see in this graph,
innovations often take quite some
significant time to be developed,
until they reach a point where
we can see a rapid progress
in terms of their performance gains.
This is this rapid growth that
you can see in the graph.
And after this rapid growth phase
innovations often enter a period of
relatively stable progress,
when their performance
does not significantly
change over time anymore.
This means that when
a new innovation, being
technological, or institutional,
is introduced in a city
to help the city move toward
becoming more smart
a relatively light period of time
will be required until the expected
performance from this innovation
can be utilized, and an important
point here is that, the different
innovations have their own
different S curves as well,
for an example
the technological innovations
we can look at the rat care
for an example in this graph,
often reach to their maximum
progress in a shorter period of time
that when you compare it
with social or institutional
innovations, which you can think of
them as yellow or
the green curves here.
But, as we discussed before
transition in socio-technical
systems is not the result of
changes in one single sub-system
but is indeed the result of
a series of changes in these
interdependent sub-systems
after broader socio-technical
system.
So, we need even longer times
until all the introduced changes
in the system reach to their
expected performance level
the technological innovations,
the social innovations
the financial innovations,
and so on, and so forth.
And this implies that without
the long term perspective
introducing new initiatives in
the city often result in failure.
The irreversibility of changes
in the socio-technical systems
is one of the main reason
we need to adopt
a flexible approach in management
and governance of transition towards
the smart cities.
Innovations such as the ones
that we have already discussed in
the smart energy, and the smart
transportation blocks
can introduce significant changes in
established infrastructure systems
and hopefully they can also improve
the performance of the systems.
But, unfortunately innovations
often fail, and the rate of failure
among innovations in
socio-technical systems
is even higher, something
around 90%.
As you can see,
in this simplified diagram
only few innovations would
eventually become a part of
the existing socio-technical
systems, while most of
the others fail in different
stages of their life-cycle.
This can be seen, for example in
the case of different innovations
to realize the idea of driver-less
vehicles, or the different renewable
energy technologies, where only
one or very few often existing
technologies will ultimately
become the dominant technology
in the sector, and this is indeed
the battle the different companies
are trying to win at this stage of
transition towards the smart cities.
Because most of the innovations are
doomed to failure, unfortunately
and because all decision and changes
in socio-technical systems are not
easily reversible, it is very
important that we try to keep
all the options that are
available as long as possible
that we can, and to avoid becoming
locked in premature technologies
that might prove to be
failures in a few years.
This is even more important when
we consider that not all innovations
can affect an infrastructure
that are necessarily generated
in the same sector, like you know,
think of what happened in
the battery technology, which
has starter in the energy sector
but now has disrupted
impacts in the transportation
infrastructure, thanks to
the introduction of
the electric vehicles.
Now, let me conclude this session
by using a simple diagram, which
I call the "Transition Triangle".p
As we discussed in this session,
it is very important to adopt
a Holistic approach in management
and governance of transition towards
the smart cities, considering
technological, economic, social
political, and environmental
dimensions of any change
that is going to be
introduced in the city
towards becoming more smart.
We also have to have a long term
perspective in managing
the transition towards the smart
cities, because we are dealing
with different kinds of past
dependencies in the system
what we already see in
the S curve of innovation.
And last, but not least,
we have to keep as much
flexibility as possible when
managing a transition process
towards the smarter cities,
to effectively deal with
the irreversible nature of
the changes that are introduced in
the socio-technical systems.
But, following these guidelines is
easier said than done in practice.
For example, it looks quite
paradoxical, you know at
the first glance at least,
to have a long term perspective
while staying flexible
at the same time.
And this is why the next
sessions of this MOOC
we'll try to get into more details
on how we can manage and
govern the process of transition
towards the smart cities
understood as complex
socio-technical systems.
So, stay tuned.