Hello and welcome back
to the course.
Today, I have the pleasure of
being with Dr Alain Staron.
He is the director of digital
transformation at the Veolia group.
He is in charge
of the strategy, partnerships
and new services development.
- Welcome Alain.
- Thank you, good morning.
Than you very much
for being with us.
Let me ask you my first question.
Can you elaborate,
as an expert in the field,
what is the impact of digitalisation
on urban infrastructures?
I will start by talking about
water and energy.
The two main things where
Veolia is working hard.
You have to consider infrastructures
are very difficult things to manage.
That takes kilometers,
thousands of kilometers,
to get water or energy
going through any household.
And the difficulty of it is,
how do we manage it?
We use to have good expertise,
very good expertise,
to understand and modelize
things we don't see
because these pipes are underground.
What is happening with
digitalisation is
we get more and more sensors that
will help you with measuring
what is happening underneath.
You can have one every
hundred meters, 10 meters
And the result of this is,
instead of having only your brain to
understand what is going on underneath,
you will get real measures
and you will get much more info
about the exact behaviour
of your infrastructure.
Doing so, it'll be much easier for
you to understand what is happening.
I would say more.
You will understand, we will
understand but our machines
might understand better,
even better than us.
At the end of the day,
the software, the programs,
the algorithms we develop
will help us manage infrastructure
much better than we do now because
it would be more customised
to any infrastructure in a city
because it takes the
measurements of any city.
It's not just the global weathering,
it's any city measurement.
It'll be much more accurate
in terms of space
because we can get
a lot of sensors.
It will be much more accurate
in terms of timing.
You would be able to get
measurements every minute.
So, it would be much easier
to manage the system globally.
Great, and then other dimensions
than the management
can you elaborate - what about
the other dimensions?
not just the management
of the infrastructures?
The good thing is with
these kind of sensors
you get more info than the
one you expected to.
You expect it for water,
you expect about pressure,
for example, or flow.
You will be able to get much
better, much more information.
Take one example:
We used to manage water
into the household.
Now, with the smart meters
we even can measure
the exact instantaneous flow that is
going into the household.
We can measure it at night
and we can elaborate
the probability for any leakage
in house because we will measure it.
That's a big change.
That's when we could first
reassure the end user.
Telling him 'Hey, be careful'.
Second, we can put him in touch
with a plumber that would help.
And thirdly, we can sell insurance.
So you can see how
from a single sensor
we can derive
more benefit for the end user.
A better marketplace
and even more services.
Great, so you know both
on the management side
and the services side you can
really get, you know,
new and more innovative ways
to organise things better.
That's great, can you
also elaborate
what is the impact of this
digitalisation of infrastructures
to reach what is so-called
known as "smart cities".
That's very interesting.
Smart cities, the study, the concept
started about 10 years ago.
It was really about that time,
you know, big machines,
big software infrastructures.
I.T.
The concept and the
target is the same
the means to actually
reach the target are different.
For me, smart cities, is very simply
is the way the cities
are transforming themselves.
The digital transformation of cities -
is called "Smart City".
All of us, we transform ourselves.
Companies transform themselves.
There's no reason cities
should not transform themselves.
So "smart city" is the exact way
cities are transforming themselves
thanks to digitalisation.
What is the impact of this?
Once we get so many data
that improve the performance,
you see that you can
go up to the end user.
And the point for us is
with more and more sensors
understanding of what is happening
you can give more power
to the end user
in the way he helps us
managing the resources.
At the end of the day
you get showers,
bath and that's the way
you use water.
If there's a direct relationship
between what you are doing
your usage and the impact
on the global city,
you start to become "electro"
in your city.
So for a smart city
the digital transformation
in cities is the way
to get back the citizen,
the inhabitants
inside the global management
of the city.
Great. Which is traditionally done
basically by the city government
and the companies
but now you're talking about having
the citizens also being part of this.
How disruptive is this
for the cities?
Can you elaborate?
What are the, you know,
big consequences,
futuristic consequences
of having that into the game?
The future is back to basics.
The first cities,
back 2000 years ago, before Christ.
You have cities
of about 40,000 people.
With this kind of scale
it was quite possible to get
everyone involved in the city.
With millions
and millions inhabitants in cities
that becomes impossible.
What is happening with the
future of the infrastructures
The decentalized infrastructures.
The fact they do not need anymore
top-down approach
to get your basic services.
And that you have locally produced,
produced by the end user,
"prosumers" that produce and
consume at the same time.
You can start to have,
to liberate the
geographical constraint of the city.
You can start to have anyone living
everywhere with the same service
that if you were
living inside the city.
And if you consider that
more than half of human beings
live in cities,
including in Asia in 2013
and 85% in western countries.
You can consider that
almost everyone,
every human being is a normal being.
Then you have to consider now
that city is no more an exception
a city is the way we live.
And so the surface of the earth
will be cities in a new sense
not geographically concentrated.
But thanks to infrastructure,
digitalisation, new technologies
everyone will be able to get,
in every place,
the same services it used to get
with with some limitations,
in existing cities today.
Great, thank you very much Alain
for your insights.
You're welcome, thank you very much.