Welcome back.
In this session we look at the
crucial role that the data layer
is playing in the transition
to smart cities.
We do this in 3 steps:
First I will talk about
why the data layer is
so crucial
then I will try to identify what
the data layer is exactly about.
Thirdly we will raise a series of
questions that all need to be
addressed if we want to make the
transition to smart cities a success.
Getting the data layer, the digital
layer right is an important
precondition for performing
smart city services.
We have seen that in the previous
session when Mohammed talked about
path dependency. Graphically
this can be represented
something like this. Over time
services are being rolled out
which contribute to more performing
urban infrastructure systems.
Getting the data layer right is a
precondition for having the services
function and being able
to be rolled out.
This is a typical
path dependency problem.
What is this data or digital
layer exactly?
In the first block, you remember,
when we talked about networks
we identified 3 layers. We had a
physical telecommunication
infrastructure, wired or wireless.
Then we had networks;
typically the internet and then
we had the identification and
exchange of data; typically
the World Wide Web.
In the context of a smart city
what is particularly important
for the data layer is this
connection of the devices
to each other; the internet of
things as we have also said.
This requires technical
interoperability and standards
so that actually all the
data generating devices
can be connected to each other.
The second element that is crucial
for this digital or data layer
is the fact that the data can be
identified and accessed and
exchanged as a result of that.
This is mainly a question of norms
and regulation whereby access rules
are defined, locations are identified
and accessibility is granted.
From here we can raise a series
of questions. Those are all the
questions that are crucial for the
digital layer to function properly.
Let's start with the first question.
I already mentioned before;
It's this question of standards.
It is not -- The digital layer
cannot function properly if the
devices that generate the data
cannot be connected to each other.
This is typically a question
of standards. The second question
is a question of
ownership of the data. This is a
question that somehow needs to be
decided so that the data layer
can function properly.
Who owns the data? Is it the telecom
operator that transports them?
Is it the owner of the devices
that generates them?
Is it the individual from whose
house these data actually come?
Is it the one who buys the data?
This question of ownership also
needs to be clarified for the
data layer to function properly.
The third question is the question
of accessibility of data.
What good is it to have data
if they are not accessible?
Who has access to this data?
Are these data openly accessible;
something that today
is called open data.
Are they restricted to some users?
Are they only accessible to
the highest bidder? Those are -- or
are they just accessible to the ones
who have generated it and
to whom he wants to sell it?
These are the kind of questions that
also need to be decided.
The fourth question is a standard
question but it's the question about
the security and the privacy of
the data. If data are not secure
and if privacy is not guaranteed
then the data layer may simply
not function. The fifth question is
the one about the pricing
of the data. Data generation
has a price. Those are devices;
that there is a cost. The question
is what is the price of the data?
Should they be given for free and in
which case, who pays actually the
real cost that the data have?
Maybe it's the customers
who give their own data and
somebody makes money with them.
It's really a matter of what is
a good pricing policy about data?
These question have to be
clarified as well.
Then the sixth question is about
the reliability of data.
What good is it to have data
if you cannot rely upon them
to provide good services;
if they are wrong,
false, manipulated;
questions like this.
Then the seventh question may
be a little bit more theoretical
question but it's the question
about the location of the data.
Where are these
data platforms?
Are they within the firms?
Are they within the city?
Are they in a country?
Are they in the global cloud?
This is a technical question,
an economic question
but can also be
a political question.
Okay so basically
we have 2 issues here:
One is an issue of standards and
ideally the standards are set
by the industry but if the industry is
not capable of setting the standards
then it may also become
a regulatory question;
like most of the other questions
are actually regulatory questions.
Those are decision that need to be
made about the ownership,
about the privacy, about
the location and that is
actually regulation
that decides on these things.
In this session we saw why
the data layer is so crucial.
What it is about
and the main questions
that you need to ask
to get the data layer right.
Stay tuned.