Hello, my name is Juan Montero
I'm a professor of
administrative law
in the UNED university in Madrid
and also a scientific adviser
in the Florence's
school of Regulation.
My research is focused on
the regulation and competition
in the network industries,
particularly telecoms and
transport, and over
the last couple of years
I have been working on
the regulation of the sharing
economy.
Particularly in transportation
and accommodation.
I think there is a fundamental
kind of legal regulatory challenge
when we are talking about smart
cities and it is that
we have a clash
between two regulatory traditions
on the one hand we
have the traditional
infrastructure, networks, services
provided in citizen terms of
telecommunications
transport, energy, etc.
These kinds of networks and services
are closely linked to the territory
where they are being established
or provided and what we have is
local authorities, maybe
the regional, national
always have an authority
that is very closely linked
to the territory, regulation these
kinds of networks and services
and we have a tradition of very
intense regulation, in terms of
licensing, sometimes exclusive
rights, or special rights of
very often, public service
obligations, very often even
direct provision of the service
by the public authorities, so
we have an established tradition of
intervention in these kinds of
again networks and services, but
on the other hand we have a new
layer which we could call
the data layer, that comes from
a very different tradition.
Most of the providers of this data
services are global providers
and they don't have a very
close link with the territory
where the service is being provided.
And even regulations have been
built over the years to, not link
the provision of this services to
the territory, but on the contrary
to provide the maximum flexibility
for the provision of
these data services.
so when these data services
were rather virtual and they were
rather related to the management
of information or content like
like the impact they had on
the music industry, on the media
industry, it all remained pretty
much virtual, but what we are
understanding now that these data
layers have and impact also in
the physical world, and the smart
cities it's probably one of
the leading examples, where we see
how this data layer have an impact
on the physical world in
terms of transport services
accommodation services,
energy, telecoms, etc.
And we are starting to see very
practical cases and examples
of this class of legitimacy between
the regulation of this traditional
network and services and
the regulation of this new
data layer above these
traditional services.
I think that there are two very
good examples of this class of
legitimacies.
The first one is transport,
and usually the sharing
economy, transport companies, like
"Uber" or "Bla-Bla-Car"
"Lyft", there are lots of examples,
and what we see for instance
is that local authorities
tend to apply the traditional
transport regulations to these
new companies, which tend to
be again, very restrictive
in terms of licensing etc.
But then we have these new layer
services, because these companies
I mean, they don't own cars,
they are not locally established
for the provision of the transport
services, on the contrary
they are just managing the data
layer above these traditional
transport services.
And what they claim is that
they are not subject to
local transport regulations,
but rather to the regulation
on digital services, typically
for instance, we have in Europe
information, and e-commerce
directive that defines the category
of information, society's services,
and very important to them
it's not only that this directive
provides regulations that
even prohibits the obligation to
be licensed, and other restrictions
that can be imposed in provision
of data services, but further more
they established the principal
that these services will be
ruled by the legislation of
the country where the provider
of the services established
enough of the country where
the services being received,
so what we see is that
transport services are regulated
very closely by
the local authorities
but the data layer is regulated
according to the laws of a different
country, and this of course creates
for a clash in the regulation of
these services that is creating
many of the differences in
the interpretation of what
the regulation should be applied
for instance, to "Uber",
to "Bla-Bla-Car".
Another example in the accommodation
industry is the regulation of serving
economy companies like "Air BnB",
and they have for instance
a strong conflict with
the authorities of the city of
New York, which again want to
apply the local regulations
accommodation, also to
"Air BnB" to the data layer.
And the automatic response of
"Air BnB" is that they are not
subject to the local accommodation
regulations, but rather to the data
layer regulations, and in particular
they claim that they should be
subject to the decency
communications act
which exempts of liability to
the providers of just this
data layer services.
So, I think these are two examples,
good examples of this clash of
legitimacy between the local
traditional accommodation
transportation, telecoms, energy
regulations and the regulation
of this new data layer
above all those services.
It is not simple form a legal
regulatory and institutional
point of view to provide clear cut
solutions, I think, solutions have
to be designed for a specific
industry, for a specific service
but I think there are some
principals that can be defined.
The points to be taken into
consideration for regulation
of this new data services.
I think the solution is not just
to impose the old regulatory
framework, which tends
to be very restrictive
and that's not taking into
consideration these new services
but on the contrary, I don't think
it's just a matter of ignoring this
local regulation and pretend
it doesn't exist, I think it's
necessary to provide, to adopt
a new regulation that first
of all takes into consideration
the existence of data layer services
only if we acknowledge that these
new services exist, we can provide
a good regulation for them.
The second one is that
regulation has to provide
a level playing field between
the traditional providers of
transport, energy, telecom
services and the new providers
of both of data services
and also of newcomers
to the market that are
enabled to have access
to the market, thanks to this data
layer, I mean all these drivers who
work under the "Uber" scheme,
or all those people who are working
with "Air BnB", I mean they have
the right to participate in
the market, but we have to
make sure that all the players
are competing on
the level playing field.
A third principal would be that
traditional players should
be allowed to adapt to the new
scenario, we should not have
regulations that keep very strict
obligations on the providers of
the services, that way
the restrictions do not allow
these traditional players to compete
on equal footing with the newcomers.
And very importantly also,
it is very important that
the overall regulatory regime
maintains a good equilibrium
between all the interest in
the eco-system.
We have now very different players
in different layers, and we have to
make sure that the whole system
is sustainable in the sense
for instance, that all
the investment that is
necessary to deploy and
maintain the infrastructure
in terms of transport, in terms of
energy, in terms of telecoms
all that infrastructure can operate
in a sustainable environment
where financing for such
an infrastructure is ensured.
So we have to make sure that
we obstruct opportunistic market
entries that just extract value
from the whole eco-system
and do not make it possible to keep
the investment in the infrastructure
layer.
And finally, I think it's important
to take into account
that all these new technology that
the new data layer gives a lot of
power to the user, to the citizen
and I think this is a very positive
element and we should make sure
that the new regulation not only
make sure that their citizen is
empowered, but that this power
is increased, and I think this is
a central element, a new element
that has to ensuring first by any
kind of regulation of this kind
of activities.
Thank you.