So, I'm Boi Faltings.
I'm professor of
artificial intelligence at the EPFL,
and I would speak to you
about concept of smart cities
and the use of artificial
intelligence in that area.
So, one of the big features
of smart cities is that
we will adjust parameters,
we will control things
to sit as well being
based on measurements
of what actually happens,
what is the constraint of a city.
So naturally, smart cities
will collect a lot of data.
Data in fact is at the heart
of the concept of smart cities,
and so the question is,
how do we gather this data
and what do we do with it?
So, when we gather data, clearly
there's a lot of things
that can be done,
for example,
if we systematically analyze
traffic data,
we can find out where
do we have a lot of traffic jams,
are there roads that are
may be underutilized,
could we somehow
channel traffic differently
so that we have less congestion.
Could we maybe offer incentives
for people drive at different times,
And all these things
have been done
and they are very profitable
for the citizens
and we can think of extending this.
We could measure more data,
we could measure more
about what is happening
in the city
and observe anomalies, and
those anomalies could be corrected.
And so this is actually
a very healthy development
and it's going on already
as we speak.
But the real interest
in the smart city,
is not to just make
small improvements, but may be
to have a permanent control loop.
That is, where we observe
what's happening,
and we adjust, we make changes,
and making changes is not easy
just based on data
because the difficulty is
that we only have data
about what is happening currently.
So, we cannot tell from the fact
that drivers produce traffic jams
in certain situations,
what will happen
if somehow flagged them
to take different routes
or if we  scheduled
the traffic lights differently?
Well, you know, the data
doesn't tell us this,
so we cannot make
that inference directly.
On the other hand, it is possible
to do this by building simulations.
And so, the next step in big data,
and this is what actively
being researched now, is to actually
use it to build models.
So in the case of traffic again,
we would build models
of driver behaviors,
how the drivers react
including their emotions.
They get upset, they get frustrated,
you know, and so
we can build increasingly
sophisticated models
based on the data that
we can gather today,
based on those observations,
and then with both models
we can simulate what will happen
when we make changes
and that is actually
a whole new game because now
we can actually make
more intelligent changes.
Not just thinking what might
be a good solution
but actually having a pretty good
prediction
of what would be a good solution.
And then the next step
that will come afterwards
is to make the city
really intelligent.
That is, to not leave this change
to people, but to automate this,
and AI can really do this
quite nicely.
we have developed
lots of techniques
for automated planning,
for automated configuration
for optimizing these kinds
of situations.
So once we have the data,
once we have those models,
actually Artificial Intelligence systems can also
find us better solutions.
So, I think there is
a bright future here.
The more they data we collect,
the more accurate this data is,
the better we can automatically act
and we can actually improve
everybody's life,
and I think it will be
quite important given that
we have a high density of people
in cities, it's quite a challenge
to make life nice for them.
Now, given all this, there are still
lots of difficulties to overcome
and the biggest difficulty really,
is that data is biased.
Most of the data we collect today
is collected opportunistically.
That is, we take what we get, right.
We have sensors for traffic,
we have sensors at traffic lights
so we kind of know
how many cars are waiting
at certain one of these lights,
so while that data is being sensed,
well, we might as well collect it.
But we don't have data
about roads.
You know, we don't measure traffic
on all the streets systematically,
so we have a lot of holes
in there.
And these holes actually are
quite important because they mean
that the models are not quite
as accurate
as we would like them to be.
So, take another example
which is measuring pollution.
Air pollution kills according
to an estimate
of the World Health organization,
about 7 million people every year.
Compare that to traffic accidents
which the same organization
estimates to be responsible
for 1.25 million deaths.
So you see that air pollution
actually is a much bigger problem.
Now, we could help citizens
if we could provide them
with some information in real time
because air pollution
that actually  kills people,
is not the pollution that you see
when it's a bit fogy, or, you know,
the diesel exhaust
that comes out in front of you.
These big particles actually get
ejected by your lungs right away.
The thing that really kills people
are things that you don't see,
gases that you don't smell
like carbon monoxide or NO2
are fine particles that stay
in your lungs
and actually go
into your bloodstreams,
these are things that you
need to measure.
You cannot just see them,
and in fact, it would be nice,
if the citizens could have access
to that data in real time.
I could avoid, for example,
going jogging on a road
that's very polluted and actually
absorbing a very large quantity
of this pollution, and I could do it
may be at another time
or in another place.
Now for a long time it was thought
that pollution across the city
was relatively constant,
so you know,
you could just have one
measuring point and it would work
and it would sort of,
cover the whole city.
Today, people have developed
better sensors
and in fact, there are  a lot
of small sensors available.
Now, I have some pictures here,
for example,
there's this, you know,
there's a company called Plume Labs
that make really small sensors
like this that you could attach
to your back pack, and you could
walk around with them.
They're not supper accurate though
I must say.
Then there's  another generation
of laser based sensors,
so this is a sensor that is very
popular in China
called the Laser Egg.
And they are quite cheap,
and they're quite accurate.
People can now measure
this air pollution,
and people have walked around,
for example,
this is the map of the city
of Zurich.
So people have walked around
with little bit more accurate
sensors than this, actually,
with the whole back pack full
of sensors in the city of Zurich
and they kind of measured
more fine-grained
how the pollution looks.
And you can see that,
you have very high pollution
along certain main roads,
and then, as you go away,
sometimes within the space
of 100 meters,
the pollution is just half,
or sometimes even down to a quarter.
So, they are pretty big differences,
and if I can choose,
well, I could go to places where
there's less pollution, right,
or at least if I have a choice
to my exercise or my bike riding.
In fact, a colleague of mine
in Zurich has produced an App
that allows you to minimize
your pollution exposure,
so you choose a bike route that
minimizes your pollution exposure.
But, these things are
all experimental.
So for the moment,
what we are really lacking
is the data and to have the data
systematically.
The sensors are now
becoming available but, you know,
we would have to put up
a lot more of them
and we have to put them up
all over the city
in order to really provide
this kind of map to the citizens.
And so, how could this work?
One way of course, is that the city
puts up all the sensors.
So the city would buy hundreds
of them may be,
and they would ring on your door
and they would say
"Well, we should put a sensor
in your backyard
because that's a good position.
And so, could you please let us in?
And by the way, we come by
every month to do the maintenance
and make sure that it works."
So that's obviously not
the greatest model.
So, we can think of new ways
of doing this, and one new way
that we have been promoting a lot
is crowd sensing.
Which means that, just like people
can buy solar panels today,
and actually sell
the electricity back,
people could buy sensors
and sell the data, right?
And that way, may be even lot's
of people would be quite motivated
to have these sensors
close to their home
because it would give them
some information about the pollution
they're currently exposed to,
but also if they sell this data,
well they could recover the cost
of the sensor, so.
This would probably give
quite a movement
and  it could also support
a little bit more democratic use
of this data because everybody
could contribute
and everybody could see the effect.
There would be no trust issue,
in the sense that,
people would have to trust
that the government does not hide
any important pollution from them.
So, I think it's really
the way to go.
Now of course if I tell you,
"I will pay you for data,"
Well, you'll say, "Great, you know,
I don't even have to buy the sensor,
I will get a random number generator
and I will feed in some data,
so we have to think carefully
about how we pay for data.
And this is one innovation
I'd like to show you
that we have been working on
in the lab
where we actually have a scheme
for rewarding
such that people who have
no extra data to report
don't get any reward.
And the way it woks is that,
you have your space,
so this would be a part
of a city, for example.
Actually, this was a real experiment
we did, with data
from the City of Strasbourg
in France.
So these are all measuring points,
the red crosses you can see here ,
and let's say we have
participants here who says,
"Okay, I have this data
to sell you."
And so it provides,
this participant provides us
with some kind of reading
of sensors, supposedly.
Then what we do is we identify
in the neighborhood
other sensors that have give us data
that have  to be correlated to this,
right, at least the fluctuations
will be correlating
and so, this is what we call peers.
And we will compare this participant
report to the peer reports, right,
and all that we'll require is that
it should be more
closely correlated to the
peer reports than to overall average
that we find in the rest
of the city.
And it turns out that this
correlation actually is enough
to have a scheme so that somebody
who has no data to report
or who just reports randomly,
can expect exactly no revenue
and everybody who actually
accurate data
and the more accurate,
the better,
actually can expect
a higher revenue.
So we have here for these points
that you see,
we have an image here
that show you
all the different census, they were
116 of them of the stimulation here
and so these are actual data that
was measured
in the City of Strasbourg
where we made a simulation
of whether you would report
correctly or not
and how it would be rewarded,
and you can see here
that census would report, honestly,
this would be the blue curve, right.
They always get a positive payoff.
Whereas those that report randomly,
so these red curves here,
they often get negative payoffs.
Note, average actually the payoff
is pretty much exactly zero.
And also every census,
every single one of them,
gets a higher payoff
and a significantly higher payoff
by reporting truthfully,
and reporting accurately.
So we think this scheme really
will enable a smart city
to actually have all the data
and to make it available to citizens
and to make it available
for decisions, for example,
If we discover that pollution
is too high on certain roads,
then maybe we will run the buses
somewhere else,
maybe we will stop car traffic
into the city.
So all these measures can be coupled
to a real time measurement
rather than, well,
some bureaucratic decisions
or decisions that maybe
people won't support.
I think if we have this kind
of democratic movement
where everybody can
contribute their data.
So if they think that my area
is too polluted
and there are too many cars going
through, well, put up more census
and you will show this to the city
and in fact, you can also expect
some measures to be taken
if pollution is really too high.
So, we think that could be a
new model and we're actually looking
together with this company
at Beijing, that makes sense
whether we can work this out
in the near future.
All these things take time
as you can imagine
but I hope that maybe we can
inspire you as well,
to think of some of
these techniques.
Thank you very much for listening
and I wish you a good day.