So far we have talked to you about
the transition of cities as
sociotechnical systems. We have
talked about the importance of
the digital layer in that transition
and you have heard
from various experts about
elements of that digital layer.
Now let us briefly come back
to the question of sequencing.
There have been raised a series
of questions that need to be
addressed for the
digital layer to function properly
and here these
questions are again.
While these questions all need to
be addressed at some point,
the sequencing of how they're
addressed may vary from city to city.
What we can say is that some
questions ideally should be
addressed at the industry level;
like questions of standards typically.
If they are not addressed at the
industry level then probably
they will be addressed at the
national level or
at the super-national level.
In the case of Europe,
this would typically be the EU.
There are a series of questions
which can or should be
addressed at the city level;
like questions of location of the
data, like questions of ownership,
questions of transparency
and accuracy of the data.
Now that we have seen what it
takes to transit to Smart Cities
in terms of getting the data
or the digital layer right,
and now that we have seen what
can be obtained from these data
from the presentation
of Professor Faltings.
let us now turn to the services
and challenges that
a transition to Smart Cities
raises for the services layer.