Hi, I'm Ed Bugnion,
welcome to POCS.
This week in POCS we'll be talking about
two related and important concepts.
The first one is virtualization,
which is a broadly used technique
in computer systems,
and the second one is virtual machines,
which is the application
of the virtualization technique
as applied to a computer's
desktops or servers.
I've actually spent many years,
probably well over a decade of my career
in the area of virtualization.
Hope to share some of those
perspectives with you this week.
This is a pretty broad area,
so we've broken it up
into different topics.
The first one, which is the module
you're watching right now,
will only focus on
an introduction and overview
of the broad topic of virtualization.
Some of that topic content comes from
the Saltzer and Kaashoek textbook.
Now the other modules are not available
in the Saltzer and Kaashoek textbook.
I'll first walk you through
a history of virtual machines...
why we are where we are today.
That's kind of an interesting
history to think about.
Then we'll go into the area
of VMM construction,
and we'll do that
in a system-independent manner,
just looking at the fundamental
principles that are required
in order to build
a virtual machine monitor
that can efficiently run virtual machines.
And then we'll go from theory to practice
in the next two modules.
There's a first case study,
which is of a system called Disco,
which I worked on in the 90's at Stanford.
And this was a precursor to ESX server,
which is covered in the paper
from Carl Waldspurger
So I recommend that you watch this module
on memory resource management in Disco
before reading the paper.
And then finally, the last module
is an optional module.
It is a case study on VMM 1.0,
which is a system that I worked on
at VMware in 1998 and 1999.
It's also described in a recent paper,
and again, this is an optional module,
and it'll give you a sense of how
you can build a virtual machine monitor
that is commercial grade,
even on an architecture
that is not designed with
architectural support for virtualization.
So let's get started.
And let's get started
with a basic definition
of what virtualization is about,
and why it is important.
Virtualization is not a principle
in the same way that we've raised
other aspects of computer systems
to the level of principles.
It's not as important
as abstraction or as modularity,
but it actually uses
abstraction and modularity.
It creates an abstraction
in a virtualized...
a resource that is virtualized
is an abstraction,
from a computer systems perspective.
And that abstraction is used
in order to enforce modularity.
Virtualization is associated with
an enforced modularity,
and that enforced modularity, of course,
is enabled through the use of layering.
So we use layering and we use indirection
in order to create an abstraction,
and that abstraction enforces modularity.
Now, there are additional fundamental
principles of computer systems
that are brought into the mix,
in order to create
a virtualized environment,
in particular a virtual machine,
and one worth mentioning
is interpretation.
In order to create a computer
that is virtualized,
that computer has a processing unit,
and that processing unit,
and the instructions in that processing
unit need to be interpreted in some way,
and so interpretation is fundamental
to the art of building efficient
virtual machine monitors.
Now, why do you virtualize?
Well, there are actually
a number of motivations.
The original motivation
for virtualization,
whether it applies to computers,
or storage, or networking,
or other parts of computer systems,
has been largely to reduce complexity,
and that is one of the overriding themes
that we have in this class,
is that complexity
is the single largest evil
that one must constantly fight
in order to create systems
that are ever more powerful
and have additional new capabilities.
So virtualization is an efficient
and effective technique
to reduce the complexity
in computer systems.
More recently, virtualization
has been extremely popular
because it enables automation.
There's one important saying
that applies to data centers,
that says, "screwdrivers don't scale."
Which basically means that
the physical world,
that any manipulation
of the physical world,
is impossible to scale,
and impossible to automate.
If you apply virtualization
on top of physical resources
then the idea, or the premise,
is that you can start manipulating
these virtual abstractions
as if they were physical resources
without having to touch
either physical screwdrivers,
or the moral equivalent of screwdrivers.
Now, as I mentioned earlier,
virtualization is a broad technique,
virtual machine is a specific use
of that technique,
so I'm first actually going to define
virtualization in the broad sense,
and then we'll go back
to virtual machines.
So virtualization is a layer,
and it is a layer that exports
the same abstraction
as the layer that it relies upon.
It doesn't get any simpler,
or any more basic than that,
but that is actually fundamental.
So if you picture this representation,
you take any physical resource, "X",
picture, for now, a disk drive.
A virtualization layer
is a piece of software
that takes one or more of those
physical "X" resources,
those disk drives,
and exports an abstraction of a disk.
Now that disk, that virtual X,
that virtual disk, is not a physical disk,
but it is something
that is functionally equivalent
to the underlying characteristics
of a disk drive...
If X is, of course, a disk drive.
Now you can substitute X
to being an address space,
a CPU, a messaging interface, a port,
and you get the same idea.
So one of the key common themes
around virtualization
is that the piece of soft
that creates the abstraction
hides the physical names from
the consumer of that abstraction.
So as a consumer
of the virtual X resource,
you actually should never
be able to determine
what are the underlying
resources they consume
in order to create this abstraction,
and this is both useful,
as an implementation technique,
but more importantly it is fundamental
because it allows
the decoupling of the responsibility.
The consumer of the abstraction
uses the abstraction
as if it was a well-understood
physical building block.
The producer of the abstraction,
the software layer between the two,
has full flexibility
to change the mappings
between the virtual names
and the physical names,
at any point in time,
and that is the level of flexibility
that is enabled by the fact that
the physical names are hidden
from the underlying abstraction.
Now, because we hide the physical names
we naturally enforce modularity.
For example, we'll talk about
multiplexing as a technique,
as part of virtualization.
We can multiplex one resource
into multiple independent resources,
and those are naturally
isolated from each other,
because each virtual resource
operates on virtual names,
and the physical names,
are never available to the consumer
of the virtual resource.
Now, I mentioned multiplexing...
there actually are three ways
in which we can create
virtualized abstractions,
and these are broadly named as
multiplexing, aggregation and emulation.
The textbook actually goes over
those techniques in detail.
I'm going to give you a brief overview
of how these three techniques apply,
with some specific examples.
So, to illustrate
how virtualization is used,
the Saltzer and Kaashoek textbook
has a couple of examples
which come from the field
of operating systems,
so the use of virtualization
within an actual operating system.
And the first example
that they provide is that of threads,
so if you think about it
in this particular way,
an operating system and its scheduler,
a multiplex is a finite set of resources,
a finite set of cores,
and onto a larger set of threads,
and it's scheduled these threads
onto those limited set of cores.
So you can think of a thread
as a virtual CPU, and indeed,
a thread resembles the characteristics
of the physical CPU,
in particular critically,
it has the same register file
as the physical CPU,
and it runs the same
instructions and architecture
as the physical CPU.
So a thread, by that definition,
is a multiplexed instance of a core.
Now, a thread is actually
a little bit more than simply
a multiplexed instance of a core,
because a thread can issue system calls,
and so it is an augmented abstraction...
is not only a virtualized
instance of a core,
it is a virtualized instance of a core
augmented with the ability
to perform system calls.
The second example
that is provided in the book
is that of virtual memory.
And I want to emphasize,
and certainly I think no one
can overemphasize
the importance of virtual memory
in computer systems.
Some people even argue
it's the single biggest improvement
over the original von Neumann
architectural model.
Not only can we store
instructions in memory,
but these instructions
can operate on virtual addresses
rather than physical addresses.
And every computer has architectural
support for virtual memory
in the form of a TLB,
which caches these translations
between virtual names, and physical names.
So if you think about an address space,
a virtual address space,
it is a multiplex abstraction
of the underlying physical resource,
which is that of byte-addressable,
or word-addressable memory.
There are other examples
of the use of virtualization
beyond simply threads and virtual memory,
for example sockets, pipes,
virtual disks, are all examples
of virtualized instances
or virtualized abstractions
that are created by an operating system,
and exposed by the operating system,
that have a corresponding physical analog.
Now, there are three mechanisms
that are used to achieve virtualization:
multiplexing, aggregation and emulation.
I'm just going to spend a few minutes
going over some of these basic techniques,
and give some basic examples.
So I mentioned earlier the three
mechanisms used to virtualize,
so let's talk about them
in a little bit of detail.
The first one, and by far
the most important one,
is called multiplexing,
and multiplexing exposes
a single resource multiple times.
But there's a level of indirection,
and that level of indirection ensures
that each virtual resource
is isolated from each other.
Multiplexing is often implemented
with hardware support.
And the canonical example for that,
of course, is virtual memory,
in which the operating system,
with hardware support,
multiplexes physical memory
at a page-level granularity,
and exposes that into virtual resources,
which are the address space
of the various processes.
Now the second mechanism
provides the inverse function.
Rather than taking
one physical resource
and exposing it multiple times,
you take multiple physical resources,
and you expose them as a single resource.
Sometimes you do that
just to simplify management,
but generally you actually do that
to provide enhanced capabilities
to the aggregate resources,
capabilities not found
in the underlying physical resource.
And RAID is the canonical
example of aggregation.
You turn multiple unreliables,
small and slow disks,
into one very reliable,
bigger, and faster disk.
Of course, you can only do that
if you RAID enough disks together,
but the mechanism allows you to aggregate
and get the enhanced capabilities.
There are other examples of aggregation,
for example, the networking domain
where you turn multiple links
into one virtual link
with higher aggregate capacity.
And then, finally,
there's a third mechanism
which is the big hammer
of computer systems,
which is virtualization
through emulation...
you add a level of interaction,
and you do that through
general-purpose software.
This is the ability for software
to emulate a virtual resource
that is different from
the physical resource.
It turns out there are actually
many examples of this, all around us,
in particular how you emulate i/o devices,
such as disk tapes
or communication channels
using different physical resources
than you expose as a virtual resource.
And the approach is also used
in the computing domain,
for example to emulate
a legacy architecture on a newer one...
Apple did that very successfully
to allow the transition
from Power PC CPU's
onto X86 CPU's.
So I mentioned that emulation
is the big hammer for virtualization.
It always works in theory;
it's not always fast in practice.
And before that I mentioned
that multiplexing
often relies on hardware support
for performance,
and that brings us to the topic
of architectural support
for virtualization.
And by that we're trying to define,
or put a characteristic or a label
on a hardware component,
whether than hardware component
was designed to support
a particular form of virtualization.
A classic example is the memory
management unit of a processor.
Since the 1960's it's had
hardware support for virtualization,
and it has architectural support
for virtual memory
built into the memory management unit.
The concept of [harder] virtualization
has taken on a more important meaning
over the last few years,
as we've added support
or advanced capabilities of virtualization
into various pieces of a computer system,
for example, the CPU, the memory
management unit, or the i/o devices,
and that has specifically been driven
by the rising importance
in virtual machines in computer systems.
Now that brings us to a closing thought
for this first module.
A few weeks ago, in the layering cycle,
we talked about
the value of adding a layer
in a computer system stack
in order to built a new feature
or deliver additional capabilities,
and this week we're talking about
a specific way of creating a new layer,
one that re-exports the same interface
as the underlying resource
that it relies on.
And so for every particular problem
that you're faced with,
you have the choice...
First of all, whether it is wise
or appropriate, to add
a new layer of abstraction,
and by doing so, whether you should
expose a new abstraction,
different from the underlying one,
or re-expose the same abstraction
as the underlying one,
and create a form of virtualization
for the particular problem
that you're trying to solve.
Now, we've also seen in this module
that virtualization applies
to a very broad set of topics,
not just virtual machines...
a computer system, a disk, a database,
broadcast domains have been virtualized.
Anywhere you look
in the field of computer systems,
the notion that you can virtualize,
and apply the virtualization principle,
has been applied
at least one or a few times.
So, as we break for this first module,
let me leave you with a closing thought,
and something to think about at home.
For any given problem,
one that you are familiar with,
in your domain,
should you actually create a new layer,
with a different abstraction?
And when should you actually
try to expose the same abstraction
by virtualizing it?
What are the trade-offs,
and the pros and cons
in each particular approach?
So that's something for you
to think about at home,
and next up we'll talk about
the history of virtual machines.