Welcome back, now we're ready
to talk about virtual machines.
We're actually going to start to talk
about it from a historical perspective.
So a virtual machine is an abstraction,
it's the abstraction of a computer.
Think of a desktop, think of a laptop,
think of a server, but rather than being
implemented in hardware
it is an abstraction
that is implemented on
top of that same hardware
and can be multiplexed, multiple times.
(Edouard) The formal definition
of a virtual machine that is
universally accepted today
actually goes back to 1974.
Virtual machines actually predate 1974
by well over a decade
but this definition from 1974
is the one that we refer to today.
And this is actually a definition
from the paper
that you'll be reading this week.
And what Popek and Goldberg
have defined is a virtual machine
to be the efficient, isolated
duplicate of a real machine.
So in this diagram we have
two virtual machines,
each virtual machine has a CPU,
memory, and NIC and has some disk.
Each virtual machine is running
an operating system,
and each virtual machine
is running multiple applications
although we only show
one application in this slide.
And the key second part of the definition
from Popek and Golberg
is the definition of the piece of software
that creates the abstraction
of the virtual machine which is called
the virtual machine monitor.
And the virtual machine monitor
must have two important characteristics:
it must be in complete
control of the system.
So the operating system is unable
to actually control the system entirely,
it can only control the virtual hardware
of its virtual machine.
And the second key attribute
is that the virtual machine monitor
must use the underlying hardware
so that the programs running
in the virtual machine show, at worst,
a minor decrease in speed.
So Popek and Goldberg made that definition
in an era where operating systems
were already universal.
So we assume that an application
is running on top of an operating system
and the performance requirement
is that applications running on top
of an operating system
inside a virtual machine
run more or less at the same speed
as the same application running
directly on an operating system in the
absence of a virtual machine monitor.
A critical definition from Popek
and Goldberg back in 1974.
So this definition comes from 1974.
What's important to realize is by 1974,
virtual machines were actually already
somewhat on their way out.
So now let me even go back earlier
before 1974 and give you a little bit
of perspective as to where
we are coming from.
And specifically we need to go back
to the early mainframe era.
Now in that era,
and by that I mean the 1960s.
there were very few platforms.
A computer was extremely expensive,
it took a huge amount of space,
they were extremely few of them
and having the abstraction
of a virtual machine was actually
a very convenient tool
that allowed the sharing of resources.
If you could not afford your own computer,
at the very least you could have
your own virtual machine part of the time.
And that was compounded by the fact
that the operating systems of the time
were very limited in their capabilities.
The concept of time sharing
of multi-users was not even available
and so having a virtual machine
allowed people to rapidly innovate
within and among different forms
of operating systems.
You could have
different operating systems
running in different virtual machines
and that was a form of great efficiency.
Now at the time, actually
people went out of their way
to make it efficient to create
virtual machine monitors
and there was hardware
support for virtualization.
As a matter of fact, the paper that
you're reading this week
from Popek and Goldberg
actually is the formalization
of a set of engineering principles
that were by that point
relatively well understood
from an engineering perspective
and were formalized
and proven in their paper.
Now what's interesting about that era
is that very quickly we transition
into a phase where
virtual machines were rejected.
And they were rejected in favor
specifically of operating systems.
And that is because companies realized
that there was tremendous
innovation potential within
the operating system itself
and it was actually more interesting
to innovate within an operating system
than add the virtual machine
monitor layer.
And this actually gave us the rise of
the modern operating system
that we understand today.
Now because virtual machines
were less important
as people build new
generation of hardware,
people start building hardware
that actually didn't even
have architectural support
for virtualization.
And by the mid 1990s virtual machines
were completely viewed
as a relic of the past.
There was no good reason
to even get interested
in virtual machines at the time.
So I actually start to get involved,
personally, in virtual machines
around 1996 and at the time
this was viewed
an absolutely crazy research proposition.
There had been no research done
in the field of virtual machines
for well over a decade.
There were no new commercial products
using virtual machines.
And outside of the mainframe world
nobody even understood
or appreciated what you could actually do
with virtual machines.
Now our motivation at the time was that,
there was actually a case
to be made for the return of
virtual machines
simply when the operating system fails.
And we were living at the time in an era
where there was an assumption
that the operating system
could actually do its job properly.
It could actually succeed in
managing resources
and abstracting hardware.
And the work of my advisor
at Stanford at the time,
the prior work, was a system called Hive
which was an operating system
for a very large scale
machine called Flash.
And Hive was largely a negative result.
Now of course it was a functional system,
it actually did what it was
supposed to do, it had some
interesting research result.
The real take away from the work in Hive
was that the changes required
to the underlying operating system,
which was UNIX,
were way too extensive for an approach
like Hive to make any sense
and to be maintainable
and to actually make it
into a production level type of solution.
And that is simply because
the operating systems
by that time already had gotten
to be so big and so complex
it was extremely difficult
to innovate within the operating system.
So there's a case for virtual machines
to be made when
the operating system fails because either
it misses some appropriate functionality
or simply because it is in practice
too slow to innovate within an operating system.
There's actually another reason why
virtual machines might make sense
and that actually rationale
made sense in the '60s
and it actually makes sense today
in a very fundamental way
in the context of cloud computing.
And that is because the
operating system is special.
First, there can only be
one operating system
per machine and it can only be
one administrator of that
operating system per machine.
Now because the operating system
is special, there tends to be kind of
a monolithic culture
around operating system
and you have a lot of monopolies
and because you have monopolies
sometimes the operating systems
actually fail to innovate at the speed
in which they should if there was
a little bit more competition.
So two issues with respect
to operating system being special,
one is there can only be one leading
to new monopolies
and the second one is the fact that
it is impossible to have
two independent entities both be
administrators of an operating system.
And so the introduction of the layering
through the use of virtual machine
actually solves both these problems.
So this wraps up our module on
a short history of virtual machines.
Next up we'll go into the details
of how you actually can build
a virtual machine monitor.
See you then.