Welcome again.
Another module on virtualization.
This time, very specifically,
we'll talk about VMM construction,
how to create the piece of software,
the virtual machine monitor or VMM
that runs virtual machines,
and more importantly,
how to create that piece of software
so that the virtual machines
run efficiently.
Now the high level answer
is pretty simple.
In an earlier module,
we saw that there were three techniques
to virtualize resources.
You can multiplex, you can aggregate,
you can emulate.
Well, a VMM uses two of those
three techniques,
specifically it multiplexes some
resources and it emulates other resources.
Now there are two resources
that are critical to the multiplex,
and those are both the
CPU and the memory
and that's critical from a
performance perspective.
The last thing you want is for the
VMM to be in the way on the path
between the virtual machine
and the physical CPU,
or similarly you don't want the
VMM to be on the path
between the virtual machine
and its ability to access DRAM.
So both CPU and memory
are multiplex resources,
and in both cases, we export the
identical abstraction that we have
from the hardware to the
virtual machine.
So our virtual machine
has multiple virtual cores
and a virtual machine has some amount
of virtualized, physical memory,
which is different
from virtual memory.
Now multiplexing unfortunately
is not sufficient.
Sometimes you actually need to emulate.
You need to be on the path, at runtime,
between the virtual machine
and the hardware.
And this is where emulation comes in play.
And there actually are two forms of
emulation that are important.
One, is there is a class of instructions
that actually need to be emulated,
even in systems that have
architectural support for that,
and we'll define that in a few minutes,
and you'll also need to emulate
resources and devices
above and beyond CPU and memory
so that the virtual machine
has the illusion that it has a
complete hardware base.
So for example, a virtual machine
has a reasonable expectation
that it will have its own network device,
its own disk drive,
its own keyboard's on screen if it's
desktop and all these devices
are typically emulated in software,
rather than multiplexed in hard.
Now to understand how a virtual machine
monitor can multiplex the CPU resource,
we actually need to forget about
virtual machines for a second
and just go back to our understanding
of how an operating system
performs layering, and refresh
our understanding of that.
Now this picture actually comes from
the textbook from discussion,
from the chapter on layering.
And what this picture shows is that
there are two distinct APIs,
the hardware/software interface
exports the instructions
and architecture of the CPU,
and then there's the whole set of
instructions privileged or unprivileged,
that can be issued by software.
And now the operating system
multiplexes the CPU
and augments the abstraction
of a virtual CPU with the ability
to perform system calls, and that is what
we commonly understand as a thread,
so if you would be running
on a Linux system on x86,
your API as an application is the
combination of the ISA x86
as well as the ability to issue
POSIX system calls.
So if you actually think about it
from that perspective,
there is a layer in between the
application and operating system
and there is obviously a layer in between
software and hardware.
What's equally important to understand
and appreciate, however,
is that applications can actually
directly issue instructions to the CPU,
and that unprivileged instructions,
very specifically,
all are executed directly about the CPU
without the intervention
of the operating system.
If you had to go through the operating
system for every instruction,
things would go incredibly slow.
So let's keep that in mind, we have a
layering system that provides protection,
and yet we also have to ability,
selectively,
for the application to bypass the
operating system layer
and directly access the hardware,
and that is critical for performance,
in the classic operating system
and obviously as we will see,
this is equally important and equally
critical for a virtualized environment.
So with that background in place,
let's go back to VMMs
and try to picture how a VMM might
look like from a layering perspective.
Now as you would expect is that
some things would change,
and some things would not change.
The first thing that would not change is
the relationship between the application
and the operating system
because by definition,
a virtual machine is identical to the
piece of hardware that runs
without a virtual machine monitor,
but also there's now change
is the hardware/software API that is
basically the instructions
that architecture export
by the hardware
because we're assuming that the
hardware is now different.
What is obviously new here is that
we have a virtual machine monitor that,
from a layering perspective,
it sits between the hardware
and the virtual machine.
And that layering, that layer,
exports the same,
identical virtualized abstraction of the
underlying resource that it multiplexes
in specifically in the case of the CPU,
it would export a virtual version
of a core running the same
instructions that architecture as,
the underlying hardware.
And if you could do that, then at least
in [inaudible] everything would still work.
Obviously we would have an issue
with respect to performance
because this diagram
does not show any ability
to bypass a virtual machine either by the
operating system or by the application
in order to issue instructions
on the CPU,
and therefore the situation
would be relatively slow,
but we can hold that
thought for a second.
Let's first think about how this relates
in the context of multiplexing
and then we'll think about it from the
context of performance and efficiency.
So what do we mean by multiplexing?
Well first, the virtual machine monitor
multiplexes the cores
both in space and in time.
Now what that means specifically,
is if you have a system with multiple
physical cores that are shown here,
the virtual machine monitor can multiplex
these cores into the virtual--
the different virtual machines.
Now we can multiplex them in space,
in the sense that
you can have a virtual machine
with a smaller set of cores
that are available physically,
and it could run next to,
and in parallel with another virtual
machine that has another set of cores,
and that's actually the picture
that we're showing here.
But we're also-- can multiplex
the cores in time,
by scheduling the same physical core
among multiple virtual machines,
so it is absolutely possible for
this particular core
to be assigned to one particular
virtual CPU for a while,
and then be assigned to another
particular CPU, for,
at a later point in time.
And that is very similar to the problem
of scheduling in an operating system.
And yet, in all cases, a virtual machine
remains isolated.
So this is multiplexing of the CPU.
Let's now shift into the
discussion of efficiency
of the virtualization of the CPU.
And the key point here,
when in comes to efficiency,
is that we achieve efficiency
through direct execution,
and specifically, through the ability
in a controlled, and secured,
and layered manner that bypass
the layers selectively.
What we're basically, specifically doing
is augmenting the picture
that we saw that talked about
layer bypass in the context
of an operating system by adding a new
construct, which is the virtual machine.
So what we had in the earlier diagram,
is the ability for the operating system
to issue instructions directly
and for the applications
to issue instructions directly.
We insert a new piece of software,
the virtual machine monitor,
which is in full control of the system.
It obviously can issue
instructions directly,
but what's important here is that it's
the operating system and the applications
that can actually still issue
instructions directly on the CPU.
Now this is easier said than done,
and the reason the why this is complex
is that the virtual machine monitor
must, at all times,
remain in control of the system.
So that's one important relationship,
which is that the virtual machine monitor
needs to guarantee the integrity
of this interface that it exports
to the virtual machine
and guarantee the isolation
of the virtual machine.
And what's equally important is that
the operating system
needs to remain protected
from the application
because if you lose any of the isolation,
guarantees that the operating system
might expect, with respect,
to it's relationship to applications,
where you run into and you would open
a whole set of security issues.
So this is easier said than done,
but this is what we mean by
direct execution,
the ability for virtual machine software,
whether in kernel space or in user space,
to directly issue instructions on the CPU.
And this brings up to probably the
most significant contribution
to the theory of virtualization
and virtual machines,
and this is the Popek
and Goldberg Theorem.
This is the paper that you're reading
in this module.
This was published in 1974 and this
formalizes the characteristics
of an architecture that
can be virtualized.
And how specifically this theorem
defines a property
of instruction set architecture
and what it does for that instruction set
architecture is classify instructions
into at least two important categories:
the set of "privileged" instructions,
that's obviously a subset
of all instructions,
and the privileged instructions,
which are instructions,
can only be issued in kernel mode and can
only be executed by an operating system,
and then there's another category
of instructions,
which are called "sensitive" instructions,
and these are instructions
whose semantics vary
without causing a trap
based on the privileged level
that they're executing at.
So you basically have-- if you think
about the universe of instructions,
you have all instructions,
among them you have a subset
which are privileged
and a subset that is sensitive.
And what the theorem states is that
you can create a virtual machine monitor
that uses direct execution,
so the ability to bypass a layer
when executing both the application
and the operating system,
and you can only do that if all sensitive
instructions are also privileged.
So if instruction semantic varies
based on the privileged level,
and that instruction is not privileged,
that means it could be executed
by an application,
then it is not possible to build a VMM
that relies exclusively on
direct execution and layer bypass.
So this is a fundamental theorem.
Obviously there's an intuition behind it,
there's a proof behind it,
the paper focuses on the proof.
I'm going to limit myself here to it.
Some form of an intuition,
and the intuition is the following:
you can construct a
virtual machine monitor
that runs the guest kernel in user mode.
So if you assume an architecture,
a very simple architecture,
with only two layers,
kernel mode and user mode,
the operating system
is designed to run in kernel mode,
but if you somehow run the
operating system in user mode,
and emulate all privileged instructions
so that they fold the semantics
that would be expected of them
if these instructions had been
executed in kernel mode.
Then, you can actually convince
the operating system
that it's actually running in
kernel mode.
And therefore everything would work.
And that is the intuition,
and obviously this is only possible
if the semantics of instruction is not
a function of the privileged level,
or more specifically, if all sensitive
instructions are also privileged,
because that means that all
sensitive instructions
would create a trap and the virtual
machine monitor in software
has the ability to emulate those
sensitive instructions,
in order to represent the full
semantic of these instructions,
assuming that they
executed in kernel mode.
So this is where we go back to the fact
that in order to build a VMM,
you need to both multiplex and emulate.
You want to multiplex
as much as possible,
and yet a minimal VMM that is
running on an architecture
that is strictly virtualizable,
according to this theorem,
has some form of emulation for all
privileged instructions
of the virtual machine.
So this is the intuition,
obviously there are details,
there are details on the paper,
and that is one of the key
tasks for this week,
is for you to get a deep understanding of
how this theorem is constructed
and the implication that this theorem
has on architectural design.
We'll talk about it in our
discussion section,
in particular around the
historical importance
of this theorem as time went on.
Now the paper actually doesn't talk
about memory that much,
and once you read the paper,
you'll get a sense of
what I'm saying here.
So let me give you
a little bit of perspective
on how a virtual machine monitor
virtualized the second critical resource
that must be multiplexed,
and that is memory itself.
And the challenge is to
efficiently multiplex
physical memory of the real machine
into the physical memory
of the virtual machines.
Now this is a challenge
because obviously,
from a performance perspective,
because nearly every instruction accesses
memory and on top of that
every instruction is stored in memory
and so it must actually be done
without any runtime overheads.
So if you actually think about what
happens in this situation,
we're adding a level of
indirection between--
within the memory hierarchy.
So an application in orange
uses virtual addresses.
The operating system
manages the relationship
between virtual addresses
and physical addresses.
Now a virtual machine monitor,
which multiplexes memory
across multiple virtual machines,
adds another level of indirection
between the operating system's
view of memory--
of physical memory, and the virtual
machine monitor's view of physical memory.
So there are two distinct views
of physical memory.
And as a matter of fact, these two
distinct views of physical memory
are generally called "guest" physical
memory and "host" physical memory,
corresponding to the two
different levels of indirection.
What's important in this diagram
is actually not the relationship,
the layered relationship on the left,
but the relationship that you see
on the right that shows the TLB
mapping virtual addressees
directly onto host physical address.
Now by insuring that the TLB,
which runs as part of the
processor pipeline,
has mappings between virtual addressees
and host physical addressees,
we can insure that instructions can
execute at the normal rate
without any particular overhead.
Now this is easier said than done,
and it's very specifically a challenge
is how to insert into the TLB
mappings between virtual
and host physical addressees when
there actually are two levels
of indirections that need to be looked at.
And in the industry and in
computer systems today,
there are actually two generally
possible answers to this challenge.
The first one is to use
shadow page tables,
and the second one is to use
nested page tables
and I'm just going to very quickly illustrate
what we mean by both of them.
So let's first talk about
shadow page tables,
and that is the technique that is used
by the virtual machine monitor
when there is no architectural support
for virtual machines in the processor,
and very specifically when there's
no architectural support
in the memory management of the processor.
So effectively,
the virtual machine monitor
is left having to solve the problem
entirely in software.
And the way the virtual machine monitor
solves this problem,
is by keeping pages that define
address spaces in correspondence.
So the operating system, on top,
manages it's own address space.
The address space is typically
routed by a register
which defines the base
of the address space.
Now that register is actually
not used by the hardware.
The register that the hardware uses
is under the control
of the virtual machine monitor,
but the mappings that are
managed by the operating systems,
are obviously stored here and
those mappings relate to,
or define the mappings,
between virtual addressees
and guest physical addressees.
What the VMM does is it composes
this first mapping
with the mapping between guest physical
and host physical addresses,
and stores the resulting mapping
in a corresponding page
that shadows the original page.
So the term shadowing
defines the relationship,
between the guest page table pages
and the VM page table pages.
And as long as the VMM can effectively,
efficiently shadow these pages,
ensure that the correspondence is met,
then the entries inserted
into the TLB correspond
to the ones that are under the control
of the VMM and the virtual machine
is executing at full speed using--
because the mappings
between virtual addressees and
host physical addressees
are directly stored into the hardware.
And for completeness,
this picture also describes,
or illustrates, the fact that the VMM
itself needs to be somewhere in memory,
and there's typically a portion
of the address space
that is reserved for the VMM,
for this particular purpose.
So this is shadow page tables,
and again shadow page tables
is a technique that is required
when the hardware
does not provide architectural support
to virtualize physical memory.
Now as you can imagine,
maintaining shadow page
tables in consistence
can be quite expensive
and quite complicated.
As a matter of fact, there were
years of research
associated with how to make that
as efficiently as possible.
And fortunately also,
that research is no longer required
because now most systems
have hardware support
and architectural support
for virtualized physical memory.
And that is what the industry calls
nested page tables,
or extended page tables.
And so this is a hardware implementation
that actually walks through two
different sets of page table structures
simultaneously, in order to
reload a TLB entry.
So, you actually have
two hardware registers,
rather than one.
One in privileged mode,
one in de-privileged mode,
that determine the roots
of these address spaces.
The first one is the mapping between
virtual addressees and guest physical,
and the second one is the
mapping between guest physical
and host physical addressees.
And then as you walk through the
page table structures on a TLB reload,
the hardware automatically
looks at the coarse--
the combination of those two mappings
in order to find the right answer.
Now if you actually -- there's an
interesting [inaudible] paper on this.
The number of page table walks,
that is required
in order to provide and implement
nested page tables,
is quadratic with the depth
of the page table
and today most page tables
have a depth of four.
So this is actually a very large number
of memory references
that are potentially required
in order to do a nested walk,
and there are many alogorithms that
have been implemented also in hardware
in order to optimize the walking
of these nested page tables.
Now, I want to conclude this
module on VMM construction
with an orthogonal point that is
important because it's a recurring point
in the industry and often
an area of confusion.
And that is the classification
between type l
and type ll virtual machine monitors.
Now, this was actually also defined by
Goldberg in his thesis
in a separate document also in the 1970s,
and what very specifically the
document states
is that the type l
virtual machine monitors allocate
and schedule the physical resources
among the virtual machines.
So they not only perform the
multiplexing function,
but also perform the
resource management function.
And in contrast, the type ll VMMs rely
on a separate host operating system
for resource scheduling,
so in this case,
the VMM performs the multiplexing
function and the emulation function,
but the VMM does not perform the
resource management
and resource allocation functions.
And as we will see in the next module,
efficient resource scheduling
is actually fundamental to any
particular layered design,
and specifically fundamental to any
virtualized design.
And so the choice of the VMM architecture
type l versus type ll
is extremely important.
If you actually look at what is currently
out and available today,
we actually see a combination
of type l and type ll systems.
Most of you are probably familiar,
or heard of Xen,
which is an open-source type l hypervisor.
So it manages the resources itself,
it does the scheduling of the CPU,
and of the physical memory of the system.
There are other type l architectures
VMware or vSphere,
and Microsoft Hyper-V are two examples
of those architectures.
But equally importantly,
there are extremely important
and significant systems
that are type ll designs.
KVM is an open-source Linux based
type ll design,
it's main advantage over Xen
is that it is part of Linux,
and so it does not require a separate
hypervisor running on the bare metal,
but rather it can run a virtual machine,
any number of virtual machines,
as an extension of an existing canonical,
normal Linux based operating system.
And on your desktop or your laptops,
you're maybe familiar with
VMware workstation,
and if you have a Mac, you may be using
a product called Fusion,
which basically allows you run
any virtual machine
running any operating system on top of
the Mac OS operating system.
Parallels is another commercial company
that has products in a similar plane.
So there are two types of
virtual machine monitor architectures,
type l and type ll, both of them
are actually still used today,
with a little bit of a bias towards
type l in data centers and in the cloud,
and type ll designs in the
enterprise and on the desktop,
where convenience and
ease of installation
is actually the most important.
And with that, I want to thank you.
This is the end of the module
on VMM construction.
Goodbye.