Welcome back.
We're still talking about virtualization
and virtual machines,
but no longer about
the nuts and bolts of building a VMM
or how to multiplex resources,
but instead about
one of the fundamental problems
associated with virtualization,
which is the problem of resource
management in a layer environment.
And this module is a case study.
We're going to go over
some of the architecture
and some of the results
of a system called DISCO.
This is a project I worked on
in the late '90s at Stanford.
This was influential because it was
one of the first papers to propose
the use of virtual machines
in the modern era.
But if you actually
look at DISCO's contribution,
and I don't suggest you read the paper,
you'll see that many of
its contributions are actually
in the area of resource management.
How to efficiently manage resources
in an environment that no longer
runs a single operating system
but multiple operating system instances.
The approaches that were proposed
in DISCO have found their way
into commercial projects.
In particular, ESX server uses
a memory resource management
technique or set of techniques
that are improvements
upon the base approach
that was suggested in DISCO.
And that is the system
that you will be reading about
in Carl Waldspurger's paper
on memory resource management.
So let's go back to the late '90s
and at the time,
one of the big areas of research
in academia was in building
highly-scalable shared
memory multiprocessors.
So the idea was to aggregate
a very large number of resources together
both CPU and memory.
You had an interconnect
to connect all
these processing elements together
and DISCO was actually
the piece of system software
running throughout the machine
providing the abstraction of
virtual machines so that
you could actually
run a cluster of virtual machines
on these highly-scalable shared
memory multiprocessors.
Now, there are a number
of challenges associated with that
when it comes to memory
resource management.
The first one was to avoid having
unnecessary replication of memory.
Memory is a precious resource
even on a scalable multiprocessor.
It certainly was at the time.
So it's important to avoid unnecessary
replication of information.
You wanted to be able to take advantage
of the tight coupling that is enabled by
the shared memory hardware.
And then there's a second
class of optimization,
which I will not talk about,
which is you want to ensure
that the memory that is used
is whenever possible
local to the CPU
as opposed to remote.
So you want to optimize the locality
from a ccNUMA perspective.
Now the mechanism that we're using here
obviously is the fact that
there is an additional
level of indirection.
You will recall from the previous
module, this chart,
that talks about the relationship
between virtual addressees,
guest-physical addressees
and host-physical addressees
and the composed mapping
being inserted into the TLB.
Now what's important about this is
this obviously is one of the key
responsibilities of the VMM,
is to manage these mappings correctly.
But it's also one of the
most important leverage points
because the VMM can actually change
any point in time the mapping
between guest-physical addressees
and host-physical addressees
without impacting the operation
or the execution of the virtual machine.
And that is precisely the mechanism
that we will use and take advantage of
in order to optimize for memory.
So again, classically, we take advantage
of adding another level of indirection
into the system in order to optimize
its performance and its execution.
Now memory is a
particularly-known challenge
and in particular when
the memory is over-committed.
Of course, if you have enough
host-physical memory to run the aggregate
of all virtual machines,
things are not that complicated.
But things become very interesting
if you actually have a collection
of virtual machines which in aggregate
require more physical memory
than the host actually has.
Now this is a known problem.
It's actually a known hard problem
and if you look at the literature
of virtual machines on main-frames.
There is a well-known problem
that was diagnosed way back
probably as early as the 1960s which
is known as The Double Swapping Problem.
And so let's try to think about
what this actually means
because it's interesting to just
think about the complications
that arise in a layered system.
So, assume the virtual machine
monitor is under memory pressure.
So, we're running out
of host-physical memory
because the aggregate of the virtual
machines requires
more memory than we actually have.
Now if you think about the VMM being
an operating system,
the VMM can actually swap memory
in and out onto disc.
And this is actually what it does.
The VMM has the ability to swap.
So let's assume the case where
the VMM is under memory pressure
and swaps a page.
Let's call this page X.
Later, let's assume that an operating
system running in a virtual machine
becomes itself under memory pressure
because each virtual machine
is configured with some amount
of guest-physical memory.
So, the operating system
also has the ability to swap
and it decides to swap that same page X.
Now it turns out that that page X
is actually not in memory.
It's already on disc
but the operating system
because it's a layered system
does not know that the page is on disc.
And so in order to swap the page onto disc
it first has to bring that page
in a very gratuitous way back from disc.
So if you actually think about
the set of interactions that are going on
and the amount of traffic
going to and from the disc,
you end up having to bring
a page back from disc
onto memory-only to swap it
back onto disc.
Obviously, this is grossly inefficient.
And this is a known notorious problem
in mainframes.
Now the double swapping problem is hard.
You'll get an appreciation of it
in reading Carl Waldspurger's paper.
But in DISCO, we actually focused
on a first-order problem
which is that of the global use
and efficient use of memory
in a workload that can be partitioned
into multiple virtual machines.
So what we're seeing on the left
is a configuration of that workload
with a number of processes,
these are the orange boxes.
Running on top of a single operating
system running on top of the hardware.
And we compare that with the behavior
of that same workload
running on top of a virtual
machine monitor
in a collection of virtual machines.
So the processes could be partitioned
into the various virtual machines.
And we actually assume
from the CPU perspective
that the workload can actually
be partitioned in a relatively
straightforward manner.
But what we see here is that
there's one data structure
that gets replicated in an unnecessary
manner and that is the buffer cache.
And the buffer cache defines the set
of memory resources
managed by the operating system
which are the cache of the file system
pages that have been read from disc.
The picture on the left,
there's only one buffer cache.
So there's only one copy of pages read
from disc and memory.
Whereas, in the picture on the right
you have four virtual machines,
four operating systems and therefore,
four buffer caches,
which may each independently store
in their memory the same resources.
And the buffer cache is actually
a critically important
aspect of a workload
and a computer system.
As a matter of fact,
a significant fraction of the memory
is typically dedicated
to the buffer cache.
And so the question that
we're asking in DISCO is,
how can we transparently
share the buffer caches
without having to involve the OS?
How do we basically get the same
level of memory efficiency
when it comes to the buffer cache
in both configurations?
Now the solution that we came up with
is to transparently share
physical memory between virtual machines.
We leveraged on the fact that
there's an additional level of
indirection between
your guest-physical
and host-physical memory.
And furthermore,
we take advantage of the fact that
that relationship could either be
a writable, read-write topomapping
or it could actually be
a read-only relationship.
So you can transparently share two pages
that can only be read by two different
virtual machines that are using
the same physical resources.
Specifically we're using this technique
in two instances in DISCO.
We interpose on DMA to disc traffic
and we interpose on network traffic
in order to identify pages
that are known to be identical
because of the relationship
between these pages and the IO subsystem.
So let me first give you a perspective
on how this works for discs.
What we see here is a picture of two
virtual machines.
Both are reading and writing
to their own disc but this disc
is actually structured as a hierarchy
with a shared base disc
that is shared between multiple
virtual machines and a Delta Disc
which contains the unique elements
of each disc.
And each virtual machine
has a unique Delta Disc
where you store the writes
but each virtual machine
can transparently share
some of the resources
of the underlying base disc.
So, let's take the case
where we have
end copies of a nearly
identical file system.
So most of the time,
the operating system
will be reading from the base disc.
And whenever the operating system
reads from the base disc
what DISCO does, is associate that page
with a particular offset in the base disc.
And to then make that page read-only.
By doing that, you can actually avoid
subsequent reads to the actual
IO subsystem because
the second virtual machine
wants to read to the same page
we obviously look up the offset,
see if it's in the map
and if that is the case, we simply
can have the two virtual machines
point to the same location
rather than having to go to disc.
So this actually saves IO
and also saves memory.
Now whenever you transparently share,
you need to be able to undo the mechanism
that enables the transparent sharing.
And that is what we in systems
typically call copy-on-write.
Now there are two layers
in which copy-on-write applies.
This is one of the very useful
and generically useful techniques.
We apply copy-on-write
to the memory subsystem.
So if a virtual machine actually decides
to write to that page,
change the content of that page,
obviously the other virtual machine
should not see the changes
and so that triggers a page fault
because the mapping is read-only
and then we allocate at this point
a new distinct page for the virtual
machine that did the copying.
And then the second case
where we have copy-on-write
is obviously to the disc itself.
If you issue a SCSI write command
which means the virtual machine
wants to write to a particular offset
or a particular sector on the disc,
then we store the changes
in the Delta Disc
we keep the base disc unmodified
and then subsequent IO to that location
in the disc will actually be served
by the Delta Disc.
So a very simple technique
you interpose on DMA
and through that you actually reduce
the memory footprint
of virtual machines that have
the same base file system,
which is the common use case is
you're running 22 copies of Windows,
and these 22 copies of Windows
actually are all running the same
Windows based file system
and therefore you can have a significant
degree of sharing in your environment.
Now the second mechanism
that we use is the interposition
on networking and for that
I want to give you just a little bit
of background because
this is generically useful
on how virtual machines
communicate with each other
and how they communicate
with the rest of the world.
And the basic observation is very simple.
Which is modern operating systems
all have a built-in networking stack.
And so DISCO actually doesn't try
to have it's own networking stack.
Instead DISCO simply exports and emulates
the abstraction of an Ethernet NIC
to each virtual machine and then
DISCO implements the abstraction
of a software Ethernet switch
that can forward Ethernet packets
between VM and with
the rest of the world.
And so virtual machines communicate
totally and absolutely like real machines.
So DISCO's Ethernet switch
does have a twist and that twist
is that it can remap the fraction
of an Ethernet packet
that straddles an entire page.
We actually take advantage
of that not only to reduce
the amount of CPU cycles required
to communicate between virtual machines
but also the amount of memory
that is used.
In particular, we're using it
in the context of
higher level networking protocol
such as NFS which allow clients
and servers to share
the same network file system.
So if you look at the picture on the left,
what you see is the relationship
between an NFS server
and an NFS client.
And we're illustrating what happens
when there is the reply
from a read request back to the client.
So the server sends and creates a packet.
The payload of that packet comes directly
from the file system buffer cache
and DISCO's Ethernet switch is intelligent
enough to remap that page
rather than to copy the content.
But this is only one half of the answer.
The second half of the answer is that
the operating system
when it receives the packet
tends to actually copy the content
from its intermediate location
which is in the buffer that it received
into its final location which is
in its file system buffer cache.
And so the normal implementation
of an operating system
actually does a regular
call at that point.
We actually had to make a very small
modification to IRIX
to change this call into a hypercall.
So we basically asked the hypervisor
to do a copying using the memory
subsystem, a transparent copy
using the memory subsystem
semantically equivalent but without
requiring copying of data
rather than actually doing the copy
byte by byte.
And when you put this together,
you actually have a solution
in which you can transparently share
your file system buffer cache
between the NFS client
and the NFS server.
Now if you actually think about
the problem that I described,
and you fast forward back until today,
so 15 years later,
this problem is actually surprisingly
as important as ever.
And that is because the size of the VM
keeps increasing.
The density of virtual machines
keep increasing.
When people are running desktops
on servers, which is popular in some
use cases in the enterprise today,
you often see 100, 200, 300
virtual machines running on
the same high-density server.
So you have a tremendous amount
of density and sharing opportunities.
And the memory resource management
is extremely important in the context
of migration of virtual machine
because the memory
of the virtual machine is
the single largest resource
that needs to be shuffled around
over the network
and an efficient handle on
the memory sharing opportunities
reduces the costs of migration
in a significant manner.
Now the case study that I described,
describes an early system
if anything the first system
that actually tried
to transparently share memory.
It's preliminary and it's naive
in a number of ways.
It only works when you already know
that the content is going to be the same
and also it does not solve
some of the harder problems,
in particular, the double
buffering problem.
Those are key improvements
that you will hopefully
get an appreciation for
in reading Carl Waldspurger's paper
which is on the reading list
for this week.
And this wraps our module
on memory resource management.
Thank you very much.