Welcome back.
This is final module
for this week on virtualization.
This is actually an optional module
so feel free to skip
if you're short on time.
And this is a case study
on the original
VMware Workstation product,
which is a system
I worked on in '98 and '99.
Now, at the time we were not interested
in publishing papers.
We were building a product
for a commercial company.
And so, the paper was written in 2012,
so I had the chance
to write this with a little bit
of the benefit of hindsight.
This paper is not on
the mandatory reading list for this week.
But back in 1999,
we had a number of challenges.
And the first challenge
that we identified was
that the x86 architecture
was actually not virtualizable.
So we learned in the previous modules
of the importance
of Popek/Goldberg theorem.
And I also gave you
a little bit of a sense
that people had forgotten
about that theorem.
Indeed, when it came to
the x86 architecture,
the 32-bit architecture at the time,
it was clearly not virtualizable.
There were 17 instructions
that grossly violated
the Popek and Goldberg criteria.
And this was a problem.
This was not just a theoretical problem,
this was an actual
pragmatic, practical problem
because our goal was to run
on modified operating systems,
and in particular,
our first goal was to run
Windows in virtual machines.
Now the second challenge
that we identified was
that the x86 architecture
is of daunting complexity
and for any one of you
who's actually dealt with
x86 at the assembly level
you probably have a sense
of what I'm talking about.
If you think about this
from a systems perspective,
the reality gets even worse.
There is an unbounded combination
of protections, segmentation,
paging, execution mode mechanism,
that overlap with very bizarre semantics.
The list is actually not something
that I can enumerate in my head.
And none of the modes,
except one minor 16-bit backward
compatibility mode called Virtual 8086
were virtualizable according
to the Popek and Goldberg criteria.
But beyond that,
there were additional challenges
that we identified.
We were trying to start a small company
and we were trying to introduce
the notion of running virtual machines
on x86 systems
and we realized very quickly
that the diversity of peripherals
was going to be a very significant issue
because it's one thing
to virtualize the x86 CPU.
It's one thing to use
Shadow page tables
to virtualize memory
which are the two multiplexing
techniques I've talked about.
But when you actually build
the real products
you realize that you also need to do I/O
and you need to do I/O
in a very broad sort of platform
so this can very quickly be challenging.
And finally we also recognized early on
that we needed to have
a very simple user experience
so that people could actually
test out the product
without actually having to
reinstall their systems.
And all of these challenges,
these four main higher-order challenges,
all fed into critical design points
of the emerald workstation.
And of those points,
I'm going to focus on
two of these contributions.
The first one is the contribution
on how to create a type II
Virtual Machine Monitor
that can run on top of an operating system
like Linux or Windows.
The type I vs. type II classification
was originally designed
at a time when operating
systems were running...
where the protection,
the notion of protection
was actually different than it is today.
Now by building a type II system,
and by going after a type II system,
we actually, off the bat,
can address the issue of device diversity
and the user experience
simply because the host operating system
is in charge of device diversity
and the host operating system can present
the experience of,
a simple experience of running
a virtual machine monitor
as an application.
And then the second challenge
that we faced
obviously was how to virtualize x86
in the context of
these sets of instructions
that failed the Popek
and Goldberg criteria.
So let's talk about these
two contributions.
The first contribution is really aimed at
providing a simple user experience.
So we run as a type II hypervisor.
So, logically speaking,
and from a learning perspective
the host operating system is
in full control of virtualization layer,
which is the VMR software,
runs as an application
on top of the host operating system.
And it is in full control
of the virtual machines
so the guest operating system
in the applications
run inside the virtual machine.
And then obviously, the application runs
under the control
of the guest operating system.
So you have very nice
Russian doll-type diagram here
that illustrates the layered relationship
between the different
entities in the system.
Of course, the challenge is
how do you actually build that
and how do you build that
in a way that is fast.
So our solution to that
challenge was actually
to break the VMware software
into different components.
If you look at the picture right now,
what you see is the CPU,
the host operating system,
and any arbitrary application
running on top
of the host operating system
making system calls to
that host operating system.
While VMware rather than being
one piece of software
is actually broken up into
multiple components
the user perceives the application
to be exclusively running
as an application
on top of that same host operating system,
making system calls like
any other application would.
But in reality that application
is really just a proxy for
the Virtual Machine Monitor.
And the Virtual Machine Monitor
runs in an environment
in which the host operating system
is actually no longer present in memory.
So we have an environment
where we have two context:
the host context and the VMM context.
And we have the ability to switch
between these two context.
We actually call that switch,
"the world switch,"
because it's much more
than a process switch.
It is a complete switch
of the address spaces.
To the point that when
you're running in the VMM context,
the host context is no longer present
in the address space of the CPU
and vice versa.
If you're running in the host context,
then the VMM is no longer [inaudible]
into the address space of the CPU.
Now, surprisingly, that implementation
can actually be extremely efficient.
You can switch between these context
with something that costs
just a little bit more
than a normal context switch
between two processes.
And by running into the VMM context
and effectively by throwing
the host operating system
out of the system
at least for some amount of time,
then the VMM has the full flexibility
to reconfigure the hardware
and meet exactly the requirements
that it needs in order
to efficiently run a virtual machine.
And so the system goes back
and forth between these two.
If you're interested
there are details in the paper
as to when we actually go back and forth
between these two.
We do it whenever the VMM
needs to make a request
on behalf of the virtual machine
that has access to a system resource,
like sending a network package
or doing Disk I/O
in which case, that is done
by the application,
the VMX application.
And also whenever
there is an I/O interrupt,
we restore context from the VMM
back to the host,
so that the operating system can handle
all device interrupts,
as if it was always
in full control over the system.
And the magic trick to make
that happen is to have
a little Kernel driver
that runs within the operating
system that does this.
So this was the first challenge.
The second challenge is
the virtualization
of the x86 architecture.
Now, because we now understand
the Popek and Goldberg theorem,
we know that we cannot use
the classic technique,
and the classic technique was simply
to use "trap-and-emulate,"
and we know that this is not possible.
So, at the same time we also know
that we need to support
binary compatibility.
So, the critical observation behind
the second contribution of VMware
is that most of these
x86 sensitive instructions
are only sensitive
when executing system software.
So, the instruction can be sensitive,
based on the level
that it is expected to run at,
or it cannot be sensitive,
in certain cases.
It turns out that most
of these instructions
are sensitive when
they're running in a kernel,
but they're not sensitive when
they're running in the application.
And when I say "kernel"
and "the application"
and when I say "system software,"
we're using extremely loose definitions
of these terms up until now.
And so our high-level solution is to use
a combination of two techniques.
The first one is the well-known
trap-and-emulate technique,
but we only use that
whenever that is possible
and we specifically only use that
when these sensitive instructions
are not sensitive.
For the current point in time.
And when that's not the case,
then we must rely on
another technique,
which is the big hammer
of computer systems,
which is the emulation layer.
So we use an emulation technique
known as binary translation
to convert the original
instruction stream,
which is an x86 instruction stream,
into a converted x86 instruction stream,
in which faithfully emulate
the semantics of all instructions
including the sensitive one.
So I mentioned the term
binary translation.
Let me just give you one slide
on what I mean by that.
This is a technique in which
a dynamic compiler
running as part of the VMM
converts a basic block
of virtual machine instructions,
so this is an x86 instruction sequence,
and it converts it into
another instruction sequence
that can be executed directly in the CPU
in a way that is safe
and that faithfully emulates
the semantics of the architecture.
Now, compilation is expensive.
Translation is expensive,
so you want to minimize
how often this is done.
So there's a large data structure
called a translation cache,
which is a buffer that holds
these translations,
and then there's a main,
a high-level dispatch function,
which basically allows you
to jump into the translation cache
and start executing instructions directly.
And then there are
a large number of optimizations
that make it efficient
in particularly the ability
to go directly from one basic block
to another basic block
within the translation cache.
Now, the challenge in
a binary translation system,
and these are systems that have been
prominently used for simulation purposes,
is they have something like
a 5x to a 10x slowdown.
If you're familiar with
the QEMU binary translator,
those are the type
of performance numbers
that you should expect.
And obviously a 5x to 10x slowdown
is completely incompatible
with a virtual machine monitor.
And so our solution to building
an efficient binary translator
was to actually specifically
configure the hardware
and use the hardware to avoid many
of the software overheads
and in particular the result
we were able to achieve
is one in which most
of the instructions
are translated one-to-one.
So, in this example,
I have a basic block
with three instructions.
The first two instructions,
which are representative
of innocuous instructions
that simply manipulate memory,
had to be converted
on a one-to-one basis.
And that is actually not
the traditional output
of a binary translator
that is running a full system simulation
because it needs to do bounce checks
and indirections and other things.
Now, the reason we don't need
to do bounce checks
is because we've configured the hardware
to do the bounce checks on our behalf.
Now there's a third instruction
that actually does require an expansion.
In this case, I took sort of
a complicated example.
This is a registered indirect call
that expands into a stub,
followed by a jump to another function
that actually will do the work.
Now, what you actually see in this stub
is a couple of instructions
that use a specific register
and that register is called "gs,"
and it's a segment register.
And that segment register was reserved
by the binary translator
only to be used on behalf of the VMM.
So, the virtual machine cannot
directly access that register
and that register gives
you access to sort of memory
that is not otherwise available.
And that is the basic trick
that allows us to operate
without any form of
software fault isolation.
Now, sandboxing is
when the virtual machine
uses normal segments,
these segments are truncated
so that they never overlap
with the VMM portion.
And if there's any attempt
that we actually need to
emulate that attempt.
Conversely, the binary translator has,
using this gs register,
the ability to access
locations and memory
that are not otherwise available
to regulate instruction.
So again, we use hardware in order
to make the binary translator efficient.
Now, having a trap-and-emulate system
and having a binary translator itself,
is actually not sufficient
to the technical result.
The key technical result is
actually a decision algorithm
which determines when
direct execution is possible
and conversely when
binary translation is necessary.
And that decision algorithm,
one of its interesting characteristics is
that it can execute in constant time.
It does not require any inspection
of the instruction stream.
It's not a function of the
architecturally-defined registers.
It's only a function of the
system-defined register state
as well as the segment state
of the system.
So for example,
if the virtual machine is in a state
where it runs in kernel mode,
or it it's in a state where
it can disable interrupts,
then direct execution is not possible
because you could get to the point
where you could actually
take over the entire system.
However, if you're running
an application space
and if you're running in a mode
in which you cannot disable interrupts
in application states,
which is true of 99.99% of applications
running on top
of an operating system,
then you can actually use
direct execution.
But that's only one of the many criteria.
There are other criteria.
For example, you have to be running
in protected mode,
or have to be running in
virtual 8086 mode,
there's some legacy modes in the systems
which were commonly used at the time
that are not virtualizable,
and whenever you're in one
of those legacy modes
then you need to use
binary translation at all times.
And in final, there's a
final technical complication
which has to do with
the reversibility of segments
which I will not go into.
So, if you put those together,
you actually end up
with a decision algorithm,
a set of constraint problems,
and if all the constraints are met,
then direct execution is possible.
If any of the constraints are not met
then binary translation must be used.
And so the definition of system software
is actually, at least in our current
terminology at the time,
the definition of
system software was software
that actually required
binary translation,
and conversely, application
software was application
that actually could take advantage
of the direct execution techniques
and the trap-and-emulate techniques.
There are many details
for that in the paper.
The good news is that those definitions
of system software versus
application software
largely overlap with what
we commonly understand
as applications
and operating systems today
Now, the good news is that
that level complexity
is no longer required today
and that is because in 2005
AMD and Intel both introduced
hardware support for virtualization
So basically an extension
of the architecture
that actually finally met
the Popek and Goldberg criteria.
And the way this was done
is by deduplicating
the four protection rings
available in protection mode
of the architecture so that
you could actually run virtual machines
running the full 64-bit,
x86 extended instructions
and architecture in virtual machine,
on top of a virtual machine monitor
that only used trap-and-emulate technique
and did not require
extensive forms of binary translation.
And with that, this is the wrap
for both this module
and this week on virtualization.
I look forward to discussion section.
Thank you.