Hello and welcome back.
Yes
in this segment we wish to briefly
describe the underlying logic
behind The Market Opportunity
Navigator.
As pointed out before The Market
Opportunity
Navigator is easy to apply
business tool that helps you to make
the right market opportunity
choice. Exactly
but to make the right choice
you actually need to understand
three important questions;
First,
what are the market opportunities
that are actually available for us.
Second,
what are the most attractive market
opportunities for us.
And then third,
what market opportunities should
we focus on.
Corresponding
with these three important questions
The
Market Opportunity Navigator
includes
three steps.
First, the "Market Opportunity Set"
which helps you to identify the most
attractive
market opportunities for your
technologies
or for your resources.
Second, the "Attractiveness Map"
which helps to understand the
value inherent
and the challenges inherent in each
of the market
opportunities.
And third, the "Agile Focused
Strategy"
which helps to make a smart
strategic
choice, where to focus
but also which other options to keep
open.
Exactly, and this is how
the main design board of the
Navigator
looks like
with the three steps that Marc just
described.
You can actually use sticky notes
to represent each market opportunity
and mark them on the dartboard.
First,
your market opportunity set,
second,
your attractiveness map;
and third,
your agile focus dartboard.
Overall this tool guide you
step by step
as you progress from the many
possible options,
to recognizing patterns among
these options to make distinctions
between these
options to ultimately arriving
at a well-designed strategy
for your venture.
Yes, and the final
outcome of this process is
the Agile Focus Strategy.
Let's take a moment to understand
what it
actually means.
The Agile Focused Strategy clearly
defines the market opportunities
that you will pursue now
and the opportunities that you will
keep open
as backup all growth options.
This helps you to manage your
startup
with foresight
and agility while facing
uncertainty. And what you create
is ultimately a smart portfolio of
options
and smart portfolio of options,
these options are actually
very essential, very important to
run
in the right direction
and do so
with agility.
Also in case you need to pivot over
time.
Eventually,
and that's what we've seen
with many startups already it
will help you to unleash the
potential inherent in your resources
and create the most value from your
effort.
And also,
the Agile Focus Strategy has
many implications for how you
build and design your venture.
Exactly.
In addition to the benefits of the
Agile
Focus Strategy which is the outcome
of
this process using a framework
for making this profound decision
can actually help you in making
a more informed choice
one that will increase your
likelihood
for succeeding.
And it will also come to think about
it
provide you with a shared language
within the team
when you want to debate discuss
about
market opportunities but also
with other people around.
Think about when you talk about
talk with venture capitalists
business agents
anyone who might have an interest in
your startup,
this provides a very precise
language.
Exactly,
and not just that
you know market opportunity choice
might
change over time.
So you can always go back
to the structured evaluation
trace it track it
and update your strategy if
necessary.
Accountability is one thing,
and looking forward is another
thing.
Exactly.
Have you been asking yourself
lately,
how do I identify blockbuster market
opportunities?
Have I missed out on any?
How do I know what is the most
attractive
market opportunity for us?
Okay now, let go of seemingly
attractive
options,
and if market opportunity
choice is so important,
how can I hedge my bets?
If you have been asking yourself
those questions
and perhaps others this MOOC
is for you.
Yes it will show
you how to use the Market
Opportunity
Navigator to support your market
choice
and therefore make sure that you are
running
in the right direction
and remaining agile while doing so.
Join us.