Hello
and welcome to our MOOC which
market to play in a tool for
entrepreneurs
and innovators.
I'm Sharon
and I'm Marc
and will be our guides for this
course. In this course we
wish to help entrepreneurs
and innovators in making one of the
most
profound decisions for the venture
that is which markets to
play in.
For this purpose
we will present to you an easy to
apply
business tool called the market
opportunity
navigator that offers a
structured framework for making this
complex
and many would say most important
decision in your venturing
or innovation process.
But before we go into the details
let us briefly introduce ourselves.
So I'm Marc Gruber
I'm vice President for Innovation of
EPFL
which is the École Polytechnique
fédérale de Lausanne the Swiss
Federal Institute
of Technology in Lausanne in
Switzerland
that beautiful Lake of Geneva so
we cannot complain about on
location.
I'm professor for entrepreneurship
and technology commercialization at
my school
and in this capacity after lots of
research lots of teaching on
technology commercialization
amongst others
you know on this idea of market
opportunity identification that we
will talk about
in this book
and I'm Sharon Tal the
co-founder
and former executive director
of the entrepreneurship center at
the Technion
Israel Institute of Technology.
I also teach marketing for many
years now both for films
and start ups using my
vast experience as a marketing
manager and as a strategic
consultant.
So over the last years we've done
lots of
research projects we basically
investigated hundreds if not
thousands
of start ups in
technology to understand this very
critical early states decision
of what type of market you can
identify
and focus on.
We actually learned many
things from these studies
but probably the most important
thing that we understood was
that there was no structured
framework for entrepreneur
and innovators when they strive
to make this profound decision.
This actually turned to be the basis
for the market opportunity
Navigator.
And together we wrote this book here
that takes you by the hand
and guides use of the three steps of
the
market opportunity navigator.
The book is filled
and the book is filled
with lots of interesting examples
case
studies from many countries around
the world.
This book will be your companion for
this MOOC.
So to begin with let's look at the
market opportunity
choice in firms.
This is a very profound decision for
two main reasons.
First your choice of market
opportunity will influence your
chances for success.
It will influence how you get
traction
in the market how you gain profits
and how you create value for your
films.
So in a way it's like finding
fertile ground
and growing your tree on the fertile
ground.
But second it also imprints your
venture
or your innovation process in the
sense that
the decision that you make in terms
of your focus market
will then shape other decisions
that you will take over time
and that then puts you in a
certain trend channel
or path.
And this will actually be very
difficult to undo if
you need to change direction.
Exactly and that's why this is such
a profound decision.
However this is a very
difficult decision to make.
As David Roth the co-founder
and CEO of Opfers wrote
in an interesting article on Forbes
understanding where to focus is
a real dilemma for entrepreneurs
and he also mentions in that article
that firms rarely fail because
their teams don't work hard enough
but they fail because their teams
actually
work on the wrong things.
So why is this such a difficult
situation or decision?
Well first there is
always uncertainty.
Uncertainty is actually inherent
to the innovative process.
There will always be known unknowns
and also unknown unknowns
that will make this decision
difficult for you.
And then there are always trade-offs
you know think
about some markets being large
growing
quickly other markets being small
but well protected et cetera
et cetera. So it's a
decision with many variables to
decide on.
And in addition markets
are constantly changing
and what seems to be promising today
might turn out to be less
promising in the future.
Making the right market opportunity
choice is
definitely key for creating
significant
value and success.
But as we saw from our studies there
are several
possible mistakes that entrepreneurs
might
make as they go through this
process.
So let's see what can go wrong as
you make your market
opportunity choice.
First start ups may simply
choose to focus on the wrong
market opportunity that is
an opportunity that does not bear
real potential for value creation.
In fact many well-known
firms started by focusing
on the wrong market opportunity.
Just take a look at all these
well known companies beyond
us what they all have in common
is starting with the wrong market
opportunity.
Luckily for us they managed to
change
their strategy
and find a promising
opportunity at the end.
And this is not only anecdotal
evidence actually
there's lots of research out there
that looks at
this question why firms fail
and there is one study for
instance by CBN search that looked
at 100
more than 100 startups
and they found that 42
percent of these startups actually
fail because
there was a lack of market need
so there's clearly something to be
learned from
that insight as well.
So before you start
running fast make sure
that you're running in the right
direction
but choosing smartly
doesn't end in finding the most
promising market opportunity to
focus
on you must also
take into account how to focus
without losing your agility.
In fact an improper
balance between focus
and flexibility is actually
the second mistake when
startups choose their market
opportunity
strategy.
Why would this happen?
Well on one hand startups must focus
sharply
or else they won't be able to
survive
and the reason for this advice is
fairly clear.
More ventures as costs on resources
and thus they must not spread their
efforts totally
but that is a
big BUT on the other hand Startups
must stay flexible
and agile to be able to adapt
quickly
because unforeseeable things may
happen along the way
and typically do happen.
So if you choose one market
opportunity
and completely ignore all other
options
you might be in trouble down the
road.
In order not to lose your focus
but also not to get trapped you
need to keep some market
opportunities
open.
This will help you to develop your
resources
and capabilities in a wider manner
and keep your cognitive flexibility
up.
So here is a quote by Stephen Kaufer
who was one
of the founders of TripAdvisor
the well-known firm he says if you
are a lightning
focused on just one thing
and aren't willing to consider
others
you probably don't have the
flexibility
to make it when things don't go
according
to plan.
So that's one truism;
things won't go according
to plan.
So as you start running
make sure not to lock yourself
into one specific direction.
In this MOOC we
will present to you The Market
Opportunity
Navigator which will help you to
make
the right market choice
and reap the greatest benefit from
your
commercialization efforts.
The Market Opportunity Navigator
is a business tool that will help
you to discover promising
market opportunities evaluate
their value
and set your strategic focus
smartly to make sure that
you are running in the right
direction
and remaining agile without
losing your focus.
Join us in this exciting
learning journey.