Hi there and welcome.
In this segment we will briefly
discuss the different use cases
for the Market Opportunity Navigator
so you can understand if this is
applicable
to your own situation
or dilemmas.
The Navigator offers
a structured process
to support your market opportunity
choice.
It can be applied in
many business situations
by different types of users.
Probably the most important
point to begin
with is that you can apply
the three steps of the Navigator
according to your own needs.
Although we portray the Navigator's
process in a stage manner,
is actually possible
and sometimes even more useful
if you apply the navigator
in a different order
or simply use the individual
parts according to your specific
questions or dilemmas.
It is also possible
to start the process from different
entry points depending on
what you already know
and what you have already decided.
For example,
you may use the navigator to compare
potential market opportunities
but not to generate alternatives
or to build a smart portfolio
around the target market opportunity
that you already pursue.
Other than that,
the navigator is suitable for
different types of entrepreneurial
beginnings.
Some firms start
with the intention to address a
specific
market need.
This approach is typically called
Market Pull.
If your firms
and falls in this category
you will find great value
in applying the market opportunity
navigator
because it allows you to evaluate
your initial target market.
If this proves to be a worthwhile
opportunity you can then
build an Agile Focused Strategy
around it.
If it turns out to be a
weak opportunity the navigator
will assist you in discovering more
valuable options.
On the other hand,
some firms may start
with developing a technological
invention
and search for potential uses
for their technology,
they are typically called
Technology Push Firms.
If your film falls in this
category you will find
great value in applying the
navigator
because it allows you to discover
possible market opportunities
to evaluate them
and to develop your Agile Focus
Strategy.
But the navigator is not
only useful for setting your
initial market entry strategy.
In fact,
finding the right direction for your
run is a difficult question
that bothers entrepreneurs
and innovators not only
as they choose their initial path,
but also overtime
as they strive to pursue it.
Because things may constantly
evolve
and new parameter may require
additional attention.
So with the navigator
you can capture your ongoing
learning and update your situation
effectively.
It allows you to trace back,
track
and update your decision.
If strategic changes are required
you will see them more easily.
It will also come handy when
pivoting
is required.
If you hit the wall
and need to recalculate your route
the navigator will assist you in
discovering evaluating
and choosing your new strategy.
Lastly,
running in the right direction is
also a relevant question when it's
time to grow your business.
Whether you are still a startup
or a larger enterprise
the navigator will be useful
as you search for your next pathway
to success.
Because the navigator is valuable
not only for a setting your initial
strategy
but also over time as you grow
and evolve.
It is suitable not only for
startups
but also for well-established
firms.
Startups that face
an inherent uncertainty
usually struggles to find their path
to success.
They need to focus on pursuing the
most
valuable opportunity on the one
hand,
and to hedge their bets
on the other
and all with limited resources.
The navigator can guide
entrepreneurs
to do just that.
It will help them to identify
and map their options
and to choose a path that can lead
them to success.
As for established firms
they often struggle to create
the most value from their existing
assets
and to identify opportunities
for new growth.
The navigator will help establish
firm to identify the next
BIG thing
and to manage their innovation
funnels smartly,
so that their entrepreneurial
endeavors
are better positioned
for success.
In addition to small
and large firms there are
other types of users that can find
the navigator valuable for their
needs.
First,
technology transfer offices
that attempt to commercialize
innovative
technologies stemming from their
laboratories
can use the navigator to find
potential applications
and customers for these inventions.
Second,
investors that are constantly
looking for promising businesses
can use the navigator as a
screening tool to evaluate
the attractiveness of an
opportunity,
and if it proves to be
interesting to encourage
the development of a smart portfolio
around it.
Third,
educators
and accelerators that attempt to
accompany budding entrepreneurs
can use this business tool
to clearly lay out
all the major considerations
of this important process
and to enrich the toolbox
of their trainees.
To summarize,
identifying,
evaluating
and exploiting new market
opportunities
is core to creating significant
value for anyone who
is dealing with commercializing
innovations.
The navigator can therefore be
applied
by different types of users
and also at different
phases of the venture.
Starting with the initial strategic
conception
and accompanying managers overtime
whenever they need to change,
adapt or advance their