Hello and welcome back in this video
we're going to show you the market
between
navigator
in a nutshell.
Yes.
The market opportunity navigator is
designed to help you master
your market opportunity choice.
It offers three steps for
discovering
and strategizing your most valuable
market opportunities.
So what are the three steps?
First, you search broadly in order
to understand which market
opportunities exist
for you, the outcome will be your
Market
Opportunity Set.
Second,
you assess deeply to understand
which market opportunities are most
attractive for you,
the outcome will be your
Attractiveness
Map.
And third, you're going to
strategize smartly
in order to understand which market
opportunity to
focus on,
the outcome will be your Agile Focus
Dartboard.
Based on these three steps we have
designed three dedicated worksheets
that lead to three important
outcomes.
You can then depict these outcomes
in a visual manner so the choice
becomes more apparent.
So let's briefly go over these
three steps of the market
opportunity navigator.
First, the Market Opportunity Set.
Exactly. This is the set of
potential
market opportunities that you can
address
with your core resources
and abilities.
It can be related to different needs
for different types of customers.
Why is this important?
Well, market opportunities can
vastly differ in their
attractiveness.
Having a set of options
can help you choose the most
promising
opportunity
and also provide the basis for plan
B or for unlocking your growth
opportunities in the future.
Exactly.
Worksheet 1 will guide you through
this
process. It starts
with a delinking step
to examine your own resources
and capabilities in a more fungible
way
detached from the products that you
may have
already envisioned.
This is then followed by a relinking
process where you try to combine
your
core abilities in different ways
in order to discover different
applications
for different sets of customers.
So it's delinking
and relinking.
And the outcome is your market
opportunity set which can
be depicted on the Navigator
using sticky notes to represent
each opportunity.
The second step is the
Attractiveness Map.
So what is an attractive market
opportunity?
It's one that has high potential
and a little challenge of course,
you know so with this tool you're
going to
depict each individual market
opportunity
under Matrix
and try to visually understand
the upsides and downsides
and then be able to compare their
overall nature.
So why is this so important?
Because marketing is different in
their potential.
You want to make an informed
decision about this very important
choice that you're engaging in a
venture creation or the innovation
process.
So intimately
you rely less on intuition
and suffer less from your own
biases.
To evaluate each market opportunity
in a structured
and clear manner,
we have designed worksheet 2 that
will guide you through this process.
The left column guides you how
to estimate the potential of a
market opportunity.
It is comprised of three different
factors
that can then be combined to an
overall
potential rating.
The right column of worksheet 2
guide to how to evaluate the
challenge they mention
once again it is comprised of
three different factors
which you can then combine to
an overall challenge
rating.
Once you assess the attractiveness
map
market opportunities
and create each option based on its
potential
and its challenge you can then look
at
them on the attractiveness
map here in the middle,
this is the outcome of step
two.
The third step is your Agile Focus
Dartboard.
Yes.
The dartboard depicts your Agile
Focus Strategy.
It clearly defines the opportunities
that you will pursue now
and those that you will keep open
as back up or future options.
So why is this important?
Well, the agile focused strategy
allows you to mitigate your risk
and increase your value without
losing your focus
and that's how you
can avoid a potentially fatal
locking.
So finally worksheet 3 three
helps you to design your agile focus
strategy,
specifically once you choose your
primary
market opportunity it will assist
you in finding the best backup
options
and growth options based on their
attractiveness
and their relatedness to your
primary opportunity.
You will then need to decide how
much effort
you want to invest in these options.
Will you pursue them now
in parallel to your primary
opportunity,
keep them open
or simply place them in storage
for potential future use.
The result of this process is
your Agile Focus Strategy
which can then be depicted on the
Agile Focus Dartboard.
Overall you can think of this as
being a white
land strategy that has significant
implications
for how you build your resources
and capabilities
and also for how you design your
venture.
So whenever you need to think about
your strategy
either for the first time
or when navigating your pivot
or your growth move applies
to navigate or to set your strategy.
Ultimately it will help you to make
sure that you're running in the
right direction
and remain agile while doing so.
As a final note Don't forget
that this is a learning process
and the navigator is actually
your learning companion.
It helps you to ask the most
important questions
before making such a profound
decision.
So appreciate the process
and not just the outcome.
Test your assumptions
and turn them into knowledge as you
evaluate
your market opportunities.
Make the process as attractive as
possible.
And debate
with your peers
and your stakeholders as much as you
can. So ultimately make the Market
Opportunity Navigator a habit
to reap the greatest benefits from
your
commercialization efforts.
Good luck.