Hi there
and welcome back.
In this video we will briefly
discuss how the market
opportunity navigator complements
other well-known business tools
and was actually designed
to work seamlessly
with them.
As we mentioned before the
market opportunity navigator
is an easy to apply business tool
that helps you to identify
and assess potential opportunities
in a systematic
and rigorous manner as you
choose which options to focus on.
It not only gives you the ability
to deliberately plan
your strategy
but also to reflect on
your learning
and to adjust your strategy
as you progress through your
learning
journey.
To make this learning process
broader
and even more complete
we recommend that you use the market
opportunity navigator together
with other key methods
and business tools.
Specifically,
the navigator is designed to
work seamlessly
with the Business Model
and Value Proposition Canvases
created by Alexander Austovade
and Eve Vienia
and with the Lean's Startup
Methodology
created by Eric Reese
and Steve Blank.
While the canvases are
outstanding frameworks for planning
your strategy, the Lean's
Startup is a key method for
validating your strategy.
Together with the Market Opportunity
Navigator they form
a powerful suite of
tools that clearly lays
out the planning
and validation processes as
you strive to find your promising
path.
In fact these tools work
together like cogwheels
with one reinforcing the other
as they provide different aspects
that are all essential for setting
of strategy.
So,
let us briefly examine this
reinforcement.
The business model canvas
and the value proposition canvas
offer valuable frameworks
that help you to find out
how you create value for your
customers
and how you create value
for your firm.
The Navigator which provides
the macro view of the landscape
of opportunities has
an essential level of analysis
with the micro planning
of the Business Model
and the Value Proposition Canvases.
Together these tools
provide the comprehensive planning
that is required for finding your
most fertile ground.
The Lean's Startup Methodology
offers an important validation
process for discovering
and developing customers
through rapid experimentations
and continuous pivoting.
The combination of the Navigator
with the Lean's Startup Methodology
were two powerful process
for validating a winning strategy.
First,
the navigator provides an
ongoing tool for planning,
reflecting,
and adjusting as you
go through rapid Lean's cycles
of experimenting.
And second,
the navigator makes sure that
you will always keep track of the
broad picture in addition
to the path that you're currently
testing.
Overall,
we strongly recommend
that you combine these different
tools
as you search for a promising
strategy.
In fact this suite
of business tools can help
you understand fundamental
questions in a manner
that none of the tools by itself
would allow you to.
So the hole
is actually greater than
the sum of its parts.
To understand this in more details
we will discuss how to use the
navigator
in concert with these tools
in week five of this MOOC.