Hi there
and welcome to the final video of
this week.
As we finalize the introduction
week of this MOOC,
and just before we get started
with the Market Opportunity
Navigator
itself,
we wanted to share
with you some common questions
that we frequently hear about
the Navigator. Entrepreneurs
and Innovators
often ask us whether the navigator
is relevant for their situation,
and why should they invest
the time and effort to apply it?
Well, here are some of
their common questions
and the answers that we provide,
we hope it could clarify some
of your question marks as well.
First,
some entrepreneurs argue that the
technology
they are developing is quite
specific for the product that
they have in mind.
They wish to understand if
the Market Opportunity Navigator
will be relevant for them in that
case.
Well,
some technologies
or capabilities are clearly
more fungible than others,
they can more easily be applied
to serve different applications
and different market domains.
Yet,
almost any technology
can be dealing from its
current product
and be characterized in its
own right to understand
its generic functionalities.
As we will explain in week two.
The Market Opportunity Navigator
can therefore help to discover
new market opportunities,
even if you think that your
technology is quite specific
and thus, to make sure that your
firm will not get locked in
and lose its agility.
Another common question relates
to the time that needs to be
invested
for applying the navigator.
There are so many things to do in a
startup
and so little time.
Entrepreneurs ask
us why should they take the
time to invest in this process?
Indeed,
time is one of the scarce
resources for entrepreneurs,
we know that.
However,
because it is so rare
it must be spent wisely.
Usually, our natural tendency
is to invest our time in
troubleshooting
and short term problems.
But this approach may
turn out to be problematic in
the long term.
Remember, that your choice of market
opportunities is one of the
most important decisions you will
make.
You should therefore take the
time to think widely
and comprehensively about
your options before you commit
to a specific direction,
and make sure that your choice
is smart so that
you will not regret it when it's
too late.
Either way you should also keep
in mind the learning curve in
applying the navigator.
A significant investment
is usually required when you begin
working with the navigator,
but over time
you will be able to use
and benefit from it
with much less effort.
Last but not least,
the common assumption among
entrepreneurs
and investors as we already
mentioned is that startups
must adopt a 'laser
sharp focus' approach,
simply because their resources
are scarce.
So how does this approach
fit with the Agile Focus approach
of the Navigator?
In our studies we have done
comprehensive research involving
hundreds of firms to understand
this question.
Our studies clearly show,
that a 'laser sharp focus'
on one market opportunity
doesn't pay off for most firms.
On the contrary firms
that implemented a wider
approach by consciously
keeping related market
options open
outperformed those who didn't
mainly because of their greater
agility.
Laser Sharp Focus therefore
comes at the price of flexibility,
while Agile Focus
helps you manage the delicate
balance between staying focused
and staying flexible,
and this is very
important especially for
startup.
Well that's it.
We believe that you have all the
necessary information by now
to understand what this MOOC
is all about
and why is it important for
anyone interested in commercializing
innovations.
It's time for you to roll
up your sleeves
and dive into the details
of the Market Opportunity Navigator.
This would be interesting
and fun.
So we hope you enjoy
the ride.