Hi there.
One last thing before we actually
dive into the details of
how to implement the market
opportunity
navigator.
Because examples
and case studies have an important
role in this learning process.
We will present different examples
whenever it is possible.
One firm however,
will accompany us throughout the
entire process.
So we would like to take the time
and introduce you to Flyability.
Flyability will accompany
us from week to week as
we progress through the three steps
of the Navigator.
At the end of each week,
we will take a close look at
how this firm implemented
their Market Opportunity Navigator
and initially chose which
markets to play in.
So to begin with,
let's meet Marc Gandillon,
Flyability marketing
manager
and take a closer look at
what this film does.
Flyability introduces
Elios, the world's first
collision-tolerant
drone,
access can find in complex
spaces without any risk of crashing.
Elios features a full
HD camera endothermy
camera embedded on the drone.
The robots
live video feed allows the operator
to get the drone to the most
inaccessible
places up to five kilometers when
in direct line of sight.
Gather close up images for high
resolution
data with a sub-millimeter
resolution,
on-board LCD lighting system
and a complete remote control of the
camera
settings allows to navigate
and inspect even in pitch dark
environments.
Flyability is a space based startup,
it was founded in September
2014 as a spinoff
of EPFL which is a famous
University in Lausanne in
Switzerland.
It is
the outcome of thesis from
Dr. Adrian Breo,
who invented basically
drone ways
with a protective frame around it
that
makes its collision tolerant,
which means it can fly
pretty much everywhere without risk
of crashing.
The whole story started
actually back in 2011 when
Adrian and his cousin Patrick
who are the two co-founder of the
company
were looking at the news after
the incident that happened in
Fukushima.
And they were seeing all these
images
of robots trying to
get into the reactor to to
have to collect images of what
was going there
and rolling robots were stuck
on their way as soon as they
were you know facing an obstacle.
And they they've been trying to
fly drones in there,
but that was very tricky
even you know because you had to fly
that beyond line of sight,
so not seeing the drone
and they were crushing the drone as
soon as they
entered the place.
So, basically they were
thinking you know there there should
be a
better way of doing that.
And this is how the whole story
started and brought Adrian
to to build that first drone
that is collision-tolerant.
And yeah from there great
great story has been
has been following this
this invention.
So,
as we just heard Flyability
develops drones that can be
used safely inside buildings
and in contact
with people,
thus enabling new interactions
and services
with unmanned aerial vehicles.
Flyabilty
aims at becoming the leader
in this segment of flying robotics,
and be at the forefront of
innovation
to continuously deliver value,
safety
and fun to its customers.
But who should be
their customers?
Clearly, Flyability
can serve different types
of users that have the need
for this safe drone.
In other words there are
many Market Opportunities
which they can pursue.
Which one should they focus on?
Join us throughout the weeks
to see how they chose which
markets to play in.