Hello and welcome back.
Now that you know what this course
is
all about, we're going to show you
some
of the practical details
and deliverables.
Yes.
So as we already said before
this course will take you by the
hand
as we go through the three steps of
the Market
Opportunity Navigator.
There is a Chinese proverb
that says "Give a man a fish
and he'll eat for the day,
teach a man how to fish
and he will eat for the life".
In case he likes fish.
In case he like fish.
This is exactly what we
aim to do in this course.
We want to give you a tool
that will help you whenever you need
to
make this profound strategic
decision.
You can always go back to your
toolbox
and implement it
and to make sure that you make
the right choice.
So the goal for this course
is pretty straightforward,
we sketched out four of
the main goals here.
So at the end of the course you will
actually be
able to tackle this all important
market
opportunity decision in a very
structured
and full-time manner.
Yes. You will be able to make
an informed decision that will
increase your chances
on focusing on the promising market
opportunity.
You will be able to balance focus
and flexibility two very critical
elements as we have pointed out.
And lastly, you will be able to
develop
the proper mindset
for setting a winning strategy
one that nurtures openness
and receptiveness to
adaptation. Adaptation.
Yes.
To accomplish these goals we
designed this MOOC
to a five weeks each dealing
with a separate topic.
We go on as an introduction to the
Market Opportunity Navigator
and to the course itself.
Week 2: We will deal
with the first step of the Navigator
and will teach you how to generate
your Market Opportunity Set.
Week 3: We will deal
with the second step of the
Navigator
and it will teach you how to
evaluate the attractiveness
of your market opportunities.
Week 4: We will deal
with the third step of the Navigator
and will teach you how to design
your
Agile Focused Strategy.
And then finally in Week 5:
we will summarize the implications
and the benefits of the Navigator
to help you use it more effectively.
So let's look at each week in more
detail.
Yeah we are just about to finish
up week one,
small congratulations already.
If you remember what we did we
talked about
the challenges in commercializing
innovations.
We talked about this important
choice that you do in
commercialization
which is the market opportunity
choice.
We introduce to you the Market
Opportunity
Navigator. And we are just
about to give you the course
overview.
Yes. In week
two
we will discuss how to generate your
Market
Opportunity Set.
At the end of this week you will be
able
to describe your core abilities
or technology in
its own right detached from
any product that you have in mind so
that
you will be able to think
and discover more applications
and identify different types of
customers.
In order to open up your your
creativity.
Exactly, and the result will be
your Market Opportunity Set.
In Week 3: we will focus on how
to evaluate market opportunities.
At the end of the week you will be
able to rate
each market opportunity along two
key
dimensions.
No. 1: The potential inherent
in the market opportunity.
No. 2: The challenges associated
with the market opportunity.
And then you would place this in the
two
by two metrics shown here on the
screen
which will allow you to
not only see where each opportunity
is place
but to get a visual impression of
how
these opportunities met
relative to each other.
So we get a big picture view
of your Opportunity Set.
In week 4:
We will focus on how to design your
Agile Focused Strategy.
At the end of this week you'll be
able to understand the major
consideration for choosing your
primary
Market Opportunity
and also how to evaluate
other alternatives and check if they
are suitable to be
your growth
or backup options,
so that you can decide which options
you're
going to keep open
and which one you're going to place
in storage.
The outcome of this week
will be your Agile Focus Strategy
which you can then depict on the
Agile Focus
Dartboard.
In Week 5:
We are going to focus on the ongoing
implications
and benefits of the market
opportunity navigator.
At the end of the week,
you will first understand
how the Agile Focused Strategy
influences other key decisions in
new venture creation
and in the innovation process.
Second, you will have learned how to
benefit
from the Market Opportunity
Navigator
over time in an ongoing manner.
And third, you will have understood
how the
Market Opportunity Navigator will
works
actually in concert
with other business tools
so to create a richer more
extensive learning experience for
you.
In terms of deliverables you
will have
quizzes at the end of each topic
and you also have to submit three
assignments based on the three steps
of the Market Opportunity Navigator.
This would be peer graded
assignments
and you will have to submit all of
them
in order to pass this course.
We designed those deliverables in a
way
that you are running journey
is getting more profound
and that you actually make sure that
you understand
the key steps of the navigator.
Exactly.
Now, if you have an idea in
mind for a startup
or if you work in a company
that is looking for additional
market
opportunities you can base your
assignments on these
ideas.
However, if you don't have any idea
you can still do the assignments
based on case studies that we
will provide you in the course.
So, it doesn't really matter
if you have an idea already,
it doesn't really matter if you're
working in an existing
firm or in a startup.
If you want to improve your skills
in commercializing
new technology innovation
bring it to the market,
this course is actually for
you.
You are also welcome to join
us on the social network
where you will be able to post
questions,
share some ideas,
exchange thoughts about different
market
opportunities, get feedbacks on your
ideas,
get feedback and help others in
identifying
and evaluating their own market
opportunities.
So ultimately we
welcome you to this course,
let's get started
with this.
We are looking forward to
accompanying
you through this exciting journey.