Welcome to this model, on basic
concepts of Statistics.
During the course of this model,
we will discuss the following topics.
First we'll introduce a few general
notions on statistics,
about populations, samples,
variables, and distribution.
We'll then see the summaries that
can be used in order to describe
the distribution of
a statistical variable,
at the level of the sample.
We will see that these can be
numerical, or graphical.
And we will investigate
the key properties, strengths,
and weaknesses of some
such summaries.
Then, we'll talk of the means
of describing the distribution
at the level of population.
Particularly using what is called
the Statistical Model.
We will see that
such a statistical model,
offers a parsimonious representation
of the distribution at the population level
by means of a few
interpretable parameters.
This might have otherwise needed
many different numerical summaries
to describe.
We will review some
important classes of such models.
We'll also see the relationship
between the sample distribution,
and the population
distribution model.
How can we calibrate
the population model
in order to fit the observed
distribution at the level of sample
as best as possible.
This is a so called problem
of point estimation.
Where we seek to estimate the value
of the population parameters
using the sample at hand
as precisely as possible.
We'll discuss the quantification of
the uncertainty inherent in our estimates.
The issue is that the estimate
produced on the basis of our sample
will never be perfectly accurate.
How can we quantify the uncertainty
in this estimate?
How can we construct
a range of plausible values
for the population parameter with
the prescribed degree of confidence?
Finally, we'll see the contrasting
of hypothesis
that we may have formulated
before collecting our data
with the data at hand.
How can we declare whether
or not a scientific hypothesis
or conjecture is compatible,
or not with the data?
How can we do so well guaranteeing
a certain level of protection
from making wrong decisions
due to the sampling uncertainty?
How can we quantify the statistical
significance of an observed trend
at the level of the sample?
In all cases, we will
try to place emphasis
on broad concepts, rather than
on specific techniques
or technical details.
Here we go.