As the title suggests
this is a short introduction to some
of the main notions of statistics.
The emphasis will be
on broad concepts
rather than on specific techniques
or technical details.
But, what is statistics?
Statistics is about learning
from data
and the presence of uncertainty.
To put it more eloquently,
I will quote one of the founding
fathers of modern statistics
Ronald A. Fisher.
We may at once admit that any inference
from the particular to the general
must be attended with some
degree of uncertainty,
but this is not the same
as to admit
that such inference cannot be
absolutely rigorous.
For the nature and degree
of uncertainty
may itself be capable of
rigorous expression.
The object of study will be
a population.
This is the general
in Fisher's quotation.
This population could be a physical
population, of living and inanimate objects.
For instance, residents
of a country,
animals in a region, batteries
produced by a factory.
It could also be a conceptual
population.
Population of all possible
coin flips
with a given coin.
Now in either case, you're interested
in a characteristic that is measurable
on each member of the population.
This we call a statistical variable.
If we knew the value of the variable
for each member of the population,
we would know all.
In fact, it will suffice to know
what proportion of the population
has a variable value
within a certain range
for any given range.
This is known as the distribution of
the variable at the population level.
For conceptual populations, for
instance the population of coin flips
we would like to know the
probability of a certain value
in a given range of values.
For instance, what proportion
of a country's population
has income below a certain level?
In order to decide on
taxation policy.
What is the proportion of voters
favoring a certain candidate?
If we'd like to predict the result
of an election.
What are the proportion of different
blood groups in a region?
In order to stock it's
hospital reserves.
What is the bias of a coin?
In order to decide whether we could
use it to play heads or tails.
What is the proportion of batteries
in a certain batch
whose lifetime is smaller than
some particular duration?
However, it is typically infeasible
to measure the value
of the variable for reaching
every population member?
Instead, we can only measure
the variable on a subset
of the population called a sample.
This is chosen at random
in order to ensure
that it is representative of
the entire population.
This is the particular
in Fisher's quotation.
Thus, the idea is that we can(INAUDIBLE)
the distribution of the variable
at the level of sample we would
like to use this,
in order to understand the distribution
at the level of population.
Now the main questions
of statistical inference are,
how can we infer the distribution
of the variable at the population level
from the sample?
How can we quantify the
associated uncertainty
in our inference? After all,
different samples will produce
different measurements.
Leading to such uncertainty.
Statistical variables can be
qualitative, or quantitative.
Qualitative variables can be
nominal and ordinal.
Nominal variables have
no intrinsic ordering.
An individual's blood type,
or sex for example.
Ordinal variables on the other hand
admit a ranking.
For instance, the size of a product,
small, medium, or large.
Quantitative variables can be
continuous or discrete.
The height or weight of
an individual,
the lifetime of a battery,
or the proportions of individuals
voting for a certain electoral candidate,
are all examples of continuous
random variables.
They can take on any value
from some interval
and there is no discrete list of
values that we can choose them from.
The number of sunny days
between consecutive rainy days.
The number of bacteria
in a water bottle.
And the number of visits to a web page
during the course of the day, on the other hand
are all examples of discrete
random variables.
They can take values from a discrete
list of prescribed values.
Now quantitative variables can be
converted into qualitative variables.
For instance, ones blood pressure
could be converted
to the qualitative variable,
low, normal, and high.
Going in the opposite direction,
is usually a bad idea.
For example, converting
the blood groups
into physical numbers, makes
very little sense.
Even worse, it creates
the temptation
to carry out numerical
operation on them
that would lead to some
absurd results.