Let's review the concepts introduced
in this unit.
The population, this refers to all
the elephants of a park.
For example,
it could be a few (INAUDIBLE) of
elephants in the W Park
in Burkina, Niger and Benin.
Or lots more in Hwange National Park
in Zimbabwe.
The Statistical variable is what
we call the key ecological attribute
or the indicator that
we want to measure
to assess the state of
the monitored value.
The variable can be qualitative,
like elephant's color for example.
And the variable can also
be quantitative.
For instance, measuring the age
of the elephants
will help us know if the population
is in good shape.
In other words,
if the part of young,
adults, and old elephants
within the population
is normal, and this would mean
there is no poaching going on.
This age group parts
we are talking about
are the distribution of
the age variable
at the scale of the population.
But obviously we can't measure
the age of all the elephants
in Hwange National Park.
Therefore we will randomly select
some elephants, and determine
their ages.
This is the sample.
After having identified the ages
within the sample,
we can estimate the age of
the entire elephant population.
And now, what the degree
of confidence
associated with this estimate is.
Age is a discreet variable.
Meaning it can take any value
related to a certain number of years
between the ages of the youngest
and the oldest elephants
in the park.
To simplify this, it is also
possible to sort elephants
per age groups.
Young, adult and old.
This way, the age variable
is converted
into a qualitative variable.
But can we be sure that the variable
at the level of the sample
is a good image of
the total population?
We will see this in Unit 2.7.