Let's get back to our sample
of elephants
in the park.
When we look at a qualitative
variable such as
the color of elephants, we will
obtain 3 categories.
For example, green, white, and pink.
Our sample is made up
of 10 elephants.
The frequency table gives
the elephants distribution
among these categories.
It is a simple descriptive piece
of information.
The absolute frequency measures
how many elephants
are present in each category.
For example, 5 green,
2 pink, and 3 white.
The relative frequency gives
the proportion of each category.
50% green, 20% pink,
and 30% white.
How this shows that there are
more green elephants,
is the absolute frequency.
And they represent half the sample
and this gives their
relative frequency.
Now, let's have another look at
a discrete quantitative variable,
the ecological attribute Age,
of the elephants.
We choose a sample of 13 elephants
and we determine their age.
Then, we arrange the elephants
in ascending order of age.
This is called, Statistics order.
Now, we are able to visualize
the distribution of the sample
according to the ascending value
of the attribute.
The next step, to better understand
this attribute
is to know where the center
of the sample is.
This is a measure of location, and
how the sample values are distributed
around the center.
This is a measure of dispersion.
The mean gives the average age
of the elephants.
It is calculated by dividing
some of the ages
with the number of elephants
monitored.
The median splits the population
in half.
It is not affected by the variation
of values of the attribute itself.
The variance gives a distribution
of attribute values
around the mean.
It is obtained by calculating
the sum of the value
square distances with the mean.
And then we divide it by N.
The standard deviation will be
the square root of the variance.
It expresses the distribution
at the same scale
as the value itself.
Finally, the sample can be
subdivided into Quantiles.
Usually, Quartiles are often used.
In this case, each group gathers
around 25% of the sample.
This gives more detail information
about the sample
by showing its symmetry
to the mean
which the variance alone doesn't do.
Here, we can see that the sample
of elephants (INAUDIBLE)
a greater number of old animals.