We now have a collection
of n values corresponding
to the measured values
of the variables
on the sample elements
and would like to use these
to probe the characteristics
of the sample distribution.
We can carry out this exploration
by means of graphical
as well as numerical summaries.
Let's first focus
on numerical summaries.
In the case where the variable
of interest is continuous
there are several numerical
summaries
that can be constructed,
as we will soon see.
But in the case where the variable
of interest is qualitative
all you can essentially do
is record and present
the percentage of sample values
falling in each category.
Consider for instance,
a sample of size
n equals 25, where the variable
of interest
is the blood group
of each individual.
All we can do in this case,
is to classify
and organize the values in
a so-called frequency table.
A frequency table lists
all possible categories
of the qualitative variable
in it's first column.
It then lists the corresponding
number of appearances
at the level of the sample
which are called the absolute
frequencies.
Finally, it lists what proportion
of the same members
has any given value
in the last column.
This is called
the relative frequency.
The frequency table summarizes
and organizes all the information
that the sample carries
about the qualitative variable.
When the variables are quantitative,
on the other hand,
one can use more sophisticated
numerical summaries.
In order to do this.
a very useful pre-processing step
is to order the sample values
in increasing order,
the so-called order statistics.
In fact, it is this very ordering
that makes
quantitative variables interesting.
The fact that they can be arranged
and visualized on an axis.
Getting the order statistics
involves
taking the original sample values,
x1 up to xn,
and rearranging them
as x(1 in parenthesis)
up to x(n in parenthesis).
These new labels in parenthesis
highlight
what the rank of each observation is
in the sample
rather than it's arbitrary position
in the initial list.
For example, consider a sample
of size n equals 2
with sample values of 5, 1, and 4.
The order statistics relabel
the original observations
according to rank,
even though the value 1
corresponds to the second member
of the sample
it has the smallest rank, being
the minimal value.
And thus, becomes the first
order statistics.
When this ordering
is finalized we can
then probe features
of the distribution.
Is it concentrated
around a certain location?
Is it dispersed?
Does it possess some symmetries?
All these characteristics
give us information
about the distribution
of the sample.
We will consider numerical summaries
for the following
sample characteristics
of quantitative variables.
First, measures of location,
indicating the center
of the sample distribution,
such as the mean and the median.
Second, measures of dispersion,
indicating how spread out
the sample values are,
and whether they locally concentrate
and are otherwise
dispersed.
These include the variance,
quantiles and quartiles
and finally the range,
and interquartile range.
Let's start with the mean
and the median.
So suppose we have a sample
of n values
denoted by x1 up to xn.
The sample mean is defined
as the sum of these observations
divided by the sample size.
On the other hand,
the sample median
is a bit more complicated
to define.
It is defined as
the middle observation
when the sample size n is odd.
Or the average of the two
middle observations
when the sample size is even.
But what do these
definitions mean?
Let's take a closer look.
The physical interpretation
of the mean
is that it is the center of mass
of the data.
Let's say we have
a sample of size 5.
And let's order this sample
on an axis as shown right here.
Suppose that we place an equal
amount of mass
on the location of each one
of these observations.
We can then ask the question
where on the axis
should we place this pen
in order for the axis to balance?
If we do so too far to the left
then the axis is going to fall down
to the right.
If we do so too far
to the right
then the axis is going to fall down
to the left.
We seek a perfect point where
the axis is going to balance.
Such a unique location
actually exists.
It is precisely the sample mean.
In this case,
it is somewhere here.
The median, on the other hand
is motivated
by a symmetry consideration.
Suppose we ask for a point
on the axis
that splits the data in half.
That means that to the left
of the point we should have
as many observations as we have
to the right of that point.
Now, if the number
of observations is odd,
such as 5.
in this example,
this is easy, we can simply
pick the middle observation.
In this case, the middle observation
is the third largest observation.
Notice that there are exactly
two observations to the left of this
and two observations
to it's right.
So we pronounce
this observation to be the median.
If the number of observations
is even, on the other hand
then any point between two
middle observations
can serve as a median.
For instance, in this case,
we have
the two middle observations,
x(2) and x(3).
Notice that any point we
might choose in the interval
between these two observations
would split the data set
into two equal halves.
The first half containing
the first two observations
the second half containing
the last two observations.
Which point should we pick?
Well, by symmetric considerations
it could make sense
to simply pick the midpoint,
the point right at the middle
of the interval.
This midpoint turns out to be
exactly the average
1 over 2 times x (2) plus x (3)
in this case.
Otherwise said, the average
between the two middle observations.
Now, notice that the mean
uses the precise numerical value
of all the observations
in the sample.
The median, on the other hand,
relies mostly
on the order of the observations.
So generally the mean is a more
efficient means
of using the data
and will typically be
a  better descriptor
of the center of the sample.
Then why bother with the median?
The reason is that the mean can
be very sensitive
to the presence
of extreme observations.
Consider what can happen
if a single observation
stands out far from the rest.
For instance, going back
to our example
of 5 observations,
suppose we take
the largest observation
and we shift it
to the edge of the axis.
Now the original location
of the mean provided the location
where this axis
is going to balance
if we've placed
an equal amount of weight
on each of these observations.
If we shift the largest observation
to the right
then the weight will be shifted
to the right.
So at this point now,
the axis is going to fall down.
This means that we need
to correspondingly shift the mean
in order to re-balance the axis.
In fact, the further away
the fifth observation is moved
the further the mean
is going to be shifted.
The morale is that a single
extreme data point
could completely undermine
the quality of the mean
as a descriptor of the location
of the data set.
In contrast, let's see what happens
to the median.
Let's again take the largest
observation in our sample
and push it to the right.
Now, the original median
was the third observation.
After all, this is exactly
in the middle of the sample.
There are 2 observations
to it's left
and 2 observations to it's right.
Having shifted the fifth observation
to the right,
this doesn't really change.
There are still 2 observations
to the left
and then 1, 2 observations
to the right.
The median stays put.
In fact, no matter how much we push
the largest observation
to the right,
the median will not move.
It remains the middle observation
no matter how much
the extremes are moved around.
In summary, the mean is generally
a more accurate descriptor
of location
and should be used
when we are not liable
to having
extreme observations.
The median, on the other hand,
maybe less efficient
in it's use of it's data,
but could come in useful
when we expect
that extreme observations
are likely to arise.
Now, once we have a notion
of center
for our sample distribution,
we may want to know
how dispersed or concentrated
the sample values are
around that center.
The variance is a natural
descriptor of how dispersed
the sample values are
around their mean, in particular.
It is defined as the sum
of square differences
of observations
minus their mean,
suitably renormalized.
It represents
the average square distance
between a sample value
and the sample mean.
How far is an observation
from the center
of the data set, on average?
Now, for technical reasons,
one often uses
a scaling factor 1 over n minus 1,
instead of 1 over n.
But let's not worry about
that too much.
Now, a draw back of the variance
is that it is not expressed
in the same units of measurement
as the original variable,
because of the squares.
For instance, if the values x1 to xn
are measured in meters,
their mean is also
measured in meters.
But their variance is measured
in square meters.
The standard deviation
corrects for that
by taking the square root
of the variance.
The 2 notions
are equally informative
the only difference is a difference
of scale.
To understand variance,
we consider
2 different samples,
each comprised
of 5 observations,
x1 to x5, and y1 to y5.
We arrange these 2 samples
on 2 different axes
from smallest observation
to largest observation
using the order statistics.
We then calculate
their sample means.
Notice that these 2 sample means
are exactly the same.
Still, the 2 samples
are different.
In the first sample,
the sample observations
are more concentrated
around their sample mean
than they are in the second sample.
This means that the first sample
has a smaller variance
than the second sample.
The average deviation of
the sample observation to it's mean
is higher in the second sample
than it is in the first.
Now, the variance
could be argued to be
too coarse a measure
for some data sets.
For example, if you look at
the 2 data sets on my right,
these have the exact same mean
and the have the exact same variance.
But, arguably, the distribution
of their values
on the axis is quite different.
In effect, what's going on
is that they have different
asymmetry relative to their mean.
To distinguish finer characteristics
such as asymmetries,
we define the notion of quantiles.
For any percentage point alpha,
the alpha quantile
is defined to be the smallest
observation
of the sample that exceeds at least
alpha percent of the sample values.
For instance, when the sample
size is odd
the 50% quantile is equal
to the median.
We term the 25%, 50 and 75%
quantiles
as the first, second
and third quartile.
We partition the axis
into four regions,
each containing roughly
one-fourth of the sample,
that is one quarter of the sample,
hence the name quartile.
Now the quartiles give us
more detailed information
on the dispersion and concentration
properties of the sample.
For instance, they allow us
to appreciate
whether the distribution
of the sample is symmetric
or asymmetric
around the sample mean.
If the distance between the first
and second quartile
is smaller than
the distance between
the second and third quartile
then we see that there is
a right a symmetry.
The second half of the sample
is more spread out
than the first half.
This is the case in the first plot
on the right.
Conversely, when
the first and second quartile
are further apart than
second and third one
we have a left symmetry.
If the distance between consecutive
quartiles is roughly the same
then we speak
of a symmetric distribution.
This is precisely the case
with the last plot on the right.
To conclude this section,
we briefly mention
two more measures of dispersion.
First, the difference between
the first and third quartile.
This is called
the interquartile range
It can be used to assess
the concentration of the sample
It reveals how concentrated
or spread apart
the middle 50% portion
of the sample is.
Finally, the overall range
or just range
is an even coarser descriptor.
It gives us the length of
the smallest possible interval
containing the entire sample.
Therefore, it's just a difference
between the largest observation
and the smallest observation.