Further to numerical summaries,
one can also create
graphical summaries of the sample.
This can often be more telling,
as long as they are not abused.
The qualitative variables,
one often uses pie charts
and bar charts.
The qualitative variables,
there is a much wider graphics
that one can consider.
We will focus on two particular
type of graphics;
histograms and boxplots.
Pie charts and bar charts
essentially carry
the same information
as a frequency table does
but they're conveyed
on a visual way
that is easier to appreciate.
Let's consider again the sample
of 25 individuals
where the variables of interest
is their blood type.
The sample is summarized
in the frequency table on the left.
The pie chart partitions the
surface of the disk into sectors.
Each sector corresponds
to one of the categories
of the qualitative variable.
Here, we have sector A
corresponding to the value A.
Sector B corresponding
to the value B,
and so on and so forth.
Assuming that the
total area of the disk
corresponds to one 100%,
the sectors are drawn
in such a way
so that the area of each sector
corresponds to the percentage
of the corresponding category
in the frequency table.
So for instance,
the area of sector B over here
should be equal 32% relative
to the total of 100%
A bar chart draws a separate bar
for each category of a variable
arranged side by side.
A, B, O, and AB,
in the case
of the blood group example.
Each bar is designed
so that it's area
is proportional to the corresponding
relative frequency
or equivalently to the corresponding
absolute frequency.
In essence, pie charts
and bar charts provide
the exact same information.
Their difference is merely
a question of style.
when dealing with
a quantitative variable,
we see graphical summaries
that allow us to easily visualize
the concentration of sample values
in different regions of the axis.
A basic such graphic
is the histogram
which is based on an idea
that is not too dissimilar
to the bar chart.
It's aim is to help us visualize
what proportion software contained
in different sub-regions
of the axis.
Let's consider an example
to see
how an histogram is constructed.
The data set on the right
shows the weight
of 92  high school seniors
divided between boys and girls
and is measured pounds.
To construct a histogram
for this data set,
we first divide the range
of the data
into non-overlapping intervals
of equal length.
And this example,
which is nine intervals,
then we count proportionate
sample observations
contained in each interval
and draw a horizontal line
over that interval
at a height that is equal
to that proportion.
Thus, the height of each
resulting bin
informs us of proportions
of observations
in that corresponding interval.
The histogram allows us to very
directly appreciate the location,
scatter, and
symmetry or asymmetry
of the sample distribution,
all at the same time.
The main weakness of histogram
is there is no objective choice
of how many intervals
or bins
once you divide the range
into.
A very small number of wide things
gives information
that is too coarse,
as it flushes out finer information.
A very large narrow bins
is not helpful either,
It obscures the general form
by giving information
that is too fine.
The choice of the number of bins
should be made judiciously
depending on the number
of observations.
The general rule is that the larger
the sample size n,
the more the bins
one should consider.
Luckily, computer software
automatically selects
reasonable choice
but a good analyst must always
keep in mind to not
over interpret characteristics
visible in the histogram
as these may depend
on the arbitrary choice
of number of bins.
To see the impact of the choice
of number of bins
on the form of the histogram,
let's compare the histogram we get
from the previous
data set for two different values
of bin width.
On the left, we have the original
bin width
with a range of the data
being partitioned into 9 intervals.
On the right, the range of the data
is partitioned into 13 intervals.
This results into coarser bins
on the left
and finer bins on the right.
Now while the overall shape
of the two histograms is the same.
we can see the two histograms
present some subtle differences.
Since these differences are related
to the choice of number of classes,
we should not put too much emphasis
on these when interpreting
the histogram.
The different means of visualizing
the distribution of the sample
is the boxplot.
Contrary to the histogram,
it has tuning parameters  to choose,
and so it can be objectively
constructed for any data set.
Now on the other hand,
it is a closer  representation
of the data set.
How does it work?
Let's use the high school student
data set again
to demonstrate how exactly.
The first step is to arrange
the order statistics
of the sample on an axis.
This goes from the
smallest observation
to the largest observation
in increasing order.
Then, boxplot is basically
an annotation
of some key numerical summaries.
We annotate the location
of the median,
as well as the location of the first
and third quartile.
This is done by using a box
that hovers over the axis.
The end-points of the box
correspond to the location
of the second and third quartiles,
while the line down the middle
is the location of the median.
Then, we annotate the smallest
and the largest observations
to fall within
1.5 times the inter-quartile range
by vertical lines.
These vertical lines are
called whiskers.
Any observations falling outside
the whiskers are called outliers
and are annotated individually.
In this data set,
the largest observation
that corresponds to 220 pounds
lies way
beyond the right whisker.
This is why it's annotated
separately by a dot.
A boxplot will allow us
to appreciate
some of the basic characteristics
of a distribution.
The middle line in the box
represents the medium.
So about half the south of values
are to the left
and half to the right
of that line.
This gives an indication
of the location sample distribution.
The lines representing the quartiles
give us a division of the sample
into quarters.
These can be used to gauge
the dispersion of the sample
as well as the symmetry
or lack of it
at the level of sample distribution.
When the overall shape
of the boxplot
is symmetric around the median,
we have  a roughly
symmetric distribution.
Such is the case
in the first boxplot on the right.
Otherwise, if one side
of the boxplot is elongated
related to the other,
then we speak of skewed distribution
to the left or to the right
depending on which side
of the medium the elongation
appears in.
The second boxplot
on the right picks a sample
that is skewed to the right.
The whiskers now
is supposed to indicate
where the bulk of the sample lies.
When observations fall outside
of the whiskers,
these observations are
called outliners
because they lie outside
the main crowd of points.
The third boxplot on the right
features five such outliers.
Outliers deserve further scrutiny
and should not just
be treated as average.
They may indicate for example
if there is an interesting
phenomenon going on
or that the distribution under study
has what we call heavy tails.
This means that the population
under study
has a non-trivial proportion
of individuals whose variables
takes on very different values
than the rest.
Still, it is a possibility
that the outliers are due
to data registration error.
We can't know that
and we must scrutinize more.
Boxplots are particularly useful
for comparing distributions
of different samples
by displaying them side by side
as is done in the right here.
For instance, we can construct
two separate boxplots
for the boys and the girls
in the sample
of 92 high school students.
This boxplot corresponds
to the girls
and this boxplot corresponds
to the boys.
By comparing them side by side,
we can see that both samples
have roughly symmetric distributions
or perhaps
the sample of the boys appears to be
slightly skewed to the right.
It is clear that the location
of the sample of boys
is further up than the location
of the samples of girls.
Boys typically weigh more.
It also as though the sample
of errors is more concentrated
around the median as is indicated
by the inter-quartile range.
The histogram in the boxplot
are useful means to summarize
the sample distribution
in a visual way.
The histogram gives finer
representation
of the data distribution.
The height of each rectangle
gives us the proportion
of sample observation falling
into that corresponding interval.
However, it's interpretation
is susceptible to change
depending on the choice
of bin width
which must be made judiciously.
In particular, one should not
over-interpret fine details
of a histogram
which are typically unstable
to perturbation of the bin width.
We should not try to extract
more information from this graphic
than what it can actually offer.
The boxplot is not as finer
representation of the data,
but has the advantage of not
depending on junior parameters.
Since it does not depend
on such junior parameters
it allows to very easily compare
between different sums.
Finally a warning, when accessing
the graphical summary
of a sample, it's important to not
over-interpret delicate features
and details.
It's important to remember
that minor features
are subject to a random fluctuations
that could be due
to the random sampling.
They may not persist in new
or different samples.
The human mind has a tendency
to try and discover patterns
everywhere, even when
these patterns don't exist.
Assessing data should be immune
to such magical thinking.