Numbers are important,
being median, standard deviation,
but sometimes graphs
can be more explicit.
As we consider
qualitative variables,
let's use elephant color
as the ecological attribute
we want to adopt
and the same frequency table
we worked with previously.
The bar chart gives the
absolute frequency of each value.
Here, five grey,
three white and two pink.
The pie chart expresses
the relative frequency
of these values on a disk
representing 100%
of their distribution.
Now, for quantitative variables,
let's once again
consider our elephant edges
as the ecological attributes.
And again, let's take
the sample of 13 elephants
of which we already know
the ages.
On the X axis, we set elephant ages
in intervals of, let say five years.
On the vertical axis,
we put the number of elephants
present in each category.
This is how we draw histograms
showing the age dispersion
of the sample.
If we change the interval
to ten years,
the shape of the histogram
changes.
Interval sizes affect
the final visual result
and this can interfere
with interpretation.
So be aware.
We can also draw a boxplot
from the sample
by taking the quartile
and median data
and by drawing whiskers that
measure 1.5 times
the weight of the box.
This gives a another image
of the value distribution
that does not depend
on changing parameters.
In our case, the sample distribution
shows skewness
to the right hand side
Elephants are whole
with two outliers on both sides
of the whiskers.