Our whole premise is that we will
use a distribution of a statistical
variable at the level of a random
sample in order to understand
the distribution of the variable
on the level of the population.
At the level of the sample a simple
way of visualizing the data
distribution as the histogram.
The height of each bar revealing
the percentage of sample
observations falling inside
the corresponding bin.
Is there a similar device that
we could use to represent
the distribution of
the entire population?
Although, the population is
in principle very large
and we can essentially think of it
as being of infinite size
so if we want to create a histogram
for the population we could try
to use one with a very large
number of very narrow bins.
How many exactly?
As many as possible.
For a discreet variable that
can only take the value zero
zero, one, two, three,
and so on and so forth
each bin would have to correspond
to one of these values exactly.
After all, we can never
take finer bins than these.
For continuous variable on
the other hand there is no limit
to the number of bins we could take
there could be as fine
as we wish them.
So the histogram now
becomes a smooth curve
as seen in blue on the right.
We can interpret this as
a histogram with infinitely
many minutely fine bins.
In either case, continuous or
discreet we speak of
the population distribution.
In many cases we can actually
describe the population
distribution by closed form
mathematical formula.
having such a formula for
a population allows us to
better interpret the form
of the distribution.
Just as in physics, a formula reveals
a physical law of the phenomenon
under study so does it
reveal the law governing
the population distribution.
This is why the population
model formula is often
called the law of the population.
Population models usually
depend on parameters that allow
us to fine tune the model
to the population at hand.
Some examples of laws that
are very often included in practice
are the normal distribution,
the exponential distribution
and the Poisson distribution.
let's consider these
in a bit more detail.
The normal distribution is a law
for continuous random variables.
It's formula tells us that
the distribution is symmetric
around a certain value μ.
Changing the value of μ shifts
the location of the peak
of the distribution.
For instance, this one has μ
equal to zero, whereas this one
has μ approximately equal to -2.
changing the value of σ squared
will actually compress or stretch
the distribution, so for example
the distribution in blue
has a lower σ squared value
than the distribution in red.
The exact values are
given on the top right.
The normal distribution is one
of the most important models
as it describes extremely
large variety of situations.
The exponential distribution
is a law for continuous
random variables that
take on only positive values.
It usually models variables that
represent the time until some event.
The lifetime of a battery
for an example.
It's formula depends on
a positive parameter λ.
This parameter is called the rate.
It actually controls how
likely it is to observe
larger values of
the variable of time.
For a large value of λ,
the distribution concentrates
around zero, such is the case
of the curve in green.
On the other hand,
for small values of λ
the distribution tails off more
slowly, such is the case with
the curve in blue.
The Poisson distribution is a law
for discreet random variables
taking the value zero, one, two,
three, and so on, and so forth.
It is typically used when
considering the statistical variables
that count occurrences, for instance
the number of bacteria in a bottle
of pasteurized milk could be
modeled by a Poisson distribution.
This distribution also depends on
a single parameter λ.
This is also a positive parameter
and it controls how large or small
the values of the variable
will typically be.
Small values of λ will concentrate
the distribution close to zero
while larger values will shift it to
the right, widen it, and make it
look more symmetric, for instance
on the left we see what the Poisson
distribution of λ
equals one looks like.
Clearly, we have the zero and one
are the more likely values
and then the proportions
of different values tail off
rather quickly.
For the larger value of λ equals 2.5
we see that the distribution is
shifted more to the right likely
values now are bigger values
and it appears that we have
more of a symmetric pattern.
But how do we calculate proportions
with these population models?
In the case of discreet variable,
the answer is quite simple
just as with the histogram.
In the case of the continuous
variable though, our distribution
model is given by a curve.
Now we can choose any
arbitrary interval that
we wish, for example the interval I.
We could ask, what proportion of
population has variable values
contained in the interval I?
the answer is that this proportion
should be given by the area
under the curve delineated by
the interval end points.
What this means is that we need to
draw vertical lines at the interval
end points, and then find what area
is contained between these two lines
the axis and the curve.
This is going to give us
the proportion of population values
contained in I.
Just as we defined notion such as
the mean, median, variants
and quantiles of a sample
distribution so can we also
do in the case of
the population model.
Now we will not give
precise definitions
but we will simply note that all
theses quantities can be obtained
using the mathematical formula
for the population model.
The key aspect is to
highlight that all these
concepts will now depend on
the unknown parameter.
It will be functions
of the parameter
since the population curve changes
as the parameter changes
it's numerical summaries must also
change as a function
of the parameter.
Now, some of these functions may
not have explicit formulas
but others do, so here's some key
numerical summaries for
the three models we saw earlier.
For the Poisson distribution
the mean is equal to the variants
which in turn is equal to
the parameter λ.
For the exponential distribution,
the mean is equal to the inverse
of λ, whereas the variant is equal
to one divided by λ squared.
We even have a formula for
the α percent quantile
which is given to my right.
In the normal distribution
the mean equals the median
and equals μ.
The variants equal to σ squared.
The quantiles of the normal
distribution do not have
the simple closed formula, but
there is one very important property
that we will now mention.
Whatever the value of the mean
parameter μ and the various
parameter σ squared might be
the following statements
will always remain true.
First of all, the proportion
of population values within
one standard deviation of the mean,
is always equal to 68%.
On the other hand, the proportion
of population values within two
standard deviations of the mean,
is always equal to 95%.
Finally, the proportion of
population values within three
standard deviations of the mean,
is always equal to 99%.
So what we're having in population
how do we know what is a good
model to use as it's law?
This choice is often based on
prior information as well as
first principles, for instance,
it is known that some populations
have properties that uniquely
correspond to a given model
and so that is the model
that should be chosen.
Other times we know
that the certain model is
a good approximation for a wide
variety of phenomena
with some characteristics.
Sometimes, a model is not
motivated by the first principles
or mathematical theory, but by
extensive practical experience.
We simply know that this model
has been successful in the past.
In some cases, when we have selected
a model, but the exploratory graphical
numerical analysis of the sample
might reveal the features of this
model are not compatible
with the sample's structure.
This means, that we may
need to reconsider or modify
our initial choice of model.
This interplay between modeling
principles and exploratory
analysis is what statisticians
call model selection.
Luckily for many standard problems
there exists a models
who's appropriateness
has been established by both
mathematical investigation
and practical experience.
The powerful thing about a model
is that it allows us to calculate
everything we need to
know about a population
provided that we know the value
of the parameter it depends on.
This value is typically
unknown unfortunately
but luckily we have our sample.
The problem of statistical inference
is to use out sample in as best
of ways possible in order to inform
ourselves about true
value of this parameter.
Once we can say something
about this parameter
we can answer any question we want
about the population distribution.
The triple of statistical inference
questions one typically wishes
to answer are
first, point estimation
determine the precise value
of the unknown parameter
and quantify how far off we
might be in doing so on average
secondly, interval estimation,
given interval of plausible
values for the parameter
will quantify the chance that
this would contain the true value
finally, hypothesis testing,
determine whether a certain
hypothesized value or range of
values for the parameter
is compatible or not with
a sample that we observe
and also determine the chance of
making a mistake in
this determination.