In this unit we saw
how to use a variable
distribution as observed
within the sample
to try to deduce the variable
or ecological attributes
distribution at the scale
of the population.
For a quantitative variable,
such as the age of elephants
let's take a sample of which
the histogram of age distribution
in five year beams
would be as follows.
By increasing the sample size
we can reduce the beam width
to three years for example
and be more accurate.
Then we try to identify
a curve representing
the law of population
that can be expressed
by a relatively easy
statistical function.
For discreet variables we don't
want to replace the histogram
with the curve, since the values
are distributed into separated beams
but we could, however, determine
the law of the population.
In all cases, the difficulty is
to identify a suitable formula
that depends on unknown parameters
that one would need to estimate.
This is where the sample comes
in handy as it allows choosing
sensibly the most treatable model
to describe the population
and to calculate the value
of the parameter on which
the model is based.
One way of doing it is to consider
the sample distribution to find
the law that comes nearest to it.
Here for example we
took the normal law.
Determining the value
of the parameters
isndone by estimating
the value from the sample.
In this case, we're allowed
to identify the values of
the standard deviation
and the mean
and their degree of confidence.
We will see these in more
detail in the next unit.
The benefit of this type of
model is that it can give
precious information in theory.
For example, that 95% of individuals
will fall in two standard deviations
and 99% in three standard deviations
provided of course the population
follows the model in place.