Recall that our whole premise
is that we will use
a distribution of a statistical
variable
at the level of a random sample
distribution,
in order to understand
the distribution of this variable
at the level of the population.
If we have a model for
the population distribution,
we can calculate everything
we need to know
about a population,
provided that we know the value
of the parameter it depends on.
So, a natural question is,
how can we use the sample
distribution
in order to infer the unknown
parameter of the population model?
This problem is known as
the problem of point estimation.
So let's say we have a model,
F x Theta, for our population,
which has some explicit formula
that we omit for the moment.
Though we know the formula
of the model,
we don't know the value
of the true parameter Theta.
For example, we know that the model
is exponential with rate Theta,
but we don't know
the precise value of the rate.
We have, however,
at our disposal
a sample of X1, Xn
from the population.
In order to estimate the unknown
perimeter Theta,
we will construct an estimator.
A function Theta hat of the sample
values X1 to Xn,
who's value will provide our
estimate of the unknown parameter.
If only 2 questions naturally arise,
one, how do we construct
estimators?
In other words, what is the right
formula for Theta hat?
And two, how de we evaluate
the precision of estimators?
We will first start with question 1,
and then eventually
move on to question 2.
What ever form of estimator
we end up using,
the motivating principal
always remains the same.
We wish to calibrate the
population distribution
to the sample distribution.
For example,
on the right you can see
a sample histogram in red,
and different possible exponential
distributions models in blue.
Each one corresponds to a different
choice of the rate parameter.
Which one should we choose
to arrive at the best possible
agreement
between the sample and
the population?
This calibration is always
with respect on criteria.
For instance, we might ask
that the parameter of interest
should be such that the mean
of the population model,
and the mean of the
sample distribution coincide.
This leads to what we call
the Method of Moments Estimator.
Another approach is to ask
for a finer calibration.
We might want to ask
what is the parameter value
that makes the sample as
representative as possible
for the corresponding model?
This leads to what we call
The Maximum Likelihood Estimator.
If the population model depends
on the parameter Theta,
then the mean of the population will
also be a function of that parameter
Let's call it M of Theta.
Now, if we have a random sample
X1 of  Xn,
we can also calculate
the sample mean.
Let's call it X bar.
What the method
of moments suggests
is to find the value of Theta,
that yields a population means
M of Theta,
that matches the sample mean
X bar as best as possible.
Equivalently, we are asked to solve
the equation M of Theta
is equal to 1 over N, the sum of X1
up to Xn,
with respect to Theta.
The resulting solution,
is called, The Method
of Moments Estimator of Theta.
As an example, let's consider
a population
that we choose to model
using the exponential distribution.
The diagram on the right,
shows a histogram in red.
This corresponds to a sample
of size 40
that we've drawn from
the population.
As we said, we model
this population
by the exponential distribution.
This depends on one
unknown perimeter Theta,
which is called the rate perimeter.
In blue you can see overlaid
several curves,
that corresponds to different
exponential distributions
with different choices of Theta.
Which one should we choose
to best match the sample?
The method of moment says,
that we should first of all look
at the sample mean.
This is located where this
vertical line is
and is actually equal to 0,938.
The method of moment then suggests
that of all these blue curves,
we should select the one
that has population means
equal to 0.938.
This specific curve is given
in grey.
So what is the precise value of Theta
that corresponds to the grey curve?
Well, the mean of the exponential
distribution
is the inverse of it's perimeter.
It follows that the method
of moments estimator
should solve the equation that says
that the population mean
should be equal to the
sample mean.
Solving this, gives us
an estimate for Theta
which we call Theta Hat,
and equals 1 over X bar.
The precise value is 1 divided by
0.938
which gives is 1.066.
The method of moments
chooses a parameter
to match the sample population
location as expressed by the mean.
Another approach would be
to choose a parameter
to match the sample and population
distribution at a finer level.
A choice such that the sample
is as representative
as possible of the population.
Equivalently, this requires
the proportions calculated
from the sample histogram
match proportions
calculated from the population
curve as best as possible.
It turns out that there is a
natural mathematical way
to choose the best such Theta.
And this is called, The Method
of Maximum Likelihood.
It says that we should choose
the Theta that maximizes
the function called
The Likelihood Function.
L of Theta.
This is equal to the product
of model function
each evaluated at one
of the sample values.
It actually has an intuitive
interpretation.
It is the parameter choice yielding
the population model
under which our random sample
would've been most probable to obtain.
It often happens that the
Method of Moments
yields the same estimator as
the Method of Maximum Likelihood.
This will be the case, for example,
in the normal exponential
and plus on models.
But it can also happen that the
two estimation methods
product different estimators
in the same model,
for the same sample.
So, one might naturally ask
which one should we use?
Well, the method of moments
is typically simpler
and easier to apply.
so that can be an advantage
in complicated situations.
On the other hand,
Maximum Likelihood is usually
preferred,
because it makes more
efficient use data at hand.
Many cases in fact it makes
the most efficient use of the data.
Another advantage of
Maximum Likelihood
is that we have some rather general
formulas to describe it's accuracy.
Given an estimator of a
population parameter,
it is important to have
an understanding of it's precision.
While the value of an estimator,
which we call The Estimate,
is constant for a given sample,
it will vary over different samples.
So, for the first sample
we might get an estimate
at a short of the truth.
For the second sample,
we might get an estimate that is
even shorter of the truth.
While for the third sample, we
might slightly overestimate the truth.
The moral of the story is,
every time we collect a new sample
we get a new estimate.
To understand the accuracy
of our estimator
we must thus understand
the fluctuations of our estimate
around the value of the
true parameter
as the sample varies over all
possible choices over the population.
If we consider all possible
samples of size N
then we can arrange an axis
all the resulting estimates
of the corresponding parameter.
We can then ask,
what proportion of these
estimates fall within some range
of the true perimeter value?
For example we might ask,
what proportions of the estimates
are going to fall within this interval
containing the true parameter value?
We can more generally ask about
any possible interval.
In effect, the estimator has
it's own distribution.
And understanding its accuracy
is equivalent to understanding
how concentrated this distribution
is around the true parameter value.
One might dare ask,
can we know the formula
of this distribution?
Unfortunately, the sample
distribution of an estimator
is not always the same.
It depends on the model used,
the parameter that is
being estimated,
as well as the method of estimation
that we have chosen.
Fortunately, though,
if the sample size is large enough,
and of we use Maximum Likelihood
as out method of estimation,
then we have a pretty good
approximation.
Strikingly, this approximation
is actually a normal distribution.
And this result is true, regardless
of the population model
and regardless of the specific
parameter we're interested in.
This is due to deep mathematical
result called the Central Limit Theory.
The mean of this normal distribution
is actually the true parameter.
Which means that on average
we're getting the right answer.
The variance, on the other hand,
is given by an explicit formula
that depends on
the likelihood function.
We are not going to discuss
the precise nature of this formula,
but suffices to say that this is
a quantity that we can calculate
for any possible population model.
What we do remark, though,
is that this variance is inversely
proportional to N
The larger the sample size,
the smaller the variance.
In other words,
the large sample sizes, the
Maximum Likelihood Estimator
becomes more and more concentrated
around the true parameter value.
The large majority of cases,
Maximum Likelihood
is a very good approach
to an estimation.