The problem
with a point estimator is that
no matter how accurate it is,
it will almost never be
exactly right.
For instance, we know that,
had we chosen a different sample,
we would have obtained
a slightly different value
of our point estimator.
A different approach
than point estimation, is to give
a range of plausible values
rather than a single value
for the unknown parameter.
This comes
in the form of the interval.
If we had many samples at hand,
perhaps we'd use
the different estimates obtained
to find a plausible range,
similar to the image on the right...
but we only have one.
So, what we need to do,
is to take advantage
of our knowledge
of the sampling distribution
of the estimator, in order to produce
such an interval.
What are the characteristics
that such an interval should possess?
Well, obviously, we would like
they be reasonably short.
The shorter, the more informative.
A long interval says that
many values are plausible,
giving little useful information.
But a short interval narrows down
our choice of parameter.
But at the same time, the interval
should come with some guarantees.
We'd like to be quite confident that
the interval constructed
on the basis of the sample
actually contains the true value.
For instance,
we'd like to have
a method for constructing intervals
that guarantees that 95%
of all possible samples will produce
an interval
containing the true value.
Such an interval, if we can find it,
will be called
the 95% confidence interval.
Let's see how we could construct
such an interval.
Let's suppose that we have a sample,
say x1,...,xn,
from a population model
according to some model: f (x; θ).
We construct the estimator of θ
by maximum likelihood estimation.
Let's call this θ^(x1,...,xn).
We know that this should be
close to the true parameter.
It makes sense to anchor
a confidence interval
around this estimator.
The interval we seek
would thus be centered at
θ^(x1,...,xn) ± δ.
How exactly should we
choose that constant, in order to
guarantee 95% confidence?
To see how, we need to revisit
the sampling distribution
of θ^(x1,...xn).
Recall that
for large enough samples,
the sampling distribution
of the maximum likelihood estimator
is approximately normal,
and this is independent
of what population model
we have used.
The mean
of this normal distribution
is given by the true parameter: θ.
The variance is given
by an explicit formula: σ^2(θ)/n.
Given this, we can use
our understanding of the quantiles
of the normal distribution
to figure our interval out.
We know that for 95%
of all possible samples,
θ^ would fall within a distance
of twice its standard deviation
from its mean.
But its mean
is the true parameter θ,
and its standard deviation is known
to be σ(θ)/√n
In summary, we know that for 95%
of all possible samples of size n,
θ^ is going to be
at a distance
of no more than 2[σ(θ)/√n].
Turning this on its head,
we can equivalently say
that for 95% of all possible samples
of size n,
the interval with left endpoint
[θ^(x1,...,xn) - 2[σ(θ)/√n]]
and right endpoint
[θ^(x1,...,xn) + 2[σ(θ)/√n]]
will contain θ.
This is our confidence interval.
Notice that our formula
for the confidence interval
can be written in the form
of θ^±δ,
which was precisely
what we had set out to get.
This δ depends on the unknown θ,
but since we have
an estimate θ^ of θ,
we can plug that in instead
to get a formula
that we can calculate fully,
since it no longer depends
on any unknowns.
This formula actually reveals
interesting
structural characteristics.
For instance, we see that
the interval is centered
at our estimate.
The length of the interval
is inversely proportional
to the square root
of the sample size,
and this is something
we can control.
For example, it tells us
that if we would like
to get an interval
that is of the same confidence level
but is of half the length,
we need to collect a sample
that is 4 times larger.
Finally, there is this factor of 2.
This factor is related
to the confidence level,
which was 95% in our case.
Choosing a higher confidence level
will give a higher factor value,
whereas a lower confidence level
will give a lower factor value.
For example, if we would like
to build a confidence interval
with confidence 68%,
the factor actually becomes 1,
whereas for a confidence interval
of level 99%,
the factor becomes 3.
In other words,
requiring higher confidence
will also increase
the length of the interval.
The extreme case
of a 100% confidence interval
would make the length infinite,
and the interval would be
uninformative.
In any case,
in most practical cases,
one typically chooses
95% confidence intervals.
To see a practical example,
let's go back to the data set
on the weight
of 92 high school students
measured in pounds.
Let's say we'd like to build
a 95% confidence interval
for the true mean weight
of adolescents of that age.
The population model that we assume
is a normal model
with mean parameter μ,
representing the unknown mean weight
at the level of population.
In this example,
the maximum likelihood estimator
of the true mean μ
is given by
μ^(x1,...,xn)=1/n(x1,...,xn)=x
This is just the sample mean: x.
So, the interval should be
of the form: x±2[σ(x)/√n]
Here, we can calculate
the sample mean to be 145,
σ(x) to be 23.7,
and √n to be 9.6.
Consequently,
our 95% confidence interval for μ
is [140 , 150].
We can draw this on the histogram
on the left.
In many cases, we're actually
particularly interested in having
an upper bound or a lower bound
for a parameter of interest.
Of course, a confidence interval
automatically yields
both an upper and a lower bound.
But, what if we only care
about one of them?
The idea is that by letting
one of the endpoints go,
it will give us a sharper bound
on the other endpoint.
We can follow the exact same steps
as before, using
the sampling distribution
of a maximum likelihood estimator.
These steps will give us
a one-sided confidence interval,
as shown on the right.
Notice that the corresponding
upper and lower bounds
have the same form
in a two-sided confidence interval.
They are obtained
by a small perturbation
of the estimate to the right,
or to the left.
The difference is the scaling factor.
In the one-sided case,
this is no longer equal to 2,
but has become 1.6.
This tells us
that if we only care about a bound,
we can typically get
more sharp intervals
with the same amount of confidence.
Let's now try to find an upper bound
for the true mean weight
in the high school example.
Using our formulas,
we know that the upper 95%
confidence interval will have
an upper bound of x+1.6[σ(x)/√n].
Using our calculations from before,
we find the result to give
a 95% upper bound of 149.
In comparison, the two-sided interval
would have given us an upper bound
of 150,
which is more conservative
In summary, the two-sided interval
gives us simultaneous
upper and lower bounds,
but at the expense
that neither of these bounds
is as sharp as the corresponding
95% one-sided intervals.
The one-sided interval
will give tighter, one-sided bounds,
but at the expense
that it only gives us information
on the one side,
and is totally uninformative
of the other side.