Let's get back to our
elephant population.
We want to know it's age,
which is the ecological attribute
we want to measure.
Therefore, we will be working
on the sample.
We measure the age
of all 13 elephants in the sample.
This way, we will easily obtain
an estimate of the samples
average age,
and a standard deviation
that will give information
on the confidence we can have
in this estimate.
Then, we determine a range
of values in which there is
95% chance to obtain
the average age of the elephants,
which we call
The Confidence Intervals.
In the sample, where
the mean is 19.3
and the standard deviation is 16,
all the possible values of the mean
are from between more or less
2 times the standard deviation
divided by the root of 30.
Here we can see that
this value is quite high,
and not that useful.
This is related to the fact
that the sample is very small.
If the size of the sample increases,
the confidence intervals decreases
as this interval is
inversely proportionate
to the square root
of the sample size.
Thus, if we take 4 times as many
elephants from the sample,
the length of the confidence
interval will be divided
at least in half.
To do this, let's take a sample
with 4 times as many individuals.
The group is now made of
52 elephants instead of 13,
and it's mean is still 19.3 years.
But now, deviance is 159,
and the standard deviation is 12.
So, the confidence interval
decreases.
The estimate gets more precise.