A confidence interval gives us
a plausible range of values for
the unknown parameter of a
population distribution
with a guaranteed
level of confidence.
But in some cases we may have
a theory or a conjecture
that the parameters should be
contained in some range of values
that we ourselves have
specified a priori;
that is before having
collected any data.
For example we might believe
that a certain coin
or a roulette wheel is fair
or we might conjecture
that the average lifetime of a
certain brand of car battery
is at least 4 years.
In such cases,
rather than construct a plausible
range from the sample
we would like to see
whether our conjectured range
is plausible or not
based on the sample.
In other words we would
like to use the data we collect
in the form of a sample x1, ..., xn
to put our theory to the test.
We wish to contrast the theory
to the evidence.
Is the observed data coherent
with our hypothesized range?
If the behaviour of the sample
deviates from what it should be
under the hypothesis then we have
evidence against the hypotheses.
Hypothesis tests are a
statistical tool that allows us to
quantify whether the degree of
observed deviation
is large enough to consist
a true departure from the theory
or small enough that it is simply a
manifestation of sampling variability.
So hypotheses assert that the
true parameters within
some range of values. In statistical
jargon these are known as
null hypotheses and they
are denoted by the symbol H0.
Null hypotheses typically come
in 2 forms.
Firstly hypotheses of the form
ø = ø0 are called simple hypothesis.
These assert that the true
parameter value is equal to
some predetermined
constant ø0.
For example if we hypothesis
that a coin is fair
this means that the
parameter corresponding to
the probability of 'heads' is
exactly equal to 50%.
A second form is that of
one-sided hypothesis.
That is hypotheses of the form
Ø  ≥  Ø0 or Ø  ≤  Ø0
for some predetermined
constant Ø0.
These formulate upper or
lower bounds for the parameter.
For example hypothesizing that
the mean lifetime of a battery
is at least 4 years corresponds
to a left-sided hypothesis.
Now the outcome of any
hypothesis test is a decision.
Based on sample x1, ..., xn
of values from the population
we decide whether or not
to reject the hypothesis.
A key element in hypothesis
testing is to construct
good rules for rejecting or not
rejecting a hypothesis.
What is good?
Well, a good rule is one
that limits the proportion of times
that we would produce
a false rejection,
also known as a false positive.
In other words, when the null
hypothesis is truly valid
at the level of population,
our rule should produce
a rejection decision for no more
than a small fraction
of all possible samples.
Let's say 5%.
This proportion is called
the significance level
usually denoted by the
Greek letter alpha (a)
and is most often
taken to be 5%.
A simple but effective strategy
is to operate as follows.
On the basis of our sample we can
construct an estimate of the true θ.
Let's call it θ^ (x1, ..., xn)
We can then look to see
whether the estimate θ^
actually satisfies the
hypothesis or not.
If it does satisfy the hypothesis,
there is no reason to reject
but if it does not satisfy the
hypothesis we should not
necessarily immediately reject.
The point is that the estimate
will never be precisely right.
We must only reject if the estimate
deviates substantially
from the null hypothesis.
What deviations are
substantial enough though?
One idea is to consider a deviation
to be large enough
and thus to reject
if a 95% confidence interval
for the parameter does not
overlap with the hypothesis.
The rational is simple.
We know that the confidence interval
contains the true parameter
for 95% of all samples.
So if the null hypothesis
is indeed true,
it will overlap with a confidence
interval for 95% of all samples.
Equivalently if the null hypothesis
is true, we will falsely reject it
only for 5% of all
possible samples.
But which interval
should we use,
a two-sided or
a one-sided interval?
Well as you might expect
we use one-sided intervals
for one-sided hypothesis and
we use two-sided intervals
for simple hypothesis.
Specifically for one-sided hypotheses
if the hypothesis asserts an
upper bound
then we use a
lower confidence bound,
in other words, a
left-sided confidence interval.
On the other hand, if the hypothesis
asserts a lower bound
then we use an
upper confidence bound,
in other words,
a right-sided interval.
If all this sounds complicated,
we can translate it
to a simple list
of conditions.
Remember the basic setup:
we reject if and only if
our confidence interval does not
overlap with the hypothesis.
This translates to the following
simple list of conditions:
For simple hypothesis
we reject if and only if
the distance of θ^ from θ0
exceeds 2σ (θ^)/√n
For one-sided hypotheses
we reject if and only if
θ^ falls at least
1.6 x σ (θ^)/√n on the
opposite side of θ0 then that's
stipulated by the null hypothesis.
In each of those cases
we are guaranteed that the level
of significance
will be 5%.
In other words, if the null
hypothesis is true
we will falsely have rejected it
only for 5% of all possible samples.
Let's go back to the example involving
the high school seniors weight.
We would like to test the hypothesis
that the true population mean
is at least 150 pounds.
We have calculated the sample mean
to be 145 pounds. Thus our
estimator deviates from what
the hypotheses asserts. Does it
deviate substantially enough
that we should reject
the hypothesis though?
According to our rejection rule
since this is a one-sided hypothesis
we should reject if the sample mean
falls short of 150 pounds
by at least 1.6 x σ(x̅)/√n.
This is indeed the case.
The sample mean of 145 is smaller
than the critical value of 146
and so we must reject the null
hypothesis at the 5% significance level.
So what is the right
significance level to choose
in order to test a hypothesis?
5%? 2.5%? Maybe 1%.
A lower significance level means
that we will be less likely
to falsely reject a null hypothesis
but changing the significance level
will change the factors 2 and 1.6
used in the formulas earlier.
Indeed, picking a lower significance
level will inflate these factors.
That means that a lower significance
level corresponds to being more
conservative.
We will only reject the hypothesis
for very large deviations because
we want a low risk
of a false rejection.
A higher significance level
corresponds to being more
aggressive. We are willing
to reject the hypothesis
even for moderate deviations.
In other words we are willing to
tolerate a higher risk
of a false rejection.
So at the end of the day we can ask,
how conservative
or aggressive should we be?
Well a possible idea is to
not make that choice at all.
For a given sample, find the
smallest possible significance level
for which you would
reject the hypothesis
and record it. This recorded value
is called the 'p' value.
It tells us what is the least risk
we can commit to
and still reject the hypothesis
on the basis of a given sample.
A very small value for the p-value
means that even when being
very conservative we would still
reject H0 on the basis of the data.
This is strong evidence
against the null hypothesis.
A larger p-value suggest that
we can reject H0
only if we tolerate
a high level of risk.
This does not furnish
evidence against H0.
In general, the lower
the p-value, the stronger
the evidence in the data
against H0.
A very important warning has
to be issued here.
The p-value is not the probability
of the hypothesis being true.
The correct interpretation
is that the p-value
is the probability of observing
a deviation at least as large
as what we observed if the
null hypothesis were true.
So a small p-value suggests
that we have observed something
that would be very unlikely
under the hypothesis H0
therefore we have evidence
against the hypothesis.
Now we not discuss precisely how to
calculate a p-value
but this can easily be done in all
of the settings we have treated.
Luckily a simple rule is:
rejecting if and only if
the p-value is smaller than a,
guarantees a level
of significance equal
precisely to a.
In other words, if you know you want
a level of significance of 5%,
you can always compare the p-value
to that value of 5%
in order to decide whether or not
you will reject the null hypothesis.
Going back to the high school
student example,
let's use the p-value approach
to test the null hypothesis
that the population mean
is at least 150 pounds.
We notice that
the sample mean is 145
which deviates from our hypothesis.
Indeed, the sample mean is
5 pounds less than the
hypothesized lower bound of 150
which corresponds to just over
2σ (x̅)/√n under the bound.
From the sampling distribution
of our estimator
we know that if the null
hypothesis is truly correct,
then a left-sided deviation of
this or larger magnitude
can only arise for 2.15%
of all possible samples.
This 2,15% is exactly
our p-value.
It tells us that the observed
deviation would be highly unlikely
if the null hypothesis H0
were true.
This gives strong evidence
against H0.
In particular, it means that we
should reject the null hypothesis
at a 5% significance level
but also for any other
significance level
that is higher than 2.15%.