To find the parameter
of the population distribution law,
we can proceed by checking
if the one we think to be right
truly is right.
The parameter we estimate
should then belong to an interval
of plausible values.
To test this,
we will take a sample and see
if the parameter's measured value
is consistent with our supposition.
This is a hypothesis test.
Let's again have a look
at our elephant population.
We think, by observing it over time,
that it's mean age is 25 years,
and we can see that
it has a normal distribution.
We choose significance level α=0.05.
For our hypothesis, H0 is true,
and the difference
between the sample mean
and the population mean
should be under 1.96 α/√n.
Now, at random, let's take a sample
a sample of 52 individuals
from the population.
The age values are indicated here.
The sample mean is 19.3
and the standard-deviation is 12.6.
The √n is 7.2.
We have 19.3-25=5.7
and 1.96 (12.6/7.2)=3.43.
H0 is not verified
and we can reject the hypothesis
that the average age
of the population is 25 years.