The Jolly method
is mentioned several times
in the book hence this
additional unit
that briefly
introduces it.
It is particularly useful
when it comes to analyzing
data from aerial surveys
and we will take
the following example to
provide details
on the Jolly 1
calculation method.
Let's consider a
1000km2 park.
We want to sample at random
30 20km long transects
by 500m wide.
In other words,
a 250m stripe on each
side of the plain.
Each transect covers
a 10km2 surface.
In the park are
the total of 100 of them
theoretically to cover
it's entire surface.
The following table gives the
number of elephants counted
on each transect,
491 in total.
The mean of the samples
is the sum of elephants per sample
divided by n and that is
16.4 elephants per transect.
The total population is
100 times this mean.
There are 100 possible samples
in the park so we are
1640 elephants in total.
The sample variance calculated
following the usual method is
144.9 and the population variation
is deduced by the formula here
so a total of 33 810.
Hence the almost 184 standard
deviation for the population.
Now, we can calculate the
confidence interval around the mean
and that is 1.96 times
standard deviation
meaning 360.
The Jolly 2 method
uses the same principles
but deals with sampling
where the transect land
are viable.
This adds viability within
the transects to the viability
that already exists between
the transects.