Having considered the notions of
encapsulation and abstraction,
we will, in the following episodes,
consider
a third fundamental notion
in OOP:
inheritance.
Let's start with an example,
and forget, for once, rectangles
and other geometric shapes
to concentrate on
players of a game.
Imagine that we would like
to play a game that involves
warriors, magicians, thieves,
and the like.
How would we represent this?
We could imagine for one
that we have a class for warriors,
a class for thieves, a class for
magicians, and so on.
For a warrior we could imagine
that we could have data members
such as a name,
an energy level, a certain
lifespan, and
certainly a weapon.
As for methods, we
could imagine
that a warrior can meet
other people.
For a thief, he would
also have a name,
an energy level, a lifespan,
and he can also meet other
people, and even steal from them.
As for the magician, he would also
have a name, energy level, lifespan
he could also meet others
and he would maybe
also have a wand instead
of a weapon.
We could also have witches kind
of like magicians
but who would have a
stick as well as a wand.
All these classes would have much
duplicated code,
and would be a waste of time to write
all that,
and most importantly, would be
problematic for maintenance.
Imagine that we do want a
property lifespan anymore,
and instead have life points,
or that the energy level is
not an "int" but a "double".
Then we would have to
revise all the classes that we made.
There is definitely
a better way than this!
This is where the notion of inheritance
comes in:
inheritance solves this type of problem
by grouping together data
members and methods
that are common to each class
into what we will call a superclass.
This class regroups characteristics
that are enriched or
specialized
in its derived classes.
In our class, the superclass would be
a class Personnage (TN: = character)
a generic character which
would by the way
solve one of the problems we had:
the fact that we did not
have a class Personnage.
Anticipating a little,
here is what we could
do using inheritance,
by grouping in the class
Personnage
the properties shared by
the classes:
name, energy, lifespan, as well
as methods, for example
"recontrer" (TN: = meet).
So this superclass groups
together the characteristics
of these characters
which would be inherited
by the thief, the magician, etc.
with each character having
his own particularities, like
a weapon for the warrior,
a wand for the magician,
or a method "voler" (TN: =to steal)
for the thief.
For the magician we could
also have an extension,
a 2nd inheritance
so that a witch is a
sort of magician,
who would have a stick as well
as a wand.
So this is the purpose of
inheritance in OOP.
It represents an "is-a" relationship,
and avoids that code be
duplicated.
Inheritance also enables
specialized or enriched
classes to be created.
So a superclass is a class
from which subclasses
are derived.
We also say that subclasses
inherit
and we draw an arrow
in this direction.
Subclasses inherit
from superclasses,
and subclasses are
as a result extensions,
either by adding data members
or methods,
or by specializing the
inherited methods,
making them extensions
of the superclass.
Before detailing this
in an example,
let's investigate what a inheritance
relationship implicates.
If a subclass C1 is derived from
a class C
or "inherits" from the class C,
we will say that C1 "is a" C.
that is to say, that the type
is inherited.
So for example, if I
have a variable x, of type C,
and a variable y of type C1,
I can in fact put y in x, because
a C1 y "is a" C.
Moreover, the class C1 inherits
from the set of data members
and methods of C.
When we say the set of
data members and members,
the constructors are not included,
so they are not inherited.
The data members of C
are as a result available
in C1 without having to
redefine them.
Finally, extra data members
or methods can be
added to C1, which is
called enrichment,
and methods inherited from C
can also be redefined in C1,
which is called specialization.
Let's see all this
in an example.
Imagine we make a
superclass Personnage,
with 2 subclasses Guerrier and Voleur
(TN: guerrier = warrior, voleur = thief).
So we said that when a subclass C1,
for example Guerrier,
is created from a superclass C,
so for example here Personnage
the type is inherited.
Actually Guerrier is also
a character,
which allows us to write the
following code.
Suppose that we have declared
a variable p of type Personnage and
a variable g of type Guerrier
that we manipulate and for example
we say that the character p
is the warrior g.
So we put the warrior g
in the character p,
which we are allowed to do
because a warrior is a character.
Of course, we can't do
the contrary and write
"g = p;"
A generic character is
not a warrior,
because characters can also
be thieves or magicians,
and we cannot put
a thief in a warrior,
it doesn't have any meaning.
So here, the relationship
has a certain direction,
it's the warrior who
is a character.
We can also imagine a function
that displays a character,
and we could display g,
which is a warrior here
and is passed as argument to
the function "afficher" as a character,
(the function "afficher" sees
g as a character),
but we can only do this
because a warrior is a character.
A 2nd aspect of inheritance:
Guerrier will inherit, that is to
say, receive, contain
the set of data members
and methods of Personnage.
So for example, if Personnage
had a name, an energy,
a lifespan, and
a method "rencontrer",
and Guerrier inherited
of the class Personnage,
then in Guerrier we would also have
an energy, a lifespan,
without needing to
redefine them,
and also a method rencontrer, so
we could do something like this.
Suppose that here, with a
Guerrier g and Voleur v,
which are characters,
g , of type Guerrier, will inherit
the method rencontrer,
which we could invoke,
if this method is
included in the public
interface of Personnage,
using a syntax "g.rencontrer(v);",
here we pass the thief v as
argument to the method rencontrer,
but what is important here is to
see that this method rencontrer
is visible to g and
can be called by g because
Guerrier has inherited this
method from Personnage.
Likewise, if we had some
method in Guerrier,
we can directly use the data
member energie like this
in a method of Guerrier,
supposing that energie is not private.
So energie is inherited from
Personnage in the class Guerrier
without having to add
any code.
It's done automatically thanks
to inheritance.
The third and last aspect
that we want to focus on
is that even if the members
of a class are inherited,
and are accessible in the
subclasses,
we can always add
data members and
methods which is called
enrichment,
e.g. adding a data member "weapon"
to the class Guerrier,
and we can redefine methods
called specialization,
so for instance, we could redefine
the method rencontrer
of the class Voleur
by saying that when a thief
meets another person, he
also steals, for example.
Inheritance is a paramount
notion
in POO,
because it enables the code to
be organized
to make it more comprehensible
by elucidating structural and
semantical relationships
that exist among the classes,
for example, that a warrior
is a character,
or that a witch is a type of magician.
Inheritance also avoids writing
large sections of code,
called code redundancy.
Be careful in how you use
inheritance, to use it
only in "is-a" relationships,
e.g. a warrior is a character,
but a warrior is not a weapon,
we say a warrior "has a" weapon,
and to represent a
relationship of possession,
we will use a notion from
before: encapsulation.
Therefore, to summarize, a warrior
inherits from the class Personnage
but will also have as encapsulated
data member a weapon.
We saw that a subclass
enherits from a superclass,
inherit means
receive and possess
the data members and methods of this
superclass, except for constructors.
This aspect is transitive,
that is to say if we have
a super-super-class from which
a superclass is derived,
then in the subclass, we
will find all the members
of these 2 classes.
More concretely,
if I have a super-super-class A,
from which a superclass B is derived,
from which a class C is derived,
we will find in C the members
found in B,
but also those in A, because
B inherits them from A,
and so they are
accessible in B.
So in B, I have the data
members and methods of A,
and by transitivity,
I also have in
C, these same data members
and methods of A.
So in a concrete example, if we
have for instance a class Personnage,
from which a class Magicien
is derived,
and if we say a witch
is a kind of magician,
then the class Sorcier
inherits from the class Magicien.
At this point, in the class Sorcier,
we will also have the
data members for the
name, energy, lifespan
that were inherited along with
the method rencontrer that were
inherited in the magician class
and inherited again in the
class Sorcier
and of course, Sorcier will also
have the member baguette,
inherited from Magicien.
Thus we have something like
this for inheritance,
a progressive enrichment
of each class,
finally resulting in,
if we draw all the relationships
between the classes,
an arborescent graph,
a treelike organization,
where we see the dependencies
between classes,
the "is-a" relationships, and
the relationships of inheritance,
of data members, methods,
and also types,
which we call as whole,
a class hierarchy,
with the most general class,
Personnnage, at the top,
and the most specialized classes
on the bottom.
To summarize, the inheritance
relationship
avoids duplicating code.
Superclasses, resulting from
using "is-a" relationships
in programs,
also called "parent classes"
are more broad,
grouping general
aspects, and so from
them are derived subclasses
also called "child classes",
that receive the set
of data members and methods,
as well as the type of the superclass
that they depend on.
Up to now, this notion of
inheritance has been
presented very conceptually
and theoretically,
but how do we implement it
in a real program,
and make a subclass inherit
from a superclass?
Let's start with a concrete example.
Suppose, that we want to define
a class Rectangle
with a width largeur and
a height hauteur,
and which is also a
FigureGeometrique.
And this class of geometric
shapes also has a position.
So we would have the
following inheritance diagram,
a superclass "FigureGeometrique",
with a data member "position",
and a subclass "Rectangle",
derived from "FigureGeometrique".
A rectangle
is a geometric shape,
and so will have supplementary
data members,
besides the inherited
data member position,
such as largeur
and hauteur that
are defined in Rectangle.
But how do I code all this?
The syntax for a subclass
to inherit from a superclass
is simply to add the
keyword "extends" and
the name of the superclass,
after the heading of the subclass,
so we would have: "class Name_subclass
extends Name_superclass",
and then, as usual,
the definition of the
subclass,
with the definition
of data members and methods
unique to that subclass.
So for example,
if I have a class Rectangle,
that inherits from the
class "FigureGeometrique",
I would write the following:
"class Rectangle extends
FigureGeometrique"
and write the definition
of the class underneath
with, for example,
the 2 data members largeur and
hauteur particular to the class.
The only thing I need to add to
the precedent class definition
for it to inherit from
"FigureGeometrique" is this
section of the code.
In the same way, if we come
back to the example of warriors,
that inherit from characters,
we would have a class
Personnage previously
defined, and the way to
derive the class Guerrier
from Personnage
is simply by specifying:
"class Guerrier extends Personnage",
followed
by the specific definition of the
class Guerrier,
such as defining a data
member for weapons.
So this concludes this
introduction
to an important concept in
OOP: inheritance.
In the next episodes,
we will continue to deepen
our understanding of this concept
from a practical point of view,
in how it is implemented
in real code.