In this video
we will continue the topic
of inheritance
and will consider in this
context
the notion of protected
access rights.
You have seen that the accessibility
of a class's member
--a data member or a method--
can either be "public"
which means
that it can be used
without restriction
whether inside or
outside a class,
or it can be private, which means
that the member
can only be directly
accessed inside the class.
In Java, there is also
the access right "by default"
if no access modifier
is specified
in front of the member's
declaration
and in this case, the member
is visible
from any class in
the same package.
This is also the case
for the default package
that you have frequently
used
in the excercizes.
Note, that we have prepared a
PDF complement on packages
that is available on the
course's website.
The question that we
ask now is
what about access rights
in a hierarchy of classes?
Suppose that we have
a superclass A
from which is derived a subclass B.
Suppose that the superclass
includes the declaration
of a data member "a"
that is private.
Since we have always
declared variables private
up to now,
our question is:
"Is this data member
accessible
in a method of the class B?"
For example, could we write
something like this
in the class B?
We have seen that due
to inheritance,
the subclass B has
a data member "a"
inherited from A,
but the question is,
"Can B use "a" freely,
and use it directly in
its own methods?"
However, as we saw,
the private access modifier
only insures the
visiblity inside the class
in which the member
is defined.
Which means that "a" can
only be used here directly
in the methods
of the class A.
Which then means
that this is not allowed.
So we find paradoxically
that the class B inherits
from A and has at its disposal
a member variable "a"
but cannot use it freely,
accessing it directly
like here in this case.
Because it is perhaps intuitive
that a subclass has at its disposal
directly all of its data members
defined in the class itself
but also those inherited
from a superclass,
there exists another
access right
which is "protected".
When a member is declared
"protected" in a given class
it is consequently accessible
directly from
any class of its descendants.
The access right "protected"
in Java
is specified with the keyword
"protected".
So, replacing "private" with "protected"
in this case,
renders this syntax valid.
Note that a protected access
enables a member to be seen
in other classes
of the package
containing the class
with the protected member.
Schematically, here is how
this can be summarized,
so suppose that we have
a protected member
in a class defined
in a certain package
then this protected member
is directly accessible
in all the classes
descendant from A
whether they are in the
same package or not
which means that in
all the classes derived from A,
this access is possible.
And what if there
isn't any dependency?
Well, in Java, a protected member
is also accessible
in all the classes in
the same package
as the class containing
the protected member
even if they are not linked
by inheritance.
For example, the class C,
doesn't have any relationship
with the class A, but it is in
the same package,
hence a method from C
can directly access
a protected data member of A
through any instance of A,
without having to use
another method.
This access is possible.
On the other hand, a class
in another package,
and does not have an
inheritance relationship
with the class in which
the protected member is
can not access the
protected data members.
Here, for example, the
class E cannot access
the protected member "a"
through an instance of A.
The access modifier "protected"
is dangerous for encapsulation
namely in that it allows
all programmers of
extensions of the class A,
so all programmers with
classes that inherit from A
to access protected members
as if they were public
which results in strong
dependencies between
because the programmer
of the class A
cannot freely modify
the class's implementation details
for the protected members
without the programmer of
class D being disturbed.
The default access right
in which case no access modifier
is specified in front of the
member's declaration,
is more restrictive
than being private
in a package other
than the default package
to the effect that this kind
of access is invalid.
With a default access,
members can only be
accessed in the classes
of the same package.
The default access
even though it is more
restrictive than protected access
hinders a good encapsulation
because it enables an
open access
from all classes
of a package.
To summarize this discussion,
a subclass cannot access
private members
inherited from superclasses,
and to use them
even if through inheritance
the subclass has them
it has to use
getters or setters
provided in the superclass.
If a superclass wants to give access
to a member to its subclasses,
then it can declare it protected.
But be careful, this
interferes with a good encapsulation.
In one word, protected member variables
are not recommended.
Finally, to understand
the access modifier protected,
you have to grasp
that it is an extension of
of the private sphere
when we are outside of subclasses
and outside of the same package.
So to take a concrete example,
let's examine again the hierarchy
of characters
with a subclass Guerrier
derived from a superclass Personnage.
So imagine
that the class Personnage
was defined in a certain package
"P1" for example.
Whichever package
it is defined in,
the subclass Guerrier,
due to inheritance,
will be able to directly access
the protected members
in the methods of
the class Guerrier,
which is in the class
Personnage,
and directly use this
protected member variable.
On the other hand,
if I am in another package,
for example the package P2,
and in a class without
any parental link
with the class
Personnage,
for example, a class Jeu,
which uses in its
principal program,
a few characters in the hierarchy,
such as in the main method
declaring an instance of Guerrier,
in this case, the data member
energie cannot be accessed
in the method main
with an instance of Guerrier.
For classes not linked
by inheritance,
with the superclass Personnage
and that are not in the
same package,
for them, it is as if
the protected data member was private.
To recap on access rights,
so public members are
accessible without restriction
by all users of
the class in which they
were defined,
protected members are
intended for users who extend the class,
by inheritance or who
work in the same package
but can hinder inhibit
good encapsulation,
and finally, private members are
reserved for the class programmers
which reflect the internal
structure of the class
and cannot be modified
without disturbing
the class users
or users that extend the class.
So this concludes this episode
on access rights
in a class hierarchy.