In certain situations,
members defined in
the superclass, do not completely
satisfy the
needs of the subclass.
Redefinition or masking
are concepts
that can amend this
complications.
In a precedent video,
we examined the example
of an hierarchy of characters,
and postulated
that all these characters
met another character
in the same manner.
We could imagine, for example,
that when any character
meets another,
he only greets the other.
But imagine if this way of implementing
this method "rencontrer" was
valid for most of
the classes,
but not all.
For example, we could imagine
that a warrior
is somewhat more belligerent
than the others,
and when he meets another,
instead of greeting him,
he strikes him for example.
Thus we are in a situation
in which we consider
2 possible implementations
for the method "rencontrer".
One for pacific characters,
that will only greet
the other character
when they meet,
and one for warriors,
that will strike the other
character when they meet.
Can this be implemented
in our first design,
without having to
change the class hierarchy?
Happily, the answer is no,
we can simply define
in the class Guerrier,
a method "rencontrer"
that is specialized.
So, in our class hierarchy,
we will keep in
the superclass Personnage,
a generic method "rencontrer",
which is satisfied for most
subclasses,
however, in the subclass
guerrier,
we will give the method rencontrer
a new definition,
in order that it corresponds
to what we want a warrior
to do in this subclass.
So for a warrior, the
specialized method
will have precedence over the
generic method rencontrer.
The generic method will
be invoked by default
as long as the method
is not redefined in the subclass.
For instance, if in a program,
I declare an object of type Magicien,
and that I invoke the
method rencontrer on it
since the subclass Magicien
does not have its own
definition of this method,
it's the generic method rencontrer
inherited from Personnage that
will be called here.
Now, if I declare an object
of type Guerrier
and apply to it the
method rencontrer,
well this time, because
the method has been redefined,
in Guerrier,
it will be this specialized
method that will be applied.
In a class hierarchy, it is possible
that a name of a data member
or method be used
on several tiers of the
hierarchy.
In the last example, the
method rencontrer
with the same header,
is found at 2 levels of the hierarchy.
In this situation,
we will speak of redefinition,
a method is redefined so as to
be adapted to the subclass.
The english term for this
is "overriding".
Similarly, it is possible
for a member variable to be present
at several tiers
of the hierarchy.
For example, if in the superclass A
we have
a data member "a",
it is possible to declare this
data member "a" again
in the subclass B.
Consequently, we find
a data member of the same name
on 2 different levels of the
hierarchy.
In this case it is important to
now, that an object of type B
now has at its disposal 2 data
members called "a",
one that is directly in class B,
and one inherited from A.
If in the method B,
we use the data member "a",
it will be the one from the
same class that is used,
and not the one inherited
from a.
We say that the data member
present in B
"masks" the one of the same name
defined in the superclass.
So, for data members,
we speak of "masking",
or "shadowing".
The shadowing of variables
in an hierarchy
is clearly a source
of ambiguity,
thus it is not a very
common practice.
On the other hand, method
redefinition or "overriding",
is a very useful and
is used frequently.
This device allows methods to be adapted
to the specific needs of a subclass
so as to specialize it.
To summarize, the redefinition of methods
in a class hierarchy
consists of defining a method
for the specific requirements of its class
with the same header
as a method
already present
in the superclass.
In jargon, we callthe
inherited method
that can be used by subclasses
of Personnage
that do not override
this method,
the default method,.
The method that
redefines a default method
is called a specialized method,
and which is adapted to
the individual needs of a subclass.
As seen before,
it is always the specialized method
that has precedence over
the default method,
for example, if we declare
an object of type Guerrier,
and invoke the method rencontrer
on this instance,
it will be the specialized method rencontrer
that will be called.
In reality, an object of type Guerrier
has 2 methods rencontrer,
the one specific to its class,
and the other inherited.
In certain cases, it can be
useful to call the default method
even if it was redefined
in the subclass.
How can we do this?
For example, imagine
that we want to give our warrior
some good manners,
so that instead of attacking
characters he meet
he greets them instead.
So this is the code
for a pacific character,
we want to keep the default method
where the character
greets his contacts
but for a warrior,
we want to keep a specialized
method
so that the warrior can attack people
he accosts, but before clouting them
we want to be able
to invoke the default method
so as to greet them.
Which means concretely
that we wish
to call the generic method
from the specialized method.
The code allowing
a character to greet another
is indeed already code
in the general method,
so it is useless to
duplicate it in the redefined method,
so it makes more sense to
invoke the default method
without duplicating code.
To access masked
data members
or the original methods
of a superclass,
necessitates a certain
syntax in Java
using the keyword super followed
by a dot operator
and the name of the member in
question: "super.name_member".
In our example, if I want
to invoke the method rencontrer
inherited from Personnage,
then I write "super.rencontrer()",
which means that I am calling
the default method of the superclass.
Of course, it is possible to
follow up with more specific actions.
Invoking a superclass method
is very convenient,
because it avoids duplicating code
in the redefined method.
Invoking a redefined method
with this syntax
allowed us to define a warrior
so as to have more suitable
behavior,
and will first greet his adversary
before showering him with blows,
and this, without
duplicating code.
Note that in Java, it is not possible to
invoke super several times in succession,
and this kind of expression
is forbidden.
This means that if we have
a subclass Sorcier,
that inherits from a subclass Magicien,
that is derived
from a superclass Personnage,
if the method rencontrer
is defined in Personnage,
and again in Magicien,
and again in Sorcier,
then the method rencontrer in Sorcier
cannot avoid the method
inherited from Magicien by
invoking
"super.super.rencontrer".
The designers of Java probably
considered this expression
dangerous that an object
of type "sub-subclass"
be more like an object of type
"super-superclass",
than like an object of its
direct class, its superclass,
which is seen as
weakening
the "is-a" inheritance relationship.
Note that this is not
always limited
in the other OOP languages,
which authorize this
kind of syntax,
namely, that a sub-subclass
can directly call
a method of its super-superclass.
Note that if the
method rencontrer
had not been defined
at this intermediate level,
then "super.rencontrer"
would be valid
and would simply call
the method rencontrer
in the most closely relate superclass
in which it is defined,
and so would indeed have
used the method
from the class Personnage.
And this concludes this video.