In this episode,
will will examine how
inheritance effects
constructors,
that is to say, how
instances are initialized.
We saw in other videos
on constructors
that in an instantiation
of a subclass,
the data members have
to be initialized.
Which is what we do
when, for example, we declare
an instance "r" of the class Rectangle
by passing the
width and height.
This is done with a constructor
which is in charge of
initializing the data members.
But if the class Rectangle
inherits from a class FigureGeometrique,
then the class Rectangle receives
the set of data members
from the class FigureGeometrique.
So the constructors of the class
Rectangle are to
initialize the data members
of the class Rectangle,
including those inherited
from the superclass FigureGeometrique.
However, it shouldn't be
the class programmer of Rectangle
who has to initialize
the data members of
the class FigureGeometrique himself,
and he would perhaps even
be incapable of doing this
if the superclass had
private data members
which he couldn't access.
So, how can the designer
of the subclass Rectangle
initialize the data members
of the superclass FigureGeometrique?
To do this, he has to call in the
constructor of the class Rectangle
the constructor of the
class FigureGeometrique.
So that the initialization of the
inherited data members
be done by calling the
constructor of the superclass
in the constructor of the subclass.
Let's see how this is
done in Java.
To call the constructor
of a superclass
in the constructor of a subclass,
you use the method "super".
And this method super
has to be called
in the very beginning of the body
of the constructor of the subclass.
So the syntax  will look like this;
in the subclass constructor,
that can take several
different parameters,
in the opening of its body,
we will have the invocation
of the constructors of the superclass
by simply writing like this
the keyword "super"
and passing to the
necessary arguments
to the superclass constructor
we want to invoke.
Thereupon, after this first line,
we can continue to initialize the
data members of the superclass.
Note that if the superclass
has a default constructor,
it is not necessary to
explicitly call
the superclass constructor,
because the compiler
automatically calls
the default superclass constructor.
Lets thoroughly examine
an example.
First of all, if the superclass doesn't
have a default constructor,
then the class absolutely
has to invoke
a superclass constructor.
Evidently, this implies that
the subclass also has
an explicit constructor
where we can write this
call of the superclass constructor.
For example, if we conside
the class FigureGeometrique,
with no default constructor,
but an explicit constructor
which receives 2 parameters,
to initialize the data member
position here,
then we would suppose
that it has a constructor like this
with 2 parameters x and y
to establish the position
of the geometric shape.
Then we have a class Rectangle, here
that is derived from the class FigureGeometrique,
and in this class, we
will have a constructor
that receives parameters in order
to initialize the data member
position of the superclass
FigureGeometrique.
A rectangle is a geometric shape
and has inherited position
from FigureGeometrique,
so a rectangle will also have
a position that needs to be initialized,
and of course, as usual,
the parameters l and h
to initialize its own
member variables largeur
and hauteur.
This constructor here, takes
4 parameters,
and starts by invoking
the constructor of the superclass
with the keyword super,
and passing the 2 parameters
it takes
to it: x and y.
So here we have an
invocation of this constructor
that initializes the position.
Next as usual, we will
continue by initializing
Rectangle's own data members
largeur and hauteur
with the parameters it received:
l and h.
In the case where the
superclass FigureGeometrique
has a default constructor,
then as mentioned before, an explicit
call with super of the constructor
of the superclass from the constructor
of the subclass is superfluous.
So here for example, we have
a class FigureGeometrique,
which does have a
default constructor,
that is, a constructor
without any parameters,
that initializes
the position at (0,0).
So in this case,
the subclass Rectangle
doesn't have to explicitly
invoke the default constructor
and we have endowed it
with a conventional constructor
that takes 2 parameters
l and h
to initialize its width
and height.
But we see here there
isn't an explicit invocation
of the superclass
constructor
because in fact
the default constructor
of the superclass
is automatically invoked
by the compiler.
Something I would like
to underline and which is
sometimes asked is
that even if a subclass
doesn't have any
specific data members,
it may be obliged to redefine
a constructor in the subclass.
The constructor of a subclass,
even if there aren't any specific
member variables in a subclass,
can also used
to invoke specific
constructors of the superclass.
Let's take an example,
suppose that Carre inherits
from the superclass Rectangle,
a square is a special
kind of rectangle
whose width and height
are of equal length.
In this case, will not introduce
supplementary data members
to the subclass Carre
(TN: "carre" means "square"),
but we will nevertheless
want to redefine
a constructor for this
class.
The constructor of this
subclass Carre
will call the constructor of
the superclass Rectangle
by obliging it to have an equal
length for the height and width.
Note that this class Carre,
will have nothing else
than a constructor here
that forces the constructor
of its parent class
to have equal width and height.
There wouldn't be anything
else, if in Rectangle,
there aren't mutators
setHauteur or setLargeur.
But if we did have in the
super class
for instance a method
setHauteur,
which received for example
a parameter h to set the height,
then in the class Carre, we would
need to redefine the method Sethauteur
so as to guaranty that the
height is always equal to the width,
and so here, setHauteur would
also set the width.
And likewise, if we had a method to set
the width, this method
would also set the height
so as to ensure that
the height is always equal
to the width in the class Carre.
This concludes this example.
So to summarize the implications
of inheritance in constructors,
every subclass has to invoke
the constructors of its superclass,
this is done with the method "super"
and the necessary arguments
for a constructor of the
superclass.
This call of the superclass
constructor must be done
in the first line of the
child class's constructor's body.
If super is invoked later
in the body,
or is even invoked twice,
we will receive an error message
from the compiler.
No method other
than a constructor of a subclass
can invoke the method "super".
"super" doesn't need to be invoked
if the superclass
has a default constructor.
In this case,
even if we forget to write "super"
super, the default constructor
will be invoked
automatically by the compiler.
I would like to remind you
that this default constructor,
that is, a constructor without
any arguments,
is a special case, because if
we do not implement it,
a default version of this
default constructor
is provided by the compiler,
but the moment we implement
another constructor,
this defaulted default constructor
is not provided anymore.
And at this point, if we want a default
constructor, we would have
to write it ourselves.
So to avoid this problem connected
with inheritance,
I recommend that you always
declare at least one constructor
and always explicitly invoke a
superclass constructor
from a subclass constructor.
Even if it is the default constructor
that you want to call,
it is better to write
it explicitly
which is more clear
for the time being.
Let's come back to the order
in which constructors are called
in a class hierarchy.
Suppose for example, that we
have defined a class C,
that contains certain
data members and methods,
and extends a class B,
which has its own data
members and methods,
and which itself inherits
from a class A
that has its own data members
and methods.
And we declare an instance monC
of the class C
by calling a constructor
of this class C.
So what happens when we declare
an instance like this?
This constructor will call
the constructor of B,
whether by default
or explicitly,
and then initialize
its own data members.
So in calling this constructor
we first call the constructor
of the class B.
And the constructor of the
class B, will first call
a constructor of its superclass.
And so, in this call
of the constructor of B
in the constructor of the class C,
the constructors of the superclass A
will first be called.
Thus the first thing that happens
when a constructor of C is called,
is the execution of the
constructor of the super-superclass,
the class at the
topmost tier.
So the constructor
will start by initializing
the data members a1 and a2
and so, in the construction of a C,
we will have started the construction
of a B
which will have started
a construction of a A.
Therefore the first thing that
happens in this construction of C,
is the construction of its section A.
I remind you that through
inheritance,
C inherits all the data
members of B,
and B inherits those of A,
which results in C effectively
having the data members a1 and a2.
So in constructing C,
we start by construction
its section A.
That's the first thing that happens.
When constructing A is finished,
we then continue in the
constructor B
to initialize B's own
data members,
in this case b1.
Once B's construction is done,
we come back to
the execution of the
constructor of C.
Once this first constructor
is finished executing,
it will have initialized its section C.
And so this completes
the construction of C.
So in the construction
of a subclass instance,
we first call the constructor
of the highest class from which
the subclass is derived,
then call in turn the constructors
of the intermediate classes,
and finally end in the
subclass constructor
with the construction of the
section of the subclass itself.
So! This concludes this video
on the consequences of inheritance
in the instantiation of objects.