Now you are acquainted with
the fundamental notions in OOP of
encapsulation, abstraction,
and inheritance.
Let's move on to another
important concept:
polymorphism.
In general terms, polymorphism
provides that the same code
can automatically adapt itself to
the type of the data to which it is applied.
This is important because it
allows code to be much more generic:
it can be written the same way
for different types of data.
Note that this video is
only a brief introduction to polymorphism.
We will be able to come back
to this concept in more detail
in the episodes next week.
Let's take up our introductive
example to inheritance.
Suppose that we have a
hierarchy of characters
and that we want to program
a game where a group of
different characters meet
a central figure.
How do we implement this?
The idea is to have a group
of characters that we could
for example store in an array
to simplify, a array of fixed size,
and we want to ensure that these
characters meet one by
one the principle character.
So we would program
each encounter
using a loop,
so as to allow each character
of the group
to meet the principle character
in turn.
The main idea here is
that in an array of characters,
we can have different characters.
For instance, the first entry
in our table could be a thief,
the second, a warrior,
the third, a witch.
And so our first question is,
since Java is a strong typing
programming language,
which implies that everything on the left
of the assignment operator =
has to be of the same type as
that on the right,
"Is this requirement fulfilled
here?"
"Are we allowed to put thieves,
warriors, witches, different,
sub-classes of the class Personnage
in an array of type Personnage?"
The answer is in fact "yes".
Actually, when we write an assigment
where we assign  to a variable of type
superclass a reference to an object
of type subclass, this is
not in contradiction with the requirement
that what is on the right of =
has to be of the same type
as that on the left thanks to
inheritance of types
in a class hierarchy that
we studied
on our last videos.
So, an object of a subclass
here, an object of type Sorcier,
inherits the type of its superclass
which is Personnage.
Because inheritance is transitive,
an object of a subclass
inherits through transitivity
all the types of its progenitors,
and can have several types.
These are aspects already
considered in other videos,
but are important enough
to have to refresh.
Our outline of the program is
correct here:
we are allowed to stock in
an array of characters, characters
of different types, which has
the advantage of being able
to manipulate in one
combined way like here,
with a loop 'for'.
So let's see what happens
when characters
meet the principle character,
particularly for certain
subclasses of Personnage that have
a peculier way of encountering someone.
We examined before how
a subclass can redefine
a method in its
superclass.
And we took the example
of a warrior who, when he
encountered someone, would clobber him
while other characters would perhaps
merrily greet the other person.
The problem we have now is
if we store an object of type
Guerrier, warrior, in a variable
of type Personnage, what happens
when we invoke the method rencontrer
with this variable unPersonage?
Will it be the method recontrer
of the subclass that wil be invoked?
Or the method of the superclass?
This is exactly the same problem
as in the introductory example,
because we stock an object of type
Guerrier in an entry of an array
of type Personnage, that is
a collection of type Personnage.
It is important to know here
if rencontrer will result in
a simple greeting or
a violent act.
We can examine this question
from 2 perspectives.
We can first of all consider that
the type of the variable
on which is invoked the method
will determine
which method to use.
Here, the type of the variable on which
is invoked the method
is Personnage.
Then with this perpective,
to decide the method we will
look for the method in the class
Personnage, and so the encounter
will result in mere greetings.
This way of solving this problem
of finding which variable goes with
which method
is called in programming,
the "...".
We speak of static resolution because
we don't need to wait
for the program to be executed
to make the choice of the method
recontrer to apply here.
If, by simply reading the code
when the program compiles
we can know unPersonnage is of
type Personnage,
consequently, it's the method
rencontrer of Personnage
that is applied.
In summary, we speak of
static resolution when it's
the apparent type of the variable
that determines which method
to apply.
Static resolution exists in certain
languages, but not
the perspective used in
Java.
The 2nd perspective is
"dynamic resolution of links"
where will will consider that it
is the effective type, that is,
the type that is stored inside
the variable, that will determine
which method to apply.
In our example, the
variable unPersonnage is evidently
of type Personnage, but contains
a reference to an object of type Guerrier.
Because it is the type contained
in the variable that is determinant,
in this case we will choose
the method rencontrer of
the class Guerrier.
So here, the character encountered
will not only be greeted,
but will also endure several
blows.
We speak of dynamic resolution
because in general, it's during
the program's execution that
we will be able to determine
what a variable contains
in fact.
So there are 2 ways of resolving
methods in programming:
statique resolution and dynamic
resolution.
Certain languages offer
the choice between the two,
that is we can choose if we want
to use static resolution or
dynamic resolution.
In Java, this choice is not given,
it's always dynamic resolution
that is used.
Thus it is the effective type
which is stored in the variable
rather than the apparent type
of the variable that will determine
the method to apply,
and so, in our example,
the warrior will fatally strike
the character he meets.
To close, let's summarize and
synthesize with an example
similar to the introductory one.
Suppose that we have a class Jeu
which contains a data member
of type Personnage that would
be the principle player, and
another data member, an array of
type Personnage, that would
contain the opponents
that will meet the player.
The class Jeu contains a method
public tourDeJeu that
ensures that each adversary meets
in turn the principle player.
Suppose that in a constructor
of the class Jeu,
the array is filled like this:
the first entry is a witch
and the second a warrior.
Suppose, like in other examples,
that a witch
simply meets another character
by greeting them,
and that the warrior encounters
others
by striking them.
If a user of the class Jeu
declares a variable leJeu,
of type Jeu, and that it invokes the
method tourDeJeu on this variable,
what happens?
If a static resolution is possible,
the apparent
type of variables is determinant,
so Personnage is determinant.
In this case, the player
will be greeted twice:
once by the warrior
and once by the witch.
But with a dynamic resolution,
the method rencontrer will adapt itself
to the type of the variable's contents,
that is, the entry
of the array.
It is this effective type that is decisive,
and so here, the player
will be greeted by the witch,
but attacked by the warrior.
This second option,
dynamic resolution,
is what is always used in Java.
So, this concludes this little
introduction to polymorphism in Java.
In the next episode, we will
be able to come back to
this notion in more detail.